In the year 2
Everybody was signing up for Yahoo email
This was back before Gmail and Yahoo mail is great
It was free
You can check your email anywhere
But there was this one
And a computer science grad student at Carnegie Mellon University
Became fixated on this problem
His name is Luis Von Ahn
The problem was that they were people who
In order to
Send spam from Yahoo accounts they would have been millions of email accounts
Literally millions not not hundreds of thousands but millions of fake email account literally millions of fake email
The spammers who were signing up for millions of spam account
Weren't going to the Yahoo mail page
And just signing up for these accounts wanted
It wasn't like they were like the real Jacob Goldstein at yahoo.com Jacob Goldstein
99 at yahoo.com
Jacob the Barefoot dancer at yahoo.com
No spammers were writing simple computer programs little.
They just kept filling out the Yahoo email sign up form
Again and again and again
Day and night
And that would generate an army of email accounts that can be used to
Tell fake Viagra
Steal your bank account information whatever
Don't know what to do about
But Louis Vuitton have an eye
So the idea was can we make a test that can distinguish between humans and computers
But also a test
That is graded by the computer
Basically ever signed up for anything on the internet
That you probably know
The idea that Lewis Vaughn
A picture of distorted letters in them
And then a little
Field below that pic
Picture where you type in the characters
And we actually showed it to the the guy with the chief scientist at Yahoo
He loved it and within a few weeks it was actually
In the registration flow of email accounts that Yahoo it was it was being used there
And we were super happy that they were just using it Lewis gave his little tested name
So long ridiculous
Name that made a short
Genius
The long name was completely automated public
Turing test to tell computers and humans apart is a famous old idea in computer science
It's a test where you try to tell if you're chatting with a computer or with a human being
If a computer can consistently make you think it's a human being
That is artificial intelligence
And this sort of Turing test that Lewis came up with
It became huge
You may even know the acronym for this
Capture
Catches very compelling captures a good name cuz it's like capture them or gotcha or something like that
It was a good name
You know captcha
Maybe you do not like captcha
And yet
The 20-year history of captcha is this window into a lot
Artificial intelligence
Into digitizing millions of books also into a little cybercrime
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm Noel King
And I am not a robot
I'm not
Not
Not a robot
But if you were
That's exactly what I put on the show a global
Decades-long war and internet that people actually use
Versus a spammy wasteland
It is computer vs. computer
And in the end the computers are only going to need us the humans
To do a little light data entry
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
They're cloud-based Platt
Form and solution
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole car
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
To make people more productive and engaged
More at servicenow
Al.com
I should say that Luis Von Ahn was one of several people working on capture of like
Tests around the same
So he's not the only person who came up with the idea
The other people develop their own
But Lewis and his colleagues are the ones who came up with the name
And their version was the one that really
When you bought tickets online when you signed up for your MySpace account
Pretty soon people were taking Luisa's little test
200 million times a day
It was protecting the world from scalpers and spammers and
Bots
Emma world of course
Responded with gratitude
Every time that I talk to somebody about about captors you know the first thing they would tell me how annoying they are
So I started feeling
Fair fair I started feeling partly responsible for at least you know
20 million times a day
And each time you type on a lazy waste about 10 seconds of your time
So now I started just thinking
Is there any way in which we can make good use of these this 10 seconds
This was in the
At this moment there is this
Who's going on
Digitize old books and old.
And at the time it was easy enough to scan old pages on pieces of paper and put them online
What computers were still bad
A turning those scanned pages
Is into useful online.
It's not searchable you cannot change the font size you cannot I mean it's just a bunch of kind of
Summer crappie pictures
So it occurred to me that you could take all of the words of the computer could not recognize
And we get people to read them for us while they were typing capitals on the internet
Up to this point Lewis has been giving captcha away for free
But now he thinks
People might pay to have their print archives digitized one captcha at a time
And he is sitting on over half-a-million hours of free human labor a day
So he starts a company called recaptcha and he goes out looking for
And what happened was I was actually giving a talk somewhere
I was fortunate that
At the time the guy who was the
Chief Information officer for the New York Times was sitting at the
And the audience okay and he said you know what
We have this huge do you know hundred and thirty year old Archive of
Old editions of the New York Times so maybe we can maybe you can help us
The New York Times ended up being recaptures first client
Now when you saw the caption next to a few random letters and numbers
There was also a picture of a word from an old issue of the times
The computers couldn't read
When you typed in that word you weren't just protecting the internet from spam
You are also helping to turn a hundred years of old newspapers into a searchable digital archive
And I have to say I just
Love this sort of
While you're doing one thing you're also doing something else
Efficiency of this like it just
Hit The Lights
Do you know it's like that
The old dream of riding your exercise bike to power the lights in your houses
Something which by the way Louis told me when he was like 11 he had that dream
And then he like looked into it and realized I actually
Like a person
Exercise bike is a terrible way to die
As Louis was getting recaptcha going
Google came out and announced that they were starting to digitize every
Book like every single book in the world or
Basalt Lewis was doing for the time
And in 2009 googlebot recaptcha and started using it to help digitize book
And then a few years later Google started using captcha test that showed
Pictures of addresses on the sides of building
When we solve those captured
We were making Google Maps work
Work better doing a little more work for
Unpaid
So that is the end of Louis's caps
Story but a little digression
He started a language come
Where people did online translation
While they were learning the length
Same like doing one thing actually do another thing
This company became super Papi
Killer is called
Duolingo if I take out so popular
But they got rid of the translation
I know it's just this app that millions of people used to
Okay end of Lewis and of digression
So now it is the odds
Enter wild captcha is working
The spammers are held at Bay
And then
Someone figures out a worker
Shady businesses
Started showing up online
An offering to break captcha for anybody willing to pay
Christina is a computer scientist
Who started looking into these businesses around 2000
And it's one of those things until you actually think I would actually let's go see. See how hard it is to
Define you might think I know this is some shady cybercriminal underground thing
But no Google for if you can find a dozen of these Services very competitively priced within all that stuff
Just wanted to know like
What's even going on here like is it for real
Do the service
Work
So he was calling
Decided to act like spammers me they didn't do the spam
But they did more or less
Everything else they built upon
And this part went around the web bumping into cat
And automatically
Every time the bot hit a captcha test
It would send it off to one of these services
Is that offers to solve
And what do those services do exactly
VP
Human being
To sit in front of computers all day long and solve one capture after another
So some person sitting in front of a computer gets a captcha from Chris's bought
Salsa test in a couple
Send it back to Chris's bought which enters the solution into a web page
And
Yes that is the plain vanilla version just to see like
Does this work how long does it
The take
But Chris and his colleagues also had some other question
So they did something else
They made up their own captcha test
Defend out to the soul
Some of those tests just said
What time is it
And the answer to those tests
Told them what time zone the people solving a test lived
They also wanted to know what languages
What's this song
So they make capsules with weird instructions in lots of different
Chinese
Spanish to Italian Tagalog Portuguese Russian Tamil Dutch
Hindi German male Vietnamese Korean Greek Arabic Bengali kannada Klingon in Farsi
I'm sorry what was the one before Farsi
Klingon
The made-up language from Star Trek
I mean of course
But they did it because they wanted to just like for the
Pusha T servers like how far will these cats
Thesaurus go
There's no way they're going to be able to answer this but
The answers we saw it showed us
Like a 1% accuracy rate
But it was on something that was so incredibly
Long of a of a question
That it couldn't have been right by chance so presumably
One of these captcha solvers
Recognize that this was playing on
Either new Klingon just because that's what them people know or look it up online and was actually able to success
Leslie solve this
Couches that was written in Klingon
You found the greatest
Captcha solver on Earth
Yes based on this part of the study not the Klingon part put the languages and the time zones
They figure out that a lot of people seem to be doing this work in Russia China and India
And they realize
This is a huge industry
People have started calling it
Captcha
Farming
And it is basically human beings opening the
Captcha gate
For an army of bots
Captcha Farms
Work
Usually they were right
Usually they were very fast
So that so the services were legit I mean they were
Potentially illegal but they did the thing that they said they were
Correct
Yeah one of the most interesting things about
Cybercrime as a Marketplace is that it works like
Any other
Like business-to-business type Marketplace your reputation is really important there and you're not going to keep your capture
Dissolving business
In business
Unless you're actually solving those couches
And how much did it cost
I won
US dollar per thousand captures
I'm so incredibly incredibly inexpensive
But this is a task that takes a typical human
In about 15-20
Yes
But God I mean you really
Feel for the people doing the work
Yes
So
If you are a spammer
These workers will solve captchas for you around the clock
For a tenth of a penny
Pet prices
Obviously like
Mind breaking Lilo
But it is still not zero
I need to steal enough
Weed out a lot of
It weeds out you know
People who are just trolls making spam accounts for fun
And people who are just posting garbage comments on a million garbage website
Hoping to sell a few X
$2 worth of
The garbage Prada
So even with the caption
Farms captchas
Steeler working to block a lot of
But
What would happen if you could
A computer to solve
Then you wouldn't need the farms in a farmer setting
The price would go to zero
And the spammers
Could go what
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
Their cloud-based plant
Form and solution
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole car
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow
No.com
So this thing kept happening for a long time
Where some spammer would program a computer to solve
Then the people making captures would make the test harder
Eventually the test.
Too hard for human beings to
Google set all right enough
We are going to completely change the way captchas
They called it recaptcha version
And there are two big changes
First of all they introduced the
I am not a robot
Checkbox
Which I have always been kind of mystified by cuz I was four
The robot just check a check
What I learned
When I was working on this show is
When you click on that check box that the site sends back a bunch of information
We'll talk more about what that information is a little later in the
But Google takes that information and decides whether it thinks you're person or a robot
If it's pretty confident that your
Person you just get that
Keep going on.
But if you think you might be a machine then you have to take
And the test is the second thing that's really different in this new recaptcha
This is when they start using those tests that said
Click on the picture of a cat or click on all of the pictures of a car
And the reason they made this is
It is much much harder for a computer to
To beat then just distorted pictures of numbers
I talked about this with Jason Pollock is he's a computer science Professor who has studied
Send example is that you want a system where you give it up
Picture of a car and it's going to tell you this is a car
But the problem is that you can have
100 different types of
Cars different angles different colors different shapes
Different models so
Expound from Cars
Two trucks to both two planes two trees two dogs two animals to humans everything you can imagine
Just even you know if we just go back to the beginning of capture right in and around 2,000 dish
Was there any system in the world that could have looked at a
Picture of a glass of wine or a picture of a dog and said that's a glass of wine or that's it
No not even close
In order to get a machine to solve this kind of problem you would need millions of label digital photos of different
And Incredibly powerful computers
And very very clever software that could take all the photos
And learn to recognize
Nice cats and wine and dogs
As it happened
All of those things happened to come together in the years right before recaptcha version
Came out you know the web provided millions of labeled image
Just and then computer scientist started using this technique called
Deep learning or machine learning but essentially trained
Powerful computers
Deep learning or machine learning
This is me the biggest behind the scenes
Technological innovation of the last
20 years
Impact today a lot of the time when people talk about AI artificial intelligence
This is what they're talkin about
It's essential to the progress of a lot of things
Take autonomous cars
This is how a car can see a kid running into the street and hit the brakes
And it's not just images
Researchers have used other dataset
Teach computers to recognize
It's fraud
To translate languages
Understand human speech and like a million other
So when is new recaptcha version 2 came out
Immediately thought I want to see if I can use these new machine Learning System
To break this new recaptcha
Simple I guess he's not a machine learning expert
And that is actually sort of
The point
Because by this time machine learning had progressed so much that you didn't have to be an expert to use it there were these
Basically off-the-shelf machine learning systems that anybody would like a medium amount of technical knowledge could use
Extra pieces
Entrance room up against
Take a break recap show with
And it worked
I'm not a machine learning person
So the fact that
Machines have reached that point
And are that good at pass to me it's mind-blowing
Placas publishes a paper about his project in 2006
And other researchers are doing the same thing we beat recap should we be recap
Of course Google knows this is
In fact
Google itself is doing all this work in machine learning they know better than
Anybody in the world Maybe
That machine learning is
Is just going to keep getting better and better at solving
Aaron malenfant runs the recaptcha engineering team at Google so if this is anyone's problem it is his
One day a couple years ago he was telling his boss about all the things that his team was trying to do to stay ahead of the Bots
But eventually you had to break it
Pretty soon the Bots are going to be able to
How to solve any kind of captured
Anytime
I mentioned to her that
Nginx
325 years
The current challenges are no longer going to be working
We need to move to a new system
And so she turned to me and just
Ask me
Why aren't you doing that
So he did
Aaron and his team started building a new kind of Ra
Where there is no test
At all
No letters no pictures no street signs
Apart from a little notice at the bottom of a web page
You don't even know recaptcha
Google just released it last year so websites are still in the process of
The switching over
It's called recaptcha V3 version 3 reasonably enough
The way it works is you go to a website and Google analyzes your behavior and then sends a score to the web
And that score is
Probability that
You are human too
And then it's up to the website what
Maybe they make you login again if you're submitting a comment or review maybe they sent it to moderation
So that's
Like the steps of what
But there is this
Black Box
Right which is
What's going on in the background how is Google decided whether or not I'm a robot
We know a little bit about how this worked in version 2 when you
You click the checkbox
In that case Google looked at whether you had visited Google sites
I whether you were logged into a Google account
And also and this part was almost entirely see
Google did some kind of analysis
Based on what you did on that
Page like
You know maybe it had to do with how you move the mouse
It's like this black boxes of course you know
The most interesting thing to me
So when I was talking to Aaron about this new recaptcha about version 3 I I just said like
What can you tell me about what you're doing to decide whether
So
What
What's public about the
The way in which you're making that risks
Yasso
The reason we don't say too much is that we do have
Adversary is trying to beat us at all
We do say publicly that we adapt
To a particular site and
Behavior for that site
And when I say
We don't mean people I mean the machine looks at it
And decides
Is this
Request
Expected for this website does it
Look like other good requests
Asus website
In other words
For every site that installs recaptcha version 3
Google's computer
Using machine learning
Analyze specific behavior for that website
And then every time a user comes to that website they say
Is this user doing what a person normally does on this site or are they acting weird
And this is a big change cuz you know in the sort of recaptcha world that were used to there's like a few diff
Different kinds of
And if you could build a bot that could pass those tests
Then you could get through
Any recaptcha on any web
Looks like you had the keys to all the locks
Now with version 3
It's like Google is making a different lock for every single
This means that if
Just because you can get a good score on the website if you're an attacker doesn't mean that you can get a good score on a
All the websites
I get that
That makes sense
I mean if that's all true
Does it matter at all env3 whether I am
Login to Google or have a Gmail account or any of that is that even relevant for 4
How you analyze the risk
I would say it matters a lot less
A lot less than what
Then used
Okay
Okay goal is that it doesn't matter
That's your that's your ndk
Right
We're not there yet
Getting there
Well I had a knife in Taiwan
I probably already said too much
A few days after I talked to Aaron a Google spokesman got into
And was able to tell me a little bit more of
What he said was
Whether or not a user has an active Google account
That matters
Google's risk
But recaptcha does not use any information about what the user does on
Is a hurricane
So they're not looking at like
How often you send emails or browse YouTube
It's just
Do you have an account
For all of the secrecy and the cleverness in this new kind of captcha
It's still a computer deciding who is a human
But now the captcha test isn't just in a little box
At the bottom of the page
The test is everything you do on
So when the spammers computers figure out how to break this week
And if there's one thing we learned is that somebody somewhere will break it some
The computers won't just be solving a little
The spammers computers will be imitating
Everything
End of file
Planet Money at the new newsletter
Every week that dives into economic questions like why did a bunch of countries in Europe have a wealth tax and then get
Do plastic bag bans really help the environment sign up for the newsletter at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
Again npr.org
Planet Money
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and
Liza Yeager it was edited by Brian First Step family senior producer is Alex Goldman
I'm Jacob and thanks for listening
I have failed many many captured
It comforted when our producer Lexi found these videos on YouTube of people losing their mind
Overcapture
Okay so apparently
I am incapable
Of identifying street signs
Intel
Now that's not it
Is a street sign
It's on the street and it's a sign is that a bus
I think it's a truck
But it could be a bus
Bus
Bus bus are there any more cars
There are right
Right
Wrong
And now Google throws a foe at you that you've never seen
Before Road
Is that a storefront incredibly
Did someone drunk make this capture the traffic light
I need felicis
Apparently I'm just wrong
I'm not a robot
I'm not