This message comes from NPR sponsor KPMG
Revolutionize your Enterprise with a i
KPMG can help you harness the power of AI to unlock it
Potential and deliver growth
Maurice Reed
KPMG.
Flash NPR
This is planet money from NPR
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taken quotes
Our friends at the NPR Podcast rough translation recently put out a request on our show and on their show
Best listeners to call in with stories of times they work on
Scam
And they got almost 200 response
They turn those responses into a great episode they just published it
You can go listen to
One of the stories they included in their show was just so delightful and so Illuminating that we said
We have got to run this one as a Planet Money
So that's what today's episode is
And now I'm just going to turn the show over to Gregory Warner
The host of rough translation
In 2010
Felipe Fernandez was laid off from his it job at Hewlett-Packard in Costa Rica
Play bass Costa Rica
The layoff was a huge blow
He didn't know what he's going to do next
Someone from his family believe they didn't want me to say who
Approached him with a potential job there was a business that needed an IT person which side
Sounds good he was an IT guy
He did work so I was obviously curious
What he said was
We actually run the scam on senior citizens
The people who needed the IT guy
They were in the business of calling of people steal their money
Senior citizens in the USA
Hello Operator
Except we have a script
All you have to do is
Call and call and call until someone bites
You know the script
Ma'am I've good news for you
You have won a sweepstakes prize
A four and a half
Million dollars
All you have to do to collect that prize
Is wire a small deposit for insurance policy that is $4,500
And you can send that today by Western Union
I was very doubtful my how can you really make money out of that
But this scam is pulling in
Hundreds of deals a week
They call it deals
Each call is a deal
The scammers are called agents
And this operation like all businesses needs and IT guy
Felipe is hearing this and he's horrified
First that this is a business
Second that is relative is involved
But Philippe keeps a poker face
I immediately told him that this is not something that I can just decide right there and then
But that I will think about it
Philippic goes home any Google the phone number for the FBI
They tell him that's not our jurisdiction
You should call up the US Embassy in Costa Rica
I called them and they asked me to come in for a meeting
Which I did
And if it's like the movies do they meet you in a in a room with you know the blinds closed
It was just a conference room and in a US Embassy
In this conference room
Explains his plan
He wants to take the job
Collect information that the US authorities might use like the names of the scammers in their location
Make some license plates. I am about to take this job and I want to stop this stuff from happen
I want you to know what I'm doing so you don't think I'm one of the bad guys
But pretty much just sounded us to hear that Joe Sealy was a US Postal Inspector
He's not retired
But in 2010
He was investigating mail fraud
Specifically telemarketing scams in Costa Rica
And weirdly the hard thing about Prosecuting these cases
Was not finding the bad guys
It was finding the victims
Because it was just so embarrassing so ashamed
The victims didn't come forward
Because I felt so ashamed about falling for the
And so for Joe Huey it's kind of the reverse of the typical investigators problem
Instead of having the dead body
Try to figure out who the bad guy is
He knows the bad guy
She has to track down enough victims
To make the arrest
We needed a lot of it cuz lot of credible victims and lots of losses without lots of it comes in lots of losses
We couldn't bring cases
Joe Healy
Is sitting this conference room with Felipe the IT guy in his button up shirt liquid little guy he's 550
For not not overly
Muscular
He's trying to explain to him this isn't some quick job where you grab some license plate numbers and addresses
He would need the names of the victims
And Philippe
Is considering doing it
Heading into the criminals Den to get that information to himself
We said okay are we can't guarantee your safety because we can't be there
I know so is long as you're going into with open eyes yes or no
Data will help us
When Philippe with a kid
He never imagined himself in it
He thought he be a cop
Like his grandfather
A police chief in San Jose
Felipe remembers watching his grandfather on the local news when he solved a big case
I remember him
Yolanda and the
And the police headquarters
The way everybody looked at him
And
I grew up admiring
His sense of Duty
Felipe's grandfather used to tell him that
Seeing something wrong being done and not doing anything about it
It makes you their accomplice
Philippe thought about what he done with his wife
He just turned 30
I was out of work in this just fell on my lap
But yeah I mean
How many people can say that they put out
Bunch of bad guys in jail
At least
How many it guys can say that after the break
Felipe goes for that job interview with a scammer
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Google domains
Most of you have a great business idea
Google domains is here to help it come to life
Whatever the inspiration there is a business waiting to happen
Google domains helps make your dream real with the tools and partners to help you build your website like a
Pro and premium security features included for free
It starts with a name it becomes real with a domain
You're ready now make it happen at domains. Google / NPR to get started
If you haven't been reading Planet money's newsletter you're missing out on stories about hidden beaches and scooter Mania at
And plastic bag ban it's just the right amount of economics and Analysis served up once a week
Subscribe at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
Felipe decides
He's going to try to get this job
And what happens next is weirdly corporate
Is relative set up a meeting
It happens at a fancy restaurant
Felipe meets five guys in suits he accepts the job
And then
Pictures going to work
An office everyday
Picture wall to wall carpeting agents of cubicles working the phones the reading from a script that is pasted on each day
Desk
Behind the agents are more senior group they're called loaders
Will take over when the victim Falls for an agent's line
So
The next day the loader my call and say we didn't realize there's this other state tax
I need you to give me a call
They could start threatening you
Here's one of the scammers
Want to do that
In this process
Calling calling and demanding more more money
It go on for months
Until the victim had nothing left
There was this time a victim
Called
And she had already lost about $60,000
And she
She was crying she was crying saying
I have to go to Salvation Army to get food
You took all my money
Leica have nothing
In
They actually put it on speaker
And they started laughing
Felipe is watching them laugh at her
And he's trying to control the expression on his own face
You hear the voices you hear her crying and
He immediately started trying to imagine what she looks like
What is she going to do after she hangs up
Phone
Is there anyone near her
You know
Herb children order
Whoever
Are they going to yell at her
She gave all this money away
It's
I guess I just put myself in her shoes
And I
That was sort of a turning point
And
Uprising happen
I really
Made it personal after that
I I I wanted those guys in jail whenever I felt like not going
Whenever I felt like just quitting
I just
I remember
That laughter
It was part of a strategy
Scammers often use
Dehumanize the victim
Even the word the con artists use for Vicks
The mark
It's dehumanizing
Another these strategies was drugs
There's lots of weed people doing coke in the break room
But there was one person in the office who seem to need no substance could do this scam totally open
I'd and sober
And that was the owner
Emilio Jose Torres
If it's one of those movies with a good-looking hero in a better-looking villain
Emilio is that feeling
Scott long dark hair a surfer to business suit
He works with a guy named Max was wanted for murder in the US
Emilio had been on the radar for us authorities for years
Joe Healy the Postal Inspector
Tell me this one very surprising thing about it
He was a really good boss
To expect it to show up on time
You are expected to do the workload that he gave you for the day
You were accountable for what you did
Hand
He was fair
I find it funny used to work there when you talk about criminals but he was fair with his people
Philippe Petit really known anything about Emilio when he started working there
But I found out that Emilio was all about business
One of the first things Emilio ask me is what do you think we need
To make this more efficient
To make it more efficient with him he was all about productivity
Felipe realizes that he's not just the IT guy
He's also the only one here with actual business experience
He worked at Hewlett-Packard this giant multinational corporation and
This is his chance
The IT guy can get the arch-villain to trust
I told him we have to rewire all the phones we have a lot of interruptions
You notice all these problems
Voice over IP using this regular interface agent got a lead
Have to run upstairs the one computer in the manager's office to look up the closest Western Union they have to start
Looking where the person lives and
Philippe Chows Emilio
We can do better than this
Every agent should have their own laptop
That's how we would have done it at Hewlett-Packard
Animalia hears that and he is hooked
They buy a bunch of laptops
That will let Felipe actually record the scammer that work
But it also makes the scam more efficient
Felipe Riggs it so that the laptop will feed the scripts and what are called rebuttals
What to say
In case
Invicta mask
The question
And
So he was very
He was very happy with me
And
They used to call me filthy
Like filthy good at computers filthy good at
Improving the scam that was my nickname up Authority office
Filthy wasn't just a nickname
It was kind of an alter ego
The Phillippe adopted
Filthy will tell the dirtiest jokes
Filthy
Was also a Satanist
And filthy was also differential
I wouldn't make any eye contact I wanted them to think that I was very nerdy
Are you nerdy a little bit
I am I mean I am
I I work an it
And filthy was always faithful
To his new boss Emilio I was sort of Brownells in him
All the time
Eunos like
Man you're so young you're done
Like
Like all this stuff
So
How long did it take you to really gain Amelia's Trust
That's fast work
Yeah
He remembers one time Amelia had to run an errand
Any turn to Felipe and said
Hey filthy watch the floor for me
Yeah
Watch the guys
You know I make sure they don't do anything you're not supposed to
And
I remember
Arrow. They knew I had them
Beth Lipe or filthy
Still doesn't have the essential thing that he came here to get
After the break
Felipe tries to get
The names of the victor
Support for this NPR Podcast and the following message come from waste.com
A web platform
For creating your own professional website join Over 125 million people already using
Wix to tell their stories online
Gota wilx.com to create your website today
It has already been uneventful summer in politics
Lipizzans Battle of emigration there's a lot going on when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you what happened not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 2020 contender
OIP was going to drive me completely crazy the NPR politics podcast
There is a list that has the names of the victims but Emilio has that list
He had it in a flashdrive
All the victims in in the Excel sheets and everything then one day Felipe sees the flash drive on
Guarded and he just grabs it
But he knows that they're searching the employees when they leave the office
And sleep is worried
He's going to get caught
With this flash drive
So I took a piece of gum and I stuck it to Amelia's backpack
Guess I knew that he wouldn't get searched
When we all left
They get outside
He tells Emilio
Is that what happened I call you back looks open
And I pretended to closing I just took this flashback back
This story like so many of Felipe story to seem totally Wild
I don't have a way to confirm it or fact check it
But I can't say the joke you leave the Postal Inspector
He confirmed many of Felipe stories
And he did say that one day
Philippe handed over to us agents a flash drive
Full of victims names
Jokingly starts calling those victims hearing story after Story of people losing all their money
He realizes this is
Huge scam millions and millions of dollars
What is one more problem
Emilio is a Costa Rican citizen
The Americans can't prosecute him as long as he stays in Costa Rica
It's a Felipe
Keeps working
Keeps being the office it guy
Is there trying to figure out
How is it going to get Emilio to leave the country
It is getting harder to go to work each morning it was just
Triad
Other agent start asking him how come he doesn't get on the phone and I'm making any deals Felipe stops being able to sleep
The front of his hair falls out
Isn't have anyone you can talk to about this
I really need it to get out of San Jose
One weekend just
Take a break
He goes to his grandfather's house on the beach
Dispense
A really nice Saturday swimming and playing checkers with grandfather
It was nice
Until he gets a call
Familia
And
He called me on
Sunday
And he said that
This Linux server has crashed
And
Linux servers
Don't just crash
Piano
It's very hard for that to happen
So you knew it was a setup because he said the Linux server crash and I was something only a non it person would say
Yeah
I asked him what what's what's going on is is I know just crashed you scratch is not working like you nowhere
Turn off the phone song
He insisted you know now I need you to come back today cuz
You know I need the phone's working on Monday
Oh wow
You know first of all what is he doing there on a Sunday
And
I was really scared
I was at my grandfather's house
The weather happy nipples cheap
And I was the first time I told someone
I told him like
Listen
I'm doing this
He was very proud
He was very very proud
And I guess because he knew that he was
It was because of him
And I told him like I've been doing this for a while
I I think they found out about it and they want to kill me
So we went through everything
And maybe says well you know us
Ask grandfather I don't want you to go
Do you have to make your own decisions
So I want
And
At this big knife
13 in the back of my pants
In
It was a 4-Hour Drive
And
I
I remember the whole time I was just so nervous
What's going to happen you know in
2 hours into it I kind of came to terms with it
Casa del Rey
If I eat this is the way I go I go
This is the way I go this is where I go
You know and
I got to the office and the server has crashed
Pacific
The only thing left to do
Be an IT guy
Philippe bends over to see what's wrong with the server
And Emilio spots the knife
And a
Emily is like filthy why you have that big ass knife
Some like you call me on a Sunday
Telling me that the server crashed
And this Derek crashes
Like I thought that maybe somebody was holding you up or something
And
Oh you bought a big knife I'm like well you know you got to do what you got to do
I fix the server and I left
And yeah
That's the one time I've seen a Linux server crashed
That day
Philippe Kahn the con man
Which is what he was trying to do the whole time
And con artist
To get into the minds of their victims
They understand the stories that we tell ourselves about ourselves
And they give version back to us
You think you're generous
The comment will help you help others
I think your Thrifty
The comment has a deal for you
In this way
Felipe played into Emilio's fantasy of himself
And first last Khan
He told him
You know what a successful businessman like you needs
Condo
In Miami
You should get an apartment in Brickell Avenue that place is gorgeous like why would you have all this money if you can really
Suspended
Emilio
Never had a chance
Corsi bought the condo
He flew to Miami and
Of course
Got arrested the minute he stepped off the plane
Emilio's prosecuted convicted
Answered 7 years in federal prison
After Emilio's arrest
People start suspecting that Felipe it help the US authorities
He started getting death threats
So
Is friends at the US Embassy Ghana Visa
And got him to the states
Where
He works in it
I'm curious
Playing the role of the comment even though you were doing it for good
You weren't trying to make money you're trying to catch the bad guys
They playing that role make it harder
Be in society and trust people
And do normal
Trusting things in life
Well
I guess I read people more now
I immediately dissect everything they say and how they say it and their body language
And it changes you
Also in the way you don't see the world the same way
I literally feel bad when I see a senior citizen pushing carts in in supermarket
Or senior citizen working
You know I think
They could have been a victim
Now when Philippe just lives his life
Are goes out in the world
He can't help but think
Everything can be a con
And everybody can be a mark
Gregory Warner is the host of the podcast rough translation they have lot
Great stories from around the world including a two-parter from our own Karen Duffin
About these two brothers one of them gets kidnapped by ISIS the other one sets out to get his brother back
The show is rough translation you can get it wherever as they say you get your punch
Today Show was produced for rough translation by Autumn Barnes and Jess Jiang with music by
Play John Ellis Katie dog help with research
This planet money version of the show was produced by Liza Yeager I edited the show are supervised
Producer is Alex goldmark email us at Planet Money at npr.org you can also find us on Facebook too
Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
Planet Money is a production of NPR up Jacob Goldstein thanks for listening