Here is something that I learned
In the air above us
At 35000 FT
It is the same
Time
Everywhere
Universal time which is the time at the Greenwich Meridian
Is you
All around the planet Earth today
Buy every single
Airline and Air Force
In the world
This is Dick Henry he's an astrophysicist at Johns Hopkins University
Think about it
Are all these
Planes flying all over the Earth
A hundred miles an hour
You don't want to get confused by time zone when you're trying to keep them from crashing into each other
Dick has talked to his friend Steve hanke about this for years
Steven economist
A professor of Applied economics at Johns Hopkins and
It is not just
Pilots who need universal time
Investors needed to
You can trade
24-hours a day almost around the clock and gold currencies
Stocks and everything else under the sun
And
Those are
All timestamp using universal time
Henke and Henry were telling me about all this because
Proposal
Yes Steven I want to abolish the time zone
No more
Time zones
We want 24-hour World Time everybody on the same clock
You're you're you're fully serious about this
Is this a serious proposal
Course it's a serious proposal
If it's 10 in New York
It is 10 in Shanghai
And Sydney
And Nairobi
It is 10
Everywhere
Hank and Henry have also designed a whole new efficient standardized calendar
The hanke Henry permanent calendar
His hanky Henry
Time and calendar
It's rigged up with an extra week every five or six years so that the calendar is
Standard year-to-year
Like January 1st is always a Monday
Come on we waste so much time for your dusting calendar is your year it's unnecessary
What would happen if the hanke Henry calendar where adopted oh my goodness
There'd be a couple of years a bumps and grinds if people read
Adjusted their schedule
But then we'd have it at an absolute
Optimum
And it would never ever change for the rest
Of human history
This is
Very
Hard for me to imagine
Two guys changing the way time works for everybody
Forever
And yet
About a hundred fifty years ago there was
Another guy
The hanke Henry of his age
Who decided
I am going to completely change the way time works
For everybody in the United
And
Everybody in the United States is still living on his clock
Today
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm finally home time as we know it in the u.s. today
On a single day in 1883
It happened then because this new technology the railroad was completely transform
Arming the world
I'm creating
In all kinds of ways
The world we live in now today in the show
What
Time is it
And why
Support for this podcast and the following message come from each raid
With all the jargon
Investing can feel like a foreign language
E-Trade makes investing simp
By providing personalized support and guidance in terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as $500
And then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro to invest at each rate
For more information visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC
Membership
There are so many different labels on food these days
Organic
Non-GMO
Fairtrade cage
Freehand gathered it's overwhelming
I sometimes jokingly refer to it as the NASCAR ring of our food like it has a new episode making
Sense of food
Find it and more by searching
Life kit all guides
In apple podcasts
Can I start having you just introduce yourself
Sure I'm Alexis Macross and I'm a professor of history at Southern Methodist University in Dallas TX
Can you tell me about sort of your background in time
My background didn't I
Well I was born to live
She was born she lived
And eventually she wrote a book about the history of timekeeping
In the United States
Start the story in the early 1800s
The concept of time in the early eighteen-hundreds is much
Looser than it is for us today
Some watches at the time didn't even have minute hands
People are mostly Farmers living local lives governed by the
If I need to travel to probably catch a stagecoach
I need to know like I need to get to the stagecoach Depot in the morning but
Stagecoaches
Capri Blue schedules they did not leave precisely at 9 at the top of the hour
They rang the bell they let people know we're about to leave
They hung around they took off very slowly
Because nobody's timekeeping was precise
Got their work clock
But every clock in town showed a slightly different
Time
Gradually
Life Starts
To speed up
Steamships
Factory
The mail it comes all the time now
People need to coordinate more
So inch-pound a degree
Okay
This particular clock
Shows the official local time
For our town
Like how many local times were there
How many towns in America were there
How many places were there
There were
23 local times in Indiana
27 in Illinois
38th and Michigan
It switches every few minutes that each small community
He's going to have a different Sun Time by 10 minutes 5 minutes
3 minutes
This is Richard White
Historian
He wrote a book about railroads
And railroads are going to become the
Key part of the story
All of human history before trains
The fastest anybody could travel Overland with the speed
The panda with railroads
That suddenly changes
Before it could take a month to go from New York to Chicago
And by the 1850s you can do it in
Date
And all my journey a train would roll through
You know maybe hundreds of different local time
Clearly this time world is not built
4 train
I mean obviously it's confusing if you're riding on the train
And also it's just
Dangerous
There were a couple cases where people running the train Scott confused about the time
And trains
Crashed into
What's the weather like
We have got to find a way to coordinate this among ourselves
And they come up with a system
They met twice a year and arrange their schedule
And what they did is each
Train ran on its own time
If you run the New York Central Line
You set the time to Albany New York
No matter what time it was in the exact place the train stops along the way it's always New York time
Zoe train was like
It was like the train itself had a timezone almost you're the train is a traveling times
Was that confusing for passengers
Yes
Could very confusing for passengers
If you get off of a railroad
Car
In a place like Buffalo would you would do is look up and you would see three or four different
Turn clocks would be much like we see in the air
In airports you can see all it's that time in Copa
Set timing at
To set time in Beijing
When you got off the train you would see
The time is it set for the New York Center
UBC the time that it said for the trains coming out of Boss
You see three or four different clocks each of them giving you a different time all them different from the time on your watch
And all of them different from the time where you were standing
Do you have to figure out
What time to get on the train by those clock
At the center of his whole ridiculous time system
Is one man
William
Allen
He's like the railroads
Time
Tsar when his Jobs is
Kateri of the general time convention
It is his job to keep track of every schedule every train size
Timezone every
End
He's not like a fancy Railroad
Baron
He's more like a bureaucrat
A newspaper description of him from the time it said that he had
Start of a nervous vibe that you look like an Episcopal preacher because he wore this
High collared vest that button up the front
Passengers were complaining all the time about this really confusing system Alan would have heard from them there
Staying calm on
Wheeze
Fix this
There's a high school principal name Charles Dowd
Who has become obsessed with
Changing the way we do time
Yeah yeah we all know people like this it just gets fixated
That is like all right everybody
Picture this
We divide the country into
Sort of vertical
Ariel
Like
Zone
And then eat
It is the same
He tries to commits the railroads
He writes letters back and forth with William a Fallon on the railroad
Islands like no
Everything's fine
But by the late 1870s
It's clear that this world where every town and every train has its own time
Just
Isn't working anymore
Trains are everywhere now they're moving people from town to town
Moving stuff
All the way across the country
America is becoming less
A collection of isolated towns
And more one big
Country
Around 1880 this one scientist
Hussein
I got all these meteorologists all over the country trying to coordinate their observations
No one can figure out like huzzah what shooting star when
The railroads
Should just divide the country into a few
Factors
Each an hour apart
Like Zone
Sounds of time
An island finally decides
Okay
The principal and the scientist
Are right
The era of every town having its own time is over
We need
To standardize
Haim
And I am the man
To do it he wants
Everybody to go and standard time he wants to obliterate local
So he engages in this
Vas campaign
Bobbing
City council's
And Mares
And
Astronomical Observatory
And anybody who was involved in
Timekeeping
Allen is
Not really Consulting the general public on this
Republic is mostly into it there are some people who are skeptical there was apparently
One preacher in Tennessee who said
We follow
God's time
Not railroad time and
He smashed
Is watch on Pulpit with a hammer to make the point
But
Allen isn't so concerned about that
This negotiation is happening in the various Halls of power
And it's kind of a
Struggle for a
Authority
Who has the authority to do something
When Alan goes to the Boston railroads there like we observe ettore and that's what we're going
Keep doing
Sorry William Baldwin
So then
I'll go to Harvard
Any astronomers there are like a great idea
Will adopt.
So then the Boston Railroad
And the city government of Boston agree to accept
The new standard
Ben Allen does New York New York
Boston did this
You better do it too or else the railroad time might come to be known as quote
Boston
Time
And you're like oh my God you're right we are on
But
The Attorney General of the United States
Looks at Allen's plan and is like weight
The railroads want to tell everyone in the whole country what time it is
No
Only Congress can do something like that
Any orders
All the government agencies to ignore Allen and the railroads
Government business is going to be happening on good old-fashioned DC local time
What island does convince
Most of major cities in America to go with the railroads plan for Standard Time
And he's successful
So I wouldn't necessarily call it
Railroad time
What's more like William F Allen time
He would love to hear you say
I'm sure
I'm sure he would
So here is Allen's play
America is going to go from being a country where every town has its own time
To a country where there are
Different
X
Call them
Time zone
And this new time era
Is going to begin on a single day
It's one of those things are you given exact date
November 18th 1883
We went on Standard Time
Alan has already done a lot of legwork like figuring out all the time changes
Rita's the train schedule
Send out notices
Newspapers are announcing this so people can get ready
And everyone
The observatories the cities the railroad companies
Has agreed that local time will be abolished
And the new era of Standard Time Will begin
On Sunday
November 8th
Big moment
Arrive
At noon
Which way does a simple question
How do you tell everyone when it's the new moon
At the break
The day
2 noon
Support for this podcast and the following message come from odoo
Monte Vista business
Check out ododos new business game
Scale-up
It's fun it's Mars and odoo offers it for free shipping included
Use promo code money on Odio o.com
Scale-up
When's the last time you had a really good workout
None of your bicep
If your brain
I'm shankar vedantam host of hidden brain
Listen every week flex your mind
Cheer was Alan's plan
Or part of the plan
Observatories around the country it would be watching the Sun in the sky to determine the exact
Hot
For example the Naval Observatory in DC would be waiting for noon in the new Eastern Time Zone
At that moment
The Observatory would send out a pulse over the Western Union Telegraph line to announce
It's noon
That pulse would run up to New York
Where activated something called a
Time ball
There were time balls in a bunch of cities and
I
Love this part
If you have ever seen the ball drop in Times Square on New Year's Eve you have seen a Time ball that is like a call back to this 19th
Centra technology
And what it was is there would be
These balls
That would sit up on like
Pools on the top of tall building
And they were designed to fall the instant a telegraph Pole
So everybody would know exactly what time it was
And they would gather around the time ball and set
At their watches
And ships at
See you would see a ball and be like set the chronometer everyone
And that's the way that they Coordinated Time Okay so
In New York
There was a time ball on the roof
Of the Western Union.
So
On the morning of November 18th
That is where William Allen and his family went to wait
4 News
People around the city we're staring up at this time ball end
According to some newspapers they were nervous
Like
Is this going to work
Are there going to be train crashes
The noon of New York's local time arrived about
4 minutes
Before
The new Nerf standard so the bells of one Church
Rain at
The true local time
And then
4 minutes later
Pulse goes out from the Naval Observatory
Alan and his family see the time ball drop
Right now
And it's noon
Again
People would come to call this the day of
2 Nunes
But this
Second moon
Wasn't just noon in New York
It was noon in Boston
And Philadelphia
And Charles
And this new noon it's our new its they are now on our time back to 1883
And just the same way there's an Eastern Time Zone and it's noon and I'm sitting down in California
Is going to be noon
It's noon
Same time
We are living in William Allen's world
William a Fallon realize
That
Time is not just
Some objective measurement of where the sun is in the sky
Is also about the needs of
Society
And the railroads had created a society that needed a new kind of time
On the day of two noons by the way
Everything went fine
Some people didn't even notice the change didn't bother to change their clocks until weeks later there are no records of trains colliding on the tracks
It turned out to be kind of like white
UK
The next day the Attorney General
The one who's been so against William Allen
Big-time plan
He was supposed to take the express train from DC
Philadelphia
People say this story is apocryphal but the Chicago Tribune wrote at the time that the Attorney General
Quote
Walks down the platform leisurely with his watch and hand
Define that he arrived about 8 minutes and 12 seconds
Too late
The railroads are gone ahead without him
Emperor wild of course there were a few holdouts against this system as there always are
A few towns who just
Love their local time
And the federal government did not officially adopt Standard time until 1918
They didn't technically abolish localtime until 1966
But of course by then
Everybody was already operating on Standard Time
Has Richard white told me at the railroad said look
You can go buy whatever time you want
But not
If you want to make your train
When a bunny has got a new newsletter
Sign up for it at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
It is one story once a week plus unless you like
One reader named Vince said that it is brief but informative
Plain-spoken but not Elementary thank you been
Subscribe at npr.org
Splash Planet Money newsletter
This is also a good week to follow Planet Money on social media there is lots of fun of behind-the-scenes stuff up on our Twitter and Instagram
You can see it Sarah Gonzales showing off
The special blanket that she uses to stay warm and are very cold office
And Jacob and Elsa got to meet comedian Ali Wong who as far as we know is the only comedian ever to shout out
Planet Money in a Netflix special
You'll be a change. Comedians
Check it out Atlanta
Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Ghazi and edited by Jacob Goldstein
Algoma catimini supervising producer and Brian or start at the show
Special thanks to Rachel Cohn by the Jaeger and our new intern
Cynthia better Pizza
If you want support kind of money one great thing to do is to leave us a review in your podcast app
It helps other people find a show
I'm finally home
This is NPR
Thanks for listening
By the way there is a plaque
Commemorating William F Allen's big accomplishment in Union Station in Washington DC
And Charles out at the high school principal Future come up with this idea first
Was
Killed in 1904