Support for Planet Money
And the following message
Did come from Michigan Economic Development
Incorporation
If you want to start or grow your business
Michigan
Is the place
And make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure oportun
California has a booming economy and a lot of people are flocking there for job
But there are not enough houses being built to accommodate all of these new
People
And because now you have so many people vying for so few available
Homes and Apartments
The cost of those homes
Has been rising at a really
Fast
People are dying on the streets
Because of the affordability
Crisis that's Gavin Newsom
The governor of Calif
And he has a very straightforward plan to fix
Estates housing
Build more housing
We talk about doubling
Dublin is not going to solve the problem is going to mitigate it won't solve it
Quadruple
Begin saw it
What's the time is would agree with this idea
Supply and demand
Increase the supply of homes
The price should come out
What building new homes can be very unpopular on the local level
Because it can lead to
More traffic it can put more strain on
City services
And it can affect the
The character of a city
And ultimately
The decision
How many homes get built in California is not up to the governor
It is up to local city council
That's who tells developers how many new homes they are allowed to build and so Governor Newsom new
If he wanted more homes
He was going to have to get
Hundreds of City council's all over the states
On board
And many of them were
But he says there was one city
That was particularly
I mean the city council just
Plano
Not interested
They just on their nose
Set the states and Newsome decided to do something
Drastic
He took that City to court
That's right the state of California
Is suing
One of its own cities
Tenacity
Happens to be
My hometown
Huntington Beach
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm dharius Raffi on we are here from the indicator Planet Money short daily podcast about economic I
Ideas
10 minutes or less every weekday
Earlier this summer at the indicator Windsor Calif
And we came up with two very different stories
One about the battle over at 4.
Housing
And what about how the very rich are protecting their very expensive houses with private firefighters
We put those stories together here and you know if you like what you hear you can head over to the indicator from Planet Money to hear more wherever
Agriculture podcast
So after the break
Why the governor of
California sued and idyllic
Dreamy beach towel
We're one of our producers
Just happened to a grown up
This message comes from NPR sponsor each race
Investing your money shouldn't require Moving Mountains
No matter how much or how little experience
E-Trade makes investing simp
Along with great value they provide the tools and support you need to navigate the market
All to help your money work hard for you
For more information visit etrade.com NPR E-Trade Securities LLC
Membership
Oh and one more thing do not forget to check out Planet money's weekly email newsletter
That is it npr.org
Lanabunny newsletter
It is a weekly email on everything from my doctors get paid so much to what Wimbledon can tell us about the perks of
Being a generalist
That is npr.org Planet Money newsletter
Now onto the show
Huntington Beach is a Seaside community that is about an hour south of Los Angeles
And it's known as Surf City USA right there and that is because it has these like beautiful
Iconic kind of golden beaches there beautiful beach
They are
It's a nice place to grow up and the legal battle that is currently roiling this
Idyllic Beach City
It Centers on one Street
Edinger Avenue
Which happens to be
The street that I grew up on this is getting weird
It's weird right my town on my block and now it's at the center of this lawsuit
They could determine the future of housing policy
For the entire State of California
And I want to get a sense of what this means for the people who actually live there
So I talked to a long time
My name is Freddy
Last name is Rafi on and I am your father
My dad he moved to Southern California from Iran 40 years ago and in that time he has really learned to embrace the honey
Lincoln Beach lifestyle he can always be found where
Board shorts and a t-shirt
With his like Maui Jim sunglasses on it
Forehead uninterrupted tan since at least 1980
Really yeah he's just like the ultimate Huntington Beach
And we met up
At our old apartment
On Edinger
Here we are at all six
Tengo unit 610
I lived it video
18 years and when we first moved to the stretch of Edinger
This was not
Anything special I mean the street was known
For like the old crumbling shopping mall in the
The corner
Like a bandit
Today though
It's known for a cheek open their lifestyle Plaza
Luxury
With all the amenities
Like the street has just
Utterly transformed
And that
All this construction and new development it really
Doesn't sit well with
They should stop they should leave Huntington Beach the way it is
And go do this thing's
Other places other City
It's not Huntington Beach anymore
And my dad is not the only person who feels
Anxiety about the
The community lights
That Huntington Beach flavor
That we all moved here
That's Eric Peterson
The mayor of Huntington
He campaigned on the promise to
Stop the overdevelopment
And since taking office he has been a vocal opponent
Of Governor Newsome's housing
Thought that there's going to be some Central planning up in Sacramento
That's going to disseminate how every city and county looks
Right when it's not what we want
You're not going to turn us into West LA
You're not going to turn us into South Bend anywhere like that when you were talking to
People from hainan
There was a sense that the state is trying to turn this
Idyllic Little Beach Community into some kind of bustling Metropolis or some sort of anonymous
Hondo written
Outdoor lifestyle
Nightmare about all these
Buildings that are
Just destroying the character of my Beach City
Things that these concerns are a little overblown not asking for high-rises when I ask you
Be possible just increases Supply modestly
Show us you give a damn about
The people that are commuting to 3 hours to come in and work in your restaurant choice you give a damn about the
The kids there that can't afford to buy a home there even ready
This fight over my town and my block it actually goes back a few years
Pickles
City council meeting from 2015
We don't need a congested City
We don't need giant buildings the previous Council
Soda City down the river
This is insanity
We are outraged
But that monstrosity
That's under construction at Beach and Ellis these are your people.
Give me very emotional when it comes to
Zoning policy
Housing
And at that meeting the city council voted
To put a halt on new development on Edinger Avenue
And that was the moment
Did set this entire conflict
So California has this law that's been on the books for
50 years
And the losses that every city has to identify exactly how much housing it
At every income
And make a plan to build a
Houses
By limiting the number of new
Units allowed on
Street tires Edinger Avenue
Huntington Beach
Spell out of
Science
That plan
For decades though that would not have been in
I mean this lot has gone largely unenforced
For 50 years
Cities have never faced any consequences
Is for naught
Actually building the house
That changed when Gavin Newsom
The office
He decided he was going to start enforcing this law
He decided to start
With my hometown
We should say Huntington Beach in the state of California
They belong had an acrimonious
It's a republican stronghold in a deeply Democratic state
And the two entities have been suing each other back and forth over a whole range of issues
4 years
Mark Peterson thinks that this latest legal challenge
It's really more about
Political retribution that is about housing Paula
It was strictly him going out
The nearest so many cities
That aren't compliant
Much worse than
But he's just
Targeting us
For some reason
Devin Newsome denies that this lawsuit is politically motivated
And he says all this noise at Huntington Beach is making that is just them trying to score political
My gosh
This is a bit of crocodile
Tears
Thought of respect
Exactly what they were doing they were intentional and what
They were well aware of a lot of nothing
Should surprise him about this I think they're finding excuse
This fight
Between these two men
It's going to have real consequences
Is For Real
Remember my dad the one who didn't want to see
See new development on his blog
Btd6 yes my impeccably well Tans dad
He doesn't live on that
In fact he doesn't live in Huntington Beach
He was forced to move
Shortly after the mares development hauled went into effect
They raised the ranch really quick in the Bible
Year-and-a-half the rent was raised
40% near me
Any got to point that I just couldn't afford the rent so I had to move out of the area
This makes sense right this city limited the supply of housing in that area
The supply goes down
Price goes up
That's good news if you own in that area
But it's not good news if your renter
Like my dad
I practically raised welts on my kids here
And I really like it
It was a nice place
And they said good City I love Huntington Beach I would love to
To come back and live
But with the rents going off as much as they are I don't think I ever be able to come back
Darius your dad is a low-income renter who was pushed out of his
Bike riding
He is
Exactly the kind of person the governor Newsom has been trying to help with this lawsuit
Right but my dad is also a
Fierce opponent of new building
Yeah which is hard for me to wrap my head around
How old is my dad support a policy
That is actively against his own interest
You would rather
If I have to leave Huntington Beach
To keep the city the same way it is rather than
Be able to live here
But see it change
Yes
This is what so challenging about all day
I mean people do not slot
Neatly into these little category
Pro-development anti-development
Pearl affordability
A huge expanse
It's extremely emotional and it
And it's where you live is part of your identity
And identities
Messi it's
It's not always rational
It doesn't
Fit neatly into an economic model
Kind of like Edinger Avenue
Exactly
Okay for our next story I'm going to head out and hand it off to my fellow producer on the indicator constanza
The guy Ardo coming up after the break
What hiring
Super expensive
Private firefighters
Maybe a good
Deal
Support for NPR and the following message come from Hotwire
Will it be great to get king crab for the price of imitation crab
Venues Hotwire
The travel site that hides the hotel name so you can get a four star hotel at a two-star price
Book your next trip at Hotwire
All book
King spinal
It has already been uneventful summer Impala
Yeah between the 2020 debate and the president's battle over immigration there's a lot going on when there's news
You need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you
Not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 20/20
Contender olympios going to drive me completely crazy
The NPR politics
Subscribe
For a second story we had to another part of California
To check out the booming business of private firefighters
The bird firefighting industry is still pretty new
A lot of the companies are based in California
Like firebreak protection
Systems in Ventura County
And you know this do not look like regular firehouses
I like big brick building with flags out front or giant red trucks
Fire Protection Systems is in a strip mall
Next to a company that installs skylight
Hi hi
Inside there's the specious office and like
Half a dozen big
Beefy firefighter types sitting at the store
Cubicles look
Computer screen
Stop music playing in the background
Chris Brandi neon supplies
He's a big guy
Strapping
Gray hair and mustache
Deep tan mucus look like firefighters
Right now it's
Holy dip
Chris used to sell firefighting
Equipment to homeowners and insurance
Things like sprinkler system special
Flame retardant foam
But then
She says
A couple of insurance companies came to him and said
Hey you know a lot about fires right
So what if we hire you to fight.
I said sure sounds like
Why not
In fact it's the insurance
They're really feeling the business
Is a private firefighter
It started getting serious about it around 20 years ago
When Wildfire started getting worse
And development in high-risk fire areas
Wheelie started
Taking off
Karen Bradshaw is up
Professor of law at Arizona State University
She studies wildfires
Stuff you think of the outskirts of for example Los Angeles
People who are living in the million-dollar homes tend to be those were attacked into these beautiful forested Enclave
Suddenly insurance companies were seeing their most valuable homes
Regularly at risk of burning
So they started hiring their own firefighting
Whose job it would be
Specifically protect their homes
Technically all these places are covered by like the city or the county or whatever so
Why
Do you guys eat
2xist black resources
The Quinn house baby enough
Resources to go to every single house
Krishna has contracts with
Several insurance
And about a dozen employees
And they deploy three fire trucks
Which don't really look like fire truck
They're kind of small like I was just like a regular Truck Yeah
But they're equipped with hoses and a 200
Gallon tank of water
And Chris and one of his employees
Ryan Barbie
Give us a little tour of the
Sawyer equipment
Back here your pack
Your helmets
We would a laptop with right in your truck where the passenger side
Huge map
Yep to all these little green. You see on this map are all our houses that we
Take care of
Green thoughts are the ones that you cover
Are there green there's yellow
The definition of companies
When a fire breaks out Chris and his team will get a call over the radio
Did you just hear that
What is a
This is a vegetation fire
Okay.
Ron Rice. You said it's on right
Turns out they didn't need
The fire was already be
But when they do need to respond Chris and his team will
Spring attack
Drive up to the area near
The fire
Find houses they are responsible for
Yellow.
And do something he called a hot lap
Which involves going around the house and clear away all the flammable brush
And spring special flame retardant foam around
If the fire comes closer to the house
Chris and his team will fight the fire
Sometimes alongside the public
Glee from the guys
Using most of the same app
Equipment firefighters
Big jacket
Helmet axe
First aid kit
You know pocket snacks man they get you through the day
Is that right in the pocket snacks
Oh yeah sometimes when you go to a fire we left
We are 42 hours or something like that
We're out on
42 hours came home shower
Shave
Slept a couple hours came back out
Just like the bubble leaf
But there is one major
If a house is not one of the green or yellow dots on Chris's
Computer screen
They leave it alone
Daddy said if the house isn't on my list
I'm not going to go to
It's
Stuff I think
Chris is quick to say that the insurance companies
Have sent them to trailer parks to fight fires they are also two very modest homes it's not
Mansions there
Protecting
And he says the law to protect homes in the immediate vicinity of the
Because you know if those homes catch fire it threatens the insurer
And he says penis team have saved a lot of houses
We figured we save someone around 21 houses over the last few years
La Salazar Park
That would be the pocket
It's of the insurance
Chris won't say exactly how much
She gets paid from an insurance company
But he says it's
In the tens of thousands of dollars
A year
But definitely less than half a mil
We did get that much
Well that may seem like a lot insurance companies have
Clearly decided that it's cost-effective
Did for them to hire Chris and his team
Especially if they're going to be saving this multimillion-dollar mansion
Karen Bradshaw of Arizona State University
Says more and more pricey homes being built in these
High-risk areas next
Forested wilderness
Hiring private firefighters is probably going to continue to be cost-effective for insurance
The reason being that Wildfire risk is still quite small
And the value of these homes in the number of these homes is really quite large
Chris says he's already seen his industry grow a lot just in the last couple of
Have you pulled up to this one house and there was
Four five different
Private agencies
Sitting there
Everybody's in different houses it was
Pretty wild never seen that before
I really like all the trucks are sitting in front of the house and they're protecting
So where is growing up in looking at our houses and there's one of them and I'm like where you guys from
They're from all over the world
They also are working for insurance companies
But now it's not
Individuals have started hiring private firefighters to
Christmas last year
When the fires got really bad
They start getting calls everyday
Some people begging them
To come protect their home
He had no idea what
Charge for that service
So he started calling around to other companies
For 24-hours was like 20000 or 25000 was
NFR year just for the wine
I was kind of surprised cuz you know you said it mean
Palot
And this just
Doesn't sit very well with a lot of pee
Write Karen Bradshaw says we have this idea in the US
Firefighters are supposed to be publicly funded they're supposed to work for the
The people protect us all equally
Not protecting expensive house
Super cheap house or you know
Annie's Mansion before a trailer park
And it becomes a real question which I think is
True in so many places in American society or the government
Has historically provided some degree of provision of a public good like education but over time perhaps
The government provision of that good has diminish and admits that
Private Solutions I private education come up and people become concerned about the differential income effects that result
And just as in the case with education
Having enough money
To get a private service
Instead of the publicly-available service can have life
Changing effects
Take Paradise
The lower-income town in northern California that was burned To The Ground by one of the fires last year
Thousands of residents last
Their homes
The whole town was basically destroyed
Meanwhile Kim Kardashian's home was
Along with her neighbor's house
She went on Ellen a few days later to talk about it
We were fortunate enough
I'm blessed enough
We were able to get private firefighters
They saved our home and saved our neighborhood
In gratitude for her home being saved
Kim presented Ellen with a giant check
For $200,000
Made out
The California fire
These stories were produced by constanza guyardo fact-checked by Emily Lange and edited by Patty Hirsch
Planet Money version was produced by Rachel Cohn during woods and Cynthia better be stopped
Also we are looking for an intern
If you're smart
If you're curious if you have a strange and inexplicable love for economics you should apply right now
It is a paid internship and it is in New York and it's a lot of fun to get to hang out with us and we could hang out with you so definitely apply
More daily economic stories like these search for the indicator on your podcast app and hit subscribe
The indicator and Planet Money are Productions of NPR
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
Thanks for listening