This message comes from
NPR sponsor
Weather Snowflake
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock.
Data Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com
1 / NPR
Who was the president
1879 and 1879 the president was somebody that we've all heard about and nobody really knows y&r
Rutherford B Hayes
Is is he the one with the
Long bushy sideburns
Or the long pointy beard
I'm trying to take
Can you really tell the difference between all those guys really what kind of stands out is James Garfield was a big player in this.
Because he has absolutely
Piercing blue eyes
Ice chip blue eyes
But the rest of them
Heather Cox Richard
Sin is a
Professor of America
React Boston
College
Isn't politics
Economy
And she said she was all the old presidents like she knows
Hudson's
I really know the old guys
Really well cuz I just live with
Who is your favorite President
Abraham Lake
I have enough to ask
Okay but back to Rutherford
Heather says he's actually a surprise
Appraisingly important forgettable president because of
How he be
Became president
His election was super cat
This other guy sandals
Tilden had won the
Popular vote by a pretty big margin but people are saying Tilden only one because
Three Southern States weren't letting black voters vote
Even though this was against
It's the law black people at this point
We're supposed to be like today
But the Southern States
It's very intimidating and terrorizing black voters at
At the polls
Like by holding
Target practice
Nearby
Holy sites
South
Technically they're not
Stopping Black voting but you know if they're holding rifle practice
Chanel most people are going to show up
So government officials go down today
Estates to figure out
Can we even trust these
And the Democrats
Republicans
Are trying to work things out among themselves
Rutherford make some promises to them like he says
Kill point someone from their party to be
Postmaster General apparently that's
Really important back then you make some other promises but that is
Basically how he wins The Electoral College ultimately says
Yes Rutherford
You are now the
A lot of people already or calling him Rother fraud behaves because he's been elected by fraud
His accidency they called him
A Rutherford B Hayes Road accident see they called him his accidency yes I did
Name-calling
Impala
We've come so far
Okay so there are a ton of furious
Democrats
Two thought they should have had
This election
And they're like we cannot let this happen again they set their eyes on the neck
Presidential alert
And this time
They start zeroing in
On
Soldier
You see there was a law on the books
What's that said if
Enough black
People complained about intimidation at polling
Places
The government would send
Soldiers to protect
At the time black voters tended
To vote Republican so Democrats hate this Soldier law there like if we didn't have federal soup
Supervision
We could control
The outcomes
Of our election
The South
And they come up with this idea
Something that has never been tried
Simply starve the government until they did what we wanted
By holding a gun to the head of the treasury
Democrats decide
Stop funding
Unless
The country makes it up
Rhyme for the military to
Protect black voters
Kohl's
What did they call it back then did they call it a shutdown
No they called it the the rider Fighter the appropriation
Some people called it the writer
Horse and Rider is basically just
A provision that
Is tacked onto an Appropriations Bill headlines that said
This is the name of this particular event what there were we're headline saying
The Confederates have taken over our government
Because it really appeared to most people to be a continuation of the Civil War
Well hello and welcome to Planet Money Heather Cox Richardson it's a pleasure to be here
I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm out the Chang today on the show it's the longest government shutdown
Ever and to Mark the occasion we're taking it way back
To the first shutdown
When a bunch of Southerners tried to Ram through
Congress
They couldn't get done
With a war
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Snowflake
The only data warehouse
House built for the claw
Today organizations need the
That rapid data inside
Let's bring to stay a step ahead of the
With snowflake
You can instantly and infinite
Scale your data warehouse
What's with the touch of a button
Delivering deep insights at any time
For all you
Start your
Towards data-driven decision
Snowflake.
NPR
Order to understand the first
Government shutdown
Ever we really need to take
In 1861 almost all of the southerners who were in Congress
Surrendered their seat
To go fight in the Civil War as Confederate
It's on the battlefield
To support slavery
And join their new government
Confederate States
America
Then Democrats were little
Different and Republicans were leading the charge for black rights
The Republicans are the ones who said we need to end the enslavement of other human beings and ultimately we need to
To guarantee that African-American men have the right to vote
Civil War
They're totally powerless
They had
Left Congress
But the
You slowly start weaning there
Fourteen years after the war
They gained control of both Chambers
And just picture this we're talking about actual Confederate officers who
Who fought against the Union
So astonishing because really they've been fighting on the battlefield
For four years and this is not a little war just you know we're talking for years I just
Destroyed country
You know hundreds of thousands of dead billions lost
And
And these guys have literally been on the field shooting
At the same people that they're going to be sitting Within
In Congress we like actually shooting at people who were other congressmen
These are literally the same guys this is not like it mean
They weren't necessarily on the exact same battlefield but yes
These in Congress are people who wore the uniform for the United
What States government
Or for the Confederate States of America
And tried to kill each other
And with these Democrats
Couldn't do on the battlefield
They decide
They're going to do in Congress
Stop
Black rice
Only this time not
With air rifle
With their
Per stream
Democrats
Hey president
Surfride we will fund the army
But only if it becomes illegal for the Army to print
Tech black voters
At the polls
We will fund the courts
But only if it becomes illegal for the Army to protect black voters
Their number of cartoons in the newspapers about how the Confederates have taken back over Washington and how they are
Liberty starving the United States
Treasury the same way that they starved Union prisoner
Annies images
Prisoners as skeleton sing boy this feels awfully familiar what are Democrats saying at the time are they like
Really proud of this where they bragging about
Starving the government as a Setter shutting the government down
Absolutely
Southerners absolutely there like we are back in town
And we one of them literally gives interview to a newspaper and what she says
We were crazy to leave during the Civil War we should have just stayed in Congress and got in our way by not funding the government
But there is one member of Congress introduced
Angular who is Kelly Rutherford
Be this
Is total intimidation you cannot cave
To the Democrats
James A Garfield from Ohio Civil War veteran is Garfield the one with the nice blue eyes that you
You keep mentioning
Exactly
Oh I can see the eyes
See what he looks like
Okay look at this
Okay but like if you had to
To cheer the cute president from the late 19th century I don't I don't think you would be the
James A Garfield
Timmy takes the 19th century cake but whatever he was the minority leader of the House of Representatives are Republican
And he says
This is completely outrageous Democrats can't get what they want through the normal process
So they are just
Destroying
The government
Hayes and Garfield look at what they're doing and they say this is Revolution
And this is revolutionary
And this is a complete perversion of the way the American government is supposed to work you affection cannot shut down
Down the government
Cannot
Starve the United States government to death
To get its way
Once you have admitted that as a legitimate tactic of governance
You've destroyed our America
Constitution CB is
Condense
He needs to
Dig Inn
No compra
Rather be
We feel very bad that rather fraud has take all these years so we're rebranding are rather friend
Notorious rbh writes in his diary
This will be a severe
Perhaps a long
I do not fear it
I do not
Even Reddit
Damn yeah
Now every time the Democrats try to sneak in this
Ryder this
No more
Protection for black voters at the
Kohl's recipe comes in with a v
He vetoes five
Bill's Democrats eventually give in and end up funding all but
One small part of the
It's basically a very many shut down and Rutherford B Hayes to Claire's
Victory says the Democrats didn't want to fund
The Army the executive and legislative branches
And Republicans
Stop that
Heather says it's
It's hard to track down the precise
Date this shutdown end
And it but she doesn't really doesn't matter
A couple hundred Court workers weren't paid but they basically just build the government later
This was not a fight about
This was a fight
About principles
Taking the government hostage felt
So radical
So over-the-top and ultimately so pointless that
No one tries this tactic again for almost a hundred
People recognize that
You could not governed by extremism
And that system of government really didn't happen again until the modern era because there was a
The premium on
Abiding by our constitutional norms and by working things out between the different parties that wanted different things
But apparently
A hundred years
Is just long enough
To forget the lessons of History
Budget rules change in the night
1970s and shutdown start to
Wheat back in
Bit by bit
There are
A few small shut down
70s
80s but it was house Speaker Newt Gingrich who returned the shutdown
To it's fully weaponized status in the 90
He use the tactic
Weiss and at one point close the government
For 21 days
That set the record for the longest shutdown
Ever
Until
Now
Shut down
Are back
And what's significant about the rise of the
Tactic of shutting down the government the present is it once again it's being Advanced by absolute
Spike's dream is to say
We don't want to compromise we want things our way
And that is not part of our American system which
Has checks and balances that has rules
Heather posted an 11 parts
Thread on Twitter
About the similarities
Between the current government shutdown over border wall
And the very first shut down
Black voter
She says
This is what Hayes and Garfield
Do it again
People who had convinced themselves that what they wanted
Was worth making everyone suffer
The idea that a few people
Few men a few white men should control American society
Is not at all unlike
The ideologies of the people currently in charge of the Republican Party
And that argument that in fact they are the ones who should
Say what is right
For America despite what the rest of us think
Is not
At all unlike with the Confederates were doing in 1879
Always should say that Heather describes herself as a Lincoln Republican and she says she gets hate mail
Dolphin boats
But Tesla
Criticizing the current government
Shutdown is not about her purse
This is just a terrible.
Tactic it never works
And what it does is it backfires on the faction that does it
So the people who are backing the shutdown
Essentially
Have to opt
They either have to be assuming that they're going to be able to
To control government entirely that is take over the government and never let anybody else in it
Which is a terrifying thought
Or they have to assume that their faction is going to go down in flames be
Because
There has never been a case where
Shutdown has ultimately ended in making that faction look better than
And it did before
The former Confederate Democrats who orchestrated the very first shut down
They didn't get what they wanted out of it they didn't stop soldiers from protecting black voters at polls
Of course yes they did later get what they wanted by making it so hard for African Americans to even register
What about
But
Didn't get that
Through the shutdown
Of 18/7
By the way we did try to find out
The exact moment that the first shutdown ended because of the center for legislative archives
Unfortunately we are closed
Normal operation
Due to a lack of appropriation
I'm shut down
Support for NPR
In the following message
Come from service
Making the world of work
Work better for
They're cloud-based
Man solution
Deliver digital work
Nike react
Great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
Ready for your hole
Servicenow digitizes the work your people happy
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
To make people more productive
More at servicenow
No.com
If you have a story idea send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Today show with
By Sally Helm in Darien Woods
Brian ter set editor show and Alex goldmark Hisar Superbuy
Rising producer
I'm Sarah Gonzales and I know such a thing for Less
Listening
I would go for Franklin Pierce
I don't even know who that guy is
Stand out as a president to eat
Tall dark and handsome
That is not dark
Dr kavan Tooele 2008-2018