Support for NPR and the following message come from State Farm
When it comes to home and auto insurance
They're here through the ups and downs
Go to statefarm.com
Tippy connect
It was one of the 19000 ages
In neighborhoods
Across the Nation
State Farm
Here to help life
Go right
Alexei a couple of months ago I did something I'm not
Super proud of
Elevator of Science Friday undiscovered podcast
Planet Money is
Is here to listen to your problems
So recently I moved into a new place
How to pay my landlord security deposit $1,500 and he tells me to pay him with venmo
Which is great I use venmo all the time at least they did until this happened
That's for about a
But also very happy on the part of your landlord
Anyone who doesn't venmo is this super easy app on your phone lets you pay your friends or
Total strangers
Pause money from your bank account
You can even add little pithy comments or or silly emojis to your transactions
So I go to venmo my landlord
Have his user ID which is basically his name
His first name is Steven I'm going to leave off his last name so no one blows up his venmo account
And because there are a bunch of people with his name there
Steven 1 Steven 2
Steven says
Steven number one
Nicf
Steven one
So I choose that user I type in the amount $1,500 no extra zeros
Hit pay
Easy peasy
Except
30 minutes later I get a message from Steven one saying
Pretty sure you have the wrong person
And I'm like
What I
I specifically check this
But I go back I look and I see that I've actually made a mistake
Instead of typing Stephen with a v
I've written it with a pH I just sent $1,500 to
Forest ranger
And I'm like
Okay
Give it back
And he says
No
Steven with a pH help me look if it's really a mistake then just get venmo.
And so I call venmo
Explain to them what happened
Steak typo
Can you just cancel this
And this mental person says
No
They can just cancel it
And now I'm starting to seriously
Play freak out
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm out of Vetter I'm Alexi Horowitz Ghazi UK
Name plus after you accidentally sent a stranger
$1,500 my first thought was
Crap
Second thought
Is there a light-hearted economic narrative podcast in this instinct
Today on the show when should you be able to get your money back
This is a surprisingly complicated question an envelope of cash is different from a credit card is
Different from venmo and The Wizard different can be a big deal
Especially when you sent the wrong Stephen $1,500
Support for this podcast and the following message come from atlassian
Today nearly Anything is Possible
And if we can dream it
Teams can build
I'm going to Mars to decoding the human genome
Atlassian is a collaboration software company
Empowering teams around the world
Products like jira software
Where conflict
Trello and bitbucket
Help teens plan track build and work better together
Atlassian products are free to try
Easy to set up
And work seamlessly together
Get started today at atlassian. Com
Drag has been around for a while
In the Kabuki tradition in Japan
Minstrel show
In Vaudeville
But one TV show made it mainstream
Now
We break down drags current Renaissance
Check out NPR's it's been in
Now
So the core question in the show today
Is when should you be able to get your money back and buy you I mean me I mean my money
The whole idea that we could even instantly get our money back is actually an invention and not even a very old one
Back in the 1960s when credit cards were first starting to take off
People with credit cards did not have the power to undo
And it was
That would be charged the wrong amount
They would be double charged
Is a staff attorney at the National Consumer law
Center or someone would take their car and and use it without their consent and they would try to
Battle with the credit card companies to get them to
To fix the error
And the problem was the credit card companies would just ignore them
And in fact
Which St
Keep demanding payment
Without addressing the consumer's complaint
So eventually Congress kicks into action and he starts
Passing laws
In 1974 they pass
What is the most
Powerful consumer protections we have ever had
This is an undo button like no other it's something called
A chargeback
A chargeback is when you
Challenge something on your credit card and it gets
Reversed its charge
Back to the merch
You can do that if your credit card got stolen and you didn't authorize the charge but also if a store charged you the wrong amount
Now you just go to your bank
Dispute the charge
And if you are wrongly build they undo it
If I'm them to make sure that happen
Not only does that mean I can now get my money back with one call
It also means everybody feels more comfortable using credit
And uses that more and more
Which is good for the credit card
So
Why doesn't venmo do this for me when I call them
Like why don't they just undo the transaction
Other people have been asking this to
Last year there was a story on page one of the Wall Street Journal with the headline
So you accidentally sent $149 to a stranger on venmo
Good luck getting it back
One possible reason venmo doesn't let us get our money back
Because when you let us demand our money back
We go wild
You know this because of what happened with credit card charge
We started demanding our money when any reasonable person would say we shouldn't get it
It's a chargeback
Canal there people whose entire job is dealing with these chargebacks
La Quinta Cove
There was somebody who had taken the series of golf lessons
And then at the end
I disputed
That there
Score hasn't improved a sufficient amount and they were dissatisfied
Solution chargeback
Katie works for square which is a company that process
This is credit card payments
So when you swipe your card or sticker chip in a machine
That machine comes from a credit card processor like
Square they're basically middlemen
Square mostly works with small business
At one of those businesses thinks a chargeback isn't fair
Square help them fight back to keep the money
In order to do that they have to convince the bank associated with the customer's credit card
Katy cobras team spent all day
Every weekday answering calls consoling merchants
And helping them gather the evidence they need to win the case
Are you guys a team of detectives
Team of chargeback therapist
Flash Detective
Can you sing some truly ridiculous charge
Like the client who received their payment for an allegedly subpar window cleaning
3 months and several rainstorms after the cleaning and question again
And of course there was the
Case of
The floral wedding
The cake was about $800
When date Katie got a call from an upset client
A bigger
She had delivered the cake and it had been consumed
And she had her no no complaints for them as far as she knew they had been totally satisfied
And
A few weeks later
She received this payment dispute notification
Thought the couple wanted their money
I did they say what they were disputing or does that sort of detail come through
There were flowers on the cake and there was some.
Discrepancy on the color of the flower
The claim was that they were a little too bright
So
Katie got to work
Calming her client down walking her through all the possible pieces of evidence that could help prove to the bank
Did the Baker at held up
Printable
She had a chain of email correspondence where they had agreed on
All the details about the cake
And
In addition to that
She had post from social media where she had taken screenshots and it was the couple
With their gas
Celebrating and eating the cake
And there were
Comments on social media from their gas saying how much they enjoyed it and from the couple saying that they were thrilled
Wasn't that a wonderful cake
What did you think when you first saw the social media post
I thought we had it nailed
It was just
So blatant I couldn't imagine that they would be able
To get away with getting their money back
I like smiling with pieces of cake in their teeth and stuff each other
What's it mean having a wonderful time
Soba stashes infuriating I'm actually getting worked up a little bit
With Katie's help the baker got to keep the money
The bank decided in
Her favor
Kitty also told us this one other story
About a small family-owned Construction Company
It doesn't really expensive remodel of a home
And then the customer chargeback
Tens of thousands of dollars
The business lost the case and had to shut down
And even when business is due when
There's a cost
Katie salary comes out of the fees businesses pay to use Square as their credit card price
And this isn't just a square foot
Every business pays fees to accept credit cards
It often there extra fees for chargebacks
Business is past all those fees on to us in the prices
So there is a cost to the power to undo
That we are all pay
After the break
I try to get back that $1,500 I venmoed Steven
PhD pen
With a pH
Scorbutus NPR Podcast in the following message come from Salesforce
Salesforce helps you deliver the Innovative personal experiences customers want
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together at salesforce.com NPR
Hey it's Peter Sagal so you're listening to this NPR Podcast
Because you want to be informed you want to learn something
What if you need a little break
Well then you want to check out wait wait don't tell me
The NPR news quiz
It's the show that lets here lizard brain enjoy yourself for once
You can't be serious again later
Listen to wait wait don't tell me
On NPR one or whatever you get your pie
So back to my venmo story
To recap
I accidentally sent $1,500 to Stephen with a pH
Because of a typo
Steven headset
Call venmo which I did I ask him to cancel it
And now it's been a credit card payment
That would have been at your I call venmo
Get a chargeback
It would have been done
But venmo is not a credit card
He told me that's not how to
No chargeback no chargeback
Venmo tells me they can't cancel a payment without Stevens permission
So they say they'll email him
He says he doesn't get the email
I called him again
The email again and again he says he didn't get it
And I start crying on the phone to venmo little bit
But when I was done freaking out
You know I asked venmo one more time this time as a reporter not as a disgruntled or weepy customer
I have some okay
Why do you do it this way
Why don't you give people an undo button you know that equivalent of a chargeback
Didn't want to talk on tape for the story
But they did say in an email that quote making funds instantly available to recipients is part of why customers love
Using PayPal and venmo
And quote
By the way venmo is owned by PayPal
And they also said they're in line with what other apps are
And that is reasonable enough and undo option would
How to suck anyway
Imagine cash work light
You know you go out to a fancy meal with your friend
You pay the check your friend gives you 20 bucks for their end of the deal
And then when you get home you open your wallet all of a sudden
Proof
The $20 is gone
That would suck
Honey buns are great for the person hitting undo
Are there any pretty rotten for the person on the other side
I know actually also said that they do all kinds of things.
Stop people from making mistakes in the first place
Like
They get people to post profile pictures
Or they'll find any payments to someone that you've never paid before
In my case none of that stuff would have asked
Help but
You know I could see how
Somebody
I think there's actually more to this
And I think part of the reason they don't have an undo button
Has to do with the way that venmo's Corp business works
And how it's actually fundamentally different from the way that credit cards do
Every time you buy something with a credit card
The business selling you that thing has to pay fees
And part of those fees pay for the Katy cobras of the world to deal with charges
Venmo on the other hand does not charge a fee when you send money to a friend
Or your landlord or a stranger you think is your landlord
Thanks but also
No chargeback
Yeah so there's a trade-off here you know you pay a fee
Maybe you get an undo button you get that charge back or
You don't pay a fee and you're kind of stuck with
The payments you make
How does venmo make money
They don't
At least they don't when Ordinary People send money to each other using their Bank
Venmo does charge fees for some premium features like faster Bank transfers and using venmo to pay some vendors Direct
It also charges transaction fees to some Merchant
How to use venmo
Bottom line
Venmo was not going to fix this for me
It was up to Steven to actually give me my money back
And the only way that I had to contact him was by actually messaging him
Through the venmo app
So
I did
Actually messaged him 18 times on that first day shred on my phone
Alexi there's a back-and-forth I mentioned earlier where
Steven Latino
But I should go to venmo get them to
I get back to Steven and here's here's a distilled version of what happened
Venmo has just contacted you
Steven
They have not
Me
I would really like to resolve this
With dignity
And without escalation
This is legally my money
Steven
Look whoever you are I am not keeping your money you sent it to the wrong person and I did the right thing by letting you know
As long as bendo contacts me
I have no problem sending it back
So basically I am freaking out I mean you can tell from
Play writing I'm like
Insinuating I'm going to see him I'm having a meltdown
And finally Stephen says
Look
Why don't you just call your bank and have them
Cancel it
So I'm pretty sure this is the first moment I actually logged into my bank account
And that's when I saw the $1,500 was still there
I'd had my money
The whole time
There's this weird thing going on like inside the venmo universe
When you venmo money to a friend or whoever
It appears in your friends venmo account instant
But venmo doesn't actually take money out of your bank account instantly
That actually takes some time
It wasn't really like I just
Handed an envelope of cash to a stranger you know even though that's how it felt
So that night
Call my bank and I tell them look
Venmo is about
Take $1,500 out of my account I do not want to give them
That $1,500
Could you block that
I've never tried this before never put a stop on a bank payment
But it's really easy they don't
Ask too many questions they're just like
Yeah okay will do that cost you $30 then like
Great
Do that please thank you
Then
3 days later I got an email from venmo saying I owe them $1,500
They're going to freeze my account until I'm settled up
But then an hour after that
I got a second email
Say actually
It's all good
I don't know the money money
Account is unfrozen
Just like that three days after it started it was all over
But I still didn't totally understand what it happened
Mean one minute I owe venmo 1500 the next I don't
Which means either
Steven finally agreed to under the payment
Or maybe venmo I decided to
Fix this for me after all
I couldn't tell which one it was
My son Steven one more message
Hey
Weird question
But would you possibly be interested in being interviewed for an NPR Planet Money segment
And he said yes
The forcefulness of you
Bam
Is a
A little intimidating
Steven with a pH lives in Birmingham Alabama and use a surprises I was by this whole thing
How's that work
You know I get a notification
And
I didn't know what it was I don't know if I hit accept
Whatever I did
You know that's just there
Oh I had no idea what was
You know what was going on
I don't know if you're like some drug lord or trying to steal my money and I don't like I don't know
I don't have your gun shot my leg off later to get
Cashback
I don't know
I thought I was being kind of polite actually
But I like that I'm sorry this kind of fear
Moore Stephens com
The one thing I wanted to know from Steven was
How is it that one minute
I owed $1,500 the next minute I was all squared up with venmo had he done something
What
What happened at your a bear for so long
I figured they weren't going to do anything
Steven says he never got in touch with venmo
Never got any of their emails
But the $1,500
Did disappear from his venmo account at one point
To Spanish.
It's like the whole thing it never happened
And frankly what went down it's a little opaque to me
Ask them about it they wouldn't tell me
What's clear is that in the end
They're actually was the secret undo button
At my bank
And it cost me 30 bucks to use it
Lundy button is basically this trade-off
The credit cards we have an idea
An awesome safety-net for consumer
But we all pay for it
Whether we know it or not
With cash there's no fee
And No undo button
Venmo is this new grey area
It's not really cash
Not really credit card
It's this new in between thing and we're using it all the time
And kind of still trying to figure out what it is
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
And we're on Facebook Twitter and Instagram at Planet Money
Planet money has a newsletter short fun essays that explain what's going on in the economy subscribe at NPR
Planet Money news
That's npr.org
Flash Player
Edit money newsletter
Today Show was produced by Darian woods and Rachel Cohn
The show was edited by Jacob
Goldstein
Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
Printers that edits the show
Special thanks to Christina Tatro Amy Circle Alan Weinberg
And Scottsdale
I'm a lot better and I'm Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
This is NPR
Thanks for listening
What weight were you tempted on any level
Skip it
Oh yeah
It was my girl
She made it
She told me to keep it
Yes
She's like the stars are aligned.
Funeral
To her
Country stars