This is planet money from NPR
What were you doing in Alaska I was on my boat
With my wife and another couple in the misty fjords
Oh and what kind of boat was this
I have a big boat
Is it like a yacht
I think you would call it a yacht
Nick hanauer is rich
Do you have a helipad on your
No no
No
Nick may have a modest yacht
But you can probably afford one with a helipad
He comes from a rich family
A family
Pillow Tycoon
We turned a very small pillow company into
One of the nation's largest pillow companies
Overtime it's cold
Pacific Coast Feather co
The family sold it at
Horseback
Well you still work there
Nick started helping them sell their pillows on the internet
And it was absolutely clear
In 1992 to me
That physical retail was essentially going to be dead
And
As luck would have it
I had a friend who shared that view is name is Jeff Bezos her
How did you meet Jeff Bezos just out of curiosity
He was dating one of my closest and oldest
Friends
And
I was lucky enough to be the first investor in amazon.com and that led to other things and before you know it
I was a full-time technology
Venture capitalist
You started a company called a quantity
Which eventually sold to Microsoft for 6
6.4 billion dollars
He then invested in a bank with some friends and you get the
Bees the capitalist
Bernardo like Scrooge McDuck
Gordon Gekko I'm an oilman style capitalist he's also a philanthropist and
Got involved in politics
And you know my theory of change in the early days was that
All of the big
Challenges that America faced
With Rising inequality and poverty
Could be solved
If you just
Had a successful enough education to
System run 2070 says
TBN to realize
That the problem was bigger than just schools
The education system is not failing people it's the it's the economic system that's failing people the wealthy
Specifically the top 1% or
The top .01%
We're getting richer way faster than everyone else
And that scared him
If this trend continues
People are going to revolt
History shows
That level of inequality results in either a police state or a revolution
Or both
He saw a future at work
A tiny few had everything
A kind of feudal world
That had to end
In violent revolution
Soap to be clear this wasn't just about do good
You was worried about himself
And his friends
You know being
Punished somehow or maybe
Guillotine Anderson
Anyway penis into Ring the Alarm
Andy Baker new causes
It's like a higher minimum wage
You got so worried
Human gamete
Soap in 2012
I gave a TED Talk
On economic inequality
That got me thrown out of Ted
Like it was so controversial that we that they asked me not to come back
Yeah so the video of his lecture got taken down
But since then he's kind of become known for talking about in equality
Especially this one line he has
So what do I see in our future today
You asked
IC pitchfork
As in
Angry mobs
With pitchfork
Hello and welcome to Planet Money
I'm Greg Wazowski and I'm Alexi Horowitz God
The wealth Gap in the US
Have gotten so big that even yacht cruising zillionaires are getting
Turning on their own time
And demanding change
It's high class war
Today in the show
A new idea to redistribute wealth in America
It's pitchforks
Versus pitch deck
Porches
Horses Porsches
The angry villagers are coming
And they have the data
This message comes from NPR sponsor Salesforce
Today's customers want innovative
Personal experiences from company
And sales
The customer relationship management solution can help
Now you can deliver the personalized experiences customers want
By uniting your Marketing sales Commerce service and it
On an integrated CRM platform
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together at salesforce.com NPR
I hope and expect this to be the only time that I will speak to you in this matter
I would not provide information Beyond
That which is already published
In any appearance
Before Congress
Special counsel Robert Mueller isn't getting his wish
He sets
To testify about his investigation into Russian interference
And possible obstruction of justice by President Trump
Afterwards the NPR politics podcast is going to be there to break down everything you need to know about what he says
The last time inequality in the United States was as bad as it is today
It was during the Roaring Twenties
We're talkin the great gaps
Flappers and fedoras prohibition
And then came the Great
It obliterated Fortune
Led to major changes and how we regulate capitalism
Elizabeth Warren running for president
Crusader against big money and wealth inequality
Recently proposed one solution to this Century Wild
Here she is on the campaign Trail
We can pay for it
I got away
Ultra millionaires tax
And the ultra millionaire tax is a pretty new idea for the United States
It is actually
That's because
It's a well pack
Not an income tax
Traditionally if you wanted to tax the wealthy in America you for the most part you taxed income
It's been that way for like a hundred
An income tax is Progressive
Meaning the more you make the more you pay
The old political debates focused on how much more the rich should pay
But when it comes to inequality
It's really wealth
More than income that matters
These two things often get conflated
But they're actually different
Income is what you make every year
It's like a running faucet
Wealth is what you own
The money in your bank your house your car your shares of Microsoft if you have stock
It's like a reservoir
So Jeff Bezos
Give a formal salary of less than $100,000
Not crazy high about the same as a
Typical School prints
What is worth at least before his divorce about 120 billion dollars
The thing that makes him rich is not his income it's really mostly his stocking Amazon
And unless he sells it
He's not
Text on it
It just grows and grows
Nick hanauer think this is
Is crazy
The reason that
Wealth is concentrating so much is that
I can grow my assets
For 40 years
Contacts
And if you don't have wealth
You obviously don't have anything just sitting there
Growing and growing
What Warren is saying is she wants the federal government to
The top the reservoir of wealth
She wants a tax wealth
2% over 50 million dollars
And 3% over a billion
That means for every dollar you have over 50 million you're paying $0.02 a year
And $0.03 on every dollar over a billion
That doesn't really sound like a lot
But maybe you're not thinking like a billionaire
Because really rich people
Think a lot
About growth
Their different estimates but it's
Kind of safe to say that wealth grows on average about six or seven or eight percent over the long run
Every year
And then it's growth on the growth growing 7% over and over again like a snowball
Compound growth
With this plan if the return stay on track
The rich will still get richer
But like half as fast
Sao innocence
3% is
Kind of high
Now we haven't really taxed
I mean we trying to do with the property tax but that's state and local not federal
And usually only applies to
The real estate
It's basically a wealth tax that taxes only one form of well
And there is the estate tax which is basically a one-time wealth tax
But the rich person your texting has to die for
What Warren is proposing
Is the federal government count up the value of all the rich people stuff
And tax it every single year
We're talkin diamond ring
Jet skis
Normal skis
Fancy tchotchke
Maserati
Giacometti
What is that
The statues for rich people
Google expects a lot of rich people
They love the idea of a wealth tax
Difference is Frappuccino magnate and former presidential candidate Howard Schultz on NPR
When I see Elizabeth Warren
I come out with
You know a ridiculous
Plan of
Taxing wealthy people
So the founder of
Starbucks hates it you can't just
Attack these things in a punitive Way by punishing
So do a bunch of other rich
Be both but not all of them
Nick hanauer the early Amazon investor
He isn't the only one percenter jumping yacht
I got born really lucky
This is Liesel pritzker Simmons
She's a former child actress
You might have seen her in
Little princess or Air Force One
She's honestly great in the movies but that's not how she made her money
My family I had a number of different businesses but the ones that they are
Best known for is Hyatt Hotels
Liesel and her husband Ian
Also Rich say they've been thinking about the wealth tax for a while
But it wasn't until Warren's plan
Basalt real number
And I thought
Yeah
This could be a good thing
This is a relatively moderate tax on a fair amount of wealth
That could go to public use
You know better than it's sitting you know in our in our art collection
They thought it was time to send a message
From Rich America to the rest of America
Guys it's cool we're down with the Weld Pak
Calling the rich friend
Among them
George Soros billionaire investor Chris Hughes one of the founders of
Facebook
Abigail Disney
Youku
Probably guess
I swear that money
And Nick hanauer
Indians that got eighteen other zillionaires to sign this letter and actually we have the letter here
Publish on medium
A Blog
But we we printed it out
And it's called
An open letter to the 2020 presidential candidates
It's time to tax us more
What kind of captures it but there's two
Other things they got in here
South America
Flag looking
Sandhill
The basically lay out everything they say a wealth tax could help pay
They say can help address the climate crisis
America's aging infrastructure childcare cost
Public health challenges like
The opioid epidemic
They say it's fair patriotic
The basic gist of this letter is this
Elizabeth Warren specific proposal says it's going to raise like 2.75 trillion dollars over 10 years
Chinese billionaires are saying
That's a lot of money that we can use to fix America's problem
And taxing wealth in this way is in
Increasingly popular
There a few poles that show a clear majority of Americans
Support it like three-quarters of them
Even a majority of millionaires say they support
This policy
But
There is a caveat
Well taxes
Have been tried before in other
And their track record
Everton General
It hasn't been great
After the break
When will taxes
Go wrong
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working to nourish the common good
By donating all profit
It's from Newman's Own food products
Ducks to charitable organization
That seek to make the world a better place
More information is available
Newman's Own Foundation. Org
If you haven't been reading Planet money's newsletter you're missing out on stories about hidden beaches and scooter Mania
And plastic bag ban
It's just the right amount of economics and Analysis served up once a week
Subscribe at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
I will text
It may be new for the US Federal
But actually wealth taxes they've been tried
They actually used to be quite popular in European countries
This is Sarah. She's an economist at the organization of economic
Make a cooperation and development
Or oecd
She did a study about well taxes and how they worked out
She says in 1990 there were 12 countries in Europe that had a wealth tax
Today there are only three
And so the trend has really been
To repeal them Brisas will Texas field for a bunch of reasons
First they were tough on people who looked
Rich on paper but were in fact shorten the cash needed to
To pay the tax
An example
I retired a long time ago was Lady braces
A house in jewelry and a bunch of other assets that make her look rich to the government
Really she only has a small pension and it's hard for her to come up with the money to
Pay the wealth tax
Another problem with the wealth tax
It was pretty expensive to track and value rich people stuff at
It's more complicated
Then
An income tax for example or a property tax where you're just acting one type of acid
So here you're texting
All types
Sunsets are pretty easy to value
Like stocks
Starbond
But others like paintings or your grandma's
Engagement ring
Or your rare ocelot
Or your rare Savannah cat ostriches
Or your Alpaca Farm tigers
So the government is going to have to figure out a way to assess
The value of olives
Which means bureaucracy
More accountants tax collectors
Calculator spreadsheet
The whole nine yards
30 shoe
Exemption
Countries wouldn't tax all kinds of assets
So like in France Free People
They didn't text or worker antiques
Why waste money figuring out what these things are worth
Other countries Exempted business hours
Things like factories machine
What are the things that like creature jobs and help the economy
And all those exemptions created a bunch of
The problems there is less money coming in because all those assets would be
Being taxed
The people with the best accountants and lawyers game the system which made it unfair
Plus it created incentives for people to put their money in quirky weird places like artwork or antiques
Which is great for artists and antique dealers but
Not for the economy as a whole
And of course which people tried to protect their money by getting it out of the country
There is
A term for this
Capital flight
Like rich people who couldn't figure out another way to evade taxes would sometimes just
Pick up and move
Like for example a ton of millionaires left
France and moved right across the border to Belgium
And
Hoof
No more wealth
Or they find some tax shelter like a Monica or the Cayman Islands are
Also not good for the economy
Sonia
The policy didn't even breathe much money like you didn't do what I was supposed to do
So back to work
Her chip are used they specifically designed their proposal with Europe's failures in mine
What is proposal really only taxes the very very rich
Those with over 50 million dollars in wealth
That's only about 75000 families in the United
It states
In Europe the threshold was much lower
In some cases around a million dollars or even less
Not the ultra-rich
But the sort of
So under warranty plan at old lady with the fancy house in the nice jewels
She's going to be just fine
Not rich enough to get tan
Plus the proposal says very clearly
No exemption
None
Zero zilch
Nada
But what about my sports car
Now yeah that's going to be that's going to be taxed
How about my pet tiger
Tigers will definitely beat
My musket collect
How rich are you alive
Faberge egg
None of that
But
No exemptions means the IRS is going to have to get bigger and way better at tracking rich people stuff every year
They're going to have to Value those Faberge eggs
Birkin bags
Pet tigers
You brought the value a tiger what the IRS is going to have to have a tiger done
Plastic Alicia how much are those anyway I don't know
Too many people this sounds like a lot but
Nick hanauer
He doesn't think it's a big deal at all you hire 300 IRS agent
They cost
$200,000 a piece
Just focus on nothing but this problem
Costs
60 million dollars
Against
Literally
Hundreds of billions of dollars in potential income I mean it's
Cheap to do
Lisa's
This valuation problem you know
Figuring out how much your Tigers worth
This can be solved
There's a very very very simple way to handle
Which is
You get to write down all of your assets and pick a number
And then the government has the right to buy any of those assets at the price that you pick
This self evaluation method by the way it is kind of brilliant
I mean think about it if you try to save money by undervaluing your stuff
You're going to lose it
And I mean this is obviously going to be a tough sell in the United
Let's see the government is able to do something
That still leaves the issue of capital flight
But
US citizens can't just move to another country to avoid taxes
The US taxes its citizens wherever they are in the world
The tax evaders would have to renounce their citizenship to legally avoid the well tab
And if you're a rich person who renounces your citizenship
Weren't supposed the federal government confiscate
40% of your wealth over a billion dollars
But you're you're a suspiciously good whistler
Thanks
But
There's another big problem
The US
Institution
It makes it hard for the federal government
It's a directly taxed
100 years ago it took a constitutional amendment to Institute the income tax
There's some legal Scholars who argued we need another amendment for wealth
And that would be a huge hurdle to do
But if you support taxing the wealthy more
In this constitutional issue ends up being a problem
There might actually be good news
0 priests that he concludes you can deal with wealth inequality without a wealthy
Our study finds that in general a combination
I've broad-based taxes on personal capital income tax on dividends capital gains interest
As well as well design inheritance taxes
Might be a more effective way of addressing Welton equality without some of the negative size of what
In effect in many countries in Europe where wealth inequality is not quite as bad as it is in the United States
This strategy seems to be working
But it wouldn't touch many of today's huge fortunes
For decades
Lots of billionaires are pretty young
Mark Zuckerberg for example he was only born in 1984
Inheritance or estate tax might not affect his wealth for like
50 or 60 or 70 years depending on whatever bionic implants he might be able to get
I mean he could live forever literally forever if we have the technology in the next
50 years to like upload his Consciousness into the cloud
Floating in our phones all the time
And look if you really want to destroy wealth inequality
Actually roll it back
I will tax of 3% isn't really going to cut it
Again what goes at like 6 or 7 or 8% per year on average
Don't Litter that Nick and Liesl signed
Because specifically for a quote moderate wealth
And so we were curious
When does it stop being moderate
How much are these doing is really willing to pay to stop the pitchforks
So we asked
Nick hanauer
That y'all don't venture capitalist too riled up so many of his fellow 1-percenter
When does the wealth tax
Stop being moderate
And when would you stop supporting it
That's a super good question
And it's something I haven't thought
Carefully about so
Immoderate
Tomillo moderate wealth tax
Simply
Slows the growth
Of
Large pools of assets
And so a 2% tax on that or 3% tax on that
Slows the growth rate from 8% to 5% which means you're still getting a ton richer than everyone else
In the country
If you take the growth rate
2-0
That's a no longer moderate
And
I guess that begins to test
Even my
Comfort
With
With a wealth tax
So
Perhaps unsurprisingly
Hanauer has limits
Tax enough to slow the growth
Not so much you stop
But he's still out there agitating amongst his fellow zillionaires
After we got off the phone with him he said he was headed to Edinboro to give a speech about wealth inequality
Are they still pushing for a wealth tax
Immoderate
Welltok
Do you have thoughts about progressive taxation for the ultra-wealthy
Email us
At Planet Money at npr.org
Print money at npr.org
Or find us on Twitter and Facebook
Want to help Planet Money
Review Us in apple podcast app
Now it's us stand out from all the True Crime
By the way if you want to hear more from pillow Tycoon Nick hanauer actually has a podcast
It's called pillow-talk no
What's called Pitchfork economics
Today's episode was produced by Liza Jager and fact-checked by Cynthia that do Visa
Bryan Adams the show
And Alex goldmark is our supervising producer
I'm Lexie Horowitz Ghazi and I'm great results
This is NPR thanks for listening