Everything alone in the studio and he isn't
Where is this
Shiny
Oh
What is this is an American Silver Eagle
2018 minted coin
I've never seen one before
Minted by the US government
Legal tender and here you are
Okay alright
It says
$1 is $1 coin
Goodbye
Candy bar with this
Have you really stupid
Why because you're
Okay that says 1 oz
One ounce of fine silver value is $1 the
Metal value of this coin
Today at this moment is like around 50
Okay so if you want a candy bar with that
He clarkwood feel pretty
Golden version of the America
Point it's a
$50 face value in the medals worth
Flight 1300
Hundred dollars today
This gets us to our listeners
Trinity comes from
Today Show we are answering questions from listeners
So what did Chris
Exactly wants to know
Is there a way
To take advantage of the
Did the US government is minting these weird coins coins
With different face values
Frontier Market
Okay
That's good question Chris
Is not the first person to notice this up
All right about 25 years ago there was a businessman in Las
Vegas a few businesses
Plumbing
Air conditioning
Painting
And he came up with a way to
To use these coins to get out of
Of paying
Payroll tax
What do you do what say that I was like a painter
I would go up
To the payroll window
At the end of my Wii
And I would say
Hello I'm here for my
Wages
And the person in the window they would hand me a bunch of silver and gold coins
That had
Face values that were like
50 bucks
$50
And that's the transaction it is
Is on the books I got paid
$50
But
Then
I could take my coin
To literally a window next door
Like physically and I got to go back to a person
Who would give me actual cash
Add an exchange rate of about life
8 times so I would get
$400
But that $400 that wasn't going to affect
Payroll taxes because
That Exchange
That didn't take place at the office is payroll window
It happened at the very convenient office go exchange
Window
Right exact
Okay so what we have here is
Entrepreneurial tax
The Beijing basically
Ocasek is he only has to record that he paid
The face value Lexington
Fifty bucks yes
But then the employees are going to get $400 cuz they're cashing it on the
Value of the metal and everybody wins that feels kind of creative
Little mom-and-pop operation
Over about 5
This businessman paid
More than 25 million dollars
In wages
Million that is
Crazy and she was not only using this for his business
This scheme was so inventive
Also became a payroll contract
And it helped other business is almost a hundred million dollars in wages
Through this coin scam
Okay so he's like franchising tax
Yes wow
Unfortunately when the IRS found out about this
They did not think
Clever and so excited
Key West
Charged with tax
Evasion and then sentenced to almost 16 years in prison
And ordered to pay the US government back about 16 million
Did he try paying with silver coins
But to answer Chris's question
Can you take advantage of the face value market value difference of American Eagle coins
Probably not no no no
Devon and okra stew not do
Do I get to keep the coin I don't know I should find out if I can expense
Cuz you bought it all right we'll ask Alec hello and welcome to Planet Money
Karen Duffin
Everyday we get dozens of messages from you our listeners lots of great questions like this one from Chris
We do read them all
Sometimes we make stories out of them and sometimes we gather up a few of the ones that stumped us and we find you
Answers
Sometimes we even save listeners from jail time for tax evasion
Stay on the show
Listener question
We will take you to a fairy in England we will introduce you to a new way to stack your friends online
And we will talk text
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Sand run you're busy
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search
Engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
I have Jacob Goldstein in the studio with me now he is back from Buckley we're thrilled to have you back Jacob
So Jacob
Alexandria Ocasio Cortez she
She is the newly elected congresswoman we've been hearing Lots about
She is proposed raising at marginal income tax
Tax rates
And there are lots of questions about what those are and so we are here to ask you
Can you explain marginal tax
I'm thrilled
I'm very excited about this
There's this
Very basic idea
About income taxes
In America that is
Non controversial
And that is
Income taxes should be Progressive
Right
And that means rich people should pay a higher percentage of their income
Temperature
Right okay so not just hire because they're earning more but a higher percentage of their wealth yes
Pretty much everybody agrees
That's okay
But that creep is interesting kind of math
Right because
Say we decide
People who are earning
Whatever less than $10,000 a year
Shouldn't have to pay any income tax
And we decide
You know $10,000
$20,000 if you're in that band
You should pay whatever 10% of your income
But if we do it that way there's a problem
Because in the system we've just created
People who are making
9999 dollars
P0
People who are making
$10,000.00
Now have to pay 10% of that
So people are going to gain this
System to try to earn 9999
It's right that your taxes if your making 10000
You're actually making 9000 and you're worse off than the person who is less than
That is a disaster of a policy
So
We come up with the marginal income
Okay and what that says is
Each sort of chunk of your income gets taxed at a different
Right so
The first 9999 dollars
Upay
And then
The next chunk say 10000 to $20,000
Upay
10%
Okay so if you're making
And $1
All you would owe is $0.20
Syntax
I do know we can't keep doing this up and up and up right we can add another
Higher marginal tax
We can say we're going to tax income over $20,000 a year at tape twenty percent
And in the real world we have seven of these
Early steps
Savjz chunks
Call bracket
All the way up to a top
Rack it up
Marginal income tax rate
That starts
At over $500,000 a year if your single over $600,000 a year if
If you're married
And every dollar over that amount in that pop
Bracket
Is attack stat
Okay so the
Currently the highest
Marginal income tax rate
Is 37%
And what
Congresswoman Ocasio Cortez
Proposing is basically one more step above that which would be
At 10 million and above
People would be taxed
So in that universe
It would still presumably be 37% for every dollar you make between $500,000
+ 10 million
Okay then every dollar over 10 million
Is taxed at 70
Okay which the vast majority of us will never
Sadly have to worry about and speak for yourself
Jacob has Big Dreams for his book
Alright thanks so much Jacob
We have Brian Dorsett in the studio he edits the show but today
We have them on Mike
Answering questions
So can we got a question from Alyssa
I want to know what's up with the brexit
Fairy
Am I sorry I mean the kind you find on the ocean
And
I'm going to play you
Some sounds
To get us in the mood
For a serious show
About the future of England's GDP
All right
Wait okay I'm going to
I'm going to fall asleep before that happens quickly turned economics
So that is the sound of the ocean
And obviously and it's in the port of Dover in English
Where I found NPR's London correspond
Frank length
Did I hear a seagull
Yes we have brought them in for this
Nice atmosphere and can you see France like Hills or Cliffs of Dover and Calais
So yeah it's pretty close so Dover is England's connection to Francis where the channel is
The tunnel for the track that runs under the English Channel and it says
Huge Port Frank told me
10000 trucks
Add a cross the channel here
Yeah I mean right now I'm looking at
An entry ramp onto the porch
And you can just see
Trucks
Rolling down it right on the fairies and there's no custom Shack or anything like that it's seamless
Just like taking the ferry safe from Delaware
Up to Southern New Jersey
It's the same kind of thing except
You're actually traveling from one country to another
But all the seamlessness might just end soon right because
Parliament is just about to vote on whether or not to accept
Prime minister Theresa May's exit.
Exactly her
Brexit deal
Because in order to leave the EU there are
Two ways to go in 1 oz of everything organized and agreed on with all the other countries in Europe and the other is to just
Say
Goodbye
If Parliament turns down
May's brexit deal
It makes it just a little more likely that England could leave without any kind of
Which would completely change this scene in Dover
Totally you would have custom checks for the first time in
Probably decades
And even their estimates that even if it takes 60 or 70 seconds to clear a truck
I'll get that could create miles and miles of truck back up
And really slow down trade university did the math and figured out that there would be six
Dake using other words
Traffic that would take 6 days to clear
Just permanent gridlock
EXO
England has thought maybe we should start working on getting some other ports moving and they started talking to other Ferry companies
And other parts like Ramsgate
Which is just North of Dover
The government gave a contract to a company called seaborne
This got a lot of attention because the seaborne company doesn't actually own any fairy
Which would seem to be a good thing to have
If you
We're fairy company so yeah that she's not going to work right away they were moving fast there will be fat
But
Europe is connected now and they're all kinds of industries that completely depend on things getting there
Really quickly so the people who do this stuff the people deliver things are making all kinds of backup plans
Frank talk to one guy who owns 250 trucks
And here
He spent over a billion box
Dim fire helicopter going to help things go really badly
He can load small item
Like lighters things like that
And be able to fly them across the channel into Europe and land and
Take them directly to the factory to keep the factory lines going this very problem is just one of a long list of
Things that brexit
Is growing up
So there
This country is kind of stuck
Doing a thing it's pretty sure isn't going to work out that well
I think that's true hard to find illegitimate economist
Who doesn't think that this makes the United Kingdom both
Poor
And have a lot less leverage because it's not a part of this giant single Market in Europe
Tell Karen
Bad news in England okay but I do have some more calming waves
If you want to go out on Kik
All right to answer the next question
Take you back to an episode we did in 2017 it was about the gross domestic product forecast coming out of
The White House the GDP forecast
They were projecting 3% growth
Over the neck
10 years
Which to be clear is
Much higher than what anybody else
And then Trump as he
What about it
The forecast even
Further
Here's a clip from our original episode
At some point
Into the future
5 and above
I just
Extremely hot out of respect the office
Okay so
Clearly
Along with most
Economist we were
Article of
That projection
But at the end of last year GDP did hit 3% for that year
So a lot of listeners have written to us
With questions like this one from David Gross
Play Planet Money
Just curious if you had revisit the episode
Here We Grow Again
Explored how unlikely it was Teresa
The 3%
GDP growth in President Trump's budget
Pirate Looks like the target may have been achieved in 2018
That is a fair question so I brought Darien Woods into answer this Darien is
Hey Darrian in the original episode we spoke with a guy named Marco behind he's an economist for the
The committee for response
Federal budget
And earlier this week
We called him back up
Is the difference between
Long-term sustained growth
And near-term Pro
He says yeah we
Did hit that 3% last year but
Let's just for one year
The forecast for
Tant
So I asked him is this category likely to continue there's only one single forecaster at estimating even close to 3%
That's the White House bicycle
Two reasons why the stars probably won't lie
The first reason for the 3% growth was that last little bit of the recovery have
From the 2008/2009
Conversation he says that probably won't continue
The second reason
Little crisis created equal
And the current 3% growth
A large share of it
Is the one-time effect of
A huge hundred fifty billion dollars a year spending bill
And even larger 200 billion dollar year
Text boxes this 3% growth rates
Fundamentally change the economy in a way that will last
Sustained
It's primarily to huge spending bill
Epic tax-cut someone time events with fix it won't lock
Back is a term for a sugar high
When I drink my morning coffee or eat a lot of sugar
That's going to cause the economy to go into hyperdrive for a period of time
But it's likely to be followed by a crash unless we do something
Caboose that productive capacity
In fact Mike says if we stay on this path
We're in trouble we're in big trouble fiscally
And there's not an easy way out
So you're really worried
I'm extremely worried
Okay so David are listener
Are you are right
United States
Did hit 3% growth
Last year
But it sounds like it's probably temper
Yep that's right
Lomax says if he's wrong about this I will gladly email that that listener
And tell them that
It looks like I was
I was wrong
Thanks Darian for the good news bad news but you Karen
Shane McCann
Karen Duffin you are intern and this is your last day at Planet
It is I'm sad to go
I know we're bummed about this
But there is one thing we want you to do before you
That is answer a listener question that I believe you are the most qualified person to answer
Yes as senior Generation Z correspondent I am here and ready
Your question alright that's older people that
Thank you
Okay so the question comes from a listener in Florida named Raphael
How do money transfer apps
Cash out venmo and square
Generate Revenue if they don't charge for their services
Okay so
Raphael is asked
Talking about apps
Like venmo is probably the most
Popular one right now so maybe let's start with what is
Venmo
Venmo is just an
An app that lets you send money to your friend
And unlike something like PayPal venmo has like
Speed where you can describe the payments you're making and then all your friends can see them and so it starts to look like
Okay so that's been
How do they earn money
So I did some research I talk to someone at venmo
And basically
The first way involves taking
Taking all of the money that
I have on venmo.
That you have on venmo that anyone who
Who puts their money on venmo
Taking all that money
Putting it in a pile and then
Collecting the interest on it at
And investing it okay that's one way
Another way is there are the small fees UK
Can pay for certain
One is if you want to transfer money to your bank more quickly
They charge a fee
Okay another is if you want
Is a credit card on
Okay that makes sense a lot of companies like them
Do that
Kind of thing to earn money but I noticed also so I have Uber and now when I go to take an Uber I can
Hey with Ben
Are they earning money off of that
They are what venmo has started to do
As they approached retailers
Jason said
Look up Uber
Look GrubHub
If you let people pay with venmo
You will have access to
All these young
People with disposable income
And if you let us process those payments will just charge a small fee
Okay so
Venmo gets money and these
Retailers get young hip
People like you
Exactly
It's our parting gift thanks Shane
Thank you Karen
Karen
Alex
I have listened to question
Before you do that's great because we're doing a listener question show come prepared
My question comes from Anthony Ellison
It has to do with the Federal Reserve and interest rates
The Federal Reserve is the Central Bank of the United States and the
The target interest rate ranges that it sets
It's like the throttle for the American economy
The economy a bit
Then you raise interest rates will
You want to boost the economy
Make it cheaper to borrow money
Contigo Spanish
But when they do this
And they change the target range range
They always do it in increments of
.25
Percent
So
Anthony Elizondo his
Question was
Why did they always do it in increments of .25
Percent I mean even when the Federal Reserve has made huge moves like during the financial crisis
They did it
With five
Or a clean one for
Always
Increments of .25
Right because we live in this super-precise world so why are we still moving this
Really important number in is chunky
.25 increments
Nobody in the office New
So I called up Donald Cohen who is now
Senior fellow at
Institution
Before that I worked at the Federal Reserve for 40 years
But he says
There wasn't any specific moment or decision that made
.25%
I think I'm a new challenge my memory when your email yesterday
But I believe when I started in the 1970
The federal funds rate was quoted
Yeah
Ace and quarters
And have then
5/8
Etc it's just easier to talk that way as
People write you work at a bank you called another bank and you say hey I want to borrow some money from you at two and a quarter percent
Two and a half
Right like I'm not going to ask you for 4:30 of a donut I'm going to ask you for
A half a donut or if I'm being good
Corte rapido
Stella Corner point was is obvious
A286 a nice
This round number
I think it's also
Large enough
To Mater
So it's a non-trivial change in interest rates
But it's not huge
.25% is like a Goldilocks
But he also says what's important is not the exact range
Did the Federal Reserve set
It's whether the range is going to go up or going to go down
The direction
That is the signal that matters
Economy
But right here this is where
I'm with our listener
If this target rate is soham
Important
Shouldn't
The Federal Reserve be more precise and not
Less
So I push down
Did anybody in any of those meetings ever say hey guys let's just try .62
I know
No not that I can not that I can remember always happen if somebody said that I think someone would have said but that's not the
The way the market works
And why would we go ahead and do that so I think you need a reason to deviate
From what you've been doing all along
And holding steady looking measured and consistent
Is very important
Alright thanks Alex
You got it
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
If you have questions please send them our way as you can tell we do read them
You can reach out to us on email Planet Money at npr.org we are also on Twitter Instagram Facebook
At Planet Money Today Show was produced by Alexi Horowitz Godley and Sally Helm are supervising producer
Is Alex goldmark our editor is brighter stat I am Karen Duffin thanks for listening
All right we're going to sneak in
One last quick question
Hi
Do you want to introduce yourself
I am your identical twin sister Marita
I got a question that I think you might be the most qualified
Answer
Okay go on
We get lots of this kind of mail for men and women
Writing in to let us know that they do not like the voices of
Specifically the women on the show
Valley girls
People sing Christian
How to throw d
I recently got one from a listener who I'm going to call Amelia and this one caught my eye because she
The question in it
I don't think she meant it to be but it's actually kind of a legitimate question
And I thought that my twin sister could answer
She said that my intonation makes me sound uncertain of myself and that when I introduce myself it sounds as if I'm asked
A question like
I am Karen Duffin
Well
Illegal.
Cube indicate that you are definitely
Karen Duffin
But I can't say for sure that you are
Why
Because
When we are born
Mom and dad did Mavis right away
So we just had wristbands
Listen baby girl number one in baby girl number two
So
You might be Marita
So Amelia is onto something
I know I'm really a thought she was just give me a little bit of advice
But really
She's uncovered a bigger mystery this is like
Connect serial
Next on serial
I am Karen duck