So last month I was in South America
I was in Santiago Chile which is a beautiful city
There are parts that actually reminded me of Beverly Hills
Glass
Towers
Palm trees
Ton of shopping
Oh I know I'm from
Cantina MD
Shopping malls
Concealed AR
Legend
So I was driving around Santiago with carola Fuentes
She's a journalist and a filmmaker who's done some amazing reporting on Chile's economy
Now we are arriving to the park at I'll go with you
Very very big mall
And we are going to the McDonald's
So you went to a foreign country and you went straight to McDonald's
Is pathetic
But I wanted to test out something that I had heard about Chile that I found really hard to believe
What I've heard about
McDonald's in Chile
Is it we can buy food here and then we can
Pay for it in installments
Right
You can paint
Installments no interest
Or you can pay nine stohlman with interest I could buy a hamburger and pay for it in 9 installments
Right
So we pull up to the window to order
In my credit card did not work so we use Kerala
I will be paying for dysentery for 9 months
I paid her back
But this is the reason I was in Chile
It has some
Pork
They're just really interesting to an economics reporter
I mean come on
The financial aized the hamburger
It's like this
Wonderland of free market capitalism
Orig developed country
That is the Envy of its neighbors like Argentina and Venezuela
All this
Came out of real car
And that story
Is one of the
Strangest and most dramatic stories in economic history
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Noel King and I'm Jasmine cars
Today on the show we go to Chile
A country that was one of the Battleground
Of the Cold War the war between Marxism and capitalism
Between dictatorship and freedom
Any chili they were Economist on the front lines of this war
Most of them and trained at the University of Chicago
They called them
The Chicago boys
Support for NPR comes from LinkedIn learning
Proud to support the launch of life
NPR's guy to help you make better life decisions
LinkedIn learning short video tutorials cover business Tech and creative skills employers look for
At every level all taught by expert
Mu courses are added every week
+ LinkedIn learning is personalized
Recommended courses based on your intro
And Life kid listeners get a month of learning
Restart your
Free trial at LinkedIn learning.com NPR
Jasmine you were the person who first told me about the Chicago boys to be honest I was a little surprised you've never heard of them these guys
Is there a super famous in economically circles in South America
So I started reading about them in right away I thought
This might be the craziest story about it
Economist that I've ever heard
And I thought
I have got to meet these guys
So I spent a couple of months calling around
The Chicago boys are old now they're in their eighties
And most of them didn't want to talk to
They have their reasons
But then finally one of them said
Okay
Intervista elevator
Very nice building okay
And that is how I ended up
In Santiago
Oh my goodness hello
Your elevator opens on to your apartment that's
Very nice
Hit you
I'm so sorry
These are not my clothes
The airline lost my bag is the worst
Anyway why didn't
Go ahead and tell me your name and tell me what you do
Best my name is Rolf losers
And I am a professor of Economics at the castle Universal
So
You are
Your Chicago boy
I haven't Chicago boys
Yes
Here's a story of how he came to be a Chicago boy
In 1958 he's 22 years old
Annie's just graduated from college
And he gets this really exciting invitation to study at the University of Chicago in the United States
Chicago has this scholarship program going it's funded by the US government
Beers at work
Looters gets flown up to Chicago to the University of Chicago he gets to get an advanced degree in economics or busy
For free
In return he has to come back to Teala and teach what is learn to college kids
Looters is from an upper-middle-class household his dad owns an electronics store like Best Buy
He's never been out of chili
So when he's offered a place
Chicago kicks
She gets on a plane with four other young smart Chilean guys
The Landing Miami they rent a car they take a road trip
And they are marveling at how developed the United States is
Tremendous
List of buildings
The store
A different world
This plants a seed in luders head
He sees that the United States has a lot of material wealth
And also a lot of free
They get to Chicago and they're giving about $90 a month
And they're told
Listen
This isn't Thailand
University this is going to be really intense
He said he took off
Saturday
But what about the weather
Bethel Sundays we would be back
At the library
Study which
For me initially was
Absolutely crazy but later on you get accustomed to it and saw a monks
Yes
Yes Sorel fluters is deep in his studies at Chicago
And while he's there
He meets a man who's going to change his life
And the future of his country of Chile
Milton Friedman
Looters remembers him as
Brilliant
Articulate
Physically
Very very small
1 meter 60 or something like that he was also very busy
Friedman was on his way to becoming really well known for his worldview
This firm belief that economic freedom
And personal and political Freedom go together
Free markets Friedman thought lead to political freedom
So bottom line
The government should stay out of the economy
So he argued that even like
Public schools are sign of government being too big
National parks should be run by private come
The operation of a
Even more
Naruto says he's relationship with Friedman was not about ideology
Lucas is interested in inflation
So is freedom
They hit it off
And looters ask Friedman to be his thesis advisor
Friedman says okay
Saludos writes his thesis a monetary history of Chile
And he turns it in
He waits a while
Then while longer
And finally he asks Friedman have you read past the first chapter
Economist
Those who ride
And those who read
And I'm one of those right so he hadn't read the rest of this
Thesis advisor and you haven't registered
Well
Did that's the way he was
Luda gets a degree
And he makes good on the pledge
In 1960 he goes back to too late.
And it's not just real food or so at this point there's now a whole group of Chilean men who studied it Chicago
And then come back to chili to teach
All of this economic knowledge
I just looters aside from all the technical stuff you were learning
What was like the big idea that you took away from Chicago
The system
Does make a big difference
In the well-being of the people
Very important
Do have the right sister
When he gets back too late is an upheaval his country is fighting
Over this precise thing
What kind of economic system are they going to have
Here's what's happening
Chile is run by a tiny Elite group of people
If you're poor you're going to stay poor there's no such thing as upward Mobility
People are fighting just to eat
But here's the thing she late is a democracy
If people are fed up they're going to vote
To change this
And that's what they do
Two in the mid-60s the government is respond
The first thing they do is a policy that is now known as agrarian reform
The government will go to wealthy landowners and say
We're going to buy your land for a low price
We're going to put it into a cooperative and then we're going to redistributed among the poor
This expropriation
Causes very deep divide
One Gabrielle Valdez wrote an important book about the Chicago boys and about with chili was like back then
Lisa Grant reform
Could you study normous division in society
Because you had
The extraordinary cases in which
The Sun for instance working for the government
How to decide the expropriation of the land of his
Pirates
And this happened in fact
This happened in fact that a man would go knock on his father's door and say hey Pop
We're giving the land to
To The Peasants exactly like that because that would be in a movie
It was one of those situations where everybody knew someone or knew someone who knew someone
Roth looters had a friend from the University of Chicago a fellow Chicago boy
This guy's dad dropped dead of a heart attack when the government came to take his land
This is a very heavy time
The fight over land reform is pushing people further to the left and the right
And this environment provides an opening
For a leftist politician
Salvador Allende
Celebrity is a complicated
To the Marxist who also love the good life
Wine
Nice clothes
Ian day is also a
Appalled at the conditions at Port Orleans are living in
And he's been running for president for like the last 18 years
Talking about his socialist vision for chili
And keeps losing
Politician he's got an issue
The copper in
Chili's got tons of valuable copper
Videos on shooting sticks in the mind
The profits are mostly going to American
And she says
That isn't right
If I'm elected
I will make those profit
It's go back to Thalia
And it resonates people get riled up
A&A even gets his own bard of folk singer named Victor Jara
Who's this handsome guy
From a poor peasant family who writes these beautiful Tunes
My guitar is not for the rich no nothing like that
My song is a bladder that we're building to reach the Stars
He's like Chili's Bob Dylan
Wake up Woody Guthrie
All of this is going down during the Cold War
In the United States Marxism is seen as the most
Sinister force in the world
Capitalism
Is what we liked capitalism is the thing that keeps us free
To President Richard Nixon
Heats communist
Tells the CIA
Whatever you've been doing in Chile
Do more of it
NES classic
CIA
Agendas running for president in the CIA funnels money to his opponents
Pace for a massive propaganda
Leaflets pamphlets
Radio shows
What are the big moves it's fear-mongering they compare I ended to Fidel Castro
And Castro
And the Cuban Revolution really are on everyone's mind
Ralph Lueders the Chicago Boys still in Academia in Santiago he's a d now
And he is starting to worry that chili is on the verge of a revolution like you
Then one day with the big presidential election coming up
One of his grad students comes to him and says
Listen man
I need to talk to you
This kid is a left
He sets Ross
We're going to get into power
And when we get into power
Yuan
All your friends
I going to be in trouble
And I suggest
You leave the country
Did he say what would happen to you if you didn't
No he didn't
I wouldn't have a good time
Looters
Gets out
He takes a job in Washington DC
And the kid was right
I didn't it overcomes all of the meddling and wins the election
Marxist
Are you for
This is beer Revolution
But if you are middle or upper class
This feels like the end of the world
And I am the makes good on his promise
She starts nationalizing
Right away
He nationalized
Spanx
Textile plants
Cement plant
Epic Brewery nationalized
Atlanta Barber
Large drilling Corporation
About time
Samosa
Large companies
Fell into government hands
Including American,
Ayinde goes ahead and nationalizes the copper industry like he promised
Hundreds of millions of dollars of us investment
Gone
This is bad for business
Cedar Street
Bad business
There's confusion there are strikes output plummets
And he also makes good on his promise to help
The poor he gives free milk to all young till and kids
He orders
Pay raises for blue collar workers
And he creates a ton of government jobs
But
You have to pay for all this
Agenda is printing money
Rachel has been dealing with inflation for years
But now inflation is staggering
If it's 700%
Chile's economy shutters
This whole time
President Nixon is doing whatever you can
Can't undermine idea
There's this
Hoarding of him in the Oval Office
Talking about Chile
And she says this is a quote all's Fair on
Kik of India
Okay it's very nexonia
Anyway he cuts off loans
And foreign aid grants and credits
The Chi-Lites
And then so does the world
China's economy is gasp
And then come the shortage
EMS government fixes price
It tells food producers
You can only charge so much for things like rice and wheat and noodle
Will they can earn a profit so they stop producing food
Rough litters is living in Washington during this. So he didn't see much of this go down
So while I was in Santiago I went to see Patricia arencibia Claudel
Tell me a story
Delicious treat she's a historian who has written a lot about the Chicago boys and is friends with some of
I asked her to tell me what it was like back
Did she ever have trouble buying anything during period
Oh yeah
Yeah
That other voices Honus Romero a young local journalists who is interpreting
His editor said that he could work with me for a day to
Learn something about Chile in his
Anyway
In 1972 Patricia is a teenager
And she's getting up at 6 a.m. to stand in line
Git
Cigarette
Wine capable
Feliciana Co-op
Google
Nada
There's no sugar so people start putting candy in their coffee if they can get
Coffee
And the hoard food and that leads to even more shortages
There was a point in about 1970
YouTube where the only food
Did you could buy what's I tell you said big pizzas
Big big
Oak and pork
Kent Kent book is similar to spam
Where you at
Spam from China
Central Chino
Patricia's family is right-wing she comes from a military family
And she joins a militant radical right-wing group
Cold but really Berta
Fatherland and Liberty
And she goes out in
8 hour
Ultra matter
Automata
Unilever glasses
Hey I don't go to the
A clock
You went into the streets in the streets
In the year 71 the worst
Very important and big a protest called the protest of the empty pots
Been in the NFL
Santiago
Bye bye bye
It's nothing in the pot
Because there was nothing to put in the box
Did she bring the pain
Oh yes
Fado music
A few months later things got worse
In October of 72
Truckers organize strikes
Across the country
We now know that the CIA was paying people to support that strike it's huge
Everything in Chile moves on land
The country is paralyzed
Work shuts down and again
People go out into the
Patricia is out there to of course and she comes across a group of leftist men
Beating up a right-wing guy
So she starts talking smack to them and they come after her
Disco
Gemini
Sunnymede south of this attackers
Set
It's a woman
Call a woman a woman
Medical pillow
If I swallow
Yo
Acuna
Angela Marcado abacab
This woman
Went to Patricia I grabbed her hair started to pulling around here
And getting her scratches
She still to this day
NASCAR
What did that what did she
It was a woman
So
Yes
Liki Tiki Village
Casino doodle
She says that
That was
Nothing it was
So not real
So
Abnormalize
That
Uno Salia La Casa sin cerveza
See you leave your house in the morning
But you didn't know if you're going to get back
The right and the left are both
Radicalize now
Identikit on the radio and he warns of a civil war
He declares a state of emergency in Santiago
Any puts an army officer in charge of keeping things
Call
A general named Augusto Pinochet
The break the Chicago boys come up with a plan
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Lucien table Espanol
One afternoon Ralph looters and I caught in a taxi and we drove to Providencia which is this ritual neighborhood
Draped in trees
Satanism
Because it would
Yeah
We waited outside of a pretty white brick house and he pointed to a window up on the set
That's weather
That's weather brick Westwood
The Brick
With the Economy Inn
Free fall
Some of the Chicago boys some of this small group of Economist who know each other from the University of Chicago
They start meeting in a room in this house
They sit around a table and they hash out an economic plan for their collapsing country
They're like doctors writing a prescription for a sick patient
Drink more water eat more fiber
Unfix the prices Stop Printing money
Cut tariffs
Let inefficient Industries die
The manuscript get so big
Someone starts calling it a lottery
The Brick
The idea is
They're going to offer it to whatever government comes next
They would offer the program
Do any government who succeeded
I didn't
While we're sitting outside of that White House
Reuters tells me
The Economist were up in one room
But in another room there are the offices of a magazine that has links
To a conservative newspaper called el Mercurio
The CIA is pain that newspaper
The turnout
Orioles about how I ended is making a mess
Out of the car
So of course you wonder
Did the CIA pay for the bridge
30 is old Declassified CIA files
From the time
Dimension collaborators working on an economic plan
But they don't
Name any name
So we might never know
Let's said the world of Chicago educated economist
And spies
And journalists being paid by spies It's a Small World
Someone in Chile's military knows that these guys are working on a plan to fix the economy
Router says when the military hears that
They decide it's time to move
The military probably would have not taking over government
If they didn't have it program
Had the military seen the brick in advance
Did hurt
Yes
Oh my God relationship between
The Brick
And the military coup in the sense that
The military coup would not have taken place
The daily
At that time
If it wouldn't have been for
But for the breaker
On September 11th 1973 Chile military launches
And one of these men who slides in between the world of military and propaganda
Takes the brick
Fires up a mimeograph machine
And starts cranking out copies
By the next day
The military will have the brick in their hands
On the next episode The Chicago boys get their shot at fixing She lays economy
Is a coup a capitalist Revolution end the end for a Time
Of democracy in Chile
That's next time on Planet Money
I'm Noel King on Jazmine Garcia
Thanks for listening