Alright padlock is gone and it is recording
This recording is the first time that Caitlin McCollum talk to end
He was teaching Spanish at a public high school in Tennessee
Most of our students came from a relatively low income rural
I told them today that I had an interview with you all and
Atkins many of them as they left plastic good luck really hope things
You know are putting the motion from this interview
Back in college
Caitlin had made this deal with the United States
Education
She promised
Teach at a low income school for four years
Heat exchange
Madea we gave her $16,000 for college
Free and clear not alone
After three years of doing exactly what she said she would
She got the letter
I remember going out to the mailbox I even opened it up at the mailbox
Came inside and
Sheer Panic just sat in
The letter was about the deal Caitlin had made with
With the Department of
Education
Yes
She had spent
3 years teaching exactly where she said she would
But
There was a problem with Caitlin's paperwork saying that she was teaching
Where she said she
The government had allegedly received that paperwork
Or maybe three days late
Seemingly not a big problem after all they got
The paperwork
Except
Has the letter explained
In this case
The punishment
Was it the entire deal was now torn up and can't
Kaitlyn
Was going to have to repay the Department of Education
Every penny
They gave her
Back in college
I remember my husband coming in the house and I was sobbing
I'm just absolutely sobbing and
We actually
I just found out
That I was pregnant with our first child
And then
To be hit with this
I feel like it's so very unjust and unethical
But there's nothing that I can do because I'm such a small fish against the federal government
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Kenny Malone
For more than a year
Two of our colleagues at NPR have been investigating stories like Caitlin McCollum
And discovered
Thousands of teachers across the country
Made a deal to help
Struggling schools
Did what they promise
And we're ultimately rewarded
With millions of dollars
Today on the show
The story of how the Department of Education
Turned into what many teachers felt
Was a ruthless
Predatory loan
Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from policygenius.com
The easy way to compare and buy insurance online
With policygenius you can compare quotes from top rated carriers
Get unbiased advice from licensed experts and apply online in minute
Whether you're shopping for life
Disability Home Auto or renters insurance
If you care about it
Vacant cover
Compare and save on insurance today at policygenius.com
Drag has been around for a while
In the Kabuki tradition in Japan
Minstrel show
In Vaudeville
But one TV show made it mainstream
Now
We break down drags current Renaissance
Check out NPR's it's been a minute
Now
So how does it how does this begin you like a tip from a
I don't know somebody in a trench coat would it How does it go
It's trench coat this is Chris Arnold
He's an investigative reporter at NPR who covers consumer protection
Yes oats I get this tap and it makes me like look at their stuff worth digging into around the Department of Education and
Things that are going on in and that gets me to look at this lawsuit wasn't digging through
I see this mention of this program called
The teach Grant Pro
Did you ever heard of this before no not at all I'm reading this lawsuit same time Chris is
Cory Turner NPR also worked on this invest
And I'm the education reporter
And I do the same thing I stumbled across
Teach Grant
Never heard of it
The teach grant program started more than a decade
Will the members in the aisles please take their conversations the back of the chamber
Teach was just a small part of this bill
Call the college cost reduction Act
Mm
It was sponsored
By Democratic representative
George Miller
For students in college
And want to teach
Did they make a commitment to teach
In difficult Public Schools
We will provide $4,000 a year in tuition assistance while they're in school
So prospective teachers could get up to $16,000 free and clear
If they went and taught at a low income School
After the garage
But if for some reason somebody took that money and then didn't go and
And teach like
Promise
There was this provision
Allowed the government to say
Hey listen
You got to give us that money
Yeah that Graham is going to become alone
Yeah and that's totally reasonable right I mean cuz if
Someone said yes sure Mana I'll become a teacher and then they
Go backpacking what is the teacher in your Universe from Fast Times at Ridgemont High
Do you like a Fast Times at Ridgemont High type guy looks like you
MMA just go screw off
Like of course the government's going to want his money back
The Corey and Kris after reporting out that
Encrypted trench Cody message
It started to hear that this nuclear option
Converting to Grant into a loan
Was being used for the smallest stuff
Paperwork are
Amidst signature
Filing a form a day late
Sister calling teachers
Who had this happen
David you're using your voice memo recorder right it running right now excellent what are the first teachers they found was a guy named
David West
One day David also got
One of those letters saying
Your paperwork
What's a couple days late
Your teach Grant
Is now a teacher
Loan
Hey
Initially my feeling was surely this is a mistake
Surely this
Can't be that big a deal
Let me call them up
So we get somebody on the phone and he explains like hey
I'm teaching where I'm supposed to
Can we just get this cleared up
And the person is like
No
You were two days late
And technically
We are now allowed to
Turn your Grant
Into a loan
David is like
White
I was
2 days late on paperwork
And essentially the fine for that
Is that I now owe thousands
Dollars on the job fine I owe you the money
I did the job fair like Loan Sharks I mean I'm surprised nobody showed up to
Kept my knees with a bat
Again David is not dealing with some shady payday lender
This is a program run by the United States.
Department of ed
I could believe it
Score.
You know you got to let me talk to your supervisor blah blah blah you can talk and she said you can talk to who you want
And there's also an appeals process and you can try to appeal this if you want
But nobody ever wins
That's exactly what she said to me.
Wow really yes
I wish I'd recorded that call I remember thinking
In the moment as soon as he said that
Does that mean that
The folks in this call center here this so often
That like
They just know to say it like
Sorry buddy
Don't even bother
Yeah it's like we start asking around and we managed to get our hands on this internal report that
The Edge apartment actually done on this teacher
Which program in in there
What is the answer to our question of what how many teachers
I've gotten screwed up like this
It was
A shocking
We have some exclusive reporting from NPR to bring
Kristen Corey ran a story about
The internal teacher
Grant report
But they've gotten
1 in
3 people
Two lost their grants
Said they did meet those teaching requirements or were likely to
The report estimates based on a representative survey that it's upwards
12000 teachers
And it's
Could be a lot more
The Department of Education wouldn't talk
Kris and Corey on tape for the store
But they did give this written statement the kind of said
Oh yeah these numbers do not look good
We're going to have to look
That radio story ran
In March
F2008
You know you do a story you get some feedback on this one it was like Twitter exploded email inboxes exploded
The teacher saying this is exactly what happened to be upset
Sad angry so many people telling us they got hurt
One of those people
What's Caitlin McCollum
The teacher that you heard at the very
Beginning of this episode
Are you guys can you team up for me get in your color groups for me awesome
Horse teaches at a low income School in Tennessee but
The first time Corey and Kris met her in person
What's on a student field trip to Washington
Kaitlyn with a shopper
They met up with is pretty noisy
Shopping mall food
For Caitlin explained
Her family had built their life around her teeth grow
Life decisions
Based on
What kind of school you had the teacher in because of these grants
Every year it seems that we've had a different opportunity or at least option that we could have looked in
Into
Had we not been in this
Predicament
To get a sense of how big these
Life trade-offs work
You just need to talk to Kaitlyn husband AJ who
Also happened to be on this
Yes the way that the grant was structured Caitlin had to teach in AJ and Kaitlyn moved specifically to a place
I swear Caitlin could fulfill her teeth Grant require
AJ happens to be in the military
Sun after they've already moved
DJ found out
Where he had qualified
For Flight School
Which was
I mean obviously dream any anybody that's that has any interest in the military if you qualified to be a pile
That's that's one of those things that it's surreal
So
We had to look at that and say we we can't leave
Kaitlyn and AJ ran the math and unfortunately for AJ it just made economic sense for them to stay where they were
Caitlin could keep teaching
Keeper grants
And it wouldn't get buried in debt
AJ passed on his
Flight school dream so that Caitlyn could keep her promise to the Department of
And then of course
Caitlin got that letter
Asia got home from work one day
And Caitlin was in tears
She said I don't know what we're going to do and I said I said I'll tell you
We're not paying it back she said
She said we can't do that and I said I said
I wear a uniform with a flag on my sleeve they're not taking our money
It's wrong and that's that was the culmination of our conversation that night
As you heard earlier Caitlin paperwork was allegedly late by
Two or three days but
But we didn't mention is that it's not just
The Kaitlyn's entire $16,000 in Grants was suddenly converted to
You alone
The way this is enforced is that
They got to go back in time and say oh well actually
These grants now they were always alone
End
Clearly you haven't been paying down that loan because
Of course you haven't
Because you had no idea it was a loan
But that doesn't matter
Now there's all this backdated interest pile
And so with interest
Caitlyn actually now owed around
$21,000
And for Caitlin
Who was making around $30,000 a year
That was a sudden
Massive
Financial burden
Sometimes I can go a whole week and not even think about
This whole issue
And then I'll be doing something so mean you'll like washing dishes or taking a shower
Hit me like a ton of bricks
Oh my God
I owe all of that money
And it still isn't fixed
And what am I
Do
And it's
Like I need a buckling moment of
Panic All Over Again
After the break
How to try and fix a bureaucracy
At a Starbucks
Support also comes from the United States Postal Service
Everyday innovator companies are Reinventing the way business has
But none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce the United States
Postal Service
See why they deliver more e-commerce packages to home
Almost been anyone in the country
USPS.com future
Hey everyone this is Stacey Vanek Smith
Co-host of the indicator from Planet Money where every day we bring you a short story about the economy
This week on the show we check in with the protest in Hong Kong we go ax throwing
And we talked with private firefighters in California
Check out the indicator from planet
What Kris and Corey had found was the
Is classic Spirit of the law vs. letter of the law problem
Technically
Messed up paperwork or whatever
Violated this deal that thousands of teachers had made
With the government but
What really was that deal it was
To go and teach in a low-income School
Takorean Chris figured if they could just explain this to the right people at the Department of Education
Shirley
This is the kind of thing that
So we set up
This meeting with
Some officials
At the department of Ed
And we get coffee
We go to Starbucks
We sit outside on the
And Chris is falling down from boss
Denso
He's there in his Snappy jacket
Should I have a snack
You always were the same Snappy jacket a lot of this meeting
Was off the Record but
Gordon Chris say they can share a general sense of
They told us sources
About Caitlin McCollum and what kind of a teacher
This is this is
Exactly the kind of person you wanted
Going through this program
And now here she is
Suffering
Because of it
It did it doesn't make any sense
It's not
Right
And so
Remember you just kept asking why
Why
Can't you just
Fix-It yeah like like the moment that I I remember like
You know can it just be as simple as
If they're teaching in a low-income school they get the grants back cuz who cares about the paperwork
Right yeah
And there was like a long pause
And kind of a shake of the head
And it would be like what it was something like for what it what was it would be at Whistling like
Well that would be nice but
You just don't understand how complicated that is not that they necessarily disagreed
They were telling us
We're not sure that's even
Impossible
So Corey and Kris were like
Okay
I guess we will just
Keep doing this story
Especially
Now that they had met the perfect example
Of how badly this could go
It's been two years of
Torture
Caitlin McCollum
Is a high school
Again for this story the Department of Education would not do an on tape interview
But on the exact same morning that this story ran
The Secretary of Education with schedule
To testify in Congress
About something completely unrelated
To the teach grant program
Were you intentionally trolling the Secretary of Education by running a story about Kate
Caitlin the morning
The device was supposed to testify in Capitol Hill about other things I think the honest answer is no but had we
Like actually thought about it we very well may have trolled her
It's a privilege to welcome secretary DeVos
For her first appearance before the education Workforce committee
Intentional or not it appeared to have worked
At least one house representative
His staffer Maybe
Just happened to catch
The Kaitlyn story on end
NPR it was the ranking Democrat of the house education and labor committee
Bobby Scott
Weather report this morning of the debacle going on with teachers who are fulfilled
In the process of fulfilling their
Loan forgiveness
Requirements
Technically not a loan forgiveness program but
Close enough Bobby Scott
How long have you Department known about that
Are you speaking of the teacher grant program
We are aware of
The issues within that program and have
Taken steps to address the issues they're in your new legislation to fix it
I don't believe so
DeVos
Acknowledges
Yeah we got
That's basically what she say
We've got
I didn't request you know is that just like a blow off yet or is that no really work committed and if that
Weiner very idea
Department of Education had already announced
A top-to-bottom review
Ava teacher
Grant program likely
In response to some of Chris and Cory's earlier reporting
And so they kept going
They worked with the lawyer from the organization public citizen
Could manage to get hundreds of document
It's about the teach grant program
Under the Freedom of Information
Do you learn that the program is better or worse than you thought
You know definitely worse things just
Caring for example Kris and Corey found this memo
Written by the contractor but the Department of Education had hired
Kind of deal with a teach Grant
Is contractor was writing a memo to the Department of Education about
The program
Basically this memo says
Gyro guys
We're actually converting to loans
A lot of teachers who seem to be
MTG Spirit of the program
And maybe that's not such a good idea
With that they had found the exact same thing you had found basic
Even this company
Is waving his flag saying
Please don't make us hurt these teachers and
Nothing happens
And then Chris and Corey found that there was this whole other pool
I'll teach Grant teacher
As many as 10
Thousand
Who had mistakenly
Heather teach Grant turned in
By mistake this isn't even the paperwork or anything right and then that raises the question
She's what they do about it
Well the answer is not a lot
But slowly
Over the course of like 7 months
Cording Crusade
Tone from their sources at the Department of Education just
Started the chain
From we don't know if it's
Possible to fix this
I think this might be possible
To we think we can actually fix
And I kept asking Corey and Kris like okay
But why did it change
Who changed it who were the evil person hurting teacher
And Kris and Corey kept saying no no it's not like that that's not always how
These government meant well but screwed it all up
Stories go
I think
In one really important
We love our story to have a
Yeah and
I think for the longest time
I just assumed that the department was
Or that the
You know the company that managed the program for the Department was the villain
That must be making money off this somehow there's some kind of scam
Who's profiting off
You know all this company must be getting rich on the back of these teachers in
Corruption corruption
And
The scary thing is this is
This is 2019 and the villain
Was Barack
I didn't with the bureaucracy that spanned
The Bush Administration the Obama Administration
And the first half the truck ministration
I mean
And this just
What is this
Machine that was not being chain
Chugging along
Hurting people
The good news
For me is that
Ultimately that bureaucracy is made
And
If we
Just
Convince
Enough of those humans
To change direction
And
Move toward
A kinder
Gentler program
It actually happened
Finally after more than a year
Kris and Corey got word from the Department of
It was top secret
But the deal was.
Department
Was going to agree
The if teachers could prove they were and still are going to keep their end of the deal
The department would convert their loans back in
Again
This was not public information
But
Corey and Kris couldn't wait
They wanted to tell Caitlin McCollum themselves
So they asked a local producer to go over to Caitlin's house
I'm going to
That's Caitlin and her husband age
And this was back in December
AGT app for dogs
Kaitlyn in the producer Lexi
Sit down by the phone so chrisanne
Inquiry
Intoxicating
Yes Lexie and I are sitting in my living room looking at my
Pine needles all over the floor because we put up a Christmas tree last night
I think we've got
Some good news here
You actually
Okay
As long as you
Can now prove
That you were still meeting the
Teaching requirements you doing what you promised you do
You're going to get your grandpa
Are you serious
Oh my God
REI
That is such good news
That's a good news
And I remember Lexie or engineer telling
That sheep she went to the other room where her husband AJ was
Star sun and
They had a baby gate
And
You know our Story begins with her at the mailbox getting that letter went
Pregnant
Her son is now I think he's
Pek to
And
As she's telling AJ
But it's all over
Elam
We have to keep it under wraps until Monday
She's leaning over the baby gate on one side and he's leaning over the baby gate on the other side and they're hugging
Living life
Aspire
You have us both
At least I'm in here so I don't know
Throughout this entire year of reporting
Kris and Corey had had trouble getting anybody from the Department of Education
You actually record an interview
On tape
What is the Department of Education started to roll out this fix
Kris and Corey got an interview
In one of the most unbrand moments of this whole story
The person chosen to be the face of this so far mostly faceless bureaucracy
With a senior official with a spectacularly long time
Diane Auer Jones with my name and my title is principal Deputy under secretary delegated the duties of us
Under secretary and assistant secretary for postsecondary education
And towards the end of that energy
There is this kind of unbelievable moment this thing that you just
Don't necessarily expect to hear
From someone representing
A bureaucracy
This is your chance to talk to a couple million people many of them are teachers
And I'm sure he's what would you say to them now about teacher
How sorry we are I mean obviously we want to extend an apology we've put
Teachers
Who didn't deserve the stress this pressure this financial burden
In a position that is stressful and frightening and
Confusing and
I can't give them back those years that I can't take away the gray hairs and I can't take away the stress
It seems like a small thing to do to say I'm sorry
But I'm very sorry and we want to work to fix it and correct it
As of this story around 7000 teachers
Have applied to get there
Teach grants
So far the vast majority of those
Qualify
The find out
Ironically the same way they found out everything was screwed up
But a letter in the mail
From the Department of
Caitlin McCallum got hers
Just before she was leaving on a family
She brought the letter
With her in the car
Her husband was driving
Her son was in the back seat
Congratulations
Qualifies you have your
Learn to teach Grant
Can you say yay
I love your dance moves buddy
If you would like more planet money in your life we are happy to tell you that we have a
Relatively new Weekly Newsletter
You can subscribe I going to npr.org
Planet Money newsletter that is
Npr.org
Planet Money
Newsletter
Planet Money is edited by Bryant urstadt Alex goldmark is our supervising producer today's episode was produced by
Lexi Horwitz Ghazi and
Of course it was reported by Chris Arnold and Corey.
And by the way if
If you like to support Planet Money
One great way to do that is it to leave us a review
On whatever podcasting app you're using
You could also tell a friend you could send some of your favorite episode
You could even help them subscribe to the podcast
Any of that would be
Anthony Malone
This is NPR
Thanks for listening