Just a quick note that today show is a rerun
It's a show about a big
Bet and since the show aired back in 2016
Stepbet concluded
At the end today will have an update on how the bat works
Carl Lewis has known Warren Buffett for a long time
We've been friends for how many years 33 1614 at 50 years
50 years
Loomis is a reporter she worked for decades at Fortune Magazine
Warren Buffett of course
CEO of Berkshire Hathaway
Legendary investor also
Third richest man on the planet
What kind of stuff do you do together
What we play bridge
He's an avid online bridge player
And when the computer breaks down at drives him crazy
Warren Buffett just like your grandpa
Only rich
Much
Much rich
We called Charles Loomis because of the story she has been deeply involved in
For a number of years now
The story about a bit
It seems like you're sort of the
The bookie
No I wouldn't say that I would think of myself as the biographer
Of the batch
I'm still going to call her the book
She is not the Boogie
She said the story the BET starts back in 2006
It's at the Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting
Which is this big thing every year
It's like this capitalist Woodstock that would have texted call me that's like the unofficial
Joke meme
Thousands of people fly in Buffett is up on this stage talking and the subject of hedge funds comes up
You know hedge funds like investment firms for rich people with the
Dalian phds working crazy long hours
And buffeted those guys
They are not worth the fees they are charging investors
So he says I'm willing to make a bet
I can pick an investment that will beat the Hedgehog
I don't nobody
Ever
Realize that anyone would pick him up on this bed
You certainly wasn't going to do it for a small amount of money
I knew you want to make a
Declaration by the size of the bet that this is a serious matter
If you guys from the headphone World hear about this Challenge and they say sure will take you up on it
On January 1st 2008
They make a ten-year bet
So how big is the bed
$1000000
It sounds like a lot of money
It is
Hedge fund guys been on hedge fund
These groups
I'm super smart
Elite investing
Buffett for his side of the bed key does not pick a few stocks he doesn't even take his own company
He picks one of the most
Brainless
Boring Investments theories
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm David kestenbaum
Today on the show
$1000000 bet over a very deep
Which is better
A group of really smart money managers
Or the simplest stupidest investment idea in the world
We asked each side
What are you thinking
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
What's that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
This is not just a bit fitting a billionaire against a bunch of head
If you have any money invested in the stock
If you have something socked away for retirement
Kids college fund or whatever
You have taken aside in this bed whether you know it or not
We wanted to understand both sides
Let's do the Warren Buffett
The weapon he chose in his battle again
The hedge funds
The simple brainless investment he picked
Is grated far from Wall Street in Malvern Pennsylvania
Is created by this man
I'm probably the cheapest guy you'll ever meet in your life John Seibel
How to buy anything
How old are these pants you wear
Yeah I'd say fifteen 15 years the sweater was that an LL Bean that's probably only about 8
Bogle as you may know founded
Company called Vanguard
Name by the way after a ship in the British Navy during the Napoleonic Wars
Yeah you walk around up the office is out there in Malvern and you feel like
They have bought every single oil painting of every old naval battle in his
There is barely a picture that does not have a ship
That's the way it is we like ships
I saw this one painting that was just an ocean of the others once just a notion you like know that is the view from the
That simple brainless investment that Warren Buffett picked in the bed is called
An index
John Bogle created the first Index Fund Back in 1970
He had just read this article by a famous economist named Paul Sammy
And what's Henderson wrote in this article was
He could not find any good evidence
That professional investor
People whose job is to pick stocks
You couldn't find any evidence that they were
Any good
If you took a bunch of professional Envy
Look at how they did over a long time
And you took the average
They did not beat the mark
Like when you hear on the news the stock market close up 1% today
You'd be better off investing in that stupid measure of the stock
Then paying someone
To try to beat
Samuelson wrote that maybe quote
Most portfolio decision-maker should go out of business
Pick up plumbing
Teach Greek
At this point John Vogel has been in the business for 20 years since he graduated from college
He has basically been one of those people who Samuelson says should go out of business
But he takes
Samuelson's arguments
In fact he decides
To check the numbers in South and I do the man
I go to these old books of Investment Company performance
And I added up each column
Ghana average
35 years and he found that Samuelson was right
In fact for the investment funds he looked at when you added in the fees they charge they didn't worse on average than the stock
And you could say well I just won't pick a bad
Investment fund
Pick a good one that can really pick the right stock
That turns out to be very hard to do
Stock Pickers who do well one year
They don't always do well the next
And there've course some who do well for a few years in a row
But you don't
You would expect that if everybody was just randomly
Guessing you know if you had a thousand people flipping coins a few of them are going to flip heads 10 times in a row Vogelsong
This and thought
So what are we
And at the end of that article that he'd read by the famous economy
There was the suggestion
And he basically said the cut through his more elegant
Words
With somebody somewhere
Please start an index fund
And I thought
Why not me
Start an index
Bogle figured she would just create this super simple index funds that people could invest
He wouldn't pick stocks he wouldn't say
I think this company is great I'm going to buy their stock
Avoid that other company cuz I don't like them
You was just going to make a fun that was a collection of every stock in the stock market
Not every single stock but the biggest 500 companies on the US Stock
So if you doing this today apple is the biggest company
You buy some of that
Yeah and then you know whatever
GE possible company you buy that too but a little less in proportion to its size and on down
500 company
It's called an index.
Because it is just mindlessly tracking
In a stocking
Actually the index that you hear on the news all the time
The S&P 500
Is in the S&P 500 closed up a quarter of a percent
So if the stock market if the S&P 500 has a good day
Your index file is going to have a good day
Has a bad day the next one's going to have a bad day
It is not trying to do anything tricky
BOGO create this in 1970s
Annie's ready to open it up to
The first Index Fund ever
This is a fun for everybody
You can put in a small amount of money or a lot
I'll go get the bunch of big investment
Used to go out to their clients
Here's this great new thing
You want in
How much money were they hoping to get a hundred fifty million dollar
How much did you get
11 million dollars it was a flop
Investment firms go back to Google and they say
Nobody wants this thing
And I said what I meant we have the world's first Index Fund
We're going to keep the 11 million will do our best
Investors don't really like this idea
Also the investment industry does not like this idea
Cuz it's an insult to everything they stand for in there trying to do
At this point in the interview at this moment in the story BOGO points to the wall play some hanging on the wall right by where we sit
Go over there that's the first reception from Wall Street
Wait that's an actual poster your point ass
Came out in 1976
He's playing at a poster that he says a brokerage from printed up back in the seven
Has this big picture of Uncle Sam and it says help Stamp Out index
Index funds are unamerican
On America
I get it right I mean one of the things that makes America great
Is that
People work really hard
How to do better than average
If you buy an index fund you are buying something that is designed to be average
That is guaranteed
Never to be better than average
And nowhere else in your life and no other important
Sing would you go for a burn
Do you know if you're going to
Going to have surgery
Would you be like okay I just want to make sure I have an average day
No no red you would
You would call every person you know you would do all the research you could
Find a surgeon who is better than average
And it just makes so much sense that if you're picking a stock
There's got to be somebody out
Out there who knows something
Things you can say this is a better company to invest in than that
Somebody called the index fund of the quote pursuit of mediocrity
Somebody else called it a formula for a solid consistent long-term loser
Google keeps the index
Anyways for the world
Come around to his way of seeing
A year goes by
And then another
A decade past
So you been up there for
10 years with the greatest idea of your life and and where are you
0%
He's rounding down
All of the funds out their index funds are like
0.4%
A decade
The idea of the electron did finally start to get on the 9th
What are the reasons
Index funds head very low
Didn't think about it this way you know if you're running a traditional fund
You have to pay people to pick stocks Panther
Read reports in French numbers in
Fly out to meet with the CEO and visit the factory
If you're running an index fund do you don't have to pay people to do any of those things so
You can charge investors lower fees
If you take a typical stock fund today
And you invest say
$10,000
They're going to charge you a fee of $100 every year
The Vanguard index fund
They're going to charge you five
Dollars
In recent Years A lot of people have
Okay
I give up
A bunch of money has flowed into index
We wanted to see what giving up looks like so we went to the room where they run their index
I mean it wasn't much you could not like it was quiet there a few computers
Could have been like any office
There's a handful of people in there and they're very intentionally
Not
Picking stocks
It doesn't seem boring it does feel like giving up essence of boredom
I'll kiss eat it
If you're in investing for excitement
You are a damn fool
Yeah you're watching the market everyday up and down hundred Point 200 300 400 Point swing
Day after day
It's exciting
But it's meaningless
So that is the story of the boring super simple investment that Warren Buffett
For his side of the bed
And to be clear he actually picked
That very fund the Vanguard S&P 500 Index
Now for someone from the other side of
The
Humans can win
We can do better side of the
His name is Ted site he's he's worked for years in the hedge fund world
He heard Warren Buffett's challenge in figured
I know some really smart people who can do better than average
I thought I had a rare chance
At the catch somebody like Warren
I'm potentially being the Patsy at the poker table
I thought you said
To catch him being wet
The Patsy at the poker table
This is the summer of 2000
Inside e-sens Buffett
A letter
Like an actual letter in an envelope with a stamp
Old school
He says he's interested in taking me other side of the bed
And so
Let's talk about what steaks you propose
Might
Table Stakes might be over dinner yours might be a little higher than mine but let's let's see what happens
Little while after that
If I do get this email and there's a PDF attached
He opens up the PDF and what happened is
David is taking that letter and just scrawled some notes on
Then somebody stands it in and sends it back to him
So they can go back and forth for a while
Start negotiating a
Safe to say he was comfortable with higher Stakes than I was
You're you're making a bet with
One of the two or three richest man in the world
Attract
They settled on that Million Dollar Bet
Buffett pick the Vanguard S&P 500 Index
Fighting for his Partners picked a collection of headphones
Buddy's knows all that data that John Bogle
Mention about how stock Pickers can't be tomorrow
But these headphones they do more than stop
Yammy they're incredibly Elite incredibly smart people and you know they
They can sell shares short they can bet against
They can get in and out of the market
They can invest in derivative
Some hedge funds are filled with quants mathematicians former physics types
They are not naive about what they're doing
Excited to spend his career working inside this world this world of people who believe they really can beat the market
He started out at Yale helping manage the schools in Downey
That particular endowment the yell endowment is run by this guy who has been beating the market for decades
Study says when you go to work with that guy everyday
You realize
He is not lucky
He is really really good
You know who else is really good he says
The person on the other side of the bed
Warren Buffett
Another way of framing the question is do you believe that Warren Buffett has skill
Or is he just an analyst because there are so many people who are picking stocks he just happens to be the guy who's out
And what I would tell you is that when you spend time with Warren
And you spend time with many many many other money managers
You can come away with a very high degree of confidence that if Warren started
Investing For the first time today
She would outperform in the future
Sears you're sure you're not.
Checking yourself
In what way
He's a charismatic guy
Ameda me you think this guy's great
It's it's not the charisma.
Temperament
Discipline
Insight
I know that all sounds like very vague managed
The question is like
I keep wanting to go back to the numbers
Cuz I ate are you meet people and they've they've done well the last X years or maybe they've the one person's done while their whole life
You know
And so you tend to think that person has something but
But maybe not maybe they're just lucky
Well I think that's the Eternal question in it
The Eternal question in in
The 10-year
Million Dollar Bet over the Eternal question investing
Is now almost at an end
It started January 1st 2000
Here's how it's gone since
The first year 2008 with 8
Terrible year for 1.
Terrible year for the
As you probably remember that was the year of the financial crisis
The stock market index fund got ham in a terrible time
Worst time to stop
By early 2009 things were looking really good for the hedge fund size
4/10 ID
We were way ahead
Like what to what
The market would have been down
About 45%
And hedge funds were probably down
About 25%
Self I'm imagining two Runners on the track like your Runner is really kind of pulling ahead at this
It's safe to say our runner was
Haven't moved much
And the market Runner had gone backwards
A few miles
The next year that was a good year for Buffett
Author the year after that
After the after that the next man kept beating the Hedgehog
That stupid simple investment
Was better than room folds of really smart
Where we stand now as of the end of 2015
The index fund is up 66%
The hedge funds
I'm only 22 /
It's a huge gap
You're not even close
Not a track
There is not much time left the BET and soon
December 31st 2017
Titus says the only way the hedge-fund could win at this point is if
There's like another
Huge stock market
The crash and he says he doesn't want to see that happen
Are you bummed about
Probably having lost this pet
Little bit
You had a chance to beat Warren Buffett
Yeah with the odds in my favor and then play out the way I thought it would
You thought the address
I still think the odds were in my favor
He actually says he would take the BET again if he could
Deepika go back to mm
He said it's essentially a fluke that the stock market has done as well as it has over the past 8 years
So you're saying you made the right that you just got unlucky
That is how I feel about going to win cuz he got lucky
I think he did end up on the lucky side of the distribution
Isn't it also possible
That is just very very hard to
To beat the market
It's not possible that's a truth
What's your advice to ordinary people who do not have a lot of money
I want to
Put some of the money in the
I think they should index
From the hedge fund side of the bed
You know
Like I actually think his whole position frankly makes makes some sense like I do think there are some people out there
Who really can beat the mark
We're not just getting
Somebody
Got it but you don't
For me when I'm deciding what am I going to do with my money
I don't think I can figure out
Who that person is I don't think I can pick the next Warren Buffett
So full disclosure here getting near the end of the show
I put my money in index
Me too
With the exception of the dollars in my wallet basically everything is in the news
Yuan to do around here
You do it all the time in real life
Yes it drives me crazy when I'm talking to a friend or someone at a party in there like
You know my mom knows how to pick stocks she knew IBM was going to do
Degrade
I just drive
Chris Lake
They were just lucky
That doesn't prove anything with your Charming cocktail party come out
So all right you don't think you can pick the next one. I don't think I can pick the next one
Also one other person who doesn't think he can pick the next Warren Buffett
Warren Buffett
If you're not in a public letter last year Buffett
Describe the instructions
For the money he's leaving to his wife and
And he said
To invest almost all of it in quotes
Ready
A very low-cost S&P 500
Lots of people are taking Warren Buffett
There are now trillions of dollars in India
But there are many trillions more infants where people are being paid to fix that
In other words
Most people are still hoping they can be better than that
The show first aired back in March of 2016 when the bat was still going
Tibet ended at the end of 2017
After the break
Who won who lost
Etcetera
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Fence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
As expected Warren Buffett won the BET heads
Society's laws
By the end the S&P 500 gained an average of 7.1%
Per year
The hedge funds made only 2.2% a year after
They got just
Clobbered
Prophetess that the winnings be donated to a charity called Girls Incorporated of Omaha
And the group use that money to turn an old Convent in the housing for young women transitioning out of
One last thing
There's a reason that we chose this particular episode 2 rerun today
Last week
John Bogle the inventor of the index fund
He was 89
Planet Money is daily podcast the indicator did a whole episode about John Bogle and his legacy on January 7th
Jacob I got the Ford Code as I wanted
Okay I think I know what I'm going to do the first one details about the bet
Both sides actually put some money into a fund paid for that
Bigfoot in half
The money will go to charity the winner gets to decide which charity will get
Call the number to if you wondering why the market is so hard to beat
Please listen to episode 644 where we try to weigh a cow no idea what the next
Codeine number 3 is that
Hedge funds and pets IDs would point out that
They are not necessarily out there to beat the market they are just trying to be a different kind of things you invest in so that in
Year the stock market goes down they don't do it that
True other win this bet they're clearly betting against a stock
Market Cota number 4 but yes I think it's a fair point
Cota number 4
I just wanted to point out that even in John vogel's family Dumbledore the guy who invented the index fund this is not
I resolved question his son
Is a stock
The show today was produced by Nick fountain
I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listening