Hate just a quick note
Today Show originally aired in 2015
Francis Galton was the kind of person who believes in
You know people who had studied thing
People who knew stuff
He figured they knew things that Ordinary People just did not
I mean of course they do
Obviously
Allende Dalton goes to a country
It's about a hundred years ago in English
And there's this contest going on it
Guess the weight of the ox
Go to the scientist and a statistician any figures
Hey I can do an experiment
Rights to figures I'm going to take everyone's guess
Take the average
And compare that to the actual weight of the ox
We heard the story from James sawicki he's an economics Journal
So he thought we were going to end up with was
A really flawed yes
Because in his mind what you were doing was
You were taking guesses of a few smart people
A few mediocre people in a lot of moron
Stop
Shelf
He figured that the groups gas was going to be way way off the
The contest organizers gave Carlton the little slips of paper with everyone guesses
He took them calculate the average
The average was 1197
And the ox
The ox weight 1198
So that in other words the crowds judgment was essentially
Perfect
1 pound off
1 pounder
This is
Super
Creepy
What's going on if there's some kind of like
Collective unconscious
Magic like a Ouija board
Nothing right but the idea that underlies this it is everywhere it's the idea of the stock market thousands of random people buy
Buying and selling shares like when you hear that Apple stock
Or the Dow Plunge
That's basically people guessing the weight of an oz
Yes everywhere right it's it's the price of oil it's the price of Orange
All kinds of things that are really important to the world working
Exactly this way
But why should it work why should a bunch of random people
People a lot of them have no idea what they're doing somehow magically producing
Answer that makes sense
Does it really work
Why doesn't hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking cold
And I'm David kestenbaum today on the show mister Dalton we redo your experiment
Penelope
Hi Penelope thanks for letting us Wii U
She's chewing one.
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
So we came up with a plan to repeat buttons
Find a fair and a cow and a big scale to weigh the cow
And then
And then we were going to throw the question out to the crowd ask the world how much does this cow weigh
We don't want to just limited to people
Fair so we figured we'd take some pictures post them online
Ask the whole world to guess
So we went out to a County Fair in Burlington County New Jersey
How we met Penelope the cow in the dairy tent she was sitting on a bunch of hay
Christian Christmas with taken care of
Can you just describe what she looks like
Yeah she's mostly black she has white legs
She has a white spot in the middle of her head but
Big black cow
What did you say
I said holy cow without even realizing what I think she's much bigger she just stood up she's walking out of the bar now
She's way bigger than I thought when she was
Sitting down
We took some pictures of you Jacob standing next to the cow for scale
And just finally decide to ask people to Fair Hemet
As it happened to his kids if they're like kids
Power Penelope
Which was fine you know
What's your name
Caleb
How much do you think Mel B weighs
6 lb
Had to come up with that number
Because I'm 6 years old
You guys want to get sandwich with Cowboys
1600 lb
But 6000
Do you know how much you weigh
Not at all
I'm sympathetic looking up in lb I had no idea how much you weigh
Like I didn't even know how to think about
Did you weigh more than my car
Scituate last in my car
I don't even know how much my car worth
More than a cat
We've had an older group of
And yet they also guessed on the low side but they had this bigger
This is really more worrying
It was a problem that adults also seem to
And it was this
The first kid said in them
All the other kids said
Basically the same number numbers that were like
Too close to the fire
Like they're incapable of guessing anything
Financista
Anissa how old are you
Alarm 10
How much do you think a cow weighs
200 lb
My name is Gabriela I'm 10 and I think the cow weighs
300 lb
My name is Caleb and I'm 7 years old and I think
The Cowboys
Okay
People are not that different from cows
We heard
If we don't know something we look for a leader
Even if the leader maybe doesn't
Canobie finish
Chewing
And we took her over to be weighed
It's actually pretty unusual to want a way to cow and the scale they had at the fair was not
What kind of scale is this
Text like a truck scales wanted
Same sauce
Scala used for big trucks
Which we use it the way the tractors on the track
It'll work it'll work for a cow
Testing you were
Obsessed
Paranoid paranoid about keeping the result of the secret you didn't want it to leak out I guess
Get all these people are gathered
3 Clear Lake Clear everybody out except for just a minimum of people
Like everything else over there
Kirsten walk Penelope up onto the scale
Play watch this little digital display
It's
And 55 lb
We walked now he back to the dairy tent
And then we were
The next day we posted photos online of the cow when you may be right
I was there to give some sense of perspective we put you on the tractor scale 165
That are Kelly Clarkson Bowie here put it all up
Guess the weight of this cow
And the idea was our Hope was
Fat lots and lots of
People would go
Because
Fundamental question here the thing we're trying to figure out is if you have a bunch of random people making their best
Guess it's something
Do you get close to
Get out the truth do you get close to the right answer
So we put it up
And we waited for the results to
Alright been up for how long now
2 minutes
How many entries
15 + 3
Reload reload
Pill 15
Still 15
Come on
Oh my God
That's all we're going to get 15
The retreat
You were here. I've been buried after 2
We also showed the pictures of me and and the cow to James her Wiki
He's the New Yorker writer we talked with the beginning of the show
Yes we wrote a book called The Wisdom of crowds
But we have to
Remember hear the actual weight of the cow 1355 lb
All right I will guess
Calloways
700 in
How did you
Come up with that number
I don't know maybe he looks like four or five times
Jacob size I guess
Usher cowser
Are they denser or not
Cell
You know whatever
Pretty random actually
Pretty random in pretty Raw
We told them Penelope's actual weight
Twice as heavy as his
It's a sad commentary that someone who's been talkin about an ox
This long has absolutely no clue how much a cow weigh
We get a crowd of people like you
Could be terrible. Be in bad shape I'm praying somebody was guessing to 2200 on the other end
Because the key question is what's the average going to be
Right is the crowd going to
Charlie's how close are they going to get
So we let this up online for 5.
Let people guess for 5 days
Our colleague Bowie tallied it all up
David you and I came into the studio we didn't know the result
And we came in today
Give us the numbers
First of all
How many people get
So the number people that guest
17205 peep
17000 that's what you get that's good
That's good it's as if you got like a small town at 2 all guess we took those guesses out of them up and couch
Calculator the app
This was the big moment
Is ready
1287 lb
Now we actually weighed 1355
Pretty close right so that's two within like what 60 lb
That was pretty impressive
Yep and they're only like 5% off you know okay sure the golden thing was one pound off this isn't that
A bunch of random people looking at this little cow picture in their Facebook feed on their iPhone
And here's another amazing
When we ask people to guess we also asking this other question
We asked are you in XP
Have you ever worked with
Cuz remember gotten fat
Express might be bad
3000 some people answered yes to that
That question Jacob you wondered where they really really extra sure these are just people clicking a button on mine so we emailed
And we heard back and they did seem pretty
You know a lot of them
We're farmers
One of them mentioned the quote absence of a visible
Actually few of them
And apparently that tells you something about how old the cow is how much it weighs
So how did the experts do
Hear the answer
So the average gas for the experts
Was
1272 lb
They're worse
They were worse it's amazing
So it's okay so maybe that is wisdom of the
To be fair the experts were only marginally worse
But they did not beat the crowd
We talked to Ricky about these results and he wasn't surprised infected rights in his book
Chasing the expert is a mistake
We should ask the crap
And the fact that the larger crowd got it within 5
Percent he said that seems about right to him
When people do versions of this experiment asking people to guess the number of jelly beans in a jar for
The crowd usually gets it within 3 to 5%
You know what I think is interesting about this is
Even though I've written a book
Done this experiment number of times
Every time I do it
And everytime I hear the results
I'm like
It's not going to work
The idea is so counter-intuitive you know it's it's pretty extraordinary in that regard
The power of this
To actually
Let the group arrive at
Really good decisions
It series
It is he right it is
There's something magical about
Attitude seems Magic
It's not magic it's just math but it seems Magic
So what he says
The reason the seems to
Is that every person's gas is contributing some new little piece of
Everybody is different everybody thinks slightly
When they're trying to get the cows
Maybe one person study that photo of the cow from the side
Some people are probably trying to figure out
How many Jacobs would fit in
How someone else might know how much a horse weighs and kind of go from there
Like every person's guess in some ways reflects
Their specific life experience
Judging the size of things in the world just from Decades of living
But every person's mind is a different scale for weighing the cow
Any one of those scales
Isn't going to be a great
Scale write each one of those is probably going to be wrong there's going to be some error in every single want the good in some way but they
I also have some
Problem with a
Yeah
One of the essential things is
Those problems
Tend to cancel each other out right maybe one person is wrong 200 lbs High
But the next guy is wrong 200 lb low
So that the wrong Parts the wrong is kind of washes out and in the end what you're left with
Is all those little bits of information
And the result is amazingly good you know collectively we do seem to know what we're doing
Circus has there certainly times when this does not
Work like think
Stock market panic
Score bubbles
A big problem is that thing we saw with the kids
At the beginning
Where one person says a number
And then everybody else around them just kind of latches onto that number there's actually a technical term for this
Information Cascade
Like my neighbor just bought a house that seems like a lot of money pay for house but he did fine
I can do the same thing or everyone's buying that stuff
Must be a good stock to buy
The stock market is not perfect
But
What is amazing about the stock market is that investors individually
Even very good investors
Are often times irrational that
I have tiny bits of him
Information they're making
Decisions based on emotion or on
You know some tip they got
And yet collectively
We trust them to set the value of
All of these companies
When you think about it
But
The interesting thing is I don't think there's a better way to do
Is not a more effective
This is why it is so hard to be
The wisdom of the crowd
Pretty good
And the people seem to be that way I can be the stop
Often they're just
In our experiment for example there were 15 people who got the cows wait exactly right
They were off by 0%
We picked one of them at random is our way
We call them up
To tell me the news
And to see how he did it
Hello
Thesaurus
Yeah how's it going
In college
Never touched a cow in his
That could not even remember his gas
We told him he'd guest 1355 lb
And if the weight of the cow was also
Oh my God
You won
That's amazing
You want to know how I got that guy
Yes
Hi Google hi Google average weight of female calendar said
Yeah I got it
Toe pops up and
A little
Fox and
Comes from
Dairy
Moose
Dairy mof
Dot-com
Dairy movies.com says average weight of a cow's 1500 lb depending on the age and whatever
Paris looked at the picture of Penelope the count said she looks a little bit on the small side he went with 1355 who's Justin
Yakima
Steely Dan
So we're going to send you
Eva cheapest plastic cow trophy we can find
We talked with Harrison but we should put on the trophy cuz the bit of a
The puzzle right
I should say I got lucky
He's actually find me that he said that she hates then
I was pushing for mutual fund manager of the year
Robert you suggested someone had to
In the end I think we are just going to say
Congratulations congratulations
Support for this podcast and the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth management client
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes and make clear recommendations for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
All right we got some point. You know at the end of research papers they put all the technical detailed there
Couple things you want to tell you
We calculate the average of the guesses we did throughout outliers like the Britney just held down the 9 key is there
Get 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9 9
Thanks for that also for people love the median we calculated the median to Glover the median is the value in the middle
Where have two guesses are higher have to guess their lower
The meeting is pretty close to the average the medium was 1245 lb
Within 8% of Penelope's actual weight
Are the median expert test was a little worse but pretty close
You can find all the numbers online at npr.org money
Also there's some pictures of Penelope the cow among other things on our Instagram feed at Planet
One other thing Planet money has a new weekly email newsletter it's great there all these interesting questions
Like do plastic bag bans help or hurt the environment
Also
Why did a bunch of countries in Europe
Try well facts
And then give up on it
You can subscribe to the Planet Money newsletter at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
You can also email us
Planet Money at npr.org
Thank you also to everybody for guessing
Penelope the cow and the Rosemary K and the other folks
At the burl
Benton County Fair
The show was originally produced by Nadine Wilson today's rerun was produced by Liza Yeager and Rachel Cohn
Brian Earth that edits Planet Money Alex goldmark is are supervising producer I'm Jacob Goldstein and I'm David
Thanks for listening
How heavy is a cow
Absolutely no idea
Absolutely no idea I
I really would
Wicked 10000 lbs into heavier who knows
Really I have no idea
It's 20,000, 20,000 I think is going over the limit yeah I know
Less than 20,000 less than 20000 more than 5
More than 5 lb