Late last year President Trump was making very strong statement
About what the Federal Reserve
Or more specifically what the Fed
Should not
She did not want the FED to raise interest rates
Write the day before the FED Med in December the president tweeted that it was in
Credible that quotes the state is even considering yet another interest rate hike
Then the next day
He warned the FED not to quote make yet another mistake
Presidents
Lovelo in
Because
They make it easy for people to borrow money to buy stuff
And for businesses to borrow and hire people but
Low interest rates
Also dry
Drive up inflation
Part of the federal reserve's job
Is to keep inflation
The day after Trump's
Fed chair Jerome Powell who was
Appointed by President Trump
Announced that the FED had in fact raised
He did the opposite of what the president wanted him to do
The Federal Reserve is ended
And this is a phrase you will hear
Fed into pain
What happened in December
President saying
Don't raise rates
And is Fed chair saying
We raise rates
That's fed Independence
There is a story of how fed Independence
Came to be and
A specific
Day that I am henceforth going to call
Set Independence
And good news everybody
You've got three days
It's the 4th of March
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm your well King and I'm Kenny Malone
Today on the show the story of how the Fed.
Its independence
And how it had to
Fight
Keep it and buy fight we mean literal fight the president and his Fed chair got in a physical altercation
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable light
And features including e-commerce functionality
The end mobile app
Squarespace also offer
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Okay fed Independence Day as I'm calling it
Is because of what happened in this country
On March 4th
In the years before 1951 the FED took orders from the treasury basically from the
We were fighting World War II and so when the president said to the Fed chair
You better set interest rate so it's cheap for the government to borrow money to pay for the war the FED said yeah okay
But after the war inflation started Rising
And the Fed chair said to the Press
It is our job to deal with inflation
You need to let us raise interest rate
President Truman
Sed
And by early 1951 inflation had hit 21%
The price of everything that Americans bought was Rising by
21% a year
So Truman finally gave in on March 4th 1951
His Treasury Department agreed to leave the FED alone
The FED not the president
Would set interest rates for the
The Fed was free
Sort of
Yeah this agreement was known as the
Treasury fed Accord
And the treasury set a cord is not a law or even an official rule
This really was just a handshake deal
The president
At that moment
With a green to not mess with the Fed
The real test
It would come when another president came in
And decided
I don't like this agreement
I just wanted to thank you for your most of the thoughtful and generous letter and I appreciate it so much and
This is President Lyndon B Johnson and this phone call happened just a few days after Johnson became president in nineteen
Pick 3
Which was just a few days after John F Kennedy was assassinated
Johnson had been thrown into off
And so he started checking in with all the important people
And it's called he is introducing himself
Fed chair William mcchesney
What time saying in this call is
You're the ex
Oxford I'm here to listen
Make it back to the shop and then he start to tell me what I want to know about it
Well I certainly will happen every way that I can make you a picture then I'm glad you around and
As far as We Know
This is the first call between President Johnson and chairman Martin
Sounds cordial
But their relationship would deteriorate
Spectacular
Obama why don't we just want to start by having you introduce
Sure I'm Bob Runner by author of the book on William mcchesney Martin I have kind of the corner on William Machesney Mall
Book out there
Bob's going to be our guide through the Lyndon B Johnson William mcchesney Martin story
So here goes
Johnson and Martin were too varied
Different types of
Johnson was this tall imposing guy race in Texas
Being a manipulator
He remembered slights he exchange favors
Any play them like fiddle
He was a man who did all the things
To get people to do
What he wanted
That's correct
Bill Martin wasn't like that
A journalist once called him the happy
Puritan his father was in banking
Martin looks like a banker he was skinny he had rimless glasses
Later on in his life he became friends and Tennis partners with that biographer table runner
Did Bill Martin ever tell you any jokes
Hey jokes
You know not a joke teller and I remember
Finding
Annies papers
Saying humor
And it didn't have anything in it
Honest-to-god
Well
Is it true
That William mcchesney Martin
Love more than anything in the world
Trying to explain the Federal Reserve to people absolutely absolutely
What were some of the analogies or metaphors he
Parrot
Probably the most famous
Was his comment
That
How the federal reserve's role
Was really
To take the punch bowl away
Just as the party got going
The punch bowl analogy
Business journalists use this all the time
Time and the idea
Is low interest rates are like the booze out of
It in the feds job is to be the responsible adult
Raise interest rate
Take the punch bowl away before the party gets out of
Before inflation starts
To take off okay so when Lyndon Johnson becomes President Bill Martin was already the Fed chair
And one of the first things that Johnson does is to push a big package of tax cuts at Kennedy have been working
Johnson told Congress that passing these Cuts was a way to honor Kennedy
And it works because pass
And then there were
The two Wars
Johnson inherited the Vietnam War from Kennedy and then
He got us in D
Fever and at home Johnson launched the war on poverty
This is where Medicare and Medicaid
And tons of other social
Rapso
These two Wars
Were expensive
Because of all this government spending a lot of money was heating up the US economy
Plus people are getting these tax break so it's getting even hotter this is great for Johnson because
Cuz people are happy and Johnson wants eventually to be re-elected
But
William mcchesney Martin is watching
And thinking
This is the kind of stuff the FED needs to pay very close at
Because
This kind of spending could very likely lead to
So he starts warning Johnson
We are in serious trouble I think the FED is going to need to raise in
We are headed for
Quote
An inflationary map
And Johnson is like yeah well I talk to other smart
People
Quote they don't agree with you
This is the classic fight
The FED wants to raise interest rates be
Worried about the
Economy in the long run
And the president wants low interest rates
Because they are good
For the economy
The stage was set
Fours problem
So the question is what kind of effect Sherman do and what's in them
What did Martin do to try to
To Telegraph the feds in town
And the concerns the FED has
So the one thing they can do is give
So we have a frustrated Fed chair
And if it happens he gets an elegantly timed invitation
Which leads to as far as we can tell
The worst
Commencement day speech in history
Yeah Bill Martin gets invited
To Columbia University to speak
At the graduation day luncheon
So you can imagine camp
Buzzing with bright eyed kids in powder blue caps
Townsend
You know how commencement date speech
She's usually sound they're all
Oh the Places You'll Go
That is not what Martin.
No he starts his address not by saying follow your dreams or some such
She says
When economic prospects are at their brightest
The dangers of complacency and recklessness
Are great
And then he UPS the ante by saying
We find disquieting similarity
Between our present prosperity
And the fabulous 20
And here is here's a Federal Reserve chairman
Talking about
You know we are in a situation today
That is
Very much
Like there
Situation
That led to the Great Depression
What
That's pretty tough stuff
What is he saying
What is he saying to these kids exactly like
We're
If we're not careful
He's now he's really speaking.
That's the problem
For the kids
This moment where the Fed chair is actually saying the words
Danger signal
And Great Depression in the same speech
Makes the front page of the New York Times today
The stock market
And when President Johnson gets word of this
He is deceiving
He asked his attorney general
Can I fire this guy
Attorney general disappointed him by saying
There's no way you can
Unseat him
Except
For cause
And unfortunately
Policy differences do not constitute cause
Summers president you're stuck with
Kyla Johnson that must have been
Havasu Chase
Oh well I mean
Nobody told Linda John
Nobody
Think about this now from Johnson's point of view
William mcchesney Martin and the FED have an enormous amount of power
They get to decide how much it's going to cost to get a mortgage or student loan
A handful of
Technocrats in the Federal Reserve get to make those decisions
Not me
The president of the United States
Who is the representative of
All the people
And to be fair some people today feel exactly the same way
Why do these unelected
Technocrats get so much power
So after Bill Martin's Columbia
Johnson
Furious
He gets on the phone and start stalking
All about is Fed chair about Bill freaking Martin
Hi Joe how are you
You'll hear Johnson in this call saying like
I can't control Bill Martin
He has
Control of the ball
I've met with him half a dozen time
Can't do anything
But I'm doing everything you know how that's is Martin half-dozen times
I have to get control at Ford
He's got control of it
So Johnson is live
But
He's starting to understand that Martin
He's going to do this is going to raise the
So instead of begging Martin not to
KeyBank Martin
Wait until
Johnson can pass a budget
In the news
Big priority
This is all happening in the fall of nineteen
And Johnson slips into full manipulator mode
He's about to have surgery
Any even tries to use that as Leverage
Johnson was going in to have his gallbladder taken out and
And he said you wouldn't raise rates on me would you be a while I'm in the hospital and Martin said oh no mr. president will wait until you
You're out so Martin does wait but he doesn't wait long
On December 3rd Martins fed takes a vote on whether to raise the interest rate by half a per
Percent and they vote to do it
Johnson is at his Texas ranch
Recovering from surgery
When he finds out
What Martin
We can't control him
He's worked as hard as he can he's threatened
And yes Martin is gone and done this
And he can't believe it's a Johnson summons Martin
To the ranch
Martin flies down
Is Call of Duty Johnson's office
We don't know exactly what was said
In that off
Here is Bob Brenner
And Johnson is just
Fit to be tied
Start right off
Found
No this is this is something that can affect my entire term
You knew that this would have this impact on me
And yet you went right ahead and you ran a Rapier right through me
You and
Federal Reserve had put yourself above my presidency
And you
Totally disregard my wishes in my policy
The Despicable thing to do
And then
There is
A reference
To the fact that the Johnson was so angry that he pushed Martin against the wall
Physically pushed him against the wall actually pushed him against
The president of the United States
Yes laid hands on
Yes he is Fed chair
Well Martin says
Mr. president
We have not but
Ourselves
Over your presidency
I told you I was going to do this
I told you personally
I told you Administration
That we were going to do this
I've given you a lot of Advance note
But I do have
The very strong conviction
The Federal Reserve Act
Place the responsibility for interest rates with the Federal Reserve board
This is one of those few occasions where the Federal Reserve
Decision
Has to be final
This is a huge
Moment and here's why
Remember fed Independence Day March 4th 1951
That treasury fed Accord was really just a handshake deal
This moment tested the handshake deal
William mcchesney Martin is standing up to Lyndon B Johnson and saying
No disagreement is real
The FED is not going to be bullied into doing what the president wants
I mean if you want
One single moment
When the Federal Reserve
Defined its independence and what that meant
To somebody who was out to
To squash it is much
Just possible
That's it
The thing about fate Independence Day is that it's really not just one day
There's the treasury fed Accord the 4th of March
There's the day Johnson shoved Martin for acting independently the 6th of December
Any didn't stop there after Martin left the Fed
Inflation started going way up
Until another Fed chair Paul volcker had to assert fed Independence
Again
Erase interest rates even though farmers were blockading the FED with their tractors
And then in a smaller way we saw this again in December
When the president of the United
State sort of Warrant his Fed chair Jerome Powell on Twitter
Not to raise interest rates
And Powell in the Fed
Did it anyway
It may sound like we're saying
Maybe every day
Is fetid
But no it is the 4th of March and after the break I have some very serious thoughts about how to celebrate
He does dragon want to stick around until after the credits
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses
Is to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
All right now working I just want to try something that I've always heard of
Okay so you know how on the 4th of July for Independence Day
NPR has a bunch of it
Hosts
Read the Declaration
It's on the air with
Yeah I've done it you've done it
For the 4th of March
Forfeit Independence Day
We should be reading the treasury fed Accord the the FED coloration of independent if you will now
But I do think we should
Go get the old document that was released on March 4th
19th
51 announcing the treasury fedak
And I think what we should do is we should get the other host and
Get that sweet music
And have them read this NPR
Alright I'm in let's do it
Subaru
The treasury and the Federal Reserve System
Have reached
Full Accord with respect to debt
Manage my
And monetary policies to be pursued in furthering their common purpose
Assure the successful financing of a government
Requirements and the same time
To minimize monetization
The public
That's it
It's one setting
Kind of confusing he was basically a press release
I am going to propose that henceforth
We shall read
The treasury fed Accord release
Every March 4th on planet
But we also have been trying to come up with original for everyone else to celebrate that Independence Day and
And we would like your help we're looking for something something with the dollar bill maybe something about how it holds
Buying power over time reasoning the Punchbowl
Anyway come up with a ritual take picture of it
Put it on social media and tag as we're at Planet Money and we're going to put some of our favorites in our news
You can also reach us by email we are Planet Money at NPR. Org
Today's episode with produced by Darian woods and Co reported by Rachel Cohn
Today show with edited by Jacob Goldstein Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and Bryant or statue
Planet Money
A very very very special thanks to Sweet to Jon Weinberg from
The Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond for walking me through
Hours and hours and hours
In the full name of Bob bremner's book is Chairman of the Fed
William mcchesney Martin Jr and the creation of the modern American Finance
Endwell by the way
I'm not joking about that
I want this to happen I want her audience to
I believe you
Yeah I know you do
My concern is that other people
Until I thought Noel
We need a special girl
Go go ahead
This is Janet Yellen former chair of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve
I want to wish everybody a very happy
Said Independence Day
Thank you for trusting the Federal Reserve and me
With the privilege and a responsibility of conducting your monetary policy
Beautiful
Happy independence Day to you
Same to you take care of thank you