This is kind of money
Heather Sanders it's Cardiff Garcia
I'm the co-host of Planet Money Daily Show the indicator along with Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm here to help
Planet Money listen
My name is Louis Sachar I'm 13 and I'm in 7th grade
I'm wondering about the inverted yield curve
Because it just inverted and I can worry that there could be another recession
Okay well listen as it happens
Leo
Planet money has a spin-off podcast called
The indicator
Have you ever listened to it
I've heard
We have actually done a bunch of episodes
About the yield curve
Already
So I'm going to make you a deal
I'm going to send you episodes of the indicator to list
And then after the show I'm going to give you a call and see what you think
That's not good
Yeah
This is a great topic
To be asking about
About right now and actually leaves not the only one a lot of people have been emailing Planet Money
To ask
What is up with the Joker
It doesn't mean we're about to have a recession
Now as you hear
Michael ho Stacey Vanek Smith can vouch for the fact that I am kind of obsessed
With the old truck
I find it fascinating
I find it mysterious
And I'm Amazed by the fact that for the past 6 decking
When the yield curve invert it has anticipated every single recession
So today we are putting together our two favorite indicator episodes
About the
Dedicate them
Aaliyah
Hello welcome to Planet Money I'm Carlos Garcia they on the show
The yield curve
What it is
What it means when it inverts
What it means that it doesn't for
An interview with the guy who discovered the inverted yield curve as a recession predictor
And finally
Our answer the question of whether you should be scared and nervous and panicking when you see those headlines
About the yield curve inverted
You should buy the way
Greg
What are you doing here again
I write a newsletter
Where can people get that sweet sweet content npr.org Planet Money newsletter that's why they can sign up
That's what I can sign up yet
Right here is the guy who first
Explain formula
The powers of the yield curve
I'm Campbell Harvey I'm a professor of Finance at Duke University
And in 1986
I published a thesis
The detailed
The predictive ability of the yield curve
The forecast
US economic growth
This was the seminal paper
On the topic am I right
Hat is the first paper
Back in the 1980s when Campbell was working on his thesis
He says that other Scholars were investigating the stock market
Get to see if it could help predict for the economy
I was going
Campbell was not convey
So the idea that equities should have information about the
The future path of economic growth
Because equities discount
Future earnings from companies
So it kind of makes sense but when you actually look at the equities
They were delivering a lot of false signal
Also the market drop
Hobbit there is no recession so I was thinking
Well
What if you looked at something less risky something less volatile
And it was logical to look at
I'm the bond market
Specifically
Campbell started looking at the US Government Bond
The yield curve shows the different interest rates that are paid by each of the different US Government Bond
Treasuries
Treasuries have different expiration date
Soap for example there is
3 month treasury bill
A 2-year Treasury
5 year
10 year and so on that is just
When you cash them out after that
Time
And you curve just shows you the different interest rates on those different Treasury
The basic idea behind Campbell Harvey
Restasis was simple
When the economy is expected to grow
Do you curve slope up
In other words
As you go from short-term treasuries to long-term treasuries
The interest rate should be getting higher and higher
So the interest rate on a 10-year Treasury
Should be higher than the interest rate
5 year treasury
And that should be higher than the inter
Straight on a 3-month
And the reason this happens is it if the economy's expected
Did you grow
The long-term treasuries have to pay higher interest rates in order to attract buyers
Otherwise Byers
Just invest in the economy itself
Like I can invest in a company
Ebony ore in the stock market
When longer-term interest rates fall below shorts
Interest rates
We say that the yield curve has inverted
What is sloping
Down
And an inverted yield curve
What is a forecast in an economic recession
Is on the way Legend
Legend
Canvas pieces
Look at all the time since the
Steve's that the yield curve invert
More specifically he looked at all the times that a longer-term in
Interest rate had fallen below a short-term interest rate for at least a full quarter
Soap for at least 3 months
And what he found was it every single time the yield curve inverted
A recession follow
Every single recession has been preceded by an inverted yield
There were no false
What chemical is his thesis was greeted with
A bit of Suspicion
By his fellow
To be frank I some members of my committee
We're pretty skeptical
Really not enough observation
And so you got
Only a handful of recessions how do we know this isn't just lucky
Campbell's reasoning here the idea that the treasury market was more useful
For predicting economic growth
In the stock market
It would immediately get a useful test
Is it October 1987
Famous day known as Black Monday
The stock market started
Crashing
A lot of people thought this big fall in the stock market meant the recession was on the way
In 1988
Not Campbell
I was
The lone voice
Saying no
There's not going to be a recession 1988
My model suggests that economic growth will be
4.1%
And I was way out there and not inverted
Did the time
Not inverted in 1987
The economic growth that was released 1988
4.2%
So it was remarkably accurate
And basically not doing a false signal
And ever since
Every time the yield curve has inverted for a quarter
A recession is follow
Usually within about a year
A lot of people have been wondering if the yield curve is no longer
Requires used
Used to be
When I say a lot of people
I'm including one Stacey Vanek Smith
But I'm not alone there is there is
Definitely room for healthy and selection
Skepticism about the
Absolutely you are definitely not alone and I'm thinking here is this the Federal Reserve
The US Central Bank
Has been a huge fire Treasury
For roughly the last decade
This was all part of the fed's attempt to stimulate the economy
After the big Financial
So essentially the government has been getting
Treasuries at maybe the yield curve has been distorted by all that by
Is a maybe the signals are sent
And are not as helpful as they used to be
This idea of distortion of the yield curve
Is not a new idea
High indeed
The Distortion the yield curve was lot easier
In the 1960's and 1970's when the Government Bond Market was a lot smaller
Fruit the same people that I actually look at
Different plenty of intervention
So this is just the norm
And try to make the case that
It's somehow different today than it has been in the past
I don't think holds a lot of water
Doesn't hold a lot of water when I consider the source here Cardiff course he loves the yield curve
It's great and he's been proven right ever since you did
Ever since yes but Campbell does say that using the yield curve to predict a recession is just part of
A model he also expresses some help
Skepticism
And he also said that all models you can stop being useful if the world changes
In some Panama
And he says it's Sunday that could happen to his model to
Yeah now yield curve
Things that you know
Got to have a little bit of skepticism about the
A little Caution never killed anyone
Or maybe it's actually
We're going to take a quick break
And after we're can answer the question of what's been happening with the old
Curve
Right now
In 2019
This message comes from NPR sponsor Microsoft
Snow leopards are very difficult to find
Researchers use Microsoft AI to analyze thousands of remote camera images in minutes so they can
Find and study them more efficiently
Morad microsoft.com AI
Hey
You know what next year is right
2020 election year
The news in Houma going to get crazier
Join me Sam Sanders
Play wrap-up of the week's news and culture that will not make you want to pull your hair out
Download and listen
Every weekend
2 it's been a minute
From NPR
Okay so we put together this next episode of the indicator in July of the
Because back in March
Something happened that we have been saying could happen
Ever since we launched the indicator
The yield curve inverted
And since March it has stayed in
Kim Harvey's flashing warning sign the full quarter of this upside down world
Has in fact
Happened
The next episode
One that we sent to a listener Leo
Addresses some of the questions you had about the yield curve
The Shield
Try to contain your excitement
So when we say the yield curve
What we mean is that the long-term interest rate
It's paid by US government bonds
Treasuries
Are lower than the interest rates paid by short-term USD
Government bonds
And for the past six decades whenever that has happened whenever the yield curve is inverted it has been assigned that the country
You go into a recession
Is it about a year
Now if you're a new listener
You might not know that I'm totally fascinated
Jason Mathias Aspen dated okay early be wrong
Not because it is a perfect all the time
And not because it's a perfect predictor of a recession
There is no such
But just because the yield curve has such a great
Track record as a recession
Forecast
And also because there were interesting questions and even doubt
About whether that's
Streak of perfect recession forecasting
He's going to continue
Would you say that the yield curve is practically
In every way I would not say that I have been careful not to say that
But you know a lot of listeners have emailed us
Specifically you Cardiff with a bunch of questions about the
Because you are so fast
Buy it
Anthony on the indicator from Planet Money
We are going to answer
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
You're sassy van
Smith is what you are
And I'm Carlos Garcia
Those questions are listen to senses were all really smart but in some cases those questions were also asked
Switch just as much SASS and sarcasm is Stacy's giving me right now
I know there
Set a channel that Spirit of inquisitive sarcasm
We are going to paraphrase our listeners questions
And have them read aloud by producer dharius Rafi on
Protest has a phenomenal sarcastic
That's true
Jeez, don't cry about it
Sarcastic
Victorious
What is your first question
Correct me if I'm wrong but the yield curve inverted way back in March so is there a reason you waited till now to do a show about
Okay FairPoint question
Here's the thing the first scholar to discover the link
Between the inversion
Inn of the hills Kerrville
And recessions
Is named Campbell Harvey
Duke universe
According to his research
In the past
The recession forecast has been triggered only when the yield curve has been inverted for a full
Quarter
And specifically a
Calendar quarter
Which means the same quarters of the year that we follow
For other economic
So the first quarter is the first three months of the year
The second quarter the next 3 months and sofa
So we had to wait for the yield curve to invert for a full cord
That happened on June 30th
That was a couple of
Go and I guess Cardiff you just procrastinated until now
Just make sure the collecting those questions baby oh yeah
So the yield curve has been inverted throughout the whole second quarter
And a couple
What weeks specifically the 3-month treasury has been paint
A higher interest rate than the five years
Oh-so some Economist like ensconced in his Ivory Tower just
Show the calendar quarter like out of his hat in that like kind of arbitrary
Finance scholar
But yeah this is the next one point that sarcastic
Hiking Cardiff to respond
Yeah it is kind of arbitrary
But the reason to wait for the yield curve to be inverted
For 3 months
Is the it field trip only inverts for a few hours or
A few days that does not signal
A recession is
Diversion has the last
Again we are following Campbell Harvey's research
He chose three months of inversion
To study the We are following that is
So you are now saying that there is
Definitely going to be a recession in the next year I can call you on this right there's a recession coming
Wow okay well this is this got real really fast okay maybe not
Actually so here is something that you might not know
Up from the time you'll / first inverse it is taken an average of slightly more than 12 months
The recession to actually
Begin
That was the average for the last 7%
Procession of the really big one that ended a decade ago
Do you curve actually first inverted 23 months early
Almost two years earlier
This time it could be sooner could be longer or maybe it will not happen at all
But the point is the recession usually doesn't start right away
So you're saying you
You can't identify a relationship between the yield curve in a recession
Isn't it possible that your
Magical recession predictor is actually just a series of coincidence
Again
Yes
I don't like your attitude but you've got a good point
It's definitely possible that it's all just
The big coincidence
Remember the idea here is not
The yield curve
What causes a recession
The theory is that the yield curve
Flexwood investor
Fish from around the world
Think about the US economy the investor to
To buy us treasuries
And the same ones who probably helped fake the moon landing
Christmas Cafe
Anyway
Okay so us treasuries are the safest financial asset
They are what you buy if you think the economy is not going to do
You just want to
Safe place
Keep your money because you know the US government is good for the inter
Payments that it promises
But when everyone wants to buy treasuries
Is the same time
In the government doesn't need to offer High interest rate on Treasury
People to buy them
So does long-term rates
Go down
And here's the important
The reason that long term rates can fall even below short-term rates
Is it investors are rushing to lock in the long-term rates that are available right this moment
Is if they waited in the economy got worse the rates would be even lower
But that is just a
And just because it's held true for the past six decades and 7 recession
Does not mean that it can't be untrue in
Someday you'll permite invert and we might not see a recession for years that could happen
Okay so now you're saying the yield curve might be wrong but you're not even going to tell me
Why it might be wrong
Yes
That's right the show's over thank you
Just take our word for it
That's all you need
It's okay. Is there a few possible reasons why the inverted yield curve might not actually be
Be signaling a receipt
This time I
So first of all the Federal Reserve the country Central Bank
Funny turn of long-term treasuries
As part of its attempt
To stimulate the economy after the great financial crisis the Great Recession
So that could actually be distorting the shape of the yield curve right now
Because the FED represents an additional buyer of treasuries
It'd be throwing off the system
Another possibility is simply the
Policymakers are aware that an inverted yield curve has predicted the last seven
Sessions
They might change how they managed
Economy Inn
Response
Example some members of the Federal Reserve
Which manages in
Straits heavy even brought up the
The yield curve inversion as a reason to at least be worried about where the
Economy is headed
Policymakers are more responsive
To the signal being sent by the
Yield curve
They might avoid the recession by stimulating the
The economy more
Yes
The yield curve signal for a recession
Could turn out to be wrong
Could be the exception that proves the rule sarcastic dharius
Sassy Stacey
Forever point
Part of what makes the yield curve so fascinating is that very mystery right we've called the yield curve
Kind of crowdsourced crystal ball for the US
Economy
And it has an astonishing track record
But that doesn't make it infallible you should still be watching other indicators
For that
I've got a pot
Waupaca
The indicator
What is a blank
Could you end it
Solid plug
Shame
It's true that is a little Shameless
I kind of like it
Cuz of your question to Planet Money so please email Planet Money at npr.org
Facebook Twitter
Instagram
Planet Money on all those
These indicator episodes were originally produced by Darius rafie on and Emily Lange
Patty Hearst
Is editor
Darren Woods
And Cynthia but your Visa produced this version
Alex goldmark
Is Planet Money supervising producer and brynhurst at at at
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And I'm Cardiff Garcia this is NPR thanks for listening
I called up our listener Leo afterwards and asked him what he thought of these Epic
Yeah I find them really fascinating
Why
I like how you like talked about both sides on how it might not be realistic
And how do you feel about the economy now having
I heard these episodes about the oak tree
Unless you're that actually predicts
The recession
Yeah it might not
You're not as worried about the economy now
Yeah
Not as worried still a little bit one