Beer Yuengling
When two people really love each other
Just tell him that we're going to talk about Xmas episode
Not your one
A couple years ago even woke up in Denmark
2 news of a
Weird problem
There was some
Smallville articles in
A very serious newspapers that
Told the story about the problem
With
Not
But having enough children born in Denmark Great Danes for not having enough babies
Is to replace the existing population
And this matter to Eva
Because she works at a travel a
And she thinks oh
We're not going to have enough customers in a few
So they're like okay we need to figure out who our customers are now where are they going what do they do how do we get them to
Keep traveling
And what we found out with that
People going on city breaks will mainly couples City breaks you mean vacation
Yeah sort of like small vacation
Two or three nights
It's to a big city of people in Denmark get 5 weeks of vacation every year
Hangouts
So apparently when Danish couples going these
Shorts
City breaks
They aren't
Going out
See the sights of Rome and Paris they're just
Unwinding
Staying in their hotel rooms
And that's why I
We did
The kind of the assumption that it going
Abroad
Might
Turn into more sex
And more sex
Have the ability to turn into children
Right that is how you make more children
Exactly
Eva realizes there might be an opportunity
To create future customers and sure to help out.
So she watches an ad can
The app that we came up with
Will do it for Denmark
Do it for Denmark like do it do it it is
DC, Wisconsin
There ads
Basically say
It is your civic duty for the sake of your country
Do it and
Use our planes
Do it in a different country
Okay so these these ads
They are not
Settle a
Like beer very
Suggestive yes it is it is
These eyes are like
Emma
She was born and raised in Denmark but she was made by her parents
In this hotel room in Paris
So it's quite obvious
It's what we are
What we are
Suggesting should happen on that
On that City breaks travel agency even ran contests that were like hey
Prove you gave birth to a baby around 9 months after your vacation
And we will give you three years worth of baby supplies and
A child friendly vacation
And if you were ovulating
They gave you a discount
Based on the input from
Peoples
Period cycle
We found the
The Puritans that they were
Ovulating and then
We suggested different
City trips
Especially that.
Wait so
Women were going to
Your travel agency
And telling you when they're next.
They did
So that they could get a. Discount
Exactly
This is like probably the only time in the world that women get rewarded
For having their period
Yeah I think we should do that
More right
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm
Kenny Malone and I'm Sarah Gonzales today on the show
Do it
For your country
People aren't
Just good for the economy bar the economy
And when a police needs people
I'll try anything we have a story of a plan to resurrect in Italian
Ghost Town a battle to save
US Congress seats
By buying some residents and a state that's looking for some young blood
Support also comes from the UPS Store
From printing packing and copying
Do faxing mailboxing and notarizing
The UPS Store offers everything
Personal
And this Memorial Day week
May 24th and 25th
When others may be closing
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
Because small business owners
Can't afford to take days off
The UPS Store
Every Inc
For small business
And of course shipping
I'm Linda home
There's more stuff to watch these days than you can ever get to
That's why we make popcorn
Alter happy hour
Twice a week we give you the lowdown on what's worth your time and what's new
Fun pop culture happy hour on
On the NPR one app or wherever you get
Scissor I feel like I should admit that when I
Her the places were paying
Population of death
I thought that they would
Pathetic little places like it seems like kids having to pay for their own friends
Lunch cafeteria
But I feel like this next example sort of puts that the rest I actually think this is like one of the best ways
Laura people
Sarah and I called up a guy named Nate Wilde
One of the people in charge of promoting this particular pay for popular
Hello
Podcast
I just want to say
I just
Visited me a visit Maine recently also actual
You have amazing National Park
Awesome Lobster Like Houses
You've got like wild blueberries Galore
And you're telling us that like you have to pay people to come and live there
Well that's one of the few things were trying
Vacation destination
Steven Wright vacationland on their license
However
Vacationland
Is not the same as population
Man gets about 36 million visitors a year
They have a population of just 1 million people
And
Those 1 million people
So our population is old and white
Generally speaking Maine has the oldest population in the country
The median age is just shy of
44 years
And what that means is that main needs people to come and take care of its agent
Population
He says there's a huge need for everything from
Positions to administrators to ITP
People who can work at the hospital
And so about 10 years ago Maine decided to basically payoff
People student loans
Mangel students in the state
If you stay
And go to college in Maine
And then stick around after
Do you graduate we're going to give you a
Huge break on your state income
Thumbtacks
Two off
Set your student loan
So if you pay for example $2,000
Student loans
You got $2,000 knocked off your state income
And if you're from a stem field science technology
Math
They're even more generous
An employer Community spoke up loud and clear and said that's great but even if we retain 100% of every
College graduate in Maine
That doesn't solve our talent
That means you are
Are quite low on Young
Yes
Swain said okay let's broaden the program
Now
We don't care which state you're from and you can go to college anywhere in the country
As long as you come to Maine afterwards
And work here
Will cut you the same deal
The state will help with your student loan payments by dropping your state
Although
As Sarah and I learned
There are some restriction
So I graduated from college in California
So I can move to Maine
And you would offset my student loans
If I moved
If you graduated in your 2016 2017 2018 or any urine to the Future
Went like actual
Enter House burn
And we don't feel old but like you're not too old to live and work in Maine you definitely qualify for the quality of life we have to
How about that
What is not a cop come on man
The quality of
Where else in the world
Can you wake up in the morning walk on the beach
Before you go to work go for a hike at your lunch break
And Beyond the ski slopes
By 3 p.m.
California
Ultra mod
That's baloney the traffic in California you'd barely get to the beach by noon if you left before you woke up
Find whatever is Maine doesn't want 30-somethings like us there I don't want to be in Maine anyway
Please lighthouses
Batteries don't need a cell main has effectively paid off
More than 50 million dollars worth of student loans
Through the storm
And it says it's hard to know which of these graduates came to Maine.
Because of the program but
As of last year around 9
Thousand
Actually young people
We're working in Maine
Taking advantage of this
What young people mean is Decades of
Work often times there's going to start a family they're going to
Contribute a few more human beings to minsk population
Pretty smart they don't have a cap on how many people can
Participate in this program but you only get your student loans
Offset
If you can find a
Job in Maine
And that's like this naturally built-in restriction
And they said that is good
Because honestly the state couldn't handle it
Massive
Influx of new
Switch on the housing authority on the school
We have two jobs
So we're not looking for a huge number of people were looking for the right people
And more of them
To choose
I like hearing man
Justina
Not old
30 year old
Although we do have so much more World experience
Down the street
We wouldn't wear
Twitter Twitter annoying thanks
We don't even know still doing the
The Vaping
We sending it for me you can go today
Nick you went with dates
That is so debasing an existential crisis
Rhode Island
I went there to meet
Carlos tobon
We ended up driving around in his truck maybe we could take a little ride and I'll show you some of the cool things
That we have Carlos is the number one booster of Rhode Island State Rep
He represents about 15,000 people and it seems like he knows every single one of them he points them out while
We drive by their houses this guy used to have a business this guy he's as he works at a lumber yard
The Puerto Rican Family clearly been knocking doors in this neighborhood
Absolutely it took a lot of campaigning for Carlos to get elected the first time
Read three times before I got elected I lost three times and in 2012 I made history just
Not the one that I want it I lost by one vote for me when people
We'll talk about counting I take it so seriously Sarah Carlos is a man obsess
Assessed with
Okay his obsession goes back decades
When he was a teenager he had the job of a numeral
Numerator
Yeah I learned that's just a fancy way of saying
Count to the people of Rhode Island
For the US Census
So I can or knock on the door
And say hello my name is Carlos I'm with the Census Bureau and
We see that
We haven't received your paperwork
Crows want to make sure that everyone in the state
It was counted
Because more people means more government
People would say what why do I have to do it
And then I would explain to them what this is going to affect
What Rhode Island will get for the next 10 years
And everything from infrastructure money in schools
The representation we have in Washington
Representation in Washington
Rhode Island right now has
Two Congressional reps
But there are brisk
Of losing one of them are state is facing grave danger okay there are 435
Congressional seats in the car
And every census
We divvy up those seats based on which states are growing in Wichita
And in order for Rhode Island to not lose one of their seats
The state needs to grow
By 30000
People and Carlos
Really doesn't want to lose
So he proposed a bill that would give
$10,000 in tax credits
Two ten thousand families
Families of 3 or more
If they reside in Rhode Island
Long enough to be counted
In the next census
So they can like get their $10,000 and then move away
Could but Carlos
This is how big they were
And I should say that
Is just one of several
Criticisms of
Of his plan Democrats a subsidized
Rich because he only wants to give tax credits
The families who make above a certain threshold
And Republicans are like this is just a waste of money
Cuz if you do the math
Carlos is built
Lacoste
Million-dollar
A hundred million dollars that does not
Theme worth
One extra congressional seat to me I don't know for Carlos
It is totally worth
What he sees it
Rhode Island
Billions of dollars from the Federal
But there's also a lot of federal spending
They can be willed in One Direction or not
Like for example
Orders of submarines
To get built in order
Do you want that extra vote to influence spending
Like that
We can't
Stan to take another loss
If we lose a c
Will be scratching our heads and we could talk about all the things we could have done but it's too late
10 years right now probably forever
Roberto Carlos lost
An election by one
I think she just doesn't want to live that nightmare again
Just missing out
I can understand that
Got to go get a see if I can score one of those
Okay but I need a co-host
The sentiment
How much is it worth
Okay we just heard about 2
Really expensive ways to increase our population
Coming up after the break
A deal so good
It's free
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editor
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to launch use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hate this is Gyros
And on the next TED Radio Hour
Stories of remarkable transformation
The face
Ordinary circumstance
I often forget that my limbs are synthetic
That's how Willie work
You can find it
TED Radio Hour
Wherever you listen
Okay so while some countries are putting out
Sexy commercial saying have more babies please
And US states are literally paying people money to move to their towns
One mayor in a small town in Italy thought
Why not just
Welcome refugees
Is there more than 28 million refugees and asylum-seekers in the world according to the United Nations
And immigration is
One way that a lot of countries have solved their population problems for decade
Countries like Denmark Italy
They develop and modernized
They get richer and their birth rates drop
So we all start to depend a little bit more on
But in this Italian town
That familiar story
Went sideways
Did you tell us all about it is
The one and only Sylvia poggioli NPR senior European correspondent
Sylvia welcome to Planet Money thank you thank you for having me tell us about reaction
Oh it's a
The medieval town perched on a hill in
Calabria it's that's
Foot of the Tower
The Italian boot
And it was until about 20 years ago
Abandoned ghost town with not more than
Couple thousand
People living there
Then something happened in the summer of night
Hundreds of refugees
Arrived at riachi
You sure that's right in the mayor Domenico Lucano had this idea
A why don't we welcome them
And he basically offered them
A place to live in the menu
Empty apartments that
In the town
And he offered them places
To start opening little artists
Beijing shops
They're hardly any businesses now it's full of cafes and shops
I'm not going to say it's the thriving town but it's a living town
It's been called the reactor experiment and several other towns
Definitely were inspired not many but a few started doing it to
Andalou, was he's become quite famous for having done
But then the
Current Refugee crisis that we all know about
Happened and that changed
Not just the refugee crisis but the arrival of a new government which is very much anti-migraine
And they Crackdown against
Aldi's welcoming attitude
Do towards migrants
And medical, was charged
Twist
Basically he was accused of
Enabling
And encouraging illegal migration they were said that he was giving
Refugees
Jobs that suck like they have to pee
Find some excuse
In any case he was first put under house arrest
And now he has been banned from living in vrchat he is the current mayor of reactionary but he is not allowed to
B andreacchi
That's right
How does he feel about that
He's pretty Furious
Yeah so Sylvia there all these cities
States and countries that are like actually begging for people to move there
Meanwhile there's this
Global refugee
Cheap prices and it seems like a match made in heaven but
It's not really happy
Definitely in most of Europe now
There is a overwhelming auntie
To my good feeling
All the policies now are making it much harder for migrants
To settle and to make a decent living in these countries
The problem is the migrants heart, stop coming
They're going to always find a way
Also this town Italy also has one of the lowest birth rates
It's in the world
So it needs my
Prince if it wants to you know
To make its economy work in the future
Or people
Could just make more babies they could
But doesn't look like people are very willing to do that right
All right Sylvia and just because you are legendary and because my to Cohoes
They ditched me will you stick around after the credits
Sure
If you have a story idea send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
Today Show was produced by Darian Woods
Bryant urstadt headed to the show and Alex goldmark is the supervising producer
Antero Gonzales
And I'm so beautiful drawing
Thanks for listening
And one more thing we couldn't fit into the show was house Singapore
Try to increase
Is birth rate
Through
Song
It's time to do our stuff
Civic duty and I'm not talking about
Beaches fireworks or parades
I'm talking about the stuff after that stuff
I'm talking about making a baby
Baby
Yeah