Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional counselors specializing in issues including depression stress and anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com money to learn more and get 10% off your first month
This is Planet Money
Frontier
Today Show originally ran in 2015
I will be back in 2019 at the end of the show with an update
All my life solar power has been the thing that's coming in the future
Why can science fiction how are we going to power The Ringworld
You didn't read it good luck
Solar panels in the real world though solar has been this fringy thing
Like I remember when I was in college
This friend of mine was on the solar car team
But they think they built wasn't really a car it was basically just like these giant solar panel and this little like capsule
Call that you had to lie down into drive
Have solar calculator for solar calculator
Those are real
You grew up in California there were a few Rich hippies up in the hills with solar panels
But it was like a special things or thing you'd see in a MAG
And that is actually
Changing really fast just in the past couple years
Power is not just for Rich hippies
Last week I went out to Long Island to meet a guy named John okay
John is a retired New York City Cop
And today I just across six guys with putting solar panels on the roof of his house
Tell me about your house
What do you want to know where do termites live
I don't know how big is your house
Guy 4 bedrooms two-and-a-half baths
So sorry
What's up with the neighbors like this is Farmingville nice neighborhood middle-class Working Families
Done is not rich
And he's not getting solar panels to save the world
The environmental part of it
Meaningful to use ml
Not really
If you are an environmentalist or if you just
Like solar power
John o'hagan is your dream come true
Jennifer Hagan is the revolution you've been weighed
He's not getting solar power for a
Moral or philosophical reasons
Not doing it cuz he's worried about climate
John o'hagan is getting solar power because it's cheap
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I'm David kestenbaum today on the show House solar power got so cheap
So fat
Basically
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Google domains
Most of you have a great business idea
Like Maggie
You always love croissants and even traveled to France to learn how to make
She got a business name
Maggie's Bakery
And with the help of Google domains intuitive tools
She got her business online
And croissants in people's hands
Google domains makes it easy to get your business online
It starts with a name
It becomes real
With a domain
Make it happen add domains. Google / NPR to get started
Greg what are you doing here again I write a newsletter
Where can people get that sweet sweet content npr.org Planet Money newsletter that's what I can say
That's what they contain up yet
The story of how solar power got so cheap
He's not the story of one braid
There wasn't one engineer in some lab
Who solved the solar problem
Afternoon
It's a story of a few things
You can split it up into three
First category is the one you would expect that not for the reason you
The panels
Pendleton cells have gotten
John the guy made out of you was getting 41 panels on his
I guess that's
Pretty typical
When I got out to his house
There was a truck in the driveway and a bunch of the solar panels were just right there leaning up against the
So is this this is can I touch this
It's one of the panel
Restaurant where to get suicune on the roof I'm not going to
The company putting up the panels on John's house is called Solar City
It's actually the biggest residential solar installer in the country
We could she oversees the companies East Coast
Installers
8 years ago how much would a panel like this a car
1000 hours
Okay
This panel just handle right here how much does it cost now
I would estimate
Somewhere around
220 $50
Go from a thousand bucks to 200 or 250 bucks
In just a few years just a few years
That's a huge step
It's a big drop the reason for the big drop
Is that
Someplace made a lot of solar power
You can actually see it.
It's written on the back of the panel
Little letters
So what what does it say
This is Trina Solar Smart Energy together
Made in China
Ignore ignore most of that ignore trina solr ignore energy together sisolak
Dragon China
It's not your typical story of China figuring out how to make something cheaper
This is the story really of China making
A mistake
Basically China decided when it was going to get into solar power
It was going to go big
The government
Set up all these subsidized loan
And Chinese companies built
All the solar power
Factory
After Factory
As a result when all these factories came on line around
There was a huge glut of solar power
The price collapse
If you one of the companies in the US or Germany and Japan that's already in the Solar business
At what is not what you
When did the Glock if you don't know about cost
With.
This is Lyndon Rive
He's the CEO of SolarCity
This is Hugo from
Lowering your car
As a standard part of the
The companies
That
Mission 2
If you don't love it
Given that alternative
Death of lawyer cost
People become very innovative
Different companies with different ways
Some companies did innovator lower their costs
Others
Died there was this massive wave of bankruptcies in the industry and
Largely because of that played as a bad news story in this country and their well-being
Little mini trade war between the US and China over the solar subsidies
But you know the end of the story is
Panels did get a lot cheaper
Okay that's the first thing that is made solar power more affordable the panels themselves
But there is this other major expense
If you want to have solar panels on the roof of your house
You got to pay someone to put the solar panels on the roof of your house
You got to be a lot of people
John's house the crew with six guys
4 installers into electrician
Jacob have you ever had one electrician out
IHOP
I mean they're handling actress
Insulation solar panels can actually cost
As much as the panel
Themselves it's a big part of the car
Again just in the past few years installation
Has actually gotten
A lot cheaper
Cheaper is
It's gotten fast
You don't have to pay those guys to be out of your house for as long
When I was at a John's actually saw some of the reasons it has gotten fast
This is the zepto this is the end-all-be-all tools
Does that to let Led Zep 2
Exactly 1/2 of the ruling
That's a guy named Brian Barney
What's the zip tool
It's a wrench is Bandit physically register these little marks on it or whatever but
The key thing is it's part of this whole Installation System
It's happening this is this is this is the meeting potatoes here
About an hour and a half after they get to John's house the crew is ready to start actually putting in the first row of
And once the first one goes in its just
It's just like jigsaw puzzle one piece will fit in the next one to the next one
And that first row is going to go up in
I don't know 2 minutes
Well let's see what time what time is it let's see how long it takes
59 to 9:59 2 minutes
Ticking clock retention even if it's just getting solar panel
It's at the guys up on the roof right right at this point there they're kind of rocking the panels in
Play feel I clean them and they lowered him down and when they're in their right to make this this
Crack them
66 panels in that first row
Few more snaps and
It was done
That's it how we doing what time is it 1:55
To be clear
Little 2-minute race is just a tiny part of the whole installation
Right foot all of this stuff does Neptune rule the one told to rule them all is that
Whole new system all of it together meme
Insulation really is a lot faster and cheaper today than it was a few years ago
How long is it going to take
4 hours
So how long would a plain-vanilla installation of Taken I don't know 5 years ago 10 years ago when you got into this installation
About 2 days
2 days
And now it's half a day
Half a day
That's you
Syracuse Craigslist
Eliza
These guys are going to be done by lunch time
Okay we got cheaper panels cheaper installation
What's the cost down to
About $25,000 still alive
Yeah that's basically what Johnson
Pacific icon
She is back
Looked into a gift for the savings and every company
$1,000
You have $2,000 short time later on no solar panels on its roof till today
This was the final obstacle
Who has $25,000 sitting around by solar panels and get them
I mean some people
But not a lot.
Right it's always going to be a friendly thing if you got to have this money
I mean I get them you can make the money back over
Overtime but it's just hard to think about spending $25,000
And this right here this is where we get to the last big breakthrough that's made solar really take off
Donald Hagen is not paying $25,000 to get the panel put on
Flask
He's not paying anything
He's not buying the pain
He doesn't own the power
The panels belong to Solar City
The way it works is John Cena con
Promising to pay SolarCity a monthly bill for the next 20 years
In the long run this will cost John more than if you just paid for the whole thing upfront out of his pocket
But it makes it work
And it makes the whole decision for John really sing
Should I go solar
Comes out a really simple calculation
How much am I paying on my life
And how much can I get a pay if I switch to solar
It just seems like a great deal that's the electric bill
40 50%
So how much you paying there for your power bill
About 180 a month
And so you pay 180 a month how much you expecting to be paying on this
I should come down to about a hundred hundred and ten
A month wants to switch your agates weapon these guys
Hook me up to the electric box I'm all set
That's it
Just that simple calculation
That is
The heart of
America's roof
Top solar boom
It's a guy who doesn't particularly care about the environment a guy who's
Not trying to make a statement
The guy who sang
If I get solar panels put on my roof today
My power bill is going to go down next
There is one problem with this whole
All set up if your SolarCity and you're going to be paying for solar panels
People's houses across America
Back it's really expensive
Twenty five
You do the math
It's like Billy the dog
And SolarCity the young company they don't have billions of dollars
Here's how they solved that problem
SolarCity and other companies in the industry
They went to Wall Street they went to Big Banks instead
Do you want to own solar panels big investors big
Big Wall Street Banks
Put up billions of dollars
And they essentially own little pieces of solar panels on you know house is like John's and they get this flow of the pain
Payments for the next 20 years
Solar panels
People's rooms across me
Until they solve the problem
And that is how solar power got cheap
The solar panels themselves
The one tool to rule them all fancy fast installation
+ 3
Creative financing
I got so far is
Subsidies is the government
There's a big
Federal tax subsidy that is is a big deal in that may go down
In the relatively near future a lot of States also have subsidies I know John is getting a state level subsidy as well
Only a small fraction of the electricity in this country comes from Solar Ray
Kind releaf
Is right
But it is growing
In fact you found this
Report by Greenpeace why do expect to be sore
Overly optimistic the report was called Energy Revolution
Animated Verde
They undressed
Where we would be today
Yeah yeah it's
It basically nobody predicted it would grow as fast as
And today
John is even trying to get his dad
Is your dad going to do it next least thinking about it
The app
That's good what
It'll come on
Come on pop what you got to save a few bucks.
2015 you got to get with the program solar is in right
Jacob you know that is exactly the kind of pissed that works for me
Save a few bucks.
Dyson look into solar a while ago I got a little flyer in the mail and I called the
Number
And the guys like what's your address
Can I tell him
Tap tap tap
I'm putting in the Google Earth
Is that tree fill in your front yard
I think I see you going to cut it down
My day is not going to work
The nice tree
SMC
So they're actually a few reasons that solar doesn't work for it for a lot of pee
People in effect trees are big when trees are your roof doesn't face the right direction
Another big one is
You got a pretty good
Read it right they're not going to
Trust you to make this 20-year deal
Unless you have
Good credit
A third one is it mostly just makes sense for Homeowner
Is it doesn't really make sense for renters
At this point
So how many houses do you think this might make sense for
There's a really wide range of estimates but from what I read in the people I talk to is it something like
10 to 20 million seems like a pretty safe bet 10 to 20 million houses
Which is about 10 or 20% of the houses in the country
That's not going to like solve
Climate change
But that is serious that's not
Frenchie that is not nothing
That's real
What time is it
Turn it on right now
So the power light green that's a good start what does that mean it's getting DC power from from the roof
So just to be clear the power that is turning on this light and this thing is coming from
Coming from the Sun
That the guys clean up the roof they put the ladders back into the truck and maybe they were done by lunch
Where they go
I think they went for wings
So that's where we left it in 2015
After the break
We'll have an update on what has changed in rooftop solar since then
Support for this podcast and the following message come from the Walton Family Foundation
Where opportunity takes root
More information is available at Walton Family Foundation. Org
Everyone is ophira Eisenberg and here I'm chatting with one of queer eye's Fab 5 Antoni porowski
What's a culinary deal-breaker for you
Ketchup on hotdogs makes me really uncomfortable
Listen to NPR's ask me another the answer to Life's funny or questions
There have been some changes in rooftop solar since the show first aired in 2000
When is the company that was doing the installation at John O'Higgins house Solar City
Got into financial trouble
They borrow too much money that grew too fast
They wound up selling themselves to Tesla in mm
16 they laid off thousands of workers and cut way back on
Sales and marketing
And that was a blow to the whole industry
So much so that the number of new rooftop solar installations
Bell in 2017
So it started climbing again
Last year
Another update
That federal subsidy for solar that we mentioned that was renewed
Currently set to phase out over the next few years
Also since we first did this show
The Trump Administration put tariffs on solar panels imported from China
But because the panels themselves are only a small part of the cost of getting rooftop solar
Those tears actually didn't have that big of an empath
One last thing
The price of panels in the other Hardware has continued to fall
So getting rooftop solar is now cheaper than it was in 2002
Thanks to Michelle Davis of wood Mackenzie she's the one who told me all the ways in which rooftop solar has changed since
But the original show we also spoke with shayle Kann of GTM research
And David pomerantz of green pee
We love to hear you think you said his email Planet Money at npr.org
We are on Instagram Facebook
Twitter at Planet Money
Lydia Wilson produce the original show
Darian Woods produce today's rerun Alex goldmark is are supervising producer and Bryant Earth deadheaded
The show
Planet Money is a production of NPR
I'm Jacob Goldstein
And I'm David kestenbaum Thanks For Less
You've never read Ringworld it's really
Solar panels orbiting the Sun and then they have this ring outside
Would very high wall so the oxygen stays in through sink
Tropical Force
I think we're almost there
I feel like 2 years from ringing