Support for this in
NPR podcasts
The following message
Come from the UPS
Offering services from shredding
To printing to mailbox
And instead of closing this Memorial Day we
May 24th and 20
The UPS Store
He's doing another thing
All together
Opening
The UPS Store
Everything for small business
And of course shipping
Hate just a quick note
Today's Show originally aired in 2000
You know what the price of a Coca-Cola was in 1886
A nickel
In 1900
Stella Nickell
10 years later 1910
A nickel
1948 nickel
Is slated 1959 you could buy
6 1/2 ounce bottle of Coca-Cola
41 nickel
And for economist
This is a
Total freak of nature kind of
Prices you can read in any textbook are supposed to go up
And down
The price of gasoline goes up and down depending on
How much is available how many
People wanted
How hard it is to get out of the ground
The price of a television depends on how expensive the components are there
Making the price of Labor
The price of butter goes up and down
Corn cars houses
Everything
Prices change the adjust
It's the basic mechanism for how markets work
And yet for 70 years
You could buy a Coke for $0.05
Coca-Cola is the best drink in the land men women children the country
It's the $0.05 drink of the nation prove the Coca-Cola quenches your thirst refreshes your spirits
Nothing else.
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum
Today the strange story of nickel Coke
Why it happened
What it says about the textbooks
Anaheim
Support for this podcast and the following message come from each raid
With all the jargon investing can feel like a foreign language each raid makes investing simple by providing per
Personalized support and guidance in terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as $500 and then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro to invest in ETrade
For more information visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC
Member Civic
If you listen to Planet money you probably love learning new things
NPR have another podcast series you might like
It's called life
It's a collection of guides on how to get your life together
From getting better sleep
To saving more money
Research light kit
Scrap
It's not a secret that
Coke cost a nickel for so long
You can go to any antique store and see the old signs
If you go to the Coca-Cola museum in Atlanta the tour guide will tell you
And normally people on the tour will just not
Yeah things used to be cheap
But one day a guy named Daniel Levy
He took his kids to that
Called The World of Coke
Entice families on this tour and the tour guide just mentioned
This nickel coaxing
And Levi thinks
Wait what
Goodnight heard that I said can you say that again
And he repeated and I kind of food crops my in my head right I should
How can that be
Daniel Levy UC is Anakin
And for him
This is a mystery
So he basically hijacks the tour
Start asking all these questions
How could coke stay nickel
Go for so long
And it's all guys like
I don't know
The Daniel goes back to Emory University where he works and he find
Andrew Young
Daniel did kind of walk in and say that he found this crazy thing one day and you know I need a research assistant do you want to help me out
Project IGI sounds really interesting let's do it
The more they think about it
Single price
470 years
Stranger it seems
This puzzle becomes really
Really amazing when you actually consider
What has happened during that period
Be at the Great Depression
Free Wars Spanish American World War 1 World War including Pepsi
Hundreds of competitors probation varios lawsuits end
None of this sinks made any difference basically like 1886 into the 1950s
All of all of these you know dramatic changes to the economy going on and then one constant through it all was that you could
To get six and a half ounces of Coca-Cola at the fountain or in a bottle
If you think that's just because Coca-Cola came up with Incredible Innovations to cut cost
To keep the price down
This is not that story
It's a much stranger
The tour guide went Daniels and Grilling and said
You should go to the Coca-Cola Park
So Daniel and Andrew do
And it has all this stuff
Posters calendars novelty items his film uni the Coca-Cola Company archivist
He says the company has saved
Everything metal signs
Magazine advertising radio and television advertising Department of Records
Product files executive correspondence the secret formula for Coke in there somewhere
That is one thing that is not there
So are Economist are going through the archive
Muni the archivist says he can explain
Hannah Coco
It was an attempt to attract customer
Late 1800s were the days of soda fountains
And there were lots of soda fountain drink
They were primarily
Fruit-flavored drinks oranges and grapes what was the cost of the competitors
7/8 baby tencent somewhere $0.05 but
Coco Quinn
Very specifically to Market itself
As an affordable product
The first sale we know is in Atlanta at a store on Peachtree Road
On May 8th
I'm reading from the Coca-Cola official history here
Dr. John Stith Pemberton a local pharmacist produce the syrup for Coca-Cola
And carried a jug down the street to Jacob's Pharmacy where it was sampled pronounce
Excellent
And placed on sale for $0.05 a glass
Eva soda fountain
Okay that's the easy part
That's how it started
But why did coke stay in nickel for 70 years
The two Economist Andrew and Daniel start going deeper and deeper into the ark
Guys reading everything I can
Books company history
Andrew Young find this story that
Seems to explain part of the mystery
Of why Coke remained price
It has to do with two lawyers from Chattanooga Tennessee
In 1899
Those lawyers pay a visit to the president
Coca-Cola
His name is a second
And they tell him they are interested in this new thing
Bottles
Selling drinks in bottles
They want to buy the bottling right
And
Asa Candler the president of Koch thanks
Bottles
This is a soda fountain business
The way The Story Goes is Candler just said you're out of your mind
If I can at least I could be effective it's not going to work you're going to lose all your money
And they said well please you'll give us the rights anyway until you just said yeah I'll sign this piece of paper
So just be I'll just sign this piece of paper that says yeah you know whenever you want and I'll just tell you
Syrup
The concentrate at $0.90 a gallon
In agreeing to do that Kendall did something companies
Never do
Agreed to sell its product
The syrup to bottlers
For a fixed price
Forever
The contract had no end date it was a Perpetual infinite non ending contract
You could never charge more for his product
Why would he do that
My best take on it is that
Yeah really this was just
Trying to get two guys out of your office
That mean anytime you get two lawyers in your office you probably want to leave Ryan he's just saying
I'll sign this piece of paper if you'll just please leave my office
I never thought twice about it
This was a problem for the Coca-Cola Company because of course
Bottled drinks took off
And Coca Cola ad sign this contract
Basically saying it would never raise the price of the syrup to
To the bottlers
This does not explain why coke stay Tunica
Because
The bottlers could sell a bottle for whatever they wanted
Stuck at the corner store
Sixth Sense
$0.07 or $0.10
It's what Coca-Cola did next
The cap the price at an echo
Understand that you have to think about the situation from Coca-Cola's perspecta
Because
You've agreed to sell your syrup to the bottle is traffic
Any increase in price at the corner store
It doesn't help
You don't get any of the extra profit
The Profit goes to the bottlers in the retail
And in fact if they raise the price
It hurts you
If Coco's up to a dime
Fewer people are going to buy it
And you Coca-Cola
End up selling less serum
So if your Coca-Cola you want somehow
To keep the price down at $0.05
What do you do
Well one thing you do is you blanket the entire nation
With with Coca-Cola advertising
That basically has five cents prominently featured
Think about how brilliant this is
Coca-Cola
Is taking control of the pricing away from the bottlers and the corner store
The company
Can't actually put a sticker on the bottle of coke saying $0.05
But it can put up a huge billboard
Paint the side of the building right next to the store that says
Drink Coca Cola 5 cents
Again Daniel Levy
I'm holding in my hand
Life Magazine
Find a Life Magazine they know
Quite old actually this particular one is a Life Magazine from 1980
13 July 10
And did the back of this magazine said is the recent ad of Coca-Cola and it says drink Coca-Cola
It's $0.05 delicious and refreshing
Is pointy stud
Since everybody was brainwashed people so this at all over
And this included $0.05
It was part of the commodity to foremost
It was hard for anybody to increase the price
Anyone selling a bottle of coke for more than $0.05
It's going to look like a jerk
But what about the soda fountain
People ran the soda Fountains at the corner store
Okay the ads made it so they couldn't charge more than a nickel
But they could use smaller glasses
Or skin pain syrup
So what do you do if your Coca-Cola
Crisfield money the company archives
You provided them with the glass
That was one point that you did it
And for many years it was actually
A line drawn
In the glass
To show you where
How far to draw the syrup
And then went with how does it feel like carbonated water.
How to complete the drink
That's a very clever way to control how much
People getting
That was the idea
This explains part of the mystery of why Coca-Cola state of nickel
For so long
Coca-Cola was locked into this weird contract
For the bottlers
But there had to be something else going
Because in 1921 Coca-Cola managed to renegotiate the car
The price of sugar gone up in the company was losing money so
Bottlers eventually can see
Finally the Coca-Cola company was back in control
I could do whatever it wanted
After two decades of being Shackled by a bad contract
Coke didn't have to be iniquity
So what happened
It stayed a nickel anyway
Part of the reason was just that advertising
It was so effective the company is locked
Itself in
I think how long it would take to repaint All Those ads on the sides of the building
Are Coca Cola trays
It said $0.05
All the stuff
Given enough time that could have change
But
There was this one final hurdle
I heard about the size of a refrigerator
Painted bright red
The vending machine
At this point in history vending machines aren't equipped to make
Change
And the Coca-Cola vending machines
They're built to take one coin
And that coin
Is a nickel
These machines
They were everywhere
Here's Daniel Levy
More and more sales of Coca-Cola
Firme true vending machines
To give you a sense
There were about 460,000 vending machines in the US
400000 of them belonged to Coca-Cola going through the archives Daniel and Andrew say
It is clear that the people at Coca-Cola really wanted to raise the price of Coke
But they couldn't
Because of these machines that only took single coin
7 people at Coca-Cola
If only there were another coin
There's a dime
But that would double the
No really
We want something in between
So here is some of your clever idea what they came up with Stacy
How about we
We asked the treasury to issue 7 and 1/2 cent coin
The US Treasury the government
Daniel Andrew say at one point the head of Coca-Cola
Asti
President of the United States
Eisenhower for help
Mature hunting
And it wasn't just Coca-Cola this was a crisis for any business that sold through vending machine
But
No luck
There's never been a seven and a half
Coca-Cola was still desperate
To raise the price
So desperate in fact of the company came up with what
Andrew Young called a harebrained idea
This never actually saw the light of day but
They're a bunch of references to it in the ark
We're going to do some internal memos and pulled out this
Yo stapled pack of you know maybe 10 pages the right in the front of it says single coin plan
Oh my God what is this the single coin plan was a very clever way
To charge more for a bottle of Coke
Without having to adjust the vending machines at all
I'll let Daniel Levy
Cutest what did they basically came up with she said
Okay we are going to increase the price
But people will still be using nickel so how they do that
Did they said
They're going to make
Every 9th bottle
Individual machine it will be an empty bottle
Decode that bottle that Empty Bottle they called it an official blank
An empty bottle
So eight customers in a row with panicle and funk
Outlook
The Unlucky 9% would put a nickel in
Clink
An empty bottle
Got to put in a second
So sometimes you're lucky sometimes you're not
On average
You end up paying slightly more than the nickel
Average price the effective price now is
5.6 to $0.05
I can imagine customers waiting hate that
I'd be so pissed if I put in a nickel and I got an empty bottle of coke not even just a thing saying sorry if you need to pay
Pay an extra axial Empty Bottle
It just make me angry I think that's that's that's that's one
Reason to abandon this policy
But I thought it was very quick very clever idea though
Vending machines that reliably make change are available by 19
But the thing that finally undoes the nickel Coke
Is something else
After the break
The end of nickel
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from American Express you want to build your business they can help you
Build your business with financing solutions for eligible business customers
The powerful backing of American Express don't do business without it
Terms apply visit americanexpress.com business
We're back with a new season of Russian
Yeah this time we are following people who break the rules part of the business
In my opinion the best revenge against Isis Pacific Humane supposed to punch
New episodes
Every other Wednesday subscribe
Inflation is definitely sort of the death-knell for the nickel Coke there's no doubt about that
You might think inflation would have been a problem for Coca-Cola the whole time
But Andrea says
There wasn't really inflation before the 1940s
Yes prices with me and her up sometimes sugar in the ingredients cost more
But they made me under back down
After the 1940s
Inflation is here to stay
Prices just keep going
What happened
The US went off the gold standard
Dollars no longer had to be backed by gold
Simplifying things but basically we have no longer got the golden anchor
And so at that point the amount of
Money just keep going up and up and up which means that prices go up and up and up
Well prices are going up and up and up
You just can't keep your
You can keep your Coca-Cola for nickel for too much longer
So in a way
Nickel Coke died because we went off the gold
You don't you can actually you can make that argue
In 1946 and 47
You start to see cokes on sale for more than a nickel
Sixth Sense
7th Sense
It's a big deal
The Press reports on it Fortune Magazine in 1951
Rezin Optical called
The nickel Coke is groggy
Like its unsteady ready to fall
At 8.
The last available Mexico seems to have been
Sometime in 19th
4 Andrew Young and Daniel Levy
The story says
One is just that life is messier than the textbooks tell you
Yes prices in the market generally adjust
There are weird contracts
Vending machine
And also
Prices are complicated things
They get stuck
And we get stuck on them
There was a time between the contract and the vending machine
When the Coca-Cola Company could have changed it
But it didn't
Coca-Cola early on said
Coke cost a nickel
I put it on Billboard
Can ads painted on buildings
And people got used to it
It felt like a promise
In a way
All prices
Is kind of feel like
Once we see a price on something
We have this
Feeling like that some innate property of the thing that it should not change
Prices have the psychological component
That's why companies will often shrink a product rather than raise the price
Put your potato chips in the bag
Make the ice cream container
14 oz
Instead of a pint
I'm looking at you Haagen-Dazs
So
Prices gets.
But Daniel Levy says as far as he knows
Nickel Coke is the longest documented sticky price
In modern history
Nickel Coke persisted for 70 years
And in retrospect
It wasn't a bad thing for the company
Is one Legacy of this weird history
That Coca-Cola is now everywhere is this time we think of coke is being everywhere
Is that in part because they were stuck with a nickel price in the only way to make more money was
What's the sell more coke
So they really put every effort into
My sense is that that is that is a big part of it
That Coca-Cola was forced to push volume to be more profitable
They couldn't adjust its price
And so it did it very very powerful push volume at at one point they were associated with the middle
Terry there were Coca-Cola Bottling operations on every single continent except for Antarctica during World War II
All there to make sure that our soldiers could always get
Coca-Cola in a bottle
Water fountain
Barnacle
Today
Koch's are larger
And the cost of a dollar more at
Write a vending machine
Nickel Coke seems like a long time
Though Phil Mooney the Coca-Cola archivist
Find out this one strange thing
In many respects the nickel Coke is soda still around
If you do it on a per ounce basis
Buy 2 liter bottle for dollar $29.39 in the grocery store on sale
And that's pretty close to
The original nickel Coke is very very
I mention this to Andrew Young The Economist
He said
That's a nice way to think about it
It's still with us
Justin Baker Botts
Laminate now has a Weekly Newsletter asking interesting economic question
Like he's buying a house overrated
Are there ways in which plastic bag bans may actually be harming the environment
You can sign up for it at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
Again npr.org
Planet Money news
You can email us at Planet Money at npr.org
We're also on Twitter Facebook and Instagram
Today's rerun was produced by Darian Woods
Printers that is the editor of Planet Money and Alex goldmark is the supervising producer
I'm Jacob books.
I'm David kestenbaum
Thanks for listening