Everyone it's Sarah Gonzales here
I have been going to the trial of Joaquin El Chapo Guzman Infamous drug cartel leader
Just found guilty of all charges against him
International cocaine distribution using firearms
And
Laundering all of his
Drag Pro
Which is the one that were really interested in
It reminded us of this classic episode that we're going to play for you today
About the time the United States try to
Stop drug traffickers
With a pretty sneaky plan that involved a
Decoy
Now Indian Chapo trial we learned about all of the elaborate ways that he moved his drug money
Around the US government claims that over his career he earned
14 billion dollars tons and tons of
Heavy money
That takes up a lot of
Space
El Chapo apparently flew a bunch of his drug money out of the United States
On his
Super stealth
Private jets that are coded in some material
That literally allows them to fly under the radar
And then Chapelwood hide all of his drug money in these
Huge underground Bank size vault
Because
This is not the kind of cash that you can deposit in a regular Bank
Without people asking where it came from
So they had to laundry they would like fill a bunch of prepaid debit cards with as much money as they could
It made it easier to transport
But apparently El Chapo didn't like this method because
It took a really long time to withdraw
$1000000
Now the United States has its own tricks and that's what today's episode is about
Here is David kestenbaum and Hannah joffe-walt with a story that originally ran
In 2012
Sometime in the early 90s
A man walked into the US Embassy Annex
He said he had information someone would want to hear
Information on how to go after some of the most powerful drug traffickers in the world
This guy said
He was willing to help
And what happened next
With the two special agents in Atlanta got a phone call
Skip Latin with the DEA drug enforcement Administration
And Bill Britton
With the IRS
Heard about this guy and thought
You got to meet him
Initial meeting was in Ecuador
Keto
Quito Ecuador
Did you go on that toe
You didn't take me
Do you have a code name for this guy or anything early
Yeah
Yeah he was a it was a code name Dan
That is the least creative code name of Riverhead
Dan the informant work as a currency exchanger
He was the guy you went to if you had pesos and you want dollars or vice versa
And dance with skipping bail he was getting a lot of requests
From drug traffic
Drug traffickers with a problem
A problem
Don't skip had never fully appreciate
You're having a very difficult time
It's just the logistics
Of laundering
Millions and millions and millions of dollars
Every week
Well yeah
Imagine the situation
The drug traffickers are smuggling all this cocaine into the United
The cocaine get sold on the
But
There's this problem
People buying cocaine aren't paying with credit
Cards they're paying in small bills
KENS 5
So the drug traffickers have hundreds of thousands or millions of dollars in physical cash
And it just weighs a lot
Bill the IRS agent remembers reading a drug traffickers house
And finding a huge amount of cash
I think it was in like 7 or 8 suitcases
And it took
Cannabis
To what to carry was so heavy
That's so funny I never thought about that but just been
Satchel mini would be
The unique problem unique to the illegal industry
The weight
Of the money
Is huge
It's absolutely astronomical
This was a huge problem for drug trafficker
There's a problem the traffickers needed Salt
They needed someone to take all that heavy cash and turn it into
Check or wire transfer
Something that doesn't wait Huntertown
Basically the Colombian drug traffickers
They needed
A bank
Kearse bail again
Couple weeks later
Skip an hour sitting down now in Atlanta
And we're saying
Let's open up a bank
Have you ever opened up a bank before
The first one
You never even have any history you didn't have even ever
Don't ever work for a bank in my my entire career was with
You're the Criminal Division of IRS
Sort of like it if only somebody could do this crazy thing and then you guys are sitting here later thinking like
Maybe we can
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David kestenbaum
And I'm fond of Jeffy walk Today Show
Operation Dinero
Choose secret government agents go offshore create a fake Bank
And launder money for some of the largest and most dangerous
Drug kingpins around
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
We came across Bill and Skip an operation to
Because while back we here at Planet Money
Got into the offshore Financial World ourselves we created an offshore company in Belize
Try to get the inside look
If this whole Secret
Pet World
And when we were doing that we discovered that back in the 1990's
The US government
Had done exactly the same thing
Except
The government went
Way way further
Witches believe Bill and skip the two government agents wanting to open the spankbank they chose Anguilla
An island in the Caribbean
And that is where they imagine their future customers
We're already banking
Those areas those
Offshore accounts are where people launder money
So it just made sense to offer an offshore Bank
Operation dinero wasn't the first project Bill and Skip had work done together they had been working together for decades
These two guys are in each other's brains
They know exactly what the other likes
For lunch every day and the day that we met them they were wearing matching outfits
Both in polos and pleated khakis
And 4 years
Don't skip have been chasing the same guys
Guys like Pablo Escobar notorious
Drug kingpin in Colombia
I'm so dangerous there are many movies
All about
Just how bad this
Assassination a billion dollar drug Empire
One of the most Wanted Outlaws of the 20th century Pablo Escobar in my opinion
Is the largest biggest criminal the world has ever seen or will ever see
Skip the special agent with the DEA thought about Pablo Escobar alive
He remembers seeing this article in Forbes Magazine
Forbes does this list of the richest people in the world
And Pablo Escobar was on it
This criminal was a
Billionaire
Exactly the kind of guy who needs banking service
Balance gift set
We should be the ones providing those banking services
We'll see where all the money goes
We'll see how the whole operation works
And so operation to naira was a go-go and Skip needed a name for their fake
Bank to service drug traffic
And they thought about it and they said well it should definitely the word trust in the name
And also we should use initials a lot of big-name seem to have an issue
So that shows rhm witch
Apparently stands
Words for absolutely nothing
Nrhm Trust Bank
Was born
And I was the first time the
That the
Any government agency worldwide had established
Hey
The bank
The sole purpose of which was to track door track Drug traffickers Money
I would imagine that doesn't have not with him like I don't know if it ever happens
Dug out some old photos we had a party at our office when rhm Trust Bank was finally approved
You guys are is that champagne that you have the federal facility that's apple juice
Cycling
Villain scripted everything you have to do
For a bag before it open
Stay put it up
Brochures
And made some official-looking IDs and fake business cards
But their Bank was very different from every other bag
In that their plan
Was to turn away almost all potential customers
It didn't set up Branch offices there are no ATMs no smiling bank tellers
Just one office in Atlanta with a telephone and a fax
We didn't want to deal with
Anybody else's money except
The drug traffic
You want ordinary people coming inside like to open a checking account and Jack White.
Villains get born business
And the way it would work is that the drug traffickers
We have this cash that needed to be.
Today facts rhm trust and account number
Anytime Abbie Burnett
Yes faxes beepers remember this wasn't
So then whoever is going to pick the money up
Call the beeper
The guy calls him back
It says meet me at XYZ
Street corner
At 10 tomorrow morning
And what kind of car you going to be
I'm going to be in a blue Chevy
Supposed to give him a code word that Bieber something very simple this is
I have a package for Amanda
Then they would call me.
And
Package would be exchanged usually suitcases
Are packages from trunk to trunk in a public place
It's amazing this is just like every cop so I've ever seen except that usually the government isn't helping the bad guys
Launder Drug Money
What would happen next is Bill and skips guys with takes
The cash to a local bank
Deposited into an account
Onfi rhm Trust Bank
And then why are the money to wherever the drug traffickers wanted
Is it sent you
And all works
The drug people were very happy with rhm Trust Bank
Dylan skip
We're getting closer
They're learning all this stuff about the money laundering world
There they are wandering around this
Dark place
And they start bumping into all these other people who exist in the dark
Like
Princeton
Turns out they were not the only ones offering Financial Services to drug dealer
It was a busy place
With established rates for doing this kind
We were competing against
Other money pickups
So if that skip says I'm going to charge you 9%
Well then you come to me
I'm going to charge you eight and a half
And you go back to
Skip it cuz I got somebody 8 and 1/2 he's okay I'll charge at 8
You're in a competitive Marketplace very competitive market and we had to make sure we were
Not so cheap
To be suspicious
But not so high that we wouldn't get cussed
Words
Spread and soon more and more orders were coming in
Which forbidden skip
More information
What were the tricks that the
I always laughed at 4
Skip one of the fighter Hulu
True owner the money was
He would delay by 24 hours and sending the money
And then we'd get telephone calls and find out o that that person comes out of the woodwork when it looks like that the money maybe in Jeff
We picked up more information
By being a bad Bank
Who didn't handle money quickly and effectively
It's high net-worth individuals net worth individuals yes
In in Risky Adventures
Bill and skip
Or winning their trips the drug dealers they gain their trust they had them right where they wanted them
But at the same time Bill and Skip we're becoming more and more aware that they weren't
Fully understanding the money laundering
That they were taking
Kincardine
Like they were constantly things that didn't really make sense they pick up money off
The street and then they be told to wire it
Not to Columbia where the drug trafficker
Chris were
But to some legitimate American Business that was selling like
Tractor parts
Was all very confusing
There were a lot of smart people
Involved in bad end of it X Bankers money Brokers that have been doing this for Generations
And it was to me
The complicated system
What Billings get for uncovering
Is now called the
Black Market
Peso exchange.
The series of cleverly Disguise money transfer
Convert the drug money that was stuck in the United States
Yen to peso
Was back in Columbia
It works by hiding the money in the normal flow of trade in
Payments for things like tractor
Surveillance gif
We're nearly there they were inside this complicated Market Place
I'm close to figuring it all
Out
Until at 1 moments they came
Extremely close
To be discovered
Not by the drug traffic
But by their own people
Buy us
Bankrate
Sad to say David we don't spend a lot of time in the show talking about how Bank Regulators are doing
Job
But in this situation
They did exactly what you want Bank Regulators to
Regulators at the office of the Comptroller of the currency this
Us regulatory agency that
Deutsche Banks
They showed up with some questions about
Rhm Trust
The head of security call me up
NSAID
Come on over here the OCC is here and there auditing your account
You better get over here right now
And so I walk over there talk to the otter talk to the
Hey what are you telling me I had told him that he had to uncovered a yo
October Governor operation
Congratulations please don't tell anybody and he said
Be stopping the audit right then and there like by the time I got back to my car
I got a call from the OCC supervisor saying they were in the process of shredding
Their notes and everything else they copy but they had already notified
The OCC in Washington and Washington
The next morning was going to send a fax out to every OCC Bank in the world
How are the United States
Notifying them that rhm Trust Bank
Was not a bank
How to do transactions with
But what happened then so they're going to set up this facts about the facts
We got there in time to stop the facts and
Matmen your cover with almost blown there almost within within 24 hours we would have been in
In trouble
If we live it stopped
Rhm Trust Bank existed for a little less than a year and the drug guys
Never figured it out
And yes I killed the bank
It was success
We got we got to be a little too popular
We were being approached our informant was being approached
Poor poor other offers to do it
Illegal things
And that wasn't our Target
Getting out there asking you to do stuff you like
We were authorized to do a and b
And they're asking us to do C&D
Why can't you do send
The correct answer that question is we can't because we're actually undercover agents and we only got approval to do certain kind
Kaiser transactions with you so we can't give you a loan or whatever else you want each other
It just got to starting to be get a little bit out of hand
7 decision was made to shut the bank
By this point it had uncovered a drug Network that extended to lots of different country
Italian government particular was eager to start make
So billing skip scramble
To coordinate a massive simultaneous but
After the break
The big
But
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did you come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Just like in the movies you want to pounce on everyone all at once so one guy can't warn his friends
Hey the cops are showing
Hide
And so at a specific time it began
116 people connected to rhm Trust Bank
Four different countries
Well rested
Bill saw a video of what happened in Italy
They showed
The police precinct and they were like
2030 of these little teeny
International police cars
And all of them scream out of the
Doubt of the
The Compound at one time and they going all different directions like ants
And they didn't show The X hours later than bring it all these
Fugitives are arrested people back in but it was
It was quite
Quit heroin
What did it feel like to watch that
I was exhausted
I was exhausted was finally over with
Efficiencies 9 tons of cocaine
And more than 90 million dollars in cash
But of the over 100 people arrested
Billionaire Pablo Escobar was not in that group
He remained out there
In fact Stephenville did not bring down any of the Ring
They say what they did do
Was make the drug guys Wonder
About who they could
Usually the secrecy of the offshore world
That is a problem
For the government for guys like Bill and Skip cuz it hides all the illegal act
But this time
It hit them from the bad guy
And it hurt the drug trafficker
I know one thing they can't trust a bank now
As a result of of of what happened here they can't they have to be careful and think twice if they go to a bank
To to trust them to handle their financial transactions
Could be could be another government Bank
You guys feel like you're winning the money-laundering battle or is it
Just a matter of setting a bag for Fears and they find some other way
I think I think we were winning 20 years ago and I think we're winning today
Because a wind doesn't necessarily mean you stop it
You changed therefore the methodology for doing it
And I think that was one of the greatest successes of the bank
That we are able to
Get them off of a very sophisticated
Process
In a bulk shipment
Bulk shipping
Taking all that heavy money and physically sneaking it across the
To do that you don't need an offshore Bank
You just need a truck
The show originally aired in 2012
And if you want to see that picture of Bill and Skip celebrating their fake bank with
Sparkling apple cider you can check out our website npr.org money
And let us know what you think you can send us an email Planet Money at npr.org
And you can find us on Facebook and Twitter and Instagram we are at
Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales
Thanks for listening