Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from Better Health
Online counseling by license
Professional counselors specializing in issues including depression stress and anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com money to learn more and get 10% off your first month
This is planet money from NPR on Nick.
We are running to great shows
Was that we first ran back in 20
This is the second
On the 1st
We made it back
Against the entire American economy
It's a little hard to explain if you haven't heard the first episode
You might want to go take a listen
Today we are going to reveal
The results of that bet that Robert Smith and David kestenbaum made back in 2015
Here's the episode
If you heard the last show you know that we hear planet
Decided that we wanted to experience firsthand
What it was like to short some
Combat against
So
You probably heard about shorting you know somebody
Short individual stocks
They think are going to
Tank
We went big
We should have the entire stock market will one expert called the Armageddon
Yeah the way we put it is
We shorted America
We bet
Did the stock market would go down
It's a funny feeling listening to the news when you are short the entire stock
Cuz everyone else is good news is you're bad now
You feel like
Like you're on the opposite team is everybody else it's like being a Red Sox fan living in New York
You feel alone
It's hard to even have
Conversations about the Warhol someone's like hey
Yeah that's that's that's great that's good for you
I'm really happy
We are not alone
There are other short sellers
Relatively
Small number
And Heavens read history
Going way way way back
Today on the show
The story of one man
Who is far as we can tell
What's the very first short-seller
The very first person to bat
That an individual stock would go down
It doesn't go out
And we are going to bring to an end this little experiment of shorting stock market we will tell you how we did
Not very well
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from American Express you've got big ideas for your business but figuring
Hangout how to make them happen can be a real challenge
Well the answer may be as simple as American Express financing solution
They have over 4,000 special
Who can help find the right solution for your business
Chat with them today to see if you're eligible
So you can get your plans up and running
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Learn more at americanexpress.com business
If you haven't been reading Planet money's newsletter you're missing out on stories about hidden beaches and scooter Mania
And plastic bag ban
It's just the right amount of economics and Analysis served up once a week
Subscribe at npr.org Planet Money newsletter
The first person shooter stock was apparently this guy named Isaac Lamar
He lived
Almost 400 years ago
And his story survives because
You looked in the Netherlands and Amsterdam
And the Dutch Dutch read a lot of stuff.
Now we don't speak Dutch definitely not old 17th century
Dutch
But we got some help
My name is Laura Tatum I'm an economist and historian from the nether
Little told us there are really only barely enough scraps
Piece this whole Story 2
But from what survive
Aciclovir seems to have been a guy who when he did something
He went all the way he went really big
Princeton
Get 22 children
Which is
Quite something special if he obviously was very wealthy I mean if you if you can Sports
22 children
Y YouTube
Just a lot of money
No portraits of Lamar survive but loaded says in his mind he always imagined
A trim guy dressed in the style of the
Will clothes maybe a cape
And a very big
Wide collar
That's what it what I imagine him wearing but
What his face look like
Will never know
No references to a giant mustache run
No sorry
So that's the man
Now for the stock
The company he would eventually short
Back in those days there were not a lot of choice
The beginning of the seventeenth Century those on one stock
It was the first Star Kenosha this out
It's obvious that there was only one
That's right
The first short
Was on the very first stock
The company is one that you may remember from high school
History class
The Dutch eat
India Company
Think big Wooden Boats pirate ship like things
Who's with big sales
Making very very dangerous trip
Rough Seas to about as far as you can go from the Netherlands
All the way to what day
And remember this is the 1600s
400 years ago
People died at Sea all the time
Many ships
Didn't return
And what were they risking their lives for
Bring back
Spices
Pepper
Also nutmeg mace
Robert I remember hearing about the spice trade in history class at I didn't think much about it cuz you know
A long time ago everything always seem
But it wasn't until we did the story that I really tried to imagine a world where everyone coveted spice
Would you like hey I got some nutmeg come over I'll cook you dinner
Apparently yes
That is what it was like
It's amazing what people really like to cook a semi I see recipes from the 17th century
And they use
Huge amount of nutmeg and pepper in in recipes
He sent me a chicken recipe it does have a ton of spices seems like it would be almost inedible
That when we say that this is the first
Company
We mean the first company that resembles what we have today
A company that issues stock
So that anyone not just you know
Rich guy who built up a committee but anyone could own a small piece of the cup
If you only shared
You own a part of the Dutch East India Company
Who ships made it back
Withhold skilled at nutmeg
Pepper and mace
Are the prophets were yours
Legal details of what it meant to own one of these shares were laid out in this giant book called
Capital subscription
With the names of all the first year home
The book still exist today they told me it is so historic vet
If you went to the archives and asked to see it
They would tell him no
But it's Pages have been photographed
And we have blood work to read the very first
Okay
Also supported hanging from the nephew fancy humbling it and go messy but also the capital
The Bona Esperanza and the
Jordan stats from McAllen
Skip ahead of
Xxxii
Famous testing today Tacoma 4cly who fail had any blenders all
But this is not even one sentence
I told
Maybe this is enough I recognize the words I recognize the word Committee in it
Commerce and Esperanza Hope that's Cape of Good Hope
This book contains this
Little line
Which seems almost like it was an afterthought
Shares shares of stock
Did the Dutch East India Company
May be transferred from one person to another
And this sentence this sentence is the beginning of
For centuries
Of craziness
It is the birth
What we now call us.
At first only a few shares trade hands
But then
Catches on
And the first stock exchange just kind of naturally forms
Not a building it happens on a bridge and if this bridge in Amsterdam where Merchants gather to
Do their business they sell grain wine beer Timber
All the sudden there was this new thing that they could sell it so people gravitated to this Marketplace
And they start selling this
Abstract item that no one ever seen before
Stock
Ownership shares in a cow
There's a description from a little later in history
And how the training might have actually gone
It's from a book called confusion of confusions which is a kind of drama written about the stock market
Negotiate a price one guy would put his hands out
Thumbs up
And Shout out an offer
And if someone would shut up
A counter-offer
And then they do something which
I don't know if you see
Today in the stock market anywhere you would then
Slap the guy's hair
Shuttle buses hand-slapping eunos houses
People shouting prices and another man coming in between and
Until they
Cartoon
Agreement elaborate game of patty-cake
To be like
Had to be done
That's it
What was the traitor
Wood stand around while they're doing this may we talk about the news of
Like your England Building more ships
And that might push the share price down
Kinda like CNBC today except
Imagine if the bottom of the screen a very short
Stock ticker
Cuz there's only one there's only
Exactly
Are the first short sale
The guy windup betting against
Is it sometimes the case in stories like this the marriage started out on the other side entirely
Pbn has an Insider in fact he was one of the direct
Pictures of the Dutch East
One of the founders
And he became embroiled in some sort of dispute with the dutchie
The details are unclear Some surviving documents make it look like
It might have been over expense receipts
Lamar is one of the directors off and had to use his own money to Builder
Outfit one of the new ships
And there was some question
About some of the marriage
Something must have gone wrong
With Isaac Romero
But we don't know if it was
Oral about a lot of money or is it was just
Small amount of money
Which is a no
We do know that it was he say he was
Horse out of the Dutch East India Company
And he was also forced to sign a document
Which said that he would
He promised that he would never again be involved in any kind of Trades
With the East Indies
Sounds pretty serious for a dispute over
Receipts
Yeah but money was a serious business for the four
For these people
I think it's physical therapist about their life
Where did the Scandal spread and it began to affect
Every aspect of American Life
When is church
His church turned in
They banned him
From one of the holiest of ceremonies
Once in a year
They have like the philosopher and
Does a Camaro wasn't allowed anymore to
Participate in in in this ritual
That's a serious punishment
So this must have been upsetting for him
Basically
The Dutch East India companies calling to question is business ethics
His churches excluding him
That's right though
That was about all he had tried
Plus it's a small town and everyone knows
Everyone knows everyone
New Isaac Lamar Back Then
I mean he was one of the directions to Dutch East India Company
It must have been
Gossip in in all the inside of Amsterdam about
What happens in
What are you going to do now
What he was going to do
Would make history
And not in a good way
La Mer
Plotted his revenge
He has to plan to take down
The Dutch East India Cafe
Even better
Make money for himself at the same time
By placing
I bet that the stock price would go down
You become the world's first person to short a stock
The bed itself the short was actually fairly
Amazingly Amsterdam back then had to kind of rudimentary futures
If you wanted to bet that the price of grain was going to go down in the future you could do that
So that is basically what exactly married
Not with grain but with shares of the dutchie
Purviance nerds out there
Exactly what he
He sold Futures Contract
Guaranteeing that you could sell the stock at the current price
At a time in the future
If the stock dropped in value before then he could
Cheap cell that the price agreed to in the Futures Contract
And make money
Is it fair to call this the first short
Overstock
Oh shirt yeah yeah
Now Lemaire couldn't step out of the bridge and do this himself I mean
Remember he was a
Former director of the cup
People might figure out what he was up to
So
Get a bunch of what load will cause
Henchman go out and do it for him
And betting against something was fine
People didn't have a problem with that
It was what he did next
That really got him in trouble
His henchmen started spreading rumors
Trying to drive the stock price down
Is at things like a week we we heard a ship sunk somewhere off the coast of
Cape of Good Hope or something or
We are at that
There's a ship
And with
Hello. Pepper off the coast of Portugal right now but
But there's some leakage in the ship you know Saturday
Pepper's really bad quality
Stories like this today if these rumors were spreading around I'm sure the company would send out a press release
That is not true these rumors are unfounded or either the captain the ship would be on CNBC satellite hook
Stop going like nope
And out of the hole
Pepper's fine
The background financial information
How long would it take you if you wanted a fact check one of those rumors
We had sent ship to East Asia
That will take you 8 months and 8 months back so that 16 months in total
But of course you could try to send a letter to Portugal and end in op
But have any of the Portuguese ships heard anything in about
Isn't that rumor
Double Take a little bit last long
But
Could you trust it
Some Portuguese say information
I mean today it's like milliseconds right and back and it was months
At 6
The stock price began to draw
The Dutch East India Company knew it had to do some
It needed a show of strength that needed to reassure investors somehow the things were
So did what any company today
The Dutch East India Company said every one of its shareholders we are doing so well
We are going to give you a special bonus
They instantly
Announce
Dividends what's the first dividend of the
Dutch East India Company
What happened
I mean
It wasn't really a great dividends to shareholders of the Dutch East India Company were allowed to collect
A certain quantity of
Mace
And I want to see Senior houses in the Netherlands
Yeah yeah yeah bring your own bucket
Yeah you bring your mug of the Eyrie they had any any cash at the time
SMS at 4
What do we have
What can we
Distribute
To our shareholders in
We have a bunch of Mason let's say that they can
Collective consciousness
From us
The company also as companies today will do when they are upset with short sellers
Argues for a ban on short sale
The Dutch East India Company writes a letter
The government saying
Short Selling was hurting society's most vulnerable people
Widows and orphans
And their reasoning is that
There was a large number of
Widows and orphans who invested all their money in in the Dutch East India Company
Is that true
Well there was there were maybe
Maybe a few widows and orphans so they were back with the same sort of weapons they're fighting back with rumors and innuendo
Yeah yeah I love it
The Dutch government did Issue a partial ban on short-selling
Annie's aquamira with bar
From accessing any of the shares
His plan to short the company
Was a total failure
According to one historian Lamar and his henchman
Lost what today would be 10 or 20 million dollar
Lamar eventually left
Basically wanted to ask
And he took up residence in the small Village near
Ludwick has been there he says
It's pretty but four is a Camaro
It must have seemed Dreadful
The only surviving document known to be written by is a chimera
This letter to the mayor of a
Asking for the financial restrictions on him to be
It mentions that he's been an upstanding member of society mentioned
22 children
But as requested
Any guys
In this little
The writing on his tombstone
Kind of something else
Eli Picasa
Exactly mayor
Call Mom
Translation
Dear Liza Clemons
Merchants for more than 30 years
Blessed by the Lord
Gained a lot of money
And lost it all
Except for
Alfred
It on the house we will dance hits Indonesia who goes to Tennessee September is an existing feeling
The sad thing of course is that he was probably the only the only one who who was convinced that he actually
Kept his honor because all other people
Well fountain
Disrespectful man
Quite a thing to put on your tombstone
Xerneas
Very long
Very long also yeah yeah
Isak Lemaire shorts
Would have eventually paid off
The Dutch East India Company
Collapsed but only after a really long time
175 years later
Timing is everything
After the break will hear how Robert and David did
And they're crazy bet against America back in 2015
Scorbutus NPR Podcast in the following message come from Salesforce
Salesforce helps you deliver the Innovative personal experiences customers want
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together at salesforce.com NPR
Going on a big group trip always sounds good in theory
But it can get tricky when you get there and have it totally different expectations
Check out NPR live get new guide on navigating Group Travel
Or subscribe to like it all guys
For all our episodes all in one place
Thank you for calling etradefinancial this is human person how can I assist you today
I called back Steven Pierson E-Trade
The guy that helped the short the stock market back in January
Hey David how are you doing there
Good night to talk to you again
Yeah same here
It's been a great what is it 6 and 1/2 weeks for the stock market huh
It has been can you actually look and see how much the
Stock market has gone up since
Since we did this
Yeah let's say so
Yeah I think we're at almost almost 6%
App stock market
That correct yeah
Which is bad for us
It is bad for the trade
Alright well I think
I think it's time to end it
Alright
Well we'll get you out here we currently got
Tropicana Hotel check-out I do we had invested about $400 shorting a stock market because the stock
Market went up about 6% we lost about 6%
Which was
22 bucks
But there's more
Yeah if you added fees
Have to pay to do
The trade we lost more we lost a total of 40
$2 that would be a negative return of about 10%.
A negative return
Of 10%
In just 6 weeks
Yeah
You're fired
You are no longer a money manager
Let's give it to Stacy
Will give it to Stacey next
Was there at any point
A moment which we could have traded out of the short
And made money on the
You're the best time would have been if we'd gotten out on February 2nd at 10:06 a.m. and 2 second
The market was down a little bit then we could have made about 4 bucks
Before He Cheats
Open for free so we would have lost money no matter what
If you like the show do us a favor leave a review on Apple podcast from Planet Money
Also we need your advice we still have this investment but I have it right here
It literally still has an IOU from David kestenbaum for $406
David while we're waiting for David's money we are taking your suggestion
What should we invest in that let us know on Twitter or Facebook were also on Instagram or you can email us
Planet Money at npr.org
That we are not going to invest in Bitcoin I'm just telling you right now
Today Show was produced by Jess Jiang originally
The rerun was produced by Rachel Cohn
Thanks for listen