Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm David
And I'm Jacob
Just a quick note Today Show originally ran in 2012
The show is
The story of an innovation
That changed the way the world works
End of the man who made that Innovation possible
He was a monk
A mathematician
A magician
And possibly
The boyfriend of Leonardo.
The man was Luca pacioli and the transformative invention that he brought to the world is
Of course that did it.
Double Entry book
And Jacob when I mentioned I remember when we were doing the story
And I mentioned the Planet Money Team that we wanted to do
Show on the birth of modern accounting
Are you joking
We are not joking it is a great
This message comes
NPR sponsor sales
Today's customers want more from
Banks that are virtual Financial
Hospitals that are digital Wellness Spa
And sales
The customer relationship management solution
Help deliver those magical personalized experiences customers want
By uniting your Marketing sales Commerce service and it on an integrated CRM
Learn how Salesforce brings customers and companies together at salesforce.com
NPR
Itz 1960
B5
A white minister is murdered in
In Selma Alabama
But no one is held to
More than 50 years later we return to the place where
To call Ally Ally
And finally saw the
White Lies
What NPR
New episodes drop
Or show today is an interview with
Jane Gleeson White
But she wrote a book a few years back called
Double Entry
How the merchants of Venice
Created modern
Jane has an accounting degree
She just got obsessed
What's the first thing she pointed out to
Buses that
In order to have accounting
There really is something else
You need to have
Numbers
And when our story takes place
Is the 1400
Much of Europe is still using these Roman numerals
But you know I thought Roman numerals must have gone out the Roman Empire that night I lasted well installation
So probably Raymond your nose as any schoolchild knows if they've tried to work with them did you contact us
You have to
Adjust
That just like a written language for recording numerals
So you can't do anything with inside a of these in
Recording thing, you may as well call them into rock
That's how useful they are well
But we still do that to him
Hey Jacob think about it right say you have
Pounds of pepper and you want to write that down
You would write down and
Proceed
DX
XVI which is not useful it is really just like you are writing out
426 in words
Like f o u r h
H u n d r a
Imagine if you're writing it out of words and you want to do math with
Udo quick what's
LX
IX Plus
XVIII
I have no idea
Do you have an ending
Are you guys really complicated for merchants cuz like a son wants to buy a certain amount of peppercorns for
Or wolf how much is that going to cost that required some math
And Jane says that was a problem
With the Roman numerals I had to have what they called an abacus but it's not the soda because we can come today because it was a boy
Water signs
With pebbles on it in The Columns of the unit said that was used for the adding and subtracting so the bank has a much
Set around the squares with abacuses adding and subtracting prices and quantities
But then I had to record
The results of that
Thumbs
In Roman numerals
In a scroll
And so there was no connection between the working the mathematical working
And the results are the two things were separated
What is no Trace
All of the procedures that have gone on the 14 additional the subtraction
What does it mean on math test when they say show your work
There is no way anybody can ever show their way
That you can't show the way
Which meant that you couldn't really tell you know if
That being an era or not
But around the time merchants in Europe are picking up on something
It's being used over in the Middle East
Arabic numerals
These are one two three four five you know what we all use to
Jane mentioned
One philosopher in Europe who said Hades numerals their super powerful every every
Scholarship e-learning them
But the church actually accuse the guy of practicing magic and thin
Simple life in prison for this was like a big controversial development
Are the merchants of the numerals
We're just super super useful
It was this new way Ford
Understanding
Track what was going on in their businesses
And the center of business at the
The time in Europe
Crazy
Siding and decadent
Venice
In that day was
I think the equivalent of Silicon Valley and New York also wrapped up together everything
Was happening in Venice it was an incredibly wealthy trading center
Much is from all over the walls from England from Germany from
Holland
From the Middle East
The merchants
Set the international exchange rates
It's for the whole of Europe and Asia
So it was equivalent to Wall Street but it also is ascenta
A brand new industry
Which was the printing press
You write that it was
Smelly
There was malaria
Play again it was known as being sexually except
Yes because of the swamp
It was
Excessively stinky and they used to put incense and perfume
Around the canals to try and
Reduce the smell was probably I'm sure any minute was
I was a place of decadence excess
People had all sorts of
Strange illnesses as well as malaria in which the Physicians
Put on set sexual excess
So
What's more I give you Manhattan
Venice at this time
It has become the center of this huge
Trading Network
You know it's no longer to
Just like little Merchant selling flower to the
Things are ghetto coming on ships and they're coming in from the Middle East and going out to
England is really this
Kind of Global Hub
And trading is getting Commerce of getting much more
Complex businesses are issuing
Letters of credit
Actually shipping physic
And Merchants in Venice.
To keep track of all this
They're starting to use
A very sophisticated system of
Counting
The origins of this
Are kind of obscure it seems like the first known use of it is around 1300
But at this moment in Venice it is really starting to
At the time it was known as Venetian bookkeeping today
We call it double entry
Antifreeze Double Entry
That means that everything you do is get centered in two different places
And so
To just do an example of this say your
A spice Trader and you have
$100 in cash
$50
And you said
$10 worth of
So you write one entry in your pepper
Showing that
Now you have $10
Les pepper
And then you write another in
Cash account
Showing that now you have
$10 more in cash
Set this double-entry thing it is basically lets you see what's going on and Oliver
Find accounts and at the end of the day or the month of the year it lets you check all the
All this Plus
7 - is
They should balance out
That's the double-entry part but really
The key thing about
Double Entry bookkeeping
The bookkeeper
It's a system of precise system for keeping track of
Everything that's going on in your business
It's hard to imagine but Jane says that really did not exist
Previously
The prophet was
Weather in kind you know so you had three extra cause at the end of your.
It was obstructed into hot numbers that you can compare with other periods and runny nose
That you had
Increase your wealth by 2%
Robin by three cars which is
Beyond measure
And you can see when you
You have you don't
Currency and you have
Animal skins and you have one you have whatever I mean
If you imagine the universe where people are just keeping track of that by writing in there
Diary
What you're doing before I have this I have that I bought this I saw
So that in there to sort of writing notes all day
The end of the year would that mean you have your notebook but it's sort of a nightmare to imagine
Trying to figure out if you made money if you lost money what what parts of your business made or lost money
Yeah absolutely that was the other benefit of double-entry bookkeeping that you could Enlighten my eyes the prophets in each account so you knew which
Which Wich
Products you doing well and what she wanted
And then you can start to think about how you would change your business activities
I think it just became one of the better what most scientific
After the break
A hype man
4 Double Entry book
Support for this podcast in the following message come from wix.com
With wix
You can design your very own professional website
Choose a designer made template
And get hundreds of intuitive design
Start now by going to wix.com money to get 10% off
If you need to be reminded
We're all more connected than we realize
Skip the storycorps podcast and restore your faith in humanity
Uninterrupted conversation
What's between real people
About the things that matter most
And this season
In honor of the 50th anniversary of the Stonewall uprising
We're highlighting voices of LGBT
DQ people across America
Stories from those who lived
Before Stonewall
2 today
Episodes are available every Tuesday
Okay so now we have the numbers we have some p
Practicing what we call Modern accounting
There's one more obstacle
This big idea
It needs to get out
The rest of the world
And this is where we meet the
Survey Accidental Hero of
Horror Story the name is Luka
David earlier this year I was doing a story
Just about taxes it was Tex
Time and I was interviewing an account
And I said
Who's like the Michael Jordan or the Muhammad Ali of a cow
You know who is the greatest
And I'm thinking he's going to give me a partner at some big New York firm or some
And he says
Luca pacioli
The guy's been dead for like 500
All kinds of things
He was a monk
A magician but his
Real love with numbers
And math
Really was a man
Grows up in a small town
Makes his way
That is where he
He sees those crazy Arabic number
He's totally taken with
He's also particularly in
Ants with this fancy way
Play The Merchant
Are using them
To keep their books
He was so impressed he says it is the best
Evolve
Booking system
And in 1494
Luca pacioli places
Is Big role in his
She writes it down
60 write down how to do the double
Instructions
Examples
How many berries
Inside this big
Huge book he's writing
It's an encyclopedia of math
That clearly Luca pacioli is not
Thinking of himself as the father of account
He think of himself as this guy who
Writing an
All math known in Europe at the time and the others
Little section about accounting I mean the whole book
Giant would be like
Thousand pages are more
The title is
Suma de outage matica
Geometry
Hibachi Olney
Property on nolita
Well done David
And so this book comes out and thanks to the newly invented printing press
The great technology of its time
This giant book it can be mass-produced
Jane kissing one of the original
Yeah it's beautiful leather cover
It's so heavy you have to read it in a cradle
It's
The page has a density density written there no
No gaps
Between the letters of each word
Just run on to the next one there are no gaps between the lie it's almost impossible to read but that was how it was at the time you know.
Very very early days of printing
HR
May you know each letter
It starts a new page
Has a woodcut of Luke bachali entwined and it yet very very beautiful
A woodcut of look up a toy like me like a
Picture of him
Yeah but I'm already holding his divided as you know that's mathematical
Dividers that like come
How do you make circles with
I'll let you measure
Circles. He's holding a pair of dividers
Yes very very beautiful book
Jacob was thinking this is like one of the first coffee
I mean you buy it
Just to have it around to impress people
It had a math puzzles
Games and it had
Information on how
Painters could use math to get
Relate three-dimensional effects
Perspective
And the book was a really huge hit
What's the first readers
Public Utilities encyclopedia
Was Leonardo da Vinci
At the time he was painting what has become his most famous painting which
What's the Last Supper
Did Leonardo use it to his painting
Leonardo raisable can thanks
The coolest latest thing it is the coolest latest thing in mathematics
Takes its like the ultra
Cool mathematics text so it stay I can't imagine what that would be today
Leonardo Vinci reads it realizes that
It's really really useful for the mathematics of the Specter that he needs
To paint his masterpiece
Which is the Last Supper
So look up Charlie arrives in Milan
Wild Leonardo DaVinci
Is painting
The Lost supper to help him with the mathematics
So can we imagine is it is it
Plausible that Patchouli would have liked
Gone over to where
DaVinci was painting The Last Supper and been like no you need to do the math like this
How to draw the lines like that
Yeah totally that were hanging out together they hung out to you know that live together often I left Milan
It's very possible that I would love it
Because they buy and I've had
Bisexual tendencies
Play suddenly spend more time together and definitely
Look up Charlie was there in the actual Church
When Leonardo da Vinci
Was painting The Last Supper and he was very moved by
Okay so this book maybe it helped
At the Last Supper but also of great
Historical significance
What Patchouli is known for today
A different little part of the book
Volume 1 chapter 9 part 11
The section about double and
In the Italian
It is
Kohl's
Particular State computers a scriptures
And it looks as it but the way that it's put into the book
It looks as if it was something he added at the last minute for his Patron
So that his patrons
Citizens could keep their accounts properly and become wealthy merchants
And one of the first things he writes is like you have to
Merchants you have to
Do an inventory after know what you own and he gives us example of a
Typical Venetian Merchant
Who has to the golden coin cases of Ginger Saxon pepper packages of cinnamon and clove Sandalwood
Boxing shamis
Skins Bank.
If you want something really the whole double enter
Yeah
Yeah he shows them exactly how to do it from the beginning so he as you said he wasn't through the whole thing he imagines that
I have never had an account before
And so the very first thing you do when you like me your books
Is taking Infantry
And that becomes your capital
So that is all your wealth
And as anyone knows if a tree's is still in central part of Ryan company
Luca pacioli publishes this book and
It's sort of an instant headache
Abroad and people start to
People read that chapter and they they start to use double entry bookkeeping is that what happens
Yeah so what happens is not funny
Does agar Broad and I read that chapter but that chapter was extracted and turned into a volume of that sign
So not long after he published his book
The Venetian Empire crumbled
And the new Center of Trade
Was what went to Germany and then to Holland
Soaz
The centers of trade spread so this new technique was adopted by the merchants in the local
Regions
So you can see
That this one tiny
Mechanism that was
Invented initially and codified by Luke
Patrolling 1494
Spread gradually across the world and by 1900
It had it was the basis of business
Across the planet
Which is pretty extraordinary
What do you think
Luca pacioli would think of
The world today
And double entry bookkeeping
Keeping everywhere not just in every business you know whenever anyone buys a business
Show me your books
You know she if you have if you have enough you if your stock is sold publicly you have to
You know basically show your book
A bunch of times a year
But also for countries you know countries keep track of their entire economies basically through Double Entry bookkeeping
What would he think
I think you'd be absolutely astonished I mean
You know he he as a as an aside
Codified and published
27 page
Locating tradus in his beloved mathematical encyclopedia
And to think that that
What had gone on to become
The
The governing system of every economy on Earth and every called Corporation every business
He would be astonished when he he keep falling backwards nothing
Jane writes that the last record we have of Luca pacioli is in 1514 when he took
Good job as a math professor at the University of Rome
He died a few years later probably in 1517
He was 72 years old you can see a painting of Luca pacioli
Billy and a photo of his huge
Beautiful
Math book
On our block npr.org money will also put up a link to Jane Gleason White's book is called double entry how the merch
Venice created modern fine
I love doing history shows if there is some great moment or person from the history of Economics or Finance
That we have not done a show about
Please
Helles
Can do a show about it you can email us at Planet Money at npr.org you can find us on Facebook or
Twitter or Instagram
Also have a great new email newsletter you can sign up for that at
Npr.org
Splash Planet Money newsletter I'm Jacob Goldstein
Thanks for listen