Sarah Johnston's brother was huh
That's how all this
Started
Last fall she was driving her brother home after minor leg surgery
. they pass this strip mall
And her brother spots
The Jamba Juice
Can we pull in there and get some Jamba Juice
That sounds so good
Parking lots
We park right in front of Jamba Juice
They get their Jamba
And then her brothers
Cease a Jimmy John
And he's like
Can we also get sandwiches
The Jamba Juice and the Jimmy John's are in the same parking lot but they're owned by different
People
Jimmy John's is in a separate building in the corner of the lot
Cordoned off
This is barrier like a chain
Separating
Vista parking lot wearing from the Jimmy John
I have a picture of this chain
It's thick
And Metal
Looks like a giant industrial version of those velvet ropes you see it red carpets
Except this one is covered in yellow rubber not velvet
And write down the chain there these shoots signs every 6 feet or so that say
No parking
Jimmy John's
Park on the street or in our parking lot
So the side of the parking lot
Did Sarah is in
Is not for Jimmy John's cut
But like
Who Among Us would actually move our cars in the
List of recently
The Jamba Juice is just
Right next door they're already parked
So Sarah and her brother just
Step over the chain and get their Jimmy John's sandwich
Their hobbling back to the car her brothers on crutches
Recetas bright yellow boots
Stuck on
My truck tire
The thing they immobilize your car tires
And
Immediately just look around the parking lot like wow like
They were only in the Jimmy John's for 17 minutes
She showed me the receipt
My brother
Still on narcotics
He starts
Yelling and a to put this on here where are you come talk to me
And there's a guy
Starting to get into a
Black sedan
The guy walks over to them and says
If you want that boot off you have to give me
$75
Because this is Jamba Juice parking only
And they pull other Jamba Juice Shake
We were one of those
We haven't even drink them yet they're still slushy
And he says
You were Jamba Juice customers
Till you cross
Into the island of Jimmy John
The moment
Jimmy John's furnaces
You're no longer a cuss
What
So at this point the Jamba Juice employees come out and tell the guy they are our customers
Please take the boot off
Their vehicle she says no the boot stays on
Jamba Juice appears to have no power here they apparently did not hire this guy
And now serious like weight
What is happening here
If Jamba Juice doesn't want this guy booting people why is he there
But Sarah's brother is
Is fresh from sir
Still has ice pack strapped his leg
She's afraid
To push this anyway
So she pays and drives away Furious
And then she did what anybody should do if they stumble upon a mystery
You should email us
Planet Money NPR. Org
Is this legit
This is what your
Who is this parking guy is he with the government
Is he a vigilante
Is this even legal
Sarah
We are on
Hijab
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I Am Karen Duffy
There is something about parking that just leads
Conflict
It brings out the worst
Today on the show
The parking lot Wars
We solve the mystery of the Jimmy John's parking lot vigilante and learn something about parking lots everywhere
Annex you're going to hit the road and find a couple more parking story I've heard a rumor that there's a straight-up
Conspiracy going down in a parking lot just outside
Definition of capital
And we have the story of a Michigan lawyer who's trying to overturn hundreds of millions of dollars in parking tickets
With the Constitution
Support for NPR and the following message come from luminary
The only place you can listen to the new podcast
Fiasco
From Leon neyfakh
The co-creator of Slow Burn
In season 1
Leon transports listeners into the
Contested 2000 presidential election
And the legal battle that followed in Florida
Listen to Fiasco
Weather original pod
Only a luminary
Visit luminary. Link / money for your first two months of luminaries premium content
Free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
I'm Gregory water
On rough translation we follow a Rescue Mission in real time
After Nawrocki photojournalist goes missing on the front lines we don't believe it I don't believe it
Lisa's family and his friends
Try to save it
When he said who is this what who are you they respond we are the Islamic
From NPR's rough translation
Listen And subscribe
I have been looking into
There is Mystery
For an amount
The time that I am too embarrassed to tell you but
I have become a little obsessed with this strip mall in Salt Lake
It's called the 4th South Market
And the first thing I wanted to do of course was talk directly to the guy in the mysterious black
I'm actually from Salt Lake I was born there so I dispatched someone I know there too
Takase 4th South Market parking
Plans this weekend
This is my friend Laura Stevens
She drives in and she parked by Jamba Juice like Sarah
She walks slowly towards Jimmy John's
Okay
Trying to lower the parking vigilante out of his sedan
I'm going to sneak under that chain
As if I'm going to Jamaica
He does not take the bait but
She does get us a clue
Surly 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
Peyton Einstein
CJ's customer parking
Jimmy John's parking
The bottom of the sign there is a
Phone number
And the name
Parking Solutions
If you're calling because your vehicle has been immobilized
Please press 1
Please hold while I try to connect you
I looked them up they have an F rating from the Better Business Bureau and a trail of lawsuits
Hey there my name is Karen Duffin I'm a reporter at night they would not go on the record with me
It would not tell me who hired them
Suit this is when my obsession really kicked in I started calling
Anyone in Salt Lake City
Planning Public Services
Might have anything to do with parking
Streets department
Zoning building that I can just
Someone sent me two corporations
Public Services
Hi Lorna this is
Karen this is Lauren about she oversees the parking division in Salt Lake
And she is very familiar with this strip mall
Yep I know the one I have the same experience
Really we're just the guy in every individual unmarked car that got me I asked her to city do this kind of Buddha
She was almost offended by the question
I mean we can't just take your property
Free from you and it's a city tickets you or boots you you can contest it
But it's not
Clear who you appeal to in the Jamba Juice Park
Which leaves me with
One final question
Is this legal
Okay to question
If it is
What
I called the Salt Lake City Police Department
They too are very familiar with this parking lot
Yeah it is
It happens very often
This is detective Greg wilken
And he says
Yes what is happening in that parking lot is legal
Because that parking lot is on private property
What we're dealing with is
Private property
And the businesses they
They have the right
Or boot your vehicle
Especially if it's supposed to
He says unless a crime is committed there is nothing the police can do
There's very few things that can be in
On private property
Like if you're in a mall parking lot and you run a stop sign
Greg
He can't pull you over
Thermo cups can but Greg
Octonauts
So
If you are Sarah standing in that Jamba Juice parking lot your only recourse
Is to sue the parking company
For $75
Which is just high enough a price that you are angry
And just low enough
That a single customer probably won't Sue
But there is one company that has a lot of customers that are being booted and that is of course Jimmy John's
So it seems like they have the most incentive of anyone to solve this
I called them up
You just keep getting bombarded with
Customer complaint this is Robert Madsen
The CFO of a development company that owns this Jimmy Choo
John's
He says he gets a handful of calls about this every week
Is a big problem for the
And I can't analyze all of their 1-star reviews
Of the people that left a message about why they're giving a one-star review 68% were related to a boot
Wow
Robert told me that
4 years there was peace
In the fourth south parking lot you could park anywhere you want it
But then one day
The owner of the strip mall set up those chains
And he hired that sneaky Boudoir guy
And Robert told me that this has become such a problem they have hired someone
Not to make sandwiches
But to stand outside
By that chain all day long
Just to say
No no no trust me you do not want to cross that line
He says
They've stopped 820 people from parking in the wrong parking lot in just the past six
They spend nearly $30,000 on security and this parking monitor more than 10% of what that story even earns
Deniers
And Robert estimates that Parking Solutions the company that is
Is doing all of this building
If they get nearly $200,000 in Boots
A year on Justice parking lot alone
They would not confirm this
With me but Robert says
The Parking Solutions guy told him
That they split 50/50 with the strip mall landlord
It's like the owners of this parking lot have found this
Petty loophole in parking lot
Are there any parking lot owner anywhere could take advantage of
It means
Feel like public property
You're in a parking lot not inside of it
Steven looks like public property theirs
Painted lines even stop sign sometimes
So it feels like a place where the normal rules apply
But
The moment you step into a private parking lot
You have stepped
Into the Wild West
Where the rules
Are whatever they say they are
Hello Nick fountain
Well I was calling every bureaucrat in Salt Lake City
You are off chasing a different parking lot story
All you told me is that
You would call me when you got to a parking lot
So tell me where are you calling
Okay if you leave
Washington National Airport
And you take
The free hotel shuttle to the closest Holiday Inn
And you walk just 50 feet down
History
You will get to a parking lot
That's where I am right now I can hear the cars
Vlad is over
And I'm here because
I heard that in this parking lot Uber drivers
R gaming this
Okay alright I'm parking lot based mystery I'm in Uber drivers
Really didn't want to be recorded talking about this
Nobody nobody want to speak English
Okay I don't need a record
I'll turn it off
But I spent the afternoon talking to drivers about
What it's like
To work for Uber around here and they told me basically the same story that you hear from every overdriver mainly
It's really hard there barely making any money
Especially when you consider the wear-and-tear they're putting on cars but they told me
The one place there's sometimes making money
Is the surge I hate The Surge the surge is when there's like
A limited supply of the drivers there's lots
Septum and
Rainstorm happens and you like you're dying and you want to get out of the rain and you look at Uber and all the sudden
3 times more
Uber jacks up the price to encourage more drivers
To come out yes I do hate the surge
And here in this little parking lot
It's not just
Strictly supply and demand
Some guy that I talked to told me
Sometimes
They are manipulating the system
What
Here's how
Babies apps to tell them
When a big search is about to come when a bunch of planes are going to land
And they'll sit in their cars and they won't log into the app
Until one of their Buddy says
The Surge is getting higher the surges getting hired don't get on don't get on
Okay now everybody go on the surge is really high
Let's all go make some
What's so they're basically like
Manufacturing scarcity
Text creator
Search
Like it's not an act of God like
It started raining it's like a
Bunch of Uber drivers in a parking lot
Decided not to sign into their app
And I asked them like
Does this make you feel bad cuz you're
Going over people like me who use the app and then like
I don't know man take the subway wait a little bit
Or
Realize that we're not getting paid a lot right and
I should say that I learned about this from a local ABC News 4
And a lot of these guys were super pissed about that news report
Because
A few things happened after that
Some of them got fired by Uber or kicked off the app
Now there's a police officer who like
Patrols the parking lot and gives people tickets
If they're not
On their app
AKA they're trying to get the surge go up some guy actually showed me his ticket
And
Uber has capped The Surge at $10
A ride so they're really mad about that you can get it
Ticket from the cops
If you're not on your app
It's weird but it's a parking lot owned by the airport
These are airport code
This is a private
Parking lot n
We have learned in a private parking lot you get to make whatever Wild West
Exactly
End
This is a super
Interesting parking lot do you have some existential thoughts while inhaling
Car fumes in the parking lot
I did
Here's what I think
We are in this economy that
More and more is becoming itemized right we're in the gig economy and all these men and women who have these jobs
Barely get to meet each other and get to talk about their work
Conditions
But
One place where all these Uber drivers
Meetup would be
The airport parking lot
It's like the water cooler of the Uber
Driving proud it's the water cooler of the gig economy it's the factory floor of arm
Modern Age and of course the first active
Collective action
Of the gig economy that I've really heard about
Would come out of here
That makes sense actually
Yeah I should get off the phone cuz there's a bunch of guys praying right next to me I'll see you back up in New York
Okay alright safe travels
After the break
We meet the lawyer who is trying to overturn hundreds of millions of dollars in parking ticket
This message comes from NPR sponsor KPMG revolutionize your Enterprise with a i
KPMG can help you harness the power of AI to unlock its potential and deliver growth
More
Read. KPMG
. us
Flash NPR
Podcast the indicator it is a Daily Show about business and economics and it is
Ben 10 minutes
I'm Stacey Vanek Smith co-host
Stop the show and this week we take a look at
How Japan is setting an example with it
Monetary policy what Facebook stands to gain from launching its own
Cryptocurrency and why the US Women's Soccer Team is doing
For equal pay
Find out on the indicator
From Planet Money
Nick Fountain your back
Yep got an Amtrak did some audio editing and here I am
30 seconds later
You're just in time for our last story which
She's also about parking but this one has to do with the country
The story starts in
Two hour parking spot
Outside the courthouse
Saginaw
Michigan
A lawyer named Mac Rhonda was sitting in
Ford F-150 taking some calls
Well I'm on the road quite a bit so I mean I think
I myself like most lawyers have
Quite a few conversations in their vehicle
He was on the phone with Phil Ellison another lawyer
They work together a lot on class
Actions they like to sue the government on behalf of a bunch of people with hope that they will get monetary damages
And while he was talking to Phil
She noticed
Is rear view mirror
Someone walking up
I saw the meter maid
In all kind of a protein at the side street marking everyone's Tire
With their Tire wand
You know these things like when you park in a 2-hour parking spot parking enforcement officers will
Go around the parking lot and Mark everyone's
Tires with chalk
And I'm going to come back 2 hours later if
If the check is
Still in the same place
You got a ticket
Looking at this happening behind him
Parking enforcement officer
Closer Chuck
Nexcar Chuck
Next car
Chuck the thought had occurred to me when she was about three or four cars behind me
Imma just pop into my head
Sitting there in his truck mat thanks weight
Did I just witness a violation of the Fourth Amendment of the Constitution
Institution which protects us against unreasonable searches and seizures
I literally blurted out is this a search
It's such a lawyer question
There was a lawyer question you know we we analyze the world a little bit differently than the average person
Play Matt's lawyer friend Phil on the phone
Says
He could have pause for a second and sitting in the next thing out of his mouth was
Yeah that's actually a good question
So they start looking into it
And they find a Supreme Court case from 2000
In that particular case the court was looking at whether the government needed a warrant to attach a GPS tracker to your car
The question was
Is the government trespassing
Like if the feds going to your house against your will without a warrant
That is an unreasonable
So how about your car
And the justice is God
Really worked up over this question
Here's Chief Justice John Roberts
Grilling the governor
Women's lawyer
If you
Put a GPS device on
All of our cars
Monitored arm movements for a month
You think you're entitled to do that under your theory
Are the justices of Discord
Yes
Under our Theory and under this Court's cases
The justices of this court when driving on public roadways have no greater expectation your answer is yes no
Problem on the coast
Equally
Needless to say the government lost
Very bad
The Supreme Court said
Attaching a GPS to your car
Does count as a search
So the government needs to go to war
Before they do that
So I didn't feel are looking at this and thinking we might just have a case
Drawing a chalk line on your tire to
Pacu is
Kinda like sticking a GPS on your
Define plaintiff
Someone who's got a
714 tickets
And they decide to sue the city of Saginaw
And
The parking enforcement officer that Matt calls quote
One of the most
Efficient government employees that has
Ever
So there is actually three enforcement officers although this particular lady who is the defendant in our suit
Hodgkins
She writes
Well over 95% of the tickets
Did she have the same job
As to other people and she's running
Circles around
Correct
If this if this parking enforcement thing goes south for her
We reached out to Saginaw as lawyer they did not
Soap Manville
File their loss
They argue chalking your car is a violation of the
The 4th amendment
It
Is an unreasonable search
Where it goes from there is a little bit technical but basically
This week a federal court weighed in and said
This case has Merit
Let's send it to trial so
Arguments over this
Chalk question will begin soon
It just seems so small
You know
But is it really that small
I mean you're talking
Nationwide
Now you're talkin tens of millions if not hundreds of millions of dollars
End in fines that are being posed on citizen
Something really is it
I mean I guess
Washes off
Yeah I mean the chocolate self yes
To be clear
Is Matt wins he wants to force little towns and cities across the country to refund all those billions of dollars in parking
And he hopes
Pay him that's what he stands to gain
But he also says
This is not a frivolous lawsuit
This is about privacy and which government actions were protected again
If you imagine that protection like a bubble around someone
That dude that's your safe Zone and if the government wants to get in that bubble they have to have a warrant
How big that bubble is
Is always chain
The bubble can shrink
That bubble can expand
And
When excitement is in these kind of cases is right on the edge of the bubble
Is the bubble going to go out in this case or is it going to retract in the
Is casein in in the Fourth Amendment protections are going to become smaller
Or I guess the third option is
Traffic enforcement officers just will chalk around the tire and not on a
So be at least they're within the bounds of the law
Matt says he cannot believe how much people seem to care about
Parking
Of all the cases he's done and he's done things about much bigger issue
None of them have come close to getting this much attention
And with this with Tire talking to Something in almost everyone has had
Some sort of experience with
Only thing I could I can pardon the pain but you not going to talk all the interest up to
Ideas for
Email at Planet Money at npr.org we cannot settle your truck
If you enjoyed listening to this episode maybe you have a friend who might also enjoy it at that little share button send
Send it to them
Free presents
Play show with produced by Sally Helm and Rachel Cohn
Our editor is Brian urstadt
And a supervising producer is Alex Goldberg
Plug time caring you just worked on an amazing two-part series for the podcast
Rough translation give us a little preview
It is about a photographer in Iraq who gets kidnapped by ISIS we followed it for 4 years
Have all kinds of crazy on-the-ground tape part 2
Timeout this week can't wait to listen to podcast is called The Rock translation
Unaccounted I'm Karen Duffin this is NPR thanks for the
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org