Hey it's Allie home
Sure is something
Suspicious
Dubai products
Your cell phone could be
Washing machine
And it works
Just fine until
Right after the warranty expires
Now you got to buy a whole new one
And you feel like
Did the company
Land for it to break
Right then
There's a term that gets hot around about this
Planned obsolescence
And I'm looking into this for Planet Money
I realized
It's really a hysteresis
2 history
Three stories in one
End
We have a new podcast. NPR that takes history stories
And make something
Vivid and related to things that are happening today
Call through line
It's hosted by run data and RAM teen Arab Louie
So
Talked them about my idea and
We
Teamed up on this episode
Today's episode is a sample of through line
And a story about how planned obsolescence
Began and
Spread
And how it kind of explains a huge part of the economy today
Run
Brompton
I'm going to start the story in the 1990s
In Germany
With us
Small group of
Book nerd
And they were nerds about one bucket
By Thomas pynchon
Thomas pynchon
Is Rainbow Comics terrifying incident
It faces The Odyssey of the anti-hero
Stationed in London during World War II
Language
Explicit descriptions of sex
Do you guys know this book
I don't like one of those cult classic books
It's like 700 pages long
Paranoid has like you know technical details about rocket science
Gravity's rainbow with something like
The Bible for circle of friends so we're really delving into the history of the noble and
Everett absolutely fascinated by the fiction that's Marcus
He and two of his friends were obsessed with this one book in particular because
They were all sort of technically minded people
What is the machine gun Marcus had studied the Dewey Decimal System so you don't machines
Systems conspiracy theories the same sort of thing that pension was right about
So this book was grateful for intense discussions drinking tea together
Smoking dope together a trip to the countryside together spending the whole weekend talking about
Light bulbs with in beautiful nature they would spend the whole weekend talking about light bulbs
Light bulbs story within the story of gravity's rainbow
Did they were really intrigued by a small history of an eternal
Light bulb called Byron the bulb in eternal light bulb
Perfectly build so it cannot just die its Eternal in the book
Is conscious and he knows that he is going to live forever but he also knows
That there is a group of people out there who are trying to get him it is a group of light bulbs
Packers called Feebas know that obviously
Sophie learns about Byron and
Try to destroy him clearly fiction once you're familiar with
You know that
Could only
Fiction books
It's very much based on fact
So the history of the Eternal Light Bulbs sounds like
Pure Fantasy
But if you dig a little bit into history
It turns out that pinching hat
Sources
So
That is what they talked about.
Which parts of this
Totally farfetch
Seeming story
Might actually be true
And he started asking solve this question
Could there be a light bulb that could live forever
I'm going to say no
Really
Because
Recall that this is
Podcast
And I am forced to reveal at this moment but in fact there is a light bulb
That lives forever
At least
I mean almost forever forever as it's been burning since 1901
Which is almost a hundred and eight
18 years
And
I went out to Livermore California to meet it
Battery repair
Shut the light bulb
I thought you flew across the country to look at
Oappl
I flew across the country to see a light bulb to interview a lightbulb
I talked to Tom brammell
Hyzaar
Retired Deputy fire chief
Anna Livermore
Fire station
This is a hand blown bulb
And when it was manufactured there was a secret formula that they used
On the carbon filament
Secret formula
Which is still Secret
Today
This bulb has been burning continuously
18 years so
Obviously no one has broken it open to figure out what
Exactly is going on
We do know that there is
Carbon involved
The carbon filament was so hard they said it would reach this
The density of a diamond
What kind of magical light bulb
Last for more than a hundred years yeah I'm
Has lasted for so long
And I literally have a lightbulb in my bathroom that we put in 6 months ago when we moved in
How do we go from
The eternal light bulb
To run deadline
I mean
Light bulb business
Actually
Soap
In 1879 Thomas Edison
This is what is
Is the first
Commercially viable light
Light bulb and
By 1901 when this long last
Bulb burst
Turns on
The light bulb market
Is booming
Companies are innovating
And there are lots of little light bulb manufacturer
I'll try to make the best light bulb that they
So that's kind of like the
The first link
In the Pinta
10 story
Because there was this
. where companies were making
Very
Durable
Light bulbs
Allah Byron the Everlasting
So that is step one
Now
Marcus goes looking for the next
Lincoln
He wants to find
The people out to get Byron
Exactly
PCS the name Phoebus
Is come up in a few places like
Like it's in this one book
But then one of Marcus's
Just friends
Has an idea
Why don't you check out the archives of osram
Which was the biggest light bulb manufacturer in Germany
And there was a huge
Trove of documents
Right there in Berlin
Marcus go searching archive system you can see who was reading the files before
Who discovered that nobody has
Files for decades
W 1st
Joseph
Through those
Original documents which is
Trimming and
Document after document
There it is
The Phoebus
Cartel cartoon named Phoebe
Phoebus cartel
Eating to make long-lasting bulbs things have changed
The market has gotten really Consolidated and they're a bunch of big light bulbs companies that are basically controller
Company Delon was governing the whole Market in France and Hungary.
General Electric had a branch for the UK was wrong was in German
That of course is more less Paradise
For an industry
If you have no computer to sad all you can do everything with the consumers because they totally
Imagine
The early 1920s
You're looking at a map of the world you could go through and write the name of a lightbulb monopolist
The countries that they control they all have their territory which is great for them
Pixar perfect in fact 1923 at least in particular for that German company off
Pretty bad here for sales
I'm head of Austrian is this guy named William meinhardt
You decide
A whole crew together
All the monopolists in all the different countries
In order to rule the whole world
Off the production of lightbulb
It's late December
Couple days before Christmas
In Geneva Switzerland
Christmas we can buy some candles flicker in the windows
Dunedin secret it's a short meeting because they've sort of already been ciatica the plan already
By the time I mean
That's if I would
Able to find it
Amanda Bynes in busan
Purpose of a stronger Corporation
Especially in order to avoid
The conflict
Because of competition
And in order to increase
They are forming
Cartel a secret group
To control the market
The Phoebus cartel
V
So the name Phoebus comes
From the Greek God of Light
Also known as Apollo
You know as these gods of light
They divided up
Who electrified
World
Really boils down
To this one essential
Restriction that they put in
Agreed on exactly 1000 hours we intentionally have to reduce the koala
Party of the Lambs
In order to increase sales
Biggest light bulb companies
As part of their mission to sell more light bulbs
Have conspired
To make
Their products
Horse
So you have to buy more
What
They all pledged
To do this
Yeah
They decide
We are going to reduce
The lifespan of light bulb from
Where was hovering witch
Around 2000 hours
The Divide
We are going to get it down
2 1
Thousand
Hours
How do you even do that
Experiment
Materials are like changing the
The filament
I mean you have to imagine that for a long time at the engineer that is
Companies were
Trying to make light bulbs
Better
And what Marcus is in somebody's documents is
Engineer's
Comparing notes
Going against
Alder training
Now
Trying to make
Products
Worse
It actually took a few years after the agreement was signed
Before they were even it
Technologically able to make the light bulb as bad as I wanted it to
So they figured out how to make the light bulb
Yeah totally they break a light bulb
Also obviously like it's hard to sort of get
Everyone
Around the world
To do this
Because I mean think about it so in a cartel
In any cartel
You cheat
That might be good for you and bad for everyone else in the
Lockhart alright like if one person makes about a lightbulb
Tickets are to take over
And the Phoebus cartel
Knows this
So is that a system that basically ensures that
People are following the rules
They have
Light bulb
Testing rooms
Like in a library
Bookshelves
Pat Roberts books
You have
Plugins
4 light bulbs I seen a picture of this
China magical looking there's a guy in a lab coat looking thing standing in front of
Glowing Rose and all the light bulbs
Are numbered
And they are burning and the cartel has
Fine
For the fiscal year 1929
They have
Penalties
With 300
4000 Swiss Francs
Which is quite a lot considering the late 1920s
Of the lifespan of light bulbs around the world during this. And the lifespan just goes down and down
Epices plan
Is working
So they were able to get down to
2000 hours
Did that translate into more profit
More Revenue
Yep sales were growing up they were telling more light bulbs
Anti-corruption like it's kind of impressive.
Wondering
There any upside for consumers
I thought this was really a
Marcus says
Feebas help move us toward
A more Unified
System
He told me the reason that there is
One kind of in can.
Light bulb
Thread
That screws into one
End of socket
That that is partly to
What's a fetus
Because they did this big coordination and it end up coordinating.
Accusing topic
So
First of all General Electric
American
They were involved in the
Car towing service
Waze through their
Diddy Riese
But they didn't have the legal trouble in the United
Dates for Aladdin
Practices
And there's a judgement against them in 19
In the court opinion
A bunch of information about Feebas actually comes out
There's no we know for sure but
This might be
We're Thomas pynchon God is in
Inspiration
But the real sword of death now
For the cartel was
World War
And it's for sort of obvious
Global cooperation among these Powers was impossible because
They were at war with
But I should be clear that for years they did succeed at this whole planned obsolescence
They made their product
Worst in order to make more money
So are we at the end
Well
As the end of this
But
As I mentioned there are two
I came across another story from this
Sam darnold
Where
Obsolescence
Changes shape
And takes on
And even more in
Phidias
Forum
After the break the Dark Art of a different obsolescence
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Sitcom from Madewell
Where the motto is
Is good day start
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts
Premium.
Then offers men's and women's Style
House for seriously ever
Also you can recycle any brand of
Madewell
And they'll give you $20 off a nuke
They work with the blue jeans go green frog
Paterno
Housing Authority
Communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit stop by a Madewell store
Or go to Madewell.
OKC
So you have
Another obsolescence story for us
Yes I do
This one takes place right out in the open
End
Changed my whole sense of who the villain is behind plan.
Desiree charts
Around the same time that the light bulb story does at
Turn
Of the 20th century
Light bulbs are getting more popular in the US
And so are
Automobiles
One Automobile in
If you went by a car in the United States you find a lot
Full of black Model Tees that all look at almost exactly the same Henry Ford said you could have it in any
Color as long as it's black this is Giles Slade he's the author of made to break technology an ocelot
Puffins in America
Okay so it's not the most glamorous right but what do you get when you by Henry Ford's Model T
I mean you can think of it as basically like a replacement for your horse the Driving Experience
Texas really like driving a tractor through a field these machines are very popular but this
Just like fire Machinery they're not very
Luxurious like tractors the way model T's were made and marketed
They were geared towards men
Here we go
Another man but his name is Alfred p
Sloan's Honda
Guy right there in PR
Diane
Full disclosure. Foundation is one of Planet Money Finance
Supporters
Like Henry Ford
Blown is an electrical engineer
He graduate from MIT in 1895
And he becomes this
Serious
Single-minded businessman
Wondering what you wrote about him made this list of his character traits including
Works every hour
Has no Hobbies
Never reads
Never drinks
Never tell stories
Sounds like
Cold front
You want take this outside right now
Phone genius so you know I don't know baby.
In one of his first jobs Sloan basically
We saved
A failing company
And by 1918
Keys copy II
General
Motors
GM is
Meaning of failing but struct
Because
The carpus is half of 19
Henry Ford has already sold the car till like
Many of the people who would want to buy one
So why would they buy a car
Don't have some ideas
First stop
He introduced
Different make
A Luxury Line
What kind of Premium line
Middle-class line
Four door sedans for families
And then an economy line
The very cheap you know 1923 Chevy
All American
Chevrolet
Wonder what the new Chevrolet is going to be like
A knife of the new ones are going to
This is a
And then just looking at the data on who is
Is buying things
Not necessarily cars just stinks
Marketing and advertising firms that began the first real demographic research in the teens
And what they discovered around 1920
Was the women were actually spending the family money making 85% of all purchases
Model T was plain simple and
Made for men to Sloane realized
He could sell more by doing a lot of things that Henry Ford would never think of doing it like
Making a much more comfortable experience to start and ride in a car
And also making it much more to start experience by you know having different color cards
Colors
Was huge because before this car is recovered in a lacquer
But just like did not hold colors all that well Legos
Black Fade to Yellow it was not really working the black was the most practical most permanent
1920s
This company Dupont which was an investor in GM they sent a fortunate trying to create durable color
Word means and in 1923 they succeeded in the next few years as Sloan
Rolled out new models and don't women they were all day
Same paint breakthrough actually also leads to nail polish as we know it
Nail polish in carpet
We're the same thing but yes
Discolored
I mean this is she is wondering
Can I sell the same basic machine
Just in a radically different package we make the superficial things the key things of the past
The fins on the back of betta radio new upholstered
All the sorts of accessories the kind of what would have been considered
Frivolous things they become essential that we won
The consumer to buy a new car every year
Gottschalk ready author of the book the deals that made the world
Overtime GM tries out different looks they lower the cars body
They elongate the hood it has crazy curve
Billy change the engine but eventually you can get the car in blue
Or red or green
Hello Alfred Sloan gets into our heads
And stays there or gray or beige
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining
I offering accounts with no fees or min
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 mins
Capital One
What's in Uruguay
Na
PR news
Okay so at this point
Blown is busy making cars
Sexy
But they weren't like
Breaking the car
This wasn't it
Feebas
None of the cars work
It's just that they were
Obsolescence psychologically
Obsolescence
In the sense of
Fashion
So it would seem
Radically
Date by year 3
Giving all the new models
So am I 1927
Henry Ford
Was forced to stop production of this Maltese
And revamp his entire Manufacturing
Processing come up
With another model
The Woodland compete with General Motors product until he came up with a new Ford Model A
Not only work for so long and eventually he was forced to bring out two different lines in different colors in face
Copy GN
Who won the consumer report
Chevrolet must have a new advertising
Awesome that will empower people to act
I bought one
Sloan by assuring in a whole new style of warfare
Psychological obsolescence
Which made the consumer wants to buy something new even if they didn't necessarily need
Was actually one of the first big businessmen to use the word consumer and
She realized
Consumers one thing cops they don't want things
Quickly enough
We could make them want something the newest new thing a little faster
The idea of obsolescence for something done to an object to something we ourselves we choose what we want
That was key that's not Freddy again and he says
Moon was like this
Psychological
He was figuring out all these new ways
Thoroughly
Get inside our heads
It's the one you bought the Chevrolet Bel Air
It came
Wiz
A catalog
The new one
It was going to be coming out
Set at the very moment Apache
They've built in a chip you know inside your head
Actually
This isn't going to be very good
Because you're going to want
This new one
But even back
Answer this a kind of built-in disappointment
With the moments
The purchase I think psychological obsolescence
Fashion
Depends on
Disappointing
And that was intention
And that was what Sloane's genius was
Giles Slade says
The last part of
The psychology
In psychological obsolesce
How to do a something that marketers and
An advertising writer
Began doing in the night
Selling products
Gaston Pride
And she
I mean I get that like a new car
Was
Something
You can be proud of you.
Driving down the street in an old beat-up one was
Something that you know you might be a little bit of
Yeah that's exactly it
Annies Sloan
Take these new ideas from advertising
And build those psychological
Triggers
Into the
The products
Themselves
Emacs
Each new car
More desirable than the last
And this is what you see with the iPhone today
DIY
We have arrived at the iPhone
Okay run Franti
When I tell someone that I'm
Story about planets
They almost always say sorry about that
So
We'll talk about it
The battery
So maybe you heard about this
Conspiracy theory
Controversy
In 2017 iPhone users were noticing that
After they had updated their software
Their phones started
To slow down
What does Prost
Supposed to make your phone better and some people felt like it was making
So people started yelling at Apple about this
And apple said
We're actually doing this for your own good
We're not bringing the phone we're not trying to shorten its lifespan
But if we slow down some older phones
They don't crash it
We're sorry we didn't mention it
And apple offers a
A cheap battery replacement
Sweeten the apology
Well I mean
Kind of sounds like
Planned obsolescence modern-day fever
I mean
Look Apple totally denies that they were doing this
Aster drive upgrade
But if you believe that Apple slow down older phones in order to make
People by X
New phone
10 job that would be a perfect
Example of plane.
Everything is we don't really know if that's
There's a lawsuit about this right now
Also in France
Frantically have a law against
Planned obsolescence
But
Progress
We don't know exactly how it'll turn out
And you know I mean apple has a reasonable case
Make about why they do
However
I think
Pick n Save for 100% sure
The apple is
A modern.
Faster
Alfred Sloan styles
Psychological
This is the new iPhone
And it lets you do some pretty incredible things
If you don't have an iPhone
You don't have the right
This is iPhone 6s
Not much has changed
Except a new color looks like this it's rose gold opossum
I have to admit for a long time
I was a sucker for this I feel like when we find ourselves wanting
New phones
Really wanted
Feeling like we almost need them
It's really tempting to think
There's a Sinister plot behind
Totally I hate ya
Like you know we imagine
There's someone pulling the
Curling person in the back
Exactly
You know with Feebas
True
So it's not that far-fetched
Psychological obsolescence
Is it with Albert Sloan.
We can't blame.
Shady cartel
We all know that that's happen
Is something inside
Get in the car
Drive to the Apple Store and standing
Long
What to get a new phone with
Facial recognition
Bright like we are cooperate
Just iPhone
This is Beijing
So many
Product
Places in
Economy
And look
GM used to be the biggest
Over the past
Couple years Apple has
Often been the
Panini America
Psychological obsolescence is not just some
Cute
Clever marketing scheme
And it's not just some trick
It's being pulled on us
But I do like
Came into this story thinking of planned obsolescence
Incise
You know something that company
Baidu
But the most
Powerful kind of obsolescence
Is it
We are choosing this ourselves
I don't think I could stop it if we wanted to
Find Monty
And you got those through line every week it has started like this and Other Stories from history that explain the world we have coming up
Next week we're covering the history of the opioid crisis so just check it out alright
Editor is Bryant AR senior producer is out School Park
Jordana hochman
Go to Michael Waldman Brian Merchant David Farber and ADI, start the music was composed by
Electric home run head v f Louis thanks for listening