We're in this moment right now where it
Feels like suddenly
There is this handful of giant
Companies that people are worried
Google Facebook Amazon
And reasonable people are starting to ask
Have these companies become
Too big
And too powerful
Should the government
Step in
Now these are relatively new companies but these are not
New questions at all
And for the next week on Planet Money we are going to tell the story
How the battle over these kinds of questions
Created this world we live in today where companies can get unimaginably
This episode is the first in a three-part series
We're starting at the very beginning
The first time a few companies
Suddenly seem to be
We taking over
Brely Evans
The history of breaking up
Big companies in America arguably starts
At an old house
In Titusville Pennsylvania
The childhood home
Of a woman named
Ida Tarbell
The house is still standing and actually just about 25 minutes from the small town where I grew up
Hi it's me to we meet Lynn Cressman she's the lead volunteer here and somehow she knows my name
I do know your grandma know her through my eyes
Small town
Anyway when was the show at this spot that little Ida Tarbell used to love
She opens up what looks like a closet door
It is in fact
The steepest staircase we have ever seen
The staircase leads up to the houses
Cupola like a little Tower
Full of Windows sunlight
Scoring in about a hundred fifty years
Is it Go Ida Tarbell was a brainy teenager
She used to come up to this Tower
The Reader books
To look through microscope
And look out the window
Like what would she have seen out here what would this look like
I think she would have seen wagons going down the street all horses
Pulling wagons loaded with barrels of oil and certain streets
Would have been
Squishing
Through the mud and the oil mixed together
Maybe that sounds gross but it was in fact a great problem
The Happening
How do you spell was the birthplace of the American oil into
It was the first place somebody figured out that you could use a drill to get a
Ton of oil out of the ground
Western Pennsylvania became to the oil industry with Silicon Valley is now for the
The tech industry
In the 1860s it what it seems like everybody here had an oil well or a small start-up oil refinery
People came from all over the country
To get a piece of the money just bubbling out of the ground
One of those people was Franklin Tarbell
The father
Ida Tarbell
Hanson Partners were into producing oil
And he was doing pretty well
He had this nice house with
An awesome power for his daughter Ida to hang out in
But one day
Ida came downstairs
And something else
Idlewood later right
I remember a night when my father came home with a grim look on it
No longer told of the funny things get seen and heard
During the day
He no longer sing
My little sister hello and welcome
The planet money I'm Penny Malone and I'm truly a sign then it would be 30 years for Ida Tarbell fully figure
Figured out what was going on that night
And what she found out
Would change her life and the way the United States thinks about baked
Today on the show Ida Tarbell versus the richest man
In the world
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and pray
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
The first start by asking you what your name in your position is
My name is Kathleen Brady I am a writer and biographer
Kathleen Brady is D Ida Tarbell biographer
She wrote Ida Tarbell portrait of a monkey
Because Ida Tarbell grew up and became a muckraker an investigative journalist but
Autobiographer
She was a huge deal to kind of a Doris Kearns Goodwin
She's written this great biography of Napoleon
Followed up with an even more popular biography of Abraham
And one day around the year Nineteen Hundred
Tarbell's
Colleagues in a magazine
Ross sitting around
Trying to brainstorm her next
Big crotch
And her editor Sam
McLaren like
I feel like there is one defining
Issue of
They decided to take up the trust the question of the trust which they regarded is the question of the age
Question of trust how about this question 1st
What is a trust
After the Civil War the US was going through something kind of similar to what we're going through today
Durbin's
Huge breakthroughs in technology
And they were allowing private companies
To grow bigger than they'd ever been
So when brakes are was the telegraph
Now you could have offices all across the country and
Field boss your employees around the railroad Network
Now your widget Factory didn't have to just serve Pennsylvania
It could ship anywhere in the country
Until the US economy started to consolidate
One Regional company buys another
Then another in
Soon the country was left
With just a handful of massive
Companies
What were known
As Trust
Truss
Trust were technically a bunch of smaller companies legally stitch together
And in the end many interests
Streets were controlled by one
Trust there was a meter
Whiskey tree
A rope and cordage Trust
There was a barbed wire fence
And this consolidation
It happened unsettlingly
Fast
Americans were starting to wonder
Have these companies
Become too big
Too powerful
So that is why Ida Tarbell and her editor Sam McClure were sitting around
Trying to figure out
Which Trust
I don't want to do sugar because it touched the family dinner table and McClure thought that
That was two trivia
They thought about doing meat
The big titan of meat
Just died
He wanted someone to profile and Ida was saying well it's got to be something like what happened in
In the oil industry and she was talking about that
Turtle recollect her own recollection of the oil industry
The oil industry
McLaren
Yes
Perfect
Oil
You were right
About the biggest
Baddest
Trust of the mall
Standard Oil
Penny Malone we are here at the old Standard Oil building
It's still write your Wall Street in New York 26 Broadway and I feel like I can just imagine
Exactly where we are
Looking up at this
Fortress of wealth in America this building is like
30 stories tall it's all this
Brooding concrete that Winston was here that special door knobs put on
I didn't know specifically how to turn these trick door knobs in order to get into certain rooms
All very big and Secret
Ida Tarbell was a biographer
She was going to focus on the man who ran it
Possibly the wealthiest man ever one of the most
Beard business man in the world
The head of the Standard Oil Company
John Deere okta
I don't have nothing
Knock knock you're able to find exactly one recording of Rockefeller
Video is super old it is
Weirdly unedited
Tell me when he says
Dear mr. holiday
Rockefellers on camera wearing a three-piece suit
And those super round glasses that you can really only pull off if you're a billionaire thanks but I'm
I'm not coming to the Standard Oil anniversary
I accidentally regret that it will be impossible
Sue Rockefeller
He was this mysterious Titan of industry and Ida Tarbell was going to figure out
Who this man really was
How did he become one of the richest men in the world
How did he build
Is oil Empire
And so she started her investigation
She's like
You know what I need
Luckily
Standard Oil had been involved in all these court cases
Is a big company so
Turbo figured there be
Plenty of records from
Plus
She'd heard there was like a book or pamphlet
That contain a bunch of records from some of these
Court cases of thought
Piece of cake because they're all these court records they're only scored records
And she thought
She was just going to
Grind-it-out
What it's not what happened no
When Ida Tarbell when search
Searching for all these court records and pamphlets
They were gone
The records and disappeared in a lot of cases
Ashley disappears viciously disappeared
Pamphlet
Entire runs of pamphlets and then bought up
And
She learned that standard oil had bought up all the copies
The man that they burn them or like I don't know what they did with them but they would assume they did they didn't want them in circulation
So she thought
Well I'll talk to my neighbors in Titusville
So she started contacting people back in her hometown who might have known about the cases
Half of them are afraid to talk to her because they thought Rock
Philly would hurt them
Some people thought you was the tool of Rock
The Feller and they didn't want to talk
Even her own father back in Titusville
Was leery of this project
He's very old at this point
But when I told him what she was up to her father said don't do it
They will ruin the magazine
And
And he was serious he was very serious
She was very serious you saw what happened and you saw their power
Nevertheless Ida Tarbell cap
And slowly
Started to piece together a portrait
Of John Deere
Rockefeller was born in 1839 in Upstate New York
His father was a con man
He was literally a sequel sales
John was very different from his dad
He was a devout Baptist
And very serious about saved
He grew up and did a good business shipping produce
But
When the oil boom kicked off
He wanted in on the action
He got into the oil refining business
In Cleveland Ohio
And Ida Tarbell gave him credit he was great at the oil business
Instead of renting barrels to transport as well like everybody else was doing
He figured he could save money by making his own bear
He also placed his refineries ingenious location
It's near the water but also the train track
And that way
Did the railroads try to charge him too much
For shipping
He had a second option
But
People were telling Tarbell
There was something more to his success
Something darker
And one day
She got a break
She goes down to the New York Public Library
The librarian is like
Ida remember those pamphlets that you thought at all suspiciously disappeared
Guess what I just
She gets this pamphlet what she fine until she found that
It presented the federal investigation into
Did the South Improvement oil come
The South improvement company
In the movie version of is Ida Tarbell with flashback to her childhood home in her little Tower
And that day her father
Was so upset
Improvement company was less of a company
More of a secretive scheme from the 1870s
Come back when Ida Tarbell was still in Titusville
And it was a shady
Essentially a small group of railroad
Got together with a handful of oil refinery
Including Rock
Propeller
And they said you know what that's all the great
Everybody inside this deal will get
Good shipping rates for their oil
Everybody outside the deal
Will get that chick
When Ida Tarbell was 15
Word of this deal got out
And the oil people in Titusville
Who were not on the inside of the steel
They were Furious
And the oil men
Revolted
Interrupted and had
Meetings by flaming torches and Rockefeller
Ultimately because of all the bad press
The deal didn't
Butter freeze everybody out
Including Ida tarbell's father
That night he came home and was so upset
It was because he knew
From now on
The oil business
Would be a world
Whitby Claire's
Making secret deals
That Franklin Tarbell would not be apart of
And as Ida Tarbell continued her research
She learned
The disk email
But it was like a
Play book
How Rockefeller ended up
Conquering the odds
Rockefellers company
Got big enough that he was able to go to the railroad
And start making demands
He be like
I ship a lot of oil
Do you want my business
I want a discount
Let's make this look
Nightshade
Make it look like I get the same rights as everybody else
Then give me some money back later
Maybe more egregiously
He would also be like
Yeah you know what else
I'm also not so crazy about you carrying my competitors oil
Let you do it
Just every time you do that
You also need to
These were bombshell
They meant
That standard oil had a secret Maybe
Unfair advantage over its competition
And Rockefeller
Do static
Rockefeller had about 30 rifle
These other refineries in
He basically said to them
You can either join me get in on this amazing Sarah Doyle stock
Or you have to compete with me
If you don't sell the me
I'm going
To lower my price
More than you can
And I will crush you
Of his nearly 30 rival refinery
Rockefeller was able to buy up
22 above
6 of those
In one 48 hour pee
They called this
The Cleveland
Massacre
I kept using this move all across the country
Jersey
Kansas and Oklahoma and California
When all the dust settled
Standard Oil
Controlled around 90% of oil refining in America
Percent
Those sketchy deals with the railroads
Help build his Empire
Rockefeller realized
Things could be even better
What if he owns the means of Transport himself
So we started buying a pipeline company
He owns so much of the oil industry
She could just set the price of oil where he wanted it
Any did
He fixed prices
Ida Tarbell stories about the shenanigans of Rockefeller and standard oil
They're coming out week after week in McClure's magazine
And the magazine circulation was getting bigger and bigger and bigger
Ida Tarbell was making
The 1902 version
Of the serial podcast
And everybody's reading this or everybody is reading it everybody is reading this around America it was an enormous success
Origination supposed to write 3
Stories
Then it was expanded to 6th and it became 12b eventually made a two-volume book out of
Everybody was reading these stories
Including
President
Theodore Roosevelt
In 1906
The Department of Justice filed a federal antitrust lawsuit
Against the Standard Oil
After the break
The death
Of Standard Oil
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
There's a modern biography of John D Rockefeller
Call Titan
Written by Ron chernow
You right about this dramatic moment
At the US
Supreme Court
He writes
At 4 p.m.
On May 15th
Chief justice Edward White told a sleepy courtroom
Quote
I have also to announce the opinion of the court in number 398
The United States against the standard
At once the room quivered with expectation that senators and congressmen
Screamed into hear the verdict
I just started to read the decision Services kind of unusual moment
Justice white said hold up hold up
Before we can figure out what to do with the Standard Oil Company
We all need to get on the same page of
There been a law on the books from about 20 years before
Call the Sherman Antitrust Act
It was theoretically a way for the government
To step in
Wendy's new giant Trust
Or misbehaving
But there were some big problem
It was vague and confusing
And it was mostly not working
And Justice white zeros in on this one phrase that seem to be tripping everybody
The Sherman Act said
Trust that were quote
In Restraint of
Trade
Weird illegal
But everybody was like what what does that mean
What does restrictive
Trade mean
And Justice white was like
Well we're seeing now
Some of the things that Ida Tarbell had uncovered
We're clearly a Restraint of trade
Making secret deals with the railroads that
Forester competitors out of business
Bad for trade
Using that leverage to buy up all your rivals
Clearly bad for competition fixing prices yeah that was obviously bad
The court said certainly these are examples of
Restraint of trade in the court use this case
Is to draw an important line
It said look
This guy John D Rockefeller he is really good at
His job
That's part of the reason why his company group
Because he's so good at business
At some point
Standard Oil just became a bully
It use its sheer size to gain unfair advantage
Is it had nothing to do with being a better oil
And so it grew simply
Because it was already big
Simply because it could
Restrain trade
The court took drastic Act
It said
Standard Oil
You are in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act
And we are going to break up
This company
It will bunch of smaller
It was a
Huge deal
But it was all for naught
Because even after the decision
Rockefeller was like
Hey
How about the officials from all these new companies
Still meet every morning at 10:30 at Standard Oil head
Again Ida Tarbell biographer
Kathleen Bray
Ida
Correctly saw
That
Now instead of one company there were thirty-three supposedly separate companies actually
Coordinating with each other
And
And in addition to everything else
Along Came the automobile and the demand for oil
Increased
It was actually 34 cup
Companies in Rockefeller still got stock
And that was even better business for him
All those new Mini Standard Oil
They were still oil companies
Oil with good business
They became some of the biggest companies in the world
Exxon
Mobile
ConocoPhillips Chevron
Rockefeller just became richer than ever
So Ida really
Didn't feel she had achieved her goal
At all I'm sorry to say I mean
Her goal was to tell a story and that she did but she did not feel that rock
Feller was
Punished in any way
Breaking the law
But
This case
Against Standard Oil
And that moment when the Supreme Court said let's clarify the Sherman Antitrust Act
This would be important
The rest of antitrust history
This clarification
Wood by the cord for
Decades and decades
It help the government
To go after misbehaving Corporation
And you know I look back at this
Case
At this moment when
When the country was really discovering
There is a strange tension
In free markets
Free market
Is great because it promotes competition
Companies have to battle it out if it makes
Cheaper or
Better and that is great for consumers
But businesses
You're not necessarily like,
I'm over here selling my thing it's going great then
Somebody comes along and sells it for less or sells a better version I don't want that
So I'll just buy up all my rivals
Before they put me out of
Before you know it I have eliminated all compass
The free market is good because it leads to competition
But the free market also can lead
Do a lack of
One of the main points
Civ antitrust law East
Solve this problem
To use government intervention to make free market competition work
The Standard Oil case showed
That the federal government was willing to do this
Step into the market
In a huge way
Try to make the market work
Next time on Planet Money
7 years after the Standard Oil decision
How one man transformed antitrust in America again
How to change the very definition of competition
I paved the way for some of the biggest most powerful companies we have ever seen
Your thoughts about the show you can get in touch with us we are
Planet Money at
NPR. Org we're also on Twitter and Instagram
At Planet Money
Brian Prosthetics are show Alex goldmark is
Planet Money supervising producer
This episode was produced by Sallie house
Special thanks
Amore sticky Richard John George priest
Bill kovacik
Abby lesko Gavin Lowe's
And Juliet hilber
And a very very special thanks to sue Bates at the Drake Wellness
Where are we
Wait is this it is the whole
That is the National Historic Landmark
That whole
And I don't know I don't know if our whole is the only National Historic Landmark or not
But it's certainly
The best hole
The whole suit showing us
Is the first place
Somebody figured out that you could use a drill to get
Ton of oil out of the ground
It happened in 1859
And the whole still actually producing a tiny bit of oil
Can I taste it
How about if we get you a fresh sampled
Too late
I'm Kenny Malone and I Julia Simon thanks for listening