Just a quick note Today's Show originally ran in 2015
I've been going to Sushi Bar since I was a little kid
But in all that time I've never been on the other side of the sushi
I've never been
Back where the chefs dance
Last week we made it back there
Thanks to chefs team Alicia Coppola at the sushi restaurant Jewel Bako in Manhattan
What's the most popular fish to sell
Poop pooping officiant
Tuna they've got lots
Of tuna
No wonder, the second most populated
You don't expect
Served and eaten
Basically every
Sea urchin of Coricidin
Poisonous Blowfish versus got a special license in Japan for pear poisonous
But in all his years as a sushi chef
He's never ever had
A single bite
Of raw salmon
I'm about to eat the South
Never
I never eat them the same way you know
So never you never even taking one bite of raw salmon
Can we get you to try it today
Not that long ago
Everybody in Japan was like you
Ishikawa
Nobody ate Roxanne
It was like eating raw pork
It just wasn't done
And then
A few people Halfway Around the World
Marshall plan to change
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm taking cold
And I just Jay today on the show
How hard could it be to get a nation of sushi lovers to eat raw salmon
Support for this podcast and the following message come from SimpliSafe Home Security
Who believes fear has no place in a place like home
That's why they made a completely wireless home security system
That can be self installed in under an hour
SimpliSafe sensors are built to protect every point of access to your home
Including doors windows and garage
More than three million people have already Protected Their home with SimpliSafe
Get free shipping
And a 60-day money-back guarantee
At simplisafe.com Planet Money
There are so many different labels on food these days
Organic
Non-GMO
Fair trade
Freehand gathered it's overwhelming
I sometimes jokingly refer to it as been a scarring of our food life get has a new episode making sense
The Food Lab
Find it and War by Sir
Life kit
All guide
Can apple
When we talk about
International trade you know we often didn't to talk about thing
Like tariffs
Quotev
There's this idea that if you get rid of those things get rid of those barriers
New products just come rushing in across borders
But clearly that is not always the
Sometimes you have to spend
Years and years and years
Working and begging and trying to convince an entire country that
Whatever thing you have a lot of wood everything you want to sell
Is something they should want to buy
Like paper example salmon
In Norwich
Hello
Villa, Altamonte
Hello can you hear us
The other day we were trying to connect to this
Video and Trump set on this little island in Northern Norway
We overheard them talking about us in Norwegian
Public in Santa Marta Colombia
Mooney Mooney planet
Hello
Does Planet Money translate as money planet
Is that right
This is Bjorn adac
And when we talked to him the other day he told us that back around the time you graduate from
This is a few decades
Norway had
The government had been
Subsidizing the Norwegian fishing in
For decades
I've basically been paying people to
And of course when you subsidize something you get more of it
It's not a very
Clever way of using money because the more you use their the worst situation get
The government says
Okay
Let's wind down these
We're not going to screw over our fishing industry
Let's figure out a way to get the rest of the world to buy our fish
They look around the world and they see one country in Virginia
Really loves fish and that needs to start importing more
Yes
Japan at the time
Salmon sushi
Is not a thing
Not in Japan not in Norway
Sure it's
Cured or smoked
But a hunk of raw salmon
No
And in fact the idea of salmon sushi just began is this
Tiny little little thing at the Norwegian Embassy in Tokyo
They were just
Playing around with ways to
To serve Norwegian products in a Japanese style
They just try let's try
To have a little bit Solomon
Drawer
Just in the end Amphitheatre
Thundershift under ambassador
Around this time
Don't get hired by the Norwegian government
Too selfish to the Japanese
Used to be a fisherman
He speaks Japanese
Kind of the perfect guy for this mission
Any figures
Yeah sure we could sell salmon
Cheap in Japan
Can people in Japan already eat salmon
Grilled
But when people buy fish to use for sushi
They're willing to pay a lot more
Sometimes people pay five times as much for the same kind of fish
If it's going to be used
So if you can get people into
Japan to eat salmon sushi
Don't make all that Norwegian salmon much
More value
Sofi Ryan goes to Tokyo
And he gets a bunch of Japanese fish industry Executives into a conference
And he unveils the next
Salmon
And they say directly over the table
It's impossible
We Japanese
Do not eat salmon Raw
Well just put it's good to taste good
No they say
It doesn't taste good
They say the color is wrong also its
It's too it's too late Reddit should be right there
The state that has a smell
And also because they knew the shape of the salmon and it said that
The head has the Bronx Tale
And the Gillis look wrong everything is wrong so
Everything
Everything The Taste the smell
The texture
The fact that the color of everything
What did you think when they said that
This this this is completely crazy because we are human beings
Phoenix Japanese but we have taste and we have feeling in ormiston
How is delicious and I think
Happy Japanese awesomest
Feel the same as I do
Of course what you taste when you bite into something isn't just
Like a chemical reaction
And it's not just the fundamental molecular properties of the finger eating
You taste all the baggage you bring into it
The more I started to dig into the the more I became aware of the importance of
Bjorn's Big Challenge was this
He's going to have to change the perception
Of an entire country of
People people who thought the color or the shape of the head of salmon
Was all wrong
If you want to change perception if you want to get people to buy something
What you do is not a miss
The Luncheonette
Enzo Buren and his colleagues figured alright
Start doing some TV commercials
Maybe have a cute cartoon character
Did you have a mascot like a dancing salmon or something
A we had but it was it was very silly it was a white cake
A Viking
Yes yes
It was a viking with a helmet and it was like a funny drawing with a big head
Animated Sentinel Eastern Seafood
He actually sent us a picture
Of the Viking of the Mask
I have to say it's like
If you were to imagine what some Outsider trying to
Pander to Japanese audience would come up
I know that right like it smooth
Super cute little boy Viking with his great big head in like big eyes
A huge giant fork
Yeah like as tall as he is
And so the Vikings surprise
Partly because there was this
Really
Bigger problem about getting Japanese people
Apple to eat raw
And that was they were afraid that raw salmon had
Parasites
People in Japan were used to eating this kind of salmon
Dependents have parasites in it
And would make you
Stick if you eat it raw
Bjorn says
The salmon from Norway was totally different
Parasites just born a problem
But it's not like you want to just
Run an ad in Japan that said
Don't worry our salmon is parasite
We didn't want to mention it at all because if you if you say that
My my my fishes has no poison than you say is no
Pyside is no
It's no bad things in it
So then people will also say that
Yeah the first thing I'll think of is if their voice
Yeah yeah yeah
Why do they save it
Why do they keep saying that
So we didn't say that at all
We concentrated our information to the consumers about
The cold
Pure Norwegian sea water
Just put the thing the pictures of all the
Fjords
Mountains
I sent additional fishing boats and end
Then then you gave the impression about
Is some something that is
Pure and fresh
Not enough to get Japan to start eating raw Sam
After years of AD campaigns
Norwegian salmon still haven't taken off in the Japanese sushi Market
And the country's fishing industry the wholesalers are at the
Supermarkets in distributors
They just wouldn't buy it
It didn't matter whether ordinary people were worried about parasites
Whether they love the viking mask
Heat of the Viking mascot
Big companies that control the fish business weren't convinced
Salmon sushi wasn't going to go any
And back in or wait their Norwegian salmon industry was getting desperate
The glut was getting so bad that they start selling industrial size freezers with
Tons and tons of salmon
The Japanese wanted to buy some of that song
But not for sushi
We wanted to sell it cheap for
For grilling smoked so companies that wanted to sell it on out on the market for for grilling etcetera and they said no
We don't want it there
Yuan says there was a lot of pressure for him
To give up
To just sell the salmon to whoever would buy it
But he thought
He just needed
One big deal
One company that would believe in his idea of salmon sushi
In a minute
Bjorn gets a break
Support for NPR in the following message come from Capital One business credit card
The spark Cash Card
Offering unlimited 2% cash back on everything you buy for your business
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Visit capitalone.com for more information
When's the last time you had a really good workout
If your brain
Host of hidden brain
Listen every week
Flex your mind
So pure and is trying to find somebody in Japan
To buy into his
Dream of Japanese people eating raw salmon
And there was this one company called nichirei
That he's been building a relationship with
Everybody in Japan knows this company
They're like Kraft or Stouffer's or something in
They self
Frozen food you know dumplings chicken nuggets
Squid
Bjorn told them I will sell you
5000 tons of that frozen salmon
For really cheap
All you have to do
Is salad in the grocery stores
As sushi
Just try it
Nichirei said yes
Yuan how to deal
Ready for the day of happiness
I remember that then and the
It was like being in the heaven if you see what I mean just the happiness
That was shared
You have a history of money hundred years of
Sushi consumption in Japan
And this
It's almost not the pocket with
There was a feeling of of making history
When's nichirei start selling salmon for sushi
The idea of salmon sushi Des teams
More normal
You'll be like if I don't know if in this country
Dannon
Started selling
Yogurt with
Raw pork
Definitely not something I would have come up with but I've been eating Dannon Yogurt on my life
Never made me sick
Whatever maybe I'll just throw one park at the bottom in along with my strawberry banana
My shopping cart
Pretty soon salmon sushi start showing up
Everywhere engine
Especially in those conveyor belt sushi restaurant
This has meant
Applebee's of Japan almost everybody is trying
Tadashi Ono is a sushi chef he's 53 now
The first time he tasted salmon sushi it was about 20 years ago and
It did not go well I was scared
Yasso
Couldn't he enjoy it
I wasn't either
Clear about how it taste
I was
Thinking about how my God
Am I going to get sick or do you know what kind of stuff he didn't get that
And he wanted to understand
Why everybody was so into raw salmon
And he kept trying it
The first time I said maybe
So you know I started liking Gates
Actually you.
Buttery
Creamy melt in your mouth
It's creamy and it melts in your mouth
Yeah it is in the way
You know it's very soft meat
This really is a testament to how malleable art
Rkc
Can food art
Fashion whatever
So that's what he told us there was a taboo against eating raw salmon
Of even touching Rock
A few tries later
He's in love with it it's like
We imagine that we would never ever
Eat something or wear something
And then we do
I'm a very stubborn guy so it's like
My mind is say it's hard to change
But you changed your mind in this case
I did
Why
Because the ingredients is good
Tadashi says
Hammond Sushi is his teenage daughter's
Favorite
She had no idea that it used to be taboo
Not long after the need to re deal Bjorn move back to New
A few hours later he was back in Tokyo visiting on
And that was when he knew
Salmon sushi
One day he was walking around
And he noticed these little plastic Sushi replicas
In the restaurant windows
And then suddenly I saw there was some oh no
Plastic copas
Percentage
In the sushi shops
See the wrong
In Tokyo
This is really a break
Can you since then Sushi is spread around the
I think salmon was a big part of that
You know it's it's easy to eat it's mild
Baddie kids like it
For sushi
Salmon is like
A Gateway fish
Any kind of Summer
One piece is okay
Jess I think you should hit that
And just one bite
Converse socks
That was delicious that was a that was really really good and it's very simple
Tell us what you think of this show
Email Planet Money at mpr.org or tweet at us
At Planet Money
Planet money has an email newsletter it's once a week it's short it's a smart essay about economic ideas this
This week we looked at arguments over the best way to pay teachers
You can subscribe at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
Again npr.org
Flash Planet Money newsletter
Special things today to you kygo omiya Japanese food writer in London
Enter chef ichimura
Today's Show is produced by Francis Harlow
The rerun was produced by Rachel Cohn and Darian Woods
If you want to support Planet Money please recommend a show to a friend
Is NPR
I'm taking both today
And I'm just saying
Thanks for listening