This message comes from NPR sponsor NCR running a small business is now easier with ncrc
More than a point of sale
NCR silver is simple-to-use saves you time and helps you reach your goals faster
Visit ncr.com silver
Today on Planet Money the second part of our story on Marxism and capitalism in Chile
In part one we told you had she laid democratically elected president Salvador Allende
The social
Now part 2
The crew
And please note there is a lot of violence
Today's episode
September 11th 1973 I remember clearly the
Airplanes flying
About our house this is Carrillo Fuentes a documentary filmmaker who was 3 years old the day the crew started
A little before 7 a.m. president Salvador Allende cancel call
The Chilean Navy has rebelled in the port city of Valparaiso
He rushes downtown to La moneda the presidential Palace
Tanks and troops fill the street on the radio and talks to his country
I have faith in Chile and its desk
The military tells IND surrender he refuses
Tanks open fire on the couch by ende asked that the women be allowed to leave
And they are then the bombardment start
Fighter jets and Rockets into the palace
And inside fires break out
Buy afternoon agenda realizes there's no way out
She shoots himself in the head
Back out in the streets
The Army rounds up Hyandai supporters
One Gabrielle Valdez who's now a professor at Columbia University was studying at Princeton that day
He gets a panicked phone call from his father
Gallegos either the possibility that they would exaggerate
When he says the fact that there were people floating in the river
Unnightmare
Are you in the supporters are beaten and shot in the streets thousands are herded into Stadium
One of them is Victor Jara the Chilean Woody Guthrie soldiers break are his fingers in
And tell him you'll never play the guitar again
An officer plays Russian roulette with him he loads a bullet into a gun Spencer chamber pulls the trigger
Until it's over
Then they shoot his body more than 40 times
And dumped him in a street in Santiago Chile an economist who studied at the universe
City of Chicago
They're watching
To them getting a car
Drive to the top of a hill and watch the phone
Chicago boy Ralph looters is living in Washington DC
Remember he was the one who had Milton Friedman essay
The thesis advisor
He got a call to
But his reaction wasn't
Fear of confusion
Military coup
Which took place
Managed by people who sought and democracy
The contradiction that difficult contradiction is that
Chile was a democracy before the coup
And if there's one thing of coup is not a coup is not democratic
Some people may have wanted free markets and democracy
But what they what happened instead was in fact
Authoritarian government
Ed
Insulate democratic election
Led directly to a socialist
Government
And then the military took over by force
In the name of the free market
Hello and welcome to
The Planet Money
I'm Jasmine
And I know Elle King
In the United States during the Cold War we believe that democracy and free markets went hand-in-hand
But then
There was what happened in Chile
Today on the show chili goes from socialism to capitalism by force and with the help of the United
States it's the story of a coup a ruthless dictator and a bunch of economist
The Chicago
Support for this podcast and the following message
Just come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Located near DC
And home to 8900 technology companies
And 144000 Technology jobs
Details at Fairfax
Next County Eda. Org
Hey it's candy Malone from Planet Money the podcast you're listening to right now
We are podcast
However
We are also occasionally a video series and we have a brand new season
A Planet Money shorts out right now the covers everything from
The tooth fairy and tooth inflation to
The man who invented expensive vodka and convinced us all it was worth
I am in that
Episode
I grew a beard for it
And I shaved my beard
It's like to see that
It is at npr.org Planet Money shorts
That's npr.org planet
The overnight chili has gone from democracy to military rule
And now
The economy the inflation the shortages the crushing deficit
All of that is the military's problem
Or more specifically the general who takes charge
Augusto
Pinochet
He's Infamous now for his brutality
But back then he was in unknown he had no government
Experience and certainly no economic
Experience says rolls looters
I saw you quoted once a saying
When it came to economics
Pinochet was an idiot
He didn't know anything
I didn't say it
I think
Because I usually don't use that expression
But that he didn't know anything about the economics right
Definitely
Look this make sense
Pinochet went to military school as a
The teenagers he's a lifelong Soldier
He's not an economist
But this is not a problem
Because there are these University of Chicago trained Economist already living in Santiago
And a small group of them has dry
Crafted a plan to fix the economy
And
The military has the plant
NJ lottery
The Brick
And and so he decided to
Appoint
Chicago boys to the
Chemical elements
In the days after the cool the experimenting in free markets begin
Just a little
The military bust of time unions
The Crackdown on the black market
And they on fix the prices
The food
I'm fixing the prices is sound economic logic
Price-fixing have been causing shortages
But if food producers can charge the prices they want they will produce food
So they do
And the price of food goes through the roof
And for 18 months it kind of just goes like this its economic
Tinkering
But Chili's big problem is inflation
Chronic
Dizzying inflation
It's running it over 300%
Do you know who knows a lot about inflation
Rolf luders
And
His old thesis advisor
A guy who's made his reputation on monetary policy and fixing inflation
Is it true that in 75
You personally invited Milton Friedman to come to Chile
Yes
Repairing vitamin B7
But he came to Chile and 7th
By now Friedman is a superstar
He is an evangelist with one simple
Free markets WETA free Society
He meets with Pinochet in a conference
Center and there's a picture of this meeting that I've spent a lot of time looking at
Init
Pinochet is sitting in an armchair with his legs crossed
Leaning toward freedmen and looking apprehensive
And Friedman is leaning back legs also cross
And he has this
Self-satisfied look on his face
Infinite resistance
Sanctum
And ask him what is thought about the economy it's on
Ann Friedman
Basically
About the needs
Office shock treatment
In macroeconomics
Stamps
Eshakti
Shock treatment meaning
You changed fast and you changed dramatically
Sample treatment always used
It's
You see it hurts less
To cut the tail
Off a dock if you cut it as once
Then if you got the thin slice
Yeah okay
And then empty treatment say that to Pinochet
Where is the two peanuts at 12 to 2
To everybody
He's right
About a month after that meeting the government announces
The shock treatment is about to begin
Step 1 austerity
Cut government spending
Including subsidies
Freeport PA
Step to tighten monetary policy
Stop Printing money
It's painful
Taxes are raised
Is the government jobs are
Unemployment spikes
The middle class and the poor are really
Step 3 open the economy to the rest of the world
Chile has had these insanely High import tariffs protecting their industries from competition
Super example the country has
17 Carcano
That combined makes 17000 cars
It's totally unofficial
Now the Chicago boys cut the tariffs and all of these foreign made cars come pouring in
Columbia Professor Juan Gabriel Valdez because of this move a lot of people lose their jobs
Sekolah Jillian Industrial
Sector
Broke
You know matters of
Under the level of unemployment was brutal
Valdez noticed early on all of these
Chicago boys being hired into the government
He wrote a book about it years ago
And he interviewed a professor who taught the Chicago boys
And this subject
Came up the subject of how like overnight
They cut the tariffs that were protecting to lay an industry
And he used every American word to describe
What is meant to do that
What was the word
You have to be a cold-blooded son-of-a-b**** to do that
But cutting the tariffs
Did change the country
Especially if you had money
If you have money now you can buy whatever you want
From wherever you were
Patricia arancibia clavel at historian who's written a bunch about the Chicago boys
Remembers how
Quickly things change
Invisible
Oh no
Oenophile
One day eyeglasses shop
When is shoe store
You can find a lot of them
It is a Pato Rojo Verde Azul there was not only
Day one red shoe that you could buy
You could find blue shoes and green shoes
Chilean journalist on Oscar Romero was translating for me this all happened before he was born so he was listening and he was
It's getting kind of ant
This letter
Economic
Competition
So they shoot that custody
The custard
Adult some pesos
No custard
500 peso
She says all of this starts a revolution in the way people think
Before you graduate from college and then you'd go work for a state-owned company
You didn't think about profits or competition
But the Chicago boys are privatizing everything
Who Industries are moving into private hands
Chile's government does hold onto the copper in
It's the biggest business in Chile
Some things are just too valuable to put on the free market
Yeah I guess so
Aside from the copper industry
The US is over the moon about
Richard Nixon even says he'll take a dictatorship as long as it's not a communist
Dictatorship
When they are dictatorial I would say they are dictatorial
I would also have to
On the other side
Indicate that they are non-communist
The Chicago Bulls change the laws to make it easier to invest in Chile
So us companies come
Everything from Banks to oil companies to General Motors which had left under IND
Billions of dollars in foreign investment in loans
Come pouring in
The economy starts growing
And people start Rhapsody
About Chile's economic miracle
Chilean public TV start broadcasting Milton Friedman TV show it's called free to choose Alex
Some people hear you may be appalled by his ideas
Like others extremely enthusiastic about the
Whichever way it goes I will be fascinated
What Milton Friedman has to say
Carrillo Fuentes was a kid.
This is
Amazing
You know
An economic TV show from an economist
From the US
Being aired
Every week
In dipolog City
And on the TV soap operas
The actresses talk about how their Chilean appliances are junk
And the foreign-made ones are so much
Does Chileans work on swimming
Black matte
Because they felt
That they were rich
Because
Income was going to grow
Because of the reforms that have been implemented
It's okay but they're not
They're just optimist
And there's a big difference
Between those two
In the early 1980s
There's a worldwide recession
And guess what
Chili's part of the world now
They have a reception to
And this is when
In the middle of the night while fluters gets
The call
He's being officially invited
To come and work for Pinochet
Did you find Pinochet to be a frightening person
He used to say dick Dublin.
You say that you know the table
Glenda means
Victims dictator
And so he said he was soft
Dictator
End
My personal experience
What's the tea was actually
More weak than than strong
This is hard to understand but I'm going to give it a shot
Juan Gabriel Valdez told me that
A couple years after the crew he was interviewing guys from the Chilean military
And some of them told him
We did not agree with the sharks
We could see that these policies were hurting people
But when we questioned the Chicago boys did start using this Chicago speak
They were smarter than us
They talked over hits
We have no idea what they were doing
And if we asked and we debated
Are we mention the consequences these
Thanks Mike have
Wiiware
Rejected in a very drastic way
And the well we we we we cool answer we would react
The Economist made the generals feel like dummies
And so the generals were like do what you want
Music
So clearly looters is not afraid of Pinochet
Now he's Minister of Economics and finance
And he does something.
Seems like it would make Milton Friedman go crazy
Intervene
The government bailed out the banks
The irony of this is not lost on Chileans
A New York Times article from back then reports that people started cracking jokes
Calling this
The Chicago Road to socialism
Looters also renegotiates foreign debt
He changes the labor laws so that wages can be cut he does a bunch of thing
It takes some time but Chile's economy recovers
Remember these free market policies were supposed to hurt at first
But work in the long run
And they did
The economy stabilizes
And then it starts to thrive
Other countries call the Chicago Boys in to consult
Today Chile is one of the strongest economies in Latin America
But
Here is a question that Chileans ask themselves all the time
Was it worth it
Imagine this happening in the United
The president shocks Arcana
Cheap Imports come in
People lose jobs
The government slashes the social safety
Your kids college it goes
Private
Osteo
What the President says
You know what it's going to be better for you in the long run
We would vote that president out of office
Augusto Pinochet could not be voted out he was a dictator
If you protested him or protested his policies
You could be killed
Port Orchard
Or you just banished
It was one of those situations where it felt like everyone knew someone
Or knew someone who knew someone it was really complete that's why I'm Gabrielle. That so-and-so whom you know
Oh has been shot
So and so whom you know has disappeared
This is the type of
So one so who was your friend
And was working at copper mine
As a
Manager
Was tortured in such a way that you couldn't
That they could recuperate
Therefore they decide to do shooting
I'm sorry is that a real story
That happened to someone you know
Kenya recycling
That's true
I just went well fluters Balise to
I know the conditions we have to ensure that
We either we're going to move towards
Totalitarian state
Or we would move
Under an ulcerated regime
To it
Stress free market economy eventually to
Democracy
You have one of two choices
There was no third way there was no
Of course
Who was not have been
In favor of having a democratic change that with a free market economy
Everybody with a flight
But that was not in the car
Because nobody believed that could be done
You follow me that did the IDI
That you needed government intervention
Economy Inn
So so so deep deep deep ternative
Which Wich
I like of course I like that
Viable
The people forget the fact
The factor that
He says Peter Shay told him
Once the economic experiment succeeded
Chili would go back to being a democracy
Absolutely convinced
Eventually should prevail
It's a democracy with social
Did he really Pinochet really want someone
I believe I believe
After the break
Pinochet takes a huge Gamble and losses
Support for this podcast and the following message come from twit.tv
Play This Week in Tech podcast
Every week
Award-winning Tech expert Leo LaPorte and top Tech pundits cover the latest news
Innovation
Privacy gear plus the pitfalls and mistakes
In the world of tea
Your first podcast of the week
Is the last word in SAS
Join the Lively Roundtable discussion and subscribe to This Week in Tech podcast on your favorite podcast
Or at twit.tv
In 1988 Under Pressure Pinochet fall of the Constitution and allowed to lands to vote
Did they want him to stay or go
The economy was so strong by this point that he actually campaigned on it
They voted him out anyway a couple of years later at Pinochet handed over power to a democratically elected
Dead Presidents
He died in 2006
Facing charges of murder
Torture and kidnapping
Some of the soldiers who
2 tortured and killed the folk singer Victor Jara
Went to prison
The officer who allegedly played Russian roulette with him did not he moved
To Florida and avoided a criminal trial
A jury there found him liable in a civil suit
Milton Friedman won the Nobel Prize for economics
That visit to Chile with dog
For the rest of his life
Rolf luders doesn't mention any regrets
He's a public figure
And every once in awhile someone will say something nasty to him or about him
On the subway or in the movie theater
About how he works for peanuts
What happened
I will continue to go to the movies and then the theater
I don't care
Hundreds of thousands
Look up people
Who greet me on the streets 2
To him the numbers prove the point
Chile's inflation
That chronic seemingly unfixable problem
Today it's stable and low
Its median income is one of the highest
In South America
It's poverty rate one of the lowest
Patricio clavell the historian was maybe the most forthcoming person I talked to in Santiago
If you said something I feel like other people were dancing around
Some people are worth
Say that it was easier to open the economy in a country ruled by the military
And she said
Whether you like it or not
We owe our economic success
To Pinochet
Now The Interpreter Honus had whatever is the opposite of a poker face
And when she said that his face went dark
Can I ask what you think about that I mean I owe you for this or you know Pinochet how old are you
I'm
Chinese
Do you eat so you are raised in the era of democracy
Do you think that
Do you think this is a fair argument that if they wanted to make the economy better they needed a military junta
Think it's
It's hot it has a lot of
Gray area
Because of course now
I grew up in a country where
My parents
Buy food
I never had to make a cue for
Brett Favre
Mute for basic
I personally
It regrets
Very much so
These things because
It was for me I very
Violin
Way to do it
It's
Huge deer mount
People who get
Torture
Forget this
It who were disappeared
Who were killed who were tortured and they were horrible and it was
Hey can you tell her what you're saying and ask her does she know you're doing yeah if it's a little gay
Yes yes I understand
A female ovulation.
She told him no one can ever justify the violation
Human rights
There are black spots in human nature
Do we have to understand that and look for the good and the truth
Are you convinced by this
It's
Very hard
For me to
Embrace that
Given the recent
Recent best of my family on
It's
I'm not a dick my mother always told me the story about her best friend
When she was young my mother
A protest and get a protista
Again Spanish
Her best friend
One day went missing
And when she showed up
Months later after my mom look for her
She told her that
She had
What they did to her was a brutal method of torture which we're not going to hear
And it's such a confusing ways such a confusing country and I think
And you just said it it's a revolution but it's a revolution that
For me it was born with violence
Chili Worcester
World
Laboratory
For capitalism
4 premarket for where are you you want to put it
That is very sad
Very strong
Things to to realize
This country my
Night night
Did the laboratory
For the rest of the world for some people who went to Chicago and learn stuff that they said it will be
Right
It's a pain that I don't think we can
Make it go away
You don't think it was worth
For you it's not worth it
It wasn't worth it
So you know how Jonas was listing the things that he never had to wait in line for bread and milk
Patrizia was prodding him along and it one point she said University and he
He said to her I owe a lot of debt to the university
This is what she lays like today
A generation wins the Great War against Marxism and they say to the young people we did this for you
And some of these young people say back yeah
But we wish she hadn't I imagine these Economist the Chicago boys looking up
From their experiments so excited and saying this is what we learned but of course
The person down there in the petri dish being experimented on is only ever going to answer this is
Is what we live
Why do people to think in this episode 1 Test the filmmakers Buford in this episode
So it's made an extraordinary documentary called the Chicago boys
She basically talked to all of them if you liked these episodes you will love her movie we'd also like to thank dr. rakkar
Cardo French Davis Dr Sebastian Edwards Alfredo Sepulveda Francisco erevena Peter kornbluh
Miguel Paz and Juan Pablo garnham Nick Fountain produce these two episodes with some help from our intern
Turn Rachel Cole Alex gold markets are supervising senior producer and Brian erstad is our editor
I'm Noel King and I'm Jasmine garsd and this is a song by Victor Jara it's called la partida