Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for
Tools tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Hey everyone Sally home here
The market
For art
Is really fickle
Something that sold for a ton of money last year
Might be hard to even sell it all next
And this story from way back in 2010 explains those Dynamics
Really well
Soap
We are re-airing that show today
We'll have an update for you at the end where we
Run the numbers and tell you whether or not
You should be putting all your money into sharks
Pickled in formaldehyde
I'll make sense later
Cure Thrift Shop
The show starts with a number
That number
Is 12 million
12 million dollars that is how much a 15 foot shark in formaldehyde
Artist Damien Hirst
Reportedly sold for in 2005
Title which I love is
The physical impossibility of death
In the mind of someone living
Title alone is worth $1000000 exactly
I have another slightly smaller number
1.5 million.
That is how much Eddie Saunders tried to sell his shark
Eddie Saunders own an electrical shop and he said he had a shark hanging in his shop before Hurst did his shark thing
And so Saunders Randa Dad saying
New Year sale only 1 million British pounds
5 million pounds on the Damien Hirst
Nobody bought his shark
That Anika by the way,
Trauma book I've been reading called the 12 million dollar stuffed shark about the r
And that
Anecdote is
Certamen capsulas what are podcasts about today why does one guy's stuff sharks sell for $12
And another guy basically can't even tell his stuff
Hello and welcome to the Planet Money art gallery walk around or yourself some wine in one of those
Little plastic cups
Take a look at the art
After these kisses are really speaking to me David the times I enjoyed that when the Bold color the vibrant
Dynamism the brushstrokes
It's so cheap it's a bargain
Today we're going to try to figure out the answer to that question that no artist likes
Discuss price
That wonderful thing that you just created a tab in are you just poured your creative Soul into
How much is Accutane cost
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
Best 300 cities where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities were people in those 300 cities
Think they're the only ones who know about that one place
And 300 cities where people miss someone
One and one of Delta's other 299
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first place
Delta
Keep climbing
Start with the sound I'm going to play tell me if you can
Identified I can barely
Hear it
Is an empty room
That's the sound of the winkelmann art gallery on 27th Street in
Big empty room White Walls
Photograph song about
Feet apart or something
And I wanted to start the discussion here because
Justice League
An Ansel Adams photograph of Yosemite National Park sold
For $772,000
When I visited the Winkleman gallery
On the wall we're photographs
Sky Matthew Albanese
They look just a dramatic one was of this huge ominous tornado training across a field
Another one was
Glacier in Antarctica another one with a
Volcano
Except that Ed winkelman the guy runs the gallery said
It's not a tornado that's not Antarctica
And that's not a box
Evil disease models out of everyday materials
A studio set for example
What looks like a tornado is actually
Cell wall
What looks like an iceberg is all made out of sugar
What looks like the volcano
Is
Tile and grout that's pretty great right now
Grenada
Foreground in Sky grass and bushes is all made of parsley
And a very convincing
Alex here like this is a
At the iceberg
Make sugar
Oh my God
Exactly like an iceberg
Wow
Apparently it's all in like the lighting he set these things up and
Working on them in the studio they like little diorama
Yeah it was linked to be the foot of these on her blog npr.org money
But Dave I have a
You have an ugly Quest I have an ugly question
How much is that going to run me
It's $2,480 framing
It's cheaper than Ansel Adams
And lookie probably put a lot more work into it
Yeah that's true
Ansel Adams
The real stuff
So this guy had to make the iceberg and then take a photo
So much harder
Federal iceberg
So it's a hard question what should the spider graph cost
I asked
Talk about price
My question is harder than that it's how do you
Decide what price tag to put on
Okay
Sound there really is a system
System
I love it I can
Imagine that the artisan
Is a system for president
People you know who aren't famous yet and
He said that there's always awkward moment you know I'll have some new artist
Really really likes their work
And you're maybe sitting there in front of their paintings and then
You got to put a price tag on it
The formula
It has very little to do with how good the artist
Okay so depends on the scale
Besides you mean yes
A bigger cost more
Yes
What if it's small and super details and beautiful
What's the scale is one aspect
Scale
What I would consider intensity
Cuz you said if it's very small and super detailed it took a lot more time
So scale intensity the third criteria is what he calls medium
Notarized what it made of is a sculpture carved out of wood
Is it made of marble
How many copies are they
If it's a photograph and you have multiple editions of it's going to be less expensive
Oil paintings in general are known to be
Twice as expensive per square inch over the same artist drawings
Really
Alright so what I'm learning is if I'm in emerging artists
I want to do big oil paintings
And not
Tiny
Charcoal drawings
Yeah really really really really big
He says at the end of the day the artist
You know you can go around the galleries in
Call Center pricing
Yeah I told you that there's actually a minimum price
You know as a gallery owner he's got his own cost right he's got
He's got his employees
You got the wine that they serve at the opening
What is the cheapest
Possible painting you can buy in the
I know a nice neighborhood they're going to run over a thousand bucks
Have back up here it's just like
One piece of art
And I'm like 10 feet another piece of art you know so
Then I can meet you
All right
That explains the prices of set of artist that are
Not well-known merging
But it doesn't answer the question
The shark question
Python requests
Why
Does a shark in formaldehyde cut 12
Is it awesome
After the break
We answer the question
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
Best 300 cities where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities where people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones
To know about that one place
And 300 cities where people miss someone
And one of Delta's other 299c
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people to go
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first
Delta
Keep climbing
I took for emerging artists
Where. Really is like a commodity
After that you know people start buying your art
Different set of economic rules
And to talk about this I went downtown to meet with William Bell Mall he's an economist
NYU
He's 8 years old
But the writing
I'm in competition with Methuselah at these days
Most people
My age
Have
Laid down their pens
However
I do remember Poppin you once
Attended a lecture by
The notion
Economist
ACP Google
And he got up and he said
You have to realize that
I am best described
As an ancient squid
Who still considered a continues
To eject squirts of ink
And the
Feel like qualify under that description
Falmouth
Certainly won my heart
It's one of the things the economics of Art
An artist in South eustachy sculpture there
Paintings that he's done around his office
And occasionally actually sells window Kali for a few hundred
I'm almost famous on this topic for a paper he wrote
Called
Unnatural value or art investment as floating crap game
We got a lot of good titles in this in the podcast
We have a copy of that paper here it's from 1985 and its
The scan
Of the original paper that the scan of a printout from 1985
Fun. Matrix
Printer paper
Bring back memories
Underline under line under each letter is Maui
I do I get to the art invest
Two partners II
It's no mystery what determines the price
Set of art art like everything else
Supply and demand
If you're famous and you got up
Line of people waiting to buy your neck
You can charge more for that
Or if you got some rich guy who really wants to buy a formaldehyde shark
Bidding against some other rich guy who also wants the shark you know the price goes up to 12 million dollars
He says what makes are different from a commodity like
Oil for ball bearings
Rice
I need the different from things like stocks or bonds
Is it with those things you can try to
Price
Good luck
State dependent swings
Inhuman taste
I am
Absolutely convinced that there is nothing about human taste
I can be cold quotes
Rational
How many cups are benzos blue is better than her head
How to use
I change my mind
At this point
Art art depends
Purely on human teeth
Here's something he wrote in the paper
Their prices float more or less
Aimlessly
What but it's not unless I mean there is I mean just like his fundamentals for stocks and bonds You could argue that are
Art
Animals are just basically what the art
Critics think about that
Inside of my jogging
Speaking of the heart
Analysis I'm going to continue to call him now
Here's what one
Curator flat artemest had to say about Damien Hirst
Formaldehyde shark
Quote it's brutally honest and confer
Rotational
He draws attention to the paranoiac
Denial of death
That permeates our culture
And therefore definitely worth 12 mil
Especially if you can talk for more later
And that is
The thing you hear about a lot
You hear that record prices for art in the news
The cost of the telephone
A hundred million at Andy Warhol piece sold for 72 million dollars recently
Christie's Auction and so
You hear a lot of people talking about art
As indictment
All says it all the time you should buy art
You should buy real estate a good investment
And in fact
It's better than stocks
But he says
That's wrong
And I can tell you as an economist just from Theory
That should not be
So here's is a Konami
Alta can I give you a choice
You can buy a painting
Or you can buy a bond
And in 10 years
They both can agree on value and be able to sell them for the exact same mm
Which would you pay more
Well I guess
Is the bond pretty
Is the painting pretty
And I can hang it on my wall you can hang on your wall
I guess I would pay more for the painting and the 10 years that I'm going to be keeping it before I sell it back
Right so at the end of 10 years or both can be worth
Same
And you just told me you're willing to pay more for the
Painting right
Crappy financial and passing rate your pain
More than you would for the bond but you're getting the same
Borat make the banda crappy
Aesthetic
Piped financially speaking
If you don't care about our am I going to put it
You're better off always here
Putting it in stocks and bonds
Benton AR
Least in theory that should that should be true
So he wanted to test that
Turn that soda hard to test because
Need a good dataset of art sales
And that's when he found
The book
Bi-Rite linger
Outrageous we have it here
I think it's called the economies of taste
The rise and fall of the picture Market 1763 19:6
60 by Gerald reitlinger
House
Pages and pages of
Works of art
Going back
Several centuries
That work
By the leading auction houses
So here
Rembrandt house Rembrandt night so Rembrandt
The painting is old man in a black hat
Bought by Lord Scarsdale 1761 for 210 lb
1760 numbers and statistically analyzed
What we found
Exactly what had been
Predicted by the theory
By you
Buy me
It turns out that art
Was a good investment
Is paid off an aesthetic
But in terms of dollars
You were much better off
Buying stocks
Awesome Bunz
Okay so stocks and bonds are better than ours
Okay what if you bought like a Monet
Yeah I think he's talking about a portfolio of all artists
I mean a PreSonus Peace during the day
Now but if you bought
Dave Roberts Raton
Here's the quote that went along with that
In the Heyday of mid-victorian romantic
Kate the watercolors of David Roberts
With a delight of King
Is fussy
It's fuzzy oil paintings and Interiors of churches could make clothes on 2,000 pounds in the sales room
But
In 1933 that's 70 years after his death
One of them sold for just 10 guineas
Which is Amazon
So
Art analyst
Art critics curators are about as accurate in the long-term a stock analyst it sounds like
Who's a very good short-term
Play but not not too many want to buy it
Dave Roberts
Don't buy at home
Hey it's a lie again back in the present
William baumol died in 2017
With 95
And in the spirit bomb wallpaper
We wanted to know what would have happened if you had taken his advice
So
What would have happened if you'd invested in stocks
Say instead of in a collection of art
All right
If back in 2010
You had taken $10,000
And invested in the S&P 500 index of stocks
You would have over $28,000 now
Now that does not include management fees which
Would be small
And doesn't include taxes
But still it's a 180 percent return over 9 issue years
Not that
Now
What about if you had taken that $10,000 and put it into art
Artprice.com has this index of art bought and sold around the world
We got the spreadsheet
We ran the numbers and
Still is not an amazing
Investment
According to this index of millions of sales of paintings sculptures drawings
Your $10,000 would likely have lost
Money about an 11% loss
And that's not even taking into account things like high sales commissions storage cost
But
Maybe you don't like having an iceberg made out of sugar sitting in the living room
Maybe that would have been worth it to you
We are interested in what kinds of animals
You think should be pickled in formaldehyde
Email us Planet Money at mpr.org we are also on Twitter Facebook and Instagram at Planet Money
Also I want to let you know that our video series Planet Money shorts
Is at it again
Give a new video out about fancy vodka and whether it is worth
The money
Producer Alexi Horowitz Ghazi has a star turn check it out npr.org
Planet Money shorts
This episode was originally reported by Alex blumberg and David kestenbaum
The rerun was produced by Rachel Cohn and Darian Woods
I'm finally home thanks for listening