This is Panama
There is something about
A food cup
You know like
Top Chef chopped
My personal favorite
The Great British Bake Off
That to me is Magic
And I think what it is is something that we all have to do everyday
A chore
And make it into a drop
We are still alive
I personally didn't want Jamie to have
To do a crappy dip you didn't at all your own dishes
So good
Empty the other day
I got to talk to one of the people who not only knows the tricks that these shows use
She invented some
All right before we start can you just introduce yourself
I'm done in Martinez
I'm the executive producer / showrunner of Top Chef
And what was your
First job
I was a production assistant season 1
You start at the bottom
Now you're the boss
Yeah
Janine and I got
The talking about her
Show it's now headed into its 17
But honestly
Pretty soon our conversation just turned into this like
Therapy /
Advice session
For producers
We
Do a lot of shows around here at Planet Money
Recovery economics
Every single day business and economics
And
We
You know it starts to be the same sort of thing
Not to say it's boring but you know what
Betrayed
Reserved
Okay and
What we are looking to talk
Do you about today
Is how to take something that may seem mundane
Like cooking
And make it exciting
And
For you to teach us some of the tricks of food competition shows
So that we can use them to spice up our
That sound cool
Yeah
Alright we usually start a show by saying hello and welcome the planet money and then our name so would you do that
Hello and welcome to Planet Money this is Donnie Martinez
Yeah and I'm the fountain
Today in the show we're going to open up the inbox
And take listener questions
On food and food-related thing
Can I got to say
There are some
Pretty weird question
But the Planet Money Team
Is going to do what we do everyday
We can report them out
And this show is going to be unlike any we've ever
Cuz Deneen is going to tell us how to use the methods of a food competition show
To make our show
Shein
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Peloton
And their newest product the Peloton tread
Keep up with your fitness goals through your busy summer
Without ever leaving home
Peloton tread operator live on demand running strength bootcamp and stretching class
It's not just another trend
It's a live at home cardio and strength experience
Discover the total body training you can get from Peloton tread
Peloton is offering listeners a limited-time offer
Go to onepeleton.com and use the code Planet Money
How to get $100 off accessories with the purchase of a tread
Greg
Yeah
What are you doing here again
I read a newsletter
Where can people get that sweet sweet content
Npr.org Planet Money newsletter that's what I can say
That's what they contain up yet
So what we're going to do today is
Is bringing
Of the reporter
They already know the listener question they're going to Aunt
What they do not know ahead of time
Is there
Challenge
They do not know the tricks that I learned
From
Executive producer Danny norkinas
Tremendous
First one we talked about
Kind of old hat for food competition shows
But it's maybe my favorite ingredient you guys use the surprise ingredient
We do try to do too much cuz there are a lot of shows that do that
So it's kind of a Trope at this point yeah
Ingredients for you at
What what is it about
Surprising
Because
It's one of those things where it's like
It's very straightforward
People can see it
And then they can t even do it at home
Easy
Simple effective
Not yet a Trope in radio journalism
Let's do it
Our first question comes from Alicia ardoin
In California
And Alicia had heard something about choco pie
Switcher Sardis like
Whoopie pie moon pie small things
She heard that they became part
Of the underground economy
In North Korea
And she wanted to know more
So I asked Elise you welcome
I feel a sense
Some dread
Good
You started NPR south
Bureau
You covered North Korea
A ton
What is going on
Which occupies
North Koreans love
I'm going to interrupt you
Yes before you tell us about choco pies
Okay
The producer at the NPR
Pets in La where you work
Should be coming in
We ask Mary to
Scrounger on the office
And find a secret ingredient
Do you have to work into your side
A can of tuna
Euro I know you always
That is your surprise ingredient
And you have to figure out a way to work that into your story on choco pies go
Okay so choco pies are choco pies as we call it choco pies is there no
Nincada Korean
Language
Figure into geopolitics
The politics of North Korea and South Korea
Because
While they were
Popular in South Korea like this
Since the 90
1870s they weren't introduced
Two North Korean until 2000
What happened in 2000
So they made their way up
Across the border through something called the
Kaesong industrial complex
This was a
Joint North
South
Special economic
This is like an industrial Zone there is North Korean workers working at South Korean factories
Making shoes and clothes and whatever
Yeah it's usually cheap
Alright so it's a lot of manufacturing going on
And
They're just one Factory after another out there
Okay bring this back to choco pies and or tuna
Okay so
The reason choco pies come into play is
North Korean workers who labored there they weren't actually paid directly by their bosses
The
South Korean businesses had to
To pay the North Korean regime
So we don't know how much the worker
Actually
Okay
Korean managers could do is pay in snacks
And at first it was delicious right when they were first introduced some 15 years ago was like okay
The fun snack I get a reward but after your 5th choco pie
Not so great right which then created this burgeoning
Choco pie
Black Market
It is not a capital
Country but there is a rather
Lively Black Market
And so North Korean workers and stop eating the choco pies
And start selling them
In order to me
The money on the black
2 by the sea
But they wanted
I can imagine that the North Korean government
Did not appreciate
These
Symbols of capitalism
Seeping into everyday life
Right plus they filled the black market
So in 2014 North Korea band
And the result
Is
The black mark
Value of choco pies jump from
One US dollar
10 US dollars
Do you have any sense of like how much say
A can of tuna would go for on the black market look at YouTube
And you still haven't tied it together so bring it home what is this mean
For North Korea and the
Often North Koreans
North Korean fishermen defect
In order to get into South
Korea by boat
Okay and
I guess occasionally they are fishing for
Tuna
Right
Choco pies are also
Huge factor in a
Defector story
From
November of 27
Okay
Tell me that story where was it
The 24-year old North
Korean Defector who made a daring Escape across that border work with a little
Blue Hut sorry that you probably
He ran through that border in November of
He was shot at
By his fellow soldiers
40 *
And then eventually rescued by South Kerr
US soldier
Turn on the other side
What's he woke up
The first thing he asked was
I can if
We know that he definitely asked for a Choco pie we don't know what fish he asked for but if possible
Anyway still Orion the company
That makes choco pies
Set a hundred boxes
Is of them to his hospital room
And then
Is
Continuing to
Supply him for life
Lifetime supply of choco pie
Elise you nailed your assignment thank you for sneaking that
Got into this very informative interview
Okay what's the newest member of the Planet Money Team
What's your listener Quest
Okay so my listener question is
How do you get the
The best salad value-wise at a salad bar
Consumption diamond in Somerville Massachusetts
But before you answer the question
I asked anene
How Top Chef might have gone about making mistakes
Limitations
You do some challenges on location
So they're in a new
Places I've never been before
New equipment that I've never used before
You know they have to figure out
How they're going to work within the space they never seen
And then kind of work with what's their like let's say it's we take them camping and there's
An open flame
They've got a pot
They have to work with
So they're going to figure out
How to work around that
So I have this reporter
Who is answering
A question about
Salad bar
Interesting
You think we should just make her
Do all her interviews at the
The salad bar
At rush hour
Absolutely
Liza are you ready
Fight get out of here and when you're back
Tell me what happened
And we're back
Much like on a cooking show the thing we just talked about mere seconds ago is already complete
Liza
What you get into
So I went out into the world looking for a salad bar where I could answer the question
We are Midtown expensive salads
Home of hundreds of businessmen lining up around the block to
To buy $20 salads in a posse box
So sad
15 straight shot 15 minute walk so I was looking for a salad bar
Rush Hour hey getting closer
Deli chain on Madison Avenue
So I asked the first person I met if there was someone I could talk to you about the salad
Got plenty to a manager and he pointed Me chords
Southern
Apron I really don't know
Why
Events manager sent me his way
Well because
If you are a person getting a salad what do you do
Island
Bye
Like to be honest
You would never by Zella.
Yet so
Kate salad bar
Needle
Is there
New other foods to buy
Now that's the last option that I have
Okay
I mean now I'll buy it
But if not I'll just get a burger
Like rolling his eyes and shaking his head and
Smiling
Like he knows how much they overcharge
Play Pusha my little bit I was like
Even if you had to go to a salad bar what would your Saturday
And he
With basically like
My strategy
Is to walk around the salad bar
And
Open up the case that has the prepared food in it
Prepared food potato salads are made like in another state last night
You'd like
Common misconception
Look at this dude over here
We're selling it for 699 a pound
Can you go to the salad bar
You know how much cost
No time for it
Okay don't be a snob don't avoid the pre-made salads
Did you have any other tips
No
He didn't
So if it was obviously not going to be that helpful I left a salad bar watch out on the Street Watching other 10 minutes
And I found salad bar advertising lunch I'm going to say how much pants
Salad bar meaning
They just put out the buffet and all that Foods were piled really
Perfect scoop
Taken out of them
There's other jazz music lovely soundtrack
So I got there any message
This guy Tony Lee
Tony is the guy who buys everything
He knows exactly how much money they're making and losing on everything they sell
And he was not about to tell me all his Secrets but he had one very basic steps that he was
Willing to share
Recommended people don't get too much of the right when you get this much the rice
Yeah you're you're making like a Jamaican like a bit
Daylight
Big V bucks
Yes so at the salad bar you have three different kinds of rice
Three big
Shiny silver tabs beautiful silver types of rice
We make a lot of money what should we be by
So there is this
Amazing things that happened at
Sony Soundbar which is at once a week
Big lobster and salmon
No
That one
Expanse did they buy it
For $20
The pound
And they sell it in the salad bar for 11:49 a pound
Alaska
Like almost half the money you're losing
Weeping 3014
They have a lobster and Dave a lot of group
They're banking on people coming in and getting a little bit of lobster and a lot of rice
So you're saying we should just
Take the salmon envelopes
I mean
Tony told me that
Get the timer
If you can
I would have never thought that
Salad bar was losing money on any single ingredient
So the purest form of saving your money at the salad bar is literally just like looking for the thing
That cost the most out that the salad bar and filling up your box
With only that
Grilled lemon salmon which edit
This is the best deal they told me yeah
Yeah I'll go in right after you
Thank you
That guy may not have been interested in your salad bar tips
But I am
Bring it home what else did you learn
I truly thought this is a great tip I loved it
But
To be fair it was not the real answer that I listen to whistle
So you actually answer the question
I came back with
Awesome
This is the ideal salary
Valley-wide yes
I meant
Okay I am
Seeing a lot of leafy greens
They're basically are a lot of Craisins and like nuts a toppings very expensive office alagar
Working a lot
Not a lot of veggies
No water weight
And I noticed that you
You took Tony device there is some salmon in here
Gladiator thank you so much for answering Sean's question and thanks for the salad
It's actually for me
Okay goodbye
Okay next up Darian Woods
Welcome to the studio what is your question that your aunt
Leonardo Plaza Pond listening from Texas ask
Why do Americans refrigerate their eggs
Nobody around the world does that
But before we enter
We asked Deneen how tops
Chef would add some dramatic tension to the segment
And she told us this
Time
Time is it an easy way to
Kind of
Up the ante with things that the oldest trick in the book works every time
No pun intended
I think so
Yeah
It's not everybody works
Against the clock that's not a normal
All right I have my timer here Darren Woods
60 seconds why do Americans refrigerate their eggs
Go 60 Seconds
And I'm just starting
Rid of five of those already
Squandered
Salmonella that is Beyonce
Because if you have a little bit of salmonella in an egg
It's going to grow and grow if you've got variable high temperature
Refrigerator cake
What's the temperature lows
Stable and the bacteria doesn't grow as fast
People get poisoned less frequent
35 European
They don't require as much handling and care with the actual eggs
American egg processors also wash their eggs which is this whole other thing with custom benefits that I kind of get into in 66
Which works better the European vaccination method or the American Refrigeration
Look it's hard to tell but why not do both
Who was salmonella Ritz
The terrible disease that kills
Americans a year from egg related salmonella
You're saying no one to dive song
I would like for there to be no decimal
You got 10 seconds left what do you want to say just want to give a shout out to my girlfriend and my family
And also the beat
Poultry hotline
They gave you some
Archie magoulas
He's my good friend now
There's a timer well done
Darien I can't believe you explain that so quickly I'm talking really fast goodbye
Welcome back to the studio thank you
What is the question that you're going to answer
Okay my question comes from Nate hibore in Hudsonville Michigan
And he is in a state where they've got the
The $0.10 deposit on the Kansas side of the five cent and he wanted to know if having that higher deposit
Made any difference
Prince anything
Okay and because yours is the last one we're going to make it
Especially hard
Oh good
Denis told me that sometimes to make good TV
You got to take people
Where they come
One of the ways is to think about
The food
In a different way than its
Known for give us a dish that
Looks like one thing but tastes like another
Heath like another
What would that sound like
Well
I guess you can have the reporter sing it
What genre
Which country probably would be the best
You know
Telling the story
Keeper emergency
Make you kind of uncomfortable you look kind of uncomfortable I mean I literally don't play the guitar
For 1
I am I allowed to like bringing help
Coming up after the break
Teeth
Writes a country song
There are roughly 1.9 billion acres of land in the United States
The indicator from NPR looks at how that land is divided and what all that has to do with
A Happy Meal
Keep your back
You've had a couple days to write a country song about Michigan
10 cent can redemption rate
Edge
You've Got a Friend I found somebody who could play a guitar
Is my friend John pinamonti the country singer
We're just going to have is going to do it
What's January tuned up here to go home already man I was born ready
Alright well I'm going to start by
Tell me one story
Going for it and then I'm going to sing you a different story
The first story
When I'm just going to tell you starts back in 1976 back then
Michigan had themselves a problem
The problem was this
On the shores of Lake Michigan
Well just everywhere empty bottles empty cans
And the people
Rose up and they passed the laws from now on there's going to be a $0.10 deposit on every bottle
And every can
That's a true story
It's always this song
It's called The Ballad of the $0.10 man
It's about a man in 2016 who decided I know about some cans
Down in Kentucky where there ain't no tens and deposit to get them I'm going to drive them back to Michigan and
He figured that was a pretty good idea Michigan
Man had a crazy dream aluminum cans got a silver atom
Did Rich perfect plan didn't have a hitch Asia cup get out of Dodge
Cocaine Arbitrage for a thousand bucks drove from Kentucky
Mm candy might get lucky with better than a nickel without Wizards
All Ghana costume is the gas at the time if you're wondering
If Michigan paying $0.10 a can instead of $0.05 a can made a difference will I was well John I can tell you
That it did last year just under 90% of cans in Michigan got returned that's 10
30% higher than in Nicola can States in 1992 in Michigan
100.4 % of cans got return
And that's hard
How to do
Yes it is
Okay let's get back to the song about our arbitrageur that's a real word by the way
Vocabulary by the time you got back it was late God
College bait
The last of the perfect plan had just one flaw out-of-state cans were against the law
Thousand bucks he drove from Kentucky 10000 cans in my Get Lucky
Nichols was always a prison
The cop at the trial that the truck was packed with 10000 KN to be
Exact the judge said you don't have to go to jail just 1,200 bucks in the mail when the judge
Just imagine what he had to say I made a huge mistake your honor
I regret it
Everyday he
That's a real quote
Thousand bucks he drove from Kentucky the 10,000 cans in my Get Lucky
Better than a nickel what's worse is a $1,200
It cost a lot more
Then the gas
Is really happened you can Google it
It's just
So good
You guys nailed it
Thank you so much
Eunuch
John Tesh
My pleasure
You guys help me with credit
Going to take us out
Old accent comes with the job
Worried about the next recession or are chord progression you can ride is it flooded money
Npr.org this episode was produced by Nick Fountain and engineered by eyes
Isaac Rodriguez latest sound so pretty Darian Woods Liza and Cynthia Bay to Pisa
Helped out with producing music www.com
You can just Google Play money is edited by Brian Dorsett Alex goldmark is the super
Surviving producer many many thanks to dunean are heinous I'm Keith Rover I'm Nick.
Johnson & Johnson manati PR thanks for listening
We got it
Wwww.