I started working on the story about recycling
I did not expect a lost ship
And the mob
Well I can tell you a story that is actually quite interesting about the origination of recycling
He's a professor of Economics at Bucknell University
To be able to understand why Americans embraced recycling you have to understand the story of the Garbage barge or the garbage ship
How the mobro
The mobro the mobro mo
Dro tell me the story the problem is
Probably this guy was allegedly part of the mafia so I don't get into mad at me still alive I don't know you can Google it
He is still alive
And yeah
We've kind of recycling
Tell the mafia
To the so-called five families in New York who made up the Italian-American Mafia
You know the gambinos
John Gotti
That Mafia
Specifically we owe recycling to a guy named
Salvatore avellino
Cell
A chauffeur and Mabus
Lucchese crime family
Who controlled garbage hauling on Long Island
Got 10 years
Spur conspiring in the murders of two garbage men
And
I found Sal
Okay
I'm going to call a real
Actual my boss
Hello
That's all
Redis Salvatore
Yes my name is Sarah
I am doing I work for an economics show and I'm doing a story about
The Garbage barge
I know that it's kind of a complicated story
But I want to see if you would chat with me about it
Well
I really rather not I'll be honest with you I want to be polite but
Good luck but I really don't want to talk about
Was the greatest idea but I was way ahead of my time
Autumn
I don't want to really go into it okay
I'm sorry
Okay do you mind telling me why you don't want to talk about it
Oh yes
Okay yes
He mines
Okay okay okay thank you so much all the time
You're welcome
Okay
Decades ago
Sal
How to business partner
A guy named Lowell Harrelson of Mobile Alabama
Not a mafia guy just a regular guy
I'm so glad that I got in touch with you
Nice to meet you
I'm hoping you did too
I wish you would
Lowell also
Does not want to tell me the story
I mean okay would you be open to just chatting with me like 5 minutes
Sound like a nice lady you give me a call
Lavazza coffee
Well then I think I'm going to plan a trip to mobile
Very good you let me know when you plan to run I would even pick you up
Okay
Okay hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzalez today
The greatest
Shame and secret of mole Harrelson's life
That changed garbage in the US forever is part 1 of 2 shows
And the first story involves
The mafia
A talking Jaguar a bug and six million pounds of trash
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working for nourish the common good by donating all profits from Newman's Own food products to charitable
Stations that seek to make the world a better place more information is available at Newman's Own Foundation.
Got to work
Next time on rough translation
The feeling you get when
Quit your job and try to start something new
You're a loser you you're worthless
An entrepreneur from Mexico faces down that taboo and accidentally launches a global community that sell it
Liberate stories of failure mistakes I was making was part of my journey
Travel with rough translation from NPR listen And subscribe
I pull up to the wrong White House with pink flowers in the front yard
Honey low tells me this is Mobile Alabama everything in this area is a white house with
Pink flowers in the front yard
Find the right house and Lowell is
Standard driveway waiting for me
Hello
Lolnexus
Chat at his kitchen table for an hour before he's ready to get into the Garbage barge and when he's finally ready
He sits up
A little taller
Will you just say your name
Lowell Harrelson
Harrelson
If you ask
Lowell Harrelson how old is he answers
Beaming with pride
Can you believe that
Still running on two cylinders
And what is your title
Really have a title anymore
Entrepreneur
Businessman
I guess you could call it that that sounds rather sophisticated for somebody like me
You can call me a farmer if you like that's how I grew up
They were sharecroppers
Group corn cotton
Potatoes
All kinds of vegetables
Typical
Capital of Alabama
Lowell grew up in a home
With no trash
We did not have a trash can
No ma'am
Wooden ammo trash
Everything we had to eat we've raised on that farm that we ate
We did get a 5 lb of sugar once in awhile
They'd also get a 50lb bag of flour low remembers the bag came with these
Little flower designs on it for my mama made my sister school dresses
No waste
No traction
Goodnight something
We were happy
All those are the days
Those days where in the 1930s
And at some point in Los life
Things changed
Now we produce
So much garbage
My God
UCI match garbage
How can we do that
This is where Lowell story with garbage
Really takes off
It's the 80
Lolis in the construction business but
Like a lot of people at the time he's thinking about
Alternative Energy
And he hears about a guy in Westchester New York
Who was turning
Garbage
Into energy
And little things
All that stuff that I hate sitting in landfills
Has this
Hidden
Use
So your motivation was to turn garbage
Into energy
That's correct
Garbage to energy it look like a very simple deal
He consults with them engineers and they say
Yeah this is a thing this works
When you pile of trash it decomposes and emits methane gas
And you can use methane to make Power
So if we got enough garbage we could sell the electricity
To the grade
Everybody agreed this had married
It was a question of putting the pieces together
By the way we use this message today to get energy from landfills but back then it was a new idea and
Lowell
Stop business opportunity
He was going to create a huge
Pile of garbage
And use it for electricity
But he would need a lot of garbage
Your local dump that wasn't enough garbage he needed
Boatloads of garbage
And at the time if you were interested in garbage
New York
What's the place
New York City in the 80s had begun running out of landfill space and
How to start paying other states to take their garbage
Salal is like Perfect all use some of that garbage for my
Big pile of garbage plan
But in New York
At the time
Garbage was controlled
By the mob
Oh yes now that's a story that'll take lot more time than we have today
Garbage in New York
That was like a control Subs
That was a cartel that control the flow of garbage
And that's a good deal.
But he didn't know any of this at the time
All he knew was if you wanted to buy garbage in New York
He needed to talk to a guy named cell
You already know esl
I really rather not
Spell had guys who collected New York trash
But they still had to pay to dump the trash somewhere to get it landfill
And Lowell
Keto Sal
What if I take the garbage off your hands
For Less
Think about it
And then the FBI shows up at Lowe's store
FBI spoke to me two or three times you know
Hey what are you up to
Hauling garbage
You got any proton
And that's when he said though you know you dealing with the mob that's what it was
No I didn't know that
But it doesn't matter
I'm trying to make energy over here
Lowell knowingly gets into business
With the mafia
Because it didn't really feel like working with the mafia there was a ride in a stretch Cadillac limo that was a
A little scary for Lowell there was a dinner with Sal
Some guy told Lil where to sit and that's
Swear law LSAT
And that was it
Laurelwood by Sal's
Garbage
He's a nice guy
I like that
He's the guy that had to talk in Jaguar you never heard about that
The talking
Jaguar
This is a tangent but I mean there's a talking Jaguar we have to
Salvatore avellino had a 1982 black
Jaguar that's what he drove the boss
Antonio Tony ducks
Carollo in
Tony ducks
Because he duck
Law enforcement
At least
Until this one thing happened on a rainy night in March of 1980
Salvatore's black jaguar is parked outside of a restaurant on Long Island
An agent
Open the door
Another agent hold
Some kind of
Cover over the Jaguar to make sure that
No rain drops spot
Deceit
Do you remove the dashboard
Lease a bug inside
Put the dashboard back
They tapped
Sal's Jaguar
And this bug recorded mob conversations that eventually took down all 5 bosses of the mafia
The car
Talked
The talking Jaguar
Okay back to Lowell
Lowe's not doing anything illegal
He's just buying garbage
He arranges with the landfill in North Carolina
That he's going to dump
Tons of New York garbage there
Create a methane
Paradise
So at okay so you had the source you have the seller you had landfills agreeing to take the garbage
Next
He has to move the garbage down
And the cheapest way to do that is by boat
Barge actually he gets one from Jacksonville Florida called the mobro 4000 a big
Flat iron deck to load the garbage onto
And he gets a tugboat from New Orleans called the break of dawn
To tow the barge
A tugboat little tiny little cute little tugboat
Pound for pound nothing more powerful
The notable
The barge gets loaded up in New York
20 feet high hell down with
Cables
And on March 22nd 1987
Tons of garbage
Set sail
Steered by
Captain Duffy St
Pierre St-Pierre one of the best in the business
Were You There When it got loaded up
Are you aware
I know I was watching that like a mama watch over her new baby
What you talking about
At that time of my life my whole life was tied to that thing
At that time Lowell is
Full of Hope
I told Debbie the captain now hurry up and get back here fast as you can so we can get another load down there for the weekend you know
Are you ready you're ready to
Oh yeah
Yeah we ready to load up
The barge is moving
Very slowly
And people start noticing
Like
What is that thing
And somewhere else in there
Crowd started showing up
I know the news newspaper people
TV people
All the popes
I want to know who this idiot is
All in all this garbage around I said here I am
What else can I say
Remember New York was already Trucking garbage to other states so
Lowell didn't think a ship would be any different
But somehow
The site of this barge
Full of trash coming down the coast
Did not sit well with
People all these people
We don't want that garbage in our
Wonderful state
Immediately it was pretty obvious this is going to be a whole different problem than what I had
I have not anticipated
Now this is just
Normal garbage from people's homes nothing especially toxic or dangerous about it
But
The EPA had just released new rules that said you couldn't dump toxic waste in landfills anymore
Someone said they saw bedpan on the barge like from a hospital or something
So everyone got it into their heads that
There must be some Yankee mobster toxic waste hidden on the barge
And they're trying to unload it on us
A court order
Lock the barge
From unloading in North Carolina
I couldn't
Do anything more to try to force their hand which was discussed you know we had a valid country
But to try to force their hand would not have helped anybody
So what do you do now
I told him
Don't Debbie get out in the ocean get away from this crowd
Get Alma Over the Horizon
Drop anchor and let's give us some time to think
You know
Are you drop the anchor so it's just hanging out in the ocean
Until we could
Meet see what we going to do that
At some point Florida goes
Well we'll take it will charge you this much to unloaded here come on over
So there goes Duffy
We get there in the coast of Florida somewhere
Outcomes crowd of 10000
Dead again
Where we went it drew big crowds
Alabama is a don't even think about bringing it here
Lowell has the barge tied to a cypress tree on the Mississippi River waiting
Mississippi
Didn't want it
Louisiana
Don't bring it here either
It was like a soap opera a helicopter is following the barge around its on the Nightly News like
Who will say no tomorrow
That garbage has been unsuccessfully seeking a home
For almost a month-and-a-half now still loaded with tons of garbage
Still on water
So this little Tugboat is tugging the barge around looking for a home
Poor Captain Duffy St-Pierre campdoc anywhere to take a shower
Aventon
And it seems like everyone is following
The Garbage barge
The most watched load of garbage in the memory of man dripping Brown ooze of possibly infectious mean
Material people everywhere talking about how they found syringes and
What not
Nothing
The EPA comes out in white suits and breathing mask
To inspect the garbage
They determine it's fine
It's just garbage
Does it matter
The Mexican Navy went to the barge to deliver a message
Stacked the barge
Was not wanted in my
Belize
The Bahamas
They sent out their Defense Forces
Do not
Bring it here
And the Lord says
He wasn't actually trying to send the garbage to other countries
They just thought he was
Too close to them I guess
They were just so surprising something of that magnitude did like it did it
So surprising it was
Nothing really
So the barges
Bobbing in the water in the Gulf of Mexico
2 months
Three months four months
Waves of saltwater
Crashing over the garbage baking in the sun covered in flies
Probably seagulls
Play that you started
Emotions of mine
What people took from the image of this Garbage barge
Sailing around from us
Was that there was no place for the garbage to go
It became a symbol for America's problem with trash
We've run out of places to throw away our throw away my 1990 Accord
According to One Federal survey at least 27 States will be critically short of space to dump garbage
Everyone is like
What have we done
What have we done to this country we filled it
With trash
Movies are made about the barge
It was a film called Sex Lies and videotape them in again
In the movie he says the main character starts out
Sitting on a therapist couch
The very first scene of the movie and she's like
I just can't sleep at night
Where is all the garbage going
Garbage
All I've been thinking about all week is garbage I mean I just can't stop thinking about it
NFL
We have to ride a place to put this stuff eventually
Last time I
I started feeling this way as when
That barge stranded in you know what's going around the island and nobody would claim it
Remember that
Yes
There were all these
That's coming out at the time
That showed that the number of landfills in America
Was
Plummeting
Landfills were closing
And people kept signing me stats in stories
About the Garbage barge
Info people put it all together and their minds
They conclusion west of the United States is running out of landfill space
United States
Wistful
That we couldn't store anymore
And where we fool
We weren't full the reason why the
Happening at the time
Yes
Landfills
We're closing
But that was because there were new rules for landfills
Stricter rules to protect the environment
BPA said you know have to do things like line the bottom of landfills with plastic so they don't contaminate the ground
And so the old town dump every little town had one
Without of compliance
You can't accept garbage in here anymore if you legal
And so these Town dumps for closing by the dozens
In their place
Regional landfills we're becoming a thing bigger landfills that could accept trash
While still following all these new rules
The natural resources defense Council says
They used to be about 10,000 dumps in the mid-80s and that now we have
Less than 3000
But we were not running out of space then
And
We still aren't running out of space
Thomas says we probably have
Thousands of years of landfill space left in the US
And even
Hardcore environmentalists reluctantly agree that
Yeah we have a lot of space left
But people
Thought we were running out of space
And
That was What mattered
And so the recycling era was born
This is when state government said we're going to require cycling
2 up cycling to occur
This is when people started
Separating their paper and plastic into little bins in their homes and offices
Because of lowland the mafia is garbage
That have more of an impact on society then
Anything else you talked about I was
That's where that's why we recycle Tuesday
Who knows we be without that barge
Recycling became the answer to a problem that
Didn't exist
They were good environmental reasons for it of course less weighs less pollution but that's not what convinced cities
Used to start sending trucks to everyone's homes
To pick up their glass bottles and cardboard box
Fear
Convince us to do that
With lies that cost more in his abilities had to figure out ways to make it work
Financially in
Any kind of
Been moving along since then
Lowe's Garbage barge made of 5 months
Thousand Mile Journey before it found a home
A judge order the trash took go back to where it came from
New York
To be burned
Greenpeace hung up a sign that said
Next time
Driver side
The ashes were buried in the landfill
Lowell
Paid
How much money did you lose
That's the most embarrassing Secret of My Life
More than I would ever want to dream of
It was a worse
Proposition I ever got into okay
And forever will be known as that dummy who sell the Garbage barge
What elixir
What a legacy
How do you feel about I mean
You are basically
The reason why
We recycle
I understand all that
But it doesn't reduce my pain of being the world's biggest dummy okay
No you are not the world's biggest gummy
But it did help me in one respect I guess
Law says the barge taught him an important lesson
That some issues are so
Totally unpredictable
If he could go back to school he says he's want to study anthropology
Understand why people hate the things they hate
My garbage
On my Tombstone I would like them to say this old boy did his damnedest okay
Alright with me if they refer to that dummy that that barge in the ocean
Shoot Me Vine
They put that on my Tombstone is a lie
I don't have any hard feelings toward anybody
I have nothing but love and respect for people wherever they are and whoever they are
And I'm not the least bit worried about leg
I mean
So
We recycle now
But should we
That's next time on Planet Money
Support Division PR podcast in the following message come from Dino the Capital One assistant that catches things that might
Right look wrong with your credit card
Send you an alert and helps you fix them
Another way they're watching out for your money when you're not
What's in your wall
See capitalone.com / details
The world is come
But knowing the past can help us understand it's so much better
That's where we come in
I'm run down detector
Where the host
The through line
NPR History podcast
Every week we'll dig into forgotten stories from the moments that shaped our world
Through line
From NPR
Listen and
Subscribe now
Planet money has made another video this video is based on our episode about the man who
The lottery
And one a dozen time
We find out how he pulled it off
You can watch the video on npr.org
Planet Money shorts
And willing to wait on our Instagram and Facebook
If you have a story idea send an email Planet Money at npr.org
Today Show was produced by Sally Helm Bryant or set at is our show and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer
Rachel Cohn and our intern Cynthia better Visa help
So much
Without checking
And if you want to help out Planet Money leave us a rating or review us in your podcast app
I'm sorry when Silas this is NPR Bigfoot
On the next Planet Money
Part 2
Unfortunately
Recycling is
I'm not saying it's dead
But
Is it certainly
I wouldn't say life support but it's critical
And I don't want to be the person to burst their bubble
You will not be the one to Break people's bubble
I will burst their bubble
Me and a bunch of cold
Parted economist