Support for NPR in the following message
Did come from Pushkin and dust
Resetting the podcast
Broken record
Rick Rubin Malcolm Gladwell and Bruce Hedley
Sit down with the musicians you love
To talk about their lives work and the music
Listen to season 2
Wherever you get your podcasts
Thanks for listening to Planet Money
We'd like to better understand who is listening in
And how you are using podcast
Please help us out by completing a short Anonymous survey at npr.org podcast survey
It takes 10 minutes and really help support the show
That's npr.org
Flash podcast survey
Just a heads up there is
One bad word in this episode
But it comes up a lot
It's the f word and as you'll hear
We just can't avoid it
And actually there's
A couple other bad words in here
Jen Lewis was a doodler
Never been the class clown I was really quiet in school
This is the most of it
She has the type of humor that sneaks up on you
Would you say that your
A comedian
No I guess
I would call myself like an internet
Humorous
But I have imposter syndrome so I've never said that turn before until right now she gets paid
To make funny things on the internet for companies like net
Netflix Embassy
One of Jen's first viral hits came in 2015
Kanye West and Kim Kardashian were at the Grammys
There's a picture of them kissing
And Jen decides to have a little fun with
I photoshopped Kanye's head on to Kim's body replace Kim's hands of Kanye's hands
Just like Kanye's hands on Kanye's face on
Yeah Kanye's hand on Kanye's butt
Kanye's hands on
Kanye shoulder
And a warm embrace and 11
Loving
It's Kanye
Kissing
Kanye and it looks extremely realistic
Jen
Put into a picture with the world in 2015 already had an inkling about
That no one loves Kanye West
More than Kanye West
She posted it on Twitter and the next day the picture was everywhere
All over the internet
It ended up spray painted on a giant wall and Australia
Eventually Kanye West even comes out with this song which seems like it could be describing Jen's picture
We still love Kanye and I love you like Kanye
Loves Kanye I maybe had part of it
Except
Wenjun tweeted her picture out the day after the Grammys
She only got 221 likes
Her picture went viral because this
Hugely popular Instagram account
Shared her picture on his page
You might have heard of this account it's called
F word
Jerry like
Brick
Siri
And it has millions of followers
Fun Jerry share Jen's picture the day after she made it and he wrote that Kanye kissing Kanye looked
Absolutely
Terrifying
And he's supposed
Got a hundred and forty thousand like Switchback then mint it went viral
So like inflation turn
Yeah
Pretty good
I know this viral picture could have been a giant advertisement
For Jen and her career
But
No one knows she made this did they credit you
No
It sucks because then you know
People don't know that it came from you and that was my that was my joke that was my idea
Jen says she asked
Both Jerry to creditor but that no one responded
Empty bothered her at first
But she got over it until Jen found out that f
Jerry
Could make as much as $30,000 for posting a single add-on his
I don't care if someone just posting my jokes because they think they're funny and they want their followers to see
But if they put a price tag on those eyes
I think you should be paying them what felt annoying to Jen in 2015
Now felt
A lot more
Like that
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Sarah Gonzales and I'm Biloxi Horwitz gazi so is Sharingan
Friends picture
Theft
As long as people have been making jokes
Other people have been stealing them
The internet has made taking jokes easier and more lucrative than ever before
Today on the show comedians band together to take on one of the biggest alleged joke thieves on the internet
We look at the weird history of stolen jokes
And how one tactic may be the only way
To prevent it
Also
We confront
The Mastermind who stole gems joke
Borrowed
Curated
We are not here for the likes
We're here for the money
Support for this podcast
In the following math
Message come from mizzenandmain
Mizzen & Main dress shirts are made with performance fabric
Designed to look great all day
With minimal maintenance
There moisture
Wrinkle-resistant and machine washable
So they don't require ironing or dry clean
Check out their gift guide
Where the guy on your lip
Who is always on the move
Handsome is it in Maine.
Michelin Man
Look great
Longer use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
Okay back in 2011 when Instagram was just
2 year old and we were all just posing
Sunset
A couple scrapy Millennials were
Scouring the internet for the funniest things they could find
And putting them all on their feet
Weed memes text messages
Pictures you don't have to worry about who made
You can just
Scroll through it and it's very funny and it's all different kinds of people and
That's very convenient
Meg Wright covers comedy for the entertainment website vulture
She said these accounts weren't creating content they were just copy and pasting other people's jokes and ID
And it appealed to a lot of
People I got a ton of followers
Which of course are followers
They got beat
Because of all these other
People who are doing
You know
Unpaid work for them without permission some of the most popular comedy accounts on Instagram are
The fat Jewish
There's betches
And the one with the most followers of all of them
Brock Jerry
She now has 14 million followers
And
Do you know what happens when you have access to
14 million eyeballs
Money everyone is on their phones everyone scrolling Instagram that is a great way to advertise anyting
Advertisers started knocking on F-word Jerry's door when he reached a million followers so just imagine what
What kind of pill he has with 14 million followers
Dating apps
TV networks fast food chain
They all started paying F Jerry 2
No mention Bumble once in awhile
Throw weapon at about MTV
Create
Something funny about Totino's Pizza Rolls
Amendment 4 years a lot of the
Gems of the internet started crumbling like
Okay these brands are reaching out to F Jerry because he's popular
But
He's only popular because he's been sharing
Our funny things
And in the comedy world that kind of thing on attributed that could be considered a joke.
And then Comedy Central started advertising on F Jerry
And that's one that goes like
Comedy Central should know better
They are the home for comedians
Giving add money to a place that has made so many comedians angry
And is profiting off their jokes
Without their permission or
Four years without crediting it just didn't feel like
Comedycentral should
Align themselves
With a place like that Meg decided it was time to unite all the aggrieved people like Jen
And start
In Internet
War every follower is
Let's say a dollar
Could we
Take $10,000 from them could we take $100,000 from them
Is on a mission
To take add money away from the alleged joke thieves
And give it back
To the comedians
Or something like that
We're watching all this wandering
Can you really
Own a joke
Suikoden expert
When do you think
The first active
Joke thievery was committed
In the Neolithic era
Chris Brigman wrote the paper on joke theft he's an intellectual property lawyer and professor at NYU
But he's a cool IP lawyer he also studies
Is fashion and
P*** my mom was completely confused by my career
Let's put it that
Mom don't come in here doing work
Anyway
Chris says if we want to answer whether you can own a joke and what stealing a joke even means
We have to understand how comedy itself
Is changed over time
We're taking this way back
2 Vaudeville
Slap sticky variety shows from the 1800s they are magicians elephants acrobats and a funny is
HMC that you've
Could consider a comedian you wouldn't recognize thermostat as a stand-up comedian
Is there an MC there they're different
Vaudeville collapsed after World War II because of more exciting things like movies and radio
Does funny ish MCS add to go off on their own
Went solo
By the 1950s this is
You're growing into kind of the first wave of what we would recognize now a stand-up comedians the post Vaudeville
One liner
Chokeslam
Joke
They tell joke
After joke
Going to be here tonight even at this salary
Not really
Sophisticated jokes no one is putting a whole lot of effort into them so no one really cared if you.
Took them it isn't until the 1960s that comedian start caring more about the tech
Putting more work
Into each joke
Comedians at more of a Persona now
Writing in a way that is meant for only them to pull off
Take Mitch Hedberg
Please
I don't have a girlfriend
I just know a girl who would get really mad if she heard me say that
Stand-up comedy explodes in the eighties and nineties
Comedians like Dave Chappelle and Katt Williams now have sets that are
Longer more intricate
Sesame Street teaches kids
How to judge people
Black Hawk Down your name Oscar
I treat this guy like s***
The entire show
Play Josh I'm writing this fake Oscar you are so mean
Yeah
You're a grouch
You got jokes that
There's more investment in
And therefore there's a felt need for sump
Protection of them
Right so they can't just be stolen and used
White people are friendly you can call that motherfukers up at 3 in the morning with the wrong number and they won't even be mad at you
Hello
No I'm sorry no Shaquita here
Phone number did you dial
Will try it if it doesn't work call me back
Now jokes are intellectual property
But intellectual property laws
Don't
Really protect jokes that well there are a lot
A barriers
It cost $35 to register a joke with the copyright office
But you can't copyright a joke that's too short
And you can't copyright ideas
Copyright only protects the specific wording of it
And because of that all it takes to steal one
Is to slightly rewrite the joke
And all of these rules are here
In a weird way
To keep the jokes
Flowing so that comedians don't get sued for saying something like
Don't you hate it when
You get sued for using a phrase that should be in the public domain and then we the economy consumers lose out now
No one wants to risk
Making jokes
And on top of all of that
It's really expensive to defend a joke with copyright
It's federal law
Fancy lawyers
Foremost comedians
It's just not worth
Chris says no stand up comedian has ever filed a copyright lawsuit
Against another stand-up can
You actually looked for
We look
We found none
Secret things
If comedians aren't using IP law
There must be something else keeping joke. In check
Duchess deep in the mystery like what are they doing are they just standing there tolerating jokes after is there something else operating
I'm here that we haven't yet understood
So Crystal
Old Holland comedian
And he finds out that
The comedy world has created this whole informal system
Extinction
That has kept joke theft
At a tolerable level
And
We could have Chris
VIP lyrics
Explain the system of sanctions but
Why would we do that when we could have a real life
Stand up comedian do it
Planet Money listeners
Jim mendrinos
There's an old fashioned on the air sign
That is the most awesome thing I've ever
Ever seen a molecular does it's not real
We're not on the air
Jim's been doing stand-up for 35 years
He says the most bare-knuckle way that comedians prevent joke theft
Is
With violin
This is actually a real thing showing that Christy IP
P lawyer found in his big report
You know break some joke Thief
Car
Removed his bumper with a crowbar
And I'm there like every time I hear you do one of my jokes I'm going to break something on your
So yeah
You protect what's yours
Also comedians created
An early warning system to combat
When there is somebody was no joke thief in the room
I'll write a note on the napkin send the waitress up with a drink for the comic
So that they don't do something that's precious to the
It's all about your reputation
I mean the whole reason why
You know to send up a note to another comic when somebody walks in the room is from reputation
Back in 2002 Jim mendrinos was at the Gotham Comedy Club in New York City
Another comedian a friend of his
What is in the middle of the set
And Jim starts writing
The note
And he's talking the waitress comes up
Hands of the drink that Robin Williams is in the back watching
No oh yeah
Absolutely
I don't think I'm talking to you love the dead but Robin Williams had a tremendous
Reputation for being a joke Thief
Stolid borrowed a joke
The stove store
What something accidentally tok do you know
Is the genie I have attachment issues
The comedian walked off the stage right after he got Jim's note
Said Thank you and goodnight
Robin Williams did talk about his reputation for being a joke Thief
He said he just kind of soaked up funny things inadvertently
And Jim says Robin Williams actually copied from him
Oh yeah and he's a brilliant mind and you know what
I hate to put it this way but
Did the job better than I am
Which is the frustrating part of it
Robin Williams also figured out a way to
To smooth things over
And then when I called him out on it. He just had his manager cut me a check
ELC
Kind of light bulbs
Never said starve stealing it is sorry for the inconvenience
How much was the check for
Which back then was a
Lots of money
Remember what the joke was that
Keystone
Hive 8485
Yeah I didn't know that was there was a few 8-balls ago
That's not good at speed really
Jim says reputation is the currency of the comedy world
If you get the reputation of being a joke thief the comedy world gets together and imposes a good old-fashioned
Public
Shaming
Comedians refuse to do shows with you Comedy Club stop booking you
So when internet humorous realize that it's hard to lock up their jokes
What IP law
They turn to the sanctions created by their comedic for fathers and mothers
And this is where we come back to Meg Wright
Rick Jerry
And the most effective
Public shaming tool ever built
Social media
Meg
Start tweeting
Asking internet to unfollow
F words
If no one is going to police them
And they're allowed to
Constantly
Steal other people's work and profit from it
Then we are free
To encourage people
Devalue them
By unfollowing
In other words she's going to kick him in the eyeball and comedians are like
You are speaking our language one named Judah friedlander was like
Hey Meg I think I have the perfect name for your movement
Freak
FJ
Comedian Tim Heidecker even wrote them
An Anthem
Jerry and a campaign
Was born
Shut those f****** down John Mulaney Patton Oswalt
Amy Schumer
He's famous comedians thrall tweeting
FF
Jerry notoriously good smack talkers are yelling joke Thief
On the internet
And we are going to meet him IRL in real life
The Tweet Tamar himself the Willy Wonka
A viral content
After the rake
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities
Is can be a smart way to hedge Market
Risk and earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces
Is fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge
Which is not available in all states
We are off to meet the guy who has
Pissed off a bunch of Comedians and internet.
At
The place
Where memes go viral
I think it's one monkey with one typewriter
Stuck in a room
It's a nice sunny day in SoHo
Get at the content Factory
It's at
Astrid
Behavior day
Now we know
Jeremy Diaz on the third floor
Can you take the elevator
Squeaky elevator
Snozberries taste like snozberries
Wait a minute
Michelle yuan
Lickable wallpaper
Vanessa joke
Willy Wonka is not here it is no lickable wallpaper or Gobstoppers
But
Asterisk
BK Jerry's Joke Factory
Is
Son-in-law
With exposed brick in a bar
Green screen and a giant almost
Florida ceiling
F u c k on the wall
And you might be surprised to learn
F u c k is not
His legal first name
How do you introduce yourself
Elliot Valley
What is your title
I don't have a
You don't have a title I guess I could say you know
Featheriffic Jerry
And then what does the founder effect Jerry do
Various things
Like like with Elliot dabeli is the kind of person who just says he does
Spray living
Period doesn't elaborate
He's kind of quiet
Looks nervous and
Seems like you just kind of
Stumbled into this whole thing
I started seeing what I was 20 years old not knowing what the heck I was doing
Draymond think twice about like
You know
Posting content on the internet and I was just
Came from a very innocent place
But at a certain point
You know I did notice that
If it 10 shalie could be become something Elliott has actually built his following into many
He created a company that does video ads social media documentaries
You may have heard about the ill-fated fyre Festival
They help promote it
The bring in millions of dollars
Elliott also launched
Board game based on popular memes and he's the part-owner of the tequila come
Anne Elliot does not consider sharing other people's memes
He says
He's a curator and there are a lot of curators on the internet
Also he did
Start crediting some people a couple years
But after the FF Jerry campaign Brands like comedycentral and Bumble pulled their ads
And 300000 people unfollowed after
I walk down the street and I feel like people are looking at me like I'm up
Yeah go to a soft fraudster
Thai person with reality I know I'm not at all
And just like that hole
Misconception of who I am as a person from all this is
What sucks the most to me
Me personally
My reputation
Did this make you sad
You don't know
Oh you look sad
Oh yeah
Actually did think
Truly upset about this campaign
And to maybe take his side for just a moment
When Elliot started doing all of this
The rules around crediting we're kind of unclear
But it is hard to be too sympathetic
Elliott has done some
Edgy things with other people's content like
For a while Elliott was using other
People's funny posts about their drunken nights
To advertise his
Tequila like
Screenshotting some other person's funny post
And then slipping his brand into the caption
Without even asking them if they liked his tequila
So I mean you could call it an dad and the sense but I did I don't see that as an ad but I
I see how baby that's gray and weave
You know where stop
You are not no longer doing that so
Are you genuinely like you didn't think that it was an ad
I don't consider that an ad now
Elliot says he has been evolving with social media now
Because of the whole everyone unfollow freak Jerry campaign
He's asking people for permission to post their material
But Meg Wright who started the whole campaign
And a bunch of other internet humorous and funny people
Say that's still not enough
But to the people who stay
Well why not paper
People for your car
Like your share at your crediting them you're asking for consent now
But why not just like writing a check
It's a media I guess it's you could call it a media company I mean you guys pay me for this interview no
Not allowed to
So is it
Should we say
That like paying people for a content is not something that you are currently
Planning or I mean
You kind of just give like a
I don't really know how to characterize what you said
I mean it's not no
That's for sure
Like like we keep saying this is like an ever-evolving thing
For now we have
Consent policy policy in place
Next week it might be you no payment
Who knows
Elliot is considering paying people
Which is a big deal to go on the record
Because it would mean changing his whole business
And if they did do it
What would that mean how would that look
They go back and pay everyone since 2011
Does he only pay the new meemers
And totally forget about all the gens that got him there
And wouldn't even be enough for the internet
What is the fair price for a good meme
And we should point out that a lot of Brands and
Count and people do what Elliot does
News sites
Aggregate funny
Facebook Tumblr Instagram it selfies are all platforms that are profiting off of our free
Voluntarily uploaded pictures
This fight is ultimately about something much bigger than F Jerry and Elliot to ballet
It's about who on the internet
Profits from all the funny pretty gross weird
Interesting things we upload everyday
Maybe everyone should be paid
For everything we post
I'm ready we'll wait our check
Instagram
Hey that's my line
Prove it prove it
Spirit Airline
I guess it's Willy Wonka's
Actress Roald Dahl's line
Send us an email Planet Money at npr.org you're mean
Attribute them please but we want to hear from all of our funny listeners
We are at Planet Money on Instagram and
Just give me one dank meme
And you should really see this picture of Kanye kissing Kanye so we are going to send you to the store
2gen Lewis's Instagram account she is
At
This Jen Lewis
Lewis
It
Looks
So real it is hilarious
And Planet money has videos
This week's is an unflinching art house portrait of the
Npr.org
Splash Planet Money show
Today Show was produced by Darian Woods
Brian Dorsett edits our show and Alex goldmark his arse
Supervising producer
Special thanks to Edinger anger and Chris Brickman's co-author on that joke theft paper Doulton Olio
I'm Sarah Gonzales and Alexi Horowitz Ghazi
Thanks for listening