This is planet money from NPR
When I was about 9 years old
My sister and I were brought
To a University campus in Los Angeles
To be study
I remember going up in the elevator and being very intimidated
Just about the whole setup and this is my sister Eliza
So
They split us up
Eliza got taken into a separate
Room and I think I was the first one with
Okay Sally tell me more about the
Escap well it was a shower cap looking thing
It was like
Gel in the hole and the little holes in them
Wires coming out of your head and I like
Electrodes
The scientist
Put this thing on her head
Connected those Al
Electrodes to her
Her scalp
And then
They turn on the
Anime Shota
Videos
That were
Disturbing
Or side work
Scary
In the other room
A different researcher is
Quizzing Little Sally and
The questions were
Weird
Yeah they asked me like
Have you ever
Anyone with a brick
Broken bottle or bat
No
Have you ever pinched anyone
Yes
Have you ever pinched anyone besides your sister
No
We also have to play it
Computer game
Finished mazes
My sister and I played Bop-It together while the researchers watched us
And it on nine-year-old brains
Just trying to figure out like
What are they
Seeing right now
Why are you showing me that there has to be something
There was
Something a big something
Sally and Eliza are very important
To science because they are not just cisters
They're twins
Yes we are fraternal twins and you Karen you also have a twin this is true I do we
Are identical twins
Yes hello
Wow you do really sound a lot like Karen
Sally last week we got all of our twins in the studio to get to the bottom of this twin study and the many many
The other ways the twins have been studied because
I promise I'm not just saying this
Because
We twins
We are this lucky break for science
Twins are a natural experiment in genetics
Help scientists answer what is
Perhaps
Biggest question of all
How much control
Do we actually have over our own lives do we have like
Free will
And this is not just a philosophical question or even a scientific one
The answer has
Real world applications for things like
How the government spends money how we
AR laws for a lot of the things we talked about here at
Twin studies help us understand things about our men
Mental Health
Earning capacity
Ability to learn our propensity for addiction
Whether we hit people with bats broken bottles
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen.
And I'm Sally home
Today on the show how did we get to a place where nine-year-old Sally and Eliza were sitting in a chair with electrodes
Sticking out of their heads
For science
We go deep on the history and design of
The twin study
We perform a micro twin study on our own sisters
We learn what those researchers were studying that Electro cap
And weep for the dark
Side of twin
In science
Support for this podcast in
In the following message come from
With all the jargon
Investing can feel like a foreign language
E-Trade makes investing Sim
By providing personalized support and guidance
In terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as $500
And then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro to invest a teacher
For more information
Visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC
Membership
Planet money has an email newsletter
Once a week
The smart quiz take on
Economics in other words
A lot like a podcast
Silence
Subscribe at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
That's npr.org Planet Money newsletter
We decided to do this show today in
In part because of a very strange coincidence by the way happy birthday happy birthday your birthday is the same
You and I and our twins all four of us
Were born on the same day
This is true that day is today August 2nd the date of the show is airing
That is what got us think
Think about twins and the experience
Yes and the experience of being a twin is one of constantly being
Pretty much any time we meet someone new people
First freak out about how much
We look alike Destra like
Hair talk like
And then
Question beginning which are always the same yes my sister and I don't look alike but
You got these two we ran through these without twin
So
One we always get
Can you read each other's minds
Do you know what a life is thinking Sally
What else
Do you feel each other's pain
No
Who's older Murray I have 2 minutes on Karen so I
Lord that over wisdom
Right
Experience she looks up to me
Something rain this kind of
Fascination that we
It's everyday
That Fascination is what
Sparked the very
First
Twin study
All the way back in the 1800
The researcher was a man named Francis
Carlton Carlton was the one who kind of like harness that existing cultural fascination
Entered it into
The scientific proof
History of heredity
This is Allison cool she is like
Russian nesting doll of twin study researchers
She is herself and identical twin who studies researchers who study twins
Social studies the history of twin studies and
She is an assistant professor of anthropology at the University of
Colorado Boulder
Alison told us that Francis Galton was a
Gentleman of Science in the late 1800s
He was actually Charles Darwin's cousin
And while cutting
Charles had
Obsessed over finches
Carlton
Became obsessed
With twin
You trying to understand why parents
And their children basically why relatives
Had such
Similar to
In other words
Heredity
Animals
Similar seasoning relatives that he
He could find
Which way
So go out and found a bunch of twins had them answer a bunch of questions
The terms identical and fraternal had not yet
Open coin but he knew that some Twins were what he called
Similar and others were
Dissimilar
So she asked for information about the
Their appearance there
Behavior
And based on what he hears
Back from these twins he makes this
The similar twins
Stay similar because they have is like being born nature
And the dissimilar twins
Dissimilar
Because they have different natures
And in the paper that he publishes
He uses this freezing that we now probably Oliver
Recognize
He talks about nature
End
Stepping back for a sec
Studying heredity like this or what would become known as
Is genetics
I can bring you to this
Like for example say a researcher discovers that genes play a role in some
Particular disease
You can take that information
And take that's great that helps us figure out how to spend money to better research or treat this.
But
If you assume that genes are
Our Fate
Then you can take that same information and go down
A very dark
Instead of trying to treat that disease
Someone could say let's
Breed that disease let's breed that Gene out of human
Francis Galton went down that day
Eugenics
Literally means I think the science of being well born
But also a social movement
About
Making sure that
Only the fittest
Are you able to reproduce
These ideas
Led to forced sterilization
Even outright murder
Eugenics took hold in many different countries
Including the US
All of the
Kind of like biological research in that era
The flavor of the flavor of like weird
Racism
These ideas and the twin studies that gaulton use to reinforce them
Showed up again when the Eugenics movement was taking its most terrifying
There's a direct trajectory
Rotten cotton to
Like A Nazi twin experiments
Nazi researcher Josef Mengele performed
Grizzly human experiments including many experiments
Saint twins
He infected them
Typhus
He did surgery without anesthesia
Used twins to study heredity
In hopes of propping up the Nazi program of so-called
Racial hygiene
Soap understandably for decades after the war i attention shifted away from heredity and people stay
Started focusing more on nurture on the effects of the environment
But then about 1980
Get this crazy story crop top
It was a big pop culture moment
Reinvigorating twins.
And pushing the pendulum back
Portal Focus
Longines
There was this highly publicized
Braided as babies
And then reunited as adults
And that all of these crazy similarity
For one thing they were both
Kim
Jim Lewis
And Jim Springer
Nope
How to say there is no Gene for being named
That is just coincidence
But
Are researcher at the University of Minnesota
Thomas Bouchard
He hears about the gym
And thanks
These
Are the research subjects
I have been look
Looking for
Identical twins
Raised
Apart
To understand why his study ended up becoming so important
You have to first understand how normal Twin Cities
Studies of twins raised together
The reason why twins are so amazing for science is because you have this natural comparison
You got identical
Twins who inherit identical genes
And
Fraternal twins
Couch are on average 50% of their genes
And actually we are not just going to occur
Blaine all this
Back to her sisters in the studio
We are here to conduct a micro twins
Unsteady mini scientific
In the studio in the collective Studios today we have a set of identical twins
And a set of fraternal
And that is what you need for a twinset that's right
Of course you need
Manny Marquez
So what twin researchers will do is
They will pick at trade or behavior something that they want to stay
If on the whole
Identical twins are more
Similar to each other than fraternal twins are
Then that suggest that
Genes or DNA
Play a role in why
Some people have that tree
For our mini study
We picked lateness
At what rate to look at
Are you a late person or an on-time person
And
My fraternal
Merced Valley the late one and
So we are
Different on the
And then I asked my ID
Twinberry
How are you on lateness
I
It's bad to be a very intentional act to become a moron Time Force
I would say that I'm the
Like I
I've been working very hard
In our micro twins
Study the Fraternal
We're different
And the identicals were similar
Take me to fairly strong genetically
Here today
So back to the Jim Twins and that researcher Thomas Bouchard in Minnesota who wanted to study
Twins rays
Person saying
James Allen
Bouchard sees twins like the gym
Anythink
In many cases these twins had pretty different environments growing up
So it is identical twins raised separately
Still end up similar
That is
Super convincing evidence
For the influence of genes
More than a hundred twins raised apart
And they find DNA does seem to play an important role
Even for things like Howard
Religious the twins are
How liberal
Whether they were attention-seekers
Assertive Nanny twin studies studies of
Twins raised apart have found results like this
We looked at 1 study that faith we analyzed thousands of
Twin studies and summarize what those studies suggest
About how important genes are how much they seem to contribute to the differences
DNA seems to be very important on the health of
Specifically Your Eyes Ears Nose Throat skin
And bones
For psychiatric health
A little bit less but still Jean seams
Play a role in about half the variability
And even in things that seem sort of intangible like social values
Jeans do seem to
To play a role
Like there was this one big twin study that
Examen rules
We could have Loosely called UIC twin project or twin study
This is Larry Baker she is a behavioral genetics expert and a professor of psychology at USC
A longer name might be the risk factors for antisocial Behavior twin study
I was wondering if
Official official name and our Publications and then we have the name and our correspondence because we
We didn't want to freak people out I could see it would you like your child to be a part of the risk.
Address for antisocial
I have your predict whether your kids are going to become incarcerated or not would you like to participate 1%
Who got a letter inviting her kids to participate
Was
My mom
And she said I have some psychopaths in the house
When did the lead researcher on the study that nice ass
Sister and I
I were a part of
The study with the electric app from the beginning
After the break
What that study found
And what modern twin studies have taught us
About nature
Support for this podcast and the following message come from wix.com
With Wix you can create your very own professional website
Choose a template you love and customize it with your own text images and
Go to wix.com that's wilx.com money
To get 10% off
Going on a big group trip always sounds good in theory
But it can get tricky when you get there and have it
Totally different expectation
Checkout NPR live gets new guide on navigating Group Travel
Right to life
All guys
All Arabic
All in one place
What Laura study
The study that I was
I was looking for was something that they called antisocial Behavior
So on the far and that's like
Psychopath Behavior
On the floor and they were talking about things like
Aggression rule-breaking lying I have a son who is exactly your age at the time we start
The studies so I just thought of all the things that
That he and his friends might done
The researchers looking for all manner of real bacon
Behavior
And that's why they asked all those questions
About like
The bricks broken bottles bad about pinching
I remember saying no to so many of those questions and feeling like I have to
Just never done anything rebellious or cool
The electric car
Anat lab
Natori
That was used to measure our responsiveness
Too scary or sad sad
Situations hooked you up
A variety of different devices to be able to measure your basically the
The part of your nervous system that's involved in kind of fight or flight
One theory is that psycho pods or anti
Asocial individuals are less responsive
Two stimuli and promotions like
Fear and sadness
That is why they had us watch those sad sad movies
Tipsy how much we react
It was from the champ
Oh yeah yeah yeah I knew was a Friday something-or-other
Yeah and little Ricky Schroder died with a fighter and his dad
Dies in a boxing match
And he's sobbing and sobbing it's been used in his studies
Because that is like one of these sadist
Phone clips of all time basically if you don't cry at the champ there's something wrong with you Sally did you cry
Brian K confirmed
That I don't know okay
Where is the
Fat Boys
Who exhibited Psychopathic traits
So kids were more likely to be manipulative or who lied more
Their brains did react
Left stuff like that movie scene
And more broadly the study found that
Jeans do seem to play a large role in antisocial Behavior
And this finding is kind of troubling in a way
It's kind of like what are we going to do with that you know is it going to impact our justice system
Is there a possibility that people will get mistreated because they're identified as having a genetic predisposition
And that would be a moral mistake but also a scientific law
Because twin studies have helped us move Way Beyond the idea that genes
Is Our Fate
Pretty much any
Sing.
You seem to have some kind of
Genetic influence
Is also
Interacting
With other genes and with the environment
Like there's a sinner play happening all the time I wasn't cool again the researcher of twin researchers
And almost everyone we spoke with told us
But the question is it nature or nurture
Is totally outdated
Is obviously
Both you can't really
Separate out nature from nurture in this really clean way
Because the whole
The whole thing
Is
Dislike Dynamic complex
Text system
Of interaction
There is a lot of work being done right now to tease out and understand these complex interaction
Like one question
Why is it that sometimes
People have a gene
But it doesn't get
Express
There's a whole field that studies that called epigenetic
And also
There's a lot of work being done right now to tease out and understand these complex interaction
Like one question
Why is it that sometimes people have a gene
But it doesn't get it
Expressed
There's a whole field that studies. Called epigenetics
And also
The whole genome
Good night
We don't necessarily need twins to help us
Sea jeans
And that let us to wonder very reluctantly
The science even need twins anymore
NASCAR about this
So are Twin Cities Still Still useful in a world where we can look at
All the genes
Yeah that's an interesting question turns out twin studies are still really useful because you can
You can do things especially to study environment
Because
Identical twins for all of our identical genomes we can still live extremely different life
Like my identical twin sister and I
I am right handed she is left
She's queer I'm straight
For radio I spent years in Corporate America
She is an artist
By looking at twins like us
Researchers can start to zoom in on
What aspects of the environment
Mattermost to have differently
Turn out
Back in Colton
Jeanswear this invisible thing that twins allowed us to
The mystery twins could help solve
There's a lot of invisible stuff in the environment
To we think about jeans lot but
Well we really know nothing about is the environment
It's the error term it's
Anything that's not genetic is the environment but like
What is that mean
Right we're so
Busy trying to sequence the genome but lie
We need to if this is the real question nature what's nature what's nurture
If the sequence of environment to
Don't worry science twins
We're on the job we got this
If you are a twin
Send us an email Planet Money on NPR. Org
Singletons are also welcomed to write
You can also find us on Facebook Twitter or Instagram we are at Planet Money
And while you're there why not send your favorite Planet Money story to a friend
Give us a review
Good or bad we are here for it all or show today was produced by Darian woods and Nick fountain or supervising producer
Is Alex goldmark Bryant AR status
Show special thanks to Nancy Siegel and Jay Joseph
Also our NPR colleague at Hidden brain did a great episode about Twin Cities check that out they do great work
And our friends over at Radiolab just finished an amazing series on intelligence which goes beep on some
Some of these questions about genetic research that we touched on here
If you like this episode you will like that
We cannot sign off today without saying this is our very last week with the great Sally home and we are so sad
So you've been such a star here at Planet Money and we are going to miss you so much I'm going to miss you guys
Around you hear me on the airwaves soon Goodwin's
I am Karen Duffin and I'm finally home this is NPR thanks for listening
Marie would you like to
To tell the story of when we switched places it worked out really well for me but
How much for caring because
It was a sixth-grade yes
Weirdest substitute
And I was a little bit of a troublemaker or is
Karen was the angel she is today
And of course during the course of the
Class I got in trouble so I got
My name on the board with check marks except my name that day with Karen Karen got check marks
And check marks work
Oh yeah that was that meant attention