The trade war with China was one of the biggest economic stories of
Import taxes
Is ungood that were sold from China into the US
Cost American businesses
Billions of dollars
And these tears could also be part of why China experience
Its lowest level of economic growth
In nearly 30 years
Yeah biggest trade is global
When tariffs are put in place between two giant economies like the US and China the economic impact Ripple all over the
The effects can be a norm
But also tariffs end up affecting a lot of people on a very
Individual
Hello I'm David Reed
I'm a peanut cotton farming
Dooly County Georgia Pinehurst
Oh I found here for 50 years
Peanut peanut butter and
These are Goods that were all hit by retaliatory tariffs
Did China put on the US
And people like David Reed
Who sell peanuts
China
Have been some of the hardest hit
Is China was one of the biggest buyers of both us cotton
And peanut
David and his fellow Farmers ended up in the sky
What does tsar and unfortunate situation
It appeared to put them out
Side the normal laws of
Supply and demand
18 was
Is a very unusual year
All the way around
From start to finish
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Stacey Vanek Smith
And Cardiff Garcia and Stacey and I are the hosts of the indicator from Planet Money if you don't know it it's Planet Money shorts
Daily podcast about the economic ideas in the news
10 minutes or less every weekday
You like to say that
Planet Money is the indicator
Twice a week
Podcast about the economic ideas in his locker
Amite today we have to
Spring indicators for you you might recall you know last summer we also brought you to Summer indicators
Making it
Absolutely
Allergies in the indicator that's the association we want here right now
You should subscribe to the indicator if you don't you should
Definitely subscribe
Anyway our first Spring end
Decatur is about tariffs on American goods and the personal impact they had what it's been like for farmers who found themselves
The Crosshair of a global political
What storm
And then
Quite terribly
An actual
And in the Second Story we are going to
Cheer up orbs OKC
Cheer down
Depending on where you're from
The latest rankings
Happiness by country
Relationship between GDP and happiness
Does having more money make you happy
Stick around
Support for this podcast
Send the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth manager
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of Pacs
And make clear recommendation
Thanks for your full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
David Reid looks a little like
Santa
But with this very neatly trimmed white hair in this tiny little mustache
Getting a blue button-down shirt tucked into his jeans from leather belt
Do peanuts on your belts
Oh yeah yeah
Penetration
Has he
Bowser trains
Informing peanuts and cotton on this land for 50 years
Is Grandfather farmed
It is just a
Beautiful area
Flat
Green low pine trees
Field stretch out in every direction
The reason David family settled to Europe has more to do with what's under the ground
Sandy soil
You just good peanut butter
Georgia grows more than 40% of the nation
Peanut
This area Specializes
Runner pain
That's what you're mostly used to make peanut butter
Jeff gets a lot of its peanuts from here also some of the peanuts in your peanut M&Ms are from this
Which are excellent peanuts the best
David Reed Farms more than 2000 Acres
Peanuts and cotton
With his wife
And when is crop started coming in last year he says
It was
Pretty Gloria
Oh yeah we had the best
Crop
We ever had
In 50 years
Andrew harston
Best crop
My life
A phoenix
Peanuts and Coke
And then starting over the summer
A couple things
The trade war with China continues to escalate
The Chinese government this morning announcing its going to impose new tariffs on 16 billion dollars worth of us Goods
Among the US Goods that China started taxing
Peanut butter and
Haughton basically everything they grow in this part of Georgia
Let a couple of months later
This happen
Heather and Brooke Baldwin live here in Destin Florida where we are covering the official
Landfall of hurricane Michael you can feel the ferocity I'm sorry I'm walking around here very Ginger
Really tried to make sure that there is no flying debris coming my way
Category 4 hurricane winds coming in
And baby got up at mom for daylight and I was going out with
Spotlight looking at my
I can see what was left behind here
Gardening
We went some for you isn't it just look like it was devastated
David lost about a third of his
Cotton crop
And a couple of fields
The peanuts 2
That show you with the peanut
You know
Oh it is Sandy this is sandy soil
She get on that he
Is it peanuts on the ground there
That's what was left
Left after
Through the storm
Peanuts grow underground like potatoes and his field have peanuts all over the dirt
David picked a couple of but they were rotten
From all the water from the Storm shows come soft
My partner's hands
Say that was a good thing that when it came out and it just somehow
It didn't we lost some at the storm
This is the thing that got hurt
The peanuts and cotton that did survive
Walk straight out of a storm and into a trade War
U.s. gun cotton peanut butter all hit by terrorists
And China is one of the biggest importers of American peanut butter in
In Cotton
And suddenly China was
Taxing those Imports by as much as 25
10%
That's a lot
Will you imagine you've said you been farming for 50 years you've definitely seen
Difficult periods before have you ever dealt with with
Tariffs before
No I've never never had to deal with tears
You know this photo taken
Flashlight that says in my 50 years
Oh so this is new
Yeah this is all new to me
Chinese peanut butter in Cotton orders from
The US collapsed over
And the price that David
Who's getting for his peanuts in Cotton
Both fell by about 30%
So
Because of the storm
You lost quite a bit of your cotton crop and some of your peanut crop
But then also
Because of tariffs the amount of money that you're getting for the crop that had that
Is left
Was like not a tie
It hurts both ways
David and his fellow Farmers ended up in the
Weird situation
Outside of the typical laws of sir
Supply and demand
Because normally when the Spy something goes down
The price of that product
It goes up
Your penis in the world because
Storm but
People still want
Peanut butter
So the price of peanut butter goes up and the price that farmers get for their peanuts
Goes up
But this was not a normal situation
The storm hit around the same time that
The trade War took
Affect
US made peanut butter was suddenly way more expensive
Super Chinese buffet
So the man from those buyers went down in the price of peanuts also went
Instead of up
Chinese Imports of us made peanut butter peanuts and cotton tank
And what had been shaping up to be one of the best years in David's
Entire farming career
Turned into one of the worst years Pete ever seen
You know what we plan to make a lot of money this year but
Lower didn't see fit part but maybe next year he's going to bless us better
But hopefully we going to break even
Break even
And theaters
He is one of the lucky one
There's some Farmers just worried you know that I've heard him talk
Inside I don't know if I'm going to survive this
Astronaut
You know is this heartbreaking
David says the economic effects of
The storm in the
Keras haven't just
Hit the farmers
They hit the whole area
It's hurting a whole community and equipment dealers
The guy down the street with the hardware store
We're not going to buy
Spend money
Is we did is prettiest
Because we don't have it
And everybody say
Spite of everything though David actually supports the terror
I thought well that's not good for the farmer right now but I think it's the right thing to do
You know because the trade balance
Soul on fire
And I think President Trump done today
Right thing in my opinion
I think he did a good
It heard us right now but I think in the long run it'll happen
David thinks the macroeconomic issues between the US and China are important enough
But the sacrifice bills worth it
He said most of the pharmacies talk to feel the same way
Now that the government is providing millions of dollars in
The cotton farmer
And supplementing a lot of
Peanut Lofts
But David says it doesn't make up for
Everything doesn't make up for all the law
At the start of this month a bill that would have provided
Disaster relief to Farmers affected by
Michael
Failed to pass
The Senate and on top of that nobody knows how long the Terrace
Continue
And
Well they're going on China could just lock down peanut and cotton
Supplies from other parts of the world
Even if the trade war end soon
The Chinese market for us peanuts
And peanut butter and cotton
Might never come back to where it was before
But David says
He is not going to switch
Leather crop now there's anybody he knows
They're going to continue growing cotton and peanuts
Just like always
Why is that
Listen to blood
You know it's what they've always doing
M&M peanuts is good crop to grow
You know and that's use the money in them
If you make it good to you
And
I just like to see him grow
Hi Josie and good peanuts just this empty heart
After the break our next indicator
Happiness
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your way
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Happiness
It is
The thing we are all striving for in life right and it is how you achieve
The Good Life yes but it can be so elusive
What makes you happy
Relationships
Do your job
Money
Coffee
Absolutely better for me at a stronger reaction to
Coffee and some money which is a little odd
But seriously it is hard to know
And
Can feel even harder to know precisely because it is so difficult to measure
Back to people
Are uneasy about how you might measure that may have been why
Economics became narrower than it should have been a couple of centuries ago
This is economist John hello
John is with the Vancouver School of Economics at the University of
British Columbia
What are the editors of the world happiness report the world
John and his team released the first one back in
11 things that uses six measures to help gauge and rank the happiness of different countries
And one for 2018 Jetta
Just came out
Today's indicator is 90
Happiness report rated all the countries in the world in
Terms of their happiness
And of course I immediately just looked at the list to see where the US was in
And it wasn't number 19
Behind Belgium
Number 18
Israel at 30
Australia
Number 11
Yes we were also behind
Iceland
Which is in fourth place
In third place is Norway and in second place
Is Denmark
Of course John helliwell told me that not obsessing about rankings was actually one of the secrets for the country that came in
Men at number one
And it isn't it ironic
The happiest country on Earth
Finland
Sanya village in the end
There's things called
The Jones effect
This is the idea that people
Think of their rank as being important
It was just like keeping up with the Joneses
Just exactly
Does this mean one of the reasons that Finland is so happy is because they don't
Care
About how much happier they are than everybody else
John said
Exactly yes
We've talked to Finn
It's not your problem there is elsewhere
CC no actually
We don't think it is in the reason is
This is kind of a social Norm in Finland that you don't
Play you're welcome you don't talk about your income
We consume
And they didn't said that means he's comparator effects
Or more or less absent there
So
Finland for the win
Happiest place on earth
Not that they're bothering to rub it in
Too busy dealing with
Six months of darkness
It's right
Hashtags USA still winning in the light
All right all right
Okay but not of the economics
The whole thing
How do you measure happiness
John helliwell says there are six measures that they used to help determine a country's rank in the happiness report
Some of them are pretty standard economic measures and some of them are
A little
Squishier wishing yeah
Two of them are standard development indicators
Which is GDP per capita and healthy life expect
Life expectancy one that's pretty straightforward
Gross domestic product per capita
So gross domestic product is basically the sum total of all the goods and services
The country produces in a year
And per capita per person
Basically give a rough idea of how wealthy
People are in a particular country
Measure number three has to do with
How much people trust the government and businesses inside their
Corruption is a problem in your country and business
And then a second one in government
And then we take the average of those two
So life expectancy
GDP per capita
Corruption
And the fourth happiness indicator
Something called social support
Secular Gallup question is
You have somebody account on in times of trouble number 5
Generosity
National average
It's based on have you been generous in the last 30 days
Two others
Binary number 6
Freedom he was at the freedom to make your key life
That's very important across country
So in some
To measure happy
John and his
Team used measures of
GDP per capita
Life expectancy
Corruption
Social support
Generosity
And freedom
And the reason that he used
D6 measures is because they had been found
Be highly correlated
With people's overall happiness
But John says there are two that seem especially powerfully correlated with
Number one
Social support
That is do you have people you can count on in times of trouble
Number two
GDP per capita
Yep
Money
For the most part
Hire a country
Top it off
The happier
But John finds out there are
A few notable exceptions to
China
India
And
The US
I know I know in all three countries GDP per capita was up between 2017 and 2018
But happiness levels as John and his team measure them were down
And this is something that Economist refer to
To add the easterlin paradox
It's the idea that wealth adds to be
People's happiness
Only up to a point
And at some point
For some reason
Getting richer
Cops make
Making you happier
John thinks that
Paradox is happening for different reasons in China and India versus
The US
In China and India John thinks they're experiencing a kind of disruptive effect that often comes along with an economy that the
Balding really fast
The decline of the extended family
And the elimination of a lot of these social ties
Social support
And the
Cute
Movements away from the countryside towards the cities
Have posed problems for happiness
Even if
Income per capita Rose a lot
USS John says he thinks the paradox
She's been caused by something else in
Hayirli
People overestimate the happiness they're going to get from
Boring, or a bigger house
And they underestimate the happiness
They would get from more time with
Show me end up
Finding themselves
In circumstances to where they've chosen
Pickle fork
Too high an income too much consumption
Not enough time to spend with family and friends
And they end up being anxious Harry
Stressed
There are other ideas about why the
Chilling Paradox existence
What is it could be that GDP is growing so GDP per capita is going up but then it's less evenly spread by the poppy
Deletion that used to be
So people aren't happy about growing inequality
And some Economist say that the
Easterlin Paradox isn't really a thing that it all depends on
How hot
This is measured because
As we said before
It's a really really tricky
Anything to nail down
Nonetheless
John says
Humans are priorities do seem to play a major role in our happiness
Becky says researching happiness has changed his own private
I used to be more
Discbound
More solitary
And the more inclined to read the elevator since they safety certificate rather than talk to the other
Open the elevator
And what I've learned in these years is that that's
Sleep bad psychology
To start conversations with strangers 2
Why would people in the streets
To assume the best rather than the worst about them
It's a win-win situation and so I I do it more than I
Are you stupid and that's improve my happiness and I hope it's a
Easy for you to say your in Canada you guys are number 9
One America we can do this
Yes Sheriff
Be there for your friend
Yeah we are going to climb the happiness rankings
Even if it makes us miserable
Alright elevators
Happiness.
USA
We're number one
No I'm checked out I don't even know where we are in the rain
Number one side is interested whatever
Give me more about like
Me feeling like
I'm improving Finland you're going down in 2019
If you enjoy Today Show and want to hear more you can have more storage for the indicator from Planet Money where everyday
Your podcast with post a new episode every weekday afternoon at around 5 it's always 10 minutes lasting
Very often it's something you won't
Heard about in other places or something you have heard about another places
Take on it
Princeton
Monthly jobs report
Indicators produced by constanza teardo and Diaries Raphael
It's edited by Patty Hearst
Play Smash Up was mixed by Rachel Cohn
And also I think this deserves an air horn but we'll just tell you Planet money has a new newsletter
And we like to think of it as just the right amount of Economics to fit in your email box
It's a good way to keep up with
The podcast and some of the other Big Ideas in economics
For instance do bans on plastic
The bags help or hurt the environment
And dwelt.
Your private and kill the idea
Why
To subscribe to the rejuvenated Planet Money newsletter
Go to npr.org
Splash Planet Money newsletter that's all one word npr.org
Planet Money news
I'm Stacy Mannix
Smith and Carlos Garcia
Thanks for listening