Recently Gizmodo reporter Kashmir Hill tried some
Nearly impossible
Paternalism
I wanted to see if it was possible to live
Without the tech Giants
So Amazon Facebook Microsoft Apple
And Google
She tried to cut them all at
But I mostly wanted to talk
The cashmere about going off
Cuz Google is everywhere
And she was like yeah if you're going to cut them out you got to do way more than just switching search engines and email
She actually asked a programmer
To make like
A gate that wouldn't let anything Google into
So it meant that leg
Google
Analytics
Didn't load and Google's trackers didn't load in Google fonts which is apparently used all over the web
Didn't load in Google Maps
Didn't load which
Shutdown having services
It was a huge problem
Kazimierz article was kind of mine
Because sure we all know we used
What I didn't know
Just how much
Of the internet uses Google's infrastructure to do
Just about everything
Example one day she was trying to go and drop off
The sheriff
So she enters your username or password and nothing was happening
And it turns out that
Dropbox uses a service from Google it to determine whether or not your
A bot
And so because I was blocking Google
It looked at Dropbox like I wasn't human and they wouldn't let me sign in because Kashmir was blocked from
Fonts and trackers in maps and a million other Google things
Her internet
With basically
You're saying that it's like
Is everywhere
Yeah it's
It's every
Basically blocking Google made me feel like I
Was
Back on dial-up internet in the 90s
And this was just the Google part
Remember
Kashmir did this for all of the
Amazon
Facebook Google Microsoft and Apple in that order in and then the last week I blocked all 5 at once
Kashmir's article was so good that
After I read it I was just like
Why didn't I see
Can I just say
Here at Planet Money
Sentence around everyone's looked at it
And we are also
So jealous of
You wouldn't be jealous if you had to live through a Heroes I must be a masochist
Well thank you for doing it so we didn't have to
Thanks for sending me a valentine
Hello X
Every year usually around Valentine's Day we Channel our feelings of jealousy
And turn them into
Appreciation
Valentine
Travel show in Shadow
To a movie that inspires
Existential dread
An obscure central-bank bureaucrat
And a brutal sport that explains a lot about economics
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable Lake
And features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR
Car for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your
Your first purchase of a website or domain
We ask everyone on our team
To highlight the things
They loved or we're jealous of this year
And Darren Woods
Play the money producer welcome hey how's it going you were the first to respond so you're up first what's your volume
My Valentines full of the bank of Jamaica
And I'm going to say what it is I'm just going to show you
So what I'm saying is a music
Video
About the Jamaican economy featuring like
A souped-up race car and exchange rates
Driving to the central bank and in the background with the oldest reggae music explaining what the central bank doing about in
What is the backstory
The backstory goes
To the sky Toni Morrison he's ahead of
Communications
Jamaican Center
Last year he was sitting in the back of Jamaica
There are these Big E,
Your phone's going on
Antonio has an idea to explain how the bank is
Is managing pricing
Central banks have a lot of tools to do this mostly boring speech
Beaches in my
Experience that's the primary tools but turning
He's got this other ID
Music
Thinking of using music
Attitude
GameStop might not really what I love about this is
Planet Money we have
I have tried so many ways to
Explain
Inflation targeting
And the psychology behind it
But these guys but Tony at the Central Bank of Jamaica
Had just like figured out a way to
Get it stuck in my head
They are smashing a
There's a serious purpose behind using music to explain inflation
Jamaica struggled with really high price inflation basically since
The 60s
At some point in the 1990s was over 70%
Like
Super high price and place
Up and up and up
Trevor the last few years Jamaica has succeeded in driving the inflation rate down
What Tony told me is that he wants to convince the people of Jamaica that this is going to stick
Because inflation is psychology
Jacole in a way right so Tony knows that inflation is fueled by the
Eat a vicious to virtuous cycle
People think prices going to rise a lot
They'll spend the money faster for the speeding up inflation
If I think inflation Will Be Loved
That in itself
Will help slow inflation
Economist call this
Anchoring inflation expectations
And so
Tony
Has figured out a way to
Explain to
Anyone and everyone
The inflation will stay low just trust
Exactly so these videos are actually pretty important
I love this
So much
Thank you Darren Woods
Sabrina Terrace
It's been a complete pleasure to set my data watching reggae videos about it
Baseline and reggae music
A message from
Bank of Jamaica
Okay next up Noel King what he got for
This year I was wildly jealous of a documentary that appeared on neck
It's called
Fire the greatest party that never happened you saw it
Two under suggestion Music Festival that happened in 2007
Which was arguably the most
Brilliantly height
Music festival in
It started with a video on Insta
Yes like this slickly produced
Video
Drone footage of this
Private Island they said Pablo Escobar's Island
It's in there playing in the water with pigs which is weird but it's cool
Looks like an Instagram
Influencers
Island dream
So people pay thousands in some cases even tens of thousands of dollars to get to
To the festival
MN
They get off the plane in the Bahamas
And the beach is
The parking lot
And luxury accommodations are damped
There are no models anywhere
And there's nothing to eat except cheese sandwiches
There was a belief on the bus a lot of people thought that now you know maybe we're passing through this are
Are you normal isn't just on the other side was like oh my God
Yeah I remember watching this in real time on Twitter
And just kind of laugh
Because basically
But then we all just sort of file this away in the
The cabinet full of millennial failures and moved on with our lives
Until
This
Because it had something kind of special right
It really did
Safari Festival is now a huge legal fee asked
One of the co-founders is in prison
Anderson journalist I could not believe the access they got
They had all of this Insider footage
Did the two co-founders
Copping to the fact that they were selling something that they knew was not real
I see the documentary and I get curious and I start reading about a
How to figure out how they pulled this off
And it turns out the reason they had all of his damning footage
Was because the people who'd been in charge of
Promoting the fyre festival
Were some of the same people who produced the document
This documentary is ethically compromised so why are you recommending it to her listeners because it's so dead
On about
What it is to live in the age of Instagram like these incompetent
Hucksters
Can inspire people across the world to be so afraid of missing out
Did even though the organizers don't have enough money or any preparation or any idea how to deliver
Thousands of people fall for it
Because influencers tell them
The documentary is fyre the greatest party that never happened
And Italy
XML
What's the Valentine's
We got
I sort of
Understood what does next one which comes from Cardiff Garcia
The co-hosts of the indicator from Planet Money
Hello Cardiff
And I do not understand this at all
Go for it
So my Valentine is 2 mixed martial arts
The sport of
And then a snake if you've never seen it
For here's a little
Clipper
Kinetic Lynch's exactly what you got
Oh
Yeah that was a
Quite a few quite a blow in with a right hook coming out of
French garlic
As we say
Why do you like this
I find it kind of endlessly entertaining
Watch
I find that there is
Such a wide range
Employed it actually is a much more kind of intellectual and intriguing
Sport that a lot of people give it credit for
But the main reason I gave it the Valentine
Is because it is such a controversial business
And because the specific controversy
Fees of mixed martial arts as a
Business
Are so emblematic of the controversies
Did exist in the overall US economy
Okay I was raised in a
Cocoon where I didn't know anything about violence or economic so
Play this metaphor out for
Start with this the UFC
The ultimate fighting
Is the main promotional organization
Of make
Martial arts the only one I've ever fight yeah exactly
And it's much bigger than all of its rivals in part because it bought so many of those rivals on its way to
Becoming huge
Because of the URC size Fighters don't have many options for other promotions were they can
Can fight to the fighters kind of have to accept
Like a really stringent requirements
Set the UFC imposes on them
Including how much it pays them
What's the fighters might say
A little
And you've been walking around the office using the
Big words
Describe this relationship between
Labor
M capital
Yes monopsony
Monopsony
What is
So in the labor market a monopsony is when you have a
A company that is either the only company that employs all the workers in a certain industry or more commonly
It's by far
Biggest in
So it just has a lot of power
And a lot of Fighters who said that
That's the UFC
Alright so bring it back how does one guy knocking out another guy
Relate to the economy rent
Even though I haven't made it obvious yet
So what critics of the UFC say is that
Because
It is part of a monopoly
I just kind of led to like a hollowed-out middle class
Within the sport
You still have some of these super Starfighter
Make a ton of money sometimes millions of dollars
Giving fights and obviously the UFC owners get to keep a huge chunk of the money that's made in
Sport
But then you have all these other Fighters most of the fighters
In fact who don't make a ton of money
They have to pay for their own benefit
Can all kinds of other things
Out of pocket
So you end up with quite a bit of inequalities
Within the sport what the critics are saying
Is it that is a result of the UFC
Monopsonist
That sounds
Could also mirror what's happening
Sing in the US economy now right
Kill Economist are increasingly worried that
Fewer and fewer companies in summoned
Street are controlling more and more of the workers Maybe
That is responsible for some of the Rising
Inequality that the US
Contumacy
Cardiff
Yes you do Muay Thai right
I do yeah
For 15 years
You teach me so much about the economy will you teach me how to fight
If you want mansure
Thanks got it
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining bang
I offering account
With no fees or minute
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
All right
So far we've had music videos
Fighting type Millennial schadenfreude is a little heady
Because yes play the money winners
We do read books and Elsa Chang
I did it's called in my father's
Houses by Fox
And I love this boy
But I just disappeared
This is a book that was less about economic
But it's about a topic I love reporting on
Criminal
We should say before you in economics reporter you reported on criminal justice
A half a day
Get right
Okay and what does book does as it explores this question of how
Criminal Behavior
Can spread across
Generations within one single family
You know the question is is it more nature or more nurture
Why that happens
Fox Butterfield
Movie starts with a
Totally startled Easton
Imagine that
5%
Of American families
Are behind half of all crime in the US I had no idea that is why
It is anyway he illustrates how crime cancer
Spread
Like this content
Allegiance moving from parents
Children to grandchildren
Burning great-grandchildren
Annie's focuses on this one family called
The Bogle
Generations from like
The eighteen-hundreds until
Present-day in the main character he focuses on is a patriarch named
Rooster
Bogle great name
Great name and rooster is this bad to the bone
Character I mean
This is one scene where
Keep driving by the Oregon State Correctional Institution with his son
And he's
Gazing out at the prison with
The sense of me
And tell the boys
Look carefully
Because when you grow up
You guys
I can end up
And doesn't say it like it's some
Morning he says it with
It is it is
Destiny it is
Bait to end up in prison
So it sounds like Fox Butterfield
Falls more on the nurture side
Well he does just that there's nature involved
2 like for example mental illness was passed down generations and That's genetics
What
Butterfield does he builds this
PS4 how much
Fever is
Learn by example
It's the bogles they were this really socially isolated family they didn't hang out with friends and hang out with other families
Tight social unit generation after generation so
One criminal would be modeling behavior for the next command
Down the line
It was literally a kid
Who committed his first
Burglary when he was
Years
Old
Because that's only saw his
Dad and
Brother's Day
And I know all of it sounds incredibly Grim but
The book was just so
Compellingly written I was
I was engrossed
The entire way through
Focus by Fox Butterfield what's it called again in my father's house
Alright thanks for the wreck outside
Happy Valentine's Day
Shout out to all of you in advance for sending a story ideas were Planet Money on NPR. Org
We put a link to all the Valentine's at mpr.org money Alexi Horowitz. Woods
Goldmark produced
And Brian Dorsett is our editor
Honda Fountain thanks for listening