This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep data in
Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Early morning last
December Dario sanguini and
His girlfriend were heading to the Dubai Airport
For the first leg of
An epic vacation
Norway
Today marks
Despain
You know Scotland
Sanguine synonym
Did Germany
Through France also Liechtenstein in Bulgaria they're both teachers so they were on a budget but
Tickets on Norwegian air which is basically the Spirit Airlines
International
Travel to go on a plane Dario settles into seating
Text his girlfriend
And the plaintiff
Mopar RC car
I am masculine
Sleeping away
Dozing
And then
Tell her to describe it between kadjar
To the left
It was like
Not if you're in a car
That's always crash into the side of you
Yeah. That was kind of the pool at the FL
He looks out the window and
Sister flying
Pretty close to the mount
A lot lower than you'd expect
And then things get worse
Define start
Define classify Crepevine left and right
But over water at this point
Sore throat and something's not quite right here
The pilot comes over the intercom and says yet but definitely got an engine issue and looks
The girl lacrosse
The Isle
She's crying Peugeot just person to to
And she was driving on tour
Cafe Le quite tight what the captain says next is pretty disconcerting
We are just going to to do about emergency landing
And run
Everyone's like what
I will I be able to do that for that okay
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Karen Stephen and I make dog food
Are they allowed to do that is it okay put your seat back in the upright and locked
Position secure your oxygen mask
Before assisting others
Fasten your seatbelt
Today on the show we go with Dario into era
Where we land in the middle of one of the most contentious fights in the world right now
Different decades
Usns allies
Have cut up around from the rest of the world
Using sanction
So This Plane can land in a run
But getting out will be much more complicated
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Support strong families and community
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf
. org
Flights like Dario's heading from Dubai to
Europe has a difficult choice of how to get
Yeah go to direct line in your flying right over a rocket
Not grades
So you can either go where your way over Egypt
Or go more direct
Can fly override
Most Airlines choose a run-in
Including Norway
Soap back on Dario's flight
The pilots see the low oil warning light
And they shut off
Don't worry there's two engines
A turn toward the nearest airport
In Shiraz Iran and they land the plane at it Wars
Weather weather
The best landing elevator when I've ever been on
Smooth Landing with only one engine. Is something that Norwegian air knows how to do anywhere in the world
But everything else beyond that
In a wrong
Is the question
Norwegian air has never landed in around before they don't have any business relationships in a rundown of the path
Passengers even have visas
The taxi
To the gate everyone gets out of the airplane
And at that point the flight crew Huddle's
With some Irani
In the airport
And they're doing the two problems here
First is getting
The passengers
Onto their final test
Second is to fix
The airplane so I can go back to making money for Norwegian
1 hour
3 hours 4 hours
And finally the caps
Back and says
All right
Here's what we're going to do
Sew weave
Obviously not getting us that Jesus is Uncharted territories what would happen as we were going to
Take you today at the hotel when catch
You don't have a Visa for Iran
So the delish me to leave your passport at the airport
Wow
Yeah exactly
Everyone's like I've seen this movie and it does not end well
No one
Is thrilled about this
But they don't have a choice
So Dario hands off his passport and everyone heads to Haute
They're kind of surprised by where they end up because you know they flew in on a budget Airline
But the hotel that they go to that was
Absolutely Lush
Peopleworks superfamily welcome to send
There was a gentleman play the piano which is rather nice
And Then There Was You
Optavia food
Drinks
Dario's tired
Just head to bed
It's actually really happy to be there
He can now checker on office
Not everyone is
Is thrilled to be
Stuck in Iran
We all just sat around in the lobby
Basically saying this is
William McCoy
He was also on the flight with
What does girlfriend he's from Ireland says a lot of the past
Centers we're Irish or Scottish if we could have some a few drinks
We would all the Irish day we said we could have had a great night bush
There was no bad cuz it's illegal to drink been around
It's not like these Lads can just go check out the local attractions
They can't even cross the
Street I had a really bad headache
So there is a pharmacy straight across rodent that can I go
I know you aren't allowed with no one was allowed to leave the hotel
Because
We have no visas for the country
Sober and exhausted
Liam go
In the morning a new plane has
Finally arrived to pick the
But one last thing before they head to the airport
Someone asks the women in the group to cover their hair be
That's the law in a run
And the hotel helps them out
Improvise
The hotel providers
It seems like always bed sheets
His girlfriend put one on
It looks
Ridiculous on her because it was
The sheet was like
Huge and she's got really small head from there dial says the hotel staff bid them farewell
They did have just one final request
Old who takes a four-lane. They are
Do a Hundred Flowers signify in Kenosha for coming to visit
Hotel in
Find clothes for Cummins Hit and Run
I had a choice
Can we go into TripAdvisor in and
And you don't tell them about the
Experience that go to the airport and
They are local celebrity
By this point
People are shaking their hands people are handing the magnets that say welcome to a run on them
And they get on the plane and leave
Yep the passengers got out on the replacement plane but now Norwegian has a much bigger problem that plane they flew in
Needs attention pic
And US sanctions are going to make that
Very hard to
They have
Turn to run
Into like the hotel California for this error
Can lender
But can it ever leave
After the break
We will try to figure that out
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information
Is available at aecf
. org
There is one person who kind of wished he was there in a Ron with REO and Liam
Dean constant tinnitus
Teens in aviation
Consultant work at Virgin Airlines for a decade has his pilot license
And also just follow this stuff all the time
So he been following the plane while this was all happy
He is the reason we know about it
Iran is such a
An interesting Aviation Space
Fred and Aviation
Does people who literally go to Iran just a fly on a handful of aircraft that you just can't fly on
Any more fuel of 54 Chevys you got a cube
If your thing is classic airplanes you go to Ron
Some of the planes in Iran have been flying
420 30 even 40 years
Because of the sanctions that existed for so long
Always classic airplanes 7 to 7707 Sabine flying around in Iran for long.
Sanctions that created this
Aviation time
Capsule were put in place after the Iranian Revolution in 1979
And then tightened in the 90s to try to prevent a run from developing nuclear weapons
They were then briefly lifted under a deal that we've all heard about the nuclear deal brokered in 2015
And Irani in aviation
Almost made it in
Into the 21st
Right at that my
Right after the sanctions lifted
Run order
Billion dollars of planes
From Boeing and
But then in 2017 the sanctions were reinstated after President Trump
Withdrew the us from the
Video
And say about me didn't even stop manufacturing the airplanes of an order for the jail
It was a last-minute Dash
I think in
24 hours leading up to the Embargo kicking in where I think
Airbus
Ferreting around 6
ATR 72 aircraft
Just in trial a canal behind each other just to get them in exactly sure when they were delivered but the planes that
Made it into a run work
Free from Airbus and 13 from another man
So
Here's Where We Are
Norwegian needs to fix it NJ
But under the sanctions
You can't import technology with more than 10% American made car
And if they want
You know a hall pass from the US government if they want an exception to that rule
Their first call will be to the treasury Department or it specifically the office of foreign assets
Assets control or ofac
How about that
The treasury Department office of foreign assets control call center is currently closed due to the government shutdown
Yeah the majority of the time
This Plane have been stuck in Iran
The US government
With shutdown
But it's safe to say that Norwegian did not
I just sit around they probably called a few lawyers who know how to navigate sanctions
So we called one to his name
Is Eric Ferrari
I feel like
For every taste that you work on you must have one of those like serial killer walls with
With red yarn
Yeah I mean there's a there's a lot that goes into it getting an exemption to
International sanctions is surprised complicated
It's working to simplify into
Three
The first one read the fine print
There are some exemptions that are written directly into the sanction
You're able to just proceed so long as you're able to
I approve that all the conditions are met but triple-check
If you're wrong
You'll get big fines
And possibly even jail we can assume that Norwegian
Has already done this read the fine print
We did call them they understandably did not want to get into detail with us
Which brings us to number two
What's 8
And we don't know this definitively
The Norwegian Deeds
Hayirli Nuen
If some other country save
Germany has this engine
Norway can
Borrow it for like
One-time pass into her
But intentions matter here
There we can't just call Germany and ask them
Time to buy an engine
Germany has to just
Randomly have it there lying around
Which
For being honest
Is a bit of a long shot
Soap does first two options are basically legal
The third one
Is where you straight about the US government print
Ofac is wide
Discretion to Grant
Licenses
If there's a determination made that it's in the National
Security or foreign policy
Interest of the United States
Duseau National Security
In foreign policy
As much as Norwegian
Want to say
Come on ofac
We're losing money out here
I mean it's inherent in sanctioning that somebody's going to lose money
Kind of the point so if
She were working on the
Best case and he were going for the
Assumption
Eric says he would write a letter that is
Basically
Gyro fat
Don't grant us
This exemption this plane stays in Toronto and that is not the purpose of
Sanctions
Also PS
If you let the plane stay there
Too long you don't have any control over what might happen to that plane if it
We get confiscated or seized by the government
So like if you want to be the ones to give her on a brand new fancy playing that you created sentient
Difficulty to prevent them from getting
Be Our Guest go for it
Obviously
This is not what the sanction
The US is not trying to disincentivize Pilots
For making safe emergence
They're also not trying to keep this a hundred-million-dollar airplane owned by one of our allies
Stuck on the tarmac in
Losing by one estimate half a million dollars every month
But this is the thing about us sanctions
The US cast
A very wide
The sanctions
Don't just punish a run
They're meant to actually cut off Iran from the rest
What's the world
And the way they do that is by penalizing anyone from anywhere who tries
Do business with a
Which is how
The United States got in the middle
Of Norwegians business
And Dario's vacay
Now that the US government is at long last open
Norwegian can start down this
Long and complicated path
But as we sit here recording this
The plane is still in Iran
Dario and his fellow passengers they did get out of her on
But not without complication
Few minutes after they took off your captain speaking
Choo-Choo The increased capacity of people 1/4 and the stronger-than-expected
We actually don't have enough fuel and you're going to have to do another message to Landon
We're going to stop
Dolphin pool in Vista
Apparently because a new crew had to fly the plane in
There were just too many
You're like really now are you just pranking us
Everybody
Buster laughing
Coordinated another emergency line
Why not
After that
Just turned into a party
A couple of Irish people in front of us and they
Speaker
People started saying into the whole sing-along going on
Christmas music
Off and on the plane switch
You don't people are conducting from the front of the plane to the back of the plane I feel like Norwegian got
Hair like this is
Kind of the worst possible
Customer Service international relations Nightmare and they got a bunch of
Chill Irish and Scottish people like Dario on board
Yeah it was there one stroke of luck
Absolutely have to change the oil in the engine failure to land in a run Assateague her girlfriend
I will I will take that under advisement
Hey you know Dean the flight nerd who kind of wish you was on that plane he is actually a planet money wasn't sent an email
The planet money at npr.org and it became this whole story
So thanks to Dean and thanks in advance of you please whenever you see something strange happening out there in the world
Send us a note Planet Money
Npr.org today's episode was produced by Darian Woods
Supervising producer is Alex goldmark
Our editor is Ryan Hurst at
Special thanks to our intern Rachel Cohen who did excellent research on the story thank you Rachel
Just want to thank dharius Raffi on
Esfandyar batmanghelidj Holly.
Batman
Fine folks norwegian.air who spoke with us on background
Also the people that ofac who did get back to us
Despite we are short a huge both shutdown backlog
I'm the fountain and I'm Karen Duffin thanks for list