Today Show is a rerun from 2017
We have a new update at the end of the show
Also Today's Show contains profanity
And
Graphic descriptions of data
White Oak pastures in Bluffton Georgia
About 2500 Acres
Will Harris runs the farm which has been in his family for more than a hundred.
Will was
Raised by his father and trained in school to be a modern Industrial
Cattle farm
When I got out of college
I was excited
About a new pharmaceutical product like
For hormone implants
Why
Increase production
You you are able to do
More and more cheaper and cheaper
Will take over from his father made a profit every year
But at some point the way you looked at the world started
I wish I had a better story to tell you I wish it was the burning bush something but anyone like that
It was way more gradual
And it happened in all these different
For one thing he started to look at the soil
I noticed that
The soil
Just over that fence
Wade
Soil right here
He saw that the soil on the other side of the fence
So that had just been left alone was teaming with life
The Swale right here on his farm was dead
She thought was it was in the world
Image of defence lawyer
A wire fence
And then there was the day he was sending off about a hundred cattle onto a double decker truck
Have to go to a feedlot thousands of miles away
He realized maybe on the truck for days the ones on the top would be going to the bathroom on the ones on the
And
If he's around those that we have had on this Farm
Nurture them
To care
It just didn't seem right
And eventually he decided to change everything about the wave
You bringing chicken
The fertilized
Grass
The grass would nurture the cattle
Shoppers at Whole Foods with line up around the block to buy his me
It was also
Perfect it was such a beautiful vision of the
Enlighten 21st century American Farm
It wasn't that so perfect that a literal symbol of America showed up at his farm
The bald eagle
But the bald eagle
America's bird
Was not on board with Will Harris
Hello and welcome to Planet Money I'm Jacob Goldstein
Put on the show The Meat you buy in Whole Foods the farmer who makes it
And a bad-tempered All-American killing machine
Farmers have been trying to put nature in a cage for thousands of years
What happens when you start to let nature out of that
Support for NPR comes from Newman's Own Foundation
Working to nourish the common good by donating all profit
It's from Newman's Own food products to charitable organization
That seek to make the world a better place
More information is available at Newman's Own Foundation. Org
No matter what you got planned you need a song of the summer
This week on NPR pop culture happy hour we are rounding up experts from NPR music we will play a ton of song
Songs to lift your spirits and might even find your next favorite artist
NPR pop culture happy hour listen to unsubscribe now
Will Harris is 62
Goatee shaved head
White Stetson hat
He drives around all day in his cheap basically running his farm and a few weeks ago I tagged along with him
This house was built in 1870 something by my great grandpa 1 download with my grandfather built
Early nineteen hundreds
My day was bigger than me and meaner than me and talk more like Foghorn Leghorn than I do
Seems impossible
Alfred Molina morphicon
By the way will Harris knows we are maybe making fun of his accent
And he's fine with that
In fact he's also making fun of RX
He told me the story about when he first started selling his meat at Whole Foods
He would visit the stores to be that sustainable farmer standing at a table
Handing out samples of his meat
A guy like you or lady
Won't mind take a little sapling
They snatch other cell phone iPhone go
Honey
Mission
I'm Whole Foods and
This is guy here and he's serving this beef and
I know we said we were going to have salmon for dinner but what do you think get beef will you think
Can you imagine what my wife would think if I called
If she was shopping to call me
We should
Mission Food
To driving down this this four-lane highway that runs through the middle of whilst
At at some point we pull off
And go down this dirt road into this really green pass
You could see there was like a
Forest off in the distance really beautiful and Will turns off the air
Engine to tell me you know how we went from being
An industrial farmer to selling you know pasture-raised organic high-end meat at home
One of the first things he did
Was quit using pasta
But when he did that these new kinds of grass has started growing in this field
The cows would need
So we brought in sheep and goats
He also quit using chemical fertilizer
I'm running chickens instead
Can we buy
Feed for the chickens
And
If he turns into poultry that we sell
By product to use the menudo that goes under the pastor that makes the grass
Genius
The chickens are spread out all over the farm you know that wasn't here that was in there
And their manure is his fertilizer
And then he realizes if he's going to sell this high-end meet at a premium
Send his animals off to the industrial slaughterhouse with all the commodity cows
So he decides to build his own sled
Which is Barry
But he's still started growing
He got his meat into a bunch of Whole Food stores and Publix this chain of grocery stores in the South also started selling is made
He was paying off that debt
And then
About a year after he brought in the chickens
The first pair of Eagle showed up
So I was very excited by the thought of great I love natural systems and I love
Nature nopales fantastic
We'll quickly saw that
The Eagles
Who Loved is pasture-raised organic chicken
But it was okay with it
Was just a few Eagles and he told himself the Eagles are like Nature's version of quality
Play Don't Kill
The quickest
Healthiest
Verge
Tropical people
You never get a sick bird from White Oak pastures
Everyone you get this
Your sister can say all but not random
The thing will didn't realize
Is that when Eagles discover an all-you-can-eat
Chicken buffet
The word spreads fast
First year they was at two or three the next year that was
Maybe till 12
Next year maybe 30 or 40
Last year
They said it was 77
You have more this year
Yeah by Usher
As more and more Eagles started showing up
More and more chicken started.
Have a long time
Her for my employees would say they are eating is up back there
Alright I need it bad
And I wanted to be all right
But at some point I had to show you know they really are
Causing economic
Lost Eminem lose money on Broiler chickens would you make money on chickens if not for
The Eagles
Over the past few years will says
The Eagles have killed
Hundreds of thousands of dollars worth of his
The peak season is winter
Right now
And will says the Eagles are currently killing a hundred or more of his chicken
Everyday
Thousands of chickens a month
And this is easy to see
You just drive out into one of the fields where the chicken
So what am I what is Sarah I don't know
Couple hundred chickens here a hundred times I don't have a son
House of a thousand chickens
And there's some of them
Some around in the grass some of them are kind of chilling out under this thunder tree over there
You on the shoulder the chicken house or something or eating the feed
Drinking the water
You like these chickens are living the dream but for one thing man
Bald
Eagles are just
Didn't they're in the trees right at the edge of the field
They don't make that
Screeching sound like you hear in the movies they don't really make any sound at all
But they do look big and beautiful you know they look like
A postage Stamper
Something you see airbrushed on the side of a van
But right there in front of us in this chicken Paradise were standing in our chickens the Eagles
Have killed so this got so this were looking at here is basically
The back half of
The chicken right there
Feet and legs
But the top half is essentially the eagle
Easiest way into the body cavity
Have you seen that
That happening with your seen thousands of time legal to sticking his head in that body cavity
Episode 2 of why didn't the eagles this is pink because it gets all that blood on it
So there's that this guy with somebody basically ate right this is a
Eating up chicken
Dividend there's this other chicken 3 feet away it's also dead
This chicken was just just killed
Cross respond
Nothing is happened to it
How many
Eagle Strike
Brightness
Just like a sport just like
Screw you I'm going to kill one more ticket
There were most pissed him off
Will Harris has completely transformed his farm to live in harmony with nature
And now here is nature
Sticking its head into his body cavity and eaten his financial
WhatsApp
It's kind of in space all the time
Betting legal
Mega missile juvenile bald eagle
Looks like
Full and happy
Breath smells like chicken
How do you feel seeing all these Eagles just coming and eating your chicken
Oh
Universal mixed bag
You know I could have it shotgun right now he's pointing at the back seat of the Jeep
He shot at other predators that were attacking his
Does life suck
But Hair Says
Hey he doesn't want to shoot bald
Abby even if he did want to
Eagles have their own special law to protect them
The bald and golden eagle protection act
Which makes it a crime to quote
Pursue shoot shoot at poison wound
Kill capture trap collect molest or disturb
Eagles
So will Harris is in a bind
Westfall he did get some good news from the Federal
Keeping granted special
Not the children
Baidu harassed
Basically try and make them go away
So he's trying all of these different things
What are the first things he did
You got one of those
Giant inflatable people like you see outside the car wash
You don't like this some kind of fan inside of Minnesota
Bend over and snap back up
He bought one of those
And put it up next to some chicken
He says it'll take about 15 minutes
To figure out there was just like one of those floppy guys
What would you like it
I actually saw this quickly
It was just lying on the ground the generator that powers and was out of gas
What about 15 or 20 feet away from a bunch of chickens
And yes one of the chicken
Will also put sparkly Flags out
Eagles didn't see
Seem to notice
You got this big old noise cannon with a barrel like 3 ft long you could hear it miles away
Eagles didn't seem to care
Another thing you tried
Admit
Over the top
Like a canopy over the open area where the chickens are walking around
But apparently Eagles do not have to attack from the sky
We were just walked in the land is woke up under the net and get the chicken
Will is trying one other thing to make the
The Eagles go away
Maybe the most badass
Of all the things he
He sent me out with his poultry manager Jeff Lackey to see you tonight
There you go right there is he going to go see just circle around to kill a chicken
Definitely I left his lunch
Oh he just move down
We drive across this field get out by chicken house
There's a couple thousand chickens walking
And just spotted eagle
Actually looks like there's one the Pharcyde that tree there
He pulls out what looks like a little little pistol
Cap gun of sorts that takes these two caps in the back
Benny opens up this yellow box and pulls out his ammunition
Take two
Black and goes into the gun so those look like little
Firecracker
Chris basically asking a small mats almost
What to say
Bird banger
Warning
Danger
15 mm
Captain has two barrels people it's one Banger in each Barrel
Holster trigger
This firecracker shoots out like
25 feet and explodes in midair
Then he pulled the trigger again
And there they go
Did you see on the backside I treat are there goes one right now
Eagles flying away
We can move them with the Birdman
And then they just come back
For the yellow go to another spot for now where we've got more birds and
Just circle around the many many pasture
That I can eat these chicken
I think it's going to go eat some other check
Yeah for the next couple hours
Then they're going to eat this chicken
Configure TV chicken
Will Harris says that you know maybe he's losing fewer chickens this year cuz of the bird bangers
Really to send it
But in any case he is still losing a lot he still losing money on his chicken
There is one other way will might be able to keep his chicken business
It's a federal program that pays Farmers whose animals are killed by protected animal
Boy killed by say bald eagle
How much do you think they should give you
The maximum is $125,000 per year
Everybody told me that for 15 and 16
Has the government giving you any money for the eagles killing a chick
Now $1
No one.
He's in this legal fight with a gun
This back and forth
What's the right way to count the losses what can
Can a proof do you need
Are we did reach out to the government on this they said the case is under review by the local office
And they are not allowed to discuss the
Whatever happens with the governor
It's clear that the Eagles are not going away
Are there like this living
Killing
Version
Of a much bigger
We want a world where we can restore some kind of balance with me
But every time we try to do that we realized
How impossible it is
Your right here on the farm you just keep seeing this Gap
Between how the world is and how we want it to be
But will is resourceful
Yorkie keeps trying to cross that Gap
At one point as we're driving around the farm
We're next to this field with some chicken tonight
And there's a pickup truck coming the other way
Wheel stops
The Jeep to talk to the driver
Hey how yo
I feel like you would I'm glad you did
In the bed of a truck
There's a guy with a camera with this giant telephoto lens
Which is apparently pretty common
People now come to Wells Farm to see the Eagles
Get the special Eagle day a few days before I was there even built cabins for people to rent out
Will Harris is getting into the eagle tourism
Yep
NPR
9 years old
I'm glad
So that was where we left it with will back in 2017
After the break
I find out how will is doing that
Support for Planet Money and the following message come from American Express
You want to build your business
They can help build your business with financing solutions for eligible business customer
The powerful backing of American Express don't do business without it terms apply
Visit americanexpress.com business
What is video games can help you and your child Bond and learn important skills and here is life good for parenting it taking
Turn on screen. When the big things were working on right now is a constable resiliency and not quitting when something is hard
Speed limits in lose and loose or since
Scraps of Life kit all guys Oliver episodes all in one place
A few months
After we originally ran this app
Someone who heard the story got in touch with Will
And he suggested something that he did seem work with other birds
That was
String a strand fishing wire up over the chickens in the pasture to
Scare the Eagles away
We mentioned it a follow-up story that Will was trying it out
So last week
I called you and left to find out how it was
We built these
Really tall portable
Pole structures
Stretch this relay
Big
Fishing lines of the Glen
Reflect the light
I think I heard those Eagles laughing while you're putting it up
In the end the fishing wire didn't work
He told me they're trying this new thing
Big fences basically so the chickens can still walk around in the pasture but with bound
I'm actually a little bit seagulls don't seem to like
But they'll go inside the fence but they're not as comfortable as they just
ESPN Wide Open
Few of them things we've learned to do
This, Mark that we're learning
The Eagles are still eating the chickens
But not quite as many chicken
Will says
This is probably the biggest pastured poultry business in the country in terms of numbers of birds on the ground
It's a new industry so there's a really steep learning curve
And the Eagles
What's good to talk to you
Glad you came
Uncle Jacob
Planet money has a once-a-week email newsletter
Truly smart I like it alot one recent issue or letter or whatever you call it that I like
With about this Supreme Court case about Apple's App Store and had a really understand it you need to understand the work
Joan Robinson this
Really an economist from the 19th
So you can subscribe to the newsletter at npr.org
Planet Money newsletter
Again npr.org
Planet Money news
If you know of any amazing stories of predation you can email us at
Planet Money at npr.org
Or find us on
Twitter Facebook Instagram at Planet Money
Today show with originally produced by Elizabeth Hula's
Today's rerun was produced by Rachel Cohn and Cynthia better Baeza
Brian firstnet editor show and Alex goldmark is are supervising producer
If you want to help out Planet Money you can leave us a rating or review in your podcast app
I'm told that it helps other people find the show
I'm Jacob Goldstein this is NPR
Thanks for the
We also have a milk squirrel call fox squirrel
But you a lot of this sitting up on their haunches
You're not from here forever cuz if I saw a monkey baby
You saw a squirrel no it was it was a monkey sound to you
Is that my voice in your head