Dell Technologies
The internet GPS in the palm of your hand
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
Derp
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been
Driver of techno
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window on a door piskor of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
It didn't please have with me in the studio Carrie Bernstein
A program manager since 2012
Enterprise Micro Systems Technology
That's the office
I mean the agency six technical offices that is devoted to doing more with electrons photons and electromagnetism
It's been possible in the history of Technology
Terry's curiosity and Science and Technology knows no bounds
What is background in the micro lectronics industry has everything to do with a mission he has taken on a DARPA
More than anyone
He's been pushing Technologies to reduce or even eliminate
The vulnerabilities to are billions of micro Electronics chips to things like hacking counterfeiting cloning
Tampering and other nefarious actions that are just no good at all for National Security
Pretty coming to DARPA
Carry an electrical engineer by training
Like more than 30 years at IBM where he worked on a dizzying array of technical subjects including Mike
Microprocessor circuit design
High-performance low-power devices circuits and architectures
New technologies that could replace the basic logic switches that underlie almost all of chips today
Three-dimensional chip integration and the ways radiation can damage chips
Terry has co-authored
Text books on circuit design he holds 155 patents
And is a fellow of the
Institute of electrical and electronics engineers
It's my pleasure to have you in the studio today
What's really mind
I'm always fascinated by the way people get interested in science and technology if there was some transformative moment or
Key person in your life that pointed you in that direction
Ivan it's sort of an ax
And if one of the most fortunate.
Accidents I've ever known
So you can it's a little kid I was always
Very interested in astronomy
Astrophysics
And God bless my daddy
He didn't understand any of the lecture
But I'd identify famous
Astronomers
Who's coming to
Lecture at the University
Chicago or University of Illinois and you would take
Was Wonder
And
I went to college anticipating I would
Study apps
Astronomy
And
I come from a family of fairly modest means
It became very apparent that
I needed to
Be able to pick up my
My college cost
And
Astronomers in St
Physicist just not in real high command at
What's the time
So I looked around in my credits
Reply to
To electrical engineering
And a normal physic
The night embarked on a career of engineering
And was the most wonderful accident
Let's talk about that move you made that pivot into electrical
And really electronic engineering as it turned out right so you can cuz you ended up going to IBM one of the most store
Ohrid companies and organizations when it comes to certain the entire history of micro Electronics
And I just would be interested in hearing about the numerous hats that you did wear there and
And what you learned about that
Technology
Timing is so much
And at the time that I graduated college
The technology that we use in current
Computing
Sea moss
Was just in its infancy and just for listening to might not know that that's such a familiar term if you're in that micro electron
Phonics world the cmas stands for what terry
I've always wondered
CMOS stands for complementary
Metal-oxide-semiconductor
And this is this is so that the work
Horse technology that underlies pretty much any chip that any of our listeners might have in their computers were were
Is there a dominant
Capri seating
Sea moss
Field-effect transistors
What's the technology called bipolar
The bipolar was very power-hungry
And the power was really limiting
How much you could do
So when I first
Entered
The space
CMOS was just starting out
And I had the great Fortune
Joining IBM
And IBM was leading the field in the development of
Processes
Circuit design
Architecture
For truly high performance computing
It's over a career of 30 years
I enjoyed this
This incredible ride
Bringing through new materials new applications
Producing the technology that went into machines that we used to play chess
Play Jeopardy
Quite a ride
There's two things about your experience there that fast they make
One is that you became part of that IBM team
With a bachelor's in electrical engineering right this was from Washington University in st. Louis and then you've got several
Phds worth of Education while you were there because you don't have a Ph.D here Ivan I don't even have a masters
Don't even have a masters but when I see you in action oh my gosh right it didn't clearly you got everything that that any of them
Hyper educated people here have
Are you learned it
Kind of insult you in the in the industry
He was
A matter of luck
That
When I entered the field the industry was moving so fast
That for me to take time away to
To take time out
To go for my graduate degree
Was actually putting me behind
Because I was not getting to participate in all the game-changing
New process
And Chip design
Technology
She's at work
Being produced
So I did take a few graduate courses
And at that point decided no I really want to
Being on the
The ground floor
Ryan just never look back
I've been very fortunate to be surrounded by just incredible human beings
There's this notion of a rising tide raises All Ships
And I've been so fortunate throughout my career to be surrounded by Truliant credit
Human beings continues here
There's one other thing that I think emerge probably largely out of your ID
Am experience
And that's your hundred and fifty-five
Who knows by now maybe this week you got another one
Tell me a little bit about
Some of the ones say that
Sick in your mind most that you're most proud of or that perhaps had the most contact
Perhaps the one that sticks out in my mind
The
Foremost
Is general purpose
Registers
4 high performance
Computing
At the time and you'll have to explain that for me and what does that mean
So
Clearly and thread parallel machines
There's simultaneous need for the same data in multiple locations
In microprocessor
And at the time
The notion was well let's keep
Keep interrogating a memory over and over and
Send its results
To each of the separate place
This is where it might be needed
The GPR
The general purpose register
Invention
How did I develop with her
Allowed us to simultaneously access the same data
And send it to
Different locations
At the same time
And
It it found its way into a lot of very high performance
Which computer application
If I was to this day
And went when did you make this development and get this patent
Early my career is one of one of my first one said sometime in the 80s
Yes ladies
Okay so let's not move to your dark adventure and another thing I really like to learn about from p.m.
Is the mechanism by which you ended up
Getting here
So some a program manager and office director at a conference
Others just were in love with DARPA for years and years and they kind of made the initial
I reach out
How how did you actually end up here
So without going Kiki on you
Over the 30 years that I was at IBM
This this happened about seven years ago
About 7 years ago
There was a
I was involved course in the design and
Fabrication
High performance
Computing elements
And
Became apparent there was a class
Defects
The class of failures
That were
Exquisitely difficult
A diagnosis
And a very difficult to image
Or to lie
Try to Define
But none the less they impacted yield BMP
Performance
And in some cases
Even had the ability to change
What the
Computer chip was supposed
To do it so you're talking about defects that really go all the way down to sort of the
Micron scale the transistor level element level
Scale of of these chips right near exactly right and I am not smart enough to be a high-level Ark
Architect I was very much
A hardware engineer
Very much about the hardware the physical design
And Fabrication of the actual listener is just a vision of this I believe we're probably talking of
About defects that could be the size of like individual biological cells 50 microns across
Even smaller
Indeed
Indeed and as technology scale
The size of the defects that were vulnerable to also
Continue
Shrink silk
It's essentially
Beekeeper
A very very clean environment
So
If you can clear to me that there was a class of defects
That we were vulnerable
Not just from a yield or functional point of view
But that potentially someone malicious
Could intentionally assert upon a process
Or a pond design
Perhaps
Compromise
The component or its function or its reliability its lifetime
Make a long story short I
Became a
Contractor
Consultant to DARPA
And Amethyst insulting era
Or phase of your intersection with our boys at 2 to begin to define the kinds of programs
That you ultimately would end up
Running
With the aim of addressing the concerns that you learned about when you're a type indeed initially it was
To consult an existing program
And
I
Became involved in actually doing things
To computer chips
And then
The DARPA program would hire
Reverse Engineers to try to find
What was done
And
We continue to make progress
At both.
Detecting
Identifying those
Those features which couldn't couldn't be detected
And
One thing led to another and after
After about a year of Consulting DARPA finally set one or two
You come to DARPA
So I retired from IBM at that point
Then came the dark
To assume
The swim Lane if you want to swim Wayne of
Hardware store
Right and released
Three of your programs and the names of them really kind of
Reflect just some of the goal that you have had in mind that I've been working toward
Summer referring to trusted integrated circuits which is known as
In the short form is Trust
Integrity and reliability of integrated circuits known as Iris
And the supply chain Hardware Integrity for electronics
Defense
Which
Is it known as short as Shield
Each one has its own individual aspects but together there's a certain kind of theme
And I'm wondering if you can actually sort of talked about them
Collectively
And of course diving into each one as you might
Feel so inclined indeed
God bless our warfighters
It is critical now
For us
To make sure that
Not just the mission is successful that that were protecting the warfighters
Executing atmel
Electronic components
We used to support that mission
Need to be
Authentic
We need to make sure that those parts do no more and no less than they're supposed to
But they were built where they claim to be when they were claimed to be
We have to make sure that they last for the full stated lifetime
We have to make sure that
There is no
Nothing done to that component during the supply chain during distribution
But there are no Trojan horses
Or Easter eggs
If you will better built in
And this is challenging right to rebuke because in the
Creation of a chip in the fabrication of a chip
There's so many players
It's so many different places that
And somebody can have your fingers on it
That that you really need some way of tracking
That's exactly right
Once Upon a Time
Chain of custody was a sufficient means
Up tracking
The authenticity and integrity of our component
But micro-electronics
Has indeed become global
And right about the time that I warned DARPA
That there could be
An issue in the space
V electronics
Space indeed
Went global
This the design is
We're not the only smart
People in the world
And so
Because of this
It was critical
That we develop those tools necessary
To be able to
Confirm the Integrity of the
One of the most audacious trajectory that you've been taking it and I get it just amazes me the progress that you and your performers
Is
With
Tiny little triplets about the size of
Glitter particles
I don't want to say anything more cuz I want you to
Tell listeners said just what you been up to with your
Performance on this task
Before you can go there
I'm reminded that
It's one thing to come up with a challenge
But it's quite another
To go
Execute
Go accomplish
Such a challenge
And to be clear the heroes in the space
Are the performers that DARPA has
Tired
Be a contract
To go solve this
I'm astounded daily just
Pick 3
Creativity the amount of themselves that they pour into the ceph
Birthday they skip holidays they stay home over
State they work
True Christmas sometimes in order to deliver
Products
Pictures of
The one that you're referring to Shield
The threat space is large
The threat space
Of mic electronic Component begins InDesign
It goes right through fabrication
And then after fabrication and packaging it goes through distribution
Shield is a tagging
Shield
Is is a means of authenticating
The parts that
We
Use it are most sensitive applications they have
To be the correct part
For a number of reasons the existing authentication Technologies were
Necessary but not
Sufficient
So Shield is a microscopic tagging
We hope to get it into the world records here before we are all done
But it is used to make sure that this is the part
That we intended
To go into
Our defenses
It has five special sauce
The first
Is a hardware root of trust
Every single microscopic
Shield
Chip
Has a unique identifier
II
Special Sauce
The heat shield I contains
Is an AES 256-bit
Encryption engine
100000 transistors
On a chip that is 100 microns by odd
Backgrounds
The 3rd
Is sensors that sense
If
The Shield ship has been corrupted
Compromised
Could Michael Dan any
Given way
The 4th
Is an antenna
Because it's way too small
Contact
And so because that we have to talk to with RF physical contact is too small
That's correct
V is
Self destruct capable
But if you attempt to remove it
From The Host
Component
It will cease to be functional
The part is powered
By the
By the interrogator is it
Sweetly supper
Heard from the host component
The goal is that at any time
At any place
An untrained operator
With no special
Equipment in this case being just an iPhone or smartphone
Can test the Integrity of their components
At any time and place
And get immediate
Trustworthy
Results
For free
Shield cost one tenth of a cent
And the entire operation would cost less than $0.01
Every time
You wished authenticate the part
When you authenticate the part it also reports the GPS location
And the TCP IP network address
Of where it was two
In this way
At least for the most
Serious
Over counter fit in phone threats
We believe we have a very cost
Effective solution
The goal is to make sure that
Counterfeiting and cloning
Becomes
Too expensive
It takes too long
For the bad guy
Right absolutely amazing description I mean this sounds to me like a bat
The highest of high technology
A certain length in the synthesis the way you're mixing and matching
Different kinds of Technologies also is just to me one of the things that characterizes
A lot of what's going on here at one thing I'm somewhat of a pain in the rear to my performers about
Because I'm just a knuckle-dragger hardware engineer
Everything we do
You have to be able to hold it in your hand
And this is a program
Especially this program where it's not rainbows coming out of keyboards are unicorns sleeping over Terminals and Magic
Will happen
This has to be
Deterministic
Quantitative
Very analytic real engineering
And after the initial Technologies were developed
Shield
Is about
Good engineer
We've engineered
A beautiful Prada
All right well since you're all about that kind of ground truthing
Where are we at with the with this
Program with these tiny little
Triplets how would you characterize the status
Shield is a 3-phase program
Phase one was to go develop
Those five core Technologies
Because they really did not exist
At that scale all five
Have been demonstrated to be
Functional
Phase two is the integration of those Technologies
Into the shield
Prototype
Phase 3 of the program
Which is the field test
Of Shield
Will begin
Early in 2018
The field testing
Is supported by
Some wonderful companies that we won't identify right now that have volunteered their supply chain
And we will do things
What's the components
Windshield attached
And use their supply chains
And we will see how effective Shield is
In Catching
Hickory we talked about
Shield
I do want to go back to to the other programs that you work on one of them is completed now and one of them is still in progress it was
Start with trusted integrated circuits Trust
I wish I believed
Kind of one of the earliest programs YouTube
Trust was the program that I actually began supporting before I enter
Trust was a program
To make sure that we could verify
Set apart is doing no more and no less than it is supposed to do
Trust was a large program
Lots and lots of achievements
We developed microscopes
We develop Solutions
For pulling netless if you will the schematic
From Chip
To make sure that the schematic is what it's supposed to
We look at both cots
Commercial off-the-shelf product
As well as Gods parts
Government-owned components
We looked at field programmable gate arrays
As well as Asic
The output of that program
Is installed in a number of agencies
All over the country
And stopping Leverage
Ready when you mentioned a 6in field programmable gate array names for
Other kinds of categories of integrated circuits
That have different capabilities
But all of which are used today and all of which we really need to feel very confident about is correct
So that's trust in that completed
A year or two ago when did that included
About
18 month
So obviously there's parts of the spirit of that program that are part of Shield
And the other program I just wanted to say a little bit about this one continues
Today and that's the integrity and reliability of integrated circuits program or Aires
The question that Iris answered was
If indeed we know that this component
Has not been compromised
In its function
Can we still be assured that it has not been compromised
And its integrity
How do we make sure with
With a low sample size
That this component indeed fulfills
Its lifetime spec
Its reliability
That it is up to the task
A performing
For $20,000 an hour
Or 100000 power in hours
Or whatever the spec is
That mission that is critical
To the defense
That it's installed in
Okay and this is to defend against such things as counterfeiting practicewear an old
Call Chip might be taken out of some unit it might than the blacktop right where new kind of
Packaging is put on with new printing looks new but in fact it's old and so might not be able to actually live
Up to its
Suspect that a user expects
That's correct Ivan
Just like human beings age
In automobiles rust
There's a lifetime to electronic components
And
The lifetime must be we depend on that lifetime when the Windows system
Is built
For that part to execute its function
Even without the malicious intent
We need to know we need to be able to
Very quickly assess
The reliability
Of a part
Concurrently
The reliability science
Is is a
Is very involved
Painful
Long-term
And so
Iris
Looked
To try to
Improve the turnaround
I'm the testing
Reliability
I want to move to a couple of other questions before we we close out
One of them is really I want you to reflect a little bit about micro Electronics
As a technology in your
Roll your beer several decades roll in
Pushing that technology forward and doing whatever you can to ensure the integrity and safety of it
And you know with some programs even moving forward thinking about
Next Generations of Mike electronic devices even in the nanoscale area
So so that we continue to have a
Progressive technology micro Electronics
As you think about all of that me what excites you about this category of technology and Terry what
I've been few months ago I had the
Privilege of
Spending a week with a 311th Fighter Squadron
At Holloman Air Force Base
In New Mexico
And after spending a week of them sharing
With me
What they do
I have the opportunity at the end of that week
To describe
To them what I do
And that's when it hit me
My son is training to be an A-10
Fighter pilot
The warthog
And when I
Got in front of the audience
They all look like Mikey
Y'all look like
My son
And I'm retarded
Steven hard now to talk
It's not just
As a DARPA program manager
Where is an engineer
As a parent
How many people
Everyone of course Wishes the best
Our warfighters
How many people actually
Current position to do some
It was one of the greatest
Epiphanies
Of my time at DARPA
Worcester realize that
I've been trusted
With
All this
Resource
And funding
And
Security
Given everything I need
To go do what I know needs
Redone
If I fail it's my fault
Because this
God bless this agency is giving me it's giving me
Everything
I need to succeed and it's all on me
And that's what's driving me and
In front of an audience like that
They deserve no less
Thanks for that.
You've been here since 2012 so you've been here longer than a lot of program managers and you probably are coming toward the tail end
When are you leaving
A September of
September 18th
I'm not actually sure you're even going to be able to see Shield through all the way to the end I know that that's you're going to
The most of the way but I'm I imagine you're going to be handing off some of the final
Testing
I'm just wondering with six years of of participation in this agency which is part of the the
Innovation ecosystem
What you have learned about it as an organization is it
Culture index
Darpa's incredible
Place
Just incredible
Of course it's a human organization so it's given to
All the variation that
Human
Endeavor
Introduces but it's such a rare place
To be given the opportunity
To go
Develop those ideas
Which you know
Can be made to work
Is a once in a life
Do you have any thoughts about
Post DARPA phase of of your professional Adventure
There are certain capabilities
This nation urgently needs
And I'm pouring the concrete in those holes
As quickly as I possibly can
My intent when I complete my DARPA post
Is to be able to move into a position where I will be allowed to continue
Toopoor that cock
Well I for one will be excited to watch you as you take your programs through to the point that you will be able
Able to end to see what you do
When you leave here now bringing your dark experience my preps back into the private sector and Industry whatever you might do
Where was I wish you the best of luck
We are at the end of our time here
This podcast I just want to thank you for
Spending this time with me
Oh thank you Ivan
Composure
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next voices from DARPA
For more information about Carrie Burns
Bernstein the programs he runs
And the other breakthrough Technologies dark but is working on
DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download this podcast go to the voices from DARPA page
I got this website