Dell Technologies the internet
In the palm of your hand operation
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War DARPA
The defense Advanced research
Projects agency
Has been a driver of
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window Into Darkness
Program manager
Their job
To redefine what is possum
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Paul Cohen
Program manager since 2013 in darkness information Innovation office
Which is also known here as i-200
There he oversees projects with names like
Big mechanism and communicating with computers
That are all about helping our all-too-human brand of intelligence
Collaborate
Woody merging
Computer-based artificial
It's a scene with deep roots at DARPA spanning back deck
So thanks Paul for spending some time with me today
Thanks very much I have
To give him the project you're overseeing here and which we will talk about in just a little bit I'm intrigued by several ass
Aspects of your background
If you can talk a little bit about those and do they really come to mind
And I'm all that you have a degree that combines psychology income
Computer science is not a degree in computer science is not a degree in Psych
Psychology but it's
Find Lowe's
And I'm also intrigued by your father who I'm sorry to acknowledge
Passed away just a few months ago
She also pushed in Blurred the boundaries
Between
Humans and machines in his case in the realm of Art
I'm hoping that you can talk about those two things in other aspects of your background
That would help us understand how it is that you ended up here at DARPA and why you are pursuing the sorts of projects
Since you are here
Yeah well
Thanks for bringing up my dad he was in many ways
Inspiration
Tumi
Think back to the
1970s
When
Not everyone had a computer there weren't laptops there wasn't an internet some people had computers
I'm computing
Was
I thought points of the metaphor of our times
Just a steam engines and electricity and other technology it's would have captured
The imaginations
Scientists and Poets throughout history
The computer
Took on that room
And many people
Certainly my dad
Later me
Started to think of the computer
Has a way of thinking about
Other things how to make art
How the mind works
We started to think we'll maybe it's a computer
Or maybe computational processes could do those things
But there's always paying attention in AI
Artificial intelligence artificial intelligence
Between whether you're using the computer
As a model of what humans do
Weather
You know you're just modeling a new kind of intelligence
It's machine intelligence
I think what's happened over the last 30 years
Is that all of us who started out interested in using the machine as a model walk humans do
I've now sort of come around to the fact the machine intelligences own kind of Intel
Artificial intelligence these states actually has very little to do with humans
You say that that
Remind me again of that combined
Not agree so talk to me a little bit about about that
Will it I mean yes I have a combined degree inside cognitive psychology and computer science
But remember that was in the late 1970s
We didn't even know what
Call that thing then it's
More recently been called cognitive science
I attended the first cognitive science conference
UC San Diego undergraduate
But but
You know I was using the machine to study
Human
Thinking
Nowadays when you talk about combining
Human
And machine
Thinking you really telling about something else
You're talking about
Machine intelligence
Its own kind of intelligence
Meshing well with human intelligence its own kind of intelligence you're not talking about one trying to emulate the other
A model the other orthodox
Stand in for the other you talking about
Too premature kinds of intelligence
Call listening to the kinds of interest you have in the directions you taking this is this
Does remind me
That your work really connects with us
Kind of long history here
Add doorbell and trying to really find out how the human intelligence
Jensen and artificial
Just so you know
Yes that's exactly right and
I think for really long time
People have viewed the machine role episode of a power tool
So the machine is going to
Do the very heavy
Front work
What's the we don't want to do it
Proofreading it'll sort of surf the web riddle
But it'll always do what we tell it
To do right and where did the phrase data-crunching comes to my side crunch
No doubt about
Who's in charge and why the machine is doing things we
So that's being their attitude towards machines machines are
You know they're there like the tools in my toolbox
They act on my Direction They simply amplify what I want to do
Now
I want to change that
And my communicating with computers program has as one of its tenants that the machine must actually
They have something to say
And something to contribute
The machine is going to be creative the machine is going to do some work
On its own
Forts for its own reasons
What I didn't count on
Is the enormous
Cultural barriers
To that view of machine
Even within my own program
Explain a little more you know within my own program
I do want most program managers do I say let's pick
Some
Use cases or
Applications that will
You know really drive this technology and so you say to all of these superb scientists
Tell me about some applications
And all of your applications they come back with
Have the machine in the role of a servant
These are the best scientist in the world
CC Macon
Imagine the machine was actually doing something for itself and it really takes a lot of effort
To think of machine says you know autonomous intelligences
Well and I think you've gone so far as to
Challenge some of your
Performers those who work with you on the
This program to even think about the machine
ACO improvise
It's a right almost like they're in a in a jazz group together we could talk a little bit about
That's
Yeah well actually jazz is a very interesting form of communication
Very very similar
Conversation insofar as
They're they're pretty strict rules
The governed The Interchange between two Jazz musicians
But there's also an enormous amount of creativity
Are there other similar
Use cases within the program one is
Taking turns contributing lines to a story
Or to a poem
Horchata recipe
What was Finding
Is that when you look at a short poem that is written both
Buy human and machine
And you show that poem to another human
That person isn't so good at picking out which lines were written by the human and which were written by the machine
I would consider that a metric
I think it is symmetric
Given that this is a program communicating
Wizz computers
The program within DARPA
Defense Advanced research projects agency
How do you imagine this new way of communicating with
Computers assuming that your Altima lease
Successful
Will how will that change
Apps away
Those in the in the
The world
National Security
Relate to computer
Those are used on
Yeah well I think what one
One has to realize
That
The modes with which we communicate with computers today
Omar
Extremely unnatural
Very very cumbersome
Can you still give me things like keyboards keyboards but actually if you want a computer to do something
And you said I have two choices
You can either
Be a programmer
And most people aren't
Or you can use
An interface that's been designed by
Programmer
You can point and click and swipe
Some things like that
And neither of them is a
Every natural way
Of interacting
With the machine
One of the
Just on that point so natural for example here we are
Talking I'm looking at you I'm paying attention to your facial expressions
I'm very gestural when I talk so you can see
I might have to going all over the place is that what you mean by Nacho
Communication
Baidu
But the sentence I just said I do is also offered during a wedding
But it means something completely different
Here
Send it does a little wedding
And that's because of
And there has never been a good account
Computational theory of contact
The wood support
Human machine communication and that's really
The biggest technical problem
In the communicating with computers
Program
It's a natural communication
Depends on context
And we've got to be able to represent contacts other When I Say I Do
You don't think that
I want to get married with you
I'm upset
So how far along are you or your performers which is sort of DARPA speak for those who end up
Working on Pacheco
Project
In
Getting machines
To handle contacts
Text to be able to discern Conte
Text in the case of
What wherever there's an I do
Were you just saying
I agree with you
Versus I want to marry you
How far
How long are they
Well
Weaver pek 3 big problems to work on
In the program
And
One of the things that distinguishes them is the amount of contacts that's available
And the amount that has to be inferred
So the simplest problem
Is to build
A sort of a castle out of wooden blocks on the table top
And the contacts that's available there
Is available to any computer vision system or to any human who can see
You can actually see the blocks
So when I say at another one
You can see what we're talking about the context this right there it's
Accessible
Then the second big problem we're working on is having humans and machines collaborate
To build
Very complicated models of biological systems
And there
The context
Is maintained by all kinds of
Clever machine visualizations
You know this molecule talks to that molecule and here's a great big network of molecules
What's the third use
Yes of a third use-cases this improvised ation kind of used
Case and there
The problem is for the context is established by the by the notes of the musician plays
Oh by the words that a person says
And nothing else
Just as in this conversation
Context is established by the words and nothing else
Not a hundred percent true right
We both have shared
Common experience
So
Context is established by the words
And this enormous background of human knowledge
That turns out to be extremely hard for machines
I have low expectations there
Machine for example would not know why
Baidu
In a particular context
It's funny because it just doesn't know anything about
Get married and what you know it just doesn't feel right I said what I'm waiting for now is the greatest metric metric of success
For me will be when when
Paul you
From your program we get
First
Comedic
Let's Segway then into your other projects at the moment
Big mechanism
Well
Why are we doing big Magnuson we are doing it because I am terrified
That our reach exceeds our grasp
We are
In the state of human history where we can
Interfere
With
Systems
That we don't understand
And
That's okay if
You're making some small experiment in your lab and you have to blow your lab up
But it's not okay if it's the climate
Or the economy
Or any of the other huge the stones on which we depend
So what's the problem is that
We have really no good way of anticipating the effects of actions taken and very very complicated cyst
So big mechanism is a program
To develop technology to help humans
Build models
Of complicated systems
Models of
Unimaginable complexity
Things That No human
Possibly build
Alone
Okay and I think
One of the ways that
You are hoping
Computers will be able to do this
Gets a little bit back to
That sort of data crunching
Brute Force aspect but this is
Right where maybe a computer could go into the scientific literature and read a hundred thousand
A million papers that are relevant
Does something like maybe
Oncology the onset of cancer or something like that something that
People can't do right
Exactly what we're doing
So talk a little bit about that ability to kind of look at the
Information sphere in ways that just impossible but then
What will the computer
Be able to
Gather from just
All of all of that information
Well so let me first describe what
What was actually built and then
And then I'll come back to you
2 question
What we have now is
Big collections of programs
That
Read the scientific literature
Temperature in
Cell signaling biology cell signaling is all of these molecular processes
Mapreduce
Effects in cells including cancer
Machines can read those papers
At the moment
And as you said can we Hunters
Thousands of paper
And out of every paper
The machine extract a little piece
Of biological mechanism
You know this molecule phosphorylates that molecule or binds with this molecule that kind of thing but every paper
Really talks about only a couple of little things like
It may be a 10-page paper but the main results is like
Tiny
So after you read
300000 papers
You have
Half a million
Tiny little fragments of a big complicated mechanism it'll. Little picture pixels of what might be a picture
That's right
Now you have to put it all together
And so that's the second big step
In Big mechanism is to assemble all of these fragments into a biologic
Medical model
Third step is to reason with that biological model to solve problems
How would I drug this cancer
So
This is giving me a sense of where
Our two different kinds of intelligence
Who's really come together because we like to be able to tell
Stories
We like to have
Causal explanations mechanism
Why things happen in the world
And we are sort of good at that but we are not
Great at at
Seeing how a hundred thousand
Points
And.
Connect
We can see how
1020 + 30
Where's the computer now
Can bring in a hundred thousand points
But if we're working with Attitude say
Computer look at those points and also tell a causal story
Then we're beginning to kind of work together am I getting yet a little bit of what you're seeking yeah and I want to be clear about why
I think this is revolutionary and to do that I want to go back
The 50s when DARPA was started
Does a response to
Sputnik
The United States
Began
To emphasize sciences and Engineering for the United States also started to reward specialization
In The Sciences
And we've gone to the point now
Where
I can't understand what the guy in the office next door
Does
We have become highly highly highly specialized hyperspace
Hyper specialized
The speed at which we read has not increased
So we read more narrowly
Now here's the problem
The world's existential problems
Do not fit
Neatly into any one academic Department
They are systemic problems
Am I can't think of a worse way
The song of a systemic problem
When to get a bunch of people
Who are experts in the tiniest aspects of that system
What we need is a big picture
And
Where humans can't machines must
And humans can't
You know I'm doing well 320 papers week
But in order to understand the system I need three three hundred thousand paper
So this is very interesting and in a way which you're saying if you look
Even just a structure
Of a university or even a company you have sort of departments
And Amber we're almost institutionalizing an inability
To synthesize in this very broad-based way that your suggest
But the institutions continue to sort of
Put us into these compartments words you're saying
We now are in a place where we can combine our desire to synthesize with
The powers of computer tab
For new kind of bug
Era of synthesis new kind of scholarship
That's why I view it as revolutionary it's not just that a machine can read a large number of paper
It's the by doing so we have a chance
Just a chance
Understanding the systems on which we depend for our survival
That really is exciting to me
But as you know there's a great dialogue going on in society now about you know what it means for
Computers to get smarter
Where to get more into
Get smarter like us
And intelligent like us were smarter or intelligent in their own ways
And this brings up some concerns it brings up excitement and concern
I'd love to hear what you're excited about
As
The computer the ball this
In fact as you have a role in that
And also what gives you some pause
If
People understood just how little machines were capable of
I think
You wouldn't be
Hearing
So much of the snow
There are, but I just want to push back a little bit there because it's a 19
Bell Labs rolled out a single transistor it was an ugly looking thing
And now you can get a chip
That has billions on the on something yet
Fits snugly in my
My palm
Those are Worlds Apart
There was nothing much that little
Single switch could do
And maybe do something in the telephone system
Initially and now we have microprocessors that do we know Wonders on
Even on our home computer so
So
If we add time to to the picture here
Do you still think the people do not have justification of some concerns
I think the people are right to be concerned
About
Fielding new technology
Second
Do harm
You know self-driving cars
Could I suppose
Get people into traffic Act
Accidents
Corsodyl
What are the solute
The reason I'm not all that concerned
Is the this is not by any means the first
Time
The society has come to grips
With threats posed by new technologies and we've always figured out
How to deal with those threats
In one way or another
Society
Finds ways
To offset the cost
Associated with new technology
We simply build it into the cost of doing business
Not till we learn how to manage the written we manage the risk
And that reminds me of some specific ways DARPA
Is working to manage the risks of a coming era
Artificial in
Intelligence and machine learning
I'm thinking here of programs like explainable AI which your fellow program manager
David gunning is running
And in that program he's got the goal of
Developing artificial intelligence and machine learning techniques
That
Not only produce results and gather data and make decisions to help you and partners manage and operate the
Complex systems in our world
But they are systems that do this in ways that are transparent to the humans in the loop
And that way the machine Behavior remains understandable unexplainable
At least in theory crustable
I want to move away from specific programs and asked you about
DARPA
As a
Part of the overall Innovation ecosystem and and what I'm thinking about there as other elements in the
Tamar say academics
About her fundamental source of questions and doing maybe fundamental research getting new data that hadn't been out there
Before I'm thinking about
Entrepreneurs were thinking about how to
How to apply science in into
And turn that into various that small and large
Technologies
Answer weird DARPA fits into
All of that
Dash in in as we sit in the very beginning and Beyond being a driver
BowTech
Well of course darvaza very distinguished history is it
The driver of
Technology
And we we could talk about why it's being so so
Successful
Then maybe I could related a bit to my personality
Experience which side work for DARPA as a warmer
For 30 years
Before coming here as a program manager
And
I have to say you know I thought I knew DARPA pretty well
But it wasn't till I got in the building that I realized I was a really icing
A pretty narrow slice of what DARPA does
Starbucks
Sits at the intersection of government-industry Academia
And other kinds of research
And it brings it all together it's it's
It's got this a big picture
Of how Innovation happens
I in the United States
And it's been very successful
Making it possible for everybody to do what they do best
You know the words that goes on in academe it tends to be if I might
Say a little conservative academics
I don't know
People will be surprised to hear this but I think academics
Tend to be pretty conservative in the problems they
They they taco
Siddhartha's role in Academia is often to say
Let's take on something that's impossible
And we're going to pay to get it done
You know so that's what that sort of the message to Academia
Of the message
The government is look what's possible
We just changed your view of what what
What technology can do
Think about how you can use it think about how you can
I use it to achieve darpa's mission of creating an
Avoiding strategic surprise
Write and listen to you talk about
Darkest place in The Innovation ecosystem in
And moving technology forward it also
Reminds me a little bit of what you were saying
About
Big mechanism
In bringing forth a new kind of synthesis nubility
You take many different
Four categories of
Nothing can bring them together
One thing the DARPA seems to do is to bring communities together that do
In ways that might not be
Very easy for the performers in their own institutions
But here is a program manager you in a way I can bring together 5/6
Performers together
And create a community just didn't exist
So we talked about Altra specialization a moment ago and you just use the word disciplinarian and
And I got really interested in the word
Interdisciplinary
Because
It occurred to me that I heard it everyday
At the University
I might hear it never
Adorable
And I've come to view the word interdisciplinary as
Standing for a problem
Not standing for solution
And the reason that we don't hear that word of DARPA
Is that
We just take it for granite
Everything we do at DARPA is interdisciplinary
All of my teams are interdisciplinary I have machine reading people I have linguicide biologists
It's just taken for granted
Right I mean I look at the P&R pyrite the projects
Which is another way of thinking about it
Problem driven way of going about R&D so if you have the end
Part of an endpoint in mind you don't know exactly where you're going because
He's our Leading Edge
Areas
But you have some sense
Then
Really
You're not saying this is a biology problem or a physics problem or an engineering problem it's just a problem that has to be solved
No matter what
Mindset or skillset you need to bring in
And it turns out that that may be a huge variety
Yeah when people get to the project
Hyundai
They're trained in machine learning on suddenly a cancer biologist is up there speaking
Their eyes get big in the room cats
Quiet
And after a few weeks
Or Mom
There
The happiest people
Because this is the way science should be done
And
They got
To participate in that kind of science
On that note I think we we've run out of our time for this discussion though I'm going to be eager to follow
Up with you
Some other times and so I just want to thank you Paul for joining me in the studio
Before this really great discussion. I've enjoyed it very much thanks so much Island
And thank you listeners for joining us
And I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about Paul Cohen
Is programs in the rest of what DARPA does
And to find this and other episodes of voices from DARPA
Visit us online at
DARPA. Bill