Dell Technologies the internet
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the Mist
To the Cold War
DARPA
The defense
Advanced research
Search projects agency has been
Welcome to voices from DARPA a window onto darpa's
Core of program manager
Their job
To redefine
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your doorposts
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
US army colonel Matt Hepburn
An active-duty army physician and since 2013
Program manager intern
Biological technology
Turtle Heparin holds a Bachelor of Science degree and by men
And a Dr of Medicine
Both from Duke University
Following all of that education he completed an Internal Medicine Residency and an infection
Breast disease Fellowship
Brooke Army Medical Center at Fort Sam Houston and tax
Prior to joining DARPA Matt served as the Director of medical
Preparedness on the White House National
Security staff
An additional previous assignments included
The chief medical officer at a level 2 medical facility in Iraq
Clinical research director at the US Army medical research
Stitute for infection
Diseases
And in exchange officer to the United Kingdom among other positions
Matt is one of darpa's program managers who comes to work in his military
Retire
In his case either is Army fatigues or a dress uniform
Either way he always wears the smile of someone
Who finds himself in a place where he just might be able to
Realize a dream
And he has said publicly
That he wants to stop all info
From killing p
Maybe so
Turtle Matt Hepburn though I will call you Matt from now on it is my pleasure to have you in
Studio today
It's fantastic.
To be here and and thank you Ivan for inviting me to be on the podcast into
Tell my story and tell you what I care so deeply about
Greatly looking forward to the discussion
And so your medical professional who Embraces clinical and field practice
As well as leaving
Edge research
What are the origins of those in
It started pretty young
I have this childhood memory of being ass at my school
The Catholic school and I was meeting with one of the priests and they simple what do you really want to do
And I said I wanted to be a pediatrician
And they said
Why an end and I said well
Cuz
Just want to take care of people
I want to take care of children
And I do think it stems from my mom was a nurse and so I think less so from the info
Florence Ave
Being around someone in the medical profession but more so just being around somebody that cares very deeply about other
Again very early on and it's a but it's been it's been sort of a consistent part of my life that is really
Yeah this was in fourth grade this whole like you know I wanted to be a pediatrician the toys I was on this trajectory and I didn't know
Of course what I was talking about you make these decisions early in your life
But my parents and my family always had this incredibly strong ethic of service
And very deeply and fundamentally cuz I reflect on the soffit
Actually it's like
Who am I in and what am I supposed to be and I think
What I do is I survived
That's that's how I defined my
Maybe one of the greatest gifts from my parents was
My dad was active duty Navy officer did RTC and served as a nuclear engineer
On a Surface Warfare ship
It was actually for five or six years stayed in the Navy for another 20 plus
Retired as a Navy captain in the reserves
You couple my mom's passion for helping other people in the medical
Field with my dad's passion of serving our country
This is almost like all I knew until that trajectory his would have guided me through all of my
Okay well if that's actually talk a little bit about that in before you came to drop you spent almost 15 years in a variety of
Simon Says
U2 for example 40
Dietrich
Premier facility for infectious
Disease
Koreatown
UK
At the Republican
Georgia
Azerbaijan
Erectile and other places I'm sure what did you learn from
All of that Global Experience
I would start by saying what a privilege
What a privilege
To have those types of life experience
All in the context of
Again feelings that I'm serving my country and make
Some of the work that I'm most proud of frankly is work I did in the caucuses with Georgia and Azerbaijan and
The program
What was under the auspices was called The Cooperative threat reduction
But really my rule there was
To engage their Public Health Community
And their medical research community
To establish that capability of finding infectious diseases diagnosing them in Ultimate
Treating them
And it was a capability that was
Those public health systems were all part of the Soviet Union but when the Soviet Union fell
These countries were kind of left to their own to
Recreate a public health in.
And so the privileged
Was to work with those experts in the host country to say how do we build that back up a
So that you can tell us that there's an outbreak going on and then we can
Collectively work together to respond to that
So did you bring in models like
The centers of Disease Control
Did we did we work closely with the Embassy Suite work closely with the state department we work closely with the CD
DC at the end of the day
It was myself and some of my DOD colleagues on the ground
Near rolling our sleeves up
Helping these countries develop the system
Developing laboratory capabilities
Developing the ability to do clinical research
2 ethical standards that would be accepted all over the world and to
Figure out how to do this you know again I look fat
What a privilege to be on the ground
I'm at and at this point fairly Junior in my career and to help by the entire nation
Improve the public health
Another cat sound like
The great privilege
What is the sequence of events matthat
Resulted in your
Current position here
DART bus app
Drop my medical career I had heard about.
And I had seen
Amazing technology that is
Come from DARPA that were aimed at addressing infection
Kisses
So I always admired from afar
Before I joined our pie was over at the White House National
Security Council
And in that role my job was to
Identify what capabilities we do not have to respond to pandemics
And then how we can organize ourselves as a government not just DOD but as an entire government
Towards addressing this Gap so we're ready for the next
And while I was there I got tapped on the shoulder
And the
Concise phrase was
You're doing all of this policy what we should do as a government
How would you then
Like to implement
And actually
Make investments
They're going to address us
So that's where you literally tapped on the shoulder
Was supposed to say It was Doctor Jeff Ling was the death
AP director of DSO at
The time
And
He at least I met him for coffee one morning
And he
Didn't literally actually put his hand on my shoulder but
Figuratively imagine a hand on my shoulder
Saying
How would you like to try a DARPA to actually invest make a difference
For all those things that you've been talking about in her the big policy word
Well and of course he provided a model of audacity because he really took on Trump
Prosthetics and other programs to really help by the Warfighter why don't we Segway than into
Your life is a program manager here in this tremendous portfolio
That you've developed which is I think a portfolio that also reflects some kind of audacious
Point of view
As of course
A reflected by that statement earlier
You want to take the lethal power out of infectious disease so the names are fantastic some of them like
Prometheus and Thor dialysis like Therapeutics in vivonet
A Platforms in will probably talk more about one of them and
Particular
The pandemic prevention plan
What I'm hoping to do now is if you could briefly take us
For a tour of your program
Cuz we can't go in depth about any of them
At this point
Take me to a little bit of a torrent
What you're hoping to achieve with some of these programs
And then we'll focus in a little bit more
Pandemic
Yeah so that tour starts by saying
What what problems are we trying to solve
And again
At the White House Nashville
Security Council staff I got a chance to say
Look for these
Major outbreak
Pandemics are near pandemic
How have we done as a government
Think about the 2009 H1N1 pandemic
I think about the West Africa
Ebola crisis H1N1 influenza
Influenza think about the West Africa ebola crisis think about how we've recently responded to zika
They're coming themes throughout and some of those common themes are we need to be much better
At diagnosing if someone has
And we need to go A Step Beyond that and imagine a world
That if we could
Figure out if someone
Is going to be sick
Or is going to be contagious
We can intervene and stop the outbreak writing
And that's for me
And that's the Prometheus
But we also need to make vaccines and treatments much fast
Then we currently
And that's one of the examples is the pandemic prevention plan
We need alternate ways of how we treat infection
And using portable dialysis
To filter the blood and remove any type of path
Is a good example
But the purchase in that case is that mean I might by might have been exposed to some kind of pathogenic agents
In my blood certain
Level so it would this kind of Technology
Remove that before could take hold and actually get me sick
Was that the idea of that yes
And it the idea would be
Again
Especially for pathogens where we don't have a vaccine
Where we don't have it
Especially think about now with what we're seeing so much of antimicrobial resistance
Bacteria
Imagine if
Where we can't use antibiotics
So if we can filter your blood and remove that Passage
What has ultimately gives a leg-up for your own immune response to ultimately
Make you well again
We like that technology especially
In those first days when we need to buy some time to develop a vaccine and when
And so my point across the portfolio is that
We have lots of investments in medical diagnostic
Text we're investing in modeling to forecast where infectious diseases are going to go we have Investments and accelerate
Braiding new treatment
But they're all connected together
They are all linked
And let me give you an example
With our Prometheus program
Predicting if someone is going to become contagious
Awesome right
We can do that
But once we predict and identify that person
We still have to
To treat them
And so
We're going to need
Treatment
Fast as possible
With our pandemic River
Pension platform
And the beauty is that those treatments are probably going to be most of
Active when they're given as early as possible
So
I think of our whole portfolio as interconnected
That we develop a lot of different specific projects to hit capabilities
But that their ultimate league going to intertwine
So that we stop the outbreak in it
Tracks well when I think of programs or darbydale have a kind of
Lifecycle to them right I mean lately certain started
Glimmer in the eye of Someone Like You matter program manager
There's a. Wedding and working with others here to really
Articulate
And formulate the program is
Best of candy soda
It's can be most effective and then kind of smoke signals go out to the world and seeking people who maybe think that they can pull offs
Some of these audacious tasks that we'd be without course then the research is done and hopefully
In the end
You succeed or if not
Fully succeed you learn from
All the research
What's going on
What is the status of that life cycle
Of the pandemic
Prevention platform
The democratization platform
Just launched
And so and by lunchtime those who might not know what that means in the DARPA context
Said that that means that completing the Contracting process
So that are performers
That were selected in a very rigorous process
Can now accomplish the goals of
The program
So they're just starting in there for 6
As part of the life cycle
These are early days
Early days because the ultimate goal of that program is so
Difficult
I'm we have a lot to eat on some ways I feel like what we have
We have a long way to go
One of the key points though of the pandemic prevention Platte
Is that
The goal is
Incredibly ambitious
But there is foundational scientific evidence
That this can be done
And that foundational scientific evidence is derived
From a previous DARPA program
And that previous Circle parade other approved the concept of depth
That's the Adept program
Because when I looked over the program it's fascinating to me cuz it looks like
We're trying to rev up the whole
Brilliance molecular world of anybody
And so I want you to go through this the sequence events beginning with this earlier program at depth
Yeah but walk us through some of the steps because when I look at anybody's to Armand my favorite proteins when I look at them
William things like
So selective
Find the thing that we don't want our bodies like gloves anyway you tell us the pieces of the program
And you know I haven't I couldn't agree more
I think all of us that are fascinated by DARPA right this very uncommon thing is we are just a man
Amazed
By the natural world and what the natural world has developed
Antibodies are grade exam
I mean there are millions and millions
Of these different versions of antibody circulating through your body at all times
And
The mechanisms are so refined and intricate
To select
Okay
Which are the antibodies that are most protective
When you're exposed to an infection
And your body goes through the process of them making a lot of those in a short. Of time
I think it's mind-boggling how advanced that system is
We've learned so much about antibodies in the last 50 years
You're absolutely right we want to Leverage
All of that information that we know how they work now and we know all that we know about their structure
We know how to make them in big vast and why can't we use that
And you're seeing incredible progress in medicine
Where we are using the
Where you're seeing antibodies approved as products now
For cancer tree
For treating autoimmune disease or the category of biological index in the category of biological tomasovic
Explosion in that space
And we want to use all of that knowledge in that technology
To solve infectious diseases
What we do at DARPA though is the fun part is we couple different fields together
And so
As you correctly pointed out this extraordinary powerful tool of antibody in
Engineering but can we couple that
With the the revolution that we seen in in genetic
And that's
That's DARPA right it's taking two different areas
Seeing if we can mix them together
Again an antibody specialist might not think about the opportunities with genetics
The genetic specialist might not think we'll wonder if I could
Use my use genetic engineering to make an antibody
You bring the two Fields together in the more you know by RR Magic
Bringing them the disciplines together we achieve that effect
And so
The proof-of-concept
Which I find exhilarating
Chills up and down my spine
Is that
We can give you a
Piece of DNA
Or piece of RNA
And
We can
Put that into your muscle cells
And that your muscle cells
Say okay got it
I am going to make this antibody that is so protective
That someone's knocking
And that's encoded by these nucleic acid
The RNA and TRNA tells that muscle cell to the muscle cells doing what a muscle cell does
But once that RNA gets inside that muscle cell
The muscle cell size
Right
I'm going to make a protective antibody is going to protect you from evil
And to do that in a
Fairly short period of time
And that idea would sound crazy 10 years ago
Too many obstacles can't be done
The foundational investment
I'm from DARPA
Prove that console
In many different animal models for many different
Fight because we're DARPA we said we're great we proved the concept
That wasn't good enough
It wasn't good enough for me it wasn't good enough for the DARPA leadership
DARPA leadership said
Okay that's great but we need to burp the baby
If we're going to take
Pandemics off the table
Nets
Why I'm here
We need to be able to
Put this together
As a platform
That can go start
To finish
From Once Upon A pigeon is identified to making thousands of doses
Of this
Miraculous
Antibody-based antibody-based treatment
Incredibly short
Period of time
Right and let's let's talk about the time scale for a minute cuz that's part of the
Did the big deal here right
What I've seen is
Within 60 days of identifying the the pathogenic agent actually have these doses right in hand
I'm in a distributable for MS
That's correct
Rain-X wipers to what
Is it to what's the state of
The state-of-the-art today depends on infect
But let's use some some reason example
We currently have some zika vaccines in clinical trials but
We've been working now for a few years
And we don't have a license
Steak and Shake
You think about our Reese when we talked about gaps you think about all of these recent out
And one of the fundamental Essence is that we haven't had vaccines and treatments that are ready in time
And
We came up
That the 60-day
Golf
Has been controversial
When we talk about audacity
You know I have
Professional colleagues laugh at me I've been on panels
We're right here discuss the program
And the other panelists joined with the audience at laughing at me
So I knew we were in the right space
The counter-argument that I continually make to the critics is
60 days is dictated by what we need
To respond to pandemic
So if you don't agree that our approach has the right way
Then come up with an alternative
Because we can't negotiate with Mother Nature and say what would like another 6 months if
If you don't mind
Especially when you think about the catastrophic consequences
Accordingly
So
We have to be
We have to do this with
And I think again
Profoundly excited cuz I think we found a way to do it
I want to try to make this concrete for a listeners
What you've actually done fairly well just now what I thought of another way we met
I do this
By combining
You know kind of almost at the the
Gaming out to the Future where let's say you are success
And may you be successful with this P3 program
Pandemic
Prevention plan
Program
Let's say that you had that P3
Ability
Back in the 1918 Spanish
I've seen different numbers of
50 million
Pandemic
If this technology existed back
In the early part of the
Last century
How would that unhappy
Have unfolded
Well my hope
Is that
50 million people down.
That
Leanne Again part of this is
Can you detect that we have a new virus
RI new version
Of influenza
And we detect very early on in the process when it's first starting out in a given country
I'm satisfied that it's happening
We flipped the switch
And we say
For that new virus
We need 20000 doses
That have to be ready within six
And then we go to win that outbreak
His first start
Wade NFI who's sick
We treat those people
I'm that are most likely to be contagious
And we stop the outbreak
Strack's
If we added we could have stopped the Spanish Flu
I think even more important
Right now today you and I both know
People who are getting very sick with influenza we're seeing a severe season
And we're seeing unfortunately children.
We're seeing unfortunately
Otherwise completely healthy people having dianping Hospital
Influenza does that to us every year
We imagine a world where this platform
Could be used
To take seasonal influenza
Write an amazing thought because
I mean this gets back to
Several times
You said what a privilege
It is
To do what you're doing because
Succeed
You will know and I know you won't take this
Pumping you up personally
It's more for what it do
You know
Kind of humanity
But you will know you've had a pardon
Potentially saving
People's lives
By cutting leaves
A pandemic
Experiences
Does off
I'll before they really get going and spread so
Really quite an amazing event and I would make two points the first is that
DARPA
My my put my team does not do this alone
DARPA does not do this
We work incredibly closely
With our colleagues in Health and Human Services with other experts in the department of
Defense in the US government
As well as philanthropy as well as
The private sector
And as well as the global community
Is It ultimately a global teamwork
That's going to take these infectious disease
Off the table but make no mistake we can say
It sounds hard and it's ambitious and it's crazy
But I challenge you to say why not
Need a white why aren't we as a society putting incredible
Even more effort
Into taking these infection
Tri-Cities is off the table if we have the if we have the scientific know how to
This is what I think we should be
It's a moonshot
But why not go friendly
And why not go for a moon shot for
Again something that could
Kill another 50 million
Why not take a moon shot against
Infectious diseases like malaria and tuberculosis I mean we've seen
You know there's there's effort in there there's Global effort that's absolutely tremendous
Why not more
Samantha just a little while ago you and I were kind of gushing about the molecular
Beauty in the biology
SHOW beauty of antibody
Specificities
To go out in
Find whatever
The hell threatening agent might be in
Kind of man
The role that plays in our own bodies
Fight against
Health compromise
Exposures
I guess I kind of want to ask you to do you have a favorite
Infectious disease in the sense that you admire
What the bacteria
Virus
Does is learn how to do over
The course of evolution
So
Lights are in a slightly different way
I think it's a
When we say we want to take infection
Diseases off the table
In some ways its it's ridiculous because
We're always going to have
Viruses and bacteria that are part of the natural world
And
We
And we've always seen them as the enemy or
Pathogens is the word that we use
One of the interesting ways to think about the problem though is that
Part of it is that they are a pathogen but part of it is how we respond
And
Modulating
How our own body response to pathogens
Is a major theme of what we're trying to do
With antibodies being one of many example
And so
You're one of the traditional attitudes of antibiotics has
Antibiotics that have been wonderful and certainly profoundly impactful
In terms of our society
As we were as we come along
But we've also discovered the unintended consequences of giving a broad-spectrum antibiotic
Concurring my
Antimicrobial resistance and
Things like that as well
So
The world that I imagine
Is that
There is I guess
Like you said before it appreciation of Passage
Depreciation of viruses and bacteria
Understanding
What they do and what they don't do
And
It's not always wiping them out but more about rendering them harmless or figuring out ways to cut it
Coexist
Is where I would like are thinking to go on the toy
It makes a lot of sense
Statistics about the number of mammalian cells in me and you and the number of bacterial cells
And there's for the world's most from just the numbers perspective way more bacteria than we are we are
But there most of the time this is
This is a symbiosis
This is a mutually beneficial relationship
And so
I did really we shouldn't always
I think about these
These microbes
Things to eat to
Consider the minute we shouldn't consider
That's right that's right and the other part is that we learn from them
It's its their evolution
That also kind of inspires us and so
It's a
That in some ways there are adversary but in some ways they're sort of that
But you know when the superhero novels and things like that this idea of the the the balance between the hero and
The villain in sort of that
Estranged relationship that often develops between the two end if you will meet mutual appreciation
Is that I think that's awesome pathogen
Tonight we're coming toward the end
Part-time hero
Just wondering if
Something that didn't come up
During our discussion that you think would be oven
To our listeners
You know your
Go hero
Scrubzah
Ridding us of
Some of some of the
The concerns we have
The pathogens
Yeah what are munchers at DARPA is this idea of
Inspiring inspiring creativity and new solutions to
And often times
We say by sort of
Recruiting in people who have not traditionally thought about our problems
To help us with the solution
And so you know I would love for the listeners of this podcast
To be more inspired
To address
Other problems in infectious
Diseases
What I mean by that is
I always say people like me have to leave investor in tires
Careers in our life work into this and we have deep knowledge
The subject
I love the thought of
People that have expertise in
Computer science
In
What we would say well maybe those fields aren't necessarily obviously related
How to
That's how we're going to solve
The infectious diseases problems of the 21st Century
And so when I speak on this it's almost part
One part recruiting
It's especially recruiting those that may not have all of the biases
Of the traditional experts in infectious
To come up with a creative solution
The solve it
So
That makes me think of a term that
Innovation
Ecosystem
Cuz you just mentioned
Whole bunch of discipline
Put in a maybe
When you first think about infections that you might not think some of the
Come together so it is there something about
You and being here at DARPA
That
Is conducive to show the shaking up that Innovation ecosystem in ways that
Maybe move for the goals that you have
DARPA enables me to do that
Because
Again they are our program announcements we say okay we set the requirements
Solve this problem
Make us a treatment in 60 days
We know that they can't do that alone and it takes a multidisciplinary team so
If if you want funding from dark but you're going to have
To work with
People you're going to have to recruit it we design it so that you will have to recruit in people that may not be the
Traditional Subs
But furthermore
Every time I get a chance to speak
And to talk about this problem
Like Imus podcast
You know again I see it as a work
Recruiting
As a recruiting tool
To inspire those
I'm to help us address these infectious diseases threats
Well what I'm realizing now
I do not want to prevent you for another minute from going out there and realizing your goal
Taking The lethality out
And we are out of time also so I just want to
Thank you this is been immensely fast made
I just want to thank you
For sharing
Ghost stories about
Got your life
As a medical professional and and how you're expressing your interests and goals here at DARPA
Well thank you very much
For allowing me to be part of
And thanks listeners
For sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again
For the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about Colonel Matt Hepburn
The program.
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
DARPA.
And four links that enable you to download this podcast
Go to the voices from DARPA page
Underpants