The internet
Palm of your hands
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War DARPA the defense
Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver of this technology
Welcome to voices from DARPA a window onto darpa's core of program manager
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Adam Russell
Program manager since 2015 in Darkness defense Sciences office
Sometimes referred to as
DARPA Starbucks
Because it's programs dive deeply into fundamental science
In search of New Foundations for never-before-seen technology
Adam stands out at DARPA partly because he is 6 feet 4 inches tall and carries a rugby players physique
But more importantly because he is an anthropologist and social scientist
That makes him a rare bird of the agency where the social sciences have not had a strong presence for decades
Adam earned his bachelor's degree in cultural anthropology from Duke University
And his doctor of Philosophy degree in social anthropology from Oxford University in England
Where he was also a Rhodes Scholar
Prior to joining DARPA he was a program manager at the intelligence Advanced research projects
Activity I arpa
A DARPA like organization under the office of the Director of National Intelligence
At DARPA
Adam Russell has been taking the agency into Uncharted territories with ambitious goals and include
Fundamentally recasting have social science is done
To the
The questions experiments data and conclusions of its practitioners
Are better more reliable more telling and predictive
Of The Human Experience
Never in the history of social science
One more thing
His new baby girl has been schooling him in ways
The institutions of Higher Learning have been unable to
Adam Russell
Thanks for joining me this video.
Don't think there are things around me
So let's start off by talking about how you became interested in science in general and more specifically in the social science
And even more particularly in cultural anthropology
My real exercise comes from my own experience
As a child I moved around a lot
My stepfather was in the Foreign Service
I was in different schools every year for about 5 or 6 years straight
Africa
Europe
And it just because
Mini cultural context with offenders in formal education
As you pointed out being the
Set a primary driver there
Realization quickly that 13 year olds are not the same ever
Toughen up being 30 year olds now move two entirely different culture
Expectations rules
Rules change
Well you start figuring out first ball
That the world does Andre differ
But that that is not an attractive
Boundary that you can actually understand what the world
In some cases
If your 13 and a new school you have to
Survival
In other cases it's really to Dalton with your benefits
Did you understand how
Sync work
In an organism cell
So even at the age of 13 you were we were observing cultural differences and
Evidently you brought that into your program when you got into college well right the social sciences
Swath of of disciplines
And I'm fairly as a
Is Regina.
But I wouldn't anthropology specifically I think because it was obvious
That anthropology allows you to come to be a practitioner of all trades
Caressa master of none
But you touched every facet
Of The Human Experience
So
You can't do as apology if you don't also understand something
About economics
Politics religion
Exchange symbolism
And what I was particularly focused on which was identity
The concept of identity
I think really is what distinguishes
Humans human social behavior from other natural
Physical sciences
Identity is a very rich and complex idea
I mean they're all kinds of identities that that we can assume I want you to talk a little bit about identity I know that
When you were at Oxford that your dissertation really focused on the subject
Right well so I was
Focus on what
I was described by thinking in some areas of crisis
And let me give you a little context
4/4 a
So we talked about Johnny English anthropology is well
Twokinds
A different husband
Physical anthropology
Wichita
My grandmother when she's asking for
What the hell are you doing over there
Food is apologies really the study like other Natural Sciences of the world that makes us
How Evolution has led to her
Species
Trades
Metaphysics that are that are play
Cultural ecology really study the world we make for ourselves
Into their we
Veer into the realm of collected fictions
Economies the organization
And as I said that genitti's that we have and share
Develop and just wait when you say collected fictions just to be clear because I think of
Of Economics for example as a real thing but when you said when you use the language
A collective fiction just
Explain that for a listener
Well it's the great term from Harare who wrote
Sapiens and I think he's right that our species competitive Advantage is our ability to sort of
Agree to believe in things at
Actually aren't real
But in the process I should make him real
Anacondas are just like
As you can see
Genesis the challenge
That we want to model sort of financial crises
The crashes as
Beobank certain fundamental physical law straps
What kind of top models from physics
The problem is
Is that by virtue of action modeling a phenomenon you can lead people to believe
That it could occur
So you actually created the phenomenon you were trying to stand the first
Show
That that
Fiction fiction doesn't mean it's not still impact or effect
Affecting the real
And we've all that way to do that because there is great power
We all believe in kind of this
Efficient
Do we can get along we can solve the coordination
Which is which is
Fundamental to complex societies
We also need two sources of complex
If my flight to fiction is differ from your class
We are we at work
Alright so let me steer you back though it took you away from
The crisis of identity which was again the focus of what you were studying as a graduate student at Oxford
Write this in the gym machines or the other world that makes us in the world we make for ourselves
Well he freaks me those words are blurry
All right we have increasing power over the physical natural world
Crises in which the world we made for ourselves no longer
Fits or explains or aligns with the natural world
Show all the categories that we use to classify the real world
Things like masculine
Tricia Nixon what makes a man
Well that doesn't actually works only in a world in which
Men are not making more money than women wear
Eventually that has been sore
A cultural stereotype
But when the fundamentals of the world being the shift
Identity sometimes
Whack
Behind have to catch up
That leads to crisis
Because
I'm in very real sense of human I am my identity
That's how I see my
Repurpose gives
Behavior
Chesak the crises really not to
How do we add Associates
Social behaviors and I
And identity
When the world is changing
And some people do it more successful than others and I use the term crisis
In this case not in the same way it's like a refugee crisis
I'm over there in Portuguese did not unrelated
When you see these
Disjoncteur you see the discrepancy between
A social identity and
In the world
Once explained in August please
Unfortunately you know what the nature of our species sometimes to respond violently to try to push the world back into the category that we
We think it should be in
Or that it wasn't where we know we understand things
Now we dumb
And that can be really disturbing for
Right and just think again to give listeners some sense of the
Kinds of identities
That
You are
Probably beginning to think about and and preps investigating a new ways to your programs here
There we have a sense of
Who we are as as individuals as
Individuals within different social context
We have gender identity we have belief proof
That we belong to
There are State identities are School identities their national identity some of us try to be worlds
Citizens and Southerners there's our Global identity
It rated me that's the kind of mix of things that you're talking about we're talking about identity in and Ivan it it took you all of that
10 seconds to identify why social sciences
Are up against such a hard problem
You just listed
All those things that are probably important Relic
For any particular social
Question
How do you factor all those things in how do you figure out what the most
Important to understand the Dynamics
And I Look to You know I'm a psychologist if people study
Animals
Where they live somewhere challenges in the complexity of sometimes it's like chimps
Gemporia station beer
But to date no one has had to deal with
As far as we know Mars is chimpanzee
Gypsy junk in cells develop new social identity
And have those identities
Be more less router under different conditions
Well you just give me an excuse to ask you a question, based on some prior discussions we've had things I've heard you say witches
That social science is harder than say physics
Which I love the idea and I think you've got a good
Argument which is
Well 80
It's not my arm
Wright's out Nobel prize-winning physicist Murray gell-mann in 5 min
Richmond Inn in Murray
But he's mine
How much harder physics would be if electrons could think and had feelings
Summarizes nicely I think
Open question
That I'm actually trying to tackle here at
Through couple programs potentially more and ideally with
It was support for
A future part of managers interest in this area and we will get to those in particular later
You know you can tell the difference between the billions of dollars
Time invested in physics
And the probably Millions if not billions of hours of intellectual labor compared to weapon of essence social
Are we at the stage where we just need better tools
Do understand these things like identities that done amateur play
Or we about to discover that wow this is really a dick
This is the stuff I sort of
Standard scientific approach
We need to think about this in new ways
Is because
There are these are wicked problems waiting for
One of which is
You change the very system you're studying
I'm so so that's an open question but I do think right now
I would I would say is harder
The weather that's always the case with it's a function of we just haven't
The tools whether it's a function the subject matter itself
I think it is like I said no one question and one that
I think really we need to understand from
Even a National City
Right well and one of the things DARPA
It is charged with doing is not only
Doing R&D that that's sort of
Specify begins to determine what is
Possible
But also to get a handle on what are fundamental constraints and limitations so
And that's actually an exciting kind of space of uncertainty to be in
We're going to move into into a sort of a DARPA segments here in a second but
But before we move away from your
Schooling in your
Time-It Oxford I just want to ask you about your your rugby career in your rugby experience because I think in some ways
Your experience in that social and cultural context
Has informed
Some of the questions that you asking and the way you go about thinking about cultural anthropology and now
In
The kind of DARPA
National Security contact so talk to me about you know rugby and how informed why you think now
Interesting I probably haven't reflected enough upon that
Did they give you an intelligent answer
That's right that's right
There's a selection bias problem perhaps in that did I choose rob you to drive you choose me
I'm not a natural athlete by any means but I
For some reason to
Cookwell for sport and I think part of it is
Because it is such an inherently social
It really is a team Orange
40 degrees
Level up
Goagent
Required in teamwork
Is room for everybody in rugby
Seems to be
Chili good at building character
I'm in
Scar tissue
But but but I character part I think is tested on a regular basis both
Against other teams but also even with your own.
I became really interested in the imponderable
As I
Describe these things like cohesion and teamwork
Leaving frankly Beyond identity commitment
These things are clearly important that clearly impact
The real world
Even in areas where we have Simple Rules like rugby
Humble that are really hard to measure
And
And remain at this point almost kind of like a match
And we look to the best coaches
Greybull to sell some of this magic and produce
My performances from teams that really help a person I've gotten there
And likewise
Dysfunctional Dynamics
Where you to have the best Superstars and they just don't seem to
Perform
That's where his remains like I said kind of this
Imponderable
The area of
Mystics and tradecraft in
In a wisdom of the ages
What is your science
Imats
That that's why I let you know I really is a long time studying the rugby team itself
I'm and I'm
Given particular date in dod you know we we we
We fight and we work
Live or die in teams
Exact actual price of an excellent
Target
Our focus on which two
Did go after these in pond
Fasting to just
Think about you what is it what is that magic is you call which maybe is something discernible and something that you want kids
That will take a group of individuals a team
And have this team achieve collectively
Human Feats that are often absolutely astounding so
I don't want to talk too much about that now but it just said that you kind of Cadillac that thought will
It's an ectopic this is an example where I think
Social science
Falls down
Because there's a lot of literature on team
But I guess you woke in the literature
Deathly reflects Duncan Watts
Sociologist
Incoherent
That the way people study teams
Varies tremendously the measures that use vary tremendously the results
Oftentimes not
Highly reliable
There's no replication of the studies
Actually this is part of my frustrations when you turned it to where
Presumably they would have the answer
Is it magic resist
There's very little
That can be drawn confer
From the literature
What's a i
God forbid given the opportunity to be organized a large group to achieve something important
What can I draw from the social science literature
It helped me
There's not a lot
Right now that I would consider be reliable or bus enough
Really help me dry Ford
Does it have to be that way or their way so we can improve
The research itself so that I
As Commander at leader
Even / Commander
Know how better to put my team together
To really get
The other most
Out of out of
We're trying to do okay well I can tell that you're hinting about something that will talk about you just didn't in the very near future but I want to move
Move our two men scrum here toward DARPA
How did you actually
What was the sequence of events where you met somebody to talk to somebody scene
There's always
How did I get my job story soap
Well I'm so don't you drive me to the rugby choose me did I choose. About to drop it to me
I can say, in this case DARPA and chooses you
So I was
Fortunoff I think
Tube having been in
As you mentioned
I've been moving in the circle of
We are program managers and this Advanced research area for
National Security
And I think
Getting to know some folks who have done work both it was in DARPA and for DARPA
It's hard not to swear to be effective
To realize that
They really do want to walk
They're willing to take these chances
Risk Investments
That another
The areas might be
Be considered
You know given what I said earlier about you know the difference between the amount of money and time spent on face
Social science
If there's agency that can actually
Make-out we've been three five years over the 20 years we might need a normally
How you know doctor did nothing
Well how do you how do you not say that
So have you made a couple of connections with
Within the building and then also have been called in by some leadership I think really understood
That
But he's a really important question
Coordination cooperation competition ultimately
Every national security question
We really care about
Has some fundamental human
Social and behavioral aspects to it
But
UFC referees my order comments about the state of the literature and they sent to which you can really inform
Are solutions this problem
They realize I think and I
Things might be changing
Culturally with a new emphasis on reproducibility
And transparency in the science
Ultimately I hope
Improve the quality of
Kelso 10
So technologically we now have capabilities to
You run experiments scales whenever
We have the ability to analyze
New complex weight
We have the ability to
Pre-register stop
That is where I announce my study publicly
Joe Alves
Almost community peer-review
So we're reinvesting Andre investigating
Regular does conventional models
DARPA leadership realize okay maybe now is the time
To take that risk Estep and see if
Bring that science
Okay perfect time then just to just just
Talk a little bit about each of your program
What's what start with the first program that you managed to
Get through the difficult wedding and approval process your
Referring to the Next Generation social sciences program which
Is pretty transparent about what you're trying to do with 2nd generation
Next Generation
Social site transparent in just
The most surface sort of way so what do you actually mean by that
Right so we're trying to accomplish two
I would say probably insanely ambitious
But that's that's what we do here
The first is were trying to get after
Experimental
Those imponderables as emergent phenomena we were referring to Earl
The things like
Quite the vagina
How does the me
Yoga by the other selves to the me becomes the
What's most important
For that serve emergent Behavior
Well
We know we have lots of case studies with lots of people who serve observe this in the world
But we don't have his experimental evidence to begin to test
These different mechanism
So we're trying to Leverage
What we think are advances now technology
Detectorpro out that experimental
In the process and this is the second bowl
We're trying to do it so that we can have greater confidence in the reproducibility of the war
All the way from
Testing multiple models
Rather than being married to a single model that I will then try to prove is true I'm actually
Actually trying to figure out which models are
More effective than others
And again these would be models about what
About Industries Collective identity
So there's lots of literature about what leaves
I made a bunch of the week
Will they all make
In many cases they make very different predictions
Under similar conditions
If you can actually get the models
That's another
His many social science model
Apples are so
That is almost impossible to say what they would predict but
Prediction predictability is a Hallmark of what we might consider going to the hard Sciences
You come up with the theory and if you can predict when Halley's Comet is going to come back around then you say hey I
I've made it
I'm approaching
I think that's true and I and I and I think there's another side that witches if you make prediction in your wrong at least you know that how wrong
When you are and that's how you make
Improvements
But you never make that prediction or you engage in a practice
Parking
Which is a hypothesizing after the results are known in this is very common if you if you
Collect your data and you analyze them and nobody ever knows what
Question was you rash in the first place
I can always go back
And claimed I was looking for the answer I found the first
Republic
And then rationally reconstruct a plausible story that makes sense of what you think
An n in social science in particular
It's hard to come up with a scenario in which no matter what answer you find you can't come up
With a post-hoc story that makes sense
No matter what I find in any experiment in social science the most part
I can go back in time and tell a plausible story is that well why that's obvious
That is a real problem
Okay so if we get utopian for a minute and you succeed wildly
In this insane Ambitions of actually coming up with next-generation social science
What will social science
Will be reminded again
Social sciences Awards live brush but if we
Extrapolate from what word
The question we're asking right now.
Extended to other questions
Things like
Deterrence and cooperation
Competition
The process to me would look very similar
Which is
People will be mining the literature that already exists
To come up with different models
That make predictions
Not just sort of qualitative descriptions of how the woman
Where's my predictions
But then can be
Tested empirically
In experiments
1/10 scale if necessary
That are transparent
Better
Queer
That are pre-registered
And that also
Are replicated
So the replication process is really important
Especially with you social systems because the answer you get the next time around won't be the same the world that will have changed
The participants will change the behavior will change
But if you don't do that your process if you don't replicate you won't know
When your model begins to fail when it doesn't
And incentives right now
Frankly in many ways are just to get published
As opposed to getting a ride
We are trying to figure out how to close those inside
So that
Getting it right Altima is what gets you pumped
So you are running another program that really sounds relevant to what you're talking about right now the ground truth
Program and the name of that really fascinates me because
The first time I ran
Across that term
I actually was related to satellite remote-sensing of
The snowpack in need what would happen if there's natural herb status briefly the Earth emits snatcher microwave
Radiation it goes through
Snowpack this is the signals can be picked up by sensors on satellites
And then with a model
The satellite then can
Convert those raw signals into
Some measure of exactly what the snowpack is and that's important information for
Example farmers who are going to need to know how much snow is going to be coming up nearby mountains
Toast but input in order to be confident about the model
People would go on the ground in their snow boots with
Long rulers and actually measure the depth
I'm in and that way
Could you validate that the models were
We're working well so in this context ground-truth and in in social science
Well
So this is a question I think you can only ask you to place a DARPA
So we will
We do not have
That kind of grouchy
In
Partly because
The very measures we take from the very beginning of making assumptions
That were measuring
We can't see the things we really care about so we have to use it
Inside of Hope
That were caption constructs
At the end of the day
We actually have very little idea how Acura
We are crew
In this question fundamental imitation
Accurate we actually alter webe
When faced with these complex
Systems
My social behavior
DARPA
Has given me the chance to serve in Port that question will be
And say okay
We have these amazing advances in Social stimuli
How to give you have you talked to John about
Upper GI Joe is very interested in this
There's enormous advances agent-based modeling that allow you to
Run lots of little agents and see how they interact
The Crazies
Emergent and very complex behaviors from fairly simple rules and by agents you mean
He could be people doing things people doing things in this case
Lil Wayne Avatar that I have
Rules
Those avatars in a rack of my computer
I am because my computer now holds his enormous amount of computational power
I can really start scaling this up I can start
Simulating behaviors on
On the scale and some cases of of Nations and International
Interactions
Right now our approaches we use a simulation to try to understand the real one
We are asked the question well
What if we put that on hold for a moment
And I using simulations instead as a wind tunnel
Right almost that ice pack
So that I have causal truth
Or ground
You know I grew this
Alternate world
Which I'm seeing
Social behavior
What is so complex
Now I give that as a wind tunnel
Social science
Social scientist and other
Other areas so researchers
And ask them can you give me
Using your meth is your best approaches can you tell me what causing the behavior
Can you predict what's going to happen in this simulation when something happens like a resource dries up
And can you also may help us understand what are the
The framers
Their most important in the behaviors
How close can you actually get
What happened
Mentos is a couple
1 which tools are most appropriate for which kind of socially complex
Questions
To what
What if any are there theoretical limitations of being able to understand and predict
And that's really important
Hey you people talk about what why do you want to know what you can
Well am I spring certainly within National Security
Dude in particular very comfortable with risk they have to make decisions
Under incomplete information
Why do you want to figure out what you can't know how is that useful
Well
That gives you the boundary
Of
What you can plan for
And if you know for
I see both
4 facts that you can't know something
If you can plan for that too
It's a much different planning price
But that's really important
And again at DMV in particular constantly has to operate in
Highly uncertain environment
But being able to say
Yes sir or mam
This is a dynamic this is a situation that we cannot predict what's going to happen next
You can plan accordingly
That's very different from
Believing you know what's going to happen
Being inaccurate
But being very confident and that leads to bad
You can't bear it Universe any idea to kind of be a World creator where you can control that world
Throwing in a very certain situations how does social behavior unfold in the simulated environment and hopeful
We learn something that you can take out of the box the computer box in the NFL plaid to the test for the real world that we live in
Breathin
I want to just talk about one more program is actually not a program it's it is a preliminary phase of what could become a program
I would show you sent out is what we call insert government speak a request
For information and that is an RFI about
About this particular request for information I was looking at the possibility
Of using semi-automated
Rules to give us
Calibrate the confidence we can have
In the social Behavioral Science research that already exists
How we can do social science going into
Ground rules that program is for looking at how how effective we can actually be
Even if we're wild lyrics
And in developing
This our request information
Is an analogy that there's tremendous amount of literature and research has been done I'm questions that you know DOD National Security care
We just don't know how much confidence we should have
In some of those claims and models
And that's best exemplified by the recent reproducibility project
I was a different
Research
Scientists Center for open science has the most
Famous
Before that where they actually took
Canonical studies in Psychology the replicated
And they did not all rap
In fact more often. They did not Rebel
And it's
Yeah there's lots of renting of clothes and gnashing of teeth that have this happen
Well part of it is working the great name for this to write for the crisis of reproducibility
Now it is and it's not just by the way social sign
Right
But part of it while part of it is because the science is hard part is also stems from
These these requests will research Praxis
That are invited by
Import centers
Some cases just
Enormous degrees of freedom that is if I'm given a large dataset there many things I can do with those data
And if I'm
Only going to publish positive results don't be surprised when I only tell you about the positive result
This is our natural human reaction it's not that people are malicious or nest
Play faking data
This is just a result of housing Centerline
And yet much of the research is solid
Right mid there many things
You can soar Bank on if you're building a model about humans
Behavioral Services
We just don't know how to disentangle them
Answer the question of race is asking are there new ways of putting together Pratt weak signal
Inherent to a study or article me the stats are off a little bit
The perfect
Has the study been replica
Has been tested on more than one population
You know has anyone I should bother to reproduce the results
And then I think increasingly there these other signals that we haven't
Historically been able to
Things like discussions and social media
Social media in some cases actually an open peer review process
You will get some more controversial Studies have come out reason
I think you know the discussions have occurred
Informative
Yes I'm that is is ad hominem attacks
Subjective discussion about the tapping into the wisdom of the crowd absolutely
The hard part is
You know the crowd is very busy
How do we
Better Weber
Those that do signals
How to make them
So that if if it is successful
I see two outcomes one is
I can more more easily more rapidly more confidently
Where is the normal filter for the story out there
Second is frankly crate almost kind of a road map
So that if I'm a young researcher or I'm a program manager
Funny research
I can look at
Des algorithm
Or this credits
For lack of a better term
And I know how I can improve confidence in my research
I can look at the things that matter for increasing confidence
And I can
I can do the right thing
I can replicate my stuff
I can make my data available
Independent party
I can test it on multiple
You know I can't I can be transparent about my analyses
Where they working where they didn't etcetera
Gauging you in this conversation it also is occurring to me there's another reason why
Bringing social science into the DARPA portfolio was so important it's just it's because of the way the vulnerability landscape
The risk and threat landscape has been changing its so much
There's so many more
Kinds of risks that are inherently in that social
Behavior and cultural Behavior space I'm just thinking about the wild wild place of the internet and how
Identities are made and created
And manipulated in in that
Global environment so
Maybe just before we close out
Talk to me a little bit about that in with respect to the kinds of efforts you're making your
It doesn't take long to talk to any driver
Peugeot manager
They begin to
Bringing this discussion you did
Of the social complexity no matter what platform
No matter what technology
Software developer
You pull that string a little bit and it leads quickly to
This
Threat landscape as you said
That's right landscape sometimes it's
Just not even understand
What should I think
This is Mario
Frankly we have to go
To be in to get a better sense of those questions
Erased
I think
You know we should be excited
About our new capability
We can use
To try to get there
We should remain humble
As weak as you go forward though
Daddy Riggins are magic rotation
But I but I do think
But if I do nothing other
With my time at DARPA
The idea that we can use these tools
Did the re-engage and try to get after that social complexity
That it has something
Contribute to National
Security that will have been a win for my respect
Okay well may we come to know ourselves better Adam Wright
And with that I just want to thank you for spending this time with me in the studio
No thank you I appreciate it
And I want to thank you listeners also for spending the time with us
I hope you join us again for the next voices from DARPA
For more information about Adam Russell
The programs he runs
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mil
And four links that enable you to download this podcast
Go to the voices from DARPA page
Uncharted website