Dell Technologies the internet CPS in the palm of your hand
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 19
58th in the Mist
The Cold War
DARPA the defense Advanced research projects agency
Has Bennett Drive
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window Into Darkness
Tour of program managers
Their job
To redefine
My name is Ivan Amato
DARPA hosts
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Mr. David Gunner
Since late 2015 has been a missed his third
Tour of Duty
The other program man
In this case with the information
Innovation
During his previous tour in the early years of the new millennium
David manager
The personalized assistant that learns
How
That led to the now-familiar voice of Siri
Through his first tour in the 1990s he managed a variety of AI
Projects artificial intelligence
Including the command post of the
The future
Which was later adopted by the US Army
As their command-and-control system
M4u cyttorak
Between his stints at the
Mr. going to play the variety professional roles
Among them
Program director for data analytics and contextual in
Intelligence
The Palo Alto Research Center Parc
A number of founding and managerial roles for
Fortec companies
And as a senior scientist in the Air Force research
Wright-Patterson
The thematic thread throughout his career
Have been artificial intelligence in human
Computer symbiosis
It's a thread that goes back to his education
David Holt
A pair of Master
1 in computer science from Stanford
And another in experimental psychology
From the University of
David gunning thanks for joining me in the studio today
Yes glad to do it
So like many here at DARPA
You work
At the intersection of different mindsets skill sets
Tool sets
In your case the intersection seem to focus on
Humankind computer kind in the ways these two creatures
I can work together
Where does Interest come from
Go back as far as you can
Well I can go back to the
Originating event that started dark
Sputnik in 1958
I was 8 years old
Living at my grandfather's house out in the country
And I can remember him taking me out in the yard at night
To see the light of Sputnik as it's flying overhead
You're kind of conveying what a shock this week
Where were you
Complete the setting
And Covington Kentucky outside
Covington Kentucky
And so that at the time
Also not only spark DARPA but sparked a huge interest in technology
My there's a huge interest in encouraging
Young minds to be interested in engineering and science
Remember that is kind of a
Ark
Started it
Later on I was in Otterbein College in Ohio in the
Late 60s early 70s
You know during this kind of Rapid change and a lot of cultural chain going on
I became very interested in psychology
So that was my first
Technical interest just how did people
Right people are clearly the issue and most of the problems we have today and
How does that mind work and what could we do about
Eliquis
Starting pay
And then I
Did that went through got a master's degree in Psychology started work
At Wright-Patterson Air Force Base as a human factors engineer which was one of the practical uses of that
Psychology degree I had
And then very quickly the first jobs I had were too
Look at the human factors of how they were introducing electronic displays into the cockpit
Does a 19 late 1970
Kind of one of the first
Are workplaces to be automated if you would
Pilots were getting the most advanced technology
They're putting electronic displays in the place of
Instruments
Pilots for making sub microsecond decision life-or-death decisions
You want to make sure they get just the right information in just the right way
You know to make those to say
And so that triggered my interest in computer science
Because quickly became apparent that all the important aspects of this job were in computer soft
And so that
Prompted my interest in computer science then went back to school to Stanford to get my master's degree in computer
Are science and especially in AI
That was one of ai's Summers if you will
There's a hole in the 1980s
A lot of interest in expert systems in one of the first waves of AI
And so that captured my interest and certainly was aligned with my background in cognitive psychology
David as I noted in my introduction you're now in your
Third tour
The program manager
DARPA
The death of the later we'll talk about the programs you
Who inherited in this latest
Communicating with computers
And the program that you initiated the explaining a guy but before we get to
I'd like for you to take us on a brief tour of your prior to
What time does the program
So let's start
With how you and DARPA met for the very first time
As a p.m. I guess this was a 19-9
Mission systems
What is the said as they started off as a psychologist then switch the computer science
In both those roles I was a researcher at the Air Force research Labs at Wright-Patterson
So doing a lot of work at
The time on the F-22 that was the latest
Fighter aircraft of the day
Now those computer displays that started
You know in the 1970s were very Advanced and in particular then I was working on a integrated
Information maintenance system
So now it was possible for the maintenance technician to walk up to a computer
Walk up to the aircraft with a portable computer
Plug it in
Download information about what failures had occurred
Get all of his tech manual instructions presented on the computer
Create kind of an integrated
You know workplace for the maintenance technician to help him do his job the question about that because
You know when you go in
Any garage tent have your own car looked
Dad
There is a system very much like that
Yes it's about this procedure this procedure that it was actually the very first prototype of electronic
Maintenance instructions anywhere
The services
I did that
Did that time on my program
And so I was doing that work that got the attention of the general who is running the F-22 program
He pulled me into the F-22 the kind of man age in coordinate of the development of all of his digital
Ecology
And while I was there some people from DARPA came to visit the try to convince the skeptic
General
Oh that they should listen to DARPA and adopt some of their new technology
So he expressed how skeptical he wasn't
Pretty graphic way and said
If you're going to do something on the F-22 you need to convince Dave
He's my guide
Computers that was with the Steve cross who is deputy director of one of the offices
Gio wiederhold
Who is a program manager here on loan from Stanford University who is doing a project in IntelliJ
Integration of data set
Using a
And so I began to interact with those guys and when go left
DARPA after his tour was done
Then they invited me to come to DARPA to be a p.m. in 1994
I just I find an interaction you mentioned
The general quite interesting because it reflects a conservatism
That
The services
Is have because they want to work with tried-and-true systems and it's a
A bit scary
Bring a new techno
Knology which does not have as much
Track record but then you were there
As someone really a champion of the new
Yes a champion of the new in a very conservative environment it's not that there
Technology adverse these people are very serious Engineers are building this aircraft
With enormous life and death
You know consequences if it's done incorrectly
So they don't want to put anything in that airplane
Right unless they really know
But they can depend on
Give me a really solid understanding in background of where those people are coming from when you're trying to introduce new
Technology
Doing what you need to do to convince them
One thing that I noticed regarding your this first
Tour of Duty is that not only did you come here
You went full Mind and Body in
If I'm reading your
Background correctly
You were
Over c9pro
Released in your period of 6 years in that
Torrent they were 9
Find programs on your
Yeah that's right I was starting
One or two new programs a year inherited a few
You know from other PMS but I was all-in
I was a lot younger then had a lot more energy and
But just love the job
She mention I've been through three times
Cuz to me it's one of the most fascinating jobs you can have
Pinnacle of new technology development
You have such a broad view of what's going on
And DARPA gives you this incredible freedom to pursue what you see is you know what division ennui
Where things should go
That one of the standouts
From the
First work is known as command post of the
The future
And that one actually did get out into
To the field so just briefly can you tell us a little bit about what the
Goal of that program wasn't and infect how
Howitzer
It unfolded
And of course my interest has been an AI all along and most of those nine programs I ran my first tour had
Had to do with knowledge and reasoning
Planning
Trying to provide intelligent decision AIDS
Two people so we created command post of the future
You know as a way to see if we could
Explorer
All sorts of AI technology
See what worked
Package that up into a system that Army Commanders
Could use out in the field so we started that with a wide variety of Technologies of varying
Degrees of maturity and risk and by time we got to the end of the program
And I have left are but by then and there was
Other people have taken over
But the technology that survived was something that was
Might call adaptive or intelligent visualization
A lot of the more higher-risk AI techniques that actually kind of falling out this
Too immature
Bright
But they had through a lot of iteration with some Visionary people from the
Army Marine Corps Air Force
And really kind of picked out the Nuggets of new technology
They were incredibly value
Basically was that if a commander and his staff could each have their own view of the battlefield
In their command post the future screen
So the operator saw the plans for the attack
The logistics guy then so what did he have to do to support the
Write the Intel guy just got to see
What information was coming in on what the enemy would do neck
In one of the commanders Army General Corelli who is the one who
Champion didn't took it to Baghdad
Ashley said that by watching his staff's
Command post of the future screens
He had a better idea of what they were thinking
Then he did if they were all in the same room talking to
So would enable them to one be distributed which is very important
Four the battle for
The two gave him better insight into what his staff was thinking
And where the bad how the battle
Was emerging
Fasting
This event is a case where the
Human machine interaction
Something into something more than the
Yes and parley critical part of that programs the way we set it up
Was the have is constant iteration
Between the technologist
And the Visionary users
Right which is your Now call Dad Jewel
Development there's a lot of
Names that has pretty much been adopted by Silicon Valley as a religion
But that strategy was pretty early in those days
And they had a lot of exercises where they
Play take the
Researchers from the University
Send them down to Fort Polk in the Army and actually put on the army gear and run them to exercise
Realsense for what
The problem was
But they also had exercises where the Visionary military guys would work closely with the technologist
To try to sort out what was the most valuable thing the technology could do
For user in the field
And not just let the technologist kind of
Hypothesize what that might be
With a somewhat naive idea
But what's needed
Some 2,000 you leave. But you go and do other things
And in 2003 though
You come back
And this time you're in the information
Processing
Office
Tell us a little bit about
The programs that you
Ram there including one that I think many
Listeners
We came back as they say
Tony tether just come in as the new director
Ron Brockman as the office Chiefs of this newly-formed office if
And It Go was also the name of one of the original dark offices led by lickliter
Is really where the personal computer was created where a whole idea of
If those days are computer metal large Ivy and run frame just for listeners
Lickliter is a
Giant in the history of Dart but he's known as
Usually is jcr licklider actually stands
Joseph Carl robnett
Lickliter
And he really brought in an ethic of
This idea that the human machine interaction in a symbiosis
This was going to be a long long theme of
LG from then in the sixties when he
Until now
So David your View continuing the age of exactly I did before he came in
Did what a computer meant was an IBM Mainframe that took up the size of a small room
And people would interact with it by
Sending Punch Cards into a punch card reader
And getting an answer back on the other side
There was no concept of this being a personal computer you'd sit down with and interact with on a daily basis
It was actually under his program is Alan Kay
Who is that that Stanford at the time in later Park
Sketched out the first
Diagrams of what we recognize today is the person
Brighton park being Palo Alto Research Center
Exactly
And Tony Rich so that was zip to ISO
Tony Taylor and Ron Brockman they really wanted to bring that back
They wanted
To re-energize DARPA to go after the Next Generation
Human-computer symbiosis
And the phrase then was cognitive system
Cognitive technology
And so Tony believed investing big in this
And so we came up with the idea for this program called pal
Personalized assistant that learns
Which even by DARPA standards was a fairly large program 250 million dollars over 5 years
And it had multiple levels
One level that funded
20 some research universities and agencies around the country
To explore a lot of cutting-edge technology in AI
In particular machine learning
Machine learning is now commonplace today
Was just kind of emerging technology in those days
So it funded a huge amount of basic research on machine learning
Let me just stop you for a second
Listening to me
Not really know what that means
We can't go into a full
How would you define that
Willne earlier days of AI we tried to develop intelligent systems by having people
Program rules
Soar statements into a system
That would tell it what the knowledge was unleaded then reason why
An expert system with electric systems knowledge bases
TurboTax
Text today is kind of a current Incarnation shuttling program
Exactly
Those ended up being very difficult very difficult to program very difficult to maintain it's very difficult for people to
But actually specify
Exactly the logic rules
They're behind intelligence
But over those decades and especially during this pal program began to realize that if you fed a computer Lotto
Data
In turned it Loose with the right machine learning algorithms which were
We're kind of learning
The statistics and probabilistic
Nature of the data
And learning different recognition patterns
The computer could learn its own patterns
They're not specified by a person
But those patterns were much more effective at doing a lot of jobs
Stand like understanding speech or recognizing images are
You know
Finding credit card fraud
Xcetera
Answer machine learning was much more effective than the older style
Explicit
Logic rules
So in a sense with the computer was doing is taking those
Assertive
Analog signal
That we humans are coming
Looking them now in there
Beta version
Right and that's what they're comfort
Yes
Exactly
And so that was a big component of the program
We also did a lot of work on man-machine dialogue
Gone
You know how do you carry on an intelligent dialogue with the computer the speech understanding to some extent was already being
How would you have a computer that could be an intelligent assistant
It would watch what the user is doing
Understand his job
Then be able to give him assistants at the right time
And one of the
Metaphors we used as you want to do create an assistant that was like Sergeant O'Reilly on the old TV show
Show MASH
For those of you old enough to remember
O'Reilly always knew what the kernel needed before the kernel
Need new himself
Right so we just
Followed the context of what the user was doing could anticipate
And provide
Intelligent advice
So that was the Grand Vision and we funded a lot of it very Advanced research and all of those areas
And in one of our performers was the
SRA International out in Menlo Park California
They were one of the integrators of this they
They are looked at all the research was being developed
Tried to create a prototype
Of this pal system that would could actually be used as an intelligent assistant on your laptop
So that they were looking at
Many of the
Component technologies that the other performers were were developing in C
See how can we put this
Exactly and I was really their job was how do we integrate the best of all these techniques and put
Bad together in night
Real prototype of a condom
And so they as long as they were doing that began to develop a
Kind of streamline more efficient version of that Arkansas
And when the power program the research version the power program ended around
They had several people who'd worked on Powell and some
New performers they brought informed Adventure called Siri
And they decided they were going to take this technology
Adapted
For the iPhone which was a brand new product
And people didn't know quite what to do with it
Azarai was very wisely said
This is the place for a cognitivist
People going to have this phone they won't have a
Keyboard
They're really going to need an assistant that can help them out
So they had this Venture and for two years it was just funded as a new startup
DARPA then was out of the picture
They got Venture money from Silicon Valley to develop this
And in two years later they put their first Siri application on the App Store
Napster was brand new
And I think it was three days later they got a call from Steve Jobs himself
Who said it first they're like washer this is.
Try to just cause I didn't want random phones
You know in the office after they
Began to believe it really was Steve Jobs
He asked the three founders he said why don't you come over to my house tonight for dinner I've got a
Vision for what I want to do with
And then there was some negotiation / selling
The company
Apple bought it
It's been several years developing it into the Sirius system
Aquino today
And for the first year of that Steve Jobs was personally involved in directing
He had really seen that
As a vision for he wanted to go but then got too well
Okay so before we move on now to your
Current
What you described she was sort of the archetypal technology development cycle
At DARPA when it's about a sex successful at the
Yet which is to say
Yeah you and others here in your
Your performers those who work
Under contract on your program
They brought a technology to a point of proteus
And
Then taking the risk
Down enough that say other corporate entities or
With the military services
Can take a handoff
And do the final development until we
Product eggnog
Turn off the dark
What goes up to that point of
The product
Prototype
Out with proof
The principal hears a case where
All of this works
But you did led to something that now is part of
The Techno scape
Of the world
So the question I have for you is just what does that
Feel like I'm here you are you you here Siri all over the place and you know that you had
A role in the sequence
That led to it
So
What feels great
It was quite a surprise in a way right as you save this
That's darpa's job we're always doing this advanced technology
We're always trying to reduce the risk
You know and we knew a personal assistant
Headband
That's been a part of the AI science fiction
Sense
2001 and Star Trek in
That's always at like why certainly will be able to interact talk to her computer someday
But it never quite worked but I don't never know how l9ng vanilla
We want the pod bay doors
But the idea of a computer that was intelligent enough to carry on a conversation being assistant had been around for
But never implemented
When people tried it didn't work well enough
There's always a little bit too kludgy
And I think that that pal program really brought it to the point that Steve Jobs was willing to take a risk and say yeah I can make
Make a real Prada
And I can say I left Tarpon 2008
It's two years later that this comes out
And renewed Apple had bought it but had no idea what they were going to do
And then suddenly it's Apple's marketing department is advertising
The product of my
I program
And that was very nice
Like my children even
Momentarily
The greatest achievement of all right
So let's then move now to your current
Here in 2015 that you left in 2018 you want to wait either.
Other things in
Industry and you came back in 2015 so again
Tell me that that approach how it is that you were convinced to come back
We'll talk about your
To program
Well one is I said I didn't just being a darpa's the best job I've ever had
Wright's interesting to go out and Industry its industry to be in other places
But if you enjoy technology and you really want to make an impact there's nothing like
Like being a dark
I was going to head been out for a while in a variety of jobs and Industry I was
Kind of ready to looking for something to do
The other Factor though is my son who lives in Roslyn nearby
Just had her first grandchild
And so that convince my wife it was worth moving from Seattle where are bases
Back to DC
So I got a great job
My wife got to play with our grandson
So that was
Pure justification right there no need for anything else
It's so let's talk about the to program 1-1 you inherited that's communicating with computers WC right
Tell me a little bit about the gold
Well in a sense it's kind of do the next generation of Siri and Alexa in those
Sorts of things
We're now that technology is there
You know what can understand what you say for the most part not always but for the most part and can provide you know minor
Assistance can set an alarm can play a song
Right help you find directions
Ncwc we really want to raise the level of intelligence
In Partnership of the computer
So it is really intelligent partner
That's you know what joint partner with the human it's really human-computer symbiosis
Not human is the manager
Iran computer
As a low level of
So that's the goal
Let's stay here for just one more minute what's a kind of
Question that I might be able to ask
After a successful CWC communicating with
Computers Pro
That I can tell
Say Siri now
Let me not you Siri but you was one of the examples from the program
Is the Harvard Medical School
They have done some work on a previous star program called Big mechanism
Where they are trying to create a system
That could read masses of research in biology
And then automatically construct models of cancer pathways
Instead of had the human biologist having to read thousands of
Research art
The computer would do it themselves
Ingrate suggestions of new Pathways offer how cancer behaves in a cell
To the biologist would have that as a suggestion
So now the CWC part of it is can we put a collaborative
User interface on top
So now the biologists can collaborate with
What's a computer
To hypothesize how cancer works
Christmas elf to design experiment
You know Soda
The computer is working as a virtual
Scientist the lab assistant if you will or
Grad student in a biology lab
Who's really helping to digest the literature
Pull out the important nuggets
And
Suggest
Experiments
I'm getting this.
I think right that the value-added is
If I'm a scientist in neuroscience
And we each spent a month immersed in the literature
You've read a hundred papers and I brought hundred paper
But if I'm working with a
Computer the computer might have read 10000
Papers were exactly
And now it has enough
Intelligence and has the right kind of
Dialog Machinery so it can carry on a much more intelligent conversation with you
Today if it was Siri or you going to confirm technology and might find me articles on
You know certain pathway
Ryder find me articles about a certain protein
Computer could do that
But it's really not going to absorb that information integrated
And in carry-on kind of more give-and-take conversation
What's a now let's move on to the program that I suspect is taking
Most of your time because
Play my mind is
Seven performers
And this is called
Explainable
Artificial
AI
So talk about the impetus for the program I guess
First
And then
Talk to me about
This status
Well first I said I came back in 2015 you know
I talked to the in-office director Dan Kaufman about
Coming back to DARPA and and so is his
Give you listeners probably no
My program manager comes to Darfur the question is what's your vision what project you want to do
You know that that's kind of a job interview better do it fast
Because it said you already have your sell-by date on your badge right you're here for a few years
And so Dan head
Actually suggested this idea of explainable
AI
I had just been to a workshop with a group of Intel analyst from.
And it was a group of machine learning and
HCI visualization people
We're trying to convince this group ball the great new technology we could
Provide
To help Intel analysis
And one of the ladies there who was an analyst at
One of the dod agency
Said that's not a problem
Her probably she already has big data analytics systems
They're recommending
Suggesting patterns are Target's
You know suspects to her
But she has to put her name on the recommendation that goes up the chain
And she gets graded
If not punished
If that recommendation is wrong
And she wanted these systems to it
Reminder the rationale
For making the decisions that
This was for her how she was going
Trust them
The machine
Trusted in you in a window
When is the machine when is this a false alarm when is it
Positive example like
I should trust
Into her
Having the explanation
Would what's really needed
And so that resonated and it's about that time is when the new wave of AI which is deep learning
Just taking off
Bright
And you hear about this cold kind of new Revolution and AI That's all about these deep learning techniques
What are kind of the most advanced of this machine learning technology we talked about earlier
We're takes in huge volumes of data
These deep learning systems that are very large neural Nets
With millions of neurons if
They're each learning weights
It helped it build a model of what's the correct decision in any situation
Electronic versions
Yeah exactly what they're incredibly OPEC
And difficult for people to understand even their developers or not
Quite sure
How do you say systems are making their decisions
They can be incredibly accurate they're fed enough data
And the data fits the world in the right way
They can be very effective
And now we're incredibly effect
Tantalizing
Faces
Objects in image
Voice record
Cognition
You know and computer games
But they're not very explainable
It's not very easy for user to understand
What these systems are doing
So for a lot of applications that's okay
If you're finding cat videos on Facebook
An explanation is not
A critical
But if you are an analyst for DOD that's picking out
Target's to investigate
Are you running a autonomous
Unmanned air vehicle that's going to go off onto a mission on its own you really want to get a good explanation
What this thing is thing
So it's a very hard problem
To some extent this machine learning technology work so well
Because it learns models
That are inherently more difficult more complex in what person
Quit special
But yet you need to get some explanation out of it
So that user can get an intuition
What the cyst
So that's the problem
So we laid that out as is typical then the DARPA you talk to a lot of researchers a lot of people in
DOD about the problem
You craft your
Solicitation you get in your proposals and you pick your performers and as you mentioned I've picked 11 performers
Or each developing what I'm calling an explainable Learning System
So we still wanted to be a machine-learning sis
We don't want to go back to the old version of Technology where you're trying to specify the rules
All the windows older versions they were more explainable
Because a human head describe the logic
It's using
It was much easier to regurgitate that logic
Take to another human
And people could understand what is
But in this case that's not possible
So each one of these 11 teams is developing two major components
They're going to plug together into Asus
One component is a modified machine learning process
So they're changing the Deep learning
A process
Were there adding a new learning Tech
Color changing something about the way the system learns
It's model
So there's more
Interpretable
More explainable
In the second piece
Going back to my
No background in HCI in psychology
Is the have an explanation interface
Which is the best combination of visualization natural language generation
You know creates just the right explanation that's appropriate for an end-user so he understands what the sea
System is doing
Even though that end user is not going to be a machine-learning
So he has to take the complexity of this machine Learning System
Create the right kind of explanation
So your average user can understand what is
The question about
This is really
The Human Side
I might do something
Behave in a certain way
And somebody might say
Why did you do that what's the explanation for your behavior
Yes and I can come up with one after the fact that sounds reasonable to me yes but I can't read
Can we be sure that I'm not
Fooling myself
Listen to just have just made up an explanation
So
Can't that be happening here
It's it can't it's called rationalizations actualization one of the techniques were using we we could
Some of the teams are taking approach where they're going to treat the machine Learning System is a black box
They don't know what's going on
But they can experiment with it they can run a million simulation trials with different inputs
And see what are the out
And see if they can infer model that explains what is do
So the test though we do to avoid the problem yours
Describing is the test is
Does your explanation predict
What the machine will do in a new city
So if you're fooling yourself
The prediction will be wrong
And especially to help user
Gametrust
You know so the user needs to have a model
From the explanation
So the user knows when
In which situation should they trust it in when shouldn't they
So they need to have
Some model that
So you know
Predictive of what the system is going to do
So they can
Create this understanding in their own head
Even though that understanding may be very different
Then what's actually going on inside the machine
It's close enough
It's capturing the main features
What the system is doing
So that they can understand
And have some faith
And understanding what the system
Another fascinating
Think of Me about
Explainable AI
And certainly hasn't learned
Is it also seems to be rubbing shoulders with some of the great questions of philosophy
Dysentery
Epistemology write a big word which means had had how do we come to know that
Things as human
What is an explanation anyway what's the nature of explanation it makes me think that philosophers would be quite interested
Unfortunately they are
And I'll explain that
And we have
11 teams are actually building the system
We have one team
It's just a group of cognitive psychologists
Who are digging into what's known about explanation
Not so much from philosophy but from psychology
Psychologist for years have studied what explanation is more effective for person
What explanation leads
Learning
Better than another
What explanation
Improve decision-making
So their job is to just a dig through all that literature
Here and help us out
With Watson
And I mentioned about the business about philosophers Interest being unfortunate
Because it's so easy to get lost in this very deep conversation about what is causality
What's the next
Coronation
And we've had a fair amount of that discussion in the
I'm trying to get around that by using a very practical definition
The test will be
If you create one of these systems a human user has to use that system to make decision
Used to manage
An unmanned vehicle
Or two
Do until analysis
Does the explanation enable him to appropriately trust the system
Does the explanation enable him to predict when the system will be right in winter
Will be wrong and that's our measure
So I want to try to avoid
This philosophical
Swamped
And just get to a practical solution
When does an explanation help a user do his job
And one dozen
So did you mean you want
Tools in hand in a relatively short time
As opposed to
A Thousand Years
Exactly right
1000 years of discussion with no tools
Sentient
So we're getting toward the end we don't have that much
But a few other things
Discuss with you one of them is you're looking at
The way artist
Official intelligence is
You received by the
Discussions
Abacus having
There is certainly some excitement I think the public is leaning toward a positive you
Beyonce
Fleets of driverless cars attack
Actually I'm working out there there's
Sorry about that but they're also result that dystopian side
Artificial intelligence is it
It's another kind of intelligence
Scary
Powerful
And that this is something to really
Fear and worry about
So you're in the midst of you are one of the
The tool builders in the AI space
How do you think about that
You're the promise and the potential
What's a great question
And one bed
We talked about a lot
I'm so first day I like any technology can be used for good or evil
Right so there is both sides to a
And we have to be
Be careful
Like to manage that
Hive overall think it's very positive
Right I think it's
Be much easier for us to avoid
Literally negative aspects
This this is where
Some of my press you and say well
But you're teknaf
Write an essay
And so
And you said that in a fairly Cavill
Forgive me one or two bases for why you have it up
What is
The level of intelligence
We're really Adonai
So what we have even though there's been huge advances
Especially in this deep learning Tech
In the last couple
We're so far away from Human intelligence
Anything that would be
An independent
Superman
Stats
Sad signs
To me it's like worrying about a meteor that's going to hit Earth
Sometime in the next million years
And in Life as We Know It
Right is not imminent
Price is not high probability
In which NASA should make sure they've got telescopes
You know around the planet so we can see that when it's happening
So we need a small number of people worrying about
Let's make sure we don't create a superintelligence
But I think the
The current technology today is so far from that
That's not a big canoe
Dystopian and point of something as you said
But it's not
Worth worrying about too much
And it's on the other side then to move forward suggest to me that you think that
Positive Ana
Points are
Really worth pursuing osher
What is just likes a driverless cars
Write that
There's a lot of issues to be worked out there but I've no doubt when that comes they'll be fewer deaths on a highway
Then it will be with human driver
Medicine you know just huge advancements in applying this to Medicine
I think one of the latest results
It was one of these deep Learning Systems can learn to recognize
Skin cancer
Events better than human.
You know so
Just analyzing the vast amounts of data that we have
Hand
You know being able to understand it or just creating Siri in personal assistance it can do a better job
There's just so many things were AI is
Going to be
Right this is making me think
Of your new grandchild
He or she
Chi heat so she is
I'm going to grow up in a time when AI is
Heart
Of the landscape
A part of the tecnis right but he will not
No right time without a high
It's kind of interesting
Have a great little video of him at 1 year old
Is first interaction with Siri
And he's learned if you press this button
The iPhone talks to him
And he doesn't even have language that we understand but he would press this
Button
And have a conversation in his own
Garbled language
You're just fascinating
So I think will be interesting to see how this generation
Pro Shop
I want to see that video at some point of time and I just want to thank you
At 4
Engaging me and really would have
Absolutely fascinating started my morning here
Lots of things for me to think about for the rest
Rest of the day so thanks a lot for 12 thank you certainly enjoyed it
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about David gunning
The program.
Any other breakthrough technology
DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA.
And four links that enable you to download this
Go to the voices from DARPA
Grand Rapids weather