Technology is a driver of our times
Tinted founding in 1958 in the midst
The Cold War
DARPA defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver
Technology
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window into darkness core of program manager
Their job
To redefine with
My name is Tyler McQuade
Since 2013 I've been a program manager and darpa's defense sign
Lance's office
And I'm your docker host
Ivan Amato
Tyler I'd like to
Start out with
Learning a little bit about you
So maybe you could tell us
Something about your background and
How that relates to
The kinds of programs
You've been
Developing and
I've been on the molecular
I love Molly
I have since I was in high school
And even Beyond
High School too early
I'm a Survivor Nova Junkie
Cosmos
Billions and billions of stars while I was more interested in the billions and billions of moloch
I've always wanted to be in
Explorer
By the time I
Got to the edge
Yo I might explore some
Aldi
Charted land
Charted and there were no more Uncharted
So
I looked kind of Frontiers that
You couldn't see
And molecules fit
Little more defined in physics
Cuz you can put it in a bottle a lot of times
Especially in the area of
Berri Conker
Organic Center
You can make
Stuff in NC
Set the properties
Play with
The combination of atoms that are together
Really it
Was sort of this
Pallet that
I really like that
Or in the world
Always been amazed at how
YouTube
Just putting together atoms and
Certain geometry certain bonding
Can come together into materials
With all kinds of
Different properties
Skin
I mean
Hugo from
Having something that can form life
To something that is
Explodes
Do something to make
It's beautiful colors to something that makes
Is your cookie
You smell great
Taste great
Your molecules
Directions are not that many molecules people.
So as a rep
This minority
How are you taking that info
In the form of
In the defense Sciences office one of the things that's going on right now one of the
Zeitgeist
Inside
Revolutionising science
How do we do
Science but faster
Better
And one of the things that is interesting about chemistry especially when we're talking about the makers the people who make meth
Materials make small molecules make medicine
It's a really slow process
I really like the idea of Reinventing science and in chemistry there's a lot of opportunity to reinvent the science
Somebody ask when you say Reinventing science
Did you mean the actual process that we were asking questions that we were trying to answer those questions and if so can you be
No more details about what you have in mind
Chemistry is a tough subject
We have lots of parameters that we don't often know how we're controlling them but if we did all of the chemistry in much more
Controlled environment where the environment was being constantly monitored we might come up with much much more reproducible
Which will then mean if it
Transportable
So another words if I have a machine that's doing the chemical reaction recording how it's done
The knock code
That record
Can be sent from one laptop to another
So you could accelerate it in the same way that the internet allows you to accelerate how information was transportable would if you could
To do that with
With molecules
Tell her this might be a good time to talk a little bit about
But you were the programs that you're working on and what I have in mind is the full defect program
And the make it
Program so why don't we start with
Old effects
That's a program that stands for folded non natural polymers
With biological function
In the fold effects program
We're making
A polymers that mimic natural polymers
So that we might
Make
Biotherapeutics more Robux
The right now if you
I'll get one of the more modern drugs right now
A good portion of them are made from proteins think
Something like
Entire bodies so for example Humira
Or insulin those are examples of protein Biotherapeutics
The problem is they are not heat stable
And
If it's something isn't heat Sable it's not going to end up in a medic bag
To our soldiers at the very place where they're going to be most vulnerable
Don't have access to the most advanced medicine because many of them were just fragile
And so we have to transport them back to an environment where
You have refrigerators you have
Handling equipment that can allow you to control that
That environment around the medicine
What if you were to make
An unnatural
There are lots of natural fibers that we used to use
And we've replaced them with non natural fibers because there more robots to me like Silk
Tonight
Yeah exactly
So if you were to take those same sort of beneficial properties of yet
Plastics in the word merge them with the beneficial properties of the biological polymers like proteins and DNA
And so that's
The full defect program but it's a platform it's about
How we make those and then how we discover them
So anyway if you think about
All of the possible molecules that one could make the small ones you know like like an aspirin or the larger one
Ones like these
Protein-based medicines you're talking about
They're really sort of an infinite to two possibilities like an infinite space that you could possibly search the app
What you're saying here is your trying to develop some tools that will enable
Even just a few people to 2
Go explore some of the regions of this Infinite Space that just have not been looked at before am I getting them on track
Oh you're so untrack you get back to my whole desire to explore that I talked about you know it's from my childhood
It is really about giving
Researchers a capability to be able to explore these these universes it's almost like a Hubble
Horoscope for
This particular Galaxy or Universe of molecular space
So that was fold effects yam
I'm also interested in the make it program can you say a little bit about what you're doing there
Make it is a platform technology for making small molecules
And in this particular case were trying to do is we're trying to democratize
Chemistry
So what if you could have
A system
Did a biologist or any scientist came up and typed in the target
And the Machine figured out how to make it
Even if there was no recipe available
So that the machine would figure out a possible set of
Ways to make something and then would go about testing each one of those ways until it found a solution
Then it would log that solution in a cloud or in its databank
And now that molecule could be made anytime in addition the
System would also figure out how to make more of it
So they usually it would do really small scale synthesis that means no mg and then once it figured out a solution
Send it with an also automatically scale it up
Can you offer to us in a concrete example maybe you could think of a
Problem or a particular receptor for example on a cell that you might want as a Target
And then explain how
The make it
Framework would go about
Interacting with that
The receptor in prep solving a medical or other biological problem
Yeah
You'll for example one very popular Target for the heart disease areas pcsk9
And so there's probably
Many papers that come out every year that describe
Inhibitors that have been discovered against that
Target
The structures are available
Let's say that I'm a researcher and I want to study some aspect of a complex cellular system and having access
To the pcsk9 inhibitor
Would be really useful
But maybe I want one that's selected in a certain way that isn't commercially available
But somebody's reported it
Now I might contact that researcher who's made it before and maybe they ran out and scan take them three months to make it
But if I have access to a make it device
I can just go type in the structure
And have the material
Maybe the next day or at the end of the week
And in addition to that
I have it memorized
The machine has
Kept that in his memory bank so if someone else in my
University environment for example wants to make that
They type it in and it'll be out that day
Cuz the solution were already be there
It's a way of saying
Chemistry has been documented
Since its Inception especially some type of synthetic chemistry
Through
What are called experimentals
These are documents that the researcher is
Using to try to capture what they did in the laboratory make something to writing it down like a recipe
So a lot of times we'll leave out details
That we think are not necessary
But are necessary
And sometimes we didn't even know they were necessary so when another researcher comes in and tries to read that cookbook like it
Experimental it might take them months to reproduce
And I mean ever
Why should we
Waste our human effort
By not making sure that we document that outcome that experiment in a way that can guarantee reproduction
So you're talking about
Capturing procedural knowledge
Correct
Yes the make it system is not just a artificial intelligence system Mora
Cloud system that's
Archiving
It's a machine that's doing the chemistry
So that the machine will be reproducible you'll be able to recreate that machine in any lab you want as long as
You replicate that machine Faithfully
And it runs the routines that you've recorded in one lab
Versus another Faithfully
You're going to reproduce chemistry
Everywhere
You want to
What are the things that I find fascinating about DARPA is
That it is perhaps unique in its place in the overall technology developed
Ecosystem
And it's a program manager and someone who's been in academe and I think also an industry and now here
Adorable
Can you talk to us a little bit about
How dark I might be playing some interesting or breathy the unique roles in the overall technology ecosystem
Yeah I think it's a
Very exciting role
DARPA is that one
Place
Where
We are thinking about
Innovation unconstrained
Like where can we go
In my mind the reason why we're doing that is because it fits our mission space if you want to
Creator for been surprised it's best to get to that new
Universe of chemistry sooner
Rather than later
And so we take
Innovations from all of the other funding agencies in other words they're seeding it
And we look for when a wave is beginning and we push it hard and let it crust fast
DARPA is
Critical because we are
Or structuring
What I consider to be that
Crescendo investment
As we are trending toward something amazing and no
The internet is an example and I'm really emulating that with make it I want to create the internet
Of molecules
How do you transfer molecules from one place to another
In the same way is a 3D printing concept
You have a design you can put that design in the cloud
And then if you have a 3D printer you could transfer that design from one place to another
So they're related
And I'm
Constantly inspired by what DARPA has done previously
Is there a question Tyler that you wished I'd ask you during this discussion that I didn't end up so
Ask the question yourself and answer it
What's my favorite aspect of chemistry
The answer for most, what what's the answer for most of this chemist Ivan do you know
I love that the structure of a molecule relates to its function
I love that one
Yeah most of my friends maybe or Serta cro-magnons I guess
Everybody likes explosions
But actually like the smell
Of organic chemistry so pretty much almost all Asters like you know when people go into like 31 flavors
Laborers are thinking of maybe in a mint chocolate chip I'm actually smelling all of the Esters and wondering I wonder if
Is that this Ester or that after directly refers to a particular
Chemical Motif if I work off my own organic chemistry part of it there's a
Carbon with a
Oxygen double bond and a few other things we don't have to go into the details except to say
That is a particular kind of
Molecular variation
Yeah classic compound
So I really like the class of compounds that are
Associated with flavorings and I don't mean just not natural flavorings I mean natural and non natural light
A coconut
It smells the way it does because of chemistry
Not that that always just really made me excited that's how it really enjoyed
Talking with you today about that your programs about chemistry that DARPA
I said thanks for being here
Ivan it's always a pleasure to be with you and thanks for having me I'm really glad to relate my thoughts about chemistry and DARPA
And thank you listeners for sharing this time with us
Tune in next time for another voice from DARPA
For more information about DARPA the program managers and a breakthrough Technologies they are developing
Visit us online at DARPA. Mil