Technology
The internet
Palm of your hand
Autonomous
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA the defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been
A driver of
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window Into Darkness
Quora program manager
Their job
To be defined
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your daughter
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Dr. Anne Fisher a program manager since
Any agencies
Defense Sciences
That's where she and her fellow program manager
PM's as they were known in house
Forage deeply into the fundamentals of chemistry
Free physics
Optic materials
And other disciplines in search of new scientific and Engineering foundations for technologies that can matter for national
Home Security
And it's making her Market.
But it's one of the few Chemists in the agent
After receiving her PhD in chemistry from Michigan State University
With a catalyst project that relied on Electra
Oakley conductor
Diamond
She did a couple of research students at the naval research lab
Which is the Navy's broad-based corporate
She also got her feet wet in the Science and Technology policy world
As a fellow
At the American Association for the advancement of
Publisher of Science magazine
Then in 2009 she began with continues to be her partner
Starship with DARPA
First as a contract scientist
And since early last year
As a dark
Programmatic
Enterprise
Inspired by her own successful journey to become a woman scientist in a male-dominated
Profession
She created a Girl Scout chemistry Pinterest
With the goal of getting more girls interested
In the molecular wonders of the world
Dr Anne Fisher welcome to the studio
It's great to be here thank you
Before we talk about your sizable portfolio of DARPA programs
With names like
Make it the molecular informatics and this one
Spectral Combs from ultraviolet
Terahertz
You've got to tell me how your interest in chemistry a rose
Because you will know most people men
Where women
Bolt with panic
The instant you say something like the periodic
Table chemical
Helmets
Yeah so so that actually goes back
Elementary School
Sitting down at the kitchen table in my house
Growing up
And my parents bought
Chemistry
Things I don't think you could probably buy today
It wouldn't be in the store today I had literally had a rack
On it with all sorts of different chemicals a very dangerous chemicals that are probably don't even want to know what they were
And it had experiments
From an early age my my mom specifically my parents both
Sort of
Just encouraged
This sort of
Exploratory experimental nature and I just watched on.
Then through High School sort of Oliver science that can really choose an end it was really solidified
In my undergraduate
Education at the College of Wooster
Wooster Ohio
Just
Do you know there was something about chemistry and the way it was taught
And that department that really
Just kind of
Catalyzed
Essentially the resting of
The Graduate
Career in post
Tell me just a little bit about that dissertation project where you used to electrically conductive diamond
Right
So the the group I was in at Michigan state was really focused on
Developing electrically conducting Diamond electrodes for variety of application
And I was in the dissection of the lab that was working on Power and energy
So we're actually trying to develop new and ultra-stable materials
4 fuel cells
That really was both a project related to my love of chemistry but with a very practical app
Application
And that was in need of the early 2000 where
There was a lot of work on fuel cell development in a lot of work
Conservatory
Alternative Energy continues today
That was really the Genesis of their technology
Mexico relies on fuels even something like hydrogen but maybe hydrocarbons
End
Mine produces from that
At the electricity that's right that's right and I'm one of the one of the problems at the time was
The stability of the electrodes and tells an electrons are what converts word of the
The fuel if you all of the hydrogen atom and example
Case 2 electron
Electricity
And we were trying to enhance acid
To believe this materials
Okay then be before you move on to your stencil Naval research laboratory and you just want to
Confirm that you did not walk with any of those
Diamond electrode you left him
I left them unfortunately no they're not as beautiful as you might imagine
There are there decent films of
Really sort of Greg utilitarian absolutely
So tell me about Naval Research lab
The reason I wanted a little bit about that is is because I actually work
Four in a row for a while
What tire to write a
Institutional history for their 75th Anniversary so I got to know the place pretty well it didn't read me to see that you at work there
Yes I work there
I came right out of graduate school to postdoc at a naval research lab working with them Deborah wallison and Jeff Long
And
They worked on Power and energy related applications not with diamond but but with other electrode type
And so I was essentially taking my interest in and sort of power and energy and alternative energy sources
I'm to a group that had a long history of
So I spent about two years they're working
Actually I got to know.
The funny thing also I work at Triple E S
As well the American Association for the advancement of science
Where you from learned a thing or two about
Science and Technology
Policies that interesting
Shifting away from from the lab and into this other
Component of the whole science Enterprise yeah so I actually learn about the aaa's fellowship when I was in graduate school
And it's you know it's a one-year potentially a two-year program if you if you renew for a second year
Where
Scientist and Engineers come to DC and either either serve on Capitol Hill and work work
Four members of Congress or Congressional committee or working executive
I meant I spent my time as a triple as fellow working at the national
Science Foundation and that was my first
Kind of Entry if you will into policy by the purse strings essentially
How do we serve change the scientific Endeavors by funding
Specific areas
Technology
Queso
I'm also realizing there is something weird about
I guess both of rcb's because I'm swerving you now into your darpet experience and you know I've got DARPA
On my resume
As well I think this is for this is it I'm not going to mention it again but there are
Parallel
So
What is the Western experience you've started as a seed a contract worker
And then you became a program manager in the defense
Science is opposite talked about the early seed of phase
And then how that
Segwayed into
Your program manager
Yes it is
That's a really interesting
Thread because
Shapes
What my interests are today all the all the way back to the first day that I worked
So actually
Heard about DARPA from a friend who worked for a company that had
Cita contract here
And while he didn't work at our but he said hey there's this opportunity is it something you'd be interested in this was right after
Aaa's Fellowship was winding up
And I
I know that sounds pretty interesting and
The opportunity was was
Working with a mathematician
The defenses off
It's been man
And
Ben was
Is sort of a genius mathematician who wanted to surround himself by
People who
New other things
Chemistry biology
Physics those are
The things in it so he was really looking for someone to come in
I'm to provide a lens to chemistry
That's her if he could then
Think about how to apply math
In that space
And
It was probably one of the scariest first days of my life but I just had to do it anyway
It was an amazing offer
Opportunity
And really the sort of
The math and the programs that that
He had going
Still again as I as I mentioned her to impact my thought process
What's the time in super guns I have today
I'm have
AI components machine learning based components
Complexity those are just things were
Who sings that song
Address for a fundamental level
Many years ago when I started
And I sort of weave through you know is as
Is DARPA goes none of us are here for for all that long
And so I'm worked for
Material scientist in a chemistry to getting back a little bit closer
My roots
But still being able to bring in those things I learned from Bandon from his
Performers in the programs that he
Right in just for listening to who might not know what how does for the basic structure here works is a program manager
Who is in charge of a portfolio of programs we're going to talk about that in your case
Soon but then each program manager has has one or several
Sito's who
Assistance so what what might be a typical role for a seat on a typical program
Remind me what would say when it comes to
At working with
Those
Research groups
To become part of the overall
Program Everett
Yes it really it really depends on on the program itself in the program manager but generally speaking
You serve as you can cover the subject matter expert where you have your the person in the room with that
Expertise in chemistry
And when questions arise about for example how to apply mathematics
Tucanes relay question
You can think about well
You know if I think about a material I think about some structural considerations of that material
Those have Dimensions associated with them how that is that
Could that be addressed by mathematics
Michael design
Formatear live
So it's it's it's providing that subject matter expertise but then also
How do you bring that perspective of that field
Into
The program at hand
Because it's always about her.
Program is exploring
And how various
A disciplines in an and approaches can impact that
So subject matter expertise
Providing
Assertive reviews of of literature and things like that and then some some help with sort of program strategy
Shiso
DARPA programs are all about how you manage
Them
To function most efficiently and towards a
Specific goal into that requires a team of people I think
Really kind of
Think through all the different ways
With which that
It's a year-and-a-half when you became a p.m. a program manager
Most
PM's end up managing just a few programs
In their several positions but you are as we
I think you've got seven perhaps even more than that
Awesome inherited from
Previous
Another
Program managers in
Awesome that you've pitched and were able to get
Approved through the hiring
Vetting process
We can't talk about all these in in-depth do I would really love to
Let's just talk about a few and let's start with the make it program which I actually can tell you it was started by
Former program manager here Tyler
McQuaid who
I have a special fund this work because he was my first guest here on the voices from DARPA podcast
So you taking the Baton
221 D make it
Program so tell us a little bit about
What's the goal is and what the status is now
The primary goal of the make it program is to
Fully automate the synthesis
Of small molecule
And what I mean by that is is we have a small molecule like Ibuprofen that might be some sort of pain medication or is
Small molecule
Energetic or a small molecule agrochemical there
Chemicals are the building block materials for for what we have on it on a daily basis
We need to
To figure out how to make them
So by and large right now that's a that's a by hand process an expert chemist we go into a lab and and mix things up in
Beakers and test tubes in round bottom flask
I really Define
A route to a molecules that route is like a rat
That you might have it
The kitchen to bake a cake with a certain Tech
Textron a certain fly
And you don't know in advance
What that route is
So you go in and you test out there is steps
To get to
A particular Malik
So molecule might take a five-step synthetic route which means I need to
Go from set of starting materials
And do
Five different
Experiments
Transformations if you will
How to get to the actual product
It takes much longer than you might imagine in your head
To design a route to molecule that that no one's done before it might take me
To do
So what we're trying to do with make it is actually
Provide
Computational tools
That can help us
Define that route
Through machine learning
And then
Build
A device
The Implement that route
Completely hands-free
And we are just need to stop you here with that machine learning as a
Applied to chemical synthesis
Which is very interesting sounding to me I mean if it sounds like you have to
Gather a tremendous amount of some sort of
Data from the chemical literature to feed to your machine
So that it can pull out of that
Likely series of steps
That would work that I get that right that's absolutely right and there are there is existing
Data from the last hundred years of
Of chemistry and what's in the literature
But we actually are having to generate a lot of fun as well because his
As you might know
The data that you need to train machine learning algorithms is both what
Works
Or the positive result
And you also need what doesn't work and it turns out that scientists typically don't
Publish what doesn't
We might have it captured in our lab notebook
But we don't publish that information and it's not available in database
And that's what you need so that your machine learning doesn't take you down a dead-end
So that's right it needs to know what doesn't work and we've actually had to both
So it's generate that computationally so we generate sort of negative results if you will
We've also built a rapid screening platform
That we can rapidly test
Various reactions and we're collecting
All of the data
The molecules that are made
And then those molecules that aren't
Homemade sodas reactions that don't work we want all of that information to then feed into
Machine learning
Then help us understand
What's the best path
A recipe to
Quesadillas machine learning but also in this if I'm not mistaken
It's machine
Make it right so so
This whole thing is really automated your machine learning a saying
Going to try these 10 different synthetic routes and then
A bunch of gadgets are going ahead and doing it right right so we're trying to accelerate both that the brain is a chemist in terms of
Of having to sort through and sit through what route to use and what route
The test and also then the implementation of that
On a device
So that will be a fully automated
Process
And not only automated from the perspective of making one molecule but we want one device
The commit
Mini mall
Nuts
A pretty complex undertaking
So as I Envision the whole system
It's it's sort of making me think a little bit of sort of like a a molecular version of the
Star Trek
Replicator or something like that but where
Maybe I would I would bring this make it
Gadgetry
Somewhere to a battlefield where
I might need this or that
Can you take us through an actual scenario let's say you're sick
Successful with makeup
You have these make it
Do Technologies these gadgets
Boxes that you can ship somewhere who might want that and what were they used for
I think about this in instead of two main ways one is one is from the perspective of
If there are times where you might need to generate some
Some medicine for example remotely in the field
This device would allow you to do that it would allow a non-expert to come up to the device
And so you know I want medicine X and the device would then be able to
Define the route to that medicine what is the most efficient route most cost-effective route the most environmentally friendly route
Be able to make that medicine
I also think about it from the perspective of a reproducibility and enabling synthesis
Four fields for research tool for fields that don't
Have synthetic X
So for example in the field of molecular biology
Perhaps they could have him make a device in their lab
And generate
Small amounts of chemicals that they might need in their research
Without having to purchase sort of large
Large products or in a products that aren't necessarily available commercially they be able to then use this
To enable their research
Interesting okay well
Good luck with that with make it may you take it
To the finish line
I want to move to another program
Which
I find this absolutely fascinating molecular
Informatics
You know me we've also gotten familiar with the idea of thinking of DNA
Deoxyribonucleic acid as an information can
Containing molecules
Contains genetic and
Say it's sort of
Has the
The genetic or the molecular in
Information blueprint of a of a person
But you're you're taking this idea of molecular information to
Entirely different
I'd rather audacious places so can you talk about
Molecular
Yeah sure so
Looking for my taxes at kind of a
Crazy instantiation of of really what would you do
If you could actually store data
The physical form of a molecule
So nature does that as you mentioned in DNA
That's that's how that's how we store information for genetic codes
And then there is work going on to store actual Digital Data zeros and ones of our our digital world
In
DNA so DNA has these four building blocks
And you can essentially
Code
The zeros and ones of our Digital Data into these four building blocks
But when we started to think about this in in terms of of
How we could both accelerate
Ultra dense data storage so that's the benefit that molecules provide is is it from a density person
Effective
You can store much more data in a very small physical form
But also then as compared to say
The transistor base magnetic memory things like that take memory yeah
But then if
If you do that they're there their serve to threats or what is that nature uses for building block
Box for molecule
Ulta store
Our
Complex
Instruct
Options for life
But there are millions of Malik
Nny limit ourselves to those for
So we started think about this from the perspective of if we could actually sort of address
An access
The Richer palliative chemistry to store data
What could that been enable from either a density perspective or a computational
And that's where we started to see this this mix between
Storing data
An archiving it
Which is which
Time is really good with DNA right now you you write the data onto a DNA strand and you put it in the refrigerator and our climate
Earlier
But
Could you actually use that information in the molecular
Perform so could you compute
On
That molecule
For some function so computations are like
You know you might want to do an addition or multiplication or you might want to do
I'm a search of a large dataset
So a large image that do some sort of machine learning on that day
And what molecules offer is
Not only
The ability to store
Data in a very very dense way
But also
Very highly parallel
And what I mean by that is
Chemical reactions happen
Relatively
Quickly and
They happen
Essentially simultaneously
So if you have a beaker full of molecules
You'll have multiple reaction pads all happening at the same time
As opposed to the sort of Serial processing or one right after the other process
Something that we might think about
Are there particular kinds of
Problems where
This molecular computation
Would be better than then
What kind of convention
That's exactly what we're exploring
You know we have hypotheses about where that might be true
We have some approaches that are looking at things like
Similarity search
Trey very large set of images
So
Can I find all of the images that have a red shirt
Can I do that much money
Faster
In a convention
The computer might be
Able to do it
We're looking at problems in involving signal processing
And optimization so so how can you optimize a response how can you get sword of the best
Function from that room
And
What we're really looking at is is
Can molecules able
Us to do things like
Faster
And or can they enable us
To do sort of a computation
That
A conventional computer that sits on your desktop would not be able to
I just want to drilling on one part of this
To see if you can help me understand say how
Hey the result of a chemical reaction
I'm saying this
Molecular
Computation
Camille corresponds to a
Redshirt in an image where
How does that
Molecule
Map
To the
So that depends on how you encode the
I'll give you a an example that's kind of easy to Grass will go back to DNA for
Two DNA again has these these four base pairs
And we put them together in a string
And that string
We can then
With that string in the code that we use for that string weather it
Actg or gcta whatever we design
Code
For a red shirt
We could actually
Then
Synthesizes DNA strand
An image that has a red shirt in it will have that red shirt
Code
So in some if I have a string of 100
Of these A T C and G
The code for that red shirt will be embedded within that
And we'd actually search for that very quickly from within a molecular
Way
And and with DNA we might do that with some complementary strand so
If folks understand that that DNA has is assertive a double-stranded process
We're working in
Encoding on the encoding and data storage side
Single strand
So we can use that that sort of base pairing
I'm phenomenon that that nature uses and DNA
To then how do we reach in
To that
Liquid stew of of data and then only pluck out
Those strands that have
That code
For a red shirt
That sounds absolutely amazing one thing that I think would be interesting to maybe
Try to give
Listen to sense of is just
How dense
The storage can be I mean you know sometimes you hear
People talking about
Storing the entire contents of the Library of Congress
And something the size of a sugar
Cube like the Library of Congress
Become a and information unit
So when you talk about
DNA as storage, how much
Say I mean this might be difficult
But in in DNA that could
Packages sugar cube
How much would that be
So
Wouldn't one of the best kind of
Images I can provide as if you took all of the data that have been generated in the history of
Time
Up until like
2015 or 26
If you swear that in DNA
You could pack all of that into something besides NSU
Absolute Style
Tiptoe to put an exclamation point on that what we're trying to do a molecular for Maddox is
Is
Provide sort of practical DNA storage solutions that we can compute on as I mentioned but then
Access that broader
Pallet of molecules which might provide
Even higher.
Right on that case
Biological evolution leads to DNA with these four building blocks acting
But that doesn't mean we have to stop there
Our purposes is
Or something else
Alligator storage
You might have
Additional building block
Boxer wants a different different functions
That's right that's right in it allows us a lot more flexibility in our in our designs
We think a lot at DARPA about
Not only developing and a blanket
Abilities but thinking about the ultimate source of scalability and implementation of those
DSO really is looking at things that we might actually realize in 10 20 30 years
But we always have that in mind
Different science
That's right
Let's just touch on two of your other programs just briefly
One of them ACDC that stands for agnostic
Compact
Demilitarization
Of chemical agents in that just sounds like a great idea
Yeah it's it
It's a wonderful and Nessa
Necessary
Unfortunately
So is a CDC program is is designed to make
Transportable
Devices that can destroy chemical warfare
So really we're headed with this is actually
Building a device that is
Almost a conventional diesel engines if you imagine a diesel engine and what we're going to be doing with this diesel engine is using
The chemical warfare agents
As a fuel
So just like his you would burn diesel fuel
In an engine
We're burning chemical warfare agent
And destroying it in the process
So we can produce energy from this engine
But we are also then destroying chemical
I'm an ultimately what we're building is
The Prototype
It's a pickup truck
With an engine in the front that in this pickup truck can drive to a site
Run
Off of the chemical warfare agent destroy chemical warfare agent
And then we can drive
Swords to plowshares
Thanks
Okay may you actually succeed in a nephew you've tested this a few times right now
Developing rebuilding the full system develop
Okay the last of your many programs that we will talk about right now is
Scout just because I mentioned it earlier in the intro that stands for
Spectral Combs
Ultraviolet
2 terahertz
And we're not talking about here. Comes that we use to make our hair look nice right this is something else
That's right
Scout is is focused on
Developing compact sources for spectroscopy
Spectroscopy is essentially a chemical measured
Of of
Varispeed
She's so if we want to know
What species are present in the air that were breathing we might use spectroscopy to five
And
Tell was really designed to take
A capability that have been developed that
Single wavelength
And expanded all the way from ultraviolet to Terre Haute
Hertz as you mentioned in the reason that you want to do that is because
Molecules behave differently
When they're
Energize if you will with light
In the UV regime than they do in the terror
I'm in different systems respond to phone
Aliso movies is very good for interrogating biological
Where is terahertz might be really good for really complex mixtures like breath an hour
So people are very interested in using terahertz
Before for those compass
Interstellar
Had to have two threads one is to develop the materials to miniaturize
Very sort of high-fidelity sources
For spectroscopy
Across the UV de Terror
That's right
To use for the sort of spectroscopic apus
Application
And the other was to actually demonstrate let's say that we can build these things in the laboratory
What can we actually do with them then in the field
And
What we've shown is that
That Scout offers the ability to do
Things much much
Faster than conventional
Systems
So I can take a spectrum
In a matter of milliseconds where it might have taken me minutes
To do before
And that's very important when you when you have something that that is a matter of whether or not you want to know that there's been
Chemical attack for example you want to know as fast
Possible and you want to know exactly what that
Agent was
I'm just kind of
Tool can tell you
And also we've been able to show that we can do
The spectroscopy over a large distance
So, am I
Link the distance
Which is really important to monitor larger areas
And this might have implications in the oil and gas industry for gas leak
Example
Also for air quality monitoring across the city there are a number of different Factor
You could think about
I'm in these are all I safe
So so we don't have to worry about safety challenges
And we're really looking to find out how we might apply
This
Spectroscopic method
In a in a DVD and then outside DVD
Why didn't you just mention along the way
Even breath analysis that that begins to sound like a biomedical application cuz I know there has been research
Indicating that
There can be in a really subtle signs in the in the sort of the chemistry of Ativan
Exhalation right back in the be indicative of
Play some kind of disease and really what you're getting in something like breath analysis or any other biological or complex
System generally as you getting a lot of chemical a lot of signals
That might change
Frequently or overtime in the concentrations might be very very low
To developing a technique that can can do both
I'm deal with that the complexity of of the number of different
Analytes if you have the number different things in that sample and also do it very quickly and distinguish them from each other is really
Okay then just finally on that for that word
Home
I take it it's because if you were to look at the distribution of wavelengths
Insertive represent each one of those is a line
Then
There's many lines in a way look like the tines of a comb
That's right that's exactly right suit so you get a light source that provides
Many wavelengths
All at once
But they have a very
Find spectral resolution
Which is really important
Again for the surf
Complex apart
Dealing with
Okay so we we've kind of touched on four of your programs and I but we will will have to leave the other one
Another time Although our
Westerners can always go to the DARPA website and find out more about those
So you been a program manager for about a year-and-a-half
And that that means that you
You're probably only have
Have a couple more years to go that's typical
I'm just wondering if you imagine
Back
2 your time here at DARPA but from a vantage
Of 10 years from now
And you've examined what has
Come of your work
Computer program
Save
Scouter make
What do you hope you will be able to say at that time
Well
I really you no looking back
We spend a lot of time here and I'm spending a lot of time thinking about
Where might these things go and that's a lot of what what DARPA does is build relationships with other organizations
Transition the technologies that would that we develop and so
I already see seeds toot-toot to what that answer might be
There's some projects I have where it's going to be continued scientific Kentucky
Call development a lot of knowledge generated
And it might be
You're 20 to 30 years before anybody sees anything and it might not look anything like it does
Today I think for four program like
Like make it we might actually see these two
Systems and we might actually see some
Some generation of the systems that we're building now
As a first generation
As commercial device
We might see some seeds
Industry
Enter the chemical production industry
Using some of the
The computational
That we're developing
I think
Programs like make it in ACDC
I can see a very practical through field adapt
Application
And more Partners like molecular informatics I think it's
We're just
At the Forefront of the
Fining
What are the questions we should be asking
To really begin to understand the opportunity for molecules
In
And something like
Write an as I game this at myself if I try to be you for a minute
If I knew say 10 years from now.
AC DC technology that I work
Help to decontaminate tons and tons and tons
Very dangerous
Chemical warfare agents
Well I mean I would feel like I have something in my life I have to say even even even being it.
On a daily basis is humbling experience but then
You know seeing something
That that you're working on and they are performers are working really hard to
To develop
Become
Used
In either the deity or a broader
Contacts
Will be incredible
All right and then that's what we're getting toward the end here but I did just want to touch back on
An interest of yours that you express way back when you were
Graduate student
When you were
You're a woman entering the world of science and and
You know in what
Tradition has been in a male-dominated
Kind of world
But going further not just getting through that yourself but also
So trying to inspire young women and girls to do the same so the Girl Scout
Interest patch in chemistry a little bit about that particular experience and then if you've actually continued
That kind of Interest
Even in your late on your career really started
In in college
College and graduate so I was actually part
And held leadership roles in an organization
My undergraduate and graduate
Tutions
That we're really geared towards
Assertive women science
And
We did Outreach
Sit tight tight two young girls and and worked at science fairs and things like that but we also then work Community for each other
Weather and the faculty at RNC
It's not it wasn't something Limited
2 to a student
I might sort of crosses
Alter professional level
And
I learned a lot
Through a lot of those conversations about explicit bias
Implicit bias and all sorts of
Of quitting reasons
You know
That
That there is an underrepresentation of
Of both women and other
Under represent
But for me it was about finding the answer for the reason it was about empowering
Those around me
And and that happened it at that level at
It still happens today but I think I do it a little bit more
Organically now as opposed to being involved in an organization's it's much more about mentoring
And trying to fill a hole of that other women might have in terms of
Having a circle of
The people around them men and women to help Mentor them
And grow their careers
And that's one thing that that I do try to focus on
And also then again make sure that I have that in my
Life is wild because it's important for everyone
Play to make sure that they build this relation
For folks
Books to help
And learning
Okay so what
We were actually at a time
But I just wanted to ask you if there's anything about science
DARPA your career as a chemist
So it was anything else you just didn't come up that would be adventurous
Well you didn't ask me it how fun this way
Well tell me how fun is it this this being being the podcast but also
Life in general it at DARPA
And I say that because
Get to interact with
Amazing top-notch scientist
Json
A daily base
Multiple times a day
That's a really exciting and it's a really fun it's amazing opportunity
And those are the folks that are doing that the
The hard work to implement
All of the ideas that we might
Generate
I'm really put them to practice
Snn again from another perspective of coming to work every day and being humbled by that
And being so excited and energized by what they have
To bring in terms of their ideas and
But I just want to thank you for spending time with me in the studio
And they're getting up to speed on your programs
Thanks this is fun
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from.
For more information about in Fisher
The programs that she and her colleagues run in the defense Sciences
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download this
Go to the voices from DARPA page
On.