Dell Technologies
The internet
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War DARPA the defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver of Technology
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window at the DARPA score of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato
And I'm your doorposts
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio Dave Palmer
Program manager in darpa's
Micro Systems Technology
2012 he has been in that office overseeing a portfolio of projects
All of them with the goal of pushing Electronics into smaller faster and generally more capable territory
The welcome Deb two voices
Thank you Ivan
Semi truck to start by just finding out a little bit about you and that's what maybe you can tell us something about your back
Compound interest
And how you became a program manager
Well like every red-blooded American teenage boy I started playing Electric
Guitar
Back then
You play through an amplifier that use vacuum
And there was some cash today with the soft glow of the vacuum tubes in the warm sound that you get
When you play your guitar through them
But that being naturally curious so
Started to wonder
How they worked and how does the guitar take the motion of the strings and turn it into an electric
Signal
That led me a day
Studying electromagnetics
I ended up pursuing engineering electrical engineering as a career
And started working as a government program manager for the Army research office about
15 years ago
Until I ended up here
Let's talk a little bit about some of the programs then since
The 2012
That you have been overseeing
And I'm thinking perhaps we can start with the terahertz electronics program
And I'm going to try to steal your thunder slightly here by telling
Our listeners that in 2014 that garnered a Guinness World Record but I'm going to let you talk about the programming
And what that does superlative moment was
Cuz when you were
That was a lot of fun
Indeed
You can think about transistors like you think about guitar strings
The low-frequency guitar strings can be heavy and
Loose
But as you move up in frequency the strings get thinner and you have to wind them tighter
It's kind of the same with transistors when you're working at low frequencies you can get away with large dimensions
And
As you move up in frequency
Does Dimensions have to shrink
So the terahertz electronics program we really took that to an extreme
It's like when you're
Put new strings on your guitar in your tuning it up
And you're winding the strings Tighter and Tighter you think they can
Get any tighter in there about to break
But you still keep whining and finally you hit the note you want
It works kind of the same way in the terrorist electronics pro
So they let me just stop you a little bit before you say more about the program
Because I'm not sure all of our listeners would have heard the
The term terahertz
I know the a above middle C
On a guitar vibrates at 440
Hertz at 4.
40 vibrations
Prosecco
Tell us what one
Terahertz isn't
Comparison to that
1 terahertz is
10 to the 12th
Vibrations per second
Which is one
, 0 0 0, 0 0 0, 0 0 0, 0 0 0
Cycles per second
That's one trillion
That's correct 1 trillion cycles per second so that's very hard to achieve
In an electronic circuit right
Yes very hard
In fact when the program started none of the performers believed it could be done
And during the program there were many instances when
We were thinking that maybe we should just circle the wagons and try to make the
Electronics work better in a lower frequency
But one of my colleagues Bruce Wallace
Said that
Chuck Yeager didn't get famous
For flying 85% of the speed of sound
So if we were going to have a terahertz Electronics program
We were going to have
Electronics at work at 1 terahertz
So everybody found a new knobs to twist
And
Kept working on it and finally we did hit that Mark
Right okay in the end at that time that what if perhaps it is now you can
Please let me know what the status is
But it did it actually was
The fastest switching electronic circuit on the planet
It's the fastest Linear Amplifier on the planet
At the time and still is and I imagine it will be for some time to come
Okay so it took you in a few hundred Inspire your performers those
Groups that work on this to to wax
Achieve this
You went to Great pains to do this
What what what what do you get by having a terahertz
There's two things you get
Removing transistor performance up in freak
One is you access much wider bandwidth
Which is like having a bigger pipe
How to push your data through in a communication
And the other is
If you work on a transistor enough to
To make it
Capable of working at a terahertz
You have to eliminate all the parasitic capacitances resistances inductance
That limited
Performance
And then when you take that same transistor and operate down
At lower frequencies saying the millimeter wave
The performance of the transistor is much better
You get lower noise
Better linearity
Better dynamic range and maybe most importantly better power a fish
Interesting soda get this
Circuitry that that
That can switch it
It hurts
I got that has additional benefits just because you push the technology for it and you can apply it elsewhere
Electronic space
Exactly right
Let's move to another program that
Bully gets back
That's what we were talking about
For which is vacuum line
Electronics
Ice-cold invest in that stands for Innovative vacuum Electronics
Science and Technology Program
I'd love you to tell us a little bit about
The origin of that program what problems and where what technologies is it is
Designs to create
And what its status is at the mall
Terahertz Electronics program pushed solid-state Electronics up to an extremely high frequency
But if you're trying to get extremely high frequency and extremely high power at the same time
Vacuum tubes are pretty much her only option
The problem is that vacuum tubes scale
Without braiding frequency the dimensions get smaller and smaller as you go up in frequency and so at some point you just can't build
So the invest program is exploring
Several different areas one is
Advanced manufacturing for example using
3D printing
Additive Manufacturing
Division there is to be able to draw the tube in a CAD program ship the cad file to the printer and ended
End up with a millimeter wave tube
While I write out of the machine to computer aided design
You have to make the cavities in which
The frequency
Occurring really small smaller than ever
4 for the frequency
The cavity Dimensions get smaller in the alignment requirements get more critical so if you could build the whole tube at once
Do you have the dimensions and the alignment
In one shot
There's another thrust in the program that's looking at modeling because as you move up in frequency
Small variations in the manufacturing process can produce large variations in device performance
And you'd like to be able to know
Which of the dimensional parameters is most important
So you need a modeling program to do that
Then there are
Other components of the tube
The cathode
In the beam wave interaction structure where we just went out looking for
New and interesting ideas
Maybe that would just blow away the current
Way of building tubes and eliminate the problem with manufacturing all together
Okay so let's say the program
Ends up being successful and why shouldn't we think otherwise
So you end up having
A new kind of family of Technologies where you've got
Does high frequency
And you got the high power
Where do you imagine these Technologies of finding an important place
So you hear a lot about
5G is the next generation of cell phone communication
You're talking about using frequencies are in the millimeter wave
Region of the spectrum
But still
Hard to get
Devices
That operate in that
Range especially with enough power to close a Communications link over a long distance
So that's where the invest program comes in
You get millimeter wave operation
Anti power
In an affordable
Power efficient
Device using your pipe metaphor which I really like you have your
Will have bigger pipes on it
Connecting our cell phones to the system
With this technology that
Might come out of
Yes absolutely
You're not going to find a vacuum tube in your handset
I'm pretty sure but it could see some using base stations and definitely military communicate
All right. So let's talk about just one more program and if this is one of your latest
Which is a mouthful to say I wanted to the short forms I like is
M cubic
He actually write that out that's m
3 IC but the wheel long form
Alce
It'll take 2 seconds or 3 magnetic miniaturized
And monolithically integrated components program did I actually say that right
Yes that's exactly how I feel like I've accomplished something
Okay well the primary goal of the program is to be able to integrate magnetic materials with the semiconductor
Doctor devices that everybody knows and loves
Today
If you
Dive a little deeper into it weave
Achieved an incredible degree of integration of electronic components like
Resistors transistors and capacitors
Largely because
You have a large
Pallet of materials to work with
That have properties that are relevant to electronic components
With Magnetic components
You're only three elements
That have intrinsic
Magnetic properties
So we've been very difficult
To find a way to integrate those with semiconductor process
What we're trying to do with the program is leverage some work that
It's been done in Material Science on magnetic materials
Over the last decade or so
With microwave engineering
To produce integrated components
Where you can actually access that magnetic physics
In an electronic circuit
In a very compact
Form factor
So let me ask you this because I'm already Amazed by the chips in Arlo
They can do so many things they have
First part of somebody Technologies
What more are you going to get by by taking
Small magnetic components now and integrating them into those those ubiquitous chip
From the user point of view you probably won't see anything much different
But from the technologist point of view lower frequency systems use magnetic components all the time
But they're large and heavy and
Tend to be
Difficult to integrate so you kind of push that functionality out to the edges of the circuits
And use it in a non-ideal way
Give me an example or two though of a specific technology where these magnetic
Components
Are Central to it even though they're not
Yet integrated onto the ships themselves but they're somehow in the overall system to what might be an overall system that has the electronic
And some of these
Magnetic components
Wall picture of walkie-talkie for example
You've got a transmitter and receiver
But you've only got one in ten
There's a magnetic component
That isolates
The transmitter from the receiver and connect both of them TV antenna at the same time
If you didn't have that you have to have two antennas
No weapon higher frequencies
You can still
Do that
But the
Performance of the components drops off some
Substantially because
They're separate from the electronics
What we're hoping to do with in cubic
Is bring
That functionality back into
Interaction with the electronic circuit so you can have that same kind of
Ease of operation at the higher frequency
Right now you have to
Try to mimic that magnetic physics with electronic components and there's really nothing that
Does quite the same
Job
And for those engineer types
Out there who are listening I think the component you were referring to just now is that known as a circulator
Wow I've been this great yes it is
I guess I just impressed you and Jessica you mentioned three complaints were not going to talk about them but I'm just now intrigued by what they are
The circulator is one of them at one of the other two
Well in the program we're looking at
Frequency selective limiter
Which
Can
Through the natural physical process
Cancel out
Interfering signals whether there intentional or not
And also at a degraded inductors which
Have been kind of a holy grail for a millimeter wave circuits for a long time
And just
Give Me One Reason Why
There they've been soaked up
Well right now since you don't have access to Magnetic materials on chip the inductors 10 to take up
A substantial percentage of the circuit
Hbase
If you have a magnetic material you can shrink goes down substantially
Make a hole chip smaller
That means it works better and it's also cheaper
Can can you say in a sentence or two what
Function inductor
The inductor
Smoothes out
High frequency signals it tends to pass lower frequency signals
And stops higher freaking
So
A very low frequencies there used to filter power supplies make noise Quiet power supplies
At higher frequencies are used is part of
Filter circuits to select out the frequencies you want and the frequency she don't want
So text me or talk about all of those programs there others that you
Also overseeing
We're not going to talk about all of them now
But what I would like to talk about is these programs and you as a program manager in a place like DARPA
And what I'm getting at here is going to drop it is it's just part of it ate the overall innovation
Ecosystem you've been here since 2012 you got these programs we've talked about what is it like to be
Be here in end
How do you think DARPA is unique
In The Innovation ecosystem
Coming to DARPA is like
Grabbing the nose cone of a rocket and holding on for dear life
It's a fast-moving place
That has a significant impact on the trajectory of
Technology for the nation
And being part of that is an incredible
Thrill
The idea that you can
Come up with a technical idea that
Interesting to you
And
Create a community
To pursue that ideas is
Add experience you won't get anywhere else
You can take flyer bets on crazy things like integrated magnetics with semiconductors
End
People will actually Soldier up and tell you how they're going to do it
Right so what you just said about creating communities is just something that
That I and II guess I've observed here to in the short time I've been here
And I think maybe press one of the most valuable things that happens here
Sword art by which is
Is it true that you are the program managers do bring together
Handfuls of research groups
That otherwise probably would not have gotten together
But in getting together now
Create event bring together mindset skillsets toolsets ways of doing ways of thinking
That are unique and therefore can push into new
Technological Terror
Did I overstate things are that about right
Now that's about right it's very exciting
Can you name one science fiction technology that you just
Wish
Live
Since I commute weekly between DARPA and my home in North Carolina
That would be teleportation of course
But I don't think we'll ever get there we don't have any wireless communication technology that can
Can transfer the amount of information
It would take you
Completely disassembled Enrique
Construct a human
In any reasonable amount of time
Imagine having to encode the information that
In every strand of DNA in every cell of your
Your body
Every memory you've ever had
Every scene you've ever seen
Scene
Take that apart
Turn it into beds
Send it somewhere and then rebuild it in
Physical world
Driving might be
Dev I do hope that teleportation does become a reality at some point in the future is a very least to make your
Commuting and traveling around a little bit easier
I've really enjoyed the entire conversation Devin I just want to
Thank you for coming to the studio
Thank you Ivan it's been a real pleasure
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
Define this and other episodes of voices from DARPA
Visit us online at
DARPA. Bill