The internet
Your hands
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA the defense Advanced research projects
The agency has been a driver of Technology
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window
Want to DARPA score of program manager
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your door post
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Arriba Peru
A program manager since 2014
In Darkness defense
Science
Throughout her career
Reba has been working on mathematical innovation
In applying them in areas ranging from
Spacecraft control
Vibration control in structures
And even to the vexing problem
Quantifying uncertainty
In a mathematical model
The scientist
Fuse to study complex phenomena
Weather and biological processes
In the engineers use
Used to design simulate manufacture
And operator
Many of the complex Technologies important
In Military and civilian setting
Thanks people for spending some time with me today
Thank you Ivan
I would love to start out for you and learning a little bit about you about your background your education
Some of the
Important things that of
Happened throughout your career
That ultimately LED you here to Darby
Tell us a little bit
Well let me tell you a little bit about my
Background
And tell you that the chili my relationship mathematics has been a developing one and I have to say that
Over the years
It has really
T-Pain
I was born and raised in Iran which has a long tradition of excellent and rigorous mathematical and
Technical education
I
Receive my
Bachelor degrees
14 applied math
Physics from UC Berkeley from then I went to
A beautiful Campus of University of Wisconsin-Madison
And then I went to Brown to get my PhD in applied math
After getting my PhD
I came back to
Meme of Postgraduate School to California to Naval Postgraduate School in Monterey and spent several years as Professor ended
Department of
Like math
And while I was there I was contacted by a colleague of mine was working and very sick
Similar research areas she suggested whether I would consider getting a job as a program manager
For computational mathematics said efforts
Of the scientist
Research
It's Arlington basic on the same block as a Starbucks
I wasn't even sure what that entails
But having my colleague and friend in a position and watching her but she was able to
To to achieve but actually an inspiration and that's when I said yes
And how then was did you make the direct connection here with
DARPA I suppose
To being a pmlc
The interesting thing was that about
Maybe couple years into my job but some program managers from TWRP approached me and they said that with the
Interested in going are coming to DARPA and
And I have to say
If I thought getting a position to a full-service scary and cut about a character I thought the
Kites DARPA would be
The scariest thing to do
I become familiar with the research that being supported by DARPA and our permission
And I was having a hard time trying to see her supporting basic Research In Math
Mathematics could be
Of any relevance to what darpro was doing and making that connection
You certainly have done that with your
Programs which we will
Talk about in a little while you really haven't discovered that there really is a connection between you and end the
Grams
Before we actually talked about those I want to pull back a little bit
Find apps how you
And Mathematics became lifelong partners and I asked you this because
I think this is true for me and I'm sure many listener is that
The mathematics is just one of those fuels are
So many of us
Is difficult
We we we kind of push it away. The earliest time that we can
And yet you've really had this partnership Tressa how did you develop this what I imagine is a
The kind of love for
For the discipline
So my interest in mathematics
Was not actually from the point of view of being interested in abstraction
Or just because this is this was the way my
Mine worked
I was always interested in problem-solving but I was also interested in gaining
Better understanding
Pictures of the physical world
So I didn't want to become an engineer
Even though
At the time it seemed like all the smart kids to with strong mathematical abilities would like to go to
Engineering or they would go to medical school but then I decided no I
I want to try to become more of a scientist so I was thinking of physics
The only thing is that I started as a physics undergrad but it only took me taking semester-long
Concourse in their experimental to realize I don't have a lot of talent that I realized you didn't
Necessarily come with a lot of pleasure enjoyed spending my time doing experiments
So then I decided that I tell you what really gives me
A lot of pleasure in and studying hard as was actually the more mathematical
Aspect of the
The physics courses
And I found out that oh I can I did a very quickly become a double major
In-flight mathematic
So that's how I started interest me about applied math is that
In that way of engaging mathematics
You are looking at these symbols and working with the symbol that many of us associate with Matt
And you are finding out how they relate
Wheel World in pretty dramatic ways
One way of making this concrete in this conversation might be for you to tell us about how
You applied
A kind of mathematics
Kind of an innovation for which you now have some mathematical entities named after you
And and how that
Led to operational
Changes
With respect to the international
Space Station
Can you just tell us that story
About
W that math
Two space station
So
The research that
Doing
During my PhD in afterwards.
To do with control and optimization of
Natural systems that are modeled by
What's an example of an atom
Sound
Animal control of
A structure
Or any combination of interaction of these
Different physical
So in the case of for example of spacecraft control
Is that beer looking at the situation we're looking at complex nonlinear Dynamics
Where in this case
So that means little changes can lead to big
Results possibly even even though the sound engineer system right this is not necessarily like climate that you would say
Quit being a Sally don't have any control over
Innate randomness
Patient but he were talking about engineering system
That we would like
To perform certain maneuvers
In an optimal fashion
So you're expecting your system in this case
The skyscraper
Needs to perform certain Maneuvers at that lets you minimize a certain
Objectives
So in this case
You trying to do it
Sometimes it minimum time sometimes you're trying to do it with minimum
Energy or
Minimum
Something to go for it
Is propellant on a
Spacecraft can cost
$10,000
A pound
So if you can minimize that
And give the Nvidia another needs to cost by the house across stuff like in the case of
The National Space
Station
The cost of refueling
Could be
I mean not that situation so you really have to use everything in the most cost-efficient
An optical Manor
So in this case for me actually I have to say that
The whole success story here I owe it to my
Basically my colleagues were able to
They said forget the theory and
The algorithms that we developed
And basically
Work really hard
How to implement
Right and if we were to just to say simply what the result was
My reading is correct is that you were able to come up with a way of using certain systems like gyroscopes
On the space station
To achieve fairly dramatic
Changes like 90 degree turns 180 degree rotations without
The used
A propellant released minimizing to a great degree
The need for
Propellant
And it's this would not have happened
I did not come up
With
Inefficient
An accurate way of
Implementing days
Right input the actual control that went to those gyroscopes
Emerge from the mathematical framework that you were able to
To develop into this
Should have brought that line all the way from the smoke.
Abstract way of thinking math all the way to this
Million-dollar multi-million dollar savings
Of how you operate the International Space Station
That to me is sort of one of the Miracles of of math and its connection to the real world
What's what's Segway than two
And the two programs that
You are working on here
So one of them goes by the acronym equips
That stands for
Enabling quantification of uncertainty in physical systems
The other one that goes by the acronym model that stands for models Dynamics and
Learning
So let's start with equips
And again that stands for enabling quantification of uncertainty
In physical systems
Sounds
Fascinating the idea of
Quantifying uncertainty
Tell us about the program what the goals are and what
The status is
At the moment
The goals of the
Program I have to say no
Southern Loft
The fashion which is not always my
Almost state of Rio Fest
Yes but I do have to say that I had very lofty goals for the
Program
And
The way
In my mind I was thinking of the program
I still do
Is
To dress like bleach
Change the wave
B
Go through our modeling and simulation
What you were saying physical world engineering system
We do have a long history
Basically
Mama Soul of scientific
History def of modeling physical
Systems and physical phenomena
And using mathematics
But what I'm saying about changing the practice of modeling is
In some ways
Taking into account
How good how how bad we are
As modeler
It's almost like being inside certain level of honesty
2R model
Innocence dad
We have to consider the fact that it doesn't matter how good
We think our models are
At the end are just going to be an approximation
It just going to be a surrogate
For the physical real
The fact that in the process sometimes we are not quite clear
About the
Let's say the discrepancy between our what the output of our models are and what the physical world is
It's going to create a lot of
Issues
When we trying to analyze a cyst
As far as physical modeling goes probably one of the most successful
Stories is basically
The navier-stokes equation
So you might apply the never Stokes
Equation for example
If you wanted to
Try to describe
How
The cream you pour into your coffee
Goes into that
Fluid in you see the Beautiful
Horse world
Or it might be the way
Masses of air in the atmos
Sphere are flowing
Adventure intermingling itself
That's the clothes at the range that were talking about with the taxi
In a basically Huff love everywhere you know
Airplane games
It's basically the fundamental of aerospace engineer
At the celebrated equation but the problem with it is that you didn't you talk to
So people who are looking at
Physical physical flows fluid flow
And they do still scratch their head and it still can say that
We are talking a certain situation let's and Hypersonic
But it's not at all clear
That this is
Equation
How to get talking about
You were still talking about fluids but it's at the scale and
Serta physical condition that
It's not at all clear
The right equation
Steven try to
Assimilate
Yes we do have airplanes that fly we do have an aerospace industry has been one of our most
Successful
Water Industries
Let the 20 Century and it will be even more in at 20th and the teacher Center
But
It makes you a little worried that the sum of the work and the mathematical work that is being done
Is based on
Certain assumptions that and the physical models that may actually not hold
Correct me if I'm wrong but
As you were speaking I'm realizing
Well
We have
These
Technology wish list
We want Hypersonic vehicles in Hypersonic technology things that are
What's the operating faster than the speed of sound
What you're saying is
We've got mathematical equations and traditions and method
Fly roughly in the kind of
Phenomenal
That are applicable in
Designing
Hypersonic vehicle but we actually don't know
We don't know cuz if it's an accurate representation of of that
Hypersonic
Arena
This need for
Quantifying or uncertainty or lack of knowledge and also the kind of error and discrepancy.
Between a mathematical models and a physical reality and our Engineers system comes from engineers
Because one of the things is that
You're looking right now in situations
Bad
The only way they can
Consist of
Certify
Let's say their design or whatever did Bill
Is
By using something right and in this case
Probably try to do it using
Well in certain situation you can test
And maybe you can if you do test summon the kind of testing maybe could do it
In certain maybe certain components
Before testing on the system
Praise up listen up Coldplay
Will necessarily have to be done on the entire when he's after you've already built it
That's a little too late in order to come up with
Ways of changing a design or changing the way it's
Being built right so you would like to be involved in that whole process
As a mathematician and as an engineer
A little earlier into that
So the only way to do that
Testing is not going to help
Personable insurance
Situation is
Is maybe too expensive
Too late
And
Something
Possible
Is using simulation
Whole thing about simulation is based on having a mathematical model
And having the simulation tools like a basic it is numerical methods and all that and a computational tool
And
Platform store
Computers that you can actually Judy
Assimilation
So this is where you see that math comes in right there
And this is the only way
That we can test out
These
These new designs on your that are not already there not built
But you have basically the elements of
The design so you can at least test it out
Using simulation
Before
Before you go
I think I heard you once
Talk about this is almost like a mathematics
Honesty
Yes it is and I love the phrase now that you're talking about
This
World of
Simulation
Which is
Based on mathematics and then perhaps
Mathematical models
Operating in the form of computer mod
But in there in that kind of abstracted
Place
An extracted operation
You're trying to develop a framework with equips
That
It is kind of the reality check in the map
Exactly how well is this
Representing ultimately the real world
Technology that we want
To emerge out of this
Mathematic
Sex and modeling
Is that
Mice characterization
And what is so fascinating about this is that the feels goes very quickly from some
May in in the beginning may think
Some philosophical
Ruminations about what is reality what is representational reality what is a relationship
Should of mathematics 2
Physical world very quickly
Some beautiful Theory
So interesting
Result that I expect from eclipse
Is to see whether it's
Possible to come up with some common Frameworks and common tools that could deal with some of the
The major challenges
Within looking at very different application prompt
This is this is going to be an interesting
A process to to observe and see what results come out of it
Because the performers at this point are looking as system as
A different as possible from each other from Aerospace structures to integrated circuits to chemical
So we'll see whether something
Commonwealth
Come out of
What's the maybe that's a nice cue to talk a little bit about
Model
Are the models Dynamics in learning
So there's actually a very nice link between
The program equips and model
One issue that I need to emphasize about
Quips
Because right now I've only talked about about basic as you mention it took
Trying to
Capture
Make honesty as part of her modeling
Process
But I haven't really told you about the challenges
That beat we have enough
Processing
One of the biggest challenges is that
The complex world that bear looking out of compass system we are looking at
The high dimension
When you say hi dimensionality
What do you mean by that sounds like there's many parts that we have to think about
Right
Exactly so so there's a lot of times when you think of dimension
And you might have heard that you're thinking about the dark
Three physical dimensions
And then we have a dimension of time so we we think our physical world is basically
Laika for dementia
But the way we're using dimension
Basically here is what we think exactly is the degree of Freedom or basically
The number of variables that
We need in order to
Build a model
What represents
At model a robot with 10 joints
Is that
I could think of that very simply that
10 dimensional problem that is
Exactly
You could be very exact
And the interesting part is that you look at a robot and you have your look at it okay but I want to write down basically
What I'm thinking about the
The number of
Variables are modes or whatever that I can
Express the physical variable that I'm interest
But at the same time
Sometimes when I wanted to
Any kind of approximation
Right
Of each of these
10 variables
Start end dimension
Each Dimension I'm actually need additional
Dimensions
In order to do my app
Approximately
So this is like at every step of our modeling here and and an approximation we are introducing
More Dimension cx-10 demand what we say is a 10 dimensional system
Ends up being for example for each Dimension I may need another 10 yesterday
Way of seeing how
10 Dimensions multiply
In that robot cases that
Each joint
Self has has these three spatial dimensions and the temporal so each one has four
So suddenly were already at 42 have to do with the physical
Relate to the physical
Representation but someone says something's Dimension comes from our
Approximation and the modeling and the mathematical work that we need to do
It's at 7
Really good question
I said what what may be talked about
High dimensionality
And this is what happens with the
A system that we are looking at
Dad's representation of this physical
Systems
Require
Lots of Dimensions lots of variables lots of
Heideman
And the and the higher the dimensionality the
The harder to compute to put into a computer actually run a simulation
Legos back to how much Computing can we do
And people say we'll know right now we do have
Extremely good extremely fast
Computing platforms
And that is true
And that's why at this point we can do
Computing physical system that
20 years ago was no pasa
But the more you do
The higher the demand on viewer analysis tools
Know about model
So model is a sort of an acronym for models Dynamics and learning
And I would say that the goal of the program is
Extracting mathematical models from Dynamic dataset
The goals of a program when you say dynamic
Dataset something a lot of data Dynamics makes me think of motion or time
Did I get that right or would you want to ask what I mean by Dynamic data set is a data set that you get from
Dynamical system with your system was Behavior changes
Spectre
So you are a dynamic system I mean it's just life is
The greatest example of a dynamical system
One of the reasons that I wanted to
Have this program
Was also again seen that existing tools
That we have or modeling
Cannot handle
Us on the complex dynamical system
That we need to analyze
You're looking again very similar but we're looking for a sample system such as weather
In a fluid
Biological systems even Engineers system like communication networks or
Eunos
Human social networks these are all examples of
Dynamical systems
But we don't have very good analytical
Medical models to
2 Express
The complex behavior of this system
If you just look at a dataset from
Something like turbulent flow
It's fascinating because you CDs
These vortices these holes these Eddie's
Is beautiful patterns come and go
Exactly that's the
What's so beautiful about these
Old is different fennel confit
6 phenomena that can be expressed and then you see at these some commonality in
And in this case what we trying to learn is that what are the common patterns that can be learned
And basically
Express dynamics of these systems
In terms of evolution of
Yeah I search
We don't have the mathematical tools yet to deal with the data
Some people say why you no look at us we not only beer at the age of Big Data be also the age of
Machine learning and oldest different ways that we can handle data of any size
But what I'm saying is that
Assisting techniques
Cannot handle
The fact
That data is
Dynamic
I know actually now going back and say look
Go back to the beginning of dynamical System Theory
I'm trying to develop
Different way of modeling
Extracting these models from dynamic
Give me one example of a
A phenomenon a system a technology that cannot really be modeled well now
That if your model program is to
Successful
Wildomar
Alaska performance in model program to start with something that we think we have some grasp of
And use it basic as a test case I'm going back again to the classical problem of basic guitar panel flow
My Hope Is that
They can
Plida methodologies
Mathematical methods that day
Developed
Two systems that are much less understood
And their system for example of data did you get for example
Wolfram neuroscience
So you're talking about things like
How brain signals propagator
How
Patterns of new Rolex
Tivity associate
The sensory stimuli
Or the way we move
Absolutely
It could be
Data that you can get even from
Social networks and so
Social systems
And basically two systems for which was really
All right
You're lacking
Proper
Mac Medical
Modeling
Before Time runs out here I I just want to ask
One question about
Being an applied mathematician at a place
Like DARPA
One of the phrases hero a lot here is the Innovation ecosystem
And what that means is
It really was referring to what kind of all the players and all the stakeholders that it takes in order to go
I'm sort of an idea about it
G2a
Technology that you
But you haven't had that
What's the operational to the field
So as an applied
Mathematician what what do you think you can do here that you might not be able to do
I saved our price probably the best place to be
If you are
Applied mathematician in fact I just say format fewer mathematician and blank to solve a problem
Because
One of the
Greatest thing about door prizes dad
There's this wealth of
Information about the
Problems that are important and
I have to say they're very very cool
The coolness Factor
4 problems to solve for a mathematician
Here is enormous
Because you feel that not only your solving a problem that has importance there's certainly broader
Impact as far as universal solvent important problems and National Security
Videos of feel like the problems are so rich
That is some ways
There is some
There's so much to contribute
The richness of the problem
Are just
Maybe the
Biggest driver
A motivating factor
Anybody
Certainty for mathematician and I and I just want to add
That is that
And I've been saying that to my my
Friends to my colleagues anybody who would listen that why mathematics is actually very important to 2
DARPA
And encourage them to come
Feature program manager is that
When
You are encountered by
Important problems
And you see that your ideas
The role you have as a mathematician that not only try to look at these
Particular Problems by Detroit to abstract out and coming with different representation that would yield
A better solution for these problems
So you basically see
That you ideas are at work I mean what better satisfaction
Well free busy
It's been a delight for me to talk
To you about
Your Love of mathematics
Coming out to your right now
And to get some sense of how mathematics does
Have that role in in the overall Innovation ecosystem in a particular
So I just want to thank you for spending this time with us
Thank you Ivan
And pleasure
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with Reba and I
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about for Reba
Her programs and the other breakthrough Technologies.
Is working on
Visit DARPA. Mill
And four links to allow you to download
Go to the voices from DARPA page
Andar persuade