Dell Technologies
The internet
Technology is a driver of our time since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War.
Defense Advanced research projects agency has been a driver of Technology
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window at the DARPA score of program managers
Their job
Redefine what is possible
My name is Dan Green since 2013 I've been a program manager and darpa's Microsystems technology office
And I'm your DARPA host
Ivan Amato
Tell me a little bit about your background and how it relates to what you hope to accomplish in your time here at DARPA
I came here through a series of fortunate events I got into science from an early age I like physics
I did physics in college
I got into semiconductor physics
So semiconductors are the
Materials that underpin the electronic
In all of our commercial Technologies today
And
Really fell in love with that area
At that point time which was in the in the 90s
When I started getting into Electronics in in
Going out to grad school it was kind of a bad time to be doing Electronics because
There is a lot of maturity
In light of
Concerned about where it was going to go from there because of
Established players like Intel work
We're heading there hitting the stride and Along came a new material system
Call Kelly nitride
Until I was part of this first wave of Engineers that were brought up
Looking at gallium nitride to understanding its properties as it applies to transistor technology
Can you just spend a few seconds talking to us about
What is interesting about different kinds of Seneca
So when you look at the history of semiconductors
Straight the transistors came out
From the labs of force
After the after
Did the second world war so it's been around for a long time
Maybe interesting pieces that
As dominant as silicon is today that was not at all obvious
When I started
And in fact when you look at the
The first transistors they were made of germanium
And they look like crazy little Contraption correct the size of a palm almost they jabbed a couple of
Wires into this block of material and were able to extrapolate from that very
Very rudimentary experiment that
Hey we're really onto something here
It's obviously translated
Too many billions dollars of
Commercial activity now and
The complexity of this we can do things today is
Astonishing
Really the key was
Going from germanium to silicon and and a lot of the technical reasons that
Made silicon
Work
Relate to the fact that it's just
It warms combinations with other materials called oxide very easily
And so having that oxide layer
Really help control where the electrons flow
The ability to manipulate the the material structure
Is really wet separated
Silicon
From the other competitors of that time
Nht peace that happened with the you know the semi characters zoo in the 80s and 90s
Was the dramatic expansion of the materials that were able to manipulate in that matter
And so we went from
Things like Silicon to our notice compound semiconductors where we use combinations of element
To create new material sets
So the first
Material set that
Hit the mainstream is called gallium arsenide
Instead of being at your regular Crystal just made of silicon atoms it has an alternating pattern of gallium and arsenic
Right and my understanding is going from Silicon to a Compound Semiconductor
Igallop arsenide
With hard enough
That it became a program by DARPA to to try to
Make sure that material make it useful as a
DARPA made early investment to take
What then was experimental technology of gallium arsenide
That was useful for things like amplifiers and
Really scale it up
To make it manufacturable
Because they realize that it was going to enable us to do things like a raise phased-array so what is a phased array phased arrays
Is it is a
A combination of amplifiers in a repeated pattern
So that you can project electromagnetic waves
So that means things like
Radars that go on our
Airplanes and ships
Can leverage that capability to see what's around them and to communicate
And what ended up happening was because of the
The defense interest in between that technology in the end the ability to bring it to a manufacturable state
I love you will realize that hey would be useful for
Commercial sector as well
It so that same gallium arsenide technology that came out of the early DARPA
So-called mimic program
In the 90s
I was really what set off the cell phone release
Because it enabled
The amplifiers that let
Those small handsets that you carry around with you
To talk to
The cell phone towers
And that expansion of of the semiconductors do we we we started with germanium with
Talked about silicon we talked about gallium arsenide
This might be a good time to consider moving to some of the programs that you've been oversee absolutely
Kellie Martin I was was really exceptional because it showed
How different material properties can be by moving away from
Silicon
But by no means did that exhaust the periodic table
Pinterest people were looking around
They realized
That there's a lot of other rocks
Late 90s early 2000
This was out
An individual researcher actually develop the technology to grow high-quality
Gallium nitride material
Elementary materials is special because
It. It offers a wider band Gap so that's a characteristic energy the material
And it enabled
Devices to be made which could emit Into the Blue
Part of the electromagnetic spectrum
Which was not available before
That's what off a whole wave in terms of lighting until we're saying that today with our pixelated stoplights and and the LEDs that we see now
Houses
But the correlation that was an able that material set
How to be more Wylie
Available
And enable those of us in electronics domain to use it for other purpose
Places like high power amplifier
Enable us to
To look at
Things like more efficient cell phone towers
But also higher power a raise for
The Navy and the and the Army and airforce
For the sensors and Communications and the
Electronic warfare equipment that we use everyday
Read and I know that one of your own passions has been to try to
Look at the strengths of these different kinds of semiconductor materials in and then try to put them together to mix-and-match them
Craze that might not have been so easy to do before partly because their Crystal structures are a little different and they might
Not stick together well but these are some of the challenges right that you've been taking on as a program manager
Part of the interesting piece
We can learn I try it is
Nothing much that it provides all these advantages but then it works at all
It's a very different material set then historical Summit
It has a mechanical element that's a part of
The way that it operates more than just the way that it moves Electronics
It has what's gonna Speers Electric
And so it actually
Depends upon being compressed
By the combination materials
In a certain state
To enable the electrons to exist
Where we can use them
So we can mix in a little aluminum for there are gallium and nitrogen
To create a different alloy and we
Can grow those crystals right on top of each other
So that they maintain their structure from letter to letter
And a lot of the development that happened in the early DARPA mimicry was enabling those techniques where we can control that Crystal
Flaring at the atomic scale
Which enables us to create
These types of very finely
Characterizes structured
Devices
Over very large area
So we can create very complex circuits
That are structured at that atomics
So where all this goes from here
Because it has this
Funny characteristic of mechanical and electrical coupling that's different is that
There's a whole swath of degrees of freedom that haven't really been explored
So I entered the field just as it was maturing
And worked at a company to help bring one of the initial products
To life in terms of
High power amplifier for the cell phone community
But my time at DARPA has really been about
Where Do We Go From Here in terms of
Leveraging all these
Hidden attributes of gallium nitride that really haven't been
I brought the bear yet
So things like scaling the gate lights down to the links that we do
And what that that enables us to do is push up higher and higher
So how do we understand that well
The
The frequencies that we we commonly encounter for like our cell phone is around to kg
And really because the scaling advantages and that we can do with gallium nitride
The higher power density that we can't we can start to realize
The ability to transmit power
Up in the millimeter wave
So that's a
Towards
30 to 300 gigahertz
It's the ability to dress that higher frequency range
Really opens up a whole part of the electromagnetic spectrum that we have been able to
Why do you want to go there
Because that will enable things like 5G
In the commercial sector
There's a lot of activity right now.
That's going to help us all stream video from wherever will
Auburn also enables us to do different things like look at different material properties
As we interrogate what's going on with with different materials with
This different party like a mini spare
So we can actually literally see the world in a different way
Because we're using light
That the possibilities of what we can do there at just starting to be explored
And the capabilities that we're developing with gallium nitride are a building block in a tool to help us
Then how would you imagine the Technologies
But you are nurturing you spoke speaking a lot about gallium
Imagine that Finding Traction
Both the National Security and civilian
So the
Technologies were developing with gallium nitride
Are going to be very are going to be very important
For National Security because
It doesn't he wants to get into these new parts
I'll be like him a nice pair
So that underpins
All of our capabilities when it comes to things like
Communications
Or sensing
Coming from the civilian sector I didn't really understand until I worked
With some of the military
Is that
Rethink why do you need to send something
And
And we know it's down the block and we're walking down the street
But if you're in the Navy and you're on the ship in the middle of Pacific
You're in a very very dark place
And you don't know what's around you in the world
Shenzhen becomes very important
Because you're you're really out in the middle of nowhere
And that's
Part of the
The piece that's missing I think when we think about this in
Context of art everyday
That the military is doing things that are very different
From what we do in the car
What we're doing with John Knight Rises enabling the technologies that will help them with those particular mission
And what will happen at the end of the day is that once we have them
People are creative
And they will find ways to use those piece
There are more relevant to what we doing
In our everyday life
So what might be some of the larger societal technological in
Security context in which your
Program in interest reside
It's a very interesting time right now in electronics
And because
Historically the US has had such a dominant position in the development
From the initial development of transistor Bell labs
Through the
The mass roll out of
PCS from Intel
And what we've seen it just in the last decade or so
Is the globalization of that technology has
Spread around the world
What are the byproducts of the early going where DARPA funded a lot of these gallimard Senate Technologies
That rolled into our defense
Defense Communications
Consulting Technologies
Was that we had a very comfortable
Place in the world where we
Could make all those components at home
And use them
And in very controlled matters for our perp
And with this globalization that's taking place
It's because of the Advent of cell phones
Consumer electronics
We're seeing now that
All these electronic pieces in these different developments
Are happening all over the world
It's a really challenges
The way that we
Consumer electronics
In the apartment
Offense
Because now we
We don't necessarily have all of those
Best components at home because there's a lot of
Activity all over the world
Until there is
There's challenges both understand what pieces
We should develop
And
Can continue to own at home
And what pieces we should leverage in that Global Marketplace
And how to put the the best of those products together
So that we can confirm a competitor
What you're talkin about here in some ways is the study of the
Technology
Ecosystem the engineering ecosystem
Innovation ecosystem it makes me think about
We're DARPA
Listen to these very
Ecosystem
Siddhartha really is
Fantastic in that
It has the ability to go in and make
Significant investment
It's too advanced
Technologies
Critical
Really be a difference-maker
For instance
It's in in gallium nitride
I mentioned
The
Newport's again as it came along
To advancing what we can do in the RF Spectrum
And really that
Technology was
Without in the world
Because of the LED Market
But DARPA came along and
Made a significant investment
In wide bandgap semiconductors or which
To push the matter do that
That's base
For the electronics to me
And because of that early investment DARPA
Has created capabilities
That are being rolled out now to the services and in
The form of new
Radars that are going to the Navy and communication systems that are going
Around the services
And
It's also dominant
Provided the backbone for
Industry players that are serving commercial Market as well
Then can you describe one
Science fiction technology either that you read about in the past
Come up on your road you woken up in the middle of the night with his dream of a technology
It doesn't exist now but that you really wish
Could exist
This is what we do here cuz I know time dreaming about different technology so
It's such a fascinating time because a lot of these things that we formally just dreamed about our
Coming to life around us
The one Comic Book Guy I did read when I was a kid was Iron Man and so
We now have all these Iron Man movies but
What's fascinating is walking around the building and seeing how parts of those Technologies are trying to make it look
Less and less crazy you starting to see
People are actually working on exosuit
People who are working on
How we connect the body to electron
How we actually
Interface with electronics
So you're talking here about complex and potentially powerful Technologies which means they could lead
To both good and
Perhaps Troublesome results
How do you think about the potential consequences of the technology
You're helping
So I think
That's a
Explanation question that we do struggle with alot
As we continue to
Expand our capability to
Compute
And
Projector
Into the electromagnetic spectrum
Really raises the ability for us to
To be always on
And always connected and it
Not only did that
Erase all the issues that
Received today in terms of
Having your cell phone all the time and
In that sense always on
But also this
Always aware
So that there's no way to hide
Until it becomes a very open and transparent
Place2be which has pluses and minuses
In terms of how we operate
As a democracy in the world
So I think there's a lot of
Implications of technology that are yet to be trifled with
But it's also
A a law of physics that technology will advance
We will continue to explore the world so
It doesn't help
Do not try to advance
And see what's
What's possible
The whole point of Darkness
To prevent surprise
And really part of our job here is to go out to figure out what spots
Hope that we can start that process
Understanding
Early
Well then I really enjoyed our conversation here today
They got
Thanks for listening and tune in next time to hear another voice from DARPA
For more information about DARPA new program managers
And the Breakthrough Technologies they are developing visit us online at DARPA. Net