Technology is a driver of
Our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the middle
The Cold War
DARPA
The defense advanced
Research project
Agency
Has been a driver
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window onto dark
Program manager
Their job
To redefine what
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and
And I am your host
Today I am pleased to have with me in the studio
Rosa Alejandra
Lucas Chevy
Known as a Lie by her
Her friends in college
All has been a program manager since early 2017 in darkness
Defense scientist
What program managers take some of the deepest dive
In the fundamental science
In search of New Foundations
Four novel technology
Relevant
Deep dive into fundamental science goes all the way to elect
Unusual ways
They can organized
Behave in certain materials and how it might be used
Engineer those
Electronic organization
Into new microelectronic
And micro magnetic.
Free applications in memory
Logic
Energy conversion
And sensors
Prior to arriving at our Bollywood
The professor of physics at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg
Burke Virginia
Before that she was a member
The physics package
At the University of
Toledo in
Ohio
And yet earlier in her career she was a research scientist
The Argentine National
Commission
Cmea
In Buenos Aires
After finishing her early college training at the University of Buenos Aires
Earned her doctorate in
In physics from Wayne State University in
In Detroit Michigan
And she completed a postdoctoral fellowship
Ship at the University of Michigan
Thanks for joining me
I'm happy to be here thank you
So let's start out by talking about
How you became interested in science in general
And then particularly
In physics and the
Antics of life
When I guess that you know mean I started being interested
Because my father was right to me articles that he was
Interested in in a magazine that he was getting delivered at home
The time you want to start as he was getting
John's RV
Which was a French magazine about latest
Discovery Center of Alamance
And he was reading this to me when I was like
7 radius also I'm universal very early start so
That was the beginning and then we'll clearly I mean in science has always been appealing to me
And I we were getting additional magazines that harm you know that I was very obviously reading on
I remember reading once about shredding the equation in even though I was like 10 or 11 at the time and I didn't know what he meant
I knew how to write it down in the deepest parts of the Quan
Car mechanics in uncertainty makes me think that your parents were
Scientist or engineer my father was a doctor in engineering
So
But yeah
Clearly I mean I was reading in this magazine as I said you didn't understand what equation man
I was staying
But I still was able to write it unit 2
If it wish I was able to draw this equation on paper
And it is a Edwin but it's from that era so I mean I was very fascinated by this and clearly well you know
Time went by
It was good in my head that I was going to go for a career in science I didn't know exactly what I say
Shirley Burch Olean Amina became very very interested in the electronic properties of materials
In my
Interest when
From their own words
To where I am right now
Rights of the first part of your
Career you
You ended up going
Academic director
William & Mary
Talk to me a little bit about that experience as a professor
When I'm going to want to hear your
How did you get to darkest
So start with a u
So I mean
I have been fascinated by the fact that you know mean is not about what we are doing is like you know we're suspicious why
Have to realize that
Our power resides on the fact that we transferred our knowledge
Is not our individual knowledge is Inola from every generation before us
Any disabled Beauty in my mind to pass this along to the Next Generation
You're part of a continuity
Right
Correct correct so I mean I was interested in in Indiana Professor for that same reason because I wanted to
To be able to you know identifying students that ain't like that capacity
The drive to go for scientific research and try to mend a tendon and in health indeed the best they could be
So that they can do no Advance knowledge in that particular area Evermore
So that's why I went far
Academia
Of course you know when you're in Academia one of the things you need to do in order to be able to
Duke aerial distance
Trying to train guys do that you have to get funding
And so clearly I mean I had to Explorer the funding agencies among them is
Starpine I got some fun
From there by Leon
And eventually you want to kind of learn okay what does it take the other side
Right to understand
How do you know select the best people to do the best work
How is this process
Being proceeded from the Viewpoint of the founding
Asian
So it was particularly intrigued by DARPA because
I said I was dropping by funded by DARPA in the beginning and so
This model of trying to find
Basic science that has a goal and ultimate goal was really very appealing to me?
Particular
As someone in academe
You might have gone to National Anthem
If you might have gotten that
Science found a
What about
Is there a Disney day
Question I mean on the one hand you know as
As an American
Not by
Birth by choice
You know I have a deep love for this
Country station for this
Country Inn in a sense of Duty regarding you not trying to have this country to continue B
What it is right now
And the best way in my opinion is to try to see okay what are the needs of the people that are at the Forefront of the car
Defending the country that would be the defendant the Armed Forces in general right
Is it what is it is going to make that difference in terms of yuno advances in technology advances in research
That can top this
This mission
And clearly they are pies at the Forefront of all of this funding agencies in that particular direction
So I was very very
Intrigued and curious and interested in being part of
Did you reach out LA to DARPA with there's somebody here that new about you what we
Was the that those sort of
Final steps
Got you
Onto the roster programmatic
I had a collaboration with store dwarf who was at a time when I was at William & Mary he was at the University of
Virginia and he was leaving and Institute in nanotechnology
And an In-N-Out took it upon myself to actually introduce my research to him Detroit
Static collaborative effort with him
And in India
Did happen and we actually got a couple of Russia
Just going inside eventually but of course I knew that he kabina DARPA program manager in the past
So mention to him that that I was in
Christian like you know seen the other side of the
Force
Is so she actually told me what wait on you give me your CV and I will pass it along and then particularly hits
Told me that he was going to show it to Tiffany dumplings
Which was a tad under the director of ESL
Meaning offense or defense
I technically correct correct that she got my city and she contacted me.
To see if I was interested in pursuing a career
So you mentioned Stu wolf and that gives me a little bit of Anna
Excuse tattoo
Maybe diving 2
Your intro
Press because I in a stool
He's a big name in the area
Tronix advances to electronics immaterial Sophie talk to me even a little more
The physicist that you are about this Arena of phenomena that so
He'll grab you
So basically in my make my career in physics here in this country have been focused
If I take orally on spin dependent phenomena
Matthias and magnetic phenomena
Depended on the spins of particles like electrons
In particular
Yes that is correct electron
Spencer
Cancel that will during his tenure as a program manager here.
Stuart actually was defended of
Can chronic in the sentence that he realized there were some discoveries I going to have
And a diamond
Talking like late 90s
In particular the giant magnet
Persistence
Affect which was
A particularly driving
Before
For the explosion in a hard drive density
And storage in general that we have eggs
Expensive Alaska
20 years
Stop you from I realize we we kind of just passed by the
Business ideas
Spin dependent the spin of electron
But there's a difference between
Spin of electron which is a little less familiar
Charge of electron negative
Chinese people do know about
Talk to me about the different aspects of
The electron and where
Dependence is
I thought you were coming to the door
Write so the electron spin is a very difficult quantity to Define because it isn't
Daquan
A counterpart In classical world I mean it's a quantum mechanical effect
Instead of trying to Define what spin is one is better suited by defining what is it
NetSpend.
Athenian General
You find it the electron
Speed
That is your
If you think of it as like a little arrow pointing in any given Direct
And what happens is that electron spins like to either parallel to each other on
And in the case of magnetic materials what happens is that the electron spins in different atoms in particular areas of the
Brent Adams
They all like each other there didn't you know very much attracted to one another pointing in the same direction
And in what that gives us an opportunity to give some meaning to this
Best answer for example you can say okay if I have a group of
Beans that are all aligned in a given Direction
I can associate that with say number one
Any they appointed in the opposite direction then I can as a say this would say number 0
And then you have the binary language and you can combine the binary language in more complex
Languages that lead to what we use in Computing
Famous ones and zeros of our digital age
Correct correct so allows you to do this in the advantages of speed
In an RR that well you can actually have these composition
Off of Spanish to be made really small which means that you can actually affect a lot of these bits
Soft ones and zeros
In space as you can enhance the area of density that you can stored of ones and zeros
They happened to be just by the nature of the materials
Protective against radiation damage rain
And in one of the Holy Grail
Cecil is being
Did you try to find out what is the limit how small can you make
This little Amanda
Spins
The store
Ones and zeros in a stable manner
So focusing on spin
Of the electron rather
Charge of the electron that
Actually have a smaller area of a safe a piece of semiconductor with or Wally's electrons are living
Small piece of metal that semiconductor will
Host a 1 or 0
Is not just a question of
Besides butt is so soft energetic
So mean you know me one of
The things that matters to you is you know
How to see how
How much power are you going to be needing in order to have these this configuration of zeros and ones so
In general you know this is what
What we found there was several effects
Associated with this activity of the elect
That enabled
Technologies
That will enhance the density without increasing the demands of hardware and making this very stage
Family and also and aggregation
So that makes
Didn't Tire you know collection of properties that are very very attractive
Not just for storage density seoul car drives but also for name
And that's basically one of their goals. That's been chronic program had the program that's
Stewart actress
Right and let me bring you back now
How to another big
Multisyllabic
Phrase that you use earlier with
Giant magnetoresistance
Reason I'm bringing that up
What is because
That phenomenon and the
Technology that
It led to
Became part of our everyday lives in our hard drives right in the read heads
Of of the hard drives
Tell us a little bit about that technology Evolution and where is it now it happened was that what he was found it was what
I'd like to the Nobel Prize in 99
98 was dead when you have layer at the systems in which you have
Do magnetic layer separated by what layer that is not magnetic
Anywho
Current through this particular contraption
The resistance of this contraption will be different when the Spencer parallel with respect when they are anti
So that gives you a mechanism to read
What is going on in Tennessee if it is parallel or antiparallel because you have now
Resistance to enabled.
That determination
And that's how you sense what is in their country
Right
So what you're reading the spins whether they're paralyzed or better because they have an effective assistant
Cracked so that is a big Power
So that was discovered in 1998
And then later was discovered was that even replaced at the intermediate layer the magnetic
Metallica The Time by an insulating layer
Then you have an effect that is even larger which means that you have MRI enhanced sensitivity what you're doing
That was a spin dependent magnetic
Aspen Dental Independence
And that led to the explosion in memory in mram
That we have
Okay magnetic when
Eighth grade
Yes I almost
Forget that uniform
Cefazolin to fill this
Just like everyday language rather not for everybody understanding science
Is understanding
Acronym that's almost half
The battle has been in the government
So let's then segue into
Life is a program manager in an actually do you only
I've been doing this
For less than a year so you have a kind of prefer
Perspective
Of an early program
I think I will be quite interesting
You already have two programs
Under your way
Ho switch stands
Weir program in ultrafast
Laser science and engineering
Is a program that yuan
The other one
The topological X
Cetaceans in electronics
RTE
That's a program that you pitched
Agency leadership and got the green light so congratulations
Map
Let's start by talking about
Pulse-width seems to be
About your sort of take
Ability to generate a
Electromagnetic
Radiation
In ways
Open impassa
So tell me what your take is on pulse in Wichita
Sherpas
I just I just stated is a program that I inherited the basic tenets of the program is that it was
Do use
At against undiscovered SF
Be encouraged
By that community
Which is related to the
Frequency
Seacomm
The frequency, something that takes
Alpena kitchen light
Super 8
Specific frequencies in a broad range
Frequencies
Can use that for a variety of Apple
Vacation home comes from Rocky cuz if you think of each frequency as a
Italian
You got something on somebody looks like the
The comb you use our address so you can select several
Citi Trends of this frequency domain and Southern Caribbean work that I was
But secretly into
Twisted indicas
Dicing with the programs that I am that I develop
People having able to use this technology for example
To get
Kind of x-ray
Behavior let the kind of behavior that you get to the secret
Facility
Big Lots
Facility on a table top
So that has been fascinating
Having able to
To achieve these by using frequency, I'm saying the Other Extreme of it was also
That people have been able to probe things
In the time domain
Widad II
Now that is a really short duration
Right I mean in Arrow II
10 to the minus 18 sec
You think of a nanosecond
9 sec
Billions
Been a second
1 billions of
Of 1 billion
One second
Is really really bad
Show that the thing about this
Is Dad
It is going to enable us to actually
Look at the time
Did not Dynamics
Because those are the only
The main entities
Isn't that going to be
Moving
And that
James said that is where you're going to be using this
So in some ways it's almost like you're trying to create
A movie
Camera
That is Matt
Onto the way electrons live in the speedway
Which is so much faster
I got another lead a human but I'll even the things are
You're being doing so far because
Cuz I mean you look at the various ranges in
Which week of the coven looking
Yes we move it song
It is
Molecules
To have a way of movie
Wynndata Translate
They brought that
And then we have seen those because those movements are not at the
CarMax Laurel
So we have been able
Want to see some of those
I mean you're getting the capabilities that will enable us
CSI
You know I mean the real
So much smaller
And move so much
Last episode this is Senor Cabello
That would be achieved by this program and it is due to their apartment this does not exist
So let's stand this one for a second before you move over to
30 program
So did this sounds like very fundamental sign of course that's why it's within DSL the defense Sciences off
Office among the six technical offices
But on the other hand we are also in DARPA
And so tell me a little bit about not only sort of
Weirdest my push
The envelope in
Fundamental science
Tell them that might actually be of relevance to National
Was some of the things that for example these technologies will enable that have been talking to her performances
Pistol for example
Provide Metrology
For example
For the math
And they are batteries that are being done at the Nano level formica
Circuits that are used in the Vietnam
Makeup of a number of Driving Systems for Mississauga
You need
Microprocessors in in in micro Electronics in the number of
Instruments in
10 + things that are used
Dubai the Armed Forces
So when you reduce the football
Their number two things that came with that
Adamine addition to lower weight
Smaller
You make a Chivas so fast faster which also enables you know faster reader
The transfer of information
But you also may enable lower power consumption which
Also enables day
I capability of having this instant
This
Gizmos
Cheap store with less
Boccherini
Show battery source
Have their own
Wage and footprint on the soldiers back
So I mean all of this
Is going into the same direction
And to try to make you know
The possibilities for safe for the soldiers
Doobie
More efficient than what you have right now
But less
Bulky and less power-hungry
Sedimentology that this technique will
Enable ghost
In an indirect action but it goes into that but
White Sand by Metrology we mean serve new ways of measuring
Very very small
Crime in as you were speaking it also makes me think that this does put
Perhaps play into
Future
Of progress in microelectronic Sanders always has been this concern for many many
Some points
We're not going to be able to use the
The techniques we use now to make the next smallest transistor
Coming out of pulse that will
Open doors for yet another era of
Of miniaturization or not miniaturization increasing capability
Current of the translational
More
We the same right Mars
Smart sensitivity for Less power even if
Advantage
Which way did you already broad parameter space
Alright so a lot of opportunity there in both fundamental science
Applying at
To the highest of tech
So let's not move over to
Your baby
Are your topological EX
Expectations in electronics
Program
And I know this gets a little bit hairy because we're using words like topological where were you going to take our imaginations down to
The electronic level
Talk to me is an undergraduate
Physics in your you're
Introducing some of these ideas
I try in a mean one of the things that I mentioned earlier was that one of the Holy Grails that we have had for the applique
Station of Spain's
In say storage or memory is how small can you make this collection of
Spins
So they can keep their information is all aligned meaning one or auraline meaning of zero
Without being disturbed by perturbations because in the end it's always an energetic
Consideration of your
Temperature fluctuations are more energetic than the energy that is contained in this
Group of LA
Calculator
Then they're not going to win and then you lose information is like I like to say my student you think your laptop to Miami and there goes all day
Information that you started that wouldn't be fun
So you need something better than that
And so
I haven't put him in the literature and turns out you know that I we have in you to our
Our disposal for for provi new paradigm
Annies with apology
Which is again something that has to do with a bit
Day of orientation or configuration
Pieology comes out of really though.
Realm of
Geometry
Like in any way
Yes it has to do with something that has to do with a special
Configuration
So in this particular case should we go to the heart of the matter I mean I told you that spins like to be parted on Type R
But he done said that is an eternity past
Fidelity designs
Covered entities that are ways in which
Engineer
For them to be content
That is making some angle between
Now you lock them into discounting and you try to put them on a surface
You realize and now they have to arrange inside themselves in such a fashion that they can accommodate accounting
And when you try to do this exercise you could take like two little bit
One upon several of them on a surface
They have to be arranged in kind of a vortex
Little Things
Aspire Ollin tornado correct
Something like that so that you can put them there right on the surface
And that is what we call
Right
Ayr this interesting
Well because now because they have counted
If you want to switch them off
Pointing in One Direction
Centerpoint India
You have to do this within Tire stent a lot
And just just for clarity when you say the word
Canting with you letter
BB spinzar
Tempted
Means it or not
Parallel or antiparallel but they're actually at a certain kind of angle almost like a
Correct
Correct correct
Is now because you're locked into this
Buy some milk
You just cannot
Switch one with us
Switching data so you have to switch the entire thing
Because you have to switch the entire thing
That cost you more energy than it will be
Doing Jazzy individual
Rights to the major internal structure more stable
. of of thermal energy a little heat snack is not enough to flip it correct
So they become stable correct that is what the topology offers
Eye protection
So that if you can like engineer this in a suitable ways such that we can create the region of Spain
Candace configuration smaller than what we have right now
For collecting the ones and zeros
Then you are in the next generation of memory device
This is a Google based
Step on this.
And I would push it that mean and there are some
Matrix itellas where can we go what will we are cheating by doing that and he's not just
Size as I said earlier they supposed to question about energetic
How much energy do we need to do this
Can you move them around can you actually do things with them so you can open up several paradigms to use this and today's
For memory loss record
Sandra Bullock
Stations beyond what we can do
I guess right now
Okay and does this still fall within the the tradition of spintronics and
Insta will Forsythia is this
It in some other Arena
In in spirit right but it's it has the saddest thing which is a topological
Action Auto Parts
Topological
That's a new thing
And that is what what this can take
Let's talk about where your program is inside
General
Life cycle of a program here at DARPA so
You came in here you came up with this
Wonderful idea
You went through the harrowing experience of bringing it to what's called Tech Council
Eyewear leadership in your
Program manager
Others are there
Wedding it
So you made it past all of all of those obstacles
Now what
Right now we have fast
Selection show a broken announcement was placed publicly so that people could apply
And you know send me the proposals that
Proposals were evaluated by teams effects
Birds
And then the stations were made in terms of
For the most
Qualified by Source selection is that those who
Can make it past obstacles become a source as it were we told them performers
Correct so right now that is De state
And so what we have going on right now will be you know the Contracting part of it so is that when the money is
Actually being delivered to the
Performers and so
We think that we will have the kickoff meeting sometime early in 2018
And shortly after we leave a review time right I mean they have to perform because that's
The difference between DARPA and other agencies
She's as well is that there are very strong Matrix at
You know that the continue with it
This reminds me a little bit of some of the early days
Here at DARPA where
Well there was a funding
Laboratory
Reason and these became kind of
The seeds
What later became known as Material Science and Engineering
DARPA had a roll there and
At least nurturing
What had was on its way to becoming a
Harley new
Field Material Science is this
This
Ascend to that kind of possibility we're
Because you're not
Ideas for organizing groups
Potential performers
You think this is going to be important for
Restarting a new field
It is particularly important to concentrate the Air Force
Experts say that maybe working on various other areas are man Ali related to one another but to console
Braden focus them on this
Specific problem with this
Specific metrics
And that may lead to advances in this particular terrain of which we are not even breathing because we don't know what they are going to discover
I mean we are thinking that one application will be
These new generation memory that we all are needing and wanted
What happened
But it so happens in this is being experienced that you know prior people including still has mentioned this to me
That often times what happens is it
Christopher former discover things that you didn't answer
Dissipate
In the girls room can go in at 8
Direction weekend and start a new program you just don't know
So that's basically what my hope is that because this is basic
There is always the possibility
Kathy Cruz
Groups of people
To discover something completely non and
That will know our minds away
Well
Well made that happen
That sounds really
Exciting possibility in some ways I wonder if at a place like darkover
Are there such a diversity
Skill set
Whether there is even more of an opportunity
To recognize when release
Surprising things
Maybe I-85 / 2
Formas no question here
Now that you're here you kind of are dropped in from academe
Your ear in the defense Sciences office
Have you met
Other
Programmatic
Pictures of run into other programs
Mom said that in a sense
Blow your mind and that are you are now beginning to think of
How they relate to your own
I'm definitely looking
Is particularly for the empty or the
The Microsystems
That is correct because these are the guys that will be perhaps
The ones I may take on whatever developments come from there so because they are the ones that are going to try to make
Actual device
Just out of this if they turn out.
To living up to
The problem is that we
So yes
Interesting Synergy there where you might
You might be on there
Really fundamental side of things
MTI Microsystems technology office
Even though still fundamental in an engineering side could take it
The next step toward what ultimately would be
The finish line and of course
This is the way DARPA works that would probably be
Out in industry or some
A part of the military service
But the result is an expected because in the sensor technology you don't know this may take you to some biology
Related sensors are we're not even thinking on right now I mean it has happened a lot
In in particularly in recent times at the lot of the discoveries.
Copying. Like for example taking the
In the area of nanotechnology I mean people were working with nanoparticles for the number to physical applications in the
And then the biology STAAR test thinking how about using them as markers
Four biological process
Viruses are things that are much smaller than cells more around you can smell
Opportunity
And we would have
You know we will see the performers get there
And then you know if there is such an opportunity will it really extraordinary
And make the
People from BtoB
Mbco gangster
Are you an excuse to mention I get another
One of the offices so that's the
Biological
And so that's that's that's from the Indian who knows I mean there might be other things that may be important for
Are tactics I mean we just don't know
I mean I know that people are in STO
You know maybe interesting
You know
Different ways
Metrology that can come from these programs
Zach will be applicable
Pacific problems that they are working on
Read it again stfc we're going through the entire repertoire here the entire set of offices that's
Strategic Technologies office I didn't mention soap
Tactical technology
The entire sex but again we don't know
We don't know where is it this particular problem is
Going to take us I mean that is the beauty of working for
You are at the Forefront of
Science we are therapist.
In that regard
Do you know that we are working with
With things that we don't know where they are
Like I said he's not a spy
Can gold
We had some idea where we want to go but we don't know if there are hidden going to be
New opportunities
Are there
Any questions that you wish I had asked you in this
Discussion that I just
Didn't get to
Yes like we're white DARPA
In the other eye contact so I mean I mentioned this in passing through other people like when I was like it
A vacation a few years ago I was reading a clock off Lenovo
And he mentioned at some point DARPA and I like
It got through the science no kind of funeral as a discus to be a hot Asian
DARPA we we do know
Has
A certain kind of Mystique and is out there in the cultural World in Barre
That is absolutely true
Yeah I just want to thank you I life
Spending this
Time with us and letting us know a little bit about
You're taking this role as a
Program manager
The future technology
Thank you so very much for being here I am proud of you in the dark remember
Thank you and thanks listeners
For sharing this time with us I hope
You join us again for the next
Voices
From DARPA
For more information about Ali lucasha
The program she runs
Any other breakthrough
Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA.
And four links that enable you to
To download this pot
And all the others
Go to the voices from DARPA page