Dell Technologies
The internet
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects
Has been a driver
Welcome to voices from DARPA
But a window onto DARPA
Score of program manager
Their job
To redefine
What is pause
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Renee Zellweger
Program manager since early 2016 in DARPA
Is biological Technologies
Renee earned her bachelor's and doctoral
Degrees in a field of applied
Biology from the Georgia Institute of Technology and then did postdoctoral work in molecular bio
Heidelberg Germany as an Alexander Von Humboldt
Fellow strategic research driver for her
It Supply tools of synthetic biology
Which draws from genetic engineering molecular biology and other arenas
To support
Biosecurity in 2 out
Pace
Prior to joining DARPA as a program at
Renee was a senior lead biotech
Technologist
Abu salha
Allen Hamilton
Where she led a team that provided scientific
Strategic support
In the areas of biodoph
Biosilk
Disruptive technology
Emerging infectious
Just disease
Neuromodulation
Ensign
Biology
To DARPA and other Federal and
Private Institute
Just a little research and development teams in the biotech
Industry
The focused on the development of immunoassays and other tools
What's for molecular biology
Disease
Renee
It's my pleasure to have you in the studio today
Thank you Ivan pleasure to be here
Let's start with how you got interested in science and
What was was there a teacher that transformed you that turns you on to side
Did you come from a scientific household
What was
This hurts me to think of a time when I didn't have science in mind even from a very young age so growing up in in Florida we always had
Access to a little critters on the beach or in little creeks in our backyard that we would play with and my sister of who
Her name is Lisa she's 11 years older than me and she
Had a career
That was really on a trajectory to be a scientist until later in life she switched to be a lawyer but in there
Early days I got to go to lab with her and kind of see what that world look
Call me really interested in so from a very early age
In high school I was a lab assistant to one of the teachers were I helped him and bomb
Some of the animals that we would dissect in classes I think I was very lucky through Elementary School and High School
School and then going into college and Beyond I always had Opera
Opportunities to be really Hands-On with the scientist to
Understand
What types of science I really liked him and what I didn't like and
I remember in
High School
One of our teachers would take us to a local
It was I think was a limestone mine and in Florida where they would
Pump out dirt and rocks from really deep into the Earth and there's many fossils Mastodon teeth and things
Like I said that you could find that really had an impression on me because that's where
I first started to learn about Evolution and
And then all through school I I did take the opportunity
Student work in the laboratory as an undergraduate
Adored attacking that's why I came back to do a PCV
Because I already had
That you're a half under
Justin for listening to it never seen a mastodon
Actually have I mean they're like the size of
Eraser
Amazing things to see
Obviously I was catalytic
And when I look at you or your
Degrees
Both of them
Are an Applied Biology which is to say your bachelors
Rihanna Dior
Your PhD
On the way but both and Applied Biology which tells me that from a very early age you were looking at
Biology as
Technology
So how did that early inside
I come to you
His estimated to think about it I hadn't thought about it that way but it but I did always see biology
Piazza is a tool
And I told understanding the world around us and later than in the University it's a tool to understand disease
And then the integrated actually even with it person moving into the medical-device world at Georgia Tech I was
In one of the early classes
That
Was working with vial engineers
They're just watching a a bioengineering program at Georgia Tech
So it was really interesting for me to interact with
Did the engineers who would actually builds a device
Based.on sings like
Cellular mechanics and fluid
Jackson and that was pretty mind-boggling
You take that
It actually turn it
Intuit device
10 proof
So for some years you worked as a contractor are you with booze
Hamilton
That's a company that's a lot of work
I would government agencies in
Ludendorff
Is that actually how you got to know DARPA
No actually I got to know DARPA
When I was working in the Biotech Industry appear in Rockville Maryland
And the CEO of a small company I worked at call Dad life this is where we were developing Diagnostics
Corner dinner tip diseases based on protein misfolding and indicators
Of disease and
The CEO of that company Alan Rudolph used to be a DARPA program manager and I had not heard about DARPA
I'm before meeting Alan so sometimes over lunch or just casually he would talk about this magical
Call DARPA wear
It really seemed that you can have a a wild idea and as long as you had a great Technica
I plan to make it happen
There could be a password to try to implement that in the more I learned about DARPA
The more I really
Got interested in
And when I was looking for the next step in my career
Alan knowing me well
I just asked you to what what do you think
Could be something that would be good for me I like the taste
Survey of the startup environment but job security it would be a little bit better
Longer-term job security would be adventurous and so he suggested
Data that I look into a different types of Contracting
He's around
The DC area
2 support agencies like DARPA
Buslers multiple archetype
I see is an end luckily I just found a great
Position
Booz Allen in
And stay with them for quite a few years
As a Sida not only at DARPA but other other
Places like ir-pi the intelligences
Advanced research projects activity
And the bill Melinda Gates Foundation is while I help them with some of the early Grand challenges
Right and you use a little government speak in there zika
Scientific
Engineering
Technical
Advisor
That's actually word we hear a lot around here there are more citas here than there are program at
You are now a pro
So you've actually warned both
And I wonder if you can just talk a little bit about
Those two categories of employees here the Sita and the program
As you just mentioned there there are
Two categories of employees here there's that the government employee which is the program manager and in other supporting staff and
Anicetus
And the way I like to describe that model 2
Two folks in biology especially their familiar with having a pi in the lab and then people that work with them to assist
Principal investigator
In a laboratory and they have a supporting staff of
They could be grad students they could be
Staff scientist II to help them Implement division
That pi and really
DARPA to me at the program manager and Cedar Villas is very much along those lines a program manager is responsible
Buffer for the vision of the program and and the direction forward in the strategy
Inesita team
There's various roles as they can provide technical content
That's complementary to the program manager they may have to
Strategic guidance
Are they may have deep darpet experience because oftentimes Atascocita
Maybe here for it for many years longer than than a program manager
Of course we're here for
Term appointment
What's nicer get into your dark life
A little bit
In 2016 who became a program manager
At that time you inherited
One program called
Living
Foundry
Please which is about
Engineering
The Exquisite control that living cells have over to atoms and molecules but in an inescapable
Technological lens
Materials
Industrial chemicals Pharmaceuticals in
Agricultural products
And then you did Elsa program
Cold safe jeans would you rather
Get through the very difficult wedding
And approval process Europe
And this is all about it
Developing a tool kit to rain in limit and even reverse some of the
Emerging extremely power
Powerful
Tools in
Genetics and genomics and molecular
Herbology
I want you to talk about those but
Before we do
I just want to hear a little bit about how you
Think about
Biology
Because as we look at some of these tools and we'll talk about
Last night
To me they're sort of miraculous
Little nanoscale
Machine that it makes me
Uniserv look
Get life in a
With a kind of reverence and awe
I don't mean to lead you that's not nice of me
Talk to me about how you view
Biology on these sort of Malay
Skeleton
And even higher
The way I think about biology is really from it of an applied
Approaching and that
Has a lot to do with I think
I'm having been
Brought up scientifically
Georgia Tech
Always
Emerson Donnelly biology but surrounded with engineering
When I look into biological
This time I think about how that system could be manipulated in a programmable way of looking at some of the tools that synthetic bile
Allergy bring saucer or genome editing like
Crisper cast 9 witches
Christopher is one of the biggest acronym so used today stands for a clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic
What does protein does it's it's really interesting it at the origins are it was a bacterial immune
Effectively wear
Feed virus would insert his DNA into a bacteria that. Bacteria would would cut up that DNA
Using crispr
Caste system
And take little pieces of that phage DNA and put it into its own genome as a memory
Of that
Infection so that if that
Again to infect that cell
I would say oh hey I have this information that I've seen this before I can now
Sew-Vac in 2012 what researcher is Jennifer doudna and others
Recognize where
He could actually program
What
Cast nine
Recognizes it doesn't have to be a phase but you can provide it within
Information to say okay
Go after the specific
Piece of DNA and that was very
Powerful I like what I like to think of from the darker perspective as a Sputnik moment and biology so we had a lot
Innovation in DNA
Sequencing and synthesis you could look over the decades that we
We kept improving that technology is very powerful now
But all of a sudden we had a toilet
How to be able to edit
That DNA
And that's that's really has changed a lot in the field now there's
There's very few organisms at
I can't be edited
I love the Sputnik moment partly because when you look at some phages
When one is named T4 they look like little spacecraft
That's right yeah there's even microsatellites in DNA sometimes
But for me that's what created an urgency for this new tool in biology that that I say
I think makes it national
So let's let's talk about the two program
We'll start with the one that you inherited
Living Founders tell me little bit
About the history of that and it's
Sure so that original program manager who launched that effort Alicia Jackson
She had this Vision to start to create a tool bed where we could
Distill biology to an engineering
Where you could
Take something like the design
Build
Test learn cycle of engineering and apply that to a biological system like a microbe
And E coli or a yeast or other types
Bacteria to make products in Mali
Would be of value
And
Really
Things that her inspiration came from looking at biology as
This incredible system that
I can make a real diversity of molecules that
Extends well beyond what we can make
Through traditional manufacturer
So when you have access to that diversity of biology
Can you start to manipulate that to make new
Molecules things that have never been made
Buy biology
The most
Ambition School
The program
Silver foundational Investments really
Created the tools under each one of those
Categories of design tools that you
You can quickly in an automated way
Design a biosynthetic
Pathway to stitch jeans together to put into a microbe
Build services that the DNA synthesis and
Insertion of DNA into a living system
Testing this
The mass spectrometry and other measurement tools to look
If a product has been made and importantly
Learning so this is
Some of the designs you make or not going to work and programming that into your learning cycle to not use that design
How to make a better design
Important
So when I took over the program The Living foundries 1000 molecules
Program was just taking
King of the first phase of the program was to build those individual components and tools and now the second phase is to really integrate them
As a platform
To create this boundary type capability that
U.s. military or a customer a business customer could go to a Foundry and say I would like
You to make this molecule
The pathway and the organ
So
The ultimate demonstration of that capability that Foundry capability is to make
And we're 551 molecules
And so our teams which are Amherst Simonton and MIT
T-bird Institute they've saved
Collectively made five
Can you just give listeners a sense of the
The kinds of Molly the kinds of molecules so they're very diverse they can be anything from adhesive to Coatings to
Paige might want to put on the outside of an aircraft all the way to a small molecule
Kohl's that that could be used
For the medicines countermeasures cancel
You name it the whole gamut of
Set of small molecules are
Being developed
Under that program
Now we're about two years into 4 year program
The final two years is going to prioritize a small subset of those molecules that have been produced
They're very compelling that we'd like to scale-up so so far we've made
Pretty much detectable amounts meaning
You're very small amounts of each one of those molecules and we'd like to move to the kilogram level so that these are not
Taxable amount that we can really Implement in enlarger
Absol exciting area me when you just
We think about biology
I think of things
Sequoia Forest you know in Amazon forest diversity of
Of creatures in an all of the tissues that
They're made of all the materials they are made of
Hormones and neurotransmitters
There's all of these these powerful
Names of substances
Come out of biology
And now here bringing a different mindset
That seem kind of
Contacts
Of synthesis
Really kind of exciting
I think it's a great point that you mentioned that that biological diversity across the globe because what many of the teams are doing art
Are looking at
Extreme environments across the globe looking at microbes looking at plants
Even looking at some some human enzymes and you can stitch those together a plant enzyme human enzyme
Extremophiles microbe enzyme all together in a in a Workhorse organism in the laboratory tutu
That's so it is
This program is very much dependent on biological
University and looking at the enzymes that that can be detected
In the wild
Doing their normal jobs that they do in the wild that we
Laboratory so you're also leveraging
The way Evolution has pushed biology to be Innovative in its biological context sort of seeing where you might find used
Things are but then
Further with human
Absolutely
So then let's go to
Safe
This is this was your first baby here right so
Talk to us about
About that
The origin of it in your mind and
What the status of that
Program is now
16 is a program that that's the part of my came to DARPA
To run in fur
The listeners that they don't know the way that program is stood up at DARPA is it it's
If it's very grass
After each type of process where it comes from the program manager and an initial idea or concept
That we can bring to our leadership
Been to the director of DARPA that gets
You into a pro
So I came to darker with the idea
Really try to harness the beneficent use of genome editing
Technologies like Chris
Best nine but to prevent
Their potential for Miss
So at this point these
Stools have
Really been democratized
It's arguable that probably every molecular biology lab in the world has access to these tools and it's using these tools
So the Genie's out of the bottle it's out there
And there's a lot of power in these tools for for editing genomes and we can do a lot of relate
Tremendous good with these tools but their potential for misuse both nefarious and accidental
Is a real
That vulnerability that
I came to
The agency to try to address simile
The ability to control editing activity if you want to use it in a given system to limit it only for you so much
System
The counter
At the
Start of the safety program there was no countermeasure available meaning no inhibitor of a genome editor that can shut down if it's activity
Is it should accidentally be misused or or in a more malicious
And then finally if it changes made how come you restore a DM back to its base
Find state to remediate then
Yeah it's it's a remarkable set of tools
One of them
I heard you talk
Reminds me of
Telomere
Ticks off how many times a cell has replicated and there's only so many times that a cell can do that
Before it dies off it sounds to me like you're something like that
That you
You are your performers and by that I mean the research
Have contracts under the safe genes program
They might be working on some similar mechanism
Limit
Hey
Genetically
Edited cell
And it's
How long you can be out there
That would definitely be under the category of a controller that that we're developing our we do have some generation
Encounters
The one thing that I haven't mentioned is the
If there's derivative tools that are made from GM editors
Called Dean drives and this is one of the most power
Uses of these
Is because
What Dean drives do is they ultimately biased the outcome
Inheritance
Where
When Mom and Dad gets
Together you normally have a 50
50 chance of of a gene in an offspring coming from Mom or Dad
But through a gene drive when you
Couple a gene or trait
With a genome editor
That can force its inheritance to near 100
Until when you can buy us the outcome
Two levels that are about
Reach up to 100%
You want to be able to have a way to
To control that if you don't want
Straight to go
So one way you can do that is to
But if you want to keep
Something like a gene Drive local you may say okay after
After five generations and reproductive
Despite Cycles this
Can shut down
And so these are some of the Techno
Write so clearly you you are
Stick in an area of
Powerful by Allah
Some of those who
Forbidden from the beginning of I'm thinking here of Jennifer doudna
Who has been in on this from the beginning it's so she's written a book that I read recently and when you read
That she is both utopian
In
Thinking about
The power of
Tools like crispr cast 9 in
Touring all kinds of diseases and doing all kinds of
Good things but she also
What is inside some
Points in the book sort of dystopia
You are in the middle of this is when you go go out to conferences the promise and the Peril of these Technologies are always part of that discussion
How are you thinking about that as someone who is in a position now to
Direct to some degree
How this research
Ghost
So somebody is once described me as
Surprisingly upbeat for someone working on Gene editing and National Security
But I'm really excited about that the promise
Of these tools not only for addressing an inherited genetic disorders but
The potential for use of the
These tools to eliminate infectious disease in a way that's Superior to our current countermeasures that we use
I look forward to the opportunity
I think there's a lot
To be sad for for biodiversity as well
In terms of
A tool like a gene Drive is going to have to
The face
Natural biodiversity of perfect Dean drive would only work in the system where
An organism's genome is identical
All the way across
Send in any
Some so I think
Reality
Some of the
Piece of these tools is
Is actually going to be.
Challenging to achieve in as long as we're addressing those risks that while we developed the beneficent used
Horse forward
When you think about the work
That you are doing
Now in the
Biological
In darpa's Institution
What do you say about darpa's
Place in the overall kind of innovation
Ecosystem
Because you work in a number of parts of that
Ecosystems
So I think you might have been
Having been at DARPA now in some capacity for about eight years I I can
Absolutely say DARPA is it is Leading Edge and
It's a place where you learn about new technologies new ideas we we have
From industry from Academia Reach Out
Time with Swiss
Concept so I I do feel that
DARPA is a special place where we have Early Access to these Technologies are at least information about
About these Technologies and
Really responsibility to
Look at that diamond and understand you know how could these
Is 4 good
Use for bad and then really be ready for a to address both of those in and out
Appropriate way
And when you think
About tools like
Forecast 9
You spoke about
This tool
Within the context
The program's you working on
But when you think of
Maybe
Best application
The answer to that question
Probably
Varies depending on on who your speech
So I'll
Had the opportunity to be in meetings with patient
For a number of inherited genetic
The ability to create a therapeutic
For an adult individual who has
Suffered long-term
From a disease I think is it in
Incredibly exciting if we can do something to
Can prove that ended
There
They're desperate for those Technologies
Is and
I think yours and an opportunity for
A lot of good
So that's that's one of the things I'm most
Excited about
And many diseases that otherwise have no.
Options at all the religious
Treating symptoms
I was trying to make peace
And the other
Is of course this is when a lot of people points to 44 Dean drive but is the ability to eliminate
Factors that
That carry disease
Says things like malaria or Dengue or Chikungunya as we
Have more and more emergent diseases that that
Are spread through
Actors this is beyond incredible
Tool to implement to
To prevent their
Right and again now we're talkin about such powerful technology so what
CNN debate here
Has been in do we get rid of these
Mosquitoes
The vector is it actual
We carry these things
Which sounds on the surface to be at sounds like a solution but on the other hand
And I think you've talked about this yourself we are talking about very complex ecological environment and so even though we think about
That mosquitoes is essentially bad things
We don't know if we got rid of them
What would that do ecological
Right yeah and that's that's something that we have to take a very
Serious clothes
Lookout because we could be opening up a new ecolodge
It's right if we
1 species of mosquito
And there are many P species of mosquito out there right so they say you can be inviting a new mask
Needs to end
Potentially bring in a different
Really this is a
Teachings of the short-term funding for four years there's no open released but we want to start to develop test beds for these systems
Understand how they behave over Generations but it but I think this
Question
Of how this might work in the environment
Ecosystem
It won't be answered
So we can roll
What is it's interesting I often think about the history of Technology
As part of the solution becomes
The problem
I'm taking care of things like CFC chlorofluorocarbons which were a great solution to a refrigeration problem
Early last century
People are dying from The Reef
That were being used
Mcfcu
Come in
You're not flammable.
Toxic then and they become
Wunderkind
That purpose
But then is there made in massive amounts
The same stability and makes them great goes up to the Stratosphere in stores
Why the ozone 7
Become up the great one of the great Ki Mobility
The 20th century
When you think about biological
What is in this context
Next episode the solution canticum the problem
What are the problems that keep you up at
Before you go back to the dean Drive examples it is that retina what are the long-term
Applications and so
This would be a genetically modified organism
Environment
And
We have to be sure that we
Carefully consider how one might.
Please use these toilets not going to be a silver bullet for every
We probably shouldn't have
50 different types of mosquitoes species engineering
Gene drives
It's going to turn into a space junk
Tight situation where we don't know how these individual
Orgasms
Interacting with each other what is the long-term effect on the environment
This is
I don't agree I don't think that's a long-term solution in Fort for me
Part of the safety program end and just at the message that I like to go out there is
Is 2
Do you have that long-term
Thinking in place
Where
And even in the initial designs of the experiments you know what might this look like
Like in 10 years
20 years 30 years will be on the end of a Fisher
DARPA program
So we can build in some of those safety
Switches
Early on at the Inception
Technology
It's heartening to me to know that you were the program manager
Are thinking about both those pros and cons the promise and the Peril of these
Powerful Tech
Technologies
It's going to be exciting to see
Where you take from your existing programs in and maybe some other ones
Janiyah in the near future
Renee is there a
Question that you
Wish I had asked her you wish some of your other interviewers from other
Interviews in the past had asked you that I haven't
So
You can ask it any vinance
One of the questions I I
People do ask me if I want to put a plug here for that item,
Answer this is an international genetically engineered machines competition
This is
A place
Where a lot of
Researchers and individuals amateurs interested in synthetic biology get there
This is a pretty low threshold way to get into
Competition setting to say
What's something cool you can do with
With engineering biology
In the organizers of this competition
Have
Always first and foremost
Biosafety and biosecurity
As part of the
Deprogrammed each of the teams has young students is undergraduate sometimes even Heights
Didn't have to
Address
Safety and Security in all of their designs and it wouldn't that be a great thing for every
Lab to be able to do
One of the things I've noticed since being a program manager is that
People are often blind to the potential
Use of Their Own
It takes somebody from the outside to be able to look in
And
See where where those potential vulnerabilities are not only for just the system won't work in might break
To wow this could actually become
A problem you mentioned biotechnology becoming the problem I think if we had the ability to
Really look
Objectively at each other's work and try to identify those vulnerabilities and then mitigate the risk said that that are
Are presented that would be much more excited about
Forward for bios
Technology
Okay well I think we're about out of time so I just want to thank you for being here
It was amazing
Interesting discussion for me thanks
Sharing these stories about how you came to science
What's motive
The program manager
Thanks I'm instead of pleasure
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices
For more information about Renee wegerzyn the program Sheeran
And the other breakthrough Technologies.
Is working on
DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download it
Go to the voices from DARPA page
Darpa's webs