Technology
The internet
All of your hands
Technology is a driver of our
OurTime
Since its founding in 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research
Projects agency
Has Benadryl
Welcome to voices from DARPA
A window onto DARPA score of program manager
Their job
To redefine what a
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm
DARPA host
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Dr. Joseph
Evans program manager since
Any agencies
Strategic technology
Which focuses on
Mixing and matching
Component Technologies
Do networks of cave of
They can adapt to all kinds of Battlefield threats
Anakin voice surprise on adver
Currently on leave from the University
City of Kansas Lawrence
Where he is a professor of Elektra
Circle engineering Inc
Computer science
Joe bring Siddhartha interest in advanced networking and Communications technology
Especially if he's applied to large
Skill Wireless Communications and data links
In ever more networks battle spaces
In everyday living
In the private sector Joe co-founded Net game
Games USA
A network gaming
Acquired by Microsoft
Mm
He also was a partner
Chief scientist
Ascend
Intelligence
Who developed the tax
Tactical ground reporting system
For DARPA and the US
This system
Was widely deployed
Anorak in
Delp Warfighter
Weirdest
Joey's personally on sightings
Find the system
In addition to many other professional involvement
Joe flies planes
Skippers boats
Runza
And plays guitar in
Including many years ago
In a band called
Nasty
Brutish
In short
Dr. Joel
Welcome to the studio
Thank you
Before we talk about some of the programs we run
With names like
Geospatial
Cloud Analytics
Shared Spectrum access for radar
Communications
Secure handheld
Resilient
The Tactical Edge
No more mercifully
By the ACT
Cher
I would like to
Know something
About where you're into
How did you get into
Twisted Insane
Science
Engineering and the elect
True magnetic Spectrum which as I look
Folio seems to be
Lancaster may be hereditary
Grandfathers were electrical in
Auctioneers
As my father
Were involved in various things my
Grandfather my mother's side was involved in
Electrical engineering for
Public projects ladavian
Yo
To work for three-letter agencies back when you couldn't say the names of those agencies
And
And and then on my father's side is involved in early broadcast
Sing back in the nineteen
20s
What is Radio is
Is really new and becoming a
Exactly and so many others been the sloth long-standing interest in radio
Engineering spectrum and then Yellow fast forward to another hose
Is a kid today
Exposed
Science fiction Star Trek and things like that in the 1960s I remember asking my father
Yeah could we make a something like the communicator in the garage and you know
No well no that's like
Too far out there you can't get the components a little balls of the tour that small and then
Fast forward to the 1990s and suddenly have a flip phone that looks like a
Star Trek Communicator
Yeah I think I've had this long-standing interest in those types of Wireless
Lowes Topix
And it's been wonderful to watch through my career highlights
Technologies really evolved the point
You can do some of the
It seems like
That were science fiction
Even
Kids you were really a
Knowing about Ray
Hearing it used
But knowing
Something about it
Everyone at 1
So what I would love for you to do
Talk a little bit
Spectrum I've always found it
To be a kind of miraculous thing
Spider-Man
It's invisible
We have no sense of it directly bodily
And yet we can
User cell
Turn the radio on
All of the stuff
Is going on now
So when you think of you
Is in your mind
I think of it really as a as a
The shared resource like the air if you might want for that
That way they have the ability to
Communicate through this medium
Obviously there's a lot of technology behind the
How you didn't build RF devices and Enzo for radiofrequency devices
Really in the end it's a it's a shared resource that we can use
For various things like Communications radio for sensing radars
On those tight types
Two things and it's something that I think as
The technology Sioux Falls we can be more sophisticated about how we use that that share
Resource
All of Me
The RF Spectrum
I will
Say it is pretty ethereal but it is one of those things that you have you you kind of have to
To visualize how the sharing is going on in this multidimensional space
In order to make you so that more more
Smartly
Watch the kingsman good excuse to
To to start in on
Some of your program
Including one
Program because in some ways
The technology you seek
There
Is trying to make
The invisible
Visible train
How to make
What's going on in the elect
Acro magnetics
Visible so can you talk to me a little bit about
This program which
Is that the tail end right in transitioning
The Marine Corps
That's so
This isn't a nice example where you can sort of talk about the original
Idea of it
It's status now when
Advanced RF
Nothing is really known by the
Name radio app that's it slid the shorthand we use for that program until the radium at program
Is really trying to provide that basic Spectrum situational awareness what's happening in the Spectrum
As you say it's lit its invisible unless we make it visible through
Computer visualization
Olson so
I'm it's a mix of
Sensing what's a out there so turning existing
Radios things like that into RF sensor so you can see what's actually see what's going
Only one in the Spectrum you can sample
What's going on in the Spectrum
You bring that back over tactical networks in our case
Is that the Marine Corps
But you bring those back to essentially
PC think of a laugh
And you run some algorithms on it and generate a visualization of what's happening in the in the
The Spectrum at any given area
In any given area and so if you may have
Military units operating in a particular area they
Generally many of those Marines Are Soldiers
Have radios
You use those radios as your sensors you bring back
Yeah all the measurements you can from that area
To that location where you can run the algorithms and generate
What looks like a heat map of colored visualization of what's Happening
In that geographic area in the Spectrum
The map shows you how much energy is there by the color of the of the map kind of the way that you do
Signals are different
Tell how strong the signals are if you think of like the weather radar that you see you know on the evening news
On that type of visualization is the way you used to look at the Spectrum
And you can see here what essentially what's
Radiating hot
In your area
And that may be of interest you may be curious about what that is
I'm so we can't we have a display that shows Seattle kind of here's what's happening over all the Spectrum
And then we have a display that shows you okay at this particular frequency at this particular part of the spectrum
Say the frequencies where the Wi-Fi networks are
You can see where the hotspot
You can see how they are radiating away from there
There they say
Situational
Ernest Rady
I can look around in
And see if there
Maybe their adversaries like
At military assets
We have an adversary's might have
This is has always been sort of more of a
Invisible sort of
A set of phenomena
As a war fighter if I know this
Now
Muhammad Ali
Says I was a war fighter it's it's very valuable because you can start to identify maybe signals that you did not expect to be
They are so a particular example that we have from some Marine Corps exercises was a lance
Scorpio was simply really that they playing with the radio map display
And I saw something that was unusual and it turned out to be the sniper team that was out there hiding and not visit
Otherwise other than there are at Spectrum emissions us are using there their radios
So they're things like that that that allow you to identify what's happening
I'm in the Spectrum and then you can decide if that's militarily important or or not you may decide
Well that's an odd signal maybe I should send somebody over to take a look
Things like things like that
Are possible course of action that you're
You're presented once you can finally see what's happening in the
Nerf
Sucker right in the radio map is getting to what we
Think of you
As one of the best finish line
Technology development
Graham can get to it
Which is to say
You're going to hand this off
In this case right side
To the Marine Corps what are the next steps for that tab
What we're doing with the the Marine Corps is working with them on
Some of these various exercises and and
Experiments in
In parallel the Marine Corps has been very
Forward-leaning in Spectrum operations
Um Spectrum operation
Since they have been adding it to their Doctrine
They have been looking at techniques procedures
How they might use the electromagnetic spectrum in a war fighting sense
And so they've been for leading on Helen
Some of these ideas of if they have the technology
And so what we're doing dark has developed the technology and we are transitioning it
To the Marines where they can then start to use it
I'm in in exercises first and then in the in the forces we roll forward so
They have you know identify this is a key technology
That will be inserted as they roll forward in there
Budget planning and their program
Let's let's talk about another program that is when not as far along
About to be
Detransition
Yet this one goes by and acronym Spark
There's two s's in the front of that essay
Sparcc
That stands for shared Spectrum access for radar
And communication
This does relate to what we were just talking about specially in the sense of
Where where are they
There's a very busy
Electromatic magnetic Spectrum which
How to say where
Kinds of
People and devices 1
Kind of have access to that
So there you are exploring something called Spectrum sharing maybe we can just
Talk about that
Concept
Becoming ever more
Important sure so one of the issues with the spectrum is that it is very heavily used
You can just think of you were cellular your cell phones they are
Using more and more of the spectrum there's Wi-Fi your millions and millions and millions
4 Dirhams water Wi-Fi and sell cell phones
Pretty sure it is
Answer there are there there's is heavy use of the RF Spectrum
That is a new modern phenomenon
If you look back in the
Yam 1960 70s even the 80s
Most of the RF Spectrum use tended to be governmental and Military
And so the the Advent of cell phones and then
Laptops and
IPads and so forth with wifi-connected refrigerators all of that has started to
Did you really be the dominant use of the of the Spectrum which means that the military has to
Adapt to having less and less freedom to to move in that spec
And so one of the things that we're doing in the spark program is looking this idea of sharing
Between Communications tactical Communications and even maybe commercial Communications
And Military radar
We have looked at the
Ladies Radars and how they might interact
With reuse the same Spectrum
As LTE cell phones and in some Spectrum bands
And all we've also looked at how military systems can share with military sis
So for example we've done some things that I have transition to the Army
Where they're developing a radar that will use the radar
Free communications with other radar sites
Oh and so there's that to get improve radar overall system
It's other things like that were that's smarter use of the
The Spectrum
Enables the military to use less
And the commercial world has this constant pressure that it needs more spectrum because of
Used by individuals and
The individual consumer
What in this this sounds like it relate
Its 2
Awesome work
That colleagues in the Microsystems technology office
Are working on I'm referring here to the Spectrum collaboration show
Which also
Is really all about trying to bring this whole idea
Spectrum
Sharing almost like a new ethicon how to use and think about the Spectrum
Into a material ey
White contacts
You know where where you been
The radios
We'll have to get smarter
And I know what's going on
Absolutely going back a little bit in my personal history
In 2003-2005 I was a
Program manager over at the national
Science found
And one of the things that I started today or was program looking at
Taking smart radios and doing dynamic
Access
Listen to might not have heard that term before smart radio can you just
Usher for so so smart radios really a software-defined
Radio in the sense of the radio
Characteristics it
The frequencies that uses the
Types of waveforms that sends over the electromagnetic spectrum
Those are all the find my scroll saw for familiar
Am and
Amplitude modulation frequency modulation at the at the lowest level Defenders
Yeah you can think of Wi-Fi
Why is being a have having it at
Subway for mother
All of these
Different types of waveforms
Canby
Basically implemented using software these days
Because of the the vast increase in
Computing power available
As well as improvements
The RF device
Radios capable of doing
Exactly
And those capabilities are getting smarter and smarter more and more
Capability is being jammed into
You know it's smaller and smaller handset
Yeah I'd like your cell phone
Tactical radios
In the military
So when I was at the National Science Foundation at NSF started this program on dynamically accessing this
Spectrum
That is using different frequency bands
They are essentially
Share the Spectrum were more intelligent
That was
Academic work
A lot of that work has matured to the point where that starting to show up in
I'm chips and systems that can be used
Throughout both the commercial world as well as the military world
MTO with a Michael
Patron XO technology offices helping to
To move that
Wave of Technology forward
By making better
Devices and creating
Better techniques
Through things like the Spectre
Challenge
Me to wear
They're looking at different
Techniques for sharing
There's definitely been a a movement throughout
Academia industry
To try to make the the
Spectrum access
Play smarter
And then we traditionally.
On the traditional way of accessing the Spectrum were
Has been
The traditional bureaucratic top down
Types of ways of managing
The Spectrum the FCC
Normally would say you get to use
This
Frequency
This time
Under these conditions
And what we're talking is making this
Is Almar
Fluid solo
My all of these connected
Devices
Can can figure out how to
Make best use
Of this incredible resource
Absolutely
Play in both the FCC and on the government side there's
The ntia Nash
Haitian
Information Age
AR
Looking at
These new technologies as
Kind of the way you feel * of the
We're hoping that some of these technologies that darpa's developing
Will
Make their job easier
Basically
In the future on the policy
Okay so let's just touch on one other
Rub your program since I know that some of your program
Program Center on
Innovative ways of ensuring access in a whenever a
And wherever
Oppressive in use
Drones
Attwifi
Routers
That sort of thing
Program I want to talk to you back here though is
Called geospatial
Cloud
Analytics
By doing a lot more with satellite data than it has
Has been
Done before
Things like using database
Geospatial
Characteristics
Crops in distress and may be using that to the dated
Predict things like security relevant
What phenomena like social
Unrest that's
So
Talk to me about
Tell me what kind of
Data is available that you're hoping to
Accessing new ways and then how that might be valuable
Some of the Genesis of this idea really.
Major General
Was the
Vast amount of new geospatial data that
Being created from commercial source
I'm so traditionally the
Satellite imagery marketplace with government
Special government satellites taking
Pictures for either military use or for
Things like
Agricultural products
Things like that
Lamps at 4 Mass
Some of those
That's radically changed
Beers with the
Launching of
How many new
Commercial satellite some are already launched summer
I'm in various ages of
Deployment
And
What that's providing is much more data on a
A daily basis
One of those
Ways I like that
Describe this is
Yeah back when darker was found it a comeback in 1958 and it was really founded in response to Sputnik
Being launched
And
Some level of panaca in the populist valteau
Well the Soviets can see what I'm doing all the time they're flying over with the satellite and
And they can see me in my backyard
Well what's interesting now is we're finally getting to a point where there are enough commercial satellites up there
That they are really are going over every day
And imaging everywhere
And it's one of those things that was unexpected I think
From a
Governmental side
What the impact of that could be the the vast amount of new and useful data
That might come from the commercial side
So then this is pictures yo data as they they say like it Optical is a second
In The Biz it can be other things are there are satellite constellations that are collecting RF data is
They they fly ever
Other
Satellite constellations that are doing radar image
As well
Combine all of these are Avast new data source to understand what's happening in
In the world
It is so much data however
That people can't keep up
It is a firehose of data to an extent that never been been really seen before
People talk about Big Data this is
Bigger than big
Data
I'm just in terms of the amount of data that's being collected from the satellite
So people can't keep up I can't look at all this data
So then you have to do automated processing
Machine learning types of
Show the algorithm so you really have to set up the
The pipeline's of
Processing
To get useful information out
Out of all that data
And
What we're trying to do in the gestational Cloud analytics program
Is make use of all that data to set up
The architectures to do that and then setup
CenturyLink business model so that
DOD customers can get that information rather than just the data
I'm in a in a sensible way so
The geospatial part of the GCA of the geospatial cloud analytics program
Geospatial part is all the new satellite constellations all that new geospatial data
There is the cloud part which is well you need
You put it in the Computing clouds the
Yeah I hear about Google cloud and Amazon web services those
So becomes widely accessible and then also can be processed at high speeds
In those Cloud resource
So you can
Actually
Crunch through all that data in the cloud
In order to produce a result at the back that then a Warfighter
We're kind of where the analytics come in
So I imagine that the ideas
Reply on Linux and various kinds of models where you
Triton lconnect
Redis raw data
The things that are even more interesting than raw data which is
What it might mean
To the conditions of crops and how
That can lead to
Food security or insecurity and then
Groups of people are behaving
Exactly so it's so for example one of the thrust we have is looking at Food security
And understanding what is happening in particular regions of the world in terms of how the wheat crop is devel
Doll thing over over the year
And a circle using these new data sources that are so much
Phresher
Then it ever was before using that new fresh state-of-the comes in
Daily your
Maybe weekly in some cases but
Much more frequently than in the past
Using that
2 then
Crunchbase analytics algorithms that predict
You know that this crop is going to do well this year or this crop of wheat is is going to be poor
In this part of the world
And what we
Seen over even the past few years is
That crop failures can lead to social instability
The Arab Spring excited as one of those examples where that was kind of the spark
That led to the Arab Spring
And so if we get our a little bit of more advanced warning maybe we can improve stability
Why you no identifying
That there may be a need for
Going to a particular parts of the world or at least EOD can position itself so that it's not a
A surprise
So that's one of the challenge problems
What's in the geospatial and
Another one of our problem areas we've been looking at is
Illegal fishing
There's a real problem in certain parts of the world with illegal in the unlicensed
Fishing
And there's also nongovernmental organizations looking at this problem as well but we're using that
As a way to try to identify when
Vessels Maybe
Showing out the in particular
Territorial Waters where their unwanted
So we're trying to use the program to explore that space and really push the low
Limit of what you can get from this
Geospatial commercial GSP
Right now I don't
Usually think of the defense department is as policing unit
Fishing practices around the world so can you just
Explain a little bit about how that connects to what might be a DARPA and DOD interest
Sure and Enzo in the in the case of illegal fishing it is a also a good
Proxy problem for General
Maritime situational awareness types of a problem so you know the Navy may desire assistant
Understanding of what vessels are in a particular area and kind of large-scale
I want to know where
We are all of the
Traffic is in the Pacific
And so these new commercial data sources are providing a way to
Ring together
Satellite imagery
Radar satellite data
Things such as a is which is one of the beacons
On
Commercial vessels that say I'm here in this is who I am
There are various things like that they can poop be brought together
Just to improve overall the understanding of what's Happening
In the maritime just last night I was looking at
Add a website that tries to track
As many of the aircraft that are in the air at any one time and uses something much like an assist
One of those Beacon
And here I am systems I was amazed to learn that at the moment I was looking at this
Realtime website that they were 14000 aircraft
In the air
At at that moment so so this in some ways is a little bit related more than
Kind of contact exactly Enzo in the maritime contact
What's the trick is
That if a vessel doesn't want to be seen it will turn off it say I have speak and
And so then you're interested in using some of those other
Data sources from the the satellite data and so forth to understand
Yeah well there really is a vessel there it just turned off its Beacon right now
Doesn't mean that you
Exactly
Okay so
We're kind of getting toward the end of our discussion here but I
Because you are someone who is experienced in Academia of experience
In the government that NSF before
Coming here
If you have experience in
The private sector
You're somebody else a kind of interesting view on the overall
Innovation ecosystem and symbol
Now that you're here at DARPA
I'm just wondering what you know what you are discovering about
Where a place like this
Fits into that overall
Innovation
Obviously DARPA has been on the Leading Edge of of Technology
Before
Decade
Certainly I've been
Working on and around the internet for most of my career and DARPA
Was that out there first in terms of networking
Tat technology
So it's both LED the way and opened the doors for four things happening in the commercial
A world
And I mentioned yeah the Spectrum sharing work well
The same time as
I was at NSF working on on that
Throws another program manager over here at DARPA working on similar issues and we
They would work together
The moves that that technology forward so
It's it's always been on the Leading Edge
One of the interesting things to me coming to to DARPA has been really the opportunity
You understand
Even more death than I thought I had
The specific needs
For the millet
Been very eye-opening what you know what problems there are that need to be solved and
One of the things that's been
Phone is putting together programs the kind of address those
Their specific needs
It's so dark of both those are the kind of
Move the technology forward but the other part that's been very interesting to me is
That doctor really I believe is the key agency in terms of military innovation
For the Warfighter
The
Opportunities to
Think about
The
Kind of big problems
Facing
The department of
Defense facing the military
As we move forward I'm not sure where else
You do that other than a place like Garba
Are in addition to your work as a program manager as a
Professor
The University of Kansas
I mentioned
The introduction of these other
Experiences
Pilot
I saw a picture of you
Look like you were skipping Abode and actually pretty scary
Conditions would like to me you think these kinds of Interest
I have some kind of
Influence in the way you
Think about you
Electrical engineering
In about how you do
Do your program manager
I do think that one of the
Things that has been helpful from those experiences coming to a place like
Like DARPA is that the opportunities offered to a program manager are very much like skippering a boat oar
Flying an airplane in the sense that you have great
Freedom to do
What what you want you operate within the limits of the technology whether it's the airplane or the
For the sailboat but you upgrade freedom to kind of set you work
And I really do think
But that's
Yeah wonderful
Opportunity work
Since you've been here in Washington have you been able
Get get into a plate and
Wise Guys
Around here not so much with all the restricted airspace around here is this is probably the
The single most challenging place in the
In the in the country to
Can't go for
Fun pleasure flight
Russell near a lot of water and we're nearly Lauder I've done a little bit better on that and doog occasionally get a chance to go
Gosick
And I'm happy to hear it there is one biographic detail that I find particularly amusing I mention
Literally right before when you were student Princeton
Yuan somebody's were in a band called Nasty
Short which you know is I
Saxifrage
Tom Hobbs
One of the less optimistic or pessimistic views on life
Century thinker
So
This does not represent you if you want
Absolutely absolutely not pretty
Maybe it was more describe grad school then
The wonderfully Fun Band
List of characters from the air
Ended up his
University
The president of a university Provost and I think they're
Senior technology
Cheerleader at a place that does business with DARPA so I won't mention it but
DARPA program manager
We are really you know just a few minutes left is there anything
About
Technology
General about
DARPA
About your programs that did not
Come up during our discussion that you think would be of interest to Arla
Just a general thought
And that is
One of the other things
It's really been one
Careful about being
Starbucks
DN
I'm seeing the
New idea
Folks in the in the Sciences
Technology industry
Are working on an end bring in and dust
Discuss with
Hey a broad Vision that that you
Don't really get in a lot of other
Parts of either the
Academic world war
The commercial world
And the thing that really comes through from that is
That as much as technology has evolved in as mature as some
Ideas are
There are still you know vast opportunities out there for continue to innovate
Really has been
Experiencing that in
I'm seeing all the other the new ID
Still
Yeah I mean I did that just makes me think of
About you know the some hundred program
Is here and when you really think about
All of the kind of
Individual Technologies their developing we are in this era now
About almost a kind of a mix and match
We were you get into a permutation game
This is what strategic
Technology officer
Is kind of about
Where all these existing Technologies
Can come together into amazing diversity of
Assemblages
Absolutely and that is
One of the wonderful
Are the systems off
Carpet glue
Turn all the office
Is that you do get to
CDs Technologies across the board that are helping to
Are provided
Capability that will make
Make the difference
For the US
So it's
It's really
I'm fun to to see how you can put those
Individual innovative ideas together
Create an even better in a pee test
All right well you've given us a bit of a snapshot about you and the work you're doing in this
Teacher technology office so we just want to thank you
You for spending this time with me
Baseball thank you very much really really enjoyed it
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again
For the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about Joe Evans
The programs he and his colleagues run in the Strategic
Technology
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA
Stop mail
And four links that enable you to download this
Podcast
Go to the voices from DARPA page
Underpins website