Technology
The internet
Palm of your hand
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been
Welcome to voices from DARPA a window onto DARPA score of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is
Is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your doorbell
Host
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio Jonathan Foust
A program manager since 2015 and his information innovation office
Jonathan earned a PhD in computer engineering from the University
Cambridge in England
But along the way here in degrees in electrical engineering Computer Engineering in brain and cognitive Sciences
All for the Massachusetts Institute of Technology
Jonathan epitomizes darpa's deliberate blindness
To traditional this
Disciplinary boundaries
In search of new research and development territories were perhaps some of the most consequential offer
Opportunities
For technology development
Reside
At DARPA his principal research interests lie at the intersection
And of the computational and behavioral and social sciences
So thanks Jonathan for joining me in the studio today
It's awesome to be here
Before we actually dive into some of the really good stuff about how you got to DARPA and how you think
About technology a program that you recently got going
Few other things
I've got to ask you something that
What I learned
About you and your family
DARPA
And I'm referring here to the naming
I love you words
Tell us a little better so my wife is also a scientist so we had a rather long and lengthy discussion about name
Algorithms and how you
Depending on the gender of a child you make
What are consonants you might want to talk valve
And then we also being scientist
Started to think about names
The scientist
Maybe match some of those criteria soap
We named our children Tesla in Ferriday and we thought very hard about that because it's pretty nerdy
And we want to be able to also call them Tess and Farah
Should they want to tone it down a little
And just how have your daughters responded to having such unusual names like they've loved it I mean we made a point
End up going to the Royal Society in London with Faraday where they have much of Faraday's Regional Lab
Put Menthol in a really nice small
Not very busy Museum
It's been a lot of fun
So I don't get an opportunity there to tell the curator
Is very positive LOL sometimes
Tesla that we do get asked about the rock band
And occasionally about there's I don't know you may have heard there's a car company
Important part of that story of courses who was Nikola Tesla's
Hero
And Michael Faraday
Beautiful connection
So I have to say that's quirky but I say that with great affection
It's a it's a sure sign of your motion to science
So what's actually not talk about
Your background I mentioned the degrees that you had gotten
Would like to hear about that those interested in how you ended up at
Actually
Getting in
Opportunity to work here
Wow yeah so I'll go I'll go way back to
The Apple II Plus
And my father with some sort of give us a date point on 1979
Father with with some great insights and no personal computers we need these in our house
And
I don't know if you work all these old magazines like bite magazine you would type in
Programs in which type in
Computer games
And I said that I said Dad I want to make my own computer
And he said
Here's the manual sun
Plugs it in front of me
And next thing you know ice
Programming
I started to fall in love with computers
Later once I got to
Undergraduate I'm sitting there I was fortunate to overlap with my sister at the same University
She was studying cognitive science this is amazing
How people think
How they behave what are the motivations for
That's fascinating that's what I want to study
And she looked at me and in a way that holding older sister can instead
Jonathan
You don't do computer science
You're crazy so I did both
And that's been my career
DARPA
Did you know about it and seek it out
Such an amazing place
That it's hard when you're in a
Field doing research and development and leading other people and doing it
Do not know about DARPA to not know about the amazing things that DARPA has done
So for me it was it was very natural to say
Well I can imagine at some point
Appropriately in my career I would love to serve at DARPA
Expendables
For five years of my life you're helping
Arriving at DARPA there's a sense of
Incredible empowerment
That with the wherewithal that you got
To really make some extraordinary things happen not just
Oh I'm going to run a program but no I'm going to write a seminal book with the best people in the world I am going to
Changeable discipline
It's an amazing feeling
And when you do all of that and you tie it back
2 National
Security +
Feeling like you're serving your country at
It's a great feeling
Yeah when one of the things I find
A most fascinating
About DARPA
Is the sort of melting
Of disciplinary boundaries which is not so easy to do with many other in
Institutions you go to a university in
Typical you're still in the biology Department of Chemistry Department
Here goes kind of boundary is almost irrelevant because it's much more of a
Project
Directed
Approach you could you sure
Oh yeah I mean that part of the superpowers you got us a DARPA program manager is you can you can
Remembering my sister grabbing my ear
You should
Think about this other if you can grab people by the ear and go I've watched this field for in my my case 25
Sears
And it's absolutely ridiculous that these people aren't working together or there's a huge opportunity
If I can bring these p
In the right way
And that's what we try to do
All right so let's talk about
How your own mindset is changing now that you
Shakira DARPA
And we'll move from that come into the program
To rub up the momentum
So you made it your mission here
Focus on
Hard drive
One of them being a modeling of large-scale human behavior
Lightweight computer
I would like you to first talk to me about your
Views about Aaron
Christian connect
Global Information environment
And how that's guiding what
You hope to achieve here in your tie
I get so excited when I think about the fact that people are interacting
Ever increasingly
Computer-mediated fashion
Now I have this opportunity
Through these kind of computer-mediated interactions to study human behavior
At a scale
It's never been
Done before
And what's exciting
People are starting to think about that world so you'll see some behavioral scientist using Mechanical Turk
For example
Actually most people would not know what mechanical means
So Amazon Mechanical Turk is a
Crowdsourced
Platform so I could say go to Amazon Mechanical Turk and I would like
Toupee
200 people
To do some simple experiment which is
Just to say you know
Click on this card box when you see it
Type of experiment or
Collaborate on a project and let me watch how you doing
So
In the social sciences there's been a huge uptick
In people using this particular platform
It's just one
Think about the fact that
When you call Uber
That it has date on the drivers
Have data on the people that are getting picked up
Think about Facebook
Think about the fact that they have millions and millions and millions of users
Around the world
Taking two interesting studies of the differences between cultures
That we could never conceive of
At that scale.
It's an incredibly exciting time for the behavioral social
Right and just one more Moment On The Mechanical Turk
What's fascinating about you for the name of that
What is it associate
A famous
Example of an
Otamatone
On the mechanical
Turk with the Kinect
I think Amazon's original Vision was
A Mechanical Turk where
It's not with a human inside
Tennis with a chess-playing automaton at that
Center of all kinds of discussions when it first came out in the University was revealed to have a few minutes so what is the
Is that there are
New ever-increasing opportunities
For interacting with humans in a way that would let us understand
Not just how they're going to act
A particular instance but what are the the kind of causal underpinning
Of those behave
Why do people act in a certain way insert
Situations
Interesting soap
I think that's a good segue into a discussion
About
The program that you have begun
It's called the computational
Simulation of online social behavior program
No in a short format
As social Sim
You've described
This goal as developing Innovative Technologies
4 High Fidelity
Computational simulation
Of online social
I'd like you to flush that out
What are the things to point out
When I
And rattling off these opportunities about understanding human behavior is understanding human behavior is
Hard and I
Far from solved problem
So
We often joke we wish we had the easy problems like the physicists do
Humans are tough
So this program is a fundamental research program it's not saying we're going to successfully model human behavior
It says
We're going to try to start to to chew the elephant
We're going to get our very very tiny teaspoon and start to nibble at this giant problem of
What can we understand about Behavior
The goal of this program is to really start to tackle
The issue of creating valid
Simulations are valid models
And there's a lot of folks
In the modeling world who will build beautiful models
And
Not do such a great job of proving that they are correct
Then there's people who will go out and do behavioral experiments but then don't bother to codified that and then some sort of Pop
Habitational represent
How do you think about bringing all of that together in a way where you can say yes
We built this model we built this
Habitational simulation
And we know
For some circumstances
It's it works with some level of actors we know one
We have things that are right and when we have things that are wrong
Right and you're bringing it again
This massive ability
To scale up
I should say the scale up in a massive
Because you will be tapping in and it sort of Mama's crowdsourcing weigh in
By reaching out to the social
Media channel
Absolutely so
One of the things that's
Different today is this notion of scale that we
Have all of these
Computer-mediated
Medication
And
If we can do
All of the appropriate
Privacy and ethical consideration
Which is things like informed consent
You must ask someone
You're going to use their data
Can we then look at this data in aggregate
We're not talking about individuals
Here were talking about
@scale millions of people
Decide
We're going to spread
A piece of information on
So we're going from online social behavior
Potentially a very big
Phase 2 of relatively simple Behavior which is
The spread
That information
So why would you
Tell me you just saw a great movie
What motivates
How does that happen and can we look at the
Various factors
Surrounding that as a function
Which environment are we
Is it something that you would tweet about it
Something you might post on Facebook
Can we do that as a function of
Information itself
What kinds of information are more likely to
And can we do that as a function of the properties of the population
This is a population that really is very connected and likes to spread information this is a population that's more disconnected and does
How do all those factors interact
And how can we
Study though
And say what we actually know and how well we know it
If you were trying to make this a little bit more concrete for listeners
What kinds of questions
How do you think
Do you know you will be asking
King of the researcher
She will be working
I'm with you on this social Sim
Program
That's a are either relevant to National
Security or other
Societally important
Yeah so I think one of the things in this program we're really focused
On is
Societal benefit as it relates to National
Security so what's what's a great example of this
US military has a mission
Humanitarian assistance and disaster
So when there's a tsunami or flood or a typhoon and
Foreign country we may be asked to go help
And one of the things we have to combat in those situations
This is
The spread of rumors for exam
So
There's a recent story about a rumor spreading that the bottled water that the US
Military was bringing
Was containing line controlled substances and they were going to
Use it to control the population
Patently false
But it led to a lot of people getting very sick
Because they weren't
Drinking Safe Water
So there's a very concrete example if we could understand why that particular message got traction why it spread the way it is
We could maybe help a little bit better and such situations
Now I guess moving in an in an ashen
No security directions there's a phrase I've read maybe on your program page
That really catches
Mayan
And it's resolving conflicts
Out
Force
Which sounds like a
Terrific ideal
Talk to me a little bit about that and the relationship
To the kind of working
Yeah that the
US military
Is very very good
At
The kinetic
Parts of operation
In fact arguably without peer in many ways
And I just want to point out for listener
A bikenetic that means things that are moving and you can think of it as metal moving through air
Among other things
The military also tries to think about operations other than War
So
When we get into these humanitarian assistance
Situations or we are trying to
Advise
Local Force
About what's going on
There's a lot of opportunity for us to make
Huge difference
Without
Metal moving through air to use your phrase
That seems like a very very Noble goal
To me I want that I get very passionate about anytime you can save lives without
Having two
Be aggressive I think that's important
This
Makes me understand a little bit more
About you and your passion for wanted
Come here
And having you have some sense that it
Is possible for you too
Move the the actual sort of
Practice of warfare away from a kinetic and and bloody one into something that we're we're again,
What's the result
Forsen
And what comes with it
It's hard to not come into work in the morning and be passionate about
That kind of
That kind of statement okay course nothing is easy so the kinds of research that you were doing and which you were you're scaling
Hang up your looking at a massive amount
Social behavior
By way of social media so this is where people
Are revealing things about the moon
Their ethics issues including privacy
So how are you thinking about those issues as you move forward in your program
There
Front and center at a level that I don't know that it's been pushed
So far in front and I'll tell you why
When you
Study the behavioral sciences
And you go through here's how to do human behavior experiment
I keep thinking about Bill Murray in Ghostbusters
Where he's doing the the shock test
With the to see if people have ESP or not
He's breaking every ethical rule there is
That was very humorous but
When you do behavioral experiments you you have to get
Informed consent and that means you have to have someone opt into doing this you have to show that there's minimal rescue
You have to go through
As a behavioral scientist I'm like
Okay
Now if you turn to the computer scientist
Westworld
They don't but there's just data
Thursday. They're like a whip there's data that's about human beings or coming from
And therefore privacy protections are
Paramount
A fun fact I don't know if you know this but if
You look at what is in this end-user license agreements that you click through without reading
There are things in there that give companies
This notion of informed consent to mess with your date I never read
That's where we need to provide some leadership we need to say yes if
We're interested in people's data and we want to understand Behavior
And we want to do the science
Of of behavior
We have to respect that from you
So we've already run privacy and ethics Workshop
We have
External privacy Consultants that we work with
Other programs that are for that are focused on
Making sure we address privacy
It's interesting to DARPA is known for
Breakthroughs in technology but it almost sounds to me like you might be moving toward some new territory even when it comes to
Consenting and these kinds of privacy and ethics issue
Absolutely I do know art director has said
It's not just our responsibility to prevent or anticipate strategic surprise
From a technology standpoint
But also from how we actually conduct the research and development that gets us.
I want to just talk a little bit more about social semi but I'd like you to do
Jonathan is is give us a service status
Where is this program at in its life cycle
And I'm going to
Askew
To get utopian
Imagine
The best success
So you can imagine what the program but so
First to satisfy
We have completed
Source selection which is to say we received a number of
Pretty amazing proposals
So now we go into the process of
Forgetting those folks
Under contract
And getting the program
Off the ground
And then as it gets off the ground and over the next couple of years
You're as we call our R&D Partners performers
DARPA
What is your what do you hope in several years when you bring the performers together and then you're you're having a
In a moment of Celebration that the
Program is completed what do you help with
Be the payoff the deliverable
A fuel changer is a changing the way this kind of research and development is done I don't think we are going to end up with
Here is a correct model of how information spread I think what we're going to end up with
Is a research community that
Much More rigorously Much More scientifically
Conduct
The process of building these kinds of mod
And everybody moves forward from that point out
To the huge
Massive possibly unbounded space of understanding human behavior
Right and one of the things that's really fascinating about human behavior and I think how your
Treatment program in thinking about it
Is that social structures are
Hierarchical wewe U&I Jonathan right now we are having a conversation this
What's a social structure
To Ben our audio engineer is with us so there's three people in our social structure in the studio
But go up from there at Unity so because we didn't go to neighborhoods we go to cities we go
All the way up to a global Community right so
So there are
You are in one neighborhood you're also in a town it's not necessarily all hierarchical cuz you also maybe in the group of
Fathers you may be in the group of Americans you may be in the group of people that live on streets called
Edison Street
And when you think about those different
Categorization
What can you learn
Apart from in the social behavior of each of those
And that's one of the interesting challenges worth for trying to think about in the program is out of those different
Let's call them resolutions are scales at which we can consider Behavior overlap and interact
So how does your
Identity as
Bother overlap with your identity as an American
Overlap with
Your identity is in your age group
For example
So they overlap they interact they may dominate in different situations
How to lose
How does operate how do we understand a small organization differently than we understand whole region of people
So are you in another interesting thing at DARPA is that so often
The Technologies
Is that program a turtle
Are working on
Are powerful enough that they have tremendous promise
But also some potential peril
You don't need some interested in your view of
Again getting utopian if your program really succeeds we develop new ways of understanding
Social behavior
A scale that we've never
I had to
The kind of access
Work
What excites you most about that kind of NuWave understanding and
When you think about it what kind of gives you
Some parts I get
Very excited about the societal benefits
I got excited about
Making sure people get vaccinated appropriately making sure people get appropriate Healthcare
That during crises that were able to guide people in an appropriate way
I feel very strongly that those are the really beneficial aspects
But there's a darker
Side to it as well
Which is I want to be prepared if other nations governments
Groups
Decide to
Spread information that isn't
So correct
And what do we do about that
I like to think about an income of 3 boxes
There's what is the US government going to do
We have a lot of laws regulate
Patients that are very specific about how we communicate
Boats with our population in foreign populations the same as these kinds of privacy in ethics
We also have
American corporation
That may have different rules
They may have got you to click on that end user license agreement
And then we have
Other folks in the world
That have very different perspectives on how you might use these kinds of models of social behavior so
Perhaps there's an oppressive regime
Perhaps there's a terrorist organization
That I want understand
How they're pushing out their messages and how they're creating influence in a way that
I don't think any of us wants
Right now another thing then came in another conversation that you and I
The pad in which you kind of revealed to me that not only are you thinking about
Really large
Scales but you're also
Thinking in
In terms of the smaller
Are scales let's say in
In family units
And the way our relationships information
Technologies
Changing the way we relate to
Each other and to our machine so I'm referring to
The issue of politeness that you're and you have a little bit of a sample
Right in your household tell me a little bit of the story what's your
Observing about how
Children
Relate to machines now
This actually motivated some
Some work that were funding
With my children we have
Alexa and Amazon Echo in our
They liked it
4 jokes
I also like to ask fun questions like
Alexa what's the smallest thing in it in the universe
Alexa
Which is pretty cool
Don't say Alexa play music
And then they'll say Dad
Get me some juice
MSA
Wait a second
That's not quite how you should speak to your father shouldn't you say
Please
And that led me to think quite a bit about etiquette and there's actually sociological models of etiquette
That describe where and how we use
Phrases like please and thank you
And to me this is a very natural place to go when you think about
Depression spreading why does affirmations
How did those please
Thank you
Help or hinder
The information may may spread
Are you
Asking your daughters to be polite with Alexa
No I haven't but it raises a whole nother conversation about how we interact with
Machines
And do we see machines in the future as
Partners
Teammates
Where do we see them at school
And if we ever want to move beyond that
New Submachine says tools
We have to think about some of these sociological
Principles of how we interact
Okay so that actually gets to
Another question
A big one that I wanted
To ask of you
So you're talking about
How machines kind of our evolving along with us and
When I think about
Robots
And artificial intelligence annies
Kinds of convergence
Coming together yeah there are discussions out there about what happens
If we
Develop artificial intelligence
Tools we develop robots where are we
Almost want to say or we do want to say
These are new types of
Being
Ethics comes in here in a huge way
If this is the case and it was never going to be thinking about machines
Do we have to
Think about what their rights are
I know you think about this a lot and I want you to
Tell me and our listeners how you are thinking about
Sure so let me just back up from the notion of Consciousness first
And let's talk about emerging
Emergence is a kind of fun word because if you start thinking about a society Society
Is something that comes out of a bunch of individual
Pretty interesting that something that
Is it planned for can can appear almost
What does a surprise that we have this
Organized Society in the physics world or the chemistry world I should say the properties of water
Emerge
Out of hydrogen and oxygen both of them gases in
Normal conditions
Neither of those has properties of water but when then combined in a chemical reaction
The Forum water then you have the emergency
I just want to
Connect what you're saying emergence in social structures actually has a kind of correlating absolutely and if you go to termite
Mounds and you go to ant colonies you see this
Yeast
CDs amazing emergency
Properties
It leads us to ask questions about
Artificial intelligence
And it leads us down a path
Looking where there have been emergent
Interaction so if you follow the notion of flash crashes
On Wall Street
You have automated trading system
Operating an a
Regulated environment
Competitively
End
Occasionally they interact in a way that's
So we have to ask yourself
If we're being honest
Way to say we can't always anticipate all of these
So with all of the discussion today that you hear about safe AI
DARPA I think needs to be thinking
10 years old
50 years out
Sing
What if there's something more than simply safety that we need to
All right we'll Jonathan I'm glad that we have a program manager like yourself was thinking about these things as we all
Go off
But without knowing how the future can unfold in an hour
New interactions with the massive amount of people in massive
Machinist
You're so so you're asking really fast
Fascinating questions this conversation has just been fantastic and I want
Thank you for Assurance and
Of course I'm happy to share
And thanks listeners for sharing your time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about Jonathan Fouts
Is social Sim program and the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download this podcast
Go to the voices from DARPA page on dark web