the embedded entrepreneurship initiative
is you know like anything else at DARPA
it's a
it's an experiment we have specific metrics that we have to hit and
you know every year we'll continue to measure its value, we'll continue to
iterate and learn to optimize this model for impact
and at the end of the fifth year then
whoever the director is at that time
we'll we'll take a look at it and see if it's really helping us achieve the DARPA
mission of creating new capabilities
that are in the hands of the warfighter and national security end users
It's that last bit that part about getting technologies beyond
the valley of death and into the hands of war fighters and national security users
that EEI is designed to make happen more
often than it has in the past. There are
plenty of business and technology
accelerator models out there Tech
Transfer Offices at Universities try to
help faculty license patents or get startups going for one there are various
business boot camps that promise to turn
technical teams into business wizards in
three to six week programs venture
capital firms bet on winners and feed
those chosen companies various levels of
funding and sometimes business expertise
to help move concepts toward commercial products and services
Gerst says DARPA poses unique challenges
when it comes to accelerating development
in the innovation ecosystem
DARPA is
very early stage you know we're taking
things from
idea often to you know proof of
principle or
first prototype and really understanding
what performance can be gained and that
in business terms that's pre-seed stage
So it's unique in that it's very early
DARPA is
unique in that most of its portfolio
focuses on the
hard tech, deep tech space that you know
materials science, biotechnology,
microelectronics that take
a long time to mature.
A lot of the original business accelerators were designed for software
and not hardware and definitely not material science.
and and then the last reason why it's
unique is that it's very
high risk but potentially high impact
and so
the result of that you know in my world
is that you don't see
many straightforward business models
where DARPA has you know developed a
technology that's just slightly
incrementally better from what's out
there today and it it nicely fits within
to the existing system
you know the existing market system and
the existing supply chain often DARPA is
going after things that have off the
charts performance that have the
potential to to really upend the
existing market structure
that require new thinking around
business models and partnerships
sometimes DARPA develops some really
unique things where we're thinking oh
this could create an entirely new space
a new industry and that needs to be from
a commercialization standpoint supported
in an entirely different way and so
we designed this program to uniquely fit
the DARPA model EEI came out of the
gates in a mad sprint
following a pilot stage the initiative
began ramping up to full-scale status in
october 2020 in what is initially
planned as a five-year institutional
experiment already EEI is engaged with
more than 50 research teams each one
with big big plans we have
54 research teams some of them are still
thinking about if they should become a
company
some of them are in a corporate research
lab and they're you know investigating
the hypothesis that there's a compelling
business case here and trying to
determine if they should spin it out or
license it but
54 unique technologies that we're
helping plan the path forward for a
typical EEI effort begins when a DARPA
program manager a pm approaches Gerst
and her colleagues at DARPA about a
research team of scientists and
engineers that the pm is working with
and that has a great idea that might not
make it through the valley of death
without the sort of help EEI can offer
the central pillar of EEI's model girth
says is to provide funding in the
quarter million dollar range for
embedding a seasoned and vetted
entrepreneur into a technical team for a
year or even two years the embedded
entrepreneur adds crucial sober business
and commercialization insight and acumen
to the optimistic and often idealistic
technical mindset that the researchers
bring into the mix it takes both to get
promising technology into practical
shape manufactured and into the hands of end users
here's how Gerst explains EEI's special sauce