Many of them are involved in war fighter performance
everything from sleep to
vaccines to making sure our guys
if they end up in a far away place and
get exposed to
unusual things that we can detect it
that we can actually make sure their
bodies are are capable of responding to
it in unique ways we are working with
operational biotech supporting our
troops in physical structures
Can we
create novel structures to as you land a
helicopter to decrease the dust in the
air using biologicals some nutrients
that coalesce(合并, 烧结的结) the sand underneath the
helicopter and keep dust down
can we create artificial reefs to both
land on and protect against global warming
Can we
make bricks
in faraway places without cement and
lower carbon footprints and creating
coalesce aggregate materials and low carbon ways
of doing this
each of these is a specific company and
a specific
embedded entrepreneur that we have
supported
In addition,
some things that your listeners may find
slightly odd.
We support individuals who are
bringing materials to
agricultural uses
in the conversion of materials that are
contaminated(被污染的) with such things as
mycotoxin(毒枝菌素) into
high quality ingredients(成分) by feeding
through insects(昆虫)