Stealth technology, the Internet, GPS in the palm of your hand, autonomous operation
Technology is a driver of our times
since its founding in 1958, in the midst of the cold war, DARPA, the defence advanced research projects agency, has been a driver of technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA a window onto DARPA's core of program managers, their job to redefine what is possible
My name is, Ivan Amato, I'm your DARPA host
And today I am pleased to have with me in the studio Mr. Paul Thomas,
known since his day one as "Rusty", because he arrived in the world with red hair.
Since september 2017, Rusty has been a program manager in the agency's tactical technology office,
which has a penchant (爱好) for pursuing audacious vehicular technologies for the air, space and oceanic domains
Already, Rusty has made his mission at DARPA to do what he can to develop new concept that will deliver more resilience, global reach and network connectivity, by way of new space systems
Rusty, join DARPA from DAQRI, an augmented reality services company, even though it does like a cocktail where he served as the executive vice president for global operations
He also held positions in a slew of commercial space companies, among them SpaceX as orbital scientist,
he has been in on the design and management of an amazing portfolio of space related programs, including the SpaceX dragon spacecraft,
the DARPA micro satellite technology experiment, or MiTex, the Iridium Low Earth Orbit satellite constellation and the US air force geo synchronous space situational awareness program
His initial training for all of this came in the form of a master science degree
and aerospace engineering from the University of Texas, Austin,
and a bachelor of scientific degree in astronautical engineering from Purdue University after I say, wow, let me say to you
Paul "rusty" Thomas, welcome to the Voices from DARPA studio,
Thanks, Ivan. It's great to be here today.
Thank you for having me.
Before we get started on your life adventure, on the forefront of space technology
I want to let listeners in on something that will not come through in your voice or words
At six feet, eight inches tall, you are among the tallest
people at DARPA, though we are markedly not even the tallest
It does make me wonder though, how you managed to fit into those thin shell when you were on the Purdue crew team
And if your fuel costs, when you fly your own Piper Dakota plane are higher than it would be if a 5'8" guy like me were the pilot.
Well, yeah, so it does cause me a lot of pain on airplanes these days
That is, that is true.
But I'll tell you, being tall was great I grew up in Indiana and I learned to play basketball for some reasons, I was kind of good at it because of that
So being 6 feet is a good thing over all, and I'll take it.
All right, well, one of the things I always want to hear from program managers who are with me in the studio is
where they got their start
And where the interest came from in science, engineering and technologies.
So I would put that question to you.
Okay yeah, great, when I'm an aerospace engineer
as you said, and like a lot of aerospace engineers, growing up in the 70s, early 80s, really saw what NASA was doing. My grade school had
has special readers where you can go and see the history of what NASA done even back in 60s
And I remember what was the point over those in great detail when I was a kid.
But the real kick for me became a career day that my schools have been made great,
where they actually pulled my father in, and I realized my dad, mechanical engineer
and his grandfather, his, my grandfather, his father, a civil engineer,
had been doing some pretty interesting things are entire career,
and they were staying on the cutting edge of of what was going on my dad's work for General Electric in the plastic industry
when that was getting big in the 60s and 70s,
and my grandfather worked for northwest and put in all the air fields
And when they are doing the Orient, pacific routes through the, through the 40s and 50s, he also helped design the LaGuardia Airport,
so had two generations of engineer behind me and at that career day
I actually have my dad was one of the people presenting,
and he walked through the different types of engineering,
and at the bottom of a list was aero space.
I did not know that was an option and all of a sudden clicked for me
that aerospace engineering is something I could do,
and I could focus on it and continue on and do what I thought my dad was doing in terms of, in terms of really innovative
things and in new concepts that could be set forward
So with that, I was in state for Indiana and Purdue was a great school
So I jumped at the opportunity and got accepted there
So while at Purdue we had quite a few amazing professors, one of them
Professor Andrisani would give us talks about how you could do no better in your career
as an engineer, especially if you stay on the cutting edge and advance technology advance what humanity can do
Look back at my head
Those words have run with me
for the last 5 years, kept moving to
where is the most advanced technology and
how can I help the most.
Well, those sound like two great lines of influence
I mean, you know, a dad, a teacher like that
And wow have you went with it.
so one of the things that I would like you to do here, is to take our listeners on a kind of Whirlwind (旋风) tours,
you can't really dwell (详述) too much on any one thing you done
I mean, your CV is just one of the most amazing documents I've ever read
[Thank you] But if you can take us for a Whirlwind tour on your experience in the commercial space.
Commercial space, absolutely. so I did an internship at a small engineering services company, and we've, I've got to work on NASA with with a space shuttle back at late 80s.
But what really got me going to commercial side was right after graduate school,
I got the opportunity to go to Motorola, it was firing up the Iridium lowest orbit
constellation proliferated (激增), lowest orbit satellites that were cross-linked and providing global connectivity in her planet
And this was a large constellation. - very large, 66 satellites plus spares (备用)
So the goal was to build one satellite per week and launched the entire consultation of of 70, 80 satellites, including the spares in one year
Never been done before
And to do that, we're gonna use a large number of launch vehicles, and Motorola has never designed a spacecraft before
So they put all that together and and back in
80s, 90s was this happening
The motorola had really good plan
They pulled in a lot of experts
They pulled in subcontractors
like Lockheed and Raytheon who were experts in this area.
They put together the team, and we ended up building at a rate of one spacecraft every 4.3 days.
We launched from 3 continents in just over, in 8 days, 14 satellites, we launched off all the satellite in about 18 months.
And actually before you move on to some more of your commercial space experience,
I remember just talking with you at another time
when I am perhaps I think was on this project, you already in project which took around the world to some of the other space cultures out there, like in China and an in Russia
So I'm just wondering if you can compare and contrast a little bit of the kind of space cultures,
and that, you know that that, you have experience being part of the hours here, and then witnessing those elsewhere.
Absolutely what the first I noticed is, when you get in the other country,
any other location is doing a Rocketry (火箭学) or spacecraft design,
You really gonna cross it as a type of engineer that you can relate to really well.
the people that do that are very similar no matter what culture they come from.
I was very amazed how quickly you can make friends with
the Russians and the chinese, anybody who was who are actually launched
'cause we were launching on the Protons rocket seven at a time with the Iridium,
and we were launching two at a time on the chinese rockets
five at a time on Delta II, which is our main launcher out of Andrew,
I would rotate between the lanuch bases in California, Baikonur Kazakhstan,
where the Proton rocket was launched,
also would go to Moscow for the integration meetings,
over to Beijing for the Chinese integration meetings in Taiyuan for the launch base is there.
It was very interesting program, and really, I found it, the Russians and chinese.
While Russians invented rockery, as we know, just the same time we did,
China was coming up to curb
They're getting faster as an incredible rate,
They're getting better at an incredible rate.
And I found that both Russia and China
Their cultures were less analytic than the American aerospace culture.
They were very much driven by test, build, test, build, test cycles.
And I found that really in the commercial space here in US.
We're serve pretty well admitted those type of things,
when you move out of the analytics
Don't spend year to trying to figure out exactly how to optimize a problem,
but build something that maybe sub-optimal tested and use that result to go to the next phase
so we see analytics, I think of of, modeling
so one thing we really, really... one area we are really, really good at in the US is very good computers and very good computer algorithms
that that let us analytically predict what a rocket would do under structural load or under guidance, navigation control algorithms,
which is great
but it doesn't really tell you everything that could possibly happen during the flight
Whereas a flight actually does tell you that.
Before we move off of this little a block what you are describing,
this international framework for getting so many satellites up in such a short amount of time.
Share with our listeners, a kind of funny experience that you had
with the Russian team when they were trying to figure out what
they should actually call you. - That's a great joy
Thank you
So, when I started working at Motorola, we would have every other month
We would have a technical interchange meeting
We need with either the Russian launch team or the Chinese launch team
So you have one each month.
When the Russians would come to town or we would go to Moscow,
we would have the stereotypical long tables with all the Russian, on one side,
and all of us on the other side and the translators.
When they asked, and we introduced everybody, they got to me
and I said, my name is, rusty thomas, they stopped the meeting real briefly
and they started talking to translators, and they came back and
said is that your real name? And I said, well, Paul is my real name
I was born Paul Thomas named after my grandfathers, but since the second or third day around Rusty has been a nick name.
And they went back and talk about this
It, okay, we get it, Paul, Parval, that is a good name
We're gonna call you Paul.
And and I said that's fine, some people would call me power, but most people here at Morotola
know me as Rusty, and they ended up in coming back and saying
Well, we're going to call you Paul, and the reason as we've discussed it, and and we don't have a nickname rusty here
in Russia, we don't feel comfortable calling anybody corrosion (腐蚀)
So, so they decided not to call me corrosion
And I was Paul from there.
I had been Paul on and off.
Since since, like,
okay, because of that, it was smooth working team
So now I want to take you back to that Whirlwind tour of your experience in commercial space
that I wanted you you to do
But I took you on a diversion (转移注意力, 消遣, 改道)
So let's get back to that
You, you talk a little about the Morotola experience now moved from the world.
Motorola was great. Then I then I moved up to Seattle following words, the most advanced technology happening.
Seattle in late 90s was, was really happening place for a lot of reasons
They had also a new company that was founded, called TeleDesic has some money coming from Bill Gates, Craig McCaw, tightens in the communication and computer industries.
And they wanted to build a global lowest orbit satellite
constellation, to do broad-band communication, called TeleDesic.
We got pretty far into that design, but the technology at the time wasn't quite there miniaturization (微型化), as we know it today really wasn't there
And the dotcom crash of 2000 and 2001, made it really hard for us to get a financing
So we ended up not going forward to that program,
even though we had got a FCC license for a lot of spectrum
And I had really good chance to be a major success.
And it was at the space of a very compelling architecture
And moved from there, engineering services in San Diego had a really good time of some of the early days of UAV, predetering Global Hawk
got to be consulted down there for the early UAV designes, and then moved to orbital sciences, where I got into the government side a little bit.
And then after it keeping the commercial side going.
after the orbital sciences curb, I went to SpaceX, I was in 2011,
and worked as a senior director for Dragon production, building the capsules that go to the space station
So it has been five years there and had just an amazing, amazing run, putting on those
those capsules up also got to work on the landing legs, and .... play a good part in those historic landings of those first ages.
Right, and just weeks really before this discussion are having now, a Dragon capsule did arrive at the international space station for a resupply mission
So when you see that, I mean, how do you feel knowing you had been part of that
Intense pride, absolutely, that that was at a turning point in how we do...
how we do space missions, how NASA contracts for for things, how NASA moves forward,
the technology gets the cutting edge, develops it and then can move that technology
to companies like the SpaceX and others of the world, who can then use that to build a commercial case
and then allowing us to move on to the next place.
When I was at Space X, we went from doing one rocket a year, one dragon every year, to four, five, six dragons per year
And now the spacecraft was ramping up (上升) to 20, 30+ launches in the given year
It's really been an incredible time to see that
approach to how you do commercial space turn on and become
reality and then become a success, and then become really a major success.
Where it's at right now.
Okay, so you sort of, told the story we already hear of
you kind of growing up professionally,
along with the commercial space sector,
which is just kind of amazing thing to think about.
But you then made a decision to say yes,
when, when the offer came through to become a program manager here.
I'd like to hear that the sequence of events that lead you in this stage of your career from that the commercial activities you been in,
and now here, as a first year PM.
- absolutely. - Program manager
By chance I happened to in the early 2000s and be talking to some friends at orbital sciences
And they said, there was a very interesting program [...] enough, was called MiTex
I didn't know much about it, it was a DARPA program
It was classified what the experiments were it was, oouh we are not allowed to know it existed. The time it was used to DARPA
experimental program to do a demo of the technology,
and orbital was looking for people who had my type of background,
a little bit of commercial, but also had the right tickets so they could do, do the work
And and they brought me out for three-month stint (规定工作时间),
and I would just gonna help do some analysis for that spacecraft
I did some analysts, and after three months, look like DARPA was going to continue the program,
orbital wanted to keep expanding,
so they asked me if I would stay on as a manager
for the, for the design of that. so I got to run the design of the of the MiTex spacecraft.
And so I stayed in orbital for not three months, I ended up staying for about 8 years
And during that time frame, we work through the MiTex spacecraft
I got to do the design and build
We actually took it through integration, launched it
And I went out to Schriever Air Force Base as a vehicle engineer
and got to be on council of flight for about a year and half.
so it was a really good experience
I, It wasn't commercial. Commerical, it was about government
taking commercial approach. As orbital is, was a very commercial company
And and this was an experimental process that wasn't a strict requirements driven program
It was there to prove some key technology that we could use in space.
It was was successful, and I, as very proud of the of the results there,
that kind of got me into what DARPA can do.
DARPA can step into an area where, where there might not be a set need, or a set said requirements are a set funding line
and say this is technology that would really help the warfighters, help the country in significant ways,
and and we are gonna say, we're gonna do a demo, we're gonna proof that this is possible,
the the proof is here, if we can actually spend two or three years and some money
to actually get a demonstration of a running
that opened my eyes to what you could really do outside the commercial world,
but still using commercial approaches as much as possible,
So followed on from there and became a deputy PM on the GSSAP we mentioned earlier
Geostationary (同步轨道) Space Situational Awareness Programme (GSSAP) is air force programming of record
now that is doing very well
It's up in GEO, and it is acknowledged but it has very, very, very good capability, and it is doing, getting a lot of good feedback from the people use it
So the GSSAP program are very successful
And after it got to the critical scientific review,
I happened to have the opportunity to to go to Space X, they were just firing up what I've already talked about that it was
It was a wonderful 5 years at the end of that
I was at Daiquiri during the operation's job of setting up the augmented reality global operations, manufacturing for the what's going to become a revolution
I'm a positive, argument reality's gonna be a very, very big thing.
And just a two sentenced description for listeners,
you might not know what you mean by augmented reality
augmented reality is the ability put on glasses that will augment the information that you are seeing, real information, with computer generated 3D graphics that that actually will float in space
You can put text, you can put graphics, you can put anything you want.
And it was is going to be contextualized around
actual objects in space.
It was not virtual reality where locks you out, and you don't see anything
In argumented reality, you actually have, still see the people in the room
We still see all the objects.
But it's adding information.
And I have seen, I think, a multisyllabic phrase for this, software-defined holographic, light control, is that related to what you talking about?
It's advanced versions of argument reality and DECARY had some of the most advanced holographic light control technology out there.
Okay, so now my suspicion is confirm that you actually are are going to develop this star[..] enterprise at some point in your career.
The holo tech is out there. OK. - So, getting back to how you actually got to DARPA.
That final turn to get me back as program manager became when the concept of the blackjack consultation, which I did not come up with
It was already been formulated by experts here
And we'll talk a little bit more about that right after this
- great, so DARPA contacted me and said, we're going to go forward with a proliferated, Low Earth Orbital architecture
to start to change how we do space missions, right now
We do space missions with very exquisite, very capable satellite,
that actually cost a lot of money, so therefore we can't build very many of them
And the Low earth orbit, proliferated approach that Iridium did, back with the communications in the 90s,
and TeleDesic was trying to do
And other companies have taken it forward, is a different approach to put
smaller, lower costs and and in some ways expandable,
but not as expendable as low reliability
But the key element is small and lower-cost satellites
that are in very low earth orbits so that you can cover the entire earth with coverage,
and like we said earlier, was 60 or 70
satellites will usually do it to give yourself constant coverage over the earth and DARPA
let me know if they were going to move forward with an experiment to try to
move into augmenting what these exquisite satellite can do with a LEO, low earth orbit proliferated constellation,
when that opportunity came in, I came in, gave a talk
and it was a match made in heaven.
because it sounds like through ten thousand people in the world [heheheheh] that seems to tailor made this kind of idea
I really do think in terms of match, in terms of what the DARPA wants to do
with a, what these type of consolations can do in the future.
And in my background is a really good match and
I'm very excited to be in this position.
And its timing is perfect.
Let's talk about Blackjack in a little bit more detail, tell me a little bit about, you know, the kind of the elements of that
And even before we start that, can you tell listeners and me where the name comes from?
Sure, the concept of of a Blackjack that instead of having sensors in space
that might come out of one or two or three this points of the sky, you could potentially put smaller sensors in many locations
Give the destroyers or the surface action group, commanders of the war or the army commanders or air force
anybody could build it to look over the horizon
with a small number of discrete sensors that they actually dot the sky in some ways,
well, if you go to a casino, and you look up, you see on the ceiling, you see all the little domes,
those little domes are all tiny little sensors, and they are making sure that nothing bad is going on, right
So the concept of Blackjack is to follow that distributed sensor approaches as you see  in a casino
You don't have one or two large systems making sure that everything is working okay and making sure that there are no cheating going on in the casino.
And just just for the record for our listeners, we do need to point out the DARPA
does not get all of its ideas from Las Vegas.
we don't get it all, but probably more than we should maybe
yes, absolutely
So the name came from the someone playing Blackjack would have the distributed sensor set around them,
so it is kind of a tongue-in-cheek (随口) name, but, but it was a good name and a good idea crossing
We give our talks at what we're doing
So Blackjack is just as they said a Low Earth Orbit consultation of sensors, that we're going to leverage and
key element of this is leveraging the commercial space as they talk my career in the past is, you can do things very quickly
You can do things very efficiently with a commercial approach,
Now, let's not to say the government approach, how we've procured things in the past is always bad
but in some cases, you don't get the optimal solution, and you could do things in a lower cost and a faster schedule if you tackle in a different way
So what the ideal Blackjack is it try a different approach
use low earth orbit, use proliferated commercial satellites, especially the buses where we will marry military payloads to those commercial buses
and then start flying a large number of them
so you can give that proliferated (激增) global constant custody constellation (星座),
and I say, constant custody, that means for a commander wants to look at a given spot on the earth
He can point the sensor to that spot immediately, because it is gonna be a satellite over head at any given time.
Okay, and you use the words that, in a way we hadn't been heard before. Proliferated.
Just want to make sure I understand what that means in this framework.
Proliferating means multiple points in the space and spread out over the surface, you have to accept an open space, of course
So any person on the, on the ground is going to be able to look up, see a Blackjack satellite,
with the full constellation developed in the sky at any given time,
and that's the end of the reciprocal (互惠的) approach works that
if the Blackjack satellite is always going to be able to see any point of the earth
at any given time.
right, so it's interesting, there 's some aspects sort of GPS-like system,
and that you got many satellites working in a kind of coordinated fashion, delivering amazing kinds of data that would not be possible otherwise.
Here we are actually talking about a lot more than the several dozen [..] GPS,
talk just a little bit more about
the various kinds of challenges that are part of this project,
one of them certainly is, is producing almost mass, producing very rapidly,
a lot of satellites,
And so you had to talk about your experience there, but there's also going to be coordination
There's going to be command and control
What are some of these other elements that you can talk us about?
Absolutely so first, yes, your analogy to the GPS is 100%
That is a proliferated constellation, but it's about at a medium or medium-high altitude
with Blackjack we wouldn't go very low, 500 kilometers to 1200 kilometers,
so arranged that that's just about the earth's atmosphere for these satellites
And and the trick is going to be building such a low enough
You are gonna need more satellites and what a GPS satellite, GPS consolation would need
So to do that, you're going to need mass production and to do that, you have the cost right
You going to need to build them, and on very short time scales
with a minimal amount of assembly intergration and test
and to do that, we're going to bring it as much commercial approaches we can
we've had an industry day, a very positive response from from over 130 companies signed up for the industry day
And we had overturned 75 folks who want to come in and listen to us
So we believe that that approach of going with discreet, low-cost nodes in space
that are almost expendable, not all expendable (一次性), but almost is going to be achievable,
and we're going to use that commercial and commoditized approached to the buses
and bring that to impedance match to the military payloads that will go on those buses also
the other key element of this and you in a little to that a second ago is that we don't,
if we're gonna launch hundreds or or more thousands of of the satellite, we don't want to require teams of multiple people per satellite monitoring them.
Right now, of the exquisite satellites have excellent teams of people on the ground who are making sure everything that that satellite does is monitored
They're gonna analytically predict beforehand what the response of any new script they're gonna send up, that gonna happen
It's an excellent approach, but we really want to get a autonomy into the Blackjack architecture
And when I say autonomy, I mean, how does the mission control work?
How does resource planning work?
How does the payload in terms of what it seem work in terms of, can you move instead of raw data down to the people on the ground
Can you vectorize the information and contextualize it what was important.
Okay, one of the other interesting things about the Blackjack program to me is
because you're not putting multiple billion dollar jewels up there, large just tremendously expensive assets that need to stay up there for years and years
here, you can do what I guess, much more frequent technology refresh, I presume some of them can be done through software
Now you can just wait as we were always upgrading
our various applications on our computers,
but this also does give you some opportunity to, you know,
without breaking the bank putting up actually, new generations of these small satellites and still having them work within the Blackjack consolation.
Yeah, yeah
And and they're 2 areas there that are very important, and we're gonna chase both of those on Blackjack.
first is, if you're individual nodes low earth orbit, your launch costs is lower than going at higher orbits, the weight is less, and the cost of individual satellite is less
So we're aiming for an on-orbit cost of six million dollars per node, per Blackjack node,
that includes a launch cost, which means that if you have a problem with one of those satellites,
you can launch another one replace it for not a huge amount of money
And the second piece, is the ability to do on-orbit over the year updates of the software
We're gonna put large processors, I call a Pit Boss once again going with a Blackjack approach
Tried the Pit Boss is the brains on each one of the of a Blackjack nodes
It's going to have a terra-flop-class processor on it or more,
and it's gonna to allow us to put a lot of algorithms on space
and not only put a lot of algorithms in space to do the work up there with the edge computers
But it's also gonna, we are gonna launch more processors, capabilities than we need for the first generation, because we expect to get better and
better with our algorithms, and algorithms typically need more and more processor
So if you can, we talk about our work to Space X, my, my boss there also found another company called Tesla, and one of the really gool, cool models of Tesla
is, you have a car, and you might come out and in the morning,
and it's done an over-the-air update, and you have a better car the next day than you did the prior day,
because they updated the software, so I'm going to follow that type of approach,
putting a lot of extra capacity for the processor, so that as the algorithms get better, you get a better spacecraft essentially for free
Although, of course, you have to pay for algorithm update, but in terms of launching a satellite, you don't need to
and I imagine you also have to think about end of service when you talking about so many discrete parts that are in Low Earth Orbit, means, sounds like to me these are gonna be deorbit in some way or another
Have you given that thought?
absolutely, given that thought. And that goes back over the Motorola Iridium constellation, every Iridium satellite has the ability to deorbit itself at
the end of his life, it has a small amount of fuel reserves left.
Those fuel reserves aren't used for anything other than the deorbit,
and has enough redundancy and electronics on board,
so that it starts to have problems with its primary mission,
it can fire the thrusters and bring itself down,
so that approach has been proven successful with with the Iridium in the commercial consultations
We are gonna follow the same approach of Blackjack, and I believe there are numerous FCC filings for mega constellations of communication satellite gonna be out there.
That'll have launched even more satellites and Blackjack, they're going to be good stewards, I believe, of low earth orbit also, and put in the ability
So that is a satellite ends its operation, like all get replaced with a better tech refry for satellite,
it will immediately turn on the thrusters and deorbit and burn up,
usually over the south pacific or somewhere relatively benign (不危及生命的), the satellites don't make a back down
They burn up in the high atmosphere during the re-entry and make a wonderful shooting star
If you happen to know where it is [haha]
So as you think about it, this is amazing to think about this is all the pieces, and you can have additions of a program
It is either one or two things about it that stands out in your mind, as maybe, particularly a rich, even we're kind of DARPA program in technology speaking.
yes,  - and logical speaking
Absolutely, so that the biggest reach, I believe, is the amount of autonomy we'd like to put on this spacecraft
I've given a metric that if we lose the ground control,
Let's say we have a comms problem, or the some type of interference and satellites aren't talking to the ground
I want them to be able to operate at least for 24 hours as a constellation, talking to each other through their systems and managing the resources
, managing the mission and still providing whatever in the fact
or our set of information, the warfighters that the people downrange need without that ground infrastructure,
so that could be interesting, and I say the matric is one day, but really, my stretch goal is to get 30 days continuous operations
without talking to the consultation, while it still performs its primary mission to whoever needs to have that information that is generating
So putting that in the place is also significantly leap forward from the current operations
We have an operations control center at ground, making sure the satellite health and safety and the mission is being managed properly to one, or you don't even have a human being in the loop
You moved the man, you go for a man, men in the loop to men on the loop.
the people do in the management are there to make sure and watch and adjust priorities as necessary of course, but not there to make a second by second or minute by minute decision
I have the spacecraft operate what they do, that's a really hard but ...
So a fair amount of autonomy but always with human beings
there as shepherds and in the loop in someway. - absolutely
- so you're a first year program manager
Typically, program managers are here for several years, three to five
I have had people here in the studio of who have done
several tours of duty as well
So people like it enough to say they come here
They do one tour of duty, they go away
they come back.
I'm just wondering if, as the first time program manager, with a program of this complexity and size,
what do you think this one program is going to be enough for you to satisfy your, your technology interest, and just because it's going to be so hard to do
Or are you already imagining taking on additional programmes?
I'm actually already, imagine taking on additional programmes
that goes back to my theme of how to get to the most cutting-edge element of whatever you do in a career,
Blackjack is gonna be a major program, I believe, it's gonna be a huge success, and it's gonna really lead a pivot (支点) to low earth orbit
But once you start working in a low earth orbit regime and once DoD and DARPA start working and putting these systems into place,
I can envision many other programs that will leverage this type of architecture and that success will come out of Blackjack once we build this global mesh network, this, this mesh this internet in space, space ARPAnet.
How can you use it to actually benefit the people on the ground?
And I think that's lot of programmer
and I just, I just want to point out to listeners that, even though Rusty, is talking about a program like that, it is,
it does not mean that it is automatically going to become what he's gonna have to really jump through a lot of hoops (磨练), and come into a lot of people and that's something worth doing
So this really is essentially glimmer on the eye
become a program, so that's one, I mean, it sounds like you migit have even more idea
Yeah, I, got a few, I I I have been spun up with augmented reality on what you can do with light control, holographic light control is an area of high interest to me
I believe that we are approaching that point where the Holo Dex, or in other words, not reconduct things that appearing,
but the ability for systems to a transmit holographic light, phase-control the light and project in a way that you are immersed in a reality that that isn't real,
but it's seen real, because your eye is getting fed the same information
It would be if the object was actually there
I believe that type of light control just around the corner,
and there is a good chance going to revolutionize
how we do interaction with computers and interaction with even people in the same way that the transistor revolutionized how we do computers
And I think that's are coming the next five, twenty years, and I really hope to get DARPA .. move in that direction
as you released in the potential applications of that training just poped into my eye  - Training is a huge, in fact not just training
But if, if you are deployed, if a military person is deployed, and you can have a holographic surgery
show how to fix somebody in your deployed, or in a very remote area, you can actually train somebody in real time to how to do something, because they can see it in 3D, right in front of them as it's happening
while there are doing a medical procedure, training for welders (焊工), training for other industrial applications becomes, becomes much more advance
of asked if they already done the
Study showing you can train somebody anywhere from two to ten times faster with augmented reality tools and in holographic light approaches
If you, because your brain is, is, is programmed to absorb information from 3D context, much faster than you are with someone talking to you or reading in a book
So you see it, you absorb it faster
So I think training is going to be an area that could be revolutionized.
Another thing just came to mind, what is ergonomic sort of discovery
So you might have a space you want to figure out the best way to arrange things in that space with this kind of technology
be able to test out of thousands different ways, very efficiently, cheaply.
One of my early early crip moves was that the internship we're gonna to work on, on NASA projects
And we will would be developing 3D CAD at a time when 2D CAD was the standard
Computer Aided Design. Computer Aided Design. and that three dimensional CAD allowed you to mark up engineering parts, and and then do fit checks, virtual fit checks,
making sure the parts wouldn't interfere with each other
And that was a huge boom forward. It really changed how engineering design, the mechanical design
I believe the same thing will happen
All we need start doing this with the interactive, collaborative tools that'll allow everybody who walk in and see what's happening in 3D space without even needing a
computer screen [...] them,
and then there is one other kind of technology project that you work, which also just represents to me, just how many thousands of thousands of technology engineering issues there are when you really thinking big
So you also were in on the design of the CRANE operation for mating satellites, going into, kind of, vehicle dispenser components.
right? after just one of the many, many things.
So this was an interesting invention
We worked as two or three of us at motorola, the problem that we had, was that Motorola was pitching the ship-and-shoot approach a spacecraft you finished on the production line
It went into a shipping container, said on a dock [contel], where the Russian proton or the Long March, Chinese Long March, or the, or the, the McDonnell-Douglas Delta II folks needed another set of satellites, and that those launched campaigns wound go and
The Russians need seven
And that was the case
We would call FedEx and FedEx showed up at the Sky Harbor Airport
We will load two or three satellites at a time
They would fly into the Russia
would loaded them up, and then we get them out to the launch base, and we wanna put them on a rocket within a day or two
And and that's obviously not help
I&T is done right now, and it .. satellites we were looking for very fast cycle times, very quick process flow and to do that
We needed to mate seventy satellites that are very close to each other, accurately and quickly
So we put together a CRANE, so I think we call the Swing and twisted eliminator, which mounted to the floor of the Russian integration hall in Baikonur
And every satellite would be brought in vertical state attached to this
And then the Russian, Ukraian, normally would swing these around a little bit, as it moved in, because you didn't have any other neighbours,
you never get a satellite tried next to you, but on the dispensers, there were 7, like wedges, there were all very close to each other
So you had to control the twist and the swing
We got to the point
We can make three of the satellites per day and have all the entire dispenser of seven satellites ready to go after three or four days of processing,
and then they would be fueled and be ready to launch
Okay, so on top of everything else, you are a CRANE guy.
So you know, you're working on things
that many of us would, consider to be kind of science fiction, technology fiction, though you can make these things real.
Are there non-space technologies that you just go nuts about?
Non-space, well I'm gonna stay in aerospace, without the space, Let's go to aero.
And I do believe that the transport of human beings as those planets is going to get to the point where we are going to be able to move at the hypersonic scale,
and in the not too distant futures, not in the area of research for myself, but I'm exceptionally interested
I guess, curious on how we're going to get some new technology that seems becoming online world-wide,
to the commercial space and how we might start moving people from, from, from, say, New York to Sydney in hours instead of the 12 or 14 plus hours it takes right now.
I think the very high speed transport, which I guess that it doesn't hit your mark, because you will probably have to go into space a little bit.
during part of that flight, but I still see some very high speed flight, supersonic, high supersonic speed flight has been a area of interest of significant potential, in the next ten to fifteen years
And I think there's gonna be some teams that are cracking open a little bit.
And so sort of, ironically, thinking bigger than this way to make the world a little smaller in the sense of [...] for any point A at any point B, in a much shorter time than  - That's right.
Blackjack will give you the mesh-network and
communicated at broad-band and for connection that moved the people.
That's going to be the next step up.
So Rusty,
You are technology developer
You been doing that your whole life but you also have taken time to get into the more of the mineset in the setting of the war fighter,
the war fighters who you are trying to server by bringing more capability
Can you just share a little bit with listeners about your experience in that context?
absolutely so I've been a reservist for United States Navy since 2004,
and as an intelligence officer, I was lucky enough to be selected to go to naval special warfare intel school
and actually went out during the surge to Centcom areas, Desert areas with the SEAL teams that help do targeting and high value targeting
We did pretty good job.
We got to go to move, move through are those areas and picked up, but quite a few of the Al-Queda mid-level operatives and put them away.
So for, I still active, I drill down in a little creek on every month, very important part of my life, although it as a reservist (预备役) is secondary.
But I also imagine that, that boots on the ground experience now, as a program manager, completes the kind of Luke for you that not all program managers can have
I think it does help.
The area that it helps the most in is when you're downrange with a special force, special operators, the amount of band with the amount of sensing you can get the distant amount of communication you can do is very limited
You're typically moving data through a soda straw.
And what I'm trying to do, as a program manager here is to give those type of deployed
Sailor, soldiers, marines, whatever they are, the ability to move data at a much higher bandwidth, and to get data from sensors at over the horizon, not necessarily organic or unit immediately within seconds back to where they are at without having to go through infrastructures
So seeing how it is operated when I have been, downrange is really help shape hell, set up the technology to for the future of what DARPA can help you with the next generation.
Well so Rusty, you've taken me and listeners on an amazing tour of, you know, someone who has been the absolute thickest part of these last couple of decades, which is evolving in space technology
so I wanna thank you for doing that
It's really been a pleasure.
Well, thank you
It's been ...  I've had a great career
I'm happy to be at DARPA and looking forward to what the next doorstep to break down
And where we're gonna be, gonna be cutting edge next year.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us, I hope you join this again for the next Voices from DARPA,
for more information about Paul "rusty" Thomas, the programs he and his colleagues in the technical technology office runs
and the other breakthrough technologies DARPA is working on, visit darpa.mil.