The following is a conversation with Dan Gable
One of the greatest Olympic athletes of all time
The bigger than records in metals to Millions he's a symbol of guts
Spirit
Mental toughness
And Relentless hard work
As a wrestler he was undefeated in the high school
Undefeated in college until his very last match
And having lost that match
You found another level
And became a world champion and an Olympic champion
He didn't surrender a single point at the 1972 Olympic Games
As a coach
He led the Iowa Hawkeyes 215 national titles
He coached
152 all Americans
45 national champions
106 Big Ten Champions and 12 Olympians
Including 8 medalist
He's the author of several books including a wrestling Life 1 and 2
And
Coaching wrestling successfully
I also recommend you check out the painting called
The art of the fight
But Mike kopke that you can buy on Dan Gable. Com
And if you visit Iowa
Like I did
You should try the Gable beer
Single-speed Brewery
A portion of the proceeds
I bought the painting and the beer
Support
The Dan Gable Museum in Iowa
Wrestling is one of the purest Sports
But beautiful
And brutal
We're both mental toughness and Technical Mastery of the highest form
I rewarded with victory
And everything else is punished
With the feet
And ever since lost weighs heavy on the mind of anyone who has ever stepped in the wrestling mat
The same is true
One of the greatest wrestlers in the history of the sport
The man who graciously welcomed me into his home
For this conversation
The legend
Dan
Cable
Be true to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things not because they are easy
But because they are hard
You're persistent I love that because you've been trying to get me on this podcast for a long time
And until I saw you
On another podcast
And you said you were rushing
Did I call you back
There was over
Because Russia to me you know is leading the world in wrestling
Almost every year
What's the difference between American wrestling in Russian wrestling you show me this painting while it's a mighty it's science it's science
Yale and
They really study the sport they're really good technically they're really really good in strategy
They Don't Really push like
The real toughness they don't push like
Conditioning
Right and so Americans we need what they have
Russians Niva we have and when you get to two together
And for me
Why could beat the Russians is because
I went away a little bit
I kept my toughness
But you're known your you're known for your toughness
And I wasn't known for my art
I wasn't known for my science
So when did you become a bit of an artist
It took a loss
Celerion block because I 181 straighten the dominant 7
And not just winning but you don't care.
Punisher
People gas and
From from that point of view yeah I might have been pretty good but I had a long ways to go yet
And I didn't
Really realize that or I should have said I should say
I didn't
Really know how to get it out of me until I had a loss and then I realized I got a buckle down
Learn some of that science
Become more of an artist
How do you become an artist
That's the Russian way has this
Drilling technique
Thousands of reps
How do you how do you think
You work on the science to Artpark
You got to study the best in the world
I think Dave Schultz was our guy
In America that probably
Showed us that
Being artistic
You needed that and he studied that he went over there as a high schooler
And Russell and some major tournaments over there
And he saw their ways
He use that Russian science and then he
Was already in American
And he saw what
How I
Trained athletes he saw what I did in the Olympics solid other people
How we held up
Any applied that as well but
I have to say he has more the artistic type he was more of a Russian than an American when it came to
Wrestling
You've coached
45 national champions 106 Big 10 champions
And 8 Olympic medalist
Which is incredible
What is a Common Thread between them
And
What are
Maybe some of the fundamental differences
I think the Common Thread is
That
They all had one of those two avenues that we talked already
Can because we intertwined them
So in a Russian wrestling room they got the same people
Most of time in American dressing room are the same people
But what I was out recruiting
At first I recruited just attitude
But I needed more than that
I needed some
Genetics in that wrestling room
Actually
That hard work people
You know they can look and see
Wow
That execution
That's unbelievable
But yet
I can beat that guy
After the first minute
So you think
You think the art the the technique
Is genetics a you're born with it you think it's nice I think your pop and your speedo your ability to
Remove a timing and timing and
Your quickness and your strength
You know the Russians
Late
Usually picked out
The people that can go into that sport
That was the old fashioned sports car
But it it's it's mostly like when you see when you walk into a rest Russian dressing room
UCM hitting
Skills
Techniques
You don't you don't see him against each other that much
Silver
You might not see a bunch of Sprints you might see him walk over to the
The ropes
And they
Drop down from the ceiling
And they'll jump up and climb a rope and then they come down
And then
They don't jump right back on
They got three or four other guys go and then they jump back on where is
I probably made my guys climb get right back down climbing right back again
But
I also realized
That
I had a mix of that what was the role what was your role I mean those guys looked up and Dan Gable and
What was the role in helping these athletes become their best
Is national champion in first of all prove that you are
Knew what you were doing
In terms of technique or in terms of everything they just
You had to be the first guy there in the last guy to leave and you had to be the most dedicated guy even though they were the ones that's trying to win the
Having ships
You had to
Prove that you're going to work just as hard as they were as a coach
And what does that look like what do so you can see it when you
You know it when you see it while you're there ahead of them and you're
There after they leave simple
I'm picking up after him
And you're analyzing them
You are welcome
You're welcome
And you don't think them
Incel use that type of strategy in overtime
When you prove it works
Because
Some of my
Kids that were the best kids in the world
Really
Should have been a wrestler I mean there weren't very coordinated
But they work so hard to develop
Themselves
What was your role in that process I mean that means pushing kids to their limit
If you're not going you can't push this to their limit and even when you push them to their limit
That's not their limit
Cuz their limits above and beyond that I mean
Yeah
Coaches sometimes accidentally don't
Palouse kids
Because of the heat because of
Hard work and all that you got to know where to go in the back off
You got to read your athletes
And
By that I mean you got to know him pretty well not every once in awhile you make a little bit of mistake but if you don't react right on that
A mistake before it gets too far
Then it's going to be a casualty somebody dying necessarily
But maybe something that could turn them off
Or maybe something that can run them away or maybe something that
Wow that was close to it maybe should have pushed in that far
So you really have to be very educated
And it's not just
What you know
It's what you know about them
And I'm not talking about the team I'm talking about each guy individuals yeah you know it
How you see in their eyes because
The first one there your last one to leave and and you said in the environment with him you're there for in the morning
Practice sometimes you're there in the afternoon for 2 or 3 hours
After practice
You might have a
A hot rumor
You might have a sauna or steam or whirlpool
And you get in there with them
And you listen
You know you're not just feeding out information
You do that
But you're taking in a lot of that too and I'm telling you when you get in an atmosphere
That they're relaxed and they feel comfortable massage
And that's after practice in one of those
Areas that
People around you learn alot
I mean you got a lot to learn as a coach
And when you get in that atmosphere when you all of a sudden you feel like very comfortable
Word start flowing
It was those words flow
You take a man as a coach and there's something probably going to be said
That you can do an act upon that's going to help
Certain situations
I've saved a couple gets lice for sure
That were on the brink
You know sometimes performance is at such a high level
You know high-level atmosphere
Life and death is actually
Involved and I don't mean pushing a kid to worry it just dies
But I mean he might feel himself as a failure
Then you may go home and take his own life
Yeah I mean but that's part of it you putting
So much heart somebody's blood in the heart and sweat and every year your whole meaning of life becomes
Winning so and sometimes it's so hard to lose within that context
If you know I think the first wrestling life you wrote about Chad zapotal
Who
Lost I mean incredible wrestler
But lost in three finals in the Nationals in has his tattoo
Pave Hawk hauling out the human heart yeah
So what lessons is there any lessons
From
The incredible wrestling he's done but also the incredible suffering that he went through
On himself again you like that we're suffering and which is okay
Okay so I have to turn that suffering
Ring around
What he makes
And feels good about himself
Are better
Does not feel perfect
Cuz you could lose
And so but you have to actually
Get him to realize
That yeah he's still unique
Compared to the Walk of the earth he was unbelievably unique
Raise the top just a little bit short of but because it was
You know he felt suffering
You now have to go about and change that in
Put into Goodwill some way and because he's you really have a lot of good well you can do a lot of good well
Cancel
It's not easy
It took him probably
Years
Years of tattooing
Years of covering the tattoos
And
Yeah he told me multicolor Iva way moving to California because he was here for a couple years after
Is rusting was done because he had a good job around here and he's
I thought he was doing a good job but you just
Should I had escaped you know same as a cut wrestling tattoo had a wrestling terminology I have to get
Need to say that I have I hate to say this
I go where you going
California
Hey Google is there a reason why you going to California
Because that's where
Everybody goes to hide
But I said
I think it wrong everybody
You know I think
What will determine
Your life will be what you do for now on
If you can find a sexy turn it around
Exactly he went someplace that he thought
He can fit into
And I think you did
And I think he's got a good job and he's helping people
Covered that tattoo with the
Feathers
Another tattoo
Well in the end it's a beautiful story
Yeah there's it really is afraid overcoming
Yeah and he's
Not done yet
Is not done yet
It's a lot more to do
So you mentioned Roger Bannister
Again I thinking your first book somebody looked up to
That's the man who broke the 4-minute mile
When everybody said it was impossible and when thought it was impossible it would die it's not cute
So what
You done your homework
Bought the book for what you've done your homework
Sitting here but Putin to do research
So what
What's lessons you take from that story for yourself The Impossible trying to accomplish The Impossible
Well The Impossible Is Possible
It's just that simple
Time changes things
I mean
I mean if you look at
What
What are the mile time is right now
Compared to that 4 minute mile
Which one it was broke by a couple tensor 3 or 4/10
It's not broke by
Another 20 seconds
I mean it by 700 people yeah people and
It's pretty much the common Ali's are you got to run a four-minute mile if you're going to go somewhere now or or below if you're going to win
Events
It said major level that you got to be able to do that
And so if you can take that and you can look at what
In time history
Has as its
Record performance
And you can realize that
At record performance
It's going to change
And they don't take it to all the factors
Acknowledge
They don't taken all the factors of
Better shoes
They don't take it all the factors of
Better understanding in nutrition
I mean it's like me as an athlete
I went to practice everyday in high school for
At least
My sophomore in my junior and part of my
Senior year and all of a sudden
A new rule came out
The rules are dumb
Before that said
Diesel motor coaches
How you feel
We don't drink in water practice
And
Gave wife cuz you got to toughen you up as a weakness
Water
And so we would go through practice I mean and you're sweating and then you're sweating so much that
You're almost out of sweat and so
You're mostly at the end of practice you're not even wrestling excuse me
You're sitting against a wall cuz you're tired
So then all of a sudden
They say okay
Call drink water during practice print Gatorade during practice
It all of a sudden at the end of practice we're still out there competing
And so
I look at my career for 2 and 1/2 years where I Junior High to
So I got another three years
Or I didn't really
Wasn't able to push as good as I could because
I just
Who's Bobby under
Yeah so what so but at the individual level
In terms of the impossible
When did you first believe
The thing that maybe probably people would laugh at your boss that you would be in the Olympics
Champion
Well I always
Visualized me being the best you believed it in the very forever
Forever
Yeah I was
Because I was
I don't need to call it a dreamer or somebody that
I was just involved with competitive Sports at the YMCA from
H5
Did you tell people that dream that you're going to be an Olympic champion Monday give me the best in the world I think they knew
And the only reason why they knew cuz there was something
Build-A-Bear about this guy
And he was swinging baseball bats you know what's 6 + 7 + 8 + 9 + 10
And he was swinging baseball bats
So much right handed and so much left hand with nobody even there throwing the ball
That all of a sudden they walked by and all the sudden the grass was down to dirt
So it's like
They saw me on the yard
Playing by myself Sports
Oriental we are you get the neighborhood kids you play a lot but if they weren't there
You know if you want in my front room I was hiking a ball like I was a quarterback and I was running not and run
Through the
Do the furniture
You know who saw this guy mostly was probably the parents
And the coaches at the YMCA level 2 junior high level they saw this guy come first and
And end up last but
I wasn't that great
I wasn't the fastest guy at that time
And
I wasn't as strong as guy
You no answer before I went to the Olympics when they tested me they tested everybody
And I probably came back with one of the highest scores
But it was
It was not like the highest
Person on this and this and that
I was all high across the board straight across the board High
On every one of them
But it was always people that were higher than genetics
But then they would go down
They never test on something else and go back up
Mind-state High all across the board
And so I really didn't have too many flaws
I didn't have any
Things that also said that you were going to be
Unscored upon at the Olympic Games
Alright so take me
Through that day if you could
1972 when you were gone for the 68kg
Freestyle Wrestling gold
Discord
Seven points found correct
I had zero points scored on you
0 Sol
Maybe
I take me through the almost the details what was your routine what was your process what was going through your mind your thoughts of that
Yeah first of all
It was quite a day
Because
Everyday
At that time
And we wait in 2 hours before the start of the competition
And saw that is mean that you weigh in 2 hours for your Russell cuz you didn't know whether you going to wrestle right away or later on
In fact in that day I don't think I Russell's a until
Later on in the evening so
Had all day to recover but I didn't really need it anyway cuz you don't know wasn't really
Pulling a whole lot of weight but just
I was just interesting
What was in your mind what were we thinking when you're nervous for you I was confident
I was confident how you knew you were going to win the gold
Yeah I know
But
In reality
I'm not I didn't know if I'm a cocky point of view
I only knew it
Because for the last
Three and a half years
I've been going to practice
I'd be winning every practice you felt good I hardly ever lose it if I lost it
Somebody scored on me
It was like
Too bad I couldn't sleep until I
Figured it out
Or if I didn't figure it out
I would fall asleep
And I would be what I would wake up with the answer what I needed why got scored upon
So maybe now that you won the gold can you tell me in the practice from somebody took you down
How do you take Dan Gable down in the rug in the practice room
Because
They were going for one move
All I wanted was one move
Somebody has no practice or half a practice or at least 10-15 minutes
And they were maybe going to score
If they can work it in their mind
But they knew that was going to be their victory
In the practice room
Maybe you can educate me
And that when you go for the Olympic gold
You didn't want to allow any takedowns
So there's no such thing as working on some kind of weird position of week for into something it's important to not let.
May I take down
I like what we're saying before
If something happened and
Somebody scored on me in a certain way
I would go over that situation situation over again
And I would come up with an answer
And then I would actually test it
Maybe I won't go back the next day
Cuz I didn't want the guy to
You do not have some
I don't want him to think that I was thinking about it all night I didn't tell him
But maybe three days later went to wrestle again
I actually had it figured out because
He wasn't able to
Or if even if I was it on to take it offensive move
And I got stopped and didn't score
You know I had to go back
Filter that
But it wasn't something that
Usually I couldn't solve
But I could usually solve it
Let's go back to the Olympic Games so I get up in the Olympics in the morning
And I'm not sure when the Wayans were but
I think I was probably a pound over
You know that's about a half a kilo in 1.1 pounds
Is a kilo cuz we wouldn't kilograms so what do you do with that pain you are soft
Asana there
And I got in the sauna and the funny thing was the morning of the of the
Of the finals
It was it was another athlete in
Lisanna
And it American or no
It was a European
I did I don't remember where she was from
Adoration
Well you know what I kind of think
Was applied
Cuz it was a girl
I just think and she didn't have her top one
Ella
And that was pretty common
And so you know it's kind of interesting
You think back about it
Because
There's some funny things that
That go on
Behind the scenes
In Olympic Games in world games anytime
When you have country gets country and so there's some crazy Stein goes on any of it affect you
Did you it was there any almost stayed too long in the Sun
You lost a little bit over
But
It didn't really bother me cuz I wasn't likes that wasn't like cutting a lot of weight so so
Your match against the Russian the house your life is not to be at two times
Will Champion the silver medalist as well
Is an incredible wrestler
So what was going through your mind
Before stepping on the mat with that guy you beating a bunch of wrestlers haven't had a point scored on you
And you're stepping on the Media serves Russian who you said was
Really they pick the Soviets pics
To beat you
And I know why they picked him because he had a great attitude
So he wasn't just the typical artist
He was a good artist
He hooked elbows like
Star July 11th he's from that area of the world where they have some of those types of moves but
He said he was a Gore
But
I cutting down a weight he lost some of that go
And I don't know if
If you got that's a process you got to
Cobalt
Scientifically
And so you know if you don't do it is it American
You can really hurt your performance if you don't do it as a Russian you can hurt your performance and they already
Didn't really
Do that a lot work usually Russell's await where it was more like your weight
And so by cutting him down maybe slotus
Belief down a little bit. You saw him the spirit was a little bit gone when your face
You don't rest the matches and he was in the round-robin and he was able to go to the finals
But he had lost another match
Actually against in the round robin against the Japanese self
I think
I had already gained enough of artistic being able to finish a match once I lost my match in college
For the last two years I took on some of that artistica
I'll working
I think that he was already
Hoping to win
But he's hoping to win by a long ways because
He had to pin me or beat me by
8 points
To be able to win the gold
And
You know that wasn't going to happen to have any chance of pain is pretty good is it hard to pin down Gable versus takedown
Down
Like have you taken risks where you can pay for them
I can't remember too many that I took
That would actually put me in a danger position
I taken risk but the risk for so scientifically technically correct
That
I wouldn't land in that danger zone
It's like 5-minute lock up and throw you I'm not going to throw you to my own back and Roy through I'm going to turn in the air
Scientific about it exactly I ate all you just
I learned the hard way early on
There was moose from Collegiate wrestling
That you did that expose your shoulders which
It cost me some early freestyle matches against wrestlers
But
I would go back to my
Collegian
Escaping type moves to where I hit a Granby roll where you suppose your shoulders you lose two points every time
But you learn that that's not the system but if you hadn't wrestle much
You would
Get exposed under
Maybe
A desperate situation you would hit it
So you won the gold
Holiday
Feel
You know you have accomplished really the highest
I think it would have I think the question would be how would it feel if you lost the gold
For me just
I already went through that once
Not that highest level but the National Collegiate Championship level my senior year to Larry Owens lawn Larry Owens yeah
And that didn't set well will you afraid of that happening again
At the Olympic level was that you know I really wasn't
But it was why I changed my
Philosophy of training and added
The science
Tific artist type
And I asked if I'd have won that match
Even though I wouldn't have felt good about it even though
Squeaked it out
I wasn't
Feeling good about that match it would have affected me a little bit
But if I don't want it I would have got over it
I mean I'm not over it now
I mean I don't know why I was
Doing this kind of stuff
Right before my badge
Light by that I mean this kind of stuffs
Yeah and I really was a good talker that I mean me and you were talking pretty good right now except for I got a little cold but but
I don't think I could say two words Harley then and
They took takes Wide World of Sports
We want you to be the introduction for our next week she'll so just say hey I'm Dan Gable come watch me as I finish
We're undefeated 182 at all
That's what they want me to say everybody assume you be undefeated
How to take a 22 x
In the last
Two or three times that wrote it out
And I read it and it still wasn't
Like I just said it
Hi
Dan Gable
,
If that type of stuff so it will be finally just close the book has a basket.
But I turned it was my time to Russell
Until
You know you just you learn that
For me it was great coaching
Experience
Cuz that's what I turned into be
You know
I coach for longer than I Russell
Add
I put up a lot of Champions
But you learn
Through mistakes that even in your own career that you had made
You know it's it's it's an Ever learning process
Saint ever learning process
Have you ever been afraid on the map
Does Fear have any role
Do you think
For wrestler
Why must be a launcher fear is out there
And I'm sure that was to my advantage almost every time I'm sure my Olympic finals is really a
He had these doubts he probably had these doubts
And that gays gives me
The edge
And I don't know if I Really Ever
Had fear
But
Obviously it was points and times where I didn't perform as well
Not many but
A few
And if I look back of it look back at it I don't think it was that
American Inn Aurora Rasta
I think it was
Probably the fear of
Not being an artist
As much maybe this guy might be better than me
Scientifically
And you know you're a scientist
I think that got to me more than anything else
I said early on that I want to eliminate
Ever having to worry about getting tired in a match
So I kind of eliminated that so I got rid of that point
And I do think that in wrestling
That is one of the fears
That a lot of wrestlers have
Actually how they feel during the mansion and
Do they get are they going to get tired
And is it going to affect my performance
As a coach that really was one of the things I tried to eliminate on all my athletes
So it was not Fear Factor
But that Fear Factor would be
Put upon my opponent
Which would give me
An edge
But
That's not what I needed as much
I need to just focus make sure that I was doing the right things
And I need my team to be focused so I make sure that from my mistakes
As an athlete or even as a coach sometimes that I didn't repeat them
Getting repeated man
Do you make a mistake once if you can repeat it
It's like
You didn't learn anything
You are go throughout your wrestling career as you beautifully put what's the work so hard that you pass out on the mat
That you'll be carried off the map
So you never did successfully in that's one of the ways you failed in your careers you've never work so hard that you've
Passed out
Have you ever come close do you remember a time you come close to even push to the limits
Exhaustion questions really a good question about
That
Pushing to you collapse
Because I don't have a coat today
Have I said that to my athletes
I don't know I could get in trouble
Because I understood isn't it by the athletes
Yeah they understand it
But the outside might not understand it
Because it's almost like
When you push him to the point where they go collapse I mean to him
And you know that's dangerous that's dangerous we can't have our kid in that
Type of atmosphere but
It's something that's highly unlikely that's going to happen but I'm going to Taylor's many times in a practice
What I pushed myself
To all of a sudden
The whistle blew or it was time to stop
And when I got up off the mat or whatever I was at
And I
Needed water
I need
I needed fresh air
Cuz you're usually a fairly small room with a lot of guys
That the heat rises
And you cannot it's hard to breathe
And that I can remember and I stayed a lot of times not by the door at the far end of the room I can member walk
Walking from the far end of the room to that door and I can remember am I going to make it the next step
Am I going to make it to next step I need air I need water I need oxygen I need to get out of here
It didn't happen often but I can country count for five times in my career that I push myself to that level
Where I thought I was going to maybe
Go out
Every step I was dizzy
Once I got to that
The door I was able to open it and go out
Add water and gets cold water on my face and
Don't know I never really was able to do that
And I think the story is it in a book where my
My daughter
Push the collapse Molly made you proud
Yeah no
Did she
Suffer because of that
Washington get to go to the next
Event
Cuz you didn't she had to qualify but
I think it
Probably helped her to realize because she was winning the race and she was beating people she normally never pushed
But she was at a new level that she had never been before and she only needed about
Five feet finished
And it was just one of those things that
I bet there's a lot of learning that she did there and it probably
Need to realize that
She'll be better but she had to hold up though
So you mentioned in wrestling life
That the Brand's Brothers
Looked up to
Royce Alger who was known for pushing the limits of physical wrestling
But not getting too rough
So how do you find the line between extreme physical wrestling
But at the same time not rough wrestling or angry wrestling
So that line
Between aggression top wrestling and
Anger
Letting anger
Would cause
Less successful wrestling
I think anger would cause you to make mistakes
And actually get out of position
Because I think
Anger is kind of a loss of control
And
There should be a furious type of
Pack
But I think if I cross the line to anger
Then you're going to be vulnerable
Install
Royce
And the brands
Wrestled
To the edge
Through the edge
But when the whistle blow
They stop
And there's people that when the whistle blows they keep going
It's like in a football game
Fight breaks out in south of the whistles bulk
Well when the whistle blew
They they backed off
So that whistle
Was
Something that in a match
That that
Kind of
Gave them the boundaries
But perhaps give you a little bit of fuel
Don't arresting tough the book that you just got for Mike Chapman now the new edition
Talks about Bill Cole undefeated Northern Iowa wrestler
And
How he talked about how my strength speed and abilities thinkware increased tremendously
By just sitting apart from the action prior to the match
And getting into a state of controlled anger
So
Can anger rolling control
So anger could be fuel as long as it's controlled
Right exactly
You had that line
One side of the line you can have an anger
Poor performance in the other side of the line
You
If you go beyond that it's not going to be for performance going to be for
Not performance cuz you going to lose points
It's a fine line there's definitely a fine line
You're talking about Royce Alger you're talkin about Tom Brands you're talkin about Terry brands
I mean that world championship titles are you got Olympic Championship Tyler you got to World silver medalist in
Anna
In & Royce Alger
And that's what I
Talk to him about the world silver medalist
He's haunted by that
Cuz he was actually 20 seconds
Away from winning
When he got beat in the end therefore that's part of the game
And
It's
I don't know whether he's okay with it or not cuz he says after talking about things he goes
I'm okay with it now
But then he keeps talking about it
So I don't really think he's okay with it
Actually make amends
John South
When you really don't do it
I mean it's no matter what the situation even with the Owens loss
Yeah
It still eats world champion
And he wanted to be
I'm Olympic champion he's not who you wanted to be the greatest coaches of all time
It also Heat
You know it's like
Why do I keep going back to it
Because you're not you don't get over those things
It's a royce really keeps going back to it
Even though he says he's fine and
But then he realizes he's really not fine
Because that's just the nature of the game and that's why he was able to win national titles in and make world
Games and stuff like that
Even what's interesting about him and he's analyzed all the people that he's Russell
And a lot of men have one world and Olympic championships
And he's beaten every one of them
At one time or another and he didn't get to that world championship gold living cold
Add
He says it because
They did it so he's he's showing people
That
I beaten those guys
But
Apparently didn't beat him at the right time
Add
So it's still hunting
You don't get away from that stuff
I mean it's just like
Anything in life that's
Really high
I mean it doesn't have to be Athletics
I mean you think I'm ever going to get over
The murder my sister
And you might not even know that
Let me pause for second please you've talked about it you've written about it
So I hope it's okay for me to say that your sister your older sister
On May 31st 1964
Was
Raped and murdered by local boy
So The Echoes of pain and anger from that tragic day
Today Ripple through your life still
Do your resting. Coaching through your
The way you when you wake up in the morning
What is that like
If you can be very emotional to me
Under certain circumstance
And
The mood I'm in
You know it can be
Maybe if I've had a Mountain Dew or or maybe if I've had a Gable beer
Or maybe you could turn the country music up a little bit loud
Emotions come out
And everybody has them
In their life
It's just so happens
You know what brings it out and hopefully it's nothing that you do to the extreme point of
Brings it out for me it's not extreme
I don't have to have any of that really I can get emotional
How did that changes a man
What it did was realize that I was already
Pretty well-developed
Because I was only a sophomore
15 years old in high school
And
I had Parents
That weren't making it and my parents are a lot older than me
And now that we're down just a me and my parents
And I'm going to be around the house for another two years
And they just lost a daughter that the only the only other
Sibling
They were handling it
They they were the ones that were
Suffering much more than me
Even though
I always
Look back upon one area that I wasn't good at was communication at that time except inside the resin room
Cuz I've been tipped off
And tipped off what do you mean
Well they really said that
Something to me about my sister
Just Cause 3 weeks before that that really
Wasn't
Normal or practical
And I said nothing to nobody
You don't
Is there a part of you that blames yourself
Yeah
Absolutely
But I'm 15 years old
And
You make mistakes
And you don't really act on everything that happens in your life
But I can tell you how it affected me if I acted a lot on
Anything that maybe wasn't even of that consequence
I mean cuz I had four daughters and I'm telling you when they left every time to go somewhere in a car or go out with some place
I always said something to him
And they always say Dad you said that last night
Care
What like I love you or like
You driving and drinking her or don't be in a car with somebody that you know of
Of the same nature
Or
You know stay out of trouble y'all don't go be somewhere where you you know you have I said you know how to get out of a car if you
Car goes into the river
Thinking ahead a little bit
Just in case of something
Did happen
And I goes back to that goes back to that walk to school with that
With that young man that when he was talking to me and I just
I took it and I kept it inside me and
Once I found out she had been murdered
It took me maybe
25 to 30 minutes
I told my dad I think
I know who killed her
He looked at me and he just like
Slappy actually
Push me against a car Aiden slimy push me to start my mom slaps me she was going to slap me around little bit but my dad
Kia
He he pushed me against something about this
I don't
For sure but
And I would probably all crying
But
And I don't like. If I was crying yet
Have you tried a lot of Tears since but
But
You know I just said
Hey
I was walking to school
With his neighbor
I never had walk to school with him before
And he was kind of a troubled kid
And he said something about Diane
And it wasn't good
But I
I can Ingles why did you say something
Hi Daddy I just boy talk you though so you don't hug me hug me hug me
And
You know it was one of these things that
It's definitely made me
A lot of who I am
Because there's been a lot of choices and I don't I took the word choice out of my life
And I just like to say I could do the right thing do the thing that's so you should do and so I don't realize it's like
We going to do this or that
Well what do you mean which one is better
Halo I don't have that choice
Just give me the right way to go
And so
Perfect by any means but it's made a big difference in my life
Oh and how I
I handle my life is probably
Give me the opportunity to be married for 44 years it's just giving me opportunities
Do I'll be better in my life and
And I you know I I want to thank a
My sister for that you know it's so
And I think my family was ready to
Make a split
Because of that incident
They're blaming each other and I think that
I was able to help but more than that they really like each other but they didn't really know it at the time
Until I got out of
The House 2 years later
It probably was going on for a couple years until I moved on and went to college
Then they found out they really like each other
When they were alone
And it worked out pretty good but I think them being able to follow me
Not just true
Collagen Olympics and world
But my coaching
So it's the same the same success and Factor
You know the excitement and and all those things gave them a real purpose
And I
I gave my four daughters they gave my wife
Real purpose to be able to be close to
Ollie's champions in championships in
And it and now it's because now it's like is a family of 22
And they're all interested in what
What Richardson in and it's going good knock on wood but
You know it's something that when all of a sudden you got too much time on your hands and you're not doing the competition much
That thing's probably
He'll get off get off track
What do you think is the role of family in wrestling can a man do it alone and if not
Where is family most important
You know you can do it alone
The why would you want to
Yeah
I think the chances of do it alone or much less in the chances of doing it together
I know they say don't bring your profession home sometimes I say that
I never got away from my profession and an awesome time
It's like my house right here
So when I'm moving home
I'm not going to have an office
Cuz I'm not going to coach anymore or I'm not going to be an assistant athletic director for a while
That
Got to do something that
Gives you a little bit of a break not Eunice La maybe the person you're living with
And so I don't know if you looked outside their I got a cabin right on the backyard probably can't see it right there but
What's in the cabin
That's my
House away from my house it's only
30 ft from my house
And it's my office and it's my workout room it's like I got a son of there it's a bed upstairs
If I needed
If I ever get too close and she says hey what you go sleep in the other house
Get the heck never happened but
I do spend a lot of time out there
Anda
It's up
A little distant sometimes
You got to know you're better know your role
And so all the sudden you're a guy that's been gone your whole life from 8 in the morning till close to 7:30 or 8
Goodnites 11 12 hours a day
Then all of a sudden you're not gone as much
Even though you still weren't she trying to slow me down now I'm doing the
Not so much like hear what we're doing right now but when I get in the car and drive somewhere
Are flies somewhere like just last night I just went to bed and I hadn't told her that
This guy called me and he wants me to
Speak for a
You want to build a Nook wrestling wants to
Start another wrestlers in business networking out end up
Delaware because we don't have any colleges in wrestling in Delaware
So I see that's my life
So
But then all of a sudden I didn't send you my wife until all the sudden this morning
And I told her that I might go on the Friday the 21st of December
Oh no
Well that well I said that's not this Christmas she goes
Celebrating Christmas that weekend early because a lot of the family can't be on be here except for that we
Weekend
And I said oh well that's not going to work
But I kind of didn't say anything to her first and then
Well I tell you she started getting all emotional
And if I want to stay married for another year 45 years
Now you better
Tell those people that
I got family obligations
Because
That depends what's most important I love wrestling I love wrestling
And I want to start another one for help start another wrestlers in business network but there's more than one day out there
But there's there's a lot of people that are
Maybe even closer
And they got big names I mean work we're doing pretty well right now you got first 2 years ago
And we got
Second this year
And then we got the women's freestyles doing good in wrestling
We got to work a little bit are Greco yet
But
But they are working on it
Are men's freestyle team right now
AR
Par excellence
Looking for them is to get them all on the same page
Instead of
Just
Have new highlights by that I'm saying
Who let you look and see who won this year will the three guys that have never won before one this year we have three world champions
Rdr2 past world champions
Didn't win this year
I mean
Is it okay you know I got metals
The debit debarros win no he did not
You got third
Oh that's right you got bronze yet I mean
Schneider got second so
Those two are men guys
He also
The three guys that came through
We're guys it hadn't won
World gold
Vacuum have never made a world team before
And so we have three world champions this year
But we needed all five of them to come through to win the
The Championships
And so the key really is
Get them all to do the same at the same time
Year-in and year-out
And not just based on
Okay girls got beat this year so he'll win next year
It's got to be every year if you're capable of doing that and that's what the coaching staff has to do
It's kind of funny that I do have a lot of influence
Actually on the coaching stats right now at the USA level because of the women's freestyle got
Guy is up
Is Terry Steiner and he Russell for memes a national champion
Got a twin brother that's at Fresno State
And then Billy's attic is the freestyle coach
And hear us over the Hawkeyes back in
The early days and now he was a national champion so
We got a lotta
A former Google influence on their butt
In 2013 the international Olympic Committee ioc voted wrestling out of the Olympics
So
A lot of folks know about this the absurdity of it
So on
Butts in a big picture you can step back now is five years later what did you learn from that experience
First of all
Did it surprise me
Yeah
Did it really surprised me know
You got to run you got to have
People running
The organization
Better
Top notch
If you take anything for granted
And you're not the person of authority
Somebody can
Kick you out
And even though
We had a lot of authority because we're wrestling where the one of the first sports to know
Olympics
Ever
And that we
Think that
You know where and 180 some countries
And
Some of the
Number one
Countries in the world
That are politically strong
Have the sport
You know we thought we were okay but then you got to look and see who's running the ioc
The international Olympic Committee
Then you got to see that
In wrestling we don't have any money in there
I'm not shocked me
We never had anybody
On the ioc
From wrestling
You know why
Because we didn't have to
But yes that's wrong
You have to
And if you don't
Have somebody looking out for you right within the structure
That is pretty easy people turn their head
But
All it took
Was
Statement
You guys are kicked out of the Olympics
You guys are done every came together I think it's the first time in ever in history
That probably all this cup compared to people
That we're working for their own agenda
Turn that agenda
To the sport
So that made a big difference
And we got a lot done in fact
In America
There was several people
That were
Really
Out there that we didn't know about
Until this point in time
And when they came aboard
Now they're still aboard
That doesn't mean we're doing everything perfect
Because just because we got voted back in before we even got kicked out really
That doesn't mean work
By any means safe
We got to do some of the things that I'm talking about or the some of the things that we didn't do before
We can't fall right back into the same mess
It's hard leadership got changed
And it's
Better
But it's got to stay better
But there are things
That we could still be
Doing to make sure that
We don't
Have situations like this
Happened when I first learned about it
I was like
I broke down and wept
Again
It's like every once in awhile I'll break down and
And I'm cry about
My sister
Or I'll break down
I don't know if I cry about losing the wings but
I thought we get more determined
But that's kind of
You have to go back at it and think about those moments when you heard what I heard that moment and I
It just
Overcame me was like 4 or 4:30 in the morning
When I heard about it and my wife had been up been up looking at the internet and see if she woke me up I thought you were joking
But I jumped out of bed really quick when she said that I know she was serious
Making phone calls right there
To find out if it was true in my phone I was truly. Was just like devastating
He.
Yeah it was one of these things that
It's a nightmare
And
Don't let it happen again
I said it's that simple
Yeah and you keep getting stronger
And people haven't read they should read the loss of Dan Gable by Wright Thompson the ESPN article that kind of
In this very beautiful poetic way
Ties together
Are all the losses of Dan Gable the losing your sister losing to Larry always losing
Wrestling from the Olympics all of these tragedies
Various forms
So
So that's the ioc is politics and your serve being very pragmatic
Stepping back wrestling is one of the oldest forms of combat.
Dating back does cave drawings 15000 years ago
If you look at
The Olympics 27 years ago
Did you ever when you wrestled a coach do you know
See wrestling in this way freestyle and folkstyle wrestling the purity of
There's two human beings locked in combat the the roots of that that's just human beings
Fair struggle between two men or two women
I don't think I ever
Looked at it
As anything but just
A combat
And
I think there's times
That have made me
Figure out how to make that combat better
There's little
Markers
Are little points and time in your life
That make you
Wonder AR should say determined
To be able to get more out of yourself
And to be able to take it to a new level
I don't think people can actually
Feel that way unless you actually had a lot of accomplishments in anything
I think there's anything out there
I mean no matter what sport are or breaking the 4-minute mile
I mean when you broke that
Roger Bannister
I can imagine in breaking it from
Is best time being 4:30
You know it's one of these things that
Along the line there
Daddy did
Had some close calls
Or
He had some coaching that was giving him the opportunity become a little better
But I think because
Was doing well and being very successful
That the opportunity came and saucer me it's like the same thing I had so much
Success
And so many practices
That went well
And so much
Goodness out of this sport
That it
Gave me the opportunity
To really
Look more
Finite
And look more how I could even make it better
And so it's like
If you look at my library upstairs I got a library upstairs
And there's a lot of books up there
From the family and
But if you look Gable books up there
I got a lot of
Russian technique books
I can't read
The book
But I can see the diagrams
And I can see the figures
They don't really show it in pictures
They do it in drawings
And
And so it's like when I was trying to beat the best that as
Label the best because
They won the World Championships every year since they been just about involved
I don't think they got started involved you like the 50's but
But you know it's
Something you know you study the best
Who's out there
But then you
Don't Focus so much on the best that you can't beat the best
You learn from them
But there's something that they don't have
That you can have
Toughness to technique to the Arts to the science
Do you when you're sitting over there you love MIT
And you're bragging about it over Harvard you know it's cuz it's true
Verizon internet
But but it's the same type of thing
That
Yeah there's something that you're probably stealing from Harvard that but
Do you want give them credit
Well then
In the interest of time
I've read that you're pretty serious
Your
Pretty serious into fishing
So what's the biggest fish ever caught
Are we talking about here I wait you talk about
I don't think I've ever caught
How big ocean fish, River Lake Ray Sherman
Child problem
Probably Northern
I probably caught in Northern Italy
27 pounds
Official like to catch walleyes
And that's the reason why I like to catch him cuz they're really good eating fish
And the best eating fish and not the real big ones
I know it's got you kind of interesting that I got people hunting deer right on my land and
They're looking for the big bucks but they're not the best either see if you want if you want to eat but they're the best trophy
So you know I do have a couple trophy walleyes on the wall but
But
Most time I throw the big ones back and put them back in there so
I love you know there's a book by Hemingway called old man in the sea
Atrovent and
Ernest Hemingway Ernest Hemingway
And he said there's an old man that basically catches an 18-footer but it's can't pull it in.
Have the strength so they together spend
Iwata sharks eat away at it
Miss is very powerful story I think one of the Nobel Prize but
He says it's better to be lucky
Dogman says better be lucky
But I would rather be exact than that
That way when luck comes you are ready
What do you think about luck
Do you believe
And Free Will that we have actions
The control the direction destination of our life
What does luck
And some other outside forces
Really
Land you where you end up
For me
I'm not about luck
But I do think there is
Luck is involved
But I think it's mostly created
Just how lucky you are
Do preparations
And things have things have happened in my life
Forever
A lot of good things
A lot of people could say hey you've been pretty lucky to win all these Awards
I don't know if you analyze
My life
I don't think it was involved with luck you know I think it was more involved with preparation
And you don't and again science
Had you been smarter had you understood that you could do some things
And be just as lucky that be great but
I'm only as smart as today
So when I was training in my life and maybe even training people
In my life
As of that moment that's how lucky I am to be able to
Have whatever is available to me
And that's what you call that a lot of science so for me I
I think that you don't like right now if I look back I got to do a Lot of Things Different
Just because
Things are proven
Differently like I
Give people water coming practice and I did
And I would let them change their running wrestling shoes into running shoes to run sprints on the country
Or I would actually maybe
Maybe I've had a guy climb 12 ropes after practice one after another
And then maybe the next day I'd do it again
I might not make him do it the next day
Lane recover little bit more
And
You got to learn keep adding to your philosophy
And your father may have been great at that time but it's at that time
And what is really important is where you at
With this time today
And so there's better ways to do things
Now you'd be ever take attitude out of it
And just depend on
Total science
Then you know you're not going to be as high as
And I think it's a listen to a couple people that are really pretty famous people
You want a massage on Irving he was a writer and
He told me so you think I really
Learn how to be a great writer
Henna
Writing School
Ice ice
Yeah I learned a lot there
But really what gave me
The ability
Stay focused
Just to work extra hours to be more discipline was wrestling practices
He was a wrestler go back to that that's what gave me that chance
You know it and there's a guy and I will that
Guy named Norman Borlaug
Kia
Eevee learn
He invented a process to feed
The underprivileged countries
Of the world
And
He was a wrestler and he said the same thing and eat any worth extremely hard
And he said
I give a lot of credit to the sport of wrestling
And even though I was I'm known for this I got a statue in in Washington DC because I
I saved a Billion Lives Plus
I'm going to get wrestling a lot of credit
Self
And I think
Some of these
MMA Stars
And some of these guys that
Maybe warrant wrestlers that had to Russell Russell had to fight wrestling guys
And stuff missed a little bit there but I ain't the ones that did have wrestling probably have a really good chance in Canada
Adapted the other ones
But I think they are every
Martial art or every activities
Good and you probably can't skip any but I don't think they're ever going to
Overlook and say that rustling pretty nights are not valuable because
It is
However that doesn't mean you're going to make it you still got to take the values and apply it
Whatever area you're going to be in it
And some people forget that
Some people can't get over
The highness of getting your arm raised in a wrestling match
And you know what what's even greater than
Me getting my arm raised
Is that if I'm a cold sore virus along with you that you get your arm raised in
And even if you don't get your arm raises what you walk away with
And how and how you will learn
Adalat as well because there's going to be some losses
But you don't want many
Just so you don't get used to losing I can tell you that
Sister Hunger for the win it's the Brotherhood The Sisterhood of the resting room and hard work and science
That's going to be luck
At the end of the day
Absolute luck you know
I like luck but I think it's created by the opportunity then that you make your luck
If you make your luck yet
Then
Is a huge honor thank you for welcoming me into your home if I have his conversation no problem good man
Be true to go to the mall in this potato and do the other things not because they are easy
But because they are hard