We choose to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things not because they are easy
Has co-authored by you first
Astride quick hypothetical question
If I told you right now that I have with me I brought I told you I'm Russian I brought with me
Back in the car
Two guys there waiting outside with a 73 kg players
They happen to be in the top 10 in the world
When is Russian the others Japanese and I'll give you $1 if you beat one of them in Judo
And you don't match which one do you fight
Tough question
Russian or Japanese which one would you play
I think I take my shot against the Russian
And the reason is that there's so much more technical
Give directions that we have great Judo explosive power
Don't get me wrong it's a tough decision either way but
When I look back at my statistics in in which
Which style of player I beat more often
I had more success against Russians an idea did against Japanese alright that's the voice of Jimmy
Pedro
I'm here at the pedro judo center
Talking with Jimmy a legendary competitor and coach
He represented the United States of for Olympics 9296 2000-2004
Winning bronze at two of them
He meddled in three World Championships winning gold in 99
Yes coach
Money
Most
Elite-level American Judo concluding Kayla Harrison
Ronda Ronda Rousey Travis Stevens reckon
Alex Luciano Taraji Williams Riley Ferguson
The Rowdy person they work together and as many people now
How many others
Those people have been on this podcast so
Nice
First Judo coach was your dad
Still your Judo coach
Always will be
Can you talk about your relationship with your dad when you first started Judo
Did you put a lot of pressure on you to win
So my dad
For those of you that have ever had the
Privilege of meeting him
He's Unforgettable
When I was a kid
Genewiz
Was mandatory
It was no such thing as I don't want to go to Judo today it was you're going to Gino's tonight and it was every night
Yeah we only had practice when I was a little boy three days a week but I was at the Jojo
5/6 days a week running around the Madison watching classes and things like that but
My dad was very heart of me as a youngster
Push me to compete push me to train
He gave me exercise routine to do when I wasn't doing Judo I had to do conditioning off the mat
You know that he brought me through circuit training and stuff like that so
Yeah my dad was very demanding father but
Is his mentality was that
Good good for me not just
To become a great athlete but
For the life lessons that I would learn through the sport of Judo and what it would do to
Tell me become a better better person
Pandora
Yeah you know many many parents want their kids to eat vegetables because it's good for them and eat healthy cuz it's what they want
Father wanted me to digital
Cuz of what I could do for me
And so I mean that is a story
A lot of great
Since port in wrestling and Judo
So the question for me is
Your father now
Your coach now
Do you and did your dad's struggle that balance between
No letting your kid do whatever they want
And
Dragging them Kicking and Screaming to training
Well I'm a different I'm a different father than my dad was but I also have
My kids have to live in different shoes than I had to live in
So my father wasn't an Olympic champion he wasn't you know a national hero in in
He fell short of making the Olympics himself
So I was I was almost doing it with him and in for him
Where's my kids feel like you're doing it for me you know where they
State
Every tournament they go to they have a ton of pressure cuz the whole world is watching them because they're Jimmy Pedro son
You know there's a lot of parents that are that can be obnoxious and when their kid beats my kid it's
It's the biggest deal on the world so my kids have to deal with all that pressure that
No kid should have to deal with
So I'm a different father I I give my children to choice
What sports to play of course as a yacht as young individuals at all did you know
They all competed up until they were teenagers
But it's at point I let them decide what sports they want to play what they want to do right now I have a son who's
Ranked number one in the nation in the sport of wrestling
As a sophomore in high school
Now he's chose wrestling as a sport
I have a daughter that went on to play hockey and softball and now she's a freshman in college at Bentley University
But I think that they're digital training that they did get when they were young helped mold them as individuals and as good peep
And so I wanted him to do it for that same reason
Anything is possible what certainly is possible but
The path to success is
Doesn't have to acquire
Excessive pressure from the coaches in the parenting in the early years
Everybody's different
I think everybody is different a response that pressure differently
You know what had I been given a choice I could tell you right now I probably would never have made any Olympic teams or
Wouldn't have
Excelled in the Sportage you at all cuz it's not something I would have pursued
My dad didn't give me the choice and it wasn't until I was about
15 years old where I started to become a man
Start to really want to do this for digital for myself
Up until that point I was too immature and it didn't understand what was going on and
You know I felt all that
Pressure from my father and I despise doing the training sometimes or
You know it was difficult but as 1516 was am pretty damn good at this thing
You know what I like being around other athletes and I get to see the
At that in a white 1560 is that the travel you start to go away from home you going to Kansas City
In Oklahoma or Florida are you going on trips overseas
Try to become fun as a teenager right
Get to see the world show
That's when I started doing it for me and that's when it really became enjoyable
And so in those years. Late teens
How did your
Relationship
Evolve
Then it really became I was motivated you know I was always a self-motivated kid anyway but
Really when I was 15 to 16 I turn the corner and I and I
Decided that I was
Giving 100% all the time and in my dad truly became
Not just a father but
I saw him as a great coach somebody that that had a wealth of knowledge
That new how to train athletes that knew how to get the most out of his athletes
And it did actually expose me to the world I think the biggest credit I can give to my father as a coach
Is that he sent me away
To learn from other people
The biggest mistake most coaches make
Is that
They keep their students
To themselves and they hold them back from reaching their potential
Because you were afraid
Did that students going to go on and learn something special from somebody else and no longer give their their original Coach credit
Especially as a father and a scary thing 2
Give up your son to somebody else
That's what my dad said he said Sana is technically technically I've taken you as far as I can take you and I
I never made the Olympic team
I want to surround you with greatness
I want you to go see
Did these other athletes
Adjust people to
And if they're not these days
Heroes that you put on big pedestal but they're everyday ordinary people that make mistakes that fall down to get back up
I want you to be around them because champions
Be around Champion To Be A Champion see how they ask you how to behave see how they think and also learn from them
My dad sent me the all the best coaches in America at the time which were Irwin Cohen who
Recently passed away and Patrick Burruss was on two Olympic teams and
Daniel Adams in England and I learn from Neil and
I sent me to Japan and sent me to Germany in
Gunther No Rider and
I learned from some good coaches in Japan and
I picked up something everywhere I went
My dad said hey
I want to send you away don't just train I want you to learn
What should I do
Bring back a new technique from everywhere you go show me what it is
And I can tell you
That as I gathered all that
All those new techniques and all that new knowledge
To this day I can tell you who I learned all of the different techniques that I did in my career from
Which is amazing
You know
So that's the biggest mistake I think the most most coaches make is
And tattoo exposed
To the rest of the world
And I give my dad a lot of credit for having the foresight
To do that for me
Is slightly darker side was there
As a competitor
Was there ever a time you consider quitting jail
Absolutely every Champion wants to quit I can tell you numerous times
When I was only
16 years old
I went to the US Open
In Judo it's
At the time it was one of the hardest tournament so I'm in the world
Cuz the whole world love Coming to America
Kids compete so we're Japanese and we had Russians we had friendship we had Brazilians and
In as a young boy it was a super hard tournament to compete in a computer gets all the men
And I got tournament
I had a great
Day I lost to the
Eddie lady who took third in the Olympics
And then I battled back and I was fighting for bronze medal against the guy from Korea
And I scored in the first like 30 seconds I threw the Korean guy
24 years old strongest hacking
Physical and Technical Honors
But
I threw all my score right away and then he grabbed me
Crossmatch started shaking my gay and stabbing
I ended up getting 3 penalties
And losing the fight
My father
What natural on me embarrass me in front of everybody
Taking that match
That I was calling to my father
I fought afraid I was scared to lose
Physically I couldn't match this guy he was so anyway
Long story short I went out in the snow took my GF laid down in Colorado Springs in the snow just cried
Just bought my heart outfit like 8 fights
You know I lost for a bronze medal of 16 years old and one of the toughest tournaments
I felt like a failure
My dad my dad
You know Danny embarrassed me in front of everybody so I want to quit
At another time
I was in Japan
And I'd spent six weeks training Japan
And I went to the kennel cough
McConnell
Is one of the best time is in the world
If that tournament
Mai Tai
I sucked a lot of weight after being in Japan for 6 months 6 weeks
I slept a ton of weight and I was all excited to fight well
My first round was against Sergey cuz minion
Cuz meaning of the Russian
First match of the tournament kuzmania
Truly free phone
I didn't know I didn't lie was
That was all
Cuz me and then threw Macklemore free phone
And I saw my friend cuz menu and on anyone that tournament is it first
My second was against Nakamura
He beat me by Pancho and Owen to in the Kanto cup after being in Japan for 6 weeks
Dieting and losing a lot of weight
Made all this sacrifice
I remember sitting on the steps at the Budokan
You know at 19 years old sick of myself
I hate the sport
I just want to quit
Terrifying
The will
Where do you find how do you continue
Every Champion wants to quit I love that
The hardest thing that I think the
Thing that most people don't realize is that they only see Champions as winners they only see the times when they succeed they don't see the
Dark days
I don't see those days where they struggle though they lost are they failed
Weather for the day in training when they got their butts whooped
Right
All those tournaments where they just fought miserable nobody ever hears about those days but we all go through it because nobody
Doesn't happen
So really what makes Champions is
How do you want to go out
You know do you want that to be your last competition do you want to go out as a loser as a quitter
Are you going to
Suck it up learn from the loss
Dig deeper get better
Re motivate yourself
Nnn become a champion of that take that was my mindset my whole career I wanted to be on the top of the world I wanted to be topped
Napoleon
World Olympics that was my goal
And quite honestly
That same guy clothes
You know he beat me in the 91 world
The next year
And then finally 92 I got them in the finals of the Italian tournament
The Guido's
You know it perseverance and tenacity and
Sometimes it pays off
Is there something
You're a grass fire early Judo
Years of training
Something you wish you would have done differently
I think early days now because you know I played a lot of sports as a kid
My dad allowed me I played in a football Pop Warner football I played baseball as a young kid I wrestled and
High School
I did you know so I had a good balance to my
Adolescent years and my childhood
Forgot to
Play a lot of sports in in learn
A lot of things about team working
It really found out that
The best thing about Judo and wrestling an individual sports is that
You ought to know we decide how good you going to be you don't have to rely on the rest of your team or you don't have to worry about having a crappy coach
You know being in a bad situation you get out of it what you put into it
Show
I don't think I regret anything as a youngster other than
I wish II
Could have enjoyed it more
As a child
You know I had a lie went undefeated
In Judo until I was 11 years old
What about when I was six
So I 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
I didn't lose a match until I was 11 years old
And that was the finals of the national championships
So think about
Pressure of going undefeated for all those years there scams
Right and having your father
Is Bump you up to the next weight class or fight the harder person or the next age category or always challenging
Yourself
Should I have all that pressure and push the envelope threshold
I had anxiety about every tournament I went into up until I was
Till I finally lost
You are you talk
Often
You yourself are graduating
How you talk often about the value of Education
So
Do you think there's room
Life outside of Judo for
Somebody who wants to make the podium at the Olympics
Absolutely
Unquestionably I believe that
Athletes who lived live a balanced life
Who don't put all of their energy into just sport
End up becoming better athletes
Because it
When you fail in sports
You feel like a complete failure
If that's all you do
But if you have
Something else that you're pursuing parallel to the sport whether it's an education
WeatherTech rear
Whether it's family
If you have something else in your life that you can put your energy to
It makes you feel good about yourself
Then
They kind of balance each other out
Sailing sport
But I get an A on this exam I still feel good about myself
Or if I do lousy in school but I just won this tournament
I feel good about myself
Because I found some reward in something I did
Where is all you do is sports
And you fail
Then you have nothing else
You feel like I sacrificed everything I gave my everything for this moment
It didn't happen so I think the Lowe's end up being lower
And that's why I encourage my athletes
Yelp eat at rental teach other students get involved in some other way like they can
They can take pride in their in their students winning tournaments
You know it is that's a parallel path
Like I said educational work or something else to provide some sort of enjoyment
What's so that's not you don't think that's a negative a distraction to that One Singular Focus toes
I think there's certain times were obviously six month before the Olympic Games
It's time to focus and put all your energy into Spa
Okay so I took it when I was at Brown I took a break from Brown
Focus just on training in Judo in the Olympics
Yeah but I never really put my life on hold
Swissport I had kids
Before I won the 99 world I mean I had
Two kids already
In one on the way
You know so I was a father and in
Coming home from a long training
Tripped or competition ronen
Overseas and coming home and seeing you two and three-year-olds run up to you and you forget about
You forget about that guy that just whooped your but it was right
Perspective
So you meddled
In 91 the world
And in 2000 for the Olympics
How many times in between
That's it at least 13 years of being one of the best YouTube competitors in the world
So what
What would you what would you attribute that longevity to
For so long being at the top
Well like I said
I wanted to be the best in the world show my motivation was to to be world or Olympic Channel
Nevada injury in there
Yes
Also plays into everything everything happens for a reason and everything plays into what you ultimately
Become
My injury was pretty devastating
Describe
People that don't know
I actually was in a tournament in the finals of a
Korea
And I got picked up in front of my head
And I tournament in really instead of taking the fall and just losing
Stuck my head out and I can write down on the top of my head and then my feet went over and I did a bridge
I didn't think anything of it I got off and I finish the fight and I lost
But then
Going home on the airplane and noticed it
My
It got harder and harder to lift my chin up off of my chest
By the time I landed
In Boston
The neck and the disc and swollen so much that it was hitting the spinal cord
Cancel Mike my chin. Pinned to my chest
Then I just had radiating shooting pain down my arm into my hand
That was no
It was like that for quite a while so I'll just say I went to the doctors
First
MRI
Doctor said you will never
You said Jimmy I'm sorry but you will never do Sports again in your life
Did someday I can get you to become just a normal functioning human being again
Remember going and I cried
Elevator
23 years old
Thinking that your career is over
And at the same time
I couldn't sleep
Because I couldn't lay down in a bed mites in my chin have to stay here
In my arm have to stay here
Ross the pain was excruciating for lifting my head in anyway I just couldn't move
Well that's cool arm in that chest muscle
Tricep Shrunk the zero
All the nerve damage wood
Happened on the right side so
I slept many a nights just sitting in the traction unit with a
Await over-the-door in my dorm room and I would just sit there with my head trying to pull up
And I will try to sleep because it was the only time I could ever get comfortable
I had about six months old
Living like that
For how long did you believe is it
That you're not doing Judo ever again entire time I was injured in the painting
Dull throbbing pain
You had no feeling in your hand to your ear
So I knew it was serious
And I tell you I
Sometimes the only thing I could do is I would drink like 8 or 10 beers
To pass out I couldn't
I I couldn't stand the pain I couldn't move
You know I didn't sleep in a bed for that whole time
You know and then
Even when it started
I got lucky
I just kept taking anti-inflammatories I kept
Doing good
Traction
And I think I just got lucky over time
The nerve regenerated itself the disc started to go back and I never had surgery
And
I started getting a little bit of range of motion back and then I was so excited I went back to the doctor I said.
And I was like
You made a lot of progress and you know he would he said okay
I don't want you to run you can't do Judo know wrestling is too but I want you to go back in the weight room
I want you to start
Retraining that muscle in that those muscles to move again
I remember the first day on the Nautilus machine
No wait
There was no way
I was just like this
Trying to train my muscles to move
First time on the bench press
Just the bar
Girls in the weight room
I just
A lot of rehab
To get that tenant finally
Overtime I got stronger and stronger neck muscles and traps and
It came back and it took about nine months to
Be back strong enough where I could get back on the mat and said doing what you call me Zin
Start to train again
Incredible
Jonestown years after that
What up
Right
How is Jimmy Pedro 1991 different from the one of 2004
So
At the beginning of the dominance to the end of the
I would say that the young Jimmy Pedro was Fearless
Was raw
Talented
Dodger gritty
And
Got after it just that just talked just flat-out
You are so not so explosive though cuz I cut a lot of weight when I was younger so I wasn't so explosive in 91 in
Mike my best years in the sport of Judo Workwear between
95 and 99 was when I was explosive technical
Superhero really strong on the mat
Physically real explosive
Is real technical
Those are my best years in sport 95 to 99 in fact
I look back and I I should have been in the finals of the world that year I could have been world champion 95
I lost or
Korean in the semi-finals
By Split Decision
And
Judo
It was a split flag decision that I thought I won
And I think the Korean thought I won
In that year the Japanese who won the who won the world
Three months later I beat him pretty easily and in Germany so
Thought I should have been world champion 95
And then
2 weeks before the 97 World Championships
Which I was undefeated
Wake the whole year winning everything
2 weeks before I was supposed to go to World Championships I went to where
Training camp that the coach
Talk me into going to
And
To the heavyweights
One guy got thrown into my leg
You took my MC my MCL
Second-degree sprain of my MCL he just fell into her swelled up
And it was only two weeks before I had to step on the mat at the world
And that MCL
Couldn't hear one time
So I didn't I didn't actually fight in the 97 World Championships
As a result of that
So
But 99 I was 9899 I I don't think I lost
Maybe two or three times and then I'll run
You know when really it was because I completed so many tournaments Right In A Row 1 week after another week after another week and body is broken.
Padang 2004
You know I was
I retired after 2000
Only because I told my family that
This is the end of my run supposed to win the Olympics
This will be my last Olympics it's time to start life my wife is sacrifice
12 years waiting for me to come home
And
But I didn't win in Sydney
I started life I started working
I just didn't want to go out as a loser
If somebody who didn't fit medal in the Olympics
And I just couldn't accept it
So
I was inspired as a 2002
Olympic Games
And I was really inspired by that my son
I want to do this one more time
So she said of course I knew this was coming and
And that was the most enjoyable
2 years of my life from 2002 to 2004
I was in the finals of every single time
Every time when I made the finals
All the way through
Aetna matter what time it was and I just enjoyed the life of an athlete again and you can be selfish
You can focus on you
Focus on yourself you can train you feel great
You never get that same feeling out of anything else in life
Lesbian
A winner or champion
Having a crowd roaring
You don't get that from everything else in business and I can do something deals but
It all on you all
It's it's all eyes are on you right
It's awesome and so I enjoyed that and so ice 2004 athlete I was
I was physically strong I had the cardia
I had
Great cardio I knew how is efficient with my muscles I knew how to
Y'all spend energy I wasn't as good of a deal player in 2004 that was in
95-99 but
Good enough to win
Do you think do you think
Like you said with age
Athletes lose
VR the fearlessness of Youth
That is how essential is that
That's stupid
Hurt being brazen
Stupid in your singular focus on this
Just drive
Absolutely
Gallant
It depends on how the athlete deals with the pressure
You know going into the
Going into the 2000 Olympics
I was 99 world champion
So all eyes are on me to win the gold
All the newspapers all the magazines everybody was talking about America's first ever goals I had all that pressure on me
And it wasn't that the pressure got to me it's just that first round I had
The Korean guy was top five guy in the world and he was always a tough match
So I just didn't wasn't meant to be
But going into 2004
I was old I had experience
But I wanted it
I was hungry again I wasn't afraid I didn't have pressure I will put weight
To compete
You know so I was older
But I have the hunger
And what happened was ironic with Kayla Harrison
You know when she was world champion 2010
She tried to repeat
In 2011
Well all you could see it in her training
You can see it in her competitions
The pressure
I'm trying to repeat as world champion
Was so great she kind of cracked under the pressure she felt it similar to what I did in NC
Didn't you feel the pressure you don't
Not sure if you're doing enough you're not sure if you're ready
And
Probably the best thing that ever could have happened to her
In 2011 was to lose and finish third
Because
It shut her up
She wasn't the top dog going into London
She was one of the favorites but she wasn't ranked number one she was number four
And she's Underdog
And she wanted to climb back on the top of the podium again so she she had she was hungry again
Where is if she had been 2011
Never would have
What's up
Admit this but
Have you ever been broken on the Madden competition for whatever reason you lost hope for confidence in the match
Has there ever been a guy Tough Enough
I've never I've never been broken in a judo match and I've never quit
Ever
Just not my mentality I bought some guys that were tough as nails
You know that that I had to fight for my life against but I never back down
Never back down to anybody
I might have got beaten
But I went out fighting that I never quit never in a match
Can you think of anyone in particular was a toughest guy I've ever faced the competition
Are you personally
I mean I I had so many tough
Tough fights
It in Judo competition I mean I had some real matches of the Little Koala malls
German he was two time world champion Olympic champion and widowed and I
Fought hard you know
56 *
Those were Wars
That golden scar we might still be fighting today
In-N-Out does a Japanese guy
Nakamura yukimasa Nakamura he was never beat my career
I never be that guy
Beat me on Sammy's of the junior world to beat me in the seventies of the senior world
Give me the channel copy beat me in the finals of France
I remember every lost
So it was just a very skillful in ERG does a lot about matchups if you don't match up well against somebody
I had a hard time to eat
But I never back down on the Never
You know nobody ever just ran over me
So I remember I talked to Taraji Williams and you said you was really depressed
After his Olympic run
Thanks II
What is that
Life after the Olympics so will you haunted by the losses is there a depression is like you never achieved this kind of
What is that transition
Do normal life until life of a coach
It's really hard
And I can tell you haven't been to for Olympics they were all very different
My first Olympics that I lost
I want two matches I lost my third
But the three guys that were on the podium
With three guys that I had beaten
And I did many times so I felt as if I should have been there
And sitting in the stands and my father I remember crying thinking
I give up my entire life
I sacrificed all those
Trainings in the gym in all that time overseas
That's it
It's older
Make sure it matches I'm done
I didn't do anything in the Olympics I failed
I feel like crap
It was depressing
Luckily I was young enough
Stupid enough that you know I wanted to try again
You know
Winning in Atlanta
Was America and walking around town and have everybody
Treat you like it hero and welcome you into their store the restaurant of their bar or whatever it was in
Show your mettle and take pictures you are a rockstar in Atlanta and it was awesome
But when you come home
You get tugged in a million directions by a million people that want your time
So what ends up happening is
You start doing everything for everybody else
Hey can you show up to this kids thing and
I'm talking to school what can you come to this appearance
Is all about giving other people your time
And you don't really ultimately enjoy it anymore because
You could see how sometimes Stars just feel like they never sent her some celebrity
Peace for yourself
Speed up doing any Purcell was always one of the people
That becomes hard
But it comes with the
I'll take the win every day of the week
Over not right
Then
Sydney was denisdaily
Losing in Sydney was the worst ever
It really was a
Start a retired can I retire.
Replace the Olympic Games for me was a total failure considering I was supposed to win the Olympics so
That was a hard one to swallow and that's why I couldn't ever swallow it forever
I needed to fight again
But yeah I could see how somebody like a Taraji who didn't medal in the Olympics super suit
Do you know as long as you did and made to Olympic team
As great as everybody else sees that feet
Is it a state when you have your sights set on
Achieving excellence in you don't
You definitely feel unfulfilled
And you can see that like I said in sport
You really don't get that same sense of elation
Anything else in life
I ran a marathon
And I ran the Boston Marathon one time
When I got done people
Awesome I said no I couldn't wait to go home
I would not hurt you. I just want to lay down and eat
But wasn't the greatest feeling now why would I do it again
You know the most people for them in such a massive
Coppersmith for me it was just okay did it I'm done move on
Childbirth I hear people say childbirth is awesome and it's
It is it's different
The sense of it but it's a different feeling then
What you get from from
Winning in the only thing that has ever come close
Me
Doing it was
Michaela 1
Being apart of something
And I believe that was destiny that she came here
For specific purpose
Some reason why I didn't win in Sydney
Because that girl was supposed to win in London
And we were supposed to help around that Journey my father and myself
That we were supposed to be a part of that
And that was the Magic Moment amazing Channel
Tune to me I cannot believe in that Destiny and I believe in
Carmine good things so
Repeat in 2016
It's setting up nicely
In the United States
A country where Judo I struggle to gain ground over the years or wrestling jiu-jitsu
Compared to other nations in the world
You have produced
Almost all it's not all of the US medalist at World Olympics in the last
Two decades
What would what is the secret
What
What is the system B follows licey if if I
How do you take a six-year-old
6 year old 6 year old with an interest and you don't give them a shout at the Olympics medal stand at by the time
R22
What is the process you follow to make out something champion
Well first and foremost there is a system
And that's that that's the thing that most
Most other places in America don't have
And that's really the problem with the entire
USA judo is that we don't have a system
To produce high-level asset
We've done it here in Boston
And
I was part of this Elite
Under-23 program where we took the 20 most talented kids in the country
Informed of that
Crop came
Marti Malloy
Travis Stevens
Kayla Harrison Nick Del popolo
They were part of that U23 program
That I was a part of for 6 years
So that was
Also my system
And really it's it's
Obviously to be great you got to be you got to be willing to work
Right you have to be willing to
Hours and you got to be willing to take the punishment
Show it's a mentality
Number one and two championship
Mindset
You have to have second
You got to know how to train
We believe in a system of conditioning
We believe in
Grip fighting
We believe in the water
When it was big into strategy
So
We know that we cannot
Beat the Russians we cannot beat the French we cannot beat the Brazilian Pizza
Japanese
By doing more Judo than they do
Because you're awesome
We can beat them with Judo cuz they have
We want people to train with
Way more opportunities
Physicality technical strategy gripping conditioning toughness
In the mindset
It will going to win in this is how we're going to win and you got to get
You're still at the believe in that system that okay
We're doing all in
We trained very intense
When I go to Russia
Is Japan
Russia's a lot of drilling
Buttock technique a lot of lot of free motion in free feeling
Not a lot of randori
When you go to Japan sea opposite
It's all random
15 rounds of randori a day in Japan it's insane in Russia
They like if they do 15 a month
Chuck is very technical
But you differences. We do really intense focus training here
And we were smart with the periodization of our athletes that so you
Tok ideas
Peking
Tick performance
So what is
Is it essential to psycho like it is why can't you be your hundred percent year-round
Because is it a mental lapse
And mentally you can't be
You need to have times of relaxation and you have time to focus focus training and actually is it
You just recently got my 16 year old boy who's trying to be the best in wrestling
You can't go 365 days a year
Banging your head against the wall
Not enjoying life
Because
In the end you'll be like this
You'll you'll be great
And you'll be here
Never have that
Performance of a lifetime
Do you need
Your body needs time to heal your muscles need time to heal and rest
Your mind needs time to heal and rest
In order to have
Otherwise it gets used to being an
Get used to being right here all the time in the zone
We want to have a Zone where
It's above that
That's was Olympic champion that's what world champion is
You know what nerd
You got to let your body come down
So that I can build from somewhere
Igc
Pretty good at that and they take it to an extreme where they get so fat and so out of shape they
Lennox air training camp for 12 weeks is 16 weeks
But that's the idea is that I'm not training now I'm relaxing but having fun so that
I can focus when it's time to focus and get real serious about this
I can push my body to limits
And that's what we believe
You mentioned
Your father is a big part of the club what role does he play
At as part of the system
Is a huge part of the system
You ask any of the athletes he gives his time
Alabama
I work full time I have four children
So you don't never going to make me Rich
Crack jokes
My Life as a joke that has helped me
Become
Pretty wealthy because of
Being involved in martial arts
I mean I just started a brand new
Just started that have been involved in in selling Fuji and how to shoot a sports goods for the last year or so
So I've been able to make my life through martial arts in Judo
But the sport of Judo is not what
Put food on my kids table
In order for it to become great they need to train more than once a day
So my dad is down here with the every single morning
He runs a morning technical training session
Try guys
Describe at least broad Strokes what
A weekly program looks like for an elite-level judoka
So our athletes train
Monday
Monday morning they train here
It's about an hour to an hour and 15 minutes of Technical Training
Winning by Technical Training
I sometimes depends on how many bodies we have in depends on who's in town
For the most part it's mostly drills
Gripping drills nawaza drills
Throwing throwing drills Tremont 3 man what you call me
Speed drills
Sprint's in the morning at the end of practice and conditioning
But they're good training for an hour to an hour and 15 minutes every more
When they leave here
They then go to a professional strength coach
Some of them go to Mike Boyle's strength and conditioning Woburn some of them go to the place I went in with pulse
Sissy
Wonder Woman strength training in North Andover
After they work out here they have a break
Been mid-afternoon they were there to strength training
Play
Judo specific strength training it's not
Powerlifting it's
Some type of circuit training depends on
What phase of training ran what type of lifting or doing it
So the pain but they are they're doing something focused for again between an hour an hour and a half
Noah stretching everything else built in an hour and a half of of
Afternoon
Then
They come back at night
NL train
Randori at night
We do another hour and a half
Pandora sucking at night so
There minimally doing 3
Training almost everyday
They go Monday like that
Tuesday
Wednesday
Thursday they have the morning off
So they just do
Weight training in in Judo
And then Friday morning only
They train
So
Shadilay depends on
The weightlifting scheduler run sometime like a Friday only have one training
Consolidating only have one training away train
But to get Saturday night off and Sunday
Less were fighting a tournament to go to the sermon of the week
What has been the biggest challenge for you in preparing for the 2016 Olympics in Rio
China team
For me it's bit for me personally it's been balancing family
With team
My wife's been at this for a long time right she's been open since 1992 she's been living with me going to the Olympics opening
After the 2012 Olympics that really took a hard toll on my family cuz I tried to travel so much
Watching
So
I took a break
When I've been home a lot and I've been focusing on the family have a daughter that 6 I have three teenagers that give Mom
Pallet home when I'm away
I'm so
I've been really focusing on family
So that's why it's been hard for me to balance because I loved you I loved the sport I love helping me outfits I love being in the game
And I genuinely feel that
Beyonce's benefit with
Having me
Honor
Charron
With them and it inspires down and give him a lot of confidence
But that's been the challenge for me is is
Bouncing balls
Now is the Olympics is ramping up again here and we're just about to turn 2015
Jamberry lot more travelling to come in with the team in
But my dad's picked up
My put my dad in that role
You know because the best to athletes in our country are Kayla Harrison and Travis Stevens oh
They're from our our territory they're from our home Club so
My dad is a coach and I'm their coach show
They can't have me to have the next best thing and that's not my dad
You know
What is the most painful moment
Remember
Maybe one that stands out as a coach
Watching Travis Stevens lose at the semi-final match at the Olympic Games unquestionably is a coach with most painful
Woman I've ever been involved in
Because I see all the boy works
See how much you want City sandwiches sacrifices he doesn't
He's a kid easy doesn't drink alcohol he doesn't
He's straight as an arrow
You know any like gave you that schedule of three times a day training
But he's out there right now doing to get you
So he trains for five times a day
IKEA mattress
You know he wants it
When he's hurt
Pushes through New Zealand part of it
I felt really bad for him because you don't really get those moments back in life we are in the semi-finals of the Olympic Games
Acumen never get that moment
Hope he does
But
That was
Flip of a coin who wins the fight
He was silver medalist or gold medals in Olympics
Yeah
That was really painful and I watched him cry on the sidelines
For an hour after that
And then he had to stop for bronze and
Normally nine times out of ten he'll beat that Canadian
Don't you beat the boy before the Olympics many many times it's just
He had physically drained his body of all the emotion
LeBrons
So your coach now but you're also and forever judoka
House of Jimmy Page worth today different from a guy who won bronze in 2004
In terms of
How's your Judo develop
How do you say technically how you think about Judo how you approached Dido
IGG.
Well I tried and I tried to
I take a lot of what I learned in my career and I pass it on to my students
Nobody ever
I really had nobody that gave that to me
What is a mental disease mental side of this game
That I learned and I trained my mind
I visualize success myself
I had some good self
Talk that I did with myself all the time
Pass that on to my students
How to use their mind to achieve success Odyssey
How to believe it
Even before they do it
They have to believe it
And they have to see it
And I'm a firm believer that if you treat that pathway in your mind enough time
What happens is when the moment comes for it to happen
Your body
Think she's been there before and that's where it's supposed to go
So it'll go
In most people
They never see it happen and I hope I want to be an Olympic champion someday
But they never really
See it
Believe it experience it
Before it happens and therefore it
It never will
Because they don't think it's possible
I never talked about it that is something you taught her and then she just felt like
The Olympics you felt like
It's almost like you're in autopilot
It's an obvious fact as you getting the gold
She's almost walking through the
Right does the steps that she's visualize a million times I was able to pass that on
And they say sports is
Like
Ninety percent mental right I mean because if it was just training everybody Train everybody would train
365 days a year
Write 24 hours a day 7 days a week I'm that's it it's just whoever changed the most but it's not
We all do the physical
Focus on that side of the game as well as the strategy and
Looking at videos and studying how to be disappointed
In what are objectives are in this match and I think that also rather than just walk out blindly and just fight
Strategy going in
I think taking that professional approach to the game
You know and with our system
You look at the number of people we have in this dojo
In terms of elite athletes
The number of bodies we have to train with this go every doing something right
Right because Japan and Russia and France and everywhere else
With what we have and we don't have very much money either
So we're Up Against All Odds yet we're still getting it done
I'd say hi. How is it different I think I'm a little bit more syrebral
As a coach then I wasn't it as an athlete because I had to learn a lot of it on my own
One of the player
Last topic
But in the last half-decade
Ijf the international Judo Federation
Has made a lot of rule changes
Starting from
Like crabs
Can you summarize the rules the rule changes and
Say whether you think they have had an overall positive or negative effect on Judah
The IGA have goal
Ways to differentiate
Judo from
Wrestling
I really wanted to differentiate the two
Sports Chalet
In case the Olympic Committee
We need to get rid of another sport which sport are we getting rid of
Just get rid of one
So they really want to differentiate
Itself
Show that was one reason
Second is they tried to make it a little bit more
Fan friendly
Wright's old men how much time has been gripping you know in ripping and gripping so they've taken a lot of the gripping rules
Who's out of the game and you not allowed to break rib so many times anymore
They thought that was a boring elements of Judo
But the reality of the situation is that Judith never going to be
Fast and friendly live sport
Interested
It's never going to be
And if you're not a judoka and you don't have an interest in
Fighting is boring
You'll can be very sore and spectacular
If you create a story behind it
And you do a one hour show
We only showing highlights of
Behind the scenes and who is this athlete and get to know him and get the
Then show his series of fights and show his throws a submissions and
Income up to watch the final and then
When the final happened just show the best clips of the final and have some commentary going about what's going on
Then it can be a good sport never be a good live sport because it's very boring and it
Always will be
No matter what rules you put in
I love I love wrestling
But wrestling if you don't know who
Is wrestling
Belaboring
Same with American football know if you truly
All the Europeans age football so boring you start your stop you start your stop and get it
Aunt because they don't have an interest in any of any team that they don't care who wins
They're not from New England rooting for the Patriots you know
Set when we watch soccer As Americans
Abhorrent
We're not rooting for any team that's really the story that people fall in love
Like yeah they do the game
The fan was at who has never done Judo
Is ever going to enjoy watching Judo and less
It's a highlight reel in real life
Cool stuff going on
So I think all the rule changes for for not I don't think they're affecting
They're not going to check the popularity of the sport
Unquestionably the knock-on effect
I go to
All of these big Grand Slam tournaments
In Abu Dhabi and there's nobody in the stands
You know you go to all these tournaments and there's nobody watching
Everybody's watching online but nobody's watching
So
I think the rule changes
To be honest with you I think it's gotten more towards sport
Rushed towards if you think about what Judah was founded on it was founded on
On sport the Olympic sport was founded on self defence
Write as an element as an element of the sport Judo has no self-defense element
Whatsoever anymore it's all about sports
No dojos really teach
Self defense element of Judo
In what Allegra
It's really like grabbing self-defense and some guy attacked me with his legs
Right so they're taking that out of it and even as a judo player who's in the sport
Some guy who's very 6 ft 1
M545
He's got really long legs so if he comes in high should be able to grab it
So you're taking that part of the sports I disagree with that
I mendakota you know that they're the prearranged movement Nobody Does that anymore really
You know I was lost a lot of its
I'm down to just being an Olympic sport
These days
Which is impractical
For the masses
Because
The masses are never going to compete in the sport is too dangerous
Do physics
So if you like Jiu-Jitsu succeeded because it's taking it to a safe place it's taking it to the ground
Nobody's tumbling and falling and doing 360s in
They're rolling
They're getting a good workout during some self-defense
But that's okay that's what if you want to make the sport popular
Everybody has to be able to do it
In right now
Judah has become a sport that only the young can do
That's why I think it's failing
The question is Judo Olympics in 60
Before that's exactly
50 years ago
So
Martial arts
In general has gone a long way in life
50 years
And even night
I think very importantly thanks to mix martial arts where they kind of
I'll put like Sumo in karate and all these things together and you realize that
The grappling Arts have a lot to contribute to
This is a really effective are
Exciting art
So where do you think Juno will be this is a weird question
50 years from now
So do you think there's something
Timeless
In the sport of Judo
Jill is trying to become more professional
Right but it's also becoming a very expensive sport
So then what I see happening over the course of time
Is all of the big programs
I'm going to continue to be big in the sport of Judo because there in the world
It's only a big program
So what's going to happen right now
They have a Cadet Circle
Show kids 14 to 18 years old
They can get on a world ranking list and there's a Cadet other Cadets
Then there's a junior circuit
You know that's up to 21 years old and all these juniors
Have world rankings
Competitions all over the world to develop
And then there's a senior circuit
The problem is
The big countries like a like a Japan and a Brazil and France and Russia
In all lot of European countries
They have the budgets and they're investing in their youth
Ultimately Road
Run from Cadet to Junior to
Tasheen
So they're going to continue to flourish as countries and get stronger and invest more money in
Grow
All of the other countries including America
Who don't have money
Why don't we invest any money right now at all
Not even I figured our Cadets are cadets
We the parents
Have to pay us Judo just to have their kid dude you know but
We don't give us nothing and I Junior
Cuz we don't have the budget for it
So all we focus on it the elite side and it's becoming more and more expensive
Fun visa to qualify for the Olympics
Soon as you shut off that opportunity for us to qualify for the Olympics
Gerald's gone in America
It'll be non-existent
Okay so
That's the direction we're headed we have less Elite athletes today in America
Then we did
4 years ago
Then we did eight years ago then we did back in the 70
Is less elite players today than there was that
The more expensive it becomes
I don't even see countries countries like
Peru
And
A lot of the South American countries Argentina
Good full teams of athletes
Nowadays the number of athletes that are competing at the world
The less and less and less and less there less money
If no budgets they're going to disappear
So what you do is going to be, is going to become
A much smaller sport
In terms of number of countries that participate
Cuz there's no going to be any programs in any of those other countries that can compete with the rest of the world
That in show 50 years from now
I don't think you'll see
How to get the anybody
Ibiza Club from Boston
The preservery
You'll be lucky to see two two Americans on that caught on fire
We get one
Guaranteed
Cuz the idea from give you one
So but you'll be like in ac2 in in in in Tokyo
The direction we're headed
The old is Marty going to lose Kayla going to lose Nick
Best athletes right now
And I really don't have on a pipeline coming out
I hope that doesn't come too
Reality book
Me either
People can find you.com on face
Vice president in a partner in Fuji Sports
In the movie Bad Company so
Would love your business and love your support
We
We we jack out clubs with the complete outfitting there gyms with mats and wall pads and all kinds of gear and then
Obviously the Game Gear we do custom uniforms Fergie's and shorts and rashguards and stuff for clubs
Equity sports.com
Girls Fuji like I'm moving to California now
Closet full of
Figure out what to do with them but
Before we end
I'd like to comment like that
I've done
Considerable amount of interview interviews in my day
And Through the Years
I will say that this is the most well thought-out
Comprehensive intelligence
Thought-provoking questions that I've ever been asked in my career
Thanks I appreciate that
Since you said that I will not hold you, in the beginning about you choosing the Russian against you
Awesome thank you very much for the warm welcome has been fun