The following is a conversation with Arianna Huffington
She's the founder of The Huffington Post
Did you thousand five
And the founder and CEO of Thrive Global in 2016
She's the author
AR-15 books
Most recent tubing Thrive and Sleep Revolution
Both
International best-sellers
These books explore
How to both work hard
I keep a lifestyle that seeks well-being wisdom and wonder
I got a chance to sit down for this quick chat after a conference we both spoke at
And got right into the big topics
Immortality Obsession meaning happiness
And
Love
This conversation is
Is part of the take it uneasy podcast
If you enjoy it subscribe on YouTube iTunes
Assembly connect with me on Twitter
Alex Friedman spelled f r i d
And now
Is my conversation with Ariana
Huffington
Be true to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things not because they are easy
But because they are hard
You tell a story of getting recognition for your first book the female woman
When you are 23 and sitting in a hotel and
Wondering is this all there is
The old question of you know meaning and purpose
So now
A couple of few years later let me ask from your perspective Now what is
The purpose what is the meaning of life
Well
Review
Believe azzam
Every
Major philosophy in every major spiritual tradition
Argues
That that life does not end with death
Whether there is another dimension of consciousness
Then clearly
A full life and meaningful life includes exploring the dementia
And for me
And that exploration has
Being part of my life from
My teenage years yeah I went to shantiniketan University in India
When I was 17 to study comparative religion and
I always wanted to understand
What life was about because I never believed that
All this whole experiment and sweet
Each individual death
And so that's for me at the heart of my life I mean I've always been very active
And
Books with a having unpause now with Dr David but that's being an underlying Dimension that thing gives away
Real meaning to life
Immortality that really interests
Question at the core of
All these velocitycu mentioned also
Memento Mori the Latin remember death
That the other
The reflecting on one's own mortality puts things into
Respond yes
Do you
And in a tough question perhaps
Perhaps not
You often think about your own mortality and what perspective
Does that help you gain
Yes I think about it a lot
And that and it does give me perspective and it does help me focus on the things that matter to me
In times of
My children my close friends ain't back that want to have
So what we're doing at 5 I have zero interest in what is known as Legacy
Because
Seaside dog thing
Life ends with death
I'm just much more interesting what happens to my soul and
Then what happens to my legacy on.
Do you have a sense
So what
Happens
After you die
Absol
Do you have a
Is it more of a feeling if you have a more concrete sense
Spiritually
How do you see the world what happened
Do your soul
2 feet 500
The heck you were while you were here on Earth what does that become
An Entertainer in time
So my son
Is that
We are a personality the body them
The mind
Is like a car that we rented
And we
Return
I'm at the airport and get on the plane
And go to another city and rent another car
I want to rent another car if you believe in reincarnation depending on where you are and your state of evolution
But definitely that what survives is the soul
And that's why how we live our lives and the choices you make an
How we treat others
I'm is so Central to what happens after death
All of those elements
You believe kind of feed
So you've also mentioned that
Under
On the harsh challenging part of life that failure is an essential part of life
So what may be a major failure that stands out to you for your for yourself
One of the toughest ones for you psychologically to have bounced back from if you ever
Dead
Bounce back from
Yes Run Festival
I don't think there is any if I don't think there's a single successful
Compassion
I was not saying that long the way I mean I
I challenge you to find one if you do let me know but in my experience
Everybody has failed along the way and
I think it would be great if
Successful people talk more about their failures
The difference is resilience and
How quickly do you get discouraged
In my case I actually probably the hardest failure
Was when I was 28
And them
And my second book you mentioned my Facebook with
Did very well
My second book witches on the crisis in
In political leadership in the West
Was it rejected by
At 27 Publishers unit one after the other after the other
And then Empire
That time I had to run out of money
I've been living off the proceeds of my first
And I remember walking kind of depressed on Saint James Street in London
Where I live
And thinking when maybe my Facebook was just a flu
And I'm not really a writer and I have to go get a real job
And then I saw Barclays Bank in the corner and I walked in and asked to see the manager and ask them out
What the
Brits call an overdraft
Is that allowed
And I have nothing
Not now I said
And for some reason the manager whose name is Ian Bell
Gave it to me
You and that kind of changed my life because it made it possible for me to keep things together for another 13 rejection
Samsung
At that point I got an acceptance and
I sent in Bellaire holiday card every year
And that he's a little bit like you know in fairy days when the hero are the heroine gets lost in the.
Darkfall Reston
And then suddenly
Helpful animal comes out and gives them out of the forest world
Sometimes helpful animals in our lives
Sign in the form of a bank manager
A Modern Fairytale
So I spoke with Elon Musk recently on the podcast
And you've had the
A friendly exchange with him on Twitter
Last year about work hours and sleep
So I myself as an engineer I'm obsessed with the work I do
I keep a schedule closer to
One that Yolanda's I would say A+ I'm Russian so I believe suffering is good for the soul so
How do you square
How does a singular Obsession in the soda
The term wall of innovation
I fit into a lifestyle you discussing Thrive one focus and well-being wisdom in wonder
So how do you score that would like singular obsession
Oh I think singular obsessions are wonderful all my favorite favorite people are addicts
Dave and obsessive personality
Abbott if you're obsessed
About
Whatever it is you're looking to achieve
If I wear this in research
Electric cars are going to the moon or anything
You need to look at the science and the data that shows that you're going to be more creative and more
Productive and more likely to achieve the results of your obsession
If you actually
And
Take some time to recharge
That's really what we're talkin about
So you're
Your senses
So science and data
These things you talk about
Things of rational people so you think
You think I The Impossible can be achieved by rational people
Does Madness play a role
I'm at Madness plays a role
But also
Looking at the results
Needs to play a role
Like I can't miss and I have huge admiration for alien mask and I wrote the op-ed letter to him
With that in mind kind of lovingly and admiringly
And then helping him
Ihob look at
The laws of human n
Because
If you
A violate the laws of human energy
Violating the laws of gravity. Consequence
And he's facing the consequences
He's being distracted
Prom shoes amazing obsession
And you think there's a way to do better
Absolutely I mean I think you should look at what happened
The results of
Twitching in the middle of the night because he's
You know he's cognitive impairment makes him do things which you know if you should not be doing
And then the ending up having to step down as chairman paid 20 million
Having to go to car to deal with the SEC who needs that when you're building something amazing for Humana
You think of more balance
Sleep cycle 25 balance
Because I agree with you that
There's no balance when you're trying to achieve something big
I mean that times when I've pulled all-nighters at times when people are thrive
Have pulled all-nighters to ship a product
In fact we make that very clear
When we hire people we're not at 9 to 5 operation where you just balance
Spanx
Baidu
You need to after that take time to recharge
And the faster you do it the more effective you're going to be with Carlos drive time
So let's say you pulled an all-nighter
Take something the next day to recharge
Before
And
Yara exhaustion becomes cumulative either you do stupid things are Eufaula sake are all the same
Things that we're staying around
Catches up to you
On another topic you
Have evolved
Throughout the years your political views
From
Maybe you can correct me but from right of Center to left of center
Can you take me through your journey of political thought and how do you see the evolution of
The greater political landscape
Along with your Evolution throughout the last
Several decades
So my Evolution was from being
A kind of them
Republican that's practically extinct now
Kind of broad choice
Breguet rides
Pro-gun-control Republic
To someone who realize that
My understanding of the role of government was limited
You know I really was a republican because I thought that the private sector
Wood-stack bopping address
Inequalities and
They needed a
Care of people at the lower
SSE economy
Rags
And I saw if I said this was going to happen and that you needed the real power of
Government
Appropriations to be able to achieve that
He does my shift
In my understanding of the role of government that led to my shift in political views
I think what's happening right now at this moment
Quimet
The chickens are coming home to roost
Like a lot of fun
A lot of problems that you seem coming
That they've been discussing at endless conferences I don't know how many conference I've been at
With titles like inclusive capitalism the dangers of growing inequalities
We talked about them I didn't really do anything about
And I saw that is on some
Different forms of right-wing or left-wing populism
And them is a very serious moment but I don't think it's going to be
Solved
By living in a Perpetual state of outrage
So
You've also launched this incredible
Platform in 2005 of Huffington Post
Apus is now called
What impact
Do you think it had over the past 14 years on the nature of public discourse if you look at what
At this course is today
The divisiveness
What impact does the
Digitization of our conversation to the online of Twitter
And then
Of more journalistic type of content like Huffington Post contains
What what do you think it
Has done for our discourse was it been a positive thing
Was it been a catalyst for the divisiveness or do they simply reveal the divisiveness those late in there already
What do you think
What the Huffington Post
Help democratize the conversation
Github elevate
What blogging was you know when we launch the having a Boston 2005
Blogging was dismissed as something that people who couldn't get a job we're doing in the
Parents basement
And because we brought in people who could have written for the New York Times like
Walter Cronkite the Nora Ephron and Larry David
We elevated
The opportunity afforded to all of us to Expresso
Bobblehead very very
Careful
Guidelines
So for example we everything was too late that we did not allow ad hominem comment
Want some point
Before I left the hobbiton bus I even ended Anonymous comments all together
Because it was becoming too hard to police
So from the beginning I wanted to democratize the conversation
Side by side with the investigative journalism and all the things that
I loved and honored
But at the same time
I saw the dangerous of
Diabetic ccd.com
Infiltrate
These conversations if they're not monitored and there is no real curation
So one of the core things
That emerged from The Huffington post's I mean there is a little bit of a viewpoint
Underlying it is left
El Centro College laugh there's definitely a viewpoint
In fact we called our journalists Beyond
Right and left I think the right left divisions
The way of looking at the world in terms of right and left
Is incredibly obsolete
Being concerned about a growing inequality
Is not a left-wing position if you are somebody who cares about Law and Order
You should care about that
Unless you want the country to be turned into it
Banana Republic with rich people living
Behind Gates
Security guards
If you care about
Climate change does it mean your on the left
What does it mean that you want to preserve the planet
So I think by looking at the world in right or left breast implant polarizing
The conversation
But
So that's a beautiful idea
And that I share it
But nevertheless
It seems that
Did there's a strong gravitational field that pulls people into left and right and no matter what they will place
Different venues into those
Polaris
So is it seems that the hogs in the public perception
Huffington Post kind of gets into the left and there's
These opposing forces
How Breitbart and so on the deck to get this
Placed somehow and to the right
And then there's the right team in the blue team
I guess my question is do you see do you notice this
Do you see a path forward in the coming decade
In the air of our current president
Maybe bringing us back together
And having a healthy disagreement on the issues
As opposed to having
Teams and tribes of red and blue
I absolutely do I think that two things that I sent really not to achieve that one is a reverence for fat
You and I have the right to our own opinions but we don't have the right part on side of face
So that's number one
And them and number two is to
Do and the view of journalists. Jay Rosen has described
Has the view from Noah
Like I think
Climate change is not a matter of opinion
So a lot of journalists feel that their position is to
Have one person who thinks climate change is real another person with things it's not and their job is to stay in
Midland play ponponpon
Spiral to me
That's like
Not at all
Great journalist men's that about having a bus definitely had to Viewpoint as you're sad
But it was a Viewpoint based on fact
And I actually recommend that people listen
Do your podcast with a special conversation with Neil deGrasse Tyson
That kind of emphasises talks about science and the importance of
Why people have
Teresa
The seriousness
Amongst our leaders towards science
As a thing that you shouldn't politicize
Well last question
How do you balance
Love
And ambition
Thinking about your work with thrive
This Obsession towards
What is building like your car is going to Mars
Building Huffington Post
Obsession with your work life
And a genuine deep obsession with your family or people in your life that you love
How do you balance that
Time
And energy
Well let me give you an example right now you know Thrive global
He's an obsession
Ending a
The stress and burnout epidemic
He's our mission and I
I've see that's having a huge impact on our hands on our mantel has an aura and they're not performance
But at the same time
I have two daughters that I adore
And everybody in my office knows that when I get a call from one of my daughters at any point
I will take it
And that and that they are a priority
That doesn't mean
I can't dogs have be obsessed
About
Why do I doing and are gross
I think this is what a false dichotomy
It's because I think when
When we
Nurture
The part of us that is about love that is about connection
We also natural the deeper parts of our humanity and it's from those parts that wisdom and creativity
Become
The More Love
Will strengthen all parts your life and improve improve productivity in Alaska
Exactly do you know interesting enough
Jack Ma
Highly awaiting Violet in the obsession Department
I'm sad in Davos
Last year that
What's going to win the future is not just IQ
Or even EQ emotional intelligence but I'll kill the last question
Average of something surprising coming from Jack Ma
But I think it's part of the shape that's happening
Where we recognize that
While Ai and machine learning are going to
They cover a huge part of our life and Destroy many jobs
The things that AI is not going to be able to do other distinctly human thing
And loving is one of them
And
So I think it's a beautiful place then Don is love
Ariana thank you so much for talk today
Thank you so much
Be true to go to the mall in this potato and do the other things not because they are easy
But because they are hard