We choose to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things not because they are easy
Buckle Conway AR
Is any particular sport
Define rules
Mastery
Chief of specialization
Taking a few skills and perfecting
So naturally most experts and teachers of movement
Eye specialist
A skill sets like gymnastics
Hand balancing
Olympic lifting
Capoeira Jiu-Jitsu Wrestling Judo and other martial arts
So, cross a general
Someone who takes a holistic approach
I guess today is Ido portal
He is a guru of movement
A teacher
With a large and quickly growing following
As he says
Luminous bag
Bigger than a specific discipline
We're all human first
Louis 2nd
Special
I actually just finished reading a biography of Albert Einstein
By Walter Isaacson
And the two of you have something in common
I desire to arrive at the unified theory
His case was unified theory of physics
Forces of nature
In your case it's the unified theory of movement
Can you
Tell me the story of the journey
To become a generalist
First of just say that
It says something that the
People use but I have a really hard time with the word master or Guru
And then
I didn't arrive at the gospel truth I am not sitting on any mountains and
I'm on my way
So
People who join your students are
I basically
Following you know in the same Journey
Maybe being in certain certain circumstances I'm a bit further ahead or sometimes I'm a bit behind
But it's definitely walk along and not walk behind kind of scene
Yeah my journey
I started as in
First and then I became specialist and then I
Detect movement basically
Silhouette
Fall started in young age and some some Chinese martial arts
Developed
I'm into some physical Sports and
Games
In school Primary School in high school
And then I met a couple
I was completely amazed basically baidu
This is art form
Pursuit that for a good fifteen years
In the middle somewhere military service and other physical layer
Physical Pursuit
And changing and developing and moving between disciplines and exploring
I just kind of
Got the same relation again and again
There is some
Threads to oldest discipline something that is
Attracting me back and basically was movement to I realized
And the next thing was
I want to learn movement I want to get better
Is a mover in a general way
Seeked out a movement teachers
Went around the world and looked around
Are some people who mentioned
Offered myself as a student in
They kept on ditching me
Disciplines
Another isolated approach
Another speciality
And I was very disappointed.
Eventually I decided okay I'm going to become
That person
I'm going to become the movement teacher
And then
The next realisation after years and years of trying was it impossible
And with that I stayed basically because I realized if that's impossible it's a good goal to have in life
Something that will keep on
Moving myself and my students and anybody involved forward
That's where I'm at
Right now I'm in
Teaching and
Learning
Moving around and trying to
Trying to gain some more knowledge about this impossible task
Yes so you still yourself are forever a student
How to fry prefer to be a student any day of the week than a teacher
Being a teacher is
Parts of human culture
We are all teachers
We will teach all the time whether you want it or not somebody asks you
Four Direction in the street you become the teacher
You as a child
She looks so cute you're a teacher
Practicing
Teaching and practicing too
The student the discipleship
Both of them are extremely important for your development as a moving
What is the price
The specialization specialized
We lose Humanity first and foremost
As humans we we evolved
To become humans
Is generalist we are the most
General list of all animals
We're able to imitate the 8nn in Tiger rents
And we can hold their breath underwater and we can do
Everything
Just
A tiny bit
We can't really run very fast we can't really fight very well
No we can't you know climb
Is as good as other animals
But we can do the most complex and generalized tasks
Out of all animals
And no one will even come close so speciality the price is Humanity the price is your happiness
Is the price is your
Fulfillment as a human being
It's the pits its philosophical but that's that's who we are
Do you think there is some beauty and fulfillment
And some value in specialization in becoming
The best of the very specific movement at a particular sport
Giving your body to dedicating to that
Sport
That's an interesting thing because
S a human race
We benefited tremendously from the work of specialist
Photo specialist
Suffer
That's a very very important points
Without specialist we would never be here we would never be Skyping right now on this computer is an end
Wearing these t-shirts
All kinds of stuff
The butt
Those
Especially those human beings
Suffered
The result of their
Highly specialized nature
And we become more and more specialized
The reason move towards
Being generalist again in the last few years maybe the last decade there is a bit more talk about that
But definitely
We are also still pursuing highly specialized
Fields
If I make a joke in my My Worship and I saved
Nowadays you go to it
If you even break your heart you know your break your hand you go to a hand specialist orthopedic surgeon
5 or 10 years you'll go to
And left hand
Specialist
And most evident problem is also our leaders were especially
The required to be generalist leaders
A lot of stuff
And there she leaders
We we keep on having the same problems again and again
Because they are
X specialist whether it's a lawyer or a military person
Economist
These are not
Specialities that allow you the full grasp of
Running a country
Yeah I think I think you put a beautifully that you might specialization that lead to innovation
But you lose their Humanity
What
Do you find
Is
The most underdeveloped
Range of motion in athletes
At what movement
Is most restricted
And high level athletes
In your experience
Who's everyone
Standoff
Shoulders
Particular other joints
Well it's all depends on their speciality of course in habits
The shoulder
The glenohumeral Joint is the most hypermobile joint in the body
Even when it's restricted
It still offers
Tremendous range of motion compared to other areas
But
What eats restricted
Even if it's just a little bit
It can cause huge problems because we are dependent on that
Range of motion and Mobility
Around the glenohumeral joint
And the simple reason is because with the hands humans manipulate
That's what were meant to do with our hands and we need that
Complexity around the scapula
It's been a few years since I've said it first
That the scapula craves complexity
But this is complexity around the scapula and range of motion so important
Across-the-board
Ivory
Your concept of
If isolate
In a gradient
Improvise
Can you describe the role of improvisation
In movement
Any profession any speciality
Should arrive at improvisation
Tirta top-level
And whether you play the violin words
You know you box
You're going to reach improvisation
Improvisation above all
The Human Condition
It's the human
The human ability the highest form of living
Is improvisational improvised basically life is improvisation you're born
You died in between doing provides a shitload of improvisation
Movement is no difference
The thing is people started to isolate concept and
Some people went the next level and integrated them
They present themselves as improvisation but actually
The cheating people
It's just
A bit more integration yet
It's just another integration
Improvisation open improvisation reading provation as we call it
That's very rare
And that's the most
Enjoyable state
It's cold so cold dazone it's also called the tunnel
You just experienced
Is beautiful thing to be empty
Just to let things happen through you as Bruce Lee said
I don't eat
It just happened so you know and zachys
You need to do
Who is movement if you Aspire for the highest things
I like how I
A guy on Reddit
Described you as Ido portal
But not be the nicest guy in the world
But he's a great coach
So that nice guy part
I come from the wrestling world
Work
The goal of a good coach
And a good program is to basically make you quit to break you
There's zero patience for people who don't want to
Put in the work
To work hard
Do you find that tough love is the best approach
Coaching people
Whatever their level of ability
No not necessary I don't I don't like the term tough love
Because it kind of
Assumes that it's importance is
Excel
It's not enough for me it's like
That's how that's the best way why that's the best way
But on the other hand
I don't see
People are made of sugar
And I really believe it
We've lost a bit side of you know
Resilient we are
And another isn't
People
Don't like the truth
You know it's just dishonesty is
When people describe me to stop lab it's not because I believe in tough
100% of the people will be in
With head issues with me on a
Personal level or through coaching
People
Couldn't accept
Criticism what I offered
You know how to get personally weren't able to deal with it
Etc
I can't even
You know in my head find one example
The person I've been working with
Who received
The criticism worked with it
Insteel complaint
But it's always this complainers and who fucking cares
Complain first and do nothing
Yeah you know it's like
When you go mainstream as
We've went with certain level
You have to deal with it because
I'm not operating
My Elite you need my special ops unit anymore
Now it's an army
And I need to accept the fact that I'm going to meet
A lot of slackers a lot of
Foxing Poindexter is in all kinds of
They don't want to work they want to talk about it they want to do this they want to do that they don't want to hear the true state of one
Accept criticism or hear how much they suck
And I just don't do that so you don't have to accept the fact that
I'll have DC Shoe in
I'm sure it will continue
You traveling
All over the world you think there's a difference in this aspect
In attitudes in the United States and Israel and other countries
The other many countries where I I don't have this issue or very rarely
We have a working in Hebrews actually is comes from German I think.
It says topless
It's like down to it
You know the heart of it
Apocalypse people are people who are like no bullshit you know directly
Tell me is it
Vista Palace
It exists in certain cultures
In other cultures eats a lot of chitchat and walk around it
You know I didn't know how to cheat chat
Few days ago one of my student told me you know I can teach at it's exactly how I felt you know
When I first
Came out of Israel started to teach around
It was Russia saying God
That was so similar to
I'm where I come from him anyway so
No problem but then when I went to the US or Canada
I had a lot of issues
With the chit chat with
Politically correct and walking around the bush and don't give it to me too harshly you know
Coverage with a lot of
Sponges around it's often the Heat
And the difference between various countries and
I need nowadays I need filters
Which are
Might might might have stood my top students were helping me teach
Some of them are great filter housing in certain countries
The W much better than me
What is perfect practice
This look like for you so do you believe in the value
Maybe this applies more to specialized Sports
But
Like I Come From Russia actually
And from the wrestling world where repetition
100000 repetitions on a specific movement
Is
Is how you achieve success
Do you believe in the value of that repetition even for a generalist
Framework
Repetition is the mother of skill
Tipping those that corrected in set
Perfect repetition is the mother of skill
Those who usually say it
Are those who don't achieve Heights
Usually
So
I'll be very Frank again I'll be very extremely honest
A lot of people talk about
Perfect perfect perfect
But that life is not
Our surroundings are not
And when I press this and when I move
It's never on the perfect
Conditions
It's never with the ride optimal
Blood sugar level in
Under the specific could you know
I don't know what
And in riding the wave of supercompensation in the perfect way and usually when people try to
To adhere to set Concept in imperfect
They end.
Falling off the wagon
The other side
Don't be a
Don't be stupid
Don't judge yourself
It's not black and white
The truth is somewhere in between
Annie's varies between people
For me after
17 years teaching
18 years now teaching moving
Seeing people
The hardest workers
Usually
Elite performers
Of course some of them are
Sharing a certain Talent or this or that but it's always
Who is very dedicated practice
They have built up that work capacity through that dedicated practice
And they cannot move that ability to other
True
Not sure how much you are aware of it but
Marcelo Garcia is one of the greats
He believes
Boldly
Against
The status quo I think that you should only train
Jiu-Jitsu a sport
Jiu jitsu
Search of success
Channel is at
But the majority of other athletes
Dennisport believe that you should do strength and conditioning programs
Sedates
At least move slightly towards the more generous family
What do you think
You think that's value for the generalist mindset for like I know your athlete's
Or should they just focus
Omnisport
To some level
Speciality can can reach a plateau because of lack of General
Base of the pyramid in some cases
But it's not a very high level of
Penal gennett generalism
Nowadays you're practicing again specialist and they devote more and more time to discuss reality
When you're doing other stuff
So it's a complex riddle
You know I'm into each case
Ezone
But I'll tell you something else
When you reach the top of your field like Marcelo Garcia.
In BJJ
You stop being inspired
Buy your own scene
You can
Gain inspiration knowledge and motivation
From your own scene
Because you are the leader you're on top of the mountain
You have nowhere else to climb
So what do you do
You look to other scenes
In
That's where it's really really valuable
To become a bit more generalized
Related to that
The many people in the US in particular
Focus on learning more than doing
Focus too much on acquiring knowledge
Verses using that knowledge
Do you struggle this yourself
Like how do you approach
Learning new things
Verses putting more time into
Old things
That you've already messaged
It's not only US thing or North American scene
It's generally all across the globe all those are more practical people unless practical people in
Country has his own characteristics
But it's a good question you need to be
It's kind of being
Super intelligent in
Oriented towards team formation
But then have this
Dumb down
Practical mind
Okay I need to work you know and having a balance across that
And that's probably
And it's at
Probably means that
You know a certain
IQ
Example will start to work against you
In certain fields
And vice versa
Hey you when you become too much you know as the Chinese say The Men Who lives inside his head
You you start to have this issue you know you have a thirst
For information
Great thirst
Information is toxic
It's exactly like water water is toxic as well almost all compounds are
Isn't we drink we drink we do we kill ourselves we kill the process
And the knowledge it turns against us
And then
That's a serious problem
Index
The problem of the age of misinformation that we live in
It's not only the Technology's toxic even when it's good knowledge
Now we also have
Dad knowledge
Mostly bad
Mostly shitty advice
The combination is Lisa than just people become paralyzed or just you know move from bling
Link to link to link with
Lazy eyes
Just never
Actually do anything
I know you Advocate building shoes work
How many hours
Today do you think
This is also a debate
Specialist
How many hours a day
Is the most a person can train
Before it becomes
Not sustainable boost before their mind
Becomes uninspired
Maybe as you said
24 hours
Twenty-four hours a day
There was a choreographer in Israel very known choreographer
Call Johan Arena says when you wake up in the morning in bed Between the Sheets
You can you can practice movement
And he's not there talking about with your partner
Even there you can practice you know breathing moving
All the time around you but
Serious practice you know
Practice oriented success and building skills
From isolation to integration to improvisation
In most disciplines
It's around 6 to 8 hours a day
Some people go more and retrieving the 10-hour mark
Periods of time
In the military you go even further than that
Other disciplines require less than in it's also a highly individual thing
So let's not even within the sport of gymnastics
Do you answer in
A woman liking and not
Who trains 8 hours a day and next to her in the same team
Also winning gold medals
The same level more less you have Shawn Johnson training 3 hours a day
And she reached
The top of her field
Olympic gold medal
Indoor Olympics
So
Time in the future
This is
Very rare
To see
History our gold medal sing
But definitely it exist
The difference there might be mental
So the question I have is
Out of the
Various elements like breathing
In developing muscular strength are joints
Which is the biggest challenge to master
As a student movement
Highland obituaries
Depends on the person depends on his orientation
Some people never require any form of mental
Training for example of psychological training
Especially Shield saying was like sports in in team sports
Soap so that aspect is covered the winners are oriented there focused you know
And then other people require help in that regard
Some people have great difficulty developing
Mobility
And just the nervous system is panic
Hold on
Text him too much
Other people are hypermobile and have difficulty creating townies
And in strengths and that he's a great challenge for them
Complex learners
They can name the can coordinate complex actions and learn movements very quickly While others are
Highly limited so
It's very individual
So that process of learning
That journey is individual to everyone
How does one take that Journey
Just listen to your own body
You can listen to your body till tomorrow
You know
You're not hearing anything you need to learn you need to create a relationship
With your body and you need to help us
Teachers that's there is only you know a lot of people saying I'll do it myself
Then you deny Collective knowledge the most powerful knowledge that mankind holds you know because
Only animal
The tap Collective knowledge
We've been able to move knowledge across generations and that's how
We have reached space
Building internet
You know who all these crazy surgery
And you know solved you know genetic issues and Etc
You're not going to do it by yourself
You are just one small person
And we have collected knowledge Generations upon Generations
So
Listen to your body that's nice to say
Most people going to your s*** it's completely silent
You need to start to decipher the signals that the body gives you
And that goes through
Practice in learning discipleship
And exploring alarmed if
Different stuff
It's a highly individual c
Don't have so much anymore
Anymore
Mentor student or teacher disciple
Relationship but I
I wouldn't be here
Without my mentors and my teachers
The shoulders of giants
Dad lifted me up
I still believe in 18 Min away
There is no other way
On that
Do you think that
For the majority of the time
Is a
Fundamentally solitary activity
Or
Do we gain from
The presence of others
So when you when you think of movement
When you're training
Is most of your training
Like the reputations done alone
I would dollars
Both
Years you know alone and with my Student Center
I spend large
Periods of time
Alone just training alone but
I also spend a lot of time being in a community
Movement is the best reason for gathering around in a community
And you know people for example nowadays they go do Crossfade or they do yoga or whatever and then they have
The yoga friends
Ndk
That's b******* you know your yoga friends can be your real friends
Because we've been gathering around movement since the age of time
Creating communities around movement around hunting-gathering dance around the fire
We've been moving together
I can recommend move with your last ones moved with the people around you you know you join a BJJ Club
It's a community
You know you go there you meet
UE move around you go to capoeira
It's a try
You go to a CrossFit gym it's a community
You go to yoga it's a community
You can move with your children you can move with your dog
In the park
It's important to move together
But it can also be done alone and some things are better done some things are better done together
How do you think movement
Changes
Soul movement
But that that whole pattern of movement will you moving alone
Versus the pattern of movement where there's two people
Either working together against
Together is like dancing
Partner dancing
I guess each other is like
Wrestling or jiu-jitsu
Do you think the principles of movement
Are different
When is two people
Horses one person
Is this a whole nother world
First they spend more time moving
With others against others in martial art cuz I spend most of my life in martial arts
Less time exploring stuff alone
But there are some Concepts that still exist like the quality of movement
How you organize your body in space
Not in relation to the partner only
But first a BJJ practitioner
Or or stand-up fighter
He needs to organize his body in relation to space first
And then in relation to the partners what
Some of the concepts existing boat While others are very different to him
And that you can train alone or all your life when somebody else is in the equation it's going to change the game completely
A major reason why we are
Under the fight laboratory with
Departed
In reality from a lot of traditional martial arts
The delusions of training alone and doing forms and
And repetitive movements alone
It's a shitstorm
You can't apply anything
You don't have any life practice and now we see that
The practices that stayed very real
State very dirty in away but very real
They are the ones who are providing tools
For the chaotic environment.
Terms of injury
How do you
Treat
Recover
And work around injury
Injuries are
Ascertain
They're not the probability
Injuries and diseases
They are also required
Has nothing solid one of my biggest Inspirations in these days the great philosopher
In order to antifragile eyes
Become antifragile to become robust to become
More than resilient
You must be able to enjoy volatility
You must be able to grow
Sunday stuff
First
I said
I said it before and I'll say it again
I injure my student
This happens
End
I can do anything beneficial without it
Animate basically
We all get injured
Constantly
On a micro-level and macro-level
It's part of our lives
Of course
We don't want to
Pusheen to meaningless injury
And we want to be able to grow for meeting
How do you train a round
How do you train around it
The hard question
Involves a lot of stuff
1st and a big believer in movement
As a therapeutic tool
Movement itself if it offers you a Temptation and it does
It's the way out
Rest I don't believe in rest
I believe in movie
Which means when I'm resting
I might
Help
On the short-term with certain aspects of the injury
But at the same time I'm creating a new problem because the process is taking me somewhere else
I'm not recovering towards movement I'm recovering towards no
So we have a problem here
In some cases you must rest
And then deal with the consequences later
What's the most cases
Is there is a better approach
Then just resting in that
That requires a lot more taking responsibility which doctors
Don't believe in your ability to take responsibility for yourself
Be intelligent and to know the amount
And some some form of a knowledge and experience in most people can't be trusted with it so we offer
Advice of like just rest resting
Stop
But but definitely
After years and years of working with people in
And taking them through
Crazy Ray's near my right hand odelia she went through a car accident she lost her kidney she broke her back
She went through three knee surgeries
Which my sister performed by the way
Nowadays she she can move like
Few people I know on this planet
And then just
Did the answer was always movement movement going back into movement
Beautiful
Continue
Move
Continue to move you don't look stupid
Don't don't hurt yourself but that's an obvious no
I guess not because when I say these things
People write the f****** common
The butt
The bat people you know yet about you going to injure yourself
Yeah
Genius
Don't go into the injury
And it again
Deteriorated escalate the situation
Of course not
You must move around it
And you must be smart in the way that you allow adaptation to take you out like a wave you need to ride
Meditation
Out of the out of the problem
Index tricky we know
And that's something that we need to educate people on
Are we to believe in people's intelligence and ability to
Take this responsibility
In China
They still have in some areas and they used to have a bone set
They didn't put you in a cast you broke your hand
They think it is for bone setting
Yeah they didn't have x-rays so that's
A lot more complex
And not as successful as nowadays
But
Having said that
They did a chief amazing rates of recovery because these
Raps that they use in the process allows some
Form of movement
Zachary to another PlayStation
Note-taking arm
Healthy harm your right arm
What is in a cast for
6 months
Take down the cast what do you see
The opposite
The arm is basically moving towards death
Is Gotten Good at not moving
The Army's Gray
You have weird hairs growing out of it stinks
It really smells and looks like death because
Movement
Is life
No movement.
We know that
We like to
Just kill your arm a tiny bit so that
Children bones can
Reform
Together
And then we'll bring it back to life
That's one approach
In other cases
You can maintain the life and the demands on the tissue safely enough
At the same time allow the recovery to have
And diet
What are some guiding principles
Will diet is very individual sing
I've been personally following
Paleolithic Cave Man Diet for a long time
How long before
It was called the Paleo Diet
And since 1997
Oregon 96
I've been doing this for a long time
Feel great on it
Still in our growing older and older and
Functioning only better and being able to sustain meeting
Improve
But that is very very individual
There is a lot of exploration to be done there
What you can withstand
How resilient is your sister
Nowadays the reason new movement towards not improving the fuel sources
Choosing the quality
In the quantities of the food
But actually making the system more resilient
So he's able
To basically withstand
Annie
Almost any
Quality Inn
That's where
We have been lucky
Weeping neglecting this area that's something that
I believe is the latest innovation
Although it's still highly misunderstood
And a lot of fat
A lot of folks are abusing this concept and giving Reaper advice
Just two
Be different
Just to say I'm not the Paleo guy
So did that's that's a small addition that will get bigger and bigger a sink
So it's almost like
How you recommended movement
To go outside of quote-unquote proper alignment
This is kind of
The diet version of that
Is going outside of
Some kind of proper framework of diet
To some level but that's
The death was an obvious thing
You know all the ways
The problem is
It's not enough
Because
What I'm suggesting with movement to go outside of their proper alignment
It creates an adaptation
But what if that interpretation cannot happen
For example
Celiac disease person
You'll exposing to gluten
And you have a terrible consequences
No maybe if you can minimising the amount you can actually train him
But that's what the patient is not going to last very
Very far down the road
He's going to get some games
But what if you could
Take that selling deceased person
Put them in the garage
Fixes machina
Change
He's tires changes
Oily map
Putting back on the track
Is a new animal
Annies vet
That is where
A lot of stuff is happening nowadays
So the genetic part of it
The gut biome
So so
Complexion in we discover that
You know we live in symbiosis with all this microorganisms dead
Just
All over our skin inside of a saint
We leave in combination with that
And that's how you see
Some dudes in Brazilian in Russia
Walking around with
You know 5% body fat
Eating one cracker for breakfast
One cracker for dinner
Euro training BJJ all day long high performance
Fueling with Coca-Cola
And send at the same time you see people doing everything almost perfect
And still having poor
Poor performance and
Inability and that gain weight with any you know extra calorie or macronutrients they brought in
Because their system
Is different and it's not only about genetics
It's more about
Epigenetics
I need some more about
What kind of
System besides your own DNA
What about these
Organisms that are supposed to help you
And live in symbiosis with him what kind of assistant do you have there
Disconnect spend more and more and more
And we're going to realize that
There is a lot to learn there
Do you think technology and science is ultimately
A positive force
You know you look at
Movement as
As an element of our Humanity
Do you think technology is
Taking Humanity away
Or
Is adding to it
I'm not smart enough to answer you that man
Be questioning
Just eat a huge question
I think we're going to struggle with that question for many generations to come steal
It's definitely create a lot of positive stuff but also brought
Tremendous suffering
Problems and perhaps
Will be dead
You know the end of us
So technology might have been
You know the most terrible things that ever happened to us
Uno's
Yes
Hahaha that beautiful note how can people
Join the Ido portal movement
Does he have a website that you don't portal.com
Yeah it'll portal.com
Facebook
You can find us on Facebook either portal method
Portland
You can join the movement culture
On a website and set up dates coming up
Soon
You have a beautiful website by the way
Amazing thank you very much
To have a great team around me that they help me with that
So I saw you posted a couple of Tom Waits
And I even a Bukowski referee
On your Facebook page
And I understood something that
I think only another
Asuc student
Of Waits and Bukowski can understand
You don't shy away from
The strange in the profound
Where we can find it
Yes have one way to put it
Is there a Tom Waits song that you find yourself
Returning too often
In your life
So many
So many is just so you know I I can barely listen to anything else
Franklin
It's been a real issue in
Tom Tom Waits
He's discographies like it
It's a lifetime of
What discoveries
It's been accompanying me for years now it's not all it's not the universal something you go through very quickly
I spend a lot of time on Alice
Example
Yea just so much stuff so much that's your way discover
Also you know III song to this disk
Weirdness is the Centre
Argos
All things
It's so important
It's the only thing
Reading
Is that can be you
Anyways
Because as a culture
We're so glad we're becoming this
One thing you don't like you walk around in London it looks exactly like Hong Kong it looks exactly like Tokyo
Looks exactly like
We have this light
Huge human seeing going on which is great and we communicate very easy
But then we lost a lot
On our
Tyrone stuff
There is only one Tom Waits you know because of his eccentric
Partly because of his General this is where genius and that's why it's so beautiful to me
To shy away from my own eccentric side
To be to feeding
But that's definitely an important see NSYNC
So you recommend
We cultivate the weird
Yakult is writing the words cultivating yourself
Because the da
Truly you know
Everybody's weird
Everybody's in the reason of Homer Simpson
Everybody has thus far everything has everybody has this interesting.
That's what also interest me when I did I want to see that weird you know
I want to see that weird in your movement
And they don't tell and they put this perfect picture
It
I'm not stupid
I know it's not perfect.
So
Just allow the witness to come out
I think it's a great lesson earphone
I'm waiting at bootcamp schedule
Also if you don't mind I'm going to torture you something
I would like to close
Bear eating a
Bukowski poem roll the dice
I want to force you to listen to it
Go ahead
If you're going to try go all the way
Otherwise don't even start
This could mean losing girlfriends wives relatives jobs
Maybe your mind
It could mean not eating for 3 or 4 days
It could mean freezing on a park bench
Yakima Jail Division
Commune mockery
Isolation
Isolation is the gift
All the others are a test
How's your endurance
So how much you really want to do it
You do it
Despite rejection and the worst odds
And will be better than anything else you can imagine
If you're going to try go all the way
There's no other feeling like that
You'll be alone with the Gods
And the nights will flame with fire
You will ride life straight to perfect laughter
It's the only good fight there is
Amen
Thnxcya face to talk today thank you so much