We choose to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things not because they are easy
Buckle Conway AR
Today I'm talking with Ryan Hall
Heading structure 50/50 Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu in Falls Church Virginia
ADCC bronze medalist
With a long career high level competition
Throughout which
He is beating many of the top golfers in the world
Is Jiu-Jitsu black belt
MMA fighter
The creator of several popular and well-respected instructional dvds
And
He's a popular voice of reason
And did you get the community
Where is Google Now
And I took a class yesterday
You give a speech
About the
Value of keeping a stoic expression
No matter how difficult things get
Explain that principle
Absolutely I think obviously at you know things that we
And it was thinking internally you know are expressed outwardly and all in the way that we act in the way we feel in the way again on the
Smiling and feeling happy
Angry she kind of face you know not only am I
Showing what that whatever my opponent or the other guy his doing is bothering me which is certainly,
For anybody that's kind of tough
I'm also telling myself that I'm concerned and whatnot so it's no different than if somebody hit you really hard in the face just stare
Nothing happened that's irrelevant
I'm all that matters is that you're not going to show
Can you watch Jerry Rice score a touchdown
Take some ball headed to the referee and kind
Watch out cuz I think he has a feeling he'll be back in there later today
What's he drops a passenger he's frustrated but he doesn't throw a tantrum
Because it's not going to contribute positively towards catching the ball in anyway
And if anything is going to show the opposition that he's getting frustrated that they can get to him
So I think it is very very important regardless of you know the situation to again and try to keep your emotions in check
They take you out to develop
Again in of course she and you can
Anyone can be frustrated anyone can be happy to be several people we all have emotions and what not butter
Basically you know. The more you can train yourself to master that the better because people
Pretty tops with you say it a little bit flustered
And they become less so and everyone is is subject to that
So in the same way that we trained technique can we train you know conditioning and we try and try and we try and everything else we should be training on
Has Walter try to respond in as much as we control the fashion as possible
You talked about moral victory
Can you explain how your morality contributes to
Do AC
The value of winning
I think there's absolutely
They are trying to manipulate you or trying to get you to buy something
Differently in two directions
Can you compete against
A real black hole
And you compete against
Is almost zero
However if you go out there and you try hard
Whether you come off the mat
To be very fortunate unlikely but
If you want answering you tried and you again I'll let you had some nerves but
Captainshack
Can you fart hard you didn't like it
The better of you
You know that would be in my opinion a moral
Will be nothing wrong for recognizing
Shots now that's not the same thing
Is an actual physical victory
But there's nothing wrong with saying what's a
Your your opponents 260000 you're a hundred and twenty
And you tie
They get the decision
Hey you know that happened in the world
Bellator super heavyweight
Generally speaking if you end up
Level
Considering that I have all the resources you don't
Make sure that I'm not shooting
I'm shooting for the actual
But every now and then
It's very important to keep in mind that you know I might just asking myself and my conduct myself in a way
That I respect that hopefully other people of value or respect
And also a way that I believe is going to produce
Actual Victory and actual positive results in a long run
I think it's important to recognize that
Because sometimes you'll see people get very frustrated let's say Frances if I
Box against people that have much more experience than me all the
Anyone that tells you differently
Has is either not training with people that are very good or B
They have no idea what they're talking
But
What I can say is hey did I do a little bit better today
More able to kind of keep my keep my focus and see what I wanted execute
I'm moving in the right direction so as far as I'm concerned is all sorts of different types of moral Victory but it will be there
The same thing as you know that's a princess
You know your mother
You got ahead of me
You have to
He's going to kick the s*** out of you almost certain
Have to hit him
It would not be it would be
I didn't get hurt so that's a win if you ran away
But that would be the opposite of the moral Victory and
Losing would still be I would say the honorable thing to do
So you're saying sometimes you have to pay the price for them all the time
Absolutely but the reality is is the martial arts a dozen
Just teaches about how to beat someone offer technique of this is that that's really not the core of the martial arts Decor the martial arts
Heart discipline dedication Focus
And if you have those things
Better than you
But that's not the only metric by which you can judge performance or judge a person
You competed more than
Many of the elite level guys
Some
And you
Competition
What do you think is the value of competition for martial artists
I believe that the value of competition is and that it teaches you the true
Purpose of
Martial arts
Yes because you'll SAU 180cc gold medal
But
By someone bigger and stronger YouTube
Free Halo that wouldn't be no that's not what we're looking for but
Competition develops
Is proper Focus proper dedication
And strong opposition it will force YouTube
The better your opposition is if you focus and you take your what you're doing serious is the better you become
. people are better Restless today than they once were people live better
Basketball players today than once were military is better now than it was in the past
Because of all of the competition
That you know that is existed over the course of time
And you know it's just kind of
Bullshitted if you like
Looks like that's a cowardly way to approach
That doesn't teach you
To really do the right things in the sanlitun not-for-profit not properly preparing
That was a cowardly way to approach
Did you intentionally left yourself an hour
Which was
If I win and if I lose it
Well you know I mean then you should have been out there
Win Lose or Draw
I'm going to go and if they go I will send them off
My gym and that's not how we conduct ourselves
And it has
Weigh less to do about this
The physical you know the result
But the proper preparation
Proper preparation and proper focus and dedication
Positive results but most importantly it's about are we conducting ourselves
So I believe that the competition really teaches us
In the room you know there's always like
Thing when you go to competition
Everyone is nuts on everyone is on the
That day because everyone is trained for that specific moment end
We'll see what happens
So you get the most out of it
Cats in renal provided that there's not a lot of cheating
Which unfortunately
Pictures of composition
Jiu Jitsu competition
But regardless you know from an athletic
Performance perspective is the most honest
Because
Courage and take some heart to really properly prepare
And put it online because you're risking
Horrible disappointment
I prepared so hard before I try so hard and I won
Prepared
Failed it hurts
I really hurt
Because you can put that much into it again that's how a coward approaches
If you have
Prepare properly
The results and that's what I believe is the real benefit
Competition of approach
Do you admire
Somebody
Who sacrifices you know like 10-20 years
Their life
That singular pursuit of competition
Towards a gold medal at the Olympics
Almost to the Olympians do
Absolutely
Sacrificing willing to work hard in any
Area of life I should book that I'm reading again that I really like is a dune
It's
Basically
You know one of the things
That
Either one of the
Preeminent
If you
If you search for Freedom you actually end up becoming a slave to your own desire
Ironically
And if you search for discipline
Define liberty
Because you're able to make yourself do what you want
In the long run where is it
Getting into a bunch of nonsense but anyone that's doesn't mean that it's
In any area of human endeavor
But as long as you're making it
Incredibly large amount of respect
The level of dedication that end the level of commitment
Risk that it that you're taking
Emotionally psychologically
Like I said you work 20 years you get that gold medal
But there's other people that work 20 years
I got the silver
I cannot like Siri in class the other day
I don't want to be too negative
Do you know that if you're working hard enough
I think you know
But most people are not very honest
Themselves they won't like most people would press a button in my experience
Look like
The thing then
That's it that's fine but
Hey it really
Victory is
Reserved for those women
Price and there is a price
Guarantee that if you pay the price that you will have victory
But you guarantee that the I mean from a physical
You'll have to learn discipline you will have shown
You showed that
You are the master of your own mind of your own body and if you're on circumstance and you can
Discipline yourself in focus and you deny yourself certain things
In the pursuit of something
Something that is valuable
Not talking to me why the same reason that you'll see guys that were
You know like
High-level military like kind of big dogs in SF world
Get hired by let's say for instance the Fortune 500
What would they know about
Business
Nothing
Everything
Because
That level of focus and dedicated like you don't get to that level of a
Ability in something
By accident
That's what I think
What they do competition
Serious
Because if you don't get the gold medal is a you may not
You may not walk out of it
But basically on
And able to
Over the Long Haul put that
What time-in but I have to
Walking off the mat
Having to be carried off the
It means
Approaching reassessing reevaluating saying how can I be better
And
How will I believe I look at myself I'm still buy
I'm still looking
At myself
What should I be due
Don't better I'm going to find other people that I respect
People that can tell me and then I'm going to ask them
The courage to listen to them
And I just as much with their saying out of
And if you're doing those things that I believe that a lot of time to work
Working hard but I know plenty of people to come in
Frankly stock
And there's plenty of people that I've been training for 4
They're pretty nice the best person that's been trained
But they could be really really really good
Because they understand how to be direct and how to focus
Disgusting all before
Went with some other ain't no friends of mine
Distressing whatever
Look at guys like Randy Couture
They're on their second career
They started
And yet they got
To the top
Maybe they weren't always Champion but they were
Freaking good
Because they're 26 year old self would be scary
Do you know like hey
They know what it is to be dedicated
Bands like you said
A regular person
So I think that ultimately the skill it's not.
Knows how to work their ass off and
Comprehend
Yeah and be brutally honest
Kill yourself
Sometimes you know it is I think it's
The price of
Eight of looking inward
You know objectively is that
You're not going to like what you see a lot
Because even if you're like all men
I'm 90% the way I want to be
If you are going to take the next step in my opinion it's you're going to focus on the temperature
Because it's like home and we're doing
Let's talk about what we need to improve on
It's what's
It's what's going to drive you to a higher level but at the same time I think it's what makes a lot of people that are like that
A little bit neurotic and naughty by comparing by a normal standard
But again you show me someone that
Super well-adjusted and I'll show you someone that's probably not a high fever
In a class you
UEFA says they were working with
Basic laws of physics
So I just read the Einstein's biography
He was obsessed with finding a single theory that we unify
All the fundamental forces of nature
Do you think their existing unified theory of grappling we can boil everything down to just
Just a few principles
Unified theory I would sincerely
Question my ability to go that way but something like that could potentially exist absolutely
Even if it doesn't
A belief in the possibility of it and the search for it
Leave you better off
And where you started where as if I was at
B******* that would never end and I don't look
Because I didn't look this certain things I want learn
I think you know a lot of times
What's Alchemy
Girls maybe that's
That kind of nutty and Dino
Highly unlikely probability of success Pursuit
Yielded
Scientific progress elsewhere
In the search for that even though again
Well if you spend
A principle based approach to graph
What's your
Process like
@the
High level
After all the years of experience what's your process like for learning new details and understanding the principles
Behind
Techniques
I bet you're going to believe that I have
Like a
A singular
Perfect approached by any stretch of the imagination
But I mean I guess what I try to do is
Block out extraneous
Princess
Both feet a lot of
People want to talk about
55 details and reasons for something this
What's going on in the reality
That you're clouding your thought process
There was a reason not to
Political
But there was a recent issue where
I remember
And they use the new drug
And it was painful
What do you believe that capital
Is valid or not I think it's
It's against it
In fact I think most of the arguments that make sense or against it
Pain has
F*** all to do with it
You know I don't care if that's like
The helix
I'm going to kill you
But don't worry it's not going to hurt
Show me the steak
If someone's going to sting I'm still going to try to fight you to the death
If someone wants to say hi
Let's go let's cut the b******* like fili feelings out of here and say hello
You forget the pain
Does this person deserted
Is there a potential for human error
Is there potential for someone having this
Political games
It has nothing to do with does it hurt
Orc which drug is it
Hey
We're focusing on the wrong
In the public in
Arena
They always focus on the wrong thing
And always hooks on the wrong address
Good reasons or bad
To do almost anything
But generally speaking people will focus on
Hundred other ones
Extraneous and retarded
So what I want
And this guy likes
It's really important
It's very very important
But
Clearly they all work
Under the right circumstances and don't work on the wrong one and it has nothing to do or very little to do
With each other
Would you prefer to be painless or horrific leaf
Okay
If it's already a foregone conclusion
I will start to talk about
Like whether or not it's going to sting
Hey let's focus on the
I need to do this
Okay so
Yeah it doesn't matter
But it's a hell of a lot less important than 2500
Things that make all of the difference
Is a lot of people
Bulshit you
Will focus on 45 little
Description details for this technique
Okay that's true but
What are the two most important
Because it don't matter
But just like anything else in life is a highway
Because would you say that would you say that
Happiness and self-actualization is a valuable thing in life
I would as well
And you know what we have the luxury of saying
That type of thing
Because we're sitting at 50/50 Jiu Jitsu in Falls Church Virginia and there's no one trying to kill us rapist
And we are also
I know where food is
That if you were to walk.
Feeling
Stare at you
F****** retarded I'm starving
I'm hungry
My issue are you are you satisfied in your life
So that's even the deeper question is are you eating something
Right
First time we start to work
Self-actualization
Don't tell me about where you're placing your
Grip
It's like you're all leaning out in your
I'm starving to death
You know
The Barbarian
Giving you a philosophy
It's like this is retarded
Doesn't make any sense
Build a better wall a sharper knife and get some food
And then we'll cover the all the others
Feel to be the most important
Component parts
And then
If I won
Reach the level of where these tiny Details Matter
That's fantastic
The difference
Between you know the ability to
The past
Successful against recovery
A regular run-of-the-mill black
It's also presupposing that you're in proper
Preposition
That even allow these details
Become relevant
And I think that a lot of times
That's problematic
Are there still in your opinion
Undiscovered position submissions a techniques in Jiu-Jitsu
I would say that
They're absolutely
Think that what we see is you get you now don't get me wrong to the core never change
Because
Physics doesn't change physics
Which is the same thing that's why I get a kick out of people that loves like self-defense argument
Bullshit has another no physics
Beyond the fact yes you can
I've never seen anything like that in real life
But you're crossing a pretty serious psychological line if you're putting your knuckles too dumb to Knuckles deep into somebody's eyes
Forget the fact that
I've never done that before
Before I wouldn't do it lightly then probably
Hesitation there what do so anyway
What makes it different is the psychological component
And all these other things going on with
No it's not
It is absolutely not
What are you talk
Physics of different inside of
And they are out in the field
Exactly the same
Now if I try to sport grapple you
Under a non sport grappling
Jiu-Jitsu is physics is is proper expression of his insanely boxing
So
I would say that as long as something adheres to the principles that that allows
To be effective and
Do you know and fundamentally sound
That you can do almost anything
Take the people will continue for tickling the kids going to get nuts
I'm just a level of the amount of
Things that you can get away with it
Conduent
Different grips that you can make
But I'd say what we're looking at right now
Is going to look
Only someone
Like what you just going to look like
In 30 years
The same way that you get to we see now is
So much fundamentally
Better honestly and and more evolved
That it was
20 years ago
And people will swear up and down
Well even 20 years ago
Understanding hadoop
Deal with jiu-jitsu
Very reduced so you can get away with all sorts of
Pretty questionable
. like sitting in front of someone in clothes.
Jordan have them not completely kick the s*** out of you
It is
That's I always hesitate to say
Invent
Don't like the word invent
Certain people use a lot
I'd say discover because you could show me I can come up with something
You know
And I could be doing that in a way that no one ever taught me
Because you've been doing it forever
But basically it's a show me the details
High-powered I discovered
Who invented the dab
People in head two arms and two legs
Long as I can
Probably longer than that
So in the history books
You're a Grappler
Wrestler
Judoka
You serious I was your dog as well
I mean only by a very very very
Low standard of computers you a tournament that you completed
All right yeah I hesitate to use the word someone a real judo player will come in and just just facepalm and stare at me
Mailboxes
What do you think is the best martial art
For defending yourself against an untrained opponent
Untrained
Statistically speaking you go through life
Minimize the chance of yourself being hurt by the untrained opponent
So Street Bar
Are there so many different factors
There's about
An ass whipping like seven people vs 3 people in
Okay that the more variables you add and it gets very very difficult I would say them
The best fighting style is using your brain
Because when winning the fight
Now I know nothing about investing
Which is why I don't do it
But let's say for instance
Did you get in here
But he said there's nothing
To do the best
Can do is wait
But you're Warren Buffett tell me the best investment
Are the best investment today still suck
Talk to me next week and I'll see what's up
Maybe
And then
You're going to kill everyone
And you are armed
50/50 Junior
But for whatever reason
Sitting there polishing their fully loaded
The chamber safety off weapons
And you see everyone else
What do you do
Wait
The Wednesday
Being the best tactical shooter
There's too many of us into few of you
Could you make it out of there
I wouldn't bet on it
That's like Floyd Mayweather
Seriously
Because regular people can't fight for s***
Literally crippled
The first guy with the right hand
The other two guys unless they're really serious
Oh and it hasn't
4 people
Free People
All these different things factor in so I would say that when it comes to the physical expression of how to best
Defend yourself the most important thing is
Situational awareness
And understanding what's going on around you because you could be the world
Greatest ninja warrior
And still run yourself into a lose-lose situation
Because
Starbucks
And you teach him a runic a joke
And then you let him put Rodger Gracie in that we're naked choke Rodger Gracie the greatest Grappler
In the world
And also a big freaking dude
And you let him put Rodger in that Renee control can you
You think Rodger gets out
Padres probably bad
He's one of the best escape artist
Escape artist
You're like a tier 1
Best of the best f****** tip of the spear awesomedude
I shoot you in the face
Do you live
Mature immature
Good fight
At a certain at a certain point it's gone too far
So now who thinks that
The above average
Very very slim
Almost non-existent
Knockout Floyd Mayweather
If you let me hit him
But
I don't think I would come in spitting distance of him
If he didn't want me to
I would have no teeth
Before I even tried
But if he sits there and let you hit them
He is a man
He is mortal
So basically under the right circumstances
Does anyone can win
Under the wrong circumstances
So in Spa
Shredabull
As a martial artist
In particular Grappler
Even if she
Allows the situation to get to far
It becomes a
Lose situation
Even for him
So
I would say that understanding that is step one
Effective
Effective strategist
Can read a situation you say
4 seconds and run for it
The physical expression of everything you want to
What's a friendship
Best things for defending yourself in real life
Say probably wrestling or jiu-jitsu
Probably Jiu-Jitsu really in my opinion
But
Fighting
I would say
Beat up more than one person right now it implies that I can wrestle
Or I can just
Actually horrible
The boxing would be nice as well
But let's say you're great boxer
Angular person
For sure but it also
Basically
If I had to pick one art and everyone knows nothing
Owl pictures
But in my opinion
Jiu-Jitsu at a high level
Involves wrestling
Lookaside grappling is
This is bigger
Everything that involves wrestling June 11
Inside control
It's not pleasant
So it's a popular idea and Jiu-Jitsu that egos
You know your greatest enemy
Have you had
Made any progress in defeating that out of me
Does it get stronger as you just a game is better
And they love that s***
But that's when you also know it
I don't trust large groups of people
And I certainly don't trust their thought process
Show me someone that takes losing well
What's a princess
5 year old
Because what am I doing
Army
But if I go
I'm not okay with what just happened
You're either
You're possibly
Realize Hixon Gracie
Or more than
Because again
Anyone
It provided that they're not it's not
You have to want to win
Do you have to run when you have to believe but you can't
Drive you in a pot
Directions
But you want to tell me that Michael Jordan
Has no ego
Horseshit
What song is this
Floyd Mayweather
Get out of here
If you ask what's
But the reality is a liar
He's bullshitting
You can say yes
He is the best
Or the British was
At a time
Does that mean he's perfect
No absolutely not
But not
Devolving into like a ridiculous self-love
Patting yourself on the back
Because you want to believe that with proper working with
Proper effort that you can achieve
Anything
But
Just you being you
Does not do any
They are sweet because of them
Rather than like
I have trained hard I expected
I'm coming out to get you
Hey do I control the outcome
No
Borderliner
But basically
Proper preparation
I was probably in the moment
I have to believe that I'm going to beat you
But that doesn't mean that I believe that I will beat you
Just by being me or just by showing up it's not going to be easy but I expect
To do well in to win
And I think that
Do you know sometimes just you guys or girls that
But don't believe
And it's a shame. It doesn't take much to
That they can beat you or that they will beat you
To really push hard
And sometimes
Endeavor
Has been made by unreasonable people
That kind of said f*** you I'm going to
You know honestly in
That is true
If you look at in popular culture now it's completely gone over
That is so sweet meme
Like that's garbage
4 positive things
If you
Do what
Is necessary for to July to generate a positive outcome
Super athletes that have done nothing
People that have
Made incredible things
The best and most successful people
In terms of Natural Resources
Good-looking or strong or smart or whatever
And they work their butt off
But I
More important the most important ingredient
What's hard work and dedication offer over a long period
You know I think that
Leaving the door it's
You know don't let it get in your way
But
Really when it comes to
Fighting it's almost all psychological
Do I have to believe that I'm a
Going to beat you and I want
Make you believe that I'm going to beat you he goes a few on that fire
At the other day it is it really is and I
Think that you know
Mosto
Believe in yourself
When this and I'm going to do that
Now if you say that
If you're willing to go like
I'm also willing to get out there
I'm willing to try
As long as you're willing to risk
The failure
You willing to come back and try harder and do it again
Then I think positive
If if you're
If your confidence is hinged on
Unrealistic beliefs that you're always going to win without doing anything
But every hila molasses that I've ever met
But that's a successful one
They believe in themselves
Working people find you
Cbs.com walking around Falls Church
Sometimes
Although
What do you like to eat in case somebody wants to assassinate you
BJJ r5050 bj.com
4 people
Can find me on Facebook
Thanks for
Text to talk in the day and thanks for welcoming
Meteor Academy