okay so let's welcome our next speaker
Keesha and he will talk about his
experimental unit cell okay hello hi I'm
here to talk about extend experiment to
make sure that I'm doing as a side
project it's called elvish some of them
may have thinners because this is once
being posted on a hacker news
well the reason I developed this gel is
driven by two motivations wanting some
more serious language because can see
the code here is so it's real code it's
real visual code from thee from Chapter
five of the visual user guide
I won't call a language that allows you
to write something like this a serious
language is more ridiculous than Perl
even it and also a more friendly user
interface and by friendly I actually
mean two things why it's friendly for
newbies it's OOP so it has to have same
defaults so like we all know with some
some some shall we the default is almost
sound useable like some unnamed editor
so and also the another another expect
of friendliness I find is also friend is
for for for the for this event uses so
as to be very customizable okay so now
we come to the language so this still
works in elvish so you can now believe
that it's actually a shell it's not some
other kind of language so this stuff I
need to explain this stuff it basically
gets the output of the curled message
ring and sign four lines that contain a
and sordin and remove the application
put it to a file yep also our
mathematics so every time I have when I
have to do some quick calculation with
my computer I always have to struggle
with an eye
Python NBC because I patent take one
minute to start and BC has their limited
capability so nobody Elvis you don't
have to struggle for this anymore
because it has arithmetic so this is the
division to division instead of integer
division and the second example looks
pretty like Lisp yes it is and you can
have functions can does anybody know
what that he is supposed to me yeah it's
determinants for calculating
determinants of 2 times 2 matrix which
is something I do every day and tables
and closures yeah I told you it's a
serious language so he has datatypes
beyond simple strings so we have tables
tables is basically a hybrid of a list
and the dictionary I love the one and
actually the reason I have to combine
them is that I run out of brackets we
have this you know we have square
brackets round brackets and curly
brackets but I've run out of there I
cannot come up with more brackets so I
just use the square brackets for both if
anybody has a cool suggestion please
tell me so you see this is these two big
hybrids so it can be indexed with either
number or a stream and we have closures
and now here I would present you the
hello world program in elvish it's the
it's a pretty Java SH way that - hello
the world you actually first construct a
lower Factory and it rings like this I
explain that later and then you give a
parameter to the factory which gives you
a lower and it's a lower of the world
and then you call the whole lower well I
was actually joking because this is
another way you actually write hello
world and to understand this code too
we can simply come compare it to the
you JavaScript equivalent so you can see
that we do have serious constructs like
closures so closures are also first
value first-class values as our tables
and in traditional shells that believes
you only have strings and yes I've
talked about this we have many kind of
first-class values strings tables
closures boolean's and and they are
actually some more and the extraordinary
thing maybe about average is that
command output may contain values
instead of just pipes like the
traditional pipeline so here's an
example we find out the oldest articles
of valve issues login names has the
string broke we can see a combination of
the traditional pipe line and the pipe
line that actually carries discrete
values here because we all know the curl
command you just pulls out some some
URLs or added content to stand out and
to and then the past Jason command will
take these bytes and convert them to
values but it turns out that the this
URL will actually give an array instead
of many Jason's so we use unpacked
command in elvish which turns an array
of stuff into just Stringham stuff and
we iterate through the stream and we
strategize gnorga name and now we are
getting back to bite again so to find
out all the lines contain both which as
described I'm getting a little bit crazy
I have only two slides left allow the
user interface it's not much because
I've been working on the language
recently but this there's still
something pretty cool to show off I
think it's called the navigation mode
and because
I believe some of you have some of you
have used some software called Ranger it
allows you to use your arrow keys to
navigate in them in the console which is
pretty cool I think and I believe that
these functionalities better built into
the shell so I did it and it actually
works unlike many other things in elvish
so well the project self is it's not
ready and that will only call it ready
when I use it as my own login shell a
lot of stuff I'm missing and a lot of
stuff are wrong yeah yeah welcome to
contribute yes
last time when I talked I suggest
against putting on a hacker newspad the
next day I saw it so if you want to do
it go ahead oh that's the end of my
presentation so I guess it's now time
for questions okay thank you for your
great presentation and sharing your
great code with us so does anybody have
any questions and yeah
is
you said you integrated Ranger features
is it actual Ranger code or is now your
own implementation now I cloned it okay
this Ranger is written Python and this
stuff is actually written in gold
sorry it's written in gold question so
anybody in your shell you can cost not
just strings yes between different
grammatical objects I am how do you make
the distinction between strings and
objects and how can you call that
program to return objects rather than
strings yeah actually the two channels
are always present both of them so you
can in principle you can have a command
that that outputs both the stream and
discrete values that's my solution at
the idea that the pipeline carries
values is actually stolen from from a
Microsoft Project PowerShell but I think
PowerShell has it tries to blur the
boundary between the values and return
the value pipeline and the stream
pipeline which I think it's really bad I
think is the best solution I've found so
far is to make these two pipelines
always to make these two pipes always
present so you're actually every command
has two inputs and two outputs sounds
awesome thank you
so does anybody have any more questions
okay so yeah once again thank you see
for your great presentation
[Applause]