Hello everyone．
In the software‚ radio‚ radio‚ dapp room．
First time 2022．
Good morning．
Good afternoon and good evening．
My name is Xian junjiao and I'm from ID Lab iMac and Gent University Belgium．
Let's talk about the open WiFi project again‚ like we did in every year．
First time since 2020．
It's the yearly update of the open WiFi project．
If you also talk about the future plan‚ plan．
In case there are new audiences．
Let me tell you what open WiFi is．
It is an open source WiFi chip design project written in verylog．
It's already functioning on the IPG board and can be used like a real WiFi card．
On the Linux‚ for instance‚ you can log in to the FPG board via SSH over Internet and operate the WiFi card like you do on resperry pie．
Just search Open my phone on the internet．
I believe you will find our project．
The project was online at the end of 2019．
After that‚ it keeps attracting attention along with time．
As in this star history figure‚ it increases almost linearly．
In the past two years．
There are two leaps in the figure．
Probably the first leap was due to the report by CN X Software News‚ and the second one was because of Hacker News Report report．
The first part is about the features and optimizations．
In the past year．
I have to admit that some of them are more complicated than our imagination‚ so the planned release was delayed several times．
Actually‚ no formal release in the past year‚ except some bug fixes and some small improvements．
Maybe at the presentation moment．
These works are still not released yet‚ but we have confidence to release these works in February 2022 because we have solved most of the issues after struggling more than one year．
The first feature is about the ampdu and block arc．
A M PDU stands for aggregated Mac P U‚ it allows the WiFi card to put multiple micro Pdus to a single physical layer packet．
So the gap and acknowledgment procedure after each macpdu is eliminated．
Apparently‚ because of this‚ transmission efficiency can be increased a lot．
This is an important feature introduced in WiFi 4 8 O2 dot 11 n．
It is optional in WiFi 4‚ but it has become mandatory since WiFi 5 8 O2 dot 11 AC‚ even if there's only one Mac PDU to be sent in WiFi 5‚ it has to be encapsulated in the A M PDU format‚ which is called single packet A m PDU．
Accordingly‚ the block act block acknowledgment was introduced as well．
In WiFi 4‚ it allows the WiFi card to aggregate the multiple acknowledgments into one big acknowledgment packet so that the acknowledgment for every single Mac PDU is not needed anymore．
Apparently‚ this will also increase the transmission efficiency‚ especially when it is used together with the amptu．
In the actual implementation‚ when Linux handles a Mac PDU to WiFi card‚ it only labels the packet that it can be aggregated or not．
Whether the packet will actually be aggregated and how many my Pdus will be aggregated．
It is the WiFi car's decision‚ not Linux‚ because only the card knows the exact transmission opportunity and how many specific packets in specific queues at that moment in the card．
So the A m PDU implementation involves quite a lot of FPJ work and not as simple as the concept．
And because of the aggregation capability‚ more packets can come in and go out in a short period of time for WiFi cards．
So it triggered some hidden box of our design‚ which is not seen before when the packet density is not that high．
Next‚ let's talk about a feature about WiFi privacy and security．
The CSI father CSI means the channel state information‚ which is available in the channel estimation module inside the WiFi receiver．
This is a refined and reflected feature based on the CSI Murder work we reported last year together with our partner．
Now you can use this feature with the open WiFi public release out of the box．
The idea is simple．
You can configure an artificial channel state information to the WiFi signal before it leaves the transmitter antenna．
Actually‚ it is a configurable F IR filter in between the WiFi baseband OFDM transmitter and the antenna．
And this operation won't destroy the normal WiFi communication because the receiver will do channel estimation and equalization anyway‚ no matter if the channel is the real environment channel or real environment channel combined with the artificial channel added inside the transmitter．
But for those sensing receivers that rely on the CSI reflecting‚ reflecting the real environment‚ the sensing won't work anymore because they don't know what kind of artificial CSI is added at the transmitter and only see a combined CSI and a receiver‚ which never reflect the real environment channel for authorized sensing receiver who knows the artificial CSI‚ they can recover the environment CSI from the combined CSI observed in the receiver．
You can find our Y SEC 21 paper‚ and the application note on GitHub．
The CSI father is actually manipulating the signal in the traditional security research fuzzing area‚ where people manipulate the bit in the WiFi PDU‚ there is an open WiFi based father called O W Fuss‚ which is developed by researchers in Alipay‚ which is part of Alibaba．
As you can see on their website‚ some CDS are disclosed already．
Next thing is about simple TX diversity．
Since many platforms have two TX attenders‚ a simple door alternative X diversity can be achieved with a tiny extra footprint．
It is almost identical to the CSD cyclic shift diversity defined in the WiFi standard．
To explain how it works‚ let's think about what happens if we fit the same or FDM symbol．
A signal to 2 attendance directly．
This is the simplest been forming case．
If the attendance bacing is appropriate‚ it could form a beam towards the right direction in the figure．
Then the problem is that for those stations in other directions‚ bad signals will be experienced because they are not in the main loop‚ they are in the side lobe．
What happens if we simply had a fixed time domain delay before the signal is sent to one of the attenders?
Amazing things will happen as we know that the OFDM signal includes multiple subcarriers‚ and different sub carriers actually means different frequencies．
The fixed time domain delay for different frequencies actually means different phase shifts．
Think about the fixed delay versus different or nonfixed period of different subcarriers．
According to the beam forming principle‚ the different face shift will generate beams towards different directions‚ So energy is delivered the different directions by different sub carriers．
In this case‚ no matter where the station is‚ it will have more or less the same signal strength‚ except that different sub carriers are received in different power levels．
But it is okay．
The WiFi receiver is supposed to work in frequency selective situations and it is the nature of the multipass environment．
The four color subcarriers and beams are just an inaccurate example here in the figure‚ the accurate analysis need to consider the multi plus fading in the environment．
There are also lots of enhancements and optimizations in architectural and low level．
For instance‚ the receiver has improved a lot for better demodulation capability sensitivity．
Also‚ the clocking scheme has been improved．
This is the clocking scheme before the RF clock ends at the baseband 5‚ and the baseband has its own clock‚ which is generated in the clock unit unit inside the arm processor A 5 4 writing reading rate control is needed to avoid IQ sample overflow or underflow due to the slight clocking speed difference between RF and IPG base baseband．
They have totally‚ totally independent crystal．
No‚ the RF clock drives everything from RFA‚ DCD AC to the open FA base band‚ till the DMA to the arm．
This leads to a more simplified cross clock domain design in the baseband and lower the timing jitter．
The actual cross clock domain happens inside the unprocessor DMA controller．
So it's not our business anymore．
Other optimizations are for helping people generate the project use and use the open WiFi card in a more easy way．
Now you have fewer steps than before to generate the IPG design project in vivado with the help of more functionalities in the script．
Many low level Mac and file configurations now can be simply set via a single register operation．
We also add test mode to the driver for easy experimental feature test and benchmarking by avoiding recompile the driver to switch between normal and experimental．
More importantly‚ after having all about features and optimizations‚ the whole design consumes less MP G resources than the previous release release．
Because we have put lots of effort into optimizing the design footprint to make sure it can fit into the entry level．
Zinc 7 or 20 IP GA‚ we really care about the entry level IPD board support because it is essential to help more users．
The name of the new release will be will seller‚ which is a beautiful place next to Leuven Belgium．
It is chosen by the main developer of the A M PDU feature mihail mahari from the vivado report for the entry level Z board‚ which has the zinc‚ some O 20 ipga‚ there are 10% reduction for the lookout table resource‚ 21% reduction for the flip flop‚ 6% reduction for the block Ram‚ and 26% reduction for the DSP blocks．
So for users who have the entry level ipja board‚ you are safe to have more open WiFi features．
Now let's talk about the bug fixes in the past year．
There are bugs about the duration field contention window increment mechanism too fast‚ 5 TX start signal time stamp issue with the IQ sample capture‚ which is reported by our user．
The short training frame‚ power level issue‚ and of course‚ the hidden bug seen by the high packet density brought by the a m PTU The complication is mainly due to the asynchronous nature of the CPU interrupt and IPG operation and effort of maintaining the related buffers and queues．
Lots of corner cases there in asynchronous system running in real time．
Let's take a look at the duration field．
Field issue．
The duration field in the WiFi packet indicates how much time occupation left is expected for the ongoing transaction‚ so other knows can predict when the channel will be released by the current traffic．
The Linux kernel Mag 8 to 11 module‚ as shown in the Linux kernel source code on this slide‚ calculates the value for this field only for 11 A and G‚ starting from 11 n‚ it assumes hardware handle this‚ which means starting from WiFi．
Four more functionalities are pushed to the chip instead of doing it at the kernel level‚ as you can see in the function．
If it's wi fi for and above the function‚ return immediately．
That's why at the beginning we weren't aware of this and always see the 11 N packet transmitted by open WiFi has duration field value 0．
Now we have implemented the calculation in open WiFi correctly．
Now‚ let's see some test results by a decent WiFi tester．
Road on swaths CMW 270．
It's probably the most advanced tester‚ which supports all WiFi standards and all subsix gigers frequencies．
Even those frequencies other than 2．4 and 5 gigers．
This is the basic test test set up on the left are the tester and open WiFi board‚ connected via Co X cable．
On the right are those are some screenshots．
The spectrum mask‚ EBM‚ time‚ time‚ domain‚ power‚ etcetera．
We have tested the open WiFi R sensitivity via the tester after our efforts of optimizing the baseband I PJ receiver．
The main conclusion is that the sensitivity is much better than the standard required‚ and similar to those typical commercial WiFi for chips．
EDM is also quite good．
It achieves -39 d B with a big spectrum mask margin．
It is as expected since 89 3 6 1 is a quite good and also quite expensive RF chip‚ and there is no external power amplifier in our test‚ which is‚ usually harmful for EDM‚ but we don't have PA if we sacrifice some spectrum mask margin further‚ the EDM can even achieve -41 d B‚ which is already capable of running 4K core modulation of WiFi 7．
Regarding the community‚ we are very happy to see new hardwares emerging in the past year．
The first one is Ant SDR‚ which is a new commercial product from a Chinese company．
The phone factor is quite small．
I guess that's why it's called an ant．
The main tips on board are 89 3 6 1 and zinc 7 O 20．
The entry level version has 89 3 6 3．
Instead‚ its support has been merged into Open A five mainline．
The price was only about $300 at the beginning on Aliexpress．
It's more expensive now due to the tip shortage during the past two years．
The second one is an 89 3 6 1 SDR hat for zylinx Pine Q board‚ which is quite cheap and widely used for Python based machine learning with IPG acceleration．
The solution is from a Chinese hobbyist and supposed to be also very cheap．
He has run Open My five successfully on the Pine Q and SDR hat‚ which is made by himself．
The interesting thing about this design is that the HDM I and P mode IOP of the Pine Q board are converted to LVDS pairs to transfer the high speed IQ sample between the pan Q board and 89 3 6 1．
The last one is also from a Chinese maker．
The design is by kikat‚ which is the most popular open source hardware design．
E D a tool．
The USBC dongle looks quite decent and compact．
I hope it could become real in the future．
In the first time 2021‚ I mentioned that low cost hardware was essential and expected for many entry level users．
Now the dream is becoming real for the entry level of WiFi board‚ the price has become half of what it was before．
I believe there will be more and more open WiFi hardware in the future about the new papers and applications from the user community．
Do check out the publication and application note directories on our GitHub．
Here is a list of those works from our users‚ such as the fuzzing tool for security research．
Well‚ this time sensitive network software‚ defined network and the master thesis that tried to buy to mymo successfully．
Regarding our current focus‚ the first one is about improving maturity of our design．
It is not a fancy and exciting concept‚ but lots of hard work．
I won't explain the detailed work‚ but I'd like to share with you a story I like very much to explain．
Let me ask you a question．
How to draw a horse．
Actually‚ you only need five steps．
Step 1‚ draw two circles．
Step two‚ draw legs．
Step 3‚ draw face and ​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌feet．
Step 4‚ draw hair．
Step 5‚ add some details．
Having an idea and building a demo sometimes only means that you finished step 1 to step 4‚ but without step 5‚ it will never come true．
True‚ the next focus is WiFi 6 8 O2 dot 11 a x．
We have built the WiFi 6 transmitter which is under testing and optimization with the help of the RN SC MW 270 tester．
WiFi 6 defines different types of physical layer PDU for the first time in the WiFi standard‚ we have implemented the single user Phi PDU‚ which can be used for single user uplink and down link．
The multi user 5 PDU‚ which is for AP to multiple stations simultaneously via OFDM a‚ the trigger based 5 PDU‚ which is for multiple stations to AP simultaneously via OFDM a‚ we will start to implement the receiver in 2022．
The future plan‚ of course‚ the first thing will be the WiFi 6 receiver‚ which will be hard‚ but we still plan to go for it．
If you want to help‚ just let me know．
Next‚ we will also continue to support our user community regarding new ideas‚ new applications‚ new hardwares‚ etc．．
Last but not least‚ add some details．
That is all for the presentation．
But don't leave not finish yet．
I have made a short video to recap the exciting moment of open WiFi in the past year．
Please watch‚ watch．
Alright‚ hello．
Hey‚ very yes．
And you will be．
Yes‚ but I think we are live．
Well‚ first of all‚ thank you very much for this‚ very interesting update on a very interesting project．
I'm all interested‚ I'm always looking a lot forward to your work．
Yes．
I mean yes‚ but I think we are live．
I have‚ I have some echoes．
Anybody else having those echoes?
I think now it's okay because I have two windows．
Okay‚ perfect．
Yeah．
Always looking forward to your talks．
Always very interesting．
So we have a couple of questions lined up here．
First one is by Andre．
He's asking‚ how does the performance and functionality of open WiFi compared to regular commercial ship sets?
Now‚ I guess you will answer it．
Quite a bit of that already in your talk．
Or maybe you can elaborate a little bit more for the art performance．
I think‚ is similar‚ but we don't have PA‚ so the TX power is low．
Regarding the throughput‚ I think we are also similar in the release．
We will release soon．
I think the physical layer could achieve‚ around 70 mega BPS if you run a perf‚ considering all the overhead‚ you can have around 50 BPS more or less similar to the commercial WiFi for a single attendance chip‚ I think．
Okay‚ that sounds really good．
And I guess that also answers Johannes question‚ who was asking which speeds are supported so far?
We have another question lined up‚ by Jimin．
He's asking why basic WiFi chips looks so small‚ but all WiFi requires roughly eightyfive elements．
Actually‚ eightyfive loot‚ includes lots of‚ not necessary and logic like those‚ 89 3 6 1 interfacing‚ etcetera for the core open life and logic．
If you look at the vivado report it consume‚ I think less than 20K route．
Okay‚ so it's‚ it's actually a logo number．
And then we have one from Daniel．
Daniel is asking‚ do you use the P L 3‚ 3‚ 0 DMA in the zoom?
Or do you have ADMA implemented‚ and FGA fabric?
Well‚ I don't think we are using PR social 0 DMA‚ because I'm using the A X I streaming DMA in the IPG site．
We have the a x I streaming DMA block‚ and it connects to the zinc arm processor HP port．
There are HP 0 to HP 3‚ and some of them also connect to the ACP port．
I think PLL‚ p L 3 3 is 0 DMA is another DMA module‚ not the one we are using．
Okay‚ okay‚ I see．
I guess that's the well then with another remark．
Okay‚ yeah．
But I guess that's the questions．
Your honor's question was basically answered．
Which speeds are supported so far?
Let me check．
Any other questions?
Yes‚ for the WiFi．
4 speed indeed is close to the WiFi 14．
The 5‚ 5‚ 6 we are doing‚ we target‚ still the 20 micros as well．
So the peak speed won't be increase a lot because the bandwidth is there．
Yeah‚ I see．
And we have to like 30 seconds．
Left me 1 question for my set．
Like‚ how big is the team that's currently working on the project?
I think‚ in the past few years‚ we have‚ like 2‚ PhD‚ and‚ 2 postdoc now．
One of the P H D's already postdoc．
And now last year we have new a fresh PhD joined from Netherlands‚ actually 20．