Hello imarband‚ this is Xian Jun from Open WiFi Project．
Open WiFi is an open source WiFi cheap design that was announced in first time 2020．
This year we are here again．
Nice to see you all．
Although I cannot see you actually．
Anyway‚ let's get started．
We are a small software defined radio group in the various group of ID Lab iMac Gent University Belgium．
This is the agenda of my presentation．
First‚ the open WiFi project．
Progress in the first year after online will be introduced‚ then with some further explanations and highlights．
Next‚ I will talk about our community growth situation．
Then is the idea of low cost hardware‚ which I believe will boost our community a lot．
The last one is the road map of 2021．
Come on．
Some of you might think this presentation is not as interesting as last year‚ right?
No worry．
Let me show you something cool．
I remind you‚ this is not a go．
Okay‚ that's all for today．
Thank you．
Any questions?
I'm joking．
Let's get started．
The boring part．
And you can prepare questions．
Meanwhile‚ the first thing is about how do we decide the release name gentyuan and luwen actually before the project online at the end of 2019‚ we 3 developers agreed that for each release‚ a developer will pick a name of a place on the earth to assign it at the code name．
Wait on the earth or in the universe?
I can't remember clearly．
Maybe it should be in the universe after all．
Elo mask is going to live on the mouths‚ but the first three releases will be named by me Wei and mihail‚ which is the order of joining the project．
I create the project at first‚ then we help you a lot on open OFDM project porting and testing‚ and many other stuffs mihail wrote the OFDM transmitter and also did lots of work to enable the 11 end feature．
So the first release name hint is chosen by me．
Ghent is the beautiful city in Belgium where we work．
The open WiFi was born in Technology Park‚ Ghent‚ where our office located．
The second release name Taiyuan is chosen by Wei．
Taiyuan is her hometown and also the capital of Shaanxi province of China．
The third release name luwen‚ is chosen by mihail because he lives in louven‚ which is another beautiful city in Belgium and close to Brussels．
The future release will be decided by the developer who contribute the most to the release．
This will show respect to the people who actually did the job．
Talk is cheap．
Show me the code．
Next‚ highlight CS ICSI means channel state information for physical year researcher is also called frequency response or channel transformation function．
Anyhow‚ the CS I believe it's available in all the WiFi chips‚ but few of them exposed the CSI to you as open WiFi is designed by us‚ so we can expose CSI definitely to external environment．
For instance‚ now you can access CSI very easily on open WiFi．
Why our set China?
Actually we can expose modern CSI．
So here I can call CSI cheap state information．
A typical usage of the CSI is to detect the object in the environment．
For instance‚ human movement‚ human gesture‚ people falling down．
For instance‚ in this picture．
And the link is here．
This is a paper．
You can find lots of paper about CSI application．
They collect the CSI‚ from the transmitter to the receiver．
The transmitter could be the AP in your home‚ right?
And they collect CSI and receiver and running machine learning or classification algorithm to estimate or detect what is in between the transmitter and receiver．
Here‚ the human gesture is an example．
I think it's a very interesting application and lots of company are working on this to count people‚ detect people．
But apparently there will be some privacy concern‚ as you can imagine．
If I am a bad guy‚ I can receive your AB signal from outside your house and try to detect something inside‚ right?
So CSI is just a tool．
Use it in a good way‚ bad way．
Depends on people．
So how can we protect people from the bad usage of the CSI here?
You can find a work from one of our experimenter in the Oka project is called CSI murder murder the CSI here is the link．
You can check all the details online．
Basic principle is also not difficult Since the Oklahoma chip is designed by us‚ we can had some random or fake CSI before the signal lift antenna of the transmitter．
Then in this way‚ when you try to collect CR CSI via the receiver‚ actually‚ you collect the combined CSI of the actual CSI and the fixed CSI‚ so with this fake unknown CSI‚ your machine learning or classification won't work anymore．
So if a WiFi‚ AP‚ or some transmitter could give people this option‚ then people will have right to‚ let the CSI work or not．
I think that would be a good progress of the CSI technology actually follow this direction．
You can imagine lots of interesting papers or research‚ right?
Because it's attack defense‚ attack defense．
There will be an endless work．
I think next highlight is about the IQ sample．
I guess all the people in this room know what is IQ sample．
Because most of the SDR device offer you IQ sample streaming from antenna to your computer or from your computer to the antenna with open WiFi design．
Definitely we can also do that．
But here we hasn't you IQ sample in a different or in a clever way because our IQ sample capture function is under a trigger condition．
We won't do a streaming to the computer．
Our IQ sample capture is triggered by the signal inside IP G by the event‚ for instance‚ the event of decoding success‚ the event of preamble de detection‚ the event of the channel from idle to busy‚ the event of the channel from B d to idle．
We have defined a 32 event for you to select when you capture the IQ sample．
So what‚ why do we develop this feature?
The original purpose is for ourselves to debark our design．
Because at the beginning‚ phase‚ we realize how lowlevel Mac is not ideal．
We generate a lot of a collision in the air．
So the question is‚ how can we come capture the collision moment and then deduct further of our I PJ design?
Then we find out this ID capture．
For instance‚ how do we use the capture to capture the collision?
We do it like this．
We set up normal communication between open WiFi and pier WiFi station via the men attend‚ right?
But on our platform‚ there is a secondary antenna．
We call it a monitoring antenna．
We can put this antenna via cable close to the PR WiFi station．
Then we set the agriculture event be that we are transmitting．
Meanwhile‚ we detect the SSI from the monitoring antenna above a threshold．
Actually‚ this means when we are transmitting‚ the other side is also trying to transmit．
That means a collision in the air because the packet will be overlap in the air．
So in this way‚ we capture the collision．
We analyze what happens in our IP GA‚ analyze the time before‚ time after．
You know that you can define the capture position‚ How many pre IQ sample could be stored?
It's a powerful tool．
And the secondary usage could be‚ that help you debug your receiver．
For instance‚ if you set the trigger condition to the CRC fail‚ then you can capture all the WiFi packet‚ that is not decoded successfully by our I PJ‚ then we do analyze offline on those IQ sample in Python to optimize or improve our receiver algorithm．
And the third usage‚ apparently there are two attenders．
You can already‚ capture two attender A Q samples and to develop or verify your mymo algorithm in the early phase‚ prepare for the mymo development．
Okay‚ the next highlight is application notes．
Actually‚ we learn this from those IC company and S R S LTE cause we noticed that s RSL t also prepare lots of‚ application notes document online．
We have set up the application notes document directory in the GitHub．
Currently‚ there are 9 application nodes covered from basic usage in different mode until the WiFi for introduction and the packaging injection．
It's very useful for test and apparently also the CSI ACU capture stuff．
Definitely if you want to explore those potential areas potential usage of our platform‚ do check out the application notes Notes．
These highlights cover lots of things．
Essential update．
As you can see in the video‚ I cannot go through them or in this meeting．
What I want to say is that they are really‚ really important．
For instance‚ at the beginning‚ user keep telling us sometimes in they encounter the colonel crash‚ colonel panic‚ or the driver dress．
And we spent lots of effort on this．
Finally‚ it push us to do a better design for the FPG arm in interaction mechanism．
Because when the for processor system‚ you can never assume the processor will handle the interrupt in time．
The interrupt sometimes is handled in time by the processor‚ but sometimes several interrupt．
They are cute and they are delayed and they and they arrive the CPU or wake up CPU suddenly in a very short time．
So lots of state information have to be stored somewhere．
You cannot drop them because you don't know when the processor will process them．
Anyhow‚ lots of lots of details between the WiFi driver and IPG hardware．
You can feel the big improvement if you run our current design‚ versus the beginning‚ initial design．
Okay‚ next topic is about the community engagement or the community growth situation．
I would say we did a good job regarding this．
If you check the open up by GitHub in the one year period‚ we got 1．6K stars．
That's already a lot‚ I would say‚ in this very narrow or professional domain．
And 200 folks around 100 watch and several issues still open．
Three internal developers you have known before and with also three external contributors．
Surprisingly‚ although their code hasn't been merged yet．
But I believe some of those code will be merged in this year．
But if you compare our project to another very hot ipga project in the processor domain‚ the rocket chip‚ the leading‚ cheap design project of the Risk 5 domain on GitHub‚ they are online for two years and some company‚ I think‚ already take out the lucky chip．
They have 1．7K stars‚ more or less the same‚ but they have much more folks watch issues and contributors‚ apparently their communities much bigger and more active than ours．
I think the reason could be related to the question I raised to you last year．
Why the computer science for me is so open and activity‚ domain is so close．
I don't know why‚ why‚ but there could be also some other reasons．
For instance‚ people maybe are so satisfied with the commercial WiFi．
Cheap to play with‚ no matter for hacking‚ for security research of false IoT application．
They are quite happy why they will use open WiFi and maybe because we are lacking the killer application of features that can only be done by open WiFi．
Actually‚ we are offering some of them like the CS ICSI murder IQ sample．
I think more will come．
For this part I we are also eagerly want to hear from you．
The third reason could be that the Linux driver staff．
As I mentioned before‚ the processor IPG interruption and IPG development are too difficult for many developers because I think‚ maybe the user space program is a bit easier for most of the developers because you software run in the pure CPU environment‚ no external interaction．
And the last reason could be that the hardware is too expensive．
Although we have try hard to push our design to a cheaper platform．
For instance‚ at the beginning of design run on the SC 7 O 6‚ which cost you around 404‚ $4000．
Now we can run on that port plus RF cost you only $900．
It's already a big push‚ but WiFi cheap only cost you half dollar‚ even less that there's still a huge difference．
I think this huge difference sometimes make‚ make the people difficult to make decision．
So if you have any idea or theory about the reason‚ do come and tell us．
We really want to grow the community．
Okay‚ regarding the local hardware‚ I have been looking at the possibility for a long time．
The final conclusion is like this‚ not final conclusion‚ initial conclusion．
I believe the open WiFi‚ the cheap open WiFi platform could be the price could be as low as $200．
Some of you already seen a long discussion‚ long several days discussion on Twitter about the cheap and hardware price．
At the end of 2020．
I guess during that time‚ lots of people had holidays．
So we have time to do the discussion anyway．
I also discuss in person with many hardware makers in Western and in China．
I feel that in the future there will be a cheaper open WiFi platform．
The price would be around $200‚ even cheaper．
Let's see．
New feature plant?
Well‚ we have spent one year to realize there isn't any feature that is easy‚ even a small feature．
A back weeks．
All things are not easy actually．
So we will be very careful to plan a new features regarding the difficulty and the resource we have．
So in this year‚ we will start to work on the WiFi 6 or 11 a X standard．
This year‚ maybe the basic physical layer transmitter receiver‚ will be developed．
And also the Mimo‚ since we have prepared some basic tools like the dual autono agriculture‚ and we also have some masterthesis working on that．
So mymo will also be started start from the atenna switch of diversity receiver and let's see‚ what can we achieve in this year?
Maybe during summer‚ we could also make a proposal to Google to hire some students via the Google Summer of Code．
I don't know．
Let's see．
Breaking news．
I think this is the big news this year．
Always big news comes at the end of each year‚ right?
Last year‚ open my 5．
This year the blade I blade I've．
They also released the WiFi design for their ipga on their SBR down a board．
Although their design and our our design‚ there are lots of difference．
I think basically we do the same domain．
Design the WiFi hardware．
The cheap via the IP GI think this is a good sign also for us．
That means in this community‚ the WiFi IPG design is an actual need from the community‚ not only our imagination．
So we will keep watching and well‚ let's see．
We hope this could encourage more and more people to think about playing the WiFi in a very deep level．
Deep into Driver and IPG to come up with much‚ much‚ much wild‚ more wild ideas．
A quick recap of today's‚ presentation．
First one is that we have made lots of progress on different aspect aspect in the first year online‚ online‚ I'm proud of the project and our developers．
We will push further for the advanced features like the WiFi 6 and my more‚ but we realized they cannot be done in one night．
But we will keep moving．
And for the community‚ we will also try harder to grow it．
Regarding this point‚ we do need your help．
No help is very‚ very welcome．
Even you．
You never use our design‚ but you can mention it‚ right?
To some other people．
You think our design might help them?
That's also a very good help．
And thank you in advance．
And finally‚ if the break news‚ another WiFi．
IPG design‚ I think that means more people will join this deep player．
Deep WiFi playing domain‚ domain domain domain domain．
We will keep moving‚ moving‚ keep voting．
Sometimes competition is good for the ecosystem．
Alright‚ this time‚ this is the real end of my presentation．
Any questions?
Please do communicate with us．
My bye．
Tie‚ so on．
Okay‚ most devoted questions from Daniel about the CSI functionality．
Yeah‚ this is quite good question．
So the basic concept is that we involve‚ a fake‚ channel response at the transmitter．
So if you consider a very simple single attender communication‚ scenario‚ if‚ if the real channel is a WGN‚ right?
If you add the fake frequency selective‚ channel on the signal‚ then the‚ I guess the whole link will be degradated After all‚ it‚ it turns from a WGN to a frequency selective channel．
But the real case is like this．
If you monitor CSI for a normal WiFi link‚ the there's always frequency selectivity‚ either caused by the arch or caused by the multi part．
So in this case‚ when we add‚ some slight‚ frequency selectivity at the transmitter‚ I don't think it will be bring a big degradation to the whole system．
So the basic principle is that‚ we make sure our fake‚ CSI is added after all the processing．
Just maybe‚ be before the I FFT‚ we add‚ the frequency selectivity on each sub carrier or after f I FFT in the time domain‚ add a filter．
Then the receiver site doesn't need to know this receiver or the whole bunch of receiver algorithm will treat the fake channel plus real channel as a whole‚ right?
So receiver don't need to aware that receiver don't need to modify Modi modified work with the fake CSI so‚ yeah．
But I believe for the mymo case‚ could be more complicated．
But the basic principle we should follow is that we add the fake channel after all the precoding‚ the informing operation‚ then let the whole‚ inner‚ inner part of the whole system‚ as a whole‚ right?
The fake channel plus real channel as a whole．
If you follow this principle‚ the receiver‚ Don't need to be changed．
There's one situation．
If the if the transmitter need receiver to do the feedback of the channel state information to help transmitter to come up with the optimal precoding．
In that case‚ I think the transmitter need to consider this fake channel added at the transmitter site because the feedback‚ the feedback from receiver will include the fake channel response．
And yeah．
But then the signal transmit‚ transmit will transmitted will also include that．
I think lots of things could be down there in this‚ anti antisensing or channel stuff．
So a second question came up just right now‚ the from young‚ don't devices like plural SDR‚ hacker f repita and others have an FPJ that could be suitable for open WiFi．
And what is holding you back reporting to do those platform?
The basic reason is that IPG on those platform is‚ too small for our current design．
Our current design is a basic single A 10 to 2011 n design 11 AGN the smallest IPG currently we are working on is 7 0 20 on Bluetooth is 7 0 10．
IP GA high even much smaller．
So so we need figure RPG?
Yeah‚ that's the reason．
Okay‚ perfect．
And then‚ the probably last question that we can ask is‚ what is the main motivation to work on open WiFi?
Like even after these‚ awesome．
After the awesome work you did the last year‚ what is is the main motivation for open WiFi to exist?
I think men motivation．
Well‚ the first motivation is that we realize‚ before our project‚ when people want to work on the cheap level of the WiFi‚ design‚ if they want to test the‚ their new ideas on the cheap level‚ they don't have‚ so much freedom‚ of‚ of free choices．
They need the National Instruments WiFi application framework or they need the bar design or for the reference design design for Mango communication with the we the license condition with some license fee．
So we will​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ decide to come up with a free software design on this‚ to help people‚ have have a more‚ more choice‚ more free choices．
And in this action‚ we also‚ I think lower the whole bunch of the whole reference design software plus hardware．
We lower the price a lot．
So this could encourage‚ more lab‚ lab or universal city．
A group could jump into this field‚ if they have a limit．