High elf welcome to this special edition of The Internet of Things podcast which is brought to you by ring
Ring doorbells and outdoor security cameras are built with home security in mind
To discover discounts and find out more information
About rings
Security Prada
Go2www
You. Ring
Dot-com
/ Stacy
That's s t a c
Ey
And now enjoy the podcast with
My take it first
First and then several interviews from
People I met on the Shelf
Last week I went to CD in San Diego
And CD is this trade show aimed at the custom installer Market
These are the professionals
To put those awesome AV systems
High-end lighting and other electronics into the homes you might see in places like
I don't know architectural Digest
So think of
Easy things like a TV screen that unfolds to show you a movie by the pool
Or something that takes your lighting and controls it based on your mood or time of day
I
Probably could come up with other crazy examples except I am just not fancy enough
Much of the show is dedicated to professional AV audio visual equipment
There are so many speakers
Fairmount and row after row Movie Theater seating
But smart home stories still wherever
I saw several startups worth calling out such as Neo which is Bill to Hub
I know it's a hub
But it has all the radios you need like Wi-Fi Bluetooth zigbee Z-Wave
Cute
Is it okay to say cute
It's askew
Black and silver
Housing
And then it also has a remote
That goes with it in this remote design
Is gorgeous
It is very Sleek looking at has a
Beautiful screen on it and it has a sensor on the back
And what that sensor does is it
What is a reading the palm of
Your hand
And in doing so
It is able to tell
Who has the remote control in their hand and so it will offer personalized recommendations for that
Person so you may have many different net
Accounts
But when you pick up that remote
You're only going to see
Your Netflix
I'm a little
Worried about the
The startup it's based income
I'm worried about its ability to actually
Last for very long but I'm hoping that someone snaps it up because it really looked
Compelling it was a Kickstarter
Another cool startup that I saw was called hibersense
And this startup is trying to make my dream of not having a thermostat
On the wall
True what it does
This is
Like many of the companies that offer
Control of
Vents in your house like kinor
Ecovent
This company offers control of both dampers and vent sweeties
Connected
Motorized
Opener thingies but it also has a sensor that goes in every room
The sensors measure the temp
Temperature
City all of that and they use that to control your AC and HVAC on an individual room
And every time I talk about
Companies doing this again about you notes for
HP AC installers Clear Lake
You blow out you know your ductwork with too much pressure
So these guys actually say they take all of that into account so
If you're in only one room in the house and everyone's there and all the others you want shutdown it actually probably won't
Do that cuz it would create too much of
Pressure on your deck
But
I loved the startup
I loved the idea that one day you won't have a thermostat
And they're trying to make that a reality
Again
I don't know if they're going to hit it for
They're going to be around for the Long Haul but I liked where they were going
There are also some
A lot of router
Companies running around so I saw some companies that were offering
Basically the ability for you
To put parental control inside
Security software
On a router made by
Another OEM so the OEM has to buy
The software
But then you can also extend it through apps on people smartphone
The benefit there is
If you tell your teenager
That
At 10
Heater turning off WiFi throughout the house
For their devices
Then most likely they're going to hop on their phone and
I'll just use the LTE networks text
But in this way you can actually
With a pond
Their phone
You can actually
Turn off
Their LTE network
As well so I thought that kind of offer to
Hole
A whole device solution maybe that was worth noting
Cool stuff from big companies to
So LG
Had this $20,000 television
That was to OLED screen
Mountain
Back to back
Initiative
It
Was gorgeous
It is for
Retail
Primarily
And it's only in portrait
But holy cow you guys
They offered this at landscape
And I had $20,000 I would totally put
Actually maybe you don't need it back.
I would just like my TV
That was
That was awesome
Lutron also launched a new product line that sits between is
Professional-grade
Maestro
Dimmers and switches and it's DIY
Acetylene
The Maestro lion uses
Is a different radio protocol
Best facial Denver
But what Lutron is done
Is a taken things like
The concept of a smart bridge and
Programming based on an app
And they brought that up
To its Maestro radio
Saratu
Radio now
Professional installers this is only through professionals is not for like
DIY people
But if you have more than I have
50 lights you can't control
So you're going to move up into this
Pro-Line
And
You can program it with an app
Which means someone might
Come in and install it for you
But then you can tweak it
The rest of your life without calling the
That actually ties into a lot of Trends we're going to talk about me
Little bit on the show soap
Keep that in mind
This idea of having a pearl come in
Install it for you and then leave your life forever
And
I also found out
Kevin and I couple episodes were kind of a little bit wrong
Not that we would have known it
I ran into some SmartThings p
At the event
And they were showing off smart thing
In
Wi-Fi routers and
Is the SmartThings Hub
But what they weren't showing is SmartThings in a TV
So I asked him about it and they said Hold Ya weave
But that basically we're not doing that anymore
It may one day come back but they're not doing it now be
Because they think that TVs are trying to make them skinnier
And flattered
And adding more videos just runs
Counter to that
But
Don't worry SmartThings The Hub is not going away
It's still going to exist and what they are doing
Is putting SmartThings into Samsung's new line of Wi-Fi
So they've got a mesh Wi-Fi
A system that will
SmartThings software
Zigbee and Z-Wave radios in there
And
It should be
Out there ready for
You're looking for SmartThings in a TV
Stop looking
Even though they said that would happen to
Just not going to have
Now those are some of the cool things that I saw
But I decided that since
This is my first year at
I should probably get more
So I talked to Julie Jacobson
Who is the founding editor of CEO
She is like
The city
She knew everyone there and actually what we were doing our conversation
Someone even walked by and said
Is that Julie and then they snapped a picture during the interview
But before we get to the things that Julie thought were
Let's take a moment
For a message
From our sponsor
Rick
Everyone we are breaking into the
Special CDF
Episode of the internet
Podcast for a message
From our sponsor
Talk about
More than doorbells
Hey Jamie how are you doing
Good how you doing
Awesome
Let's just get started with what
Because you have moved
Beyond doorbell
Into this
Concept of building a ring of six
What does that even mean
Bring a company our mission is around a different kind of neighborhoods
What is a Solutions company until you started with
Important place for any homeowner any Resident to secure
Delivering the presents to naturally help protect homes in neighborhood
And then we moved to the ring a straight down the hall
The other products
Thornell coming out look like
Spotlight cams and all these other cameras and now can go around your home
And then later in the year will be
Okay write an alarm system
But before we get to that
Which is exciting
Talk to me a little bit about how
Cameras
Doorbells
Help
Your neighborhood
Not just you
What we found is that what
Really impacting neighborhood is the lack of
Cousins in the neighborhood
Delivering presents
What are products
Intellectuality a motion detection
Allowing you to answer your door from wherever you are
Russia able to reduce crime in neighborhood
A real true that we did a study with the LAPD when we play
10% of homes in a neighborhood with the ring video doorbell
And in that study available to reduce crime by 55%
By just having 10% of the homes with having that presence of the Ring video doorbell and adding that presents back into the neighborhood
That is awesome
And we're going to hear more about that in a little bit
And now to Julie Jacobson of ZTE Pro on the cool stuff she saw it CDA
I think we've been sort of saddled with complete custom work in our industry and what happens is
An integrated will go into a home and complete completely set up a configured system and when they walk away the consumer
Kind of stuck with that may have to call the installer for every little change so what we're really saying is a trend towards person
Conversation were you giving the end-user themselves many more tools to configure their systems once the install is
Household
What do you think is going to be
The impact of DIY type stuff and smart home stuff on the industry
Canyon early on was Ohno everyone's going to go DIY but I think it's been clear not just to the
Integrators but to the larger industry as well everyone from Amazon and Google
Down to the Nick markets that the integrators provided very necessary service I mean let's face it we can
Lawn mower Lawns but not everyone wants to mow their lawn so he mass-market is bringing so much awareness and
So much attention so much excitement to the mass-market about smart home technologies that are really good
Can only benefit those who install the stuff for a living what is some of the most exciting Tech you seen at the show
Fighting is kind of a strange word in our industry because it's little things like control4 is that an if-then
10 engine into their home automation software to allow as we discussed earlier to allow consumers to
Create their own scenes after the installer is left
But there's also a bunch of mass-market things you excite me that the Samsung frame TVs I think they're fast
Mating
For single lot of applications for
Motion art moving art barcode very high-end
Producer of video projection screens is teaming up with Neo that's in Rio
With a motion art
Service and you're saying some fantastic applications about here in the show so it really runs
Pogamat from Amazon Echo is huge and it's having a huge impact even on premium products Georgia
Acoustics of showing a product that
Pair Echo streaming and control with the premium multi-room audio
So we're staying at really a wonderful blend of DIY with premium products and services
Is Julie mentioned origin acoustics
Scare was awesome
You have to buy it from a professional installer but the capability it gives is really compelling
The system
Call the valet
And it's a more powerful speaker Plus
Power and ceiling cover for the echo
So you'll end up buying for Echo dots for about
$200
And then you get this kit with
Set the mounting system and a superior speaker for about six
And suddenly you have liked
The premium in-ceiling speaker setup that acts as a microphone to capture any command set
But it wasn't all cool technology
The biggest things I think I saw at the showare to
Is the business model challenges facing the professional installers in
Companies like control4 in Crest
And the other
Was
Perhaps
What might say that
Which is I'm going to call it the rise of something called
Do it for me
So if you consider that many of us RDI wires that do it for ourselves
And then there are those people who pay for fancy systems in their home
And how other people install it for them
The do it for me concept is somewhere in the middle kind of like that
New Lutron sir
Basically you take consumer-grade technology like a nest thermostat or hue bulbs
And you get someone else like
Custom installer to come in and do it for them
This is kind of what Amazon is doing with its installing server
Best Buy's betting on that for
The Geek Squad
And you even see it from some
Professional monitoring
Like alarm.
Honeywell
And
Tim Becker day the director of product marketing at a company called savant
Which I like to think of his Apple
A smart home
Talks about why the do it for me model
Might not be the worst thing to happen
Professional
What are the trends that we're seeing here is the
Do it for me
Concept which is where the custom integrators come in and
They are
Starting people
What do you think about that
First thing you know some of them see it as an opportunity to
Get clients
Early to get them started on maybe a simple any
People in Hawaii Market
Yuge
But
You're my friend he's a banker
And he does not want to deal with his own technology
He wants to
Come home and just have it work
But he also doesn't want to spend alot of money
So you know he can have a cup
Masala come in
And put in
Some of those
Consumer-grade
Pieces for a door lock
And security and you know maybe thermostats and maybe some lights
That you can pick up today at a Home Depot
But they don't
People don't want to install themselves
From the air that it comes to me the greater hazard
Customer that has a
Brass Durga
Going to get married
The step up the same way someone who's
Buying a Toyota today might be buying a BMW tomorrow and
They might be in the market for a Ferrari
Hope
A lot of these
Oh here in the channels
Field that customer base
Give them that
That service
Throughout their lifetimes that when they
Move up
They get older
They get to know
Maury
And one
Bigger better
You know more integrated
However
Even as companies find a business and helping install things like nest
Amazon Echo
This could be very disruptive
To the business model
Foremost custom integrators
Richard Gunther with digital media Zone
Who has his own podcast on the smart home explained
All right Richard so big thing we're seeing here is all the diy things are trying to go pro
Is it going to work
Time when all of these big companies
Microsoft and Apple and
Google are
Putting product out there in
Setting expectations for users
You
Have people paying
Top dollar for custom systems
If they don't have access
Products that are just as cool as this
They're just going to go and buy these things themselves
Potentially your baby
Look for a different
Provider
What we're seeing here is
I moved where
The Lord companies
Are trying to get
The Dealer's when bored
I'm trying to help them under
1st and Wyatt
Oyster benefits
Afraid
And at the same time the dealers are trying to figure out how to make that work because it's a very different Financial
Familiar with that financial model can you break that down for me
Looking for a
Music service in your home
You are working with a dealer that
Cells
Control4 Crestron or something like that
Thousands of dollars
Likely
Hard drives
Stores all of your music for you and it's all local in this wonderful but
Frankly it's not necessary
Seymour in what you probably really want
Is
Your Deezer and your Spotify
And services like that
The problem
I think
Realize
These products aren't as expensive
Bose dealers
Make their money on Market
You sure there's money in installing it for you they also make a share on Market
Product is a product only cost $169
Instead of $4,000
That's a very different financial situation so I think the challenge for the four installers is going to betray
About this alot
We monetize long-term.
And we're back with Jamie siminoff to CEO of
Ring
Talking about
Is products
How to make your neighborhood
You mentioned
That you guys
Reducing crime
And that sounds awesome
What other features
Are you building into
Product line
The app itself
So what day was closed recently is
A camera which replaces a motion detection flood light
HD camera
Etsy motion detection of flood lights when you walk by you get the light on but now
Play audio
So that we came out with judicial products called Spotlight cam
Little bit smaller one is battery operated and what is power
And so now you can add light
And Camera all around your house regardless if you have power or not
That is awesome so if
You see something
You can actually say something
And that's the whole thing with
Presence of being able to not only
What's going on and get the alert on your phone
Something happened
Now that this alarm set
Any more details on that
To the alarm we haven't given any like real details on this
Specific
Around
Features
Largest alarm company in the world ATT is so scared about it that they're suing it's over it
I was just the only reason why we talk about it
Will be coming out in the end
A lot of your product
You started in
Professional installer
Yes Elite Wheel of the professional install
Initially started answer the DIY consumer market we've come out with the elite line
And that started with
The doorbell the ring video doorbell Elite that's a power over ethernet
I really I can install the time top of the line
Products and so we're going to be continuing that Elite line throughout our product line
And adding those two of those features to other products rehabs that we have a full line then
Installers to install a professional line in homes
Power over ethernet
Yeah did you see a lot of power
Future products that we have in it
The lines that we already have out there attic power
For sure
Awesome that's a lot to look forward to
Thank you so much
Thank you very much for attestation
And now back to the show to understand further some of the distress
After Trends facing the industry
I spoke with a custom installers been to the show for The Last 5 Years
To find out how he's thinking of adopting his business
Reagan Mena
Owner and president
Audioseal in Austin Texas
Says he's seen the products from Big consumer Brands infiltrate
Great the show
In this segment he talks about how his business has changed with the influx of new tech from
Startups in Tech
We'll get a new pilot comes out into the market and
Nothing ever goes out to any of our clients houses must we do some thrill testing
Lucy it adds value
To whatever type of automation system reporting it
Sometimes these products are so popular that
Google head and
Install them as part of a
An emerging Trend but most of the time we'd like to see how well they can integrate
Santa Barbara
Are custom automation
So that that's really the key is to seeing how well plays with all the other products we currently
It's an adoption or you're going you're going the way of the dodo essentially it comes down to knowing those type of products and
Applying an hourly rate for insulation and also supporting that as well to
Some companies Implement a recurring Revenue aspect of it
Are the times at the one-off and then
Accountable call back if they need
More assistance
I just kind of Line in the Sand between some integrators who
They do large-scale installations and they have a
Recurring relationship with their clients and then
You start to see a lot more
With clients these days that they have smaller setup still need as much because they become a lot more tech-savvy and we're just there
To help support the things they don't understand or don't want to install
And what would you like to see from the industry that maybe they're not giving you or maybe some people are giving it to you but as an s
A custom installer
What do you want
When it comes down to it it would be nice if
Coyote side of things and also the custom guys could find a little bit better common ground in terms of
Alder oldwyn play well together in the future either sides not going away I would say the iot and
Great products that are coming out on a consumer level
AR
Fully encroaching more and more the custom side of things but the way I look at it is you have to look at these things and
Find Wade Implement them with some custom products or quite frankly look to see if those those type of products can act
LeapFrog what you currently have and it's sometimes hard for integrated to look at that and say
Here's a $250 device
Quite frankly
Performs better than my $2,500 X Y and Z product
And it's just something you have to look at hard but then also realize that
There is a business model behind approaching these products installing amuse have to be smart about it
There are plenty of other trends that I saw at the show
Such as an emphasis on both voice control and Apple's homekit
Energy management was also a big trend
People at boots
Ranging from Sonnen
2 Savant showing ways to manage power generated by residential solar
As I departed CDA though
My focus was on trying to figure out how the world of high-end home automation
Would react and adapt to the encroaching
Consumer technology
From the outside
It seems as though they've been caught
Flat-footed
Reacting with me to Prada
Instead of delivering
A lot of innovation
Alex capecelatro
The CEO of Josh. AI
Explains why that's why
McKay's
Man doing so he makes me wonder how any industry can withstand the onslaught
The big Tech
A lot of the Innovations are coming out of companies like restaurant in control for which at CVS seem like very big companies
But they're tiny compared to Google and apple and so when does Innovations are coming out of companies that really aren't that big
It's hard to do things like voice control which takes hundreds of Engineers a lot of brainpower to pull off we had about set
7 years of research and development before even launching his company we had our own natural language processing engine before we went in
Productized it
So we really started with the hard stuff and then the control system stuff isn't easy by any means but
In this landscape
We did the thing that no one else hears really able to do first and then we both around it
That's it for this episode remember to get your discount on rings home security products
For both consumers and professional installers
Visit www
. ring
Dot-com
Slash
Stacy
Let him know you listen
Once again I'd like to thank Jamie siminoff.
The CEO of ring who shared Rings Vision around neighborhood security
Andaz 4th
Coming efforts with
Alarm system and products
Professional installers
For making the show
Thanks for listening and we'll see you later this week with a regularly scheduled episode of The Internet of Things podcast