Welcome to the special CS edition of The Internet of Things podcast
Brought to you by the open connectivity Foundation
Open connectivity Foundation is dedicated to ensuring secure interoperability for
Consumers businesses and industries by delivering a standard Communications
Platform abridging specification and open source implementation and a certification program
It allows devices to communicate regardless of form factor
Operating system
Service provider transport technology
Or
Ecosystem
At this year's CES The Internet of Things was the default setting
Booth after Booth featured sensors
Hubs or Randall devices that connected to the internet
Even among the major chip vendors
There were stations dedicated to
Retail and beacons Telehealth or 5G technology
And the pig topic was how to connect more things to the internet
So with that in mind I interviewed all kinds of people on the show floor and in meetings along the strip to get a sense of where
The Internet of Things is headed and why it matters
Connectivity and power consumption were big
But so is the lingering concern about the viability of the
Consumer Market
For startups
Just a note for you guys
I know that Madame a and
Google home or everywhere
And that's the big story that most people took away
From the show
But I'm trying to go a little bit deeper
Cell
Let's kick off the show first with a focus on the consumer news in insights
Starting with Comcast
Comcast purchase stringify last year's one of the mini smart home deals that are
And now we know what they're going to do with it is Chris specialty EVP and chief product officer at the cable Giant
You guys are
Smart home automation for all
That's a lot of our listeners
Stone In Love
So what exactly are you doing the stringify for your custom
So we we love stringify because they have a great number of adopters
Steeple relationship zip login
Taken
Paradoxes
Little Dalmatian system
Combined it with our own that we were building
Available
Initially for everybody with an ex by Kate we were Moss gateway to everybody
Eventually
Home automation making it just a layer in the home
So as a user what is this going to look like for me when it
Pops into my Comcast world
So imagine the system
Knows what you do everyday and Sons if you leave in the morning because you on the alarm system
You lock your door the camera sees you leave
What we can do is
Set up for you
And all for you that is a single sub is so that you never have to get any of that again it don't go through all those steps
So you're basically turning my 8 steps into one
Will send you a steps into one I'm making it simple to integrate
I'm not in the Comcast service area so what happened
Stringify for me
Are you still be able to use string find the Comcast Lobster you know to lose your stringify kind
An older great Services already provided
Alright thank you
Another consumer news Samsung spent CES expanding on his three-year-old Vision to make the Internet of Things Morrow
And it's doing this with SmartThings
A company that bought back in 2014
Samsung has Consolidated every consumer app from its dishwashers to it
TVs under the SmartThings app
So we talked to Alex Hawkinson
Who is the CEO of smart things
To find out more and what's next
For the smartphone
PS with Alex
Can send to your SmartThings and we are talking about
Because
In their Keynote
Everything was
SmartThings
And apparently
Samsung has now integrated
Everything
Talk to me about WhatsApp
Ask him sitting in the back
What's a queef
We reached a point where
With the
Consumer Internet of Things
Smart home going to the mass Market
End
You know you told me not to spend early adopter
Thomas oh
Younes little bit ly
All
Samsung
Devices all of its effort so Unified
SmartThings platform and what's awesome
It's still the same completely open
Completely open modeling stance that we've had
Enough for all time
As well so
Every new Samsung device will be connecting to
SmartThings
We also announced that
Every Sans
Open devices
Screen and every play every device
The screen will not have one app
Control all these things and relax
And if I am
So Kevin and I
Please show we actually
She said that
This year was
Is the first year that we thought
The Internet of Things
The story of Cs
Which is all these device
Method
Standards War appears to be over
Yes we're talking about boys
What what is it
Mean
Going forward
Now that we're like
Coyote
We get it it's going to be there
Internet of Things
Moving
Deonza things
So we have
We found it another
370 devices
That work with SmartThings now across all the top
Use cases
Smart home and otherwise in the source of working
More more lively in available more and more around the world so what's happening is
Nelson opportunity for the developers and service providers the world to build over the top of the
So
You have a chance to
Used music
Existing thing
Ansible services unimproved
Lights everywhere
The gadgets
You connecting device
Future
Is about
Services you can buy over the top
Has recently
Last year a deal with ATT
Service provider
Talk to you about why they decided
Basically I'm smart
Cloud and what that means for them
The types of things they can
Their customer
Well you don't talk about it
Specifically in the
One of the top music
Has been answering the question are things okay at home
For safety and can
Convenience and all the other things then
ATT
You know they got their start as being maybe the biggest proprietary platform in that space
They found it at
There's this revolution around internet-of-things the reward more device
The consumers wanted to use in their house
That could
Dissipated
Having a proprietary snap they couldn't integrate all the
I working with
Are open stamps they got to
Make it possible
Deliver
Professional monitoring with people
At a much lower cost
Without a contract
And you
All those
G+ device
Are things today
A better service for the consumers that's cheaper deliver higher margins all those different
It's bringing it up
All right it is a SmartThings Hub
User like a normal early adopter person
What should I expect from
You guys
You know what you see is
Why is farewell to the building
The platform for the level scale
Millions of tracks
Devices
Broadening
Program
You should expect is
Much
More Innovation higher spacepaste
Invasion of the course the next couple
You seen it
Point where more than 50000 Developers
Sign up for a new
Developer tools
This new app.
On every device with a
Screen
Innovating
New ways and create new interfaces
Does an apps that run on any
Of these devices
Around the world
And so I just think that that is
It's going to open up a new
A whole new space of
Mission by the developer
That'll make
Some awesome things happen
Let's take a quick break for message when they open connectivity Foundation
Alright Dave last year we heard for the open connectivity
Foundation
And it was after the merger with the all seeing Alliance
And I owe tivity was out
But then we didn't hear a lot from you guys in this last year
You're so
Where are you today
2017 was really a year for a say retrenching
And re-establishing the work that was underway in 2016 prior to the all seeing I'll join
Merger with the OIC
Perform the open connectivity Foundation we've been on a path to publish the first
Release of our specification and open source code through Teva t
And we had actually done that we were just in the process of getting some of the first implementation
When the murder occurred and to be honest post
Of the organization
Involved in the merger and the leadership said
Hey look slow down the work-in-progress
Let's take a look and make sure that we're bringing the best
Both of these organizations
New technologies and specifications to bear
EXO
Each of the respective groups underneath basically took
The time
And you know what may have seemed dormant to a lot of folks in Industry actually wasn't we were
Deep in the throes of going through reviewing the specs bring the best out
Reincorporating nose and
Quite honestly had a
Very effective results from that in the recent announcement in publication
Of the new specification to come out post-merger
Less known associate version 1.3
And with the corresponding release of the activity open source code
To go along with it
The results of the specification open source and surf
Application from the 1.3 effort
Has now resulted in products coming to Market and the first wave of rocf
Logo devices
For the final day consumer story I spoke with Ben Nader CEO of butterfly
About
Puma acquiring his smart camera
We discuss the deal the saturation in the camera Market
And what other consumer startups should look for in an acquisition partner
Because you're probably going to need
My name is Ben Nader and I am the founder of butterfly and now I am the GM for the butterfly product line
Great the first thing I noticed is that I have been saying butterfly wrong cuz I'm always like butterfly I
So
Saturnino you guys just got bought by Uma
Can you talk to me about the decision to sell your company and how that came about
Yes I I really think it was one of those situations that one plus one equal to 3
So we built this great product we put a lot of engineering and R&D into it I thought it was very differentiating
What woman had a really great
Security system but it was missing the camera piece
As well as they have a well-established brand name to have a big sales and marketing team
What are they wanted to grow butterfly name and Brandon get the product out there
Are we going to have a large sales and marketing team
Say what's a cat it was a great match it's like what I said one plus one equal three
IHOP
A lot of companies that build smart home devices in the last
Couple months of seoul
Because they found the market to be just really tough to be like differentiated and sell to Consumers
Was that your experience at all
You know that the camera Market was crowded but we were we were backed by some good to be seasoned
We had opportunity to continue and and raise more money
But I really appreciate it was to accelerate the sale
An accelerator Channel access to channel and sugar to the market
Various marketing and branding opportunities
We have
What will you do what advice would you give
Other
Connected devices
Smart home companies
Going into this year
Find this one plus one equal three
Find this visit just a marriage that one plus one can add something bigger
Lumineers is whole security complete Security System
As well as a bigger sales in China that day one that can attach to your company I'm be able to to groin
Awesome thank you thank you
And now let's move on to the Enterprise
CES is obviously about the consumer but people probably show floor from all Industries seeking the next big thing
I ran into a gentleman who worked in R&D at a Building Products Manufacturing
Explain what technologies might Inspire our future housing
I work for a building product manufacturer
Okay what are those guys do
I pretty
Zenni
I'm not anybody
Building products that are used in
Construction global
What are you doing at CVS what are you looking for
Well our team is a
Research and development group
Looking for emerging Technologies new could leverage for the building industry
Okay and it sounded like you were excited about the
Smart home stuff
Are like have you seen anything that
Caught your eye
Not yet
Only been here very short amount of time
Baidu
Anything that could be
Applicable to products
It weather is tracking materials or
Connected devices is something we're very interested in
Visualizing
Materials like augmented reality and virtual reality
Reading Plus right now
One of the things
Things that people are kind of talking to me about is the idea we're going to build our sensors into walls
Which to me sounds
The same because power
Consumption and all this other stuff
Are those are the kind of far-fetched things you're thinking about
I think I'd say
Construction level heads
Intriguing to us because
It could add value to what we offer
If we have something that's smart and
Gives us Competitive Edge
Don't we know what it's looking for and why people want them
What are the big challenges for the Building Product manufacturing business
Disconnect
Between the manufacturer and the end-user
Because there are many Distributors and the contractors are not the same people as the people manufacturing the product
So
Our group is mainly made up of Architects
Who have
An overlapping to technology so we understand that
People specifying
Maybe not always the people that'll be occupying space
So
We have to understand the technology
She said that we can
But we're looking for
Awesome thank you
Construction was also an 8 Williams
Williams is an entrepreneur-in-residence at Kleiner
Who spoke with me about what he's thinking about
In Enterprise
Coyote
Any guess what are you excited about
Yeah this is my 13th straight show 13 years in a row and I'm excited about the evolution of connectivity
For the Enterprise
So things are really interesting to me
Number one would be
The idea of Transportation Logistics
Examples 35 billion dollars
Pharmaceuticals each year
Are lost
Stolen or broken during Transit
I think we could solve that issue using sense
Second thing is the idea of iot
Securities we talked about
Are utilities
Hisun Pharmaceuticals and other things
But have to be secure
Is a bunch of great companies are doing that
And lastly an industry where I think there's going to be a
Unmoor a Technologies Chinese
The show is construct
Can we look at making these
Construction site
Safer
It'll get better building Tech
Regency
Autonomous robots helping
Built some of these next generation
What are the main issues in the construction industry that you're looking at
Yeah first thing if construction is been traditionally one of the bigger businesses and expansion
Tracks with the economy
We're seeing is the last 30 years
Process technology hasn't changed much
Tell me like Altair and others that are out there
They're actually adding sensors
Robotics another autonomy to the
Construction
So couple things first day is number one better quality so we looking like drywall finishing
Play something called level five how you can get to the best type of drywall finish
To make an office building with greater house
Second to safety
There's a company out of text are called killer Tech
Which is actually measuring
Things like
Humidity
And decibels Xterra make sure you're complying for OSHA
Flossing is just in terms of overall worker safety
Christina company that can allow worker to understand when they're using their back to live
So here she may have an issue
So what we'll see this year is the
Application of sensor Tech and other autonomy robotics
2 Construction in a way to make better outcomes with more safety and ultimate try to bring some profitability into the
Once iot changes how we built
Can it also change how we access building
I met a few people thinking about using digital identities as a way to get into their office
Work may be in place if their social security number
Centos keep getting hacked
So I asked Todd Graves but Allegiant
About how iot can change access as well as what he's looking for
At the show
I'm taught Graves and I'm the senior vice president for engineering and Technology at Allegiant
Wow that is a big title okay
A lot of people are talking about why can't I use my
Digital identity
In the real world
What are the kind of challenges are things you have to think about when
People are asking that kind of
Well I mean first there's it's important to distinguish between identity and a credential
Right identity is something that you
Uniquely identifies you
In a my mind there's really only
2 today to robust forms of identity
There's government identity
So
Here in the US you've got a social security number
You probably got a driver's license
And maybe you got a passport and those are all
Uniquely identifiable to you very hard.
The fake so they are robust forms of identity
The second robust form of identity that's more private is the bank
But it ties back to government identity
You can't establish a bank account and get a credit card without a government ID
Online forms of identity unless you've used a credit card to establish it I would say is non robust
So I can set up a Google account
An Apple ID or establish a new Facebook account and call myself Joe Blow and there's really no
Cross-checking of that identity
So there's a really
Really radically different level of robustness between what we normally use for online identity and what we use as
Credential based identity in the world
So I'm probably not going to ditch my key card to my office anytime soon for my Facebook ID
Yes because if you think about an Enterprise
First day you show up at work
You fill out an I-9 form and you show the HR department a government ID and then they log you into the EHR system with
Something that ties back to your government identity
Mountain Enterprise could say
We're going to eat then tight
Your Facebook identity your Facebook login to that but they're always going to need to tie back what's in their system
To a robust form of government idea that's the law
But there are opportunities to
To tie
Your online identity with your Enterprise.
Okay and one more question for you since you were the CTO
At a very large
What are the technologies that you're looking for here at CES
I'm looking for conductivity
At low power
Because
The most critical devices
For us are battery-powered iot devices
Their security devices
And so yes it's
It's about power and reliable connectivity
Graves wasn't the only person thinking about connectivity
After this message from our sponsor will talk to Two Fellas from John Deere who discussed 5G and how to train a machine
Need to learn when it's on the edge of an unreliable Network stated
Yes we've so far seen a couple products with the ocf sticker on it
What should we look for in the year ahead
From the group
When we first started ocf the vision was to have a horizontal standard that can work across a variety of different
How to use case
Including Smart Home in order to get
It's thing started to this be
The organization did have to focus until we chose smart home being one of the fastest-growing and most interesting areas
For a members in for the consumer Community alike
Until what you seen in the initial C yes introductions are things that are much more smart home Centric
But will
Definitely evolved and I think a big
Change in activity in 2018 will be the addition in the
Result of
Work that we have a new group focused on other verticals that expand Beyond this morning
I'm so for example
Batting over the
Over-the-top kind of services with iot for personal and digital
Care
Aging-in-place Solutions connected car connected home and the interoperability
And media and control and security sharing between those
Even spanning out into things like
Community Management
Smart Building Solutions
Smart cities acceptor so
Play the number of
Different Landing zones where
Millwork of us yeah
And the use of Iowa City
Will find its way into products
And services and by the way that also include software
So think now about having his community of ocf devices
And connected ecosystem that service providers
Can you
And developed application
To run from the cloud
And to be able to
Deploy deliver and monetized
These capabilities on top of these ocf connected devices
And now here's Wally Pelon Juan Sanchez from John Deere on edge architectures and
5G
Willie talk director of new technology of Blue River technology
Okay
You guys were recently
Play acquired by John Deere you do computer vision on
Farming equipment
You can detect weed is very exciting
Can you talk to me about what it takes to do the kind of machine learning you guys do
Basically it was the edge of a
Baby not awesome Network
Yes so we trained everything off
So we have dab carts that we start pushing through
Fields and relax
Thousands of images we haven't even labeled with Mechanical Turk
We then
Trainees networks on a GPU
The office
And then deploy the models out to the field
I'm weak and attacked
When those models are performing poorly or a low confidence
We prioritize that data for upload so that the network continuously
And
II
More
Different fields of exposed
The machine to the bat
So what happens is when I'm out
Farming
I spraying for weeds
Spraying for weeds
And
I've got your your your information
It's running through that and it's
I don't know what this is in your life
As a farmer do I have to
Do anything or is it just
Strictly yorkin
Computer is like oh
This date is super important
Let's do something with
When we get back to the
Garage
The barn
Extreme and say that guy
Safeway
Save the cotton
Machine
Rights if they drive it into a soybean field or corn field
Our network has not been performed
Do we need to build alert them and say hey
Something's wrong
Either you're a
Something is wrong
And then they can make a decision what they want to keep going or not
And then they can also upload the data that machine will automatically upload any low coffee
Prince data
To us we can assess it now in that case
In some cases
Hail damage
Which is
Actually looks quite different than regular car
We're going to
Take a bunch of these images off the machine
And train
What's on in the next days
Do you pull all data from every path eventually to the cloud
It depends when we are in the in the development process early in the development process yes and yes she's FedEx to get it all back at 6
Too much. Blood
Further down the road in the development process when
We start uploading the
Places where we're performing for aliens
Alright thank you
Julia Sanchez director John Deere Technology Innovation
What kind of connectivity environment and connectivity technology are you guys looking for precision
We certainly still recognized at rural areas suffer from connectivity so traditionally we've looked
That store and push architectures
Where we we don't always rely on constant productivity or high bandwidth connectivity we are constantly exploring
Low-power a broad range a type of solutions and then expecting things like 5G and Technology
Just like 5G
Will really help us redefine what real-time means for us
Real real time for us right now memes probably around 32nd
With 5G technology
It'll really redefine our store and push model
And really help us use the cloud in the true Real Time with say less than one second back in
You guys are actually great for 5G because
Spell their crops to get in the way of the
But that's right it is all the sudden it removes the the barriers that prevented the network companies from investing in that in
Awesome thank you
Again
I know we didn't talk about Madame a doll in the show
And that's supposed to because it's all anyone else who went covered
The rise of voice is important
But it's also an established interface right now
Which brings me to one of the cooler things I saw at the show
So stay tuned for that after one final message from our sponsor
And Dave
Before we leave today
What are you most excited about
I think that we're really excited about it ocf
Is the fact that
Getting these devices now into the market that can
Discover each other in
Securely share data
Can create all kinds of
Possibilities
In terms of services and
Intelligence
And really building
Not only
Controllable home
But actually the truly smart autonomous
Home environment
And deliver the experience
Did you see on the shows and you hear on the radio
And finally will be able to
Bye and deploy and enjoy
Bosch showed off of men's projector that fit on the module less than half the size of a credit card
And that module can be embedded on a lamp or even an Amazon Echo
This man is projector can projected interactive touchscreen on any surface including our skin
A complete videos at 480p
Or 720p depending on how far away the projector is
So just imagine if you ask matinee to show you something
And your Echo projected the options on the table it was sitting on
And then you could use your finger to select whatever option you chose
I thought it was really cool and would love to see this embedded in
Devices
Visit the show notes for a link to the video I Shot
And thanks again to the open connectivity foundation for sponsoring the CES episode of the show
I hope it took you beyond the obvious story
Grace and offered you some insights
Yuan
And remember
Do you want more iot news
Please
Sign up for my newsletter
Envisat Stacy on iot.com thanks for listening