Hey everybody welcome to another episode of The Internet of Things podcast
I have your host Stacey Higginbotham and here is my co-host
Wonderful
Kevin tofel
I love surprising Kevin I'm just
Never know what you're going to say I just know I just say my name I just read the cue cards
Heaven Waits for me
I guess you're talking to me all week there's nobody else to talk to you on this ship
Surprising
To be like in the founder of
Apple
Kevin tofel
I feel like no Aunt sorry
No no
All right
Speaking of Apple
Kevin got a
Present in the mail today he's waving it around like you guys can
See it
Kevin this is a podcast
I know I know
You can see it though and isn't this pretty its beak
38 mm
Apple watch
In space gray aluminum with black sports band
Yeah I've only had it for an hour
I'm already noticed a couple things though
I know I've talked about the watch from going to the launch events
And I think I said oh yeah work really fine really quick everything else
It's not quite as quick in real life those can demo Zara
Contra reason I think I'm not saying it's like super sluggish but it's noticeably slower at certain things so
I am shocked
I mean shocked shocked
Do they have
May have manipulated
It's demos
Well I mean they're not the only company to do so by any means
And yeah I mean
It's again it's not slow but it's slower
It's also interesting the few apps that I put on here literally white just before the show started put the dark sky app with
The absolute love cuz it's like
Pinpoints of a minute when you're in a precipitation of some kind
I was using the app
And you know
Going to the screens and there's a
I'll add you use swiping if they wait a second
Because it's got to get its data from your phone
So there's a
I'm interesting
Aspects to it here
Very interesting aspects Twitter
And then decide to Stacey again before the shell sure there's everybody there's a lot going on here from user interface
Standpoint
BC was it
I wonder to shows ago you had somebody on there talking about the user interface challenges
Mark Rolston who is
The chief creative officer of argodesign
And this man knows you I
So he was
He was saying that
He felt it
One that there was a lot to learn but to he felt it
The Apple watch spends a lot of time
Conserving battery in that
Affected
It affects the user
Experience
To the user's detriment
And I think I understand where he was going because as I get notifications in from my connected iPhone
You know if you don't take action on them right away they kind of Disappearing like one or two seconds and
NyQuil where to go how do I get it back
You just turn off the screen because you want to save battery life I can get that but
You know which of these two buttons do I press turn tablet or touch the screen do I swipe
Little learning curve involving not I'm trying not trying to
Dismiss this as a
Part that's too complex or difficult to use time will tell
But it's not
Clearly not to me a product that you're going to take out of the box
And in an hour or two or four even
Really have a good understanding of how to navigate around through all the glances to notifications
The apps
The
Friends bit where you have your favorite people showing so you can quickly send them a text or a call
So there's there's a lot going on at the store the best way to say it
Not that
Not trying to throw this out here to get on the Apple train
Are the watch train
Even my Pebble I still
Mess up and hit the wrong button to go forwards or backwards
It's
Navigate on a small screen when you have limited options
Buttons that you're not used
It and that's it right there right you know we were trying to cram a lot of interaction into a small device
And there's
Multiple
Touchpoints
No pun intended there's you know that the touchscreen itself that you can
You can tap you can also
Press down even harder for the force press to do something else
You got the digital Crown to spin around and also functions as a button
You got another button
You got voice interaction so there's there's a lot going on here
And again because of the battery management
Some of these things don't even work when the screen is not active
Right now the screen is inactive so if I were to say hey Siri
Nothing happens if I lift up my wrist
Now now it's inactive mode and hey Siri would do something
Interesting Lee you and I just tested a phone call
Which I was a little skeptical on how it would work but I've done two phone calls now
The one I just did with you I initiated by saying Hey Siri call Stacy and
It went right through and then
It's a Bluetooth headset to my phone
Whose symbol is quick
Probably what a foot from your face
And it sounded
It sounded like you were far away but it was no worse than taking call from someone who's in their cars
Right at the Atwood
Say it's more like a speakerphone type
Experience
And if you're in a quiet environment like I was in my home office talking to my son
As soon as the watch arrived he was on the school bus actually coming home
You can hear me just fine I could hear him just fine because I was in my quiet office
If I was out and about
The one thing I don't really want people hear my conversation but to
I probably wouldn't be able to hear so well so
So I again only an hour with it I'm not going to say too much
You like that yeah you got to have it or no don't buy one
Maybe we can revisit that
We're totally going to revisit that cuz I actually sent
Kevin some work more homework system I sent him some
Summer media work
I sent him some Hue bulbs
So hopefully he'll install those and he can play with
CSM connect a device
With his watching
Look at him
Is test out
What it feels like
Talk to a wife
Play with that
Yeah absolutely I mean you're giving me summer school homework already but
In my defense I time
Literally I've been taking my
Comp sci class at night school so that's over this week so I have no more excuses
I will get the Hue installed at the bulbs I will get things down installed
And I will play with the watch as these things all connect
Yes because the thread is what I'm going to fire you from the podcast heaven
I will do it
So
Other big news
In the kind of smart home front
When is
Comcast
Comcast which most people probably think of as
The cable company
That did not get a chance to buy Time Warner and make
More more Americans lives possibly
Miserable
We'll just go with it everybody hates the cable company
I'm not going to sugarcoat it I'm sorry Comcast
But
They have
A connected home and home automation product called Xfinity home
Earnings call this week
They said that they have
Play 500 thousand subscribers which is a really good number that is a lot of people
That's a good start
Ya adtpulse probably has a bit more
And they haven't actually released numbers but
I'm pretty confident
Armoire
I feel like alarm.com probably has about a million
Is what they said
So
Good start for them
And today
Brian Roberts
The CEO of Comcast
Showed off at the cable show
Nine new partners for their business
And those Partners in
Glued
Nest
Makers of the smart thermostat that we all know and love
August smart locks
Automatic
Which makes a
Connect a dongle for your
Automotive Diagnostics port in your car
Cough which actually I don't think is out yet but it's a connected it's a
Piece of connected jewelry that acts as a
Notification device for your
Phone
It's for women
And a activity tracker
It's pretty
It's actually very pretty
Lutron lighting woo Shadow to my favorite Lighting Company
Leo we talked about them on the show before the connected night light
That also doubles as a way to
Here
It listens for your smoke detector and then send you a notification
Vacation if it goes off
It kind of is a way to retrofit your
Protectors for
Smart Home
Smart idea
It includes rachio the wifi-connected sprinkler system
Skybell the connected doorbell
That let you see who's at your door
And
Whistle the activity tracker for dogs
Yay
So all of those companies are going to be
Available in work with Comcast
Xfinity home system
And I think this is brilliant for Comcast
And also for these startups
So Jason Johnson the CEO of August
Told me that this was
A no-brainer for his company because
Comcast has
Massive
Marketing muscle
Comcast is going to
Mark at the heck out of all these
Startups
Through actually I think it's a little over
21 million subscribers
Across the US
And they pass a lot more homes
So
They send out mailers all the time and can you imagine
Imagine getting your
You're cool connected device it features one of those that's awesome
There's a lot of reach are formed for these startups in terms of Comcast marketing as you said subscriber base and saw
Salon
And when I like on the flip side is Comcast isn't just
Saying we got home automation service that we can offer you and here's a switch and here's a door lock
There's a wide range of products that are which I really like such a smart smart play
Exactly and later this year Comcast is going to open up a nest
BK a software developer
Make it for
Other companies who want to
Get in on the Comcast
Beecosystem
And this is this is nothing but good for Comcast
Cuz they've had kind of a lot of these
Solder device
But it's been very closed as a Neko
And I get it
I mean
They've got to support all these customers
Is who
These aren't DIY
Customer sees our customers are calling up Comcast
You're calling of your cable provider and saying I really want the smart home stuff
You're not the kind of customer that's going to be like
Like me who's going to spend hours
Yeah playing in tweaking West
Another
DIY person I'm typically not a fan of
These
Companies that will provide monitoring services and such for a fee when I know I can do this myself and
But you know why I realize that you and I were definitely the minority here
The way for this Market to grow
Is through this type of approach so I think it's
Good for
Both sides you know the DIY people
Because it will eventually bring more products to the market
And then for the people who don't want to go with the complications and stuff
It brings you know a simple way for them to have their their services monitor
Comcast Comcast is providing space a service then
They are so what they do is
Typical canoe
Service business model
Comcast send out installers now right now
They will not install
Between the hours of 2 and 5 or I'm sorry I had to go there
No okay
So they they have installers
To do there
The current lineup
They don't install the new products
Yet the plan is eventually they will which is another great thing
Because
Some people find installing an asteroid
Like my guess is they'll subcontract a lot of that out and it's
Here's an interesting tidbit I actually was almost an installer
It consultant type installer for Comcast
Modems way back in the day
What Kevin you can get in on this now
Do quite well for yourself back in the day it was something like $100 for an install
And this goes back to the 90s
Wow
Wasn't that like there's a company was actually here in town motive communication
They lived in Austin
They actually like
Totally killed that business
Baidu
Self automatic
Okay Telecom trivia for you guys they were now about by Alcatel-Lucent
Sorry
Okay so
Comcast
Will come out to put all the stuff in
And then you pay you sign up for like a 2-year contract
And if you how much
It depends
It always depends and there's fine print and there's fees
The basic is
If you just want to do like the DIY stuff there's like a package
Pikachu
Open close sensor when camera or Therma
Thermostat
I think a lighting unit some other stuff for twenty bucks
And with a 2-year contract
They do all the
All the gear
I was part of it
And then there's
A monitor there's two levels of monitor
The cheaper version cost $40 a month
That has
3 Doors
Touchscreen controller
Fancy
One motion
Sensor
And a wireless keypad and then there's a $50 a month one
It has like
Just more stuff
And both of those are monitored 24 so
And they have like a different level of
Insurance and assurance
Associated
And those are
Professionally installed
There is a DIY installation option on the cheaper version
If you want
Or you can have the Comcast people
Come out and install it nothing
Terrible not terrible. I mean
It just depends on how you view your time and then you could buy additional sensor
And stuff like that
And I don't know how their pricing
Works on that stuff
Well now I know what the pinging iPhone bit on the Apple watch does sorry about that
We're keeping that in here Kevin now it's now you know what that sound is alright so so that's the Comcast news
Is it a big deal
And I think it's at those also
The home automation markets going mainstream
So we're getting there tell your friends they should be totally listening to the show
They could be even smarter
And next in the big news
Let's talk about
Everybody's favorite Gadget or maybe it's just fine
The Amazon Echo
I think it's just yours and now I'm kicking myself that I didn't get in on it for $99
If you can believe this I've actually just reapplied for an invite to buy the Amazon Echo
And I'm going to pay 149 for it because of my
Stupidity I guess
But here's what got me interested in it
All of a sudden
I saw on the if this then that log over the weekend they have introduced the Amazon Alexa Channel
It's funny that they're calling it the Amazon Alexa Channel when it's really Amazon Echo but I
I guess I get it
So basically you can now connect your Echo
Two up to it was 116 and 117 channels
So you can set up trigger events with if this then that and have things happen when you talk to Alexa
But there's a bit of a caveat as Stacey explain to me right before the show
So it's a bit Limited
And
You basically when you create an if this then that channel
You get what's called triggers and the triggers are the way that you
Create your recipe they're the things that they're the
Third event is this
Or the bad part
So
For Alexa that if this
Is all shopping list release
So Alexa has
Two features
That you can do that are kind of
And basically you can
Be a voice add things to a shopping list so
I walk around like
Oh
Alexa add wrapping paper to my shopping list
Or Alexa add make a doctor's appointment for my daughter
To my to do list
Those are actually the only triggers right now
That the assistant that channel allows
So anything you want to do with Alexa
You have to do it through those which
Has created some crazy hacks
Yeah
So they are really useful ones actually around the to-do list like
Beforehand your to-do list in your shopping list actually only appeared in Amazon's app which was a stoop
The place for them because
I don't know about you but I don't create a grocery list
ICarly would like you to trust me
But you know my grocery list is actually it's actually a piece of paper but let's pretend I do it in
Now I can actually just send
All of that and mailed it with my grocery list on Evernote
Which is cool
It is so that that could be happening all the time in the background and that's it
That is cool but then there's the smarthome aspecting
What you did Stacey actually share their screen with me before the show
He showed me how to create a recipe to control her nest with the Alexa
So explain that one
Sure so if I wanted to create a recipe to make my nest
It's a little bit
It's super hacking no no sane person would actually
I would have to
Decide that my to do list
Would be mostly useful
Most useful as controlling my dad
And I would say
If I ask
Alexa
What's on my to-do list
It's going to set my temperature
For my nest
And so
Whenever I'd say Alexa
What's on my to-do list
My recipe would automatically
Play turn my nest
275 degree
Or whatever you can figure it in the recipe but that's the key you can only configure to one temperature
Right
Self super super happy here
Is super hacky
It's super Limited
And it's the same thing for any other smart home device
And because there's only probably there's about nine triggers
Because they're all equally hockey
You have to remember like if I wanted it to be like setting at
275 degrees
If I want to do smart things to turn off a series of Lights
I have to remember that
If I'm asking
What's on my to-do list
Control my nest if I'm saying add to my to do list that controls my living room lights
It's not logical here not not logical at all but
Hiatus start
I give
You know I give him some credit for
Figuring out how to do this and we know that the SDK for sale except for the echo came out
I want to say February early October or early March
It's early days yet and I think once that is official and
Make some progress
Maybe we'll see more trigger events or just better integration
I expect so
Amazon's got to prove these
They're being very careful about it I know a lot of people have
Apps in the works right now and some of them seem really cool
So
I'm really excited so far
So far it's great and you know I don't know if you saw this
You probably didn't see this because you're not using an echo
But they added the ability to talk to it and ask it about sports scores
So
My husband's walking through all the time asking
Alexa how are the Cardinals doing today
How are the St Louis Cardinals
Searching out my Arizona
Factual clarification
I mean if I had said the real Cardinals that would have been
So
It's just it's getting better
It's very exciting
It is it is and they just added too and I know we talked about in the past one or two shows they've added official support for
WeMo and some other things so
It's it's
It's starting to Intrigue me I didn't want to buy into it for the
Potential that it had
I want to buy a product that was
More useful at the time and I already see that it's getting more useful so
So is it now worth it
A 50 extra dollars
And with this if this and that caveat I don't know
Which is
Maybe you should
Wait on honestly maybe I will wait at all I've done so far is asked requested an invite
To repurchase
Just so you know so
And even
If and when I get that which could be weeks away for all I know
I know they're Backwater for months so maybe I just let it be
See a lot of this
It's too early to say for sure a lot of this can actually be done right on my
My new watch
I could just say hey Siri
And there's Integrations there with a lot of these smart home type of things already so
Maybe redundant
Well speaking of your watch
We should go there for
Brief moment
My sources are telling me
That homekit maybe
Longer in the coming than we expected
I know I am expecting
Sometime in June that we should see something
But it's not the full on
The full-on roll out that we're expecting
It's much smaller
So
You know that
I've been at this may sound stupid but that bit that doesn't terribly surprised me and here's why
I know how long is a platform
However I also know that
Apple wants to make some of its own devices
And I think it's not just going to put the platform out there without its own devices so if they're not ready
If Apple Hardware isn't ready I don't think you're going to see a lot of movement
On third-party Hardware support just yet
Well
We had that means we got a whole lot of weight and going on
I'm so
Soap
Get that insteon Gear Up
Screw in. We'll see how that works for you I can guarantee you that I will be able to screw in
Green light bulbs
By the time we have our next show cuz the lightbulbs are on their way to my house
They are there
Should be there tomorrow
Okay so
I guarantee you
I will be able to talk about light bulbs and controlling them from my Apple watch and other ways
Next week
Excellent well that's a good Segway for a scab
Because
Our next big news stories are lighting related
It's right now in New York City
Is light fare
Which
I wish I were there
I really do
Yes because
Everybody who has a light bulb
Is there an
Y'all
I love it
Couple big announcements from the show there is a fancy fancy pants lighting company that actually based in Austin
In Texas called ketra
It has done something really cool
It is been hanging out
For 6 years actually in stealth mode
Serving the commercial Market since about last year
They have an LED light bulb
That
It cost between
100 +
130 bucks
Purple
So expensive
Mostly for high-end residential in
Commercial markets
You can find it in
Auto dealers
MGM hotels
The Tiffany store in New York the Art Institute of Chicago
The cool thing about these bulbs
What is
The LED light
Inside
The semiconductor part the LED
It not only emits light like a light emitting diode
It also
Receive some of the light some of the receptors actually turn into sensors
So it's self Tunes itself itself calibrated
To self
Which is kind of cool
So that is pretty cool actually can be tuned to like different Pantone colors
It checks itself throughout the day
Basically
But it's still running along the right software program so it's incredibly consistent
And
Just kind of super fancy
Apparently all these other companies that is like tested it
Love it
I have
I've seen it a demo over a
A computer which is a terrible way to evaluate like
Play Kai yes over my webcam that lights
Looks amazing
Indiana
I'm in tree go by there the self calibration in the end more smarts as opposed to just a radio for communications that's
Essentially a wireless switch right
Putting in more smarts in these things makes them far more interesting to me
So we'll see I'm actually going to pop by and check them out when they're not at like Fair
Because they are in my home
Downtown
And check out the quality of the light
And
I will not be able to put them in my house they guesstimate that it
It's going to be about a thousand bucks per room
So
Yeah if you're feeling fancy though
And you want to invest in these
Papa man let me know what you think
Because
I'm intrigued
They have some amazing software patterns obviously everybody's got them
Which brings me to another announcement
GE
Also that G's lighting division they announced a partnership yesterday
Monday with Apple
Did they are going to bring out a new consumer light bulb that will work with homekit
It will be later this year it is a tunable white light
Which means
Runs up and down the White
Color spectrum
I love that because I've often bought
Bob's without paying attention to the light or the white color and
I've gotten
They're just you know either soft white when I want a natural
Sunlight
Eyeballs or vice versa
Yeah that's very good
So
I don't know
I feel like if you're going to go tunable you might as well go all in on full color but
It depends on how much they
I mean yeah
Obviously it's all about
Standard consumer
I don't get out much like the sunlight
Type bulbs will the GE they're playing at their circadian rhythm there is natural sunlight thing
But you know the way they were playing it up though I was kind of like does no one else
There's no one else did she realize it every other light bulb has a circadian rhythm pattern
Do they think this is new
It's very
It felt very much like she was very excited about stuff that people were excited about like a year-and-a-half ago
I don't know
Well
I mean they have to sell their product I got to build the hype just like everybody else I don't really have a problem with that
You're so you're so generous
They also did a deal with Qualcomm
Jeeves like
All over this are like lightning we're on it
Qualcomm
To put something that is not a beacon but sounds just like a beacon in retail
It's called
Visible light communication
VLC
Basically
It uses the camera in your smartphone
In encodes in the light to the LEDs omitting information that
Can be read by an app that
It's running on a consumer's smartphone
And this
This app uses
That
To basically triangulate your position in the
Store
Based on the lights
And that
Tells the app where you
You are
So
It's not a beacon but it behaves like a bee
Beacon in GE thinks this is amazing
I think it's a little weird because I don't know if I'm going to be walking through the store with my phone out
The technologist behind it said that you don't they're still going to be using radios to pinpoint you
In the store and then
Ideas
If you're going to pull out your phone to look up for more information that's when it would pop up and get it to you which is the perfect
What time to do so make sense
But I'm still kind of like
I know so many things are vying for attention now and sometimes it don't want that you just want to
Just want to go walk around the store and
I don't want things pinging me off all the time
Yeah it is like this way it doesn't ping you because it won't know where you are so I was like oh that's nice he's like so if you're standing there
Front of the toothbrush
Are the toothpaste aisle inside of your like there are 30 options here which one do I choose
Maybe you pull out your phone to research it and suddenly
It says
Oh look
I see you're standing in front of the toothpaste do you want some more information and then you can be like
Why yes vote I do
I don't know
I mean in Subway's I'm like oh that could make sense I just
So that's that's the kind of that's how GE plans to take on lighting and make it awesome
And let's see
I think
That's a lot of stuff
Do we have any other stuff
There's some there's a little bit about we know they re up there if this then that channel
The connected Cree LED bulbs that are so awesome and cheap those now actually work with the WeMo system
So that brings
That means your Cree light bulbs will work with
Philips Hue system
And with the WeMo system
Yeah it's a nice way to get those
Kinkos light bulbs are like
15 bucks
So they're cheap connected
And
They work with law
Lots of different system so
Don't get some cuz yeah
Why not
Alrighty well this week we don't have a guest on the show's given there so much news and I'm trying to wrap up
Figure out
Some editing things in getting the show on iTunes
So
Stay tuned for all of that and
More
And with that we'll call it a wrap and we will see you next time on the iot podcast