Hey everybody we are back
Fourth
Internet of Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel
Here
No I already said that
The 4th
Internet
You can see I'm going to say it two more times
Three episodes of for next week so we probably V
That is counting it's so easy
See if only I messed up on the 3rd be
Because then I could do
But no
Note 5 No 3
I can't it's for
Okay
So this week we have some exciting things for people who like to get outside in the
Springtime and garden
We have the launch of a really cool
I think it's really cool
Cool product Kevin
I just don't have a need for this but I know a lot of people would appreciate
C i I don't actually have a huge need for it because my yard is there Escape
Where's my daughter closet xeriscaped
Since I live in Texas which is
Excuse Lee drought-prone
I have basically a bunch of decorative rocks and some succulent cactuses in my yard
But I do have this tiny little patch in the back
It has like
Things that I like to grow like herbs
Make a shrub
Lovely shrub
That's nice
It's your likes better than a rock
Because if it's a little bit of greenery
So this product is called
The Eden
It was eating and there's two products
There is
A garden sensor & water valve
Anasazi dyn
Yes
Eden
So
Play I'm sure
Are the proverbial Eden Hazard
Garden of
And what this is
It is one of the connected
Sensors for
Your garden
Unlike many of the kind of
Older generation sensors for your garden
This
The Stars more
Is it smarter
It's two pieces
Is there is a garden center
The Texas oil data
Weather data
The weather today
From your phone
And then the water valve connects to
A source of water
Maurice sprinkler system and turns in allows you to shut it on and off as needed
Basically
You pop this in the ground
And it says
Your soil is this kind of soil
You should add more of this
Because your soil needs more worm casings or alfalfa sprouts
Composter
I don't know things that make
Make your soil better
Then you can plant the following kinds of plants in the soil based on these weather conditions that you have in your hardiness Zone
Can you tell that I'm like a half
Parted Gardener here
Yeah but you know what you're you're hitting the high point of his father's because it doesn't just take the data and say
Your soil pH is too high or too low go do this
It goes a lot further because it says
These are the types of plants that you should be planning in your garden such as for vegetables fruits herbs Etc
It's taking all the data from the sensors which are light humidity temperature soil nutrition Etc
Telling you you're at a very low level
What you should be planting which is I like
Yes I was here tells you at a high level
As opposed to the low cuz a lot of products tell you like
They give you like he's beautiful charts where you're just like
Wow
I can see my pH going from day to day and then you're like
Wow I don't know what
What to do with that
This is just like you.
Judging by this you should plant League
Here likes
Sweet
You're like what what if I want to plant strawberries
I don't know if I say to it
I imagine if I said to it
Give him where I live I want to plant strawberries it would be like
Just don't do it
Yeah
I mean if it's not on the list of
Things that would thrive in your soil in your environment if I would even show it so
But it would be kind of need
If it could say you know
If you want to plant this
You should probably add
Like if there are things you want to
To do and could live
If you added like
Things that are atom
Hannibal Lecter
Or
Sure if you make your soil just
A little bit more
Kriti
Vikriti I mean
Bad things
It rained a little bit
Then you could totally do that
I like this
It
Is available on pre-order
It will start shipping in
Spring 25th
I feel that it is
Start shipping what's the cost on this I was just about to tell you that
Eden Garden Center
And Eden water valve cost 5999
So that get you started and they're saying One sensors good for about 250 square feet
So if you have multiple watering Zone to me anymore sensor so I totally understand that
These are wifi-connected and it looks like they
Only work is only works with an IOS app from what I can see but I'm not 100% sure on that
What I
I like and you mentioned an x-ray before the show
Being a big solar panel guy I like the fact that there are
What looks to be solar
Small solar cells on top of all these sensors and such
There are these oh yeah these are powered
Their power.
Their own
So I like the fact that
Take them out there in
And they do their thing
It does look like a
Gets iOS
Which is really sad
Cuz I was thinking of
Purchasing me
Yeah I mean
This is typical right now in the industry has been for years and not terribly surprised
I respect that if they
Near do well in selling these products still have enough funds to devote resources towards putting an Android app together
Again I'm assuming I'm only saying iOS on their site
It doesn't say in the FAQ is or anything about
About this
It also says an epic use that there is a battery
Setting is both have solar power in the backup
Right right
And they aren't they said they plan to open up their API to third-party developers next year
Which
There could be some interesting Integrations coming
I'm trying to think
What I would want
Oh when my son pulls home and the driver walks down the driveway I love to have the water going to be great
Motion sensor TP TP your house
Between the hours of
Light Em Up with the hose
Go eat and go
Yeah I bought it for my garden really I bought if it's soaked the kids when they
Sorry
I can see it that's true I like your neighbor who always has their dog
Poop in your yard but you're going to pay for it
I wasn't even thinking about that
When I have an iPhone maybe I'll
No no
I'm sure that's not worth the investment is today
So that is your spring gardening
Update kind of product
Anthony Eden
I will look for that and if anyone tries it out let me know
I will be excited
To hear your
Your take on that and if you want to send us a
Actually a tip or email you can just send it to info
At iot podcast. Com
Yeah we've had one for a while I just have enough shared it
We are Towing real legit
Hopes I'm finding this out as you are I mean this is breaking news breaking news last week
Now this week we have an email
Stay tuned
What else might we go
Alright animated gifs on her website
We could do
Sprinkler gone off on the kids
You set that up Kevin and then we'll go
I do know what actually I'm going to try to set up this is going to be
I think my husband
He listens to the podcast
But I don't think he ever goes this
For Father's Day
I want to set up this is probably way TMI but
Are you going to order a hue light for inside of our bathroom
Because we have like
In our master bath we have like a little toilet
Bright
We didn't put an outlet in for a night light
So
You know if you're in the middle of the night and have to go to the bathroom in the middle of the night
You have to go ahead and turn the lights so bright here like oh my God what's happening
So I realize
I don't know why it took me this long to realize but
I'm in install a hue light
Cuz there's a download
So I'm going to install the $60 hue light
In a little motion detector
Andra set it up for your SmartThings
So during the day
Can you set off the motion detector the light is just going to go on
So you no longer need to hit the light switch
Might just goes on but after about 10
30 at night
Then when you go in I'm going to set the Hue to go to a red light
Light because red light doesn't wake people
Pull up
So I'm going to set it to go to kind of a lower red light
So then you can still see but it's not going to be like
I'm awake
It is 4 in the morning
That's better than I
Stop what you're going to do with it I thought you're going to different colors to Signal what you did in the bathroom or something
Okay. See that's just that's just way too much
I'm just saying you know it's what you talked about the changing the light colors on the Hue of the time I was like where she going with us
But no the red light works actually when I go out stargazing and such I have
Red film covers for over my flashlight and such for that very reason
You don't want to lose your night vision
Which is very important you're sleeping
Except when I'm going to the bathroom
So this way
It's more important
Now there's the too much info
Okay
So
That's that's my plan I'm going to set it up I don't think I'm going to tell him
And then
So one night he
He's just going to
What just happened
That might wake him up
But then I think he'll be
You might want to tell him it's okay
Really he's going to be happy
He may not even notice
I mean that would be ideal
SS
Awake
I don't know I'm released
So there we go cuz that's like I already have a motion detector and not using
What's the cost of a $60 light bulb Plus
Maybe five
The 10 minutes of programming that
It's just simple
Like after between the hours of 10 in like
6 in the morning
My son is red color
The time and
That way we don't have to flip a switch on and off
So
That's going to be I was going to do it for Father's Day
But maybe I'll do it too
All right
Speaking of like
Crazy home lighting
I did it I talked about lighting
I'm sorry you would
Even before the show
Let me let me give people just a little bit of the back infect side information here before the show we talk about what we're going to talk about on the show
And as soon as they see gets on the Skype I'm like okay so what light bulbs did you try this week
Google
I did you know I was expecting some new light bulbs but they haven't arrived yet so next week
Next week
These are these
Supposed to be like awesome you
Internet of Lights Show
It's true I'm not even going to light Fair
So there we go
Imagine if I went to that you guys
Okay so
Speaking of life
For the last week I've been controlling my lights
From my
On which is not
Unusual
What is unusual I've been controlling it
From to new apps that let me
Basically
Control
From the lock screen
Of my Android
Ice
We've actually talked about one of these on the show
It is old Incarnation when
What is an app called you know me and you guys may remember it because it woke me up at midnight playing
My radio
Because I thought I came
I'm home
The fix
Fat
With an update
So that that's good
But the new one I wanted to cut a dick into is called reach
And
It's on Android only right now so this
If you got an iOS I'm sorry just
Fast forward this
But basically what it does it's
Supports
Wi-Fi devices for the most part
And
Right now in my house
It is supporting
The nest
The hue
And
My Sonos Sonos has
But it also supports
A bunch of
Other devices that I don't have
And what's cool about it is
Whenever you walk into a place that has anything
These devices it will automatically detect them on the Wi-Fi network and I'll be like hey yo do you want to connect
And these devices are a Chromecast anything made by LG
Make a smart TV
Heroku lifx bulbs
And then the other devices that I mentioned so WeMo nest
Sonos in
And she likes
I will say I've been having issues with my nest
It keeps making me link my account
I'm so
Every couple days it's like
Oh now you need to relink your account and I think that's because it's an
Unofficial
Integration
So there's the benefits of being official vs. unofficial
But I love it because all that I do is it comes down
On my notification screen
And I can do it's it's very much designed for those quick things like oh someone's at my door let me just pause my
Sonos music really fast
Soy
Pull down the notification screen and I just hit pause if you
Like all I see all six of my Sonos players
Back and hip pain
Or when I'm going to bed at night I just
Pull down the notification
Screen and I can
Turn off my bedside table light
With my Hue relief
It's
In in Granite because of
Because of how I live and how many things I test I have a
Dozen different ways to do a lot of these things
But I have to say doing it from the lock screen
Is really freaking sweet you guys
Yeah this is this is a very clever implementation I guess they're using all the apis from these various devices
And consolidating all the controls right into that pull down notification shade on Android
And that's just a beautiful thing I'm looking at the theater face on the Google Play Store right now this is the
Free apps in beta
I actually it took me awhile to find it it's cuz there's a lot of apps called reach
So if you do search do a search for reach Smart Home
Now that's where you'll find it's
Buildfire developer jch connected Tech
Ink
And yeah I mean
Stacy it showed it to me on a Skype video chat
Not too long ago and
You know I got to see an action was kind of neat now it recognizes and finds all the devices quickly
Just looks really clean and it's the consolidation
You know I talked about using a phone to connect to all these devices and control them I actually like that
Do I like doing all these different apps new I do not sow
This is I like this idea and because it is almost like a widget in a sentence
It is
Yeah because it is I wouldn't surprise me I don't see it here yet
It wouldn't surprise me to see them
Easley Portis over to Android Wear watches and if they ever come out with iOS version again on the Apple watch where are you
Have all those things within you know an easy swipe away
In the wealth are there going to be doing an iOS version
And they they are looking at
Their whole goal is to do
Is to not replicate all the features
It is to do something that is
It is to do the quick features
In the easiest format so they are very much looking at watches
Is there very much
Looking at
Easy ways
Things outside of screens
Rhino
You're getting your not it doesn't give total control over all these devices what you have is the most likely things are going to
I want to do with them turn them on turn them off as such if it's a light
Play or pause on a Sonos or change the volume on a Chromecast you know something you're streaming to a Chromecast
So like the simplistic idea because it's quick one
Pull-down and you're there
Yes
And I love it
So
I've been having a lot of fun with it
The first time
It in it
Again it's in beta it's gotten
Progressively better
Like the first time I downloaded it oh my God it crashed ever
Every 5 Seconds
Now it's very rarely cry
I'm so if you're on an Android
And you like to play around with this stuff
And you have a lot of
These devices
I highly recommend you give this
Because it is
I'm not going to say is change my life
It is a lot of fun to play with
It is definitely something I'm using
Everyday
So
Check it out
And on the
You know me friend
They have fixed a lot of there
Issues with the geolocation
So they added official geolocation so now you're not getting all these reminders like
You left the house when you're really still in the house and it's just your Wi-Fi network that's flickered
They've kind of
Twitter support for
A lot of their devices so it's
Much better
And did my final thing on all of this stuff that I would say is
I'm going to beg the guys over at WeMo
You
You guys need to work
On your API
I
I've talked to a lot of people in the deaf community and
And as someone who owns the WeMo Staffing
Is connecting it to a lot of things
I'm getting progressively more frustrated as a user
Because
My WeMo doesn't know if it's on or off
And the more things I connected to
The harder it's
Becoming for it to know
What
State of being is
And that's that's becoming very frustrating for me
One solution is obviously like
Hey Stacy
Maybe you shouldn't connect it to the reach app and to the echo
And to the SmartThings app and to all these other thing
But
I don't know if that's really anti if
Bissonnet and
You're you're not the typical person that is
You know
Is that is out there buying is priced you're trying them all and you're trying to make them all work together
You know for a cover it because we talked about it cuz you have to understand it
So
I can understand you know
I can't do but even on this richat for example the WeMo
The WeMo implementation is a little frustrating
For even the developers be
Because
It's kind of a Dodge
It's a little iffy on the
Annotation size
And for the echo people
Again they have some issues and Isis
Suspect there issues
With it sometimes working in
And sometimes not working
Not just because I've gotten the code word strong which is another issue
Is because
Of the
API
So I'm trying to get the
Go to talk to me cuz I know they've been trying to revamp their API
So
I'm hoping that this
Coming down the pike but I would really like
As a ninja
Because
I know that I try every
Everything out but I think a lot of people are connecting
What's with this way when you start connecting one or two things in your house and then there's all these other products
You're going to want to look and see what else you can fit into your environment so I get that I do
Connecting light
If this then that
Yeah that be fun and then maybe you're like maybe if WeMo doesn't work
Swift nest
Then suddenly you're like
Yep and if they don't work or
I agree
So on on that kind of Grimm note
Please WeMo help us out
We will leave
For this week
And
So we've got
Cool new products for you some new software that's free
So will leave you will leave me with that and stay tuned because
We have our guest
For this week is Michael Symon who is the CEO and chairman of log me in which
Has utterly revamped
It's exactly iot
Cheap platforms
Businesses and the internet of things and
And of how they're starting to do some cool
Cool stuff with that
Hey everybody we are back with the Internet of Things podcast and today's guest is Michael Symon the CEO and chair
Chairman of log me in
Hello Michael
Good morning Stacy
Good morning I am so glad to have you on the show and for those of you guys who are like
What is LogMeIn doing on the show
Log me in
Is the company behind
Lively
It is a cloud platform
For hosting
Hosting internet-of-things type services
Michael probably has a better way to describe that you want if you want to give it a go
Sure
LogMeIn makes
And by product I mean it
Microservices
Esl to
Companies
Or trying to sell ship
Iot products
If I can make him
Example home lighting
Decade
I want to have iot interactive home lighting
Technology that needs to be implemented to make that all work
And I was in the business of delivering.
Alright guys you heard him he brought up lighting I did not
All right so you actually have done a great
Job
Explaining to me
Your customer base
And in doing so
You actually help me
Kind of segments the iot market for businesses and I'd love for you to do that for our idea
So
You guys provide your service to a certain kind of
The clientele
And it's those companies that offer
An existing service and by making it connected they actually
Can help
Basically do it better and hopefully
Increase their profits
And maybe even make it cheaper for their end customers
Can you kind of talk to me about
The low-hanging fruit
For a connected service busy
You are so pretty clear distinction between
A product that is connected to the internet
And a what we call a connected product business
HP printers have been connected to the internet for years
No not not really
And
Connected product business
It's really defined by the notion
That you have a product
Yeah but user a customer
And you have the company itself
And I cannot katanick business there still ongoing
Lillian and during relationship
Between those three
Call parties
And it's not just
Employee
Oh that the company
Keep tabs on
What's going on it's actually that
I have in that relationship significant
Product
Stan's Lee better
I actually having that ongoing relationship
Walk-in any company
That has
Needs for Logistics
Delivery Maybe
Replacement replenishment apart like a filter
It is a perfect candidate for a knife
So you can imagine something as simple as that
Well I'm at a secure place you can throw papers though
Pretty simple business and its construction
The devices
South Bend has been which is kind of like a garbage can with a lock on it
Is not terribly high-tech and its construction
But you can imagine if I added
That was at work when not being is full
It could be a substantially better service
They won't have to ever worry about it overflowing and
Full capacity
At the same time
The company stand
I actually was damaged dramatically reduced
Collier service
Yesterday told the company when they're full
I couldn't do a better job of sending people to service an empty those then
In a way that is
Better balance between producing cost
I also have the same time has a high quality of service
And those types of business there's this
Lily
I feel like this the sooner they can become
Sure and you guys have been doing this for
For several years and
I can think there vending machine companies there restaurants
I rather
There companies that monitor like refrigerators and restaurants there
You're right there's scads
And
In the years that you guys have been doing this
What is the evolution that you
Senior
Customers
Like do they call you and they're like I have just read about the internet of things and now I'm a shredding company and I want
Modules on my trash can that enable me to do like
Just in time truck rolls or is it a little
Bit more
Gradual
What is the evolution of
The connected business
Heating pad
CNN it's it's interesting
Acog scope of companies we interact with
Industrial Light industrial applications to Pure consumer
Smart
Country that makes Smart products
Life Sciences company
And even though the businesses are very very different
I'm sort of the evolution of
The company's thinking on iot
Usually follows a similar path
Products be better
Maybe by having the product in Iraq
With an iPhone on an iPhone or an Android phone
User interface therefore be a better product
Step One is awesome you just won
The product could be a little bit better
And we think we can do that by having it in Mobile
We have to have a
Dive lyrics
Connectivity
Share that belief
Until what they start saying is all right well then how come
It's not the better product
To make the business better how can you improve the quality of service
How can you get smarter
About how people interact
Sometimes hear that
Data is the currency of the IMT
Metaphase 2 and how can we
Suddenly
You get much more
Intelligent about the needs of our customers when you start engaging and having relationship with them
Commanded that information
It's at the data self can be overwhelming
A shocking amount of data can be produced
How you actually what you collect when you collect and how to ensure that
Properly secured
Why the Sears is addressed properly there's a data management
All right
Are we going to
Integrate
Are connected products
In our overall business includes
Integration inside Legacy business Information Systems
Erp system Salesforce
Others business integration
Also going to need to engage
Your lisp with my products customers and partners overtime
The way back
Halogen
And then
Price value both to the customer and upon the company
So we really see this
Trajectory from can we make it work
How do we get smarter than
Finally
Overtime not not just
Launch button
One year two year five years
And how
How long does this
Take
The evolution from
Hey I just I want to add a feature to my iPhone to suddenly realizing
Oh my gosh I've got all this data in realizing that I am now
Not just a product
For a services company but I am a
Connected company
So icy
When we sit down with us
Customer Prospect
We try and walk them through this process
If you could come to the top once it's kind of not that hard if you
Come over a little
I wonder how much further it is to go
We're trying to be a guy
Are the journey for a lot of our customers
People's own devices is that that process of discovery
Can be anywhere
From the day they go live for the first time
Within a few months people suddenly realized potential
Energy that is
That comes with a connected
Opportunities and obligations
Pretty quickly
Arjen Robben
Is to make them easier and faster
Okay
And as you said I am a big believer that data is the currency of the internet
It's the value
So
You guys just launched a
A new version of ivory that has a really interesting product
Is part of it called blueprint
And when I saw it I thought hey this is the compliance section
Which for a lot of Enterprises
This really important
And for the Internet of Things is
It's incredibly important because this is
This is all about
Being able to
For lack of a better word tagged data
With permissions with
Rolls
Sue an accountant can access this data
This customer
Created this data
They're permissions associated with it are
As follows
It's it's a very complicated thing when we think about
You know
Permissions associated with the customer who's granting the permissions
Who at which companies
To have access to the data
Can access it
Which companies can access it
So
In building that
Why did you guys kind of
Create that
How does that relate to
The stages of the business
UC
Companies going through
I actually
It's awesome, customer standpoint it's maybe
Started their Journey
And gosh I was going to manage that once we go live until
Blueprints weekly just rolled out this week
And
It was in response to sorted
Repeating pattern that results of unmet needs
Ark Center customer base
Blueprint what it is that allows our costumes
Camaster business are clouds
Place to capture and manage basically all the roles
And permissions throughout connected business from the employees in the business to the products
To the customers to Partners you might service Buzz bottle
In a sense of place where a lousy one
Who are all the parties agents
Actors in my connected business
To what what do they do
How do they interact
I'm with each other what's the relationship you had each other
Then what is there air rights
And
So
Blueprint is a place
You can say all right
Customer is allowed to interact
A certain product
A particular
It also might have in it that
She can't interact with that same color in that
But a service agency
It's its roles Commissions in relationships
Access to devices
Access to data
Because the data that is generated by the iot
Is in enormous in its volume
But also has
There's a real need to be able to manage it and away
So that through the the life of that information
It is
Protected if you will and associated
With the right people are not inadvertently shared with those who we shouldn't have access to it
Blueprint in the case of data needs conscious
And and her diving system important part of it
Gratitude assembly cache and data that then you have to sort out in the future
Taxi capturing data that has gluten in it
So bad
That information is easy to make sense of
The Seattle Center
In building that
It sounds like a huge
A huge job
How did you guys kind of think about architecting
Which handles
I don't know I don't know you'll have to tell me how many
Hundreds of thousands of nodes
And then in building kind of what sounds like a huge kind of Knowledge Graph
Relationships in
Data
How did you design the system because that is a
Problem that a lot of companies who are dealing with the Internet of Things in the back end of that are thinking about in
It's really not something that we've established, Target
And what what makes it technically challenging
It's just the scale
How much information and how many devices are interacting
I normally would never have any reason
You're the largest Enterprises in the world might have
Few hundred thousand employees and they might have
Seven-figure is about interacting with their mostly desktop
And so the notion of devices connected
Since 2004
I've been running and service back
Total connected over 300 million devices
Avenue neighborhood
Mom cell
We are getting exposed to that
Years and years
Feeling back
Laird
We have to build and implement
Getting data from two devices
And so we build our while we have mqtt a Mexican compliant
Solution
It's actually built on the data brokerage system that reviews
That are built on
Securely got a brokerage system
The anchor tenant
But on top of that
Things like blueprints
Capturing time series data capture
I really felt
Off-the-shelf database
Technologies
And
There's not the Technologies office
How to deploy it
It it really had to
That you have mourned
Can you do the bathroom
And what were
Focused on
It's not simply doesn't work but doesn't work
When we did send a message we have to
Authenticate that message in real time
Ambi
Can certain people and they have lights receive that message
And then transmitted I have to do that all
Custom systems for data ingestion custom systems
And Andrew optimizing together in such a way that
Low latency delivery messages
Are the same time Insurance Commission
And I believe I saw that it was sub-50 vilaseca
Within our data
Celtics
But a typical using the bathroom.
Oh that's all the way out to me like
At the end
Exactly
Okay
Well that sounds really impressive if you want to ever like
Show us Batman Lego engineering blog post
You know let me know
Because I am
I love that stuff
And Michael thank you so much for coming on the podcast
This week I really appreciate it
And that's it for the Internet of Things podcast
Join us again next week