Hey everybody it is Stacey Higginbotham and my colleague
Kevin tofel and this is sorry I caught you off-guard there Kevin but we have not
Talked in awhile so you kind of threw me for a loop there we go this is this is the first time we are recording the internet
Set of things podcast as it is now called without
Without the gator on Logo because
He know I'm his
Well it is it is no more
And so you're still here we're still here and we're still friends and we still love The Internet of Things
We're trying this on our own we'll see how it does and you guys have actually been super supportive in
A little demanding asking us to keep this thing going
So we will we're going to give it our best shot
We do what we're told we aim to please
We do
And so first off we'll get started with the device that I have been trying out in my home
It's a device I recommend to lots of people so you know ye it is called the Staples connect
At home hub
I had tried out initially a couple
Gosh over a year-and-a-half ago now
About a year-and-a-half ago these tables connect home hub version 1 now I've got the second version which is manufactured by.
I think it actually came out in August
But
I know so long ago
I hadn't gotten a chance to plug it in until now
I hadn't had it in my house until a couple weeks ago so I
Popped it in the house I tried it out and
I got to say
I still like this thing a lot I really do I love the way it works I think it has
A pretty great
Array of devices for people
And a wonderful UI for people who are
You know interested in the hub
Ecosystem right who are interested in connecting a lot of things
It has five radios so this version they added two more radios Bluetooth and zigbee
To their existing radios which were Wi-Fi
Z-Wave and Lutron
And it's kind of the Lutron that makes this a little different because
Not
When it launched not everyone had Lutron
A couple other hubs like wink now has Lutron but this works way better than the wink hub
I'm not going to go there but I never ask you a question so
The difference between version 1 and version 2 it's obviously the new radios
Is there a price difference at all and and what other
What other changes have been made to this hub
So
Earlier Hub was manufactured by Linksys
And then Cisco sold off Linksys and sold it to Belkin
I'm in Belkin so
So now this Hub is manufactured by D-Link
Which also has its own a smart
Camera lineup the Arlo light up with gear
But it doesn't have a hub so it makes this one
Probably is a price differential but since the other Hub isn't out there anymore it doesn't really matter
So
There's no real comps there right now they're doing a deal
I believe the Hub is 7999 if you bought it on your own very expensive but don't do that
Do I loved you
This is actually pretty good one so if you buy two connected devices
At Staples
Airbus
You will get the Hub free
So basically you should just go spend sixty bucks on connected devices
Bright light switches or Outlets or lights or something yeah switches Outlets
I'm going to spend a little bit more and all honesty
I personally like would go out and get
Like this this would be me right I would go get maybe some Hue Lights
Were packing a Lutron dimmer I'm a huge fan of the Lutron stuff you guys know this
Or if you want to get like a
They got the Arlo cameras they've got
Support for one of my favorite devices which is the Jasco outdoor links
That's great around Christmas time I know it's not Christmas time but
You know any time you got outdoor
Lights are things you want to plug in
I love those things
I think
I bought mine on Amazon for
I want to say they were about 25 bucks so that may not get you there
But
I think they're more expensive inside the store
So and being a cross-platform guy
Can I use this with iOS Android and anything else you can use it with IOS and Android
They also have a web browser
What I've noticed that they did and I think this is really
A very smart move
Is they started
Doing two things
1 is
When your
Looking to add on to your system they ask you things like
Do you want to manage your home security
Or
You know
Have your lights to something you don't have your lights turn on
When you walk in the door
Did they offer you little scenarios and then
Then you should buy a connected light switch
Shopping
And that that's actually kind of nice it's giving you little hints about what you can do with these products
And that's that's a good idea because a lot of people
Don't know when you say I have a smart home what what does that mean what can I do with it
You can have 50 different options that people
Probably don't know about right or is like do you want to buy a motion sensor here like
Well I don't know
So I like that and then the other things they're doing is they're actually doing a lot with the data on the back end
For both consumers and retailers
So on the consumer side
They'll show you their they're working really hard to show you
If you have the following three products in your home you might also like to buy
This product
It fits well with these other products that you have
And on the retailer side they're showing the retailer the same sort of data and then offering them the chance to go
Give you coupons or
Special discounts or maybe an email marketing campaign towards you
You may or may not like us
I'll steal from the company
That's in my backyard practically Pennsylvania's it from his own off so this software back into
Amazon AWS
That does all of this stuff end
I noticed by poking around in the app a little bit
A couple things that aren't available today like appliances
It kind of hint to me that maybe we're going to see some cool stuff in the future
Like appliances I'm actually on their webpage right now
Now and they say that they're suffer framework scales across mobile devices and such which we knew that already but also HGTV
These Blu-ray players clock radios picture frames so you could really start seeing a lot of smart
Devices around the home that we don't think of today
True I know that they
So
Zod provides the backend software for the Salton Sea
Remote control blinds
Which is kind of high and proprietary
Home system
Hours for my blood
It's so they do that and I talked to the
Paseo Mike Harris the other day and he mentioned to me that
We should expect in the coming months to see new channel partners
So
I'm very eager to see what he's got there and he also mentioned to me because
I don't know if
I guess we haven't talked about this cuz we've been on Hiatus for a couple weeks
But Amazon
Has
Put a call out for Developers
Porous SDK there that I've actually started releasing an s2k for its Echo
I don't know if you remember this but when
I was trying out the echo the one thing I really wanted to do was command the echo to do things like open my blinds are turn off my lights
Softcore says like Mike are you guys going to work with the
Amazon STK
He said that was something they wanted to do so
Song Welcome to do that too I know so I'm hoping that that comes because they had actually had a deal with
Ivy the voice controlled alarm clock
That didn't
Work out so well on the Staples end I don't think Staples offers that product anymore
But
You know in my quest for home automation voice control is really high up there
One day
I agree if the invisible interface I said that for years
Did you write I've heard you for years
I'm sorry
No it's okay there's a reason you're here
I'm going to go check out my Staples now because
I'm kind of excited by that you
It's a good deal in Uno if you don't mind
Swapping out your light switches
I really love the Lutron stuff I know it's an old interface
But it works so well oh
And
For all of you guys out there who really like
Who really like lighting and I know I get in trouble every time I talk about lighting I'm sorry Mia culpa
But
This is the only platform that I've experienced so far that I can actually use the Lutron Pico remote
To control both my Lutron lights
And any other lights that are tied into the platform
So I can control my Hue Lights
My like zigbee or other lights
In
All of that on one little remote control which is
I'm going to say it pretty darn handy
That's nice I know you like your remote controls as opposed to using
Your phone so that's that's that's great
Picking up the phone unlocking the phone and opening the app on your Apple watch don't worry
Like I'm buying the Apple watch showing all your experience with user I think
I am weight
But you have an iPhone are you going to buy the Apple watch use a mall
ISO from Windows phone all the way on up or down the stack are we going to look at it I don't know I'm still not
Not convinced
That is going to do
Enough for the price for me if I do get when I will say this right up front
I'll probably get the smaller one not just cuz it's $50 cheaper
But also because
I'll get the sport model
43409 so
I'll save some money there I don't want spend five six hundred or more on on a watch
Not smart watch
Okay is that is a lot of money to spend on a watch
And
So
What would you what are you most looking
Forward to about the Watcher does it
Meet your needs
That's the thing. You know I wear an Android Wear watch now and it I think meets my needs better
Because of the Google Now contextual notifications that pop up throughout the day
And you don't have that with
With an Apple Watch at least not out of the gate
On the flip side is
You're locked in if you buy an Android Wear watch you can only use it with
Android phone and I don't always use an Android phone so
I may just buy an Apple Watch I don't know I also
Back the pebble time so I have that coming in May
Which is cross platform
Well and you also I mean the Apple watch is the same thing I made it only works with the iPhone
Exactly what I like.
Yeah that's why I backup Pebble time quite honestly
I prefer a cross-platform solution
Pretty much anything I need these days
So
I don't want to have to worry about what device I'm using who made it and what software runs
I would just want to use apps and services
Across
My choices and
So
I don't know yet but I'm not
I'm not sold on the Apple watch I will say this haven't used it at the end when it actually for a little while at the Apple event
Earlier this month
Even though it does a lot of the same things as the Android Wear watch
In typical Apple fashion it does
Have a very elegant fluid
Way of doing things
I do think they got away from their Simplicity a little bit but you're
You stuck with a small screen and few buttons it's very hard to keep things simple with user experience so
Jury still out yet on that
Well I do also I remember you writing many many many
Months ago or maybe it's years ago even
You know nobody knows what they want a smartwatch to be
So it's very hard to design
A simple interface for something when you don't know what it what it really is yet
Yeah this isn't evolving category and
It's going to change and there's no doubt about it
I think back to when the first iPhone came out in 2007
That was kind of a turning point for the smartphone era
But it was really about a year later that we really got what we all wanted in that was apps and it's going to take time for the
The Apple watch to get its abscess while so
This is going to be an interesting year of evolution I think
And maybe maybe
Interfacer
The model for the watch isn't apps
I kind of look at that and I think
I really think it could be sensors in just like an interface or just providing additional context in
In that situation you don't even need
Apps per say you just need
Sensors interacting with things around yuan
Yep that's it
At that point it also becomes a presence indicator and identity indicator and there's a lot of other things that are
Not
Abcentric that this could work
In the future so
But then you need you need a lot more around the watch that works with a watch for that
To actually
For it to be valuable enough to people
A whole ecosystem I know an apple
Apples good at that again though I think
I think
You would have to have homekit be already out in the market I think it's going to be hard if you're not cross platform
As the ecosystem
Gets
Wider as it spans more than just a phone in more than just a computer and it starts didn't touch
Every aspect of Our Lives it becomes really hard to be so vertically integrated
I guess or so to have such a wall Garden
It is a challenge
But it's also a challenge that Apple has face before and they have experience with it
And some people like to be inside Apple's world nothing there something wrong with that and it's perfectly fine. You know I know I know
I'm not like everybody I was actually happy to hear that
Android where may I should be coming to iOS
In which case you could use an Android Wear
Watch with an iPhone
I don't think it'll give you the best integrated experience because of that
Vertical integration that's
That's missing
But
I might be happy enough with that again I I like Choice that's just that's just me
Okay fair enough
I want to say I also want to draw your attention to the fact that Google Now did they talked about
An open API for Google now so you might actually get Google Now on your Apple watch
You know two things come to mind here or you can already get
Google Now notifications on iOS devices if you install the Google Search app
It feels in which is really clever of Google in my opinion
So you know I'm using an iPhone today and I already had a couple of contextual notifications pop up
So pushing us over to an Apple Watch really shouldn't be a big deal because it's just a notification
But as far as Google Now itself it and the openness of that that's
Coming there
This is becoming a whole little mini platform for Google
Please Google Now cards that start out with just basic contextual things that it learns from you about your penis through your email
Baylor Fort Worth to other Google service interactions
Now that they're opening this up to developers yeah it's great to have you know a little cards that pop up from apps that say hey
You're near
The coffee shop you want to check on the FourSquare or something
It is bridging at that gap between the app and
And having to
Please unlock your phone go to the right app and so on apps come to you that information comes to you and I think that is really
We're Google now it's going to be 6 continue to be successful
I cannot wait
I think that's probably a good place to end today or this this note of optimism
And
We'll stay tuned for our guests who is Brady Forest of
PCH Highway 1 incubator
And he's going to talk about how to build products that don't suck
Which I'm really excited about make them cross platform
But we did talk about making sure that you know they work and support usually
Yeah well you know you'd be surprised how many don't work
So
Or maybe you wouldn't cuz you talk to me and you experience the joys of them not working yourself I only buy the ones that were
I on the other hand by all kinds of stuff but I'm going to Staples that's it
There you go well if you if you do set it up let me know what you think because
Right now
That's probably the best platform out there for the mainstream consumer I would say
Alright house I will let you know
All right
Hey everybody it is Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
And today I have is my guest Brady Forest who is AVP
Highway 1
Is an accelerator is part of the
PCH
I will call it Manufacturing in fulfillment house is that the best
Version of peace
TCS designs Custom Manufacturing Solutions
What is a handle company supply chain
And so they
How companies make things that help companies move things around
Package them
Design
Can you show up
With
Your product
We can make it
All right well there you go so
Highway 1 is PCH
Accelerator
And Brady manages that
So that means Brady is your guy
For kind of some of the really cool connected objects coming out of
I don't know Silicon Valley other places in the world
We take care of the world
11 companies
Four of them are from overseas Irish team
I got steam in Indian team
Awesome I know all go home after after the
All right and you probably will I know you guys who listen to the show have heard of these companies because I
Talk about them so
Some of the ones I know you've heard of would-be
Wrigley
The drop kitchen scale
I'm trying to think of others that I know I've talked about I
Well I don't know what are some of your I won't say favorites Brady cuz I'm sure you love them all but what are some of the ones that I know
I know have hit the market cuz we try to talk about things that are mostly on the market
Things that are
Let's let's do mostly on the market and you can throw in one or two
Are available on crowdfunding
Sure I mean I think right now it's really just dropping ring
Things that will be available sooner rather than later or birdie and Toto
NFC
Things that justic crowdfunding yesterday or switchmate photo
Okay
Which is a Bluetooth
Oh yes I got excited about I'm a real fan of buttons
I love to press things to make things happened as opposed to
Relying on my smartphone
I'm so
Button fan
Okay
So
The reason Brady is on the show is because a couple weeks ago I just got so fed up
With getting devices that didn't work
And
I am constantly testing devices so part of this is
My job
Is getting these connected devices in
Playing with them
But after probably 2 years of doing this
And they showing things off to my friends and having that moment of like
Please please please I just talk to sub to everybody and pressing a button and then nothing happening
And my friends going wow this is really awesome
I realized that
The smart home is never going to take off at this is the user experience that people have when they spend you know
Two hundred bucks on a device in
It only works half the time
So
I thought because
So far the two devices that
And there's more than just too but
PCH
In my my
Highway 1 devices it really works
Well
Out of all the devices that I've tried
So I thought you'd be a good person to talk about
When devices
You know when can they actually be kind of like
Beta devices and then
How do you get
A device into the hands of
Consumers that does work
And isn't kind of an iterative process while it's out of the market
So
Let's start
Brady with
Gosh
When can a device be
I guess in beta still
And Beyond
Because there's no
There's no registry that says Okay a product is finished
And reality is
That said there's a big difference between
Thug
Where it
It doesn't
Which hopefully most of the things you're experiencing are bugs
And
Crab say
What's
Castle call designs on gourds
Which is
When it doesn't work the way it should but it is actually how they
I work
It's on the one case
Honestly I think
Which happens all the time
Or
They had
In a lot of the mobile platforms that these companies depend on
I have ever shifting
Code an API
And so sometimes the stack actually changes underneath though
Or you're using some configuration
But they were unable to test
Cuz I'm Lottery
AR
Constantly changing for Developers
Hundreds of thousands of Android phones
Numerous
Bluetooth stacks
There's thousands of Wi-Fi router
Docker Network stopped working
Elizabeth connection
There's also the design flaws
And that's when
The inventor has come up with something they think
A device
But let's say a switchmate
You design it to turn off your lights
From your phone
But
Like what you said Stacy you don't want to turn off the lights
So
When you first get it
Definitely turns off
Your lights whenever you want to
You don't like you got an erection
And you wish it did something more until in that way this kind of
Failed in that scenario for you
Okay well in India time
I'm less concerned about that because
I am forgetting that you know
The people who are building these products
You know they have a limited
They're usually startups they have maybe
Five or ten people on a team they can't get
I feel like if you meet your specs that you've advertised to me
You're doing great
That's all I want
I would say though
That
So so let's
Let's talk about the ways that you can fail the consumer cuz I think that's that's probably really relevant
Phelous
You can fail in many ways as Hess I have discovered throughout my life
So there's there's the failure of a product
Working as advertised and I think
One way that this happens is
When someone launches like on Kickstarter
Or promotes their product
There is
They often have the list of basic features it'll do the following things
And then I have the list of like things they would like to have and then they have things that
They promised when they talked to reporters about
What they're doing
And sometimes that all gets kind of muddled together
I don't know if you've noticed that
I don't know what the advice is and I see this all the time I mean I see it with like
Products that talks about algorithms especially they're like oh it's going to anticipate your every need
But that's not going to come out for another six months after we launched
Great
And really my everything
I don't know
That sounds awesome I'm going to totally Bacchus fresh
So
When you when you think about that is is that somewhat
What would you advise companies to do do you think they should be
Talking about those
Things do you think it's maybe people like me the reporters who are like all this sounds great
A little bit I got to admit
Well I think that
Companies should always be clear when that
What is its width Now versus what it will ship with
And
I think they should be clear when something is going to require a lot of customers to get
2 scale
And so
When it's something that's going to anticipate your every need
Comedian
That says
What has alot of data it will be able to figure out what users in various situations do
The thing is they shouldn't over promise those things because
Until they hit mescale they won't hit
No scenarios
And so they won't know what to do and that is stereos
And the reality is still never
Every scenario
Even Google it
You know
I forget the percentage but it's never seen everyday
Google
More queries that have multiple pets
User cache
Don't have that advantage
And so small
Companies that are trying to take advantage of user data is it only have a small user base
They're not going to
Be able to anticipate your every need
That is a real bummer
But you're probably right
And what about
What about Baseline features cuz this is another
Spot where I see companies fail so
For example I recently tried out a home security system
That
And in this might be good for birdie because birdie is a home security
Customer in air quality monitoring system isn't it
Air quality monitor
Is a scary
That's right different birds
I'm so pretty air quality NVM
So I tried out a home security system
And what are the things that
Actually wasn't a future but
It should have been a future in
Maybe now
Was but it didn't notify me when it went offline
I thought that was
You know a glaring failure
In the product that
Wasn't even part of the design specs so
And they could add it later right and I'm sure they did
But
So that that's okay swear it wasn't a bug it was just
I guess that design
Failure in
I don't know how like
To think about things like that and how
You prevent something like that on the product
Design side
How do you advise your company's
I think about things
Like that
Well we try to get our company is to
Beta units into the hands of customers as soon as possible
And that's that's how you that's how you figure that out
Bluetooth controller
Several small let's say Alpha
Runs
IMusic sometimes like 3D printed super ugly and I sent them
All over the US
Just to see how people would use them
And that's how they realize that they still needed to be able to turn on the lights manually
Not just
They had one user
Actually you know knock it off the wall and break it
Nothing really like
Treat this like a
We need to ask
Insulated rubber gasket to add more friction
And they also put a little buffer unit around the XL controller so that the the end product
Could stand up to
Getting your product
To customers to see how to use it
Is how you find these laws
Another example is
Current lettuce with their product
They launched
Kickstarter beta
In January
They
Did the kickstarter a confidence 30 units I believe
Sold out in 24 hours
And all the customers who bought it
Will get
A new Fitbit
When the real product comes out
Or at least 10
Promised by signing up for this Kickstarter
That they will send feedback
And help inform the team about the product
When actually ship
Orlin actually wants the real crowdfunding campaign
Deliver the experience they want
We pick up people to pay for the device that they're going to test
That's awesome
You'll have the features
And I can control the heater and lights
This is a fully functioning device
However
It won't be the exact experience they want
They're still learning how to interact with it with the software
So I mean
These are going to be expensive
Current isn't going to make any money
No they didn't even find the cost of like
The original betas
Even offset the cost
Beta unit
It's great
Okay
So that's that's good feedback in the fact that maybe maybe you can even get people like
If you have some sort of product that
Really hankering for you can even get them to offset the cost of your Betta is great
The other
But let's talk about cutting the complicated
That you can fail with bugs because I think
That's where a lot of this
Happens
In this is super hard
And you brought us a really good points and I don't know how to
I don't know how
Companies can deal with this
The idea that there are so many platforms
Then the idea that their people are clamoring for Integrations
So if you got a connected device that you're trying to
Launch
Do you recommend that people start with maybe one platform like maybe just iOS
Get it out on the market and then try to
Build for Android is that one way to control kind of the Experian
Or
Is that not good enough fight I don't know
I think simplifying the number
Limit the number of bugs and Stereos got to deal with I don't feel like people in the eye
Hold on Android for too long
Because there's still quite a
Salina technical world there's a lot of people who use Android
I'm an Android user
I will tell you that
Yeah I think it's quite tricky to to totally avoid
Keywords to get caught up in a lot of things
Scenarios around relying on other people's platforms
I'm so excited
Playground
Here at Highway 1
Where we have it so no sweetheart Hugh we have SmartThings
We have a nest
We will have a flex what kind of switchmate will have the birdie
So the people can test
How their device interacts
Actually get into the home
You know it's a work with SmartThings
You know it'll work with nest
Less people going to blonde
That magical experience
From you
Systems work together
Or they could send it to me cuz you just described my home
And I even have more if they want more
What we can put you on our business
Bacon bacon just be like I will send it to Stacy
Her home is a nightmare of epic proportions
Alright so
So let's see cuz cuz that is I will say
You know what I actually
The first thing when I get a device
I actually
Tested on its own Merit
That's before I
Hook it up to anything
Because
Because I fundamentally think it's unfair to be like
This is awesome now I'm going to break you with like hooking you up to 20 different things
Because I mankind
Maybe I'm not
Find I don't know
What it comes to
The Integrations this is this is really tricky in
And I don't know
How your your companies and how you tell your company's
It is a consumer I don't
I know what I do but I don't know what the normal
So let's let's get your take on
Things don't always work even like when I test out my works with Nest integration
A perfect example will pick up big companies cuz
Cuz they have they have power they couldn't they can handle it
I was really excited about
The shoe works with Nest integration
Because I love my
Hewn
I like my nest
And I thought the integration was really clever
So I hooked it up and he was a great toggle
And then I noticed an idea was when you
Link your nest in your Hue Lights together
When your nest goes to away
After about a minute your Hue Lights will fade slowly off
And you will save energy
And if you
You're like oh that's so nice
And then if you're away for more than a day your Hue Lights will randomly go
On and off in a random pattern to mimic someone being at home
So you're like
So cool
Okay so I was sold I thought that was great
Turn it on and then
I had like a television crew in my house
And I'm like this is going to be great guys watch this I told them about this integration they're like
And then I turned I turn my Nest to away
And we're staring at the lights
And nothing has
I think it's going to take a minute they want you to be able to walk out of the house
Without
You know pump it into anything
They don't want the lights to all go off at once
So we're still staring at the lights and they're like
Nothing
Finally
We realized
It just didn't work
So I'm like
And because I me you know I have the ability to call both nest and Hue and be like yo guys
Disintegration it doesn't work what's going on
But a normal consumer they're like man this doesn't work who do I call you know do I called Nest to Echo hue
Both of these are actually have the consumer hotline which is nice
You have to go to the forums
Did they actually who pushed out an update
It was a couple people had needed an update
Make it work
The bottom line is
These don't always work
And
What are you tell your Custer your company's win like
They play with these big Partners or small partners
And our customers are like hey what's going on
Doesn't work
I always tell them to get out front
I mean
MC not more with
I see it was like
Manufacturing delays
Don't let people know that
Where you're at
And just be
Open about it
And I think
I need that
Some people need to realize or companies need to realize
Integrations
I mean you and consumers in your direction
After they already want your use case
So
In the case of IV
You want voice control for your phone
Fact that it works with nest and you have the nest
Like me and you in the direction of Ivy over say Amazon second
People want to sing
Financial platform
But
At its core it's going to be
Whether or not your device looks
Fair enough
So
Who can you who can you
Kind of test devices
Cuz
I do think that there is a market
That you can test devices on so is it your
Clearly labeled Kickstarter bettas like the is it
Fish bits
Was that the name of the company
Chris Peterson products
Okay fish bits
The fish pets product
Is it is it like a clearly labeled beta Kickstarter is it a normal kind of
Indiegogo or Kickstarter crowdfunded kind of thing either self-funded or however
Self-starter kind of thing
Or is it
It it's not at a brick-and-mortar level it's
Probably not on your website I don't know
At what point in time can you
Kind of
Have these preview Hardware things
Can I borrow a little glitchy
And at what point in time do you transition to something that
Pretty seamless for the end
I mean I think it's a chance on this on the company
And product
A lot of V ones
Regardless of the company in the size of the company
Are often the bugs just because
Actor Leinster bulbs
Call Sang
About your cello under
Many eyes
And
The reality of these teams are five people
7 people
Extended shipping to 30 people so they're going to catch a bunch of bugs
Obvious one
But it won't catch them all
And they won't catch them all
Even after this ship to 10000 people
They will still encounter new box
Encounter
Hopefully they'll fix
I'll be able to fix the bugs as they encounter them
New bugs
Best product
Okay so it's like don't buy it like
I remember a friend of mine bought the first
The first version of like the Mercedes
The first model year of the Mercedes like sport utility vehicle
Already hated that car and he was such a loyal Mercedes customers whole family about Mercedes all their lives
You know I was like dude
You just bought a Mercedes why are you complaining all the time
Kiddo that that kind of stuck with me I was like okay never by the first version of a
You make the Model T automobile
Don't buy the first version of a self-driving car
It's
There
Good companies are figuring this out they are figuring out
I mean
They are trying to create something new
And trying to create a company
Trying to figure out the company
The building that product
So
It can be a challenge to do both
At once
It's like
Building the airplane on your way down
Okay very scary
What happens if I mean because a lot of these are startups
What do you say
What do you recommend for these companies do they have like a
A parachute do they have an exit plan for their consumers or
What do you what do you tell them in case they go out of business and they leave people with
These connected devices that may or may not be so
Deported after
A year to
I mean
I onion I think that that's something that the iot states is going to encounter
And we'll need to figure out I think it's something that they can learn from the web
I remember when Billy was first coming out
And there was a lot of concern about how
URL shortener
You don't know
Where is actually meeting you too
And that's
And I brought on a lot of those
Ruined the world with rickrolling
Having perpetrated that way
Italy
Their credit
Argument
And said okay if we ever go out of business we are going to open source
Our or make available our database
Lynx
And so that other people can
USB is cuz we don't think you are going to go away but at least
Translate our links
And that really I think
But these people can
Still use the bit ly URL Survivor the well
And I think
Iot companies haven't hit that issue
Where
They are going to have to deal with
Their products going away
I think the first consumers
Yeah cuz the first one we have right now I think
Well it's probably not the first one but the biggest one that I can think of is the revolve Hub that
Googlebot
Revolves in
Will stop supporting the Hub after a year
I mean in that that was a company that was bought by Google which is
Legitimately so legitimate business and
Piano
That's that's not just a
Zombie kind of company so
I don't know it is interesting I'm very curious of the devices that I have purchased
How many of them will be supported
Especially things that I have like unscrewed switch plates and rewired into my wall and like
I hope I don't have to risk dying of electrocution again
I'm reminded of the leave it loose
Yeah Microsoft
Trying to shut down some of those guns
Which method people would lose their music
Could have stopped at 3
Big big fat in soda
I believe they got stuck
Make a note
Now they got Legacy
Google can easily
You can picture the revolve code and system
Blowing into Nest right so they can easily
Sends a new nest
Every resolve user
Right but that that's a lot of radios to pack into some
So
I don't know
We'll see if Google calls us all upset hey wait
No promises on our behalf
Brady we have
We have solved we haven't really soft we have
Traded one intractable problem for another
But I appreciate your your thoughts on this because I was
At as I'm getting frustrated with things I will remind myself that there are lots of platforms
Their ever-changing
That you can't think of everything all at once and that
You know unless it's a gaping huge security bad that I feel is like
Ridiculously
Ridiculous
In the sense that
Really guys you probably should have had this
Maybe we can come up with some best practices that should just be baked into all designs or something like that
I will try to be a lot more forgiving of the
D Minor bugs and
Add the major ones to my best practices my mental best best practice
So thank you for coming on the show
You're welcome thanks for adding me on Skype