Hey everybody this is the Internet of Things podcast in this is Stacey Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a wonderful issue for you today
I am going to talk about lights
We're going to talk about the Amazon Echo
We're going to talk about mysterious FCC filings
Dunt Dunt
Yeah
Oh I guess I should have got a spooky music like
Still working on sound effects for the show
No no that's it that's that's all we have
Okay then
Or maybe that was probably more like a
Wentworth
Sad trombone
Okay so
Let's get a started with
Oh I don't know what's more exciting
Mysterious SEC filings are brand new Bluetooth lighting
We talked about letting a lot was talking about the FCC for a minute
All right
So
Kevin you want to kick ass off
I would love to sew first and foremost we don't know exactly what the FCC has tested
But they have tested something
That would be related to internet of things we think
Thanks to your Dave's that's over that's not funny he noticed
A Google filing with the SEC where a device was tested a smart device
We're not sure exactly what it is what do we know we know it has Bluetooth
And that's it that's all we kind of know
In terms of the internal radios and such they seen I spent some time looking at the filing
Really couldn't
Make too much heads or tails of
What does Maybe
Some people are saying it has to do with Google Glass I don't think so at all but
You know because it only has Bluetooth and there was talk of
He label in August for the FCC label
Touch screen type device
I was actually wondering maybe it's a beacon of some kind
That's kind of what I looked at it that's what I thought in that we should explain for those who don't know
Well I was going to say we should start with what an easy label is
And why they are so the FCC has to approve any device out there with a
Most of you guys probably know that
But to those of you who don't
So anything that has a radio
Has to do with FCC approval because
Sting's interfere in
That's bad
Assisi Heights
Cuz it was bad cuz it's bad when your cell phone doesn't work cuz you got some cheap microwave oven like
Mess with your signals
So that's what the FCC approval label in
You'll find it on
Everything from Lake toys to
High-end iot devices
I used to have to be used to be either extra on the device to be a paper label but now they have electronic labels where
The FCC certification IDs and such
Canby
Sean just like the software version on your phone
Very nice so that's what this is
It's it's fairly new it it was only recently that the SEC I started allowing that
How do you say need a screen for it so it's if you don't have a screen on your device or not to have any label
So this device has a screen
See we learn something already
Most vegans don't have screens
True let's
True and and in the testing data there was talk about normal usage
I've only just
5 mm between this device and something else so that kind of put the kibosh on the ibeacon thing to exist
Some degree
So okay so will it first fall will tell people what a beacon is so a beacon
Is
It's a device that uses Bluetooth to offer location data
And it
They basically constantly transmits to your
Your phone
And your phone if it has the appropriate app will open up an app
Tied to that Beacon and says something like
Hey you are here and here's what you can do based on the information that you
You're here so I can be like
Historic
Coupon if you're in my house it could be like
You have access to this liquor cabinet
Or
Do you like this
Room this temperature and it will share data with the house that says you know there's a person in this room you should turn on lights
My house is
Isn't that smart yet but one day it will be
I'm very excited
So that's that's kind of the promise and Hope
The beacons
But this if it has a screen
Bluetooth Google filed this on April 20th
The Friday before I saw that Samsung filed
For a Smart Lock with the FCC
And I got all excited thinking
Oh my gosh
Samsung S introducing a Smart Lock
But they were actually doing an nfc-based Smart Lock for the
Small to medium
It says business and it was actually more like
NFC RFID kind of Base
Listing with a card
But that is what I learned
Samsung actually had
The Samsung home division over
South Korea four
Yahoo new
Yeah probably everybody over himself
So what's a nice trip so maybe then this could be a Smart Lock that ties into the holding
Nest Dropcam infrastructure
And set your phone with its Bluetooth unlock Sherlock I don't know
And you would need a screen I mean you wouldn't need a screen but a screen
Might work
For that
Will fix a touch screen there might be an alternative
Method of Entry such as entering a PIN number or something like that
And a lot of people that again keypads
Very popular way for small business
Google's actually been cut
Keenan Smallville
But whatever it is thanks for the FCC testing we know it will be safe
Safe and not interfere with your cell phone
There's Our Mysterious SC
Sissy device
And since we're speaking about Bluetooth
We'll talk about lighting we do talk about it a lot but this is the first Bluetooth lighting device that actually tried
It's from a company called ilumi
And
This just hit the market actually last Wednesday
I was in New York so I didn't get a chance to fully run it through its Paces to talk about it
Before last week's show so sorry about that you guys are a week late on this but
I've been living with these I've had
The two kind of air called a 19 so the normal size light bulbs
And I had a down Lamp Theater
Full color
So full color LED lights
The a19 version the normal light bulb
Persian is
89.95
Yowza so 90 bucks they're very heavy
And the
Downlite is about 90 bucks
I'm sorry is about 19:9
95 Silverado hundred bucks
But they're all Bluetooth so all you need you don't need a hug you just need your phone
But after living with them for almost week I can tell you you
You want more than your phone
You want a switch
Because the second you run out of Bluetooth range
You can't do anything with the light
So if you want to turn it off
You got to go walk by the light bulb
You're not
At that point in time my God
Why Suburban totally defeats the purpose
Especially if you were like me and you live in a big house with an open floor plan
Cuz you're like looking at the light across the room in your like
I would have turned it off
I got to go
I got to get up and go near me
To turn it off
That's a lot of dough for
Limited range light bulb
To me but but but I will say this in the video that you took
It was actually kind of cute your dog dancing around underneath the light switch was changing colors
The light colors look pretty intense in my route
They do that they're amazing so the light
Colors are like
The Christmas light quality they're very vibrant the blue is phenomenal
The white
It's very stark white I wouldn't
Wouldn't recommend that
White what I will say that these guys have got going for them
It's the software experience
The more of these
Alternative lighting
Things that I try the more I realized that Hughes app
Sucks
These so illumi has built
Experiences
That's what they call it
And what they've done is
The ones that I've tried that are really interesting
Are called
Torch
And this one actually the lights will follow you
Now I only have three tests bulbs but they
They notice where your phone is
And they light up as you walk through your house
I like that isn't that fun
I'd like that that's like. That's why I want begin to my house and have it all tied together
Here you don't need that
Pékin because you are your friends The Weeknd
Exactly
It is fine if you have your phone on you
If you don't
It's kind of a bummer
But
So so that was a really cool thing and to enable it all you do is go to the experience section and you literally collect your lights you want in
Can you turn it on and boom
Again
You run into the problem that we talked about before which is
Your house is a shared environment and your phone is personal to you
But it runs on IOS and Android
So you can't have you know
Two people having this kind of experience although you're going to have dueling you know
Lights flickering on and off
We didn't put it
In our front porch so that was kind of neat when you come in
You know the front hallway light will come on and you often have
With you so that's fine
The other experience that I showed with the dog was the Dance Experience
And that thing was up
So it tracks through Spotify on your device
Or Google Play
Or iTunes
On your iPhone
And if you're playing that through your phone speaker
Or I actually went through a Bluetooth
A Jambox that I had
On the bench by my door
The lights turn
Bright colors and they
Have different
Dance mode that is all colors they have
Cool mode that is cold colors
In a fire mode that is
Only one color
And that's pretty
Nice
Very nice
So those are
Those lights
And
So far I'm not sold on
Unlike on the Wi-Fi better
Well wider range for one thing and then
I like the torch feature I I think the
The mix of having both is going to be kind of fun or just having Deacons
Better deployed in
Yep
I'm kind of disappointed we haven't seen more
Pecans for the home
Implementation
But that's just me me to they're coming
I'm I'm still waiting for the zoo Lee Outlets
You know there's the
The Wally home
Sensors that are integrated with nest
But you're right there's
There's not a lot
Actually out on the market that are tied into other
Nope
Nope nope nope by speaking of Nest there is something to talk about
That you actually have you can't use it this way yet but you got an Amazon Echo and we talked about it last week
Wait don't I talk about the Amazon Echo actually you know what you didn't talk about it much
After you did the review from that that time until
Until just recently when
It came some third-party Integrations we talked about it last week
What is it
Right now integrates with
Define exactly
So you've been able to test that which is very cool
But now that Amazon has the SDK out there for these 3rd party invitations
Absent developer I guess he has Early Access
I'm assuming he's using the official SDK but I don't know for sure
PayPal apps that you can control
Uses Echo to control Smart lights through Corky's wink hub
And he can also control his nest thermostat right through
The echo
Yes
So I saw that I have a tried it and
I kind of want to although we can't yet cuz he can't publish that dab
Here we're getting into some question
Okay
I use the Echo app literally every single night both me and here's the
My husband
Hello
That's big
Doesn't use almost
He uses almost nothing in our house that's
But
We also I
I talk to Google
To shut down my nest
So
Make a Google Now
I'm not going to say it
Can you talk to me
But I actually tell it to
To turn my Nest down
If I'm downstairs and I don't want
So I don't now I'm going to have option
Do I tell him
Alexa to do it or do I tell
My phone to do it
And I don't know
Cuz my phone is named Charles in my
My echo was named Alexa so
It's a job
Bear in mind I'm currently using an iPhone
Because I'm doing some testing of a case with an e ink display in it
And in the
Google
Voice command I don't want to say it
On iOS I can't control my nest
So for iOS users who have an echo and a nest
There you go
Oh so my husband will be thrilled
I don't know about that but
He actually he will he's really liking the voice control of all of
The stuff and it is I will say it's super handy like when you're in bed cuz we
Like I said we have the remote control in bed and
Okay Alexa
Make it colder
She's like
Boom
I'm really liking her she is
She's becoming my favorite person in the house I'm going to be honest
See now I'm disappointed because I had the invite to order
And I chose not to because there were no Integrations there was no SDK available
I'm like
A hundred bucks I got to wait 6 months for it now shows
You chose poorly lesson learned
No what did I do I got up at 3 in the morning order an Apple Watch that I still don't have report
But it's going to be worth it I hear that the Hue app on the Apple watch
Is amazing
Well I'm looking forward to trying the apps and as a former Android Wear user I still have my Android Wear watch
It's amazing to me that there are over 3000 Apple watch apps on day one
Where is Android Wear we didn't have that much
And they're very very few apps that control
Home automation systems on Android Wear
Will actually have to get you some
Home automation devices set up so you can X
Play with that
When you actually get
Is that that's it that is a subtweet
To get my insteon system setup again yes
Yes I know I don't think there was anything about it but I think it was that was pretty
So I also wouldn't there there's a few news items that we should
Talk about
There's a company called scanadu
Which
Makes a
Tricorder
Guys
That's why rings
Is it
Oh my gosh it's Star Trek that has this tricorder right very good thing that you got that correct all the Star Wars
Bands of the all over your face
Sueldo I knew it wasn't Star Wars cuz I'm trying to picture the Star Wars people
I see a doctor McCoy
Edwin
So these guys make the tricorder is a hockey puck size device
You stick it up to your forehead for about 30 seconds
It measures five vital signs
Measure heart rate
Respiration blood oxygenation
Blood pressure
And one other item I cannot recall right now but I thought that was pretty good that I got four out of five
The other items really important
And they said that to your phone and it is
Is going up for FDA approval sometime at the end of this year and by next year it should be out in the market
About 8000 people currently have one because they had a
Indiegogo campaign
Last snow in 2013
So those people
Their devices shipped to them last year
Their data
Was actually the kind of
The day today
Submitted that will be submitted to the f
So scanadu that company raise 35 million
And they kind of did an update
It said by the way y'all next year the device is going to be out
With FDA approval
And going to cost
$199
Not bad
Which
That's reasonable to me
That's
Oh you know what the third item is
Stress
Temperature
Hello
Has taken again
Temperature we're just talking about the mess
There you go
Not that.
So
I'm really I am really excited about
Both as a person
Who has kind of Sam Lackey blood pressure things going on but also because I'm a parent and
Mostly because I
Blood pressure issue
Cosmo
So I'm really excited about like monitor
And I think you should be much as you but
The collective you because
Quite honestly we talked so much about home automation and smart
Sync devices in the house but really
I Ortiz
Is going to be very big in in health and was just today that
I think Los Angeles hospital has put 80,000 of its patience on
Apple's Health kitten and such you know
So
There's so much Health Data out there and it's hard to get at it's hard to get at these
These different measurements which are constantly changing so devices like this are super helpful
Oh I agree in what I
And in talking to the CEO of scanadu his name is Walter de Brouwer
This man is so smart and so fun
But
Biggest thing that's going to be happening here is
He believes it
And if the combination of
The processing power in your phone
Cheap ubiquitous sensors
And
The digitization of medical data that can be aggregated and made searchable
And crowdsourced
Will basically create kind of a Moore's Law
The medical industry
Wish
Basically he means it's going to speed up the medical industry
Incredibly rapidly
So he thinks we're going to see all of this change
Consumer Healthcare
Faster than the personal computer change business and consumer technology
Back in like the 90
And that is
That is huge and I really don't think that many people
In like the pharmaceutical industry or the insurance industry kind of really grok that
So I cannot wait
Exciting stuff
All right
Well
Stay tuned because we are going to have Mark Ralston
The CEO of Argo designs
Come on the show and talk about how to design smart home apps
That will work on the Apple watch
Hey everybody we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
For all of you Apple watch
Aficionados and those of you who are just waiting to scoff at the Apple watch
I have a treat
I've Mark roasted who is the founder and chief creative
Officer at argodesign
Highmark
I am really excited to have you here
You are also
Either of you have a naughty relationship with a company called Peak
They make a home hub that is sold in Best Buy and other stores
And I'd love for you to tell us a little bit about how you related to them
And we're going to talk a little bit about how you design
User interfaces
For the Smart Home
On the Apple watch
Yeah thank you thanks for inviting you puke is I guess some simple shorthand
Or one of the equity Partners in this company
Develops Smart Home Solution
The Client List
And I think that song
Just helps driver behavior in the different
Would Peak succeeds you guys succeed
All right we'll Peak is one of the
I'm going to go with almost
Almost a dozen kind of home hubs
I tried out and
Coming hopefully later this week you guys are going to do a refresh of the app
And the new version I've seen
Parts of it and I have some really cool
Kind of things and hopefully later on we'll talk a little bit about that
The first
We're going to focus on the watch because that
Is probably what everyone is focused on right now
So Mark why don't you start by telling us a little bit
Because you have one
Can you tell us a little bit about what you've experienced
Since you've had one in
What you like what you don't like
You're not sure
It's finished it on there for several days
And it's kind of a hot mess
Wait we should wish ask you which version did you get
I got the stainless
You'll
38 millimeter versions of a smaller one
The stainless steel band that wraps around
I'm hardware and it is absolutely gorgeous
Feels nice
Put on
Relatively comfortable
You know I don't want want to watch like 20 years if it's so far no 3 Days Inn
Beautiful logic
Votes not in yet
It's clearly going to be on screen quality
Beautiful bride
These little moments where
You look so you swipe up to get one particular menu
Like to watch you Excel if you can swipe up
To get the client has a slight down to get another menu
That's how that works
Let's go to another
And you
Costa-hawkins don't follow you
I just condition
I'm not even
It's cool it's definitely
One of those products do you got to learn it
Distance to complicated
For what it's actually do
It's certainly not like the first couple days of the iPhone
6 Mile
Is it a function of
There are too many
Different ways to
Control it like too many different options or is it just a function of they don't
Logically
Seem to follow
Auntie Christmas early too much going on
Okay I can't find kind of a logical usually you can kind of see below the hook
And I'm not saying that they weren't grappling something that couldn't have been solved
Like maybe this is it
Because the nature of a problem
An interface on a risk that complicated it could be
Good
It is it just feels like I'm still trying to figure my way around
Surprise
I said to someone earlier today
And I kind of imagined play music I want Steve Jobs still
Loud and in charge of things this is the kind of product
He might have sent back and I know it's hard I don't care
I don't think you would have sounded that nice about
Mystery we want to keep our clean G rating
Again I want to sympathize with how complex it isn't then literally I'm new to this problem is
Because a problem Samsung did
Android Wear
Can you see Peyton icicle no more
All right
Glad
Little Caesars
Okay its design for tiny fingers
And so far it has a
We'll call it an inconsistent maybe syntax
Design syntax
The mechanic
The underlying interaction
Lamodels housing
Time elapsed
Watch faces sells a whole lot more than just
Breakdown
Once you get into a nap it's all pretty easy
You didn't want to ask me
Will guile to get back to the main menu
Watch face
And that's where things get weird notifications of course
Interrupt
Access
Annapolis
Exactly clear
Okay let's talk about building
The apps and con of working with notifications and all of that
Because some of the best apps that so far I've seen
On The Watcher that I've seen people review on the watch have been those that kind of
Appear to be very effective at
Managing notifications kind of in a Spartan Manor and also giving people
A lot of information or
Ability to take
Quick action
Swipe credit app
So
How were you kind of thinking about designing the app
For the peak homes
The promise the pcap
Pretty simple
The same way that a lot of this
It is very simple premise which is
I want to turn on my lights
Or
You know my favorite scenarios I'm coming home and I
Remote switch
Between away and home
Gunsmith a trigger
So do not lock the door
It's Great Compromise
Felt like the right place to do that sort of thing
Eventually become a voice control
Watch so far
Better than the phone
That
Along little things like a somebody just arrived home
The kids come home
Backdoor results
Camera
Is there how can I feel good
And it's crochet
That's one of the reasons
I like this
HomeSmart homes for rent
And we've been developing the app
Sounds great
And that we imagine
Will the Ikea track
Ronnie Lott
What WeChat
How that relationship works with the way up Apple setup to watch
Super sensible and SMS
Will they give me permission
Cereal place
City Cab
Right now I can't do that
And I can choose take a couple of those things because
First party
First access
Features
So instead of the watch being your home screen by default
Are the watch face being the home screen by default
The PCAT becomes my home screen by default
Las Vegas
Got much ones
So
It needs to go 90 further than just nearly I can
Customize the grid of icons ride with the phones and Android
IOS
Dama
Let's become mine and they're good equally accessible
First-party and third-party apps
Far far more control over that experience that little grid
On the way I can just fine
Watches just
One Step too many
William Anderson
Awesome just launching into getting a petit smartphone
Ticwatch app with B
Launching
Scream right now
Physical pain in the ass
It cuts out some of the possible Magic
Level access nothing
How many steps does it take to launch the app have you counted
Let's see okay so I got to reach over
Up comes the
Good rap songs
I can pretty much directly tap you up
And then I'm on at the first screen
Set alarm
Nicely designed and it's basically
The the anyone gets
Little squares
Some that utilize control
One aspect you how one of them could be the mode Switcher
The way
Another one can be kitchen lighting
And you just going to rain slows in a row on the watch so something the first one shows up and you swipe
Brighten you
So it's
It's three steps
Are four steps if I want to like turn off the light
Switch from home to work
2 steps
Envy Apple
Significantly better
Tiny tiny
Intimacy
I don't think it's funny at all because right now if I want to turn off the light
I hit a switch
I mean
Is usually the way we're trained now if I want to turn off a light if I
Counted out
Getting up I'm walking over to a place
And I'm turning off a light
But
In my head
When I think about it
All those other steps are complete until I get to the light and turn off
Like my brain just discounts all those other steps right
Today's news
That's a losing battle but a couple of things
A different way
Are there
That's one aspect of this compound
The way of being
Address of house
Lily magical scenarios
Watch and various switches that mean IQ
Weirdest shifting gears
Another was much more complex
Shifting into night mode
Which Baron allows the bathroom light to turn on read it supposed to light so that it doesn't
Or
Steering wheel
Lights up
When it notices someone's walking up a stairwell
Excelsior
Beautiful
The watch then it's less about these like
One switch after another but instead
Youth small gloves
Controls
The Peaks Apple Watch app
So my kitchen camera
I can see.
I think maybe two steps
Raptor on the pole counting steps for the same thing
I can do that while I'm still in the meeting and not be staring down at
Lansing MI watch
In the office
And let's talk about this broad kind of
Design rules for the Apple watch
And
You know let's just about design rules kind of for the wrist
Even you know
Well we'll keep it probably more Apple watch Focus
You know if I'm breaking it down I'm thinking about
And in tying it to the Smart Home
Or the smartoffice however we want to
I think about that
You know I'm thinking about it in terms of notification
Versus
Taking an action
In a building where maybe I'm not
Or maybe I'm in it and I just
I want to turn my lights off
Without getting up
So
What are kind of the things I want to think about from a notice
Application standpoint
As a user I can think about
You know I don't want to be overwhelmed by notification
I've already a little overwhelmed
Sometimes
Buzz false alarms
And also things that
You know what I get on my phone and I'm like
I really can't do anything
This information I think you were with me one day when I was like
What am I motion detectors has been moved in
It's a
Closet
My house right now so when they happen
BMI
Yasso
So I don't really want to get that on my watch because that's
Yeah it's going to help me
Frenzy of worrying
You know if I don't have my phone on me there's probably really legit reason for not having it right in front of my face
Set the time so
You can think about early
Notifications on the phone
They were basically an extension
Latin for the extension of what astronauts have become in the market
It's important call out
Look like now notifications and Pulaski
It's just a design flaw since I can't just quote
I got really talked about the fact
Sociology
With the song
People have changed at the same rate
That was come up with new ideas
How to communicate small static messages
People
Spencer trying to do other things
Scorned
They've grown to want to see information of 30
Vielen dank
Despotic scepter
But literally just moving Target of people grow into
Living with nothing
Ears
Show me exactly what I need to see
I want to see interesting things about it
Is
Hard to pull up and they don't stay up on the screen unlike the clock face
I get the logic that they it's like
The message
Fake police things basically
Your listings you feel the vibration
Little something I was typing when one of them went off
And
Retreat at pointed
Interrupted me
Made its presence known
Couldn't wouldn't stay long enough so that I can get to read it
Turn out to be one of those rules
At least Apple earnings
Right now it's spending so much time
Ninja gets battery feel like I spend almost half the energy dealing the watch on my wrist
Just keeping awake
Going to do with it, single it for me
Menu operations clear enough
On taking Act
The flip side of notice
Applications
Taking action
It's cool tell little commands
It's a very short concise list of things you can do
Get to the fullback
Enough talk response
And
So you like song
Whatever you want
Absolutely beautiful
Works really well
Lieutenant standing
I will Siri works on your list
Given the limitations and processing time
Ergonomics
Your list
Galatea
Bad idea
Beautifully well
Absolutely meaning creature
They can imagine them really tuning the whole messaging systems where
The list of the central Play Store
Carry on conversation with me
Right now it's still a little weird it's just too hard to get them
Because it is bad new
But I realized
Even if it takes
Ocean
Interrupt your conversation with people
What are Deep Pockets
You know exactly how to use it exactly how it will be on
The Watch
Easter version 1.0
Liabilities actually
Inconsistent
Fall back asleep
I think I can fix that I can imagine 1.11.5
If you get that reliability down
I can never lose that talk about how these
Interactions of Steel
Right now it's pretty tough
Making judgments about them because they are
Other beasts
Call Tanya
It's kind of like me in the morning you should never make a judgment about me early in the morning cuz I am
To try to find
And I'm just clearly not at my best
And I'm going to ask you one more question because you're a big voice
Aficionado kind of like me
Can the Smart Home
And you and I have before the show were talking about
The Amazon Echo and using it to control our hue light
With Siri being on the
Apple watch in that being such a
Good experience so far for you
Nailed it
So
How was your divvy up kind of the idea of
Controlling
Voice
On your wrist
VS kind of right now I just shot up into my house
Or if I'm in
The bedroom I shout into the room
I speak into the sea the echo remote
Control
So
Do you have a sense of like where we might go with
Voice Control in the home
Yeah I think I imagine the watch adopt
That's good angle button
Siri takes over whatever you want
You can want you to invoke Siri you can
You can say lots of things that are in that something poking lots of different application
What are you say you want to
Look up
Something on the web look up an address
You're doing it from the same Central interface
And talking
And
Mustard seed
Because at that point you could then say
Siri or you can pull them to say tell Peak to set my home
The computer on your wrist starts making
Incredibles
And all of the things of complained about the sleepiness of the lodge
The number of clicks on that goes away
I think as you have concrete
Holding the button down and Truckin
You let the computer catch up and its own time because
Xian in Computing
Tastic advantage in the real world
And the originals optionality
You and I
In the bedroom there anywhere you can just shout turn on the
Bedroom light
Electric Repair the system you just say that and
Echo
Simpson desert
Willingly takes a second what we were recognizes
Wow that's impressive
It just feels good
Points in Tyler Technologies
And that's why I think when you actually do it doesn't well
The Watch
Ultimately that promise
To finicky the field Magic
Got it will wait till home cake comes out too so there's there's more on Horizon not just version
This is all going to be Newton
Couple months hopefully
Indeed well we'll get this out very soon so
No worries
All right
Thanks so much for coming on the show
We're going to call that a wrap thanks for joining us
And