Hey everybody it is Stacey Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel and you are listening to
We better Newfie music
Since we don't have any
I'm actually going to pick out the music
All right
Today
Closing because I realized
For all the poor people out there
I think the show just
Yeah I kind of want to give him a little heads up
We like
Thank you for listening I think that's all
That's fine I think I think we're all on board with that we're on board with something other than
The person be like yeah thanks for having me that was fun
This is not the internet of things so let's
Let's get down to it first things up
Kevin you woke up at 3 a.m. on with a Friday
Friday morning on the East Coast I know I'm still I'm still tired from that
Yeah that was to
Pre-order the Apple watch which
Honestly after playing with a device twice I'm not going to say I'm not impressed by it but I don't know that I need it
However from a work perspective to test gadgets and try different things I did buy one
Welcome
No nobody got it
It launched but you can't get it yet and April 24th you'll be able to go into a store and still not get it because all you can do is
Order it online
Now so I don't have it
If a cat 307 that was 7 minutes after the
Pre-orders began it had already pushed me back to a mid-may delivery date
So I'm not even having on April 24th when it
Quote-unquote launches
And I
Shame on me I ordered the most popular
Apple watch with the most popular color and of course
The most popular colored band I got a space gray aluminum sport model with
Black
Sport strap
And yeah everybody else got that too so
$350 later I am waiting at about 5 weeks for the
So was there an option
Pink strap
Absolutely although I have some data
From slice intelligent stop talking about who ordered what and sliced I don't have ever use slice it's for iOS
An Android you can
You can slice and what it does is it monitors your email so it finds
Receipts email receipts from things you order online
And then they actually gather that data and get rid of all your personal information and then
Put together reports and they put a report together on Monday
And said that the pink
Strap and one of the other
Pasteli color Caesar they like the iPod touch colors
For only 4% of people ordered those
So I did not and I could have gotten that but
I didn't want that I want something I can wear everyday pretty much all settings and
Yeah I don't think that pastel pink or blue or
Whatever was is my thing for that
I could have warned
Pastel pink
I know you could pull out of I could not
Although I say this wearing a white
I see the way
Pebble watch there
It goes well see it's going it goes with my current outfit right now
You got the whole monochrome thing going on here
On the radio
And don't see my
So I am excited to get to watch because of the potential that it brings
And the fact that may lead a little bit into WWDC
I was going to say you can tell by the time it comes out maybe we'll have homekit devices
And start playing
I
I suspect we're not going to have
A big homekit push until June 8th which is when WWDC
Kids place at Moscone West in San Francisco
And the reason being if you look at the logo for the WWDC event which
Just today it came out
Yeah I don't want to read too much into this is not like
And I'm trying to decipher the logos here but it sure looks like an Apple TV in the center of the logo to me
And we've heard rumors of Apple TV getting an upgrade hasn't really seen one since 2013 refresh
And there's talk of homekit
You know being
On the Apple TV as a as a hub which I like as we know from the last show because
I don't want to get zillion Wi-Fi things on my network
And say she's laughing at me again
The big thing about home
What's the big thing about made for
The made for
I
Devices program
It's
Kind of Wi-Fi beso a lot of these
Devices have a
Part of the security + cert
Location is over the Wi-Fi
So
It could be that even if there is a
That's all right
Europe you're bursting my bubble but that's okay I can live with that
I was just thinking with this this whole
WDC
WDC WDC
Worldwide about WWDC
Yes yes
H-E-B wdcb whatever worldwide developer,
Okay
We need to get you like a conspirator Kevin's conspiracy corner
We're going to change your name
Because I can't do it
Not happening
CCC so this is your Apple
WDC conspiracy
Get the logo is shaped
It's like an Apple TV
We're going to have an Apple TV refresh
At the event
And it's going to be home care
Kind of face
Because
Apple TV
Refresh might include
The homekit
Apple TV
I think that's a safe that regardless of the logo, so I think that's a safe bet mean there's been
Some leaks and rumors about the new Apple TV and that it will have
More apps will get a refresh in terms of apps
And when you think of home kit and apps
So just all fits together
I agree with you so
As someone who has played around with most
Apple home
Hobbs already
The biggest weakness of apples
Can't when it was tied to the phone
When your phone leaves
Your house suddenly has
And that
Because you still want things that you
Scheduler
Seems to happen
Especially things
Security like my lights
To go on and off
Midas shades
All of those things still need to happen
So it makes total sense
That you would have some
Now
I am really excited
I'd like an Apple TV is fine
I hope that apple
Doesn't just
Because I don't
I would love to see any of the intelligence
Get a home
Not be relegated
It's just one
Because I don't want to buy Asus
Take device to me
Like to act as a bridge basically
Ready
So could that be done and we'll iCloud be a big part of this I suspect yes
Probably
So Apple has
Apple TV
They also at the airport
For example
So I could see like
Bad acting
Bridge device
You know you want to add Wi-Fi to
Cheap locksmith
Instead of buying
How many Outlet
None
Right
So you would hate all these Bluetooth Lawson Bluetooth devices that require a Wi-Fi Bridge cuz you have to
Plug in and out within just live there all the time
Every outlet has a Wi-Fi device in my house
It's crazy
You got more stuff on your network and they're taking about
I know
You got a device
So I just thinking about all the kind of protocol
All the devices that apple
Reasonably call ahead
Apple TV that I don't know what else to do
It could be their brand new cool device like a
Amazon Echo type devices
Siri I don't know
I like that idea
Fundamentally here's my crazy predict
Like a year or two after homekit is lost
Apple will launch
Real product
And that product will be fundamentally different
In a true kind of
Something completely different for the home
It makes it
Usable for the mange
I don't know I think you're wrong cuz I can't see how they would design a logo for that
But that's just me
No I think you're I think you're spot on
This is
This is been a long time coming I'm an apple announced homekit at last year's WWDC if I recall correctly
The last June
It's been a long time just to get to product version 1
And
As we all know it's
What is Apple do they introduce a product that doesn't have every single possible feature or the best features just yet we're the best
Experience yet
And the iterating iterating all of a sudden they got you know a market-leading products oh yes I would agree
World and they don't even have a crime rate
Actually
At South by Southwest
Jason Johnson
Who is the CEO of August
B-connected lot
Who is a homekit partner
Actually said that
What you may not realize
This is Apple came to them
NSAID
Hey
We need a lot specify
Application and since you're one of our partners
Expensive
So they did in so
That's kind of how that came to be
And that's how
Home kits facts for other products also came
State work with their partners
My hunch is Chamberlain
Winchester Park around the garage door side
The garage door
So
Yay for all their partners
Got in on the ground floor
And that
Means actually for
People who are used to working
Does products you probably have
What is going to be like to work
Specs
The huge advantage
Totally
But it also means that
We probably are going to see a lot of really cool innovative
You know we're going to see kind of what we
I don't have a sign I'm trying to picture what I need in my home
Today or tomorrow
Aluminum
Or aluminium
I want sitting somewhere doing
Something that I don't even know
Actually I do know I want it to end
Is that too much to ask
I mean
I'm still waiting for my husband and my daughter.
You mention Amazon Echo
There's some big news I read it
But not into tell I knew you were that's why I didn't
What's the big news because it is big news
I think it is
Amazon
Actually supports
Hue and WeMo
Over the Amazon Echo now
So
I'd leave my living room guys
And
I say
Alexa
Turn off
Living room lights
Go off
Alexa says okay
I think it's amazing I always want to say thank you
Can I catch other people in my house doing the same thing
We're always like talking to Alexa we like
Please do this
So I have both the polite family and
We don't know how to text
So
What it does
Is
If you want to set this up
If you're one of the few people who have an Amazon Echo
It's in beta
And you just say Alexa
Discover my device
And Alexa goes through your Wi-Fi and discovers
Your WeMo devices
Right now it only supports
Three wheel motor
It support
What's the
Outlet
The Outlet Plus energy saving
And a light switch
Arduino
And the WeMo is a little buggy
I'm going to tell you this
The WeMo API
On the Hue side it's
Support Steam
Hugh
Colored lights
In the light bulb shapes with a night
The lights
And the moon things
Does not support the other thing we talked about last week
Hugo
No Hugo
The bowl with a light in it
So it doesn't support that yet
And it also supports do I say the Hue Lux white lights
He didn't but now you did
It is
A little bit weird
So it took me awhile to figure out how to group the law
In the Hue app
You can't actually group your Hue Lights
In a room setting
Which I've always liked you after I speak
Yeah
So I got four living room lights and their names really stupid things
Left front
Living room light
So if I were talking to Alexa
I would have to
How to say turn on left
Excruciating
So
The Hue app you have to prove it in the
Amazon
That's I was wondering if there was an interface in the Amazon app now
There is but it took me awhile to find
Whois
Wander over it that's not funny
If you guys like our show you love that's enough
Is it
The URL just wwd
Wf.com
He took me off to hell
How you can actually find
Amazon Echo
Intonow
I've named it living room lights
And so
Once group
You can just tell Alexa
Turn on
Living room lights you can
Tell Alexa
Dim
Living room lights
To 50%
You cannot
Manage the
Color preferences
Sindecuse
With Alexa
And
There's a little weirdness that I'm sure they will
Update out
But right now if you're
Turning the Hue Lights Off
You can say turn off
Switch off
But if you're turning the WeMo
Off
You have to say switch off
Only switch off
Yeah I'm not a I'm not a fan of those very specific commands like my Xbox has the same thing and I'll turn it off
By voice
A lot of noise control with it
And sometimes I say the wrong turn off command I'll say switch off or something and it does nothing but blink at me like what
Obviously not the right thing
The nice thing about
The interface is
When you get it right
Alexa
Will say okay
When you get it wrong you get this tone that is like
Sad trombone
If it would be better
Womp womp
Instead you just get this like
Yeah
Makes sense
Let me ask you this since you now have
Connected I'm sorry you have control these devices
Through several interfaces now in the past
I don't know how many months
Is there what would kind of lag time is there between Alexa and say your lights going on or off
Less than a second
Okay it's a really it's really very effective
What I've done because Alexa has a remote
Control
A lot of people brought this up there like I only have an echo in one room if my
My house
Q's in other rooms
Good point
My
Downstairs is a
Floor plan
So I have it
Downstairs
Kitchen area.
Control my entire kitchen
That's the area where you have your blender that just goes on by itself when somebody hacks your network
We keep it there but I keep the remote
Control
Stairs cuz I have
The Hue Lights
Thai table lamp
So now I can
And that work
Controlling my
In-N-Out
Yeah because the remote that comes with the echo actually you can speak to and it
Does its thing just like
The Amazon Echo itself does okay
That makes it
Is there a third option in that you can control through a phone interface with
Amazon
You know I'd there is an Amazon Echo app
I don't believe it's in here
So there you go something
So there you go
Cuz then think about it
With iOS
Or Android Wear watch
You could even
Speech you're watching
Do it that way to take the phone out of your pocket
So here's the deal.
Once you take your phone
And you open an app
You might as well just do it from the apps
Already on
You don't even have to unlock the phone or open yet
Because all these apps right now for the lunches are extensions of the phone apps
So boom
Oh my say boom okay
True fairness you are right
All right so stay tuned
Because
This is all I have on the echo
Unless you have other questions Kevin
No I'm just happy to see that kind of integration I didn't buy an echo even though I had the invitation
Partly because it didn't do enough and had no
Home integration now we're seeing the first
Steps for that and now I'm much more intrigued by
But you don't have any Hue Lights
I don't have any
Thing right now because
Cuz I'm a slacker and haven't reinstall all of my crap
So once again I'm going to
Here right now
Kevin
Where where are we now
How many 6 months behind I'd say
You've been harping on me
If I'm going to my wife
Ashley she could care less tickets
Hey it was it was my birthday on Sunday
I know happy birthday
Yeah and you know what
Turning on your blender from Pennsylvania here but
I was going to say let me make you a mixed drink
No I would say
Beyonce
Okay
Since you're not going to get the Apple watch for a while
I got nothing better to do than setup insteon stuff at my house you're right
You're not covering mobile or anything
You're not right for five bucks a day, 7 days a week again
Oh okay
I think
That's probably
Some awesome stuff
That we talked about
And if you stay to you will learn we have Bluetooth lighting
Coming down
We talked to
Volume
Syllabus
Smiths
Who is a VP of marketing at Sora
In Surah is a company that provides lights for restaurants like California Pizza
And hotels
Like Starwood
And
They did a deal with company called C
To put bluetooth connected lights in a lot of really cool public places
That you will be at
Can we talk about what that means
Where and what it means
For the businesses
And opportunities
And diet
It is pretty darn exciting
I very curious to hear what he has to say because what I think of Bluetooth I think of
Personal security and pairing and such so
I'm curious
Personal security
Well like when I when you turn your Bluetooth
Phone Bluetooth on your phone
Don't you see like a gazillion Bluetooth devices around you
Be prepared
A lot
Fair enough
Box of stay tuned
Hey everybody and welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
And
We are talking about my favorite topic this week with
William
Silversmiths who is the director of marketing for a company called sora
Sora is a lighting company based out of Fremont California
So hi William how are you
I'm fine
Thank you for joining us today so
I would love for you to tell us a little bit about Sarah
Because one of our founders
Nobel Prize
Chitticks last year in 2014
Because of his contributions
General illumination
Time in Japan
Later he moved to California inventions
By which he called LED 2.0 it's based on a different material system and
He has to be manually making lamps on this new LED technology
And we have done that since 2012
Buy lamps you actually mean light bulbs
And for the most part your customers are
Commercial clients in high-end residential
Yes that's correct
What we do is in our lamps when you focus on very good, right
And we focus on directional lights
And directional lights are used in restaurants
Instance stores for example
And some of your commercial customers are companies like California Pizza Kitchen
And let's see who else are some of your customers
Do we have a restaurant change
The Jews are lamps desk hiring restaurants anywhere
Dona looking at restaurant
People trying just to create a pool of light over the table
Dinner table
And you need to pretty nail spa
Tattoo creator
Okay
Until we're talking today because For the First time ever
You guys are announcing that you're doing a partnership with a company called seed to add Bluetooth connectivity to your
I thought that this was pretty cool
Because one I feel like this is 2015 is the year for Bluetooth
Into
I think it's actually a really interesting to talk to a kind of lighting manufacturer about
Cut up the future of connected lighting
And I I wanted to talk to you about why Bluetooth and then go into kind of
What your customers are going to be doing with this so
What are you guys think like why are you adding connectivity to your lighting now
What is the promise in the Hope here
You know
Things that sent people that that determines how lighting looks like an intervention who is Neymar
Augusta
60 lighting designs
And then when they do
Lighting design that we try to figure out how to space looks like
I want to get dark
So you can imagine that you want to lie.
Embarrassed
How they talk about this
Today
And how it works today
It is every group of light as Beyond common
If you want me to calculate you snaps together
So you have me
Artistic desired and spaces designs
Everything is flying together
Things that you can do with wireless
Is it to control every land individually
So this whole constrains us how everything is going to be wire together that is gone you can have
Switch off switch
Orange and 1 control panel
Cast
Directions to everyone individually
At what level
And you can look at it individually
For customers
It's kind of at a lighting designer level so if I'm in a restaurant
I know that I've been at a restaurant because I have a young child so we tend to die in a little early
And we'll have this kind of moment in time around like 6:30 or maybe it's a
7 when all of a sudden we go from like
Daytime dating two
It goes dim and we're suddenly in romantic night time dieting
The lights are 30% lower and somewhat your
Telling me is
That could be maybe a more subtle shift or maybe that happens in certain areas of the restaurant or certainty
How does this actually play out for the consumer
When they're sitting in a restaurant
What you mean example
Restaurants
Everything games to the same degree while if you're still at the window I'm right outside
Chicken restaurant that is
Individually dawlod in
Especially related to Bluetooth to something
Really
Interesting what we like about Bluetooth is that everybody has
Just be like this for quite a while already so and if you have a Bluetooth
You would need a louder
Spanish words
And the whole
A process of connecting to a connected device
But it's not
And what you can do with Bluetooth
Instantaneous access to Atlanta show
You can imagine in a restaurant that I think people think that restaurant when you come in
We can imagine that the restaurant within a certain band
Are we get people adjustability
Difficult
We can imagine.
Did bring you sit at the table depending on your mood and your niece
How you make within a certain range adjustment
That is possible
Directional lamp
Okay so I could
I could read my menu if I
I can't see it or maybe I could
Turn the lights up when
I'm looking for my inevitable drop silverware napkins
Always happy
Since when I'm at a restaurant
You can't take me anywhere
So what is this mean for the restaurant
If I'm you know California Pizza Kitchen or
Stacy's fine dining establishment
Are there opportunities for me to
I mean it's a better customer experience
It also seems like it might be kind of a pain for servers
In terms of having to educate the
The consumer so
How are they looking at this
As
Kind of
Revenue-generating opportunity or maybe it's
One of those things
Things were there like hair designers love it but
The servers are like
Oh this is like TVs in the back of a plane where you're like
Pain in the butt
I'm a tech perspective
Talk to Consumers about
Keep running I don't know
We don't know yet
I can't breathe
You know what I'm seeing
Restaurants
Can happen alone
App Store
It's not always clear what you do
In general what we see if we give customers
Interactive that opens new ones for the retail chain
How to create Interactive
Alexa get more
Applications
I can see the menu and that's about it
Lighting
Connection with Bluetooth connect
Mobile application
That makes sense I mean that
The Starwood Hotel chain is using
Connected locks actually as part of
A reason to join the Starwood kind of guest program
And that is a really compelling reason to book through them
Is that you can actually use your phone to unlock the doors these sorts of kind of real-world interaction
Are really
Interesting reason to get people to actually use
Who's the apps
I will say though
Having 800 apps on your phone for each individual place that you go is still
Not something that I think most people want to do but for like the top 10 places it could be a compelling enough for
Can you do the room
You stayed there before
Immediately
Oh no that would be cool art his star with a customer of yours
You're working with a company called
Seed
It has a protocol called Silver
That is
The Bluetooth kind of backend for all of the
Now my guess is that if
Are you integrated with Starwood
Are you decided to work with Starwood and
Entitled to their guests
Back-end they have a different Bluetooth back in for their locks
This program so
Would something like that be difficult to kind of bring together
How how would that work
Reason for us
Sheet
Is that what about lighting
We think we know more about LED
Palace pets that are home to us but we really like it I want you to use
Distributor
Bluetooth SmartWatch
I think she will help
That would be really exciting because
Lamps are a great spot to put
Presence detection and Bluetooth beacons are kind of something I'm really excited about
And I'm curious
With your lights
Are beacons something that you're considering kind of presence detection via the
It could be for your restaurant customers it could be like in hotels
But once you have kind of a Bluetooth radio you also have the ability to say
Hey this phone belongs to Stacy or this
Is Stacy's wearable and then
Using that information tied to an app on my phone you can
You can offer me that that preference that
Stacy likes her
Her room this way or
Last time Stacy was in this restaurant she ordered this maybe you want to offer her a coupon
Absolutely
The nice thing is about Lambs
And there's power
My definition to every LifePoint so
If you talk about Deacons
Not long ago on my phone
How many Bluetooth
It's already
So attached to the beacon
It's something that is
G-Eazy and I think she lives in India
Lives
Platform protection sensors
So is that something that
Sora does or is that something that see does
With their platform like
How does that kind of get worked out
So anybody integrating sensors into
That is something that we would work on it
Coming full circle for you guys so these are the first connected products we should see these in the market for you guys at what time
I know you're worried you've announced the partnership
So how long till we see
Connected sorella's
So I expect before this summer
2 years
Or do you think you'll go all connected like what is the future of your biz
I firmly believe that everything will be clean
You know that there's a lot of stuff
Don't be wire homes or don't be why in restaurants and hotels every every two years
Do you know everything that we will sell in two years
I will be wirelessly connected
I am super excited about kind of pet future
And I can't wait for more Bluetooth lamps I kind of like
Chafing at the bit
To actually
I'm sitting here looking at my own house and I'm like
Gosh we can rewire a circuit my
Yeah I guess
We could and I'm like or we could just wait another year and then they'll be Bluetooth lights in my husband to his
A longsuffering man I have to tell you
When it comes to Connected gadgets kind of looks at me with like
A little bit of fear in his eyes he's like
Yes we could wait for a Bluetooth gadgets
Light bulbs
I guess
Getting the electrical circuits
Replace a dumb b**** is one of my biggest headache
Because I wonder likes what insurance pays
There's no Outlet there is no
Anime
And then
With
Connected lamp
But you don't have to worry about
Or
Implementing
That's why I can't wait for
This year which is supposed to be the year of Bluetooth so
Start launching get those products out in the market
Alright in so how long do you think it'll be until you guys have
Possibly more than just Bluetooth in your
Lamps are we was talking
Next year we talkin five years out till we see
Kind of like sensor Rich lamps in the home in business environment
No it will be it'll be quicker than that
We're moving as quickly as we can
I'll be next year
Architecture down it's pretty straightforward
Silento
The length of the side by side
So
Smart Launcher
Or a light source to become smart we have to ask
We we going to leave
I love it I agree totally with you
You do need sensors for things to be smart
So
Thank you so much for coming on the podcast to talk about this
SI
I am really excited about the future of lighting as all of my my audience will tell you there's like stop talking about lighting
Casey please
So thank you so much
And that's it for this week's show