Hey everybody
Welcome back to the second
Iot podcast
Stacey Higginbotham
And
And Kevin tofel
Hey we're getting better at that Kevin
I practice my name for a whole week
Excellent
And this time we have we have video on so I could have
Point to you and be like
That's right read the cue cards
There we go
Alright so we'll start off this week with
Okay I'm just going to be self-aggrandizing
Do it I know where you're going to you're going to Nightline aren't you
Can I talk about it
Stacy
You were awesome on Nightline for those who did not see it you must go see this segment
It had to be at least I don't know 7 or 8 minutes
I mean I know that your house you told me like 4 hours
9 hours that was distilled into how many minutes
I didn't count so
Like
It was like the segments on a run
And I was like
You're right there nuclear nonproliferation.
Stacy Stacy Smart Home
Awesome
Prom proposals with afterwards I thought I was going to
Proxibid
Yeah I think prom proposals wins that one but
It was awesome I watched it two times I thought it was great you showed off
A lot of the gadgets that you have in your house many we talked about on
Pryor podcast before
There was I know I know Nightline wanted to take an angle of hey how safe and secure is this so they had this this hacker guy is
Well on the segment was trying to get into your
Home netwerks who never did which
Kudos to you for that
But eventually I think you let him into the network just to do some demonstration things and
He scared the bejesus out of you turning your blender on right in the middle of you and the in the house talking in Iowa
Laugh my tail off for that that was hysterical
The not so funny part was
When he had access he was able to unlock your one of your doors
What was kind of underplayed
In the
The segment in this was actually I should
Make it clear this was actually shot back in
In January so this was shot in January
May 12th
So not even a week after I got back
And
What happened was Nightline to contact
And asked me to set everything up on the wink hub
Because the wink Hub have a known folder
Mobility
That they can take advantage
So I actually dismantle
My
Set up
And put everything
And they they specifically wanted
Get on a version of the Wings
Actually hadn't been patched yet
So folks this is how your TV sausage
Scary
And they had the hacker come in
And he
To get into my Wi-Fi
He drove around
The handshake
Show
In the plan was that they would get the handshake
I would run it through
Get basically
Accessed
My password
Code cracking
So they've got a Super Cub
Cheaters attack you
That they were like
We're going to try to get
That's not so stupid after all was it actually had
They have legitimate clients that are not
So those clients also had a job running
That took up a lot of data
So
My my password my Wi-Fi password is
Longer than password
1 2 3 4
It contains you know
Different
Characters letters
Isn't that sort of
Special character
Iot podcast with a capital p
There you go
Guess that you cracked my code who needed supercomputing
So yeah so
Basically
My guess is they didn't have a lot of
They just have several
Whatever
Maybe they had the equivalent of 2
Do Smartphones work
And I'd given them
So I basic
Sickly
Typed in my
But it was still very creepy
Sitting there
You know looking at his little interface where he was like
Look
And watching things go up and down
End
Hello
It was very uncomfortable
In actually until it aired I didn't realize that he never got my
And a mirror at the hacker lives in Austin
So I was like
2 there's this guy in Austin who may or may not know my password
I should probably change that
And this is the issue
Because I have so many Wi-Fi
Connected devices
Do I really need to change my password
Well yeah I mean you think about it
Not right now maybe in your case yes but for everyone else
As we adopt a Smart Homes
And we have all these devices more more devices in the coming years connected to the Wi-Fi network
And we change the password that's it that's a hassle
Yeah the nest
When you have your Wi-Fi password on an S that is in click wheel is like putting your password in with a rotary phone it's
Okay so the learning experience
From
Nightline
Other than TV shows are not exact
As they appear
On TV
We already knew
Was that
You know your house
Is vulnerable and
I actually have as my guests on this way
Sweet show
Josh Korman who is from I am the cowboy
Cavalry
Which is a
Security organization working to talk in more depth about that
Soon but
You know I just
As we're putting these things in guys
It is really important to think about
Setting a password
On your Wi-Fi account
Also to make sure that the devices you buy
Research them beforehand
And make sure that they are sick
Secure in that could be as simple as
Looking up
Wink hub
Secure
Or
Kwikset door lock
Secure
And then keeping your firmware up to date
I was just going to say that I don't know about you but I tend to set my devices up
For auto detection of new firmware updates and Auto download and even Auto install if I can
I know that could actually introduce a problem as opposed to help solve the problem but I feel a little bit safer knowing I do
Don't need to maintain the stuff
You know every single day
That's actually a really good
Best practice
Especially
Especially with the
Smart home because some of these things
Can actually come on
It update when you're not
Write about using cuz
There is nothing more frustrating than b
Haven to turn on my lights
No you're not
The firmware update
I just need a light
I don't need firmware
I can't read my book because my firmware is out of date
Exactly
I'm trying to show my friends my really awesome lights
And they're like
Yeah this is
Are my house I just flipped a switch
Speaking of life
Oh here we go good Segway
So I got in the mail
Just blast
Brand new light
And I know I'm not supposed
What to talk about lights but it's brand-new you guys
So I'm going to do it
This is the
Go
Two words
Hugo
I named my Hugo
I'm so
So predict
So this is
A
This is a hue light
That fits in
The palm of both of you
So it's a bowl
It's a boy it's a bowl it's a translucent bowl with a light in it
It's about 6 in in diameter at the top
And it is
Beautiful
And you can take it places
It does everything a hue light does
It changes colors
It dims
It's connected via the app
So it can work with other lighting rest
Recipes
It's kind of like
The same shape is
Friends of hue
Too late if you guys are
Familiar with those
So it can rest flat on the ground and
Like the bowl like
Or you can tilt it
And it's got a little stand that you
Tilted up and then you
Shine it up with
Against the wall
So if you have like a boring white wall
You could actually turn the light
You can highlight nice artwork you have on a wall
There's all kinds of things you can do what makes this interesting is that it's completely wireless and I don't mean just from
Being I am assuming it's wifi-connected it is
Like all Hue Lights
Is it be connected
Got
It
Connect via the Hub
Your Wi-Fi Hub
It connects
To EUR
Wi-Fi networks at the house
Right but the other
Pardes from a power standpoint it is Wireless as well as a rechargeable battery inside
So you can literally take this little light bowl anywhere you want
Put it on a nightstand in the kids room put it like I said you up against the wall to show artwork and so on
You can if you're doing work in the garage and utility light maybe you can use it for that
You can go anywhere
However I asked AC before the show how long does that battery last
Go ahead
Philip says it guarantees 3 hours off its base
I had it on for about four and a half hours
And it was doing
Just fine
And because it's an LED
It doesn't
Dim it just
It's on
Tree binary
And you know I would also say like this light
Sense8
Came and we turned it on and plugged
And it has not been
In my head
My daughter has been using it is
Is a prop in
Just about every
It's been a crystal ball she
She stuck it in the bottom of
Cauldron
Animated witches brew
So I can see this coming in really handy Act
I think I think there is a target audience in kids there because it looks simple-to-use
If you can control it through the smartphone app that you were showing me before the show there's even a button on it that you can change the color of the light
Right off the bat and my kids were getting when they were younger they were getting these colored light bulbs to put a mood in their room but now
Now something like this on the kids nightstands or they can play to their hearts content
I could see a big a big audience there
Shirley Phillips actually has Partnerships they have these lights that they
Make with like Disney
Where you can download like a Disney storybook app
That changes the light with the story
The book and it's like a special
Light + storybook thing
With something like this you would just
Download a story app
And then
You just like
And that's that be really cool like it
With your bedtime
Whole new environment for what what is it little mermaid or here's the question though
I was waiting for it just ask the question
As with all the lightbulbs I always ask this question how much is this one bowl of light
How much would you pay for this wonders bowl of light
Well given the battery life
I don't know that I would
But but but I would say
I wouldn't surprise me if it was at least $50
So
Double that it is 99
What
Desist Phillips
These people are.
Expensive
This is not
She plastic
Expensive expensive plastic
Paradise beauty
You would not mind him
So I'm wondering what will it cost me to take an Arduino board and an LED light board and make my own for 6
You wouldn't get the pretty enclosure
I mean this is something I have a very nice
I mean you see my home on night light
I would have his sitting in my home
My home is
Fairly nice I have your own password I'm going to turn on your blender right now
Good luck my friend
Good luck
Good luck with that the blender is it normal for everyone
Normally I don't have Frozen flute
Frozen fruit sitting in my blender waiting to scare the bejesus out of
99 bucks for this thing okay it is expensive
But but I just
It'll be on sale May and June time frame
So
Good present
For Father's Day maybe Mother's Day if your
Here in the market
It's on
It's going to be on sale
The Apple
Amazon
Best Buy stores
Sonic maybe you'll get
Atsion Lake
Philips did
Just reduced
Is the price
On
There
White their Phillips
Q
Luck spells
Switch to their white boy
They were
30 bucks
Per bulb
And a hundred bucks for
Kid with
2 bulbs
The Hub
And now that that
Kit is a TBH
Okay and
The
Light bulbs are
20 bucks a pop
So that's what they're bringing everything down
He's coming down as more people buy then I can
Yeah
So you may not see a lot of
The Hugo
The Hugo Bowl
Ghetto
You don't need it
It's never going to be something
Can you need I think it's a great
The sort of stuff
It is a lot of
All right
So
No Segway here
I say we just move right into it
What's next
Last week big news
Yeah Amazon Dash This is
It's interesting I'll give Amazon that and it fits within their whole e-commerce
We want to sell you everything
Mantra
4 people who aren't aware of the dash I think it's by invite only for Prime members right now
And I do not have one I am a Prime member but I haven't requested an invite
These are little sticky buttons basically
That
When you press the button
You will actually order something from Amazon and that something is very specific
Like on their site to show a picture of the dash button with the Tide logo tide
Laundry detergent which
We happened to use
A theoretically ever get one of these I would stick the tide dash button on my
Washing machine
And when I'm running low on type I press the button
An Amazon
Places the order for more tied to my house
And Amazon has
17 Brands already
So some of the brands that they have so far is
Tide as you mentioned
They have
Cottonelle
Bounce
Kraft macaroni and cheese why didn't I just saw that we were not at all the time
See you can
You can
And Oil of Olay to oh my goodness I've got everything covered
Yeah your Oil of Olay Beauty bars
I think this is
So what I saw this I was like
That's weird when a lot of people saw this they thought it was a
April Fool's Day joke
They did
I wish I had I thought
No no this makes total sense people love buttons
And I saw in the New Yorker actually had a really great
Take on this
One of the writers there wrote a store
Hot take about this and they're like
This is basically reducing friction even more
And
Every time you run out of something you have the choice basically to not buy it at
Armada switch brands
So this is great for Amazon
You never run out so you never have to make that choice
Maybe I don't know
Maybe I should switch
So by pressing that button your
You're basically like
Consumerism
Keep going if it's Amazon
You know standard operating procedure and what they're in business for I totally get it
It does reduce friction I could see that
I
Don't think I'll go with any of these even I see some of the products that we use
I anticipate
Some more
Amazon Smartwatch apps that will
Let me just speak my order
You've already got the echo
So you can see erratically
Order from
Your Echo with us I would imagine
As opposed to having lots of little button stuck around your house yeah that's the thing cuz all these buttons
I know
I know that they are not making a lot of noise cuz 99.9% of the time they're not doing anything is not until you hit that button that
Any data is going through my home network and whatnot
And I didn't look into the technical way you know how these buttons connected to a Wi-Fi network I presume so
Yeah
And I don't I don't know that I want more items on my Wi-Fi network unless I unless they're high value items is what I
I guess I would want to say
I don't want I look at my Wi-Fi
No address table now and there's got to be close to 80 or 90 items on their between tablets and phones and
Xboxes in Connected TVs and iPads and
Laptops and
I mean I just don't want to clutter that up
So you're going to really hate the second part of this so the dash buttons are Amazon's retro
What's really interesting about their announcement
A lot of people didn't focus on beak
Because the buttons are so
Impressum is the
The second half which is the Amazon replenishment service
Part
And that is a program and the first devices will be coming out in the fall
But Amazon's got Partnerships with
Companies like Brita
Like the Water Filter Company
Brother printer
Corky
Which makes all these
Quirky connected devices
And other products I see what you did there
And
Whirlpool even
To integrate
Basically the capabilities to reorder from am
Into a hardwired button
I'm inside
A machine
So
And you can either have a physical button
Hardwired
Or it is something that automatically detects when you're out
Andre orders like that
Now that you don't even do it
But
They're going to have a device that
Still on your network so Corky's launching
A pet feeder
For example
So this is something you stick
Keep or the pet food into the
Automatic pet
Peter and then suddenly when it's
Runnin low it's going to be like
Your Amazon
Pet food for shelter
At your door you don't do
And I like that you know what I'd like the end result it's just the implementation
And it's personal thing is this isn't gonna bother everybody I know that I almost wish they were either Bluetooth or
60 buttons
That went to a single Hub or switch
Through my phone to my Amazon account
As opposed to all these individual WiFi devices
So you're at your issue is just that it's I mean you could call if your Wi-Fi router the
I could call it that but it wouldn't change anything
You're right I could
But I won't
Okay so so you just don't want it going straight to
Cloud
Not not that I don't want all these individual WiFi devices
For for individual items
That I might purchase like I'm looking at the 17 items we use bounty we use Clorox wipes I go through Gatorade
Like you wouldn't believe
Tide we go through type mac and cheese come on everybody goes to mac and cheese
It's not the items but think of
Do I want a button for every one of these and every one of the buttons is a separate Wi-Fi item on my network
No I don't want that
That's really interesting cuz I was thinking by my immediately went to the waist for 10
God what if I
On Tuesday I I hit the tide button and then on Wednesday I hit the mac and cheese
And then I'm thinking about like
All the packaging that comes in
I'd rather have the
Orders held in aggravated but you're like
It's very odd to me that you're focused on the device you are saving the planet I'm saving my network
What we we do Amy we order from Amazon at least once a week if not
Twice
We tend to bundle things UPS
For that reason I mean we try not to be frivolous
With that.
You know the the shipping in the packing cuz that is a big part of our life and we do try to stay aware of that
So
I guess I didn't think that far ahead yet I was just thinking of my own network but
Yeah I mean
But I don't want
Packaging and FedEx or UPS here everyday just to
Bring me something I can actually go down the street in a mile and a half and go get anyway so
Okay will close out the episode now that we've
We each had our own like weird issues with the dash
I still kind of excited about it I
I've applied so I'm hopeful that I will
A dash
Submit a recommendation let me know
Faces thank you
Stay tuned because our guest is going to talk about
Security and we're going to spend a lot of times actually
On cars
I'm in he's going to cut it
Scare you scare you a little bit
But there's hope
So I'm going to go get some mac and cheese and then TuneIn
There you go get your Mac and Cheese get it already
And stay tuned for Josh
Korman who is
Is a founder of I am the cavalry
Hey everybody we are back with the Internet of Things podcast and I have with me
Josh Korman who is a founder of I am the cavalry
. org
And he is also the CTO of sonatype
Hey Josh how you doing today
I'm doing well
All right well I Ask Josh here because
I am the calvary
Is a
Security type organization and I say security type organization which is so vague because I'm going to have him tell you a little bit more about it
Sure
We started I am the Cavalry official launch was at Defcon 21 so largest hacker conference in the world which is
August of 2013
And it came from some of the
The members of the security community that had noticed that our
Our basic problem statement that unified us was that our dependence on connected technology was growing a lot faster than
Our ability to secure it
And while many of us got in a hacking culture as a hobby we weren't paying attention it became our profession
But we noticed over the last five years is that once again weren't paying attention and now software and vulnerable software was
Is going into our cars are medical devices are homes
Our critical infrastructure
And wow 80 billion dollars is spent a year to protect
Credit cards and it's an abject failure I mean most of us have had a credit card compromised
The failure rate for the merchants for example or Enterprise security is nearly 100%
And what we said is we're now putting up
Marble connected technology into things that affect our families are Public Safety in human life
So few of us quietly
Work used our careers and our credibility to get it high and deep as we could in the government and intelligence community
Internationally domestically and what we found is we we naively believed that if you got his hind if you can get and get the right
Message the right stakeholders they would quote-unquote fix it
But after doing so
It was obvious that
Even they weren't
Informed are empowered enough to do anything
And it was so boring and what we said to ourselves as you know the Cavalry isn't coming
No one's going to come save us
And this is simultaneously
Destroy your confidence but also is empowering
Because it says what they
Can't do it it falls to us to try
I am the Cavalry was really a personal declaration that I can Scream the darkness or I can be a part of the
Absolution
Emily challenge the hacker Community to do to a Grassroots non-profit
Renovation was
Let's be a voice of reason and Technical literacy and let's fix the the education in the public in the
Public policy makers in the affected Industries
Because in a real knowledge Gap and if we can beat at ambassador
That we can help
Speak to them in their terms and elevate
During staining them will make smarter choices
We're not against technology when I'm saying smash all your iot
But what we see is that where we place dependence on this connected technology and we want to ensure that's worthy of our trust in at the moment is now
Okay so you've told me
The basically what we're doing we're putting computers in places where there
Have not been computers before and so
Software you told me makes the things vulnerable and connecting it to the internet
Makes it exposed
So
Kind of given that
You started this organization and you said that there are four seas to your
What are those forces
It's collecting connecting collaborating catalyzing
And it's not just something we say it's it's how our
Approaching this this value in this Mission so we collect
Existing research and researchers so we don't have to reinvent the wheel there's a large body of work
That has been done
By solo artists but we believe it to be stronger if we collect them
We connect them to each other
For the first time in a long time turns out there's quite a few car hackers for example
I will also connect them with willing teammates in the automotive industry or medical device for example
We try to cause some form of
Working groups in collaboration whether it's for an individual company
Or whether it's an industry initiative
And we try to catalyze
Action that would not have happened otherwise I would not have happened as soon had we not tried
And what we don't want to do is simply admire or describe the problem what we want to do is cause safer out
Come sooner
And those four seas
I've been pretty successful
I'm primarily in the automotive
And the medical device product is hot on a scale
Okay so
You guys have been doing this
For about 20 months
And
It obviously Detroit has been one of your kind of Automotive space has been really good for y'all so far
In those 20 months
What have you
Done
So we're taking a Long View on this and we know that some of this is building Trust
So
We're not going to see
Super awesome immediate results we have seen a few
I was talking about the first nine months
Signing those willing allies and teammates
Are first birthday we published an open letter to the car CEOs through writers
And with it we published at Five Star Automotive cyber-safety framework or we basically said look you guys have been making
Safety improvements over the last 50 years India
Actually care about driving safety into your products
Are your Masters at your domain
We are masters of our domain
And now that our demands are cloudy
Collider Bergen of the safest outcomes is soonest if we work together
This framework of five foundational capabilities
Because if a car is now computer on Wheels there in in Harry a lot of the
Similar adversaries attack services but the difference being that the consequences of failure far more severe
So that begin
The more overt public
Collaboration right behind the scenes weed help
People with their structure design
You saw
Fruits of Labor such as that the Tesla car company published according disclosure policy saying it would not see third-party res
Researchers that was amazing staff that we're hoping
Bothering others in industry emulate
But let's talk about your framework before we get to the Tesla stuff because
That actually follows
Some of your framework
We got to we got to tell people what it is before they get all excited about it
So you know actually put this in a tweet once but the more verbose version is on the site but the idea is we think it's a
Forgiving the all systems fail
I think anyone with any sort of engineering background knows this intrinsically
So giving it all systems fail is not an issue
Cars will be hacked it's
That when they are
Whether it's three accidents are adversaries
We want to have it ready posture
So these five are foundational
Activities and capabilities that any should have some when I put them in a tweet it said how do you
Avoid failure
Take help avoiding failure learn from failure respond to failure and isolate failure
But that the five
Verbosely on the site or do you have a published
Attestation of high do safety by Design so what steps are you taking much like Microsoft does with their famous STL
To keep your customers safe when they're cyber cyber physical system
Number two says look when I miss stuff so you won't engage willing allies acting in good faith
And we therefore have a
Policy saying we will not Sue third-party researchers who report
Bugs to us in a predictable way and there's two ISO standards already on how to do coordinates closure
They don't have to reinvent the wheel they're the third one's pretty darn important it's think of it like tamper-evident frantically sound evidence
Capture like a black box in an airplane
Will a car companies simultaneously crying that there were
There was no evidence of of hacking
In the field and yet none of them that were making that claim had any ability to notice if they had ever been hacked
So at least the foundation capacity we should be able to see tamper evidence and have it be Court admissible evidence
So we can start to learn in the Auto industry much like we do every time a plane crash it really critical one that a couple companies
Have other ones are elected to do
Is the respondent failure and that's really do you have secure updates
Now you lead us to be over the air and Tesla provides this and I think you can save some of the recent BMW compromised
I'd actually fixed the Bonneville software over the air before they even announced their customers that they were honorable so that things
Example of a response in days or weeks as opposed to months or years which may be the case he requires a physical
Recall
Any isolate failures at CIA
Tell us how you separate critical from non-critical systems
Right now for example there's so much flat conductivity in the vehicles that
It's possible that a compromise of the radio or the infotainment system
Could turn the steering wheel or disable brakes and what we want to do is separate critical or non-critical systems either with logical or physical
Isolation
I so that when the inevitable compromise happens
The full reach of the damage is contained and we don't think of this is like a PCI checklist of if I do these things I'm done
Adidas foundational table states that when you add connected technology to things that can kill people
These are the must-haves and where
Aggressively trying to cause he's that become table stakes in an automotive Medical
And other areas
So these are the bare minimum so you should start here
And then from there
You like everybody's designing from the same space
And then from there is where you start building on kind of
Damn you think about it we're taking all the attack surface from software
And Enterprise computing
You know some of the vehicles were vulnerable the same in some of the same open source
Flies that like are played right if
You're going to use something that's
Going to give you functionality from the private sector from other use cases and it's going to get compromised
En masse in the public and you lack the ability to do anything updated you got the attack surface but you don't have
The copper bowl Windows update or or Mac OS update
So with this dependence on digital infrastructure comes
Another responsibility to to maintain it and have a prompt and I'd life cycle like
Anything else
When he different so is you have to look at credit cards
Is an acceptable fraud rate annually in as long as that industry stays within that acceptable fraud rate whether it's 4%
Or whatnot
Then you're okay if I asked you to Stacy what's an acceptable failure rate for your family's safety
I guess it depends on the system I mean like
My brakes
Gosh
Nothing
Brighton
Isn't my maps or GPS
You know
For me probably it's pretty high cuz it's not like I know where I'm going anyway but
Well I mean
Fair enough but I think that's one reason for these 5 being necessary because right now perhaps a compromise of an a
A Pandora app store or your GPS may seem benign but can be a pivot point to your brakes
And your steering
You were recently in Detroit and
Tell me a little bit about that so so far what is the industry kind of response been to
This
Primark
Well you know they're very new to this issue so they're going it's almost like Microsoft from 15-20 years ago they're afraid
Play the share they're afraid to talk about what they're doing
Right now the narrative is controlled by the public hacking on the news and The Sensational headlines
Joe
Many of them are pretty good things but none of them were talking about it so it's a very one-sided narrative I think in
One week you had 6 minutes
I was at the time I was like the BMW hack was announced
NBA she wrote analysis why that was a success story and how they were embracing at least some of the framework
And the BMW Hack That was was that over the OBD port
Now this was they had something like an OnStar system that allowed you to maybe call and say hey my
I locked myself out of my car can you let me in
And
Some researchers found the ability to compromise that
So
In the process of accepting that third-party collaboration without sending them
They work behind the scenes they shouldn't over the air update before they told him was broken
And in the process of doing so they also realize that they're over there update mechanism was passing
Things in the clear so they also migrated to using http
To me it's like these guys are already dependent on kinetic technology
And we want to do is put them on a path for that virtuous upward spiral and that learning and continuous improvement process
So while we are a bit mortified at some of the failures that
Allowed under the compromise to happen
We are really pleased at how elegant the response was they use it as an opportunity to bring themselves but also
By disclosing some of those details in ways they didn't have to
They also let the industry get a little smarter
So you know that happen.
A few days later the 60 Minutes piece showing DARPA
Attacking
Cars without physical contact is that the one that cliches is that
What always requires physical access they did it without physical access
Myself and I Craig Smith Grand open garages we did one on NBC New York Road that the journalist
Was manipulating a vehicle from New York
30 Rock
All the way to Seattle so 3000 miles away
They're not manipulation
Alexandra markina Massachusetts announced his in his report for hacking and tracking
Which took a year-long investigation into the state of security for the automotive industry Street in a lot of heat and light at the same time
Time
Any parallel we've been trying to build trust relationships with the
Groups like the software Society of Automotive Engineers SAE
We're just paying their working groups I've done things with Department of Homeland Security in DHS for connected
Cyber vehicle for the government
Solis worth it worth trying to harmonize on
Instead of
A bunch of private Solutions everyone seems to be talking about this five-star is the lowest common denominator or Lisa
Some sort of
Common Ground everyone could could strive to implement
No cars are designed
Sometimes five years out
Some of the technologies that goes into
And so
When realistically am I going to see a safer vehicle on the road how much is this is going to be
Implemented in time
Well it's a unevenly distributed right
It's a
Some of the vehicles already have over the air updates some of them was Tesla alluded to earlier they have a pump
List Cornell
Disclosure policy so
Researchers are encouraged to find a random issues which is going to make them smarter and safer sooner
Other car companies have a lot of stuff in the works but yeah you're absolutely right I asked a simple question
There's a scenario that many of the people in history have known about for years which is
That the remote kill switch allows you to remotely disable stolen vehicle
Honest used in different ways different countries
And a lot of them are implemented in securely
And I can't be patched or updated
So I said look at it we're just kind of all waiting with his Sword of Damocles like who's going to
Disable a fleet of vehicles or emergency response vehicles
Or gridlock a city
Yeah this is going to have a crisis of confidence in the consumer population if they no longer trust their cars so
Let's say that you you get hacked
It's your company this is a back in November I asked about eight of them were sitting around having coffee during the breaks
And they were competitors and I said so if yours is hacked tomorrow and you're on the news
What's a stop you from being the next BP oil spill that just gushing
And gushing for days and weeks
And none of them really had a good answer so I can let me phrase it this way
If yours was hacked tomorrow
And you're on the news tomorrow what's your minimum
Response time best casement and response time
Andeavor crickets
When you can hear a pin drop
And one of them said all right I'll go first let's just face it in 2018 models are already done his best first answer
2018 models are already done
Notice there was no
Something that they could do it over the air update
And then somebody else said yeah it's actually worse than that cuz they're a third-party supply chain is done through 20/20 on cases
So you're talkin multiple-year response time if something is serious is
Kill sweatshirt brakes being shut off on mass were to happen tomorrow
Do we already have the weakness the question is are we ready
To respond that failure
And all the sudden it dawned on them that okay wait you're not trying to post something on us it's actually really good
If we can have a problem as a response to keys out of headlines not a material impact or stock price we're not the next embarrassing beep
Coil spill
One of actually pointed out
You guys a lot less stigma on a software update in Arizona Factory
Recall
So I'm a little dismayed the fact that you know
20/20
Still
5 years out and some automakers
Are not able even if they wanted to to adapt
Components of fitness
So
Yikes, take this framework cuz you've mentioned medical devices which
Also important
Are they a little farther along
You know what the reason is sliced up these products the way we did is each have a different cohort of manufacturers
They each have a different time to live for the technology so you know industrial controls Queens 30 years and cell phone that's too
They also have different government
Regulatory Frameworks in data structures so
You know I look at the FDA the Food Drug Administration for medical devices and there isn't a lot of guidance or enforcement yet
And it looks like an intractable problems on the reasons we lean towards car first
But that's Edward we are finding different ways to catalyze growth are we looking bump purchasers like you know
The Mayo Clinic is a fairly large influencer purchasers in evaluation so
You know how the Mayo Clinic steers its its criteria has asymmetric impact on industry
I'm looking at legislative
I'm an executive branch options for medical so they all have their different challenges but we're very focused
Start identifying that chain of influence and just like good white hat hackers were fussing the chain of influence and we're trying what works
Per industry
Diversity Automotive guys had a bigger Head Start without being required to
We think that free market forces
Are promising there with medical it's going to be
A disruptive that ecosystem
But we're focusing on what's reasonable on your
You should see a five-star
Medical save cyber-safety Frameworks suing that was very very similar because we think these
Abstract capabilities
Evergreen
And good for all four projects
Okay and what about the Smart Home
So smartphones tougher in some ways because
You know it's one thing to get like GM and Tesla a Nissan and Toyota to kind of changes only so many players
The internet of everything right it's a whole Debbie of these Indiegogo Kickstarter size company
Now I do feel that people like Sony in
You know
Kenmore and dularge
Iot manufacturers are more likely
To look like the response received from the automotive industry
But I also think
It's going to be a lot harder because there's different economics for these very very small devices with a very short time to live
So it's in some ways a much harder problem
But that's why groups like build it securely or Blitz. ILY
I'm happily
Specifically focused on that one's they can give a good reference architectures and good things to consider for anyone developing these
And some folks are donating their services to these Inigo Indiegogo Kickstarter sized innovators
It's hard to tell who the next nest is going to be but if Nest doesn't get it operational security model correct for example
You asking to have a very large impact on the future
Wechat platform
And I
And I said I think our tactic there has been let's find the highest leverage watering holes whether it's the hardware platform
Azure the development environments or the groups
That people flock to you when they're designing developing these
But that you know I looked at your excellent
Television spot on your connected home
And most of those were benign if they
Compromise you but I am concerned that most of the Bluetooth door locks or
Are about security systems have been compromised I think
Leprechaun my co-founder both when he was at
Trustwave running spiderlabs in his new role
His oenis friends tested most of the Home Security
Technology stock I don't think it's not a single one that they couldn't easily compromised so
The batting averages
Incredibly low
And if you think about it we buy these Technologies to keep a people out of our homes and they may be the very thing that lets got people in their homes and
And that's the life in my physical safety type stuff
This is this is something and maybe this a good place to leave
On I don't know
I feel like most people when they buy these things
They buy them too
Not necessarily keep people out of their home like
If I'm buying a
A Bluetooth door lock I am
Less interested in
I mean I'm interested in locking my door but a door lock can be compromised whether or not it's connect
You're not right it's actually much easier to break into my house via just just smashing the window then
Packing my door lock right but the connected door lock gives me a lot more information and even a connected
Security camera
Brighten system
Gives me a lot of info
Information about who and what is in my home if my home is compromised
And I think
When you talk to people about those system
They find them
That information as opposed to
Why doesn't accept that their home is going to get
Broken into
They just want to understand
That it's happened when it's happen
Guess that makes sense
I think it's kind of a subtle difference in
How do you think about it
But I think it's worth kind of understanding that
Mindset
In one of her foundational beliefs is that
Again I didn't say we were LED lights in rear smash Oliver technology and go back to the Stone Age
We think you know one of these I I put it I haven't lost you agree and
I used to study
Stuff like this in the different schools of thought in
It's human nature to adopt things for their obvious immediate benefits but everything is a risk reward or cost-benefit equation
And we're really really good at seeing the obvious instantaneous benefits but we're really really bad at calculating the less obvious
Deferred cost
And what we're doing is our our attitude in our address to adopt
Anything and everything is
We've got to stop doing that cost benefit analysis
So if in fact the incremental risk introduced by technology is worth it
For the the games are going to get by all means do so
But we're not rendering very transparent
What does
Trade-offs are and we're not making very smart ones so it's not always more expensive for example
To make something playlist hackable we finally found the guy you first the first Bluetooth on insulin pump
Why the heck would you put a marble Bluetooth stack
Are insulin pump that can kill somebody
And there was no requirement to do so it was just kind of the bacon pretzel everything's better with bacon everything's better with Bluetooth and
Once they put it there every competitor had to also have it and they all implemented them with a vulnerable stack
It's like if you really want to do that either have it off by default or go through some some sort of threat modeling or adversaries
Resilience testing so you can have the benefit of the Bluetooth in the convenience
Without an elective
Wide-open attack surface
We war not against
The benefits of is iot I mean the the geek in me wants more and more my home to be connected and controllable
I just want to do it anyways where that risk is worth it
That makes sense
I am 100% with you
Well Josh thank you so much for coming on the show today I really appreciate it and I will add links to I am
In the cavalry
. org
In the show totes
And also to your your tedtalk that kind of explains kind of
The founding principles
Thank you so much for coming
Thank you for having