Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
We are going to be talking about
Specifications
Apple's home and homekit
Changes from actually last week
Samsung investing a lot of money in The Internet of Things
In
Possibly Elon Musk
Crazy new idea
We're also after that going to have our guests who is Matt
A first capital
Talk about
Finding money for your iot startup
Supposed to be
Enthusiastic
Extremely difficult after Korean BBQ and karaoke in New York City
Goldie got half of
Fairy guy
I'm pretty sure
Let's hope so
There will be no singing on the show don't worry
No I'm all sung out trust me
What's your go-to
I don't have one because I don't do karaoke so I got roped into this last night and fairness that the team did
Choose several Beatles songs in
On my behalf
Appreciate that immensely
Next I still can't sing but I do appreciate
I also
I'm with you I do not have a
So all right
Let's talk about Pluto
Yes
Last
They
Announce
Said they were going to do their Bluetooth
Five Points
Oh
Beijing the Sig
The special in
There's a respect you special interest groups that actually
Like is a special entry
But my interests align with these guys soap
I like this
I don't know
Some of the standard things
Is that really good for us what will that mean for users
Let's go
A little bit
4.
To I believe and so they decided that
The four dots
We're done with the forced removal
So
This is also Bluetooth low energy so the Bluetooth 5 is going to work over Bluetooth low energy
Which is
Good in that used to be called Bluetooth
Smart in case any
Oh
A couple name changes yeah
And we all kept calling a Bluetooth low energy cuz I was supposed to
Feature in Fallujah
Mysmartmove
Exactly
You're at least three-quarters of a
Mostly I mostly
Alright so
Here's what you need to know
Basically
Increase the distance
So now we're talking about from
Right now it's about 30 to 50
And it's going to go to 200
Enough to cover your house cuz right now at last week when we talk about these light bulbs that ran Bluetooth
You know if I'm downstairs in the light bulbs on my roof
I don't have the mesh Network
That's like theoretical best possible case
Strangers I don't I wouldn't want people thinking you can literally be 200 meters away
Maybe in an open field with no other radio interference
Eat while you're going through that's going to hurt your signal cell rearrange
It's still good though
The other thing is speed
We conferred sending one megabit per second data rate
To 2 megabits per
Which means you can send more information over
You're still need to be able to transfer
Free HD movie
Yuan
Do that
Try but you
So
That's good news I think that more is like a
Kokua file sharing
Yeah I mean it's
Obviously iot devices
She has small bits of data are obviously covered here so
I'm trying to think of a smart home
Perspective
For maybe and I am
Industrial perspective what you might want to be sunny
Good chunk of pipe there
It is I mean you probably going to send
Video but maybe
Still
Yeah that that could work
You know just images
Snapshots you know a JPEG file
Not super high-resolution yeah
That would happen in a second or two
So
We'll see how people
Use it
Is in this is the big deal thing
I'm just saying is
When you're broadcasting data over Bluetooth
It supports more data
So
What's Happening Here is instead of just like it's it's mostly for Beacon
So instead of saying
Now it's going to say things like
Here's a URL
I'm here you're so other day that you might
Your side still that I can
Physical Webster
Physical web
Is kind of the first thing I thought of
Is Google is Google actually isn't ever
We should mention that Kevin works for Google
Yes
Chrome
At work on Android for work but I will mention
Yesterday as I was walking around the office in New York City I did get a little pop up about Peter the physical web next
Nearby
I couldn't find it so I must walk too fast or too far but
Devastating
I should have just went retraced my steps and everything else was on the way to a meeting in like I missed it.
That I don't know I'll never know
Inside
The idea is
He would walk by something like maybe you're waiting for a train or
You know an office
It'll pop up hey there's a physical weathering and you click on the link
And it'll give you information so if it's a train station it's going to send you to like
Oh you're next trains could be at this time here's all this other relevant information
So it's just an easy way to give you information about the world around you that you may not otherwise be able to fight
Dad's in this is one of the key things I've always said with iot and smart devices it has contacts
Use your walking past something you may not even know that you're walking
Cast it
Something may get pushed to you to let you know that you're walking past something that may be interesting
Are useful to you
Now the downside to all of this
This is advertisers
Yeah
There's pros and cons
We'll have to see much like the internet
We will just have to see how people use this because
I really don't want
To be bombarded with
All these ads now you do have to have an app
That reads
You know the beacons
So this isn't like your phone is suddenly going to
Well
You're mostly right I think but see
I'm just using Chrome in my Android phone and I've allowed
Prone to have access to the locations
Permissions
And that's what triggered when I walk past the physical web Beacon
That's what triggers there was no action
Strap in that particular case
I'm thinking like
The retail case but you're right so
Maybe we should
Check was supposed to see if we can get someone from Eddystone to talk about like how they're going to control for things like that cuz
We don't want Minority Report or whatever
Total Recall I guess it was worth me to walk past often
Personal ads
Cameron do you know
I do not want that
Do not want
No alright
In the finals
You get all of
And it
2.5 *
Less energy
Basically better power consumption with all that which is
Quite nice for everyone building things that run off batteries so ye Bluetooth Sig
This is expected in about 2017 the sit the Sig
Is basically said hey this what we're going to do so now they got to finalize the standard
What should happen later this year
Early next
And then the chipmaker's actually have to build new hardware to support all this so
Which means your current devices are not going to get all these G whiz-bang features
Right
Monogram
That's that's all part of the cycle we know that we may not like it but we
We know that
And this is all
And talk about Bluetooth Mesh networking this is separate from the
Here's the update on the match
Mesh Network
King stuff is actually
For 4 and 5 but
That's expected
It's on a separate development track
So they're going to have a
Detailed update sometime in the September timeframe
Deployed
In 2017
Like on the earlier side
They said
So
Pay attention to September
For the mesh
Will be part of you can add that
To Bluetooth 5 and they're also planning out at 2
So the mesh Network
Wingstop actually compete in your existing Bluetooth
Devices
So that's the mess
It's a little
There's a lot going on
It's gone from just being a
Almost like a single-use case kind of thing to a lot of different things and
Super important iot
Alright let's move on to
This is last
Switch big news but Kevin and I had to
Early
Before WWDC yes
It's totally worth talking about
Because we were like
What's happening with homekit
Sad sad sad
Apple basically said
Alright here's what's happening
I'm going to give you
Home
Which has its own application
Group all of your homekit stuff together
Basically added support for video
Which was a big deal
And
Announced
New devices that are
Along with that home app the IOS app
Home where you can control your devices
Like I said they proved everything all your controls
Babe
Front and center in iOS now have an install the iOS 10 beta but once I do
I will be able to drag up from the bottom of my screen
Just like I do today with control center
And then swipe over and there is my presets
For my home app
So we are much quicker access
And all those presets and such
And controls
Will also be available in the home app for the Apple watch so
They make it a lot easier to control things which is what one of the things they needed to do
Yes and
It's also going to be sick
Supported
With the Apple TV which means you when you leave your house this was a big
Question mark for every
Not for me
Aeropostale a year ago
Yes
With apple you never know
That's true in furnace it was only Apple never announce this
Until just this year so you are correct the last year
They updated the Apple TV support page to say that it would be
A Gateway for your home kit
Teresa soap
Kevin do
Now the rest of us
Saul
If you didn't believe Kevin
Cherokee
Not always not after karaoke
I should also add that it's not the only Gateway device
I don't know if you called this
IPad
Yes that's correct so you do not need an apple
TV to remotely access your homekit devices when away from home
If you have an iPad which I guess has to be
On in your house and
Can I get to your network while you're away
You know what's interesting here
Is a lot of
Cydia type Developers
They actually will
Retrofit and iPad in
Pappadeaux's
Your wall in your wall so
That's actually kind
Never really smart
Yes it is
Penguin
Be bad on iPad sales
That would be like another use case
We actually have two iPads
If we were better they would all run the same apps but that's kind of impossible
And how many things
I'm in and out of my house but parkour apps
It's nice
Because everyone
You can always find something and when I have gas I just give him one of the iPads and I'm like here
So now I mean I could somebody in a cup of coffee or a drink 66 here would you like an iPad when somebody comes to visit
What is there hot
This is Terraria
I am not just any of the keys to my home I'm heading you
My smart home
What day would I have better
I'd like more of a budget
Or maybe just a die
I can play their music
I am I am a nice
I would say that you should open up like a smart home B&B
Alright so
I have not played with this yet
Because
Hey I don't have
Might my husband's not like him to hand over his stuff to be so I'm going to have to do it on the iPad
So it's going to be a slightly different user experience
But in watching the videos that people are making
This
Apples
Worldview on this
Sister give you the
Away in Homestead
What's I could buy
Good morning the modes is what a lot of
Companies call this and then they give you the things
To control
And that is a very
Xiamen
Kind of architecture for building these apps
And I was a little disappointed because
I didn't see anything like truly innovative
On the
Making automations controlling individual devices it felt like apple just kind of looks like
Capitulated to the status quo
Yeah
You're like no
No no
Did but that doesn't surprise me and the reason being
Apple standard operating procedure is typically to wait for a market to develop
Watch
How people react to it
See how manufacturers and device makers kind of screw things up either through UI or
Capabilities
Or instability
And then they come in and say we're here to save the day we can fix this it did with the MP3 Market they did it with the phone market
Even you could say tablets good tablets have been around hello PCS first one and two thousand one so yeah I'm not surprised that they did
Well you so to speak
But what they done is made it
Intuitive
Easy and hopefully stabling
Simple to use
I think what struck me is how none
Intuitive
Things are because this isn't
It's actually not that into
It's intuitive if you were familiar with
With the space
Is a normal person coming in
I feel like
I'm not saying that's apples
Fault I'm just thinking
A truly intuitive interface by play with a lot of these software things would actually ask you probably a few
The questions and then
Start trying to do
Right and I think there's like a big divide between I want to
Control it
Just kind of the early adopter
DIY
True and then and I don't know how apple is educating a
Customers
In regards to homekit in the new home app
I don't have a homekit any homekit devices
Avenues the home app
So
I guess I should get one and go through this person see maybe there's some guided bits that
Trying to explain the magic you know
Here's what you can't have that happen automatically and here's why that helps yuan
So I'm usually there messaging is very good
It could just be the
I haven't used it and I do have good messaging I don't know
Yes but I am also going
We'll get there probably
I won't get there for the next show is next after that cuz I don't have any device
And I'm moving all next week
Nope I'm not assigning
Nope not this time
I will choose not to accept it if you do
All right
Quit music
So Samsung
Who said this week that it plans to
To invest one
Point to
Weatherby
With a B
In the US over the next 4 years
Boost the iot vision
A lot of money
It is a lot of money
And I guess the biggest
News
Part of that investment they've purchased joint
Yes
Giants yes
So what we got here is it looks like
Samsung is getting serious
About 4 minutes
We've seen kind of like was it bought smart things back
Twitter million dollar acquisition
I thought it was a great move because SmartThings was so open in Samsung 8
CSN 2014 hit just got
Through telling us how Lake
Amazingly open it was going to
You and I went to the Consumer Electronics Show and they touted Anastasia to Kino and that was going to say 2015
Okay
Open
Samsung kid actually a couple months ago announced it
Arctic
Cloud
What are they doing with art
That's like a whole that's hardware that's a bunch of pieces
So there's
Vegan Arctic
A cloud called Sammy
Saami
Which basically was like a data
Data Lake like a place where you can put
Your data escrow
I just edited
Corporation
Someone's hosted on
Cloud you just throw all your data here and you can share it
It's got all kinds of policies
And then
They built on top of that article
Which is
The cloud
It start to Cloud it's
Going to have
And it's unclear how much of this already has a good iot Cloud should have a way to
Get devices
Sending data
The cloud
It should have
Ways to manage those devices at
Scalable easy
It should have
Ways to control
Those devices like
Wasted
Connect to other clouds
Control other devices
I'm not sure
What all the Arctic
Cloud House of those thing
But that's what he's trying to build with choice
Basically it gets a massively distributed architecture to the
Dildos
I'm enjoying it has
They're a bunch of old son guys in a few remember son history you know distributed computing was
Like they're bad
We'll see
What happens here at the outside the arch
Modules
Is a specialty
That's
That's what I'm looking at right now there are three modules the one the five and the Ten of various sizes and capabilities
And the basic saying this is Sino everything you need from Harbor perspective to get started
Developer documentation online tons of it as ice
Scan through here
You know developer guys on connectivity and audio video and
Wireless networks USB
So
Tons going on
We can try to get Samsung to come on the show and talk about all of that if that's something
Well considering how much they're spending and how much of a player they want to be in this market
I would love to hear more when they're done
Samsung TV mod
Player in a TV is a great place to Papa Hub they actually already did SmartThings on their smart
TVs
And they added a zigbee and Z-Wave dongle
Just plug it in and
And all the TVs run their own Mouse at their own butt
Generally open source
Kaizen
Tizen platform and that's
What's going to tie everything together they say so
Yeah I'd be very interested to hear more about this from them
Alright we'll see
I'm a little fun thing
Is Elon Musk
Crazy wheel
So many of them
Fungi
Tesla
Type with rockets in space
SpaceX I can't remember if you
I hate V Rockets into space is what I tell my kids
The key part is he
Lance them
Intact
So most the time
Some of the time
He
Is on the board of a company called SolarCity that makes solar panels
And
Has his crazy bottle for financing solar panels and making solar panels more accessible to everyone
And his cousin is actually the CEO and what happened is on Tuesday
Elon says
You know what
Cuz we can
Well it does make sense and the finances are going to be very interesting cuz I thought
This is like a 2 and a quarter billion dollar deal
I don't have the numbers in front of me but it was a big number
But it makes sense I mean solar energy and I can I can attest this personal you know
We have 41 solar panels in the current house I will miss you when I'm gone solar panels but
We also had an electric vehicle and it was just a perfect marriage
To just plug in our car and
You know recharge from the Sun are everyday and
Save money
Just make sense
Just sits a good integration
For everyone who's thinking about this
And it's a 2.52
3 billion dollar deal
Right on the money
This makes sense this is actually very similar to what GE is doing with its current spinner
The idea is it's creating a truly connected
Supply chain for energy is
Think about it
It is trying to work with
Power generation
Companies
It's also thinking about rechargeable battery
And Dennis working on the demand side with
Sensors and Lighting in
Commercial areas
And basically trying to help manage the flow of information in the
Control
How much people are paying
Use electricity
So
When you apply this electric cars are one of the
Going to be a
Huge draw
On the electric grid
And if you think about it that way
Pouting
Insight into
When to charge them based on the availability of solar power because again solar power is not constant we haven't been
Most people have solar panels do not have battery back-ups and such I tried but I couldn't do it and then I did try to get in
The Powerball thing with Tessa
Which is a battery destroy that energy
But because of my system though it's configured I actually couldn't do it
So
It may make sense right now a lot of people charge their cars over
Goodnight but it makes more sense
It to have that intelligence right now
Electric car
In
I think that's going to be
An essential piece of info
Information
For kind of building like
Some people called the internet of electricity
A real toy
You have to shift the demand or the supply because let's face it solar power is awesome
For half of the day
Thrift near at night
Skinesis oh
They've got to figure it out they got the tools to do it with the powerwall
SolarCity installing the panels and then you got the car for your demand
Thinking intelligently
Shipt
When
Are you charged or when
Power is available to you and
It sells the whole problem of
Quote about using solar power at night
I maybe they'll just you know jet your new Tesla over to you on a rock at night
Mine Asteroids for more
More energy
Please stay tuned for our guest
Matt Turk who is a venture capitalist
Who is going to tell us basically how to think about raising money and spending your money and these uncertain
We're breaking into the iot podcast
From our sponsor I've got with me Todd Alice got the CTO of wolf SSL
His company provides
Security inside over a billion devices
Toddy is here today to tell us
Why you should use SSL for securing The Internet of Things
The short answer is
It is the web security protocol Congress currently used
Everything for you
Banking transactions in email
2 year
Home shopping
SSL TLS provides
Privacy
Integrity
Complication
Drop on you
Forgery by messages on you and most importantly
Does it cost extra to add
SSL from a processing overhead
It does a little bit and that's been an excuse in the past not to do it but then things I talked about integrity
I think those things out way
The slight increase in a resource processing
All right and how can we
Best place to eat
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is matter
Who is the managing director at Firstmark capital
Hey Matt how are you doing
I'm doing great sweetie how are you
Thanks for having me
I am super excited to have you
Thanks for coming because the end of March
Awesome
A survey of the iot industry
I think I saw past me like 18
Let's get started with the status
Venture Capital Industries
That's who you are for the internet
What has changed since you publish that
I think they c2f think we are in an uncertain cycle for the ventricles
Going to stream General
Can we hold strength of your ads
What is happening in some of it is rated to the ups and downs
David Natural Market
That's it
So pretty clear that the market has cool down quite significantly since Maybe
Las Palmas
Menu for 4 months
The impacts of the general
Cooling down on the internet 06 industry is
Significance
TV internet of things like many other emerging areas and maybe that includes other wolves
You know Bitcoin and blockchain for example
Internet of Things was a an emerging area that in some ways I think was little bit of an acquired taste
Four letter v
PCS meaning that people wear curious and
People were excited
Look at
New iot Ventures
And we're willing to
Experiments
But that thing is the market closed down people tend to Natural retreats
Towards
What areas of Tallahassee
Experimental
Berkeley what's happening
Right now so if you're venture-backed startup
Or any startup so we'll start with people who've already raised some money
People who are they
What do I do
What would your advice be
Companies who
Have raised money
And are trying to get their products
Companies that have raised money in the name of the game is quite often to get
More money and the
You're very practical by theories
Take money from wherever
1 Cam and that means that one should not have to leave the focus.
Getting money from
The brand name VC me that happens with so many great and by all means they are as chilling number of tough name
Beaches.
Storage space
The same time the great news for the space I thank you
What's the corporate investors and stretchy investors that beat
Reactive
And quite frankly compared to a lot of your
Average BC some of the Strategic investors can bring almost mold value
Especially those investors I was catching investors are in areas that are immediately accretive
2 startups whether they are
Manufacturing
Or insurance
I think those are great sources of money in one should actively engaged
Wizards players
I think he knew the Shinto strategy can corporate investors
Contra Dance
Can be interesting as long as they did
Amused
To finance your inventory in knots
You just financed
Extension of your Runway
You have the key learning hero the key lesson
Is that one should be overdramatic and state rate
How to get money from Whataburger
They can't they are still sources of my
Okay
Thinking of starting what if I feel like oh my God no one's made a connected
Shopping
Don't actually do
If I'm looking for money
Where
Should I give up hope for what should I do
I think one consequence of the Venture Capital markets
Cooling down at 1 should be
Stickley careful
Insult for when starting a new venture
Indeed there is a question
Around availability of the product
And the business model that one cheats
Think through
Perhaps more than
In the past
I think there is less
Solvay
Immediate needs to rush to create a new product
Recent you got completely excited about
New products in Indonesia and the potential of the products
I think you should
Work very hard time getting the best
Possible
Team
There was
During the last couple of years maybe more
Torrentz4
Teams that have never done Hardware before
But so I could to the figure it out especially with the help of some
Third-party provider
Some incubator
Because the bar is hiring now you should definitely optimize for
Getting the rights
People on the team that includes the people who've done Hardware before
Funding is a very viable option
I think we have all learnt in the last couple of years back
I want to be careful with crowdfunding
Because creates a lot of pressure on the entrepreneurs and I think the time to launch applied funding campaign
He's probably much closer to actual shipping date
Other people stop before
It looks like about exits because they've actually been a lot of exits
In the last
Gears 4
Comedies that had started really early and I'm curious
A lot of them are small they're not very well publicized
Some of them look like
Sears Buy
Airbnb
Sproutlings
Acquired by Mattel
What is this tell us about
The exit Market
The market has been somewhat confusing so there was a first wave of very large acquisition
Send Hangouts Dropcam and
In the first place that the very beginning of the cyclic rate of the excitement because the
The time between Christian of the company and then and then very large exciting exit was very short
That was the first wave and that was some of the head fade because
Just that created more and more excitement than the market probably warranted
I think we now in that second phase of the closest Market Square
So
Whole wave of companies that are funded maybe in the last couple of years that raise the AC ground or
Sometimes
Small
To reserve that are now getting to the stage where
The market or defend a position in the market
That makes for interesting checking acquisition from water companies that also feel the need
To play in the space but I know Natalie willing to invest hundreds of millions or billions
In the company so we sing that that whole wave
Now
I think the next logical wave he's probably
234 years away that's when the larger companies by
Startups that have grown in a
Quizlet revenues large teams
X 1 2 or 3 products allowed
That will take
Another
That's a good cutting from a nap
Acquisition stand for in
I think the
Pool of potential acquirers is
Large
Not afraid
Type of acquired
Suggest yes but that was one of the always one of the questions for Hardware
How companies is who buys you and what was interesting to see in the last two or three years was that some of the large
Internet companies which so far I've been
Completely software companies
Showed an interest in the in buying our company so specifically Google for example that
You can think of
Companies like Amazon that I'm starting to play
In this case as well
In addition to the large
Companies the traditional industrial and manufacturing companies
Also stunning
To show
Plug in chest into space a because
They don't come from a good nav
Are we going to have
To buy a little bit of some companies to bring in
Challenge
And products
And graduates was formed themselves into companies that will be one more software
Bass
EQ project
2 3 4 5 years old
Then my guess is that you'll see a lot of non-traditional Lee soft
Square
Bass companies
Hardware
So I just filled in a device companies
Buying one more
Tech companies
Yes I've seen a lot of people in the retail people in the entertainment space getting here
Let's talk about
The industrial internet
Versus kind of the smart home and maybe some of the other connected-car somebody's other trends
Where do you want to place your money now
What's growing what's the
The status of
Guess what I'm personally
More excited by the Enterprise and Industrial side of things
I am in Smyrna I'll explain the wife in a second but
From my perspective
Enterprise energy spiritual includes both the actual and present industrial plays
A whole range of
Enabling Technologies developed to play
Data plays
Elite Enterprise in additional time for example
Helium which is a full stack
Intuitive Solutions
For the Enterprise
They provide a very modern
Take on the
Surprisingly insult problemos
Keypoint sensors and getting
Data
Are things in a way that is very developer-friendly
And Best of You scalable
But you know that thing is going to be a whole range of
Signs to go vertical specific
Platforms
Two Souls comparable problems for example in oil and gas
I also think there's going to be your whole
What range of Appleton key you around
Security plays for the Internet of Things
Turn around data plays I think this whole set of Interest
Things are possible when
One industry that I am excited about Vivitrol drone
Industry which I think he's part of into the other things if you think of it.
Connected
Hardware I think they are going to be about the casements around collecting you forms of
Data using
Drones
Agricultural data of utilities data organelle pipeline inspection
And this whole range of
Enabling Technologies for drones but also for robots
Did you offer some general that
Okay let's talk about the consumer friend
So MD consumer from that personally find the category of bit more tricky
At least as of right now
As is at least to me it feel so bit more like a hit
Business
GRCC Detroit area that I look for in
Consumer iot plays
Three of them
First one is that I like
Show me plays that
Are mission critical
Which doesn't mean it's only mean that they are mission for
Nicole to everyone at all times but I believe the product should be mission-critical and I must have
For a large enough category of people
At least at certain points
In the life
So
Mission critical categories for ground pool
Include
From my perspective
Security
Who's health
Although
Not health care of because it's tricky because of the fda's involved and because pairs involved
Let's go digital health
Believe the family category is interesting
Meaning selling products
Two parents
That
Have to do with a children
Possibly their own aging parents
I'm so products around babies are interesting because
People become temporarily price insensitive around the time to have babies and are willing to change the consumer
That's a nice way of saying insane
That bad happens to
As a parent I'm like I went through that
$400 for something that will last for like
3 months
Sorry
What you mean mission-critical also includes products where
One of these days in the early obsessive Behavior
We can be quiet
Selfie can be music and can be gaming
Consumer products
Leading to very deep and repeated engagement
I'm so over this for me is isthmus
Pretty cool
Musically
Excludes gadgets
Stuff that
Icing sold first world problems and that's my perspective
Timber Products in the connected home category which I think is an otherwise very interesting category but there are a number of products that
Fall in that category
Pennsylvania
Problems that
You know you didn't really know you if you had
Christmas 2014
Consumer products that I
Really better
Because of their internet connectivity
And even better alike
A consumer product that simply cannot exist
If they were
Not connecting
My Circle K area is at like quite frankly a lot of units
Space
I look for products
Where are the reschedule value Beyond Hardware sale
Could you go around
Kitchen subscription services and and data plays
I think it's been a little tricky with bad luck categories that takes a long time
Gets to the stage where you have interesting data plays
And
It's been one of these shoes that I think
Investors I've been grappling with
Hey it's your because
Text
While for a consumer connected products
To gain critical mass
What's the shipping then to get critical mass
By the time you have a
And I get to company to you as an excuse be in tonight because I'm serious
See that
Data plays not in Indian slow motion just yet so it requires
I'm sure he's going to receive that screws to be sometimes a bit more
Believers in division that description the ER as Leaders take investors that for sale for PlayStation 2
To be otherwise very metrics-driven
And let's talk about the difference between
Products
And infrastructure
Terms of building credible
I think we still in the early days of think the
Core connectivity problem is
Surprisingly unresolved committee that he will be resolved
Tune button
It is sold to some extent in the home through Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Somewhat souls for long-distance connectivity which
Sounds like it's going to be increasingly
Cellular
Connectivity
Price of silver connections
Seem to be going down at least four
Connected devices
I think this whole range of connectivity issues in
Between
Delivery near connectivity and the
Connect
Lachlan soul to the oranges
Players
Sigfox addressing
Connectivity issues but
You know if there are number different circumstances where I need your contacts where there are temperature
Curry shoes and Community shoes and wear the machine so the assets that you wanted monitor are in the basement working
Activities not sold
Unimpressed with your phone. I think there are plenty opportunities around
Security
Amvets
He's going to be a very important need at the same time for meeting.
Respective
Impurity have
Believe in the market because
The current security needs
AR
Just
Emerging
Security in many cases for
IG blockers
To look it up an afterthought
So is investor insecurity plays you have to believe that the problem is going to
To be a merchant very quickly and in a very drastic way
And you have to be willing to invest in companies that quite frankly don't have traction just yet because they don't
Have no a very large and
Well founded
Customer base
I also think it's Securities interesting because
It feels like we need a new sim
For the internet
And it's still up in the air how we're going to actually do
Do it so it's awesome
But if you don't
No no no
He's coming to the territory of
Inari station Vassar you have to
Do cows have some sense of
Where did you take having a season surround its and then you have to be fortunate enough
Define debris
Best people
In the specific segments so I'm trying to solve that problem and that the end of the day you have to
Lyrics intellect and their ability to adapt to changing market conditions
Quite frankly and support them as much as
You can't but that's a that's a life of an artist Asian dresser
I would never be able to do
I can barely I can barely trust myself
No face
Alright what Matt thank you so much
I really appreciate you coming on the show I have learned a lot
It kind of makes me
Feel good about not being
So
Any final words of wisdom
Stepping into short-term life
For Internet of Things entrepreneurs
And the VC's bad back them he's going to be a little tricky and challenging at the same time
That's what encouraged everyone to continue to be enthusiastic and certainly not lose faith I think the
Can you teach self continues to be gigantic and exciting I continue to think that it is a
A fundamental paradigm shift
Happening in
Computing in general
I absolutely believe that the world is going in the general direction to work
Everything will be connected to the internet
One way or another and that open
Teas to build large infrastructure companies but also to build new consumer companies that
Will essentially becomes a new branch of tomorrow so I think the the reality of the approaching the
Continues its are going to happen over the next 10 years
Cleansing markets go up go down
But if you end of the day great companies are created in Old Cycles
So what I've been crate show everyone to
Just to keep the face
Thanks for having me Stacy and really enjoyed it
Thank you that's it for this week's show please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
And thanks for listening