Hey everybody Welcome to The Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have some
Amazing news this week
We've got the Google home Wi-Fi
Hypixel
All the Google Hardware announcements stuff
We have
Iot botnets
We have a new survey from the online trust Alliance it's going to tell you how to
Protect your smart home
We have a bunch of dues bits
And we have a wonderful guest but first we're going to have Hewlett Packard Enterprises tell us a little bit about their analytics at the edge
And then we're going to have Danny hertzberg a Miami Beach realtor talk about
How to invest in your smart home
So
Before we get started
Let's hear word from our sponsor
In just a few years the Raspberry Pi has revolutionized about how we think about system design at arm
Tech con 2016 Raspberry Pi founder and CEO Evan Upton will share his vision
About low-cost widely accessible Hardware technology will drive future Innovation I love Evan
Check con 2016 October 26th through the 27th in Santa Clara
Register today at arm techcon
Dot-com
Okay and now to the show
Kevin
Let's start off with
Your disclaimer since we're going to
Shake It Off with goo
Oh that's right I do have to say that so I do work for Google I do not work in their smart home area which is obvious
Talk about and all opinions are my own not my employers
And I know that they're sending you some dollars under the
Atlantic Avenue
Well they're probably been paying me too because I'm really excited about what we saw it
So Google
Announce the whole slew
New pixel phones
Those look lovely but we're not going to talk much about those cuz we're not a phone show
They also announced a new router called Google Wi-Fi
And
Google home the much-talked-about competitor to the Amazon Echo so it is a personal assistant
And speaker
Yeah the end Google home actually was introduced at Google IO back in May of this year so now that Prada
What is actually
Available yet they can pre-order I believe
You can pre-order it it's $129 it comes with these like swappable bases so it's a it's an air freshener
Color coded base for
The Hive speaker
If the smell of iot in the morning
Mine I ordered it yesterday mine is estimated to arrive
November 8th
What do you what do you think of the pricing and the reason I asked is because obviously the Echo goes for $180.
This is 130
But of course Amazon recently
Did the dot 2.0 for $49
So I will have to wait and see how the speaker sounds
But I feel like the echo is now to expand
Just like if you're if you know nothing about the products
And again I still haven't lived with
The product I think
Really important to say yes
The echo
Could be
Price too high
And but what I imagine is
We're going to see some amazing black
Videos were Cyber Monday on Amazon
Tuesday
Whatever
Captain's coming into the holiday
And folks can always find referral to recertify decos probably for like 1:40 to 1:15 to save a few bucks anyway at any
Yes
So let's dig into some of the things that I was like
Oh this is cool and then some of the things that I was like
This is missing
Talk about the missing because you ordered one of these and I did not
Yok we should ask why do
Fort Irwin
Well the main reason is that
I've been a huge proponent and fan and user of the Google
OK Google services I'm sorry I just turned everybody's feeling on it
I apologize
We should okay before you get into this we need and create a code word like she who shall not be named
Bi-Rite cuz I'm getting a lot of complaints
So what should we do this
The G-Man
No cuz it's a woman 2
Assistant can we just call it
We'll just we'll just call you Google Assistant
China
Google assistant is really
You could say the
The maturity and
Combination of the old Google Now and Google on tap
And it's now built into home and you can speak into it just like Alexa and
I did that too
And you can speak
And you can speak to it like you can with an Amazon Echo and it will respond
I'm so it has a lot of similar capabilities and ecosystem which for Android folks
That's a good thing I think
But what it doesn't have at least at launch is enough partners for me to actually purchase it
And that's because it's limited
Two working with Samsung SmartThings
If this then that
Nest obviously and Philips Hue
So what's missing for me personally is Winx
You love your wink
Now I feel and in this is something I haven't had a chance to report out cuz I was on a plane
I feel that in the next couple of weeks
We're going to see a lot of
New partners com
That's that is my hunch
Because I know that I talk to people in the smartphone
Community and they are
Eager to get involved here so I think this might be kind of a
I don't know if it was a rushed kind of lunch
But I do think
Keeping things under wrap and also
Which they did not do
Clearly this was not ready for a launch in May when it was introduced and that's
Obviously it didn't watch
It happened now
You would think that
The product team behind you go home with working to integrate partners and
Those potential Partners had it
Information to make that happen
Maybe there was some early lunch deals like a would mean you can be our top three
First Partners in Seoul
I don't know
I think you're right I think
Google lies heavily on partnership in an open platform
It says here you're the product go do with it what you will
So you're right I would think within the next few months we should see
More announcements from partners
My Hope
No
There was some discussion
About if you worked with Amazon Echo that you
You wouldn't be worth
With Google
There were reports of that some exclusivity stuff
But I haven't read anything official on that I haven't seen any Partners comment on that
It doesn't make SmartThings works with the echo
Philips Hue works with Echo and homekit
I'm trying to think
If this then that works with that buddy
Yeah so that kind of proves the fact that it's probably not exclusivity thing
So so that's good
Now
So you're not buying
Cuz you want wink support
Yet yet
Sorry
And I would say so
Wait we mention the partners
I would like to see and I think the smart home Community would like to see
Wink support
I know that I talk to the CEO of August Jason Johnson and he's looking at supporting this because any voice activation
That's really key
For their products
And then I'd also like to see the Logitech Harmony home hub because a lot of people seem to have that in like
That is actually really
Good thing to integrate with us because you can be like
Google Assistant turn on my Netflix
Why not
Although that I was just going to say that actually can be done with the Chromecast
Because Google home does speak to Chromecast if you have one in the house
And Googled it announced a new 4k Chromecast yesterday as well
Apps that you can say
At least at launch
You can say play this video on Youtube it'll
Put on your TV voice control the TV
Netflix was announced as a early first partner's well it's not
There yet but they did demonstrate
Hey show me whatever movie on Netflix and Hulu
Thanks
Stranger things which is very good by the way
You do get voice control of a TV and it's one of the things that I've always felt as lacking width
My echo and Fire TV box
Guess they don't talk to each other
And that that is silly
I'm not sure Amazon's getting on the
I'm at right now
The other thing
Because
Google watch this
Nuding is
That you can actually Chromecast
To other speakers
With auxiliary power so if you have a Chromecast audio
And I think those are like $35 for a Chromecast audio
If you plug that into like the back of one of your Sonos
Place or something
Like that then you can
Can Chromecast
To that Sonos
Talking to it via app
Sorry talking to it via
Google Assistant
Right so that gets really interesting and I should also know that the Google home also comes with support for tuna in pan
Pandora Spotify
In a couple other
Services very similar services and it also let you set a default most likely
Rail
For the music folks this could be a really exciting
Dang if you have like a bunch of Sonos is lying around and you don't want to wait
With the Echoes go
Look at that support
Yep make sense
So
That is all that
That is all there I bought mine
Until you guys
At the second I would wrap that thing
We're getting on the show and recording something
Maybe we'll do a back and forth in
I will owe the other thing I was going to say is
It sounds like
They have different voices
Great Lake
These must have been recorded demos because
The voice quality did not sound
Great
The Google Device
And I was a little saddened by that because it sounded kind of like
The Google voice thing was at the bottom of a well
Yeah I don't know when they put together the demo videos and and whatnot I do know that
Sundar pichai a talk about how Google does
Natural language processing and Records tons and tons and tons of phrases inside chin
I didn't get the demo anything I actually had my hands on a pixel phone and in New York City yesterday but I did not try Google assistant on
I didn't have a chance to us
I can't really
Can't say either way I guess we have to wait and see you for the final product
Yeah and I'm outside looking forward to a couple things I'm looking forward
A better Interactive
Back and forth
Things to Google Assistant
I'm also looking
Poor Dad in the power of Google search on the device as opposed to Bing
Is there times when I'm like
I just want to say you know she who shall not be named
What's a spice that goes well with asparagus
And if I ask
I get an answer
If I asked
And then that speaks again to
Sunrise presentation were
Pretty sure a December he said something like
Dundee
Machine learning aspect heading out of the knowledge graph now has
70s
Billion + 70 billion
It knows 70 billion people places things cutting out
Especially saying Hey Google we have all the information and we're making it available to you in a
Easy way to access
Ed and you actually mention something
Else I don't know if we
Specifically said
You said you were
Jersey or you were looking forward to interacting with it
Because it's contextual
You can can carry on a conversation
And you don't need to repeat certain keywords so to speak so
You say who is the
Who wrote stranger things
And then you later say what is his birthday
You don't have to mention him by name so there's that aspect which I think some of the
AI bits like an Siri and the echo kind of fall short
I knew you were going to know that isn't that crazy
Example
See you just handed me the ball
I know it's not on the show notes folk she recalled that from memory
From Henry
Useless things I know
Oh that useless
Okay so
We should also talk about Google Wi-Fi
Because in addition to home
And
Some people were hoping that Google home and the wife I would be like
But you know I was when I was one of those people
I hoped that it would be you know kind of a
Voice assistant
And Mesh networking router thing but it's
Just a mess
Networking router thing just a mesh Network
Jobs that make you go we would be like
You know I want one of these
Very badly because I have an onhub and
There are a few areas in my house where my wife is not that great we could really use a mesh Network
But I don't know even though I tested the Euros
Which were great
I don't know that I want to spend like $5 for a set of euros
Now
And not all you can spend
It's 129 for a single pack of Google Wi-Fi so one edition
And it's
299 free
3 pack
So that's a big price difference
They will be available for pre-order
In the US in November
And they will also be sold at
Amazon Best Buy
Walmart
That's weird cuz Amazon doesn't sell
Amazon doesn't sell Chromecast but
That's different
That's so here's a question for you and see if you know the answer to this one
Smarty pants
Why are they selling a
Single pack
Network extender
What would it work with
Well it's not just a network extender you can
Habitat is your router
I believe so
It can messaging wasn't
Next to your land
I believe it maybe they're selling a single pack if it's not an actual router
To work with you
Bingo
It was something I had hoped
That I would hear about
On stage with the product they didn't mention it however
Being happy on HUB owner
I went and checked the onhub support Pages which were updated to show that
You can add a Google wifi device
To an onhub
Why that wasn't discussed I don't know why cuz it was like they killed the onhub that's I mean I saw
25 comments immediately
Nope
If this is an in addition to
They also other the on HUB has it
This device for smart home people you're going to like this it has a Bluetooth radio
So you got Wi-Fi + Bluetooth radio which means all of those tiny little doorbell chimes or
Lock Bridges or anything
That has a Bluetooth radio in it
Will eventually be able to be supported by the
Google Wi-Fi
So that's exciting for people who don't want
How to plug in a bunch of
Yay
And we're going to see that in a lot of routers that's not
Going to be specific to this but like
If you're buying a new router anytime in the near future in your vested in the Smart Home
I would look at like securifi
This one I think the Netflix orbi might be Bluetooth ready to
I'm so start looking for
Bluetooth is part of your router
I'm a double check on the orbi because you
It's always worthwhile to say
Hello
I'm not seeing
Not simply
Dyson
Putting Bluetooth in router doesn't make sense in the morning get rid of hubs so to speak and I'm all for it number one and I shall sacrifice
You are absolutely right this is a router by itself
It is so cute you were right
I love it
This happens so rarely
Okay
EXO
That is
The Riders Inn
Guys I'm going to tell you so I am actually reporting out a story on
The right router for your smart home
Which could be like
Holy Grail Quest because
It may never be complete
I don't know if that's really
Who's there
But I'm hearing a lot of mixed reports from
People about
You know if there's too many devices in a lot of these mesh networks it becomes
Really congested
I know that there are things about like how Apple sends data around a home network that is
Makes it really hard for
People with mesh Networks
An Apple devices
This is not me saying that mesh networks are bad it's just
There seems to be
3 by 4 kitted user experience
And it seems to be related to the number of Gadgets in the types of gadgets you haven't
So in my quest to help our listeners
I'm looking into all this for
I'll let you know what I find
It does require me to purchase a crazy expensive
Spectrum analyzer so I'm hoping the
That I can just get that
Borrowed for a little while
Yes it would be the texas-based to FCC Testing Lab
Let's see next story are we done with Google do we feel like we have sufficiently discuss Google
I think we have like I said when I can talk about the phones those were the two those are the two i o t a
Types of things to talk about the end
It's all we can do is talk about them now since we can't actually get the products in hand just yet so I think so
There we go anything Google can do to expedite my shipment I am all on it
Ready to test
We'll see what happens
Alright so the next big story
Actually let's do a quick update
Because last week
Talk about your Apple to Hawaii
Watch all the Apple watch 3 that's right I did real quick say I was going to run a half marathon and test the battery life so
I ran an hour 50 and I had Bluetooth
Free music
Heart rate monitor and GPS
Battery went down 43% so with all the radios and sensors on I'm thinking it's at least a four hour
Device for you exercise feedings
Everybody else
Exercising
Get up and move number one
Your wash it easily last a day mine always last more than a day so
Got it you know a Dancing with the Stars they practice they do for our practices isn't that insane
Like exercise
Sorry I I learned this fact and I was like
Holy Jim
Calories being burned
Yeah. One of those people I lose
Okay so
Let's move right along to iot botnet
We can talk about this attack last
But now there's more information
There is and it's worth saying because I didn't
But when we recorded last week.
Yet to do
My interviews that are structured at the
I have yet to do the interviews at the structure security conference with a bunch of people about iot and security
So I learned a lot of new things that I thought was worth sharing
So
To refresh
Deer are too big
Botnets
It were
Unleashed upon the world
That relieves it that got up to about 6 between 600 in
Whatever they sent they they measured it like 1.5 terabits per second
Which is a lot
Atrophic
So what was happening is
Originally Brian Krebs was forced offline Brian Krebs as a security researcher
Because of this botnet attack that reached between 600 and 700
Gigabits
Per second
So
Massive Attack one of the largest we've ever seen
And
There was another against it is pee called ovh
And that was
Bigger
So
These were made of
Iot devices so I was like oh my God this is
Terrible
And they were actually made of networked DVRs which is not a tradition this isn't like your refrig
Auto Repair happened fridges that are par
Certified Nets
This is
These closed-circuit video cameras that
Small businesses deploy
And then they later connect them to the Internet so they can be like I can watch someone robbed my store
For the comfort of my own
Orlo the Fire HD
In HD
So what's happening is people are taking over these devices because people don't update them
They're not really designed to be always connect
So
People are concerned
The flipside to our privacy worries and security where is on the internet of things that we always talk about white people hacking into your baby
Monitors
Is
The people are actually
Turning all of these devices into botnets and using your home's bandwidth
Watch these crazy massive attacks it because there's so many devices and their into many homes
It's less a function of so many it's more a function of their spread out and that they're not updated
They can be used for
4 years on these crazy attack
Because nobody's like
I'm like a computer slowing down you don't notice when your DVR is like
Siphoning off bandwidth
Their there they're not devices that you would be paying this kind of attention to and then she said they're very distributed
Now what
Really interesting what I learned at the structure security
Conference is there's like
Two to three groups that are actually
Organizing and controlling these botnets and what's happening is
As they fight each other
They're going out
And patching
The devices for
Are people so their enemies can't use it
I like you
Thanks but also
This feels
This feels scary
Little out of control
Light outage
So
And that brings us to our
Next story
Segway
Be way more effective
The Segway has released this week Shirley Tuesday
A
Checklist
On enhancing the security privacy and safety of
Connected devices
This is a great tracklist and this is brought To Us by the same group
That they had last year worked with the
National Association of Realtors
To do a smart home
Like decommissioning checklist that was
Really helpful
New checklist which I will link to in the show note so you all can download it
A lot of its common sense
It has things like you don't
Know all the devices with your home and workplace that are connected to the internet
I'm just able to unload it on use devices
I have a pet peeve here though
This is a great thing to do I try to do it
But even things like my Eero
Or even when I had software that measured my devices
Imagine that based on
You're all those aren't always
Telling you what they are
Yeah that's that's tricky
You're not trying to plug the product because if I work for it's just a product that I used
With the onhub
You can actually name devices and you have a better sense of what they are like like to suck hell out of them self identify which
I do see some mac addresses in the list of devices but
They are far and few between
So
So yeah my time I'm looking at my Eros right now to see what I can see on the network
Take a minute
When I
Like some of them are great
But then a lot of them are named after like
Bishop's like summer like
Crazy number Nest Labs Inc
Sound like okay I only have one Nest devices
My house
I have brother Industries
Amazon actually did add their name to sir
So used to be
Medeco had just a random
Mac address but now it says Amazon Tech
Technologies Inc
My Fire TV is all have a specific name and whatnot yeah
But like
I got it so the ring doorbell is good
My Sonos has are all good
But I have all these ampact
Technology
I don't know what impact
Technology Inc
What
Craig's iPhone is on mine
That's my father-in-law who the heck is Greg
That actually isn't that the other thing here
A lot of these
You know easily viewable router table so to speak
Are showing
Previously connected devices
Just wish me no longer be in the house
You know mine's divided up on currently connected
So I feel better about that but
Yes just for a minute there I was like
Craigslist
Okay
We've only got through the first
The next piece of advice
It's to contact your ISP to update routers and modems to the latest security stand
Change your router service I didn't know that's what is SSID stand for
Router service set identifier
I mean I know what my SSID is I just did
I said change it to something that does not identify you your family or the device
That makes sense
Check out contact information for all of your devices and make sure they're up to date with
With your current email
Melidress
Confirm that all of your devices are able set for automatic updating
And make sure you're getting the latest firmware patches
You can do all your passwords
And where possible
Implement multi-factor Authentication
I
I'm not going to do that
That problem
It's a lot of work
That's tough but a lot of these
Stats are the thing is
We need to be doing a better job at
Yeso in this is a smart one although exhausting in a possible
Review the Privacy policies and practices of your
Your devices because it is your settings can be inadvertently change during update
Spotify
Drove me nuts
Reverting everything to publican
Because my daughter listens to all this stuff
I really need everybody to know that I am listening to Katy Perry Non-Stop
Can we do now
Yes well it's my daughter
But yes that
Sure
And then
Yuan clearing data off if you return it or sell it
That actually got people in trouble with
Security camera
The Arlo's actually
Review your location tracking
In the back of your phone
So these are pretty obvious
What agency on here
Was change your router passwords
And make sure you got a password on your router
Yeah I mean
We might they may think that's a given but no added a lot of people just
Just take the default if you know a my network name is Linksys password
Alright let's go where am I
And that's not good
Work that's not going to lie
No
That's that's kind of not my house that doesn't fly
Presidents
All right
So let's see
Kabul news briefs
That's so that's the OT a survey that's how you secure your smart home a little bit
I mean again
Some of these devices just are not
Really securable in that is sad
That is sad
We're getting there though I do feel that the industry is at least much more aware of this and is like
Oh crikey we really got to support this
I also would say
You know if you're going to invest in a lot of devices
I should tell you guys that
I want to do this in a couple weeks when I find the time and my husband lets me shut down our Network
But I'm actually going to go super extreme and create a separate Network
For my iot devices
And I'm going to try to set up a firewall
Behind them
And I got this idea from Andy Ellis who is the CTO of a Takamine
We're talking about security stuff
And so he and I are actually he's like this is why
What you should do as I like to you
So we're going to figure out we're going to figure it out
Together
So it's possible we won't have a podcast for a couple of weeks cuz I will look
Totally broken my neck
Ono.
Hopefully that does
I mean I might totally
So this is my grand plan when I implement it I plan on writing like a detailed how to pose for anyone who's crazy enough
What you want to do this
And you know guys feel free to send me stuff
Set questions at iot
Podcast.com
If you have suggestions
I know it's not a question
But send it anyway
All right
News briefs
Some real fast stuff is happening that you might buy to be aware of
Let's start with
I do not okay
I feel like I've been talking a lot
Let's start with
Let Echo
Flacco
These guys made actually think the first phone using the Qualcomm 8
20 chip
Nothing 21 that's in the pixel
But and they also bought Vizio
They are launching an iot division here in the United States
And they hired rachna.
Who used to be at Qualcomm and
Doing all the All Join stuff
And then moved over to a start-up called helium
He's in charge of this so I'm really interested in like another brand
Coming over with some
He is an exceptionally smart guy and a good could hire Facebook's I love Rob
Yes
Good endorsement
Other news looks like
And those are the
The only
Maker sometimes it feels that way and Intel are doing smart glasses smart
Eyeglasses that you know will check your stats track all kinds of crazy stuff
I feel like step trackers again
They are there already
They already are
Blink which makes these tiny $100
HD Wi-Fi cameras they integrated with the Amazon Echo so now you can tell
She who shall not be named
To arm or disarm your blink security system
Yeah that's that's very handy
These guys that you can buy like a pack of five of these for like
330 bucks which is
Crazy Cheap
On their battery power just they look like motion sensors basically
Set them up on a wall
They're real fun
I know somebody someone emailed me saying they used it as they like
Camera in their refrigerator so they could see like when the door opened it
Detect motion
Take picture
They can see what's in the fridge
Because it's battery powered you can do that yes
It's not going to
I don't know if it actually
There's two things there there's
Cold and the Faraday cage
They're happy with it
It's relative
That's cool
All right
So
That is it for this week show
Jetpack cell phone
And stay tuned for our guest
Who is a realtor in Miami Beach who's going to tell us what devices we should stock our smart home with
It's for the best resale value
And now for a word from our sponsor
This week sponsor is hpe
And talk about HPV
Dr. Tom bradach who is VP and general manager for servers in iot system
So we're here talking about the ability to deliver hybrid iot
And you mentioned to me that
With the Internet of Things
There are three physical places that you have to deal with it
Can you elaborate on that for me please
I like to refer to him as a trihybrid
Ikea
Because there are three places
The first two rather obvious it's either the
On-prem Data Center
Cloud and then the other off Graham that's emerge
And the edge has many dimension
Like with respect to this all your teeth as they are
As you know what I ain't asking for a
City tram
A smart building the wind farm in or regular
Energy grid
Dimension of the edge
That is not the iot is also very important for the other off crown
Domains of Telecom media CDN
Campuses in Branch offices
Are there free places now where I T
Is going to be a dominant technology
Xen support
Improvements as well as scientific discovery
Civil engineering games
Into the things that are out there
NY does
The notion of it emerging at the edges extremely important
Realized because
And in subsequent podcast
What's happening at the edge NYIT is so important there
Another reason
To keep the trihybrid approach
Someone does not want to be confined restricted
Sherlock you know that on Prime data center North
Child lock in door being forced to keep things remote when indeed it would be better
Managing better drops
Local and give you more control
So what is Hewlett-Packard Enterprise
Have to offer
How many people know that hpe excels in
In the production of it equipment in the deployment of IHG
Robust cloud
As well
And the edge that's emerging the Third
Of the trihybrid
Applications of it
I work literally shifting out
In many areas
Altoona
So what we offer is
Ability for a customer to enjoy familiarity
Compatibility
Nez scalability it all free
The trihydrate locations in this hybrid
Pikachu
And where can I learn more
You can learn more by going to our website
Hgtv.com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host ACA
And today's guest is Danny hertzberg
Who is a realtor with
The chills in Miami Beach Florida
Hi Danny
Doing great thanks around me Stacy
Man I am so excited to have you
Both for selfish reasons and because I think this is going to be a fun show
You are here this week to talk about how to sell the smart
And since I have eight
Leicester
Devices in my house I have corset like who
What should I put in there was a goodbye
What was it
Let's just get started with a sense of
How do you when your
Putting a house on the market are looking at a listing
How do you define it a smart
House
Defining a smart home
It's a new you know a new term
And what we want to talk about typically is the connectivity of devices
The ease-of-use
A lot of consumers lot of the buyers they respond to brand names
So instead of saying you know we have
Smart AC system we might say
Property is controlled by nest
And we instead of talking about smart locks we might say an actual brand name of August locks because
That's something that resonates with buyers and when they're looking at
Hundreds of homes and descriptions on Zillow Trulia realtor.com
Brand names
Smart technology
She stands out to them because they're looking at
You know the whole experience of the property
And if it's something that's going to benefit them in their daily lives it's going to track them to that property and maybe make that home Stand Out verses
The house down the street
Got it
So if I'm considering
Selling my house what brands are worth investing
Sure
So I work with a lot of investor
Developers
And there are looking to maximize every dollar now that they put into the properties
So what if we tell them is
Yeah they have to be smart technology that
Benefits of experience in the daily lives
So the buyers because when I'm showing it it's one thing describing it
When I walk into a property with the buyers
They have to get excited about something
So one of the
Products that really stands out that tires are used
To sing in
You know high-end Homes apartments they're staying at it at
In office space
This is nest
It's known across most of the consumers they respond to it
Very simple to use and has a sexy
She look
So that's a brand that I think stands out lot of
They coming to the property it's very easy to show them to
Explain the benefits of that some of them don't understand
All the Smart Home Technology
But they surely can understand that in some homes you have to go up in every room and turn off the lights
And other homes you're going to press one button and all the lights are off when you leave
Not something that we
Stick out
From home to home and I think
Things like lighting HVAC
Smart Lock
That goes above and beyond the value of the
The investment
Okay so Nest smart lighting
Yeah like Lutron August locks
I mean those are those are kind of
Big names
In the in a smart space released from
Higher perspective
Okay do you get a lot of
Questions about how these things will work I'm just thinking
Not necessarily in a new house but if I were to sell my house for example
Conveying some of the stuff to the new buyer would be
Kind of complicated I don't know if it's a turnoff or not
Yeah I think it's
It is complicated but I think it's it's
It's important that
Whoever selling the property whether it's the owner themselves or likely real estate agent that agent
Understand Ted Hughes
The system and understands how to explain the benefits of the
So that's a big
Component of it
After walking
Through I mean I've been on showings where
The other agent
The property has a very complex system
Where how to use it
And they're not it's not working
And it doesn't you know they can't turn the lights on they can't turn the music on they candy
He's a Smart Lock
Versus another experience
Or somebody's walking them through showing them how to use
Components why they like it while they have it in their own home
Tell me the story of daily life like once
To be nicer
It's so great that I don't have to carry cheese anymore and they open up a lock
Phone
That resonates
And that really makes a difference in most markets across the country their competitive markets
And how do you stand out
Some homes are in a brand new kitchens and bathrooms but if all the homes are doing bad
This is the next step
The only thing that's interesting is
Byers at this point
If a home is brand new or fully renovated
And somebody didn't put in a smart system they look at it as almost as you cut corners
Okay and do you have a sense of
What that can add to the
The price of the house in terms of
Sales price or how quickly it moves
It's very hard to tell because you don't know two homes are like right and even if we had two identical properties they would be they were
I want to be on the same parcel
What's the location to driver
But I do get the sense over all that
Similar price point similar square footage
It's a standout
Feature
It's also standout feature if the home had you know a brand new kitchen or standout feature if it had
Brand new pool at those kind of things
It's right off of you it's it's an aspect selling aspect
I think Home2Home I've seen buyers
Lean towards one proper
There's a perceived value above
With it installed system
Above and beyond the cost
If you think about it
If a buyer
What's a home on the market
Is a million dollars
They realize
Pools going to cost
It would probably pay above and beyond the cost of the pool because
Pulling permits if I knew the contract
The same is true with the Smart Home Technology buyers want to come in
And have a turnkey home bring your toothbrush
That really related
Smart Home Technology also
Got it what happens
If I'm listing my house and I've got a crust on or insteon system in there
Are you going to tell me
Stacy
Back office
Try some of these other things or is that still cool
It's so cool I mean people still appreciate the control for the Crestron
They like them
I don't know if you'll get the full value
So if you already had it
Greatest benefit
But it's okay if somebody came to me
Unless it's at their very very very high-end
You define with different you know
Components smart
Components of a work with each other and maybe
The home has an Amazon Echo and there you know that's kind of the Hub rather than have York restaurants
System hop
You cannot take my Amazon Echo Dot
Does not convey
I have taken that guy with me
It stays
Redcoats
Yeah I think that I think that you'll see
Maybe at a very very high empress
Price point you'll still see some of that the Crestron savant
Metro Ford
The pretty much across
The Country Inn condos single family
You're going to see how the different components because the price point like
I can't justify to a client building a million-dollar to million reason $3000000 spec home
To put in a 30 or $40,000
I can justify putting in
1520 $500
System that pretty much for most
Consumers
Accomplishes the same thing
It's true
I
And now I actually ripping and replacing old Smart Home Technology
New stuff
Which
I feel really hard
But I'm going to get over it
Eventually
Evolving
What price point does this become like a must have
And I know this differs based on different markets but
Can I get a sensor
What do I need to have this
I think the science is whatever the market is
Wherever the perception
The luxury price
So in a lot of markets
You know what's a million.
And some and some markets 500000
Luxury price point
Yashow market
Miami Beach might be 2 to 3 million price point
Or LA or New York
So I think it's out entry-luxury price point
But there's a huge benefit
To even at you know
$200,000
Property mean you're seeing at the home builders that are building tract homes all over the country
They're putting in
Lot of bass
Smart Home Technology because
People appreciate it they can
Buy it
Probably put in fist
It's $4,000 a house and
It sells faster and
It goes above and beyond the value of the investment that ski
You don't see that in a lot of other things in a home where
You know I can say you know it's hard to show
It's just
Experience-based evidence
But I think most builders that do it once they continue to do and that says a lot
It'll most of my clients are a little bit like hesitant maybe when they're like what's the point of the smart locked I really need smart HVAC
And I get them to do it one time
They do it every single their project after that cuz they see how people respond to it
Awesome
Does it has this change your job
I think the changes
Is there's a lot of educating but I've been doing
Educating my sellers wife
Important it's
Educating the developers investors why they should do it and a lot of its educating the
The consumers so the buyers come in and they don't always understand
The system what's
The benefit so I've got to
Explain it to them in a way that impacts that
Somebody might not care about the fact that
You know you have a smart HVAC it means nothing to them
Am I really respond to this morning
Entertainment System
That's Chase my job a lot I mean we're always educating about the marking about the home but
The technology education and you know
34 in my industry and relatively Young
So I'm
And educating a lot of agents that work with that are in the 50s
67 days and it's not always engaged
Are some very tech-savvy agents
On the older the higher end of the A train
But once they try it
And they they feel in the touching the user
Yeah that they're hooked on and they loved it as well
I'm very curious about
The issue of longevity
And driving standards because some of the stuff it feels like
Like actually a good examples homekit
Kind of has been hovering at the edges and now seems to be really entering the market
Bright
Or the drama over at nest
What are you tell clients when they're like weight does this work with that do I want to invest in this forces
The other yeah it's hard I mean I can only share like my own personal experience with people what I would have used it
Different clients homes everyday
In the system's I'm using their what I've use personally
You know
There's different tribes with different things
It's very hard
It's hard to tell people what's good and also their price point also their budget
So you know I'm not in the business of selling
Smart home technology or the products
But I am in the business of selling homes
And I think that just like
You a lot of real estate agents understand different types of wood flooring and they know about
Different types of fixtures and they understand
No types of construction this is one of those components that
I think it's here to stay I don't I don't think it's a trend I think it's going to continue to grow
All right
And then what would you say to the industry
Like you're trying to sell and talk to people who may not know about this stuff
Everyday
Whitewright what can you tell them
The ease-of-use is critical
One thing that frustrates me about
Even some of the Smart Home Products I love
That
Although everybody
You know they're smart company so they want everything to be kind of
Digital app
Yo
Q&A but they still need to have
Some of the old school personal touches Witcher
If somebody has a major problem
Tele telephone number
And try to find
Contact number on the most
The smart products
They Don't Really typically want to speak with
You said that's something I could tell the industry that
You know it's somebody's frustrated trying to get into their home cuz they're locked.
They're not using their Smart Lock correctly
Are you having trouble with
You know they're nasty whatever product it is that
Luckily they don't come up often
Is there one way products but when they do I think that
Personal component
Even though they're not direct sales direct-to-consumer
You have to have that aspect for a lot of people because it goes a long way and end and I I do commend in the street though because
Does it seem
With a lot of products I think I just saw with Nest that
They have like if you don't feel like you can
Put in the product
Yourself here's a designated Personnel coming
Installed for you
I think that's a really nice easy way to transition to
Yourself
Some people don't have the time or they don't have that
You know
Way that they're able to do that even if it's simple screwing in changing wires
It's nice to make it easy and approachable for everybody so it's
Keeping the email to human touch with helping people get onto the smart products
Yeah well the stakes can be incredibly High when you're installing a new thermostat
Absolutely I only take the hottest or coldest days of the year
Just because I like the extra
Okay and you
Live in a somewhat smart
What are the gadgets that you
So am I home I guess I'll go from the entrance I have I just moved it to home
So this is little by little but so far I'm using a
I use August locks
Smart locks that do not carry Keys anymore
Has been phenomenal been able to let in
Real friends when I need to if I don't get locked out or not to carry Keys anymore
So the August locks are you have nests
For all my thermostat
Smoke alarms I use Mass I'd love the look like
The glowing light
A little ring at night
77 NightLight if you walked
The bathroom
What else we have Amazon Echo
Which is great
Getting used to speaking to it a recognizing me but I think they're like Central Hub voice activation
It's like the future of smart home technology
And just not having to
Reach for your phone and open the app just to be able to speak commands
They're really nice aspect and
And that's where we are so far
I had a I was in an apartment
Before that
I fixed off and putting a lot of smart home
Products and
End up selling it in
Recently got married and moved to a house so we're doing
You know step by step as we go but so far in
Naproxen and Grading
And we're still waiting for dining room table and sum
Other smart products that will see
Dining room table going to be smart
I don't think so not yet but I see some cool smart tables with the embedded you no touch screens and all things like that and
We don't have a smart refrigerator yet cuz their refrigerator they was here
Sky like a classic
Old Sub-Zero now probably run forever but when I does Burnout I'm definitely getting one of the smart refrigerators where I can check my phone
Inside of it
And open up with you lifting up your foot and in all those great aspects
Wow alright
You sound you have drunk the Kool-Aid my friend
Okay
Well I think
That's about it
Thank you
Danny so much for coming on the show this way
It was my pleasure was great chatting with you thank you so much
Well that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free
Free to sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
Stacey on iot. Com