Hey everyone welcome back
To The Internet of Things podcast Stacey Higginbotham
And this is my co-host
Kevin tofel we have
Care about light
Everyone cares about lighting
Without it
Alright so we're going to get started with
Smart home stuff for you because
A big part of what whatever
There are
Three things happening
One is Phillips has updated its app we warned you in advance
This is going to happen
You don't have to use the new Philips Hue
New apps
But if you want
What this Windows is basically turns the Philips Hue app into
I don't know an app that was good like 2 years ago it gives you all the functionality that you kind of expected the original Philips Hue
Got to have
So it's things like being able to divide your lights up in two rooms and control them
So it's very nice it's very
It's very fast on my Android phone so I am enjoying that I've got a test version of it so
I'm not sure if
The actual version
We spoke last week about the six
Security updates in the Philips app
Which kind was the precursor to
The new app
And even
Prior to that we talked about some permissions challenges on the Android side for the Philips Hue at those are already fixed as well so those are non
Known issues for this new app
Right in the security issues was basically
Third-party apps
Authenticate
Right so
Many of the third-party apps
That she was worked with
Most of our favorites
Have already done this
Proceso nothing
Should be back in changes nothing to see here
There are
Few apps that did not work
Phillips on this that will not have
Security token
It's like four of them
And two of them I've never even heard
So you can find all that until
But with the new app in the new features
So you can
Like I said there's there's rooms
So
Yay
There's also routines you could set alarms and timers in the original Phillips app
But you couldn't actually sit like full-on schedule
So now you've got they've made that process a little bit.
And there's a
A widget teacher that gives you
Access
From home screen
That you can
Program up to 10 scenes to do something like
Super fast like
All the lights in this room on or off
I actually cut
Created a bunch of those things using the Hue tap
The physical Hue tap device cuz it has
Five settings I believe four five settings
So you just press a button
So now you can do it
And that is good to hear on both counts scheduling I think it's very important for the lights and
I love love love widget
Sportsmart home
Controls that have the wink one
With all my shortcuts right on my home screen to one tap in your good to go
It also does home and away
Is it done geolocation
And then it also Phillips has a tie in with nest
A works with Nest integration that
Ideas to do home and away so
I didn't really
Feel a lack in the previous app
But you know it's nice for people who don't have all that
That the Philips Hue app is finally becoming
Really what it should have been in the beginning
That's the update there the other update is for those of you guys who really love colored lights
There is now a
Outdoor safe
Colored light from ilumi
And these are the guys that are doing Bluetooth lights they have an indoor BR30 and an indoor a19 which
Just a normal light bulb
And now this
Outdoor flood
I'm excited about this cuz I have a rooftop Deck with lights
I would love to be able to do some cool color changing kind of things up there when we have parties
The light bulb is $70
And it
Will begin shipping in summer 2016
So it's not a cheap lipo
Noble and to be honest when you first told me about it right before the show as I can with a lot of money it doesn't use a hug which means that uses and
Use Bluetooth on your phone through the app
And it wasn't too keen on it but you raised a good point that I think is worth reiterating
If you're having your party on rooftop deck and you're not going to give out like access to your yourhub so people control the lights outside
The rapper. So if you want to give them Bluetooth access
Stewby's lights you can do so
Pretty easily
And the fact that it's
Outdoors ip64 rated
46 rated I believe I can double-check
Stereo 60
So it's you know dustproof and and can handle water and all that I know
Don't like you said too many outdoor lights that you can control like this
WeMo actually had a string of outdoor lights
That was the only other one
This is actually this is disco lights
Super stoked
The other thing is I tried
I think somewhere in my Twitter page you can see a picture of my dog dancing
Colored lights
I'm in that was actually
And there's a setting on the app that lets you
You don't have them changed with the Beat of the Music that you're listening to which
You know it's kind of fun
I'm not sure which I'm more impressed by though that they lights can actually change their color and all to the beat of that or that your dog Acts
We should know
Okay then she is a dancing crazy.
I think these are Nate I am probably be
Because I'm a sucker for lighting
Smart Home Technology I'm probably going to buy one or two of these just a test them out
When they're out on the market
And I will let you guys know
And maybe shoot another video of my dog dance
Who knows
So
That's that
Check those out of here in the market
And the final thing is
I had talked about these
Lights about a month ago these are the stack light
From
Company called stack labs
And
They actually announced this week that they've got an a19 bulb
Which is again that normal bulb
Cool thing about the stack lights
Is there a design with the idea that you will never have to touch your light switch
They're what they called
Responsive
Or say anything
Or do anything
Yeah you just
Well you do have
Walk into the room that's correct. They have a presence in Decatur
They do they have a motion sensor in there
Both types of lights they have a BR30 that I've been testing out for over a month
And then they have the 819 both have emotion
Detection
They both have an ambient light sensor
Supper ideas if you walk into a well-lit room the lights just one
Turn on his break
The sitting you energy
In practice I didn't see a lot of that it had to be really super bright for the lights not to turn on at all
It is always awesome
And have the lights
Obviously they've been light switches with motion sensors in the decades
But this is actually moving at sensor to the bulb
Interesting thing here is and I think was I don't this was just announced today or recently
It was
Do you think basically an ultrasonic
I guess I'll call it a sensor
To act like radar
So
What that means is these lights can actually sense your presence even if there's a lampshade in the way
Right cuz most motion sensors are
Parc
Passive infrared
They send out sound waves
They basically like a bat
Figure out what's in front of them or what's around them based on
Sonic
Picture they're getting
Also like radar
Like you said
So I have not tried the a19 with the new type of sensor but
I'm very excited about this this is research that actually
A bunch like the University of
Has been doing a lot of
Things with this in Wi-Fi for understanding gesture-based commands
So it's possible that we could see
You know what a couple of years
Better gesture recognition for
In home control
Based on this technology
Excited
Replied so early
Another bit I mean this is kind of a new technology involves
What surprises me is that it's not adding a ton to the cost of the bulb
The standard a19 I believe it's $28 a bulb
The symphony 19 is $28 but these bulbs do have a hub so you got to buy a starter packet first
Oh, and the initial starter pack for
39 teens is 8999
And I could Chuchu bulbs
Github
If you want to do the BR 30s
Those that's a $10 more for the starter pack
And it's
$60 a bulb
Differential
Big difference
I should also note
The $28 is the pre-order price
But
I would say
Based on my
Using these lights
It's in
I actually want to get a couple of 819
Because
I want to install them in my
Closet
Rate for rooms where
They're closed off so I have an open floor plan of my house so these
Decent work super well
In those rooms but any room that's closed off like your office
The laundry room
The study
Oh that's also the office
Closet
Really well I thought for this so
In hallways
Everything was always because they have like a daytime mode in a nighttime mode so you can
They probably need walls to bounce off of an if you have like a very open concept floor plan it may not be the best area is what it sounds
Actually if it just that you
Trigger them all the
So they are really really good
It's just that like
I pace around a lot
My daughter Paces so ghetto
You're walking in front of
Curious and I'm sure you can't answer the question since you can get a chance to try that da9 teams
I'd be curious if you can modify the sensitivity of the Ultrasonics
So that way
Going to hit you are here
Right ahead and they're going to actually
Later on
Like newer versions of the BR30
Should have
Ultrasonic
Sensors in them
Chris just like
Hey we have this idea we might implement
It's great so
I am probably going to buy some
I'm not sure how many yet but
Once I figure out like
My whole home lighting plan on share it with
And the integrate
Thank you answer my question I don't want another Hub if I have to have it what else can I work
4 piece with this what I'm going to say
Right
Cuz without Bluetooth there's
Okay so
Music on four lights
But this week is like there
I forgot about that
How Could You Forget About Me
Should I tell you how could I
They also
Has a circadian rhythm
Whatever time of day do you trigger them they're going to be in their circadian rhythm for that time of day
Which is kind of me
If you're into
For the closet Maybe
Four bedrooms in offices
Okay
So what else do we have we have
Wearables
Wearables Nokia but
Whiting
It makes sense in hindsight most these things do but I was surprised when I heard the news
Nokia has done a lot of different
Things to try and get into the the Health Market in the past either through apps or
Or whatnot bedtime
Here it's just a flat-out acquisition of life things
And
I forget how much they paid with something like almost 200 million dollars I got 290
Yeah we're good for why things
They've always seemed like an underdog in the space and for people who are not familiar with the name
In today's
Health wearables section or sector
You can have a lot of
Digital
Smartphone e like type
Devices
Bicycle with with digital screens and so on
Why things takes a very analog approach
To all the tile tracking and
They make devices that look like
Traditional watches
4 things that you want to wear bracelets inside
And they just have like an indicator like a sweeping hand
4 steps for example work
Arepa calories burned it mean to have apps as well as I don't want to say they're completely analog cuz they're not but
It's just always thought there an underdog here
So I think why things feels like an underdog for
What is there French
50%
In in 2015 I believe it was that they said that about 50% of their sales come from
And then the rest
Come from your opinion
Like 10% comes from Asia
So
Right there you know
Probably
A bit more
Global in their scope but the other thing is
They have a lot more than just the activity K-pop
They have
Pulse
Which is
Activity tracker that also at the heart rate sensor and it was actually one of the first to have those of have a heart rate sensor on
Like that type of
Activity tracker
They have
A bunch of devices
Like a baby monitor
A smart scale for weighing your baby they have
A scale for weight
Normal people adults
They have a blood pressure monitor
And a couple of
It actually worked really hard like it getting FDA approval for their more medical devices
Are they actually at CES were showing off a new thermometer in New Canaan
Thermometer to
Broad range of products and and that makes it even
A better fit for Nokia in my opinion
Yes and that's what I was going to
Which I don't think they cornered the market in it all
Holistically about
Quantified Self data in there trying to get it
To where it actually abused for the medical
A profession where some of like Fitbit and Jawbone they're kind of like
We don't really care what David pay those companies tend not to want to deal with the FDA here in the states
Yeah and I also I think
You're not as focused on
Bridging the Gap
In-N-Out
4 V bucks in parables
Money in healthcare is for the insurance firms
To a point where things are FDA-approved
Simplethings
Yeah but probably better or more aggressively than most of the others in the in the space I would agree
It's all about the data
And what
You can do with it how accurate is it end
Frequent use it you know in healthcare industry
So I was kind of shy but the purchase price was a little small
Just to put that in context for a 2015 reported 1.86 billion
10 in Revenue
Not all of that
Miss from device sales
Diesel Service as well
Yeah so true if you think about that
From that perspective you know
Almost 200 million is
This is nothing
Thinking about their actual Revenue
Agreed
28 2015 they sold 21.4 million connected Health and Fitness.
So
They are the leader
That's kind of where we are
Here do you care to think about like
Nokia
Backing devices
Oh I mean it's in their DNA has been minnow for a while I'm in a company
What hundred sixty-seven years old and started out
With the
Yeah exactly
I just turned into
Youku
Conglomerate of many different
Businesses
But either they don't have a true device
Group you stay is considering the whole Microsoft purchasing
And all the phone business and so on so
That's more people there they have investment funds of money
And then enter the good folks
Don't know what to do I think
With Y things to add to continue growing it so
I think it's it's nice to see Nokia in a return to
A segment that gives them some play on the device side but also on
I'm on the outside as well
Got it and they said that Cedric
Hutchings who is currently the CEO of why things will lead
They're digital Health business
That will be great
Anderson proximately 100 R&D people that Nokia has working on digital health
MLB part of that
And I'm not going to say where he's probably going to be
Cuz I say it wrong
In Finland
Take the city
I want someone to actually put I know what a print of one of her listeners corrected me and now I forget
It might be us but like I forget but whoever it was thank you for correcting me
Yes we appreciate it
Even though we have not put that knowledge to
I'm not going to lie
Whatever you know Act
She sometimes
We like to get it right
The other story I thought worth mentioning this week
Questyle
Which I should just bought one
Tile is a Bluetooth tracker that you stick on things
And
That sounded like an ad did it because did you buy one because you lost one
No
If I spent $25 on my
My tile.
$12 water
That's what it was so
Lust
2 $12
Water bottles
What's the title run gymnastics
What's the title cost these days
The tile is $25 if you buy just one and 1750 per tile if you buy a
Triton T2 Bluetooth tag for folks are not familiar
Yes
To your phone
The cool thing about tile
And why were I'm so excited about it
Is that
It has the potential
It's kind of become a poor man's GPS
I think
I say this because what happens is when you lose
Your device or when you actually when you buy a tile you install the app on
On your phone
And from then on your phone becomes
Able to detect other tiles
So someone says
I lost my bike and there's a tile on it and so they Mark the tile
Is lost
If you're walking by that stolen bike without missing bike
With your
Phone in the tile apps on it
That your phone will actually
Seamlessly to you you don't see it happen will send a notice
Vacation out
To the service
It's like a crowdsourced device GPS thing hits
Weather in
It's great so
They actually do this not that I bought
The actual actually reported their revenue for the first time this week
And they in 2015 sold 43 million dollars worth of tiles
Salat times
A lot of Trials
When I looked on my app I had 15 almost 15000 Tiles near me
Which meant that there were
I know
Oh sorry no 1500
Still alive
What's a 15 + I'd say a lot but
Kitchen
Yeah so that's people Oliver Austin that if
You know I leave my water bottle
Somewhere maybe
I haven't left this water bottle
Anywhere yet just
The test this out but we'll see
I probably will soon
And is part of actually making money
They're kind of going
Not a different direction but they're adding on to their business
They could have deal with
Integrate tile into
The car
So this is interesting because now your car is basically like
A walking tile
SSO is this to help you find your car or is it for the car to remind you that your device with a tile
Is it with you
Both
Double bus
Mike Farley who is an executive
He told me that this next year tiles going to focus on these integration so you should see more
More tiles integrated
Other device
Actually with an umbrella in it
Which you know you'll never lose your brother again was kind of idea
I don't think that went
Very far
Because it was a very expensive umbrella
Yeah
Yeah when you're talkin about adding tile to
The cost of an umbrella versus adding tile to the price of a car
Micardis
Sucks that price right into it so it's not a big deal
Seattle
I was excited by this I was excited by the fact that I get connected device come
He is making
That much more
Good on tile
Which brings us to
Tencent
If you want another in your life
Let's talk about what you should get
Has by golly I got an ass
Nest
Pebble
Pebble Hill
I don't know how
I think the Pebbles not a bad by because it's not that expensive and adds a lot of value
Well I mean
I mean the regular Pebble that I would say just
You know what gives you the basics it's not that expensive
Okay so the regular
Pebble
Alright then
I'm sorry
I have one
So you know it's out there
Is it like $75 can you get it for less than that I bet you could get
It's about right though
So so that's the basic Level Kevin
I was going to suggest a title
Because it's great to put on
Yorkies and it's like
25 bucks
And
Also if you're younger and you lose stuff
Often
You can actually like make your mom to have to look for it as often
Hypocrite
It's like the gift that you give yourself the gift to her
You know I I thought about you
Putting one in my purse or something like that though the other thing is from the app
Make the tile beep and it'll tell you where
Your stuff is
That's always nice it's nice if you are not the type of person who
Sister phone
My mom kind of is so so
That's wassup.
All right so other things for your mom
Do you think you buy your mama knows
Or Barb
Your wife who is also
I mean they don't really
Like we have a nest
If we didn't I would buy one
They wouldn't be like very enthused by it at all honestly
When they sent me that.
Campaign outside
You know
Connected devices
But if my family bought me a thermostat
For Mother's Day
Be kind of like
Yeah I don't I don't think that would go over too well
There are devices
Could go over
So if your mom likes
To cook
I'm going to recommend maybe one of the automated sous vide so the Anova sous vide is out there
And
That's pretty
Cool cuz they have both Wi-Fi and
About to drop scale
There's
That is actually $100
And it makes both
Cocktails
Aunt
Baked goods will any kind of
So the Anova cooker is about 180 bucks
So that's kind of expensive
But you know your mom she's nice
Let's see what else
The echo
I was going to say it
But
How you know
I don't want to overdo it cuz I know we tweak we are third fix fans of the echo
It's an easy-to-use consumer device
Cuz remember if you buy your parents
How to connect a device
You're going to support them
Would you would you actually go with an echo or would you go with something like the.
Ter
Roughly half the price
I would go with the echo
Because
Like a Sonos or something like that so I think my speaker
Capabilities
Gotcha
That's that's my rationale
Makes sense
They both do the same thing
If you're Stacy Bettis
Brings us full circle
Cuz my mom
She was established
Takashi super nice
And she's like
Cash like anything so the only other thing I would suggest for
Video doorbell
And
I'm going to say that because
You know if your mom is worried about like security she can see who's at the door
That's always nice
And
I don't disagree with you.
I was thinking to do
Dimension lights
There's a lot of moms out there who
You know they like to lie in bed and read or whatnot I actually don't know that we get a connected light but I would get a maybe I can I get switch like the
Inside switch
Oh
Because you can you know that
Region free phone and
Say shut off and it shuts off you can schedule it
1011 at night whenever you're done reading
If you were
Super generous and bought an echo as well as at the echo.and
Now Mom can say
Shutter down
Lights
Okay so I will go for that
Maybe you and your siblings
Can all get together
So those are kind of some things that we that we thought about from the bombing
That would be
Kind of nice connected devices
For your mom
Golf devices
Is coming on
Where are Springs
So stay tuned because our guest this week is actually
Super worth listening to its
Hans vestberg who is the CEO of Ericsson
You may have heard of their giant Communications infrastructure company
And I talked to Hans
After the company reported earnings last week
Which actually
Their stock drop 10% after they reported earnings
Wall Street did not like
And they announce the restructuring of their business
The reason he's on here he's going to talk about 5G
He's going to be talking about
Turning your company into kind of an iot Focus company so the digital transformation that a lot of businesses are facing right now
And
A little bit about that
The carrier kind of perspective on I
It's okay
So
Stay tuned
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast to tell you two things the first is that I've launched a Wii
Weekly Newsletter devoted to the internet of things that you can sign up for it Stacey on iot. Com
That's Stacey on iot. Com the second is that we're now accepting ads on the internet
Little things podcast we have packages for big companies and startups so if you are interested please email
Call Andrew at iot podcast. Com and now
Back to the show
Hello everybody this is Stacey Higginbotham and you are back listening to The Internet of Things podcast
Today's guest is Ericsson CEO Hans vestberg
I'm finally
Great but I bet you guys
Doing better
Ericsson
Actually when we're recording this reported earnings and
What street was
Was not impressed
So
I'd love to talk to you because you guys are great
It is trying to adapt your business to it
Let's start off with
What you saw coming when you saw it
And what you guys decided to do about
Until the next Generation the old networks in a little. But I think we
We thought it of course having a baby
The network switch deal is very important
Cloud it needed
Drake's net worth
Based on our anchor Core Business web developer Jason B students.
And of course honey much more soap franchises in Thailand
That was sort of that
Epaystub
Area
The structure that
Support
Okay
So judging by your results
This is a difficult transition
You're really trying to thread the needle here as your
Core Business Network
It stack meaning
It's their consolidation in the industry there
Traders are buying
Bus stuff they're transitioning to sdn which means they're going to require less
Of your gear
So how are you guys thinking about
Adding Services it how is that going
How to say I'm looking for structure
Market
Dramatic transformation
Then of course
Which one you think
Based on our strength on the telephone side
Growing plant
I cannot pillow sets
Step ladder
Slower pace
Okay
Let's talk about some of the services
Units
Cloud computing
Media network products and then services
So
The service aside I'm guessing that's the side that's probably most related to the internet
You can say that we are
Gearing up for a structure for real helicopter
America movie
Products and services
Using If It Don't Let It Go
We're coming from
I think no
And it will work with transport companies Affiliated companies
Gearing up the organization to will dust
How Port will those new Services be to Ericsson
After we have a patient up 20%.
Geico customers
Meaning yet
Even though
Patent portfolio
Giving up on orientation
Okay
What are the things that I'd love to ask you about is
Network Services
The actual providing connectivity is going to be
A small part of
Curious
How you think your customers
As the carriers are going to kind of
Are these new businesses are they
Think about that
Netflix
Then you have some
Service enablement that they need to put together
Mexico
Pasadena
It makes your drive more efficient something like that
And then everybody needs
Shoes
Eureka Pizza
The area so we can get
Concrete sandwich
We're not doing applications Bautista
Organization
Money Services Company
I think
Ultimate doing yet
Cathay pacific application
Got it
Alright let's talk about 5G
Because everyone's keep
Throwing that term around and I've heard it apply to Wi-Fi to
Cellular
Even millimeter wave technology so
Tell me what you think of when you hear 5 G
Card games that are different
Define developed
That's nothing
5 years olds a different
Thinking of you the whole network
Where you need to orchestrate the whole network dealer in Utah
Let's say you have the wrong tonight or if I connect what's up with you girl
Let's say that you have another sniper
That is delivering a letter
Show on you can go with different type of slicing in the network
Four different type of
And when you talk about
We will embrace
What technologies are you most
Because right now there's
A dozen different kind of low-power wide area Networks
Running around out there
Millimeter wave stuff from like even Facebook and Google are getting it on this moron delivering actual
Backhaul and access
Players that are not traditional
I think that's the most exciting is that there this time
What you said
Very sexy
Even if
I need to compression
Tri-State mobile network in the world
Which is older
Because you guys
Are over in Europe and I always feel that Europe is way ahead of the US
Cities
Businesses between smart Manufacturing
Radio Networks
Businesses
Is that true do you view Europe still is kind of more advanced
Yeah I would like to compare like that but of course
We have seen them knowing that you were being in Baltimore
Everything problem
Even though
Development
They will have the best donuts
Marcus like the USA Korea
UEFA Euro
Adidas
To do these type of things
Should be worried about
Spectrum
Cellular
How should we be thinking about
Allocated Spectrum
And then
Between licensed and unlicensed bands
First of all I think that's all they needed
Both lights
And we build you can actually move a thing between them
I think that's going to be important.
Men of quarter Circle
Would make
Honda cheaper
Add devices sheet for essay
But that we will need to use
Accident 78 Highway
When we talk about slicing
Slicing and dicing
Wireless networks
Spore
Kinecta cars which needs
You know different application
Next Level service levels
So that versus
Voice call versus
You know delivering data from a sensor out in the middle of a field
Do you think this
Getting
The network neutrality debate started up again
I hope not because it benefits our society
Need some different type of used AC
I'm in that everybody should have access
Internet
Henrico
Main attractions in Arkansas
I need some candles use technology
Sew-in talking to Wall Street about this transition
It feels like you guys have been looking
Forward for a long time
You're trying to prep and do something that's a long-term plan
Does Wall Street understand
Are you able to communicate or how do you
Communicate this to Wall Street
I wish I could walk or to communicate with her go away so I'm not
I hope that
Transparent
The way we have been
Finding Oreo or businesses
To be transparent
You can pull up the nest
So what would your advice be to other Executives who are in the middle of a digital transformation
So fast
How do you say
Do you have any advice for how they should
Communicate to shareholders
Customer
Define where you want to be young
Then you need to see that you going to have me for dinner
Turquoise and pink
Like the books
That's what we are
Going through
And you guys actually
Over the last
Like 3 years or so have actually
You've let it
A bunch of jobs go
You actually brought in a bunch of people with new skills
Actually really good
Example of kindness
How you're having to adapt
Can you talk a little bit about that
Yeah if you just give the number
On the basis of hunger Pizza Dalton at base of course
Very big transformation to have the right
Open Android Market
When you're moving into new area I need you
Thank you for
You basic
It's erupted 34000
Tricycle transformation
Continue
Products
Awesome alright well I wish you guys good luck
And thank you so much for talking to
Thank you very much
That's all we have for you this week but join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast thanks for listening