Welcome to the Internet of Things
Stacey Higginbotham
Hi it's great to be here I have been such a fan in following
Your podcasting
Been on it before so it's great to be costing
And for those of you guys who are deeply concerned about Kevin tofel he will be back next week
This week
Man
We have hit
Because
Today
How to say Google but it's been so long since I've been spending Google
Andy Rubin who used to be and was the co-founder of
Danger
Which was bought by Google in
Turned into the Android platform has come out talkin about playground his
Hardware incubator
It sounds really exciting
Oh my gosh does it sound exciting
I can't even
Stop thinking about what the
Potential is
So I have to tell you guys first
Carla is a product designer who
Specialty is
Smartlogix
Actually pretty smart
Custom Sounds
So playground is basically Ruben is going to design
Books that are going to feed into neural network
So basically they're robots basically
I'm part of the board
I was calling at the Borg
I shouldn't
He's designing products that are hopefully a little bit more future Pro
It's kind of his idea
A hundred percent sure what exactly
Designing
One of the first things that they talked about in this article and we're sourcing this from a wired article that is really dumb.
Is a dash cam
Smart dash cam
So let's say you had a video camera in you
Your car for example and it will know the car's location
Automatically
Attract it
Footage
It will
Be able to know what's happening
Driver as well as
What's happening
Around the world and if you then crowdsource all of that you can be
Recording
Everything that is happening
In an entire area and that will be
He also moving so
What's exciting about that is that that's any
Ugly Wicked thing to half
Build
In today's world
And what Andy is
Proposing with playground is to have one place
Where I somebody
Wanted to develop
Like the dashcam
Could have
All those
Parts
Together so you know you need
GPS
Camera
And you need
Incredibly smart artificial
Intelligence to be able
How to recognize faces right
Recognize objects interface that with
Maps data for example
And then you also have all of that
Stuff communicate
Continuously
So we're talking about systems were talking about Hardware
We're talking about
A lot of processing
And he's proposing that wood playground somebody who want
What about
Something like that could
Do it Under One Roof
Which is pretty cool cuz the only other place that I can think of there's like maybe four or five places where you could do that today in there
Google Microsoft
Amazon's 819
81926 labs
Amazon
Amazon's lab effort
Maybe I am Samsung
Yeah so you really can't do that unless you're a big company and when I talked to startups that are trying to do crazy cool
Things
This wicked cool voice interface cloud
Facial recognition products
Awesome
And then you know that later I get it and I'm like
Wow this is
It's not great
Six months after that Amazon sends you something like the echo in your life
This is what they
And you're like sorry
Public playground this could all like
Maybe happen which is kind of cool
But it's probably likely
I don't know what do you think these guys might build this stuff and then
What are the big companies just coming in
Wow
Buy the thing to pay bill
I think that
The playground part of it is
Most exciting life
Like you said just the fact that they will all be facilitated Under One Roof cuz one of the biggest issues that we have
With everyone developing products
In the
We know we might call The Internet of Things
Robotics whatever you want to call it is that they don't
Play nicely with one
Another right they're all using different protocols and
They don't connect with user experience
Which is what I really care about
Is terrible
So you know the idea of uniting forces
Has so much potential I think
For good hopefully they're not
Things that are being
Bought by big companies but
You know I have I'm I'm such a Utopia
So I always have a fan
ICF
The next
Mom and Pop Shop being a
IRobot developer
Robot developers that are designing using protocols that will work together and maybe
Oliver
It's like the Android Robot developer
Kind of concept
Yes okay
And I'm thinking of like the little like
Similar but different
Is that same that different what is the Android advertising slogan are you familiar with it
You don't have to do with it
You know what it's because I've been to the movies and I played it before all the movies I've been to lately
Surprisingly
I surprisingly don't have a lot of commercials in my life these days
Cord-cutting
Okay so
As a practice
Kid stuff
Would you a Medusa sound like an idyllic kind of place to develop stuff for
Disesteem
What else would you like to see here
It sounds like
An extremely idyllic
Place to build stuff you know I think that there are so many ideas and like the story that you talked about
When you meet people who have a new product they're developing and then a year later
They run into so many roadblocks and I think
Those roadblocks can be solved by
In touch with the right people and being able to collaborate
Owen and recognizing where your knowledge ends
Someone else's knowledge
Begins
So I think that
What he's building
Is a way to take away so many of those roadblocks and
Really speed up
The process of having
Robots in our everyday lives right
Alright so
Should I fear the robots
In our everyday life
I'm not a fear the robot person I'ma love the robot
All the robots that I've
Panino's very friendly and helpful
I've learned to do tasks
Clean up
Very polite
So I I don't I don't do that well I got it I'll do I have
How to say and everleigh I do a lot of
Talks
On robotics in our everyday lies and I inevitably get one question and every talk about you know the robots joining forces
Taking over
And what I think about that
I don't see that
So I'm less worried about the robots taking over
Some sort of malicious
I got a lot of Slack
The Nest is a robot
All these other Robots coming in and
Orchestrating my home
And I kind of help people I kind of shrug and I'm like yeah if the nest is a robot this is a robot
Tumi
Xiaomi smart home
If I'm going to bring a robot in and they're they're showing all these lovely little robots drive around with like a video camera that has facial recognition
Can do things
If it doesn't have arms so it can fold laundry or empty the dishwasher do something that like a little bit more functional if it's
Just like turning on lights in
I don't need an extra something running around my house tripping over things in life
Videos of walk the dog at the
Okay but other than that
What is your stance on Lake
Robots in the home that feel to me like a little superficial and I'm thinking about like Jibo or
I feel like they're on Kickstarter all the time I'm just blinking on some of the names
I know you see me
Sure yeah bro
I actually worked on
Very very early stages of Jibo consult
Dr. Cynthia breazeal
Up at MIT and
I am all about it
I actually
But I do think that we have to be
Careful
Because if
You have too many at your jeep has a character
Geebo is
Amazon Echo
Coming off of your shelf and expressing it
Itself physically
And
Yeah I think that
There's a lot of value in that
I think that
You know there is
Value in getting rid of Art
Keyboards and mice that are going to be this vestige
Of the past
At some point
And
You know that
Jibo does by adding
Physically animated expression
Is is one more
Step into
Helping us
Be able to just be
Humans and not have to learn machine language not have to learn which button sequel
What is the price right
So I think it's very exciting but
Do you think that
Gebos
A really good example of an everything machine
That
It's going to help you
Do recipes in the kitchen and you know read stories and you know that's that's one thing that's very
Ambitious
That will will Grier and I have to see it's very very hard to do it everyday everything
Apple has
Master D everything machine
As has
Android
But many many many other companies
Have Nots
But I think
That
We have to be
Careful with all the things in our lives
What's being too
Too expressive
So you know
What's the role of the designer that's why I love this work
You know that's why I think it's so exciting is because we have to use that
Almost like it's it
It's a color or a material and you don't want to use
Too much you know
Shiny Orange
Stuff in your home you want to use that as an accent
You should see my living room
There's a lot of Shanghai Orange
Remind it's true
When it does that plus my laundry machine
Does the lake
Okay well let's let's get back on track just a little bit because
Last week
About a guy from Google named Max brod
Who built
A Google Now mirror
Everyone was like oh my God
Since you are designing actually
A smart coat rack
I love Google Now
Huge fan
I check it every more
I love the idea of putting it on my mirror
I love the idea of putting on the windshield of my car like the pattern is driver-side windshield so like what I got in my car it's like
What you got going on today
Don't forget you
Eric Ryback
So what do you think
Shall I think that Max bronze mirror is
Watch designer I think it's very beautiful there's something really lovely
About
Seeing information
Floating
You know something about the mirror house
Not seem like it
Especially the one that he has
Is an edgeless mirror right
Oh yeah
It's just this kind of beautiful sheet of Ra
Reflection and mirrors also open up
The space so there's a lot a lot
Beautiful
Designery
About it
And I think
You know it in the
Blog post where he
About his project he says the other lot of people have tried to do and it's been in the movies so
I think it's very cool because I have
Envision the mayor for sometime
And when I did my New York Times piece are walking talking
Objects invited me to do admittedly really
I'm Tongan
She can play for slideshow and I have a mirror there
It's in the back
It's been something that I've been
Envisioning for some time and I was inspired by haven't gone to the MI
Medialab
And they had a mirror that could read my heart rate
So
For me what's
You know
The potential of this I think Google Now
It's
Rate
To have
You know whether and your calendar stop at
It's another place where we have
Be careful especially in the bathroom so I teach a course called
Smart objects design of contemporary products at the University of Pennsylvania
And last year we had a group that was designing
The bathroom we had
A lot of conversations about how the bat
Is one of the last
Tranquil spaces
That we have
In life
The bathroom and
Used to have
The airplanes
Not so much anymore cuz we have
So now we have
Right
So
Are you first walk with Max brought that like
I don't like I said is beautiful
I'm so well X
Executed
Great
To give you I'm at a glance
Information
I think the potential for the future is to have
Health
I think a lot of the fish
The smart mirror
Is that it would be that the bathroom is a place where you
Think about your
So I had seen at MIT media lab actually
Has a camera in
In Arabic
See the color of your
Skin and
Can actually
The nuances in color so that it knows when blood is rushing in a rushing out
And can read your heart rate
So I couldn't
The video camera in the Microsoft
So
I think
It can get even more exciting
If you think about the
Peripheral
That could
Plug into your Android phone that could maybe
You know heart rate or
Your temperature
I
Then
I think about
Health in the bathroom
I like the idea of
Weather information
This is a good segue because
Oh yeah
I was like that was a terrible song
In the hallway
Yeah right
Yes
So I am developing a smart coat rack
And
The idea behind that is
We don't need all the information everywhere we only need certain pieces of information
At the places of times with their most
Needed when you're just walking out the door is when you need to know
To grab your coat
So
What I'm envisioning is this really intuitive
Split Second
Conversation that you have with
Smart device
What's telling you
But then you're going okay
I'll take that ring
So you're developing
A coat rack
Somehow
Does it lift the coat how did it tell it what is division here that it has an API to the weather
Channels or something
Yes yes so it hasn't epi2 AccuWeather and
Can
Light up can highlight the code
When you take it when you walk past it
I have to have that ring
Code on 140
Yeah so it does rely on user experience so that's part of what's in the works with
Design aspect of it so that's a good point
It relies on
You having I also have had this Vision I'm I'm one of them one of those designers
Designers I've always had a vision of Heaven
Days of the week on
On my hangers in
In the closet
You sent that exist Carla
Yes
No I'd love to have like the clock that actually the closet that you open it
It tells you what
How to wear baseball
You're a calendar you know
For a while
I had my hue light bulbs in my closet light up a different color for
Temperatures because I get dressed in the morning
To walk my dog
Benefits in the winter if it's below
I wanted to know because that's when that's a temperature at which I wanted ad long and
Underneath my pants
So
I was like
I wanted it to light up blue
In the closet
So I have
Just one bulb in there
And I sat at using Lincoln if this and that
Recipe for you
It was great
Yeah I was wondering how it worked out
It was a challenge
Because they require
Because you couldn't turn out the light
Turn out the light then
It messed everything up but
It was kind of a
It was not
And ideas
Prototype
For this one
And we'll see how it goes I have a boyfriend
In the UK whose name is Brendan Dawes who also prototypes a lot of
These types of things and he's he's been doing some experiments in the closet and he's also been doing
Going to some very physical
Weather devices
Flip around
Let you know
What the weather is going to be so I've been taking inspiration
From that as well
As the ambient
Umbrella
The weather so
Can I have the lights up
Write the Latino
I just think there's an
Dance to that
But I'm going to really have to think hard
About to cuz I've been relying on myself to put the right code on the right hook actually we will close out the
Episode with this
Connected coat racks connected mirrors
Carla thanks for hosting
This week with me
And stay tuned you guys because my guest this week is Zach
Sepala who is the CEO of particle
We're going to talk about the electron which is awesome because it's bringing cellular connectivity to
Your things
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Podcast
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's
Guest is Zach's about he is the
CEO and co-founder of particle
Hey Zack thanks for joining us
Thanks for having me
So
Article is an iot dashboard
For the longest time it seems like everybody who I had on the show
Had one
I mean there were three
And now they're much fewer
And you guys have
Special news because
You've done something that
Mad if you asked me five years ago I would have said this is
Impossible
You actually let me let you tell it because this is your Triumph
Band
New product of the electron the electron is our cellular development board so we have tools for people to build
Products that are connected to the internet
Through 2G and 3G Towers and with it
We're including
The hardware that you need and a SIM card in a data plan
And the cloud back in and so is all kind of included one box
But the big thing that
I think it's really exciting about it is taking hardware and combining it with
This Heart of Hope carrier side
So that our customers don't have to figure out where the SIM card comes from the data plan
We just hand it to them and they can get going
This is truly like
For those of you guys who have not
Slog through years of
The development of The Internet of Things
This is a big freaking deal
Because
Forever if you wanted to do anything with the carrier you had to go to them
As a big name company and they would be like
Oh so you want to connect something
How many sentence
Yeah
Exactly I mean they're they're set up to deal with
Customers that have millions of devices designed for smartphone
And so if your Samsung or
Apple
Or something along those lines
So easy to figure out how you engage with carrier cuz they want they want those, those contracts and if your
Not Samsung you could still be a big company
But still not but just not shipping millions of devices every year
It can be really hard to engage of the characters cuz there was not set up
And that can be really painful and slow and it can stop you from building
A product
That is actually a good idea
With a good business by propositions behind it because you just can't get through those barriers
Kindle launched it was difficult for them to get
For Amazon to actually
Build that with
Wireless built into it because they couldn't find a carrier partner it took a while for them to get to Sprint
And this was this was actually a known
The jet company
So imagine if you're like
Somebody who's who just experimenting with something
You know even if you're at like Procter & Gamble
Or
Ghetto Halliburton
It's still difficult
Exactly right
All right here
Pretty neat thank you
And yeah I mean it took us a year to get this together at 2 to negotiate that contract with carriers and we had to go through
The ups and downs of
Who's the right person at this organization I had a lot of phone calls where I'm talking to somebody who
Clearly was not the right person I talked to the wrong person at every carrier 20 times before I talk to the right person
I got hung up on at least one
You have someone who is
Upset that we weren't doing things the way that they said that we were supposed to do them
And it was got that figured out how we can pass it off for customers
You don't have to do all internet to go through all this pain you're not to do this yourself would just taking care of a cellular plan
And now you can go and it works everywhere and it's affordable and you can just ship your product and not worry about it
No one has to hang up on you guys
So you guys
Started with a crowdfunding
For this product
We did did that help
Actually
I'm assuming that helps like get you to the right
People initials
So
We spend
About a year
Talking
Carriers in the US
Trying to figure out who's the right partner to
To do
This product
With
Let me talk to Oliver
And
Again we sometimes talk to the right person we sometimes talk to the wrong person
It's hard to figure out
Do you know who had some plan
Work for what we're trying to do
And we got to the point where we were ready the hardware was ready
And we had a plan from
Carrier
And it was
Good night
It's all time of our problems but not other problems
It was a starting point
And we said you know what
We're about to go on Kickstarter and launch this to the world
And we know from our previous experience
Doing Kickstarter campaign
Did you get a lot of visibility
Bed
Corporate
People
That you want to talk to are watching Kickstarter they're trying to see what's going on out there so we had this idea that maybe
Once we launched this campaign
Do we get phone calls from the right people at the right carriers
They can help us figure out the right
Truss
We launched our Kickstarter campaign
And within the three days after launch
Every major carrier
North American in Europe
In European called me
And said
We like to power this product
Until we're in a great position we got to negotiate with multiple carriers got to figure out who's the right partner
And we got to build a platform that gives us Global coverage around the world
I'm at an affordable rate because of the visibility that we got with that crowd funny
Okay and
I'll do this for you so you don't have to feel too hard that you
Have to pitch this but
Right now you've got
Coverage for this product
So if I if I did this
I want to build a product with
The electron
I've got a virgin over a hundred countries
Some of the carriers that you say are involved are telefonica AT&T T-Mobile
Most of those are names I've heard of
Yep
Maybe not
And this is a $39
Cantar board
Basically
Bertucci
$59 for 3-g
And I will say
What do you think the odds are of getting a
T4g
Version
Will get there
So right now
It's really interesting three spectrums that people are playing with you at 2G 3G 4G and of course there's the whole CDMA vs.
Gsmst
The types of applications that we support this is low bandwidth stuff so we're doing sensors and actuators a lot of a lot of times it's
Reading temperature data off of a sensor
Once a day and uploading it to the internet and so
I don't really care about band
2 G is plenty
But
2G has issues being sunset in the US
I was going to say 2 G is about to leave
Right and this is a this is a problem
It's very unfortunate for
Internet of Things
That teaches going away because most of us just need to cheat now it's not going away yeah in
Overseas in places like Europe
But that's a factor
SO3 G really only matters from
Perspective
Compatibility making sure that it works and will continue to work
Years
But of course then the whole world is going to hell
How to eat an LTE is the future but I'll see chips are ungodly expensive right
Even the ones that are designed for iot
I'm at least twice as expensive as the 3-g ones which are more than twice as expensive as the 2G ones
So
Right now we're focusing on 2G 3-g we're waiting for the chips to get cheap to do to do LTE and as soon as they're uh
Affordable we're going to make that leap and bring our customers with us
Baidu
Right now
LTE doesn't a lot of value
It just creates a lot of costing and so we're waiting to for that to change
Well let me ask you because
You know there's LTE
The current versions that we have right now that I use on my phone which
Maximizing
Capacity
Now everybody calls it something different so
There's lte-advanced
There's 5G
Version feltie design for the internet of things that would you
Skip kind of the current LTE that is in our phones for using those kind of chips
It depends it depends on how fast it happens because at the end of the day
We're about enabling
People to go build products today
And I'm excited about a lot of the stuff is coming down the pipe and there are really good
New Solutions designed for
Lowering power consumption
For lowering lowering on the ship
Flooring
Bandwidth costs
But
There's multiple options we don't really know which of the variety of
Future
Protocols is going to win
LTE so much more complicated Spectrum it looks from the outside
And I think as a consumer you look at it and say
Before there was GSM and CDMA at least in the US
And now thank God we're on the same protocol LTE cuz now it that makes the world a lot simpler
Behind the
3 letters LTE that a lot of complexity there's different bands
There's different categories
Categories generally are a band with sitting so hot like cat
Cat6 cat7
That's high-bandwidth cat 0 cat 1 that's that's low bandwidth
But so
There's pieces of Lte that are built
Best expensive
And the question is are those pieces that are built in to get cheaper
Before
The
Future protocol is designed for iot
Actually get
Completed and
Deployed and are usable
And so
Right now we're just basically saying
We're going to keep our eye on it
If you're doing a project today
It should probably be 3-g if it's in the US and 2G if it's in Europe
And
Just go for that and
We'll keep our eye on it and let everybody know when the next Generation stuff is ready for consumption
Okay question
Animal skit office
Esoteric
But I have to ask are you guys looking at any of the low power
Wide area network
Standards
Like
What's a foxes doing like Laura or any of those other things
We are and I think it's really interesting
I think that there is really great
Applications I'm really skeptical of national rollouts
So you know sigfox isn't has as well. In some countries in Europe
Laura is being rolled on some countries in Europe
And everybody
Looks at the US
As this
Giant country with a kind of empty middle
And also really exists really expensive to deploy new radios on to cell towers here because of the economic model
So
Everyone looks and says we're going to do National deployment I will get to us someday
And that's a problem has a huge market and
That's often where these products into played first so
I'm keeping my eye on it
For sure and I think that themselves the things like
Are really interesting regardless of whether they're deployed on a national networks they don't have to be
They can deploy with more of a DIY bring your own
Gateway Tower kind of
Deployment Racine that start to happen already so I am very interested in that I'm keeping my eye on it
As we think about our roadmap
Radios peruanas support in the future
Stephen something we're looking very hard at
Informa economics
Perspective
For your business
It doesn't necessarily you don't need to sell
Tens of millions of your product
Like for each radio you support
Yes or no
No I mean we we can make it work we can make our Economics work for any kind of
Any kind of radio is different
For sure that the way that we
Cellular has this bacon data plan
That makes the economics work in a certain way
And you have to buy data
Another soul
Redefines the the the economics of a cellular base product
Wi-Fi
Bialy
Zigbee thread
Laura
Sigfox
There's more flexibility that was more wiggle room
So you can
Decide to make different decisions about how you monetize those products
Totally sure how we would charge for
But
Will figure it out
There we go alright
Let's move back to the electron which is the name of this product
But you're lunching
And
Let's talk about you got about 200 in the field
Expedia customer
So
What are people doing with it
It's a lot more industrial vet
Products we were exposed to previously
Sew weave
Had for a couple years now
Wifi-connected development platform
And that means the people are building
Consumer Home Products a lot of smart home pet toys gardening systems
Things that are consumer applications we had
I think 22 companies have now launched products on Kickstarter or Indiegogo that have been funded
Platform Figueroa yams
Mostly under NDA
That do
Appliances and security systems and things like that
But
With cellular
The customers are a lot more industrial so the types of things people are building our
Monitoring expensive equipment
On manufacturing lines
And
Oil rigs
Controlling
Huge industrial water pumps and motors and
Irrigation systems on farms and
Distributed sensor Networks
Municipal applications
Garbage cans street lights
You know it's a huge array of products and very different
From what we saw on the
Wifi sign
And it's really only have 200 out there so
It's still pretty small number of applications were being exposed to
But now we have 10000 that are on their way to customers
Today
And
They will arrive and will have
Orders of magnitude more people building stuff over the next three months is winter really going to learn what are people doing
What do they need this for
Why are they doing it
And how can we help them be successful
Have you seen differences in
Data patterns over cellular vs wifi
Yeah
You're paying for every bite that you sent
And so it really changes the way that the
People think about sending messages
With Wi-Fi
If you have a limit
And we we we rate limit our devices to send messages 1
1 per second on average
So a lot of people just go straight up
Publishing a message once per second and their graphing that and that's totally fine
End
Good cost for
The inbound and outbound data into AWS will be to play our stuff it's
Yeah it's really not a big deal it's pretty cheap
Siler's expensive
And so
Lemons for the customer they have to
Think how often do I want this thing to actually send a receive
Receive messages
It's expensive for
Potato plants expensive for power
And so
We see a lot more applications where it's sleeping for a long time
Maybe waking up sending a message once a day going back to sleep so that it can last for months or with a small
Solar panel can last forever
And cost
Couple box per month
For really low bandwidth plans are the types of things we see people doing with cellular
And we've built a lot of stuff into a platform to make it easy to optimize so we've worked
Really hard to
Take down
The bandwidth
For encryption
So all of our messages are encryption secured is a huge part of what we do
We don't want customers to have to worry about whether something is encrypted or not but you pay for encryption it costs you money in van with v
Because
There's a handshake that has to happen there is
Keys that have to be sent
And those cost money
So we've done a lot of
Tweaks to our
Protocol
To reduce the overhead of conscription so you can have secure Communications but not pay more
Or not pay much more than you would if it were
Unsecured
Got it
Okay and then with these beta customers that you've had so far
I'm sure coming back and talking to you in a couple months would be really interesting
How to change from
Encryption but what else have you changed it
One of the other changes another
Efficiency trade-off
We changed our protocol from TCP to UDP in this is
Kind of esoteric that actually mean something
Important
TCP and UDP are two of the most commonly used
Basic Protocols of the web TCP is
Is it socket connection it means that we're we can confirm there were talking to one another
EDP soccer
You can come and go as more of a transient communication
And Eustis has been with because you don't have to acknowledge every message that sent you can just kind of
Type stuff out
If you think of web websites or use RC
Through TCP because
You ensure that all the data from the website gets to your
Browser
Skype
Is done over UDP
Because if you miss a couple bits here and there
You can
Take it on the back end
I'd like a stream of video or audio
So
We switched our protocol to use UDP to save on bandwidth but what that means is we used to tell people
Weather device
Online or offline
And with UDP that idea goes away
So
Is it online or offline right now is actually a hard question to answer
Because all you can really do is
Send a message to be like
Hey by the way are you still there is someone listening to this but that cost been with so you try not to send this message
So
We've had to change some of the ways we communicate
For customers
What's happening with your device
Because of this new world that were living and we were trying to save every penny
For them
Oh that's he that makes me feel like
Deeply sad feels
It feels so terrible that
It cost so much
It feels like you're giving up so much
Right
So I guess I want to talk to your customers
How do you deal with that
Cuz it feels like such a sacrifice
The products that make sense
They're more products that make sense
If the technology underneath it is cheaper
If it cost twenty bucks to connect a product the internet there's only so many things you can connect
If it's $10 to get a lot more interesting products it's $5 more so
$1
Now we start to get into world where everything
Things connected and of course Moore's laws pushing us there on the chip side
Matters to
And
It becomes an important trade-off when people are trying to build cool stuff
But they're paying for everything that happens
Applications might be economically infeasible
If they're sending a certain amount of data
But
Feasible if they can get below that threshold
So we work hard to push people below the threshold as low as possible
Affordable as we can
Do more people access to the tech
Archie and to enable more products
No I get it I'm just like
Indesit this is one of those classic
This is one reason why I feel like
Low power
Wide area networks are going to be
I'm not a huge believer in them because I fundamentally believe that once you give people connectivity
And eventually the cost will go down
People are knocking at people to be like why
What is the value of a sensor that wakes up once a day and reports its shadow
When you could have something that wakes up
Five times a day
What's a test or
Report status + you know
Grabs this other day that it can
Also grab
You know and I'm just like
Or replace it once a second
Because I can't
So
That's that's just me cuz no one ever says
I got an update I think
True and I want this to work like
In my mind this works like a w a square
You just kind of the prices come down every year
And you just get an email from AWS once every 6 months that says hey Kyle cheaper
And now at this point anyone has deployed stuff on Amazon for the last couple years is just used to it if you don't get that email you get upset
Why didn't the price come down there
So I want this stuff to work that same way I want to be sending my customers emails
Are regular basis and saying
By the way this is cheaper now so you can do more.
I'm and I'm going to work very hard
Make sure that we're always offering the most affordable
Solution
So we can get more products
Connected to the internet
That comes through
Continuing to
Negotiate with carriers weather
Through further optimizations we make in our Tech stack
Through adopting new radio as they become available
Like future of Alta Vista
Low-power Wireless area networking
Whatever it might be
What's the sooner we can get to the world where connections are free
The more the internet of things really becomes a reality
I think Amazon gets to that because Jeff Bezos built his own
Infrastructure
Civilian servers scattered around the world
If you want to get to that
Think
You need to
Telco Network or
I need to replace Randall Stephenson over at AT&T with someone else who
Has that same
Single and drive cuz I don't think he wakes up in the morning and
How can I lower the cost all of my customers
Write what you know
What starting to let us do those things is that we have the developers so we now have 60,000 developers in engine
Our community their building stuff on a platform that never gets bigger every day
And in this industry
Internet of things we have the most
People building stuff we've been most people who are on our forums with the most people building projects and sharing them with one another
And
That's becoming really powerful Leverage
In talking with carriers and having those negotiations it's fundamentally what allowed us to do this in the first place that's what made the electron
Work from the kickstarter
And now we have more and more people and we can go to the cares and say
Look at what I've got look at these developers that I can bring to you
Don't you want these people building products on your platform you need to work with me to get these rates down
I really
I really do
I want
More connected devices in more places and I want the coolest things and I know that they're going to build it on stuff like
I know they're going to build it on the electron
It's you know the power of the developer it's any you see it happening everywhere
Look at the investment that
Intel is making into
They're like 13 of the developer tools
Like the Addison Carey
Semiconductor companies telcos
All of the companies you look at his
Old-fashioned dinosaurs
Are waking up to the power of the developer and
It's just starting to happen but I think over the next couple years going to happen even more
Hope you're right
Thank you so much for coming on the picat
Today thanks for having me
Thank you for listening and please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast