Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
I am your host
Higginbotham and
This is my co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a great show for you we're going to start with Fitness tracking information we're going to do a review of two products the
Xiaomi outdoor light
And the rachio
Connected sprinkler
We're going to talk about
A possible deal for
Control
So let's get started Kevin
I purchased
Fitness tracker
Yes
Tell tell people what you bought
First because you did not get yours yet you ordered it I actually have two in my hand so what did you buy
I bought the Under Armour
Healthbox
You recommended last week
Week 4
Father's Day special in the reason I did it
Because I have been looking
SportsCenter looking at it
Since it launched
I got a $40 off
Promo code for UnderArmour
Because I'm at my fitness
Sam
Yes we say
And there it was already $50 off in the store so I got a total of 90 bucks off I don't know what that's going to
Astilbe
Available to People by the time this run
Right
The $50 off was
The way it was
So you don't have it yet but as I mentioned last week I wouldn't recommend it if I didn't like it and I do like it
I haven't
I think what you'll appreciate and we can talk about
Why does the port in a few minutes
I think you'll appreciate the whole view that they give you
Of your health meaning
If you wear the tracker in the heart rate monitor and use the scale
Obviously getting your weight body fat
Getting your steps
Your sleep
Activity
Because they own map my
Fitness and also MapMyRun
You can track your nutrition at MyFitnessPal
Sinks in nicely so you get a nice dashboard
In there app for IOS and Android
It's complete I love that I love that the reason I'm not using it
Is because they don't have like a GPS tracking device which I like to use when I run
I like my maps and whatnot and I've got seven years of data in RunKeeper all the map information and elevation and
Anyway that's why I'm not using it but I love it I think you're going to love it too but when I guess we'll find out in a week or two
We will it arrives on when
So cool
Okay so I actually did go out and purchase to fitness trackers
In two days
Over the past weekend
One's going back already
Tell you what I bought and why is my back and then leading to the bigger picture here because I'm going to get cranky in a few minutes about Health Data
So I bought the Samsung Gear Fit
Which looks very much like a Microsoft band it's it's
Pretty slim in Felton
Has a beautiful display and I love the harder
Just it just launched last week I got it like the day it came out and $179
It does
Work with any Android phone
Android 4.4 better and I said that because
Previous Samsung
Wearables on the first timeout only work with Samsung phones which was a
Terrible no no shame on Samsung for that
Twitter iOS user this is pretty much useless to you as well
So
I used it for a day and I will like the hardware the software is okay
It pretty much tracks everything is got a optical heart rate monitor
Scott GPS Senate even though it's
Pretty small
It actually can store 1000 songs
Turn on Bluetooth
It really nice
Sleep information was kind of like
The reasons going back
Has to do with my bigger picture
I'm going to get cranky now
S-health is the software that uses
Samsung S Health
Until a few days ago S Health really didn't work with any other services
I say until a few days ago because it wasn't update to S Health
I just Friday last week I believe where they share data with Microsoft Misfit RunKeeper and Strava
But here's my issue
And this may not be a problem for you Stacy cuz you're all in one package
Record
I am calling for a global
Mobile Health Data standards
Because all of these different
Applications all these trackers Ali services
They all want to own the data themselves
Occasionally
Some of them let you export your data manually which is great
Some of them sink to some Services some of them don't seem to others
And even when some a service or tracker says it syncs with something
It
You want to check the fine print because only certain things go
Get synced over property example
S-health actually does sync over to Fitbit
But all it stinks over is steps
To all of my
Calories burned my
Tracking my activities
None of that goes
They say it's thanks but just
This bit
Guess you better
Okay so this actually ties in cuz our guest this week is it for Desta Ramirez who is actually a
Public Health
PhD who did research on this so wonderful about why this matters
What's happening
But
What about
Something like healthkit
Cuz that's kind of what
IOS only
Right ok Google as Google Fit which actually is IOS and Android if I'm not mistaken it's Andrew and obviously
But frankly
It just doesn't track enough information and does not sync reliably for me I was thinking
Data over to Google Fit And it's like 4-5 days it would show nothing and then all of a sudden it would show like
Three days worth of stuff
It's just not reliable enough for me I mean I know other people use it
Google fits great if you don't even have a Tracker because your phone is your tracker
And in that case maybe it works well but I have dedicated trackers
Because I need more than what my phone gives me Android don't want to carry my phone everywhere
So you write how get it supposed to be that book of record Google Fit is supposed to be that book of records
Microsoft has their healthvault
The problem is
It's still very segmented peep
Still want to own the data
You know what it does not get any more personal than my personal Hell Date I should own the data
And be able to use anything I want and make it work
Because I have a broken toe for the last 4 weeks
Really disappointing
Bye
Jawbone software it is like
Stacy
Okay I'm like
I think I should be an injury
Itsfunneh
It's funny you say that because there is in your Under Armour app if you're going to have you can log a day as a rest day so you won't get mad
It's beautiful
You can you can you have
Now every time.
Consider that rest
We also I forgot to mention I also got a Fitbit Aria scale because my daughter has a Fitbit
And I just figured it was an easier thing to do is just at 1 skip
Then again it's getting the data from one map to the other
So we're on the Aria scale
Automat my
Yeah
Scale data
REI
It does so eat you will find things duesing but you got to
Don't assume everything will sink when somebody says it sent but you are correct
You can get your your weight data
Into other apps through MapMyFitness
Okay
I just hope this will be big for me
Cuz like I've never owned a scale
All right with that
So
New news
No actually read reviews first
Because
Sorry about this I mentioned this on a couple podcast ago
This is the first
Color rated outdoor
It's a par38 downlight
Yeah out there
Set a resistant all water resistant
And super water resistant
Because it's actually rained like 9 in
Since I put it up
And my uncovered roof
It is in a
So it's in a lighting fixture so the lighting pic
What it is
Because of the radios that are in it
It is a little bit more sensitive to moisture and dirt and stuff
So this is been up on my roof
For about
Two weeks now
This is the ilumi Outdoor rated color
BR30
It's $70
$60 is
Running rate for you-know-what connected light bulb
That's color
And it uses Bluetooth
Not to be
Bluetooth light bulb
And
It's been out there it's been like
Raining a lot it's super hot on my roof
Cuz I'm in Texas it's been like 95° outside
You know it hasn't made it through the 110 degree heat but you know
It's still pretty good
So
I really
Enjoy the illumise
They
Make a nice green
B Hughes don't actually do it
The green at all
And it has a fun feature
Where
You could do typical scene-setting in that sort of thing but they have a music setting which for my roof where we hold a lot of parties and stuff
Secret to
Spotify
Or Google Play
I hear your phone so what happens is and on your iOS device it will actually sync to download
That is
The music thing and what happens if you play this on your phone
And the lights
Go intermittent times
The downside is
If I
Because it doesn't work with Sonos switch
Speaker system I have on the
I would have to turn the volume down on my phone
Cuz it's not actually pulling for the volume
Are from the actual physical sound
Turn the volume
I can get the same kind of party
Experience
Fancy I
Sink a little
Like disco effect
And you're not really worried about the
You could do the same thing
Yeah since it's Bluetooth radio inside these there's you don't need a hub this works on the app
It does so here's where things get a little bit
Because it's on my roof which is really far away from the rest of my stuff
It's setup a Bluetooth mesh Network
But
Right now I don't have an
I don't have any other ilumi lights anywhere in the house so I have to actually go in my second floor and kind of Stand Out On The Roof
Like a little bit on the terrorist I don't have to climb the pole stairs but
To turn it on
Gotcha
Limited limited range of Bluetooth and it would help if you had other devices other
Illumise cuz she said it would be mashed
So that is your downside
There's no way to make them work with any Hub but she might therefore Place little closer to them or no
I don't see that is not an option I
Now there are Bluetooth hubs out there
The
Mesh they're using
I should have checked this way
I will find out what mesh there
I don't know if it's the standard
Richard Smash Hit
Is tomorrow cuz I'm not sure if that's actually
Implemented yet is a
Tortoise and
I know that it's been talked about
I don't know that everyone
Got that out there
Right
Right now
I can't I can't control it from anywhere except for within woot
What is range
Of the light bulb itself
Your mileage may vary
Outside
I mean I think it's
The color is
Ed
Udo having having the ability to turn your outside
You know your porch light or whatever this color
Is just fine
What do your neighbors think of this
My neighbors know I'm
All right
Let's say we should talk about a bit about news of the week before
Skipping to
Another review this time for the rachio 2nd gen sprinkler
That my
My father-in-law is going to help us
And I don't
Oh I do I'm getting away from that lawn and
Right you're leaving here line
Leaving one acre behind
Let's talk about
You got something from Domino's
Yeah I thought this was kind of interesting I mean it's a little less irth but still smart devices
Domino's is actually testing
A on time cooking service for pick up customers
Basically they're going to use the GPS
To track where you are
On the way to pick up your pizza
And it really going to make the Peter start making it when you're close enough to the store so that way it is as fresh as pause
Possible literally
Custom made for you at a specific time based on your location so
If you're going to Domino's pick up a pizza and using the service you know don't make any side trips
You're going to
Hours of the pizza
Delivery
Because
They're going to make it in a computer
But I thought was kind of needles it's a start use of GPS
It is and other most people probably
Well maybe people order p
Pizza delivery on the way home I'm trying to think about the use case cuz
I usually order
Pizza when I'm already home
Driving from someplace to someplace then I just
Pick it up yes yes and actually use you still will pick it up but once you order it
Oh
They won't make it until you get close enough so that it's guaranteed so to speak fresh
They're trying to cut down there the time to actually making and they want pizza sitting around
They want them fresh for you when you get there
Don't know that because they'll see you so to speak on your way to pick it up
And oh no it takes us 7 1/2 minutes to make this pizza
Stacy is 7 1/2 minutes to get that thing in the oven
I guess it doesn't occur to me to actually
Stop and pick up a Domino's
Because
I cannot say that I we just we don't have one nearby it's like 10 miles away so
Yeah there's two people to do a common thing there's a coffee cup
Today in austin texas that call briggo
And they have a
Robot coffee maker on the UT campus that
When you it uses your GPS to know when to start making your coffee
Similar things
Other news
Last week I reported
That
Comcast and alarm.com are in talks to buy icontrol
What's going to happen is they're going to split I control into two bits
I am control
Flight control actually became
They control
That is the
News we should hear hopefully something on that in the neck
And it sounds like a deal that
Basically I control when they they
Put out some products
This is part of the kind of DIY effort
That seemed to confuse their customers cuz I controls customer base was companies like ATT and Comcast
Xfinity home
And I control
Would manage the backend software for
You started putting out products that were
They bought Piper which is an all-in-one security device
And then they introduced on the call Touchstone which was helping diyre setup
They're kind of home secure
Dirty stuff
And I probably
I'm imagining it best confuse their customers were like High
These products compete now with our product
What's happening
So
They've been kind of having some issues and some of their customers have not upgraded to
New contracts with them or added new devices with them
I'm so
Sounded like I control was having
I should note that
Because of recording schedules we are not going to be talking about what was announced it Apple's event
Cuz I type in a few hours from now
It's happening soon
We won't put this out for awhile in
Kevin is on the road
Because Kevin is
A man in demand
On the road all day and cross-country trips today in about an hour but
Before packing a lot I was paying attention to E3 which is the
Video game Electronics conference that's going on right now it's kinda like the CES of electronic video games
And I noticed
Late last night as I was watching the live stream
Tiaras getting a healthy nod
In the form of actual games on consoles with VR headsets
I think the HTC Vive will actually be supported by Bethesda software
And they are the makers of and
These are not kids games
I'm working it out
The makers of Doom
And Fallout 4
Both of which they were demonstrating in VR you can actually go where VR goggles and play the games
I thought you were out there in LA which I was not but
I just thought it was very interesting that the VR as we will
Boom right
From the center there it was at that III so it'll be interesting to watch
We'll keep an eye out
Alright well Kevin thanks so much
Let's see I think we will
Skip to our rachio review now and then stay tuned after that for our guest
Who is Ernesto Ramirez
Talking about public health
Data actually
Medical data and Public Health
As I mentioned before I'm bringing my father-in-law Gregg Allman on the show to talk about his
Experience with the rachio sprinkler
Where is I do not
So we saw this about 6 weeks ago and
The install process would you think
Steelers very simple Acts
Promise of the rachio is that it takes your old kind of dumb
Irrigation controls in Dad's kind of a wifi-connected
System that
Look at the weather forecast
We need to water we don't need to water it also takes into consideration, the type of
You can remotely control
Your Zone
What goes off at what time
So overall Greg
After living with this
What do you think
I think it is an excellent approach
Frankfort water
I
Think that
As good as the other measurements that are available
And in that regard about some issues
Nothing yet
Having mind
Home location not being too consistent with the weather station data that I'm
Ah-So
Your weather station how far away is
Does a mile and a half
All right and you told me that you had had
One day where it was
At your place in
0 according to Ranchos measure
Correct
Now you can connect sensors via if this then that
Put your own weather station in Leica netatmo woodwork
Or you could also add like
Moisture sensor
Jennifer soil
I think there's actually a connection for that but you don't have any of those things
Do you think it's safe
Yuan
Why would raisins
Certainly is contrasted
To just letting it
We're in one of those water areas where
The city says you can only water on these days so you have
Set that up
And then rocchio resident deciding which date
Side skip or not
Always a trainee.
So it's skip quite a bit
And therefore I've been saving money
I'm in my alternative in the past
That part is handled and if I'm away from home
It's only handled where I couldn't otherwise
Best Russo like
I think you were out of town for like a week
A couple weeks ago
We were out
It was raining
That's correct
But I did get messages
I was saying okay peace of mind and that way you got a little link to the weather back home
All right and what are the downsides like I know
Some trouble
Honda Wi-Fi
That is
Screw you do need a
Strong enough WiFi connection
30 weeks
Corner of the garage or waves
My router
We got it up
To turn onto it
Call three blues
But then I found out that I was getting messages but Russia was
Offline
And so I can put it that
Intermittently at least disconnect
Be quiet
So that's on the Wi-Fi
So I did Remedy by getting up
Stronger range extender in the new location in sunset time
It's been steady
All right
So the big question
The rachio 8 zone is $200 and the 16th
Is $250
When I take this away to send it back to rachio
Would you buy another one
What what you doing
Certainly has to also think through the other sensor situation because
In our local condition I think the make it
Really
A good performing
Item
I'd have to put in some sort of local sensor
But it's enough of a savior
In terms of not having
And having that
Remote access I guess for testing sprinkler heads
Isn't that kind of thing
All right well that's great now I know it's get your Father's Day so
And for the rest of you guys
You also
Because after this
We are going to be back with the Ernesto Ramirez talking about what to do with wearable data's and privacy and Public Health
Greater break into the podcast for a message from Wolf SSL here I've got Larry stefanik who is this
CEO
Larry who is
Wolf SSL
Stacy worthy experts on device security we've been working in the space for the last decade
We're now the most widely deployed security solution
For the iot with over a billion devices secured at this point
That is a lot
Devices
What goes into
Securing an iot device
So we think about three key things first of all
The data in transit or the data between your device
And your cloud
So the the traditional are most popular way
To secure that data is through
The SSL protocol which is the protocol that is used
Unrest of the internet for securing
Data in transit
We also think a lot about
Securing data on the device itself
So encrypting data that you might have on your device that uses
Needs to be private
And it finally we help companies secure their firmware updates
It's one of the clever things that attackers like to do two devices is installed their firmware instead of year
So what you need to do is have a secure Channel
To your device the best way to do that the most common way to do that is through
SSL
And we do all of the above that's what we do
4Runner smart grid where in automotive Industrial Automation consumer devices
In medical devices and we address this wide range of markets through a long list of Partnerships that we
We have with the silicone vendors in that the operating system vendors
Alright was everywhere
Where can we find
So just check us out and wolf ssl.com coyote
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Ernesto Ramirez
Quiz a program director for the Quantified Self lab
He's also a PhD and Pub
Very recently
Congratulation
Thank you
And he's written about
Connected devices for The Last 5 Years
Zoe super-smart Ernesto
Thank you for coming on the show The
Picture of an excited to be here
Me too so I met Ernesto
Go to South by Southwest event
Was right after Apple introduced healthkit
And he was talking about what this
Gave to the medical community and how they might do something like
And I was just
Smitten
Smitten with his ideas
Let's talk about
Wearables
And Health Data
Big picture
What should I be thinking about
This space
What's the Big Apple
I think
They're almost
I wouldn't say there's
Limitless opportunities
What's available and what's possible with wearable but I think
We haven't
Quite scene
You know we see lots of things like
Step counters Eagle on your wrist
Hot reminders now that you can wear on your wrist
But I think the interesting thing that's going to happen
When these type of devices start talking to each other
And there's devices Note 8 screen start talking to other
Like the things in your home
Like your car
Like your medical record
Okay so like
CII know that I talked to somebody who
Kind of devices for monitoring people who are aging in place and they were talking about using
Censored on the bathroom door
Assess someone's
Health
Because apparently there's a correlation
Those are the kind of things that you're talking about
Exactly so
Yo I'm more connected future
What are the things that I
I think would be exciting this is something I'm still looking for someone
Hopefully one day I'll have enough money to buy it
If my bathroom scale
An my wearable device to understand all of my fitness
Can talk to my kitchen
That's what magic can really start to happen
So secrets in Seattle
Getting a lot of weight
I'm not very good at tracking my diet
What kitchen do what kind of food I had you can recommend the meals that I
Can make
No regionals and I'm ready to be physically active
Am I a technical standpoint I think will be really interesting to see in the future
My freezer would never let me at the ice
I know it
You haven't exercised
Enough
She want to lose those last 5 pounds
The answer is no
This is a great vision
Let's talk about the where we are today
It feels like I am inundated with
Studies showing that like my Fitbit isn't accurate was the most recent one
My Fitbit data into one of my doctors and they're like
Stacy I do not want to see that I don't care
So let's talk about how do we get this into the medical sphere or should we even
Get it into the medical sphere
That's a great question I think
Future
Which is a very very interesting question because it starts to get
Yelp
Try to ask yourself what
You know what is a Stafford what is the heart rate
And you have to really ask
What are these things
Could store and Bear
Even your bathroom
Stop medical device
Haven't gone through
That's rigorous FDA clearance process
Required of the things that we
We can't trim clinical
Actually I think
Fairly accurate the things that they say they do
And then
Once we decide whether or not they are accurate
Useful for what kind of day today
Getting them to talk to the medical record
It's a huge conversation and it's
So
Let's see how do we get them to
To talk to
A medical record cuz most of those are kind of proprietary they're locked up there
HIPAA compliance stairs
So what is this future world of
Look like
There's two pieces
What you just said that are super important
How do we get this data
Into the system
Which is not a insurmountable
Although there are closed system
But you had your ethics in your cerner's
Electronic medical record providers
They are starting to be
More open to allowing data from other places
That's me, text
Is a
Not easy thing to do but it's not something that's going to be impossible
The social tees I think is even more interesting and
Probably orders of magnitude more important
Anti-social onion is how do we get the medical system
All the way down the line
All of those providers the position
The nurses
Assistant
To understand the type of information that people are using in the course of their everyday lives
How can I use that for actually impacting that character.
And so far we've actually seen this
Happen in a couple of instances there was the
The famous case where
Some guy 42 year old man cave
Commando hospital after I believe it was a seizure
They used his Fitbit data so it feels like and I don't know if that's
Indicative of more to come
Is that
I don't know what do you think
Because I have something wrong with her heart rate
Know if we will chat
The wearable throughout their right
Now what are they measuring
What do people actually do anything
Health and wellness spaces
And then they're measuring what they eat
And those three things
Really add up to
I'm major in Canada to having a major impact on
Chronic disease
United States and worldwide
Edison could figure out a way to actually make that part of
You can have the conversation of hay
We noticed that
You know you haven't gone for a run or gone to the gym or you haven't got more than 5,000
Going on
How can you be helpful
Yes I actually have a friend that I share my fitness data with
And
A couple weeks ago I actually
Dislocated my
Sounds ridiculous but
I've been walking around in this boot
And I haven't been able to walk as much so
She actually sent me a text and she was like
Dude what is up with your barely making 4000 steps a day
You may not believe this but
Part of my dissertation research was
Talking to people about their experiences using
Talking to someone about their physical activity for what's going on your life
Is not actually that uncommon
We do it all the time
See that's so how do we
Take something like that
And make it I mean that that is kind of interesting if your doctor like even if it was an automated text
About something like that
To you I don't know how
How would you turn that into something
Good for health
There's a good example of people doing
Stuff like that
Nothing
PeopleNet
A company in San Francisco
What they did is they took
Clinically
Statistically significant
On obesity
And overall health
And they took that basically said let's just make this thing and now they're showing the same
We can make a difference
You can stay called yesterday
Base of a program that was developed a while ago
Without these
Schools
That being said
I don't think that that
It's going to be probably the case
Overall I don't think magically everyone's going to
Because
Well what happened
If there's data
Inside your physical activity tracker
Sitting in your weight scale
And that shows that something might actually wrong with you that they nest know what are the
Cactus plants
That's something else I don't think any of us know yet
What my doctor didn't see my heart attack coming on my
Fitbit charge
Exactly this is the world we live in
Stop
That information
You know what's weird is that responsibility
That's worrisome
Let's switch a little too
Another use case for wearables
Cuz we talked about it mostly in the medical sense
Switch
Yeah but there's also an option
And players are keeping their employees
Fitbit sore jaw bones and
That opens up a can of worms on the Privacy side
I'd love to talk to you about
Kind of this the day that we're collecting
Privacy
What it means when
Your employer is asking you to wear what
Starting to give
Their employees devices
As part of these corporate Wellness
Plant or subsidized
Weight scalar or what-have-you
And then as part of Wellness Lee makes it up
Petition
North Central College
Corporate Wellness
And
It remains to be seen on way or what
What do we have a right to enter
Privacy around
Best Health Data Networks tracking you know it's not maybe as
Privacy Centric as blood testing results
But it's not
Nothing
You know it could be used against us for whatever reason
What might happen in the future
Sure I can see I think there was an article in the Wall Street Journal that talk to I think it was
Shrp
They had this crazy anecdote
It was hypothetical
If you saw that one of your salespeople
Slept really well last night versus the other one who had
Like 2 hours of sleep
Seem to be lagging
You would choose the one that got more sleep to make the big pitch tomorrow
And I thought that was a really interesting
Example because you know there are plenty of people
Who is he of course she would give you know this person who's
More physically fit
To do something like that but that doesn't take into account all kinds of extraneous things like maybe they have a newborn at home and
Maybe they're still really awesome at pitching
Even when it had 2 hours of sleep
Cuz people tend to make correlations about things
Without actually
Having the root cause
I get what you're saying at the end of the day
Whatever you know you're wearing one of these things
You're using your phone to track your active
Heads up
Zeros and ones in the database that's some kind of information
It doesn't really know who you are if you can't
Tell who I am
Employee and just because
I took
Steps one day and 10000 the next
I don't know
I might make some
There's a Reddit article and it was confirmed
Of Fitbit being able to anticipate somebody being pregnant
I'm just based on I think it was her heart rate
That was really interesting because
My employer's of all been very cool
About people getting pregnant but you know there's plenty out there who are not
And if someone could see something like that
Especially before the employee told them they could fire them right away and not run afoul of any sort of
Can people from fire
These are not
Crazy farfetch
Maybe
Definitely not and I think it does kind of
Who makes the case for us being careful
And how we use these devices
Where this data goes what decisions make about it
There was actually it is
Remind me there's a great example of
Tesco in the UK
I put device tracking devices on their users basically RFID tags
And how much
Where do we going in the warehouse
Expect too much time
In the restroom
That is the other
Utopia
So what do you recommend I mean like
Let's take it from a variety of different
Perspectives
From the perspective of a fitness tracking
How should they be thinking about these
Is a privacy
All of the things
What's your advice
I think
Whoever it is it's always think of the individual
Using the system
Yo
A person that that bought
Or is strapped on
That device on the wrist
For the person who
And who's wearing it
That's true
Is it to get the end of the day it is always going to be the person that
Excuse
Where is haneda originating
And you don't
It whether or not your employer pot it for you
Or your grandma
If you're wearing it
You are the originator of that data and that at the end of the day
Needs to be
You to understand that they can trust
Whatever entity
Is making the right decision
So that
They are protective
In terms of their privacy
But also I think
You know I'm a big proponent of data access
It's actually quicker
Privacy is being able to actually have access
Should the information that you're creating and contributing to these huge data system
So I think as long as people are are taking those
Taking those ideas to Heart
I think you could look pretty good place
Okay and what about
Regulators so if I'm a lawmaker and I'm
Looking at these cases
What needs to change about how we manage the stuff
Should be done be looking at like what HR is doing
Like I said I'm a proponent for Access I think we should have some sort of legal structure that sets up
Are rice
To access the data
We are collecting
So
Lafayette Indiana weather.
You'll be able to go online and get a CSV download
Or
Being able to understand where that data is flowing
The way data flows right now is
Is just a weird tricky jumble of
Contract
Negotiations that we never see
I think having that open up
Especially with this deeply personal data
It needs to be taken care of at the legal level
Okay so what would your advice to
The businesses
Who are buying
Wearables
I think my number one piece of advice
Protect
And
I think
What is it
Things that people could do to protect our users
Make sure people have access to their data
And like I said
Especially because
This is it still the Wild Wild West
In terms of like wearables
Devices in companies you know every day you hear about
1 feeling are going out of business because they feel they couldn't make enough money to keep the lights on
And then crazy things are happening
Either they just
Turn off the light
Shut down the servers
And that day.
Gone
And the people that use that device for
Six months or a year or a decade
Never going to be able to see it again
Or
That device in that data that IP the servers
It's sold to another third-party that
Keep device alive
They may contact those users again say Hey you can buy
Come get your dad out of this system
Who knows what
Actually
I don't know if you ever heard of the co that sleep tracking device
Remember this thing that you know you was crazy like a headband
You're really nice
Ariat
Really nice your sleep tracking system
And after two years I just couldn't make a go of it
Shut the lights off close down
But then all of that data and all of their IP was sold to another third-party
Call Musa
Hundreds of days
One day they had access the next day
Let someone else had all the
Clear data exactly and then someone else has all of their data and they don't know who that someone
Sometimes these companies don't do very good job of saying hey guess what
Shutter doors but
Yo company XYZ
She bought all of our stuff and they're going to do a really good job and they're going to
You know do all of these things for all of our past
No not the rule in this industry unfortunately
And then the people that actually signed
Disinformation and those devices note application
The left with nothing
You know a device it doesn't work
An application to stop tracking anything anymore
And nobility to make any sense out of that in your Richard formation that was a part of their life
Yes I would be really ticked off
If I lost all of my previous
Years of Fitness tracking
I've been wearing one since 2011
So yeah
Exactly
Just don't exist
That's why we hold them
To a higher standard
Okay
What is your advice to doctors
Or medical
Professionals who are looking at all of this
Listen to physics
No I think
Even though it may not be clinically
In terms of your practice
It doesn't mean it's not clinically meaningful for the life of an individual
I think understanding of what role
The devices in the data play in the life of the person
That's why I think we need to spend
What time is it
Acknowledging
These things are important
And how they can actually help them
Illbleed life they want to leave
Will end on that very profound
Ernesto thank you so much for coming on the show
Thank you was great being there thank you for listening and
Please tune in next week