Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Kevin is back this
Because we're
Snooze
To talk about
How is that was different London last week
Glassworks Abbey Road studios in all
And this is all part of your new digs
Will Abbey Road Studios was not part of the tour
Yes I do have a new gig and actually just announced today that they were recording the show
I am going to be will know I am I am working for Google
Of all places the Google
I can't really say what I'm doing though
Obviously.
But yes I was in London at a Google event
Last week
And that's how it's not on the show and I hear that you had
Mr. Mike Wolfe a former colleague of ours
I did we talked about all kinds of fun
So cool
Some of the topics will be Revisited
Robotic bartender
Weather
Alcohol
This week
We got to talk about the stuff
Kevin's going to be very clear about what
We're going to be talking about some drama
August doorbell camera
Amazon
As always skip
The group called I Am the calvary and they're releasing
Recommendations for security in the Smart Home
If security is your back
Love those folks
I do too
I don't know how loud it is cuz I've never done a place on there in like this but yes that was my Plus
StubHub
Golf Club
Nest
So Thursday
AR podcast
A website called the information
Publish the story that
Wow Dropped a Bomb It talked about
And had an interview with Tony fadell the CEO of nest
The Exodus of over 500 employees
Abbott company
Why
Nest has not managed to
Introduce new
Products in the two years that
It's been since Google has purchased it
And
Kind of laid bare a management style that is
I don't know how would you describe it
You know
An anesthesiologist
Stop people clearer I don't know anything about this internally at Google so this is just speculation and observational
Answer your question
Barely controlling
Turley controlling and mean
Tony fadell came from Apple
Which
Controller
Standard operating procedure
Tight controls over Hardware software and messaging you know messaging about
About products and such
And
It's a
Based on the information story
N3ver pretty solid now that's I don't I don't doubt
Their sources or anything
Seems like
Maybe things are too controlling over there I don't know
And seeing people leaving from nest for quite some time
Fortunate
Didn't have a
The access
These guys got with
But also didn't have
The time
Delve into this but
Men
I have no reason to doubt the story because it
Chives completely with
So
I would also say
From
All of this
There's a couple lessons we should probably take from the
Explains to me totally
Why they're two totally different protocols called weave
One from Google it went from gas because it sounds like the people at Google
Are not really working with the people
Add nest
There's a little anecdote in there that Google is building an Amazon Echo
Type device
And
The Nest team was like hey we want in on that and the Google team was like
No thanks
So
That feels pretty damn
The other two this was
The Dropcam part
And that's kind of a surprising to hear who who is the person over there it's Greg Duffy
Yeah
Nest purchase Dropcam about
6 months
After
Google hit purchase nest
And it kind of lump those two together
Basically
When
Greg Duffy the CEO of Dropcam left everyone was kind of shocked and there were rumors
Nast wanted to put out this video camera
Hated working there
People are crying and working out
And now for the information story
Actually talk to them and explained
A lot of things
Like ghetto
How Tony fadell
Treated him maybe not
How someone who
Had previously run a company would want to be treated
And then on Tuesday
Duffy actually posted
Something on medium that said
Hey that story
I just want to say that my employees for great
Has Tony fadell had insulted the Dropcam employees in the story
And
He went further and said that most of successes
From the previous earnings report we're actually Dropcam successes
Seems like a pretty big
A grenade a lot in the middle of this fight
It's getting ugly
And I don't know if we're going to continue or not I hope it doesn't but
Pieces of the story are you right lobbing grenades and and it's just not not pretty
It does show though how tough it is
To make
A smart home device
Tony fadell has for years
Been a proponent of the intuitive and responsive home
As opposed to everybody else who's trying to pitch these like programmatic homes where your like I will tell my lights to turn off at 10
Adele's version has always been that he wants
Your device is to react to you
Ness was very much part of that
I think so
Ask the space kind of heat it up
It became more and more difficult
Control all of that
Because
Credit score
Nest can't be a plateau
It has to be an ecosystem and I think it's hard for someone who's that controlling to open up and let that happen
And then we talked about this before I'm into to your point about it but it's difficult to make a device these days
There's so much changes going on between protocols and
Radio technology and dealing with people's privacy and security issues which are certainly valid
Nnn opening things up to third-party developers do you or don't you
How do you do it if you're going to do it
This is not a revolution that's going to happen in a short amount of time and I know that sounds obvious because innocence Stacy you and I been watching it going
One for several years now
But this
Really does speak to the difficulty of it and why things
Tornados
Quick as they could be
You got people such as a apple who are
Want to control everything
Down to the security chip inside
There's so many moving parts
And everybody wants to that to control a known bits of it
It's very very
Frustrating
Incredibly and I would say that I would love it to be
More like the internet
Common protocols everybody works together but it's so far
And that's why we're going to always have these
Bridge services
Services like
If this then that or you thinking
That's an awesome Segway
So what
Talk about what
What's happening with
Send that
I'm saying again because now it's more of a kind of bad news so to speak
Coming up Delaware
So here's what happened
A service called pinboard which is owned and created by one developer
Social bookmarking for introverts
Attack something you favorite something and
Are you save it for later like any article or what you like on the web
Cost 11 bucks a year
It's a cool service a lot of people apparently love it
And what happened was
A post
When if this then that said hey
You know your ifta integration is going to break
On April 4th
And if you wanted to keep working
You're going to have to develop something with the new code that were release
And the developer was like
And then I guess she had some back and forth with it to send that because a second post that went up
I believe on Monday
And it got some play
It was like
Yeah so here's all the things I find wrong with this so
And I think it's because his users were like
Hey if two saying our stuff is going to break what's happening
And basically this is a tough
Because
Totally right in saying
Yeah
I think it's great that you did this integration of my service so many years ago
Now that you want me to develop it for you because you're turning that perfectly fine working one-off
I'm just not going to do it
I totally get that
I do too and you know it Services mature and change and then there's infrastructure changes to make things better or not
Presume that's what's happening
With if this than that but
I'm looking at the
The note from the pinboard developer notes
Sites that want to work with if this then that will have to implement a private API that can change without warning now
You know it says I'm all for glue Services big and small and I think I would if this then that is to Glucerna as it's great you can put
Bug pieces in and make things work together
And he says it's better for the weather they connect a stable document public apis rather than custom private ones
I get that in a minutes
That's the ideal that's kind of part of that whole ecosystem effort worth
Founder of if this then that
And
I was like
Linden
Here a couple questions I have for you one of which was what's up with this
He responded that he says we are working with pinboard to find the right steps are in tension
Platform rather we want to do everything we can to help Partners take ownership of their Channel improve it over time
But in his argument is
And his statement
We simply cannot maintain improve and make each of these channels great without the help of the services themselves
We could have done a much better job in communicating this desire for change in ownership with both pinboard and are user
So he said they have over 300 channels on it
Bissonnet today
They want to have thousands and they can't support this without
People's help
Doubt
There's some stuff in in the post about the developer terms of service where
Basically all of the data
If this and that
Looking out with this actually
Personal like the consumer terms and services
It looks like
If the sin that takes my data
And it puts
Information about me and all the things that I'm using with that it's stores all that information in a folder
Is personally identifiable
They say they don't share it
Unless they've got
Law enforcement or legal processes which I believe
A civil case
Eeyore when it's necessary to do so to protect the rights and property
Or others
In the same terms and conditions it says
Quote we may share our data including personal information about you with our partners and joint ventures in furtherance of our business
That's a little contradictory
Yeah and I asked Lyndon about that and he didn't actually respond to that
So
Yeah
You don't they have to monetize in for the last year-and-a-half they've been working with
Third parties seoul
Comedies like pinboard except companies that want to be associated with if
And they've been making those companies develop their own
API Integrations.
So
It's been something that's been happening for a while
The fact that they're going to turn off the freeway or the early versions that they built up to like establish the platform
Users
It's kind of WhatsApp setting
That's upsetting as well as I do and I don't know the answer this question but I'm wondering how much
Advance notice that they gave to certain people
You know cuz April 4th is right around the corner
That's true
It was on Twitter when it received the letter he started to
In which case that's not enough time
No
Okay so he received a letter this week and they're shutting it down basically
Yeah that's that's
Okay so
Don't have a lot of conclusions there it looks like if they spend that is doing
Services
In a with a developer Community to make themselves exciting for end-users and then they kind of switch the terms because I've got to make
You put the plumbing in place let people use it and then you turn off the spicket
So
Not good not good so we'll stay tuned
We'll come back to this
Issue again especially with the user terms because I really would like to know
WhatsApp
My data
Undecim
Better stuff
August doorbell
Camera
And
What you think
I like it like this doorbell since I saw it way back in December and thought I was going to
Get it back in
But it's good some of the reviewer say it's too big for the door frame and it is it's a big Square
I know you got a skinny space so you may not go for it
Yeah I do
But I can tell you it will not fit in
I'm sure we'll fit many people store so
It'll fit for me and it came with a mounting block because my doorbell is not on the same wall as
The door is ajar
Catty corner
It's none of the above
In which case is probably a good solution you going to see the side of the person
Facing the door I presume
What they do is they make these little mounts that
Can't it out at like a 45 degree angle
Is August is the only one of all the doorbells that actually
It comes with one
Which
It's very easy to install
A lot of people and I'll just say this
Don't be afraid to take your doorbell off
And install one of these doorbells it's about a 15-minute operation
And I have a stucco house so
You know I'm talking about drilling into the Mesa
You know she may not need new holes you are if you're doing Bricker
Stucco candidate the little anchor bolts
It's so easy you guys
And and yes there's some wiring to connect but it's so negligible
Give me the wiring essentially I got some beaches for power it's it's actually capturing video and such
Over life I assume
Yes yeah so you're not you're not wiring a video feed
Innocence you just wiring another
Essential another doorbell
So if people are cuz I know some people are like one install a little bit higher someone for like a hundred bucks in them
And it's not just because I am handicapped
You just take off your doorbell nuc
You have another doorbell
You're going to want to
$199
It has a wonderful HD camera
Unlike the others this has more of a square view as opposed to the long way
Landscape View
You can see
So clearly during the day at night
Maybe not as good of quality is the skybell at night but I found that it's a little bit more
Reliable
On the notification side making sure that when something happens
It let you know and then it's faster to load
Wichita
It took about two seconds to resolve
The video feed when I'm in the house
Not bad
There's no service or anything that you have to pay for them no monthly Fabian the only reason I ask is because it will actually eat fabric
Call record every single
Interaction and you can reply those
Is the cloud service isn't setup
He's coming back right now
It it does not have anything like that
There's no fee associated
Tulelake
See a certain like
Up to a certain time
Birthdays
History
Catch up yet I bet they will have that okay I see it now coming soon and then August app update
Animal Crossing
Beautiful
Well
The service
30 days worth
Is that make sense
Got you okay I'll have to go look and let you guys know but
I know that
The ring doorbell you can actually download videos
From the doorbell and store them yourself
So that is pretty handy
If you have a ring you may already know
August doorbell cam
I'm excited I think it's the most beautiful of all the doorbell
Just for my
Pretty person
Yeah no design it's beautiful
So that is that other things
That we talked about in the oven
Oh you love the June oven
I did I think it's such a fun idea to have like a I-4
Expertise
Internet of things makes you an expert
Without actually having to be
So
Kevin you want to say what's going on there
So the company has raised an additional 22 and 1/2 million dollars in 5
Financing
And for those who are not familiar with the junit
I I like this description on on TechCrunch cuz I know I've said it before deposits like an easy bake oven for grown-ups
Some
It's going to cost you $1,500
So why they raised more money
Did Ashley delay this the launch of this is well yeah it was actually in June
Now it's going to come out
In the court
Holiday time
That's a big change
So here something's
What they're trying to do here is they replace like the typical oven light
Inside the oven
So that like incandescent kind of style light that you got with nmds
Put
Sensors in the feet of the oven
They've also put a GPU in a
Camera
Inside so I did a camera inside the oven so it can look at the food in the gpus to do kind of machine learning
So I can say like
I'm going to totally
You know cook it this long so you don't have to
Know how to cook
A pork chop
In talking to people in the home appliance business sole kit Electrolux
Whirlpool
Whenever I ask him about that they were like
Yeah you know putting LEDs inside of an oven environment is super
Hard
And
Some of the stuff they were trying to do any
A camera inside the environment is also super hard
Just to do at production scale
So what I'm wondering is if they kind of realized that
What they're attempting maybe a little bit
They swallowed more than they can chew
That's possible in an animal so wondering I mean
The idea behind us as the oven will actually know what you put in it
So it's not like you to say I'm cooking a pork chop
What you just said
And I wonder
Algorithmically are they having challenges there as well
I'm in stitches. Vast array of
Foods
Yeah but that mean with machine learning and deep-learning
That doesn't feel as in
Intimidating to me
The actual
Stuff they're trying
And if you think about putting a semiconductor
Oven work
So I mean
I don't know
What they're doing is hard
It's worth
In their defense and along the lines of what you're saying the challenges maybe they did say they said in the statement
That they decided to work with new manufacturing partners for Plastics and cosmetics sheet metal
So
It could be supply chain issues could be proud of challenges
At least partially
The reason why this is being delayed
So there we go
Cuz I really want to try this
I hope you get a review Winnetka
$1,500 for this
Probably here
Let's talk about what we
$1,500
Was it $90
89 99 plus tax
So
Before the show
Kevin and I both
Received our emails from Amazon
If an arriving Thursday on time
Right
Is the smaller version of the Amazon Echo
It doesn't have the full speaker in it but should
Presumably have all the other fan
You'll hear more about that
Thursday
And we actually talked about the other Prophet came out with about the Amazon tap
And you got an email from a listener and it you know it
Shame on me for not making the very good point that he made
Yes so Joseph episode
First portability
Like all for it
And then second
Never wanted it
Echo to creeping her opinion
Because it's always
Teacher is a great choice for our home
That's a really valid point I'm in
Some people don't like the always listening function
That's in the Amazon Echo today and the tap
Doesn't have that you press the button when you want to listen and I remember saying that that take some of the magic out of it for me
But some people are fine with that they rather give up that magic and
Be safe and secure knowing it's not always listening so
It's a really smart
Smart observation
So yashow he's keeping his wife happy
And he's one of the
Yes
Now we know who those people are
Apparently
It was a no-show so they can't be all bad
Also from
Amazon
Is this week actually marks the anniversary of the Amazon Dash
Which
We we don't talk about the much but those are the buttons
Physical button
Fix the things
Like
Your washing machine washing machine
And you just press it
Order
A new product there specific for one product so a tide Dash
Only order you knew
Tides
From Amazon
So to me it feels like
Like a lesser cousin of the dash
Assume that service which I think is suica Google
It has like censored
In orders at 1
Texture Olmos
Stout that's awesome
That I like that I like
Like this this is nothing more to me than just moving the one
Click buy button off your phone or tablet and put it on your physical device
People like it because Amazon is announcing over a hundred new button
So
Imagine how cluttered your home could be
I'll check the new buns maybe I mean if there's some product
Maybe
But
I don't know
We'll see
And usually the way Amazon has done it and
Previous year
Has been
By the button
For like for 99 and then you get a credit off of your
First order us whatever it is
So
They cost money but
Do you get it back
Do you want to talk about
Well yeah I mean that's something I would reward
It's something I wish I had a button for redelivery
Yeah you you actually
Tune me into this something smart
Wine bottle
It's called a Cuvee
And I've never heard of this before but it is a wifi-connected bottle
The bottle is not cheap I think it's $180 if you pre-order
Hundred dollars
And you can use it to actually
Order
Refills of wine that will retail between 15 and $50
So it's it's wifi-connected I didn't see how you do the reorder thing
Doesn't sense it
Do you have sensors in the bottle
And I know you're supposed to go to the website and pick out the bottles that you
So they're going to do a recommendation
Service kind of Amazon
Well Amazon Netflix those kind of companies
So it'll
Take your taste into account
So
If you find a way to order
You can actually order it directly
The bottle 100% sure how that would work
Matching you have to decide like
Like I really like this one particular
Fresco
Right
I think
It's an interesting delivery model is like the razor
The razor blade model for
The Internet of Things
In this case the razor is like
Too expensive
It's interesting how we're seeing a shift towards the ordering process in the purchase of things with with iot
Not buying it what she thinks of buying everyday things
Biote
And we just talked about the dash buttons this is kind of similar to literally order the wine right from the wine bottle the reusable
Wine bottle which actually keep your wine fresh for up to a month as well so
I think we're seeing is I mean this is a totally legitimate business model but I think was going to end up happening is we'll see
Subsidizing
In device
After a certain point so what we're going to do
Get is
Companies that
Maybe cheaper version
It's got sensors it's got the
Pre-ordering
And it's also
Has to be like vacuum sealable
Gear whine
So
That could be incredibly expensive and not
We're subsidizing
I really think
Example
Coffee maker
Like a Keurig or something
Is connected
Mr. coffee connected
Peacemaker and then they do deals with
Ghetto folders in
I agree and it and it takes away a lot of activity from
What smartphones and tablets and computers and
Put it where you
Never you want and use those products
You know
And the challenge will just be getting the hardware cheap enough
And getting people comfortable enough
With the business model that the manufacturers of these products will be
Comfortable subsidizing
I'll be curious to see how that works cuz even like right now with the Amazon Dash
I haven't ordered any because when I look at Amazon I'm like
And their pricing for toilet paper is way too expensive
Like
Take away my ability
To choose
For me
Prices kind
Trump's convenience there
Confirm much of America that's probably still
McKay's
I could be wrong
I would say so but I think over time
Millennials growing up in Saint convenience lb
More about purchasing decision
Yeah and you know
Procter & Gamble is doing the experiment connected Febreze
Plugins
And they're actually
Experimenting with this model intent of selling Febreze has
I don't think they're selling it directly to the app yet but that is their plan
Pay anything to sell more products
More stuff
So while you're drinking your wine
Connected
I would love for you guys to do us both a favor
And our survey
So it's very short survey
2 minutes maybe if you had most
At most
Go to ww.w. Iot podcast. Com
/ survey
And I put it in the show notes
And if you guys
Awesome
And was that we should go to our guest
Who is
With the Atlantic Council and recommendations
The smartphone
Yay
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast to tell you two things the first
First is that I've launched a Weekly Newsletter devoted to the internet of things and you can sign up for it at Stacy
On iot. Com the second thing is that we're now accepting ads on the iot podcast
We have packages for big companies and for startups so if you're interested please email Andrew at iot
P podcast. Com thanks for listening
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
If I guess today is Bo Woods who's the deputy director of the Cyber statecraft initiative at the Atlanta
City council
Hey boo how are you
I'm great sweetie how you doing
I'm doing so well so thank you for coming on the podcast this week
You guys have some really exciting news and by exciting I mean
Slightly terrifying
So let's talk about what you're doing
New release today
Port on
Security and the Smart Home
Smart Home Security
Security in the
Home-based Internet of Things
I'm so we looked at a handful of different segments
Of the
Smart home environment
Those three being home utilities
Things like power on electric gas
Metering systems
Things where you could potentially save money
Is by using Spark
Home devices
We also looked at a home appliances things like fridges
Laundry machine
Your internet-connected toaster or sous-vide maker
And then Internet connected or Internet of Things
Security and safety devices
Baby monitors
Surveillance video cameras
And other things that you buy to make your home
Safer and more secure for yourself in your family
The exciting thing about this and why you're on the show this week is because
You're part of a group called I Am the cavalry
Which is kind of this security researchers working with government and working with industry establishing these framework
Parts for connected devices for securing connect
Two devices
And you guys did one on the automobile
Is now done with the FDA on
Medical devices connected medical devices
And this report is the precursor to one on the smartphone
Yeah it's
Distinct
But not unrelated
It's so
I am the Cavalry free stock round is like
Set a group of security researchers
Animal eyes that are dependents on connected technology
Is going faster than are billions
Sure that technology
I so particularly where that comes to
Human life and Public Safety
Type devices
Such as automobiles
Medical devices Smart Homes
Public infrastructure
Planes
Trains
Public Utilities
And now this report fits into that fairly well
Although it's not directly a
I am the cavalry
Framework document
It certainly has a lot of this
Hallmark San Marcos
I particularly need some of the recommendations
I see a lot of familiar faces in there
Edit can be used it as we
In the future work on a iot framework
For cyber safety
Let's go into that because your recommendations
Your first recommendation which is security by Design is something people talked about for never
And it's also like
I feel like it's the bare minimum but it's also like basically the standard that a lot of the connected device makers are actually kind of trying to
To get to today as opposed to like
4 years ago when they started building these things
So
That talks about I mean the basic assumption and I will include in the show notes a link to this document every
The basic assumption is that you
Assume that there going to be people trying to attack your device
So you heard me
You continually test it
He's crazy tremendous like lines of code so you can avoid
You making overly complicated devices with lots of Entry
It's basically
From there you go on and you talk about third-party collaboration which I read is bug bounties or at least not suing people who brings
Security issues to you right
You guys are appropriate funny
Well work with Pro don't see people who are trying to help you
I think is a better way to think of it
And then you've got seven more and we'll probably talk about most of them
But how are some of these different for the smart home then for automotive and medical devices
One of the major ways in which
Smart Homes environment is different than
Vices and Automobiles
Is that their candy
Allure consequence
Also
You look at some of the economic
I'm smart homes versus medical devices
Albertsons
Auto deals
You've got a lot of really small Kickstarter size projects
That are maybe 10:50 hundred dollars
Smart home space
There's not a lot of room
To add on different
Siri features are security measures
I told you a lot of other things so particularly with the two that you identify
Security by Design
Third-party collaboration
Those are things that
Reduce the need for external dependencies
To ensure security of the device itself
At the same time that there are
Septic tank on the kickstarter side projects for Internet of Things
They're also Kickstarter size projects
Security platform
That would be Edition
Internet of Things Smart Homes devices
Not where you started
You kind of the model as we have in corporate it
Let's buy a system
And then
Layer security defenses around it
In and out of this cost model
None of those things that really doesn't look for a number of reasons
Main ones doing that the others know how am I
Also if
Consumers are going to have to buy additional things
You're probably not going to buy the additional
So you'll just have insecure devices that
Ashley click
I am third
Consumers believe that these devices are not inherently secure
Dental inducer prices
Confidence
The Titans
Or people are very very hesitant to accept
And other things connected devices in their homes
Okay let's go back to your number two point
Because it's worth teasing a
But I think you're about as the pain of the system's nature of the Internet of Things in the Smart Home
Which is I might buy a hub from one vendor and then connected to other products is that kind of what you were talking about
Yeah you buy
Some type of a hug from one day vendor connect to the other products
You might also have
Something more like a mesh Network or different things connected
Lost my talk
Q but it might not talk to Alexa for instance
Got it so that's just not as effective but unfortunately that's how we're setting up a lot of Arkansas
Times right now
That's right
It's less effective the tire cost
Tire maintenance
That's it requires a
High degree of expert
What to use on the purchaser
And ultimately I think you're seeing some of the effects of bad and
Alexander reluctance to buy some
Set the devices are to use expected futures
Because people don't quite understand it and they don't feel like they are masters of that demand
Nor should they have to be in order to use a
In order refrigerator
Baidu security for a living
And yet
I would be hard-pressed
To adequately secure my fridge
Norwood I really want to spend the time securing it
And I'm with you I've got 40 semi connected devices in my house and I am like 100% sure that if someone wanted to
They can totally take them over I'm living totally in this Blissful security by obscurity
I probably shouldn't admit
But
That makes sense and we'll get to kind of demand for these but I did want to continue going through some of your recommendations first kiss
You got some really good ones
So the to that kind of really strong like struck a chord with me with the date of protective measures in the informed consent
For data usage because most people can see that
The Internet of Things is about
Getting data
And then
Glean insights from that data whether it's
For the company itself weathers for the user
We currently have an issue where a lot of people
Aren't just worried about their security other devices they're worried about the privacy of their data and these kind of points
Bring that up so I'm curiously
Why these are in here
How do you really
Sorry I mean
Like you said it's
Data privacy
Is one of the biggest issues with a Chinese consumer devices from the consumer
Perspective
ISO
A commitment to preserving
The agreed-upon trust
That consumers have with the companies that they buy these things from
I think it's really important it's a signaling mechanism to the company or to Consumers
That we value
Your privacy as much as you do
For whatever varying level
I'd agree that you don't value it
And what's one of the things that we call I get to hear is
It's not necessarily a binary
Privacy or no privacy
That is not necessarily A trade-off that everyone will agree on
I'm certainly
Facebook doesn't have the same views as
Odyssey
Diverse Power
They just never will agree
But
If you can set up the
Some situation in which
The company in the individual
Can together jointly negotiate
That data privacy
I think that's a really good point to be able to get to
And if we can
Cuz decouple some of the business model
Consumer value
Then we can start
See you there
Will having a
Your privacy conversation
Call Nat individual
Level
Kimberly payoff
If you have the ability when you're going into user device
To say I just
I want to be able to have this level of day to you sir
Or I want to be able to agree any time
You want to hand over
This data to third party
Or I want to have some kind of a saying that
That's a level of granularity that we don't necessarily have today
But it might be worth having a discussion around
M4 manufacturers to have a way to reassure consumer confidence
Not without
Especially imposing a one-size-fits-all
Our judgments
Must suffice for everyone
Tesla Model
How scalable is something like that for me implementation standpoint
And most manufacturers feel like if they do an opt-in kind of model the lose
Like 80 to 90% of people who would otherwise be part of their kind of
Data samples
Is that in your experience
True and is it possible to actually implement this without destroying kind of some of the business models
You know I have a feeling
Until we try it
We won't really have great data
Until we have some this granularity and transparency we won't be able to figure out whether at the mall with it works well
Scalefast
I think that it's a design choice
That kind of gets built into your business model
In some ways
Hyannis
It's one that might be
Stereo risky to summon facturas but
You can look at it
Delaware
You are the only one in the marketplace offering
That type of granularity
You might draw on a bigger group
Do I have the feeling this
Once one or two offer it several others
In the marketplace
Will start to come about an offer
And you can
These are the effects of those different files into different experimentation
Dozens and hundreds
Thousand
Maybe this can be a competitive differentiator for some of those devices and some of his companies
So that
Somebody by pick their device
I think that's like I said there's just not enough
Yet
About some of those choices that people would make
If they had them
Which I don't think there are any device
There are a couple devices that allow you not to put your information on the cloud
But you're right there very few
I think I've mentioned them I know I've mentioned them before but
The welcome cam 400 is a
Video camera that allows you to
To keep all of your data
Inside an SD card in the device or
On your own server at home
Then there's also an up-and-coming project
From silk Labs called the sense
Video camera that does this
Same thing
So what we'll see
What about this
Because you got
A couple recommendations about
We'll call it what happens when the device isn't connected
Maybe you go out of business which I think is a really good one to talk about especially because in the beginning of the
What you bring up the fact that consumers
Aren't exactly
Adopting the stuff in droves like
We thought
Right yeah that's a great question one of the things that we that we found, really on our research shows that
Is there another thing sucks company they go
Bankrupt all the time
Alarm or just stop making the device
Or
Maybe they forget to renew the domain name
And you can have all these instances where those loss of digital assets
Really make the device on functional or
If I'm thinking like a criminal
I noticed that
Possibly forget to renew their domain name or they go out of business
Michael and snatch that domain name
And then just push out an update that will do something
The customer has not agreed
So
Having some kind of a capability to operate
When the company is
Got underland
Domain is not reachable
When you send out an update that
Somebody might die
Necessarily want to apply
Thinking about those types of things
It's really important and it's an important again at commitment to your customer
On how you will treat them
I think one of those
Interesting Dimensions that use
Got at the Forum past shows
Is
Changing
An arbitration clause
And bundling that along with some type of an update
System
Especially the case when you have something like a
A change in a binding arbitration clause or
Functionality update
That
Might be bundled with something much more essential much more important
Where you want a high degree of adoption update
And you want to separate out those two
Different pieces of the two different
Goals are choices
For the consumer
If they don't agree to a new arbitration
Claws
They can still agree to
The change in terms of service for the future set that they updated
Don't lie I totally agree and so
I have a couple quick questions for you
One being as someone who's got a deal with
Updates
I find it one of the most agonizing thing is firmware updates
Like around the connected devices so like
I go to like open the app
Control my lights
Cassette like dinner pretty lady
Firmware update required
Do you have any advice for people about when they should
Try to update something that
I don't say it's always on cuz it's not but it's not the sort of thing for your leg
Oh I really want to do this right now
In Isaac in a perfect world
Updates
ABCmouse
Are there wouldn't have to be some decision-making process on the part of the the customer
It would just happen and nothing would change except for beneficial
You get extra features to play with with
You could then read it out later
Just right now they're enough
Problems of Racine
Some of these
App updates
Firmware updates
That it really should be
Something that
The customer decides whether or not they want
I think imagine
Coming back from a long trip
You come in and none of your lights work
Because
Okay and final question for you before I let you go
Do you have connected devices in your house
I do not
I've spent the last
4 years without a permanent home
Moving about everyone
Six months in different parts of the world sale
I unfortunately
Don't have much of a home to connect
Okay that was the saddest answer ever
Have any connected devices
Absolutely
I'm not sure what they would because I haven't been shopping for them but I would absolutely take out the sometimes of the connected device if I saw
A really good reason to really get benefits
Do it I don't know what's out there today that would
Substantially add value
To my wife
I think some of the value that's going to come from these things is integrating
6 a.m.
Different things
With some Pelican online profile with
Daily calendar
And then
Getting some of the benefits in that way so the Sun
Degree
What are you thinking just have one it's like the old lady
Are you can't eat just one
You can't have just one smart home device
I realize a lot of benefits.
But you have to get multiple
I bring them together for the the network effect
Which brings us back to one of the original problems that we talked about so we'll have to
Hope that people read this document and change their ways
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you Stacey
That's it for this week show thanks for listening and we hope you'll be back next week and if you can't get enough internet of things news
Please sign up for my Weekly Newsletter at Stacy
On iot. Com