Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I have your hoes
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today
We have some
Sad news for
All the wink lovers out there which means
It's just me I'm the only one
Emma wink Fanboy all by myself
It's it's only you well the news
Tuesday morning
Quirky the company that owns wink filed for bankruptcy they file for chapter 11 bankruptcy
Which means they're trying to restructure
As part of that
Agreed to a bid from Flextronics
Which now goes by Flex
To be accepted flexes bid for 15 million
For the wink
Home automation subsidiary
So
You may be wondering
What does that mean for you
Exactly wondering that what does that mean for me not the listeners are near me
What does it mean for me if I love my wink
The only one in the world who loves their wing
But you know I'm actually running a wink right now so
I I wonder what it means for me
Running away Inc
The answer is
For the neck
60 days or so
Your wink should still continue operating
What they're going to do as part of the bankruptcy process
Flex
Has made what is called the stalking horse bid so that means
That
Quirky
Likes flexes bid
The best
And if any other bidders come along that offer more money and appear to be
Better for the creditors
End
Winks business is an ongoing concern basically
The bankruptcy court in the trustees would say Hey you know Flex do you want offer more money otherwise we're to take this other company
I don't think that's going to happen they've been trying to sell wink for
4 months
Yeah it's it's a numbers problem written up the story when the news broke and
It sounds like they were between fifty and a hundred billion dollars in debt
AR
Yeah
So Corky has between 50 and $100 in debt
They have between 10 and 50 million in assets when I spoke to Ben Kaufman
The CEO the he's now the former CEO of Corky
All the way back
July
He said that 40 had about 2 million
Recite 12 million dollars in cash left
So that's that's not a lot of
Cashland
No and according to the bankruptcy filing you had said Flextronics is the biggest predator
They're owed about almost
What's 19 million as it is so you know 15 million there just trying to
Recoup as much as I guess as possible and then
May they do if they get
The bid accepted
So they get the bid accepted their goal is probably to keep it going as
A legitimate business
So
Flextronics
It's actually made the wink hub
Cricket
So
It behooves them
Actually keep it operating for a couple reasons
One there's all these wink Hub still out there on the shelves in the relays
And then there's a whole ecosystem of devices and partner
It also
Are Flextronics
Text customers to be quite honest their contract manufacturer
They also
Work with startups through their lab 9 division
Building a lot of connected products
So
Having a big black eye in
In terms of wink failing and
These Partnerships
Integrations
Mine is probably not in there
Keep this going and maybe
Maybe turn the business around for Wink in terms of
Continuing to sell products Maybe
Can you sell the other Wing products that are on the shelves and
Recoup some of that money that would be great for the
Yeah well I mean that's
From a consumer standpoint of me and you might be might be able to get a deal on the wing Hardware in the near future
But you don't know what it's future is of course
Right
And so I sat there and I emailed
I'm a wing spokesman and he
He said
Quote this does not impact how users experience wing
And they will continue to receive the same support
After the process
This is finally
So that implies that after the 60-day period for the bankruptcy
Proceedings is over
That Wing is going to continue as a going business
That's My Hope
I'm going to
I've also reached out to a bunch of the wink partners because wink has these Partnerships with Lutron
What's Philips with Amazon with ramberlyn with nest
All these companies that have these Integrations in
That's actually why I'm still using my wink is because it
It has these relationships
I depend on his part of my home automation scheme so
My Hope
Is that all these companies are like yes this is a
The setback but we love working with wink
Love it
Blah blah blah Kevin tofel is a fanboy we will continue to support Wii
So here's a question
Yes or no we don't take into detail
Have you talked to the SmartThings people about this
Not talk to anyone I have Ivory shout at this point to a lot of pee
Chia
Cluding smart
Secrets
I mean if I had my wish
Would be like some
Other established
Company that's already in the space
Kind of absorb it and continue it
Or some iot Consortium of companies say
We decided all together let's just work together and
On a platform Hammer build off of this I don't think that's going to happen that's high in the sky but
But smart things I could
CEO Samsung Maybe
So here's the irony
Irony alert
I know I'm like
When we say that there should be like a red flashing light
That would be awesome
Yeah my lights just flash dreads
There you go
So we were going to talk to Kevin and I were going to talk about this actually last week on our
Show who should buy wink
Because to me it's like this
Sad asset running around out there and I could very nervous about would happen
So I was going to go with Amazon because I had talked to sources who is said that Amazon had looked at when can the
Then backed off because of the security glitch way back in
And I thought
With
The integration with Alexa
I'm sorry everybody who's who trying to call you. Just went off I apologize
So with the integration with the Amazon Echo I thought that would be a really nice kind of software platform
It would bring a lot of really interesting functionality to Amazon
And I don't disagree with you but I don't know that Amazon wants to be that player in this market I think they're high
Happy being
An interface that connects then a gazillion different things
The week is kind of that's what we wants to
I absolutely princess switch
I mean it
The echo ADS-B
Voice functionality but I don't see a real big dipper
Is there really
Turn off
I don't want to disagree with you
But I'm going to subtly disagree with
You are
Another surprise to me
You obviously knew this but I did not get the third largest creditor for Corky
Is UPS
You know
I was looking at that you know I saw that would be
Why because do you remember again that security glitch back in May
What happened was they basically bricked all their devices with a upgrade
A certificate upgrade
So if your device was
Sprint
WinCo
Let you
Ship your device
Back to them on their dime and then shipped it back to you after they reset it
What was kind of funny is all
But I shouldn't say all you had to do was
Basically go to your router and reset the DNS
And then upgrade the device and then turn your DNS settings back
That is not something everybody knows how to do and totally understand
Yes but they did put up a website and let you in told you how to do it and it wasn't it wasn't terribly intimidate
As things go but
Apparently a lot of people took
Come up on that offer
And I think that's probably what that
That UPS bill is
1.3 million dollars who am I
If you know there's
I got a lot of brown trucks
Welder shipping also
Product
Yeah they're in that there's there's actually some of the other creditors in there
Where are shipping related
As well
Zodiac
DL Industrial
Oh I'm sorry Eastfield
Lighting
Is actually a
Asian
Shipper
So I thought having been Kauffman who is the CEO of quirky on there as a creditor
Is an unsecured creditor was really interesting as well
That seems very rare
Later on in the list is also a former president
Calf Corky
Who is listed
I hate to see it all kidding aside
The wing is actually works really well for me and I know other people have had different experiences I totally understand that
It's my Hub of choice right now
And I guess
Going out on a limb I mean if I was going to buy a house right now I guess I probably would not buy a wink Hub because the Futures on sir
So which one would I buy
I'm glad you asked
I am in the same boat
Because
There are things that I
What the wink Hub has offered me
Is Lutron support
Switch not a lot of other
Jobs offer
So
That has been kind of killer for me because SmartThings would be my automatic
I was put back to smart
Thanks so if you're like me and you have Lutron support
Dang it I love Lutron
Your your other options are going to be
The Staples connect
Hub
Which does have Lutron support
Or you can go with the honk
Support
If you're a big Apple user
What homekit support
You're going to
When does 60 days are up and we don't know what's
If we if everything goes to hell
Then you know you can see
But
If all else fails
Tomcat will have
Lutron set
Plus other devices
Or you can do Staples connect
And they have Lutron
Plus other device
Not exit the devices don't match up
Like device-to-device
Write the other option
Like Staples connect doesn't have
An Amazon Echo support
Is Amazon Echo is the most important item
SmartThings SmartThings is you're going
Have your back
And I
I've told the Lucian people I beg to them
How to get me a Lutron dongle
So we can just plug that into the back of SmartThings
I don't know if that's going to happen or not
Well we will have to say I'm already on the SmartThings Hub
Page 99 bucks I'm not buying anything right this second
But
I'm going to have to have a backup plan
And it's going to SmartThings as a good backup because
This is a good Segway
It the nest 2nd generation hub
Has Intelligence built into the Hub so not everything is cloud Reliant
And I know
Yeah because well we know why because
It was the cloud you lose your smart on basically and that is pretty much exactly what happened this week
Again
This time
Instead of Ness going down
Although I did hear that Nest may have
Have had some issues to
What happened was
Amazon
Web services
AWS
When is happens there people in the
Community Grill
What so many people use Amazon web services because it's so inexpensive
It is and it's
It's actually quite reliable
Except except for the Ashburn Virginia Data Center
That that thing I don't know what's
So
What is brought home to me
You probably were sitting there going up
Everything in the cloud
It's bad there was there was an override
I believe on CD
I'm sorry Kevin
Picking on your site that's okay
There is a gentleman who is
My Amazon
Echo went haywire it caused Mayhem
And the Mayhem I saw was that basically his dog woke up at 5 in the morning and you can turn on the
Light switches Echo
Yeah I mean okay to get used to a certain
Convenience factor in Holiday
I guess you could construed as Mayhem but no I was inconvenience that very night because
My echo will not play music or controlling my lights either so Ed Sheeran
Hit the light switch so
Mayhem it was not for me
We had the same issue
Mayhem was not the word I chose
I was like what the heck is happening was the extent of my
But since
Since mine is kind of sometimes not working I just assumed it was
Ghost in the machine kind of thing
Leslie Cloud Reliance for The Internet of Things it actually got me thinking about how many services actually run on Amazon
Because a lot of them do
And if not
The winged Cloud runs on Amazon
Obviously
The echo has Timberland sunny
Amazon
But a lot of
Even Cloud products like
Electric imp which provides the
Connectivity + cloud services for things like
The rachio sprinkler head they actually run
On Amazon
They now offer an on-premise device but
Ala which is kind of it more of an industrial
Cloud provider also runs on Amazon
And the list goes on
I used to I used to track which once ran on Amazon and which didn't but
It became kind of silly because most
Devices actually
Amazon so that's one of those problems that people don't really talk about I mean everyone kind of acknowledges
Yeah
I mean
They that got built-in redundancy and
Your data centers all over but it mean when they have something that
XM widespread level
The only redundancy that you could have in places have your service is running on a separate companies cloud and that's expensive
Batman you fall back issues and someone
Text for 2DS
You're another company's Cloud doesn't look
Quite like Amazon's cloud and it's not like you can actually architect
A Wonder one solution have
Optimized
So I totally get it. But we've said this
I think probably for the last two episodes in a row
Having IRT solar line upon the cloud
Brings
Challenges and
I still keep going by right before the show we were talking about the hubs
Because my favorite husband all that actually might the do-it-yourself insteon Hub that I ran here in my house
Not connect to the cloud but everything here
Was running on a headless server
That's it I thought you know I didn't worry about Amazon web services or anybody else's cloud
Oh my God
So like the cloud
That were proselytizing
We have become
Redundant
My lights just went red again
Oh yes
Yes I sure like
We're not going to talk more about this
Because there's really nothing more to say so
Since neither of us are offering a service nor can we really
I really can't think of an option
They helps people
But if you guys listeners have an option
I'd like to know about it
Because this is
This is a continuing problem
You did actually given option of that was
At least I consider the SmartThings Hub which the new one does have some
Smart's new logo
In case the cloud is not excessive
You know the Amazon Echo has some smarts local
So
You know I think
Your counterpart is eating at talked about
The alarm is being said inside
The echo
What are some local stops yeah yeah
So
Hybrid
There's a hybrid approach but you know no one is going to be
No one is happy when their stuff is
You're always going to want that
Always
You know it's like
Unless unless you're like in a life-or-death situation
And you're kind of stupid thing is you don't see the cloud
Right you know it
It's like when your power goes out in your
Curses power
You know your
Like my only income
Convenience food like in the middle of a hurricane or something are like
Volcano the power's out but
But at least I have
My family
We're safe but this is not that
This is like
I have to get up to turn my lights lavender Ahab
I don't know where I go
Let's talk about smart
Let's talk about presents
Because
Did you get me presents
Oh wait what kind of presents
I cooked I got the smart plugs
It's from a company called zuly
And
I got to tell you Kevin we have talked about
Presence and Bluetooth for god it feels like years
Trevor
And
Now that I finally tried them
You like it don't you
I do like it but I'm also like once again this is so hard for me
Right it's like Christmas where you're like Christmas is Christmas and then Christmas comes in your like
Okay well yeah that was
I guess yeah that was cool
Which makes me feel like a little ungrateful
So silly in this
Julie is fine
Julie makes the smart plug
They sell for $160 for a 3-pack
Which is what you're going to need to actually do presence in your home
Or $60 for
Single
Smart plug
They're beautiful
They plug into any outlet and turn it into
A smart outlet
You can plug
Any Appliance into it if you plug the lamp into it it turns into a dimmer
It also measures
Energy usage
It can do scheduling
It can
Let's see what else
Measures my carbon footprint for that device
And almost sounds like the
WeMo Insight switch that you had sent me
Yes and that is also 6
So if you were looking at both of these
Is senior like
I really want a smart outlet
That does some cool things
You know I might
Recommend you do
The Soule because you're going to get the
On off capabilities you're going to get the
Energy consumption but you're also give me the ability to dim a light
I don't believe the inside
I think you are correct on that one
But
For the time being
This is only iOS
So iOS only for now Android is coming later
I don't know about
So the big deal about the three packets besides saving yourself a little money
If you have three or more of these they
Use Bluetooth to triangulate your presence your location in your home provide it and I said this
Between years ago provided you have your phone on you
Yes and I know when we talked about this way back you're like when I don't want to carry my phone everywhere
But I bet you're doing it now aren't you
A little boy
Here goes okay so here is
Here's was Julius
Zulia selling presents
And they're selling it tied to Bluetooth on your phone so yes you do have to take your phone with you
Which I kind of lose because I don't always have pockets
But if I take my phone with me
Here's what I
I can walk into a room
And theoretically the lights will turn on
In the lamp that I have plugged
Into the zoo
It will turn on when I in
And that is actually pretty
So I'm walking through my house and it's like
The lights turn on
The TV turns on
Vistaprint
Do the lights turn off when you leave the room so yes
I accepted into our bedside table lamp
And her master bedroom is actually my husband's bedside table lamp because
Mine is already plugged into a different smart lamp setup
But his was set so five minutes after I leave the room with my phone
That it will turn off
And DUI on this is really nice so when you're actually setting that up it warns you it says
By the way when you do this you could be leaving other people in the dark
Do you still want to do it
That's nice I really did think that was a nice
Yes I do in my
Thanks a lot
So
Yes I did
And
When I left with my phone
Boom
It turned off
Actually
Once again
Nice
I did find
If I left
The room
But I didn't go into a room
That had a Zulily
Outlet
Didn't always turn off
It was a little hit or miss
And that's because it's it's basically figuring out which one of the Zulus are closest to with your Bluetooth ready
When your phone so again triangulation and
It's not going to be super super precise
Because of that it is my desk
Right so if I
If I went out of the master bedroom
Into like the office where there is another Zully and then I went someplace else
Then the light would turn off but if I went for my master bedroom down into light
Like a living room where there was no end
I bypassed all the others ulis
Yep it was just like
Because you're still closest to that one or yeah just doesn't know where you are at that point
So
I was like oh I guess I need to buy more of these two really cover my house I was just going to say you pretty much want one in like every room
Room that's one thing so here's the other thing about living
It integrates with the net
I can't tell if this is a great thing or not a great thing
So I think I need more granular controls but for most people they're going to probably
So you know how
Most people have their nests someplace out of the way and sometimes you're like
In a room and suddenly realize your nest is decided that you're away from home
Oh my God
All the time all the time
So this integrates with the nest already
And this would stop that
Because if you stick the smart plug
In there
In that room that you're in most the time with your phone
It'll just be like your nest
She's here
Don't go away
So these can act as basically external sensors for an ass which is very nice
It is except
I have my Nest upstairs
And when I go downstairs
I actually like that my nest
Turn off
So I was kind of like oh
I kind of wish I could turn my
Downstairs sensors off since I got a downstairs and upstairs thermostat
I wish that I could turn my downstairs
Sensors
Zulys off for the nest
Which is
Maybe a little more complicated
But I'd kind of like to see that in an update because I think that would be
Nice to have later
Totally agree you and your tell me about these before the show
You mentioned something about the battery life on your phone
Yes and this is the final day
I noticed and I install these on my iPhone
Because
I didn't have the Android app yet and I don't use my iPhone
It's my work phone
So
I noticed it until usually I
Don't charge my charge my work phone once every four days or so
But this guy
Running this app I would go through
The battery like once a day
And this app uses the battery
2/3 at the bat
Yeah we went into the battery settings on your phone
Right before the show and took a look to see which apps are using the battery the most
And it was nearly two-thirds of the usage
Was from the zulia
And that's kind of concerning to me I know it's using bluetooth smart and it should be low power and all but
The app is probably constantly looking for the smart plugs
Even when you're not at home as my guest but there may be some
Some geofencing involve are that alleviates that I don't know
There's a whole lot of pinion going
Yeah now I don't know if it
So this is the question does it use geofencing to notice when I'm away from home
How to turn off the
Cuz I'm a little weird as a tester
I work from home
Right so it's people who were home you know
Not working at home but we're out all day
Maybe it stops paying for them
The app would have to know that I only know to know that I would it would need to be in a GPS or Wi-Fi or some other
Some other way
I'm going to suspect not it's just a guess on my part
It dogs location
It does ask
Maybe maybe
It is asking for that permission
You're going to have to go work in a coffee shop for 8 hours and then see if it still use 2/3 of the battery usage at that point because that's
The only way I think to find out unless the company
You know
Tell you for sure
Potato
It is going to Ping a lot because it's
Constantly checking to see how far it is away nachos from one Zulily
But for multiples awais
In the final wish list I would have for the Zulu
Right now I can't use the presents for anything other than the zoo lease
Really want to use the present
Send Taylor the CEO of Zulily
Said that they're working on
But I really want to use like
Azuli presents isn't if this then that
Trigger other thing
Thanks because
Yeah my lights
Are not lamps
So the fact that it's
Plugged in
Devices
This is very limiting to
Tell me where is I want to be like
Yo when I step into this
Broom I want my
Lutron lights to
Turn on my Philips Hue Lights to turn on
So that's the next stage of zulia
You know after they work on the battery issues and after they possibly give me granular
Controls may be before the grid
I wonder if they're even considering
A second product
That would be less limiting to you and that would be easily smart switches
CNY
As we've discussed which is all the switches are hard for people cuz no one wants to install switches
Everyone's afraid of life
They should be
But afraid of
Before we had all these connected bulbs which is arguably much simpler to install
You know all the insteon stuff I have we're all smart switches
Redid mosto switches in my house
I'm with you that I've
Redid motion
We are in the process of
Redoing most of
Lutron
Now I'm feeling like
Oh no that's why I'm Like Glue Sean give me a dog
Please maybe I can build my own
I still like a radio from inside a Lutron or Pico and see what I can hack together
Kickstarter
Hello
Well we have talked a lot about a lot of things some good some bad we've made some good recommendations for people
And now it is time for us to take a
Quick interlude quick musical interlude
And then stay tuned for a guest who is liat ben-zur
She's with Philips digital health and she is going to discuss Aging in place and how the internet of things can help with
Fat and change Healthcare
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things show this is Stacey Higginbotham and today I have is my guest
Liat ben-zur
Who is the Senior Vice-President of
Connected
Digital propositions for Royal Philips
Hailey. How are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing great thanks for having me I'm so excited you are here to talk about something that is
Actually really important which is
How we can use the internet of things to improve Elderly Care
And kind of the concept of Aging in place so
I'm super excited to have you here
So first off let's set the standard width
Phillips
You are right now part of the same company that makes the
Philips hue light bulbs but that is not the case for much longer
Correct
That's correct
We're actually splitting off of the lighting business by the end of this year
Alright so
Let's get started with kind of this concept because everybody much everyone's aware of the demographic Trends happening
Which is
They're about to be a lot of
Older people and
We're kind of concerned about
How we're going to care for so many aging people
With the resources that we have
And there's a lot of opportunity for The Internet of Things even if it's something as simple as
It'll caring for your parents and
Having the ability to put sensors in their home in it
Non hopefully surveillance kind of way
Just make sure they're okay
So
You guys have created actually I think it was about two months ago
Have a think tank
How to innovate around Elder Care
Correct
Yeah that's right actually we definitely do see
That there's a pretty big problem to be solved out there
So I think today there's
Seniors are actually using more of the healthcare resources per capita than any other group
And patients are 65 years and older are representing 40%
The Vault hospitalized adult
We think that there's a lot that we can do there there's
Technology Innovation sprouting around
Everywhere and you're you and and and his podcast talks about a lot of them
But it's
A bit rare to hear people talking about how those technology Innovations are are
Helping the elderly
And in research that was done between Phillips and Georgetown
University we we actually learned that it's not because the elderly don't want to adopt a pet
In fact many of them do
I think that one a little bit of help
On learning how to use it
But oftentimes their caregivers are just so overwhelmed with that day-to-day care
But they don't have time or the patience
So the Aging well hub
Which is that what you're referring to
Is is like a think tank
That we started
With a lot of other lot of other partners
Georgetown MIT age lab Humana will S Health and more
Focus on driving Innovation specifically
Around attacking issues of Aging well
And so far have you guys discovered anything interesting or what is kind of
Do you have a
Focus for your research yet
I think it's still very early days so a lot of these things are just getting started but
We're going to be stay tuned
To hear about what comes out of that about aging well hub
I I certainly will maybe we'll have you back in a year to see see what you've learned
So Phillips has actually been doing
A lot with
The elderly
Ocean sound like
But you guys have been in the space for decades with the lifeline
Product
Which
You know I think we've all were familiar with I fallen and I can't get up was at the tagline
Lifeline's tagline
Master concept of the concept I think
I think you're right Lifeline is has been the leader in the United States for many years in
Helping elderly to be more independent in their homes
With these types of solutions at
Detect Falls
And a lousy nurse immediately be
Connected to back and response
So
How do you take a product like that which is
You know connected to a cellular network
And kind of upgrade it for
The current
Generation and era
Because
You know I look at something like that and I'm like a that's
That feels very
Old school in
How do you tie something like that in with
Ghetto Sensors how do you make it may be a little bit cheaper I don't know I mean
I'm sure expensive because there's all this back and monitoring it's not just like
Are there people on the other end is so if you fall
You know it's calling actual people who will send help to you so that's
I assume part of the cost but
How do you get a chance when you're very very expensive
This is actually a very complex solution of a Lifeline system
Takes over 9 million call the year that's almost won a minute and their average response time is 22 seconds
So it's a it's a pretty serious
I'm solution to make sure that there's always someone there
For your loved ones when they need it
What's your question
Your question in terms of
How do you take these
Core Technologies and drive them
Into the Brave New World
Coyotes Rectify that
Coyotes what's hard about the same stuff that's driving
All of the wearable companies
That we like to talk about
To do
Cool stuff the same technology that they're putting into two to their devices
Are going into
The Next Generation
Philips go safe Solutions
Which is really a wearable pendant
Include includes
3G modem
Give to Les Bois home communicators GPS
Wife I told your bread crumbs audio begin
All the stuff that we talked about
In
I would say going to the more
Consumer Centric
Sexy stuff that early adopters
Talk like what like to discuss
But it's designed for the elderly
It's it's not the stuff that you see when you
First walking to Best Buy in the home automation Zone
Autoalert detection there is
Really designed to make sure that if someone Falls
Not only is at detecting the fall but
If a person falls in Camp themselves make a call
It automatically starts the call for you
There's someone that talks back
I'm from the response Center and make sure everything is okay if you need assistance
And then you can start to think about how this can go beyond
Just
Those types of
Of extreme cases to also providing
Support for elderly care
I'm going to need my assistance
So is that someone's been
Locked outside of their home
Or
I need to pick up some medication
Or they need help do you know to go to a doctor's appointment
They have that on them at all times with someone there 24/7
You can try to contact
A various people in there
Care plan
To get help with him
That's really useful because
I I know that Lifeline feels kind of like
Oh my gosh you know
I have literally fallen and I am unconscious or
You know you're going to send an ambulance versus
Fall in and I'm kind of stuck
But I don't really need an ambulance I just
Can you call my
I just want to call a like a family member whose nearby and have them come over and
Help me out for
Maven esterly help me out but just kind of come over and comfort me or
You don't make me some soup
So that it's actually it is
It's an incredible thing Stacy I I've seen a lot of Technologies
I actually went
To visit the lifeline
Team
On the East Coast after taking a lot of these calls
And when you listen to someone who's
You know 9503
Person
Calling in in Encino just asking for help Small Things testing
System
And the happiness it brings up some on the other side right there immediately to help them
It's much more powerful than just the obvious thing that we think about in terms of
I'm salt
Call support
Deliver for Meals on Wheels before
And just
Just being there for someone is it's like
80% of like
What people need happiness it's Comfort like human comfort
So
Absolutely
So in terms of
Providing
Again
Healthcare let's
That's kind of talk
Beyond that solution let's talk about
How we bridge the gap
Between kind of consumer-grade medical stuff like a Fitbit activity tracker into kind of
Hospital in medical
Call care because
As you get older
You're probably going to
To need more wearables and more
Hospital-grade kerin
I'm very curious like
What that should look like
In kind of this more consumer I guess we'll call it the consumerization of
Medtech
Because we had the consumerization of it
But what should that start looking like to make it a little bit friendlier as we kind of try to bring the stuff into the home
Because
Where could I have to write
We can't just rely on hospitals for that
We don't seem to meet to as much anymore
With kind of better Wireless better sensor technology right
I think we have no choice
Actually I think
With the Aging population growing
The number of chronic diseases growing the overload on the medical system growing
Healthcare costs
Growing
It's just not sustainable
Absolutely there's no question about it the Healthcare System needs to change
And the way that we see that happening kind of depends on where you are
In the continuum
Continuum of Care what we call the
Care
So depending on if you
If you're someone who's
Healthy
Or perhaps
Recently went to a doctor and we're told that you have the potential of getting a chronic disease
If you don't change your lifestyle
These need to be Beyond
General
Fitness tracker
It's really about wearable Solutions
I'm not going to focus on some real Healthcare issues designed by doctors and psychologists
Like really leverage clinical knowledge
In order to drive programs
That can drive change
Behavioral change
That's kind of one
Part of the continuum
If you're someone who's already sick
If your son is already sick
And you're in the in the healthcare C
Systems there's also opportunities for 4
The Internet of Things in the consumerization of of healthcare and
Wearables
To play a huge role
I'll give you an example we've been working on
Intensive Ambulatory Care programs with Banner Health
Where we focus really on
The most complex and high-cost patients like the top 5% of patients
Austin elderly
Multiple chronic conditions
Accounting for 50% of all Healthcare
And those patients
Get a bunch of connected Hardware
To get Android tablets
To get customized software they get all kinds of biometric sensors blood pressure oxygen saturation
Scales whatever
All of those Solutions are tied back
How sweet digital platforms
Doctors have access
Nurses have access
To see the information that's being out of the country artists that information patients are matched to healthcare coaches nurses social workers
And
In just two years since we
Ben
Do we not program with Banner
Is a significant impact
Actual Healthcare cost Racine 27% reduction
And cost of care
Which goes up to 32%
I'm injection for acute and long-term care costs
And 45% reduction in hospitalizations
Overalls
What are the common
Things
That you needed a hardware side
That you need on these
Software side that you need on the cloud back inside to
That makes this different from
You know Alex hitting me with like
A Fitbit and maybe some home
Cameras and
Electronic medical records
System
Some other kid
Yeah so there's
There's a few key variables
That really matter when we talk about
Changing
Landscape
Number one is accuracy of data
So
Lots of solutions out there but accuracy of data really matters that's you know why
Much much harder.
2 things to be considered medical devices
Number two is
Wait a second so accuracy addata if it's FDA approved that means should I assume that that means the data coming off
What is accurate
Sweating.
What indicator
What's 1 indicator but of course
These Arduino accuracy of data can
Go beyond just
Care medical devices right because when it comes to
Being able to
Addictive
The more context you have the better
You can imagine all kinds of things around you providing contacts
And I think accuracy of data
Is one of the things that the medical community Ashley struggles with there's so many things out there what do they dress
And noise in the system
Good really / results
And there's no tolerance for that in a minute
That's one that's one variable
Another key variable and probably one of the most important variables
Is
The ability
For data to be used
Color of a cross
Longitude of
Things you do in your life
What I mean by that is today
When you buy wearable devices
Or smart devices
At the store
All the data that's collected
From those devices
Chesapeake elected in
The spirit clouds by each manufacturer
Liver
. device
So if I have 10 different connected things
Around me on me in my house
Usually the data is going to 10 different places
One of the things that we're really trying to do and we think it's absolutely critical for the success
Love
Healthtech and Generals is to create an open platform
The public cloud
If you will
Where
You can start to connect the dots
Home Health Care
Systems all the way through to
Devices that are more consumer-centric
Secure
HIPAA
Compliant cloud
Where
If the consumer
Consents to sharing data
You can actually start to connect the dots
And this is very very important because if you want to do some of the things that we think
Are necessary for Predictive Analytics
You need to be able to take that wearable data
And
Connected up to the healthcare
I'll give you an example of
How powerful that could be
Summit lifeline
Wearable pendant we talked about earlier
The one that elderly people might be using more for you know call detection and
Having someone there when they when they need help
We've been looking at the data
From the past several years from Seniors who have been using that
And working with a lot of clinical scientist
Data scientist
Even able to
Do some
Really interesting data analytics
Where we can detect
Proactively
When patients are most likely to have health issues
That's really allowing doctors and caregivers to intervene before problems occur
You know of course ultimately helping
Patience
Stay healthy reduce reduce hospitalization
But
That's all using historical data that was gathered from Lifeline users
Over the years and combining that with real information that's coming in real time from the from the seniors wearable device
The care stage program which is the name of that analytics platform is he won't start
Change things from being a reactive care device
To proactive care device
Extremely powerful
You can't do that if all the different things were using to collect data on lives in 20 different clouds
And you can't do that it's the things
I'm requesting or data are living on cloud
That are not secure not HIPAA compliant
And are not going to lie to do
Connect those dots.
Okay so it's like the predictive maintenance for Machinery but applied to humans
You're like that's terrible Stacy
Don't don't say that ever again
Okay
In that make sense
You guys have done
What will probably wrap this up quickly but
I I do want to focus on some of the diseases that you guys have been
Because you have this very
Are the lifeline programs for generic
General help you guys
Also have
The Ambulatory Care Program
Which is also can generic but you also have some very specific disease programs
I'm with diabetes you have diabetes specific Care Community you have a
COPD
Care community
I'm very curious like
I guess why those exist what you're learning about doing specific care communities versus General Health
I'm guessing it's just a
When you focus on these care communities you're getting both
Is there a
Specific like
Being able to get better data associated with those care like
Having a specific
I guess Patient Group
But is there also is like a
Inability to bring those actual patients together if you want
Beer kind of social media or help
Yes absolutely
First of all
Phillips is
Involved with
All of the above
So we're offering programs that are very specific
Two unique cohorts of populations
Such as a diabetes platform that was announced this week at dreamforce actually
Well I'm with Salesforce
And that's
Really about a digital Health Solution to help improve the care for like the nearly 400 million people that are living with diabetes
Huge population
And it's all about diabetes self-management
With an application
Integrated
To a backend that has an online community for collaborative
Care
So it's the first time that there's an online community that can connect people with diabetes to clinicians
I'm two other
People that also have the disease
So that everyone can share
Personal data clinical Health Data whatever they want to share in a secure
Southeast Network
You know
Just a
Just a simple example of of the types of things we're doing but we're involved in this
Various points of a Continuum including
General Health Solutions for people that maybe want to
Just start to monitor their blood pressure
There their heart rate their sleep patterns
You're the most fundamental
Things in your life are your sleep
Your nutrition
Your activity levels
And
Between those three things if he can if you can be coached
To change your lifestyle you can actually prevent having all kinds of chronic diseases later on in your life
And we're looking at those opportunities to
I think one of the
The most important differentiators coming going back to your other question
What separates all of these programs
A lot of the other solutions that are out there today
Is the
Clinical expertise
And Healthcare expertise
That were using
To deliver the coaching to deliver the recommendations to deliver the
Change behaviors
That are necessary to
Imbruvica
Stop. The real key differentiator
It's not just about tracking data and presenting
Pretty graph visualization
What can you do with it
And how can we use
Are benches
Seal Behavioral
Change scientists psychologists and
NICU nurses in cardiologist
Everything in between
To help deliver
Programs
These are
Solutions that we often build
With the patience
And with Hospital
Burberry clothes
The last mile of healthcare
In order to try to make an impact
Okay so it's the involvement of the doctors
And
Creating a community and getting an early start hopefully
Absolutely
Alright well we have moved from
Your elderly
I'm always forgetting it's it's the elderly
Hub no elderly Innovation Hub
Aging well hub
My brain my brain reacts against it cuz I'm like oh no it's an actual hub
Anthony M physical device.
So the agent will have all the way to I guess it's also aging well as but it's earlier in life
With specific preventing specific chronic diseases hopefully
You guys have a lot going on I'm excited to hear about it and I feel better about my own
My own efforts of beijing
Which which really involved is waking up every single day
So
Thank you so much for coming on the show that I appreciate it
Thanks for listening and join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast