Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a
Impact
Show
Man
The brand new sense
Heart Smart Home hub for the
Internet of Things We got the
Is CEO that company coming out as our guests this week we have
Crazy news about the Amazon Echo
Complaints for the Philips Hue we have updates on wink and WeMo
Course talk about the bass story about government
And
Maybe we'll start off with
Stuff from Toy Fair
Family that Barbie has a new smart home
Yes she does
It's cheaper than yours
HEB
Smart home for Barbie
Edison smart home comes with
Voice commands that you're tipped
Can't get to Smart Hub
Are the Barbie Dreamhouse
What does it do Kevin
It's got a little party mode that flashes lights and plays music and
You can turn the staircase from the second floor of the first floor into a slide
Very cool there's an optional accessory that you can purchase also
The Starlight Adventure RC hoverboard
So Barbie can go around the house in her own little
Hoverboard which really doesn't help her butt
Wait we're not going to go there right now
Entirely it is a separate accessory
Oh okay awesome
That would be
Awesome if she could actually hop on the hoverboard and hover but
Okay
You can put the lights on in the house operate the elevator wait a second why does she have stairs a slide and an elevator
Barbie Dreamhouse
Normally Barbie dream house does not come with
Stairs
I had a Barbie Dreamhouse my daughter has grown out of her Barbie Dream House
I'm going to tell you guys
Peace
Crap
I'm just going to lay it out there
These things are made of the dinky has plastic you will ever encounter
I have broken
Like my daughter's Barbie Dreamhouse I broke putting it together at this was like
The quintessential made in China
Just don't
Just don't so I'm not sure if this is something you really want to invest in
Personally I would take some little bits or some other toy
I just make your own like connected adventure for Barbie
You know I like a doll house or something
Just buy the $99 I think it might be 150
I think Barbie's dreamhouse unconnected is like a hundred fifty bucks
It's not cheap
That's why it was so galling to know houses
Now that's a Smart House
So anyway
Barbie Dreamhouse
Also threw out there that Mattel showing at the Toy Fair this year
A $300 connected printer for kids witch
Personally $300
I would go with
Instead of the Dreamhouse
Kudos to Mattel I mean they're there
Changing with the times that got into to go with it the Internet connected Barbie Dream House
You got the
Thingmaker which actually used to have back in the day with obviously wasn't a 3D printer
When you can like make your own toys
They're big into the
Virtual reality that got the View-Master
I mean you know what they're really changing with the times
They are all have some issues with her
They had a Barbie that they worked with
Company and that Barbie actually
Kind of
I had some security issues
Remember
Barbie
Expired Norco
Concern
And
You know so that that was hopefully
As they're bringing this stuff online they're going to
Turn a little bit about locking that stuff down so
We're going to talk about that in a minute this would be a brilliant Segway but I want to get some of the
Smaller news out of the way
Talking about Barbie dream house it is voice control just like our favorite
Suffice
BabyCenter favorite
It's up there
Amazon Echo
We got some news
Kevin wasn't here last week
So we didn't talk about
Amazon integrated
Spotify
Yeah
I'm so excited
You're like the biggest Spotify fan I know like you couldn't wait for it to be on Sonos
You just that's awesome
And the best part about this is
So we tested in our house cuz again
We have Sonos we have Echo with Spotify you can
Play
When you're playing Spotify
On your Echo you can also play Sonos or Spotify on your Sonos
And it doesn't shut it down
Probably cuz it's on the same Wi-Fi
And you'll have a family
So that was pretty sweet
The other thing that I thought was awesome
Is
Android handset
You can actually Chromecast
Your
Okay if you're playing Spotify on your phone
When you come into your living room
Or it's whatever room your Echoes In
You can actually Chromecast
The Spotify
Music
Right onto your Chrome
Is your Echo so it is resist a Chromecast
Now that's really interesting I didn't know that because I don't have Spotify I don't live in Stacy's dream home I don't have all these things
It's getting there
You know you can you can Chromecast it to any available Chromecast device switch
The echo apparently is
Know that until I come
I don't think it has been never before that's what that's why I'm saying this is really interesting because
You know Google has the Chromecast audio in the car
Chromecast video devices in the old Chromecast
They've got the Chromecast extension so you can pretty much ahead
Computer to any
Chromecast setup
I did not know that they've
Use that
To integrate into the echo
Pictures of China
I like it
I believe you I had
I believe you now I'm wondering if I can
I got an Android phone I've got an echo I wonder if I can Chromecast other stuff
2D Echo
Now you have homework
Not so I can live with this homework
Just getting to
Let me ask you is your
Phone already connected to the echo via Bluetooth cuz that's how you would normally connect
It is
Connected I do randomly disconnected
It's so
It might be doing it that way although no cuz it gives you
It tells you that it's a Chromecast Apple device
Unless it's just because I've on a Nexus and it's just like
Bluetooth equals Chromecast but that would be weird right
It doesn't over Wi-Fi as well I'm it uses Bluetooth but also Wi-Fi so no it's not just the Bluetooth connection
So I'm
Connor
Stymied on this because I didn't realize that you could do that
And to be honest I'm real quick on in my apps
For the echo just to see if there's
Anything in the settings
That's new that I have might have missed
Well it going
Interesting
Well I'm going to have to
Ed Westwick
Yeah and turn off
Later not this not this show
But next show
Yes so the echo is one of my paired devices
So it could be
I don't know I'm just
Eucharist how this all works with the Chromecast
So that's what I am definitely look into that
Well here we go I turn I unpaired it
So now we're going to see
If devices available
Oh so it's still available and it's through Spotify connect
Now so is it available on the Chromecast
Through Spotify
Then you know what I'm guessing it is specific to Spotify and it would Spotify emblem
This way
Twitter app
If and if that's the case and I can't like
Say
Chromecast
Google Music to the echo
Like that you know
That's okay I'm still going to take a look around because it's very interesting
Development here it is it is through Spotify now
Beforehand it's it gave me the Chromecast option but now it's giving me
Spotify so what I turned off Bluetooth
Okay
Centrist
Mystery solved
All right
Did it there's more
Yo there's more
There is more
Alright Kevin
This will be kind of quick but very interesting for people who have an ecobee3 home thermostat
Because you now have native Amazon Echo integration
And that's very different than using say a skill
Or if this than that like we've done with the Echo and nest in the pass this is
Straight up integration
Full support
I do not have an ecobee3
Unfortunately I cannot test it
I do not have
I have been using with my ecobee SI
If this then that integration with my
Amazon Echo and it has been
A little weird
Because
It only gives you a certain number of degrees and not all of them
So when I say
You know so-and-so trigger ecobee warmer
I can only select you know what I trigger that I
Can trigger
It to do
6 degrees
69 degrees in 71 degrees
I can't trigger to do 72
So it's a little like
It's pre-specified as to the the temperature so if there's a temp that you want does not support of your kind out of
I just have to get as close as possible
So
That's really important to you
You got to have to open up your phone and turn on the air
There you go and then finally
Man
Amazon skills
You can call an Uber
You can order your pizza from Dominos
Which in all the reading
It looks like the best way to do that is to actually pick one kind of pizza that you really like and then
Order that one all the time
I'm so if you're the kind of person who like
Stop nose and likes the same kind of pizza that this is for you
For me
I was going to ask if you if you order frequently from Domino's and I'm guessing not
But that's okay that's okay we do order from the Amazon
Is it favor
Saber hits Amazon Now app
It has the restaurants
We actually have some regulars there so
I could get my
Austin had a restaurant called phonatic we did
Vietnamese ordered all the time from that so
Definitely
Okay there is three things
Three things
You can call your Echo
I didn't realize this I thought there were only two
Which was I'm going to say it
Everyone bikes down
Shield your ears
You can either call it the Alexa
Or the Amazon
But I just discovered this
You can actually call it three things
You can call it Alexa
Amazon or Echo
The world just went crazy with tights
I know I've liked I warned y'all
It was like the trigger warning
But if you do that
I'm going to warn you if you're not going to list or show
Because we're going to keep calling at the Amazon Echo
That's the news on that for
It is and just to add to it or close it up
It's interesting to me that over the past two weeks I've seen so many articles
Mainstream articles television spots
Where everything you do what
Amazon has a sleeper hit
Amazon's going to control Smart Home
I'm sitting here going where have you people been for the last 14 months
Come on tell all those people like everyone who's like
Oh my gosh have you heard of this device
Tell him about a podcast y'all
Okay moving right along
Philips Hue
You have an Android phone
If you don't have an Android phone you may want to
If you have an Android phone they just updated their app
Work with Android
Is it 6.1
A 6.0 Android marshmallow
So
They just updated it and boy people are up
Set because they updated it to allow
Permissions for geofencing
Location of where and then access to videos on videos and photos on the phone which they use to sew you
You can
Your Bachelor lights
Have a fun feature
People link
But
They did it wrong
That's what we're thinking what would Stacy night before the show actually tested out the most updated app and we're in
Some problems
And
I haven't read the reviews of the latest version of Stacey hasn't said that
Philips is getting hammered over this and I can now see why for people who don't know Android 6.0 bring
More granular permissions to apps
Runtime permission
And so that way either either when you install or when you use an app
If you need to Grant permission to the app you have the choice for summer to have IOS does it and there are three permission
Is that Stacy just mentioned that are in the the new app it's the location allow access to media and files and
Allow access to photos and such
And the thing is that's the way Android
6.0 apps are supposed to work
If you don't have Android 6.0 which most people don't you're not going to take full advantage of this yet so
Don't sweat it
Season 6 out
And when we actually denied
Access to the app to say look at our photos
The apps like okay and how about this permission how about that permission
Super geofencing in Media
And then the after shutdown
How about know what's supposed to happen is
The app is supposed to run just not have that feature where would access the photos turn on or whichever feature YouTube
It should not have access to
Unfortunately app
Just shuts down
We also found out that
If you go through the process of
Enabling permissions or deny permissions
And then you go back into the app it may ask you again in fact we denied all the permissions
Went back in the app
On the second time it's got a little check box it says never ask me again
So what do we do we check the check boxes never ask me again and deny permissions
At that point
You can't even go back and change those permissions
Because you've already said don't ask me again so
It's really kind of flaky right now does not seem like it's been implemented a hundred percent correct
If you do run into the problem station I ran into where we couldn't even change the permissions anymore because we said never ask again
You just need to uninstall the app and reinstall the app
Yes cuz what happens if you do not have permission
You can't open your
It's just going to shut down
Exactly you did was just there but it won't do a darn thing for it just shuts right now
So if you want to control your lights
So basically everyone's upset
Because they're like
I just want to give you all my permissions
My location
Cute you're in my house that's all I want to do
Turn my lights
I need to know where I am
He's like
Yeah it's not supposed to work that way and I suspect they're going to fix it
Pretty quickly I would hope
She has done a great job when everyone
It was like so hats off about you like
Messing up
The friends with Hughes.
Community we were like okay
We are not going to
You guys are on your own
With enough support on these things but we're not going
Turn off
And make things not work
With our app
They fix that pretty quick re-read
Yeah it was
Yes so I'm assuming I reached out to Hugh they haven't gotten back to me but I sent it
Pretty late last night
So
They haven't got back to me
And
They're usually pretty responsive so I would imagine
So that's the Philips Hue stuff in the meantime
Uninstall
Reinstall
Except permission
If you don't want to accept permissions
You gotta know if you update your app
So there you go
Wink
Has updated their firmware
And their software
Yeah yeah I am so happy because as anybody who's Will Smith show knows I'm not 100% sold on a cloud
Only type Smart Home
And now I've got
What is direct access
2 between the app
And my lights
Provided that on the same Wi-Fi network
Which they are so it's not a problem
And what that does is if the cloud goes down I don't have to worry about I can still control my lights
The Wink app
And even better
There's reduce latency because you cut out the hole
Send
Command from the app
After the Hub how did the cloud cloud back to the hub Hub to the light
It's just direct app
Two light
It's a beautiful thing I definitely noticed
Less latency
Lights turn on and turn off faster
I'm so so happy about this
So the other thing to know is
WeMo also at the W Front
Which you know has the
Who in alphabetically by the way
Amazon Philips twinkle wink and WeMo
Close enough
Football
Which is the Belkin smart
Stuff
Update your software finally
I know you guys I don't know actually
I don't know if you remember but they said way back in like
The fall of last year that by the end of January they were going to really like
Focus on their software
It was going to be up to date in
Lawless
Better
But better
Put better
Because it was really a mess I mean like I don't know how many of you guys there's 1.5 million people who get stalled WeMo
Stop out there so that's a lot
Some of that stuff was really just
The devices were always nice
This is just a software experience
You know sometimes it was just telling reliable
Ivor YouTube
Switch like
Daylight savings time this would happen and then suddenly nothing would work and you be like why
So it's better
Actually the beginning of February and its four star review
Storage they were happy to put out
On my end I've noticed
It talks actually a lot better to the
Amazon Echo
Which is nice
There's a lot less like
I don't know what you're talking to or that network devices available
I've also noticed
Stat
It doesn't
Sometimes
Things we could ask you like so if I turned it off in the app
Theater wouldn't recognize that it had already been turned off and so it'd be like yeah I can't
I can't mess with it right now
Seem to talk to
Each other just
So maybe better synchronization between WeMo and other items other hubs
Panda
Stability is important to me that mine's been pretty good I just have the Insight switch on a LED bulb in the bedroom
Shut it off every night before bed
Eight nine times out of 10
Pretty solid but every once in a while I got a hiccup when I'm hitting the button and nothing's happening. It says I can't connect can't see it
I'm on the same network in the same room
So hopefully I mean I just got the app update hopefully it's gets it to 10 out of 10 times
10 out of 10
Pretty girl
Alright Fido
Final
Let's do it let's Dive Right In
Going to be good
So the big issue
Last week it really I'm going to say going forward for quite some time to come
The internet of things and using it to spy on
People how does that make you feel Kevin
Not good
Okay so James Clapper the US Director of National Intelligence
Came and spoke to the Senate armed services
And it's an annual review of like
Hey this is what's going on in intelligence
Surveillance intelligence
Threats
Does a threat report
So in it he said
In the future intelligence Services might use the internet of things for identification
Surveillance
Location tracking
And targeting for recruitment
Or to gain access to networks or user credentials
Everybody was like
Holy cow Internet of Things
Could be used to spy on people
And I'm kind of like yeah we
Do that right yeah we should have
We've had the thing about this Samsung TVs they can listen in
And people are rightly worried about you know
The Amazon Echo they're like oh you know what they're always listening and the answer is no
Is not always listening
It only listens for about half a second when you
Or it only recordes sorry it only record your statement
About half a second
But it is always listening
It's just
What adheres doesn't go anywhere until here's the trigger word
Bright
And for those of you who are actually really
Paranoid
There's a setting where you can actually turn on
A chime
Did people make
When it actually is
Sending your words to the cloud
So
You can actually
While you're looking for that this was also a big to-do when Microsoft decided to require
Originally the Xbox
Kinect with the Xbox One
If people say that's always listening it's always looking what are they doing
It's under
Your device O Mine
Stacy's
Thunder sounds
And then there's a
Wake up sound
So it says play a confirmation sound when you wake your Alexa device
And then an end of request sound
Play confirmation sound after you finish speaking
Alexa
There you go
And they're two different things so
If you want one but not the other you can do that
Yay
Okay
So that's the Amazon
And Amazon
Keeps all that information
Sew in
Kind of talking to companies
There's a couple things that they
Think about here
Is people should be aware
Of what their devices
Not just what they do but what they have the ability
Okay glad I was going to say this might be too but I would say companies need to
Clearly explained
How these things work so that people can make their informed decisions as well
Yes
Companies need to also
Well actually companies need to make a point of not becoming a pipeline of data to
The US government
Dirty joke
Needs to remember
4th of May
Which is the protection against unreasonable search and seizure
Just in case you guys are like
What's happening again
Because
We got the Constitution right in front of us all the time
How is Caribou Coffee
So
Let's break this down because there's a couple things here
A reasonable and that you can do today
You can say hey
But if you're listening to the show you probably have already
Not done yet
For considering doing that
So
There are things like we're actually about to talk to
Argos
The show is actually
Making a device that actually doesn't go online
It does go online but it has privacy safeguards and we'll talk about that
So there are devices that
Don't actually ever have to
Connect to the cloud
Where the connect to the cloud in a limited way it have
Encryption
The CEO of
Silk which makes
The sense
Smart home hub that way to talk about
Is
They do encryption and in
Encryption so your data is always
If it's in the cloud encrypted
Device encrypted
So even if he has to give over your
Your data
All he's
Able to give
That's the way it should be
This means that he can't you
Build a business
Steak
Selling your data
So
Think about that
So there's those kind of
And then there's also things like
If your company
And they're going to give you a privacy policy maybe they should give your privacy policy that isn't like
40 pages of legal aid
Maybe I should be a little bit
Better
And maybe you should ask them like
How do you participate with the government
Do you have things
Looks like
Do
Wait for subpoenas her if the government comes to you do you just like
Headed over
Yeah. You need to understand what that companies
Policy is in that situation
So there are those kind of things
I don't know
Kevin what do you think
I mean it's it's really
I said this before and I don't people
Some people have not liked it when I say it but with we almost
With crossed a barrier when it comes to privacy mean if you want certain Services you're going to have to give up data
Having said that I'm not saying company should have free rein to do what they want with that data that's that's a totally different aspect.
So like you said you just say offline by devices that don't connect anywhere but
You know
It's kind of tough to go back and I want you cross that line and and have access all this information on your own the information that you want
What services that provide value to
So now I think it does come to town to some of the tenants that you just said in that is understanding
What advice can and can't do with a company
Who creates a device that provides a service
What it is they do what what do they collect what do they use today to 4
How did they Safeguard it and what situations might be
Might be provided to a third party
Weather Sacramento or not and it was just a matter of understanding
Of course we're assuming there's Clarity and truthfulness and what two companies tell us obviously so
There's there's a lass back there too
We're also assuming that when the government comes
I was knocking to come knocking
Turn my front door is supposed
Frappuccino come siphoning off data
Without anyone at the company knowing
When is prism taught us anything it's that the cover
It's like you don't want to give us your data
Let's go hack into your
Fiber optic
So in case there's a lot you can do
Except
Not have the stuff
I'm so you know there's also this idea that
Encryption is really your
Choice
So
If that's that's kind of demoralize I can sad because there are very few devices out there that are
Being sold
It is that I think that's going to change over time but they're just going to be
Too much backlash over privacy in that people will not
Many people should say will not buy these devices
Unless they know their data is at least encrypted
So with that in mind as a consumer maybe start looking for things that are only in
As a journalist I'm going to start asking
A lot more questions about this
Keep that in mind as I
Going to interview
Andrea's call who is the CEO of silk which is a company that makes the sense hub
And I will also say
Just for those of you guys who are out there and
Oh man
The netatmo gear
Which is from
That I know haha
They make a presence camera
Their stuff
Is
It's all data
Stored on a physical device
Or that the presence camera is on
Is a camera where the data is stored on the device are on an SD card
Aldo store
The server
Have yours
So if your privacy-conscious this is a good device
Are you
Because
It stays in your home and in your network
I don't believe it's encrypted though
Well it's still a step
I had its that you're not relying on
The company is providing the service to actually store your data you can control your own server if you like whether it's encrypted or not
At least you know
You're managing it and that's another challenge to an obstacle but
Within your realm of
Patrol little bit more
Right and if you don't want to manage it UK
Okay
So now
We will
Closeout
A Chia Pet show so much fun and information and we will go interview on Driscoll who is made this
Smart home hub and he is the former CTO of Mozilla so privacy is important
We are going to learn all about using actually facial recognition
Send to build a better smarter
Hey everyone welcome back
Did The Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Andrea's Google who is the
Founder and CEO of silk
How are you
I got the great to be here
Thanks for coming so you guys are introducing
Kickstarter
A Brand New Concept in the connected home
That is quite frankly beautiful
You better tell us what it is
Actually what you're trying to make is a device that can act as the ears and eyes and importantly the brain of your house
Respond to you and help you with all the it device.
Okay
So
It is
Fruit for you guys who are like there
Okay that sounds kind of cool
It is a smart home hub
It has Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Has a camera
And it does image recognition
For me it when I saw it I was
So it's like the welcome camera combined
You know me software that like
Controls
All of your
Devices
Plus something else
And that something else is
Port of the IntelliJ
But
It's hot out so I haven't tried it
Your address is here to tell us kind of like
Why he built
So
Why are you guys doing this
Because
Excited about the potential
Listen to don't think such devices
But you're not really satisfied this is state
The art
As you can buy them in a store today
Something not intelligent and not responsive enough
You have to come home and
Use a smartphone to control your house
And said I want to come home and
I want my house to recognize me
That was the driving force behind making this device
It in the demos that I've seen it
Basically this thing when someone walks
I recognize this person's face and I know what they like and so I'm turning on their radio station
Nest thermostat to what they like and I'm playing their music
And
It's kind of cool
It kind of gets to this idea that I'm hearing a lot more from start-ups which is your smart home should be responsive
Not actually smart
Because smart is just like
It's not happening
Is that a fair assessment
Call from Santa
Smart
Wifi light bulb
W not smart at all they just remote controlled by a smartphone
Search for use of the word smart
Staying away from the term smarter than you use responsible for intelligent instead
Because the word smartass or overloaded
And used for devices that we don't leave receive a smart or intelligent
And you told me about your nest as an example of a first-generation
And if connected home product can you kind of talk to me a little bit about what a first gen
Product
Is an
Why that's a problem
Yeah so it was Nest devices
Until then
Some promised
This idea that the heating in your house will self-regulate
After that, said that's very much rooted is built on the Harborside
On the hardware side he was very simple sensors
Motion detector
How many people are in the room
And they cannot tell the people apart
O'mighty changing a second
On the nest
He doesn't bring enough
Different resources
Do they make Intelligent Decisions for you is be limited in this reflects often experience
Tell you that
The device canopy
Deborah heater a lot of people in the end and start using it
Beautiful Emmanuel and non smart thermostat
So you were telling me that you like your nest for example at 65 and your girlfriend likes it at 75
And so
From your disrespect
It just knows that there's this
Continuum Shift back and forth
Temperature
So for your device
It would know that
Not necessarily you but a person that looks like you
A person. Completely different person it would be changing the temperature because got the facial
Mission
I think that the first step to be able to solve
These problems
Offer
Experiences for these devices to understand their surroundings
It's not enough that the motion sensor that tells you there's something moving a room just one or multiple people or pets
You have to have something in it
What happens around
So this is why they're bringing a lot of computational power
Miss Tobias
Camera in your room
I can see the individual of people there you can read recognize familiar people
It's a flex strangers
Information to use to make my own decisions for you
So then
That's the problem
Now how do you actually
If you were telling me with your girlfriend
The solution is its just 75 in
People that individual preference
Probably is until you have sufficient information to understand what's going on
You cannot offer any meaningful solution to this
Schedule nest if there's two people in the house that like different temperatures
Onesti's going to see that
The temperature has been set back and forth
Palio's
And then not be able to understand that this is because
Sometimes you're cool and sometimes you warm because two people fighting over thermostat
Soproxi the first episode
Increased amount of information is available to understand what's going on
In our case we can do the receipt that two different people are selling used to be different temperatures
Which one would you prefer to apply
Are the same time
Go Solutions
The previously
Penis
It goes back between two temperatures when sitting in the middle
Atlantic bullion happy
Got it
It's obb
Temperature may not be a great
Like example for this because it's pretty
Fighter you're either hot or cold
In a lot of ways you know where you can make everyone unhappy
What's the temperature at 7
You're too boring your girlfriend
Cold
But for things like
Lighting it might be really interesting because you know
Don't you see the whole family's coming home or maybe a bunch of strangers are over in your house can be lies
Maybe they're having a dinner party or maybe this is happy
And then
Does become
Interesting
It can make
With greater
Pieces of information that can make
Decisions that could be useful
So I like this
Now
With the idea of bringing facial recognition into it and having a camera that's something that people get freaked out of
So how are you going to dress ideas
Oh my God there's a camera in my house and
There's a whole search engine right now
People can have
Hack into cameras and that's freaking them out
I don't know
What about that
People in
They don't want their naked butts on the way
That's how you can sum up camera
People's houses right now
I can very much later that I spent the last seven years or so of my life
Looking for Missoula
Most recent technology
Important to me and
I'm very much worried about these developments
What's wrong with you by don't answer example
It's almost as if Google is moving in as your roommate
It's always watching you
420 concert yard
Spy camera devices
So this is one of the reasons that you put a lot of computational power into the device itself
Instabox able to do computer vision tasks locally in the device
I can talk to the cloud
But it does not have to send out the actual video stream
All your personal data on all the imagery stays inside your house
And advise maybe sense off bedtime for me
Notified When a Stranger is in your house
It's not recognized by the device
Analysis of all the pictures
But not send it to the cloud
The only thing that would be sent to the cloud is one actually financially if someone recognized
And a picture with not knowing who the Clown
Okay that's awesome so it has to have some Cloud connectivity
Could it be set up so there is no connect Cloud connectivity through like my own after
To be server or anything like that
Absolutely does not rely on the cloud at all
The demo that before you earlier
Actually it is complete
Because I didn't want to rely on
Current connectivity
Do you use for car connectivity
You can do that
Is it preferred that is completed
It's a possibility as well
Baby trying to put all the data
In your house after you control
You decide what happens
And you know we're going somewhere doesn't
Okay that's really promising
Cuz I know I got a lot of
I got a lot of people ask
Give me about
Good devices if there
Worried about that sort of
Is there a slot for an SD card if I want to save anything
SD card for internal storage
Device if you do that because someone can come in and steal the device in the new SD card is gone
Seth Rollins
Information that might affect your privacy so
Weekend
Not notify you and not store videos
The stranger the house at longer someone
Hungrier in the house
Limited to Simply if there's nobody know the device in the house and a stranger pops up then you can send a video clip to you
In stored in the cloud
Giving you so much better degree of course
What's happening around it
And how because
One of the things is the smarter these things get the more difficult it is
Programming
Or rather maybe it's
The Dumber they are the more difficult it is
How to program them
Because you're sitting here going
If this then that
My experience
Playing with a lot of my
So how is it that I am supposed
The program
This particular
Yeah so there such things as I think it's make it accessible to much broader range of people
Am I mature I'm smart enough to program is this my parents cannot do that
Technology that makes
Feast of Isis
Smart intelligent than accessible to everyone
You can sweetie program you don't have to program or device
Behaviors
The device essentially interacts with you and tries to learn your behavior
It's okay have to program it
Ability for developers to get access to the device and they can
Programs they can publish them in the marketplace
Would like these experiences
Meet Developers
What are consumed by consumers will Marketplace that's easier than having to program the device directly
It's similar to the way that you go to that Apple Store
ITunes Store
Will the Android Google Play Store on the smartphones
Top 10 new behaviors and new capabilities for your device
How to program that yourself
So you guys are releasing an SDK along with
Switches awesome you also are trying to build this app store mod
Which
Because I've been doing this for a really long time
I have heard before so I would love to understand because historically this hasn't worked as well
Partially because
The audience hasn't been big is very hard to make a market for this order
And also because
Actually supposed to because there isn't a huge market for a lot of these apps
Developers haven't slept
Because there is no mark
So
How are you guys going
Kind of seed this and how are you guys doing
Yeah so it's actually really right now there's more learning
Rotation this message right to really unlock what these experiences feel like
And the way you want to interact this is ontology
Cisco's device of Jamaica right now
It's not going to get the mouse Market
Is aiming in early adopters and developers who would like to learn the sauce
What are the right behaviors and what is intelligent behavior that they won't have home devices
Does Marketplace is not
Meant as a place right now to make money for us for fathers
Amen to the place where
Experience
Early adopters
The first McDonald in Estacada and learn how to program this device
Would like to
In the future when I come home and stop this happens for me
But for soda coupons
We can bring into existence today
This is like a dream this Kickstarter
Okay well I want to live in that world
So
If I want to live in that world today I would give you guys $249 I believe
On Kickstarter
And then I would get this when do you think it'll ship
Century in Ventura
And we have
Designs that we will have a short video off on pages
Tektronix and deductible design for this
And they also fail far along the soffit pieces in the air show in a couple demo stuff that here and there
Visol dated this year
Okay I can't wait
I definitely will
I don't have a $250 for a hug
Okay let me think about it
I will think about it
Especially the ones that you can buy today like
It's a little thing at the hot in the closet
End up
It's necessary so some other device function
Experience.
I strongly believe in five or ten years all of us will experience today
Given the nature of what it does I feel like I would have to have this piece of the future like in a couple rooms of my house
Hold me back a little
In the future you will
Stop device like this
He's got that ability some devices all around your house
And Austin is not being dedicated devices
4K TV these days too often with a camera built in
Spy camera
I sent you this is this is this technology
We would like to help the industry
Cameras and other sensors in there and also to visit in a better privacy
Preserving faith
Today at countryview are using
Even if you only have one device that you have purchased
Kickstarter
He might be able to see you only one room
Signature if you're carrying a funeral miss you
Let me know when you are home
What can you use the house for another door because you Lucas
So it is not
Exactly the rolled in 5 or 10 years where there's a camera on a device I can every room
And you to put this device in a prominent position in the living room
Design it was a very nice appealing
Physical design that fits into your life in your living room
Is there a charge to put in a place where it can see you
Got it yes I think I would rather trust you over you know baby Samsung
Or any of the other big device manufacturers with a camera in my living room
I mean we have a lot back on doing this
I have done personally
Missoula last 7 years
Working on improving the state of privacy on the internet
But you're not
Because
You seem to be more trustworthy than some others
Fundamental design devices
Technology that makes it impossible to get this wrong
What are some things to do for the video streaming software example
Is the device is a smartphone
Using short distance
Is Bluetooth called acacian to exchange cryptographic keys
And then she can only be exchanged if you're very close physical proximity
The device
Only did that key on your smartphone can you ever watch
A stream of the device
Give me a shout when you're traveling
Smartphones for direct physical proximity
Wait to see that stream
So it might seem
Scary articles on my search engines for little things baking like watching other people's cameras by either
Defective camera
Or I'm flexible losing a password or someone guessing their password
Search engine
Because obviously Miss end-to-end encrypted between you and a smartphone
Add devices in your house
Okay that's a bold statement
Maybe I will do
Okay
Well thank you so much Andreas for coming on the show.
Thanks very much
That doesn't fit this week's episode
Thank you for listening and please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast