Hey everyone welcome to the internet
Podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
On this week's show we're going to be talking about Verizon's new network for The Internet of Things
We're going to give you an update on last week's Nest story
And we're also going to talk about some new devices from the
Capri plus we're going to do a review of the wink relay that Kevin has in
Stalled in the middle of all this we're going to have a message from our sponsor macadamia
And after that we're talking to our guests this week
Corey Reed of John Deere about Precision agriculture
It's going to be a great show
Alright let's kick it off with
A new iot network
Verizon has
Teamed up with
Welcome
And last week launched
Okay here we go Cabin
LGE
Cat M1
Network
Cat M1 number and we got
So actually
It's not that red
I figured it wasn't
I was just going to
With the Telco standards
It's that the GSM organization has its
CPT 3 piece
3gpp
1 G 3 and 3 piece
Got it
They actually for all their LT
Twohey's
And other version
Stop they have categories
So
Cat and
1 stands for
It's the it's the
Machine category
Unlike those Telco
Stages
You're so clever
Alright so you guys don't have to
I care about this what you do need to care about is
This is a cellular modem
That has
10 years
Battery life
And deliver speeds of
Between 200 kilobits per second and 400
So
Not crazy.
You actually do something
Especially if you're just sending random bits of data like
Temperature in time
Probably perfect for a M2M type
Transmission
Yes and
Am I thinking
Is that this is going to be kind of bad news first
Samantha Laura
Boats the Sig foxes of the world
Ingenue although
And I'm
These are all the folks
We're trying to create their own iot network
Yes there are actually have greater
Yes
And so
AT&T is testing
Cat
And1 net worth
In San Francisco
Verizon says there's is going to be out by the
Beginning of next year
Which is
Crazy fast
Basically putting this on their existing
Is justice
And I think
We'll see a lot of
Companies that
Leica Fleet Management
Those kind of Apple
Applications
Choose
A carrier because they're trusted
They know what they're doing presumably
Over some of these upstart net
I do think
That Laura and maybe sick Fox
Still have an opportunity
If you're like
Trying to build a service on your own like so if you're like
I'm trying to pick up
The big mining company whose Name Escapes Me
Rio Tinto
If you are Rio Tinto if you want to build a low-power wireless area network it may make sense for you just to build your own cuz you've got
So much you want to monitor in a limited area
But
Brother people
I'm thinking they're probably going to
I suspect you are correct
So the early first-mover type
Networks I mean I applaud what they've done but I I kind of
The same as you on this one
It's interesting to me that Verizon is also integrating its thing space
Platform-as-a-service within the modem
So they are
Cut a deal here with Qualcomm
Just before the show you and I were talking like this is that
Does that mean this modem looks
Exclusively use thingspace platform I don't think so
I think it's just a
Option in there
I think you're probably right it makes sense
This is great though because
For people who
Are not going to
Like you don't want to spend the time at building their own platform I just want to put a chip in it and have a cigarette sending data
This makes a lot of sense
That's great for Verizon
And it's good for actually think space
And
One of my my favorite little company's bug Labs is actually one of the
Core pieces of inertia
Traction things
Farm sale
Shout out to them
Good Vibes
Yeah
Set Verizon actually already has a
Customer for their new cat one
Cat M1
Iot solution
Because they also announced that
I said what's going on right now the
Ctia super Mobility
Super Mobility 2016
16 show
Verizon announced that it is working with a water metering
Company
Neptune Technology Group
And actually there are two other modems also Qualcomm modem
LTE modems
B
First one is
Pacifically for electrical
Utilities
Also has a 10-year battery life
And connectivity
10 megabits per second which really
It seems like Overkill to me but it is what it is
And then for water and gas companies will you get a
I guess someone call it a dumb down modem but you get one that goes up to 1 megabits per second
More than plenty both of these are I think Carly 2017 as well
Yes
And
The 10 megabits could be interesting for sending video I know that AT&T is also doing some work with Qualcomm
On their drone platform to send video from neutrons
Excel
Going to be really interesting now that the
Carrier
Like oh
We've really got to do this
So let's make it happen
Moving on to net
Last week we told you that nests
Are software Developers
We're going over to Google
And we were asking lots of questions about what that meant
Well I talked to Miss This
This weekend they said that it's not all of their software.
It is just those working with the work
Nest
So
The thought here is it there going to be
Creating this like
Singleplatform
PetSmart
But yes
They're going to create a single platform for
Nest
Google products
They work well together
I'm not a hundred percent sure
What that means for some of the Sanders that we seem like you don't believe that
There are two of them
But I think it's a really good sign because Google is clearly
With Google home
That hopefully we'll hear more about on October
Is a big play in the Smart Home
And it makes sense that they would want to integrate that with nest
Yeah that's my hope is that if they're both there will be a Google home announcer cuz the product is supposed to launch this year
Google set an IO back in May
I don't know if I'm stages are going to talk about this aspect of it the whole works with nest and what they're doing with nests and how it
What size in a Google home if it does
But I suspect that follow up
Recording will hopefully give us answers
Indeed
And
We should also say that
It was this week or last week right after the show last week with the one-year anniversary of the on
Onhub router baidu
Have one about 1
As a consumer before I start working for Google
The one-year anniversary celebration
Added support for
Phillips
Hue light controls
Through your onhub witches
Sort of misleading in a sense because you still need the
Hue Bridge
And you access your lighting through the web
Can you go to
Oh shoot is it on me let me get it right
Let me get right
On. Here
In a browser
And once you
Go to on. Here
On your local network free web page will show you
The Philips Hue devices as well as any Chromecast
So that's
That's not exactly new their butt
So
It's kind of just taking the place of the
Hue app I guess
Really awkward way
What I would imagine is
Once you start building these Integrations
Between these two devices
For example
Maybe we're going to see more war Integrations on Beyond
I don't know again this Miss
This ties into like oh Google and Nest coming together and maybe works with Nest becomes the Google platform
Integrated Smart Home
Much like
Homekit is for apple
Speaking of homekit we should acknowledge that
Apple event
Set to happen this afternoon
Sarah
We're not talking about anything you have to wait till next week
To get our Impressions thoughts
If their impression / thoughts
Oh I'm sure there
We were never short of an opinion
True
Okay so
The other thing
Nest has
Hangout
I just
I can't
Having
That's just in the middle of
Let's just call it a crime
It's like the media is just beating up on it at lost its founder co-founding CEO after but
How much people like this guy is
Really micromanaging and kind of
There's a lot of questions like Google you spent
3.2 billion on this thing
And
Basically
No new hardware
So
Nest has
Decided to
Release new hardware
Actually there is actual physical Hardware
Today
Basically
It is launching the outdoor camera
You guys about
So that is happening and you
You can buy that
It is adding
3DO colors
To The Nest Thermostat
Which I kind of like wow you're in a lot of drama
A lot of pain
And you updated your thermostat
3D colors
Those colors are copper White
In a carbon steel
Black
That already has
That already exist everything will be available starting
For September 8th
With the exception of the white thermostat
Which will be available set
And
Then is also launching a new service
Called sightline
This is actually really interesting this is for the outdoor camera
Internet scams
And it's basically a way to comb through the
Hours of video that you guys are going
Cameras always on always recording
Basically recognize this when something significant happens
And then creates a thumbnail
Around that
I can send you that from now is it
Acacia
So
It's actually a really nice
So that's
Interesting to me because I'm seeing a big push for
The application of machine learning in Google products
Example would be if he's the inbox app
The smart replies
Machine learning is used to generate a smart replies and
That's kind of interesting so
That sounds like that's what they're doing cuz I also know that machine learning is what they've used
Photos
Help with identification of things and searches and so on.
Good I know I sent a lot of pictures of
My dog Norman
I was just showing somebody in photos like a let me show you know when I just type dog and boom every single dog picture showed up
It's not just search
It's also
Machine learning from what I understand
It sounds like that's what they're doing here
It is
I'm in it's important to note that the Dropcam
19 habits
Mission and vision as well
Write before Google bought them
And I assume that were continued when they got the influx
Scrum
Yeah so what this does is
Like what's a the UPS man is coming up to your door
The outdoor camera
Will just be like
I saw it in action like
Leaves blowing did not register ism
Bread at all
But a squirrel passing
See through
I'm passing through
Did
And you basically get this cool
Timeline view that has like
Thumbnails where something
Interesting changed
That I love because
Separates the signal of under noise really adds a lot of value
I like that
Who is the fastest
When it sends notification it will
Not it will say we think we saw a person
Or
We saw a person
There is act
So there is activity is the lowest level
And that you get when
You don't like the Squirrel Run
Crossword
A car passes by
And then you'll get a thumbnail
When you click on that notification
That shows you the
So you can see
It's a raccoon
It'd be nice if you could
Kind of sum up or thumb down this
Can you teach it was important to you in a few
So you can't do that
I did ask about facial
Position in Africa
That doesn't seem to be
Priority
For them
Yeah
Maybe it will be
Overtime
It seems really good
And you can ignore
A lot of the notifications if you're like a
I don't really care if the car pass by I only lyrics
There is definitively a person here
So
That isn't that also helps at work and say it has a doorbell camera
To be honest
Schedule you should get your notification.
And then you can talk to the person
Outside your door
Sounds good
Sounds good we'll see
Daddy's out of trees how that works on the battery life and how many notifications you get depending on how many cameras you have
The Killer
But having had a camera facing outdoors I have
Welcome Cameron I had a facing outdoors and I was getting notifications
All the time
Because like
I was just going to say at some point it becomes so annoying that you stopped using the product you might as well just sit on the front doorstep and just watch for yourself
Exactly
Yeah so
That's the new Nest news out in that site line is going to become part of
Of the nest aware
Service
So you only get syteline
With the nest aware service
Otherwise normal users will get
3 hour
Window
If you don't pay for the subscription you get a 3-hour window of what's Happening
They're really upping the ante they're on the sea
Services
How to make money
Airport all that
Streaming video they're sitting in a
Okay that is the best news what else do we
We have we have
Oh
You out yet because you're going to use the
I will say it
De ligt wink
Hub 2
Cuz it before on the show we were saying the winkley Cub to inactive
Working on self
Dave's ass
Sue right there that's not funny, I'm also a good friend of mine that I saw this weekend
He shot me an email this morning said hey you might want to take a look at this on Reddit and sure enough
Somebody went to a Home Depot and was using a
Computer inventory system which
Why the ban on Reddit if that's
Publicly available.
People like I use it all the time I go and only one disease that I've never done that
But in case somebody did it they found
For $99 in the Home Depot inventory
Coming soon
Wink hub
2 499
Lux and then
There's also a link to Amazon
And if you go to Amazon you can find the wink Hub 2
Temporarily out of stock of course cuz I haven't been announced yet
I also she has a price of $99 so
We don't have much
Information on this because it's like I love my when Colin like what else would I want with it but
According to Amazon it says that they have a
More powerful wifi radio in the wink Hub 2
And many people will be happy in Ethernet port
I don't want to
That's just me
I also a stronger processor
Not faster stronger
And more memory to make your smartphone faster
As if your smart home move switch it doesn't
They say that on Amazon that
Original wink Hub owners
Upgrading can easily transfer your ecosystem connected products in under a minute
And it's sleek
Modern industrial design makes it worthy of standing alone on your coffee table or bookshelf
Which you better hook your router is nearby if it hasn't even at ports
I'm still happy with the wink Hub so
There wasn't much missing but I think people will be happy with
You don't have to
No one's going to try your way no one's going to make you sweat
Having stronger
Given the timing.
And it clearly has a new Wi-Fi
And I just saw this buried in the product
Prescription not in the bullet points it says hubba 2 is compatible
With more smart home technology
That lends a little Credence to your thought they're on homekit
It's possible
So
Maybe
We don't know when we're going to see
It is exciting
I would probably switch
Because
I actually
Want to put my wink hub
Not in the middle of my house
Would like to be hanging off my router
Cuz I have a lovely Little Shelter
On the floor in the hallway so I can point well taken
So I love this idea
I love
The idea that they're going to Knicks
The transition easy
This is kind of become
Table Stakes for
Upgrading your hub
SmartThings had an easy kind of upgrade pattern so did the Staples
Hub when it existed
And the Philips Hue also
What software
That's hard stuff
To transition your step
Easily
And best of all
We have to share this
It's a footswitch
Amazon list
Yes
Yeah you this will be hard to find if you didn't know you were looking for a look inside
Industrial electrical
Devices controls and indicators
Then industrial switches and finally the last subcategory
Foot switches
That's just
Things like I have a foot pedal for operating a sewing machine
So want to turn your lights on just kick the Hub 2
There you go
So yeah
And the price
Is a little bit more than the kuragin
Wink
Which I believe is going
At a high-end for like about a TB
But it's in line with the SmartThings second gen product
Rich
Okay and it's cheaper than Amazon Echo
Which insect has to make some money
Yeah I think they make money at all the other devices they make
Wheel of the wink hub
Well wait until you what
Think about this version
And this
Talk about perfect able to talk about the wink relay
Yes I only have one I don't know if you said earlier in the show relays but I only have one
Review unit
And it is installed
Kind of wish I had to because I could have tested that cool intercom feature
Where you just press a button and talk from one wink relay in your house to another
But that's okay I will just shouting
I guess I've had it installed for about a week and a half now
Generally pretty happy
It's larger than I expected
It's it's at least 6 inch by 6 inch I would say
So it's it's pretty big I mean
In my house and took the place of one rocker switch
So it's a big difference
To have
A larger
Device there on the wall but
Put in the bedroom
Liquid took me 20 minutes
Install not difficult very good instructions include all the tools little screwdriver with both Phillips head and
Flathead so
Literally simple to install just make sure you turn off your breaker first
It's very important for any installation
It's neat meaning for people who have not seen it is a
Small touch screen
Along with two buttons on the right hand side of it and those buttons
One takes the place
Can take the place of the switch that you replacing so to speak
So
This is Eric our closet
Switch and I just
Press the hardware button
It's just like I used to have the talk about in there now just
And then you can assign the other button to anything you'd like I would
To turn on the air-conditioning for sale
Touchscreen itself
It's interesting and I didn't know this and maybe you did I don't know if you did did you know this thing runs Android o
I think I did
I didn't say it because
Cuz I didn't think it was that big
Will know it was just interesting to me and and what what clued me
Into this was the first time after I installed it
It said upgrading applications one of 43. Just like an Android phone would after an Android update
Sorry I actually asked that
Wink.
When was the touchscreen replicates The Wing Cap to a large
Degree that you would put on your
IPhone your Android device
All of your shortcuts that you previously set up for your wink hub
Just automatically appear
Only shows 2 shortcuts at a time that you can just
Swipe over and see the rest of them so
You can reorder them and so on so it's kind of nice
And then have witches as well and has widgets that show
Whatever you like such as the time temperature the weather and so on so
How do you put your Fitbit on there
You you could connect and Link a Fitbit and then therefore see your steps and Daily Progress and such
I did not and the only reason I did not is because
Bad timing
I literally just left the Fitbit ecosystem
Because I'm using the polar m600 Android Wear watch
Which
Is
Exercise activity focus and has Android Wear so it's kind of The Best of Both Worlds tomato
I stopped using Fitbit right at the time
That I got to read
Kevin ru
I'm so so sorry and besides I don't think I want like my weight showing up on the wall
Everyday
Yes they'll be motivated for the kids make fun of their dad
It's an interesting product not to use a pun here but
There's been one little quirk
For some reason
The touchscreen you can set it too hot to go on automatically with the proximity sensor
Or you can
Disable the proximity sensor and tap the screen to wake it up
What a headset for the proximity sensor for some reason in the middle of the night
The screen keep coming on
Anna
And on and we're just sleeping just laying around
Any kind of brighten the room
Psycho that's got to stop
My wife complains about it so I went to the touch
Based only and when you have the touch option
Obviously touch the screen comes on for
Set amount of time but there's also wait
Tap to turn off so you
You can turn it off so it's not on
Too long the strange thing is at least twice now
In that mode when I tap the screen nothing is happening
And
Frustrated and finally there's a very small hidden button at the bottom of the wink relay
To reboot it and I've done that and that seems to get it working again for a couple days so
I don't know if my wiring I don't know what it is but every once in awhile it just doesn't respond
Does it not respond for a while
No it just does not respond for a while
Weird thing is not so weird but the annoying thing is when you're rebooting or when the touch screen isn't working
Even that Hardware button to turn the actual light on the physical button
Doesn't work
Yeah so that's where it gets really
You like all I can't see my closet
You're like I'm standing in the dark
Yeah
Could be again could be a corker
You're my wiring or something like that I don't know
I thought I mentioned
No that's good
Right on
Until I wish two things I wish
It could act as a remote sensor for my ecobee3 because it really
Is gathering information to sensors are there
Or temperature and humidity inside
But I can't and that's fine that's that's an integration bit it's not a problem with the product itself
Elsa related
I can't really use it
With my ecobee that much because
You can't set a wink shortcut for
Temperature setting
With the ecobee
Like you could I
I thought you could wait
I don't recall it's been awhile
So really I can't do anything with my
Thermostat
This
Palmer
Okay
Create like a robot in the actual app
And then have it
From there
Haven't found a way to do it
Perhaps there's a way and I
Just didn't find it yet
No one
Yeah like what in the Wink app you can actually set your
Your temperature because you have a little rotary-dial
You know and you just type whatever you want
I haven't seen where to do a shortcut reset
Temperature
Got it
Yeah so if you can't do in the Wing Cap you can't do it on wink realize what I'm gathering
You can do it
With the echo
Stop
Although when you do that
I've noticed that
It doesn't resume
Like your schedule it keeps that temp
I'm sure the settler ever forever so you have to be careful when you do that
Yeah
Okay
So we
Are pretty much out of time
History
What about next week
Stay tuned for
A message from our sponsor
And then
After that
Argos
Text Corey read a John Deere used
Culture and how to build a business
Based on connected services
Hey everyone this is Stacy I am breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a quick word from our sponsor this week Spa
Cancer is macadamia and they are an iot user experience
Zen design firm
And this week's product that we're going to talk about is a Kinect
Conference room
So first we have
Scott Lewis here to talk about
Their work with a company called built IO
Scott what exactly did you guys built
What does in general is just allow
Organizations
To manage them
For a user
What you see depends on
The different scenarios
So I might want to
You know all the sudden just have an impromptu meeting I look up
And see the green light outside my meeting room
I know now is open I can go in
Another scenario that
Perhaps Love got a meeting running long
Can I stay in there or do I need
The late again tells me
So
That type
Love scenario is what makes
Super youth
And I can do that be
Because it understands underlined
Technology understand how people book things on the calendar
And it will even tell people friends
Hey
Looks like you're not using the meeting
Cuz it can sense other people are in there is it okay if I just freeze it up
It's really about the
Solution being non-intrusive
So rather than you have the technology yelling at you that you need to
Cynosure
Conference
Instead of kind of gives you a gentle nudge
You're not there for the technology you're there for the meeting
Are the Technologies actually helping
I'd love to under
1st and
Why you picked that for
Killer problems
Mount Scott
So what coyotes really about is solving practical
Problems
The distances are people have day today using technology and simple elegant way and this was a perfect exam
Clojure problems that come up all the time
Meeting room scheduling is a nightmare
And
If you can
Solve that problem
Simple technology
Why not
Is there anything you
Thomas The Internet of Things
The thing that we've been looking for in technology ever since
Started
Building spaceship
We want to move towards
The future but we want to do it in such a way where technology enables Our Lives
But it's not in your face
And today
Starting with iot we actually finally have something
Platform
Several
That allows technology of Truliant
And Scott
How can we find you
You can find us at
Macadamia
Dot-com
Flash built
Now back to the show
Hey everyone welcome back to the internet
This is your house
And this week's guest is Corey read a senior vice president of the intelligent solutions group at John Deere
Corey thanks for coming on the show today
Hey Stacy it's good to be here
You guys started your Journey 2
Businesses and products
A long time ago I feel like I've been reading about your Kinect
Contractors for
With five or six years at least
So can you let a talk about
How John Deere started
The king about connectivity in there
Yeah absolutely soaked
You're really the Precision AG business started for us nearly 20 years ago
Started in the precise positioning business the guidance based business and we acquire small company to do that and
We've been building on it ever since
And what are those
Precision-guided
Is that
Your Corrin
Primary product
Or how should I think of that is that just an enabler for all your
It's one of the critical enablers of precision agriculture overall so
Technically it's about bouncing low-watt signals off of satellites that are moving through space at
Very rapid
Speed and being able to
Use a position receiver so an antenna that sits on a a tractor
Understand exactly where that tractor is and then being able to use correction signals to help
Automated drive those vehicles to really tied accuracy on the ground so within an inch
Of actress in many cases that allows those machines to position themselves appropriately
Know where they are and then know what seeds chemicals in products they put in the ground
Okay and what has changed in the last
5 years
We're all talking about the internet
What did you guys
From your position of having had this system in place and then building it
Two decades
What are you thinking of adding her
Yeah I can tell you what's changed as you add on top of that precise positioning so the ability to know where you are
Lauren guided vehicle
To real-time communication so our vehicles are going out the door
At the end of this year with
4G LTE Wi-Fi Bluetooth enabled communication devices
Take the combination
A precise positioning in the ability for real-time communication on and off those vehicles
They become a real platform for unlocking the next generation of products and services in Precision AG
And
What about the role of artificial
Because
When I look at the Internet of Things
The next big thing is
Actually having computers help me
Decision so I'm curious where
You guys think that might go and precision
Absolutely if you take automated driving a vehicle she had to that on and off board Communications
You can start to think about how
Whether it's
Intelligence that sits off border machine is data is being communicated
Into service providers like a John Deere dealer who may be able to provide
Uptime services or to an input provider or egg retailer
Who can make a recommendation on the type of seed or the type of
Crop protection product to be used
On a sealed now all of a sudden that
Connectivity enables the best intelligence the best
Processing that can be done anywhere to be moved quickly on and off of a vehicle
A lot of people think of farmers is not being
TekSavvy
And I wash Eternal actually tested a story
On this
Talking about a
Case IH
Cabless tractor that basically is a self-driving tractor
Ashanti the farm show
And their headline was Farm Show visitors marble
Scott
Contractor and I thought it was kind of funny
Because this is very much what it feels like Precision agriculture is moving towards this idea of machines doing
So I'm curious in your
Experience with your customers
Are they tech-savvy are they worried about
Are they stopping at self driving tractors probably one of the most
Analogically Savvy groups of of most of of industrial Industries if you will if you think about
Farming it is
The production of a crop in an open biological system so you have weather
Do you have a lot of things that can happen with pests
She have a lot of
Characteristics of soil
Nutrients that all come out
At the same time to help either produce a crop for profit or not
What a lot of producers have done is they've invested a lot in technologies that help them understand how to get the most
Out of the primary tools that use their operation starts with their land
Every piece of land is different across North America the characteristics of it is different they've had to invest in a lot of Technology
Jesus help them understand what is the potential of that land
And then this Technologies helping them understand how do I unlock
How do I select the right
Seed chemical fertilizer
But in addition what can I use in terms of the best
Agricultural Equipment Technology
Be able to ensure that everything I do is done consistently with maximizing the profitability
On that land so
Able to grow more and in many cases do it with less
How long is it good for the bottom line it's also good for the environment so
Technology has been a big part of the generational change in their culture in the last
20 years
The automation silent one of the things that's happened
Agriculture largely the labor required to produce a crop has been reduced dramatically over the last
50 here so automation is interesting
It's more interesting in terms of
Troll
How do you actually plant better
Spray better
Harvest better not
How do you reduce labor most of the laborers already out of the crop now certainly labor variability is important
And producers are interested in how you control for the variable of different operators in the field
That's why I'm automation is exciting so
I don't think they scoff it automation
So to speak but how it's used I think it's most important
Do you guys have plans for a self-driving tractor
We've actually introduced a self-driving tractor over 10 years ago we had them running
In fields in the Southeast running in areas like Orchards and Vineyards where there's they're spraying chemicals and fertile
Weiser stats
That you don't want people exposed to in the environment so it's
It's not about the availability of the technology it's about what's the highest value use of the technology certainly one
One of the things we can do with that and have done in the past
Is creative fully autonomous systems
A lot of producers actually like to be involved in the system they like to be in the seat they like to be able to maybe to do other things
Thanks from the cab so use that communication technology to communicate on and off to their technical advisers or maybe Market there
I think a lot of the commentary here is when our people ready for that system to be the predominant system
When do you think that might be
I'm not sure I think we're prepared for it if they wanted to go there in a couple years we would be there right now
If you think about what's happening I'll use an example for you
In the last
50 years and certainly in the last
100 years
There's less than 1% of the labor required than what they're used to be to create a ton of wheat or a hundred
Bushels of corn
Actually a lot of the labor is out of the production of the crop what's change though
Is the value of the inputs that flow through the hour in the field that someone has with a p
Equipment weather to tractor combine
A springer is increased by a hundredfold over that same period of time
Actually
The use of technology for Automation and control over the execution in the field
Of the jobs that are getting done
Is far more valuable to a producer
Then to be able to take that last one percent of Labor
Out of the equation
Got it
So later is not the issue
Making them
Biggest best bang for your buck
For your fertilizer for your water
Absolutely in labor isn't where I don't want to leave you with the impression that labor is not important it certainly is because
Variability of Labor from one operator to the next
It doesn't necessarily take so long Tommy to do that it takes control systems to be able to do that Metairie see a lot of
In the industry going
Is in two control systems that help manage the variability
The ultimate in that is to reduce the variable of Labor altogether and reduce the person
We see that as an opportunity
Potentially but not as the priority
Okay
So let's talk about how this plays out in your business
Because
You guys
Spell actual
Trackers
And combines
You are so
Data and then I believe you sell
Advisorservices to Armour
As well so
Walk me through
Kind of the role that connect
Activity the dimensions that is added to John Deere
Can certainly Precision AG technology overall
The role is to both help differentiate the underlined product the track
Combine
Sprayer
Planter
That we sell
And it does to that it helps those products
Work even better and helps
Them execute in a way that maximizes yield manage cost
It's also expected to be a good business
Like any other business within John Deere in for our shareholders and for a customers
Obviously we sell products like tractors and combines
We sell
Hardware in the position hbase like
Position receivers telematics devices displays
Who sells software things like activations for autotrakk or correction signals for guidance systems
Sell software that helps
Turn automatically machines on and off when they come to a point row if you think about control systems for sprayer nozzle
Score for planners
We also work with our dealers to sell services
Uptime services
Proactive maintenance
Services
And then we connect a lot of economic advisers
A lot of people who have core expertise in
Putting the right seat on the right
Acre putting the right nutrient at the right time in the ground
And we connect them through this Precision AG system to give Growers access to the best in the industry
So each of those represents
Not only profit opportunity for the the grower the producer
But also up a place where were John Deere can deliver value and
And collect value
What have you learned about pricing based on the diff
Products that you sell
One of the things that I think is really fascinating about
The products is
You have to account somewhere
For the cost of
Supporting a product in the long term
I'm so you guys might have rental fees for the Precision tracking
There's a cloud back-end fees for
Various things so
What if you guys kind of thought about
But how have you come to manage that
Obviously
Any pricing strategy starts with a firm understanding of how you're creating value
We look first
For which of the
Products whether it's a heart I am product
Software-as-a-service we can deliver
What are the things that we can do that point of the value being created in that space that's the starting point
And then we at we look across the
The chain of people involved in delivering it so if it's with us and our dealer and a customer
Shasta Creek
Value for the customer first and then there has to be enough margin that can be shared
Between those three components us are dealer in the producer
Ultimately that's a primary sort for how we think about which products actually make it to our portfolio process
If they create enough value
The available margin associated with the product
Can be shared
Across those in the still good marching in it for the customer
Value received versus what it cost
Then we'll move the clock forward
NM price it appropriately
If there isn't
Then it off and won't be at the front of our portfolio process to be worked on
Do you have any examples you can give us things
Maybe didn't
Give enough value caffe
I look at a lot of companies
I feel like they are
If this mentality of a put a chip in it
Put some analytics on it
And I don't know how far ahead they're thinking
Thought their pricing strategies and like the number of people who might have dropped it that they have to support over
So
Any more color you have there
Would be wonderful
We've done some of the automation space I use one itec pro as an automated turn back to the automation
Conversation
Some producers really like it either say hey
I'm willing to actually turn on the End of the Roll myself so we can almost fully
Automate
In field operations of a tractor today
For some producers
They just rather turn on the end I know my operators involved in responding and being aware
I would rather have them do that on their own so that's product while we're offering it today
It doesn't have the same kind of take rate to some of the high value products
I like section control or the ability from a row by row perspective to turn your planner on and off or you
Your nozzles on your sprayer
Specialty Products it at both ends of that Spectrum
We'll just wait till in a couple years when nobody else knows how to drive because
Autonomous cars are all the rage in the
No one knows how to turn at the end of his rope
Seeing and understanding the developments in the autonomous car industry in the fact that we kind of chuckled early because we've been
Drive down i80 between our headquarters in moline and des moines
Probably 70-plus percent of the tractors running on either side of Interstate 80
Already driving themselves and then we're talking about when will the day come when a car does that
Ultimately it's
It's an interesting
Challenge though because
While you can drive down I-80 or if you drive down I-75 I'll use
I use the Auto industry is a good example from Detroit to Miami
I will that highways fairly similar in the Technologies can be fairly consistent the farming that goes on either side of that Highway North
South is incredibly
Every Farm is different every field every crop
The complexity hbase is actually much higher
In the complexity in the automotive space now this steaks can be higher in the on-road environment have people's lives in
Obstacles in in those things involved in
That has a different dynamic
But actually the complexity of growing
Dozens of different crops and dozens of different soil types in different environments create a very complex
World and one that the egg industry has been out
Son of most other Industries in the area of automation
It has do you have anything you guys can teach your offer to the self-driving car manufacturer
I don't know how we can teach him we spent a lot of time talking to him allowed to Precision Technologies what we've learned is there's no
Single technology rely on exclusively
If you're going to be in the space you need to think about how to use
The best of all of the Technologies one of the areas we focused on
Isn't
And being able to merge
The different sensing type Technologies from
Visual to tactile to GPS
You get better Solutions
The more solutions you can pull together so what
Technology are you most looking forward to or what technology do you look at right now and you're like
Oh we in a Precision Adventist
Space we gotta get some of that
The awesome
We spent a lot of time in the
In the positioning area and and that's exciting
I think we're learning is how a lot of the technologies that have been around can be used
To do even more
Once you know where you are an example
We initially said the hey that was about yield then we said it's about driving a vehicle
Now the interplay between different Vehicles what are you using
GPS is your primary input or visual or a feeler system a tactile system
The ability to now manage between primary applications in a field
The ability to think about positioning of
Fleets
Differently and
Processing that goes along with that what's happened is
The ability to both process massive amounts of data in this is one thing Rado is helping us a lot
Because a lot of the processing power required is bringing down the cost of processing any of the use of cloud-based
System that allows to move data to where it's needed to be processed and then move it cleanly back on
Actually there's a limitless potential as to what you can do in the field
Strip challenge for industry not just of John Deere but our industry
Taking all those capabilities and boil it into products and services
That's fit the needs and the evolution of where customers are
Wanting to go
Today
Alright Corey thank you
You so much for
For coming on the show this
Happy to be here Stacy thanks
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
This week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to sign up
My newsletter Stacy knows things at
Stacey on iot. Com