Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Hey we have got it we are going to be talking about
Hotel rooms
Incriminating yourself with a pacemaker
The Boston Consulting Group
Some tips
Google home
Fitbit layoffs
We also have an open
Board update mini project discussion on how to start your smart home
Evereve a great guest for you this week is Felicity Mormon she is the CEO Stratus which is a company that connects
Apartments
So for all of you guys sitting there asking what can I do
The answer
Will come
After this week's News segment
So
Stay tuned for all of that
But first a word from this week's sponsor sponsor is Ayla Networks
Enterprise internet-of-things platform that is empowering the world's leading manufacturers by simplifying the inherent
Text complexity of the iot it's enabling them to turn their products in a smart connected systems and transform their businesses
Vista compete in the game changing world of connectivity agile iot platform abstracts the complex
City of developing connected products by some of the world's leading Brands so they can focus on what they do best
Ala solving the internet of things so you don't have to download their whitepaper 5 key traits of weed
Leading iot application enablement platforms at Stacey on iot. Com
Aylaa
All right back to the show Kevin
Should we get started with
Google thing
Sure wish I could start with Google things and it's
As long as we
Ride it my normal disclosure out that I do work full-time for Google as a consultant
I do not work in any way shape or form on their iot stuff so my opinion
Your pigeons
That's true I never give them away
So actually you do
You give your
If you give them away for
Free
That's right that's right this this actually surprised me this news so we talked about Google things a couple weeks ago which
Ryzen android-based iot platform from Google
Essentially take the place of
Cortical project brillo and all that
Yeah it's actually Google
Android
Just been named
Google thinks this is one of the many Google things but it's actually called Android thinks you're right
This is their platform
You said every place is Brillo
It's actually kind of platform it is connected device requires actually
Significant
SPAC shame the platform
Sorry
I had to say it
If it's okay
This is
This requires a lot of memory and isn't really for sensors it's more for things that will be
Controlling the Senate
I'm not fat shaming anybody
Just coming to
Jewel
Five seven
Which is
Call it it's a fact
Computer board it's a big computer
And I'm not touching it
Computing be like fat pigs especially if we wanted to make stuff with it
The jewel 570 is capable of doing
4K video
Ram it's got 16 gigabytes of storage and WiFi
And it's a big board
What is this
It surprises me because of the existing supported Android things boards Witcher
Lower power
Slimmer
If we go down that thing like the Raspberry Pi in Intel's Edison chip and XPS Pico board
This is using
A revamped Intel Atom Processor and again for Giga as you said
It supports even with the realsense 3D depth camera so it's adding a lot more power
I was just surprised because the other existing
Supported boards are
Not the Lesser boards but less are capable
Yes well I think this is actually really good because
This looks like a
Great board
Play with robotics
Because of the recent
3D depth
Capacity
So I think it's a really forward-looking move for Android
Just because
This is actually really interesting platform
For it robotics
Out of the Smart Home
Crazy iot
We haven't even really
Experience
Right at night I agree with your baby when I think of the traditional stuff that's supported you know you don't need all that power
But it's a good point
Looking had that things that move around
Things that
Need more power this does make sense it's going to be interesting to see what developers do with it cuz it I assume it'll be one of those
Developer cats on the Android things website soon cuz I don't see it there just yet
This could be good for like Industrial
Oreck commercial settings
They shouldn't miss out on
They should totally
If they can
And also who else should not
Miss out on the space and I didn't tell
Which because the spaces really been driven by a arm architecture type
Processing power
And yes Intel Edison is supported but I don't see many people Billy stuff on the Edison
By comparison to what they're building a Raspberry Pi's
And such a later in the show on a different arm board that you're going to be using for openhab2 nope so
Prevalently
This industry has been built on arm so
Again until can't miss out on that
All right
So let's
YouTube app
Because we can
Because we
Last week I promised to get started doing open house
Because there is now a new version of oppa
Have in this is a smart home
Hub Software System is open source
On the eclipse Foundation
Basically it is like the most powerful
Inflexible system out there
It requires a lot of technical
Or maybe not a lot that's what I mean
Discover
As an update on the project I went out and bought a
Ein
A 64 board Kevin already has one Kevin
Help me out with this
I went out and bought the 2GB combo set
Which has the board itself a Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Sheet module
A microSD card
With the software I'm going to need to run it all though
That's actually not the software on
Use
I'm going to use an opa
Have card
And
Power supply in a
And then I also bought
Easy way for
And so the total for these two things
90 bucks space
And that may sound like a lot
Now I got my pine64 I got the same board that you got I also bought it early right now you can buy that board for about
30 bucks
And that's just giving you all the processing power in your ports but
It's another $10 for example to add the Bluetooth Wi-Fi so that's in your starter kit
You're getting an acrylic case I don't have a case or mine actually took an old
Raspberry Pi case like I'm kind of covered in that regard
Power supply power supply is super important with pine64 anybody
He's buying app on 64 I highly recommend you get the power supply
When you buy the board
Even though it's a micro USB power supply
You like
Plenty of these must have a hundred things in my closet from other phones I bought
10 years
It's very very specific on the voltage on there's very little tolerance for error here
And I tried about 4
Micro USB phone charger with micro USB and I could not get the pine64 to
Boot up
And after we're going to the pine64 wiki which is fantastic and great resource
I found out all this information on the power supply and the
The voltage that is needed
And luckily I found one that has exact voltage
And booted up like a charm so you're getting old the one that you know is going to work and that's going to take a lot of their frustration
Out of it that I had
Yes
Because there is nothing more than I hate the digging through my bag
Words in trying to
What and what makes it
More frustrating is a non-supportive power supply will actually light up the little LED On the Border like
It's getting power
I can't be the issue and you end up troubleshooting all these other issues
That aren't really issues it's actually the voltage
All right
So that is the update there now we should move on too exciting other things such as
Freezies
Surety and
Personal privacy issue
I think we should start dinner
Let's talk about this dude who basically self incriminated himself in our Sky because
This story has pretty much everything
Yeah
The interesting thing is there's nothing
IRT assure smart homie about this it but obviously it does get to the privacy issues that are related to these device
I suspect this was a standard pacemaker that is the focus of the story correct
Yes
So this guy
Apparently was committing insurance fraud
And he decided to burn down his house
So this man his name is Ross Compton this was back in September 26
He's being charged with setting his house on fire
Police when I talked to him he admitted that he had a
Artificial heart
So the investigators use data from his
Peacemaker
To show his cardiac date right before the
Fire started to show that
She was able to
Move all of the stuff and do all of this stuff
Because the data from his pacemaker didn't correspond with
His version
Stop the story
Right
If you say you woke up in your house is on fire and you ran out
Which the pacemaker would show that you were
I'm sleeping
Then you ran out but
It looks like the date of the Pacemakers allegedly showing that
He was pretty active before the fire
Yes
Now what's
Also worth noting that he had gasoline on his
Including as well
So depressed
PowerPoint switches
Usual infires
Not arson
So
There's a couple questions here
When is did they have to go for the pacemaker
Is the pacemaker data
You don't just that there's there's a
5th Amendment
Closet
Constitution of I'm trying to decide what the right words here this is hard for
The Fifth Amendment
Says you don't have to incriminate yourself
Allstate when you plead the 5th which we see all the time
Congressional
So the question is is your pacemaker did yours so this is like incriminating
Yourself or does it belong to someone else
Police can get it and
It is not selfish
So that's actually really
Interesting legal question
And neither of us are lawyers so
All we have are in a just outside opinions on
I'm assuming
My personal opinion is
That pacemaker data is his data it's not going to a third party or anything like that
As a way to transmit it to his doctor and so on so forth and then there's
What kind of policies do they have for privacy and so on
It's not like he's
Uploading a stuff to a server every day I presume
So if those details are not
Correct
And this is not a voluntary device I mean
Pacemaker
Is
That is so kind of crazy
Is it really interesting case it actually I'm going to have a lawyer come on the show in a few weeks time
And I sent this case off to her S1
Point to talk about so
For that because
Scary
It seems like with the case about the
The Amazon Echo
Police are looking at this data and they're saying hey
This is a treasure Trove of information
So this next story is
Also about scary things with
This
Involves a hotel getting hacked its door lock system getting hacked
Held for ransom
Basically
So this is the
Kevin
The Romantic sea Hotel
Cigarette Alpine Lakes Lakeside Alpine hotel in
Australia minutes by car from Salt
So what happened
Hackers basically got into the system no one was locked in their rooms known as locked out of their rooms but
B Hotel couldn't
Program
The key cards for the door
For new people yeah
And I thought this was really interesting because basically this is a ransomware attack there like you enter access controls this
Custom back pay us in bit
2 Bitcoins
Which I don't know
Know about 1850 ish
$1,850
That's a matter of perspective I suppose but considering that if you couldn't take any new guests
So you could lose a lot more money than
The not so yes
True
So this is the sort of thing that I actually think we should be
Worried about ransomware is going to be a huge
Easy topic for hackers right now with the iot
And I think it's going to come in the
The Forum has maybe it's hotels later on we're going to talk about it with our guests actually because apartment
Dwellings art
Great Target
Because they're so many people I think maybe like a company like nest
Might be
Kobe cars I mean you want to start your car today you need to pay me a hundred bucks
Yeah so I don't know if it's going to go towards
The individual level I think eventually if it's really easy it could
You want to control your thermostat
Haney half a bit
Yak
After the centralized
Administrative
Consoles where they get the maximum effects and then and then they also have a company
It has a lot more money collectively then
Although this is a relatively small amount of money
For a hat
40000 or even a hundred thousand.
I obviously don't condone this
But if I was one of these hackers
This actually makes sense this type of lower amount if you make it too much it's it just becomes a it's a lot easier
Easier for a company to pay $1,800 and get rid of the problem example of 1850
As opposed to
I want a million dollars how many
So yes
This is
You're worth noting for
And
I don't know
It Feels Like A Brave New World here and hopefully
Hopefully we're
We comes down to one of the key things we discussed on a weekly basis not security
And then companies
Iot companies and service providers
If you're not making security one of your top
Pillars of your product or service you're just asking for trouble
And it's not just part of the product or service though it's also things like
Access to your database in
In the cloud
It's got to be secure
Absolutely
From beginning to end
With that in mind the Boston Consulting Group issued a report this month saying that
Companies are expected to spend 250 billion euros by 2020 on the in
Internet of Things
That translates into 260
Billion
US dollars
Switches
Quite a considerable sum
And this report which will link to into in the show notes because it's got so much good data
Talks about basically how to pray
Prepare for the Internet of Things companies really need to have
Good business processes so they should start with use cases first
They should understand what they're doing and he hears those words
And they should develop into in solution
The report goes into a lot of death about how all this is going to come about and they also focus on
10 use cases that will drive iot
Those include things that we heard and talked about sex to predictive maintenance
This one's really interesting self optimizing
Production
Which is kind of corollary to
Predictive
Maintenance
Ideas connect to factories can use iot to monitor
Their production processes
And then
Make automated adjustments to improve quality or
Efficiency and
Inventory management is another
Remote patient monitoring
Zack and we're bringing back the pacemaker
Smart meters which we talked about for like a decade
And is actually a real thing
It's just going to get better
Fleet Management
Connected cars
Distributed generation
And Storage
This is for energy again
It's actually something that
People are really excited about
Things like Tesla's powerwall technology which utility in California just
Open data to the grid
Things like that we're going to be seeing those things really
I guess start to come online soon
It's it's interesting in the BCG report that they have a time frame for maturity for Ollie's
Topics that you just mention and
I'm not surprised to see remote patient monitoring being the farthest out for maturity and the reason being is
Is all the privacy laws and some we're still figuring all that out
We're going to get there because we have
We are hitting a demographic
Crisis in
Actually everywhere
Where there not enough doctors to see people
And the doctors aren't necessarily in the right place
As a patient so
This is going to become really
YouTube people ask your Echo
Here are my symptoms what should I do
By the way
Let's talk about new skills for your personal assistant
Because holy cow
There's some really cool stuff
Morris County
So this is a Google home tips
This Is Us in it
Brought this up and I had no idea this
Could happen but you can actually tell your Google home
To remember
Where you put things
So
You say hey G
Remember that my passport is in
My dresser drawer
And then
Later on you can be like
He where is my password
And it will tell you
Which is crazy
It's actually it's a really slick
Tips and tricks
To use because when we think of tracking we always thinking of
Devices
It was slap a Bluetooth
Tag on something you know and that way you just go to your app and you go find it
But this is using
I mean this is like writing down a notepad
My password is in the dresser
And then putting that note somewhere hoping that you don't lose that too
So it's it's a way to voice tag
Where things are
Now the key is
To keep it simple because
This is probably not like I put my keys on the counter
Tennis standings
This is probably more for
Like esoteric things like
Your voter registration card to send this file
You're going to have to remember
What you told it
So you're going to have to say hey
LG where is my voter registration
And
Too many of those
I forgot what you told it
Yes you do need to be very specific in what you call things but
If you
Set up a reminder
In the most
First thing that comes to your mind most common sense thing and you're describing an object
What time you'll be okay
Totally see myself setting all kinds of things
I don't know let's ask
What did I tell you Google
I wonder also you can actually live going down the path that you can't remember what you called something
I'm pretty sure don't call me and we can check this
Pretty sure there are many ways to see what
Data Google has are you provided to Google because I know you can export that dated someone so worth it would not surprise me if they
List of all those things are available to you online
Getting to it
I will say the Google home
App drives me nuts
Because
It defaults to like
Play Store
Not the play store YouTube
Google
Whatever store
As opposed to like cards that
Inform you of
But you're probably right I don't have my phone right now
Text me so I can't
Here is the other skill that I was like
We got to talk about this which is Starbucks
Is now taking orders
Echo
And through its iOS
And he's our voice orders
Because obviously Starbucks has had an app for a while
You have to have the Starbucks app
Once you enable that skill on your Echo you can say
Hey she who shall not be named
Order me
A Starbucks latte
It's even apparently
Half-caf soy milk
Grande latte you problem
Probably will have to say Grande in
Inventi and all of the words
What's that
I thought that was released
Yeah it's I wish I'd known about yesterday was in New York City and it was cold and I stopped in at Starbucks
Just use the applicant only went to pay I didn't know about that sort of tried it
Order order me a grande white mocha I'll be there in
3 hours cuz that's how long it takes me to get to New York City
Graham called Lexia on my phone
Right so you could theoretically just use the Lexi app to
Be a proxy to your Echo and do it that way
Skills
Let's see what else should we talk about
We got to talk about
Question
From
Which is
We got a question about how to start
I don't mean like how to turn it on or nothing like that I mean
If you're going to build a smart home
What is start and it's actually
It's not a simple answer to that and the reason being
In my mind is like to your pic
A hug first and then you're locked into the certain devices that work that up
Do you pick what devices you want first and then go find a hub that works with those devices
Do
Pick a voice control unit for speed
Echo Google home or some other solution
I don't there's no right answer here but I'd be curious to what your thoughts are Stacy mine are
I would probably pick
What devices I want first and then see what Hub is going to support most or all of those cuz
There is some difference between
What is a wink hub
Support Services with a SmartThings Hub supports and so on
And then face on that then you can pick your voice control unit who works with those hubs
Yes
There are two things that I always ask
When they cuz I get this
Question all the time all the time
So I asked him
What do you want to do
Because your use case is by far the most in
Agreed
But if you don't know cuz some people are now with the echo they're like
I just want to
Turn my lights on
Wait that's what you want
The second question for them
Is what kind of phones do
Use or what kind of existing Digital Services
And I asked them that because
There's the homekit question
Which
Honestly I don't recommend people cuz it
Apple
And so many people don't have
I felt so many people do
Right
It's very bifurcate
So I always ask them.
And from there I basically go down the path of
Like the best products in
Those things now it's someone's just like I want to make my home smart I'm like you know what start
Lights because
It's such a great
Easy use case
Is ice tear them to Voice Control because that's going to be the best way to control lights
And so I steer them to an echo or a hoe
I steer them to
Either the Hue bulbs
Cuz they're easy
Although they're expensive and I tell them
Toyota Center
Or I steer them to
The WeMo
Because
It's a it's an easy to implement outlet that works with Google home
So
Those are the kind of 2
To use cases
Able to
If they want to get really excited and delights
Because I really recommend switches and then that gets into Lake scary things
Like electricity
And then people are like I don't
I steer away from switches for the same reason I mean you do installation for some people it's just overwhelming so be it and it's fine
I kind of prefer going with the bulb route over switches because I often find it cheaper
Really
Yeah I mean what's it what's a to swap out a light switch these days how much does it cost to a tablet connected light switch
5265 2
Depending on the switch
But then you can usually
Since you're going to get a hub anyway I don't feel like wiring I'm like you know what you spend fifteen $20 per bulb
It just seems
Cheaper and it's a lot easier to switch a ball that is to switch a switch
The switch turns off
Yep
No question about it and that's that's where duct tape is your friend just duct tape it up now hitting a kid
Play right that's that's the first thing people say what
Yeah you're right you're absolutely right
Can't argue with that
So those are like The Big Heist
I would say
2 somewhere
Looking at the space
Is a MyQ garage door
I see that
Because it is such a wonderful
Use case for like
90% of the world
Which is
You can see if your garage door is open
Switch a lot of people are really like
Concerned about
Who did
And so I think
It doesn't work with anything else because the Chamberlain
They don't want you to be able to say
You know hey Echo
Open someone's garage door because they
Security issue
But
It's freaking
Awesome
To have it on your phone to be able to check it
Condor Avenue
Application when it's been open
And for too long so I actually
I gave that to my
My in-laws and they love it
Degree does another your two benefits that come to mind I mean one I've left
The house
Thinking of rajouri close behind me but maybe got jammed in
For safety reasons went back up and I did not see that since I'm leaving my garage door open all day unbeknownst to me
And to get a lot of packages
It's kind of Handy to be able to remotely
Open the garage door for somebody to drop a package off inside and close it behind them so
Benefits to those devices
One thing leads to another
Cameras
Just to get started you don't need to go Hog Wild
So yes if you're getting started I say pickle
Queso with its I'm worried about my garage being open maybe it's I'm worried about
Like I want to control my sprinkler remotely
Or maybe it's just I want to play with the smartphone
Sand
Personal assistant
Ways to go
So that is hard advice there
Take it
And run with it
Because
It's so funny
You guys it really is
Superstar
Let's get to the news item
Before we
Move on to our guest
Hey Kevin
Profound
Yeah I just found out about something called
Ping and we talked about trackers earlier in the show saying it on Bluetooth
Slapping on a device or product and you can track it with Bluetooth
What happens with a Bluetooth tracker when you move out of range
Bluetooth trackers
So these folks at ping and it's a ping gps.com
How to get away what's inside
Have a Bluetooth tracker that also
Has GPS
But wait there's more it actually has a 3G cellular radio as well
So you pretty much have
Ubiquitous ranches pretty much anywhere within reason obviously
You can get a cell phone signal
See where this thing is because it's got all the radios inside
It reminded me of the the tile which is a Bluetooth tracker we talked about in the past
Because it's it's similarly shaped and it's not that big 1.34 in
Chi-square
So not much bigger than a quarter or a face of a Smartwatch for example
And it's got all these radios inside now
Early birds can get this for stability of $79
It's going to be quite a bit more expensive if you don't get in on the early bird I think it's a hundred
$30 but interesting thing is the cellular service so that you can go
Stop and find this thing pretty much anywhere
And then what happens after that year was my question so I dug around
$36 for
Cellular coverage for this Tim tracker
For each additional year and that's not bad $3 a month
To be able to track something pretty much anywhere well beyond the the
Range of Bluetooth so interesting to me I'm thinking about getting one not sure where I'd use it yet but you could you can put it on a pet
You can give it to a kid put in a backpack I mean there's a lot of
Yeah just look around the house and he's sleeping so
Interesting because it does put in
Far more radios in caused and is not
Terribly expensive
Roughly three months they say before need to recharge
That's great
It is rechargeable so it has a panic button built into so if you are out and about and something tear
Terrible happens
You just click the panic button and contacts through the GPS and cellular radio will get notified
Nice all right
Other news is
We talked about them actually after CES because they were going to watch the App Store and one of the reasons we said that might make sense his
Because it's really hard to just sell devices
And make money and low and behold
There is a Slowdown in
Market Smartwatch kind of market and Fitbit
Laid off 6% of its staff which is about 100 in
Handjobs
And
They only sold 6.5 million
Devices in the fourth quarter of last year
And that was actually a good quarter for them cuz it includes the holidays and
App Store
So that's not great news
Fitbit CEO James Park
Says that they're actually
Making some Acquisitions I'm going to do some interesting cool things
They did bipedal they actually bought
Better watch
Some assets from
Coin
Which one you talk about next
So we could see
Payments and some other interesting things come here to make it a more compelling
Auction
Yeah I'm as far as coin a Fitbit bought coin
Back in May of last year and that is the programmable
Looks like a
It a smart credit card I guess you could say you can load it up with your credit card information and it looks like a credit card and
And companies can swipe it for
Payments but you don't need your credit cards there cuz I leave formation is stored in the card and
Then the magnetic strip is reprogrammed
Coinstar
Because some
Cardiff
Correct correction Fitbit botcoin last year they actually did say they're going to shut down the coin developer Pro
And they did that and now they're saying that the product services for coin will be shut down at the
The end of February
The cards
If you have a coin you can still use it
As long as the battery lasts
Because you can't replace the battery
But once the batteries God it's useless at that point
Sad
Grimm
Use the sad news bets for the day
Let us move on to our guests
Goodbye Kevin
Goodbye
And prepare yourself
For Felicity Mormon who is going to talk about smart Apartments
Hey everyone welcome back to the end
Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Felicity Mormon
Who is the CEO of Stratus
Hi Felicity
Hi Stacy how you doing
So well
So
First off we should talk about
What Stratus does so people get a sin
So what we're going to talk about so
Tell us about Stratus
Perfect status provides access
Energy and automation for multifamily
Which is commercial residential or apartments
So anybody who is renting an apartment right now and is still listening to the show despite our crazy focused on
Single family
This is your
Show
Those are you guys are in over a hundred and fifty thousand
Apartment
Peanuts right now
You guys door locks you do energy control little bit of automation
You do it all
From the perspective of the land
The right that's cracked we really focus
On a return on investment for your property owner or manager
We find but they're the ones who are purchasing the technology
To put into the building
So our focus is on making sure if he's been by
Why would a property manager
Put
Connected
Devices
There's a ton of reason
The most frequent reason we see like I said his return on investment
So if you have an access manager
Control platform
That French
Bluetooth as ours is
Suddenly you don't rekey door locks anymore
You don't replace credentials with hard cheese
Now you're at
Troy just
Sending a credential
To the phone
Or even a smart card or fob
But you're no longer creating
Those hearts
And if you think about hospitality
Princeton when was the last time you used the heart
Christian hospitality
We don't do it anymore for me as well
Jackie
And frankly the same thing for energy
Martyr control of your buildings energy usage
The residents when they leave
There's a real return
On managing. Unit
For you
And not the maintenance person whose painting it
So we're seeing real return on investment
But that's not the only reason
Multifamily the hot Market
There's a lot of buying and selling the wing on a building
And it's a great way to differentiate your property
When there is a super sexy Tower going up across
So you throw in some Bluetooth door locks
Smart thermostat
And you can actually LeapFrog
The new construction
If they're not careful
Got it
So
Most people who live in apartments are like
My landlord won't let me put in a nest
My landlord won't let me
You know put the August lock on
Can you talk about some of the Practical reasons why
Yeah absolutely so that door lock is a big deal
You don't want as a property owner or manager
To be locked out of that unit
For maintenance
For emergency
From a fire marshal
Perspective you have to have control of all of the credentials
In your building
You're legally liable
So if you switch that out without your property owner or manager knowing and there is a maintenance issue or a management animal
Emergency
Are you now
Chicken that liability onto yourself
Adventure
The owner still liable
So there are some serious ramifications
Can switching out the door lock party
Not from an energy standpoint
It's a little looser
But at the same time
A lot of these building management systems or energy management systems that exist today
Around 9
HVAC system
Won't interact well with a brand-new thermostat
These were installed 20-30 years ago
Sometime
So we're seeing a lot of conflict
Emma technology when renters try to put in something smart
Or something
Knox
I was going to say old and dumb let's say it
Boiler systems
Sometimes decades-old
Yes cuz you guys are based out in the North
Exactly
And despite the fact that we're installed in 45
State every single
State has its own
Boss
Around access
They have their own laws around energy
Around what the landlord is liable for
If there's no heat
Princeton
So these are pretty tremendous
Really obstacles to overcome in the space
Lived in apartment actually for
Fairly recently
Why you guys renovate at your house
Yeah
I think it was a nightmare
Just for the visual it's
3 kids
Two dogs
Myself and my husband
And an occasional nanny
In a three-bedroom apartment
Which is 18
Which is a huge apartment
But we were talking teenagers
So we have a
Ended beyond that in some pretty much the way from these are not small dog
30 pounders
This was
A learning curve for me
All over again
So during that
You actually said she came up with the
It sounds like about a dozen ideas for
Connected things
Was in the apartment
So I'd love to hear some of your ideas
And see what
People who rent can actually do in their Apartments even if their landlords aren't
Connecting thing
And he's maybe two.
No that's
A great question
Just
The ability of a cell
This is somewhat embarrassing but
I lost my
To the door the second day
We're moving in
Hectic
Life is crazy
I never lost my phone though
Somebody call me
Google find my phone within 2 days
Lego Back to the leasing office at the Saturday there's maintenance person they're going to charge me $175
Painful
How old is Bruno $175
A nice apartment like I said it was a big one the only place we could all fit so there was
The ramifications
Really painful
And I thought you know
On my home
Just my phone why can't I do that and apartments and then I started thinking about the
Comparison
Paula Deen I thought
Starwood
Is moving towards best
Bluetooth
Prudential
Why can't we do that so it's really what started me thinking
You're the next thing I know
The washing machine and dryer inside the apartment break
And I have to go and use the community
Washer and dryer
No I'm washing clothes for 5 people
This is no small task if I did everyday
I would have multiple loads
So
I don't know that a lot of people outside of Apartments were called this even but I'm trying to
Watch my laundry in between
A dozen other people using that washer and dryer
There were multiple
But there was never a Time
When it was obviously and easily free and accessible
That's another thing that we can see with our app
When is the laundry open
How many people are in
Space
Beacon Technologies tremendous how many people are in the community center
Is this something I want to participate in
So
One thing led to another
And it became so obvious that an app
Four arrested
Living in the community
Could give me more information
10 even
A single-family home app
Do I have a package
Do I have a free washer and free dryer
Do I need to give access to an Airbnb guest
I mean things.
Go even Beyond
What's happening in single-family today I was surprised
And sometimes unfortunately so
To determine that there were a dozen
Additional use cases
For multifamily
That's awesome
Just makes your app
An offering soap
Hopefully better
About certain time
So what about
People who live in
Prince today
I get emails every week from people who like I can
I guess I could do some light bulbs
Are there any other things
You know iot that
B on the go that can make apartment life a little less painful
Yeah so we love light bulbs
For this reason it's something you can take with you so you don't mind investing in it
We don't recommend investing in anything that becomes a fixture
In that apartment obviously so that includes the door locks and thermostats to your point
We are having a
Re-time
With
Google
And with Amazon
With their AI
Both home and Echo
Are tremendous devices
That will connect
Any device
What's the cost of a practical in disagree
Timer
Priority
If my 8 year old can use it
By all means give it a shot
Sounds good okay
But you guys
So with Z-Wave you can actually like make
You could I could bring in like a SmartThings
Controller for example in make my Apartments existing sensor system a secondary part of the earth SmartThings
How the secondary controller for those things
Absolutely
Is that something that
You think is a
Bible Way Forward for people who aren't
Nothing crazy like that
I think it is
And one of the things that I've enjoyed playing with
Since I got into this space is the lamp module
It seems obvious
As a
Tremendous part of what we're doing but you can plug anything into that
Lights on off
Since my curling iron because I am the person who's guilty of leaving it on
I make sure it's off
Simple easy iot play
But anybody can do and you can plug in lamp
You could plug in your radio
I know who has the radio but you get my point
You can plug in any device
That can carry that load electrically so you want to plug your refrigerator into them obviously
But that's a great opportunity to play with home automation in ways that are meaningful to the individual
Write in an apartment you're going to lose out and take them with you when you move
So.
Opportunity
It's a great one
Anything you can plug in or screw in
Go for it
Got it
Alright so
What is the future for Seymour smart Apartments is this something that's
People kind of
Are apartment companies waiting to see what standards I don't know
Yeah there's a lot of wait and see
But with nearly a hundred and fifty thousand units installed
If you can
Count a real return on
Much of the property owner
The person who's paying for that
Then they will buy
Still looking for a return on investment
Around
2 years
Anything longer than that and there's a lot of ambiguity in the future just like any real estate
But if you can talk about it to your return on investment or exit
Or energy
And you're going for a smart building play
That includes smart residence
Then your integration
If you're looking at the resident
Then you're going to rely on Revenue list
And that's a much harder sell
Okay yes cuz I was wondering like
Do you think people are willing to pay like 30 bucks extra a month or 40 bucks extra month for
Automation in Access
We are seeing Revenue list
In Houston but which is a super-hot multifamily market
We've left around it completely smart automated
So this is access
Is energy and this is at least one automation play which is typically a light switch
Andorra bulk
Fairly simple for you and me who have spent so much time and single-family but for
Multifamily that's a serious play
And so we are seeing
You know 3540
As much as
60 on the West Coast
Dollars a month
No I don't rely on that because Market shift
And certainly real estate market
I'm sure today smart
Tomorrow's news
Exactly
Something worth seeing
In this industry and I anticipate it will continue today
Differentiator you know this is a competitive differentiator
Tomorrow it will be a competitive advantage
Cars that are reliable
2xist
Pretty soon it'll be industry standard
It will be the way that it is much for hospitality
So
What are the concerns around security and what do you have to do to harden
Kind of especially for something like access
The heart in that
Multi-family units because I can totally
I have Bluetooth door locks
Cisco shopping
Yeah absolutely. Is something that is our primary focus
So we have former googlers on our team focus on security
People who have done this before careers
Emma and I try to stress this with the most space especially
Now you're not dealing with the
Single-family home you're dealing with 300 home
In one whack
You have to be more cognizant and more careful
Encryption is that much stronger
And with that much more focused on the handshakes between devices
It's what we spend most of our time on I had somebody on a panel the other day say
You know what are they going to do you know hockey thermostat into what temperature it is
But they see you and I know
That's what happened at Target
And they were on the hook for billions of dollars
We can't be lackadaisical. Security it has to be foremost Focus
Focus
Anybody
Trying to enter iot But specifically this space
Where you have
300 units under your control at a time
It's that much more important
Sure that's like
300 potential MacBooks are television
Exactly
The Smart Home
Single family
Barely it
Barely Main Street it's not mainstream
It's like
It's less than 10%
Adoption rate so far
So when I think about apartments
Maybe the people are younger but do people come into this
These apartments and they're like where's my keys so I'm going to use my what no
So how is that process of
Acclimating residents to
Smarttech
Yeah
So there's definitely a learning curve bear as well sometimes I hear away already have a smart
Apartment because I have
Amazon's Echo
What are you connecting not to
Well I know the temperature outside
Okay great but can you control your lighting
Or do you know that your door is locked
Or can you adjust your thermostat
So there is an equivalent education happening
In
The multifamily space
But it's happening 300
Home to the time
And that's a really significantly different
Funny
People are very accepting
Smart access
And Smart Energy in multifamily because they too can make that connection between
Multifamily in hospitality
Oh I use the smart potential at the hotel all the time
Oh I use my phone
Open my door at my hotel
So there's
I think
I'm easier
Time
Poor education
With multifamily
Then an even single panel
How do you have that conversation with
Single-family home owner
Is that on the floor of a retail establishment
No our property owners and managers are having two conversations on our behalf
I'm excited about
Again because we focused. Return
Vitamat owner
So they're happy to tell you about your smartphone
As a credential
Or even a card you don't have to have a smartphone
To have a smart apartment
Oh that's good cuz I was just thinking of all those and I'm sure there's not that many
But there are people who
Aren't you know when my dad got a smartphone
I kind of shifted my own thought I would like with my dad can use a smartphone
He just doesn't love tok the way I do
But when you got one
I thought okay the
Types of really
We're really moving into a safe space for expectation
Abusive
So I'm not running too many people who don't have a smart device as a matter of fact
Alyssa
Surprise me
We're finding Boomers
Who are downsizing
I'm moving into apartment
And manage condo type
Spaces
To be equally
Excited about this
Is technology
There's often times
Fixed income
And they're really cognizant
Who they love
To use their phone
To adjust the thermostat
They check up on each other
Honey did you you know turn the thermostat down or we're going on vacation
So wishing Boomers is excited about this technology
MLB family and even Assisted Living
As we are millennial
That's really surprising
That's pretty cool
Awesome
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
I really appreciate it the pleasure is mine
No it's great to talk to you I appreciate it
If you want more Internet of Things news sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things you can get
Stacey on iot cam once again thanks for listening and will
See you next week