Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Evan Topol
And Kevin today may sound a little fire away but that's because he's in the midst of his move and you're talking on
What are you
I'm using a phone headset
18.4 in
Android tablet call the Samsung Galaxy view which is a little ridiculous when you think about it but
It suits my intended purpose which is to use it
Kitchen
Computer kitchen tablets watch
Content online and so on so forth and so happens work
Skype
Kevin always has crazy gear
I mean I have crazy gear but none of my gear actually does
What is supposed to do
His does
Distance backflips no no
You could have it do backflips but then it probably wouldn't work as
You could do one back
What
So this week in the podcast where you be talking about the end of I-5 and how did end of life
A connected device
We're going to talk about reports of a pat
Connected crib
Free to talk about
Best practices for ending your account is
Part of me talking
About the Arlo connect
Two camera
I don't want to talk about so I'm going to not use that freezing anymore
And I guess this week is Ryan reist Whois
The VP of innovation for American family
Mutual Insurance Co
We talked about
The future of insurance and also kind of
What's next for the Smart Home
On the insurance
It's going to be good
Hey
Just a quick break to talk about Ayla Networks
Which provides the industry's first agile iot platform
Accelerating development support and ongoing enhancements
The connected products for The Internet of Things
Halo software fabric runs across devices the cloud and apps to create secure connectivity data analytics
And feature-rich customer experiences
Offered as a cloud platform-as-a-service a list flexibility and modularity enables rapid changes
Practically any type of device
Cloud a nap environment
And now back to the show
So let's kick it off with
The end of ice
You told me about this
Doing a web search for the letter i v
With what are you talkin about I completely forgot because I used to review of the products from
I-5
Spell e y e
Either like
SD cards with whip-like Wi-Fi radios in them
And you would use those to get your photos from a non connector camera
Some other device
Take the card out just pop it in another computer
Gets rid of the whole sneakernet thing every was literally just
Wireless a transfer tank
But
Obviously
The rise of smartphones and other connected devices
Obviated the need for a lot of
Yes I V came out man like in 2000
R2000
6ish
Sixth sense about right and
In time 2
An era where
People actually had those little point and shoot cameras
Which you know I had one and
It was it was a little frustrated he would you take a picture and then you'd be like
I have a digital picture and if you wanted to you
Method usually with a USB cord and some
Proprietary software
And then you can get it on your computer and then you could do things
Things with it but
Sci-fi was
Pretty awesome and then it made it
Easier
You just shared it
It didn't always work I had really iffy experiences with
Will a little because it work
Two different ways and
We said it beginning II the end of I-5 one of the ways sort of will still work
We'll talk about that in a minute
Maine weather in people used it was to
Abbott photos
Send automatically to an
Through a Wi-Fi network
They were round
After the cloud and then will be synced on whatever devices you wanted set up everything
It seems to me as I read the
Rachel on I-5 site that after September 6th
Battle Cloud it is
Pretty much defunct
Because you can't sign up for new
Accounts
September 16th
There's another piece of it which I think they called director mode
Which would set up an ad hoc network so you could just wirelessly transfer
Turn off all devices
Hunt's photo
Set DSLR
Have the card in it
So that is
Theoretically still working and it should still work because that doesn't have any do with the cloud
But there's no guarantee it will work so bi people say after September
It so people are really upset because
Basically sent out an email last week saying that they were going to
Shut that aspect of the service down basically all the clouds stuff
And people
They had
Stocks development of these cards
In 2012 but they were sold through authorized retailers
Through March 2015
So people were like hey this is like a little over a year that I've had this if they just bought one
And then apparently unauthorized retailers
Still selling them so like you know if you go on Amazon sometimes you can buy something
That isn't available anymore
Those people may have bought it you know
Who knows when they would have bought it
And those people are really upset because they purchase something that
You know maybe they didn't even get a Year's worth of life out of
Right and not all of the products are actually being discontinued or unsupported after the 16th of September
And I say that because
The X2 cars that are ghosts
Specifically mentioned herein those of the older ones
And they are they being eyesight they are giving
People the ability to upgrade you there movie Pro 6
Citicards
After three units at a 20% discount
And you have to do that before September
So they still have something
Going to happen are in fact I'm looking at the website now the movie promo cards if you buy them now
You get one year of the ice iCloud service so it's literally just
Product line that is
Being discontinued here with cloud service
And there is probably their largest
Ryan Reynolds
They say this is a security issue
And this brings up a couple things so
I'm sure going to hear that it is like the second revolve
I think it's worth thinking about
What it means when you buy a connected device
How long-term the support is going to be in for the manufacturers
Do they need to put
Closer watch on their retail channels authorized retail channels
What kind of plan for if you're going to obsolete something
Maybe you shorten your window and then you go after
Are authorized retailers more aggressively
There's kind of pros and cons to that because you know sometimes
Things aren't so through authorized retailers
Jennifer variety of reasons maybe it's refurbished
We'll get to that later that could be bad
Mechanism of controlling your channel which sometimes is it the best for the end consumer
That's where I was going by the inventory Channel
So it's one thing for a manufacturer or a product
Designer to know that at some point we
Romance obsoletus or whatever but
Do they plan for that inventory probably not if people can still buy them
Chances are they going to keep making them
I mean they're going to sell what they have
Also consumers don't we don't know
We don't know what's going on behind the scenes what the plans are so it's
It's really frustrating
I guess we'll skip ahead a little bit
Because this ties into
The Arlo
Camera from Netgear
So I've been testing this out and we'll talk about in a minute but
It was two weeks ago I want to say it was recently the subject
Security
Thread on Reddit
And a tissue was that somebody had bought an Arlo camera decided they didn't like it and returned it
A couple weeks
Slater they log
Vacation on the go
Motion
The camera that they
Return to the vendor that they bought it from
I got an email about it
Correct
This person was like well that's terrible that I can see this family
Quit
Purchased
His discarded cameras
So daycares response was like we're aware of this which is why we tell our sellers to actually send
The devices back to
Netgear
For hard reset
Which wasn't
So
That makes me feel like
Okay
Are the retailers
So are your authorized retailers going to be your friend
Your phone and are you going to treat them
If they're going to be such an important Link in the chain here
It's got to rethink the relationship between
The consumer and retailers and the manufacturers and their authorized retailer
I see both sides of this one for one thing we should mention we can already be personal return the cameras
He didn't like reset them or do anything he said he forgot to reset the
So
There's some burden on the can
Consumer to think ahead
Which une iot device if you're no longer going to use it or going to retire it you should be trying to
Factory reset it if it all possible
He did not do that
What's your
Yeah we got a level of trust
Third-party vendors worthies middle
Where people that you know sell products
I don't know what Memories Are
Can you tell I did it for 15 years a long time ago
Middleman in this transaction didn't do their job but the fact of the matter is
Retailers don't make money doing things like that retailers make money by selling products
So what's the incentive
For that retailer to
Send it back to Netgear or trying
Mulefactory set himself to sell as a refurbished unit
They're does in
With connectivity we actually have a really good way of going about doing this
So
I will say
It's possible to know
When connected device changes networks Wi-Fi networks for example
It could be very easy
Maybe not very easy
When a new device connects to a new network
Ask the person
Are you XYZ the last known person on this account
It's very similar to how if you log onto like a web services account from a different
Computer
Sometimes they will
Be like you'll either get an email or some sort of notifications
By the way
You just like
Completely new device
Is issue
Or the web service will say I am not logged in here on this computer you know please enter this
Password or whatever
And there's another level of authorization
Exactly so if
Something like that
Is doable that could be a way around something
The other thing is
As someone who tests a lot of these devices
Create counts download stuff
Put things on my network and then I send them back
So I will say that I always
Look for a way
To delete the device
Where do a hard reset on my devices
I will say though
Did not every product offers that
That is also true and every product should any that should be
A given for these types of devices
Sometime before you know
Alpha Testing and sending it out for beta you need to have
A way to
At a minimum delete the device
Count in the software
So I guess we're asking for three things here
Hard reset button on the device awaited to delete the device from your account
In the app
And then
Is
Do you want to get extra fancy create an extra layer security by noting
When a device change
What other got here I want to let Netgear off the hook here
And here's why I'm saying this and you can tell me what you think
The fact of the matter is this guy rich
Camera okay
When he got the email notification
That says hey your camera just detected motion
Obviously the camera is connected somebody else's house
They have their own cow
What is tied to that camera
And yet
His
Account is also tied to that cat
That should never happen
That is true
It should be a one-to-one
Your user to device
Argue
Like right now
Cuz I shared my Arlo camera
I was with you so you could see what
What it's about
Which I forgot to look
Satanic big party for Fourth of July I missed it cuz I was packing
It's not even Skyping it
I'd be watching
The camera
Saints score
Shooting off fireworks and drinking while I'm sitting here packing up
U-Haul
I can see why you
Sorry
Your
Did you have to create a separate account
Want to get access to it
Yes I do it's easy to accept this invitation I'm reading the email that
When you invited me
I got
Advantage of create your own Arlo netgear.com account
So there you go
So it is time multiple accounts
To a device
A better way
Sorry
Okay I was like cuz that's that's a
Semi legit reason to
Do it is if you wanted to invite
You know
Maybe it's something in the baby's room and you want invite the grandparents to see it
Oh you're right you're right I mean I don't know what if there's a better way
When it's more secure and sell them
I don't know what just seems like these two accounts
Obviously these folks are not on purpose sharing their
Camera with him
Is account is just still attached to it
Give me some division there between
An account that has access to the camera
Because if their camera and an account that is shared
Or temporary
Like maybe instruction like I would imagine
If you didn't want me seeing your roof top camper anymore you could shut me off
I can I can
I wonder if these people can
That is another good question
When you buy a new connected device
Are there things that you should look for as a user to see
If it's been bought and sold or if there's other accounts attached to it I imagine there's not
Wrote there a lot of these devices that use
Tape to close the boxes and some of them you can tell if it's been opened
I suppose you can reseal that particular tape a lot of things have
Ink printer tape it says you know
710 Freeway
I remember unpacking these things and I was like
Holy cow how am I ever going to get this back
Together to send it back
But
Sia Magic
Sorry
Flashbacks to that cuz I was actually a huge deal
This is just so arduous
Okay
That's probably enough of that
We'll talk about the Arlo cameras next show
Because I've actually got some other cameras we can do like a all cameras all the time
Let's skip to the
Nest connected crib for a moment
Because
Dang I got this is pretty cool this is Rico found a patent
So we have no idea if Nest is actually working on this or not
But it is a connected crib
It has
Cameras microphones
Sensors in
Matricide
I mean it
Wi-Fi
Thermostat
No no that's what they're known for
A way to quiet
That would be
Worth it
So worth it
So I will say
Parenting is one of those
Markets in the iot that feels just
Rich because parents new parents will spend
Gobs of money on ridiculous stuff and only later when they would like return to sanity they like
Wait did I just drop
$1,000 on a
Oh no no no this is a baby shower wish list
You have somebody else by this for you
I did also
I bought a crib
I did buy the mattress and then I bought a baby
Baby monitor
Hey why don't we
Magical system
It makes sense to me though I mean it seems like the next logical step baby monitors
Rate
Cameras microphones Etc
I mean if you got sensors in there to track the baby's moving so you can tell if a baby is asleep without having to go in there
Yeah I guess you can tell from the cameras well unless
I can't see the baby's face
I think a lot of value
And there are mattresses that like will detect SIDS for you so sudden infant death syndrome
Some of them are sensors that are underneath the mattress some of them are mattresses themselves and there's also a whole generation of companies like
Owlet and sproutling in
I know that
Offer some sort of wearables
But you either attached to the baby's clothing or you put a sock on them or like a little bracelet around their foot
This is a rich Market
Because people will pay anything
There's a lot of information
I love the idea of having like you can track your baby's weight
Very well through like
Just putting
A sensor inside the mattress
I think why things
Biggest why things has a
Baby scale
Just a straight-up connecta baby scale so
There's a lot that could be done
I wonder if they could even add that I don't think it's listed in the patent but but patent application
Yak to tell the actual
Skin temperature of the baby and then timeout true
Just so happens if they make a thermos hepatitis
App to view the baby down radhey
As needed
After 30 minutes
I will say though baby cribs
Are one of those things where you're not supposed to resell them
Cases because there's a baby cribs are subject to
Crazy numbers of recalls
A lot of people
You know baby crib is not a device that
It's like a generational thing like
Literally my daughter slept in my old
Very not safe baby crib
That was at my parents house you no one would go visit and
Please do not
And the CPS
With a connected Crib in like the life cycles were seeing
This is something that
Time is it going to be recyclable or
What because this isn't something I feel like you could have for like
25 years and keep it in your attic waiting for grandchild
No it's not it's all integrated in
Benefits add-ons to
In frame or something in the mattress that's one thing but it's integrated in no I mean it's like saying
Smartphone that I bought this year is going to be my smartphone in 25 years obviously this topic
Yes lot of skepticism here about
If this is a product
What am I look like
I will say I talked to a parent and she was like oh that's awesome I can't wait
Possible disc
And
What else do we have let's talk about wink last week we spent a lot of time on wink with the relay switch
Which was the connected Wi-Fi light switch
Titan deer week system
Show you all kinds of cool stuff
We said that it was $149 for two and $99 for
Reply
Come to find out later
The wink had actually done it as a promotional price in
I was not aware of this
So after we launched the podcast we got a bunch of questions for
4 people say hundred $49
So I reached out to wink and they said
Yes it was initially a promo but we decided to make that the standard
MSRP
If you bought it from
Seriously tell him I said
And a lot of you guys seen
Really interested in this product
Your feedback
Yeah I was actually disappointed when people started coming back saying I can't get the deal
I actually was online I was able to get the deal
Whatever I didn't buy it
Rack up the credit card so
I'm thrilled that it's to Toronto
Yes
So there we go
Russian out
If you are so inclined
Alright final news of note
Is
We got to talk about this
That's cuz I'm a sucker for wireless network
Capital keep me from going to.
All right this isn't this is important
Laura
Which I think we talked about
Daniel Conrad the CEO of beat Network switches alluring at work to talk about the standard
Long distance
Lowe's
Network
For The Internet of Things
Competitors would include sigfox which is doing kind of proprietary
Same thing
Some of the LTE cat 0 lte-m are all efforts to kind of take LTE
And create these
Low data rate Network
And then there's
Ingenue and
I want to say there's a couple others running around out there
I don't know what happened with weightless
Miley Cyrus older 3-g Networks
Apparently
There's more efficiencies and redoing it
There are and you know 3geez going to Sunset eventually
Not anytime soon 2G is being sunsetted right now
And that's after 115 years
At least
If not more
This is cheaper there's battery life considerations like 3-g is not the most power-efficient mode
There's
The cost of the modem itself
So it is
They're also redesigning for like cellular there we deciding things like
The number of packets that are the header soda
Creepy smaller payloads basically to send over the network
So there's a lot happening
Sometimes it's
It's better to start
Dr. Laura
Because a couple big news announcement
Have happened
There's a company in the US called Senate
S e n e t
That has built a network
810 US cities
Before you get too excited
I know that these are very small cities and there's only covers about is it's less than 10% of the population
But
It's really a great start their other companies were trying to build Laura networks in the US so
Ghetto
We could see our smoke detectors and
Trying to think of other things that you might want at the sensors like parking sensors
I was just going to say all the Smart City type devices
Exactly and smart cities
SK Telecom
Is doing a
First I believe Nationwide Lora Network and they're doing it in
South Korea
And
They actually put out pricing
Looks pretty good
Interstate at one-tenth the pricing of their LTE based out of
Offering switch
No baby gets into creating something new from scratch their able to do so more efficiently but
Es6 different plans for
Companies were cities that want to use their
Lora Network
Ranging from
Well the data allowances I should mention
Range from 100
Killing bites
Two 100gb switch
Why are you the cell phone you like nothing
Of course these devices really only Center
Fixing bleep something of information here and there hopefully depending on the device you know
A water meter doesn't need it
Sending outside gig of data every month
No it's not.
It's this time and I'm
Open
Enclosed
Exactly exactly not
Continuous streams of data
Where we would use for them for streaming video
One example but
I'm sipping a pricing standpoint that 100 kilobytes will cost 350 Korean Won
A month
Which is a whopping
$0.30 us
And then if you want
Any plan of 100 megabytes for your devices
It will cost you 2000 Korean Won
What is all the dollar 70
Now 2
What's crazy is
If you take the
$0.30
Her hundred kilobyte plan you translate that to megabytes
You had a twin
It was 30 was at $30 for
That was for a hundred megabytes
$0.30 so
Yeah
Wow it's adds up quick
So if you're going to
Consume many megabytes
Which
And again this is what the carriers do with leftover cell
More BiggerPockets cheaper on a
Megabyte or kilobyte
And hope that people don't use as much as
I think
Haven't had a Colonel Sanders
Chicken bucket in quite a while I've seen
Five different Colonel Sanders in the past too much
What's up
Kept like I'm scarred for life
This is this is pretty cool
So and then there's also in Scotland
The University of Glasgow
Glasgow
Class Portland
Guess I'm not going to
Because it would just be a bear
Network in Glasgow
Dora is really
Taken off
Sigfox which is a French company
Was
We heard a lot about that about a year-and-a-half ago
And
I'll be curious to see how well you know
Laura versus sigfox
How to play this out
I mean there's no one that says we have to
At 1
But it is nice if you're buying a sensor in
You know
These are tiny tiny little devices they're not going to support multiple radio standards on
One of these devices
So if you don't have the flexibility might have a tablet or phone we've got room put in
Modems larger modems in different video
Antennas for frequencies
So I should that's a really good point maybe we do need me
Maybe we'll get just one I imagine I mean if I was denied once
Competition
Ashley between
Linode ideas going
Between a a sick fox versus a
Laura at work
Appeal to me
For Smart City you really wanted to be
You don't have
One radio that works with
You're in
Austin and then a different radio that works
Dallas
On your car
You know what they're going to do is they're going to
There's going to be a whole market for hubs that go on telephone poles that take blue signals in
Jamar hubs
I was like an hour back at the beginning
Alright so now that we've come full circle
Please
Stay tuned for our guests Ryan rice
Who is
At American Family Insurance
And we were talking about the future of insurance
The future of risk
And
What technologies ensures might bring into your smartphone
Hey this is Stacy I breaking into the iot podcast for a sponsor
Search I back with Todd Alka who is the CTO of wolf
SSL
Hardware acceleration for securing the internet
You guys have invested a lot
In building software thick
Can take advantage of co-processors
Various devices
Why is that so important
It's really important for our users and makers of devices
Because it increases the security level
Safety for the users as well
The cost
Because I don't have extra memory and fast
Processor
Consumer Buttowski because there's less
Power consumption
So the long run Macy
Cheaper priced operate the device it's also huge huge increase in performance
Consumer perspective what does it have to do with security
The Securities are we done in Hardware so there is less chance for attack
And you can create your safety
It's that sounds a little obscure in the home i a t Market you not think of that
Pick up printer attack with someone issues
100000 jobs in a row
Duty cycle the printer
As a consumer do I have much say or influence in helping make devices more secure
Consumers can have a say is
By picking and find bison Sprite that have
Locations in this case
CM Security
It's highly important to many many users and probably most of your listeners so no one wants to broadcast their
Iot devices in vacation mode weather on vacation right or
Stone monster
Flight schedule
Public
So if I'm a manufacturer who cares about
My customers
Why should I
Better security
Good security helps
Shimmer with the privacy and risk for the Builder
Resume curso
Win-win
So you guys helped implement
All of this
Iot devices
Where can people find you if they want to call you
For more information
Easiest way to reach this is Cam coyote
Hey everybody Welcome Back To The Internet of Things
Things podcast Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Ryan reist who is the director of it
Innovation at American Family Insurance
ICC doing great thanks for having me on the show
I am super excited because I think the insurance world has a huge role to play in adoption of the smartphone
So
This is going to be fine
Let's get started with
You guys have been super innovative
Y'all done some Partnerships with ring the door
Connect the doorbell company Deltona partnership with Nest protect
And I have subsidized
The cost of the devices in some cases
And you also offer discount for
Companies who are installing
So
What is your take on the Smart Home
At Anthem
That's why I'd agree with you I think insurance companies have a really unique role to play here I think
You know
American Family Insurance
Have been
Trying to sort of talk about insurance differently as protecting people's dreams as you know elevated Insurance out of this
Product
Don't really want to use don't know what it is
I'm skeptical about it I don't
Interact with it much and
I think the Smart Home
MS
Huge opportunity for an industry that is going to change a lot
In the next I think 10 years
Okay well let's breakdown kind of the role of insurance going forward because you're right you guys are thinking about it
When I talk to you guys
You're telling me things like
Usually I have to call my insurance company
You guys are thinking about making Insurance part of my
More helpful so
Can you kind of
Break that down and talk about some of the stuff that you guys have
Sure so we talked about it this phrase proactive
Protection
And I think the opposite of that is reactive reimbursed
Which is really what insurance has been for a long long time and if you don't Insurance places
Fundamental role in
The economy how many people would own a home if you couldn't get
Insurance
To help
With Banquo
Insurance places big rollomatic a little bit of micro-level just
Consumers don't
TV everyday value so
I think that's a huge opportunity I think
Today the last year year before I think insurance companies interest was really piqued by the idea of
Loss mitigation
So a home that has
Leak Detectors
Is going to identify and detect a lie
And hopefully homeowner will prevent it before it causes massive damage
Fires we know that funk
Smoke alarm
Prevent fires
So I think the original sort of interest is round loss mitigation I think that's definitely
Thought an angle
I think the long-term angle that the better approach is
Product services
Beatrice duchess
Help customers solve problems and all
Okay so
What would that look like so let's let's fast-forward three years I've got a bunch of stuff in my home
How would I start to interact
With my insurance
Church so I think it starts with that sort of same digital
Mobile
Experience that you might
Used for
How can I get home products today so I think that could be part of your insurance
Experience I think
And iot triggered event like a leak detector
Instead of just notifying you on your home
There might actually be serviced
Maybe send somebody else to help you
Check the water offered to help
If you start the process of
Cleaning up
I think there could be Services that's one example today what we're doing was Ness
Is where
When your batteries
Diplo
If you're part of our program American Family automatic
We send you replace the battery
Call batteries last long time but that's a cool sort of
Think that insurance companies never used to do in the history of insurance
You get this data and it's really important to talk about your nest program
People at first or like what's happening
Where's if my insurance company seeing all my data
That's a little scary so
Which nest
You don't actually see the data and asked shares the information about
Battery life different programs with Masters the works with Nest there's the safety Rewards program is Xavier
Doors program was
Design for
Insurance industry and we make it very clear when you enroll
We ask customers if they're willing to share their data with us
So
There's a clear opt-in there's
No way to opt out
And so we are getting battery health data
Top of the people that have
But if I opted into that
Weekend in triggering event
Based on low battery so that's an example of a service that I think is really the tip of the iceberg for how weekend
Get to
Adjust notifications popping up
So is part of the nest program
The people who opt-in get subsidized Nest protect and they also get a discount on their insurance
What's in it for them other than
So they get a discounted product so if
Nest it's a free Nest protect right now their work or running in
And state of Minnesota
And in addition to get 5% off of there
Homeowners policy
So there's definitely monitoring to a customer
But when we talk about it's your cousin
Today's hits about
Helping
People say this. Practice protects
We don't know yet
The relationship between
DIY Smart Home
Connected home
And insurance
Now we have 85 years of History
All the bad things
Can possibly go wrong
When you're home
And cause damage and injury
So
We're trying to figure out what is the relation
Shep and can we prevent some of those bad things from happening
What are the next so you got the nest
You got a program with ring
What else are you looking at
Do you know
Traditional Going Back 2 years I think there's a few insurance companies looking at the typical losses in the home so fire
Are water and staffed and that sort of order
Are the perils
Apparel
60% of the losses are really wind and hail
Stuff that happens to your roof and siding the other 40
Percent of stuff inside the home
So can we
Create a marriage
Connected home or we can actually help prevent these
Carol's are happening inside
The water is
It was a really
Space that we're looking at
Surprisingly there isn't a ton of really gray water detection
Solutions out there there's a lot of sort of low cost
Contact sensors
You can put around this connect to a hub
But I think that's an area that we're seeing some
Innovation and receipt companies
Start to do more
It also kind of brings up to
Point of retrofit which is
This isn't like cars
Where everybody's going to have
A new car in 10 years
How do you retrofit a home how do you put
How do you encourage customers to let you in their homes
Stick a water shutoff valve requires a plumber
That's a pretty big ass
Sprite
So I think something I've heard you talk about is Smart Homes going to take awhile to get there
Because we're all living in homes that are going to be ready
It's true this is this is something that makes me so sad
As I rip and replace all kinds of stuff in my home is actually it was built in 2013 and
Justin
Justin 3 years
This I would have put this in
Course I probably wouldn't work
Working 5c
I won't worry about that
So what about trust
Because
This sounds really nice I would actually love to have
Hero
A notification
Stacy by the way you got to leak
Or we're sensing a lot of water coming into your house somewhere
Here's five plumbers that we cover in your area
Do you want us to start asking for estimates
I would love you
Forever
But
A lot of people look at this and think about things like
They're going to start costing me money maybe if I don't fix something or they're going to see data and they're going to be like oh we do
Not one insurer that house it's got like crazy drafts or I have
So how do you kind of address the idea that
You guys are going to get this data
And
Use it for baby
Differential pricing
I don't know something punitive
I think that's a very natural
Expected response
Summarize the time because I think
You look at the insurance industry the whole it needs to change I think
Find a different areas where
Call Jessica
I think
If you understand the business we're in and we're rats today I think it makes more sense so
What's walk down at example of
Aviva insurance company I mean I already today
The insurance is in what we call low engaged
Consumers do not interact with a very often other than paying for a bill
Maybe once every 10 years you have a claim
What's the fact that we live in an age
Exponential technology growth we live in an age of One Click Amazon
Shopping
And Uber description of experiences the den entrepreneur Ozark rating
That's a recipe for Destruction
So I think any insurance company that thinks they're going to use this data to
Sophisticate there their pricing model which is already pretty sophisticated and not
Ensure people raise prices
How is that going to impact
Customer experience in any sort of positive way
They want
And I think that's the recipe
For failure
So
I mean we're looking at this really at the long-term and saying
How do we take an industry that
Yo is it love today and how do we make it lost
Because that's really where
Long-term
Excessive going to rest
And as we add this kind of data
How does this change
Underwriting practices and kind of what risks because if you can say
You got the sensor in your house that
Can detect a leak before it gets bad
Your reducing a large
Chunk of Rights provided someone takes action
So
Does this mean like eventually overtime my insurance rates could go lower insurance as we know it
Because we know it is going to change so take the car for example
People predicting anywhere between
20 and fifty years that there will really won't be personal Auto Insurance
Anderson companies either companies are going to make the artificial intelligence that runs the car they're going to pick up the liability insurance
Another example is
Is cyber cyber threat
Cyber insurance
So much of the world is going from physical to digital that a lot of threats or now
Cyberspace so if you're not into cyberspace 20 years from now
Yeah will you be around will you be relevant
So I think
Risk is changing
Customer perception of a current industry is not great
And I think the connected home presents this
Wonderful opportunity
B2
Be a hero brand you better
Farris Motor Company you guys have a team driving program and I think it's actually exemplifies that type of thinking
Do you want to talk a little bit about that I'm very passionate about that that was my job for
Well over a year was to travel around Middle America in
Meet with parents
Continue to try to convince them to put this
Basically a video camera in there
Cars
And that's sort of the seeds were planted there I think of American families Innovation or rats today so what happened is
There was a video event
Recorder that would get placed in the car and it would be triggered off of motion
So it's the teen driver did an erratic turn or slammed on the brakes all the things that actually lead to accidents
Hayward be a video clip that was sent to the parents so it only recorded you if you did something
And so quickly overtime in a very short period of time
Beetlejuice
Went from like 40% to 100%
So all the sudden have kids with driving with a seatbelt
The next thing was parents started talk about tailgating
Stop texting while driving those types
What is program
Doubt it was
Economically was it sound no cost for way too high back then but costs are coming down
And
You cannot do the same thing with your phone basic
Zapp's today that you can mount on your dash
Duke primary the same thing
And out of that program I saw parents in tears
Saying I will never switch to another insurance company you guys helped save
My son or daughter's life
And that's a really powerful thing when you're in the industry this
Has historically I changed a lot
Can drive a whole new different type of business
OKC and I would
Question
Power to you guys protect my child
To show every time you break rapidly
My husband would go for it.
Yeah and if you look at where the usage-based insurance industry is gone
There's very few companies
Second cousin
Sleep analyzer
Driving bad most of them
I think most insurance companies are hesitant to go in that other direction and to penalize people for
What to eat Pacific risky Behavior
I certainly know
Are we taking
Incredible amounts of
Carson and
Effort
Detroit number one transparent with customers
If they know what's going on
Why are using a
Opt-in for the voluntary
Answer some benefits of them
I think what we found in are certainly connected home and working the connected cars that's the recipe for
Mutual Trust
And
Awesome
Alright well let's go into the connected home a little bit because
You guys have experimented with I think you told me for every program y'all Implement y'all have tried out 22:30 differ
Other devices on the back
Gantz o
You seen a lot of stuff
And
Where do you think
Smart Home
Yeah I think if we were to sign intelligence
Score
People that this is the intelligent home
I think it's somewhere you know around an IQ of us
Sixty or seventy I think it's you know it's sort of a mentally deficient
Home it's not a smart
But that's good because
Fights in years ago it was a totally unintelligent
What I'm seeing as
Success
Companies
Salisbury specific problems
Wonderful Whites of the nest
Thermostat
Was way better than the old
Programmable thermostat
Sold a very specific problem right then try to create
Smart Home
The ring video doorbell
Is about
Preventing
Justin burglaries in neighborhood
And everybody has a dork
Nobody knows
That the old doorbell did one thing and the ring doorbell does like
20 awesome things
I should interrupt you for a second
To know that you guys are an investor
Thank you yes we are an investor with a venture capital
We have a investment in
But ring is interesting because people get it because they sink
Did they want they wanted to protect their home
Outside in a public
Space
Scrapy in any way
That's something somebody can hack him
See inside your home but when they get it they have all these other benefit
It's like they see when packages arrive
Macy win
Your friends come to the home and now you can unlock your door
From ring administrations that they're building so I think
Rings for broke through
By being really really good at
Solving cost
4 problems
Pacific area
I think what's going to happen is now with sort of programs like works with nest
People get these things it solves problems for them
And I can maybe get another thing in the Abby's building blocks
And then pretty soon things like Amazon Echo come along make
Easier to work with them
And I think it's going to take time off
Will get there
So let's talk about Amazon Echo because in the last probably I'm going to say 6
12 months
Everyone's like oh my God I have a smart home I have voice control it's amazing it was it's kind of like
Possibly
What is your oven do you have one what are you guys
Speak about that
Yeah I have one eye
Can I retested Schoology
Devices
Test of in my home personally
Oh my pasta
Big family issues with cameras in the house and
At the echo is
Really interesting
She follows where the customer adoption
All these devices
It's a lot of the stuff is early adopters will buy anything
If it's cool
Engadget e Wright
What happened with the echo is you know it took the interface from the phone and
At a fatigue
To the physical world
And I don't think anybody would have predicted
The echo
And for me you know it's something that my kids use
In fact we got a rule if you if you play Shut Up and Dance One More Time
Vehicle goes away and it's something my parents are not giving away to their friends
The problem is connected home is really bridging into that mass market and I think
Carla Thomas gee
Are the problem I think is
Making the devices song
Customer problems real problems in the second part of it is making it really easy and natural
I have to ask this because you are an investor
And it was a step back for the industry the shutdown of the revolve Hub in the absolute
The way it was handled felt really
Preemptive
And now they're giving
A refund to people who bought it
Aren't the nest guys are getting a refund of people about it
Beforehand they just for like hey Rita shut this device down
And
Thank you
So
How did you feel like
That was handled or that could have been
I can't comment on
Specifics of nest
Handling of the Revolt shot. Bride you think it shows you
And if you talk to the people at Bolton other places and no Hardware really well
It just shows you how difficult it is to be in the space you know how do you sound setup
How do you turn something off
Because it was so publicized
I think it did
Do some damage to adoption is a whole cuz people were forced to suddenly realize it there is spending a lot of
Nice things in
Is something that's owned by such a legit company could suddenly go away like
It was kind of like
What am I really willing to invest on all this stuff
Yeah so if you spend $203 on device how long do you expect it to last
That's a great question
I think we're learning I think
Industry still trying to figure that out
Okay
Final question for you
Because you tested so many things
What are your
Favorite devices or what are you looking for excited about then
Years to come
Well I'm really
Interested in
Now is
How these devices
And how the data from these devices
Can lead to service
So I think that opportunity for
Connected home is not
Notifications in apps I think it's healthy
The data the real data from The Real World which is busy
Instrumentation
How do we use that information
To create new products and services that
Never existed before
We still screen and test a ton of
Devices ID
Amazon
That goes for the Breakthrough
In the last year
There's a lot of cool stuff for looking at now and that's where the water shut off side
But I think
Really it's about
Services I think that's what we're seeing from
Consumers wants
Yo bro get a real big aha this last
Which was it's not really the connected home it's the home
It might be that may be connected
It's the home and it's homeowners that are living in the home that have real problems
That they need salt
Owning a home is one of the most complicated challenging things
32 speight painting to home
Childish things that you're not doing right now and I'm not doing that we don't even need me
No need to do
I change the furnace filter
Every six months or
What we started
Dive into
Is less of the gas
Three more of the problems in the home
And how can connected home be apart about holistic solution that includes devices-and-services and insurance
I can't wait
I should ask you I lied to you
One more question
Am I ever going to have to have like an app for my insurance company for monitoring this or do you guys want to do most of this through
Partnerships
I think you're going to find delightful
But you have insurance companies do it right with
You know American Family certainly thinks we're heading that direction you're going to want to
Use your insurance app
Mobile app or mobile experience because it's more than just
What happened
It might be
Contextual information about
The weather it might be
Information about
Non iot device
That you care about the robin
Oh you could do a partnership with next door
You could be like hey there's been a rash of burglaries in your area
There was a company we looked at that was
Layering from connected home to external Transportation so do I want to go get on the
Bicycle or do I want to take the bus
You're so not just me and my home but as I leave my home and go by lights
Flight yeah I think actually
Connected home app
Is going to be part of something bigger
Sing
In the future now is that insurance
We certainly hope we're
Have that sort of role in people's lives
Thank you for having me that's it for this week's show please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
And thanks for listening