Hey everybody this is the internet
The things podcast
Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel
Yay this week we have a lot of awesome stuff for you
Actually I shouldn't say that because
Restart on a pretty Grim topic
Which is the question of
If
Be smart home
Is crumbling
Are people still really into the Smart Home
We had a couple of news item
Recently
We had Leo which is a company that makes a smart light
Tired I don't even know how to do
Describe Leo actually it's it makes a smart night light
Also listens for your smoke detector to go off
And then it will text you if it goes off so it's kind of like a way to retrofit your smoke
Actors
It is also a night light
Does that make sense
That makes sense
Makes sense
It's interesting
It's like the Labradoodle
Gadgets
You just come by and some kind of random cool stuff and you get this
It's a nice Gadget I've actually tested it out
It's about a hundred bucks and
Yeah it's a it's a fun thing
Last week the company laid off
About 30% of its staff it was 16 people
And
I talk to the CEO and
Basically the issue is that the
The smart home is kind of getting there a little slower than anticipated
And they wanted to conserve their cash and they have
They raised 37 million info
Their pretty good
So we have that
We also had
We talked about it in previous shows
The quirky was getting out of the making all products
Business and was selling
It's wink
Home automation Hub software in
Platform
And
I kind of like of the opinion that
The wink was not a crate
Platform the software is actually really good but the hardware just in
Was it just didn't work
And so
Taking those things plus a couple other instances for example there's a Smart Lock called Gucci
I don't know if you remember this cabinet lunchbox
I do remember it
So it actually hasn't shipped
It was supposed to say It was supposed to ship in December of 2013
People are basically if you go look at the Twitter account
It's kind of sad there's this one
It's like one for a person who's having to handle at least
Say hey
I would not want to be that person
Yeah
That's Tuff
There's also plump which was a
Wifi-connected light switch the founders were actually cedia
The Trade Organization for kind of
Yeah I am home and install
They launched in 2013 in
They still haven't produced eras light switch yet
Still available
Pre-order they say they're going to ship it in
So there's like a lot of stuff happening here that kind of made me
Look and realize that
Maybe it's time for a reckoning
Will you notice I think there's two things going on here one is a lot of companies and started to jumped in
And promised the world and I commend them for that cuz I I
Like a lot of these
Potential products
A lot of them haven't delivered yet
And
It's funny because I've said in the past
Smart Home Market is kind of moving so slow but in some respect between pretty quickly when you have all these companies jumping in with potential products
The last couple of years
The thing is
Promising the product is one thing
Implementing and delivering is another
And the market itself that with so many bigger companies getting in
Seems to be crowding out something small guys to the point where like
Who this product we promised sounded great when we launched it but now we're competing against
Ab&c here
This isn't going to fly we need to either retool rethink or or something here and so I think they get into the state of paralysis
And it looks to me like it's really just a lot of companies that
Didn't deliver timely enough
And we also have a lot of consolidation going on in this industry right now so
I think it's those two things going on
I think building good Hardware is hard
We talked about that plenty
I also think there is
A lot
Of
Poorly reviewed gear out there
And that makes people nervous and there was an artist inside study that
Came out last week
About
Demand for Smart Home Products is
Dropped 15% in the last
Year
So from May 2014 to now and then
It also showed some data in this is August
Isn't
Counting actual sales their measuring things like
Reduce inventions on social media
But they actually
Got a pretty good track record of predicting what's going to do well so
That's why I'm actually mentioning it
And then
This week
Icontrol
Put out some data about the Smart Home
It is also worth kind of
Looking at in terms of like demand and who's buying a
Basically
It looks like
Younger people are much more likely to buy it in the age range of 25
Are likely over 50 about 50% of them are likely to purchase
A smart home service are connected appliances
Within the next 12 months
Versus
Consumers
What you say
About 31%
Would purchase a smart home service
And only 25%
Purchase a connected
Appliance
And across-the-board the percentages are
In the
Mid-thirties for everyone purchasing smart locks
Connected home cameras connected lighting and connected door locks or what they're measuring
So
It looks like if you get into this 25 to 34 age range
Which theater URI
Sorry to spell thank you appreciate that
So it looks like younger people are a little bit more willing to spend but even then only half of them
It looks like when they're willing to spend is is worth mentioning to because
It looks like people don't just like walked out to Best Buy and pick one of these kind of connected devices up
Looks like May
They're waiting for
Events like the birth of a child or
Moving to a new home
Yeah
Yeah it's it's also interesting to me in the eye control report on and we've hit these two topics before but it just want to highlight it since it's
Two major obstacles found in the study for
Consumers
Privacy data concern 71% of consumers share the fear their personal information make it stolen
No surprise there
And this is
Big thing with me I can say no forever
Can your devices talk to each other 60% of the consumers wish their devices to a better job
A talking to one another to me it's it's a platform thing it's not just individual
Fragmented devices and hope that you got radios that talk and work with each other but not
And I think that bodes well for the
Cornhole platform makers we've talked about him getting the pass and how it's been slow but there's an example of a platform that will
Probably resolve that issue of Kenya devices talk to each other
Exactly
I will say another thing
Another concern of theirs is that smart home technology will have too many bugs
57%
People
Are worried about this
And you know what they are
Your home is a minutes
Where you live at
Where you at
Sleep
Affirm for new nights when we work I mean we can't have bugs in the home
Meropenem in ants and roaches
Know that we can have those either however
No we can't have
A broken smart home that needs to reboot every year
3 hours
Yeah you want to relax you want I mean
Yeah it's it's a basic thing
Your lights to turn on a mean I even get frustrated with Netflix if I'm if I'm trying to watch TV and I'm like
You know it's like
Oh
He must detect the internet is working
Oh I'm connected to the internet
Now
Who's watching I mean like all these steps and you're like
Just want to watch Netflix just want to see the movie
So I can so I
See that by the way
The entertainment
Internet Security in the eye control
Survey is the
90% of people buy a smart home for security so they're they're emphasizing that as they would
Icontrol
Provides
The backend smart home software for
Comcast for
ATT
For a lot of
What is so security is one of
Selling point
Entertainment is the other
And people are ready
To connect their entertainment rooms first followed by the kitchen
And let's see
I'm trying to think what was
What was the other thing
And then the bedroom for a second there I thought it was the bathroom
Smart bathroom
It's not there
Percent of people are in
Connecting their bath
Yes
I really don't need my toilet to tweet every time I use it
Oh Noah needs that
I would say actually I have speakers in my bathroom a lot of
Smart sales
Good lighting
Those are all very very nice to have but
Certainly.
So
That is kind of
Where people are in the Smart Home
Tom and
I think
If you can serve your cash
You're putting out a good product
And
You know you're in it for the long haul I think that's probably the way to go
God help us please let's get some smart platform just like let's get things talking to each other in a real
Easy-to-use way
So there's our learnings from that
We should talk because last last week we recorded before nest made there
Huge announcement
Siri announce
But we'll go with Kevin and
Your sarcasm
Kevin
Shall we shall we briefly cover what Nest covered
Version 1.01 of nest
It's getting a software upgrade
There's a brand new Nest protect
Smoke detector
And
There is a
Brand new
It's now the nest
Scam
Nest
Cam with a
Capital c
Instead of the Dropcam
Which
This condo at this looks The Nest cam looks a lot like the Dropcam
Ampro
Two hundred bucks
Yeah
The Nest protect is still at a hundred bucks
And
You know the nest thermostat is 250
I will eagerly await my software update I'm really glad that they did not introduce a new nest
Turn Nest Thermostat because I'd hate to
After ripped mine out of the wall
Yay 4th Avenue
Who I expected more boo boo
I know we have rumors of audio
We had
Like some sort of home audio entertainment product we had rumors of voice control
We had some great room
Rumors aside I mean really
This nest
When was when did Google buy nest for 3.2 billion January
Okay so you're in a half ago
And what's really happened since then
Not much
I got a check when
Nest
Best spotter Google bypass
No not much has happened and the features they have in these things are not
Rocket science they're not like
Daunting
Especially in the camera side they're not
We should get ahead of the cops
Petition
It was January twenty
Audio
Sonesse was a big
Kind of
The biggest the biggest thing and we'll probably talk about it on another show cuz I'm
Planning this
Crazy idea
The
Announce that American family which is an insurance company
And Liberty Mutual
Are going to subsidize the nest
To protect
And give it out to homeowners as a way to like
Help prevent fire damage in homes in hopefully
Lower
The incidence of payouts for fire damage
And if you do that you get a free Nest protect
From your insurance company and you also if you send them monthly data reports you'll get 5% off
Nice
So cats in
For American family which is the only one that offers this program now and it's only offered in Minnesota right
Right now
You can actually staff discounts so your security alarm discount that you might get
Say to get 5% off each month format and then you can get 5% off for the nest
Defender like woohoo
That's good deal good deal
So
However
It's still not that exciting
So
On the really exciting energy
The front we have this awesome
New Gadget
And I talked to these guys a couple of months ago they're based in Austin
I've been super excited wanted to tell you guys about it it's a product called curb
And
You install it in your circuit breaker box
Is it a circuit breaker
So you like the box with Breakers
Open
And if you don't actually install it an electrician install
What you can
Do with this is amazing
You get to see
On a device level
How much energy something is
Is consuming in your house in real time like
I sat through the demo in
He remotely turned out he had it installed in his home the CEO had it installed in his home and he remotely turned on a space heater
And you could see the graph in the kilowatt hours
Soon to go up
Like
I can't remember.
It turned red in light
The numbers got a lot bigger in
He's like sea based on this you know the space heater just turning it on for like a
8 hours a day would cost me
$5 a
$5
It was
Amazing DD
App is very
Compelling it's it's very easy to read
It's currently hard for me to talk about
.
So I'm going to say in a personal level I am super enthusiastic about this
Because I have tried to do this in the past with the
Kilowatt meter so I don't know if you
No those are actually kind of like
Smart
Smart Meters that can determine how much juice is flowing through a particular Outlet
The curb does it at the
The circuit level so
Guess
Pair multiple things on a circuit you're actually
If you can break it down to those individual things
But that's okay
You can break it down I mean it depends on how your house is
Yes yes
And that makes total sense but so so the kilowatt that I used to use a couple years ago
You know that was
Literally just
Measure 1 Outlet the
Outflow of energy
1 Outlet
This can do at 3
Full House
Which I love
Part of the reason I love that is because I have 41 solar panels on my roof
I can tell you to the second how much energy each panel is producing
Because
Every one of the panels as a microinverter and its shares
Data over power line to a little web server have running and so when I get historical information real-time data yada yada
Thing is I don't know how much energy I'm
Assuming
Steve
For my monthly Electric
Bill
Since I am
I'm still tied to the grid
And I can't reconcile it really on a device level
So this is
I think I'll standing
For someone who really wants to
Get a feel for the energy consumption in the house
I agree in
Another reason I think you would be such an interesting candidate for this
Solar is the top reason
But the other is you got
A fold or lease
Hypervolt
So you can actually calculate even
Better your Energy savings because when you plug your car in
You can see exactly how much
How much it cost to charge your car so
The CEO sent me some data from someone in Austin who has
Two Teslas
Lucky man
He's got a roadster and an s
The one week.
You know that he tracked it
His car is cost him
$27 a little over $27
To charge
So
That's that's a week's worth of
Charging
Are those things
That's pretty impressive in
That's how she's amazing data cuz you can start seeing like
Is it time to replace my fridge because
She's assisting cost me a hundred bucks a month to you
Yeah the the electric-car bit
It's actually not that impressive tomato I'll tell you why
Because unlike a lightbulb
Or some other device
There's a fixed amount of energy a car can
Can take can consume and I know the capacity of the battery in my Volkswagen Atlas
Bass Elite 13 kilowatt hour battery
So
I can just multiply my
Hourly
Usage rate
To figure out how long that is it's about a buck and a half for me I know it is on a daily basis
It a little bit
You know
Beneficial to me for the variable type things
Okay I would love this before I put in do you know my
My Ness and that's where it's at my Nest my ecobee my LED lights because
Actually have a sense of
Am I saving money or am I just you know installing $250 thermostats just for fun
Yep
We probably both it's a little bit of both because I keep my house at an ungodly Hi-Tech
Temperature
So
Speaking of savings we should get to the downside of
Which is this thing is very
It is
It is the devices on Indiegogo
Right now you can pre-order it
Indiegogo
And it will ship in September
One one unit is $350 and that measure 16
Different
Circuits
Centers $0.18
16 zones of appliances what it says
Which in my house I actually
Three of these
And then there's also the charge
For the electrician to install it
Which
They're trying to
Current that the guys at Kerber trying to make it so
Still have a network of installers that will pay a set fee
Right now
They haven't got that in place so he estimates about a hundred
$250 for one
Eventually he'd like to be $100 for one and a hundred fifty for the two pack
We'll see
I am getting one in my house
So I'm going to be
I feel like maybe I should have them send it to you Kevin because
With a solar you're like way more compelling
That's up to you
I bet I'll let you decide how it looks like there app is available for IOS and Android so that's a good sign
And
Yeah looks pretty good
Yeah so that's our excited that's our exciting thing on curb
Indiegogo is doing super well
I think I've been there they're so close to getting there
There they're raising 25000
Ed
I'll tell you guys a secret there shipping in September because I already producing these
So
It's it's a little less produce safe
Yeah it's a little less
Yeah and in the end plan is probably to go install this in
Like talk to
Solar power cup like when you're getting your solar installed
It's a perfect match for that absolutely
They're doing because they've got a smart home initiative
You know just
Pop in the sky in here cuz you can amortize it with
House
French
As expensive as it is I think I could get started with the early adopter package at 309 and that's
A tenth of the price of a Tesla battery that I actually reserved
So to me it's
Probably worth the 309 if I get an early I might I might
I guess talk to my wife
Oh
You know what this was the 309 wasn't actually available
They must have opened up some more
Early doctor either so there's a few left
Yeah okay
It's okay
Yeah and in the large home there's a two pack for 5:49
It just to clarify the reason you would need the 2Pac is because
You have two circuit breakers
Actually have three circuit
My house is very
Overachiever
What my house was wired for the future
Yes so
So when we built it
2 years ago that's that was our
Thought process
So you know what yes we are overachievers
But
That's I also going to get really granular data when I am
Does pops away with
So I can I can tell you how much
My washing machine
I can't wait y'all
Okay
Moving right along
Arnex picked
Snooze
Which is
Amazon Echo
Oh I thought you're going to do your echo echo
Echo echo
I would but I'm a little peeved
That means it's good news let's just say what the news is Amazon Echo is available to everyone
For 179 99 you don't need an invite
And I believe July 14th is when they're in stock
Ship July 4th
Yeah so as we all know I passed on the echo.for $99 and you
Got one for $99 as a Prime member
I later said on this very show I think I'm going to reserve one again and I did for 149
Well
I never got the 149 invite and now I've got to pay 17999
Sometimes it pays to be a believer
Yeah we we should say that this is going to be today's 5 minutes
Yes Papa
Because
Because I think
Now that anyone can buy it at
Reply
If you were unlucky like Avenue
You would have gotten it but now you can go buy it
180 bucks
So
Okay for those of you guys who
Have not heard us talk again and again about the echo this is a
This is basically Siri combined with a
So
You talk to it
And
Is connected to the Bing search engine is connected to a lot of other things
And you tell it what you wanted to do or you ask it a question
And
A response
Set also plays music at axes like a
Bluetooth speaker with your phone
What else does it do
Well they've added a bunch of things like a lot of content I got to Pandora
And I could always read you the news from NPR
I wouldn't have the timer
Timer so and
So so in the last so when it launched it was basically
Connected to being so you can talk to it ask us some questions it would tell you casket jokes it have the timer
And then it also had
Amazon music search
Write a Prime music Amazon Prime
So it could play you could be like Alexa play Taylor Swift
And it would play Taylor Swift
If you happen to have that album in your pregnant
In
You know what for 99 bucks
Set the time
I thought it was a joy
A joy to use it was wonderful to talk to is the most effective
Kind of natural language translation service I really encounter
It was really it's really very good
But it was such a limited
I did nothing
He wanted to tell it to do things
But they did change that in February this off I think it came out in November and February they said we've got a
Early SDK for developers and I started to add some things and they later added
Smartphone type things such as Philips hue light support
WeMo support
Couple of things
It's this and that
Fort for select services
So long with all the home automation stuff it's also added things like the ability to
Read your audible books and
You know you could always do things like add stuff to your grocery list and now you're just
You're basically saying it over all expansion
So
The question is
Who should spend $180 getting a
$449 to Yuan
But that's another story are not doing that deal okay I retract the question
Not if I have a question
I still would like to see it have things more Integrations with Spotify
I want to give it
More commands in my home
I can already talk to my house like my thermostats using
I'd like the nest thermostat I can use Google but
My husband and I both use the Ability we tell Alexa to turn off her lights
Every night
You also have with the device a remote control that you can use
To speak into
For when you're far away
Or at the room is too loud
And we use that a lot too
I personally might buy another Echo
Go actually for upstairs
That's how much I like
Yeah
There's a lot to like here in a minute because they've expanded what it can do I was not
I didn't want to spend $99 at the
The time because it was very limited in my opinion
The funny thing is I just talked to my family about this
And I said you know if I get this you guys going to use it and even after watching the video which has been updated to show
All the different things you can do now
They're like probably not so
Surprisingly I would be the only one who would theoretically use it according to them
So I don't know if I'm going to do it especially having to pay $30 more
I don't know I have a lot of other things I can talk to and do things with such as my phone one of my watches and so on
I like how it's all integrated into one device
But
It does duplicate a lot of things I can already do
But it does them so well
My family didn't think they would use it
But I think we probably
And I don't have soap
It is a no-brainer if you have a huge music collection
Turn on Amazon
On Amazon which we do not
We do not either so but I will say to
Two people who do
This device
Will be amazing
Because you basically just tell it what you want
And it plays it in the sound quality is pretty
It's its equivalent with like a jam box or something
So
But that aside my husband didn't think he'd use it
But again he uses it every night
We actually use it at the dinner table to settle like
Debates
Who is president in
Oh you should ask it who was president in
Because that is
Secret Pop Quiz question and you will be surprised
Put that there
I'm thinking but I don't know
That's all I know
So
I think you should spend the money
If
If you have actually Hue Lights you should see
We've actually set it up so when you tell it to play music are Hue Lights in the living room flash on and off
I didn't see the color circle
Which is fine
So my advice
If you have music
On Amazon
Prime
Amazon yeah Amazon Prime music service
If you have
Connected lights that are Hue or WeMo enabled
And if you
What are elected like you're very excited about voice-activated technology
This is an easy
Easy Spanish
And it's actually relatively low cost
When you think about what it does do for you so that's fair
What's gravity group
And I use the kitchen timer part of it all the time
Everything I have plenty of other timers but it's very nice just to be like hey Alexa set a timer for 15 minutes
Or hey Alexa what time is it
Everybody's if you have one right now it's going off
Sorry y'all okay
So I think that that
Covers Us for this week that's a lot of news
And
So please
Stay tuned
Because our guest today is the CEO of lumoid
Which is a company that allows you
To rent
Cameras
Drones and wearables
I'm going to talk about some surprising data that lumoid has to offer people about werewolves and where they met
Donuts
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and today our guest is
Aarthi ramamurthy
Who is the CEO of
Lumoid
Healthy
Hi sweetie thanks for having me here
I am super excited
Because you get to live the dream you're living the dream man
You have
Resume Lloyd
A platform where people can rent gadgets and try them out
Is that
Fair way of saying it
Yes that's exactly right I am living the dream I am a gadget nerd and
Everyday eyeshadow look at work and I get to
Working for you this all kinds of really cool
This is pretty much what I wanted to be when I grew up
Why does a try before you buy service
For electronic
Wevent
Spell all kinds of gadgets we started with Photo & Video gear
Cameras lenses psychological to things like that
And then expanded into Jones
Angles of taking off is doing really well no pun intended
Chimpanzee launch wearables
Adidas here
And that's been going really well to today we work with
We have Apple watch in the face
A whole bunch of other variables
And we have a great time for you by thermostat lock him up
Yikes it sounds awesome and I have to ask
Because
I am in the enviable position of getting a lot of review gadgets for my my smartphone
Stuff
But I know a lot of people out there especially if people listen to the show or probably like
Hey
Are you guys going to go go into some of the smart home devices
Anytime soon in 2 out of article 3
Okay well
That that'll be really exciting I know that
Friends of mine abused actually the site to rent photo
Before vacations actually guys Pro tip
Lumoid jd.com
Walmart.com
Solenoid cam if you really want to like
Try out a fancy camera testengeer
Before a big trip
Or an event
This is actually really good way to do it I know several journalists who've done this before they've covered stories in that sort of
So
We're mostly concerned about your wearable stuff
Because
In addition to like
Having the stuff in the business line
You are also a dataset
And your prior company trueandco
Which I have also used
Was a kind of an online retailer meets offline retailing for
Surprise
And you actually sent people bras out to try
And
Gather data on what bras
Actually gather fit data for them
Then you sent the prize out for
And then
You guys
Kind of track
What people actually kept from the ones that you sent to them
And then felt even bigger and better profiles
So how does that attention towards data kind of
How does that influence what you're doing it live
When I was doing so I went off the coupon first air
My job was to go
M14 pinyin online
One of the things that the exact blood
The entire world was going from
Physical retail stores and online say the same
But people still wanted
Chest and touching feeling
Actually try out items before they committed to buying them
The try before you buy was a no-brainer that worked out really well
Anthony spark needed even more interesting and useful on both sides
And so far as the story by
Is something that we tested before and it's worked really well and in the age of consumer electronics
Now you're seeing Manufacturing moralistic
And Scott is getting into manufactured and used in Kickstarter campaign
Just lots and lots of manufacturing Innovation happening
And the net result here is that
Are many many options to try
But there is no way for you to test drive in
In the comfort of your home
Unless you was deciding to pay full price
Awesome so
What I'm seeing like
Right now you've got like a runner's kid on the site
And let see in that as the Fitbit charge HR the Garmin vivosmart the Jawbone UP24 in the street
Fusion
That's poor and I get this for like a week and it cost me
It looks like $25 is what this cost
Do weed work if you get to either pick a kid
You want to measure
We also have these fun little kids like things like that
If you'll fit into one of these please set aside
Buckets of what kind of credible person you are
You can get the kids or you can pick and choose up to five items
And it's all on the cartwrights and you can add the
Winter Park
Try them out for two weeks
Whenever you decide at the end of two weeks when you decide which one
Is the best for you
Everyday commands
Workout with me
You're really bad at context
And at the end of the lease once you decided which one
The best for you
Will send you a brand-new one of your choice
And that
Price of judicially pig
$25
And then it goes up as you get more expensive devices
That goes towards the purchase of the item
You also have a really interesting gender split on the wearable side
I think four for most of your product so for the drones you have drones and photography are your other two section
And those it looks like they're about 74% male
Yeah and that's what's the interesting part
The most exciting part
Monday-saturday photo video gear
And then you find it
Drones
Retracted gender split and for the longest time
26 virgin female
Launch printable
And Parabola is volume 59%
Answer me that was incredibly surprising because
The perception that you see in mainstream media that gravel dissolve used by men
It's cheetah to understand the sizes are good chords
Pragmatism
By the people who are actually using this
Happened to be more female than men
And you'll have a coordinated dance
+ 4
Most marathons 60% to 55%
And 42
McCormick's very well with back pain
Yeah I wonder if that's because women are more likely to want to try or if we're just more active
For we just care about having
Stats I don't know
2 months ago and you've been tracking it initially we just thought it was an anomaly
And maybe decorated falling out the crib
I've been excited reaching out to the customers and
The more we cleaned up the green Adam RV rental
Define
It's actually true and you know
Kind of different from the rest of consumer electronics has how the perception is
It's much more females are there
And we should be able to just conference play one of the speakers at the same thing they were like
Our customers are
Mostly female
Largest airplane
And I think this is something that we go
We started telling manufacturer Partners to
You need to take notice there's a lot
Maui now
Not sure if that's how you're confusing it but that's ardida
And it might be helpful for you to keep that in mind for your next version of the
Oh that just means more people
That's
Unfortunately that's that's what what I've experienced so far in the gadget world
Let's put some pink on it
You also have the
The Apple watch
Twitch
Is
Ghetto super hot
And it says I think I can
You got a wait list of over 4000 people
The train
How many watches do you have
And then
How many will how many Apple watches
Do you have
Right now we have a little over a hundred units
Apple watches and
Is it Rangers I mean we have most of what we have are
Apple watch it tells we have about
25 units
Get much more expensive and
People want to castrate them
But did you for trying out the sport edition
Because that's the one big injector Toyota Venza
OKC $350
It's a compliment to my phone I can see myself
Music in Paris
Inside out
Hibbett Sports
Waiting to drink only water
Did you work with apple to get those or did you just go buy them up on the site that night
We just went and bought them
Okay so now puts of the wearables
You mentioned sharing data with some of the manufacturer is so do you have Partnerships with those manufacturers
We do with the manufacturers we have Partnerships and now that you're moving thousands of units
Manufacturers are coming out and talking to us that's been denied Spark
And so now he's established on the timer
Ice dragon
Bunch of these companies
And more new ones I think you're doing it please
Jodeci Partnerships
And that's been taking off Julie and
Okay and I can see the rental market for photography being a great sandal in business
But it sounds like on the wearable side it's really like
Hopefully I passed
2 conversion
I don't see a lot of people thinking of man I really need a
Fitbit for a week
It's kind of like
It's more of a try-before-you-buy as opposed to like
A drone to do a project or something
What are the percent of people are percent of purchases people who convert
Parables
Nearly every other customer
About 50% in conversion
Nice
And it sounds like the most popular wearables are the Garmin Vivo
Vivosmart the Jawbone UP24 in the whiting's pulse O2
That's the most popular to try but it looks like the ones that are most popular buyer a little bit different to jawbone up 24 in
Garmin vivosmart are both on that list
The most popular one to buy is actually the Fitbit charge HR
Fitbit charge HR
Beacon off
One eye tearing paper
Think about it and book
Did I think there's this whole section of people who just sang
Bible verses
Exercising to come and go
It's not going to stick it out
Well yeah there's Apple watch that everyone else is going to feel
I think the signing but I do know has like
Making these people
Gravity Auto Sales and the margin that they
There's Something About This variables
I want to try it
Take me to Thai Chili has started doing a really good job with marketing then I need monkey the app
I think they sponsored The Amazing Race recently
And you can eat a lot of that happening and I think that
How much
What do you get
From something like
Yeah mean initially
Much bigger issue when he started the total video.
Initially
But you know we started looking at what other companies like Airbnb
Square
PayPal login companies
We started using the thinking to BPI 50 you
We have our own so I could think to mention theme
Do you that only took them to understand what are the odds of the person committing charge is
Everybody every
Determine whether we shared.
Should we take a refundable deposit for some customers
Are incapable
No
Sixty-five 70% of our customers we don't have any
Deposited
Dave Franco
And being able to shut the box
I like you can always send a drone to hunt them down
I'm imagining you have this huge Warehouse
We do I think we have the largest Native John's in San Francisco
Right now we have 74 so Jones just sitting here in Texas
But what's your favorite drones
Since I'm assume you've tried the
DJI Inspire 1
Beautiful 4K video
And you know what
I think I did it again
$20 to replace
But the doors are locked and the video for kids
Awesome but what is your favorite Will Blast your favorites in all categories
So what's your favorite
Photography
I'll get the year I used to shoot with Canon by mechanic
But recently
Alexei I don't like a small it's full frame
And to baqarah full energy
Ridiculous
Now it's just
Did you send such a good job
Jason Stryker
The expanse
I guess I'm trying to Jawbone up3 just came out a couple of weeks ago
I'm just driving back
Iran economy
Vivosmart
I like it alot
I don't know if anybody else on my team like it but I'm trying to convert them
I'm a gunner
I really like the Garmin vivosmart executive drinks with the connector
Apple watch
And
How to play Candy Apple watch
Battery for my phone
Take me to an iPhone 6 Plus gesture that I get more battery life
Engraved everything
But I'm trying to
You know it's getting better
See I was looking through and I was actually
Kind of tempted by the
The Fitbit Aria smart scale
But I thought maybe I don't really want to nobody
Body fat
Percentage
Everyday I have it every day to Rio
Halloween scale in the office and I have one at home
This is basically what we do it's a lot of fun and it's a lot of numbers
And it's everything is all Quantified Self and
I love it
Slice of pizza
And I having everything at Islanders we have a blood pressure monitor
This is a lot of fun
And I'm sorry but
It just has to have all these gadgets with her
So I
I am totally with you I love having gadgets just for the
The sake of God
Get some things to play with
You know because you have your expertise and data I'm curious
You got you mentioned that you haven't you've just kind of started to do stuff with
Set the data
But just
As you're playing with this stuff do see this is more a toy and fun for you or do you really see like
Life changing
Potential here
Is it just kind of like oh it's a fun thing for people who are well and
Can into that sort of thing or do you think this is really something
Change
Healthcare
You need to have the mindset of the perspective about
How healthy or unhealthy you want to be
And use the wearable with a way to stop dementia life.
I think a lot of people
Once I get
This particular wearable
It's going to change everything I'm just going to quickly lose weight
Elmore
I'm going to be able to
Skinbetter
That's not how it was
You can't expect everything to change just because you have you noticed watch on you
And I feel a lot of people trying to do that continually
And I almost want to tell them what what did you expect
Annies
Because how is it suggested to him this is just for you
You can take it or not ticket
Got to talk to you to be able to read
Internalize it and do something about it
Are they thank you so much for coming on in talking to us about lumoid
Wearables
Send
Hopefully we'll see your next
Business unit come out and maybe it'll have something to do with you know
The Smart Home
Connected devices in the home
Then we can all be excited about that
Thank you so much for having me and yeah when we get into smartphone will be the first
Yeah I'll be lining up to start renting things
To try before I buy
Alright thank you
That's all for this week thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week on the Internet of Things podcast