Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
Is your co-host
Tired Kevin tofu
Tired Kevin
Tired tired
Oh good
That you're happy to be here on Earth
Virtual
Podcast called
So
You just got back from Google IO
Hence the tired part
Maybe we should remind everybody that Kevin
Does work
Google I can actually say I work with the Android in the Chrome folks now I can say it
Got it just so people know where Kevin is
So
First order of business
Google
Home
Yeah
No I've no I want to hear what you have to say cuz I was excited to see it and I know that you were two
Super excited
So here's my
Quick summary
Last week
If you were not paying attention
Google announced
Competitors Amazon Echo competitor
Is it called Google home
It is called Google home and if you go to home. Google.com you can sign up and get
No updates on it yes which I'm sure you probably did I pray
You make it updates
But so
What this is is
It is a speaker
Link to Google Assistant
Which is also new
And
Unlike
The echo
It doesn't have a name that I
I'm aware of yet so there's no lady that you
To call out to and say
I think in the demo they said Hey Google but there is a video that they show that we can always go back or linked to in a shirt
People can see because
They show a video of a family using this device so
How they use it I presume would be how you would use it
Which is so exciting
So there are two features that are really
Freaking awesome
Multicast
So if you have a bunch of these you can actually linked to them just like your Sonos
Play the same thing in every room
Twerk
Yes
Yes you can you can tell
You can say hey Google and I think they're going to use hey Google I'll tell you why
Cuz a lot of phones
Ucok
Google and I pause on purpose
So I didn't stop everybody's phones some people have it set for always listening so if you were to say that
Which device you're talking to right
Yes
Should I point
I wish they went with something a little
More human benefits with Google
The others
Multicast
Well I just want to mention
Google home and they said this in the keno is built on the same technology that they that Google uses for
The Chromecast products
That is important right so the multicast for example
If you had multiple Google homes
You could say
Hey Google Play Rihanna in the living room hey Google play in all rooms
Play
Sachin Sachin a different room so yes you can multi casting control it by voice per room so it's a saunas like experience
Via voice
But it's also
Again because it's
Tied into the Chromecast Technologies
You can
Stream things to a connected TV from it via voice which is something I want so badly
On my echo and my Amazon Fire TV but I don't have right now
Yes
So that is key
And this this is actually a
A bigger differentiator in my house
Which is
In the video
They showed the home device
Beeping at the woman
Wandering around the room
Hey Google I'm listening
Talk to her it gave her a notification
To me this was like killer
Because
Right now my phone
I run Google Now on my phone
It tells me great
Pieces of information like
You should leave in 5 minutes
It's to make this appointment
Write contextual information get surface to you
Yes
That's because I wrote about it in
Before the Android Wear watches came out
When I said contacts this King and I want Google Now on my wrist
There you go so this could be Google Now
In any room that you have
This device
Which
Awesome sauce
Absolutely
I'm super excited about this now
The thing that I
I wrote about it actually the newsletter but I'm a surface it here too
Is
I'm really disappointed
In a couple thing
I'm disappointed that Sonos every time I
I can't talk to it
I just like what
I stopped using my
Almost completely
Leafar really subpar speakers
Because they're easier
Every time one of these comes out
I'm just more irritated
I don't actually
Want to buy a device
To tie into
Because white pictures
Because
I really want it to be more of a like
And here's where Sonos still has me it's
It's okay will provide a really good speaker
You can
Put whatever software you want
Timmy is where the world
Should be going
Because I
May want to Google device in one room
I may want an echo and another and I don't really want to replace my speakers again this is an early adopter thing
Right right
But this is actually going to
Cause people
Pain that financial aid will call it that
Income slow adoption because it's a lot harder to say I'm going to commit to this
Whole ecosystem then it is to say I am going to buy another
Bluetooth light speaker that has these
Escapeability on the back end
And this is abacus
Can product
Yeah because this is why I mentioned
I said Google assistant is also knew because the whole back end
Is this new Google Assistant which
Is I guess the next evolution of Google now so to speak
It was
Touted onstage how
Google can do
You know this type of contacts better than anybody because it knows more about
People in
You know the algorithms we have any idea aviata
And In fairness I I actually do agree with that be
Because when I look at the echo what does Amazon really know about me well
It definitely is my purchases
It definitely some of my consumption habits based on what music I listen to
Emma Cleary's I asked
Black
Knows where I live
But
Amazon itself doesn't have that relational database of all of my contextual information some of it like
It knows my search history but it's not
The results are not coming from it and they're coming from
Maybe you will from Alfred or you know Wikipedia or being
And whatnot what Google is saying is
We provide you all that information yeah we don't just get your search and
And your consumption areas we actually have the information we can tie it all together
So you getting
You're right Google home is a front-end to the Google Assistant
Back-end
Do you want to tie into that ecosystem I mean it's a personal choice and personas users I totally get it
You invested money you want to stick with what you have your happy with it
This website is a lot people don't have a Sonos and
Chromecast the whole idea was userland on speaker
I don't care what speakers you use just plugging this little dongle you know what
You can
Use that with Google home
And use the speakers already have so to speak so
I think you're right I think there's going to be a lot of people like no I'm not going into this because I have a Sonos or be there still a big mistrust
How Google uses data what it knows how much it knows so
There are people who would just say I don't use any Google probably cuz I don't want Google to know everything about me
I think that's true and I would also say
When comparing the two ecosystem
Honestly it might be nice to
To do both because
Who is banking on
The back end in the knowledge
That it has a
Right
What we haven't heard yet
The echo
An Amazon has built in this very open
So what they don't know about you
You can actually pull from just about anywhere
And just say hey I want to enable these skills
I have all
Apus access to things
If you combine the two
Man that would be amazing
Cuz you brought the skills and I agree with your and I think Amazon is in a great job I mean I have the Echo and a DOT
Right now and we talked about a bazillion times in the show and I love them
And you're right you can plug in if your
I mean you are I could write a skill
Create our own little skill
Or the echo
If there is someone out there that meets our needs
But
I think Google took a different
Approach in that
It makes it easy for developers to tap into
IT services
A little bit easier as opposed to skills on the echo
They seem like a
I want to say I hacked because they're not
It's just it seems more clingy to me
So
Yes
They also have and I'm sorry everybody
They have
Voice services
Yes I do yes which means
If you don't want something kludgy you can actually again this is a dedicated device but in this case the dedicated device doesn't have to be
Speaker it could just have
Access to the bank
And we haven't even
Apple
It apparently is working on something similar and it plans to open up the SD
Dk4 Siri
Or at least
We're not 100% sure
Because at Apple
Where it's going with this but it wants to give developer
Siri which
Yay
Siri came out I want to say in 2011 and I say came out meaning it came out on the iPhone 4 commercial or
Consumer use
Technology in the company actually existed before that
An apple purchased it
But the implemented into the into iOS
I think 2011
I don't really see what they've done too much on that
What's inside and I've said this a couple times and post and podcast
Kenneth Siri, got stagnant
And it's it's almost past time I think for
This to happen but it's still very good
It will make a lot of people
Happy once
Apps are fully integrated into Siri
Our with Siri I should say
Yeah no I mean I've I've started using
Anxiety
Like I
Say okay
And then I say
Google and I can do a lot with my phone
Yeah opening up other apps
Everything Zen
So it's kind of my husband sometimes
Siri
And you're right it did come out
Faurecia
So
That's that
Pictures of pulling one last thing I'm
Siri unless you're in a Tyler Moore
I'm wondering what they're going to do with that and homekit
Will Siri does control homekit
You can do things with it
And I forget cuz I am not as good with numbers time is a
A fluid thing
With the always-on Siri that
What's in the iPhone
5S
It came out maybe a year ago for plugs in devices but now the newer devices don't need to be plugged in for it to work
Certain on plugged in
Having until they have that it was kind of
I thought silly
Of course the fact that home kid is not really fully baked yet
Is
You know kind of
Arella hurt
It makes it almost irrelevant
You can say
Whatever they
Wake up word for serious you know turn on the lights in living room
And it should
Nice
That's there I haven't played with it
Recently enough that I can tell you what the
Sure
All-in-all I mean what I really like is
All of these
Are advancing
You know that the user interface for your home weather
Lights or whether it's energy things or whatever it may be TVs
And that's really the key to me and end
I think you're going to see a lot of
I said more competition in the space now
It seems like it's gaining traction the market has been proven
Mainly I think by the echo
Which
The CEO of Google Sundar pichai actually give a shout out on stage saying
No thanks Amazon for
You're showing
The world that
This can be done
And people are enjoying it
So
You know it doesn't matter to me which platform you use I think
All of them are going to get them immensely better over the next
6 to 18 months as a result of all this
This is why you don't want to hardware
Well
Yeah you need you need some kind of Hardware you need microphones and need speakers and you need something to capture and
Something to send to the capture text to the
Web services that translate the natural language processing and
Sorry I hear you but I don't know how else you
Could do it yet
I like
You mentioned the web services that Amazon offers notice I didn't mention her name you could build that into a TV
For Allah
Sprint live chat
Speaker a small chip in the end of microphone so I like the way they're going in a sense because it's
You can put it into any hardware supposed to
Find specific Hardware
Yes but you do have to build the ontology
It is says
Vocabulary of words that will turn your you know
Cuz I really want to tell my Roomba to
Uflymike
It's very
Actually work
The Voice Services her voice service
Supports the words fly my pretties and recognizes that that will
Actually
Which still though I mean we're making progress here as opposed to
When Siri first came out that was really the first one
Lucy and natsu
That's true and that's where the openness I think that's where
You know the echo building up the developer ecosystem matter I mean
Siri stagnating I think is partly because
You just couldn't
Do much with it
Beyond like what
Describe Apple
Exactly it was a very native bacon solution and it's finally now becoming what we I just hoped it would
Become
Openness yay for the win
Speaking of openness one less
Quick thought
The one thing we did not hear from Google while we've been here a couple things I wouldn't hear price or availability for Google home
I think it was later this summer or maybe later this year
Better this year okay yeah there's a lot of products announcing their all later
You can't get anything that was announced yet
Except for something I know we're going to talk about shortly
And
The one big missing piece to me
Where was thinking about you and I talked about this
As soon as it was announced
There was no list of
Partner products and such that it will work within the home
Other than of course nest
So we don't know
You know is it going to work with WeMo is it going to work
Wink smart home there's more things in
Intel Cannon
And then all the others
So there's a lot of
Open questions on
Who is going to be a partner for this
All right
We're moving on
These are could be shorter Converse
Pebble
Announced some new products that will launch
Again
Actually not even later this year some of them won't come out until
The beginning of next year
The pebble core
I was so excited about this you guys if you heard me talk about it was
The device called The Mighty you'll understand why this is a
Clip on iPod Nano
Has both
The possibility of a Cellular Connection you will have to buy your own
And
4 gigs of memory so it can store your Spotify playlist
You can listen to it with
Wired or wireless headphones
And I love it
I love you not having to carry
Phone
On a walker run specially as it gets hotter in
My clothes just
Super excited early bird specials on Kickstarter
And it's going to retail for 99
But I won't be out till January
No I run a lot both with a phone and without a phone
And I like what they've done here
But I probably will not get one and the only reason why
Is
I can already do all that on my SmartWatch
I don't need to carry my phone like it might have GPS in it
I have
I'm working for a cat 4 gigs of storage I have Bluetooth
Compatibility for
No foreign
Listen to music
So
I think
At this point I think it's great and then and I do think they'll do well with it
But
I almost feel and you intersect I want to throw this question at you and you can please just agree with me
I must feel like this is a little bit of a pivot for them
It is
So they also announced
It is to new watches but they're really the same
Old watches
With the addition of a heart rate monitor
It is a little bit of a
Pivot
It's a reckoning
Maybe they plan to do this all the time
Baby the idea was
Entrance through wearable Computing and I do think
Wearable Computing is going to have
A billion different form factor
So I think it's really interesting for any company that's looking at this because personally
I think
The technology should be
Freaking interchange
Alright and it's how you execute
It's going to be
The pebble is really if you think about what they're doing they're really trying to do that
It'll be hard for a small company though to build a bunch of school
You know a bunch of different products like that
Whenever you know I'm glad to see the moving out of just SmartWatches because like
Fruit for your example
I don't like
You know I get it I get it
So I like the fact
Score in
I also like the fact that you don't maybe they'll get into like
Jewelry or maybe they'll get into something crazy like sticking modules inside athletic
Close
That's kind of where I think this will go
Anna I don't disagree. I like
That there
The recognizing we can just
Be a smartwatch company we need to be a smart wearable company
So I think you're right I think they're going to
Continue innovating new products after doing SmartWatches now for the better part of
At least 3 years
I remember their initial Kickstarter was the largest Kickstarter ever
I do find it interesting that they're using Kickstarter again as the
Point of sale for this it's kind of
Super strong release
Yeah
So that's
That's what that is
Yeah I totally get it and you can go
Bed Retail Partners as well as it's not just the kickstarter think so
Probably smart for them to Leverage
Leverage the relationship with Kickstarter and I don't want to downplay this by Pebble Court too much
I mean everything I won't buy one
It can do something that my SmartWatch is my car smogged
Just can't do
Because there's a 3-g connection
You know if you want to pop a SIM card in there you can do that and
Not just could you stream Spotify instead of
Plain local playlist
You could actually
Send your location in emergency
It has a programmable button so you can you can hack away kind of like the you know the Amazon tile
I make it a single-purpose thing and
Again my watch when I go out for a run and we just found behind I can do everything but
Tell my family hey come pick me up I got a problem or whatever
There are certain smart watches and
I think you're going to see this actually
Quite a bit in the future
Have integrated 3G or LTE but
My watches don't so the Pebble Court definitely has a an advantage over what I have
We're still going to need that
Yeah I guess either you know 5 or $10 a month to add has a device I presume
Characteristics plant
Pricing
Yeah that's that's what they've done with smart watches that have LTE just a device like a tablet for 10 bucks it's
I suspect maybe it'll be five bucks
Highway robbery well yeah because considering how much
How little did are you use on a
Pebble core vs connect a tablet I agree but if you
Portray it as
Emergency contact
I suppose
You know you're paying $10 a month for being always able to
Connect are you a Spotify user
I am
And I am not so when I sit here in and see
That you can only stream Spotify without 3g connection to Penelec
Why can't I pick and choose my
They're going to add other
Partners in maybe they'll have another reason
Set partner
I don't know
Yeah so we'll see
Okay
So this should bring us up to more wearables which is Android Wear in Tyson
Which
The rumor has it
That Samsung is debating
Using tizen on its SmartWatches as opposed to Android Wear
Now
The story came out and was like
Kind of walk back
So write the story was
Samsung is abandoning at Android Wear essentially an in Samsung to huge and our partner so
Of course everything
But then there's been an update which is
Not much of an updating anyways Engadget spoke to
A Samsung representative and said no no no everybody is missing
Interpretive essay
And we didn't say that we're not going to do Android Wear
But they're not saying that they're going to either so it's really kind of
Fuzzy right now
But the reality is
Samsung actually started with Android wear with its first Gear watch
3ish two years ago to si2
Cuz I don't want Android Wear hasn't been around that long
But they eventually came out with additional models that use their
Not there ties in with the open-source ties end
And then they switch the Android Wear ones that they have on the field they sent a firmware update and updated them all
Tyson so really
It's not a huge surprise if they don't make an Android Wear device anymore
Because I really not doing it today
I think it was more of positioning that the media token like is a big big issue
I don't know that it is or not
Okay
So there we have it
And then
Will ended
An update for you guys a couple episodes ago we talked about
Vampire power consumption and I said I would wander around with my
WeMo Insight switch and test power consumption of
Wink
And
What you find out
They don't consume a lot of power
Yay
This is good news
Zodiac
Roughly 3 Watts a day
Wow that's low
Superlo
So I take
Really high electricity rates I pay like $0.16
Per kilowatt-hour
I I get very confused when I think about this and so it's saying I'm going to use
About
$0.34 a month paying for my Amazon
Sunlake
Totally worth it
And then
Which is the Hub that
Used most often
Antennas less than 2 what
The cutoff point for the WeMo
Inside switch so I I can't
Tell you exactly how much
Consumes
It could be less
Estimate like $0.20 a month to run it over
It is okay it's okay it has to be less than
The $0.37 from
America
It's west of the 34 Cent
Just a quarter just a quarter
$0.25 I don't know
It's still super loud which is awesome
It is you should be running all kind
Because why not
It consumes $0.22
Sam's close
Yeah you were you were very close it's saying today it's
It's so far consumed less than
A tenth of a penny
That's pretty awesome
So there you go so
Both are always on connected devices that are
In my house always on and
Neither
Is going to break the bank
However
If you have
Doesn't something
If like certain
People like me
You may find yourself consuming a lot of energy
So that is
The update there
Keep trying if you guys
Try anything in
Particular icon
Play things and I'd be curious to see what a IP video camera
You want to plug in a Foscam into your inside
That's a good point I do have a Foscam I may be packed already since we're moving but I will I will look for it
That's okay
At precisely the wrong time.
Okay
All right
And now it's time for our guest Our Guest this week
Is Ryan Kim the CEO of
A newly-formed company from Belkin
And we will find out what they're doing there's a lot of noise and hives around
Founded the Internet of Things Market
Everyday another company emerges adding to the growing Den
It's difficult to rise above the noise and position your company is a leader
Callisto is a marketing Communications agency in The Internet of Things
They have successfully launched iot startups and turn them into Market leaders
They positioned incumbent companies in iot providing unique
Messaging and campaigns that help them stand out as thought leaders
Everything Kalisto does is centered on creating a strong Roi
Fritz clients Market
Wedding programs
Through its content marketing public relations and social media service
Calista could help you tell your uni coyote story to the influencers that matter in this growing Market
Free consultation contact Marissa Evans
@m Evans at Callisto. Com
Or visit Calisto @www
A. Chal
Why
Sto
Dot-com and now back to the show
Hey everyone welcome back to the internet
Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Chris Klein Who is the
CEO
Co-founder of
Rachio
Hey Chris
Thanks for having me
Oh thanks for coming on the show we had a lot of questions about Russia
Listeners who don't know what this is can you give them a brief overview of what you are selling
Sure so we make an internet-connected bring the controller for residence
Ira places on the existing timer that you would find on your wall in your garage and once it's connected
Weehawken
Consumers
I got its information about their about their Zone in their landscape and then take that information
I don't do things like adjust the frequency of watering
Adjust the duration of watering
And we can watch for a ringtones and make sure you're not watering in the rain
Awesome
And I will let you guys know that I actually installed one of these about 2 weeks ago
Water
We'll talk about that in the future
It was easy to install
And so far my father-in-law's house
What I was actually kind of
Surprised out when I connect to a
Weather station that actually is kind of far away from
There's no sensors here I kind of always thought for something to be really intelligent
I'm very curious like
Do you have plans to kind of
Add to the product or do you think maybe you know you'll do that through like an ecosystem play
Yeah that's a great question and I didn't weather specifically is
One that we get a lot about a lot of questions around in
Birth certificate the same exact circumstances you ran into where there is a weather station that is
If I were 6 miles away
The really good news is
Absolutely approach
Perspective and create another
Accessory
Study we can also leverage other products that are out there like
Uid number of
Text mother station then
Yo where did using one letter seriously
Plan do I do that until you can
Imagine that there is a number of
Personal weather stations in all kinds of weather information that will make
It's a digital version of whether I'm better and
You better resolution as a user
I feel like I don't know if I want to digital version to the
I feel like the real-world analog versions of the weather
They're alright you know some services are getting really good at analyzing radar and weather stations and
I didn't even using water balloons and the other getting out of basically one square kilometer of high-resolution weather
15 minutes
Get really cool and you can kind of get that digital version of it and use it in our software
Let's think about how all this plays out because
A lot of companies
I feel miss the Mark is a start up there like
Intelligent
I think that a lot of them
Don't realize it
Maybe the in-service that you're delivering here isn't a connected sprinkler that's easier to program
But I know that's what my father
Curious how you say
Kind of rachio when you think about the actual problem you're solving
Start a company with with a mission to really
Save water in and make it available
Sustainable way
And your water use
Outdoors is hugin in the US
And you know a smart sprinkler controller
Where the input comes from
In terms of weather and
Soylent
Even Flow sensors
Yeah you can really start to dial that in
Especially with great that's what's great about a product is weekend update the software over the years and make it better and better
I'm in and really reduce that that way
And that's really interesting for
Just holidays to a lot of
The Westin house
Water reduction
Whataburger or
Goals are ejected they're trying to meet I think
What was really close when you have Cactus products
Analytics bacon look and see if they're beating their targets
Or even predictive
Alex on when we think we might water may be based on last year or
What we're seeing in the upcoming couple weeks or months
I was thinking about this because here in Texas we have
Edgewater
Conservation
Program
And I was thinking you know if everyone in my neighborhood for example
Like the neighbor neighborhood
Right now we've got water restrictions so like you can water like maybe one day a week if you're on one side of the street
Another day the other
You know if you're on the other side with the system like this if everyone has some sort of
Intelligent sprinkler system in that data would you could contribute that data to
Neighborhood pool
You can actually
Maybe do a lot more
I guess personalized watering and maybe
Baby the city takes over as a service
I just think the power there is really interesting but I'm not sure how
Never get to something
Know yet that's super interesting to us as well as
Actually we didn't work in a couple minutes polities. If you have Ark
Controller you don't have to follow the restrictions because of some
We have some type of schedule that only really Waters when it when it needs to
And you're
Artificial Warriors butt
I think
Yeah you touched on it that is as a community
Yo almost like a budget and look at the fair budget
Hey we only have this much water today at to use Outdoors
This is the most often used for it
I am your municipality in
Customers and Technology can work together to really create a task
It's a sustainable watering
Planters Outdoors
To me that's fast
Although then you kind of get into issues of Lake
Although it also turns brown
Is that something you guys would ever
Waiting
Americans love their lawns
Is that something you guys are thinking about her
Yeah absolutely I mean I think you would even love to be able to make recommendations on
Yo people in
In your area have benefits many zones are this this much square footage of a lawn
Buffalo grass or Kentucky Bluegrass and
Now you may consider
Switching some of these islands out to I'm more of a Zero Escape or a drought resistant
Pipezone
Here's the recommendation
How to do that
And yeah I think that's definitely part of our plan as well
I am
Let's get going
I do I've given up
That's kind of
Long-term vision
Today you guys are on your second generation product
What have you learned because the last time I talked to you I think it was before you launch your first-generation product
You are amazing cuz y'all were already in
You're going into Home Depot so
How's it been what have you learned from now
2 Generations
Yes oh it's been
Experience
One of many things we learned in 900 should just be a given but
I'm sorry that it seems but
Create a really reliable products
Hardware to Software
Connectivity
Customer support
Helping a customer sometimes
No it's their first connect device or even a second
Make that transition into a connected world where they found from
Wanting to
You're wanting to but that's what they were doing
Do controlling it
Falling asleep
Hey
We're going to watch for water and we're going to adjust your schedule over the month
And experiences.
Build that trust those those customers out overtime and make sure that information at their fingertips
Nothing much at this time of day
Other than Running Springs prices like that was kind of first and foremost get all that right
And there's ways to have optimized from there
In specifically because I know a lot of
Companies are trying to get their products in a big box retail
Words of wisdom for those guys
I didn't realize we were the lucky situation where we were at the first product of her kind
And retailers were really looking to build out this connected home
Japanese second home category
So the number of Dimes
Got in touch with us they did with other
Entering space
Same time
They dilated products and you know they they brought ours in getting into retail
Wasn't necessarily difficult for us
I think that was just a function of
Timing in the pot if you're watching
And even things like Bike Shop in the last
But I actually
Going through the channel is where ye'll it starts to get a bit more difficult and I think that's where we're really learning as a
As a company now
What are some of the things you've
Insofar
Telling the story of iot at the Shell
Is difficult
There's a lot of information to kind of pack into that small area that you have on on a Shelf
You know one thing that we're finding right now at retail and
Witness it first-hand
Just last weekend for example
Izod I it's really
Appears to be a destination sale
Well you have a lot of
Murders that are coming into
The Stars themselves
Driving to the store. Just last weekend
I'm talking to someone in the irrigation
Daughter unit
It's amazing how people come in and ask for it by name
I was at the shop and I was standing there another gentleman walked up and
I'd like to have the wink on cat
Where is it at
I think that's what we're seeing right now at retail is that it's really the onus is on
Start up companies like elastic I'll bring those people to the shelves to go by the product but not necessarily
We are going to find that magic formulas and I'm than learning at the Shelf quite yet
Difficult
Know that there's a lot of information
And I'm delighted by the idea
You're standing out in the
Irrigation
Local hardware store
That's about it
Happy lighting aisle or the
My my look
Accosting random stranger
Hi
How is it
Dealing with your customer
Because one of the things that I find from
People who have built
You know pretty successful connector
They have
And dedicated customer base who is not afraid to tell them
When they mess up
And I think it's both a blessing and a curse so I'm curious like how you view
I don't know the early adopters still that your cuss
Yeah it it's funny you should ask that we we were very vocal
Customer base and we loaded our community is Super Active online
As we are even near the road right at other channels
AR support directly
But our community specifically they give us great feedback on all kinds of features things we're planning things that we
I give you a great example is
Beaver trying to simplify the product a little bit
And actually produce a better scheduling system then we move the future
I met a girl
Call rr Flex scheduling
It can be somewhat unpredictable sometimes
It really is the right way to water
He was great in helping us understand that we should bring it back
Can we listen to all and they brought up some really great point that we hadn't even thought through
Because that we're excited to bring it back and she better rate on that product with them
Actually really know what the problem is that was all that now
That kind of stuff is invaluable
True know how then as you become
Hopefully we'll cross our fingers more successful
How do you
Account for the demands of a vocal few perhaps like you're hardcore users and then
What everybody else me
It's because I think that's going to be
A challenge for a lot of these companies
As they find success
Oh absolutely that's a conversation we have on a daily basis
Nothing for us
It was
We didn't try to make a reaction
We want to do is replace one type of schedule with
A different time
And you know we talked about it as a group and said
If we weren't going to
If you're just going to say we went to remove this feature the future that we ended up
The scheduling
Turning off would we actually do that
Or we compromise anything he will replace it with this
Yeonwoo scheduled mean on the new schedule really wasn't what they were looking for and what you kind of went through the process of
Dining around saying well actually all we've done is taken away future.
Yell at certain percentage of our customers really like
We made a decision that we should bring it back until
It can be completely replaced
What's something that would make them happy and it is hard to evaluate by The Warriors versus the majority
But we do have data only have an idea of you know how many people have those types
Schedules and
Time you were able to make a decision on that
Awesome and
What is next
For you guys
You've done that the first gen sprinkler
Sprinkler controller
2nd gen product
Enclosure and outdoor enclosure that
You sound like
There's some logical
Yeah
You don't have to pass to go down
I think one is DP accessories kind of modeling
There's a number of pieces of hardware and
Products that are on a road map that we can make good I think compliments
Controller nicely
Yeah there's I think the software called the company
Very excited about
Natural extensions that maybe you know Tyson some enterprising and and I
Or maybe business and let me buy.
Trip to
Adjacent markets that are really interesting.
What is a professional landscape space
70% of these controllers have been solved by
Landscapers 4 years
I am
Yeah we're we're trying to learn from them about what makes our controllers
How it can possibly improve their businesses
Or make their communication with the customer better or you know Christian relationships and bonds
I'm about to produce products to them that they can help him.
The other Jason Market is really utilities
It's really interesting to see how they're approaching water conservation problems or even things is simplest keep shaving
You know what really starts to happen when you have this
Throat
Disconnected nodes out there that can help solve some of these bigger problems
Balance of those types of
I'm heading frosting
You know we're looking forward to continuing to
When I open my rachio I noticed that this was
Actually the whole things made in America
And I did want to ask you about
True Manufacturing efforts
Because
Struck me as
Yeah
There's a lot of things that go into that
And
The only was first launched in the product
We wanted to
Because to a manufacturer we wanted to be able to move with Speed and Agility
And
At the same time
Blvd Costa design process
BO2 45 minutes from RR 290 pictures then
I can't tell you how valuable that has been
Show me different circumstances where you get to drive up to the the factory
I was all on the side
You don't get the process back up and running
Driving that was the most important
Things for us when we are first starting
Apple at the same time
I can't tell you like how great it
Feels to walk onto the Florida manufacturer
I'm a ninja.
You know you're helping put people at work
I not on people are excited to work on your product in
That's a great experiences while in
So far it's been rewarding enough.
You know we want to continue to manufacture here in the US
All right
How many do you guys produce a day
We can produce up to 2000 today
Wow
Awesome Chris thanks so much for coming on the show
Thank you so much for having me
Thanks for listening that's all for this weekend we'll see you again next week on the Internet of Things podcast