Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Awesome
First Step we're going to have
Conversations about
Light bulb
The thread group
Comcast
Conversations about what happens when your devices don't work
And our guest this week
Is Charlie Kindle
Who is the head of Amazon's Echo
So the first thing I have to
How to tell you is for the beach
You're going to want to run over to your echo in Muse that microphone
Because we can keep to the Alexa rule
I just said it couldn't talk about it
But first
Let's do a quick word from our sponsor Lively
Working on a better connected product
Don't do it yourself
Its complex
Could be years before you're up and running
Yours Uke
Can't afford to wait
So accelerate your time-to-market be riskier investment
And Leverage is ivory
They're iot experts and business ready award winnings Ivory platform will help you launch quickly
Securely and at scale
Learn more at jd.com
That's x i v e l y
Dot-com
Okay
So
Thanks idly
Let's get started with
One more reminder turn off your Echo Bike
Let's talk about
Big news of the week
Which is
I don't know there's not a lot of big news for this week but we'll talk about the thread
Because
Keeping up with the osc
And basically this is like standards alphabet standards
Red is the protocol it's a wireless protocol that kind of competes with Bluetooth or Wi-Fi that was
Secreted by nest
Silicon labs
Freescale
Big
Crossword
Fans
Couple other company
What it's done is it
Low power
Mesh networking standard
It is also IPv6 compatible which means your sensors can talk directly to the public internet
Is it 8:00 or 2:15
Yeah
That's the same
Radio
Zigbee
Protocol uses
Sew-ins
Together on backwards
That's
There
Indeed
Ocf
Brushes
Formerly the open connectivity Foundation
Which is formerly
Known as IO tivity
This was a standard group that Intel kind of pulled together
To act as a communication to Discovery platform so
But if something's in your house and talking to another thing
If you like high
This is what can talk to me and how it talks
And what it can do
I'm in somebody else would be like I refrigerator
I can accept the following commands to do the following things
And it's this was a really
Cool idea focused on kind of interoperability
And it
Peter with all join
Which was the Qualcomm standard
Same thing
Qualcomm people ended up going over to
Intel
And
Then
Eocf
Was created
Kind of
Pull all that in together
So
Qualcomm now back thread
If I'm not mistaken
Alcatraz facts
Grouping
A large hamper company
Is Communications protocols or like
This is the radio
Blair
Ocf
UC application
Is that make sense
So just like you said the application Level with
These are the things I can do my device will tell or expose what it can do what commands what functions
And the radio level is where all the communication habits that make sense
Now there is no timing on their service
Medication and
That's kind of
Frustrating
That if you have a device that will be thread certified at some point in the
Unknown feature
CF
Certified
Those two things
In the summertime
So that's the idea
That's the fun
That's the new
I don't know what else to
To say because right now until we actually see
This could be something
Yes
It's good for the
Industry as a whole because it does mean that all that standard soup we were talking about you know two years ago
Even last year even last week
Sorted out
That's the Hope every see these kinds of announcements all the time we seen them for years with wireless charging standard and then you saw consolidate
Weixin overtime between different
Groups different companies different Technologies and approaches
You're starting to see some
Of that in IRT and it's super important because you need interoperability otherwise you've got this
Fragmented mess of products and standards and radios and
Cubs that just
Add devices
Promise the world but they're little silos and we don't want that
For people who cuz I asked them about what happens with a joint
Because a lot of people actually implemented
I was told
Microsoft is going to be
Ensuring interoperability between
The ocf
In all joints
So they're in the process of doing that
For Windows and some other members are trying to
To do the same thing
For other platform
There's no timing on that
But
That's really good news
If you were like an alternate doctor
Because I'll join with super easy just
Could share what it did
Still emerging
And
Don't lose hope
Bet on that
But
Honey
Baby
Lose a little hope
Smart bulb vulnerability
We should we should have a night this caught my eye because I have three osram bulbs in my house
Houston with my wing coven
They work really well
However
It wasn't me make sure I get this right
Rapid7
Came out with a vulnerability report and found
9 different
Vulnerabilities with the osram Sylvania
Lightify bulbs now
Some of them
Four of them have to deal with the home platform which is what I use and five of them
Deal with the pro platform which actually did not know there was a profile for nothing
I'm going to use it
I just thought that was kind of interesting
Some of these
Items have been fixed
It's already some of them have not and there's no indication of if or when they will be
But one of the ones going to keep once that was fixed
Is that the
The osram python restoring your
Home network
SSID or network name as well as your
Passcode to get into the network
In plain clear text and that's yeah
Security 101
I know it's just it's just I'll say inexcusable
This point really is
Yasso
There's some other other issues
Persistent xss in the web Management console
Of the pro side and that's why I didn't see this myself cuz I don't login to control
My osram bulbs on a website but apparently with the pro platform you either can or you to
So there was some cross
Scripting
Issues there that could inject
Malicious JavaScript in
Best way take control of things through the browser
Since again I use an app
Don't have that concern but still it's that the problem that one was fixed as well so
We should put a link in the show notes of the vulnerability so if you can keep track of them cuz I know that there's not just home users of osram
Wake me up probably some Pro users as well so
I shall make it happen
All right. Speaking of security vulnerabilities there is a lovely story on motherboard by Bruce
Shania
Spire
There's no d
Gyros
Who wrote David and Goliath
Excellent book if you haven't read it
Aurigny
Care about security
His story he talked about basically the vulnerabilities that the internet of things is going to
Kind of Usher end
And it's not like we don't know a lot of this stuff
But he makes a huge prediction in the story which is the next
President
Will probably be forced to deal with a large-scale internet
And I was like
That's a pretty big prediction.
Some of the things that he's saying that are actually worth
Worthwhile
Are that the government needs to play a larger role in iot
She want some
Standards
This is kind of working on this
For other aspects
The internet so it doesn't it it makes sense that this would do this for the Internet of Things
Policing
Compliance switch
Could be
I don't know what other agency might get involved there I mean if it's
If it's infrastructure you can even see like the. Or any of the agencies
Responsible
I don't want to agree with him but I sort of 2in that his his prediction of Doom and Gloom
Is a likely scenario
I mean it's one thing when we are getting hacked for digital
Information photos
It's a totally different
Situation when
Physical thing
Better controls
Via
What you say
Iot or the internet
It could be
Taking over or causes death destruction and such a man
It's concerning and I think he I think he's right again I don't want to agree with him but I do
I don't want to see this app
It's true in a lot of
Companies are really like a lot of the big name companies are very focused on his but when we say things like
The awesome stuff you're like really guys
That's not acceptable so
Let's just light bulbs in a lightbulb
Probably isn't going to
I mean I guess you could
Make it go out possibly make something explode I don't really know
Yeah I mean
Chances are
The light bulb itself isn't going to hurt anything but as we seen through the
Security vulnerabilities we just talked about
Somebody could've been getting network access and then have access to
Other things that could cause destruction in your networks so
It's really to me that's just like I ate a front door
Into a bigger problem
Yes
And he does some lovely math here if 100 systems are all interact
Each other that's about 5000 interactions
Potential vulnerabilities
Resulting for
Interactions
300 or interact
That's forty five
I mean it was exponentially because of all the connectivity
So he talks about interconnection being a big issue software-controlled being a big issue the software
Challenges something we talked about on the show before because
They're basically saying
Today we rely on patching
And kind of continuous support of our OS has to patch our smartphones
Computers
But with
Devices in the home that are going to be there for 15 or 10 years and have a business model that may not support patching
So it's funny that you mention it because as I was reading through hearing and I noticed that
I'd like to know what we've already set a very very bad president when it comes to security patches
With
What are the most successful devices
Ever on the planet
Smartphone
There are billions of them out there and yet
Security always seems to be
Talk about but more of an afterthought when it comes to a permutation and especially so
After the sale of the device
And that's because the device makers
Don't
You know that better
Expend resources to pass these things
But they're not getting any information revenue from that
So it worries me that we've got we've set up a very dangerous trend
With security patches on mobile devices
And it's even
It's magnified when it comes out of Qi devices I think
It is and
That's one of the reasons why I
I'm very interested in
NC nudist
Says bottles even though I hate the idea
Description
It may have to be the way to go
Go to support
Because it's the device makers are going to provide to do so
Then your I agree maybe there are
Opportunities for companies to do this and
Give people peace of mind you're willing to be a subscriber
Yes
This is why
Companies like Comcast see an opportune
Trinity and that was my
In the IRT is because they're going to be the ones
Patching and focusing on
Delivering devices in doing so as a service
No matter what we think of Comcast
Their Xfinity home business actually
They reported earnings this week and as part of that
Their revenue in the other category which includes Xfinity home
Increased
13.7% year-over-year
So just 644 million for the quarter
Year-to-date so far that's one point
3 billion
So
That's not insignificant now
The other Revenue also includes advertising
And
Is it regular
It's hard to say that how much of it
Applies to their Xfinity home
Bit but
But I imagine it
What you doing
Okay
We'll keep an eye on that
That's on that side
So maybe a Services model that has a big player checking security
Comcast get security right maybe that's good
For the industry overall
I don't know
I know people are not probably excited about give
No but you know going back to what we were talking about
Potential business opportunity for companies to build Security Solutions or patch solutions for IRT
I would hope that
My $30 a month for Xfinity home
I think it's their base price animal can't right now
That they will
Take on that role of patching and keeping things secure I'd love to see them actually
Run Security reports are scans on your
You're stopping to say hey we got to the secured
And I do that every 6 months
People at peace of mind and you're already paying it
A subscription so
Implicit to me and I don't know
Scriber other service
Is that these devices are secured and patched
Celeste
Artwork
Because
This was a
Lovely wait for devices that aren't work
This ties back
Pandora
Model 2
For a little bit for some customers remote access to the nest actually went out this week
I don't know what to say here
That's what happened
They went out
Usher
Possibly not fed during our outage
Lawson schedule
So
We always talk about having
Control a basic functionality on the device
Yes
If your nest thermostat in that case it was just remote access
Which man if you are away from home and wanted to change
So sorry for you
So
That's a little more worries
What if you're on vacation
What's my option for feeding my cat
Right right do you happen to know if
How long between the outage
We're winning out of started how long it took them to contact customers because
Do we have cats
I'm home all the time
H I know they can go if
Worst case
A day without food
Yeah I'm hoping that
This was a timely response
I'm looking to see if there was a time
Timely response
Just hoping it wasn't an after-the-fact thing or
4 days later by the way
By the way your cat may not have been fed this week at all
Hopefully you don't
I don't know what happened in Scituate
But
What's another word of caution for companies want to be in these spaces
They need to make sure they're communicating
Quickly with customers when they have issues
I'm not seeing any timing on there now
So
What a bummer
But this is like $150
Peter Katz
And I'm looking on their their Twitter account
RPI baby they sent out emails to people
Email
No idea
But
So the point here is
When do things go out
This kind of ties back
Continue talking about the f
TC
And there are questions that we talked about last week which was are you selling device are you selling a service
I think
Pastor that is when something goes out
How much functionality do you have left
Right so
And then
If you are selling a service
What kind of like
Refund should you be getting
Consumers like when your cable company
Has an outage
You can actually fight and ask them
For a refund
So if you got an old adage you better get a credit on your bill
Some people are that way sub
So I was thinking about this both because of this but also because last week I told you about the August door
Tell that I have
As frustrated because
I don't have
Access yet to
They are they haven't turned on the
Motion control
Or is he
And they said they would have it by the end of June
So I called them and they're said okay now it's going to be the end of
Sometime in
So
6 months without
What I consider basic functionality in a video doorbell
Two of these acts
For 6 months it hasn't even worked like it's supposed
When I feel
I feel like if I were
Any other customer I would be
Asking for a refund
Because
It's except so many frogs come out better and in the functionality is so you know 50 to 80% of the way there and
Features XYZ are coming soon stay tuned
And you still invest in it
Because you assume you're going to get
The product
Centos features
Hey what if they never show up
That's a possibility
Abby Weatherford away which is exactly what the case here and
Yeah it sucks
Agreed agreed
Are there any add-on costs that will come with a new features like for the cloud stuff for now
And there may be a
Subscription service
Some of the cloud will be
Okay one
Wait a minute
Well
You know say the first three months will be free because you were late you know
Going to waive the fee
Amazon support
The other thing is they didn't
Tell me I had to ask
They did not send me an e
Email
Saying
Hey I know in our press release launching
Medicine everybody reported that this was going to be out by the end of
But
I guess it comes down to it that people buy the product
Specifically for these functions that are coming cigarette some people may not care
Let me not and and that worries me even more because what if
A majority of the customers
Don't care
And the company has been in generic terms but obviously I'm applying it to August here what if they decide to know it
Are you the bases and clamoring for this
America was never great
I don't want to think about that
Cuz I really want
The cloud storage
Lesso
Although I like it having
Doorbell YouTube
Although it does take a picture of the last time
So I can see who was
Even without it
But
The motion detection is like
That's like a
Basic theme
Video doorbell if you're using it for security that is that is
It's important
So those are thoughts here
I'd like business models need to adjust
People need to understand if they're selling
Service
Probably should communicate better with customers when
Blade
And should we think about prorating the cost of devices based on their functionality or should
What do you expect
And you know that is true
But
I think if you
We're never going to get anywhere as an industry if everyone just shrugs
DES office early adopters
China products
Feel like really doctor Prada
Okay
News for us is
Racker
How to get to news one you want to talk about tracker
Yeah real quick real quick so I bought V trackers a few weeks ago maybe two months ago love them just found out yet
Yesterday
The tracker and Elsa's family
Sharon
People who
I want to know about trackers
These little Bluetooth things that you attach two items keys for Depo wallets
You can track them you can make them beep and someone sits at way to help you find lost things
If you don't want to lose
Tracker already had
Crowdsource
I'll call it GPS or tracking up devices so that way you could
Have the tire tracker audience
Help you find a lost item
Data tracker installed on it
Now that included family sharing so that way you can create a little private group of families friends neighbors roommate Etc
And we're together to find a lost item
If you have it tracker attached to it so
I can like that
Yeah that's
Very nice cuz
We had we had stuck a tracker on the dog for a little bit
And nobody else can find the dog Striker it doesn't really help get you much so this way
You can have
Ditto Olive
The Austin area looking for you
Yes
All right and then
This is more industrial news but it's worth it she is having there
Conference this week GE announced
Predict
Kit
So predicts is there iot
The cloud where you get developers can sign up for
Their own predicts accounts in track
Whatever industrial internet stuff at build
Applications InTouch for it
What day is now done is created a prediction
Kit
That's a hardware and software bundle
Connect
Manufacturing
So
You can use these kids
They're configured with the Raspberry Pi and Intel Edison and
GE sold hardened
Platform health field agent
And you can use this to like basically attach this to some device that you want to measure
And it will send that data so we see these things with
You know IBM has deals with
Barry silicon providers
Thai
Dev kits basically to their Cloud so it's just one less thing that you have to do in braids it a little closer
Two kind of web familiar developers to work with like
Harper data
If that makes sense
And yeah that's
That's it but it's it's worth knowing because
Biology is produced platform is probably the top
1 in the space
And
This was kind of a hole for the
All right
Guys you've been patiently waiting
Are you ready
But after that
Are you ready for Charlie Kindel Whois
Is the head of Amazon's Echo
And
We are talking about
Answering questions about the Echo and we're also he also gave us
A lovely tip at the end for how to play music and multicast it over
Diego Sol
Stay tuned for all of that hey everyone it's Stacy breaking into the iot podcast
Cast to tell you about an event in Seattle that is really going to be awesome
Are you interested in how iot Tech will change the way we discover Shop store and cook our food
Then you won't want to miss the smart Kitchen Summit an event that explores the
The technology and design convergence that's changing how we
Eat Buy store in interact with our
The smart Kitchen Summit is brought to you by my friend Michael Wolff of the smart home show
Am I just created a discount especially for listeners of r-pod
Just go to smart Kitchen Summit. Com
And use the code iot podcast
That's all one word
To get 10% off 2
I'm going to be there and you should be there too
So join me October 5th
In Seattle
And maybe we can eat at 3D printed Pizza together
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is super exciting it's Charlie Kindle
Director of Alexa Smart Home
Hey
Charlie
Hi Stacy
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
I'm really glad to be here I mentioned earlier when we were talking that I've listened to a couple of your podcast another really podcast listener and I really enjoyed
Learned I learned a bunch of space for a long time
It's fun to see
Other still tons to learn
Everybody we warned you it's getting in the show but
Please if you haven't muted your Echo
So it's not listening
Uso now
Because
Holy cow
We're going to say the name Alexa
A lot
All right
First off I have to start with the question
Everyone's going to ask
Pretty sure you're not going to answer it
But
How many
Echoes have been
We hear between 3 and 4 million
A lot
So we can make
Got it
Okay Siri is kind of a difficult
Keep in the market
Hungry I think it's a good problem to have I mean we we feel super blast it or in the situation
It may be that I'm a smart home nerd in
II III
Decemberists
Was it 2015 or 2014
Time flies
Yeah that was November 2014
So when I
Received it
I had all my colleagues were telling me
Stacy why don't you to spend $100
It seems kind of silly I like
No no there's all the smart home stuff
And that was actually
I'm curious
Is that the killer use case for a lot of people or
It is
You know it is I mean the product gets used across a lot of dimensions
Sendai
Are we have tons of Reese's Run music and
Free teen and
All the other two buildings
But when we first launched
The sperm capabilities
Summer year ago now
We were
We are really delighted with how
Cuz there's a single love it and it was
It was interesting cuz he had been working on smart home for a long time my career is but kind of got it revolved around it
Going way back
And
Pill
You know this vision of wanting to turn evil
People to interact in their homes in the natural way with all these devices and all the cool things you can do
And we discovered with voice
Alexa is that the really simple scenarios that are I use the term directed device control where you
You have a device in mind and you say
Sitting on my couch in the living room reading
And the sun goes down it gets a little dark
I'd like to have some light on
I could get up and walk across the room flips light switch
I'm going to get my smartphone out
Start with a rapid is I used to control my smart home you first find it after unlocking my phone
Navigate into that particular light
You press the button in light comes on or I can say
Alexa turn on the reading light
And
You don't get down. Sing it all the scenarios
We envisioned around smart home going back to 1974 when X10 was invented
That's a really simple scenario
It's like the most basic
And it turns out he's also the most
And customers just
Are demanding more and more and more
And so it was worth all that you know when we were
The first one more like yeah we're onto something here
My understanding is that was
The smart home control is actually a relatively late
The product
Well endowed achievement play after it launched after Alexa has been in beta for a while it was
Marches for April last year
When we when we first enable
Nicole lights
So Alexis always improving you know we we launched new capabilities every week across-the-board we have
Since the beginning or continuing to double down on that aspect of it
So it's kind of hard to say that was a really nice developer or not
This is a device that is totally like
You could pry it from
My cold dead
I can't imagine my house
Stop it now
What speakers
I will say that
I have a hard time now
Navigating some of the things I can do with
That's just simply a limitation of understanding the right commands to say
Bruce Lee understanding the right commands to say so if I'm trying to do a conversion I feel like I have to remember special syntax if I'm trying to
Syntax
What voice does well and what
Doesn't it do
Well it is always getting better and that's the beauty of beauty machine learning and in these deep learning techniques that we
That we really rallied around and done a bunch of invention on
And
Football today there's
There's no complicated things that she doesn't get right
And it does get right
It's just it's just a matter of time really in in the morgue
It's a shame more people use it the better it gets
There are some parts that are awkward to use a term called multi-turn
Whereyoueat talk to Lex and she talks back to ask you a clarifying question or whatever
And all the time those are those aren't really human like
And it's our goal to continue to invest in
Making it even more more natural
You guys had a remote shipping with the original beta
And then it kind of dropped off the product and now it's a separate
Was that
The result of anything you saw in
I'm kind of debating users like I didn't use my remote very much at all until I
Remembered I could bring it upstairs and then basically have two echos
Optional thing for customers and
We just as much cost as possible
Let's talk about the smart home API
Because right now you directly into a couple products
Like lights thermostat
They just they just work I don't have to have a skill for it it's just there
What is your vision for kind of expanding the smart home API
Program
Yeah it starts with imagining all of the types of devices that customers going to have in the physical world around
That they want to use an intelligent
Voice agent to interact with
And
Wait look out in the future of the things I've done in the past
And anything you can imagine we want to enable in a
Safeway
Very deep integration around and it really ends up being about The Primitives of those devices and so if you look at the lighting API
Smart Hub supports today at that lowest level
It really boils down to
On off brightness
The thermostat API it's really about temperature
And you leave a brightness and temperature there there a gradient right
And so as we build out the API we have to think about those with the
Primitives are
And then with the business logic
I'm required within the API test
Port mapping
And did the goal is to go after all the device types are out there and as we do that we develop more more
Primitives
They're useful for other types of devices
Example of customers today
Use the fact that
You can turn
Lights on and off
With a non-directive
And that same thing applies to anything that can be turned on and off
So in my house
A little embarrassed to say this but I have about 200 devices
It Alexa
Uncontrollable bile
The majority of the Ozarks
Majority those are lighting loads I have a house that has a
A Lutron lighting system in it and I built a custom skill adapter for that
That allows me to interact with this some kind of Legacy 2001
Generation Lutron lights lighting system
Something like a hundred and twenty of those loads are
Are lighting loads
The other ones are things like my television to my fireplace so I can say Alexa turn on the kitchen TV
And I can say
Alexa turn on the living room fireplace
Turn off living room
And so that's going back to town original question which is even how we View
A supporting multiple device types of her time is pretty much anything out there in the way we do that is by
By focusing on that have a deep vertical scenario like lighting or thermostat
Imma get that right and he's got the right Primitives and then enable is permitted to be used
For other devices well
Affordable Smart Home
You had people wanted to do things like door locks
Send
You guys now have a skill for the August door lock
But that is not yet
Smart Home
Verbally being able to control the security of someone's home
I think that what we want to do is enable customers have a control and do the scenarios they want to enable and we have to be
Someone
Patient and cautious about that
The August door lock
Skill for Alexa
Is really cool
It enables you to to know the stadium of whether or not doors locked or not so you can ask Alexa
Alexa ask August if the door is locked
And it's not locking
Aldo support unlock
And as we talked to all the locks Riders out there their they're also very reticent
Send text to support unlocked at all
I'm even within the mobile app for the reason cuz you really don't want people to be able to
Unlock your door
Without really having great
About that
And so it's our business we build this out to invest heavily in the
In the scenario is it and make sure that that those things are
A safe and secure for customers
Okay so like voice biometrics
There's all sorts of
Types of authentication mechanisms and so forth that were investing in overtime
So what are the things that people
Email me a lot about they ask
Should I buy the echo Dot
Because
It feels like
It's been out for a while
Amazon could release a new version of this
Dispersions powerful enough and all the improvements
Turn the clouds but
What would you tell those
People are like
I don't think they should be I think the devices that that we built today are
Super high-quality
They've been engineered
With long life cycle in mind and most of the intelligence of Alexa and most of the power is actually in the clouds
Device has very little and then I was a very intentional design
To make sure that
Customers investment in the hardware would last over a long. Of time and the product and always get get better
Coyote and not really sure what I have T names for what are the things that I do like about some of the definitions is
The idea that it
Music devices you buy
Are always getting better and they're not
I want it done type of thing
What is Amazon's Vision around
I still like smart home was a killer app for it
Now that you guys now that I can
Buy things on Prime
Super easily without having ordered it be
Before
It feels like shopping could be
Really interesting
It doesn't feel I guess to me it doesn't feel as exciting is
The smart home stuff but
Be curious like
Where you guys been
Tell Jeff Bezos said it multiple times
Reviews
The vision is near crate what
Reviews on Star Trek
Star Trek computer but for the home
The course of human history
Tens of thousands of years ago when
Human communication started
Eunos predominately
Voice
Sound
It seems he's all sorts of other cues that use the sense of sight
Caring
And smell to communicate
But speech and sound is
Is Central to human communication
And
Up until recently
Computers
Interactive computers
I think our vision is a voice has become the technology on voice invention that we've done around far field
Voice recognition speech recognition we do in the cloud always getting smarter
We're at the point where
You actually can interact
Computers using natural voice and it's
Shockingly good
Changes the Paradigm in so we think we're at a point where this
It's kind of similar step-function to
You know what you saw when we moved from character base
Basin racks on computers to GUI
Back in the 80s
And now we're at the end of Tipping Point
Natural user experiences centered around voice
It doesn't mean that
Voices the only way
Certainly just as humans
Like I said earlier use all sorts of
Other
Census
Inarticulate
Vocal cords is afford to communicate
Computer as well as well
And we've sent the vision of Alexa is
Tune able
Shuman Center Act
With their environment in the most natural way
What can't voice
We talked about
Unlocking your doors today
But I don't want to
Epicurious
What those scenarios are that you guys are like you know what that's just not good
I think we're going to we're going to let customers dictate that for the most part
Ice the same as
If you and I were in a room together
There's times when
Saucony appropriate for me to speak out loud
I'm going to kick you under the table
Or I'mma send you a message in the same room because it wouldn't be appropriate cuz we're in a library
So I think that there's
There's also social norms and environmental issues that will dictate that
Dim the day it's going to be up to customers
When they want to do it in the inside corner of adjectives
To build a system in anyway such as flexible enough
So that all those modes of communication interaction can be used
I actually talked to accompany the other day who is Brie whose customers were bringing the echo.
To business meeting
To answer questions about sales forecast
And I really thought this was interesting when you started talking about
Cultural norms
I tried it
Picture like the echo with an actual seat at the table
This could really create new cultural.
Set up curious if you guys are seeing those develop maybe you and your license
At such an extensive collection or maybe at Amazon
You probably see it in your own household I certainly see it in mine with
The social environment you have people over the house and they discover that there's nothing in the room that can talk to
And suddenly becomes the center of the party
Unless that's another example of that
But also I'm one of those
Your crazy smile is easiest
She mostly is but but she for a long time is called our house this
Oh my God would love her
And it's and it's really because
First of Technology tradition has been fairly fragile
Particular when it's homegrown
But really I didn't give her a lot of value for the things she wanted to do
She didn't understand the value of
The automatic routines and
And the fact you could double tap on this button and it would do something different in Boca scene
These things just didn't Delight her cuz
There's two kinds of products in the world is products are vitamins and its products are painkillers
And ideally you want to be building something that's a pain killer because
Yeah they're going to beat all demands for that
Because I have to push vitamins on
People really frankly the lot of this connected Home Smart home automation stuff for the last
Two or three decades
Has been
In that mode
But we found his voice and in my house it's
Absolutely the case
Juvenile
Interacts with the house using voice all the time
Never she recommends it to other people had a friend come out to me the other day I'm talking about his wife and he likes
Oh my gosh she's encouraging me to buy smart blinds
Give me a high five
Oh so this way you guys could be a gateway drug
The Nerds are that were Amazon
To the Smart Home
What we should do something about music
I had multiple conversations with people who have high-end
You know a whole home audio
Systems with
And then I'll just use the
Echoes giving up on the
The Puritan high-fidelity
The audio file
Respective
So because the convenience of interacting with voice to select the music you want to play
Is so much better
And I would also say this touches on something
The beauty is important which is
Right now
Smart home controls
Play through
Your
Which I have a 9 year old daughter
Set so she loves the echo because
It basically gives our access to a lot of the things in
In the home
So I look at this and I think
This is one of the first high-quality thing
Devices to
Work in a shared environment
I don't know if you guys really thought about that but
It feels like something else
And we use the term communal internally that resume product is a combination of a very personal
Experience with also something that works very well in those shared communal environment since and it said that the power in the magic
Far-field voice technology
Let's quickly go into the future skills before I get you for your favorite
Amazon Echo
Track Santa
You guys are making
Huge strides there so many skills now not even a guess how many there are at the time
I'm sure it's like baby off
But there's over 1500
Used to be a mess to find them you guys are now at allowing people enable it by voice which thank you
But how do you say skills playing in two kind of Amazon's
World is just like a new app store like people like to think of it
This is one of things where I think we're at day one we're just
Scratching the surface of what's possible
We are very explicitly enabling Alexa to be something that
That isn't entire ecosystem that all companies where the hardware company software company service companies
Can
Participate in
And get whatever value it is that they want on a vehicle
Their customers
And
Are the 1500 or so the skills that are currently enabled that includes the smart home skills
Or just us to the sampling it was possible
The
App stores in the world
She go back to 2007 when the iPhone first came out
And enabled the App Store 2008
The period after that was a
Yeah I just a fascinating gross. For the industry
And we kind of feel like there's an opportunity to
To drive that kind of value
For customers and flexibility and benefits by enabling
Anyone
Take advantage of this
Voice experience
How long until I
Do a custom name
For my echo
It was a custom wake word
Accustomed
Yeah you know we support Alexa Echo and Amazon today and we got lots of lots of
SUNY able
A Mother's Day out of his specific ones they want and indefinitely customers ask about having
It's a very very hard problem requires a lot of invention each time you do if you have to get it right you have to
You have to make sure you don't
Have what we call too many false
Except
Which is when the system
Here's something else I hear something and thinks it's the Wake words you can't have false rejects which is where
You say the Wake word in the system doesn't hear at end
So we're continuing avastin that we've we've been going to talk for shipt it was just Amazon
Amazon Alexa and we added a collator
And something there always work
Okay
Now for everybody's favorite part
Tell us
Your favorite
Tips tricks
Skills
Nutella
What do you like to do with your neck
Or what would you tell other people
I've done is using Echo dot which has I'm audio out so you can connect to other speaker systems
I have several Echo dots around my house
Connected to my my multi-zone audio system in my house and so
I can say I can stand in the kitchen which is next to the dining room and I can say
Alexa turn on the
Living room speaker
And out of the dining room speakers I was there her say okay
And then I can say Alexa play
Dark Side of the Moon on Spotify
And
All that music will fill
Both dining room and living room
And it's really easy to set this up if you have a whole home audio
Just like this you can either use the analog audio out to that
Or you can use a Bluetooth audio receiver
I actually do that in my master bedroom and this morning I love Flash
Yeah I guess in the morning and I'm in the bathroom when I say
Alexa what's up
And she starts playing my flash briefing with tries customized for me
Play the new sources I care the most about
And that comes out of the speakers in the ceiling
Stop my master bedroom because when we built the house way back when
And the way that I wire that up is not a little Bluetooth audio receiver
Connected to the power amplifier for that in the Echo dot connect to that Bluetooth audio receiver
That's kind of a fun thing you can do
Obviously I use the smart home stuff a lot
For me it's just so nice to be
Going to bed and be able to say Alexa turn off
Kitchen TV
That's a really really mundane things
But it's to me and my family
Unbelievably delightful
It is fantastic
As I
Turn off the fish tank light
I got a WeMo plugged in there so I'm just like
Turn off fish tank
Fist bump right
I actually still do
Privacy
Just me all right with Charlie thank you so much for coming on the show this week
Can't wait to see what you guys delivered in
Alright thank you for taking the time
I enjoyed it alright everybody you can turn your microphones back on
Are Amazon echos and thank you so much for listening this week we hope to hear you again next week
And if you get bored and need more of an iot newsfix please sign up for my Weekly Newsletter
Stacy knows things at www.dot Stacey on iot. Com