Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast which this week will be held on a construction site
I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And the construction site is mine
So just
You're not under attack
I thought maybe you were at the Target near the Metreon and they're expanding the IRT store
Or maybe it's Apple getting ready to build their own smart home next door
That's not happening y'all that was not an official sanction a rumor
Okay so
Got you all excited
But there are really cool things happen
Socially start with
Google onhub router reviews or should we start with
New thermostat
Take your pic
What's up with Nest cuz you got the information I don't really know what's going on with Nest other than I saw hints of an FCC
Filing that
Eluded
To a new Nest Thermostat
Is that the real deal
New 3rd generation
Thermostat
Is a Slimmer profile
And a 40% larger high-resolution screen
It's party
And now my nose looks bulky and ugly
Dang it
I will not
I'm sorry
I don't know if they can hear me
If it can
I'm going to be prepared for
I don't know either too warm or too cold sleeping tonight
This is what happens when you have to
Can the smart things in your house
So it's got new features
Including
They are calling this one
Farsight it automatically displays the
Target temperature
And the time when it senses movement in the room
And I'm not sure
What that means exactly
Oh I can tell you okay you tell me
I don't have this but I can tell you that my Nest has nearsighted meaning
You have to be back within two to three feet of it
Ford
The screen to actually open up and display show you the temp in Saint sauveur
So far sight sounds to me like
You can like you know being further away from it and the
The screen will actually light up
This explains also for people who heard
Probably a couple weeks or maybe a month ago
The Apple Store was
Seen getting rid of its nest thermostats and everyone's like
Spirits
Google owns Nest Apple Altamonte
Yes
With apple putting out yunnan pushing homekit what is this mean
But really what it meant was that they were clearing inventory the old inventory so
When the new Nest came out you could buy
Fresh new Destiny you wouldn't buy one
Today
Right before they
So this is actually available
Now for 249 the same price as the original nest
Yes
As of the time this podcast will Air
This is available now
It'll be available at amazon.com and it will come soon to Best Buy retail store
Google stores
And Lowe's the Home Depot
Target Verizon Wireless and the retail price is 249
Aren't you tell him
Thank you don't want this better display you can save yourself fifty bucks because they're going to
Discount for 2nd generation Nest
That's like retailers for 199a suggested retail price money to find a cheaper
So there you have it
Yeah so that's that's the new Nest news very exciting for everyone who
Lexi's nest
Anything else we should know
I do people care about how many pixels per inch are on their nest
But now they don't
That's why I know the new one has 229
Pixels per inch
Is
I wouldn't call it
Comprable to the retina displays and such on iPhones and similar devices but it's pretty darn good
More than the second
Generation X
If you go
Again to me I'm like am I watching
YouTube I mean
No no no I don't think and I would not recommend
That most people who currently have a nest
Upgrade to the new one I don't see the point
I don't either unless you're like
Your thermostat has something you're continually running into and the fact
But this is slimmer
Be compelling but
I Don't Think It's $249
If you're really running into your nest
Currently a lot in your house
I would just save your money and buy their house because
I can see by some glasses or stop drinking quite so much during the day
Your kind
So that's the new nest
Exciting
And
That's yes
Was it last week that we talked about the onhub router from Google it was tired last night
Oh see this
This maybe be drinking
Can too much during the day cuz I don't even remember
Because I am so excited
And this router
Is Google's router and it has weed inside
Which is Google's kind of protocol for The Internet of Things
It also has
Red
It supports thread we should say which is
Wireless radio
Nest Samsung and several other semiconductor
Companies are pushing
As an alternative mesh Network
Zippy
Z-Wave
So what we have here are
The reviews are out
And actually today today is the day guys
I feel like a dr. Seuss book today's
The day you're on your way go to the store
And by 1 today
You can actually buy Google onhub router
Yes
Today
At many locations including the Google Store Walmart
And
Amazon I believe
199 and I was interested in buying one
Because I do have while I do have an 8:00 or 2:11.
11 AC router that I bought
Timbuktu years ago
AC
66 you and I know they've upgraded at once already to the 68 you
It's been great for me except the routers in one corner of the house on the second floor and in the opposite corner on the first floor I've got a
4K TV
Sketchy with signal
So I thought about it
And then I read the reviews
And I'm not thinking about it anymore
Because
I would say they're generally
In agreement that it's not that spec
Angular the only one I read that was
It was with the verge
It works really well in his house he
Router issues in his house
That's great I'm happy for Dad
But
Ron Amato guitarist
But if you're interested in the actual graphs and charts of actual test of this router versus many others that are out there
At similar price points are even less
You can see by the throughput and signal strength this is not up to
So that the big thing here is yes it makes it easy to
Set up because it comes with that
Software the on software
What
ARS Technica is testing worries ma'am and it just doesn't seem like it's going to solve any of my
Current problem
Then there's the other thing you've using the back of this thing right
I have
I will get there
They are lovely pictures however
The picture show that there is a definite
Black ports
Is there is one USB port that is basically useless right now if you can't connect to
Hard drive to router near the storage
There is
S1 internet port
On the back of it
And that's
And then while I appreciate that this looks nice and you could put this anywhere in your house and they want you to I want you to put in the middle of your house
Most people don't have their
ISP
Hardware
Wiring coming through the middle of their house
So you're still got to stick this somewhere in a corner of your house probably for most people
What else is on the back of that thing I'm looking for my pictures now
There is there's one additional
Port one Additionally the airport
So that brings it to okay Stacy you got X number of hugs here that all to connect to your router.
Or you have to buy it
Start Me Up
Switch right
And I actually so i a
We already have a switch plugged into my router Plus
Four ports
Send my router
And they're actually already taken up and I have
Switch
With
For additional ports
And those are
So you're an edge case I'm
Not quite that edge but I manage case as well
Your you're done
You have nothing
No help for you
You have to do the whole switching thing in that takes away from the
Simplicity
It's clear that Google has
High aspirations for this because this has a
Say relatively high-end smartphone processor inside from Qualcomm
It's got
A gig of RAM it's got 4 gigs of storage and I guarantee that is not all four
You know that the song
They're going to do something more with
Best we know that
But you can't do anymore with it just yet and what I want to do with it I really can't
Here's what
I didn't see a lot of
What's up
I didn't see great things on the software side of
Sinner reviews
A lot of things I don't like this was kind of a missing issue
Did you end I only saw so I
I read the verge's review I didn't spend a lot of time with ours
Ours is
Sweetie
Did you see that any coverage of like
I did and basically they said
It seemed towards Simplicity and the non power user
So you know for us you may have to go in and change the NAT tables or
You know Pocahontas firewall and so on
I don't know how much we can do here
I'm taking less nap tables and firewalls in Moore
When I think about a router today in the home
I think about a router from list
10 years ago in
A corporate Network
So as a parent I want to be able
Not just as a parent but is like
Connect network administrator of my home even though I don't think of myself that way
I want to be able to come
Control access to
Add devices
I want a software interface that lets me turn off my daughter's Kindle or computer at 8 at night
Yeah and as I look through the many many screenshots I know ours has a bunch I know
Some others do as well
I don't see any weight
You can prioritize Wifi traffic to a particular device
And it does capture the device names and the uploads and downloads
Of data over the past
7 days 30 days whatever so you can see
Historical usage
Do I see any
I don't see any
Setting such as that
There's just DNS and wins settings there's
Cloud services and usage stats
What's a good I mean
Oh yeah
I think that's really
Important to have that kind of clearly defined
Ability to control devices and I also think
As iot becomes
The router is a great place to
Control a lot of devices
Like
Especially things like gas.
Access
That's up where we be great to be like
Hey
Sure like the five devices I want my guests
Where am I
Kids to be able to
I don't actually want my
Especially as my daughter gets older
Maybe I don't want her to be able to
Control the nest
Because you know
I know when I was a kid
You know I always wanted
Turn my air conditioning down to like 70 in the summer
And that never met her
Talk to me you know so I was just
You know Crank It Down
Going to be like
Battlerite
You know I'm going based on the reviews I don't have it a unit here right again I thought about buying it but I'm already heading towards not
Waiting to see
What they admit you know cuz I again nobody's mentioned any setting and as I look to the screenshots and it's pretty expensive
Bunch of screenshots of the software
On hard I don't see what it is that you're looking for
And I think it does need to be there
It almost seems to me like they got this thing out there
It's a lot of potential
The capabilities
No Doubt
And it looks it looks very kind of
Programmable kind of like an egg
What kind of a
We kind of way to program
So
I'm actually considering buying
Although I would say for your problems
Have you considered an access point
I actually do have two additional extenders range extender as access point in such so yes
Yeah I know I mean I'm not I'm not sucking wind in that that room is just it's not as consistent as I would like because I'm sharing this again
Pushing it
No further further access points
That is not ideal
I just want something more stable
But that's just me you also mentioned
Ziggy
You did it because this does
Work with zigbee
However
I'm looking at again Rotten Tomatoes review
Here's here's the deal
I'm going to just throw it in here so it supports
Sew thread is a wireless protocol.
It's built on
The IEEE 802.
15.
Standard
That's standard
What is the same
Radio
Precinct
So
Zigbee
As it is is that radio + software stack
And if use a different software stack
It makes it thread
So
Because
The differentiation is in the software
If you can make the
Two things work
Can run
You can
I mean but the question is
Will that eventually happen.
I'm just going to quote Ron here
Onhub 02. 15.4 support is close to zigbee
But it isn't compatible with zigbee
Zigbee devices can toss out the zucchini label get a software update and join Google team
But it doesn't seem like it will make itself compatible with them
That makes sense
Yep
Integrity software and chipsets
Backwards
Compatibility
Companies that are using those chips
Update your software
See what it comes down to me is
Again a lot of potential here I see where Google is going and I applaud them and I'd like the directions
But this gets back to way back when the vehicle came out
I didn't buy the echo in November for $99 because I looked at it like
It's got potential
Blackjack no guarantees or it's going to be able to do
You know eventually
I came around obviously in got one because of the additional features and things that work
I'm just leery of
What I'm getting for dinner dollars right now would I have to wait for and what may never come
I am with you on this
I am actually
So this is in my device I don't know about
I know I had it
I have it on my wishlist
And I'm I'm thinking about it and I
There's also a Kate Spade handbags
And it's basically the handbag
Well
You're like I really don't know what to say there I'm not sure where to go after that what I'm going to do is
I'm actually going to go to the Google store right now
And I'm going to see if there is
A 30-day return policy
Because that's the only way I would consider doing this
What's currently out of stock so it really doesn't matter
If it does have a 30 day return policy I will consider buying one and taking the chance for now
I'll look at you
Take one for the team
If you go to Amazon right now
It's not available right now so it's only
It's $400
No it's not cuz I'm not paying that
I may have a really good return policy too but I would not
Buy a 3rd party through Amazon
I'll wait and see when it comes available and maybe I'll get it
How can eliminate my access points
And still have fantastic coverage
Then it's an upgrade
But that's a lot to pay for that upgrade
With more potential
You know
It's true in
It's designer
Living room
Speaker
Is there a microphone out there's no microphone I've already looked at Maaco here's their answer to the echo
There's no microphone
Kadai enabling
Smartphone app that you talk to your phone and then
Maybe but
3 watt speaker Echo 15 watt speaker
Will in the here's here's the deal I've been waiting for this
And I don't know if it's actually
Make it in time or what there's a there's other wi-fi system
That I've been waiting for
It's called the Eero
Ber
And that's not going to come out
December 1st 2015 butt
Amazing
From a router stand for
For the internet
Thanks
It's a pretty sweet handbag
199 for the individual
The back has the same two
To Port problem
You can buy a three pack that has these access points
What are designed to solve what your problem is
Gotcha
So
Decisions decisions
I know I'm really excited though that Wi-Fi is actually finally becoming like the thing it should be which is
A recognition that it's super important
We still in
What is dead zones that we're trying to solve
Too much time talking about Wi-Fi
What is so important
Let's go into this new sensor thing because I am super
Interested
I don't know if you
Is this the sensors that make that according Cordon ApplianceSmart
From LG
Good lunch
Like I said
Lunch to Spanish
Smart brilliant
I'm so these are LG's new smart
Fix'd sensor
This is ifacs
Just this week and next will probably be talking about last stuff that I have Hader
Everything about today are at the LG sensor
Quickly and then
SmartThings coming on later
In the show
So this is the sensor it's a circular sensor you can stick it
On things in
It sent you a notification to your smartphone
Twining
So
I'm trying to see what's
Pretty sure this has all join
You don't want that kind of cool so that kind of opens it up a little bit
Supposed to like some of these older DIY
Tech savvy.
I'm hoping that when they officially debut this
Words free that would be better
No I hope that
Very quickly there's an if this then that channel
Alex gets to support this somehow
Maybe I mean with all joined what would be really cool is
This actually so
LG TVs already
Support
And I know not everybody has an LG
Letv but
Certain
Android phones can support
So
If you start looking at things like that
Maybe even cooler
Instead of having an assistant that channel for like my mom
Nativist better I agree
This suddenly just gives you a notification on your TV hey your washer
Stop
Oh crap I was just in the best part of the show
That's exactly what they're going after here
For people who
You don't know what these could be used for him and you can put it on the fridge and they say yeah
Send notification when a food item is about to expire or how many times the doors open
It's just about capturing data from these appliances which is interesting
I like it
Homeowners to use their smartphones to set the cooking mode temperature and cooking time for a given dish
I don't know how it actually implements that
I'm assuming that's on an LG oven
That's my suspicion because they even care
Sorry if I ever
Now they also have a smart air conditioner as well
Okay
Plastic lettuce.
Proprietary
Yeah soup
Not a retrofit
Bossa Nova
Okay
So
There we go
I was excited
Sorry to burst your bubble
My bubble can't stay Bruce for Long Beach
Also this week
Starting
Today
Hey you guys
If you go to smartthings.com
Order
And receive
The Next Generation huh
For $99 you can get the
42409 you can get a
A package of
Hub Essentials
Hub Essentials that is
That's not what I meant
Looking for a house
Security Essentials
So the new Hub is out
It is not homekit certified so I was speculating did
I was wrong
Tell us later on in the show
I guess it's Alex Hawkinson
CEO of SmartThings
He will tell us that it was actually
For international distribution and
Rebuilding entire app
From scratch
Cause of delays
We asked him about that so stay tuned to understand
Why that's not
Does he also
Tell you what's difference in this house
Of course he does
The short answer is
It has a battery backup
It has its own brains
So the previous version doesn't have an arm processor
So basically when it goes offline
It can think for itself so
Your programs will still run
I can't even do that
So that that's
Crucial difference
It has Z-Wave
I believe that will support
It adds Bluetooth
Other stuff so the new service it's going to
New services including
It supports
Video cameras for the first time
The services that they built
And what else do we want to know about smart things
I don't know but for 99 bucks
Just met order one
Dude is a great hub
The wink
I have a shoe release you said to me just before the show Hugh really only does lice so that's
Not too exciting so I can take the Hue out and put the SmartThings in there
She still has to
Prudential
With all of these
So much of that router
CC
Don't just go get a switch
The reason I'm excited because SmartThings
SmartThings is not supported on the Amazon Echo
Yes and you know what I have
No shield for SmartThings which means you can make
To work with your smart thing
If you're so inclined
Interesting
Which
You know if you're a DIY kind of person which some people on the show are
Not just on the show
You can actually make some crazy stuff this is not something that I do necessarily but
You Kevin
So maybe maybe I could
Ask my echo if the stock market arctis a how's the stock market doing and through the smart things are dino
We could light up green yellow or red depending on if the market Valpo down or unchanged
Sea or lake
Your house could go into like lockdown
You could prepare the apocalypse right there I am so prepared for the zombie apocalypse is not even
Funny
Just ask the people at Costco how much water we have bought in the last year
Water in canned goods
Can't wait
Bring it on zombies
So you know most people use it to make like homemade garage door openers that
Thanks but you know
You do what you want
I like to make little pretty lights blink
So there is
There's what you
I can do that with that
And
Yeah I think
Alright well let's hear more from from Alex cuz you got all the details
Stay tuned for that
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast and today
We have on our show Alex Hawkinson who is the CEO of smart things
Hey Alex
Hey Stacy
So good to have you here so
Last week actually Kevin and I talked about the integration of
SmartThings with Amazon Echo and
This week we talked about the new SmartThings that is coming out
Actually
Now for people who will buy it online and then in October for people who want to buy it on retail stores show
Retail store shelves
It's probably a graceful way to say that so
Congratulations
Yeah thanks it's been a
A big year
A lot of heads down work and getting ready for this so we're really excited to have the next
Next version to product in the platform out the door
See I was going to say it's been a long time coming
You can tell I'd I'm not trained by anyone to say things politely
People avoid me at parties
You guys actually have been
Pretty heads down pretty quiet
Actually like the last year so
I've been working on the new platform
We were expecting it back in May so
What happened what have you guys been doing and then
I'm going to say what took you so long
Oh you know just getting everything ready for the global scale now
Since we merged with Samsung a year ago you know the opportunity to scale up all the way
Around the world this is in front of us now and
Realized
You know announce the new Hobbit CS
But then we looked across the
The platform and realized you wanted to do much more and bring it all together
So not just the new hot but new
Devices
I totally new person at the Avenue video platform
And then of course please
Distribution channels for the make it accessible to people in the US send
And now beginning in
In the UK and send them to you as well
So you're right that is that is a lot going on
And since we actually
This last week we talked about you guys being
The granddaddy of smart
DIY smart home moving
Surreal to me because it still feels like it's gone so quickly you don't have to
Wake up everyday and realize that again remind myself it was just three years ago
You know that our our Kickstarter campaign is actually went live on August
XXII
And
33 years ago that were in the middle of the kickstarter campaign and not notice or knowing if we're going to tip
Yeah and so on and it
That's really been a whirlwind
Since then.
Of course now
Tucson news very quickly and
3 years is a is a lifetime
You know we didn't know about a lot of things
Things that happened in Market
At that time
Let's jump in our time machine and go back a little bit because
I think it's worth kind of exploring
What has changed and how your philosophies
Changed because
The I actually recently picked up my SmartThings
Hub an app
After kind of a bit of a Hiatus with
The whole Amazon thing and I was like
Oh man you know
I've long bulbs SmartThings because of your open philosophy
And that has been my favorite and I recommend it to anybody who has
A lot of technical expertise in a lot of patients
Because
To me it's kind of like the Android of the smart
The sense that
My God it will work with anything
But you kind of have to be willing to work with it a little
It's not exactly
Intuitive
I'm sorry I
I'm so sorry
But it does require you to like really be like I know what I want to do
Erica Robertson dead.
It's been a big fight at point of the new launch but yeah you know
If you want to talk about this
History
I think the vision for the company's been consistent throughout and putting with this new launch you know we always
Yeah I had to sweat in my family house in the mountains and it was shocked back in
Zack and 2000
11 when I didn't realize that it was happening
How can be how can the world
Connected in a way that other things are
Jesse our smartphones and the initial Vision was going to try to make this easy enough for
Everyday People to get access to you but really realize also that the Innovation was
Income from
A worldwide movement of developers and device makers send to all sorts of other things in
It isn't open plateau
Farm so easy and open of all has been at the heart
Of SmartThings
And your your top use cases are security energy-saving inconvenience
And then
What you would call sign in
Entertainment
I think during sex
Monitoring
Dirty I don't
Like to just focus on security cuz it really is just out of answering the Clash
Is everything okay
In my home at this moment send that's a universal need and it's by far the
The top starting point then after that it
We said comfort and savings so kind of making it
Simple to be comfortable while saving money and the thermostat selenium
Example. There's lots of others by using energy rides and then
Bizaardvark episode of convenience and entertainment trying together its fans things that
May or may not save you money but people love them for lots of different reasons I connected lighting and then things that entertain you or make your stay
Please come to life
Like
Can I get audio then send more so those are the big three I wanted to kind of get to this idea because
A lot of other companies have had to do this in the space which is building a developer community
And then wrangling it
In front of everyone
I'm in front of your users in front of the press in front of
Everyone in
I actually think you guys have done it really well you've been very graceful as a comfy
Company doing this
And I would love to get
Sense of how you guys have done this
Speakwrite
I'm most of it is where were
Straddling
Set of two competing things seen as being easy and being open
You can be a toll against each other in some way
To be easier it's right something to close things down and try to make it narrower and narrower
But you know it's really this
Unconscious
Amaze to buy
The developer community in what they're doing
With the platform and all the things we didn't think of that are really meaningful in Prosecco
You know in everyday life
Frontier that easy nothing vision
Has always been at the heart of the company but it's
It's always it's fundamentally they pull in each Direction because developers want to do new stuff so that's not necessarily
The mainstream
I need queso
Enterprise at the heart of it I guess it
It took a while as you saw in the first-person the product and then we went through some decorations and now getting to this full revamp of the u.s.
Blacks but it hardens probably are
Are certification
Program
And
All the processes we built around that so developers start to get a sandbox
I can do whatever they want
But it's not exposed to all the other consumers in the ecosystem
And then we've created this
This really rebuff process where is smelt
Just want to share
With the can
Consumers and publish their Innovations for the devices are apps are now apps can have a ufi user experience inside of
May nap if you will
They have to go to the certification program
Not now includes
Security privacy checks
Enough putting it into the taxonomy
Consumers can understand where it goes and how it extends their lives
I think we're still in the early stages but thanks for the company
If we can't make the two sides the
Ecosystem easy and open both work then
You know I'll feel like we failed the position of the company
We're dead set on making it happen I'm sure but this next iteration
You'll get a lot more feedback
Is this looks like
This actually looks like
The version of the product that's probably going to hopefully push it into the mainstream
This user experience kind of concept in how your
Cuz this also
Touches on how you guys are introducing services
So there's kind of a lot to unpack here
Care of it
A new service
That you guys are launching as part of your security and monitoring
One of your security and monitor
Offering
So why don't you describe that for us and then we'll talk about like
How developers can
Sure
So
That there's a lot to unpack I mean in a nutshell what we're launching is we called smart home monitor and there's
I literally new kicks that goes on the retail shelves called the
Home monitoring kit that lets you
Answer that
Problem is everything
Okay at home
And it is made to be incredibly simple it's got its
User
Grant's inside of our app
It's very centered on
I'm answering that question
With that comes a premium service that's totally optional
Which is
Adding Bisquick video
Recording for connected video cameras and we did that in a very I think Innovative way
Consumer cell
It's unlimited clip
Recording where if they have connect
The cameras when an event
Checkers near house like the door opens in their way
It can take a snapshot of
That that's been
Acute up on our hub
And
See see what happened before and after the events and do that for any number of connected cameras
Tendency that way to be clear
People to get this they actually have
To buy the new hub
For $99
And then
You also have to buy the
But the additional new sensors
Which would be that whole kit for 249
You have to have the new hub.
That's true because we
We don't let the data from these
These cameras leave your house unless you physically requested or there's an incident they're not all the streaming
Because we found a lot of people.
Didn't want that
A model so it needs a new hub
But anybody that buys that and then I ended up working
A camera that works with it initially it's a lineup of Samsung
Cameras and D-Link cameras and then I will be over others but it's part of a broader Ark
We found that the Developers
You want to not just
Still device Integrations to make new devices work or a new what we've called smart apps
Historically which is for the behind-the-scenes
Rules or recipes or
Whatever your analogy is that run behind the scenes in SmartThings sensor to make
Yeah but they lights come on in response to the other things like that but now
We found this big desire to make life better for consumers by adding the services and
We created a mechanism
Using our own developer tools
We built this smart home monitor
Lippitt Hall uri inside of our app and now developers have access
It's not
As well as
And so we haven't announced them yet but we
See a proliferation starting to happen where there's this opportunity to launch Services that's all
Consumer problems and make life better
Upper people and the model will be
The developers have a chance to make money from that will take a small Revenue share that is similar to an app store
A model and you never really excited about it cuz it lets
What's a guy knows those mainstream consumers let them see a solution in place whatever that might
Be rather than it being the sort of gadgety things that run behind the scenes
So I could always set up
The smart home monitoring
But what I would pay for it
Where is the ability to store those clips for an extended amount of time from any of my cameras
Correct yes
As the solution inside of inside of smart things that you buy the smart come
The home monitoring kit
You can do it for free forever and if you have connected cameras
Streaming from them and then you get a trial of this
Premium
The clip recording
DVR service
And the ability to escalate to friends and family and so on and all that that is part of the page
It service and we don't know what the pricing is
Going to be on that
We haven't announced it but it's even my commitment as its you know part of making it easy is making it so accessible
That's going to alienate some of your partners who might also have a Services Revenue option so
I know that today
You guys don't have like a formal works with nest
For example but their nest cam
Has a Services model where
You can pay
X amount
I think it's
$10 a month for unlimited
Cloud storage
So if I look at what you might charge
And if I have a nest
Wait a second
I'll just store the interesting mon
Events for my SmartThings system
Finessed me look at you guys and be like you know what
SmartThings
Never
I hope that's not the case I mean it
Again we I think we have
The most open
That's of any platform out there so
Even our own
Services
Solutions which we're just trying to do it right by the consumer and make things easier for them but
Those are all published as exam
Samples in our developer tools they're all built with our own developer tools and
I'm sitting this test but I use for what an open model looks like but if others built a connected device with it
Sun premium service
We love to expose.
In the platform
And so without talking to nest
Yes specifically you know about their devices but
In a sum of their approach has
Then as open as we would love
To see
So how you know from my standpoint I want to give consumers maximum choice I don't think it's one size fits
And you know we'll let the marketplace in the developer because
System consumers decide for themselves
What they want
And
Let's while we're on the topic of devices
What kind of devices are going to be working with your new Hub in platform that we should be excited
At this point were
About 200
Compatible
Devices that consumers can all Discover right within our new app
And we talked back at CES
That you had mentioned that you guys were
Interested and supportive of homekit which is Apple's
Kind of standard in this space
We actually even talked about being interested in supporting thread on the new
So
Where Do We Stand assist
Is this
Sublet out
I don't believe it's hunk it certified so what happened there
You know I I love Zeppelin
Virus
Products
Apple products use a lot of them myself
Considering placing our customer base and
And I think that
It was funny after the
Integration of Samsung
The first iOS bugs that came out in
Spell community
Initially like
See I knew it you know but then we
Continue to iterate
And have a very big debt
Team around it Monster Apple Watch app
Yeah completely committed
I'm with homekit you know I think the
The disappointments so far we've been watching really carefully is been the proprietary Hardware components that you need in it
And we haven't seen the value
Yes in that ecosystem does not mature enough yet
So
It's not
The homekit chip isn't in the tub this new Hub can be expanded
Of your ports on the back so we're looking at it carefully and I'm totally open-minded about homekit in the future it's just
Still in the really early stages
So
Indeed it's not
Homekit certified the bunny hop
I yelled at this point
Standard scene I really all the scene SmartThings
Horsham clinic VA
Gnostic
Soldan's DeWitt
So
In cases like thread will say
French leaving weave
And others this Hub is LSA future ready for a lot of these things so as the red becomes means
Stream are Hub and devices
Portage
And then there's other emerging stand
That were very involved in some of the older ones like sigelei
Which is matured a lot of the last three years you know we're on the board for zigbee we're on the board for Z-Wave and we're trying to shape all these things
Directions that
Makes things easy for consumers and make it open for
Developers going to start charging you a quarter every time you say easy in open
Eugene open
That's my pocket song
You're like I'm just going to throw it out there
Demanding radio
Alright for that one
I want Lutron
And that one
Give me a test you know we see the actress
System emerging
I think the open model is
Is winning but I
You know you don't see in all cases of the other large companies
In space we don't see them all with a pure
Model that we
Be best
So we try to hammer
Sam of those those two messages every every time we sent
Especially without using the words easy and open but let's see what happens
How have you fared
Under a Samsung's ownership
Especially
You know that you you mentioned Apple obviously and people were very skeptical there like
Given their relationship
That's kind of dicey
But I think it's the
As other
Companies enter the Smart Home
You know I'm even thinking like appliances and
Televisions
Are you finding that companies
Speaker companies especially
Are a little nervous or skeptical about working with you guys
No I mean it's been
Honestly
This has been just the opposite it was what I was most paranoid
About when we decided to go forward
With the acquisition we we wanted to do it to reach Matchbox
Scale cuz we've always felt like we have this chance to
Bring our platform instead of change the world
Dubai
Bringing together consume
Sun Developers
True that
Model those two words
I talked to you earlier but
I'm in Samsung has incredible reach
Around the world
1 scale opportunities but
You know how to keep it I was worried about it staying completely pure and opa
I'm so if maintain SmartThings as a separate company you know we have our own offices we
Do things that are first principles like
We Samsung uses the same as a partner uses the same developer tools and certification price
But anyone else does on the outside so there's no
Favoritism towards their devices in our model on
Customer privacy and so on is Sanford developers this you own your own data
Answer that applies internally as well
It's actually not used in an available to anyone else so
All these policies I think of kept us open and then we seen what's great is that the ecosystems loves the scaling
Trinity so the chance to go out and serve reach more
People touch deeper into the home
Make this more inexpensive through the manufacturing scale
God and so on so I think it's been
The belief will be an execution now
That we are out in the market
Continue to demonstrate
That openness
But I think
Consumers and developers will really realize the benefits of the the scale knows we're in millions of households
Well think about the opportunity that that creates
If you're craving services on top of the platform to
Reach additional consumer
Berserker creating new device to get it rapid exposure
Guitar bass cell really excited.
No I'm not saying that he's not
But I
I'm confident that we're on the path
To be
You know even in this past year you know continue to grow really well
The company
You know it's four times the size that it was at the time of the acquisition and the developer ecosystem is really
Really accelerated end
I would mention the consumer numbers but you know the smart home is
Living right now past
The early adopters into that
Really majority so
Weihai
Good timing and we have a lot of resources to help educate people around the world about what we're doing
You're going to get me your numbers I know it
Alright well thank you so much for coming on the show this
Thank you Stacey I was enjoyed and love to talk to you and your
Evasive listeners
Yes actually
For you guys who
Maybe her not familiar Alex was actually
I think the second guest on the
The iot podcast many many years ago
Bullock back together and say back in the day
Get out at some point so I can't believe you called me the grand far off the grandfather of
The grandparent of the SMART Notebook and what what's it going to be in a few years we'll see
The great granddaddy
Good Lord
Wow
Alright we'll buy your rocker
Connected router
Thank you
Thanks for listening this week
Play podcast please
Make sure you tune in next week as we talked about
More great things happening with the Internet of Things