Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have an awesome show
Filled with
Well
The biggest eel happening was arm
Getting purchase
Is there actually a offer from SoftBank
We've got an FTC advisory for your smart home
Devices
We're going to be talking about garage door openers
Locks
Some smaller news and
WiFi and privacy just because that never gets old
In our guest is the CEO of arable which is a company that is
Taking
Data
About farming
To Dura Spanish me
You're going to like it
Culottes
I thought were to have a Pokemon go I guess not
No no that was last week
Pokemon go is over
A lot of people paranoid
They are
But I walk the dog at play
You did start playing
I did I did while the kids are playing on Mike let me go see what's what here and
Yes I installed it
I walk the dog it's the only time I fired up
Cuz I got to walk in like 5 6 times a day there's a park across the street
We take half mile to mile walks and
I caught Pokemon while he does his business
Rate
That's probably a good time to end
Agency
For reality
Cuz I don't like the actual reality of that time
Yatagan Valley
Alright so
What start off with
Arm
Because that's probably
Barney anything exciting happening
Couple days the biggest news we're going to see this week
I se biggest
Ship deals
Maybe
Comment
Trivago
In terms of dollars
Okay
I was looking at was even looking at it from a financial standpoint but you're right
Pronunciation standpoint I think it's the biggest deal in 10 years since Intel sold office exhale business
Oh wow that's a pretty
And that was that
Exactly
Suzhou future in small chip
Well for people who like oh God they just went off the deep end here's what happened if you miss it
SoftBank which is a Japanese will call it a
Paying a conglomerate
Carrier
And Sprint
Here in the US
That
It made a buyout offer at 17 pounds per share so that is
24.3 billion pounds
432 billion dollars
Boom
Which is the company that makes
The
Design for
Mobile chips
And micro
Microprocessor
Actually produce any chips at all
A design
The chips that pretty much
In just about every mobile device these days
For people such as
Apple Samsung Qualcomm Rockchip mediatek
It does it even includes companies now designing server chips
Amazon actually make
Pixar base chips
Which I always thought
I did not know they were a licensee of army
They must be
Arm does not disclose its licensees
But it's licensees are welcome to say that there
Licensing arm
I'd like to say that
So much
And so basically this steal everyone's like
Oh my gosh
This is crazy it did come way out of left
There's a couple things
Think about
One topic started talking to arm
About two weeks ago apparently with the steel which puts it about
Two weeks after
Brexit vote
And the pound
When dropping
So
There's this idea that this is the first babe
Tech acquisition after the brexit
End
Matters
I'm not sure that it really does
I'm going to say it might be cuz I think the pound is down
I'm going to take a guess here so don't quote me by mass at least 20%
Since
The brexit
But they are paying
They are paying 70 times the annual net
Income I believe of arm
It is
It is not
And you know that's
One of the reason
Arm is always been in a weird space
Because
It is I always call it an arms dealer
Any hardware maker and it is
It's designs
Mean that basically no chip company could ever perch
Because
If your Qualcomm or if your Apple and suddenly
Apple purchases arm than qualcomm's going to be like Willow now
That's not cool I can't decide my chips using the arm architecture
Regulatory with wood would hold that up I would think
Also regular
I just think the customers
Wyoming living
So
That was always an issue and has are moved into servers and other markets
Companies like Google that may have been acquirers
Suddenly we're kind of left out
So don't wouldn't kind of saw this coming arms always been attractive but it's never been like oh I'm going to pay a lot for this because
It was unclear how you can get a lot of value
There's no Center
Yeah
I have an open question and we're not going to get the answer for quite some time if we ever do it all
But my thought is based on the that's 70 x net income
Metric
And the amount of money that is SoftBank is coming up with to do this deal
I'm wondering
FB
License fees will slowly creep up a little
Faster so to speak because they
I would imagine it's been going up steadily
4 years
Apus
What I call a
Expected basis
Rape
Will bees fees go up higher than expected in the in the coming years I Wonder Pets off and try to make back some of that money
That is one of the question
So
I'm talking to a couple of Chip companies Slater
Our licensees to figure some of this
1 is
Hey are you worried about price raises
But the other is
Owner even if it's someone who's not necessarily competitor
Simply because
Well SoftBank has pledged to double the employee headcount in the UK and
Invest in arm
It's an arm could certainly use it
It's really unclear if softbank's really going to go there
Because I mean if you look at it Sprint deal it invested quite a bit in Sprint but
Do not invest Weller wisely I would say it it felt like that's that's not a great deal
Right that's a valid concern because I mean if
The
Case of innovation coming from arm suddenly stops so at a company sort of stagnates or just
Goes to hell in a handbasket
What's that do to the mobile industry
I mean
. sexy
Chip industry not just that like
Cannot display
Arm has Graphics processors that they're still a relatively small part of the market but
Yes
It's 95% of all smartphones have arm-based
Instruction sets
Possibly all now
Asus phones out there
You know whenever some Dell
Android tablets although Del is getting out of that business
Subway 95% sounds about right but I mean
There's a couple things you got the devices
Then you've got what about all the software that runs on these devices if there's a whole new architecture that has to be built because
Armies
No not
Cutting it anymore
The implications could be massive
Chester UK
Massive pregnant
There are alternatives out there
And not just mobile there's also
Servers because arm is getting in there although that's not widespread by any stretch of the imagination
And then there's
Cellular base station equipment they actually have some quarters that are used in
Cellular network
And there's all the microprocessors
So
I'll put a lot of power and softbank's pocket
It does
I mean alarm had that power before sex it's no different in that respect but
Arm is a known entity in this face
It would have been around since the 80s
Was it I thought of the acorn computer
So the acorn computer guys and apple got together
Formerly spun off arm
In 1990
Dairy okay so they were talking before him
Yashow market
Picture was great
So
Yes we will see because
Again
This is huge
Huge
And we've had this like benevolent are
Grace Slick
Climatic
British
Stated company that's like
You know investing in
Putting out
New cores
And working with everybody
You know what the video call, summation Apple
Samsung I mean
There's hundreds of companies are using the architecture gear
If I'm not mistaken I'm sure you noticed there's
Two different type of licenses so you can just
License
The Beast
Arm Staffing
Credit chip based on the basics
Where you can customize and pay extra and so on so forth
And that's what Apple does and I think Samsung and some others
Yes those are called
That's that's the word I was looking for
Is something wrong with anybody so I'm going back to my
Open question about
Pricing
Backwards potentially squeeze out a lot of these smaller chip makers
You know and then granted the bigger ones will be happy to take up the slack but
I don't know
More questions than answers than answers in the stomach
It's true it feels like Switzerland just got invaded by a like
Let's just say Japan
What's that mean
I'm sorry but you totally falls apart we should
Just go English just got invaded by Japan
All right
No more
Noma
Okay that's the arm news
Let's move on to
I don't know
You want to talk about privacy
We should talk about
Privacy only because
It came up it just before the show you and I were chatting out what to talk about this weekend
We had a pretty Full Slate but then we noticed
That a new startup
A Wi-Fi * called is in reach
Just emerged from stealth with 15 million dollars
And apparently and I'm just quoting from the Ford Store that covered this
One third of the city of San Francisco has log into
Zenreach without ever realizing it
Which got us thinking about privacy so we start digging around
Within Reach one of you tell them what it is I'm going to let the Privacy is a company that advertises itself
It provides free Wifi for restaurants cafes
Other places
And it's basically
It's a little different from the sponsor y5 Market
Because
They provided you tell login to give them your email address they give that to the
Business owner they make miniature
Event list for the business owner Etc
Your Mac address
Send your email associated with that
Get sent as in reach
When you sign up for that
Free Wi-Fi access
End
Then when you walk in
Later
Anytime even if you don't log into their Network
They'll know it's you because they got your Mac address
Right which is a very unique identifier of the hardware in your phone or tablet
What so
That's kind of interesting and doing things because there's
Euclid actually does this
It's the same thing actually they they track
People's Mac addresses
Yeah
Packers have used this in the past on both Wi-Fi on your phone and even on Bluetooth devices
Because when your phone doesn't
The place in your Wi-Fi network is on
It basically tries
It runs through all its Wi-Fi network
Works looking for one that it's been on
Data is
Captured
And by analyzing at they can figure out
Random things like
Attach most often to a Wi-Fi network in this part of the city
Or
Etcetera
The difference here is Centereach gets all of that data
Plus
Your
Yeah and that whole quote about
In 1/3 of the city San Francisco
Login is invalid even knowing it that's what kind of thinking
Will the sky be Travis implications there so we took a quick look realtor.com privacy
If you're in California you're kind of
Up the creek
Because right at the bathroom saying we don't even recognize and respond to the do not track signals in California cuz
Bethel still in flux so you can print it trying to block it that way
You can opt out
But you pretty much and can't use the Wi-Fi networks of the retail establishments at all as I read it
Right
Topped out
You would have to go to the network advertising initiative or there is a formal
Do not track
Effort
California California
Macarena
Turn your Wi-Fi off a side which is very nice of them to suggest
Oh
You can use the digital advertising Alliance
Consumer opt-out
Or the network advertising
So both of those places but
None of those places actually guarantee and if you
Anything like clear cookies
All of that actually can go away cuz they put a cookie on your phone saying
Participating advertisers.
So
I
Because
In the master of is this than that
Actually wanted to let you guys know I know on my phone I use
A simple is this and that recipe
For when my phone goes out of my home Wi-Fi
Automatically turns the Wifi off on my handset
So this has to
Nice things it saves battery life marginal
And it also
Helps cut down on tracking
I want my network Sia
That's an option
If you're like
Forgetful and don't wanna manually turn off your network that's
Double and then you can always turn it back on
If you're like oh I need Wi-Fi
If not it's a good thing that's a good trick
I imagine you can do it on iOS to cuz
But I've no
I sent I don't have an iOS
That's a good question if I was a little more finicky about
External control of phone settings and such
Supreme
Detailed iOS
Yasso
I don't know
That Maybe not maybe so that's the
Messy stuff
I don't know what to tell you
Your privacy is basically a force
Other things happening
The FTC
Speaking of privacy is looking out for us
They put out an advisory last week
On
Basically talking about
After the nest revolve
Tissue
Asking people who manufacture devices
To consider
Not sun setting them in such a
Terrible
Careful way
This is like the most
Toothless Pig
But it is like
The FTC to look into the hole
Nest reball shut down between I know we talked about
Several days ago
And decided not to further investigate into it based on several reasons one was he
The actual users of the product
I guess they felt it was
Not
Large enough to make that big of a deal obviously if you are one of those affected you will feel otherwise and
I totally appreciate that but
Yes so they they did come up with is your right it's a toothless
Blog post essentially saying what happens when the sun sets on a smart product
You know they mentioned
Meme nesting revolver
But they did say
Yeah of a recent investigation into one company's decision kind of prompt it us.
Take a look at this and
So that they're giving some guidelines to companies who make iot devices to deal better with
Consumers
And then be more transparent
And I would like to
To say that these are actually
I said guidelines so the first is are you selling a device a service or both
What are you telling consumers
That you're selling
Cuz a lot of
Will tell you something in the value is in the software and services
But they're telling you
I'm not paying $250 for a nest thermostat because it looks pretty
I know some people do but
If it suddenly broke on my wallet
Because I know
Think of it as Justice
Are consumers getting a fixed term rental or subscription are they getting something they will own and can rely on for the life their device
Most companies
Choose to do a one-time purchase because
Consumers hate paying for subscriptions but if the FTC wants to really start asking
Questions about that that could really change that business model
I like the very last one actually
What did you tell consumers at the outset or what would
They otherwise expect
About the security would provide for the life of the device
Credit as a vendor with sunsetting devices well because there's residual data afterwards but
I like the security aspect like that they're asking that question
An unrelated note very related note
Since I moved recently I left my nest in the old house and I put the ecobee3 in here as we talked about last week
When I deactivated my Nest I got a nice confirmation email
So you want to close your account
I did that
I sent me a confirmation email after that saying
We removed all of your information from our servers and so on so forth so that
That was a great way to handle that not so much on the revolve side but
I'm a mess I with my data that was great
Got it
Show me
As a consumer also
As a recent picture
Isn't just telling you this because they think it'll be nice they're telling you this is a warning
Unfortunately or fortunately depending on your point of view
Agency
Is
Not going to Lake
Right off of the big steak
Start beating people with it
They are specific
Stop showing their stick
Look what we have
This is what we care about
We have a stick
They're not afraid to use it
Not at least so far
Post presidential alert
Everything
Alright what else do we have
Forget the docket I'm going to interject
I must
Okay
Because you assign me homework about a year ago and I finally completed it
Insteon homework
Now when I thought I thought I was going to be
My dog ate that I got it no the quick
Z-Wave lock
I forgotten
I know it's been awhile
O'Jays
Well I it just made sense to put it in because
When we got to the townhouse I figured I have to rekey the locks and change all the locks that's in all the way to 2nd station
Kwikset Z-Wave lock
Maybe a year ago it's got to keypad that connects to my wink
Install it over the weekend
It's working super super well
I get concerned that there's four batteries inside you you supply the batteries I have
How many Loops in there for
Double-a any loops and I don't know how long they last
Is right now nobody's carrying keys or I'll just use the keypad to get in and get out where using phone unlock the door with
No batteries means no exit and no entry
If it's locked
So I will say so
Since we had ours up for
Probably a little over two years
They've lasted between 6 and 8 months
Stay last less login
But recently
If we actually had a bachelorette because bad batteries fit
They stopped working after like a week it was crazy
I will say though
The manufacturer says that if you put batteries in
And you don't
Connected to anything
It's going to rain a lot faster cuz it's constantly
Painting to look for a Z-Wave device if you're not going to have it hooked up to something for a while
The radio chip out
Well yeah I'll leave it in because it's it's
Connected to the wink Hub which obviously I put in prior to the
The quixotic setup on my lights and everything else and
I'm back to the way I was in the old house
On my lights and such so
That's good to know but I'm going to leave those better than cuz if it's working great
I love having to be honest
Awesome
I see we got a visit from Norm here
Yeah
Smaller house
Happy
He's adorable if you're not following Kevin on
On Instagram I should just get him his own darn account but yeah
Play I put on warm
After all the pictures
Is going nuts
Okay so some quick news to round out the show
Is wechat skybell
My favorite HD doorbell
Out there right now although I haven't tried the ring Pro so
Skybell is connected with SmartThings
Yay so if you have those two devices you cannot make them work
Work together this is also a good time to say that I'm a little disappointed in August right now because I have the August
Connected doorbells and things
Promise that 90 days after the product launch they would have motion sensing
And
The ability to save your
Videos
And so far they don't yet
We are now past
30 days it was supposed to be about the end of June
So
I felt like I'd wait a little while and
Before saying anything because you know things do take time
But
Clocks ticking clock is ticking
I have two of those and I
I'm kind of a little miffed that I bought these on this promise that so far hasn't been delivered
Maybe I should get a prorated
So there's something else the FTC
You can look at
And finally the White House
As part of the
Kind of
White standing bunch of investment
They have
Said they're investing in four hundred million dollars in
What does this mean exactly
It basically means that they're doing a bunch of initiatives through the advanced Wireless research initiative is part of the Nationals
Science Foundation
In 5G Network
So
It's not actually iot it's more than networks
Iot
But it's a lot of money
Question about or noting
Its and it's
Early days for five DMV that's becoming the buzzword I remember when the whole 4G thing hit
You know two years before we actually saw an implementation but
This exciting stuff
You know too much speed of a network
Interesting
The FCC last week said that they were going to give basically 1100 gigahertz of spectrum over to 5G
And when the FCC
All frequencies
A range of frequencies above 24 gigahertz
That's on the Spectrum chart that's going to way up there
That spectrum is
You know that's not going through walls very well
It's not great Spectrum but we've got a bunch of new technologies that make it a lot easier to use
Ardmore economic ice
So that's what the FCC
What do you Telecom guys talk about when they talk about 5G is actually
3gpp standard
Which is kind of like LTE
And what's interesting here is
5G isn't just about
Mobile broadband like LTE was
Angie is going to be about interfacing
Networks in the cloud together to deliver specific type of apps
So like there might be standards or
Protocols for connected cars
And then there might be a slice of the 5G Spectrum allocated to
Hospital
So
There's going to be a lot of interesting stuff here but
Until it gets a little bit
More clear we're just going to have to wait
Before they close since you mentioned frequencies can I just make note of one
Interesting tidbit
O spectral stuff
Well not for long story
Do it
So I came across a very interesting article from Marco
Armand to is a iOS Developer pretty print iOS Developer
He was having problem with his cars Homelink transmitter
You would open the garage door but more often than not it would not close the garage door which is like
You pulling out of the driveway hit the button and why is the garage door
Closing
Well he did some digging and
Found out that
Pierce
Issue had to do with a no-name LED light bulb in his garage door opener
The reason he found his Nabi saw an article that says government guidelines for Led manufacturers require these control circuit
Semi LEDs to operate
A frequencies between 30 and 300 megahertz
By coincidence
You know it's most rush or opener remotes have been assigned frequencies between 288 and 360 megahertz so
There may have been some crosstalk overlap there
Sure enough he took the No Name LED bulb output in an old incandescent
Problem solved
Which was kind of interested in condesa actually burned out later the same day but that's just a very funny site
Okay tell is it the No Name
LED bulbs like what a named LED bulb work better
Depends on yeah I guess it depends on testing what frequencies are using I don't I couldn't say for sure I mean
I would
It would be nice if he had put in some different brands of bulbs to find out
But he just said I want to sell my garage door problems original bulb
Okay
Alright well I think
That's it for
Today Show
Please
Stay tuned for Adam Wolf the CEO of arable
As we talked about Precision farming and The Internet of Things
Hey this is Stacey Higginbotham breaking into the iot podcast for a message from our sponsor
Exactly which is a iot platform as a service
And we have
Patty
Sweetheart
Who is the GM exactly who to talk to
In the connected home space we're seeing a lot faster.
What's the Internet of Things
Why is that
Thank you Jay Z
I think the primary reason is that the users and the connected home segments are more willing than
Others to push the envelope and take risks
In order to get much better immersive experience
This typically leads to faster refresh Cycles in a connected home
Space where product Williams or manufacturers are
Innovating very rapidly even if they have to subsidize the hardware acquisition cost
2klab adoption
Think about it most of the products in the connected home space are still operating independently
So as much
Traction as we have already seen the space
Just getting started
What are some insights for the early adoption in the
Vacations from users have evolved very rapidly
Onboarding app experience
Service expectations
From users have dramatically changed over the last several years
The more successful connected-home members are the ones that fully Embrace this
And we strive to deliver delightful experiences and first class
Support for these
Connected Home Products
What is a Fast & Furious the time-to-market and time in Market
The best companies in the connected home and and even have the larger scope of the Enterprise segment
Don't waste their time
In the lab
Trying to build infrastructure and plumbing Technologies
But they tried to get to Market as quickly as possible so that they can learn from
Their products getting adopted
Rather than spending time building infrastructure
We tend to think about this as connect
The product management are the
Suite of applications that really enable East product Williams to get to Market
In the quickest possible time
All right how do you see the iot market transforming over the next
I strongly believe that in the next few years we will stop thinking about iot as a stand-alone phenomenon connectivity in physical
Products will soon become an expected part or
Unexpected feature of
Everyday products and customers will begin to expect iot functionality on anything and everything that has a scent
On off switch with this changing expectations from consumers
Connacht williamsville soon be able to deliver products
That allowed them to get
Much closer with their end customers
I'll also give them
Valuable insights into how their products
Are being used and consumed
So that they can create and deploy new features
Instagram to their Hardware products
What should I call we deliver software over the internet today
Century all of this guy's back to product Williams having the capability to
Create new business models using their physic
Awesome and Patty
How can we find you
Are you getting check out
Our website at zulily.com Bly. Com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and I am with Adam wolf who is the founder and CEO of arable Labs Inc
Hello how are you
I'm doing great
HD here
Awesome I'm excited to have you because arable
Is a startup or going to
Protocol UA
Startup in the world
Farming
And The Internet of Things
And then we'll take into kind of
What you guys see yourself doing
So quickly you guys call yourself actually a risk
Management
Can you talk about kind of arable in that context
You're not as we
Started the
Company
From a lot of different
People
Drum
Crop insurance
People developing
Watermark at 2
People managing
Giftster and bonding and rely
What do all these people have
Is the day you need to know what's the difference between
What they thinking
True and what's actually true
What are the facts on the ground
Collecting data that
Really
The story of what's Happening
Plants
Prospective
And the weather
That is the key right here is part of your strategy
Not just data delivering
Inside let's talk about
Your sensor because you guys are launching a physical sensor
Why go physical Hardware
You're really real
Interesting
I got my
PhD
Stanford sponsored by NASA
Satellite data
Which means
I got complicated model of how plants work
And just like a weather forecast.
Constantly checking the
State the system again these observations in this case from saddle
So
I got to the end of that and I realized
The band
There's a lot of other stuff that you really want to know
Like what was the weather
What did the person plant
It also
Discerning
Coincidence
Set of data
Not just
State of the plant
Sound like
The shape
Why is this plant growing faster here than this same plant over there
Not really required
Merging
Microclimate
And
Plants
Probation
Which is black
Okay it in our conversations before this you would talked about
Your business model and it is to
License
These pods two companies
And then you also have kind of a
Data analytics service I guess it's the best way to put it I'm not sure
And is
Really
Are North Stars around empowering people
To make
Decisions around
Natural res
Listen to company is not
Bounce
To this device
And yet
We knew
Because of
All of our prior work that this is a pinch point for us
They also discovered there's a pinch point for a lot of people that actual grounds
Focusing
On making a device
That is
Globally
Scalable
Pick one device
And it becomes mass-produced
Costco
Because
Vanishingly small
You know we have to look back at how we understand
In a really fairly marginal small holders
Outlander parts of the
Developing world
All the way up
Into the most Elites
Tulip farm
And raspberry producers
Well over $100,000
Break all of these rely
You can use data
Gods
The value-add
Crothall beans
Parts of agriculture
So how would it
BBA
Giant soybean
Grower use your stop which I'm assuming is kind of a lower value crop
Versus someone who's making raspberries
The challenge
Or start up like orange
Is really to recognize the
Midwest is bad
The Ukraine is Basque
All the places where they grow commodity
Crocs
Are extremely expensive
You know I'll send it has to be said that when commodity prices are depressed
Money into
Uncertain value
Is the investment in this piece of Hardware really going to
Unlock
What they need to be unlocking until
Really the path to Market is
The work
West the
Agricultural service providers that are already in those fields working with left they profit by
Where the crop advisors
They are
Like the tech support in many ways
That's the person
Who can really look at the data
Say okay
We're going to change our plans we're not going to be
Here today
We're going to have to put off till next week after this Halestorm
So in that case you don't tell directly to the farmers you're going to sell
Agricultural service
Yes exactly
And it's time to do a couple things that I think other businesses can
Take something away from
Which is
You guys have recognized that the data that you're Gathering
It's not the be-all end-all
Is the insights in the ability to help a company
Kind of offer
Risk management
And you also realize that the people you benefit may not be your actual End customer
Because
They may not have
Either the income
The sophistication
So kind of what you guys are trying to offer
So I'd love to kind of understand how you
Figured this out because it's a hard thing for
Businesses were like
Hey
We should totally connect
You know and get data from
This particular aspect of our world and then
Try to sell that
So how did you kind of
Get to this point
It starts with a lot of list
And it's
Somebody
I don't pop out
You're talking about something
Then
You're not solving
Often times
Let's say
California
That would be the widespread for
Perception
Farmers
AR
Experiencing a pain Point around irrigation management
And you might take a technology about this is measuring
Wishing you would want to measure
And yeah if you talk to the farmer's day like I've got
A magic sensor that will tell you when to water
They roll their eyes
Now that's a I'll call you might be the 10th person through my door that does that
To be honest we've got a guy who does that
China weekly schedule
It's not
Like a plan
But if you go to that same person
Yul destination crop forecasting
Or
Decisions about marketing
Their eyes pop out
So what does that mean to like somebody who is not a friend
It's like how many berries are in the field
Whataburger
Absolutely how many berries in the field or another customers how many
All right with you
Isn't interested the used taste around lettuce production in the UK
Just a couple days different in the face
Makes a big difference on where we saw
But what
So you could tell me if I were a UK lettuce farmer
Are you can say
Hey
It's going to rain tomorrow so you should Harvest today or do you instead tell me
Hey this field got rained on so if you can hold it for two more days it'll dry out and then it'll have a longer shelf life
Absolutely
Both of those or
You know we control remotely
Because we are measuring a particular set of set of parameters
Elephants have condensation
It's a. Might say okay
This you have to sell
At your local market but this you can not ship to Spain
Okay that's useful
So who are your customers
Challenge
The demand
The expressions of Interest ranging from
Very large
Midwestern
Companies serving commodity agriculture
Two especially
Specialty crops
Producers
These folks that often. Grower-shipper said they grow it but they also
Marketing
Insurance
Is a
As a gigantic interest
Especially in the developing world
There's this obstacle to ensuring it which is valid a claim
Even price risk
So we have to look at
Global Entry
And right now we're just
Very carefully
Choosing
People that we want to go eat with
Sure so in the case of an insurance firm would they compel the farmers
How to put the sensors in the field
And they would be your customer and by the hardware from you
And then also the kind of data analytics that come from that Hardware
The exact business model is not in
Byerly worked out
You're not a participation by the lights of a ID or the World Bank
Temple
Is East African or even Central African
Maize production
Farmers
Can achieve much better deal
If they use improved seeds
In fertilizer
Insurance
What place
That bag of grain
Farmers afraid that if he buys it
And put that out and loses the crop to some of them
That
They're not just
You know hungry but they also lost
Will replace that bag of seeds
But in order to do this we need
To be able to validate
Claims
A1 device / Village
Okay see you get a bag of seeds from your insurance
What's this device and then
They ensure that
Crop because they've got a way to kind of
Control in as much as one can
Against the loss of
Ensure
Take the last time you did auto insurance or life insurance
Current history may be William to school
Your mortgage on time
They're looking at Morrill Hall
So what's interesting now is that once we have devices in
Waze
To reach out
Apartments with advice
Make sure
Good day at Sea the best out
Okay
In what
Look ahead 3 years
Into
Farming
As you guys
Expand
Totally
And as Precision agriculture becomes more
Accepted how does that change the way we
Really
Interesting question we
Started tracing
Really
Measurements
From Farm to Table my wife is a is a chef
You know she said she worked at
Some famous restaurants in California where
The ideal
Was really having a row
Ship with the farmer
And dessert
Thirty-One perfect
God let's look at
The date
There's many opportunities when this came to us on Friday
Where
Chastity excited to look at the
Brix level
Sherpa measure of the flavor and quality of produce
Where farmers are able to provide information
That lets them
Claim additional Revenue
About
Having more sustainable practices are higher quality
Potentially reaching
More local markets
And so there's a
Platinum value around
Deeper connectivity between
The plate in the field
Dieting
Both consumers and farmers
Awesome
Because yes
I think everyone has their
Christian Peach
Are Christian fruit
Which is the perfect
You know for me it's a peach Brothers at maybe an apricot
And it would be wonderful to be able to recreate that kind
And make it come
I mean I have memories that are
From when I was her crop advisor
Working around the Lodi area
Arms that
Remind boss made
Dumbass
Charice I've ever had in my life
Being able to
But with your taste buds
Is lost as
You buy
Come on Mark produce
And you don't get a chance
To say that wasn't the best set of strawberries
And yet
We all want that
Ensure
What can we do
Be able to serve you better
Because that means higher
Got it alright for Adam thank you so much for coming on the podcasts
Absolutely it has been such a pleasure enjoying talking to me
And I hope you tune in next week to The Internet of Things podcast