Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higginbotham and this is your surprise
Why is co-host
Grant clauser
So Grant is joining us in place of Kevin
Because Kevin is
Traveling
But do not think that this
Because Grant
Is the Smart Home editor at The Wirecutter
So we have an opportunity to talk to someone who is not just like
Well he might even be better than Kevin don't tell Kevin I said
Grant good to have you co-hosting the show with
We're going to talk about
All kinds of thing
Thank you very much it's it's a pleasure to be here so it's it's been
I think a pretty exciting week for the
Iot world
So there's a lot of stuff
There is this week we're going to talk about if this and that getting
Channel 4
For Louisville Kentucky
We're going to talk about your smart TV spying on you
We got a kitchen m&a deal we've got
Echo
Chitin chat
How I'm going to call that
We've got
Europe's big Cydia show happen
Right now with some exciting news
Who's there
Some security products
But first
Let's get a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is Ayla Network
Ayla networks as an Enterprise internet-of-things platform that is empowering the world's leading manufacturers by simplifying
Apparent complexity at the iot enabling them to turn their products into smart connected systems and transport
Turn their businesses to compete in the game-changing world of connectivity is agile iot platform abs
Strax the complexity of developing connected products and is trusted by some of the world's leading Brands so they can focus
What they do best a list solving the internet of things so you don't have to
Download there white paper five key traits of leading iot application enablement platforms at state
AC on iot. Com Ela and that's a y l a
And before we get started with the show I'd like to ask you guys a little bit of a favor
I have a
Listener survey available that I would love for you to take if you can please go to Stacy on I
Coyote.com
Slash survey and fill it out it should take less than 5 minutes and if you get it in before February 7th
That midnight
You will be entered to win an Amazon Echo or a Google home your choice
All right back to the show
Oh I almost forgot
This week's guest is Bruce Sterling who is the famous science-fiction author and
Futurist he is also building a smart home lab in Italy and we're going to talk about all of those things
So
Stay tuned for that
Grant
All that out of the way
Thank you for doing this let's get started
With
The if this then that channel
Louisville
Chucky
I think this is awesome so Louisville
You guys maybe like more familiar with it
And you realize because that's where CNET smart
Was that actually put it on the market now they've got a smart apartment
Building and
What's happening in Louisville Kentucky is connecting be created and if this then that
And so one of the things you can do is take your Philips Hue smart light bulbs and when the city of seas bad air quality
City data
They can turn your hue light bulbs red
How big of a problem is this in Louisville
I don't know I've never been to Louisville I kind of feeling bad about it
Maybe the barbecue Smoke Gets in there and
That would be
I would rather have the lights change color when the barbecue is ready
That is totally doable
I think Char-Broil Char-Broil has a
Make it smoke right now
I better be pretty easy to do this yourself with an in-home air quality sensor of some sort
You could or you could
Probably
Because they've got an interest in that channel they probably have an API which means
If you could access it you
You could do it with
If you didn't want to do your lights for example
You can do it too
I know what a little alarm that teens
Send a text message
Since you're something to alert you to
Put on the gas mask
Three. But that's a little harder
Also
If this then that
Sounds good
I know that we had a woman on the podcast
Weeks ago she actually did a connected
She took Transit data for the city of London buses
And she built something that basically told people when the bus was 5 minutes away
The light returned
Orange
Yellow
When it was 2 minutes away it would
Red
So you got a chance to
Like the bus is coming quick
So I think those kind of things would be great although again
I don't know how many people take public
Well the other problem is it is known as
Quick so well the bus could be gone by the time
What's the message goes back and forth to the Cloud Server and turns you like color
That is true
Alright so
Transit stuff
That's a
Good question about
At the light bulb
Grecian
Like how long does it
With air quality to guess
If it was a 30 second delay it's not going to be a big deal because
Then you wouldn't have choked to death by then but
Something that's really time-sensitive
I think it'd be a better way to to better public alert system
There you go so
But I also think it's nice that
You know Louisville is actually expire
Flooring something
Like this
Because it is it brings that kind of data to
Are citizen levels
If you can actually you know
He's at this and that to pull data streams into a spreadsheet
Could be something as mundane as I
Charting it
What also makes it interesting is that
Create new stories like this and help
Spread awareness of the types of features that the things that you can do with
With smart home devices that I talked to a lot of people who
Who wanders in why would I want a light bulb that changes color or this and that and
Looking into some more interesting applications of this technology I think it is always a good thing
Speaking of what people are doing with
Let's talk about Vizio
Holy cow
Grant do you want to share with Vizio
Well what does you're doing right now is just paying a fine for things that they did a while ago
It was revealed that their TVs were
Tracking and sharing information of the other internet connection
And they kind of got caught and now the total pay a big fine for that we cover this when it first came out
The models that
Did this
Who does is they had a
An opt-out map
You didn't opt in to allow your data.
Opted out of it and they made it
It's hard to
To find out where you can opt out this exchanged
But I think the bigger story is that it's not just Vizio it's
Almost anything that plugs into the internet is doing this kind of thing
Sangria
We did a privacy blog about this last year
And
We looked at the privacy
And data collection
Processes or policies
Standard
Internet-connected devices from your streaming media services to just standard web browsers
And it's
Some people may be other people
Program but a lot of people be shocked at
How much information
Manufacturers rubber companies have about you just based on
What's plugged into your house in
And what you're watching on TV and what you're doing online
Agree with you there is like
Any connected product
Is also
Giving your data
Sharing.
But what I did find
Upsetting
About the Vizio
Details
What was that it was
Hidden
Very well
Activity
And basically they were like
This enables program offers and suggestions
Which is kind of what Netflix does
Netflix also
Watch
What
What's does it do
Who is track
Other services
Just going over there
I can't
So did the other thing is it provided customers IP
The address yeah that's a sneaky Park
This is where I feel with the smart home and
Connected devices
Our idea of personally identifiable
Call information
Is going to have so what's known in the trade is pii
Is isn't sufficient
Basically
Where we've got so much data that can be
Triggered back to us like I'm probably the only one in my
Austin Texas which feels like
There's a woman in Austin Texas
You know
Who has these characteristics
You actually probably could identify me
From Lake
My IP address yes you could identify
From a cluster of different devices that are in my house
What turns everything into pee
What will somewhere
Yes or lots of places probably there's a profile of Stacy
Of what she owns what she does in her house
Know what her her standard
Temperature is how often she
Opens and closes your door
I thought it was
Because I was like
My husband
He's like yeah I know I could
Cooking
That's weird
Potato ad
No coming in a year
Coming up next showing up on
Yeah your browser what's on
Pandora
I would like to see if
Buy potatoes
They're delicious
The Other Woman I thought was disconcerting about this was
And you mentioned it is the opt-out
You're automatically opted-in to Olive
And that's actually the way
List my devices
Standard
Yeah
End
I don't know if you guys notice others are covered it but there was a lawsuit actually a couple
A couple months ago about a connected vibrator in the
The people who purchased it
Didn't realize it
There
Sessions
A toy would be
Sent to the manufacturer
With the settings
And that and the standard
Responsible manufacturers is
So we can improve the product
Witches of
Open the door
I mean there are good things with this like if you
You can approve
The product
You can actually do really interesting like it if my TV gave data about like what it was on and what I like to watch
You might be able to do some Energy Efficiency
Things you know
Like the show that she loves is about to come on
Add Sesame I watch TV in real-time which most people don't
You know you can you can start to plan for things around that in the TV could be turned off
Completely off
And then try to
Fire up
But that's not what they were
You're just selling your data and I think that's that's a model that
If we don't fix that it's going to engender a lot of distrust and
People are not going to want some
And probably one of the reasons that model has
Has grown
Cuz it could but
To the pressure to keep
Prices on the hardware constantly going down
It's got to come up with some of the revenue stream so
The customer becomes the product
I think that's going to go to Wayside actually
I think we're going to see
See a lot of ships
We'll see I'll have to come back on next time next time Kevin's traveling
In February I'll be like
Did it come to pass I don't know
Let's talk about
Attention. Because I love kitchentek
How do you feel about that
I'm on the fence
Smart Home in the kitchen
If it's something that I need to be in front of
To experience to appreciate
I don't need to get
Alerts to my phone
Front door Decor that's hurting
Maybe when I buy some
Smart kitchen
Crock-Pot or something else change my mind but at the moment
I don't have a smart coffee maker I mean the
Echo in the kitchen that has the timer button
Grant if you were standing in front of
I work at home so I don't leave the house
I have the same
So here is the news
Electrolux
Consumer Appliance
Bought a company called Innova
Ana Nova
You guys may be familiar with it because they make a sous vide circulator
I have a connected one
I've really basically all this is is something that
Bluest water around
I'm keeps it at a certain temperature so you can
Can cook your eggs at like
120 degrees
In a little plastic bag
To the perfectly done
Or your meat
I I don't know what like do you sous-vide
I know I know I know there a lot of
At Wirecutter
And in fact
The Anova Precision cooker is is our choice in in the guy that we
Mapreduce
Our tribe
Just haven't gotten around to it
It makes me think of boil in a bag food
But I know it's not that
It's supposedly
Way better like I've had I've I played with it a while back in
Can gear Wirecutter
People they're so good because that is a really awesome product
Electrolux plant brand
As they entered in this
Market in
And nobody actually said that they plan to
To do some additional Hardware around the smart home possibly even a Smart Oven
At 8
Connected kitchen show that I was at
In October
So
It could be that you know
We'll see a smart connected oven which means that the wire cutters totally get on that
Beat in like a year or so
We were looking at a lot of smart appliances at CES this year
We tend to think that
Or not internet-connected kitchen appliances is it going to be the default
No sooner than later
For some applications I think it makes great sense that I haven't used them really myself just sort of
Cinema at trade shows and whatnot.
I think there's a
Everything is is getting chips in it's going to happen
What's your ideal refrigerator
If you're going to have connectivity there
I don't know I want a refrigerator that doesn't leak cuz that's what I've got right now
It's okay
That's terrible I'm going to suggest you
You get there
I got nothing else
Okay
So there is this
Crazy rumor going around
The hue
Actually you tweeted this this is about
Possible upgrades to the echo
And I'd love to hear your take
Okay what are on a on a Facebook
Group for Echo users
Is someone posted a picture of their app
The settings
Part of her app that showed that
Their app had a new feature called synchronized audio
And the short description on there was it it was too
Synchronize audio among different Echo devices you remain after your. And what not
Which would give it a similar ability to
Twitter Sonos has system has or what the Google home can do and that you can play
The same music all over the house and it's synchronized and people watching this
This Thread we're going nuts
I've tried to verify this the screenshot look legitimate
But I've contacted all my Amazon contact
And they won't say anything
And I'm getting ignored so I'm wondering if this is
Somebody just playing around with Photoshop or it's a real thing I hope it's a real thing because
It'd be an excellent feature
You would have play your
Your Amazon music or what not all over the house and be a lot cheaper than
Like a Sonos system
Multi-room audio is basically like I play things on one Echo
I actually so we kind of jerry-rigged
Spotify
Connection
So this is a common question we actually get a lot on the show
Echo versus
And so since you guys have this amazing
Review product reviews
What are you guys
Recommending to
What features do you have
What overall reviews
I think of the two Echo versus home the echo is
Is better and most of the
We did
Very detailed sound measurements and blind listening test
An echo
Came out over home a little bit not much
And it also tested better as a listener in most situations
But not all
I'm actually Google home is better hearing you
While it's playing music then than Echo is
An echo dot has more smart home Integrations
Google homes is better at searches if you ask a question
And as we were talking earlier it's
Understands language more naturally than
Then I go does sometimes you got to
Twist yourself into knots ticket
Exactly the right phrasing
To turn your lights off or something
Anal with with Echo so
Both of them recommend
People who don't have a lot of smart home experience
Tempered expectations a little bit
It's not going to completely change the world you got to learn how to use a prop
Khalifa
They're almost the same
We tend to think that
More people be satisfied with with a Coleman home but it's not a dramatic difference
Okay
And now we're going to get to the
Professional
Slash old school smart home stuff
The show because
Great you were actually an old
We are home installation
I'm certified to design control for systems of I haven't done it in my
My knowledge of their programming up-to-date lately
And for many years I was the online editor for electronic house and we covered the
The professional smart Hallmark
I've been in a lot of homes
With high interest
Okay
Old school
I know they never do
So what's happening right now is a show called Integrated Systems
That's over in Amsterdam in
Ayad mentally call it the city of your
This is for professional installers you see a lot of
Really cool
Light bulbs some news is coming out
So two bits a newsletter
Someone interesting
Is
One control for
Has integrated with the Amazon Echo in the UK they had had a
They did it actually last years CD
Here forth
You asked
And then also Crestron
Which
Has a
Professional commercial install
Club Mercury
They actually
Are announcing that that they have
Crestron Mercury
For in-room meeting so it's an all-in-one meeting room
Product
From them
Did they announce the
And they're working with polycom and Microsoft
This is interesting because a couple other companies like Citrix is using it
Tableau platform to do this
Some people are hobbling leasing cobbling machines together with Amazon Echo
So
There's definitely demand for Stuff
And now here's what we get grants
Let's talk about what would you advise
I get a lot of people that like Stacy how come you never talk about insteon
Crestron or
Or Supply.
And I talked about him a little
The professionally installed systems
Pictures of on Crestron control for Elan
Yeah there's a couple more
It's a whole different
Experience than what you can
To do with Saya
A wink or SmartThings
The relation is going to
No clean and basically invisible
You want to have snow Blinky sensors all over the place
Telling people who
Who come over and visit the home gadgets everywhere
The experiences
Once again installer will do when they
When they're setting up your system is so come on sit down with you
And just talk about
What you do in the house talk about your lifestyle
And then design the functionality of the system really around that
That's a lot of money a beginning one-room system
Might be
5 grand
Just run the DAV in the temperature in one room
The level of function that you can get with love you do it yourself
Is getting much better
But the reliability doesn't match that of the
Prosystems
And I agree with
If you I would also
Say that anytime your circumstances change on the
The prosystems you have to call them
Back out again
Well you have to
Call to call him back out anymore because they're they're getting much better with
Cloud access to your system if there isn't something
Physically
You know wrong if it's some
Switch that they can do
No freezer on computers
Google web
Most can do that but
I should say you buy a new Blu-ray
And you want to hook it up to your home theater can't really do that yourself
She got to call his daughter to come back
Look up right things and then do a little programming magic into your system so yeah it's um
This car sticker
That's what they all say
What do you think
I have no evidence
EXO
Everyone should always have a little bit of paranoia but not too much
But that's just that just you know
Goes without saying in most of life
All right and I brought this up because I have neglected to tell you guys about this for a while and I actually think it's pretty cool
The almonds
Router
Which I talked about the past because it's not just a mess
Wi-Fi network it's also
A smart home control system
Has a signature
Chip in there and
Very nice Caesar
Interface
And I think it's TSA actually announced an alarm so now it also doubles as like
Oh crap button
Which
They've added iot security to their device
So basically it knows
Because it knows what's on your network
It will check your
Network for vulnerabilities on
Play spices everyday
And when it
She's devices that are going out to sites that look suspicious it will block
So
That's that's actually really cool and you can also see the data usage which
If like you were infected by the Mirai botnet
On one of your cameras
You would notice that because your cameras would be consuming a lot of
You probably wouldn't notice it
Any other way unless you lie
Like physically went up to feel them and they were super hot
Cuz they were just
Running
Cuz he's our
It's not like a computer
Sonic's we got this was really good and then Grant told me that
You guys are actually working on something right now.
Wirecutter
Yeah because it's a security for your smart home devices has has become such a question would we get
About it all the time
That we're going to be a developing a guidon
Devices like this
I saw the Almond at CES and I think that's a pretty interesting one
That I was intrigued by Izzy
They keep a profile
Of some of the top smart home devices I think right now they've got about 20
Which one has the Hue bulbs and nest
And that profile
Is of the sort of the standard operating parameters of that device
And if it notices that
Your
Nestor baldwood not goes out of those parameters it tells you it says
Something's not right
It could be suspicious and could not
I will also tell you what ports are open and what ports are in
I think the challenges is translating
That information
Into
In a sort of actionable
Languages that the average consumer knows what to do with
And that is the hard part Del Alma.
A pretty nice job it gives you these alerts and then
You know it it gives you a little bit of like
What you can do
I don't know if that one of the options
Is Burnet at this
Look if he's got the infected
You know if you got cameras that are affected by the Mirai botnet but the hard-coded password
It just dump that
It's no good to you
So we'll see most of the devices
We talked about on this show
Are over-the-air upgradeable in so you should expect actually to see
Patches come
Pretenders and then yes you should Def
All right we'll print thanks so much for coming on the show this week I think you were an amazing
In an even better Grant
Cool thank you
Stay tuned we've got a message from our sponsor and then we've got
Bruce Sterling coming up next
Hi we're breaking into the podcast this week with the message from this week sponsor sponsor is really cool
It is the MIT
Internet of Things bootcamp
Want to meet the brightest minds and Pioneers of iot
Look no further than MIT
MIT is launching its
Its first-ever internet-of-things boot
An intense week-long course where students will build connected systems
Using sensors Arduino is raspberry pies and other open source hard
The MIT Internet of Things boot camp will be held in Cambridge Massachusetts on MIT campus
May 29th through June 3rd
Admitted students will be able to learn from MIT faculty and guest speaker
Meet other iot enthusiast
Potential co-founder
And have a chance to test themselves at a hackathon open to the greater MIT community
So are you ready to solve big problems with
China computers
Apply now at boot camp
Gott MIT
. EDU
Coyote
By February 26th
I'm going to give that to you guys
One more time
It's boot camp
Dot MIT
. EDU
/ iot
By February 26th 2017
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Bruce
Sterling
Who is an author
And a journalist
Hi Bruce how are you doing
Hello how are you
Stacy I am super
I I know I say this every time you guys but I really am I'm super excited to have Bruce on the show because he is a science fiction author he is
Is also used to come to South by Southwest end the show
With like these really
Awesome
Presentations about the future
So this is like
You are doing something
Really interesting and
I think really difficult
So
And I'm going to link to this in the show notes but
You have a Flickr page where you are in
Is it Torino Italy
Does Rihanna wear in Turin
Torrid okay
Robert cirino as the Italians with
I prefer to call it okay I was a little confused about that I was like
Shroud of
Okay
So you're in Turin Italy and you are building Casa Jasmina
Can you tell me why
Are we came to turn my wife yasmina and I
Some years back because
Curators of a local electronic art fair which is called share Festival
Journalist but I also like to write about design and especially keen on electronic card
Signs of Life or send high technology art set
We were hanging out with
Serenity Electronics
Some of them were makers and some of them where I go you know guys and some of us just you know
Weird weekend hippie
Aren't people
But we befriended
I became quite close to them
Build a house
The house
Where were you been carrying out some of these electronic activities
So the house is
It looks like from the pictures that you guys
Took out
An older house and you
You're basically
You retrofit
Well what it is is an old Fiat founder
Car company here in
They're building
This particular building is
Fablab in it
It had the Arduino offices
Design coworker
Space
Moscato
Print shop
A combination of light and a place to piss domestic tools
I know they'll a little show class at a place where we have cultural events
Okay and
This is a house for me curso
What does that
Mean to you
Kwik King on Internet of Things
Issues
Cuz that I've been I've been writing about
For a long time and used to write science fiction about that kind of densely Network
Connected world
We do
So they're just like all let's let Bruce of jazz Meetup be like the curator in the hostess
Of our space
Set of roused
People among our group of
Creative
And I'm the curator in the sense that
I say what goes into the place and what we
This is a very Lively make her scene
So it always are pretty to a lot of this stuff and
I used to be a columnist for Make magazine so I
Do people at the O'Reilly Circle
Make her seed in Europe
Just because I know a lot of people who were doing it and they do stuff
Just wouldn't see in the US and I find that of credit interest
So what are the sorts of things you're putting in Casa.
Well you know it's mostly stuff that we either made or had given to us and it's mostly open source.
We just ended that means
Protection
Table
Feel like a multimedia set in the area tile big screens and
Kind of hardware
Who work on Riot style that's the kind of
You always complain
RT Podcast
Like the lighting system in
Door lock system
Of course they're all slaughtered
Weather Underground
So she really barely work
Graduate student
Project is opposed
Yale locks are Nest stop
So we've got a lot of
Raided frazzle
All the weird I'll Electronics kind of plant for the wall in it
Install a thermostat
Taken from the things you're doing in your house
What translates to how we're going to live in the future
Or
How you might build a house for normal people in the few
Why would you a lot of people to our house and most of them are iot craftspeople I mean the kind of people
Internet of Things
No
I don't know that yesterday Alexandra deschamps lancinho contingent
People from Munich from Berlin internet-of-things things con
So we did a lot of good I went to basically political discussion
Amer
Principal declarations about our ideas what the internet of things out of be
Santa Cruz Superlight open source people wear
Are you down on
Surveillance marketing
But it's our policy not to about people in the house
We have a feminist group in this house the internet of women things
It's been a lot of time
Considering domestic issues like why does a wife
Mother want these devices in her house
How do they change the way people relate to one another
These are kind of intimate cultural issues
By people who
We're just trying to make the numbers for the next quarter
Affect
The tenor of society in the long run
What are some of the
Domestic or cultural issues that you see from
Bringing all of this can
Nativity indoor
Well it wasn't quite good book that was written I don't know maybe 10 years ago by Adam Greenfield there's a friend of mine
Everywhere
Iwa re re
Speculating
Kind of
They're all personal effects at this kind of ubiquitous
Answer the things he said
What time
Really shocked
Weather
This declaration was that
Mobile devices
Change cities more than cars have
Oh come on this is pure height
How could that possibly happen and you know I think it's coming true
Yeah you can actually set of see it on the streets Jedi with the other kinds of
We got Lites strange little electronic rentable cars in our neighborhood now
Things Adam talked about
Differential permission
I'd like to set up a system to automate
Your house
And it kind of automatically locked
It's not in the interests of an inquisitive 7 year old
Or you know the 87 year old grandmother who's living in the back
Bringing out these kinds of
Power strike
What to say to Dad's using his Android
Is a remote control for everything
Kat makes dad that remote control
Like Dad turn on the lights dad open the windows dad open the garage
Dad do that everybody either husband Magnum
If he's left
Whatever he's effectively
Imprisoned everybody
One of the secrets to
Excessive
Amazon
Cowboys computer interfaces The Talk
Can donkeys I like the color
I can't say her name
Minor program
Is true
He who cannot be named as we like to call her in the trade
Everybody in the family
7 year old cat
Asked
The main was Donkey
The play Jingle Bells
And it will
Endigo
It doesn't segment the family and it doesn't
Doesn't cause he's annoyances
Andrea Lee
Horace kind of family power division
Why do you call these personal assistant
Devices tok
I think you need a term for Amanda. I think it's science fiction
Free makeup
Slang for stop
Geologist
But I am cuz it's kind of a lot of
Right and I think they're going to end up kind of attached all kinds of
Services that kind of a do
No smart
Refrigerator
Where you used to have a webpage unnecessarily attached to everything we're going to have one of these
Unnecessarily attached everything
Issue that I'm looking at and struggling
In my life which is
They are like talking donkeys like you said there
Not intelligent about everything
And one of the places they really break down is
Knowing
Which one I'm talking to
And what makes sense
To ask
Context
Well you know I actually appreciate your effort to struggle
Cuz I was listening to that
A healthy naming protocol for these boys
Got to change the kind of language
Nearest because General natural
Language recognition
Although it's Advanced YouTube
Pretty badly off
Are there a lot of situations where you could make a verbal slip and like accidentally Set Fire to the house I need to know
That has not happened yet but
Donkeys become more often
The present of people just start randomly
If this then that processes
Oh well you know
Nameless Amazon one
You're so smart go out to be able to figure this out and instead you just set up set up a situation display
Fire really
I can easily be literally I mean you could say something like nameless rhyme
Turn on the stove and there could be something wrong with the stove
You can have a gas explosion
That is why they don't hook these up yet
Gas
The echo team is very good
Door locks for example
You can't actually can
You can laugh
Already
Audio generated Google Now malware
Surprise me at all because you know where we've been or doTERRA where you got this
Used out of state supported
Cyber crime activities
Who do nothing all day except look for zero-day vulnerabilities
Man who wouldn't want to who would not want to hack
Always on micro
Yes I fully believe the NSA it's already done
And besides it's just plain doable
Wrote about hacker crying
Walkabout
Packer crime actually cash
That's involved electronic crime and also the political
Power of it
Are so motivated that we really died of a massive International class or full-time criminals
Which never existed in the past
And I think this is one of the major
Differences between
Shooting world
Old school internet of the 90s
Siloed
Barre Cypress
War friendly Internet of Things
So what should we do about that or how should be
Think about that
Because if we think about domestic techno
She's so like in the home
That's actually not
Terry Bradley widely adopted
Fatso
We could be like just just don't buy into
This is not a good
For the rest of Industry which is already adopted this because there are real benefits
What do we tell them
The point of view of somebody
Italy
What can we do about this
Because they're on the receiving end of this almost all the time
Mini military G7 industrial Nations
Equality
Google Apple Facebook Amazon Microsoft and NSA
They're not where you buy or not at all
Huawei timeout Samsung Gear not the Russian Anthem at the Chinese
Intelligence units
Certo bottle
Santa Monica is home automation
And Italy
And it's been around since flight
Animes like dinner with thermostats and whatever
And sometime
Kitchens that like
Kitchen equipment
Rakhine enough it just give us
Stop
Which we use in which yolk usually oppresses are Italian
A really good kitchen
Okay I think
The European response to this
Initiative
Well eventually the
Some kind of Lifestyle packaged alternative
Internet of Things
And I'll probably say things like well we don't spy on you
We're not Facebook or not.
Prop
You know you can have some really nice chocolate
Is your guitar really nice espresso will keep can tabs if you're really nice clothing
I'm all deliberately do less
And Silicon Valley does
When perhaps they can do it in some
Safer and more regulated way because that would be
The classic European response
The pretty much any American technological initiative
But okay you guys do it and we'll do like the cute version
I will do the beautiful version that's elegant and private and
Possibly.
Well as the Japanese say that all of Europe is a boutique and America is a farm
I would predict some kind of European
30 corresponds eventually
Okay and as a user as a plain person
Makes money thinking about alternative scenarios
Where do you think we're headed
And ask that question
And I don't really think we have the words for
Barham
I was listening to it on one of your interviews
Reason why we were talking about augmentation a kind of everywhere
That's where we're going
Icon Vintage Ubiquiti
Cuz I've been very keen on ubiquitous Computing and augmented reality
I thought many years ago that if you're going to have time to tationil processes
Going on you were going to have to have some kind of display wherever they were happen
Is one of the biggest problems
You can't see it's working
That's not visible right
Disconnected like little things are little prickles of disorder
Life
Particular
Beloved of mine
Science fiction
Intelligent light
Are like JustFab cast
Literally
But I don't I don't
Mother's Day that I can go and only one way I think we're going to see various breeds
Augmented Ubiquiti
I think we're going to get a balkanized internet we're in for an era of
A massive breakdown
We're not going to see
The kind of
Handshake
One-size-fits-all tcpi world
Not because it doesn't see the institutional interests of the major players
We're going to see silos
I'm going to be like
A protective kind of situation
Market segmentation
I really don't want this in my bath
And I want somebody to prove that it's not turned on
I don't know what the reaction is going to be it's not going to be one
The American way since that is always say
Consumer and I just won't go and buy that down at home
Home Depot
But then I got to be offered that chance
This is going to be epic struggle on a very high geopolitical
And it's not really about you choosing between an 800 PC and a Mac
It's true I mean you have to have a phone now to do just about anything
And those things are
Fantastic tracking
Information gathering
What should we do about the FSB
For like the Russian intelligence services
And the response is not a whole lot I mean you can be aware that there around
But it's not like you get down to go there and vote with your pocket
I'm going to go someplace for the FSB
Nowhere now
You just compared iot to the FSB
The Russian state
They infiltrate the internet and everybody knows but they not
Exactly
So
This feels very
Dystopian we can't do anything
But it's also a real life
So
I feel like it's a
The person I have to be able to do something
Cuz I can't
American
Response
Kind of like that I'm an individual and I have to do something
Pragmatic
I know people think that way
Everything will I have to go to the plaza or you know I have to like join a different political party or I have to find a
Patron tequila
Protect me from desk
So it's not like their health was
I just don't think that the individual
Very much
I've got to like work to my city council
Born some kind of clique I got to get my community or my political party to help me out here
It's not that different
Different way of life
I know I don't like to
A determinist about this and kind of like
Make people Despair and feel like how they can't really do anything
Only country I kind of do like a lot of stuff
I just don't have an illusion that it's super effect
Like just having a house where people can stay
I think it's been very helpful
Does a lot of people who are very active on the internet and have all kinds of friends and social media
Who does Matt have dinner with
Because it's like trouble
But yeah we can set us a why don't you fly over here and stay for a week and turn in our house
Interesting place
You don't have to pay
When it's a little weird you might get a few plywood splinters
A very nice kind of social intervention
We have people show up
Weather not Industrial
People like that
Antonella
Curator of design Museum of Modern Art
We had Palace drop by a cousin
Okay I like I like this
Fatality ID
What would you do with your house okay we have an Internet of Things house but it's a house forest and kind of a
Internet of Things node
I can be really like push the domestic aspect of it
And I think that's actually very useful thing
Anybody could build a castle yasmina
All right
Question here which may not end up being a question
We'll see what happens
Novelist just a storyteller
On the show because I think stories are so important
Play to something as abstract as technology
Do you feel that are storytellers are
I sort of feel like they might be
Failing us a little bit
Not providing a new visions
MP
Maybe less positive Visions I don't know
Our storytellers are shaping the future in
Have we reached like a
The point where they're in the future
I don't know
Bright
Well
Author novel SSI prison
Doesn't literature about that
Nobody was going to say our Barbers are failing us or our plumbers are failing as a gas station attendant
Dino guys were like quite the situation
Better guys
Play groups in the United States that interests me a lot but I think they have a big future here
We're kind of academics
Who actually want to occupy a space between science fiction detective element
So you've got guys like a Arizona State University
But I have
Groups
30 not doing set up like the Washington style of ass
Neal Stephenson hangs out with their I might hang out with them
ASU science fiction and you'd find
Define guys there who are basically academics and kind of think tank
We're trying to come up with ideas they published science fiction books they also
Can you do industrial stop at
Hang out with movers and shakers
Another is a group and
UC University of California San Diego
Arthur C Clarke Center for human imagination
Yes quite good terms
We see Kaze yasmina as a kind of sister Enterprise to them in some ways
I was there last summer
The vitra design Museum
Hibiscus robotics
Like what's the impact of Robotics over like a 20 to 25 year.
You can go out with some rather
Where people have no special effects
Equipment
3D modeling Hardware you can do some
Pretty good
Cultural intervention
Set up put into a museum and self-worth
Alright Bruce thank you so much for coming on the show this week
Thanks for putting up with me
I enjoy this
That's it for this week's podcast thanks for listening and remember if you get a chance please take my survey at
Stacey on iot. Com survey and if you do it before February 17th
Midnight you have the chance to win an Amazon Echo or a Google home all right I will see you now
Next week