Hey everyone Welcome to the
Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we are here today with lots of little bits of news so we're going to try to zip on through
This should be live
Pacn
Full of
So to kick ass off
Let's start with
The
I'm going to go with mind-boggling news
Gartner's news
They said that there are now six
Now we are going to be 6.4
Billion
With a B connected
Things
Things in use
In 2016
Up 30% from 2015
I've actually kind of amazing
I should have done the math before the show
I'm the third what
Is that 4 billion ish
Devices that are kind of currently connected
That's about right
3.8 I'm sorry I'm looking at their number installs by category millions of units
2014 3.8 billion
2015 nurse biking 4.9 and then in 2016 6.392 or Isaac
6.4 billion
And so most of these devices
In their category breakdown
Are actually consumer devices
Which I thought was kind of pretty crazy because
A lot of people
When you say internet of things I know we talked about the consumer a lot but most people are like oh it's all this crazy connected Factory
But no
Know the vast majority of their devices
This year it's like
3 billion
Other 4.9 billion
AR
Connected consumer
Devices
And even going out to 20/20 when they expect
20 point
8 billion devices to be connected
13 point
6 billion of them are going to be consumer
Set alarm alarm
Skewed percentage any surprise me too and that's why I added to the show notes because
You're right and we think of there's all these vertical markets and the industrial sector
You know smart meters and all these other things but
Really it looks like
The consumer Market is
Driving
Well that's in terms of number of things
But then we get into
Dollars
Here's where it gets a little bit more fun
Consumer applications will about 2
546 billion dollars in
2016 so that's next year
What's the use of connected things in the Enterprise will drive 868 billion dollars
In that same.
So
Consumers
We've got
More stuff and connected objects
But the Enterprise stuff
Makes our cost more money
Which you're getting ripped off
Yeah basically
We're all doing DIY and they're all like healthy Consultants ready for Enterprise logo on there
Struggle the price
So that's the Gartner study it was out on Tuesday
Band
Totally worth looking into because
Because a it's a lot of things but it feels a little bit more realistic than some of the earlier studies that we had in Tallahassee
Study that had I believe
50 billion devices in 2020
This is a little bit more realistic at 20.8 billion
But you know it all fairness some of these numbers were like just tossed out like
Probably
I think it was like 3 years ago
3 years ago this was pretty new and we were all like
Do you know A lot's changed since then
We got a little bit more practical
And you know
Forecasting stuff is never easy but you're right a few years back or talk about such huge numbers right not going to happen but
Reality is there sharing 2014 and 20th
Pmdd data actual data
It is prime
As Beijing as fast as they said it would have several years ago so
Besides you think might be a big thing Sunday
Really I am
Stacy's cat
There's a subcategory for hubs and right now you've got the market share so
So next item up
In terms of spending on connected things
You can buy the Amazon Echo in retail stores
For the Christmas season
For the holidays
This is I think very good news at
So kind of surprising since
8U Amazon obviously sells Kindle devices and other things in retail stores but they're also known as the
Shopping Hub of
The online world
And The Echoes of very unique device
Keep it to themselves to some point but
But now there's a whole list
You never talk about them right before the show
Who is the who's going to sell this RadioShack which surprised me to be on the list at all
Staples switch
Now that makes sense that got the whole connected home
Get up so talk about right then
Brookstone wearable cost twice as much of the riverhouse navigating
Home Depot
Westworld PC Richards at Fry's
Hhgregg
Sears where you don't pick up your vacuum
Clear bags if your me
Lincoln shutting down by May 6th
Hard to find a Sears but yes they will be in serious as well BJ's Wholesale Club so maybe get a discount there
It's not because
Notable know your place I didn't see it two of them
Target
And Best Buy
Which is kind of a shame
For the holiday season because
But I don't know I mean I don't go into
Site for the holidays
Too much every day of the holiday season for me so I'm in Best Buy a lot
But I was actually kind of surprised because Best Buy is actually really
Trying to create life
Service business around the connected home and they sell a lot of other connected
Tom products
And the echo is
Actually really good beginner product
Believe it or not
And Target
Because they're really
Doing some really cool stuff around the connected home
And once again
Day
Are really emphasizing how these things all work together and the echo is really done a lot to
Kind of
Trace consumer awareness I think
Both of those stores probably feel a lot of tension
With Amazon
Although they I believe both of those stores also sell
Candles
I think they do I know what kind of Target
Does Imagine Best Buy doesn't actually I just bought something at Best Buy this weekend they will
Match Amazon prices so I got new a discount on that so you're right there's tension there there
They're definitely in combating
Amazon there so
I don't know
I mean cuz the echo is not just a smart home automation Hub it's also a
Hey
Person who lives in the Echo
Will you pick up
Will you order this from
So we cannot live
It's a pretty good product
Even without the smart home integration stuff and we talked about for the smarthome bits
Touchpoints book
You know Isaac connecting Bluetooth speaker a personal assistant software
It's pretty interesting
Okay so
Next item
Let's see
We've got hope
Do you want to talk about a smartwatch
What is the greatest
Not this one but I will
So
I remember it was in May or March
Intel said they're going to be working with tag hair
Create an
Android Wear smartwatch
And at the time I could have sworn I said
It would be powered by their clock chip
Set sound right it says sound right in their courtship is now the chip that's on there
Siri platform
For those and the tree platform is Intel's wearable platform
It competes with
It was supposed to compete with
All of the arm low power
So so
So background good now present day
Earlier this week
The watch was introduced
It's called the tag
Are connected
What Carrera connected watch
It will cost you $1,500
It does not have a QuikTrip in it it has from what we can tell an Intel atom dual-core chip that's
Clock IT 1.6 gigahertz but then
Ramps down to 500 megahertz because I don't want the battery to
Run out in 3 hours
Here's the interesting crazy bit and there are lots of Android Wear watches not working today that start as low as $150
So if you would like to buy
K-Swiss
Made or Swiss made brand
Android Wear watch you can do so now
I'm kind of scratching my head over so because really you buy Swiss made watch I have several of them
Mundane
Tissot Omega
Hamilton songs
You buy those for the mechanical bits inside that are Swiss made
But there aren't any mechanical bits in your
Strictly brand you're getting a digital watch face
Made my tag hair
And
1500 boxes to part with for Android Wear smartwatch
Here's a really great party
Paper to your back-up plan because I don't think they think it's going to be successful
At the end of two years when they think the watch will be outdated
You would then treat your the option
I should say to trade it in
And pay another $1,500 and get a real tag hair
Carrera watch
One that doesn't have a chip in it
That's correct.
Traditional true Swiss made analog mechanical watch
You're going to pay $3,000 in the end if you go that route
And you have to give back an Android
Watch which probably will be outdated
Wait so how much is like a real Tag Heuer watch
Easily 3000 you can spend for 5
Oh okay so like
So basically I'm getting a smartwatch
You're going to rent a townhouse
Yeah pretty much
Pretty much
Okay it's just really the most it just reeks of
We don't think this is really going to work
And we don't think you are going to buy this for 1500 so we're going to do is we're going to add some incentive
And say
You're halfway paid towards a real watch
It is interesting and it's cheaper than a Porsche Carrera which is all that
Well yes
Much much cheaper than that
When I first heard about the $1,500 so I can know where they're going to sell any of these quite honestly
I don't think Apple sells a lot of their $10,000 and up Apple watches for example
But you know what there is that incentive that
Yeah it's kind of like a downpayment on a
Traditional watch
2 years from now
Okay well that's
See and I was looking at this strictly from the standpoint of
Has Intel Curie platform
You managed to become
Like competitive with arm
In the answer appears to be no
And
Also apparently if you are a watch band
This may not be the deal for you
Well I'm in the only a 1,500 saved up for your new tag hair and maybe it is
Will know it sounds like you should probably have
F3000
Cuz if you paid 1500
Then you spent $750 for
IWatch for a year
Unless you can stretch it to 3 I'm really good at stretching things out like that the life of my life
Smart watches I don't think
3 years is going to cut it
I just don't
So fancy smart watches
It's not our thing
How how long are you going to keep your Apple watch
You know that's a good question I don't know when they might refresh I don't know if I can do a yearly refresh
I have to see
What they added
You know what I assume they'll put a GPS radio in there next time around which I would really like
But other than that
I'm fine with what it does and
What I have today
How much was
I bought the cheapest one you can get for 350 bucks
The average sales price
Tends to be between four and five hundred dollars are not selling
A lot of those precious metal watches they're selling a lot of B
Entry
Model the sport edition actually about two-thirds of the estimate
Two-thirds of the total Apple watch sales are in the
350 $400 ring
Alright next news item
Let's see
Oh
Speaking of wearables
Let's talk about arm because
Well because you already have your arm
So much for
So much worse
Officer
Okay
Arm is coming back
It has a new
Processor design so things to know
Background
Is arm doesn't make chips it is a chip design
That makes
Designs
And then Jacob Riis license arms designed and then they build their own chips
And they can either build straight from arms designs or they can tweak the design
State Farm Gibson
To a certain extent
And then
Annabelle demon pants
Send customers Qualcomm Apple
Even Intel actually has an armless
Believe it or not
The newest arm architecture design was announced today at
It's user conference
And
It has
Two things worth noted one is the A35 which The Internet of Things show doesn't care much about but it's for
Basically blower power
Smartphone
Consider going to be cheaper
But
This shows purpose
This is what we really care about is the
Really terribly named
V
M
Architecture design
Which don't even think about that because
Hideously name
I'm basically what it is is arm is taking its trustzone
Security features
From smartphones and server chips
Kind of chips for smartphones and servers
And bring it down to the microcontroller
Where's that's what I am stands for
And
This is awesome because that means the Internet of Things is finally going to get some unified security
Teachers at the chip level
Which me and it's going to be at like
The design
Double the arm design level
And this is important because right now
A lot of the security we see at the chip level is coming from like
The chip vendors themselves
And they're like all their MCS have different layer like different ways of implementing security so if your developer in
Building on the Capri scale MCU you got one way to do security
Lmcu you got a different way of doing security
So
What's Happening Here is
Actually a unification
One step below that
Witches
Awesome
Now that's
That's good news for these devices and we talked about security and
Smart Homes and iot a the past and it's been a
And eyebrow razor like
How is all this going to be secured and there's a lot of other aspects of that your data in the cloud so on but
But at the device level
All the way down to the third ship level
This is cake that's pretty exciting and then we also have in the esoteric kind of like
Hardware standards world we also have
Threat certification which is out this week
And
I don't know this
I'm excited about how do you feel about thread surf
I can it's important it's important I just
I haven't seen much
Tangible
Products Medical Products using thread yet
Finessed
Okay so here's what thread is
If you guys for those of you who don't remember
And that's okay if you don't because
Kevin's right
It's not out by then the market because
Basically just been invented this is a wireless protocol so
It's like zigbee or Wi-Fi or
Bluetooth so it's a it's a way for devices to talk to each other
It's a mesh Network it is
Low data rate so tiny little bit today.
Is close range
And
It speaks IPv6
And it goes straight to the cloud
So it can talk to her but
It's it can also go straight to the cloud
And those are kind of the big salient
Do I have to say it was a mesh Network
I think it is
Okay great
So it's going to compete or coexist depending on how you know
How you want to feel about it
With kind of existing Wireless protocols
The big companies that invented it and kind of gathering around it are free scale Samsung
Nest
Silicon labs
Osram
Salary
Appliance
So I actually got off the phone today with Procter & Gamble
The Giant
Consumer goods company and they're actually trying to innovate around
Arthritis swelling
I talked to someone there he was like yeah we really believe that this is actually going to be
What Society moves towards for the connected home
For Consumer products
Interesting
It was on my Proctor again
So that a company I would have expected
Yasso
A
Guys Procter & Gamble's excited about the internet of things and be
Vocalizing around thread
Hey
Pretty cool so
Red certification
It's out their current products using it
Nest later products
We'll see
All right
Until finally
Kind of talks so much on the show Kevin
That's okay I'm listening
If I could just hug you for that
So
Big is
I have been testing for the last like 2 days cuz
This isn't like an in-depth test
It's not really end up the product but it's pretty cool the roost
Smart home I don't even know what to call it it's a it's a battery it's connected battery for smoke detector
I don't know if you remember me talking about this Kevin but
I don't I don't in an action curious because you know we do the whole
Swap out the batteries
When we change the clocks
We didn't do that
Smoke detectors this year so what is this do
This is going to be great for you
I don't know okay so
Roost is a Smart 9 volt
Battery
Design to go in your smoke.
So this is a wifi-connected battery
You pop it into your smoke detector
And you download the app and suddenly you can see
When your smoke detector is on
Right and you can also see when it goes off
You'll get a notification on your phone it would also tell like a circle of your friends
Spike your neighbors are whoever you want to notify for alerts of things
And then you can also it'll also tell you like
Hey your battery is about to
Obviously I've only had it in for 2 days so I can't tell you how long the battery last but that is when
Weather today
This is interesting this seems like a way to retrofit and turn old
Smart smoke detectors into
Smart one spaceship through the battery I like this okay
And so it's a little bit expensive
It's 3499 for One battery
It's 65 for 2Pac
A batteries
But
That's cheaper than a nest
Protect which is the current
Right now your options in the connected
The smoke
Are like
Replacing
Your existing smoke detector with like a kitty
Is that a kid I don't know how to say these
Sing. Leah k i d d e n
They have a proprietary radio so you have to work with like one of their hubs
If
So that's not
Great for anyone who doesn't want to mess with
And no smoke detectors are
Fletc
Look at how much a Kidde smoke detector is
I think they're about
Actually
You can get something like that
And yeah
So some of the some of the connected ones that talked to the hubs are a little bit more
That's if they're only $25
So
And you can get versions that are little fancier with different
Lights
So
This is kind of within that price range but you basically just
Plop out of battery
And
You're golden in this way
It connects to your phone you got the app
The other option you have is something like Leo
Which is like $100 night light that listens for your smoke
Alarm to go off and then can they give you the notification function
But that can't tell you
When your existing smoke alarms about to run out of battery so you still can have that issue
I like chirping at 3 a.m. and not knowing sure
We have to chase the trip in our house addresses nuts
So this this eliminates that
You don't at first I thought $35 for a battery no but now that now that it could basically term
Dumb smoke content with Smart Ones
And as if I'm reading this right the battery last for up to five years
Yes oh yes it does last for a long time
And the nice thing is you don't have to take it out
You know every year like you do your other one
You're going to know my name
Yeah now it doesn't look like it you mention there's an IOS and Android app that this works with now
It doesn't look like it works with any smart home hubs but they do say that they are
Opening up an API for it so I presume we'll see some decoration points
So I am so this is one of those things where I am okay
With my smoke alarm not working with a hub
Mostly because
It has audio sounds as it is
Yeah and I'm I'm less worried I mean
Guess they're cool automations were like my Hue Lights can
Lexi
Get off my smoke alarm goes off my Hue Lights will
In a Flash reading
I can flick see through the smoke and I think that's me Nest protect has that kind of integration
Euphoric symbol
But I'm actually okay with
You don't want it if this then that channels that we can turn on you no water
My rachio sprinklers
I'm okay without that too
IIA don't have the sprinklers in
NB
It doesn't bother me if it's not if it doesn't have any other Integrations is just
It's a personal preference and end up speaking only for myself
I like to have everything in one app
Nice as it is I have a folder of apps and
Annoys the crap outta me that I've
I want to do this
Just a person
Yeah but for me this is not a nap I'm ever going to
This is truly just going to be something
Yells at me
Install on 5 years from now you on here
Front wheel
That's that's the plan
And so I got eight smoke detectors in my house
So I'm looking at
$260 to upgrade my entire house to smart
As opposed to eight Nest protect
$200 for two Leos but then I I'm still doing chirping and since
Play 3 night
Three weeks ago I was chasing a chirp
It's still fresh in my mind some kind of like
60 bucks more not to chase the chirp
It's worth it
It's going on my holiday listening
Christmas stocking
Yep so all right all the kids will get one
Oh thanks for the
Battery fad
Yeah
They're on sale at get russe.com
Homedepot.com and amazon.com
So
Keep an eye out and
That does it for the show
Stay tuned because I have a guest for you
I have a guest for you guys so surprising
No my
Our former colleague Chris Albrecht
He and I were at
It is that last week on the smart kitchen
So he and I are talking about
The smart kitchen surprise
That was run by a former colleague of ours as well it was like
Return to giga
Sarita talked about robotic team Acres
And
More on the Echo and we got a little
Earl Grey hot
If I ever have a robotic tea maker I'm going to program it
With your voice
So every morning I can wake up
Can have
Now you're scaring me
There you go
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
And we are here with your guests today who is Chris Albrecht
He was an MC at an event I was at last week called the smart
Kitchen Summit
Hey Chris
Hey Stacy
So it's important for you guys to know that Chris is a former colleague of Kevin's in mine from gigaohm
And currently he's at a startup called one hub
But the most relevant fact you need to know about Chris
We were both at this event
And the next most relevant facts you need to know about
Chris is this
Chris
Do you want a spark kitchen
I got to tell you right now I'm not really seeing it
All right
OKC
Kind of reinforced a little bit by this might get to Summit having said that
I want to make sure it's understood that I thought it was a great
Conference our former colleague Mike Wolfe put it on
He asked me to MC it and even though I'm not
Super interested in this market December they were a lot of great speakers that day
With a lot of interesting
Content
Yes sir this was like an all-day event with people from
Like the start of World that we've had on the show like the June oven people that drop kitchen scale
Tons of connected devices for the kitchen
Even some folks from Amazon
And then a bunch of people from like the Appliance in Old School world like that
The president of Williams-Sonoma was there
Guy from Electrolux and Jardin those the people to make the connected crock pot which is not refrigerated
I did not I was so crestfallen when I saw that I got so excited for you cuz I know for years you've been talking about the refrigerated connected
Crock-Pot there is a device you guys on Kickstarter called mellow
That is kind of like a Crock-Pot it is also refrigerated
But I feel like
It's probably not
Actually come to fruition
But
You know we'll talk more about that on another show not the show
I'll try to get the
People on to see if this
It's going to be a real thing
So
Back to the smart kitchen so that's what this event was it was really great
Lot of good content
First off
Smart kitchens we kind of talked about
What that means for
Increase you don't want a smart kitchen
What do you even think of when you hear the phrase smart
So I think it's also important to kind of set the scene a little bit my wife predominantly does the cooking just cuz she loved
Loves to cook
And she's a much better cook than I
And so when I tell her like oh there's is neat I love gadgets though so I'm all about
Oh what can we connect our up and what can we do
What's the neat little doohickey that I can look
I use my phone with
I want to bring that up and she just kind of looks at me and gives me the the cartoon blank blank
Like why would that to see why would you want that
So it there's sort of a
Because I know I'm not the predominant
Person in the kitchen for good reason
We pretended not we
We're not really a smart kitchen house
And but I
I love
Kind of the gadgets that are coming out they all just seem so expensive right now and I feel like I'm kind of rambling and I'm sorry
That's okay
Alright so
I think one of us
What I think of a smart kitchen I actually don't think of what
I don't think I know what you're saying
I don't think about a bunch of gadgets I actually think about
A kitchen that
Can actually help me because when I am cooking
I am actually performing
A bunch of really highly choreographed
Steps Ray time
Chopping a bunch of stuff I usually have fire going on somewhere
Usually
I am
You know trying to do like way too many things at once cuz I never like
Prepare everything all at once right that's
That's like just did
Pipedream for me
So
I'm running around and tossing things into the pot
Washington
And
I don't have time to pick up my smartphone because my hands are dirty and because
I got some things on fire
So for me that idea is I really want something
That integrates into my workflow and doesn't
Take me out of it
So I want
Things like the Amazon Alexa
Okay sorry the Amazon Echo
Where I can be like
Hey
Lady in the Echo
Set a timer for this amount
It happens without me pressing anything or going some
Place
I doubt she actually be Echo with some of the people talked about a lot during that day
So and actually it wasn't a device that
I am intrigued by and I went back and actually read your big article on it when I think it came out in June
Without that piece it came out for the General Public
Somewhere around Mayer
Right and so
The idea of to your point like
Not coming up
IPhone or an iPad
But the ability to connect
What I want to explore is the ability to connect
The echo
So
You can
What I want or need to find out probably
From you or other people I just how well the voice commands work
And how many steps you can throw in cuz I think actually
The echo was a really good idea for
Creating what you are talking about
I think
At this event and I don't think we really
Got into it as much as I would have liked
We have AAFES Silicon Valley types who are like
I have reinvented the oven for you I've reinvented a robot that makes tea
And
We didn't really talk about how this is going to hit mainstream
America
And how we're going to get this into her kitchen
Today
Right well and I think one of the things
I mean part and parcel with
That right is
Silicon Valley startup people are used to kind of this planned obsolescence
Upgrading your phone every two years upgrading your TV every 5 years
Write like
And when you get something big like an appliance
Like an oven
Which
You know comes with a house typically or has a space for it you know has a big empty place with wiring all set for
What I see when I see those interfaces under cycle what's going to happen when they upgrade
What am I going to miss out on
In two years from now when they're software does X
And they haven't
You know they don't
They don't support
Versions behind
You know what I mean
When when they add like a high-definition to my
My Smart Oven
I'm stuck on this
Standard definition
Are 4K you know what I'm stuck on HD
You can look at garbage
I need I need so many pixels for my turkey
So that's to that kind of like here's why I like
And where Amazon is going
Because between the echo
But also just their dash button
I think are so that I think that you could talk away into things
And as they expand
What they could be good for or maybe make them programmable
So and I apologize if this has been written about but if they had like a barcode reader
I think just a blank one
And you had a barcode reader
Since I was like oh this one is for
Pasta or this one's for this particular kind of bread
And when I get low I get the button
That to me is really interesting
Let's put a line of demarcation here
Cuz we've moved from talking about kind of Lake
Gadgets and food prep
And now we're talking about like
Food acquisition
Or I think we're also just talking about unifying the kitchen at a workspace right like making extremely
Okay so like to your point I think
Granite we are talking kind of or approaching it differently
You know where is you are looking at a for a director to kind of
If coordinate the symphony when you are creating your masterpiece
I'm looking for something that seamlessly fits in that I that I don't feel will be
Obsolete especially now when we're getting like these are all first-generation product
So I I think on the dash side
I think
Yes
You are you are so
That I think that is a really great
Solution
Both from a retrofit standpoint like
Awesome because
You know you paid for 99 you get this button and you get 499 discounted whatever it is that button orders
Amazon is expanding the program
There was a guy from Amazon. She was at the show talking
And he was like
You know our retailers are excited about it
We're excited about it
He said that
Anchor most popular button is the Smart Water button
And
People interact with that every 11 days
I got to get there electrolytes
Exactly I'm like
Jennifer Aniston made them do it
Emirates Airline
But that's also something really easy that like my son could use
He's going to get older and more sophisticated
But like if
When it in the next couple of years he likes
You know he likes dried apricots
And if he runs out of dried apricots then week
You know that's not something that I'm necessarily paying attention to
I mean even though I do want
But he could it's simple enough to where he could press it and it's not going to
You know require getting into my accountant
Get okra filling out a card and doing all the other stuff it's just something really simple
That he can learn to keep track of
And that's
That's awesome and Everyone likes pressing buttons actually the Amazon guy said that he gets
Biggest fan mail for the dash where
Couples are like
They they will email him and they will say things like
My husband says I have it he waits until I get home
Until we can both press the button
Together
That's how much we love this
Well that's
Once that you would do that and then to that you would write the guy at Amazon
And say
I don't normally do this but I wanted to tell you about
Your product to help me buy more products
So great
But
So I think
I think there's a couple things happen
I think one is impossible to imagine that Amazon could give you a dash for air
I think the idea of it being programmable
Is actually kind of
Smart and fun and I bet Amazon will do that eventually
They also have an addition to the dash something called the Amazon
Dash fulfillment service
And that is an automatic
It's for products and they build basically sensors in that connects back to Amazon
So without you actually having to press the button
Free things like
A dog food dog food in a dog food canister
It will actually
Automatically sends when that
Canister is running low
And sent you more
So another way that this kind of all ties together right is that I've been on a kind of a diet for the past few months
And I use one of those food that's not it like a special one it's just sort of like
Hey hey dummy eat less
You don't need to jam wheat wheat thins in your mama all day long right but it's it it's got a food tracker in it
Pet scan the barcode and then brings up all the nutritional information about that and then I input how much is a 8th of that particular thing
So as part of that I was eating a lot of eggs
And so for it the kind of tie in with my shopping list
Some kind of Amazonian shopping list it will go like
Oh hey
I noticed that your Fitness tracker that you've been eating a lot of eggs and
Based on you know
We think you might be running low based on whatever maybe I bought a dozen eggs and it seemed that I've eaten six of them by Wednesday
Then it could automatically add that to
That shopping list
Okay so this gets into something that
I am super passionate about most people probably are like
Which is
There's so many ways to input data into kind of
Look at the cloud The Internet of Things whatever
So you could grab that data from
Your Fitness your your food tracker
Right
Your food tracker app
But that doesn't
Get everybody in your household
It's probably not the best way
You could get it through like a dedicated device like I used to have the quirky egg
Minder
Stop it like device which actually literally counted how many eggs are in my refrigerator
It was a dedicated device for that it was the
Stupid money
You could also get it from like a camera in your fridge that like
You know A in food recognition that then exported it to a shopping list
You could get it from like you telling your Amazon
Echo
Hey I need more eggs
You see like
And I think what's going to happen is
Every family is going to approach this a little bit differently because we love having Variety in choice
So I think the key isn't actually going to be like
Iceman dating
How we want to do that it's actually going to be developing standards around
How we
Call an egg an egg
So
When we say we want an egg
All of these things will actually be able to recognize what an egg is and they can just like
Pop it in the list and then it's out of it
Does that make sense
Yeah absolutely in that the reason I was bringing up the like a food tracker thing is cuz my wife will often say is like
What do you want me to pick up at the store
And
What's the device for you
Okay it's called the haiku
Okay $50
Your son might even lie
So what you do is a refrigerator magnet
And it has a barcode scanner and voice activation
And then it also has Partnerships with both Walmart and Peapod
So
You press a button and we had
The CEO Haiku was our guest
We can talk about food all months
Because hey it's almost Thanksgiving
Yay see press the button
And you say
Add eggs
And then it goes to both and
App on your phone or your wife's phone
For Andrew Weissman rather
And she can either pick it up at the store or you can create a list in
Can I pick up curbside delivery at participating Walmart's or you can have it delivered from Peapod
I will check it out
Are there are two things at that we've been talking about that to think that we have kind of danced around here
And that I want to talk with you about specifically one I want to give you a call back
To the stupid expensive
And then to talk about platform
Alright feel like those are two things that are holding me back one lets the start was stupid expensive
There was a tea infuser that eforia
And
Man that guy was a TV evangelist
They it's a very Sleek looking very Apple looking they call it a Tesla tea maker
That device that supposedly makes a way better
A cup of tea
It'll know if they comes in pods
You tap it to the top
You dump your loose leaf in and then it knows from reading a pod what kind of tea it is what temperature the water
Beyond all this other extraction stuff
So it creates a more complex
Tea
Which sounds great I drink tea I mostly drink just kind of
Straight up PG tips cuz I love that black iced tea in the morning
So I'm not like a connoisseur
And I'm intrigued by but it's also it's
649 / 700 box
Like that's a lot of a big ass
For a device that dispenses tea
It is yet I actually met two people at the show who tried the tea and Ashley
Put money down and bought it
Oh yeah I remember talking to one of those guys I got one
Wow
He's like what he was breaking it down right like if I get seven uses out of it or if I get
You know a hundred uses out of it at seven bucks a t which I guess if you do
Kind of the macro
The big picture on it I guess you could do that but it's still just like
Wow that's a lot of money
The other that I'm I'm actually curious about it from my family might be worth the money as the coffee maker
Can you put green beans in
Not green beans
Not like string beans
But like you put
Yeah green coffee beans in
It roasts and Brews the coffee for you
Again
Customizing it to your particular taste
This is the cellar coffee maker and is not available
This is
This coffee maker looks like it was extruded from like a spaceship man that it's it's very pretty it has literally no
No button switch me that's a deal-breaker for me cuz you can only control it from your app but
And not like present-day spaceships
Spike future spaceships that are all
Cool looking I was going to say like mid-century modern spaceship
Beautiful design
Tamara 2001 right
So so yes
I am with you I am intrigued by the coffee maker as well I don't know how much it cost
Alright well let's hit your platform
I'm texting question and I've listened to your guys's show for a long time
Somebody even say I was there at the beginning
Thank you Chris somebody to say that you
Pushed us to start the show against our will
I did
Because I had to
Turn the Sala. Make it all about me
The platform questions so when I get to the Amazon Echo
Right or in this is something that you guys have touched on a lot which is what's going to communicate with
What other things what platforms are going to survive
And I look at the Amazon Echo and I think that's really neat and if I can connect it
Giganta like some kind of visual dashboard
I could see that being really useful at the conductor in the kitchen
But I don't need it I don't have Amazon music
I have Amazon Prime video
Which might be interesting but I don't really want that in the kitchen
And you know I'm
I'm on an iOS
Where does it get to with the do I have to create a separate
Ecosystem in my kitchen that Amazon between Dash buttons and Echo
Or we know how does this all tie in together
That
That fits into my life in a way that's going to stick around
Would that be be
Echo
Babe
That is one of those niggling awful questions
And if we're lucky
It will all just work itself out and work
If we're unlucky
Which is where we are right now
You're going to be stuck
Dealing
With
A bunch of devices
That only talked to each other
What's a lot of work
Or don't talk to each other at all
And
It's going to stink
And that's a terrible question I mean that's a terrible answer to your totally legit question in this is why consumers have not yet adopted
Like a lot of faces
Because I could almost see you like I can
I almost see Amazon being the echo system in my kitchen
Because it's also tied into my shopping
And then I almost feel like I'm going to have apple for my entertainment because I'm already
Kind of deep in with the entertainment
With the movies and stuff
In the living room
Through them
Okay so you got Amazon in the kitchen
Apple in the living room
And then
Lord only knows what is send the rest of your house
Well right now it's a giant mess
Okay well
I'm glad that we've settled you know at least two rooms and it maybe you'll have a magic
Bridge between
Well the one bridge that I do like the true play came out today that you play software update for the Sonos
This is why I love
My Sonos
And I'm really excited cuz they did they trueplay witch
Optimizes the sound in your room
Based on where you place the speaker
Until I ran through and did it this morning walking around my house waiting my phone up and down
With a microphone aimed at the speaker 2
Optimize my phone
Arabic crestfallen when it said you're serious placements fine
We made a couple of Minor Adjustments but don't worry about it
OC I'll have to go do this
Yes cuz I was really excited about this
So I will
Can't wait
I'm I will also go and download the true play update on my Sonos has
Maybe I will
Does it adapt
The speakers or does it tell you to place them in a better spot
What it just says place just because we're going to play some so I have one in the kitchen and then one in kind of living room area
And there different sections of the house
And
It says it shows you a video
How to waive your phone up and down
Sound and you walk around the room where you listen to the music waving your phone up and down in like a wave like a sine wave or whatever
And then it did
Use the microphone in your phone to adjust
The speaker settings
And
Yeah I buy Bentley my placement is just
All right
We'll see you guys we got
Chat on the smart kitchen and a bonus device review from Chris Albrecht so Chris thank you so much for coming
On the show today
Thank you Stacey is my pleasure thank you guys for listening and we'll see you next week on the Internet of Things
Podcast