Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham
I'm your host and co-host
Kevin tofel
So this week we have a lot to talk about we have some
New Gear from August
Connect
Really exciting stuff
From
What do we have
Company
Has been called the Apple
Home automation
And I have been
Playing around with my Apple homekit stuff
We're going to talk quite a bit about that
Because there's quite a bit to talk about
And I am dying to hear all that
Cuz homekit has been really slow to get going
So you want to do the news first
Where do the news really fast
I can wait a little longer
Alright so
For August
August
The Smart Lock Company it was designed with Yves Behar and and locks
Stick
On the inside and the outside of your door replaces your Bluetooth certified so
You just like walk up to it
It's pretty cool
I tried it Kevin have you tried it or seen it next
I have not and I would like to August
Is making
Three things so we're going to talk about three whole things August has a brand new lock out
Is home
Certified
That locks going to be on sale
It has a video doorbell that's going to be on sale and it's
Wired in
We're going to get to White
And
We mentioned this actually a couple shows ago because our buddy Dave.
Is so smart
Comes the FCC database
Agape
Keypad
It works with their lot
And that's going to be $79
And if upgraded their bridge if
If you want remote app
It's important you don't actually have to buy the bridge
If you don't want
Angie bought the video doorbell
Set up bridges for WiFi
Is Bluetooth only
But if you want WiFi access and you would want this if you want to
See like
If you want a remote control your life
Control your life
What Bluetooth only
So if you want ad that Wi-Fi you got to get either the bridge
Or the video doorbell
Both of those things
Trinidad wife
I could also see another reason for wanting the Wi-Fi if you have a bigger house or you have a large yard in your Outback
Bluetooth might not cut it
Would you want to
Open your door from that
I might if it's a pizza guy and I'm out back with all my friends
OKC and that's
So that gets to the second
Things in August
These Partnerships is called August Act
In August whole goal
Cuz you can't just make smart locks
In this world you have to have like a Grand Vision to transfer
Farm Society
So all his Grand Vision is to Lake make you feel comfortable letting people inside your home
Pizza dude
Or the FedEx guy
Or like a whole plethora of San Francisco tech companies like
Postmate sir Alfred a rinse
All these companies
People in Middle America are like these companies and what do they do
Delivery services
Laundry service
Courier Service
Dresses
You can basically
Tell ring your doorbell if you're like it's the Postmates guy they deliver anything
And you can just let them in your house
Give them that so you give them instant access with your August lock they can open the door
They can drop the costs are boss and then they leave and you
You can watch them go and then
Score
I got my cough syrup and I never had two egg get out of bed or maybe weren't even
Yeah I was just going to say this is the ultimate for lazy people because you not only are you so lazy you can't get cough syrup you have someone bring it to
You're too lazy to even open the door for Speed
Or maybe you're not
That maybe you're not well
Maybe you're not you're in bed
And that's why your
Right now actually said this is
By the time the stairs I'll be back but I'm on vacation right now in Florida and
I've had to I was on a roller coaster
Sister both times
This happened which is a shame
Because my doorbell my video doorbell
And
Afterwards I get the notice I was at the door so I couldn't actually talk to
While they were
Tell them to like leave it on the doorstep but like I got to FedEx packages sitting on my doorstep
Right now that I'm keeping an eye on
Using my video doorbell
It would have been really nice if I weren't on the roller coaster
And I had an August lock or some Smart Lock
I could let them
Access
I could be like
Hey actually just drop it
You know just open the door you got access
Just for like 5 minutes just open the door
Drop it inside
And I close the door and door lock
That would be amazing
But I was just
That would be cool refresh my memory the August lock this is the one that has batteries inside because
It has a mechanical mechanism to actually move the bolt
It does this fit
Over your dead body
This is not so there to kind of
Weather
The two kinds that I most commonly replacing are
You take your entire deadbolt lock mechanism
August is the other
Over the exist
So this is a little bit easier to install
Are people who are may be intimidated by take
Making a screwdriver
Screen door lock
Yeah I guess so it fits basically fits over
Well actually now I'm looking as you mentioned I went to their site
You still have to
Open up the the Depo mechanism from both sides of your door to install this
Yeah but it doesn't look complicated mean is not
Challenger install a deadbolt
No
No I have I have literally in back when we talked about homekit we're going to talk about
Installing yet another
So I install locks with
It is not
Yeah this looks this looks sad painless
It is very painful
When did they give you like
Did I think they give you everything you may need a screwdriver but I can't remember they may actually
I can't quite recall
Obviously I'm excited about the video part because that's what I need and really that's the only place on my door that I have
Room to actually put oneself
Video doorbell
And so the competitors here are going to
Ring ring just got money from Richard Branson
199 bucks
There's skybell
Also 199
Vivint offers one and then later next year so 2016 we're going to have something from
Chamberlain
It's called the notify
So every single one of these is a little bit different I'm hoping to do a
Comparison chart I should also mention that you
Pre-order all of August
Krista as a
Actually now but
The stuff will ship over the next eight weeks so the doorbell is actually going to be the last
Bishop and ask
Mid December
So that's August
Weight limit one more time
Only only cuz I just noticed it on their blog as you were talking about it's obviously I'm very interested since the
Precise
I see that they have their Smart Lock integrated into the Xfinity home app
It now works with Nest cam as of October 1st
They have an Android app all new
And I was 9 support soap
This looks like a this is one of my Christmas wish
Oh yeah and I should actually say so the homekit version of the lock there's a version 1
That has been out for a while
That's actually 199 they're going to keep
Keep selling it there's a new version
Does homekit certified
It's 229
So you may be able to actually if you're not really interested in the homekit part go with the 229 there's some slight
Mechanical differences to
About it so you know
Keep that in mind
Soon as I get my video camera
The video cameras
Two separate things
So if you want the lock and the video camera
You're looking at like
$400
The video doorbell is
So you can you don't need lockplus
You could just get the video
This is true I just have to see what it looks like cuz all them been too wide for the
Wood paneling on my outside of my door
I have seen what it looks like but I don't have the actual
That's okay we'll figure it out
You was you will see on the website
Go to the website
Get thee to the website
Okay
So
Other news will go zip right through this Savant which is the apple of home automation
They did Steve Jobs
Castle
Hi and they actually went a little lower into like last year
And by lower end
$200 /
Korean
Yeah
So
White Louis
They actually just teamed up with ammunition which is the Design Group that did
Beats headphones
EReader
This kind of comes together because the former CEO of Barnes & Noble is now.
CEO at savant
They have created a 499
Remote control
And
Tub unit
The actually looks pretty good and looks like it is going to compete with like the Logitech
Ultimate Harmony
Remote
And
I bring this up because
I said a lot of pretty good things about the Logitech
Gear
Which was kind of a hug for your hubs
And brought together all your abs
This is less a hub for your hubs but it does bring together all of your AV stuff
It kind of works with like
Your shoe lights and nests and other stuff and Saban is
Really good at the software behind
Home automation
So I haven't tried it yet but I want to try it
I'm going to try to get a review unit so I can try it
Because
This looks really compelling but it also
It does end and you're actually the
Probably the target for this because you prefer not to use your phone for controlling things
You have a remote with us so
When she's a remote
And
I haven't fallen in love
With any of
I haven't fallen in love with Alexa
It's a good solution but I haven't
Loft
So and like
I have a Sonos
Shoes
Roku's I have
Add a lot of these devices
And my husband
His ears perk up with a v
Supposed to
Sure we'll see so that's the Savant stuff it's out
It's 499 you can pick it up on their website Best Buy
Magnolia
Yeah so now
Are we ready Kevin
Let's do it
Tomcat time
Who killed
All right
So
Deep breath
I tested
A couple things I tested the Lutron Bridge
I tested the
Schlage sense
Lock and I tested the Hue Bridge
Are the Hue Lights so those are my three homekit things I tested all of this
On an iPhone
Set
So there's a reason I'm telling you all this
That's part of town
When I install I'll give you the individual
Does the Hue Bridge
I don't know if I'm actually going to buy it that's the first thing
I mean I am going to buy it because
Reviewer and I feel like it's
Get better butt
Like
Comes very little into my
Like day-to-day life because you already worked with
My Amazon Echo I didn't
Find talking to
To Siri to be better than
In talking to
Talking to my echo
And that's because
I don't always
Around
Because Siri on my phone
Requires me to pay
With one exception
And that is if your phone is plugged in at the time
Yes but the new iPhones
SpaceX as the 6s
Plus do support
A phrase for her to be activated
When they are not plugged in you do have to
A train
Her
To recognize your voice
Yeah sure
If a train blah blah to recognize your voice which is actually good thing so that way Stacy you couldn't walk into a room and say hey blah blah
And have your husband
Phone start doing things
It's all individually pair to your voice which is a good thing
But I agree that the limitation on all of the other eye
And iPads and iPod Touches
The battery plugged in or obviously you can double press the button
Yo bring blah blah up
So here's the second one
What is a bit of a smart alec
So
Yes
The echo
Is actually
Pretty nice is
Is a robot in the
Hurts when I say
Turn on the lights
If she can't find the lights
She just goes to the
And you get that like the next
Or sometimes
She's like I can't discover the lights
Or she can she says
Now blah blah
Must give you some running commentary like
Some of the lights don't seem to be interested in turning on
Or I turned on some of the lights
The other lights
Art responding
I mean that's useful information
But I prefer the
The Amazon Echo for this
Cuz you don't find
Which lights aren't
See I didn't know because I haven't tested interesting well that's kind of yeah I guess you have to start walk around your house then to see what lights are
Which ones are not
Exactly
So I'm not
It would be interesting if she was like
These are the following
Aren't you know she called them out
But don't she just like that but everyone's apple is getting better
Contextual conversations
There and I wonder if they could add
A feature where you just continued conversation and say which lights are not active
And therefore she could then tell you
But I don't know.
Obviously it's not that possible yet
I did try to ask
You can't get a little bit like
You can't have
Conversation
She will initiate following
Crustaceans with
Did you meet this one and you can see
So that is helpful
Where is
The echo will just be like
Total energy
Oh it didn't work
Try again
Blac Chyna
Okay
So that's the
The Philips Hue kind of
Experience I will also say the Philips Hue Bridge does not work
The echo yet
That is something they know about
Working on
But it broke my bridge connection
My bridge connection broke
And it does not come back
Broken Bridges are bad works with Nest work
With this
Bread the Philips Hue Bridge
Status still going strong
When I
Initially
My wing connection to all of my lights
But there now back up
So I don't know what happened
But it's
Yeah and that is it
Myinstants in that integration
Are working
Finish up that make sense
As as someone who has so many Integrations I was like
Let's see what's still up after
If not the reason I said it should work is because that's all cloud-based as opposed to
Hardware in your Homebase United csat some temporary glitches say between you know when carbon
And something else
In the house but the cloud services
The wink
In Phillips is actually cloud-to-cloud
Turn on AWS
Okay so that was that
Now onto the next
So the Lutron stuff in my house
Once again
I love it all the time and the user experience there the Lutron app
Brings in my Nest just because
It does not bring in
Mike Hughes or anything else
So far
I believe it would work with the elegado
Stuff the homekit Elgato stop but I could not find a way to bring it
Houston
Nor could I bring in my Schlage
Sense
Keep that in mind
I thought this was all going to be one big platform that
Everything just
I thought so too
Just checking
The other thing to know about
The Hue Bridge
Is if your Lutron light
Are attached
To the Lutron
Bridge they can't be attached to your Wii
That's it that's all you got and
It works
Great everything works as
You can schedule you
Do all the things
I had no problem Siri recognized everything so I haven't
Water MC
What that was
Creative Zone
Upstairs at downstairs series
Cool with that and I put the Philips Hue Lights upstairs and downstairs as well and so when I told
Sear
Until your name I'm sorry y'all it's okay
Okay when I told her to turn my downstairs lights off
She turned off
My Lutron stuff
And
My Philips
So that was a win
Yes the only unifying factor I had there
Was Siri there was no app where I go
I could pull all that
So that was cool on the light in front
Because I had
1 Commandos like
Everybody your downstair
I would have brought the lock into
And the Schlage sense lock
Has keypad
It has
You know Bluetooth it works you
You can go and you can go out with your phone
Very nice
Having installed many locks
Serious about security
Oh yeah I mean I've installed a lot of Kwikset locks
Can I install the Kevo
Which is made by Kwikset like has a lot of
Much sturdier
Lot more screws to screw in in
I was very impressed
Kind of a side note but if you actually care about the
I don't know how
Installing more screws makes it
So the lock is good the app
Yep kind of
Was not as pretty as some of the other apps that I've worked with but you know
It works
You know what you're doing
Pikachu history
Knock it and lock it
There's not a lot you can ask for here
I could not figure out
Houghton
Siri will unlocked
My daughter-in-law
Lock my door but I could not figure out how to tie it to anything else for like goodbye
I'm leaving turn off my lights LACMA
Right I tried
Well it could be that we were just really now seeing the first generations of the homekit devices and the plateau
Form I think apple is mainly focused on
Security of it and getting it to the certified chips into product Partners hands and so on
Usability wise I think it sounds like there's work to do
So I'd say we should give him some time
Lovely future
Homekit where when you add a device all you have to do is take a picture of a code on the box
Star on the device
So on the Philips Hue Bridge
It's on the back of the bridge on my lock it was on the instructions for the Locker on the back of the
So keep your instructions for the lock cuz on the actual back of the lock you've already installed the lock and soda
You don't really want to
Uninstall it to take the picture
Add apps to net worth
But it's very easy to add devices to your
I will give
There is no like
Password is saying there's nothing like that
But the core problem of having
A bunch of apps
And having to work with all of those apps
I still had to add all these apps
Phone
Siri
Figure out geofencing and all these things that I wanted to do with them
And only then could I can
Control limited funk
Ocean ride
I have a question and you don't know the answer that's fine we can leave it as an open-ended question for now
Do you still have an Android phone and if so have you tried using it with any of these new homekit products
I do still have it
My iPhone is for work
So my day today phone is
I have not tried
Well actually it's oh the Hue Lights I use with the Android phone and it still works
So the bridge works both ways
I have not tried on the lot I can't see why they wouldn't work
My point though is
If you
Karnataka iOS
Household
You're adding homekit
People who don't have IOS won't be able to voice control things will have to use the app
Well right now that's true like I can't voice control
My lights anymore
That makes everyone
My husband is very sad
And he actually
Refers to you
The echo
Supposed to
And
That is my follow-up comment
I was going to say I know I said this before
I would love to see two things happen
When I said before I know for sure and that is
The Amazon
Echo app
It's not called
I don't know why on IOS and Android you cannot use that app and your phone which has a microphone to actually be a
Voice controller
For the echo
And if they could do that
And some of these
Hardware makers
Let make the hugs in the end
And so on could integrate
Alexa voice services
Which is freely available now from Amazon where you can end table them to be
Voice controlled
Tumi
There's your underlying interface
And it doesn't matter what
You know phone you're using at the time doesn't matter if you're
If you are Echo is not in the same room as you and so on
Problem solve
Exactly because you know
Some kid has some valuable thing
The security
All of that stuff course people would have to buy new stuff
I mean you're going to have to buy a new Gear with the
Kit Hardware
And it cost more and it cost more because of the hum compatibility
Addition
Right
It's secure
But if you added something like the
Services
What would happen is
Then you can control all of the stuff at once because right now I have broken rui for home in testing
Because I had to take my Lutron lights off
What the wink hub
Right
To put it on homekit
Which doesn't talk
And now they don't talk to anything else
At least when they're on wink they talk to other system
I had to take the bridge the Hue Lights
You know that whole Bridge broke my access to
The
Amazon Alexa
So now like
You know I think I tweeted a couple nights
Mexico High broke I spent
An hour fixing my lights
I finally just
We had to go back to school
So I
I'm going to take this off as soon as I can because it doesn't work for us
It's terrible
As I as a user experience and I'll have to put it back on eventually
Again but it is it is no bueno
It's early yet like I'm not reading it off but I'm
I'm suggesting that
It's not going to be is
Appealing to as many people as
As if it were more open I guess it's the best way to say it
And it's a broken interface as it stands right now
I mean
Even
Okay
That's where it's at
I will come back
Because you know there's more device
I'm going to try out cuz I know that there are Apple
Locations in devices that are supposed to bring these things together
I just don't
Have them
I have a purchase the right devices
It will it still early days like I said they're going to they're going to
Continue tweaking this and making a better make it more interactive with
Various apps and services so
I am willing to give him a little bit of a past but right now what I have today is working really done well for all of us here I just wish it was
Expanded to again
No smartphone apps
All right
Well
That's enough of that
So we will stay tuned
For our guest
Today's gas
Is
A professor from the University of Illinois
Who is going to talk to us about using drones in both
Farming but more
Typically a little closer to home
And helping our parents
And grandparents even Asian place
And making kind of warm and fuzzy drones that will
Deliver medicines and you know active kind of our friend for people as they age
So stay tuned for that
Hey everyone this is feces
Higginbotham that I am back with the Internet of Things podcast
JB have an awesome guest it is nayyirah acumen
And she is with the University of Illinois and we are going to talk about a bunch of things
Warm-and-fuzzy drone
Drones on autopilot
And
Yeah
Analysis released basically two kinds
Making drones a little bit easier and more acceptable to a variety of people so
Thank you so much for coming on the podcast
Today angelface super having me
I am really excited
It's so
I originally reached out to you because I read about your research with helping people Asian place with the aid of
Robots
That were designed to be a little bit friendlier I think the idea is called Aspire and this is kind of some of your
Research would you like to talk a little bit about what that's
What about are you sure it's piyo stands for automation supporting prolong
Independence residence for the elderly
So this is an NSF funded project
This will give us the opportunity
To design robots without more friendlier
Acceptable by humans
Unbuyable but she'll be mean strong
Underground wallpaper
It can help us to develop a complete sophistic system
4 people aging gets
Play Project 8
Goodbye 2017
The population of boxing
Will docker
Which means that
The nursing homes of Assisted Living
Facility
Maybe understaffed
To support so many
Wypipo
And that's why we believe
Legends people have Technologies
To leave in their home longer independently
DevilDriver
Choose to
Stay at home
Then go to the store
Facilities
For example
Imagine a person who needs
Thule child for the medicine on a shell
And if he's hard
For somebody over 65 to do it alone
They can have a user-friendly tablet
IPhone with a push button launch a small drone
Fetch that message
Simpro Michelle delivery
To the person
Underground robot
So I really like this
Concept
Because you talked about
Kind of actual safety versus perceived safety
Intent of building out the system
I like the idea of fuzzy drones and making them kind of friendlier sometimes robots and drones
Look like the stuff of nightmares like
Scary
Scary scary
Yes
We are trying to distinguish
Between actual safety and procedure
What does it mean it means that people usually tend to be afraid of flying objects
While in reality they can be safe
So how to distinguish between actual sanctity
Proceed safe
12:30 fundamental questions I will project
Is that an interdisciplinary school we have a psychology Professor on the team with her professor from you
Human factors
Computer science club all together helping God
Technology to develop the Next Generation
Aerial aerobics
Design
To look more friendlier
And be less scary
Virtual reality lab of universe
Where Google immerse agent people into a reality world
So that I'm with the help of the biometric acquisition system
Will be measuring their heart rate
Skin conductance a lot about the parameters to do psychology professors
Things that are important
To have it handy
To judge on people's
Conception
About the flying technology
In close proximity
Fly a drone I'm actually kind of Highly stressed because he's are pretty expensive machines
I mean even at $300 I'm like
It's going to fall from the sky and it's going to break
So what is controlling the the Drone to go pick up the medicine bottle for example of
What's it's probably not
You don't my mom or my dad
No they will be autonomous which means that summer Cruise button on your
Tablet or iPhone
The drawing will be launched automatically thanks to its autonomous
Compulsive
It will be launched autonomously from your pool spots on it will go
Deliver definition
So it's a piece of
Software that
Can be developed today and there a lot of flights today
We are just trying to make sure that we can get them
Differently for their use
Indomethacin
Environment
This is possible
First of all
I would I would like to
Kind of project
Enjoyed it today our parents
Are scared of blood
Flying next to them
By 2030 2035
Does the projected timeline it's me who is going to be
And if I'm
They developing the technology in the law
Bennington 15-20 years most likely I won't be afraid to use it in my home
Okay so
I'm still trying to imagine these things flying kind of all around me
And I do find it a little disconcerting
Kind of walk me through a day in the life of
Someone who is aging-in-place in their home
Can I have this vision
I assume they're still someone who comes
I assume it's not totally isolated
I'm so
What time it is maybe I'm communicating with my robots in the drones are kind of acting as extension of hands or delivery
Before the robots I don't know but
What do you see
Your this is 20 years from now and you're sitting in your
Futuristic Barcalounger
What is what is life like
Marisol
I'm sure all of you remember the Cinderella costume with Cinderella
Helped by meissenburg to set up the house
Sosa's preparation for this
Fire project
Kind of related to that Cinderella
Cartoon
My students told me Cinderella could be held by my son
The bird then we can have it
As well have drones underground robot
Things to draw
The Cinderella movie
Imagine 20 years ago none of us had to sell
Today we'll have a few of those and we know how to operate them
Smoothly
And how much we can accomplish with the healthcare
The cell phone
And
Within the next
When to use the drones will be the self
Is the cell phones at today
The way I Envision is that first module Industrial Revolution
Using PlayStation 4
We'll have drones flying collecting data helping the farmers to take
Regarding prescription farming
So cold when they will be
Applying
Fertilizers that taking care of weave
I'm different types of issues that agriculturalists AC
This can help us
The technology into the hands of the farm as long as the farmer is using it
In his farm he will start using it in his backyard
People slowly gets used
To the idea of changing the drawer
2 something
Most friendliest brindle Mastiff
Why some people have to start to using
It's 11:36 in a research and understanding
I'm working with psychologist helps us
Stanford examples
How to design the
Passport
This'll be flying at home
Around obstacles
Golang test 12
Single perception check abilities
Seeing the void
Like YouTube
It should have a vision system
And old dad
Humble intelligence
That's going to be developed
Over the next ten
220 years to make them
Friends of people and not like
Karaoke
Check the round
Okay
So you're saying that
But kind of the computer like
PC actually
Little beginning offices little transition
Gradually
To the home and then
Our pockets but
You know to a warm and friendly place where it's the first thing we
Turn 2 in the mornings and probably the last thing we
We deal with
Since we go to bed
So actually let's talk about Farms
Because you actually in addition to your research
Which
Itsfunneh
Cool I like the Cinderella reference
Two mice for my favorite part of that movie
Actually so
Let's go to your startup which is called intelinair
And you guys are kind of building
You call it a controller
And it sounds basically like
It's autopilot it's a better form of autopilot
For drones for commercial aircraft and even for highly automated mechanical systems
That's what I'm building a highly intelligent also intelligent husband's birthday
And intelligent
In air rights
The objective of it is to achieve actionable intelligence from Able information with recorded
So
Did Justin is to have a drawing
It can be automatic
How to clean lungs from an iPad or iPhone by a farmer
Farm in the mall Stockton
Collect
I mean take pictures collect information about the Weeds about the water damage and various issues
The farmer may be facing
Take real-time decisions about
The need for fertilizing.
Pesticides and other types of
Treatments that the farm meaning
Health Department
Implement
Decision
So we know that
9 million people are hungry every day are dying from Hunger everyday
To save the world to solve the Hungary
We need to bring advanced technology to large farm
So that you know to have anyways
Otherwise
It would be impossible to
Feed the people
Which is the next 20 years
So I'll autopilot functionality
To give the farm
Butterfly
Consult
So that he flies easier Supply smoother he's not
Scared of unpredictable events
He can fly in high winds in inclement weather
How far away are we
Delivering a
Drone
That is so easy
I don't want to insult Farmers I'm like so easy to fly that farmer can do it her
Just power how far away are we
From delivering a drone that is
That capable
Into the hands of
I think only maybe
Google Toolbar very close
Launch their drawing
Skull
Purpose in the second or third quarter of nine
The other company
Names that have similar Solutions
Which Maybe
Partial information process
Right because when we are talking about
It would be capable of taking all the decisions
In real time do older in La cakes
This isn't a complex system to achieve that level of perfection
Have a complete system
It may take a few years
But
There are already two solutions
That address the problems
Possibly this may distinguish one or two weeks for example order
Be targeted for water damage Solutions I don't have everything on the top of my mind
How much would something like
That cost
OG ideas
To make it low cost and low coasters
Disposable in this is where the science
Take significant role
As a consultant acknowledges that can tells you to take any system
Blue loaded with all possible sensor
Making it
Super expensive so you can solve any problem in the most easiest way
Define to talk of lost cuz you my mom kids you're trying to make something accessible
To Farmer is an end-user you want to make it as cheap as pulse
There's a certain degree be on the way to Compton
Cheap because any of this advanced
Control guidance navigation just won't work.
Defensive
Performance level is required for old is Al Gore
To work but on the other hand and the sense of. Also getting cheaper and cheaper so we're hoping that
Eventually down the road
Technologist make cost around $500 or even less
Okay and so how much is it is it like $2,000 today is it
It like $5,000
Let's put it today today something for 5000
Can do quite a bit
I would imagine
Savages Enterprise to 500
Okay sounds
Alright
Thank you so much
For coming on the show today I really appreciate it I've learned a lot
And
Yes
Thank you so much for having mixed with a great pleasure
And that concludes this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you next week