Hey everyone welcome back it is the Internet of Things
Podcast
Did I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
Medicine
Kevin tofel and we have a great week for you hopefully know CES
Although I am going to do one quick plug for the Amazon Echo before we get to
Too heavy into things
There is we're going to talk this week about the
We're going to talk about the best Wi-Fi water sensors
Are actually the only two that we could find
Egg minder are the quirky egg minder because Kevin just got one
And
Hot new gear from Under Armour
And we also have a
I guess that will leave a surprise but
Near and dear to our hearts
So surprised it's a very good surprise
Let's get started with a quick
Last hopefully last mention for the Amazon Echo
Which
This week
Or actually news last week
Amazon announced that you can actually get your Kindle
Books
Read to you
From the echo
Which
If you're into that sort of thing
It's it's not like an after reading it
Noted that you're right it happened last week it was
Friday afternoon news dump kind of thing it happened to catch it right away
Read about it and tested it
It's there's some good and some bad here. Did you try it yet
I did try it
I didn't think I would use it but I like to read
Okay
And I love to read I read anywhere from one to three books or paper books a week
And
I'm not an
Audio
Book fan
I like
To read
However you know it's not terrible you is using as you said Alexis voice is not using a professional
Actor
Voice actress you not getting this
You know the feel of the
The tax
It's what she does okay I think
I mean
Voice kind of yours
Yeah but the nice thing is
Amazon audible I don't remember when they did that but I know they bought Audible
Sometime ago and if you want to hear professional
Read your books to you
Audible's great way to do it I forget what the subscription is like 10 $15 a month
Whisper book to use and so on
This is actually free
So that's was like I was like wow this is awesome even if it's not outstanding it's not going to
Really compete with Audible
It's free for some people who maybe there's vision-impaired people want to hear their books and don't
You know
We also noticed
Who also love to hear Echo talk so I agree with you
I have about 250 Kindle books in my account right now
And out of all of them it was like a handful five or six
We're not eligible for this
So pretty much like
Who's my whole Library I can just have
Bianca read to me
So I just thought that was worth noting for people who may not you know Amazon Echo newsletter
Every week
Which
Don't know
Somehow I'm not surprised redo
So we have an obligation to our list
So this week
We're going to talk about Ness
Because why we talked about this
Why are we talking over the New York Times
He has a sad
Is he wrote this week about our last week
About the
The issue that Gizmodo actually wrote about
Kind of during the middle of CES
Csb
Nest 2nd generation Nest out there that have an issue with
A software glitch that drains the battery
If you're not using
Wired power
So it's it's less than a percentage of the second generation Nest
And if you want to fix it it's like a 9
Step process
So it is not a simple thing
And I think some people if they actually fix it
Which
Problem this is coming on the heels actually if you know we complained about some issues with with my nest
And I don't know about you Kevin you said you might have an issue with your nest
Say about it I told you beforehand and I had some that mention I didn't have the problem but I just found out literally right
Thank you for the show
But I never got the software update that actually caused the glitch in the reason I know that is because
Got an email today from wrestling
Hey we've noticed that you haven't
Don't have the latest and greatest software on your nest even though I know it got it
Configure to get the updates
So it told me how to
Reset the nest
And that's a lot of buy back and get one or two of the steps that people are doing actually fix their nests
And I and I didn't know if you pushed the ring in for about 10 things that actually reset resets it reboots it
And I had to do that today
I will get the software update soon
I'm not
Worried about having a battery problem because
I have wired power to
Got it
So there's a lot to unpack
I want to start
Products physical products
Is hard
I don't think that could be interesting
Because
Has a really good job
You know we can say it we can know that the nest protect had you know
It was recalled for a while
Because of the whole waiting in the air thing but
You know I still buy Apple products that you know have recalls associated with them because
Malfunctioning or
You know
Your battery
Good Hardware products
Is really hard
So in some ways I'm like
When you add
Computerize parts
Anything you make them infinitely more copper
Located
And so
This is a problem
Yeah and I don't think you're giving Nest up a pass here I think what you're trying to say is
You know this happens to various products any products
Like this
Faces so many challenges so and I agree with you on that
So I think as an industry
Overall
We've got to figure out because Nest problem
In what state is stuck to someone's wall
People like I used to forget about me
Right
Deal
With a thermostat
You don't think about it
Think about when people
I was at my parents with
They're just like
Why does it have to get an update what's it doing what's it getting what's the changing
Kind of a nerd
To that now
I'm sitting in my car
Which happens to be a Tesla
And happens to have a lot of software associated
And
I was like
What the heck
And I'm trying to troubleshoot that and then my phone for some reason was also
Not working
And it's totally Verizon provides the radio in my
Either I am liking a cellular black hole right now or I'm having
Some sort of
Weird
Issue
It was so frustrating to me because like
I have two things in my life that
Phone usage
Find
So we have all these things around us that are just getting kind of
Squishy
And I think the bigger picture here is that we
We have these great new devices
That are solving problems worth making things
Better
When we come to re and we come to rely on them
The point where
You know you expect your
Your heat in your house to be on when it's cold out and Sonic and Nick Bilton
He woke up to it was like 64 degrees in the apartment and the baby was crying probably because it was cold
And he was like
Distance versus make life easier for us
But anytime you add complexity you run the risk of
Essential making things worse
So
It's a challenge is a challenge so we've got to figure out
Is there a is there a solution here I don't know
Is it lambasting
You know I don't know if it was on the front page
Complexity
From a breeder formula
Listener this person was asking about
Wi-Fi sensor
I do not want to hug
And given Kevin you probably can't blame them
I was like
There's there's a couple issues there we found two
Using smart home DB
The D-Link
Water sensor which retails for
About 55 to 60 bucks
Depending on where you go
This works
Any Wi-Fi not just dealing
Connectsense
Water sensor
Which is 150
Michelle
For me
Similar reviews I was looking on Amazon I haven't tested these out
Personally because I
Have I think I have
A cluster of hope so I use Zippy and Z-Wave hubs
Just to clarify these are water
Detection like water leak sensors
Water leak sensor so these are things are going to stick
Under your sink spider
Water heater wherever you want
3 weeks in my house
Since I moved into it
Fun fun
Actually ever been
Where
I've had a leak
Theoretically
My mileage
Sneaky water download sensors aren't
So
The challenge with Wi-Fi sensors
Is because Wi-Fi is such
You have to plug
So
They all are little funny
Play that's why most of the water sensors
Use a hug
Is because you need a zigbee or Z-Wave or some sort of
Really low power radio
So I'm just giving that to you guys straight
So even if you're like Wi-Fi
You may want to
If you're going to really like sensor outfit your home
You may just be Leo
I'm just going to invest in the hub
Sehrazat
Makes sense
And it's ironic that you had this topic on the show notes today because I just put some plants in the house that I want to get some
Soil / water sensors
And how goes into my
System here
And they're not cheap either I mean
Achievement
Heartless the parrot flower power
Looks nice and I think it cost
$60
I mean that's just for one
Potted plants
You know that's that's not cheap I saw the plant link
Which is a much smaller sensor and the center itself is only $35
But you do need
Plantlink hub
So if you buy the Hub and One sensor it's like $79
Anthony traditional sensor because you can have up to 64 sensors at the base station
Level is $35 I told little bit less expensive overtime
It's not cheap I
I wish it was that either I mean I know I can buy a nod non-connected one you just like a
Give me to plug in a thing and it just reads the soil over time and when it's done you throw it away disposable on
It's a lot cheaper but
You
LASIK
I know I know that you're right that's exactly what I'm doing now because
I'm checking that the top inch of soil and both plants right now bye-bye feel so
I can live with that. I'm not going to spend I don't think the money is just just just too expensive
Yeah
You could try those watering stones
Wiring stones
Yeah they like Whiskey Stones what are you do with the are not buy them from like The Container Store like fancy
Pipe catalog
They're like little glass globes that you stick
Water in and then you cook them in the plant and they're supposed to water them slowly over a. Of like a week or two
So this is good for people who travel more people like me or forgetful and then you just said
Reminder for like
Every every two weeks
I might do that. You know what though I also saw alveron instructables for
People have the time to Tinker you can actually use an Arduino
Pacific sensor
And if you want him put little LCD on there so tell you exactly how much moisture is in there
And you could use that and the parts were about fifty bucks that's
It's actually less than a lot of course
Download the source code know what you're doing
There you go alright well I look forward to
Going to make an Arduino sensor
Did you something
Equally silly
I think so
You purchased
A product
Once retail for $60
Yes and now goes for a
I'm interested
I didn't
Wicked Amazon I just
Saw something for $15 a night and I spent $15 on the quirky egg minder
You and your first question I told you before the show is
Would you mind at 4
Because I don't want to take my ex out of a container in Stick
Sure sure so it's so it's basically a plastic egg
Crate container
That holds a Baker's Dozen plus 1 to 14 eggs
Two dozen eggs at a pop
And there's a little sensor inside each
Holder for the egg
So there are 14 little sensors
When you take an egg out it notifies the Corky app through with my case wink
Bet that egg is gone
And now you know how many eggs you have it all time
The other thing it does there's a little blue LEDs next to each
Egg
Soldier in the crate
And it lights up and says this is the freshest egg
It says so in the app as well
Physically as you put the eggs in it
It's going to tell you which ones you put in
First
First in first out basically in and tells you I didn't buy it for that cuz we go through exit so quickly I bought it thinking
It's nice
If the whole family knows how many eggs we have in the house
At any given time in case we need them
Wow
Would you recommend to others
Should have said
Well I think
If you want to know at all times how many eggs you have in your fridge I would say yes but with caution and I'm curious if you
Saw any issues such as I'm saying
First of all the setup was kind of
Looky it just didn't seem to want to connect
Add to my Wi-Fi network in the way you do it
You actually use the Wink app
You add the quirky egg minder to the Wink app to the wink Hub through your app
And then you hold your phone
Face down over a sensor on the quirky egg minder and it flashes lights and that's what tells it
What
Wi-Fi network in the password is
And took me like 10 tries to get that working for summer
Did you have that issue I did not have
A problem
Yeah but that was only one of two challenges because I'm looking at the
App
Are the Wing Cap right now and I'm looking at the egg minder and it shows me 14 little eggs in there even though I know three of already been used as of yesterday
So it's not
Either it's not refreshing
It's not refreshing or the sensor isn't just seeing that there's no egg in those three spots anymore
Sure
I know one thing about this because of my
G with the Wi-Fi you know it's kind of a wifi
How much Wi-Fi signal is need to get out through the fridge does it only work on the doors open
I'm thinking it just
Dinner the Faraday cage as you would have talked about once before
Can you close your app
I've always had to close out
And that's all what that's all about
Supposed to
Yeah
I just did that and reopen the app and all the eggs flash like they weren't there and then all the eggs and out back there
And they're all there even though I know they're not
This is definitely it don't bite
It doesn't do it
Function well it could be because I'm connected to a Wi-Fi network with a router is on the opposite side of the house
And the only reason I had to do that this is another
Potential gotcha
The quirky egg minder only works with 2.4 gigahertz
Wi-Fi network
MI
Am I Google onhub
Kind of merges those to the 2.4 in the five
And I It wouldn't connect to that one side to connect to the further away
Router
So there challenges here
You know you have to know your instructor at your house to really know who's going to work for you
Interesting point to make about connect
Devices because I know that my Roost
Connected smoke alarm
I have another couple devices that only connect to the 2.4
Yep so
Daddy is at done because of its cheaper cheaper chips
I don't know I pay extra that work with 5G network is my reliable
Which is not far from the fridge at all
And that's a very future
Design right there
Watch investigator
Alright let's see
What else
Oh I know what else Kevin
Json testing out some excited
Kevin you've been reviewing everything this week I love it
Sit back and take a vacation
Quotes about your other
What we mention this
One or two shows back I think two shows ago that
Under Armour has a new
Help kid in a box I connected a bunch of connected devices in a single box called the UA
Healthbox
And it was announced at CES I actually had it before so yes we can talk about it
And even when it launched at CES
I couldn't give a final review because the UA folks told me
We're going to have additional software update you're not going to final software for another week or two
So that means basically we couldn't really go into detail about it until this week
So what can I tell you was just to recap what's in the box
You can have wifi-connected scale that works with up to eight different people
You get a
UA band which is designed by HTC actually HTC Desire
Scale as well
Bose very well-designed products working very well for me
You also get the UA strap which is a heart rate monitor that you can wear if you'd like
Addition of that
Outside the box I also received
A pair of Gemini 2 speedform connected
Sneakers running sneakers and I've been running in those quite a bit since I've had him
That's where we
They have a sensor inside a radio inside battery inside
You'd never know it from looking at it
The trends will wear out before the battery is what these folks tell me
I put about 40 miles on the sneakers
Annies automatically
Sync up their data into the MapMyRun program which then sink
Everything up
The other devices into the UA record
App
And I am
Yeah
In the Box there's a scale there's a band and isn't there an activity tracker
The band is the activity tracker
Oh wait
That's correct
There are three things in the box which is $400 if you want to buy them separately
Just real quick the scales 180
The band is 180 the heart rate monitor
Yeah if you want that and then you can add on if you want somebody else in the house to use the
Band
180 they cannot Abandon All ties into the same system
So it's
Pricey
But I like
What they put together here and the key is
I think
The key is you a kind of bought their way into
Having a big audience for this because they purchased the MapMyRun and MapMyFitness
Software
Platforms
Last year
Faking like a hundred and thirty million
Users of their platform to track nutrition and Fitness
And then added more
Wearables that work with it
And you're
A fan of those MapMyFitness and MapMyRun products
You'll be happier the shoes just sync automatically I mean you can go for a run with nothing on but the shoes walk
Close hopefully no bands no phone no nothing
You didn't have to turn the shoes on you just go for a run
An automatic retracts of NSYNC the data into the MapMyFitness stuff
Which is all viewable in your dashboard in UA record
And that my fitness also pulls in your data from other
Ticketspice
It's one of the best ones out there for tracking
Suit
That would be great
Is pal
And they're all kind of
USA map
In my brain
And you you mentioned tying in those those abs tie into with a lot of other devices as well which is fine if you want to use us
Jawbone whatever you want is fine but here's the thing to UA record app which is your record for your health
Baptizing all that scale data the Band-Aid
It works with your but I can link it with
Apple Health Apple watch
Connect powered by Garmin Jawbone
Fitbit Suunto Misfit Wego polar
Dead bug and Believe by Sports Authority
So if you don't want to use you a apps you don't need to order devices
But I will say that there's an integration that works really well because
Not that far from Apple your butt
They own the hardware and the software
All right hand
Yes I I keep getting insights from watts and although today's was really weird
Today's word something on lines of
Out of all the other people in your age group using map my or MyFitnessPal
They have three point five friends
Am I good for that
Last Bachelorette
And then I get that it wouldn't all the other apps that have used I appreciate the social aspect because I put my
Running out there
You know on the line as they say in the
The Internship
I have actually run and had real-time geolocation of my races
So that people could see me and why not to let people continue because I wouldn't want to let those people down or actually help me
So now there's a lot of
A lot of aspects to that so
I think you'd like the band I know you've learned some other band Stacy and this one
It's comfortable
It measures your steps and measures your sleep it does both those automatic it was a beautiful thing
As the time has alarms the silent alarm
It's got a heart rate monitor built-in at checking your resting
Heart rate right before you wake up or at the end of your sleep cycle
I got a ton of great data and I
I've lost several pounds I reduce body fat
I am running more because of this granted I'm doing the work yet
UA health kit
But
It's working well I'm getting all information I could ever want
Okay cuz I'm actually in the market
Core Fitness
I would recommend looking at least at the band even if you don't buy the other things and
The reason being you just said you had lost some trackers and they concert a lot
This
I literally don't take off at all except when I take a shower
And when I took a shower I usually put this on the charger
And it's last
5 days on a charge and it only takes 30 minutes to charge so it's never
In a place for me to lose it so to speak
Nice okay
Well I'm at
Guess who Our Guest is
Who is it
O'Malley
I know that guy we all do
Piece in the New Yorker that everyone was talking about
About what was it
Infrastructure
And how
We are currently in this era of how companies
There can only be one it's like the Highlander era of company
I'm very curious how that plays out with
Consumer devices and
The smart home in the internet of things because
I know a lot of companies believe that especially if they're selling Hardware
But I'm curious how that's actually going to play out and sit so mad I are buddies he's been my mentor he great
Decided he would talk to me about this so stay tuned
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and with me is this week's guests
O'Malley
Hello how are you doing
I am great Stacy Happy New Year
Happy New Year
Happy posts
CES
How old is a venture
A true I'm a partner in
I will see I was be escalating you I'm so sorry that I had to other show this week
Typical
You wrote
What about
A really good
Story of The New Yorker
How
Startups
We are Becoming monopolies
They're doing this because they have this infrastructure advantage
I'd love for you to kind of give a quick summary of your article
And we're going to talk about how that may or may not apply to the internet
So my theory is that there is a new
Which applies
Pretty much any languages in the
Connected space
So
Salute goes like this
The service
Infrastructure
I logged into
Dada
And that Loop
Keeps going
More data you have more intelligent
Are you allowed to them becomes and from Dad
Your service becomes more useful to the people who are using it
Like this is what
Google did so effectively this is what Facebook did so effectively and
I think I see you were doing this really really
Aggressive user of uber I know
Need the predictive nature of uber is pretty scary
But it's also pretty nice because they
Populate my
My Uber VIP
You know. 15 to 20 drivers
Who I actually seem to like to give
I started eating more often than others
And that is actually a pretty
It's a deeper relationship not just
Read the service but also with the drivers themselves
I know their names
I know how they're doing
Is United member to ask the questions that need to be asked
Next porch light
Uber the dog
Like them trying to make any
Interference
Right it's not creepy it's just a very
Are there drivers like waiting outside your house
Remove
Them knowing that at 9 I need to go to
Is pretty scary
So we got this virtuous cycle
Am I question for you
Because what I read this was like this works for internet services
Uber obviously
It's a real world service
Does this work
Physical devices in the Smart Home
Because
There's there's a huge difference here with consumer devices
I have to spend $250 on a nest
And I know with like
Nest cam when it was Dropcam they actually did very well
Creating is virtuous Loop
By having enough
People
Submit kind of
Data to them that they were able to create
Facial recognition that helps make a better service
And they did an itemized to that sort of thing
So in some ways this is true they had enough data to create a better service in
People loved it so can you do this with a physical.
Okay the number one thing I would say on that
We haven't seen the device
Make which we make this
But we don't love them enough
Laura
Scale
Yeah I don't know how many nests are out there may be less than a million
February 1st I'm hoping we'll know
Alphabet
What's number
So
That's not
Enough
Nest in the market
Wacky hat
For them to have
Say
Stockbridge
Which can become more useful to
From from that standpoint you know it still radio today's for
Internet of things change
So we're looking for
Do you have a sense of how many
We need to have in the real world
Apple was smart in
Nina badric together
Homekit would be very very
Good way to move forward
Pumpkin cars
The ability to provide identity
Store and manage data
And create a more personalized
Expedient
And have the infrastructure
For Independence
Small
In The Internet of Things
So far it has been
I miss it's not even a hit in the mess
Is a complete mess
Same goes for Google right Google can do exactly the same thing
Amazon could do exactly the same thing
Unfortunately
I'll be doing
Like any of these companies
You know look outside their silos
So from my standpoint this is an opportunity for somebody
Maybe Facebook I don't know but
There is an independent service provider out there
Who can you can capitalize on this
Opportunity
Individual
Device makers are still so small
And they don't have what it takes I don't think
Samsung has water takes what example with the SmartThings
United status
It seems like. Quite a mess like I stop using it
And you know and then there was blank which was a good idea but
Never really took off until
But you know the Phillips we don't know they have their own Hardware agenda
Everybody has their own agenda
And nobody's getting mumps
Scary just
Anyone get scared going to be
That you will get the loop right
Okay and
You know it may be that it
Because he's our devices in homes
And there's about a hundred and
20 million homes quote-unquote homes in the US just in the US
I am curious if that's even enough
Scale
Yasso
I remember
You and I talked about
Last year
About
Like I want to connect to
Annapolis
Play like it is such a basic building block
Gmail
Every little gadgets in your house
Quasi connect
Right
Quasi internet
The Baxter
I still think those guys have the right off
Somebody
Who can make
Really affordable power strip
Is it really nice
Openstack with people can plug into
And that becomes
Building blocks for
For what comes now
I think I still feel
$15 product is the right entry point for Internet of Things
Hello Manuel
They got to get scale before they can get that
Cuz
The power strip you're looking at Wi-Fi and a Wi-Fi chip
In one of those like
You're going to add $5 to like
Building materials and then
No but I think it's
It's like you look at $5
You look at
You know you have all these new like microcomputers which other
Take Micronor you can call them Nana computer the same tree
Which are coming to market now
If you have those and you can send for less than $10
I think there is still room to make a smart intelligent
Power strip for like less than
$15
What are the key for that is to have
A stack which is more
And innovate more programmable for other people
Do you know
Piggy back office
I took
I do look at people like Belkin have their power strips but
You know they don't have a stack or they don't have any
Intelligent verification
What to do with that
Innocent opportunity I always think
The most basic thing you can do
With the internet of things in this is the power strip
The five belkin.com
Okay you know
Just open yourself up to all of the guys out there trying to build a 15-2
$20 power strip giving you
Call Sol
With that in mind
In your role as a as a VC
What do you think right now given given the FourSquare just had a Down Round given
Bet there's been some consolidation already and kind of
I guess it was in The Flash sales Market
What do you see coming into 2016 for the internet if they
I think that is too big trends with
Are happening right now one
Is the Asian manufacturers
Quickly imitating some of the more successful products
And offering them
To turn parties AJ
The old
School companies which resetting power strips
And become enough
Connecting
Power strip
Satellite
We saw the rise of the
That is the Wi-Fi routers and stuff like that
So that is a huge Trend which is going to
Suck out any prophets left in the market
I'm a little worried about that
From from a startup perspective I think that is a
What is enunciate
Carbon monoxide.
In my opinion
Ain't nobody sees it just one day just got you though
And boom
You're gone
And the server Market by quantity and
Are those guys just
Took away everything from
Some of the more established
He saw the same thing in phones and we have seen that in a turnip
Is happening really fast
Situation
II
Isave
I think the biggest challenge remains
Very few Internet of Things companies are gone from
You know they go from 0 to 25000 customers very easily
But it's very hard to go from 25000
To 250000
And 250,000 to like 25 billion side view
Dollar girl challenge
We don't know how big it is
Play the biggest
Internet of Things company
You still don't know how big it is
Gun show
It's pretty big I mean
It's been around for a while and living selling
But we don't know
Right
That is a challenge nu-vu
Have gone past the 25000 Mark in
You're over
Unit 2 words
Marching towards to
250000 users
Our buyers are accounts whichever way
You want to calculate it
I think you're on the right
That's pretty good project free
Yeah I would think nest in probably a Philips Hue
Are probably the biggest connected
Products in Phillips
It's kind of its own Beast because it is
Phillips
So
I understand a little bit more presumably hadoop support products
Weibo has 1.5 million users
Which is
A lot
They're actually struggling
And their own by Falcon which
Sounds a lot of physical product
Kinecta Prada
Not so much
I think so I don't know what
The challenges of Belkin may or may not be my view is that if
If you
Have multiples
Use like
You know they have
I mean it's it's very hard to be a very focused
Connected device company
What's a separate company
Running independently as a
Tech company and not as part of Belkin
I bet you they probably would have
Way better cracker
Action did they have right
So we're calling for a spin out of WeMo
You're calling first.
I was seeing a Toyota Cruiser
An independent company that would have
Way more
Controller test
Alright so what are the biggest challenges you think for the
Not just a smartphone but just for the internet of things because I feel like this year is
This could be a big here at CES
I saw a lot of big companies coming into the space
We can call it taking a startups ideas
A lot of the ideas coming from startups we're really just like hey I've got these awesome sensors I'm going to connect them in the
Then I can do amazing things with her
Which
Yes that is a novel idea but it's also kind of what technologies all about
So
Dallas.
You know Procter & Gamble I've got you know
Sleep Numbers
Coming head and connectivity to their mattress in a way that
Smaller companies have already done
So
What do you think this year is going to bring us
I think the whole thing really reinforces when I was talking about is that
Because
It's so much
Easier for
But the Asian
Manufacturer
Replicate
Successor of someone
New startups
And offered to
Do the old established brands
The time for Stardust do exist in isolation
Be Market leaders is much much shorter
So if you have a product
Which is ahead
Then you can't really miss your shipping.
Miss your
You know your growth projections like you have very little room to fail.
And that's that's a bigger challenge
My prospective mm
16 and still going to be very much like you.
You highly focused
Point Solutions
Which offer an ongoing service
Ben sexy
I can't say more so just to be clear we are investors in a bunch of companies which offer
Services on top of that like Unilever
Adidas Fitbit
Investors in Peloton
Which is a connected biking offers
Service service riches like
You get biking lessons on
Cream
Which is attached to Bala.
It's
That thing you look at companies like
You know we have ring which provides
Disservice on top
Beauty Masters in narrative which provide storage and
You know I like that image processing services on top of that
That's how you're going to
You stand out you're not going to stand out
By just selling pure Hardware
So the service has
And service my mean
Service for China subscription attached to it
Call Manda people hate
Subscriptions
No I think subscription revenues are the right way to value a company now
Especially in this Hardware space for Jesus
The margins are so low
Okay I look forward to buying my my 50
50-odd subscriptions for all my kin
Connected devices
Again that's enough
Trinity for somebody write somebody
Hello Cupertino are you listening
That's why I tell Amazon
This is your Market you have my credit card
You have all of my data
Let me just
Hey you to manage all of that
Let me just give you like
We buy everything from you
Please
Or in your case
Apple
No I'm I'm a big Amazon
What's a Catholic
Less and less share of my daughter
It's not doing too good
Job
Easily taken more
More dollars for Federal Express for music
Or what if it was for
E-commerce or stuff like that
Done a good job. By the way yesterday I use instacart
And I paid you.
Pictures like
It was pretty seamless
I did not do anything
Nothing just
You know like touched
My community
And so I
That's kind of seamless I think
You know I wish Amazon
And afterward not in a fight with each other in fruit makes life so much easier
See there you go see and I buy all my gadgets through Amazon so if I could just
Or like when I'm talking to the echo
I could just be like
Oh here do this
That would be amazing again
Shameless
Echo is so racist
Yes, it doesn't it doesn't
I just like Siri I mean
Seriously
Billion and a half people how can you be racist against
You know what
I'm going to say
They should train it better
Yeah
How to understand what I was saying
It's it's true that that's inexcusable
And that just is so much harder
I can be trained
No no nobody can fan use
Dime just buy my own personal yes you are
Awesome bull before we let any more of my secrets go I'm going to say thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you Stacey for having me
The Internet of Things podcast