Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Cohoes
Kevin tofel
And today we have amazingly huge news
We've got reviews of the Amazon.
And some Integrations that
We start a review of the osram lightify switch
The big news of the week which is
Nest shutting down the revolv smart
Hub
Later
Actually it's Nick
What's my next turn
Next month
Because Kevin
Works for Google
Annies nest
We're just going to call
Google back in 2014 when they bought
Revolve
And so
What's happening there is
Let me just clarify actually
Alphabet bought Nest but Nest itself but revolve correct
And I only said it because it's kind of like a separate
I think there was told her to be
Beaver Run autonomously
Yes although what we found a couple weeks ago in the story from the information is that
When next fight dropped
That was actually a bill that was brought to them by the Google
Corporate development team
Which
You're like
Beaver Falls steel happened
In October
Which is several months late
9 months after the deal closed
And that's almost
2014 A7
Yes. Ness pot revolve
Gotcha
So
And actually at that time I thought they said
That they were no longer going to sell the hardware
So what they said at the time I went back and looked at my stories cuz
Remember you cover it
Yeah well okay
We said what
No I guess not
People have evolved devices the service will no longer be available as of May 5th
Revolve app won't open in the hub won't work that's
I'm reading that verbatim from the revolve block right now
So that's what happened there is a tizzy
And a very
Legitimate sense
Totally understandable sense of frustration from users
To purchase the revolve
Which I thought had lifetime service guarantee number one
And it did have a one year warranty but since has been sold in a year I guess that's all at the window
Well
Yes so what happened was
It was $299 for this Hub and at the time it was going up against things like SmartThings which cost about
Important notice
When it was sold
They said
Rapala / nest
They said they wouldn't update the product
They also said they wouldn't Provide support after a year and they also said
Because of a 1-year warranty at the time
You and I on our podcast
Prior to this one said that you know that probably meant you shouldn't buy a revolve anytime soon because
It was not going to be updated or kept up
No time
Did they say
Hey
Yeah that's essentially what's happening is the back-end services
Are shutting down leaving these
Hardware
Deaths that people paid to 99 Ford
Arundel
Useless because
It's tied to that service
And
Again I'm going to read from
The site
We're pouring all her energy into works with nest and Incredibly excited by what we're making
Unfortunately that means we can't allocate resources to revolve anymore and we have to shut down the service
People basically a hardware that's just no longer going to work there's no
There's no alternative service don't get into
Nothing has been said about
Do you think Services being open source or anything like that
So
If you have one of these it literally will not work after May 15th
So consumers
Correct that means
When you bought the platform back in 2014
Or late 2013
Because it did exist then
You were probably like
Crap I just spent
You know $300 on something and it lasted me for you know
Not even
And I can understand me so I can understand people's frustration with the news in the development here but I can also understand why people
Chose revolve back that even though it was more expensive
Is if I remember correctly
Wasn't that the how the heck pretty much every single radio
It had every single radio and when I did I did a comprehensive review of smart home hubs
Christmas of 2013
Was actually one of my favorites
It had good software it had great pairing
It it was a really
Good product
Don't know how well it sold
It was only on the market for a limited time
Was expensive
And so when Nest bought them
It was kind of like
That's a bunch of good Engineers from Boulder Colorado
Bricks for the base ship
So I don't know how many people are upset
My hunch is that it's
Probably not as many but
It does bring up
Really important issues for the in
We talked about a lot so it's so funny I mean I hate to have bad news
Reflect back on the themes that we've been harping on for the past month or two but
We haven't talked about this we talked many times about
Cloud vs local when it comes to Smart Homes and IRT
We talked about holding devices hostage
Instalok
It's a shame that something
Tangible had to happen to resurface these discussions but they have to be resurfaced because
There are still challenges that have to be
Resolved
It was a big economic challenge actually we don't talk about
And I
We probably should
On the side of the nest folks
Supporting
Project with limited users
That is not making additional Revenue when you still have to
Buy server infrastructure in dilute and engineer or possibly to I don't know how messy it is on the back end
To it
Is expensive and
It doesn't really justify the cost over
The potential life cycle of the device in that gets into that disconnect between
Installing something in your house and expecting it to last for 10 years and being a business whose like
Oh crap I'm not going to want to search
Forever oh my God what did I do
Yeah because it becomes a numbers game what's the bottom line
That's that's frustrating for
Consumers for you know any of these products because
It now reaches the questions of you know what other services may go away to render things
Useless you know I mean this could apply to cars this
Reply to
Tea party Lee everything is connected
So there was a wonderful recode story talk about Nest only pulling in 340 million of Revenue
And not meeting its like 500 million dollar a year
Targets
I really don't think the
You don't nest
Google would let Nest become little
Warts on your wall right
You know it's true
If you Woulda thought that's what happened to revolve either right now
This is exactly why
And I do I have a lot of doubts about companies
And they're their thought process around this very few companies I talked to have things like
Oh we got an escrow account for our software
In case we got a business or
AR
Some sort of money to
To keep operating our cloud
If something happens
I love that I wish I wish
Everybody in this industry
Took that approach but
Obviously not everybody does
I'll be quite honest I've said many times how much I love the wink hub
When you were reporting that Flex
Butt wink and wink with Sinnoh
Digesting of working everything else I was concerned
Don't my whole platform for my house is that going away will it
Will it shut down
Is it gets frustrating peppermint industry perspective
Right in this is one of the reasons why consumers are like
They're going to look at this and they're going to like
Oh shoot dance that bullet
Screw this Marco
That hurts consumer sentiment as a whole
Which will hold up the industry
So my hope is we get
Some form of
Industry-standard and maybe it's
Maybe it's like security like as a member of the media
And we should be talking to our guests like Hey how do you plan to support your stuff if you got a business just like we started we started asking about
About security for the
Yeah
It maybe should be a you know what
Another must ask question on the list now
And then
The flip side is too mean I'm actually like
To the point where I'm well gee maybe I need to go back to a completely local Bass Run on server kind of thing
You know I mean it
Assassin
What to talk about building your own smart home hub
Raspberry Pi
When you can be done
Raspberry Pi openhab
Openhab
So that's the nest
Revolve
Drama
In a nutshell
I really like that
And our take on it is things like escrow accounts open source software or rather just put in your software in there if you
I want to make it open source
In case something bad happens
Negotiations you know when you're negotiating a deal like an m&a deal
Baby you make some sort of
Users
So
I would love to see that
Cuz I mean the value of these companies
It's not actually clear yet what it is
Is it the data is at the user base and
That
It all starts with a user's because you don't get dead without users number one and
If you don't have a product
Offer to people that they want him in
You're not going to have users to me it's all about users
Well in that spot revolves though they said it was more about the engineering
Date fruit
So that was kind of an apple higher
So I guess truth the writing was on the wall
Possibly.
Actually kind of us cuz they did say they were going to
Add new features and supported after a year so
Yes they didn't say they were going to turn it off
Let's move onto a week ago will actually last Thursday so a week from when you guys are hearing this
Kevin and I both
Received
It's actually
Did you got it on Wednesday
I did
I'm not that that matters to anybody who's listening
Yes I got mine before you did
I'm going to talk about
Amazon
Okay
Smaller version
Of the two new products that
Amazon
Put it out and it's
The echo lineup what's actually figure out what the heck we're going to call the Amazon Echo.
In tap what are those see that's the thing that there's the Amazon Echo
Then there's the
Amazon.
And then there's the
Echo tap I believe
I thought so
I'm checking as we speak
Summit I remember the standing out like all of these there's no consistency in
What is were
Amazon Echo
The Amazon Echo obviously
The Amazon tap and the Amazon.
So only the echo is the echo
Right
Question in our challenge here is
What the heck are we going to call these products because
There's a word for the more than the Amazon Echo we have to save the Amazon
Something's
The connected speaker line that's not really it
Bear
Voice assistant voice assistant
Listeners
Let us know if you have a great idea or if you've heard the actual term
Cuz
Kevin and I cannot read it
Alright so
Back-to-the.
We both elected for.
What we talked about why we had a reader talk to us about their privacy
That's why they got the tap
That's because you are
Tap it on to listen and then tap it back off
Where isthe. Is always listening and has a
Smaller speaker
So Kevin
19 hours
What did you think
I think
I love it I mean I'll I'll be blunt I love it
It's it's everything the echo is minus the big
Speaker so it literally few
Cut the speaker out of an echo and put the two remaining puts together in middle of a hockey puck that's the.
The speaker that's inside it
I really thought would be like maybe just like a phone speaker
It is better than that but marginally better than that and you're still not going to fill a room with
Bass and Rich sound but
Her background music which I often listen to while I'm working all day long
It's actually fine for that
A little louder than I expected
And
Payment setup was a breeze if you already have and I could come through the setup process pretty simple using the same
Amazon Alexa app hate to say her name but I had to
I don't know if you noticed this but your skills and my smart home Integrations all came over
I did not to do anything
McLoud Cafe
Are there well that's the benefit
I never said that
Cloud cloud is bad I'm just saying
You know you got a hold of cloud is available and and up and running for you
Seamless if you already have
Amazon Echo your right everything is transfers over the beautiful thing
She was literally plug-and-play at that
Let's figure out
Let's figure out where did you put your
Dot it where is your Echo
Spell to
The echo used to be in
My home office where I am now on the second floor and that meant only I would be able to use it because
I don't have the door shut when I'm working and someone
I have moved the echo down to the family room so it sits between the family room in the kitchen so that everybody can use it
There was also no way to control Smart Home Stuff
I'm downstairs now there is for everybody
So now that God is taking the place in my home office sitting behind me and I had to connected
Temporarily to a
Jawbone
Big Jambox because my Marshall stanmore speaker is broken which I didn't know until I
Connected
Okay
Did you name them both I have to say it you guys
Did you name them both
Yes I did you don't get any new choices to get the same 3 choices
I kind of thought maybe you could call it. But I thought so too
Yeah no no.
No. And if I'm in the middle of the two of them like I'm on the stairs
Between the first and second floor and I shout out her name
She responds on both of them and
Hopefully one or both ears me and they both respond
They work independently I want to be clear
You can't multitask
Music through the
Yet
It's a cheap way to add the echo this is what I love about it's an inexpensive way to add it
To all
That's what that mean if you've got it so
We didn't actually specify this but
It comes with a line in
Jack in
7.5 mm cord in jackass
Puppet in
I called line in cuz that's the
Commander my sodas
Stand alone till you don't need to connect to a speaker
You do not
I can buy what it is
What is great
I also connected it to my receiver which is in my AV system which is where I thought I was going to end up putting it
Oh my God it sounded
Like
Just fabulous
I was like what
But we realize that
Because that's
Sarhul
Home entertainment system
That it's hard when it cuz then it's right by the TV and then if we're watching TV we can't shout it
You don't go to church or the. To turn off the television so we ended up
Keeping
Original Echo downstairs to the kitchen where it was
After a couple days and then we move the. Upstairs
Bedroom and it's actually
My husband
Throughout his alarm clock and made it his alarm
Sports crate for that absolutely
Now it's funny you mention the TV because as soon as I got this
All we can figure and put the echo downstairs by the TV
I have an Amazon Fire TV connect is that TV
And I'm like okay I can use the voice remote for that and I can control the TV you know the playback of Amazon stuff
Wouldn't it be nice if I could just
Use the echo to do that
Unfortunate you can't spend mix there's no way that I know of yet
So that is unfortunate now I will say
Here's where we get to some
Integration
You guys are gonna
Or not
So
3 things to know
It integration
Amazon is integrating with
Lutron
My favorite light switches
Time interest
Because I forgot to tell you the show
Michael pecina the CEO of Lutron is actually Our Guest so stay tuned for him
And
Comedy clubs you know me that we talked about before also did it integration with nest
Like you said and then three
Amazon on Tuesday this week
Announced
That they're smart home skill API
Is now available
Everyone they launched it originally as the Alexa lighting API
Sorry I said
In August 2015
So all the companies that offer
Like lighting support like SmartThings Philips Hue Etc
They were all working
Through
That API but now it's
Available to everyone
Yay yay so now if you got to connect to thermostat connected lights of any sort you can actually make it
Tourettes with
The echo so then you can say I'm going to say it again you guys I'm sorry
Alexa turn on lights as opposed to
Ask lifx
To turn on light
Yeah it's much better with it
Native Integrations because it's a more natural language as opposed to the skill
Which is a pattern of words
Hope it all make sense
I have some lights that are
Controlled
If this then that trigger
Russo
And then the rest of my lights are normal so I'm constantly struggling with like
Turn on bedroom
Lights
Yeah
Set it for the integration is the various choices we have with if they're saying that different apis sdks and all that
So nice but ultimately made it as ideal because you don't ever think about how to ask it anymore
You still have to pay
Think I'm actually running out of
Words to control
It's more consistent.
You don't have to think about cuz I control history if this and that's why I need to ask it this way
In-N-Out
Yes they're slightly less
But sometimes I'm just like
Right
Whatever works
We're not there yet
Okay
But
Okay getting back to the TV
Because science
The integration with yonomi
Which is free software that anyone can download on iOS or Android
And it's much better than
We reviewed it like a year maybe longer ago
And it was a little buggy but cool
It recognizes
Products like Sonos the Amazon
Nest
Hue Lights
WeMo
The Logitech
Harmony
System hub
A couple other things so there's a lot of connected products on it it's free
They come with like these setups already programmed
So like
Every time my phone rings
My Sonos is if they're on there
Pause
Which is
I think it's awesome
With the Amazon
Devices with the Amazon integration
Now
You can actually turn on your TV if you have a Logitech Harmony Hub
Because an all you have to do is say
Hey lady a
Turn on
Movie night
Or whatever your
Your routine is
And you know me
So basically now I can control to a limited extent my Sonos has
The echo
I can now set up my TV to turn on
With
If I have a Logitech Harmony
Do you like so much worse.
It's okay
That is cool
That is cool to do this
You need to do a couple things or else it will not work and you will be as frustrated as I was
You have to add a device
To you know me you need to
Manually for the next like until they update the app you have to manually like
Find devices
And once you've done that you have to go back into
Echo
Discover new devices
Keep your order of operations
Write the checking for new devices
In the Amazon App should always be the last
I believe the last step
And if you have the Philips Hue Lights you're going to have to go punch a button
Finally
After that
Immigration
There's also the Lutron integration
Which I was really excited about
I realize
Cuz I have Lutron lights are connected to the echo through the wing
Link up and I was like
Now I can talk directly to
You can actually talk to right now.
So
Can I get rid of that hug just yet
Not that we
Link up but but you can still use your Echo to control your Lutron switches now
Because of the
True
If you don't have the wing but you have like the Lutron Bridge which people may have bought for homekit compatibility
Cuz it was one of the first ones
We'll talk directly
So
That's a plus that is a plus
More lights
More control
Speaking of light
Yes
Please tell me if you can talk about this new Switch
I am Because You Loved Me
I love the osram tunable white bulbs that I have in the house I have a couple of them they're all connected and
Change from
Soft white to warm white tube
Daylight I love my love my love
Banana have a switch
They do so this is the osram
Lightify Wireless dimming Smart Switch
That's a mouthful
Osram lightify switch I guarantee you're going to see this is like a
Fancier light switch
It's about $30
I bought it because
Someone actually told me about it
I was very frustrated by the fact that
My
Light switch
Was always
If it wasn't on a Lutron
Or like a wifi-connected dimmer
People would turn it off
Whatever people turn it off
Get out then my
Connect to light bulbs didn't work
And that was always kind of
Frustrating
So
I got this thinking I could put it anywhere and it would
The way it looks
It looks like it actually toggles
Your switch cuz it comes with different backing plates that you put on top of the existing switch so you don't have to mess around with electricity
Okay that's the other reason I got
That's cuz I know people are kind of worried about that
I was like Hey would it be awesome if I could tell them about this connect a light switch that
Still toggles there
Switch physically
And keeps track of state which is what I thought it did but it does not do
I know it almost looks like so it fits over existing switch
It does
Basically just talks to your existing osram lightify lights
So you press it up and down
It doesn't control your physical switch so your physical switch will always stay on
He put it over the switch and then that switch
Now talk to your eyes room lights
And you don't turns off and on
It is
Zigbee compatible
I hooked it up to the wink
And it didn't quite work the way I thought but I think I need to hook it up as a remote instead of as an actual switch
So I'm still getting this
I'm still trying to find the use case for it cuz I was
Again
I thought it would like
Well do something different
So I mean it dims your bulbs
Yeah that you can you can already do that through an echo or hug or whatever
But this also gives you the physical option now of giving
Write so someone goes and hits that switch
They're used to just hit the switch on the wall they're still going to be able to hit the switch on the wall
End
The nice thing about it is if it pairs to your lights
Your underlying physical switch will always be on
When someone actually touches
The switch which is on top of the physical switch
And I would imagine that it didn't give the state of the light bulb
To any apps or any like that as well
Exactly
And you don't even have to put this over an existing switch like I see a picture of it on Amazon music. On a nightstand just
So it comes with three different bag
And one is for the
Traditional toggle switches with a little
Toggle sticking out of the switch
One is for the
Flatter switches
Rockers
Chips or rocker switch
And then the other
So many reason were here is a plain back
And I'ma put this on the wrong light
1st and
If it took me like 5 Seconds
Ghetto unscrew the
Screws holding my existing light switch plate in place and
Can I screw this guy in and
That was it
It's really easy it was easy to pair
So if you need something like this
It's 30 bucks
It does stick out from the wall my husband told me that I could not leave it up
Yeah it looks like it sticks out a good 1/2 inch or 3/4 of an inch from a
Wall
Yeah it's pretty ish it does have it right on the switch
Yeah
Sure
Sure but it does
It tells you this
The top is at the bottom
Well in the any other thing I like about this I mean
I don't think it's for me because I connect
You know your eyebrows are involves going through the way again the echo.and
Stuck at the apps I got the voice
Interactional s but my family still isn't into the whole shouting at something to turn lights on
So I could see
Them using this is proper some reason why use a phone app or
Or doesn't have a voice activation system for these things
Yeah cuz it needs a physical product
Or yes
Or it's good for if you have a light switch in An Inconvenient spot
And you can put an osram bulb in
Do you hook up a parrot to this guy
And then boom
You now have a light switch wherever you want it
Yeah
Wireless light switch kit
Okay so that's what this is
It does work is easy pair
And
30 bucks is 30 bucks
It's available on
Amazon in
Okay so we talked about quite a bit I think that's probably good for us
Before I leave
Please
Please take Riot podcast survey
Which you can fight it iot podcast. Com
/ survey
Great stops so far
Yeah it's a little late if it takes you a minute it's
It's taking too long it's there's not that much there.
It's very fast
Don't take a lot of time
OKC to Our Guest
Michael pizzi who is the CEO of Lutron he's going to talk about
Bringing another radio protocols
Secrets to Smart Lighting in your house
Did you know Kevin that we are all using
Way too much light
I'm not surprised by that he's an awful lot of like
It's it's not a scarce resource but you're not letting your home correctly
Stay tuned
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot pot
I have to tell you two things the first is that I've launched a Weekly Newsletter devoted to the internet of things you can sign up
Airport at Stacey on iot. Com the second is that we're now accepting ads on the II
RT Podcast we have packages for big companies and for startups so if you're interested email Andrew
Coyote podcast.com thanks for listening
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your hope Stacey Higginbotham and today my guess is Michael piscina Who is the co-ceo
And president of Lutron
Hi Michael how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm doing great how are you
I am really excited to have you on the show because I have
Probably five or six Lutron switches throughout my house and
I love them
And I'm kind of very curious to find out
The future of these things that I have
Put in my home so
Let's talk about
What she looks first tell the audience
What Lutron is
Thank you Stacey and again thank you for giving us the opportunity to tell her to tell her story on your show
Somatron we have been
55 years in the lighting
Pro-business
Back to Genesis of our company is our founder
Under The Lights dimmer in 1961
Products
Serve the both commercial and residential markets and Factor about 50% residential and 50% commercial
So since you got a pretty long perspective here is a company
What has changed in the last let's call it for 5 years with relation to kind of the Smart Home
The launch of all these hubs and kind of the snoo
Exciting
Is it just
Going down Market
For the smart home or is there something different happening
I think there's significant things and I thought maybe maybe Stacy would be
Alfred schedule is just a very very and I'll just take a few minutes if I could
Timeline about Lutron
But I mention 1961 or founder patented
And that was an obviously the input that was the start of the company
Important
You asked about 5 years ago what's different and really what happened in two
7 2008 with a smartphone
Smartphone and everybody's hands today
Now all the sudden gave you the ability
Two notches control items
In your home
Your home from outside of your home
And the development of apps
With our reliable lighting control technology was just a natural
Putting these things together
Such that
Again you have the control in your home
Or if you want to set scenes or have geofencing or any kind of capabilities of
When you're approaching your home have your lights turn on automatically to welcome same so you never enter a dark home
That was a natural I think that's been the big change I don't think it's as much
Downmarket although we've developed technology for the mass-market the wireless technology
It's really been that the smart all-sec smartphones and tablets have made I really made the
Connected home
Potential
Much more of the mass Market product
Okay and that dope because
Agree with you the smartphone is really opened up a lot of things
What I have seen
In the next
Will say in the next few years what seems to be coming
Technology that works directly with the smartphone
There's a Wi-Fi light bulbs out there
Lutron has this amazing
Proprietary radio technology
But I'm very curious
How you see the future
Of kinds of wireless tech and
It's supporting that across many platforms and making it kind of interoperable with some of the other Gadgets in the smart
I think space you're exactly right we we employ our Wireless Clear connect technology
And it's all about reliability
It's all about when the button presses occurred
That you want to turn a light on
Not only does it always turn on
But it turns on fast we called Liam
But I think
When you look at Bluetooth
Where you look at Wi-Fi are you look at other protocols out there and zigbee and Z-Wave
They have a part in this connected home
We'll look at Bluetooth technology and Wi-Fi technology
For the setup
And that you're very very simple setup of our Tech
Of our lighting control technology
What we have to do is Ensure
To the homeowner
It's not about
The technology what is Bluetooth Wi-Fi
Clerk connect
It's about we believe
Precinct
Does it give the homeowner
The effect
That they wanted
Number two
How can we even with different Technologies in Bluetooth and BLS much different than Wi-Fi technology
Can you put that behind the curtain so the homeowners G
Just plug it in
And it just works
And the third part of that
Is the reliability
Will it be reliable over time
We always like to say you don't want to reboot your lighting
But it's true you don't want to
Expected
You don't say see one of the things we do is we look at
Okay how how
Close can we get to the reliability of a light switch
Let's take this a little bit further cuz you guys today are launching
An integration with the Amazon Echo
Let's talk about kind of the future
Lutron in this kind of
Interoperable Multi-Device connected home
Where do you see
That's a great question
I think one of the things
Currently that what we are talking about with Amazon Echo and what we're launching
As we looked at this and we thought
The Amazon Echo
Really is a very good software platform we've been very pleased with that week
Testing at 4. Of time I know it's getting good response
In the marketplace
And we make great software and Hardware
So we thought it was a natural of bringing Amazon Echo
And the Lutron caseta platform together
So I think one of the things we bring to this
Internet of Things
Is
Making sure things always work
I'm at bringing this back up
Capability
Because again
If the internet goes down we want you to always be able to control your lights reliably
Okay
And let's go platforms because
I think Lutron is now on
Almost all of the big ones so you guys have
Your Bridges homekit certified
You've got the web platform
Look at the Amazon Echo
Do you have anything with the works with Nest program
Yes we are part of the works with Nest program
All right so that's a big for it seems like
I don't know if there's another big one for you guys
Well we we have worked as
We have work this part of there's been announcements with both AT&T Digital Life
And there's also been announced
Since with Comcast
Work work as a part of cell
You know we take
You know there are approaches is very simple we believe that we are working and are committed to the
Best lighting control in the world
And we want to make sure it's seamlessly integrate with all the popular platform Stacy
Salt works
And have these protocols
That are outside behind the scenes
Just work
In a fashion that the homeowner doesn't need to worry about
When we say Lutron is going to work with a
In that part of the desk
Platformer work was part of homekit
You just connect it
And it works
Head
Will do all the hardware and software verification so that that occurs and happens
And
I think that has been our strategy
As well as having our own Bridge capability case somebody just wanted to do lights
Shades and temperature
They have that capability also
And among these platforms
Can you talk to me about
The ease of working with them because they're
There different levels there is
Works with Nest is very much developer Focus kind of application thing
The echo seems to be more in line with that and then there's home kit which requires Hardware
I'm just kind of curious
As a company that is deciding where to invest their time
How are you evaluating this and what would your advice be to other companies who are looking and trying to decide which platform
Sport
So that's an excellent question
First of all I think our relationship with all these companies have been very good
And
But there's different levels of integration what we did with link is we embedded are clear connect technology
And that takes a little more time to do that cuz we work out on
Not just
Software
For also embedding the radio on the antenna design so that has take that took a little more time
What we do with Amazon
And we're doing as part of the nest program doing part of homekit
It's really cloud to Cloud integration
So we were very reliable Cloud platform they have a good Cloud platform
And what we do is work on the software
So these
Basically cloud-to-cloud Stampley
We can integrate very
Seamlessly
That would be a little bit of an easier approach
Overall all of these companies have been good to work with
Which platform has the most users right now
Or most of your users
I don't know the answer to
To that question.
Who has the most users
I can tell you that are
Zeta platform
Selling our kissaten our Bridge has been very successful
And is continuing
How to grow
Only the caceda version so these are more the
What has a mass Market switches
A mass Market
PECO
I always want to say pico projectors
The mass Market
Pico remote
Those are the only ones that integrate with all these other connected home platform
No the radio raw and homeworks
We announced it
Acedia last year
Are part of nest
They're part of the Honeywell platforms security platforms as well as
Honeywell
Thermostat
Are those
Part of the Maestro line or is there a different line
So meisterwood brr stand-alone wall box
Control
But radio radio Rob
Is a wireless
Control system of the 200 points
Control
At home work switch
CVS
Level accounts
That is
You can have thousand
Thousands
Control on that and I'll say very customized
Stop program
Yuan Phillip circus Ada and Philips Hue
How about it 50
Okay good to know
Because I am
Huge nerd when it comes to lighting
I I tried pretty much everything
What are the big trends you guys see in lighting that your kind of follow along with Ben Hur really
Excited
Well I think one of the things that it's occurred and and and lighting ceremony in the past 3 to 4 years is
LED technology-infused if you think of what's going on
An LED technology is used the benefit of having a microprocessor and every light bulb
It's also added a lot of new people in the marketplace you know in the
And add that what I mean by that
Is your company's today light Cree
And like
Song in and others in the LED Marketplace
Which weren't there
R56 years ago
But the other thing that that's occurring is obviously with a Micro Control in there you can put radios in light bulbs
Special put what radios in lightbulbs you'll have the ability to
Call them directly
Commensurately
Did the addition of voice technology
What's the Amazon Echo has
Capabilities
And Siri also
Send out we work with those for those platforms so that's something that's
Changes that are occurring we work very hard to stay on top of that
Let's talk about this for a little bit
Because I I kind of walked through my house every now and then play a little game with myself about
What's going to be in at 10 years from now
And I'm assuming I'm making a lot of assumptions
Bear with me
But
I'm trying out some lights right now that I have motion control the cat temperature controls built into kind of ambient light sensor
In some of my rooms
In the hallways and small rooms especially like closets and bath
X
It's perfect I never touch a light switch
Like
It's it's awesome
What happened to
I'll use Sonos again cuz it's a good anime
Creed eyes perhaps
Crate Tech
Work super well
But
Ask the internet of things kind of happens
It's a very real question about how that will disrupt like
Your business model so
I might not need my light switches
Well I think it's something you know I've been asked many times Stacy
Talk about disrupt
Disruption actually can be a good thing
Spinning around a little bit and don't think about the disruption but look at the opportunity
So what's the opportunity
And and
Connected light bulbs that have sensing capability
We believe there still a need
2 in the event
From sensing standpoint
You're still going to need the ability if you're standing still and things like that should be able to
And and we think they're still opportunities for us to be able to connect to these light bulbs and ways and
Offers Superior
User
Experience
In a closet application again we could see
Interfacing with those
Type of applications
So maybe you would want to be able to control the lights even before you enter the space
And
You could be able to control them
Maybe by sensors
You ever you approaching
Particular
I can tell you that happens in my hallway today
With our wireless sensor technology
When I get into the hallway
Before I get into the closet
My lights in my closet
Come on to
40 to 50% and then when I get into the closet my lights come on
To 90%
And again there's anticipation
And I think one of the things we remain to be is a very very good very reliable hardware and software
Technology company
Are you guys going to be adding it sounded like you were going to be adding some sort of
When you talked about anticipation which I think would be
Kind of cool because the less I have to program
The better
I'm really not at Liberty Stacy to talk about future developments but
Okay
I have to ask because I'm kind of curious if you get this.
Everytime I actually was a crazy chain
I use the Amazon Echo to turn off my dining room light switch
Stuck on a Lutron switch
It's the Amazon Echo
To wink
To Lutron
Do you guys get to see that data
It's going to it's going through so many places so I'm curious
The day that we would see as we know the
Product is being hooked up we don't know the specifics of that
On how it is
Working in and we don't know the specifics in terms of users
And how the users are using the product that's
Obviously information and
That we would not interfere
4 or 1/2
The intruding in people's lives but I think one of the things we do is we'll hook up
The Amazon Echo in our technology and we'll look how people are used
Dance day in and day out
And then final advice
I would love to pick your brain since you are
Become CEO of a lighting
Give us some advice on
Lighting settings
Because as people are
Transitioning to LEDs that have this level of customization
Let's just run through some basic
Scenarios
Give them to you and then you tell me you kind of
Where should my lighting be maybe it's a temperature may be a
Adapt
Are you ready for this do you think
Do this
I can try for my experience
Okay
Movie night
Individual setting could be anywhere between
Anywhere between camdude
30% depending on how much light to give available in your room
Dinner party lighting
I think it's dinner party lighting
Is candle lighting
Cuz the best
Adelaide in the best lighting is somewhere in the neighborhood again as I'll say any to 10 to 24
Okay
Good morning
I think probably one of the greatest things about good morning is having a nice warm light
Probably would let somewhere it's between 30 to 50% and the shades
Smoking
Nice
Okay
Reading before bed
Reading before bed obviously has to have the the light next to your bed stand
Come on to the right level having
The shades closed
And having the lights around you at a night light level so in the event you had to get up
You would have the lights at a night light level either of their Wireless.
Or just on a time clock
Is there ever a time that we should have 100%
Lighting
Operating room
I think commercially there are
Applications
It also may be a situation where your cleaning up your kitchen
Or cleaning up your your bathroom or or something and you'd want the lights on full
All right guys it sounds like if you don't have some sort of LED light on a dimmer
You are doing it wrong
Unless you're just cleaning all the time which
I really hope for everyone say that is not the case
You so much for coming on the show today
Stacy thank you for the opportunity and and we look forward to continue
I want to work with you in the future that's it for this week's show thank you for listening and remember please sign up for
For the iot newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com