Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Today Show we have awesome things for you we have a
Who section on updates around various Dev board
We have data on carriers in the internet of things we have
A whole segment and a guest
Who is the deputy director of the Cyber statecraft initiative at the Atlantic Council he went to Defcon
Black hat and b-sides and he is going to tell us
All about what we should worry about and what we should probably just chill
A little over
And we're also going to talk about
Staples connect
Which did bite the bull
Purple
But first
Let's have a word from our sponsor
Working on building a connected product don't do it yourself it's complex and it could be years before you're up and running
Years you can tap
Afford to wait
So accelerate your time-to-market a riskier investment and leverage dively's expertise
They're iot experts at business-ready award winnings Ivory platform will help you launch quickly secure
Shirley and @scale learn more, that's x i v e
Ally.com and now back to the show so
Kevin
Ticket office in a little more exciting the death board
Sorry everyone
Let's start with staples connect
Sad so here's what happened Staples connect which was one of the initial home hubs actually it launched
About the same time that revolved and SmartThings version one did
I actually tested all three of those
And the original Lowe's
Iris platform
73 years old
Yeah I think that was a
December 2013 story that I reviewed all of those so
Its agent in the world Electronics
But
It was really a great
Set a route to versions of it in both of them
We're awesome
These heaux
We were actually my favorite
For a long time
We're the ones I would recommend anyone who is kind of a beginner getting into the Smart Home
I thought that SmartThings was super fun and open but was a little more happy and you had to be a little bit more clever and know what you're you do
Doing
The Stables connect were design for mainstream customers in
By golly it looks like the mainstream consumers did not take them up
It's kind of a shame because in addition to being one of the first usable ones on the market usable hugs
I recall
Events
Where they showed off the
Staples connect display
And they're showing consumers how everything would work because
Really you know it's at the time PetSmart on Hulu with that wasn't me maybe our listeners did but the mainstream audience
Consumer did not
And it was one of the first I think to do a great job explaining all the benefits which products work with which how they work together
Why you want this
And it was fantastic from consumer experience standpoint but you're right
It just didn't catch on
It did not end a staple spokesperson
Told
Twice wechat
Is a publication
That the move was prompted by quote
Changing market dynamics
And a focus on more business-oriented solution
Unquote
And this makes sense so Staples actually tried to buy Office Depot
The FTC said no no no
They got some issues
So
They are still going to sell Smart Home Products they just aren't going to have their own branded Hub that
You know
Works with us products
So what but there's good news for people who do have that huh
Yes
Kevin
Yes so
What Staples is doing is they are turning everything over in terms of sales and support to Zone off
And other Z-Wave products which is an online retailer
That sells obviously Z-Wave products
So that's
Good news for people who know how to solve love the sub
I was just not going to die
Like certain ones that I won't name
Revolve
So yes
Basically the continuation of your Staples connect is brought to you by the letter
Z
I have purchased things for the Z-Wave products folks
A Z-Wave remote actually
And it works fine
Arizona
Is
They've been doing this for years there actually in Kevin's backyard
You keep telling me to go visit them you've been telling me for three years they have a laugh
It's really cool
So I won't ask anymore Kevin
You're not yourself
So anyway so so tough
Actually
Is how we're supposed to say it
Is
Supporting this they're going to
Continue to make updates
Connect app
Which
Is awesome because
You know these guys change their devices all the time so it's really actually hard to be kind of a Hubbard integrator
Because you have to keep up with the changing of
So that's going to still happen
It may not happen forever
But they will to ease the transition
Have a
Dedicated website which willing to in the show notes and they also have a hotline which is
1 800
1 V
1/8
So if you have a Staples connect system because I did recommend this way long ago
This is where you will get continuing help for at least a little while
And that basically leaves
Only the lows
Product
Out in the market as a kind of vendor
Retailer supported
Device cuz I don't know if you guys remember it was a
Flash in the pan but Best Buy had the peak
Platform
Which has disappeared
I'm sorry if you have
Pink platform
I didn't get the sense that
So cuz that that actually have a service fee
Associated with
So
Business models for the iot going forward and all these include dying
Maybe a service plan is it
So crazy
I know
Sacrilege
Blasphemy
So that is
The Staples news
So
Good luck to you guys
On a side note
I will say that
If you are looking for another hub
Because you just can't get enough hubs in your life
The wink
Is currently the Hub I'm recommending I am playing again with the SmartThings Hub it's still no
Not as reliable and I really wanted to be a little easier to use
So
It is definitely more flexible
So if you are feeling
Feeling it you really want to go for it
The SmartThings Hub is gray
If you are a hacky kind of DIY person
Just doesn't feel mainstream
Yes it's true I am still happy with my winky know by comparison to everything else so
Sacraments
Well yeah and an even more surprising because of you know
GE quirky
Getting selling off wings
2 flags and there was concern there what about the product without the support or the service
I don't feel like it's affected me at all
So
And
I've been traveling a lot this summer but very soon I will have wink relays in my house
I've gotten some feedback from the snow
And they say that they love them so
Is it a little touch screen $99
In-wall pennies right
So those aren't those are coming
I was going to send them to Kevin
Oh I like that idea okay
What's happened to Kevin
Although then we'll hear the review three years
Sounds
Let's go onto now will do that for
Kevin you found a really cool price
Interesting yeah it is a Kickstarter
Project keep that in mind when I make that caveats beforehand but
Pretty little as $5
You can get a little development board for iot
The Omega 2
There are tons and tons of add-ons for this thing I'm very impressed by all the add-ons
It's super small it's about a quarter of the size of a Raspberry Pi a third the size of an Arduino
Uno so it is pretty small
Tons of expansion packs as I mentioned runs with Linux
As a remote
Integration Clinic call it Cloud integrated so that you can
Remote control to it from anywhere in the world using the onion cloud
You can do the status of it real time you can deploy software updates to it when it's in the fields that's interesting
Start expandability has Wi-Fi built in I believe
You can add Bluetooth you can add cellular to it
Maven connected to an Arduino
Tons and tons of Integrations here so I'd like this for people who want to
Tinker with iot Solutions on the cheap basically I mean
You have to stay out on boards and you start talking about some serious money but
For five bucks and get started
Okay and I was like the onion Cloud I have not heard about that but it's it's it's cloudy
It's actually for Debbie
Made by the
Not the satirical
Journalistic
Playset type of this is an onion. IO
You're not living your best iot
Sorry
Broken it
Okay
Speaking of death boards
My devices the company that makes Cayenne
Which is a easy to use programming
Eat language for iot
Partnered with Arduino
So now they support the rest
Pi and Arduino which
Alarm I listen to send me emails that I didn't read
And they like
Cayenne
You know if you're one of those people
Now works with Arduino
Then finally
Particle the company that makes
The photon and
Other
I'm trying to think of the name
The spark
Scorpius
Parkour parkour
And in the photon which has the cellular can
Activity
I believe
They have a cloud
Which
I may be honest guys I really thought they always had a cloud because you connected your bored and sent data to their claw
To somewhere
They formally announced it last week and they also have built-in Integrations with Microsoft
Azure
Google
Their cloud of infrastructure if this and that and some other places so now it's
More fully functioning for Enterprises in comedies like Keurig
And
Cleverpet
Use it so
There you go
Particle
That much more legit
And that
Cats are deaf for the day
Let's see what should we cover next
Wheaties it at the beginning some interesting iot data points in terms of the carrier's
Oh yes so this is for my friend Chetan Sharma who
Is a wheelchair we do
He's a wonderful person and he's a
Really kick butt analyst
If you're if you're needing data about carriers Chetan Sharma Consulting
She tells us Kevin actually you should do the
So I clocked out
Freaky datapoints at lemon chatting if anybody's ever read his
Analytical reports
It's like volumes of information
So I just went in and
Snagged a couple
Of interesting points
First one for the first time I O T which includes bathing suit and connected cars
Net ads for carriers exceeded the net ads for phones and tablets combined
I guess it's a little I don't to say obvious but
A little unsurprisingly
Phone and tablet ads have been slowing
Did you see that with my
Like Apple's iPhone sales that's been like the big
Topic of conversation in the last
Everyone likes that
Transition
These numbers would higher than these numbers for the first time ever
Now
In terms of AT&T there connected-car onboarding pace is twice that of its connected tablet space
What's a wheat back to order sign up with saturation
But
Other interesting number AT&T is expected to reach 10 million
Connected car subscriptions very soon
Repeat in roughly twelve quarters
From the time you first started doing it
Compare 25 quarters
Super tablet so
They're just getting their of their chips and servicing cars
Quickly
I still don't I have connected car options in my two vehicles I just don't use them talk about that II
I don't want to
Prepaid Verizon their iot and telematics
Is risen 25% year-over-year 205 million dollars
Which chance has hey we're getting close to 1 billion dollar a year run rate in that business for Verizon which is
No small amount of chump change that's very
Cricket
More context
Before we talk about connect
Okay AT&T achieved according to chat
A $1000000
Verizon is playing catch-up
AT&T is the master when it comes to connecting
In cars
Tesla
Chrysler they have
Bunch of brands
So they really won this and I think actually a lot of people say that
AT&T ability to get Tesla is what
Prompted a lot of other carriers to say what
We should really be talking all this connected thing people cuz we danced out on
Okay Kevin tell us why you don't
So I guess I struggle with with
The business model from a consumer standpoint
I'm
I've already got a phone with LTE or maybe after for phones my whole family is with me
In the car
Why am I going to
Make a hotspot here in my car why am I why do I need that connectivity
When I
Sorry
No no eye mask
Cuz mine
Mycompass
Okay
I love the
The fact that my car so
Again I'm not trying to lay first world problems people are like Beavis and you said I do
Has an AT&T
Connection
I don't actually have autopilot Earl out of the fan
Fancy Feet
Or that
Tesla pays for the
An index the difference the car would be
Almost useless so I actually have this thing because they're at their like we're going to pay for it for the first I think it's seven year
Of the car
Anime
AT&T hasn't even set pricing for what it would be afterwards in Tesla's actually like
I talk to my friends have you know 2013
Models in there like
Yeah I don't even
So
Without
Connectivity though if I have to pay for it
My car becomes
But useless but
It becomes less exciting
Unless like a luxury vehicle that I paid a lot of
Right and
I think
Did they should be taking the Kindle model on these things because
When you're buying a car now
Most people are thinking they're buying
Computer
So
If you're actually buying a computer than
You just got to have the connectivity is part of it in the manufacturer needs to pay
That's that's my gut sense and then they can limited all they want they probably like
I can't stream Netflix in my test
And that's fine by me
So that that's my two cents
So I think the big difference is
Hazlet is probably an outlier
In that it's including the LTE
For you
Where is my new Volkswagen
I got a trial for 6 months
Which includes
Security in that features and so on so forth so
But after that you do have to pay and I think that's probably more of them
Prevalent model
Should it be that model Maybe not maybe
You know
Didn't going on your take on the Kindle model
Maybe it's just be there should be connected I don't know
I just think so much like
How are they going to do it over there updated that's not
There
Stock cars are going to need those so my guess is they could do that and they just cover the data charges through the
Carrier directly I never know about it we just pushing update will you get your vehicle updated at the dealership
Dealership dealership
Amazon Prime for car updates please
Got me a USB with all the data I don't do that
All right
So those are the fun datapoint
A bit about Canada
I wonder if maybe luxury cars have this
So anybody out there who's got like a
I don't know BMW or a high-end Mercedes with lots of fancy stuff on them
Let us know info at iot podcast. Com
Because I'm very curious like
Are we going to have this model wear
User-pays or wear manufacturer pays because the
I connected features are so much part of the selling point with a car
Okay we're going to run from connected cars to security but before we do that
There's a new toy in town
It is the
Logitech
Home switch
It is a $40
Programmable button
That will work with your Logitech Harmony but also many of your other smart devices
In the home
And you can program it to basically
Beaverton
Anything you want like goodnight house
Click the button
Turn on lights
You can actually do
Different presses a single press a double press in a long press
So this is kind of like
The Philips Hue tap
For many many moons ago
But it works with other things and it also can it has an app that
The text all the other devices in your house so you don't actually have to like
Fiddle around with
Like what you do have to put all around
Now that I think about it is just
Hit it send it send it starts
$40 there is a starter pack for
$100 but we're not sure yet what's in the starter pack in with multiple pops
Or what but normally I'm not a fan of AC
However
I could see myself spending $40
One in the main reason why
Nobody in the family likes using the echo to turn lights on and turn lights off other than make so they sit there
Is there anyway I can you turn up the lights on
Yes really
They don't like talking to the device or devices
So I would spend the $40 at this point because it's so aggravating
But I will just
Spend $40
And get them a button
That turns lights on and off basically
All the switches I just replace after we replace with a smart button
What weight you should switch
Okay I'm so confused they won't get up and go to the switch
I mean if you're not going to talk to something you might as well like this
Suck it up and
Well these are non switches their lamps
All right we'll see
Because here's my dream
Actually I wouldn't buy it cuz I now have a DOT by my bed but
Actually
It's a great fun thing to have a button by your bed that like turns off
Regular
Is done and I actually played with the Hue tap but it didn't
Control anything other than the lights
So that was kind
It was fun to have it for
Controlling lights with this
Lock up the Fortress turn off the lights turn on the cameras
Everything happen
So
Right now the echo doesn't work with all of my stuff
It's not clear a Logitech actually has a lot of good stuff it works with
More so than the echo
Actually it works also with the echo
So
Maybe you could be like
She who shall not be named
Activate my pop button
That would be so fun
Are we done it
Anyway
I'm just being silly this way
But with this thing
I think it actually would
I like button
And my daughter likes button so
She's got this thing where she doesn't want quote-unquote robots in a room
But maybe if I just gave her the button instead of she hits it things happen
She's she's pretty smart she probably realize it was a robot
Kick it out but
I like it
I Would by One in a heart
And probably will
The other thing I know about this is
This is great for people that babysitters because it ties into the
Logitech Harmony Hub
Which if you program that correctly you know you can actually have your TV come on
Dial with one button
So you ready
You can create those kind of setting so like
One button is cable
2 buttons
Is
Video three buttons is
Your house is on fire in Everett
When she get out so that would be
Really nice for people who got parents are guests who come in or let go and God your TV Soca
Complicated
Flix and chill.
That is a Logitech
And now we should talk about
Hackable
They're not hackable buttons they're hackable a
Kevin brought up the story about 75
Bluetooth smart locks
Can be hacked
And later on I'm going to tell you all the locks that were hacked and I'm going to tell you August
Response
Cuz they're a popular
Play the one with the most mindshare I don't know if they're
The one with
But the most market share.
Kwikset locks
They were not in the way
But
I am aware that
Kwikset lock is really easy to open
You know if you have a screwdriver and you just want to open
Sorry Kevin I know you
No you know it's working really well for me but yeah if it's at the highest grade Quality Security oppressor
Install.
Connect to Schlage lock I was like oh
This is way better
Okay
Let's see Kevin did you see anything you wanted to bring up about Defcon
No I mean just a general comment I always
Fringe this time of the year when we have black hat
Defcon and all these security things because
That's when all of these reports come out in and N people researchers have been sitting on
Security issues for possibly 3 for 6 months whatever it is
It's like the scariest time of the year
So kind of cringe mean it's a good thing that they're doing what they're doing but
Universe just tons of Doom and Gloom
Things that came out
Last week or two about security sites
Disney Channel
All right well after a message from our sponsor
I will tell you you will be relieved to know that
Bose comments pasrr
Don't panic
Good
Stay tuned for that
Hey everyone this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast with a message from our sponsor take Monk
Developer conference for people making the internet
Things happen
Is annual conference in September brings together technologist and designers who build core infrastructure for iot platform
Happy that you'll see two days of expert speakers
Including me
Giving talks on everything from Bots
Industrial Automation machine learning to time series data
Programming language choices
Ux
As a special treat their also bringing back the famous thing bunk hackaday
Sponsored by IBM
Still have a short Watson and Alexa skills Workshop to kick things off with no prior knowledge required
To learn more about the conference please visit
Www
. thing mug
Dot-com
Iot podcast blisters get a 20% discount code for any of the days or a combination of all three days
So to take advantage use the promotional code iot podcast when you register back to the show
Hey guys it's Stacey
Before we get to Bo Woods I did want to jump in with the correction from last week
Last week we talked about Phillips in their new line of medical devices
Watch
A body scale
ABP monitor blood pressure monitor
And an ear thermometer
When I spoke about them I said that they were FDA approved but that wasn't actually true
Two of them the healthwatch in the body scale are listed with the FDA as a medical device
It's kind of a lower bar
For them to clear it basically just means
Not be duplicitous
And be suitable for intended uses and
Be properly labeled
That's worth
So that is kind of what that means and then the other three devices that your thermometer and the
Blood pressure monitors
Both the wrist and the arm
Are medically cleared devices
And that means that the FDA has determined that they are substantially equivalent to another legally marketed medical device
That is what you need to know
Not approved
But
Listed and clear
Thanks
Now on TiVo
Today's guest is Bo Woods
Who has a what is a deputy director of the cyber statecraft
Initiative for the Atlantic
Council
Thanks for being here
Can you tell us what that means and normal people language
Thank you Stacey it's good to be on again with you so
I have a long background in the information security community and Industry
When
I came to the Atlantic Council
Did so because I was going to hopefully
I'll be able to bring some of the technical literacy to public policy makers who are making decisions about technology that
Influences of everyday things like cars
Medical devices
Critical infrastructure
We probably need a lot of fat
In the public policy
Is fear and actually all over the place
You talked about
9 points
A little bit safer
You should it was awesome
Is back in March
Now we're here because
Bo was at Defcon
Last week
And there's a lot of iot
Just in general a lot of people testing the boundaries of
Cyber security
Impressions
On the show
Yeah sure so I was out there all week long it was a grueling August in Vegas
Is pretty hot but visited the b-sides Las Vegas
Security conferences well as Defcon and heard about some of the things that went on at blackhat
Like you said there was lots of iot hacking
Overall it seems like the level of it hacking is going way up I helped to run the contest
Storages in advance
Defcon
And that's where we
Held
Car hacking Village
It Village and biohacking
I got to say cracking Village was pack
Wall2wall all three days
There was so much good content
A lot of people would set up
Demonstrations and workshops
But they were doing
They had a special badge this year that was in the shape of a car and it had an OBD2 connect
Electronic that you can use to
I checked in your car and reach of the day off and then as well as to do some other things
Okay wait
I do like no
Mysterious nefarious labs
Yeah well who knows
Who knows what's really in it the real hackers will go and don't have the Curiosity to dig in and find out what's on those
Pcbs
That's what everybody else
Yeah
Plugging something into your car unknown provenance
Might not be the best idea
You're planning to do it for test purposes
Go ahead
Security tip number one
For you don't plug strange things cars computers and other
General Life advice
It said the car was a big thing
Did you see anything
The guys who did the Jeep hack
We're back
And I'm curious the ones who stopped a Jeep
Everyone is very excited about it
They wanted to
Actually I think it was control the brakes of a car
This time around
Did you see anything for them where they impressive
Yes so I I
Wasn't able to attend their talk
But I heard a lot about it as you can imagine
The last time
They did a demo
Are they kill the engine on a highway in
St.Louis
And then brought it off the highway to do some other things with it
This year they were back and they were demonstrating how they could
Do a lot of the same things that they were able to do in
Very slow speed
At actually very fast
So they seem to
Automatically go through every year and try and bust myth
I hate to miss it was busted this time was that
The only car hacking
Make it happen of turning the steering wheel
We have to be at a very very slow speed and therefore it would be consequential on
Highways and things like that so it couldn't be a
A broader Public Safety minutes
It could only be something that was done in a lab
Accentuate
And white Christmas Charlie showed is that that was not the case
That they could do it at speed
And it could cause
Type of large-scale
Highway denial-of-service if you will
That would be things like massive traffic jams right
I think that one was
With much-talked-about
I got a lot of coverage
Okay so
Just for those of us who are like
Holy cow
That's scary
What should automakers do
Should I would actually tell me first should I worry
Well I think Douglas Adams said it best
I said Don't Panic
Grab your crying towel
And
Just do it the fact that these things are both true and scary and also not likely to affect you at Lee
At least not anytime soon
So while there should be a large degree of
Awareness
Among consumers LeBlanc automakers is on policymakers
I don't think it's time to go out and stop buying cars right
The worst thing you could probably do is to buy an older model car that has less safety gear
Rather than a newer model
A car which has more safety gear
But in which there's more chance of an exotic
Type of failure of security failure from
Newer cars have lots of cool gear
That keeps you safe on the roads
The older cars don't fare as well and some of the performance testing
That way
Because of the the great capabilities that
Computer system to call activity can actually bring
So I think that's the number one lesson is that we want to preserve Trust
It is more safe
Vehicles
Okay
So don't panic
Buy a newer car as opposed to one that has no technical things because it's probably going to be packed with safety gear that is
More likely to save your life than someone is to hack
Yep that's right and just a brief aside there was also another talk about
Autonomous vehicles
And
The national highway traffic safety administration
Ministration Nitsa
Measures the number of deaths per year at around 35000
I am like 94% of those are caused by human error of some sort so
Let's be single.
I ended up where it was related to an autonomy
Driving vehicle
I'm not even fully autonomous just driver-assist
I believe that's what caused it
And there
Still very bullish
On the idea of having
This driver assist feature because it will save lives
So as we look at these types of things that make headlines
If you want to talk about
It's also important to keep those in contacts
So if there's
One death per day
Drum driver assist vehicle but there's 80 deaths per day
From a
Non driver assist vehicles
Then keeping that it within context helps us see the bigger broader impact
Improved rather than
Decrease safety
So now
There were tons of exciting hacks
What's the most
I think the one that got the most headlines was probably
The Bluetooth locks being hacked
And this was
Someone who hacked
I see it was 12 out of 16 available Bluetooth lock
And
So what is your take
Yeah that all sounds really scary but
There's actually a Lockpick
Village where they can teach you to do more effective techniques against a broader array of locks
From the same distance
That is right next to a door
That within some certain proximity of it
A lot faster
With the traditional
So
While the Bluetooth
Lock hack
Is definitely scary and there's some
Very basic hygiene
Seems like. Missed
Those on the
The computer side the Bluetooth side and the beauty logic
Processed as well as on
Basic physical gear
Like you mentioned
Screwdriver can let you in
That's your
Well that's the level of physical security that you're putting into these days
It's no wonder that some of the computer
Security stuff is not
But again to put that in perspective somebody's got to be really close to it
And if they're really close to it
They can just smash them
Yeah
There's someone
Yeah so the real security that most of these blocks
Provide
Is that the delay of someone getting in
So it
Hopefully gives you time to detect them and respond to it
Or it stops a casual person
Being able to get in
Undetected
If somebody smashes your door
To get in
Rob you
Then obviously that leaves a trail
You're able to get in by picking the lock or by
Breaking the Bluetooth locking mechanism
And there's no detective capability you don't know someone
Was in there
To be
Your worst
In some cases that might be worse than more disturbing than two
Not your door off its hinges
Somebody's kicked it up
Yes it could still be in the house every babysitters nightmare
Adjust for Alyssa
Some of the
Step were hacked
Were made by quick luck
Iblue lock
Plant Rico
COV
El cycle
Okie dokie and mesh motion
I did reach out to August
Maker of the
Ever-popular August locks
And they said
August locks use AES encryption Cipher Block Chain on top of the standard blue
Encryption
And they've actually been working with
Those hackers for a while now just to make sure there's
Ask yourself
If you have an August lock
About it
If you have one of those other locks
Hayfield Lesco
The floor we also saw the first ransomware
On a thermostat I believe
Is this something I should worry about
Yes first demonstrated rants
Somewhere on a thermostat so this is
It's essentially
Research and the researchers did a proof-of-concept demonstration
Which is
Maybe not something that's viable in real life
Now you don't have to worry about the exact structure that they use
Which required physical access to the device
Security card
Buckets
Type of thing
Is very similar to actually the last
Thing I was on your show talking about Stacey
Witches in some of the coming
Potential problems in the Internet of Things
When you're connecting everything to the internet
And it software wasn't built to be connected to the internet it wasn't designed to resist
Accidental adversaries
Then it's potentially susceptible to any type
The specific one demonstrated here wasn't real they didn't release it into the wild
However what it did is it essentially set your thermostat on some consistent level and said
NBA Bitcoin
Or you'll never be able to change
The temperature again
Which is actually a common type of technique
Used in other computer systems and we've actually seen it
Accidentally hit some healthcare equipment and the researchers he reported that same type of capability
To a new platform
Type of pots
And there's a growing body of evidence to suggest that this type of attack holding
Home systems for ransom
Might actually be something that's coming
The future
Secure spannabis a robot
Dirty saw that in the first episode of
Reason why season 2
Where a smart home was
Essentially entirely taken over
And if you're watching the
Mr. robot show
And did you read the document that we put out in
March
On
Smart Homes in the internet of everything
We had a kind of Doomsday scenario and
Which looks a lot like the mr. robot scenario which is going to need to have predicted
Mr. robot
Maybe they just stole it
Listeners by the way I will link in the show notes to the episode that but was on so
If you're if you want to lose some sleep
You can go listen to that
Make a secure you should go
So
Absolutely
Physical access because this is something
I feel like when I think about
Securing connected devices
Stairs
Can I have to ask myself is this
Physical access
Desperate
Is this a threat
From the wireless radios like
Pekin overheard a man-in-the-middle type attacks
Is this a threat
Like getting my data or passwords from someone else's
In Astoria still in the cloud
Or is this
Let's see
I don't know what else there is what other category should I be worried about
If I'm thinking about this like as a
Normal consumer
Right so there's many different levels to take on
Because you kind of talked about the physical access
One thing to keep in mind is a lot of the radio that are typically used
Talking to this thing
Such as Bluetooth
Have a certain range
Thursday
Normal range that is supposed to work in
And then there's the Amplified rain
Which I think the research has demonstrated a quarter of mile to isn't the Bluetooth
Assistance
Are the some of the
That's a larger threat surface
Or potential number of attackers
Then if it's a physical thing where you need a screwdriver to get in
But it's also a smaller
Attack surface
At War number of physical attackers
Then something that's connected to the internet where it could be
Attacked by a new
The five billion or so people
You have access to the
This is one of the interesting parts of
Looking at
Smart devices
Is as weekend the model
Home lock
We assume that someone will be right there don't need to be right there to jump
To defeat that lock
On the internet
Someone could be anywhere in the world so
The number of potential attacker
This way up
And as we know in most cases it only takes one person
With an internet connection who wants to do something
To be able to pull it off
Know that sounds really scary until you think
What is the good of having someone unlock my door unless they're actually outside my house
That's a great question and I think we've
Come to the point where
We no longer have to ask
Can we do some
Talking with technology
But we haven't yet started to ask
In all cases
Should we
Judas with the type
I think that might be the growing
Question that
Manufacturers
Should be asking you that
Consumers more important
We should be asking
Do I want this device
To be unlocked
Do I want my front door to be unlocked
From anyone on the internet
Or is it sufficient
Stop someone right there doing it
Highway
Bluetooth
Or with it
Number combination
Warwick Davis
God forbid a physical lock
I have one
That's kind of good to think about I actually have had
Milocks
So I have a Kwikset zwave lock
And I have them attached to a wink hub
And I had a lovely hacker come over to my house hack into my wink hub
And through that he actually was able to unlock my
Z-Wave locks
And I was like
Suck
It didn't take him quite some time and
To be fair I did have to give him my Wifi password
It was a bit of a contrived situation
2Xtreme
So if we're not worried about Bluetooth locks
We might be worried about rants
Which I would die if someone took over my thermostat and said you know
You can't have it
Set it to anything about like 77 in
Summer
So
What else did you see anything else there that you're like
Oh man
We should also worry about this
Maybe on the medical device
Well I'll tell you this
Maybe not
Hey we should worry about this but I saw a lot of things going on with
Here's what we can do to
Did you better
And one of those was at
Bsides Las Vegas
I am the cavalry
I'm also part of
I had a track
On
Any updates
So what the landscape look like
As well as an attempt
To come to some
Really good profound
Discoveries about what we will need in order
Virtu at scale
Ensure that
Technology that has the ability to
Impact Public Safety in human life
That is worthy of the trace
The trust that we place in it
So
The details of that you can check out through videos which will soon be released by besides
But I think we made a lot of good progress on figuring out what each of the stakeholders
In that ecosystem
Including buyers can potentially do
I took make sure that
They're more secure and
More safe
Okay so do you want to give me like the top two things
Buyers can do
Sure
We already talked about one of them witches don't panic
Understand things in their contacts
And understand that when you're getting a
Driver-assist
Type vehicle that
Can automatically pilot you around
That a single exotic death
Or single exoticaxxx
Should not offset the games
From the many many Monday in Acts
Consider prevent
Another thing is to going to ask question
For Physicians
You are looking at new medical devices are hospitals are looking at new medical devices
Or patient
Ask whoever is in the conversation with you
What's the safety what's the f
To see what's the security of this device
Same thing goes for people buying home devices
No ask at the store
It turns out as we
Talked about last time I believe the customer is asking it
Store-level
Is actually a really good lover to be able to go back to the manufacturers and say hey everybody's asked me about this
What do I tell them
And then maybe a third thing is to look for certain indicators
Security measures are
Precautions
So if you look for things like coordinated vulnerability disclosure program
It's a manufacturer
Makes available
It seems an indicator to the market that
We're very confident safety
Security of our products
To the point where we invite people who
Find flaws in
DFCS
Tell us about them so that we can make them better
Okay cuz I was like what the what
I don't even know what that is but you're talking about a bug Bounty Pro
Bug bounties one instantiation a bug Bounty is a system where a company pays researchers
4 flaws and they find
There's another one which has a lower bar which basically just says
We won't see you if you report in good faith
So there's lots of people who are out there using their devices and accidentally run across flaws
In certain cases
Manufacturers have either ignored reports of this laws or have actively tried to sue researchers or others
Fishing report those laws
So I message from the manufacturer that says
We won't sue you because we believe that our customers
Must be protected
Against these types of laws
Yeah that's a good indicator
Okay
So super fast
If I
If your manufacturer look to build in Safety and Security in Europe
Tire design
Life cycle
Take reports of flaws or
Defects from those who find them
And work with them
And third make sure that your
Products are updatable
So that
When there is something better way that snow nor
Aeroflot it's found
You can respond to that and at least
Make the fix available
All right
Are there are there other
People in this value chain we should talk about
Government
Yes
For policymakers
It's a subtle nuance
Thing sometimes
Different stakeholders within the government can have different roles
One that's taking a
Particularly active interest is the Federal Trade Commission
Who looks at things like
Baby monitors
Stay they are secure
Actually they're not sick
And looking at claims versus actual
Effectiveness
Food and Drug Administration has done a great job to date
Coming up to speed on cyber security and safety issues within medical devices
The Department of Transportation has recently shown some good sign that they're coming on board
I in January they published
A roadmap of what their working
Towards
This year
And one of those was to work with security researchers you often find flaws
And you can help be a part of getting those flaws fix
Strengthen the automotive ecosystem
Alright well
Thank you so much for both sharing your experience
Was there another one
Share your scary experience
And for reminding us what's important
When it comes to thinking about buying connected products
Thank you
Thank you Stacey it's always a pleasure to be on
So excited about the internet of things do you want more news make sure you sign up for my newsletter de Seno's things
At Stacey on iot. Com will see you next week