Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Your co-host
Kevin tofel
Today we have got a great show for you we have got
Nest new features from it
We're going to talk about the Amazon.
Intapp we got
Awesome updates on semiconductor sales
We've got mozilla's
Iot strategy
What's up with that
And I'm a
Even talk to you about why I
I'm not sure we should call the Internet of Things The Internet of Things anymore
So
Big Show
But because I'm traveling
A the sound quality maybe a little iffy
MP we don't have a guest
This is Jessica Kevin and Stacey
Baby show
We'll make due
We had a blast.
All right now wait to get to the Amazon stuff we'll talk about it later
West 1st
Asperger's
So
Nest isn't
I think
Is great will let you talk about it
Yes there are two new features coming to Nest thermostats which is nice cuz we never had we had a ton of
New features lately the two figures are family accounts and home away assist
They are pretty much what they sound like
Family counts
You don't have to after the you get this update you won't have to
Share your login your password
Because right now
You don't like on my Nest I'm signed in with my own Gmail account and
Amion password
I have to give that to everybody in the family not a big deal
Pretty much trust my family but still
It can be a bit of a hassle for other people who want to share their nest
Access family access to the
Set thermostat without
Sharing credentials so that's kind of
Cool
Leaving the throne copy of the monthly home report
Which I like to see all my little leaves as i r in them
Solar house
Lots of leaves on trees
Yes so there's that I know you're pretty excited about the family accounts
I am so
Well I'm excited about boats
The second picture is
Basically it's an improvement on the features
Nest traditionally has used
IR sensor proximity sensor
Tire sensor on the thermostat
But they've also built
What's an algorithm
Hey early in the morning if you don't sense motion
It's most likely that someone has left the house
Like for the day
And so it'll more quickly transition to the away mode when they
Turn off your heat or AC
If possible
And so
What they've done now is there using you
Your phone
Because I don't know I just happens to me a lot cuz my office
It's not near the thermostat I'll be in my office for a while
What happened
My head out
And I'm in the same boat because my home office is on the second floor of the nests in the first floor in
You know their initial attempt to do home away settings I think was a step forward at the time
But now they're taking advantage of
Available hardware and smarts today
To bring It Forward even more I think
Yes there's a couple things
This one is the big macro thing that I love from
Twitches
Masters final
Getting things ready for the fact
People don't live in a home by themselves people live in a home usually
So
This is great because the family account
How to make it
Very easy to share and you don't like let's say you've got
Airbnb are you get gas coming and you can't even give him that without compromise
Security
And also kind of comes back to this idea of like your home
Maybe getting its own email address
Previous shows about this
Send
Scott Jensen
Who works at Google
He's like
I don't actually like my home having an email address
It's still better than one person
Being tied to a device so having a home
Or Family Ties
Two devices
And then the same thing for the
A wasting that's also a nice way to kind of keep track of a number of people in the home
Especially in a larger home with
Upstairs Downstairs
Unless whatever
Working on this with Integrations from
A bunch of other partners like
Zoo leaders I'm testing out some lights right now that that I'm home
Even when I'm not in front of my nest
So there's
There's other ways of doing this that aren't the phone
Especially
If you're someone who
It's like
I don't have a cell phone
Or you got a kid that maybe doesn't
Actually that's the key I don't know if he made that clear up front so I apologize for the home away assist uses
Your phone data sensors on your phone
To help Nest understand who
Is home and or who is away
Whether it's GPS sensors or whatever else
Rental homes
So they're expanding their
Smart around proximity who is home and
Is anybody home and visitor who is it
So this is an opt-in feature by the way
It says when family members opt-in
It lets the harmonious use data from the phone
For the nest so you don't have to use
This feature I know some people may have concerns about privacy and
GPS in geofencing and all that so
But the nice thing is if you do opt in
The home away assist won't switch
To away
If they're still somebody in the house if it and it knows that through the phone
So I like this because Nest is it essentially
Expanding its presence
Yeah and if you think about it it also gives you away to say hey
If I'm the only person in the whole because now it's got a family account
It can say
Stacy is right now the only person home
I could then setup my Integrations to work
With things I like when I'm home
So that's kind of cool especially if you
Like you and your
Pick another fight a lot over the
Temperature
Like
This is not a feature by the way that Nest is offering now
Thinking forward
Think about things like
My guess is Stacy's home
She likes it you know 75 degree
Oh Stacy's husband's home and he's by himself he loves it
I would expect them to expand
To that type of personalization
In the future man I know I will see a technical reason for not happening
I don't either
What does it mean
It will
Complex and then they've always been
Depart of themselves on being
Really easy for
Consumers to get
So you don't have to wake
There's not a lot of programming there's not a lot of
Conditional statements you're making
You know a lot of that stuff that
Happens with a lot of other application
Ensign services
Okay
So that is the nest news and it's pretty good
I can't wait to try these features on my nest and see what have
Will light in the South with Mozilla and its iot strata
Kevin has a penny
We should say back in February so February Mazzella said hey we're going to not be
A mobile browser kind of
I think we're going to be a connected device company
And they decided that that's where they were going to focus
Add Mozilla
You're not aware is the creator of the Firefox browser
Tan and gray things to advance the web in an open-source over the past house at least decade
And I have nothing but respect for what they've done
And unfortunately hasn't really panned out
Firefox browser market share has been declining in the face of other browsers and Salon
And they're kind of pivoting a little bit but
You know I think there's still a lot they can do here I think it's a smart move for them to get into it IRT
Space I mean
You stepped back a week because they announced a couple of
A potential Solutions as they say on their on their blog for iot such as
Endless Run 3 is real quick project link
Which is at personal user agent that understands preferences for how you want to interact with devices
Father's project sensor web so it's a way to get
Data from sensors to
Apps and such there it is
Project Smart Home
Which they say is a middle ground between solution such as apple homekit and the Raspberry Pi so they want to
Middle Ground between the in a box solution and then do it yourself
Elena project Vanni which is an
IRT enabler package for developers and device makers
I want to add a voice interface to their devices which sounds really cool
It all sounds really cool I'll be honest
Banana pudding on my
Opinion hat for a second
And it just seems to me like
A lot of this already exists
And it works
Pretty well
So it kind of saddens me to see Missoula used too often be at the Forefront of new technology
And leading the way perfectly with some
Open source approaches to it
Now trying to
I'll say ketchup
To say for voicemail
Go to the series in the Google Now is in the Amazon voice services and so on
And I say that because when I look at their Wiki
Thanks for that project Danny which is the voice enabling
They're saying right now the van team is brainstorming how we can create our own unique solution that does not have to compete with or catch up with
The existing players such as Siri and Google Now
It seems like they're just
Floating an idea out there that really not don't have a lot of focus yet and I'm not sure there's a big need for what they're going to
Potentially offer if they offer anything at all
So that's the best I take my pain and head off now and I'll shoot it over to you for your thoughts cuz
I want a bathroom too much air
No that's fine in time
Privacy and
Which I think is a reason
That you could
See something like this flourishing
And maybe Danny is a terrible example
The project smart home sounds a lot like
Something like SmartThings only
It sounds like it would be completely open as opposed to being built
I would love
Something like this I think if it got enough market share
You could see
Developers building for this
In a way that
It makes him not have to participate with some of these closed-door ecosystems
Resources you could just pick one that you could pick something
Hidden Lake Project
Especially with them
Established already
And in their wikis
Things on it
Wow this is really
I'm with you on
Choices good in the end they could offer something at the others
Don't especially when it comes to you no privacy security
Simplicity. Some of the things you did mention
But is that going to be enough
At this point in time
I don't know I do know there are things I would like
So on The Voice side I would love to see if I can if this then that service
Integration
Amazon Echo
So I think that would be
Awesome
If I were
It just a little bit easier than their STK which is
Great Bear Lake
Developers
Going to build their own
Suffer for this a little easier and I think it'd be kind of
Awesome to have it
So I think that would be
On the open side you know if if they could create like a true bridge between something like homekit and all the other stuff out on the
Market
That would be really valuable
You just don't know if that's
In all of these are very much
Much like
We are literally throwing this
You know props to them for being late
Hey Ya
So that's what mozilla's doing
I think we should probably talk
About what would you chew quick items
Amazon
We are going to talk
A report came out
For the McLean group
Semiconductors
You guys are like
Who cares but
We are about to hit
1 trillion semiconductors sold by 2018
In a single year
That is one trillion
And that is a lot
A semiconductor
What's kind of exciting
And it just give you a sense the industry is expected to sell
An 86.7
This year
September
This is all anytime.
Play ten million
Yeah and then they say 950 billion Siamese next year and then it's
1.02 trillion in
In 2018 which has happened to coincide with the number of zeros in a trillion 18
Ingrate
We know cuz we chat before the show
We did
Before you guys get like and it's not just the Internet of Things
This is just a
Ramp up
We just use more chips because we can there cheaper
The average selling price of these chips
Is only $0.30
It's because over 70% of these chips are in
Include
Opto sensor discrete
So these are like tiny little things like actuators
Resistor is little power management chips
Little tiny bits that you
You sticking
Senior phone
International single-purpose
It's been expensive chips
That brings the average selling price down
But they're still
Pisces which are integrated circuits which of the fancier things like
Microcontrollers
Application process Solutions
Server chips
So lot of chips
It was crazy about this as if this didn't happen I mean I mean I know this is going to sound obvious but
Your phone's wouldn't be as powerful as inexpensive as they are relatively
Expensive
Iot devices to be a lot more of the easier to get into that market
It just it's amazing
What is impacts
It's
Are everywhere
So
Yay 1 trillion
All right that's it
Weird passive Wi-Fi I just wanted to drop you
Because it's not real it's not
Commercialized
I mean it's real that people
What is making stuff up today
No this is real but it's still research that needs to be commercialized so
Take that as
It's called
Passive Wi-Fi and its
It's low power Wi-Fi in this isn't like the Halo Wi-Fi spec which is
At the Wi-Fi Alliance right now trying to get certified this is
Actually
A way to
Transmit Wi-Fi signals using kind of a reflection of a signal called Backscatter
To transmit the data so
Like ten thousand
Sometimes less powers
That's a huge huge difference in terms of power and
Well I wouldn't say something like this say in a connection that you want always on and always fast cuz I think at the moment they test
I stood up to 11 megabits per second
You know I could see it lesson phones and tablets and TVs and such
Four more in iot devices which
Today might use Bluetooth instead of Wi-Fi and so on
So you're getting Bluetooth like speeds but even
Much less power than the Bluetooth
Yeah and what's kind of neat about it is
It's much more Distributing so it's kind of like a peer-to-peer data
Link as opposed to Lake
Your thing talking to your router and then to the public internet
The things can actually use this to talk to each other
And then back to the
So
From an architecture
This is kind of really fascinating to
But we're just thinking about it
Research being done
At the University of Hawaii
And it looks like I killed a company
Call jeeva Wireless jeeva
To help commercial Isis
So
Be interesting to see if they make this happen
Yeah but they've been working on it actually since
So let's go
Hopefully all right
Shall we do it
Let's do it been waiting for days to do it
Dino Amazon
Which is 2 days after
Recorded it so
Yeah
Lunch tomorrow or the next day
Kevin
All right
Foremost
Everybody Knows by now but for those that do not
Amazon has added two new Echo devices
3D family of echo products
When we we had rumors I've been kind of knew about that would be what is called the Amazon tap
And that is a smaller version of the current Hardware
But it's also portable battery powered
And yes you do have to tap the button or press the button before you can get your voice services
Go and get your
You commands in such
The other one kind of came out of left
Field
And I think
You and I both ordered it on day one
We did that is the echo Dot
So imagine if you will
Somebody
Smashing down Amazon Echo pushing straight down on it to get rid of the your speaker in the height and all that
And that comes up with something that's maybe I don't know 2in tall looks like a hockey puck
It's like the top of the echo in the bottom of the echo no middle
That's because you're just speaker inside it short of a small speaker similar phone speaker
So the
God
Is always listening always on which is nice
However if you're going to use it for music you would Bluetooth or wired parrot 2
A set of speakers
So it's basically
An echo without the speaker
The way to add your own speakers to the
Self but you prices for these are 12999 for the portable
Echo tap
And 8999 for the echo Dot
An interesting way
You can only order the.
Through your existing Amazon Echo you had to ask
She We Shall Not Be Named to order an echo. Which
Work well for me and I'll die for you
Super Why
If you work around 6
You could do like
I think it is
You could go to the app and do it
Some things like that
If you really want it.
So quick take you want to go for it or should I go
Well we both were the same thing
So let's talk about why you didn't and I can do the same
Why you didn't order the Amazon tap
Alexa enabled portable speaker
So Timmy the tap looks like kind of like we said originally when we were talking about the
Does product because it's portable it doesn't have the always-on speaker capability
Anatomy voice is a hands-free kind of
User interface and tap to touch something to talk to it
Sex the magic real
So it feels like Amazon here is
I don't know if they're testing
The viability of portability
With this product
To see if that you know has
Is leg somewhere
Send me $430 to get basically a Bluetooth speaker with with Amazon voice services
A lot of money
Nothing I wanted yeah I mean it's all about the portability
I completely agree with you
And I don't think I'm going to changes having to Tap a button
To do voice services
It does take the magic out
What is the
Like the magic the coolest thing about the current Echo it's the fact that
Anybody who is it within voice range can ask it a question send a command get information
Having to walk over and tap the button I know it sounds like a
First world problems
Really that's the magic of the device so
I'm a little disappointed this this comes with a little charging puff that you plug in and you set this Amazon tap on tablet
Charging pack
And I really thought I think I said in a private show
I really thought
Maybe they will enable it so that if it's sitting on the charging
Meaning it's not going to use the internal battery for power
Maybe we're having always listening mode it does not from what I can see so far
That could be changing the future but then again
It is called the tap I don't think I'm going to take the path away
Ya don't say anything
Cute app
How do you feel about this
A little device
So
I don't know
So that's
I am very curious
Like looks at the tap
That is something I need in my life
Please let us know why
We won't make fun of you really really
Maybe I'll go
The voice is Magic
Maybe I mean and I totally get the pole portability thing I mean I've always wish I could it was easier to move around the current
Echo that I have
The answer right now is go buy more echoes
So this geocache this is another Echo but this can go anywhere in the battery will last for up to 9 hours of playback and
And if it had always on voice
Listening then it would last for 9 hours so I totally understand why they're doing it that way
It doesn't give you any other features that
The existing Echo has other than really portability
Now on to the Amazon
I ordered it
You ordered it
Kevin
I mean the fact is okay it's
It's an Echo - the Maine
Speaker
But
I can put several of these around the house
And instead of having to
Going to a particular room to use the the echo on you know I can do it throughout my house now it's
Adding microphones and stands small speakers in the House Everywhere I Go
Be invisible interface that's what I want my house wherever I am in the house if I want
To control the house
Music writer I just want to do what I don't have
I have to go somewhere or Tap a button
Or whatnot so
Doesn't do anything differently but
I just like the idea of
Buying one of these as opposed to
Spending
You know double the money for a full
Amazon Echo
Also a lot of people really like to use their own speakers
So
You can do this
You can do that with that since I meant to do that so I like that as well I don't need speakers in every room
Define with
Just having a small phone like speaker that can read back anything I ask
The echo so I'm fine with that so to me it's just a way to expand my echo ecosystem in the house
At a relatively low cost
Two of those for one Echo
And so
If I cuz I was looking at
Buy another
So
Where is your Echo today where do you think
My echo today is about 3 feet from where I'm sitting right now on my second floor home office
Yeah I do have
A Fire TV with a voice remote downstairs in one of the base of the family room
So we could do
Things through
Through the voice service through that
I hope I put this closer to the kitchen and the main living room
Because that's where I spend most of our time
Will I use an external speaker and play music on it
I don't know
We're going to have like a Jambox I could always wire to that or Bluetooth it to that
So maybe
But it's getting more for informational and smart home control things for me
Wiring it into my receiver in
Sticking
In my living room
And so
But it would go
Over my
My speakers
And then I'd have all the home control that we already have and then I've moved
Upstairs
Go to my officer I still want one in the bathroom
Do that the places where we are the most are the places where we want to
Control the lights that are around us in the rooms around us when I control the thermostat
Do you know
This is crazy
Is I want I want to just go out while I'm in the shower like Play the song
And I want to know what time it is
Possibly information about like my day or my commute
You know while I'm getting ready
So
I don't actually
For my bathroom
Which is why my husband thinks I'm crazy for putting something because he thinks of it totally is a home
Echo please flush
Touchless
No no no
Sorry
That's kind of
I really actually that's one of the
Few places where I wanted to have like a higher-quality
That makes sense and as far as the speaker goes
You know I have not heard it I mean that we're buying this Sight & Sound on scene
But it basically they do say it includes a built-in speaker
So you can use it as a Smart Alarm Clock in the bedroom and assisted in the kitchen etcetera so
Don't feel like you must attach speakers to it if you're just going to use it as a voice
Assistant type device
You know it will work
It's not mandatory to add speakers to it that would be if you're going to listen to music
It's interesting to me because it essentially
This has become similar to my current Android phone which
I can
You know a cat by saying OK Google at any time and then perform voice command
And that's always with me so it's very similar in that regard
This is so tied into my smart home
System right now that
It just made sense for me to buy
Right
So March 31st is when we get ours
What's happening
I'm curious if you know it seems to me like they weren't sure this was going to
A big hit just yet so they did what they've done before The Limited
Who can purchase at 6 women to one unit per order and only 2 per customer
And you had to buy a technically had to buy it
Through
The echo
Set what wax you could through do it you're an Amazon Fire TV as well so
I would have things I don't know that you know
Mass-produced
Ginormous run of these
As of yet
It may just be a test
That kind of
Amazon
But I did think it was kind of weird
Because I'm very curious like with a lot of people
Reading about the ecobee
Successful
And now I'm at this tiny little one
Instead
Cuz it is to say it's a nice lower price points so we'll see
And
I don't know why I can't wait
Yeah I'm looking for 2 minutes again it doesn't do anything that
The current one doesn't do base the right price point and it's an easy way to expand if you would like the Amazon ecosystem
We do
Yay
Okay
The only other thing I wanted to talk about first episode about a bill that was introduced to the Senate last
End
This is just introduced it may not go anywhere but it's worth talking about because
How to get the Internet of Things
Digit bill
It's to get the FCC the Federal Communications
Commissioned to do a report on and then to regulate The Internet of Things
Which is worth notice
Because
Up until now most of the efforts around iot
I've actually been
Federal Trade Commission
To the FTC
And that's been around things like data privacy
And devices
Give that up
So there Ben a couple finds out there
Basically on establish laws and then now the f
CC
Is saying an innocent been kind of burbling over in Washington
Entities to agencies
Has it been like
Maybe I'll take care of the internet
I got it I got I got
So this bill
Is basically saying hey
Let's give it to the Federal Communications Commission
And it's
It's calling for a working group till like study this
Again
And they want the FCC to study whether there's enough Spectrum
Yeah the regulatory barriers that might
Exist
Getting more Spectrum
Understanding what government
Stakeholder should be involved in any other regulatory processes
I think it makes more sense to be with the FCC then with the FTC quite honestly
What does spectrum stuff
Yes there is there's a role for the ftce
Asking several agencies to get together to
Can a Prius medical reports that will
One day possibly lead to laws
After this one day possibly leads to Allah
And those agencies of the Department of
Asportation
Tftc the National Science Foundation and the Department of Commerce including at the national telecommunications and information
Administration
If this is a little bit different I think then then Pryor
Industry efforts to either regulator
Monitor or protect
Citizens and such because
IRT is such a broad range of devices and services
We talked about car so how do you not have an automobile Regulatory Commission not involved
It may make sense in this case to
As broad collaboration
Between these groups
Security and safety in
How things will work together and so on so
I don't have a problem with this I'm not saying that I'm in all four more regulations or anything but
This is something that is
This is literally calling for
A report
Now that I'm for it
Make a report it's going to be like
I better run along cuz this industry is changing very quickly
Very quickly
It is so this is the developing Innovation and growing The Internet of Things at
Which I wonder if you come up with a lob
The clever acronyms
Probably not
Done
So this is it this is out there
If you guys want to look it up
Go for it
Try to follow it
We'll keep an eye on it
Interesting happens there
I think that's
I'll be at South by Southwest next week
Fighting for their review
Are you guys
So far
And who knows
Sounds good
That's all for this week
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week on the Internet of Things podcast