Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today your co-host is
None of the Mike wall
Mike Wolfe who is
The founder of founder in podcast Iran
The smart home show so if you like our show you'd probably like his show
Mike thanks for joining
Yeah I'm really excited I was out your way last week
It's out by
We're to talk about that on the show so this week's show we're going to talk about
What Apple didn't announce
With its
Event on Monday
Weird to talk about
Retail and selling the smart home and we're also going to talk about cool kitchen devices that we saw at South by
And we may even get into
Some Enterprise stuff with Bashas new
Cloud for The Internet of Things
And this week
Our Guest is Daniel Conrad
Who is the CEO of beat Networks
And we're going to talk about
Laura
A low-power
Wireless area.
So stay tuned
It's going to be off
Okay Mike
Taking it off
Apple
Monday new smaller iPad
Smaller iPhone
No homekit
Were you surprised
I wasn't
I mean I think the last big
Apple shindig that had conference they mentioned it once in almost in passing
And I knew from coming
The previews are going to be about mobile devices and so
I didn't even TuneIn
Cuz at this point
I'm not expecting homekit news
So I wasn't surprised it didn't announce homekit news
Man I'm really disappointed mean if you were betting on homekit
It feels like we should be a little further along or am I just going to crazy
Well think back a year ago coming out of Cs last year
It felt like the story of the year
4 smart on this going to be
Homekit
There's so much excitement
A lot of companies were really a lot of startups for investing Alder
Development hours in Oak get in
The year went by
It was it was fairly disappointing cuz there's a lack of news things move very slowly
And so
I think
I went to the energy Industries moved on but a lot of startups
Who were betting
I don't get a year ago
Have turn all of their resources elsewhere
For this point
They're turning the resources to
She Who Shall Not Be Named the Amazon Echo its
It seems like
Of all the smartphone platform set feels like
Where I'm seeing
The most kind of traction
I agree I mean the reality is
To roll out a hunka device is a little more involved in integration with
Amazon
Echo as simple as more of a software integration you do cloud-to-cloud with
Homekit it actually involves
Hardware near me
Balls of chips o
And if you're waiting for Apple to give you the green light
On that thing you're going to be trouble you can have a lot of money stuck in inventory
That isn't available ship so I see why companies moving on
Man so can apple come back from this do you think
It's Apple so you can't right now blog
Mom I think that
You know if they decide
Serious about this
Yeah I mean
It's funny I was talking to someone
Could meet some folks from Apple they said something to the effect like
Wow homekit
So you guys are really into the smart home and
I think the response was like
Well we're not really into the smart home so
It just feels like
There it was almost I bring this before
It feels like it's going to head for them they basically wanted their toe in the water to say hey were going to do something here in for bookmarking this
But they haven't really
Taking it too seriously and I think quite frankly it was more complicated than they thought I think
It's what's up with a rollout
Like a new accessory or new
Interface like
You know that dinner is about to do a smart on platform I think it's Walmart, catechism
Ecosystem have to juggle
Right and
The way they're going about it with
Security efforts and then having profiles for each individual device that
Built up and then certified is
Pretty
That's pretty laborious both for apple and for the people who are going through the companies that are going to be home kits or
Daiso
Yeah I get it and see no just speaking of someone who's trying to make things work in her own house
You don't need things to play nicely together is not
It's not easy maybe we won't see this and maybe I should give up
Don't give up me to the credit I think that you know we should say that
Good for them for considering
Security and making out like that the number one priority cuz I think that's
Really it's first and foremost thing in their mind
That is so
I think that's probably why
A big reason why the movie Sully so I bought that
But also
You know seems like
Then she's moving on all of it
Yeah and they require a hardware that require an mfi search
Certified ship so
If your Hardware isn't
Going to be built with that
Then
You're never going to be
That device is never going to be home
So
All right moving on to
New things in retail when I was at South by I actually sat on a panel with someone from beta and I kicked myself
For not
Because the week before I was in Palo Alto
And I didn't go into the store
So for listeners who are like what the heck
This is beta
And it's a new kind of retail Concepts that
Shows off the connected devices
Before you buy them and they don't actually care if you buy them there
It's really all about the data for the
Mike you said you had written a bit about them
Yeah it is
Beta I believe it
A lowercase b
Please don't don't put a capital B on their Stacy
I always have trouble writing when I start them with the
But
I
Hammer and about them that you know the way they pitch the service is
Retail as a service so they basically
Biking it to it like a cloud where you basically can rent
Capacity in the form of shelf space
What I like about that is it's much
It's a showroom concept
So you can
Beastly
Take a product put it on the store shelves they don't only Midori
And say you're a big company or small company you want to see if you
Your company or your product is resonating with consumers
You can base it put it in beta and see how consumers react to it cuz they've invested a lot into
In the store
Engagement Analytics
So you can
Shopkins how much time consumers are spending in front of your device
I think that you did a blog post or an infographic
Or I can award at Israel Oscar
Can Oscars
Awarding the most engaging smart on products or more smart devices
Until they have really fine-tune analytics around how many time
Time people are spending with the price if you think it's really important in
It's a different kind of concept
Compared to regular retail which I don't think they get that detail
So I think it's
Victor Nutra Scott up for the iot age
Yeah a lot of the so
Kind of some of the things that are little bit different
From talking to the guy from beta
Ido if you wanted to do an order with Like Home Depot or Lowe's or another big box retailer
You know
You will sit they ask you for a set amount of product so
How many units and it's usually quite a bit
And you ship it to them
And then
You actually don't have any sense of how it's doing as a manufacturer unless you like
Wander around all the stores and check out
Which is empty which is
Which cells are full that you don't get a lot of that data from the retailer
And the beta model is that you will get a lot of data it's not the same kind of data cuz
Betta isn't is concerned
But actually selling
Through
But
If your
If you've got a product that's kind of young
And you're like
Hey people are clicking on your video
But then they're just walking away and
Where they walk away in the middle of your video
You know that you was not properly
Only done well right
That people never pick up your device
You don't those kind of things are
Kind of really interesting
I will see if there correlated to higher sales or not I think that's still to be proven
Yeah I love what they're doing a mean one of the other things are requires that
The Product Company spend time in the store training their salespeople cuz
Unite no we go to the lake
Angelo's we go to
Some of these other stores big box retailers
A representative on the floor by the connect
They don't know what they're talking about but
Bouillabaisse reindeers make sure everyone on the show four is almost like someone
At a Genius Bar
And then Apple Store like really knows the product
I think that's
Really important
Cuz these products are so different and they require so much consumer education
Another thought I have is
I think this is going to be really interesting if the expanded footprint Beyond Silicon Valley
Impertinent
Yeah I mean
We all know if there's a better Google Engineers going in there that's a lot of a different than someone going in the middle Cleveland or or
Your Miami so I would be really interested to see how this
Scales as they moved to different geographies and I think it be hugely valuable to get data
From different cities
Around different products cuz I
You know something on Research I do
People react differently
Caprock stiffening what region they're from
Cuz I bring a lot of
Baggage depending on where they're from and they're kind of a lot of
The ways to think about products probably shaped by the way they're from
So I think it'll be interesting to see how they expand this outward
Yeah and this is
This is kind of in contrast to Target has their Smart Home store which I did pop my head into
Just to see what was there
Which is bear lab space for showing off Connect
Attitude products in
Their vision is all about showing how these products work
Together
The beta vision is just
The products individually
So I don't know if you have any thoughts on that the beta guy was like you know
I don't think people are really that's too big of a sail to be like
Hey this is going to work with this and this
The song
Play together
He's like you know people just want a one-off device for the most part today
So he he's like I don't think
Well I think they're different things I think
IPod idea
Showing consumers
Scenes and how things work together
Around consecrated use cases like in a baby's room
Waikiki tonight teens time to go to bed hers baby
But will you bring up Target
I just want to mention the secret of project that was in the news a couple weeks ago
Call Project goldfish
It's a secret project headed up by a guy named West Stringfellow
Have you heard about that Stacy
Heads down focused on some other stuff
Between now and then so
What is Project fi
Free which publication first broke I think it's movie twice or maybe actually Mini
Minnesota
Newspaper
It was discovered
Via a job posting on the
I'm a Target website
Or at a head of engineering sent you a CTL for a
Prodigal prodigal fish
The description was
Around the park was they wanted to reinvent retail
And use technology
Did you bring new experiences in
New products to Market
And
Is based in Silicon Valley
And it makes me wonder if there may be
Taking some of the things or warning in this lab which we talked about the connector
They're home store and maybe
Taking some other things maybe they're taking some contest from what they're seeing a betta who knows
It just will be interesting to see what they do is
It's a curious thing to look at each check it out
I am checking it out right now so yes I see West Stringfellow
Who is
Doing this it's pretty secretive
It came out while I was at South by so now I
Yeah there's not a lot of detail
That's looking at ways to streamline order fulfillment better manage inventory across all channels
That seems
I don't know I know that
Holiday season Target had been
Working on
Ways to manage inventory so
It's sometimes with ship items from the stores as opposed to from the
Warehouses to meet kind of demand
Especially if things weren't selling well in an area
But that is pretty in a
Yeah and
So it was also West repos one of their entrepreneurs in Residence
Another on Frontier residence
There is nothing called
Future future collab
Which is being put on by
Panda Adventure back by Target and audio
About Reinventing the food ecosystem
And that was
Being shepherded by another
Afternoon residence from Target to
It's interesting to see the stuff they're doing there they're trying to reinvent the food system another trying to create a new franchise with in Target
Targeted at
Recreating retail innocence
So pretty
I can't wait
OK in speaking of food
And food Tech
At South by Southwest
I ran into some cool companies and I thought of you because I went to your smart Kitchen Summit
Last November and it was awesome
And I saw a lot of these guys here
Size of Southwest that I've seen at the Smart Kitchen Summit such as teforia
Which makes the connected teapot for
Got it sells for an ungodly amount of money
I think it was pre-order for $700 at
MSRP is like
$1,400
Did you happen to eat
I did have some tea and
She made me green tea because I told her I didn't like green
She's like you will like the screen t
Like that green tea
If we did not hit did not turn me into a Believer I could tell it was different than the other green tea but
Yeah I wasn't
Truly honest was not sold
Are you seoul
Do you have one
It's a lot of money
So I probably won't buy one
I do have a
PECO
Brewberry Appliance coming soon I think they were there as well so I'm excited about that
I'm excited to brew my own beer cuz
I can see paint fabric
Preparing machine
I like beer
800 dollars for coffee maker that is not cam
So
I am totally fine
Spending a lot
And something that I really
Jacob Bernoulli
I was going to say speaking of alcohol
A company that
I was super pumped about this listeners of the show know that I am
Was there there a company that makes
These bottles
Toppers East Bluetooth powered bottle stoppers for your bar
And
In conjunction with an app you basically look up the cocktail you're trying to make so
Example that used with a sidecar
So you use cognac
In orange liqueur like a Grand Marnier or something
Lemon juice
So
I would have these Bernoulli bottle caps on top of my bottle of Cognac and on top of my bottle of Grand Marnier
And
Basically when I start pouring it
The app will tell the bottle cap
When to stop pouring
And then
It would be done
And then I picked up the other one and
It would be like I was she's got the
Grand Marnier
And I pour it and then the bottle cap stops the flow of liquid when I got however many ounces I think it's a
121 Conner a show there
I was just like yes this is awesome and it was eight of these bottle caps for
$300
But they won't ship
For a while they said the end of the year which I always add
Three months to
Yeah it's a different approach to
Common automated or smart bar
I mean another one to be the one from perfect company which they're also at the Summer Wars more descale ProScan like the Dropkick
Kitchen
In the Paso
Just tickets
It's a different approach I like the idea and I actually see commercial applications for the Bernoulli
ABC would love this because you couldn't have a heavy pour on your
You don't see all your alcohol with
Oh yeah you can also monitor how much liquor your
You're playing like if you're if you're trying to monitor how much alcohol is coming out like that might be like one way to do it
And make sure you get the Perfect Pour every time
Although I would say
My thoughts on this are kind
Conflicted because
I've use the cocktail function on the drop
Scale which is like the perfect
Do they have another
Perfect bacon
Pink Drink
Perfect drink
A perfect drink actually just do the deal with absolute
Sparta
To make better cocktails
Anyway
I kind of like the idea of doing
Scale approach because if you want to make your cocktails and batch and then bulk you can
Kind of adjust the recipe in a way that I'm not sure you
You could do with
Bratayley house I haven't played with it
And I think
Pictures are way better than the massive
Robot bartending kind of machines that you
Keep cut your liquor into
And then
You program that basically the drinks are
It's like oh I got the following six
In a bottles in the back of
Here's what I can make
Yeah they drink robots are interesting
Did you try the Keurig kold
Cat CSI had a cocktail
Made For Me by the Kirkwood I left you that is pretty good that's obviously
They're mixing
It is a pond a system
Mixing like a
Margarita mix into a
Some liquor but
There's lots of different ways I think bars becoming interesting as we applied technology to it
Final news element for us is Bosch
Which is the Robert Bosch company in Germany
You guys maybe like what
But they've actually done a lot of really cool stuff with Kinect
Two containers connected industry they call it industrie 4.0
All the German company Siemens
Bosch they're all like industry for a where I live
We are Manufacturing
My sensors
Bosch earlier this month they had their connection world event and they launched an iot cloud
Compete with
Looks like Kayla IBM's iot Cloud Amazon.
Pcloud
Azure has their eye on
So worth noting
Because Bob has such a play in
Automotive check-in sensors in manufacturing
Also because by golly
Who would have iot cloud
Take the GED
Of Europe you know they've been
Eating their own dog food
Could run iot for notices 2000-2018 they start requiring companies to get that expertise in house
And the other
Crater like these European Union wide
Charging networks with auto recharging all the stuff where they use iot technology
Looks like they're basically commercializing
I want what they've been warning or the past few years into their own cloud
Yeah and Bayliss we are spending 548 million dollars on Innovation and connected stuff
Which
Is maybe a lot
You're like what
So
It's a no less than 1% of their actual Revenue
But still
I'm not going to stop at it be
Because
They're clearly big Believers in the technology
We should I pay attention to them I don't know
That's it for this week show and less Mikey
You got anything else you want to share
Now this is been a lot of fun
I'm glad to catch up with
Yeah it's been used to work together
Always followed him because he's such a smart home expert
Smart home show iTunes
And he does a lot of stuff with the connected kitchen
Which
I love so
Yeah we're having another event
This year what happened in October
Okay
I know where I'm going to be
Is in Seattle
Yes you're coming out
I am there
Okay
So stay tuned because next up is Daniel Conrad the CEO of beat networks and we going to talk about
How hard it was for him to actually get into building a network
Or that he was building a
Connected speaker
So entrepreneurs listen up and then to we're going to learn about Laura which is one of the low-power wireless area Networks
Yay
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I have your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Daniel Conrad
Who is the
Co-founder and CEO of BP
Networks
Hey Stacy
I am super excited to have because
We are going to talk about low power Wireless
Area networks which is so hard to say about your
Torturous Journey
Torturous
Maybe I'll find it
Cruise
From any entrepreneur is the journey is a bit torque rest so I'll take it
Okay alright so
Google first started
It wasn't deep networks it was just beep
Correct
Okay and so
You may remember beef is this tiny beautiful
Basically
Wifi-connected speaker
And
Now it doesn't exist or it exists for
For a couple customers who bought it but Daniels you want to tell us what happened
Sure you are motivation throughout the history theater around like what is going to be the next
Platform
Transition that we see
And ever really excited up packet
The computers are a few bucks now
And they can be put inside of it
And what
First incarnation of
Deep was to take the functionality of Sonos
Put it on a check
And then
Bake that into
Every speaker that isn't Sonos
In the world
What's that connect everything
So it's kind of like we're going to be
The other speakers
What's first shot across the bow was the
Nexus line instead of the reference design which is this
The Shining
Copper on dial
Simultaneous
Music streaming is one of the most difficult things that you can do online
For any
Problems with it
Really really low
Virginia Russian music
You want to
You want to throw that thing out the window
Interesting technically challenging project
The problem was Ben Larkin
In a while we're working
Apple and Google
Amazon removing A Space Odyssey
You know the goal wasn't just to be
Computers
And speakers typically have microphones and to move in the direction where
In multiple rooms of the house you have a difference
Facing west
That are with with Chromecast
Google News aggressively into the space with Amazon moving into voice
It was pretty clear that the market opportunity for us is going away
So
We ended up
Having a sunset
Doctors
Give me
Couple of years into developing a shipping product
How many dollars investors money
When is the bad Andre
That was the other day
So that were
Really sad to see us go
Is this reality was able to build a large
Music streaming product
We're going to need to go in a different direction
So that has got to be
Tough how did your investors driving did your investors tell you this did you guys just wake up one day and realize it like
How did you both come to this realization and then how
Did you communicate it
Your masters
Customers in
To your employees
Realizations don't ever really happen overnight
Build over time and then something clicks and you have a decision to make
Came from our own understanding the market we
Do it better than anyone
Face the reality that
With a team are size trying to go up against Giants who
We're willing to lose money on every device
And then try to push distribution and Partnerships with the love of Louie needs to be successful
Was
Not going to be the best use of the team that we assembled
So then you decided
Oh my gosh look
Let's do a low-power wide area network
Not quite that simple recently Actiontec sometimes I sent an email to my investor
And basically
Given the reasons that
We were going to pull off of music
Then we set ourselves a very tight timeline to explore other options
And
To find UniFirst a technical Direction I'm a business Direction and then to get the point where we thought
We were convinced that there would be the smallest
So we were familiar we are aware of
Somebody's radio technology
We heard the specs and we didn't believe him
Because
That's always the case of me radio technology we explored a few other things we are building drones here for a while
Define radios
As well
A few things
Eventually couldn't get
Lora radios
At the time that we start looking at this
So some books in Europe that had
Souderton chips out on board we got those
Shipt
Over here
And I dropped one of my desk and started driving
We got about a mile away
And we're still getting signal through and we said
I think there's something here
Alright so
For the people who are not aware of the we've talked about it a couple times on the show Laura is
One type of radio
Technology for these low power
Wide area Networks
Others are put forth by sick Fox
There is
Ingenue
Which is doing
Completely different standard
And then there's also things like lte-m
So other standards and those are for the cellular
Maverick so basically there's a bunch of different ways
If you want to send
Very small amount of data
A certain distance usually a far distance
Away
This is what we're talking about doing
And so
To help people out
Why
Why do we need
So the first thing is
AR
We saw some the couches Wi-Fi reliability
That's complicated annoying
Cellular is
You just
You'll get a SIM card and stick it in and or or activate your device in
And you're good to go for you
But
Cellular has a limitation
The matter a lot
When you're talking about
Devices that don't need a lot of bandwidth that do need
To be battery powered
So you guys
Focused on
Basically sending small amounts of data
Step wooden
Consume battery power
Video
Is chyler Leigh
Cancel Google messaging
Or
Anything like that
It's complicated to build a wireless network so what are the challenges that you guys have to
To deal with cuz I'm thinking
You know in a traditional cellular network you got Tower sighting
You got to deal with
Multiple radios
Fourier
PlayStation speaker
If the client devices
Is all of that the same and then I guess we can talk about the authentication and billing cuz that's another big problem
So
It's easier for the developer but it's not easy for the network operator
Which is what you're trying
Kind of
I believe so
And I think that
Persistent
The benefits are you can get two years of battery life
On an implant device
And
You're not going to be able to do that was a lot
Or a number of different applications were actually installing sensors in
Warehouses right now
Last for 5 plus years into the installation
When I say installation I mean we just put them where we want them
And the networks that are out
It's just like
Dissenters and don't think about it for 5 years
There are other things like
If you need productivity in an area that Verizon isn't
If you have an area that Verizon
Cover you never will
Get them to cover it right
Put a sensor that you pay a buckle up for
I'm in your Fielder
So there a couple things
There are few of these
Value areas
Taylor just doesn't work
And the reason that we have the standards
The developing things like
A bureau in all of the new coyote standard for cellular is because they recognized
And
They know that they need to get one
Questions when will they do it
Royalty ever really
Become a first-class citizen on cellular data
Smart Start
So the technology that we're building what we're focused on here
Deep Network
Is is about
Basically making not as easy as possible
As simple as possible
Either so that means
Maximizing the range
Small
Changes in
Range
Huge impact
On the number of
Powers that you need to cover an area like where
Working here in San Francisco
Weed in the early testing
About a mile range
Our current testing we're getting as much
Outdoors
This has been a very high interference environment
Out in
Rural areas New Egypt
Situation
Maricela
Wow
So yeah so this is
Unlicensed spectrum and yet they have better range than
Cellular Sales
Is
Crazy low power
Weave
You said between 1 kilobyte of data
Are kilobits per second to
300 kilobits per second but we haven't achieved that because that's
Really close
What are people doing with this in
One of my big issues
With these kind of low-power Wireless
Area networks is
I just have a hard time believing that someone who
Has connectivity is going to be like
Hey
We're good that's enough connectivity
I cool just sending this one piece of data over
Cuz usually people are like
In tennis one piece of data over
What if I want to send
Another sensor
Or what if I want to send multiple pieces of data or maybe collect that data more times a day
How does that go
And I look at it the same way I
I think that what you just said is
Dr. orsi
I have a sensor the telling me what temperature it is in suddenly I
I need videos
I have one sensor
And I want Chad and I want 200
And so
Architecture that we're working with
The network Protocols are built on top of these radios are designed to scale on number of devices
Device
You get
Tens of thousands of devices
Connecting to a gateway
That's how we think
Now frequency
What's great is that when you can actually
We need the same thing.
Effectively
I just got just fill-in more gateways as we get to capacity so
And how do you think about the competing networks cuz you guys are building your network
The first net worth you have in San Francisco
Can you guys all coexist does that make sense
The technologies have different advantages
Sigfox
Is a very low data rate
Radio Sol
The Laura has has been more flexibility you can actually change the data rate and trade it also
Range and software function of the radio
And then in
Ingenue ingenu is working with her on
Critical Ops
Thailand house in the building on a network on it and
So if you end up with a different kind of ecosystem when you're
When you're doing that when the
The chips are available from the carrier
What kind of all
Apartments together
I think that there I have not
Got any testing with their technology I believe it's
For my understanding from
The way there
Describe it as entire throughput
Operate on 2.4 Spectre witches or Wi-Fi is so their pluses and minus
SLAP 2
What's exciting is ever going to get a new kinds of networks that aren't cellular that have different structures we're going to get
A variety of competitors and we're building up its Network
So
It's not about
Being limited to the conductivity auctions we have today
Explosion of new opportunities and new ways to
Connect devices it
We're not available.
That's awesome
Digikey
What was crazy to me
Few companies in Silicon Valley
Are aware of or working on
The psychology because
So from your perspective if it's so easy to start up this network
And I can go out and buy these chips and
Volume
They're relatively inexpensive
Your expertise what are you going to be selling what your business model and then what's your competitive advantage
The hardware you like that you know you by the chip in at Dunston masne and communicates the
Leslie Erin
And receive them
The network protocol that sits
Implemented
I'm in any
Like
Play open
What are
So we've done our own implementation of the network protocol is that
Radios
So then what do you sell
Since the day we have we are your date appointments
Sensor
Solutions.
Solutions like we Droppin hardware and give you a login to a. Where the shows your
Your data
For some customers that's what they're going to want
Four four other customers going to want it she said that so they might want to do
They might want
The Builder of sensor and use steroid hardware and just
Connecticut.
Are libraries to basically
Activity
Hard thing that were solving is
Getting
Where we see our value is doing
The hard work of conductivity making that really seamless
That was a long way of saying
Flexible
Start up
Figuring it out
That's the moron
We accept
On the show
Okay
So now we have a sense of why this matter
What's your doing
What Laura is
And
Possibly how you're going to make money and apparently a very passionate call to action for other people
This is great radio technology
You should look at it Daniel thank you so much
For coming on the show today
Thank you
I enjoyed it
What's good to catch up
Thank you so much for listening to this week's podcast will see you next week