Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
This week I have my lovely co-host
Kevin tofel
He is back with us
Hello Kevin
Hello hello and I should doing the show with a different set up to them I'm on an iPad using Skype instead of a full
Computer
So guys make sure you complain
And if you don't like the way cabins
I will change anything but we do value your
So much that we don't show
All right
So with that
Now that you know how valuable your
Feedback is please
Keep sending us to Europe
Will move right into the show.
Because a lot
Has happened this
This week was just amazing both from the consumer and the
Lookout the developer side
Philips Hue launch day new home
Let's talk about that
Nest
The
Alphabet
Country formerly known as
Google's nest
Adjust Nest launched it's weave
Platform which is not the same as Google's
Of course not
They just have the same name
And Amazon
Is set to launch its iot cloud
Did Microsoft actually launched
So where to stick with big names
On the show
And we'll see how far we get with all the
So let's start with
My favorite
My Bob's
The Hue Bridge
So Kevin why don't you tell us
Let's run down the Hue Bridge
Well sure there's
I went to a ton to tell here it's a brand new Hue Bridge
You have the old one
Yours is already updated congratulations still works obviously but
The new one actually is homekit certified
It will cost $60
If you do have the older
Kubrick's like I do
You can
Get the new one at a 33% disk
The $40
I believe that this is
Either now available or ready for
Order pre-order
And the deal on the $40 price tag for previous customers
That's actually a November 1 to December 31 deal so
I found that kind of odd I guess they want to get new
Customers first with the with unit
But the big deal here is yet home kit
Meaning you can say
I won't say it
I want to stop iPhones but you can ask
Siri to turn on lights
Adjust the brightness to colors
Turn on multiple lights to receives and so on so that's
That is the Q news
Stacy I'm kind of
Myths that some of these
Products
We're going to have homekit
And then we all have to re-buy them in a sentence
So
Let's hold that thought for a little bit
Because we're going to talk about
Cuz I'm I miss
But there's a couple more things we should know about
And that is
1 your old Hue bridge is still going to be updated and supported
What software
So if you're
Not planning on moving to homekit don't worry you can keep your existing Hue Bridge
And
That deal did Kevin mention
Jennifer existing Hue Bridge owners
To do one upgrade
Spanish while supplies last
So November 1st
They want to not wait till
If the middle of December.
Jump On It
The other thing is
The
Hue Bridge
If not only
Support homekit it's actually going to support Google's new Nest protocol
And
It's going to have
Computer inside
So
It's worth noting these things
Just because
This is doing two things
One is updating
Kind of for the homekit protocol
But it's also adding a lot more functionality such a
Just kind of that cloud backup
About so some of the commands that you have on your
Obviously won't get remote access but some of the scheduling and things like that Uke
Can actually now get
Without going out to the cloud
So Kevin
You might appreciate that
The other thing is that
You know it's going to support the nest weave protocol
We should probably talk about this a little bit
That's going to make a lot more sense
Come back and talk about upgrade
Psycho
With that in mind
Let's talk about
So hear the details
What this is
This is not the same thing is Google's we've protocol that they talked about
Who's this summer
This is totally
Wipro
Which is a kind of like
Qualcomm's alljoyn
Device to device
Is protocol
Except it's not sourced
By the way y'all
Google is now officially Google and the rest of the company alphabet
That happened
This is a device device protocol
It's got a couple things that works on 64GB of ram so it's design for small sensors in Micro Control
Of all the way up to larger things
It has its own security baked
And it is designed for anything that works with nest
So you have to apply to nest
To work
With this protocol in to get access
Let's do it basically it is a mesh Network
So
And it controls like how a device
Can talk to another device
And how a device knows what it is
Intuit can talk
System of the security features
AR
That because it knows what a device is
It also says
What advice
Talk to
So washing machine
Example probably will never be able to talk to your door locks
Because Nest doesn't really see a great
Use case for the
So that's one of the
I think that's actually really a nice
I do to it at
I think that's a smart approach
Although this is
Sort of new for the rest of the World by understanding is correct
This is what nessa's been using for the past several years and it's just now that they're opening it up
Yes
NASA's use this in a thermostat
And it says
Nest protect
Smoke detector
Presumably
It also runs over the thread Wireless protocol that nest
Help develop
Samsung and smother chip companies
So that's kind of where this works
But here's
The Clincher
We've only works
In the nest
So what we got now
Device-to-device communication protocol and I'm not entirely clear because I have
Unseen it nor have I talked to any developers using it yet
How easy the system
So I'll join when I talk to developers about all Joe and they're like oh it's so easy diplomat
This couple lines of code you pop it on it
It's time to here
I don't really know
So high I be curious to hear about that from
People who don't know even though they share the same name as how this is going to work with Google weave
Yeah that's
Nobody knows
Message spoof app
I don't even know if Google's we even real actual
So that's what we know about that
Do you want to mention the
The first product
That's going to
I know it's not super exciting but yeah what is a partner
I guess you could call the works with Nest program now and
Don't be using
Nest weave with their
Linus
Connected lock which is
Giant
Keypad
It's like a oblong and
Inset different
Password combinations for people to get in get out
And
LG monitors when the doors open and close see who use the door that's assuming everybody uses differ
Passcodes
Panda it's interesting but we see this before I just want to make sure cuz it is something that's going to work with Google's
I'm sorry with nest
With next week
But it won't be out until
And I think partly that's because
Going back to see what net said I think
You know they made the announcement now
They're actually not opening up next week until next year
Oh I thought it was just a
I
Do not think so
But I could be
Wrong song official Nest blog posters that says we've been using it meaning we've in Nest products for years
And next year
Will be opening up to everyone who wants to make a K'nex
Home Products
So they're kind of pre announcing this week I guess
More with the
The pre-announcement
So
What we have
Is we have
Weave protocol it's going to compete with things like I'll join
It will also compete with homekit because homekit is an application Level
Device to device
Ace Communications and security
And it will also probably
Compete with
Whatever is coming from the ioc if
People are actually using ioc
So we got
A bunch of different ways now
Devices
So this is our worldview
Now and now we're actually sort of having products now that homekit has actual products
Coming out
And I guess next next you will have
Weave products
Coming out okay
Now we should talk about Philip
Because this is kind of
This bridge
Is kind of
I think the beginning of possibly
A lot of decision making
I think that we're going to have to go through
As early adopt
People who listen to the show are probably going to so
This weekend I started retrofitting my house for
Home Care
And next week we'll be talking about that
But I'm kind of looking at this
What I'm like God
Am I going to buy the Philips
Am I going to upgrade my
Guess I have to
It's kind of part of my job
So but I I look at this and I
Not really excited
Plaza
I feel like the discount is is good
Right and I feel like telling promising customers that they're going to
Support you know the older version
Hopefully for as long as I can
Is good
But I don't
See an end yet
To the need to update
Your physical
Hardware
Because we haven't
Yet achieved
Some kind of status
I don't think we got
So unless you're willing to like
Purchase
And we haven't even achieved like
Unification on hubs
You know
So I'm worried that if I tell someone gosh you know update your Philips Hue Hub and then you'll be good to go
Really telling them
You know spent 40 bucks on
40 bucks
Sir 60 bucks on this device and you know maybe in two years you're going to have to do it again or maybe I'll just have to buy a router that does
So this hopefully next
That's the problem that would work we got His Radio spread out all over the place
Personally I don't even want the Hue Hub nothing against the product or the company
It's just I need this
Bridge for the specific brand of Lights
And yeah I know I control other lights are the two but
I can control other lights with other hubs
Get up for me to use my wink with the Q
I still have to have both
The wink Hub and
Hue Bridge
Where is
I can just use the wink Hub with
Pretty much any other line I want
It's all
Frustrating
I don't want to add more hubs and more
Bridges
More radios inside of
Of these things you know it's kind of crazy
So yeah so I'm sitting here thinking
Do I stop recommending the Hue Lights
Because now I feel like we're still too early in the game you know we've gotten
I can't in good conscience now tell you
You're never going to have to update + now you're still stuck
I can in good conscience tell someone to go out and buy a house
Cuz I feel like if you spend like I can I can in good conscience tell someone to go by $100
At least you can control a whole bunch of devices and if you have to go into an update
To another hundred dollar hub
Write because by that time you probably a few
If you filled up your home system you probably got you know maybe a dozen different devices that you're controlling with that hub
So you were lying on its own
You know so much
Just for your life I mean you could say while you're controlling up to 50 like
I'm also a little disappointed
Because the The Bridge update
Still only let you go
Control 50 lights
Which
That's not it I have more than two
What's in my history
So
I'm kind of like
You beat up your husband you
So and I'm not try it this has become dealer
Let's stop attacking you for a second and let's let's go to something like
The ecobee thermostat for example cuz they did did thermostat upgrade to homekit
You know what you would just bought a ecobee that wasn't homekit certified was their rationale for
Updating
And we're about to see a bunch of other homekit products at the market
Because they're chip inside there's two legitimate question like there's going to be a homekit enabled Chamberlain Mike
And I look at that and I'm like
Crikey
I'm going to have to replace my you know the door sensors going to be fine but there's a
The Hub so don't know how did it start 20-30 bucks or whatever it is
Yeah and so they're going to have to replace the admin have to replace
That
That's actually device I love and use Allah
So I'm like
Dang it yeah I mean
I'm taking the approach of
Trying to keep things simple and
Control the most or the broadest range of devices with a single
Hub system
I know it's not your favorite but for me right now that's the wink
I would consider switching over to SmartThings which
Probably will not get homekit support
They don't know why they're not
I mean Alex is said that
He doesn't like that
It's not opening
You know what the Mikey was going over to SmartThings eventually and I'm obviously I'm going to test the
Homekit
System because that's my job
I'm like
Yeah my husband has an iPhone I don't
I really see no need in my house currently I'm like
What's the best way to go cuz
I really don't want to update on my device
Say the other thing
Chairs that kind of comes to play at least for me is
Google can I can live without homekit and saying
Siri do this do that because I'm already telling
My Amazon Echo to do those things
Right but you can't tell the Amazon Echo Dot
Garage garage
He could now
I cannot tell the Amazon
Echo
So Chamberlain
MyQ
Is connected through the
But Amazon
Echo Dot
They don't support you okay so
Right so coraggio
I said I oh but garageio actually does now as of this week have Amazon Echo support so the more things that glom onto that please
Deco for for boys
I'm fine with that
Okay
We'll see so maybe we'll get some and I should note
Because they send me emails all the
Ivy
Which
I have not tested
But was an early voice activated
Many many moons ago
They've actually launched in 99 dollar
Competitor the echo
Poet ivivi
So it's a
Kickstarter Indiegogo
Eucerin Indiegogo
Ivy has launched an Indiegogo
And there
Trying to raise money
The pre-order it for $99 and it's
It's kind of like an Amazon
Echo type device for this with thing
I haven't tried it but it let you control your nest it does let you get Spotify which I'm kind of intrigued by
But I don't know if I purchase it only worth looking at if you're interested thing it works with Hewitt with Lowe's Iris it works with SmartThings
So that is
Yeah I remember when they first announced that it was probably two or three years ago
It's taking awhile to get things moving here but
Well this is a new one
So the other IV was a
Smart Alarm
So this this is a new
Version of ivy
Iv2
It's kind of
I don't know if
Yes baby too it looks
Kind of I don't know how to do
Looks like a microphone
Phone stand without
You're smaller than the echo I mean it definitely smaller
House speaker
Yeah I mean it's a
Lesser price Amazon Echo like device
I don't think it's going to happen
Broadest ecosystem available to its setting when compared to the echo
Probably not but you know
For now it's got
The same sort of
Send a lot of the big
Programs like nest
Austin smart things are actually and even that cold makes their ecosystem open so if you're a small developer you can just
Just throw your resources at the
Those those companies to make your stuff work with it
So that's it let's move on to
What kind of sunless
Tell me Focus stuff and more kind of developer oriented in big kind of brand
Cloud. Which is
At AWS
Reinvent the Amazon web services,
It announced
A iot service
Stuntin done
Is joining
Microsoft and IBM
And Salesforce and
Send a Lot ad
African fan
Julian other companies in launching
Basically an SDK
And kids
That will allow a developer directly to their cloud
And
The cloud platform that Amazon is offering is built on its acquisition of telemetry
From back in March which is the mobile kind of device management and monitoring side and
A data analytics platform that Amazon is building
Called Space Needle
So
This is a little bit
Pre-entry because we're recording this on Tuesday and
Amazon is expected to announce this on
Thursday
But
We've got it on pretty good authority
But all this is happening because we haven't
New season
Memos that Amazon sent out partner soups
So I'm curious to see what the impact is for them
Because more interesting
I think
So aw is had to do
Because you know everybody and their dog has
McLeod play for
Iot
But more interesting lie is so many of the connected services today already hosted on a
So
You know Alice Petsense yeah
So ala electric imp
And
Particle which used to be
Spark actually offer kind of development
Kits
And cloud services which is exactly what Amazon is
What kind of building in
I'm putting together here
So these companies all offer that but they host their Cloud portion of that
On AWS
So in a way
You know Amazon's kind of cutting into their business
But most of them
Aren't credibly worried because they're like you know we're already acting as a system
Integrator for our customers
Some of the stuff we offer
Is
You know we offer some Amazon stuff we
Pulling some other stuff that Amazon doesn't offer for our clients so hopefully
I'll stick with us there they're pretty nonchalant about it
If your smoker
That'll be the dead horse but I think wink is an AWS customer
Swing hesitated because they went down
Yeah
Dropcam used to be a huge AWS
Customer I don't know if they've moved yet over to Google but
I would imagine movie
I don't know because the last time I checked into
This was about
6 months ago
They had
It's a pretty big operation
Because they react built for AWS
Pictures of all of your info
Moving a cloud it's not easy
Exactly they're not as vaporous and light as you might think
So
With that
That's kind of some of the big news happening in the cloud this week
You guys should stay tuned because we are talking
With Alexandra
DeShawn
Sunset
Who is the creator of The Goodnight Lane
Camp and she and I are talking
About actually
Consumerism
And The Internet of Things
Said how this is leading us to buy more stuff
Maybe not a sustainable stuff
And what we can probably do about that for hubs
More hugs yes that is actually we we talked about Phillips so please stay tuned
Hey everyone welcome back to the iot podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and I'm here with Alex
Sandra deschamps
Who is with
Design swarm and iot consultant
Hi Alex how are you doing today
I'm very well how are you
I am
It is but the mid-afternoon where I am
Yeah I'm in London and it's raining what a surprise
It's always raining when I text
Geez Louise
We have to live up to expectations otherwise people will be at confused and actually want to live here
And then they'll be more of us
No wonder you guys got the
What was it the umbrella that tells you when it's whatever lights up when it's about to rain
People that came out of a London design firm
You're right I think it was California actually
Nuts
Which is also why it makes so little sense
Because in California
In England and it would make no sense
Because you need it all the time where is in California it actually would make sense
Because it's you know something you need to really be reminded of
There you go
Just have a glowing umbrella
Okay so
I brush and the podcast here be
Because
Actually been on the podcast before
To talk about
A product that you've designed how the good night lamp
And you should probably
Briefly tell
People with a good night lamp is
Just established that you know what you're talking about
So
Why don't you
Do that now
So the goodnight lamp is a family of internet-connected lamps
Big lamp Little lamp
You give the little ants away
To anybody around the world
And when you turn the big lamp on the
Once turn on
And the idea is very simple is
It's a very simple way of saying I'm around right now and I'm available
So when you have family members in different time zones
You're dating someone in another country or your grandmother lives on her own
It's just a simple way of knowing
The people are around
And I
I have been working on this
For 10 years now
And
Now on sale
In the UK
Are you going
I know it's been a long journey I've always liked this concept because it's kind of like an ion status message
Search in the real world for people who maybe aren't great at I am status
Yeah and I think
People also would probably people 10 years
Younger than both of us
Struggled even know what an ion status message is but
I think
The way mature people can't explain it is also kind of us a bat signal or
Facebook
Online or offline status
Made made RioLearn
Major physical and I like that I like that people can always
Pics of technology that they associated with this idea of them
The most closely and it means that
Even after 10 years
Do something people get rich
So we're not here to talk
Which is
Kind of a shame
Because I really love
We're actually here because you went on
You were quoted in a website
I think
You called it like a real estate blog which I'm kind of like oh okay is part of their maker Monday serious
Talking about
The Internet of Things
And you talked about how we're going to be buying the internet
And this is something I've been thinking about a lot
So
I wanted to talk to you about
How are we going to be
Buying
I wasn't in a particularly I think you know feisty mood the day they interviewed me
I guess
The Sting I'm really wondering about
10 years into a career talking about the internet of things and seeing other people do the same
And Building Things and making things is
I worry a little bit about
With which we can now make things into the world
In a way
How little people care about things
Now I think that's our appetite for physical
Products
Has increased
Tenfold and we certainly
Don't care about them as much as we used to I think there's maybe a very small number products that we
We could consider pulling from the fire if our house was on fire
And I think that number of
Products is probably
Very slim now
If you'd asked people what they might buy for
Christmas Bell have a
Particular
Idea and
We're trying to
Cater to that I think I'm making connected things and work
Trying to connect
To a world
It really likes to buy things
And I'm not sure that's a reason enough to actually build things but I think that's the reason that people are using in order to be
Building in this interview you said that the iot will be a mechanism for people to take electronics into a space that's new
In order to keep up with the hype of consumerism that we've been experiencing since the end of the second World War
I think of it as kind of this mentality of
You know put a chip in it
And will charge you know
10x the price or maybe it's
Only three or four
Surprise
And I look it even what I've done in the last
Couple of years
Switches
You know I've
I spent $500 replacing to thermos
And I've gotten a lot of value
That's what I'm not
The first to do
But
When I
I did that a couple years ago and now the next generation of those
Suddenly I'm faced with the fact that I have put Hardware
Connected Hardware on my wall that's going to be supported
But it's also
Dunes kind of an obsolescence cycle
I'm kind of like
Man
I really just do that because I don't know if in five or six years I'm going to really
Want to replace my thermostats again
Especially at 250 bucks a pop
Yeah it worse is they used to be Things That No One
Really replace
You know you you wouldn't even install your own thermostat
It's actually illegal in the UK to do that
Did these desert infrastructural products that we're just that they were infrastructure
Where is now they've become
Consumer
And they become part of the consumer landscape
Desire
And sales and Edom
It is that planned off the obsolescence of
People have
Worked out in the car industry and worked out in
Turn the fashion in
And now we're working that out for everyday products
Which is the
Problematic
Do you think it's
Is nefariousness planned obsolescence or do you think
It's really value I mean
Do you think we're getting value-add
I mean I would argue that
A nest thermostat on an ecobee thermostat does
Offer
You know significant power saving
Yes and no in Chinese
You know it could be interesting to kind of look at whether
You will have
Received 250
Dollars worth of savings
In how long in between replacing it again
And then having the Next Generation
Timeout I think the
Every two to five years
Kind of okay I suppose
But I kind of apple style upgrade of every 6 months is a new thing
I think it's
Just really really aggressive consumerism
And
If you have made a product
Well enough
Provide value
For your quest
I think your first customers should always be the ones
State you
Really cherish the most
Supposed to make them feel like they're
Lefton
Stranded because they happen to have the older version
I don't
Thanks that we necessarily know how to
Buildings in that way
I'm really
Generally kind of
Pretty
Intrigued
Spy
2 Cycles
Switch very well-funded
Iot company
So I'm calling startups when they have millions and BC
Iot companies are
Expecting to grow
Because I think that the pressure is on them
Really
Show
Aggressive sale increases
And the only real way to do that is to imitate the Apple model even when not a relationship
Ever develop with a
A thermostat but
You know
Let's go let's
Triad
Let's try to make it feel like
Consumer product just like any other consumer product that we have just like our phones have contracts and our laptop
Dogs get old and
Let's just do all that stuff away and replace
Well there's a
Whole bunch therapist
What kind of impact
First of all I think 2 to 5 years
For thermostat is
Well I I would prefer it to be tender
15 but
I think that if you told a company that is has told their shareholders
That they are going to have a hockey stick graph and
Terms of sales
And they will realize how
Smaller Market is
And then
Just aggressively sound to that same Market over and over again
Okay I see like
If you think about it thermostat
So if you look at nest with popular example right
Set Nest Thermostat
Looking at maybe
15 year
Replacement cycle on a thermostat seems
Kind of reasonable
Maybe with the protect smoke detectors have like a mandated life on them
Permasense our perspective so it's about
I think seven years
You're so five to seven years on that and then you got cameras
There you've got an opportunity
I feel like cameras you probably don't replace
Is that a 5-year thing I'm curious what the numbers were
Could be on a replacement site
And then you could always come
Gets people to add
So maybe your strategy for hockey
Growth is a
Maybe you're not a one device company maybe you become
Multi-Device
Company with different
Cycle so that's one strata
Product for
But then there's this idea of the electronics themselves
Because
Most of these companies will have a Services Drive
And those services are going to increase in
Computing or
Maybe different radios all kinds of different things over time is
The environment changes
Infermon Electronics perspective
You know I think every two years
It's kind of not crazy to think you're going to want to update the hardware
Where and I don't know is a hardware person
Dealt with that even in your own product
What are your thoughts about kind of
How to handle some
Well I think what brought me to this conclusion to begin with is work to
This line of thinking too
What is the realization
10 years ago there were things that
Wyndham tee product design
Sphere people were discussing
Got completely dropped
Partly I suppose
Juju iPhone coming in and things like that but
People used to talk about design for disa
Assembly
Cradle to cradle
And things like that and
Concept
Spell applied
Two looking at the products that you were making in a way that made it
Easy to disassemble take apart
Replace the right piece except
When you're talking about a product
Where the casing
Could be at the electronics could be replaced and upgraded
The tendency for Mom
The product company now is not to say
Will you can send us back the old one will replace the guts
For the new with the new tag
And we'll
Just give you back at one
It's not even an option
So
Your you know whatever upgrades
You might need to do from a hardware perspective
I think
If you're doing a good job you should be planning for your Hardware at that last
Longer than
The software upgrades that you need to do which you know will need to happen firmware updates things like that you've talked about
This concept of owning the customer relationship and who has the responsibility for owning that relay
Relationship
Can you talk a little bit more about what that will mean for
Connective life cycle of a
Prada
And how you think about designing
And also
Does that mean that
Models like Tesla's where they actually own the customer relationship start to make
More sense
Yeah I think I have
Having a relationship with customers directly when you
Spelling
Very high-end
Cars made
Text a huge amount
You're building a relationship with someone you're really cares about what you're doing
And the luxury Market really knows how to do that
If you want to buy from
Chicken luxury Brands you can only really buy from them they don't really do stalkers
They Don't Really deal with anybody else
And certainly for a long time even Apple
Don't have that they were you know there was
A very small presence
Reseller
Stool is really
Stores in their own brand
It's more easy to find apus
Products now
Elsewhere
The ownership of that relationship is one that I think
Little attention is your tooth
Put on when you're talking about
Consumerism because really
Brands of most
Products hoping you never call them back when you
I need to dispose of
Something
They put that responsibility onto the recycling services that cities
Will have
Certifier
And the responsibilities always someone else's responsibility
Ability but
I think
And this is sort of what kicked off this whole line of thinking which led
How to talk I gave
Two stalks I gave and then this article
It's going to be I think as of this year it's illegal in New York to
Throwaway electronic gadgets
Until we're kind of entering a world where
End-of-life and every single little thing that might have been free once is
Actually not free because it has huge
Impacted
And I think that we are aware of how much impact
We can have when we work
Technology how much the web has changed
The way
People interact with the things that they love
And I think that we should have that same
Sense of responsibility and ethics
In
Product
And Design
Products assertive
Traditional industrial design
Sort of has been baked in
But
A lot of iot
Startups or not
Traditional industrial designer
So
It's a whole new population
People that needs to be told about
Basic environmental print
Okay and so outside of the
Let's get back into this kind of idea of how people might buy
Kind of connected
Gadgets over time because
I have kind of
I don't know if it's a frustration or its
It's kind of all just using example
Philips just let earlier this week actually
Talked about how it just announced
An upgraded hub
For homekit and kind of the new Nest weave
Protocol
Sell Philips Hue Lights have a
Do they have a bridge
So
All of your
Philips Hue Lights
Continue to work with your existing bridge if you have it but if you want it to work with homekit you're going to have to upgrade to
To this
Newbridge and
It's a $60 the new bridge is $60 or it comes down to about 40 bucks if
If you are an existing
Philips Hue owner
So
And I'm kind of curious because I'm an existing Phillips
What's yuan
And
I'm very glad that they're go
Continue supporting my old bridge
But I'm also kind of like and appreciate the discount
Upgrade
And I understand that there's a hardware
Upgrade required to get to
What is an early adopter I'm also
Gosh dang it y'all
Now I got to go out and spend 40 bucks on a brand new bridge
When there's a new standard coming out of my got going to have to get a 2 years from now spend another $40 when does this
Send
What kind of products
Make sense to do this for
Do I have to upgrade everything in my house cuz you know
Earlier this summer I was going to have to if I wanted a home kit in my ecobee thermostat has to have to buy a brain
Thermostat
So
I don't know I am kind of feeling a little
I don't know early adopters commonly face
What's with the Internet of Things it feels like it's still so unfinished
I don't even know what to tell people
Yeah yeah I think
We're going to suffer from kind of Bridge Creek
Really really
Especially for things that really
Are perfectly fine on their own
Really when you think about it because
Having a bridge for your light bulbs
Raise
Having a bridge for like a very important piece of
Computer only having a router for
Your computer makes sense
But yeah kind of mini bridges for everybody
Interoperability needs
Is
Probably you know something that will eventually decide
Disappear when they just start making better
Amor multitek
Routers
But before we get there in
Before Cisco decides to build such things at an affordable price
To wait and have
Languages
I do think that early adopters
We're in the phase and we're going to do the face in the face of
Early adoption for a long time with iot I don't think that we
Are going to
See
Mask
Consumer appeal and in these ideas
Until they really feel very excessive
I think people are starting to
How to build a vocabulary around them and just in the way that
10 years ago when I was
I was presenting the good night lamp people used to tell me
Is that the time it was a wifiber
People used to tell me oh Wi-Fi
Doesn't that fry your brain
And
That's just
Change in society and
Constant
Inconstant
Education on the part of the text
With respect
To the benefits rather than the pitfall
And
I have no idea whether Wi-Fi fries my brain but I've stopped caring about
Answer to
The job was done
Adequately
And I think that
With iot we're going at we're talking about so many different
Competing
Technologies
That people will
By the end-user application that they find is interested
And then realized
Stats
Something that they will have to
To suffer for
Because they got into
Just did a little
Kitsune
I don't think I can
Traditional product design work
Flatware
If you bought something
40 years ago cancer
This were
Dad yes they might be in
And you were more interesting version made out of a better plastic later on
But you didn't feel cheated by the first version if anything
Dad gained a bit more Authority because it was the first version
And I don't think that we've
Managed
Tudo Certo
Vintage iot
Simply because things are really just stopped working entirely I mean I have an Avast text somewhere in a box
Exposed it in my office for a little too long to
Sons of the Plastics really turned
Colors
And you know I should have sent
It hasn't even aged
Well as a product
Never mind as a
Connected
So
Yeah I think we'll
Will definitely still suffer
A little while
Will BVM canaries in
Buy what you like
But you will suffer
A wonderfully Grim way to end the conversation
And this podcast
So Alex thank you so much
For coming on the show
Thank you for having me
Thank you list
Prayers for listening
To this week's show and we'll see you next week