Everybody
Welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
Kevin tofel
And this week we have a great show for you
Ring raising a lot of money
New lights from Philips Hue
Are we go to SAC lights and Miracle grows bread
Internet of yard
Internet of plants that sounds way better
And I guess this week
Senior vice president of digital payments
At Labs at MasterCard and we're going to talk about putting payment capabilities into clothing
Rings
And even golf clubs
So stay tuned
All right
Let's talk about
What happened with ness this week
Last week we talked about the brand new features which we were
Solid
We are happy
Turns out
When does introduces new features
Use your smartphone's location to help calibrate your nest so it knew if you are away from your home or not and the other was actually
So you could share your nest app with other people
The password
When they launched those features
Nest also had to change and update their terms of service and privacy policies to
Because they're collecting new information and sharing it with me
New people
So when they did that though
They basically put
A note in the app
Would you open your app
But other people open their apps
Who discovered that they had
Two choices
Conditions
They could not
Well the second option is they can get more info about the terms of service changes
But there's no I don't accept
So I actually just installed the nest app on a brand new phone because I've been using the Wing Cap on it
How to get exactly what
What I would say is relatively big issue in that if folks don't want the new family accounts and Houma
Assist
Well it's too bad you don't get to use your nest at all
If you don't want to
If you don't want these features
Or
Rather you don't have the option to say hey I'd rather
Grandfathered under the old privacy
And not use those features
Emissions
There's an option that's missing
So
This brings up kind of
Twitter a couple people like me and you're holding my Nest hostage
And I actually thought back to
Phillips when they implemented error
Android update
Android 400 update
For the shoe
Messed up a little bit in their implementation
Emissions
It's so basically we agree to like share
They're photostream and share
Location
And also just access to media and files on the device
That's it
They didn't agree to that
Just close
Music
It wasn't even you could accept to other three
Keep using your ass
Add accepted
Update on March 3rd
So now they're doing the permissions
Correctly
Pick and choose what you want to share and now you
Use the app
It's a little different though
The issue is in this points to an issue that Kevin and I were talking about before the show which is
My gosh we have these physical devices
And we have a rubric for an upgrade permissions on software
Physical devices installed in your
Your home like on your wall or in your light sockets
You know how
Much of an option to take it orally
But short of
Ripping out a piece of hardware and replacing it with something that's comfortable Better or Worse whatever you decide
And that's obviously not ideal
Exactly so
What was the mistake one is
Intentional but it's not intentional and some like we're going to start sucking all of your data out kind of way but
I guess there's nothing to say that
They couldn't do that
I mean I don't know what Nest is going to do here
If anything's
But
If I were them what I would do is
Keep the old terms of service for any and also Implement app permissions to use these features
And if people say no I don't want to use these features meeting you know
Permissions I want to get permission on my location Etc
Then just let them stay in the old terms of service because they're using
Nest as it was
Under that terms of service
And therefore if you accept the app permissions to use the new features
Then you have to buy default agree to the new terms of service
For the future
There's nothing on the software side in terms of the permissions the app permissions
Mitigate this right now
And I should say in most of these companies would say this
Most connected Hardware companies build their devices so they will still work even if the app is gone or
So your nest thermostat was still
You can still control it for the wall we're just talking about
Recommend
Replacing the Philips Hue Lights even if you didn't have it on the app
I can still turn it on and off
Light switch
And and I should mention
And I said I did not have the nest app installed on this new phone I do have the Wink app
And that still work perfectly fine
With
The nest
I want to use my phone to control the temperature for an apple
So I guess you couldn't
There there's a workaround if you don't want to accept a new privacy
Terms and conditions
Possibly
By going through another
Github another app
That feels like
Yeah
Very possible it's very possible I don't know how long that may or may not last I haven't tried with you Amazon Echo to see if I can still
Do things as well so
Really nice nice nice to own and fix this issue addressed this issue
And I think it's probably relevant for everyone in this industry to start thinking about
People feel a sense of ownership
These devices
Physically attached to their homes for example yeah
Figuring out a way to gracefully
It's not even graceful degradation
Implementation of
New features and possibly new privacy
Right conditions is going to be essential
Imagine imagine what I'm at the home but think of all the other connected devices imagine if your car
New terms of service because of something maybe new GPS function
And you didn't want to use this function
Well you could either use the function and agree to the new terms of service for your car just stops
Your car doesn't work
I mean essentially the same thing
Soda Springs to mind an issue that happened last year
John Deere
And actually General Motors and they
We're basically saying they used copyright law
To argue that
Company are people who bought their devices couldn't modify them
In ways that basically they argued that modifying their vehicles
Wood
Break copyright law
Chrysler software that runs inside the pickles
Change your tires
You're not allowed to get a flat tire and go buy a new John Deere
And people were very upset they said this is like the opposite of ownership
People no longer on their vehicles in the copyright office back in November
Timeout
And said that actually
Actually you can modify your vehicle but it's only under certain really Limited
Conditions
So you can't violate you know Department of Transportation
Any payroll so
This is so funny that this is coming up now because just over the weekend and is not the first time I've done this is the second time I've done this
But just over the weekend I bought a
Box that I can make it to the engine of my 2016 Golf R W
Apr Golf R
And basically Alters how the engine works because it
Sends different signals to the ECU or engine control unit
So I'm getting like an extra 45 horsepower an extra couple PSI of boost on the turbo and
I mean I'm having fun with it
6 Pawnee Dr. Funner to drive
That makes sense
If I break any laws speeding that's you know
Where are the parks in there or not that's on me
But you know how violated any copyright laws now because I don't own the software
In the engine control unit
Now that's a VW Thing even though I own the car what do we own
This is really a good question
Yes so it especially as more features are enabled by software
So
That
We've come so far
Both
Like we said
The companies building these devices are going to have to think about this but then we might also have some
Some lawsuits to look forward to
Okay so
I probably shouldn't mention this on their then because he probably will have lawsuits
I didn't change my car honest
Alright Kevin is
On the straight and narrow
Hey you know it's my car if and
I want to change something where the ECU or the radio that's on me I think
Can
Yes I'm held accountable for that if I do something illegal with the vehicle
Whether or not I modified it
And yes VW can say I'm out of warranty
But that's a choice that I choose to make
Here with mass going back to the very original thing
Right now I was saying people don't have a choice
So after spending $250 on a nest thermostat
It might be pretty much
Speaking of spending money on connected devices
We have got a whole new option for people
SQ his
Announce
New
White
But that doesn't really sound exciting on the surface but it is
Because
These are the Philips Hue White Ambiance lights
Basically as I see it
These are tunable white lights
Switch I actually prefer my house because I like to go from
Different color temperatures from soft white to warm way to Daylight and so on Depending on time of day and
And these will do that up from the 2200
Hey toots 6500 case you get
Hallway down to like warm yellow all x-ray
Daylight
With these tunable bulbs I do not know the cost of these yet by the way
What's also interesting knows they're smart enough to adjust
The shade of color temperature throughout the day if you would like
Similar to and CC I don't know if you use any apps like this with similar to something called
Flux on a Mac
Or G Luxe and Chrome
Basically these are software bits that
Remove the bluish white light from your screen silver with a reddish light
And the reason being there been studies saying if your
Looking at blue white screens
It becomes harder to sleep you could lose up to an hour of sleep because it stimulates the rods and cones in your eyes and so forth
So that's kind of the object are these Ambiance lights
It's
Progressively changing
White color based on time of day activity and someone you can do that smartly or you can
Programming
Okay and
If you don't want these
They still make the Hue Lux Witcher 2
Dimmable
White lights
Yes and
I'm looking for the price
To see if there is a price here
I couldn't find one
They were just announced that I'd say a day ago so information still trickling out
And I looked at those
Hue Lux bulbs
Dimmable but
I really like tunable that's just a personal preference in the
They didn't have one up until then so I've been using the Crees and has worms
And now there is actually just for people who are is obsessed with lighting as I am
Is the C by GE that also came out so
You came out this spring as well and you can order them
These are there going to be the homekit lights
And they sleep and see life
So one is designed
Are there different bulbs in
For your bedroom you're supposed to use the Seas sleep lights
They're supposed to dim all the way down kind of at night
Using the Circadian rhythm from like the super bright blue
Daylight to EE warm yellow light
I guess that's where the Sea comes from
Oh you like the letter c
Yeah yeah
C is for cookie that's good enough for me
Today Show is brought to you by the letter c
And the number for just because
I'm sorry
That is okay
Okay
Too late
I can't I can't talk about these jokes right now
So the starter pack is $50 in
That includes
And I believe a hug
Two of each
Deal
Regular price is set
$70
If you want these
Weather now
Because it is a good deal that's a good deal for
Circadian rhythm
I might do this although I don't think they work with my wink
I don't know
See if they work with wink because
They're going to be homekit compatible
And
Android is coming soon they don't you can't even spell the app
Going to happen
So
That's okay
For other gadgets that you may want
We got some exciting news for you
Oh wait to see by GE bulbs are connected via Bluetooth
Cheetah mobile app
So it's phone control
Could using stairs an Android app
So
Knowing that we got to two options in the lighting category for you there
I am testing a
And these guys
Are really cool I've been really excited about them and I've been living them for like a week and a half
I'm part of that time I was out of town so
My review is a little
You're going to hear more about them as I live more with him
Because they also learned
So these lights
The cool thing about them is
They want to be responsive as opposed to program
So they have motion sensors and ambient light sensors
And
The awesome part about them
Is
They are very responsive
Unlike with my
When I was testing the connected home plugs
You would walk into the room and it would be like
I'll let you walk halfway into the room sometimes and the lightstone wouldn't go on
But here the second you walk under them food the lights turned on
And I found in the bedroom this is amazing
So I installed
Lights in the bedroom
My bedroom and
A little Abner caught the potty room I don't know what the graceful way of
It's like a bathroom
Just a room with the toilet in her master bathroom
So I installed one in there and I installed one
Or I stopped several in the hallway
Right outside
In our bedroom
So
Nice
Use cases are
They automatically have a circadian rhythm setting
So
When I walk in in the middle of the day there
Wherever they are in their circadian rhythm setting and getting that kind of light
They have a wake-up alarm function so it can
But gradually brighten the room
Had to think of what all that they had a lot of really cool things
What I've discovered though
Is
Living with motion sensors
Is a little bit hard
It works really well in
Like the tiny little bathroom
It doesn't work as well in the hallway because when
We get near the hallway
The lights
Turn on like even at night
Editor nighttime mode is kind of nice they have a sleep mode where you can put the lights into your belly to be off or you can
Make them glow it like 5%
Series have, second ambient light
Yes
But in the middle of the night when you trigger the hallway light
You're like
It's still comprise
Send it times out
So I have mine set out to timeout at like 1 minute because
That's a lot of light
And so
I guess there's a lot there's a learning curve to using
But
Did the closest I have so far to Magic
And I'm pretty sure that was some software tweaks
Is there going to be
Almost as intuitive as they want
Interesting
And as I'm looking at the at the bulbs on the stack lighting.com site looks like a hub
Which uses a sick day for
Mesh networking all the lights together
We shouldn't have its own hug but
They look pretty smart
Super LaRon so to speak Endo programming requires you to
Yes I do I mean like
Again there's some things I wish like I wish I could put the whole house to sleep all at once when I hit
But instead you have to go room by room
Which is kind of like
Like when I lock down for the night boom I want it all back down
So they don't have
There is an apple right
But it doesn't have like an all off for
Yes
It does not have it does not have that everything's controlled by the
Legacy like as it gets
But if I had these throughout my house like I wouldn't want to put the whole house to sleep maybe if my daughter
Up in her room
Yeah where somebody wakes up in the middle of the night
It's sensitive but I'm in all off mode can't turn on now
I mean there are still things but
It is
The most intuitive so far and the
The promises that these will learn your
Kind of habits
I haven't you I feel like I haven't used them long enough to really learn
The captain start understanding
Like what I'm doing things
But I'm eager to see what that
Now
These are $60 a bulb
I do see what the starter pack is
Believe it's 150 because it includes the Hub into
2 Bulbs Plus The Hub
Okay
Yeah these are not cheap
Discern
BR30
You know I like
Standard bulbs which they say are coming soon
They are at CES and
The cool thing about those is how do you get a motion sensor
Work through a lamp
How do you get an ambient light
And I should say the ambient light sensor is awesome
Because it does it pulls
Some of my lights don't turn on would like the the windows are open
And I walk into my bedroom
Only like one of the lights that is kind of further away from
All the light for me
Windows
So it's kind of cool you like
It's my turn on the light that when you already have light in that room that area
So
Interesting
I'm liking these lights
I feel like I should also say they integrate with nest
Southern motion sensor can talk to nest
And be like hey someone still in the house
Don't turn off the air conditioning
And then they also integrate with if this then that
So I
Trigger them via the Amazon Echo
So
All that works seamlessly
And issue
Has potential I like it
It does
It's got to be good
So
If you're a lighting freak
Like myself
I would say go and buy some and start playing with him you're going to need probably a lot
I would just kind of an investment
If you want to wait
Like another couple
Of weeks or a month or so I bet I could tell you like
Yes they are significantly better
Stay tuned
We have money
Ring
But connected doorbell maker
Has raised 61 million dollars is a serious around so that's a third round of funding for them
And a racer from Kleiner Perkins
And they also
Launched a brand new girl
And this one is a slightly higher and doorbell it's
Instead of costing $200 this one cost 250
This is the ring video doorbell Pro
It has
PhD as opposed to 7:20 so little higher hi-def
And it also is all wired so it has a Slimmer profile
In the old ring
$200 rate original
Serena used to be known as doorbot
That was not a great product
Currently waste a lot of money
Prior to the Stingrays.
I want to say it was $28 round LED by Richard Branson
The point is
New doorbell
I'm kind of excited about it cuz
Cuz I love my video doorbell
Yeah it's not as quite as wide as the old one
You know because the old one would not sit on my door
Because it doesn't have batteries
So you have to wire it in
You take out the battery and then they also use
Components for mobile phones that supposed to I guess traditional Electronics components so the whole profile is much slimmer
I can't wait to see it because maybe I can fit it in my door
Maybe I was going to try to get you out and they also have interchangeable faceplates
People who care about the color of
Which actually is me
You could change it every day of the week very cool
So that is
I don't know I think it's I think it's
Samantha rings
Good on them
And
Connected yard
Which is not something I ever thought we'd be talking about all that much but
I don't have any art that people really really really care about
We get a lot of actually inbound requests
How to test sprinkler
I'm still working out house
We're supposed to do that so
Stay tuned because I do want to get some of those on the show and be like hey this is better than that one
But
Miracle-Gro
Scott's Scotts Miracle-Gro they have a
Baby introduced a platform called the connectedyard platform I think it's called grow dro
It's a platform
Basically allow lots of different
I'll sit mostly Smart Water type controller such as those from Blossom rachio green IQ
Center to parrot
Quaintly
So it's basically platform to get all these
Sensors and devices talking to each other
Which is Enter Sandman because all these things would be tied together soil
Moisture for example would be interesting to a sprinkler for example so
Connecting
Peace
Makes sense to me
Make sense at Scotts Miracle-Gro add B12 company seducao
Do we have any
Other information I don't know when
IPhones actually launching or has it
Yeah this is this launched
Well this lunch
The news of the popcorn line
In
Last week
I think of it like a health kit for
Yards just going to go in and tie in with weather data so basically
Hey
Water main yard
It's also kind of promising because
If this will actuate and it sounds like it will
It will
Be able to
Set some of these things off because it's rachio for examples
Control controls your irrigation so
Oil sensor says
Heart
It could be like
Oh I will turn on the butter
And because it integrates local weather data
It may also be like
If you can hold out for just a little longer it's going to rain
I was just really promising for trout areas drought-stricken areas and also takes idea just a
Iot stop providing information and starts making it
Again letting it
Idevices app
Even do so without
Amscot says long-haired lawn care services to
People will come out and so on
Your lawn and
Delta recommend certain fertilizers and certain cycles of fertilization and so on
So in a sense it could even help
Company itself
In terms of that
But instead of just having one person come out one time and evaluate your lawn
This is like a constant evaluation which kind of need
Data and
I'm going to guess that they're going to let you know the
Rapper X
Stop light
Proper squats
You know
Fertilizer indoor plant food
IT shop if they didn't I didn't
This is possibly a service Revenue play
Sending our technicians out to you but it could also be a really useful way to gather data
To help sell more of their product switches
I want to see a really
Good way for a big company to be like
Hey here's how an open platform
So
Yay
Very cool
Super Bowl
All right
And I was at South by Southwest
And I spent a lot of time talking to
Companies and I'm just trying to think about the coolest things I saw
When I give you one in the rest I'll have to think about
Tell me about next show that I did see a company called Bernoulli
And if you are interested in cocktails
Like myself
This is really a neat idea
This is going to be launched
Is lunch now
What is RR
Blue toothpaste
Bottle stoppers for your bar so your
Your alcohol collection
Eight of them for $300
I know it's kind of
You go to the app and you're like
I have the follow
Things in my bar
Are the drinks you can make with that
I would like to meet this one
And then you
Pour the drink
When you're pouring the alcohol in
It's going to actually stop
The flow of liquid
Reaches the Impala
Clever
I saw it and it works
I was actually that was like the most
Magical
So the top
Lights up
It's like oh this is the gym
All right
But I get your address
And they won't catch me
Go ahead kids make the drink for Daddy
Chinese martini
Cuz I played with a lot of robotic bartending
Because you got a stick
Professional use
Similar idea only
That sucks up all the moisture and then you got to clean all those tubes
I don't know when you're dealing with like
Alcohol
Mixers were talking about you no stickiness
So I was like
That seems like a lot of work
A lot of money this is actually relatively speaking much cheaper and
It really doesn't change how you
Make a drink today in essentially other than
Doing the measuring and the recipe for you so it's not like there's
A convoluted hurdler involve
There's there's just about
No hubs good
They're not wifi-connected bottle.
What's good
Russia how are they connect
Got it makes sense make sense
Spider Lily
Go to my Christmas list
Dude there you go
Presumably that's what they say
Keep an eye on
All right
We will move on to our guests who is Sherry Hammond who is an SVP of digital payments
Closet MasterCard
And we're going to talk about the future of how you will pay you for things
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Am I guess today is Sherry haymond
She's an SVP of digital payments and Labs at MasterCard
Hi Sherry thanks for joining us today
Hi Stacy thanks so much for having me
I am super excited about this because I
Hate
Grabbing my wallet out and you guys have
You have this new
Call the thing
Coming for lack of a better word
With the Arnold
Palmer Invitational golf tournament
And you guys have put
You've worked with a partner to embed payment technology into a golf glove
Which I think is kind of fun
You can
Wave your hand to pay for Refreshments on the golf course
Can you do other things with it
I think that's probably the you know that the most prominent
Case for this
So with the gospel is actually a proof-of-concept
I'm it's something that were able to enable through a broader program that we have called
Commerce for every device
So what that program allows us
What to do is
In a really simple easy
Picture away
Is it possible for
All kinds of different devices wearables jewelry clothing
The manufacturers of those
You know item
To connect with our platform
And Hobbes
The consumer that using that device
Or Gadget or clothing or wearable
Ask
To have their payment credentials
Gander MasterCard pay
Credentials
Securely put on to that device
And made available for that device
To use and so
Although you know not in production and we did do that
Special
Bespoke for the Arnold Palmer
Invitational
It is an example of what can be done with our cut
Sandusky
Callaway Golf Clubs
And there's a payment chip
In the club
That connects via Bluetooth
On a phone
And you can
Scan your card credentials
Charlie into the phone
You know at which point
The app basically makes
MasterCard
We assure know that you want to put your credential on for the device
Stuart a methodology we have
We make sure with the issuer that you are you
And then we make that payment credential available
In a tokenize way so we don't make the real credential available
But instead a surrogate
Credential
Together with
Secure cryptographic keys
That make sure that each transaction is safe and secure and unique that uses the same technology as EMV chip card
Okay
So that was that was like
Everything I need to know
So this is a prototype
Close
Can people actually use it
Well the people at the API and will be able to use it but I mean
Don't currently have plans
Available commercially
But we'll see when you know what gauge the interest on its Callaway or any other
Glove manufacturer
Would like to
You know it's definitely
Possible as an example of why it's possible
Partnerships with
Many other
Clothing jewelry device manufacturers and
Closest to this actually is a designer named Adam Selman
I'm here
Is probably most famous for designing
Dresses for Rihanna he does all the cost
Inspire her tours
You're beautiful clothes available
I'm at high end stores today
Operation with Nordstrom
We worked with him
To again make some prototypes but later this year we will be working with him
How to make those commercially available
I'm in the prototypes
He created included address
Sunglasses a handbag on
I'm so they weren't golf clubs they were
Fashion
Winter gloves
That is in the winter you are
Going out in the morning you know you can
Citrulline
Payment credential.
So that example if you're in London UK
I can wave your hands over the turnstile at the CFL magically entering
Be on your way with your eyes
That magical in
And you guys have agreement not just with some of these by Ashley this is not allergic
Company but you have an agreement with one of our favorite devices which is brainly
Cocktail ring that I currently wear it whenever I'm dressed up and I want to get notifications on my phone or from my
Looking at my phone
And soon I'll be able to use it
Pay for things with my
That's exactly right so we've been working with ringly
Such a great company
And you were very lucky to in the fall when we announced
Star Commerce for every device program
The name of this program that were
Using two
Easily connect with the device manufacturers and enable payments on the devices
When we was actually one of our launch partner
So we worked with Chris
Go bring Lisa and her team
To actually put
Picture painted credentials on to wait that we had at the show and they actually work
And so for me I mean I'm a working mom
Simplification of my day today that I
Do you know I connect my ring any in the morning anyway to my phone
In the fall or
Later this year
Will be able to I will also be able to
The Charlie
I'm transfer via
Bluetooth encrypted Bluetooth technology
I'll be able to
Shirley transfer cards you know accounts by provisioned through an app on my phone
To my ring lyrics
And then when I'm
You know off on my day I'll be able to
You again later this year
At my ring at Starbucks when I'm getting my coffee I'll be able to tap my ring on a New York City
Cab near when I'm
Running between meeting for example
Functional
Beautiful
We're working with ringlets a great example of how we're adding payment functionality to something
Is already
Very useful to the
Until all it needs is to have an NF
NFC and Bluetooth chip in it
Route to work
Pretty much I mean the underlying technology is
A check that's enabled with NFC and then also
Bluetooth
However the
There's obviously
An integration that happened
Between
Either the device manufacturer or an enabler that they're working with
And we're working with Darius and ambler's including nxp
Qualcomm
And coin there's several others that have not been announced yet
We're going to be integrating with our
System
So that
The device manufacturer doesn't nest
Integrate directly with us
Got it
Now
So let's let's take this back as couple steps in as like a normal person who's going about their day
Ordering a coffee
What is the process look like I wave it
I always my hand can I buy like
I don't know a stereo with this or how does
What are the limits to my my new-found
In fact this is actually all of this
Technology is actually available in Market
Today
You know so for many years we've had available
Not only in the United States but globally
What's called MasterCard contactless technology
It's built on NFC
Technology
Actually is underpinned by the same
You know it's available at more than
4 million payment terminals
Globally
So
Each country has its own specific limit
How much you can
What the
Amount of the transaction
Complete
Using contactless functionality without having a
An additional cardholder
So here's what I mean in the United States
Does a $50 contactless limit
That means that up to
$50
You can do it
Without having
To do an additional thing like provide a signature
After the fact
On credit
Until
You if you wanted to actually buy
A stereo or a TV
Best Buy
Obviously that's going
Over $50
In that case
You would tap your ring
And then it was at the merchant
Terminal
Thank you for a signature after the fact I do this actually every week with
Either Apple pay or Samsung pay I use both
I'm at
Every weekend
There you go so let's think about this because I'm very curious about
The world of the future of payments because right now I can pay with my phone
So
Allen tablet down I got my ring Wrigley now
Baby I got some crazy handbag
So
I guess is it
Oversaturation or how do you view liked the the user going through their day
In choosing these things thinking about how to
Make their payments does it just become like whatever I
It's convenient
Exactly
So thank you you hit the nail on the head so we don't think that there's going to be
A winner here
You know people have individual taste then we're in a world where
Customization and personalization and they want to be able to
Do things like pee
With whatever is most accessible or convenient or attractive to them just like you know you pick your
Clothes everyday and you
Pickyourshoes
Millions and millions of choices for those things
There will probably be many many choices for
What object
You enable
Car payment and I think different
Ways to pay are going to be more prevalent
Four different use cases right so everything is
Actually
Use case appropriate
You know you won't be using
A ring
The tap and pay
Charlie at
A restaurant
Possible but I wouldn't necessarily
Think that that's the go-to thing for
Example of a car dealership in your buying a car or
Or if even you're at a high-end luxury retailer
Weather
Sensitive very hands-on experience
You may not be
You're not in a rush
You're not
It's not giving you that kind of seemed like instant gratification pop and go quick
Convenience as you might expect
For transit or four
Parking are for a quick service restaurant or
You know that and I think there's going to be many different payment options
Better all states
Temperature at work together
To make payment
Seamless chart for the consumer
Got it
Total sense
I'm trying to imagine buying a car on
Credit and I'm like wow I need a bigger credit line
Or really terrible car I'm not sure
With the idea of you mention security so so let's talk about the protections that are given to the consumer
When they do this because I can think of a couple things
There's obviously like
Oh my gosh formation is going through the air and we talked about how that's not actually a payment information that's a token
So yeah
But then there's also worries about you know NFC sticker RFID sniffing
There's probably worried about people stealing your ring or
Gloves I mean I lose my gloves all the time
So how do you deal with those kind of issues
So they're each different I'll take them one at a time so
Whatsapp sniffing
Alrighty it is
Tokenize
So the great thing about a token is that it's not only a surrogate value
And it doesn't only have
You know a unique code your cryptographic
Psychesec
Create a unique code
So we also lock it lock that token down
Buy Channel
In some cases by merchants
So here's what I mean
If I have
A token
Available on my Langley ring
There's some specific domain controllers that are around that
Cytokines only going to be able to
To be used
Ancient Oculus location
Coming son the device
So if someone were to sniff it and put it on white plastic for example
And swipe it at the point of sale
MasterCard with no in the back end
But that transaction
You know that.
Credential mother had been compromised
And we would not allow that turn back
So because of these domain controllers it becomes
Much more secure because even if a token is
Stolen and we do assume that the hackers are going to hack
And that it will be data compromises
Throw the whole purpose
Tokenization
Was to make sure that the data
If it was comp if it were to be compromised
But useless
And that's what we've accomplished with it
Innovation technology
Okay awesome
And then
About
Like someone just grabbing my
Mike loves her
Less likely my ring
I think it's going to be different depending on the device
So this is like a multi-layered answer but
I'll try to make it simple
Some
Wearables are jewelry or
Some devices that
You know we're talking about right now
Will only work if they're Tethered to your phone
This may be because for example with ringly the whole point of a ringly ring
That is only active
If it's connected to your phone
Because its purpose main purpose
Did she give you notice
Applications of things that are happening
On your device
And so with the wiggly rangaiah
Expect the payment
Nationality will only be enabled
If there is that tether if you're in close proximity to your phone
Someone grabs your ringing
When you know a mile away and then
Another local
Whatever
Store that had a contactless terminal
It wouldn't work
There's other examples like Fitness bands that may
Had built in
Persistent authentication Technologies
You authenticate one
In the morning you put your mini band on
You know that you're able to use it for access to get into your workplace or into your computer at things like that
Like
Is there something in that device called
Persistent authentication and if it's attached to your skin
You know your biometric
Check signal
That is still on your hand in that
That's your hand it knows that that's the magic of the minivan
It will know the only enable payment functionality
When not persistent
It won't work otherwise
So again I'm giving different examples
Each of these wearables employee kind of a difference
Methodology for
Securing the payment
There are some examples though where there won't be
Authentication and it won't require a tether
Ian in that instance we're relying on the fact that it is
Tokenized
That there are
What you can do without additional cardholders
Application of course with MasterCard
There's always be reliability
You know it's something that we have is a benefit for cardholders globally
And today for example if your physical card is lost or stolen which
Very well
Adidas happens all the time
You as a cardholder are not responsible for
Any transaction that happened
You know after it's lost
So long as you were reported in a reasonable.
So there are going to still be those
Use cases and again I think they'll be less and less
Gets better and better and we are encouraging
Enjoy that are manufacturers to build in
Some kind of additional security protection
But with tokenization is zero liability protection
George
Awesome yes my credit card does get stolen like at least once a year
I don't blame you and I appreciate that
MasterCard
And also Visa very quick to let me know
So
Can I pay with this
With these types of devices
At any contactless payment
Place or do I have to okay
It kind of sounded like there were side deals that had to happen
And it's not at all
Not at all she has to do is actually turn on
Kentucky Kentucky
Functionality
So the large majority so
North of 90% I don't know the exact number but more than 90%
New terminals that are shipping today
Are shipping with NFC technology in there already
Because it has a mansion
Before it's based on the same technology that powers
And so
Terminal
Exactly
Who's not speaking matters
Credit cards
That's right and so we know we're in the midst of a liability
We're in the midst of a ship
To migrate terminals in the United States for security reasons
Nils frahm just magnetic stripe
She also
BMV chicken pen
And
I said happened and Merchants Merchants go through their regular
Terminal
Replacement cycle
You know we expect that most of the terminal
Well
Ready made with this NFC
Functionality to do is turn it on
Nice
And I can be walking through pain with
Leaves of my hand with knots of my head who knows
Even perhaps I have to ask because
I just saw the Amazon is talking about letting people pay with a selfie and I know that MasterCard introduced this
Can a concept I don't think it's real yet but I could be wrong
Where are you guys going next
So we could we actually so salty pay
Is something that we've been talking about
Amazon
Introducing at As A New Concept
But we're making available or API
Integrated into master bath
Somat surpasses master
Digital wallet
Services platform
We have
Acceptance
You know several hundred thousand Merchants locations already
You know with many more
And he
So different from all the other Platforms in our competitors
Does is it allows our banks
Integrate
Human functionality into their own
Mobile banking app
Or in a separate bank-owned app
So there's many people that
Choose to pay with Apple pay or Samsung pay or Android pay or
There's also
People that want to get these words
Services
Until masterpass allows
To add payment capability
Something that consumers already used to signing on to
And I trust and love witch
Online banking
The first Temple City
Which one is one of MasterCard
Biggest customers
Has a
Has a masterpass
Wallet
It's the city pay masterpass wallet
And you you can use it today
At Merchants Lake
J.Crew
And Wayfair and you know you can use it at many merchants
Is today that are already live with masterpass with many more to come
Later this year including some that we've announced like JetBlue and Walmart
And you use it.
Best Buy
Basically logging into your online banking credentials
So selfie pay is going to be integrated as an authentication method
We're going to be making selfie pay
Available via the masterpass apis
So that it's a bank
Azure integrating with masterpass if a bank chooses to make this Authentication
Mechanism available
They can make it about 8 available
Best Buy
Accessing
You know that part of the US
And I are making available for for banks like today
Awesome so I can pay with my fingers I can pay with my
Face it going to be
Final question for you
Where would you like to see
Contactless payment
Easier payments
Maybe it's your own life or where do you think you could have like the greatest impact I'm trying to think of like
Started my car might be really interesting cuz I'm in Texas and I spend a lot of time in it but
So
Yeah we're working I mean
This is this is a
Super exciting area to work and I think I have the best job
In the world because there are literally like Sherry go out and exactly what you said
You know we'll want to do not only from a contact list
But also
Embedded Commerce
Shameless Commerce
Experience is not only
Tap and Pay but also
You're using a
And other things like that
We are actively working
You know together with partners
Motion which have not been in that most of them
Yeah but we are actively working on
Use cases on building out in ecosystems for experiences
Connected car
Connected home
Really great pushing forward what the retail experience is going to look like
I don't want to say too much cuz I don't want to give it away but
Now you can you can definitely look forward to a bunch of
Great
You know not only pilot
Announcement
I'm in demonstrations later this year where we think we're going to be there is
Okay I will have to stay tuned it sounds like
Boucherie thanks so much for coming on the podcast
Thank you so much for having me Satan
That concludes this week show and thanks for listening to The Internet of Things podcast