Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Kevin tofel
And we have got an amazing
Start of the holiday season
Episode for you
We are going to do it
Quick that have news very minimal
We're going to have our gift guide
Then we are going to talk a little bit
Throughout about Black Friday deals that we know we're up and coming
So if you hear this after Black Friday
And finally Our Guest this week is VB Norte who is the CEO of
Data
And he's going to also offer some select pics
And talk about the future of retail in The Internet of Things
And now a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Samsung
Samsung artik is the integrated smart iot platform providing the fastest path to secure interoperable in NJ
Intelligent iot products and services
Samsung's artik smart iot platform provides both Hardware modules and cloud services either together
Or an integrated platform with an ecosystem of tools and partners to speed up your time-to-market
All right
Here we go into the show
Oh
Kevin
Hit the news
Fast
Okay so we have some news that is just reported news is not necessarily true
It's not officially acknowledged by Apple but Mark Gorman over Bloomberg is reporting
That apple is getting out of a wireless router business
And I'm scratching my head over this because
They make several routers including one that has
The backup function in a time capsule
I'm just kind of surprised
Prize that they would do this because
It kind of fits in with the whole Smart Home homekit
Market to me now the only thing I can think of is maybe
All the other new router
People that are popping up on to the market or are just
Pushing the margins out for apple and I just
Don't think it's profitable business
I don't know I mean I feel like
I just spent $500 on 3 mesh routers I feels like
It feels like a space where Apple really
Hey has the bonjour is it bonjour is a protocol they use
Thank you Spanish or four
Yes I'll say yes
Keep it simple
They've actually put a lot of innovation here in
You know up until
The launch of all these new products
What was the way to go if you wanted an easy to set up Wi-Fi
Kind of operation
It was expensive yeah that was a couple years back it got it was easy and I agree with you but now it's some of the
The newer players make it at least as easy if not easier I think
And I don't know what that there's a lot more innovation
I don't think Apple can out innovate the month on Simplicity year
Other news is
Have you guys seen that now your Amazon Echo
Has all recipes recipes in it
So basically you have the skill you
Ask for recipes and boom
You got them so Kevin
You tried this
Actually I didn't
I tried the new text messaging skill
I'm sorry
Yes that's what coordinating before they Shone like oh yeah I tried that thinking it was the text messaging I didn't
Qunar
Recipes
Well let me tell you about it cuz I have not tried it yet
Miss you guys
Nice butt
You should because Amazon
Has enabled an Allrecipes skill
The skill that you find
You can actually give the Amazon Echo
Ingredients on hand it will help you find a recipe that works for those ingredients and then you can do step by step recipe guide
Switch assembly I've been asking so you can say pause next
Repeat
Skip
So
I actually thought this was pretty cool and I can't wait to cook with it
Sadly I have yet to actually make a meal that
Involves all recipes but
Soon
I will let you know how it is in Kevin
The skill that you tripe is this the AT&T text message
It is it is I'm actually surprised it's coming
From AT&T and not a different carrier kind of figured T-Mobile kind of tries to push the
Boundaries of things Lil bit more but I'm so if you have an AT&T
Account
And an echo you can link the new AT&T text messaging skill
To your Echo
And then literally you can speak a command
To send a text message to
One of your preset favorites to set up to 10 favorites
When you do the setup of the skill
Tel Link through AT&T website in your account
And then you can just speak that person's name and say I want to send a text and
You can speak the text and it will repeat the text and then send it to that person
The person knows it's coming from
The echo however there's a little
Put her in the
Text message they receive it says sent by
Chicken shall not be named yourself
Got it
Brooks weather
That's pretty cool cuz actually one of the Google home features I liked with the if this and that was the ability to actually send a text
Message to someone verbally
So
Yay
Are we ready for the
Holidays
We better because they're here whether we're ready or not
We'll get away some of our
Black Friday commentary
In the into this cuz we've been searching for deals for you guys
As we do our gift list but
This is the
Annual gift guide and I wish we had the
I could sing some
You could I could
Let nothing you dismay
That are we in the spirit now
Okay
Let's get it
Started with
The wearables category
I got a
Hi love
Use wearables from all my running and whatnot so I'd look for a wide range of wearables
Because certain people have funeral on GPS other people don't want GPS I get that
I think
For most people I would probably recommend a fit
Fitbit charge 2 for their activity tracking
It's a $150 normally prices Black Friday deals for 1:30
Yeah
I think they do I think they do
So don't pay more than
Yasso
What would I
I mean there's tons of good choices in this price point where even last time Garland makes several choices here
You know you could even use a pebble watch and track your activities and such but it what I like about the Fitbit
Charge 2 with ecosystem it supports both IOS and Android that's a
A big bonus
Choose your device by based on what phone you use I really like the social aspect of
Fitbit ecosystem as well as
The smart
Exercise SmartTrack exercise recognition
There's so many times that I don't have a charge to actually
Got these surge cuz I wanted GPS built-in
This does not have GPS built-in it will use GPS of your attached phone
But
SmartTrack I just love it you know you decide I'm going to go for a walk and you don't have a said anything it just decides hey yo
You're walking
I know it's your walking and it just
Tracks that for yuan and locks at Sault
I kind of like that opposed to Long battery life
Can get at least four if not five days out of it. Sleep tracking
Get reminders you need some basic smartphone alerts
That's I think
Pretty good for most people
I
10 to wear however I Smartwatch and I alternate between
It was for iOS notes for Android so I've got a choice for both of us
People
Both platforms
Well obviously the Apple watches is going to be your
Your iOS device pick I have an Apple Watch 2
They start at
369 I believe we have watch to I would recommend watch to over the series 1
Because
You get the GPS built-in you get the faster chip and so on
Much better I have the old Apple watch have the new Apple watch
Much faster open apps
Really really nice does a great job with the GPS in the heart rate
So if you have IOS and iPhone
I would definitely go that route
Android you got a lot of choices
And I think Stacy you would said that your mom has like a
Gear Fit 2 or S2 smartwatch
Gear 2
Here to OKC
Certainly not bad I'm in there newer models out there
I tried the Samsung devices
Decent
I don't care if it's for the fact that they run the tizen operating system because you're limited to tizen only apps in there
Far fewer tizen apps that are Android apps
So after trying and I think I've got four five different Android Wear devices
The polar m600
The $329 has
Integrated GPS and heart rate monitor
Waterproof you can swim with it
Obviously get all of your smartphone notifications
It is bulky but if your
Interested in tracking like
Everything sleep and outdoor activities swimming and so on
I think it's one of the best GPS activity tracking iPhone to be the most stable Android Wear device so
Again 329
That would be my take if you have an Android device
Got it okay
Good
Pics from Kevin
What you got
What's a cat what's a guy
Okay
I'm into this health and wellness kit
So I'm going to recommend the sense sleep
Monitor
And the Sleep pill
What this is I'm sure you seen it because it's
It's actually very pop
It's a white orb with like little lines all over it
$150
And basically what it does is
It monitors your sleeping environment
And then it managers
Your sleep
And then you're supposed to wake you up at like an app
Each day like the best time after REM sleep
Can all of that
What's interesting is if you have a bad sleep environment it actually tells you
So it attracts like
How you sleep
To your entire
Which
Some people
They may not be anything to survive
Complete waste of money because they sleep well and they have a totally awesome
If that is you this is not a device for you
There plenty of sleep trackers that you
Are built in a fitness tracker
But if you're constantly sleeping badly and you're not sure why
This is actually really interesting way to find out
So I think it's a good gift for someone who's maybe a little Insomniac in
We're just
Freep Sports
So
And it's pretty
So pretty
If you know you get all these basically monitors the air condition since
Humidity and temperature in your bedroom so if you're interested in knowing that anyway
Yay
Damn
I also have
This is something for families and you can buy these in Lowe's
This is for the tech afraid person in your life like maybe it's a grandma maybe it's an ant
Uncle I don't
The nucleus smart intercom system
It's 199 if you buy a pair of them
And basically this is
I don't think this is good if you have a text Abby person don't buy this
If you have someone who's kind of like
Weird are you you're sick of having those calls where you're like
Open Skype I'm going to call you
Okay
You know and then you're on the phone with someone while they're calling you on Skype and it's
You know so in if you got FaceTime and someone
Comfortable using FaceTime
Probably again.
But
Here Comes nice
It is
A direct link
From you your home to someone else's home or at the direct link inside your home so if you just want a video intercom
This is actually really
Workable solution
The video quality is not super great it's only a 5 megapixel camera in there
It didn't adapt to lighting
So like
Don't put it where are you
Your back
Find a window
But other than that it works
I know that sounds like a terrible wreck
You know half the things I tried don't
It's a good thing
So
Alright so
We talked so many times about smart assistants and voice control in your smart home or just streaming music
With your voice
I was thinking what is the
Best way for someone brand new to the space that wants to experience
What we talk about when we discuss all that
And
I have to say I think the
Newest Amazon Echo Dot
The second gen. For $50
Is the best way to get your foot in the door there I mean
It works without a wireless Bluetooth speaker because it does have a small speaker in it
So you don't have to connect to another speaker
If you would like to you have that option I have mine connected to
Awesome Marshall Bluetooth
Speaker that
Alexa skills you get your
Information
If you
Ever add Smart Home
Devices to your house you know you can likely voice control
If this then that recipes that work with with the echo so
I think for $50 you just can't go wrong
And don't pay more than 40
Because
Amazon
Best Buy in Target
So Amazon
And there's probably some multi packs if you buy multiple
Echo dots as well there's a deal for 6
6 /
I don't remember
One for every room into for the bedroom
Bathroom
Bathroom bathroom
So
I would I would up this because it's Christmas and you love his pee
Alright so
I would say
Spring for the Philips Hue
Light bulb set I know there's a hug but it's the easiest one.
It works with
Just about every
So that
Is
I believe it's $70 for starter pack with two white
Ambience
And actually actually I think we saw a deal
42 bulbs
Two Philips Hue bulbs with a.
Oh yeah
Tornado
Seether
That sounds right I think so
Okay
Something could so many different people
We're terrible
We brought you these deals
Everywhere
I think
A hundred bucks you can introduce them to the smart home Concept in a way that is
Like freaking awesome
I would recommend if you do this one
A really great way to put that into
Effectus put it in your bedroom and replace your bedroom table side lamps
With those bulbs
And then you've got an alarm clock
Wake up light music
You've got
Your news briefing in the morning and then you could be like turn off my bedroom light
It wasn't even send text messages from bed hands-free
Yes
Cuz we all do that all the time
I have it I have a. In our bedroom
And
It is
We use it as an art
Hazard alarm clock now although at the internet does go out we are
Your host
You're not leaving forever
Maybe not forever
We might be late
That is that is a great deal
Andy tow
Google home is on sale
I'm seeing it for $99 at Best Buy
I'm going to tell you guys
If your die-hard fans of the space
And go for it but right now the home is not as good as the echo
Their ecosystem is Anna strong
I agree with you completely
I do have not ordered one for this very reason it's set
It's it's a new product and we're waiting for partners to come on board
Yeah and Ito Kevin actually
2 years ago didn't order an echo
Even though I did
I did not when it first came out it wasn't until they added the partner ecosystem for the smart home that I was like oh got to have it
Okay
Let's see
Next on our gift list
We went low-cost and now you got to go high-cost
I don't know who $200 for us
Starhub sister 3
Okay
High-cost June oven
I know you guys are sick of you talking about this
And I'm not going to talk about it
After this maybe
Baby
Joshua
I probably will
What's this is $1,500 * 9
Can I give you the
Gimmicky pricing
So $1,500 now the reviews from the tech press have been impressive
The reviews for normal people apparently a lot of normal people had some glitches so there were glitches there and there were people who are fresh
Frustrated with their
So I don't know what to say about that
I had a great experience with
Sing and I loved it
So I don't know
But like the Fast Company guy he had a terrible experience
Send
His semen took too long to cook
I forgot about it and he was irritated by the number of notifications although you could turn those off
It felt very different
Like his experience with
And that happens
What happens if it's a brand new product
You know lots of
Not moving Parts but lots of
Complexity unit to kind of simplify the cooking experience and some people going to have a good experience another system people
I guess so
I'm standing by it though cuz man
If I found this under the tree
After the show I'm going to show it to my wife and I'm going to see what she thinks cuz she's a normal
And she gets frustrated on my tax stuff so we'll see what she says
I'm going to have my husband Andrew
Come on the show
Talk about so you are going to here about it
And that's that's a big endorsement there it is
All right
Yeah
So we talked a lot about bulbs
The past two years and
Now is always a good time to add more bulbs I think maybe you can get some good deals
I keep coming back to two brands of bulbs for my needs and I think they meet a lot of people's needs
They're not fancy
But they do the trick
So4
Low cost smart connected bulbs that work with
Just about every
Platform that I can think of
The cree bulbs for $15 white Cree bulbs and get them in soft white or daylight 50
$10
Again work with a lot of different hubs in and what not
Controlling my voice with different assistant
I don't think so wrong for $15 plus their LED so you know your electric bill
Also like the osram lightify
Tunable connect
Did bulb switch again are still white but you can tune
The light color the white uniform like that all the way down to
From soft wake up to Daylight anything in between
You going to pay twice the prices agree about so you had a really really want
Tunable bulbs for these became both birthdays are dimmable I should say so
Those are my two Bowlby pics
And just for perspective cuz I just replaced
Light bulbs with LED
Much cheaper
Well
.
Yes they're cheap
But
I actually
They had for $15
A
Sylvania
Not connecting
LED in the
This was a BR30
It was actually br40
Abdou BR30 was
So
Just for perspective
For $15 you
Epic reconnect
I decided to not do that because I
I just wanted to control it from the switch for these bulbs so
It's not I mean you can buy cheaper light bulbs
For like
High-quality LEDs especially if you're going to put them against a dimmer switch
Which you really wanted to get
The higher quality
Don't
Don't hum
Yeah
Keep that in mind
For what it's worth and Anna
The best either not connected or
Standard LED bulbs at Home Depot last week and there are
Four packs of
40 and 60-watt replacements for 20 bucks of 5 bucks a bulb
Nice for the creases
Answer was this
Are the typical normal bulbs and the ER thirties and forties are down that bulbs
For those of you who do not speak fluent light bulb
Because why would you
Okay I'll talk
Emendation
Because I tried these this year and I love them I'm going to recommend the stack lighting
Even though I ultimately did not go with them because I have Hue Lights in my house
And I just wanted one
Setopati
The stack let's have a
Hub
And
Screw in a lightbulb
And what happens is there's an ambient light sensor in there
There's a motion sensor
And
You basically when you walk in
The lights turn on and you can set the program
With these light bulbs to be like
Hey
I'm turning on at 100% or maybe I'm only turning on it
You know
5% because it's the middle of the day
So you can settle that way
What the schedule and date they learned your schedule over
OurTime
So
After a couple of days
Oh you know around this time
She reads a lot
Maybe I'll
Will not turn off the
The motion detector
Turn off the light bulbs
So these are pretty neat
I like them they're $89 for starter kit
Normal a19 bulb so that's to normal size bolts
Or $99 for a
30 kit
So
They don't work well in open floor plans but they do work well in laundry rooms bathrooms
Closets
Places like that
Griffin
Cool
Will speaking of if this then that and turning on your lights intelligently
I'm going to recommend
For people who are interested in
Having your lights turn on when they get home
But without
Any interaction
Automatic Pro
This is a little
ODB Port dongle you put in your car
The main intention of it is to get diagnostic data from your car but also
That's a crash alert
System
So would you
Unfortunately do get in a crash it will paying the automatic Pro folks and they can reach out
How to emergency responders for you
You can keep track of where your car is located at all times with the app because again this has three
LG built-in just cool
And there's no subscription fee for 5 years without 3G so that's handy
You can't I answer if there's some that we're use of a bunch of different apps that are integrated so
You can say hey when I'm a half mile from the house on my way home
Automatic hate reach out to the nest or whatever thermostat and heat up the house cuz it's cold war
Turn on touch lights.
Not want to walk into a dark home
So 430 bucks it doesn't awful lot
And
Mini pottery places
Some of the car services that you can buy from dealers and such like OnStar and so on
It integrates nicely with a lot of Smart Home Products so I think $430 is not a bad deal
130 or
Not macro is 12995
Okay
All right
Let's see what else do we have
I have in the
Hit the button
Business because I love fun
So a lot of people are going to tell you like these flick buttons are great and they're not bad but they're Bluetooth
And I hate Bluetooth buttons because my phone is never where I think
I guess so
I spend
Speaker money
For the Logitech pop
Buttons
These are $99 a button
They're made from Logitech so
It's a legit company that we've all heard up
And you basically
You assign
Tasks to a certain type of button press and then you
And
It works
That's all it does
You can do anything you can program
Which is kind of cool
Yeah so like
You can program it to turn lights on and off
And you can stick the button like on your bedside table
You can also have it connect to maybe like some sort of Health and Wellness tracker and every time you drink a glass of water you feel
Glass of water you can just leave it by the fridge
Puppet
With Addison that you can just say
Hey everytime I pop this this way
This happens
So there's a lot of like cool fun things
Basically
Just a button
You can tell it to do anything
I love in this is why I love buttons
Because I'm a very tactile person
So
That is a fun gift
Especially if you
Do you have someone in your life
Quotes
So if you have people in your life who lose things all the time there are number Bluetooth
Tracking devices that you can get
And I got hooked up I think cuz you mentioned it
Yeah we have a CEO in our show
Exit the tractor folks right so
The trackr Bravo is is small it's like the size of a quarter
Probably twice the
The thickness of a quarter
Nothing more than a Bluetooth tracker
You can get
1 for $30 but I would say take a look at the five packs and they even have
Higher quantities as well
5 pack
You can get them for $18 each
So
This you can attach the keys put in a wallet stick it in a
Purser a Gadget Bag and anytime you can't find whatever the item is
You know you're going to your Tracker app and then I can where might it be where was it last seen and if it's close by
And even have a Tracker make a sound so so yeah so the trackr Bravo you know again a 5-pack
You can stock up on him give one to everybody in your family and hopefully they will never lose anything again
So here's another little pro-tip for you can actually get your tracker Bravo's monogrammed
Weather
You get it
A laser
Is it laser printer
You guys are etched
Design or whatever on it so if you're like
You're thinking of like hosting
Maybe not party this is kind of an expensive party favor
But if you're looking for a gift
Here's a useful product
Maybe they'll be like the USB
Okay
King of tracking
One of my gifts
Recommendation
Is the circle router
It's really not a router is a device you plug into your router is from Disney
And basically
It's $99 and it lets you offer parental controls but not just like hey turn off this device
This time it actually let you see and control the apps your child
Warriors bow sight
I guess if they don't have a
Privileges
So
I think this is a really kind of
Compelling device for somebody who is really concerned about what their child is getting into online
Maybe it's just like you know what kid
You don't need to spend 9 hours a day
Instagram
Let's take it down a notch
It's really simple you just plug it into your Wi-Fi router
And it's
That's really all I have
How to say about that
Cool I have one last item it's not
Smart it's not connected but it is saved my bacon so many times
But I think it's worth
Mentioning
When we have we live in Northeast and we have storms we often have power outages and
No power is no fun so
Couple years ago I bought something and it's still available
It's actually cheaper now
It is a small
Solar
Battery
Set
That is
Useful as all heck in these kind of emergencies
Set of small 15 watt solar panel pretty minutes it's not big at all it's not the kind of solar panel you put on
It's kind of like putting a window or
But outside you know
I mean things probably 18 in wide
And foot
Deep
It plugs into this charging base
And in the charging base there's a 54 watt hour battery
Laptop charging base also has
Two USB ports as well as to other 12 volt Outlets
And the set also comes with an LED light that plugs into one of those Outlets
So
I constantly use the sun to keep the battery in the same charge
And anytime you have an outage
We plug-in phones we use the little LED light
It's just so handy to have and it's a hundred and fifty bucks I think I paid
229 4
It's actually it actually comes from a company called FedEx International
Any create Solar Products for
Regions of the world that just don't have
Electric infrastructure in Grid
So this is how they bring electricities places but again
I bought
For here because it just
It just made sense and it is
Easley paid for itself
A number of times so it's $150
Fenix readyset solar is the name of it
Nice
Here's a gift idea for a child
Because
We love children here
There's tons of robots in
Cool things out there I leave y'all to that but
If you really want to push your child
I'm going to recommend the Kano computer kit
I love this thing my daughter actually loves to sing this is a computer consisting of a Raspberry Pi
And your kids basically build it themselves
Am I billed at themselves
Basically they plug in all the
They take the board they take the attached like the little speaker
Attachment
Is building it in
The most nominal size
That's the word but it's fun it lets kids
How to see how things work
And they get like this instant sense of accomplishment and then they can get on there and play Minecraft and learn to code
And you know do all kinds of fun things
So it is a Black Friday deal so it's 9999 right now
Sr850
Now
It doesn't come
With a monitor so you have to plug it into it
The TV your
An existing monitor that you have
If you want
They have a computer kit bundle that's $240
It does come with a monitor
And
It's a little storage case so they can
It's like there
A little laptop case
I love this my daughter really enjoyed it
I
Maybe it's cuz I'm a nerd but
I really like
Yeah sounds great
And I think that's it that's it
Did we consult gifts
We said we did
Are there any other Black Friday deals we wanted
You shouldn't pay more than $200 for a nest 3rd generation
Thermostat
They're 199 all over the place
Keep an eye on that your Amazon Echo is
Is 140
At Best Buy
Sew-in I bet Amazon's going to have it cheaper Amazon currently also has
Tap on sale
For like 80 bucks
In tap is there little speaker that
You press the button down it's the battery power right it's not always listening I have one for outside usage on the deck I love it
There you go
Absecon
A smoking deal on that
Also
Here's here's some fun other deals The Nest cam at Best Buy is going to be 150 so that's
$50 less
This Is the End
And I'm excited about this one because
I actually have these in love them
The Arlo cameras
AR
34994 a four pack
At least they require you to have a hug
So
Do you know if your
If your Kevin
But everybody else will be happy
I don't like I've I've now suggested like for gifts that come with the Hub so
Buy switch to exactly
Maybe two
8 Port switch I like the TV
Okay so the Arlo's are normally 499 for a packet
403-4944
These are great
They do require batteries are low this year released
Rechargeable version
So if you're
Not wanting to if you really want the rechargeable version because saving $150 on these cameras
You know what then spending so much on batteries is not your thing that's cool
A word of advice
We suck one of our Arlo's up in a tree
Which was great from a visual perspective and getting a grape
In a bird's-eye view of the home it's terrible for having to replace or even recharge the batteries
So
Just keep that in mind
All right I think that's pretty good
That we've given people a lot of
Things to buy
Yes we have
So go go spend that money
Going to stop
Stay tuned for a message from our sponsor and after that
Stay tuned for vboo
Norbit who is the CEO of beta
Everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham breaking into this week's podcast with a word from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Bluetooth
With us today is Van Kruger who is VP of us operations at
Akasya Network
Fan
What is cassia do in
Why do you use Bluetooth
Casting Networks we make the first
Extended range Bluetooth router called the cassia hub
Really focused on making
Bluetooth better
And trying to help it become the ideal in a protocol for the internet
And the way that we're doing that are they were extending the range up to a thousand feet or also an eagle
Multiple devices to be controlled at the same time
22 devices at the same time or in broadcast
No draxie able to hear and listen to hundreds of devices at the same time
Brussels able to control those devices when we're not on the same local network
Still making
Bluetooth really the ideal protocol for The Internet of Things
Because you connect to so many things
I imagine the interoperability
Is very important
Most definitely that's another reason you know we work with the Bluetooth Sig and Bluetooth technology
Different sample in Ark SE
Consumer products
It lets you stay paired and connected up to 22 devices
Add an extended range
Which allows you to control your Bluetooth devices from your favorite spot in any room
You know in that language is Lucci
I mean along with cassia and
He also takes interoperability as seriously as we do
Are big on collaboration and you know as one of the 3000 member companies
Do we have the opportunity to share knowledge
Contribute to the development of the new Bluetooth features and functionality
And why is that collaboration
You know working with the Bluetooth Sig and using Bluetooth technology
Apsara products
I guess it's the ability to shape the future of the smart home and you know smart Enterprises well
6 goal in which is our goal as well
Is to make the iot accessible to everyone
Unique features of Bluetooth you notes Ubiquiti interoperability and open structure
Make it possible for secret easy
Acure products forecast
Participating updates to technology units also important to us
And things like increase range speed broadcasting capacity you know Bluetooth 5
Eventually there will be standardized nest
As well
And you know really in a possibility are Limitless
And
Right now you know we're building some new Bluetooth router Cena specifically for the Enterprise
Yeah they're meant to connect even more devices in our consumer products
Applications like medical devices
Hospitals
Elderly Care Homes
You know or multiple speakers and spaces like restaurants and hotels
Where can I find Out Boy
Delphox can learn more about Casting Networks
And all the products we have to offer at www.castingnetworks.com
Cancel Mike's encourage Developers
You looking to get involved with Bluetooth to visit bluetooth.com
Ford /
Develop - with
Dash Bluetooth
Jeanette's cassia with two s's you guys thank you man
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Naughty
Who is the founder and
CEO of
Beta
How are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing okay a little under the weather but really excited to do this with you
Okay well I'm so sorry that you are under the weather I hope
I hope you feel great
I will
Okay so I have talked about beta I went there for the first time a couple weeks ago
Go in
Looks like my Nirvana it was awesome
A store full of connected products I could
Touch them
Real fast
Why did you guys
Start the store
Me and my
Two co-founders William landfill
We all work at Nest together
And
Help them
Build some of the retail efforts on the softer side
And
Start learning about how difficult it is for
Bakers
You know our manufacturers people to make products
To get into stores
Madden stores
And
Provide a compelling
Experience for
Their product especially in Connect devices
Very strongly bad
The way to
Approached
Selling a
Hubbard Park today is to take out the box
Provided MO
Tavistock member who has
The app on the device so they can show you how it works and so we felt like the best thing to do to solve this problem was actually go out
Stop round store we open one in Palo Alto about a year ago called Data V8
The number 80 a two more that we are launching this year in Santa Monica
And in University Village in Seattle
Put stuff in Egypt
Yes exactly
Sao Paulo x 80 products in the holiday season how about 90 and then our new stores are twice as big
Santa Monica have almost a hundred sixty connected products every store is different and it really depends on
What these makers believe is going to work in those locations
And for those of us who are not
Santa Monica
Or Seattle
Or Palo Alto
Wake me at Austin it sounds like you guys just did a deal where I might see some beta gear
In other place
Yes really excited we just today announced
Our partnership is Lowe's called smartspot basically we did as we took
The same things that
People love about Paul to the you know hands on
Demonstration products
Train staff and also a great assortment of not just like the traditional large
Check out some of the smaller ones
And we
Put them into a small shop and Shop
Out in the front of a couple bowls tour
Unfortunately you still have to be in California to try and
Curses I'm shaking my fist at the sky in frustration
All right
One day
One day this is
There you go
So
I actually brought you here because this is our special Thanksgiving
Episode where we're going to be talking about
What should I give my loved ones for the holiday
I also wanted you to come on and talk about the future of retail and to give me a sense of what
Kind of Trends we can look forward to in the space because you probably see a lot of really neat stuff
Way ahead of the rest of us
Yeah I would be happy to
Well let's get started with kind of the future of retail so you guys
Have a very interesting business model and then you also have you use a lot of sensors and you understand pretty well how people are
Interact with the product
I'd love to know like is that something that would work beyond what you
One way to ensure conceptualize what we're doing is
Taking the same Concepts
Of iot and applying it to an entire
Physical store so you can think of our store is a big iot object
In the sense that it has sensors
It's connected to the internet at all times
And it's sort of a vehicle for picking up data and
And also being able to be manipulated
Free software absolutely we
You know we always thought retail
As a whole
Needed to change and not just for connect devices but we really like the space
Because our customers
And you rarely mention we have a different business model to our customers are actually the people who make products day it's a super simple business model
They subscribe
Two space in stores
And we send 100% of
Sales tax
Tibet company.
Next
The challenge with retail today is not just that it's
Hard to get into if you're a very small company of Say You're Just a product off a
Kickstarter or Indiegogo it's that once you get into
The store if your product is sitting in a box
Kind of lifeless on a Shelf
And
This is by far the most common way that we still see every product
Merchandising. Customers are not going to
Interested and that was like the most basic
Something that we felt like every products
Needed
And you guys also give the data on sales
Back to
The customer so
The maker of the product knows like that X number of people got a demo on this in
Annex number
Which is actually pretty unusual in the space right
Yashow retail
Is changing really quickly
And when people coming to stores today they don't always walk out
With the Box
Read that moment you know we've all done this I do this
We walking to
Store and lock her name any names we see a product that we think is interesting and the first thing we do is we take the phone out of her pocket
And we load up Amazon
And WeChat
And see if the price
There is better
Oftentimes
It is sometimes more convenient to get the product
Assertive same-day delivery tour
Delivered in 2 days to your house or maybe you're buying it
Real still are stores or two monitors
Everything that's happening
Outside of
Justice sales with me also
Tracking UPS
Easy then what we want to understand is
How many people are actually learning about your product in the store are they engaging with it who is engaging with it
You know how it like you said how many demos are we
Providing of that product as well and
What categories are doing
Really well also has four categories
So we have connected home
We have
Connected play
Future of Transportation which is
Maybe things like electric skateboards and bikes and we have sense
Which is a category of augmented reality wearables virtual reality
Are new stores launching actually have built-in audio and virtual reality
Rooms
So weird
We're going very deep into those categories want to make sure that people like you are trying the Oculus Rift for the first time or not bumping into other customers
Person like the chaos of a normal store Department
I think
Like all of
Retail it
Really depends
A lot on season if you look at our data from all year long
Connected play has been a really big
Deal for us and certainly in December last year we opened that was a really hot category I think we have a lot of
Adults who walk in and want to buy things for kids
In the summer we noticed
Connected home was doing very well
So I think
We've got like
I would say wearables what the Temptation is
Really
All year long
Certainly
Electric skateboards are going to sell the summer and maybe not in a cold place where people can't use them
But wearables are
I've done pretty well we're not
You'll have a whole
Pelota wearables today
I'm a lot of them are made by very large companies that we tend to focus on
The small ones who are getting the first cancer retail
Ibotta
I bought the spire
Been a lot of self-improvement devices and
Like anything there's no magic there you have to
Want to improve in
And actually be proactive and they can just help you keep you on track but certainly like was firing
Upright posture trainer which has been a hot seller for us you got to put in the effort the device can only catch
Pictures of horror
True
Okay so let's get to the fun part of this where you tell us what sort of things are going to be hot for the holiday
Laser that you would put on your Gadget gifts
Sure so yeah just a precursor
The average price point are store for pots. 200
$25 I think
We definitely SKU I think
C-products little bit more expensive than we do have some affordable options but a lot of the suggestions that I have
Today are
Between 200 and
$3,000
This is not a pipe
Yeah absolutely
But they were also like you awesome
All right will let's start with the most expensive just so I can
Level set here
Couple months ago
This is the part that we do not carry it beta unfortunately
We hope to hell months ago Microsoft made their hololens
Available
For anyone to buy a developer
Kit Edition
But
If you have not tried
Microsoft hololens
Is there augmented reality
Glasses product
It is
Truly mind-blowing technology
If I'm thinking about
Someone who
You know maybe engineering your family or you want to go into the future
This is the only one that's readily available on the market today
$3,000
I believe it's $3,000
And it's a headset that I put on and then I
Grar
Basically you put the headset on and
It's got this clear piece of glass that covers your eyes
You can still see the world and
The hololens software
Places
Objects 3D models in other all kinds of
Pictures
Into the real world
So for example you can play a game in
Your living room
Where
Your hand is a is a weapon and they have these
Bugs coming out of walls
And they look like they're actually coming
From your
Living room
It's super fun super interesting without all kinds of other productivity apps
As well it's really hard to
You have to try it two times
First and why it's so cool I'm recommending it you can you know one of the things that my wife and I did is
Now we sat down and
Draw in space
A very large screen to watch
IMovie on so you can imagine having like a 40-foot
Display right in your in your bedroom
It's just it's a really phenomenal experience and it's worth a try
All right
Hurry up and get that stocks
What else
SRS
Again
A little bit on the
Expensive side
I've really enjoyed my juicero
Have you have you tried you sorry yet I have tried and I've tried
Statues
A $700 juicer Plus
Lucy is it $8 for the
Juice packets
Yeah $47
And
If it does come with subscription and is it can be quite expensive
What's really interesting about
This company is
They
When you get a box of juicero juice delivered to your door
The fruits and vegetables
That are inside of the packs are
Usually no more than a couple days or a week old
Color Farm
I really like the software
I think the hardware is beautiful
And the quality of the food that it makes us
I'm really up there
The best of them
Let's pop down to the baby more attainable side of
Catch it recommendations here
By the way this might be our one of our top sellers all year but this is a
2999 dollar
Car finder and
USB car charger
Call Nanda by Zeus
It's a really simple product but people really like it basically
It's a dongle that plugs into your the cigarette port
In your car
And
I will help you find your car
Are you even a parking lot
Are you coming before you put it
And then it's also a fast charger for your device it says got to USB
That is a good
And this is not something that goes into your OBD port
Pikachu Diagnostics this is just straight up
Find your car
Or
And as soon as
Is Bluetooth
Find your car yeah it's like it's like tile for your car I would
Okay
What else
Let's see
That feels like a stocking stuffer you have any more stocking stuffers running around there
There's an interesting product at
Launch maybe just a month-and-a-half ago or so-called revolar
R e v o l a r
Under $100
And it's a
Emergency
Safety device
Yeah I think
The team behind it
View reader stories
It's pretty inspiring but
Essentially you can give it to you for example
Your grandmother and
And this actually happen to me very recently and so this is
Ella person all the money
Mother took a fall in
Had trouble
Reaching for the phone or calling for help
And it's the button that you can wear on your hell or put in your pocket and you call it in
I will call for help
And does it is a
Bluetooth
Or is it
Sirius Bluetooth
Yes they do have to have the
Pho nearby to you
I love buttons
Alright let's talk about some
Kids
Since those are such a popular seller
At your store what should I buy my children
My little baby children and maybe my
Preteen
Children
A lot of amazing products for kids
Today especially
Chinese word of Education
Cosplay space
Osmo has a
Osmo Smo is a
Augmented reality
Kit for your iPad
And you know how kids love their iPads
Basically you can put that you put the iPad
Into this dock
And it's got a mirror
On the front facing camera
And they have a series of games that you can play
With physical
Objects so free sample to have a
A set of letters
I have a set of
Numbers
They have a
Apple coding kit
You can basically play with these two squadrons in front of the iPad
And interacts with the with the apps
A lot of accessories
A lot of games but after the iPad
And
It's
Quite affordable they have
A couple different kits
You can get one for under $100 the osmo genius kit
I have a new one called the author of Wonder cat which has
Codeine
Has a Creed a creativity set for kids that like to draw
When it's really it's really cool product and something you definitely
I should have
And does it grow with your kids like what
CH range
It does sound sad
Minimum five years old but some of the games
Are Cam Kit even for adults
Let's see what else for
Maybe older
There's a product called electric blue guitar
That we just debuted and it's a
It's a guitar electric guitar tab
What you built and
I can teach you how to play
So it doesn't
Guitar
Yeah it looks
It's like a small electric guitar
The kit comes with the parks and you have to
Together
And then it teaches you how
She got to play videos or with
I like iy
How much is that guitars $149
For the basement we have some other colors that are done
Brown children
And you can also buy an amp and
Chords for
Another
Are between $1,500
That's so you can actually hear the music
All right
But if you have any other kid gifts or should we move on
Yeah there's there's one more this one we don't carry her store but
If you haven't tried honky
Overdrive an-ki
And they just launched a new
A new product as well wishes at a cute little robot
But the Anki overdrive product is a
Artificial intelligence race track
Where are the cars
You places little cars
On the track and they raised themselves and you can race against them
With your phone
The technology is really cool
But
Having tried this with kids
You know anywhere from five to 10 years old
They really really want this especially
Your kid isn't into cars at all you can pick one up for
Look at it
Okay Daddy 149 at Walmart
Methodist Christian
Yeah
All right maybe it's Black Friday deal
Oh I'm sorry it's 1:40.
Target
It's 2:20
So Best Buy in Toys R Us
Oh it's the starter kit not the full
So you don't need the full kit it just comes with I think extra tracks and extra cars
Verisign
Okay
Dial
Hard gift right here
What should I buy for my
Take another if you are a very practical Gift Giver
This is the year of
Amazing wife new Wi-Fi products
So I really think everyone should be looking at some of the
The options out there today Eero Luma
Onhub
Notting Hill
That's super boring
Do something fun
Maybe for a guy
Really cool product called
Broly
Rol I
And they just launched
Stryker blog
Anesthesia
Is connectable
Modular
Music studio.
But you create
Electronic music and they're really
It's really fun the really interesting and even if you're ready not very talented you can still makes up the sound pretty
And they're really fun to play with a just
Just came out last week or two weeks ago
And for not available data there
Exclusive Apple stores
The main
You know that you need is a hundred 7995
Anime Similar add-ons for about $80
Sweet
So anybody Likes music
And
What about
I
Really like
Mural camp
So m e u r a l
So this is a beautiful display and it's really a monitor but
If you look at it in real life you can
It's got this interesting for a matte finish
On the display so it doesn't look like a display
And you can Scott gesture control built into it and you can basically swap out
Different create artworks from
Everything from
Photography 2
Pieces that you might see in the loop
The quality is great
They have a bunch of different finishes
And
The price anywhere between
The 500 and 600 depending on the
An exact finish
Great piece for your home in
Now that product in our stores has
I sold like fire
Well I think I saw it
Yeah it's it's very nice it's probably
Would you say it's like to buy three
3 or 18 inch bike
Yeah about there it's about
18 in
At that it's but it is it is large it's very pretty
I didn't realize it was Cheshire Cat
Control that super
All right
Any final gifts you want
Throw out for
There's been some interesting I mean this
You know we've had
Wifi photo frame
Many many years
And this year in particular has been a new crop of
Very nicely done
Wi-Fi photo frames that have
I really great software that connects to your phone
I'm 1/2 just launched is called Hora frames
What is scattered on the high-end
I believe they retail for $400 but
Beautiful looking object
But the software is really really cool so basically you can
I'll take your entire photo library and never
You know install the app and never ever
I have to like sync photos to your
Frame
It just takes off the best moments in
Magically
You always see something new on your on your friend which is one of the
The big letdown
Oh you know guys this was it this is our aaura
Smart picture frame
And it was an old magazine
Favorite thing in
Tan tantan Oprah approved
Yes Oprah not on the same page here
Great that's going to do very well
For your store then
Alright thank you so
Much
Coming on the show I should ask you
Because it's
Almost Black Friday
Are you guys going to have any great Black Friday deals
Yeah so let me first call I really appreciate you coming out I'm a big fan and a listener and a lot of my
What team is as well shut up the Gilbert Chan
Your biggest fan probably
Yasso
We're doing Black Friday a little differently
So we're not doing like a doorbuster you know wait outside in the cold type of
Black Friday
Partly because it's never cold in California
But
That we will be open
The store I'm going to have
Mimosas and
Have a fun Lively atmosphere and
I will certainly have
A lot of discounts on
Bikes that you need
I mentioned on the show
All right
Get ready to shop
You guys
Thanks so much
Well that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show
Feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
Stacey on iot data