Hey everyone welcome back to this week's I was going to say CES podcast but it's actually
The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we are talking about CS because it is more show than
Cover it and even
The one last week
Special edition pop
250 ES hangover show as I said before we started recording
Exactly and like any good hangover show
Well I have a cold
So you have the CES flu
And you seem surprised that you're sick but I am not Cousin 10 years ago and I always got sick and everybody gets sick
It's just
Part of CBS
I feel good more than
It's a badge of honor wear it Own It proudly
Like the other hundred and sixty thousand
So there
But I also
So
We're going to get started the show is
Really awesome actually cuz we actually thought about what
CSM going to talk about
Who is the star of CES
Fitness app store
Why industrial is the height iot of the future
My home getting an email address
Carnival
And there
LG cruise ship
And I'm going to get to that door hinge sensor
Didn't work out so well
And
We'll also have a
Message from Dell
Who is our big sponsor this week and as our guests we have Lucy Rogers who's going to tell you how to become a make
Just in case that's one of your New Year's resolutions
And why wouldn't it
But first
Let's get a message
Primary sponsor
This week's monster is level education
The Internet of Things is going to be the hot job at the future so prepare for it with iot training from Level education
Can in Cisco it created the iot core program which is a 15-week blended learning
Transfer the foundational knowledge associated with the internet of things you're going to have ample Hands-On learning opportunity
Real world examples online learning hackathons and project-based learning you're going to emerge for the 6th
Experiences the course starts on February 13th
And to find out more go to level edu.com IO.
That's level edu.com
Flash iot
Kevin
Stacy
This year
Was the star
Well obviously because I wasn't there I'm going by third-party reports since I read a ton of coverage
And it seems to be I'm not going to name her name but the woman Inside the Amazon Echo with star of the show and
She really wasn't even there
It's not like Amazon has a booth
They didn't write but they did have a truck that dispensed Gadget
Oh I want one
Can I order one
Would love a truck filled with treasures and trinkets and gadgets
I am sure
Prime now
What's
Usually I have seen Amazon products in the past but it's usually from like the people who put the chips inside and so on
You know the fire tablets and things like that
But yeah so
It seems like
They were tons of gadgets that were incorporating
The Voice services are inside the Echo and I strategically didn't mention your name I thought I did a good job.
Now again I wasn't there so I was reading 3rd
Stories
Did you see some of these gadgets that
Came out like I know LG has one where was Algeria Lenovo has the
Eraser
Prettier version
Right right it's a Sydney two-cylinder just like the regular Echo apparently has a much better speaker in
Which I don't think the speaker in that activates all that bad to begin with but hey more sound more bass that's good
It's interesting to me that they just basically created a what I think is a clone of the echo
Which anybody could really do because of the voice services are
Available for developers so you can
You know if you got some Hardware smarts and some developers March you could create one of these things
But they weren't the only one it just seemed like there were so many products
It's my companies that said hey
This is already working so well for so many people let's not develop our own
Cloud-based
Voice recognition system let's just use one that's available and that's of course I win for Amazon as well
So basically what Amazon has created here is
Incredible platform
And they did it by being open
So when someone came to them and said
Into the Trilby guys I was like hey you guys are actually doing
It was a speaker for the kitchen
Using
We kind of have to say it the
Abs
Cicatrix
So using AVS
Which is a voice service
They built basically
It had a few modifications but it was essentially an echo
And I talked to them and they were like yeah it was I was cool with
They wanted this out there so yeah
That is the mark of an excellent platform and that What's Happening Here is Amazon wants to be the os4
For The Internet of Things
Or maybe it's the OS for the boys plaits
It's
I think those are two separate things that we shouldn't get them
I think you're right I would I would classify as they want to be the interface
For your smartphone
Just like apple brought.
Capacitive touch
Right
Baby had resistance before that resistance touch before the capacitive touch was a ground changing
And they define the features hinchan Zoom swiping
What's happening is it
Amazon with the echo is
Or with AVS more specifically is defining the interface for
End
Actually we could see this
Coming because
Companies like a rant
In ALA
Those two guys are helping
Product manufacturer
Basically create
Cloud services for
Connect two things so there the brains
Are the brains in the muscle that are actually make
You're like washing machine
Your smoke detectors
Connected
And those guys
Have integrated and made it super easy for the manufacturers to add
Avs2 there
Air Products
And in talking to those companies they're like yeah
Every single manufacturer is come to us in the last 6 months and said we have to be on the echo
That is number one feature
That we need for
For consumers
So
We saw this coming
It's actually out
Google
Where are you
I've got to say that like
I know that Google has the apis for
For their voice but
Antarctica
So I think it was a really good point I'm also just real quick going to disclose that I am a full-time consultant for Google I do now
At work with the Google Home Products or anything like that I work with Android and chrome stuff
I agree with you though first-mover status here has been huge for Amazon
Like making the platform open by being developer-friendly
This is why I mean
I work for Google and I don't have a Google why not
I have 4 echos In the House
Why do I for icons
Because it open enough and came out sooner
So that the products that I want to use work with it
I can't say the same about Google home or other
Similar devices so
Yeah first-mover Status here has been huge in my opinion
So I did run into wink at the show and they said that we should see them on Google home
So those of you with the wink
He said in a matter of
Weeks
I've no doubt it will happen
I mean yeah wink is I think a
A solid player in this in the space for smart home hubs
And there's many others that we
We talked about
Them in the past
So I'm sure it will come to Google home
But you know again then will people like me say I've already invested in X number of Echoes
What's better with home or whatever other competing product and
I do think
For information
When you're requesting information I think maybe home has an advantage there
But I have my phone and other devices for that so I don't
Nebat personalized
I mean I switch quite honestly even one wink support comes
You know Google home is better at more than just information
Because when you talk to it as much more conversation
Also
When I tell the echo to set an alarm
For 6
Is it always ass a.m. or p.m.
So I have to remember am now if I tell Google home
To set an alert for 6
The clock it's like
Done Saturday
I set an alarm for 6 a.m.
Yeah I think it's
Yeah I think that gets into the context that Google Now is brought
Go to Google home
Which is very good
I also wonder if
What would happen if you set that alarm at 4 in the afternoon
Because I'm wondering if it just sets the alarm for the next instance of 6
It might
And that makes a lot
I'm just taking a guess I don't know cuz I can't I can't text on my phone I suppose with Google Assistant but I do think
Text or standpoint
Google services do have an advantage
We'll get into this at another show cuz I'm actually writing an essay on
Context
It was the
Context was the undercurrent of CES
That's too many to get into now
And I want to write it before I talk about it
It's at all a morphis in my mind
But it's
I hope your reference my 2012 or 2013 article that I wrote for you on
Is the title was
Why won't Google Now my wrist
Context is King
Call Kev
Alright so let's move on
Yuan to
Fitbit
App Store
We will take their plans to
I want an app store this year so they don't have an app store yet
But they're going to do one
Okay cool what time am I just do it cuz everybody else has an app store Napster the big thing the big try
I'm not sure I want to see if Fitbit app store in the reason why
One of the things
I think my Fitbit so successful is it's really good at a few core features
And it's simple
Bring an app store and you start adding complexity and such that I don't know that
Would help this product I mean
I love Fitbit of had
2-3 maybe even for fitbit's and they worked great for me
I don't know if there's even talk into the Verge had talked to the founder of the co-founder and CEO James
And so the purchasing well there's it's undoubtedly meaning that fitbit's going to also a launch create a smartwatch
Unlike
Why not just have the Fitbit app
That works well on an Apple Watch and Android Wear why do you need to do that
Come scratch my head on this
What you think
So this is everyone has to have a plateau
And you know Fitbit is in a hard spot
With the financial markets
Member is public
They've got to do more than sell devices because devices are come out
Quality business in this is the truth of everyone who is going to get into the consumer Internet of Things
This'll be a good segue into a later segment
What we got here
Where is all of
These company
Are like
I need another source of Revenue
I need to
And so it's not enough to have Fitbit you know extend its API to all of these other devices out though
Thayer witch
Honestly it's the best interface for iot
They got to have an app store
And it got to have a revenue model that gets them a chunk of change so
I don't like it I don't think it's the best way to go but
I see why they're do
I asked you why I think you you laid out a very good case for it I just wonder I mean
They don't just need a nap store they need a successful App Store and
By investing resources development in SM mean it's got a payoff otherwise they could be in worse shape
Goodnight I just worried that the being worshipped but I don't want to see what happened obviously
Will you know they acquired Pebble now I don't know how it didn't acquire
All of the
In Pebble had an app store and they did
Well wish
With it
I don't know where there any apps on the pebble App Store that were actually purchasable
I believe you could purchase apps
I haven't had a pebble in quite a while and that's another example of a device that actually works really well it didn't do that much at
First what it did it did really well
That was no smartphone notifications and such
And then they started adding complexity
Out of the same thing it was already existing popular SmartWatches and it didn't work out
So that's my fear
Alright so
We're a little worried about Fitbit
Let's move to the high seas
Carnival Cruise ships
So this is a really interesting story out of Cs and it I think it shows what you can do when you have a closed ecosystem
So moving from open platforms let's talk about
And this is Carnival is basically creating
Iot device
The ocean medallion
Have you can wear it on your wrist you can clip it on your thing it's waterproof so you can swim
Baby fall into the ocean eyes
So what's happening here
Where is this becomes
The digital representation of
Cruise ships
And it was created by man named John Padgett
Cool also
What's the guy who helped create Disney
I love the fast fast so what's happening
Is
This allows Carnival
To personalize your experience so when you're walking past like a connected
Touch screen
It's going to read who you are and it's going to be like oh
Here's your itinerary for the day or here's the things you're interested
You're going to get
Directions around the cruise ship
From this
You're going to actually have all that you had the chance to on the web fill out your
Court papers so there's a lot of paperwork before you go on a cruise and usually you do it right before you get on
Now you can do it on the web
It transfers to your medallion
And then you can just walk on the ship
I think this is really interests
So this is all theoretical this is CES
Is there really working on it
But it's going to be out November on
The top-of-the-line
Cruise ships
There's a lot to learn here so I'm going to keep an eye on this project mostly because I think there's some cool stuff that can be applied to Smart City
I think they thought
You know what the advantage and the fact that it's
It's a commercial endeavor
You don't get much more closed environment
Cruise ship
Yeah and it gets back to that theme of contacts I mean if you're walking past a restaurant
On the cruise ship
Then maybe you had look for a reservation and you didn't find any
OpenTable
Look and say hey if someone says walking past guess what let's ping them
Hate you had you one of the spot we got a spot now just opened up come on in
Exactly
And they're interesting things that kind of make me a little nervous but like
If you like gambling for example it can actually give you directions
Route you pass casinos on the ship
Well isn't that convenient
This is the sky's the limit stuff we're iotb
Becomes really interesting
And I think we're going to see these cases develop first in these places like Disneyland
Disney World
On the cruise ships because
They can control everything they have all the
So
What's also interesting is the aspect of
Privacy security
In that
You're going to be letting the ships
System know where you are at all times more than likely which is not necessarily A Bad Thing
From a safety perspective that could be very useful obviously
But I wonder if people will say I just want to go on a cruise and I don't want them to be no one worm
Vuclip
I know they they do anyway but this is just a
Another this is a little different because this is something you're wearing to allow that to happen
As opposed to say Tamara's and what not you know
Very passive things this is an active thing
Will you have to wear
So when I said you can't
It means like if you want to go on these
Medallion chips
Ditmore
Hopefully
You must wear The Medallion
Habitat
It's the same as your room key
Like that let you in and out of
TCU have to have it now you don't have to interact with
You don't have to fill out all the personal prep
But I do want it on you
Because it's your room.
Key because they need to track p
People around the ship
Center for safety
Actually like in a situation like in Apache
Situation or even if
Norovirus
Comes out all the time
Cruise ships want to track who was on certain
Dax photography
Affected by
The virus
That's actually really
Useful for both the ship and the passengers
No doubt no doubt I I mean I do see positive things too as well I just
Just asking a question allowed here like
And I mean that you're not wearing it and you must watch everything MP3 overboard I don't know
It's not so extreme is all that
So
This ties into industrial being the hot iot of the future I wouldn't classify Carnival as industrial bi-weekly
Classifiers Enterprise
Is a business case
Again going back to
Fitbit consumer was everywhere obviously the Consumer Electronics Show
But the big money making opportunities
Really seem to be an industrial because there was a big sense of the show that
Consumers hard and we're going to get people to pay for ongoing revenue streams and
I don't know if this is really going to work
So tied to
All of the mini smart home platform
Forms I saw there
Silver Lake over a dozen
Some of them were from
Carriers like in
In your opinion
Asia and all that and some of them were actually just
Chinese companies that have actually stepped up in their design and like Zmodo
Is a Chinese company in
They're showing off some really compelling products I actually am going to try to get some and review them
And they have a whole smart home sweet and there were dozens of these maybe not.
There were at least a dozen
Ensue
It feels like the smart home stuff in
Consumer-oriented
I was going to get come out of ties so fast
You're going to need new revenue streams if you really want to be a player here
Probably going to have to be big
So then
All of the activity should be turning to Industrial
In Enterprise
Because I think that's where we're going to see people actually spend
And it's a lot easier you make one
Sale for example and they could be worth
Millions or even billions of dollars you know as opposed to trying to piece mail
A million consumers all around the world to purchase your products so I definitely see that a lot of bang for buck there
What I didn't see a lot of with smarts
I saw some use cases but I didn't see I didn't get the sense there's a lot of spending
They're so
I mean I saw so many LED can I
Nexus street lights
We should put LEDs in
I don't think
And again I haven't been to see us in two years so I could have changed I don't think you're going to see like the
Municipalities showing up to see what technology is out there I think that's probably a different show
So that's probably why you didn't see that
Probably
Okay you're right
Expected EPS I'll give you that
Can your 10 years of CEO
So that's and colds too.
Ten codes 10 years
All right
Okay let's talk really fast about
Comcast
Because
Last time we checked which was about a year ago it's at 500000
Connected homes like people using a smart home and home automation
Call Xfinity home
And I saw them at the show this was their first CES
And they were showing off
Two things worth mentioning
One is they did a deal with a company called sierant
To help with
Provisioning
In provisioning is the act of getting devices on
Weight gain and connected to the cloud getting them on
Night so that takes a
Cloud side but it also takes the consumer going
Like downloading the app
And doing whatever
They need to do
There so many ways
Supervision
So
What Comcast showed off
Was
That it did this deal with. And
Now any device that has secret software and there could be more
Are already online with Comcast public Wi-Fi
So what happens is you bring it into your home
You download the app in the app searches for
The most recently connected
Device to your net
Redis trying to connect to your network
Is Caesar
And it says hey do you want to
Activate this
And you hit the button and it does
If it's in a Comcast home and you have a Comcast router in this is important
You're not using a Comcast router
Get this
It will actually give you two options one is activated
Like the manual way
The other is activated on
Comcast Xfinity home
You press that button
Literally everything is automated gives you your SSID
It does all of that and suddenly your device pops up on
Which is pretty cool
Yeah we'll set up Simplicity is a big thing
Smart home mix one of the reasons people don't want to get things like I don't have to mess with us
So they definitely made it easier that got a new Gateway that I think they're coming out with this year
5:30
Gabby's going to say what they got the new Gateway and then all of the software features that you're talking about I think we'll actually be
Apply to the old gateways as well so you don't
Necessarily have to get the new gateway to get all these features but
I could be wrong
No you are right
I'm two for two
No wonder I have you with
I'm so glad I cannot wait to see you spell weight
Your nuts
Okay so the other aspect of Comcast that's worth
Doting is I actually
I don't have strong lovey-dovey feelings for Comcast because I've
Cover net neutrality in the past
End data caps
Which Comcast every time I say the word data caps they're going to argue with me
It's a data cap
What is a terabyte
What they done now
It's actually really nice they've created
Three or four years ago.
Bought a company called Power. Which made a really cool wi-fi system so way before everyone else was like
Hey wife I should have better software it be easier for Consumers power. Was doing
So when Comcast bought them I was excited to see you
Finally it has happened
The acquisition of power dog
Plus all the time automation stuff and
Good routers coming out
Put Comcast into making software on this new Gateway
It is
So user
Friendly
And it's even cute
So
They let you create profiles for people they let like
Many of the things you would expect
From a modern router
Such as you know
Being able to see
All of the devices on your
Being able to see who's associated with
Being able to see how much they're using and when they're using it
All of that is now available
And I love it
And they'd have cute little designs
State to have like
Profile animal
Like your spirit animal
Xboxes and Rec
The design was done in part by a guy who used to do
Nike's fuelband se
So that's all great and it offers up to nine gigabytes of Wi-Fi
You know if you have a massive
Connection
It looks nice and simple and I can't get back to you
Bring Simplicity but allowing for control which is what you want to do with the steady want to go to control who has access
I maybe
Certain time you want to flip internet off for certain people or certain devices that's great
So it's not going to work was she who shall not
I was like what about voice there like we have the Xfinity X1
Yeah they got their own boys play their side I'm not surprised by that
But you know you do have to find her
Voices the invisible interface
Visible if you have to pay
I agree
News and finally
2 weeks ago
Her name is a week and a half ago
I don't remember
I purchased the GE Z-Wave
Wireless smart door sensor
Hinge pin
So
If you guys are like what the what
This is
That is supposed to be an invisible open close sensor for your door you basically stick it on the
Hinge pin
Of your door
In
It has a little thing that sticks out and hits the door
So it's kind of shaped like a
A number seven
Little arm basically
A little arm
It hits the door and when it goes past a certain
Point is supposed to trigger it to say hey the door is open
In
I looked at this and I was like oh my God I have to
The Habit is awesome so I plop down the 40 bucks on Amazon
It arrived
And I went to install
And that is when
I cannot recommend this product
I'm actually I printed out the return label and I'm sending it back
Probably tomorrow
Because
Set up was easy I hooked it up with my wink hub
And that was great I also hooked it up with my SmartThings Hub
And that was just a just to try it out for both platform
And
Installing it on the door was okay
I mean I just had that my hinge pins were a little rusty
So I had to let Billy Wacom out there basically you just have to take a hinge pin out put this thing on the hinge and then put the
Pinback I'm guessing
Next
But
It does not fit tight
To the hinge pin
Or the wall
Which means
When the door opens
The bass moves
Because the clique
To trigger it from open to close
Who's fairly sensitive
When you open and close the door the whole apparatus moves in does it messes with the
Operation
Does happen
That's that's a shame because I'm paper this sounded so good because it is essentially invisible right it's it's not like a box
Aksara
Something that you can
Easily see if I can fix you
Emacs
You can actually buy paintable version
Yeah so they're there it's made to be hidden but smart and informative
And I'm just going to ask this question I think I know the answer
You don't have any
Unique or special hindered or that you're applying is to unassuming
No this was
Regular
This was an outsider
So it was a little girl front door
It was the door to my room
Cuz I was like if that I would love to know when that soap
Right right so for an exterior door using it on
But it would have the same problems on an interior door
Even though they're not as heavy
I think the the big flies that it just doesn't fit tight so it
It moves when you open and close the door which means
So you can't accurately measure that point
Yes we spent 40 is so my husband and I spent 45 minutes calibrating this thing
In
We never got it to actually work
So we never actually got it
Close
At the right time
If you held it maybe if I duct-taped it down
Well there goes the invisible Factor
These were these were the
Whitney
But yes it at that point it was like
Nope
Traditional open
And I am going to try the census
Strips sensitive strips at sensitive
Two A's
Right those are the three three mm thick strips I think that you just put inside a door framing
It's a simple open close sensor that you really can't see easily
Yes but I have heard the
They have a similar problem
Their hearts
I don't know why those are hard to kill
But you know
We might discuss
I guess the point here is probably don't want to buy this sensor
Maybe if you have really maybe my hinge pins weren't fat butt
I really don't think this was something that was actually a parent in the
Reviews
So I just want to
You are don't you worry about that
If you can somehow
Tighten the thing to your hinge pin
Maybe that
Work
I don't think we need to tighten the store in Japan I think there needs to be a analysis and redesign
Yes
That is Stacey Higginbotham
Review of
The hinge pin smart door sensor
Easy to connect
That
Probably is good for the news Fortune of this week show
You're going to still hear a lot more about CEs from us probably
Because I still have lots of things
I think about
And talk about
But it's going to be more Blended in
With the rest of the show
Next week I'm going to talk about my
Hulk
And
Stay tuned for a message from our sponsor and our guests who is Lucy Rogers
She's going to tell you how to become a maker and give you to project
One of which is controlling a dinosaur
The other witch
Is making a SMART Bus notification system
You're going to love it hey everyone we are interrupting The Internet of Things podcast with a message from Mars
Sponsor
Who is the iot solutions director at Dell here to talk to us
About blueprints
Hi Kevin
Tell us about These Blueprints and what they are
Absolutely Stacy said Nobody Does it all in iot Avenger says that they can
They're either lying
To you or their delusion
And that's why we work very closely with our partners to develop these blueprints
What seas are there use case Focus
Where we take
In a working from the industry's broadest iot infrastructure
Portfolio that Dell Technologies
These can offer then we work with are curated Partners to integrate their different
Ingredients both software and Hardware
And then we validate
Missions in riot
Labs to ensure that are custom
Get to our life
You're in the business space
Type of iot is actually doing it
Disservice because it's making it harder for
For Business Leaders to really understand
Where they should focus their efforts around iot
What initiatives they should be putting into place
And that's why I hear Adele really working hard to shift
From use case stories or what I call Flying Pig there's a lot of those in
In iot
Can moving more towards real deployments real r a y
Cut through all this how you can help our customers really make
Impactful decisions around their iot an issue
All right what is it about the Internet of Things
Requires companies to have
You know the issue is that there's so much fragmentation
And iot today 400 different and grieving up to 400
30 difference
Platforms that analysts are tracking
And what that means is every iota
Deployment
Tends to be a snowflake
Might look the same from a mark
Texture perspective but really when you dig in its
Unique is totally different there's lots of custom code being written
And the challenge there is that slows down our customers from
Really getting the return on these iot initiative
And that's the reason why these blueprints
Provides repeatability because I can't we validated it in our labs
And ultimately our customers can then trust because
It's proven
That they can implement it and not have it be a snowflake but had to be something that they can manage and secure and deploy
Boy faster
Kevin I've learned so much about Looper
Where can I buy
The best place to learn more is he go to dell.com iot
We have a learning library there we include all of these differ
Blueprints actually published 20 of them today
You'll find blueprints like cold chain Logistics with our partner IMS
Evolve
Connected machines with GE
Predicts
Among 20 others
That's a lot of opportunities for you to learn about these repeatable Solutions and IRT at dell.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is
Dr. Lucy Rogers
She is the
Creator and head of maker torium
Which is an engineering consultancy
And it is focused on problem-solving
And The Internet of Things
She also has a book she's going to tell you about and she is hacked many
A dinosaur
So hi Lucy how are you doing
I'm great thanks have a meal
Oh man thanks for coming I am super excited to have you
Because you are a Peacemaker person that I follow and
Excited about
Guys I've got to be all Fangirl
Tell me about the book
The book is called wiring The Internet of Things it will be published by O'Reilly
Later next year hopefully april-may time
It's already available on pre-orders you got to have a look on the O'Reilly website
And it's all about connecting
Hardware with aerobic like
Computer
Using node red software and
Mqtt messaging protocol
And just how you can put those three things together
And if you have the ability to put together
Ikea furniture
You have the ability to put together your own internet so sing sing
It's true and we're going to talk about that later in the show
So first off let's kick it off with
We've been like throwing around the phrase the internet of things for years now
And a lot already in this conversation
What does that even mean to you
Who is someone who is
Probably been doing connected stuff for way before this was like even
Get the Internet of Things me the million things
2 million different people
To me and how I like to think about it
Is
Guessing something
Say
The toy
And so you won't
Put a toy in your child's bedroom
And tweet them when it's time for dinner so you want the toy to start worrying if it's it's
Toy dinosaur you can
Facts that
Put it on your own WiFi
Connected to the internet
Tweet something else and it will make the dinosaur noise
In your child's bedroom
Take another step further what if
I know
Elderly parents
They're on the road
And that quite happy that quite good but
I'm a little bit worried about them what if I
Especially in person to monitor their electricity Supply and I know
My parents
Make a cup of tea first thing in the morning so that be a spike in their electricity
I want to see
Is that Spike happened
I don't want to see that
I just want to message that tells me
Other side of the country
That's yes
Put the catalog so everything's okay and if they haven't done that on my way to give him a ring so I want the message to say
Casino Newcastle Spike has been noted in electricity Supply
You might want to call your parents
Kind of Internet
Things connecting
Things
But we may not quite know about so quite we want to
Going to intricate detail but more
Insurance things make things have a life of Their Own
And then if we can take that a step further and stomp actually
Analyzing some of that stuff
Take Canadian industry.
Where Internet of Things is really going to work
So this gets to me
Theory of making
Because I think the same way you
I got all these bits and Bobs and what can I do with them to make cool new things out of
It occurred to me after covering this for a while that most people don't
Shake That
Most people want prescribed recipes are products that are like
I do this
So is this an eighth thing and everyone looks like
Creativity and desire to make it how can we make it
More so I guess
Future Generations is that even in
I think it's really important
I think
It was a night
And
If you look good
3 4 5 year olds
Will they doing all the time that playing with stuff
That making things happen they using their imagination
The filing and the filing Austin
But it doesn't matter then
They keep trying again and they build on that
Episonic climb a tree they might
Full of the first Branch hunting salesman
Dinotu
Hold on better next time
And so this
Picture of learning
What we do when we
Playing
Is really critical in to be creative or what happens if
What can I do when
How do I make this do what I wanted to do
Which is oldest things that we have as a child
Thought
School
Parents growing up
Something
Nazi sound of us
We don't want
Play anymore we don't want to be seen to be failing
But I think the actual
Having fun the creative bit
Alps Iceman and houses get
Tudo que what is it that I want to do I no longer want to just be
Even
Dissolution
Because what I want isn't actually
What
10 of the people want I want
To me and said to get Luke bespoke Solutions we're going to have to start doing them for ourselves
So for kids I love her like
You're a big fan of the Raspberry Pi so
Maybe this is why
But like
If I want an easy way into this as an adult
Or if I want to provide something for my kids
What are the tools you think I would
I'm going to go with the roster
Because
It is an expensive is 30 pounds for a Raspberry Pi
It has a base of the computing power of a computer from about 10 years ago
Answer 10 years ago you wouldn't have given anybody here you all his the family
Computer this
Thousands of pounds
You wouldn't let someone just going to hack into Old try things
With it too if you broke it that would be a big
Copeland
If you break a 30 pounds computer will not such a big problem
I'm not computer that. Moseby
Supplies the brain
Which you can hang other things off so whether you're programming it
In a programming language or
Node red which is visual flow so you can see he doesn't need to worry about the semantics of
How about through color in the right places do I need to
Finish this with a colon or semicolon on how does this work the first step but that's my knee
The computer step
The brain bit
What I really like is actually
Reconnecting that
To hardware
Putting the toys
The things
Some boots
That you can Suites the McCulloch and they'll change color this LEDs in the bottom of them
I bought them and they just lit up but now
Because of hat
You can treat them and they change color rather than just going to the pre-programmed color that was already on there
I love that you as an adult
Spotlight
So
It sounds like a Raspberry Pi
Possum
Since you got no red on there
You can learn a lot from that until your book comes out
Check it out
And then
The actuator
Parts in
Yeah do you just buy these from like Adafruit or
Where would I run around
This is
At the moment still the next the tricky stage
Because you're at the moment you still have to
By the by
What scooter hat
Which you put on top of your Raspberry Pi
And that enables you to connect mooses or
Next census to the pie
But sometimes you still have
How to do some soldiering
Which is another
Coupe to jump so if you don't have a soul drain line if you've never
Done and Isolde ring
My soul drink five years ago was horrendous I found some reason it is Big blowup sold everywhere I used to burn my fingers
I'll take it awhile but
Uncle Philip better but those first steps already a little bit daunting
Product School
Back inductive
Which is paint
So you can paint your own solder
And use that for the smaller items you can make cards and
Cause that light up with LEDs because you just painted the soda on there are lots of things to get you started in
And then these hot some of them have
Screw terminals so you cannot just screw the wise in
Adafruit
RS Components
A lot of these companies have
Bits that you can take
As a maker
And
Adafruit on Broad Street
Pi
And RS Components and many other
Websites out there
Showing you how to do these things there was a wonderful community
We make a community of
This is how I did this
You can follow my step by step instructions
This phone I've done a PNC but I can't get to DNS what did I do wrong
You'll get many suggestions
If you could have done wrong and how to how to get there
Okay now you are also a mechanic
Sophia
How much of that
You rely on
But I have a
At the Graham
Mechanical engineering
And also PhD in fluid dynamics of the page that I must say I'm not relying on it to have late when I'm doing any of this
Baking stuff
And actually not much
The degree
Inasmuch as the mathematical calculations to find out how to do
I'm not using
But my experience all
I know which materials are probably best for various things
The electronics of Greeley
From scratch
And onion Last 5 Years and not Spain
On the way
Undercoating I've learned from scratch in last 5 years
From the web and from people helping me
Okay so that it actually feels really
Doable
You're probably a smart woman
We got lots of smart
Anything you need
Is the logic
Remind
To know that
You go to do this before you can do that
Before you can do the other
Order of operations
Recipe how do you cook
Cooking recipe you can follow a lot of these things on the web
Okay
So
Let's get to the
Project
Fortunate
I'll let you choose
Your projects
I'm helping
Best Buy speakers
So
Take a project and let's walk
People threw in a little bit
Okay I'll work with the bus project that I'm fat
Just finished
I gave a talk
A while ago and
Using raw sweet pies and what up and doing in the interactive dinosaurs that we've been working with a theme park
A lady came up to me at the end and said
What I really want
Is a Visual Alert
That tells me that in 5 minutes time the buses going to be at my bus stop
Which gives me X. Makoto
Go downstairs
I'm get to the bus stop
Just before the bus arrives
Should be up this apps that you can look at
As soon as I look at my phone
I checked my emails
So I just want something visual that flashes at me that says right now is the time to go
Get your bus
About this and she lives in London to transport for London have got on the website
When the bus
Did you
Hub.
A lot of the transport infrastructure now
Space information Outlet so you cannot see it stopped because I've used
You're on your own.
Okay so would it be like an API that I
You got to go in and that she have a look at it so it
You need a little bit more understanding of what's that website will give you it is that which they write Pi that you'll look
Okay
Bus API
Yep I bet I'm going to get a Raspberry Pi
Yep you've got a real sweet I
Buns on your home
Wi-Fi
So you set out to run on your home Wi-Fi
Which
Theoretically is very simple as long as you've got a keyboard and the monitor
And you can just plug lighting and type in your
Wi-Fi code
How about you can bend take out
The Monitor and the guy is
Is working only
Network
You don't need it pumped into anything apart from the mains from then on it
So do you need Wi-Fi
I'm bored
So you don't need even to plug
The wife I don't go in anymore
Used to in the old applies you go to
Depay running and you put some
Code on that which basically says
Between the hours of 7 and 8 in the morning
Go to the
Website and
How to get the information from this API
Who tells me when a bus is coming
And is a different number is it says it's less than
Between
2 in in 5 minutes then
Something red
SI Pat Green
And if it's longer than 30 minutes so there's no bus coming within the 30 minutes flash red because I need to know
That
I've got to go and get another message
Getting into work today I can't go to the boss because there are no buses that there's a problem with that
About sea
The node red roster
The pipe is enough of put this old up online and you can just download it has its up on GitHub
You can download my software and put it on your thigh
And I will s*** I would like to that in the show note
Sofas parts
Your pie is still plugged into your keyboard cuz you're going to have to
Controller
You can either do that
To your keyboard or actually with another laptop
Computer that's on your WiFi
Can you use it for a web browser you can program the pi through your web browser
Got it. You just look into that pie
You built like this 3D enclosure and you
Created like this LED light up bus which is adorable
My house is full of
Like hue light bulb
Which does have an SDK
And I
I think also
So I saw this and I was like oh how can I use my existing infrastructure as opposed to 3D printing something
Cuz cuz I'm lazy
Is there a way to do something like that
Or is it just not
Fluid enough yet
Are we not open enough
I believe you
You can I haven't tried it yet
I might now have to stop thinking about that
It shouldn't be too complicated if you can get
If you can control of the
The light bulbs with your phone then you can
Control it with a Raspberry Pi
Okay
Yeah
The Browns beat pie is too soft
Rabbits about that's the brains
Connected to
A light
Answer me I had a
3D printed little bus that I made
Did I put in some neopixels smelly days and I connected.
Through
Wemos
The one chip
It's
A chip.
Has wifionboard so you can
Tok Twitter
Over the Wi-Fi
And you can program it just like you program an Arduino
Gatlin
Ghost and tools
Makes your LEDs talk to your husband pi
Did the Busby
He probably doesn't have to be in the same place
Azul light
Oh nice to
You could actually
Build json incel it
You can as long as I can get it on that Wi-Fi thoughts
Turn on the Wi-Fi
And it be
Tied to that
Yeah good gift for your neighbors guys
If your neighbor is not going to look at you funny
You sang I'm always late
Nevermind scratch that don't make it again
Okay
I like this that gets to the reason why I'm going to
Segway here
It's the reason why we need
Kind of that long tail Solutions because no one's going to manufacture this because
Pasta is so intensely local you can never
Produce enough until enough to make something like this worthwhile
Yeah so
Yay
Reason number one
Actually
Let's talk about project number 2
The bus was connect
Change a website to some lights
Basically
What are Michael Jackson's I found Grace Van Der waals was hacking the toy dinosaur that I mentioned earlier
Photo of a
Small electronics
Kit is designed
For 8 year olds
And it's a Dinosaur say when you
Pick the switch the dinosaur
Notes head up and down
But it's
It's an assembled
Sing to you slept like a 3D jigsaw puzzle
You connect to the
The switch in the battery and that's your electronics training
The children
Took you take the switch out of that
And put in a little bit of electronics
Which
You can do with that very cheap electronics but I see the ordering with you you plug everything your resist
Justice and transistors
If you've never done that
The full that cynical complex all that I have written
Upload post for the magpi magazine
Easy downloadable
Play magazine is the wrong size
Magazine
How to use in that
I can now tweet my
Toy dinosaur
Orthomed
Set it up to rule when
All the other dinosaurs roaring
Tweets those or even set to talk with an empty TT feed
If you want to do that
Celexa
A great fun little project
That sounds like fun I
I'll need a soldering gun
Note because it's designed for the eight year olds
You can do it with
What's called a breadboard which is
A piece of plastic with lots of holes in that you can stick your legs
Tronix into
You don't need
Trusting to any sold ring
However
It wouldn't be so secure so you wouldn't be officers around
But it's it work for long enough going to be secure enough
Tri-Cities ER ornament on your desk
All right
I loved it
You're building this stuff I can't wait to see what you make Nets
I really appreciate you coming on the show this
Not a problem
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week on the internet
Set of things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to sign up for my new
News letter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com