Hey everyone welcome back to the end
Internet of Things podcast I'm your host Stacey Higginbotham and here is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Had today we have got
Lots of
I was going to say we have lots of security news for you
But actually it's insecurity news
We almost were in unison there
That was not planned either know nothing about our show is plant has
As most people. They probably can tell Kevin
Pretty obvious
So
As a parent both of us probably had the same reaction to the news this week that Packers
8Ball actually not hackers a single hacker
And this is a person who actually isn't selling the date or doing anything with it but just
Just to see that if he could
Got into vtext servers and
Basically got access to the tally is now
6 million data on six million children
It is at 6.3 million children and 4.8 million parent account so obviously
Some of those parents have multiple kids using VTech products
And this this is just a tragedy I mean yes
Brass parents but just in general this is terrible
I mean there are photos of these kids chat logs all kinds of things and it's
It's it's just such a shame in VTEC
VTech is said it admits the database was not as secure as it should have been what was your first clue folks
Sorry
No no this is this is this is bad I wouldn't
I wouldn't call it a tragedy I mean there's there's not a loss of life here
This is a Taxco this is more of a
HS something hack is opposed to a
What we call it a actual breach stats
You know design to show your data
Hurt
Cause actual harm
The VTech makes a variety of toys they make a
Connected tablets for kids they make
What else do they make
Etsy
Some of them have you know I have some smarts to them and displays and obviously some have cameras
It's a wide range of of kids toys
And basically what happened
Is
Behavior performed basically he didn't SQL injection hack
And this is this is kind of a Brute Force attack
Have they they
Insert malicious commands into the websites forms
Tent
Trickett to get
Other data
Database access database access
Once I had database access
What they discovered was that the
Passwords
Were not stored
Well they were stored securely but they weren't hashed correct
The passwords were hashed
They were protected so they weren't
Like that's not
It's not like they were in plain text and so on so are you know
I don't want to backtrack when I said to be check is obviously they realize they have an issue but
At least they were not in any
Plain text passwords
Yeah cuz we ever we've seen actually a lot of hacks recently and
Basically what happens is they get into the database
Boom
Your passwords
All right there
Exteriors
So okay
But what the heck are did discover is that
They could actually tie the information about
The kids so they had the kids names ages that sort of thing in the nick of time it back to the parents
Which then
Had the parents names and their addresses so they had the kids
Tied to their parents which gave them the kids
Names
Your address
Genders birthdates
Photographs
Remove
Yeah it's
It's not great
The chat logs that the audiophiles cuz you can do audio chat on some of these devices they are encrypted by AAS
Is according to vitek's
Public statement on on the topics princess chat logs are not encrypted
Okay so they couldn't hear your children but they could see what they were typing
That's correct no credit card information
Social Security numbers or any or driver's license numbers of parent that's not part of the profiles
So I mean it's just
Some identity information and a lot of it obviously is
Mimosa is is children
And so
Again
I'll say it as a parent your fear here isn't
Is it a visceral fear of your kids
Picture
Interstate is like
It is kind of like a like a
One-Stop shopping
Pedophiles is basically
Skip that that's that's worst case I totally agree
So
It reality
This is probably more inflammatory because you know again that that root beer is pretty bad is
The parent you're like oh my gosh you know you're never supposed to put your
Kids picture online we do it all the time you know if if I'm looking at someone's Facebook page I could probably figure out where they live they got
Their kids picture up there
You know is it that hard
If I really wanted to get that in
Information prop
It would be worse obviously if it was a true hack to get and either
Salwar
Give out
Information but that hacker did not do that this was a
A test of his abilities and their seeking VTech security
So from that perspective it it's it's a little
Better than it could have been
I'm surprised the hacker didn't
I should say this way I'm surprised VTech didn't find out from the hacker
That's what I would have preferred to see happen in this situation
However when asked what have you checked on that about the Bridget said they
That they received an email
From a Canadian journalist asking about the incident on November 23rd
So they found out not from the hacker
Yeah
So
It's been all around I mean it's
There's nothing good here and
There is going to be something good, and that is there going to be f***** there are protocols on how they handle
The state
So going forward you would hope that
The odds of this happening again are far less
So if there's a silver lining that's what it is
Maybe
Yes I mean that is the Silver Lining it also I think
Guitar necks point which is
Yikes
A lot of stuff that we have right now
Redis connected
Why the information companies are asking for
We really should
Be asking to them
Do they need this and how are they storing
And I think the fact that this is
Information about children
Which right now under our laws are
Kind of a protected class in a way because of the
Additional
I always forget the name of this law
BMI
Digital Millennium Information Act maybe Digital Millennium Copyright Act
Okay
It's an act
It's always Lucy
However
Basically
Say that
You can't collect information about
Kids under the age of 13
I'm getting you can advertise to them rather is kind of
The actual link are the
Issues at stake here
VTech obviously wasn't
Advertising to these children
It you can actually collect information about them
But
The fact that it puts this data at risk like that
And puts his children at risk
Kind of all kinds of things
Nobody in Congress is
Is going to be thrilled about this which means the FTC is probably going to be like
Oh hellos VTech
What is talk about your data storage racks
Perhaps well
Step Up
Yeah and if I'm not mistaken VTech is based in Hong Kong
Yeah but if you want to sell your product
In the United States
Yeah
Totally agree
So hand you know as you can see in the list of where these
Accounts were
The US has a rather large Market
PTAC
Based on the fact that 2.2 million of the parent accounts are here in two point
Yeah almost 50% of the parent accounts
We're from the US
Sidebar
Third to a half of the child profiles were from the USA value
So
Yeah
Also so that that's our hope is maybe maybe now Will get less of a hands-off laissez-faire approach to
How
Not only just
Giving us lip service to privacy around their data in
Companies needing to
Be kind of car does it have this but actually
Okay maybe we need to start setting some baseline standards about
How did he needs to be stored and it may be that VTEC would be following those minimum standards but
Hey let's get them in place
You know I I wonder though if it's
If companies have put standards in place but having evolved them with the times
I think right now
We should
Set some standards
And I'd like to see outcome be standards as opposed to just like
Thou shalt store your databases are passwords and hashed insulted her with his hashed insult
How to databases
Ouch ouch
You know
Maintain and then I guess this is this is kind of one of those things
Top Shop perform audits on your database
Udo
Password
Where you store your passwords
You know every 6 months and you don't
Make sure that
A hacker with this level of skill Kant
You know spending X number of hours on it can't get past it
Maybe that's a way to think about it
So
Much more outcome is opposed to prescriptive
Because that feels like
It may be a wiser way to deal with security especially since things just Arkansas
Circling to continually evolve
Yeah that the trick is that
Security was always important it's just now it's important for far more
Devices
And industries then it was say you can just five or 10 years ago
Every every industry is now impacted by
Data or big data and therefore leads to
Have security measures in place
Yeah and maybe
Maybe there's a
The way that we should be thinking about you know
Baby
Not every company needs to handle their own security
Maybe there should be
Escrow I mean
In a way that's kind of one of the services that a lot of the big cloud providers offer is they store your data for you
And some of them are
Better at it than others
I don't know I mean that kind of creates a booming industry for like an IBM Iran AWS
And then you get into who's watching the Watchers
It's it's there's no easy answer
There isn't
But being able to shrug your shoulders and say that's a hard problem I'm not going to deal with that I was going to offer kids a connected to
Glitter I'm just going to offer
A you know connected cooking stove that's going to pull up a bunch of data that
We may want some day doesn't seem to be the right thing to do
Here
Hagrid
Angry
We can't just walk away because
It's hard
So speaking of security
Or
Practices that maybe we should think about might not be the best
We saw the sea who was it who published this survey
That is
OLCC consult
Yes SEC consult
This this was worth mentioning it was a
Is a survey that was published on Wednesday right before Thanksgiving
Not the greatest I mean I got to say but
You know I picked it up and I'm glad they did
Because
These guys
Analyzed firmware from more than
4000 embedded devices
From 70 vendors
And it looked at them and they said
Holy cow these devices
Use a remarkably similar number of
SSH host keys because they're all using the same
Software
Development kits from these vendors
Time in Saudi
This is akin to basically what would it be like Kevin
Do you like yeah you know out of a hundred of us 50 of us are using the same password and
We all know what that password is
Exactly
How did you know that I use that
Oh Manuel
Just tell her 50 closest friend
What are the odds
So basically we're all using password which would be great if everyone's as trustworthy is Kevin and I that you know
Sometimes we have friends who aren't as trustworthy and they might use password and since they know we use password
They're just going to pop on in and be like
Hey I bet Kevin and Stacey are also using password and I really want access to their device let me see if they're using it to
You never talked about this a little bit before the show even started and we're trying to figure out why this situation actually exists and I think you hit a
On the key point
Cuz I thought was it a technical issue how difficult is it to generate a different key or whatever
And you said no it's probably pretty easy and it's
Got kind of a matter of laziness
It is not laziness out of maliciousness no no no it's just laziness because up until now you've
Never really had to think about this before because
You know who's really mucking around with SDK on some random sensor
Connected dog collar right and that's
You know these things have been used in like these weird and better
Projects for a while but now that they're getting an stuck in like consumer devices
Is there becoming kind of interesting
Targets
We may not even be that attractive
Honestly but when you're like it Blackadder doing something you know they're they're certainly like
Celebratory targets
I just acted toilet
So
I think what happened is suddenly people in like
Oh shoot now I got to close the back door
Yep
So that's what this is and we'll put the link to the survey for people who want to you know I don't know security people like to see
The stuff they like to argue with it
Whether there's a lot of good day to here and in particular I was looking at the vendors and products that were affected
They said they were more than 900 products from 50 vendors to be vulnerable
Based on just their limited survey and there are big names in this list
Oh yeah I'm going to go pick 3
What do you want
Take 5 I don't I don't care there's MN
People will know these names this is not you know
Small companies
Okay so these are I mean these are the CD link
Netgear
Western Digital
Cisco
Ride time
GE
Phillips
Motorola
Pirelli they make tires
Maybe the tire sensors the air pressure sensors or something I don't know
Sierra Wireless Seagate
Yeah Ubiquiti Network
Oh yeah it's nothing against these companies that's not why I brought this up I'm just wanted people to understand the
Breadth and scope of
Of what in a way this problem actually is it's it's pretty widespread
I mean these are yet these are not
Do not these are not kickstarter's
These are yeah and these are in this is not by any
This is not by any stretch of the imagination like a
Idea here is there using things like broadcom's sdks and there
You know they're basically just
Using the keys that came with it and there's no stopping that code and they're like
Now it's Anarchy no
Because
Because they've always done it and I've haven't had to think about it
They could get away with it before but
Given the way that iot the outer market and
Mainstream consumers getting into smart devices you can't get away with that anymore
Yasso
So this is this is pretty cool
Cool in the sense that like
Yikes
And cool that this research is out there and has been done so
I'm going to encourage you guys if you're interested in it take a look at it
A scary but also
We're looking at got to be informed and this is this is the first step to actually doing something about it so
Let's make it happen
So that was the scary part of our podcast
Let's move on to something exciting times happy times
Let's talk about should we talk about
The latest Pi zero or should we talk about making
Christmas
Iot enabled
Let's go with the pi zero because
You know this is a time where everything is low-cost cuz it's on sale for the holidays
But this is low-cost all the time five bucks it's brand new
On Thanksgiving here in the US Senate
Not on Thanksgiving in the UK
The Raspberry Pi Foundation launched the pi zero which is a
Chip chip chip
Bored
Containing a 1 gigahertz arm
11 processor
It's got an SD card and
I'm not going to go too much into this because our guest today is Eben Upton
Who is the creator of the Raspberry Pi and we're going to talk a lot about it
I'm it's a shame Kevin wasn't here for this because he in
Get Evan could have had a great time
So
Stay tuned podcast because Evan is going to talk to us about like what you can use it for how it differs from like the other pies
Why cheap
Besides being cheap yes we talked about it and we can talk about that earlier if we actually get kind of crazy detailed so
Yeah we talked about pin counts manso
Those who don't care about pin count
Just bare with us
Yeah you know it's what's crazy about this $5
Card sized computer
They're saying it's half the size of the model A+ What would
Twice the utility
They didn't just
Take all the components in
You know downsizing Alex still has 1080p 60 frames per second
HDMI out for example
I literally am thinking about getting one to turn into a home media server
Current for streaming online content
So you can't get one now.
Because I know it's sold out there only making $10,000 a week
So you may have to wait a little bit don't call anybody just just wait
But in the meantime you can maybe order the the chip
Which is a $9 computer that also went on sale on Cyber Monday
Which was November 28th November 30th
I mean that's for the next thing Co
And that
Also I believe has
A 1 gigahertz processor
I don't know it's
Scrap Escape
Abilities
But
Also cheap
Skip pretty cool. Great for tanker and little computer projects learning teaching kids program
Learning how to use Linux I mean
There's so many things you can do with a Raspberry Pi
There are
And will will
We'll come back to that
Later on in the show
But
Moving right along
Yes
Because we have to
Let's talk about Christmas
Because you guys might be getting your holiday decorations out
And I have some
Some ideas and thoughts for you
So
If you were listening to the show last year around this time
Have you may have heard that I bought a pair of connected lights
These were the itwinkle lights from GE
And I have to tell you
But I brought him out again they still work after
A year in
And I brought him out actually for two holidays cuz you can turn the lights a bunch of different colors
I'm still in the market for a slightly better connected light
These are bluetooth-connected so
In actually the updates to that make them better
So they can connect both to the IOS and Android phone
And they play music
Free connected pair of
Lights the cost about 50 bucks I think they're on sale at Home Depot so it was it's 25 lights
Teaching yoga to strands of 25 lights their huge ginormous Globes you can also buy
Smaller versions of these for your tree
I would like for them to be a little bit more customizable
But basically I can't get the lights to do much of anything except be all one color
Unless I'm also playing music which my neighbors
Would kill me if
Yeah
That's the downside of
Desperate
Particular brand of light
If the Philips light strips work outdoors I wouldn't get those at heart
If they look nice we've all actually has a
Set of outdoor light strip
Outdoor lights
Think might be colored
I'm going to try to get some of those and see what
How they work
I'm a little funeral Erie of the WeMo software experience but it is Christmas
I wish that I was thinking the
WeMo
Switch my work outside is probably not the weather resistant unfortunately
Old standby policy Jasco Z-Wave
Sorry it's the GE Jasco
Z-Wave outdoor switch it is connected to my SmartThings Hub you could also
Dear wingcup
It is pricey I think it's about 40 bucks right now
Hot Home Depot you're going to pay more for something that's weather resistant no that's fine I have four of them
Those guys
I know I buy I buy more every year cuz my my light show at
And every year
But this year
New new tweak on that old design
Because I got it blows on SmartThings
Or you could do it on me
You can group them under a setting on your Amazon Echo
Now if I say to she who shall not be named
Christmas
Turn Christmas on
Boom
Are you outside lights are on
All might well actually I
Put it up into
Show all Christmas comes on
What's a scene
It's ass eating baby
Wow it's pretty freaking awesome
Nice
It is nice and if I could actually get my Sonos has to reliably work
Actually make it so late
Music
Which kind of amazing
You have to give tours of your helmet that point Christmas tours
Yeah but just the whole voice command thing the kids would love it
Music on the lights go on
Oh yeah
Dance
I did see in the Wall Street Journal Gregory Fowler they're kind of personal device columnist
Yep has a
He actually used some little bits to make ornaments for his tree
Smart
So I'm actually going to
Can I see how that works out for us because I hadn't thought of that and I thought that was a really light up ornaments
Pretty slick idea yeah
Yes yes very nice
So that's what I'm going to try out I'm going to try out some
See if I can't score some
Different outdoor lights
If you're if you're in the market for him
See if you can't find the I twinkle lights on sale they're pretty good
Of all the ones that are out there
They were the best we tried another brand I can't remember right now and
Last year
I'm surprised actually that the lighting technology has knotted
Willits
It's not cheap for one thing and I think with the lighting companies are doing is focusing on
Lowest paying for most bang for buck and that's indoors
You know traditional lighting
Christmas
People spend a lot of money on Christmas
People spend $60 on their pets but they're not putting lights on them so I don't know about that I think
They're spending the money where they
See the biggest thing
You could do
Youku
Holiday poop
All right I think you bought something cool you want to talk about it
I do want to talk about it but I can't talk about it because
Much because I don't have it yet
Don't know I don't know I want to share the news at least
The news is
That
And this is
Not all this is brand new news
Back when Amazon came out with this new Fire TV which I think was September
It said that it didn't work with
The Amazon Echo
And it did but now
And I can't give you the exact date because Amazon doesn't updated support pages with dates
But this week I saw that the Fire TV now works with the echo specifically to control Smart devices
So you know what
$25 off with this
Cyber Monday deal I ordered a Fire TV actually needed a streaming stick anyway
I order Fire TV with the voice remote
And the voice remote
Will be
I'll be able to control things around my house
Through the Fire TV remote to the echo
A very roundabout way
But that's a good thing because we only have the one Echo and it's
Second floor of our house my home office
Where is mostly watch TV downstairs
So
For watching TV on the
Fire TV we can still turn off lights
You can still get information from Alexa and actually I don't know if you knew this station
The information pops up on the screen almost on like like giant cards
So if you want to Wikipedia entry
Our traffic or weather
It'll actually visit visually show that on firetv I did not know that
Oh man I wish I had known that cuz I would have gotten the Fire TV cuz it was on sale for Black Friday
That's what it was
Cyber Monday 2 and might still be on sale I don't know how much did you buy it for
$75 of the voice remote
Okay
Well
He was it's okay it's interesting thing the voice remote looks like the same voice remote you use for an Echo
They just pictures Bluetooth. I suspected the Fire TV and it looks like the identical products and maybe didn't even need to buy The Voice remote
How much is it without the voice real
We can just get a Fire TV stick
First low well over the holidays it was $25
That does the same thing
The same thing as my Chrome
Basically yeah yeah if you have a
A voice remote for your Echo you could probably Bluetooth connected to the
TV stick and use that in lieu of
Chemically speaking to the echo
I do have
Voice remote for the echo
We could see if they work together
It's 3999 for TV stick now
Papa
Killer all the sea in the cards up cuz
One of the things we actually do
With the echo is my daughter
Isn't a Spanish Immersion program in so
We ask the echo what something is in Spanish and she sends the translation
To the cards
But it would be kind of neat
To send it to the TV instead of to my phone cuz then what happens is my daughter takes my phone
Well the full price Fire TV is 99
With a voice remote the Fire TV stick
Does not come with a voice remote
It's $40
But you could probably use your existing is my guess
Well
It's something to think about maybe maybe I'll just wait for the Fire TV stick to go on sale again
Hey go
All right
Will awesome
Let us not take much more time on our section of the show because
I want us to get to heaven so he can talk to us more about
The pi zero
And he's also going to give us some advice which
I want to spoil it for you guys but
I'd inspire me
Actually fulfill my New Year's resolution from
This last year
And it was
But if I told you it would say would tell you was the advice so you're at your
So stay tuned
We are fat
Did the holiday break with an awesome guest
This is
Evan Upton
Who is
Oh gosh
I don't know the head of the Raspberry Pi Foundation
Make a little generic here because
What is your actual title
And so I'm one of the founders of the foundation and I'm currently the chief executive of Ralphie Pike Trading
Which is the for the foundations of Charity and it has a
Have a surgery
Restart the engineering and marketing
Got it
Okay
So you know
It's a longer arm so maybe then then you will look
New
The most accurate
I'm always looking for the most accurate and
That's what we want
Alright so you guys had big news on on Thanksgiving day here
In America and
November
26 / the UK you guys released the
Pi zero
Tell us about the
$5 Pi zero
Let's let me think
0 is
Cheapest
Raspberry Pi tonight so when we been around for about
3 + 1/2
We kind of kicked off with this $25 the idea building
$25
Answer most of our existence we had a
2520 $25 entry level product
$35 Deluxe products
Product ads
Reasonable person
I'm sorry I should
For people who don't know what the pie is it's a linux-based computer
Kevin actually has one and he uses it to run a
Actually runs a server off of his router that I think he uses a printer or some sort of thing in his house
But you can use this to do
Any number of things you can
I actually had one for a while and I didn't use it for much
Cuz I'm more of a nerd
Shame on me no I have a
You can now if it is telling us what the pi zero is I just want to people
Delicious
Can we build a little credit card-sized computer that cost about 25 bucks
About the same amount you
Tie for a school textbook
Can we make a
Can we make a little PC for kids a little program located kids
They cost
I'm so weeping we three and a half years now we've been selling
Several iterations of
This product
Priceless
It's going really well we sold
787 million
Open now
Please do all cells only one week we go to the $25
And prosper
But that we still keep meeting people
So who who say things like
Yeah you know I'm interested in getting in
Getting involved in in Computing and programming
I'm Point taking the plunge
It's
It becomes apparent to us
Reno
$25 35
It's a significant amount of money is enough money
You might choose not to spend
Michuzi
So over the Lost year what week
Trying to figure out how we can make something for people who care about this sort of thing this is a 1 gigahertz
Processor with
512 megabytes of RAM
Right now
You got to warm get pressure ulcer
Why buy anything but the stamps in the last 5 or 10 years
This was 2000
Pomsky
Norcross replies always be
About delivering a doll
Performance
Delivering
What's the performance of wood if you would have seen in a PC
Take you out level performance they would have cost you hundreds of dollars
I've been delivering that app swell
Well if I'm a kid can I can I use this to play Minecraft on
Yes
Disappointment a special version of Minecraft
That the pi zero
Yes
OKC that's
Casino as it as a child
I feel like that is like
The number one thing that
Scratch
Minecraft
I don't know if they're like a trifecta of programs that you think about when you're doing this
Poison gases
Estelle Parsons
So I kind of utility stuff a web browser
You know it's important if it's not a computer if it doesn't have web browser I think he's probably fat
We run we run a good web
YouTube
Vaulted my browser
Okay
Alright so
Let's talk about what you cut out to get
Because it is a $5 computer
That is modern
In possum by the standards of
Mm
What
What doesn't have the big thing I guess it doesn't have his it doesn't
House memory
It has an SD card slot that you can use to connect do you use the storage site still operating system
Fish with a high-definition television
I didn't have a has a USB a single USB
So all of these any peripherals you want to plug into it
Do you unplug
Be home
People just plug in
Plugin keyboard
Into the USB connection in the happy
Other negative plug in a keyboard and a mouse on the maybe a wireless network adapter
Angel thing
Of the people login
What's a PC
Give me one of these
A low-cost desktop
Applications
We'll wait because this doesn't have I don't see room for battery
How am I going to get power to this thing
Okay so that you can either pirated house
How can I
Sublime
Tsp
Cedar Point
Go plug it into the wall
Intuit
If you want a parrot
Fabrics
I'm popular gif
All right so I brought you in this is
This is a tiny tiny little thing
Bunty
I'm terrible it
I'm terrible at
Thinking
We don't like me a few original music credit card
Comic books
All right
So
So I've got this
Spend
You know
You're on the iot show
And I'm having you here even though this is not fundamentally
INE time I see cool cheap Computing devices and you know the pie Community is
Amazing
I mean people people build supercomputers with the sayings they're just a bunch
I love them through the nuttiest people in the face of the planet and they talked about what they're doing and they're really helpful
So
What do you think
For the people out there who are listening in her like I want to build with this is
Cheap and finding I can blow stuff up
Because I feel like that's kind of our listeners mindset sometime
Benign
Like I say
If you want to do iot tub stopper
What are you going to need to plug some soul
Radio
Body so I would probably plug a
Attwifi
So I would be inclined to plug that into my single USB
An Eddy Max
USB Wi-Fi dongle
Take it out of its case
I've wrapped it up in concert
I've been sold an adult in the back
The pants only
Disemboweled
IUSB
Wi-Fi adapter
Update on the Eric
Slightly
Not waived in Wi-Fi
I just got
You're not going to come up with
So why of getting Wi-Fi conceivably Bluetooth
I'm on to that and that's going to be there
Yeah cuz I feel like I've got like a $15 Bluetooth
Kind of radio that's just a straight-up
E90 little Bluetooth radio size of like maybe
I mean it's like a little like a nickel
So if I stuck this with the
Computer
That I could actually make some of my presents that I can give my presence detectors a little bit more intelligence that I've been kind of blue
Looking for
Outside of the
Proprietary
So that
This wonderful thing about usb
You know USPS is going to lowest common denominator
Stand up for collecting stuff together
If you go on
If you go on eBay
Amazon
You'll find
Really really really really cheap wireless USB dongle for every conceivable Wallace
That's why we picked
The wife
Because it just means you just got buy things for a dollar
And it'll give you some kind of right here
Which is providing the brights
I think we can run Linux
I'm a man
So the people that want to use it for a little hunger it peyote project
Mango salsa
Effectively the weekend
Okay and how long it take for a power consumption perspective
What am I looking at
At the power consumption for this board
And can you talk to me in terms of like battery life
As opposed to
So ya like it well
Starting off from the vault
Outside the thing drawers
Something like that
It's something like
Between 150 million
Actually
USB device compatibility
G303 vs Rey
It sits on the
You're without doing any
It's
Under Hawthorne
Consumption
Keep this thing
Just running for a very nice on seeing the bowl light
You know 45 hours
Something like that particular lady
You know it really yeah
It'll keep going
I need you prepared to do
Clock speed
I stopped turning things off on the on the CPU on the device you can probably squeeze another older my vagine out of them
All right
So maybe I should look for someone to start squeezing
But doing the work for me cuz I am not
I'm not that kind of engineer
To like start turning things off of this
Pretty good about about the pie Community mentioned
Is that generally Google is your friend not right so
If you want if you want to
Squeeze the packets of Julep I download
I would guess the doodling
I want to reduce the packets option of my Raspberry Pi Bolton turn off $100 goals
A people who done these things already
People being that before you know Blaziken trial
United States
The stuff's going to work
How do you confirm we're here
Okay
This is awesome
So let's talk a little bit about
How did you
I read somewhere that
I believe was it
Did Eric Schmidt tell you to actually
Yeah yeah this is business advice from Eric
This is one of these this is one of these really weird,
But you know you see them
You seem to be very effective
And
Can be hard to tell when someone is effective because they
Fact beaker's lab
Over there if I could because I would like it
But I have it I decide to Charleston beach
America
About 3 years ago
Estados mm
Yeah II
Google Chrome
To distribute
I'm dumb
He was there at the announcement
Volume
I'll stay
Bealls me what are you doing
A bit more expensive
And he told me I was an idiot
That was absolutely the wrong thing to do and that I should try be cheap
But
That I should try to strive to find ways to make
The product
Closer to free
And so I went back to the end because
Because
Cheapness
Leads the volume
Volume leads to
Ubiquiti
Lately
So I went back to the office and I cancelled
Making more expensive
If we did all this
Eventually
If we take it late
Good morning Spencer
What we did was this
Tie-dye longer harder route
CrossPointe
Yellow
I was just thinking about how do we take
Speech about you know how do we make something cheaper
Halloween
You're welcome or you're welcome you remove from the pile
What compromises
Did to be cheaper the first fruits of that was his toward this reduction of all entry level price point from 25 to 20
You lost yet
Ultimate consequence of this
Nice all right
I've answered an interesting question which is there is Eric Schmidt small lucky
There is a 12 we'll see I mean so far you sold out
When can we expect
To be able to buy more
I'm so we made
Mm so the first post
Lawrence Municipal Dynamite couple thousand today
I would expect
These will make their way into channel in the neck
She dies
We actually need to
Front of a magazine
So we have our own magazine called the magpie
I'm we put on the front cover
We have some
You get up
You got free
La Frontera
And the rest will get put into reverse distribution channels in the UK in the US
Ten Thousand Fists
Which is actually quite slow for us
I mean in terms of the big product
Weebill
What would it be it would be
60 of 70000
Aquatis bowls calibration first of the month
Hard to wrap it up
Got it
All right and then in the spirit of a
In the spirit of Schmidt
What would your advice be to people who are listening and
Thinking about
Building their own product or even learning learning to code I mean there's lots of people
Who look up to you
Ucumberlands
You come across people who have
Like an idea you get these people who
I just need to find
I'm am
That's iron
You going to have a technical
Albertsons
This is probably going to want
Do you have
Technical capability comes
So down song Sometimes in terms of I set up
In terms of how I think about
Problems
I know what you think about
Launch
Product
Before it's
Oakley polished
I'm going to reply when it was
Good enough
I hope we love la
Is that
The perfect
Particular
These products
Developing emerging
Coyote
Yoga
I want want
Venues.
I'm so so you got the lunch thing it's kind of a well-known Dixon
Buttocks it is very relevant
In the it World by Kahala spice
Weeping
Rolling those things we've learned
All right
So
Learn to code
Laterally
Lunch Austin
Those are
You know
Necessarily new
New Society
I'm at cliches because
Because
People ignore them
Things are well known to be
Disabled people inside
Exactly I was going to say
I've been meaning to learn to code for you know
3 years now and
Still haven't so maybe this is this is the
It's like it's like those speed is broken
Turn off Bluetooth
Alright well thank you so much for coming on the show this week
And I'm excited to
Test out the pi zero
I get a chance to order wine
Hey thanks for listening and we'll see you next week