Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
I am traveling this week so if there's any weird issues they're probably on my end
Especially any just general
Weirdness
So
Let's get this party started
This week we are going to
To cover some great stuff such as the Philips Hue bulbs
Were they hacked
Buy drones
Google home some quick impressions
Nest is appliances we got thread
Going Enterprise
We have some cool products to review and talk about
And we also are going to just scare the pants right off
With the question of is the US ready to attack
Russia
Using the bus cyber
So the Cyber the Cyber I couldn't say Cyber attack
Directory
And we will have a ad from
The Bluetooth Sig a new sponsor this month
And our guest this week
Is rum melissani the CEO of securifi
Which makes the Almond router
And that is going to be a fun interview
Talking about
The future of the Smart Home & Security and yes router said that's that's more than a router
But I'm sure you guys going to talk about that we will talk about that and I actually have
An almond router that I have not set up yet because I haven't been
In home
But
In a coming show
So awesome let's quickly go to a word from our
Sponsor
This is
Samsung
Buick manufacturer service provider looking for the fastest path to enterprise-grade secure interoperable
An intelligent iot based products and services Samsung artik Smart iot platform
Bad patch learn more about how to leverage Arctic Cat Arctic. IO
AR Tik. IO
Alright it before we go to the show I'm going to do my own little plug for me which is I have a newsletter
Are called Stacy knows things
If you don't get it and you want to know more about the Internet of Things
You should totally sign up at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Kevin said that but I don't know if he
Actually reads it
Eye to eye to
I love you
Alright so let's get started
Philips Hue
Big news
Was it this week
Maybe it was last week I think right after we recorded the
Pirate show
Yes we recorded early last week we're recording a little early this week
Will get you there
All right so what happened is actually Kevin you want to tell him what happen
Because it's pretty
It's almost scary but I should preface the story by saying it
It was more of a
Demonstration that anything else so don't panic as I tell you that
A drone was used to hack Philips
Hue bulbs and the did Supreme about 450 meters or a thousand feet away which is
It really is scary out on the surface of it
What happened was a vulnerability I believe in the zigbee
Protocol or stack
Was found by some researchers they did the right thing they contact a Philips Hue
Over the summer
And I believe last month Philips Hue actually put a firmware patch out to address the
Tissue
However having said all that the demonstration still happened
And folks were able to
Take control a Philips Hue bulbs they they injected some new firmware
Into I guess the hue
Bridge
And whatever like send SOS message
From a drone through the Philips Hue bulbs
This coming on the heels of
The Mirai botnet
Which is still ongoing
We shouldn't say like
Like that's done
Cuz it's not
And actually that's a bigger worry because they have all of these devices out there
Recalling and that's going to be a hassle and a half
But not all of them
Not all of them
Who knows
Yep unplugged
Unplugem
Buy new stuff
Sorry
I mean that's a terrible thing to say but it is
Baby iot devices need a kill command a kill switch
Hilton
Just thinking out loud
I like it
There has actually been some researchers talked about doing something
The do-gooder
Which
They're testing a research environment but what it does is it automatically goes in and changes the password
Now the downside is
That's like an automated bot so
What would happen if your password on your infected device that you may or may not know is actually infected with suddenly change it
You couldn't get to it anymore
So that
Probably
Bad idea
Killswitch
Yeah
There's iot security people
I get away glad this is happy
Because people are
Are now paying a
Attention to it
So
What is disconcerting is there so few Avenue still for fixing it
I would focus on
A building secure products but be thinking about how you
How you can fix it
Over the air updates are like the best option
Mitigating red distributed
A solution is very very challenging
It is
But
Like that was really helpful
Security researchers pay attention
So
We don't have a solution for keeping an eye on
People who are smarter than we are
Cruising Solutions so
Hopefully
Hopefully we'll bring you some interesting stuff
In the meantime
I have been playing with
Google home
My
Google home is the Amazon Echo light
Speaker device that you
You talk to personal assistant speaker
And I can say
Fit at UK Monday
And this is Tuesday
And I left town so
I did not bring it with me
Said it was super easy
It took you know maybe
5 minutes and that includes it's time to
Then I tested it it sounds good
I don't know if it sounds better than the echo in all honesty some
People were saying that jury's out on that I'm seeing mixed comments on that
Bass pretty well
I think a lot of things
Trouble
The higher pitches and Dad
Lost
Maybe it depends on what
Kind of music you listen to
Google home
I did encounter
An issue
And it feels like it might be like a Stacy
Only issue but I'm going to tell you about it because there is
The customer help portion of this which I was kind of
Not as impressed by
So
I was able to connect my Nest thermostat and that integration worked was very easy
I then went to connect my Philips Hue Lights because if my husband can't turn on the lights with his voice he feels like my tire job is worth
Dark in here against a serious they say I have to turn it on for the switch
Oh that was a terrible impression of my husband
Nobody tell him
So
It didn't connect
And so then I went to the troubleshooting page it showed me automatically the troubleshooting page but it was pretty basic it was like Harold
Are they on the same I find it
And is your Google home
I was like
Just all of these things
And then was a try again and it didn't work
So
I done went to the
Bigger troubleshooting page which basically had me do all those things again and then it was like okay reboot both devices
And then
I did that and it still didn't work
And I never like
Okay enjoy the troubleshooting got it so there's a there's a phone number there's online chat
Do you can call I did notice that Google does not make the phone number like
Easy to click you can just press the phone number to call you after like cutting
Pasting to make a call
What's odd
I know I was kind of like dude Google
Clearly don't be calling you
So
I spend about half an hour on the phone she the customer service agent was very polite
Took me through all the same steps that
Weather
Faceit taken
And after that she she had to call in like
Extra troops
And at no point in time did I get that they didn't ask me what I felt were probably some basic questions like
Hey
What kind of Wi-Fi router
Using
They did ask me what kind of phone I was using but that was just a chic
You could tell me where to go
Go to press the button
So
I found online someone said that they actually swapped
From they were using Firefox
And swap to the Chrome as their default browser to do this connection
And he said that made
So I use Adblock
Browser on my
And so
I'm going when I get back in town I'm going to swap over to
Chrome and see if that works
But Google when they decided they couldn't help me
They're like well we've escalated it in within 24 to 48 hours will send
So that's where I am
I didn't think it was the best experience
It was a terrible
But I didn't feel like the Google if you called Google you would get anything other than
What you would get online anyway
Yeah that's what it sounds like it sounds like the same process just now with a purse instead of a computer
Which is good for people who don't like following instructions
Computer but for me it was super frustrating
Well yeah because you know what you're doing and then you've already been to the types of warrants
I'm surprised that they didn't ask for or
Will ask for permission I pull a log from the Google home device
This this I thought was interesting so
Google home it said
Send feedback so I was like
Okay g
Ecology
Send feedback it was like what is the problem
And then I was like I can't connect my Philips Hue Lights
It sent it
But I don't know what happened
So I don't know if that included lawsuit or is that was just like me telling it I just
Yeah that's that's swell
Without knowing what was sent to me that's kind of not a good experience either
It should be.
Free Christian clear so I forgot
But not in that division
Right at school
And I did not order a Google home as of yet because pink is not a partner in my stuff is a twink
You talked about maybe work around a little bit later in the show
Alright so
Wait wait one quick question
I can treat you for what
A lot of people were
Curious what would happen if you were to say the
Keyword for Google home
When your phone is nearby and you have voice detection on the phone why did that
And I'm betting I'm hoping that it worked only on one device not both
It did so both devices were like your listing
And then the message on your phone screen is
What is it say it said
Answering on another device
And then the home
Would answer
Perfect
Alright so
Two Nest they did last week and announcement all about new appliances they work with so they
Have a list
Some of these we actually already knew about and I just don't know if they
Existed before this but Whirlpool it tells your dishwasher to start automatically when you leave the house
Or
Have your washer clip your
Clothes fresh until you get home
Jenn-Air
Which is the oven
If you forget your oven or stove is on and Nest says hey she's not home
You can get a notification that says by the way you left your oven on
Turn that off
Yes please
Yes well maybe not maybe a preheating while you go in
Get something dangerous
What's an oven
Okay this is what I'll tell you guys in my house
Princetown
So ream is another one
And
Hayward
Oh this is a pool
Kleenex
Yeah your non-essential pool appliances
To turn off during energy rush hour or demand response active
So
Nice
And then Samsung has your powerbot vacuum
It can turn on when you're not home
That's actually bad for me because by actually it's not a Samsung powerbot but my robot always gets stuck
Its Spots and we could only vacuum
Kind of counterfeit service
It does
All of these things
Seemed pretty cool Kevin Williamson
I love it I love it
We need more this more more more because
Typically and I know it's early in the whole Smart Home
Market
For a lot of people
A lot of things that are coming to Market a lot of products just replace an existing interface you know let's use voice instead of a light switch
Did the real benefit is when you start tying these things intelligently together
Which is what is happening here
Yeah I don't want to be home when my Robot vacuum is vaca
You know because
I don't need to be there for example
Crate
That's known as I'm not there fire up the robot go clean
Same with the other stove examples
Perfect music great safety feature
So I I want to see
So so much more of this cuz really we don't have Smart Homes yet
We have a lot of
A lot of smart
Devices that
Still don't really
Too much together
Yes we need
Yes
More give me more
More connections for Kevin in actually in a couple of weeks we are going to do a holiday-themed show that's going to talk about
Cool things that we have connected and things that you guys might find useful
So if you guys have done any cool connections with your hubs or things like that that you want to share that are like totally long
Until
Send info at iot podcast
DACA
Thread now onto thread
So last week
Thread group
Which manages the thread Wireless protocol for you guys that
You don't keep your wireless protocols memorize this is like a mesh
Network
Low-power mesh Network that also supports IPv6 which means
Go Direct
So they said
We are not just for the Smart Home
And they introduced some
Enterprise they said they were going to work on Enterprise use cases for lighting
And some other
Stop
So
They
Will start adding
Kind of
Extensions to the thread protocol that let people handle like security and Authentication
At all these kind of
Bigger subnets of thread devices that you
Can manage
So all of that is coming
And
Red is also
Good arm and
Other
Companies are
Producing radios that will basically let you run
Red and Bluetooth
On the same radio
Which is really interesting I said this was going to happen a while back but
It is actually going to happen
And the thinking there is maybe use Bluetooth to connect your thread devices to your phone for examples
Making the connection process easier
But I would be excited to see like a thread light bulb
Butterfinger also uses Bluetooth
And then you can get presence detection over your mesh
Lightning Network
How awesome would that be
And then could you theoretically access that light remotely without a hub
Yeah directions to the web
Yeah actually I guess you could
I'm thinking the cat
Yeah
Oh but you fancy man
Anyway to get rid of a Hayabusa
Teddy day I can get rid of a big breakfast
Will stay tuned for the
Scarify talk
All right so that's a threat news
Here we're going to get into
Actually let's talk about we've got some product stuff first but let's talk about if this then that
Before we get in
Because
It just feels better
So
If this then that one of our favorite
Averitt
Bobby holik
Connectable services
Flexible service
I don't know if that's
They changed
Their recipe
Keys to a
And this is a nomenclature thing they also integrated the
Baidu
I was like I can't
Remember what all these apps were
The integrated those
All back into the app so that's all
Bond
Which is fine you know I had to do I had a couple do apps and I almost never
Cuz I like physical buttons
Call me crazy
Basically
To create
Aplets it's the same process
Pretty easy
What we did notice there we're playing around
With a phenomenon
Is
Did the Google assistant is a channel and that works on your pixel phone or your Google home device
I'm very happy with by this this discovery this morning because I did not buy a home
Because what's a represented by Necco at first because it didn't support what I needed to support my case wink
However in doing some quick
Playing around right before the show
Yeah I will be able to create a
Applets
Using
The Google Assistant Channel and my wink shortcuts
I don't think it's working quite
Right to say that I think it's
Speakers having issues with my wink Hub at the moment so I'll keep playing with that but
I can now
Theoretically
Control things through the Google assistant app on my pixel and order if I buy a Google home
Yes and I will go home and test this out to sow
If you're going to try this out
It also actually means
Theoretically your Google home could also control
WeMo or
There's so many issues
Controllable things out there your skybell
Sure
Like so much
Now if you want to connect it to your wink Hub you already need to have a shortcut ready for what you want to do which is an art
You just go create shortcut
Say what you want to have happen
It happens
You also have to do to if you want your lights on
That's one command
And if you want your lights off
That's another command so you've got to
Create all of that
So just keep on short that's her both of those so
So you could end up with a long list of shortcuts
But
If you really want to make your Google home
Uno programmable
And I imagine because if this and that has a lot of latency you're also going to deal with latency but
It still might be fun so I'm going to try it will let you know next week
I would do it right now but
By golly Avenue
It's it's a good alternative until
Petition Partners come onto the whole Google
Homemade lights
Yes and
Let's just say this rate
Shofar
Amazon Echo is still
Chilling in my house
I love Google Assistant I think asking it questions is nice but like if I were going to still put everything around me
My house at still go with Amazon
Mohr partners
Will for me the goal is to smart
If your goal is to access like
Massive Google
Intelligence then
I can see where the home comes in handy
I'm thinking actually I'll put I get a lot of questions in the shower
A lot of things coming to my brain
Put that in my bathroom
Can just ask random questions
Instant that looks like an air freshener it's like perfectly bathroom yes no one will know
Alrighty
So
Let's go into Fun exciting
Products
Takis this is something that occasionally people ask me about so there was a product while that
Call Troy email
And what it was it is apparent
Does a wifi-connected mailbox fit
Kids can basically
Talk to
Parents could leave messages in the toymail app and then the kids could play it back on the little mailbox
And how cute is that so parents who travel a lot
They can connect to
Communicate with her
While the parents at work
Share with the kid
Sota
I went away but now there is a
Plush
Animal
Call the toymail talkie
Basically it's
You exchanged voicemails with your kids
So
You can use your phone and send it to the toy
So I would send it to my daughter for example or my daughter could push a button on the back of the Taki to say something to me
Or to another kids talk
So
It's $50
I really want to get one of these because I love like
I love the idea of while I'm gone
Communicate
I think it's fine
So
And I'm putting it in a toy to cute implementation
The plushie is actually kind of cool because
It's kind of a
Hello local
What that's not a word
Anyway
Able to be cuddled thank you thank you
That is available
Online and it's available at beta
So
Speaking of beta
This is the store I went to last week in Palo Alto that had all these Gadget
I bought a crazy silly device
And I'm going to tell you about it
Because
Cuz
Country Cat
So I would advise
Call the spire
And if tracks your respiration
Tell you if you are tense, murrin
Focus it also acts as an activity tracker
So this is a $99
Alternative activity tracker it's based on Research from Stanford
So it feels
Scientific
And they also offer you meditations
In the app so the goal is to get you to like learn how to be more
And I thought it would be good for me
Because I am super tents
And lo and behold
The app does register that it's like
You have had 298 tents minutes today
It's nice it is not a need to have because I am so focused on being mindful
I thought it'd be good for me and it has kind of helped with that
I'm still being through the tutorials that are helping
Can you breathe better
So
And I will see if I'm more
Peace
Is it a necessary to buy snow and then part of me feels like God I got so much crap stuck on me in the world
Ifitness tracker I've got this thing I've got a ring that you have
My phone
You know if you're trying to be mine
This is kind of fun
So it looks like this device Clips on
To you it was like a like a like a belt clip
It has to clip onto you and touch your skin so the device actually has to face inward
If your girl that means like in your bra like
Restaurant
Somewhere
Or in your pants like
Attached to your
Facing in on you
It's Raining Tacos
In this clip my God you guys this clip is so strong
I'm I'm constantly wrestling
What is high quality
Materials it looks like a little Stone
Clippers again
Fairy
Aries Spears
Hefty
And that it's got a wireless charger
So you just set it on the charger it vibrates to say like
Sweet
And that's it
So
If you're if you're looking for something like this
It does work
But you'd have to be really looking for something
Like us
It's interesting because it reminds you something that was just rolled out with the Apple Watch 2 and Ice apples new breathe
The app on the watch
Now
I don't use it because I'm not
One more thing. To deal with during the day but
I don't know that monitors your breathing but I know that reminds you to
Take time and breathe and walk you through
Deep breathing every symptom times a day I turn the function off but
I don't think it matters which this would
Yes so if you do buy it
The app has to be on
2 track
Into sync with
Spirestone
Used to consider device
So if you and it only stores like 6 hours
So
Yeah that's that is actually something
Here's a fun Kickstarter
This is The Big C
I love this because I like gestures in
They showed it to me in a kitchen and I was sold
Put on this ID
That's all you have to do
Get this in the kitchen and you can celebrate
Is it tiny sensor
Census year
Hand gestures in the air and commands whatever device you program it to
So
It works with
If this then that
Music and lighting control GoPros
Your phone
You can even put it in your car in like gesture in York
Car that's actually a really interesting use
Or on your bike
You could use it on your bike
Control your GoPro
Where to get
Directions
I'm intrigued by this and it's $80 for one
I think it's $140 for a package of two when the kickstarter is met its goal
The estimated delivery is March of 2017
So
I probably won't buy it on the kickstarter
I might buy one
I appreciate what they're trying to do here
And
Gestures are not easy and you have to have
The device work with a lot of other devices
Value
I wonder how difficult it is to like
Swap the usage
For that cyclists say at your in the kitchen you want hands-free scrolling on your iPad they show that ended MO
So you're needing go and
You don't touch screen CD
Swipe
Yeah over this device grape
But then
What do you do when you want to act like now change it over to
Dimming lights
But you gotta
I guess there's an app and you have to tell it now you're going to do this one
I would think
Cuz it's can do a lot of different things and work with a lot of products
Switch is awesome
I just wonder
I think you're going to need
Yeah so I did
Have to
Define what
Each of them
Now they did say to reduce latency they've got a direct integration with lifx
Q which is a
And the battery on this thing lasts about a month
And so
Cuz you do have to charge it
Yeah so that's what we know on this and
I can't wait till I actually want to see it
So
Looks cool
It does
Okay
Kevin do you want to talk about Russian cyber attacks
What does Cyber more of the cyber yasso
Okay everybody if
Russia interferes with the US election the US government is already too
Pushback using the cyber
That's crazy NBC News who says that
The US military hackers have
Unable to penetrate Russia's electric grid Telecom networks and the kremlin's command systems
I don't know
This is kind of scary actually I don't know if this is hype this is just posturing this is
It's true it's scary no matter which of those scenarios it really is
You know it is it opens up a whole new world of like
A Whole New World
But not a good
Not not the kind of
Thinking Out Loud here do you think it's a question of
When there's an attack on a mass scale attack on the cyber
Versus
If
So like emasculata Connor
Physical infrastructure
Yeah let's say by let's a state-sponsored
Yes
Actually Kevin it's already happened
Back in March 2016
The FBI put it out at the justice department
Claims that Iran had attacked
Us infrastructure online by infiltrating the
Shiraz controls
Of a damn that was 25 miles north of
New York City
So
The point here is
Not if
Not win but
I guess what
What's next
What will be the next Target when and what do we do
Annette that seriously concerning
Yes so in the reason why it actually didn't
Cause
Damage
Is because the physical infrastructure was unable to actually open on
So
In that instance
Free pick up at Target
Latin for sure
So
But yes if you have
I mean this
Again underlies the importance of
Protecting these assets and think about security
All the time in
I would say
Thinking about security
Not as something that could ever really be finished
That is that is a really big issue that
We just be like
There is no secure
Thoroughly products that
Contact yet
In that world view how do you change your mindset
Figure out updates you figure outfit like stopgaps like
If this goes down
What's your next backup
Especially when we're talking about actuators like things that actually make stuff
So
Scary scary
But don't worry
As we now have something super lighthearted
Next
We have our guest
Rob malisani of securifi
We actually do talk about security unless they are the makers of the Almond router
And
Little interesting side note
Rob was my first podcast guest
On the Internet of Things podcast all the way back when it was a giga
Wow that's like 3 years ago
Yeah so he was my very
First
Wow
There we go
So stay tuned for rum
And
Alright everyone it's time for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Is the Bluetooth Sig and I'm speaking with Alessandro who is the CEO of
Bluetooth Sig member company
Schumann
Alessandro thanks for coming
I understand that you've got a wearable
Call the human beta
That's right
Warminster train better
By measuring the way that muscles are using oxygen in Wartime
Based on this information we can tell
Wendy warm up
Afaria from deleted how to recover
All of this in real time for performance Improvement workout
And where did this idea come from the market research project with MIT
Technology in biology
Increase something amazing top people understand more about that body you wake up in the morning today
Gas in the tank at the tires oil in the engine
You don't have access to the same level to me all the information you need to keep your buddy when it gets best and that's what
What will excited
People who are ready to embrace this concept
Use different station
Woody Allen
Because we could help them
Soldat biggest problem
What does knowing how hard to push himself and a****** so when
Clear that Bluetooth would be the way to go as it was
Easiest way to connect a wearable to phone 2
Deliver information
In real time in a convenient way will technology.
I love you exactly how far I can see you guys are in theater right now
What kind of feedback are you
Devices to a speech over the US
And when I say about this program
You know we we get a lot of feedback about the quality of our data how
People information Bay
When they could get a real snapshot into what's happening in the body
Skip back so we can tell them what to do
And we help them understand how their body is reacting everyday
So you've had athlete
Has anyone else seen it
Yeah we had the chance to them alongside
Two others Bluetooth stick companies
At last month at the Discovery Museum
And that was an amazing opportunity to interact with
Yaz most influential
To demonstrate how Bluetooth
Houses built such an amazing solution
And we destroying people externally aphids
And where can our listeners learn more about your product you can read all about it she wanted
Human. IO and it's your company with an Innovative product to ask I would
Encourage you to participate in the next
Discovered blue event at CES in January you can find more details on cruises.com or
.com
Hey everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
Today's guest is super special
Is rum melissani who is the CEO of securifi
Securifi is a company that makes the almond
Router
So hi Rob how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm doing great thanks for having me
Man I am so excited to have you
So guys
Way before this version of podcast I did a version that
And
Two or three years
Ron was my very first guest all the way back in 2013
So
Come full circle
Yay
Yeah we did
Isn't that crazy we've been doing this iot stuff for so long
Littleoralandie
I know so this is a good good place to start you guys started securifi
Back in 2012 before everyone else was like I know it let's build a new kind of router
What was your thinking
With
Starting the company
I've always hated my home router
And I think
You know there was
Gas was
The one time I have to help my landlord set up her Wi-Fi router and
Just a very simple thing I ended up spending like 30 minutes
40 minutes
And I realized why you know I'm supposed to be the expert at the stop
And I struggle with my home router just imagine
Regular consumers
And that was the founding story of
Is a big opportunity to make Robin's easy for consumers
This was in 2000
September 2011
And that's
Just when
Android phone started getting big so
Screens are getting bigger and cheaper so we thought why not put touch screen LCD
On the router itself
So you do not need to do the 192.168 stuff
So that was the founding Story song
It's it's funny for us because
It's like Silicon Valley woke up last year
About Wi-Fi or maybe this year
You know we've been screaming and shouting about the importance of
Easy to setup Wi-Fi on importance of routers that look
So you not show them inside closets
Yes
And you guys also
Was it
Maybe not your first router but your second generation writer also
Doubled as kind of a home hub or you had other radios other than Wi-Fi in
That's correct the first one router
I did not have a smart home hub
But we lost Almond Plaza
The next year
CES 2013
And that one did have zigbee and Z-Wave all integrated into the home and I think that's when
Right before that
Was Ben I was on your podcast
Giving your crazy perspective on this industry
Excited about the Smart Home
Just about as long as I have
Weird almost four years off from it so how do you think it's going
So
I'll talk about this from the Wi-Fi perspective and the smart home perspective I think
They are they are related but they are orthogonal in
Sometimes
Wi-Fi sign in
You know
Everyone's just realizing the importance of Wi-Fi in home
If you go back a decade
You just probably had a laptop that required
A wireless internet connection
And so that was just one device one or two devices
He told the homeowner laptops
At home
But today
You know
Yunnan Wi-Fi everywhere you need Wi-Fi in the living room
Bedroom
Front door because of these doorbell cameras
Kitchen
Your bathroom you know you're mostly Plano take their phones and iPads to the bathroom
Backyard
People like working from the backyard
Play
In
Just around your home
I read you can live without Wi-Fi sauce
Become
Really interesting
And I think the number of seniors
Average American household has about eight
Wi-Fi devices
You know what
Comcast actually at its most recent earnings last week
Said that they've got 11
Wi-Fi devices on average hanging out their Network
So that's might be the
American average and 11 we are at 16
Social Security index
I guess even hayatabad
So that's on the wife I said
Still Wi-Fi has become extremely critical
Piece of infrastructure at home you know it's like
Water and Electric
So on the smartphone side
Yeah things have been
A bit of a mixed bag I would say
What we learned a lot of things
Thanksgiving we were so early in there
And we learned that
The Hub
Is
But most consumers it's
It's a very abstract
You know it's not the way consumers think about purchasing products
Listen to smart home space
That's what we learned
And we've seen
The industry has seen
Sunray
Wine product successes lyrics cameras
Know some of the bulbs from Philips
But
Was difficult cell phone
As a consumer product
So what we're doing with some of our newer products has I guess
Integrating
Some more value into the Hub
It sounds like it's not just a hop that just talks to all these devices
That's one of the II is
This is going to be a long
Slog
In the smart home side
I think
You know there was
Way too much hype
In the industry
I think it's not going to grow as fast as
It was hyped up
But
Here is my analogy
If you compare the smartphone
With the Smart Home
When you purchase a smartphone
Everything out of one device
So you got your
Instagram or Facebook or messaging apps
Games whatever you do you got all the value
Through this one device
I think that's one of the big challenges
It's it's
Even if you have the money maybe you don't have the time
Because
A smartphone
You need at least a bunch of things at home
Connected
And then you start using
But no one wakes up
Besides
Change my washing machine.
50 lights and whatever one day at a time in a percentage
Who do that
But that's not the main
Extreme Behavior
Okay so yes Hardware transitions requiring
Many pieces of Hardware are definitely more difficult than buying hey I've got a phone I have upgraded my life
So do you think so that there is a challenge in
Marketing to Consumers so you talked about a hub being abstract
I actually think the whole concept of connected devices is a bit abstract for most people
That's why we've seen a lot of people purchase one off devices
Weather like oh
This doorbell I can see and understand what it does but when you say to your lights
So
How can you as a company that is trying to
Sell a hug maybe make these sort of
Connections abidi
Yeah I agree a hundred
Percent that the
Hobbits to apps like today and maybe
Maybe Mike
Guesses
Maybe the whole hog
Concept is couple of years
Too early right now
Or maybe doesn't work at all
Serious
Multifunctional
Mainstream consumers I don't know
You're ever going to want to do any
This
It's possible
Very very likely I do think
One product that could change
My perception around this is the Amazon Echo
It is effectively a hub I mean it doesn't talk directly to all the devices at home but
You know I talked to a lot of the popular smart home devices today
So
I think that probably is what we'll get
Customers
Used to this concept of a hub and maybe that's what will make it less abstract
In the consumer space
So let's move on though because right now yet another thing that's coming against
Connected devices is
Security issues we can't stop talking about the Mirai botnet
Should we invade culprits in some of these security was our routers that you don't have hearts hard-coded
Passwords are the manufacturers didn't build onboarding processes that Force
Customers to change password
I'm curious what you think about all of this security
Drama here and then how you guys are
Thinking about address
Before I jump into that I just want to clarify one more part I have on the hubs and why I think
The knot
I think in a
When you go to Consumers directly yes it's been abstract but I do think
When you go through
Some interesting
Other channels like b2c maybe something like an ISP or even
Insurance companies
I'm actually makes more sense for them because from a Catholic perspective it's
A small one-time investment and they can keep adding capabilities
I think in the future
You mostly right now all of the smart home stuff is being
Either home security or
What's provided what what do you get on Amazon
So I do think as these channels make sure
I think Rob will have a very important role to play I just want to clarify that
So back to this idea of
Security
Yeah I think this is
Become Suddenly at an extremely mainstream issue
In the last couple of weeks
I do think
Lot of fun
The Fulton Industrial
Talking about
Security with.
You know we were all wondering about
I was going to hack my lights was going to hack my
My cameras are look at what's going on
That didn't happen
So they work some of these devices what hack
And it's strangely enough
Did not hack tool
Mess up your lighting
They hacked
Mess up other devices in create an army of these
HotBox I guess so which is
We just kind of him
On the traditional
Thing that most of us were worried about when iot security first came out I thought that wasn't
Mustang
The second thing is yeah
The crazy thing is this whole heck happened because of default passwords and
And that's just
Get on
That's just crazy because
If we cannot
Get that right
I mean there are so many other things that can go wrong
Security certificates
You're much more advanced things
So I did not being encrypted
We are at the ready
Base level in terms of how poor the Securities with some of these devices it's just
I don't know it's just awful
So when you say we you mean the industry not secure
Oh yeah oh yeah so tell me what securifi what you guys do
What are the basics for security do you think
That a product should have
We were the first company
In back in 2012
Randomize every single Wi-Fi
SSID password
The admin credential
We were the first to do that
Nice
Yeah back then you know everyone Netgear and all these guys
You still just have the default name for the
Everyone up there
Devices
That's all very first week
If I was about to say
Thesis even back then was we still believe in that
Good security comes from good user experience
Youfit
Easy for customers to change passwords
If it's if they feel confident that
Okay
I can change it easily I can I can find the password at this place is Ali
They're more likely to change password
So you guys were the first two
Make default passwords
Easy to change so yeah good on you what else do you guys do
So we
Currently have no devices on your network
You can see you'll get a notification
That device joined your network
If it's a device that dinner
It's a neighbor trying to hop on the network and we have
Esophagus coming up
Very soon where it'll be a paid service where you'll be able to
Monitor some of the sites visited
It's going to be a basic service
Jessica less the
Sites initially but
Eventually we
We'll have more intelligence on it and we'll figure it out
Unusual pattern
So as an example
We'll have a service where you can figure out that
Your Nest thermostat is talking to service in Russia
So we think we are
Router
Can play a very significant role I mean it is going to be a firewall
Home
Got it okay well that's in
I assume your routers are updatable over-the-air
That's over there updates and then
You know we make the updates very easy you can just go.
You'll actually see a little notice on the Apple pay
Does a new phone battery
That's the second reality
Security
Contradict
What bugs are going to come out next year I mean this is something that manufacturers have to stay on top of
Because a lot of people say that
The reason that manufactures don't stand top of this in the
Traditional routing industry is because
These products are relatively cheap they send up they set him to forget him
When I buy a securifi
Device
How long is it going to be supported or how how do you think about the economic system porting
Continuous Security in
This is a challenge because there's always there
Download price per acre in consumer electronics
But
I think you'll have to beg him some of this online service cast into the hardware so that's
One way
On the 2nd
Is
We expect when we launched these monetize services like
The Internet Security offering that I just talked about it
Publix
It will go out
Next month
We think
Some of our customer base and convert to despot
I do think pandas have to think about baking and some of these cars
To give you a specific example of
How we deal with
Dalian Ramen was launched in
2012 July
And we still giving updates to it
Okay how do you account for things like that I mean
Let's say you have
I don't know ten thousand of those out there in the world and
It takes however many hours to develop
The patch for that thing
At some point in time
They are going to cost you money
It is that the point in time when you say hey it's like if I'm a phone
Like a payment Apple or Google I'm like a certain point I just don't support it anymore
So it's a good question
I think by one good thing now is
Because
Our customers download the app when they set up the product
At least they have that visibility into
We haven't reached that point yet with any of our products
Exped. Updating
Especially
Critical
Piece of infrastructure at home
But I think communication is the second thing one is
Security updates
We kind of think of them as mandatory
II
Suppose you
Dell customer service
Maybe
Resale Hardware
The industry needs to think about
Okay we're going to support this
Hardware for X years maybe that's the sort of thing we have to come into
My guess is
Sonic FTC is going to look into something like this
In the future
They are thinking about it
Fatso
Act now Russ
So let's look at these Services because this is another really kind of
Interesting Trend that we're seeing develop which is
Delivering Wi-Fi and itself
As a service
Or
Delivering services like security or something on top of WiFi
So
Talk to me about that that's a big shift for consumers I think it might be a big shift for vendors to so can you talk
About why this is happening
Auto
Call it a new thing at all
Because we were
In the USA
You always had the modem fee
Service
Right we just always have it
But yes there is
But almost all of us now have
Yeah so that's
That's the service I don't know I guess it's
Anywhere from $2 to $45
What's a $7 now
How it's a cash cow
Oh wow that's
So goodbye at your own router
But less than that you can get a basic almond for less than that
I think
What you'll see it perhaps is
Some of these
Isvs could give out
Better remote and charge I don't know 12 instead of 7
Okay
And now if I has pee start doing this
This kind of shrinks your Market in a sense because people will your customer base with them become isps
Supposed to direct-to-consumer
Yes that is actually
It's it's a long-term Trend by the way in the US and rest of the world as well
Where
Most gateways today are
Given out by a species
Not purchased through retail stores like
Best buy on Amazon or Walmart
A trial with the
Cable company
So we do think is be will be
One of the key channels for the movie called
Real fast before we go
What percentage of your users have activated the Smart Home
Settings or
Use the smart
Depending on the skill it's anywhere from 5 to 20%
Currently
All right
LeBron takes so much for talking to me today and
I can't wait to try this thing out
Yeah thanks Stacy thanks for having me it's always a pleasure to be on your podcast and day
I love your newsletter by the way
Thank you
Saigon Market
Well that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to sign
Sign up for my newsletter
Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com