Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy haiduk
Android co-hosts
Kevin tofel
And Men
I have to tell you guys this week I'm recording from a hotel room in San Francisco
Where
I'm at the structures security conference so expect some good things about security
Coming out this week next week on the show and the sound quality maybe a little bit Waukee
I really didn't
But having to make up for it
Cuz he's so I'll talk I'll talk Twice As Nice
Twice As Nice
First let's talk about what we're going to talk about on the show we've got the new wink Hub coming out finally the details are live
Amazon is working with some smart home companies to deliver packages
Kevin's got a review of the
Apple Watch 2 as a fitness tracker
We're going to have to talk about crabs and its giant DDOS attack enable by hacked
Iot devices
Get the news from
Sap Snapchat particleboard and maybe we'll get to some other people's reviews about
Cool stuff you can buy
M have a wonderful ad from hpe
And then
Finally Our Guest
Is Carlos Herrera the CEO of petnet which you guys may remember because it is a service that went down and everybody was worried
About dead
But Carlos tells us
Everything that happened and what he learned from it
It's a good interview
So
Stay tuned for a moment from
A message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is armed nothing highlights iot security more than a hacked car driven in
Into a ditch Charlie Miller part of the team that have two cheap in 2015 will keynote arms techcon in 2016
At their October 25th through 27th event Miller was described how he and his partner infiltrated a movie
Moving vehicle and how we can tighten security across the network so join arm this month in Santa Clara for arm techcon and
Register today at arm techcon. Com I will be there so I will see you
Okay hopefully you're not going to be in a jeep so good
Let's talk
About
Nuthatch keeps other will get to hacked cameras
I don't think there's where that a Jeep is involved in the
In the DDOS attack
Verso
All right
The new wing
Hub
We had heard that this was coming from a leech
Amazon screenshot
In semi
Pink stuff at the home
Lo behold
In October
Wink will be
You providing us with a brand new hub
And it has
An internet port which
Kevin you are not excited by but some people might find it
I'm not really moved by that but I do think it's a good addition
And it's going to have Bluetooth
The reason Bluetooth is so exciting as it can act as a link for
Your
Bluetooth enabled
Things like a doorbell and it translates it over
Wi-Fi network is only have remote access to all of the stuff in your house without all these little
Like Bluetooth bridges that you have to
And so that's cool
Other reason
The Bluetooth is exciting is a new thing that we did
It's going to make
Actually setting up iot devices
Easier in this only happens during the
Initial setup
But during the initial setup your instead of
Relying on the soft AP creation which is what we call it when
How to connect a device
Plugging in
Creates its own wifi hotspot
Has to find it in the
Everything happens right on my Android
Because my phone is like trying so hard
You keep me online
I have to turn off the cellular data on my phone
Actually hook things up to my device
My phone otherwise is
Like it never works
So yeah the phone the phone is trying to get that redundant connection because it thinks you want to be connected all the time obviously and
Make sense
It hates when I like adding a device using my Android is always
What's up
The Bluetooth connection no allows
The
Data about why something's messing up
It tells the devices Echo stop doing this so now they've built software that makes it a lot easier to
And this will be nice for people who are like
A little bit more normal who are like
Not listeners
Perhaps of the show and
I did not know I could turn off my cellular data on my
And
That is going to be
Wonderful the other thing they added as part of the setup process is if you have an old hub
You can actually transfer everything over
The Staples connect Hub actually did this but
And it's no longer on the
Useful so if you have an old week though you might be saying
Gosh
Do I upgrade
Kevin are you saying that
Yeah I'm kind of I'm kind of on the fence on this and I'm a big fan / user
Of the wink Hub that I bought maybe a year-and-a-half ago or fantastic for me my entire smart home is built around it
The fact that this one is 25% Slimmer it's nice that's okay it's not a compelling reason to me
Ethernet
Personally not compelling to me however I can definitely see why people might want that
I actually preferred of wireless connection with the wink Hub because I can put it anywhere that it does not. Hang off a router
That was one of the actual selling points to me what again this is a bonus for for a lot of people I'm sure
Turn the radios they've also added a thread capable radio and really there's not much that takes advantage of
Not yet a compelling reason to upgrade
So I will tell you
Tell me you're not home Kik
Compatible
At this moment
There is a place for a home
Kit radio
But
Place for it you can't go until you're
You're actually part of the home
Correct
So
That is
TVD so if homekit is important to you
This may not be the Hub
Yet yet
But again
I do like an again not enough for me to upgrade you like the fact that they've I think
Up the memory inside from 64 mag to 512 mag
My Hub run stable so I had to run into that issue one thing I do like and I'm considering this in my
Decision making
Process here they have beefed up the security and I believe I think they've done it through
Hardware in that the wink Hub when it boots up will make sure
It has
The same
Secure verified firmware that it had the last time it booted up and if it doesn't
It will be able to revert back to the safe secure
Meaning it's a lot less
Susceptible to being hacked or reprogrammed without your knowledge
So that's something
That has me thinking about it
The security efforts they went
Through here
Given the beginning
Horribly inside
Secure hub
It just was it was hacked mode
Multiple times they fixed it
But that really shows that they are working
Hard on getting
Ignis Wraith
And I will say that the new Hub is $99
And
They're adding a new retail partner so it will be available
On their site
In Home Depot
And at
Walmart
Yeah I saw that
Song that's that's good
Yeah I thought it was I thought it was really kind of worthwhile because Walmart is definitely
Now I also kind of wonder if it's
Because they burn Target
They had their big giant security
Blind
Recall kind of thing
And that I think
Turn them off
Yeah I could be I could well be it's hard to decide what I mean so long as there were they mainstream retailer I think I vote
Was very very well for forty Winks one other one other aspect that again is on Meatheads
Me thinking maybe I upgrade
That new Wi-Fi radio
Is no longer just 2.4 gigahertz actually supports 5 gigahertz haswell
Yeah that's that's pretty big
It's $99 I mean this is not like a $500 outlay of cash so
I say that I
Probably not going to upgrade but I have a feeling at some point I'm just going to pull the trigger and do it anyway
Sew-in and I asked I asked WinCo's like
What do you tell people who have this is something they should upgrade to and he's like you don't
You can if you want we're still supporting the old version
This is really a product to get new people in the
Amen in that respect I think it's a very compelling product at that price point for what it supports the radio
Upgrade the security
Yeah I mean again I bought my wink very happy with it
If I didn't have one
Without a doubt I probably go out and get this one so you can also wait for Christmas
And you know give someone you love
Be smart home package cuz I bet there's going to be somebody
That's my Hutch
Cuz you got Walmart
You got Black Friday
You got Home Depot
Good point
So if you're not in any Rush
VII Council people to Russian
Into the Smart Home
Don't you want me to
So yeah
That's that's the Wink News I'm excited in for all of us who were like
Quirky went bankrupt what happens to WinCo o-flex potwin
What happened to wink now we can be a little bit by
I think
It feels like ants
Company in a product that we're like
They're behind it
So let's talk about how your wink might be delivered to you
Yes so some people may really like it is whereas other people may really hate this but Amazon is
Reportedly working on in home package deliveries
Not at home in home your package will be in your house I will they do that well the information says
Listen attack princess report this as well
That Amazon is working with some of its iottie retailers or the products
It sells it products with
Such as August and garageio
Working with them to give temporary access to get in your home to leave a package
That's kind of scary and cool at the same time so August make smart locks
Garageio makes
Siri you'd order something from Amazon and give the okay to have the package delivered in your house provided you
You have an August lock or garageio garage door opener
I don't know I mean it's his great Stacy for people who
Aren't there to receive packages don't want them sitting out all the time maybe they've had packages stolen
But are you going to give access to your house
So August has this quote they had actually the access
August access
Almost a year now
Amanda
They will that be
People into
Like people are actually using this for
Both
Normal people like your Maids your dog walkers those
Things but also for like delivery of services
So it's a formal service that August offers and they have Partnerships with
Postmates in
I want to say
Sears appliance
That could be a
And with that I mean the ideas you know if you have Smart cameras in your house
You can actually watch this house
Which if the person went into your house in like
Mike stole your dog
Like oh well that's who did it
I'm not sure if that's that's comforting or not
So this makes sense
And I love that Amazon might give is
Imprimatur
To this
And say hey guys
Why don't you have that like
I actually today today on Wednesday while we
We're recording this I'm getting a makeup delivery
At home and I'm really sad about it
Really hot and
So I would love the ability
We're like my Blue Apron tool
When those real
Inside
I just feel slightly better
Sophia
I definitely see the value I just wonder what happens the first time something doesn't go
Alright like somebody is delivering something in your house and something missing or they're sitting on your couch watching TV for an hour
Can you find out what is
Amazon going to Deming they're putting potentially their name and brand behind this that's the surprising bit to me
In a situation like this
I imagine you have a cat
If Amazon actually does create its own
Own network of delivery
People with
Its own airplanes all that good stuff
True true
Treated like
Budget Inn
Employees I mean
We let people into our homes all the time
Not everybody but some people do
And you don't have to do
That's the other thing
I mean
Laundry for people who feel like
You know and I think having a camera will help
I'm not sure I would do it
But I also work from home so I'm not sure I really
I just want as many options as possible to have the
Storage lockers
They have
Am I have drones delivering stuff to you one day they have them
Putting stuff in the
People's cars
Anything I can do to remove barriers between you and a product they're doing or trying to do so I guess
Again I think it'll be
Polarizing
But the end of the day you're right it's
It's up to you if they do decide to offer this
Each individual makes a decision so
And by golly if they're going to offer me Disco
Super excited
Oh you have to go around
That this locked
Because none of my front doors have
But it's free delivery if you let us put an ad on your door lock
Man I bought so many I have the ad version of the Kindle
Oh my gosh
I have bought so many
$3 books
Because of that thing
There you go
I'm like
You're very good
Okay so
That's cool stuff coming
In-services friend
Let's talk about the Apple Watch 2 as a fitness tracker since
Last week because we were so busy talking about I don't even know
Well that's okay because I literally just got it the night before the last show so it's probably best that we waited a week because
I've now had an extra seven days to determine if it's a good Fitness tracker
And I have to say in just to put some perspective around this I run everyday I think today is day 111 of my daily
Running Street I do track my steps I'm not so keen on tracking my sleep which the Apple watch really does not do
Effectively partially because of battery life partially because there's no native function to do so
What is a fitness tracker having previously warned the fitbits and Darius Android Wear watches
I'm pretty impressed I have to say no granted I bought the series to watch which has GPS
And that is that that was a key
Negative for me on the first Apple watch I had to run with my phone if I want to use the Apple activity
Cracker witch
Just didn't like running is my phone
So the GPS is working fantastic I've compared to the
Various seven or eight runs that I've had this with prior runs GPS looks spot-on
The heart rate monitor is kind of disappointing to me though
I do run with the heart rate monitor on and it seems like no matter what every time I start a run
The Apple watch has my heart rate pegged around 160 to 170
Yeah that's like what my eight and a half minute mile pace is when I've actually been running for a bit like
What's going on
The strange thing is usually about halfway through the first mile it seems to settle down back into the
140s Maybe 150s
What is throwing off my average heart rate for sure so that's very strange to me I don't know why that's doing that don't know if that's
Just me and my Apple watch with others are having that same issue whatever
How does the heart rate monitor work is it is it the lights is it a galvanic
Carrabba's
Yeah I know it's it's the same as the original Apple watches are totally unchanged it's the same for Led You Know
Node sensors under the under the the base of the Apple watch so
No difference there and I
I don't recall this being an issue with my earlier version but then again
I was so kind of turned off McNab GPS I really wouldn't
Spend a lot of time using it as a fitness tracker so
Regular heart rate monitor is fine I mean if I check my heart rate now I'm sure it's you know probably 165 70 beats a minute
Uggs
No I'm old
So that's that's 1 1/4 I will also say this
If you want to take your Fitness data out of the Apple iOS ecosystem it is still nearly Impala
Possible there are some third-party apps that try and do this for you they don't get all the data
Apple has not made it easy to get at share the data and that's disappointing to me I have
I don't know 7 years now of data and RunKeeper so I like to put my my
I did in there I have to do it manually with the Apple watch and that's that's frustrating disappointing
It's it's just disappointing
One last bit on the GPS
There's no indicator to tell you
If
The watch has a GPS signal and I
Down that frustrating at first
But they do a really good job at using Wi-Fi assisted GPS and other methods to
You actually
Get your signal pretty quick you don't know it
When it has a signal yet
It's
Pinspot on
So kudos to the man that I do is that an indicator there so
Okay and then
How does it affect the battery life
Yeah good question because the original Apple watch was definitely just a one-day
Device on a charge
It pretty much still is I'm getting marginally better battery life and that's including
The GPS tracking as well as listening to music on my Bluetooth headset headphones and heart rate monitor
Typically if I go out and run anywhere from music 35 miles in a day
I still have
Battery life left at the end of the day
So the GPS isn't hitting it that much and warm apple has boosted the battery capacity which I believe they have
This watch is a little thicker
I think it did a good job managing that I quit on
I can probably answer that question better next show because I'm running a half marathon on Sunday with it which will be
Roughly two hours of running
I'm sure to get through it all because Apple says
5 hours with GPS
So
Okay well
I'm back in next week
Alright in kind of
Smaller news Atwood
Definitely thought we should cover
We have to talk about the DDOS attack
Brian Krebs
And the reason we have to talk about it
Is
Apparently this was a
Between a 600 and 700 gigabit
Per second DDOS attack which is freaky
And
Part of the devices that were in this attack or actually
Security cameras IP security cameras
And
Some smart TVs
So
That's insane
That's another reason to like lockdown your
Because my God
That's actually at this event that I'm in
We'll talk about it next week
Cuz I got a bunch more iot stuff happening
Today
But one of the big seems is peep
People keep bringing up his attack
Can their legs look
Having connected devices everywhere
And just bringing him into your home
And your business
Increase your attack surface but it also increases the tools that hackers
Could use to it
Attack people
And
Because he's are devices
The people you know
You can tell when your
Computers at fact
For the most part
Put
Because you don't check in on your iPad
Very often
Because hackers are very Savvy about how to
I use it
Decency
Can be infected in
Depart of like
A botnet army
I was just going to say you never know as long as you're getting you know your camera feed on command or on demand
You don't know what else that processor inside that device is doing with the connection that has
So
You just wouldn't know
Exactly so there's a lot of talk out there about this being a
Threat against
Free speech be
Because Brian Krebs was actually take
Down by
Was actually
Attacked
And his
Security provider prolex
Akamai
They said hey you know what
We're doing this for you
For free we had to absorb you know almost 700
Gigabits per second
Traffic
Do this so now he's actually under
Google
Has there
Shield Project
Journalist
So kudos to Google
Golfer for having that
Cuz they they aren't there now hosting
But
All in all this is just a this is just kind of
Scary
And not just for the
Consumer report for the World At Large
This is going to be out there in that that's going to be a big
Nothing here is with the proliferation of so many connected devices
I suspect this is not the first time we're not the last time rather that we're going to see this I mean
So many of them really are insecure and people don't realize that and we've harped on this before
Security of a device should be part of your decision making process
And
So I'll try this there was a there was a story about
I think it was a Texas mom I can't remember who.
Houston
And their baby camera
Was hacked
And what was interesting here is they were like
Look we actually change the password
My camera
From you know password rap
We change that
And what happened was they hadn't changed their password on
Their router
I'm bringing this up because we hear a lot today about this is how you saw this you changed
The password on your device
I feel like most sophisticated
But
Now you got to go back and be like oh
My router
Password
Change that
If it's a whole chain of devices that's the thing and then
I think people will miss out on that and I just will do what you would just Jezebel change the password on a particular device sale
Okay now the problem is fixed
And yet the weak Link in the chain is not fixed so
It's actually getting kind of crazy man you almost have to be an IT Network admin to start
Really making sure that you're 100% secure
Yes and that's
Not tenable
It's not why we think about that maybe next week I'll have a brand new security model
Why haven't you come back with a solution
Probably not guys
Talk about it
Cool news sap has decided they're going to spend up to
2 to billion dollars in int Investments they started out by buying a
Company called
Platte1
That is kind of a Jasper like service that offers
Tizen 2
Rihanna platform
Coyote
And I also bought it
Company in
When was Norway
Adam and that does kind of
Vision stuff
Patience.
They see the future it sees things
Computer vision in also is part of creating a digital twin
And this is a concept that super popular in the industrial leader
It is a cool concept
Comes from NASA
And
The idea is that
In the real world you have a device or app
Piece of machinery
And it is so outfitted with sensors that you can create a digital version of it that
Do all kinds
Crazy cool testing
NC housing
Affected
I think it's going to be
If you imagine like a r
The face
Woo
Scary
That's Tuff
But they did
Which has the digital
Capabilities
That's that's good news for them
Keep and keep
In the investment going
This is
A good thing for you Kevin
Because
It involves Google
Also we should give
Oh yes I consult for Google but not in their Smart Home
. also
My opinions are my own
So particle a developer board
They have teamed up with Google Cloud
To send data from physical devices directly into the
Google Cloud platform
Infer analyze
And
I forgot this was kind of cool because
It particle has its own cloud
So there
Tainan
The Google stuff
And because Google has it's like
Like crazy information
World I can see
Google like
Overtime but they've actually been experimenting with particle boards
Time data from their G bikes
With the purple acid trackers
They're showing basically how they
Track these things see what he
KFC usage patterns
Data visualization
That sounds like a very googly thing to do and I do love the bikes by the way I ride them every time I go out there
Interesting Lee this ties into a theme that we heard a Google IO has continued in some of the newer products
The Google hasn't asked
Let's machine learning Google is really making a machine learning push
So this is a really nice tie and I think
Yeah because
Machine learning is great about looking
Camphor like clusters
Patterns
Once has been trained
On what to look
4 and what to optimize for
There's going to be so much data from
Putting sensors in the world we're going to have to rely on computers to start
Like helping us filter
I just think it'll be fascinating
To see
Like you can imagine
Bikes and where they're Park
Are they are
You'll you'll be able to see like
Usage patterns like where
Kind of cluster.
I don't know
Now it's 5 completely agree
Maybe not about the bike so much
But you know that I like to buy
And then
Finally
Snapchat glasses
Yeah from a new company will not new cover a newly named company snap
No more chat
We're just taking pictures
Yes
Yet this is kind of interesting only because I'm not to tie into a whole Google theme here but
Google Glass which I think was 2013 was available really got pans
Mainly because
The creepy factor of having a camera that could take pictures and record video and sell it
And yet this is exactly what the Snapchat glasses
Do but then again this is Snapchats
This is not all right it's all about
Sharing snaps videos
What's wrong with your social friend so so these are sunglasses that will I think they cost 129
$1 when they become available
And they have a camera built-in obviously and they will
Literally record
Short snaps of a videos
And there I believe there's a light to tell you to let others around you know yeah okay to let others know that that's a
That's actually recording
And it will automatically send these circular videos and if you notice that that's Heather differential
Getting these to your friends on Snapchat
So
Important
Are Samurai
They disappear it's after 24 hours I think
Oh yeah used to be a lot less than that but I think it is up to 24 hours now they have a couple different ways I am not on
Snapchat these days I couldn't tell you not with the kids you're not hip
I'm cool I'm not well that's that's why I actually joined it not to be hip and cool.
See what my kids are doing and when I saw that they were doing like not need to see this anymore so I got off
Snapchat I hope it was all innocent fun Kevin
It was fun I don't know about Innocent but yeah whatever the kids some discussions were had
So
Yes I think
I will be curious about their reception
Because it might be a wonderful example of
Just it being the right time
So the generational shift
Google glasses
Yes
Might be enough to be like
Yeah we don't care about 5
We can walk into bars with
Crazy teal
Coral or Black sunglasses
I'm just be like
Yeah
Record this
I don't like it
I8 yeah I think it's interesting I think you're spot on I think the demographic is very different and it will be more
Italy
Accepted by the younger demographic, and that's fine I mean times are changing
Yeah I mean you got your phone with that say just use your phone
I will I will say that using your phone
Is a pain
Because you have to pull it out take the camera
Wait for
I mean it's not okay
Pain is really at the wrong
Satchel Paige
Picture with my butt
Where is fu
The fact that their sun glasses
Is kind of nice Beach
Because it's not like you're
Going to be walking around in
Inside with
Do you know this it just feels Connecticut outdoor fun
People might already be in public places
Maybe that was Google Glasses overstep is they
They made it
Too much
Always uncut
In your face scary where is apparel
Look at someone's walking around outside and
Has a pair of sunglasses on it
If I'm outside
No I'm probably
Other people
Can see me I feel like I'm in a more
So that's
A small difference
I will see how they look different I mean Google glass look like to some degree of a small computer
Strapped to your
Glasses frame
It was
Yeah
It was scary I did I I still have pictures
Stop myself wearing those things yes
There you go
Hopefully Snapchat will not have their Robert scoble in the shower moment and maybe that's all they need
Maybe that's all
I hope not I'm sorry to break that up some things cannot be unseen
Sad
Okay so real fast we're just going to stay at the sweet home
Which is a wonderful site
Part of The Wirecutter site
Actually The Wire
I like the sweet home
About sheets FaceTime
So they have decided that the best Wi-Fi home security camera
What is
Now
No longer The Nest it is now the
I'm going to say I always thought I was feeling nervous saying this
The Logitech
Litchi Circle
Which is about $170 on Amazon
They like it because it has a lot of really awesome
Some features and
And it doesn't have the
Subscription plan
So
I'm so anti subscription to although
So our last week's guests talked about
It was Canary CEO and they actually have a
Membership
Where in
And his whole point
It's not just about
Cloud storage you have to offer real service so there is is
If your home is burglarized
They will help you
You call them up
They tell you like what you
With your insurance
Please stay home
Which feels
Nice
I can't hold
But
The Wirecutter second choice is the
Netgear Arlo Q
Which is expensive
But apparently
Very nice
And their budget pick is the blink
Twitch
I have one suggest
People that they should stick
A fridge so they
A visual of
Because it's like $100.
Stick on the wall
And then the nest cam is like a
Yeah yeah yeah
Have you really likes my
So
That I thought was worth mentioning it
Because people really love their
Home Security
Cameras to spy
Set tax
Well yeah but if they're going to get the Amazon in home package delivery service then they may want this
Stay tuned for a message from our sponsor
Hpe
And
Our Guest Carlos Herrera who is the CEO of petnet you are really going to like this one
Everyone we are going to take a break for a moment for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is HP
And we have Nigel Upton who is the director
4 hpe universal iot
Hi Nigel you told me
About this concept of
Any device any network
What do you mean by
There are so many different types of things in the internet of things as you know there are literally millions
All things are not created equal
Do I seem like a connect to doorbell or a smart refrigerator
It's already difference to a complex piece of machinery
Fences all over it and say an aircraft engine or in the middle of a manufacturing plant and
Premises
The whole thing's not connected equally
There is a different sense of priority and different type of network
Appropriate for the right type of device
Signature what kind of networks are you thinking
You should when you think of things like connected cause
Then you think about cellular connectivity and that's a really good fit for the type of conductivity for the connected car
If you think about
Saya doorbell
Then why fight would be much more appropriate
Because it would normally connecting to your hair with Wi-Fi but we have
Too many use cases
Where you think about
Something you ate merging Technologies like the long range low-power wide area Networks
Galatians like the Lora Alliance oh companies like sigfox making tremendous strides
People looking at how to
Types of palm trees
The process they wanted to use was to be able to
Digitally manage how these trees are grown and so they put sensors in the ground
Sunday use a lure that's worth to be able to connect the senses together they didn't gather dates and put it through again
Gateway diesel
Because of this particular case it's one of the largest plantations in Malaysia
And the only connectivity choice they have a satellite there is no other choice what is hpe
Come into all of this
The platform
Which is absolutely agnostic
On any type of device over any type of network
To ensure that they choose the appropriate
Work whether it's based on latency or whether it's based on cost
What's the type of deployment of devices or things
Does are actually doing
And I would encourage any purchaser
Eleni iot platform
Kissing kiss about making sure that you have a platform that is open to allow you to be able to make
The choice of network
Like type of device
Where can I find out my
You can find out more about website to hp.com forward slash Fire TV
Hey everyone welcome back
The Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and this week's guests
Is Carlos Herrera
Who is this
CEO of PETA
Hi Carlos how are you doing
Thanks for having me thanks for coming on the show
I am really excited to talk to you
Because I have a dog
Needs food
+ 2
Because you guys had a well-publicized
Outage
Earlier this summer
You're willing to talk about what happened what you learned
Think about going
For it is
Let's first talk about
Petnet
And
What you guys are built
Glitter or mission is
Very simple
It's to help
Pet owners
The right tools so that they could feed their pets
The right amount of food
Pacifically for their pet and also to help guide them
The right type of
Meaning matching the right ingredients to their pets
Endemic qualities are pets nutritional needs
Self dispensing
Pet feeder and then you have a $49
Bold
Basically
Tell you when to stop
That's exactly right they're both have a
Companion app
When you on board to the device we ask you some really key questions about your pet
We have some about your
Are there age weight level of activity
Lost asking about their breed
And eventually bought some of allergies
The reason we ask these questions is so that then we can
Figure out
How many calories should be eating per day people are overfeeding their pet
Almost Hospital
The world
And if there's almost a billion to MediCare at the dogs around the world
Almost half of them were obese or overweight there's ways to to prevent this and it's just about having the right tools
So this brings us to
You guys have had this out on the mark
Yeah we launched the smart feeder the first product in August of 2015 so it's our one year anniversary
The product Market
So about that time
You guys
Went down for about 12 hours
Is it a server issue
People
Up
Sat
There is a lot of like
Oh my God about holiday what if my dog died
In
Much has been made of
What I thought was really
Pricing was when I asked
About this
You said that you guys were
We're actually from the Aerospace
Industry which I think of
Because having so many redundant
So careful
So I left
Understand how you guys
In a week we come from a very core team cuz they're very strict
Engineering background
When we notice this particular failure which
Made it so that our haircuts
Are trusting us when we went down we were
We were serious
They were at we actually went down at
About 8 p.m. Pacific time and we were up
Until 8 a.m.
The next day but looking for a fix
You know when you're at when you're designing
He's very large scale
Engineering Systems
You can choose your path so you can make a closed system you can make it an open
The world we live in now
Everyone's more inclined to build an open system because you end up in a greeting with
Pieces of the system that other companies are just better at you know they're there better at building
Distributed real-time data distribution
What we wanted to do is
Ensure that we were leaning on those capabilities leaving on those companies who are experts at 6
We end up with a system that is
Integrative third-party services in a lot of iot companies
Are built this way because if you really wanted to close a system
Mensaje we'll build everything you'll never finish you never bring your product to Market
With the amount of money that you have
To the system that we built
How's redundancies employees
But a lot of the
Received a lot of failures that are small.
Our customers don't even notice
We both redundancies for them immediately but a lot of them
We see them
As we encounter them right
And one spring counter them then were building their redundancy
That's different than
The Aerospace world where you know you're building aircraft
Chinese aircraft have to stay in the air forever all the time
You can't have any failures
And uses the aircraft systems are
Designed and developed on a 20-year cycle
Are we in the iot world we build things in them
Through your cycle right so you end up
Sacrificing
A lot of tests
Time
In order to get your product to Market
And at the same time
A lot of
Test time cost
As much as development time
She really just don't have the budget
Detestable
Do you really have to do
Just be on your toes and ensure that you can react quickly
And in a plane
Cost
Dollars vs
Pet feeder
So
How many third parties
We're in your sis
How do you think that
Compares to other IO
For us we have a 7 third-party integration
Aldi's third-party Integrations we've got them right there. They're not small companies.
I won't mention any of them but there
Large
Publicly traded companies there
They build their systems with
Redundancies in place
And you know of any one of these can
Fell
The killer dolls to build a system that
Can quickly react and switch over to a redundant system
Redundant systems are usually a little less capable right so you end up with
For processing less bandwidth but it keeps the system up and going so
The key to it all is to try to predict
All the potential failures
Android software to detect and fill over as quickly as possible
A lot of people saw this
Outage
Hazard
Good example of a resume
Why do why companies should put
Intelligence
So in the case
The internet going out
Servers failing
Or else
Everything
Default back
Physical devices
In the in the Aerospace world we call that a no comms scenario no communication
The interesting thing is an iot world you're very dependent on Communications but you have to design it so that if you lose
Communications for
Any amount of time whether it's one second one minute 12 hours in our case
Your system can still do
The basic functionality so with every
Every scenario where you lose a particular capability in this case we lost Communications to from our servers to our devices
The devices still have to
Work and
We will end up losing a little capability like you lose the real time on activity where you get the updates break-resistant
Wait for the update
Come out of your home
All the way to our servers and then down to your phone
Oh what Still Remains was ability to
Feed your pet
And what's interesting is that we built that in that was actually
The capability that is in the system was in the system prior to the failure so everyone's pets were fed
What happened was
People weren't getting the updates to their phone
Prince can you guys did a great job
I mean sending out of
Proactive email
Hey by the way this is
What's happening
I think it did get lost.
The pets were actually
Fed
That maybe the media is false
I'm real sorry about that
Certainly we didn't react
On the media friends I called his kind of like startups
Learning exercise right week
We didn't know how to react to a crisis we're so busy
Just building. Morales is awesome let's build his capability
That we we we weren't prepared for the media
Getting ahold of the
Story at 8 p.m. where
You know in the other side of the world it's 8 a.m.
And this the story is going
Live and it's spreading the end it's all the s*** it's a very important issue people are trusting
That we are feeding their pets in
Here we are with pet owners are not receiving confirmation that their pets are being fat
And that turns into panic and spin a sort of way or you know that's a startup we we are attempting to
Abdul exclamations infrastructure
DIYs I can
React quickly do that now we know we learned our lesson but
Rest assured on the engineering side your pets
We're said at the time that was scheduled
What else
Would you
I can see
Wiehle Ave
Like so you've integrated lots of
Partners
Are there steps
Is part of that energy
Operation that you
As an entrepreneur
To help
Maybe increase your
Liability or maybe
Just
I'm like
The importance of dashboarding what would we take away is
We need to build out more tools
That can help
Detect
Sellers more quickly
You know and not just tools so that
We wake up the engineering team and they start
Taqueria fix it also alerts
Rpr partners and our marketing to answer prepare for
For the backlash because people are paying attention they're trusting these devices.
Smart home that's the value proposition
You know the smart home is taking care of this for me when it doesn't
People get upset Justin
If I had someone helping you out in the home you know
If they didn't do their job I'd be upset at them cuz that's what that's the value proposition that you're paying for
We need to understand as a company
I think all iot companies to understand that
The value proposition
Needs to be real and he still always work
And when it doesn't work you need to prepare for
For those scenarios
In the software
World
There's this concert
Set that move fast
Curious because
A lot of people think that
That's a very Silicon Valley eat
It also kind of feels like
Maybe not the right
Hardware company
What do you think about
That is like
Amantra
Just in general
I think I think it's it's to be honest you have to move fast what happened Hardware however
You can only move as fast
As you can test an iterate through things in software
You can iterate
Through version
Quickly I mean you can walk over to someone's desk say hey can you try this get another build out in your test servers and your
You're up and running
With Hardware it's a little different you you do get the
Soccer park
Every all Hardware has software
However if there's an issue with your Hardware
Florida shooting
We had back in August of last year
Summit a few hundred customers were affected
In order to fix that piece of hardware
It took us three months
We have to re-engineer Reed School
Get the new tool.
Production
Make sure that will was come out of the fact
Was what we wanted
Finally finally we have to Ocean Freight which takes another month
And after that we have to track the product
The stores and they finally the new customers
We moved fast and we broke things the whitcomb's
Hardware
You're governed by
Hardware Manufacturing
Do you have to
Follow that process to a T
In
Do you think
Some of this is a functionality of you guys being a startup
And
Figure company
Wouldn't have these
Kind of challenges
Is possibly cuz there
Building
You know we have a lot of advisors
A lot of them
How many of them are
Big corporations
Not have dual consumer electronics for decades
And you'd be surprised
They have the same issues with the with the luxury they have
Is the house larger budget
They have more time so
With a start-up you know that the fundraising cycle Avicii fundraising cycle
Bushes
On the schedule that you need to have
Minimum viable product
Then you need to be in the Market within the second year then you need to be able to scale
Within the 30 are you here all these
Early man
A company that has been due to
Decatur
They have a 8-year product development cycle
Windows 8 years and not just developing one version their developing five
And they're doing marketing research and they're calling in
Groups of people to test and provide feedback
And by the time to get to eat
To the eat there like we are 99% confident this probably is going to work
We are 9% confident that people are going to buy this
And that was 8 years later
And there's benefits to that there's also
The big challenge is to that because it's your designing something 8 years ago
I know you could arguably say that it's it's already obsolete by the time
You get to Market so
I think with was larger with a larger company
Did you get it
More robust reliable iot product however
It don't get the Innovation The Cutting Edge technology because
A lot of these systems are just designed you know 5 to 8 years ago imagine 5/8 years ago
What what did we have
It was only a year after.
Nothing displays in my decision
There's a balance that I think a lot of
The Innovation that comes out of startups has to be balanced with
Agility and just
Awesome people
In the company that can react quickly that can build
Solutions to account for
The flaws
Fastest
Call Carlos thank you so much
Explaining all of this
I appreciate you coming on the show
Absolutely thank you for having me for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show
Feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com