Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
And I'm your host Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin coval
And today we have a hodgepodge of exciting projects
Starting with let's
Hold on hold on
Okay is it a potpourri of iot
Oh my
Goodness it is a potpourri of iot
I will never do that joke again I pray
Cuz I asked
Cuz I never say
This is a shadow
For everyone who is running while listening to podcasts
Cuz apparently they're like 5 if you out there
Go run run faster faster and for the rest of you hurt slugs like me
Just chill it's all good
This week on the Smart Home
Prince what do we have we should start off with
I got a little testy about smart home stuff
Yes you did
You cut it off on the whole industry
I did well
I'm just going to say it
Mad I got really frustrated
And I
To tell you how frustrated I got I basically said the best product out there right now is the Winx
Smart home hub
And that that gives you a clue Kevin
End of how bad
I feel that the industry
Oh I know that's bad because I'm like on the wink bandwagon and you
Got so many different hugs in the bridges and whatnot that you like me
But
The fact that you're saying that the best product
In the market
Maybe made by a bankrupt company is pretty telling
So my issue is
Every
Company out there
I feel like everyone is basically accepted that early adopters
Are going to early adopt
And everybody else is just
Going to follow them and there's this Acceptance in the market
Sometime
People are going to start buying these
Men
There's no care for the
Consumer
And people just keep
Pushing out
Products that
Need to be updated in terms of like
Like home kid and we even they're pushing out incompatible stand
Nobody is telling a
Coherent story
About
What is devices do
And
Products are really expensive and people are installing them for the Long Haul
Yeah I mean your home is a
Tell me the biggest investment that most people make and when you do things around the house
Spend that money
And you'll do it over and over and over and over again
Like you and I do with our Gadget
So that's one aspect
Some of these companies aren't even pushing a product or pushing a vision
And then we can have a problem
You mentioned you know we've and
And Google's thread and all that you know
Nothing's come of that yet
Red is a newly launched
Are relatively newly
And yeah those products are not really in the market
I mean they're backwards compatible there's a couple of things that can be updated the thread if they were using zigbee chips
With homekit coming out basically
Anybody who's purchased
A smart home
Product in the last to know three years
You're going to have to buy everything new
For home yet if so
You know everyone's like well orally adopt
Do you know that's what have
What happens if you want to do
The nest
Weave
That's a new protocol that also
Isn't actually quite in product Seattle
Won't be till next year is
Talk about
What is Thatcher thing
Also what if you decide you don't want to
Stick with apples
Ecosystem
And you want to switch phones
I've got all these locks and whatnot
Installed in your house
This is terrible for the engine
This is just
Terrible it is terrible and
I mostly agree with your point about
What's better nothing about the consumer I think most of the companies would argue against that
Hopi prophecy reasons
I think really what it is they're all trying to
Innocence I almost blame Apple for this
They're all trying to own the experience
So they're pushing everything they can at getting
You know broad acceptance
Products installed in homes
Getting their apps on everything so
People can do stuff with them
This is kind of why I like
Amazon's approach because
They're pushing your own experience by
Putting out a plateau
As opposed to
Putting out
Actual Smart Home Products
Bright and as soon as I see Amazon embracing or babies other people embracing Amazon and I talked to him
A lot of different
Companies
Pushing smart
Sun products
Soon as I see more of Amazon so-called
Competitors
Building stuff on
Viecco
Play service
The Voice servicenow
I will I will
Bailey Bryan
Into it cuz that's really what I want to
You know please Google
Urm Google is actually
Titus calendar
I asked
My echo for my calendar for the day
I want to control my Sonos
Over
My echo I want to
I want to get Spotify on that
And that's a thing I mean it's going to take time for these Integrations and actually I think out of everybody
Amazon probably done the best job by putting there
Code and SDK is out there and leaving it up to all these smart home product manufacturers to
Use the cloud service or not
It's to the point though I were still have to buy so many different unique
Hubs and bridges and things
You don't think people don't want and I said it before I don't want all these hugs and prayers only have one
Ethernet port on my Google onhub router I don't have room for a bunch of hugs and brushes
Well then that's okay I knew I was okay because going back to the very beginning
Topic
Cause my wink doesn't have to be hardwired to a router it works over Wi-Fi
Hey he works what can I say
It does what I needed to do
Link is so
Temperamental
And it turns on my lights
If you have much higher standard
And that's okay
My high standard
Interfering with my ability to enjoy it
That's correct
I'm glad you said it not me
Alright well if you have high standards like
You may be disappointed
If you don't
Perhaps you should be in the early adopter camp
In
Or pick up the wink
So so this is my my call to the industry is
Stop treating customers
Like guinea pigs
Especially if you really want us to get beyond the earliest
Because I can tell you
People ask me questions about this stuff all the time especially when they find out what
I'm writing about in there just like
Stacey how do you spend like that kind of money on something when you know that you know it's going to be obsolete
And I'm like oh I'm kind of hoping it's not going to be but but it might be in
I have to swear to be okay
Then I just kind of shrugged and I say it's my job but honestly if it weren't my job I don't
I can't really canceled
I really can't
It was amazing to me is that
A Smart Homes are not new
Just the consumerization of them I would say is relatively new
And even from where we were
5 years ago
Even where we are from 5 years ago
We got the basic building blocks in place we finally settled on the right radios and so on
And we got pretty widespread compatibility between mobile operating systems to control these things we got voice
Recognition to handle it
And yet
There are still so many different
Ways of doing it and it's just
It's annoying as all get-out
I don't even think
Solid
Be honest but
That's okay
So that's that was me going postal on the smart
The ministry
Get your stuff together and
But in that vein
For those of you guys were Brave out there brave enough we do have a lot of I get the occasional emails from
You guys keep up coming
Love it
From people asking
Basic questions
Kevin I thought this would be a good time to to answer those Bass
Questions on
How does
People get started what kind of questions should they ask in
Do you know we do this every now and then but I figured now's as good a time as any to kind of go over this so Kevin
What kind of questions should people ask
Ask themselves when they're considering a smart
Take me like oh I want to have a smart home
Short I mean the end there so many
And so and when I can obviously come up with all of them but I can come up with a bunch of the top of my head
I think the first thing you want to do is figure out what
Devices you want to control
Do you know some people may not care about locks
Garage doors and one I just met want lights
Timmy want integrated music system
I would make a list
And what you want to add first cuz it's tough as we just said does not come cheap
I think in your article you said you'd spent over $3,000 in the past
Er-2
Yasso
I was call it what do you want to do
Say you want a smart home
Yeah I'm absolutely I'll figure out and prioritize a list of what it is you want to do and I think that's a perfect
Perfect start
And once you do that
Then I would say I would
Start researching
Various hubs and platforms
Because
Some of them support certain products emblem support others
Certain products and maybe the products you're looking at
Are supported and maybe I want to
Pacific garage door opener doesn't work with Samsung
SmartThings
Throwing it out there and let me know
Give me an example
I think that's your best bet
Is to figure out what supported products are on your list work with which hubs and they're going to find overlap
Which is great I think that's ideal
Temperature outside going to find some things
Can't be controlled by certain
Certain hubs
I would ask if you want to you know do voice activation and control that means you probably won't either
Homekit stuff with serious resuming an IOS person
Whenever you go with me Amazon Echo
You know nothing there are other we talked about the IV I believe
I would say actually
Yes
That is
Emerging
By far
Is the most used
Way to interact
You won't use it everyday but until you can like
Program
Like a great rules engine and
All the ones out there kind of
All right
It's just so handy in the beautiful thing is I know I said it before but I really think of bears repeating
Actual post I wrote four years ago over a cake all about
When Siri came out I said this is the invisible interface of the future and that is a beautiful thing because whether it's Siri where there is
You're saying Google what you're saying
You know Amazon Echo
Anybody can use it as long as I can speak obviously so you're not tied to
Everything happening on your personal phone through your personal apps anybody in my family for example
Can turn lights on and off
You know she opened
Close the door and so on
Give me the voice activation that's a beautiful thing as well
Those are good things to
To start with
Also say
Amazon
Dot-com the retail side in their home automation Channel
Actually shows you they have a wonderful setup it shows you
What devices
His work with
Yep so
That's a wonderful place to do research once you've decided
Hey these are the following sick
6 things I want to do in my home
And you can kind of look and be like
Oh look here all the devices that were
So starting there and then I also had someone ask
Ask me about smart outlet
I was just talking about those this weekend and I'll tell you why after you talk about
Okay this person wanted to know what
Type of smart outlet
They should install which
Dear God that's actually a really hard question
Because they didn't
Ask me anything other than that
So there's
There's a bunch of a smart outlet
Like a diamond dozen
You can get a bunch of soap from a feature category
You can get a smart outlet with
Pretty much any radio
Zigbee Z-Wave
Bluetooth Wi-Fi
So I would recommend anyone who doesn't have
Like a hug and doesn't want a hug
You just want to pop a smart outlet in there
Go with a Wi-Fi or
Bluetooth
Smart outlet
Best part Daniel
And before you go any further are you are these Outlets
Actual replacements for your current Outlets or add-ons to your existing
Because that's another question if you don't want to do installation by ripping out your existing Outlets
Mostly she just plug right now
Caesar daughter picture
So some things to look for in these Outlets
This one is
Does it take up your whole Outlet
Just think about that cuz like the old school wemos
You played that baby and you have
Like Trader Joe's
And that's no good
Think about the future
Outlets
A lot of the ones on there
They monitor your energy usage
Which he might be like yay or you might be like
Screw that I don't need it
I'm paying an extra ten bucks sport
Two there's one that offer presents
There's actually only one that I know if that's the zuly we've reviewed them which is kind of a cool feature but you have to buy three of them to get that
So if you want
Don't do it a lot of them will offer dimmer capabilities on a lamp module
So if you're going to plug a lamp in this is great
If you just wanted to turn your Appliance on and off for
You don't need that
Let's see what else can these things off
Well let me tell you what I was looking at this weekend and why
You were kind enough to send me I think for my birthday a WeMo Insight switch made by Belkin
And those go for like 50 bucks so they're not cheap
Also not too big too big won't lose an outlet
It's an outlet just
Like any other smart outlet as you would said there's another dime a dozen
What I like about this one
That I can
Track the energy usage
Both in real time as well as historical and it will tell me my estimated monthly usage
So if you're
Plugging in something that may use a lot of juice
And you want to keep track of that you can do that right in the app thanks to the outlets with gun additional capability
Lottery winners don't have
That's cool
I tend to
Dislike have how do you feel about the WeMo soft
It's okay only have one we moved the one WeMo switch I was thinking this weekend about adding another one because we
We're going to put a heater in my step daughter's room and we don't want it set to a temperature
Because of
Type of heater that we're getting
We want to put on the schedule
So
I thought that we would be good and I can also see how much juice is actually using so
I'm okay with it I mean it I just pretty much use the on-off button in software
I don't see where yet. Can I get to my wink or any like that
That's a whole nother aspect going back to original question
Luby's do you want multiple apps or do you want
You know everything in one
And right now I got multiple apps for different things
You should be able to
Insight switch
200 not to your wing
That's exactly
It's funny you say that because then this could be helpful as well
For people who don't know what Hub they want
You can actually download the software for these hubs the apps for these hubs that's just SmartThings app or the WeMo app for the win
Hub app
And in there when it says add a product you can tap that
It will show you all of the supported products
So that's an easy way to research what sports what is well
Is true although
They also.
For profile
Zigbee and Z-Wave which means summer genetics
Yeah some of them
Just kind of add on your
Okay
So that's kind of a little bit for newbies who are like
I want to add stuff but I don't know what to do or maybe you're just
Older people
You're your old hands at this in your like
I just want to
Yeah I don't know
Okay so exciting new products on the market
Just run down
Some cool stuff
Corner
Which I remember if I've ever talked about this
But this is in the homes
Security space
This is actually really
A cool looking product it is shipping now
It's a cool thing because it is a home security products
Four Lake Apartments
Safer transient spaces but that made
What is that mean
Apartments
It was in a box I don't know
A container
But it's $98
You got this like
Dongle that
A plug into your router
+ 3
Tabs
Corners
Open close sensors
That you can put on
Your door
Windows whatever
In and out
I talk to the CEO of this company and I thought it was
Is vision is basically
Just cheap and easy security
Four people and then
You know instead of being monitored security what it is is you
You created an app that
Is a circle of friends that gets notified if they
There's a break in
I think this is a great value
Three of these for $98
I love that I love the fact that these are very unobtrusive looking you probably won't even see them quite honestly because they
Kind of blend in with the casing around your window or your door
Musicbee so we got a standard there
Couple things I'm not
Keenan I don't have another place to plug a dongle in my router and
Not everybody else does either in even if they don't have an onhub they might have something with you
Just for ports this gets back to too many things
Being plugged in and also
Again this does have an app as you had said and that's what the notifications go
Again
I would love to see some consolidation
So that everything goes
The one that I want a smart home interface not
Smart Home
You know but that's not
Is the new product they could integrate it with
Different holiday credit to credit with
Amazon's Echo who knows
So that there's a lot to like here in a couple things and I'm like
Improve anyways
Now I will say
And talking to people who build these products
Wi-Fi
Stability like the way
Link has bad ads
It's about books
A couple bucks
Steer
Base building materials
Json
Retail term
So and I know in talking to the Sea
CEO the important
If it's super cheap
Because he's
College.
And these are probably
Targeted for those folks who don't have any other smart home stuff right now for me you know where the wink hub
Academy support
Call correctly so I don't necessarily
Yes I don't need this the stick that comes with the
The corner
You know I mean I do need it because I tell the projects designed to work right now
I know what the audience are going for but you could expand that audience for people who are buying hugs and a
Broader smart home ecosystem
You know
I can't see the FAQ is here
But if it's
Supports like zigbee
Zigbee h a 1.2 wink actually supports that so then you
You could actually bring it in it wouldn't have the profile necessarily but you could probably try to bring it in if
Yeah I mean I would give it a shot because I don't want that
Extra zigbee dongle
Add to my router already have zigbee on my network I don't need it
Kevin I don't like dongle
Bojangles
See it I'm sitting here
You know what I want I want Anna
Extra Lutron
I can plug into
Smart Hub
SmartThings
Oh because you've run out of
Which by the way guys
I know that I've tweeted pictures and I am
In the midst of reviewing are trying out the
SmartThings
Version 2
Bear with me
Dying to know I know it's
If they really go bye-bye
Great I am enjoying putting it on I playing with the software it's a good user experience so far I went in and
Tried to do something super advanced
Did I mess mine up
Not SmartThings fault it was me
Just messing things up because I was
I was too ambitious
See guys
So give me give me another week as I try to extricate myself
Basically back to life
Spaghetti Smart Home Health
Ya basic
It's a special thing when you
My whole family is
To hang this to us
Just pick a system in
Stick with it for a week
Just tell them that you need a second home and that will be your smart home
So so yes that's quarter it by the way it's corner with a
Make a wish you wouldn't know
I'm using my hard k sound here
Corner safe.com
With a k
So
I think Lucy
I feel like we've done a good job today
Do you have another topic
But I don't think we're
Surprise okay okay
What about the kitchen in little
Products
To Baker boards yeah we got to talk about this for all the developers in
Y'all are still the kingmakers
Play Coyote poop
Okay
So
Exciting things
Is Intel announced a new note in Tilden in
Sitwell until now
Pianos it was a joint announcer with the Arduino folks
So they said that they were going to put the
Mercury chip
Reno bird
Which up until now featured
What was it
Arm-based atmel
ShopRite
So actually if I'm not mistaken this is the first shipping product with until scary module inside
Even though they shut it off
Announced it in January at the Consumer Electronics Show
Is it okay well I guess it's not they shut it off also in a fuss
Watch but that mean
That's not shipping yet this is this is actually available
Okay well an Arduino board
Yeah so it doesn't look as good on the rest I'll grant you that
Geek Chic in some parts of the world
So I am eager to hear your experience with this because
I know that
Some of the major boards that people had tried out
Using
Which had that had an atom
Chip on it
Kansas has the cork I believe
Yeah they had an Edison with a cork
On it
Nose Edison with Adam those Heretics superhot
Ayodhya play with it
A couple of those at the
Maker Faire
This is not going to run hot this for this is a 32-bit cork
Processor
Kilobytes
With a k
Flash memory 80
Kilobytes of RAM
A digital signal
Signal processor Bluetooth LE radio and six-axis sensor
This is the tie
The type of physical and digital worlds together
So what is it this is not
Intel Core i7 power dynamics
This is not your future
Definitely
30 bucks
Anda
Yes shipping Now song
Sure I have an Arduino board since I could do I want to get this
The difference is the chip release I don't I don't know if I'm going to
Drop the money off
Maybe
So
In another
MakerBot
Ford Flash
Imagination which is a semiconductor company that does more Graphics chip
Damn
A maker
Coyote
Based on the maps
Architecture
Mepps man I think I had a pocket PC or PDA with a mips chip in it
20 years ago
Oh no no no no I'm not I'm not bashing to buy any maintenance great they're still around
Options are good
So now
The mips architecture now
They're telling us that
End and I have no idea
Is this diskin's a little bit out of my purse
But they're saying this is great because you know up until now
All of the
Other
Maker and death boards have been using
You know arm-based
The
Pi uses
It uses a specialty design
Broadcom SOC
Up until the until announcement that used a
Atmel
But with the mid stuff
This is
Not a mobile
Bass processor
This is especially designed for iot
Now the specs
Sound too girly iot
Other than it has Bluetooth in it yeah I would agree this is probably more like a Raspberry Pi competitor so you could
I still do iot applications and design with it but it's not like Arduino there's a definite difference
For one thing is more than twice the price at $65
It's a duel
Kormit
CPU
You correct as Bluetooth 4.1
It also has 802 11ac
Wi-Fi
An audio DAC
An SD card slot switch to me this is more like a
A Raspberry Pi competitor
Which
Still has tie-ins to 2
You know iot and smart home type things you can
Do all kinds of things on a runs Linux or Android so
This is a low-cost computers with us
Oh yeah and I
Interesting
Cuz I know you can make the
Yeah
Done
Alright so those are two new boards for people out there who are excited about Mickey
18 Hardware Goforth do so let us know which
And
I think that's it for the
Today Show
We will end
Stay tuned for our guest
Who is
Jim heppelmann
Who is the CEO
TTC and he's going to talk about using augmented reality in the internet of things and the concept of digital
Twins
For your physical stuff
And why that matters
One of me is scary enough
Best
Don't blame you
All right so stay tuned for that
Hey everyone this is Stacy
Katie Higginbotham and you are back
With the Internet of Things podcast
And today's guest
Is Jim heppelmann who is the CEO of PTC
Hi Jim
Hi Stacy how are you happy to be here today will thank you for coming on the show
So we have you on the show today because
PTC is
It has been for like the last 2 years buying up startups
In The Internet of Things you guys started with I think thing work
Send keyboard up
Heceta and just recently this month you guys have bought
Before you from
Qualcomm
Is an AR
Play what's a lot of people were like
AR augmented reality in The Internet of Things how does that work together
So
I guess we should probably start with
Congratulations
And then
What is your vision
For The Internet of Things
Yeah well thanks again Stacy so
You know what we think that what's really happening here is a convergence of digital and physical
Elements in the things are the products that we interact with everyday
Refrigerator or an automobile or a truck is partially there in front of you in a physical format
But it's also partially implemented up in the cloud with analytics and iot
It's 04 so we've been assembling
A collection of technologies that helped merge together
Both the elements of the product but also the
Ways in which we would interact with products that are part physical in
Buy digital
Platform
Helps connect the physical product
Up to the cloud
And then our cold-light acquisition helped us to perform analytics against the data that we were
Gathering Findlay products
And now the beauty 4 U technology
Credible ability to go
Back to the physical product into projector
To augment all of that digital knowledge we have
Back under the physical product
Dashboard what's going on with the product or
Explain how to operate It Works products
We can kind of Mary
What we know diddly about the product
With the actual physical product that's right there in front
So I love this concept
Because you called it a digital twin
You also called it in Avatar but I kind of like the idea of a ditch
Triple twin because it sounds a little less science fiction e
And I think it's
Cool idea because and it's a
Easy one for normal people to grasp
Switches I have a
Refrigerator in reality
And
It's doing everything I normally would expect it to
To do but it also actually we're going to stop with refrigerator because
Everyone mocks the connected
Let's let's take something a little bit more
More practical
I have a Connect
I actually have
It has its
Job in reality
You know it's a lie
But there's also a stream of digital information coming off of it
That I can't actually see
See but it's becoming just as important to me and it's
It's this weather
Connections
Two services
So
Various different platforms that might be connected to maybe it's
But it's also data about you know
It might have a temperature sensor in it might have
A present sensor
So all of these things are also relevant
Not just me as someone who cares about the light in my home
But also
Platforms that have
That's correct I mean
The term Avatar sorted means the digital counterpart to a physical pain
But you're right the term
Digital twin is actually better because
Coincidence
Born at the same time
The point is each time you create a
Physical instance of a physical product
You wouldn't react it
Digital twin
And therefore all of the experiences
And exposures environmental conditions
The were experienced by the physical product
Can also be experienced by its
Digital twin
Indifferent any point in time you kind of have a one-to-one mapping between the two
This is important
Because there are many people that want to know what's going on with the physical product but it's a thousand miles away
However the digital twin
Is a couple of
Lost connection
So in terms of the engineers wanting understand how they designs performing
They can check in on the digital twin
What a service technician
Who I wants to understand if there is something
Service needs coming out board
To use Predictive Analytics
Can interact with the digital twin
Wait just one second before we take it to that level
Because I think
I want to keep it real simple gesture
For a second
Picture with it is
Nnsy
Anime
Not giving my my listeners all the credit and I'm sorry if I'm not
Taking the light bulb example
Cuz I think this is really worth
Exploring cuz I think it's
What's before you
You're buying this augmented reality
Qualcomm hit develop
What's in lots of developers use it and it's really powerful in
And basically
You can hold up your phone
It's your phone that
Are there other ways
Certainly before you would run on phones tablets and of course my classes okay
So probably
A lot of use cases in the industrial world with migrate toward
Glasses because they have the advantage of being a hands-free
So I hold up something
Like my phone
Smart glasses
And I if I looked at my light bulb
I could actually see
See all this digital information that I can't
AC current
That so I could see for example
It would a identify hey
Look at the light bulb and it could show me like all the services that I have
Connected to it
It could show me like
Hey the present sensor says you're here
Hey this says it's connected to the Amazon Echo
Stacy haiduk says it's connected
If this then that
These are all theoretical and this isn't what PTC is actually
Doing this is a smart home exam
The listeners
Now
Jim
But I just want people to understand
This all could come to light like
Flash
Right there and then
It could be super awesome because right now
If I look at this late I have to go to an app and try to figure this out after Remember When
I connected it to and there's nothing really on the market that does the
So imagine in my garage at home I have my car
And my wife has her car parked right next to it and her garage lot and I walk out and I point my phone at her car
And it shows me that the gas was a little low
And the driver side front tire
Isabel law
You really should change your transmission fluid because
So disability
Interact with physical things
But because of the digital twin
The gather all of the information that's specific to my wife's car and map it onto my wife's car
Because
And then when I move the phone over and pointed it at
My own car
We've been linked to the digital twin of my car
And we see that the transmission fluid
True Predictive Analytics perhaps
Needs to be changed so
Actually the transmission is glowing
When I pointed at my car
Whereas when I pointed it at my wife's car
You know perhaps the tire in the yard
In the gas tank we're glowing As Seen On TV Gators
What needed to be dealt with
You know it's my transmission
She was going to be like
Hey there's a part of my car that's glowing
What's that
Well let me tell you that until the next step would be
Homeowner
Is a consumer I'm not going to work on my transmission to let's say I wasn't
The mechanic
I need to work on
I could know again using my glasses tablets on whatever look at that transmission and say
Explain to me
How I would go about service
And it would say well you've got to come over here and open those like
And then you need to remove this so I cover panel and then you need to come down here and do that
You need to come under the car and drain the fluid here and
What is not a general process for a general transmission
Specifically what to do for this specific transmission that's right in front of me with full wariness of won't spin
Bright
And that's
Awesome so
You guys have
Let's say you have
A lot of deals with Industrial
Companies
Actually got a partnership I think with GE on their brilliant Factory
Product
How is this going to be implemented
With your customers
Because there's
It's not like
One the deal isn't closed yet I think you said you were hoping it be closed
Later this quarter
So how does this
Cuz there's a lot of Technologies involves to walk me through
How this becomes
Yell if we take this idea that I have a closed loop with a product
Meeting Dad through Internet of Things
I'm getting information from that product
Two analytics watching that information to find things that aren't obvious
And then through augmented reality I'm able to see what I need to know
Is a dashboard or an instruction
I'm going to get back onto that product
This idea of a closed-loop interaction
Could be implemented in so many different businesses
In so many interesting ways
So I think we should just an explosion of possibilities of what things
It what what companies could do
People could do it with this type of technology so what we're going to bring to our customers it showed of
Technology platform
That's a very
Fastway
To implement some incredibly
Innovative
Now that we're going to
In our Enterprise Solutions business we're going to try that
Pre develop some of the most obvious Innovative use cases
But I think
So many possibilities here it's going to be very difficult to get the end Solutions all into a box with a bow on them
I think it's dead will be
Providing the enabling possibilities
Maybe if I could Stacy imagine walking into your laundry room
Yeah.
You know my washer and dryer at home have lots of buttons and dials and displays
Actually need that stuff
I could just have white boxes and Sheet Metal
Washer the dryer it would augment on to the washer or dryer
Appropriate digital interface
And then I could customize
So I could say I want a button on the washer for blue jay
Get all big load hot water
The cold Ranch
Etcetera etcetera
Whatever I want I'll customize that and say that
Now when I put my phone at my washer
In addition to all the standard stuff has got a big button that says blue jeans
And I just touch that button on my phone
Intruder
The washer to configure itself to do blue jeans just the way I like to do blue jeans
So you can see it even with
Causes to retake the whole way we design things
Why put all that human
Machine interaction Hardware cost money
And you know can be a little complicated
Why building a tall is a machine
When
Wow although
I'm going to tell you
Two things
One I love the idea of having a programmable button
Or two
5 on my washer dryer
But
I hate the idea of having the
Carry a phone around for the rest of my days
Because none of my products have buttons on
I would I would just die
Cuz I I just
This is this is a recurring theme
So I don't want
But I like the idea
To make the world
Programmable
Through
Maybe it's a R&B
Programmable
Cool with that
Very cool so
It sounds like you're going to have a
Death platform
For this and so if I want to make
Before it apps
And like play around with like
Maybe I'm Tesla and I'm like hey this sounds awesome
I want to make an overlay for my world
Or maybe I'm a hospital that I want to download this and start like playing around with things the nurses
Dua for a patient betke
That sounds
Awesome you
AR
Certainly I mean I could look at a patient with the
Smart glasses are again with my phone or tablet
Who the patient is
Everything
Any alerts I should know right this moment but also you know how are they doing on the fitness program
Body temperature
If example anything I could get somewhere volts or from
Things like the bathroom scale that this person interacts with
I can aggregate together on their digital twin
It's all I'm always just comparing the physical to the digital twin and mapping information from one to the other
I frankly both directions here and it really gives me
The beauty of the physical experience
Which is still the person in front of me I see that
But all the richness of that digital information that used to be filed away in databases and I had to look away from the purse
Now I can bring that rich information right here into this experience with the person and she both the person and everything I
I need to know about the person
Soda in the same frame of vision
So right now though my digital twin
Like
I've got a crazy at my house has it
Will twin I have a digital.
Twin but right now all of my digital twin data
Is locked away still in different database
So how are we envisioning
The creation of the
Is digital twins in them
Coming together so like researchkit feels like
A really cool example for the medical
Coalfields of getting that data.
Come together
Place
I don't see how purple things developing in other Industries
Well I think if you do research on
It's working from NASA
I have the second space shuttle disaster
They knew on take off
That a piece of foam had broken loose and hit a tile
And it's suspected that maybe the tile was dislodged they didn't actually have a twin they couldn't stay well
What if we talk
A digital replica of the Space Shuttle and we knock the tile off it
And it tried to simulate the re-entry conditions what would happen
The theoretically could have done that but not in the time frame available to them because they didn't have any infrastructure ready to go
Ashley pioneered this concept of the digital twin
Which is we want a digital point of a space shuttle
Any point in time by looking at the digital version
We know what's going on with the physical version it's a little hard to look at because it's
Ability to understand
I'm a little complicated here but the basic idea is to have a one-to-one counterpart so for a person that's unlevel
I suppose your digital twin is your social security number
So how could I go and connect elements to Beta
In elements of experience
Social Security Now
Now when we move
Into the industrial world
We ain't got you like I did your points to be conventional
Because when we try to augment
Information from the
Digital twin positive physical
Counterpart
We want to map it in 3D space as well
You know if I want to attach a gauge
To a motor on something about machine
I have to know where is the motor on that machine
And how does that change as I walk around the machine
Sit ups and down to Subway
Okay I guess the Internet of Things has a big debt to Nasser that we should
But not today
Because we are almost out of time so
Thank you so much
For coming on the podcast I'm a little chilled by the idea of my social security number
And all of the information I'm creating being attached to that but we'll have to work on some security associated with that
And
You know for people and then four
Devices
I know you guys are
Already
Adapt it 3D software and all of that so I look forward to seeing
Kind of how this plays out in the real world
But we'll be doing with our digital Twins and how that's going to change manufacturing you want to give us one quick example
Should I walk through a factory in there are many pieces of automation equipment in the factory from different vendors
And I point my phone at 1 after the next on the knees while I get a dashboard of
How productive that piece of Machinery is
How much you should say odd and what service needs it down
That's not move on to the next one
Can I get a whole different experience
Different piece of equipment from a different vendor and you know I'm going to factory filled with them
What is ability to interact
In a rich interactive way
One thing at a time
In a way that's
Specialized to that thing
Alex a very powerful exciting idea
Thank you so much for
Coming down the pike
Yeah thank you Stacey
And that concludes this week show
Thank you so much for listening and we'll see you next week