Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things show I have your house
Stacey Higginbotham and this is my co-host
Kevin coval
And
Let's see we have got a
Great show for you today but
Here's a quick note we are not going to talk about Apple because
The timing of Apple's event we consulted with Evan you know what they did
Didn't move the event I mean I don't understand
No we record on a Tuesday
And Wednesday is when Apple's holding their event and Thursday is when we do the podcast
So
Instead of us
Speculating and then being proven right or wrong
Probably wrong
We are just going to hold it till next week so
All your Apple news will be next week
And we will open at that time
I do hope that we see a lot of homekit stuff
I do too I have been talking to sources in
They also hope that
You never know what the last minute Apple
Has been known
The poor things so I'm hoping there's an update
And we see some realistic awesome cool things
We have been told that September and fall was the time frame for that so
Fingers crossed everyone
Is very intelligent and connected people familiar with the matter
Say that
They will be home
And it will be greatly in
Prove so
Next week
We have talked
Nothing but homekit is what we are
Nothing but home test
So all right
Onto the show
So let's get started with
Nest
Outages
It just happened it just happened last night that they before we are recording the show
And I was affected by a square
Because around 9 p.m. eastern time
On Monday evening the Labor Day holiday here in the US
Nobody could connect to their nest I was in my app and it's like just turned and turning and turning and then finally said
Can't do it
It turns out that
That's was aware there was a service outage
And me work on a fix for about 3 hours and
At midnight everything was bad
Which is great
And all
But
This really irks me Anna and I shouldn't complain he was like hey firstworldproblems you I could get out of bed to go downstairs to turn
Turn the air conditioning up over
I know life is tough
The point is
Is what I said for a long time
I worry about iot devices that rely solely on the cloud
I don't like them for this very reason that's why I went with that insteon system
And the Headless server
4 years ago 5 years ago now I'm in
It didn't matter if the
Cloud services went down because all of my rules
Everything was
Still available locally and things just worked
Hold on
Your Nest would still work if you got out of bed and touched the dial
Correct
Yes but that
Yes y'all can't do I just I want to make that clear
No you're absolutely right
Can the nest itself still work as a will call it a day
Old school manual thermostat
In the fact that you could still go up to it
Turn the temperature adjusted turn it off to whatever
It was the
Ability to access it remotely
Weather in new home or out of a home that was lost but the cloud service itself you couldn't
You couldn't remotely connect
To your nest from a nest app
See your dropped
Nope
So that that is a
Probably a bigger problem but I don't have a Dropcam so I was
Obviously not affected by that you're absolutely correct
Okay so I am and I wonder about the smoke alarms
The smoke alarms with still work
As a smoke alarm
Set a fire
They would still
Be back
But remote
Access Lake
Telling you like your batteries out or something like that I'm sure
Compromised
Agree
Again these are not
Major problem depressed back in the stone ages
It's just you know the promise of the cloud as being the
The bridge for all things IRT
It's just not a perfect scenario
And and
Extra dark me for the longest
Time cuz I'm like I kept saying is going to happen someday it's going to happen to be affected and boom it happen
And how were you affected
I had to go
All the way down stay I know I don't want to come
Beacon Grand scheme of things it's a small problem
I'm great but it speaks to the larger issue of ever so much Reliance on the cloud instead of
Having some type of hybrid type
Cloud / local systems for iot
It's true and actually with SmartThings their latest thing that just came out they actually put some local Intelligence on it for the
That exact reason
Because the cloud does fail sometimes
Seether
Massively like the nest systemwide outage or even just locally it's like
Your own personal internet camp
They relied on
Make sense
Witness
I'm trying to think they don't really have
Because of the way their system is designed
I'm not sure where they would put the brains because if you're thinking about having brains for a smart home system
You have to have a hug
The hover were server something that can still manage the devices in lieu of a cloud
With Google's new rap
And it's new fun weave and Brillo maybe they just pop that into
You know you pop Weaver Brillo into any sort of router and that becomes your hub
And they could talk
Yeah I mean I could see that and I like that idea as a secondary / backup system I don't want to sit here
And say I need to run a nest server in my house I don't want that
But I do want some
Physical device that have those rules that can take over
Freenas or whatever that product Maybe
When the cloud
System breaks down
Does any of those systems need some sort of
Basically you need like an arm cortex
Kind of chip in that
Because you
The microcontrollers that are inside like an aster any other kind of connected device probably isn't
Powerful enough to run the all
I think that's fair and I don't know that I want localized
Wheels and storage in
Intelligence in all of my
My actual devices I like the idea that you were talking about a hub or put it into a router or something
Where again
If the devices are peeing in their cloud services
Custom colors outage
Okay
Reba Harbor whatever the brain's is local branch as well that's a problem
I'm going to go to my localized rules now
And I'll keep peeing in the cloud when the car comes back we'll switch back over to the cloud service
So do that
The dreaded s word
So I like that
And while we're on the topic I should ask you
Speaking of the Google router
Did you
Perhaps
Purchase 100 the onhub yes yes yes
So I literally just before the show check to see if it was available in the PlayStore been checking on a pretty much a day
Basis
It has not been in stock
However
Also just before the show I check bestbuy.com and they do have them in stock at the normal 199
99 price
Could go to Amazon to buy an onhub but you
Pay 28999 right now because of the markup switches
Ridiculous
Don't do that people please don't do that
So I do have one coming cuz I just ordered it
It will be here I did not do expedited shipping soda be on Thursday when it's podcast was live which gives us something
Something to discuss next week
All right so hopefully we'll talk about
Homekit
So I did not because
Kevin is buying the router
I decided I did not
I want to buy the router
Nor did I buy the
So4
A few people who ask me who sent me emails like did you buy the handbag
Did you buy the router if the answer is Ibotta
That's a tough decision I feel you there
Handbags are very but it would have
Who's going to hold my
Not just any hair
If it was a connected handbag I think you would have had it
Spot someone did send me
Synthetic
Twitter
Perfect leave it behind your phone
Rings or something
I just need to bite the bullet and buy them
It was because
I've been leaving stuff left and right I need to put one of my water bong
You know what that's what I'm going to
That is what I
Tile
Those are the Bluetooth tags that remind you when you've left something behind for people who do not know
Yes there's a Bluetooth has and they actually recently just got an update so they actually have a louder alarm
And by golly
I need them
And best of all they don't rely on cloud services
Speaking of cloud service
Who actually
Posted something
On Google Plus which I saw because no one else
Like I told my hundred thousand plus followers over there
Miss Augusta
Wow a hundred thousand
Kevin you are the Lord of
Google play oh no no no other people
The far more important to me that has millions of
A followers of Arabic
You and Larry Page
Alright so
You said that
Google
Should buy if this then that
And I thought that was a really fun topic that we should we should talk about but first we should tell people what is 2
System that is
You want to do the honors
Oh no you do that because you are the IFTTT Queen
So is this and that is a web service
The basically connect
Your
It's actually any web service
To any other web service or any device
So using the
Programming language
If this happens
Then that happens
You can link things like
Your phone to your Dropbox
So if I take a picture
With my
IOS or Android phone
Then
Send that picture to Dropbox
Or it could be something as fun as
If the Cardinals score a point
Then my Hue Lights
Turn red
All of these are actual recipes that I've cream
Created using cannabis pen that
I have created in my time with
The service probably dozens of recipes
It's super fun
I recommend it to every
Because I almost when people ask me what it is I almost tell them
I don't know if you know what an API is butt
If this then that is almost like apis for dummies
Yes I would never use apis because I'm always
Trying to explain it
What's the weather like
They don't know what it is
Sure
Thank you this is why you should have explained
You did fine I just
YouTube
Okay
So that's what if
The shorthand for it
So yes
So that's the service and they also have something big
Do
Like two buttons
Hindus are
Like a single button that you press that make something happen
So on my phone I have one that turns off my bedside table light at connect to Hue
My Hue lamp on my bedside table and when I
Push that button
Hue lamp
Turn soft
I used to have one for my gigaohms slack Channel
Where I pressed it it said
Stacy is
Away from her desk
But I no longer have that because I no longer have
Mike Ditka
Slack Channel
Because there is no longer a gigaom that I work at
The do buttons kind of interesting because
It is an easy way to create one touch shortcuts for your recipes
Kappa button and whatever you want it to happen
And the nice thing is in this is what led me to my comment about Google should buy them is
They have brought the two button they being if this then that
Hey Brother Dubai
To Google's Android Wear watches
So now you've got Quick One Touch shortcuts
For whatever
Recipes and things do you setup
And some of the examples that the if this then that team
Provide adjusted
Illustrate this
With a three-button you can
Free sample set your nest thermostat to the perfect temperature
Assuming a services
You can block off an hour or next hours busy in Google Calendar so nobody will
You know bother you a notification to come in
Don't download the slack bit you could ask Ali some slack if they want coffee
To the pre-programmed buttons
Made by software and
And if this then that recipes
My neighbor watches perfect for the
I just thought it was a
Really really smart
Place to put the seasoning on the home screen of your smartphone is good to of course but
The more I thought about it like you know
We're past the point where smartphones are just
You know
Functional connected devices where we going to have to go do something and then we're. Never going to another app would do somewhere.
We want these things to start reacting to our knees we want these things to just
Do more
And yet we don't want the complexity of having to program them to do more
It's really not complexed to do that with the do but I don't like Google
What huge opportunity you have right here too
To advance the smartphone by integrating if this then that right
Into Android natively
Exactly it actually in talking to Linden Tibbets who is the CEO of Lyft
He actually wants to do
Dudududu
He wants to integrate the do button into apps
So
It's very easy
To like
Right now with
Android
I think Android and iOS
It actually there's a do for photos
Can I do for nose
So when you take a photo
You have a dual button that will automatically like
When you take a photo it automatically does something with the photo so you
You hit the button
It automatically like sends it to Dropbox are automatically
Posted
So that kind of like again what button
Support that you can build
Is so
Easy and powerful and customizable
If you can imagine that
All over your phone
With anything that you any app
That you use
Enough
That's awesome
I mean it really is and
They have over a hundred
60 Channel Park
And they span the web
The crossover the physical devices
It is nuts
I love it
Horse of the echo
It works with the echo although
The triggers are a little limited there and the triggers are limited on
All of the things
But
When you think of companies like
Google would be great because they're open
Like apple could also buy it and then just
Shut it down
Only use it with that
Ecosystem kind of like Appleton
Testflight right
How do you say
So
Facebook would be another good
Fire actually
Because Facebook's really trying to
Control the mobile lab and build out this amazing walled-garden kind of
Really fast Speedy web services
So I could see Facebook being a
A good buyer for
I don't know but I really think
And of course you know
Is the synapse
It's a really undervalued service and maybe it's because there's not a lot of people using it
But I think thinking about it as a
As a service with users as opposed to thinking about it is this amazing back end
For the next generation of Lake
I guess like this
Underpinning or service that underpins the entire mobile web is like a better way
Think about it
I completely agree I mean
We talked about if this then that
Many times before but
It still
To the mainstream person I think it's still very esoteric I don't think
It's very commonly known
And yet it provides tremendous value with such little investment
And that's why I'd like to see is you said that you know
Focused on non-users
And I think I'm going to go could really push that
You know there's lots of other potential buyers as you said
Where would be a good fit
Right now I think the best it would be Android Google Android
Already
So
There we go
Just sold off if the
This and that
And if you haven't tried it
Please
Go try it because
I guarantee you like even my even my daughter and I we have
It's just addictive
Yeah we get commission if I do Byron
Yes
Speakers
There's so many things
For sale
I do think they actually have
I'm alright
Let's eat before we go we should probably talk a little bit about some Enterprise news
Is that is worth talking about which is last week at FIFA
Which is like
Who is it like the CES of Europe
Yeah it's actually bigger than CES if I'm not mistaken it's like the largest type trait event and that kind in the world
Impute
So arm and IBM
Announced
A partnership
They actually have had a partnership for a while
They just basically took it alot.
Deeper and then IBM also announced
Tweaks and addons
You know IBM is very good it like
Basically
Taking news that it's already announced in in
Adding a little bit of
Some extra tweet
Jason Phillips Twitter
Now I'm going to make it to
And put out another press release
So
Basically what what they did is
IBM has a
Take back in Cloud product foundations
And it's part of it
Bluematrix
Cloud
Product
What this is is
You basically send all of your iot connected
Device information
Up there
Data analytics
Scott device
Management
Compliance kind of stuff all the stuff you basically need to like
Have all this device stayed in
And what arm has done
Is they taking their mbed OS which is
A real time operating system for their
Microcontrollers
And any other kind of
Arm-based microcontroller
And the connected the two
With a line of code or two
You can basically connect
Anything running
Mbed OS
IBM's
Iot Foundation
It's basically an easy way to connect any device
Tybee
And
That is important
Because
Well I'm thinking Analytics
Python thinking big data analytics because that's where IBM is really pushing the boundaries these days you know what the
Watson platform for example
And I don't know the details of their IRT foundations Cloud product but I'm guessing that
It has to do a lot with
Reviewing all the data coming in from these devices
Safe place because you know you don't want all this data going
Any place like just any old cloud
It runs on spark
Which is
The real-time processing engine
You guys came up
It's not enough
I mean you could send it over to Watson if you wanted to
But it's a secure place to analyze all this data
And basically it's it's kind of like idiot
So if you're like the VP
Are the CTO of a company that's like making washing machines in here like hey we got a really get a connected
Washing machine
This is an easy way to say
I've got a bunch of arm-based chips and sensors
I need to put those in my washing machine
I need an easy way to get all of that data from Those sensors
Open to a secure cloud
And you know
Nobody gets fired for buying IBM
I'm going to send it on IBM's cloud
This is an easy way to do
And that's what this is
And it's not a way to like build a connected manufacturing center operation you know this isn't this isn't like
I'm sure IBM has products for that
But this is just a simple way to get your products connected
If you're like a big name company that
It doesn't want to spend a lot of time Reinventing the wheel when it
Most of the Internet of Things a building
Nectar product
I think
IBM among others are obviously
IBM is really well positioned here
You know provide
Device intelligence
And similar data and analytics to these device makers
Which will eventually hopefully make them smarter
I can't say I'm surprised by this
I know this is a long time coming now there are startups in the space there's companies like Ayla Networks
Venture-backed startup there's also electric it is kind of in the space they provide a
Cloud services well
They're older companies like
Exata
It was
Papaya PTC
They're a little bit different
But the offering sound a bit
The same
And the other thing to note is that this is using arms mbed OS
Prior to this most
Companies that you buy microcontrollers from they usually have their own proprietary operating systems
And
Arms mbed OS was introduced last year
Around this time
Two kind of
Cuz defragment that market would be a way to think about it
Are Bandit will become publicly available
Arm told me that it would become publicly available at Tech con this year which is in November
So we are all waiting for the
The public version right now it's in a beta version that you can download and play with
So
That is that is kind of this is a little bit more enterprising but it's
It's really important
So
This is this is kind of like IBM's big play here and it's not exclusive
Armor work with other clouds
Will work with other artists
So
Keep an eye out here
Pretty big deal
For both of these
And that
It's kind of the big enterprisenews there
I think we should probably skip ahead to our
Guessed which this week is Michael Wolff
He is actually a former colleague of ours
And he is an analyst
She hosts a podcast
And he is also hosting a smart Kitchen Summit so I asked him to come talk about
The connected kitchen and specifically
Tiny bit of news that we heard
When we learn that Amazon was firing a lot of Hardware people which is that it has a secret project called cabinet
Lab126
It is a
Connected kitchen
So
Stay tuned to learn more about Amazon smart kitchen goals and actually just a bunch of really
Cool connected Kitchen products
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today I have breath
A special guest
Is another podcast host
This is Michael Wolff who is the host of The Smart Home Show
So you guys should check that out if you enjoy it
She's also a chief analyst at
Next mark
He is
Really really super smart when it comes to
The smart home and actually other things
Hey Mike are you doing
I'm doing great so good to be on the show I'm a fan of the show I'm a fan of Stacy
I've been I've known you for five years now
We should let people know we work together again
Yeah we
We used to
Supposed to just like randomly meeting under a bridge somewhere
Yes we used to work together at giga
And before that
Man I used to call you like
Like a decade ago about like when you were at like ABI research
Like I interviewed you about like
Bluetooth
I don't know if you remember that
At this point have gray hair and I've been falling asleep way too long
So there's a few of us have been fun the stuff forever I'm one of them
Yasso
We're old but we're not bitter
We're excited we're friendly
At that
That's why we're so late Jazz to be here and talking about
Smart
Kitchen
I'm just going to warn everybody listening right now
About a month ago you guys may remember I had a shift on the show talking
About connected ovens and connected
Cooking and
If you guys aren't into that thing
He might not be excited about the show cuz we are going to talk about
Same sort of topic again
But this time with the attitudes hook
Amazon
And its plans for something called
Cabinet
Mike
What do we know
Well we know that Amazon like to spell Cameron with a k
Like the Kardashians
Yes
And this is something that showed up in an article I Believe In The Wall Street Journal and it was almost an afterthought
It was an article about
How Amazon lab126 which is their hard work group for all the things like Amazon Fire
The Fire Phone excetera
It was about
The main focus of the articles about how they were laying off a big chunk of
The people who are
Responsible for the fire phone cuz that by and large
Interfire funny Crash and Burn
But apparently there's there's something else are working on called the cabinet which is
Called an article is called a smart kitchen computer or kitchen
And what's that
It got me to thinking about what this thing could be
So I wrote a post about it for Forbes
As well as my own
Am I on block and
That's what I would like to talk about me or just speculating about what exactly a kitchen computer from Amazon could be
I don't kiss like what I saw that
You actually were the first person I thought of
In Seattle maybe has
Snooze other lab 100
She's not in
Seattle
But
When I think of Amazon in their kitchen computer I actually think of the Amazon Echo
Which
It's actually on my kitchen counter
And we used to control
To me it's like our our calendar it is our question answer it turns on her lights and does all her stuff downstairs so that
Let me Hazard kitchen computer at orders
Keep track of my to-do list to my grocery list so I'm like
What on Earth would my
Kitchen computer actually do
What else
Do I need to do and you
You have some ideas around kind of
Shopping list and even kind of thinking about food prepping recipes
But I thought we're kind of
I don't know
Crazy
Dare I say crazy
Well yeah I'm the crazy analyst and that's my job could come up with crazy ideas and you know what's interesting in your comparison to that Co is it
It actually sounded a lot like an echo
You have to kind of just quote that article basically says
The cabinet will be designed to serve as a hub
Birth internet-connected home
And take voice commands for tasik ordering merchandise from Amazon
Well guess what
Can't you do that with Amazon Echo
So I thought well maybe it's a suit of echo or they're going to do something more
With all these different efforts that they have
I also think that they'll have a screen on
I mean one of the things that that go doesn't have it it's largely a headless devices it's kind of almost mint act like a router in a sense
Even though it is a kind of voice interface
Birthday quotes
Kitchen computer
You probably want a touch screen
Inability to bring up recipes in kind of Explorer
The world of food Audible
I think that's one of the aspects of it I think we'll have that differentiates it
From the Amazon Echo
Okay so is screen I totally agree
Cuz I I will say that I kind of wish I could
Fling myrecipes onto a screen
Not onto my echo but I wish my echo could actually read recipes
Is to me
As I'm cooking and kind of slow them down for me
Psychedelic
Hey
I want to say it too loud so people's Echoes don't wake up but
What's next in my process
And she could say you know add to
Splenda sugar
But the other thing that I thought was really cool that you had had in there was that it would likely use the dash replenishment
Service
And I'm not a huge fan of Amazon's Dash buttons that you
Press the button and it automatically orders
One thing for you
But I do like this idea of having
Replenishment service that automatically detects when you're out of things
In order stuff
So
Let's talk about how something like that might
Yeah you know I think that I shall be called maybe a dashboard
Sorry that's terrible
But I can imagine
It being a central
Clearinghouse for different types of Amazon Dash
Replenishment Services I mean I think
MLB step back in what
Maybe look at what Amazon division for the homies with with Dash is
They want to basic automate reordering for all the consumables
Any Kitchen & Beyond
And
You're the problem is with a button
I know you and I probably don't want a lot of these different
Glue on button
13B sitting at War
And if you start to integrate Dash which is the bigger Vision I think with Amazon Dash replenishment Services integrating Dash into all these different
Appliances
How do you get a controller if it's if you have one device from Whirlpool you have another from LG
And you have something from Samsung
How you going to
You all know someone that well you could use a nap
I mean that that's probably like the the lower
Friction round may be the easy around just have a dash app that kind of symbolizes all this
But you know Amazon probably wants to
Go even further than and I think that what the kitchen computer it could be a physical manifestation
Become a physical device that manages all that
And so it'll incorporate
Trucks and all these different devices
Don't have features in the end
Dashboards that allows you to kind of monitor everything you've ordered
I think it's just one asked
Spectra that I think we never seen one
Okay
Now I wonder if it would be
Similar are you familiar with the Haiku device
Yes I am
The Sea of hikers coming to my event
That's excellent
You are either my friend will talk about yours
So
Haikyuu is kind of a meld of like the
The shopping list
On the echo
And
Maybe the dash replenishment service cuz
The shopping list
It's just
I give it a list right I say
Add wrapping paper at milk
It does that in the app nothing else happens
Haiku has these kind of fun Partnerships with
They're mostly high-end grocery stores in other
Countries
Even understand they're going to happen here
But I'd say add milk
To a haiku if I were in France or the UK
It would actually add milk to my list and it also
Conveys that order to
A grocery store
And then I can either go pick it up later in the week or it will be delivered to
Incel
If you think about that
As a replenishment service is supposed to be like
Having a special container that has a sensor on it that automatically lets Amazon know that I'm out of milk
This is a perishable
What's a terrible example
Changes to dog food
That kind of gets
Interesting
I'm sorry Rob I probably just
Killed your business
So I don't know that was another one of your kind
Cabinet ideas
And then
You talk about this idea of
Cabinet bingo
Physical manifestation of the
The kitchen operating
Which sounds terrible and he said it sounded like a call to Arms
Jang
What the heck is
Why does my kitchen need an OS what is
What is that going to
Ten-tails I wanted to
Get some thoughts for me
Why I think that there are a number of like startups in this goes beyond Amazon who are creating Point devices
And I think the initial reaction to
Some of these devices be these know these connected scales
These are the things
Maybe can't connect into these different
White goods is
The white Canary Factor saywell
This is great but what's happened
Kind of work together
Rather something that plugs into I think
Be looking with orange Jeff is trying to do I think there may be moving down that path as well
I think you know haikus interesting Haiku to me is more like an arms Merchant that can be a competitor to everyone who isn't Amazon
But I just think it
Rather than having a bunch of different things that don't work together
Amazon what's going to be the central point with all these different things in the kitchen were together and so
Dwayne leave the foundation with this kind of the services and they pii
With Dash
I'm with Amazon Fresh
And in some of these other rappers so I can Alexa which is going to be the voice interface for these
If you can bring those are all together into one device
And then they'd go out to do Partnerships with all these Wicked manufacturers as well as
Are some of the the brand so if you look at the dash button
That's very much a strategic rollout in the chosen some of the biggest
Consumable manufacturers in the World rides on YouTube
Whoever those are Johnson & Johnson Coca-Cola
Those are very strategic partner so
I think they're giving a taste of what a dash embedded world can feel like with a dash button
To these Brands and I think they're going to reel them in hopefully over time we secure Amazon
And say when we have the speaker Vision we're going at this kitchen computer
Do you want the service in this Replacement Service hooked into your you're
Is your brand
And I'm sure the water can be rented a two-story I mean that's I'm sure it wake what their vision is to relay these this kind of brand attitude
Dbrand
Register I think that rather than having all the stuff piecemeal they want to bring it together in one unit
So I'm picturing I like
So cuz I couldn't break up the kitchen
The Kitchen Story into
Maybe it's not a story
Maybe it's my task
I break them up into planning
Prep
Cooking
Consumption
So on the planning side of got my kind of
Recipe apps
My Pratt I got things like the drop kitchen scale orange Chef the countertop
Kind of stuff
Cook at the June
I got whatever other kind of
Cooking devices there are
And then consumption I got things
They even go so far as like
MyFitnessPal in
Even things like health kit with my data
So on top of all that
I'm trying to think of the things that need to run across all of that
Photos of ruined storage
I'm going to take you to one of things you have is like
Obviously refrigerators you have other guys were making
Smart containers
I'm that I think are interesting
I think I want somewhere in there you slide in
Replenishment in in purchasing
Which I think is
Maybe I won't go into consumption but
I think Amazon sticking all the way from
I have this need for consumables I have this
Planning process I do for cooking
I have is consumption around
Food and I are going to the impacts of Health excetera
I have a storage of it
And if you could tie all those together at thinks that's the big vision
Got it okay
And I think what size hose together is data around food right nutrition
Recipes are kind of a way
Today the the recipe is almost the OS rate
But that's not digitized in a way that's that's friendly
Nitrate in food is not digital so
Okay this is fine I'm thinking about this
And we'll be able to think about it more because you have this kind of fun show coming up November 5th in Seattle it is the
Smart kitchen
Summit
That's going to say show but it's the smart Kitchen Summit
It is a see if we can find information about it
At
Kitchen summit.com
Excellent domain right there
Thank you
So and I think you did you have a discount for a readers
I did
Coyote Pawn
Is the discount code to get a 15% discount
Awesome
And you got some great speakers there
You got the president of Williams-Sonoma coming you've got
Brock from Haiku you've got people from June
You got me I'm coming
Let's see who else is probably the most exciting part for me
It is just one of those I can't wait to see you and you see Chris
Chris Albrecht our friends can be Dempsey
There you go but you got actually some grape me follow you got Jardin
I'm someone from Jordan who makes
The Crock-Pot
The connected crock pot
I'm going to ask him about my refrigerator Crock-Pot I've spoken to them before about this they are still not making it
Must not be a good idea
I don't know why
But why we are on this topic I would love to ask
What are some of the kind of
Other companies
That we should be excited about
In the smart kitchen
Where should I be looking for good ideas I know that there is some startups making these Point devices that we kind of talked about that
Who else is thinking big about this
Well I would say that you know I made this comparison
The people to come and show them what where my thinking is I mean when you look at 10 years ago we're all excited about the reinvention of the television
And yeah we're just at the end of the beginning of this revolution that has unfolded
Before I sold last decade were
10 years goes all through cable box
But we knew if we can get internet to the TV it was a massive potential
Opportunity for disruption yashow market is 50 billion dollars
10 years later looking at where where are Netflix is is the largest
Pay TV provider in the US
You all this conversation about disrupting the television I think we're at that phase right now
When we were ten years ago it with TV were right there with food
And
As I said if people knew everyone needs
The food in the grocery in the restaurant business in
And then just that total Market is a much bigger Market probably
Exponentially bigger than TV
I think it's really exciting in
You could just go along all these different pockets of innovation I mean there's a lot of interesting stuff that people put up like the scales except for butt
I'll give you one example, that really is exciting is coming hotel for you
And
Their copy that
Is trying to reinvent something that's been
People been doing what are the same way for a thousand years
Witches Brew tea
You know I love t
But it is the most simple thing you could do
Drop a bag of tea in hot water and how can you change that and that was very skeptical before I talk to him and so
Ponytail you say you you have t you love but you can only drink it before 5 cuz otherwise you're going to be up all night
What's a for you to say well I want to do a nighttime Brew this tea
And I want to reduce the amount of caffeine I can do those turn this knob
Oh by the way I really think an antioxidants are healthy
I'm getting to that age where I think it's going to be to make me live longer what's turn up the antioxidants and you could do all this with the tip for a bird
You can just change
It ended kind of make it taste of Indian accent
Kind of turnips in accents and notes
And that to me for I have been diving to the world
Politely and there is a massive Community there's like T conferences and there's just these team through this and I think you start telling about this
Tell me some people are skeptical
But I think there was some people be really excited about
I think that's one really kind of interesting example of a
A company is trying to reinvent something
Done the same way forever
No I'm
I'm sitting here thinking about that I'm like okay
Yeah change the way I brew tea
Some people will argue that that is
Just kind of mechanizing a process that maybe doesn't need to be mechanized
I guess
This is an area where you see a lot of gimmicks
Like
To meet cooking is something that has
Is fundamentally unchanged a lot of ways
Because you know you heat something over a fire
Like thousands of years we
Bend Heating
Chopping things up in the various Cuts or bits and
Eating them over virus
The way we heat them
Dictates how they end up tasting
So
Fundamentally that hasn't changed
And a lot of
Cooking
In devices and Innovations in cooking have been based around gimmicks like
You know a lot of people have like
George Foreman grills or
Exodus
You know we've all seen the
What is that thing that makes you look the connecting meat thermometer so it goes like
You know adding Wi-Fi Bluetooth on something in and kind of making that a device
I agree is a gimmick
List that actually a connection thermometer can be really helpful especially if it's a cure
But I was thinking like maybe vessel like a
Something is something that
You don't like
$200 glass
Spec tells you what you're drinking or how many
Glasses of water
I would argue in a
That is something that has been in a widely pan
I'm ask you something
Someone that finds that really intrigued
AYSO
You know sure you can look on the can of Stephen Colbert said and see what's in it but what if you're someone has like a very specific dietary need
I'm yet you know you were some of that really needs to closely monitor while you're taking in over the course of a week or or course of the month
That is very hard to do just by trying to transcribe what you're drinking
As you go Adventure some of the travel so if you had something like this that can
Do that I think that's
That's usually viable
I am
Technology
Right not against at and I'm actually really excited about passive data collection
I am panicking that idea because they're very opaque about how they do
Writing whether or not it's
It's whether or not they're their molecular sensor Works anyone thinks it's interesting to them about them as they have
A weight sensor is awesome at Mach or sensor with the big
I guess mystery box
Kind of the unknown is how the moisture sensor work
But I think of it does work whether or not it's not them if someone else can get that I think I Choose You diable
I think that is valuable I don't know if it's necessarily
Consumer technology at the beach
But yes yes I'm not against
That I'm
Market device
Yeah I think most of these Technologies are not consumer technology since beginning their they're like rich people technology for the 1st
3 years and look at the June of it right I mean
You're talking about $1,500 for a basically what
Looks like a toaster oven
It's much more complicated
Getting that now but it's something that is a size 1
But that is something that is not going to be Mass Market
But let's go to the Next Generation to the Next Generation
Another example is the peak of a right to the peekaboo is a 15 or $2,000 device
It's still fairly big in my wife
Laughs at me when I say I want a peek a brew my house
A kiss is still big
What you should tell us what a
What is a peekaboo so picobrew is a home
Beer brewing Appliance
And it's their basic taking
Iot technology in applying and applying to science to beer
What's interesting about what's a step back about you know kind of that the product Evolution forbid
What's interesting about that is
No home brewing is something that is widely variable people have been doing it for a long time they're enthusiastic but one batch of the next
You can't really make it
You can't really say with any degree of certainty is going to taste the same
And if I give my my buddy my recipe in Austin
I sent it over the internet
Chances are that he can to the same
Unless you replicate it
Using technology like this and there's no there's a technology called beer XML
So you talked to him about this kind of the idea of data which is really interesting there's actually data and kind of Frameworks around getting beer recipes
Shirley Rodriguez KO up to like
Brewery size beer
Brewing down to Lake
Half a gallon
And you could just scaled up or down so I think applying technology like that is really interesting
And it does something that
I've never really been done before and this other guys like we're about as well
You haven't really been able to brew in the home
Cost effectively using technology in replicating really good recipes
Until now
Okay
It's like a b r o s
Abuse abuse schema
I got your schema there we go
That's awesome
And I can't wait are the picobrew guys going
They're going to be there and I'm trying to get them to bring a lot of beer
Golf Course
Pico in and of itself implies small so not as small as Nano
Or maybe that's smaller
Nano Brewing
I don't know what to do between man on Pico both imply small but
Anything compared to Lake
Sierra Nevada small
But enough probably to Philly give us give us a nice Buzz
I don't know actually I can
I will save my bravado for another
Another beverage
Okay
I think we're out of time
But I'm really enjoying this
So I cannot
Wait
Visit your conference and before we go I want to get you
Really fast
Big trends give me
Listen to big trends that we should be watching for
In the kitchen
I think this is an overused term democratization of technology that was really only used in professional kitchens
Is coming to the consumer Market example that is
Is the others two or three connected to beat makers
Recipe makers in general whether or not they're connected that's something that really didn't exist
3-4 years ago
Brick and Timber prices
I use one
I'm making better steak I've ever met before I can make I made pudding with it
Stacy we haven't tried when you try to destroy fun
Oh you're inviting me to
I'll make funny. My suvee cooker
And I think this year you alluded to that kind of the fusing of
Appdata in cooking
I think you know this idea of taking healthkit
Data
I'm in in August of really understand where you are in Ark
In our day in our hour
And more long-term
Having that feed into what we buy and feed ourselves at I think it's going to be really important I don't think anyone's really crack that
I think Apple's trying to lay some Foundation but I think that'll be a really interesting Trend watch would like to see big Brands actually start to push
Nutritional data
Their data
Actually
To Consumers I would like to see them get on board
Maybe through apis and starting to release some of that a little bit
So I'm not the one laborious Lee
Typing all this into my app
I have my app crashes
Do it again
So that's my hoe
The big Brands will start to realize that there's a lot of value and there's probably even some advertising opportunity
Actually there
So we'll see
Mike
Thank you so much for coming on the show I cannot wait to see you
November 5th
In Seattle at the smart
Kitchen Summit
And
Thanks for coming on the show
We'll see if we ever see the cabinet what are the odds
You know I know that Amazon has
Done
Projects that they kill
And I'll talk to books have been behind some of the projects and then never made the light of day
I have a feeling this year if I were to put odds on a Sprite no over 50% will see something
But who knows it could be something that is playing with and they kill it
All right
Everyone thank you so much for listening and we will see you next week