Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Kevin tofel
Show for you today
Stuff
Like Amazon Echo smart home staging kit
Youth fitness trackers everywhere
Restart a new ecobee at the FCC and our guest this week
Is gilad Mera
Who is the CEO of Nora and we're talking about
Two things artificial intelligence and building a data repository and how to keep it secure
The new model for securing a personal data
Cool
It is cool but first
A word from our sponsor
Looking for an edge in your iot design
Get exclusive access to design strategies methodologies and tools for Leading Edge iot devices
By attending this year's arm techcon in Santa Clara California
I'm expert in ecosystem Partners will be on hand to Showcase their latest Technologies and answer your most pressing question
Attendees get access to nine technical tracks arm technology training
Expert Keynotes and two days of exhibits Advance registration ends October 14th armtec
Khan.com
Don't miss arm techcon October 25th through 27th
And now we are
Bat with our show
So Kevin
Pottery has stopped
To talk about today
Waterbury
Cornucopia cornucopia
Show me all the stuff
What should we
We
You haven't talked about the Amazon Echo in a bit and I think we should because there's rumors of a new music service
And this is odd to me
Specific to the echo devices
Yeah I thought this was
Crazy whack
Especially because just a few weeks ago the echo was like you know what
Do you want to switch from the default being the Amazon
Prime music
How do you say it
Yeah you can switch to I think it was to
Noah's Pandora or Spotify
Azure default switch I probably did because we use Spotify
And that has changed our life
Better
Well that's important
Not.
Huge significant ways
My life is changed forever
Better
Decide by.
Yeah I kind of like
Is Amazon thinking here is it that
Necessary could you just make prom better I'm spending $100 a month on
Yeah it's it is kind of strange man Amazon is known for trying different things and different models or
Different takes on existing models of services so
So the newspaper folks who might not have heard the word from my country code
Sex yeah they they got information says Amazon facility cheaper music subscription service
Which is fine never disclosed a cheaper music that's great but it's only going to work on the
Echo devices and
That's kind of weird because you've already got as you said Amazon Prime music which is what I do use with my echo pretty much all day
Long when I'm at home
And I have the the echo Dot and the dash
Different places for different use cases
And I'm happy with that I'm a Prime member obviously so pay my 99 bucks and
Taking full advantage of it
But the deal here is it Amazon made do they second service that is going to
Cost either for $5 per month
And again it would be limited to
B
Amazon Echo devices
And I'm not sure I get that why would you
I want you close
Service not wear at a headache low service is probably better way to say it is opposed to you know using the more open service
Because
Prime music you can use on pretty much anything he's on my iOS devices my Android devices and obviously my echo devices so
I don't know everything
It just seems odd to me and I don't know that I'm going to pay an extra five bucks
If I'm already a Prime member music and am happy Prime music
Which I pretty much am for my purposes
Taipei
$10 a month
Spotify
Because they change the default now
It's so easy like it was kind of a pain to be like
Play Kanye West
Amazing on
Spotify
But
The other thing that's weird is
Spotify for me
And some of these other services that people can subscribe to
They go after
Sprite and
Delimitation
And it's also like the only thing I can think of is you Spotify doesn't have a huge heart
So
If your Amazon and you want to work a deal with music companies to get more music cuz right now not
It's not a huge
Selection of like you are songs or esoteric songs on correct correct
These are like
You want to do this you want to make a reasonable here's how we're constructionists and they're going to have to acquiesce to
Give people more variety in these are people who may not be technically Savvy or interested in survival
And that makes sense except for one thing Prime music I already have the Amazon Prime music
Service
Is that the only Subscription Service have for music now I'm drawing a blank
I think so so
Instead of coming out with a Prime music that has more than the million or two million tracks that are currently Veil
Mobile for free included with Amazon Prime
This is their play to
Have a broad
Basic music
Available for subscription
What time
And it's fine
But why Limited
So
If their focus is on getting people to buy the echo
And use it for an into love it right because when you start streaming music
I feel like all this just has a timer
But if you're like hey for five bucks a month you also get all the music
Yeah
No no that make sense
That makes sense
And as you were saying that I was double-checking myself there is a pair of there is no
Add on Prime music subscription that's just
You have Prime music with Amazon Prime
Or you don't
So this is they're taking maybe you're right maybe it is to sell more Echo devices and
As they get more of those devices in hand people will
Buy more things and use more Amazon services and really that's
Kind of their play so
Just
People who don't have Amazon Prime
I mean I'm trying to think of
They're obviously our people who don't pay $100 for Amazon Prime
And for those people
If you've got an echo
That's the question of how and we don't know
How many people have don't have Prime but do have an echo
Tumi
It's got to be a small amount of the overall
But this could be them trying to push out into the broader
I mean the echo is turned into
Even people who are not tech nerd so my friends who just don't even think about like smart light bulbs
I don't talk to those people and we talked to the text you want to be my friend you got to have a Smart Lipo
Belleville East
So
I don't know maybe I'll go hang out
Echo in Best Buy
I would be curious what they think because I'm struggling to see this as a
Big big
Play you're just seems really really limited and I'm not sure I understand it yet
Everybody
Building a
Schedule for the
Between 3 and 4 million is kind of thought process and then imagine the overlap between
Has like certain connected devices
You know it's probably
They won't want to leave money on the table if they can pick up a
Relatively small percentage it's still a lot of people
So it would add up so
I was going to say so
I'm super intrigued by
The smart staging kit for selling your house
I want to know because you just sold your house
How you feel about this so what this is is Coldwell Banker the real estate firm
Has teamed up with Lucia
Yes
In August locks
To create basically a package to Stage your house
That includes an August lock
Which I'm sure the realtor would love to
Easier to go in and out
Two Lutron connected like light switches
+ + the affiliated
Pecos and whatnot plus a Lutron Bridge
And
Nest Thermostat one smoke detector in one drop kit
So
That's that's what's in here and it's basically the espresso the
Hold if you wanted to get everything if
1135.
Which is what I would probably cost you if you did it on your own
There's no like super discount here it's just there and then they also offer
Professional install of all of this for 500
Course they do
So I asked someone who just sold their home and I left my Nest behind but I took all of my
Hubs Bridges bulbs cameras Etc
I understand why Coldwell Banker is doing this
But I think you know they see an opportunity here
And I assume they're getting the the hardware at a discount so they're making some money there
But
When I hear home staging I think of
Renting stuff
But if your stage your home with furniture and pictures and all that
You don't buy it and it stays in the house
U-Rent It
And it's in there for the showings and then it goes away
This stays in the house if I understand correctly
You don't return it
I'm buying it
Right
SO2
If they're calling it staging which I think they're
Playing with the wording here cuz to me
Yeah this is just
Let's make your homework charger by turning into a smart home
With these products that you could do this all yourself
Santana
Kind of Mitt Romney idea
So
Baidu
We have down the street from a somebody built of 1 Point
Dream is a home is being sold for 1.3 million dollars
And
I'm looking at the listing for this home
I was
Struck by the fact that they are advertising all these smartphone feature so they've got like a MyQ garage door opener
That's like a hundred and $2,930 garage door thing right
High-end homes anyway
Those are the big selling point so it used to be
Advertising the granite countertops there like pushing is 1.3 million dollar home with idea that it's smart and has like a
Connect to garage door and I was kind of like
And that's because they're selling the feature to people who don't understand
This Market the iot market because
People who do know like you
Let's honor $30 garage door opener
Install that in French
My house did not list for a million and change but it had you know the nest and I could have
Don't let some other things in there and
Anybody can do this you can have a $100,000 house and have these things so
It's people who don't yet understand
The cost of these products they just see over the garage door can tell me when its open and then the camera
Tell me what time is the front door this is amazing
Well it is but it's also not
Matt expensive
So Coldwell Banker put out a survey
In response to this in the interview at 12
Again
Coldwell Banker sells real estate so it's important for you guys all to know their biases here
They asked some people about
How they Define move-in ready
And
44% said that the mood and ready home has Smart Home Technology already installed
45% said a move-in-ready homes new construction my husband the totally
These people must be in the south
But they also said
If two homes are exactly alike
Most Americans would choose the Smart Home
But they don't want to install the gear themselves
36% of us respondents believe that having smart technology is a major selling point when buying a home
But 32% said they would be scared to install by themselves
And I think the the demand numbers for that is only going to go up as you know younger people would be
Brought up in
Smartphone age
You know I'm leaving this house doesn't have a Nestor
And August lock or whatever you know
I think it's going to continue but I also hope
That
The public starts to better understand what the actual cost of these things are and the fact that
Many of them are not that difficult to install
Because they took pay a premium for house or example because it has these things
Doesn't make sense to me
Can I get myself on the cheap
You are
That's the kind way of Truth
Weather that we won't say
I understand understand
There's a second listen there's a sign of the population that
Doesn't want install doesn't want to know how these things work they just wanted their and they went to work
And they're willing to pay for it I get that I really do
Me too but I would hear seriously Stacy Higginbotham plug
You can install a Smart Lock even the August in like 15 minutes my daughter who was nine at the time helped me
Install it
You can swap out your switches that's a little scary because there is electricity
Especially in a home like a neutral wire so relatively new home
You can install the stuff
So easily and I encourage you
2 tribus super empowering
Now if you got two screaming kids you
Working all the time and you're like exhausted then
That may not be for you but
Try it it's awesome to be like these
I do again what Coldwell Banker is going for I still question the whole word staging but
You know what that's a marketing thing that up
Technical singing
That's their business so
I'm sure some people take advantage of it
The New York Times a couple weeks ago had a whole article on
Is staging really worth
So
We did not say to her mother
Okay and position is so it's like you know
Hey if you plan on moving
Maybe the better way to think of it as if you plan on moving
You know it's on your house or right
So
I will give them some Kudos though on the smart home staging. Com site which is where all this information is
They do say for sellers
What you sold your home
Here's how you should return Smart Home Products their factory default settings which is something I remember to do
When I left my house but it's easy to forget that if you're selling your house cuz you got a lot going on
I think that's really useful
I agree
There we go in at some point in time I'm going to have a realtor come on the show
And talk about
The investment
Solar panels do I can tell you that from experience
Southeast Pennsylvania
Okay let's talk about
Oh I don't know Kevin
I want to talk about this NFC ring because you like smart jewelry
Yasso
Back in June or July forget which I'll double-check right now to make sure I did it right
Visa it was June Visa announce an nfc-enabled payment ring
14 Visa sponsored athletes to use at the Rio Olympic Games and
Olympic games are over now
I'm so what happens all those Rings will they keep working obviously
Their little ceramic
Rings that look like a normal ring
And have an NFC chip
Inside at no power needed it's just using the electromagnetic fields of a
Point-of-sale terminal you put the ring
Are your hand over a 20syl terminal you can pay for stuff using your Visa card
Tell tokenize insecure in songs Airport
Apple pay Android pay Samsung pay Etc
The thing is there weren't just for the Olympic athletes we find out because you can go to
Nfcring.com
And
Purchase your powered by Visa smart ring so it's open to anybody now
I really like
Hey the look at these things
I'll be the price on a 50 bucks which isn't too too bad
And see the fact that you know it works with a very standardized system you know NFC and Beezus payment system so
I thought I was kind of neat don't know if you saw these at all that one looks just like my wedding ring for Crown but I can swap at my wedding ring cuz
I think I buy tungsten carbide ring now but I could replace you with a similar ceramic ring
I have NFC
I love the ideas
Sweetie
Replace our wedding band with
Best trust me that's no problem my wife just lost her second band
Power couple weeks ago and go to Amazon and get a wedding ring whenever she doesn't care
We're not like that
I want to
These are very mask
I will maybe that's why I like them more
So
Yeah they're 50 bucks there's one that's 60
They look nice
If you want to pay for things I feel like
They don't do much other than payment
They symbolize your love for Nobel paint
With have you tried to pay for something using NFC like an NFC product or a wallet
I got your phone without being asked to show ID
Yeah man
Okay I'm asking
Then you just say this
We don't even need your phone I don't think with this
Straight up NFL
Yeah I don't think you I don't think you need your
Your phone at all and it and to be honest it's also not just for payment so you can
Use that chip to unlock doors
Ketorolac supports that
You can share information through NFC
You can program it with that so there's there's more to it than just payments even
Yes and they actually have their cheapest one Kevin
You should only 525 and it has it
I like that it's like basically there
Prototype
Theaters
Just like
So
That's the Vintage model that makes sense
And you went did we ever think we would call NFC Rings vintage
So
I like the eclipse it's got that textured
Flip2it
Okay
So
Lychee
Next we should talk about
Ecobee
I got a notice on Twitter from
Dunk it
Who he is
He's a reporter at
Asteroid
So don't really know
What that is but
Public hello
Sent me
News that the FCC founded FCC filing
That says there's a new
And he's right because we check the FCC database
And it is the ecobee Lite
L i t e
Bike light bulb
Like
Light bulb
Sorry
No apology
Okay
So
This feeling
There's not much in the FCC database we know it works son but
2.4 gigahertz
And in the 900 megahertz range switch now that's it
Exactly so we were talking about this before the show were like what is he could be doing
IPhone get version
Maybe it's a sensor free version but then
It's got 900 megahertz support
Providence Support Center
What is it
So what is
What does ecobee light mean
We can't tell you
Rihanna
Because we don't know
I can't tell you
Stat ecobee recently took 35 million dollars from
The Amazon
PT's punch
Try not to say
She who shall not be named
So they're fun for the echo
And it's possible this could incorporate something like
Echo voice services
Right which means you wouldn't need to have an echo like I have an echo and I tell my echo to change the thermostat by voice and
And it does so
Maybe this is native
Voice services
And that makes me wonder Maybe
The touch screen is not a touch screen that it's only voice control and that would be the light part
Yeah and if that's true.
A cheaper car
I got to refurb unit off Amazon ecobee3 so I don't remember what the cost nowadays
How is your son
Okay
So I did find interesting the Globe and Mail wrote up
About ecobees funding
Time and day in their story mentioned some great shots that I thought were useful about a third of the
Users
Actually
Blink their devices to either homekit
Or the echo or SmartThings
So actually going to be a little bit higher
But that's okay
And ecobee has a 24% market share
According to NPD
So it's right behind nest
And that's in the Smart Home
So
And personally I like the ecobee
Three more than
Same here I left my Nest behind at the old home and then I put the eagle be in here and have a sensor here in my office so
And I'm getting too warm in the summertime on the second floor
Yay
So the point here is we don't know what is happening
But will keep you apprised
I'm going for no touch screen
Voice control online
And that would be great cuz that would be
That would have to have a cheaper product
Touch screens
Okay
Let's see what else do we want to
Kevin YouTube
We got two little car tickets we can talk about
Going to talk about
Delphi
Identify yes yes yes so they Delphi forces with mobileye to develop AC
Self-driving system
And mobileye if you are not familiar they are the folks that I believe Tesla works with for their
Automatic
Driving abilities yes
That's right yeah yeah yeah so so I guess what Delphi mobile I are planning to do is kind of created
An autonomous driving system
That any car maker could just
I want to say plug-and-play cuz there's more to it than that but essentially create that solution that will work with any car and car makers
Easily just purchased the driving system and install it
Enter there
Vehicles
Yes in his cars become
Computers
I think
The idea of
Creating these kabaddi parts for these modular parks
Computers went down and
Tremendously
Once we were like
Hey
A standardized on you know this kind of instruction sets osx86 let's standardized on
A graphics card slot in different buses
So if you think about
That's basically this model and I think it makes a lot of sense
So we'll see if
The carmaker's think so
Can I get a smart move
Anything else I got you
Notes for the next carpet
Connect Adobe
The plug-in module
These are devices
Every car made after 1996 has this slot below the steering wheel
Down there
You can plug in something to it and it's like on board diagnostics you can see date about the engine
Gas mileage all kinds of fun stuff
Automatic all of them
Have these products that can reduce data and give the data to your smartphone
So what automatic is done they have launched their second generation products which has
Cellular Bill Jen
And it's I believe 3-g cellular
And what it does is
Since that day. Not just to you over like when you get home
World connection
They also send now can send it wherever you are at
This is important for
People who like want to see the actual car locations of your parent
Or if your insurance firm
Discount space.
Which I do I have fun module plug into a two-door cars
Sweet
It really the most interesting thing for my perspective on this is that it
Doesn't have a data subscription
So there to whisper sink
And it only cost $30 more than the original
People who are like
What what
It's $100 for the
Anon 334b 3G
And
I'm wondering who's did a network they're using a money gesetz AT&T
But you're right AT&T is good for cars Verizon's been doing some really cool stuff though with
Connected
So
I don't know who funds them and that isn't
Really darn good question so
If we find out who let you guys know
We will find out it something time and
While we're on the subject
OBD ports and what not real quick
They're great for getting information but did you know that they're all so awesome for
Sending pushing information
So much as I have flashed the software of many Android devices in my time
I have flash the software of my car using the OBD
Yeah it's it's actually it's pretty common noun for 3rd party
Companies to create new engine mapping software that will boost your
Attorney Brewster turbo pressure boost the
The horsepower the torque and so on
All done through software and they push it through the OBD port
Huh
ECU engine control unit of the car which is also for bass
It's flash just like you flash a phone or tablet
Okay
Sorry I mean sorry the curveball
Listen to if this than that which is fine because then you can like
Kinds of other fun stuff
And if you ever want
Time time-wasting
That they do actually offer like their blogs sometimes has fun posts like where the most aggressive drivers
Yeah I program my list
Upstart
That's what why do you think I made my car faster
Kevin your number one
So
And be most aggressive people
On highways are actually in Phoenix
In case you were wondering
Also on City roads also in Phoenix
So
Yeah I believe it in there many times. Believe it
The chillest drive
I also believe that Seattle
I believe in Seattle to the Lord every time I drive in Seattle I'm like
Oh my gosh you people you're so polite and nice what it was
But in the rare aggressive driver
Just like totally Knock You Out
Where you coming from
All right
Well that is 25. For this week show
And we will see you
Next week
Kevin and I are but first
We're going to introduce Our Guest gilad
Mara
Who's the CEO of nura
They make a I don't know how to describe this thing they provide artificial intelligence
Two companies so
Based on data from your phone and other devices that
Already score their son
They also act as a day to reply
So
He doesn't much better job
Explaining this pretty complicated cast
Ai and data privacy you should definitely stay tuned
And now a word from our sponsor everyone it's Stacy breaking into
The iot podcast to tell you about an event in Seattle that is really going to be awesome are you interested in
How iot Tech will change the way we discover Shop store and cook our food
Then you won't want to miss the smart Kitchen Summit an event that explores the technology and design conversion stats
Changing how we
Eat by store in interact with our food
The smart Kitchen Summit is brought to you by my friend Michael Wolff of the smart home show
Am I just created a discount especially for listeners of our podcast
Just go to smart Kitchen Summit. Com
And use the code iot podcast
That's all one word
To get 10% off tickets
I'm going to be there and you should be there too so join me October 5th and 6th
In Seattle it maybe we can eat a 3D printed Pizza together
Hey everyone it's Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
I am here with Mary
Who is the CEO of nura
And we're going to talk about something everybody is super excited about
Artificial intelligence
Hello good
Hello Stacy thank you for having me
I am so glad
Taboo because I am super pumped about
How we make sense of all this data that's going to be coming in
So let's start off with
What you guys do so people can understand where you're coming from do you want to give me a quick 22nd view of Mara
What it is we do we understand
Human contact
In what we call the alternate to anything that's not working tonight we try to break down the avial and life into us
60 components
Then we allowed
Users to Shelby
Components for the environment
The environment can be response
A door lock can be sure it's locked after it realizes you fall asleep
Vulcan
An annotated realizes you're on your way home etcetera etcetera
Got it
All right now you guys first right now have an app
And I actually downloaded it and it was fun
It focuses mostly though on
Health right now today yes
To our product is an SDK
We do have an app that dap is used for
Maybe either testing
Assistant manager
I just want to make sure
How cold it is an ingredient
Sits inside
Good healthy products
And did these products and then ask
SDK questions
Good answer for example you want to know any other fell asleep you want to know any users on
Sweet home
When user is starting to run
And as a result of the answers we provide
Theater solution can change its Behavior
Sounds kind of worrisome as a user I'm like God I don't know if I want something that knows all of this information
Json about me
Telling other devices unless I let it
Festival you really need to understand
Lights out
If you believe that door lock that make sure it's is it is locked after you fall asleep is beneficial
And you would like to have this functionality
And the question is how
To make it
The most secure and safe
Convection
That you can possibly make
But I do agree this thing
We must convey
To the users is what is the upside they're getting
So can the music player
Bring me that special music when I'm running or
When I'm running this phone can stop at pushing noise notifications
Do not disturb me
And the car will realize they just finished a run
And cool down the car
Can all of this
Be beneficial to me and if so let me share these pieces of my life
With these Solutions so that they can personalize themselves
Alright,
How are people going to use this what is this going to look like
If your vision of the world comes to fruition
Believe again
Similar to the internet
And devices
Mobile experience
Lily personalized insult to our needs
So
I can't think of a chronic disease
Be connected with my diabetes results
Hypertension
And the answer is definitely yes
A glucometer today
Is this a sensory
Takes your blood glucose cut, cable
Overtime
What is the glucometer look in real life
The time I just
Woke up and I'm on my way out of the home
Now would be a good time to interject
MessYourself
I understand that I am about addictively to start a run
And I haven't measured myself
For the last 3 hours
Enso mattress
Advise me to eat an apple
Measurements
Now this glucometer
Changing the behavior to me versus to University or third person
And takes care of
And this can happen tomorrow
Technology
Make this
Happened to Momo
You can think of any type of medical
Solutionwhere
Example they want to provide you with Insight so today what's happening is
You have 6000 inside and they just throw some Matthew hoping that they would work
What is this solution realizes that I'm about sleeping so the inside tube
Potato to mining
Verses on my worst exercises
And so these inside need to be tailored to my niece
So now
Again you and me
Mike gets very very different
Experience
From this device
Solution
And so on and so forth I really believe
That the power of context of AI is relevant tomorrow and not necessarily
Innotech is from today
Awesome
This feels almost like magic so
Talk to me about
How this happens in
What do my devices need to know when how is the setup
It's important to realize that this
Interweb inter
It's nice if you and me
Clever wording to Google
Google try to understand what is it I mean when I say gift in you mean when you say gift in personalized results when you and me
Going to Amazon
Home page and why is that
Because
Amazon price to increase our conversion to make it more relevant to us
In what
I called the ultimate
Mobile experiences
In the experiences we're not there yet
Whole Space is much more today
I will stick to you like that will focus on Health and Wellness
And presently we work with a glucometer so think of a glucometer the tree lights
Feel about starting run
We are about to enter restaurant
And as a result
Advise you to admit to yourself or give you some insight on
Children shouldn't run
Aeromexico
Set a remind me to take that
Medication at 8 a.m.
Medisafe with another customer can remind you to take that medication before you leave home predictively or
Just after you wake up which for you might be 6 a.m. for me might be
10 a.m.
And so
Again
Little Things
That
Will take this opportunity
Into a a sweet same Evolution as the internet went through
Similarly
Will experience
Better engagement ring conversion better personalization
Okay
So many of these examples that you could have mentioned I see
One company that has the data in makes this change in their individual product
What's different about the Internet of Things is there
Lots of products and
We're trying to get them to work together so I'm curious if that changes how you build something
Solution to becoming a small solution you got all kinds of ways to do it
Some ways legal equal subject matter
Door locks in the oven
Whatever
Delightful
But some of them
Diesel 82
What is the human
Contacts
We talked about tomorrow call example typically what you say is
Talk about Entertainment System
Talk about telematics you talk about autonomous driving all of these
Ozone the car
Sleep deprived
Lights when you enter the car we just finished a run
You sweaty when you enter the car can impact
The car Behavior
Luck has nothing to do with the car
About understanding the person
Rental cars
Car playlist deep focus on what they do best
Which is their own device
In with we do
Philosophy we advocate for
Let's understand the human in a good holistic manner
And then
These understanding can benefit multiple facets
Standardization protocol play then
An action subject Methodist
Got it so then I would think that a company like Google
Or possibly even Amazon or Facebook that has a lot of information
About me is a
Person already
Might be a venom more powerful position to do this
You can bet the Google is not interested
To cool down my room
I did not why they buy Sims card company
They're interested in.
Odell doing building very proactive
To get this sort of what again what I called the outernet
Things are not Webbie
It's definitely
Specifically we feel
Technology
But the model by which we work which gives the user full transparency
Just think about
This amount of data
Is now being collected and aggregated around you
Anyone
Midlands action recipes Constantin very limited
Serve your needs
Which is not the Google Motorola
Old Amazon
Let's give you something free
And sell your life to a Nike phone ad
Okay so how does this how does this model work
How are you guys collecting all this data about me
Against the way we advocate for this new
Economy
Is to provide compelling
To the user
You want the door locked
HELOC after you.
Make it make sense for you to let the door lock know that you falling asleep
And in exchange
Get that value
The door being locked
You need to understand that
What doesn't need to get is the fact that you
Waking up or the fact that you are
Sleep Quality vs. Sleep Quality or how much time you sleeping are you sleeping next to
Interesting for the user
Let the door lock know if the door lock connect to just a Sleep Center
Then they get all of that
Type in to get the burden of only listening to a sensor or not
Utilizing algorithm
This is definitely the mother that we advocate
The way we do it then
Alcoa skillset is essentially algorithm we collect data from multiple channels app 200 channels
And we take all of that to put it into an agreement
Try to figure out what does this picture mean does it mean that use a fell asleep
In the falling asleep example
It can be anywhere from sensory activity like
Sleep sensing motion sensing
Mobile elements like
Is there lights
Are you charging
UPS to Patton Elementary this your home
This we typically sleep at
Have you home this is the time you color you typically fall asleep at the Tara Tara
Whatever we get would fit into very agile
Algorithm
Sin City 1 or 0
Okay
And then you sell your SDK and a company would say hey I want the results of this sleep data
Coolest I want to be today
Example when the user for the sleep wake up sore about to wake up predictive later.
As a result I'm going to change my
Solution
I'm going to
Turn off the lights
Lock the door reminder take a pill whatever
But again if you use all solution user
Must be involved
So the door lock will not come to dinner until he knew I want to know when
Stacey fell asleep
It would go to Stacy and say hey Stacy
I want to make sure the door is locked
After you fall asleep in exchange I ask that you would let me know
Understanding the value
Will approve the transaction
Got it
So
Where are we today with the deployment of
Will call at AI in the outer
I think it's the really initially think what you see is that
Fulton Health and Wellness
Received the spaces siloed some elements
Space amoeba world summer list
Examples most home today
People are still going to focus on the basics lollipop
When I tell you to lock u-lock
Michaela Conlin
That's it
If you can do that I'm good for now
In the space is not even there yet
In medical for example you have dozens of glaucoma till dozens of mobile apps
Today
And now they're seeking for that
Differentiate
Okay bye I can give you some basic lollipop position
And now let me
Personalize it like me
Hey make it more intuitive to you
It's very similar to the internet
Used to have
Dumb portal
One website fits all
Evolve evolve now
Your website
My website would not
The same lips that do not behave
2 Yuan to mean the same as
Are you concerned that when people think about AI
They still think of Skynet in the end of humanity
And I would love to get
Your response to that
Because
Do you feel like we're anywhere close should we be worried about this or are we still so far off
Technologically
Technologically I think
Even if you scrape the boundaries of
Psychology today understanding
Human behavior
Predicting human behavior
Extremely difficult
I do think that the way
That has been handled
Is
Something of concern and I think you see it
You see how the market this concert like
Coyotes not about what websites do I serve
Select my home systems my car system
Health Systems
I think we have an offer
Tunity
Two again change the rules of the game
But
Honestly think he is being utilized
As a buzzword
Trading
Expectations article
Not really easy
And I think we're potentially getting going to get hit by that
Because two three years from now experienced are going to get better but you not going to see any Terminators roaming the streets
That's good yes the Terminator probably shoot me
Before I got here
So you mentioned
That we have a chance to change the way we handle this data to me it feels like a lot of
But that horse is already out of the barn so I'm kind of curious
Why you say that
And how we can
Put the horse back in the barn
Craigslist in the internet
No one reads terms of agreement before they press I agree
That's again descent of the things
Also this one set of.
Goodwill not used to sharing
Even Samsung you see the de-emphasized privacy
Very much
And so the Google way of doing things is being challenged
Even Google itself is taking measures to
Increase transparency
The way I look at it is this is as follows I think you have enough companies
The don't deal with data
But I'll players in the Internet of Things by Samsung hblg Lenovo
Good movies to give you valium
You buy some
And they have an embedded incentive
Increase that value
Enhance add value
You asked
So
You have multiple players
Will at least appreciate
An alternative to the Google way of doing
If we can present them with this alternative that is technologically good
They will use that
So I think now is essentially a race
Network effect Weber can get
What's a good AIC
Technology to enough hands
I will set the tone
Oh my gosh that's a huge burden for consumers because they don't
They may not understand the terms and
What is even going on here
I mean people are just as freaked out about Samsung televisions that are unicorn quote always listening
As they are about you know
Google
CM Nest thermostat in their house so
How to communicate that to the end user
I agree with you completely
Anythink
Against a lot of
Incentive to
Not make the screen still in to the user
This is why you have 50 days
Signs of a gay man that no one reads
And you expected to sign to get whatever a Gmail
And I do think you know
Christmas
Experience
Did the Fiasco that happened so far for example the Samsung TV
Something that it has
Card Samsung
Significant
They are actively seeking
I mean that's a perfect example of
A company realizing
Get this done wrong
Klein
Very profusely to change that
I honestly think
Consumer loan will not be able
She was at movement
You need both the demand side and the supply-side realizing that there is a business model
You're not being a spy
Letting being
A villi
Diligent with how you handled that there is money to be made in Gotti to be
All right I love it
And I can't wait to see if this works out so
Thank you so much for coming on the podcast this week
Thank you appreciate it well that's it for this week show thanks for listening and if you can't get enough
Of The Internet of Things podcast please subscribe to my newsletter Stacy knows things at Stacey on iot
T.com as always will see you next week