Hey everyone welcome to the internet
Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham
Is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Today's podcast we have
So much stuff for you we promised we talked about Apple
A crazy access
Point from Samsung
And we have
Salesforce getting into the Internet of Things
And
Kevin we get to find out about his onhub router
Experience
Yes
And our guest this week is Paul Masson
And he is with Ping Identity and we're going to talk about creating and identity layer for The Internet of Things
Okay so let's start with Apple
What did we hear from Apple
At home kit about their show that we were so eager for
Last week
Kevin
I can sum it up in one
Word
And that where it is
Nothing
Yeah
It was a real bummer I'm going to be honest
It's it's kind of it
Interesting him and what does it say about where they're at with the platform in
You've written several stories in the past several months
About how the challenges are with the
The platform requirements Apple security requirements the hardware that's needed to be home to get certified
And
Apple you know it's probably said no everything's fine you know we're just we're just had flow products at WWDC
Yeah but
I would have thought
Especially with the new Apple TV that they did announce as well as new iPhones new iPads and everything else and watch over
Os2
Oh I thought they would have done
Homekit demo at some Home Care partner and some announcements
In fairness though I don't know if you saw the event Stacey but it was about two and a half hours log there was a lot of stuff
In it so it's possible that it just wasn't enough to Warrant a spotlight on the stage
So
What I'm hearing is
There's been a lot of back-and-forth
There's been a lot of
Between the Apple
The chip suppliers
And the actual vendors of the
Connected products
What's been going on behind the scenes
What is people have been
Building and testing
During the test things have come back
Not working the way there
And so they have to go back to the drawing
Not all the way back
Necessary that the chip layer
But this is a lot harder basically what's happening is Apple's trying to build
An entire ecosystem
Behind the curtains
It certainly does seem like apple is trying to
Round up a herd of cats to some degree
But
I kind of put
The burden on them they're the ones who brought all the cats into the
Yard to play
Maybe is not it I mean
Yes
Can I see all the cats
Sounds like actual cats peas
Maybe maybe the dogs that are really trying to
Did you want to work with
Destiny want to make this
Work so
I think we're actually going to see a big Improvement
From what I hear from people
Is this next iteration of homekit
We should see
Improvement
And features in usability
So
What I am looking for an iOS 9 which should come out of beta you said maybe tomorrow
I'm on the day after recording this podcast by the time everybody hears this podcast it will be available
Think about too many things I live
So we're going to see some really interesting things like triggers
Which
You know most of our audience who actually has smart home devices are probably pretty familiar with but these are things like
Location so
When you're coming to an area
Your location actually triggers like a light to come on
A certain device or sensor going off
Can trigger
Something else to happen so
When my garage door opens for example it triggers my porch lights to come on
We talked about that on the show
Schedule
Time is also a trigger
So those are things that we should see their support for that in iOS 9
And I'm actually really interested to see how Apple has created the programming interface for that
Because that's one of those things that
Make-or-break kind of things
Consumers I think
If it's too complicated people won't use it and
Honestly Apple does try to extract the complexity away from things so I think they'll succeed in that area
I'm hoping
I'd like that is like one of the first things
Yeah I mean this was a big event and apple apple typically has to fall events one in September for the iPhones
And whatever else and then in October that generally have
And IMAX
Anything else
Kind of thing so it's possible
But they still have an October event
Even though the announce the iPads
In September
It is
India
So the other thing that was a little strange and it was kind of awkward for Apple I thought
Was that when they did the iOS beta put up a website after the event for iOS 9
In-Home Care
And at the bottom of that website
They actually had a link that said find homekit enabled products
The Apple site for homekit enabled products and if you click that link
Took you to the Apple Store
For any of their home
Even the non-home Chipmunks gas so I spent like the night
Went last Wednesday I spent that evening
Emailing everybody I do on that page
Are you home yet certified all of a sudden
And basically everyone came back
Me and said
No not yet but we will be
Stay tuned
So
A lot of the results like Phillips for exam
The makers of the Hue Lights
They actually updated their developer page
The day before or maybe it's two days before the Apple event saying that they would be releasing a new SDK for Developers
Before October
So they were hoping sometime in September and before October
And my hunch is that that's going to have homekit support so we should see Phillips hopefully before October
Anticipating that
We should see idevices switch actually made
Splash at CES
Maybe even connectsense
Have devices very soon
They're homekit certified
So
At this point
The insteon the newest insteon Hub is homekit certified
The insteon
They have a hub
Sorry I'm trying to think of who has hugs at our home gets her to find I can't think of any others but you may know some
And Neutron both have
Subs that are certified
And
That is if it's elegado has a sensor Bluetooth sensor kit that is
Certified and then ecobee
As its
Thermostat ecobee 3 thermostat that is homekit certified
They've been the same for products for the last
3ish months I would say
And nothing else is come on
It is now default time frame so we are expecting some new ones
Yay
Reaching out to people that that time frame seems to be reasonable
I have seen though that some companies have actually pulled back
From certification so Lake
We talked to Alex Hawkinson a couple weeks ago in the podcast and
They actually did not get there
Home hub
Certified
With SmartThings
They may one day do that but they aren't
Going that route right now
Ian said that he had told Mashable in an interview that he'd prefer to cover the open route
Yeah so that's that
So you know
That was kind of
I'm surprised they will still support iOS
And you know
Maybe one day they can always add
Hardware for
It support if they were
So we'll see
So that's the homekit news for everybody who is like me in
I can't wait
Equating
Yeah
Maybe you'll see
Maybe next week is the week that I will be able to try
It didn't even get a mention with the Apple TV which
If you go to Apple support site for the Apple TV it says it is a homekit gateway for remote access
It's not the only one who can do it also through iCloud from what I'm hearing and things up
That is true that that's one of the things that
That I've been
That was one of the things that
I was kind of a sticky
All right
Let's see what else have we learned this week isps are adding third-party devices which is good if you
Rely on
Comcast or AT&T to provide your home automation setup or you're interested in going to
Comcast or AT&T to get a home automation setup
Because they do have that Network installers and they will do it for you
So yeah
Comcast has added Chamberlain garage door opener to MyQ
Iona
In love
Chewits
Network of third-party devices it's also going to add sometime next year the Arlo
Camera which is from Netgear this is actually a wireless camera
The wireless camera that can go inside or out
Side and an AT&T their Digital Life home they are going to support the nest
They don't have as many
Devices is Comcast is supporting
Comcast is now going to support through Xfinity home 11 devices
Correct me if I'm wrong Xfinity home platform users out there but I don't believe any of them are actually supported
Today
Believe support is coming in the next few weeks for most of them
I think it's a good solution for people who are like
I kind of want something cool devices out there but I really don't want to install a bunch of motion sensors and other stuff in my house
Yeah like
I get what you're saying and I know that again I said I was before you and I are edge cases would rather get her roller sleeves up and break up the toolbar
Boxing install these things
It's getting to the point where
It's not that difficult to install these things and if it is then there's something wrong with the product itself I think
Yeah and Comcast has charge like $40 a month but with that $40 a month you do get monitored security
And a lot of people are really excited
Like that so
I can't not people for
You know I know
I just spent like 2 hours this weekend playing with freaking light
So
There are get it
Lucy Samsung they have a new
A new access point
Tell us about that
We don't know too much yet because there's nothing that I could find on Samsung's official new site or anyting
Whoever is this Korea
Which is based in
What do you think
I'm going with South Korea
You are correct
They have put out a story that on the 14th
September Samsung released an iot access point
That has the support with three radios
Zigbee
Wi-Fi
An Bluetooth
Wi-Fi is 802 11 AC
Say it sounds to me like this is
I want to say it this is kind of like an Uber access point because they already make access points for your home network
And they're able to 11ac access point so they will
Extend your current Network further to get onto the nooks and crannies of your house
It seems to me like this is the same thing only data Bluetooth
Nzb
To help with iot
Networking site coverage as well in your home
And I thought this was going to be accessed
Picacho car if you
So yes that's exactly what this
Siri can do that for you
Siri
That'd be a really fun thing
High breathalyzer
2 Series sew in
Take the breathalyzer
If this then that if this is what alcohol level is greater than .08
Contact Yellow Cab Company and send my location
That baby
Make it so
Desiree
That's really all we know about this but I like the fact that
Companies in surprise that Samsung mean they're making a big iot push right now
I like the type of companies are
Thinking about
Creating additional useful radios in traditional devices access points for example for Wi-Fi networks
This week is dreamforce which is like
Someone said it's the Super Bowl of it conferences
Fair enough
I would agree considering that it when it's in town in San Francisco I mean they shut down so blocks
Yeah I went stayed in like
The crappiest Hotel I've ever stayed at
Because
For same here
It was like a blanket on top of a card
Box
It was 50
Alright so Salesforce introduce today it's
Iot cloud
And that is iot cloud with a
Kelsey
And what this is basically
It's a data Repository
So what you do is
Companies can send their data through any of the Salesforce
Apps so any of the apps
I said so if you got Salesforce running if your company
You can have it all of your
Salesforce data going into this iot cloud
If any of your
Force.com apps
Can also
Center data in there
And it can link up with other
Companies that also are using
Salesforce and iot Cloud
So it's very similar in concept to something IBM actually launched a year ago
Called
Iot Foundation
They're really good with these names
Like I said I can't mock this because I have something
Called the iot podcast
Salesforce's iot cloud
IBM's iot foundation
And pussy Salesforce has partnered with Cisco
Dively which is a very
LogMeIn product
And all of these are very enterprise-focused
And
It's basically a place where you can run a lot of data analytics
Really quickly
And I'm trying to think what else people might want to know about the
What would you want to know about this
Well it's Enterprise so probably not much
I don't know I'm kind of surprised that Salesforce is getting into iot it just doesn't seem like a
Natural
A natural fit horses love the internet of things since time immemorial because really
What they can do I mean this is all about data
And The Internet of Things is all about making
Your data accessible
All to you
Collecting all this data from customers anyway
And now it's basically to try to find a way to monetize
August 8th
And
Then offer people
Once it's got the data in there at connect let you buy additional software
So you can see the data
So you can analyze
It's all about the money
It is the nice thing is once you have is data in there
You can offer people infinite services to like let them
Do things with a
People aren't going to want to lose that data all around
And
The other thing is
Garage Motel rate once it's in there you really don't want to let it out
And because it's Salesforce and you got a million other people and companies using this data
If you have someone else
If I make widgets
And you make
Okay let's not use which
Craigslist
Pekin actual price
So let me make light bulbs
Jose I make light bulbs
What's in you make
Lamps
So we have a partnership
Because my light bulbs are really great in your land
I can start sending you data
About my light bulbs in
I'm sure you would probably send me your data about the customers buying
Your lamps
I can share
The dated about the light bulbs that fit in your lamps
With you
And you can share the data about the customers buying your lamps
With my light bulbs
And we can actually only share that sub segments of data that relates to our shared partnership base
Basically in bills like really
Partnerships or sales strategies around it
And that's a great business tool
That's kind of what Salesforce is trying to sell
I was kind of a
I don't know if that was a great
No no I get it I get it now I just surprise me I don't think of them as a kind of company in iot company but I probably should
Considering all the big data that they handle
You know I have to use going to
Lots and lots and lots of little bits of data and it's going to be
Hard to manage that into something useful so
Speak about it like nobody wants to be a lamp come
They want to be a Services Company
And that date is going to allow you to then
Offer people services
What's wrong with you being a limb company because lamp companies they just sell a product once you want to get
Recurring Revenue
That's why the cords break after 3 months
Oh come on built-in obsolescence
Come on alright
I think it's time though
For the onhub router
Because I really want to hear
Got to say about this
Goodwill and ordered it
Literally right before he started the prior show week ago it was supposed to be here in 2 days and it came after the next day
It was awesome
Thank you bestbuy.com I did buy this out of pocket
I got to say after having setup
Taylor modems and routers and bridges and hubs for the past however many years
This was by far the
So
Google
Kudos you have succeeded in that area
It was drafted Temple Italy from
The time I open the box till the time I had the network up and running
What's 5 minutes
That was it
Super simple
Super Simple Songs
Onhub app is available for IOS and Android I had an iPhone in my hand at a time so
I use my iPhone very simple
You actually you actually set it up like the echo your how you connect a device to
To the echo via Wi-Fi to set up the Echoes Wi-Fi
You do the same thing here
Got it. That's how you set up a Wi-Fi network on the onhub router you actually connected Wi-Fi to Wi-Fi Direct
To set it up in terms of
Using the app
You can only set up one network and I actually have multiple networks on my prior router so that was a little
Disappointing the reason I do that is probably
Not something everybody needs because I do video show that I co-host on Wednesdays
I have a dedicated Network just for my online video
Cleanscapes Connection in Summit
Actually cheated was using that for my 4K video streaming as well bits
Regardless I just have one network out that Ashley brings a little more Simplicity as well because now everybody in the house is like
Do I connect to a or b they don't ask me that anymore there's just one network
One of the downsides and I'm finding is that it's a little too simple
You can't
Really control things and I know you would ask this question we talked about this
Before there's no parental controls you can't say
Limitless device
To access the internet until 10 p.m. after that it can't go out so you couldn't shut off the kids devices for sample
The only thing you can do on a device level
AC in real time and historically
How much
Been with her using up and down
And you can actually prioritize
Traffic fast track it is what it called it to a device
For a set amount of time so if I know I'm going to be watching 4K TV
And I don't want anybody to mess with my stream
I prioritize the TV
That way I got the best connection
That's about it there's not a lot of advanced features here
Are people who are tinkering with the routers installing your own firmware this is not a device for you
This is more for a mainstream home
That may have not great coverage or not have the fastest
Speeds
Tenda WiFi router
Because
Contrary to some of the reports on reading I'm having no problems with coverage and signal and Steve it's actually working
Better than my old 802 11 AC router is that was
I thought that 2 years ago
So I'm very happy with the performance
I think some people will be disappointed in that it's not Advance you can't do too much to it or with it
And yes it is limited to only have one available ethernet port
I actually thought I was going to use that for a smart home hub but I'm not
I forgot I have a network printer that I connected with her either not to router
So that's what's taking up my extra
Ewnetwork
Luckily the wink Hub that I use
Runs over Wi-Fi so it doesn't need to be connected to a router so I didn't lose any smart home functionality as a result of that
Philips Hue hub
Which is not working right now because I don't have a place to put it yes I can get a bridge and all that but you know out of the box
You're right I'm I'm kind of stuck
Maybe I'll send you a switch
This was a hundred and was it 199
It is 199 99 I know I've got to return. With Best Buy that I can send it back but
I don't think I will I mean it looks nice but then again
My Broadband comes in
In the
Second floor
In a far corner of the home so nobody can see this
If I have a broadband connection the middle of my home
Yeah I need this thing out looks great
But I don't
Okay and you've got a
She who shall not be named
An Amazon Echo so
Next to the echo
Is it the same size
It looks just like
Yeah it's it's shorter
And it's wider
And the Ridley does have a ring of light at the top just like the echo does but
That ring is always on
And that's because it has four different colors to tell you am in setup mode and BM
Working fine or see there's a problem and so on so
Again it's hassle-free
I don't need to switch networks when I'm having problems I don't need to
Seek out the best network
It's all just happening
And I have no complaints
I want to say full disclosure
There are so many variables
Two wireless network signals that
What is working well in my house at my architecture and my setup
May not work for everybody I just
I got to say that because
I don't want people thinking this is going to be the best thing since sliced bread
And they have no Faraday cages are at their house and it's not working so
But those of you who live in tinfoil houses
Boat Fender tip about buying from Best Buy with a good sword
Return policy and restocking fee
Oh I don't think so I don't think I've ever paid a restock fee
Alright Kevin thank you and
Good show good show of Jeff
I don't know where that came from
Weirdest from Stacy
Surprise
Alright well thank you
For this week show and everyone to stay tuned
For Paul Madsen as WeChat about identity
And what is next for passwords and The Internet of Things
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast and we have our guest today who is Paul metzen
He is in the office of the CTO at
Ping Identity
And as you can guess we are talking about
Identity and The Internet of Things
And Paul
Thanks for coming on the show today
I'm happy to be here
I'm really excited to have you here
Because
I follow you on Twitter and you get into some really interesting discussions and
Unlike some of them are a little above my head so I'm going to have you
Probably keep it down a notch at the hits ale People level for me
But I go I go all levels
All levels all layers of the stack
So
Let's just get it started with kind of let's frame the issue
Because I know my issue with identity and then another thing
Switches
Well there's there's a couple
My issue is
I find it very hard
Enter
My identity and password across
Like the 30 to 40 devices that I've got
I got different passwords for different Services cuz
God help me I know I'm not supposed to have the same password
Search for everything right
That in theory and Theory
I'm going to confess that
I have a certain limited number of passwords
It's because
Your humans
I am human I'm not a machine
And I don't have like one password or any of those things running on all my devices
That's
I don't do they even do that
No I don't think of you right girl optimized for the web We Have Nots
That's one issue that I know I have I'm like
I feel kind of guilty about it
So there's that
But there's also
The issue of
The identity of
There's my identity but then there's other people who are accessing these devices
And I have to share my
Current passwords for some of these devices with them and sometimes they get their own password
Depending on the device
So
There's like
My family's idea
And there's also
Guess I did
And I don't know if we're going to talk about that on the show
Play I hope we do because it's yeah let me know if those use cases are going to become more and more important
And as you say sharing a password
Weather for you
Wifi router alert
For that things in your house
Doesn't scale well maybe it works when it's just your rotor
But when you want to allow your houseguests to play through your
Sound system
Can you connect two speakers
Beginning of your
Can you search he's got a couple of points
Ux constraints
These things and
And as bad as passwords are
Typing into websites
And now they're infinitely worse if you have to try to enter them directly in
Yeah. There's one issue how do we get around the usability
Limitations
Clearly that
Songs that we have
Offer
Something there right we are going to be
Used to connecting
Devices and things
With the assistance of our phones
So there's opportunities there
Far easier to
Buying
Non-existing identity to a device
Leave your phone
Trying to type it directly into your thermostat or what have you
But separately from just the pain passwords and entering them
Is Sir the reality or the recognition that
I don't always want to have to create a new identity
For everything
I bring into the house
We've been through that on the web right where every site
45 years ago
Command that you create your own account unique account with
Usernames and passwords are
And just the number of accounts
That implies for users
Dragon scale on the web
So we count ways to use existing ID
To get into application
Can I take that model
Is going to be necessary
On the iot as well
Rather than create a new account for some
Speaker or light bulb when I bring it into the house I'm going to be able to use my
Existing identity
Either out of social provider like a Facebook or Google or maybe some
Iot platform
I've already
Soda created
Start a relationship with
You're my provider
Okay so we're talking about something like
Lego watch which is like hell Facebook
Twitter
That's what they use right
Facebook
Exactly that sort of experience
Login with app
We're exes
Some providers
I already feel comfortable with
Should have already invested in the relationship
You want to use their
Version of you
To interact with that thing rather than something new
No I already do that with
A bunch of my device
What's interesting is I'm not just logging into these devices but I'm also giving certain
Permissions
To those
Like what will go to examples because
What is the easiest thing in the world
So
I log into
My Nest thermostat and they have
Works with Nest their developer program
Bright and when I
Link my Nest thermostat to
My
Wink hub for example
I log into my
Nest
Tlingit
To my wink
Home hub
And when I do that
I'm giving
The wink system of variety of
Permissions associated with the nest
We can see the temperature
It lets me I think
Turn it up and down from the
Wink app as opposed to the nest app
Write in a get certain
Can a data access
Permissions but it also doesn't get
Other things
Right now today though
I'm not exactly clear
In all cases
What it can and can't do
In like
I know for example but I'm authorizing a Twitter app for example
Or signing in with Twitter
A lot of the time I can see what it
Can and can't do
I don't actually get that right now
With everything at the device level
Consider two points that sort of disability into
Permissions you've assigned it is critical
Sell Twitter Facebook Google me I'll give you a page where you can
CD other apps that you
Connected
And you know what you dig deeper what permissions you've given them
And I give you the ability to revoke those permissions
And that's that's kind of
You get that for free with with a loss
If
The Google and Facebook
Choose to implement that model
Now what you described when you connect wink
Two-ness
Right
Believe
You're actually doing is
Is your connecting
The wink
Cloud
To the nest cloud
So you're using your using a wasp
Queen
Two servers right Andrew
Pub talks with Cloud through some proprietary
Identity mechanism
And the nest thermostat does the same up to its cloud
And then to Cloud your sugar glue together with or
Which is powerful
But you still created multiple identity
It's just sort of the permissions layer that they
Giving you two to control permission
You know I think that model
Using something like or
More generally
Delegated
Authorization
We can also try that
Right down to the things themselves
And and not necessarily rely on
The cloud for
Hooking everything up
Oh okay so that's a very subtle distinction that even I hadn't thought of
Okay
Just a matter of
Who gets
Token
That is going to be presented on
On all these interactions
And how you got it
So then in that case what happens is
Devices themselves each generate a token
Albany not generated something with generate it
For them but then they would
Issued ID
And somehow they would
Get that token stored away in their own
Secure Storage
Can I use that
Whenever they need to
Interact or Fennekin
Something else whether that's
In another device
In the home
Maybe it's
The router maybe it's some
Third-party cloud service
So before we get into the token because that's going to get a little technical
Let's talk about what this looks like then
In the real world
The theoretical real world where we have these tokens and lots of things so
Help me understand what this might look like in my house
Where I have
You know sensors and
Today actually my sensors
Connect to
Cubs in
The onboarding process is usually through like as a zigbee radio so I'm pairing them
There's an authentication process
Yes and you don't necessarily when you bring up a new device into the home you got to get it onto the network weather
Wi-Fi so
That's one secret or one credential
The bootstrap
On to the network before that
Viceland
Do anything else whether talking to the
The cloud or just staying local
So I think
Clearly
NFC or rble
Different ways where we go
Bootstrap that credential
That the Wi-Fi credential or or similar
Aunt advice
But the next hurdle for that singing
When you say bootstrap that
Credential
Right is that me
Ultimately we got to give
To the new device
If you're trying to hook it onto your Wi-Fi
You got to give it
Either the password
For the Wi-Fi network
And there's various ways you can do that everybody
Kingsville hit dented their own whether it's
An ad hoc WiFi
Network that you connect
Via an app on the device
That's the means by which you
Provision
The real Network
Credential
The flashing lights
But some people have or
I know that I've got some security systems that I've done that have like
Some audio cable thing that
It's like highly secure in magical
Right okay I see what you're
Flashing lights are typically away of
Helping you validate that you were actually connecting to the thing you think you are
Because there's
There's an opportunity for someone
This way to insert themselves into that protest
Get on to the network
But you've got to get it onto the network before it can start talking to the other devices
Let's go to the first
Authentication challenge
But arguably a bigger one
Maybe there's
Chance for optimization in the future where
Typically you
You've got to tell that device
What
Count
When you already have it when you chew
Shut up
With the corresponding provider
Q light bulb
Set it up with a new account
Currently
The reality is
You know you're going to
Download the app
That is specific
Take two that lines light bulbs are that device
You're going to create an account in the app you're going to log into the app
And then.
Different mechanism
Connect you
That account you just created
To the device the light bulb
Ceremony or that experience for the user presumes that they're willing to create a new account
That you aren't supposed to
No using an existing account
Some other
Platform provider
Whenever it's
Apples
Coyote calls
Platform on Google store
Brightlight listeners I have
I'm probably going to stay at least 60 of those based on
The devices I have
Tried out
Closing those accounts
After
Sending back
Device
Yeah it just just keeping track of those
Identities writing
Do I have an account what was the password they are needed
It's the same challenge we have on the web just
Steel. For everything in your house
Now you know you're an early adopter but that's the reality
For the users
Economist we
Something different
Okay and so your suggestion is creating this
This identity layer
And it is an interoperable layer
It's associated
With whatever
Whatever stack whatever technology stack that
We're going to build for the inter
What I argue is the
The importance of
Standardization
And so interop
At night
Talk about that
DeKalb right now
That work has started I think
I'm not alone in recognizing the
The importance of that so there's there's some encouraging
Initial steps on
Define in how
How to bond
These Concepts
Identities and
Relationships onto those new
Protocols
And what are some of those steps so far
So for instance there's a ace group Ace
Authentication for constrained environments
India ETF
Panera working group.
Looking at
Reality of
Constrained devices
What are the constraints is
Memory your size or battery
There's an effort in the
Open ID Foundation
So
Not an organization historically focused
Coyote
But there's early
Work there in defining
A model where
Cancel silicate the issuance
Betoken
To a device
An app on the phone
Let's talk about the constraints because we kind of went right in there and I never got back to
The constraints which are
Some of these
Devices so if I look at a sensor I'm I'm looking at a tiny little arm base
You know it might be like an arm zero microcontroller on these things
This is not something that is capable of
Running out of
128 bit
What is an encryption
Actually I'm saying that like I know
I don't know
The acronym
It is not a nice acronym I feel like it
That's a lot
That that's kind of a lot of number I'd I have a vague sense of hashing and What needs to go into that
It feels like a lot for that level of
Microcontroller
I made that statement I was actually presenting
On on stage in the summer night
Just made that blanket statement
These things will not be able to do
Modern crypto
And I was immediately corrected by somebody who knows
That would be nice
Macaulay Culkin
So
We're both wrong
Well point is valid
Right perhaps not specifically around Cliffdale butts
At least these things cannot do
Clara mobile phone can't work
Some of them
Write summer going to be connected to the house
Electricity and so we eating Taco battery
Battery power
Some definitely have constraints that we need to
Anticipate
Music about how they authenticate to other things and how they prove that they are
Still valid in an operating and a half
A particular user
And how often do they need to do that because if I look at like the latest zigbee hack
I'm it wasn't really a fact
If somebody who's like
Hey look most people when they do zigbee
You know other occasion right now they're just like
For the most part they don't use all of the encryption
Available to them they're just like
They use the same encryption code every time
Yeah
I'm not familiar with that hot but
But yeah there's a general pattern of
Relying on
Whatever
Shirts Ortiz were were burned into the device
At manufacturing time and
I just relying on that
Fault
So
If and when those things are compromised
You're just shot
Right cuz there's
There's no way.
Step back from that
The model that
Wheat
Argue for is
Ghost
Secrets that are broke into the chip when the thing is manufactured
Primary credentials
MasterCard goes we don't want to use those
Each and every time that device
Appendix
We want to instead
Issue
Secondary
Secret secondary credential
You know Austin
Primary
I know secondary
Secrets can be shorter lives
They can be issued only if the user consents
To the woods
They can be targeted at particular applications
Lots of
Security and privacy damages
That's simple operation of
Start with the shirt that was
Burnt End of the chapter trade it for something else
And finally is as the end user
When we start talking about adding an identity layer
And making that interoperable
What does that mean for me in terms of additional
Steps or work
Or
If it's shorter battery life on my
Devices Maybe
What does it mean to me what am I going to
I hope what you see is
Skewer
Prompts for password
Yeah
Yeah that's a good thing right we're seeing that on the web
Not reflect
Emergency
I suggest you're also going to see
More prompts for strong
Vacation by bringing something into the house
Credential or token that it's going to use to
Do its job
That's a sensitive operation
I want to protect that
I'd argue that it's relevant to
Impose
Rarely and infrequently
A greater authentication on bird
Burden on users
And we currently do
So Prince
Bringing something ended up the home and I'm setting it up
I should be expected to the fennec 8 through more than
Single
More than
Password
Also perhaps by swiping
Something on my phone
Communicate that's mean idiot
Touch id based login
So I'm going to have to use a fingerprint login
Whenever I bring a new device into my phone for the for the first time
Well I'm not saying it has to be fingerprint I'm saying it should be something more then
Just a password
That you used to login to that website
It's appropriate
I think
To require greater
Assurance
Of these sensitive operations
And provisioning a new device a sentence
Passwords
More
Strongest indication operation
Stun infrequently
And
Fewer account creation
Right
Not a given that every device
I bring into the home
Should have
Corresponding unique
Identity
There's a cloud
Why can I not use an existing identity
Like I can on the web
That would be exciting
I could use
Fewer apps will
Right now I can use fewer apps
And fewer account creation
Yeah
That would be fun
Okay
Will Paul thank you so much for talking to me about the
Recite I feel
A little bit better how how far off do you think
Well the model
Has already proven itself on the web
People.com
Respect
This sort of
Identity interoperability they don't call it that of course
On the web
So that the protocols of the Earth
Patterns are there
That the standardization efforts are just beginning
I expect in one or two years we might see some
Products that actually Implement these models
Ultimately depends on
Pressures better
Consumers in this context
Play something
Device manufacturers in the platforms
Alright we'll device manufacturers
Consider yourself pressured
Because by golly
I am running out of passwords
Alright thank you so much for coming on the show today I really appreciate it
Was my pleasure Stacy thank you very much
That's it for today show thank you guys so much for listening
And we'll see you next week on the iot podcast