Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
Does your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a holiday schmorgesborg for you
For your Thanksgiving either
Restore post restore
Black Friday or Cyber Monday or whatever day
Pick a day any day
So the idea here is Kevin and I are going to talk to you about
Your favorite connected devices
You should probably consider buying for yourself
Or a loved one for this holiday
Something like that or if you don't like someone
We
She might recommend our favorite holiday
Homekit products or a hug
In case you really want to give them hours of fun troubleshooting devices
Fun for the whole family setting up a
Smart home hub
They've gotten a lot better
Anyways
So we'll get started with the most
I don't know the most common
Products out there that
Pretty much everyone
Can I join witches
Activity trackers and
Watches
Kevin this is your neck of the woods tour
Wrist of the Woods
Terrible why do I even do that
What's your recommendation for the best smartwatch out there
Yeah that's it that's a toughie because
I typically wear my Apple watch but it's
Only work with Apple devices
So it's really hard to recommend that
There are obviously some Android Wear watches that do work with Apple and Android phones
But you know what
If I want to just a basic smartwatch
I didn't want to run a ton of apps
On my wrist which I actually am not doing these days
Probably would take a look at the pebble because it's
Cross platform support
The good battery life and relatively low cost
Yeah I think the most
Recent version which is the round one
Which is an interesting look
Is 249 at last I checked
You're buying for one of the
Fair Lady
And your life
This is probably a good
Good option
Yeah folks who are not familiar with the pebble though I think most
People probably are
This is the one with the epaper display
Color now the first
Addition with only a grayscale or black and white
But now their color and Pebble has its new interface called
Where the timeline I think they call it timeline where you can see past present and future events and activities and data so
It's really intuitive to use I think and
Even though I said you know if you don't want to run out on your watch this is a good one
Pebble still does have an app stores just
It's a relatively Limited in terms of functionality and choice
Yeah I love it I love my puppy
The first gen Pebble that I got for like
Man this was last year around Christmas so I got it for likes
65 bucks
It runs actually I use it mostly to get my text
And
You can get it for
Actually you can set it up for even emails but I get it mostly protects and taken in
Finding out of my phone's ringing while it's in my back
It's great
And bonus for you or well for Pebble on his but not you because you're not on AT&T just today Pebble added the ability
Do you speak back text replies
But it only works with AT&T phones that's very interesting how they been Limited
You can actually
Reply back
With certain predetermined
Like yes no okay
Animojis
I can't tell you how I feel
Some people are like
Stacy
Would you like to go you know
Out for happy hour tonight and I respond back with like
Little wacky emojis
Some people are like
I don't understand why you sent me a baseball glove
It was the closest Emoji to my
Finger
All right so that's that's our smartwatch
Woke up with the dihybrid catalog
Smartwatch activity tracker
Because this is
Both
Actually we'll just going to activity track
Best activity tracker on the cheap
This is for someone who's like
No not really sold on the concept or maybe they're just like me
I'm going to go with the Jawbone move
Which is about 50 bucks
The zip
Would be the equivalent in the Fitbit category
I picked the job on simply because I like the software I think the
The Jawbone software is
Darren good and
I think around for the price I don't think
No I mean this this thing is
End
I've used a Fitbit I need his jaw bone I use the white things
I can't think of the white things hacked
Chevy Tracker thing that they called it
Andrea Lee
They all do basically the same thing
I just like the job on software it's
Nice
And
The nice thing is is you go up Market in Jawbone if you go up the next level to the Bluetooth equipped up
In
Whatever ap24 up up
You can actually start using your jaw bone to talk to your house so it'll work with your nest and your SmartThings
And you can actually once it sees your moving around in the mornings for example
Let's that awesome let's use as a trigger and
And start doing some cool stuff
Like center Coffee to go
Maplewood
Turn up her desk
Do other things
So
I think that for
Bang for the buck
My bad
Competence.
All right
And
The intermediate category of
Hey
Smartwatch it's an activity tracker
It's
Did you actually go or dementia at the Y things activity pop
Yeah
150 bucks
I like this device
Vici really do I kind of
There's a Black Friday deal that widens
Has tweeted out
This week actually and it's 45% off the activity pop
And I am looking at it and I'm thinking
Well you know this is a perfect device for people who want to watch that looks like a watch cuz really that that's what they
That's just has some some smarts inside it and
A a little
Counter
Hand to show you
You know steps and such
I don't know how else to describe it
Circular it's got hands and it's not digital at all it's
It's analog
So
It's got the hell tracking stuff in there
It has it has walking running
It's water-resistant so you can
Women and I believe
Vibration alarm
It's got sleep tracking if you want to sleep in your watch
And it's got a 8-month battery life in his cup
Bluetooth Bluetooth
Satellite sent the data to the app and you know that's great MI
Haven't actually checked
To see but I presume it works with both Android and iOS
I believe so my other wedding stuff
Pass so I assume this out.
So if you're hardcore this isn't going to be for you cuz it doesn't have a heart
So Kevin you want to share your
Your thoughts on for the hardcore Fitness activity tracker guy
You could go nuts here on so you can spend hundreds and hundreds of dollars like five six hundred or more I'm actually going to throw a curve
Purple out here that may surprise people
And say
I would consider the Microsoft Band 2 for $250
Now that I own the first one I do not have the second one and the first one was fantastic for me
Acceptance
Fit
Comfortably the new one is more rounded and looks a lot nicer to wear
What it has inside those
Actually pretty amazing for such a small band type device
It has an optical heart-rate sensor gotten accelerometer gyroscope GPS which is nice
I go out and run I don't have to carry a phone I can have everything track speed distance route and so on
Has an ambient light sensor a skin temperature sensor and a UV Central actually tell you hey you've been out in the sun a little too low
Today
It has a capacitive sensor to passive touch screen
Galvanic
Skin response
Switch I really never used
Microphone for control and also a barometer
Also has Bluetooth 4.0 so I can wirelessly send or get data
To and from
Not just a Windows phone but also an iPhone or any Android 4.4 better device
2 and fifty bucks 8.8 does a heck of a lot
What is the galvanic
I guess you know like if I get over radiated by an x-ray or I don't know
I kidding
It might be sweating to be quite honest I don't I don't recall
Oci just usually
I'm sweating
Yep galvanic
Skin response is skin conductance
Interesting thank you Wikipedia
Alright well maybe someone will let us know what that means
Let me actually be something about seizures
I'll have to I'll have to
Keep looking that up I know that their skin bands are bands out there to measure
Like if someone is having a seizure
Or not
Feel like I read those words
Near the word seizure
But
Again
Google will tell me
Okay this is why
We should have a medical
We're not we're not doctors we don't play
It is true
Okay so that is
Those are our picks for wearables activity trackers
And you can argue with us
About those later
Feel free and now will move into
But let's look at the cameras cuz this year
I have gone like a total 180 on the camera front
We got a lot of
Like smart home devices in like a good half of the things we recommend have cameras in them this
This year
There's no hot
No hiding this year for me
All about the security on the outside so
I've got two doorbell cameras
Because this was the year of the
Connected door
Connected doorbell
I decided I went into I was in San Francisco last week and I tried out
Two new
Connect two doorbells one is the August doorbell cam
I might be the one of the first people who got to see that in their office so
Both of these next devices I have not tried out on my house
Important know that I've only tried them out in their office but I did make them
Taking out the Wi-Fi not working
Do some test
So
The August doorbell cam
Works with the August Smart Lock hundred $99
Of all the doorbell cams
This might be my favorite because it is square in my house is
Rectangular high like the angles on it it's very nice
It works with your doorbell chime
It
As actually kind of the most interesting field of view it's actually
Taller than all of the other doorbell cams out on them
Market
And it takes about
Two to three seconds to get a doorbell feed like the feed going
XM the second you get your notification you pull it up
A little bit faster on your in-home Wi-Fi versus your
Kind of Lte experience
Good IOS and Android
And
I deal with August is if you
See someone in your doorbell cam you can be like oh hey UPS man
What up
Please leave that package inside on the door and you open your August lock and then boom the UPS man comes inside your house
That's why I need one of these
There you go
So two hundred bucks
Sketchy one
Cool thing about it is
The entire there's like a
How to say it's about
Two and a half inch diameter
Is that the whole part of the circle
Is the diameter
That would be the diameter yet
We are we are not geographers either but
Giai Tri
Geometry
That's not a word
Okay
Math majors
Who started our holiday drinking
Early on gravity podcast
Well that's good you got that one
Radius is the half
Diameters
It's a big button
Big button on this thing the hold
Two and a half
Circle part of the doorbell is the button so
There is no wrong way to press this
Kind of like
Very nice
Is the camera quality
He is very good
Pretty good mode
So that's August
And
I like that because
Because of the design of
Set for my house
Now
The other doorbell
That we have
Connected video doorbell cam
Is
The skybell HD
Now this isn't going to go on sale
Until December 16th on the skybell website so right now it's sold out do not be fooled by the Skype
Adele version to that's on the website right now
Wait for the skybell HD
As you can imagine this is HD
And this thing is really nice
It is a round doorbell
It has
Couple really interesting features
It's got LEDs that are customizable on the outside
So you can change like the little lights on the outside of the doorbell
To be like whatever color you want
You can like your Hue bulbs exactly like your Hue bulbs actually
So for Christmas you can have them be red and white or red and green knows I'm probably only only one color one color only
Red grid
You can actually turn off the chime if you'd like to
And then it will just send you notifications to your phone
This is nice if you have you know
A baby or dog like mine that's just like
Oh my God the door I got a burnt my fool head off
And
It has a really nice
Wide angle of view
And it has
Full color night vision
Those LEDs I was talking about
Yeah they let off enough
Light at night even when it's pitch-black
Owl camera can actually see you in full color really well it's
Pretty slick
That's impressive I have a couple webcams that use like i r type lighting to
Can I do that
But they're not great
And it's interesting to me they're using regular LEDs and what not that's that's impressive
This is I mean
If book
So those two
Each of them or both of them or 199
So
That's $200 not $2
Probably not going to be on sale since they're both so new
I'm guessing they're going to be pretty hot
Pretty hot items
So go doorbells
Alright Kevin I feel like I've been talking a long time why don't I send it back to you and you can talk about
Arlo
Arlo Arlo Auto that's a wireless
Camera security system you can get in multiple configurations so if you just want to like
One doorbell cam like I want
You can do that
Or you can get multiple cameras that come in the kids all up like five cameras included
And then there's add-on cameras if you want even
Keep it running in a really that got your home
But the kid actually comes to the base station as well as a camera
And the lowest price one if you buy it direct is 17999 for the base station
And 1 wireless camera with an HD camera
I does have night vision it's an indoor outdoor cameras weatherproof
It's completely wireless menu.
Plug it in either
The base station is plugged in obviously but the camera
Has batteries in it
Comes with batteries so
You can mount it outside and not worry about it till the batteries
Are dead
If you do go on to Amazon right now you can get this for a hundred fifty bucks
And that's
Probably a much better deal or save yourself $30 there
So the base station would obviously be in your house somewhere connected to your network and then you have your camera outdoor so
I don't know in terms of functionality if it's as robust as maybe some of the other ones that you were talking about prior like enough about notifications inside
So you can get notifications on this thing
Arlo
Is Netgear
This isn't the camera itself doesn't
Talk to anything yet
I talked to the SmartThings guys and their kind of ion the stuff they're like oh that's that's a nice-looking camera
All right now Arlo doesn't
The Netgear guys
They've told me that
For now are those
Is closed system
So my hope
Because you know how much I hate things that don't talk to other things
Is it our love will open itself out cuz man
I would love to be able to pull
There's not a lot of great quality
Outdoor IP
He cameras
You know
Out there
I would love to be able to pull this
Into
Some of my other kind of home hub systems
Cuz I
You know I got a rooftop deck and I would love to be able to
See who's up there
Safety but to
If you like leave something up there
It is really a panda
The climb up all those stairs
To go like
Just check the roof so you could be like hey dude
Do I need anything up there no
That's just me being lazy again which is the primary reason to install Smart Home
X-ray
Okay
So
That concludes the
The spying on people portion of the crisp
Gift guide of the holiday gift guide
Let's go to
Light bulbs
What's your favorite light bulb
Doesn't have to be the same as
Kevin Ware back to you so I don't have a light bill this year
Because
I frankly I'm not really
Super stoked about any of the ones that I've tried
There's there's some new lightbulbs coming down the pike but they're not here yet so until they get here
I haven't found anything the only thing I really like
Enjoyous / are the Hue wireless light bulbs
Right and those were $99
They don't really actually tie and any of the other systems
Right now
And they're just fun
I'm kind of too expensive
Pics of a great gift I guess but
Sit there handy cuz you can put them anywhere in the house
Scannow anywhere you need to let you just put this bowl and
Flip the switch and
You good
Yep
Which I know is your thing
So
I'm less of a changing color kind of guy so that's why my favorite
Bald this year
Is the osram lightify bulbs
See I've got a couple of them in here I have
Also the Hues I got the
A couple trees and some other dogs
I like the Oz rooms they're a little more expensive than a typical white
LED bulb
But there's a reason for that
It's because they can be tuned to any color temperature from 2800 kelvins all the way up to will over 65
Hunter Calvin so what that means is
If you want a soft white
Yellowish light
You can do that with his balls you can tune the color down
If you want to bright white you can tune the color up a little bit more
You want daylight
Crank It Up you got full daylight
You can also dim this
You just can't change the color itself
White
Or
But how much are they
Well they go for about $30 and that's a lot for a white LED bulb
You know it's the heuiser
Probably little bit more but you can have any color practically up in the Spectrum
70 * 30 bucks they work with SmartThings with the wink hub
And if you have either of those who actually work
Through an Amazon Echo as well
And do they come and BR30 S&A 19th
I have the a 19th I think they come in for your 30s
All right maybe maybe I'll go
Usher
BR30 Obsession BR30 is are the big flat lights that you stick in Tennessee
The cans in a 19 with a tip
Typical
Light bulb shapes
Just for the people out there who
Like myself a few years ago did not
Speak fluent light bulb
Razorsync zigbee by the way so they work
With the Beast
Excellent
All right so that's are those are a lightbulb
Recommendations
And let us go now to
Hold let's go to my favorite room in the house
The kitchen
Which is where I keep my
Amazon Echo
Yeah so we've already talked about the Amazon Echo there's really no more to say
Except for
This last week
If you didn't have enough reasons to spend a hundred and seventy-nine
99 on the Amazon Echo to give it to someone you love this week
They announced and if this then that integration that's a little bit more complete
And so now you can actually connect the echo to your nest and you can actually tell it
Turn your desk tan without resorting to some sort of janky hack where you inside like
Your shopping list to your nest
Stinnett will turn it to 72 degrees
When you say
Add something to my shopping list
And that will make that
One thing happen
Now you can just tell it to turn your nest to 70
Degrees in
Boom
I've been using that new functionality ever since it came out
The past couple days
Love it absolutely love it
What's your favorite
Are the nice one that's the only one I'm using so far I haven't gotten
Around like making more triggers and whatnot but
You can do so many more things now because of this new trigger command
That was the one thing I was like missing from my my echo
I really wanted
Turn on the nest
And so now do you
I guess cuz you got an iPhone now that you're using
So you don't use the OK Google
Command anymore
No
At mostly is in my iPhone these days
Yeah I mean I could try the OK Google stuff too
National very easily but no
It's I'd rather I mostly my office and that's where the echo is
So boom
Every time we have the right we talked about the echo so many times in the past year
I think there's a good reason for it
It's a very compelling product for the price
And it keeps getting better
It does just go buy one already my goodness
We're just not going to let you
Put it down if you don't
So one thing I will tell you
To not purchase
For people you love this holiday season
I'm going to recommend you don't go
In on homekit stuff
Just yet
If you want to update your
Philips Hue Bridge
You've only got a couple more weeks before that discount
Runs Out
Remember
How to upgrade your Philips Hue how have you better go to the Philips Hue website
Cogat basically the Philips Hue upgraded
Hub for $40
Instead of $60 on that
Device
You got to do it before like the end of this month
Or while supplies last
I'm probably going to do it on a Feeling on the fence about it cuz the phone
The last time I tried out the review Persian
Bro, Integrations and I hated it
Yeah but
I got to do it
What's my job
For normal people
If you're not
You know if you're kind of on the fence about the Hub
You know
If you're basically like I wish I could go buy some more homekit stuff
Wait just wait
We've been waiting and I agree with you I think people should probably keep waiting
So if you don't have to move on it don't move on it
You're sitting on the fence on the Hub and you can afford waiting for 20 more dollars
You might as well
But if you're like $20 that's like
A fifth of a gadget
That's big money for me Stacy
Well
All right that's almost a light bulb
It is almost over how sad are we
So
And you know
If you're sitting there looking for
Toys
I'm going to recommend to microduino
We talked about them a couple episodes ago
I still love them you can get a starter pack
Microduino site for 99 bucks
They work with Legos
Their lair
Arduinos
The sensors
The work with Legos
What's not to love about that
I agree
There's also little bits
You know the cloud that's are great
They also have starter packs that start at $99
Perfect for kids I am going to get for my daughter a drop kitchen scale because I didn't get her one for her birthday
Still haven't heard the end of it
This was in August
My bad and drop did add cocktails to their mix
So
I can now make cocktails on the scale and
I think
Let's see
Hennything
House on the connected device front that were like
Excited about
I'm so you know what you know what it's not that far away from generous Consumer Electronics Show so I have a feeling
Febrile
Satellites look forward to
Man there's so many
Cool device
What is coming out
I mean
Guys
I'm even like
Things coming down the pike that are like
A lot smarter
Algorithms going nuts here we're going to see like next year
Doing the show like in 3 months
I would have a whole new class of devices
Is that I'd be like
Wow
They just cost a lot more
Where can I hold off
And
That's pretty much it I think so
Stuff your faces
Go shopping
Connect activity tracker and workout for dinner
Yes
That's probably the most mature class of devices we have out there
And
We will see you
After the holidays
Just
I think after this one
Yes
Isis like oh my gosh
Leaving for a month
No we are not will be back
Lucky you
All right
And there is no guess this week because we wanted you to enjoy your holidays and start your shopping so get on that
And thank you for listening