Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Excited
About
I think Intel's actually excited about the earnings
Announcing its shift away from the
PPC Market
Place which we all knew it had to
They said they would lay off 12
Is a lot
Not good
Good luck for those people
And let's talk about their Internet of Things
Because that's
What are the places nearby
Yeah it is some infectious their highest growth area out of the other lines
The business of misery said they're kind of
I wasn't getting the PC market
Putting
Less emphasis on it with other areas of opportunity
Out of style 13.7 billion dollars in Revenue they still took in 7.5 billion in there
Current Computing group
It's down
But that's okay
Is Internet of Things the Internet of Things group Revenue has
651 million which is up 4% sequentially and up 22%
Which is good and
Until Ashlyn calls it out saying this is their big growth area and where they are investing for the future
Is it actually earlier this week I met with rose schooler who's ahead of
She's in charge of data center
Enterprise pit of horizant
Platform for iot
Everything to do with the Enterprise and big business
Road maps
Corporate
Pikachu meaning
And bring out is
The recognized
Technology especially on the back end with regards to cloud data processing and security
Bring that too
Now Rose is a really honest person so she basically told me she's like
We are trying to get to
50%
When we going to incorporate
Corporate client
And we're just not there yet
And she's right
Right now if you're doing an enterprise-level
Deployment where you're trying to
I don't know you can do all kinds of
Are still highly custom jobs that require systems integrators
That's just not going to be
A business
I mean it'll be any type of business but it's not the kind of business
Pregnancy huge
From so
Rose and I talked about getting to that kind of scalable reusable
Enterprise internet
Until school is
Platforms
Sanders groups
And their technology
Sew-in getting Developers
So that's that
I don't know if that really helps
It's not a bad message it's actually
Quite good for Penthouse point of view there if they're banking on more than they're still at
Yeah well they have for now I'm in
Recognizing the big trends in the industry so it's just a question of
Christopher companies
Or
Yeah you can go to Honeywell
If your
That's probably the real question
Twitch
Interesting in the next 10 years
It's almost funny to look back at some of the big
Computer / platform companies
From 30 years ago how
You know the PC really helped make them
And now they're struggling innocence
But they are pivoting and Reinventing themselves
Shifting assets and Investments
It's just kind of having grown up in that era
When they were all up and coming in big
You're watching it happen
Which is another way of saying getting
In other news
Which is not necessarily A
Household
But they make amplifiers
And RF components for a bride
There's actually some silicon a bears in the
Echoing other things
So
But
What does it mean
It basically means that we're going to start seeing
Consolidation
Around Radio
Technologies
And
Zippy is
Good that because it's all so it's on the same protocol radio layer as thread
So
My guess is
Is corvo seize an opportunity here
There are in the space specially at the component level in
Brinkley for the internet of things a lot of the radio stuff is probably going to be kind of
Martha component-level
Overtime
So this is a good move for the zip because
Well I read
Cordless betting on it being
Will it be I don't know but
It's interesting. Just letting it run numbers green pee cuz
Shipped over 100 million
Zigbee chips in the smartphone market which is why I mean just
That's a lot inside the Comcast
RF remote so instead of using infrared
Set the Comcast Xfinity remote
Okay so it's a wireless not an infrared
You install a home audio system in there like I put a screen in here
Yeah we can extenders
Can I have a little sensor out there for your IR remote cix
Those days are over I think
So yes
Green tea can I guess corvo is betting on that
And in some ways I might be bad for the market like if you're big
Radio company in your leg
Silicon labs
What do I have to offer other than just this
Space component
Cuz that's that's a different world of chips than you know
Being high up in the staff
Yeah can we talk about chips a little bit more just real quick
Always
Just before the show you shared some interesting information with me about a chip in your smart
Citizen Beach it won't even better Segway what the heck happened to your light bulb
Just just read your Tweet
All right
I haven't
UShip
Espino People Get Ready
Get ready
Alright so here's between
The 20-year lifespan on my smartphone at the two-year lifespan
The radio inside
80 more years
What
Well
Essentially this the lights which means
When I talk to my lights
Spell for example using
The echo
I will say turn on kitchen
Well actually I'll say turn off kitchen
Everything but one life
Turns off
You sure it's not just
Something set up in the with the Hub or anything it's definitely the ball but you switch sockets or actually reset
All the light bulbs
And it didn't
Reset
So that's got to be paid like 40 or 50 bucks for a
A basic this is the original $15 GE link bulb
Too bad
Dollar so7
When I realize I realized
So basically I got about
18 months
This actually happened
Tutu lights that I got
Originally and I returned
Elderly on the process
Martin super smooth
Last year or so
And I don't have the packaging anymore because
Do you know after a year York
It's just clutter at that
I'm going to have to pick up
I'm probably going to put in an oz
Yay yay
No no I haven't
Idaho
You could I could send you mine
So yes in this gets to
A bigger problem for the internet
Once we talked about it
But it's
A lot of these things are in your house
They're designed to last a really long time but the components inside of them
You know there
Their Hardware
It's probably not going to last that long
So
How do we
Yeah I mean I've got
A closet full of dead devices which everything to go with bring to the electronics recycling
If they have it
Something
Computers
Tablas whatever it may be
5 6
7 years before
Some chipset went bad or some
Something happened
Yeah when you're talking about things you put in your house that you expect to last a long long time ago
Switchable doorbell
Stats problem
So that the next problem that I'm about to do
Is it's also a pain to
Unhook these from a system so when I'm going to take that bulge out
I'm going to have
It's not as simple as just replacing a bulb and everything
Discovery
This is probably really first real world pop problems but they're real problem
First world
And so that's one thing I will say that I did it I talk to a company named eco
Which
I did profile in my newsletter
If you decide that
That's okay because this company is selling
Hot swappable light switches
Little boxes
Modular switches that fit into boxes the boxes are wired to your
Electric electoral system but the switch itself
Pop out
Exactly and there's
New homes will have
Basically smart bulbs
And the cool thing is that the founder of this company
And I were talking and he's he explained that it's hot swappable and he went with the
Grey modular system because
He knew that a lot of the technologies that we have to
Today
Are not going to be the technology
5 or 10
Different Technologies
Protocols
Wireless
Whatever yeah absolutely
It's a pain to wire those
Well that's funny you say that because
For my 2010 installation of the insteon
Stuff I still have
Three insteon switches hardwired in my house
Even though I'm not running an insteon system at all I'm just using his radio switches obviously
If they're still little LED on their tail
What's the latest
Honor office should be on or off
I just didn't want to be bothered on wiring a butt with Chico's doing is
Okay.
Popping a different module
If you decide like
But no longer Z-Wave caliper
Is a loser
People
Selling a strictly to contractors at this point
Strictly to builders it's actually a
Prototype
Right now
It's a switch box
An electrical box
The shell
The frame that sits inside the wall
Electrical wiring
Bright
You could that mean if you're doing like a
Reset a retrofit of
Your house
Remodel
Just the remote
Expensive
Alice nightmare if you're doing that you could probably
Try for this but I'd wait a little longer because right now they're still testing
Macy's I would be interested in as an end-user consumer because I would like to swap out different things in but not well
This looks interesting because they're switch the hot swappable switch has a capacitor glass touchscreen
And that they have three different kinds right now one is like a basic dimmer
When is
I think
A couple different options in the one is a 4
Program for things in it
Four options like
The switch that you went to the room that you're
The light switches in but also like a button
Controlling the whole house
I'm turning it off
And
Again I think it's a smart way to go about it it's not as fancy as a lot of the light switches that we
Today
I'm thinking about like the most mainstream consumer is
Future-proof in terms of the technology
Tunic set like they're not interested in time is light switch is to
HBC system
That's not something
Other builders are really big they're looking for ways to offer
Customers services
Make a charge for the
So you could see your Builder
Echo Plus something else
Creating a software for
For your home
You passed $10
No
I know you want to
It's something to think
I already thought about it and
Sorry I'm not subscribing to my house
Well you know
My friend is so I'll give you
Sister-in-law
Pest Control built into the wall so it's kind of like those
You remember those old school indoor vacuum
Full House
I don't know what those things are called
Pest control company comes in and
Basically
Pest Control
Delivery thing to like this to becomes
And it runs throughout their whole body
Deception is the home
Daughter got a cut of
Whatever
Company is delivering at service today
So it may not be as simple as a subscription to your home it may be like a 2-year dusita installer
I don't know
I know you still don't like it
I'm also.
Poison Spa
Yeah
Andre Rieu should be
Leary
Why were
Random everywhere subject
Cuz we are at their nose
I found another use for the Amazon tap
So
Tapped is
But I ran into a person
I was going to say that's really good that you found
And if you don't have
I'm still not sure I buy one
Here it goes
Because I thought this was worthwhile
The top which is the portable Amazon Echo like
Device that you have
Talk to you as opposed to just talk to you it's not always listening
This guy
Cuz there's a little rubber sling that
Kids it is can't actually run around the house carrying it with him and basically they
They bring their music with them and
Bring it for like
Whatever else they were
I want to do with you
Oh no I haven't imaginative
Echo actually broke
He was one of the early
People who on an echo
When it died in
His whole family was bereft
Surprise kids with their tabs
Okay
We see that it's not on
Let's send you to they send them to a link
And the link basically had to reorder a power supply it came for
Like the next day
They were going to send
That's impressive
So there's your Echo if it breaks
Cuz apparently they've got
The kids are getting a lot of really good data from this
Or they
After discovery
The tapster
Let's go onto things you discovered
Oh yeah
Yes yes yes so
Avery Dennison now there's a name that I wouldn't normally equate with technology nothing against them just
Office supply typing labels you going to Staples Office Depot
Will do really is for everything out because Avery Dennison and everything
Are going to put
10 billion pieces of apparel into the world of iot with
Smartlabel Spacek
This is kind of interesting and not something I saw it coming at all
No I thought if we were going to get smart clothing it was going to be through like weird Fabrics like project Jacquard or there was a new antenna
It was announced earlier this week
It's obviously research that could also like
Communicate
Wirelessly
This is it this is now
And
And I should also mention that everything is
It's a you prefer minute
Everything within
But no other house
Starts with an E and Annabelle
So
It's it's primarily I think it
Right now it's primarily about
Authenticity
Counterfeiting
Yeah and I seen labels attached
Certain things I got bought by Liverpool Jersey or anyone Arizona Cardinals Jersey and it comes a little
Navigation hologram with a number
If you want to check on SimCity you can go online and punch the number and all that
Gets rid of all of the number punching and then so on
Yes and you know there's actually
Another company
That is working with them
Jack Daniels and other liquor manufacturers to prevent like counterfeit
So they're actually putting labels
Alcohol bottles of alcohol
To prevent
So that's a similar thing
So
Sears hardware
Please read the label and they're hoping to
For third-party applications
Reorder something
Favorite white shirt with
Smart label get stained
Checking inventory we got one
I think it is kind of cold because it's again not from a
Company that I would traditionally have even thought about
Getting to the space
It's not actually that
Crazy they didn't have to invest in like crazy
Stop they're doing it
Do it with inventory tracking now
From the manufacturing standpoint but now it's coming out to the consumers
This is kind of fun I don't know how worried if we're going to just see it like as a counterfeit prevention method or if it's
Which actually is a
Yeah
I mean for me at you know there's only five Arizona Cardinals fans on the East Coast so we like it
Somebody has their Jersey on and I my jersey on maybe there's an applicant
Tell me the
The right around the corner go have a beer with him
Weight when they just like
On the same day the Cardinals were
Airplane window
I don't just wear it then
I'm a fan
All right
Cardinals fans
Who's out there
Give me a shout out
And if you do
I got you a but if you do I will show you the little device I have in my hand right now
Please tell me a joke
Child friendly
I mean you can like
I suppose
Okay yeah
I know is child friendly and if it's one of their kickstarter's that I back that actually came through cuz it's so awesome
Nothing against
This is the pine64 missile attack a Raspberry Pi
Is $15 the base price is $15 with a small board
Thumbs up
Quad core arm processor
Half a gram
Ethernet port HDMI couple USB ports whatnot
I actually
Moved up to the
Highest paid model which was only $29
That got me
Oh yeah
What's your secret for 29 bucks
Mehandi all aboard with
The same chipset in all that
All of these have 4K video output with
Pretty impressive switch low power
Obviously
More line with
Computing projects
Like the Raspberry Pi
And less so with say chayote in Arduino
You could I'm still thinking about that once I get the
Linux install a nest
Of using the openhab apis and
Playing around with openhab
Interface for Smart Homes to see what I can do and just run everything off this little guy here
Remind me
We should have talked about
Until recently started shipping
That is a $15 board
Futures oh my gosh are you ready
The quark
Yeah I think it looks just like a little bored I have on my closet shelf height are they came to
Get around to it yet
You got one of these
I did I got the little devil
Just a little bit kid
This is like super behind the times
Because like I can buy
I think it's actually a $25 Raspberry Pi that has a 64-bit capable
It's like 1.2 gigahertz I think
This isn't a computer
This is what this is
Yeah this is bridging physical and digital
And I have Arduino set somewhere
And then I got this and unfortunately I just been busy and haven't taken out of the box yet but
Maybe in a week
I was excited
I'm looking for
Quark
Containing
Siri which is the
Sprint
As a friend
I don't have the other until board in my hand but
It's a frame of reference that Intel board is about
Third the size of this
Computer boards I have in my hand right now and this is pretty Smogon I think most people probably of an idea of how big a Raspberry Pi as this until
The board is less than half a size
Source Mall
Incidence
$15
If you don't you're feeling like you want to play with Intel's efforts
Just to see what it's
Got offer after Edison
This would be what
Okay let's
Talk really fast
Because there's a couple things that happened with Hue Lights
Fair is coming up next week
Light bulb
So we won't be complaining about lights
New radios hope
Hopefully CrossFit
But
What's happening is Philips Hue is actually they updated
Their app
And they did a couple things with it
They changed
Color
I will tell you why in a minute
2 they upgraded their security protocols
They basically did a token
Program with their third party
Partners partners
And most almost everybody
Has opted in
So
They've been working on this for a while so now what you got is basically a much more secure way for your Hue Lights to talk to any part
Cars that also use you like
Hue Disco
There's a real big popular one that
Next Syracuse to the
Apple
ITunes
Right now
So all of that
And the reason why it's happening is Hughes
About to launch a second-generation app
So that is why it changed the color this one now is going to be gray so your existing Hue app
And then your next gen Hue app
It's going to be
Knock knock
Not great
And you have either of those two
And I'm hoping this is coming soon and will find out more about it
But you know that's something to look forward to or
Deceiver I'm not sure
If you are a
Q
Aficionado
This is not the result of any attack exploit her insecurities it's just them being proactive right
Right I asked
Nope we're just
Just trying to get things
Good on that
So yeah it is good
Because the last thing you need is to have
Lions at these things out
The good news is that your kitchen
Secure
Yes yes my kitchen is the most secure
I shouldn't say if I will through the Brightside
All right
I think we should probably in the show
I have some great gadgets for you next week
Wildlight Fair news
Started playing with openhab but there's no pressure just yet
John Butler
Who's in charge of all of Ford's connected car platform
So
We basically talked about how to build a business for The Internet of Things
Specifically how far is building it
How their thinking about the car
It's a phone interview
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast to tell you two things the first is that I've launched a week
Weekly Newsletter devoted to the internet of things that you can sign up for it Stacey on iot. Com
That's Stacey on iot. Com the second is that we're now accepting as of The Internet of Things
Broadcast we have packages for big companies and startups so if you are interested please email Andrew at
Iot podcast. Com
Back to the show
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Today's guests
Is Don Butler who is the executive director of connect
Did vehicle and services
Ford Motor Company
You guys may have heard of
So thanks for coming on the show today
Date it's great to be with you
I am super excited about this
I will confess
I don't drive
I am really excited about all the programs
So you guys have time from the integration with the Amazon Echo 2
T-shirt leasing program in Austin
So
Let's talk about what do you do on a day-to-day basis
What's the leader for connected vehicles within the company I charged with overseeing
All aspects of that within our business
And so that involves
The
Consumer and understanding
You know where they looking for what kind of experiences can we deliver
I'm a vehicle side what kind of Hardware is necessary inside the vehicle to make sure that that takes plays Harley designs
Software
Communication systems
To take advantage of that
Then working with network providers in terms of
The data transport mechanisms for the cellular or Wi-Fi and then
Integrating app with our backyard it system
To both deliver services as well as
To receive data from Vehicles as well
Facilitating
Remote control vehicle
It keeps me busy throughout my day
For sure
Okay so
What's
Idea that
Ford
Has really kind of changed
Maybe for years
You guys have really moving from
You know thinking about
You know attaching a phone or something
It's not working with my phone in the car
Telematics
To this concept of Transportation as a service
How is your thinking evolved when did you guys
Yeah I die Che
If you had to 10 point in origin it might go back to
Want to talk
That built Ford gain at Mobile World Congress
2 years back
In Barcelona where he
Really in a sentence
Took
His great-grandfather's vision of
I'm open highways For All Mankind and so to the Model T was the
Single-point solution for that affordable transportation that was available and accessible to
You to everyone
And just kind of thinking and projecting forward and looking at some of the trends that are happening in terms of globalization and terms
Job organization along with that globalization in a few
Project forward hour
Kakarot
Vehicles are operating in a week There's roughly a billion vehicles
Better on the global roads today and he Protec forward
Even the growth rates of where we are and would be
You another billion Vehicles added by 2030 and they're just just isn't the infrastructure for that
We're also looking at
Changing Dynamics in terms of consumer
Looks at Albertson's coming together and thinking about our own business and the fact
We
Defense counsel the hardware and we're beginning to shift from
Kind of just that Hardware Focus to thinking about not just the vehicle of a single-point solution not Jeff
You know the only way that you can benefit from afford is to owner or lease it but
Really doing
The business ads
Not just providing Mobility
From that perspective
Let's talk about the hardware size
Because this is
Ford 500
Point five billion dollars
Right
That is
It's a lot of
Switching from that kind of hardware
Investment
Because they're fat
At least in the near-term going to stop making cars
Very excited
How do you switch
From making Hardware in all the investment
This other
Investment in
Software and services
It's still managed to
You don't make your investors happy
Absolutely we need to make our investors happy in that
Yellow hundred forty-nine billion dollars of Revenue
It's certainly very important to us in end as
We
I'll look at these emerging businesses one thing that
That Mark has been very clear to us about Mark Barfield or CEO
Is that we cannot
Forget
Aqua business
That we see in this inflection point that were talking about
It will play itself out over time
It's so it's not as if two years from now
You know there aren't going to be any Automotive Sales
Did the projections that will continue to have
You're fairly consistent
5 to 6%
Grills and we go forward but none the less we do recognize that
Go forward
The landscape in that Matrix
Revenue and earnings opportunities
It will need to shift
One perspective that we have is if you look at the
China decor
How would you say the hardware
Automotive
2.3
A trillion dollars of a combined Global Revenue
And our share of that is roughly about 6
Sr global
Market share what we call transportation services
Any way of getting around short of
Jet travel
You know that's another
Five Point
Australian dollars
Of Revenue
In our share of that is 0
And so if you think about it
Dis
Core Business that we have continuing to be great at that continue 8 to deliver
Cheaper products that people love their funded dry great to look at
But also looking at the transportation services Landscaping understanding what role
You know could we possibly play there
Okay in a lot of companies are trying to do this right now so
You
Luckily Are Not Alone
How do you align your company and how do you think about
Management structures
Settings
Investing in these new areas Casino
Ford is a huge company but it doesn't have infinite resources
Yeah and it is a challenging and I don't want to minimize it by saying yeah we'll just grab Tommy's emerging opportunity
Put up what we call Ford smart Mobility as an umbrella
Or each of those activities but then we got a step further and said
Because
Some of these things are going to be so different
Then the core business
Right
Those processes
That I talked about earlier in terms of what it takes
To each your 30000 equal parts come together in a well-integrated high-quality way with a
Absolute safety
In with absolute Integrity right those processes
Don't necessarily s***
Me and some of these new emerging spaces because you do need to move a much more frequent
Or much more rapid Pace because
The ability to
Experiment in to learn into engine case
Alright it's okay
It's not okay to feel when you are putting an airbag inside a vehicle and you got to make sure that it operates right it's not
Okay to feel they're right until you got to have a rigorous process
It is okay to stay all potentially even in in the experiment
Instrument in Austin in learning about shared Leasing and learning about how do you
You know how do you slice up
I'll at least amongst different people how do you allocate who gets to use the vehicle how do you make sure that that process works
Right Where I Need to learn
Until what we decided to do is set up
Separate limited liability Corporation
I called Ford smart Mobility
Jim Hackett has been named as the chairman of that entity
He going to be putting together his own team beginning with the CEO and then others
Come inside our core business today that will move over underneath into that entity in lb
Actually probably a lot more that will come in from the outside and bringing in new ideas bringing in new ways of thinking
And the way that that organization moves and the way that it will be constructed will be much more nimble
How much more oriented toward Innovation experimentation
Learning moving quickly
And it's obviously going to have some investment associated with it and we kind of gone through
No one exercise to understand what's going to be critically important for us as we go forward in our business
Fortunately in terms of some of the things that we've been able to do in terms of cost control and efficiency
And being very
Intentional without corn dust
I'm looking at things
On a global basis
And you know reducing redundancies and driving those things that help us to be Capital efficient
You know we're able to allocate
Your money to this new element to be the emerging opportunities in, set up
Separate entity
Separate but still connected to the core business because
We want to benefit from the learning that happen there and their
Maybe something that happened in that emerging business.
Ultimately become part of our Core Business there may be something that happened in a merging business
She's as well but
But related
And want to set it up in a way that
We can
Forbidden city
From let's just say the
Stability of the mothership without being encumbered by the gravity of the Mothership
So on this
Spin out this new company for your Innovation what do you need
What kind of Technologies are you guys looking
So, technology standpoint in terms of the things that we think we need
CertainTeed
Continuity and all the aspects related
The conductivity in
Wireless communication
But you know the latest versions of Bluetooth and looking at
Things like dedicated short-range communication so now 5.9 gigahertz and
Things like vehicle-to-vehicle communication
Increase computer capability on board vehicle so more powerful microprocessors definitely
In terms of broad categorization and some of the things are happening in the tectonic technology front voice
Invoice based interaction
Increasingly important for us as you can imagine
When in a vehicle first
Safe and secure as your operating the vehicle
Continue to operate the vehicle today and then till we get to the day of fully autonomous but
Voice enables you didn't you know control and interact in a way that keeps your
Your eyes on the road and your hands on the wheel and then
In addition to those technologies that are doing things that make sense
Coming out on the standpoint things like lidar and sensors cameras in
Being able to characterize on Burnet and react to it
You know you're in an appropriate way
All right and let's talk about some of the things you've already implemented so for example you guys did this integration
With the Amazon Echo
We named her on the show
We don't want to set up your Echo
You guys have done this
This was
Rate this was at CES everyone was excited
Can you talk about
How you think
Best way to do that
Sure it's so what we demonstrated at CES
When Amazon was around the Echo and
We out to actually be launching
Service
Where Amazon Echo later this year
In the whole idea is to just understand
How are people interacting with
The world around them in with their home
Book a music and with their services
Attracted up
Amazon Echo
What's the network that was being built up
Around Echo & the difference
Skills at work
That we would have access to just by connecting with Amazon in this network
Is a way for us to a build
Accessibility inside the vehicle
Without necessarily needing to Plum each of those individual kind of lines right itself
Certainly will do some things with Wayne can and will do things with others but if there's already
Then why not take advantage of that
So let's let's have some fun here let's talk about the future of the
The car because
I drive it
It is
Superfund because it
It's constantly changing
A huge learning curve for me because it is constantly changing
For some reason the temperature
Temperature moves around
Display
Now it's over here
I don't mind that but it is a little
It's a weird to get used to having a car that
That that like the car of the future
I should I should probably mention that
First
No I get it I get it
Fisher
Very futuristic today but I do
In a self-driving
Cars a lot of the automatic braking
Technology
You're going to feel really commonplace
Artuso
Where do you think
The future of the car is
Is it
You know right now I've got two in my garage I really love to only have one
You know I can't imagine giving up a dedicated car but I'm oldest so
I don't know
Where does where does
I think there are a number of different scenarios that that will play out and I think it will depend on
You know what your lifestyle is
And then where you live
So I can proceed
In urban environments for instance
And you know highly congested situations that
Or number of different reasons it it will make sense for people
Did not necessarily own a vehicle right they will
Potentially the biggest
Consumers of
Transportation as a service
Ansell
One of the things that
That we're working on within that within that context is how do we
Continue to deliver a Ford
Experience
When someone doesn't necessarily own a Ford vehicle when they may be a user or a passenger within a Ford V-8
And that's one of the reasons that we introduce fortaz
Which
Onyx face looks like just
Another mobile app but it's really a platform for us
To deliver Mobility Services and so whether that's
Using sync connect them in remotely connecting with a vehicle that you happen to all and and or
You know you're traveling but we got your profile information and so we understand what your commute is and we can
I'll help you with the best way to get
To you know for instance you are at your office on that day and so whether it's
You know taking a train and then a box
And they're doing a shared ride or today hey the shared-ride would be the best route for you
If you are you know that you're someone that lives in Suburbia and you got a family then
At least for the next few years I imagine it will be somewhat difficult to
Think about swapping car seats in and out of a number of different Vehicles riding so I think through it
The traditional ownership or leasing model wolf will still be prevalent there
In all of those situations what you'll have it in
Vehicles that will absolutely improve and get better over time I think there's actually a lot that we can learn from Tesla and turn to look
They're doing
Auburn soccer updates
In our case you know we want those updates to be at seamless
If possible and Adnan
Life interrupting that possible
And we had Josh
Gorman from the cavalry
On the show
It was 2014
It was all about
Protecting
Car is kind of a digital asset
And iiii will be curious
Has Ford
Are you guys looking at that and say hey we're going to take this
We've had a focus on
Security for quite some time
It's not something that will just
Waking up to you at this moment even even going back
To you know the early days of up to you at Century right we had rolling codes to protect Security even with
In 2007 write a firewall between
War of the information and
Entertainment area of a vehicle in the communication Boston
Separated
Typical firewall from the
More important
Vehicle control sidelight powertrain like the chassis
Control
And even as we move into this environment we're certainly
Surface
Is it worth growing in terms of increasing Connections in the vehicle both within the vehicle wirelessly and
Outside the vehicle on a cellular basis
We are very very conscious of putting mechanisms in place to protect the vehicle as a digital asset
The data as a as an asset that must be
Secured as well
And we are constantly evolving
And improving our systems were constantly looking at ways of with lyrics
Code signing encryption to
Firewall to understanding you know the various
Attacks that have been promulgated on others and
Not just saying Old Tube after that but looking at it and understanding exactly what happened and then going back and looking at our own system
I was just something that we would have been vulnerable to
Is there something that would be similar to this that would have presented a vulnerability to us
Bright plus after they hacked
Why are you were you were all over that
To understand exactly what they did and how they did it
And
Yeah we weren't again
Acceptable to that particular attack but
All they did cause us to look at some things that were doing and in the way that we'd engineered some of our Solutions and just
Add that extra bit of rigor in terms of of controls and end up some things that we could look at to say
And what vulnerable to this one but you know what
Here's something that we could look at it something that we could change
Security by obscurity for you guys
With your your billion cars on the road
Price of success
Okay yeah
True
So as connected era and you guys are
What is Fords
Adidas Advantage how does that shift from Manufacturing
How do you say
Biggest
Actually is our brand
And it's the truck
That we have with the Ford brand and
With
The
Relationship actually that consumers have formal enough
Going back more than a hundred years
The Challenge and the opportunity that we have is to
Turn those
Sort of infrequent get kind of explicit references in Gulfport at the time that
Potentially I buy my vehicle or
Time that I service my vehicle for instance 2
A couple different bats number one
The more than $900 a year that people spend inside their vehicle and the opportunity that we have to
Improve that experience to make it a more delightful experience in also
To learn and gather data from those experiences again with the informed consent of our customers
To help us not only prove the vehicle but again improve the things that they do in the vehicle right helping you interact with your home
Voltmeter Amazon
As well looking at
How can we
Become part of
A person's life if they don't necessarily own afford
Look for cash as a Mobility application understanding how we can facilitate Transportation even if you don't
Because we think
Again
That is actually our brand it's the truck that we have in our brand and that's what we've been able to deliver
And really kind of you relate to Consumers on that basis
Awesome
So much for coming on the show today I have learned a lot
Stacy it's been terrific to be with you
That's it for this week's show
Thanks for listening and we hope to see you next week
In the meantime
Please sign up for my newsletter