Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a great show
For you I know I always say that
It is it is always great
It is fantastic
6o
We thought we kick it off with the
The story for the New York Times
Which is
Just how much power do your electronics use
Kodak put
And the answer is
A lot
Good question
Yes it's great
Kevin you said that you actually started deal out so the story is actually all about
Vampire power draw
Which was a big deal a couple
A couple years ago because of steady came out showing that your game consoles in your
Cable boxes
Just sucked power like there was no tomorrow
That does kind of
Version that we got here
The newest kind of
Twisting the story
Is
The burgeoning kind of smart devices
Because they're connected
Are always on because they got you no Wi-Fi connection they need to maintain and they need to send data back
They're also
You get that always listening kind of affecting that takes a small power draw to
So
Yeah the time study shows some actual power drains on devices where
Most people probably think while I'm not using my cable box about watching TV so it's not using any power but
Perfect example is the Samsung cable box and then not paying on Samsung this is pretty prevalent in the industry
They use a 26 Watts
The power when it's off
Turn phone off and not recording
When you're actually using it when you're watching TV
And recording something
Additional to watts of power so it's
Most of the power
Consumption
Is happening all the time with a device like that
And as you said Stacy you got always on devices connected devices that
Many updates are there always listening or
In the case of cable box it's getting guide information which is
Just changing every 30 minutes as you know show cycle through
List of ads oven and I knew this a couple years back
It was a big meme about the whole vampire power Drano people finally started understanding that device
Isis use power even when they're cooling Court off
So the two ways you can deal with us one is it just obviously on plug
My device
But I took a more
And I guess I'll call it a technical approach anyway I can spend money I do
I bought these so-called smart strips
Which there power outlets in a Rossini Stacy
I have
Yeah
Oh okay I have one almost in every room of the house and I know that adds up and it yeah there's a cost-benefit analysis of
How much does electricity cost
Versus paying for these things still use less electricity
We won't get into the mat
Regardless
What disease do is they have a master Outlet
And you plug in a a device into that and when that device is turned on like in my case
In my office right now
This iMac I'm using is the master device when I turn the iMac on
The smart strip says okay now we can let power flow to all the other Outlet
So
Other peripherals and they have connected that I wouldn't want draining power when the iMac is off
Now start using power as they should
When I shut my iMac off
The smart strip says no more power for anything else connected to this thing
There are some hot Outlets as well so you don't have to
We totally depend on a single device
Comes in handy for say living room situation
Your TV when your TV is on you can want
If your Blu-ray player your DVD player to your stereo
Your Apple TV
You want all those on as well when the TV is off you don't need those on
Suck my TV is my main device and the smart turn my family room for Snapple so
It kind of hopefully save me money in the long run
So I just looked at the 10 Outlet smart strip
On Amazon is
Wow it seems high compared to what I paid but
You know
Yeah there's a bunch of
So actually has one
Maybe slightly
Another option is just to have a
Straight up switch with an on-off outlet and then you can just turn those off
This one I like because it's little bit more automated
You don't have to actually reach behind something and be like
Now I want all my stuff
Exactly
It's okay to just happens you turn on the master device and
Advantages manage for yuan Roth
So in the other thing
That we talked about doing his I had installed a device called a curb
I actually had it installed by a certified doula
Electrician
I'm in my house that tracked my energy use
Buy Appliance
And that was really interesting cuz I saw what was sucking power all the time
I saw the impact from changing my incandescent to LED
And they have a couple of these kind of devices
And even a nap
So curb is a device
Anime
Quick ask your card gets installed at the circuit breaker level
So you have to have an electrician do it
Unless you were
Really really comfy
Barbara Stager
With your
Add your circuit box
Actually take the data from
Each
Individual circuit
They have a one 4:16 and I think one for 8
So you can actually see
Your air conditioning and how much that's using
Versus something
Actually two of those
There's also another device you can install in your circuit
Am I just make
Panel
The Box the rectangular thing with the switches
Switch off
So the device
Just call dinner Rio and that also installs there that doesn't actually
Deal with each individual breaker
It's for the whole box and it measures electricity consumption
I'm just going to call and fancier algorithms it's
Trying to detect
The patterns in various
Types of energy flows to tell you what's happen
So that's another thing
You can use
Overall energy consumption
Figure out what's sucking
I just got turned onto an app that will help you as well
It's called chai energy chai like the tea
It's a free app
And the way gets the data it actually reads in What's called the green button data which is the like this
Smart meter type information that's being fed to electricity providers
So why let them have all that information
Chai actually guess it the same way they get it
And shows you graphs and such on your phone of electricity usage
And gives you ways to save says maybe your AC is running more than should buy
Compare the average Etc
Unfortunate for me even though this does work on IOS and Android
My electricity provider is not yet participating in
Either getting the data or sharing the day that was chili
I can't say I've tested it
But I should also mention if you want to get the data I think on your own
They do so it's called the chai energy Pro
Which is a box don't know how much it cost
But it will actually read it directly from the smart meter
Itself as opposed to getting it
Through the electricity provider Alex it's only $50
The curb which I think
Expensive I don't know if it's that expensive but
I'm am looking at
While you're doing that the difference between the chai energy app and the trainer do pro as obviously there's Hardware buy with the pro
Chai energy app only get you
Once a day energy usage monitoring it's not constantly pinging and pulling and getting information
The pro Hardware device
Is real-time energy usage monitoring
You can even tag appliances so you can specifically say
I don't know how much power the dishwasher uses and so on so forth so
Said some interesting intelligence
Yes and your Bo is $180
On Amazon plus you're going to need the electrician in
Install that
And
Curb it was hundreds so I don't remember how many hundreds
And it may vary by how many
Sensors you actually put into the breaker as well
It is $400
So that's the sick
Zones
So that's not
Crystal Tarot
But the 200 is the
The 2 pack for large
Looks like I have to
Yeah
I wonder how it would be actually interesting to compare this $50
Chai energy Pro
2 m solution
Just because the massive cost difference
And see that the data is
Any better more fine and so on a more expensive one
I will call them bingo
There we go right there also say that
Check how much your
Devices are consuming
With the WeMo Insight switch and actually there are a couple
Smart outlet
Let's I just happen to have a WeMo insight
Text Wichita
What does this
It also is
By the way
But
When you plug a device and you can see how much power
It's using
For a while but now
For next week show I'm going to plug
My echo and I'm going to plug a couple other kind of connected devices into this and I'll take some
Readings measurements and we'll we'll come back to this because
It sucks being a lot of money for electricity
The story says that about a quarter of residential home energy use
Tron from Vampire power
Sounds high but I mean I'm sure there are cases of that and I
Is there's a lot of cons
Yeah it adds up
Okay
So that's your grim
How much are spending on electricity
You're not even using it
Moving right along
We're going to talk about
Open
Thread
Wait wait is that like thread from nest
Except now it's open source and you can pull it down from
And
The catch it so there's a couple things
Cuz they catch
Before I get to the catch let's just stay with
This is
Basically
The thread
Protocol in
Prayers because you may not remember thread as a wireless protocol so it's like zigbee and Z-Wave
Except it is using the 802.
Oh man I hated seeing
So it's the same radio IEEE radio standard that should be uses
Except
Thread is both a mesh
And it's also IPv6 compatible
That means any device that uses thread can go straight to the internet
Itself without going through a hub
Friend so those are the things his nest Samsung silicon labs freescale
Bigassfans a couple other companies created this couple
How to say was
2 years ago now
Time flies when you're having fun and
They introduced a certification program last November
For this and kind of devices are coming out
So
What they've done now is there like
Hey
Momentum we got it
Let's open this up to the community
Your devices will still have to get certified
So basically what you're doing is you are
Able to download this
Work it into your devices but they are going to still have to
But if you want them to be
Which is slightly better I think from a financial standpoint cuz I think
Beforehand you had to pay to have access to the specs of
Thread
Yeah
So now I assume you
Don't you just need a paper certification
Bright I'm guessing that was a
The control thing
But this is good news because
Thread is actually a really useful
It's got a different kind of mash than the Bluetooth
Mesh
It can handle more devices basically is the bottom line
And it's a little bit more modern with the IPv6
Compared to say pee in the zigbee guys have actually done a really close alignment with
The thread group
So
Which is smart I think it's super smart so some zigbee devices
Will be
Thread compatible
The chipset is backwards compatible
You know what else is compatible
My onhub router which is a Google router
I'll have the thread compatible radio in it
Using it as far as I know
But maybe they will and now that this is open-source another peep
Download it
That would be cool don't forget to that next week which
I will not be here on the show
Because
I will be at Google IO
And I
I think there's something on the schedule or in the sandbox demonstration areas about open thread
There is
Maybe you'll get to see that
Next week show we're going to have yonko
Another word
Lake who actually is at CES Asia this week
And
We're going to have lots of fun on that so
Sneak peek
Okay next
Topic
What is RNA
Stop it Kevin
How about the Almond router then we got a question about that off
Couple weeks ago
What's up with that
I've seen all these new router kind of things happening in
Nothing from them
So
4 people who aren't aware of the Almond router is from a company called securifi it came out probably like
Two or three years ago actually with
The idea that the router is the hub for the smart home and they had all these radios at a zigbee I think they might have had a Z-Wave version
You don't think they were just chugging along but it was also pretty kind of
Easy interface
So Cut Above the modern routers that
Well they got a new router
Actually they call it a home wi-fi system
Abby Allman
And this may sound familiar to people this implementation I'll basically
It is a as you said it's a lot of the smart home stuff in there we'll talk about that in a minute but it's a router for your home available for pre-order
Will retail for 149 99
You can get a bundle a pack of three of them with Mesh networking
For 299 Grand Prix motor and retails for 399
So obvious comparisons to the ear OST
Thank you
Obvious comparisons
To that
But what's different here I don't think those
Other products have physically radio inside nor do they have touch screens and
And so on so forth so
This is kind of interesting
In addition to the ziggurat inside you're like okay well maybe we're going to do with it
It actually and I've done the sound off
Three other routers the new one the Almond plus as well as
The Omen 2015
They all now work with
The Amazon Echo
So it's almost
Yeah it's interesting that they created a skill set
We talked about skills before this small program that you can enable on your Echo
Use voice commands
So what they've done here is they've
I must you like it if this then that approach we can create rules
Through the
Skillset and the Almond router
So there is ample as you know party scene where you could say
I won't say her name but tell almond to activate party scene
In which case the temperature goes down on your thermostat
The lights go down your music starts playing and so on so you could do
Multiple
Actions
With one voice command so
That is kind of cool for all of the Almond routers that I have to say I'm more interested in the
Newest one just because of the Mesh networking
Yeah me too
We want to talk about outside of the universe
Sandy crazy radio protocol universe is something a little bit more fun at the application layer
Apple
Homekit
Somak world
Published a story saying that we might with iOS 10
CA Unified
Which we call this like a software-based hub for homekit
And it would be called
Home now
With all Apple news
This could be changed at any point in time
So knowing this
It's a huge gap
Right now if you have a homekit certified device you can use the app that comes with your device so if you've got the
The eve sensors from Elgato
They've got an app but you have to download third-party apps to actually create scenes that might Bridge like
That you sensors with your Philips Hue Lights there's no like universal control there
And so basically this would be
I've still hearing things from the community about Apple
That make me feel like
This could still be a long time coming
This is good news
Especially for people who are
Still waiting
Yeah there was talk about this happening in iOS 9 obviously it didn't happen so maybe this is the time
It kind of needs to happen I mean I'll be honest I'm sitting here and I'm looking at all this smart home
Apps that I have
Granted having root in a folder called home
So it's like okay at least they're all easily accessible in one place on my phone but
Some type of consolidation or centralized management
On the hand side or whatever
Just makes so much more sense I think and
Everybody was involved in the spaces working on their platforms to integrate the hardware and the
The functions
But I don't see any integration on the user interface
And that's really what I'd like to say
And you know there's there's a couple software programs out there
To do this
Actually work
Catso
Will keep you updated on that
It would be a nice thing to have
And then finally we have some Industrial iot
Iot world is this week
It happened to this week I guess in the
Magical time travel of the show so
The two biggest companies that came out this week with like
Basically internet-of-things divisions are Hitachi
Which is
I talked to them about this already made five
Play 4 billion and stuff that we
We consider internet of things so what the heck
What's created division
With Itachi what they're doing is
They have pulled
Used to be there
Group with
Tahoe and stuff and they basically put that aside and said that group is going to be
Working
With all the different Hitachi divisions
And you know whatever you get to be these conglomerates it's pretty difficult
They have over 900
Hitachi company
It's ridiculous wow but they pulled it out until like 12 big groups
I'm so let's say they're there bullet train division wants to do some sort of iot based
Track management system
That division would actually work with this new iot division
To get get a real-time Data Insights maybe some cool algorithms they work very closely together to serve the cuss
TN customer though would work with the
Hitachi rail division
So basically
The way they set it up as Caesar
It's like an internal service provider to the division
Spear not going to be a customer of this company or division
Yes that's kind of how they
Is a notch
I'm in a lot of organizations which is you know
It just serves the whole company that was like
Cloud so
We'll see
Hitachi did as they created a platform called
Gumada
OU Mata
This is their iot platform effort
Schleich bluematrix
Is IBM's
Pot Farm effort Around The Internet of Things
And then moving on to HP
Who is also
Doing an iot
Kind of effort in platform
Hpe Universal
Platform which
Well it's interesting that I see the e in there after HP so it's
HP Enterprise
Oh yes I can't referred it because they split their Enterprise business with
Printing
The server the cloud computing all of that is
So yes
So basically
Again this is HP
Coming in
Against Amazon
IBM Microsoft
Everybody
Last week Honeywell
In everybody's got the same thing hey will take a lot of your data
Will format it to something that you
You can use
And we make it easy
It's interesting says almost
Then it's not just hpe that students it's almost like a big data play on IRT really
It is I mean that's that's what this is about
The differences that you'll want to look for in your platforms
There's a bunch
Everyone's calling it a platform in the platform is kind of like open it
Disguise any number of Shenzhen
Emissions
With many of these
It's mostly a
Send your data to our cloud
And we will make it something that a web
Like a web service will turn it into something people in the web can access
Or it is send your stuff like connect your product to our cloud and we handle everything
Termite provisioning to making programs to handling data
It's really important that you make the distinction you understand what you really
You go with
The platform providers
It offers that
An impersonal note it's interesting to me because I look at the way the 41 solar panels on a roof
We have a small web server
Hardware box that's connected to
All the micro inverters and all the panels that data is fed from
The panels to the web server
And then that information is available
To me in a dashboard on the web and act freely available like I've actually share the link in the past
But I wonder if the company that I'm using
An outsourced at 2
Someone liking hpe I mean obviously not HP since they just launched this but
We're doing it themselves
Most do it through AWS
Like
Probably 90% of the companies that aren't
Huge Enterprise
Do it through
Sure
And that makes total sense for scalability reliability and so when I'm wondering
Who did the actual
Coding for
Taking the data and presenting it and so was it worth it you know AWS
Didn't do that they probably host it
Yes okay so what's the name of your app
Maybe we can figure
Well it's Enphase energy
Ian
Phase
They're the ones who make them microinverters themselves
Which feed the data to their little
Enphase branded box
Okay well if anyone is out there
So many mysteries on this week's show
Have to come back for a year
Your power will have to
Detest some devices
And their power consumption L we went back awful Circle all the way around power
My head is spinning
It is Rich Brown
Who is the executive editor of CNET
CNET smart home and Appliance coverage
So we are going to talk about CNET Smart Home
That is very similar to mine except they got a bunch more people running it I think your guys are going to have fun
A lot of noise and hype surrounding the Internet of Things
Market everyday another company merges adding to the growing din
It's difficult to rise above the noise and position your company as a leader
Callisto is a leading marketing Communications agency and IRT
They successfully launched iot startups and turn them in a market leaders they positioned in combat companies in I
Providing unique messaging and campaigns that help them stand out is not leaders everything Kalisto does is sit
I'm creating a strong Roi for its clients marketing programs
Through its content marketing public relations and social media Services Callisto can help you tell your uni
Any coyote story to the influencers that matter in this growing market for a free consultation
Contact Marissa Evans at M Evans at Callisto. Com or visit Callisto at w
Ww.w. Kalisto. Com
Hey everyone this is
Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
Today's guest is Rich Brown was an executive editor at CNET
How are you
I am great I am super excited to be talking to you because
Think you are in charge
Of possibly
What are the only homes that is
A smart or maybe smarter than mine
With like DIY kind of installed project
So
Yeah thank you
Sexy. I'm psyched about this we've been working on it
So let's let's have a house in Kentucky
I've got here about 3 years ago
And we hired a bunch of people
Launch
Are appliances
Smart home coverage
And this is before we even had the house
So
You before then we were testing all the stuff going around homes
Yeah
She likes the whole deal
Is that two years ago where
Wieser decided you know what we need
We need a real house
Judith bright
This is awesome because I've
Actually
Probably the last two years I realized
As
Connected appliances come out on the market it is impossible
To actually install
A washer and dryer
Swapping between refrigerators that's crazy so you guys are doing
We haven't done a lot of large appliances at the house for the reasons that you stayed for example we had said no
Countertops
To get in
The Samsung Wi-Fi ranges
The large Appliance
Testing
Pretty much stays out at the warehouse
A hole
Sort of climate
Controlled test chamber for each each category
Okay and why do you guys think it's so important to test these
In a house
Well
For us it's really about
Seeing how well
These devices work
Part of the Holy Ghost
Write me that if something says that it works with nest
We want to be able to see how it works with nest
And how well what's another product would say they work
I totally agree
Now you guys don't live in the house though
Actually lives there
That's right
Got it okay
Let's talk about what you discovered in the 10 months that you've been playing around with all this stuff
What are your favorite products
Call Manuel
Amazon Echo
Just meet our lives
Really easy
And it's good that it kind of
Matured when it bitter a really kind of
Brought on
A whole bunch of connected
Devices into its ecosystem when it did because that's right about when
The SmartThings Hub that we were using
Willie
Unfortunate
Okay so you like the echo on your thermostats I see that you did not go with
Traditional Nest you went with
My personal favorite
What was the thought process
Yet so we you know this is
The second one
Things in the house so we started out with
And I think it was when
Ecobee announce it's echoing
Integration
The punch that's only said
All right we're switching over we already were leaning towards ecobee because of the
Thermal sensor
They came in the Box
But you know
He said hey you know words
Ecobee and pulled ahead we're going to ecobee3 instead
Axanthic ancestor we have a 2 zone system
Also on the first floor we have ecobee
Hilltop Ford
Because there's some things we want
Try out there
And at this point with given that
That's why they added location-based tracking
For your phone
The recent update
The kind of
Home Depot
Comparable I have the same setup actually have a nest upstairs and you could be downstairs
And I would say
Cuz I don't carry the phone
With me
I like having a sensor in
It just is in that room
I will to say though
All the other kind of temperature sensing devices that I've been adding to my house
They also talk to the nest
Kind of make the ecobee sensor a bit of a
That's true and that's
Partly why
We tried that out in upstairs in the master bedroom where we in
Installed a I swear the nest up there their generation
And we have
Big Ass Fans
I just want to say
Haiku ceiling fan
And then we saved
Keen smart vent
Up there in the master bedroom and in the kids
Oh my gosh tell me how this works I'm loving it
You know we really wanted to see what it was like to have the nest
Haiku fan
And Hakeem all working in his own soda
Really regulate temperature in
A little more precisely than you got juice
This is one thermostat
Tahoe floor
I'd say that I would feel better reporting an actor
Christine that if we had someone spend the night
With all that said not done yet
But that's
Hopefully we'll be able to
But I
We go all in on that Netflix
Because
It's the optimization of algorithms that need to
Like once you get all these working together and I've discovered this in
Drinking any number of devices
It's nice in theory
Machine learning models that actually
Take into account all of these things
Maybe you'll get some of the Comfort but you won't get the Energy savings
Discovered in my own testing
I'm curious to see what you guys do
You know I really wish
This is one area where
Temperature are Appliance testing Warehouse
Traditional lab setup
It's here where we have
A small integrating Sphere for example to throw
Are LED bulbs anywhere we really do
You pretty rigorous color temperature testing all that stuff
What I really
Wish we could do the house
We haven't done is just
Time and cost
And everything else prohibitive
Is that really really proper lab environment there was like
True climbing
Control where everything is
Temperature regulated air flow regulator and all that
I think for that reason I don't know if I'll ever really be comfortable reporting on energy force
Really help climate controls but
Jessica produce ballpark
Let's talk about
Your favorite light switch is the Belkin WeMo and your favorite security camera is the nest
And I am kind of curious
About
The WeMo because in the lights what did you like limited to only Bluetooth and Wi-Fi because I found the WeMo light switch to be
Not everything I hoped for in a
Connect a light switch
Driving
Tracker behind the WeMo switches that at work so she who shall not be named
That's why we don't duck
I know the history of
Frustration
Wi-Fi
Getting getting we must have set up on Wi-Fi I've experienced it
We've got to learn to live with it I guess
Yeah that was why we went
We went
Which ones do you like
So I haven't found a Wi-Fi switch I like it
So my switches when I in
I put them in
Which is because I've got a wink
Steph
And that talks to the echo as well so
I would love to find a great Wi-Fi switches
A really common question I get
But we know it's just it doesn't of the features there's a new task called The Plum
Which is Wi-Fi
I don't know if they have a skill for the
So
You guys also
Just do a quick run down your favorite security camera
Torn between
Emma Chamberlain
Your vacuum is Bonito
I've got a room but it doesn't have Wi-Fi
Can you tell me why I would want
It's really what it does is it
Brings the remote
That might come with your vacuum on your phone
That's a primary thing
You know you can do scheduling you can manually drive it around
That
For us
Was probably secondary
What we like about that whenever the Roomba is that
It's a better vacuum
AR testing
In room clean quickly
That was really bad
Driving
Okay so those are kind of your main
Products
Are there things that you guys
Tested and thought
Hey this is pretty cool but it's such a niche case that no one would ever want this
Ashley Clark Thompson hair is
Does one of our smart
Kitchen testing
And
There's a thing called the pantelligent
Was she loves
Oh yes
But our readers
And Arduino she did a Facebook live session
And people are not into that thing
I don't think it's the
If your listeners are familiar it's connected
Saucepan frypan essentially I had sense
The bottom of it has a Bluetooth
Receiver
And the handle and it can give you kind of
Precise
Instructions on as far as
What the heat of the pandas
If you put it on a
Stand-alone
Burner and plug it into a Wiimote switch it can actually control the temperature itself
And it's $200
Which I think
It's 199
Yeah there's one point of criticize
I don't know if you
Feel the same way but I'd heaven
Seen much
In the way of connecting
Devices that really make me excited that really sank like
I'm with you on this site again the one thing that I've asked for
A thousand times
What is a refrigerated crock pot
Because
And not think about it
I have a dream
Well okay
Meli Melo right
So I have
What day is it
It's not
Try to have an imaginary Crock-Pot
Concept
I think
Big promise with a connected kitchen is
The expertise
Second
Copper supplement so I really like
Like the concept behind intelligent I like the concept behind the June oven
But I don't know if people are going to really pay those prices for
Worcester
A fridge
It doesn't have a giant phone on the front
But actually has
A camera inside that takes
Pictures that says
But I can call up a picture of my last name
I should totally get milk
Annex
You know we have that straight drive timeout
The giant Samsung fridge
Guess that's what it's got the family Hub fridge
And there's the LG fridge that they showed off at CES where you
Knocked on it in the door went clear yes
Is that out
You know it's not my knowledge no
There's a whole world
I don't know
Pet stuff
Get connected baby stuff for I think we're going to do
Maggie's around right now
You know the Sleep Number bed thing with inter
Christine and I mentioned that earlier where we have my daughter spend the night
Yeah we can tell you
It's really expensive is a Sleep Number bed right now you can't even going in
With an extensive platform
They can tell you what you know basic
Sleeping pattern so I can play how long your kid was asleep how long
Playing around bed for whatever
This was a handy thing from there you can kind of gamify the bedtime routine
Where you can if you can get a little love
Yeah Rewards
If you lie
Go to bed on time you brush your teeth
Considered cetera
I think there's something there
But price
This is probably need to get a little more realistic I think the bedroom
Quotes about $2,000
Definitely not the most expensive but
Okay
So
Those are kind of some of the devices
End
What still needs work I mean we should spend a lot of time talking about interoperability
Siri is a huge
You know issue today
Are there other things
You're thinking of
Because we kind of cover those others to death
I think
That what I would
Really
Like to see
Is
We went with Echo
Largely because videos easy
You'll get a lot of automation with Echo as you know right now you can't it's not really designed for setting up
Seems our kind of
Kalmar Nation type stuff and
Anyway that made our lives easier but
What is really good at is
Multi-user
Better for worse
But you know anybody can walk in the room
With initial command
And it will respond
Not all the other systems
You got very well
So it's not a very Democratic set up in the house to have
SmartThings or
Wink I think of running everything you know
This one person is going to end up being the
The main control point and then everything else to run
Jordan Peterson our experience
I would love to see that
Work a little better
Without having
Lindsay Ellis
Guest account
Another crazy longest log into the NFL
Because it really is
Precinct
That's great what about
Getting things online just the ease-of-use
I mean I still feel like this isn't ready for the mainstream
The echo brings a Little Closer
Partly for reasons you said but also because there's no
Recipes
Scenes that you said it's it's pretty easy
Do you think this is at the mainstream yet
Are still early adopter
It's so early.
Yeah
Yeah I don't know if you agree but I sent to me it's it's yes you can have the pain of getting things online
I think an extent what kind of used to that at this point right in the USA with a lot of things around the house
Sign up for grocery put your email in there put a password in there would do that with a PlayStation
We do that with Nest Thermostat you know looks different sing with you
What's a lifesaver lock whatever
Depending on how it gets online but
The basics of that I don't think you're too bad I think
Where
The early adopter thing comes in is just a share my risk
Involved in
Buying into the smart home right now
You know
You got the revolve
Beds
Staples connect looks like it's almost dead
Wake was looking taxi there although I guess it's back on now or has them back on
Forgot sex
The standard-bearer
If I was going to try to out to the whole home
And that's a whole lot of money doing that all that volatility
Would really give me a lot
Got it so then what's the hope for the smartphone
There's been
How do you think this is going to
Play outside
Annies
Your guess is as good as mine
Suppose
Ever murdered anybody
You know I don't know that I would have predicted a lot of drama around nest
A year ago
But here we are
You know I think
There's a lot of enthusiasm around Echo
And that's the
I'm still
Fingers crossed that
It will eventually emerge as
Apply from the people are excited about
Doing
I'll take a side bed
Not how well
I'm very down on
I feel like apple bit off more than
And it's kind of trying to figure out how to think about the Smart Home
Because it's
It's base assumptions
It's not wrong just
They were too narrow is probably
The way to think about it I think
The most successful companies are going to be those with kind of an open and flexible mindset
And I think the way Apple
Controls things and that's a huge advantage to its user base
What kind of
Haunted in the smartphone
That's my take
That's why I'm willing to be wrong because I would love for
There to be a beautiful
Interface for the smart home I just don't
Think we're going to see it
From Apple
At least not for a really low
I totally agree with
Open versus closed
Issues going on there that you mentioned
And I will be
Surprised
I really like this
Security story they have to tell
As far as
Certifying every devices
Comes in both on the hardware and software level
Fingers crossed there
Does if it does get get any traction I think it's
I'm hopeful anyway.
It lives up to its
Okay
Thank you so
Much for coming on the show today
Stacy really thank you this is awesome. I've been wanting to get on your podcast
I'm glad you got in touch
That's all we have for you this week but join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
Thanks for listening