Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast either host Stacey Higginbotham
If this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a great show for you today we're going to talk about Google home Atari and iot
Possibly some new Wi-Fi low-power effort
A bit about
Smart home hubs
Plus
I have a great guest for you it's Chris Herbert who is the CEO of tracker
Who's going to talk about a brand new indoor positioning system
Which
I love
We love presents
Alright so let's get started with the Google home the information
Which man are they just like rocking it hard or what
They typically do they they have really good sources and they get some good scoops
They do so
They are reporting that
The chip inside
Google home and Google home is the Amazon Echo
Like product
That is not actually at the market
People are calling it
Air freshener
That you can look like an air freshener
So this has the same chip inside
As the
Kevin
Chromecast is what the information says they have a dispute with a person with direct knowledge of the plan
Notes I work for Google I have no direct knowledge of the plan
But this is what they were told that the guts of Home in the same as the Chromecast
I can't say that I'm surprised because
When the Google home personal assistant product was announced at the Google IO Keynote
They said it was built on Chromecast technology so that kind of
Let me to believe it be similar and I don't know that it's a bad thing cuz the Google Chromecast
Is
Relatively popular relatively inexpensive I think it's about 30-35 bucks you can usually find it on sale
Great to stream mirror
Cast audio to video around the house and so on so I guess our people staycity thing people are getting talking about this
Because they're thinking the cost of Google home will be low like a Chromecast
I think people are just excited about Google home in any Speck of information
Gets them something
But
I will say
Having a wide
Birth of products
Use the same silicon means you can buy in Greater bulk
And every time you're buying
Chips
Focus better
Total or your ear
Your cost per unit
So can I looked at the
Purported ship inside
Amazon Echo
Which of these are based
Teardowns in the end of 2015
From ifixit.com
Yes
Lovely people
And so
So just give me a little chippy but bear with us we're getting chippy we are
The Amazon Echo for its brains
Uses
I was actually kind of surprised it's a lower power TI omap
DaVinci price
It's a DaVinci process
Correct correct
I think this particular chip debuted in 2010 its head berries variation since then
But this is not like a super high-end chip like you have in a high-end smartphone for example its
It does the job obviously cuz it's a good product
But this is not an expensive chip it's not a
Super powerful chip
I think we looked we dug around for cost and I think we found under thirty bucks for the chip
Write in
I can guarantee you that Amazon snot
Although you don't it doesn't have to drive a screen
Which means it can be
Lower performance
But with the
Google chip in there using the Marvell Armada
It looks like that
Mini Plus
SOC
And that actually it does have to dry the screen
Inure
Television
It cast output video content at 1080p s
So that's that's a little bit more
But that ship only costs what does that cause
That one I haven't seen a cost to be honest
So yeah I'm not sure how much.
Prospect
More than
The Amazon Echo
You know just for me
Performance perspective
Looking at this it looks like maybe
The Marvell Armada can deliver a little bit more gigahertz
Performance
It's also we're sourcing this from a non-tech
Because those guys
They're freaking out
They know their stuff absolutely
Yeah
The fountain actually went to work for Apple
I guess at the end of the day
You can't
Figure out what the cost of an item to be based solely on the bill of materials but it does give you a good indication of what
You know what it may cost them in the company could choose to
Pretty something at a loss and so on and so forth but
So I guess if
Again people probably trying to figure out how much Google home is going to cost we don't know
But you know I
Could it be as much as an Amazon Echo it could be
But
I don't think I'd be higher by any means
But it also gives you a sense of what these devices are designed to do
In a relatively low power processors
In there as the Braves
Shows how much of the
Computing brain power is actually
Cloud
Not a surprise but sometimes if you see like a crazy high power chip in there you'd be like
They're going to run some stuff inside
The reason this matters is things like smart home hubs
You want them to be able to actually do something still even when they're not connected
The internet
Very much so very much so and with these personal assistant products the natural language processing is actually done in the cloud
Finger point about where the processing is done
They don't need to know the latest and greatest
Mobile chip in these things
Bright and we don't see a lot of memory
I think there's four gig in the in the Echo Basin letter down for example
A conversion chips but nothing like
Super excited
Just keep that in mind guys
Little context for your day on the
The information's little story
I don't say little in a mean way
Just the story that wrote about this
Well they call that Google home Little secret
So that's where the little comes around
That's really little secret but I did click on my headliner
What is the great headline but I was kind of shook my head in life
All right so other chip news
Qualcomm
I was going to say comdex I'm just I'm not on my game today guys at computex
In Taipei
In Taipei introduced the Snapdragon wear 1100
SOC
Less smart wearables I like that
Well that was my head like that was actually my show noticed I called it less smart because they actually introduced the snap
Dragonwear 2100 back at Mobile World Congress
And that was going to you know get better battery life and
You bring more Smart Start device isn't someone
The 1100
As you can gather from the
Numerical naming
Is
Lower spec
Chip and it's basically for
Things like kid tracking and other
Type of wearables that don't require a ton of processing power so
We can still do everything and
It's just not going to be as a performer that would guess
Yeah it's got LTE built-in + 3G Bluetooth Wi-Fi
And
Haswell in application processor for linux-based applique
Patience so
That's
That's actually pretty good
I think it's really worth noting that as The Internet of Things
Expanse chip companies are really having to work their butts off to create these different skews
Which were seeing their good at that
But they're also
As they do this they're having to change their distribution model
To deal with
So many more potential customers
Beforehand a company like Qualcomm had baby
Maybe a couple dozen
Less than a hundred customers cuz they were just selling chips for phones right
So
This is a big
Not this individual thing but this is part of a whole
Pixie change for all these cuz
These chip makers who are like
Oh man now I got to support so many more customers they're turning to like distribution Distributors like arrow and others
And they're also like oh my God now I don't have something I can sell like a billion chips
Right it's a far broader distribution of
Taipan
Customers you said
And even their companies coming out of woodwork now just building phone building
Wearable devices virtual reality things I mean in Qualcomm
Did they have to know they got to focus on all these different form-factors where they didn't have to as much before they got to worry about chip size and
Brightmoor. Battery life
Not that they didn't before
But
The variance in all these is it's just you know it's good for them it's good business for them but it also is a challenge for them
Exactly
Other
What else what else
Should we talk about
We should talk about Jabo
We should talk cuz everybody's talking about dry bone and everybody's saying lots of different things about you
So fun Friday Fortune reported
Jawbone with exiting the speaker business
Jawbone
You know you guys may not be aware of it
Probably are makes the
Chipmunks oh my God what is it called the marmara
Okay
Makes that so they were talking about exiting that
This week Tech Insider reported that jaw bone had halted there
Band Productions
And sold off their name trackers to a third party
Reseller
But
Payback in
Good night
So
What we do know is back in November they laid off
Chunk of their staff
There
Neck-and-neck with Fitbit or probably less neck-and-neck now which
Indicate something
And business is just getting super super complicated
In there
Statement
I'm saying that hey don't know we're still producing up Fitness bands
They did indicate that they were willing to go to
Clinical
Quality bands
I thought that was kind of
That's very telling
Fairy Tail
Yeah I could fit it really has been owning this wearable
Mail tracking Market
Of weight
Based on reports of
Market share sales etc mean we really don't know we don't have to
All the exact
Details but
That's what the reports have been
And we all know that
Okay the next step for wearables is not just consumer-grade but actual clinical grade
That requires you to get FDA approval that's a whole convoluted process
But that's what's next and I think
Again these are all these rumors but I suspect they are true in that job was trying to get ahead of the Curve
Build upon what it
Learn through the consumer wearable Market
And jump into the clinical Market as soon as possible it's kind of beat everybody to the punch
Except I can't be
Certain
That's a very good point there they're not the first to jump into that market
And this is probably why
Also recent news Nokia but why things
And I have to make a quick correction
Did not say that
It was doing the clinic
What's the verge
Reporting that jaw bone with still make wearable devices and it's creating quote a clinical grade health-tracking related
The heart monitor
So
Jawbone
Basically the only thing
You said officially here
Is that
The brand is not going to
So 30
So there's a lot of if he's as someone who wears a jaw bone
Tracker
I would be really sad to see
The software go away although I did notice that very recently my permissions changed drastically
And I was curious what that meant I thought maybe it meant that they were
Either going to add
About your new features or that they sold it or something
Can can you export your data out of the jaw bone
System
Yes vote has been very open job has been kind of fun because in the reason why I went with it is because it works with so many
Other connected
Home systems
So
An infant Deadspin
I hope that we could still have jaw bones although I'm a little concerned about
Buying another job phone so
Baby don't do that
Yeah I don't know that I would do that right now
I guess it's the best thing ever
Let's see what they do
Hold on
Alright other cool news
Is
I don't know this cool it's a cool cuz it's about it is cool it's cool for multiple days
So basically Atari has teamed up with sick Fox which is the low power
Wider in neck networking standard they use in France they're building at work at San Francisco
How to make iot devices for the Smart Home
And this kind of came out of left field
Yeah it came out of nowhere I'll other
I'm a little confused cuz there's a
House for lease on the Atari website that
Dated May 5th but this really didn't come out until May 29th
So
Yeah and the date in the Press phases May 31st
Yasso
I kind of was like
Think there might be a little bit of an issue there with the date so we're going to call this
I feel like we would have noticed it before now if it were
So
There's not a lot of information
In this world
It's it's basically like Hey we're going to make some
Connected
I will say sigfox
The standard
Super low data rate
We're talking like
This is this is this is the IRT Network that they say I
I think it has over 7 million devices on it
Yes but those devices are things like
Tyco smoke detector
Well that's okay
Yes it is I'm just I'm just trying it like so these are
Wicked awesome
Massive
Data consuming kind of things
Price likely
I'm thinking
Sensors
You know
Again we don't know maybe M2M types.
In the sigfox network requires
A separate infrastructure so
The other thing to think about what this is if they are working solely with cefoxitin and that may not be the case
They can always put Wi-Fi into the
If it was sick Fox
The devices will only work in a limited number of places where sick fox has it Network
18 countries right now I believe
I don't know
So not terrible just
Worth
They did a luta what they're going to bring with what Ataris going to be
Building and bring them to 6 Fox network and I'm just going to read this right out of the press release
The initial product line will include categories such as home pets
Lifestyle and safety
I know that's very nebulous but
It speaks to I think presents
Your pet tracking
Safety again maybe
Yeah could be a pack my smoke detector I don't know
So
You will have to see what they're going to do but
Still kind of thought it was because it was Atari
Yes
Which of course ran to the website and yes yes yes they did
Sold
Few times since the video game crash
In the early 80s but yeah
Still around
That's that's
It will it will see what
What comes of that
Other bit of news also, super geeky but keep your eye on this because
I don't know I am excited by Wi-Fi
The IEEE is looking at
Proposing a wake-up receiver
Standard for 802. 11 which is the
The Wi-Fi stand
So what this is basically
Only low-power you let your
Wi-Fi stuff would actually go to sleep
When it needs to wake up
Data packet to the
The flow that says go
Wake up
And that it would wake up
And everything could be active
Send transmit whatever data needed and then come back
That's not how Wi-Fi works
I think that's actually how
Bluetooth
They have a
Wake up
But
Either way
This is something apparently that's been in the works for a long time
Sidelines by the Wi-Fi Halo effort
And those are basically in the
Those are in the
In a different Spectrum band
It's 900 megahertz and those efforts are all about giving you better coverage and places where the
Current 2.4 and 5 gigahertz radios just can't
Riesling
Checking stuff
In your basement
If they do say they are low power but
They don't have this
Yeah I know
The obvious benefit here is this would save power and actually I I have a device that I wish I'd had this now
One of my
Smart watches
Has Wi-Fi so that way when I'm out of Bluetooth range from my phone
I can still get notifications and open apps and do things
It just connects over Wi-Fi to do that so it's a very limited
Time them using Wi-Fi and if that Wi-Fi radio is on all the time and actively saying give me today to give me data
You know it's wasting juice so
Another place this would be great as a lot of the water
There's not a lot of leak sensors with Wi-Fi
Another's the battery life
But something like this where it wakes up
You know
Once a day
Am I wet
Okay
This would only work for
Like rushing it in your house you
I don't know how
Speaking of water leak
I should mention this because
It happened after we recorded the podcast but it's actually big news
Belkin
Has
Teamed up with open or which is a plumbing supply company to create a brand new company called
Spin
What is doing Leak Detection sensors
Spinlaunch last week with 40 million dollars in it
Phy in
I just thought I wrote about it the newsletter but I thought it was worth talking about of the podcast because the idea here is
Is not that you'd have sensors around your home but you'd install something like underneath your sink faucet
Or if you're a builder you can actually install it on the water main when you're building the house the line into the house and you could install
Automatic shut-off valve
And
Sensors with
Detect leaks based on the amount of water flowing through your house basically the same sort of thing they do
Do it on the electricity side with
Proteinuria
Curb
Monitoring of flow
This is kind of really promising because I've never had a leak in a place where it had a leak sensor
I was like yes please
Yeah I know it makes sense that it monitoring
The actual water as opposed to just
A specific
Spot where you might be looking for a week even though the league might be three feet away and the sensor doesn't see the lead so
Make sense
Now this isn't out yet
Just creative company
It has 40 million in funding
I'm Keen to see what happen
Prince here I hope to try this out
Because again
Weeks super expensive
I love the fact that they're going after not just kind of consumers but also like insurance companies and
Know what are they called builders
Steelers
So
That's just
Kind of cool information
As long as I can turn it off when I fill my pool in the Memorial Day weekend
Wow
You don't have to turn it off it just would check that
Timothy Lake weather
And you be like no that is not a leak
That is not a week false alarm
Is it a little baby pool
It's only if it's 2500 gallons is not
Not like
30000 gallon
Trulia
Never get there.
Anyone
Though I can't imagine
Prof. Xs
I'm sorry
Okay
So final story for us this way
Which is The Wirecutter
This is actually we should have put it in last week
Ranking
Smart home hubs
And it shows as their number one pick
I'm cringing cuz I know people going to cringe when they hear it
Samsung SmartThings platform
Which
No
But you you're saying no I'm saying I don't know cuz I have not used it I've only use my wink and in terms of that and the wink was
Is there also great pic
I'm not as good but also great
But we've heard and we reported on some of the Samsung Smart Home issues in the past between security issues and
Developer mentality and mindset and so on and so forth
Love the mind
Right now they're having
Problems even before they had their problems
They were having reliability
I would say if you want to follow this
And get one
You know I love playing with
I would never give this
To somebody who's not willing to put in the hours
Gotcha
It's gotten better like maybe 85% of the time it does what it's supposed to do when it's supposed to do it
But like they have this monitoring service with Scout that you actually pay for
Don't do that
No because you need more reliability
They're just not
They actually do cover a bunch of other devices that they tested and get pros and cons so it's probably well worth reading the article I think
Yes because they talked about the
The caseta smart home plug
And how you can try that with
Homekit
Then move it you know in.
Beyond lighting
What's a Barbie on lighting
There's insteon which is our favorite
Lowe's Iris Smart Home
Cuddelink staple
Disconnect hub
That was that was originally the runner-up pick
But
Since it's going to be
Possibly discontinuing that
Didn't choose it as a renter up
Which fits with what I thought I loved
I thought it was actually one of my favorites that's the one I would give to people
Who didn't
You know
I didn't want it
SmartThings
So yeah
That's that
Check it out with reading especially if you're like you do I want to do this date that should do a good job covering some of the pros and
Cons of
The home hub ecosystem as I'm home
Xanax an article
So that is that
And I think
If you guys stay tuned for our guest
It is Chris Herbert
Who is the CEO of tracker
Which is one of those mini mini bluetooth based tracking devices
We talked about
Trackers
We talked about presents and we even have a good conversation about
Chris talked about chips actually this whole show so chippy
So stay tuned
For that but first break in with an ad hi this is Stacy and I'm here
Coyote podcast to tell you two things the first isn't I've launched a Weekly Newsletter devoted to The Internet of Things
That you can sign up for it
Staceyoniot.com
The second is that we're now accepting ads on the IRT
Play podcast
We have packages for big companies and startups
So if you're interested please email Andrew
At iot podcast. Com
I'd also like to thank my devices and Callisto Communications who supported the show in the past
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Cast this is your host and today's guest is Chris Herbert who is the CEO of
Of tracker
Hey Chris how you doing
And thank you for coming I am super excited because
I don't do a lot of things
My family loses a lot of things
And right now I have a product from one of your competitors actually
My water bottle
Because I had replaced the $12 water bottle
Like
Three times and I was like
I've reached the point where it
It cost more to like replace it
So let's talk about
Kind of
How you got
You guys have been doing this since 2009 and that's really long time
Christian after we die
Actually lost a cube on a surfing
Trap
And actually parked my car on the beach
Indiana
Reason to start
The ocean was by
Wall up my car
3 hours
Maya keys
Call me
New things
At least I don't think I'm
You have to manually memorize where
What if we could get the task
Where I can fire
So we don't have to
Right so that your
Derek knows where everything is in your house
Office
Your life is completely mad
Now that's nasty
Graduated
Which of the dongle that lasted about 1-day battery life
$70
And then in 2012
Release
And a tracking device
Not really
It help desk is mainstream Dan
Continue.
Bravo
And it also our new product
We are going to talk about that but
I'd like to think about cuz this is
This to me is a crazy stat
One that you started the so early
Into that your first iteration cost
60 to $70 and you had to charge it every night and people still wanted to buy it
That's nuts
Dykes in the in the process
From moving from that to where you are now
I'm assuming things like hey there's now Bluetooth low energy
There's also
Superchips
Let's think about how the world is changed
Made it easier for
Yeah I mean a lot
And continuous change dramatically
Is that
Bee Company
Watching a launch with a cheerful energy
I thought that was
And
And it was only able to talk
On BlackBerry and
So now
Eating with the adoption of
IOS enable
Really
And I think that's
People with it.
And iPhone 4S.
And
You are able to get
Smaller and cheaper because all the Silicon manufacturer
Everyone keeps on Staring.
And billion devices are 50 billion devices
Now going to be I believe 18 billion devices by 2020
18 billion / 25
Especially
Nordic really
Stop reaching out to
Startups in a plane
Get to Market quickly
Really bruh
Sheknives I think the entire
Industry for all these different years
Smart tracking devices
Panda
Adoption of
Mm
Xidan Fitbit started
Stopping 7
I'm trying to think I think the first one was another Market until like 20
I want to check that
Fact check
Turn around
Wednesday
There will be 28.
That's their latest and greatest forecast
And I think the
Tire industry
Dalian
And
What do you think about
We probably have a
Read
10 billion
That is super exciting I can't wait
And you guys
Can I taking it to the next level in
Cuz you got this project
Actually you got two things that all up tees for people
Listen to the whole thing because we're going to talk about
Everyone knows I love it
Which is the Amazon Echo
And how
You guys are thinking about that
So
Let's take
Location in the home
You guys call it project Atlas
This is huge I
I'm constantly walking into rooms
Why doesn't my house know where I am if I'm not carrying my
So what are you guys kind of doing with project
Subway
Keeping organized
Keep track their items
So we looked at home location in Indore
One of the features of our product is that it shows you on a map of where
Okay
And
Your kids are
You didn't need it out sell you that you knew your keys were somewhere in the house
In the house right
Users
And after
And I'm
Definitely
Target user car products
Bang bang bang
Honey you know you seen my backpack
Luggage
It hurts me that the response is always right
Kitchen in the bedroom
Oh have you looked in the garage
The living room
And it's not
You know a lot of other people try to
Look at it think how can we just get
Locations for the home
And the smoke
In the Alex
Look like
Each makes a room in your house
And then
Is Wi-Fi
So it's
Anteroom
Items
And then it sends up their server
With the item and
The room until then on your app
You can actually see it
Items aren't
Inventory tracking
Idea
There's water app tracking
Already
I think that
We've really been able to
Consumers
So that
You don't need to remember where all your I'm sorry
Champion
To say how excited I am about this
Because
I don't have an attic
The way we've designed our house so I have a lot of storage closets
And I have the garage
My like holiday decorations are like summer the bedroom Summer of the guest room summary
Garage
And I would love to be able to say hey what's
Stick
You know lipstick plugs everywhere
Let's drop
Tag
Eye tracker in
This one's Christmas decorations are Christmas lights
So I can dance
Q juice
Speck case Beyond just
Hey
Let's put these are my keys
Absolutely anything
Because
You
Computers
And I believe that
All your items
Will be tracked
Brown Deer Christmas decorations
Tear your jacket
Backpacks
I mean
Everything will be
Chalkable
And so I think it's a really important Evolution for
Smart tracking
Space
To just go from
Hey let's find something after
2 + and you
You want to just keep track of your stuff for your family
A lot of families have one person in the family whose like knows where it is
My family is my wife she knows where everything is located
And so I was thinking.
Attractive
Everything
In the house
Ketchup
I am also that person and constantly like
I don't know
I really don't know
Backpack
And you really don't want
Let's think about that
The Trackers right now the trackr Bravo cost $30
How much is the Atlas plug
Concept
So we have for $99
Two-bedroom
Bedroom home
There's a big question here
There's other companies
What's the do this
Zulily is wine I've tried out there they
Garden outlet
It tracks
Miso its presence detection based on my phone is supposed to track
Nothing
When I think about building a service that are truly compelling service that fits with the iot
If I say
Hey this is tracker
They're building an indoor
You know inventory system
And is there a what have you thought about
Ways to open the supper create this platform and how would you kind of do it given
Hey there's a lot of competition just in the tracking Market but there's also kind of indoor location map
Petition
Probably want to open ASAP is that were costly looking for like
Each Creek Softball bags
Another company check
Theron traffic purses
And then I think
New Atlas device
Ennui
Started
Programs that we can have
It works
Future platform
Drum bearing stood in what SmartThings
I'm interested in to see the future
I don't think
Really really early days
A lot of these other
Smart home companies.
Everything that
You need to be we're going to do
Witchita inventory tracking it
One part of
Should know
Very basic
Yusuke sub for me
Okay
And you guys
Are teaming up with Amazon you actually took some money from the Amazon Alexa fund
Not in a Robert kind of way just did they invested in you
A phrase that strangely
If I team up the Amazon Echo and your
Atlas project
That I have the ability to ask the echo
Hey where's my stuff and she'll say
It's in the kitchen
Entirely
Right
Sing your style
Entirely yet
You're looking at homes
She walked down at the time and
Echo integration
Katy release we were
Instantly integrated it
Because
I'm asking Echo where are my keys
And having the
In the kitchen so I bring them for you
I'm really sorry about that
One-point Lee
Find dress right
AR app
Look and then press the button
Safariland
Look around
If they don't find it there then they're going to open up
R&R tracwrap and then
I want to have to get you a point where
People are using
R software
Before they look for themselves
If that makes sense
Writing reliant on
Memorize phone numbers right
Now
You don't try to remember
Phone number
Your phone book
Some people would describe this is like the end of
Community
People song Let it Roll
I did want to ask you
Because
Tile which is one of your big competitors recently gave figures
About 40 million
For this day is selling $40 worth of tiles in the next year
Which is a lot of $25
Trackers
Okay see your Damien trackers really difficult for me
I'd love to
Where where do you stack up against
What does that say about the market for this thing
I think that is really starting
Any
Is
I mean
Contracted number
I mean I think
Over 1.5 million devices
Dan's
Yeah that's a lot
To the market
However
There's three
Do they have a whole lot of
Stop the track
Right so we're just scratching the surface
Next right now
Thanks what we're trying to do is
I think that you just see more of
Braiding
Yahoo
We have other software applications
Are tracking technology and siblings
I think that
To finish off
What are some of the
Most interesting or surprising use cases that you have
There I mean there's definitely
People that are trapped
Weird things like that we have like peoples are tracking the bunch of
I didn't know this was a thing but
They actually hibernate
Table like going dinner corn and hibernate and not move
And that was kind of surprising for us
Another
Measurements over time
Dan
Would you
Take a note
I get moved
And then the Stars
Tracking devices underneath the ground to go next
And then where
Really excited about
Something stop
Like don't know there
And I get another entire city
Everything
I think we're seeing some cool use cases
Excited
Cases
Desert Sands
Coffee mug
Every single day in office
And I think
Smaller items
I'm really
What kind of change
Interact with other items
And try to remember
I'm thinking about it you stick one on each kid in the school
And then you know where they are
Related to the school
Which is
Actually done in a lot of places with like
Badging in
Schools have kids badge
It's also kind of a little
I don't know
Scary
Significant
Right now because we don't want
So unique
Jellycat
Yes we want
Sure that works
Grateful.
2 weeks
I think
Live tracking
People talking
Entirely
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
Listening and we'll see you next week