Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is
Is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have an awesome show for you
Cuz we've got a brand new Raspberry Pi
Stuff from Saudi
Ready to take on the Amazon Echo
I don't know if that's a gay or boo I was waiting for Kevin I'm on the fence
All right
Wechat
Cheaper watches
And do watch
We've got
Update from last week because we didn't talk about
New developments in the stand
Community
And I guess this week is Chad Curry who is the managing director for the center of real estate technology at the Nash
National Association of Realtors
You got it
Bringing smart houses
And I'm really curious to hear the interview because
Cos
That's a lot of opportunity for iot type
Connected devices in the home real estate market
I'm finding more and more Realtors I talk to
Are really getting into this thing
Okay so let's get this party started with the raspberry
Reply
Always room for pie
So latest and greatest in this is like only a few
Months
Jax Ali like 2 months
That node 3 months
Because it came out
November
The pi zero this is a better equipped by this is
And it has
Integrated thank you
Bluetooth
On board
So everyone's like this
Raspberry Pi for The Internet of Things
Yep yep yep this is nice because I don't believe the previous pies had integrated connectivity
I could always do add-ons look forward to things like that
They're doing this at the same price for the Raspberry Pi 2 which you can still get for $35 but
Why would you
Cuz for $35 you can get a faster chip
It's a 1.2 gigahertz
64-bit
Quad core
Other thing is 10 times the performance of the original Raspberry Pi which the make sense
It's been 4 years now
Debut that
It's the first six
64-bit Raspberry Pi
Which is Big because you can turn this into like a little mini server
Yep yep that one of the things I like that they did over the Raspberry Pi so it's it's fully compatible with the original
Pies and all the accessories in such all the try to keep all the pins in the same spot I think they only move like one LED
D indicator
Unisex he's got like add-on boards from the older pies
You should still be able to use them with the Raspberry Pi 3
Oh that's nice so I was
It's still good feel good exact
Exactly so I think it's still broadcom empowering this right
It is still a broadcom chip there still
Stay in bed with broadcom
Hey now
I don't know where that came from
That wasn't supposed to be anything
Negative
But you can't unlike would like the Arduino are other
Things you cannot buy the chips that powers the pie separate
So that's something worth noting
Because you could buy the other chips that are the brains behind
Like Arduino or any of those others you can buy those separately but not with
And if you have kids I should tell you
That Cato the the computer for kids
I should say that I
Put together as my daughter and love so much
They actually have something
They have a new computer coming out soon
It will work with this
Pi
And
They're going to be available for pre-order for one night
It won't ship till June
But if you want
You can buy this version of the pie
And you can just download the
Pokeno software on it today
Inner work
And I only say that because I really liked the
Aquino and I thought it was a really cool
OS and system for teaching
My nine-year-old about like
Parts of a computer and here's how to like program your own stuff in Minecraft which she was
Yeah
A software perspective
Just in case people are interested you can still use all the old
Software the raspbian
Pi
Suffer image
They are still keeping that same 32-bit software but they're going to consider
Making that a 64-bit
Operating system in the future
Because you know I'm in
You got the hardware that can support it so maybe it makes sense
Okay so on the
Next topic
Sony
And it's
New Amazon Echo
Tell us a little bit about
Yeah this is an interesting prototype device that Sony debuted at Mobile World Congress last week it's called the Xperia
Agent
Not yet for sale and they don't have any
Potential dates running like that they were showing it off
Is very similar to an Amazon Echo it looks
Have a similar form factor although it's more
It's not supposed cylindrical against tapered at the top and that's because they have this
Rotating ball that actually has a camera in it and a projector
So unlike the echo
It can actually project information
So that you know if you ask questions about maybe the stock market I could just show you
The stock market numbers at the time or something it's a small projector made it a little it looks like it's projecting maybe a 2in
Square down on a tabletop it's going to work through voice
So just like the Equitable control it asked questions just like any personal assistant
I'll search through gestures because it has a camera
They haven't really explained what those gestures
Would be what
You adieu
People also
Potentially they said be tied to your smartphone
So that way using your smartphone for information
Presence
When you walk into a room
It would see you get information on you and literally set the room up in a scene that
Is custom to you
Turn certain lights on perhaps turn music on to a certain station
And so on
It's like jam packed with sensors
And have a lot of
Potential but it is still just a prototype at this point
OC that seems really very close to prototypes I've seen from like
Almost a decade ago
I'm really excited about this
The concept i think was frogdesign had something called
The room
And it had a projector it had cameras
I think it used modified connect
Is actually
And
You would gesture
And it would turn on lights if you gesture to a light
Or if you set you know lights on it would turn whatever you were gesturing at on for example
And if you were
Looking at used also like
It's image recognition to understand if you were looking at it so if you were addressing
The device is opposed to another person to ask it a question so you never had to do anything like
Funny wake words
It was really kind of cool but it was also super clunky and kind of like weird to set up but
The other cool thing about the camera was
Then you could interact with what was projected on the screen because the camera could see what you were
Interacting with
Which is really kind of fun
I like the surface table
That sounds cool
Again they the projections really small so I don't at least at this point
Smalls I don't know if
You be able to interact with it or anything I think it's more Just for information and
I like the idea that
As much as I like the idea of gestures as well
I personally prefer voice control over gestures any day of the week and I found that out
Long-term using my Xbox Kinect
I voice control the thing all the time
I could do dressers for things but I tend not to
It's his voice always seems easier to me
I think it depends on what kind of what you're doing
Voice is great when your hands are full but you do have to think a lot more like I found when I
Controlling the echo
I often give it the wrong command cuz I've got
Five different lighting commands
SportZone Lake
Oh I'll be in
In one of them
Suunto turn on
Running rampant
You know what then she's like what are you talkin
Yep in a situation where I was like he just turn on the lights
And then I was gesturing and both of those things could be put together to turn up what I wanted on
Because I'm not.
Articulate
That would be really nice
It's tough but you know what
It would also help if the natural language processing word prove which
It is
So that way you can be a little more vague I mean obviously I can give it the wrong like a turn-on that's
That's exactly what's going to happen
That's user error
So we call user error in the industry
But you're right there certain
Phrases that have a very
Particularly
Spoken
Especially like stay with it the triggers and skills that
The echo is using these days
So yeah I'd like to see more freedom in an improvement there
Of this weird
Isolation is perspective I feel like
The people who design
The smart home scenarios must like not live with people
Because
Music and do whatever you want
Okay
How many people actually walk into their like
House like their actual home
And
Live alone
And don't have other people to contend with when these things are happy
Cuz if I walked in and like my music played
I guarantee you that my husband would be like
Oh my God why is this
Who are you Stacy in the Royal we
The program
The house
Yeah that's that's definitely a good point I think it's
Set plates interesting is it practical
For a lot of people know
Exactly I'm just imagining my 9-year
Run music
We'd all be like
Jamming down
Calvin Harris
Stats Hood
Calvin Harrison
Okay so
Cool things SoDo pricing
Prototype
Still a concept
So much stuff
Sony doesn't sell cheap stuff so right off the bat I would agree
Okay well we'll look for
Things like this I imagine many people out
Maybe not many but some of y'all out there probably built similar things feel free to tell us about it because I'm kind of curious
Thoughts on speakers it's a big
Fun topic
Next topic
Fitbit has a new watch out
The Fitbit Blaze
Did Market udderly
Fidget
Is shipping now
And I don't have one
I don't know
I think my next like
Wearable
Is going to be something that has my heart rate
And
I don't dyslexia
Pure pulse heart rate
I just I feel like $200
It is a lot of minister
What color the flagship device it's got a totally different design and their prior devices that looks more like a regular watch
I didn't want to say that but yet it does what it it's
What did you with the corners cut off
Also it's Sino octagonal and
But it has it looks more like a traditional watch than their prior
Products which look like tracking devices
So
You know it's our Flagship and it does everything that I think most people would want like you said it's at the heart rate monitor
It does include
Call and text notifications and calendar alerts so that has
A little bit of
Smart watching is to it
You can record running cycling cross training Etc attraction
Steps to distance calories floors climb Auto sleep
Got a 5-day battery life
It's nice
I will say it's nice
I actually just bought something different
For about the same price
That is all the same stuff plus electric store and play Wireless music on
Do what you buy the TomTom cardio
Plus music device
It was serious like $25 more than this and it was actually a
On sale so you would probably spend more I would have paid full retail
But I'm very happy with it and it's great for everything we just said
Plus I have forgiven stores to put music on and go running
With the GPS in the heart rate monitor that's built into it and
And listen music at the same time
Remember that
We're going to get to music
Just a minute
Okay
But first we should tell you also in Smartwatch news
I'm thinking about it
Smartwatch news
Pebble time has actually lowered
Racing
Yay
Yeah that was actually the extended on I believe
Devices the time and the time round
Time in the time
Timer on but the time still stays
Okay
Haircut
Cuz it around versions of the Pebbles have been out that long
No they haven't which makes me wonder how are they
Just not said
I do not know I haven't seen sales figures
So War
I think last I heard they had over million sales as of
Oh I don't recall when it was but I haven't heard any numbers in a while it's well say
So the time
Is 149 99
In-N-Out on round 1 round
Is 199
It's $200
Who's got a $50 price
Cuz I was just too much
I'm just going around
In the time steel is still 200
Yeah I actually had a pebble time
That I sold to somebody at a discount because I wasn't using it
Part of me says that maybe I should have done that because they did add some help features back in December
And you know it's using some sensors to track things like sleep and activity and whatnot
It just wasn't granular enough
For me to
Be that desirable
You know. Dedicated Fitness tracker with heart rate monitor that's kind of where I was going
So I have my ancient first pebble
I loved
Because it was
It did exactly what I needed it to do and I still wear like my one-off tiny little tracker
And I've stopped kind of wearing it
Because I tend to wear my ring
My ring late now and I need to notifications and
I also carry my phone more places but I'm wondering if the weather gets warmer and I start ditching
My phone cuz I'm not wearing pockets as often if I'll strap it if I'll be
I need upgrade my SmartWatch
I could be
Even though you had the older pebble
I think in and you can correct me if you know I think you got the time interface that they launched last year
I did as a software update
Past present and future stuff
It was an interesting take on things
I like their interpretation
Changes not
I'm not one to be like
But I tended to use my Watch solely as a watch
And then I only had notifications for like
Text
And that was pretty much it
And I tend to keep my phone on silent so the watch or the ring is the only thing I have that's like
Gotcha gotcha
Everybody everybody
You know we should mention down to folks who just bought a pebble timer time around if they bought it after January 21st
At the higher price
You can reach out to Pebble by April 1st
And get a price adjustment on the difference
No.2
50 bucks
Back to music
I saw this
And I wanted so much
I think it's so cool
I may actually
I'm so this is
Hang on a second I have to say before the show
As we talked about what to talk about
Stacy was gushing over this thing so if it's not a parent enter voice right now to trust me
She is dying to see this
I love it okay so this is called the mighty
And this is
It's an iPod Shuffle for your Spotify play
That is like
I don't know who called it that
How did that but
That is what it is so you need to have a Spotify
And it has to be premium
Spotify songs that you have
Download certain songs
Download your songs for offline listening when you have a Spotify premium account
So when you decide logos onto this life
Little
Device that is
I-75 in
Yeah it looks like
It's just cuz it's a little square with a basically not like a jog dial but round button placement
It very much looks like a iPod Nano or Shuffle rather
That there's not much in it I mean it
There's a battery there's
Ortega storage
There's a wireless connectivity for Bluetooth headphones there's also a regular headphone jack
Oh yeah I didn't realize I thought I had to I thought you had to do it over USB very cool
Sweet
Anyway it's such a Nifty little something
Would make Maybe
That would sell gazillions of
Puppies
Units units
Students
Man I'm so glad this is being crowdfunded
Although I don't think it's made it to it
It's cool yet so it's
$9
For one of these
Kickstarter
Right
You can also pledged $5
And getting in
Yeah I think I won't do that
So it is raised 180000
Send
Now that's $10 you can have a photo of one
Excellent
So they raised about a hundred eighty thousand
Send 200
I go back at its going to ship in November
Actually happens
I am content
Concerned about licensing hopefully Spotify works with them
Hopefully the licensing of the music like I can see how there might be problems
I don't know about that and I'll tell you why I mean if you can already download
Music with a Spotify Premium subscription
Can listen to offline on your phone
I can't really see the difference
Pushing across one more wire to another device
There might be intelligence
DRM associated with
The app on the phone
Typically cuz I believe Microsoft
Do this way back when with the zoo and you could download all the music you wanted
From your subscription
But you had to resync the Zune
With your car
Computer so we could go and double-check
Your subscription status every 30 days or less to make sure
That you still were paying if not
That it would automatically DRM lock all the songs
And that's what I'm assuming what happened cuz it was Spotify the same thing also like you have to
Castle link every
I think it's at 4:30
Days may be hung
So
I love this because I like to go out without my phone
I love the idea of having
Dislike little tiny clippy thing on when I go running or working out
And
Maybe then I wouldn't need a smartwatch that
Guitar music
FairPoint
Alright good luck
Good Law School
All right
Now
Industrial news
We don't talk about this
Because I forgot
Occasionally
There is trouble in standard land
And let's see if we can get this right with all the acronyms
Hellboy
I know
We got a new
Foundation
It is called the open connectivity Foundation
Ocf
Dallas New Consortium
Includes Intel Microsoft Samsung Qualcomm
A whole bunch of other vendors
And they're going to push what's known as the iotivity stand
Going forward
In this standard is used for discovery of devices
In
Communicating what they can do
You guys might be going
Wait a second
Some of these guys have their own standards right
Allcom
Had
All joy and they actually form the all seen alive
With some of these Microsoft actually was a premier member
They were really important
Electrolux in some of the other kind of companies
And
When Intel launched their Foundation
Which they called the open internet
Consortium
Intel launches a Qualcomm freestander
Because that's
Essentially what it was both kind of groups
Pushing the same
Standard which was device discovery
That never happens with standards
Never
So here's here's the bottom line
What I discovered in tok
People
And this was not easy cuz no one ever wants to admit
Things made out of
Rosie
The Qualcomm folks that were working on
The development of all joy
That whole team is actually DeCamp
10 God / 2
So those guys are not working until
Which I
Imagine hat
No small
Leaving it we're taking our standards with us
Still exist
Is there still
Working for the good of
You know the Internet of Things in the standard blah blah blah
It looks like
Almost all of the code and development is going to be happening
Under the open connectivity Foundation
We should expect to see
Most of the work happen
There
Device discovery
Most of this looks like a license
That's an issue
Can get into the Arcane politics
Standard settings organization or
It really super duper arcade politics of license
Guess who
But that's kind of what seems to be
Driving
Is
To license the standard and who has to pay if we use this technology
It's rather interesting to me after watching Intel on Qualcomm go at it in the chip business for
The past I'll say 10 years or so
When it comes to mobile and desktop / laptop
And now they're
Fighting it out / working together
For the iot chip business
It's
It's nice right you like
One less standard right is what it kind of feels like
But yeah it's essentially one list
It's by no means
The singular stand
Because
Homekit
Is trying to do the same darn thing only it's closed in
Apple
And then Google
With
Weave
Is not necessary
Which
May or may not be doing this
Is also doing this
So
We can't really have like some singular standard when we have two of the largest players in the industry
From the handset side
We like our
Let's try to make these
Yeah
Say hey
Headsets
Not needed we're going to go with gesture control invoice
Smell you later Google and Apple
What do we think
No I think the smartphone isn't going away anytime soon
Maybe find why someone try though
Good luck with that
Smell Ya Later app
Okay so that was that was one on the
Kenneth Moore Industrial side of things are the more
Can Enterprise E
Less Fun Gadget side
And let's see what else do we have here
We have
We have it's time for a guest I guess that's right
Like we said it is Chad Curry the managing director for the center of real estate technology and if you stay tuned
He is going to talk to us about
Touchy Realtor about technology giving smart hubs as a closing gift and how your ml
Things may change
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Our Guest today is Chad Curry
Managing director of the center for realtor technology
National Association of Realtors
I'm great CC thank you so much for having me on here
I'm so excited
So
We had this awesome conversation
Smart Home
And he told me
Why Realtors
Interested
Absolutely you know
Here's the thing is is we ran a 108 year-old Association
With 1.1 million members
And they are in more homes than anybody else you know they sell about 5 million homes a year in a lot
Happening in the space right now and you know by 2020 their estimates of
No 26 billion
To 250 billion
Iot devices being connected to the web
And so we got to get out of that
So that's why we turn to slap
When we talked before you you had talked about improving the existing
In home stock in what
Is
Get maybe new homeowners
I'm bored
Sensors that showed them things like
Hey your air quality
Could be.
Show them their air quality
Didn't think to make investments
In their home
Then boosted
The value of the home
Realtors happy
Winger
Yeah so it did that that is predicated
If you think about
You know say that you didn't care about
Taking 10000 steps until you got one of those turn things right
And that's kind of what we think is going to happen with Environmental Quality sensor
I mean you got this invisible are around you your breathing and you have no sense of what's in it and we think as a closing gift
What if
A realtor
Gave a homeowner
Ihob
And some Environmental Quality sensors that could allow that homeowner to understand
What the CO2 levels are for the home
What's the temperature and humidity are for the home
What do you particular matter levels are for that home in the vocs
And those metrics are going to help them understand how their living
And those things affect our health greatly
NIH just put a study out of
A few months ago actually about
CO2 levels outside it was Booth focus on Commercial properties office spaces
And they talked about what a difference a regular office space
Makes compared to the Green Plus or green
Office spaces that have
No air filters that are
Much more
What's improved
I mean that's what I bring to the existing home stock we want to make it so that people who buy an existing home because Millennials are
Clamoring for existing homes
And so we would have been
Bring things to them
I can help them have a better quality of life and was existing homes homes are built a hundred years ago that didn't
They were considering air quality air temperature and humidity at that time
But if you could mitigate
Problems like mold or bacterial growth
Bi monitoring what your humidity levels are in a home
Going to go a long way to having a better quality of life in that home and we think our membership can be a part of that to a partnership
What's really interesting is if you start taking that a step further and you give
People the tools
It makes them familiar with it in their homes
They could actually take that to
You know things like home water testing and then
Implicit activism on the scale
You could see
Leaving out of prevention of Something Like Flint Michigan
But I mean
Empowered enough
It said holy cow
My hair is
Really toxic
Yeah this is this is about improving the housing stock and quality-of-life for everybody and then that's exactly right
Things that where we're actively participating in our things like the array of things project
Keep using the word things but I
I can't get away from it right now we're talkin the iot podcast
But the array of things project is happening here in Chicago and the city of Chicago
University of Chicago Argonne National Labs
All received a 3.1 million dollar Grant from the National Science Foundation
Put 500 nodes around the city of Chicago so we can monitor things like air quality
The amount of people in an area outside it's not it this is not a surveillance thing it's that is not anything we're interested in
What were interested in though is
Is traffic levels in an area because that could impart you know what's happening with the commercial
Real estate
Immunotherapy trophic levels go down there might be an issue in that area that could
I'll be improved upon to improve the commercial real estate space where the residential space
Project the way we are approaching this entire
Space is if we think of the home as a cell
Right now there's nothing in the home that allows for homeostasis
The self-regulating as you have in a Cell for biology any of the eukaryotes that have the nucleus
And self-regulation
So you think about that you got the home and sell
As you work those homes work together and you have an aggregate of data
You start to build tissue
Commercial buildings and become like organs
And the city itself becomes like a body so you have this organic living breathing thing
And this is this is already happening these things are organic
But we don't have any insight into their performance
So we can't make improvements upon what's happening already and that's what we want to do is
Has helped build that
So
Our communities can take action to improve upon their quality of life and homeowners can do the same thing in our members can be a big part
Okay so you start with data about Environmental Quality
The Next Step though once you have this data is taking action
Where are you guys
Or is the array of things project
Going that next step
Or is it just
Okay so what are you
Project open data
I'm so app developers can build upon that
So the data coming off of these devices will be in a repository at the city Chicago site
So people can take that data and start building apps that can tell you about the best path to walk if you have asthma
Or you know what's that
How quickly is standing water being taken care of in a city
Or what are the traffic patterns like on a
July vs December in Chicago
And what I should mention about that
Project or not only other thing they looking at
Chicago they have 15 partner cities around the globe
We're also going to do the same thing put these devices out so
And so
What we're hoping is
With our little project we've been doing we're calling Rosetta home and I know I given you some screenshots when we
Meet we talked about last time about what that looks like with CO2 monitoring and temperature humidity in
And an energy monitoring
We want that
2B you know
Got to be a place of action for these homeowners in for the community itself
And I think that's a really important
And I I'll be curious to see how
Home Motors any good Realtors kind of take
Action because
It's one thing
Here's an informative app.
Succezz
This is happening
And then
There's things that
Individual action and then there's the collectively
Better axe
Yeah and I think you know for us
Our members you know the value to our membership here is that they have a relationship without a homeowner
Outside the transaction
Right so they're able to work without homeowner in and be a partner in the ownership of that home
And the value is you know that they've got a relationship that they formed and in that naturally becomes a elite generator
But also when that house comes back on the market and 7
Veneers that homeowner is going to work without realtor
And when they work with that Realtor
Things that can become gachas
Over the process of owning a home things like mold you didn't know you had
Because you weren't monitoring the humidity or
Particulate matter that could cause
A child to have a hard time breathing with respiratory issues those are things that you work with that homeowner to help mitigate so when it goes on Mark
That's less time you have to spend on
Dealing with those issues
Proactive type thing between the homeowner in the realtor
Will we ever see
Sensor data Spark
Also that's the project we worked on is exactly that we both over a course of a few weeks we took it to
Are standard body in real estate is called reso the real estate standards organization I'm a board member
And I took my team down there Chris Cote Varley lab engineer and Dave Conroy who's our lab engineer
The three of us went down there and we presented what we done which is where we took a listing
Tv listings right now
There static there is essentially what you had in the listing books
Before we had the intern
Why not make that
Why not have that information accessible
22 Byers you know in and we think that when a buyer's first moving into that process of of going
Away from the home they own to this new home
And we give him a closing gift of this device with the sensors
That's an opportunity for them to them start
Moving down a Paso
A corrective action on that home in a way that is informed
You know that they know what to work on because they have that data we had a few mls's talk to us about including that data and their list
Now I wouldn't want my actual data
Set the show at
Catholic
It would be aggravated you don't want you know you don't want to be able to see certain patterns like CO2 patterns
You know if you had CO2 patterns listed on a on a regular basis
Hourly basis somebody could look at that and see how I know when they're not home
Why do we break into their house then we that we do not
Of course so that's yeah I would have to be an aggregate a type of date
Now you can totally tell when people in my house are taking a shower
Yeah
Because
You are so associated with
Real estate market in everyone loves
Or at least that's what
Everybody I know loves talking about
Let's talk
Well it's not really a game
What bone exist
In homes of tomorrow
So
I think this all the time
That's my job
Because I'm a weirdo
So I'm going to throw it out there I think
Cheese
These are probably something we won't have like
No I don't know what
What are you thinking
Yeah so I gave a talk at a conference
About a month ago where I talked about was called 5 mind-blowing Technologies but
It was really about
What are home would look like in 2026
Things I don't think we're going to exist
In 2026 are things like the thermostat on the wall I think that
Within our
Homes
We're going to have sensing technology integrated into the wall
So you can see temperature and humidity all up and down that wall as well as air quality sensors built into that
So you get a good sense of what's happening at ruin water sensors to I mean if you have a leak behind your wall
Yeah so what if a wall could
Change color where there's a leak in a way that's
And also alert you
Yeah
Takes it takes some time so what if it is soon as that leak happens
You are able to be informed upon you know that you're good but whatever device I would have limited to a phone
I with the wearables coming out
But whatever device you're wearing what if you could receive
An alert
On that and that's the beauty of that's a beauty this technology
Drywall will have sensors built into it your windows
I imagine it
Future Stacy where as you update your home
The listing is updated with data from those devices you're putting in your home you know
There's that there's a commercial
All kinds of card building information modeling I think that's going to come to the residential market and it's going to be informed by these smart device
We're putting in our homes I think you could have less and less of dog was not talk to people at work a beacon companies and they talk about beacons and what they can do
Anna Begins now are these these
Little Rock sir would have you devices that are freestanding
But I think Beacon Technologies going to be built in things like your lights
Or
Outlets whatever else you know wall fixture
So I think it's the world we interact with become less obvious in the home you know what I mean by it's not visual you don't
See the thermostat on the wall
I would I would love that
I would also love for my power outlets to go away but I think we're a little far off from
Tesla What will what happened to Tesla's hopes and aspirations you know
No one wants
Just yet we're working on it
Eventually
So here's that yours
I thought because this is something I think about
What about lights
Stairs
There's an inherent
I actually had a designer in the show a couple weeks ago and he got me really
It was really the Scott Johnson
And he was talking about you know different types of lighting
Ambient lighting
Lower levels versus are overhead lighting
In
I was really fascinated by thing
Thinking about like
Yeah why limit lighting till Aiko
Q has with a light strip
So that allows you to do different
Places there and they have the bloom I think it's
So I mean you know I didn't end
I agree with you
Going to be limited just to the fixtures above your head I
I in fact it was a really interesting
Concept that is University of Cincinnati adult novel devices group over there
They had
Office in the office but I can see it working on as well
World Harvest
The Sun's light
End broadcast
Throughout the the office
She don't have that
Fluorescent light beer actually using sunlight
To create Lighting in the home so it's a very passive type of lighting
Isn't
A critical smart but it can be controlled without you knowing
Baffle of sorts so you can you can
You could have it be brighter and darker based on
Are there natural light but
I think the integration of
Smart devices in the lighting will lead to things like you know sad mitigation that seasonal affective disorder
And it's already happening with you but I think that
A sad room
As it were almost like a safe form of typeset
I think that helps you almost know it sounds really silly for me to say it that way I know
There's somebody there are so many things I want to take back in
That statement
You're actually you have a room that's going to help you be happy
We'll call it a happy room
Anyway but I think
There's so many opportunities for light to to be more natural and more surrounding and not feel like it's coming it's just
One Direction
I think there's a lot happening in that space
Let me go with
Like a super contra
Burchell predict
It feels kind of disturbed
Good everybody
Clearing House
This is less for somewhere like the us but more for a place like chinaware
You know
Density is important
Sitting
The cities are jam-packed full of people
But also wear
What about this idea that
With TVs in it you don't 4K and soon-to-be 8K
What about we lose windows
Which actually makes
Buildings
Very interesting
And somehow you think about Lake
Lighting that can be delivered via LEDs
Can prevent
Seasonal affective
Yeah
How to screen
I don't know is that crazy
Yeah I mean I think I think it's not
In fact our lab we have no windows that we have glass that is out to a hallway and I often think about
I mean you can make an experiential
Something very experienced you know there might be a place you love to visit and maybe it's
You know I love Florence maybe I have
Florence projected on a wall
You know it it has.
Natural light color with feels like I'm sitting in a conference room with a large window
Ionic and not
Can affect you
Office productivity in about about Smart Technologies I had there's a
Center for the built environment at Aaron's and his team David layer
Out in Berkeley they've been looking at office
Productivity and
Comfort levels in the office and they come down to it being a behavioral in fact they talked about Heating and Cooling and how much energy
E-Waste trying to cool
Are heat entire room and they come down to having products actually have something called hyper chair which is an office
Trailer has fans and heating and cooling elements in it
And you can control
Your comfort locally
At that space you know what I think
I think you know that
I kind of figured out there but I think that window you're talking about or that of that led technology
That that fits a long it's the same type of thing or your
Dealing with someone who has a personal preference
You know what I think you could have some really resting I mean I can get to the micro units and smaller places
Can you start to have
Less and less opportunities to have like come in naturally and so what can you do to
2 offset
And make out to pleasing environment there's actually a
Call Black Mirror have you seen anything for you
That's what I
Picture of the guys
Riding bikes
Yeah exactly that's that's
I was thinking about that as well but I like to think
What's dystopia with respect to that I hope I'm hopeful La time
I'm pretty hopeful for the the quality you can bring till
Cuz yeah you're right I mean it could be very
Very lonely
You know there's a possibility
So what about let's let's go cuz
We brought up Black Mirror so it in the episode that we're thinking of it I can't remember the title of it
Stationary bikes
People energy to generate energy
One thing that I think about a lot with
Smart Home in a lot of these Technologies is that
We're probably going to consume more energy because we have more devices
Set to consume energy
There are energy saving things out their butt
What are you kind of working on
You know what the idea that
Hey yes we are adding more stuff to her wall outlet
But what are we doing
Please save energy
Yeah you know there are some really interesting things happening in the What's called the energy harvesting space
University Michigan has group
Collab 11 and a Gentleman and purple. So it's his group they have a lot of
Smaller devices actually when I talked about having sensors inside the walls they have a
Something called smart dust to these computers that are about the size of a grain of sand and you can have an array of them that mesh
And they
Have different sensors in them but
They are working on a lot of different types of energy harvesting Technologies solar panels that Harvest energy from the light above you radio wave Harvest
Testing Technologies
So that those those devices are self-powering
But I think energy harvesting is the is what's going to happen for those devices met something I'm very interested
You know I talked about beaconing technology earlier and you have the limit of the battery so
As you to play more more sensing technology around the city what if we could
Be responsible for its own energy
Solar panels that I don't think
They're going to have solar panels just yet but I can imagine a future where those devices could be powered by solar is it becomes cheaper
For those devices to be produced
It's actually Kevin and I are
Actually right after CES we had we talked about
Arm has shown off some of the
The smart dust kind of Motes
And this was a tiny little chip that had
Like
Basically
I can't remember the arm processor name but it was like it did on the edge of my fingertip
Kevin and I were kind of puzzling out different things we could use it for
And I should have thought about
Powering
Wallpaper
Cuz it's solar-powered we're like
You can't swallow it we were talking about using it as like blood pressure in the eyes but
You think about sticking it you know
Wallpaper
Connecting with natural light
SodaStream might have Windows
Really interesting or you know there were others that could be powered by
Temperature change
Interesting options
Yeah I mentioned University Michigan they actually had some a research project where they had this
Additional Bluetooth connected device that sat on the
On the pipe of a shower head
And you could tell how much hot water the whole was using because it would heat up to a specific
Point
And it would fire off
Play music by a capacitor that they would fire off
Answered
You know give you a sense of the temperature for that
The shower scene with hot water you were using
Very interesting
Research project they were doing
Thought so
Yeah but I think
Lobbying
Being what it is and in
Things like the pi zero coming out and Chip and and all that they cost you the stuff is coming down
Pretty greatly
So I think in the pi 3 coming out
Do you know what side the Bluetooth connection now
As of today
So that was pretty exciting me
Cheaper and cheaper
And the worst of a difference doing with their their iot educational arm I think there's a lot of opportunity in this work
Write 2
What is the one thing that you're hoping to install in your home
Like this month this year I don't know
I'm
Really
Very interested in voice
Ina what that's going to mean for our home and so we don't have an echo in our home
We are looking with Josh 8.8 eyes doing over
J-star
Thinking it over there
I'm very interested in voice interaction
And actually as voice interaction comes on
I'm interested in voice recognition
Not just that the voice interaction
So
If I have the Amazon Echo I'm not going to
Toyota Prime in my home because I have to
Kids who love
They love certain shows and and I don't want them ordering
Pacific shows on their butts as it moves forward
I'm very interested in having voice
I ain't what that's going to mean for the home I mean people disabilities and
The elderly what it means for them to control their home and have the settings match where there
Voices for me
All right. Thanks so much for coming on the podcast today
I really appreciate it
No problem thank you so much
That concludes this week show and thanks for listening to The Internet of Things podcast