Hey everyone welcome to the inner
Internet of Things podcast
I am Stacey Higginbotham and I have my co-host
Kevin tofel
And we are here to guide you
This week show we're going to start talking about
Hacked cars
Should you be afraid the answer is probably yes we're going to talk about
Quirky the future of wink
And we are going to talk about
Heaven's latest and greatest smart home setup
We're going to talk
To Chris Bruce
About why crowdfunding is no longer the best way to fund a
Hardware
Alright let's kick it off
Have it wired has an awesome
Some story
On
This dude driving down the freeway in St Louis and all of a sudden
Hackers took over his
Chrysler
Jeep
Chrysler Jeep LeBaron
Which is not Apple
It is a Jeep which is
And
It actually sounds pretty darn scary and
Yeah this is
Well concerning for a few reasons
A lot of people are talking about this today that they were recording the show
Essentially
Let me just get his name right here it was Adam I'm sorry Andy Greenberg
Who writes on
Security topics for Wired and what he did is he
Did a little experiment with two people Charlie Miller and
Chris Blazek
And those two guys are are hackers there known hackers they working
That one is work for the NSA I mean they paid their in the industry
I'm security and they have since
Going on and looked at different exploits for things in this time
It's connected cars and specifically
I think it's a 2014 Jeep Cherokee that
They were hacking into as the author
Andy was
Driving
On Highway 40 in St Louis
He says he was driving 70 miles an hour when the exploit began to
Take hold so let's just let's just pause for a second on what happened here and I'm really surprised they actually did the
In actual traffic on a highway
But essentially the two known hackers
Took control of his vehicle from afar
They weren't in the car they weren't near the car
They were able to cut the transmission cut the brakes
Change the radio station change the climate control excetera
Turn on windshield wipers
All kinds of things
Let's pause for a moment
Once you said cut the brakes
And they actually power down is transmission which meant he couldn't
Control the acceleration or anything in his car that's where I would focus like the fact that he couldn't
Move his windshield wipers at that point or
The radio station
Like I don't
Okay from a safety perspective I guess
Probably not
It would certainly not as big a deal is
As having control of the
Are the cars actually no acceleration and so on
They could even control the steering wheel
But only when the car is in reverse
They think they can do on the cars going forward with this to be a full remote control on hack
And they did it from 10 miles away
And they did it in this is this is relevant they did it actually over the cars cellular now
I think she took the Jeep Cherokee has the Uconnect system
Which I think that this service is provided by
Sprint and what they do is they used a Sprint burner phone
And they were actually able to remotely
Do the space device-to-device connection from miles away
Exactly
So
What should we learn from
Well first of all don't do don't test me think on the highway I still can't believe they did this I could have done this anywhere but
Whatever that's beside the point
What do we learn from this that
The car industry this is actually something we already know the car industry does not move quickly model years or once a year
They changes far slower than the Consumer Electronics industry and yet they're putting consumer electronics capabilities
In the vehicles
So if nothing else
The car industry as a whole I'm not trying to
The point fingers here at
Chrysler at by any means cuz
This could have been done on any
Brand vehicle has got to connect a car
They all have to start taking this
Far more seriously
These two hackers demonstrated
Similar things on Toyota Prius 3 years ago
And Toyota said well yeah but you had to be in the car to do and at the time they did
But now these guys are proving you don't have to be in a car to do it so
The industry as a whole must
Begin to take this seriously
As a consumer I'm a little concerned
I mean I don't know what else I can say
But I'm a little concerned I do not have a connected vehicle
I don't think you do either at this point
Oh God now my car doesn't
But you're safe and don't worry you're safe
I like IHOP
Automatic win
So we had actually episode 2 of the iot podcast I had Josh Corman on the show
We talked about this very issue
Josh is
Part of I am the cavalry
It's an organization that's made up of Security Professionals
And it's purely voluntary their nonprofit that is trying to educate the media the government
And
Anybody who will listen basically
About
Security for connected devices
And one of their first efforts was the
Automotive industry
So Senator Markey introduced a bill
This week that is designed to protect
Consumers against
Breaches of privacy and security from
Did killer hacking basically
I'm in a lot of those are similar to kind of the principles outlined in the automotive framework that I
I am the cavalry
Had
Post so they're things like
Basically if a car has been hacked is there a way that
Vehicle
Shows that has been hacked like a trail
That you can
Kind of show and prove
Is there a disclosure policy that
It shows what you do if a car has been hacked
And a way to communicate to customers what is happened
Can your vehicle be securely updated in a prompt manner
So like 4
Example this this recent
Cheap thing
The way that the update
Happens is an over-the-air it is
USB drive
Wish
You either have to
You can actually download the the update onto a USB drive yourself
Or what most people probably do is go to a dealer
Or really what most people do is sell be like
That sucks
So these are some real issues I know with
BMW
And I think we talked about this on that that episode
At the podcast
They actually had some
Walking
Issues and they actually
Change their system to be an over the air update
To deal with it
And that kind of
Worked for them
But in the past
Auto manufacturers didn't want to do over there updates cuz they perceived that to be a c
Security risk
So in a lot of ways there's like a damned-if-you-do damned-if-you-don't kind of
Feeling and mentality among these guys so
Got episodes really into
Sing this whole issue is really in
Interesting
There's very much a sense here that we cannot ignore this any longer
And hopefully the industry
I I would hope not I mean I would hope that
They don't wait too long to wear somebody gets hacked and seriously injured
Before they actually take action
You hate to see that happen
So that's
That's the biggest challenges in getting their attention now is good
I don't even think
Because I don't think it's really out of the realm of possibility that we're going to have driverless vehicles at some point
It's not really a question of if it's question of when
And
At that point
You know
It's something that you pretty much given all control over to a system in the car
And
Did the situation could be even worse
That's something we talked about or is that something the bill covers and something that this
Standard the security standard that these guys published
Talks about and that's kind of
It's called air gapping or physical isolation so not every system should be able to connect to the Internet so
What are the critical systems
It's like maybe the steering should never be connected to anything
Disconnected
Maybe acceleration should
I don't know
I mean there are definite advantages
To having that especially if we're talking about self
Self-driving vehicle
So how do we how do we build that in
Again
Real questions that we need to figure out
And I think also this mentality and I don't think
Detroit or you know the big Automotive manufacturers really have this yet I think some of them do so Tesla I think
I think probably some of the German car manufacturers are getting there
Is this idea that
You can actually build a connected
If ice and have it
Stay static and secure right
Nothing Bill disconnected
Ecstatic
It's always going
To be continually attacked
So we have to start building things that are going to be
Continually updated and reacting
To their environment
And you know the attacks that are going to happen to them
That is a huge mentality shift not just for like
Automotive industry good for every industry
Is building anything
I agree and I would second your
Your point about
Either firewalling off
Or
Sandboxing certain system so that they don't interact with each other
To to alleviate in a total control our Total Takeover that's that's an obvious problem
Takeaways for people who really care deeply about this
Www. IM
The cavalry
. org
Is where you can find more information on this
The article that were referencing
Came from wired
And we should probably move on
For all the people who are getting upset
Or maybe there's a couple New Yorkers out there like I don't have a car I don't care
Well let me listen to this in your car don't don't panic
Don't panic
And if your car does get taken over
Pop your hazards on
Popular driving in
The neutral if you can
I just got a beer over
To the right side of the road or your near shoulder
And just you know calmly exit The View
That's about the best
Device settings
I can offer you got any other advice for those folks
That's probably best advice you could give at this point
Don't panic
I'll stick with The Hitch-Hiker
Guide to the Galaxy advice which really works in just about any
Any
Grab your towel
And don't pay
All right
Let's move on to quirky
I was at the fortune brainstorm
Tech events
Last week
In Aspen
If you listen to last week
Flicks podcast
Do you know this
And we got to see Ben Kaufman who is the CEO of quirky
Come out on stage and talk about both quirky's future
And where it is now and also Corky
Has a majority ownership stake in wink
The connected home
Gadget company
Software
Hub thing
And he talked to that was a terrible description
Why do they let me have a pot
I don't even know
So he talked about kind of Winx future
So, bullet points there
Ben got up on stage
And it was a hilarious interview I really suggest
If you get a chance
Because it was a model of transparency
In the sense that he basically answered every question that was put to him
Really brutally honest
And he said basically that Corky is out of money
It is seeking more money
He gave some advice like
Don't start a startup within a startup
And that's really hard to do and that's kind of why wink
Was
For sale
Wink is no longer for sale
It sounds like he pulled wink after the security snafus that affected wink back in April
You guys may have remembered that
They did a security update
April that kind of bricks a whole bunch of wink devices and
People who died that didn't come back online they had to physically mail their devices
Back to
Quirky
And then
Corky had to reset them in
Email them back to the home
Was kind of a big
Wakanda
Brouhaha
Yeah it was it was not ideal for any
But they actually solve the problem that was awesome for them and
Homeowners did not lose their settings which was
Nice
So after that happened
Cricket they took quirky off the mall
I'm sorry it took wink
Off the market
So what what we know now is that quirky
The parent company has $12 in cash
That is
Exceeded by its liabilities
None of its creditors want to put it in the bank
So then gave me his option
Order
The first is Wink raises no less than 5
And that gets it through a couple of years
His second option is quirky raises money and that's enough to help both businesses stay afloat
But it doesn't solve his problem that he
He's got two different businesses he's trying to
And he doesn't really want to run both of them
Is third option is he
Put swing back on the market
Which
He's not really a fan of
In his fourth option is so quirky and wing
And he really doesn't
Is that all
He's assured me that
People who have won cups
Do not worry about the
Detroit there wink hubs
Wink will find a buyer we got lots of information about
Wink it is by far
Like I usually successful platform
So that's amazing
He did promise me that
Future generation of wink Hub that's going to kind of have direct support for Hue and kind of
Lower latency and things like that that will start seeing that support come out very soon
Which
I am really looking forward to I'm actually ready to plug in my wink and try it again
I'm here with that BS software update to the existing hubs
That is unclear he made it sound like
I could see that as soon as like the end of this month
I'm going to try it in
MC
It could be a software update
Actually
I see that describe to me two different
So I'm going to plug in my existing
See
Cuz right now the way that wink supports the Philips Hue Lights for exam
Is problematic of the latency side because basically
You're talking to the wink Cloud that then calls out to the Hue cloud
That then says do this
And then
All of this happen
It's a it's a chain of cloud events at that point
But they were saying that
They will have
Philips cloud
Cloud
Integration so it should be faster
I'm unclear exactly
What that means
And no one's giving me real specifics
Because
What I just described sounds kind of like Cloud to Cloud integration right
So
I'm like oh really
How to set how to set differ from
And then it'll just be faster
So if the net result is it faster
That's all.
Really cares about
So the other thing to know is the wink he said
Is now in 300000
Homes
That
Is
Brazy
In one of those new
Is yours Kevin
That's correct
One of them is my that's why I asked the question about the software cup ticket
Yeah
Can we talk about that now we should I should also tell you that he says it's not going away so you should not be
Concern
And II would be a little
Still I've already I've already started it and eBay
Option for my wink Hub that I just bought that no kidding
No I'm going to ride it out and
Brinkley
I only spent $50 on the wink Hub to begin with sweet I don't feel like it's a huge massive Financial loss it's
It's an annoyance if
If wink support actually stops and
Is one of the reasons I drive
Preached in the past I don't care for cloud-based
Home automation systems however
There's a reason I ended up going with the wing so let me know when I guess I should explain why that is
Two Worlds collided
Late last week
I was in Home Depot
And I saw the
Sylvania osram bulbs once or twice
With their whole
Lightify system
I don't think we talked about it
But yeah it's a nice
Yeah and and you can
Certainly by a lightify
Little plug-in Hub and whatnot I think was $50 for a bub a bold and the
Small plug-in hub
But I saw on the box that
The osram bulb with wink
Certified
Let me see what the wink Hub cost
50 bucks
I said I could live with that
Let me let me try that in the reason I actually bought the wink Hub also was because even though I have a Philips Hue Hub here
And I thought the osram bulb would work with it
I'm like if it doesn't work with it then I get a bowl I really can't use to let me get the wink Hub now
If I don't need it I'll just return to the Home Depot on open no harm no foul
Well I couldn't get the osram bulb to pair with the
Hugh
Hub
So I'm like well I'm glad I bought this
WinCo
Can I talk to you in 5 minutes later set up my account
And was able to connect to the new bulb
I should mention the bulb itself
The standard LED bulb a19 base
Or shape
And
It's $30 which
Is less than the Hue bulbs that aren't that you color those are $60 I believe
Yeah so this was 30 half that price
It's the same as
The Hue Lux
White
Yes
Which are $30
And you can even buy connected bulbs for
Connected white LED bulbs for as little as $15
So why did I choose a $30 bill
Because all of the connected white bulbs that I found including the locks if I'm not mistaken
They're all 2700 K color temperature which is the yellow e soft white color
And that's all you got
With the osram bulb
You get dimming which is pretty common in most of these bulbs
But you also get
Tunable color temperature for the white
So I can go from 2700 kelvins to
6500 Calvin's meaning I can go from a yellow light to a soft white to a bright white
All the way up to Daylight
So if you're familiar with those in the stores where you can see that the differences between
Soft white and daylight
This one dog does all of that
So I opted to spend the extra money and get the osram bulbs and I sent that at you more and I actually have three of them now
Did you work well with the wink Hub latency is really not an issue
Which is nice
And I mentioned at the beginning of this I said worlds are colliding once I knew I had a wink hub
In mine I quickly ordered
Next day delivery for an Amazon Echo
Is working wonderfully I can tell when we make sure the microphone is off on Alexa yes it is
I can tell Alexa to turn my office light on
Can I do that before you can walk into the room
Tell her to turn the family room lights on them to bulbs downstairs go on or go often
In the Wink app I scheduled
Times for the lights to go off to make sure nobody leaves them on all night and so on
It's working pretty well and and there are more wink devices than I realize so
/ $50
I thought it was a reasonably good investment
Don't know what it's it's really nice and
When I first reviewed the way
The bug oenis the hardware
The problem but I actually I've liked
What's the software a lot so I'm curious like
How did you find
Scheduling and how did you find the software employee
The software I think is reasonably good
I'm running it on iOS but I know there was an Android version as well
I took me a little time to find the scheduling aspect of it but it is
Pretty easy to set up
And it's working perfectly fine you can have
Daily things will weekly or every day I'm not at this point I just have the family room lights go off at 10:45 p.m.
Based on the schedule I've set that up in the iPhone app
No problem
I also like that you can set up shortcuts
In a one touch shortcuts to
Turn on one or multiple lights
You can do that in the app
But in iOS you also can make those
IOS widget so literally just pulled out of the top of your
IPhone screen and there I got three shortcuts that I can easily tap
To quickly turn lights on or off
Did the software also supports nest
And Isabella does replicate The Nest app in the Wink app so it's
Nothing fancy their butts
I hope they expand that in the future that's we'll have to see what happens there
Profile suffer Wisin
I think it's pretty simple and it certainly working well
So would you be interested cuz this is
Now that
WinCo
David actually added some sensors
They did also add
Z-Wave
Chickpea
Profiles so you could actually add some
So they have there
Tripper
Ink sensor
Which
I looked at
I was like it's like 20 bucks for
Like basically a door sensor
That could be fun so when you open your door
A certain life
Keto on
And they also have
What is today
I bet they do integrate with
The Chamberlain
Garage door opener
If you have one of those
Blinds too I think they do
They do have some blinds
On the express Caesar
Well yeah if you have them already
And I think
You've got some Foscam cameras I don't know if they play with
Play nicely with flask
That's a good I forgot I forgot that even have those they're packaged up with of course the insteon stuff
Yes I know
Come on iPod hug this week
And it's true I'm not giving you enough credit
Ghetto send you in the show you've purchased it was
You've taken ownership of our not ownership you tried out some Hue bulbs you purchased a hug
You know I
I'm giving you credit man you're doing a great work there Kevin
Good job
Yeah I know I have cuz I've had I've installed the wing
Wingstop date they also work really well with the Lutron stuff
There's a bit of a delay that makes solution less satisfying
And that's actually something
Dd2 update
The Hub Louisville
Because that is a cloud thing in the Lutron stuff really benefit
It's from having
Device to device
To each other
But if you want to add some Z-Wave locks
You could have you could do that
And it would actually be a lot of fun
Cuz that when you like
Unlock the door some
Now there's like there's a lot of different possibilities around Cyrus again I went to the product page for the wink
Site and found more than I expected which was nice to say
What other aspect I like about the Hub aside from the low price
It doesn't have to be wired to your router
Where is I believe the hue
Hub.
It has to be connected via Ethernet that's a $7 extra
That's about
I think it's maybe 5 to $7 extra building materials to add Wi-Fi to
To the hub so
Which is interesting because the wink Hub is cheaper
Well they sell it at a loss
Well there's a couple that explains a whole lot about corgis
It does
It is not a product
Sold for what
Well that's better
That's awesome I'm glad I look forward to hearing more about that and so we're going to call the Oscar and lights
Baby 5 minutes
Divisive
For this week
And so it was so real quickly
Since we spent more than five minutes kind of talked about that
You like these lights
Are tunable
They're $30
Dimmable they are quiet when dimmed which is wonderful
Yes cuz
Because some of these lights like the Currys are there loud
They're not they're their got opaque they're not
Like the cheating link lights they're very they have a glare
A lot of people
These do output of around 810 lumens for those interested and they use 9.5 watts of power
Woohoo
Shuluxe they put out there they use 9 WhatsApp
Which is a random fact that my brain knows for I don't even know what she
So that is awesome
Thank you
So much
7 for this week
Answer
Guys
Stay tuned
Because our guest this week is Chris Bruce he's the CEO of sproutling
Who which is a
Actually connected baby monitoring device
Which would be a fascinating topic
The conversation
But we're not actually talking about that
We're talking about why crowdfunding
Is a dead model for hardware store
Keep listing
Hey everyone welcome back to
The Internet of Things podcast and today's guest is Chris Bruce who is the CEO of
Sproutling
Hello Chris thanks for joining us today
64 Avenue
I am super pumped
Because I think we talked about two years ago maybe when you guys were just building sproutling
That's right you were the very first interview
The company
It's great to be back in
Sian
I will start with I really expected
You guys to have a
Protestant
Which is kind of part of the subject
Today's interview
And
Sproutling
Fruit you guys are like
Is this a plant thing what is this
It is
Really something I was very excited
And still am
It is a baby Mana
That your baby wears around his ankle
And it's
It's a 299 device that
It measures your baby skin temperature its heart rate motion
A variety of things and it connects with a
Divisive
It's in the room that has a microphone a temperature sensor
And the really awesome thing in the very forward-looking thing about this is
It's Gathering all this information and overtime it builds up a profile about your baby
Will hear Chris you explain it a little bit better about what it kind of can-do
The potential here
Sure it's very interested in this world
And all its information flowing in
You look at your car
Connected
There's a lot of data
The United States
Taken 3 years to do
They managed to monitor 1070
And since then 1600 babies have been born
Really the world's first sensing learning in predicting any monarch
Temperature
Motion
And
Position
Like you mentioned
Noise level light level humidity
Does have a microphone
A statistical model for every
When there is a child's heart rate
Predictions
Give you recommendations
What if your
Able to lower the room temperature by 5 degrees
It's really about
Nelly having me smart internet connected
Devices
Unprecedented
Anywhere else before
And that's what's so exciting it's cuz I have I have a bunch of things that give me a lot of raw data
But the idea is especially as a parent when you don't get enough sleep as it is
Having something that's just like
Hey
You
Lower the temperature in your baby's room and you can
Can sleep longer
Oh that's like gold right
So
It's very exciting
Now
When we last talked
Can I was this was still something you were working on
And then
It sounds like
You guys
Did a
You didn't do a Kickstarter you launched pre-sales a couple months back
Casino
Last August it was right so about a year ago
On your website
And then you promised that this would be
I shouldn't say promise that makes
What you said it would be out in March and that didn't
Happen
And for their
You guys learned a really valuable lesson in that could have led to the reason that you're on the show today
Which is you tweeted that
You thought the model of young companies going on
Crowdfunding sites
In Kettering
You know sales and then Venture backing was just broken and it wasn't going to work anymore
And I'd love for you to kind of talk about
What you meant by that
In your experience here
Or
Venture-backed
Started
Really popular
Dormant for a long time not allowed
Ace Hardware
Cam
Ugly Hardware
Champion you have
Degrade
You had bleed motion with big braids
Funding campaigns
Really kicking off hardware company
Gunther angel
When on
Indiegogo
And
Got a lot of
Necropolis
I didn't raise the rest of them to actually bring the pasta market
And that was
Yeah and you had to do that as well
Company because the feces actually wanted to see that before they would
That boosted your valuation is a company it really helped you
I mean if you didn't go show the PCS
That you could
Get those kind of that interest at the customer level they weren't going to find you
Anyhow
So
That's exactly right
Wisconsin
Customers there
It was
Willie Morris
Where anytime
You can use it
Turn to having a baby
On a set date
Babies coming no matter
Shipping or not
You are the time we really tired of that we
You know we are pretty confident that we're going to be
We want you to be like any of the other one
Some seed money enough to get
And
We're looking good today
I think a lot of companies
Azan through crowdfunding campaign
One country to another
Other manufacturing issues after chemo
Before I could tell you how much it's going to cost
All of these possibilities with you
Which was hey we're going to
Docker sales
We're going to go raise a big round after that
Will be happy
Is that
I think the investors appetite
And
Pre-sales amount
But still have to go
Raise money and shows our numbers
I realize that
Most of the time that we looked at
Free shipping hardware company
Companies that should have been
You realize that.
Twins in that
Really certain
Interpretation bicycle becoming unrealistic
In some cases they want to see the traction but
Not really early adopter Foxy's a product rule
Probably conceited cell
Party time
Now you may have a problem and its really
Is broken
I would do it completely different
Well I think you also got
Kind of the double
Another way me in the sense I guess this would be your triple Whammy
In that not only is it not an early adopter Market
But
There was enough publicity around campaigns that didn't ship in time
That if I were expecting a baby
Not only is a baby coming on a set date
But you only really care about monetary
Your baby at that level four
A relatively small amount of time
Like
The window in which your baby like you're freaking out about their sleep schedule is
It's like maybe a year year-and-a-half
Or even four months I mean depends on how
But
You know once they start sleeping through the night you get a little less frantic about like
Oh my God I pay anything for them to sleep an extra 20 minutes
Or are they going to know
Where you check in on them every every 5 Seconds
It's like I still breathing I can't believe they let me take this thing home from the hospital
So if it's late you know it
Is it important time it really does kind of become useless to you
And I can see how people would be very hesitant to invest you know I think you said it was 249 for
Pre-sales
As opposed to the 299 on the
How it would be now
So so that's a problem
So what did you guys do
How do you write I know you got some money initially from first round Capital but what did you guys do
To raise money or have you gone
Actually you don't ween raise
Erase another
Since then
Call me realize was
Try to go for a big round
Usually anywhere neighborhood
No
8 to 12 million after
T4
Huge
You know she did he drown
And
Take a little bit light-headed
And then really bring the Sparkle Market have enough money to actually
Try some sales in
Some products and then go around
I think the reverse
Finance the production of the people already bought
Until
Exact model
Definitely.
Like I said we took money out of
When this had in the past
Beebe actually got our products
Shipping in the market and other companies that are still struggling
Today parade presale
Canteen
Shift Impala
And there's a
And emotion
Kickstarter campaign and
Nobody buying
That's true and they had a lot of hype a lot of excitement and then
The product didn't quite live up so maybe it is better to
So maybe fewer and then iterate on your product
Over a smaller number of users
Congratulate make it better which is traditionally how
Products
Especially
Hardware type
Apple products have
Developed over
The crowdfunding
Krowd
He will
Very early.
So if you have
The Great Khali
Today shows is that
Elderly doctor
Coffee Cabin
To the morning stream consumer
And one of the biggest
But really prove that
And you also learned a valuable kind of PR lesson
I think
And I think it's worth noting for people
Because a lot of people still do
If not crowdfunding pre-sales on these things
And we should also talk about the value of pre-sales
And because you're still very
I want to say hi on pre-sales but you still find pre-sales to
To be very value
Circumstances
Crowdfunding campaigns
TR
And so if you really think about it
Dinosaur
Taking advantage of
It's really critical
Now the farther you are away from Shipping
The higher the barrier is
Somebody actually
Punching intercredit
That's what I said
The less likely to take a chance until
Icantina
Getting a lot of tea are around
I think it's going to be
You're much better than
What you say is he today and
I also would argue with that
Ozarks
Just early.
Give me a sentence for what kind of people not to buy at once
Letterkenny
So and especially for you
Cuz hopefully
30 days
You know feeling like
I would probably buy it
Baby products Illinois
Line-X
Next Bachelor
Now you're going to be able to order it
Going to be there
University within 4 weeks
Yunnan
And
I think traditionally.
But I would
Really courage China raise enough money being
I really feel the product get it ready for me facturing
Work with a partner
Thunder standings
TR
Or any of the sort of non-essential things that you would not spend money on
And I think it's
Yourself
How to make some compromises
We realize it
Commitment time really quick
Way too much pressure on us and
Naughty and I think the cause us to continue with the marketing
Continue
With a PRN in spending money on things that
You know we really should have just waited on
Annie support
Restaurants Capitol 4Runner for sale
We had a lot of experience
Church's goodbye
We're still flying lessons as we go
Swelling and I would say
Real fast for me
What are some of the manufacturing lessons you learned because I know you said something earlier about starting in the USA
And then switching over to China
So do you want to talk briefly about that
Yeah sure
United States
For some of these products
Accessible in United States
And we were working with
Need the Nike FuelBand
Tax return
But
It turns out that
China Inn
Well they're there we have it so
And in Flextronics is a no-name it's not like that's
Like a fly-by-night operation
Exactly
Doing something in China
I think they're wanted if you're using like
Entering the facility
Yes cop Knocks
Staffing the highest
Employee satisfaction
Any of these contract
Button
We realize that
Be better and in the end
Sitting right there in China
Problems
The song
Literally salt in one day
Or anybody please
You really live
Top people
Sitting on the line
Watching
And making sure that they're not messing up
Because
It just would happen
Attention
Got it all right
Chris thank you so much for coming on the show I think we learned a lot about
Building Hardware
I'm a little concerned about the future for Innovative Hardware companies now
Hopefully we'll see maybe some smaller runs of interesting products
And
We'll see where that gets us and hopefully a venture capitalist will still be finding them hopefully crazy early adopters like mice
South will still be buying them
And
I look forward to talking to you maybe in a year now that your product has actually coming out and in
We'll start seeing some data and we can talk about how
How parenting will change with the internet of things because that is
As a parent something I'm really excited about
Yeah for sure
Definitely something
Very excited
Hopefully
I can't wait
Thanks for coming on the show
Appreciate it
Well that's it for this week show
And I hope you come back for next weekend
Thanks for listening