Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we got an awesome today
We have Richard Tucker
Mark Zuckerberg
What does he think
New router vulnerabilities
New GPS
Beer batter
$199 Smartwatch that
And as a special holiday treat we are gifting to you our favorite iot smart home use case
So don't say we never gave you
We have
This week's
Sponsor is Samsung
Set a reminder
Husband
On the show
He's on that cranky
Coyote
Listen to what they think about living
Always changing
You know what's a mood booster for Cranky Pants people
Alcohol
Okay well that's a given yes
Super Mario run
You can't be unhappy playing that game on
Okay
What will keep that in mind
Look at Kevin's review on the latest
But first
Let's have a word
From our sponsor
This way sponsor is level education
Level education is going to help you guys prepare for the future with iot training they teamed up
Set up with Cisco for an iot core program this is a 15-week program it's a blended
Learning experience for iot foundational knowledge there's a lot of Hands-On learning opportunities
World examples hackathons and project-based learning
You'll emerge for the
Experience has quote
Iot ready
The course starts February 13th
And to find out more go to level edu.com iot
Best level edu.com
Okay that actually sounds pretty cool I know that some people have been asking me about kind of some course worked
Prepare for the iot future
This
Level education + Cisco my
For you
Sounds good
Talk about
Yeah I was kind of hoping Zuckerberg would have built like the actual Iron Man suit with Jarvis but no no no you just built
Jarvis
But I have to confess I've never seen Iron Man
In my brain
This is like his digital butlers
We're not friends anymore
Woodspring Kevin
Okay
Jarvis it yes
Jarvis is the
Artificial intelligence that
Tony Stark
Built
Not just for the suit but for his lab and everything else that he interacts with like
Jarvis is
Pervasive in everything that Tony has
However yet most people do equated with the Iron Man suit
Okay so it's like a less murderous house
Yes that would be well I mean it is certainly has attacking her people but they say they were
Zuckerberg built his
Jarvis /
How less murderous hell
And
Did it work
It does work if it's limited but it works and and this is what does October gets spent as he said his
Personal challenge
For the year 2016 it was to build a simple AI to run his home
Just like Jarvis in Iron Man
And
He only spent a hundred hours I taste pretty darn talented because
He actually does have a fairly
Complete system
He's got a server piece to it
It interfaces with various home systems such as Crestron system
Thermostat d'orsogna Spotify etcetera even a toaster which is kind of neat
He has user interfaces that he built
I want is a Facebook Messenger bot
Sorta makes sense considering he's the CEO of Facebook
He has an iOS voice app and he's got an Android version
Planned so I don't
Nobody's going to do with these different versions baby switches phone that's cool
I am outside the door camera as an interface which will talk about a few minutes how that works
And then he's got some a I built into it with language processing speech recognition facial recognition so
But long story
Short here is
That he's kind of replicated what you can mostly get
From an off-the-shelf systems
Through an echo or Google Assistant Siri
And various third-party products
But it's really interesting he
Tackle this as a learning project
Obviously learned a lot route up a really long post on this which I highly recommend the read
But also in doing this he figures AI
Natural language processing is a good 5-10 years out from what he really wanted to be
And
I think it's important because here somebody who's in the nuts and bolts of things
And that's
Kind of a different message in some people taking away from media stories and product reviews inside
Actually
This is this is kind of fun he talked about on a psychological level
Once you can talk to it
System so he was talking about using both text
Invoice
To communicate with
What does Jarvis and he actually
Thanks
Text is actually a really good user interface and he focused on that because he doesn't think that's going away anytime soon
But
He mentions that when you can speak to a system
You attribute a lot more emotional depth to the
Then you might otherwise
And actually
He says that once he built voice into Jarvis you also wanted to build more
Humor
Later on in the show my daughter actually talks about this how she what she likes about
The echo is that has metaphor
Personality
I would actually agree to
After using various a smart assistant systems
I mean when I talk to my echo and she does only for me I almost always say thank you after work knowing full well
Knowing full well she doesn't care not listening whatever
She's not really there
But yes there is definitely a more of an emotional
Connection
The interface adapter
Guess which is why you should always treat your children to be polite to
Yeah but I also thought was really cool about this is he talks about the role of
Image record
Technician in computer vision
In his system
And I stink
You know we do have things we can talk to him
Stuff happens what we don't have
Yet
Is really high quality computer vision that can tie into
Like the people who live in our house so I seen it
But in this case
He built
With the camera out his door he he tied that like
The computer
Recognizes the person and then the person is also on his calendar
To unlock the door for the
That was a tough use case
Yeah and that's that's not something that you can buy off the shelf these days that I that I know of
Instead it's all
There's somebody at the door let me show you who it is and then you as a individual have to
Unlock the door say
Echo please unlock the door etcetera so he's taking it a step further there
I'd like to see more of that
Couldn't sleep because again that brings we start telling systems together I took before
That's when you truly bring the smarts into the Smart Hub
So I could see something like the August
Door lock
Could do that
You don't recognize your face when the doorbell
And then unlocks the door ahead of time
For you based on that
But I think that's actually something even if the Technologies there
I don't know if the average consumer is
And there's also the issue of things like
Can you forge Forge way through for just popping up
Words but some of these
Smooth your face yet
True and and granted if
Like if somebody was
I don't know it's a bad person took me to my front door and I didn't want not want them in my house
But they use my face to get in at that point you don't because the computer still comes on
That's obviously not good it's a extreme case
Restaurant
I don't have to sexual though
Cookies from a sari
So maybe don't want to
I just think we need the intelligence to make it work
The way you want it to work
Okay
Is that only one
Talk about
Yeah now let me recap the Iron Man
Movies free no no
I'll watch them eventually
All right
Also so we're talking about spoofing things
Hand
Security again
News of the World of routers there is a new
Attack
Vulnerable home
Working routers
And this one
It changes your DNS settings
And redirect your traffic
Too fragile it domains that can
Further cause harm to your
Yeah and secure networks as well there's all kinds of funny business going out oven
Once you lose control of your router that's
It's like losing the key to your front door to go back to the last story in
You let people in that point to do whatever
And this is called so
This place called DNS changer
So
Looks to see what your IP address is and if it's interested in having a
Get your IP address it's like I'm taking over
What can alter your firmware
Yes I did instead was just bad all around
How can you
Stop
That's a good question don't buy one of the router Center
I'm not sure I just
It's proofpoint that sounded a reported this issue
And that they say it's impossible to list all of the vulnerable routers but
They did mention three in particular for what it's worth the D-Link dsl-2750b are
Netgear wndr3400 V3 and related models and the Netgear r6200
Hundred
Doesn't mention
Previous
If there was another Netgear vulnerability disclosed I think that was one of the Molnar
Routers
So is it right this makes me wonder at you know like I have an onhub and I
Last week makes me wonder if
It's at least on the surface I think it's good to have a router that has
Auto firmware updates coming from the cloud like Google will automatically push updates
If they're monitoring for these kinds of things that are just mean Google I mean
Does other companies do this as well but
Air monitoring for these things maybe that is a good
Way to
Quickly address them
That's true of all of your router suddenly start
Like if a whole swath
Have your gear as a router
Suddenly connect to a different place
In that place has the same place like to grab it smaller
That's actually something that any connected
Company so any iot
I think that's actually a
Big security thing that you should be
If you don't have an ionic or some sort of
Heuristics like a statistics sampling on your devices to
Notify you when these things happen
That's probably a prop
And most people would not have something that that would notify them so you know maybe again the cloud-based
Monitors
On routers may be helpful I know obviously that the onhub
Mywifi Google Wifi do this
Euro is
Connected
Right
I'm trying to think if Luma and some of the other newer type
Mesh networking ones are cuz a lot of mass for your
Email address and I keep track of things
Some people don't want to do that but
There may be a benefit to doing this
I know that we're all okay
What are pros and cons to this
Being able to keep an eye on your stuff
And where it goes
Is probably a really important
Element of security
Right
I would agree
I am not that I condone people wear support
The idea of using your
Modem from an ISP or as a router
But then again there
Well
Equipped to Monitor and handle things to
Okay
Let's see
We've also got
Yeah we had GPS
Serve in the military here in the US and
I'm just going to become a
Location standard beehive glonass
For ages as well
Now there's a new GPS
Galileo
And this is Europe's GPS system that's
Been in the works for a long time but they now have finally
Enough satellites in orbit 18 right now with 30 projected by 2020
And Galileo what is it bring the table is different location
This would you location to within a meter for everybody and if you pay
At a premium
You can have the location down to a few centimeters and I was thinking who you know
4 cars the difference between a centimeter and a meter is
Pretty drastic and pretty useful socar smart cities
Obviously not useful and phones and actually will be available in phones that meet
Galileo's approval and turns out that a bunch that are already on the market
Bunch of chips the Snapdragon 650 617 625 and 820
Actually 10 use
Galileo's
Location services
It's just I thought it was interesting cuz I haven't seen a lot of change
GPS
In the past 10-15 years
Yay
Let's see what else
Do we have we have
We have this $200 Smartwatch for $199 smart
Watch
I kind of miss the sun Kickstarter nothing I follow a lot of Kickstarter projects but it's actually out of Kickstarter available
Directions to company for $199
It's called the ticwatch 2
And
Normally when I see a hundred $99 Smartwatch in like
How much can it really do in
But this is surprisingly getting good reviews it's built on Android 5.1
Not Android Wear which is kind of interesting it's not the standard Smart Watch flavor of Android and Scott
Nice skin on it of Android and
It does the basic subunits it's great for health tracking exercise
Smartwatch notifications obviously the time you can change the
The watch face can be customized and
What's an Android and iOS so
Kind of surprised about the positive reviews I thought I mentioned it since so many
Apple watch iPad 599 from Apple watch for 199
Maybe I'll get on the App Store
Could use on Apple watch but Franklin not use a nap so
You just want the basics might be worth looking at
Also say
Seen it
What do we call seeing at it's a tech publication and they have great smart home coverage I love rye crisps
Light bulb reviews
So very thorough
They are launching a
Matrix
Are you on if this then that or you
You working from home kit
Devices that work with them
So this thing for consumers who are like
It'll probably like hills have
My job which is
Does usually cause cancer
Will it work with MyQ
Should I buy the Hue or
Peter that the wink system and I'll be like oh here will tell
It's interesting cuz we've had pointed out a
An online site that says what works with what
I figured with an actual name of it is
And it's been a great resource for me but I don't think he gets a lot of attention from a lot of things going to be easy to find where is
This sounds very similar
But would be much more accessible to more people I think it's pretty wise I've seen that to put this together
Smart Home Depot
That's the one
It's so easy to remember
I just ask Jarvis.
Okay
No
To you
Which is we thought it
You guys made Jessica
That's fine replaces idea
I thought I'd share some of the things
We've done it we've connected in our house
Houses
To help you guys like think about
Some of this stuff
Because honestly some of the stuff
All use cases are pretty highly individual
And it can be kind of
Overwhelming to be like wow I can
Turn my lights off for my phone
That's not exciting
If you can turn your lights on voice command then it is
We decided
Talk about some of our iot use cases over time
What we've done with stuff that we
I'm going to tell you about
Tracking my daughter
Bathtub
Time
And rather whether or not she was flashing
Too much in the bath
Back when she
So this is no longer
In my house
What I had I had a SmartThings system
And I took a SmartThings water sensor and I put it next to her
Bathtub
I could either have it notify me
Or I could have it turn my light on or off
To let me know if
The water sensor
Was what
And this isn't me leaving
1 year old
6 year old in the bath while I'm here
Just down the hall
And
Little kids that get excited they splash
A little splashings okay a lot of splashing
Hey
Nice
I'm going to cheat a little bit and recycle one of my older ideas just because
It is
Giving me so much peace of mind and I think it's useful
What we think about scheduling things in a smart home
We tend to
Think of the basic senior like turn the lights on at sundown
Continuing the various rooms and turn them off
You know when the Sun rises and so on and so forth
Deborah time-based but sometimes you want some my schedule and you don't know the time and I know that sounds weird
But I know a few shows ago I mentioned that my son who works
Really odd shifts
At the convenience store to work cycle come in at midnight or 2 in the morning for tomorrow I never know
He was leaving the stupid front door open all the time
And so I would never know when that was going to happen
So what I did wasn't like there's gotta be a way to do this
Anyway to have the door locked behind him regardless of the time
So
I actually did setup using my wink
App on my wink Hub and the Z-Wave lock set
On the front door
Saying you know what
If it anytime doesn't matter when
The front door's unlocked for more than 5 minutes
Just lock it
And since then I've never had more than 5 minutes with
The house
Unsecured
It's just something I thought of
Until I
Ashley Rendon the situation so
When you're thinking about scheduling things
Think of things that may not be around a certain time.
I like it I still like can't offer you guys the right way to
Tell your house go to sleep without telling it to go to sleep or telling the echo to make it go to sleep
I worked on that
If it was a way like three of this than that to use your if your mother in your sleep with a device if it's easier
Resting heart rate go below a certain
Mount
You could assume you're sleeping and then
Shut everything down
Mechanical
I did use
Jaw bone
When I tried to
Connect my Jawbone
How is my jaw bone is connected to my nest
That caused some drama so that was a member that I remember that guy I think in Syria could be done
Here's why
Because I don't
Because even though my heart rate is
You know my husband might be up
And he gets real cranky
When you know he's downstairs reading a book and all the lights go out
Yeah I can say that and then you won't be sleeping cuz he'll be yelling
Exactly
Here's a fun in
Somewhat
Silly
Okay this one's actually also the door locking Arena but
Evidently practice
So what I did was I actually
Gave my husband
This is a game using SmartThings
Say I chose mostly SmartThings stuff to do
I figured that would give
You guys some
When my husband
Was coming home from work
I gave him a SmartThings presence
And then when his car got into range and we left in his car cuz he didn't want the
It actually unlock the garage door
So
I got these Z-Wave locks on my garage door so basically
Husband pulls up
He automatically opens the garage door with his car and then the garage door like the door
The car in the garage that automatically
Fox
It was it was super nice and then
I also have
This is through the
If the garage door goes up
After
Darkbasic
The porch lights
If you drove
Which
Good morning at these things to work together intelligently the better iPhone
I have another one and it's actually perfect for this time of year because I used it
5 years ago
I like to still use it
We had
A problem with her
Christmas tree 5 years ago
And if anybody has pets in the house they might have run into this
Situation where
Press
Whatever
Pets was urinating on the tree
Edit freak me out and I want to know which one it was and all that so
No no you buy
Cameras for security reasons are to monitor things outside the house and so on and so forth
But there's sometimes a good reason to pull one of those from its
No no place
Put it in a place like this I put it
Right next to my tree
And had a record and it would notify me when there was activity
I should turn it on before bed and then woke up in the morning and turned it off so I can get notified all day as people walk around
And protect the cats privacy I told him in advance I was going to watch them
Tell nobody nobody
Yep they and nobody disputes anything or have any
Problems least nominally heard
Aside from the fact that I found out which
Cat in my case was the culprit
It actually generated a hysterical
Dirty
Fast video like a diaper video of the entire night
And I see my cats are running around and staring the tree and hitting each other and all that so that was worth it right there
Dfir
Video I think I shared it on Facebook five years back and still out there so
But it can be handed it to pull those security cameras in
Monitor for something inside the house when you really need to know what's going on I think
Yes
And I actually use mine
I use my security camera
Facing towards my backyard
And I have a
Motion sensor
You can use a motion sensor vibration sensor
Or
Bye-bye dog door so whenever my dog would leave
If it would start
Recording what was happening
Backyard
My dog has a dog door
Recording starts and I did that because my dog is an escape
Artist
I always have to be aware that she might get out and
If she does get out
I can either get a notification or
I can see how she's getting out so I can Shore up that section of it
Pets
Make sense
You can also do this with children
If there
Doing something
An open close sensor plus a notification is a great way
Maybe.
Lock certain areas you don't want your kids to be but maybe you want to track who's
Who's doing what are. Who
When Something's Happened
Thanks so like we had one in our liquor cabin
Then every time
Yep
Diving
No it didn't make sense though
Okay then that's a perfect use of an open close sensor that
People may not think of this thing open close all I wanted my door is one of my windows a security security
It's not just about security
Yes you could even guard your cookie jar Dunt Dunt
All right
So sorry
For you
This is
Hopefully something fun that you can do
And of course you can always connect your holiday lighting
MINI Connected plugs both indoor and out
Griffin together and suddenly you can say something like Echo turn on Christmas or
Turn on Christmas
And Wallah
It's like magic
Yep
It works really well when you're
You're bleary-eyed
On Christmas morning actually
Coming down the stairs feel like
Mass
I'm sorry
I don't know
How to help you with that
That's it for this week show I hope you guys have a happy holidays if you celebrate them
And if not I hope you have a wonderful weekend
And we have a gas right
We do have a guest Kevin you're so useful
We have
To call me Jarvis
Are two deaths this week are my husband Andrew
And my daughter Anna
Stay tuned for a real-life perspective
Not people like Kevin and I
On what it's like to live
With the internet
All things
And Kevin
I'll see you next week sounds good happy holidays everyone
Hey everyone this is Stacy and we're interrupting this week podcast with a message from our sponsor sponsor
Is Samsung art
And I have a beer in the director of product marketing
Arctic
Cloud
Before we get started remind the audience once again
What is art
Cloud
King comforters iot technology to easily and quickly Fed rate between many-sided devices and Cloud
It's a Federation of clouds
It's a mechanism to facilitate open data exchange between
Traditionally siloed iot devices and Cloud
We provide companies a super-fast way
To connect many solar devices
And applications and deliver new service
All right well I just signed up for this so
How easy is it going to be
It's that easy
Let's take an example of a healthcare provider let's say you are
Hospital in Yuan to create a patient monitoring solution
You want to use data from
Personal health iot devices like a pulse oximeter blood pressure monitor maybe even a sickness tracker
These devices were never designed to work together so bathing a solution
Like this is actually pretty hard
However without a cloud we've made it really easy
We've got connectors 2/30 + popular devices diesel connectors we've tested and verified
Chase your device
Is within that mix
You can
Quickly create devices in
Start getting data from those devices
It's like we've got devices created in as little as four minutes
You can also connect surgical devices and we support http
Websockets into DD collapse you have a lot of options
In connecting devices and collecting data from them once you have data in artik Cloud
You can now start to use our powerful tools like orchestration engine
Where you can act on many events
How many devices and send many actions
So in the healthcare example again you could
Look at you know Wendy oximeter reading exceeds a threshold and let's a blood pressure monitor
Seesaw
Special Andy occupancy sensor in your home
Indicates that maybe you haven't gotten out of bed
Well that might be caused
To send alert to a physician and maybe also to a loved one
So that would be very easy for
It developer to do with artik cloud
And finally all the platform entities in Arctic Cloud expose API
So somebody better percent point they can start doing more with the data very quickly
Building a mobile app
All their building of visualization tool or they're feeding that data into a
Analytics
So it's very straightforward very easy for the developer to use
And provides a lot of value to come to
I can't wait to get started so where can I find out
You can get started
Today without 3-tier at arctix. Cloud that's a
RTI
K. Cloud
Start with a free tier you get access to all the capabilities we provide and you can start building your applications today
Hey everyone welcome back to the intern
Ran out of things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and as a special treat Our Guest this week is
My family
So I have Andrew here who is my husband
Say hello Andrew
Hello
And I have my daughter Anna
Who is 10
And has her own perspective
Say hello Anna
Hello alright
This is an exciting event
Podcast history
Basically what we're doing is trying to help
You understand how the internet of things can affect
Your family
Because they have opinions and sometimes
They're not opinions you want to hear
So let's kick it off with you
In the last year we've added a couple more things to our house can you tell me kind of your thoughts about this year and are smart
I think the coolest Gadget will call the gadget we
We tried this year was the June oven
It was also the most expensive
And I think that if we only had one oven
We definitely own a June oven hours are second oven
And I'm contemplating maybe buying it anyway
To add to our collection and replace our toaster oven
Wait before you go on
What made the June oven so can pay
To you and everybody
Andrew is an iot skepta
He is your every man
Who is like
I don't I don't want to leave my light switches on to make things work
What I love about the June is its practical right so
For those that didn't listen to your review about that Union
Basically you can put food in it
And it says
This is what I think the food is and if it is then it just Cooks It
Cooks it perfect
Quickly so for example we put
A 5lb chicken in there
And it said
Is this a chicken
Yes and then it said how would you like it cooked
Juicy extra juicy or well-done
And we said
Cooked perfectly and it said how it's done so it's kind of foolproof cooking the other time the other good use case for
What was we were baking cookies and we had guests over
And we went out onto the deck
So we weren't there
In the kitchen
But it
Through the iPhone
When the food was done and we were actually able to watch it
In case we were skeptical that it was going to actually tell us when it was done because there's a camera on the inside
So it showed exactly
We could actually watch the cookies
Baked
Which is pretty cool as well so
I think the hands off
Approach the fact that it's
It's kind of idiot proof
I think those are two things about the June I like now it does come with a $1,500 price tag which is about the cost
About how much I think he's were are Ovens cost
Abbott also plays directly into a regular outlet
Which
Or if you hadn't up and you have to add a special circuit which I think was a few hundred dollars as well
Okay
So outside of this
Particular device
What other changes have happened in our house this year
Oh hey
That was worthwhile or
That was not
I
Hue motion sensors and so we tried this
Where the stack lights this year is that when I tried to wear this year
It all runs together
The stack lights were also.
Malaysian sew to put this in perspective their couple
Rooms at our house we're having a motion sensor for the light
Archie
In one case there was when we designed our house we
Did not put an electrical outlet in the little toilet room in the master bath
So there's no way to put a nightlight there
And so the stack light was
Was a great solution there because you walked in and had a motion sensor and weak
We're able to set it so that overnight it would be a dim light
You know what maybe twenty 30%
So that was good solution there but you know the stock had another
Hub that we had to add to our Network in so the Hue motion sensor does the same thing for us
With our existing Hue hub
So
In motion sensor in that toilet room as well as now in the laundry room
Which was another Little Flower
Heavenly designer house where we put the switch in the laundry room was not a great location plus when you go into the laundry your hands
Anyways so
I think what else
Doorbells I know you test
The doorbell is this year and in my mind
The doorbells are the smartest security device
That we can add
To a house and so
Here we kind of went a little form over function I think it first would you agree
I would
And we did that because
As you value
I do got this modern house
With all these right angles
And so be August lock I think
Looked the best it's a square
And then the
Thank you the August 12th
But the skybell I think
We found work better but it's round
So it still looks nice but both of them I think
Better than the ring
But at the end of the day
Your doorbell doesn't
Connect right away work like
It's supposed to then what's the point
It seems like the August
Doorbell is working better now but for a long time there
I know someone will come to the door and I get
Little China my iPhone saying hey someone's at the door so I click connect
And by the time I connected they were gone
Because it would take 20 or 30 seconds that was kind of an issue but it seems like it's a lot better now
I should mention this guy Bill is a sponsor of the show
I also note that you
You guys and I'm also curious because I'm times I think some of our issues with our doorbell was
WhatsApp Wi-Fi
And this year we changed our WiFi network
So
Do you feel that our Wi-Fi coverage is better now that we switch to the
I would say did I notice better connect
Tivity around the house probably not
But maybe that just means for the most part it was was working
Okay you didn't not notice connected
Let's move to Anna because you know you're kind of is grumpy practical person of texo
At a you forbade me to put any connected things in your room
Can you talk to me about
Why you taking that
Because I feel personally
That
Things that
Teacher's response
Disability and
How
Function works
In our lives
And I feel like especially when you're
Gallagher
That you need to
Where are these responsibilities and how the world works
Sometimes connected devices
What do those things
Taurus
And
We bought learn like
Like habitat
And where we live
How to operate it
And sad will go depending on
A smart device or a computer
Or technology
To do it for us
And I just personally feel
That
I want to do some of these things for myself and
Get the feel of
Gellan gum
My way
That's not to say you don't use this stuff in our home so what of all the things
What are your favorite
I really like Alexa
Because
She does have apps
Silly
Some personality
Which
I really value because
She's just kind of Les
Robotic
And more
Like
Interactive
She also would you do things
That we already have two
To do if Catholic
You can't Milly
Get
A song to play
And I don't know one of your
I'm speakers
Youjizz
Can't do that
Yourself without technology
So
That's more or less
Something that she can help on
What about the light bulbs
We've got some colored light bulbs downstairs I've offered you colored light bulbs in your room but you said no.
But how do you feel about 10 of our lighting situation
That's just plain fun
Can I get a connected light bulb in your room or no
No because I feel like
This time it's more about my room
Not really like the tech in my room it's just that my rooms already
Really
Colorful Island
Standout ish
We've also played with some connected toys
Do you have any things that moms brought home to play with with you that you really enjoyed
I really enjoyed little bit
Because this
Time.
Was more about function and it was an activity that we could do together
Awesome
Any other toys
I also really like
The drop kitchen
Because
Was just
Me and
You
Daughter and mom
Playing
Having fun
We
We're just really
Just interacting we are baking together we are both doing one of our favorite hobbies
It just
Really
Instead of us interacting with the device
It was
Accenture acting with each other
Wow that's awesome
How did you feel about the cosmo
Also really nice because
You got to be the influence
There instead of it being your influence
It has a personality and you can build up on that personality
I find it really funny because
You can play with it and
You can watch
Emotions
And
How it reacts
To certain things
And you can teach it new items and help
Get in touch with both the cat world and the real world
Okay
That's awesome thanks
We brought into our house Google home
And I've noticed Anna that you have a challenge
Where sometimes you
Want to talk to the echo
But you're in front of the Google home and so you're like hey and it doesn't respond cuz you're not
Calling it by its name so
I was just curious is it hard to remember who you're talkin
Yeah more or less because the name is kind of stick with me since they're my everyday life
And so when another smart device
Tom's
It'll just kind of confused me and I'm like
Because really
Like Google home and Echo
Both serve kind of the same purpose
So it's based on design that yacht
Two different style
Invoice and other features
But it's really
Hard
Find me because I just interact with one most of the time
And then
Like a station now they're closer to me
It's just sometimes confuses me
Guys what don't you like
About her house
And all of the gadgetry
I personally don't really like
The way that
Everywhere in our house
Is kind of crowded with smart devices because
In general I personally just feel like
It's kind of
Helps us operate Our Lives
But
Sometimes it can get annoying and it just feels really crowded when we have like
Lights flashing and all these like
Smart devices cameras many motion sensors like
To Oliver House
I like everything's connected
And Technology advances on us
It just
Makes me feel
Really crowded and
Yeah
So I would say so personally I love cameras outside the house
For security which is why I like the doorbell's I know there was an incident around our neighborhood recently
Where someone came to to rob a house
You know having a
You know that doorbell that captures the image
And such as good
I don't like the idea of cameras on the inside
Just from a security standpoint of them being hacked
I don't like the idea of that in our personal lives inside the home being recorded you know that's face it granted
In your case a lot of the
Gadgets you get our beta at best maybe Alpha
So
Which hint
Running into lots of issues are the other thing is we bought this Nifty thing to make garlic
Tronix Shades go up and down
Based on time of day
Well it's been like
Year-and-a-half Fifty Shades of Grey
Just because it hasn't been hooked in
Correctly what whatever what hub
It will work on any hub
Merry Christmas to you
For Christmas I will connect the shades
Okay
Cuz I have to admit it is pretty cool that
You know we've got these big
Windows floor to ceiling Windows facing west
It doesn't matter much in the winter but in the summer it gets warm and so
However you had those set up so they went down automatically in the afternoon
To keep the Sun from
But again was pretty nice when it was actually set up
Okay
So anything that you guys want to see or you you feel like connectivity might be better for
Like in the coming year so
What isn't connected that you're like if it did this
There's a tough question what isn't connected in her house
So many
Yeah that's
Quite
Hard I guess
You could have connected garage
Store
We have Kinect
Doorbells
Flights
Well you know so I will say that from we have tried some things from an Alexa
TriCity usage what's the
Yeah I think it's still pretty hard to get good granular idea of how much energy or using so there's no
Real-time troubleshooting around it
That is simple to use so that might be interested
I think
That it's less
New
Items in our house and more
Like personality so I think that over the next few years
We
Could get some of our
Already connect
The devices
Give them a little more personality
Because
It's just
You feel kind of it sometimes feels unsettling to be talkin
To robot and giving
Monster robot but if you
Kind of
Get to know that robot and
Not personality like a
Human butt
Because that would be kind of
Scary but
Just if it had some personality of its own to add it in a bit of flavor it would be nice
Guys
I hold on hold on what are you planning on connecting in our house
Odexed year
You know I really want to try out
Cleverpet connected dog toy I will tell you that
All I know is that going to walk now it's not yours I'm waiting for the Drone that does that
Actually later this week so it's a shame that we didn't get a chance to play with it beforehand but I am going to connect homekit in a
Which will see if you guys like that or not and
It's going to break things isn't it
Things are going to be broken
And we didn't actually talk about that so you guys are really
Patient because I know sometimes I come in and you're like Stacy
I can no longer turn off our lights with our Echo
That's a momentary issue
Just hold on there
Well but I forgot where the light switches now you know I haven't had to use it in gear
Light switches are big bonus
Contention I'd like to actually replace more of our light switches
With Lutron or
No there's some new gear
What the Lutron works just fine
I will say the other day when
I had to print something
And the printer wasn't working
I was just standard Wi-Fi networking stuff right then
Yeah I troubleshooted it for 20 minutes and I came down honey do you know why the printer isn't working or you trying out a new
WiFi Eero
The plume WiFi pod that I do
Didn't bother to connect
The printer to it
Maybe I need an iot connected testing and
Project
Flight status
The Whiteboard
If you don't need it to be technology-based
Okay
Alright well thank you so much you guys for participating
I will make you dinner tonight as a thank you
Maybe Becca Bachelorette
But not the June oven
Not work on that one alright that's it for this week shows thank you so much for listening
And if you want more Internet of Things news please sign up for my Weekly Newsletter Stacy knows things you can buy
By that it stays he knows things. Calm and in the meantime stay connected stay happy and we'll see you next week