Hey everybody is Stacy haiduk
Bothell man
Kevin tofel and you are listening to The Internet of Things podcast
And this week we are going to be talking about the first thread chips coming on the market
Beauty connecting oil wells in the Gulf
And let's see
A brand new lighting project that I've got started
When did my house that you guys are going to love
It will have our guest
Who is Andrew Farah the CEO of
A company called density IO
Which is making a
People counting
So stay tuned for all of this and more
The Internet of Things podcast
Alright Kevin so how was your fourth of July
It was nice little
Quieter than usual for some reason to the neighbors decided not to light up things after 10:11 which is awesome
Really light up as in fireworks or light up
Set something on fire
Of Noah stay away from
Setting things on fire here but know the fireworks yeah usually don't go till midnight or what not
Are two cats in the dog goes crazy and whatnot but
No it's nice and quiet
You know I was looking at the videos of people sticking fireworks on drones
Switch
You know
It's a bad idea
Don't it does destroy your
You know there's a lot of connected
Fireworks
Kind of things out there
I was trying to think of what I could do related to
Connected
Devices fireworks
The best I could come up with was like chromecasting some some YouTube videos of
Cool firework shows
Yeah I can't see many opportunities there I should have thought about I should have powered up the Drone and it has it
Capture on video the fireworks here in the neighborhood
I'm a relatively safe distances
Calorie content to look at
So that would have been cool alright so aerial view of fireworks
From a relatively safe
Distance
So yeah
I say readers but listeners let us know if you can come up with any cool
Connected angles for the 4th of July maybe next year we'll do something along that line
Reasonable
And then say
I was like from a safety
So
This week
We'll get started with some news bits
The Red Witch
For those of you guys who are unfamiliar with it which is
It's probably most of you
Thread is a new wireless protocol for the internet of things that nest
Silicon labs
Freescale and
Big Ass Fans and some other companies have come up with
It is basically, it's a Mesh networking standard
It's kind of like
Well it uses the same
Wireless layer is zigbee basically
And
That was going to introduce last year we've all been waiting to see what it's going to look like and what it's going to be like and
Creepy cat company that makes sippy chips that are in cable boxes
They've announced that they have a
Zigbee / thread compatible chip
That will be
Sibling
And will be coming out
In volume
Which means in large quantities
At the end of the third quarter
So
Sounds like we should start anticipating
Thread devices
Very soon
Well actually not very soon
By the end of the year because
The Silicon is finally coming out
Very cool you know it's funny that you bring this particular news bit up because over the weekend I was thinking
About Smart Homes and connectivity particular
And let you know what
I went around my house and we
I'm just going to say that we have way too many TVs in this house
That's the only issue entirely for another show but
Isn't going around in like all these things have Wi-Fi
Why could they not
Be like repeaters for my network and or
Contribute to a mesh Network for this morning
You know why not put these
Chips the zigbee chips and someone right in the TV is because
How many TVs do people have a man sure I'm not the only one that has you on multiple TVs in the house
I don't know I only have
But I know
Wechat
We're not like
Now that's a good thing
I only have three people in my
And you have like dogs cats chilled
I don't know
Are the kids all have their own TVs and then I'll be honest
The dog goes like to watch pets TV on FiOS but that doesn't mean to get this on TV
Poor poor abused puppy
So yeah that would be great
Except for Wi-Fi is not a mess
They don't have no no right
Wright would have to be an additional chip
Protocol one
Communication methods such as big bang what's red so
So for those of you guys who were like sitting here is still going
Stacy your explanation
The thread did nothing for
It's basically Wilkins
Repeat with
Zigbee and Z-Wave
It is a Mesh networking standard the key to it the two things that are most important and all that thread is its
Low power
It is mesh which means it communicates like
Point to point to point to point as opposed to Lake
Well that's a terrible description of him
Yes
Which device talks to one another
How's that as opposed to going
From one device
Listen to Kevin I can see it in my head
Directly
To the internet using IPv6
Allure power version of IPv6 but that's
That's really what
Importing those three things
And
Bluetooth actually is probably going to be but isn't yet the nearest
Competitor
The thread
And in the years ahead
That's what you're going to be looking for
Most companies who are building things for the smart home have already started referring to zigbee and Z-Wave
Escort Legacy Networks
And they're looking for thread and Bluetooth mesh
To become kind of
The next gen thing
There you go that's your little 411
And the thread standard isn't actually even finalized yet so I'm amazed that there's going to be silica
And it's actually happy
But hey
That that happened with Wi-Fi
Why why not have it happened with
So
That's happening
Let's move on to other cool things little quick news brief is this week
Okapi
The ecobee3 that's homekit certified is actually selling an Apple Stores and on its website as of now
Today
That's worth noting because even though
Homekit devices record Encore announced last month or the month before actually this point
If it's July
Priori Kobe's are not home
Compatible we've established that I believe a few weeks ago right
Yes so if your ecobee cost 250 issues
249 99
That's your homekit certified ecobee look for it
But the cheaper 229 ecobee is probably not home
Get certified
So don't feel like you're getting a smoking hot deal
If you want
The home kitchen
Patient if you don't want this to homekit
The right ahead
So that
That's kind of worth noting
What's the other little news bits I'm trying to think
I got nothing
So we'll go straight into kind of
A topic that has been weighing on my
It actually have news related to its over so we can sort of
Do a less graceful Segway now that I
Messed it up utterly
But
BP the oil and gas company
You may have heard of them
They are connecting there oil wells so this is an industrial internet-of-things application day of
Signed a deal with
GE
To connect oil rigs
Instrumentation
Kenneth are doing it so they can
Real-time monitoring and
Basically
GE is going to connect
British Petroleum RBP swells
And
Is part of the first pilot project
And as part on each well R4 all 650 these Wells they're going to have about five
100000 sensors
And they're grabbing all the data they can
And they're going to update
From those centers every 15 seconds
So that's
4 times a minute
500000 sensors giving you
Half a million sensors giving you a lot of data 4 times a minute
It's mostly time series data so we'll think about things like
Temperature pressure inside the well so it's basically like
At this time temperature was X
Very small it's not Big Data
The total data that are thinking about is about 8 GB
It's a day so it's not huge but figuring out how to manage all that do something with it is kind of their neck
Next big challenge
They're probably
Have been monitoring certain
Aspects of the oil rigs for forever
Son wondering where's the value in it yet I'm not sure I see it but that doesn't mean it's not worth while for them to do
The curious to see what they come up with on this so what they have done in the past is they've had their own homegrown software
We're monitoring there oil wells for the past 10 years
What they're doing now is there
Basically doing more of it more often
They're doing a pilot project with 650 Wells but by the end of next year they'll have 4,000 Wells so all of their way
Wells connected
And the idea is
Make better decisions so
Maybe they'll see up in the
Off the coast of England and Norway
Pumping conditions are at this pressure
That's what you should strive for
So it'll help them make future decisions based on the historical data then
Yes and
Don't know how to react to things like in real-time like weather
So
You know
Is this like the best time
And I don't know what chemicals they use to live
Extract oil in house
But that you're not you're not a geophysics
Experteer I don't understand
She's a former geophysicist but I on the other hand
You weren't expecting that we're you Kevin
I was not
You got me on that one
So I think that's really fascinating because it is
I mean it's it's industrial use for the internet of things and we don't see a lot of
Use cases for that right now that people are really talking about
And I get a lot of
People who in this gets into my topic Dushore which is I got a lot of people who kind of downplay the value of the
The consumer Internet of Things
Enter telling me that
Stacy
Why are you so
Freaking worried about
The smart Homer why are you so
Hot on researchkit in
The consumer Internet of Things
Because
Industry is where matter
I don't agree with that one but
It matters in books that at just to be clear
Exactly
Play so well and I agree so
But I think it's worth a discussion because I think there is a lot
There's a lot of value to be had in the industrial internet-of-things and there's a lot
If you look at the internet of things as a marketing term
Right so I was wonderful podcast about the internet
Things right Kevin
Video
And you know you could argue that that's just a marketing term
First like this hot topic that everyone's talking about
But we're really talking about freeing up data
From all
Blocks of life that we haven't really
Had access to before so in BP's case it's the exact time
Temperature and pressure deep in the ocean for the oil wells and then again at the sensor in the ability to get that information
Every 15 seconds
And to do it basically really cheaply
So
When you have that what can you do with it
And that's really what the Internet of Things
In the same thing is
Premier solar panels that is also General
Zebra showing me
At what what day did you get with real-time data
So I have a system called in Layton it's a little web server that
Gets information from all 41 of my solar panels in real-time over the power lines
And I can find out
To the second
How much energy is being produced by each individual panel of the panels all together
I can find out.
Historical basis how much reproduce today
I can see what how the weather affected the panels at various points in time
I'm so basically all that production data
Steven
Just to take us all a step further say
Perhaps the best
Scenario for Internet of Things is the
Intersection of consumer and Industrial
So you take my solar panel data to see much I'm producing
You take the curb system which we looked at last week or you talked about last week that measures how much
Power is being consumed at the circuit breaker level
And perhaps the
Utility company can say hey we can
Better
Put our mix power out there for certain people who aren't using lot of power now and so on and so forth
So
You got to have the consumer of all with that or it just doesn't work
And that is
Exactly my
I think there's a lot of value in the near-term
For connecting devices inside man
Manufacturing up
Industrial app
Operations and using that data
Just to make your performance more efficient so like exactly what we're talking about BP in GED
I think
Long-term in big picture
Something like taking your solar panel data
And time that back to you
Production even
For these guys
Well we just had
I don't know 700 new houses come online
This area of the country
Maybe we don't need to produce as much or even send as much you know
There
Those are the kind of things that
Will be made possible and you can only do that with connected consumer device
Exactly
Exactly in fact
I was just thinking back to the curb day that you would show me right before the show because you got it installed now
You can see for example
Each individual client
Practically how much power is using at various points in the day how much it cost etcetera you give that data to the electrical
Company and they can be monitoring saying you know what
You might want to go and replace this particular Appliance because
I can bet you at least 5 to 10 years old is not energy star etcetera
And now you've actually got a feedback loop that says hey consumer
By giving us this day to you can we can give you smarter purchase decisions to save you money
Exactly now I'm not going to talk about the curb just yet I'm actually going to wait probably another week or two so
Blisters
Hold up because I want to have this device to my house for a little bit longer and play with it and get
Can I have a little bit more used to it before I
Subject you to the thoughts on it
I spilled the beans I'm sorry
And then we'll talk about it a little bit
But yeah I'm actually excited because when I start reviewing gadgets I can actually
Start telling p
Hey by the way this actually
According to my data cost
$0.50 a week to run
Which
You might be like
Okay
Yay
I don't care but what if something cost you know
What if I start looking at like
A bunch of you know connected cameras and one cost $5 a week
Iran versus the rest that are all
50 Cent
Or if you want to determine if it's worth the money to change out the lights in your house
Which is a great segue and we're going to
A Bissell Bissell actually brr
5 minutes
Review
So
Because I am obsessed
And with the Amazon Echo
Captain understatement
I have come by to my two favorite things
Into
Is Stacy
Lighting price
Voice activated lighting
Farragut
For those of you guys who don't
You can use the Amazon Echo
Control Philips Hue and WeMo products today
And I have
Had it controlling my Philips Hue Lights in my living room
But those who lights are $60 above for the
BR30
For the big BR30 flood light
But I have those globe lights throughout my house and I I just
I love being able to tell
The echo to turn off my
NetSpend
I've been waiting for Philips or
Anyone really
To produce a
That's white light
And connected that would work with the Philips Hue system
And I found one
It is the GE
Link light bulbs that were designed to work with the wink system
So the GE link lights you guys may be familiar cuz the a19 came on the scene at $15 a bull which is like
Freaking
Low and unheard-of
So the
BR30
Are actually
$20
They also have some par38 flood
That are
$25 Apple
All much cheaper than the Philips
All much cheaper than what I would assume would be about $30 for a white only
BR30 from Philips but that does not
I went out I bought six of those to replace all the current lights in my kitchen
And so that is
What does if you guys who
Are not great at math that's a hundred and twenty bucks
Witcher like holy moly Stacy all this for voice control
I will tell you
It works
The steps to making this work
Install the light bulbs
Turn him on
You
Go to the shoe app you search for new lights
If found all of mine no problem
And then
Once those are in there you can name them whatever you want
And then you go to
Your Echo
And you say Alexa discover new
Devices
And then you hit the button on your Philips Hue Bridge
And then Alexa discovers them then you group them however you want a group binding to both the kitchen setting and then I grouped all of my life
Accentuate downstairs
And then
Your business
That's all it takes
If that's that's pretty good that's a nice way to save some money but yet add the
Connected white bulbs here the link bulbs needed the wink
Cabin and RV label
They're so there's any bulbs that RHA 1.2 compliant which means they work with the huge cyst
Perfect
So
I tested it out
Before I actually had
And a night
Tensor normal-looking bulb
Hanging around so I tested out
Before I went outside
120 buck
Sure but
So let's talk about the cost because with the curb
I was able to see that I was spending $0.04 an hour
On the 6 incandescent lights that I had
Old school belts
Old school balls
And so that's not that much it's like $0.24 a day if you use them for 6 hours a day which is about what I would
So
Corte Madera
But now
My usage is actually gone to zero
It's not even
Not even a
So I actually thought that was pretty cool
And I add my cost analysis
It's going to take
If I assume 6 hours a day
The 365 days so every day of the year
It's like 88 bucks a year that I'm say
Pretty good and those and these are the bulbs that'll last me know 20 plus years I can take say 22.8 years based on 3 hours per day so
Even if you do 6ou
Half of that is 11.4 years so
They're going to be around forever
And
I can dim them
That's nice too
So all in all
I'm really satisfied
The only the minor quibble I will have in
People who are very design-conscious are going to
I don't know if you like this or not some people were probably like it
The GE Link light bulbs
Instead of having the opaque
Top to the light bulb frosted color
Frosted glass
They are totally
Clear they do look funky date they look a little funky I kind of like them
But
My husband is kind of like
It's like a modern-day Edison bulb
It is and
You know you can see the little spots for the LED when
If you look up
They're very bright
I'd like the light quality
Victim very well in cleanly there's no flickering
So
I'm really sold I'm really excited so if anyone else is sitting there going
Man I really want to talk to more lights in my house but I don't want to spend 60 bucks a bulb
You don't have to you don't have to
You can spend 15 for the normal a19 the wink bulb
You could spend 30 for the Philips a19 in white
Or you could spend
What tea and get the floods from the GE wink
What are the GE link
Line
And this may actually push me to get that Echo after all cuz I was kind of
Moaning about that the new price
You know what don't get the
I want to see Echo wait till it works with insteon and then maybe you'll install
I'll probably be moved by then
Better then I'll mail you the app
Oh there we go
I'll send you an egg
Siri
Laxatives
All right so stay tuned because my guest is Andrew Farah who is the CEO of
Density
Today we have our guest name is Andrew Farah he was the CEO of a company called density
Hey Andrew how you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing really well
Awesome
I am
I think I'm doing well I think I might be coming down with something so towards the end of this if I start to get a little hallucinatory
You know listeners
That's what happened
Guide Me In
Guide me back home
You got it
So density I think you guys are really interesting startup
Because you're basically
You're counting people
Inside public places is that a good way to think of it
Yeah we essentially are have people counter and an API
It's kind of that I think the simplest way to describe what density does
I'm going to I'm going to help you out a little bit
Because you
You guys offer a sensor that
Is placed on Doors
Restaurants
Public places any sort of building that has a door week
Papa density sensor on a
And then
That data
Basically
What essentially make that available so what we work with
We recently installed
Indoor frames
To measure bi-directional movement in real time
Typically will partner with another tech startup like a point-of-sale system
What does distribution to these cafes restaurants and bars already
And we'll install the hardware for free
And then we'll license the real time
Put traffic data back to that point of sale system more
Or directory like Yelp or Foursquare
I like
You guys so much because I'm a huge believer
That when we have
Access about
People in places we can do
Cool things like you guys launched a consumer Apple while back
It was like Hey are there too many people in this coffee shop or is now a good time to go
All the way up to hey is it a good time for me to go wait in line at the DMV
So
Excited
But
You have the score thesis when you guys were developing density
He had four points and I'd like you to talk about those four points really
Sure
We really want to see the movement across the entire city
I just kind of just started with our favorite coffee shop we just wanted to see how busy our favorite coffee shop was
And we thought there was already
Technology to solve the problem
And there wasn't so that quickly became
Well let's build something and then
It was well for your builder for this coffee shop why don't we build it for all of Tokyo
The problem with that is
In order to turn on Tokyo you have to figure out massive distribution
Intuit otherwise
Largely disconnected
Set up business
Cafes bars restaurants they don't all go to
Museums in or go to South by Southwest and then like adopt the ladies
Piece of software
So
This was a distribution problem as much as it was a
Hardware and
Signal processing
So instead of building a giant inside sales team
We essentially wanted to
Partner with companies who could do the distribution
On our behalf and we could help them
But in order to do distribution without public outcry
The system had to be
Real-time accurate
Anonymous
Cheap desert kind of r410a
It was too expensive it would be too hard to do distribution if it wasn't accurate the data wouldn't be relevant
And if it invaded someone's privacy
You know we we saw some some pretty interesting things happen
With Nordstrom and and they're pink
Euclid analytics provider
They're doing Mac address tracking
Consumer backlash and then the provider got ripped out of Nordstrom as a result
So we wanted to avoid that insofar people seem to be totally okay with an anonymous people counter
Sure I like the idea of an anonymous people count
And I'm kind of interested
It in this idea because
Do you think we are at a point given their like beacons are kind of coming into play so beacons are these Bluetooth
Choose kind of devices that
Retailers can put in
Their stores
The track people
Via an app on their phone
So
There's an argument to be made that if you install a Retailer's app on your phone your kind of opting into being trapped in the store
Buy pecans
Is that kind of a
Fair thing to do I know that's not what Nordstrom was doing
Euclid
So I think there's a couple things one is
Beacons are often
You know by virtue of downloading an application
And allowing Bluetooth
To work
On that phone or two notice begins
And then physically being in the store and leaving Bluetooth turned on
Those are all different points that you can
Opt out of the
I think the biggest concern
Right now
Tends to be in like the facial recognition
Side of things and a little bit lesson to Beacon and that's just because I can't
Turn off or stop
A video camera from recognizing my face and turning That Into You No data that gets consumed or 2 better marketing
Oh you're jumping ahead CIA
If it's okay I was I was going to say our beacons preparing us for being tracked so getting us used to this idea
Retailers in
Maybe people who own stadiums are tracking Us in public places in even getting us
Used to this idea of getting
Like a coupon or some sort of digital good
In exchange for giving up our location
Yeah I think it's interesting because
103 in short Navy
But I
Really think that Bluetooth is still struggling boo two companies are still struggling to figure out
Like the Great
Killer context-aware app
When you look at the Bluetooth like Beacon Market
And the startups in companies that are involved in that it
It's very heavily advertising marketing
And
Retail dollars
Trying to drive coupons or discounts or whatever else.
Consumers to advertise to them better
And I assume
Amazing technology around the corner
Take a DNA but Bluetooth but I'm not quite sure that deacons have yet
Can I get on that
I don't I don't think coupons are red I mean do you have you hit head up Bluetooth coupon yet
I have not I mean
So I will confess
To everybody that I actually clip paper coupons
And still use them because it's
Easy and
My God sometimes it's like a whole dollar off when you're buying like toilet paper
Coyote
I am digitally Savvy but I'd like
My God
It's like funny
Right there for the taking
But yeah I guess I've use like a Starbucks app kind of
Coupon but none of the
Bluetooth related
Unzip Safari
They're asking too much
Quesadilla
42 little
So
Maybe that's
I got an example of one that I wish existed
Whitney's China internet
I want around the world with
Your Bhajan
Pretty consistently and I live in San Francisco
I don't have a car so I'm doing grocery shopping or I'm going to a restaurant to get something to eat
Sometimes I encounter a television
That the community
Lake behind the bar behind
You know whoever serving
It'll be like a newscaster
Are you a sports game or something like that and I'm listening to NPR
On my phone and I would love for my phone to recognize
That TV
And to be able to tune in briefly to the audio
I think that's like so cool but
It's going to take a long time before
As possible
I'll see if delineated actually worked out we could be
We could be living in that world
What is DLNA
DLNA was actually a
It was a
Standard for communications between consumer electronics goods from back in like
The late 90s
And it was
Failure because
Everyone implemented it their own way and know to DLNA devices work together the way they were supposed to and it was
Is a big sad thing
But
Basically the standard it just required everything to be a little too smart
And that was
Its downfall
So
But that's where things could have been enabled under
Fatso
Okay maybe we'll get all trying to do something like that.
That could possibly happen
Using like all play
Okay yeah
I like that idea though
That the free idea guys
Somebody take it build it
Do it so let's go back to
Kind of this idea of privacy
Because you brought up facial Rec
Recognition
That is probably outside of beacons in Wifi track
Facial recognition feels like very much the future and I'm talking to a lot of startups that are offering
Computer vision on a chip basically
To do facial recognition and people counting
For public places
And this is true this does kind of freak people out a little
But it also feels
Inevitable
It does feel inevitable
Also
So explain to me kind of how you guys might
Compete against
Well I'll kind of economy uses the most energy
Christine startup in that space I think it's placemeter
I believe you actually may have written an article about them recently
The vehicle company they just released a new sensor I think it's called a sensor but I'm pretty sure it's a video camera
Start of a small video camera
And then they do the computer vision processing directly on the device and then send up
The raw data which is definitely a good way to avoid
Some of the issues of ministering faces
I think the issue though is
It's going to be tough to install a video camera in
Millions of bars cafes and restaurants
Museums in otherwise
NN have
Users any be okay with the fact that their faces are are
Constantly being tracked
That said
There is a market difference between
Being tracked online and being tracked in the real world and we've seen legislation already
Start to move towards
Really not being okay with tracking people in the real world and I think he recently the
BFF
Orem
Some in a major
Consumer advocate
Walk out of talk
With some of the companies that are using
Facial recognition technology to to drive advertising you know what I'm talking about Stacy there were several companies
Was the effd
Center for democracy and a couple of other
Groups walked out of it was at the Department of Commerce
Was holding kind of
Talks for industry self-regulation about using facial recognition
Take action
Did walk out because the basically felt like the industry wasn't
They weren't considering any
Right and I think it's that kind of
Damn the torpedoes
Concept that is going to make it hard for the technology to take hold
I personally don't want my face to be stored by whole bunch of sensors I think the technology is probably inevitable but
I think it's going to be hard to turn into a consumer product
Very soon because most of the buyers of that data are
Another big retail there
Their day researchers their financial technology firms
And
Consumers don't like it when their data gets to
To go to the prophet Civ of some larger Corp
So inept that picks up an interesting question though
Cuz there's there's a couple things that are interesting about
Using video or facial recognition
1 is
Wow
Placemeter sells a video sensor and then they have their algorithms
Or a video camera
You could argue that
Their distribution which is one of the things you're struggling with her you're attempting to do or to
That's a terrible word
Cure attempting to optimize with
Using
Achieve
Real-time accurate an anonymous kind of
People counter
They're already able to do because
Video cameras are kind of everywhere
So if you could find a way to
Create like an algorithm
The process data
Maybe on the sensor light placemeter
That's one place to do it but you could also do it
You know on premise or you can send it up to the cloud which would be a lot more bandwidth-intensive
Distribution could almost be taken care of for you
We're not at a point where things are open like that yet
That's also conceivable
Yeah I mean the infrastructure is certainly already there you have surveillance cameras in
The number of surveillance cameras that are in the United States is staggering
This point I think though
They initially began with just plug a sin
To when you're in techstars just plug it into your
You don't give us your feed your data feed
State UK
Video camera
Yeah and then also you can use like an Android phone and will pay you to put it in your window
But I think ultimately
It's going to be challenging to get really granular like in house
Data
And a lot easier to get
Like
City street data
I think you can make this point that
At some point the data inside of a room becomes a little bit more challenging to know
Which I think is kind of what we're focused on what we don't really
Count cars
Or people pedestrians walking pasta
The window dressing where we're more interested in capacity within a location
Until
But I don't know
I think there's room for both Technologies
I will also say though the market for a little bit different and thereafter
Larger retailers and researchers
And I think we're much more focused on
Distributions Tech startups
So let's talk about that because
I think in some of our previous conversations you
Kind of made a really good
Point that I think a lot of
Kind of connected device startups or Internet of Things startups
Miss
Witches
Your end audience
This isn't you're not selling a sensor
You're selling data
And in that changes your audience
Fundamental
Because the value you have isn't
Just for the singular restaurant
It's it's this platform play
When did you realize this
Did you did you know this going in
How does that change what your how you look at your
If we could at least this consumer at we just wanted people to see how busy
Another favorite places were
And we immediately. Calls asking for Innokin can I implement this technology Within
Our network of locations
And we must have had
Ken serious
Technology companies reach out and say
This could really improve
Are Baseline data to compare sales data
Too or to better understand or predict foot traffic in the future or to handle Staffing
Automate discounts
I mean it was
All over the place
So we decided to essentially Focus all of our distribution through
Other people that are data could be more useful to
Ultimately consumer application is only as good as the number of eyes that interact with it or the number of transactions that consumers
You through it
Ultimately we want that to be free
So
It seemed to make much more sense to be able to have one conversation with the head of product to the startup that has 5000 Plus locations
Get a green light knob sudden have
She was pipeline places in to be relevant to allow more consumers
And I think the last one that I would say is
The hardware can't matter
And we have to be agnostic to the hardware
And I think that that was unique to us mostly because we never built Hardware before
We weren't like experts at video surveillance and facial recognition software or
That type of of learning
So it was essentially like what is the cheapest way we can get a sensor into a door and this is it
And it's infrared
Is infrared distance sensors
Yes
We measure
Simply spikes in voltage
Then we look for shapes that help us determine whether or not it's an entrance or an exit
And so
Your sensors cost how much to put on the door today
Cost us
Yes in Swedish
Since we bear the burden of the hardware there
About sub
Sub $40 at this point
Congratulations
All right
And they should go lower
Yeah I really like him to be a $25 or less
And then installing them is that a big deal or is that just like
Double-sided tape gun
Yeah well we actually
Everything has been engineered to be
As
Fasting install as possible
But we run to a
To an outlet
Specifically so that it doesn't ever lose power
And I was about 15 minutes
But
A single person can do a whole bunch of installations very quickly
As long as they're not too far apart from one another so
I would say we start to make our money probably in
Interment 4 or so
That's better than the alarm company
I'm not sure what their their margins look like
Also this is
I should also say you know we charge
$25 / location
In 4 months
And
What I'm really excited about his once we have
Baseline data to then start doing interesting repackaging
Like what is the last two years of the financial district in San Francisco look like
Lingcod becomes really
Really cool.
That's true and then you could sell that Beyond just
Door custard-like the core customers like the merchants you can sell that too
Demographers to
Patisserie players
Gaso
That would be really exciting
And
Maybe then Google buys
Yeah I mean I think it's so interesting because I don't know what these larger companies are trying to accomplish but I think one of them
Points that you and I
Bounce around at one point was
We're just not going to wake up one day and sensors be everywhere
You have to figure out some kind of distribution in
Garza's
Is kind of straightforward but if it works
I think it'll on Earth all sorts of really interesting data about how cities get used
I think you're right and so I will look forward to you
I mean I can see you guys signing deals
Payment providers so a belly
A square
MasterCard any of those guys I know that you're talkin primarily to Tech startups but
You don't think big
Hopefully hopefully someone in a large payment process
Keyshia Cole
I do think it's crucial to get data about where people are
Inside cities
Not just inside commercial establishment
Butt public
Establishment
Send
That's not going to happen
Until
You guys get much broader distribution
Because
Yeah I Miss Polly is not going to be like oh I really want better customer service
Sure
Maybe that's what I mean we've had
It certainly like universities have reached out
And inside you know we'd love to be able to provide this to our students we've had some interest from
City planners who work for like City governments
You are interested in putting it in public spaces
Larger
The top-tier financial institutions have reached out about some of their their marketing efforts to be able to see
Not just
Transaction when someone uses their
Visa or
MasterCard
But all of the physical for traffic that goes into location
So I think
You know if it works well it works the way that we like it too
Hopefully this will be integrated into
A lot of everyday companies that they you and I
Use Eno regularly
I hope so I really think this could be like
6 biggest waves
Oh thank you that would be
Spectacular we would love to be as big as Waze
See there you go all right what Andrew thanks so much for coming on the show I really appreciate it
Certainly certainly thanks so much for having me Stacy
Well that's it for this week show so I hope you come back for next week and thanks for listening