Hey everybody this is the fortune Internet of Things podcast with your hoes
Stacey Higginbotham Andrew
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And you
Astute listeners might have noticed that we added a brand name to the beginning of our podcast
That is because
Nothing about the show will change but
Fortune is now going
To be affiliated with
So if you guys aren't aware of the IMF
Senior editor Fortune Magazine
And Kevin you are a
A contributing writer at ZDNet.
Later in the show Kevin and I talked about the ecobee3 thermostat
After we recorded the show we found out
Did some of the information that we had was
Was incorrect
The ecobee3 thermostat
What is homekit
Compatible
Must be purchased
Now the existing ecobee
Trees are not
Homekit
Compatible
And now
Onto the show
All right so getting
It started with this week's news we should start with
I don't know
Google IO
Yeah let's do that since I Google I always last week
And
Not too many surprises there
In terms of everything it was announced and even some things that weren't announced
But I expect
Brillo
Became reality we heard about Brillo before Google IO
And the Rumor at the time was it would be
Google's
I'll call it second
Attempt at The Internet of Things cuz I do remember their Android at home
Effort back in 2011 that really went nowhere
I think it's time as we might have talked about on the Pryor Show
But yesterday announced Brillo which is
I guess you could say it's a small slice of Android for later devices that you may have around your home
Are there also an ounce
Weave which
Are your thoughts on Stacy because
It was kind of like this
Nebulous
Platform was going to tie everything together
They also said
That they would be Wi-Fi Bluetooth sport as well as
Thread which I think again we talked about it last show so
New products
Announce this kind of reminds me of what Apple did last year
At WWDC in 2014
Hey working at home kit
And you're not smart home
300s and yada yada
It only just now a year later the Racine products for that so there's no
Willow products at this is Google
Doing what they do they put the platform of the tools out there
And hope that developers and
Hardware partners
Support them
So exact
I think there's a lot going on
Behind the scenes
Google
I've got to be honest I talked to a lot of people
Those before Google IO and then after Google IO to figure out a little bit
More about brillo and I have heard so many conflicting reports
Conflicting they're just
Brillo could be so many things to so many people and it sounds like Google's not even sure
What they're after
You're like I can't even get specs
On
The processing power of the memory footprint needed to run Brillo which is
It's going to be an OS for the internet of
It is designed to be lightweight enough
According to the two minutes that Google devoted to it
Hey Google
To be lightweight enough to run on you don't blocks
And small device
Says but also be powerful enough that it could power you know industrial internet operations like
No farming
And
Machines
So
I kind of look at that
Wow you just basically defined the entire ecosystem inside we're going to build something that's going to run on that
And it's a stripped-down version of Android
And so I think
I don't know if there's a one-size-fits-all there
Google has the
Props
And Acumen to do it
When I look at Merlot
It could compete with some of the other operating systems out there such as
Arm is doing an embedded OS
That's a little bit lighter weight
There's a lot of
Custom
OS is out there
For iot that come on a lot of the chips
And then there's a lot of custom platforms out there from
Kind of a lot of these
Cloud providers that work with both
Hardware and
The cloud side sole
Electric imp
They do a Wi-Fi module plus a cloud side thing
There's particle
They've got modules plus a cloud support side thing
So
It looks like
Google could be going
After all of that
Ennui
I don't even know what to tell you
They showed two slides
Did I think they should actually
Sephora total slides
Related to iot one of which was like
Google The Internet of Things
It does lie detector
Satisfy that actually showed
Brillo it action and there was actually
People were very excited about
A TV
Be listed among the devices
Controlled and yes I do think there is going to be
A home entertainment component here because it just makes sense
And then there was the weave slide which showed
Basically
Brillo at a circle with Brillo
Weave in the cloud
Are the arrows all went around
And there's a little bit of code
You know some people were trying to parse
The code and
I am not sure if that's great or not I look at we
They said it was
Communications
Schema
They were very careful not to call it a proton
I still think it's going to
Pete with all join
Anaya tivity
So
The idea is to
Talking about what device is schema that says what a device
Is it communicates what a device does
And that is exactly what both
The Intel kind of iotivity
Standard is trying to do and that's Intel and a bunch of other companies Bandit around them and then Qualcomm
Other companies are doing all seen
And all join
With you all seen Alliance
And that's exactly what that's trying to do
And we've looks like it might sit on top
Top of that or
Do the same thing but it might be kind of
A couple layers
But I was going to say you know a little bit more about the
So I'd be curious like
Schema versus a protocol if you know what that means
Will a schema defines data
So I asked her to get that I mean you have your new might have XML schemas and in
Apps and web pages and such
The thing is
I think
Principle I agree with everything you just said
It's
Ultimately this is so far very confusing because you said Google is very specific
To say that we wasn't protocol
And here's the funny thing
If you go to developers. Google.com oberlo
Which is where you should find everything about furlough
You have one webpage
And a contact form on it
And right smack in the middle of the web page it says
Weave the iot protocol for everything
So they're sending a lot of mixed messages here I think
It just matter what you
You originally said that they're just going after the entire
Space here
And
Yeah I don't think that's a smart approach
I can imagine I'm not going to say that Apple's going to be successful here
I think Apple will be at least
Initially more successful because
They focused on very specific bit
Accent Home Care
We'll talk about that in a minute
I will say so the one thing that we didn't talk about and we should
They said that
Android devices will automatically recognize devices running
Brillo
So consumers Ed even people running like Android tablets and stuff and Industrial Ave
Vacations
That's a big deal
Because that gives it that kind of home kit
Capabilities
In the sense that
Boom you have automatic
Hey
Look it's a
You're at your phone will be like
Yo it's a
It's a TV running
Brillo or it's a door lock running Brillo
I know what it is I can talk to it
Presumably using weave
So that's
That's worth noting because I that could be
Huge because the Android ecosystem is huge
Massive
One other one other related pointer that Google says that support for weed is built into Android
And easily available for iOS so typical for Google they will
Make their services available for iOS even it was a smaller group of people with a very engaged group of users
I'm happy to see that because I'm all about the whole cross platform support I switch phones over time
My phone is collecting dust right now and I have an Android phone this week so
Again typical Google I'm glad
All right
So so yes that that's
What we know so far about Brillo in
Weave
Alright next up also at Google IO I was really excited about this
Because I'm So Into
Fashion and also
Because I hate screens
Kevin knows who I know
Is Project Jacquard
Which
Is one of Google's advanced
Technology project
What it is
Is Project Jacquard is a way to weave
Conductive thread
Into any type of
Google
As a partnership with Levi's if they announced at Google IO
That they're going to work together in
Kinect developing
I'm guessing conductor
The cloth
Conductive cloth is not new
We've actually talked to some companies like own signal makes
Shirts that use conduct
The cloth
Wechat at
A company that makes
Socks I actually have a pair of them right now
Constance Aria
And the socks are some sort of Fitness socks and they have conductive threads
What this does is this basically like
Yuan the fitness side
But you take all kinds of like heart rate respiration
Pressure sensors all this kind of stuff is built into the fabric and then it communicates to an electronic device
And it goes to your smartphone and all these Fabrics are actually washable
Once you take the little
Electronic
Pod out of
And project soli
Is really interesting even beyond the clothing project soli is
Google using radar
A device emits radar and then
It can detect
Beer
Tidy little motions in your fingers in disruptions in the radar signal
And it reads those is basically another gesture interface
So if you put that on the fabric you can like
Pinch the fabric or like big tiny little gestures on the fabric
And you're basically
Creating a touch interface on
Wherever
Yeah this is this is all interesting as you said we've we've had the conductor fibers before I test of the arm signal shirt
Got my respiration heart rate and all that fun stuff
Washable vest
With these fibers in them
Your test of the socks and whatnot
It's the twist here obviously Google is going after interphase as opposed to gathering information
I'm not sold at that
Going to take off
And the thing is
For most of the advanced
Technology projects in Google group
They want to go from
Idea to product within two years or their thought is we spike it
And in two years I don't know the Ring of interfaces
Hilton to close
Listen and have people accept the fact that
Yeah you can use her shirt
To swipe through screens on your phone and such
I think it's very ambitious
And it's interesting
What are the things they talked about using it on furniture
And what if you take it outside clothing and you think about it as
Anything where there's fabric
EXO
Sure like so your chair that you're sitting any kind of like a captain's chair and
And the change things
That displays on your screen that you're staring at on the run your desk and so on
Yeah I mean it. Just moves the interface from close to something else
Other than the screen
I don't know I mean
Furniture we we we still even talking about embedding
Wireless charging into furniture for three or four years and that's nobody's really interested in that either side
Doing is one thing but having people mainstream people really go after it is another
Well yes
I haven't found anybody
I've not seen it
Inaction yet
I don't even have and I try and get all the way to stuff
End tables pretty clunky
That's that's
Keep around
I don't know you
All right
Let's see
What else do we have
Oh
Other exciting news is
Tuesday in
London a researcher security researcher from OpenDNS
I should get a really interesting presentation
Related to
Corporate networks and The Internet of Things
This I hate this acronym but people
Love to talk about BYOD which is This Acronym of bring your own device into the network it have
Years ago when everybody
I was doing it at least a decade ago
You're such a rebel you're an early adopter Double Trouble every day
So what's interesting about BYOD is now with all these crazy connected gadgets
OpenDNS as research has shown that there is actually a BYO iot
Movement happen
Hang and
What they did is
They looked at DNS
Records
Did they can see from their clients
Stay host
DNS servers
So they looked at
Basically call-outs from
Devices on
Clients Networks
Stussy like what devices were on the networks and where they were calling out to
And they discovered that a lot of Highly secure
Industries
Have a lot of really in
Secure connected devices from the home like
Ness and drop cams and
Smart TVs and things that
They may not be insecure
We're leaving the home but for a corporate it Network they're not
Up to
Corporate it
Par I guess would be the way to think about it yes Kevin
Oh absolutely not these things
And you know I come from the rebellious side where I was bringing stuff in all the time
But the fact that matters East things to bring risk into the Enterprise
In terms of you know losing
Potential
Data
Becoming infected spreading malware or viruses throughout the network
Git level
So this is this is
If this is a problem I mean especially in regulated in
Right where that method the data is
Has to be protected and someone is over that's that's it
That's a big issue
It is but this report to be clear was not trying to uncover a hat
This is talking about a pattern of behavior that enterprises don't even
Real Isaac
What struck me about it
Was the recommendations which were
The consumer devices
Need better.
Segmentation for corporate net
Cuz right now they're built
For consumers in
Did it needs to be aware of where there traffic is going
And he gave the example of the Samsung Smart TVs which a couple months ago I believe it was as they got in Allah
A lot of trouble over in the news because
The terms of service
Noted that
These are boys control TV so the TVs were listening
For their wake
Basically all the time all the time
And
This researcher pointed out that
A lot of these TVs are in boardrooms where
Companies might hold
Very important
Insecure beatings and
Did you really want something
Could be
Listening all the time have that capability and was attached to the internet in a way that
Wasn't necessarily secure and was also apparently calling South Korea
Ito
Is it malicious
Probably not
Could it be exploited
Yeah
So that was kind of a really IOP
Report it don't freak out but I would say
Suggest if you're if you're in corporate it you may want to check out there
Report otherwise if you're building a connected home device
When they sneak into the Enterprise
Maybe you should think about that market in Star Building better security
What just building better security but documenting it better
Because
That will only help everyone
Finally
We'll go to our final bit of news
Which is
Homekit devices
Are coming
Very soon
Really soon
That to our
Get ready for my music Kevin r
Minit review
So let's let's
Talk about some of the devices
What we think about
Yasso
A lot of these devices
We heard about them before it's just now becoming an availability thing we have the
Apple WWDC or worldwide developer
The conference next week so
I'm sure all these were some of these
Harbor Partners will be on stage
Show off
Homekit devices
I think
I'm not mistaken the first one is currently available solutreans
Caseta Wireless line is that correct I said it correctly
I think it's caseta I take a setup but I'm pretty sure it's cuz he died I talk to Lutron and I
Okay well that's what I got to write that most the caseta wireless line of switches and dimmers
Among the first products
The starter kit which I think has two dimmers two remotes and two pedestals
Humsafar to 2995 Apple Stores will sell it
So as other locations I know Lutron put out a big press release about it today
Making a big
Splash
So there's that one right there
Smart home which is what I've shop many many times over the last 10 years they've got their insteon hubs
Well now the new $150 insteon hub
Pro is
Compatible with homekit
It looks like
That's not going to start shipping until July but you know I know you can order it today cuz I looked at ordering when I actually added to my car at the
Check out
I have a older insteon Hub here States and I suspect
I'm guessing it's not
Firmware upgradeable
My understanding
Cuz I talk to insteon CEO
At CES
And I asked him this question thinking about you and your insteon care and he said that you're going to have to buy a new one because
The
WiFi and mfi certification stuff inside
Certain ships only certain chips
Are going to be
Needed and
Probably don't have
No probably not
Pains of being
Early adopters
Let me tell you because you use that Smart Hub
So so much yes
I used to
Anyway
To you and I I think
Well you switch your thermostat quite a bit I'm I'm kind of sold on the nest
I know you swapped yours out
2 * 2
I don't know if you tried the ecobee3 but now that is homekit
Compatible
Sell directly to the Apple Store
In Apple Store it is
It does say as of today at 2 to 3 weeks delivery window it's $250
Disable controller from your iPhone iPad so on and so forth the auto way to text
Cancel very similar to nest
Can't think of any major
Differences between the two and I don't know if you know of any but
To see what a set-up guide
This is by
Farm I
Favorite
Thermostat
Ww3
Made by probably my favorite favorite thermostat
So
Awesome
Because ecobee learn from the nest
And took all of their like
Nerdy openness sensibilities
And crammed a beautiful design wrap around it
And then they went one up above nest
An added sensors
So with the ecobee3 you get a sensor
And you can buy additional sensors
That you put in rooms outside the thermostat
And they actually communicate back to the thermostat and then there's the magical Outlet
The tell your thermostat
Oh hey
This room is like
85 where is back in that cool hallway that you're in it's like
78 Sol
Maybe we need to crank up the are a little bit more because
This is the priority
You can buy additional sensors
So you can add it to as many rooms as you have in your house or as many rooms as you
You want to monitor
And
I love it
I really do
Weird constantly working at home but the thermostat is downstairs and we are both upstairs so
Sometimes we are hot when it's cold downstairs
The sensors should help with device
Olor devices because of the line of device
Message from Elgato it's bees product line
These are relatively inexpensive
Just kind of nice but they're mostly
Sensors in an information-gathering device
So you can
You can get the indoor air quality temperature and humidity inside you can you put it outside sensor and
Sketcher temperatures are pressure and so on outside
Their door
Sensors for open and close actions
Which is interesting but also
Keep track of what time those open and close and also the duration
And so you know maybe you can find out if somebody left the back door wide open and they're letting all the
Flies in the summer or something like that
And also you can add
Smart's to appliances through the eve energy
It basically sits between
Well it's really for four lights I would say
Put a lightbulb in this and then you put this
This into an outlet and you can measure the
Power consumption and also turn
They switch on or off
So these all Ranger price for about 40 to $80 so little
Less expensive
And that fits with how much most sensors right now
So
I'm looking at those in
That to me
Strikes me is very much
In competition with all of the kind of smart home
I was out there cuz a lot of those have a lot of sensor options for SmartThings has a bunch of sensors
Weibo actually has just announced align its es&l Salina sensors that still aren't on the market yet but
Presumably are coming out in time for the holidays
So
It is kind of odd to me actually because
And this is great because we have as our guest
On this week's show Chet Pipkin who is the CEO of Belk
Owns WeMo
We're going to be talking about
Why the rush.
Add sensors would write down most consumers seem to be buying
One-off devices to perform a single function
Are people really ready to grab
And by all these sensors so
We can look forward to that
Yashow from a review perspective
Cossetta's
Now I'm exhausted I've lost
Casita
I cannot recommend them
Like I loved
They are functional even when they're not connected
They are just really a great
Product you do have to install
The switches
You have to rip out your existing switch box which isn't hard but can intimidate some people
So you may want to get an electrician to do it if you're worried about
Turning off your breaker in messing with the wires
But they are amazing and
The remote controls
They work with all
Kinds of things I'm really curious to see if homekit
Will support using those remotes later on with other lights like used because
That's something that
I could do with the Staples connect Hub and I actually
A lot of value from doing that cuz I
Connect a bunch of
Desperate
Devices
Penguin remote control
So look for that that would be cool
And then
Can't recommend that Highway
And thieves product line
I mean it looks like
I will tell you though
Looking at all those white boxes I'm not sure if I really want those in my house especially with a lot of other War
Multifunction device is coming that will do
Indoor air quality temperature and humidity
Like those sensors from
Humidity and
Temperature
So you may not
Need bees
Just think about it
It been with a lot of these products safe for the insteon Hub you don't need a hub
And so that leads to one last question that I have for you and I think it's very time we considering next week
After WWDC will be recording another show
Do you think
There's a new Apple TV that acts as a homekit hub
I hope so there has to be if you've got these open close sensors and things like this
There's no reason to have
Sensors if you're not going to have
Them
Trigger action
Especially with other devices
Guess
Just notifying you that a door open and closed
Is not exciting to the average
So
You want to know that that door open and close did you want that to trigger
Your lights.
Or
Say something
I don't know what I said to do that
And to do it consistently even when your phone is away from home
You need a hug
Inside your house
So I think I think you're right and I do think we will see that next week
That's
I assume it's going to be an Apple TV but
Maybe they'll be a coloring box and it will Doom
We will see
Awesome alright
That's it for this week
And
Stay tuned for our guests who again is checked
Pipkin the CEO of weibo
And we will see you next week
After we do more from Apple and we will have an exciting device review with the ring doorbell
And it will be a lot of fun
Thanks for listening
Hey everybody welcome back to the fortune Internet of Things podcast
And I have with me Our Guest today
Who is
Chit
Pipkin who is the CEO of Belkin
I checked thanks for coming on the show
Hello and thanks so much for having me here
I am really excited I was
Just before the show started I was talking
Chat Noir saying
You guys have a great business because I think I have bought
More products from Belkin that I have either
Lost
Store has stored in a box
And then we bought
Because I needed it and I couldn't find it
So ye on you
Spell thank you very very much for all of that we've been around for about
30 years or so so we would hope
Set you have at least a few things
Stacy
I do might the reason you're on the show is because I have
WeMo products
WeMo is your lineup
Connected
Home Products
Sand
They include connected Wi-Fi light switches connected Outlets
Confusingly you guys call a switch
Connected cameras
And an upcoming line of
Sensors
And a bunch of other things light bulbs
Actually also
Yeah we've actually been building up
Platform for about
6 years I'm not always
That excited about this term of like smart home or
Connected home but I don't think we have found a better way to be able to
The kind of talked about that but it is
Short of being able to enable experiences that people want
To have hey I want my lights coming up
On when the Sun goes down
I don't want my irrigation system to
Water when it's raining outside
Big Apple to unlock
These kinds of experiences for folks is really fun place to be
I think it's a good one you've been very open so far you guys have done a lot of work with
If this then that
Which is a connected
Platform that lets you link devices to web services
You actually are one of the two companies that work right now with the Amazon Echo
And
For a long time I have had devices on the SmartThings platform that work with WeMo
Pad
What
Appear to be hacked
WeMo things with applications on my phone such as
Reach or you know me
So I'm very curious because this week we are in the middle of a bunch of news in this space we
With Apple and Google
Both announcing pretty big
Efforts
Where is WeMo going to play
This is all sort of
Unfolding the way that we would have helped it too and that's great to see other folks coming on
Okay now you are not a apple
Apple homekit partner
Write like a formal app
Yeah we're not announced formally today
So we're in did really close dialog
To figure out on a collective basis
What's the best
Way to really enhance
And further
Stand
Liam homekit if experiences and the WeMo experiences
In the bath
Possible way
A couple weeks ago I got on the podcast and was a little frustrated with me Moby
Because I couldn't
Use
My
Switch exactly like I wanted to I kept having issues with it
Kind of understanding what state it was in
And I suspect it was because I was using it with
Too many
Apps
So I was
I would turn it on with my Amazon Echo and maybe I would turn it off via SmartThings
And
Sometimes it just would
Worker wouldn't know where it was
So I would love to get your take on
Is this a problem that I'm experiencing because I am just
Crazy and using way too many app
Applications
I know that some developers have expressed
Appreciation with
Keno cloud and I just love to hear
As a user
What should I be doing here
And is there anything that we most trying
I don't know address
These issues
Yasso
Our promise and our
Commitment around the WeMo brand
Would be for us to do everything we can do to make
Those experiences you you are having
Reliable land
Consistent as we
Cam
And it is
Inevitable that this is going to get
Increasingly complicated for all of us
So working off of the WeMo app
Is complicated
For us but it should be really simple for the
User
Being able to
Access of Leverage off of all of the insights that exist on the internet
Is it dark outside is it light out dumb side
When is it that I want my lights coming on and off
I don't want to think about it
Can I just
Hook in
To I'm all of that data using if this then that
Now I want to be able to use my voice
Using my Amazon Echo
Our goal
Is 2 a make that a very straightforward and very reliable
Experience for you
There are some folks out there who are packing into WeMo
It's a little
Chopper to make those a really robust
Experience
And I think
Over
Time
You'll see
More and more of us working together in a formal
Authorized way to help
To ensure that your experiences are really I want you can count on
And that you are really good at a lot of benefit joy out of
I'll blame my
The acne
And we're hacking into the
Are hacking into the WeMo cloud
All right
With the idea that
You guys
Launched at CES
A bunch of
Shutters
Which I thought was actually kind of an interesting move because it seems kind of like a step back in the sense that most people right now
I'll seem to be gravitating towards
What off devices
Why did you guys launch all these sensors
When
A lot of people
Seem to be launching
Kenneth Comcast and ATT and all of these could have bigger vendors are coming into the market and they're saying Hey will do all these
Centers and all that for you and then you die
Just bring in your bring your own one-off devices
Which
Height of seems like it might be easy for consumers I don't know
So I'd love to hear your take on kind of where you think the Market's going and
Why you guys are
Betting on the sensors being
A big deal
We think that
The markets in what
Boomers
To Adorn unfolding in a way that we thought they were likely to
First
We thought that it was
A really critical thing for us to do to build out this
Platform
That would
Easily
Port and allow lots of different
Experiences
Do all work as one experience for folk over the coming years
So while you're right there's a lot of
Success
From one brand or another with the singular type
Experience
Overtime
We think that it is inevitable that people will want
Everything in their home to work well with one another we are think that there's
Benefit
I'm not being able just to kind of sense one spot in your home
But rather to a be able to take a look at your whole home
So you will see our thinking around
Sensors and
And switches being
It's easier to add one
And it's easy to on the add more so I can have as little
Of my home or as much
My home
Sort of covered
Censored
Monitored
And then
Managed IT exactly the way that I would want that to Abby
And it's great for Belkin to because I found with my smart home gadgets
No one can buy
Yeah that's a really really big piece
Ivar's thinking to is
Some of those other brands who I'm named
And the way that the mothers are thinking
About this people would have to make a big
Commitment upfront
Said they might have to
Commit to a monthly fee
That's an asking people
For a lot
If what they want
Two-a-day was just one thing or they want to see how that one thing
Works
Prior to adding
A second
So let's
Let's talk about the rest of Belk
Can because you guys also on the Linksys brand of router
And I have always been kind of really interested in
The role that the router can
Play in the smart home because I think like the specialized hubs are
Dirt their tradition kind of
Thing and
All that kind of
Mini radios that live in the router
Any intelligence that you need in the home will probably also live in the router baby lives in a set-top box I don't know
Epicurious like
What your thoughts are there in
How you'll have to work with vendors and what kind of intelligence
Ends up getting
Pushed into the router
Still weren't fortunate space
As a total organization here because
In addition to a WeMo we
I also have Linksys
We've been in this wireless router space for longer
Then that we have been doing WeMo item so
It is always been our thought that Wi-Fi will be a early
Predominant way of us looking things up in our home
The Wi-Fi's got
A couple of limitations also
One of those is the amount of power that it takes
2 I run that Wi-Fi signal
So
You mentioned zigbee zigbee another kind of radio that
People would not be
Nearly as
Comfortable with as Wi-Fi
And we don't want people to I'm even have to think about that
So the way that we approach the non
Wi-Fi way of
Getting
Smart devices hooked up in
My home
Is
Do offer the WeMo link for the WeMo link
Is a Wifi to zigbee bridge but it's a really curated experience
With specific saying
Our first thing is are smart bulbs both ones made by WeMo and
So
Wi-Fi is going to play
Really big role is as it does already as
The big waves
Getting things connected in my home
All of that takes place through
My wireless router
And we've got a lot of great experience with
Linksys
All of this will work
Two I'm gathering
More and more seamless way over time
All right as a consumer I look at a lot of things
This stuff and I'm really excited about it
But I also
And looking at it and thinking
Holly golly gosh
This is very expensive
So
When I look at the
WeMo Outlet
I purchased mine
3 years ago
And it was $50
And it is still $50
Switch
I felt by now that the pricing
Would it come down quite honestly on this
And then I
Also look at things like the connected coffee pot
Is $149
That is a lot to pay for a coffee pot
And I understand that the
Coffee pot is not just like
Hey we put a Wi-Fi radio in
But
When can we kind of expect to see
Prices come down
Really excited to be able to bring these new kinds of
Experiences in
Benefits to a
People's homes into
People's lives
Like I'm you wear I'm highly motivated to be able to find ways to a be able to do that
Static even better cost benefit
Overtime
And a little bit of it depends upon our
Perspectives
For example prior to the WeMo sensor
And switch
The only way that people would be able to benefit
From some of those capabilities
Would have been to get actually
A multi thousand-dollar system
Brought them in
To their home
Maybe with recurring
Charges every every month so
The huge cost
Benefit
That we might brought
On day one
Was a celebrated I think that correctly in that moment
But now
Couple of years has gone by so I think we have a new
Perspective on
What things should have cost
While you I'm haven't
Seeing the price
Of that switch go down
Yats
I think it's something that we will see for sure in the coming years
And I think that on
Did the appliance side with things like coffee pots and heaters and
Other things that
We have in our homes
In most cases it's
The high-end
Of them everything that is first being brought
End of a smart home
And I think that I was at my
Braids down
Into
Lower price
Point items
Will see them cost of connected items come
Down
Well I look forward to that
And then finally
This is a fun one for you
What devices
Do you want to see
For me it's the kinds of experiences that I want to have
At home
I look forward to a system that works well with one another
And what it is that damn I expect out of that system
Gosip
Virtually every single day
So used to drive me nuts
But I couldn't get into my
Garage from outside of my house
Then I was delighted that I could
Could do that off of my WeMo app
Then
I was irritated again that I was driving away from home but I couldn't
Get WeMo to do that for me automatic
So my expectation for what it is
But I wanted my own experiences and my own home
Go up
Every time that I get something done I wanted to
Do more that'll be a both a little bit of a curse
Integrate
Ability for
Future great experiences that WeMo and the mothers can unlock for
As the systems work in a more holistic way
As soon as my smartphone connects
To my
Smart Wifi Linksys router
My system knows that I'm home
Things should be able to
Happened for me automatically
With about me I'm thinking about it
So these holistic experiences
Everything working to gather in a seamless fashion
Is definitely what I'm looking
Forward to
Me too
I'm
Going one harder though I'm looking forward it to it happening
Even though not all of my devices are in the same platform
I think I'm crazy
Let's hope that you're not as crazy as of your thinking
I'm I'm with you I will drink to that only I'm not drink
All right
Thank you so much for coming on the show I really appreciate it
It's really really good to hear thank you for having me and I look forward to seeing you soon
That's all for this week show stay tuned for next week