Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Kevin tofel
And today we have some awesome news
For you
We got
New light switch type things from WinCo
We've got
Sidewalk labs news
Wi-Fi changes and I wrote a thing on doorbell sound
.22 and then finally
We're going to have
The CTO of
Wink
Nathan Smith
Come on the podcast to talk about the new relay switch and everything else
Hookah prices new and we'll talk about that in a few
Let's talk about the news from Amazon with
Well so what happened Amazon is making a big to-do about their skills so what
What did Amazon announce Amazon is
Celebrating birthday
The
I'd say her name but I'm going to do it
The Alexa skills kit has turned
1 and there are now over 1000
400 Alexa skills
Which is pretty quickly I'm not using any sand I want to talk to you a little about if you are using them
But the catalog of skills has grown by over 50% in just one month
And
Yeah you can now also search for skills are you skills by voice which is
New and interesting
And they change their
There's two other things they said that
There
Smart Home
API usage is up by five times
And
That's great
Because I have started out with lights
A couple other things now
To it and the other thing they did was
If you go to the
The library online you can actually organized the skills Library so it's a little bit easier to navigate
Which is important
Because of the 2000 skills that is
Yeah also in one of their stat they say Amazon says customers that made over 3 million request using the
Top 10 most popular Alexa skills
Cuz you're right there are a lot of them in there some of them I would never use some of them seem very useful
Make sure not using any at all
Really
Yeah and I don't know why
I don't know why maybe I just haven't found in one
Looks like I Gotta Have It
I'm going to use it everyday
I got to get this thing on here
So I don't use any everyday
I've enabled quite a few
My biggest challenge is actually been remembering the
Q words like so the semantic keywords that you have to
To use that's why I'm not using them
So I think
Play Jeopardy will will help me out a little
Cuz we use it we use it to play games we I'm trying to think of what other skills I've enabled the 7th
Workout skill although I think I've only used it twice
When she talks
It is
Not very
Inspiring you're not like
Let me jump
Jump give you a bunch of jumping jacks really fast
Oh
Push-ups yeah
I really really need some A to Z Astic coach boys screaming at me
And she's pretty
We also have tried the farting one
I'll be honest lyrics
I could see that I could see that I do like how you can now enable them by voice the thing is unique again you need to know that
That keep it the skill keyword
You could just guess to me
Like you know alarm has a skill alarm.com
Has a scale
And
That is
Enable alarm.com
So
And there yeah okay and there's a there's not going to be hopefully one alarm.com
Skill
Is very specific because it's time to their website
The name but I don't know maybe I need to go back and look
And see what new skills are available it's
It's easier now
It is easier yeah because it's categorized so that helps
I don't know just using a cigarette at an app by voice and having another very specific keyword
Just doesn't seem very natural language to me
It's not
And that's
Best part of Lake
That's a limitation that
Yakko has
I talked to them so I wrote about
The echo being Amazon
App Store
Possibly
The next gen App Store
I asked him if they were going to
Office of Revenue generating opportunities for companies
And
They're like
Baby
So I'm still waiting to see like maybe the next thing we'll see is something about like
Hey
This is how you could pay up cuz there are skills like there's the
The nutritions
The Foot Locker app
Sorry food lockers
I'm not using that now because it doesn't tie and anything that I use bit
Something like that would be amazing
It would it would I'm sure developers would like to see some kind of
Revenue stream here I don't know that Amazon cares
Edward wants to monetize this
I just I think it's more of let's build at this ecosystem then let's sell the hardware and
And gather information you know
That's they're doing a lot of that I'm in for obvious reasons so
Yeah and if that's true so
We shall say Amazon also did
More than 50 new Dash buttons
Yeah nerve Play-Doh
Fiji Water Milano cookies which I like Clif bars I love Clif bars
Who is ordering
I imagine if your kid found it I hit this button Play-Doh comes to my door and I'm sure if I would like
6 years old I be bang bang bang hitting that button every day
Trident gum I mean I'm more interested in getting a dash button you know that the hacker version or getting one of these and
Andre jiggering it to do it
I wanted to do
Yeah yeah
I don't I just haven't been sold on this either I know what Amazon trying to do a trying to
Remove any possible barriers
Between you and the goods you want to shop for that Amazon can send you
But I'd even I've seen a lot of people complain like I don't use it anymore because I don't even get get the guaranteed best price you know the
The price variances I can't tell because I hit the button and just
You know I don't know what the price is
And it does vary so
I don't want to chat
It's kind of a step
Surge pricing
So
Amazon
Amazon is famous for making up stats
That sounds awesome but really tell you very little about their business
Saudi - stat
Kishore is that
Twice every minute
Someone
Order something using a dash button
That sounds kind of cool right
You're like oh that's like
One point
It's a little over a million x 1.05
Takes a year
That's a lot of Play-Doh
What is a lot of Play-Doh but it's not a lot of an Amazon order
There was a story over at Gizmodo in 2013 that said that people in the Amazon warehouse
We're basically trying to process 35 orders
Second
Which
Make that two minutes or two orders per minute
What kind of lame
And I know in the Christmas surge Seasons they get up to 400
In 20 I think was also 2013-2014 they said they were processing like 400
26 orders per second
So it was like it's a lot of orders
It doesn't get
Batman
3 -
And I'm kind of curious how it how it interacts with their subscription business because that's probably what the stakes from
Is my cat
Yeah I mean if you're in on a recurring delivery schedule for something you don't need a dash button I wouldn't think. For that way too many
Maybe this gives you more control
For something fake
Then you can just order it when you need it as opposed to being on the recurring
Down for life
2 weeks and you're not going to use as much
I would be
Curious if any of our listeners are using Dash buttons or have tried them and then no longer use them or still use them
That would be kind of interesting feedback
Tell us about your dash at
Question
At iot podcast. Com
Okay so that's the Amazon news. Exciting we also have weird to talk about this later in the show
But we'll talk about it a little bit now
On Tuesday
Week
Daymaker The Hub basically said that
They had
Dummies Partnerships with Uber if this then that
And
Fitbit
And it also
Talked about something that actually have been going on since June 11th
They've been selling their relaced light switches
You know 149 for 2 or 99 for 1
Which is a big deal
Yeah because I looked at the wink relay way back and for those who are not familiar I think it's the
Been around since 2014
It kind of looks like a little
Almost like a little smart phone a touchscreen smartphone embedded into a switch
And there were two hardware buttons to the side of it
And basically it replaces a light switch and add smarts to whatever is on that circuit for that light switch
Plus it has
Wi-Fi and I think 60 connect connectivity
Okay so it's hardwired to take the place of a
Traditional light switch add smart
I'm the screen against a touch screen
So we can show you almost there I can show you the short cuts like you might have set up for a wink in your wing cap for example
But now with these new Partnerships bring up a Fitbit I can see my Fitbit stats and such on there
And I forget how much it used to cost I want to say was closed at 2
Yeah I was like I've talked to hundreds or 249
It was a non-starter for me because of the price but now
It's 99
And I'm thinking especially cuz I'm moving next week and I'm taking my
Wink Hub with Maci actually only smart home stuff I'm taking with me
I'm thinking about getting maybe two of them
I know you are more because it will broadcast your
But we should say it has a microphone
Present sensor speaker
Temperature yesterday
You getting a bunch of sensors you're getting connectivity
You're getting the ability to access your wig shortcuts
And at smarts to whatever is on that circuit where you put the light switch so yeah I think I'm going to grab
That maybe two of them
No I've I'm actually thinking
Same thing you do have to
Install them you need a neutral wire
Which is
I mean I've never seen a Smart Switch that doesn't require one
Which is unfortunate for people in old houses by
Okay so yes
In
Will wait for Kevin to move and then install them and tell us how many thing
Meantime
I'm actually looking at
Plum which is another wifi-enabled smart switch for a while we didn't have great options in the wifi-enabled smart
Which we have WeMo
So both of these
You can set up dinners for
And Plum is really interesting because this is
This actually
Launched like two years ago was called a booby
Actually like
3 years ago or maybe even in 2012 I cannot remember it's been forever this is a Kickstarter project that what happened was they
Did the kickstarter without even having the product
I don't think the product was Eva
And then they realized
Oh no this is not the way we want this to go
And so they
Basically
Went back to the drawing board
And
Read it the whole thing and so now these are light switches with a touch-sensitive
Panel in the front they look just like a light switch
Looks like a toggle switch almost
Looks like a toggle switch
And
Can you see the pricing on their is it
99 for a single unit a three-pack is 289
And then you can buy 10 packs and 20 packs if you want to go hog-wild it resemble a 20-pack would beat 1807
That's for when you're building your own house
Or someone else's building your house
So
This product is
Cool because what it is is it's got processing power and each light switch
It runs up Applegate runs
Honor language is a programming language used in distributed computing and the idea is that each of these switches is
It's going to be
Part of a distributor cap
Computer network that actually is acting as your Hub in your home
I was just going to say so this is a hubless solution
It's it's a hubless
Solution
Using Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
I don't believe it has the mic and speaker
I do not believe it does
My immediate issue is that it requires an iPhone 4S or higher or iPad
IPod Touch that's right this is iPhone only
It's not actually I think it's just shipping to the kickstarter
People there they're getting ready to do
More stuff
So I'm just saying this is out there
Minkus actually really out
If you want a Wi-Fi switch
Mad at that price
Wink is owned by Flex
So it was on backwards
Bankrupt
Hip flexor
She's not going to do
Definitely not
We'll talk more about that cuz we're talking about design stuff
I think you'll also hear about the sensors again
Yeah go get a drink of water
Okay
So
Other news that was. We've got
Wi-Fi
So the WiFi started
The Wi-Fi Alliance has a new Wi-Fi certified AC
Addition or enhancement
Right in AC is the most
Recent one
Is it Wireless
Version of
Wi-Fi so it's the most recent one for routers and others they also have Wi-Fi Halo
Which is actually the new aspect but it's not actually certified or standardized yet
That's for that
Low power
Hard to get to places
So what's new with the
AC
So they've added multi-user Mimo
Which for all of you for going
Basically means that your Wi-Fi it's a tennis can send the data to more than one device at a time
Which ads
Basically makes
Connection for reliability
Is make it faster Kevin
Can I get faster on certain devices
I'm going to use
An example I think it still applies
And a lot of older networks you could be slowed down if you had one slow device because made
Maybe it was a
How to say nato to 11. B and everything else is a 211. G
You know there was there ways around that to fix that but
You just kind of stuck
With your slowest device slowing down everything but now that should not be an issue
And then they also increase
Grease the channel
Yes maximum Channel bandwidth
It's going from
80 megahertz to 168 Channel switch they say potentially doubles transmission speeds obviously
We can do the math
But that is good at catching I remember we had
20 megahertz channels what is like
Super fast so this is
Fantastic
Yeah
So ye better wi-fi last week we got better Bluetooth
This week better wi-fi in this actually Albion devices in the coming
Weeks
So sad
Wi-Fi lights
I wonder
Yeah I guess this is not just a simple software
Upgrade meeting older 802 11ac devices will see this I think this is hard because
They're actually break me up 5
Of the first sip Wi-Fi certified AC price to support the new features
And comprise a test bed for interoperability so
I think this means new hardware
I'm not seeing everything about older devices
If I make sense cuz implementing multi-user
I believe
Yeah
From an antenna perspective as well as others yeah
Radio
Yep
So free wifi
Little bits of news Columbus Ohio
Was the name to be
Winner of a grant from the Department of Transportation
Say
40 million-dollar grant for the.
10 million from Vulcan
Capital Paul Allen's company
Basically this is a
To build a smart City
And
I'm a little sad because Austin was also in the running for this 11
Casey and some other cities
Columbus apparently had the best plan and they also brought in another
140 million + local
Crimson
Can I help
So
It's a lot of money going to improve
Transportation with bike smart cities
Smart passes for traffic Lanes I think it's that got autonomous buses is something they're looking at 2
What interesting stuff
Coming out of Columbus
Yeah but they have
That's part of the project they have
Cars that are kind of have that lidar and radar sensors like a
OK Google Maps car and they actually go around all the time in theory
And see where
There is open parking
NFL communicated to the people live there that way they can get to the
The closest
Open parking spots that are driving around in circles for 10 minutes and so on so
Kind of dressing
I would totally
Play I wonder how much extra traffic that adds I putting those
Cars out there to actually check the parking spot so I wish there were sensors in the parking spots where you can say it
I don't have three times on on top of me so it
Yeah I would think you'd want to do it cameras just because he wouldn't have to change the batteries in Those sensors and
That's
More bang for your buck
Anyway
The reason why we bring this up is because ye Columbus but also
Because we heard from sidewalk Labs which is Google's
Well
Which alphabets alphabets
What are the alphabet
We should also say right now right here
Kevin
What's for now that company called Google
There you go
But he has nothing to do with
Unfortunately
Kevin you can't do everything
Santa Claus is
Google Smart City
Santa Claus is alphabet Smart City ever
And
What it's apparently do and nobody really knows a lot about what it
It's doing
So
We
The guardian got papers saying that it is going to run Public Safety or public transportation Networks
In Columbus
So, this is part of its effort
To implement all of this kind of traffic
Stuff
It's using sidewalk labs
Software called
Flow
To help manage its transportation
So
I'm not sure exactly what that mean
But that could be part of the public
I've been pretty sure that it is Court will that's according to the guardian
Which found this information
I thought that was interesting
I'm very curious I'm hoping to get someone
Sidewalk Labs podcast
Because I Got High
I want to know more
Alright other news of the week
Let's see
I will let you guys know that I did a review for The Wirecutter on
Connected doorbells
It came out very nice
It did it
Took forever
So I have had
The skybell
HD
The August
And the
Ring
Not the pro cuz that wasn't available for reviewers yet
On my door for like
Months
And
They live through
Torrential rain they look through all kinds of stuff
And
The review turned out to
I said the skybell HD was my favor
Actually change cuz beforehand I thought the August was my favorite in fact I
I now own two August doorbells
And finally we have some news from CD insights who actually this week put out a report saying that smart home
Funding
Is up for the first time since the last quarter of 2014
And
I thought that was kind of
Worth noting although the biggest eel
It seems like
A lot of that was
Was due to
Ring racing
61 million
That was a good chunk of the of the quarter here
So
In the first quarter of 2016
24 companies raised 114
Million dollars
The peak was in
The fourth quarter of 2014 when 36 companies raised
251 million
$10
Is that a drop precipitously as often as the case inventor world end
It'll probably come back up again
Yeah
In part of that funny
Is it less smart home but it is iot
Ala raised 39 million dollars
Which was a
Endura
Which is a company that's actually providing
Back in kind of machine learning and intelligence for smart home devices raised 11 million
There is a really interesting company it's kind of seeking
Three you know houndify
The company that provides
A easy way for developers to add voice
To there
Products
You're a kind of wants to make it easy to add machine learning and
Context-based intelligence 2
Products
Any product
Yeah it is all right so
That's kind of
All the News That's fit to talk about this week
I think
Anything else I know I'm done just debating on how many winks
To buy right now wink relay
Sanam very curious to hear what our guest has to say about that.
Indeed so stay tuned for Nathan Smith the CTO of Link
Who will tell us a lot more about
Why I chose the radios and sensors he chose and all about the kind of design efforts that they're making their
Hey this is Stacy breaking into the podcast with a message from our sponsor today sponsors
Is Ayla networks and Enterprise platform-as-a-service for The Internet of Things
We have a list CEO Dave Friedman latest news which is
39 million dollars in funding
What are you going to do with that
Is 39 million is about 60 million total for the company and
What site to use it really to continue
Building out our Traction in the market where
Nearly a hundred customers right now of
Companies building things are going to go in homes and buildings
Providing this service is a really
How do you see the market
Hit the market
How to evolve as an ecosystem I think the Internet of Things is an incredibly complex
Challenge
Different things work things is important here
They want to come together from
The fight side to networking to Cloud application
On our side we partnered very closely with chip vendors these include Tommy's like Renaissance
Broadcom Qualcomm Marvell mediatek
And also work with companies like apple and WeChat in China to make sure that these
B2c applications
Seamlessly work
With the devices in the cloud together
So who are you guys working
Our customers are typically leading manufacturers
And you're some of the public ones are
Companies like Hunter Fan
They're launching a homekit enabled fan on or service later this year
Air conditioning companies like Fujitsu I sent TCL bunch of Chinese companies door lock
Pretty much if you see something in your home today and it's starting to get connected somewhere
We have a custom on our platform that's doing the same thing
All right and if I want to build
Some sort of seamless software experience in the cloud how can I find you
Www.netflix.com and that's a y l a
Network s.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
I'm your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Nathan Smith the founder and CTO of wings
I'm doing really well thanks for having me on
I am super excited to have
Because I have almost completely gone
What what do I do with my week
But so far it's been work
Awesome
And it sounds like you guys are getting
To make it even better
Yeah absolutely Flex been in
Incredibles parent company in such a cool company and and
We've really been able to focus on on the product and and
Making things even better than they were before
You guys are here
Because
You announce
Partners for the relay switch which I didn't even realize was actually back on the market
Your new partners why don't we quickly run to the news so who are your new partners
So we made Partnerships with
Marquee brands does Brands art
Uber
Fitbit
I love if
You don't control things from
My wink
Ecosystem is
Is NASA
That's so much cool stuff you can do and we really see this is the first step of
You know I'm starting to integrate them with them a little more deeply
And so you know right now you'll be able to use
Is the relay button says that if
Component of the
The knot recipe
And so you can say you know
If this button
Express Tax
He said maybe you can
Can use that as an alert to text you if you when your kid comes home
School
Another thing you can do it on this way sign in
Is that you can use
Using with the Logitech Harmony
You don't have a physical button that turns on your entire a view system in the
Transit off at night
When you go to bed
You need at the real and I think it's more convenient than trying to like menu dive to your remote
That's true although I can actually control my Logitech Harmony through the echo
Which crazy
Superfund
Let's go because when you guys at
Gosh like a year-and-a-half ago was it
Yeah so bad thing was $250 you had to
Install it in your wall the relay guys is a
Your light switch goes
And it also has an income
Chanel
What looks like the wink interface on a touchscreen on that switch
Came on the market
In my humble opinion
But now it's only $149
For what we are really committed to
Continuing to update this product so you know
Without having
To buy new hardware or anything like that
With the intercom with these new service
Substantially upgrading what the weather be like
And you've mentioned that like
It's sort of like an interpretation of of
Wink you know
On your wall
What we really wanted to do it this was
Not so much even about
The wink out itself
It was more about
Like what how would we reinterpret the light switch for the dish
Like what makes sense
What's more
When we're Gods with it is that we think that it's B
Becomes really nice coffee
Fermented things
Like Amazon Alexa
Internet
It's a sleek and
Unobtrusive
Implants
Simple interface and that makes sense for certain use cases
You might order an Uber through
Your Amazon Alexa
You know voice control device I cannot go or something
You like that where you might order it through your cell phone
But you know you can see
See how long how far away the car is
Anyang
Relay and I think that that makes a lot of sense and that interaction between like the active
Blake The Voice
And the passive like the relay
When am I actually on my
Original ecobee was that I could literally just walk by and see the weather
It's not like the stupidest thing but it was awesome
Yeah we have weather on relay as well and not yeah I use it every single day I rarely ever open up the weather app anymore
So that makes a lot of sense
And you guys have actually been working hard at Integrations why are you doing this focus on
All of these other services and what do you think the wink platform provides
Wink is all about connecting things
I sometimes think about it as
Like an operating
For the home
We have this Mantra internally a twink that is use wink more but use the app less
And what we mean by that is that like
Like we love connect
Together two
Create the sort of futuristic experiences that I think that we
We all want from
He's connected products and
You know
It takes a long time to for everything
Immature and
For everything to
You know
Potential but we feel like rely just on the precipice.
And so
We think about
The smart home is something that
It's it's more than just like physical Hardware
It is also be services
Earlier today you told me that you guys kind of don't believe there's going to be a central Hub in the home and that's kind of
Fyu designs
The relay
You designed the relay to act is that hub
What should we take from this given that he don't double A has fewer radios
Better than the walls design in it
Thinking about
Biscuit future
Hub replacement
We think that there's going to be a house in the future but we think they're going to
Piggyback on other devices
Especially as
Low energy
The chair is National
We thank God
It makes a lot of sense
Combined
Browder's a game consoles and like white switches with hub
Yunnan places where you have power you have
Wi-Fi already
And so
The reason that we put we take zigbee for the
The relay Hub is that
We feel
That's the real Isaac
Decor a product it's about controlling
Smart light bulbs
And because we are focusing on that Whiting use case
And the bad
Adoption of
Light switch to the 20
Centuries
We felt that Digby was the right protocol because
Of the choice and availability of
Zigbee bulbs
We don't particularly endorse one protocol
Over another
You have a microphone in there and you have a speaker because it's now an intercom
Are there any other kind of sensors
Temperature might be an interesting thing
We have temp
And you can also there also is a proximity sensor
So you know we can see if there's activity in the house
We have some pretty Advanced machine learning
Programs going on right now and they will make use of that data
Outfitting my house
4 and trying to make it a smart home
I felt like for advanced users wink was a great place to start cuz it work
A lot of things
So
How many of these would I want in my house how should I be thinking about designing my house or is it still too early
Well it really depends on the houses
SKS I need
I live in New York so
I can only
Really have one
But
You know if you got a larger house and
Intercom
Use kiss makes a lot of sense for you
Then you know we've had people that have ordered five
Before
Because I want one in every room
You know what you can have a button on one of your relays
That causes down the in
Entire house
For the night right
So that might not make sense on a relay in the living room
But you know my name a lot of sense
Relay like by the garage door
Something was it difficult to figure out a user interface Works in such a small space
Potentially do so much how do you kind of think about menus and accessing that
Something about designing for Relay is that we actually have some really interest
Constraints design around
And what really does best
And what it does better than
Mobile phone
It can convey information without being a
Answer. So we really try to focus on is
Designing widgets in a way where you can look at it for
2 seconds as you're passing it
And you know get useful information
Information about things
I'd like the weather or you stopped
Like that
And it doesn't work like that with the phone the phone is a device that
You don't always want to have tethered
Why you don't want to carry around
Your phone in the house
24/7
And so the relay is sort of that
A match between
The services and
Information
Do you care about
Youth at Toronto Raptors
That's why we try to design for it
We don't spend a lot of
Time
You know imagining
Use case
You
China autumn
Relay For example like if you're setting up
You familiar with iRobot system
Automation
You wouldn't
Want to set up a robot
The relay
But
When it comes to looking at information passes lie the relay
Excel
And sales.
That doesn't use gas
Should we try to spend
The majority of our
Design timeline
Okay
And speaking of your robots because this is something that
When Apple just introduced the home
App for iOS 10 I saw this and I was
I was frankly a little bit disappointed cuz I was hoping they would push
Kind of the men Ewing and Concepts forward
In
Kind of the way we've been managing
Multiple devices in our house
And I don't feel like they really did
So I'm curious like
Do you see us
Programming are smart homes in the not-too-distant future
Or could it be something like as simple is
Telling something what to do so maybe doing it verbally or maybe it's
You know generated by Machine learning and you can say
You can offer me like an option
And the app like Stacy I see that
You tend to do this at this time or whatever this happens you also do this would you like me to set up a robot
Yeah you are alluding to some subjects that are
You know very near
Jerry West
We love
Robots
The ability to set up complex automation
And we think it's really powerful
For a certain type
And that type of user is
Savvy and husband you know
Selling these devices
Destroy a long time
It's really familiar with what they
They can do it makes a lot of sense for that
The dryer user that is maybe just getting their first couple smart bulbs
You know what they're trying to accomplish
Specific use case
Navy
To determine
Burglars with having lights come on at various times
Things like that
That's her to set up
You know
The things that maybe we Azhar
Like enjoy doing
Give me some kind of TV
Incel
You know we are we are looking at ways that we can make that easier through machine learning and
We
Are going to have a string of I think
Really interesting product news throughout the year this year and
And savenia stay tuned for announcements
Anada in that area
Okay and
What will be talked after kind of after the bankruptcy of Corky
You had said that the smart home was taking
How to buy Life twists and turns the gist of it was that
The pause between some of the products that you guys have planned when you were part of quirky
End
Ability to take that time
After the bankruptcy
To kind of get things right was really welcome
Because the industry was changing so much
Can you talk to me a little bit about
What you've seen change and maybe would surprise you
Sure I mean I think that your article in your newsletter touchdown this little bit night
I really
Agree with the fact I think that this year is going to be
A year of calling to ascertain
Next time
I think that
The changes that are going to happen or that
People are
Going to be the last
Interested
Enteritis
Start new
Forms and ecosystems
And more interested in
And taking advantage of the good mature platforms and ecosystems
Is that are out there right now
So I think that this will be the year when
When people start concentrating more on those and devices that work with with the sir great platforms
Better out there
And I think that's a good thing for us and I think I work
Racine that reflect in the in the
Popularity the platform
Okay
Let's think about your platform because in talking to
Some other people they look at the platform is having control of the operating system
Apple with homekit
Whatever they do
Google home
And then the other platform people seem to be keen on Earth
It's jumping out of them it is
The Amazon Echo
You work with some of these things right
But you're also trying to be an OS for the home
Which Maybe
And I kind of tend to think the smartphone
Is a great sensor but I don't know if I want
My Holmes OS to live there
So I'm curious
Where do you place yourself when you're thinking about competitors
Sure
I mean
I try to not think of
Like anyone
Editor like
I try to think
Is that you know
About how we can work together first
Because
At the end of the day
It's like
Consumers expect and what
The best experiences is
If
Thing if you can have choice
In what year
You know and so
If there is a way to work together with someone else
You don't we will
We are a neutral party
Next time we're not trying to
To compete with our
Core Partners Julianna Grace you know
I feel like you mentioned
Google like we're not trying to
We are just trying to add a layer of functionality
That you know
Consumers
Fun really engaging get a lot of use out of
Whereas
I think
A lot of other companies that are are
To make platform
How many block forms
Du Hast
Teacher conflicts that that limit them from offering the same choices
That's where we think we have a big advantage
And what about the business model
Is your business model going to stay with
Selling like
The relay in the
The hug
Or do you see
Something else evolving
Siri actually is quite a bit of evolution going on right now
Certainly selling Hardware is
Straightforward business
Something will continue to do
But
We also work with companies to help them bring connected products to Market
You know a lot of companies are entering this is the first time we've got a lot of experience and
You know that's where our boner Flex
Is a really really great
Parent company
Because
They are
One of the best if not the best company in the world that manufacturing connected products
And so
You know we're trying
Leverage. To offer companies
Is that are in the space s you know
Solutions to
Getting products to the market
Quickly
And getting products to the market with a built-in ecosystem that already has a big footprint and a lot of support for
Connect another device
But beyond that you know we do have other
Other ideas as far as business modeling and
Treatise dialysis
What we we spent a lot of hard work
End time
Making is hard as a platform ghost
And you know that will be something that will probably touch on in our our product updates lettering
Linear
And for the people
The people at home who have awake system
Can you share just a couple of your favorite robots or
Anna favorite things
Do you like yes
Yes let me tell you
Yeah so what am I adding my favorite
Is
If the smoke detector goes off turn on all the lights
Unintuitive things not like what you
Really think of when you start
Connecting something makes so much sense I really love that one
Can help people
Safer in it
It's not a straightforward
Another one that I really like is
Is the ability to
Shoe
Enable or disable sensors
With the
Canary
We can actually trigger
With dictionary mode changes
We can turn on and off robots right so
The way that I have mine set up at home
Is that a sensor
My doors
When I leave the house
Canary goes
You know cuz armed
It's basically enables the robot that turns on notifications for this sense
So then get the door open
You know well
I'm not home
Then I'll get a notification
But then when I come home then you can I get back
Privacy mode it turns off that robot
And so that you know if I walk out on my patio on Holland
Annoyed
Vacations coming
Jenna from the sensors
Got it in the canary also send you a notification if that door open
Well the canary
It doesn't phase
My front door actually face
Okay
I seasoned it settings on the backyard but you know
I don't really like having
I am so with you
That's a good one for people who don't like hammers in the all right
I like these ideas
And I think I'll have to go pick up some relays
Could you do the intercom
Like install a relay in someone else's house or do they have to be on the same network
You absolutely can
If you wanted to have a little like tin can with the string you know between
Two houses you could absolutely install a relay NH
I am taking it might be fine for like
A grandparent or something
Be like Bob
Mom
Yeah I'm sure she loves that
Yes yes
Totally would not
Why did you bring this to my house
But it'll kind of a fun
Alright thanks so much for coming this week
Thank you for having me well that's it for this week's show please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
And thanks for listening