Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I have your host Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And this week's podcast
Is brought to you by security we have
A quick word about Kevo we're going to be talking about Google
And we got
A new chip from arm we got some autonomous car laws
And a new security framework for the industrial internet-of-things plus an assortment of bits and bobs
If we get today
And this week's guest is John Troutman of canary the All In One Security System talking about
How to build services for The Internet of Things
But before we get anywhere
Let's have a quick word
From one of our sponsors
Are you interested in how the internet of things will change the way we discover Shop store and cook our food
Did you will not want to miss the smart Kitchen Summit an event that's happening October 5th and 6th
It explores the technology and design convergence that's changing how we eat buy and store it in Iraq
With our food the smart Kitchen Summit is brought to you by my friend Michael Wolff show and he's created
Discount especially for listeners of our podcast so just go to smart Kitchen Summit. Calm and use the code
Iot podcast all one word to get 10% off tickets I'll be there and I hope you will join
Alright let's start this week show
So
Last week
We talked about the
Kevo Smart Lock
Which
2nd generation Kevo and I said that I was not enjoying it so much because it was
Is a bit iffy the touch-to-open feature didn't always work
You're not the only one that actually had some issues too from reviews that I read
True
But you know I'm still playing with it maybe it'll get better over time but I did
Actually make a mistake
Winnipesaukee
This is terrible
It happens it does
But we hate when it
Happened so let me let me correct this
I told you guys that the smart key rekeying feature
Was a new feature in the Kevo 2nd gen
But it's not
It's actually what they've done is maven
Improved it
Moore security
So
Do so people know in case they missed it or don't know what
Smart key is that's where you can actually bring your own key to the lock
And have the lock
Intelligently rekey itself to the key correct
Yes
Is it only for
I think it's only fair
That's a good question I know the Kwikset
Lock that I have
Does it so yeah I guess maybe it is that's a good question I had to get something else around here and by saying yes when I don't know
I haven't seen it yeah I haven't seen on other brands
But
Searching
Yeah I don't I don't recall seeing that on other another devices and
It was actually kind of interesting
New technology that's only offered in select
Kwikset keyed entry
There you go
So we got it we got it right that time
We did we got it right
And I should also say
I don't
If in the excitement over this
I mentioned that
The Kevo Kwikset
Bob's
So the little fobs you can carry
They actually just
Actors
A replacement for your phone so you might give that to your kid if they don't have a smartphone
And then they too
Can touch soap
Yeah so it's like a Bluetooth presence sensor probably
Yes
There's the Kevo stuff
The bottom line still is that this lock is
A still a bit temper
It works it's really cool
You Really Want Your Love
100%
Moving along
Let's talk about
I don't know Kevin
Which of our things should we talk about you talk about the new autonomous car laws
We can do that cuz it's going to turn into something else on the chips either we're going to talk about later so the Federal
Government has decided before the states get all crazy with car laws for autonomous cars
We're going to put out a list of guidelines and
I don't the regulations yet
But
It's a framework
So framework that's what we call things and in-flight yes it's a Frameworks
It's just a framework
. so not only
Framework that is
A public framework
Yeah so so this is going to
Address
Some of the potential rules of the road for autonomous cars again before the states decide to all do different things
Really be crazy for car manufacturers in such as to deal with so we didn't look at it I think it's like a
300 Pages this thing is
15 rules okay
We can't call the rules
Suggestions
It's a 15-point safety assessment that's
That's my bad CI
Yeah what they're talking about
Is some of the things
Include
Ethics so
What
So having the same set of ethical decisions around a self-driving car so
Do you run over the small child
I'm going to suggest no and I really don't need the government to tell me that but anyway
You know you're not enough
And I imagine there's going to be safety standards
Like I said
Like we have ISO
We have nist standards for the
Elements of physical safety
Echeckup
Don't make sense that makes sense and also in here I see some information about
The manufacturers of these cars providing actual data
And I guess that's going to help
Home some of the potential rules of the road later on
I wonder how these sad that you know how the Tesla's and all these other car companies are going to feel about sharing such data because
I just think back to the unfortunate incidents with Tesla of of late
You know I'm sure they they want to do their own investigations keep all the information kind of close to the to the best
But I don't know they're all going to be able to do that and are they going to push back on that
I think it's important
To have
There may be rules about like how the data shared
Like make it doesn't become
Completely public
But it's important for every autumn
Reddit self driving
And it shouldn't should actually starting
2B standard
And in some cases it may be
How kind of a black box so
When something happens we can determine exactly what happen
Is it a software failure is it
Driver error
Somehow
Just like we have with planes
Just because
We're going to have to be able to interview these cars basic
If some
Nothing goes wrong
Safety purposes but also like lawsuit
So
Right
Thanks Obama
Temperature
Also on the safety front
So if your autonomous car
It's got to be super safe
Because there's
The risk of a huge loss of
What should be in that car I wanted to be there new cortex r52 design
That they put out this week
And this is a chip
Actually it's not a chip
Sorry
Arm is a company that licenses its architecture to other ship make
A design
The first licensee is St micro
And this is for it's for autonomous cars robotics it's for what did you say Kevin something about loss of life and limb
Will it it adheres to certain standards in industrial circles
Set that have to do with safety and
There's a whole level of criticality on potential accidents that this would
Theoretically avoid and yes so they categorize them by you know but just a minor injury maybe loss of it.
Whenever I live to massive loss of life
So it kind of fits with the car which a moving vehicle could
You know take out 50 people so
They're playing industry level standards to the Safety and Security of the cortex r52
In my Safety and Security they're talking about
Prevention from hackers root access to the chip itself but they're also talking about
How the chip is built
So it's built to be really fast
In understanding what's going on
To be incredibly redundant
So there are two processors working in parallel to do each job so if One processor overheat
I can lose one engine you still got one left
So these are the types of thing
Talking about this is a new design
And it shows how the
Somebody is trying to
The push into
Obviously outside of just
Apple phones fit into all of these
Robotics and Industrial
Kind of manufacturing jobs that are
Happy just Automation in general
They're showing all kinds of potential applications are saying farming Healthcare Industrial
Obviously Transportation building automation
Aviation
So they won't expand obviously beyond the handheld devices and such that they're pretty much known for right right now
And this is an area that's really up in the air because Nvidia has been doing
Great work
Self-driving car side
With the processing of like lidar and radar and all of this information
And
This doesn't
Do the cortex r52 isn't going to be
Investigating your lighter this is the stuff that's going to be
Running your engine and making sure that all the information
It's coming into it
Actually
Is acted upon accordingly
Yeah
It'll be it'll be interesting cuz you're right in video
The last couple CES show is NVIDIA time how you think that four years ago and
Their partner speaker would be like
Audi and they were talking about it look at our trip runs their dashboard
Dismiss missing their car I wonder if Nvidia
Which is an RN license ewill
Implement the core r52 security features in some of their upcoming ship designs for the cars
Hello we shall see
Another security story for you
Industrial internet Consortium
Which is
It's just a bunch of companies I'm not even to go through all of them tons of companies EMC now Dell
All these guys doing
Industrial internet stuff
Have released on Monday
An industrial Internet Security framework
There's that word again Kevin
So this is the iic
Doing the ISS
Independent set of best practices to help people
Assess risk
And defend against
So
This is
The big threat
For the industrial internet-of-things
What is nobody knows how to
There's no standard everybody's doing different things at everyone's pointing fingers when things go wrong
In
It's terrible
This group says it wants to identify requirements to
Create stand
Syncope
Practices
It's a good idea it is
They haven't gotten into big specifics they're basically like
Hear the big things we need to focus on safety reliability
Resilience
Security and privacy
Electoral Givens obviously but I do like that they are outlining the areas that they're focusing on an accent
Communications monitoring and configuration
So at least
Because I said something physical to think about here and see where they're going with us
And they did something that's really smart and this is something that I
I think we take for granted a lot they're pointing out that everybody
In the chain
Kaiser roll
Also in a chip makers to
Systems integrators to the actual end-users
I think that's really important and we don't kind of harp on this enough insecurity
But it matters in this way
So it's not enough to be like oh I just bought a new secure smartphone
And actually
This is a wonderful example actually this week
Where someone posted on Reddit that
Their neighbor was able to unlock their front door using their
Siri
Telling Siri to unlock the front door
In August lock that was attached to Siri
Is part of the homekit thing
And I read this and I was like
Okay no
That is not how that could ever happen
What actually did happen
Bend is
When you use homekit to unlock a door
It makes you
Put in your path
Even if your phone's like
Hanging out there
Or the iPad
And
This particular user apparently didn't have a
Password on there
Hello major major faux pas
So
This is a wonderful example of hay user
You are also responsible for your own security
Be in the situation
Yes
And
I also bring this up in case anybody is running homekit and doesn't have a password on their iPad or
Because Hey look
I'm a little skeptical about the story itself but
You know I'm a maybe I can I don't have a
I'm Catholic I mean
The thermostat hear it which I can control my voice in a security issue there
I would love to get to really see if that
An accurate story because if it is
Well yes I agree with you 100% from a user standpoint
That iPad a homekit Hub whatever she is should have a password
I think there's a little bit of
An opportunity for improvement on Apple spark there
To say if you're going to
Control these things by voice
Require password on the device
That's a fair
Amiibo spoofing should happen I'm not I'm not blaming Apple here I'm just saying nothing area for opportunity
The user should absolutely have the password there
Yes and
This is why
Like the August integration
The echo the Amazon Echo doesn't actually allow you to unlock the
She calmly lock your door
Exactly
Yes so anyway
Safety Frameworks
Tell me about recognizing the entire chain of value
One more security type thing
I was at fig monk last week
London witch
Amy's really super hot
My God it was like almost 90° there
And there's no air conditioning Inlet
There was three presentations about the Smart Home
Antenna consumer iot that
Really bums me out
Basically there is a lovely fellow
Whose house
Sounds like my house basically
Play he's implemented all of these things
And
He was miserable
On the smart home because it's it's
Which is
But he also pointed out that most IP security cameras can be
Gordon Court hacked by just sticking a
Paperclip in them to reset them which I haven't thought about
But
No I mean that that okay so that resets it and then I guess you could set up yourself as a user and didn't gainax
Access to it
And probably the individual owns the camera wouldn't really know other than the fact that they can no longer see their camera
Right so if you
You came in and ride
They did not in every case so especially cameras that set up their own wife
Wifi hotspot so if you brought your own way
MiFi hotspot
Eventually
Wifi hotspot
This isn't something I've
But even just hit a reset just
Turns off at
It reset
So right
You're no longer
Yeah
So I thought about that
All right I'm going to have to Outlaw the paperclip
Dang it
It's so useful for resetting
So there's there's one thing that I learned it
And then basically
We got a long way to go and smart
Yeah
But we're getting there
This is a fun
Kind of concept as we're
Coming up to October 4th which is the
David Google is presumably launching Google home
Here we should
Take a moment for
Kevin's disclosure
Yep I consult for Google and I do not work on any other Smart Home Products
I told any views are my own
And store
I was speaking Google
When you talk to Google
You don't say that
Like when you talk to Amazon you say hey she who shall not be named
Hey Siri
Sorry if not you're okay cuz
Press the buttons on the phone song
For much longer
All right
So you have
These women
Google
Have a name
Google home have a name
OSHA 12 students assistant have
Assisting is what Google calls its AI ever
Hertz in
Write the powers
When you say
Should I say it ok Google
Brexit who doesn't have a
A name it's a mean other than the company name
Right it's a branding thing to me so I don't really have a problem I think
I'm very used to eat saying OK Google to my devices
I have four I don't know
3ish Warriors how long
It's been out
But how if you've got like
My phone is almost always around if I say that am I going to set off my phone
Pain in my home
That was a question that
Many people had a Google IO in Google home was actually showing off we don't
No because
They're not going into details about that so
Her people don't know you on an Android device
You can have
Your phone always listening as well as an Android Wear watch if you raise it
You can say OK Google and
Korean sauce
So how will all this work
But the same keyword is the question
And I don't think that
Question has been answered yet so
My suspicions
Is yes it will cause conflict
Commence just a guess on my part
That's because there's no mechanism in place today to prevent it from multiple
Android Wear Android devices
Right so unless there's eight some new secret sauce
Hearing Google home
It will be an issue
What about the
I always mess up
What is a
VSP
That Amazon introduced for the
Multiple echos
The latest I
With room level
Right
So yeah so that was announced last week with a. Where if you have multiple Echo devices which she would
And I both do
When you speak
Out loud to them
Only one should
Listen to take action words today
Got me I have two or three of them go at the same time because they can all hear me so my guess is they are then
Owning the software to say which is the highest level
Up from the microphone and I'm going to presume that
The one the person speaking together closest to it
So they could do something like that here with Google home
Possible
Or if knowing a phone is in the house today
Are nearby maybe they route everything to the
Well I don't know I don't know
It gets complex when you start doing things like that because you're relying on so many different potential data points that you may or may not have
Agreed but it will actually that goes to what I was going to say
Google
Probably does know
If your phone has the always listening function on
Because all this is tied your Google account and there's Telemetry information that can read
So my guess is
I'm getting more people than not actually don't have the always listening function on
Japanese
It's not on by default
So typically you have to like
To use the function you have to actually go into the
Google app
Pour into a Google search screen
And from there once it's enabled you can say OK Google it will do
Whatever
I think very few people have that always listening
Picture on always on their phone
No this was just cuz like
And then there's also the personality
I mean I would not
She who shall not
She's getting there
To get their High great as
I've never actually
Yeah but I like Cortana Lotta Love what Microsoft is down there
NF personality are for sure it's
I think she's a really good example of a blend between Siri and Google Now to be quite honest and
Play well done
I don't know even even on the new today Google released the allo messaging app and that has assistant built in
And as well
So that way if you're in a chat
You can even make me make a group chat you can do a nap Google
In the chat and say show up show me great taco places right and everybody will see the results and we can all decide oh yeah let's go
So but there's no name it's just
Google it's at Google right
Teuta consistent thing
Do we like it or not I don't know I'm guessing you don't you
Just like I just
As you move it
A as it becomes more aware of
It feels weird
To have it be
And then also
As it's in your house and more people are interacting with it like
Yes my daughter will be fine
I'm saying
Alexa in some ways and I'm sorry
Guys
Has become like our arbitrator at the dinner table for exam
Pause for a moment
Oh wait no
We're like boom
And she's almost got like a seat at the
Inside
I totally get that because and doesn't sound stupid when we stayed anyway there many many times just buy
Conditioning in
And politeness when I'm done speaking to my echo I'll say thank you
I wouldn't do that with
Google home I don't
Cuz it's a
Company it's a brand it's not a personality or a
In a person in a in a box
So to speak
Flip a person out of the box
Orsillo
Kushner and air freshener
Alright so
That is our
Our question
It's not a food never done but now we have one
So it's not bad
All right I think that's
Cats
Great for this week show please stay tuned for john-troutman a co-founder of
Canary which just launched a brand new outdoor camera
And a new service that
Is really
Interesting
First a message from our sponsor
This week's monster is macadamia and we are talking about the role of prototypes I have time in the day in for Macadamia
And Kevin Bailey the CEO of design first anyone can make a prototype
What should I be eating
To do when I stop
This process
With the maker movement
Anyone can build something and deliver a proof-of-concept
But detected make a prototype that actually looks and feels like the actual product should can get it
User passed a Chasm of disbelief
Actually touch it and feel it and start thinking about the services that that product can deliver for them
Questions
Should my prototype
Seek to answer
It's helping you answer
Whether you can make this product desirable
And will you be able to make 500 of these and at what cost
And can you
Kayla can you deliver it to thousands of users ethical is viral
A lot of people think that building a prototype is more just
Putting their ideas in physical Hardware
And bring that into show
Without thinking about the
Future manufacturing viability
Is that really the right way to design something like this
The concern there is it if you start moving from makerbase
Piece of hardware and try to commercialize it you're going to miss some key elements around security around have you been asked
Scale with a platform is with the cloud infrastructure is
And by building a prototype on top of the scalable platform from the get-go which the cloud enables
You can actually save a number of iteration
And get there
For a cheaper and faster
Physical
And software
Virtual based
How do we think about bringing those two experiences together
The challenge with the hardware
Inside wall is
To understand limitations
Communications
Coin collection of us playthrough
Proof of concept where you have a very rich
Play
Only to find out on the product you going to have to come up with something much
Experiential and turn the colors and then size of this playing
Concepts
Cos2x
That way when people experience about accusing optimize around
Something still enjoyable within the context of what product
Become
The whole proof-of-concept is looking at Opportunity risk
It's an opportunity with balance the designers are looking at opportunity and then the engineer
Earring team is looking at with
And their jobs
Change nothing
Together any prototyping
You really doing
Creation building test
Sing learning
And that posters get you towards a viable
So if you can balance the risk and Designs constraints earlier on in the Prototype phase you'll be able to ski
Scale that prototype as it involves and take many of the ideas and Concepts from that prototype into production
Commercial
Where can we find more
Jumpstart your IT solutions go to Macadamia.com JumpStart
Hey everybody this is Stacey Higginbotham and you are listening to the internet
We are back with this week
Guessed it is John Troutman who is a co-founder at
Neri
Hi John how are you doing today
Hi Stacy I'm great thanks for having me on the show
Thanks for coming I have like the canary forever
And by forever I mean like for the last year to have to
Sears Helena
And that's basically forever yeah yeah
Okay so for those of you guys who don't know the canary is an all-in-one security system at this little Lake
Black or white cylinder that you stick in your house
All these sensors in it
And a camera and now Canary you guys are
Introducing a whole bunch of new stuff so
Starting with everybody's favorite device and outdoor camera
Yay
That's right yeah we just announced this week the launch of canary Flex
Which is a companion products
To Canary and it's an indoor outdoor camera
It works plugged in or wire for Isa has built-in rechargeable batteries and it's totally weatherproof so you can use it
Spider house you can mount it up on a tree in your front yard you can put in the garage
Or you can use it inside in the baby's room or just like
The same way you would use Canary indoors
Okay so
There is like an outdoor camera zeitgeist
Right now
So you got to talk to me about why you guys decided on this particular
Product because
S&S has one
Netatmo is launching a new one
We just got the ring stick up cams out there
I'm trying out these are Lowe's I mean there's
There's a lot of outdoor cameras
Yeah when we launched
Canary a couple years ago
We're really interesting this idea of being
What's be connected on the inside of your home in and even if you're on the other side of the world feel like you're inside your home you know what's happening
And you have that
Immediate connection was happening there
I think as soon as people have gotten a taste of that either through Canary or through other Wi-Fi cameras
It just makes sense that they wanted to expand that into
Even more areas of places they care about
So it's an outdoor
Security camera but it's also
Just a very versatile camera that can go anywhere
It's our goal was really to
Take what people are already interested in which is
Can I give me places they care about
And allow that coverage
Ensure that connection to go wherever people really wanted to go
One of our core tenants has always been to really listen to our community when we launched a crowdfunding product
Community became really important to
Canary as a company we had about 10,000 people that were immediately kind of bought in and giving us feedback
And so as soon as we launched keryflex
Got a lot of feedback as far as what what it was doing for people and then what people wanted it to do for them that it wasn't doing yet
And one of those things that we heard kind of right away was
This desire to take it outside or two to put in other places which the product wasn't
Designed to do
All right
Tumi
Not that I don't love outdoor cameras the most exciting thing that you guys are doing
Is launching a service Club membership
And
This is
Security service in a lot of ways very similar to
Like 10 for storage on an ester ring or something like that
You guys are taking it a slightly different direction
With being able to reimburse people for their deductible
In any idea is much more proact
I'd love for you to describe
The thinking behind
Worship
Yeah absolutely right now with
With Wi-Fi cameras right now
Well a lot of what we're seeing is
Companies
Trying to compete with Who had who got the lowest price for a for video storage
Everytime recognizes more like you know we don't want to
That's not the game we want to compete at United mean
Baidu the idea of
Paying for storage
Yeah exactly
What is you guys design like
If that's your plan
How does membership
I feel that
We designed membership to really
Go against what all the other what other
Wi-Fi cameras are offering it's it's not based on
Video storage is based on benefits that
That are
Really designed to give you
Better security and
Have Canary work with you if you do have a security or an emergency incident
So that starts with a dedicated and incident support agent
So as a canary member we actually
We have dedicated
Supporting us that will work with you
2 and hold your hand really through if they're everything you need to do in the case of
You have your home burglarized
It's crazy because when we when we launched Canary we've seen we have discussion Hunter the discussions of people that have
Just had their home burglarized
You stay as I don't have any sexy have you ever
I don't even want to say it cuz what if someone shows up but
But yeah
As you might imagine it's very like
Scary and Adam Panos
It's a difficult situation to go to a people out of time people are kind of like scrambling to figure out
It what I do what's the what's the right steps how do I how do I manage this process you feel very like violated when it happens and so what we
One of the four things we designer Canary membership is how do we
Actually be an active
Participant wenzhou users and help them through that
How come to that process
So
So this this feature having a
Dedicated incident report person that we can actually hop on the phone with you and help you know here's the information needed
Connecticut police
Kira is at here's how you handle working with your insurance company
Especially walking through every step of that process
So before like right after I called nine-one-one I should call Kenny
Yeah I mean obviously the first thing you should you do it you should do is call 911 actually use the canary out to disconnect with the police
And then you know once
Once you do that will actually walk
Things you can do we can go in and help you you know
Access
Nav other information that you might
Need from the canary app as far as
You know exact timestamp when things happen
And then we can actually work if you have a really strong about
State Farm
And and other insurance agencies
So I can walk you through the best process of how you work with your insurance company and then on top of that we actually
Do as for Canary members we reimburse you for your insurance deductible
So you know that your insurance will cover everything after you pay your deductible will actually reimburse you for that deductible so if your
I'll miss burglarizing your Canary number
I'm going to be out of pocket
Anything that has well
Pepper that for you
Okay
That's
That's an interesting idea because it feels like
The canary
The canary in a lot of these cameras not just connect
Feels like
Something I could use after I've been burglarized but not something that
Pitstop app
So what am I missing
Cuz I'm paying my deductible
Will not actually we're not even worried that you're going
Yeah it's it is interesting security companies I think have
Failed to come
Complete the circle of life protecting you before an incident
During an incident and after its incident
Often times it's only
Kind of like part of that
And so we've actually
Designed Canary in the canary
Experience to help you in all three of those cases so
It's before an incident
Can I give you an insight into what's happening your home let you be connected to your home
During an incident will send you a notification
Allow you to sound the siren that's built into the device
Connect to the police duty app
And then after the incident that's really working right memberships comes in
Are we helping you can't manage that process
That's really complaining that circle before during and after
The circular
Crisis I'm sure that's not your
How to say idea
I am fascinated by this idea
People who are building Hardware recognizing that iot is really about services and so I love membership because it's
A really interesting service
How did you guys go
Come to this idea that you needed to deliver a service or was it always there
I mean I think a lot of it is coming
Come to
Come from recognizing that
So many
Subscription plans that
Coming in not even just talking
In the
Subscription plans
Tech companies are usually about
How do we strip away some features
Put it behind a paywall somebody has to
Has to have a transactional relationship with us and pay us
You know what I mean
It's like how do we how do we make the free experience or product not good enough
They have to pay us so we here
Ensure
Yeah we're like
I mean
Most up
Most companies that do the state don't have like a son of a freemium
Then where
Shirley Spotify
Yeah like Spotify
Adam
Or even even other connected home cameras are products like
You know you have a little bit and then after a month all the sudden you like oh that's the product I bought I thought it was going to do all this other stuff
And we don't we don't want that kind of relationship with our customers we don't want to transactional relationship we actually want
A relationship where we're going to be there for you and help you and so
Service plans to us
We didn't want to come
Key.
Hayward's going to make
Cheaper and cheaper storage
But keep it behind a paywall to where you have to do it
What other things
Can we offer that would be meaningful that would actually
Frito-Lay relationship that exist longer than them purchasing us selling their products and then
Maybe it's hanging up paying us on a monthly basis
Cancel membership came from that it's like how do we actually
Hold hands with our users through things that could be difficult for them
It reminds me a lot of AAA so you could obviously drive a car
Without
Having a membership in
If you have it so
Yeah yeah
Also underlying
The whole
Membership
Platform that we built is this idea of a Marketplace instead of underneath that right
That initially there's these three benefits that come
With membership for because it also
Include
Stop 38th and video history and unlimited downloads
Now there is a storage
Yeah but it's like
You know we kind of take it off a table cuz it's like
Call
Is the whole month of
A video storage
I'm ready downloads no data caps
Add rat like tearing it like pay this much I pay this much more to get more storage just just
Built in there that's not really even
That's not the core focus of it
So with the marketplace are these going to be
Mostly security
Focused in oriented or is it going to also
Build upon Lake dictionary for example has air quality
And
Sensors in
I don't know what else you could build with that but
I'm sure someone's created
Yeah I mean there's really no limit to what they can be our our Focus
Has been out of the gate to make sure that we're offering
Time cover security that's been
Core focus our company
Manticore promised to our users
But if there's definitely
Potential in an opportunity to a lot
Opportunity to do a lot more
And I wish I could tell you everything we know that but there's definitely going to be some
More exciting things coming through the marketplace in the future
I
I cannot wait for that
So
Go it looking forward to
In your company
Your focus is on security
Usell
Couple pieces of Hardware you got your existing Canary you got the flex
Got some accessories to go with that
What percentage of your business is going to be
Services versus hard
Yeah I mean I think we should consider ourselves
In the services business PCS
Dabbing built a thing here that we can build
Continue to build upon
And really offer a lot
Tree services at Canobie
Corridor business
That being said
Where is very very design-driven Product Company
And the hardware is
Is just as important as anything else
We're not we're not in the business of how do we get how do we make cheaper and cheaper components
And then
And just tell those so that we can do services
It's really like all tied together for us like we're
We're committed to
Delivering really high quality
Hardware wood
Nazi from
All the companies in the states so that's something that's very important to us
We're very focused on
Doing a really great user experience through your mobile app
I'm in now with membership we're showing that we're going to level up some
Step up our game when it comes to Services Sarasota Trulia
All three of those things together for us
What would make in your mind membership successful like what kind of
I don't know acceptance rate among your users or
I have no idea what how are you going to judge the success of them
Membership
We judge the success of a level lot of what we do
Bust through
Quantitative stuff but also qualitatively a lot and we spent a lot of time reaching out to
Our user base
That's a lot of the success in my mind is going to come from
Actually talking to our community and hearing from them
If we delivered
What we believe is a needs they have
We want to hear that from our users
With your products
I've got to ask this poem kid has become a bigger deal especially with the launch of iOS 10
And the home app
And you guys a couple months ago said that you
We're going to release a second-generation Canary product
It was homekit compatible
Yes yes
So
When can we expect that
Or do you want to give us an update
On the home
Sure sure yeah we are we have been working with apple on this actually
For a little while it's if it's been
Good
Fun process working with them as they've been
Trapping to announce if they recently did the home platform
We have the beginning of next year when we watching was called Canary Plus
Which is the next generation of the of our first
System
Entire place was going to be as a pumpkin chicken batter Bowl
And we think for at least at least
A subset of our users
I'm nothing to you
Kevin exciting and meaningful addition
Guess I'm sure it will be could you bridge from one Canary to the other
You're old Canary to the
Canary
What are there all accessible through the same
A map of course
Homekit
Ship that you're at the harborage if you put in the product
That makes it home kit accessible
Doesn't mean you can't pull in a video feed from a different
So I could I could see that one
Made in the home app
Which means I'll be hanging out
Still in the canary
In the flex camera
And is that
Careflex isn't at this time
Okay
Chine
Thank you so much for coming on the show I'm excited to see you guys evolved
We need to talk about computer vision
But it lets go back just one step
Cuz I I do want to actually
You guys have actually been one of the Pioneers in
Deep learning computer vision
To your camera Prada
And I remember training Maya camera
When I first tried this thing
For like weeks I was like that's my dog that's my dog
That's my dawg
I'm in the night I realized that wasn't it
Be at it for a while but now it's out
Side hurts your face
How does it how is
That playing out for your users
Something there is
Excited about
Yeah and what school actually what you were doing Stacy and and you were one of the thousands of people that were doing that
It wasn't just training your device that was actually training are back in system to recognize things that were
Caribbean clustered on the back end and needed labels but that's them
So what we've been doing from the beginning is
From when it first launched it is
Trying to have the system I learned identify and recognize patterns
In home environments that could then be
Filter out if they're not import
And so over the past few months
We watching a movie
Speakers some of them are user-facing and some of them just happened in the background to make the product better for our users
In a sentence
Has been really great as far as
Users noticing a difference getting
Fewer and fewer false alerts things that they're not in
And more attention to the things that they actually want to be notified about
Spider dog or for some people it cuz we haven't we actually built sensitivity slider that's in the app
I'm so some people actually took a slider over to where they get
Fewer alerts Madrid actually filter out
Pets
The canary actually caught my dogs
On my bed
That's good for you yet
Awesome okay
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
It's my pleasure thank you so much for having me
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to sign up
For my newsletter Stacy knows things
Stacey on iot. Com