Everyone welcome back to the internet
Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
At this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
I am back from CES
The Consumer Electronics Show in Vegas and Kevin is
Still still
Still in Pennsylvania
Dealing with the cold weather
It's 11 degrees
No it's it's an upper twenties today but we did have some snow
I think it was like the first snow of the season for us
Is Dan usually have something right now but
You know I live in a place where when we get snow
Shut it all down
Who know that does not happen here
Well so we're going to start off the show we got a lot of goodies plan for you we've got a CES wrap up
Some final thoughts
We only recorded half the show
You were only out at CVS like the second day of a whole week when we recorded the last show
Exactly
So we'll get the rest of CES and will cover
New bits and bobs for Amazon Echo
And will also talk about
Our guests who is endorsing
Who is the CEO of
Rectal thermometer did you say he's interesting
Oh India
Sing
Oh okay
I know that's a great name it is a great name he is also interesting
So it's
Like a double on
What is Kenzie
Connected
Thermometer
Imma said thermostat which it is not unless it's a thermostat for the human body which I guess it might be
No it doesn't control the temperature
So it's going to be fascinating
When we do the interview was before why things actually announced their own connect
Thermometer at CVS but I'm sick of the kids up because it is $60 to
$100
And having seen both apps
Kind of like the kids up
Myself so
There we have it
Let's kick it off
With the rest of CES
What a tide
So when you were not at dueling piano bars
What did you see that we didn't talk about last week
You weren't going to talk about the dueling piano bars you know I had to bring that up
All right
So
For you Kevin
I met with
CEO of WinCo
GERD and
I discovered some really exciting news for all the wink Hub owners out there which is
Local
Troll is coming starting with
Lights
It will come sooner rather than later so the next update for your wink hub
Should give you local control of your lights which means
Lower latency
Not waiting so long
And I am looking for the local because
When the clouds down I don't want to have my smart devices not working
Exactly what I'm hoping actually it will
Maybe take care of me
Poopoo poopoo poopoo poopoo poopoo what's going on in sequence
List all at once
Yeah
8/8 interesting you have far more lights in your house connected
Then I do
The only I only have one room or have multiple light and it's only two lights
And they do come off do poop
But not
I don't have a whole string of them so that's probably why it doesn't annoy me as much as annoys you
I have listened
My entire kitchen is
Is connected to my wink
You have how many lights in the kitchen
Sex
So sexy boobs
Text boobs
And it's
Kind of
I understand that better now
It's always wondered why does that bother you so much
Play never hit me I don't have that many a single room
If I had a hallway in the boot
In line with the hallway that would be different
Do you like a Runway
Exactly that would be cool
Follow the blinking lights this way people
So
The other thing I have from
Pink is we talked a little bit about Flextronics which now owns them and I'm more convinced
Thing
I'm so gay and there are 1.2 million
Lync qualified devices out there
Which is actually a lot that is not the number of hubs which I could not go
For the life of me
I'm sure you tried
I did everything short of sitting on the person
Twitch
But Define
No
It was not for any of
What happens in Vegas stays in Vegas
Probably would actually go in my
Yeah anyway so 1.2 connected devices are devices connected to wink hub
Yes that's what we know about link
So get excited
Soon actually get details about you no updates
The platform that sort of thing
I didn't they were actually kind of excited about the bankruptcy
With plans last year to issue a new hub
Actually kind of gay
Time to
Temperature around new platform switch
For them have been kind of a nice thing
I think so because you know you've got if they're open platforms to begin with and you've got what Google's doing with
Pillow and weaving
And the whole
Thread and nexton
I guess they want you home care take that got that to consider there's a lot that has happened
Since they put that first hello
Going to put the second like in May of last year
Homekit
All kinds of things
Speaking of
Last year home kit was like the belle of the ball at CES
The sheriff
Not so much
We just didn't hear a lot about it
There were a couple homekit company or homekit devices
Lots of
You know I devices was out there with
Huge boo
Products
We're still waiting for more profiles
From Apple
And that means certain devices so we have to not work with homekit
Right so we can lights
Sir support if we've got
Natalie thermostats
Search supported locks are supported garage doors
Supported but we're still waiting for things like video cameras
To be supported
And that just takes time and so that's kind of what we're waiting Owen more sensors
So that's what we're waiting for on homekit
I think Apple's taking their time for one thing cuz I think they want to do this right
They focus so much on security that has slowed things up in my pendant
I also wonder if they're starting with the basics no lights in the
Baby locks
Thermostat
I wonder how many people
Mainstream people that are starting to build a smart home
Platform in their house
Actually considered a video to be on at the top of the list I know security is important from the homeowner standpoint security is the most
Most important from a home
Standpoint most people get into the smart
For security
Believe it or not
Bites
Send home automation
Are actually energy saver
Wood slices part of it
Secondary
That's from surveys from both Lowe's and I can
Both of those matches
Interesting
They're at their numbers are slightly off but the number one reason a security number two is energy-savings like thermostats
Lighting controls
Distance
Energy savings and then third is like automation
Lighting and fun
And yes I know I said lightning twice
That's okay for Energy savings
Lighting for fun
Yep
I just got done I get I totally understand that with the metrics actually show a guy get it
Sometimes I think when I talk about when I talk to people there like video cameras in the house that's just creepy
An apple is kind of like tries to positions of the anti creepy 2
Google another
Send video cameras in the house
Looking at your family
And that is creepy
Or I think
But there's also video cameras facing Outdoors facie
Windows
Indoor Bells sing like your front foyer
On hallway
You know
Is a little less creepy
So
And I don't know why I get it
But I also see you like a lot of the use cases that
Kind of tend to resonate with people or things like
Hey did my kid make it home
You can do that with a a little door sensor but you could also do it with like a video camera and then your kid could be like
Word like Raichu crazy notes throughout the day and be like
Pop in front of the camera and beans
Minecraft cookies and you can be like
Child
My phone with notifications with
Advance for cookie
Maybe it's not the creepy Factor that's held them back but it's the security aspect of it cuz they want to ensure that nobody else has access to that
That video that you do not want them to have
I will say that Apple has done one thing well and people have commented on it
And we're commenting on it at CES
Which was
Getting devices
And make it easy for people to get devices online
As
People bring more stuff into the home
Is becoming more and more apparent
Getting them online and typing in your Wi-Fi password
It's not
Huge pain
But people are becoming sure
Wait a sec
What if I change my SSID for my WiFi network
Crap
Public Service Announcement if you want to change your Wifi password
Are you have a really like
What you feel is like
Really awesome SSID which is your Wi-Fi network
And it's like
A random string of numbers and letters if you're going to bring a lot of connected devices in your home
You may want to change
Is that right now to something else
For you bringing all these connected devices cuz you're going to be like
Name of that
A lot in your password
Aesthetic
Going to be
Something you want
How to be able to type
A bunch of times
Yep just name your network Linksys everything will be just fine
But do keep in mind you know if you're going to be connecting a bunch of devices to your home
SSI
Alaia
Okay so
That was our little PSA for the day
Cartoons
Little scoop I heard
Amazon Echo support for thermostat
Is coming
Soon
Native support native support
This is going to be like
Right now
The Echoes supports lights
And that's it
In the Smart Home
Connected home I think is what it's called
Thermostat
Very cool very cool
I also heard
And talking to some people
The original plan was to actually along with lights was to support like
You know other settings but it became the syntax became too cumbersome
So they had to back off.
So you know like an Siri how you can have
Seems like dinner party lighting
That was kind of the plan to have
Amazon to
Progesta Logistics around
Figuring out how to do that across so many different
Possible
Platform
What is natural language processing
So
But it's coming
The thermostats
Soon and neck
Speaking of
Amazon Echo
And people don't realize this
Will you and I only talk pretty much on the show these days cuz we don't truly work together anymore
Different from writing perspective
But we wrote I think they exact identical story
Based on some news that came out
This week's coming yesterday in fact
Yeah I thought my story was probably
I bet it was 300 worth
But we still wrote the same thing what we're talking about is
The Amazon Echo me have a baby is what I'm saying there's reports anything
Journal Wall Street Journal was the first to note this
That it's expected that Amazon will release a smaller version a Portmore portable version and cheaper version
Amazon Echo soon I don't know what soon means but
That's what they're saying I'm taking a couple weeks
So it sounds like from their description is like the size of a beer can
And
Yes exactly still a chance
I have batteries inside but will also have a docking station so you can recharge those batteries it one of the
Things that we observe you and I both in our separate articles. Talking each other as
If you have enough battery power
We're hearing that you got to press a button to be able to do your voice commands
Motorcycle that defeats the whole purpose but
The thought is if it's sitting in the docking station in a different room than okay is probably always on microphone least that's what I'm
Open
Why are we hoping
Won't because we otherwise we just use our phones or whatever and then there's there's just no point
Cuz it takes them bad check out of this
Yes
So
See the value in having
Multiple echos
Especially if you want to
Smaller
Basically a link to echo to the mama Echo
Elsa satellite
Is multiple in like party mode for your speakers
Cuz then you have
You can play music around anywhere in your house
It would also be nice to be able to you know
Give commands
You know that work throughout your house right
But only if you can talk to it and you don't have to
To touch it because the magic of the echo
Is this
You don't touch anything otherwise
You know I have a good Chilean devices in my house that I can control here by smartphone or through
Some sort of tactile interface
The reason I love the echo is because
I don't have to use any of those
Guy Curry
I can understand why they want to limit
The always-on microphone when you're running a battery power that's cuz
You're going to shoot your batteries pretty darn quick
If it's always listening
So I get that I'm just hoping that they
Haven't always on release an option when it's
Plugin I can't see why not
Brent there's no
Power constraint there
It's plugged in
True I mean your phone has an always-on
The way Amazon's theoretically
In the way Amazon's always on listening
Works is
It's always listening
For the trigger word a trigger word
Try not to say
Correct and then if yours
You know what it starts it wakes up and starts processing
And sends those
Those words that you said after the trigger work to the cloud
And then it goes back
Back to sleep essential
Then it stops
Sending those
There are processors
Make
Light work
That kind of
AI for listening
To those were
Listening for a trigger
And those kind of processors are currently in a lot of next-generation phones or current generation phone
Like which iPhone is it
It's the current
Jen iPhone
Right you can you don't need to be plugged in and you can just
Speak to Siri
An adult
Do what you need to do I think it's
I want to say it's only the larger
Are the two latest iPhones
There are processors there's a Qualcomm processor I'm assuming that there's a version of the a
Is it the A7 that Sunday current
Benign
It's okay so that's not insurmountable in that gives you
Yeah whatever
Three four days worth of battery life I am not sure it's been pretty much a day for most people
Really
Okay so you still have to charge
Kills that theory
Dead in the water
Do you know what would solve this whole problem
I've said it once I said it doesn't time
I'll just let the Amazon Echo app on your smartphone
Listen to your words and Bluetooth them over
Through to the speaker or up to the cloud I mean
We all have a little remote in our hands
All right all of us but Stacy have a little remote in our hands
I think our survey said that like 30% I know I know
I know it just seems silly to me that have that app sitting there and not be able to interact with it
Via voice
Bipolar
I won't go there again
Alright so
Let's see if this is cheap enough depending we'll see when details come out if we would buy
We would buy such a thing
I have a feeling we will
No matter what
And I'm going to I'm going to go out on a limb and say it's going to
Cost 79 to 8 at $99
That sounds about right
And you think that we can tell people to buy
Listen put multiple ones in their house I think it would
I have a Sonos already I would rather see Sonos
Let me know Amazon voice services in there
Why isn't there the new Sonos
Aren't they supposed to have a microphone on them
I don't know I haven't looked so I feel like I do
So if that's the case
Then
I don't know if I would need
But that's true that's true I would definitely buy one
Because I really want
I don't know if I said that
But I really want to know
Echo
In mybatis
That's you have said listen
I stripped my head last time and I'm shaking it again to go ahead
How do you say I want to hear music while I'm taking a shower and I want to ask
The time
Weather in the morning I like
Like the news
Honestly
At the end of the day I want this
Everywhere in my house
Because I don't want to have to be in a specific room
I have a question or I want to know the time
That's the whole point of that that invisible interface that permeates your smart home
I want it I want it now I want to cheat
Exactly
Alright so
Garnet will buy them
Give it to us
But preferably with always on voice
So
That is that has he any other oh I was going to say final OCS.
Are two things worth mentioning
We hate doubt over these tiny little moat
Switch actually not
They were introduced maybe last year
University of Michigan
Has
Developed a technology called
Easy
Little
Chips like to MMM lacrosse
Yes they like
I took a picture I'll run it with the podcast
If you see it
I mean this fits on the tip of your finger like probably like
I don't know like 15 of them could fit on your finger
I don't know about a finger but they say like a hundred and fifty could fit in a thimble
Istanbul
I have a connected symbol
They're really tiny and they have
A radio they have processing power I mean and they have itsy bitsy photovoltaic cell
Pressure sensors a temperature or
A temperature sensor or motion sensor
Some processing power
Radio
And some power on this thing
Is a couple bucks
Is
What I was told this was at the arm Booth by Andrew over an arm
And they last for a couple years
I'm not 100% sure what I could do with one of these
Honestly on the radio
Send the signal light
But they want to get it to 20 and I want to start
It's funny you say that cuz it was we were talking about it before the show Psych I want these
I don't know what I would do with him that it doesn't matter I just want them
You can make Computing more self-sufficient
Smaller put in like
More places that were previously on accessible and you can like it or
Information from it I'm like
My God why wouldn't
Yeah
I mean they're talking about
They were like you could stick this in someone's eye in like measure
Blood pressure for glaucoma
Yes you we need to get out by Medical
Coding for it
But that is not hard
I hope I'm curious to see what people
Eventually do with these things
Yeah you can swallow them yet because
I need solar
Power I forgot about that I said that before the show I said I want to eat one Justice
I don't know measure something inside body in
Well no solar power there
It's so small you could eat it you could accidentally eat it
So I was excited about that
So
Guys get excited tell us what you think
Think you might be able to do with it cuz
I don't know
Maybe the University of Michigan is going to listen to this and they'll be like idea from some random person who listens
Super smart
Probably know y'all probably have like
Who cashes at these and you're like
Stacy
Boring
Already have
Already done
Final CES fight is
On obsolescence
Chance and we'll talk more about this because it's worth
About butt
I was shocked at how little people were talking about
Obsolescence
At the show
You're sticking like I saw you know the Samsung refrigerator with the Giant
Android phone
And it's very large
It is
Refrigerators get a lot of heavy-duty usage and they last for like 8 or 10 years
And it felt really strange to me to stick
What is essentially a giant computer in the face of it
In some ways it's super cool cuz like
Yeah I want to be able to read my recipes on my refrigerator
Set a rather have it like next to me on the counter or in front of me on the backsplash but that's cool
And I love
Message boards and
Pictures and
Maybe a calendar that reminds me of things on the refrigerator
I also like
Dang
Download away
Yeah that is it
Terrible
Place for that
Cuz we spell all kinds of crap on a refrigerator
Right now I think there's like
There's some soup
I'm like two nights ago
Okay
I mean I'm going to get to it
Sometimes
Maybe my husband is
You know and what do you clean the computer with
With spandex
Stainless steel refrigerator cleaner
It's a tough call and we've already got so much E-Waste you know on this
May not make the most sense to have these kind of Integrations
And I don't think we can get
To your concern now that we figured out how to really disposal stuff the right way especially when we're adding more and more
Trudy's products
And then that yeah and
I mean what if someone throw something in the kitchen at cracksat screen
Go to replace your fridge
Let's hope
But then like think about software updates
Sand Lake
Two 5G radios
I mean like in your application processor in that thing it's a little slow and you want to run the latest games I mean
If you call someone out and they have to like
Replace the motherboard on that thing
I don't disagree that I'd rather see these things no more modular in that you know just make it magnetic
Back on a
Application-specific tablet or something in and let it stick up on there so you can just
Put down in
Replace that when needed
I don't know yeah I'm just thinking of that
Qualcomm didn't answer modular thing for cars a modular Lake
Electronics
Box for cars basically
Which is kind of in that line of thinking
Which is good
Cuz I already want to replace the 3G radio in my Tesla
44 GB
Because 3-g
It takes forever to load my maps
And ghetto
5G is going to be here in
17 if you believe Horizon in 20/20 if you believe everyone else
Anyway
Okay
Obsolescence
Skip think about it guys
I'm looking for Solutions
And now
That is like
I think that was enough
Okay so now we're going to
Talk to August about how we're going to
To stop the spread of disease by using connected thermometers
It's going to be awesome
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and our guest this week is indoors
Who is the founder and CEO of cancer
And you guys may be wondering
Oh my God what is this
This is a connected thermometer
Oh my gosh
So fine we're going to tell you all about it
So Interstate you so much for coming on the show this way
Thanks for having me
Appreciate it
I am super excited
Because
Connected thermometers are my
Because I have a 9 year old daughter who is constantly bringing
So
Why
Why did you get the
It's in your head that
You're like the world needs
Yeah so it looks like the product first
And tell you about that and then
So it sounds simple it is
It's a SmartPhone connected thermometer and makes it easier to take a child's temperature
It automatically stores
Remember screen brightness automatically stores the results
Offer you and each member of the family can put in multiple different profiles
And so that way when you go to the doctor
And they ask you how did
You were your child's illness start
Grass there's no question
And beyond that it should have realized the vision of what
Consumer health product always ought to of done right in my opinion
Consumer health product to him always
Ought to have
Not only
Comforted
But given you guidance
About what
Our product
Realized
In the product we have you
Rules that based on your fever and certain symptoms we give you formal guidance we tell you
Absolutely to take your child to the doctor talk to doctor right away and
You know if a newborn has a fever that
You need to go see the doctor right away so we tell you that
How does it do this for me so let's say my 9 year old has a temperature of
103 which I always am I
This is really high
Yeah so let's say that it's the middle of night
3 in the morning
And your nine-year-old comes in here and says mommy mommy
So you pull the kinsa thermometer app
And you get her to take her temperature
Do you take a temperature
Usually in under 10 seconds
You get these professionally accurate results
And with a few simple Taps you can input sensor
Show the proper numbers for you
How to start an interesting share that with your doctor later or
Your babysitter
You're concerned that she may have some severe symptoms and the app automatically processes that information whether there's a
High fever
What are the associated symptoms
The age of the profile and gives you information if it's cause for concern it'll tell you
And if you want more information on that you just happen
You can get all the sources for the medical experts themselves
Now imagine that you your child has a fever
You're concerned
She may have caught something from one of her friends at school so you go check the health at her school
So we have this group's feature that allows you to opt-in
To seeing the aggregated
Anonymous help stats at your child School
And here you see that say 5 out of 24 kids RL
And you see in the message boards that are associated with that group
Bad strep throat
Well that's a little bit more cause for
Turn the common cold so now you decide to talk to Medical
And starting
Middle next year we will have a ton of disintegration that allows you to talk to a doctor right then and there
Right through the app itself
I'm for now it just gives you that
Information that
Hopefully
Help you make a decision as to when when and whether you want to go see the doctor
Right now it's based on schools and I know that you guys have a program
With your
Kenneth stick thermometer
At schools
Could you also do this based on like
Zip code
You could and that's part of the broader vision
So take a huge step back
We didn't
Create the product
For the product itself we created a product
And our mission cancer is to create a map of human health
Track and thereby stocks
Spread of disease
We started the company with no product
With no business model
And with this mess
And we thought to ourselves how can we
Begin communicating
With someone who has just Fallen ill
To help them
And simultaneously collect the data needed
To track the spread of disease
And thermometer became the most ideal
To piggyback
On the thermometer is
The single most ubiquitous medical product in the world is
The first product that parents turn to
To confirm illness even before they call the docker
Go online
And it allows us to aggregate really interesting information that will help us track
On the spread of many contagious illnesses like
Influenza and like other contagious illnesses
What are the challenges in dealing with
Information like this is
It's medical data and people might be kind of worried about
You know having their children
Labeled as having some sort of awful contagious
How do you handle things like privacy
And identify
Yes absolutely it's really important
To us
Engender the trust of our users
Xiamen certainly one of our highest priorities and buildings product in
People are sensitive to the fact that there is health information
So first we adhere to all regulation
State local
I'm in Federal Regulations around health information
And we have a policy of never sharing anyone's individual information without their Express
That will never happen
The more importantly I think it's important to understand what kind of information
These are ensuring by using prod
It's really common
Fever and Common Sense
Things that everyone has it's not very sensitive
We're not asking you for whether you're
Cancer positive HIV positive excetera not if there's nothing like that it's it's very common symptoms and it's
Yunnan temperature
Second by default we don't actually ask
Personal
You don't have to create a login to
Use the product
That's again to engender The Trusted user really help everyone to understand that what our goal is to add
Target population data
Should we understand the spread of disease it's not about
Marketing information
Necessarily to you it's not about collecting your information it's about this broader mission
That will not only help you but will help societies
Okay
I'll keep that in mind
Your history is very
Very interesting
You actually worked for the clintons help finish it for a while
Yes so
How did all this kind of come into being
In a place because
It's kind of a good story
Yeah it was really born
Are my experiences there was born out of my frustration
I'm in my final year there was there for about 5 years my final year I remember being in this meeting
Where
That this was the final meeting to allocate
Almost to
A hundred million dollars
The curb stop or prevent the spread of disease
This was a major funder in that
In a global health wealth and I remember being in this meeting
And scene
Some of the people that were providing
I remember there was an expert malaria that stood up and said you know they're 280 million cases somewhere in the realm tears were there
And I remember the next expert which is a professor at a major ivy league Institution
I'm still up and said there are over a million cases of malaria
I thought to myself
Wow
You have no idea we're talking about it more than three factors
Difference in the projections
And it became really clear
Stats on the world doesn't have
That system
To really understand where and when does this disease is spread spreading in real time was really really frustrated
I'm not the most patient person to world but I was increasingly frustrated I remember I pulled out my phone cuz I thought to myself man
Is very quickly
I was looking Google Maps
Trying to figure out how to get
I'm looking Google Maps
And I'm watching him out
And I'm looking Google Maps
Money and it struck me that
We have so much
Real-time information
Every other ass
Burl Ives
We know we know what our neighbor's house cost
Through price of Zillow and Trulia we know
How to get downtown fastest
Google Maps
In ways we know what our neighbors dog is
Feeling like through Facebook
And yet we have almost zero in French
When it comes to
The health situation around us
Not situation effects of intimately
And it was a travesty it was complete travesty.
The world spins so much
Money I mean if you aggregate
The amount of money spent
I'm trying to curb stop or prevent the spread of illness whether it's the flu whether it's strep throat whether it's croup or
Whooping cough
Or malaria age
Is TB a respiratory infection will you add that up
We're talking about
Several GDP
Key points of the world
Massive amount of money hundreds of billions of dollars
And so how do you allocate
How do you put the Reese
The drugs a diagnostic
The vaccines that work that we know work
How do you direct those
The people who need the most
In a timely manner
That was sort of work answer was
Well that was the first pillar
How cancer came to be
We believe that stopping the spread of disease
Is one of the biggest
Ways to change the base of a world in which there was no
Spreading
We also believe that the way to do that
Is with better information
About wearing
When it's spreading so you can intervene early
With the drugs that Diagnostics to vaccines and other products that work
You can stop it before it affects the larger
So I still feel like you're going to have to just quarantine all the chill
With that in mind you guys are started
A really interesting program where you
You pass out the cheaper version
And here's why I should say that you guys have two versions of your product right
Be smart
I guess it's the cancer
Smart Stick
Thermometer
I need to call the thermostat so if I do that tell me
It is $20 and then you have the ear thermometer which is $60 in the ear thermometer
Pop it in the rear end
And it works and then the Smart Stick is a traditional you stick it under your tongue
Thermometer
Kind of thing
So
The cheaper version is the one that you guys give out to schools
And you know it had those in schools for about 18 months and some places yes
That's right
So we threw our fluency program we give the kinsa smart thermometer the stickers in a way and we give it to school
Schools around the country that are deserving of its where they are really enthusiastic
And it's a philanthropic program
And we see how those small clusters of parents use the product
And we've had about
9 schools have been using for 18 months and then we increased the size of the program this year and we
By the end of this flu season they'll be more than a hundred schools using the products are really excited about that
We have this great story I love this
Within a week and a half of launching is program
A 1-carat went under their school group and posted saying
My chemistry in the morning
My child has rosy red cheeks and
Checking the origin
Another person responded still in the middle of the night
Another person
Responded and said
My child has
The same thing
They had a rash
Interfacing
Inner chest with red and a fever and the doctor diagnose this
Disease and he basically told us there's not much you can do but it's highly contagious
The first person respondents said so no need to take them to the Urgent Care Facility
? right
It's exactly the kind of information you need right she was basically saying to seeking information to make a decision
Do I need to go in right away is this really deeply concerning or can I wait till the morning
To book an appoint with my normal pediatrician
How do you see the stuffing illness
Because that is kind of cool right
And then
What comes next do you need more devices
Or is it just how do you change behaviors
Yes they see we're just getting
We believe that when we reach
A level of penetration
Between a quarter and a half of 1
We will have in
Information to the tap to start taking into
Flu season
Faster and better than any
Hyperlocal bases in really empowering the system
I'm going to answer your question
What does this particular program do parents with information
To respond early
And ultimately we believe that that's going to result
Unless
Children matter of fact
If you get
Your child to the doctors office early
Then it's less likely to affect other children
But the earlier you texted me earlier you were likely to stop at whether that's affecting another person or whether that's progressing to significantly
If you guys are excited about this
You can get cancer thermometer
In Target you can get both kinds you can get the $20 stick in CVS stores I believe
Both on Amazon
Interested in the fluency program
How could they get involved with something like that or is that just you got to convince your school
Well if you're excited about the product
And you are somebody who would be enthusiastic about telling other parents at your child's school about it we'd love
Look for you to apply to fluency
It's kinsahealth
. com fluency
And you can fly there
And you'll have someone from cancer
Reach out to you and chat with you about the demographics of your school and if it's it's the program we'd love to
Okay in the IOS and Android
It does yes
Stick thermometer is a wired product that connects by the headphone jack
And works on iOS
In Android
And the ear thermometer Wireless product that communicates via Bluetooth to your phone
Oh my gosh what happens if the iPhone takes away with
Headphone jack
So it's a good question we have some we have some plans to tutu account
Oh my gosh yes cuz
How would be dire
Okay
Now I know who who to call the first day of that happened
Oh my gosh
Tell me Plan B
Thank you so much for coming on the show I am excited and I cannot wait to find out
What happens with more data
And
Kind of house
How this works out because
This is one of those things like I will never say this word correctly but
Let it go for it
Epidemiology
I broke
How The Internet of Things
Can kind of
Work with public health officials in
Epidemiology
Because it's just
Fascinating and it's such a rich mine of kind of
Data and how
All of this will help with Public Health
Thank you for sharing
Citi thank you so much for the time we appreciate
That's it for this week thanks for listening
And we'll see you next week on the iot podcast