Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
If we have got an amazing show for you today because Mobile World Congress is happening
And because
I'm really seriously hot
Internet routers have been launched
This week
So we're going to have
Eero routers
We're going to have an update from Philips we're going to have
Numbers from Verizon we've got some Tyrone action
New chips for The Internet of Things
Make a new money
And a whole new network
Okay so
Let's start with
Eero
Who actually their CEO Nick Weaver's Our Guest
And I actually also tried out the routers so
Free to talk about those first
This is cool now
I did not pre-order these I remember it
I want to say was a well over a year ago that Euro announce these
Small router / repeaters / metal mesh network devices
And they're much cheaper than they are today because they're available
Around now right for 199
Kickstarter
The crowdfunding will collect
And what's interesting about these I mention Mesh networking
Everything many people probably by multiple euros
And this present time in a free pack right now
499 and I think the kick-start price was 290 nights I wish I had
Me too because I'm going to tell you
I really like these routers
They're amazing but I definitely need three and in the evening
For in my house
Which means I am looking at
502 $700 worth of routers
Is a lot of routers
It is a lot of routers is also a lot of money and which you know some people say why not just
Go in and retrofit hardwire whatever
Your house is pre-wired I know but other people
Might consider that
But you don't you have more flexibility I think with the wireless network
Something to tell you
Tell me a couple things
I
Have
I really
Kinda complicated
House cuz it's really tallest really skinny
And it's really like
Long front to back
So
I've never likely to my house instead
Wifi
Router is
Right because you have like
Three stories plus like a rooftop
Yes and because I have always connected gadgets
Connected stuff in my garage I have connected devices on my roof
My house actually does
Need coverage for I feel it needs
Average cousin
There's no point in having a connected garage door opener that doesn't actually open anything
Good Wi-Fi and that's the point of Euro
If you think of nothing else the whole sole purpose of this company right now is to deliver
Really
Great Wi-Fi cover
Really easily
And that in itself is
Worth a lot for love
People so when I setup my network
I had
3x
Lights and are about a hundred and twenty-five
It's about a hundred fifty when I bought them 3 years ago
So they're they're actually
Copper bowl
Price and you can buy
It in the challenge with an access point is
They're kind of a mesh Network
But they're kind of a pain to set up
Captain assign IP addresses
Yeah and sometimes they create separate Networks
Experience depending what you buying we got some range extenders have created separate Networks
Yes that's what I was going to say
It's probably
Pretzel
The nice thing that the arrow is
The box is like looking at you and your phone is like your phone's like
He's like little pretty diagrams on it like I'm doing something magical and it's making these blinking little
Things
Magical and then like 30 seconds later it's like
So set up is easy
Yes
I have not set up a notch
Oh okay I have is pretty simple it's it's basically like setting up most any other connected device that's
Seamless to set up
These things are talking to each other so it's best the setup process is
Each one of these little boxes
If you have multiple of something that is
Are setting up a mesh Network and the ones singular
SSID or net
Yes
So you got one SSID
Yay and you can
These can actually be wired so in my case because I've got ethernet Jacks throughout my house
Minor all wired
But you can actually
Have them be Wireless
An attack
3pac you only get one ethernet
So that's to go from your modem
Eero
Right so the one hangs off your modem like a traditional router and then additional ones can either hang off those
I guess
Daisy chaining them
What are you doing that for
Wirelessly
Through Wi-Fi
Yes got it
Although they don't
Feel like there Daisy
They feel like
They're not actually
Gearbest
Okay
Wow complicated
So how does it work
It works really well
So like
The coolest thing was
In my house
Time Warner Cable who is my internet provider hit actually upgraded
They're upgrading whole country to 300 megabit
Their whole service footprint to 300 megabits per second
Service
And I was like I haven't gotten to yet
What they had
And I just didn't realize it because
Actually my access
Which I bought three years ago
They're probably
802 11
And the best
Yeah neither Gyros RAC
So
30C Trump's in
It does
Ndng a day
All of the others
Switch is the Halos back for the Internet of Things
We'll talk about that some other time if it ever happens
It happen
I digress
Faster WiFi
The app is nice there's not a lot to it
Best feature
In the again
Coverage the next
Text feature that it's offering right now is
Guess networkx
SSO
I now have the ability to do instead of getting my guess
Act the actual SS
SSID and password
Social Network I can give them
The guest password
That the generates for me which is some weed whack password
And
I can text it to them or I can give it to him
And I can do it all for the app for lease
That is very cool and I should mention Eliza swimming today on Hub
The Google is adding this to the onhub very recently I haven't set it up yet but
Similar thing it you can use the app to set it up and then
Textured EMF share the
Information for Fergus
So don't have to get these little scrap of paper that's
Like the Wi-Fi password is this that you'll lose our look at
Yeah
So it's super fun
I like them
They are expensive
Good Broadband cannot be be
So yeah I mean if you're going to pay for
You're taking your case 300 megabytes per second pay for 150
You want to have internal equipment that can actually handle that otherwise you're paying for something you can't really use
Can you can handle it everywhere
Everywhere in life
210 minutes of setup
Like literally it took me more time to run up and down the stairs
These things that place
Set them up
I am very tempted
Backpage
Make the investment because I love my onhub
But sometimes in certain areas the house it's just not cutting it
And I thought about other Alternatives so this might be one
I will say this I read a couple of other reviews on this because they all went live today that they were recording
And couple
What is a couple people commented about how
Eero requires in the app that have your
I think your email address but your
Phone number as well
Okay so I can explain this
And I was wondering if this comes up in your interview and if it does then we can just hold out till later
I don't remember
Alright well
Prescott weather
CC
If you're hearing this twice
It's because
Friend is actually security feature so it ties and all the stuff security stuff
Sony Cleaver the CEO
Said that so many customers were setting terrible passwords like password 1-2-3 was a favorite of everyone's
Videos like
And given all the scrutiny to router security lately he was like this is terrible so he said he's
He's not doing password so the reason why he has
Or the company has you give your email or your phone number is so it will email you or give you
You or text you a verification code
And so it's kind of a password
You
You answer that in and then you get the verification
Sentence for the setup of the actual router
Next to log into the system every time you need to log into
System
OKC
Every single
So what an end that makes sense so now I don't know if
Other people understood that from the other reviews I'm glad that you asked him that we found that out
I'm wondering then
Can you still
Normally set up a password for devices to connect your network or you still at your current
Wireless network
Will have it
Same password
So
My network like Stacy's home network
If my home network password was password one
23 it would still be I can still set my
My SSID for Stacy's home network
Ssids pass
He tried everything
So this was just to get into the app
Got it
Got it since I first line of defense
Which is you know
Cuz if you baby change the password on my
Like actual wireless network
I would come I would
Dumpty's routers in the ocean and then I would like
Set them on fire
I I know that's kind of like impossible to do but that's what I would do because I have so many devices
Changing the password
I get it
So yeah if you know my wireless password it's highly unlikely
Kevin's like
Haven't tried in awhile me see if I can
Turn lights on
All right speaking of Lights let's go
Good Segway but I'm not looking forward to sharing this news
We talked last week about Phillips
And they're Hue app and they updated it on the Android
Punched everyone Chagrin and they
February 12th after today
Permissions for Android 6.0 incorrectly
It sounds
Like and we mention this last week that it sounded like they implemented this incorrectly and it does not appear fix
Text as of yet as well
And if you missed our show last week basically if you've got the Philips Hue app right now
You'll start to see the app ask for
Individual permission
Android 6.0 marshmallow features
IPod Philips Hue 4
Doing what they should be doing to prepare their app for
Compatibility on marshmallow
The problem is two problems really one
Philips Hue haven't really made it clear why they need these permissions although I understand why and once you understand why you're probably
Oh okay I get it now
Regardless of that
The way the app permissions are implemented today in the current version of the app If you deny permission for one of the three things
History things are camera storage and location
The Apple workout
So
That's not how it's supposed to work basically if you don't want the app to have access to your camera
Which is actually needed to create light scenes
It should still work that function
Wouldn't work though the app itself should work
So really they got if they got to fix this we just before the show checked in the Play Store
And that's at the last couple days they're still getting hammered people cannot use the Philips Hue app why can't user lights
It's very frustrating and I hope it gets resolved soon
So yeah Phillips
We reached out to Phyllis before last week's show they didn't get back to me though until
A couple days ago so yeah
They just wanted to let us know
That and let everybody listen to the show and who might be affected in feeling kind of like or Phillips
Only makes use of these permissions when the functionality related to them is being used
I don't access to usage data for these permissions
Any other purpose than
What we talked about to creating light scenes
Storage is using is also used to create light
After photos
And location is
Is Portugal fencing
So that's it
But they are also currently working on a fix for this
So it's implemented correctly
So they're going to come back to us when they've done that fix
We really hope it's soon because they are taking a beating in the App Store
And hopefully that happens
That is that
Phillips is on it you guys
Bingo that you're upset
But they're not using your data in any weird nefarious way so please
Feel free to continue using Phillips and Grant them those permissions or feel free not to do it
And maybe don't
Top 10 light some candles
Enjoy okay
So let's see we've got news Verizon
Verizon is doing
Really well it's catching up to its it's
Ginormous rival AT&T in the iot space
Bear
Revenue from their iot and telematics business has total 690 million
As of year-end in 2050
Teen Witch is up 18%
Which is
Not too shabby
Yeah I think that 18% is
Yearly growth and I dug around us and another figure to put this in perspective
Back on October 28th when they
Announce their
Thingspace platform
They had said then that their IRT and telematics revenues were at
495 million year-to-date
So from October 28th will basically two months the last two months
They've jumped the revenue for 495 million to what we just say 600 end
90 million + 90 million
And that's that
Pretty good
But as you mentioned they're just still catching up so they're big rival AT&T
Think you mentioned before the show they were there IRT business was a billion-dollar business
As of last year
It was on Pace
Billion dollar bill
And a lot of AT&T business comes from the connected car cuz they've got to pick up for the fat Tesla they've got out
They got a lot
Golang
Not axle nut Studebaker
Verizon thingspace is there developer platform
Just in case you guys are
Like what what
It is a cloud platform
For Developers
You know Verizon has been very upfront about how it's looking at this it is
Definitely saying we have got to sell more than connectivity
That is that is not going to be a big Revenue grab which I am thankful for because then the data plans would be you know just
Crazy insane
Expensive
And they're trying to sell strategy around this so there
Holding
Cloud together with Consulting
And trying to create these Partnerships with companies that are already in the space
To build kind of
It's basically a Consulting and systems integrator kinda
They worked quite a bit with Nokian Erickson on the on the network itself and what they're saying
I'll see you today actually from Emma World Congress they said they now have 4,000 more than 4,000 Developers
On thingspace which is
I'm impressed by the number it may concern they just launched it back at the very end of October
Yeah that's that's pretty good I don't know
I mean it
How do we count
Yeah that's it a tough
It's hard to quantify minutes it's just a single data point I mean I'm curious to see who actually does
Some of these developers and partners are what products
Delivered or plan to deliver
So also
NWC
Trendsetter Cloud apis on things face will be available soon in beta
Statway dad's can create mobile apps
Retrieve photos video music and other clouds
Content so
It's all very interesting kind of reminds me of
What Amazon is doing with
My birthday for devices but that's just me
It would be here
I'm also at Mobile World Congress because how can we not talk about the show with it going on
This week
AT&T announced a plan to
Well is it a plant
Degree to test
Agreed to test for G
Drones in conjunction with until
So what we've got basically is drones that are capable of
Assuring really shrink data really fast
Not only that I mean I look at this as somebody who owns a drone and yes I did register I do have my FAA number
What's interesting is
I can pretty much only use my drone in line of sight because it's using Wi-Fi
So I've got a pretty limited range when you really think about it compared to 4G all the sudden you open up to a
I offered you networking
Songs on following the rules
Fly my drone
10 miles away
Oh my gosh your drone could become a package delivered
Yeah
Exactly you know what Amazon it
Do those round thing for deliveries but why not like pickup
Let me just have my drone drop down loaded up and
You could become like an eardrum could become like the equivalent of a
Uber driver
Logistics
Boggles my mind
Cool
But yes
Yes this could be awesome it also kind of creates new ways to police the space if you think about
What kind of things you can do with like
Cellular data and
The controls you have there
Not only did they talk to each other to avoid collisions
The Operators could then have a lot more
Control over
How these things are running
Because I can
Control how they're talking to each other
Yeah it does it to me because I wasn't thinking about it no with multiple drones you know
Turn on Wi-Fi networks here you know
Where were separate where were
Not able to share data between drones or talk to each other or someone like that
I bet you put us all on the same network
Responsibilities
So exciting news there
We'll keep an eye on that
Also at Mobile World Congress Nokia announced
Money
They have create Nokia growth Partners has created a 350 million dollar internet-of-things fund
And this is actually for
It looks like it's more for
Technologies to enable the internet of things which
Yay
So
Not just like hey I've got a connected fork for you but
Things like
I've got some I got a cool technology for real-time data access or maybe I've got like a new way to control drones over LTE
These are the kind of ideas you can give to them and
This is a global fund so
It's not just you eccentric
Yaever
I have not limited to espoo Finland
Also not limited espoo Finland
I like to say
The arm
You want to talk about the army yes yes yes
What is happening arm has a new chip that is
Probably going to find its way into maybe like a Raspberry Pi device
But also
Looks really good for wearables it's the cortex a 30
The big deal here is
Arm did something smart we talked about this before the show and I think we're both in agreement that you can disagree if you'd like
They decided to make the CPU just 32-bit compatible not 64-bit
What kind of work were bandanas around thinking that kind of makes sense because you know with a with a wearable device a real small device
Are you going to need to address more than 4GB of memory probably not
So that introduces some overhead gives them a little bit more
Power efficiency this thing
Jeezy say it's less than 4 milliwatts of power at 100 megahertz clock speed
You can have a
Quad-core version that's where it's less than 75 milliwatts
Procore at 1 gigahertz scale it up
How do you say to recently fast speeds for something like a where Laura or a pie
But they're also saying no internet of things things my
Like this nicely so
It's interesting
There's a couple things interesting here and
You named almost
And I just want to break it down for people who are like
What the heck
Just happened Kevin was like
Talking like a normal human being and then he just like
Yeah
So
Artmix
Ship designs roots and I'm going to give it a shot
I may not do any better than Kevin
Arm is not actually it doesn't make physical chips
It makes it designs
Seven other companies like apple or
Samsung Cloud
Take the designs that are make
And actually makes physical chips
Specially designed ships and other people make the chips for the butt
So fun being complicated
What happened in Computing is
There's like this whole like end of Moore's law say
Great and I'm going to I'm going to go there be
Because I think this is really a big Transit is really exciting and we're talking
Even if this weren't iot show
Moore's law states the number of transistors on a chip
Doubles every two years
And because of that
Are chips are gotten
Just much faster
Art store just got
You've got more storage for less money it's amazing right
But what's happened is we just can't do that anymore
At this point we
No we were going to get the
There for years but we're at this point where we've been experimenting with all these crazy new architectures
Because we don't actually cedar chips to get faster anymore because
It's way cooler if they're more power-efficient
If they're smaller because we're using our chips not just in these massive servers and
Computers but were using them in like
Wrist watches in washing machines and all these other crazy place
So with this computer
Arm is actually saying
Total race to get faster and faster and party that's like
The fact that they've gone these 64-bit chips
Because you know our smartphones and needed to get faster and
You know they want to get in the server so those have to be pastor
Who said hey wait
Wait
We don't always have to go that way
We could actually take a step back and do a 32-bit computer
Did still
Got this more modern instruction set
And has his more modern architecture
Do it because
All kinds of crazy
So I think that's kind of like
Big picture of really cool things
What's happening
And I don't know if that helps
And what time
Spell memories
Make any sense
But yeah
Is awesome
So
That's that's that
Blissey final thing should we talk about
New wireless networks
What about now
So company called ingenue
Launch a wireless network
The Internet of Things
It's kind of like sigfox
Or
Laura is a standard a section out of
Separate network but it
It's a separate radio standard for
Networks
Carrie like small amounts of data
And are usually pretty cheap to run
And there
I never really interesting kind of option
Connected devices
So ingenue is saying they said it Mobile World Congress that they were going to lunch this network
In
Pitea bunch of different places yes
Yeah I think they said they have 30
Private networks now in
25 countries that will be providing
Connectivity in 25 countries for machine traffic
Yes and these countries included the US
But they also include Canada Nigeria
Chili
Japan and New Zealand
South
Thailand
United Arab Emirates
I'm at home. I was going to say I'm about to sing It's a Small World
Yeah
Don't do that no no no
So the cool think so
What they use is a use a radio technology they don't use Laura they don't use sick foxes technology they use something called
Have to find it because
It's crazy acronym
RPM a random phase multiple access
Great you want to tell us what that is
I'm not sure what it is it sounds like a teleporter to me
Okay basically it's a low power
Network that they built and it only
Has the only carries that are small bits of data it's not very fast it's not like I'm far 4 G networks is
Purpose Driven Network
I think I'd seen that the top speed of the network is like 624 kilobits per second
When is basically machine-to-machine specific Network
Yes it is 624 kilobits per second
That's download speeds than upload speeds r156
Kilobits per second
So
But slower than 2G
Yeah I was going to say it's like you're
But interesting thing to me is
The range of this network
Because they're carrying
Small bits of data
Slower speeds and they've got their RPM a protocol which again I don't have the details of
They can have
Cellular towers for this network that are
1 towering cover 300 square miles which is
Not many Towers compared to our heavy data-centric networks of today
It's true but it does still require Towers
Which means
And all of these networks actually do require
If a significant investment which makes them kind of
You know whatever I am looking at these types of networks or any type of wireless network
Because everybody has a dream
I'm starting to wireless network
A lot of people I need half the screen
You always have to look at things like the economics of it which are how far apart of your Towers cuz that's a big city
Investment
Read how
How are you going to get
Any sort of specialized radio protocol like RPM
Requires some sort of specialized
Chip to read that radio protocol in the device
Espresso
You're going to have a special purpose to buy so how are they going to get that
Chores who are their partner
Interesting in this case is the people behind this company ingenue and it used to be known as Reiko Wireless
Under that name of the work with T-Mobile and was part of its in Denver
On the board of ingenue is Ivan Seidenberg who was the former CEO
Verizon
And dr. Andrew viterbi who is the former CTO Qualcomm
So
Those are actually two very smart guys when it comes to radio
Technology
And cellular at the economics of building a cellular wireless network
Sound like
Could be cool
Lot of challenges yet I think but
Yakiniku
Yeah I'm still I'm always skeptical about these just because I'm like you know what's you have data
You never say this is enough data
He always want more more
But you don't baby so into do without their its competitors or things like Laura
Like
Sigfox
And you know that the cellular carriers are also testing
You know like lte-m
So the LTE machine Networks
We'll just have to see so keep an eye on the space because it's
In a lot of
Storm and fury here but I just don't know if there's much
I'm curious as to what spectrum there going to be using and someone as well
Well that's that's a big issue
That is it
Alright well
You guys have been so patient
Now we can
Stay tuned for a chat with Nick Weaver
Who is the CEO of hero who's going to talk about
Well he may talk about some of the things we've already talked about but he's also a lot more stay
Listening
Hey everyone it's Stacey Higginbotham and you are listening to The Internet of Things podcast
And today my guest is Nick
Weaver and he is the co-founder and CEO of Eero
Hey Nick how are you doing
Great City how are you doing
So let's get started with
What is Eero
Yeah so euro is a
A really simple whole home wi-fi system
Key difference between
What folks normally have
To power their home Wi-Fi is
It's typically
One router
And so what we
Offer instead is this whole home system
Where you at multiple units
All connect to each other
City of one
Single Wi-Fi network name that blankets every corner of your home with
With really fast reliable
So
Just for people listening
I have had
Whole-home reliable
Wi-Fi
But I had mine because I had
I have three access points to my house plus my router
And
Then Nick came over and he and his team installed Eros
Which
Installed apps
Because they are really easy
Kevin and I have already talked about it
Most people though you're right
They buy a router
They're like oh this is great except
It doesn't your
Exactly
It is one problem and I like to think of it as
You're part of this whole new generation
Companies that are alike
My God my Wi-Fi router
Is
Probably one of the most important pieces of equipment in my home
Terrible it hasn't changed in like a decade
We're more
And
It's got those janky software it's probably a security risk is this article for the Wall Street Journal has discovered
And you guys set out
2 years ago
Yeah we got started in the beginning of 2014 so you guys set out two years ago to change all that
And so
Let's talk about what you did because
Design is probably the first thing people notice
This is a
Pretty little white box
So when I get to spend a lot of time talking about that
But then
The other thing they're going to notice is the fact that each one of these little white boxes cost $199
Kind of a lot for a router
So what are you
You getting
Yes so with with Ichiro you're getting
Some of the highest performance
Home WiFi coverage available
So
A single unit retails for 199
And if you buy system which starts with three units
Prices for 99
What you're getting with Eero is you know if you go look at the
Home networking category
You'll see there's Home wireless routers
Sherpas home
Wireless access points
And there's also things called
Range extenders
For wireless extender
What what year was it
It's all three of those things all in one box
And our software we felt
Well automatically detect
How your system setup
And optimize your network
Docker no configuration no settings
All you have to do is just say I want to
Network
With this network name and with this password and then you're up and running
So you got
These guys switch
Really was as simple as I took it
Brand of software
On the app I downloaded the app and
Do you want to add an arrow and I was like yes I do
It was like
It's on the Eero
There was like
I found the Eero connected the arrow in the air was like
The lights the lights the lights
It was
So
In my network
It was stopping it from being awesome was actually my old school switches
Which
Nick has kindly sent me an email news like
Hey Stacy your switches are for a hundred my networking
Which I thought was cool but I couldn't see that on my own
What we do
Every Network
Is constantly running Diagnostics
And
Alpha Diagnostics improve more and more that information will find its way
In2 into the app
So let's talk about the app
Because
Really that's kind of I think that's probably
Totally agree
Oh wait before this that we have to tell everybody
Why
Why with the internet
Things podcast
Do we care about
Better wife
Yeah it's so it's so what's what's been fascinating over the last couple years is just the number of devices that are connected
So not news to you or anyone else who's listening
You know we now have connected thermostat speakers camera sensors blinds lights
Events the list goes on and on and on
And as all these devices come online
They need to connect an
Every corner of your home
So when you don't have great connectivity
It's really
Card for these connected devices to come to life
So
There's there's a combination of the number of devices and types of devices that are connecting
And
Cutting the cord has actually taken hold
Where
People are now streaming video everywhere their home they aren't relying on
Just their cable or satellite provider
So you have these two forces murdering one is
Lots of devices
Disconnected everywhere and the other is
You need really high speed reliable
Connectivity
To stream video in every room in your home
Got it
Totally attached to the first which is
I have
Sonos speakers on my roof and then all the way down in my garage I have
Actually I have a Tesla.
Needs over-the-air updates via Wireless
And I also have a MyQ garage door opener that it's like
I'm connected to WiFi as well
So
Yeah
So Wi-Fi totally important to me
Let's sew on the connectivity front my TVs are Hardware
Which I totally recommend to anyone who can do it
But if you can't I did run some
I was watching something on a tablet
Over this since I was like hey
It's not stuttering
Nice
What is Sutter's I'm sure that's not necessarily my
My face at work it could just be my highest p
Which actually brings me to a question because I thought
Given
The Diagnostics you guys have in
If you have
A huge customer base you're going to start seeing a lot of really interesting data about
Kind of broadband speeds and connectivity just around
Hopefully the country depending on how
How large customer base you get
Is that something you're kind of thinking about using
Or if you're totally correct that's
That's information that we do have and we monitor really closely
The reason we monitor that closely is
Can directly impact somebody's experience with their Network
So what we found in our peda. Where we have
Under the customers and thousand of Eros online
As you can see the Ebbs and flows
Your connectivity across the country
Well you can see everything from weather creating outages
Certain parts of the country have faster
A burger medium Connections in other parts of the country
And it's so as more and more your networks come online
That becomes a really interesting dataset to understand
Exactly how well does the internet work
From a speed and reliability perspective everywhere in the US
So where would you like to live based on the data you seen
Where does someone who really loves Broadband Bridge today
Where should I move
Yeah it's so it it's interesting there's
Median speeds are definitely faster in call the top 30 metropolitan areas
But then you also have these outliers we're
You have
Regional providers that that might have their own fiber
Where you get really really fast connections
And in some smaller geographies across the country
Exciting all right let's take it back to the house and let's take it back to kind of
What you guys are planning to do with this because one of the features you'll have is kind of a guest Network
You make it very easy for me to create a guest Network for p
People
Which is
Super nice
But in a previous conversation that we had
We kind of talked about
How to think about identity
Four things on the network
And I'd be kind of curious about
Going forward
What is kind of
Your goal for all of the smarts that you're building into this
Router because
You could do a lot with
This platform
The biggest wanted is
These devices are
For lack of a better phrase Arthur typically just black boxes
Authors
There's a lot of information
There's
A lot of different devices connecting and a lot of the work that we have
Accomplished and also ahead of us is
How do we take all that information and make it really easy for people to understand
Done as always devices. Connecting throughout our homes
Looking at your home network is it is a great indicator of
What's happening in your home
What's going on
What devices are connecting
And then what things are happening
And a lot of the work that we're doing is helping people understand all those nuances
Edit it starts with
First let's get you really reliable connectivity so all your device devices are connected
The one network
And then from there let's
Hope you understand exactly what's happening
From
Number of devices connected to the types of devices connected
Why
This box
Now why did it take a startup to do this
When we have had
We have these major companies Cisco you stolen linksys now Belkin has it I mean
Netgear
Dealing all of these are major companies that have
Lots of big budgets why aren't they
Why does it take
A startup like
Make yourself to do
When you have a an existing
Is density of an existing product portfolio
It's really hard to start from Square One
And rethink the entire product experience
So when you when you think of
Typical home networking products today they're all
White products
Meaning. They're all designed to act
On the round independently
So like we talked about earlier
Most homes run on one router and it's so that's what these devices are
Design for
Single device in your home providing connectivity failure
Devices
Now
Hazard connectivity needs have
Changed as more devices have come online as streaming has become more and more important and as the canoe
Directions speeds into our home
Have improved dramatically
Allow you to have multiple devices
Allprovide Wi-Fi
Track your home
Now that the Big Challenge when you go from one device to multiple is
All this configuration all of these settings
And
What we've done to simplify all that is basically started with a new
Architecture new way of building this product
So what we have is we have the same software layer across every single year device
And
They're all tied to the cloud
So what the cloud allows us to do is
You can think of it as your
Friendly network engineer in the sky
That's what's responsible for tuning in configuring and setting up your network
So as a customer all you have to do is
Think about your network name and password
Then all the settings the background are all configured
Empire clock controller
So with everything in the cloud
That's a lot of information about
You got all the devices in my house you got a lot of information that you can infer from that about my comings and goings
How secure is that
Yes so if you're we take security very very seriously
In terms of
What information is available at the cloud only captures the information that's
Bishounen the app in terms of number devices and speed
We also have diagnostic information to help us tune
That works and that's all around connections
Speeds and links between Heroes
At no point do we ever know
Where you're going on Pine
That's not information that we care about it says it's both now capability of the system North it's
Something that that's implemented today
Okay so you know that I have
Nest thermostat and 6
In my house
Example
But that's the extent of your knowledge
Or is the extent of your knowledge just that I have 27 devices
We have the the names of all the devices so
Every time it gets displayed in the app
That's that information is coming directly from iCloud
And the reason
That's important is
You can be off your network so across town across the country across the world
I mean you could still be able to check in and see
What's happening on your network
On the security front aside from not
Capturing
Information about where I visit
There's also the issue of keeping your both firmware
And everything else updated
How are you guys
Looking at that
Because I know that a lot of the existing routers you're talking about 10 year old firmware you're talking about Hardware that isn't updated
All kinds of
So it's really interesting
And it doesn't
Really come as a surprise is the vast majority of
At home networks have never had the software on the network updated and that's becoming an increasingly
Larger problem
All these devices are
Your home network really become the
Security layer for all the experiences in your home
And if you're not updating your software you
You're really leaving yourself vulnerable
So and that's one of the biggest benefits of
How they are devices tied to the cloud where we update your network automatically
So
That you always have the
Latest firmware
With the latest security patches
And you also get
With only products you
Typically have to go to some support site
Download a firmware image find the right page in the admin utility to upload it and then once you upload it
Wipes all your settings and you have to reconfigure everything
There are other
Routers out
Kind of launching
Couch
Using a router I think that's a boxes
It's in front of your router
But then there's routers like luma
They're actually security specific
Routers that offer some of them run software that's
Continually updated to fight against
Malware
Some of them have
Looking for
Bad Network Behavior
Is that something you guys are kind of looking at or doing
Yeah I think the first order is
You have to just make sure the software running a network is really secure and up
That gives you a
Huge Head Start
Compared to the other products
So
The first thing you have to do is make sure those systems are in place and everything's up to date
Play the terms of adding more preemptive
I features the monitor anomalies on your network
Yeah that's that's definitely something that's very interesting
You got to learn to walk
Absolutely
Got it
Now let's talk about features because
I feel like this has the potential to be kind of like the Amazon Echo in the sense that it could get new stuff over time which is cool
Because right now it feels pretty
Barebones III love the speed test I love knowing what devices are in my
But I do want to have
Kind of more granular control over them
Partly because I tested other routers that already allow me this so I'd love to be able to say
I want to add like whitelisted sites to my daughters camp
As opposed to
I want to say hey turn my daughter's computer off at 8:30 when it's her bedtime
Interest rate up gun
So are those features that we can look forward to Overtime or
Is that just not
The plans
The number one thing we're focused on
Is providing you with
Really reliable
And estas connectivity everywhere in your home
That's a core feature that's been overlooked
Buy a lot of products and Ernie's evolved in our homes because all these connected devices and
All of us
Streaming the people do on a daily basis
You know that need
Continues to grow
In terms of other features
A lot of those things are pretty interesting
And a lot of customers have have
Reviews on from you
Again that's the that's the beauty of this system
Is it keeps getting better and better over time
Juicy new products for example coming out
Like right now you're doing this
And I know you're only 2 years old but you know everybody's got a roadmap so
What would come next sludge
For you guys
Again
Today we are really focused on on fixing the connective
Three problems in the home so
Anything we can do to improve that
I'm so that all these experiences in our homework
That's what euros
Pakistan
By that much
You might want to start an ISP
ESP front
That's pretty expensive starting a starting hardware company is
Is expensive as well but laying fiber and
Karate connectivity everywhere
That's
That's a pretty big
That's not something you can
If you can I wish you the best of luck
There we go alright
Thank you so much for coming down the pike
Thanks for having me
That doesn't this week's episode
Thank you for listening and please join us next week
The Internet of Things podcast