Hey everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham and you are listening to The Internet of Things
Podcast
I am your host
And she's co-host
Is
That's right y'all Kevin is a Google IO
Actually so is yonko
But something in 4k
He's busy
Spelling is Nuova.
Exactly
Yonko is
Former colleague of mine from Ikea
He is the smartest man in the room if you want to talk about
Well a lot of things but the fate of digital media television
Like both hardware and Zack
Programming and
I don't know what else yonko
Good I was always exciting
Weather for this week
And I should get right to it because I
I think there's a bunch of
Google News throughout
Vishal today right
We have a lid actually we have the words with Nest to be confused
Basically
Just announced a whole bunch of new Integrations for the
Works with Nest program
So we're going to talk about a couple of them
Most notably for a lot of old-school smart-home people
The Belkin WeMo finally works now with
The nest
So this is exciting because a lot of people have wemos
And it works with your nest thermostat so if your thermostat notices the house is empty
Light skin turn off
Maybe your Crock-Pot or your curling iron whatever is in there
What I saw at Weston
It does
Lucretia how that works
Two cameras work
Each other
Oh so this is the August doorbell cam
Okay so this is actually cool so the August doorbell cam
Basically what you do
Is when someone
Comes to your door
Eventually the August
Emotion sensor
As part of this soda
And utility comes when the August doorbell is like
Hey something's at the door and what'll happen is it will trigger your
Camera
Basically being able to say
Because they have this August Access program
Can say the person at my door it's the guy from Postmates
Delivering something
You can actually let him into your house
If you have an August lock
Now if you have an S cam you can also keep an eye on it
While he drives whatever inside your
Front door
So
The light bulb
Integration made
More off your scent
Beware the camera senses motion
Lightbox go on or off
If you want to
Exactly
Dollars for you
So there's one that I want to talk about because I think it's
I don't know if it's pee or if it's going to be like
The Breakthrough device
It makes the Internet of Things
Things useful for like
Middle America
I don't know if we talked about the
Febreze connect but basically this is one of those
You know how you can
Plugin sense
It's not potpourri it's like those sensory
Essential oils
You can actually
Plug the P&G
Febreze Connect into an outlet in
Control it from your smartphone
So what they done with their nest integration is
They've got algorithms
Because everyone has to have them
That will actually
Time your
Thermostat
Spike turning on the hbac
Whiskey release a fragrance in your house so like
Fragrances disbursed
Most efficiently
Okay
What kind of extensor doesn't smell
Aladdin one Rohan.
Yeah so I kind of like
But I really am curious because the pg4 rescan it is what it is like
Maybe it's like an ant
Grandma or someone always has those like fragrance
It was in their house right
I don't have them
Maybe it's when you turn 40 or 50 you get this and I just haven't experienced it yet
Baby. So anyway I'm really curious to see
If people find this really useful because
It's a product a lot of people buy already and it's actually relatively
So I don't know
So
AR
Worth mentioning
Just in general some of the other companies that it's going to work with is a thermostat to work with Lutron
Misfit Waxman which is a water leak
Sensor so
This is cool because if it detects
There's a leak and your way from home
It's going to give you a one touch dial to an emergency contact
Hopefully we will eventually
Instead of just being able to call someone and be like hey something's making my house go turn off the water would be awesome if
Here's the number of local plumber
That's a business model
So I have a question
You sing this
Is Nest sort of
I mean obviously everybody likes to work with other devices but everybody else
Do you think that is is part of it like
Tassets mix together
Dick Hannah Lofton
How many devices
He said I could
So the way Nest has
People share data with it like Nest is very limiting
With what people can do on its play
So some companies like SmartThings had decided it didn't want to work with nest
Because it didn't like the terms other companies have talked to me behind the scenes and said
Just ask them to do a lot that they didn't want to do and it first they didn't have the power to say noted
But now that they're
More platforms out there that they could integrate with
To have negotiating power with nest
So I think there's kind of a power shift happening in the industry
Competitive thing
I don't know we don't see a camera on here
Example I don't see any
Fire smoke detector
I don't think that desk
Could resend
It's
Program
From somebody who has an established thing so you know it's got so many lighting kind of things I don't think that if it
Ever decided to introduce a light bulb that I could take all those others back
Because
Users would probably revolt
So I guess the answer here is
Nest is kind of growing and learning ally
The industry as a whole
And I'm guessing
What I would look for is the security stuff
They don't have a lot of
Security sensors or anything like that so I'd be curious
Skitto
How that kids integrated
We don't see a lot of those.
Decorations
Travis just
Especially
In light of the
Confucius over there with
Getting you
New devices on the house
Launching new devices
Power struggle
Having some of that maybe
But
It's interesting to see like this
These moves under those
Google sites
It is
I think
For a while nested no
How it wanted to play the smart home game
Seed a little bit to the reality of the industry which people buy one else devices
Instead of hugs and hugs are just too hard
Plus that's not a strategy they ever really
Working and pursuing
So I don't know
Bassinet stuff
I want to talk real fast about some big news that actually happened last week
Which was
Amazon web services launched an iot button
Basically
It's like the Amazon Dash buttons
So those are that
One press button
Is that you
Can use order like
Certain products
Brita water filters
Toilet paper
Do you have a dash button
Okay me either I've never been like super excited about it but this
Is basically a programmable button
That connects to
The Amazon iot Cloud so Amazon Lambda and what's interesting there
Where is it people are super excited about it because
Right now getting a device on to Amazon's iot cloud
Requires you to get a certificate
Enter the code on the back of this
Iot dash button
And boom your device is online and
You can start playing with it
So
To me this is kind of fun because it's a marketing move and it also gives you like
Ability to be liked
Turn on my Hue Lights
Quick
Do that
Exciting
How did the differences
Specifically for Developers
Exodus not something that
You would envision
Gettings consumers like this
The first step
Amazon
White label e-juice at some point
Settings
1 this is totally for developers It's 1999
Find a ticket sold out right now
This is to get them to try
I forbid you actually have to learn
Like so I talked to someone who is set up
A Raspberry Pi
As their home automation Hub and they use this to connect
Route command
From the dash button to AWS Back Down 2
Wichita to like their lights
So
They had the three press it's a it's a
One single press
A double press
Lawncrest
3 button options
They said it was fun but this is also they also pointed out this only has a thousand clicks
Before it runs out of batteries
You throw it out and get it
So I don't think this is going to be like this huge thing
Super home because most people don't
Program and you can't just be theirs
GUI interface
Hue Lights over tula
The button
Programa as easily as I could like
But I think it's good because right now in the cloud Wars
The warrior for iot is
The word for develop
And this puts Amazon kind of in a stronger position to get them
Right now probably
Microsoft Azure is one of the
The number one clouds for
The Internet of Things
And then IBM
And its iot foundation
Cloud
It's probably
Second
So
Alright yonko you just got back from CVS
Yes
Just got back from Shanghai
I don't even know how many hours ago because
That's quite a jacket
But it was sad
Interesting events with cas
Obviously everybody knows the main Show in Las Vegas
DeSoto
A couple of
Spin-off
Cities around the world
But csho tries to be the
The whole wheel trade show
Specific event than Asia
Unifocus
And this year
I was there last
Egg for 3 days
Show happen
And it's
Chinese
Oh you got to explain cuz yonko you and I were at CES together so
Yes
To be honest
I mean it's it's as much smaller show so I think
In Las Vegas today
I don't know how to 20000
Attendees every year something
Hear that 30000
And was also at
300 exhibitors
Magical anyway you could actually see
Almost everyday
But it was a little hard to understand
It was in China and
That was very
The folks on the
So I try to find my way around anyway and try to see you
Reckful riding outside
The media Focus
And there wasn't quite as much
Ragazza media Austin
Shipping devices
Thanks
In part because I didn't have any TV stand
Exhibiting in Santiago Peak
TV's really didn't play that much of a role which was kind of surprising
But everything else bad drones
They had IRT they had
Weird fun devices to haneda robotic suitcases
It was kind of cool it's a it's a suitcase of kind of follows you around
You hold a sensor on your hand and it dries
Behind
Tickets at the airport
Pretty cool
I like it when is that coming out
Butts
A lot of things to be honest that had
Big Sean
Previous in CSS
It was weird
Especially pets
You have a lot of Cs and out in all states
You are
Twice now together
When you franchise a little further into
To the hearts
You would like
Who would make a massaging West
Well the people who does it go to CSS Rancho de adictos other people with me
Pretty weird products
Interesting stuff
And any cool Smart Home Trends or anything like that or was it pretty much the same
I think it was a lot of the same things except a lot of
Cause of Chinese takes
Trends
Pop that has to do with
Light companies.
Business
So you can look you up
That's right and
Facebook Snapchat
Just one of those other exam
And then there are big
People have this conception
Chinese cat
I think it's partially true partially that's whatever
Anthony. But there are some obvious example
Ding dong ding dong
Is
Did Chinese Amazon Echo
John Bailey
And it's made by jd.com
Chinese speak
Meijer retailer
So they decided to make that one smart speaker
I think the exterior
Last year but they just added more capabilities to it
So it's not black
Wind speed
That's not quite as round
Olympic death
Shape
But it does a lot of the same things
Ask question
I can't read some stuff
The news
Korea calendar
You can play music on
And
All those things
Thing that you can do which was
Surprising
That was the first
That's what everyone does
Yeah I think so maybe that's
But yeah so they told me they were going to add that as well and
I thought it was interesting
Because it's a very popular product
The US and
Supposedly it's inspiring companies that Google to do the same
Officer assaulted by big companies in China
Alright well we got to cut this short
So thank you so much Uncle for coming in
Thanks
Hi we're going to have a quick message with Kevin bomber who's CEO of my devices in a quick sponsor
Good interview
Hey baby how's it going
You're here to talk about cayenne
What is cayenne
So Kyon is the world's first
Dragon drop
Iot project Builder
That empowers users to quickly create iot projects
So we're literally talking
You're taking an iot project Down 2 minutes
Instead of
Mutts
And why did you build this
The primary reason is when you look across the landscape of iot platforms are out there there's hundreds of them
Organizations who want to start building iot projects just don't want to spend the time or the money
Did it takes to get invested in one of these large iot platform
So even though ours is a very powerful plant
For misery easy to get up and running literally in minutes and we launched this at the end of January 2016 Ranieri
20000 developers and we think we're satisfied
Create rules and triggers you can do scheduling
Are you going to visualization and business intelligence so we think it's a great way to get started with an iot project we wanted to be the
AutoCAD for iot
All right so where can you find Cayenne
Stacy the easiest way to get it is to go to my devices. Com
Or you can go on to the Google Play Store and search for cayenne
From my devices or on the iPhone store so it's available as an app or off of my devices. Com
Thank you so much Kevin thank you
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and I am here
Rick clemmer who is the president in
CEO of Xanax
Hey Rick how you doing today
Terrific
Thanks a lot for having us I'm so excited
VR technology for
I want to ask you so many questions
First let selfie
People what NF
So our real focus is
Providing secure connection
For the smarter world you know what you call it internet of things we're not really sure what the internet of things really is
So we like to call it this morning world which is more include
Includes wearables
Include smartrdriver
So as we think about
The Internet of Things or is
People like to think about the Internet of Things
We actually think about it as a smart of world and how we can make all of our Lives easier and safer and more
Secure okay well that kills my first Quest
Like it's too many things
So you guys make all of these chips
You make microprocessor
The tiny little brains
Who makes sensors
We do
Secure things that organizes things
We do anything else we make the connectivity to be able to do it and importantly we make the security
For example the chip that's on if you've recently gotten a bank card that has a chip in it we make
There's a good chance that we make
The ship that's on your card in fact if you're in China
And you have a contactless card which is more advanced than the US
Payment cards
There's a virtually a assurance that it's an egg
Picture of associated with it
Alright so this week you guys did
Really too cool announcement
I'm sure you did more than just too cool announcements but I'm thinking about
The coolest
And one of those was the first of those
Was
With a smart car
You guys
Have our work
Blue Button
Department of Defense
Department of energy
Yeah
Yeah so what we're basically doing is providing the capability for car companies and for the men
Manufacturers that are providing
Technology for the car companies
Actually have a demonstrated will product
So that's the Computing horsepower has them
Microcontroller that we use for automotive it also has a microprocessor that's out of her digital networks business
It has all kinds of sensor capability and software
12 users to really experiment with a.
What's with assisted driving
With automated driving
Figure out how you can make driving more safe
If you look at that
Through basically the third level
It's about 80% of the semiconductor content of a completely self-driving car but
It really provides
Much more
Safety it provides much more assistance
What's the driver about 85% of all accidents
What's the did happen today
Are created by driver error
So if we can make the driver smarter but they're running the more information or helping them out
It will make driving Cypress
So 80 /
Percent of
Conductor Conte
My car is
Adidas today
No not today
I think when we look at it going forward you know the significant growth engine associated with components
Will be in the p****** 8 oz
If you look at the Innovations in the automotive industry
About 90% of the Innovations in the automotive industry is coming from Electronics today so it's not coming would steal its
You know with different forms of them mechanical
Platform Electronics
Ixtel driving innovation
And the car today but 90% of it
It really the area that we see the most opportunity to really
Assist drivers in make
Driving safety
Is in the area beta
As we bring
More
Computing into the car I think we're going to see this
But the car is a really good one
What needs
How to change about
How cars are made
How even car manufacturer
Think about
Vehicles and then also
As a user how should I think
About my day
Yeah so you know it's really interesting because the user experience if we can help a driver you know I'll give you
One example of its kind of be
Extreme so you know we are one of the key semiconductor
Suppliers to BMW in the seven series which was the car of the year at the New York Auto Show
BMW
You're such a good partner that we had an investor day in
New York and they actually brought that car to show to our investors
Because of the capability we have over $300
Semiconductor content
In the BMW 7 Series
And with that the feature you can take the key fob that we manufacture by the way
You know better
But you can take the key fob and you could actually
Park the car so when you approach the parking spot if it was too close
She could get out of the car close the door in with the key fob
Actually pull your car in a park
Associated with
No this is just parking the simple parking spot where there's no closed doors but it also would do parallel parking impact
I had that lady I was trying to shesus with my husband can't park the car in the garage so he can use the five to be able to do that so
So you know what it's really about making driving safer
But things as simple as parking
Is a convenience
So we make all of our life easier but really the key features are being able to make it safer
Warning so if your
If you happen to doze off or be doing something
And you do across a lane
Being able to have Lane change warning
Stability where somebody stops in front of you and you don't happen to be looking to Auto stopping word
Stops your card
So that you don't run into another car
So that's really the key features that were trying to be able to provide when it comes to the
So
You're talking to
The car maker so I think it's really interesting.
Most of my electronics items last
Baby 7 years maybe 10 if they're really amazing
And hardened
But my car
Actually last 11 years
Right
That's about the average age by the way of the US Car Fleet I think
So
I guess how should they be thinking about it as they add more
More advanced
About module
So one of the key things that we're trying to do is work with the car company so we provide the Platforms in the technology
So they can upgrade that on the Fly and actually was some of the products actually upgrade over there so for example and
Security
There's always hackers are always making progress and Improvement
So we actually are trying to develop technology we're over the air or let you know through the network
We can actually upgrade the security levels associated with
One of the key things in working with car companies after the
Hacking incidents that took place last
The car companies are very interested in security so we're working
With the car companies on a three-tiered approach to be able to make
The cars absolutely safer soap
For example will put a secure element the same device
As I used on your bank card
In conjunction with the input the LTE input into your car
ISO that provides that someone can't hack into
Qcarbo32
Access
We can put
Hi security
In conjunction with my crew
Controller so that the processing knows that any input coming in
Is actually supported
And actually we're the leader in NBA goal networking you know if you'll have the transceivers in the car because of all the lights
Points
It's a were actually typing out a product later this year will but
The basically the same thing as a secure element
We have
Which bank cards are electronic passports in conjunction with a transceiver string vehicle networking
Subwoofer secure a note in the car so now you don't need that for the
Complete Car Care
Your electric windows you probably don't care if
If that's secure to keep it from being hacked
Your mirrors you probably don't care that Jasmine is you know
Prevent that from being hacked
But your engine control your breaking your speed
Those are things that you want to have control over that somebody can't hack intake
Are they thinking about how to
Speed up the development process
On vehicle because I know right now things are coming out on cars
Thought of
Really built like 4 years ago
Yes it is changing and one of the things that we're working with them
Is how to provide that information you if you look at it
Historically the car companies have used intermediary electronics companies now they're working with a Semiconductor Company
You still have the
Continental Zar Bashas
For example or delphi's build the product
Weather doing is a working with the semiconductor companies to understand that technology and then specifying that
To those companies so that the decision process about what they do
Is now a shared responsibility associated with
But that's really a significant change for
For the car companies
A lot of the car companies are putting some
Lead technologist in Silicon Valley so they know more about what's going out
I wanted to things that were excited about the blue box is being able to work with all the car company so they have the ability to
Begin to think about 8oz
In automated driving
Without having to have a complete architecture of a car but just having a simple
Experimental tool that they can use
Is to be able to
Experience
A Dawson the efficiencies of automated driving
Eros on demand
Alright well let's think about smart cities because you guys are working with the Department of Transportation on the 40 million dollar Grant
Smarter cities
Trials here
Here in the US
What do you think of
You know I think it's a really a phenomenal experience so you know secretary box
Department of Transportation that has originated this with this
Were they had a grant in the rooster
I think it was like maybe 50 or 60 cities across the US that actually applied for this and the finalists were
They're so sweet five or six and they ended up with Seven Cities original
Nothing we're close enough
Could not eliminate down to the absolute by but they have seven cities that are going through this process and what
What they've done is we're working with them to be able to provide the technology to each one of these cities so that they can then structure there
Proposal
To Department of Transportation to be able to facilitate this now
In addition to the 40 million dollars
Vulcan Ventures going to Paul Allen's companies adding another 10 million out so it's actually a 50 million dollar Grant
The city that Wednesday is
So we're working with them where they can drive
You smarter driving so the Billet deeper
Buses and
Police cars and Transit vehicles to be able to communicate with
Each other
So that you can prevent accidents so that you
Can regulate traffic
So that you can provide the capability associate with that but we just announced
What's the today
Soda partnership
We had originally we announced a couple months ago after CS with the Department of trash
Station we just announced
Expanded program with the Department
Transportation today
So we take some of these
Security capability and Technology
Need to wear for government documents
And expand the program to include that so we're now working with the cities
On how they can do Transit ticketing
Be able to facilitate that where they can do electronic vacation of government documents you know where the Red Sun
Driver's license
Exactly
Regulations
So then you won't have to worry about you know the the Youth of today
You know we're all trying to get their fake driver's license so they can go the bars
If we can put a chip in it then you can at least be sure
It's really a driver's license
Continue don't have that
I know some teenagers who don't like the fact that we're proposing this but in Europe
All drivers license X
We have a chip so you can authenticate that
Chucky
A police officer they can actually scan that to confirm that it's a real device
You know it's not like you have the opportunity to have a fake ID
Let me ask you
2 questions about
Kind of smart cities in actually this relates to driving
What about standard
Cuz I can see a lot of cities being like
Hey
We got this reading is even even bigger standard like we're going to use RFID to track people
How do you see
Your customers thinking about
The fact that people travel from place to
Things need to work sort of the
Yeah so that's one of the challenges that we have is
Is we need to be sure that we can provide the technology whatever it is so you know
Iconnectivity yoga all those areas you talk about with
Bluetooth or NFC
You know that's all connectivity capability until there are standards associated with connectivity
Is positive
But we also have to be sure that the interoperability exist so that you know is you have a electronic wallet on your smartphone
Did it came work around the world
Night so final question
What are you most
Excited about
So you know in the next 5 years
I think we're going to see a lot of change I think the ability to make all of our Lives safe
By having security associated with it
Thank some of the examples that we talked about
But making life easier
It whether it's self-driving cars
Stability
The only carry your mobile phone around for using for banking for entry for door entry
No just making all her life easier
So much for coming on the show
Fantastic thanks for coming to her technology forum
That's all we have for you this week but join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast thanks for listening