Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a Whopper of a show
We really do
I think it's going to be kind of late
A downer of a show
I was just going to say that if you are
Expecting something peppy and bright and cheerful for the holidays were acting to start off with some not-so-happy stuff
Yeah I'll do it if you want I'll sing a song we can we can have a cheerful holiday rendition of like Deck the Halls
Later on
Or or an item
It's the truth but I'm still listening
Well
Okay
So let's get started with
Earlier this week
Start with my
Instigation
I caused it
Stacy is the IRT instigator of things
So I tweeted this week that my nest
Was roasting my family in the middle of the night
In
It's true it is what's happening is for the last about six weeks
On random nights but usually on the weekend
My Nest Thermostat
Which is upstairs
Is
Turning on and confusing my summertime air conditioning settings with my winter time heat setting
So instead of keeping it like 68
At night for heat
It is turning it up to 76
Switches what we have it set for AC in the middle
Summer
So like at 4 in the morning
I wake up and I'm like
Oh my God
I am dehydrating
Sona mode
Yes but it
A dry heat
It's pretty bad last weekend this happened and it woke my daughter up
It usually prompts a migraine in me
And my husband would probably sleep through it only I am
Highly dramatic and so I
Wake up in
Like I said of throwing off the covers and I'm like oh my God
And this time my daughter did wake up
Like an hour or so
I was a little cranky and I fired off at
What's open late to eat
It's a polite
Yeah I was like
Nest
What's happening you're roasting my family I think a hard reset is the only way to go
I heard from like
4 people maybe five
Maybe 6 I don't
They're also having this issue and I also more importantly heard from dust
Instead they will they help me troubleshoot
So
Which is good that they're monitoring
Twitter
They are Fitness is good and I did at nest
Right so a couple things to know
I did look at my schedule
To make sure that
I wasn't
You don't like
I didn't have it set on my skin
Retinue
I actually this is
Been going on for a while and I had been resetting it back hoping
To teach the nest
I didn't want this to happen
My heat settings
I'm so I had been actually playing by The Nest rules for a couple weeks and that just wasn't
So with that in mind
Polite
Height of discombobulated tweet later
I heard back from nest and they asked me for some information
About my account
If I was using any works with Nest program
And
Yes I was
They pinpointed the issue
As being something with
It's works with Nest specifically
It looks like they decided it was my
My MyQ my Chamberlain MyQ settings
Your garage door opener is messing up your thermostat
Just what the
They said
I'm raising an eyebrow I know nobody can see it but I'm sitting here with my face
Yes so that they asked me the question I asked was do you have any worse with Nest products or service
You do would it be all right for me to check your account activity log to see if they could be adjusting the nest
Best temperature
So first of all I want to give them huge crops
For asking
Like all kinds
The permissions before they go
Skip and being very specific and what they are
So yes they did that
They decided that
They implicated the MyQ home
Control settings
And they asked me
Turn off
Maya Maya
Control arm IQ
Works with Nest integration
And I did that
I also got with the MyQ
Soak City
And I was like hey whatsup
Hey we're looking into this too cuz this is strange and you know this is hard
Making things work together on the back end while making it really super easy
For the front end
It's hard I don't disagree with that
The sawed off the top of my head
Is that
It's really mess that's in charge of everything that's going on with the nest because it's their API that gets used in the
Words for death program
And I can't imagine that
Non Nest devices
Call go take control of a nest and make changes
Ness would take information maybe
And perhaps do something but
I'm not following
The thought process here from The Nest box
So I talked to a lot of developers about working with
And
Most of them say
When they choose to work with Nest or some of them say they've chosen not to work
With nest because it's one of the companies out there with the most restrictive partnership program
So
It doesn't allow companies to take data from
Nest
It doesn't allow companies to really
Interact with the nest API you can only
Give Nest information
You can't really take in
Information from
Has been
I really should be I think, I have no problem with that
So
Kind of makes me question
How old am IQ
Which
Can tell the way the MyQ setting works right now
With my garage door opener
Is
It can tell the it based on me
You know opening and closing the garage door it tells the nest if I'm home or away
Now at 4 in the morning on
The weekends or
Saturday in this
I'm not actually opening or closing
My garage door
It doesn't actually mean any
Cuz buggy software
True it could be that my cue software is sending off a trigger event that you didn't actually do
Possible
But
My understanding of how these things
It's work is that it would just be saying
Hadoop
The garage door opened
Stacy Lattisaw
You could go to a wedding
And then ask it's to say
All right what do I want to do with that
In this case the nest is saying
How can I turn the
All the way up
Will you know it is winter time and maybe thinks you left the garage door open I don't know
Letter fry
So
I still have my face on because
Something is not jiving
Compared to the bottom of it but
Again
You provide apis so that way you have control over things
And
Unless
Somebody's using a nest API in a way that Ness has
Planned for I'm just not seeing it
Chamberlain is going to get back to
Hopefully we'll get back
Hopefully
This weekend I will not be roasted out of my bed
5 -
Yeah I have to say I have a question because a couple people did respond or tweet saying they are having similar problems with their nest
Did any of them say they have any other devices I'm just curious
Who is experiencing the same problem and they don't have a mic
That changes things
I'm so I was going to say guys who are listening who have a nest thermostat
Email me info at iot podcast
Do you have an S
Are you having a similar issue
Do you have other works with nest
Problems
Because
This kind of seems
Something
There's a bear there
There is I am trying to recall I don't think it's all that long ago when a firmware update we're not to the mess I'm not trying to pin pointer pointer
Fingers here I'm not saying that's what it is
I'm just trying to
Consider all the potential
Potential root causes here
It wasn't that long ago
Have you been how long have you been having this problem just out of curiosity
So winter in Texas
Is
Not really
Devastating so I don't think we turned on or heater until sometime towards the end of October
So not until
Not until we turned on our heater
So yes
Whatever that happen
You know
Again this is one of those things where
You know the nest is
One it's irritating
This is costing me money because
It's expensive and it happens you know once maybe twice a week but
Running your thermostat up to 76 degrees in the middle of winter is
And when you're asleep you don't actually notice until it starts getting
Real hot
And
Waking up my kid
Not fun
Triggering a migraine
Really not
I'll be curious to see what the end result is assuming wanted
When is found
Ultimately I say that again I'm not trying to point fingers
But the way this whole platform is set up
Nest has to own the works with Nest program
Ivory
I want to hear back
I want to understand
And
At the end of the day this has to be something that Nest solves
For not just me
Imagine you know people don't have your contacts in this industry Avenue been able to reach out to a bunch of companies here
But yeah Joe Schmo off the street
Just going to sit there and scratches head contact Nest support and
Things get workout
And a lot of people are like well I'm going to buy a
I'm going to buy an ecobee
We'll talk about that in a second but you know spending $250 on a thermostat
Then having to rip it out of the wall by another connected thermostat or just
Staying screwing
Got the answer
That's a really crappy
Decision
Speaking of the ecobee
Yeah
Kevin you want to talk about what
Well
I don't because it's more bad news but I will now this is not a problem that you are I have had I do not have actually
Abaniko pig11 s
Which is working fine
For the record
But apparently Reddit a few days ago somebody posted at their ecobee3 remote sensor was
Wasn't detecting occupancy
So
They reached out to ecobee support
And I hope you're sitting down folks
Ecobee Support Center
Take one of the sensors apart and see if the motion sensor which is a small circular pillar with a little plate
Kinda like a solar panel
To see that it's a line properly with the little window on the front
It turns out it wasn't
So is person check his other two sensors and they were on wrong as well
All three are fixed so that's the good news
And the information is out there publicly available to the other two
Search for this type of problem we're on ecobee3 is not detecting occupancy
You just learned that hey if you kind of take this little bit of part and you can rely on the sensor of your okay
Not great but you know what
At least it's an easy fix it's something that once you have the information you know you have you how to fix it and can fix it
So good on ecobee to actually say
Hey you know what we think this might be the problem can you check it out and sure enough it was
So there you go and you know
Ecobee3 is actually
When is the product
I have an ecobee SI downstairs
I really like my ecobee I'd love to get an ecobee3 but I can't really justify spending $750 on 3rd
Thermostats in my house
Gwine to run all night
Well yeah
Well
If I if I do give up the nest this is
The ecobee3 is actually the
Thermostat for me
Although I will have to check my okapi
Okay moving right along
Guess
What
Everyone
Good news
Good news what
Flextronics
Has closed its acquisition of the wink
Home
Hub
Yay well well well wait before I cheer as a as a wink Hub owner
Why is it's good news
This is good news
Because
The deal is done and be I talked to the head of consumer products
The consumer products division at Flextronics
Aunt
They are continuing
The wing product line
Yeah I know I can cheer
So you guys everybody was
Has a wink
Know that the wink investment
It's going to continue I ask him about the product roadmap they're not ready to talk about that until after
Because
They just closed
Well they just closed it at the Consumer Electronics Show is all kinds of other competing products with my give them some good ideas and
I'm at
But yes
So this is this is good news for everybody wink is actually hiring
So you know if you've got some
Crazy mad
Iot skills
You don't hey
, anyway so
Nice
The good news out of this is
The wink is planning to continue
Its investment in
Both
Help desk functions adding
Devices
Also
By having flex and I keep calling at Flextronics so if you hear that please
Mentally correct it to flask
Because Flex
Tronix became Flex earlier this year
And I know I've covered Flex 4
Like over a decade
And vibrates just knock
Flexes I used to be just a contract manufacturer and now they're like all designed to
Scale so basically they help you build
Now they help you build products
From start to finish if you're a startup or if you're like
Nokia
So this
Changes my potential purchase plans because I was going to buy a SmartThings
House anthem
So
I've been playing with SmartThings for a while and I hate to do this but SmartThings is turned into an 80%
Isn't it only works 80%
But we the same even more money
So
Just
Unless you're cool with it being 84
No
Okay cuz wink is week is actually becoming more reliable for
SmartThings there still a lot of things I don't like about
The new SmartThings is really only about eighty per
You know I think a lot of it will also be dictated by what devices are actually connecting to the hub
You got a ton of different things a whole range of devices
Add sensors and so on
I only have the nest
And a whole bunch of
Lights from different companies smart like I don't have any
Door locks or
Other connected appliances and and so on
Kevin will
I do.
Who put the batteries in and I got it you know locking and unlocking in my
But I did not replace it on my front door because we start using the front door that mounts or no
I can't believe it
Sorry
Suicide I do think that may have something to do with you know some of the Hub issues you seen with link that I
Haven't seen
I don't know
Yeah
I take the range of stuff
Lights are a premature lights
You got
Motion sensors in your house you've got the warlocks you've got
Garage door opener right now
You can you have a wider breadth of products
10 interesting theories so maybe like the more stuff you have on these things the more likely they are to break
Which is kind of bad news
It would be that would that would be
Bad news for the
Smart Home in dust
That was bad
So
I don't know what to say there
For the weak people
Good news
So
And if you're like me and you're running
Two hubs
Both wink and SmartThings
Because I do have a lot of the sensors that I've never enjoyed adding by traditional zigbee kind of sensors
Zigbee and Z-Wave sensors to the wink platform because I don't like
I haven't really enjoyed the
Weights supports the zigbee and Z-Wave
Profiles for devices that it doesn't actually have in its files
Striving more generic type profiles I guess they use
And I don't
I didn't want to invest in the
Branded sensors
My thought is I could
Double up with the Amazon Echo is the controlling device for all of those things but I haven't seen the sensors under the
Geico yet
Skip
So maybe it will
I was trying to go to the whole podcast without meds
Oh
We were so close
That's okay. We have to talk about really briefly anyway because last week I had said I would heard of Fire TV
That's right so talk about your fired
Yes it won't take long cuz everything I said last week
Is pretty much spot-on what I thought it would do it does really really well
It's
I have a downstairs can I go to a TV obviously it's Fire TV
And I have the voice remote with it
My echo is actually in my
Second floor home office where I am now
But it's like having a another echo in the room downstairs maybe cuz you just hold the voice button do you sell your commands and
It's good to go
And as I had said on on the show last week
A lot of the informational bits that the echo will provide you
It reads them aloud
Also put some up on the display the screen I've been on
Make a 60-inch TV that got these ginormous cards
Information when I do a web search
Russia War get the weather or play
Amazon Prime music whatever it is it's all right there visually
It is a beautiful thing I did say something last week that I want to correct
I'd said to you Stacey that I'll bet you the
Amazon Echo remote
The Bluetooth remote is the same as the one that comes with the Fire TV it is not
And that's because there's some additional buttons on the Fire TV remote for playback of
Media which is really what the Fire TV is for
However did the integration between the Echo and the Fire TV is outstanding
Absolutely love it
Sitting in the room watching TV just press the button and tell
She Who Shall Not Be Named to
You know turn the lights down so I can watch TV and it doesn't it's a
Wonderful
That sounds awesome
I was
It was the same do you leave your TV on more now
No I mean there's a lot of
Similar devices like Google Chromecast
Can they have something called letting its whole backdrop where there is a
A screensaver
Android information like a local weather that will cycle through if you want to leave your TV on but I'm not big into wasting the energy you know I'm in
I really try and conserve cuz we're
Generating
Electricity with solar panels I don't want to
Now I'm just
You going to let me know
True
How's your solar panel
Wonderful we've been thinking a lot of energy this year it's
It's a year-to-year basis May through May is is
What my electric company
Measures
And I haven't any balance like an overproduced
I get a check from them in May
But basically I had almost a full month's worth of electricity
Cortical in the bank with them last month
Used about a third of it this month because it's been
Shorter Days Inn
Not so great weather and so on but
No I knew we haven't had an electric bill when I at least 10 months so it's it's a wonderful time
Sounds awesome
All right
Well let's see
I wanted to take us into a little bit more of
Part of the Industrial
It's not industrial that's not the word I'm looking for
The kind of corporate Enterprise
Best thing because
This is a topic that I've been thinking about because
As we kind of gear into the holiday season and into the Consumer Electronics Show
I've been thinking about how
Who is buying the Smart Home
Home and if they really should
Give in my feelings about
Hubs
My Nest recently
I've been kind of like down
Average consumers probably should not be buying a lot of things
They're kind of not worth it
I mean
You didn't you know how I've been kind of
I love I love this stuff
For most people it's
They're not going to get a lot of pleasure and they're probably going to be like
I was just going to say the bang for buck
Or value
Aspect of it is still
Not quite right I think for
Massive mainstream adopt
It's getting better but
It's not there yet
So I've been thinking
In the last couple of months like
If it's not the consumer who is going to buy this where is the market
Where's the money where's the money
I figured it out
Okay
Kiss why not
Why not make grandiose
Interrupting
This is actually what I do while I'm so
I think about
I dream about it
Insurance companies
And comedies like ATT so insurance and security
These are the people
And I Enterprises that are going to be buying the smart
For you
And I actually got some great data on
I'd love to kind of share with people just to bolster so you don't think I'm totally crazy
So here at this is from Accenture they're putting that they put this report out this week
And I actually got date on
Is so most insurance company
I have already started with some pilot project
So
American family has
Is a pilot project with
Ring
Connected doorbell company and they also have one where they subsidize a nest protect
Smoke detector
So nearly 4 and 10 ensures of piloted or launch the connected home or building offering
So far this year
Which is pretty freaking
Has more than tripled from
And
Last year only a minority had any iot
Plants related to Iowa
Or any iot
Plants related to the home
So
That's what
And then nearly half of insurers believe that connected devices will be a driver of Revenue growth in
In the next 3 years
So that's kind of a lot to think about but I'd love to unpack that
Because
I think this could be
Really scary
For consumers if you look at it like if we don't have like regulations or I could wait at 10
Think about this
But I also think it could be really awesome because it's a really good way to get this kind of
Stuff in people's homes
And probably a good way to get
The good stuff like the tested stuff in
So
On the positive side
The program that American family is doing with the nest protect is
All they want to do is I want to see
Hey
Are the batteries in your smoke.
Because if they are
You're way more likely to be notified if
There's a fire in your house and
Rachel true
That's awesome
Like everybody can agree
That right and that's how a lot of these are
With the connected doorbell camera
It's a little bit different but they're looking for
Burglaries cuz he seems have actually been shown to help prevent burglaries because you can
Pretend like you're home
Even if they realize you're not home
Do you actually get
Footage from
Who's robbing your house
Which Canadian
Catching the thief chair
Yay
Bad example in the dryer when you get these are both
But I called bigger bang for buck things people understand
The value that way
As opposed to seeing a bunch of products on a Shelf
Worden cap somewhere
Well this is cool though
What do I really get from it
You know any insurer in this cases are subsidizing
Sometimes fully sometimes
So a lot of people are like
Yay
Other insurers are like USAA testing
OBD port
Isis like automatic
And so
Let's talk about like
How do you feel about
Where does this become
Scary for you
Well you know what
Me personally I'm on more the do-it-yourself let me figure it out let me figure out what I want and what I want to do with it kind of person so
So
There's that side to it but as I look at the at the market as a whole
Your mainstream
Sumer
I'm not scared of anything about it I think it's a good way to
Expand and broaden people's awareness these products
Search the ones that will add the most value to them
As opposed to again like I said
Here's a catalog of things
I'll pick some in and make your home smart
Why
What am I doing this for you know
There's a tangible benefit to doing that unless you can figure it out yourself
So I don't have any major issues with it from of privacy standpoint again I'm okay with
My insurance company knows if I have
Batteries in my
Smoke detector
Especially if they're going to eat me and maybe give me a discount on my
Insurance because of it
Help me in and helps them it's that it's safer for everybody around so
I don't really have any issues there either
I'm trying to think of it I have any privacy concerns with these
What about if your insurance firm starts penalizing
Don't happen
Well yeah that's
Obviously that's the other side of the coin
I mean when I guess you could argue that by not by offering the
Discount
Yeah it says they are right there penalizing people switch
The thing is
Obviously not everybody can afford nor made me not want these things and they're not mandatory for safety
Smoke detectors in SIDS they are but
It has to be a specific kind of smart smoke detector not necessarily
Sorry we have a problem if they did actually
Penalize me
For not having yeah I know I'm just thinking about the
Discus
Like the other issue is
Once you start adding connectivity into homes
You're going to start changing the risk profile
Across-the-board
Write like the risk will go down significantly
In a home that has
Connected smoke detectors because
That's my assumption
Or like a
A moisture sensor
For example
That's the thinking I will say that I've had several leaks in my home
And none of them have actually occurred
Place where there is a moisture sensor there
Qdoba in the places where you know
Your refrigerator clothes on your hot water heater overflows
Switch I understand does happen
Puppy crate
So there's kind of like how much will that change service profile does that drive down the cost of insurance everywhere
How does those costs get spread around the
Industry
How are those savings get spread around the industry
Everyone's premiums go down I don't know
And I also think about Lake
When we start having
Can conversations about risk and privacy
Are regulatory bodies events
Ready to start
Having this
Conversations cuz right now I'm not sure if they are
I would say it's premature to have this conversation so I don't think so bad if there's so many other more pressing issues to be
Dealing with
Areas to regulate
What makes sense to regulate areas to not regulate
So I agree with you on that one
And then finally let's see how I should also mention State Farm is launching a program where they are
Giving out
Canaries
So Canary is an all-in-one security device they're giving it out to First Responders
And
I thought that was pretty cool
I was also thinking though
Canary has gotten in the news a couple times because people break in and they get camera footage of it
Youku
Satan call the police
Police are not
Always
Excited to be like
Oh here's the footage of this person breaking in
Especially if maybe in major cities were there like
But you know what we got like eight murders we've got to solve
And this is not becomes noise at a certain point I'm not trying to say something is more important than the other thing
Pet from Power Station Sandpoint for
Does resources it becomes noise
So I think
There's kind of an interesting
Sunset Lake
Hey now that we have these kind of
Resources available to us
How will that change things
Lion Force
I don't know big questions what's good question
If you have answers
You guys should tell
Because
I don't know I'm just
It's okay to be Minority Report Sunday don't worry
No no no no that's the worst
Let us all not turn into a
That would be
Or anything starring
She went there
Okay alright alright Maverick I'll let you go on that one
Okay so stay tuned because we have kind of a new feature
That I'm not sure we're going to keep it up but you know
I had my husband on
To review the haiku
I don't even know what to call this device it's so new but kind of cool it's the connected
Speaker magnet
Grocery list
Making thing
You'll just have to listen to discover what it does
It's basically you talk into it and it collects your grocery list it's connected you can scan stuff into it it's
It's pretty cool
Because I don't grocery shop I had him review it
Any idea is that
There's a lot of things
Kevin and I
Don't need or use
Sparetime sprinklers are one of them
Probably
Aging-in-place kind of devices are probably another thing
And
I'm kind of thinking we should probably talk to people who actually purchased these devices in her living with him
Kind of start conducting some reviews because
Nobody knows how connected devices going to do until you actually use it
So with that in mind stay tuned and you can learn more about the haiku
Hey everyone
We're back with the Internet of Things podcast
Instead of a guest this week we're going to do something a little bit new little bit different
And maybe something that if
If you guys like it will do in the future
So
I had a chance
To review a gadget called the Haiku but since
And it is a
It's a magnet we've had the CEO of the
Device on
The podcast before
It is a magnet that you attach to your fridge
And
You talk into it and you can
Get your grocery list
Do you tell your grocery list and if you're in the right area
You actually can send this grocery list to Walmart
Or to Peapod and
Neither
Delivery Peapod will deliver your groceries or Walmart
Well actually
Some of your groceries and you pick them up at curbside delivery
Since I don't grocery shop for my family I didn't really I make a very terrible reviewer for this
So I asked my husband who does do the grocery shopping for our family to review
So
Andrew hi Andrew
It's yellow
Yes
And what I'd like to say is if this
Is something you guys like
There a lot of gadgets that
I don't actually get a chance to review because I don't have like the facilities of perfect
Example is
Lawn sprinklers
Because I
Actually is there Escape
I don't need to water it
Are you guys really want to know about connected lawn sprinklers
So
Email me if you have
You know a rachio or droplet or I guess the Green Wave system and maybe we'll start doing more
Kind of user reviews because
Really the best way to
Know if you want one of these it's to live with it for a long time and porch
So info at iot podcast
Animals
This is something we want to
And now
Andrew
You have the haiku
Which is a 49
$99 device
What was your take on this
Yeah so you know you described it as a magnet it's really like
Got a tiny voice recognizer and
Barcode Scanner and one and it sticks to the side of your fridge
From a magnet
And I'll say that I came from this
I'm one of those people
I do the grocery shopping
For the family
And I usually write my list on in a
Paper and bring it to the store I'm not one of those people that keeps a list in the iPhone so I knew this was going to be a big
Adjustment going in
In my experience might be a little bit different from someone who always keeps our list
On your iPhone so
First of all the scanning feature of it where you can scan barcode is kind of a dick
To set it up
It took maybe a minute to set up
Basically just
Downloaded the app on the iPhone went through some setup instructions and was all set up
Should I was super simple in any kind of you start
Using the scanner on
NASA shoots out kind of a red typical kind of barcode scanner
And it's kind of fun right cuz you pick up products in
And you scan it and it's a little bit of Dick thing I know I'm kind of weird that way
But I really like that the scanning feature and then what it does when you scan it basically sends the product
Name
To your iPhone app to a list there so that was pretty neat
And I should know that Andrew is
Is a little weird
Which is why
But also this is something that
Work not just for the iPhone but this also works for
Yes yes it does work with Android as well
The basic idea here is you are trying to capture your grocery list right and in my case it was to bring it to the garage
Grocery store not to use
Peapod
Or at WalMart delivery
There two ways to get something onto list when is the scan the barcode
Any other is
Talking to it
And so from a skin perspective I'd say
80% of the things I scanned
Or in the database
The majority of ones weren't
That weren't restore brands from the dominant grocer here in Texas
HEB
So that was a little frustrating that
A lot of those store brands weren't in there
When you scan a barcode it gives you
Sound feedback saying whether or not it found the product or not
Sometimes National products a couple of them I couldn't get to work at all and sometimes just scanning the
Barcode
Had to try it a few times two
To get it just right but
Over always pretty happy with
With the scanning feature
The voice recognition
It left a little bit to be desired
And the issue here is not whether or not a recognized you it's whether it recognizes you correct
So I'd say
Again maybe 80% of the time I'd say something into it like
Pomegranate
Macaroni and cheese and it would get a perf
I do it add it to the list and it adds it to the section of the list you know dairy or produce
It made sense
Other times I would say something in it and recognize something else
And put it on the list in this
Came a little bit of a challenge
Because I had to double-check I almost had to open up the iPhone app after I would say something into
The Haiku just to make sure I got the right thing
Is otherwise I'll be scratching my head at the end of the week when I'm looking at my listing it
You know says to buy marshmallows why did I put marshmallows on the listing and really I meant something else
So from a convenience factor
Hey this is just on side of the fridge
And I can talk into it
And it'll added to my list that's great but at least in a couple weeks I tried it I wasn't a hundred percent comfortable that way
Capturing the right information
Okay so the question is
Would you buy this
450 bucks
Is it worth it
I would not
Because I'm not the type of person who
Keeps a list on my iPhone I think if I
Kept the grocery list on my phone my Android or iPhone
Then I think this would be worth
Working with
But for me it was kind of frustrating in the store having to unlock my phone several times to see
To see what was on the list
One cool thing I did like
Compared to the old paper
List
Is it you can swipe off items after
Do you get them
And so that way you don't have those two things on your list that you overlooked you get home and your wife is upset with you. That's
Never happened to me I like that that feature as well
Okay
And
Another thing if you
What do the pickup
Would that change like
They're rolling his pickup out
Lacrosse
Hopefully
The country
So we have a Walmart actually fire daughter
School so
Would that change
Equation
Give me what I buy groceries at Walmart or what I get to hike
Would you get the haiku
Note to the Walmart but so yeah I think that changes a lot right
For a couple reasons one you have to enter your order electronically anyway so this is a lot
Easier way to enter an electronic order
Then typing it in a searching for each product
Too I think the accuracy would be a lot better the product you're getting I mean when you
I scan a bottle of Heinz Ketchup
It doesn't just say ketchup
Anna haikyuu it says you know 18 hour times you know it's got the barcode so you're going to get that product
I mean it's delivered so
I think that makes it a lot more interesting you'd still want to review the list
Before you submit it
Or your delivery or pickup
Because
Especially if you use the voice prompts what you will
Then you're going to be an especially for produce and things without a barcode
You just want to make sure that it got the right thing so you don't get strange things in your order
While missing other important things I know you would love to get it
Extra bag of March
Just don't lie
I do so that's actually something I've
Telesto marshmallows what is good idea Haiku thank you
Like I said I got a little carried away with it let me scan notice it was all for testing purposes though
Offer testing
Excellent
Awesome well thank you so much
Andrew
I appreciate you
Sitting there
And doing other testing and
All the grocery shopping
I think that is spit is really awesome of you
So
Haiku
If you like making grocery list
In your iPhone
Or Android
This is good at the other feature I should actually
If we both actually stopped at the grocery store and regular basis
You can actually share your list across phones
Which makes this kind of a nice to be sure because
Somebody who's out can actually say oh hey we're out of milk according to the Haiku I'll just stop in and get it
Which if you're the kind of people who actually
Shirtless this could also be a good cutting gadget for y'all
We don't do that because I just
Leave the house because I work
Work from home
So
Like it's true guys
It is
All right
Well thank you so much
For doing the gadget review
Remember you guys at this
This is something you like let me know
And also you can start volunteering for things I am actively searching for people who have Kinect
Kid sprinklers
So
You do have to purchase it with your own money and have lived with it and I will that these things
So info at iot podcast. Com
Dicks
Thanks for listening to the iot podcast will see you next week