Hey everyone welcome back
The Internet of Things podcast
Ice with your hoes
Stacey Higginbotham
Cohoes
Kevin tofel
I don't actually know why I guess I'm also a co-host if you're my host Kevin
Right
I don't know I don't know
It works either way regardless of who's hosting
We're on iTunes.
You stole my thunder
OK congratulation
Yes we are on iTunes now at the Internet of Things
Podcast
We have a lovely blue logo that you guys are familiar with if you
Grab this podcast on the website
I'm so
Go put your RSS feeders the right way
Or your
Your aunt oddcast a pin
On your iOS device or whatever you use
However you get to
Now you can get to it on ice
All right
So on to the meat of the show
We will not spend the whole
Nothing celebrating
Scuba Stars
We did that before the show for an hour
Also unfortunately
I probably won't
All right
Will start the show with
Let's see let's start the show is shopping because
It's so fun
Everybody loves a shot
Send the shopping front
Connected devices is Target
The day after Memorial Day
May 26th
We shall see in Target stores
A new
Home automation Center
I we know actually that it will host a
Piper home all-in-one home security system but we don't know what else is going to be in there
8 feet of shelf Space 2
Other home automation products
That is very good because that is a sign of a further sign I guess I should say of the home automation
Smart home sector going more mainstream
Do you want to do
Cooler Simon is going mainstream I picked up a market
Stewart Living
And you know what was in it
Was like eight devices that will
Save you money and make your home smarter and it was like the August locks
There's a Dropcam
There they were
I didn't recognize the thermostat they had chosen
But
There were several devices that we talked about on the show and I was like
Go Martha
I'm guessing she didn't have August locks where she was before she came back out of
Wonder Man
Do not talk to not speak ill of Martha
Don't don't the backtalk don't sass the most but do not
August lock when she was in prison August was
Interjet
I know I know
Now has an
Home automation section
I will say
As someone who visits the home automation section in her local Staples
And
Home Depot a lot
I'm going to hope
That
Target keeps there's a little bit better stock
Dehumanization section in my Home Depot is
Constantly
Picked over and
A lot of the time it's an incap and it mostly has the wink products and then
The Nest stuff in the rest of stuff is kind of spread throughout the store I find
And I've been in my Staples and I've looked around and
You know it looks like they have
The right idea with the hole
Cluster of smart home stuff but
It just
Doesn't it just kind of feel like it's tucked in a corner to me all the time and yes it's a little
In disarray when everytime I go as well so like I don't quite understand that but
I was hoping it was Staples has the stuff
Actually hooked into like a
I'm trying to think of the words
There's a demo area kind of like so you can press buttons and make lights go on and what not I was the one wanted that I visit
So that's that's actually nice Home Depot doesn't seem to have a lot of Education
So
And I haven't actually been to Best Buy
In Forever
So I have to go check out Best Buy
This in Target's wants it stopped
Report back on who has the best
Retail experience for the smartphone
That's a good idea you guys can also tell us
Your thoughts at info
Iot podcast. Com
All right moving to our next order of
News
Let's talk about
Collector cars Kevin
Oh yeah there's a sexy topic for you because
It is interesting most of the of the gross now for the carrier's is not coming from smartphones because hey pretty much everybody
We have one in the US
Tablets that are actually the big
Addition I guess when you look at net subscribers and left in the first quarter of the year and we have some data for
Good buddy Chetan Sharma you just had his quarterly
Us mobile market
Date
I came out
And some interesting bits that
Came out
To my eyes were that machine-to-machine
Connections and car connections
Accounted for 39% of the total net additions for all the carriers
And who's the leader here it looks like it's AT&T which
Probably not a surprise if people have read our past coverage
Over the years of
M2M stuff with
AT&T connected car business will be a billion dollar
Revenue generator this year says chatting
And
That's pretty impressive attack
Out of the 1.2 million Wireless net additions in the first three months of this year
Were cars
Which was 62% of their total net add so
That's a big deal I mean a billion dollar
Revenue generator right there
Yes and that was a lot of numbers right there
That's a billion dollars out of
The whole cell phone industry or AT&T is total
Do you have AT&T is total
Revenue for the quarter
Or for the year
I don't have it for the year
I do not have it for the years I don't know what percentage of This Is Us
I was looking at it more along the lines of
You don't currently it's if the biggest cruise driver and their net additions
It is certainly big
I'm not going to say
AT&T has clients like Tesla
So
I would buy a Tesla
Although I will say
Having I am kind of shopping around for a new car
And actually just last week
Boa
Obama administration or rather
The department of
Asportation actually
Fast Track
The vehicle to vehicle
Wireless communication
Which is
It's it's in the
Wi-Fi band
Turn the upper levels to Wi-Fi Beyond
And it's basically a wireless communication protocol
It's going to let cars
Talk to each other
And basically the idea is they'll be able to say like
I'm here I'm here
Don't hit me don't hit me
And ideas
They're going to mandate this
Come into vehicles
Starting in 2017
And then
Delta start adding it into vehicles
It's going to be awhile before that is
Real
So there's car-to-car talking so that's Vita V is what they're calling it
There's vehicle-to-infrastructure
And that's like
Cars talking
Signs
Toll booth
Some cells
That'll dovetails with the autonomous cars though that's
Way down the line
I think it in terms of mainstream
But in the meantime there's a nice stepping stone to get the car's a little bit smarter so that
When one of them that's three cars ahead of you suddenly breaks
The cars behind it already know even if the driver can't see that
Gdb
It actually Dia caddies
The caddy CTS with a fancy high and Cadillacs will actually have Vita vea
In those cars
Start in 2017
Sober as a
Person who right now in
In 2015 and maybe the 2016 models is looking at cars
I'm looking at all this technology
Even even LTE and trying to look at like what kind of car tag is going to be there
I'm like holy cow maybe I should start leasing my vehicle cuz
My Korean car
Which element guys I bought it in 2005 doesn't even have Bluetooth
And I've had it for 10 years now
I'm like Oh my goodness
If I keep my next car that I buy you know in 2016 for 10 years
Be like a dinosaur
All the other cars are going to be talking at talking about it behind its back
Bluetooth that's like so 2006 I mean come on
We're talking about car to car WiFi
So just think about that I am curious and I'll let you guys know is
This journey for a new car Progressive
But the wireless tech
In the car connectivity
Even even talking to you
Getting getting my wireless access
It's kind of complicated
I'm leaving bye
That's a good question. Cuz and it's funny because I release on the 2013 Chevy Volt actually runs out in October
Uber so we're going to be looking at something
And chances are really look at
2016 volt
With the new
I can look at a tattoo
It's new it's new
Redesigned
Has a fake V seat in the back but that's not going to go there right now, but more importantly
More battery range and so on and
Eric nicely with our solar panels on the roof I just don't
Know if they have
4G LTE Connections in there I think
General Motors has been pretty hot and heavy on that though
They have I am
I'm pretty sure it does
I get it I don't know I don't know if I want another bill
That that is
Yeah
All right so we will discuss that I'm sure in the future
In the meantime
Let's talk about
This crazy dude this is more businesstech but we're going to talk about how
It might apply to
Consumer home
Which is
Honeywell
Command wall
I think this is
I think this is like really cool but I also think this is overkill
And so
What this is
Honeywell on Tuesday
Announced a
Who called they call it this man while I look at is like the touchscreen that's in Minority Report or any other science fiction
The movie where you get the characters and they're facing this giant
Screen in there just like
Blinking data left and right in the funny video screen and things are popping up
It's amazing
That is exactly what the
And the cool thing about it is
It's infinitely customizable and you pull in
Data it's design for commercial buildings
They got it customers right now who are trying it include
Landmark skyscrapers
Data centers Airport
Hospitals
These customers are integrating
Bear
Access control so there sit there security systems
There
Video camera feed
Basic HVAC stuff to
Yes sensor data HVAC
Employee records in there other like
Their own customer files in their also bringing in outside data like Google Maps data or
Files they might get from like law enforcement or
Publicly available Act
They're pulling it all this data to create basically their own Dash
And
Kind of amazing
To see it now
It it actually isn't surprising that is coming from Honeywell
For one because I wouldn't call them a cutting-edge it type company
I watch the video maybe we can link to in the show notes
It's really neat because all of these different smart devices and door sensors and such
You just tap on them like say you tap on an icon of a video camera and boom the feed just pops up right there
There's all these little touch points in and information flowing all over the place here in
Yo I remember working in it and data centers for almost 15 years before I started writing and
You know I had a dashboard that may help me manage servers and routers and such but this is like
A hundred times beyond that I'm in this is this is just
Out there it looks really nice
And it's worth noting that Honeywell will work
It will work with Honeywell sensors but it'll also work with Honeywell competitors and
As for
The date of its pulling in it pulls it in VA
Barry's apis and it
Attempts to pull it in
Like from other data formats
It's crazy that it's coming from
Building management kind of
Bender
I'm as opposed to an IT company but maybe that's because
These guys don't have skin in the game
But I would love to see something like this
In my house
Best Buy sells a home hub system called the peak
And it has it actually
Similar user interface that can show you
Kind of what's happening in your home and they have a
Partnership with zube
Which is
A device you can stick in your
Cars
Diagnostics port
And that
Will show you where someone's car is in real time so if you have a teenage driver for example
You can see their car
From the dashboard
The peak
Witches
It's kind of this idea
Really cool if you could throw that up on kind of like your TV screen or just like a dedicated screen
In your house
Instead of having to go through the peak dashboard
And then maybe you could combine it with your Evernote shopping list or
You know any other system
Yeah I mean this is this is like a dashboard too. Oh and this is this is impressive
I've kind of really really excited
But maybe that's just
Me and my desire My Desire for customizable dashboards I'm surprised I'm really am I'm really surprised that we don't have something
It's already
It's kind of sad for
Well yummy when you see it it's like
It's like common sense I mean through all these things together get them talking to each other
Get the Data Vault easily touchable and viewable and everything else
Tok why is anybody else doing this
There is an app called numerous it's actually iOS only
And they
They pulling any
Number related data
And they throw it up on a tablet
Kind of Anna dashboard
So that's
Sort of like
That and I think they have some sort of
Watch integration
But
Again
Not nearly
Is open
Or
Seemingly is flexible
I have not played with this
I do not own it landmarks guys can a hospital or an airport
But
I would really like to
Will work on that will do a Kickstarter for you
Stacey would like to own an air
Honeywell Command Center
That's maybe I should just call Honeywell and see if I can get one
Maybe I haven't made it to let you take over somebody else's sky scraper for a day
Salad nicoise
Rent a building
There we go
All right
Are we ready for our Innovative Lee named
Segment
New segment
What's it called
It's the
5-minute review
Oh I like your
You do what you do are sounded
All right
Kevin I
You've got our
Review of the week
I do it's it's actually a
Website and online database
As it were of
Smart Home Products and super useful
If you want to see it you want to go to smart home db.com
When you go there you'll see this
Online database of various
Home Smart Home components
Hubs
Product reviews
If there's all kinds of views
Citizens online database
They slice and dice is information anyway you want it so
Do you want to see what's compatible with
IOS or Android you can just click the compatibilities tab
Start picking up products and we'll tell you what works with your ear
Smartphone operating system for example
I'm thirsty does the same thing with apps with companies and just products in general that are related to Smart Homes
Also nice is
Product reviews by people who actually have bought these products
So we know you can take a look and see the Philips Hue Bridge has 4 and 1/4 Stars
I-25 and 103 people have reviewed it
If you want to see the compatibilities you can just click the little
NYX palette
Compatibilities works with graph
Clip app for any product which I just did for the Phillips
Hub
And now I've got this ginormous graph of all these different products that work with it from
Quirky and Staples and Phillips will of course cuz Phillips mix The Hub
Nest Lutron Belkin
So you can see before you actually buy Smart Home Products
You can actually kind of plan out
A little bit better I think
Because everything is right here
Easy what's compatible with what what products work with witch
Which have been highly rated which have been highly rated
There's prices for all of us
I'm so it said it's a
Really nice simple way of finding more information about your smartphone before you actually
Invest in your smart home is that make sense
It does
Although I wouldn't say that was a five-minute
I would also I would add that there is a
There's a section on
Cloud Server versus
Yes and no for those of you guys who hate sending your data to the cloud
This is actually kind of a nice little
Segment cuz I know there's a small
Or maybe it's a growing my majority I don't
What's a small minority actually
It might be growing
Keep their data on premise
And for those of you this actually gives you
The Limited number of products
And
Yeah so that way you can see if it's the Standalone product or it's based in
You know the cloud and you sharing data
Sew in
Kevin found this but I will say that actually this is been shared with me by like
Two or three people so
Thank you guys for sharing this with us
And
It is has a instruction set so
It's
It's really just a nice
It's a very nice
Kind of databases
Product to look at so
Check it out I will include it in the show notes for you
And
Hopefully you guys can spend hours
You can get lost in this thing
You can and you can spend probably a lot of money after getting lost
And
Lord help you
So I think that's it for us this week
And stay tuned because we have an awesome guest we have robbed
Coneybeare
And he is a partner at Shasta Ventures and we are talking about what devices will become
Connected and smart in which will stay decisively analog
Hey everybody we are back with the Internet of Things podcast and I have
A wonderful guest for us today it is Rob conybeare
Who is a managing director and co-founder at Shasta Ventures
To be here with you thanks for having me
I am so excited so I asked you on the show a couple weeks ago because you wrote
How do you say it's an amazing blog post
Switch
Might sound a little was called what will stay defiantly analog
Login in it you kind of analyzed
Basically what products are going to be connected and how those
Look
And your three categories were do you remember them or do you want me to break it down for
We can go back through them but I'm happy to walkthrough am right now
3 word products it'll disappear in the digital age so if you think of newspapers
Stand-alone cameras
And at the other end of the spectrum of products that remain defiantly analog and that would be things like writing instruments and
Notebooks and you can see how many people still buy Moleskine
Notebooks today
It is between it's hard to say
There's a number of product selection literally but he'll become connected and evolved over time into
New category
To me the most exciting I I took issue with some of your things
You have some thoughts about the kitchen we're going to talk about
I I really wanted to kind of think about the things that become connected in a Volvo
Time which is where I imagine you're probably making a lot of your bets
What is a venture capitalist
Is that a fair assumption
That's absolutely true
So in this category
I think of it as a spectrum there's obviously
Right now I feel like we're adding intelligence
Products
That
Kind of on a one-off basis so
I'm thinking about things like my nest
Stir like my Philips Hue Lights.
Act alone
They provide some sort of value or energy
Payment
And then when I look in the future I start thinking like you mentioned that connected chairs
And I feel like those things
Probably gain more value
When they become part of an ecosystem
And I'm really excited about that but I'd be curious how do you kind of
See that
Evolution
Products
I think initially
And for the next five maybe even 10 years you'll see silos continue to be the main way in which we see can
Divisive
I think part of it is because people tend to think
That way
So
Right here in Silicon Valley you might get excited about the idea of cuz your thermostat talk to your son assistant talk to your garage
Talk to your coffee maker
But I think the reality is
It's the silence
People really care about it
I like to have music in my house
What I like to have a thermostat the program
And I think a lot of the other scenarios have drawbacks did
People don't really think through
And the reasons that you haven't seen
Companies that have been focused on building these ecosystems that you're referring to
And what are some of these drawbacks
But I can think of is a user
The hours I spend making things
Connected work together
There is probably a big drawback
From your perspective what are you thinking
I like to think about you
And I like to think about
How a consumer would really interact with the connected device so
One of the examples that funny examples that people like to use
Talking about the internet
Coffee maker
And it's ideas at your house can figure out when you wake up
When you're headed downstairs and automatically brew a cup of coffee for you
Turning on a coffee maker and starting it Brewing
It's only a
A small part of the problem
So
When I think about making a cup of coffee
I even if I'm using Keurig I still have to load the coffeemaker I have to put the package in there
Put a clean mug in there
If I'm using a coffee maker that grinds beans I have to fill it with game that's put a filter in Africa water in
That's about 95% of the problem the actual turning on the coffee maker is only 5% of the crop
And
I think about everyday 10 or 20 times I use the coffee maker
I'd much rather go down and turn it on
5 minutes
Before I actually need it
Then they have a 1 + 10 * 4
Even one in 20 times
Activated the wrong time
When I come down and I have a cold
Hi coffee
It's actually going to be two or three times
6 long to get the coffee as it would be otherwise
So when I look at something like that I start to thanks
What would be far more interesting is if the coffee maker
Is able to tell when I actually need to order more beans
Do things like that
In my view is really more of us
Sight word activities
Where the coffee maker is getting its materials
Supposed to react into other things
Smartphone
Got it okay so are you excited about the Amazon fulfillment
You take a look at the ideas
Putting a little button on your
Washing machine
That's when the bottle starts to get empty
The bottle mic recorder so you could imagine
In 10 years
Get bottles
Free Wi-Fi built ending until in Ramsey but
He might not know where there's more bottles around the house
Replenishment button right there
Play Take a pretty interesting one and I think in a lot of areas
React
The Internet of Things
Starting to incorporate that into either buttons
Self replenishment services
Very interesting
Glimpse into the Future
So I like that I like the idea of replacement
Or kind of
So as opposed to just connecting things around your house
Connected object
To think about it as having kind of a replacement service Milton
I also am really excited about and I'm curious your thoughts on
Education so
And this is actually one of the reasons why I'm interested in the
Kitchen
In a coffee maker might not be a great example of this unless you ever really high end coffee maker
But
Devices
That
That know what they're doing and can
Can teach you
Or offer recipes or
Ways to
To improve your coffee so it in the coffee maker thing
Maybe my coffee maker
You don't give me my two shots of espresso and then it'll also
Because I told it I want
A latte it will tell me how much milk I need to put in there
How long I need to steam it and it what temperature
And all of those things could become
Immensely value
Especially
Midday Pick 10 but it ends up getting baked into an iPad or an iPhone
Next to that device
So you can opt into that information and you can do it but
To actually control the
Milk that goes in Turkey
Call the sugar that goes in independent of your measuring at yourself with a very very
Simple measuring device
Does devices have mechanical moving parts
Why you say you don't multi thousand-dollar
Espresso machine
Because they have a lot of moving parts inside
And being from Italy a lot of things break all the time
So I think in the connected kitchen
It's about
What are you trying to do what are you trying to solve
You still have to wash the pots
And you still have to order the food you still have to measure a lot of the food I think
Are Instagram models that are coming along like
4-H
Other companies
Deliver food in
And
Portion size for portion sizes
That makes sense
But at the same time
I think that
Studious
Relatively
Inexpensive it is an area where the artistry
Anna high social element
Did I think people really enjoying
That's that's why I have some Skeptics
Says I'm about the speed at which you see that
Connect to Kitchen really start to take off
I understand like I agree with
A lot of fat
I guess I see things
I see because I like to cook so much I see a generation of
Friends of mine for example in people who are even younger
Who don't know how to cook and I see
Things like
Meld is a good example of to Kickstarter for
It's both a
A knob that you put on your stove
And a temperature
The thermometer that you
Dropping a pot
And what it does is it
In conjunction with your iPad
It tells you basically how hot
Something is
On your stove and then
You tell it what you're making and it tells you kind of it controls the
The temperature out
I'm trying to think of what that is that
We all have
Say hey
Turn the oven to 375 degrees
And we all know that that oven could be anywhere from 300
25 degrees to 425 degrees
Or
The temperature of the burner
1 stove I put it at
Medium
I put it at Lowe's
The same amount of heat
Question 2
I guess that you're trying to cook
That type of problem
She better and better tools but they're still similar tools they're their measurement
Tools
But the idea of automating more the process of cooking as opposed to improving individual
Skepticism
Oh okay
Yeah cuz I could think of I can think of dozens of tools that I would be so excited to have
A little bit more intelligence in
And we're not quite there yet cuz I don't think the
The connectivity and the intelligence is it cheap enough yet but you know I would love a spoon that can measure viscosity so when I'm
You know a sausage
To be like okay now we're there
Looking at a stove
You can see all the variations
The idea of being able to build devices
Get a very accurate
Reputable
Better knives better spoons better dishes
Call those things
Okay we'll see we we weren't so far off
Same time you're not going to see a cheese grater go away
Which is a decidedly low-tech device
Oh no
Preparation preparation
The moment at which
Cut it or slice it open it up
Is when your
Releasing flavors and Aromas and all the things that make cooking so magical
It's true although I would love a little bit more high-tech
Built into my
Kitchen
And this is something I
I've no idea for get there but I was reading about Ikea actually has
A
I wouldn't call it an RF
Pee but they have like a vision
For the connected kitchen
And one of the things they're showing off and I'll be very clear for everyone listening
This does not exist today
This is something Ikea's talking about
I'm looking for
One of the things they were showing was something like
A smarter countertop
So it is
It kinda had a sense of what you were putting on it
Either through a computer and a projector like a camera and a projector kind of set up that said
This is a fish
And then it would project things onto the fish that said like
Here's how you're going to
Deponent
It's something like that
That would be hugely value
As
The reality of where those things
Today would be a lot like
Those are probably 40-50 years out the technologies that would be able to track where the fishes and then put the donation
Information
Projected onto the fish is a ways out I think fit
Some of the visions that people have for the kitchen right now or a lot like when people are expecting self-driving cars back in the
60's hits till about another 50 years old
50 whole year
Alright well
That's that's really depressing
Let's talk about things that
You think will disappear
There's a couple things that I I would love to get your thoughts on so
Books
Are they are they going to disappear remain defiantly and
That's a very interesting one because
They do have the advantage of
Instant good time but that's going away this
The thing that I like about books in the thing that I do
When I read books has I like
Annotate physically
And it's been very hard for me to get used to the idea of using Amazon to annotate so
When I use a Kindle
I can see who else is
Annotated to give him section I can see
Comments that people might have made there's all sorts of interesting
Advantages to the hive mind so to speak when you're working with textbooks and other things
I think both have a much longer tail than what you see with newspapers right now
Because when people
Look at that object
When I'm in my library at home that's absolutely filled and stuff
When I look at that book it brings a memory back in a way that I've never get in a digital domain
And it inspires me and helps me think about other things so it's the physical artifact
But I think people find
Interesting and appealing
At the same time
A lot of that is just how I think about quotes and I interact
And
What I find with my kids my young kids
They
Between both mode
Stay still enjoy enjoy picking up physical books and reading books
Very very
Seamlessly move over using it
Kindle as well and
They really don't
Cure to have a preference
Between one another
And I think it's
The Arc I think it's the tactile
Temptation of a book
That is very different than a newspaper because it has a life
Beyond when you read it
You go back you reference a look at it later having you around has meaning
Newspapers and other disposable periodicals
You don't have that same interaction
It's true although
We had a paper mache project that was
Do and suddenly realized that we had absolutely nothing far paper mache project
Oh no I know I'd like
What will happen to the
Kids of the future
When you think about it books have a lot of things going for him the newspapers don't because even today news Prince comes off and
Your hands and
Target open up when you sit down in an airplane in a tiny seed
Oh yeah
Issues I think that people have with newspaper
You don't quite have with books
So I think there'll be a lot of physical artifacts
You stay around but it
It'll be a good thing to see NFC and
Maybe not as much mass produced as many Masters
We're going to go down at list
A quick little list
Okay
I've got some ideas
I'm ready you ready
All right
Jewelry
It's Kind of a Funny
Yes why I think Julia Pfeiffer
Navigate into two categories and one of them is fine jewelry
And the other is fashion
And when you think about things that are fashionable these things fit
Typically
People wear for a year or two or three
And I think that's a little more
Tune to
The light cycle of technology in advance
Technology
When I think about fine jewelry and I think about
Things that are artistic
There's an expectation when you buy it or you just it
You'll be using it
Decades
Whether that's true or not
That's a bit of the expectation
And
Part of the way you talk about the phrase diamonds are forever
You look at
The way that people interact with these
Items in the way that they build on top of it
I think this was fine jewelry people don't want
Literal picture
They want
The
Positive
Sometimes negative emotions that come along with it it's still in your mind and there is much more of an arc
Please do it so
When I think about jewelry that's how I
I think about that category
Current that makes sense
What about
This it this encompasses a lot of things
So we can break it down further but building materials
That's a good one
I think you start to see something that happened with technology
Such as
Chalkboard
So you start to see advances in technology we can have paint that looks the same on whiteboard paint that allows you to write on it
I think those are some things that happen with physical characteristic
On the other hand
You look at the door
The door is stayed defiantly analog for a very long time hinges work well the idea of being able to pull out a pen
To be able to remove a door
These are things that work particularly well
And I think we'll continue to work well for a very long time I don't think we're going to see the Star Trek sliding doors
Make monkey noises every time they slide open anytime
Or Worse the depressing door is out of The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy
No it's the same time I think you will start to
See
Companies like August
Lockitron
And
Unikey
People that are building internet-connected locks
I think there's a lot of utility to be had there I think he'll start
See more and more of that
And there are
So many doors
Somebody access points but that can be an enormous Market
Like to see the really
Mainstream adoption I think you need to
About another 5 to 10 years of reliability built into these devices
Because there's nothing worse than getting
Locked out of your house because the batteries might have died
Like I got locked out of my house all the time
Keys
Batteries connectivity at all
It doesn't matter
So I'm like whatever
What about you what about things like
I feel like windows are kind of an interesting
Interesting thing to think about maybe not
803 years for now but maybe 10 years from now just because in some ways they're kind of like a screen opportunity
I I don't know I
I have no idea what you're
If anything at all
Anytime you start to put something
Physical and then you start to think about
Cost of installation
At least run adventure capitalist point of view
Start to get a little frightening
Because it starts become Capital intensive
To inform people
And teach people about the benefits that you could have from
New windows are building materials like that
One of the things I've done in my house is
Put on 3M protective coatings
To reduce the UV
Protect are also to help with heating and cooling bills
But that's something that you can apply after
Retrofit Easley
And I think anything that's in Material Science is better suited to large companies spend
Got it in you and your
Your post you actually talked about furniture so
But let's talk about furniture we also mentioned Ikea and they're sticking
Charging stuff
Charging pads into their furniture and I know I
I got Kickstarter all the time and
I see some really interesting furniture
USB cables built in
The things that are
Suited
To The Internet of Things Memorial stamp first
I wear your solving
Really clear
Problems that people have so I think something like
The Nest thermostat and being an early investor they're one of the things that we saw was
You could go into a single point products
Connected to the internet
And you can pay for itself within a year along with all the other benefits
Will you look at
Something like
Looking at a leather chair right now
It might cost
As much as 500,000 $2,000
My expectation is a less that chair for 20 or 30 years
And I think that a lot of these charging devices and things that people think about building into Furniture in about
For five years is going to look like having an 8-track player in your car
Especially Theron Apple charger
And everything that's around you I think it's about
Mapping
The life cycle of that product to the life cycle of Technology
So if you have a product that you have next
Station that you use for anywhere from 1 to 3 years
That's where you'll start
She technology
If it's something where the advantages are just so overwhelmingly powerful like what you see in a thermostat
Put an item that you expect to have for 2030
Years are longer than 10 years
I don't think it's a
Place that you're going to see them be anything other than Analog Devices and backdrops for other products
So this will be our final question our final product category
Clothing
Clothing that's a good one
Well ask you how long do you
Clothes for
Woke up with fashion versus fine clothing
It's it's a similar it's a similar divide maybe not as long as a diamond ring but
But I think in general clothing
If you wear a regular later we're up
Clothing
Design
Only designed for
30 40 50 Washings before they really start
Come apart in general
It it's true and indefinitely when you go in
There are things I buy that
Like my Summer shirts and shorts those will probably last me
A summer maybe two
But like a fine like a suit or something like that or if I'm going to buy something by a designer
I expect that to last me
Probably a decade
Because
Where
You will see technology overtime but the price points have to get down to a point where if you
Incorporated into the clothing itself it has to be
Vanishingly
Inexpensive cell
I think the only reason that you won't see it on a broad scale
Anytime soon
It's just the cost of the technology and
I need to recharge I think
At the point that you're able to do energy Scavenging and wifi-only cost you a few pennies
Carmen
They might start to see that sort of thing
I've had the experience with a a shirt that
Edward at South by Southwest on your neck of the woods
2 years ago that had a
Graphic equalizer on the front and a batteries
And would actually
React
The music
And whatever venue I went to it South by Southwest and it was a huge hit love wearing it
I think you'll start to see some of these things
I'm into fashion
But it's an area where I think
Points make it very difficult unless you have a very unique
Reason that you're using it such as Fitness or or some other purpose
Yeah I think Fitness and I think also an interesting use cases things like
Health Lake
It'll sunsun tracking UV tracking is a really kind of interesting
An example especially like kids clothing
So when you look at something like that then you ask whether it's
Better for it to be
A highly effective state-of-the-art sensor that you clip onto the clothing
Survivor run through the wash if you forget to take it off
Is opposed to something that you would add to every piece of clothing
The kids has it might not be as good as sensor
Well it in that is the question but some of those some of those clips are very expensive and I'm thinking of
Like a rash guard that I put on my kid every time they go out to the beach when I'm most concerned about it might be
Interesting way to go see them building
Measurements of your form and Effectiveness when you work out
Areas where you have time and you're trying to make the most of your time and
It's much more measurable it's something that people will pay for and pay more for us in it
Guess I certainly
I certainly don't need my everyday clothes telling me I'm slouching on the regular
Yeah
All these categories is
Part of the human condition is
Spitting up in manipulating and working with
And touching and interacting with devices in our everyday lives
And so much of our world I think whether we feel it or not is about creativity it's
3D sidewalk on this side of the street of that side of the street or
What do we want to have for breakfast or how do we want to cook it and what do we want to do and I think
Art's Place
And creativity plays much bigger
Part of our daily lives
I think because of that that's where you'll see the tension between
Silicon Valley that wants to
Automate everything
Connect everything to technology and
Areas where I think you'll see
Thanks the analog four
Decades if not centuries
And I think
That's a wonderful topic that we could probably explain a whole nother podcast because I think actually some of the stuff opens up
A lot of opportunities to be creative and completely different ways
For people who want to explore that like I
I had a fun time building a
Pressure sensor into one of my chairs and
Tying a tie
Distance you lightbulb so when you sat in that chair and only that chair the light above your head
Pokemon
It was silly but it was kind of a fun party trick
Actually measures how much that person
No no that would be a terrible chair
No one wants that are displayed above the refrigerator
Can you imagine
I can't
No one would visit me again
All right
Brought thank you so much for coming on the podcast
I love that post I think it's a must-read for everyone all included in the show notes
And
Thank you
Call Stacy thanks for having me on the show it's been a great conversation
I will see you next week on the Internet of Things podcast