Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is my
My co-host
Kevin tofel
And we are here to talk about
That's awesome things
And moonshine
Let's get started with the news that Oral Roberts
I don't know how to stay religious University the
That's kind of what it is
That's what it world
So this university has is putting
Mandatory fitbit's on its students
Which a lot of people like crazy but it's important to note that students actually before they were
Stuck with mandatory fitbit's
To track people's Motion in health
Fitness
They actually had it
Fitness and activities
Beforehand
So
This is
Yes
A technological upgrade but it is not
Like
Like totally crazy so
I think it's a little crazy what do you think Kevin
Oh I don't know I'm in there fighting the Freshman 15 that's often so happens in my son will be a freshman this fall at his university
It'll be curious to see what happens there
Again late like you said they've been requiring students to
Kind of monitor
Aerobic activity and such manually
This kind of adds more data to the to the process and makes it simpler I'm in
If you're wearing Fitbit
Got your Fitbit account
You know you don't have to to manually do really anything which is kind of nice
I don't have the students feel about having the
School have access to that data
You know overall I think it's a good thing
It's a lot of data
You shouldn't have to log
Well I don't know if you had to log your sleep data
I'm just thinking about all the data that my Fitbit
Not sure which fitbit's there
Getting exactly
You know some of them
Log more data than others
And there's the one they're using doesn't have GPS so it's not like the school can actually see where everybody is or isn't
Which is a plus I think
That is a plus
Now you can see what people are psychoactive
One of the quotes in the article in the guardian was
When they're on spring break in Africa or South Africa
Weekend
You don't see how active they are in like
Yeah
I like the intent here and there trying to do something
Positive
Yeah yeah
And it says it is an issue
The real issue that they're trying to resolve them it's pretty
I would say you know everybody goes to college and games away but it's it's a common
The common challenge so
You know I kind of think it should be
An opt-in
Saying
But
There are technically I think requiring this
They are
Let's let's twist it a little bit
What if you're in
Lawyer
Had you often
You know
Nothing Forest
I'm pretty much okay with
Any opt-in solution
Quite honestly you know as long as I've got control and I make that choice so
I'm going to say person I don't have a problem with that
No
What if your health insurance starts doing this
If
Himmler
Yeah and I think you know whether you agree with it or not I think that's kind of where we're heading
I don't think it's very far-fetched to think that in
Five years or less
You know that's the
More common than it is today
You know I'm in it it's helping the business the insurance company better managed healthcare and
And subscribers so I know
I don't know if it's to the point where it's almost like the whole privacy thing when they kicked up ears
I got one still going on
At some point
You know what if we have to give if we want to get something in return
Now I will
I would be in
You know there's a
All the lawsuits there's I think a class action lawsuit right now against Fitbit for accuracy
Are there
Heart rate monitor
I believe it is the heart rate monitor
So
I am kind of intrigued by the idea of
Man once someone sues over this then
Do we get the lawsuits
You know well
How accurate is this anyway do we have
Federal settings
Which I actually think is an interesting kind of question because
There's even some doubt about the 10000 steps is that a really great gator health
I will be the first to argue you know that maybe it's not the best gauge maybe because I only
Achieve like 6000 steps a day
WeChat
I just admit that
Everyone who listens to the show
6000 steps a day
You don't my resting heart rate still at like
Channel 52
So
Okay
Yeah I mean you and I are mostly work-from-home people so it's not like we're walking to catch a bus or walking around
City that much
Turn the work today
I still like the idea of having that goal in the end
The apps and devices I'm using these days you let me set that goal I don't have to
Make it a default 10,000 or live with that I've actually got mindset to 8000
It's a guideline and I think it's good to have because it it gamify something so that way you can
You know
They have something to shoot for during the day.
That's true maybe we should be partners Kevin we just had our steps together
I would be embarrassed cuz some days I barely even
I'm pretty good now I've been running everyday since the beginning of the year so rough about its
It's almost 2000 steps for every mile
And most days I don't even have to go walk around which is good
OKC and I even take like yoga or Barre classes and I'm
I'm still not itchy
That's not true it's a different type of thing you're not achieving steps
But the steps is not the end-all be-all again it's a guideline away
A simple wave
Everybody can
Get a little healthier at least be more Health aware that's all
So Oral Roberts may or may not
Be pleased with us
Our insurance
So we hang on
Aren't there some insurance firms already doing this like made with an automatic or
Or someone will give you a reduced rate
Automatically
Exactly
I wasn't thinking about it
It just rolls right off of the time
I would have to double-check
What if someone is so USAA
Infested and automatic and is researching using
I do not know if they actually have a program in place yet for ottoman
I was thinking actually of progressive I'm pretty sure they have something that you can plug in and
What's my next one
The progressive
It's on black box
State it is
A 6-month program though
It is not a program that
Continuously running
And it's not then it is an option
And
You share your data with them for 6
The driving dead
So yes
I probably would do it
I believe
Are going to be some kind of
New stuff this year so
State Farm is looking at this USAA
Is also looking at this and so is American family
Which has
Have some interesting kind of investments in the space
This year should be the year that insurance starts getting kind of crazy Innovative with some of the stuff
Look for it
Okay
Let's move on to
This week's news
Which was actually kind of big
On Monday
Alphabet
Reported earnings
For the first time that broke out all of the little bit
The alphabets in a little bit
Cleverly called it
Show the other bats
The other guys
And Google reported
With a B
Revenue that's Olive
Google
And
That's 23-point
23 points
Ford
I was deciding how far I wanted to round
23.4 billion
Again with the b in operating in
For the year so that's for all the 2015
That's a lot of money
Mostly an ad Revenue
Little better that's probably from the cloud
Segment
And then the other bets
Include things like
Nest
Project access
And
Those are probably the ones that are made
Money
Made for deer
448 million
And they had an operating loss of
3 point
6 billion
With me
Yeah so
It's a big loss
But
The money that it made
That's coming from things like nest
And
Viber
It's kind of disappointing because I was hoping to see Nest make
A lot more
And
Recode actually had a story back in November where they expected Nest annual sales to be 450 million
Yeah this is just under that if it 448 million for all of the other Revenue
Yeah and we were I mean
Google actually making money
Fiber in
A couple of like three or four cities now
Provo Kansas City Austin
Where they have actual customers
So granted they probably don't have a lot of customers
But they're making money on those guys to
So
The nuts and bolts of it
When I saw this number was maybe the nest business isn't as big as we thought it was
I don't know that that means
Shouldn't have spent the was at 3 billion dollars
Sunrise
Amnesty
3.2
Yeah
I meant okay I mean that's that's a big figure I'm in the end
Eli getting back 10%
This particular year
At best because they're ugly said there are other things that Google can make money on in the other bets category or segment again
But I think it's a long-term investment
Wasn't just the hardware it was
Just the technology and so on so I
What the remains to be seen that how Nest expenses business
Cuz right now they're really what
Just a couple products
There's Nest cam
Protect and then there
Sprite
Alright so
Nest eventually be the smart home brand for all of Google products
Ways to say I don't know yet
Swelling
The other thing to think about is Nest as a proxy for the home
The smartphone
And
Coming away from all this I I was kind of struck by that number because
WeMo
Has admitted that
Has admittedly
This is something to be ashamed
But they have
One point
5 million
Yeah we met
Chamillionaire
That's looking at this number
Furness
But maybe a million user
Assuming all of that revenue is for nest
Max of 2
United States around 1.25 Ash maybe 1.5 the same as we do it best
Yeah assuming all
And
That's most people who have one Nest product
Usually
I'm going to guess have another one I mean I'm just thinking if you have a nest protect
She probably have
Most likely
The people I know with an s
Respirtech usually have
Multiple Nest protects
Sprint
So that's an interesting time now
I will say
Last year in
Early late in the fall kind of timeframe last year is when Nest started announcing Partnerships with ATT with American
Family with a lot of like the insurance and security forms
Was like hey
You sign up for
If you sign up for like ATT service or
Do you want to get like
An insurance discount
What give you
Nest protect
Discount so
That's
It's going to take time for that to kick in
1 state right now
That'll be really interest
Yeah we might get a better idea on that in the next
1 or to Coeur d'Alene
Reports now that we're getting is Breakout by segment
So and it'll be worthwhile to see
I mean it'll be nice to see some more
Segmentation possibly on fiber
As the FCC starts releasing more
We might be able to get more interested more information there too
On how how fiber penetration is going
Yeah I don't know because I mean when I had heard that they were in a reorganizing to alphabet never going to report by side
Simonson's salon
I figured we'd see bits from each company here but really
All the non cortical Google companies
Under alphabet where Lumpkin child are bats in
And I listen to the car
Call Annette some in other bets include their efforts on
The smart contact lenses with verily
But we're not seeing all that broken out
We are a step closer to the big picture but
Not that much closer
I wouldn't expect
I mean all of these
So young
If you're a startup trying to do anything you don't want to be all transparent with
What are bats and efforts
Cuz then other people will like
Do with that data
Yeah that's good point that's good point
This way there
Now if you're like a smart home company if you're like
Ecobee or Honeywell you're like
Wechat data
It's not great day. But
It's a little bit more clear
And now maybe you feel better or make me feel worse I don't know
By The Way We Were
Looking for the
Quarterly revenue for Google in the other bets just before the show here and
I just found it
They're a bunch of tables on the bottom of the press release so
If you're curious the other bets for the holiday. Which I would think would be good for
Sacred nest
Was 151 million in revenues
Prior quarter was 142
Then summertime 75 last March 80
So
10 holiday 2014 was 106 million * 151
Million for 706
Year-over-year
Brother bets
Oh so it went down
You know I went out from 106
I'm sorry
06 December 31st 2014
To 100 to 1 million December 31st 2015
Misspell that advertise
All the fancy psychedelic Nest as I saw everywhere
Okay
Well let's move on from moonshots to something for the
Tinkers at we got two things for the Tinkers actually
Bring it
1 is
How to build your own
Amazon Echo
Kevin
This is interesting it's an echo clone
But it doesn't use and it surprised me when I saw that the details of it
It doesn't use
Amazon support services that Google services
What I thought it would but it doesn't it
It's actually using IBM Watson
And the Intel Edison board
Getting Watson for the speech-to-text that's kind of interesting
So
So if you if you don't trust
Amazon
For some reason
That's your choice but you'll need an Arduino
Expansion board for the Intel Edison
USB micro Bluetooth speaker Keno odds and ends
I have plenty of the my closet
And then a working knowledge of node. Js
Nodejs
Codes actually in this and then I'm assuming we're going to Lincoln the show nuts all the code is is here on GitHub and in the
Blog post
Showing you how to make it work I mean like here's how it how it tried ties into DuckDuckGo is instant answer API
4 searches for example women
It if you're into coding at all
It's kind of interesting just to look at I think
Yeah and it's not $180
If you bought all these parts
You're probably looking at
I don't know what the
Expansion board in the
An Intel Edison Hardware goes for
I would think most people have a USB mic
Probably a bazooka Bluetooth speaker that they could use
I was following the links and I thought it would be like
Oh here's where you can buy it
But it it's just that
System architecture
Yeah
Corazon
All right
So I'm going to put the links in the show notes cuz
You know I know there enough of you guys out there who are like
Crazy enough to want to do this so you do build this
Let us know how it went
Because I would love it so info at iot podcast. Cam is where you would tell me or send me an email to tell me
Funny how this goes
Before we talk about our next kind of developer Orient
Two thing actually don't let's talk about that first and then we'll get to our last
Segment
Sure
I don't know if any of our listeners or you Stacy
Back this Kickstarter project but I did it
It's for the pine a64
Oh I remember reading about
I did not back
Okay
I couldn't not back it was $15 that I think I upgraded to the $19
A 64
Plus board
It's similar to a Raspberry Pi it's got a cortex a53 chip
Valley 400 GPU and I got the one with extra memory so I think I got a gig of RAM on it
And it's got 4K HDMI output so it's like a nice little TV computer let's see. Let's do that
I don't have it yet they haven't started sending them but it's
You know
Hey I could always use another 3 by 5 in
Computer mouse so why not
But I just found out last week
And I did not know this when I ordered it but now I'm really glad I ordered it
That they are going to have
Modules that will
Fit in with this and I'm looking to the models right now aside from the USB serial programmer module
Also
An ambient light sensor you can get
A humidity sensor
Actually see me the end temperature
A Z-Wave module
A Wi-Fi remote module so there's
There's some iot stuff here we can do with this fruit with this little 15 $20 Gizmo excited now
No I'm noticing that the
The net working on this though is
Or
This is on ethernet
As opposed to what
Correctly there is a Wi-Fi module that you can get and they're also experimenting with power over ethernet not working
Yeah so
A lot of different options
Originally was just going to be this little computer and
Run Android on it
Zumpano's Linux and all that but it seems like they've expanded it
Far beyond that now
But the gpus you could use it
Media player gaming platform
Farm to absolutely
Absolutely anything for you know 20 bucks or less
When you confront so for people who like
Are into this sort of thing you could run open wrt
So
Hey hey
If you want to be a writer for you or you could run openhab which is
Open Smart Home
Kind of platform
People come on the show
For a while
So one day
One day it's going to happen
So that's
Worth noting
As I'm scrolling down and learning all about this
I'm so okay well cool as you get the
Let us know what do you plan on doing with it
Are you I was just going to make a little Linux machine and do some media and whatnot but now that these modules are going to be
I don't have the pricing at they've announced it
Now I'm thinking you know what else can I do from smartphone perspective
Not that smell every good to get them on the show and talk about
So yeah
Maybe I'll make you
Hahaha
Look at that snout
Didn't have this before the $59 I owe TPAC
Includes the
Little computer 8 gig micro SD card with openhab on it
Power supply enclosure Bluetooth 4.0 and Wi-Fi module
And Z-Wave plus aniyo car
39 bucks
Wow
Womp womp
That's so sad Trump
Yeah that's a sad trombone
There we go
Alright Movin right along we got a comment from listener
Last week that's worth sharing this is from Nick
Last week we talked about
What do we talk about we had Scott Jensen on the show
Google and he talked about
Moving our smart devices with us and he gave his home an email account
Because
He was like
How about making his light switches smart he was using NC on light switches
And he was like I don't want it
Associated with me I wanted associated with the house so he gave us house a Gmail account
Except he's kind of hurt by it
So
He didn't like his idea he he wants a better identity kind of issues this is
Flash
Things that he will make better possibly
In his life
So
Nick Roden and was like
Scott mentioned that you wouldn't take her smart devices with you when you move much like he wouldn't take your dishwasher
I don't take my dishwasher because I expect my new house to have a dishwasher left behind by the other owners
The same goes with a stove
The refrigerator's on the other hand people usually do take those with them when they move
So it's not expected that you would buy a house with a refrigerator
So I bring my own
But for a smart device I don't expect to buy a house with smart devices because most houses don't have them
So if I sell my house with all my setup and move to a new house I'm going to have to start
From scratch if I put several thousand dollars of smart devices in my home
What's money lost when selling my house
And I can't really say my house is worth more because of those devices because most people right now wouldn't pay the extra cost of having
That's a really good point
And I know I would not pay the X
Patrick Hospital
And I love her
Yeah
Highwood
I
Probably would not know
You know we put the solar panels on her house and
That added about $30,000
To the appraised value because
Clearly they're not coming with us for not taking down 41 solar panels
When we move there permanently attached to the house
Turn on my smart home stuff I would definitely take with me
And
Would I pay more for a house that already had it
I kind of want
The choice of what I want to use so I don't know a kind of trying to go straight and say well hey
Either take it out or leave it I don't care not paying more for it I don't think I pay more for a house because it was
Fit in with that kind of stuff
Yeah kind of depends on how
Well spit it out
Many people today already pay for
Certain types of media system
Sounds like you pay more for it
In-ceiling speakers
You might
I would maybe like a projector an HDMI HDTV projector its mountains at the ceiling with a screen
But I don't think
Alarm system
Irrigation system that's connected
I'm just that I'm starting to that mean Lake
Yeah
I mean there's something to that happen if you got a whole package of these things
But you're not going to break them out and see what a house is worth $4,000 more because I have all these things so you know
Will you just
Someone is having a pitch one day
You know that's like
Smart Home Tech is the new granite countertop
In a sense
A granite countertop is not going to make it
Break
Your house would have
A certain price level
If we can we can sell our house last year cuz we didn't have Granite for go ahead
I have Corian
But
At a certain level people
Expect certain amenities
Countertops
And I think
We're going to get to a point
We're at a certain level people are going to look at your
A better irrigation system or Nest Thermostat or
You know that kind of
Things like it really high-end homes
You expect smarter lighting
You really do
Liquor store store
So
I will let you know what
I agree with you I guess I question the timing I think it's I think we're a long way off
From those types of things impacting homes
For all but high-end homes
And I would be curious if any of our listeners
Have sold their home
With and without Smart Home Stuff
And if that effective negotiation or price I would love to hear from somebody who's actually gone through that and
Desmos princess Asher
Okay so listeners
If you make yourself
The Amazon Echo
Or if you were Soldier home
Add a smart device or a smart
Kind of home automation system that is helped
Affect the value of your home
Please
Sandestin Outlet info at iot podcast.
Stay tuned
4 hour gas
2 is awesome
It is checked
Kenosha
Who is the CEO of Starry
Which is a brand new
Brand new just launched last week
ISP
That is going to start in Boston
You may remember chat
Is the CEO of Ariel
If he is now launching and ISP
It's actually using millimeter wave technology
You don't have to worry about that the reason he's on the show is because there is also an Internet of Things component
To his Broadband offering
So once again chat is taking on the big boys
In this case he's taking on the entrenched isps and he's scared to talk about what he's
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And today I have a special guest for you this is Chet kanojia
And he is the CEO of Starry
Paycheck
How are you doing today
I'm well thank you
I am so excited
To have you on the show because you were combining two of my favorite loves Broadband in The Internet of Things
You guys lunch story last
Last week and it was up
Big
Freaking so why don't you go
I telling everybody
Seriously what story is
Sure so sorry was known as project decibel while we were developing
But basically it's it's kind of think of it as a entire communication
If you will
It starts with
Depending on which way you look at it either from home or or some
The goals of companies to provide a
Broadband access
A way for using
Wireless technology
Olympics
Second is in home appliances that combine and simplify
Interfaces the consumer has to the internet
Goal ambition
And goodies for the passion is to make
Things that are simple easy convenient
Consumers will adopt them more and then get a greater benefit out of them
Okay so
You were doing
Broadband service to
People and just just to get people really excited
How fast
Is this internet service
It's going to be
Sonar technical test we've tested up to a gigabit
But we think ultimately will be able to do more but that's the max that we've demonstrated to ourselves and I
Oh wow okay
I don't usually hear
Technical test we can do a gigabit
And then we think we can do more I usually it's the other way around to do it take a bit but really
You're going to get less
So
Okay
The idea is I can ditch my
Traditional IRA
I put one of your devices if I have a house it's going to be
On a window
I stick this in there
It's going to take
Your
Crazy
It's crazy technology guys don't worry about it
But on the inside of the house
It turns into Wi-Fi
So outside of the house it's
7 millimeter waves
Y'all can worry about that later
Inside of the house it's Wi-Fi
There is another device
It's called
Let's see what is it it's the starry
It's called The Starry station
And
Is
Wireless router
Plus AI
Hub
An Android application platform all combined in the
Awesomely beautiful looking
It is very pretty I am kind of excited that we have this this
Huge number of pretty routers like devices in her home
So the story station is kind of what we will focus on here
Because
This is the Hub
For you guys
It has Bluetooth it has 11 AC Wi-Fi
We spent a lot of time optimizing
Power amplifiers in antenna design in.
Maximize coverage
It has zigbee
As well and
It will also we would also launch a Extender with it soon which basically
Creates a tunnel between
Abuse isolation and extender to extend the reach in
More concrete type of construction on brick and masonry Caprica
Instructions
My situations
Okay so I do have to ask
Because this is going to have
Bluetooth
Busy Bee
The Wi-Fi
Sounds good it's got the Android Bass
You told me before the show that
You know one day it might upgrade to thread
Why no Z-Wave
So we went back and forth
Turn on the decisions and betrayed use to put in there and put a long time to at least two months there was a lot of
Passionate debate inside the company I think we broke down the
Coyote Channel alarm
Debating the same
I think the conclusion we at least of it seemed reached was
Unipower started thinking about some a power perspective
Which method zigbee made a lot of sense for low-power applications
Ble obviously program applications include
Bridging two speakers from Wi-Fi etcetera
And
Your Instinct was that a lot of
People were beginning to build
You know Wi-Fi into these devices as opposed to Z-Wave and we saw
As a roadmap
Nothing that deter deciding if we had zigbee and
Wi-Fi and Bluetooth we wouldn't be able to cover a lot of Apple
And you know this is not you know
You know I mean this version of the product has.
Things change in the future
I'm sure we'll upgrade or change our approach
But that was for the Box
Can going into
Okay is there a port on the back where I can plug
No the radios built into the device itself
I'm okay
So
Let's talk about
Why you decided to combine because this is probably more Salient to the normal people out there who listen to the podcast
Why you decided to say hey
I'm going to be
Be an ISP
And I'm going to provide an iot hub
I think that some
Approach we take is
Experience
And I think of my experience and education
Expect a lot of pee
Feel the same way
Is when you don't have
Environment in which you providing the entire stock it is very difficult
To provide a great experience to Consumers
So we wanted to do the entire and do anything to make sure the experience that we could put our name behind
And you know I Grand and get passionate about
Was controlled by us in terms of equality
Right now in attempts to be
You know you have an ISP that has a cable modem or or DSL modem or whatever
Particular transport to use
And then they
Either package in
The cheapest possible access
When did they can find or encourage you to go by
You know I'm more sophisticated wireless router AP
The problem is at the service provider they don't have any
Control over the software intern
Quality Inn
Upgrades in
Women's
And it just frustrates
Consumers
Same thing applies to iot devices yuan ultimately to think about it
Entire ecosystem
That can be managed by the consumer anywhere anyhow easy to deploy and simple
Do you want to have access to the entire software stock so you can
Really provided gradle
Experience
I'm even Bluetooth pairing as such you know half the
People stumble on it
Writing and then
Pairing any of these other things devices are daring and a Wi-Fi
Extender is yuno a science project for an average
I shouldn't be that hard
Nothing what ends up happening is people
Call
The service provider ended up set of the cellar
Service provider
Somebody else's phone
Compared to what
I don't know why I try to avoid
That is our goal is that you don't have to call us
Which is why
We put it at Android screen in there
Because we think
We can then develop
Great network-level application
That you will be able to control know and hope Nina perhaps in the future will open that up as a open outside
Okay so let's talk about that cuz you just kind of opened up this whole
Addition
In
About to dig into it so
Are you guys thinking about
Adding sensors and other devices or are you thinking more like you're going to bring in third-party device
I think we will try to develop a few of Our Own
But I think we we think that's opening up that platform and
Stables
The software and Hardware integrated software Hardware environment
Poor People's example that makes sensors and take the burden away from them to have to add cell yet another hub
Anna's Pizza software that goes with it as opposed to just writing an app in Android app
Okay
Sew-in in you're not going to do any weird for version of Android like the Amazon did with
You know it's fire stuff
No it's it's pretty stock-standard I apologize I don't remember if it's lollipop or not but I do
Okay that you don't have to you don't have to worry
I won't ask you if you're on marshmallow or
KitKat or lollipop
Actually
Lollipop would be relevant
Because of the BL
Oh so nerdy so nerdy chat we won't go there
Okay
So
Check you have
A Thornton is peace
And your previous
Start up
Ariel
In that case you were
Upsetting the cable company
With the ability to
Basically stream and record over the air TV
The shutdown
Buy a court case unfortunately
I was really eager for it to come to Austin so I was
Sad because I can actually get over the air TV in my
My house
But
I'm sure you probably learned a lot
And
I'm curious what did you learn that you think might apply and in this particular
Business that you're starting at now
Sure it's interesting. You know people's first reaction is as you raised
Is that we are going to get a raise
That's a nice piece in and I just don't understand
Why we live in a system where a
Competition Amina obviously
An Amazon sells you a bunch of stuff and sodas in a Walmart
Nice competition it's Greg everybody created
You better products and their services and attract customers
That's for the model in the
Access
And I don't understand why that is the case I mean I know why it is the case but I don't understand why
People think
Somehow it's not a good idea then and now
Oh I think it's a great idea I'm really excited
Little I know you are and I think a lot of pockets are but just ascend
Companies that the reaction tends to be
Well we don't like this
Okay great let's see what you can do and then we'll push the boundary to and and
See what happens when we the best
Approach is the best company win
And in the study room for everybody
And in particular I think people don't like upstart
It's doing that I don't understand that
Ew that's a lot of
Great Innovation and
Interesting ideas come out of people that are not encumbered by the conventional
We're thinking about
But be that as it may
Either we learned of
Fitbit in
I dare you
You know a lot of that was
How to build a technology company while
Your buildings
Facilities based infrastructure
Stop because area was also a city-by-city build-out kind of a model which is
Ghana
Different than what clean
Here
We learned how to
Market online which was great we learned
That we
We started started we made sure that we
Entire marketing
What is the foundational marketing team of Ariel
I wish it was with us they won
Because we learned the hard way that it's so hard
To build a Marketing Group after the fact and when you don't date on the right foundation to the bottom over the same Fields team
The hand of all the areas
Expansion came over
The same RF tmall revolve you say augmented the team
On the other side
Outside quite a bit
But yeah it was ultimately the team had a lot got a lot of
Confidence out of execution material because
When we started area we have it was sort of this like oh my God how we go
Going to do this
Like what do you mean you have to like
Rent buildings and rooftops
Cities in United stall stuff in you know rent cranes do you know
Raise boxes and
Air conditioning
Those nuts
And we learned a lot and how to get it done then
Got a lot of confidence
Starting distance
That look like this mysterious set of things that need to happen to light activated service
What we kind of did it we know what the mechanics are and we've learned a lot
In terms of how to do it faster better as well
Those what kind of dog
Execution things that we took away from
.
Starting dinner in a lot of other ways a lot of innovative companies that have come in you know people mailman.
Products and services
Tend to be very useful that I'm thinking
Uber another country
Things like that that have had challenges
In the Clarence of the week
Incumbent
Climate and I think that the biggest distinction between Ariel and some of those company
Please was the we had a single point of failure which was
Federal court versus
How you did
Beauty legal framework
State and city in
Mini Plus
So I think avoiding a single point of failure is
Another key lesson
It was unavoidable in areas case because copyright
It is what it is
That was a that was a good lesson to learn that
And if you're going to push the boundary in any way shape or form not that that's
The case here but that was just a good academic last
That tried to distribute arrest
I like it
All right
And for people who are
Oh my gosh how can I get this can you tell us a little bit about what start
Is going to cost
Starry station which is the iot Wi-Fi blue ble all combined have which is going
You can reserve it now on our website it goes to sale and get clothes on sale next week I think February 4th
On Amazon as well as our website
Is $249
So you can order that
The stories Internet Service Wichita Starry internet
Will start beta
In Boston at the First Market
In the summertime thing with Target
And then
Much like we did with the area we let it soak for a few months learned a great deal
Entrance
How to do it
Better faster
Build our support infrastructure with that as well
And then we'll start rolling that out in
Testing multiple more cities
Okay any word on
The cities that you plan
Not at the moment I mean you know obviously some of our test licenses are public information but I wouldn't message
Primarily focused on making sure that we have testing done in
Various different types of
Biological geographical and
In the weather conditions with them but we have not finalized this
But again it's a start-up I think it's fair to assume
That you fish where the fish are
And so we will probably go after underserved markets and or where that is only itching the coax provider with
ESL
In order to you no bring a better dynamic
Excellent
One more thing because
This will actually run on the day
Your Starry station goes on sale
Is there a reason for me to buy the starry station
If I'm not in line to
To get Starry internet
Absolutely
Because if you
Are frustrated with your Wi-Fi
In terms of its
Performance throughout your house
If you're frustrated with not having simple and easy apps like I like I don't know if you have children but if you want to have school
We have a great app on the station called screen time which allows you
To set up policies on and filters for your children so they can email be online and certain hours
Block other things Etc. So all those apps that new parents would find easy and simple to use
Essentially just
Clicking top
It has really cool interesting features that will make your life much easier for example
It monitors
To put on a poor client level
And actually then also on the wide area network and creates an entire Health score for you to tell you
Which devices may be struggling
What day are SSI levels are and adults example if you got
An Apple TV
That is attached to a 2.4 gigahertz
N Signal because the power in a power 10
It'll automatically detect a days greeter couplet at 8
Inferior
Pizza Spectrum it'll create a five gig version of that Network
Pop up something to say to you
We are going to now connect you with Apple TV to the V Gate Park
Standing enforce that connection and
It's not really smart learning
Features built into it
That'll allow you to
Make life easier
If you go to YouTube you're not like you know the one Tech person in the household becoming an admin for the entire day
Extended family
So it's a better router
For your family
Better
Performance
Easy
Simple and you know we designed it in a really interesting way which was the screen is for the hero
The product really two reasons
With a better user interface but the second thing is
Yeah I'm sure you know
You know most people will stick their AP somewhere or router somewhere in a Dusty shelf behind a bunch of book
Bookshelves etc etc
Which potentially hurts
Performance matters
Putting a screen in building an Ambien
Play that is continuously telling you the help
At a glance
Wokano ask people
Basically the move it in
It's somewhere that they can see it
As a result
Routers are becoming like
The superheroes of the home network
It's so fun
I'm loving it
I
Half life
3 access points that
May soon be upgraded
I'm going to wait till y'all have an extender
Because I I don't need
I don't need three
$350 access point one $350 with a next
Exactly I need to I need two or three
I have a weird
So okay
Chat thank you so much for coming on the show I really appreciate it and I cannot wait
To see what you do and till you get to Austin because despite
A plethora of gigabit providers
I still got nothing
You still stuck with Time Warner
I'm still stuck with Thai border
There we go
Great thank you so much for having me this is a lot of fun
Thank you for listening and please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast