Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
Text Jay we have an awesome show for you as always
We are going to be talking about
Mario Batali about
Ellipsis new plan for lighting
About black cat
New grants for iot security
And my experience with a Brita water pitcher
And some more fitness watches
In Babysitting about traveling
Our Guest this week is booked
Stockland the CEO of
Which is a Wi-Fi like that with
Multi-touch
But before we begin
Let's start with a word from our sponsor sizely
Around the world Spring to market the most successful is innovative iot products available today so I leave connect
Product management platform helps companies connect securely manage connected products of the day today
Reimagine how companies engage their customers
Urgent care of the internet of things so you can take care of business
Business at www.liveleak.com iot
After the show
So let's get started this week
You want to start with wearables
We can do that I was going to actually say something about traveling cuz I suspect you are traveling based on the
Audio feed coming from your side of conversation
You're right
So I am traveling
This week so apologies
Or weird sound quality
I promise I will be back in the studio next week
And I'm exploring different setup
Or making my travel
Rick a little bit more compact
So you really phoning it in this way
Literally literally phoning it in
Dunton
You can talk more this
I hope you got your coffee
Let's get started with
Phillips on
Is actually Monday or Sunday night introduced a bunch of new wearables
Which
Many of those are probably like really do I need a fitness tracker
Scale
Thermometer and blood pressure cuffs
Sam Phillips
The answer is
Yes if you wanted to be FDA-approved
Which is interesting because a lot of the wearables that are Health Focus
Typically not FDA-approved
She's not necessarily a bad thing but
It speaks to how accurate the devices may or may not be
So it's something to keep in mind when you're searching for
Health-related wearable
Exactly is really competing with wiping
Most of the devices
The same set of devices
Matheson Pocus witches
Actually getting
FDA approvals of doctors at Health Systems
Actually use them
In Phillips
Many of you may not be aware I don't know not only do they make Lee
Sonicare toothbrushes sales make list
Ultrasound machine veggies and other things that are actually
Hospital
Sophie devices are a little bit more expensive balance watches like $250 for
And
It's kind of a fitness band kind of a smartwatch
It does give you heart rate
I'm sleeping patterns
It goes down step-counting
Is basically offering like
Better actress
So it's not what I would call a smartwatch in the traditional sense of the term if there is the traditional sense
August
Definitely more of a health-focused and a higher grade
One more accurate
Device than what you would buy it in a typical Smartwatch that can do the same things
Working with
Hospital
And with
The insurance companies in
March
Squares
To try to get people to
I'm going to install these devices
Is that really you're just you're just wearing
I don't think they're going to try to
Branch out that way in
You know we talked to Michelle about having Fitness
Trackers
What wearables on your body provided by your employer insurance
Company
Until
Not I mean
Some people are fine with it some people are like
You know I really don't want
That day.
Those people
TT how this works out
It does have a really big potential impact
Precision Medicine Show
I'm really torn on how this
Should I play out
I think in general it's a pretty smart move I mean they're not just offering one product that's actually a suite of products as you mentioned there's a scale
Wearable
A thermometer at two different blood pressure
Coxswain for the upper arm on for the rest
So you have a whole Suite of products is I think more appealing to
People can just a one-off here and there
And also as you mention if they get in with employers or large companies
It's possible that could generate large sales quickly because those companies might be able to
I don't know if these are
Expensable type items because they're update approved their health-related and then there's there's a lot of different
Ways this could play out as opposed to the consumer Market
And I will let you guys know
Phyllis is sending me a
A bundle of them with everything except for the thermometer
Eventually I'll be able to let you know
I should say about Healthcare bundles I wanted to update you because I have been wearing the Under Armour
Under Armour Fitness box
Because I was going to ask I was going to ask about that
I don't love it
Okay
Pictures a box I got it for 300
This $300 cuz
But it's $400 it contains a
Scale
Weight body fat
It also contains a fitness band
Heart rate tracker
And then I get to use the Under Armour record app
Like it alot
Yeah I think this is where you being an avid Runner
And me being an avid let's do other things like coming to play so
AP we emphasizes
People who really want to get fit really tractor Fitness at a really high level
Is it really me
It's really kind of a little bit frustrating
Calibrate your stride
Toy that fitness tracker
If your butt
So it's like
No no calories
Right there's no GPS in the unit so that's very important thing
And then also they cream so much information on this band that I'm kind of like
Wow you have to go through a lot of menus to do things like set the alarm
I think that's three menu prices to set an alarm maybe even 5
And then
I can't get to some things on the band
But I want to
For like what I'm probably the biggest downside to me is that
It doesn't automatically
Register
What I'm doing for today
Maybe I'm spoiled because job
Batman
I forgot to track like half my workout
Yeah that's a fair point and there's a lot of devices that still don't do automatic tracking by sensing what exercise you're doing
That's one of the features that I actually
I love on my Fitbit Surge and that's exactly what's on my wrist right now and has been for
Two or three months
You know I've walked around New York City yesterday
To the office to the
Port Authority Bus Terminal
I didn't have to tell it I was walking it just later said hey you walk 24 minutes he was your heart rate he was your distance you or your steps
So that is a big bonus for people who are focused on on the health
Packing bits
As far as the
Getting two different things in the band yet
Like everything else
Mobiletech everything's a trade-off see fit a very small narrow screen on the band to keep the band
Abandonada giant watch or anything and
You can
You said so there's a lot of menu options just to get what you need because you have small a small screen to deal with so
Those are all very fair points and maybe it's
More Focus for
Somebody and I run everyday and that's
That's why I like that
It's Anza
Contrapoints
Yeah and I mean the scale is fine
T heart rate monitor works really well
It did take a little bit of time to get
Could you do a shift to actively track a workout
Heart rate monitor
Better
Right right
Not to add more to your budget but
If you want automatic tracking with that system they actually do offer it just not in the what's in the box
They do sell the Under Armour record shoes with a built-in sensor
You can use those for calibration
They're always on and always tracking so when you go for a walk it will actually
Track it for you when you go for a run it will do that for you cuz the shoes are already gathering information
So for what that's worth it's an option but it's another matter $240 or $150 to add so
That is a missing piece to the Box
Yes and a lot of my workouts are
Spin class
Pilates or things that do not involve
Joshua
Right I feel like this is great for runners
And
Experience since I've mentioned that a couple months ago and wanted to let you guys know
Moving back to wearables
I think
You was pulled on
Cooler
Using Android Wear
Yeah this is interesting your sister for the first
Long-time traditional GPS
Fitness companies
To actually adopt
Android they came out just
This week with their new Android Wear based m600 GPS sport watch
And
If anybody sees the polar device before they're actually pretty good for tracking running exercise and swimming and biking it's on
But if you want to know Smartwatch functions you were going to get that so what they did was they integrated
What builds their new watch around Android where week is Google's
Platform for wearables
And
That adds all the Smartwatch functions you may want if you do such as you know call notifications text
Google Now notifications app notifications
Music controls the whole shebang
Plus you can
You can add then Android Wear apps
To the polar m600 which is something you can't do with a traditional polar or Garmin or whatever
I know Garmin has their own app store and so on foot
How do you spell connect IQ
But regardless it is interesting to me because it's in a
Gps-enabled
Please music because it has Android Wear support which supports music playback directly on the on the wearable
6 LED heart rate monitor
Be curious to see how accurate that is
And
What's at the polar Flow app as well as all other Android Wear app so
It's an ice melting of of traditional
Exercise wearable with
Smartwatch functionality so it's literally just lost his new reviews out yet
It's 329 99 when it comes out
Next month I relieve gas September
So just interesting to see somebody else adopt Android where someone you wouldn't expect
To do so
But it's alright well that's useful shows consolidation
Is a little consolidation in this industry
Or maybe
All right and we already talked about
That's not funny has discovered
New Philips application at the SCC
And this one looks like it's for a motion sensor
Philips Hue
Ecosystem for life
And
This is actually
Really useful we talked about kind of Lights
Have motion sensors inside on the podcast so there's
Stock lights
Theater lighting company called comfilytes is also building dead
There's probably a lot more out there
Lights are everywhere
Philips Hue ecosystem means that you don't have to like
Do some sort of weird motion detection thing with a
Twitch
A lot of people who hate hugs
Appreciate
I just want multiple hubs and the fact that a hub is in one single spot
It's not going to really do anything when I'm not around it from a sensor standpoint so this
Looks to be like
Queen FCC submission that they found it a zigbee
Sensor. 2in Square
It actually sounds like
Person with my ecobee sensor which I'm looking at right now my office so
Obviously types of the ecobee thermostat keeps my office cool when I'm
Not near the ecobee thermostat sale
It may I have no idea what the
Inside the Phillips
Answer yet but if I were Phillips
I would say you know what
If I'm going to sell a standalone motion sensor I'm also going to put a temperature sensor in here I'm also going to put in ambient lights
Just because
That helps
And you already has a deal with
Yes and
These things are going to start working better at system
Studies is companies are thinking about Building Systems the system
And to do that
You're going to have to do some pretty deep integration
Especially like
Looks like
If this is how my sensor communicate
The following
Here's experiences intolerances
Nest would have to
Say OK based on that here's how I would use your sensor data
Suggested the temperature in
People's house
I agree and we don't know obviously what
Mary not be inside here at the FCC if anybody looks the FCC documents are not it's all for testing purposes.
You're not going to get the full
The full monty on what
Idevices capability is
But
I kind of agree I'd like to see them expand
Beyond lighting
But honestly I mean if it's just a motion sensor for lights to me and my
We can do so much more you know you don't need to put that much more in a little box 2
To get much more data
Create better Prada
Sprite for the long-term to
Right
I will say Trish one of my
This is super nerdy
Pictures of fun music
Cuz it's the most actually did because it got their medical grade wearables right and then they got their lighting stuff
Ski Safari parts list
People talking to each other
How awesome would it be
If you're trying to track your heart rate
If your lights
Titans
Fitness tracker
Hey
You're the fat burning zone right now
Maybe
You had a heart attack but there are all kinds of like
Fun things you can do or even highly utilitarian thing
You know I would love her
My heart rate tracker
Not be
I would love for HP
Tell me a little bit more Ambien
Yeah I mean that's that's a perfect example of mean if you're doing
Riding a recumbent bike in your basement or something you got your lights on
You can look at your
Smartwatch perhaps and see what zone you're in a heart rate but what if you could have the
The information go to the lights and then maybe they turn orange when your
Getting close to puking Reddit Peak heart rate of someone so you can
You have to look anywhere else it's just
The information table round
Innocence
Yes
Also I would like party mode if I
On my scale
Full House was like yeah
Eat Mexican tonight just so we can have party mode again
So
You bring all these things into your life though and you've got to think about
Security
And we got cheese
Security stories this week
We're going to have a lot of it next week because this week is blackhat Defcon
And the iron is Hot Topic there
There are a lot
Companies and I think they said
50 companies
50 groups trying to hack
Iot devices
13 were accepted
Last year we had to hack
Jeep Cherokee I remember how they stopped in traffic
Is a big to-do I think it was wired that might have
Got in the car and
Patent like stall out or stop on the highway I remember
Yes
DPAC
And they're going to try to
Happy
Cheap end tables
And they want to do it
Apparently the last time they did it they told me stop the brakes on the car
Moving slower than 5 miles an hour
They're going to try to make a car go faster
Cancel
Really I do not want to be okay
No
I'm hoping there's a sun Trevor
Yeah
There's a lot of money involved with this too I know that the
Defense Advanced research projects agency at the Pentagon
According to journal they're sponsoring a three-hour all machine hacking tournament
The winning team Pockets a 2 million-dollar prize
Yeah well it makes sense
Yeah you really do
I'm playing original Atari 2600 games on a Raspberry Pi I should be hacking stuff instead
There you go
We can arrange for that
I will say that
Poor people who are great
There are best practices out there that company should be following
Please do not always follow them as in last week
I saw that people's Wi-Fi passwords
In plain text
Witches
Just
Like me opening my front door in
How do you know if MacBook Air is just right by the entryway
Come on
If you see it come take it
That
Not a good thing
But
Most of the Hawks year
Probably pretty
Vulnerability
The things that should be passed but
Hopefully most of them won't be as egregious
Things like that
That's the plan
And if you are worried
You should note that Georgia Tech just had a 9
Quick $4000000 krant
To study
How to monitor winsome
Compromised
The internet
They're actually
The research is based on the electromagnetic signals
Any device
Getting license when it's processing
What happens if they use machine learning
Check and see when something kind of goes out of whack
And if they
See that
Then they're like big investigate further to
Siesta devices
Yeah
It's also interesting to me that that 9.4 million Grant guess where that came from
Chaka
DARPA
Clearly the government
The US government is
Trying to learn as much as possible in any way shape or form
About
Cyber-security hacking and so on
I think it's rather smarter than 2
Kind of put money out there for public and private companies and such to do so
There's a lot they can learn
By doing that
Yes
And we
Really
Really need this because we are connecting
So many things
And
It's stunning to me how much
I guess ambient information we're just about it everything that we're connecting gets off and how much
Now that we have a compute power you can in
Positively and negatively
Yay DARPA
Okay
Less broad topic
We can talk about
Water
Wonder
So I
Was sent
A Brita water pitcher something I haven't had since I last looked an apartment after college
But the cool thing about this one is it is part of the Amazon Dash
Metservice
And so
Basically it's got a wide side shift in the lid
And
I'm betting it's got an ultrasonic sensor in there too
Check water bottles and
At the end of
The useful Life Of The Brita filter
Another one is just going to automatically show up on my doorstep
I'll text the Amazon automatic
It's a kind of like that - built-in there's no button it just monitors
When that
Filter needs replacing I just ordered it for you
Info
I'm not at home right now so I can't split the plan is over the next week I'm going to
Basically water my plants
40 gallons of water just to see
Like how this process is I can tell you so far
There's two things that are worth noting
When this picture has a design
In that
It has a max fill line so you have to fill it every time to a certain level and you can't go about that level for it to cool
Against
I guess the gallons
Send a picture
So that line
Is black-on-black in the
Glossy finish in it
Artist
My first notice
Like I bake that easier
Import
Accuracy of the device
Menchu
This is a lot of fun this could be really fun to do and setting it up with a
We can freeze
You basically go through
You
Login for the picture which made
Really another app
I can't
But then it
You login
Automatically says do you want to connect it to your Amazon account
You log into your Amazon account
Amazon lets you choose what they replaced
Option is
There were multiple options in my case
And I chose
And then
I got an email from Amazon
And I'm done
Until I can't wait to see you like
Will this work but I actually liked
The fact that I could choose
Is that all the dash options that you chew
And then
I didn't like having another account
An Amazon process was super easy I mean I love with him that I was going through Amazon for anything because
It's just like
If we have everything
Just answer your
They do make that easy
You from a technical perspective I'm just actually looking at the system requirement says curious if you have to
Charge this thing I suspect. I suspect there's a
A battery inside a battery inside so it looks like a traditional
Filter if you flip up the lid up a picture
You'll see probably a 2 by 1 and a half inch square box
Underneath
And that box is where I'm assuming the Wi-Fi connection is
Ultrasonic sensor and
I'm assuming there's an ultrasonic sound
Sure I don't know
When you
Delta picture
So in the Wi-Fi cuz I was concerned about battery life
In my fridge so the wife I've actually always
It's going through basically a faraday cage
Can be hard on
Battery life
So
Monitoring but I don't know
Yeah I don't I don't think it'll be a problem and I'll tell you why because I look at the system requirements it
Says that you
Should activate the picture near the sink that you're refilling the picture and that your Wi-Fi router should not be more than 25 feet from
The saint that you're referring to picture
So I suspect it's only sending information
When it's
Being refilled
Yes
Yeah so it's not in the fridge
It certainly doesn't have a high-end Wi-Fi Radio based on the Range and they say it only works a 2.4 gigahertz network switch
I've been around for a long time so
So yeah I know I don't think it'll be a problem in your fridge
Did it say how much it is
$44.99
Time tracking heaven
How many gallons in putting through this thing
And we'll see if it's accurate and
CVS Pharmacy
My Brita replacement filter
I'll let you guys
And
I think we're probably good for this week while you think
Yeah we have our guest this week is oats Baldwin to his to see if plum
Club Mix de wifi-connected light pad
Everyone is always asking
About this one does have Janine konshens it also has multi-touch on it
Is a Touch tablet
And you can actually you don't do one finger tooth
All kinds of touches on it
Very fancy
Chokes we're talkin about
That
She was also the former president of CBS so we got some tabs
Professional installation kind of perspective here
She's running erlang
Aden stay
This is actually not just to let Pat actually distributed computing system
The smart home so
All of you guys were like oh the internet goes out what happens to your smart home or really don't want to listen to this
Station 4
A word from
Our sponsor
Hey everyone this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast with a sigma
Developer conference for people making the internet
Things happen
Is annual conference in September brings together technologist and designers who build core infrastructure for iot platform
Activate you'll see two days of expert speakers
Including me
Giving talks on everything from Bots to Industrial Automation machine learning to time series data
Programming language choices to ux
As a special treat their also bringing back the famous thing Monk hackaday
Sponsored by IBM
They'll have a short Watson and Alexa skills Workshop to kick things off with no prior knowledge required
To learn more about the conference please visit
Www
The thing mug
Dot-com
Iot podcast blisters get a 20% discount code for any of the days or a combination of all three days
So to take advantage use the promotional code iot podcast when you register back to the show
Everyone welcome back
To The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is
Baldwin who is the CEO of
Love
Andre Stacey thanks so much for having me
Super excited just a little note for everyone listening
I am recording this from Seattle
Make the sound of rain
Why don't you give us a little bit of your background
Because I think this is really important
Yeah that's
Connected home and
Electronic is really in my blood
I've been in the industry since it started
I called in a nice homes pulling wire when I was
School
Latest equipment racks
Call products into homes
Ultimately I owned and operated a
Systems integration business for about 15 years
I also served as the
The chairman and chief executive officer craspedia
Those who don't know that acronym it's a custom electronic design installation Association
It's the global trade organization that has represented the Connect Four
Over 27 years now
So why do people think that internet of things is in its infancy but I would argue it's more of a
Very awkward adolescent phase because there's so much change happen
This is great because your perspective
It's something that I feel like we miss a lot in the show because we focus a lot on the DIY
Solutions
The pro installers in their life
Stacy
Why aren't you talking about
And you know I've always been
Of the opinion that
That is a completely different business and its
It's reserved for kind of the upper echelon
You guys have designed the plum light switch this has been a song
We first talked about it
As you guys were working on this perspective
Industry
The title of our story is the thrill and Agony of Hardware startups
With my background of a connected home
Obviously this I didn't have just an epiphany one night and a light bulb went off
In my head
Pardon the pun
After stepping on a Lego right my move into this
Venture was a bit more calculated
When I was running the Trade Organization
High commission several studies
To determine the size and scope of the
We'll call it the Legacy Market write professionally installed
Consumer electronic systems into
Three large estate homes
2013 numbers 14 billion dollar industry
As you mentioned it's for the upper echelon music
People living in very large
Is the third most popular sub system
In the connected home
Industry today behind your putting in a home theater media system
Or Distributing music for your home
And it has far greater utility than any other subsystem in your home
If you think about
How you interact at home the light switches be most used device write in a busy household
What interacts with it dozens if not hundreds of times a day
You have to really haven't been much
Innovation there
So our goal was to
Deliver all of the
Features and benefits of a
Traditional
System
Without all of them
Hardware
Without the complexity and obviously at a much lower cost and we looked at the current landscape of paw
Products that are out there and there are a couple of Cenote connected
Or smart light switches and dimmers
There are a couple that are Wi-Fi
And of course they are smart light bulbs
And we've made the determination we believe that the intelligence belongs in the light switch
We wanted the relationship
Between the consumer
And a device that was
Familiar
Which is the switch in the second dearly
T-Mobile app
We believe strongly that
You walk in and out of your kitchen
But you don't want to pull out your smartphone to turn on your lights
We focused on the switch
And we spent
Couple of years in development
Built our beta product got it out to
Select
An audience and tested for a good nine months
Learn from that
And we made
The decision to make some pretty key changes
So before we go on to the sad Saga of manufacture
I'd love to actually get your
Your perspective as a
Professional installer because
Minecraft
Morso insteon actually
In Savannah especially are coming kind of will call it down Market
So I'm curious how you view
They're kind of transition and do you think they can
Orchid
Work with all these other systems
I do and I actually think it's very good for the industry but
Companies like
Savant
Lutron
They proved
Years ago.
The city of channel was a great channel for them
Vet
And test products and iterate
Before they went
Mainstream
Companies like Savannah now releasing
Ngannou
Remote control or Lutron
Bridge
Are not only helping the Legacy marketing
Panthera Market
Opportunity Market
But they also have a great deal of experience
And what works and what doesn't
So they're approached
Reliability
And user experience
AR
Improving
And these products
I believe will do very well
A transition to
I want to see cross the chasm but start to reach a broader audience
And help
Startups
Innovate on some of those Concepts and ideas
And what would your advice be professional installers
Sounds like 2 hours a week
Impossible for me
Should they look to installing kind of some of these more established
I have no idea I don't know what to tell people when they're like I just needed to
Works
Yeah I think so the market is obviously second
There's going to be a group of consumers you and I and other technology enthused
Stat
Love the idea of bleeding edge technology we are more patient and tolerant
Soggy things because we want to try them
And we are also more patient is as it relates to
Interoperability challenges or or limitations
There's another group of consumers
That
Have a certain amount of disposable income in might not be living in largest state home
But they are
Subject
To some of these new technologies right desserts
Consumers who purchase the nest thermostat or Sonos
Better now
Being exposed to a company like ours
Plum
And interested in these types of
New technologies
But there are still limitations
In this new
Era of
Connected home
Flash iot products in
As a release interoperability
Right there is not a killer app that controls everything buried
Very well
Interoperability
Is one of the the key challenges to
The connected home internet of Things
Moving forward
Rent-A-Center type of customer or those that are living in
Large estate homes they are typically being driven
To making
Purchases
Related to Connected home and consumer products
Through an influencer a building professional like the architect or designer or Builder
Those are the ones that
95% of the time are being introduced to a systems integrator
Who handles everything from the design
The schematics the engineering the project management
And integrating to all of these other subsystems
A very large and
Sophisticated
I will be the first to admit that
If a homeowner is looking to integrate everything in their home
The most reliable
Way to get it done right to get a fully automated home today
I would still leave
Towards
A professional installer with a proven track record
That
Can deliver a full solution across-the-board otherwise there will be
Some limitations
14 points along the way in trying to
Piece together
A lot of disparity
No
The day is coming
Back pain point
Will disappear
Right week we know that the big players
Google Amazon Apple
Are all
Buying
So that position
Right and we will get to a point where
Devices will operate
Seamlessly in an ecosystem
And provisioning interoperability
Discussions will be a thing of
How far away
A question I don't think we're that far off honestly I think that within the next
The 10 years there will be much more ubiquity among
Connected devices and interoperability
I don't think it'll be
Completely liquid
Will certainly make a huge enrolled in the in the neck
So let's talk about you guys because
Speaking of an eternity
Actually
Released it
So you
That is completely different products
You definitely
Tell us your story
Maybe hopefully
Store
Companies in also a lot of company. Out there without getting it the first time
Industry so
Let's talk about what you guys did
You're right you know
Minimum viable product
Works fine with soft
White with mobile apps you can get the product out of dust you can't
Launch
A consumer
Product is a minimum
But you can't retract your Hardware in and start over
Just doesn't work
Aplomb
From day one
We were driven every business decision every design decision
Was
Prioritized based on user experience
The time I spent in the industry
Designing systems and integrating things and and developing new user interfaces on touch screen
I obviously learned a great deal about how consumers want and
Expecting rain
And not only
You know that the guy riding the checkbook to his
His wife
Teenage kids to visiting mother-in-law
And everybody who interact
These Technologies
Unfortunately the Legacy Market I would say is a bit guilty of
Chord
User experience
An older touch panels are
They look like Star Trek in their cluttered
I'm a big believer in less is more in than keeping it very simple
And so
When we decided to
Go through this endeavor
Are we really looked at the feature sets that were important
Particula Lounge
User experience like provisioning right making
The setup as easy as sending or receiving a text message
The look and feel of a technology in the mobile app we didn't want it
Present technology we wanted to
Something that everybody in the household
And we put together our team and begin to engineer this thing and
When the first units came in we were quite
Thrilled they were working
We started shipping amount
The field
But we
Quickly
Realize that
You know there were things that were not ready
And we could have chosen
Send our beta unit through agency
I getting a CCN
Safety test
Start shipping products
But we made a business decision
To postpone it
Little Things
Like the glow ring we have an LED glow ring that wraps around
The button
But the court touchpad
And the glow wasn't
Particular
But we knew
Status
How you do anything is how you do everything
And
We may changes to both of our boards
I mean bored and our power board we may change it to every single mechanical piece
How to that redesign
So when you say when you're made a few minor changes that's very kind of you we did
Essentially scrap that beta unit and start it over
But we knew that that was the right decision to make
So what was the
And then what was the effect on the company itself
Because it's not like
That's an expense
The proposition that you
Right
Did have a pretty significant impact on our timeline
And I believe
You covered us
When we won demo 7 Santa Clara and the fall of 2012
And had died
Touch base with us over the years as we went through development
And we are if not to one of the I think Z
Most delayed
Technology
Gadget Kickstarter project that's not something
Products
But
In hindsight we're very glad
That's the path we chose because the product that we've now delivered
As your business
So you you were stars
Because you
Starter
Without actually having
Physical product designer even on
Which I was like wow
Crazy no one would do that
So your Kickstarter ended when
April of 2013
Okay
Your first
It was signed in 2014. The summer of 2014
And then you pulled that back and now you shipped
People really seem to love
That's why we started shipping in December
So you know from
April 2013
To December of 2015
Was you know the challenges of a hardware startup
It's fascinating
Ear with the innovation
10 things like a development board Arduino and Raspberry Pi and beaglebone
3D printing technology
A startup is able to
Develop a proof-of-concept very quickly
Great Hardware startups and
Innovation in general
But there has been no major disruption in
Getting a product from a Prototype 2
Production it still takes
Years of time and millions of dollars
Which is why many Hardware startups
Or simply fall short of meeting
The expectation of user experience
So we're fortunate enough
You would mention that we didn't have a product or a designer on staff and it's
That is hardly true we did have
Are we did have a prototype when we launched our Kickstarter we hired a
A major odm based out of Taiwan
How to spell Tino
Millions
Electronics
And we had to invest start on dollars
About 30 prototype
But they were
Ugly Betty
And we originally thought that we would
Can you to engage with an odm and
Is a contract manufacturer that can handle all of the design
Are you product as well
And we thought we would remain very lean
Start-up organization
Outsource the engineering
Ana Manufacturing
And
Really manage
The design process
But that didn't work out
The way we planned
We have two separate or sever ties with that odm and that's when
We decided to begin raising
Investment dollars
Building our own engineering team
And the rest is history we started
Disability chronic in house
And contracted with the in-home very reputable contract manufacturer to to build a production version
Okay so you spent all this time develop
Penis product in
I'd love to hear
What you guys decided on because
You switched out the boards and this was all about providing more intelligence
In the home
And distribute around the home so it's
What kind of talked about
But you guys did there and
A little bit
We really started taking a look at the potential not only
Score
Penetrating the Home Depot Radcliffe reading Home Depot
Are we really
We really took a deep look at archived
And we made the decision to
Increase the processing power
Essentially each one of these light pads
Is a computer write its running at 400
Megahertz
Ar9
I in the firmware we chose is only called her Lane
Which is a distributed
System even though the light pad looks and acts like a dimmer what we really created us to
First distributed
Computing cluster in the space
Everyone iPad is
Contextually and situationally aware of every other light pad
Not to mention
Any other it enable device in the home
And they're sharing processing power
Everything is propagated
Down to every single device
Which opens up a world of opportunities
Wrong Turn 4
The connected home and Internet of Things
No question
Serrapeptase and contacts for people early MS
Distributed computing language that runs in
Data centers its is kind of
Very popular for
For what we think of his cloud
Picture so that bringing this into the home is just
I was kind of stunned to discover that so can you talk about
Why
You want to make every basically all of these like
A node in a distributed system
Yeah there was something not too long ago
About
The internet of things and critically the connected home
But it is not
Platform but an
And I couldn't agree with you more
Most experts in the
Field of iot
Truly believe that
Solution to iot asmongold fog computing
Which is especially when I getting more computer power
To the edge
With the number of devices
We believe we'll see in the home
Moving to a distributor
System
I believe sets
Stage 4 that Ubiquiti
But we all hope for
Meaning that there's
There was more analytics happen
Coming at the edge
We sedated so to speak having to go up to servers because more can happen
Locally
Another benefit is
Less dependency on the cloud
If you lose your internet connection with Apple iPad
It's still function
Still control all of your lights
Over your local
Wi-Fi network
We are
Currently working on messaging are Bluetooth radio
Before you know redundant radio mechanism as well beyond
Wi-Fi
A host of
Advantages that moving to a distributed system
Will provide including supporting
Other Technologies
Because any company can
Run an application
Across our secure
Distributed Network in the home
Okay so let's talk about that let's say I make
Emotions
Sensor to work in conjunction
With your
Light pad
How would that work
In the future
Your computer's what
I mean we're talkin Bill Cloud to Cloud integration
Walking through that ability is directly
Device to device
Rather than cloud-to-cloud or device
Cloud etcetera
A manufacturer of emotion
Sensor or a moisture sensor
Bluetooth
Wouldn't necessarily have to create
Club on Gateway
They literally
Write an application that can
Run across our Network
And that provides them
The gateway to take
Garage sale
Locally
I would provide them
Autonomy or removing the dependency on
Cloud
I wish
Ultimately increases
The value to the user not user experience at
How much more
Security and privacy
Host of advantages to working in Arkansas
Distributed
And isolation from the cloud
Will when I say
If it's a hybrid right
Cloud and distributed systems I believe will will work
Together
To provide the most
Most value and
The highest degree of security and privacy
Okay so instead of
Worldview instead of doing an API
This
Instead is I'm building
A full-on
Does a lightweight up
No API needed you just
Loaded across our
Secure system and you're off and running
Really a viable proposition for a lot of these companies
What we're going to need to see is
Plum lightpads out there
What's your strategy for Conquering the world
Getting these
If you can go to sleep.
Bullet is about cobbossee critical mass but it doesn't just have to be
I like that
It's about the art
And this can be applied to any technology
Any device
It's really taking
A
New approach
The Internet of Things in the connected home
Far too long
The industry has been focused on
Central controller
Or hub
And we simply believe that
Bill Hobbs our solution for today's
Problem
And not
Forward-thinking
Enough
Every device in the home will eventually have the type of
Q Power
Capabilities
They will all simply be mashed
Together we are simply
First
To prove that that's possible
Wright real machine-to-machine communication
It's what we set out to prove and that's exactly what we're doing
And would you license is it
NOS I'm trying to think about like
Getting
It's one thing to be like hey this is an architectural we like it's another to get paid
People to adopt
Your version
Overall Market
It's certainly a possibility
We just started shipping 6 months ago 7 months ago
Our first priority is
To demonstrate that
That the feature-set and the user experience that we
I believe consumers
I would
Appreciate
He tried so hard
The game critical mass over the course of the next
12-24 months
And allow us
Learn
I'm not
Our device has a host of sensors in it and
We can begin doing some behavioral modeling and have a better understanding of their
Ihome's Network or
How they interact
Device
And we can make business
Decisions based off of what we learn
Dorado AR device but
Partnerships with
Third party companies that we are integrated with
Awesome
I'm very eager to
Try this out but also see how this distributed architecture works in the real world because you're right A lot of people seem to be
I'm trying to get to that direction which as a user I'm like yes please
To like
I guess have my lights rely on The Intern
Alright thank you so much for coming on the show today
It's been my pleasure I really appreciate you spending some time with us to learn more about plum
And thanks very much for having us this week's podcast thank you so much for listening and if you
I Can't Get Enough iot news remember you can always sign up for my Weekly Newsletter
Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot