Later on the show we talked about Phillips and a decision it made two
Take away some of the functionality
Its hub had that enabled it to work with some 3rd party lights
Well
Since the show was recorded Phillips actually reverse the decision that it made
It has recently upgraded the software so Philips Hue Lights
Didn't work with 3rd party lights
When we did the show
That still remain the case but on Wednesday
It actually reversed that
Because so many of its customers complained
So what is going to do
It's going to
Reverse the software upgrade so lights from other brands will continue to work as they did before with the Philips Hue system
So
In a statement the Phillips provided to me it says they will work on the reversal at the upgrade and they will shortly confirm when it will be available
When you guys here Kevin and I talked about this
Know that
While our discussion
Is still relevant
Phillips has decided that it will not
Kill off
Third party
Functionality
Hey everyone welcome back to the iot
Play podcast
This week we've got a great show for you
I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham and Azure co-host
Kevin tofel
So we're here to talk about
Canoes for hue
Great news from IBM and
And Watson
Cabins
Crazy do
I will call it mining operation and
In his office
And updates
And our guest is
Going to talk about
The connected kitchen and also
What to do
Decommissioning a connected device when your company gets sold
Sam
Exciting times
Alright so let's start with
What everyone's talking about this week which is
The hue
The hughleys
It's funny they have a new program a new certification program called friends with you and right now
I don't think anybody wants to be friends with you
They're cutting support for 3rd party bulbs
Yeah it is
It's brutal out there for a third party light bulb
Hand for a customer review
We first started getting reports of this when people were updating their Hue Lights
End
All the sudden there Cree there Ostrom there GE link bulbs
He had previously worked under the hue
Hug
We're certified under the zigbee light Link profile
Just suddenly stopped working
So if you weren't a hue light bulb you no longer worked with you
So just to be clear for people if they did not yet update
They're Philips Hue operating software to version 1.11 I know you can
Check that in the app
Man they still have the 3rd party compatibility
Mine still work
And I have not done the
There you go so
Word to the wise if you don't want to lose this
Boys for now
Maybe I love
You know
Maybe now it could be that he does a forced update
At some point in time
True
Let's talk about what's going on here because I'm very much open platform kind of guy so the fact that
The Hue Bridge already work with zigbee wireless particles was was
Plus
Is that not pretty standard that particle
It is it is
Okay I mean I think I know the answer I'm trying to give you the
Benefit of the doubt here by playing a little dumb
So basically they're they're closing things down a little bit more well okay
So here's that
It snows it be is a it's a radio
Now leichtling is actually a
Profile so that's software that runs on top of zigbee that zigbee assertive
Now zigbee is you guys may remember is kind of in a little bit of turmoil because of the up-and-coming
Red
All comes back to thread and we Haven
So with
Thread which is the nest Samsung
Freescale
Silicon labs
Kind of a couple other
Companies
And let's let's go see is Philip Sousa Porter of
Because that may answer some
Some of what may be coming out here may just be kind of some
Protocol confusion as they're trying to move to kind of support more modern standards like thread
It's it's kind of unclear like
What
Is happening here
Yeah and just as you were
Talking about this I looked up on thread group chat Oregon Phillips is a can
Contributing member to
The threat group
So maybe that
Maybe
It just
And even if it is happening and I'm okay with that but it's B
The manner that it's happening it's just pretty much somebody flipping a switch here in a software update
I don't think this was very well communicate
Headed to the users
It may not have
In-N-Out Phillips has always said though that
The support for these other
Bulbs
His
Always been
Kind of
Just support for this
Profile
So they have never been proactively
Testing or doing anything with these bulbs in
In their conversation with Cena
About this change what has happened is
Customers have been coming to them when these
Light bulbs have had issues or problems and it sounds like Phillips is like
This is become kind of a pain people are coming to us about bulbs not working
And we don't know what to do with it
And I get it and in fact they are actually going to deal with it because they do have this new friends of hue program
Wish hope
Let them certified
Designee bulbs bulbs that are no longer working after the software update may actually work in the future
If they go through the friends of hue program
And yes and so the question then becomes will Bosch how hard is it to
Become
You know interoperable with the friends of hue program
This is where
Something like
Alljoyn or
Some
Sort of real interoperable HTTP style standard for The Internet of Things
Would be
Freaking
Amazing
Because what is happen
Is instead of some sort of universal again HTTP is a wonderful example
Some sort of universal
Standard
We have interoperability
Programs
And
That means
Everybody has to work that much harder
To get things to work together
And it's kind of pain
For the consumer
For the startups for
For the big companies that have to set up these programs and then certified
Test everything
It's just really frustrating
Cuz I think about how cool it could be if
Your light bulbs just kind of talk to each other because you inserted like
One or two lines of code that said
Hey
Here's the code that says I'm a light bulb
We already work this out
And you know what I'm going to go back on Sunday cuz I gave incorrect information as I look something over here now that's on my screen
Apparently
Your light bulbs
If they're already added
Prior to the software update built
Continue to work
There may be problems but they will continue to work
The issue here or what would fill up the saying is they're stopping users from adding new third-party bulbs to setups
Oh so that's not as bad as originally thought which is a good thing
Seeing either Kevin or I have actually changed
Neither of us have updated because we're both like
We both have 3rd party light bulbs as part of our systems we don't want to break our home
Yeah
So now I don't feel so bad and it what I said about not getting a software update obviously it's a personal choice you guys on your device is not me but
Now I don't feel like
I need to hold off on that update
Will you let us know how it turns
What you know I don't have no plans to add any new third-party bulbs currently that could change in a week but
For now I'm comfortable saying yeah I'm okay with this now
See I kind of feel bad about this because I'm still waiting for my
White dimmer
BR30
From anyone
Except for you
Sex
Okay
So that the work
I can tell you that
I don't actually think you has the white
BR30
Don't know have not shot for any in awhile
No they don't they don't have
The white Bea Arthur
That was my
The only thing which case you need a third-party I need a third-party cuz all they have the $60 color
Send
So expensive
It is well don't update your tub
Well I was going to say I'm still not updating my light bulbs
I'm very sad about
Okay
So that is the Hue situation
That is Stacy's rant on interoperability for the day
Maybe we'll come back
Who knows
So
Little bit more we're going to move to some Enterprise news
IBM
Xi'an Tuesday
Igloo
Big blue
We don't talk a lot about Enterprise but it's a big deal in IBM
Back in March announced a 3 billion dollar iot initiative
And in September they appointed a woman named Harriet green to be the general manager of their internet-of-things practice
She's actually also the general manager at their education practice
I know random
I asked her about it and she's like yeah basically stuck
Kind of new business
Stuff that's me
Education iot
Sure
I spoke with her
Last week
And we talked about
IBM's initiatives in iot couple things worth mentioning
The announcement this week was about IBM throwing Watson at iot
Ye Ye Big Data Big Data
Intelligent learning
Use machine learning
I think I can just come
So Watson
You may know him
As hey
Computer that plays Jeopardy +
You actually play Jeopardy against Watson once
I did I lost
Well most people do
Interesting
I don't know if Peregrine told us or somebody else at IBM but I'm looking at your story now and I'm
Just flabbergasted about the amount of data
That they say connected devices are generating
Oh yeah it's a big number what was that number
Well
I'm going to Restasis
What are the square and given that IBM says there more than 9 billion connection devices operate today and those devices
Will generate 2.5 quintillion bytes of new data every day or the next 15
That's a lot of data
Angela Watson
Exactly and
Through
They say that most of that day. I think 90% of it is unstructured so it's in the form of
Words and structure tax social media things that
Normal computers can't read
Did you fight Watson
Watson is literate Bealls
It can take in that data
In processing
I don't mean to cut you off that's really interesting to me because I think of how much
Structured data like that we work with on a daily basis as writers and consumers and so on
I'm surprised that there's been no standardization
For this data maybe pick up the breadth of devices and that type of data but you know why can't they use XML or
Where are Json or something
Trinetx the data structure
Have you seen like
That will this is things like doctor's note
Consider just scanned in
Right right yeah it's it's such a range of data I mean a light bulbs going to generate different bigger than a doctor
Is Kendall Jenner a different data than my Raspberry Pi and sunset where I get it I get it sorry diverse
It's just an interesting problem
And it's important to know that when you're dealing with IBM
IBM's Best Inn
Biggest hammer in their toolbox
Is Watson
So
When you have Watson
Every
Have you read your stinking structure problem looks like a nail that Watts
There are some really cool things so what they've done is they have on top of IBM has a product called the iot
Foundation cloud
Which is their Cloud for The Internet of Things they've got
It's basically if you want to build a connected product they've got
I'm a partnership with arm
And so
Certain arm-based chips
Will send their data automatically up to IBM's Cloud if you want to
Appropriate code
It doesn't automatically happen if you write the code
And then you can start sending your data up there where it's at
Organized and Cooling
Infinitely scalable
And
Now you have access to it basically like a
For API calls for Watson services
It's in those are
Add API for voice recognition so
And a Predictive Analytics service
A video and image recognition service and a textual analysis
That's actually really cool so like
You know about the unstructured data
You got access to that
If.
Voice recognition natural language processing service
The Predictive Analytics that GE always talks about that's in there too
And then the video and image recognition kind of stuff that you know Facebook and Google all talk about
Actually use in their products you can actually get access to some of that from Watson
In IBM's iot
So those are the big things that IBM launch today
And it's actually pretty sweet
And today by today I mean this week
Cuz today happens to be Tuesday the recording this but you will not hear it until 3
Gobots
Show the one other notable thing for you guys out there
Is IBM's taking a very vertical strategy
With the internet of things as opposed to kind of what I think of is a horizontal strategy that the Silicon Valley
Folks are taking
And that is worth noting because
It seems to be very bifurcated based on
Where you're coming from so a lot of the old school Industries
Like Cisco GE IBM they're like
Cricket at this like
Here's my solution
I even sat Solutions
Like I'm some sort of corporate
But here is a set of products for the retail industry
Here's some for the
Automotive industry
Aerospace
Where is a lot of the start of some companies I talk to
Cancel is Bali there like
You know what here's a sensor platform you guys do with it what you will so I'm really interested to see how that
Pans out because
They're very different
Ways of looking at kind of the Industrial iot
Throwing that out there you guys
Shall we take it back
Sure
All right
You want to talk about what we should do a quick messed up
The last we talked about my Nest trying to
To laugh roast
At 4 a.m. when the garage door open even though it didn't
Right
Dennis told me at the time that it was my MyQ that was doing
Well
We turn off the MyQ
And it didn't stop
I called Napa
I know
We're like no we call that one
We did
So
Ness was like oh you know what we read the logs wrong
We think it's your job
A Jawbone
So
I did set up my Jawbone to work with my Nest but I have a jaw bone
It's the Jawbone move it it's the El Cheapo Jawbone as I like to
To think of it
Because I lose them
I've lost every Fitness monitor no matter how fancy it is
And so
50 bucks
So
I connected it but when I was connecting and I realized this
One actually doesn't talk to my house because it doesn't have what it needs to do to actually connect
With my house it only works on the up to and Beyond
So
This one doesn't talk to my house
If it was connected and so that's what they said was causing the problem so I disconnected that
And it hasn't tried to roast
Xiaomi since
I don't know if that was
The problem
I can't really
Say with much confidence because we actually had a heat wave in Austin
And I ended up turning my air conditioning back on
Gotcha so
We're going to stay tuned
I'm not sure if the problem is solved
Maybe
Maybe.
I'd still be surprised if that's what it was but okay let's see what happens
So there is the
Yes I do or maybe not on
So that's the update there so Kevin
You want to talk about your
Your latest purchase
Yeah, it was a waste of money I'll say that right up front but
I learned so much
Never waste of money to learn
Don't know I agree I agree and when we were talking before the show you know I kept thinking I have to justify this purchase to you because it believed
Doesn't a lot of
Value for the cost and talking about a $35
USB Asic or application specific integrated circuit
I'm using the solar USB dongle
In a Raspberry Pi for very low energy Bitcoin mining
Right of the bat
I'm not going to get rich I've been doing this for three days and I barely heard a penny
Okay
But
And this is where I get into the hotel location bit
I had to learn
Didn't have to I enjoyed learning so much about how Bitcoin works
How do you say
Specific
Pieces of Hardware actually work
I have never ever surprisingly never built
An application from source code in Linux and I got to do that so that was cool
And I'm just having so much fun looking at the little grass so this thing turning out hashes for Bitcoin
It's actually got me interested in buying
More robust hardware for Bitcoin mining
And the big advantage of that I have over many other people that do this
I don't pay for electricity because I've got 41 solar panels on the roof for the house so
Most
Months of the year we have no bill actually
Over producing in Wipro
Balance of power hurdle up a bank account of power in with our electric pump
That's the big thing is Bitcoin mining people I got to pay for electricity
I don't have to say I think I might actually
Take us away further
If you're going to do that
I don't recommend
Doing it on Raspberry Pi with
I bought the Avalon
Nano USB
Asic for this again $35 that cost me
It was a lot of fun it was challenging to I'm just getting the
The pie to recognize the USB port
For some reason was was a struggle that
You don't have to couple hours at anchor and I had a lot of fun doing it and I learned a lot
All right and so
We're talkin
Is it is it the $20 pie the $35 pie
I've had it for a while so I don't think the $35 one is probably one step down
The beauty is the pie can actually still be used as a regular pie was going on because
All of the processing for Bitcoin
Mining
Is offload to this USB dongle
It's to the point now where Bitcoin mining is so
Challenging
Intensive about Computing process
Irregular CPU or even most gpus it be a waste
She have to buy these very specific Bitcoin mining pieces
Is hard work I do at this point
So
Soledad is also did say
Did the pie
Utilization of the CP on the pies like 1%
I'm doing all this
I was going to say so I can't like offload
Sekrit like a city from my home
Call the computers in my home network
It's somebody it's funny you say that because I was doing crunches numbers for Saturday while I still can on another computer and
And before that
And I got to thinking why isn't anybody built
Those typos
Number crunching
Bits for for specific Hardware
You know it's probably just too expensive like a study program to do that but
It would be really interesting because they're so they're very application-specific
No you can't like uses for seti or something like that
It doesn't know how to do that
Candy with one thing and one thing on it
The funny thing
Lake Mead
4 senses
Month for $35
Yeah
Why can several years that thing
Payforit
Yeah sure
And and you wrap the ice pack around it
FeFe
Don't go
All right well I sent you a picture of an ice pack extra that was my heatsink yes
I got to figure something out getting hot
Like I'm being sued that
Picture in the show notes Here
Just for fun
Yes that they're doing mining bitcoins on a Raspberry Pi door for pennies per month and we're using an ice pack
Turn the freezer as a heat sink
Adjust. It does not get any better than that
Nice
The talent this is how we're paying for the pike
All right
Let's see also this week we had some
Some sad news
Happy news I don't know what to call
I will call it in
Determinate news
The orange Chef Co which made I don't know if you remember this Kevin but
We got all excited about it
The prep pad was
Connected scale
You may have actually purchased one
I have the drop scale kind of
It's slightly different market segments but
The prep had was $150 scale it was connected sold at Williams-Sonoma
And another retailers
And it you know when you wave stuff
When you put stuff on the scale it would weigh the ingredients you would tell
App what it was and it would
Tell you the nutritional information in what you are making
And I thought it was a great idea
30000 people bought it but it wasn't enough
And so last week
The orange Chef Co sold to yummly
Front undisclosed amount 60% of the staff went to
Yummly which is a recipe app
So our guest
Up next is Santiago Maria
Who is now the chief Revenue officer at yummly and he's going to talk about
What comes next
Gimli after it has acquired this company
And he's going to talk about kind of the lessons he learned building
A hardware device that ultimately didn't succeed
Why it's important to kind of
Create and build a device
For iot with failure in mind
It's
It is I feel good topic but it's actually really important one in in Santiago is great
Ensuring Lessons Learned so stay tuned
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast did I have as our guest
Santiago mobile
Who is the chief Revenue officer now at Jung Lee
Santiago
Welcome back to the show
And since the last time we talked you have had a title change in a company change
Oh my goodness
What happened
Thank you thank you yeah
I don't think happened then you know we
It's funny cuz we want to
Smart Kitchen Summit
Between
Presentation
I had a great conversation with Dave from yummly
If you're from Yemen
Translate to Maria today so
I'm going to say that you were you were part responsible for that just you being there
Just might miss your presence alone
For you guys who may be turning in a little late or in case Kevin and I don't mention it what happened was
Earlier this actually it was last week now
Gradle with
With the time shift here
Is that
Yummly purchased
The orange chef
And the orange Chef Co make
Coupled products
There's these cool like films that youku
Can put over your iPad in the kitchen
It made the prep pad which
You are a long time listener of our previous show over at the
I coveted the scale for quite some time it was
Scale
You put your food on it
Temperature actually put your ingredients on it
As you were cooking and it measured the nutritional information of the
Final product
Yes
There is a going to be
A new product
Countertop
It sounded really amazing
Integrated
Like a Vitamix
Mixer and I love my Vitamix blender it's a blender not a man
Mixer
With kind of
Similar products
That also measured kind of your food intake and then made personalized recommendations for you like based on your activity
Get connected with
Was it all fitness trackers or was it like
If it's a jaw bone
Ashley Santiago
Tell me what it was
Yes it's a nation job
Stacyplays
I'm so.
Integration analysis to get your IQ today.
Show you
You know Russian Tilikum Nations that will fit your day
What's granite countertop
Actually
Mostly on a software upgrade
From The Hobbit perspective you have some new components
Another to retrofit appliances
But honestly like
Stephanie trost
You know
Indiana software
You know I say this because
A lot of people are like yummy like
I don't understand.
But it makes a little sense because
We have to we have to tell them first we haven't told them what deadly is yet
Pretty Woman
I have amazing children
I'm just doing now
I don't think most people know like
Call DWTS personalization
Now whatever I talked to young lady they have been very much
About rethinking the recipe in kind of
Rethinking how we can have digitized food which I've always been Keen
I got this huge thing where am I
I eat a lot of food
I love food I love cooking but I always have a hard time
With the idea like I really want
Track what I eat
Also track
Like the food in my kitchen in in my recipes for keto when I grocery shopping
Everything Auto
I totally outed myself
Last episode
Admitting that I don't actually grocery shop my husband
But I would love for
The recipe creation
And the generation
Can the shopping list
Bli bli
So very fascinating
What
Is the combined company
Can I do
So
It's already doing
Most people don't realize
The current version update
Asiago
They are
Going crazy
A personal exemption
1 significance test
Refugium
Yummy basically start understanding
The underlying
Young Thug standing
In general
Type stars in the standing light
Massage
Trends
Trencin ingredients
Understand site combination of ingredient substitutions
What a specific person likes and dislikes
Incredible because
You know
Create
Instead of
Glad You Know lyrics
Google create very specific
Sign if your if you care about nutrition because
Emily is that
Cuz like you guys don't have to reinvent
The wheel
And you get a wider mainstream audience right
She's like I love you so much and I love you so much because
Hold on
State we are doing the same thing but you guys started dislikes or 6 years ago
You have no
Over 11.5 million users
Okay
Obviously we need to talk a lot
Baby on countertop
I need a 182
Why do I need to scale for
Kaiser travel recommendation engine
Seacoast ideas
Okay
People like you know what they're looking for
I'm making you know another way
We will need to find another source of income
In the meantime
Fine sanding
To be able to
Types of
So as a hardware person to it
It's time
As and as someone who almost spent a hundred
$50 at Williams
Sonoma to buy your scale
Last Christmas
It's time to figure out
What happened
To the prep pad
Because I believe you said you had 30000 users
You know I seen that
What you were born to do when your
I don't know what your interests are you for the hot water if you want to discontinue
Because
You can just like
Dependence on cell phone
You can just like turning off on
The right way to go about it
Continue working
Puppy Bowl Channel
New features
Time machine
Is tomorrow for whatever reason like we don't talk anymore like
How do we keep the spark alive
That be cancer
Unuseful project
Right let's talk about that strategy
In just a little bit more depth did you have like an escrow account to
Fund
Developers for it I mean cuz
It's one thing to be like I am committed to this
I mean take it to need to update features with new
As is the new operating systems come out that's
That requires effort
I don't know if there's a cloud service
EAS
A combination of
Also have people that are like you know
Investing in this company
Shenzhen Supply
They care about you so so you talk to these people Sunday
Understanding the tape
She likes
Yolanda name
Updating executing a Touchback
You have to think about what each product like
Brings to the table in Sons of Anarchy
A sample that is very very
It's a consonant generating
EmazingLights
Food data
Site
Only Starlight you know looking at information as a whole
Trends looking at trends of a people are eating what kind of food you like abortions combined with what
Amazing Frog
So someone that has a
An interest in understanding these trends
Might be able to keep the experience alive
Just2good
Trident 3 Tucson
Sheetrock screws
I think there's a couple kind of interesting things
In
About
What you guys have just gone through
Then you actually managed to sell your company which is
Great
MCU
Men should take 60% of your Workforce you're still supporting your product
In many cases what has happened here is probably not the ideal scenario that you were hoping for it going
And I think
In in Silicon Valley there's this
This kind of fail fast kind of
Ethos end
I think with software that's really great but with
Connected products
In kind of the internet of things that may not be the right mentality
So specific to iot
What are kind of the lessons you have learned in building the orange Chef that you would like to share
With the audience
Yeah
Baby pink
I think you understand me with your love
Elisa company what year it is
What I mean by that is not just a direct communication with them but I also like I just explain like
A very well put-together strategy
So it's okay to try
Out there that I'm not
Iot weather like
She's such a storm.
Discontinued
Discontinued all the time
For whatever reason we sing.
It'll probably be when you forever
What is a banana
Chiquita banana
$50
And hopefully that will never
Of course
You put somebody down there
Yuya
Christian stopping supporting
After
A very short period of time
What happens next what happens if you take too much
It's very very very important and you have to have that
Wrok
Isopod concept
You can do it
I just need the right way
Big Show
Make sure that
An expectation that should be like
People shouldn't take
Play Coyote toxicity
Do you think they
Exposed to
No
1T. And support.
Anywhere between two and three years
Just kidding.
Vertical
A shorter lifespan
Okay that was good advice
Any other
Okay that was still the first one
Be mindful of
All that kind of stuff
Fundraising list
Biggest
Penn State
Like I kind is wrong
I underestimated
How much money in the beginning
I just turned everything like
On the present and the future
Because even though you used to justify your future
Information on the rain today
I'm so
Fairy
I'm guessing your friend racing
You have to be
Denton jail
Lower margin set soft
So
In general
Company
Should have
Lower margins for
What I mean by this is like you can expect to
Who is the singer on this company
I have the same type of
Population
The Sofa Company
Beijing
A color that you're selling
I saw you
Larger than
Sales
Questioning like this
AliExpress.
Is it impossible if it's more difficult
Specific
You know how that much more longer-term like
Strategy for fundraising.
Email software which allows you to like
Change
Pinterest
Slapstick
Sew in
Credible
Shuffle bike don't have
If you're really like
It is really like something you want to do
Just do it
Difficult
Yes
Is it
Descendants songs
But that shouldn't be in a position to prevent you from life
Doing something
Be mindful.
Alright inspiring words
I love it
Alright thank you for making the time to talk to us in
What was probably super busy week for you
Congratulations
Since I'm moving over to yummly
I'm excited even though I may never get my retrofitted connected Vitamix blender
Attachment
Never Say Never Never Say Never
Around Partnerships and Revenue
How to explain to school in Germany
I will never say never I just
Just now
Thank you so much for coming on this
Absolutely thank you
That's it for this week thanks for listening and we'll see you next week on the iot podcast