Hey everybody is Stacy
Higginbotham if you are listening to The Internet of Things podcast
We are back and here is my co-host
Kevin tofel
Welcome to the show
We've got a lot of news today we've got some exciting Gadget reviews and we have a great guest
Who actually is also the CEO of the gadget company
So we're having a gadget
You are
And I'm a business gal and acatic how so many
So let's get started with the exciting news that is not exciting
Actually it's kind of sad
That's a terrible Segway so ninja blocks
Company out of Australia that was making a really cool
Home hub
Device
Call the Ninja sphere
It looked kind of like
Heck it looks like an alien ship that was
Landed on your coffee
Table basically it was part Spear and part pyramid they called it a Stearman
They did and we had we had Pete Moore who was a co-founder of the Ninja sphere
Made by the company that made ninja blocks
On the podcast about a year-and-a-half ago and he talked about kind of
Thinking of his thinking about the market and designing this thing and
Kind of the differentiating factor about the ninja sphere
Was that it used gesture
Controls that used EMF actually
To figure out
Where your hands were in in the room
Seafood Chester to the ninja sphere to turn your lights on
Or
Actually was mostly used for lighting but I thought that was a very nice you I think
Cuz it it kind of conceited it maybe you don't have your phone on you all the time and maybe you don't want to pull it out of your
Pocket
And open it up and
Turn on your lights
Comedian
This is true
And I tell you it was an interesting looking product
It was really expensive I'm in a hit
Carbon cost of a normally do but
$249
It was a bit much I think
It was it was expensive and so what happened
They wrote a blogpost about it
They ran out of money
They
They spend a lot of time developing the sphere
And
Basically
They
They couldn't raise their next round
And all but 300 of the Ninja Spears were built in box
And the ready to go
So they are going to ship those
If you ordered one
And you didn't
If you ordered one and
You're one of the 300 that
I can't make
They're going to prioritize those by those who
Ordered more than one
Set the ordered multiple ninja Spears you're probably only going to get one of them
And they're hopeful that maybe they'll get
Somewhere someone nice will give them additional money to get those last three hundred
If you bought from the site within the last few months you'll be getting a refund
And
Kickstarter backer Kickstarter backers will receive their Spears
I'm in
Sanders
Yeah it is sad
And
Yeah
That is
That is sad
And there's the only other thing I would like to point out is they did talk about like the cloud cost because
How to make the ninja blocks
They have
Scale back some of the
Features and servers associated with the ninja block service
So they're going to try to keep that as well
To keep that going as long as possible
So you should expect it may go down
But they're going to let you know before
And that's kind of an interesting conundrum for anyone
Who buys into some of these cloud
Back products
I was just going to say that we've talked about this past shows how
I kind of prefer to have a
A Smart Hub in my house that's not really cloud connected but
More something that I'm in control of
Because while this is one of the reasons I think there's a couple of the reasons that I would prefer that but this is a Big E
It is in you know Cloud connected services do
Kum & Go it's it's very hard
I guess if you don't have a big back or two
Even if you do have to be back or Sony actually
There's a internet
Austin's 404 kind of Tumblr that
Tracks this sort of thing there's actually not that many products on it but
Sony's aibo robot I don't know if you remember the robot dogs they were like
Been around awhile
Sewing
2014 they finally took those offline officially
So they stop supporting them
There no more
Little doggies
They put him down
I flipped a switch and put my puppy down
Companies don't support their products forever
That is the moral here
So sad news
I'm for the ninja blocks
I Spy
I think they did it the right way they were very transfer
You know you can feel in their posts that they wrote that they were kind of bummed about this whole thing
They're doing what they can and they're trying to let
What does
So
There we go now we'll move on to
A big company doing something
I don't really know if
Happy or not it's just a big company doing something
Today at The Internet of Things World Conference in San
Cisco
Samsung
You may have heard of him
Has launched a
Series of chips called the Arctic chips for The Internet of Things
Benton done in competition with Intel
Qualcomm broadcom freescale
Nxp
All the other
Atmel
Really every building tips for The Internet of Things
So there are three of them
There's the Arctic
1 which is a
Tiny little looks like in MCU
Bluetooth and A9 access
Sensor looks like a
Nine access
Gyroscope accelerometer
Addison's motion sensor on there on the Arctic. IO site
Okay
And that is running
Embedded artists the nucleus OS its artists from mentor Graphics I know that
I've heard of other companies using this there's a good Chilean million artists out there so
Is that your flavor of the month
That's what it's running
And that's design for really small
Things
I don't know if it would run in watches that's my guess
Watches kind of things designed to work with the phone
And then the bigger versions
AR
Downtown and smarter phone is kind I think maybe
Smart Hub and
Door lock
It's hard to say it's hard to say me when you look at the the specifications for the Arctic 5 in the Arctic 10 you start
Getting close to a glow and smartphone
Processors here in Reno
Dual core and octa-core arm chips
512 Meg memory or 2 gig of memory
You get the addition of
Zigbee and Wi-Fi the 802 11bgn flavors
So you start getting you no more until
It was like a low on smartphone
But this is the Internet of Things Kevin so we're Thinkin thermostat
Connect sub
Yeah
Feel like
Smartphones
Police seem pretty powerful force a thermostat or something I mean they're talking about
Hardware video codecs you know of
720p decoding at 30 frames a second for the Arctic 5 in
1080p video decoding Sullivan
But it seems like overkill for a thermostat I don't know what they're going to use these for
Well I mean maybe if you
You stick it I mean if you think about
Kind of a connected wall plate for example
You might want that to run
That's what you just can't
Maybe not Netflix but you might want to run videos who's at your front door or a tree
Brown birds
Your canoe
Office
I have no I
Sew in
Honestly
They're probably I assume they're repurposing
I think I read somewhere that they're repurposing their exynos line
Chips so
It makes sense that
It might be a little Overkill but
You start out with some intelligence in one place and you never say Kush
I wish I could do less with
Whatever says that
Not nothing you typically not a good strategy for business no
So
So that's what these are and
On the OS side
I was kind of surprised
I don't know if you were but
They aren't running tizen
Yeah that does surprise me because you and I sat at that it's a small world keynote at CES were
Samsung song about Internet of Things
And we're all going to come together in one ginormous Global Group Hug
And Tyson's going to be the platform the ties it all together for Internet of Things
There's no mention ties at all instead it's all
Yo Arduino that uses nucleus OS
Programming in Java and C + + +
Yeah
Where's the worst Eisen
I don't know but there is so there is
For development environment on these chips they do support groovy which is what the SmartThings
Home hub is using in SmartThings was bought by Samsung
For those of you guys out
There who are like
High on SmartThings
That is the Samsung chip announcement
Well we'll move into broadcom also it internet-of-things world had an announcement that
A lot of people might be excited about
One is a chip that does faster Bluetooth CC speed of
Give me the rates
Yay
That'll actually be good in your watch
Oh please hit need to let me just say that right now
Because all the appdata on the Apple watch coming from the iPhone it says it's faster sometimes for me to just blow the phone
I kid you not
I wouldn't doubt that is this the first generation
I probably excited about is the
Is a software
Platform
On top of it
Chips
Developers and
This one they're adding homekit to it software platform
And as part of that
It's called wicked
Platform
They're supporting homekit
And
We're kind of reading in between the lines are actually we're not it talks about it directly
It talks about how it's supporting the bridging strategy
For homekit
And basically
It talks about having the bridge and capability to connect in points that are not homekit enabled
Yay
Yeah in fact they specifically Give an example they say this was a product like a bluetooth smart light bulb
To connect to a Smart plug containing brockhampton
Protons wecan module
Creating a bridge from the bulb to the homekit supported app on there
IOS device
So
Dairy Queen
So yes and it says
It'll make it easier for customers
Using Siri or iOS application stink
Patrol
Homekit enabled
Just kidding
That's not that's not in
I got all excited like I could use Siri to control mine on home can not yet not yet
Not yet my suspicions would be Apple products
Woodforest support that and then Applewood opencv upload more
That's the hope
Apple stuff
Now
So that's that's kind of the big news for this week I can't think of other big news items
So here we got sadness
And we've got chips
How about a little
Joyous light bulb
Review
Joyous life reviews I love it so yeah it last week I sent Kevin I had the shoe folks send Kevin's
Some light bulbs so he could actually get in on this internet of things and smart home stuff that we always talk about
It's about time right now
It is about time yes I did not have to unpack her like my own
Stuff
From my
Move that didn't happen last year
Instead the Hue bulbs were sent here alone with a bridge
You were right on the last year you said this and take me like
5 minutes to set up
Kudos to the folks at Hugh because it took even last time I mean literally
Pulled out the
Raspberry Pi that I have connected to my home router over ethernet
And I plugged in the hue light Bridge instead in its place
Literally press the button on that had tube light bulbs already turned on screwed into the
Various textures and boom that was it
I never just a matter of getting the apps but Hue app on my iPhone
And I'll be honest I like the Hue app
Far better on my phone that I do on my Apple watch more than a second
You obviously said Stacy you've used up the Hue app so you know what it's like you can
Pick the color of any and all lights you can change the
Brightness on any of them so I was having fun with that
The iPhone
And then because I do have an Apple Watch it says hey we got Apple watch sport do you want to put that on your Apple watch I said sure
It's kind of limited
I'd say it's more like the
Like a widget
Basically did
Literally you pre-load certain scenes for your lights on to your Apple watch if you got off on the phone
And then when you go in the Hue app on your watch you have those scenes
I just have them
And the lights change so
You can't control brightness there I would love to see that digital Crown be a nice little
Raise or lower the brightness level
But maybe that's not possible just yet so
It is early days as you said the Apple watches version 1
I don't have to use my phone to actually change the colors of the lights are
You know cuz I can do that from The Watch
But it still has a little bit of control to be desired yet
Have you seen on other watch apps a little bit less of the widget feeling more of a true
Absol
You know I didn't look for I know there are other third party app
But I really just wanted to use the native
Hue app to give it a full
Taskus
I think most people who buy these bulbs are probably not going to go search around for apps are going to follow the instructions in the
In the cat and if they are going to go get my
My app from for iOS or Android
I don't know if they're going to venture beyond that
Oh I was thinking more
Less specific and more just in general on other
Apps
Okay well
Play honestly the only true native apps on the Apple watch a really those from Apple itself
Even though with the watch
Kid platforms available
Developers can't create native app so basically what they are they're all extensions of iPhone apps
Right now meaning they're very much like widgets
You can do notifications and glances and such but again
I'm seeing more of them that look and feel just like the widget you might add to your
Your notification screen on iOS right now
It again early days
Apple hasn't really opened it up yet for
Richer functionality
Okay
So now
Edwin Sumo CA an insteon review
Right
You just you just wet my appetite
Now I want the insteon
I'm kind of tired from screwing any three light bulbs to be
Describe my life
It's on my to-do list
I look at my Apple watch in the to do zits on there
There we go
I can't wait to see
All right
I will report back actually on me
On the Amazon Echo
In the house just a quick little reporting back I've noticed it getting a little wonky or lately
Hue Lights
In the last
Week
It has been
It has responded when I asked it
To turn off the lights
It said okay but then it doesn't turn them off
So
It's it's kind of interesting I'm trying to figure out what is going on on the back end
Or maybe we need like a full reboot of the system
I don't know so
I reached out to Amazon to try to figure out what might be happening
On the back end
And I guess I should reach out to you as well
I'm just to see it because
And then I'm curious readers
I guess you could be listeners listeners noticing the same thing if you got this
You know tight end
Let me know info at iot podcast
Dot-com
Because
It's a little weird
Cuz it it had been working perfectly and now it's getting a little
A little laggy and a little
Iffy
So
Silly silly Cloud systems
I know how do I reboot the cloud
Okay so we're going to start a new segment on the show
We're going to see how it works but we're calling it
It's in the spirit of it podcast and other clever naming
The 5-minute device review
What will it be let's see probably five minutes of device review
Where to take 7 minutes and talk about flowers
So this is
5 minutes
On a device
I haven't actually time this so it may actually not be 5 minutes may take a little more a little less
But this week's device is going to be
The Mayo
And demaio is an armband
That you guys
You put it on your
Forearm
And it is a gesture control
Device
It is brand new
Well it's actually not that day was about a year old
You can buy it now from Amazon and you have been able to buy it for the last
Couple months
$199 it's from a company in Canada
And
It's called Thelma claves
And they sent me one because on Thursday they're announcing basically that you can now use them IO to control press
Presentations
I have been excited about the Mayo since it was announced back in like
Because I think gesture control is really fascinating
I've been playing with it all the way back in
Thinking about like using
A disco
A disco kind of rmotion till I turn on my lights
Party boat I thought I'd be like
Superfine
Even then Stacy was hooked on the lights
Even then yes
I'm I'm hard to live with
And in my disco our motion is is over-the-top completely
So
I just did
There's a place for gesture in the home and with the Internet of Things
So when they announced this I was like huh
This could be really interesting
So having tested it for only about an hour or so
I think it's too much money
To spend on a very limited use case
Unless
You have
Severe Mobility problems
The presentation thing was not as interesting to me because they don't give a lot of presentations that I actually think if you were giving a
A lot of presentations
Some of the gestures like double tap in
Making a fist and rotating them
Would actually be very distracting
4 people watching you give the presentation
It would be kind of like
What what is she doing up there why is she doing that little weird mining dance thing with her arms
But
You can actually assign mouse keys to
De Mayo
And keyboard keys to the Mayo
Fairly easily and that's what I was playing with
And so you can actually
Instead of like clicking on your mouse
You can actually
Assignment
This rotation so instead of a double tap
I assigned a fist rotation
Is that was actually kind of fun
It wasn't
Exactly practical
I think I would have to spend a lot more time
Figuring out the
Smoothest Jester and then training myself to actually
Instead of using a mouse just using
Tamao and my body
Right
We had a lot of promise and
Since I have
Especially towards the summer a lot of carpal tunnel
I thought it might be worth it cuz I actually spend 75 or 80 bucks on like a really fancy
Sideways Mouse
Another hundred and something on
Dragon dictation software so
Yeah I think you're hitting the nail on the head I see this more as a
Essex
Tool for people have limited Mobility because this doesn't just
Just measure how your forearm itself is moving but as you said
You can make a fist you can
Do different
Gestures at the finger level
Because they're
Special
It has sensors that
Can actually track finger movement as well
So that there's a lot you could do with it and for somebody with limited Mobility I could see a lot of value here
Exactly it
Because what it does is it
It rests right in your forearm and it's actually
It seems
Pretty comfortable to me
I don't know how long the battery last
And it does take up a USB
Port for the Bluetooth
Connectivity
If your if
Short on ports that something to think about
End
Like the tapping there's there's
The finger motion there's fist
And then there's like a
Lego
Forward backwards risk music
I meant with your hand that's kind of
Fun and useful and I'm not sure
Again
I haven't I haven't played with it enough for set up the right sequence that I would feel comfortable using it all day long yet
It's definitely worth playing with
Or something like that or even
I would be really interested in getting a physical therapist
Play with it and set up
Something for me or for someone who's having a hard time using it
I think that would be kind of
Definitely worth paying for it if you
Could set up something effectively
Sure I could see potential industrial uses as well robotics
Control and such like that
Picnic, collapsed at that you should get a full day use out of a single charge so the battery should last you all day but
I don't say how much of a day that is in constant use or
Occasionally yours about the day so
My mouse uses
Pretty constant so
I did not I did not have there is no Disco
Disk arm movement
Unfortunately
I'm going to have to wait for
For something to do
Control my Hue Lights
There is also a developer
Platform for that so if you want to play with it and you have $199
You go right ahead
If you have
Some technical Little Star
Will be excited
Maybe I'll try it
I'll try
Your app out
So
Are just coming up is Andrew Thomas who is a co-founder of skybell which is a
Wifi controlled
Doorbell
That shows you who's at your door
And they're part of the
Bevy of startups that got the deal with Comcast last week there also homekit partner
So stay tuned to hear from him about kind of
How he got those deals and kind of the choices he's had to make because of them and
I think that's it so we'll see you next week sounds good
We have on her show today Andrew Thomas who is the co-founder of a company called skybell
Hey Andrew
Thanks for coming on the show
Hake fish is absolutely thanks for having me
I am super excited because
You make a product that
Actually I want I really wanted one of these for a while and I've tried a couple in have been a little disappointed in summer
A couple of yours but couple of other products in this kind of
World Of Products
So you make a connected doorbell that offers a camera
And when someone
Ring the doorbell
It sends a notification to my phone and it also can send me a video
Yes exactly
Skybell is a wifi-enabled video doorbell and it replaces your current doorbell
And I don't actually have to be on my Wi-Fi network in that case
That's correct
Absolutely you can be
UPS guy just leave it at the door.
Sign for it
Exactly
Calling you if you don't leave it there
There were there we have it I could beg maybe it would happen
The skybell is available for 199 you can buy it on amazon.com
Bestbuy.com and if you want to see it in person
Have to go into a Best Buy store
We're having on the show because this week you guys actually just signed a really big deal or I think it's a big deal
You signed a deal with Comcast
And you are one of nine actual Partners in their Xfinity home business and
I thought it was kind of significant what did you think about this deal
I didn't get to marry
Significant
About the announcement and CVT fluid in
Xfinity home announcement
I need a Comcast has a great plan for
Answer
You know the market and the team is focused and they have
More security for their plot on by letting their users know who got their door
Animal Control
You may be above all else.
Their attitude about the
Space
Secondary
Ashley Nissan
Trinity 2
Creative very nice Seacoast
And they have always prioritized
A user which is very important for us to so
Are same values
Nursing priorities on
Finding out how to
Create a truly good user experience and presenting it to their subscribers and
Responsible
Or a little
As they want
And
So we wanted to be a part of that
Excited about it
Got it so you guys
Now have this Comcast partnership and before
This you are also a
An apple homekit partnership I recall seeing your your name up in lights
Last
WWDC
On stage in June and
That's a big deal to so
How are you kind of
Managing all these Partnerships are how are you kind of thinking about how you're going to sign these Partnerships going forward as a
Start up with kind of limited resources
That's a great question
The Apple announcement for homekit was
Almost a year ago now
It was
Such a big moment
At that time
We work
Just barely under a year old
Six months removed from Shipping our first product
Sky Valley
Included in that keynote presentation
Left us speechless it was such a big moment for us and it was
It was a big validation for
Geico
The device but I think also skybell
As a group of people who want to make a great product
How people
So I think they
Validated
The company in division
Omniscience
Answer your question how do we prioritize
To work with the best company
In the world
And our goal is to get Sky those on more home so that people have
The security mean a feedback we get some people just continues to motivator
Forwarding
And we've already been apart of preventing a couple of break end
And when you get these stories it just motivates you want to get high though
Von Maur home so
And when you look at
I can do retail item
Partner with people I can look at resellers what we love about Sky balls at
We can participate in all of those
Go to market Channel
And someone can go to Best Buy and just say
Autographs
That wants to be part of a greater whole
The Naked Bee
Your home care
Smother clowns
I'm working it out staying or they can say I want someone to come in and help me
Comcast
Come help me and you take care of it
Set it all up for me
Ridgid work perfect I want to reach people every way
So for us
Having these two companies who are absolutely top in their class
Just phenomenal
And
As we move forward we're going to continue looking at the best companies and what can we do with them too
Create good user experiences
You'll raise money and build a table supporter
Are they decent
Validate user company and used to think that
Top priority
Have the resources
If it's bigger deals
Will let me see cuz
In previous conversations you've actually told me about
Kind of when apple called you up that first time to tell you about being a home kit partner asked you about it
Because you know they didn't put your name up on stage without letting you know first thank God you might have
I don't know what would have happened
So why don't you
Tell us about that because I mean for any company in this space
Having Apple give you a call and say hey you want to work together that's probably pretty cool
I don't know if they've never called me up and said hey you want to work
Together
Absolutely right
It was
Really cool I mean
That's that's what you want right so when we
Start a company
Next to Wi-Fi doorbell so
People can see who's at their door
We had an idea who we wanted to work with
And he's already I wouldn't it be nice
We did that
Basically
13 +
Nanjing 2014
So literally
Island paperwork
Spell announcement was made in
Yes I have that happened
In between those two
X.
One by we got the message and
I first had that conversation
And they come to you right
Track
Big they reach out to us
We were only a couple months old
It was just starting out an Indiegogo and finish
It was just amazing and we just didn't think that would happen
So quickly
And have them
Reach out to us to just save
We love what you're doing
And
Don't why don't we start having
Conversations
Curly it is
We just weren't we couldn't be happier in
Incredible
So speaking of all of this I have to ask you and
When
When is Apple
Going to actually release their home kit product
Estates at the top one
I don't know if
I'm going to space where I can answer that for you I'm really sorry but
Yeah but have to plead the Fifth
Sofitel B
You have to kill me
Is that is that what I'm hearing
Yeah that's what I'm about
I even like how you're he won't even threatened to kill me here in the here on the podcast you're so that you're so nice
So I will wait for then I will I will keep my
My I will wait for my Apple products
And
Maybe maybe I'll cross him off my list of things I'm
I'm hoping for for Mother's Day
So
We're probably going to be waiting but
We want mines because
When it comes out we're just going to be like this is awesome
All right
What will keep that in mind
So
Let's let's talk a little bit about
Kind of the limited resources and we'll tie this in with the Apple stuff because you had mentioned
Set design apple has a huge focus on design
You guys have had a huge focus on design your your product is actually
Very attractive
It does not look like a 3D printed monstrosity that you know I've duct taped to my door
Actually my duct tape things to my door cuz that's just how I roll but my
Improperly
That's how he rolls
So
With the resources that you have
How have you made your decisions because a lot of the companies who are in the space that are startups
They did they don't have infinite resources so how do you make
Decisions on what to focus on cuz
Ace Hardware is hard
And so
What have you guys decided to focus on and why
Absolutely right Hardware
Hard work was hard enough
When you just needed to make a product
NL Hardware
A product that has to talk to you
Smartphones and has to talk to platforms
And servers and
Are the days of making a product and putting it on the shelf or
So it was just a couple years ago
Restart WiFi module
Everything that we met
So
Big thing for us is when we need to go going to be raised $600,000
That was very helpful
Getting us the resources that we need
Experience making Hardware before
So we've been able to do this pretty Lane
Breaking too much money at early-stage to get through the first Federation
Prioritize how do we make the best video doorbell
And I think
We did a good job at version 1 and then we took a lot of theoretical feedback that we got there
Indiegogo
Combine that with the real world that we got
Conversion wine
And then we released
Version 2
So
For us we just been focused on
The video doorbell
Even before we thought about Integrations with companies in other products
We just said we got to make
Skybell is great as it can be
Skip it to give his many the feature that people have told us that they want we got to get that to them
Before we even integrate with other people
So that Focus
Till a couple of months ago
Skydive Chicago skyline
Crazy distribution offers
Call Wendy great if you did this and
This is a separate
Completely
But it's always just been focused
Getting our progress
So that's that's how we do
If you can't make
Hyde Park
Same time
So we just went back to make one product extremely well
Animal
Next steps
And speaking of next steps
What kind of company where do you envision the company in a couple of years because
A lot of companies
In the space right now
Are stuck
Thinking about Amaya Product Company
Or am I really a data company
And I hear that a lot from
From start-ups so
Where do you kind of see
Skybell
What we are planning
Reaction
Smart Home
Security company
So you know what is home security look like
In the future
And that's sort of what we're focused on so we're starting with
You know about that
Gives you a great sense of security at your front door where a lot of people really want it and then
We do use data we do collect device
Status about weekend
Understand how people are
Actually using
And what's important for us
Limited resources you have limited power
So you can't do everything
So if I know users are
Are having longer video sessions or there
Then we can prioritize
How we allocate power outage
Or we can fireworks
Somewhere so that certain features
I'm a prominent and others
And we definitely done that
Still one example early honest we got feedback that people
Wanted the ability to turn off their indoor chime
So that
Baby bouncing house
FedEx UPS driver doesn't wake up their baby
Describe how you can hit a button
I don't know that turned off your indoor chime
That was all based off of user feedback
It's always
Great feature list
And so we just been doing that along the way and
It's been working out
I'm very well.
That's the word focuses and
Will keep using data to
Prioritize
Teachers of people want in the people we know the features that people are using
I like it yeah I love I love that idea
Using both data and user feedback
To actually prioritize your future releases
It helps
Mitigate kind of the most vocal user problem
Cuz sometimes they'll tell say something but you cannot now actually look and see what people are trying to do and then you're like oh
Let's do this
You brought up an interesting thing though
What do you think security does look like in fiber
Let's just say five years
Would I have a connected home for example
I have a lot of things my security is now automated in the sense that
Devices in my house talk to each other so when I'm not home
It takes on the role of turning lights on and off or turning my shades of down
I'm in all of those are triggered based on certain events happening
So I'm just kind of curious like how a doorbell might play into that or maybe
Maybe your version of security is very different I don't know
It is lame s*** out of the doorbell
That would be awesome
And we just filed that actually
There you go see
Cocina
Yesterday's news
Find the real deal
Let's see if you don't have plans coming out of the door
You know five years
Yeah right now he's got a solution this type of 2G Wireless
Fortress around your house and if
Penetrate it
Then you know what call the police and I think
There's always going to be
Trump's are not right.
Call monitor
Home security solution
Yes
I feel like
There are so many opportunities for
Homeowners to do exactly what you just talked about this
How do I appear
Eye exam
Kumon Mason Kenny support and help
So I see all of these preventive things possible
Because of home automation
Upper down
Team light coming on
At the same time
You can sort of customized security
This is what I need I don't
I don't quite need a $50 a month
Through your commitment
But what I really want is I want to know who's at my front door
I want to let them in remotely
And maybe I want to censor the backyard and something on the garage
Between us three products
At 6
I got exactly what I need
Got it alright final question for you
Just like this is like Final Jeopardy
How many seconds I don't know
No
So
Recently I think it was the Wall Street Journal there was a great article on this being kind of a bubble the smarthome bubble
It talked about
Products like connect to toothbrushes I I've actually tried one of those
There I think there was b-connected fart detector
That I have not tried
But if I were a teenage boy I would totally race race out its
Support that
As a company that is selling
You know
A connected device in thinking I'm sure you know
Probably think of yourselves as may be more valuable than
Connected fart
Detector
Little bit
I didn't think it's a good product for a certain demographic
Bubble in the space
I look at you know the ryzen platforms
Comcast is not making a secret of its interest here
Google has in a nest in his buying
Arbat Dropcam podesta actually
What do you think your future looks like
How do you how do you
Plan to do you plan to stay independent how do you plan to continue
I guess being the best company you are and I should also throw in there that Fitbit
Crazy Fitbit just filed for an IPO in what will be last week by the time the stairs
So
You know what it feels like
Wow there's a lot of really interesting opportunities here for a successful kind of connected device
I agree I think there's there's tons of possibilities
Sometimes I think that
A lot like how
Social media was
Yeah couple years.
Direction More Than A couple years back now
Delaware
Got
Twitter you got sleep
Are you got a ton of other stuff
Social networks
You know
People going out there and discrediting Facebook
Twitter because they Loop in this social media clock on this
Dog owners than
For me it's
We're getting articles like that because it shows
There's something here
Ricers
Interested
People just going in and trying to innovate every angle of the space witch
Look at me
It did for social media so
I kind of feel like
Lappet faced were even friends there was still around
Your Myspace was day we don't know where this whole thing's going I just know that
It's for real when companies
Apple
Yeah Samsung
Google
Microsoft
Comcast
Involves all the ice p
Home Depot Amazon I mean it's everywhere
I don't think it's messed
Barely a bubble I think
We're getting a lot of
Good attention
Could skybell become
The
You know that I am in with Google buying nest
That was kind of one of the big kind of
Hopes for a
Independent company that rises out of this kind of
I want a bubble but this flurry of activity
Add skybell be one of the big independent the eBay's are the Amazons coming out of the Smart Home
In a flurry
You know I never know what the future holds
I think this
What we have with skybell
We have a lot of great things going for us
Portmore very grateful to be in a position where
Almost every
Group that we've spoken to has reached out to us
Because they know that having coverage of the front doors in the big part that's missing
When I look around
I see the one that do all that do something at get real valued
Nest Thermostat helps people save money it's also really cool
And it's really convenient
Started
Skybell gives you security
Tangible real security at your front door
Your parents feel more comfortable leaving kids alone
So that they can
And so
You know our hope is to be relevant in a couple years
We're going to continue looking at ways
Stop real problems
Aspirations
The gift people
More real value
So I think when you say focus on real value
You can create life
Company
That's that's what I'm banking on it
I know this
Solutions that my staff
Install problem
And I know that there's something for everybody out there but
What are meaningful impact that we can make some people
I stay focused on the other sale
Involved
Security
All right
Well Andrew thank you so much for coming on the show today
I appreciate it and I
Look forward to playing with skybell NC
Actually seeing the pizza guy from
For the roof when we're up on the rooftop deck that that's been my biggest case and I can't wait to see how else I use it
I'm looking forward to it so
Thank you
Absolutely Stacy absolutely
See you next week on the Internet of Things podcast