Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Is Bacchus
We have got an
Excellent chauffeur
So much goodness
May bridge homekit and
The other protocols
We got a bunch of Google related stuff with pixel in Android watches we got
Security
Sabeco data
And a bunch of Mobile World Congress news about net
Some of you guys may not care about but
You should you do what you do Stacy
About it
Tim Cook uses homekit
Because it's always good to get those kind
Opinions
And I'm finally finally going to talk about my experiment in double Network
We're going to do all of this time we're gonna have a word from our sponsor spin dance
And then we're going to have Jenny
Who is the head of techstars iot incubator talking about
What is trendy
Right now for startups in the internet
Now
Before we get to all of that
Let's have a word from another one of our sponsors this week sponsor is a Lynette
Kayla is an Enterprise internet-of-things platform that is empowering the world's leading manufacturers by simple
Find the inherent complexity of the internet of things in their products into smart connected systems
Transform their businesses to compete in the game changing world is coming tippity
Complexity of developing connected products and is trusted by some of the leading brand so they can focus on what they do best
Kayla is solving the internet of things so you don't have to
To download the whitepaper
Biggest mistakes manufacturers make when launching iot products at Stacey on iot
.com
Paper cuz I'm very curious what those massage
State Farm
Alright Kevin
Let's get started
Let's start with
Yes and that's which has a range of products or products they have improved the notifications on their nest cam
It can now identify a door for example and turn it into like a a Zone
For monitoring so that way if it's
And you said yes it is
They can actually monitor
Activity through that
And that will help you understand who's coming and going in your house
So you could always manually trolleys activity zones but now that Nest is smart enough to actually kind of figure out
What is ask you is this an activity Zone you might want to look at us
Additionally
The alerts on the nest protect are better because
If your smoke alarm senses smoke or carbon monoxide
You automatically get live video from all the nest Cam that you have in your house which is kind of cool I think it was like
Is this a false alarm
Is problem right now
You can tell you that right away so
Can I see Improvement and there's no additional cost for this kind of Nest does charge for
You know saving recordings in the cloud
Tanner 30 days at a time but this is all just built in in the
And available with the new update
Actually that might be good for
Fireman when they come to the house
It is
Burning town
They can actually get a visual inside the house before the cameras belt
And since it's all stored in the cloud Maybe
You know if there's a
Investigation after
Data from
Those cameras
I don't know yet
And I think if you would have been
Every home should have like an emergency plan to evacuate
If you can quickly pinpoint what area of the house is the problem area you need to get out
That may impact or help you get out quicker because you'll need to go that way so it's B
Yeah yeah
A few seconds
We should say the nest is owned by Google
Is not owned by Google but he does work for Google as a contractor but I don't work with the nest people around
Any other smart home initiatives at Google
Okay
Dimension
Thread
Recorded the podcast
Thread actually announced today that they have
Thread certified chips out
And the big news for the week are about
How is that
New thread devices will launch before the end of this year
In fact
I talked to somebody and
They told me that a new thread based device the first one will launch in May
I don't know
Well that actually jives with
Threadgill's kind of buried in their press release it says certified thread based products are expected enter the market in the first half of the
Urso
There could be more than just one in May
There we go
Looking forward
I actually am
We were talking about third for a couple of years and it just
Whiskey talkin about it but
We're not seeing a ton of actual progress
It was a
Rin
Protocol so true true they launched in 2014
Shred that work
Build this and so that actually me
Makes sense
It does take time
Cuz it's right
All right
So some other really
I don't know
This is this is cool that this could be
Where I want to give you guys
But it's CSI miss this and someone pointed it out to
Which
For 4
There's a pub called The Mix tile
Made by a Chinese company
Falcon Crest
And this device. We don't have pricing we don't know what it's going to be out
The cool thing about it though is
Hug that could
Tire home
It's tough to your Z-Wave and zigbee
Cuz it Doesn't it's apparently mfi certified
So I don't know what to say here other than I am
It comes out so I
It sounds cool like we said we don't know which
It's actually going to launch win cost and all that
So if I'm understanding it
Frankly this is a way to get
Essentially some non homekit
Devices working with homekit and the home app in your Apple
IPhone ER
Wear your iPad
Does that sound right because I'm going to be nice to Adnan homekit tanks
So it's either going to have its own app where you would actually then have to work at
Everything but I'm hoping it brings the stuff
IOS
Yeah that's that's what I'm thinking is it supposed to do
Which is good
You've got the security
Chip inside
It's hard to mix tile because it's mfi certified
And then hopefully that would handle any situation shoes from the non homekit devices
Yeah
I will say it's nice to have that option
Although what you're going to end up
We will see
It was worth every one noting
Will keep up on this
Moving away from home kit
Let's talk about
Google
Hanson's Kevin's already given his
My disclaimer
When is you can actually control Smart Home devices
Pixel
You have
Yeah so this kind of brings
Google home
Capabilities
2 in a limited degree to a
Google pixel or pixel XL phone through Google Assistant
And it sort of makes sense cuz Google assistant is really the
The brains
Inside
Google home
I haven't seen any official announcements on this
So I didn't say anything originally when I first
Read about this last week
People all over our reporting it and also
I see the setting in my
On my pixel
If you have a pixel or pixel XL and go into your
Google Now settings
You should see a smart home
Teacher or devices future
Where you can add support for
WeMo
SmartThings and Philips Hue
And that will add voice control through your pixel 2 those
Those devices github
So I don't have
Hue setup I don't have smart thing so I went wink
But I do have some WeMo switches so course I tried it
And it works just like it works with my echo you know I just am not going to say the hot word but I just say the hot word so that the phone is listening
Can I say turn office on my office lights
There's really no
Lag
Or anything like that but then again that
Particular setup I have with the WeMo is a direct Wi-Fi connection so it should be quick there's no Cloud involved but actually there is cloud
Because the phone is going to I presume
Send that to Google servers
No there's no cloud
Yeah I think
I think it's I think it's straight in the case of the WeMo I think it is a straight connection over Wi-Fi because you link your wink not you
Either way it works fast
The shoe would be cloudy
And so
Exactly
McDonald's
And so you know when you go look for this you're going to go to settings on your Google assistant and
The title is called
I know so many different words for
And
So
You may be
Questioning why you want your phone to do this I personally
I think it's awesome
Not in the room
Device perhaps
But if you want to do this with the Amazon Echo
There's actually a way you
I can do that without the ra
Amazon doesn't ask
There is an app called me app
Download
And basically
You open the app
You press the button in
Can you tell
She Who Shall Not Be Named to do something and low and behold
That's pretty cool cuz it also works when you
And I still think it should be part of the
Official Amazon native app but that's just me
And I'm not trying to
Put the people at a business by any means I love what they did but
Really it should be native
All right
Let's talk about
Smart watches
Kevin
It's terrible
I'm on my second cup of coffee is okay
Cuz I saw the Android watches
The task
Best casino
Gotcha so
So officially Android Wear 2.0 that's Google's platform for smart watches came out of developer
Preview it is available for
Device makers to use and so on
LG actually has two watches out already
They are available online and in some stores and a carriers
I just tell you that
Between the two there's a big difference
Some the LG watch Style
$49
It is thin ish
It's thinner than the second one I'll say that
But it is missing a lot of features from the second watch
So there's no
LTE dedicated LTE connection which The Logical don't really need anything
There's no NFC so
We can't do Android pay with it there's no
Or somewhere new GPS in it so
So it's not for me somebody who runs everyday and wears a sport watch outside this is not for me it does have Google Assistant
Raise your wrist and you can
You know just ask a question and
Presume that you should be able to control the things that we just have out with a pixel
Through the watch that way
I presume I don't know cuz I don't have one of these
The LG watch sport is $349 to a hundred bucks more and get you a dedicated LTE connection
There's actually a nano SIM slot inside the watch
The watch comes with a
A special wrench
That you take the back of the watch off with and popping a SIM cards crazy senior phone calls
You have a data connection you can stream whatever music and so on as long as Internet for it
So that's kind of interesting that could be
Used
How to control a home when you're out and about running maybe you
Need to open up the garage door for somebody for example
Right
Oh I was going to say or you want to set your AC down
I said when you get
When you get back here like
And then again I don't know that you can actually do that but the capability certainly there I don't see why you wouldn't be able to do that
Maybe in the future if not now but sub
But the LG watch sport is very thick in about 15 15 1/2 millimeters thick
Clunky and big
You know it's got every kind of sensor
Feature you would want in a smartwatch
And I can't think of anything that would be missing in terms of up sensors and so on so
That one is available through AT&T and Verizon
Either on or off contract but
We all know that friends don't let friends buy devices on contracts
That it's five or $10 to add that LTE connection to your account as well so
But yeah this could be a handy way to do some remote control type things
Yeah well I would like it just to
Listen to
Music without hearing my
Roundabout
I do that now with
My old Android Wear watches as well as my Apple watch
Because you can
Store almost 4 gig of Music there
Are you used to say when I stream music
No I could actually
Restore it like
I see Spotify is is kind of an outlier in that
Yasso
With apple music and Google play music you can download to your various watches depending on your platform
And like I
Cute mine up with like three hours of music so I can easily go run a half marathon
And I I just
Carry my music with me that way
Easily run a half
It's not easy but I could you know fall down a bunch of times and still cross the finish line and still have
Music list to listen to
I don't advise that
Hope you like heaven
Chow dog
One is bad enough we don't need more of me
The Mirai botnet
But you probably remember because we talked about it at
10 * 5
Late last year
This is a ran on
Connected
Linux
Devices so
Network DVR players were big culprits couple routers
And what it is
It was part of the big DDOS attack
Against
Adena systems and took down
Major websites around
Very exciting
Mariah still out
Someone has
Where did it
Windows machine
Oh thank you ever do that sarcasm
What this means basically is
I don't know how often you going to like your doctor's office or maybe a point-of-sale turn
UCD
He Windows prompts but that means all of those machines could now become compromised and
Part of the spotnet which puts a lot more power at merized
Scale their scaling up
It's so yes
Is this good news now
This is bad news and
Depending on how the technology is
Figured so if it has a hard-coded password
If the password hasn't been changed
Mariah even if you take it off the machine is just going to
Come right back
So some of these devices are going to be compromised forever
And we'll just have to take them offline
I'm in some of them probably can be
Text
So
Semi-good news
Bad news
Speaking of security
That's actually
This is a really interesting story so this came out this week and this is from the Verizon 2017 data breach
Digest
Which is a
Report
What happens here is a named University
Basically had its iot Network
Compromised and then turned against itself
So what happened is B
Vending machines printers and other connected objects that are kind of part of the
The iot for this particular
University
Basically they were hacked and then they started
Looking up Seafood searches which is held
People love
Citrus ending
There were over 5,000 discrete systems making hundreds of DNS lookups every 15 min
So this is basically grounded their Network to
In the button it actually was spread from device to device by brute forcing default in
Password so does the same thing that was happen
Mirai
And once it was known the mall where
Malware had full control a device
And it would basically change the devices password and locking everybody out of that system
So this is really nasty stuff
Here is kind of separate your Networks
This is going to be a
Breezy world
Iot devices that are systems or other
Websites
If there's 4 turned against themselves we're going to see
Stores that can
Curtis actions
Medical Center Hospital
Catastrophic
So
Do better
Yeah
We don't know that the university but the best soon as
You mentioned this story I'm thinking now you know my son just started college there are connected vending machines and every floor the dorms with
Card readers in what. He was just complaining about slow Network the other day and that's what the more the first tip-off seven issue were in
Particular report
And it's not my son's interest I don't think it's just you know just get me got me thinking you know
How many people can be impacted by
Such a seemingly small thing right one little thing gets into that Network and all the sudden
You know these guys
Texas University locked out of
5000 systems
What's the impact is huge
And there's a lot of connected stuff out there
Yeah
Soho
Okay
Moving from security to
Back to the echo actually
Play so I just thought this was an interesting stat so I thought I'd share it with Parks Associates
This week
Put out a report that says 2 to 4% of us Broadband households have purchased an echo
In the past 6 months
That's
Totally
Interesting and we were running we are running Friday survey
In of the people who responded with things they bought
Bye
Google home in the Amazon Echo are like 200 people
The last six months which is crazy
And I'm not surprised I mean it's
It's really taking off because it provides
That invisible voice interface to do so many different things
You know as well as getting
Getting information
To you and I may be enjoying music and so on
What it is
The poster child for the smart home these days end
In a related stat just
I think it was yesterday before Amazon had shared its quarterly numbers
They broke out their revenue for subscriptions
And it was like so I can
I don't recall the exact number but some analysts did
Some math and said you know
There's about
64 million Prime subscribers send that jumped out of
That's because not just for the revenue
But also
That's a huge potential user base for the echo devices because you really
Want
I think it's part of all this and
I could see a lot of prime people keep
Take an extra pad echosign add smart on blanks
So with this in mind if you are one of those people who purchased an echo they recommend
Couple things for you
Because
My far away
The most useful Echo skills
Smart Home
So
If you are
Kind of a nervous Nelly
I would say to take your first Quick Step into a smart
I will connect you to the Philips Hue bulbs into some lamps
Or I would say 42
Chipper
Experience
Pick up a few WeMo switches there about $35 and
Just connect those and then you can suddenly control your lamps
Voice
It's freaky
Awesome it's a starter gives you a taste of what you can do and
And I've said before replacing
Physical switches with voice
Interaction is just the baby steps when you start connecting things to do things based on
Actions that makes things smart but this is a great way to dip your toe in the water
Migraine
You're going to like it
Stop right there did you guys
Stop the presses just because you were talking about this
I don't know if you guys talked about it last week when I was not here apologize
The Amazon tap
Is now
Look at that so and I say this because the tap is cheaper than a full Echo although the
Echo Dot
But the tap which is a battery-powered
Echo device
Previously you had to literally tap the button
And then you would speak your commands and make things happen
But now
I said they should have done from the beginning
You can
Guest voice control setting in the
App that
Disappointed that I want to say cuz it's her name
That you can just enable the Wake word
And I tested it out works great so now I've got a tap down in my dining room where
Now I can just
Speaking control lights and do things it's a beautiful thing
It is plugged in for me all the time except when I take it outside on the deck but now there's winter I'm not doing that
I thought they should
Or would add this feature if and only if it was
Sitting on the
Base charging
But no it can be done when your on battery power it will reduce the battery life not the battery like but the actual
Length of time you can run on a charge they say about 8 hours
Because of the
Coding for always listening functionality
Okay that's
How long does it last
I haven't tested but they say about 8 hours
Which is probably only one to two hours
Rest and it would be without that
You don't have to use the future you couldn't save your battery life and turn the Wake word off in which case it's a manual tap
Let's see now we're going to get into Mobile World Congress is
It is such a two weeks from now
Who am I what day is it
So it is two weeks for now we're already starting to see a rush of news about
This is where Kevin
Bear with me because this is actually a big deal
So one of the things we talked a lot about are these low-power wide area
And basically these are
Networks design
For the internet
They said really tiny amounts of data but the cool thing is they send it that they cover huge areas so like cities
Entire
Counties
And it's
It's kind of like the cellular
But it's not always
That's where it gets low
AT&T is going to launch
And iot net
This
June
Chats which is actually pretty
Amazing and I use a standard called LTE
And this is
A cellular standard
Bifurcated
Two networks but they're going to take it to these very small
Verizon is also doing
An LTE
At 1
So these are going to be like
Hopefully cheaper
We're still waiting
Pricing on these butt
It should be interesting
With things like
Laura and sigfox
Some of the other
Networks that are out there
So
Also
On the cellular side
Nokia has done
I don't even know how to say
Created a network called
Wing
Which is basically
Cellular
It's going to have some
I think it's going to have some satellite yes
Cellular satellite
It might even have
Laura other networks I don't
Actually no
Nokia says are not going to be buying Spectrum
For this so
They're going to be grabbing Network
Capacity from its customers basically a service provider
Customers
Doing deals for that and then they're going to create this Global Network
Curvy large Enterprise
And those companies can basically go to notes
Kia or they can
It sounds like
Nokia will also white label this
For cellular providers so cellular providers
Can then
If you are like
A company that's doing Logistics you can actually go to you
Your carrier
A carrier
Where in say hey
Global Connect
And I think that's the key difference when you mention AT&T and Verizon and whatnot
They're not implementing anything with
Satellite as of yet
Understandable reasons given their there
Company focused
This seems to be like a
A solution offering where Nokia is going to say look you know
Doesn't matter
Matter what kind of data you need
We can offer it
Multiple
Network setup
What's seamless to you but
For us we're going to use either satellite or
Use cellular
So4
Shipping bike overseas and such
You know they can offer something that
Carriers right now don't seem to be interested in
Cargo ship
Because I think
It's fascinating
And I realize this but
Because the
Containers
Strapped down
And they're just got piled high in high seas
There's like a large number of them can just fall overboard
The shipment service
I was going to send this and I'm like oh
And you know they expected
Stash's Subs
The top of the
You could actually fight
Or at least see where they
Also
Story is
I tell you
Is also introducing
A network in this network is actually going to be
A long-distance low-power Network
It does not use cellular
It's much cheaper
They're working with inmarsat satellite provider in Satellite is actually
The backhaul for this
Wherever you're putting your radios
And then it'll talk back up to
It'll go to the internet
Through an inmarsat satellite
Which means you got like a Lora Network
Work on a ship
You have a Lora Network in the middle of Lake nowhere Australia
It's actually really cool if we actually
I did a story in the newsletter
I think it was about wiring up a volcano
One of the technologies that were using as Laura and
Carrabba
And
That might be a good solution for that
What's interesting is I think
IRT is probably one of the
Best
Use cases for satellite
In that
We've seen Satellite Communication in satellite internet
And so on when you're bouncing your signals up to 22,000 miles up into space and back down
You reduce latency right so there's a delay
So it's not ideal paper video conferencing
I might say something on a video call with you Stacy
And you see my lips move and then two seconds later you hear the sound
For example
But for iot it kind of doesn't matter
Right unless it's
Unless it's like I'm a security type thing where you need no latency
So buttfor
Logistics and tracking
Just general-purpose IBT
Satellite is actually probably at fantastic
Way to boost coverage
Quite honestly
Because there's small amounts
Data going
It's
Going to be more
Satellite ride terrible
Even easier
It's just
Function of a technology
I think you're right
Astute observation Kevin
That's cuz I'm on my third cup of coffee now
Alright let's talk
Let's let's move on to
Out of networking and let's hook up Tim Cook the CEO of Apple and how he uses
Homekit
I know that I am I'm overdue for using
Cancer next week
About that
But Tim Cook
He apparently has outfit
Expensive house with
Homekit
So he
He says good morning to Siri
And his house lights
And his coffee starts Brewing
My hunches his coffee is probably
We plugged into an idevice
I was just going to ask how you know what coffee maker is homekit compatible
Believe that there is
Do I
Chelsea Wenzel
My hunch is he's probably using a switch
Coffee maker is already set
So that's still good
I can't
Personal use that cuz I had to press a button
Tim Cook
I can probably
Afford it really automatically
I'm guessing he knows an engineer to that can help with that problem
Beautiful aluminium
Farragut
Jesus he's doing that he's got a
He sets his thermostat
And he also is created and I'm home command
Which
I have also created a
I'm his controls the lights and thermostats and window shades
So what I would like to see
Is
Tim Cook
I need to tell Siri i'm
Am I just going to set up a sensor
And when this happens
It's going to work
He does apparently use geofencing so
Could have that that smarts implemented at this point it's not clear from the CNET
Article interview
It was on
Conference
RSV
He's selling home
I use it and so should you
IAAI
All right
So
Let's get to
My Xperia
Two Networks
Yes
I talked about this a long time ago actually
It came up first because of the Mirai botnet
And I have to tell you
After like two and a half months and that it wasn't working
Religiously
This is not to
Chris AC feels the pain so you don't have to
So here's what I would recommend
Because
In the challenges are there
You don't
I want to control things
Sometimes for my smartphone
So my smartphone needs to be on the Wi-Fi
For certain
Locations to work
The same network that either your hub Android devices are on
Yes
So if I put everything on one network then I can't
Use my
My phone
Where if I put everything
Including my phone but not my computer
You could
If you want to put your phone on one network and a separate Network just for your
Computer
That is doable
You just can't use your computer frame
I think which is fine unless you're working
No it's actually fun
Unless you're pulling data
And that would be
Don't think there's
Else
If you want to login
So that's a possibility but then you can't do any banking or buying things on your phone you have to remember to always use your
Gordon quotes
Here's a thought you could
This is not ideal by any means but you could actually separate things to a point by not even having your phone on your home Wi-Fi
And I say that because we talked earlier about the pixel on the smart home controls
I actually now that I'm thinking about not have my third cup of coffee I turn my Wi-Fi off on my phone just to see if I could
Remotely control my WeMo switches using Voice
And it worked I was over in LTE network then
And that didn't work it was a little bit more lack of course because now you're talkin about another Network
Essentially I separated things to some degree there
I'm not saying this is ideal
Cuz it's not
But
But you could do it that way
Yes you
The other thing I did
Is
So so that's my idea of a guest
But then
You probably should have two guest networks you shouldn't iot Network and then your guest Network for natural gas
You cannot control your attitude gadgets
Was a terrible idea
And everybody
Yeah
Head okay
What do I most care about
I care about my Mikey
Garage door opener
I care about any locks
Z-Wave lock so I decided not to care about those but if I had like an August lock or something that talked
Via Bluetooth sore and then had a Wi-Fi remote
I might Karen
I care about cameras because
All the time
Manors at privacy
So you can
You can put your cameras
On a separate
You actually could put your locks I didn't try that because I don't have
I don't have enough
August Locker
Or I don't have a Wi-Fi
But you can't do that
And
That is
Les Payne
You're so then you would end up with
Basically
Gesnetwork
That has your iot devices on it
If you're okay with your guess having a
Access to the which most people would not be I wouldn't think but
So then you're gonna have to set up
Let me tell you
This is going to be my pro-tip
For everyone out there in
It's too late I'm sorry
Going forward
Do this
Use your guest Network
Because
In this day and age
It is silly
I agree
If any of your devices
Compromised
Network Bad Dudes
Even if it's like you're at your kids
I mean like I would never let my
Kids friends have access to my bank
Because oh my God
Their computer I barely want my daughter to have access to my
Computers are festering disease holes of
God only knows
Divide
I called this divide and fail to conquer
Experiment
Networks
I wonder if there is a product opportunity here
For improved firewalling for IRT in today's routers and War
A separate
Bridge or router specifically for IRT
That will only allow certain traffic to pass
Last week's
Grant night
What about some
Stuff
There are some routers that have
More transparency capabilities or the following
Traffic patterns of devices and then say
Write what I think would be really interesting
Is doing it at
Protocol
Also
Actually we've from Google is thinking about
It's saying hey
This door lock should never need to talk
This camera should never have to talk to
I actually should talk
Got your lights The Nest actually does
There's
A way to do it that way but it's probably kind of
Limited
I don't know
About that because as you were describing it
When I first start thinking was
That kind of sounds like Android app permission
Only it's now device level permissions from device device
So
I don't know if it would be that computer intensive I think it just needs to be done at the setup
Point
And you know and then the rules are enforced going forward
Yeah I'm just taking it
New device
Like let's say I set up a device
And it's
Cuz there's two way communication so
Then when I bring something new on the network I can set its permissions but I have to go back inside the
Emissions
I mean I can be done
One Fell Swoop I think
Yeah I don't I don't see why I couldn't be
I'm on it I'm so on it
I'll leave I'll need a fourth cup of coffee
Before we go
We should say August's has
Added the ability to unlock your device from your
Security issue
Oh my gosh
Holiday Inn
You have to tell the echo to unlock your August locks and then you have to give up
So
Simple
Elegant and hopefully nobody who wants to
Get into your house will actually
In the room with you when you give set
There is there is that but not I love this invitation I don't have an August lock
But I'd if I did I'd be thrilled right now because
I don't think any of the locks really allowed for unlocking an s
Again as you set a security issue udoka some anybody
With a voice can talk to an echo and say hey that's unlock the door
This ad the security Factor locking is not a problem so that's that we can all do
But this I think this is great
All right
Lettuce
Take a moment for a word from our sponsor and then after that
We will have
Jenny Fielding
Techstars iot accelerator
I want to talk about investing in the internet
I'll see you next week
Hey everyone
We're dropping the podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is spin dance
And I have Brian toll here who's going to tell us a little bit about spending
What is the thing you guys do
We are a full-service iot consultancy which basically means we help organization
Design
Develop
And manage their iot software
Sounds like Ford Motor Co
Company in Whirlpool but we also work with a lot of smaller companies and even startups
Okay so why would it
Company like
Ford Aurora
We help them develop their iot products
That's usually a combination of embedded cloud and mobile software it's not a typical for an organization to have one of those skills
But they rarely have really good iot developers in all three of those
And we work really hard to bring a team together that not only under
Stan's embedded in cloud in Mobile but knows how to work together and knows how to bring those skills into the iot
He space example developers aren't just great at developing apps they really
And how to build apps that work
Seamlessly with Cloud over the better software
The provides 24 hours
Yes we do have a team that provides 24/7
Support
And that's really important with with iot products
Cuz obviously the product is out in the field that's working want to make sure that the software that powers it
It is always up and running would people want to use it all right if I have software developer
Where is already on
But I still need you guys
Absolutely wheel of collaboration
We love work with other developer
We really like to work hand-in-hand
So just a quick story we recently developed a mobile app for a large
Manufacturer
They already had their firmware team
Tiemann place
And just needed our mobile
Used to work with them so we developed a great collaborative relationship to get there
Homekit app out the door and then into the market
You guys sound really smart really good
So you have any advice for
There's two common mistakes that we see a lot of organization
Making the first is a lot of businesses are really good about developing an iot prototype but then they don't really
Take the time to develop that into
Full-blown go-to-market app
Application they're forgetting things like security the forgetting
Software updates they haven't thought about analytics and know they're all really important things
To have when you go into the market
We take a lot of the mistakes we've seen in the
The Press you know the big denial-of-service attack from a couple months ago a lot of that just comes down to an experience
On the iot developer
Inside another big problem that we see
Is a lack of overall
Design we see a lot of organization
Dalian
Embedded portion of an iot app for
The cloud Porsche
Another mobile portion all in Iceland
And they're not thinking about the
The system design
That's how all these components are going to work together
The greatest seamless
Experience
Early everybody should that's the best way to develop iOS application
I'm all in
Your system design
So where can
People learn more
If they'd like to download a white paper they can go to spin dance.com coyote and we always luggage
What's up they want to reach out at hello it's been dance.com with love to start conversation with him
Betty Brite
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Jenny field
Jenny is
Managing director at
Text Stars
Iot
Hi Jenny how are you
I'm great how are you
Awesome
So
Jenny is in possibly freezing New York right now where is Ian Sonny Austin
And we're here to talk
About trends
That she sees
In startups and also
Hopefully in like
Debenture in exit
So let's kick it off with
Text stars for the people who don't know
What is it
Well first of all thank you so much for having me then the big fan of yours so it's great to be here
Techstars where a venture capital fund
And we invest in entrepreneurs at all stages of their entrepreneurial Journey
And so what that means is we have things called startup programs you probably heard of startup weekend
Weekend bootcamp
It's for people that want to let you know work on projects and potentially start companies down the road
We have accelerator programs which are three months
Mentor driven intense
Programs around the world so we're on
25 of those
And then we have a venture capital
Fondant we're on our third fun
So
We do a lot of different things that I techstars
And I focus on Internet of Things
Which means that I run accelerator program
An investment company is around
Which is awesome
I'm excited because you guys are now in your
With your iot program and
You just did a kind of
Eton College mod
Which means you are accepting applications for
New companies
And when is sat deadline
Yeah so this is actually our fourth iot program
And the deadline is April 9th
You can find out all the information on our website
And towards the end of this interview
What she is
Specifically looking for any tips she kind of has her anyway
So stay tuned for that but first
We're going to get a sense of where we are in the
So what are you saying I know you've been traveling around
Are there big trends bubbling up
You know when we started investing in iot a few years ago
We were really focused on consumer because I think that that's really where the landscape was it was
This idea that
Like I like to call Tino Hardware 2.0
Entrepreneurs were realizing that it was
Buy a vault
But not a lot of money and not a lot of resources to actually start Hardware
Great rebirth
What are first class we had
Really cool companies
You might have heard of Outlet
Which is the baby monitor
Keen home which is a smart and many others we really got to understand
The consumer space
And II program
We decided to take some chances and really look at B2B
We branched out invest in a company called filament which is doing Wireless Mesh networking and
Chargify which is wireless charging and our last program we decided that we wanted
How to focus on Industrial B2B
We had
Companies across verticals and Healthcare construction Toc Logistics
But with a focus on B2B
Will be continuing that Trend in the snacks are 4th program
Focused again on B2B and Industrial
So it's
Breakfast down because this is something you know why I say that this is the Internet of Things podcast but
There is definitely the smart home I think of
Industrial being Factory in that sort of thing but then I also think of Enterprise and that be
Hill Campus building management
Happy Workforce things Fleet Logistics
And then maybe there's Medical
When I try to start classifying this stuff I'm like
So do you have a class B
Vacation kind of system that you're thinking of
And working from
What's a really interesting point I think you know iot
Is really morphing into you no internet
Of everything and so at you know I kind of joke
The people that I hope that I will be out of a job in
2 years because
To three years because we won't really be calling things iot anymore will just be calling them things
In the same way that you know
Mobile was a vertical oin vest
In Mobile
Now people don't really say that because everything
Thing is mobile so we see that as it can
And that iot is really in fuses all areas of our lives so
In fact. I also joke
People say well how many iot companies has techstars invested in I say
Well between
60 and 75 depending on how you
Define iot that day
What kind of go into this idea of
Security
Because I think it's
He's one of those Technologies we're still not sure how we're going to
Scale security
For the internet
So are you seeing anything particularly novel or exciting
Happening there
Well you know I think the the two barriers were
What's an iot you to me are around interoperability and security
Before we see you know why
Brad adoption
But interesting Lee I'm not seeing a ton of startups work on this and so it's it's something that I always talk about
Kind of in my newsletter when
I'm speaking as likes to have to be more startups that are working on
Security
So much
Focus on on Cyber
But really that intersection of actual physical product and cyber we haven't seen a ton
So yeah there are cement
Purchasing companies working on it there's a few in Israel that I recently met
But definitely not enough so I think it's a huge area of opportunity for startups
And then the other is the operability and I'm not sure that startups are going to figure that out or
If it's really about standards that larger companies
Whether it's Google or Amazon are going to sort out but definitely something that needs
To be handled I think
In order for consumers to have
Really seamless experience with iot
Right now you here a lot
People talking while it's not the smart home it's the dumb home
Because things aren't really working with each other and you know I think that you're going to see a continuation of that skepticism until
We sort out some of those fundamental shoes
Is true although voices Bender
Unifier for a lot of
Even though it's like an overlay on top of
Many many standard herbs but yes it's it's
I should ask you
You actually about voice because
Just like you were mentioning mobile like I invest
It feels like we went from a mobile-first and we're now moving into this concept of
Voice first
And that's going to affect things like how we decide
Build stuff
And I am very curious have you seen any
Companies
Doing stuff there did you guys have any
Companies doing stuff
You know we are actually running a program in conjunction with Amazon call the Alexa accelerator specifically
Play to explore areas
With invoice so
It's an area that I think it's about being in that we're really interested in
I think there's an overlay between the automation we've seen kind of in the bot world
And the boys world
We're seeing all of those Technologies now come together but I think you're right it is the next Evolution from
Mobility
So seen a lot of companies I haven't invested in any of them yet and it's definitely an area that were interested in forearm
Moving to a voice first world
What are some of the challenges
That you see
For example I feel like we don't really have
Pinch-to-zoom for Boise is how I think of it but like accepted that goes across all platforms
Talk to something
Which means
It's really hard still
Command things via voice cuz it's not quite natural
So that's one and I don't know what other kind of challenges there might
Especially if you're talking about bring it to the Enterprise
But I think that you know natural language hasn't exactly become a norm yet right and so
You're Siri
Isn't always giving you exactly what you need and so if I know
In the consumer space I think it's probably okay but
You know that those nuances with natural language processing
Think have to come to bear before week
Can apply them effectively in the industrial space right if you think about
Voice operating an airplane
Right you want to be pretty sure that the commands are correct
I think those are some of the challenges we'll see when it comes to us a self-driving cars or
Or planes are or things like that
A lack of trust
It's kind of been one of the issues that that I stay with us
Or just
Step 2 platform
Robust enough
Yeah
There's a natural Caden
That leads us from start to
Definition of conversation
And can the chat replicate that
Think that were close but we're not exactly there
Enzo again like in the consumer space I think we know we're probably okay for assisting our virtual assistant screw that up
But you know in the in the business
Arena I think that the implications can be
So that makes me a little bit
A little bit nervous
Okay so you guys are in
New York and they're iot kind of hubs all around the country and all around the world
What do you think makes a
Good
Iot
That's a great question and one I'm exploring right now I'm on a
A pretty big trip around the world
What are places that I am spending a lot of time with
These days is in Germany
And specifically in Berlin and Munich
Sing a lot
Start up there and I think
Part of it has
To do with you know kind of legacy
Industries in those areas right and so
If you're looking at industrial iot for example
A lot of people there who have a lot of experience in industrial sectors because of them being
So prevalent they are so whether it's Mobility weather is factories
You know we're seeing a lot of interesting companies come out of those areas so I think that's
Something to look at
That's one of the reasons that I'm excited about New York if you think
The history of manufacturing and
Everything that's happened you know in New Jersey and and places like that
Make sense that New York would bubble up
As being in a place where
Iot startups
Get some tracks
So you know PCB boards are actually built you know across the way in New Jersey so just makes a ton of sense
To see those communities pop up here
But you know he's obviously see large Pockets out on the West Coast
Or staying a little bit and where you are in Austin and indefinitely we always
I'm from the Midwest
So it sounds like you need some sort of maybe manufacturing experience or history
You probably need do you need venture capital or do you need
Big Partners to test out
Concept
I think that Venture when it comes to hardware and iot
Is pretty specific and yes you need you need that Capital but I don't think you need to be around that capital
Sentara Leigh
I think that Venture investors who are interested in those spaces are used
Two traveling around quite a bit
To invest in
Companies where they see it you know the good ecosystem but you know like all startups having access to engineer's and
You know if you have a hardware device
You also need electrical engineering industrial designers you know those things are pretty specific
With startups because one of the things especially as we move into Industrial
Is it
A challenge for them or how should they think about selling to these mammoth
Companies because if I am
If my job is making turbines
I want to work with the
The company that I
Entrust is supposed to
A startup
So how are they navigating
Bad customer acquisition
Yeah that is X
Play great question it's when we thought about you know quite a bit so we're on our first iot program
We only ran them with one corporate partner what we realized is that
Iot is very specific and has a lot of challenges especially if you're developing Hardware firmware
Software all
Solitaire elements and so
We think that surrounding startups with corporate Partners who can provide guidance to the startups and also
Partner with them early on give them a sense of
Legitimacy in the market can be super helpful
We think that partnering with corporates
One way to do it and you see a lot of the accelerators whether it's xlerator has partnered with BMW Mini
For their program or you know there's there's so many other one
And it's very complimentary
In our program one of our startups did a white paper and with PWC
Answer that brought down
Kind of a sense of credibility that then they were able to go out
An approaching very large construction companies
And during the program
This company called pillar was able to get a signed pilot
Done a lot of that
Do with the credibility that PWC was able to bring them
Nice
And I do like in this could be just strong
I feel like there's a lot more strategic investing
Kind of Enterprise in industrial iot
I think that's exactly right
Again
Very hard Industries need a lot of capital to scale
And I'm just make sense so one of our portfolio company is still a man
They had a proper venture-capital lead for their last round but they also had Verizon
Samsung
Participate
Because those Partners can really help give them the scale and the distribution so we are seeing you know a lot
A lot of that
If you look at Siemens and their Venture group next47
Bashas Venture group GE
These are very large large organizations
And it just makes a lot of sense for them to be partnering with earlier stage companies
And what about exits so
Who is buying these
Companies
And are they going public is it again int such a huge space so it could differ unlike consumers I look
Look at Fitbit and GoPro
I'm just curious your thoughts
Yeah well I mean we saw it last year was one of the best years for m&a iot in fact
IRT was help driving all of m&a activity across stack
That's really
Interesting but
You know Verizon was super busy spending billions of dollars on very Solutions everything from Smart cities
Mobility
Wifi
Hugo Boss
NGE were equally as busy
With purchases so I think that there is real opportunity on that side you know these large company is
They can't move fast enough they really need startups and then I'll take a position is the top-of-the-line for all of them
I feel like 2017 is going to be kind of maybe.
Although I like the sound of that in a headline
I think there's going to be a lot of companies that are kind of going to go by the wayside
And I think there's going to be a lot of m&a especially on the consumer side cuz we're seeing the end of a cycle that started probably in Twin
2013 and 2012
So I'm just curious what you think we'll see in 2017 for kind of m&a
Even maybe the end of some businesses
Yeah Minnesota it's a great point I think investors rushed in
About three years ago into Hardware people that had no experience investing in Hardware iot
But you know got excited by Kickstarter got excited by you know a lot of the consumer companies that were coming
And then had a little bit of a
A shock when they realized how hard
How hard it is
Hardware company how much capital
How difficult it can be coming up with new products
Betty facturing in places like China
All the difficulties in so I think we've seen a real retraction
Which is actually good like the Venture capitalists who are really focused on it and know the market will double down and
And everyone else will it will kind of go away so unfortunately for us
Nars there has been
You know somewhat less Capital especially in the seed stage
Or those early-stage hardware and iot companies as compared to a few years ago
But I think that's okay I think that we don't need tons of me-too products and useless gadgets
I'm really want to be funding on spinners that are
Breaking barriers innovating and really thinking about what snack so
In 2017 I think we're all very excited about you no autonomy and how that will impact
Things like cars
Airplanes I'm personally very excited about Healthcare I think there's still a lot to be done
In Elder Care
Excetera and I think that coyote you have a a big place to play with in that
And again you know I hope we see some more Securities company is popping up that are working with an iot because
I think there's a huge opportunity there
Which is
For your application process which again
You should remind us of the day
Tell us
What are you looking for
Yeah I mean as I said earlier we really look across vertical so we'll look at everything from Healthcare to robot
RX AR & VR
Home automation construction tok
Industry 4.0 the really crossword of goals
We're really looking for passionate entrepreneurs
If we look back at the Sphero example not everyone knows but they started
Their Journey at techstars as a garage door opener
So we know that products
Come and go and change but the entrepreneurs and the passion is what stays the same so we're just looking for awesome entrepreneurs
The deadline for techstars iot
April 9th and the program will start this summer
And you can find all the info on our website
Techstars. Com
We can see all of the different programs that were run
And there's tons of resources there for entrepreneurs and the course there's application
Awesome alright Jenny thanks so much for coming to talk to us.
Thank you so much Stacy
What is it for this week's podcast thank you for listening and if you want more Internet of Things
Sign up for my newsletter Stacy nose vein
You can get it at Stacey on iot. Com once again thanks for listening