Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your other hoes
Kevin tofel
And today show is going to be
How to say mostly about the Amazon Echo
We will call her
She who shall not be named
Because
I turn her microphone off so she can't hear me which is good but you're right today it's a it's a veritable potpourri of small
Smart home discussion
Indeed why was he better other
Our listeners who might be
They might also have
An echo
Oh yes yes
Or email sessions
Emails from people who are like
Nevermind
Turn down my echo
Knock it off
Will try really hard but you never know
I catch my husband actually all the time
Whatever
I do the same thing
It's okay people you can say thank you
Is it shows you're polite
Even to our robot
So this week's big news was that SmartThings
Which
Listen to the show you know that I am a huge fan of SmartThings
SmartThings support has come to the Amazon Echo
And
It's awesome
I
Promptly when I saw it hooked it up
And have been playing with it and
I'm going to say it was a bit of a let-down
Show that build up and it was just a little
Why what's the matter say I don't have any smart things stuff here
So I will say I live in a smart home divided
Because this
So I have already moved over all of my lights
To the wink Hub because the wink had been
Hooked into the app
So I've been playing with my lights
For the last couple weeks
I'm
So I had no lights on
SmartThings
So when I moved
My SmartThings stuff over I was really curious like what would actually show up
In the answer was
My Sonos
Valley Vet because
Right now
The echo doesn't suck
Support a lot of the sensors
And
Z-Wave switches
That I have
In my smart my SmartThings gear is mostly
Motion detectors
Samsung smartthings multi-sensor
My zwave locks
And
Z Wave automated blinds
And I didn't I meant to hook up my Z-Wave
Outlets to see if I could turn the coffee pot on and off from it but I did get a chance to
So say to next
So
None of them showed up
And there's actually a really
Good reason for this
Well for some of it
Amazon decided that you know maybe it's a bad idea if you say something like
Alexa
Open the back door unlock the back door
There's no like password or anything
Associated with that so you know anyone could just like
Turn open window shop for the echo to unlock your back door that's okay that's a fair point
So it was kind of a security
Concern
Maybe that's why
See that
Coming anytime soon
Perhaps
The downside is you can't do something like
Alexa
Go to bed
Or
Get upset your house
Good night
Make a scene
Yeah
Don't make a scene
She will not be making any seeds
So
In what I send you the locks which I actually
We just installed you will find that I actually put one on the wink
Just to see if the wink would actually
Except the
Z-Wave locks as well it doesn't
Oh now.
You're gone but you're still getting the locks
Deal with it
Okay
So that is
That is what I learned
Interesting
Well guess what's this
It's funny because a blog post on the SmartThings blog Ashley went live
Before Amazon officially announced it and then the block was pulled because
Amazon I guess was ready to announce it so we knew this was coming last week and then shortly after
Ibloom we we found out
But there weren't a lot of details on what
What SmartThings
Devices where I should support you says the Hub and some devices
And I'm still digging on Amazon site can't find it
I did just want something very interesting though it's interesting
Yay but also disappointing boo
Brightness control is now support on the osram a19 bulb which is bulbs that I bought because those are the ones that are color
Tunable color temperature
Shoe Carnival
Connect to the osram a19 bulb Astra actual blood
They spell it wrong on their website vlug
Means require SmartThings Hub so even with my wink hub
I have the right pelvis but not the Hub
Who is getting frustrating now
Oh well
It's okay because at the end of September it looks like SmartThings is going to have a new
Hub as a SmartThings consumer I got an email
Last week
I want to say
Let me
Pre-order a new hub
From SmartThings
That would be out by the end of
Two things here and moon is going to be a step back just I know it meant to SmartThings before I just want to
Real quick to the history this is the
Brand that went on Kickstarter 2 or 3 years ago
One of the earliest brands
In this market I think
And was later purchased by Samsung so everytime we say smart things
What time does Samsung own property to show folks know that
And secondly my question is for what is the new Hub going to bring
Okay I knew you were going to ask
I'm sorry
I'm allowed to make a scene
Okay so
I was testing SmartThings
In my house
Sign June 23rd
So that's what that's how old the hub's a Time
Currently running
I know it's like ancient
Old man
Now the new hub
I talked to Alex Hawkinson
The CEO of SmartThings
Back at CES
And he told us it was going to have
Couple new radios in it
Mostly to keep it
Online so right now if my SmartThings Hub goes
Loses power
And internet access it goes offline
And it won't do anything
I think so
Now it gets
A full-on brain
Naked cellular backup
If I want it
I don't need it
Cost a lot more extra
In the Hubble add Bluetooth smart
Now
This was all back at CES that they talked about this
And
It was supposed to launch in May
But I think what happened was
Adding support for homekit kind of push this back of the
So
I think what's what we're seeing again is that that delayed homekit kind of
Time frame
I'm expecting that will hear more from smart
Things very soon
I've reached out to them hopefully
Willard Moore
And
I know that I will probably be in line to
Order myself a brand new SmartThings Hub
In keeping with that house divided theme
So back to the Echo and kind of the SmartThings integration because people with
A Sonos
Might be interested to discover
How this works
Yeah I'm curious I don't have a Sonos
And I probably won't get my meds so curious how they integrated
So
Sonos through SmartThings is known as a lab
Which means it is not officially supported
Because Sonos doesn't officially
Support anybody's
We're all very hopeful
All of us being
Domino's Pizza
So what it does is right now
You can use your Sonos
Speakers is basically like the voice of your smart home
And
You can also play a existing playlist
So if your Sonos
Is currently playing
My Sonos one or any one of my Sonos
Sonos is always playing one of my daughters like
Top 40 pop hits playlist
Anyone
So now I can tell Alexa
Sorry I
Just wake up everybody staying as a bad person
I can tell the Amazon Echo
Play
Kitchen
Oh no I have to say turn on
Sonos
Cuz that's in my in my SmartThings
It is labeled kitchen Sonos
Okay and you have to use the same nomenclature
Sure is the same keywords kind of
As
Lights turn on kitchen Sonos turns it on
And it plays wherever it stopped playing last
Only place that playlist
And then I can say turn off
The only things you can do
Turn up the volume you cannot fast forward
So it's a very minimal it's an on-off switch essentially by voice at this point which is very similar to some of my lights even though they
They are dimmable I can't
Use the brightness controls got so
It's interesting that it was straight
Even though we're getting these integration
Since we're getting them piecemeal innocence and
Eminem
Probably okay for most people
There for you and I've been doing this kind stuff for several years
Anthony a little frustrating
Yeah the only thing basically the only thing I can do with the echo
Is lighting related
And DeSoto
Narcissus
I know it's Sonos
Don't make a scene
So that is
That is what we've discovered
Now I got
I want to say
15 or 16 devices now hooked into
The wink hub
Across
Sorry no
15 or 16 devices into my Amazon Echo
If I count the hue
As a hub
I've got it
3 hubs
Sonos devices are now
Going into the echo
Which allows me voice control basically
Of all of the lights
But I have Kinect
Which is actually pretty
Cuz now I have
Have a group for outside lights
Have a group for downstairs
Which turns off every light down
And I have a group
Kitchen living
Dining
Pizza Patron basically a group right
It's okay
You know I'm liking it
I think it's fine
And
Yeah
Blunt one other question I suspect your setup is similar to mine and that
You have one Amazon Echo not multiple units
You probably also have it
Either in your bedroom or your office or somewhere near that
I actually have
Have my downstairs
Oh okay well then it's opposite because I have mine right next to me in the home office
And
I kind of feel like I'm missing out because I when I'm downstairs
Not working
You know I'm basically using my smartphone apps to play with the lights and so on and so forth order on timers and such
You also have the remote
We do have the remote and we it's it's sitting on
It's actually in my bedside table drawer
And we don't actually use it because the Bluetooth in the remote
Because of the distance
I have a little dodgy
So
It works sometimes but
We're just kind of like
I've had good luck with Bluetooth radios and devices in my house
However
I'm still hurt
That I like the concept of the remote I'd rather maybe be Wi-Fi then if it can't be Bluetooth
Been up for training purposes
The moon Portland
Just put the
Microphone
Voice Control in the Amazon
Echo app
Your phone already has a microphone built into it
That's true and that would be
Actually
And I shall correct myself it is no longer the Amazon Echo app don't know if you noticed this when they have to SmartThings stuff
Elsa updated the app and is now called the Amazon
You know who rap
Oh it is I did not realize it was this
Who shall not be named
Yes Baltimore
Oh I should also say
Another thing
The things you cannot control via the echo
You cannot control
Finesse
In the Chamberlain so I have those hooked in through the wink
Same here
Can't control those
Nope
And I also I have the ecobee
My downstairs ecobee
Fear the SmartThings
And that is also not so anything that I
Lake-Link through an email
Assuming most of these are via a lot
Those don't
Tie into
I'm sure they will at some point just gets back to my point that
Our people have been waiting on this for so long
Piecemeal
Sure and I can't I can still control my
Nest through
Redeemable there
If I guess if I wanted a voice
Control thermostatic
Could have gone with the
Honeywell lyric
I just miss
Speaking of wings
I actually discovered my my issue that we talked about a couple weeks ago
With my
Inability to make a robot
That works with the wink system when calls their recipes for home automation robots
To make it so when my garage door opened that my porch light
Turned on
So
I finally had to break down and call the wink helpline beak
Because I
Figure out why
Sure and it's a known glitch with
Oh so anybody who's out there
With the wink system and is trying to do anything with the schedule
It runs
Overnight into the next day
It is having problems this is a tip for you
We don't do it doesn't do that
Don't do it because it doesn't work
And that explains why I have not had a problem with my wink Hub because
My robot to schedules
Never go past midnight or from one night into the next day
They just added you things like checks to see if the lights are on at 10:45 or 11 p.m. and shut them all off
They never go into the next day so that makes sense
Cinderella
After midnight it turns into a pumpkin
Kids so I had wanted to have my
When my garage door open
I wanted my porch lights
To turn on and I wanted to do it when it was dark so between the hours of like 8:15 at night and
6 in the morning
And it it just wouldn't work
Tell me why
It didn't work
So
I called them and they explain that
And so what I did is
I now have it go away I have two robots one that goes from 8:15 at night till 11:59
And then another
Echoes from
It's a good worker and I mean it's not
Ideal core
But you can do what you wanted to do now
Yes I mean as long as there's a workaround
I won't complain
Slightly and
Do you like the only set up these robots a schedule one time
Basically so to me it's
That's a very minimal bit of effort for this work around
Flawless at work
It's very convenient
So gay on that
And we should get to
Will get to the new products
First up SEC filings show that there might be a new Nest Thermostat
We know very little about that butter buddy Dave's that's over at zatznotfunny
Man lives in the FCC database
Closet I'm guessing
I think he's a clerk for them it doesn't tell anybody
Seriously it is it's possible so he discovered that he actually also saw a new filing for it
An August Smart Lock that
May actually have a keypad
I know
I like to keep ads cuz they're good backup
Entry Point Casino
So those were two like worthwhile things that he found and then we should also talk about a brand new product that's out from Phila
It's a new product for their huge line
Is there Wireless dimmer kit
Which goes for 3995
It is
Going to be on sale
Next month
So September
And I have
I tested one
It's actually in my back
Right now
Don't even ask I was just going to say I don't know why you're doing lights in the bathroom with whatever you do is your business
Wake up when I go to the bathroom in the middle of the night
I guess so keep lights down low he and I just thought you were running out of room to Stew
You know testing this is also a problem
So the dimmer switch
So what this is
The kid
It comes with a Phillips
Lux
Light which is there white dimmable light that
Is Kevin pointed out is it
That's correct
Best soft white 2700
Calvin's
And it's it
Sunny and warm
And it comes with a remote control that affixes to a wall mount via
A magnet I'll cook it for you guys
Interesting
Click
Very high-tech
It basically has four buttons on it
On off
And then a brighter and a dimmers
And
I didn't like this product
Glad to hear
It's not laggy it works as advertised
It's just
As someone who
Has Lutron lighting
This did not behave like I wanted
A dimmer switch to be high
First of all
You can't start you can't turn the light on
Crumb
The dimmer position so you can only turn it on for the on position
And it remembers the last
You can turn it off from
Spot does that make sense
So does that mean this is a switch that turns the light on in office what was Tims it right or no
Yes but
In most dimmer switches you can
You can hit the dimmer switch
All the way down
Okay I see what you're saying
Here you hit the dimmer switch and it goes to as dim as it can go and then
But it's still on right now
Understood
I didn't know how to
But you did
I got there eventually
So that's that was
What kind of issue with it the other is that it just doesn't feel elegant the remote control is
A little thick
It's
If you wall mounted
The magnet
It's not tight so
Kind of cookie like
Here it is wall-mounted and when I
Punching it it kind of wobbles
Here when I do hear it wobbling
Yasso
So all of those things just
It is it feels cheap and it is
I mean the light the light
Is $20
Right
The switch and remote is $20
Basically
What I thought was in
Interesting two things
Is the Phillips Phillips's first remote
And it's the first thing that works without the
The bridge
Yeah I was going to say you know this doesn't tie into that goes directly to the light
No it can't work with
Okay you can breathe
The bridge but if you want
Buy this off
The Shelf
An atom
Dimmable light
Yeah so how do you link the the to the light bulb and the and the dimming switch
Contagious
Best work right out of the box
They're already prepared okay
3 - paired
Okay you could buy
That
And then a bunch of other Hue Lux lights and then boom
Your business
Would it work with the
Hue color bulbs or no
It will
I think when you add it to the app
I haven't
Play it around I haven't had a
Enough time with Bridge
I was going to say that probably requires the bridge anyway
Sugar so I haven't
I haven't done that yet
Cuz when you have disco night at your house you can dim the lights and what not
I guess so
Again I'm still waiting for extra settings to like
Get the bridge although I did download a new app so maybe we'll have hue
Shoe app date
Talk about some fun apps
Yeah
All right so that's a lot that we talked
I knew this was going to be a lot
But I feel like we've done a lot
Good things
Guess
Yes and we haven't made a scene
I feel like I made it
That's okay
I'm too overly dramatic when
I acknowledge it
All right so I think that's
That's it for this week so stay tuned for our guest
Who is Claire Rowling
Who is the author of Designing connected products
Read to talk about
You at
User experience for the Internet of Things specifically
Consumer
And we talked about all kinds of fun stuff even things you may not have thought about you problems you have not experienced
Stay tuned for that
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest we have
Claire Rowland
Who is the author of a book called designing connected products
Actually she's the lead author on this
Many others
Lots of them
And hi Claire how are you doing
I am doing very well thank you and you
Super well so you're in London where it's raining so if you guys
Start to feel
Sleepy during the podcast that is not us that is
Soft
Spits of rain
Polygon clear
But hopefully it will keep you engaged
This is a great topic
So
Clear in writing this book
What
Surprise YouTube
Oh well
So I guess
One of the things that inspired me to write this book Quizlet was things that I had learned at surprise me
Ux design of research shows
The Prototype S&M I previously been working in
What happened mobile inside and software answer
Cross-platform services
I'm going to start working in commercial iot
They remember things that this would have jumped out at me as the CDs at these are things I have not to think about before these are things only
Hadn't anticipated speed to be having to deal with tutu quite the expense
And I think I lost it then why
Alabama technical issues
Copesan white background but it was
It was things like
So the impact of
Things like networking
On wheel wells
What happens when you are trying to control a thing in the real world
And you I know and suddenly it might take the seconds to respond to you
So it might not respond at all
I know you saw those aren't there's a quiet visit
Things we take for granted I guess one way when were using the other what happened
Turn screen sometimes they're all these delays and failures
Are we supposed Rising but we we know what to do about this thing
Listen to Real World objects
Consult to feel quite broke
What is a mass-market
Consumerism scary things like
Turn the lights on and it takes 30 seconds to respond and sometimes it just doesn't respond
Sometimes Vamps having you a lights on when I say it's off
I know this is a really really weird things
But I think you know this is kind of every doctors at this time we supposed to type ground say but Ashley doesn't quite strange
Pocket uses
So that was that was nice I guess that was the kind of
The challenges of eventually making the stuff work
Reliably is
Pea flour market expected to
And then I was also
I think the other technical complexity so things like interoperability and just the
Another fight but we have to
I think it is designed as a kind of tend to approach this the stuff with disability lies vision of you know all this stuff just going to talk to each other when
That point yet
On the wrong reasons
Why
We might not be at that point
For example
Connected devices my run on batteries they may not be constantly connected to the network
So actually instead of one kind of great big system in which everything you know is what's best website and everything that is everything else is doing
San Francisco Museum
I think that the kind of states that license say the reliability the intro fertility in the kind of discontinuity Takashi
Really which I guess is this another suppose down to what happens when you put the network
Can things
Didn't work quite the way perhaps I'd expected it to I'm not cool to some really interesting issues design
Okay so
This for you is like
Wow
This is really broken so it's
The challenge
Yeah I mean I think that's the thing that I don't say it's entirely broken but I think that there are sesame some chili
Challenges in
Bringing it to a mass-market Williams Show cyanotic particularly in the home which is a
And I really wish people really don't want you breaking my things
I know probably raising somebody watching the book was that I wasn't saying that you wasn't seeing some of these challenges being told about else by
Okay
How pretty is the internet of things for consumer
The way you're talking about it it feels like
Maybe it's
Not that ready
I think it will get better
I think it's behind snots
I think it's in the process of guessing that
I think there are
Challenges in making
King sings work
As well as
Staplehouse
It never stops my smoke it wouldn't synthetic spice
I think probably won't
Say is it in the in the case of certain products
Conductivity out in connectivity outside and go intelligence will make
Perfect sense within the context of a product with a ready welder signs
Function
So something I can do about something I can.
8 mics
Perfect sense
To be able to wants to be able to access those things while you're
Leasing a car
Strong
I think
Will probably take more time to take off
Is
Thesaurus
Vision of lots of interconnected systems
So are all systems out by which which which which which
Security which one of these things or these things still together
But I think
It's going to be awhile before
I think right now when I was at the point where we can make those things into quite well and it's it's not just a question of
Tell us a question of Designing Common Sense things for bicycle bicycle denied and keeping the
Let's talk about that because
I am so done
In most people look at me like I have grown a third head when I start
I always say
And it's really a second
The second head is probably what would drive
The third head
So I drove my second had a dealer like you're so crazy about the Internet of Things
Talk about why this is compelling
Because
I tried to explain to people you don't demand response and how being able to
Control like
Electrical use in being able to space out you know my washer and my dryer
Let's find use cases where maybe it's systemic but let's get people excited about
Home automation
The internet
Because
You know again this is very exciting to me
So what's exciting about it to you what's the positive why are you do
I think it's about giving people more control over their wealth over their environments
About knowing what's happening
I think it's
About making less environment
Small so that it can it can do some of the
The kind of work that that we don't really want to have to do
I think it's
You know I have a I have a kind of have another thing as well that I kind of like the five of those computers and stuff in there talking to each other enough
What are the challenges at the moment is that it's really hard for people who are not
You don't have a programmatic mindset
Ashley to Tucanos to do go to the specific configuration involves systems that that do
Handle coordination between
Multiple things like Kenobi.
Counter stools and lighting and Security in
Ion safety Systems
Anticipating how old are those things should coordinate with one another
If you push up bad moms
It's going out to people to do that until I will let you know of course I want my I want my sprinklers to come on when I
Looking out the window
I want to come take you to schedule
I'm not scraping social condition some ass tonight then I don't have to worry about watching the god
You forgotten that not things running
Exceptional
There are always the problem is that realized I'm taking home I think he is quite is quite messy
I'm particularly if you if you live in Ohio weather alerts of people coming
Those rules inside but I always want this thing, never want this thing happen
Until you stop casting to get what I want this thing to happen but not when X y&z
And then before you know it
So many exceptions and so many rules, things talking to a coordination how things
It's very easy to select again. New situation where you actually lost
Control rather than gain more of it
So I think that's one of the reasons aside I think Anna Anna in commercial and Industrial settings
It's often very much easier to to codify how things are supposed to be working until identify what's an exception is
What something is that that require someone's attention
And what's not to know when should an alarm one of the things I will continue to research with
People around security systems
One of the problems that people with teenagers have
Is the Titanic unassembled Hive it was tonight
I forgot that folks I forgot to phone spy forget
I forgot the code
Who is always true always triggering alarms in a lot B long shouldn't
Identify
Turn off someones that he shouldn't be bad but actually got somebody
But it really hurts what's it to identify the difference
Because you called
Will oil not person to be able to identify themselves through the conventional mean
I think that's why I say that I think the home is particularly complicated
But I take it you didn't trust me because it's a sizable challenge
I agree
Listen to I adjust written a story
And if we talked about this actually and why am I smart
And someone actually so I talked about reasons being social
And being like a lack of good AI
And kind of a lack of Interest
Stability but
Someone actually looks like
LCC
Why do you want your home to be that automated this idea that you want your home to know this much about you
Maybe that's just not the way to go
You know he has a point
And maybe it wasn't she I don't I don't remember who it was but you know this person had a very good point where
I'm envisioning like my home really having
A wonderful sense of who I am and who is in the home
And being able to react
Accordingly
And I know that's
I know we're not because I actually live with all these devices and I know how dumb
I love them anyway
But I recognize that most people will not want to
Deal with that
I got to pick him like wokasch why do I want
Is it because I really hate turning on
Light switches
Is that so hard
I think in my case there is a passive and it's going to sound like
Does a bit of techno utopianism. I really wanted to be like that
Elias I want the United States to me that they won't survive all that just doesn't let just tell the boring stuff.
So I don't have to
I think it's
There is that kind of berries that kind of dream
It's just a you know I think that fool
Mainstream consumer right now
If you put it turns on
Cortisol
Sing is a nest of all star system is 100% reliable
And if you have something that's
Some of these systems only works maybe 90% of the time
Open maps know it's telling you I saw a real review of a of a connected X system
We shall remain nameless
I was just lost him masturbating Tuesday istick but Seth has
Vice versa
But it's okay cuz you were in the room at the same time so you can see whether the lights on or off
This is why we put the internet
Let's switch gears just a little bit and talk about in your book you have this this fun kind of chapter on
Different types of
Interactions that people
Can have and that's that's one of my favorite things to think about it because
I think when you're thinking about
We've had
Computers you had
Keyboards
Wow
Touch screen
Another category
And now we got voice and that's that's
Excited and thinking about the different ways you can interact
Other things really with wearables
Skin kind of
Talk to things you got the ability to lie
You know there's this
The thing that measures your heart rate
There's all kinds of ways you can
Stop so let's talk about some of the interactions out there
What did
Possible because
Dang it
I don't think we did that in
Beyond
It started to talk to me and respond
It's so
But ticket Beyond things like touchless
Let's talk about plausible you eyes for
Ashley lets slip
Straight to the weird Crazy Ones
Let's talk about what you think is probably
The top you eyes for the
Smart Home
Wow I think he is very much about
What about what's appropriate for what you're trying to do and that will be different for different types of system so
Think that one of the things I would hope
That we can do as much as possible as trying to
Alex light. During the Yuan question but I think
Is learn as much about contacts
Possible
Just as a kind of exhausting longest wooden it be nice if you can if you can do a fixative like
Gesturing to the audience to bring on all your
Hyman's timer system
In front of gas stove
Be quite fun on your I bet it would be kind of embarrassing in front of gas on its also
Just deserve it
Awesome whatever problems I think they're the kind of waving at the nest protect thing from in a year-and-a-half ago I think
People do when they're actually on fire
So
Yeah that's that's that's it.
Challenge invoices
Voice is kind of an interesting one because that's the
It can be quite noisy that can be call me to call 2 to get right it means that you've got to
People can hear what you doing
Which plants s area waste waste want
So I think that was the something about 70 something about devices being able to
Descendants
When you need them and infer from my contacts
I don't know if you've seen this the Concord Towers fixing who used to be a frog who produced a concept design for summer
Roommate
Jared and
Mark Rolston
Quesadilla
When they were frog that they invited me over
It was in Austin
Add a camera
And I believe it
It is interesting about Rumi was it Wilson spouse
August things go to Voice interface this thing has a gestural interface
You notice things using using
Tactile output
Breakdown for 8 it was about it was a combination of two message
So that you could point out alarm
On-site turn on
Stop Islam pea
Whatever it was
And between the combination of the cameras on invoice
Assistant
You you wanted to turn on my lamp and which lamp it was that you that you want to turn on
I think it's it's combining it's the combination
Interface types
On the understanding of the simple thing to do but in a minute it's a relatively simple
Inferences contacts
Foam mat
Makes a much more compelling cyst
I think with the ability to have like
Bluetooth mesh Network
Or if you want to say
I only say Bluetooth because we have
Do cheetahs kind of the accepted wearable standard
So if you got Bluetooth sensors now in your light bulbs or
In
Little things around your home
Other bluetooth light bulbs are Bluetooth plugs
What you've got suddenly is the ability to do proximity sensing in a room so you can say hey this person's
In this room
And you can say
Just turn on the light
In the Assumption as you would be turning on the lights in this room
As opposed to right now when I'm turning on the lights I'm telling
I'm saying turn on living room
This is addressing one of the other problems which his everything in the home is connected
Said you got lots of things
Anna needs a friend not just to figure out which things you're addressing at 8 points and meet you end up please
You know can you can end up with
A massive zones and scenes in groups of elements and send some of these systems
But also then I'll just switch things am I addressing at the moment but I will say which things might I want to be doing something with it
Configuring something to happen to us another time
And so those kind of
Anything I can do to help
A little bit easier running is a scribe
But it's a ways that's always a challenge with contact sensitivity that you can
You can it's pretty easy to live
Well you know I make too many assumptions about what somebody wants in that moment
So I think it's
I think it's about
Combination bios I think it's about options and I wanted to say little things that's really I think
Quite interested in is
The option to choose
The interaction Channel
Best suits audio needs but also your
Abilities of disabilities
So
I think this is a kind of
Is it snowing
Beam
Taraji P
People walking in this area of of accessibility on
I think is it that some extremely powerful potential.
So if you think about it a kind of conventional heating controller for example which generally has a
Tikki bright LCD screen
Listen to somebody with low vision to see
If you can duplicate that functionality in a smartphone. We have I perhaps there that the phone will have Macy's accessibility
Pictures of stuff like my voice over on the on the iPhone
Channel that that person
Which is good for other people but it's also good to people who don't see the Box very well
Missy
So what kind of devices do you have
Your house is it is cluttered is mine
Which is very cluttered it's very toxic but it's not particularly houses with
Connect two things
I don't know if it's composite CSU pumps my fake
Does a couple of fitness trackers
But they kind of the sporadic to use
Is a pebble but again
Baby sporadic to use
Because I'm waiting for my watch to get off of work
Does the wangjing scale
Hue Lights
Amazon favorite Hue smart plugs
I've been testing home monitoring system so kind of spent the kits that
We have an unknown connect
Security alarm testing kind of stomach makes his stuff but I'm already gone to any of it suited to work as well as I would like to
Bissell so I was only featuring control up she's a British gas
At the British a product
It's not The Shining you e-file wanted state is the old one
So that's what we have to do we have anything else
It's so much for coming on the show this week and I appreciate your Insight
White sand
Guys if you are and if you are
Excited about
You asked for the Internet of Things
The book is designing connected products
It is
There's a hefty tome
I'm not going to lie to you
But there is a lot of stuff in here I'm still reading it and I'm still learning a lot of stuff from it so
Yay thank you Claire
Thank you very much for having me
Please
Make sure you tune
Tune in next week
She talked about more
Katie's happening
Internet