Hey everyone welcome to
The Internet of Things podcast
Stye in your eye
Stacey Higginbotham
And here is my co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we are going to talk about
A lot of things
Including our SmartThings
Review part 1
We're going to talk about
Creating a checklist for your smart home when you move
Verizon and its new booze for
I don't know
Building a business on the Internet of Things
Yeah that sounds great
Good luck with that
They've already made almost half a billion dollars so far at this
Year that's pretty impressive
I'm excited because they really haven't
Big leaps into the space yet so that's good
Yes but they decided it was not good enough
So
I'll tell you more about what their
But first
I know you guys are eager to hear about my experience with SmartThings
Which I am sad to say so far
Has not been awesome
What wire
Yeah
This this is already considering to me I don't have the details yet because as I said on the show in the past
If wink kind of goes away
My number one hugged and system goes away and SmartThings is going to be my
Backup plan
Prepare to to Tinker
I believe is one of the reviewers said
So
Here's the deal
SmartThings had sent me a review unit early on in October I was in Harry Potter
World
At Universal Studios hugging minions and having a
Jolly good time
Which by the way
They have these awesome ones
At Harry Potter World
Proprietary technology
But I think they would make so much Bank
If
You know you buy these ones
And they had something like NFC or zigbee or
Bluetooth or anything in them
And when you got home
You could like Point them
At a senior house
And you could say something like Wingardium Leviosa
Open your blinds
That's that's interesting
Proprietary no because it's Hogwarts magic so you know they're not going to do something standard
But that would be cool kind of
Pointing at the device you want to control and then leveraging what I called the
Invisible interface to voice
Or she we should wait a second we should we should build a business around this hang on a second
Seaweed have to
Play JK Rowling
But
I think
How magical would that be
This is my business plan that unfortunately
Involves paying license
To somebody
Get rid of all those silly Way chords We have forever always devices you know
Exactly you could do your whole home in like
Harry Potter or is she or you know
Until 8
The Hobbit or something like that
You are precious
You could be like Gandalf I don't know what does he have like actual magic words or what I have to learn Elvish
Well he doesn't have his own they are there typically Elvish yes
How scary is it
Okay
Now that we have totally out of our cells is
Crazy crazy
Hanging lights up my Middle Earth map of Psyduck
Active
SmartThings
All right
What I
So so having had this II started out
Trying to get devices online
And in this took me a long time because every time I encountered a snag
Being
Someone add I would just say
Well while I wait for this to connect all go play with this other two
What devices today include by the way
SmartThings sent me
Diversion to Hub
And
What they called their monitoring kit the monitoring kit contain
To open close sensors
To the new smaller open close sensors
A
Motion detector
And an outlet
They also sent me a siren
A water sensor
And Samsung
IP camera
Those are not cheap and
They also sent me a roll of really sticky double-sided 3M tape
Which is very
That was the entire package that I got
I don't know the
Retail value of all of the stuff the
Home monitoring kit which contained
Before sensors and the connected home
Was I believe
Right right
And in all of these products that they sent you for who you are available to purchase and are shipping to Consumers now
They are all available in China
One more quick question
Homekit or no homekit support
Just clarified okay
SmartThings The Hub support zigbee
Z-Wave
Bluetooth
Wi-Fi
Those are those are your radio
Okay
A wonderful wonderful option and I've had version 1 of this in my home
For like
Two and a half years and I love it
It's
Lighthouse version 2
Version 2
So when I
Connect so the connection also did a completely fresh
Refresh like a fresh connection I did not try to upgrade
From version 1
Conversion to
Upon their advice they said
Don't do that
It's pretty
And that's actually Fair because I don't think
Most people buying this
Have already SmartThings Hub in all the other fun stuff
Okay so
That's enough if you have it and you want to do
A
Versionone to to refresh let me know how that goes for you
Good luck with that
No I am very curious
So my
So I made a brand new account
And
The setup itself
Very easy of the Hub
I had my account
All is well
And then
I started adding sensors
And it was very quick it was like hey do you want us to find sensors
You clicked yes
I think you click next
And then it started looking for sensors
At that point it found
Two of the four sensors for me and found the motion sensor and wanted the open closed sign
Atlantic capital
In about 5 minutes into that process I kind of got bored
What did it not find
It did not find one of the open closed sign
Sensors
And it did not find the outlet
So
That's kind of where things stood for a while I also added the camera
Dad the camera
You actually set up the camera on its own
And then you added that
Like you would any
Normal secondary device so smart things the benefit of smart things is that it's a very open and it's app
Import hundreds of
Outside devices
So Dad the camera
You would just
Find it as a supported device
And you went into like their security section
There's a section for cameras and it's
Centos supported there like Samsung
And that again makes sense to me as well because
The setup process would require getting the camera and IP address on your network and you know getting that connectivity going on
That it would be able to actually use the camera so that that's fine
Yes and this is the first version to is the first
SmartThings Hub support
Cameras
Why it's different
Special
I have trouble with the camera and I don't know if it's smart things or if it's Samsung or what the
WhatsApp
Hold up is now Samsung does own SmartThings
So I kind of find a surprising
You have to enter like many things
Do you want any Kate when you're trying to connect to
Separate devices
With a password
Some reason
My password just wasn't accepted
So I did a hard reset of camera twice to try to
Make sure that I was
Skating at the right path
But I was
That was frustrate
That was one of the frustration
I'm so I still haven't yet
Scene
The camera
Inside smart things I seen the camera outside SmartThings and it's a lovely camera
I guess it what you just go to a IP address of the
Cameron web browser
I didn't I didn't get so fancy
Passcode on iPad
CNN typically only cuz I have a couple IP webcam
Get there fast games are old
When I look through the browser if the same thing you still have to sign into thumbtack
Which Wich
Make sense from security standpoint
Yes you
Secure home camera
Forever
Sometimes I do sometimes the cats and dogs really
Sometimes put on quite a show but you're right most people don't
Online faces my back
So this is it this is my use case that I was trying to monitor
The goal of setting this up with
Again my dog is escaping
She's very very good at that
So I set up my motion detector by the dog door
So when she walks out the dog door it would trigger the camera to start recording
And since it's facing the backyard I'm trying to figure out which hole in the fence she's getting through this time
And then
So that's that's my goal
I haven't achieved it yet
There's Hope
What's the savers on we're going to get there
So I can let the dogs figured it out and change the password on you but that's just
I know
That that was first issue
So when I came back to it a couple of light
I thought I took a
Wii cost basically for messing with this in
But when I came back to it
I was like
Let's try it again Daddy sensors
So this time instead of doing be kind of generic just find whatever is available I went to add them individually
That also did not work
So
The outlet
They came with it is a zigbee outlet so I moved it closer to the hub
Hoping that would help
How close
5 feet of the Hub
Observation connection
And I press the little button so
Light is blinking everything is good
It didn't connect
So
Not sure what's going on there
And just to clarify this is not a third-party generic zigbee switch this is an actual Samsung SmartThings
Sprint
Yashow SmartThings this came within the Hub
Open close sensor that did not connect
I don't know how to force it to connect I took out the battery to try to
Force
A new connection
It's so far has not
So we're going to
I don't that may just be a
A dead sensor
I don't come
I also tried to
Connect a couple of my devices
And that
Didn't work
I tried to connect those to the wink Hub to make sure that those devices were not
Fault is it connected to the wink hub
And then I
Disconnected them for the wink Hub 2
Because you can't have things connecting on multiple Networks
And then tried again to connect
Candismart things and they still weren't ready
Those received wave device
What about the open close sensor that is
Seen by The Hub
And the open close sensor that is seen by The Hub
Is always open
Even though right now it is
Technically supposed to
So
So what's working
So I have a working motion sensor
Yeah I have also added my Hue Lights
And they work
They are controllable and they're very lovely
My Sonos has also we're seen that's a
SmartThings has a Labs feature which means it's kind of
We have to stay together and
That sort of
So that works
I added my ecobee but it's not showing up
But it technically is supported so I'm not sure what's going on there
And so
Right now
Yes I feel that
This is not
A great
Experience
SmartThings is not so smart right now
But
Have a hopes
I have hopes that I either have a really bad hub
And that I will replace the Hub and
Work
Or I got like a
Sensor that went through like an EMP on the way to my house
I don't know
But we'll figure it out
Because
In the past SmartThings has been amazing
The software update
I've used it actually with my older SmartThings gear because the software update came out
Prior to me getting the Hub and I upgraded it
With my new stuff
With my old stuff
And it was
It was great
Let me ask you a question that
The old house that you have that everything's been working well
You Got It upgraded
Do these new devices
What should these new devices work with the old hub
I don't know because I didn't
Want to mess with
Theoretically I'm thinking they should
Theoretically they should because
The old
Hope still supports those radios
Yasso
Temperature is and I know it's time-consuming for you
Pictures if these sensors that are not connect to the new Hub acts like you connect to the old Hub that's been software upgraded
I will
Try that after I
Yeah they come and give Stacey homework
After I get through this
I've been trying to avoid the SmartThings support Beyond
Basic stuff because I don't want to get special Lake
Right yeah but we weren't us all the time as reviewers you know once
The company finds out your own problems they attach a special
Team 10
Fixed up as quickly as possible but consumers don't have that
So I try and do that what you're doing go through the standard support process and
And so on
Maybe on their help forums we're kind of a little more anonymous
UE
Their health forms are good
And I have online chat
Inspire things actually has great
Like
Normal people
SmartThings will get people
But people will call you
As a norm
A person if you're having a lot of trouble
They actually will get some
Someone to call you in
Think so it's not
It's not like wynk that has a
Support line that you can call
Read after you've gone through like a support forum
Iran chat
Everyone scratching their heads they're like
We're calling
So it's it's not too crazy but I'm kind of to the point where they
I really have done it
Thanks
Well and you have more patience than most because this is
You know that's what we do
9 and 4 standard everyday mainstream consumers
If they had gone through what you've gone through right now I think they probably would return the device at this point
I think a normal consumer probably would have returned the device after
The sensors were not found
Like in the beginning
Which is when I stopped and started adding
Other devices of mine
And it started like
Sure actually broken
Cuz you said it could be just a bad Hub it could be
Something that's a one-off
Hardware issue
But to me is somebody was considering the purchase of this cuz I am
Just like I said I mean if one goes away this is my
My next best choice for me
I'm not
Turn up the lights yet
Well you don't have to
Because I have a spare hub
That's even better good news
So yes if it is if it does turn out I haven't pulled out the spare hub yet
I really thought the
Well I also think there are some sensory issues here so hot
Couldn't even spot that Hub out
If you do nothing else
Cuz it could be that
That is the neck
Good
Next week
Maybe I'll be like
It was the EMP at the post office
So now I will figure this out and
Maybe next week I'll be singing the Praises and you guys should all rush out and buy one but not the one that I bought
One of those thought or question hero I have not I was
Traveling yesterday and
Busy on Monday I have not read other reviews of this new product I'm assuming there are some out there and I'm curious if other people have
Praise this or have had similar problems
So the reviews are really mixed in
The professional reviews
Haven't really said that the hardware is good the software
Is iffy
Which
It's kind of
That's been my
Previous experience with this so I was like that's what I kind of expected
The Amazon customer reviews who said that
Getting this online has actually been tough
And then there's the typical five stars that are like gray product
So
The reviews are little
The place quite honestly
Happened to review the challenge of getting it online and working
And some of them have been kind of like prepare to Tinker
So I don't I don't really know what to say about that
Other than
This my experience may not be that unusual
And that
Seems to be kind of ominous
So that's
That's why I try not to read reviews too much
Before I go into
Same here
Because
But once I once I start experiencing trouble then I'm like okay
It's just me
What's happening
So that's that
Stay tuned
Next week hopefully
Will have a new Hub Maybe
Or maybe I'll have fixed all of this
Maybe it's maybe it's the foil I wrap my hubby
I would say anybody who is thinking about buying this you may want to wait till next week show
Or just a
Definitely wait till they
Okay so
Enough time I'm at let's talk about
CIO magazine
Cover this and I'm glad they did because we covered this before but
I know I do this existed but
The OT aide online trust Alliance put out a check list
Things you should do if you have Smart devices in your home and you're about to
To move
And I'll put a link to it in the show notes
But it's
It's pretty cool right
This this is a pretty comprehensive list and honestly when I have my house for sale last year I kept
On my to-do list make a list of all the things you need to
Pull out of the house or
Reset passwords for its own because
With all these gadgets and things hooked up into the home that somebody is buying
You can't leave them high and dry where they have all these smart switches and the
You're not working cuz I don't have access
You certainly don't want your old data available to the
To the new buyer
If there's a ton of stuff and I didn't really realize until I saw this OTA checklist
Yasso
Some things on here like
Again will give you the complete list but
Things like
Modems gateways hubs
Like in some of this you got to think like are you going to pull out
Your Nest right
Leaving to pull out your connector garage door
So you got to think about book passwords but then also resetting that make
Making sure they can't get to the day
Those are probably the big things
Connected switches
Which I have site mean they're hardwired in
Yeah so it's same here like all my Lutron switches
I like do I
Do you give him like the Lutron
Bridge do you tell him hey
If you want to control these from the internet
The nice thing about my switches and probably yours are they still work as switches even if you don't
Correct
So big they work like normal switches
And
I guess technically anything that's
Part of the home when you're actually selling the home should go to the buyer unless you
Work out something so I guess what we will do cuz we will still be moving just
After waiting for the kids to finish up High School
You know I think what we'll do is we'll just negotiating said do you want these
If so we'll leave the man that will make sure that you have passwords and all that
As a buyer I guess I'd be concerned out
G are these people going to still have access to the things after they're gone I mean
You know it's probably a conversation that actually need to be had
In a way it's kind of like I don't know about you but like I have a
I have a list like in case I die with all of my
Not as social media but email credit cards all those passwords that are there for
My husband
You kind of have to create something like that for your house
But happy thought
I know you're right I mean
Morbidity
You're absolutely right I mean
Otherwise you know it's like
You're gone and then the family is like I don't know how to turn these lights on anymore I mean
Seriously that's that's kind of crazy
And you have to remember like
What are these light bulbs
Bright
Laika the last item in here is like disable connectivity for devices no longer supported by the manufacturer or replace them
Holy crap
Cuz in 10 years am I going to still remember who made my LEDs that are now like halfway through their life cycle
So this will leave in here
It's a great topic
Conversation
For you
Great kind of thing where you're like in the middle of moving now I'm going to have to think about like
Having a conversation and remembering all the passwords associated with all of my connected devices some of which I may not even remember
All right
And now
We should get to
Verizon
What are they doing
Verizon on Wednesday
Is set to announce because today is Wednesday
Is set to announce a
Kind of effort
No that is not a word that is not over
What's a boost
It's internet of things kind of
Revenue Generation by creating
What it cost tools
So what it's doing is kind of
It is launching a cloud platform called thingspace it'll compete with Amazon's Internet of Things
Cloud IBM's internet-of-things cloud and all these other Internet of Things clouds that are out there
How many clouds
Houdini cloud
It is going to have like
It's basically a place where developers can
Point there are things at and send data and then build apps against
That's pretty like normal
Right everyone
But the cool thing that's pretty specific to Verizon is that is partnered with sequins
Sequence the Moto Maker
And it's going to offer modems LTE modems for
Basically half the price of an LTE modem
So about 15 bucks
Really high but it's not as high as it could be
And that's that's important
Because
Cellular modems are expensive much more expensive than Wi-Fi and Bluetooth modems
And that
Really adds to the cost of any sort of device that you really want to build that
Go anywhere and be always on
And it's one of the reasons why
We don't get a lot of trackers that
Doesn't depend on
You know your phone
And
Petition
They're also going to be
Doing
Different profiles and data plans for quote-unquote things
Verizon did not get specific
About the type
Data plans that it can offer unfortunately
But it is willing to negotiate which is kind of an unusual stance for it because prior to this it wasn't
So
If you're planning on making a connected Pet Tracker
Please please because again my dog
She's got an escape at some point in time
And I would love to be able to follow her beyond the
Wi-Fi network
Because right now
I cannot
In a cellular modem on her collar would be
Great for that
Alipay
Maybe a slightly different subscription fee
Alright what wait hold the phone for a second
Because I was joking about this two weeks ago on Twitter but it actually exists
There is a cellular caller
For Pet's they actually showed a video of it with cats but
It's literally a phone its GPS and a speaker in microphone
And it's on the collar of the animal
And you can track where they go and then you can
Speak it up and you can hear what they hear
I was at the meow meow thing
I don't recall what I was laughing so hard when I saw the Cat video of a cat being told
Is it like that French video and it's the woman's eye
Where are you
Yes that's exactly what it is
I did see that I wish that does exist
And that might
I don't know if your dog listens when you
You know tell her to stay or come inside but
I will cuz I can help you
No but you know at least I could see her she said she'll come back eventually
It is it's more just like
She's not being
My coyote
Yeah that's not something you want to hear on a cell phone
Ocado
Oh my God
Total Downer of a show
Oster digital will you pass away if your family don't forget to listen to your dog being eaten over the phone
Yasso
Let's just go straight to the guest
Because of happy guests
It is we're talking about saving energy and
Commercials buildings
I'm a guest is the CEO of enlighted his name is Joe Costello
He has
Actually two cool things
That he's going to talk about 1
Is
Saving energy in commercial spaces
Hbac
And then he's talking about actually
Doing a b testing in the real world
Space
And like the number of people in an office space
And I actually enjoyed it
A big nerd
Discovered from the beginning of the show
So I wish I could say goodbye to you in Elvish can you say goodbye in Elvish Kevin
I could but I want to
There we go
We will not say goodbye in Elvish or Klingon or any of the other languages that
But you know
You can you can say in your head if you
So instead we'll go with and stay tuned for
Joe Costello the CEO of enlighted
Today's guests I have Joe Costello
Who is president CEO of enlighted
Hi Joe how are you doing today
Fantastic Stacy thanks for inviting us
I am super excited to have you we have talked
Bunch of times about enlighted
And this is a company you guys that makes
It makes LEDs for corporate space so
I was going to say Enterprise space but that is not really a thing so
You make it for commercial buildings
And
You don't just jammed lights up there you also Jam all kinds of sensors up there so Joe you want to tell us a little bit
More about enlighted and what you can do with that
Yes
It's actually everything perfect for your show or Internet of things for commercial real estate
Is the best way to die
Describe it
And we put a sensor Network into the ceiling of the building
That's what brings that building into the Internet of Things
And in fact we attached
1 sensor module to every light fixture almost every life
And the light fixture gives the little sensor module power and it's also great for position because if you have one of them
Light fixture it almost guarantees you see every square inch of the buildings ejaculate every square inch of the building
And so we got the power in the place from the light and we give the light back a brain
To send every life we give a little
Piece of a processor that's inside the sensor to the lights
To control the lights
And optimize
The lightning function as well as energy
And we typically say
About two-thirds 67% of the energy
It is used before we install the network we reduce 67% of the light energy used in buildings
Typically it is that because you transfer in addition to doing the sensors and all the benefits that provides you also do an
LED instead of
Incandescent light
Looking really interesting you get a kind of a double whammy typically in a typical installation
Is
You'll get about two-thirds of the reduction of whatever the energy whatever lighting that you put in once you install
Are censored
But most most of the time
We actually put in LEDs at the same time you get even
Morning savings
Because of this is a savings you get from the LED so there's kind of the two factors
There's going for fluorescence
Two LEDs that gives you savings and then there is the savings you get by putting in our senses which takes it even father
Okay and Those sensors were going to tell you a little bit I'm sure
About some of the things that Those sensors and Evil
So
Couple things were going to talk about today which is
You guys have a brand new deal
We're not going to go too much into that
But it'll be a good kind of example of
What you guys can do and then I want to talk about financing
Because you have a really cool model so
As a use case
Let's talk about jll facilities management company in your two new apps because this will give people a really clear understanding
Standing of how you guys kind of get the savings and what you do
For a customer
Yeah exactly I think it's it kind of tells the whole story so the sensor Network that we put in
Is really about Gathering data
On the entire building
Obviously the lighting in it but also the temperature
And then everything going on inside the building all the human activity
People
Assets equipment so
The sensors are being put in
Not
Just to control lighting
Lightning is just a very small subset of what the data that you get from the Sun
Duke
This isn't this information your gathering on the building the building environment can be used
For all kinds of things
Yes lighting this is a great first application
And it's wonderful because we save so much energy that is essentially cost justifies the installation of the net
But once you get that sensor Network any build other applicants. That's exactly what we are announcing today
Is the first
Public Announcement
Other half
Which is our application which allows you to control your HVAC system using this data
In space which is a tool that enables people typically real estate real estate management people
To manage their space and figure out how well or
Hopefully it is utilized
Okay so are is
Dive out there other companies who
Do Air Management there's like building robotics is kind of
Lets people control their own air
Kind of temperature controls now this is measuring temperature up at the lighting level
And
It's basically saying hey
Your cooling an area right now
The people aren't in and that's where the savings come in
Connor different ways you can save energy in HVAC
Systems just like
Lady one of them is what you said
Around
Drunk me I'm cool and beat the heck out of the states
Because it scares that worthwhile attempt
And let's talk about
Space
So you have
In addition to are you have space What is
So this is really interesting to get a whole different now
Energy-savings
Kitchen lighting in HVAC
Is giving real estate people in space planners as they're described
The ability to
Real time
All the time
Exactly how their facilities being used
How many people are in every single space every single minute of the day
But no such data exist today
When you talk to those people about the day-to-day use
They actually use about two things they never one batch data
Did the person come to work
If you have no idea where they are
Then the second thing they do is they do study for people walk around
Literally either with no tags or the beginning of a nation is with an iPad
And then you go into each room and area and count the number of people at a certain time of day
I keep walking
That's the day that they use a one-time event of someone walking around the county people
What you say
Breezy inaccurate sister
Have the actual real time Dairy all the time every single day
There's a gigantic leap in the information they can use for planning their space are there real estate
Buescher in once you have this and you start looking at this
You can take it a step further and
Well you can kind of put the space planners possibly out of a job bye-bye
I starting to recommend things to
Space planners or
People like
Oh
For a
White-collar consulting firm
In this type of Sophos setup
This is the amount of space you need
Yes but you know what the interesting thing is all the space planners absolutely love
This capability
And I get on their passionate about it when they see this week we've been in beta for
Almost a year with a lot of
Customers
It when they see the Olympics
And playing with it
Mitsubishi
If you been in space By Any professional your whole life
You get an instinct
Thanks you have a feeling about what you smell use not well used what the needs are
And he said it so we have no idea who that by the way
Your product
It's great that you weigh more
A whole nother level
We actually have a decent idea about
States that are grossly underutilized
Comedians and we talked to
Put these two different floors and buildings together and save a whole bunch of a real estate rental or whatever
And up
It happens is he getting a meeting
And it's all politics
Is that some corporate vice president with the Henderson group or general manager that's a bunch of baloney
You know my guys know we have just barely in a space we can't cut down you don't want to ruin people's productivity and janz connect
The problem in this business is it's never been data-driven
To have the data
Show people and make a data-driven in fact
Is a true Revolution it's what we've been waiting for our whole life
Okay and that makes sense that a lot of things
I think
Being data-driven is going to change a lot of them
Discussions and
Want to see how it really affects the people who are working there maybe it won't
You find about this is that
Misconception
You're one of the things you find
If you're coming out next year with a product run conference
Conference
Dirty test
Real estate
The truth is when you look at the actual data
That's usually not true
The conference rooms actually aren't that well utilized
What is really going on
And
The problem is
Didn't order to manage conference rooms people set of bookends
And then what people do in order to make sure they have a room is they overbook and of course that creates more of a book
Conference rooms look like
Brookings or that they might be
No we don't have enough conference rooms
But when you actually look at how they're used
They may have to use 25 or 30% of the time
So you have to have a tool to give the feedback
It says he opens up let someone else use
Example of what you can do when you're actually have the day off but I'll tell you over all looking at
Hundreds of thousands of square feet of
Space now that we look at
I've never seen a floor or a space that didn't have at least
20% opportunity for improvement in efficiency in those areas
Or you just have a ton of wasted space and even places where people
Stop the company said
I thought this was a pretty good shape but when I see the data
I realize that
We'll have to see I'm I'm curious Lake
You don't have in common areas or even just having kind of a vacant area where you can like
Momentarily go to rest in the value there
I have no idea what we'll have to see
Cuz your point is
Really interesting cuz there's another group
Maybe a different approach
People who tried to reinvent the workspace
Just as you described
Where you have
It's been having your cure your office in the strict area that you're supposed to be working in
Mix it up a bit more common areas for working anywhere open areas in public areas for
I'll make a little bit more relaxed environment you can collaborate
Etcetera
The interesting thing is that the people that are trying to build those kinds of work space
Love to stay tattoo
Because it tells of the kids some feedback
Is it really work
What is the culture change were trying to effect actually
Doing anything
Exactly and I won't need the name of the company but we had a recent experience where
One of the people here just
Implemented
What are these new workspaces in the building
Running into the building
Can I see it though
Show them the data
And he looks at it and literally in 6
60 seconds he went
It's not working
You said it's not working I can tell looking at the flow in the traffic patterns and what's happening here this is not what we intended
And the question is is it because we didn't educate people
We didn't tell them you know how it was to be utilizing what the opportunities were or is it just designed Willie and so
She got real time data for the first time that we instead of anecdotal or subjective
She could look at it and instantly see it wasn't what they could plan
Wow bummer for him and
What a cool opportunity to be like
Hey now we can try
And this is this is kind of the cool thing about the Internet of Things
And if it works for everything is when you have real-time data you can Implement changes
And see if they're working like
Instantly and you don't have to wait
You know
4 weeks or months you can actually make small changes and iterate very quickly
And things is largest you know changing your company's culture
Which I think is really
Really powerful
It strikes
People I think intuitively think the Internet of Things is a big deal and it is
We just have to find those applications and places where it is at the theaters
Just what you described as what people found
When people went to internet via level of marketing
Websites you could change
How you approach to the cast
Tons of experiments
The same things possible with the internet
More Realty
Experimentation
Truly database with quick
Turn around bright eyes a b testing in the real world
And be like okay guy
Change something this weekend he do make a great catch a case study for you later on
Okay
So let's talk
About
You guys and
You did something very cool probably
I'm guessing about two years ago now when you came into the company
Because
Your product is not cheap
And you had a really tough time
Selling it
Two companies not because they didn't see the value in what you were doing but because it
It's expensive to retrofit your buildings and
As you put it
Facilities management
That is not a budget line item that gets a lot of love
I think you put it a little bit more
A little differently but we won't do that because
Facilities Management so you guys built a really cool product
I say it's really cool because I'm a finance keep but I'd love for you to talk about
What you guys do
No you hit it on the head I got when I got to the company you see this
You put in the SEC
Energy transfer itself
And so then
Turn off the shelves was the first clue
Is an ass
Buildings done....
And it's right there the problem
It was a hundred companies which for a young company with a lot of company
One building
There's one company with a hundred buildings and 19 between 2 and 8
And so clearly we weren't moving from one to two to three buildings quickly
Problem do people not like it is their nose or some tissue
Not at all the issue
If it was just what you said
It was the capital Lobster
Every single building
Costas decided as you said
A couple of dollars a square foot to do this kind of
And the Capital Equipment
Approval or priority inside companies
Facilities as pretty much at the bottom of the barrel they don't get a lot of love I think it's a great description
How do you solve that problem
Will they want someone company which was AT&T
And that's where the problems have been solved
At least the seeds of the problem had been solved
They are we did something that we now call the go model for financing or it's really a business model
AT&T
What's exactly is Experian
Solder technology thought it was wonderful
Went to go get it done
And realize in the process o my God I will be retired by the time I get 20 buildings. It's just going to be
Arduous
Crazy process to get approval building by building
And the issue is
We got to get over that hurdle and so that person at AT&T
In a couple of people at
Ablation invented this year model
Adagio model in its ultimate
The simplest way maybe to describe it
It's like SolarCity for company
Yeoman SolarCity going to come to your house or any of its brethren
SolarCity comes to your house
You don't have to cough up a single penny
It'll take out gather alone without any money
They come there they designed they install the solar panel system
And all you have to do is
And that's what I go model is for corporations
Around the energy Savings in lighting
So we come into the company
We say hey look we're going to all of that
Impinge your balance sheet 1iota
And you start getting the Energy savings right away and share at the beginning to get party Energy savings of course
Your tire price of God
Of the design installation and maintenance of this
Yeah censor net worth
At the end of the term of the contract issues anywhere between three and the longest we've ever done is 10 years
The customer gets all the savings and so this is a capital freeway
How people get all they sensor networks installed and have their entire portfolio real estate
Become
Smart building
3D sensor Network
Paid for by the Energy savings
Finance
To our vehicle legal range for the financing just like SolarCity
And how many other customers have you added since been doing
So we have a starting at the end of the last year
So at the end of 2014
Change the focus of the company
Hayirli to focus a direct sales on Justice
Geocel
Portfolio selling
Not interested
Still it's not the right match with what we're doing
AT&T at the end of last year we batted so far this year six
New jio customer
Gone for the portfolio wide
Approach
An interesting discussion today about errands
Space
Is that when you go in and you talk
First of all those decisions have to be made at a sea level
It's released
The CFO the CEO of the clo
Administrative officer
Potentially sometimes the general manager is someone at that level
Who's looking at coffee
Tire Company
Tire real estate portfolio
And that person typically
Excited is one of the application
You're so most recently I was with the CFO of Fortune 20 company
What are the largest companies in America
In the Sea of Love lyrics
Instantly got the whole Space
Application
They have 35 million square feet of space and their real estate portfolio
Lisa Frank
Untended Garden we just don't have a handle on it
It's been very much
Partition done building by Building Group by Group by area
And we've got to get our arms around that
And we need the data I want that data on every single building so I have an ability to manage everything I want all night
Feliz marte's
And the beauty is
There's no way
I would work out in his case until 7
In order to do the SMART building upgrades you know to make that happen but he goes with your GF
The energy saving space for it and I get my smart buildings that I get that space application so I can actually manage my realist
Facebook data for the first time
You have given
Miralax
Food for thought
About
Many things
I'm like financing models
Occupation data-driven real estate
And of course energy-savings
So
I really appreciate you coming on the show today
Look it's been fantastic we appreciate the opportunity
You know you have a passion about this Internet of Things
I'm telling you it
Well-placed fashion it's going to be an explosive Market over the next few years
Thank you
And
For the audience please State why she don't stay tuned this week but next week please join us
I said thank you for listening