Hey everyone this is the Internet of Things podcast Stacey Higginbotham and
This is York
Kevin tofel
I am bringing this show to you from
London
England
Home of the all kind of
Crazy things including cabins
The Beatles
Football
And the Premier League
I mean apologize in advance because it's possible that I don't
I probably should
But in good news I am
Primacoustic panels
On my way
Studio walls
I have a fancy new microphone so hopefully
I'm going to sound awesome
And Kevin always help
British accent yet so that's good
I'm working hard on not having and keeping my U-Haul
Alright this week we've got a lot to talk about as usual
Amazon news
Low-cost.
Lunch in the UK
We're going to talk a little bit about
Connected sex toys
The Department of Justice
And their creation of a security study group
And then we're also going to say goodbye to Microsoft band possibly hit on Apple's new news cuz we didn't talk
Got it last week
Because that was
And we're also going to do a review of the Kevo 2nd gen lock
Philips Hue motion sensor
Which we promised in
Always go with me forgot to get to
In between that all of our news and our guess we're going to have a message from our sponsor macadamia
And they're talking about how they built a
Medical device that actually integrates with the Alexa voice services
And then finally we have Adam justice of connectsense
If you are cast this week talking about homekit and the home
App on iOS 10
Cool
It's going to be awesome
Let's kick it off with
Amazon news
Yay yay
It's kind of a muffled ear because it's not huge to us but it's it's a huge price reduction on a new.
Yes a. Normally cost
The $90
I thought it was cheaper than that but yeah I guess I did pay $90 but now the new. We all knew. That kind of looks like the o
Is priced at 4999
I'm totally taking one of those up for my daughter
I've been I've been waiting for something like
Because I can plug it into her Sonos Play 5 speakers
And
That will that will work
It will be awesome
Michigan
Talk to her
Will you buy her one in black or the new white color
I'm thinking probably White
Looks nice look shiny
It's always good not always good but
On the inside apparently Amazon has what's called a new Echo spatial perception technology so
That should help
If you have multiple echos are. Sore
Well the cap wouldn't matter if we have to press the Papas
So apparently the new technology will help
.
Determine which room you're in so to speak so they are all
Talk back to you which happens to me all the time in my house actually
The people complain about that a lot
Very rarely does it
Separated by 2
Respect you
And that's that second
That's actually going to be available to the older devices as well so that's good because they're kind of stink if one was smarter than
Then the rest of them so to speak
So
Looks like software updates coming
Eventually
When will probably
Be smarter than the other
We got hopefully a little bit of a ways all right and then also
Anybody listening in the UK
We're recording this on Wednesday to collect tomorrow but Wednesday
Amazon launched their
You kick it like availability for the echo in the UK
So everybody who's always asking me about that
Today is your day actually be in Germany as well
Adam Germany
I'm not in Germany I'm not I'm not focused on the excitement there until you swing by and pick one up there
The people in London
Are very excited
Okay
Enough silliness
Let's talk about
TV underbelly of The Internet of Things
Department of Justice created and ioc study group
I don't know what we think about this this this basically is a 10 to 15 members
A group of people that have created a threat analysis team to
Talk about the threats posed by self-driving cars
Medical devices
Other interconnected
I think I want to make sure that
Jessica's going to say I think they have to do this isn't somebody has to do this I'm going
Glad to see an orthopedic justice department but that's
Neither here nor there
We talked so many times about
Different hacks and tweaks and things that
Have
You don't given personal information through Internet of Things devices and
There's
Obviously cyber security issues going on in the world today so
I think it's a good thing though
I think it's a good thing
I always worry because
You know a lot of these things that they
Get together
They research things for like a good year so and then
Report and then nothing happens
That will have you know I have two cars
Problematic and then we'll have
A flurry of activity
Ignores most of what was advised in that initial
Report and then we'll get some laws that filled
But maybe I'm just cynical
No I don't think you're cynical I think you're being a realist and
And you're you describe accurately what typically happens with these groups but
I guess it's better than nothing so to speak
We should get some good information of bacon actually heal
If you Department of Justice you cancer
Subpoena automakers and sadism
Hey
We are looking at that so we want more information and
Automakers pretty much have to give it to him so
I feel like we could get some
Important
Stop coming too late and just the fact that they're under some sort of scrutiny
Hopefully we'll get them to
I think
Ben
We really should
Pay attention to this even though I know
Felipe
Okay today
The other
Little piece of news that
Against dark seedy underbelly of Internet of Things
Isabel connected sex toys arstechnica has a story that
Yes it's true interest in sex toys so it's connected vibrator
It actually is a lawsuit
Filed by the owner of the We-Vibe connected
Typewriter
Poo
Basically says that the company because it's
The word
How long her vibrator was used for and the vibration settings
She used
And send that data to their servers in Canada that they were violating her privacy
Big cheeser is basically the lawsuit
Terminology
And I feel like
On one hand
Any connected device you have is going to send your data back to manufacturer in their store
But on the other hand
It sounds like she didn't really get much of a privacy notification and she certainly if she did didn't get it until after she had purchased the Prada
Which is incredibly
And that's why I was just going to say that's the key and that's pretty much the norm for all these devices unless you really real
Really digging around before you purchase an iot device
And check
To see maybe on the website with the privacy
I'll see you at your place we buying something and then you're finding out
You know during the setup process perhaps order needs deletion or whatever maybe
Yeah
I don't know if
How to change that quite honestly how does the industry change that
Well I think we need probably some sort of
We need some sort of federal intervention
Or a lawsuit may be a judge
Judicial intervention that says
Hey
You know what
For like a physical product
That you guys are selling people
You can't retro you can't basically after purchase
Force them into these onuris privacy conditions
Or
Arbitration clauses or insert whatever kind of
Issues it's right there
In
With software people
Allow that to happen even though judges
I just hate you
They're like well you can
Alita install at whatever
With apps
Eunos ideas
It's free you just get rid of it if you don't want it which is kind of silly because it's not like you're not going to use Google because you didn't
That's probably the way this
Please out if we want to
Stop this
The question is
Will
The federal government or
Consumer organizations
And I think probably not at least not for awhile
And I think
A lot of the burden is still on a consumer to understand how cloud
Cloud enabled devices working
Let me know pervert example
In this particular case
You could if
You bought one of these connected vibrators your partner
Could be run the world and control the device
Right
That doesn't happen over over Wi-Fi it's happening through the cloud and servers and so on so
You know that going in I think
We have to collectively raise the mainstream
Intelligence about
Peyote and cloud and then so on unfortunately in and I hate to say that because but
People need to understand this stuff
Because it's changing the world is changing the way we live
And yes you are going to give up some privacy
So you need to know this going in
I would also say
Like this could be deemed quote-unquote sensitive information and maybe they could
Medical devices that are connected those things are governed by like HIPAA
Maybe we think about legislation that
Glasses devices that are
Personal
I don't know I mean
But I would also say the rest of the world isn't always a
This freaky is the us about sex
So
Just Beat It
Even something as mundane as like a pill tracker
That's going to know what medicines are on
That might be covered by hippos that it might not be
Against
We'll keep an eye on this because it is interesting especially given the
Companies don't always protect their data and
Yet
That's a problem over the cat act
Kevin you brought up
Microsoft
So for folks who don't know Microsoft does have health tracker
The Microsoft band it's been out probably for two or three years now
I did purchase one when it first came out really liked it it's cross platform
I know an update to it the Band 2 came out maybe last year
But it's looking like the band to maybe the last band
For Microsoft looks as though according to Mary Jo Foley zdnet
Who's very knowledgeable eyes
Great sources
It sounds like the band Hardware is being
I guess discontinued
They're going to sell the current inventory but
It doesn't look like they have any plans to make a new band
There's discussion about the team behind the actual band has since been disbanded no pun intended
But instead of getting out of house tracking what they're going to do is they're going to focus on their
Microsoft health platform
Which you can use to track your daily activities exercise
Y'all different metrics and so on
I have use Microsoft health
Cloud platform
At the time it was not totally impressed by it but it has been a while so I don't want to say anything about the current state of it so
But it looks like another another
Hardware
Dismemberment hear of
Microsoft
About dismembered
Pretty strong
Lychee we've now lost
How many bands like we've lost the FuelBand for Nike
Was killed
Jawbone
When is in
Disarray is probably the kindest frailing for that the maker of
Connected Fitness
Bam and Missy
We got
I got the Under Armour store
And I actually action glad you mentioned that somebody sent me a message on Twitter yesterday saying the
Under Armour
Health kit box
Which I think was was $400 at the time
What is available at Target for $120 which makes me wonder is that going away
I was thinking about that I feel like
Because
I can easily pull in information from other sources it feels like
And because if you look at Fitbit
And what it is.
With the market
People are probably like you know but the engagement should be at the app and you can
Bring all the stuff in
So why don't you leave Fitbit the low in
Band business better phrase
And
Just focus on the software experience of building any coaster
Which
It makes sense
This is kind of how I figured a lot of this way
Play out
Almost feel probably have like Garmin and
Polar
Fitness trackers for really intense people absolutely
Absolutely actually next time on the show I'll have to talk about my polar m600 Android Wear watch
Suu admissions
So yes that's
And we should mention
But we won't go too far into death because our guest is going to
Really going to death
With iOS 10 butts
Wechat iOS 10 and last Wednesday is when the iPhone 7 launched
With the airpods and that sort of thing so
I feel like we should probably talk
Momentarily
Play about it I I will say that I did a story
Last Friday
On what I think I feel like
Putting Siri in your ear
With wireless audio basically gives you
Siri in your ear
Control of the Internet of Things
For the future
Not today
This is very much an interim step the power
Consumption
Texas to hired battery life
Whichever
Everyone think of it
And it sounds like the audio quality on these things
It's probably
Probably about the same as the wired quality
But yeah you raise an interesting point or many in that article
I think Siri has a ways to go before it becomes the end-all-be-all
Your assistant
Not to screw
You purchased
Have you used
Can you purchase the airpod
I did not
I did not purchase the airpods because I just don't see
The
I just don't have the need for it I have other wireless headphones at do
That will work just fine
They're including the lightning
Wired
Earbuds in the phone with the phone
And frankly
It sounds silly but I Twilight I'd agree that Apple has Salve pairing problem for Bluetooth headphones
You only
Typically paired them once
So it saves me maybe 30 seconds of frustration and then
I move on I just did you seem like a very
I don't know what's it's
Typical Apple product
I'm going to say in a wireless World pairing is
A pain point
And you can see they put the
Same attention to detail in the caring process and getting things online
You basically use your phone
A picture of the device
And
It connects to your phone
What's Happening Here is there just like I think they're chipping away a lot of problems that we really know we had at that make
Normal people do I didn't think about what they did with
What airport did they bathe they just made it really easy to set up like a Wi-Fi network
And we're finally getting to the point where the rest of the night she's like oh hey we should probably do some
So again
I think it's a problem
It's not a huge problem but Apple doesn't
Necessarily have to tackle the huge problem
Not very very true I agree and it shows a lot of innovation on their part to create a new Bluetooth chip
The WW1
Which they said they're not going to license
I'm so beat
Specific to Apple products which
Shagging
Typical
But
So an endless are airpods do work with any other device over Bluetooth just you've done
Repair themselves
Just want folks understand that they're not specific to the iPhone
Sparta
Yes you could have airpods
You too could have airpods
Yes
Tell us how they were
Alright so
Let's talk about the Philips Hue motion sensor because we
This is
We must this is Phillips lunch this two weeks ago I've had it in my house
In various rooms
Playing with it
This is a 3995
Motion sensor that will
Basically
Turn your Hue Lights On
And it will be available in October
And having lived with it I really like this
The motion sensor solved
A specific problem that I've had in
In the bathroom problem in the bathroom
And that is
When you go to the bathroom at night
Turn on the light
2B and it blinds you and
You're awake hysterical
So I wanted a light that dims automatically
After I went to bed basically
And then the rest of time it would be lovely
And
This is so sad
The Hue app lets you said
Times for the motion sensor when you setup the motion sensor
You can say
During these times I would like my light to be
This color is
This level of brightness
During these times I would like to be
And then I would like it to go off
After certain
They didn't have the option of going off like
Saying
During the day leave it on for 5 minutes and drink the night leave it on for only 1 minute
Pikachu
I love this
Because I'm going to use the song I think I'm going to buy this
Or a couple rooms were exempt those kind of rooms are usually in clothes
Something to put it in the bathroom
I'm also going to put it in our laundry room cuz I'll often times
That switches are weird
Spot even though I did move it
Using Lutron
Remote on the wall
Switch
I'm going to have to take those out because you can't use hue light switch
Lutron dimmers
But I'll take that switch out
Motion sensor in there any time I open the
Laundromats going to turn on
Your hands are off in full
We often leave the light on
So
Closet
Maybe if you have kids I'm trying to think of that would really be
Crates
I have an open floor plan downstairs and I try to get out there and I didn't like it
There
Simply because
Which is always moving back and forth down there the lights
That's the Hue motion sensor
Goodbye I will say though if you don't have Hue Lights
The stack
Lights
Have the motion sensing capability inside the bulb
You do need a hug Kevin so you will not like this
Buttfor
For $90 you can get a traditional a19 kit
How much is a normal light bulb or for $100 you can get a starter kit for
Downlights
Par30s
Impose
Oh that's two light bulbs in the hub
If I didn't have the Hue system already in my house I probably actually choose this
The staff lights as
Because they can do the same thing
Except you don't have a motion sensor wandering around
That's the review
For you
You can also run 12u motion sensors
On
Sounds like a good solution for very specific use case I don't think it would take out my whole house with a bunch of motion sensors
No I mean it's it's not really worthwhile in the motion sensors themselves
Are not particularly Innovative they're not like
Small order
Motion sensor
Now I will say I have
I think
5 different ways I can turn my Hue Lights on and off now in my house
Yes
That's right it's almost scary
Isn't it though
All right
And the other review we have is
The Kevo 2nd generation
Smart Lock
And this is a Bluetooth Smart Lock
But I insulted my house and
The key feature is that you
Touch
Unlock it
In I'm not having a lot of success getting that to work
But
I will say that the lock install
Easily
I did a video on
Hoping to post it for you guys but
King in London
Fixing a little fun and hard
Aaron's
So install is easy
The software is easy
It doesn't have
A lot of features in
The second generation
The new features they have is a
Smart key
And what it is basically is
It's just extra security around
The Walking Dead
The smart key is All Souls are wreaking feature
Ocado you can rekey your locks using
Smart key
I have not done that yet I pulled the instructions out
I was kind of a little overwhelmed by it will try and see how that works but
I'm not sure
I'm not sure that there's a lot of extra
Value here
Well if the touch feature work and I'm assuming
It means
Sometimes
Okay
Okay cuz so so and what that
Explain to me what that does that when it works so it
If you touch the lock
And then check to see if phone is in proximity that it unlocks
Yes
Okay
Some of it
Might be
I installed this and
I may have been a little too rapid fire and going back and forth this was on my back doors
We don't actually use that door very often
The pros of it are
Kwikset lock which is a
Daily Standard blog
If you've already got Kwikset box at your house
Probably going to fit so that install should be pretty easy it works most of the time
I will say there is a bug with
IOS
10 coming out that
The touch to Rockwall
Work until the issue affects which they expect
I feel like
I wouldn't rush to buy this product
And you know if you're looking for a Smart Lock
Like this is a Smart Lock
It didn't feel like
I need to have product it did not change my life in any way
You can buy an extra key fob
So you can buy a key fob
Quick fats for $25 that
But again
Doesn't seem you're not a must-have at this time
If you have specific questions about the locket would like me to
Do something with it I am happy to
Do that
Eva fans now
I think that wraps up our news for this week
K24a cast
Who is Adam justice of connectsense will be talked about homekit
Some fun tips and tricks and things you could do with
Home app
Before that stay tuned for a word from our sponsor
Everyone we're going to take a break for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is macadamia which is an iot
User experience design and software developer
We have rain and Taemin from Macadamia talking about
Healthcare
50% of your business is actually Healthcare and I'm really curious what's happening right now at the intersection of
The Internet of Things
Clevescene explosion in healthcare and iot and it's
Read me about
Connecting devices and apps
Applications and data
And that's really where we're seeing a lot of exciting new project submerge both in the on the clinic
Girl facing side
Sew-in hospitals and
Clinicians offices
And on the consumer side
What if you guys built
For this Market
One exciting project that we worked on deals with implants there's a sensor in the
Implant during surgery the surgeon can
Manipulate
Depending on where the implant is to figure out the appropriate placement or the ideal placement to ensure that
Got the outcome postoperatively will be beneficial and then postoperatively when they're doing patient phone
They can actually turn the sensor on
And get real-time data and Trends data that they used to correlate with patient
Recorded information about potentially you know activity levels and they can
Sakura.
What they see is happening to the sensor and make appropriate adjustments to their care plan or their
Rehabilitation
More on the consumer front
We're working with a client building a really neat
Kojak product leveraging
Alexa voice services and its product actually help seniors live
Longer and more independent lives at home
So for instance when mrs. Jones wakes up
This device will actually ask her hello Martha how well did you sleep
And we'll find out whether or not she yes she slept well
Will reminder if she's taking her pills if she hasn't because they upset her stomach
That will be recorded in that information
Can be provided not only to the physician in charge
But also to send her daughter
Who is primarily responsible for her care
What do you need to know about working in
Patient privacy and security as the opportunity to take this
Solution to the cloud is happening
Architecting that solution in a way that helps
Healthcare companies maintain their hitrust
And HIPAA certification
Cure connecting a device
And sending information to a mobile device
Because it's being used for clinical reasons if it needs to be FDA-approved
As we mentioned in last week's podcast
The user experience for these medical devices is critical in many instances they won't be used by people who
Add experience with an iPhone or a mobile device
And we'll be looking for a very natural way to interact and communicate with that device
I can't wait to learn more
To learn more about Macadamia and its Healthcare Solutions go to Macadamia. Com Health Care
Hey everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham and we are
The Internet of Things podcast today's guest is Adam justice of connect
Hi Adam how are you
Hi thanks for having me today Stacy
I am super excited so
I told Adam for really long time because connectsense
Started out
Man
Three four years ago making wifi-connected
Outlets and sensors when did you guys start this atom
Yeah we launched that brand in 2013
In the Wi-Fi Center business and
Since
Expanded from there
Getting into homekit with the outlets at
Yes so
Adam was last on the show back in
June of 2014 when Apple launched
Homekit
And I thought it'd be great to have him come back because he's been doing his video interviews are these
I guess they're not interview
Is there there video demonstrations of
What is excited about with homekit
So before we start talking about that
Adam just give me your take
Apple's approach to the
I'm so far
Yeah I mean I stink
You know we were very excited when last time I was on the show and
Finalize apples
Doing something about homekit
And you know that took a little while to get off the ground but
We finally started to see it on products shipping last year you know in quantity
And it started to gain momentum
And
Now with
Everything you're doing an iOS 10 it really feels like apple is finally endorsing this
Putting its full weight behind it and I think it's a really exciting time
Brung it but for the industry in general and kind of home automation
In general
Why are you so excited about the industry in general cuz right now I feels kind of like worth it
Trough of despair
And people are question
So many competing standards than efforts and
I kind of look around my house in like God some of this is just junk
So why are you excited
So I think this is really a moment for the industry where you know people are going to install iOS 10
And this week and
They're going to see this new app on their phone and start to think alright what can I do with this you know maybe that brings them into an Apple Store
Best Buy or somewhere
I got to see that homekit logo and really start to get
You know what idea of what they can
Do it. And I really think it comes down to
Consumers having that one
Great experience
And you know
Comcast says a lot of things
Right
To get that first kind of wow experience and I think once you have that
It leaves you wanting more and
That's one of the nice things about
Don't get experience as a you add more
Products
To your home
1 + 1 is
Is more than
You might be for 5
Okay so
Listeners who are not well-versed in homekit
Basically to get certified as a homekit device you have to have a special Apple Certified Wi-Fi
Work Bluetooth chip IP
Init
In the device basically being
Mfi certified
And that allows Appleton
Ensure the security between device
That's important so every home kit
Device out there has this special chip
And
Let's see what else do you need to know
The other thing to note is that
Are the standard in general
Memes that if you
Buy multiple products that bear this logo
I'm you're not going to have to worry about trying to figure out how do I get these
Things to talk to each other or how do they coexist
That's just kind of comes natively
Awesome so
Last year these devices started hitting the market but you could
Control them individually through the apps for like the elegado Spencers or for the Hue Lights
What's happening now with iOS 10 is
Apple is releasing
Home
Which is an app to control all of this together
Now third-party companies had
Released these types of programs before but
As Adam pointed out these are
It's far different
And far more mainstream when apples like
Here it is
And
I don't know if it's actually going to be right on your
What's that screen called where you
Pull it up with your finger and like
You get your
Flashlight
Can your Wi-Fi settings you scroll over to get music and then scroll over that you get
Home
Yeah so that's called the control center
And I really think I just put out a video in the last week
I really think this is one of the killer apps for iOS 10
And homekit
Because
You know
That home app or you know Siri are great ways to access stuff but being able to
Just flip up that
Control center
Do something really quick is
Really nice and elegant
Got it
Okay so
Let's talk about
I played with
Home
In iOS 10 and you have to so let's talk about some of the features that you know
We think are really cool
Ashley Let's help people
Let's start with adding homekit certified devices
How would we do that
How is this differ
So that's done there's a little plus button up in the upper right-hand corner of the home app
And that's where you would go to a device
And
So some of the things that
Apple does here to make this Annie
Easy process
Is they have a a process for Wi-Fi accessories called Wireless
Accessory
Configuration or wack
So that means
For a certified accessory
You don't need to go find that little
Piece of paper that has your Wifi password on it
If your phone is already
Talking to
Your Wi-Fi access point
It will just pass those
Details write down
Statics
So that's a really nice
Simple way to get
Devices on to Wi-Fi and then from the security perspective
I'm you're just going to use your camera to scan a code that goes with every accessory
And then boom you're done
Enough from there
Customize it kind of put it in a room
Decide if it's a favorite accessory or not
The things like that but the set of processes
Is pretty elegant
Pretty easy
So when I first start
With this
You know if I'm imagining myself
I'm excited about
Do you have any advice on what the first device
Someone should get is
How to even think about what they should be
Either the first device
Is always
A hard one but I think you want to solve it
Easy problem so or kind of a
Convenience Center
Your life
Shows this can be as easy as like I want to turn on this lamp
You know he's away your you know I want to run this on a timer
Like that so
In a frog getting started device I really like something that doesn't
Acquired
Too much install you know like are smart Outlets
Where it it just fits over an existing Outlet
And then you know once you get a feel for what
It's all about
What's going on then you can
Going deeper with some
Sound like a door lock or thermostat or something that's going to require a little bit more
Install time
Got it yeah I'm always like light bulbs are good Outlets are good
And other things
They're a little bit more
What else like when first homekit came out
People kind of got frustrated because it was hard to tell Siri
What things to turn on
And there's very
Real naming conventions that you need to follow
Do you want to give people some advice about how to name things for homekit
To avoid Lake
You know I I remember actually I had this issue when I got my Amazon Echo
And connected it to my lights it was like
Kitchen light
It was a little ridiculous
So
What about what makes it easier or
How would we do that with him
So there's a ton of different ways to kind of give Siri commands to something
The most basic would be what you name a device
I think something that's
Easy to remember and
Easy to under
Stand
Is definitely important
And
Also that you know Series going to understand it too I think there were some issues early on that this is God
Way way better as time has gone on
Even throughout iOS 9 and definitely more in Iowa
You don't have to memorize a script book of phrases
You know things you would naturally say us you know
Turn on the bedroom light or turn on Adams bedroom lamp for
Something like that it's going to make sense and however you're going to phrase that
Siri will be able to figure that out
When you add a light bulb
Example to a room or lamp it gives you the
The option of saying
Hey this is Anna living room this isn't it better
And you should actually take the time to group your lights if you're doing
Several rooms at a time or one room at a time
Because then you can just
Say hey turn on the bedroom
And then that will have
Yasso
Definitely setting up rooms is a great way to command a bunch of devices at once
So then
You also have this concept of services so like all lights
RS Turbo
So then you could say things
Like
Turn off all the lights
In my bedroom
And that will
If you want to get him more cost of you can also program was called the scene so you can
Group together multiple devices
All at once
I haven't seen them like goodnight is a great example of one that
Built-in
Default and so you know
Whatever you want to do lock the doors
Turn off the lights
Set the thermostat down
When you say goodnight
Making program that all into that one action and then Siri understands
You say
You know hey Siri
Goodnight then it's going to program that scene
Set your house for whatever you sent there
All of our podcast listeners their house just went dark
Apple really did something cool here I think
Actually I first saw this with Sivan
Which is a
Can a higher end
Home automation company
But they actually let you
If you get if you basically set your lights up and maybe your thermostats perfect maybe
The dimness is great everything's perfect
You can actually just tell it to take a snapshot of that
Create that scene
Which I think is great cuz
You may be like hanging out
You know doing something to eat, look up and you're like you know it this is pretty nice I'm very comfortable
This is how we watch movies
Let's just make this our movie watching
You don't have to go back in life
Figure out how my lights are
20% or anything like that my air conditioner at 75
You just
It knows and I think
Those kind of touches are
Very Apple
Like actually I used to call Savant the apple of home automation
Now that Apple's doing
I don't know what I'm doing
Let's see what else do you like or is worth talking about
So I mean I think beyond the basics in the whole map
You know once you get diondoes
Initial things
Definitely getting into that automation tab is where you can start to do some more advanced stuff
So this should be where you kind of run
I do a lot of kind of scheduled stuff so my front porch lights are tied to this
So I have a
Daily automation to turn those off at a certain point and turn them on at
At sunset
You can also say
You know when
This device does
Something
Then
It'll trigger the scene
So cool example I like a V
To be like
Is there something you're doing anyways
That would say I'm going to bed so let's say
You turn off
Your bedside light
You could actually
Make a automation that would say
When I turn off my bedside light
Send trigger that good night
So instead of having to kind of be
Commanding of it
Just do that activity that you do anyway
In your regular routine
And I think that's where it starts to get
A little bit more while a little bit more
Senator tell everybody who tries to do this as someone who once spent six months trying to create the right
Automation for going to bed
I'm not sure it can be done if you live in a household
But I started with turning off my bedside light but then I ended up turning off
You know
Everything downstairs while my husband
Can we still down there
So then I was like okay
Let's say
Let's what I turn off my bedroom light and there's no motion downstairs for 15 minutes
That was not great because then
For 15 minutes afterwards like
Nothing would happen
And I was like
Go to sleep
So
I played around with a bunch of different things in
I finally gave up
So if anyone else has some creative ways to indicate that feel free
My other thought was just stick up button on the bed and just
Prescient
But I got an echo when I just tell her
What do you do
Worse
Do you have more successful automations Maybe
I do a lot of timers that I'm running
I do some automations
Stuff like that
You could also get pretty complex you could kind of give it
Some variables of like
Only do this
When
You know this light's not on or something like that so
How to take it account that
That scenario
But yeah I mean I think
The important thing to remember to hear is like
They're just getting started with this stuff
It's definitely going to get more elegant and more advanced overtime kind of got to build a foundation for
Somewhere
So I think it's a great place to start and
It's only going to get more exciting
I feel like right now I'm having the same sort of feelings conversations and whatnot that I had probably too
Two or three years ago when all of like
SmartThings and
Staples connect Hub in the Lowe's Iris Club
Hub came out
Which was all around
Kind of programming an Automation and scenes
What is different this time around
I would say the
Big difference is that
Certification PC talked about earlier
It's really important for
Security but it's also
Ensuring that all those products are going to work together so
I don't know that some of those other systems
Go to as much of an extent
To certify products it's more like you know that product builds in integration and
An Hayward
This is pretty deep
Level
You know integration
And I think as we move Beyond in a home automation where it is
Today 2
You know more of the kind of conscious home
Concept where
Enter your home is kind of adapting to you as you move through out at throughout the day
That's where this kind of
Deep level of integration between devices
Really going to matter
Another thing is how people might use apps
So you know if you're like me and you have dozens of connected devices you also have you know
Doesn't have to buy apps on your phone for those connected devices
Part of the promise of Home seems to be that I don't actually have to open those apps anymore
And I'm curious as a company that's making a device
Is there a way for me to like setup
Do I need to even
Download The Connect Sense app to
Connect a
Connectsense
Outlet
To home
So certainly we would still love you to download our app but as a
It stands today no
You wouldn't have to download it
For anything other than a firmware
So that's something that you wouldn't be able to do in
In-app so we definitely still recommend to our customer
Samurai pain there
Especially for that
I'm one of the cool things
Home does it do
Is that if you dive into the details for an individual device
Is it'll actually linked you out to that man
Facture app
So I think any time you're going to have
Middle set up or maybe troubleshooting or
Even some more advanced
Can't go into too much detail but we're working on
New features for our smart Outlets that you're not going to see in home
You know home is at basics.
You want to be able to turn outlets on and off
We're going to build
Some deeper cooler stuff that you're only going to be able to do in are at so
I think there's still a place for manufacturers apps
Home becomes kind of that
Default everyday experience
How many people do you think will want to go that much deeper
Is it feels like to bring
This into the mainstream
Homekit is addressing a lot of the issues like it's hard to get things connected
You know there's so many features that's hard to figure out what you want to do with this stuff
So in a way home is like a nice entry point
And the hope is you people will go deeper
How many people do you think
Really well
Yeah I mean I think you've got your mainstream user and
And they're probably going to
Stick mostly to home
Most manufacturers I think
Probably will recommend set up through their ass
You know a lot
Do
Special things are going to have some special sauce they need
Setup process
But that's fine but you know I think you have also your your hire end-users that are
You know
More
Going to want to do more complex things and I think that's it
Interesting place where manufacturers
Can still be Innovative and
Bison
Other unique
Queso
Most people feel like Hardware is going to be kind of commoditized in the space overtime
Are you guys worried about Apple kind of taking over the customer relationship for y'all
I'm not particularly worried about it I mean I think
It's still
They're going to help bring it to
To the mainstream and
That's good for Hardware companies
And
You know we are still going to look for ways where we can differentiate and provide great hardware and Grading
Experiences
And you know to me is it's a partnership
So I was excited when I saw
Stall mats I saw it as a
Endorsement I'm not seeing it as a threat to anything we're doing
Okay
All right things got a little dark there why don't you tell me your favorite thing to do with home
I would say my
Favorite things
Do is probably set up favorites
And then like I mentioned earlier you
Use those favorites
Control center
As of uses throughout the entire beta process that's probably the one thing I find myself using
The most cuz it's so quick and easy
And
Just gets whatever you're looking new
Get turned on or off for control Done Quick
Do you Siri very off
I do I still use it from time to time that's probably one I use more so for
Scenes
Quick control of another individual devices control center
My go-to
Okay and we should also mention that
When you're out of the home
You at will need an Apple TV to actually
Heard like timers and things that you said so scheduled items
You'll need an Apple TV to make sure those run when your phone isn't around
Or an iPad
So
I assume you have something like that in your house what is your
I do I use the Apple TV the latest
Greatest thing as Apple
Before
Contact us at HUB but I was really happy that they also gave that
That option for an iPad
In the settings field
Sitting for a lot of people iPads kind of a couch device that doesn't necessarily leave the home alone.
So that makes a ton of sense
Gives people some other out
Oh shirt yeah I've got
Who say I have iPad scattered everywhere
Mom so now I
Anything else you want to tell us about him
I know I meant think it's in
Exciting times definitely think
People should check it out when they upgrade to iOS
And this week
And if
If you have questions you know I'm sure Stacy and I'd be happy to feel them meter on Twitter
Find us
Define social networks
Twitter handle
I'm at Adam Justice
Takis taste
But you guys need that
Adam thanks so much for coming on the show today
Thanks for having me well that's it for this week show thanks for listening and if you can't get enough of the
The Internet of Things podcast please subscribe to my newsletter Stacy knows things at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
As always will see you next week