Hey everyone this is the Internet of Things podcast
Stand this is your
Stacey Higginbotham
And your other host
Kevin tofel
And we have got a lot of really good stuff for you this week
So far we've got Google's new router
Intel
IDF which is a
It's developers forum
We got some new findings from some iot startups
And we have an awesome guest talking about
How
Enterprises
We'll be able to like take advantage of the Internet of Things
So with that
Let's get it started
Let's Get It Started actually Google got it started and we talked about this possibility in the past and now it is real
Google has a brand new wifi router
Which of course everybody has a Wi-Fi router or two or three Vanessa pose in their home
So this is the onhub and what
Makes this different
Couple things actually
This is actually supposed to be
Put out there not hidden away in a closet or data center
Don't room or whatever
This actually looks like a nice router make
Do you have a date
Bats entering your house
I can neither confirm nor deny a Datacenter Nore safer
Excellent
Will you know what I mean some people
Crazy little mediacenter closets and such were they have all the servers for
Stuff
That's where the router is and also
Well that's no good because you don't want these Wireless signals to be
In the corner of a house in closed room with walls for the signals to pass through
This actually looks like a nice little
Gadget or Appliance and I know there's a difference between the two
It's a nice-looking router doesn't look like a router I guess it's
Probably the best way to say it
The onhub
The other thing is supposed to do is not to look pretty but also its
Should be simple to use
It's a bad end Google has a little application course there's an app for everything
And the app is good for Android and iOS
So that way you can configure your router or you can
Check the status of it and so on
There's I think like a dozen or maybe even 13 and 10 is in there and
One of them is constantly checking
For your network quality and what the
The ratchet does the onhub
Lashley
Several other routers on the market but
What it will do it will change the channels and provide
You look like a quality of service
Certain types of traffic so maybe you're watching video and you want to make sure
That you're
2160p stream from Netflix is working good
You know the onhub can help with that
That's the tie level but at a lower level
What is this have to do with iot and
Stacy I think
You might have said this in the past
Maybe there's going to be a router that
Will support natively like brillo and weave and all that stuff for IRT from Google
Will gas so
Back in the day
There's actually two reason
One is religious
The most obvious
Which is that there's a lot more devices
What's with the internet
And when you have more devices
Your network is just inherently more
And
When you're sticking something that stationary on your wall or on your door that's going to rely on Wi-Fi
You're actually going to
Since you can't move it to find like the best quarter in your house
To get Wi-Fi reception for that thing
You need the best wifi all over your house
So having a really good
Browder
Impossible even more access points is really cool
The other thing is
Being able to prioritize is just
I don't know I just think it's so essential
Especially like if your
I just think the more devices you have the more you need Tennessee's enterprise-class
But
Sexy stuff
We did talk about Brillo
Specifically
As kind of a
A real time operating system for The Internet of Things
The Google was talking about
Putting inside
Routers
In
We still don't understand how this is actually going to work but the idea was that
It would have some sort of Hub device
That would kind of talk to other devices on the Note
And how to control them in
Onhub could be that device
Right now the Amazon Echo actually is the brains of my smart home
In many ways
So it is not crazy to think
That a router could also be the brand
Smart Home
Especially
If it did more than
Well this actually does because it supports Bluetooth as well
Once you start supporting Bluetooth
Then
This could act as kind of those Bridge devices for things like
The August door lock that doesn't have Wi-Fi built in but you want to give it that keep
Ability
And you don't kiss again a lot of these devices that are Bluetooth only
That you want to add that remote connectivity that Wi-Fi get you
They sell these
Extra
Plugin WiFi Bridges is kind of what they're called
In
I think I've seen about
Four or five of these marketed
Ford locks there's some for sensors
In the problem with them is
I don't have that many outlets free
In my house
And they're very ugly
I'm pretty but you know you only want so many white boxes
Stick it out of here
So if you can cram all that door router
My God
Please do it because
Hey it's one less you know $50 Bridge you have to buy
One more Outlet to free up
I'm excited about that
It looks a lot like there is a startup actually doing something sort of sim
Call the Eero
It is e e r o
And they're trying to make a beautiful router with awesome kind of
Features
Much like this it has Wi-Fi and Bluetooth in the router
In doing a lot with software so people do not have to
Become like
Years in order
What there
Yay
So I think this is
Awesome this looks kind of like a reference design or may not
Quite the out in the market
Dad is fat
No it's actually available now for 199 99
You can get it now from a couple places
Direct
From the Google Store from Amazon
Walmart.com That's only in the US
Starting today
And it will be on sale in retail stores in the US and Canada in the next few weeks
So it's
It's actually available as of
The show literally today
And there's a follow-up is going to be another one made by a sus
That will also cost 199 so this is
I guess that's kind of where you going with this is a reference design
It seems like there may be a anyways Fleet of these types of
On hubs are not calling and routers are calling at the onhub
But you'll be able to purchase
Got it okay so yes that's what I'm thinking about 9
I think I was reading about the AC
Made devices
Right later this year they didn't specify when that would be
That's great cuz you know I forgot tp-link access
Set my home and I've played with the tp-link cloud management software
Adidas no bueno
You know I talked to Chet Pipkin he was on the show and I talked to him in a brainstorm Tech event
And I was asking him I was actually begging him I was like you know you guys bought the Linksys name
You know what
Bringing back the iconic lie
Linksys router shaper
Is a cool idea but you know the best thing you could do for the Linksys brand to keep it relevant
Is introduced some awesome
But consumer-friendly software that does the things people want to do
Cuz his response was like
If you log into your router you can do a lot of that
Technically he is correct however
And I don't care what brand router you use I've tried most of the major ones
Yes he is correct if you just log into the router you can there's usually web interface
They're not
Not not
Friendly or easy to use or not intuitive
Most consumers I think would
Look at half for only be 3/4 the verbage on these
Set up
Apps and say what
It does that even mean
So
Your chances are there's a lot of routers that do some similar things to the onhub now you can you can
Specify quality service for video streams and so on and so forth now but you have to know how to do it
So if they've created software that makes it simple it basically says
Would you like to prioritize your video
Streaming right now I'm going to say yes
They're not going to know what the other
Jargon is
No see what I'm looking at this article in wired all about
The onhub
Guess what it says
It supports Bluetooth Wi-Fi and Google's new weave language
Which which is designed to help appliances in Connected home devices talk to each other
Yes
So there we go we've got brillo and weave
Presumably brella somewhere in there definitely we've we still aren't 100% sure what we've is but maybe forget a router in
Start
Start playing around with it we'll figure it out
Maybe we can figure it out
All right
Okay
There we go we just spent $200 each
Really one of us
LOL cancel my order
Cuz I'm currently
I'm always happy
Just out of curiosity how old is your router and what standard or standards does it support
Oh it's a doe isn't your tooth at 11
Alcatraz is mine
So it's
Recent
Enough
I can't tell you what version of mymo it is
And how
Up-to-date data
That's okay I don't want Rider Envy of yours is better than mine
Cuz I was serious I'd actually I haven't streaming 4K Netflix throughout the house and that the router is in the second floor on
On one corner of the house
The TV is on the first floor in the far opposite corner of the house
Your TV should be hardwired
I don't have any hard wiring in this house of Fortune
If it's all its
Is Wi-Fi or nothing in my home so
And I have to say I have a masseuse it's older it's at ac66u is the model if I recall correctly
And it was one of the best investments I made
Two years ago whenever it was
Netflix stream 4K working rate and that's with other people
Using the network in the
Very
Perhaps one day we will do it
A total episode dedicated to router subnet
And really like lose every
Today is not that day people don't worry we're done go ahead
Is Intel in other big company news is Intel
Right now this week in San Francisco
Will say across the street from the
Target open
At home store
Intel developer forum
Which is
Big
Great show
Today or Tuesday
Intel CEO
Did the keto
Which was
Surprisingly
All about the internet
It's not surprising Because The Internet of Things is like the hottest thing since sliced bread but it was surprising because Intel didn't actually
Can't talk about any data centers he didn't talk about
Any of the new light chips for workstations or laptops or servers
I'm not surprised I mean that's
That's not sexy in 2015 you know I mean I know that's important those chips are very important Data Center
Obviously important
Considers is Fort
Billion dollars
Alright so it's important to the capital i
With but the point is what's up incoming and
Obviously we know because we talked about it every week
And Intel has
Been late to Market when terms of mobile for example
And they don't repeat that when it comes to IRT and that's why it's the S this year
That was a big part of their
They're keynote as well it wasn't
It wasn't those data center chips and graphic chips
And so on and so forth in the newest core chips for PCs
They were really showing off skin
Iot wearables and stuff like that so
Wasn't surprised that's what I mean
Okay and
So from a chip perspective
Really what we saw it was something they introduced in
That's it yes but when they introduced NCS it was a concept
Yes
And
Inside it had a
Arm chip
I said it out loud
What was a concept I don't I don't fault them for what happened for folks who missed it they were showing off I don't recall
It was like a
Headphones that could measure your heart rate or something to that effect was something with their wearables division it was Prototype
And we later found out that even though they were talking about their own stuff all the time it had an arm chip in that particular probably because their chip
It wasn't quite ready for this
I don't fault them for that but it was a big brouhaha the time
So
Now
Several months later they have
It's called the Curie module
And this is a module
It's a whole pack
Which has the
Work which is their kind of tiny low-power small
It's a 32-bit
Chip
So the courtship
It's got 384
Kill the Lights
A flash memory
And it has a
DSP sensor hub chip
Bluetooth low-energy radio a 6 axis accelerometer and gyroscope
And
Battery charging stuff
Like I'm Epi Macon it basically which is a battery charging
Capabilities so it can be plugged in if you can charge it
So this little module is about the size of
Thumbnail
Little bit
It's hard to tell
So it's really tiny and they showed it
At the the
Keynote speech
Integrated into handlebars
Cuda BMX bike
Language of course
Was on stage doing
Crazy tricks because you know
You can't have an event like this without welding
So that security platform
And it runs a lot of different
Soccer kits at Intel calls.the Intel IQ software kit
It's there's things about identity
There's things about time to do
Pills with scheduling
There's a bunch of them
There's Fitness ones like
It's kind of the answer to
Healthkit
It's more like
We give you give us a bunch of data and
These IQ systems run algorithms on them and pop out like
Useful answers are useful information
I'm and they're designed to do it like in a very small kind of
Computer memory
That is what Intel's that's kind of the Practical platform
And
Keto at the actual event
They should have some cool stuff like
A little clip that you can stick on your baby's car seat that you know when you
Can you put them in the car seat
It won't allow you to walk away from the car seat without the baby
You know what's nice for not leaving your baby in the car seat
And you know people were I I was I was on the Engadget live blog for a moment they were
Who does that
So it happened sadist people
If you could pay that have that not happen to you
I guarantee you you would pay to not have
So silly
So there's there's cool things like that there's the date of you know for the bike handles or other athletic equipment from the tree platform
You know so with Intel idea of things lot of flashlights of in no devices
Lot of wearables lot of I
Coyote which parintele actually are two separate divisions
I still don't know why
Maybe one day we'll
So that's what that was
At this point I mean the Kure even though they announced it was coming
When they discussed it back in January this is really I guess Carrie is coming out party so there's no actual products as of yet that use it
Don't
I don't I don't know how
I don't know of any it's
It hasn't know it hasn't been a
Approved by the FDA
Absolute Radio
You can't have it in a product
And Intel.
Seem to me
I don't think so
That's about their Style
So yeah so we should be looking for until
To really kind of get into the consumer iot a little bit more which is
Well
That's kind of leads to an interesting question you know
What Intel needs now that has a chip and a software platform for it
Who's going to partner with Intel
So that they showed off Google
They should have some
Some real time audio kind of stuff with Google
The Shootist
Project Tango which is Google's 3D
3D imaging
Yeah I said it's a developer kit right now it's a tablet with them a bunch of sensors so that way you can literally
Get a 3D map of a room or object
Using his tablet and Intel has their own software called realsense which uses depth sensors of the Dell
Android tablet if it which one exactly it is
Uses Intel's depth-sensing I'd heard that those two
Supercuts
Working together now.
Realsense and Tango
Yes and they showed that off at the Keynote
And they use the word sense of occasionally
Which meaning
Shutters
No no no
So that's that's not Curie that's their the real Sin
Monster
Yassi
I'm just thinking
Again having seen until get
Essentially demolishing the mobile market by
Arm processors
People have so much people I should say that
Company's product companies have so much
Time and money and effort invested in the arm
Platform
That I wonder if they're still going to be a struggle for until to get a foothold in the wearable Market
Now intel did show off
What they said was an Intel powered
Android Wear smart
Watch
That was made by father
Interesting Yokai fossils of the late to the game on Android Wear but that's okay
And so
All we know about it
Is that it's going to run an inn
And that is all
I'm going to suspect that's probably not curious while I'm going to say that's a small Adam but we will see
It is a small
Yeah that makes more sense cuz it that I know what kind of phones they need in the Android Wear watches
Good luck in telxon minutes
What you know
Again I never bet
I don't know until because they have marketing they have
They can buy stuff if they were
Taking subsidized stuff I mean that's what happens with the low-cost Windows laptops you know that that's why they're cheaper than Chrome
Looks with your running arm chips
You know Intel is putting their atoms in
Tablets
Laptops and paying the the hardware vendors to do so
So I
I don't know and you know they bought basis which is one of the best
Hardcore Fitness Mark Hour Fitness
Activity trackers out there
A lot of people
I agree I wouldn't bet against a migraine
So we'll see
Little short bits of news
I'll send a big companies on the startup front
Filament which is a company that I have loved forever because it
Combines two crazy things which is the Internet of Things
End
Blockchain
Transaction database behind
Bitcoin
So
This company has raised $5000000
And has come out with its
Core product which is a
Ruggedized
Sensor
And in Bacolod
Tap
In the network
Kind of architecture the taplerun on
And the network architecture is basically a technology stack
Around blockchain
So it's going to have blockchain for
They kind of distributed database
It has
BitTorrent for distributed file sharing among all the sensors in the network
It has a
Mesh radio technology called
T mesh
Which is really cool it can go 9 miles and has incredibly low data rate
It's like
300 kg
Minutes like might be the first dial-up modem my head
In the 90s
Actually sorry
It's really slow but
But it would be for
Small amounts of data
Diverging from devices
Is this sensor on is this soil
Fred dry
Yes basically Boolean type on off
Pets
So is Elsa runs Tallahassee
Which is a private messaging service so that's
How these things are going to
Communicate
And
I feel like there's one more thing that I'm forgetting in here
The authentication software
Oh say can you see
Which is apparently that's the contract kind of
Authentication software
And it is used it's an ietf standard and it is used in a watt
You may be familiar with a lot because anytime you sign into something using Facebook or Twitter IDs
On the web
That is a lot basically
So
That is
That's the network stack that they've built
It's a really compelling idea because
Tidy is compelling because it's
A decentralized kind of
Coyote
Internet
The reason that school is because if you're somewhere in the middle of nowhere
And you don't have like the internet connectivity
This allows your devices to actually you give them a piece of information or a contract and they can just keep
Running off of that until you update it
So until like
If your
Your farmer in a field
Until you drive out the next time with you
Your phone
Or a satellite phone if
If you're going out
Middle of truly nowhere
You know you can
Update with that connectivity like on a one-time basis every week or every month or every year
You know when and then
Pick up the information
Distributed
Price of it so the data will actually be stored
In devices until there's a connection available
Texted get it and or
Send receive
Yes
So it's good for
Crazy remote places it's also good for
Security because there are places where you want to have
Troll you don't want things always on the air
So this
Highly secure device
Gather data from it
Again same concept
And it's
Cheaper
Then having like a centralized Cloud Server that you know
Maybe you don't want to pay for that for 15 years or 20 years or however long you
Plan to have a mining operation in the middle of the Australian Outback
And maybe that's Overkill anyway
So that kind of Deeds
That's the market they're going out
After so it's not the same
Normal Market that we talked about a lot but it's a really interesting idea
They are not crazy
In the sense that they're not alone
IBM and Samsung are also testing the concept of
Using the blockchain
They're actually using ethereums network I believe
Where is these guys are using bitcoin's blockchain
Technology
For those of you guys who are like
What the what
It's basically a difference
It's a difference in how they
Cryptocurrency
But yeah so I'm really excited about them I
Wish them luck and
$5000000 is
It's good for them and I can't wait to start hearing from customers
The Beatrice NYC
These things get implemented and see how well they work
It will be
Crazy interesting
Because I love having multiple models of thing
A b testing in the real world Network architectures
Alright final thing
Ring
We talked about it before they make a connected video doorbell weave
Tried it out
They also received funding they receive 28 million in a round that was led by
Sir Richard Branson
You may have heard of him
I have
They're not changing their name to the
Nigel
I would expect them to
It's a shame
So that's just if you have a ring or yours
Sitting on the fence going
Which doorbell should I buy
I don't know which company will go out of business first
Maybe you're not as cynical as I am
I know
But they make a good price I think there I feel safe buying something from them
Aunt
Their CEO was
It's really smart in that earlier on they made
Product that wasn't a good product
You know I asked him about it he's like you know we realize that we really needed to focus because we compete against
We don't compete against other video doorbell
Today's when you hit the mainstream consumer market for your product you're competing against Apple and Samsung
And if you're asking the consumer to pay $200 for device
That's who they're going to compare you again
Yeah it's interesting how certain brands have set up a price expectation
When you are at lesser no name and then
Nothing is wrong but I don't think most people would
Recognize their name or the product just yet
Yeah you're going to be compared to the apples the same songs and so on so
It's almost unfair but unfortunately the reality of it
So
I think that's probably all we have time for
For today
We have a guest right
We do
So stay tuned for our guest
Dr. Satya
Ramaswamy
Who's with Tata consulting
Currency services
And he is he did a report that we talked about a little bit a couple weeks ago
On the internet of things and he's going to talk about kind of how a company
Parrots of culturally to make Bank
With the internet of things so stay tuned for that
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
But I have our guest today
Ramaswamy who's the global head of the digital and
Enterprise frittata
Consultancy services
Hello Satya how are you doing today
I'm good cuz he's already doing
I'm doing so well I am really excited to have you on the show
People around the world
On what other companies are doing in the internet.
Space
Delta flight 795 of them
Completed the survey in Seoul right today between the answers
All the questions and that is what we took for analysis
And definitely
Seesaw
And yeah I was actually kind of stunned so what you guys found was that
80% of companies were already
Deploying internet of things kind of projects
And something
They're spending a lot of money
It's ugly and infect the quite a surprise
The fact that in a photo flight companies that actually
Do we sing something on the Internet of Things
Mainstays
And also the impact.
Example about the companies
Family departs another company
Project
Increase by 16%
In the areas where they are using
Which is really big
I'm sorry their revenue increased by
16% so16
On average
And then grows about a small group of companies about other companies
Increase of 30%
WWE
Initiative
Did you think about the revenue increases one of the biggest challenges that companies face
Because of intense competition
Flea markets
I'm at the same time
The cost
Prediction Cassidy's tomorrow
Maximum potential
So Cal Gas Company Springfield Avenue
Biggest caught up in what we call the volleyball
And I want this seems to be an important tool that is helping these companies break through that Valley boundary body
So the concept of the value boundary
Is what
It is that
Increase your Revenue substantially
And you cannot also reduce your costs
Density
Because most of the costly was I've been up late in the last 10 to 15 years
Then you're not
Distance to be able to increase the value of 40
Companies are really looking at
And what you're seeing on the ground is that
Help them accomplish
Brasier report
I was really struck
I was trapped by the numbers
Because they are actually really significant and
I'm not hearing
A lot of the companies that I talk to
They are looking at
The industrial internet
Looking at this is a way to do kind of
Our return-on-investment so a lot of the times
They're kind of doing sandbox trial projects
The kind of
Become a little bit more efficient
They aren't looking at it is a kind of severely innovative
Play right off the bat
And despite what HE tells me in their press release
So
This next part of the report I really loved and
You had a whole section that the entire back chunk of your report
Talked about like
Highly successful iot leaders
And
You know I was I would love for you to tell me like
First off
What are some of the companies that you classified as some of these iot leader
Report
Damn.
30% or more of Revenue in
So
These are companies that are actually seeing
Substantial
And this is not just related to the amount of spending that they do
But really
David shining as the leader
And the thing to find out what exactly are they doing
Differently or what is common
Among all these companies
Thanks
What are the key observations that we have is that what the last
7 or 8 years
Did audible the five important digital technologies that are coming into play
Angry call about the digital 5 forces
The first one is about mobility and pervasive computing
Second one to support Big Data
Good things about social media
Fortis stock
Insist on this machine learning
Intelligent
And this
Flight technology so it won't go any faster
And internet of things happens to be what we call of the composite
Because the class combinations of all these things
And in fact one of the only composite Falls that has all different elements
Yeah but it didn't work
And the net result of this composite for The Internet of Things is doing the companies
Is giving them an opportunity to completely re-imagined
Themselves
And I'll be calling cuz digital remaster Nation
And it's interesting seems to be important.
Angelina's
Before
We're actually going
Computer
First one is about creating and telling your business model
Second it's about creating and telling you products
Conservative that never existed before
And third one was about creeping customer segments in babies that was never done before
And the fourth one is about creating entirely new channels of distribution of their products
And the first one is about creating and telling your business processes
Complete remodeling
What they had before
And what you found that as a common theme
Accomplish
The 30% increase in Revenue Andre Ward initiative
Was that did not looking at a tactical rail
Port Canaveral transfer meteor imaginative
Ended up going and impacting all the six areas that I talked about
And that was one important thing
Okay wow you just gave us a whole lot you gave us
5 kind of
Big trends you gave a six ways that you should be looking it was six ways right that
They're changing their business
So let's unpack that a little bit
Because
Again
A lot of stuff there
Let's take
Applying Big Data
Across all of these things
And then let's take how
A company might view its Workforce its
Change Iris are changing
Using all of these things to reimagine its Workforce how it interacts
His customers howitt
How it can be imagined it's business
And let's let's talk about how one of your leaders is doing
Short so
Take the kids of
A leader and
Let's talk about the six areas from business model
Products and services
Customer segments
The business part of the business model
Engine types of business model
Changing a business model is extremely clogged
But if you can make the change happen.
And if someone took advantage of Auto industry that is competing in
Coyotes
Helping them do that important
Inductive by creating watercolors data transparency
So the ability of a manufacturer to Caribou Sublimity into
Hold the product of the creator
What does a jet engine used to being
Is performing at is being used
That's created the opportunity to intelligence the business model from
Capital expense business model tomorrow for an operating expense
People in industrial talking about the hole
Jefferson Industries
It's moving from
Selling engines for millions of dollars
Who actually selling Plus
Customer service
Soda dungeon
Or take the case of insurance companies
Insurance companies
Google play classic edition
Red Sox
You could have done then
They have a fuel classifications of drivers
Discipline
Characteristics
And then they determine the premium based upon which segment.
I know you are not sending it
But that is not the optimal
Because for example some segments like a team segment
Are considered as bad drivers
From the get-go
And even if somebody is a good driver he does not get rewarded for
Winston August
Transparency for example vehicle to one of the
Insurance companies in North America theater system
Where do you use the sensors on the mobile phone
Telematic device
And that system intern talks to the Big Data System
And this data last message. Driving the cell phone tracks
Though you're driving too fast.
Song
Or are you driving at the weather conditions Changed by combining data from
The telematics device the mobile phone with the data from
But that sources for example
Anthony
Creative or I could just profile of the individual
So that no the premium can be determined at the individual level
So that's a fundamental difference.
It makes sometimes
Business model
Got it makes a lot of sense now I talked to some companies that are trying to introduce these swords
What's a business model
What they've run into though
Is it the middle men
Or their distribution Network
Makes that sort of change
A challenge
They
Don't want to be cut out or maybe they don't want to
Sell that new model
I think what's
Most interesting about this shift is company C
That the business model needs to change they try to make it happen
And then what
Define inertia in their distribution chain
And maybe they're like a home and now I have to remake Midas
Houston chain
Or they're like I have to
Condense
In a whole new layer of
People that I've never had to work with before to work with me
It really is an ecosystem play and it seems like the whole ecosystem is it quite
There yet
I completely agree with you.
Iot using ecosystem play 1G
From the
There's no one single player who is going to dominate
I'd like plants when we actually go in 30 employment
Play one
Fieldpointe dual-channel tens on his credit card and the companies do need to
CVS of taking the channel along with them
Seventeen.com
We brought about lot of difficulty Santos Tunisia
But if there is substantial value that is being delivered
The customer will come through the change
Rachel Noble
Doesn't listen W have from the internet Revolution
And I would say that the Internet of Things Revolution
Fuel Moto
Because the Internet Revolution was all about
The digital replacing II
But Internet of Things is all about the digitally enhancing.
Right
So in many ways
I'm very important question example one of the most inspiring example
I think about is the HP instant ink program
Ink by themselves
So you think about it the whole.com Revolution was
Basilic got replaced by a machine
But now the budget is a mission
Right so
There's no intention of a human being from a buying site
That's a really astute observation
And kind of scary
The fire is a machine
The seller is a machine so where do people fit in
It has created so much of value.
Even if I get replaced by a buyer let's take that example
The printer Arlington ink in creating value for me or not
I'm not emotionally attached to the fact that you know I could go on and Order
Oregon and order return online on my webpage
But the fact that the printer is detecting it is running low on
And automatically ordering it
Everything gets delivered to my doorstep
And I don't get into
Ganges Restaurant
What time of day it is
So
What is that
Does cryptic summative value
For all people in the value chain that people will go along with the change
In a positive frame of mind
And I
Physical exam
Okay I agree with you
Probably even the people who are responsible for ordering ink it companies would rather spend their time ordering
I don't know anything but ink
So let's dig into a couple things so we talked
Some about kind of
You would offered these seven
Tenant 7 things that the
The leaders did
I'm in
We we talked
I hear you're a big guy for numbers and lists I'm sensing
You know you're at your five big shifts your six
You're six things companies can realize
So
The first thing went
Was literally iot leaders are more likely to reimagine their businesses in
Produce substantial values for customers not just values for themselves
And we kind of talked about
Second they deliver that value through new business models products and service offering
We talked about that
Third they appear more likely to see the Breakthrough potential of iot getting the ultimate truth on how their products and services
They're performing for customers as well as the actual usage patterns
I think we actually probably should dig into that
Actually one of the
Great benefits of iot and I think
I want to hear some sleep anxiety to product development
So the traditional software product development
I want a big change because now you can actually
So you can
And you can use that $2
The next version of the Torah
And make
Lord of incremental
Industry
Talk to the digital
So that was a big thing that happened with the last
YouTube videos of analytics on software products
But now I want is actually golden Abel.
And then to something is sometimes what you hear back
Something machines may not exactly be what
You want
Company is coming
Many times to hear things that are not exactly what
Catolica
So how do you react to that
Got it
And so that that covers those kind of stories cover your fourth and fifth points which are the
Iot leaders
They organized themselves to act rapidly based on this performance and customer usage data
And they're just stay
Get better at dealing with internal resistance to hearing the truth about their toy
So
People ask for this button they must love it and then no one ever
Press that button
That's a hard truth
Or people really hate your product
That's a really hard
R-Truth
They make six I thought was great they may coyote reliable in the field
Especially reducing risks
Cyber security breaches
I think a lot of companies right now are still falling down
About that I'll be honest
I've noticed a lot of blaming the customer
About that
Or just outright ignoring it
And 7th they make small test investments before making broader and bigger one
I think
That last one is
Explain
You know if we want to end this with a sense of kind of
Security what is your advice to customer
As they're considering
Either
Connecting their own manufacturing or their own
Internal operations or if they're planning on making a
Product
Where do you think
They are when it comes to security what are the conversations they're having
2 IU is this point of security
Primarily because
Implications of the phone
And the computer
So the text
But good internet of things you're going to impact something in the physical world
So think about the impact of something happening to a jet engine burn this life is my dad
Or you are going full speed in the expressway and something happened
To the car because security please
AllMusic tonight what is system in your home and you talked everything was Secure
And then someone please play security and now they can actually deactivate
The Simpsons
So the implications of security office
Full
Performance
And I
I do think that it does not fully appreciated yet in its full magnitude
But the lot of the good Solutions providers that the worker
You know what
Are taking notice and solutions.
And the systems that you put together has security as one of the foremost
Things that about
Simply because
What are the implications of a beach
On what system that is operating in the physical world is just simply too big
Got it all right
Such a thank you so much for coming on the podcast today I really appreciate having
This kind of in-depth conversation
About
How
Companies can be successful
In the playing kind of iot in both their products and hopefully in their own operations
A Blog and I think so too great to talk to you in person
Awesome thank you
And that concludes our show
Thanks for listening this week will be back next week with more iot goodness