Hey everyone welcome back
Back from Arlo on holiday vacation this is the Internet of Things podcast in case you forgot
And I am Stacey Higginbotham and this
Is my co-host
Kevin tofel
Hey you're right on there
WR you are fresh and ready for this week's episode
I Am Phresh
And ready all good I was home
Cuz I I am a little
Quite frankly not all here
So
This week we were talking about
Black hat
Last weekend
So all kinds of hacking of The Internet of Things
Cree connected light bulbs
Google
Crazy alphabet announcement
And a couple other exciting things
And we have a really interesting guests this week we have
Chef
Ryan from
June
Which is that connected oven company we talked about a couple weeks ago
Yeah yeah easy bake oven for the 24 2015 I remember that
For the 21st century it's actually for 2016 is when it will be out
But we are talking about
The smart kitchen
Really fascinating conversation we are literally going to understand how the sausage
Gets made
Cool before we do anything
5 we have to talk
About
Google News what do you think
C is for cookie and that's good enough for me yes the alphabet
C is for Calico
Google's longevity moonshot project
I really are they come up with 26 different little subsidiary type things now
They've got five or so of them covered already
So what happened is this week it was actually Monday
Google
Which is no longer
It's just Google
Purchase a Larry Page put up a blog post saying that
Google was going to become
Alphabet
Or actually alphabet was going to become a conglomeration of companies
And Google would only become
Part of those companies so Google would be one part
Write alphabets like a new public holding company
And Google is one of the
It's a subsidiary of alphabet
Rate
The company's name will be the alphabet Inc
But it will trade under
Goog goog the public shares of the company will trade under GOOG
And
Sundar pichai
He is going to be the CEO of Google
And all the Google properties that we know and love and use like Android Google Maps
YouTube
Hangouts
Gmail all those things
Are going to be part of Google so basically the ad funded side of the
Write the product side the
Yeah they're there their the money-making side it was all go under Google
Yay
Understand
And then
All the kind of crazy future thinking stuff like
Fiber
Nest
Project X Project X
Calico
And
It's Google capital and Google Investments are
I'll go under
Other category so what happens is now Google it has
It's two reporting structures for Wall Street investment purposes
So you'll see the beautiful money making side we're all that ad delicious delicious ad Revenue comes from
And then you're going to see like
Other
I expect it probably doesn't make a lot of money
And that's where
Google's making all those
And Larry and Sergey will still be the
And I really don't know what they're going to do I think I just want to have more fun and less responsibility that's just me
I have to say
We want I wasn't kidding I don't think you were either
Yay for Sundar pichai because he came up through the ranks and
Took over Android for Andy Rubin couple years back and in 2013
And then he got Chrome and then he got all the Google products the docks and all the EX I think he had dogs before all of this
And now he's got like
Their entire product portfolio that makes the money so and I can't think of a better person there that promote from within from
Loadout slots
That's good news to me
She has earned
The blog post
To me it looks very clear Larry Page in the blog post said it's clear to B&R board
Siddharth deserves this
It sounds like Wall Street canopy adults
The table feel they were pushing him
So it makes a lot of sense
From The Internet of Things perspect
Couple things
We got to look at Nest I think this is great
From the perspective of nesto the other thing is
All of these Google
The separate other companies in alphabet
Nest is going to be its own cum
Each company is headed by its own CEO
My guess is he hasn't actually pink
Confirmed anywhere
Tony fadell will continue to be the CEO of nest
That would make sense that make sense
Should that change
Will let you know
I reach out to nest for comment they weren't commenting beyond the press release
But this is good for them because all along they've been a separate subsidiary of goo
When Google bought Nest back in
January of 2014 everyone was like
Thermostat this is terrible terrible terrible news for my privacy so anyway this is good
Well
Yes but I mean really
That dated will still get fed into Google I mean let's be honest
No doubt that's just been very clear that they don't give that dated
Okay alright I guess the bigger picture is that
These other companies will still feed data into the
Into the Google
Google
Shutting itself off from Gathering data from these companies
Well
If they do that they would have to change the terms of agreement
Nest
So
Google is not right now grabbing the nest
Yeah it is because it is separate
So what you're saying
Is it actually happy
Yeah well I guess that it will alleviate some people's concerns
I did okay so so they break it out and there's there's these walls that were implied or were really there before our
Certainly there now
And you know that the big questions are now is it
Much easier to spend this out
I would also say this is a very different
Revenue model
The Internet of Things play for Google has always
Post kind of an existential threat because
The beauty of the internet of things as you spend
Less time looking at a screen either your smartphone or your computer and more time
Interacting with
People in the devices around you hopefully in a more naturalistic way right
So
In a sense you spend less time searching and more time just like
Demanding things happen
Or just hoping things happen and they happen
Bright
So
We we know about nest
And we've seen what they've done
So far they still kept it separate and it is going to be separate going forward
I don't know that that's been
Great thing for Google's IRT efforts because
Less
With her and you can correct me
Set the nest team really hadn't work with Google on their brillo and we've stuff it was just nope those are two separate things
So it's like huh
What what are they doing
Well that is a darn good question
Because
No one I've talked to
In any of my source
No one
Don't want anywhere on the planet anywhere
In the chip world in the like device world
In the software or router world
The sense I get from all of those people is Google doesn't yet really know what
Brillo and weave
Is going to be
So
I find it
Futuristic so I asked
Google
What this meant for brillo and weave which was an Android effort
Said they would work with nest
And all of my sources say that Berlin Weaver coming out of Android they're not coming out of nest
Today will work with nest
Which means that brillouin we've just got split off from nest and sober alone we've are going to be
BOS effort
For The Internet of Things
And that's going to still be
Google
So is Nest just
Pretty much
Smart thermostat and a smoke detector and whatever other similar products they can think of
NetSpend is going to be a physical Products Company
It's a juice as you were is extra margins and revenue will come not just from selling physical products
But we'll be building better products in understanding how to use the data that it Gathers
From those products to
Field Services
Build additional better products and that's where I think we'll see kind of the Innovation coming from
On the nest
And I kind of thought they would have already made some Headway there I guess that goes back to my point that they really haven't done much of anything
I actually wondered was it worth it was a 3.2 billion dollars to Google patroness was it really worth it
So far I haven't seen a lot of in
Indications that it is
I'll be honest with you I think
Build some pretty devices
The promise that Tony fadell
Had
Was beautiful devices
And he's done that
Total check
The secondary Prime
And we'll get into that
Said lovely Segway actually is building these anticipatory kind of devices that give you
You information
When you need it in your home
And that is a lot harder
And so
Idea is that you know your thermostat your smartphone begins to know you
Can anticipate your needs
Is there a variety of reasons one
Being that
Devices don't work together and it's hard to build a stable of beautiful high-quality devices that
Minivan Apple
Apple doesn't build that
Devices
That's that's very difficult
So
My Nest is a wonderful example I think the works with Nest program actually is it's a really good program but even it's not perfect
And here comes mites
Then why is it not perfect Stacie
Tell me Stacy
I think it's a great motto
And one of my favorite examples is
The hue light bulb integration so
When you are away if you have an S
And you have the Philips hue light bulbs
Switch with the works with Nest program and
When you go away
In your lesson
Thermostat says hold is persons away
Are a few light bulbs will turn off and if you're away from more than one day
They will start toggling on and off on a
Pattern that somewhat random based on your schedule
I went on vacation
And my my lights did that
And it was
Awesome cuz I didn't set it
Except for that one time that I toggled
Except
When I got back from vacation
I noticed that my
Lights
When turn on
I don't know around 6 ish
In the evening
And when
I would get up in the morning my
Lights downstairs and if I left
If I left my bedside table lamp on
Like I didn't turn it physically off at the switch I left it on like for the
Electronics to take over
If that would actually turn on around 6
6:30 in the morning
I could not I was like
Okay
What is happening and what is this attached
What it what automation is causing this random thing to happen
Do you know what that sounds like
Well think about how the nest
Works when you get it you install it
And then you manually use it
Emitting about over the course of a week
A quote on quote learns how you want the house
Heated and cooled
And then you don't do anything anymore right uses the away sensor as well as your schedule because it has learned your schedule your behalf
I almost almost sounds and this is crazy it sounds to me like it's sink
Spent while you were away
That lady behavior is your actual Behavior
Check the schedule that
My nest
Tad ebright yes
Yes it is set my lights based on
That schedule yeah that's what it sounds like
Yes
That is what happened
It's so smart right
Not so much now but it wasn't
Smart enough
To realize that
When I came
Back
Did it had to turn that
Off exactly that schedule should be no longer
Valid
So it wasn't smart enough in that way in the other way it wasn't smart
Was there was no way that it
Tell me
That's what it was doing
That's right exactly it maybe if you're if you're not me
You probably don't have your Philips Hue Lights hooked up to your nest
To your wink
Echo
Write to you know me
Smarty face than that
Yeah
Running down at list of things going
This probably isn't Edge case I would agree
But
I really want my smart home to have
Central Dash border like
And IRC or someplace where it's like
Hey Stacy I turned your lights on its 6:30 in the morning today
Because of this command
It came from here
If you don't like it
This is why
This gets back to where I used to love
Mine
Vnc on headless server
We're going to remotely log into and see the log file see all the commands see the scheduling and see everything that happened and why
And I understand that
Today's products don't have that because
Most people don't want that they want the Simplicity of it just working
The trick is
For people who do want it or need to dig into that those types of logs like you would probably want to do when you get home from vacation and noticed
Yeah this problem
It's all hidden away it's all distracted
And that's
You know that stuff still needs to be acceptable in my opinion
And I don't think that's too hard I think figuring out where that lives though
An issue like right now I don't have a 1 Central
Place for
So I finally figured it out and I wouldn't I turned it off
The world was a happy place in
You don't start waking up
When are lights in volunteer
But that was that was it a case of a little bit of wonkiness a little bit of something being
Not quite intuitive enough
But you know getting there
So that was that was that
We should probably move on to
What if it hadn't been just a little bit of wonkiness what've hitted been
Got done
Packers
And I am officially wearing a black hat today
Seattle
If only I were wearing my
Yeah there's a lot of action going on
I didn't catch the story but you mentioned before the show there was some type of zigbee hack
Again in I really probably shouldn't call
You know why I write these in headlines and I feel instantly guilty because it's really a vulnerability
So jiggly is
One of the more popular
Wireless radio protocols in the home
So if you got you no sensors in your home
It's highly likely it's a zigbee based sensor
Is a wireless mesh Network
Can protocol
Windows locks
Light bulb soda
My Philips Hue Lights
State-run zigbee
And they convert back to Wi-Fi
Lot of stuff
So
But don't freak out
So what happened is
A researcher
Presented a paper
At blackhat
This
This last
This last weekend
Found
A couple vulnerabilities with the zigbee profile
It and it's basically housing B shares its
Keys
It's encryption keys
So basically what happens is
It is it be Network
All the notes like they exchanged aqui
And the key basically that is used in most profiles is
Password it's the default encryption
Actually is it Bass Pro at the profiles are actually
128 bit AES encryption which is really good in Creek
Instead of like
Choosing
Many of the option
In search of psychologist
So
Kind of like using admin or password
If you guess the default you're highly likely to get in
Password is 1 2 3
Exactly so basically
Bet that's the first element and then there's some other Ella
In there like
A lot of the nose out there they're not using expensive zigbee radios they're using like these little low power
Not very smart CB radios so someone messes with them
You can't really tell because they don't shut down if someone messes with them they're just like
London. Someone mess with me now I'm like a
I'm like a
An evil node on the network
Hahaha
I won't tell anybody cuz I'm too dumb
Is that what they really sound like
That's what they sound like if you're ever around when I'm playing with my network all of my devices
Just have a little funny voices
After the show I'm going to talk to my light bulbs and see what they say
Didn't like that it is somewhat deadens the pain as you're like sitting there is hooking something up again and again to
So that's the vulnerability
I wrote about it in my call I say it's really time
To stop blaming the consumer
The Internet of Things is really complicated it is way too much to expect consumers to be like
I mean gas consumers should totally be updating their firmware we should be updating all the time
We should
You smart passwords I agree
But after that
It's time for a manufacturer's to like really step the heck up
Yeah it mean this is again this is different than and I know we talked about this before this is different than a mobile device
Sore
A laptop or desktop which obviously that gets
Packed into his is a bad thing no I'm not saying otherwise
But your house I mean that's your home that is
Azure domain and we need to make sure
But every safety precaution is taken when we start
Turning over
The house to these gadgets that special the connected ones
Exactly
I just
I'm kind of sick of this idea that
You know people are like
Is there so many camps like the New York Times just ran an op-ed
Yesterday in this this woman
Was like
We don't need the Internet of Things
You know it's
It's going to be insecure and it's stupid
And that was kind of the
Idea of her thesis was that
It's just too risky to attach all the stuff to the internet
And she ignored all the potential benefits and
I just was so frustrated by
That's like saying what are Amazon's what 20 years old now I think 15 years old whatever it is
Thanks 15 years old that's like saying now in today's day and age
You should never shop online Amazon because
You know reason AT&T
Security in
Privacy and
Credit card numbers
I mean
We got to realize this is the way the world is not going back
What time does SpaceX
I'd rather than
Say Doom and Gloom and don't ever use these things
Let's figure out how to beef up the security and make them
You know good enough that people are
You comfortable putting them in their houses and using them in on that way 15 years from now we don't have these kind of things about
House hacks and so on
Exactly know Morehouse hat
Yeah
How about a car hack
A car a cat tell me about your kayak
Yeah this is disappointing because I think
I think it had to do with the OnStar system in particular although I'm sure it would work with various cars
And we have few no OnStar on the on The Bold and whatnot but
Yasso a digital researcher his name is Samy kamkar he
Put together $30 device
That can
Where do I copy the signal
Cars remote you know that the key fobs that unlock the car
Like many hacks and I would say this
Is a hack
This is only under certain situations and basically his device has to be
Near the car
When the car doors unlock so we can go grab
The wireless key code
It's not just
One key Cordova second read several because these things
Typical use rolling codes
Purple Tarzan for garage door switch
Attack works on garage doors to I can capture the codes to
To reopen those
So
Yeah that's that's bad and it again it gets back to what you were just saying
This comes down to the manufacturer's because what happened here when he figured out that the way to exploit this was
Codes don't expire
They can't be used more than once these rolling codes to unlock a car or garage door
But they don't expire so if it was never used in the first place because his
Is little
Device captured it
It's a valid code
So the manufacturers have to work on some expirations on these throwing codes and such because right now
There's somebody who can
30 bucks go out
Get a little you know what device to
Get your key code and unlock your door for your car or
The garage door
Honestly I my car I'd probably rather
My car intro
Keep anything in my car
Bluetooth 2.1 replacement anyway
That's true
We will talk about my journey to a smarter car soon
So that's all I think that's almost all the time we have I should
Note because
People who like Wi-Fi will like this
D-Link
His launched a Wi-Fi
Water
Sensor
Which is exciting
I cuz it's Wi-Fi because it's Wi-Fi
So
Yay
It does have to be
Be plugged in
So it's being plugged in at the wall
And then it's
It's a 1.6 ft sensor cable so what you do is you plug it in
And then
There is a
Lan cable
In the censors at the tip of it
So that's how they dealt with the power issues associated
I would
Are considerable so this
My mind is
So far the only Wi-Fi water sensor on the market
Which is why I'm telling
That's about it
Because a lot of people like that sort of thing
And Belkin WeMo is supposed to have a Wi-Fi water sensor
Sometime
And send it to email will work with Echo
Incentives Wiimote will work with Echo
Which means the echo could possibly be like
Alert alert
This stealing one will actually
Also work with the siren
There's a Wi-Fi siren
Or you can
You can just have me around your house saying alert alert if you'd like that
Maybe you should put an MP3 up on
Podcast
You could be ringtone it could be your ringtone
Side
Wait one more thing before we go to the gas real quick I'll keep it short at prom
Way back I want to say in December last year you tested the Cree LED connected bulbs is that right
Okay and you did not like a particular aspect or two about them which was
Oh they Buzz
Yeah when you Dim them
That's true they buzzed
All right so I talked to the folks at creepy I asked him about this and they're like well we don't know what space is used
Listen that
So they didn't acknowledge that there was an issue or any like that but I said look at it if you don't think it was any more send me one
So guess what
And I have been using it for the past week and a half in My Den I got to connect to my echo so I can
Got turn it on or turn it off from the echo or I can do it from my Wink app because it's
Wink compatible bulb
And I'm not here in the buzzing you know what I'm getting old so I said you know what let me get my kids to a much better hearing
You guys listen to me dimmed it
Always
Six ways til Sunday turn on turn off
Didn't hear it either so
Mine was in a
That may be why then
And the GE dimmer so both
Dimmable LED bulbs
I tested them in a
Dimmable lamp
Okay so they only Buzz
Best in the dimmable
That's okay
Good to know so people if you're going to Disney's these bulbs
I don't want to put them in the right table lamp
Just put them in a regular laughing and control the dimming through an app for voice however you want to do that so
These are the $15 white bulbs just so everybody knows the color temp is not my favorite it's 2700 Kelvin
Sandwiches
Yellowish soft white but that's okay
815 lumens
And only uses 11 and 1/2 watt we fill the 60 watt replacement that they sent me
So it's working great
I'm fine with the soft white in My Den I'm not keen on that my office I use the daylight
Types
But
He's in a regular lamp then
They should be just fine at 4:15 bucks you got a connected zigbee bulb
From tree
Hey and Kevin just for those of us who don't speak Eldon
What is the daylight temperature
The daylight temperature is between 5000 kelvins 5000 kelvins and up
The bulbs that I have the
Sylvania osram bulbs that I have three of those
Those are tunable so I can go to down from 2700
Kelvin's to 6500 Kelvins
Does go all the way up to daylight which is 5000 and up
So that is
The update on the crease which is awesome that gives you another $15 ish option for those of you guys were like
Connect LEDs or bus
Relatively cheap I should say you know it's still more expensive than LED bulb but
4:15 bucks you almost can't go wrong
I certainly can
So because I've got it connected through the wink hub
Through the wing
Steppin
You talk to through the
That is correct
It's all seamless it doesn't mean it sounds complicated but it's not it's not can you control cuz I had control
Decrees also through the Hughes but I could only do that I think a tattoo out of
Three of the Crees I was sent
And I had to do it manually
I couldn't search for it automatic
I only have one Cree bulb so I couldn't say how it work with multiples but
I did the search actually in the Wink app you just choose you know to add a product and
There's like a zillion choices in their anus
Go to the bulbs and craze listed in there and that was it
I was just like discovering any other bulb
But if you didn't have a wink
I don't know because I do have a wink
The question
So
I don't know if you want to unpair it from the wink just to make your life interesting
And see if you can add it to the hue
Cuz you would also could serve for those of you guys out there who have an echo but no
Wait wait
But you do have a key
That would be another possible option
That's correct
So I could possibly try that cuz I still have the Huey others not active right now
You don't have to
I'm just thinking out loud. You love giving me homework
Baidu
That was a terrible evil laugh is it really work
It's cuz I'm not really evil
All right
We have got way over time
Keyboard with us because
If you stay tuned
We have a wonderful guest it is
Chef Ryan Baker Who is the
Research Chef at June
The makers of a connected oven and we are going to talk about
Technology in the kitchen
Connected kitchens
And
It's actually literally how your
Your sausage
Is going to get made in the June oven so it's a it's a fun segment
Keep on listening
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast you are listing to Stacey Higginbotham
And I am interviewing
Ryan Baker who is a research Chef
At June
Hi Ryan how are you today
XTC
Man I am so excited
Because you
Combine like
Two of my love
The Internet of Things
Yay and cooking
So
Hideout riot at we can talk in ahead of the show and poor Ryan
He's going to be very tall
Because
I've already like bombarding him with Quest
So
To get started
Ryan
June is a company that I have written about
It is making a connected oven
It's very expensive but I'm already kind of like who I cannot wait for this to happen so
First off tell me a little bit about
June and why you came to work
With them as a research Chef
I came to June because
I was immediately Blown Away
Buy the product
And I was
Super excited to be part of the team that was
Doing something that nobody else was
And once I got to know that the people in the company I really got us sent the pictures of thing.
Integrity
Design something
You know Lord really really well
Awesome
So for those of you guys are out there
Okay a connected oven this is not connected oven that is in your wall this is a countertop oven
And it is not just connected to the internet
What they've done
Is a padded Wi-Fi
But they've also added
Sensors in the feet of the oven
They've added a camera
And they've added an AI so basically what happens is
You can
Oana temperature probe
I should add that
So you can pop something into the June oven
Can recognize that using the camera
And the AI
And it can tell how much this object that you put in their ways
I can tell you the temperature of it
And then because it recognizes what it is how much it weighs
And it's temperature
And it has this kind of database of recipes about it it can
Basically say
Hey looks like you're baking a roast
You want to cook it for this long and it kind of gives you an ideal sense of
How long you should
Cookies
Is that about it
Getting better
I probably could have cut another 30 second
But
They've launched and I want to say it costs about $1,500
So it's kind of pricey
Most
Trays if it's most things that will not cook your Thanksgiving
So this will not replace your existing oven for people who are probably serious about
Mega cooking
But
You know what do you think about the products like from a
Professional chef standpoint
I love it I think it's a total game changer
What I love about it is
Cooking can be very intimidating
And
Having to do is is really inspire
Confidence
Tujunga
It's amazing how getting
Something bright
Create confidence and how you want to
Do that again
I think some people when they try recipe and they don't get it right the first time
Totally
I'm not going to try that again
I'm such a bad
What we really wanted
Really good people in their kitchens and
Inspire them to
Create Greg Nielsen
All right
So this isn't actually just a big giant
Woohoo going by the June oven
The reason I actually had you on the show Ryan is because
I am a huge believer in
Kind of I guess
The equalizing value of
Technology in the kitchen
And a lot of people are kind of like
I do not need
PetSmart
And did they used to be the truth of the Internet of Things
And I'm totally with them I don't need a smart refrigerator
I have been trying to sell and no one's made it for me so far but I've been trying to get someone to make me
Actually a spoon that measures viscosity
Because I think a spoon that measures viscosity
Would be an amazing tool for
Someone learning how to cook because
When you're trying to make a sauce or
Candy or something like that I think
Understanding how thick
Your sinuses is really an important thing
So I think tools like that or even something like having
Camera in the oven that can understand that
The skin on your roast chicken is just Brown enough that's the perfect amount of doneness
Those are the kind of ways that technology can really
Help home
Cooks are people learning how to cook
I'm so I would love to get your philosophy
How technology
Can really help
Cooking or help people
In the kitchen
And maybe doesn't learning to cook maybe it's people who already know how to
How to get
Ryan's
Philosophy of technology in the kitchen
Recognized
Edible ideas
I did a spoon demetric viscosity
I look the same.
You know you work for a company that
You know that they might get on
I love that I think that's a great idea
Isaac technology
As long as it as long as it works
And
PS I think I think
Doorways
Currency to simplify
You have something like a sous vide
Machine
It's such a simple easy
Appliances
Absolutely stunning
Consistent
Someone play
Are my feet so
Nervous to
Chicken breast
Because they don't know whether or not it's going to come out wrong
Or overcome
Music something like an immersion circulator sous-vide machine
Temperature
I can see the machines doing the work for then making sure
The chicken comes out perfectly
The way I think about
Technology in the
Kitchen
Is
I kind of divided up into three things or maybe it's four things
Google datastore will figure this out
There's the planning side of it
So there's the
The meal planning
Right if I'm thinking about
Home chef
There's prep
And so into that I'm thinking about like the drop kitchen scale
Or
Countertop by the orange chef
There's cooking so into that would fall like the June oven or
I can't think of the name of it but it's that little knob on your stove
There's the
The iGrill or the
Amber
Thermometer
Kind of things
I don't know if there's anything on serving
Consumption so that could be like
Vessel that the cup
Maybe the habit
Twerk It
Any sort of calorie counting apps or things like that so
I think about the world
Kind of Technology
Does that seem like a fair kind of breakdown
Absolutely and I think that's such a
Common philosophy that's growing
United States
If you if you look at it like that
Where do you think technology like
Does it make sense to have technology across all of those
Categories or
Where do you think it makes the most sense to
If your home cookware does it makes the most sense to invest because
Right now
Things don't necessarily work across all of these are going to be nice if I could buy a tool in each category
I could assure myself that everything worked across every
Category right but they don't so
Removing more
Toward integrated products
I'm having a built-in digital scale
Temperature
People are going to restaurant
A lot of new technology
Restaurant vent and hearing new terms and they're they're going to bring that home
There's a you know
A common theme in restaurants
Precision and concision
Is
Really wants restaurants
A lot of consumers want that in their home
How can I make
Perfectly
Cooked chicken
165 degrees and how can I do that each and every time
How did you use technology
Prior to working for June
In your kitchen
Cuz you were a private Chef before and then you would also worked
In
Professional kitchen
Restaurants in San
San Francisco as well yes
I definitely do know a technology
Cooking
A modernist
Innocent III
I love
Because technology that's coming out
You know my favorite
Appliances in my home would be
An immersion circulator
I use a lot of
Chamber ceiling batting machine so I can
Assist with cookie TV tonight
Take care of ingredients
If I go to the Farmers Market
Ansan incredibly beautiful
Strawberries I can vacuum sealed
The winter
Another one of my favorite tools is
And
It's a high speed blender
It has a
Heating element
So you can actually
Cook in a blender
Oh my God you can make the best lemon custard and what if those things
Sorry
Incredible
Hollandaise
I'm making yeah making ice cream bases
Risotto
Wow cuz you would lose all of the leg
Chunkiness yes
Of the
Risotto
Yeah and I don't know how you get
Maybe you know the agitation from
The blender might be able to
Okay I'm sitting here imagining like
Ricey cheesy pudding
Creation Institute
Which might also be delicious I I love anything
It's
Start cheating
Cheesy
Custody
As you can tell
At 4 my lemon custard enthusiasm there
So those are now are any of the things in your kid
I'm not using I don't use any of my my
Did Isis control them
Cuz they're at they're actually
A sous vide
Any sort of connected like some of the more popular in early connected
Devices were actually sous vide
Kind of homemade sous-vide things
Done in Crock-Pot
Actually just hack together with Arduino shoes
So I'm kind of
Curious because you could actually control
And modulate the temperature of things from afar if you wanted to
I don't know if that appeals to you or not
Yeah it is absolutely doesnae I think that those early model
Their only drawback was
Precision
Thermostat
Devices for using
Sous vide
Just it's all about precision
Censure
More and more companies will be designing
Circulators
You're able to control from you
I got another device
Yeah I can't wait for that
We talked a bit about your philosophy of
Cooking in the kitchen
End
Like I said like you like you said actually
This opens up
Kind of a world of cooking and I will say that when I was testing out
It was the drop kitchen scale
I thought it was kind of frustrating because they had a very modular recipe structure
It was like
Do this then do this
And I'm a little bit more slapdash in
How I cook and I like to consolidate bowls and that sort of thing and they were like
But this invisible and
Put this on the scale
I hated it
Scaleworks
The recipes that you had to use are the recipes they had in there at
I thought were a little
They used a little too much butter
But
You know it was fun my daughter though loved it she's actually wants one for her birthday
Because
She's never begged before and she loved the fact that it told her step by step
Told her exactly what to do and then
You know when you measure it on the scale that step was
What's done in a rush to cross the iPad screen
Nextep appeared
It was it was so interactive it had the screen component she thought it was fun she's
8 years old this is great
And watching her do that I was like you. This is a great way
To learn how to cook
And iiii just be very curious like
Bring this kind of technology in
Two everyday objects
Without it being quite so
I guess maybe quite so expensive or quite so I mean cuz the drop kitchen scale was $100
And then you had all these kind of customized dresses
The peace that you had to run
With the scale
Obviously you could use it like a normal kitchen scale but it wasn't his kind of
Fun in modular
And just trying to think you know normal people are not going to
Redo the way they
Right
That seems like a big ass
Ferlife
There's there's supposed to cost element to Bringing technology into the
Kitchen and then there's also a lot of these kind of services ask
People search
Either pick up new recipes or kind of
Cook a slightly different way
Do you think that's just crazy
I don't think it's crazy I think that
The cost will go down with you
With a supply chain unit when the microwave
Enough
Wildly expensive and
Now you know
It's one of those things that
You can buy a cheap one at Sears for $80 on sale
Amanda has been one of the most revolutionary
You know inventions
Kitchen island
What are you doing as a research Chef
At June so Lake
If I bought a June oven when it comes out next year
Are you are you the guy training the AI
I am yes
Think about that I'd be cooking
Dinner for you
Every night if you were using the gym
You certainly wouldn't be doing it every time
Because I'm lazy
Well maybe not
What are the things that we have to do is
Because people
Super tired and excited
I craving this eat that
Might be something where one night you're like
I just finished for the chicken breast
And that
Chef Ryan
Cook for me and then
You know on a Friday or Saturday night you might say you know what I want to get in
To be controlling the 7th and
Chef Ryan
What do you have to tell me not to call you
Canadian nickname I do not vent
Chef Ryan and Spider-Man
I'm going to toss him so much
Some veggies and some apples and
The parmesan cheese and breadcrumbs
Let's go
And it'll be like
I don't do that
So so what have you got
What if you got cooking
Be safe
Really sucks
I'm designing the cook settings for the computer vision
Right now
We
Have the ability to recognize 15 different food items
And
What I'm doing every day it is
Constantly
Casting
Chinese item song
I might be cooking
Cookies in a day
Or 15 batches of cinnamon
Making
Testing the oven
I'm seeing how long it takes
For salmon to cook at 350 degrees
Lighting all of that data
So we can come up with the ideal
Exciting
As we started tiling
Thailand
And really mastering these
Computer vision
I'm going to
Work on designing actual recipe that we recommend
It's almost like we have two different companies like
Thursday Hardware
June oven
Products
And there's a
Jus recipe which is just
And it's just as big a part of it
Designing
Recipes dinner
For our products
And John within that will have
Really beautiful photography
And instructional videos like right now
Using
Extended maybe 12-minute long
Cooking video
Everyday is just like constantly collaborating with the hardware and software
Improvement
This is something that just popped in my head as you were saying this but what happens when they do a software update
Do they confer with you because like if they do is certain kind of software update could it like totally throw off your cooking time
Times and estimates for Lake
Salmon
Control all of my oven
Using
Do you turn on my computer so I
I'm writing command line
Control the oven
Wichita
I never ever thought I would
Ever do like writing code
Yes
Campfire cooking
Burien shooting like you roast a s'more like you're cooking a marshmallow into like a light like burning too much
And you move here
Your hand in the stick away from the fire
And the same thing except
Lower the heat on
The oven
It's incredibly cool
I never in a million years thought I'd be
At my computer you know
Commanding
Five different oven
Yes
A lot of the software
I'll be giving the software engineers
The settings based on the command line
So it really weird that you know there's
A synchronicity between
Design and the software
Okay
Yeah I know I was just suddenly thinking of Michael what happens if
Cuz I would be
Okay
This is
This is fascinating
An awesome
And I cannot
Wait
Taste
B
Recipes that you come up with
CDA I I don't even know what the results of this will be
But I wish I were there on cookie baking day
Probably salmon
Actually probably just all the time I'm sure you make a lot of wonderful food
Did they get to eat it
As long as it's not right
Lots of lots of lots of like everybody taste everything
Yeah it's great nothing ever ever goes to
I'm sure it does
Lestat
That is super fun
Well thank you so much
For coming on the show
Ryan and
I again cannot wait
To play
With the June oven
Of my very own one day
At
See what you've been doing for the
All this time
My Father's Day
Thanks for listening