Hey everyone welcome back this is the Internet of Things show and I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And we have
Kevin tofel
End
Today we have actually a lot of news we have a brand new smart home from Lowe's we have an update to the Bluetooth
And we have some fun kind of new devices on sale in
In various places including a new night light so
Let's get started we'll start with d
The launch of the second generation Lowe's
Iris
Which
To be honest I have yet to try out because I'm actually heading
I guess I should say I'm heading out of town because by the time
Y'all hear this I will be almost back
And I hadn't had a chance to try it out yet so I was like
Like hold a review for a minute
Did want to talk about it because Lowe's
Has actually been
Really prescient in the space
DIY retailer you guys are probably familiar with it they launched the iris platform back in 20
Which is way before you know smart things and
Revolve if you guys remember the revolve home automation hub
And other things rather
It was ahead of its time
For what it offered at the time
It did and when I reviewed the original Iris I dinged it because
Cuz it had well a couple reasons it had it
First off it came with a
Premium
And another it came with it
Three-tiered
Subscription plans I had a free version
A
Medium version and then
Premium version
The new version has
A two-tier plan which
What is Friant
I didn't like the idea of having a DIY system that also had a
Subscription fee
But you know what
That's the bottle everyone is actually turning to
The other thing it had its hub actually had both a backup battery at the time and the option to
Papa cellular modem in
Which is something that SmartThings is actually doing now
But I expect to see that for a lot of other
Hubs to make the best of it more resilient the SmartThings option is
It's an integrated option I assume you don't put in a plug in a modem or anything
I believe you actually
2/2
The original SmartThings didn't have the backup battery out
Which is important
I don't recall it what the original price
Of the iris Hub was but now I think it's $59
The original price was $99
Current price for the new version is 5999
Which puts it
Very close just $10 more than the wink hub
Which is what those rifle
So
The other thing
The big difference
For the lowest version
Github
I guess so kind of will lay it out for you
The Lowe's how is controlled
Bi-Lo's so
Lowe's hosts all of it in the
In Microsoft Azure so it's hosted by Lowe's
They control everything they offer support for it
So this is not like wink was actually
Africa company in
Now it's
Since work is bankrupt
Minkus on the market
Flextronics is offered to buy it will stay at the bankruptcy court allows it to
It's a little different setup than most of the other
Jobs out there
So lows also
Has its own branded Gadget
Cats that are Iris branded gacha
Step work with the eye
Lowe's does not bring in
Hue light bulb
That's what I was going to ask because I've already looked at the new Iris by Lowe's website which does have the new Hub and
Looks like there's a
A starter pack for $249 with a bunch of Gadgets in there
But all I see are Iris Brandon
Devices for that so is it not as open as some others
It is not now I
Lowe's does work with
Established vendors to make
Lowe's
Stranded
Versions
Of their products
You're not going to see a Lowe's Brandon Ness
But you know they work with centralite they work with
Aaon Tech they work with a lot of these other
Kind of companies that make
You notice the motion sensors that things like that
They have connect
Do pet doors connect
Garage door openers
Cameras
A lot of the things you're going to
Want they just
Brandon Iris and then they sell them
For your kind of customer is a few
Play so this isn't for someone who's shopping on Indiegogo or
Kickstarter and
I can't wait to buy the latest gadget
This is for someone who's like
Perusing the aisles of lausanne is like I really want to automate my house
Hey
Connected Outlets
Great I'll buy them
Will too limiting for me I think
Is this is probably not for you and I but
If you're like an insteon fan this
Insteon limits you write in
Yeah baby
I got into insteon back in 2010 because there weren't many other options
Since then I got to wait for him because it's not as
Open and passed away in current or some other hubs and such so
So so yeah so this is for those
So once I have a chance to get it get it in my hands and review it I will say that
One of the other complaints I have when I did the original
Lowe's Iris
Was that it was
Web-based
So they had a web portal
But I couldn't do things on my mobile which was really weird to me at the time
Now it seems like they have switched based on
Well they better than iOS
Send Android app
I knew that going in but based on a review that you found cat
It sounds like they may
Gone completely away from their web version
That's what it looks like and it's just according to One customer review so you know I can't validate it by any means I don't know
I don't have the
The devices and such here
He had
A number of complaints but I'm not going to think it's fair to go through the living that
Is a sub even available yet
Or I guess
They have this available now
As of month
I almost don't feel right talking about 1 review but okay
It just you never know it could be one person's experience
I will say that it concerned me that he said
It couldn't as a pair of any Z-Wave devices but as we just said
You know
It's the iris ecosystem so
Maybe it's even trying to take non Iris devices
I don't know
His version one key fob isn't working with the new version to HUB as well so
You know that there's going to be transitional paying for people that probably the first
Version of this everybody else maybe not
You know what I will say I do like this cuz I mean I know I sound like I'm the hating on it a little bit here with
I do like if you go to the website
And they show you all the different things you can do you know when the activities in the devices
Codify them by saying
Is this one simple to install this is a moderate project to install this one's involved
This one is free this one is premium
It's really nice how they actually show all that's very consumer-friendly in terms of presentation
There you go
And iiii will remain like when I tested the original Iris it was very
Consumer-friendly like
When you
Pair to device The Hub actually beat
You didn't have to wait for like
The device to register on the screen or something to possibly flash a different color you just had a instant comp
Information
And this was back at a time when you repairing things and
Sometimes
You know
Your app would like timeout
Or fail and then you would be like I don't know did it work
And then you have to restart everything in poop there would be like magic and you like
And then you know
But you have no idea
So
You know they're there little things that make
A really big difference and that was like
I thought you know I didn't like the fees I didn't like some of the other things about it
DUI was only so
So so
You know it felt very consumer-friendly but it also felt blessed
But some of the more advanced things that I was testing
They totally didn't nail the basic
Looks like Iris
The timers at Rita
So I can't wait to see what they've been
So let's stay tuned for that
In the meantime
Let's think about
Let's see what are we thinking about let's talk about the new Bluetooth which by the way
Is one of the new radios that the Lowe's Iris Hub ads
Yay
That's cool
Oh yeah so so after our show last week
The Bluetooth special interest group the folks at
Promote the Bluetooth standards and help great Diamond songs
They
You're talkin about bluetooth smart devices next year that will be sending information farther and faster
So that's a win-win
They said they shared some details of their 2016 road map
Telling us what to expect so
Weather sion
Assuming everything is accurate
On the road maps are saying the overall range of Bluetooth smart devices will expand four times over
And data transfer speeds will be doubled over today's Bluetooth devices
So
What seems to be driving this
Is IRT
As soon as I can I guess
I guess you can guess
But I know you would have said I was
Cuz everything
Hanson Brothers
So you know this is good even better though which I love I love I love this in this is actually a nice bit for iron
Bluetooth will support as of next year
Mesh
Networking
Okay
So here's where things get a little crazy though Kevin
I have talked
To SIM network
Engineers
And we have had
Actually
I don't know if these are network Engineers are just radio nerds like in the chip industry so
Weaknesses
These are the people I drink
We got to visit discussions about mesh Network
Am I understanding is
The way Bluetooth does its Mesh networking
Is
Inherently inefficient
Did they argue that Bluetooth
Mesh networking
Is less efficient
And kind of can flood your network
Because the way it does it is it basically shouts out to all of the devices
Hey
Tell so-and-so dis
Hey tell so-and-so this so the more divide it tells every single device
As you increase the number of devices on your network it tends to flood the network
In Kabul
Now the way like
And these are thread propone
So take all of this with a grain of salt because
I can't evaluate that these arguments I can only like
But this sounds
This is accurate like when I look at the
So this is not inaccurate
I just don't know
On the thread side
They're going to a proxy
So they go to one thing and they say hey
Tell this
You got your in charge of this message
Tell the following
When someone checks
For this information
Tell them this
Witches
More
Bandwidth efficient
Well you know I
The Bluetooth say didn't share all the technical details.
Supreme
Outline with a roadmap
Plans are
So the implementation on how it's going to work
I don't know and I don't
Unfortunately I don't go out and drink with radio nerds but
That is a
It is I know I believe I'm missing out trust me I haven't answered your question probably
So I just want to say
What I'm saying
Radio nerds if you were listening to the show like the Bluetooth
Tell me
Give me the answer to this like
Maybe the threat guys
Like you like yes that's true but the downside to the other way of doing Mesh networking is
I don't know
It's Radioactive
Let's hope not puppies are named in getting those proxy so
We'll stay tuned to hear that
Okay so that is that is the update on Bluetooth we we kind of knew that was coming because we did know that
You know the Bluetooth say was looking at mesh Network
Because
We do need
Better mesh networks this does in my mind
Weed to once again
Are we going to have Bluetooth or we going to have thread because they're it they're still setting themselves up for kind of a
The Showdown
There was a Clash of the Titans cuz both of these standards
Why can't I type
In terms of data
But
We'll see did you find out what the data rates
AR
With the 2x date
That was one of the questions I had
And I didn't get any answer
No I do not know
Second question for the Bluetooth Sig people
Explain to us
Radio networking the new data rates
Because
That's important
And will will definitely update on that
So now
Before we sound like real idiots explaining
Something we don't know much about let's move on
We've got lissy a new retail channel for some more iot stuff in
I am super excited about this because I love being able to go and put my hands on more devices
Send the device is the Leo night light is now in Lowe's
Stores in Best Buy
Best Buys in Toledo NightLight is a
$99 smoke detector we actually might have talked about it last week
When we talked about the roost
We might have benches
It sounds familiar my TV on
Banana show way way way back
At one point in time
It's a
Plug-in night light that's connected and listens for smoke alarms
So what it does is it listens for your smoke detector
And then it tells you basically
It tries to figure out where
The smoke detector is coming from and is like hey and then it
A Pikachu
So I can send alerts
Retrofitting your smoke detectors without buying the $100 desk in as many rooms as yes
So it's kind of a nice option that night light isn't LED that changes colors my my daughter loved it when we tried it
It's very
You know it's fun
So you could use one of these to monitor several smoke detectors which is worth the cost savings
Exactly
Yeah okay
Annie's early
Gotcha is there a monthly fee or anything
Back in the day it was $99 I believe it is still 99
So
Sketchy your whole house
It will not tell you though when your smoke alarm is out of battery
So you stuck in the 3 a.m.
Unless you buy what we talked about
The roost
Yeah
So
There you have it
What's interesting about Leo is
Back in June they actually did a layoff or they laid off a couple
People
And lo and behold there still like it we were all kind of worried we're like
There is a lot of money
They are doing layoffs
Going to be a sad sad story
Do you know if this is their only product right now
I believe it is their only shipping product they are
Planning to make a wide array of Prada
Text Leo is interesting because they have a global
They want to be global
They're very focused on making products for
Specific Geographic areas
So yeah
Oh you know what we haven't talked about by the way
No
With all of our Smartwatch moves
Fossil
Buy misfit
Route 206
60 million dollars
Yes yes yes yes Misfit the folks with the make the shine the shine the really pretty tiny live
Tracker tracker
They make
Connect to light bulbs take to make the bolt
Connected light bulbs something that I always forget
I have not tried the bolt I have not tried them either because I'm like
Random products
Fat people
But I wanted to get your take on that news because
I was kind of it first like
Why is this house
Fossil people do not think of fossil when it comes to smart watches and I'm not going to say that people
Are thinking
A lot about smart watches right now but when they do they're not paying me fossil
They should because fossil has been involved in the store
Smartwatch
Business for well over a decade
Penny helps make
The first Microsoft spot watch 2004
The Abacus I still have one
So they
Try this before
And didn't work ahead of its time
They're now making their own smart watches
And now by adding Misfit what they can do is make traditional type watches
At low cost with fossils not a
You know there is some $1,000 brand easily
You know they're not they're not Rolex then
Tag are in a week
Talk about them
So it's
I don't say that inexpensive way but it's a a way to get in better integrated into the activity scene with watches
The people who may not want a true Smartwatch for notifications and Bluetooth and
Music and call so
I don't think it's a bad purchase I mean I'm not a financial analyst I don't know if it was if it made sense financially
But I do like the idea of him
This is a unexpected move but
Once it happened like I'll be up that make sense to me
Okay and you know I will say that
I'm looking at
Fossil had done a deal with Intel or they
Akon on stage at IDF with Intel
Doing an Android Wear SmartWatch 2
And fossil CEO I'm not going to butcher his name
Costa car
Sodus
Cardinal Terrace
He had said back in August during earnings call
That
He thought the most significant long-term devices would be
Quote-unquote smarter watches
It's just adding chips and extra functionality
Not a full-fledged
Watch when operating system and so on like an Apple Watch run Android Wear watch
It's it's more of a transitionary kind of thing to the Inn in between product for people
You don't want to
Another Kiki watch on there
Brest but
A nice watch like that like the Y things activity
You know that's a nice analog watch
We can still track your steps and I'm leaving a Bluetooth now or they can shoot me information to an app and all that that Timmy is a smarter
That's a good example
Yeah and I thought then
The purchase of Misfit makes sense because they've always had a very minimalistic design
And they've never been kind of about life
The watch there's no real like OS it's it's been very much about
Conveying information
What does little battery power is possible
Flashy
So so it does make sense I kind of always thought
If your watchmaker and you were going to buy a watch
Company should buy pebble
Because you know
What's cross-platform it's got like
This open OS but
I guess if you're watchmaker you're probably in your thinking along those lines you like
Did you buy a computer I want to buy a watch
Smarter
So this follows along the
And to be honest with a company like a fossil or another traditional watchmaker that wants to do this could do what tigers
Just go with Android Wear
When it's available open they have to pay for it
So they could just do that the differences how do you stand out from the crowd of Android Wear watches
Fossil I don't think wants to do that
I think they wanted
Compete at the
As you said smarter watch
Area
Okay see you soon yeah
I can't believe we almost didn't talk about that I forgot about it
Terrible
We're building up this whole Smartwatch Galbraith
All right
We will skip ahead to our guests this week
Who is
I haven't talked to him yet guys so
I'm just going to punt on his last name until I talk to him
His name is Alex he's the CEO of Josh. AI
We're going to be talking about building intelligence for the Smart Home
And specifically Building open intelligence
Anti-police
So
It should be fine
Stick with me and just to be fair Stacy knows his last name is just the pronunciation is the trick
Yes I could spell it in a heartbeat this is what happens when you take a print journalist
And you give him a podcast
I'm not even going to risk
Until I talk to him
Yeah so alright well
Stay tuned for Alex
Procrastinate
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And we have as our guest
Alex said Here Comes his last name for you guys
Kappa salon
Hi Alex how are you doing
I'm doing great and you now my last night
Aqi I was working hard at it
So Alex is a
A product called
Josh AI
Jocelyn
I'm going to get that.
So Josh is a
Product that is actually not in the market yet
It won't be in the market for another 3 months
And Alex real fast
It's just a wee bit about Josh.
Yeah use the company was really founded on an artificial intelligence backend
Where we cannot into all sorts of interesting to my products
And in this particular instance
Tronical releasing
Is all about the home
Connect with
A lot of yourself product so you're nasty
Philips hue light bulb
Restaurant Depot
Conversation
You speak to the Sea
Excellent okay
So with this in mind I had you on the show because you guys have
Been producing some really fun stuff
Actually run medium
And you talked about kind of
What the smartphone
Return from bat
Send it
You talked about kind of
Idealized Vision so I thought for you to kind of
Talk about
Your vision of the Smart Home
Even three years from now
It's interesting
Overseeding right now
The hardware that comes out of the companies are making their own app
Which means you have a whole collection apps on your phone
Think about it
Nothing
Turn on the lights and having lights go on his wonderful
Combination is more about Craig and Orchestra
Do
Magically based on the time of day
It's over the next three years we think it's coming
It's really truly realizing
Home automation
I really mean that contractors
There's a brain in the home the home
Is intuitive able to recommend
I just wanted to quit
We have
Number of Nest products at home
I know I'm not alone in saying it's extremely frustrating when they learn
What stinks are habits
And it turns out to be
Completely wrong
Los Angeles
Air conditioning really cooling the house down
Thomas Whitaker
Last night I set my thermostat to 72
And this was not trying to be too smart
Having the ability to automate but also
The intelligence to not do it in a bad way
Why voice
As the primary
And then we'll say
Why is it so important
I have this or how do you build a
Voice interaction
The first of which is
I think it's really important.
Really just
Clearly Define
How were talking about artificial intelligence
And that really ties into a voice
As soon as Jerry came out and we have the ability to
Potter have a little bit of this
Almost Human like experience
Everyone started saying
Arise
Across the board in scrum
Quote unquote use artificial intelligence
It's really into
Important
Is that Siri really doesn't use
Any artificial intelligence
And a lot of what we see today
Is it true artificial
Intelligent systems
Is behaving human-like
Human-like is free thinking
It's working with a system like you're working with the purse
Kylo Ren
Open this door
Turn this light on
That's a very easy thing to call me to do
To tell computer to do that
Today
Very flexible but in all reality
If you wanted to say something like
Send Stacey a text that I say hello
The system doesn't
Understand
The nuances of what you're saying
You're basically matching your words
And if it matches you get a response
Dirty South something like
Let me search the internet
Or some other answer that
In all reality it just doesn't know what you're saying
And then
Is very true but we see what Google Now
And even with the first version of Josh that we're working on
It's
Fortunately or unfortunately
Artificial
And I think it's important to put that out there because
Restart reading about artificial intelligence
Skynet
Computer taking over
Consciousness
Free thinking
We're so far away from that
And so I want to make sure that people understand
Is really not a human-like smart
Computer
It's a
If you took something like the Amazon Echo
Or even
Apple Siri
If you want to say want this product to be all about
You realize you just have to figure out rooms around home
So how do you say the turn on and off the light
How do you say to lock and unlock the door
Music
You realize that this problem
Problems
I'm much more to sign then
General purpose AI
Google Now
Problems with AI
Mass market products
Is that
You don't know what to ask you systems because they
And that's something that we're very directly trying to
Opposed
Worst thing
Dumbass costume
Make you feel better
All those things are
Possible
We want people to understand
Josh
Should be able to do anything
Therefore
If you can think of
A way to explain his statement
We want to guarantee the job he's going to be able to do that
AI
In terms of natural language
Processing invoice
So excited about this for a couple
The first insight
Beautiful products
Experiences.
What's Soca
Confusing
Is that these products are often
Complicated
You're confusing
Just have to learn multiple systems that don't
Talk to one another they don't work together
Are building around a graphical user
Lola's voice everything
So
How are you going to work with these companies
Is I mean right now one of the big challenge in creating these cuz I actually can create
I have so many
Devices in my home
Play the song so I can create a lot of things right now
How do you plan to do it because the big problem for a lot of these companies is just Manpower in integrating
All of these connected devices together
So how do you plan to kind of address that it's
Not an easy problem to solve and it takes a lot of group
A number to Hardware companies
Very beginning did not want to talk to
And I will be in touch later and the only reason by the way
Is it they don't already have a public API
Does only have a public API
We're off to take me to get furniture
Rather than dealing with the echo
You're the federal rules that we work with
Hardware companies
Porcine
And we're going to do it with
The products that are
Customer service
Disregard creative ways to make it work anyway because
Quite frankly Anderson
Airbus
There's almost no Securities most iron
Network
It's what that means is we can gain access to almost everything
If we're on the local network
That's the way Josh Gordon
So we're basically taking the hard
Approach
To building the stuff out ourselves the most
I'm in other cases you're working with companies
Better provider
Just hi
Dana 80 or
In the building Engineers working with us
Often times it will find you
We say our customers need this product
We're going to make it work one way or another and you just figure it out
Okay so that is very much the kind of SmartThings approach
Quite a while
So you mentioned
Security
Let's talk about
And privacy
Because
AI is built on
Training sets a
Basically
And using that data to train neural network
Parks and
One of the things that
I'm fascinated by this is the fact that
You know you can't
Develop gradle
Credible kind of models for them
Without lots and lots of data
So how do you guys look at
Being able to hit like
Train
Your algorithms and train your models for this
How do you kind of reconcile that with
The Privacy policies that you're thinking about her saying
Got a couple things going on
Understand that you mentioned that a lot of a eyes book
That's perfectly true
I'm in the way that neural networks work
You essentially are training a large system of data on
Neural Nets are very well
Established
I can recognize cat photograph
I'm going to do is I'm going to load in a million photos
And therefore when I show a photo if there
With language however it's very very
System
And that's really the only case
You need now
In terms of what word
Voice
They're basically three components
First there's the speech-to-text
Someone is going to speak into the microphone
And this isn't going to convert that speech tax
Once you
Send you a text to text translation
And this is really where the brain
The text that says
Turn the lights on in the kitchen
And it interprets that means this action
That's going to connect to this device and then it's going to generate
The responsive generates
Steps converted back to speech
That might be what you hear is just
Okay
Turn the lights on that happened in
So what you doing
Perspective
You're actually have to explain all three of those and understand that they're different
When you're looking at the last adventure
Text to speech
Open source technology
Apple Google Microsoft products
Something that we've been able to use you
That's something that a lot of really really smart people
Stunning
Jackie Chan
Word the benefactors of a lot of that
However it's not
There's no product on the market in my opinion.
Good enough to just taken worth it
We still have to do a lot of creative engineering around that
That's what I mean
If you were to say something like
Play Netflix on the TV
If Netflix is not understood word in the vocabulary
It's not going to pregnant
Computer
It's never going to spell anything wrong
It is what it is
Try to not snore
Dictionary
How to make salmon Grill
But then she just jump into the middle layer which is really where
This is what we need
We
You think about how many ways can you say that
Turn the lights on
Turn on the lights turn on the lights
Please turn the lights on
All sound very similar ones
Computer
Instead of what we have on one level
Is there a flexible
Basically programming language
That can handle
Do you have to language processing element
What was Santa's house
If something says what we don't match Google directly
What we try to do
Figure out what you might be saying
The other thing that we do
When you say something that a system doesn't
Your natural response
You try to say it again
So what we have in our system has something comes in
Would like to check did not match rule did not generate
Response
Later than usual
Something else
That's it soccer system that those two things might be
They might be trying to stay the same thing in a different way
And so there's some areas that we actually
Extended dialogue
Basically
Recommendations to human engineer II review
Another cases with system tries to auto-update
I'm basically get smarter on its own
Anime
Give me the date of what users are saying but
Really the context around who sang it
If you are Stripes can you something and Josh doesn't do it it doesn't understand it
You're able to do that action another why
Next time you go to stay that
Same thing
We should make sure we do it right
Got it
All right well on that note
Alex I really appreciate
You coming on the show
And I look forward to 3 months or so
Not being able to
Test out trash. In my own home
Thank you for coming on the show
Thank you so much
And that concludes this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you next week