Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofu
And today we have
So
Much
This is this going to be the Stacy and Kevin jail
I think yes
This is the Stacy and Kevin show this week
Because otherwise
There's just no room we've got so much stuff
Our guests sorry I guess you'll be back
Don't worry
I have wonderful guest for
Are you guys coming up
We are going to talk about
Wow
Google did a bunch of news things for the Internet of Things We
They got partners for Google home
We talked about Cortana getting an SDK because that could be used for iot and we're going to do a little
Quick dive into Amazon's AI as a service and how it might
Compared to Google Assistant
Then
Where can I get an ad break from
Our sponsor Samsung
And we're going to go in the news cuz we got a new
Ble Hub that's Bluetooth hub for you guys we've got some homekit sensors which is a pretty new thing
We got zigbee over
Thread
Industrial news from GE
Saint Cloud news from Ala
Maybe some government news and we've got some self-driving car stuff
I'm out of breath already
Me too I didn't even say anything
I know just listening
Nexen tires
So before we get into all that let's take a word from our sponsor this week
Our sponsor this week is skybell have you ever wondered who's at your front door when you're at work or what
What a package arrives or when your kids get home the skybell video doorbell lets you see who's at your door
Or from your smartphone replaces your current doorbell and when a visitor presses the button that sends an alert with live
Video so you can see hear and speak to the person at your door I love this doorbell I review doorbells for the
The Wirecutter and I will say skybell HD was my top pick and because I love
Love all of you guys so much and because the CEO skybell loves you we're giving iot podcast blisters
Discount you get $50 off using the code Stacy
This code is good through Christmas day so by now or don't but I think you should by now if
Looking for a video doorbell cuz it is great
Now
Back
2 hour show
Where Do We Begin actually we should probably Begin by me saying that I do work for Google as a consultant
And I have nothing to do with their IRT efforts and the only mention that because we're going to be talking a lot about the Rio 2 efforts
Yes let's just get started with Google
Because
By golly they did two pieces of news so
We talked about it a little bit last week with
Google opening up its SDK
Axel home
Is what it's called to the program's actions on Google and it allows you to
Build stuff for Google home
You're kind of like the skills for the echo
But a little bit different
So in this is worth noting so would you build
We're going to have to come up with some terminology
Hero it's remember how we had to do scene 2
Recipes at bows at all
So guys skills are for the Amazon Echo
Ecosystem
And Google calls them
Actions actions
It's okay because I think
If I read correctly it's actions and conversations are the two things you can do in a conversation somewhere like
Informational chatbots that you can add to
The Google Assistant
But actions are yes very much like skills
So when you do the conversations what happens is you enable this conversation and then and entirely
Play new entity pops up in your Google home
So it no longer sounds like
Google home voice it is now
Whatever voice
Conversation company has chosen
Kind of interesting
So if you're talking to WebMD you make it
Eye Doctor Li voice
What a doctor referral
I like I bet it'll be male
Pyruvates I write prescriptions very sloppily how can I help you today
12 what the brand thinks is it
So that'll be interesting and then the actions
No here's a question and I don't know if
I could not parse this together so
We're going to link to the other big news which actually happened on Tuesday
This week which was Google announced
That they changed their Brillo
Tiny device OS that is not actually that
Google things is now it's called and it's out of developer preview
And they also announced
Weave is avail
And we've is their kind of operating system
I guess it's how we should
I would say Android things is the operating system
You're right and rude things is the operating system and its 4
You know it's actually not for sensors that's for slightly bigger things
Communication
Right right there that's the one that tells what devices what devices can do what I think my guess it's ask
Schema I think Google is technically calling them
Oh shoot I forget what it's called now
They used to call it a
It's yet
Traits
Traits sound like
If you have a lightbulb
The trade can be
On off
Right right song
Sprite out of power switch component of a dimmer component the trait for dimmer will be brightness and so on so it's
More of explaining what device is telling each other what they can do
So this is going to compete directly with iotivity
Because that is also device Discovery Communications now they
They call it a protocol
But
Whatever it it also gives the the characteristics are the traits of a device
Much like all joined it now alljoy did come in
And converge with iotivity
So
That's
That
When we talk about weave that's who you should
Compare it to
And there's also Nest weave
So is part of the Google
And we talked about that before and we wondered why are there two weaves in in Google and
But I'd say that you said
What's going to happen is
Google's weave and Nest weave
Will converge and there will be more information about that
Coming out in 2017 according to a Google spokesperson
So that's good news that is good news so that means basically
With
All of this iot news
Things that are using weave
Will speak to the Google ecosystem including Google
Home
And they
Google assistant on the pixel phones yes so now you can control your nest on the
Actually
Good but the other implications of this are
That there are a couple of devices that Google said already
Support
We are already using weave and those devices include products from Honeywell
Wink
Tp-link
And falcon
Which is why
We also heard on Tuesday that WeMo
Is going to work with Google home
So
Your
That's
Well I'll let you do the butt first
But it's not available yet
Is coming soon
Yeah but that's okay
Oh I will
Reboot your butt with a that's okay because
Again I still have not yet bought a Google home is like I bought a Ford
Echo have an another. I got two weeks ago
Again it's all. What devices these things work with what Partners they have who's supporting what and
It's been a little light on the Google home side until now and still is but
At least we got news
But here's what's coming and that makes me happy
And yes and I got confirmation from wink
That a wink version
Are weak support
Hyundai
Google home
Is also coming
But I don't have any PA
So we can probably expect the tp-link outlets those are cute
People love them
And Honeywell like There lyric their water sensor there
TV
I don't remember the I think it's the T5 thermostat that's slightly cheaper than the lyrics
Lifx bulbs First Alert
Smoke detectors as well
Yes
Should be
Coming and I will say
Kevin you didn't buy an echo
So I bought my echo December 2014
$100
We just watched something
If you want it
It just came out in November I remember that
USA versus I'm passing on home
But they didn't actually announce the Smart Home
Features or capabilities until March of 2015
That is correct also
And that's when I bought my
They took a little time
We're going to let we're going to give Google home the same time
That's fair
I give them
Them being Amazon more leeway here because they
I want to say invented the category but say they brought this
Type of product to the mainstream masses
Monica said he did it first but they brought to a wide range of people
First and therefore
I'm okay with them adding Partners overtime and obviously cuz I fought for them
I'm disappointed some other following competing products that did not have
A wide ecosystem available on day one
I agree but
Well they have apparently had to get weave all in one
That's fine
I don't know
I will say it's kind of overwhelming like if you imagine these things launching
With everything
It would be too much like people be like
I think it first if you were the first one to do that yes but now that they're
You know you can go to Home Depot or Lowe's whatever
And by connected light bulbs or a hub or whatever
I think it
Canopy who's these products work with all of them that are readily available out of the gate at this point in time
Not so much in 2014 when vehicle came out I agree with you
But
Or maybe I'm just being too optimistic on the market and I don't know
You know I think
So
Back to Android.
No it's worth delving into a lot because I see
Three different hardwood products you can use with it and I have one of them so I can't wait
So yes
It's going to suck
Support
You can start building with
The Intel Edison
Tnxp
Tipico
Raspberry Pi 3
Now there was
There was I saw on the Google developer Google Plus page
Which
Why not go there
Someone asking about Arduino and the response was that that just didn't
It wasn't a robust and
Platform
And I know if you guys remember but back when Android things was Brillo it required I think 64
Was it megabytes it was megabytes of memory to run
Which is a lie
So
It's possible that Arduino is just
Yeah
The other thing to know and this is something that I had heard about
Confirmed with Google
Is that if you want to use Wii
You're going to have to use Google's Cloud which means you're going to need an account and you're going to have to use the weave
Can we server components
Security saying and a control so like when they roll out
New traits
Isn't that sort of thing
That's also that all goes through one
Fun places
Taylor & Son
Location of Android
I see the
Wisdom
Making that
Decision
But I can also see people being upset saying what what if I want to use somebody else's cloud
I'm sure there will be some grumbles
You're going to have to be by 4
But later on after
Later in the show will talk about
Let's see what else do we need to know about the
List Aquino
So far
I don't know that we know much more
America's Best
From Google that's not Kev
Actually, that knows what they're talking about
Yeah so we don't I don't mean this was just an end developer announcement
Developer should say not any consumer announcement or anything to that
Extensive
I don't know that there's much more we know yet
In addition to this news we should also talk about Microsoft
Which
What no
Got an SDK that
Also on Thursday
Which
I think it's actually worth bringing up
Because
We're all waiting for like what's going to happen with
Microsoft in their iot home play
And what it looks like is the Cortana SDK
Is going to be
That
It's answer
Which is you can put Cortana on any device much like Amazon let's they have I'm going to say her name every
Alexa voice services
And you can put that on
Any number to buy
What is Microsoft's early Cortana s2k Partners is going to be Harman Kardon
The premium audio manufacturer which incidentally was bought by Samsung
Which is really odd which feels really
Yeah not that Samsung. Harmon but that
Samsung has their own iot play here and yet there
An early device partner with Microsoft to and showing off a
Audio speaker that you speak to
Cortana
Just like you would with an echo it's kind of strange
And so I would be curious given
Not necessarily.
Given
The SDK is now that are out
And the
It supposed to go home
So thick
No actions
We got the echo
STK
And we got
Cortana SDK
What is Cortana and Cortana skills kit
Cortana skills kit so you can build skills which thank you
Cortana for keeping with the skills nomenclature so I don't have to stretch my brain anymore during this show
What do we think about all this what are people going to use
Who are we going to talk to Kevin
Book
We're going to talk
Hopefully in the future it won't matter
Is my hope
I remember one of the first articles I wrote about
Voice interface is the invisible interface was
It will work because it's
Simple it's Universal anybody can use it without cortical learning interface if you know how to ask question
Speaker command
You can use this interface
Your question though is
What about
Multiple interfaces in a sentence
How do we manage that
This is some strange coming from me but I think
Microsoft is actually
Best suited for this challenge because
Cortana works on
Windows
On Android on iOS it works on my Xbox
And then they're going to have these additional devices
Hopefully through partners with their SDK
Souffrant terms of
Of Brett's of that
Invisible interface
He might
Beheaded the curfew
And they also downstairs
Microsoft translator using their AI skills cuz
Microsoft AI
Backend in
Speech-to-text in language
NLP
Language recognition all of that stuff
Is
Freaking
Amazing I mean Google has really good stuff
But Microsoft on Tuesday also announced real time
Translation
Like between groups of people speaking multiple languages
Is in person
That is insane
That's impressive I mean
That's really
Amazing
So
You may be right
Especially if we think about being able to talk and speak to something
Natural
Now
Let's throw a curveball in here
Because
Amazon
It was actually at reinvent at the end of November and then they also this week had a pulled it all together in this Nifty little
Blanco
Amazon is actually really trying hard to offer an AI product
For Developers
That
Capri train models basically
So you can do both custom algorithms and custom models but they also have
Pre tuned stuff for developer
And that's all going to be through there
Cloud
So now they have these Amazon AI models that you can run on top of Amazon's machine learning
If you guys are like
Head exploded
Just be aware that
Basically
Is giving developers the ability to use the developer state
With Amazon's AI
Algorithms
So you can basically
Use your stuff to build new smarter things and you don't have to develop all the AI that like
Yeah it seems like the race is on
Or maybe
Come out everybody
Everybody wanted to provide a cloud service okay we do that everybody wants to
Provide us the case for that cloud okay we all do that now
Now everyone's
Provide an AI
For people to use so
As you were saying Amazon that I see three different things with your kind of interesting just to break it down a little further they got Amazon
Text for natural language processing
Forgot Amazon poly which is at X
Text to speech service and Amazon rekognition which is
And image service
Open the cloud
So they're providing all that to developer switch
Again a lot of
Others do that Google does that Microsoft does that as well so
So maybe the race is on is probably the wrong way to say at the races hopefully
Heating up
Dot-dot-dot and who is the beneficiary
We are
I'm going to play this for you I don't see if I don't know if this is going to work
Let's see if
You can hear it but this is Amazon Polly reading quotes
Sufficient
Technology is indistinguishable
That was Amazon Polly
Just reading
So
And she's really good in British
I guess that's piss
Right
Why not
Exit
Okay
So
That's a lot going on
Everybody's got their components
If I were to judge today I would say Microsoft is probably the most
Advanced in terms of
Speaking back to people and maybe understanding followed by Google maybe they're neck-and-neck
Amazon has the biggest ecosystem right now
And with their AI stuff there
Place to keep that ecosystem
Google
Has the best
I can't answer that question.
I'm like Google who has the best employees
Google probably has the best lake
Google knows what I'm talking about
When I ask it a question
So
We'll see
This is big you guys so
I'm really excited 2017 is shaping up to be really cool
Alright let's take a quick a break
And then we're going to come back with more
Hey everyone we are taking a break in The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is say
Samsung Arctic cloud and we have Janine
Who is head of developer evangelism for Samsung Arctic Cloud to tell us
Samsung artik what is Janine
Simple Arctic cloud is an open data exchange platform for the internet of things that provide easy-to-use opening
Tools to collect store and Eric on any data from any connected device your cloud service
Transformers
To accelerate device interoperability
Enable nudata inside
And why is interoperability sew in
Predicts will be over 20 billion connected devices by 2000
All of these things
We're not meant to work together
You know all in your own to be successful
Interoperability is critical
There was a study done that is shown that interoperability is required
For 40% on average to 60% and some settings
Artix headphones the problem of breaking down those silos by allowing for the true interoperability
Between devices in service
That sounds like a really powerful platform
What are developers doing with it
Incredible with developers are doing using or
Arctic hotspot formed
Recently added houses on where they filled out an industrial iot
Solutions
Service iot
So they used to check
To Monitor and troubleshoot the machine
Enter data Within
To Arctic Cloud which stores the data for clearing data from the chatbot
Issue with machine such as a high temperature reading
An article was created to send a notification
To the chat bot to communicate
With the operator said something went wrong
We also had somebody build a smart City solution which optimizes waste collection and reduces fuel consumption
Garbage trucks
The sensors are installed in the lead of the garbage container
Measure the temperature of the container and the dumpster is full
Isn't transmitted article
Waste Management Company
It's really easy for developers to build an increase in the rate of solution
Behind the complexity of iot development
And provide simplicity
We provide apis for everything in order to simplify that whole process
We have 10 ft kzzu schools in great sample code
Help you get started
And your development efforts
Awesome what you need where can I find out more
Developers can learn more about artist
Start using it for free by visiting
Order to build out and
Innovative iot solution using artificial intelligence
Tik Tok
Build wireless network
Disconnect low energy object will be doing a demo with crafty I as well as big box
Alright we are back and it
Instead of a guest we are still here both Stacy and
Kevin
Talking about
News we did a big deep dive on
Holy cow all the new
A iCloud personal assistant
Talkin things
We should probably come up with a better name for them
And now we're going to get into some of the week's news that that we haven't covered yet
Such as well just get started with some new products out there in the market
Cassia networks has created a
Bluetooth
Home
Hub
And you guys are like
Who cares
But know this is great because Bluetooth mesh is not great
In this Hub actually makes your Bluetooth
Go further
And supports a lot of
So this is good for both home
And a lot of people in the industrial world are trying to use Bluetooth to actually because it's already
History of Aquarius
Yeah and the short actually the short range of Bluetooth
Advantage for them because it's a little bit more secure
Like within the factory there like
What I like about this and not enough
Typical it big
I don't say Phantom Bluetooth is I love Bluetooth
Very specific things
I would not think of it any router but
What I like about this and even though you can do this on Wi-Fi
I like Bluetooth for presents
Not not like Christmas presents but where I am present
You don't want blue
That would be cool to the best of both worlds
I also like this because right now
Bluetooth
Things like light switches are sensors it just doesn't make a lot of sense because it just doesn't have the
The range
I have in this is going to make this
Possible and it should hopefully it will be Bluetooth 5 compatible since they're just lunch again and
Bluetooth 5 specs
Out so I look forward to seeing this in the real world
This is actually an Enterprise version
And some of them support power over ethernet
Plug it in have connectivity
And you don't actually have to have the cloud Kasia SDK is both on the cloud is and on the rug
Router so yeah you can keep
Local
Disconnect
AKA
Look all right so I think this is actually really cool product worthwhile
The other news in this is big because we didn't talk about her
Siri and app
The news here is that fibaro which is a maker of really awesome Z-Wave sensors
They're making homekit sensors
And
This is significant for two reasons one is for borrow is a Z-Wave hub
Company so this is the first time they've gone out of Z-Wave
What
And these are bushes her
Yeah
Pair Bluetooth
The other is that this is going to give some sensors to homekit
Which
Has been kind of
Left sensor
Focused I guess
So fibaro is going to launch a flood sensor
For $70 a motion sensor for $70 and a door window sensor for $60
They're going to start selling
Natsumi
So
Yeah
Yeah that's good
And I'm going to get some you guys cuz I don't know
Come in my house I'm building at home kit ecosystem I've got the Elgato sensors
Eve sensors in their
Which also Bluetooth
And some
Lights
Some homekit lights
Philips Hue
Device
Idevices smart plug
And then I have some
Lutron
Ellucian hub
Switch mileage
If you guys are thinking of doing this
Know this
Are your Lutron stuff it only works on
One system
Or it like
One thing or the other so I'm going to break my Lutron lights for
In my husband going to
See that's gay
Shrugging right now
Actually yes it be as if it's not over wife over by so if it's a Directv billing
Z-Wave
Or Lutron those only connect to One Network
At a time
So
For the Lutron what I'm going to do is I'm going to have to run it to the Lutron hub
Which then I can use the Lutron app on my
Android devices
Just still control them
But I can't type
Since
Might my husband
You know
His life is already missed
So okay so that's that we should talk about sleepy
You know why cuz we got like two other pieces
Yeah Evergreen thread
Zigbee running over the thread protocol
Holy cow guys
ZTE running over the thread protocol is
Real so now Icees they're going to show this off that this is work
And for you guys for like
Oh my God Stacy you're breaking my brain
Protocol is a wireless is a mesh Wireless protocol
Much like zigbee and Z-Wave are mesh Wireless protocols
Like those
Thread has low and doesn't use a lot of energy
Unlike those
It is IPv6 compatible so it
Can go directly out to record
The differences when you're thinking of thread
Throw it down at
Zigbee and Z-Wave
Once Bluetooth has its mesh network will throw Bluetooth mesh in there just
But now
With zigbee running over 3
That means you get the zigbee
Software stack
Over the thread protocol in the zigbee software stack has a lot of stuff for lights that's really powerful
For managing huge lighting net
Works or big lady
So that's that's why that
Hatteras Sol
Probably good for a Industrial
An Enterprise has announced that they're going into the Enterprise a couple weeks ago so
It also means that anything that supports the red so
I kind of think that Google
Is going to be a big supporter of thread since it came out of nest
And in fact
There is a
CB radio with a Google WiFi
So
I imagine we're going to see
Zippy ever thread coming from your Google Wi-Fi routers at some point
I Can Only Imagine
Can I say otherwise cuz I don't know
But I did get my Wi-Fi
Something I'm actually using right now
We're going to talk about
Stay tuned
You guys
Cool
What other things do we have
There's lots going on all of a sudden so
Google self-driving car efforts
Which were part of I guess part of the X lab X division
Are now a separate company under alphabet called waymo
I guess so
W what's the next letter to be used in alphabet so
Waymo is its own
Company under alphabet
And
Google is partnering with I want to say
Chrysler Fiat
For yeah yeah so
This is probably a CES event I suspect we'll see some
Demonstrations of self-driving
Minivans
Are pacifica's I can't recall which
Ephraim Chrysler that will use the Google tech
And
Yes it's interesting because a lot of people recently were saying Google shutting down and self-driving car business not like really
I wouldn't know cuz I don't I got not on that team
But then
No they're not shut down their spinning off to its own company
Yes
And then Uber
Is like
What up
Yasso
I'm very curious what Uber drivers think of this but I'm sure Uber Riders
Will be
Intrigued
The first self-driving Ubers are
Alive and well in San Francisco
So this is a very limited
Market but yes so it's starting
Well today that they were recording a show witches Wednesday
You can get a self-driving Uber even matches one if one is available
Trying to figure out did they say that it said how many
There are how many Ubers but
As far as I know
I would hope so
That would be a problem if something happened you don't say don't say
It's a they're spending their self-driving pilot
Williston
Depend on Santana local
Ordinances and such but
Yeah they really don't say anything I'm looking at their blog post right now
There is
There is one
So maybe Uber drivers won't care
They have less to do
Okay
There's going to be a driver in
In the car
Yay
Cuz I would be kind of nervous and
Now the drivers don't have to drive
Also
Yay so yeah this is this is actually happening
You guys and I would not want to drive any self-driving in San Francisco seems like a freaking nightmare
Cuz people are running in and out and there's construction everywhere
I highly recommend we should link to this video in our shonos because I highly recommend people watched the demonstration of the Uber cell
Self-driving car because
The poor driver
It's just sitting there bored as all get-out looking around out the window
I will link to that machete
Yes I'm an Uber car babysitter how can I help you
I don't have to keep your eyes on the road
I guess I have to be
Prepare to take over but
That would not be
Okay Industrial
So we got some clown news here
Ala which is
A company that provides a cloud service for
Any company that wants to build connected devices basically
It works with it's a cloud service that's authenticated and lots of chips you put the chip in your product
And it said that you have a cloud back in for all of your
Needs
Have announced it they are doing
The echo skills for people
So they will support it
They will make
All of your stuff you can figure your stuff and then they take those configurations and then they tune it to the echo can
Integrations
Presumably
Stay I did talk to them there and talks with
You know all the other providers so presumably they will tune your stuff to the other providers that handle the fact that
Google requires you to have
To separate
There is on cloud implementation so
This is great news both
For companies that are like
Complicated
It also for the companies that are
Like
Hey this world is complicated we will do all of the back in nasty stuff for you and
YouTube pays money
And so this is great
Plus
I got the ticket from the Ala guys there were like yeah we had to do this because all of our customers were like we don't want an app we need voice
Recognition
So
I feel like that's kind of a no-brainer but there's another
Example of
Voice really winning
When it comes to the interaction for The Internet of Things
We will
Other cloud news GE is building industrial networking gear for its
Iot industrial iot stuff they're using Cisco and HP gear
Basically building gateways
Randa gateways
Sensors that sort of stuff
Because you can't
You can't get stuff to the predix cloud if you don't give him the hardware
Kind of strange because I know that GE already works with like
Gateway's and stuff from
Like Intel Dell
There's a bunch of like
Really
Archaic non-computer vendor kind of Gateway providers
That have been in the industrial space for a while that
LG also works with so
I agree this was kind of strange when
When I saw it on the notes and whatnot but then I'm thinking you had the whole products that is
Without data
It's kind of useless but it needs data
So I think they're just trying to remove obstacles to getting at that dated from industrial machines
End-to-end solution that
When is right
Man you want to talk about Wi-Fi or
I feel like we should just skip ahead to Wi-Fi
What do you think
Yes that's what we talked about
MiFi as I said I got my Google Wi-Fi units
Which cost me to eat
129 I think under $29
And you already had that
I did I did have the onhub and remember when Google Wi-Fi was announced a lot of people are like my own house
Done if you don't know
It's actually part of this Google wi-fi system
Where can be if you already have an onhub so you can
You can actually
Create a mesh network with multiple on hubs
If you wanted to but that's expensive so
I went the cheaper out and added one Google Wi-Fi to my onhub
Ramayanam is downstairs on the first floor
In a two-story town house about 2000 square feet
I had Wi-Fi signal issues and obviously speed therefore issues in the backside of the second floor of the house
So am I getting what I want to put a Google Wi-Fi on the second floor and see what that does and oh my goodness
Just like
You know when hero or Bloomer many other available Solutions
It did the trick
Time it was very simple to add
Alright to the new Google Wi-Fi app
The old onhub app is now Wi-Fi
Just put branding purposes as I suspect
And so I've got this little mesh network of snow 2 nodes and it's working really well
Yay
So you really notice the
And how did that go
You know I did try the Eero and when I got the Wi-Fi and tweeted about it people like
Compare the Euro that you tried and so on
And I'm not going to compare them I said they both do the job and the reason I'm not doing a strict comparison
Is because I tested the Eero 3 pack in my old house
Prices
And therefore
It's not a fair comparison I mean Network
Testing you can add variables in and expect a good test
Well you can't
YouTube
But but it's a totally different environment so you know it's hard for me to say
This is better or worse than any Rover example or some other
Whatever you want
I don't I can't compare it cuz I've never tested those here in this house
Severe is again
All right well I also in testing Wi-Fi so I talked about these last week these with a plume pods
These are the little WiFi things that there hexagonal
Metallic beautiful things that you plug in there's a radio in a network
You plug into it electrical outlet
What you could do that
When you plug into your
So
I set it up
And then I didn't tell you guys about it last week because it's a
It's a learning system so I didn't test it until it has been in a week so it would
Learn what it needed to know
So
The key here is it's all connected to the cloud
And for me
I did notice that my Wi-Fi network
Has improved
In places that are hard to get to
Now the comparison for me is going to be the Eero
Because that's what happening in my house
I did notice that the plume Wi-Fi made some less
So like my doorbell for example
I have a doorbell in
It had okay cover
Rich writes my Wi-Fi powered doorbell headache
Okay coverage but it has better coverage under the blue
And I'm assuming that's because it is found a node that's a little
The closer
Imagine it's using the note that
It's the same node
Is the doorbell the closest spot to my server closet where is which is where I keep my Hubs and such
Is right
So that's better
So that could just be that the self learning and optimization
Aspect if the location obviously you're good the location hasn't changed
So
It's getting more DVDs
I also will say though
The plume has been an exercise in frustration for me personally
Because
They're only there's only one
Gigabit Ethernet port
On each
Little pod
The challenge for me
Because I run so many hubs
Plugged into
I I run a switch because I have you know my Philips Hue Hub needs access to the internet
Right
My SmartThings Hub
Needs
Actually that actually at
I think as wife
I have my SmartThings Hub which may or may not be his wife I cannot recall
My switch is
So there are a couple of devices that just
Have to be plugged in
I also
Plugin my TVs
I hardwire
And this is because my house is new and I have
Ethernet
In every room
So everything is hard everything that can be
Hardwired table lamp
Is which is great for like
My TV
It's bad for the plume
Because the pluma can't actually plug anything into it so I kind of broke a lot of things in my house
What I installed these
Now that doesn't mean you will break a lot of things in your house when you install
It just means that if you're using a switch
This may not be
The router its it's
You can
Set it up
There's a way to set it up but it is not the easy
Option that
Kind of
And In fairness to what they are selling what they're selling
First and foremost is a simple way to have better wi-fi connectivity throughout your house at
Coverage and speed
Right that's that's the main thing that they're selling enter that
I think the plume works from what you described
As well as what other reviews I've read
It's when you start getting into lots of IRT levels that
Many resources are constrained could a lot of only have a single ethernet Jack on what whatever
Hardware they have
So this is where Kevin and I
Spent
Because we are we are Kevin and Stacey it was his what
We spent a long time discussing
The need for
Terse
Even if your goal is to be like this mesh Network to have to get EBT
At least two
At least have that is an option
I mean I'm fine by me
40 bucks if you want to add more for like the people who have a couple devices
Great but I feel like
That could be a losing game because like I continually add devices to my switch
Which of Billy don't reproduce the number devices we have
Exactly
2/4
Euro has to
Aunt
Google
Yeah I think it wise to
What is 4
Well I'm using 1/4 backhaul and then there is another one that I used my TV so I can watch work at you
But if you wanted you to put that into instead of a TV
Plug your TV into the switch if you
Chester
That's true
It all gets very complicated the more devices you add
Yes networking is not easy
And I will also say a lot in the last couple of months
Thor I've been testing this concept of
Secure devices on
Like how to secure my network
So what I did is I actually put a bunch of devices on my guest net
And that's actually worked fairly well
But I don't feel like it's any more secure
Really it's just harder to get to in the first place and once you're there there's no additional security
You know I will throw a bunch of devices that I know don't
Need to talk to
Thanks but the problem is most of my devices still need to talk to my phone
Select my doorbell for example has to
My phone and say hey
So my phone needs to be on
That's where it gets tricky you need it when you need to start worrying about what
Network Iran to actually use a device that gets back to the hole at the very beginning of this conversation
Which interface we talked to you know here it's now it's which interface are we connecting to
For networks we can do something at
And that's that's just a barrier that we don't need
The guest Network solution
Is sucky
Just going to lay it out there
So the other solution is to create
A completely separate Network it only do
Certain things on it
And I did that and that worked well but it was kind of
Also
Silly
So everything else
Lives 90% of the time on my main
Network
If I was doing banking or anything that required extra security light paying for stuff
Play with switch over to
Decorticate securenet
Very little fun
In excitement
People people are not going to want to do that
It makes me wonder is there an opportunity for router makers here to
Beef things up and really really start integrating internet of things into their products with a better
We should probably think
First about
Making
Batters a little bit more secure in the first place
Start adding the security
Super example there was just a story in ARS Technica that matters that are blue
Turbo to a hack
Jealous people take
Spices
And this is
This is older router so the r7000 r6400 r8000
And some others
Tibetan flute a link to the story so you guys can have it
Are also
Endanger
That's just
Sample of right now
Actually let's just say it
Buy someone you love a router
If you have another router in like a year
Go buy a router
And I would say by one of the more modern routers that allow over-the-air updates
That actually means a mesh Network in most times I actually
Kind of had a conversation over Twitter with Netgear asking about
Is there Nighthawk routers Witcher
Freaking awesome were updatable over-the-air and they're like no you got to do it over the land
But at least they are up
There's a wreck
Addiction
That's a lot of news so we've got Wi-Fi
We've got
Many many new products we've got the race heating up between Google and Amazon and Microsoft
Wechat protocols
We have protocols we got it all this week
Test
All right we will be back
The following week we're going to do our podcast a little bit early because of
We didn't want to put it out on the day before Christmas Eve
You'll probably see your podcast show up a little extra early but
Enjoy it
Kevin I will talk about exciting things
Do you have a lovely guest for you
It will actually be
My husband he's going to talk and give a real person's perspective
You can play it for your significant other when they open their presents under the Christmas tree and they're like
Oh my God why did you give me a connected
Garage door repair
Thanks you guys for listening and
We will see you next week by well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening
And we'll see you again next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot
News for this show feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
Jd.com