Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today we have for you apron
Cohoes
Andrew allemann
That's right
This is a special occasion Kevin will be back with us next week
But Andrew is my husband
And today he would be playing the role of a smart home skeptic
Which
Actually I drew that's the role you play pretty much everyday
Right
ICandy eye candy around this household
It's hard not to
Skeptical
So Andrew just so you guys know in addition to my husband he is also a blogger and a podcaster himself
He blogs over at domain name wire about the domain industry
And he also has a podcast
Just about the same time
So let's get this started
You came on the podcast probably about nine months ago
And at that time
You're pretty
I meant to say ambivalent but you were kind of down on all the stuff that I brought into the house
You actually only like one thing I believe if I recall correctly and that was
The SmartThings home hub that I brought in and programmed with our blinds
And had them going
Up and down on a schedule
And since then I've taken that away from you
Yes
You have sorry about that
But
I'm hoping that
We brought some other Gadgets in the house
Are there any things right now that you actually like
About her smartphone
Well to me the whole game changer the thing that shifts this to something that
Is practical is the Amazon Echo
For me being able to
Use voice commands
To control lights for example
Is great compared to having to open up
Right if you have to press a few buttons or find your phone and kind of losses
Its effectiveness
I mean that
Huge
I frankly think that
As far as this ecosystems concern that could be a big game-changer
You've got the Hue tap
Which is nice because you can control Smart
Device without a game getting out your phone
That's like the Amazon Echo is
Is that it's a big deal
All right and
In our house we mostly use the echo
Go to
Turn off the lights downstairs
But
Do you ever use it or could you
You see using it for any
Oh yeah those are the main things and again it's one of those things that works part of the time I don't know if that's
Alexis salt
Echo
Corset
Lights
Are we having
I could see myself using it to for example control the fly
It's on the other side
Just be lazy
And tell it to do that so if there was a way to cook that into the
Do the blinds make them clothes when it's hot out or son of your whereabouts
Watching TV
I think that could be valuable as well really AT&T
Smart
Connected devices if you can control them from that
Voices just much
Easier in most circumstances
Then
Using multiple table menus on a phone to pull up what you're looking for by that time
You may as well have
Found the remote
Or
Dundee accent
Got it
Alright so
Any other things that you're kind of like
Thinking oh this is a nice to have in the house lissy
Connect two thermostats
I feel like
You may not touch the nest every day but I feel like that's a device that
You certainly use and
Yeah and it's very useful
2f say you're out of town
I'm at the office
I mean obviously it'll go to auto away but
But you know the program that
And then when I'm about to head home program
Again
On the phone change its go to a cooler temperature I think that's
That's valuable
I'm so certainly the
The thermostats are good
What else we have the blinds when you actually had to look up
I actually
Can hook them into Alexa
Cynthia boe's wink or SmartThings
Okay
See I am I pulled it out
It's going to be a birthday present book
Looked work again
I was often very long time
You hate keys
And
I know where front door doesn't really work with a lot of smart locks out there
But do you have a sense of would you prefer to have a lock that just opened when you got
Near it with your phone in your pocket or would you
I know you like keypad lock
So do you have a sense I know how you feel about
Kind of connected lock
Here's the thing
There's got to be
In addition to having that
I don't know what you called but what you walk up to today
Automatically
Locks unlocks
There has to be a way to do it manually without having the kids while so a great example would be the Locklear downstairs
We had to keep an eye on
And you can do it
Is there a number of times I run down to the garage
I don't have my phone
You know and so and I don't have the key
So I'd like to build
It's super fast and easy ride to type in a four-digit code unless your hands are full
So I also question and maybe there's an answer for this but
Take for example our garage
Not our
Electric garage door right
Butter other
The door to the garage
Okay so if it unlocks things for when you pulled into the garage at automatically unlock the door
Where that went from our garage to our house
It did now I'm going to tell everybody right now we have the Kwikset Z-Wave
Connected locks
With a keypad
So
They're both connected and they have to keep
Spencer Locke and yes we did have it hooked in through SmartThings
And you had a presents tag in your car so when you drove up
The present stag
Triggered
That lock
To the garage
To unlock
So that was helpful
Why do you always take away the things that I like I said I don't get it
It's not because I hate you
On the presents tag actually ran out of battery
And I didn't know
I could I could put that back on
Because the locks are back on
And the other thing is
I took
The
That the blinds are controlled by a Z-Wave controller
It is a bit gimpy
To install it's not actually
It's not recognized by a lot of
Of the hubs that we have is not recognized by any of them
So it's hard to install
And so I uninstall whenever I uninstall it to reinstall it
Takes
A little more time and effort and
I usually
End up unprogramming are blinds and that
Cost $8
Come back and fix
And then you get sad and grumpy
Yeah yeah I was a little suspect on
Idea of
Yes I guess in as you walked out the door was unlocked and
When your presence wasn't there
It's interesting
You know
I don't know
Tesla
Now that I've seen how that works for the Tesla or you just leave then
Turns off and takes care of all that.
That's kind of Handy
The other thing I like
In-N-Out in its being skeptical at first week
The Chamberlain garage
Or wear it
Where you can turn it
That's one item or being able to shut
The door or open it
From the phone is help
For to use cases first of all in our case
Beef cuts
The garage downstairs and then you walk upstairs
The house
And so
Getting alert that you forgot to shut the garage door and not having to go down
Outside of stairs again
To shut it
It's helpful.
And any other thing
Someone needs to get inside the garage for some
Be able to grant them that access when you're not home
Fat is healthy
All right
See so now discuss the things you do like
What are the things that you're like
Stacy
You try this out or
You know maybe if you can purchase it and I still don't know why you
I think my main gripe is the same it was
Before what you see things just don't work out
In the Box
There's some there's something that doesn't work and maybe
Because our house
This is a test
Items interior made lyrics
Fighting with each other
Redfin
Even for a while it seemed like our lights
You're working
Then the ones that were connected into those GE light bulbs that are connected into
Weak now
You know how they work
Part of the time
Well the one where I guess
They actually were connected through the
Shoe-in for some reason the Hue connection
To the GE link bulbs
Through the Amazon Echo
Suddenly didn't
And I'm not sure actually
Savannah
Switch them over
To the wink
Except for that one
Wish weekend
Broken
Defective so you've got
You spend 20 bucks on these balls
Which is a lot cheaper
Hughes but then
He's got three months later one of them the Z-Wave
Stop
Thankfully Home Depot is really easy
It was
Nicki sorry
I told the lady at Home Depot the Wi-Fi
I don't think it matters
Any idea
But I was talking about she just wrote as return light
Turn on
Please work now right I mean
If we say Alexa turn off living room lights
I mean it seems like
20% of the time it doesn't work
I would say
That's too high I think it's like five
5% of the time it doesn't work but I think
They just didn't
Update
That should help
So I haven't seen it not working
But yes you're right
No voice recognition seems to be
Getting better
I member at first
Understand what we were saying but
That really anything to me on
On Alexis we're going upstairs and Beyond
Turn off downstairs
And at that point we're halfway up the stairs
Light from upstairs we can see so we don't trip and everything downstairs goes off
So
What would your advice be to someone
Like
If you're hanging out with your friends and
And someone mentions like hey I think I'm going to buy a connected device or I'm interested in home automation
I'm other than
Maybe you tell them talk to Stacy or maybe sick God don't talk
What would you tell them about
What they should buy
Cindy Pickett
Open and I think that use are cool and
They're fairly simple
I mean if you do have a hug
That you have to plug in
But they're fairly simple underneath party
If nothing else
Yes there are some cool practical things
Having them go on when you're out of town
And be able to control them when you're walking away it's on
But I think those are nice
And it's kind of all in a box
Solution to try to get that wet three bulbs in the hub
So that's interesting
And then the other would probably be locked
I think we did some presents check but then then you're getting into
SmartThings in a hub as well so it gets complicated there but I know people that do like
Short-term rentals on houses or have people come in and eat them to be able to come in
To do something real quick
I get them you know one time use passcode or something like that
Status Seekers
Practical
But I probably start
And I know you say you're just get frustrated when he talked about light bulbs all the time but it's the simplest easiest example
Okay
Not like a thermostat
You don't feel like we're getting there
Value out of are connected thermostats or anyting
Well that's a good point
Yeah I forgot I forget about those beans
Connected and maybe that's
Because they judge
Is worthwhile
Right I don't
The only time I log into the
Is from same iPhone in
When something is happening right
That's a good point that's a fairly easy
On ramp ends well I guess it worked sort of easy to install
We had to get a little bit of help there
You know anyone can do that right anyone can
Screw in a lightbulb with a lot of jokes
Anyone can
And I think anyone could just
Put the
Plug it into the back of the router
I really think that's easier right you're not
Installing sump
10%
Okay
Well it looks
Let's go back to the thermostats and
My latest thing because it has been
The hotter months of the year here in Texas
We've been talking about different
Products that help you optimize your
Air conditioner
Sing in bioptimizers I'm not talking about
Not like in the nest
More in the way of making sure that you
Your air conditioning is running most efficiently
So there's a product from Everson called Comfort guard
And what this is you have to have a professional installer coming out
And what they do is
They install about $100 worth of sensors into
Your furnace your docs and your
Air conditioning unit that sits outside your house
And then you pay like an 8 to $10 monthly fee
And Those sensors gather data
And it's like a Predictive Analytics kind of service for your home so it's supposed to be
Checking all of the data from Those sensors and saying hey it looks like your air conditioner is only running at 60% a fish
Efficiency right now
You should call someone and have them come out or
Maybe because the installer who installed it as hell
Contract with you
Movie they come out
Come out and look at it
There's also
Some kind of interesting new things tied to data coming out
Soon
I can't talk about all this
But then we also had our HP AC guy come out
Just the other day for a regular maintenance check
And he told us some cool stuff
So angry when I talk about some of that
I think the more interesting thing about what he's obviously he has
Incentive
This guy doesn't think about it that way right
Attack but
I think it was interesting what you said and I think it's interesting because we
I feel like some of the things you tell me about
Smart Home
Connected devices kind of get ahead of them
Sounds right they aren't solving a huge problem and so
I would question in this case is like well
Love you so
Almost two years at the guy at 250
Right is everything is working fine
Cleaning jobs outside
Lead staff into the each of our units
He's like well
You know installing something
She just get
If you just get fairly regular maintenance on these you're going to
Catch it
In advance
You don't even a leak on something isn't something that overnight
You know it loses all its power
Or something like that so I guess the question is how much it cost
And how much
It's ongoing
And having a professional come out and install it
Ali really fixing that big of a problem
Also said the fact that we had both an ecobee n&s so we had connected thermostats he was like
Is news things detect a problem or an anomalous use
They will also let you know
Which I thought was kind of
As well
And then
Yeah I haven't I haven't
If they would actually
Do
I was I was a little curious about that myself I was like
I did not think they would do that
But
We also running the
Bruker things from curb
So we're checking our energy usage
Can real time
And that actually will send us a notification if
Fitzy's vet
Were using
In the curb is need but you know there's another one where
You know you have to have an electrician come out I'm sure I don't know how much it is but I'm sure it's expensive and it's like well even from
Cost savings perspective right eye mean
Maybe it's cuz we don't
Use a lot of
Energy relatively speaking by
How much are you going to say versus how much
Does it cost
Is one of those things that
I think when I see some devices
Ashley
Prevent something
Mildly bad from happening or
We save you money
It's felt like a back.
5 years
I'm probably not interested
Wow C on an air conditioning I feel like
Because those things are like $9,000
It feels like well
If something was to go wrong that would actually break it and make you have to replace entire thing will that's one thing
Oh look it's not working as well
Needs to be even if you don't have anything
Is my utility bill
So much higher than usual at that point then you pick up the phone you have someone come out
And they say I'll look that's because of this
This is dirty or this isn't working
Air compressor sailing
IFixit
You know most
Townhomes for 500 bucks
In that
Wehrli
Did something happen
Replace buffer units especially
If it's on older ones
Is Tommy going to happen anyway
That's true and I get very excited about
Possibilities of all of this data
Because I'm looking so far ahead but you're right as a homeowner it seems very
It's a very difficult
So I guess we'll see
So any final thoughts
481 in this industry
You is a guy
It's kind of like
Probably
Way more mainstream buyer of all of this Tech than anybody
Spike especially me
And Kevin
What is your advice to
People who are
Building this in
I say make it simple
Make sure there is a very easy to understand rli
And then make it work out of the box
By the time it ships
It just has to
Castaway
You know I think it seems like an and I know you get plenty of Alf
Test your first words have been said
I got to ask what about your data private
Are you worried about that
Particularly
You know the only thing it cameras are the one thing that concerns me a little bit I like the idea of cameras on the outs
Dial home
Because you have some breaks on or something then hopefully you can get the picture then that doorbell we have is kind of neat
Morrison walks up to it at
He could take some video of them
I mean I don't know what the nest
Is going to get
That is going to really cause a privacy issue
I guess I could see one of these being used in a court case when someone says they were somewhere and they weren't
Yeah it's mostly cameras and making sure that my
Privacy
You know nothing
All right
Thank you so much for coming on the show today and
I'm glad to be a fill in for Kevin but I'm sure your guests will be throwing
USAC next week
Oh nonsense they love their perspective from
Guy who doesn't
Sincerely. I was going to say no much
But that's not the right word
The guy who doesn't necessarily
Love the Smart car
Alright just let me know
And I appreciate you inviting me
There you go I'd like
Your paycheck
It's in the mail
All right
Thank you
Stay tuned for
Our Guest this week who is
Nandini Nayak who is going to talk to us about building Living Services and how big companies and
And small companies are going to have to adapt to having connected devices everywhere
Hi everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and today my guess
West Nyack
She is the design strategy leader at
Yours
And she's also for the time being heading up there San Francisco Design Studio
Hainan how are you doing
I'm good baby how are you
I am awesomeness
So I'm really excited
Need to talk to you because you have actually
When I met you a couple months back you actually put into words very eloquently
A concept that I've been thinking about for a while which is this idea of living service
Do you want to
Kind of talk about what that is
Let's read
You don't Living Services in
Fjord has talked
I mean all of you guys talk about the internet
And you know the fact that you know you can have
But I think what
We believers
The more interesting aspect of
Is technology it should be a fun holiday in April
A new kind of service
A new kind of living
My dad
Give me about
Digital Services becoming more human-like
You know more responsive to contacts more
A meeting with Kim and expect
So we called it the era of living service
Galaxy
Age of nginx where you know finally he had access to.
Assign you think
Computing has become
So every day
Double X back
Have
Everything
Begin to kind of connect together to help us live
Better life
Okay and that's
That's a very nice overview
And I think one of the things that I thought was really
Compelling about it
Is that it offers this kind of sense of customization
So this idea that
You not only design a product to put in people's homes
But what you're doing is your
Again building service
And the service is
Unique 4
Maybe individuals maybe it's a family that lives in the home and consumes the service
I guess it could be a corporation we can talk about that
So you're developing this
Service but
It doesn't what what I think is kefir
Businesses is that it doesn't end
With a purchase
The product is going to exist
Far and Away Beyond
Purchase
So it could go
To be a washing machine that I
Can I buy
But I'm also going to
Consume
Some sort of maybe it's a replenishment service with it
Or maybe it is
I don't know
Maybe it's a warranty that's actually a little bit more Interactive
Can you give us an example of some of these
Living Services
As you see it
Anything fundamentally living from 2:40
Talking about is the digitization of a
Which means
Yak everyday devices of washing machine your strength
I'm eating your counselor your fork me have some level of ability to change the environment
To capture some data and also respond in
And that's what your he's object by themselves
Are not the product
Human in Chinese
Big service
Let's talk about the washing machine
You know whenever I'm in
Add doing laundry
Weather I have all the different detergent I use for different
Imagine of
Washing machines in the future.
Determining whether I have enough
That I am running out of something one of them
I'll be able to on again
Kind of
To my shopping list
Signal the brain to send it over to me
I don't even have to
Drink about
Odoo I have enough
Magically
Is alternates a mundane task
Add button to my day-to-day life
Austin & Ally I Think About You
All you may think about whether my mother is out of
Not because she's a diabetic
I'm so I need to make sure
The truck after the hard product
Rubbish
Participation in my life not just in the washing machine
Help me deal with e
Cast of Walking Dead
Eventually you may even think about whether the
The interface that that washing machine has could do other thing
Like in my laundry room I have other things going on like how often do I need to do laundry
Why do not be with my son.
Don't we have settings that he does everything in one pile
I want you to point to what you were talking about
Lutetia Vision specialize themselves to individual
Do. You know
When I walk into the room
He decided settings for how I might
You can imagine how this
Would extend into the future in terms of
How
The environment
The ecosystem
Begins to
Connect to individual to a present
Iron Sheik
Skin challenge around
Okay
In these examples sound very
Consumer-oriented in maybe you cannot just consumer but consumption oriented
It's so I'm picking Amazon Dash
For example are Amazon's replenishment services
Are very
Nascent maybe steps to this
But let's think about can you bring Living Services outside of
Me buying more stuff
If that makes sense
Because right now this feels very much
Align
Buying things that I need right now but
Let's take it
To something else
Let's think about the working
Doing people are working today you know most companies have
Songs about the future
Practices you know you're coming into second time and time you should have certain types of
Are you doing
Differentiate between
How I like to work which is how they see me like to work
A weather alert during the morning times where I think he likes you
Standardized
What please
Luminosity be helping productivity
50 company
How people need to be supported
Highly cognitive
And you know how you be set up for that type of work
14 ammo
Begin to have dentures in
Doing a certain type of what
It's not too much consumption oriented it's actually
What might be the cops number
Even in the washing machine
Ecosystem for back
I think you think about it as
What is a human intentions
Supported
And how do you support them
Catching that I take notes about that person that have it
That College
Tossed and turned
And you'll begin to see
You don't work environment adjusted.
Think about it
Audrey
Printing Supplies similar to house washing machine
Usher
And I can think of in the home
Do you want to leave the laundry room which
Crazy specific
But you can even think of
Gosh is
It's my my home can read my contacts
Clues appropriately
It could figure out o
Josh Stacy right now is getting ready to cook time I'm reading the symbols she's
She's coming into the kitchen she's turning on her work lights right above the
The counter
You know she's she's washing her hands
She's made like six trips to the refrigerator and then to the pantry
Those are all pretty indicative of
Setting her prep getting her prepped together so then
My kitchen can start adapting itself
My kitchen
Settings which is
In addition that lighting there's
Music I like
Be awesome if Mike my robotic Butler could bring me my glass of cooking wine
Yeah but you know we'll get there my Amazon
Echo could start you know pulling up the recipe that I sent
And you know I can see these
Kind of things start
To develop and that is not consumption that is purely
A service that would help me
It leads to consumption
Hopefully the consumption of delicious food
And in 20 minutes or less
And I think that one of the important things you like to do
Stop thinking about Industries
Louisiana find them today right
Unhide products
I just because we are talking about supporting human pattern
You probably think about ecosystems off services that make Carson
Okay so like in that example and ecosystem
Is it a kitchen ecosystem so then I might need
Because I don't have all appliances from one Bender I would need my Samsung refrigerator to talk to my Bosch dishwasher
In my Delta faucet
And my
I don't know who makes my pots and pans they're not connected but
You know
Getting all that plus I'm going to want my cookbooks and recipes to be communicating also it probably to
My fitness stuff but also to my family's because
It would be nice to know what they've been going through that day or maybe what they got on track
Cuz if my husband is planning on a
13 Mile run tomorrow to help train for his Marathon
Maybe I can cook something that helps him prepare for that
And you may know that he's planning for a dirty mind even before he
Like you might be going on the lunch tomorrow
And I guess you're kind of also means that you know that
H-2b
On that allows you to connect
Steve individualized
Based on what
Specific intent
But then how did it connect to all of the others
In the context
Destiny Achievers and what is the band what is
What is blinding
I think that's going to be an interesting
Evolution of
What brand small atomizer
Taking that you're going to be an interesting time to examine how landing page
Well let's talk about that because right now I see
If I think about Brandon that context especially in the home I've got like
We'll just works with x
So if that works with homekit
Works with nest
It works with whatever brand is out there
But if I'm Ge
Or if I'm bi
Or
And that's in the consumer space if I'm in the Enterprise space if I'm IBM or if I'm Cisco
How do I build
A brand
Around
These experiences
Do I build a brand around experiences or do I build a brand around
Products
Or servicer
I don't even know Nan help
My God
Yeah I think I can
Interesting question
If you want to bring the Vans and I think we've talked a bit about
You know how many
True blance can a human
Have a relationship with
Did she was in the vacuum
Don't believe any money Branch services
And sometimes it's not
Shingles
That's media
So I can if you depend upon what
Platforms in Ark
And whether branding becomes
Important enzyme the recognition of a concussion
Method of how you do things
Is the collection of brands that
Show me Product brands have to figure out how they become
Experience branch
Experience brands that
DD's Connections in the mostest
Recognize
Rachel's example
Infuriating that donkey
Competing products
Guess what
Not going to be
That DJ Jason sees the connection
The collections of services that you recognize
Add something that participates in your life
So we can be have answer to that
Yes but I think you do
Transformational time when
So we're going to have
A reduction in the value
Brands that sounds like
And what's going to happen is we're going to have a
Quote unquote living brand
It's going to be kind of experiential
And it's going to be
These brands are going to be these
Curated
I guess we'll call it a platform
Of these atomized services
An experience
So then my question to you
Is
As I'm building out these Platte
Forms
Does this living brand sodas
Monolithic
Platform
Are they choosing
Who they play with
Is there no like real interoperability or are they going to be doing the hard work of making
Things in Rockford
And as the consumer does that mean we're going to have to choose between
Establish cluster
Brandon
Experiences
As opposed to kind of building our own
Yeah I think more and more you know
Even though
Number of Living Services.
I'm available
You want to have
Knowing Translate
Cuba Cuba
Play similar to
Think about it like a travel agent
I need you to delete all the time
Travel
Arby's song
Booking on a
Locations
Looking on this device
Travel
Some point to point
My home travel experience of going to a particular
You may begin to see Airbnb may become
Because
Deactivating a
Part of that experience but they are beginning to look at json
They may combine with other
You may think about Airbnb
Maybe have some flexibility in picking
Chuggington from different brands
I think it would be interesting to
Experian
And then how you
Ida
Give up control to one of those bands
Insecurities
Kayaking
Ultimate Ninja potions that you want to have some flexibility of control over
Chess master
I think it would be interesting to see how this notion
Living Brands come to life
Where your total expense maybe a combination of brand with one or two
Okay that makes sense
It does that
Make sense
All right into if you're an established company
As opposed to
A startup
How do you kind of
If you want to
Develop a living service
How do you canoe
Get there
And then do these companies established companies have an advantage in establishing a living brand
Orteza startup
Don't you think about it
Create a living cell
Creative Living Services that fundamentally is that you have
No
I'm going to beaches
The contact
Read how the service was rendered
Who is being deported
You know how do you know the contacts on an ongoing basis
She knows nothing about individual
How they connect you to other
One aspect because at the node
The other dimension
How do you been
Lexor adjust your service
To take the signals
That you're getting
Dimensions the intersection of them
You can think of about 15 ground for the diesel
Pokemon company I think it may be a bit
May not have the history of how they have
Known
If you would like to disappoint their customer base
But I think.
Juanita Jackson would be
Is that they should not just think about themselves
Show me things about
How is that correct laying into a human
Experience in Iowa
The education Keys Lounge
Amal Fuller capabilities
It allows you to even have an API on a connection
Something more
Xiamen company
Think about
Something Beyond
What I'm trying to design
Designing
Born in a warm environment
Jupiter Center in to figure out
You know how warm is going to be
Pikachu
Adjust
So if you are going to be
Maybe I can offer you at
Starting a new company
Begin to think about
Products in terms of services on living furniture
Benefits
Ashanti
For more established companies I think the challenges they have
Lots and lots of data
And absolutely don't know
How to extract the patterns
The one of the things that job to think about
Understand how to
Understand what in the data
Are there
Insights from the data that can be used to create new living
And you could also ask yourself
What contextual information to enhance the product or service that
I'm already creating
Because the tunnel vision into this is how I think about
Think about how to
Change the Viewpoint of how they think
So I think there's more transformation
Big companies that can be done from the start
That makes sense
And
When it comes to building
A living
Brand
Do bigger companies have it
Easier
I think because we have an established brand it would seem that they may have an advantage
Depend upon with the keeping up with the
Straight Talk
I can think of companies are beginning to see that the Conte just got to come
Experience
Movie back in action
Where did beginning to do mashups with smaller
A new version of intellij idea
Can you use that brand Treasures
Stewie evil tulip
Dog in the state
I think that extends
Are you conceited a positive
On the other hand
If you don't
Expected Market that you're beginning to do that
Go lights
Late shows to be a benefit
As well as
How fast you're moving
Man thank you so much for joining us
Today I really appreciate it
And I've learned a lot thank you for having me
That's it for this week's podcast please
Join us again next week
But the Internet of Things podcast
Thank you for listening