Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
My co-host
Kevin tofel
We're going to talk about the brand new
Free to talk about for the best switch for the
Sabbatical Miracles thanks to the Internet of Things
Trouble at SmartThings
And our guest today is
Matt Manley
A fiord who's going to be talking to us about
Wearables and specifically designing smart jewelry
Which
You like what you like I was going to say
You still wear that by the way
The ring way that's what I meant to mention this like two weeks ago in the show but they now have a bracelet
Call the Aries bracelet that
Is
Very attractive
It's a thin gold band with a jewel in it and the Jewel is just like the Ringley tools so it's got the Bluetooth
The LEDs and it connects to your smartphone notifications
Be at the very attractive bracelet on your wrist
And
I was really excited about it
I believe you can order it for $195 during the
A priori
And yes early supporters
20% off
When you said the price 195 I cringed a little bit
But but but
This technically is
Jewelry that's not just a notification light.
Is designed to be
Jewelry yes and it
It's something that
I tend to wear so the actual and I should tell you the list price is actually
If you really think about this you should
With the ring
I don't wear it everyday but I do wear it
But I want to look nice
The nice thing about the Aries bracelets
Probably have mint
Is it is also acts as a fitness tracker
That makes a big difference
So yes
Sorry my bad
What is a step tracker
Plus provides all these notify
Vacations and
Movies in October
So later on this year you're going to actually be able to make payments
With it because they have this
Tie up with MasterCard
This is like a feature-packed device for people like me who don't like to carry their smartphone maybe in their paw
Pockets around with them all the time or who don't want to wear something that looks like technology
Right
This is pretty
It's it's very attractive
If I would wear it
What notifications are you getting right now on your ring wake that you probably would get also with us
Just like your diesel for emails if it were certain
Because the Ringley is so much more personal
I use it more for it so any time I get a text
A phone call
I also use it for Uber notice
Applications so if especially because if you're I'm waiting around like
And it's dark and weird outside I want to be like distracted by my smartphone
So when they River arrives my
And I tend to get Ubers like leaving very loud places like a bar or place like that n
You can't hear
The phone buzzing like
You can actually see that that's not nice
Feedback it vibrates
You can also see it because it glows I think my
Turn the LED
But you program it yourself so you can do Facebook notifications UK
Twitter
Email
It's not like
Massive amount of Airstream of notifications you're selecting which specific ones
You want them
Is it limited to certain numbers a certain like
Can you only do three different types of medications for samples and you have four
Different levels of haptic feedback it's like
1 vibration
2 vibrations
Before
You can make as many as you want I think after a while you might be
Hangouts
The other final thing I'll say about this
This is
They have a setting called Your Inner Circle
Armada Center
You can actually turn off notifications except for certain
People from your contacts
Craigslist
So then if your liking a super Inn
Meeting
Only distraction you're going to get from that thing is like
If your husband calls or if your daughter School calls would be my exam
I love it I think it's really applicable I don't wear it everyday it is expensive
It's probably one of those
It's a it's an add-on
I like the way it looks like actual
End
I do think the future of wearables is probably really cheap electronics stuck into every
Yeah yeah and we'll talk about that actually
So
And you know you could do in cufflinks to
Guys
Stay tuned
Okay
After that day
Fruitful day crash
Let's talk about routers
Woohoo
Routers we have to talk about routers
For two reasons one is because I'm sending back one that you loaned to me that you use in the past
But more importantly because another router company just got some
Funding dollars
I from Amazon
Which is
Honey
Saginil how many sides are there I don't know they're not sir
Six sides
Hexagon
Hexagons in your choice of colors white gray
Beige brown and orange
Aluminum
Make sense make sense
Lisa Rinna
Previously they're still available for pre-order they're very similar to the Eero devices which
We talked about before we'll talk about them with more 3 minutes
There's a lot less expensive at least get the pre-order level I know we talked about the prices before but just real quick they're 149
My First Single device 299 for 3 pack
As the police the pre-order price is cuz they're not quite available yet you can go on Amazon get them
I'll get on the list and pay for them I guess
But the years are 199 and
Side for a single in
3 pack soap
Big price difference at least
Initially put
How much did they take out I think it was
I was thinking how much did they raise
2.5 million.
Kneeling with a bunch of factors including though
Amazon
Excel
Yeah former AT&T CEO
Results are back
And its founder Paul Judge one of the founders
Is
Big security guy he actually found a pin drop
Security
And
You know he's
The firm is based in in I believe Atlanta
And the idea with Luma is that
It improves your coverage using a mesh Network much like Eero does
But the big selling
When is going to be
Cheap rental car
Yes they have a really nice UI for
I I think it actually is done by
RPG and Chee
So you can
10 of Define the levels of
Access your kids can have
The Eros
Today
Hopefully that will change
They actually have kind of
Did they have much more granular permissions like you can turn off devices after certain times and that's
And in addition to the financing at they just to have sale serving out to
Major hires Matt Duffy who was with Sonos and apple one time
How do you spell head of supply chain out for Luna and they have a new VP of engineering
Who comes from AirWatch and VMware in his path
So happy
Yeah I think is in
Emm Enterprise Mobility management system company
Yeah but but you got VMware as well
Zachary so I'm so you're right 60,000 I didn't realize that I'm looking at the numbers right now
30000 through customer pre-orders and another 30,000 through retail
Channel so
He plans to intervene in June so
If you wait until Junior
You're probably going to pay a lot more because
Is the pricing
We'll go up to what looks like 199 and 499 for the one device or three devices
Which is exactly the same as that you're also if you want to get in
Tulum azerli
Now's the Time to do it to save yourself a bunch of money
So I got to ask
What did you think
Hero
Yes
So this weekend I ripped out the Eros because you loan in the meeting I don't know two or three weeks ago I replaced the Google
P******
With the Eros
And guess what
I got a fever and the only prescription is more mesh Network
Oh man it was great it was
Great I mean I have my onhub back now and I already do
Miss
Average wind speed in some areas of my house that I had
With a 3-pack of Eros that you
Got for me to borrow and
Review
I almost want to send them back but I have to
By those by those Lumas now
Well that's a thing I mainly because if I went and bought the Eros now
It's 199 for what I reviewed
Yeah they were fantastic
Everything Titus 1:15 actually know about pre-ordering the lumos because I can get
Hopefully the same experience
At a much lower price but we will see
They were fantastic I couldn't say enough I did see some people complaining about them either reviewers or peep
Bottom
You know they're like I don't see a difference
You know it's so tricky with networking because there's so many variables every configurations differ
Every house or business
Is different architecture early materials are different
I don't know it my house all I can tell you is they worked
Great
I
Well second that I did notice though and they fixed it
But I did notice that when my
Internet access when offline
It took them
A little extra longer to come back up
Cuz sometimes during the day my internet get
Would get kind of spotty
Fix now but
When I was happening I would be offline and it would take them another five or 10 minutes to all boot back up again that was a
Yeah that's certainly frustrating I I did not have any I have FiOS here at the house 150 megabits up
Up and down never
How many outages while I was testing me so I can't I can't speak to it
I don't know
Oh yeah
So let's talk about
Best switch out on the market today
Because The Wirecutter
Actually put out
The guide
To the best smart home Outlets when they were they called everybody and calls it a switch but you and I know it is a
Outlet
Right now these are
Technically switches are
Trellis Spa
That's okay
Yes they reviewed I don't know 7 or 8
For people who are not familiar with The Wirecutter that's what they do they they pick a device type
And they going yet
All the different competitors
Anime
Spend hours and hours and hours testing
And tell you what they think is the best in its class
So
I don't agree with
There
Zyrtec actually
I do too actually cuz I have one
This is a controversial I will say
Yeah they picked up Belkin WeMo Insight switch
We've talked about it before
You send me one I think makes my birthday to work all day was Christmas
Cuz I like
Thank you. Do you still have one or multiple cities or not
Amazon sale for Lake
40 bucks on Amazon
Actually goes on sale
Regularly
Keep an eye out
You know we used it actually 2
Find out how much energy are fish tank consume
Because I felt like
Consuming a lot of
I realized it
I can actually plug it into the fish tank light and only the 50
And now I'm going to turn off when I tell
Play Echo to turn off downstairs at night
Is an awesome
This does integrate with Echo obviously am with if this then that
It's great because it's
Cross-platform so whether use iOS or Android you can use the app
The app will is Stacy just said show you the amount of electricity consumed
Buy anything plug into the switch
It's 80 Wifi switch
Just hope the folks know that you don't need a
Don't need a hub or anything it's it works directly with an app
But it does Heather's integration
If it was a downside I would say
Tumi
It's just a single outlet
You know it would be nice if I had I can connect two things to this was just a single 3 prong outlet
It is although it's much smaller than the original
It doesn't take up your entire Outlet
It's also very sensitive the switch on top
Find myself
Oh this is something to note because I plugged it into a fish tank
When WeMo did its firmware updates
It would actually turn the fish tank off
And one day that happened in none of us noticed
Everybody to bed in
Thermometer
This is not a
The heater
That one off to in frozen fish
Yes we came to
Very sluggish fish than exmoor
Morning so
Get into something.
Fishdom
That would not be good
Some of the other ones they tested should we just at least mention us
Idevices
That was a runner-up by the way
And it's $40
Set a little cheaper and if your home kit family
Go for it cuz it also has a night light that has a little LED strip that changes colors
Some of the other ones in the competition that they
Tested but they didn't add to their best Paycor runner-up was the
Connectsense smart outlet
Not her that when I say it's the most expensive switch they test it so I don't know how much
It cost
So connectsense is a Internet of Things
Division of a larger
Actually interviewed Adam Justice they're smart home.
Related to some apple stuff on the show before
People who care about Wi-Fi
Should know about them because they make a lot of wifi-connected sensors
Like water
Water sensors that some other things and
It's nice because they're Wi-Fi they're not like zigbee or Z-Wave so you don't need a hug
Pecan to them
Is they are super
You know if you want to go out
Do the guys you should look
Gotcha yeah I'm looking these are $80
Switch on Amazon right now
What is a 82 Outlet
Bible say that
And does have him connect to
Certification
So who else had a look at the iHome isp5
They say was the only
Homekit compatible device they tested that has an Android app so
Obviously you can't use the homekit bit but at least
If you have an Android device have Android you can still use the switch
So that's good but
Play problems with it in homekit
So that's
Why didn't didn't make the cut
Feeling we all know
But they have a DSP w215
It just rolls off the tongue
Bluetooth
What is a Bluetooth plugin
Witches
So they're using Avion
Which is a back-end for actually some of I believe it's ge's light switches to Bluetooth powered light switches
It's a Bluetooth mesh
I haven't been thrilled with the performance of any of the Bluetooth mesh devices that I've tried so far
So it becomes a challenge if you a don't have enough of them in your home
Create an actual mass in b
If you get too far away from it from your phone
You can actually control it
So depending on
Besides your house or
What you want to control it
Becomes kind of like
Forsook
Knock knock
Hidden rounding out the list with the Enemy
SP 2101w
Comes up with these names
I suppose yes
They said it'd be knocked down to the bottom of the list cuz it was the only one they tested that doesn't offer any sort of smart home integration
What I don't see though is
Like there are antech
Make something
Switches
Did actually
Tie into the SmartThings platform so they didn't try any of those
And maybe it's because they only work with SmartThings although there's a b switches sound like
Not really
Lowe's actually has some smart
Consider
Oh I probably know why cuz they're not wife
Bluetooth
These were all hub
Consider make sense
Zulily
And
I don't know if you remember but I'm super keen on Zulily and they are
Bee smart Outlets that have the presence monitor
And it is I like
Yeah
I thought they were fun
They've actually since we last talked about them integrated with Philips Hue
So now like
Your Hue bulbs can come on when you enter the room
Which is kind of nice it's not just anything plugged into the outlet
So that feels like something they should probably
Very different
I'm betting you could reach out to them and make that happen
Yeah
So
Okay
And
That's kind of the
The Smart Switch you should buy
Moving right along we've got news from
I know the medical world
So
This is kind of a wacky story
It sounds I think cooler than it really was
But basically the story is
Intuit
A seizure
And doctors actually used his
Fitbit
See if they were able to give him
Some medicine to help bring down his heart rate
So
Just saved his life
That may be overstating it
Little Foot
So what happened is he came in after having a seizure
And
I noticed that he had a drill
Fibrillation
I'm so super fast heart rate
Heartbeat that
Is a regular
And
They have medicine they can give you
To treat that if
It's not a chronic issue
So what they did is say with the skies permission cuz he was up in conscious
Does Fitbit data to see if his heartbeat was always that wacky
Him and I found out today
It wasn't and it was because of the onset of the seizure
That his heartbeat at all
Call crazy
They were like
We could probably give you this medal
And that is the story
Actually I think I'm looking at the story now and I heard I seen the headlines
I'm just going to call that the doctors decided to reset his heart rate with electrical cardioversion
So
The Gamers app or something now
You're right
Yeah I was reading about this
This is this is why we don't talk medicine too much
The drive specified
Yeah yeah
Yeah so
I mean they're taking that just what the device is showing at that I'm looking at the guy but
As you said they're looking at his
The day that
It had collected
And that gave them the PetSmarts in the data
Decide what to do next
So it brings up some interesting questions the first one
Which for me is
These things are notoriously inaccurate so
I don't know how I feel about that
You can learn a lot from the trends
So let's let's say in certain situations you don't need 100% accuracy and when we say these things are not accurate
A lot of them
Have some glitches here and there or they're like 95% as accurate as a better actual
Heart rate monitor
That's good enough to get Trends and I think give them like in this case give the doctor's information they need to make a smart decision
So
Also speaking of Medicine
Because I thought this was really cool last
Was
Pfizer
You may have heard of
Lots of drugs
Teamed up with IBM
To basically build a Parkinson's monitoring
I'm going to call it a service because
It's not out yet
It's this isn't a theoretical we're talking about its age
And it's not one thing
So basically what they want to do is they want to wait
Monitor Parkinson's patients 24/7
Various different aspects of
You know how a patient's feeling
So they can start creating personalized treatment regimen
Which I think is really interesting
Also think it's really hard so I reached out to Pfizer to ask him a little bit more about this
Cuz they they want to build a clinical model by 2018 and start testing it and then have something they could prescribe to patients bite
20/20
So I was like wow that's
Big order
So they said what they're looking for
Is off-the-shelf sensors
So this could be anybody
And that they're looking for things that measure
Motion acceleration
Position
Interactions of a person with objects in their environment
Muscle activity brain Act
Breathing patterns in language production in organization
So some of those things actually can be done today with the smartphone they're actually apps
Detect
Parkinson's
Symptoms
They're not
You would then go to the doctor
So they're also looking for things that typically elderly and people who are struggling with motor disabilities can use which
That is a tall order because
A lot of the current Tech is really
Complicated to kind of implement
So you guys are trying to work with IBM to basically pull in all this off-the-shelf stuff and create
I really easy to use system and I'm not sure if they can do it in three
Tears
It's at I think it's a big ask
In in 3 years
I'm sorry two years
It's even bigger ass now to me whether they do it or not is that they putting out
An opportunity here because they've got this vision and they're specifying here's what we're going to be looking for from sensors and so on
We're going to work with IBM
To sift through the data and make these modern systems
I mean you might see a couple of businesses pop up as a result of these kind of
Announcements and that's very interesting to me
Is awesome it speaks to the fact
That Hardware is going to be kind of a
Commodity here
Looking for is to create the data and Analytics
Around how to measure Parkinson's and that's going to be super
Best hard part
Yes and if you think about how then you might prescribe treatment to some
You're no longer just getting like a handful of drugs you're going to be prescribed like a
A monitoring system
Before you make it your
There's things like Holter monitors which measure your heartbeat
Like all the time
You get those if they're trying to figure out life
Mycase why you keep thinking
People that got yours already
Prescribed medical devices but they are
Horrible clunky terrible things
So it'll be really interesting to see how this goes
I look
Exciting
I can't wait to hear more
And speaking of smarts
Sore not-so-smart depending on the situation
Exactly
Set home hub in Platte
Was purchased by Samsung
For the last
August month
Yeah
SmartThings users have been experiencing some trouble and I'm really sorry about that
What did you do stay safe
Mess with their databases
Apparently they had database weeks ago
Still having trouble
It's caused a lot of the rules to stop working
Yes there are 1207 replies currently with an estimated read time of 184 minutes so we're going to save you three
3 hours
And tell you what's what's what
A lot of upset people
A lot of upset
People talking about how
They need to fix the underlying
Infrastructure
SmartThings is
They said on the thread
Situation they tell me that they are working on it
They don't have a time frame for that fix that they're willing to share
So I can't tell you anything more than
If you have SmartThings and if you noticed your rules not working or things going some people have reported there alarms going off in Hawaii
If that's happening to you
You're not alone
And
Effects of Cipro
It's interesting to me because just last week we did talk about
Revolve
The backend service is getting shut down so basically anybody who owns a revolve
They have nothing going to come May
Was the 15th or 16th
And I know I had mentioned
As I have in the past
Maybe you know a local bass system setup a server-side system cloud-based is the way to go
And sure enough I mean you can almost have the same thing again here because
What Samsung is saying is the issue the degradation of the system is because it on the database and messaging
So
You know
You're lying on the backend services and it's
Interesting that it's a high load on the infrastructure because
They know how many products are selling their for they know how many people there supporting with this and what the
Infrastructure needs to be able to do
But
It's not doing
Please not right now
And I'm trying to
Remember I don't
So that's another good question
A lot of companies
Is are using
Amazon
Uibe
Is there using a will say a well-known
High-profile
Cloud
Service for everything which is
I presume that they are
All of those are highly scalable
That's a good question
Yeso
What we don't know
We can only speculate
For next week
Well maybe it will be fixed by next
That would be the best solution ever
So what
So just so you know
Oh
Oh what
I think they might be hosted right now on
Samsung Sammy
For the internet Sammy cloud
Yes I'm looking at a blog post from
State of Butte SmartThings open Cloud of suffering data aggregation service powered by Sammy which is Samsung Cloud for
Coyote
I'm biting my tongue
Maybe that's
What's happening cuz Sammy is actually still in beta it's supposed to
Okay I'm not going to
If there is dating Samsung Smart Home a smart things are hosting this on a beta cloud services
They have
Why would you run a production service
On a beta cloud service
That is a big No-No to me
Yeah
We'll have to ask some
This blog post is not making me feel like
That's not giving you a warm Sammy
It's not given
Alright so that's it
Stay tuned for our guest
Matt Manley of fjord
About smart jewelry and
Hopefully come back next week and we'll know a little bit more about what's happening at
SmartThings
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast to tell you two things the first is that I've launched
The Weekly Newsletter devoted to the internet of things that you can sign up for at Stacey on iot. Com
Is it we're now accepting ads on the iot podcast we have packages for big companies and for startups
So if you're interested email Andrew at iot podcast. Com thanks for
Listening
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Matt Maher
Family who's a group design director at Fjord Chicago
Hi Matt how are you doing
Great great thanks for having me
Oh I'm so glad because I am a sucker
For wearables and smart
Jewelry
Which is the topic for today so
I'm very curious because you and I had this conversation before the show
About
Your thoughts on where this is going to go
And so
Let's talk about
The future of smart jewelry
Are we can have lots of it
None of it
What do you think
That's kind of interesting
The way I would look at it as we probably will have lots of it but we won't know it
I think that's kind of the underlying can a premise is all of the
That Notions of snow jewelry Society is kind of ambient intelligence so
At some point I think maybe the way it will kind of Eliza's you'll get used to just assuming that
Any particular kind of trinket or pieces
Baby wearing
Might actually kind of Hardware that little
Inside intelligence there other kind of smart
So what do we need to get there cuz right now
I've Loved smart jewelry because I hate looking at my phone
And my phone is off in my bag so I need something on my person that's like
This is ringing this is happening but right now it's
It's really hideous
I mean
Icy necklaces that look like little Kindles on
On ropes in its
I'm not wearing that
Yeah totally and I think we've we've kind of hit that point where people say you know
And one of the things that we we kind of joke about young in the studio is
Really you think about the first piece of smart jewelry or kind of connector
Text Amy this a house arrest bracelet
You know that's the thing that people kind of wearing their ankle
This is kind of announces hey this is a smart piece of jewelry
And we've kind of moves through that
Little segments as well where you look at these big kind of cocky
If screen that are sitting on somebody's wrist and it absolutely announces
This is basically a slave to my phone that's trapped in my body
People are kind of cleaning out of the market today in
And I love looking at the overall kind of kick-started universe
Just thinking
Keeping it like real-time ideas as how
People are checking these
Forms
Ideas
Let's just kind of
Create an object
That is really good
At signifying change or some kind of
Change in status
And how elegant we can we just
Acknowledge that that happen
This increasingly not becoming a screen.
Okay so I am
With you on that I have compared my two devices that I wear most often
When is an old school Pebble which has a screen
And the other is a Ringling
Which
And really is a beautiful piece of jewelry to me
I am kind of curious because it seems like
There's an issue of like the information we want at any one time for these devices and maybe something about
How we're handling notifications
Looks like maybe we need to
Accommodate ourselves to fewer
Notifications are only the most important ones
You're the only the most important I think is Witcher is what you're really kind of getting it and again something that we see everybody
You is kind of the right level engagement for them
This really get the initial kind of idea of what we would call Cam technology
Abacus Xerox Parc
Over 20 years ago now
At this point
Call David notion of Cam Technologies
It's some kind of change in status or gold kind of change in the Ambien
The world around us it happens
You may not need to know exactly what that changes at that moment or depending on how you set up your notifications
And you may know exactly
The type of changes happen
Really need to know that one woman is a
But when you talk about in a few minutes ago you some since you want to read a text
Since you want to get a little long form with and kind of know exactly what details
That's a completely different mode of thinking
And maybe you're not in the meeting maybe hopefully you know you're not driving you're not doing any of those kinds of things here
You're the moment of rest
You kind of get into that
Let's that frankly is probably a different device
And that's something that gets away
Anyway
I think overall smart jewelry is going to so if we if we accept that jewelry is going to be
Place for contact
How many
Variations of notifications do you think
Creatinine
There are things
I want to know very specific
So like
Is my daughter's school called
And that's a different from the haptic feedback I get for if an Uber has arrived which is another great place for
Totally
I mean that's kind of a great question when you think about me
How many in and what's the changing texture here that we have
Frankly that's a rolling question that is something that we always have to just kind of watching and it gets
And no pun intended there
But it gets into your basically personal app
I mean for some people
The notion of saying okay 1 buzz on my wrist needs an Uber is here and two buses mean 5th and all might my ring lit up
Color
Things like that that's actually the complexity
Some people
But I don't know if there's ever
Going to be one kind of canonical
If this is it
Space to play in
Is getting people kind of the freedom
And see what we've got all these different devices
With all these different applications that offer certain survey
The way we look at it is this notion of everything that we do is a little
Service
Give people the opportunity
To make their own orchestration
But what about
The particular devices because that's another way I could have my ring be my
Child
But I'm totally
You know a watch that gives me something else or I'm thinking that there's a bracelet I think it's called the June bracelet that tracks your
UV exposure
Actually
I think it doesn't
The color
I'm going to be stuck with not one device that's getting us everything like a smartphone and we're just having
First threat of her body
I think again
People wanted to do it that way I wanted articulated they absolutely could you the way that something is
You put it on now that's
Qi devices right there there on the market
And there's many others or you could
Kind of divide and conquer if you will types of information
Fur type of device stipend
It might be kind of a mental look like for people to kind of know if this happens it's this classification is
Information
I think it's entirely possible
I think one other thing that you can see that again is
Bring it down to one device
Could basically use things like light haptic feedback
My other screen color changing with the light as it is a very interesting thing every kind of looking at 2 but it just really kind of gets into
Articulation how complex you wanted
I'm some of these devices
Once you get past qunar
Light
And vibration
As a general color changes
You can do a lot with your sister
Two simple things so I don't know if we need
Necessarily more and more
Plx devices I think it comes down to
A personal choice
Individual
I think I could actually use one of these for like dessert or eating too many calories I could use like a little
A joke about that to all the time just kind of been negative feedback
Sky devices
It's funny when we do our user research all the time you see
You see people kind of phone that's really the one
Cancel
Campaign
All about it can't wait to have a can't wait to think about the power that they could
Kind of harness for this to make your day that much more fluid
And then there's the other Camp it automatically goes into
Dog leash territory
I'm kind of a slave to be
And so we kind of jokingly in a get into geofencing and things like that
If in your case with dessert If You Walk This Way
Or whatever
Yeah we just kind of
You gently remind you your
You're flying too close to the Sun here you're kind of going a little bit
You're too far over there but
Rest assured that if I break my dessert diet I am not doing for carrot cake
To get these things as ubiquitous as I feel like you're
You're saying they might be
I feel like they have to be a lot cheaper
Are we going to war
I don't see a reason why it wouldn't follow the the basic premises tomorrow slots
Increase power cheaper price
As you see the proliferation of these things happen and then frankly is the market kind of
Find new ways to use this Intelligencer
New situations that could be benefited from this intelligence
I don't see why there wouldn't be a driver to help keep in
Several causes of
NBA games into device
No sew when I'm using these devices
And as they become more ubiquitous
There's a challenge associated with
Programming them
So designers could go one of two ways
They could make it basically a soft programmable
Kind of devices
Myron Lee in many ways is that
Because I've got
So many options with the app
I assigned you this ice I knew that we could just go with a 1
Function device
Set selected UV monitor
Maybe a health bracelet
Looking for a wearable that has an accelerometer on it and just
Tells people when I fall down
That's all I wanted to do on cuz I faint a lot
I wanted to
Say oh my God Stacy
Call frigates the new phone and I can't get up
Mantra
Exactly
So I guess the question there is
How do we think about do I develop a soft programmable button or do I develop
Dedicated function
Is there really any bifurcation there I don't
Sure
So I think again
I tend to kind of go more towards a programmable just because if a if I look at this from the marketability standpoint
And there's a couple of days a couple days to cut this frankly but
If I look at it from a programmatic
And points
And again we were talking you before
Ford about if this then that
The nature of being able to kind of give a lot of people
Very easy ways to string together events
The daily program
Having a kind of agnostic kind of language to again chain things together in an easy way
My mind anyway would only increase the ability for a device to be except
Because it's either something that I can with
Little to no programming knowledge but
Am I pretty easy to grasp mental model
You can put these things together to make this device work for me
I got it
On the flip side though another way to cut it nothing at the kind of concert
Something that you can bring out this it's kind of like the Google search bar and an idea to do one thing or do one
What we talked about the Studio's is kind of the Polaroid camera are the gumball machine affected only does one thing
Put a nickel in it I get a gumball I push the button I get a picture
SimpliSafe
The sing about that
Is when it's a single-minded object
Those markets are they there now
I'm so depending on how good quote-unquote the idea is kind of depends and kind of dictates on the marketability of the Opera
I tend to lean more towards programmatic so people have choice
Make the device shape-shift
I'm a little bit more for that purse
Okay well in those devices would probably be more expensive because they have more sensors or more outputs
Where is a single function device might be
I assume one day we'll get to the point where we have like
I can be bracelet that's
It's just everywhere and maybe it's really cheap so
Sure
I think it's totally fair especially in the near-term and I think again that that follows the same general kind of premises
You know right now that multi-sensor device may be more expensive
36 months from now so I don't know if I could be a part of the conversation
Gosh I hope
Not cuz I
My theory is that wearable technology will be
Pretty much
Ubiquitous
And hopefully
In as many things as possible much like yourself
In the big questions I have about it are
How are we going to program them
And
And I also have questions about the environmental aspects of that
How do we assign functions to them cuz I can think of
Well I can think of so many things I mean
Like that the golf club is a great example
I don't know if I would have thought payments with a glove but
It makes a lot of sense if you think about winter you know going through Subway turnstile and having mittens with
So
Totally
Yeah it's a it's kind of a short hop from you know here were talking about the spirit objects with
Necklace or ring what have you
Pretty short hop is leasing to get more and more Ambien going to give me work talk about outer outer edges of things but not
Terribly far away
Conductive
Thinking about
How to weave these things into
More more can an interesting objects it's a
It's not far off
Ethereality,
Google has projects
Jacquard they're working with Levi's
I actually at South by Southwest side backpack that was made by a company that does costumes for Rihanna and Lady Gaga
When you're listening to music the back of the backpack has like
This little light show
Everybody behind you loves you and you
Exactly exactly
It was very pretty
So I enjoyed it but I was like man that's going to cost a lot
Can't really see a lot of utility there
So yeah
What's interesting about your payment
Going to go
I don't know if you seen you've probably seen the Top Shop
The Barclays Topshop
Penetrate gets a little payment object that they've done a little jewelry that's all payment
Air bases in the UK but
Super super interesting kind of fun form-factor obviously they're their kind of geared towards the Top Shop
It's a huge Market kind of thing but
Just really interesting Begley kind of J-pop kind of form factors and things like that there's a barclaycard integrated with it
As well so can you starting to see
Is this kind of interesting intersection
Greensky payment logic in all these different kinds of objects
Pushed into all different kinds of
Mia bracelets Rebel just
Interesting statement pieces that don't
Explicitly look like
Your computer
On my wrist
Things like that so
Obviously the Disney Magic Band and all that kind of stuff
Gone over that ground well as well as coffee ground for them to
Well and I feel like we've gotten
So used to
Before
We've gotten so used to bands with like the jaw bone
Fitness trackers in them
I'm trying to remember when that started but
Aldi Livestrong bracelets those those
Big fat yellow bracelet
I feel like we've been training ourselves to add to becoming
Used to this kind of
Conky plastic ugliness underarms
I totally think at one point
What's really interesting is in you look at with Tory Burch did with Fitbit
Yes it is the classic men's black plastic form factor going to just kind of Screams and technological object
Yeah it's up here at the end they get together with toy birds
You look at their site you look at their kind of merchandising
It's the Tory Burch X Fitbit kind of thing in there and their jewelry sleeves their their sleeves
Just like the Fitbit with indicted
These are upwards of $200
Interesting thing of logic and fashion and you can look at it and go it's
Basically a container to hide the Fitbit Within
People don't advertise you that big chunky piece of plastic
I kind of look at that again is another read from the culture that
Some people might want to display the fact that it's a smart object with have you but
Once the kind of moment if this is
Kind of disappears or maybe there's other statuses that are more important
What you mean
Then showing that I've got a technological apps
Then you see these other companies coming out of it snow
Be very kind of consciousness
Other brands going to move into that space that's obviously signal sensitive
Osher and
That's one of the things I'm curious about because if you think about building 2
Containers for these devices
It limits where you can put them
It limits the style of jewelry
And also
Because these devices change their form factor overtime
I don't know how long the Toria at like if I spend $200 on a bracelet
Promoted bit I'm really hoping that Fitbit doesn't
Make a form factor that's bigger than my bracelet or
Venusaur
Yeah
Totally and I think that's always going to be
Kakashi
Elizabeth fairy Liquid Marketing General in fashion
Generals of is a pretty liquid market so I think you're right the kind of had some kind of caution about changing forms and
You can work now we're kind of getting into the idea of him
Tekken
Standards oh that's
You know that's never a problem
Internet
Yeah they mean so that's it I think you're very right to going to bring that up
Things like that so they don't
Didn't necessarily hide the fact that there might be some form factors from the Fitbit line that aren't
I'm going to work with you
What do sleeves but
I think that's something to kind of be caught and who knows maybe the bracelet
I'm attractive enough
Just work on its own even if it doesn't have any
Macon haidian weekend
Do I have to ask
Before we go
What is your thought
On SmartWatches
Or watches
How do you
I think they're great I mean honestly there is about a year-and-a-half ago
I was kind of the doubting Thomas other than said you know we're going to look and see what we were working on a wearable
Point of view that a little bit over a year ago and we can't really
You talk about it and if we kind of live with it and kind of bring it in and kind of
I'll be able to speak from experience as opposed to just secondhand heard of it and
I was pretty surprised
Intransigent
Personal relationship to the watch me there were times I felt like it this is Jeff
You just a thing that's kind of telling you what I already knew was going to happen and I'm maybe a little bit slave to it
But there are certain situations
Particularly with driving and driving directions
I was really kind of helps me but
But in general don't look at the watch and you see again
The nature of the four factors of watches
Is kind of
Disappearing away from those ideas
Object and getting back tomorrow rethinking this
The classic golden quotes
Your representation of a lot so if you look at something like that I call here and they're connected Lots
I'm a look at their faces and some of these luxury watches that are coming out
Are they still kind of
Hide their smartness a little bit
I think it's a piece of jewelry as a way to kind of
Convenient relationship status I think it said it's a Greek in the middle of the line piece
Be simple as he watches for notification
Amore
Just some point can give you a little bit more information
The first notifications and things like that
If you need to
I think it's xbaby just another way of looking at a piece of
Piece of jewelry or another object that
Can be assumed to be smart
It's totally fine
Okay and I would like to see all of this stuff
All of the data move into
A kind of
Unified place like a healthcare or jewelry kit
Maybe it's a way to think of it
Because I really would like to be able to like
Linked my jewelry of the day
To my phone
All of the information that I'm trying to
Today
Worried all of the things that I've decided work with
Each piece of jewelry
Sent to it each day so it like authenticate each day
As opposed to
Having a device that have to individually program
Or the missing
Does that make sense
I think the closest way to get it that is through some sort of third-party aggregator
Again where you can kind of raita recipe or something like that so you're not
And stuck with all of these individual
And I have to choreograph everything on the device by device levels opposed
Maybe these things can all just kind of integrate with one particular Harbor one centralized area and get all of it since
I'm that way that's when it's almost like a style sheet for all the devices and kind of cascade from there
Got it so it's been 10 minutes on it
As opposed to spending
Every morning opening up different
Applications
Totally
I mean it just seems to be kind of a drag
If your home nature and whole kind of idea underneath all of this
Yo sensibly is CID has Ambien and teller
Okay great
If I have to spend the first part of my day
And it's raining these things I'm telling you what to do and everything on the Nikes Wikispaces
There's not much that's ambien or intelligent
Hopefully the ideas of these things can also learn a little bit
If you want more anticipatory once
You set the basic
Awesome but I eagerly await my earrings that
Can you give me directions
There you go
Actually done a couple
Exactly like that but snooze haptic based navigation
I'm using different devices
Just like hearing some things like that's a really interesting kind of projects we can put it together
It's that whole notion it's very silent
Very kind of just-in-time intelligence to help
Eagle owl
And that's not going to the day
Get you away from glancing at screens all day and helps you
How to be more heads up in and presents
I can do realize that supposed to kind of falling down from digital hole 15
Awesome alright with Matt thanks so much for coming on the show this week thanks for having me it's been a pleasure talking to you
Thank you so much for listening to this week's podcast will see you next week