Hey everyone welcome to the special Internet of Things podcast
CES Edition
We're able to do this podcast
Thanks to the sponsorship of the open connectivity Foundation
Is helping devices on the Internet of Things
Talk to each other
Weather in a standardized way
Regardless of their manufacturer the operating system
Or the trades
Call used ocf is developing a
Ossification
Talk to each other in a secure
Standard whey
Bus
Making them interoperable
We're going to hear more from the foundation a few minutes after we get through some news
And other
You're going to want to stay tuned because after the news were going to look ahead to see what
Company should expect in 20
Ross is going to do with business model
Consumer trends
And even discuss a few ways of
Tackling the problem
Device
Longevity
So
Let's get started
First off
There's no Kevin in the show it's all me and different versions
Even the CES showroom
In floor so there's going to be a little bit of noise in the back
Ground for some of these and some people are going to say
The Amazon Echo
Echo's name
Consider yourself warned
But this is a fun show and doing something a little different
Wiko
I love all of the gadgets on display
Yes but my first job was to try to establish some sort of Baseline
Are We There Yet when it comes to mass adoption
Will this year be a year
But maybe that was the wrong
Question
Corey series the vice president of
Connect
Explains that maybe we won't know if we're there
Until we actually get there
You know we launched
Our first connecting garage opener
It's hard to even think back to
The time when
Only 35%
People have smartphones
What really makes it hard for adoption to be mosque
If one of the requirements is
Just have a mobile device
Software since then we're at well north of 70%
Most people are
Comfortable
Right
We're starting to move into the technology getting easy enough
App for people to bring it in
The homestand
The Experience on your
Your phone is getting
The point where I think most people
Getting ready
Before
Understanding that you
I think there's a lot of building blocks happening
It's interesting conversations we have
In the industry
There's this idea that
This could be like this big bang moment
All of a sudden
There's going to be a big marketing event
Like a day's going to happen
The whole home is going to be available like I was going to retail and it all be merchandising perfectly
It's really big
Much less exciting
What I can say is
We've done a lot of work
I'll get over the last couple years and
Announce that this week
And see that
Ross
And really that's
One of a few different emerging
Standards
That's really
Widely available
If you have an iPhone
You already have the home app
So do you think
Homekit is going to be
The Tipping Point or that one moment
Stacy so I'm not sure there is one
Amazon
Really impressive
Samsung are doing a great job
Inserting a really widen out with a
SmartThings
Nest has been a fantastic job
Google
As part of that
Story
Is really interesting
So is this just a part of the garage door openers I don't have any great
Forecaster
I think that there are some really interesting
Building blocks that are happening
Jason Johnson
The CEO of August
Add more real talk to offer
About adoption of
I think there are more products
Amor homes
To say that there's more smart home
Strong
To use we're seeing these individual Point Solutions appear at home
And then and then people get a second item
Third item less than 6% of homes in North America or what we would
Call the smarthome insteon truly connected Can like
Your home Stacy in my home
I'm so we have a lot of work to do
To really create smart
Home spit
People are experimenting and they're trying these different devices and they get really satisfied with
Aside from the smart home there was smart everything's at the show
Smart hair brushes
Too smart
Sun shades
All the way over to
Toys for children
It was crazy
So
I found it
Head of ezpr
Who is a smart home early adopter
In a general skip
To get a perspective
From someone who isn't selling anything smart
Water connected
I wanted to get his take on the state of gadgets at CES
He starts off by telling me what he
He has in his home
Am I how am I have two echos I have one.
Downstairs I'm about
12 mile
WeMo lights
And
And how do you feel about that
Today is a really smart
And if they are lost Mayan
Stop myself
Stroppy State like a childish state
Turn off the lights and I have
SmartThings
Connections
Everything downstairs
Alexa
Downstairs lights off
Like a child
Because I have to leave
Things being that
Which is a worrying statement
Light switches work
It wasn't the worst thing ever
Be about them
So now I see us now that we know that you're kind of like an early adopter aficionado
What do you think of CVS
This one was satisi yesterday
Epicene
It's like the entirety
Technology when
In what two directions
They said they going to do a v
Real product
Three I'm going to make a drone for some reason
And they all look the same
And it doesn't matter it's just I must stick Wi-Fi in is I am waiting to find like a
Wifikill Austin
Show me back or something
Ridiculous now
To the point
Of insanity and there's certain things
No I'm sure could be used to
With internet in them
Tons of things
Switch on both
Snorting person
What is the most ridiculous thing
I really think the smaller
Headrush is the
One thing
Because
A friend
Come by yesterday we got to use that in French
She grabbed it and ran it through a hairbrush they did not like
And she described
And I paraphrase
As a cheap CVS
So it wasn't even a nice happy
Two hundred bucks I need to connect to Wi-Fi
Anakin stop you
From breaking your hair I guess then you have toothbrushes work
They were hoping to do that thing where it
But you're brushing too hard
Like hair is stiff
I just think it was just as amazing
Cluster of bad ideas
Not on the smart shower that cost about 1200
Dollars
It doesn't even really thing
Kind of having a conversation about this
What would make sense if you could set
Pressure
Heat settings on the sheriff sale for like two buttons
You know that saying that
Everyone uses forever
I love hefei
On top of that electricity running
Through very in my pipes
It's a great idea and you need to ask
Said Brandy came over and talked about the head bro
Professional electrician
Coming as well as a plumber
This is like an expensive mistake
Is referring to the Moen shower we will have one of them own Representatives justify the shower
Later on
You told me you had lots of thoughts
About fridges
What are they
This two things one
Jokes
The stupid they try and it shows up
About the internet works but on top of that
What do they keep putting screens on
Fridges
And what do they keep
Print to do list
I really don't know anyone who regularly uses it to do list outside of the
IOS reminders
I don't need a 29in
Screening
My fridge
And somehow these people
I'll let you know what we have the ability
If you to see inside your fridge without opening
You can put Pandora on
It's just as so many bad that doing these things
For real people
And it suck LG and Samsung
I believe both
Sing this beats true for most people to load washer
Pretty cool so these washer dryer
Stop loading
And front-load
So you can put inside a bunch of towels and you have some shirts
Need to be put on delicate so you can wash the towels
Normal jumbo whatever saying you put your towels on and on the talk you can put in your shirts or any other delicate
End
Facial wash
I actually probably saves War even if you just doing one small the Lord
Was there anything that you like
I think
Lost
3cs is that's the one thing I saw
That's actually a big deal
Almost feel bad I put washer dryer in Lost
I'm excited about that washing machine
But I too found that Moen faucet I
Ridiculous
So I found Michael pillow
A senior product manager at Moen
Ask why they replace the faucet with this weird
Button pad
We looked at a lot of different designs
Controller with all the
Buttons is what
Summer Resorts around the size of the button
The look of the button to texture
The way there
Raise off the controller
To make an easy to use without actually looking at
Controller
Orientation is over changing temperature change
Is this better than a faucet
Shower system
Precisely control temperature
Digital readout
In your shower knowing exactly where it is
You get a personalized shower every single time
To my Amazon Echo and tell Echo to Start Me Up
10 degree shower
Is that a maybe something I would do something that we were looking at it see if there's any
I want to make sure we have the right consumer experience and have a product that works
Quality Inn
What is the business opportunity here for mowing
So this is something that we're looking at as a trend in the marketplace
Is something you see consumers or Desiring
Hispanic market
Doctor hunting down the Moon
I ran into Neil orchosky
Ephraim Lucia
To talk about it's news from the show
Announcing a couple of new things
Rcs-1 being
SmartThings integration you can now
SmartThings
App control your caseta wireless
Lights and shades
Disintegration be launching
Sometime early
Are also announcing
New Nest integration
So we already have integration
With The Nest learning thermostat
Nest protect
Now we're announcing
Integration with
The indoor and outdoor Nest cam so that
If the camera
See the person
You can program your lights to automatically
Turn on to make it look like you're still there
SmartThings integration requires a Lutron bridge and
SmartThings.
Yes.
Lutron was really early and integrating
Some of the new players in the smartphone
DIY
What kind of area
Can you explain kind of
How that help the company
With caseta wireless
I tried to be on the Forefront
A working with all the the best brands in the end of
So
Originally launched
Are smart Bridge technology for control lights
Rodger home and away from home
Within a day
Technology used to work with
Apple homekit
Siri
Additional brand such as
Amazon Echo
And Sonos
And how smart
Things are really round out
Ecosystem
Will we ever see Lutron put their radios in a hub like they did with wink again
Flooring in Benton AR technology into other products if it's the right fit for the
I also finally got the scoop on the new standard for
Device device
Vacations
Hi
Everybody
Most of us though don't know what that. Is
Can you explain that for
Are we taking the heritage in the huge implementation is a
Products and what we've been able to bring the market and taking that out
Location where that part of it that describes what the devices are
Or making it available over any IP based network
We're really excited to be partnering with a thread group
Stopping at the market first
We're looking forward to seeing all sorts of devices talking..
The cross thread based Networks
And I'm in the future other i p Bass neck
This means I could eventually have that. Talking over
Wi-Fi
Bluetooth
Everything is IP base should be able to talk.. And I see that's the vision and that's what we're we're bringing the market along with hundreds of other
Are active in the alliance many others
So if I'm a developer and I'm like I don't know what I'm going to do with it can you explain to me what the goal is
At this layer
The goal at this layer is really to give intelligence to the different devices that are on the various Networks
So I can tell a light bulb how to turn on and off
It doesn't matter whether I'm using a zigbee network
Thread Network
Wi-Fi network
I'll be able to make that
That part
Happens a lot more easily with the.
City sounds like it's
Yes
I will right now we have a probably a lot more products actually deployed in the markets in those and we hope to actually be working
These different groups to align and harmonize a lot of what we have in all the different device object
Awesome okay
What should I expect
This year
From the alliance
From the alliance this year you should really start seeing that the first products are coming out with.. You also see hundreds of products
Other girl already really.. Abel through our zigbee
And speaking of Standards this is a good time to pop back in with a message for the open connectivity Foundation
Who is the sponsor for this specials
CES edition of The Internet of Things podcast
Today I have VJ K7 who is chair of the business strategy working group for ocf
So let's kick it off why does the Internet of Things need a standard
I said I don't want to focus on putting together the basic Plumbing for devices
Talk to each other what I want to do is in the afternoon I just want to bring a device out of the box
And I want
See that you can talk to other devices
I just buy a standard
Glad it was based on
Sleepless
When was
The need for a standard
So that all devices
Talk the same language
The second is a certification
A device
135i ocse you know that
Easton talk to any other OCS 35 device
But also a reference
Implementation
So that's it to activate the development process
Open source implementation of the OCS specification
So that developers can take that open source code
Do a protocol utility
Under control Solutions on top of it
So why was the merger with all seen earlier this year important
For the Iowa
What are the three things to enable internet of things as you want a standard for devices
Talk to each other
Do you want a lot of consolidation
What is the very detrimental
Fragmentation of the standards and tie combination of the industry and also
He was trying to
Achieve the same goes because very logical for these two organizations to come together and what's going on
Indulge
Are utility is an open source project that is sponsored by open connectivity Foundation
Anita's restaurant
Implementation of the OSHA standard what's going to happen is
Ocf and all things have come together
The first step is we want to make sure the device is from these two ecosystems can talk to each other
People that we are creating a bridge it just want to make sure that transparently devices that talk OCS or
Taco joint
Talk to each other and moving forward you're going to make sure
The beaches
Best of the Best of Both Worlds can come together
In one standard
Specification
And how can a company get involved
With you
They're minibeast
So you can company can get
Enroll in OTs
Strategy
Whether you're Building Products whether you're offering services
Opleiding intersection to the iot space
I think osseous is starting an organization you should consider joining because by joining the organization you can infer
Linda strategy in the direction of the Consortium you can influence the specification
The standardization work that is going on
You have the ability to
234 your products and build products that are OTF
We also encourage people to start using our utility
D2 Building Products
Introduce features into a utility
And where can I go to find out more
Information about the open connectivity Foundation
Open tentatively. Org website. To learn more about
The open-source implementation
Listen to implementation for OTs
And we're back with this week special CS edition of The Internet of Things podcast sponsored by the old
Open connectivity Foundation
We're now moving into some of the deeper conversations I had while I was at
CS
Search is a fascinating talk with dr. Michael Bjorn who is head of research Ericsson consumerlab
He shared predictions with me about
Technology Trends facing us in
All right Michael you have put out a list of 10
Prediction
Sport this year
Is this year already
And we're not going to go into all of them
There were a couple that I thought were really exciting
Society podcast
Let's hit the iot predictions
So we have a trend about consumer setting the pace
The things
There we go
Asking
People about what they think about them
The things we should say that
People don't really know
What that means right
So instead we asking more complete things
Things we talked about
It's the fact that about half of
The people we surveyed
Would like to talk to household
Old appliances
Stop you walk around at CVS
UCLA
Nothing right now and it's actually very much related to
It's right that we called AI everywhere as well because
Internet of Things is kind of
One of the first
Applications I would say for AI assistants
So I think you should also be looking at
The uptake of all these new
AI assistant
That could be a litmus test for
How is the speed of internet
Developing out there
Okay cuz I seen a i
Toothbrushes
Which I was kind of like
I need a lot of time with my toothbrush but I've also seen some really interesting things
Autonomous
And that is also
Part of one of
Yes true but I think even though there's lots of cars here
I think we still tend to think about the driver perspective for cars
And of course if you
Is there a Thomas
So we decided we talked about the patent
Respect you before this year with
We decided
Other
People out there in traffic
Pedestrians
A court of the people we talked to
They would like to actually have all cars being a
That would make them feel safer when they're crossing the street
Those are also the people who would like to have
Which I thought was really interesting as
How do you communicate as a pedestrian with an autonomous car
Because normally like if I'm going to do some
I'm crazy I'm going to make icon
Contact with the driver first
To be like him
Are you doing man I'm getting
But I can't do that with
How do we start thinking about
Crossing the street in front of line
And or the standoff
I got to stop
You're like you're there I'm not going to go
What's your address and there's card in person because of cost
Once we get into situation with Iraq
Ashley Outlet on these cars out there on the streets
It doesn't mean that that's the only thing that's going to change
So actually the whole traffic situations going to change fundamentally
One of the things we looked into was
The fact that you know you have all the street signs and stuff up in the air
But if you're going to be
Add more focused on what you're doing with your smartphone maybe or other things
You looking down
So people would actually have liked to have
Things
Embedded
Example
And potentially also course I should be able to look on
On what's going on with the cars
Not having to look up in the air can expect
So we thought Wally how you know
Self-drive is not just for the cars
It's Russ we when we're walking we're doing other things we need some
Self-drive kind of functionality
Aspidistra
Awesome this is like Paul the billboard
It's going to go kaput
What I could
Add to that that
Another Trend we talkin about here we called augmented personal reality
And actually that's about how you will be using a r
Potentially to customize a personalized
What you see around yourself in the world
So maybe do doors are not going to go food per se
How about if you can decide what you want to have on those Billboards yourself
So I find this trend really disturbing because we're already living in
Such a filter bubble as
Consumers of information
And even
Look at the US elections this year
And you're kind of like
Filter bubbles are bad
So when I think about augmented personal reality I'm like
Oh my God
I could avoid seeing things I don't want to see
And it's a little scary
Yeah actually I tried one of the other there a couple of new Tango Project Tango phones coming out here at csac
Release Spa
Yesterday
The Asus Zenfone AR
I tried it out and actually
We had a bit of a hole in the wall
And I decided to put
Some piece of furniture in front of dad
I was pretty cool because I could do that on the screen and then what each time I looked at it this morning she was still there so I didn't have to see the hole in the wall
That's not such a bad thing
Talk about person my session actually we
We talked about personalisation as a good thing right
Echo chamber social Silas kind of discussion
We decided it's just a bad thing I think it's actually human thing
This some good and some bad things with this
If you think about your
Neighborhood
Where you live maybe your other people like if it like you living in that neighborhood
Is that a bad thing
Where's a good thing I think it's part of human life
And that's what happening online as well
You turning the online world into our digital neighborhood
And I think it's only human that we would like to see
People that are big like ourselves
Out there
And of course there's some
Ramifications of that that we need to deal with going for
That's true and I can actually now when I'm walking through the neighborhood
My neighbor has a
Hideously colored door and
Just be like
Making something pretty
You guys also
Because you conducted your focus groups for this or some of them with the VR users
You guys discovered something else
Huli resonated with me
So
Just go ahead you call it bodies out of sync and I was like oh is that like
Drake dance
But instead it's actually
But it's actually about the fact that
Yeah this a lot of technology changed
Sometimes it's hard to keep up right
Mentally speaking
So when we did VR virtual reality research in
Virtual
Reality world
We realize that a lot of the people there were already talking about getting their VR legs
Your legs
What does it's a bit like in semen they used to talk about sea legs so
You need to get used to this sort of this
This is the waves coming and going and not become seasick from that
And that's what's happening at actually also with virtual reality if you think about that so one of the vision
Mobile
Living room
In the car or your mobile workspace or something
You've tried reading in the back of the bus
But some of us can do it I was kind
We we need
Car sickness pills
And telling us that you know this is probably
Maybe even more
That's all well and good for the big picture
But what can CPS tell us about what to expect for 2017 when it comes to the Smart Home
For that I turn back to Jason Johnson of August
To get his tag
The voice is really becoming a mainstream interface for the home
And all the announcements of the companies are integrating voice capabilities into their products
Tells us this is really moving to mainstream
New Amazon the echo devices
Pave the way
For others to integrate that capability
And allows two
To do a lot of great things in our home by not having to pull our phone out of her pocket
Open app
What seems certain is that we're still not getting a single standard to make all of our devices
Interoperate
Grant Erickson the president of the thread group
Says we're probably going to have
I think it's going to actually be a while Stacy until we see that convergence there's a lot of
Different value propositions that each of the different players bring to the table
Isaac vegan has a very very strong history of strong products
What their applications
Google NASA me bring their own
Value to that ecosystem
They bring
Consolidation anime impact
They all
Exists for a long time and there's interoperability and Gateway is another solution to come in the market
Smith's Raleigh sink work well together
As a consumer what is
This mean if I'm like
Crap
What do I do
Absolutely
There's no reason to wait
There's great Solutions there's integrators to make all the stuff work together
Before we get too mired into the standards debate
Consumer should prepare for another challenge hitting the market in
Subscription play
Zach supalla the ceo of particle
And iot development platform
Explains why his customers are rethinking how they charge for
Connected products
So we see some customers
Who are trying to operate their businesses away.
Github always operate
It cost me $40 to make
Birthing sl400
There's $60 left I split it with the distributor everybody goes
That's the old-fashioned way selling Hardware
But without me there's an ongoing cost associated with
The product ID your paying a platform company or you're paying
Cellular data plan
Or you're paying
Someone to host your Cloud software something cost
And
If you behave in an old-fashioned way you get frustrated because your margin is
Other companies are relying on ongoing
Reminisce
Like
Consumables reordering like
Subscription fees
To make the economics work for 90 product and those companies are General
Successful
Now that requires educating customers and often works better and Industrial
And Commercial environments where companies are more willing to pay a recurring revenue for ongoing value
And consumers are still warming up
To that but
Those companies are working out and the companies with
A fixed margin and ongoing
Costs
Are struggling to figure out how to make
And is there a way for that to work works if you grow fast
It works if you are sales grow faster than your castas and and you have
Central growth it works
But if that doesn't happen you end up
Holding the bag of a lot of cost
Revenue to support
And ideally you're doing that why you grow and eventually you're going to pop a subscription plan or something on top of
Or some other way to create online
I think that's as good example
That is fundamentally a product
Taipei fixed cost for
But they have other ways engaging with
Power companies to do
Response
There are other sources of revenue that either they do today or they can do in the future that eventually close the gate
Hopefully alternative revenue streams give Nest the chance to last
Otherwise
Google will
But all other connected products out there
Should be working hard to add features worth paying for
All in the podcast and what feels like an optimistic
Manufacturers are thinking about their business models
And how to keep supporting these products through several iterations of new standards or upgraded technology
Much has been made of Intel introducing a smart card format that would allow device makers to add more brains to their products.
Down the road the products would have to have an Intel processor inside and we need a slot that would fit the card
But it's a nice way of thinking ahead for a device that could live for
For 10 to 20 years in your home
Best eyelid with Corey series of Chamberlain
Who's back to spell out how he thinks this race to fit standards and more features on a product
Play out for the time being
I'll give you a hint
It's going to involve more hubs
You know I think it's an interesting challenge
When our goal is
Chamberlain is the build
A quality
Highly reliable pocket Alaska
And Technology changes every two
And we're trying to accommodate that in our products
Kohl's
And what we want to do is say your accessories and ways for you to
Keep up with technology space
Without you
Tearing out the entire
Price Chopper nobody wants to do that we know that
So we launched a product
Announced the launch of a product
I'll come out in April called the MyQ home Bridge
They'll allow existing MyQ users
The ability
Top rated homekit
As an additional accessory to
They're either existing garage opener with MyQ or two
Alright y'all get ready for more bridges
More
We're almost through with this year's special CES edition of The Internet of Things podcast
What do I find a word from our sponsor and then I'm going to tell you my favorite device
The whole show
Ceviche
What is 2017 look like
For the
Open connect
So we can look at it from different vectors
What sort of product announcement from
Member companies of ocf announcing that they have
35 products in the market number to one of the key
He goes as far as to make sure
Did the OTF ecosystem and the all seeing ecosystem completely the devices on these two ecosystems
Talk to each other very transparently
Is going to be out there in 2017
Beyond.
Is going to start
Putting resources into more verticals and the specification for other vehicles
Like healthcare
Industrial
Transportation
Mexico utility from an open-source perspective
You're going to see support or more additional
Platform
Weather is
Hardware operating system that's already and
Constraints implementation of iot that is out there for embedded devices
You'll see. Getting in her
A new start to see more and more
TeacherTube
Expand into new areas like enabling be better connectivity options to the cloud
Breathing into other ecosystems
Normocephalic
Alright y'all
It's time for my favorite device
It's been roundly bought in the Press
But my favorite device from the entire CES
Was
The microbots
Push
This is a $50 robot
That you attached to it
Button on a dumb Appliance
And you can program it and it pushes the button for you
Bus
My coffee maker which is not smart but cost a lot of money
I can now make it smart by adding this button presser thing
This is not a device for the mainstream
But
I really liked
And that's it for the special CES edition of The Internet of Things podcast
We'll be back with our regular podcast time on Thursday
With Kevin and I
And in the meantime if you want more iot news sign up for
Stacy knows things
My newsletter that shares all of the News That's fit to print
Every week
On the IRT
You can find it it's Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Thanks for listening
We'll see you in a few days so that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we
Will see you again next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for
For this show feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
DACA