Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast diameter hose
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is my co-host Kevin tofel
Pamela said George Jetson I'm sorry
That's very appropriate
Soyo
George
Anyway go ahead
Okay I was ready to
Smoothly segue into
To the things we're going to talk about
Kevin ruined
What kind of charge
So we're going to talk about SmartThings
Because we got more information
We're going to talk about some news bits
Such as a new integration
Jennifer ring we're going to talk about Google's OS
Best for the Internet of Things
Rillo
Everything about hoverboard
Even though they're not
Let's get started with
Smart thing
All right last week we spent a lot of time because I wondered if my smart
Things home automation hub
Most haunted
Turns out the Hub was just not really working
We
Hydrema right
We were we were right we were wondering what the heck happened
We're going to still wonder I finally got my
I'm sending it back to
Tell SmartThings to
Figure out there
Or dissected or whatever it is
Is autopsy
And figure out
What happened
Because
We replaced the Hub and now everything works
So my experience
Should not be your ex
See this is good to know because two reasons me personally and I've said this many times that's going to be my backup if we
You know Winks away into the background
People who are considering SmartThings
They probably walked away from last week's podcast making
New one of these artists
It's not working
It's not working for Stacy is not going to work for me but
But
You should not
Worried so
Take two on SmartThings
Is that you could actually add things very easily
So when I
Launch my new hub
I was able to add all the sensors
My camera woes iFix
So instead of adding it
As an app
On its own
A separate camera thing is
Instead added it
Spruce SmartThings
So instead of adding it as a wireless camera I did have to compromise and added as a wired camera so it comes with
Ethernet cable and I did that when I did it that way it worked
And from then on
And I was Off to the Races
One of these shoes you had was some of the motion sensors or door open close sensors are not working and one
Was stuck in open mode and
Something of the stadium
Plug which is a zigbee device it never found the zigbee device
Yes that's that always result
Yay in what was weird is that
The problems I was having wasn't Lake
One radio wasn't work
It was like just a bunch of things
So we don't know
We still don't know when SmartThings
Autopsies
It tells me what happen
And because I've asked if they do that
I will let everyone else
What the heck have
We should probably point out now are you
Did not
By this
Correct
The one that I
Tested was a review unit
That they had sent
The one that I swapped it out for was one that I actually
Purchased via ammo
And you would purchase it before last week's show
Which is why we knew you have to and that's why we're saying no LS swap them out and see what happens
So that's what you did
Gotcha I know I only said that because you know the review units
I've gotten review units for a dozen years
Thursday
Companies and they are often times when review unit doesn't have the latest software or it
They produce some quickly off the line to get them out
Are the early reviewers and so on
This has happened before I guess what I'm saying not trying to give anybody passed but the reality of the
Situation is
It does have
Instead the one you bought does work
And I'm guessing how did you go through
Typical Samsung support or no
The way SmartThings does their support is they have both email support they have forums and then they have like a chatbot
At a certain point in time though if it's not working I have seen
Them support via like finally they're just like okay this isn't working here let's call let's get to the bottom of it
So in a situation like mine I imagine that someone from SmartThings would actually you would end up on
On the phone with it because there were enough weird crazy things happening
They would just be like
Okay
Yeah I mean support can always be her Miss for any company and I said that if somebody who's managed support desk for the previous life
So get your experience could vary but
My point being
Chances are if somebody else had similar to the same problem
Play Wicked solid support from Samsung
Amazon
Samsung Tab e
Samsung and I will I will say that
Yes I have
I've been a SmartThings user for
Gears
But their forums
Are awesome
They have a lot of really dedicated users who do a lot of crazy stuff
And so just
Kind of trolling around the forums you can actually find a lot of fun things
You can do and ideas
So
This is again more for the DIY person
Not the person who's like
I just want to plug it in and have it work
Write it sounds like there's a good robust Community there that's willing to share for the DIY people
But even out of the box if you just want to use the product
Now that it's working the setup process
It's good you know you think it's a solid
Entry to
Start homes for people don't have anything right now yes so if you were taking this out of the box you've never if you were going
To the smart
Some space in your leg
Holy cow what do I buy
This looks pretty good
I would recommend
SmartThings
And I would do it
Unhesitatingly for
Like probably 90% of the population
I would say
For people who are not
There are people who are not going to be comfortable kind of
Playing with software setting rules even things like Winker probably too complicated for them
Those people
Should probably just get a nest and
You know just
Toggle things on and off or maybe they should just not really
Worry about the smart
Gotcha maybe they should call their ISP it have
Set up every
Just just reach out to Stacy
Papa
You mentioned when
So let me ask you this is somebody who owns and is very happy with wink
And this is a personal preference which
Would you go with if you could only choose one
I would go with
SmartThings
Because because SmartThings
This has a more consistent
User experience than week
For me
There are things like the lights all come on at the right time for me SmartThings works
More consistently
For me then winked has
I do lose those some of my favorite device
This is so right now Chamberlain MyQ is not supported on smart
Southern Chamberlain has told me
That they will
Eventually stop
Okay so no garage door opener
So my garage door open
Now you got to have fun
Chase now I just have to hit something else in my app
So there
And there is
SmartThings does have an Arduino Shield so there's a possibility of me doing a work around there
But that is not
No it's not your everyday person
Only people who do podcasts and speak Elvish
We're back to you
It also doesn't have in this is actually big
It also does
Support Lux
Your favorite
It's are my favorite
So
I have begged Lutron to make a dongle that supports their protocol that I can plug into the SmartThings
Dongle
Elvis dongles and
Iot Bingo that I'm going to make that and we can print it up
For Christmas
Best for everyone who listen
That will be my Christmas gift to Olive
Holiday gift
So
With the Lutron
You don't with the SmartThings you there are ports on the back
Plug China
Things into and make it
You know ad on radio
So they haven't done that yet but
But it's their potential
Lutron would be like
Then I would just
How to make me so happy so
Those are the two things I miss most
That's why right now the wink Hub is still
Kind of actually right now it's unplugged
I unplugged it as part of the setup process in troubleshooting but
If it isn't plugged back in it stopped working
For some reason
Everything just got to stop
United 7
Bothered excited cuz
Catch-22
I don't know that we've ever talked about this before but I'm curious again
Personally I think for the audio
Amazon Echo integration
How robust is that and how well is that working
It works
It
Turns on
Buy lights
It does not there at there are definitely things that does not
Work with
So it doesn't work with the locks
It doesn't work
Blinds
If I wanted to get the special Stacy support
I think there is a way for it to work with my blinds
And I can work on that
And tell people about that
But I haven't yet
Cuz I spent two hours on special Stacy support
Aetna
I felt that that was plenty sure
I wonder if there is a way to do that with if this then that which is your favorite toy
SmartThings is supported through if the subnet
Amazon Alexa
Still has limited Triggers on FSM that so
Come on Amazon
We would still have
Add blinds to shopping list
So that's how SmartThings is doing as I create new recipes and things will definitely come back to this
I'm sure
And I think for a while I'm going to stick with this hub
Although
I'm going to
Just going to throw this out there the next see if people have finally worn me down and I think I might try a Nexia hub
Because
Because I feel kind of bad about not trying one out
I'm getting a lot of questions about
No no I mean the more the merrier I mean not all at one time obviously you don't want to have all these things going on in the in the same house because
I could actually cause problems that people would not have so I say go for it
So
That's the SmartThings experience
So I recommended if you guys are into it
I'd like the apps I think the software is much better I used to recommend people didn't SmartThings
Really feeling good about tinkering
Now I feel that the software has a lot of use so bring it every bring it
$99 for the version
Hub 249 for monitoring
Kit and also by
I can't
Not going home care
RockAuto
So if you want to come get this is not your answer
And it doesn't work with Nest beak
Because they also are not
Super appreciative of the nest
Terms
Frederick how the data is used in what they share
All of that again with the
So speaking of
Fitness no longer belong
Google
Now
But we'll talk about Google and Google has released its operating system
Some for the internet of things called
Brillo
We talked about it before and we scratch their heads because it was more of a concept and everything else
For those who missed it Google announced their iot platform
Comprised of brillo and
Weave
Yeah they did that at the Google IO event
In June or July always forget which month it was but
Oh my God I met this year you're right right
Taryn Toomey
And we hadn't heard really much of anything since then
Other than that saying
Our Nest we will be available to people in 2016
And it's different than Google's weave
So that's a whole nother mish-mosh
But regardless the good news is right after the last show of course
Google release the SDK for Brillo
If you go to developers. Google.com Merlot you can get the
Limited information they've shared
Publicly
But you can then also request an invite
To the Brillo SDK search array
If ice maker or are you just morbidly curious like we are you can request an invite for that
Other than that there is a introduction to broil a video that's all a matter of 3 4 minutes long
Didn't really tell me anything that Google didn't already say back in May so if you miss the announcement way
Way back when you could actually watch this and maybe get a glimpse at what Google is going to do
There's a little bit more info
Formation so they're going to be updating it every
Etsy well actually I should
Hello
Works with
Google
Sweet yes now I asked Google about if it was going to work with Nest we
And here's where things get a little acronym
I'm going to tell you exactly what Google told me
I'm going to bed it's either a subset or a superset
Your guess is as
So here it is
Quote
We're working closely with Nest ensure that nest
Stand workshop with Nest devices are interoperable with Brillo devices and we will have the same grade out of boxes
Experience and set up built into Android phone
Unquote
So it sounds like it doesn't work with
Ness
We've yet
Correct that's how I read that as well
So
That's that's it that's what we do
That's all we know that's all we know
Brillo will be
And this might be not news but I'll
Mention only cuz it is on their developer site
Brillo is
Chelsea Hardware diagnostic as a platform because it will be square on arm chips Intel x86 chips
MX based Hardware
Also you're not limited to just one
Chip architecture if you're making devices and they're going to release updates every
6 week and
Bigger releases every
Smuts which I actually thought
So that that's kind of interesting to me because I also a cover Google Chrome and Android platforms
And
Google is committed to monthly security updates for Android
And every six weeks it updates Google Play services for Android as well as
The Chrome OS gets a full stable release update every 6 weeks
It's just odd to me or interesting that they're using the same timeframe
So
Maybe this
Ties into that but see will use your Chrome knowledge here
Is Google's Brillo developer kit is based on Ubuntu 14.
4 + Android developer
Including Android Studio
No
Including
Bebe
Android debugging Bridge
I may have gotten that wrong but basically
8 Ibiza is a command line tool set that you use
Imma that I've used in the past to
Control and modify Android phones from a PC or a Mac
So it's a way that like
Little custom ROMs on my Android phone I wipe out Google's Android I put on
Something else Cyanogen or what have you
I don't want to
You throw a bunch of names out there cuz it doesn't matter what it is
Use ADB to unlock the device use ADB to push the new
Image to the phone and Flash
The phone and so on so
It's a toolset that developers using
Easiest used to modify their Android devices
Okay so it sounds like that I could use this to develop on my iot devices
I would say probably because ADB is actually a
Small part of the Android SDK
Okay so and we knew that Berlin was a stripped down version
Have Android anyway
Yes so it sounds like they're staying true to that
So this is going to work on devices
This little is 32 megabits
Megabit
Bytes megabytes
Bytes of RAM
+ 100
28th May
Historic
Which actually is kind of big
Yes it is
So this is not a sensor thing
Cognizant
Liam probably the
Google onhub router
Which we know is
Going to have pillows
Support built in order
LOL. My bad
Google
Is it nestweaver Google
But we do know
Ashley
Okay so that's what we know about Brillo
If you guys are confused
Well well
So is the rest of the world
That is what we know
Unless confusing
The only because it just caught my eye
We mention Android a lot here we just mentioned crom and we'll talk about boiling weave
On the developer site for Billy says extend the reach of your IOS and Android apps to the physical world with weave
So I just want to mention you know they're not in typical Google fashion they're not sticking solely with Android for this it's
Bear cross platform
On the mobile site
Right still don't
Have anything we View
We've waited this long for Brillo
Which we know
How's I know that imagination
With their developing
Board that we talked about a couple
Citgo they are supporting Brillo
Whatever that is
ASL words
Lots of languages
But
List of all hey look you know Google really has not shared a lot of
Details here out to Developers
Person trying under
Standing
Eventually someone will build a product that uses this but I think what's happening is people are looking at the center like
What are we going to do with this OS
Splatoon until we know a little bit more about weave which is actually going to do the talking to two devices
We kind of don't know what we want
Well and that's fine
You and I sat through the big
Come by akeno last year at CVS with Samsung talking about
How the internet of things will
Tie the whole world together
My guess is that this January at CES you may see
Google's partners
Maybe Samsung but probably others
Have a little something to show for all this
We can't start docker
Nope
It's less than 8 weeks away
All right moving right along
Just blowing right through that
Going to talk about
Little bit of news for those of you guys who like doorbells
Jalisco August said that they were going to start selling a doorbell door lock
The doorbell part of that won't be out till the middle
December but
Can buy it now
And today or rather
Yesterday
Ring
They company that Richard Branson invested in
Has announced that it will do an integration with
The Kevo
Door lock
Which is
Matador LACMA
Kwikset
Bluetooth suddenly photos of Bluetooth door lock
Are pretty the deadbolt
And so basically what happens is you can have similar function at when someone is your ring doorbell
You can give them commands to open
If you have a key
Yes
Find nice it sounds like a
There seems to be this coalescing vision
Is it no longer can you just have a connected doorbell
We're connected door lock now they mad
Integrations are good
Yeah it's it's another way though
I will say
Cuz these door locks are like between 200 200
50 buttons
If these doorbells are about two hundred bucks
So suddenly you are now investing about 404
$50 on your
So probably more than the cost of your front door
What kind of front door do you have
A piece of plywood with a Holguin
We live in the sticks with a lock anything up it's just left opens pretty much a mesh screen
Just kidding
You're like we have one of those but I don't know what it came with the house
Gonna be a heck of a lot
Got it
Okay
So
That's out there
I'm a big fan of
Connected doorbell
Genre
So that is definitely on my Christmas list
Speaking of which Kevin and I are going to get together and come up with a connected device Christmas list so stay tuned for that
Because Kevin doesn't know
We're going to start that very soon
Surprise surprise
This is why I should have cute cards or teleprompter I had no idea you were going to make us do that
Boom
Probably for our Thanksgiving
Podcast
Have a guest will
Get it all cute up
Good ideas for your turkey UK
Start shopping
Preparation for Black Friday
Okay
I know it's going to my Christmas list cuz I already bought my own Chris
Early
Oh nice Segway
Tell us all about it I see on your Facebook
Post this is looks like
Alright let me just preface it by saying it's not
Really an iron
40 things
Really cool face
I'd allow it
Yeah thank you
I ended up buying and I bought one on eBay but I
Since part two more of these
A little bit less
A self-balancing
Scooter
You could call it a personal transporter you could call it a hoverboard but clearly
We're not hovering with this
So what I did was I bought one of these things that
Britton Segways
Before I love Segways
But there now 56 Grand whatever they are
I'm not going to go get a Segway
There there little bit cocky little bit clunky so
What I bought is
Similar concept but it
Looks more like a skateboard
Innocence
But you don't ride it
Like a skateboard but it goes
Just wright
So you're sitting you stand on a hoverboard
And what it has it has small 6in
Wheels
And it has
Two independent Motors and a battery inside source Electric Power
Recharge it up takes about 1 to 2 hours to charge
And then you put your feet on this thing in there foot pedals to where you place your feet when you press
Your put your foot down on these pressure points
It knows your on it and it is ready to ride
It also has a gyroscope inside
So that way once you get over the first five minutes of initial trusting I guess.
I was trusting your balance on this thing
Itself balances
So it's on two wheels you're standing on it and it's self-balancing
The interesting thing is
The two wheels are obviously connected by an axle but
Your left foot in your right foot each have an independent motor and operate independently
If you want to go forward either lean forward or push your the front of your feet down a little bit more than the back your feet and you go follow
Same backwards you lean backwards
And it recognizes that you want to go backwards
The interesting thing with the independent axles is
What you put one foot so your left foot forward and your right foot back you literally spin
In place
Very easy to ride
And 11 electric movie at solar panel so I'm all for Anything Electric
How long can you ride on
With that one charge
A single charge I have
Maxed it out yet but what it says is depending on how you ride it
Terrain the speed that you ride and so on
Is anywhere from 9 to 12 miles
Sounds like that's actually about as much as a Segway Cortana
Speed-wise
You can stand in place not go anywhere you can crawl along really slow or if you go full speed which I just kidding
Comfortable enough to do
You going to bounce
1011 miles an hour so basically
6 minutes
Pace
Per mile
Holy moly
Oh you can haul you can haul and it's silent because it's electric so actually
This is really
What they did is
It's got two little blue LED headlights so that way when you are
Moving
And activating one or both of the motors the light for that motor I should light up so people can see
And also if you go
I don't know what the threshold is Victor going
At 8
Close top speed it starts beeping so the people around you
Can hear you and get out of your way
Along pretty quickly
So what
It is really really fun
Is really fun
So how much
Well that's great I'm glad you asked that
Happy car
What I found out
In doing a lot and I did a lot of research for this
Thereabouts
Three maybe four companies that make these
And they're all in China they are all the same
Products
I bought a no-name brand and I paid 343 I purchased two additional ones for the kids
For Christmas don't tell them anybody
And they were 299
If you buy a brand name one which is takes the exact same thing
And slapped a logo on it such as iowahawk Levi board funky duck or any one of a number of other
Brand names
You will end up paying
I've seen him for 599 I've seen them for 1,000 I seen them
1499 and I've seen them for $1,799
Don't do that
Don't buy one of those for that much it's not worth it first of all
And second of all you get the exact same thing
Probably run 300
In fact if you shop around on Alibaba which is
China's
Take online Commerce Place you can get it directly from the manufacturer even under
Note 8 to 2:50
Yeah and if you buy in bulk
OtterBox
But I'm not going to get into the personal transporter real hoverboard business myself
Corporate gift-giving season is upon us
There you go
Now I will say this as fun as they are to ride
The outer shell is
Is completely plastic
And that's fine keeps the weight down it's certainly sturdy enough
However when you
Are learning to write it
Kind of jump off at like a jump off a skateboard
And what happens is
Nothing rolls over on itself
And since you're
Probably getting a sidewalk or road or driveway
It gets counted up
Really quickly so you want to be careful when you're learning to ride
Metal shatter
Crap to be quite honest but that's okay I can live with it
It's something you want to be
You don't consider when you when you do if you buy one
Learn how to write a note
You can ride on the carpet that we learned actually riding it in the house
Yeah we are on that we have bamboo floor so we've been around
Various rooms are resource that we went on the carpet no problem
Not that great on grasping out all the grasses but you could do it and what is it
Pretty
Strong National
How much does a
That's a great question is it is heavy
So if you
I do not like right in the city or on a college campus or at work and then you find a place we can't ride it yet to pick it up
And it's about 22 and a half pounds
It's not big but it's dance because it's got some Hefty batteries in there you got the two electric motors in
That's why these posture to keep the weight down
So it's heavy it's not something you're into putting a backpack and tote around when you're not riding at you're going to ride it
And then you can eat off it
I'm not going to want to carry
Got it okay
So I think
That is some awesomeness
Disgust
Some great dad
It's actually
Yes I'm confusing operating systems
And if you stay tuned we will have
Actually some more great gadgets
Sansom Commerce
For the internet of things and business models with Rob catcher who is the CEO of
Haiku
Which is a
It's what kind of connected fridge magnet
You can use to
Shop for
Thanks shop for groceries actually
And they just signed a deal with Walmart so weird to talk about business models for the internet of things and it's going to be awesome so
Don't touch that dial
Hey everybody Welcome Back To The Internet of Things podcast
And I have with me my guest today is
Rob catcher who is this
CEO and co-founder of haiku
Hi Rob
Stacy how's it going
He is going super well today it is a beautiful day here in Austin
In Texas where I am recording
And let's see
If you are where are you
TIME in San Jose
San Jose which is normally very funny San Jose but but not today
Today is raining
San Jose
Found inside
I'm glad to be here
Awesome
All right we'll haiku
You guys are doing something that is near and dear to my heart
Because it involves food
And I love it
So why don't you start by telling the audience a little bit about what haikyuu is
Chorizo
If you've ever had what we call that oh crap moment
When you get back
The grocery store and you realize you forgot something
AccuWeather
Credit fix
I'm so I could decide this round
Devices
Beautiful little device
Magnets for fridge
I'm going to have the single button
And you can press that button
Tiger scan barcodes
What's peking
Imagine a scenario
We're getting breakfast ready
Your family
Nu Finish
Cereal and bananas
How are you going to
And if you're like me
Three kids for cat always running late
My wife's doing lunches on
Breakfast
Pazzo
If I would have taken my wife in that moment like
Hey get out your mobile phone
There's no way
But I can say to my little one
1 people sent for Daddy
So do what you get the big smile on her face
Graphite you up
The fridge and the cereal say bananas
Now that goes to a shopping list that's available on my phone my wife's phone
Instantly goes to the left
So that when we walk in the store when you don't
We need
I can also pick
Shopping list
And then actually actively go shop for you online
And
Purchase items
Several members for you shops for you
Combat Tycoon
Or in a fridge magnet
Netflix
Adora fridge magnet
Either way I mean baby you're doing the nutshell like
So this week you guys actually just announced
Here for people in the US
Partnership with
Walmart
And Peapod
That will now allow
U2
Put these things
What's in your shopping list
And then you can pick them up
At Walmart store at participating Walmart stores and
With Peapod they will actually deliver to some people in some areas
Absolutely so we've integrated with both of us online grocery stores
To allow you
Bata Shop
What I'm excited about is this idea that you guys have built up
Connected objects
Has a business model at
Attached to it so I I want to ask
Explora kind of
How you're doing this because
How do you guys make money right now
I'm spending
For now it's a it's a $50 to buy send for me because I am a very busy person in our family is busy and I
I have a child
This is
Totally worth $50 for the convenient but
For a lot of people they might be like who
Armani to keep track of my grocery list
So let's talk about
Why you went into this and then how to think about kind of building a business model
Cuz I think there's a lot of options
Explore them
Couple different questions than their the first one is
Why do the spa
Why does it why does this device
This is a first world problem
So why create
It is a first world problem
There's no doubt about
Like we recognize
But fundamentally we got tired of running out of stuff
Ain't we got busy family
Demanding job
3 kids
So yeah we tried mobile app
They're a good step in the right direction
Can you get your list with you when you walk
The store you can share with others
But In the Heat of the Moment
I do not like in that scenario like a
Describes about getting breakfast ready for the family
In the Heat of the Moment you fall back
Because it's fast
Easy Uke
Shut down
Mobile apps are not necessarily the right tool for the job
I'm inside the house
So we wanted to create a
Fast and easiest pen and paper
You had all the benefits
You got a nap
Is it available on both Apple and Android
Can I just talk to it or do I have
Have to manually added
Type in microtia
Are apps you can on the Android version you can both stand and speak
I mean Apple version
There is
Skinny
Speaking yet
You can pick some regulars
You can
Manually type git men
Lots of shopping list
Oceanside
You can share less across
Even if
You might have
IPhone your husband has Android
No problem
Shopping list
So that when you walk in the story both have to list with you
Yes
Android and iOS are they both important
They are
Thank you for doing both
So what kind of think about building a business
Around the connect
Where do you see your company is going to
Revenue coming
From is it from consumers buying the device is it from building out revenue from third-party services how do you how do you want
Certainly
The device yesterday
Absolutely
But when we think about the business bottle
It's more about
For bringing retailers orders
Then we expect to become
Stream charging
Retailers
Tesla charger
Francis well
But you're lucky blast me like
Advertising on a product
I'm in a potentially down the road
Maybe
And absolutely wechat
Monetize
Stay at the station
Gameworks still focused
On speakerphone
I'm delivering
Experience
And that means
A shopping app that remembers for you and also packed
Recharge retailers
Absolutely
No doubted
That's one
Where do you see
Kind of the future of food acquisition grocery shopping
Walk me through 5 years
Kind of what it's going to be like
Now you can just grocery shopping just the active
Crafting recipe you're thinking about what to
What to make cuz there's a lot of other connect
Did products kind of vying
My kitchen space and some of them are really interesting and like this idea of you know might this just don't view of like
Connected activity tracker saying Haywood for a run you should really eat some potassium so here how about a banana smoothie
So I don't know maybe this is 5 or 10 years but like walking through the six.
What is a
Cricket stick things I'll be be made over
Inside
1 is good
Like you're like you're talkin
Hey, got your second Championship medical look back on that
Yale five ten years now.
Like you know how did we prepare food before
Today we we might think
We do research
How did that work
Microfiche
Exactly oh my gosh I better that one in a while
Yeah
Boats to package wine
And I think for punishment is another
Ideas shopping
The things that you're you're buying on us
A fairly regular basis
All your house
Consumption
Audition for that
Continue to be
Answers
Inside the home
That
They're aware
When you are low on some
Madison
Need something
The creepy way
Magnetic is really important
Getting you touched on this earlier about life
Yeah people who are
Yeah freak out by things listening
You listening all the time
You don't think they should be
HB creepy technology
Faith Technologies
A good number of years
There's an influx of technology that made life
Waiting
People in hell
Nighttime think like
Washing machine
Dishwasher
I didn't want to date a live tonight
It in Atlantic City apartment without a without a dishwasher
Taylor Swift die
Is that okay
Yataghan Gatsby's are first world problems
Yes we understand
But they're also the impact on
To think about the future
Retail will irritable move inside the hall
Angelini net doors are setting
Skittles commercial
Experience of
Being able to buy things
Will be more kinky
Great Adventure
19 places where cops
That's a little that could feel yucky
Am I single
Because that's really important
Yeah cuz advertising I think there's new advertising models that people aren't really talking about
Instead I think
Are really interesting or could be interesting
Around like apis for I think it was like kind of the old Campbell's cookbooks on steroids
And I don't know if you have those cookbooks for the 1970s but
OKC
So my mom had that
Scrum was a working mom and she used them because
The working mom
And so I grew up on a variety of Frozen vegetable meat in Campbell Soup
Casseroles
And that was a form of advertising and I think about
You know today with an API
You really have an understanding you are like
Proctoring
Campbell Soup of
What people are consuming
Based on you know
But I'm logging in activity tracker my food tracking
And you can start delivering to me some you know
Crazy recipes I customize rest
And then you could you know
Maybe help.
Compile my what are those called meal plans for the week that could be helpful
That could be depending on how it's done and you know if your
Automatically filling my shopping bag
You know that
I is a working mom might really actually welcomed this if I could set parameters around that ghetto
Sodium intake and things like that
But I don't think
I don't know if Custer like companies are really there yet I don't know
Such a good point about
You know that balance
Examples
Where
Things have been helpful
Based on
Other companies knowledge of what
You like don't like
Watch.
Bright Netflix
First come to my mind
I like Netflix
Most people do
Radio is another good example that I think like
Pandora and Spotify
I'm going to make you mad
Predictions for
What you might want to listen to
All recipes that far from that type of
Negations and
I think what would be important that recipes would be being able to
Control some of the parade
Campers at Lake
I think a company wants to
Send me an and I think food companies are getting a lot smarter about changing their off
I certainly don't want a bunch of recipes that offer me
Really poor option
Cuz I'm not going to
That's right that's right you also don't want
Feel like a like a commercial in
No one likes
To feel like the
But people do want
And that's certainly the way we approach our product
Is
Yes focus on delivering value today
I'd help
If you do that
The belated Builder
I guarantee it
If you do that
True you guys are really doing this so
I guess
From me I do want to make sure how are you building your product to make sure somebody is equally good scanning and voice
Enginetech she doesn't have built
Mico
Which does exactly the same thing
Take a look at it
A big
Advantage
Publishing a
I am weak
Created this guy
Thing in your house
Can you scan
Speaking
List of shops
Are you satisfied
And
You looking at you like a like a like a Fitbit
Where
Even after
I copied like
Jawbone
Nike
I and others moved in and created similar type
Fitness trackers
Has data from
A year ago that they still controlled 68% of the market
Your people saying well you know well now Apple
Looking at it's going to be all over
Do you know if there's an idea or I should do thing I feel already
Any startup that makes it to an IPO
That's a success
All right
Well then your final challenge
Cuz I am still think
Myself it what the heck do we
Call this category of
Devices
The Shopping Bag
Rob thanks for coming on the IRT
Play podcast in discussing your shopping button
With us and I look forward to a testing out the Haiku and hopefully grocery delivery since I loathe
Who's going to the grocery
Start with all of my heart
And don't we all
Oh my goodness thank you so much I really appreciate you having me
Thank you so much for listening this weekend please come back neck
Next week