Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is Stacey Higginbotham and I am your host and we have my Coast
Kevin tofel
And this week's show is
Is going to be a big one we have
The police
Data for the Amazon Echo
We have Google and some smart watches
We are getting ready for CES
And we also have
Some news about Amazon Intel
And maybe a little philosophical discussion on what the smart
Home chef
Pat in the
Standard sets
What personal Avatar
Tire should be there
Symphony if any
We'll also have a message
From Samsung our sponsor and an interview with God he was a founding partner at
Wing Ventures
When is the BC who did the
Iot report that we talked about earlier this year so it's a good interview
I think you'll enjoy
And now a message from our sponsor level education
Do you feel prepared for the future of the internet of things if not prepare for
For it with iot training from Level education in Cisco they're offering a program called iot core
That is a 15-week blended learning experience for iot foundational knowledge it has amp
Hands-On learning opportunities real world examples online learning hackathons and project-based learning
You'll emerge from the experiences iot ready the course starts on February 13th
And to find out more go to level edu.com.
That's level edu.com iot
Okay let's kick it off with this week
Which is not
Despite the fact
Next Bachelor
Police
In Arkansas
Walmart Walmart
For data
Yeah well this is only a matter of time and then anything that captures information recordings and such
It's likely to be
Subpoena door
Requested
DL warrant
This if I read correctly was unfortunate you know a murder case
It is
The information which actually found this
Story first
Amazon Echo in the hot tub
Which I have to say
Good headlines
So what happened is the police
A gentleman named Bates is a suspect
James and Ruby
Which is really on
I'm in the police are looking for
Any audio recordings from the echo that he had and he also actually
Had several other smart device
Vices
Pizza set to go to trial for the first-degree murder of a man named Victor Collins
And what they're arguing they're looking actually not for like the murder caught on tape
But understanding
Who was in the House basic
Looking for voices that were in the house
At the time
Interest so Amazon didn't get the police any information
Did the echo dog down its servers but it did Handover Bates Account Details In purchases
Police say they were able to pull some data off the speaker
So they were able to access physical data from the
The device
Confiscated yeah that that's correct him and my guess is the because you have control over those recordings of Snippets
After you say the Wake word
Those are all saved for an indeterminate amount of time but you can go and delete them
Obviously this person did not
Do that mean who would you know
Honestly really premeditated everything
That's good to know I'm glad you're taking care of
Yeah
My understanding is that Amazon felt that the
Warrant request was too broad
To actually hand over everything
Including the recordings
Yes
What was
And I know that the echo is like everybody's focused on that and it is
Voice at scary
Police also say that Bates had other smart home devices including
A water meter
And that show that 140 gallons of water were used between 1 a.m. and 3 a.m.
The night that Collins was found dead in Bates hot tub
Yeah that's probably more of the cortical Smoking Gun if anything
Still
Stantial
Yes
I'm sure he's going to be asked
Simcorp what did you do with Outer 40 oz of water between 1 a.m. and 3 a.m. and specially if that coincides with it
What time of death and so on so
Is there a useful information for the
Prosecution
And I would not have thought
That my Smart Water since I don't have one but if I had one
Deck that could be used against me you just a water sensor like
Wrightwood
Beautiful format
Well
I am not let's make that very clear right now on the air
So I will say in this sounds really creeptastic
Behavior but when I am away from town
Sometimes I look in
At the sensors in my house so I look at my Nest Thermostat I can't even look at like I have
Devices that measure sound in my house
When I can look at that and I can see like oh this is my family talking at The Breakfast Table
You know cuz you can see this biking
Decibels right
If you have a humidity meter
You know in your house you can actually see when people have someone is taking a shower because the humidity rise
Isis
People may not be aware of it but
And it is kind of creepy that I'm like
I miss my family let me go look in the blinds are open they must be awake
No it's actually it really illustrates that by understanding what's going on inside the privacy of your own home
You can actually piece together what is going on right you totally can in
I have motion sensors for example on a bathroom light
And you know that motion sensor goes off in
I know someone has
Walked in at least and then walked out of the bathroom
Aunt
The closet or the laundry
So
People may not be aware and it's
It's fine because it's
Private butt
What people don't necessarily understand is some of these privacy policies
May make that information public and it is easy to piece together this
And part of me says that this is just an extension of the date of this already available
Through traditional smartphone usage
You know where you are
What you're connecting to
When you were out of place who you talkin to
It does because now your instrumenting so many different
Other physical thing
And that can get in when you take the Telemetry data from all those things you can really piece together
Timelines of actions and locations
Far more
Accurately
And in the case of Christmas I'm going to let you guys know that you know
After we installed Arkin
Connected doorbell cameras
I realize this was a side benefit but
When people are walking up the stairs with
Your Christmas presents like they're about to
To wrap them
You can actually see them
Doorbell camera
The point we're making here is
It's light and fun baby when it's you looking in on your family and everyone is aware of these things
But this is information that
Part of your digitalfit
Redis
And if we don't have
A real clear understanding of how laws are going to
Protect that we're not
So
This cases
You know
A really good example and you know the attorney for Bates is arguing that this is private information so we'll see what happens
I want to follow what happens with this because I do want to
See what how
The Court's address the Privacy Issue Number 1
But I would hope that people
Listen to show or just aren't interested in IRT don't just say I'm not going to do any smart all morality stuff
Because
Look what can happen if these are simply tools and just like any tool how you use
And what's your doing
Tools themselves are not inherently bad as what
What I want to get at
Yes and I think
To me because there's so many benefits of having this information
This is really a wake-up call
Or
Consumers and the industry to
Actually start thinking
About
Privacy
And how do we want to regulate
Because we can't just say we'll figure it out regulation will come eventually
Because right now I'm having his regulations going to come
Quartz
And that's always real
Elation
So that's our thoughts here
Kevin has exciting news
We should note
Kevin works
Baidu
That's correct and this is not internal information which obviously I wouldn't have no could I share
There's some information from The Verge who Intergroup interview Jeff Chang
The product manager of Android Wear at Google so we'll talk wearables for a few seconds here
The folks who can't follow the Android Wear platform
He probably already knows about recap real quick that
It's been several developer previews of Android Wear 2.0
Over the past
Toss a 6-7 months and
The final version of Android Wear 200 is expected in 2017 will all along with that software
Jeff Chang is told of hers there will be two new flagship smart watches in the first quarter of 2017
From Google
They probably would have assumed similar to the Nexus and pixel devices where
Hardware is
Me to showcase the software
Interesting ladies will not be
Branded Google or pixel which is the new
Google Hardware branding
Which is kind of surprising to me
Together
Yeah I don't understand that so I mean there's so many
Harbor partners that
I've created Android Wear watches so I presume one of them will partner with us and it will be
There branding on back of Union Motorola LG
Casio polar
HTC Huawei a sus a whole bunch of folks have partnered so I don't know who the part
There isn't an Jeff Chang did not say who it will be but
It'll be interesting to see what
Hardware showcases the software is as I said before so we'll find out early in the first quarter of 2017
Okay
What are the features that you feel like
You're the smart watch
Way too many of them
What are the features that you're like
If you are going to play in this area
Unitus
Table Stakes on a smartwatch these days are obviously the time
Smartphone notifications Rich notifications that you can interact with
Very contextual notifications that we get today from a Google Now for example Siri does this to a
Small smaller or lesser extent
APA contextual notifications are important
AI Voice Assistant type thing so I
Presuming I do not know
I'm just answering your question
I would hope to see
Google Assistant
Which is
Davi rebranded Google now that's in Google home for example and on the pixel phones
I would expect to see that in a flagship Google Android Wear device
And then
Sensors for your exercise and health tracking
Are important to me I mean percentile so I can see GPS because I run with just a watch and listen to music through Bluetooth so
So I wouldn't say that
I must have
Those are the
Key
Things I would like to say
I would like it to be
But that's just
Evans like I want
No no no no no
There are many SmartWatches that I bought are not very pretty and some that I really like the design of
With apple you get
1 basic look and you can customize
With color War
Bands
With Android where they're actually you do have a very wise choice and get a Michael Kors Smartwatch for example that
It's a little more upscale in the fashion area fossil q line is also another
Nice-looking
Line of Android Wear watches and then there's some of their very utilitarian and those are the ones that I have bought because
Included a GPS where is the fashion ones did not examine the Stake Center
Or whatnot so you actually have more choice I think when it comes to Android Wear
Whether or not they suffer experiences the right one for you or with platform use that's that's personal choice
Okay
So
Will bring this into a
I think Stacy is found on the internet
Really excited
Product category
I was actually in my in my perusal of Amazon's smart home stuff
I discovered
GE Z-Wave Wireless smart door sensor
It fits over your hinge
Pin on your door
So it's like invisible
So it is got a ten year battery life
And now this product
Has kind of
It looks like calibrating it
Is tough so I ordered one because by golly
Why not
So what we'll see how this works but it's $40 in the idea is when you open the door
It could trigger
An action
Or I guess if you close the door in this kind of gets rid of like the open clothes sensors that
You know I
Because I test so many things I have so many open close sensor stuck to various stores at
Nintendo's those are all add-ons to the
Traditional door
Right you have like this
This thing that you have to add to a door frame or inside the door someone
This actually replaces a part that's on existing door which I like the concept here
I think it goes over
So it doesn't replace it I'm look at
When when it arrives I will tell you what it does because
It's a little unclear
But yes
You don't have to remove the door
Kiss
The best way to ruin a marriage is to try to install a door with
It's literally the hinge
Canton that you're replacing
Yes you just left.
I'll be right back in there
Right
So if this works with lissy according to the instructions
It works with SmartThings Nexia Trane
LG Smart Security + Lowe's Iris system
And
I guess we'll see
But
For those of you guys who are like
Oh that sounds good cuz I hate those ugly open close sensors on my door
Free
Someone also pointed out to me a company called sensitive I will put this in the show notes but it's
Sensa
Tive
If he's already $60
They look like double-sided tape they're just
It's literally just a 3 mm thick strip
That you put in like you would put in door insulation or something you know
Not visible to eat it's not noticeable either
And it's a Z-Wave product as well
I had never even seen his Heir Apparent
Leah crowdfunding
It'll so if you're in the market for non-intrusive sensors
Both of these options look really interesting
So I just thought I'd throw that out there since you guys
My listeners are always like a great
I also will caution though with this open close thing I've been kind of thinking about that cuz I started putting motion sensors to control lights around my house
It is very hard
Defined
You know you want to think about when I open the door
Do I want the same thing to happen
Everysing
Not necessarily but I think it at a basic level you could either you would either a want to a notification that
Somebody has entered or left your house would be
In certain
Times of the day
You may want a nearby lake to go on as you walk into the house
Yes and that's
I'm thinking you know you could
This is interesting because I could open when I open my front door for example my patio lights could go on when it's
Dark
This would be awesome until like the one day I'm like trying to see like if there's a burglar outside and I hope
Victoria Justice
To see what I can see and then
The lights go out
This is me always thinking the worst case
Moving right along
Cea
Do we want to talk about it
We'll talk a little bit about it
Just a little because I am not going
But you are and it's you head out there next week so
I think you have a
See we talked about CEs from CVS next to
Yes so we're doing a special edition
Of the iot
Podcast
From CVS
And this is going to be a show that comes out on Monday so you guys are going to get to
Actually this will be the Monday after CS
So the week of the 9th you're going to get to
Guess what
Add
While I'm there so next week's podcast you're actually going to get some really exciting news we're not going to talk about
Some of the things that are happening
Because I can't yet
But I will say
Voice is going to be big
Service providers people who are you know
Making these iot experiences they're actually there's some really good stuff happening there
And there's some great news for lighting
So
If you guys are like on the fence about to
Click Buy on a lake
Fighting kind of product
Wait
I often tell people to wait on consumer electronic purchases at this point in time just because you know the consumer electronic show is
Going to have a gazillion different
New options
Not all of them are readily available as of
The Daily Show so that's something to keep in mind as well
Mynews however
Subway time
That is my advice to you
I mean you don't have to if you really want to buy it but you
Which status
All right before I get too philosophical
Let's talk about
We don't actually talk a lot about
Some of these other hoes like Nexia are very light
But
I saw it a new story about Intel and Amazon
Are demoing a tiny smart
And it's powered
Spy software called
Neo s
Aosm iOS
Maybe it's my
Well it could be a capital M little eye
Big big ass
So
Maybe they were little I
I just gets no love
No love for the
Okay so meiosis is the meiosis
Is the company behind the vire
Xavier light system
Which is a Z-Wave smart home system
It
I've tried
It's okay
It's all Z-Wave so it's never
But I kind of want to do because I want to throw a bunch of stuff in there
But it is a solid system
I'm they work hard to support
Wings it Iz
Totally reasonable
So
What they did is
They have a Gateway with Intel Core processor
And Amazon Echo
Is doing the voice control
So
The Cee Pro is reporting that so far
This product that is being demonstrated
Controls Philips Hue Lights
Oh
I wonder if that's who a new hardware.
If that's through the Gateway that's interesting cuz that means that
But it could be just the echoing
Philips Hue with you have a nest thermostat a Sonos player
Soundbar and subwoofer
So not the actual speakers
Legrand Motors motorized shade
Somfy motorized awning
I wonder if they can also do the song people right shade
Avira security cameras
Amazon Fire TV
The Plex Home media software
And
A Wi-Fi Gateway with Intel
Anyone
Anyway in
Any Quinn
Why do.
I'm going to go try to find this
It's a yes
Embassy
What's Happening Here
Cuz
Yeah I'm curious if it's more
Demo and not a
To gauge if there's interest in a product
Maybe
So I will say
Lutron sent me
A casita
Bridge
To test with homekit
And as part of my homekit testing which
I guess I won't tell you it because next week's can be
He probably also yes all the time
Sometime in January
We're going to get into my house
Homekit stuff
I'm thinking I might actually be able to get rid of my wings
Hub
Use the Lutron caseta to control my Lutron stuff
Amend
And various Echo skills to control everything else plus I have the Hue hub
Already so
I'm actually going to
Going to try to see how far I can
Go
Without having
Like a SmartThings like a big brain hub
Write the traditional
Smart home hub
So
We'll see cuz
I think
For a lot of consumers that
Mets
I don't know
It depends I mean you know what you'll be using the echo.for a lot of your interface and interaction I suspect so
For consumers who don't have an echo
I don't know that I would get rid of
A hub
In that case
Listen sometimes
Like I have to tell you
In the middle of the night when our house cuz it's been like 80 degrees here in Austin this week
When our house gets too hot on like
I want to tell the echo to
Turn the nest down
I can't cuz my husband sleeping next to me safety
Padma
Right now
You don't keep a phone on the bed
Stantler
Don't because
Don't look at it
Before I go to bed
Sucked into it so I can charge my phone in another room
I know I'm not like a real human
It's weird
Sep
You are not
All right so let's talk about
Who should be your avatar in
This is
A conversation brought up by everybody's favorite Japanese
Oh Japan
Wish I could go with ya creating virtual wives and girlfriends to help you
Navigate your life on a daily basis
There is a video probably it was before Christmas
Anime
Like setting a lava lamp looking thing
She's concerned about a Japanese salarymen well-being
Ghetto
Oh how are you very friendly virtual wife virtual girlfriend is what they're calling it had a bonus now of being able to control it on
Which
This is nothing like
The idea of
Animated
Virtual girlfriend
Japanese
Men is nothing new
The home automation is a newt
Twist it got me thinking like
What do we want I mean like
Are smart home
Controller to look like does it need to be
Anthropomorphism
Well
Dino that was big bonus points for Stacy
A lot of people talk about like Rosie from The Jetsons and they're like
Opposite of this little creature
Turn the lava lamp
Do we want this like
And all the voices right now or female so like do we want this like
Woman
Actual figure to be one of them
Woman's voice like
First of all I'm in some some of the assistance that are out there you can change the voice to male or have a different diet
Elector or accent
So I think Siri you can have a male voice if you want to
So but I think going back to your original question it's do we want to see the interface
What do we want something like
In the movie Her
Which is sort of what we have today with voice controls and and response back and
As you said right before the show we were discussing this briefly
It seems like apples going that way with the airpods and Siri access in there
Whereas
Amazon is looking
Wer
Distributing The Voice through multiple devices in a house not to
Two headphones that you could have Amazon voice services in in a single device that you wear for exam
That could happen
I think it comes down to especially after looking at this video do you want to see your assistant
And do you want
Well you shouldn't you should be able to have him or her look at the way you want because it's a personal assistant but
It's early days yet so
Japan has this little blue anime girl
Fine I'm sure but I don't know that I want to see
A virtual
Assistant
I mean if I'm going to see something that I want something like
An actual Android
Natsu Landry buy a robotic
Android that can
Physically do things around the house to that mean I'm going to buy Bicentennial Manwich
My favorite movies
And that's that's so cuz there's all these like Jibo in these little robot things that
Can I put a
Face again a face to
A voice
But for me I feel like if I'm going to have
Robot
Or like
A robot my house I want to have arms so it can
Right where I mean if you're going to go
Go all the way at this point
We'll see at CES a laundry folding robot although it takes a really long time to
Tefl those
Those towels
May takes me a long time to but
It's funny because I think I'm the last show we just talked about the
Personality of some of these
Services assistant devices where it said
I often after speak to my echo will say thank you after she does something for me
I already have that personal connection I don't need to see anything to get a more personal connection
But that's just me
This is one of those things for him like
I know I don't want like a little weird
Avatar thing and I've never been in
I think the Jibo and those kind of robots
Cool but I don't realize I would never spend the money on it cuz I'm like
Already have most of that and
Haven't seen roaming around my house doesn't
No no
And you know I dedicated robot
The price that it would
Write a program
But there's there's hope 10 20 years from now maybe it's but no it's not something that most people going to
Get in there so few options out there to being with right now anyway
Right I'll save my money for
The self-driving car
So I have to say that we had
An awesome
Comment
As last week's episode where we kind of was like
Hey this is what we've done to automate our house
And Scott
Lawrence Lawson left a comment on a Blog and he
It's great idea
Which is
Change the switch or the plug on your garbage disposal to a connected one
So you can use voice control with the echo
Orbitz Google
And he gave it with
Hey smart thing
Turn on off the drain
And he said this is really useful
When doing dishes with wet hair
Its and it's
I want to see I would never have thought of this
Possibly because
My garbage disposal
Yes which is just covered
Mike Massey Pizza
Iwatchonline
I totally going to do this
That's perfect for hands-free I mean that the perfect scenario so
Well done well done
Guys feel free if you have these like
Easy things send them our way because
The beauty of
All of the stuff is there's a long tail of things you can do in most of us just don't even think about it until it's
But basically tossed in her face
Almost done with this week show but first
I want to say because
Close
A big thank you
To all of the sponsors who have helped make the Internet of Things podcast possible
I started this as a full-time job back in
January
Companies
Supported the show and then you guys who are supporting my sponsors
Are really helping Kevin and I keep this going and actually make a whole career out of it
Which is crazy awesome
Suffolk Avenue
It's still awesome it's still awesome
So
Real quick
I want to just think wolf SSL
Ayla Networks
Xylem
Arm
Macadamia
Hewlett Packard Enterprises
Samsung
The Bluetooth Sig
Atlas RFID store
Skybell and level EDU
And level education
Aw
We're supporting the show this last year
This is a really big deal to me
And hopefully to our listeners who really liked the show and wanted
Genucel
Thank you guys so much and for the listeners
Feel free to go support our advertisers if and when you can
Kevin
I think that's it for this week show
All right so I guess folks have to stay tuned for the guest
You totally should
Stay tuned for
Quora
Card
Who's going to talk about investment Trends where he thinks the internet of things is going to shape up
It's a really good interview so hopefully you guys will enjoy it
And Kevin
Thank you so much for
Doing this with me
This week
And I'll see you next week sounds great thanks
We are interrupting the podcast with the message from our sponsor sponsor is Samsung
And I have Mark Wright director of product management
At Samsung
From the very beginning I have heard much about Samsung
Module Hardware side and also on the cloud side
Can you just give me a quick overview.
Put this all together for me
Arctic
Is an antonym platform
That integrates modules
What security have pre-programmed the connectivity so that they have secure transport
Into a cloud
So where we can virtualize products
We can then store data from those products
Control products manage those products
And then it's also
Rapt
In an API first
Design methodology so people can
Then also writes drawing apps for those products
And also do connections to other services and other cloud
Okay so this sounds a lot like something that manufacturers might be interested in
Systems integrators and I heard you say security a couple times so I'd love for you to talk to me
About what's unique
Here on Arctic
We have an end-to-end platform
For manufacturers
Systems integrators
To use in creating product iot connected product
But as We Know
You know from any of the reports
And even things that are going on in the world right now security is top-of-mind
We sealed platform development.
The best place to
To put security think it through at the beginning
And
Been implemented
And what we've implemented for security is a best-in-class methodology known as AAA security
It's Authentication
Authorization and ability to audit
What we do there is we have Hannah Kate
The user and a device
So that falls into the module offering that we have
Write and in the software we have for that software for onboarding
The end product
We Them secure the trance
Sport into the cloud
So the second thing we offer is authorization
So what authorization
Is the user
That utilizing this
Product
Do they have the proper role are they authorized
To do what they are trying to do
And we use certificate-based Authentication
For that process
And then we have the ability to audit what has happened
In addition to security what are the other benefits of having an end-to-end
Tell the benefits of an end-to-end platform
Are that when a manufacturer is looking at
Building a thing to be iot connected
It's a change in their business
Generally for a manufacturer
There is the electronics there's the software there's the product
But now on top of that they have to consider RF design they have to consider protocol they have to consider cloud
I also have to consider
Mobile app development
And each of these
Are additional software development efforts that they have to do on top of their normal product developer
So utilizing an end-to-end platform
Simplify stock
And gives them single SDK
Where can I find
You can find out more at dub dub dub
Arctic. IO that's Arctic artik. IO
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is gaurav Garg who is a partner at
Wing venture
Hi darling how are you doing
Great
Thanks for having
I am super glad so basically
You guys
Actually earlier this year wrote a really awesome report that delved into kind of some funding
Not just funding information but also Trends in The Internet of Things space and I will link to that in the show notes but I thought it'd be fun
Fun to have you on here to talk about
Kind of
What you think the role of the internet of things is going to be
Going forward and how that's kind of influence in your investment strategy
Let's dig in if I'm looking at this world how do I break up the opportunities
I had
So there are very practical things that you mention like for example security
Place to be
Authorized user interaction there's also
Lake life cycle management there's so much to think about
So
Where do you think the date opportunities
Are that makes sense from this maybe not the ones we can't see cuz who knows what those are
But some of the ones that are a little bit more visible
What looks the first thing is
If you think about what we talked about
It would seem a patent
They at
Driven by iot in various definitions of iot
Technology ecosystem will probably expand
Buy a very large amount relative Americans today
Maybe for 5X
And occupy an even larger portion of GDP than it does today
It's not very much
Whatever is kind of every decade right
Footprint of the technology Industries got up by 5 to 10 a.m.
Imagine that happening enabled
Baidu news
So
Where are we in the life cycle this earlier very early
Maybe
1% aloe vera
The way I look at it is that
Any new ecosystem like this
Did usually starts with
Semiconductors
Which are
August a hard place to invest
Blood in iot
One can imagine
In the short-term
Meaning the next 4-5 years
That there will be opportunities driven by specialized semiconductors I'm not an expert in semiconductors
Imagination
But the power honesty
No pun intended
You're going to have to stop at semiconductors
Then there's a phase of Platforms in
Assistance
Which becomes important
Yeah stings proliferate
And
Come off
Operating systems that are
Peterbilt for
Industrial
Networks from 30 years ago or beds
For computer said we as human beings interact with
New platforms to be created for iotv
As Wheels
Some of these tax on services
Like
What do you need to do in the cloud to collect Olive
Sustaita
How do you deal with security
So on and so forth
Of course I will be
A normal amount of investment as well in the actual sings themselves
Sambal fish was saying
Any ideas like drones
And
At some point
They'll be a set of applications
And message
For all of the things as well as the applications to talk to each other which will probably be the biggest slice of
The pie
A lot of that we cannot imagine today because we don't have massive
Deployment
IPhone came out in
When did we really start
Saying native mobile applications like uber that wouldn't make sense on the desktop
Took a few years I mean never there
But it took a few years before they really started taking off something will happen here
Stevia proliferation of platforms and creative people
But applications that really can't
Take off today but that ultimately will be
The largest piece of economic pie
It just so people know
IPhone came out in 07 in the App Store
Which was the big
The Big Kahuna
Came out in 08
Yeah thank you
But I think of
What to invest
Austin today
The concentration of investment is going to be in the actual thing
But you're going to be presented as vertical applications today
Or
Platforms
Isabella stats form like services
That's what people are going.
The notion of what applications run on these things and how do they talk to each other
Beverly bits and pieces but it's still a little bit toy
And we're not quite there yet
A ninja
Kind of report you actually
Bless you all for doing this cuz you guys names like
You found 700 different
Platforms
Platform
And I was like oh I feel you man I
I feel like I've met at least 300
So
What do you think the fate of these platforms is and what is maybe a sustainable
Look like I don't even know if that's the right way to parse
It's like a credible number of companies trying to be platforms or what
I would love to get your
In industrial applications or anything
Things like cars
They look like men
The closest Sam's today
And the person that makes a car or make
X-ray machine
Whatever you think of those other things as well
They have this vertical stack where they control August
The reality is
Dad
We're going to get to a word
Where
Software that runs in cars or an industrial machine
In all things in general
Is going to come
Partially
From software developer
That have nothing to do with that particular car mats
Exit right in the world of distributed applications and
The weather please
Disco Donnie
Together now
All of that
Means that they're going to be some very rich ecosystems
Develop software in to write applications
And like most are forms of
Today my guess is
Those
Can attract the most Developers
Linda hearts and Minds moving what that looks like in the future
I don't think it's going to be
Steak mobile platforms which is basically two or three operating systems on the desktop
Which was similar
I think I ought to be out of necessity they will be more than one or two
But I don't think it's going to be 600
How to put a finger on it but
Is Ewa Beach some concentrations of ecosystems depending on
Types of devices.
Just picked up a really fun thought exercise for iot I think's going to develop
Vertically or horizontally
If you're kind of thinking about being a plateau
So that could be horizontal by Pio
Verses like I'm going to build something for
Restaurants
Beverly some places where they will be vertical development cars that are obvious one
The stars are going to be
How's a large part of the it conomy places which have specialized needs you have this 4000 lb
Vehicle traveling at 80 miles an hour that is suddenly connected in
Does a
Lot of implications of stats relative to
I like boat ride
Or my telephone
I suspect that just because of the outside
Fraction of economy that is occupied by the Auto industry
And
Because it is very far along and getting connected
Cost example of a place that you can imagine
Will probably be
List of consumer products
Where
Because you want companies will attempt
I have that song Feeling sexy app on Google
Have their own horses in the race already
Hard for me to
Think about how
And small independent company can become platform player in consumer products
That just seems super hot to me
I didn't get the answer is it's going to be a little bit up
Let's talk about Enterprise iot
I'd love to see how you break down of Internet of Things world is it consumer Enterprise Industrial
Does multiple categories does industrial designer prized as wearables does home
Des health
Does Auto
All of these are probably already
Looks like by the way
And I don't know very well
That could be an overlay across some of these things or
An independent entity all together
And then there's also
Dirt of public places
Where are you know Stadium train stations coffee shops restaurants on so far to wear
Romani people occupying buildings
Where
For not employed
Do you guys also I feel like you had a drone category in your research
Search as well
Yeah
I'm sorry I forgot it
I wanted to see if
You guys have less you had a sudden like
Good point I still have
Difficulty believing
Dad
Jason the United States
CSA score
Police drones for every purpose
Possible
Send you're well aware that they've been fairly conservative so far
I can imagine that explain drones
It's already in use today
Which require airport at all sorts of regulations
Starting user security
Surveillance
Fan agriculture pretty heavily
Symptoms of
Piloted Vehicles as well as drones
But I have a really tough time believing these
Quadcopter
Type drones are
Going to be given free rein by the FAA to do
What everyone imagines can do
That's part of the reason we being a little bit more
Circumspect at least for the US market
That makes sense and like one of the big things I think about when I'm thinking about iot
When you're dealing with the internet of things in this concept of data being everywhere and everything being connected
Scalability really matters
If you're going to think about
Platformer
And from a regulatory perspective
It doesn't feel like drones are going to be scalable
Yeah
Who knows how the FAA will deal with it and maybe technology
But
I just
You know when you hit all the tales about
Drugs being delivered over the Border by drones Southern South America guns getting delivered to prison spy drones
I just I have a tough time believing
Bed in the United States
Just going to be
Go to free rein red rose can do whatever they want
Sure and I can imagine like UCI Pharmacy drone
Planet
The sky are like
Just a
Maybe this is
Some good drugs
Okay
Let's go
Touch on some of these categories so wearables actually is really interesting because we've had a couple deals in 2015
Wearables was super hot even consumers love them
It feels like we're heading into like a retrenchment on wearables
And I am curious
Where you think that my
Old temperature of reality
That's the truth of the matter is
They haven't been doing very much so far
And
As they do more
And if they develop more sensors
Centos become more useful
They'll get deployed in
Various ways
Sorry I have an Apple Watch I use it all the time
And frankly what I like more about it
Funnily enough
Notifications
Dan
If measuring
You know the number of steps I walked today
It just tells you that it's
None of the variables are
Let me they been doing a little bit but
It's been fairly restricted
But one can imagine like I'd like to have a variable that measure my blood sugar all the time I don't know if
If you could be integrated into my Apple watch
Boy
But that be superheroes
Let's go back to this concept of The Internet of Things
Because
I think what is most baby. Most disruptive but I think one of the things that we don't
Really comprehend yet is the fact that
Computers used to be built kind of for individuals
Or to be owned by entertainment One Singular entity.
Consumer
Enterprise when we start putting in everything
It's impossible to have a one-to-one
Relationship with
So
Like that's for me upkeep standpoint
Stampy
Even the way we have it now isn't really sustainable where I have to have an app that works with the specific
Product on my phone for exam
So how do you think
That is going to evolve what even needs to have
Wow I mean that's such an interesting area
And you start thinking about security you think about
Policy
You think about public policy in terms of who has access to what
But also on an everyday basis
What types of services are being enabled
Every LED light in the future has a camera built in
What does that mean the the Spheres of control
An access
Bar a day obviously
Russell the fact
Put it very well it is
They're going to be many
Science
Off the information that comes out
And many people looking to sort
Vegas Nevada
Birth control
In spheres that they are given permission to enter
So
Lot of possibilities
In areas like Administration
Security computer vision even
Genesis Next Generation environmental control applications all of that
Public places
This is quite possible and and quite interesting
So what role do you think the government
Either
Federal level or even a municipal level if you're starting to deploy these things
What is their role in the
And then what is your role is like a citizen
I just think these things are so far forward that regulation cats always catches up to Innovation right eventually
Hopefully I don't think people are going to know what it means for a few years
So
I agree I just thinking about like some
I was thinking about things
Cameras
Hurry up we have red light cameras in cities kind of can program
Like the yellow lights to be super short so more people get caught in the red light
Right
If you start thinking it
About that is just one example of a very low-tech
Thing happening
When you start thinking about life
Parking meters that are digitized
Basically even having access to see all crime in a city and figuring out
Cuda charge
It feels like we're going to need like an oversight board that is not accountable to
That particular
Municipal government
So I've been thinking a standard
Department of weights and measures Department of Agriculture things
Gasoline dispension that we have today
How do you bring some model
The general account
Accounting Office GAO
Connected cities I don't know
An example would be
If there was a carbon monoxide sensor in a car
And it goes off
Do you want the car to call 911
I'll have the police come in
You don't help you or is that an invasion of privacy
Should you roll the windows down and call the ambulance immediately
Whether or not you requested it
And you know you can imagine variations of that
Gesso
What is the Concorde send
Said you were in trouble or
What is the cost of the sense that you're drunk
From the driving is that a public
Hollister
I was going to say that's probably a very
That's an excellent news
By the way there's a company that can already do that
And they're selling the product to commercial Reb
Operators
And forever for all these non-british
English speakers out their lorries are
Tractor trailers
Or Siamese depending on where you live in the US
Yes those are those are exactly the sort of things
Once you have automation coming into these if you don't come up with policies around automation it's going to be
Really exciting and
We could also say that you know if you're drunk instead of calling police your car just doesn't start
Which is like
Basically the robots conspiring
Against you
Or
But if they don't have to tell anybody
So even for that exam
Where someone sufficiently drunk you don't want them to be out in the road
As a hazard to other drivers
Yes but if they're car doesn't start then they wouldn't be just be safe
Questions radio drama decline
Okay
What date is there anything else you want to talk about I should ask
What are the trends you're looking to invest in you guys just raised a new fund of 250
And what are you guys looking to invest in
Iot security and policy that
State Optical right now and going to be an area that people are thinking about getting into their products over the next
Another area that was quite interested in his computer vision so this is
Really chine proliferation of cameras and
Types of cameras
Sarah going in everywhere
And what do you do with that information
Beyond
What Google Facebook like to do witches Drive advertising
This many other interests
Applications as well as quite interested in the services around connect
Vehicles
Going back to the beginning
All the fixings
Statin products
Temp services
There may be other services that Jack built on things are super interested in those as well
Pandora hard for me to Define I mean this example we talked about
With the carbon monoxide
Is that something the car company provides or is it somebody else
Adapter for the car
Has a software service
Right
Taking me many others like that
Auto stores
Services are enabled
That particular return policy
Services or
Services enabled by the fact that a certain thing. Connected
All of those are great interest
I think I think it's worth
Underline the fact that just because you own the sensor
Or just because you own the platform like the car for example
Doesn't mean
You're going to automatically win when it comes to delivering that service
And I think that's a really important thing that
People usually the bigger companies who own the platform 10/2
Havis Huber surround
Well we'll do it and will be amazing
Because we've made washing machines appliances or cars forever
And then the sensor guys
They seem to think they're amazing because
You can get sensors on things pretty easily
I'm curious like
Who will win and where
I don't know if you have
Stanley speaking you know
Become things of the past
Keep going and they have customers but
Very rarely today
Change
Dynamics of the future or become the Giants of
Dinosaur Next Generation facts
You see that all the time
All right will Gaara thank you so much for coming on the show this week I really appreciate
Yeah I think it was a pleasure
Well that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to
Sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot data