Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And this week on the show we got to
Awesome stuff
Kevin installed an ecobee3 in
Discovered
Something
Difficult
We're talking about Pokemon go
Just because everyone's talking about
Pokemon go
We got a new outdoor camera from nest
Its first product
Forever
We got smart car news and some other big news in the IRT space
But first
For my sponsor
Shively
Working on building connected product
Do it yourself
Its complex
Before you're up and running
Years you can't afford to wait
Accelerate your time-to-market
Do you risk your message
Expertise
Rio TX
The business radio
Award winnings Ivory platform will help you launch quickly
Securely and its tail
Learn more
That's
X i v e
Alright Kevin
Let's go
Take it off with
I don't know let's talk about your LG experience
Yeah what's up I think I said in the last show that I was moving and we did move in between then and now
Still unpacking but
I want the first things I did once I had
Found my new ecobee3 that I ordered
I try to install it
Well as anybody who
Has any covino's in for those who don't
It really needs
5 wires coming out of wall for the thermostat
Tips on being a common wire
And that is for I'm not mistaking just for the power the power up to
Keep the power on on the ecobee thermostat itself
Because if the ecobee has a
Touch screen
Explains on sofa
What's so
I only have 4 wires
Oh
Yeah but the townhouse that I moved into his Fulton mm so I'm not terribly surprised
You still have the original thermostat which was fine just a regular
Programmable
Thermostat
That shouldn't be a problem because included in any ecobee3 box is
Say happy birthday call
Tek
I forget what it stands for basically
Standard kit
So
If you use that or need that which I did
You actually have to crack open your HVAC system and find the circuit board of it which
Found no problem
And there I found 5 wires and 5 terminal
I'm like okay cool
The PCAT
As I understand it would essentially does is
You connect the 5 wires of the PE
Hey
To the circuit board of the HVAC system
And the wires you from HVAC system
You connect to the inside of the p e k
Any basically Bridges
5 wires into 4 I think it
Ty's the power through the yellow or green wire don't quote me on that but essentially kind of creative virtue
Show common wire
Got it
Yeah that's how it's supposed to work
Well no matter what I did once I hooked it all up and
And putting HVAC system back together and all that
Then showed power like the screen was on which was awesome cuz it wasn't on the first time
Without a common just to see what
I knew it was kind of
But basically
The thermostat work
You couldn't control it because you couldn't see it
So once I use the p e k
I had power d4b everything was good
Except when the air conditioning won't turn on
You would actually only blow the fan so the compressor outside was not on there was no
Cold air coming in
You have to realize
When we move last week
It was. 95 degrees and 90% humidity so we couldn't live without
Are
So am I, I don't have time to deal with this right now
Unconnected everything and reconnect it back to the original thermostat and then reconnected everything correctly
The HVAC system and just had air Michael do with his later
I found an excellent article on
Steve Jenkins blog and hopefully we can put it in the show notes
We will
Super it explains exactly what you need to do
What my issue was
In particular in every HVAC system is different of course
I had multiple wires in the HVAC
System control board connected to the same terminal
Send
Instructions are clear but they're not going to deal with every single
Nielsen arioso
I didn't realize I needed to keep certain wires connected and remove other wires and all that
And the last time I did this
I thought I had hit the
Switch on the HVAC system to flip the breakers in a power is going on and I
Didn't
And fortunately
When I was connecting some wires in there it's pretty tight space
Two waters
Are supposed to touch
Actually did
I had a spark
All of a sudden a little LED on my HVAC control board
Went dead and like all know I've got to control board
And it's really hot outside but I was
How to say was in a panic
I sat there after retinol over the shock as well I sat there just rubbing my fingers getting feeling back
And
Then I realize
There's a fuse on my control board in the HVAC system
I pulled it out
Turn off at 3
Fuse was
Alone
Which is that's yeah that's better than losing
Exactly
Exactly of course
We still had boxes everywhere I didn't have spare fuses so I went out to my
Car
When is the fuse box in my car that lowest amperage I can find them
Spare fuses
I make money just put this in and see if it
Brings back
Controller back to life
I did that
My LED popped up
I connect everything properly / Steve Jenkins article
Upstairs cast of the air
We had air condition
It all worked out in the end
It can be tricky and even say an eagle be instructions
If you need to install the Tek
They warned you you're going to have to mess with your control board of your HVAC system
You may can I come without you may want to get electrician etcetera etcetera of course
On everything
So I can do that
Yeah well
So Kevin's like
The wire hot
I'm going to install an HVAC system in the summer which is also the only time I install my new age
Back hurt my new thermostats and I
When we installed
Ecobee
And we did the ecobee smart SI cuz I installed 9 years ago
I know I need a
I'm sorry but
We actually had a similar problem
We actually had a
Because we had a 2-stage heat pump
You messed up our wiring a little bit but
Peekaboo people were super nice they haven't
Awesome support
If I don't know if Steve Jenkins had written his article cuz that did not come up in my Google searches
When I was dealing with this but
Let Kevin
Experience piano lesson
Not a lesson that
It's too hard
You shouldn't do it
Because you totally should I have never wire to thermostat and things are really
It's not hard
It's not I mean pretty much every HVAC system has
At least four wires maybe five
The ecobee system the kit
Should be able to manage it
No matter what
Give or take him in or what your situation is
Don't go what one word of advice don't go by the color of the wires because not every installer
Puts a red wire on the red terminal Green Mountain Regional Center Etc so make sure you're looking at what the terminals are more
As opposed to just looking at wire colors
But it really is easy it is
Honestly if I knew what I was doing the very first time if I had Steve's instructions
That would work for mice
Scenario
It probably was a 10-minute install literally maybe 15 is
It's not that difficult
Bright but would you like
I have no AC
It's 95 degrees
Yeah
The clock was running and I didn't want to everybody in my house to be like super hot especially if we have you know
Pakistan Pakistan live pets and it's just not good for anybody in this heat so
Needless to say it's all working yes I blew the fuse hello spark fixed it
Diego beats working fantastic I have included remote sensor which does presents and temperature
That's in
Right here in my office cuz that's where I am most of the day up on the second floor so
Ecobee will not go to away mode when I'm not downstairs like my Nest ID
Because of the sensor
Nice and you can actually buy extra sensors
Pro tip
Amateur tip
Is
Don't wire hot make sure you turn off your breaker
Into
I know, I thought you knew but
My bad
The other two
Is take a photograph
Of your wiring before you start removing wires
I do this
Before any install
You know I take off that plate
I'm faced with wires
It's stuck under Terminals and I'm like
Oh
This is so awesome in your gut
Changes like to start on wiring
No
Close up photo you are dead on
Correct on that and I actually did do that both at the thermostat and the HVAC control board before I mess with
Anything
I'm glad I did since I had to redo my wiring at the thermostat
Dancehall the first time
And I would have forgotten it like that a red jumper cable was actually between two terminals
My old thermostat so
Yeah
I still have the photos I probably will never get rid of them
You just never know
Dropbox file
Wiring photos
All right
So that's Kevin's experience
Don't let it scare you it's not scary please install and uninstall thermostats to your heart's content
It's super fun and worthwhile to feel like
I am the master of my home
Badoo turn off the breaker though okay
Let's talk about
The hottest
Staying since
My God
A Nintendo Wii maybe I can remember how people were like so hot
Now we're hyped up on
Pokemon go
It's interesting its and it's
You know
Nintendo mobile
Market that's transformed everything the past couple years until recently they put out me told me game
I think that's what it's called
Avatars basically it's a little social network he kind of thing and it was okay I installed it
I did not install Pokemon go which is an augmented reality game
From the same folks that created Ingress which I did used to play
Both of these rest created in conjunction with nianticlabs
Which was a Google company
Then was spun off as an independent company when Google
Transform into alphabets we can not an alphabet company it's now a standalone company
And
Basically you just like Ingress or people are familiar with that you run around you know how the real world and
There might be a Pokemon nearby and
You look at your camera on your screen on your phone which has access
Set the camera
So the screen is showing your
World around you that you can see and then occasionally will show a Pokemon that you have to capture and so on so forth
I didn't install it
I did ask my stepdaughter to yesterday and she's like I don't want to do it and then sure enough once she did
She's been playing it all the time
Awesome and I haven't installed it because
The one
When I was
Ready to install it
The servers were down or having trouble so I was like all I'll come back and get it then I was like
Plus I'm on vacation in
Nowheresville made so actually might be interesting
To see if there are
The points cuz there's probably far fewer people out there in general
And that doesn't mean there's fewer Pokemon capture
That's true
So
What's interesting in there a couple things that are interest
1 is
A lot of the social
Any other is this is a really
This might be the first mass-market use of AR
Which is augmented reality
Which is different from PR
AR
Superimposes
Digital stop on the real world
As opposed to BR which is like immersing all of you into an imaginary
Virtual world
And I've always been kind of
Alex Fierro had an AR game I don't know if you remember the little
I mean that they had this like game where you roll the ball and in like capture things
It was It was kind of fun but
And I think it over the real world is really with me
Making this
So compelling.
But
It's also posing a bit of a challenge
Because we've had people setting up Pokemon lures to grab
Tumblr people there with a then
Rob them
Their concerns from
People who
Are saying
That their homes or places like the Holocaust Music Museum
People are trying to catch
Pokemon
Fair
I think it's a really fun social
It is an end of the Holocaust Museum
Has me questioning why isn't there or should there be rather
A way to say my personal property or this Museum
Whatever this Landmark is
How do we make this out of bounds for these ar-type games because we don't want people
Visiting Holocaust Museum and not paying attention which really important there
Instead they're capturing imaginary Pokemon
There doesn't seem to be a way to do that yet and I think there should be
Well in and I stink
Niantic is probably recognized
Such a mess
Hector like holy cow
So I don't know if it'll be like
Their database
You know you can submit things kind of like you did
Google Maps
Crowdsourcing
Information
Like
And that would be kind of more interesting it
Infinitely more scalable probably
You know you'd want to quickly be able to like
No this is this is not where you want to go
And that that would be kind of like a wave extra
Taobao
It'll be
I can't wait to see what they come
Hopefully they're coming up with something I know people are very impatient to hear this so
We'll see but
I think it's great
Only the best
The best use of AR that I've seen
People use it
For you know
Fixing machines I've always said it could be interesting
Assembly like Ikea furniture
It's worth noting for people who have not yet installed it they might have read some stories that
The app actually if you sign in with your Google account cuz you can either sign with Google or with a Pokemon account
Bassani with Google
Literally the app had
Full access to your Google account
Massive scope
That's a bad thing
Apus
And since that
Report came out it which was confirmed
At 9 second said it was a mistake
And they have actually created an update for the app that you can
You basically revoke all the permissions and then reapply permissions and it only has maybe your email address in your you're
Have your account name and your name and so on
They reduce the scope from like everything to
A lot less what it should only have
Not
No option have access to your full Google account save for maybe a Google app
Essay for Google
All right
We should o
Because we mention the word
We mentioned the G word
We should mention
Google home
Time
Not an idiot
Okay
Which is good because we're moving into nest
We're not going to talk a lot about the
Because
Our Guest today is
Google
What is a product manager
Of Nest outdoor
Camera
They don't have another camera
I know but now they do
New products from nest
So this is actually nest
What is launching an outdoor camera
And
What's notable here is
There's there's
That's just watching it
First new product
It was acquired by
If we
We don't count its revised
Dispersion of Dropcam which was kind of just like
Every brand
It was a Rebrand of a slight design shift but nothing like
We could debate whether it outdoor cameras really a design shift
But it is
You because
In this camera
What they did this is a very nice thing to do
Something that most people probably wouldn't think about which is the adapter so this is actually a wired camera for outdoors
And everyone's like
They make the adapter so weatherproof
Could sit under a bank of snow or in a puddle of water
And still work which means you can plug it into any outdoor
Outlet on
If you have
And so it makes it much easier install so
I actually thought that was
Did they say what this is going to retail for
This is going to retail for 199
Pre-order it as of
Today
Today being Thursday
And
It won't ship though until September
And we'll talk we'll talk about some of the other stuff
In the interview but we did wanted
But you guys know that that's out there
It is going to compete with
There's outdoor cameras from Arlo which
I'm working with now
I'm also in the fall we're going to get
An outdoor camera from netatmo
Call the presents camera
And then there's the stick up cam
I'm laying
Which is
Wireless but has its own solar panel
And they're all in
French they're all
At Darla's are bit more
Tampa Bay stations
Stick up cam
Presents
1-99 range
Cool and then
I see that if you have a nest aware so
Subscription
It person alerts
As well
Yes
Then and we talked about that it's basically the camera
What's a dog
Car
Useful for
Send a text Sharon
UA new products
New products
You can learn a lot more
Frowned upon this camera
After later messages
I was going to sing a little after these messages
Talk about
Smart cars
And not Tesla
Not Tesla
Alibaba
Which is the
I will call it China's Amazon
Yeah that's fair I I did not know I mean we knew they weren't e-commerce
Play before I did not know that
Working on
Their own operating system for iot
Yeah it
Well they had the Arduino board
And they have the you know a switch is there iot OS
And
They're putting that in this car that's going to retail for
I think it's about 23,000
Now they're not selling at us so
Don't get your hopes up
But what's Happening Here is there putting this OS in there with the idea of creating
A smart car that can
Payments
Work with internet services like radio services I don't know all the type of things in this
Because
This makes sense because they are an e-commerce as we said like the Amazon of
China and it seems to me that most of the at least initial features in the you know s
Inside this car
Are all Commerce related so you can
Reserve and pay for parking spaces
You can pay for gas you can
Pay for coffee so it
The key word is pepepe where I guess
Bye bye bye
So it makes sense it's almost like if Amazon weird
Put
It's
Don't say her name but
The Voice services
Voice services in cars natively
So that you could do the same thing just you know
I'm heading out to the movies
Histamine
Buy some tickets for me
Pay for my parking let me order food whatever it maybe
Anythink Commerce
Cremated ashes
It just kind of fit
I don't know that I want that in my car and I granted I can't get this car but
Could this be a trending if so I don't I don't know that I want to let me know
It just moves everything from the phone to the
Car
It's going to move everything
To the phone
And of the car and your home hub
The idea is that it'll be so deeply integrated
And hopefully
Like they're talking about this is a platform that works with Chinese smart cities
Imagine if you
You pulled up to a parking meter
It communicated with your car like a 2 hours of parking
It's going to cost you ten bucks
And the accounts already there so you don't have to download like an app for every city that you're in
I mean
That's why
It done well
Adam poorly than yes you're going to be like
Play Everybody's shouting at me to buy stuff
Everywhere
Yeah we can definitely reduce barriers to make it easier to buy things and
And get Services you know maybe that maybe going to a parking garage in your example and as you check in you know normally we get a ticket
Google search for space
He could actually say there's a space on level two
Spot47
And
Is it $10 do you want it
You know so yes
Makes things easier
But I worry because
All these different operating systems and platforms moving to
Other devices now you
I want to use the F-word Bonnie's at fragmentation you know
So I pull in with my car that maybe it runs a voice
Services not using her name
Not
You know s
The Amazon Echo
Play services
So you know then
I mean I'm sure I could pay through normal means
But
It's not a major mishap
But I just worry that you don't send
It adds complexity at the endpoints
You know
When things don't work it's going to be
Worse than ever
When you can't park in the garage or you can't
Well I mean I know people now that won't shop at places that do not take Apple pay
Android pay or Samsung pay
Gogoat someplace else
Because to them it's more convenient I don't
Like maybe I didn't care in my wallet.
So what are we going to do we're going to drive our car parking lot and see who they take
They work with you know S I can't park here
You know what
I don't want that
I don't think that I can't imagine people living room on the table like that but I could be wrong
People did do that
With Apple
They didn't enter coming back around now too and adding
Support for the different payment services when they tried to
Focus on
Using only one for that
Bright it's going to be harder
Before it gets better
Sadly
All right
Will hear some quick news we're going to run down
First off
Canary
All In One Security device has signed a partnership this week with Liberty Mutual
End
This ties in with last week's podcast we had Ryan rice
II was at
American Family Insurance
I'm talking about
How people might buy this
Smart Home
So
Canary with Liberty Mutual what's going to happen is you get a discount
If you have a canary
Canary also has a partnership with State Farm
You don't share all your info
Cremation you only share some of it but the idea of like being able to
Monitor things while you're away is really
Compelling
Shopping burglaries also
So everyone wins
That should be good
Now I will stay
Canary was a partner with Apple homekit so if you are excited about getting a canary you may want to wait
The fragmentation issue
Because they're going to launch a second-generation product is going to be homekit compatible
And I know that a lot of people don't want to give up there
Personal information to get discounts on insurance
I kind of I understand that
But actually I'm doing it I'm doing it through Progressive with my auto insurance my wife and I both had to do a little
Odbc
Montreal the plugs in it Progressive gets
All of the data from our cars
And we get a discount in return for providing that data so
Any monies money I'll give it up
Next item on the news is
Let's see what is the next
GE
Predix
OTR
They signed a deal to partner with Azure so customers who are using critics as software
Hosted on GE predix cloud
Products which applications
Microsoft
And this is
This is actually
Grateful
So it's great for Michael
Because in my conversations with people
A big Industrial
Conglomerates
Their customers do not
I want to say they don't trust you either but they're like geru really a cloud provider
RIT Department
Feels better
Going with Mike
So
This is going to help GE get those customers who are like
I don't know about your Cloud it may be awesome but my it department is not keen on that you know cuz what's happening is
OT. Operational tag
Can the industrial tech people there like we love GE
But it Department
Has to get involved now with I like the industrial internet-of-things
I love Microsoft
So
This deal makes a lot of sense
And it's great for pretty much everyone involved in GE will still have its own cloud
For people who want to just stick their stuff there
But I imagine a lot of
Microsoft in
Let me just tell you Microsoft is either a marketing genius
Or they're really winning
A lot of iron
Deals
They've been killing it on the other side
Honestly
Obviously battling Google
Amazon Amazon web services
Several other traditional Cloud players
So this is I think they're doing really well they're doing what they need to do
Is
Stay
Relevant
In this club Meets World
So the other
Piece of news is really an app recommendation I did do this I'm on this week in Google
Recommended it there so you
You can just like skip ahead if you
I want to hear it again
But I had to tell everybody
The podcast because it's
It's called Alexa Alexa it's by the Unified
Unified computer
Intelligence Corporation
Yes ucic
If you Google Alexa and you see I see you're going to find it
It will put in the show notes as well
It's for iOS
Turn Android in all it does
Is you press a button
You bring it to your Amazon account
I thought you just press a button and you're like
Turn off living room lights you don't even have to say your name
And then
I didn't mean I've done it in my life
Wish I could say
C4 my netatmo camera
Is basically replicates the
Feature of the
Hardware remote that you can get
With
The echo
It doesn't play music so you can't set timers and you can't
But that's okay but but it's a software implementation of the hardware remote which is
Really clever
And this is
I thought it must have been eight months ago
It's not longer I said
I wish
This type of functionality was built into the
App that comes with the echo
You know why can't why do I need a Bluetooth remote to speak to the thing when I'm not in the same room that why can't I just use the app
Can my phone as microphone
Exactly how I do wish they would do a widget
That would be nice but are you 100% sure this is IOS as well because I'm looking icy it for Android
I lied to you you're right it is
Only
Android
Sorry so sorry people with the iOS
Tell if your side just went out from the iOS
Oh
So that I think
Is pretty much everything
That's all the News That's fit
I guess no need to talk about this week
Kevin Kevin was moving
And I am on vacation so
It's possible we missed some stuff
And you know what will come Circle back to it
And
I'm still recovering from
Trying myself
Yes
Don't wire hot
Who
No so I want to hear more about the nest outdoor Cam and I think I know who's going to tell
Yes stay tuned for May who
Naughty weather
Is a product manager at
Hey Rita break into the podcast for a message from Wolf SSL here I've got Larry stefanik
Who is the CEO Larry who is
CeCe worthy experts
On device security we've been working in the space for the last decade
We're now the most widely deployed
Security solution
For the iot with over a billion devices secured at this point
That is a lie
A devices
What goes into
Securing and IRT
So we think about three key things first of all
The the data in transit or the data between your device
And your cloud
So the the traditional are most popular way
To secure that data
Is through
The SSL protocol which is the protocol that is used
On the rest of the internet for securing
Data in transit
We also think a lot about
Securing data on the device
6 l
So encrypting
Data that you might
Have on your device that you
Needs to be private
And it finally we help companies
Make sure they're the firmware update
It's one of the clever things that attackers like to do
Two devices is install their firmware instead of yours
So what you need to do is Havasu
Secure Channel
To your device
The best way to do that the most common way to do that is through
SSL
And we do all of the above that's what we do
BrandsMart created where in Automotive
Industrial Automation consumer devices
In medical devices
And we address this wide range of markets
Through
A long list of Partnerships that we have with the silicone vendors in that the operating system vendors
Alright well
Refined
So just check us out and wolf ssl.com coyote
Hey everyone welcome back to the iot podcast I'm your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is mehu manual
Who is a product manager for the nest
Easier to talk about this big news today which is the release
New outdoor security camera
Hey man what are you doing
I'm getting great thanks for having me
Really appreciate it
I am super excited
Because
I love Outdoors
Security cameras I'm currently testing the Arlo's
I have an order in for the netatmo welcome
So now I'm like oh my gosh
Come September I should
Check out the
Nest outdoor cam
Tell us a little bit about what you guys were thinking
When you decided to go
Design
Sure
Take a step back
All experience using Nest cam indoor and we decided on a place of peace
That you wanted to go to the camera on
And yet realized after you
Joseph dropped MN
Users had told us
They want to use camera
If you want to secure their homes the benefit they when I get out of this protect their own
And if they want to protect their home
Look around today your security cameras better
Market
And you realize that most of the cameras either
Rely on a motion light sensor
And unfortunately this resulted in a camera
Either
Off all the time
Essentially dependent on Angela. Sanchez
Oscar results
And the question
As a user if you wanted to buy a camera
Woodley traffic camera
That actually stays off all the time
You know how can security camera be a camera that sees off all the time
An answer was very clear to us that we had to go to camera
Add stands guard 24/7
We also wanted to go to Canada Actually
130 degrees
Indian Knight and Day
Absolutely athletically beautiful so that my wife would actually
House vs bee industrial design that typically does cameras have
And lost
But actually texted bondage of the machine learning
That is available
Bill vision
Westchester
Pain
Okay
So let's dig into this little bit
The camera is
Wired so I have to have it plugged in
Are you told me that is ip65 rated which means it's good for rain dust and other outdoor use
It's adapter
Is actually a higher rating so I guess you told me it could be buried in snow which is super fun
I would love that here in Austin Tech
But that's okay
Mine is more like it will it melt
Beyonce all the cameras that are wired
Available sounds of your life that as a user of how to drill a hole in my
On walls actually take the virus the doctor
Bikes
Which essentially difficult puzzle DIY because yfu
Uses of calendula research
So what we did is we designed the first
Apple wireless adapter
Mitch is IP67 radio dimensions
/.
Inside a small being a pot of water
And I don't obviously recommend to put it inside of puddle of water
Videos season
Weather
And you could easily plug into your outdoor outlet installation
Got it yes
Because that is the reason most people are like sacrificing your wireless camera
I just don't want to mess with
Treeland stuff into
My house which is
Intimidating
Before you get to the software is
You guys have a microphone on this camera
Which I thought was kind of interesting because it means
I could talk to people and they can talk back to me
Why did you
Just realized the bunkers
Number one that's Run for the burglars of Dialga
Camera camera
And wild and Luke kissing
Queen for the house that they want to work like that
And if you can tell you is the camera there is a person in it
Camera
To get their attention and say hey
Why are you here okay
What's up can I help you
At that point in time and becomes a quite a bit of the trying to get their attention
That was a fighter
The second reason is that a lot of people you could just
Erin Broderick
Franchi Auto door
And that's right there is a delivery driver
So this seems like it might encroach a little bit on the video doorbell Market
Obviously you're going to tell me I should buy an outdoor nest
Instead of a video doorbell
Could these devices work
Together or do you really see them as
Little things that
Let's talk about software
You guys are introducing new software
This camera or is it a new Nest app for honest
Devices
It's a new one that's that for all NetSpend Eliza
Specifically for all net
Users and abusers
Will be able to use this
And then there are three critical
Teachers that were bringing it back
One of them is
Dropping users had enjoyed through.
We're bringing that to netcam as well
And that feature allows you to
Shadow video feed
Off your camera
Your neighbor out your nanny or two grandparents
II
Features are called spaces
And then as I mentioned early on little bit
Feature that allows you
Pictures of beautiful to rectangular few of the radio stations within that's how it in their house
Living room
Dining room wherever they have police camera
It is that a beautiful
What it takes
All the connected devices
Are protected or any other devices
Puts it in between the spindle space
Odoo user
Now I no longer have it
Think about whether this thermostat
Or downstairs living room or upstairs
Now the states of southeast
Easiest way to
Absolute
Teachers that we are introducing which is available to all natural
Subscribers
But has yellow on Dropcam
This feature is called person
And we really work
Hard
To understand
How to bring about the machine learning
Nei capabilities into this cameras and what you're trying to
Did you get that human behavior
So
Does humans
But you know that it's not there not perfect
Because we miss the things and we sometimes
Communicating
When there's a person in front of the camera there are times
And I kissed
Might be hidden behind your mailbox
Kind of spending only face is visible
Or they're just walking towards a vehicle in between toe only torso
So then we actually give you an ability
Still get the alert by saying the hay
And the reason behind his back we realized that ultimate judgment ultimate decider is you
You're the owner of your home Georgia
The Protector
And you want to
Used machine learning and AI
To augment your intelligence
Not just
Give me the answer
Which is black and white
Would you also be able to do facial recognition on top of this because I know that I have the same UPS
A notification
From my outdoor Nest cam
That's a great question
As I mentioned early on
With this journey we've started about a year ago
Work that journey in this is some definitely something Vivint
Thinking about it
Trying to figure out what is the best way to provide the benefits
Can you set an alarm
Okay and then a question about spaces
What is the visual
Component is it
Actually the rooms of
An image of the rooms at the cameras in that I'm seeing
Or is it like an iconography
Groupthink
Inspired rooms
So if you already have a nest
We have significant number of users with multiple next exercise their home then you will get the app
Show live view on the spaces that bus cameras belong
What's the weather in living room or backyard
I'll try and Yarbrough upstairs Loft
Thermostat does not have
The actual
Next time. Just be obvious
You have to use iconografia some of the rake
Create spaces and allow users
Can you control other Nest devices from that view or do you just see like
Oh there's a thermostat here and it said a text
You can easily tap on the same icons that you had the same
Concept
Tap on it and easily
Think about it
Is that
As you bring number of devices
Number of connected devices
For your home
Lolly as a user you would want one app
But you're going to want
But this is a really easy day for you sister navigate the various connected devices.
If we
Inside their home
And there are many press reports earlier about Nest developing some sort of security home security hub
And is that something that still under development or does this kind of
Portfolio free
JCPenney
Different categories in brightness for all this evaluating
Vegas
Want to do what is right by customers on
Today I can talk about
Can tell you that
All right question
For you I love
Set Nest I'd love to understand
How you guys
This particular product
Kind of working with nest
You guys have so many partner
Are there any Things Are
Thinking about here it's
Yasso Alden
Converse with nest
Integration that Nest cam indoor has but harness them as
Do all will work
Is new Nest cam outdoor so for example
Witness
Protect
You know if there is a security man that's come automatically turns on at the court
Regardless of whether you have a nest aware subscription or not
We will do the same thing here as well
In a similar fashion
Philips Hue Philips Hue if there is an activity detected you can set your Philips hue light bulb
Turn on automatic
And it all the snack that 8tracks
Integration that we already have into enough tomorrow
Awesome alright majul thanks so much for coming on the show this
Thank you very much that's it for this week's show please join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
And thanks for listening