Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And my Coast
Kevin tofel
This week we've got a great show for you we have got
Review of the week transfer process switch
More on that soon
About the Google pixel and Google Assistant
We've got
Whole section on thermostats
You guys
A light section
A light section that will become clear
We're going to talk about
Migos all in on Philips light bulbs and maybe something about
The echos new calorie counting skill
We also have an ad from HP
Talk about analytics app
The edge
And
Mike Wolfe
Is Going to Be Our Guest today
Mike Wolfe is creative the smart Kitchen Summit so we're going to talk about couldn't get it cookie
Yeah he's a Foreigner he's a former coworker to my love
Yes
We are keeping
Cult of gigaohm alive
All right
Costa Coffee
We're keeping
Update
All right
First we have a message from our sponsor
Arm
Arm engineer magically this year became just V American the summit Annapurna
Wearable and mobile technologies that made his journey safer and more predictable so come join me
2016 Expedition and describe how small lightweight low-power devices are
Arm techcon 2016 October 25th through the 27th in Santa Clara
A-arm petco.com
So
Let's gets
Started with the show
Kevin guess what I did
I'm guessing you got a new wink
I did actually I got that earlier but they told me to wait to make sure my my software was all up-to-date
So last night I transferred my old wink Hub my V1
To the V2 version 2 Hub
And I will say two things about
It worked
Two words
This is really exciting it actually work
So
So what's the process like
The process is like
This you
Plug-in
The new hub
You keep your ass so you keep your old Hub plugged in
You plug in the new hub
You can either connect
Headed to ethernet or you can use because now it has an Ethernet port
Or you can connect to Wi-Fi I like to just to do it over Wi-Fi because
One of the hubs to
Senior each other
So
You
Open your Wink app
And it's like
Wink
It's okay I think there's any wink you're like there is anyway
And you put it on your network
And this is the first time as an Android User that I've had something come on to my network
In a way
It was seamless because normally I actually have to turn off my
Cellular data on the Android because it's constantly
Trying to
Whenever I try to connect to a connected device the Wi-Fi process
Becomes all wacky
My phone's like
No we cannot be connected to the internet so that it dries and it messes up
Right because
Four people have
No setup say it echo or something similar
When can your case
You're actually connecting your phone for the app to whatever the device is directly over Wi-Fi
So the phone says hey I need my connectivity and that's probably what happens if
Falling back to Cellular
Exactly in
It's big frustrating thing
Is it happens to you a lot in her life is that happening just turn off your cellular
Temporarily just temporarily
Unless you like me and you
Please call me
Nobody calling me anymore
That's true
All right
That was a notable thing and I was excited about that
Sewveryeasy
Then it's like
You got an old wake up and would you like to transfer your programs and everything over
Like people yes I would
So if it bought for a minute and said the process will take approximately 10 minutes
And you will have to manually reconnect your Lutron light
And I was like
I was like that's okay cuz I've got a couple
What programs
So I said yes
The lights flashed it was very exciting
Pink blue green colors
And then
It was like hey I'm done
Now let's connect your Lutron
Actually it was really nice because it said hear the
Here are the four light switches we see
Do you want to connect them
It's at and I was like okay so I clicked on the connect button I walked over to the light switch and you basically hold down your light switch
Until it flashes
And then
Stop holding on and the wink makes his connection
So
That's how it's supposed to happen and that's actually what it does but for me and this is
This is actually been abuse of mind
For like
Ears
It has this affirmation error
It never tells you it's succeed
Might only about 50% of the time will tell me that
The connection has been successful
So mine actually timed out was like
Something's gone wrong
And then when it
I was like okay cancel
Then it would show up as
So
That's kind of odd
It is but it's not
For me it wasn't it
Especially
If you guys are going to do this and you know that's going to happen
Just wait and see if it connects cuz I was like dang it
I'm failing at this
But then I was like
YouTube manually had to do your Lutron stuff
But did you have other
Other things
Yeah okay so we'll be so it just carry over all the connections as for lack of a better word
To your other devices
And probably any robots and
Shortcuts on
Song
I was mid
Schedule item so my Halloween lights were on
They were scheduled to go off later that night
And lo and behold they did it was like nothing had changed
Titan Magic
And my doors unlocked and lock
So the Z-Wave
Just fine
Yes yes
It also works with the Zippy stuff
Garage door open and close just fine
And
I'm trying to think what else might be on there
I have some outlets on there and they worked so everything transferred seamlessly and it was
Other than the minor like
The Lutron isn't working
Oh wait it is
It was great so
If you're going to buy a new wink
I haven't live with it long enough to say wow this is
A real Improvement
Write more processing power there's
Bluetooth
In here
I don't have anything that I was like
So
I haven't lived with it enough to know that like
Do you really need this Hub if
If you have an existing
Happy wink
When this was first announced that's kind of where I was. I do I'm very happy with the wink Hub. I haven't liked do I need to upgrade
People again why I think the big draw here is the
Ethernet port
Ethernet maybe blue
Who has more things
StarTalk
You haven't
Right I don't have a lot of fun fact I don't think I have any Bluetooth devices in the house or smart home anyway
If I were looking at something then maybe I would upgrade of the sea
It would be nice I mean cuz like Bluetooth Mash isn't
All that
Two lights
Alps
A little bit better
But that's really the only reason I can think
Pick up right now or if you have the locks in your life
Woobox
That is the wink Hub and I really enjoyed it
And now Kevin
It's time for your show
Oh
Well actually not show until cuz I don't have something in hand to
Talk about
Oh okay so yes yes I do I'm holding right now
To the Google pixel
Reviews came out
And why do we care about that on the show
Welco's Google
As assistant
Built into the phone it's baked right in and
In fairness
Google Assistant if you're not familiar it really is a updated or rehash version of the
I don't want to say it so I'll just say the assistant
I want to say in exit off people's phones right now
The assistant feature that's already been an Android
Plus the Google on tap
Function which could scan your screen and show you web information based on what's on your screen so if your
You know searching for
Hotel monatik
Could pop up with directions and such
In any case it's all Now call Google assistance what's a rebranding its
Exclusive to the Google pixel phone
And you can speak to it and it's like a boss that will when teligent we speak back to you and
Show you information
But what it doesn't do
Yet
It really didn't somebody over computer wrote this article answer
It's actually pretty good article it says
Google pixel phone packs a powerful
Voice assistant
But it's no
Amazon Echo
And actually the article is dubbed
By The Echoes
Name
An impression
They were exactly
And that's really
A good observation and good point
Why isn't that
You know it
There just isn't enough third-party integration yet
And yet this
Service has been around for at least two maybe three years
And I would love to be able to get my new pixel which does arrive next
Text will have it not to show and tell but I'll have it
For the show
Next week
But it's just like
Will the episode which untapped potential there
And I'm sure Google is
Google is play nicely with others in the
Past so
You know it took
People forget this but Wendy Echo launched in December in the preview mode it didn't actually have any of the smart home stuff until
March and I didn't buy it until March 4th at recent that's a good point
And in it we also do have Google home that is
Coming out
Which
When I get mine
Yes or yes we are so that will actually directly
Compete against the Amazon Echo
For music and information and Smart Home
Capabilities although
Again comes down to Partners
There are not as many partners
With Google home there are with Amazon Echo so
Nests and if this then that I think
Yeah so it's on my wings not going to work with and that's all I can live with that
A Time
ESO the pieces are all there but they're still being put together I guess is my point it's kind of
I'm just disappointed that they're not on this
True first Google made by Google phone which is really one of the Keef exclusive features is the Google app
Assistant
But yet you're not going to be able to at least yet you don't control things with your voice from your phone
Just another Asian little disappointment on my part
I'll get over
With the echo
You can't control
Phone unless you download something like Rogers or
Lexi
I've been disappointed that for a while
Download Lex
INRI I know I could do that absolutely
Play it just it just
Now Amazon if you're listening
We don't need Bluetooth remotes when we have bluetooth on a phone that has a microphone
Anyway
Okay
Start
Let's talk about
Stats
Yeah
What do we have here
What do we have here what we talked about the ecobee Lite
That was sleet rumored Etc official
And it really is
Light because it's lighter and price at $169
Enoch little later and functionality because I do not see any mention of the ability to add one of the key feature
Pictures of ecobee remote sensors
I love Simon on that one
I can see their thinking in the thinking here is
They want to compete
With Nest at a lower price point
So
David she's not here
Yes
Kananaskis
Full price
Ss250
A lot of people actually say that they don't the sensor functionality isn't a huge thing to
The people who aren't crazy Cooling
Right right so
You know it's a learning thermostat connect all these things they're like
Hey that's cool I'll take it
So I can see is this like
World-changing news
Is it smart
And maybe we'll see a lower price nest
Possibly
And I
Because Honeywell
Actually just a couple weeks ago released
There were they actually change their thermostat lineup down for
I'm like 32
The lyric T5
And that is $149
Tyler's basically does everything
The Nest Inn
I guess that you could be like that
It doesn't
$150
Right
Directions to home
Catan
Isn't that so
It's a learning thermostat as well it's just not a
Not a digital thermostat
Yeah it looks what is it
Avenue said it look
It looks to me
Like an Apple Watch just not on your resident with a strap it's a it's a square
With rounded Corners thermostat
Just very basic looking
Looks nice I think it's appealing
It's kind of funny because Honeywell actually sued Nest over there circular design
How do you spell pioneer that circular
Babies harder to
Build I don't know enough
Enough about Manufacturing
So the other thermostat news in the section
Because why not
Nest changed its Auto away
Praising to eco
Because AutoWay confused people or people would put their
Thermostats on to Auto away to try to get the little leaves
Sleeveless vest
I forgot how to say
So they were like you know what let's just call it go and make people feel good cuz that's what they're being
Eco-friendly
Yeah I'm just looking at the
The news on this
Didn't really it like so now you've got you know
You can actually turn it to Ego in like turn it automatically to the leaf
Used to be
Like if you were right
Really jonesing for a leaf you had to turn in
Up in the
Summer or down in the winter
For me it's always up
Because Texas is still ungodly High here
October
But
That's how
I triggered Alief but
Now you can just turn it to eco
Feel good about yourself
Interesting
And you have to manually switch it back
Correct
Integer multiples of deer on each one of those Nest thermostats
There we go
Then they still have a way so
When you wander off
Your home will still going to a way and will trigger all these other thing
EXO
One of the reasons they did it is because people would be like let's tell that I'm away
And then like their lights and all sorts of stuff would go
Go crazy another were still at home and
Make sense
So there we go
Very exciting
Like I said there was a light section
Light section
Alright so
The other thing
I wanted to talk about this week
Is Phillips
Neither is there we go
I had to talk about these because I got the new richer color
Philips Hue
Light bulb
And
Amazing I used it like the gold standard for me was the life Expo
Because they could do these amazing greens and it made this beautiful turquoise blue that I love
Philips conduit
Until now
So now they have the richer color light bulbs
And I'm like well hot diggity
Everything is better although I still have unifor of the
Actually I like six of the old
Choose him like I don't want to upgrade them but
They can't do turquoise
I'm not spinning
How much are these out of curiosity are the same price as the old Philips Hue bulbs so that is 60
Taxable for
Downlights and
204 a starter kit with
The Hub Ann
3 volts
Ceph
It's not like I'm more expensive
They're the same price
Are you to replace with wood cost a lot of money but for people are buying the first time
The same price as before
Enable
And I like them
And
You know I know that I talked about a lot of different light bulbs on the show off tuck also
Starting this month
The new Philips Hue down lamps that I've been
Denso jonesing for
The last few years
BR30 flood lights that are
Are the white ones those are out
Now I believe
And they or maybe next week
And they're going to be 40 bucks Apple
So
Yay
Very exciting
And all the accessories that Phillips has makes this
Really like it's hard for me to go into other light bulbs now
Cuz they got everything
Fairly reasonable price these are $10 more than I think
Actually only $5 more than the osram
In color
Osram white lights in the BR30 s
So
I just feel like
Because of the The Hub that you need
For Philips bulbs
I just feel like there's a lock in kind of thing there because
But github doesn't work with many other things
Github works with
Everything
It even works with the Google home Kevin
Well I'm not saying it right you're you're correct your
I don't know
No yeah I guess that's what it is I guess that's what it is
Observing like you should see my little
Yeah I did
I don't want a hug for everything I add to my house I mean that just kind of silly to me
Do you know
I'm in Ontario makes a Drake has so many things
Work with existing outside I get that
You enjoy them that's all music
A picture a picture of your house like the Willy Wonka Factory with all these colors and
Lights go in them
Chocolate River
No chocolate River in Filipino you have to buy all these apps to actually do some really cool stuff with it because their app is pretty
Like run-of-the-mill
And nobody has a great UI yet for doing color transfer like
Changing colors in lights I'll be honest
Now if you want to change the color or cetacean you got to manually create it and then you
Call it something that you remember and then
You know you can you can do like
You can tell the echo
Pocono
Turn it to Sunset
That feels real
Silly silly
So
That's still something
Like I can't say make it turkey
All right final little thing because
Maybe you guys are as obsessed about this as I am but I like
Actually I don't like counting calories I theoretically want to count calories but I'm really lazy
I'd also like to eat so it
Depressing
I like consuming them
I like
But you can now ask the Amazon Echo
Hey
A
How many calories are in
A cinnamon roll
And she will tell you
Yes
And that's yes and that thank you Stacey for making me do that before the show detest it I will never have one again that I love them
I love.
How many calories are in a
I think it was around 330 per hundred grams of cinnamon roll at 9 just ordered 100 grams of 7
I can tell you that
But I actually have no idea what I
About a hundred pickup weight of a hundred paper clips which is
Not that much
Thank you
So there we have it
A lot of calories in a cinnamon roll the echo will tell you in
You will probably
All right
Stay tuned
We have
A message from our sponsor HP and then we also after that
A conversation with Michael Wolff
About
The smart kitchen
Where the service fits Reddit
Hey everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast for a word from our sponsor this we sponsor is Hewlett-Packard
Enterprise in to talk to us today about analytics at the edge we have dr.tom
Brad it she was a VP and general manager for servers and iot systems at hpe
Tom
We talked about the internet of things being about data
And you want to take it further and say that it's also about insights
And in fact the data
At the edge
At The Internet of Things
Is older and faster and bigger than all
All the types of Big Data come on
But what is more profound and I like to take to another level is it's the inside that's the right from the day
That's the Renwick
And then further after the inside is dry what action
Staking and I like to look at innisfree age there's the acquisition of the data analysis
Ebony action
And the business value or the
Scientific or engineering value is manifested in that flask
That's what you called the action
This whole segment is on analytics at the edge so why is doing this at the edge so essential
Action is the address where the Saints resign
NBC15 Flora city tram
Smart
Carsmart the building
And doing analytics at the edge
It's so crucial for 7
I'm very very quickly
It takes time to go to the cloud or just a location
With the information and get an answer back
What is bandwidth
Internet of Things presents a big analog data
Tremendous amount of data logging
Bamboo spikes
30 cost
One has to pay for
The bandwidth even if one has the bandwidth
Security
Location
Is exposing more vulnerable to cyber attacks and hack
This is
A duplication of resources when one caches and storage data at the engine the needs to send it all back to
Play center there will be some
Duplication of resource is this notion of corruption and reliability
It's too flat
And packets to drop
And descendants of 7 is
Are there a corporate or federal rules and regulations that govern
A transfer of data
Alright give him those 7 reasons
What is h
Have. For hair
Hpe offers both
The cloud approach to doing analytics in the aisle seat and also the edge approach
Two doing analytics in the iot
Depending on what is needed we offer very deep
Computing
Aerobus manageability
And we manifested those
It systems Analytics
Keep computing
Accelerate insight
Sherwin new product line called edgeline systems
East Edge line systems converge
D Computing with enterprise-class manageability right at the edge computing
Is up to 60
Concours out of the edge
Where can we find out more about Hewlett-Packard
You can find more by going to our website
Hpe.com
Flash iot alright thank you
Hey everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
Today's guest is Mike Wolfe who is the creator of the smart Kitchen Summit
And an analyst who covers this Ma
Hey Mike how are you doing
You forgot friend of the show
Download why did I forgot friendship not just a friend of the show but if
A friend of mine
Work together known each other
For a long time
Before I had this show and even worked with him at gigaom I used to
Call him because he was a
Your wireless analyst covering things like Bluetooth
Wireless in digital home
At ABI research way-back-when about 10 years ago
I know
We're so old
We are
I'm old
You look the same I've got a lot of gray hair
I'm a vampire in
You got gray hair
Here we go
So Mike you recently did
This event is smart
Kitchen Summit which was
Awesome
I loved it I loved attending it
And I walked away from it and I said
Bismarck kitchen is dumb
So that was my take
You'd loved it
But then you said this Market
Is dumb
You know nothing works together
You tell me
What is the smart
Kitchen what is this tell me what your vision is here
It's about
New technologies coming into the kitchen surrounding food
And in just kind of hoping to reinvent that way then that's something as simple as that connected
Meat thermometer
To something like the juicero which isn't it
Like an entire
Indecision trees were like an ecosystem where this is complete vertical integration
Based on the fact that
Music connected device
It looks up and down
Of the supply chain
There's a lot of different aspects to it enough reasonable to read mention of cooking
Was that Sia Precision cooking
Etc there's just a lot of different
Things that are now trying to change the way we cook Away by food we eat
That's one of the reasons I wanted Savannah just kind of Explorer all that together
So
Let's break this down because you have
Basically cover the entire
Basically what you're talking about is like adding intelligence to the
Where is the most
Stuff happening where is the real like where where we making actual strides here
There's obviously
Big Appliance makers that are looking at okay now we can actually connect these things at intelligence
And have data you know we've never really had
If you're an appliance manufacturer even you're a food maker you never had
Point of consumption data
Before
And so that's actually possible you're starting to see
These platforms be put in place with an arsenic in it but also you know, like perfect company
Jackie spun out of data business I'm were there actually doing datametrics for people who sell things like vodka
And they can give you
Did around the types of drinks people are making it in Fairly real time so that's actually pretty fascinating stuff all that
Information that Sgt based probably on surveys before
Or Nielsen type of panels
That's why I think that's really exciting
If you're some sort of company that
The mix food or provides consumables into the home
Okay and we should
Stop here and say the perfect company
Makes
It's a scale
For the kitchen
And
It is a scale that can be used to measure out cocktails
Stood for baking
Or even they just launched at your show
Making like
Smoothies in a blender
That's
For everyone who's like what who's this
It's a cheap scale it's a cheap scale but it's a skill that actually provides metrics they actually partnered with Vitamix
Two people probably know from
People making platters slender Evergreen
And they met last year might have been
I think big
Harder makers who sell stuff in the small pint division at Target or whatever want to make these things more intelligent
Where you at you and I know that this is true that is okay
What can you do with that makes it interesting I think
Xiaomi providing data metric
To the people are selling food and somebody that is interesting
Prophetic a lot of it's about like how can you make the consumers lives better cuz the consumers who's the one who puts down the hard-earned cash
Two different themes I saw emerging out of this as you know
Automation and intelligence could be out at 2
Devices for cooking
So let's go into this cuz
There are
I heard two kind of different audiences kind of jumped out at me
At your show
When was
We're going to teach people who don't know how to cook how to cook cuz Millennials have grown up and they know nothing about cooking
To was
People who want to make
Crazy fancy or esoteric stuff
Like the picobrew and all the sous vide
And there's the Practical Cooks who just want a fast dinner on the table this is me I was bugging people I was like
When can you have something that looks at what I have in cheddar it's a grocery list or looks at my family's likes it is like
Like cures like
4 meals you can make this week in less than 30
So
Starting with that let's talk about what you saw for the kind of
Learn docker
Can a fancy expertise kind of
Area
What interesting things I think
A lot of the same underlying technology service both of those archetypes
Is Iran a panel
During the day and we talked about this some of these archetypes
What are things we can I reach the conclusion of
I may be one of these
These people in the middle wig
And I may be a different person
On the weekend so if I'm tired
My kids are beating it out for me
I know I have to provide them with some food I made
Have some sort of
Device that has a web automation that makes my life easier
Button on the weekend I want maybe some sort of guidance to give me a safety net to take my scrap a higher level
I don't know if you served those two audiences with the same piece of technology
Maybe you can with something like a thermomix
Or or something like the Hess in Q thermomix is like I had never heard of this but this is like
$1,800 piece of
It's a crazy I have one of my house I'm trying it out it's mainly been sold in Europe
To the tune of a couple million a year
Well in Europe
Just now bringing it to the US it's
It's a device that's like one of these 10 in one devices
It's like the instant pot
Steroids
Is it is it is
But it's not when he's crazy and if you seen in these are craske robotic
Types of cooking devices from somebody San Francisco
Took him to sing is more
Two more practical and then ready for Market
To get back to where you asked about there are these different
Audiences
A lot of the same technology in particular Automation and in some sort of like intelligence
Surenos
But ultimately is probably different type of product
That is serving those types of people and we have both cuz I I have two practical me that I have like the guy wants
To be like a better home chef
What seems like a good idea for
People who are like
For People Like Us in the middle of the week
My weekday shift
Acting like a really cool party sure could be something like the Artesian like actually some sort of like robotic
Drink mixer I think with itin terrible mixing drinks
That was another start that we had
Call the bar startups I will say I love them and Theory
And for a party trick
But they all have these tubes and you got to fill things up with alcohol
I feel like something like that the scales are a little bit nicer because you could just stick everything on there and they take care
Portions for
I will say it having you use the thermomix which is a scale bass system that there's real utility there cuz you just
You're literally just pouring drinks in it and you watch the little
Geico
So you're right that actually
That works really well scale BAE systems work really well if you
Don't want to pull up measuring cups to catch raso
Yeah
The Gooden Center I think it was called the the Nema
I like that I mean I do think
Having
Routers with serious food allergies
If that they could provide some sort of
Device where they can go out
Teeter or even something at home then know that they're not going to flake pop up like a
Puffer fish
I think there's real value in that
Those are just a couple of Pokemon that I think there's a lot of different technology
Did you try the juicero juice did you like it
I did like the juicero
Snail to me this feels
Less like a home Gadget
More like a
A commercial kitchen kind of
Anything because
There are two things that I learned about
Did you Sarah is a $700 device
What is 5 to $7
Packets and it's cold pressed
Juice in the ingredients take hold the whole time
The first thing that was really cool is
The CEO is trying to build a business around basically
Iot everywhere
So he's taking for granted that he's got to guarantee
Cold Supply Chain which is really awesome
Cuz that's
So far been really hard to do really Out Of Reach unless you're like
Like really wealthy
Refrigerated
Tracks right
That I didn't know is that
These juice packets because they're fresh fruits and vegetables you can actually use them in cooking which I thought
It's kind of fun
The reason I wanted
Him to get out season 2 like a kind of almost a case study because Lake Easton something really unique way
What you would do with this end-to-end
From the home all the way back
Supply chain created this entire
Secretion and delivery system
If he talked about how he tried to go out and talk to food processing plants
Create this
In Dino
Tino Martinez, she really did that in her how much she had this vision is headphone
Beginning
Yeah that's why they raised on $1000000 to kind of Bill out this entire
Everything I think you're right
I think initially it'll do well in
Restaurants near Michael vultaggio
This that's what we chef
He really said about the juicer
Because he says don't want to necessarily put cold pressed juice
Juicers in there in there
Space-constrained kitchens
I also they're going to do well in my
Cafeterias like places like Google
High-end cafeterias within not Heinz Ketchup
But over time if they get to the point where they can reduce the cost and I could see you like this one really popular
I think you get it pulled out of three or four in the dollar price point
This is a premium product people who get cold pressed juice or not
People hurting for money
They're willing to spend $10 at retail for a glass of juice
So I don't think this
The sticker shock of $7 is really that shocking to them
Cuz they have this lifestyle with their want to spend that type of money
That is a lot of money
That was one of the other things I noticed so all of these devices that you know oven is $1,500 I can't remember
How much the hestan cue
Cooking setup which is a pan and
Induction cooker that
You don't know what's the temperature of the pan and what you're trying to cook it
Basically cook set
All of these things feel
Like I don't know you remember bread machines from like the 80s
They feel like
Bread machine
Switch
You know everyone loves warm baked bread but very few people kept their bread machine somewhere like
Yeah. I'm still making it
When asked
Chris Young chefsteps hear what is going to be
The fondue Machine versus like something that has
Real sticking power that's still
Ultimate Eternal question ever talk about
New devices in the kitchen cuz if you know it's kind of become a cliche now
Major Innovation microwave in the microwave
So you know
I hope you know I was just going back into asking a damn Visa buys it and I know what's going on with your cooking tonight
That's really interesting to me
Cruises embracing that
Cuz I feel like that that's really interesting
The guys from Nova Steve got up and talked about okay we want to do a Combi oven I sent you a copy of them for the kitchen
No one's really down a really good consumer, Ava and end in does no doubt that steam actually adds water
An oven that has
You know heating but I'll sounds like steam Alamance excetera Apso
They're really popular in
In professional kitchens but no one's really consumer eyes. Well
So
That is the ultimate ROM
Question what is a gadget in like a parlor trick versus what has real staying power
I don't think that all these things are expensive we talked about the high price but I think you know you're obviously sing low price sous vide circulator as you have another perfect
Scale
Any price went down there
What sticks is can be really interesting
I think the appliance manufacturers big Appliance manufacturers embracing things like in it is really interesting
How fast has become common features and how much consumers use those walls also be interesting to watch
Okay fair enough
And then
I feel like cooking and kitchens today like everything's pretty attitude
Even if I get like another device in my
My kitchen
Is there anything that
We're going to replace so should I be like hey
My next house isn't going to have
Adamant
I didn't like I-4 like in in 10 years my house will have a thermostat
Right
Some people like you won't carry Keys is there anything in the kitchen that you're like
Hey
Stacey you're going to get rid of your garbage.
I don't know I don't know
If you get rid of things I think that's one of the things we're talking about on the first day is like
Jonny Gray
Talk about your there's only so much space you have
Anyang
Kitchen countertops
That is a real consideration Bachelor
You're fighting for space
And so if something comes maybe something else
To go
So that's really interesting conversation I think that's why
People like home builders need to be part of this conversation
I think that's Broderick
The Justice smart kitchen right I think
Overtime
As more technology comes into our lives
We have technology goes into the fabric of
The countertops in the beams and all that
Like that's a really interesting conversation to have
So the built-in appliances
If you build an appliance like an oven
And it has technology for home builder
You better make sure that that has a lifespan of
10 / 20 years
And Samsung doesn't decide to say
Okay we're going to move on because we thought this would be really great I did have a Twitter client
In our oven
So we could
What is baking
Now it's not going to work this we decided not to support that software anymore so
I don't know if I answer your question directly as in the say I think that's a big important conversation for not only the pipe like home builders accept
You did not answer me
But that's okay I'm just thinking back like high-end kitchens now usually have to have a wine
4hr beverage fridge
The kitchen
And that's probably the last big new appliances microwave but I think wine fridges
Probably
Settle Inn
I think if you're just talking about small appliances that's a limited conversation to mean old family the appliances we buy or getting
Smarter whether that's like a
Adding Wi-Fi or Bluetooth to a coffee maker
But I also think it's going to go beyond that so there's a lot of starts doing things like okay how can we
Do
Right pantries that are smarter to kind of know what's in there and in
And how does that work
How does a
I drink a grocery list I really do I want
My kitchen to tell me
What I need to buy to make
My Nail Spa
And you want it to happen where it's not more work
Write like
That's the challenges like
Don't make
Give me at like something like a smart refrigerator
We're have to like inventory everything and read NFC tags like that just sounds like a nightmare so I think the challenge these guys is
Making things work better
I think the Samsung family Hub refrigerator was interesting I think the image recognition Technologies get
Anymore Basswood
I don't feel like it's quite there yet
I do feel like
With the Giant
Yeah yeah yeah
So we focus on the tablet because it is freaking
Ridiculous but inside it also has computer vision to recognize what's inside
Yeah you play with on the ratchet
It's pretty cool cuz you can do
Dragon soul
This has to be really hard to explain on the podcast
Speak to some limitations of Audio Only format
It's
Has a huge screen on the front and you can see inside and you can
Take your finger and say okay this item
The smoke I bought two on Tuesday and fairly quickly doing
Add a date to it
So it's
There's some
Pretty interesting features around adding
Inventory and making sure it has time stamps on a butt
Still a little bit too much work
Right now I just put a thing in the
Colony milk in the fridge and you know when it's gone it's gone
Or if it's chunky
Well Ico
But I've been really trying for last year just me personally you know cuz I've had the stomach to think about the food I buy
Because I waste so much food Stacy and for you to like
Maybe you're better than person I am but
I waste a lot of food I hate it
Like and I haven't found technology help me really good
My arms are on that
Exo-m better than you but I'm going to recommend
A wonderful curry recipe
Knorr vegetable soup recipe
Awesome
Quikrete
Put him in the show know I'll put that in the show I have leftover vegetables
Wasted
Final thoughts
How long
Let's say let's say I wanted to make a smart
Kitchen
And I wanted to do so before the holidays at this year
What would you recommend for people to get into it now and
What do you think I should wait on
I would suggest
Maybe buying like like I don't I don't want to push specific companies like I think it's scales good way to go I think that's how you got started on
The orange Chef scale
The drop scale
That's kind of a good Swiss army knife at a low-cost point I think you know you can get the perfect scale for like the $50 price
Makes a lot of sense
I think
If you want to try Precision cooking anything could get a sous-vide machine for you know hundred to $200 that's a good way
Obviously you know this guy
Freely if we're going to take the new sheptoff one is coming out in May
Wood product investment in their software
Around daddy cooking
So that's an interesting one
And you know just to talk about replenishment
I have diesel Dash buttons around my house that's I think that's part of Connecticut as well just Auto
Refinishing
Your kitchen
What supplies
Using the dash button
The normal street are they five bucks Maybe
If I bust minus a credit
First order Sith
So longer-term I think you I I don't even know 7
Brewing beer with my picobrew at by backing on Kickstarter
It's got a few Kinks to work out
But it's actually
Pretty easy to brew beer
So that's what happened if you want to spend a little more money
I might be up
That's probably who I think six or seven dollars post Kickstarter
Is your beer any good
It is good
Every all of my friends
Homebrewing expire
I would hesitate
That's why I schiphol like let's do it in my bathtub phase and I had said when technology makes us where I can make it
Easy I'm going to do it then so
That's why I backed
A Kickstarter what is connected bedroom appliances
And then what about the apply if you were going to buy an appliance
Like a dedicated cooking appliance what would you
Firewood you wait on those
I would wait cuz I think price is going to come down
I'm Cermak and spend over $1,000 on a
But you know what I think some people might
But I think you're going to see those overtime come down in price
And I see no one thing to talk about my panels
How do we get the entry to work
Together
You know if you're a Whirlpool within it
Will that work with the Samsung
Dishwasher you know I live in a multi-vendor
Kitchen like I don't have like all one manufacturer
So I want to see a world where all the stuff starts at work together so that's a conversation that she needs to have
Yes and they're totally not having
More depressed than ever after listening to the Jenn-Air Keitel
Well
We don't necessarily want to
Work with others because we want our stuff
We want you to buy all eight appliances from us
That was what I was trying to get you on my mind
Buckeye Lake industry
Have this conversation
Because
In the real world
Stacy and Mike's the world moved into the house and it had like a KitchenAid refrigerator
But then I bought this dishwasher
And I don't
1up 10 apps to try to make them all work together
All right
Will Mike thanks so much for coming on the show I really appreciate it
And
Hey thanks for coming out to Seattle
It was awesome
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to stay
Sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com