Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your Coast
Kevin tofel
I don't know if you realize this but
When I make these intros I actually gesture over to the
Who's always sitting
To my right
We should invest in one of those telepresence things and you can actually be pointing to a little screen with my face on I can move around 2
We have had requests
To do this live
Which I thought about that
Since we do it so early in the morning I'm always a little underdressed
Plus he'll have all the banter we have off the air
He's just really cute cards people
This week we have an awesome show for you we're going to talk about Google home partners
And we've got some great news on the echo
I think it's great
Is Kevin's not so sure
Ring raising a lot of money
We got some updates on jaw bone
We've got openhab2 oh if you don't know what this is
And we're going to talk a little bit
About
Apple homekit
Because I've been playing around with this and have some
Opinions
I guess this week is Susan Norris of P G & E
Who's going to talk about Energy Efficiency programs at how startups can work with China
But first
Let's go to a message from our sponsor
Our sponsor this week is June
June makes an intelligent countertop convection oven that takes the guesswork out of cooking
And let me tell you guys I love this thing it uses an HD internal camera along with the latest in art
Artificial intelligence to identify the food that you're cooking it's a Jessup Reset program that they've developed
And they close it and it's Android notification when it's done if you'd like and basically
Is awesome I love this thing I actually bought one
So in putting my money where my mouth is on this particular sponsor it has 100 day risk free guarantee
Auntie for all purchases made before March 31st 2017
The next two months you can test this out basically and ship it back if you don't like it
June oven can be found at www.even.com
It will also be at the June pop-up showroom which is located
At The Village at Corte Madera in Marin County California if you're out that way
Okay Kevin are we ready to get on with our show
We are before we start only because we're going to talk about some Google stuff I just want to say to everybody who met
Not already
Regular listener where you been
Google I mention that I am a full-time consultant for Google
I do not work in their smart home iot efforts at
Any way shape or form I should wear with Android and chrome folks in the Enterprise.
Just want to get that out there
And so far it hasn't affected
Kevin's
Wonderfully unbiased
You know a lot of people are surprised that I have not yet bought a Google home which is what we're going to talk about instead I own four
For Echo devices and I mention previous shows why that isn't
We're going to continue to talk about that maybe I'll change her mind but it's not because
So the news out this week on Google home is that they have
Teamed up with
WeMo Belkin products
And
Honeywell
Works with the Honeywell
Lyric thermostats
I don't have a Honeywell thermostat but I do have WeMo products and I hooked it up
The hookup process
Super easy
Basically when you go to the smart home section
You can add a device and then you'll see
The new options
So let me just quickly ask because I don't have a Google home
When you say go to the smart home options I'm assuming that's in the Google home
App
It isn't actually biscuits to something that drives me a little nut
That's because Google home the app actually encompasses a lot of different
It does the Chromecast
Southern Stone
So when do you actually go to the app
You go to
Video Star
So I get YouTube as my first option Google Play Movies & TV
I have to actually go to the drop-down menu to the
The home control section
Catch it again I don't have the app because I don't have Google home so I don't know how it works
That sounds sort of similar to how you set up an echo with Smart Home Stuff although
All the different options are pretty obvious on the main screen even there in a list on the left but
Home
What happens if you go to the
Home control section in the drop top
And
You basically
Do you click on a device
You pull down the home control in the drop-down menu and there's a tiny little plus sign at the bottom when you hit that plus sign
You get
In those options are nest
Philips Hue SmartThings
WeMo
And
Honeywell
Basically
I've learned everything except for Honeywell and with WeMo
Which is the latest and newest thing
I noticed a couple things
1 WeMo has historically been a little iffy about state
If you switch between clap
So knowing if it's on or off
If I turn it off with like
SmartThings sometimes it would be like
When I try to turn it off using Echo would be like
What will it now
So
With Google
Home this hasn't been
So that's good
That is good cuz I actually see that cuz he's multiple phones IOS and Android and sometimes on
The WeMo app
Even though a light is on the switch shows it is off when I switch phones and
So I've seen that
On phone so that's good I don't know how they resolved that but
That's good news
So I went back and forth turning my
WeMo switch on from my
Echo and then turning it off
Where's my Google home
The other thing I noticed which is really nice is
Google home you can actually say
I'm just going to tell you one of my WeMo switches called Afro Circus
It is from Madagascar 3 or 4 to my daughter named it
Just
So I
Minor called mortar
The Shire
Okay
So I say is Afro Circus on
And it says
Yes the afro circus is
So it's kind of nice because you can't do that you can't
Ask if something is on or off
So it will tell me state
The other thing is
If I want the echo to do something I have to say
Hey
Turn on
Afro Circus
But with Google
I can say
Haji
Turn Afro Circus on
Or I can say
Turn on
With the echo
Order of operations actually matters otherwise she would know what to do with Google
Interesting
Those are the two things
That I've discovered
So far
Obviously this happened yesterday so I haven't
Tivoli Lake
Discover yunnan
If it's going to throw some errors
We'll talk about it next
So even though I don't have a Google home I do have two WeMo switches
And I actually will get to try this in the near future I don't have a time frame yet
The reason I say that is because
WeMo and Honeywell
Coming to
The assistant on the Google pixel as well
It says Google this is an soon
Kunming
So
Using Google Assistant I'll be able to do this and try it out as well as
Imagine that expression
I don't know yet but
Give it a shot to
Yay
All right also in
Voice controlled speakers
We have
The echo has a new wake word
In my newsletter last week
So if you got that you're already up on this news before everyone else
But
The new word is
Computer
Which is taken from
Star Trek
Yeah which I love the I love the fact that
Star Trek fan always have been
I love the fact that you can now
Call your Echo computer in that respect
But for practical purposes I do not like it and the reason why
Because if you look at the existing wake words and looking at run through the 3 hours on that there are
They're not common either they're not things you would say a lot
The computer
These days computers is use an awful lot in my house I don't know about you and I just
It just would not work in my house
Calling it phone or tablet
No it's never going to work out
I would challenge you to try it for
24 hours
Because I thought the same thing but we don't actually say it we say where's the laptop
See
So we don't actually say computer various
Oh I'm so sorry
Oh my God
We're going to have to figure out if that's really a problem
Going forward I don't think it's a problem for today cuz I doubt many people automatically to switch it over last night
I love it on you
That's fair I just swap it out for 24 hours see what happens
And then next week we'll
All right do I have to set it up on my computer I just said the word
I'm kidding
I will try it
All right so that's probably enough of all of that
Let's get the funding
Because holy moly
Ring
Doorbell company has raised 109 million
Dollars
This comes on top of a 61.2 million year ago
And
Team on top of the 28 Million Dollar Round which is when Richard Branson actually gotten
That's the
209 million
Dollar Tree
This a lot of money it was led by
Dfj
Goldman Sachs
Qualcomm
I don't know
One I would love to know them cuz I'm wondering why they needed
Itchy raised
Almost
Enough money that's almost double what they previously
Write this is like an IPA
Kind of this is for a smoke
What I think is happening
They see that the market is going to be a make-or-break here for a lot of
You're going to have to
Grow massively
And figure out your established business models and ring has actually put out a lot
Different pieces of Hardware is part of their
Jamie siminoff the CEO of ring calls it his
They thought
You know they're two doorbells
They've got
Outdoor camera and then they now have
They launched at CES
This outdoor camera
Light
So imagine if you've got a neighborhood full of rings
What happens if
1 triggers you know some weird activity and
Maybe Simpson notification to the homeowner and the homeowners like yeah that was my package
And then all the lights go on
Everybody's ring down the
Kind of like a coyote neighborhood watch
Yes
That's the vision
It takes a lot of
Product in marketing to get to that because that's not going to be useful
Unless a lot of people have that's right
Right right right you need to build up adoption to get the maximum benefit for the neighborhood
And they got a lot of people that got a
It says a thousand employees which is a ton of people
My understanding is in this is what sources of Told Me Not
Confirm
Talk about this
They're not profit
So they've to make an IPO you got it prove that you're
Profitable and then you have a good pasta
And I don't know if they've actually achieved out yet
Plains weather
Candice Edition
Yeah and it's interesting that
Yes I read that looking at it on venturebeat who reported this
It's also debt element involved as well so it's
I don't know if that's part of the 109 or they have a line of credit or whatever
I think it's back to the
What you said earlier this is a make-or-break year for a lot of companies I think now that they have
Grab this
Chunk of change
This is probably their make-or-break year if they're going to go hog-wild with marketing and train
Achieve
Jamie's vision
Am I going to go quick
It is
Speaking of make-or-break years and companies that raised a lot of money
Jawbone
Jaw bone has
I ever this down his jaw bone is giving out but really what happened is
Jaw bone is
Stopping
It basically hasn't communicated with this customer since
December
The middle of December
Is it the support
MS support group
This is the support
So like
Most of the fitness trackers have fairly good support
People
They buy them
They wash them in the washing machine
I'm in a lot of them you know if you if it if something happens to it within a year they're like will replace it so
People have been
Emailing with Jawbone support
They're not getting anywhere
Pazzo job and support has gone silent
According to the bird
And this is maybe not surprising
Kevin you want to talk about
What you think might be
Well it kind of relates back to the
The funding store
I just talked about with ring and actions such as this when you might have company takes down and support
Process
And it has been known to have
Sales problems with its Hardware
It's almost like those are a series of steps to just train
Keep the company going as long as possible as long as there's money
While they trying
Keen other money Thea true funding
Through sales and like that
And
They're obviously not going to tell her
They're doing
They're going to try and keep things afloat for as long as I can.
One of two things is going to happen to be there when I get some funding or a buyer or they're just going to
Sold
And I don't know which it is
They don't
You know when the money is gone the money is gone so that's the way I see this when I ask again I hope I'm wrong
Their efforts behind creating like true medical devices as opposed to consumer
Skip it and I forget what that was
Don't bite about a year ago yeah
Back in May I'm sorry
Alright so that is
Other news for people who love their Smart Homes and their smart home hubs and feel particularly
Kiki
Openhab which is the eclipse
Open
Smart home where is this the open-source version of
Built on Eclipse
Yes yes
They've released openhab2
Confess that I said I was going to do it
Openhab
Configuration
And I
It takes a little effort I mean you're not buying at a hub you're basically building a hub with a Raspberry Pi or a
Anticodon and you're using it open have software so your
Creating your own Hub so
I was really into
I looked at it and like all right
Pi
I got to get it
So then I was looking at the pine64 Smart Home
Care up there
Do the smart
Conversion
No but I can always add
To the pine64
Yes
I was looking at that and then
I looked at the instructions and then I was like
Holychild I am going to really find myself into
So
It's always been like a
What to do but
Because openhab2
Apparently has a nice
It's better
Better
It's not cloudconnect
To the top logo
And
Nice dashboards
Call this nice
I don't know
It's much cleaner and more modernized in the field
It's pretty
Pretty so
I'm actually hoping
To do this because
I think I can I think I can
Call Kevin
I'm going to call Kevin
I haven't gone through this and set up and had myself but I I set up a ton of different things on Raspberry Pi
Brothers retropie with
Game emulators
Or
Linux or whatever maybe
It may look intimidating but I think
You'll be surprised
Two things one it will probably be simpler than you thought
And to you will learn a lot
It's actually good experience to have in a minute that's how you buy these raspberry pies and so on so forth anyway
It's a tinker so
I don't think it's going to be that bad in the benefit is
Perspective or somebody doesn't like cloud-connected
7/8 local
And you pick and choose what radios you want you can
Customize
Door hardware
To the way you want
You should do is
I want all the radios
So what you're in your house you need all
Not all of us have a hundred different things connected in her house
Don't have that
Yesterday
I love the fact that you know what I look at my wife
You only have basically f45
Wifikill
And then add your Bluetooth you see way they should be excited I'm like I'm not so bad
But then I realized it
That doesn't account
Other stuff
Sad
All right
So
Let's see so that's open have news very exciting
Stacey has a promise
The promises
Actually download and do this
Alright this is kind of tie a couple pieces of news
Together
It's topical we might get a little political
So just
Retro
Everybody everybody
Let's take two deep breaths
Okay
So
This week the FTC
The Federal Trade Commission filed a complaint against
The breath
Which is a Bluetooth connected
Breathalyzer
And
It also appeared on Shark Tank
So if you've heard of it that's probably why
If your Shark Tank
So
The FTC basically filed a complaint saying that
The company lacks scientific evidence to back up their
This is, this is what the FTC does it basically protects consumers against
False
It's one of its many sticks
Well it's actually probably one of its few sticks
It has to be
So the FTC actually did this very recently
Earlier in January
D'link saying that it advertised it
It's routers were more secure than they actually
And so
Once again FTC
Basically
People for bad advert
What is interesting here is Edith Ramirez
Chair
Woman of the FTC actually step down
Because she wasn't Obama
And with the Trump Administration come
I'm very curious how active the FTC is going
To be here
Consumers can always make
Complaints
But the FTC doesn't actually have
Act on them
And
All of these connected devices
There's
A lot of opportunity
For complaints coming
Related to privacy
Related to false advertising and I'm curious who will pick up the slack
I bring this up
Because
Lily
The maker of
That robotic drone
I guess it's just a drone
The Drone that you basically
Toss up in the air
It follows you and takes pic
Everyone is very excited about
Lily is actually been sued by the San Francisco district attorney it filed a civil consumer protection suit
Saying that the company had lied to customers with its launch video
And
It couldn't actually do any of that and so Lily basically said that
It wasn't going to build its
Cool drones
Sings everybody
The next day
The San Francisco DEA was like
The question here is
Certain States going to
Pick up the slack where the FTC
Yeah that's that's going to be interesting because people especially with how easy it is to order online
From other areas of the country
Towel that will actually be effective
Right people will find ways around that
True now the publicity could be
Be interesting and I would say a lot of these
Companies are based in
In California
Which
We already know is going
Which Prides itself on becoming a thorn in the side of
Current Administration
So
It kind of makes me wonder
I think there's going to be jurisdiction in those cases if
Companies based there
And if anyone in California orders one
Thank you for that
So this is going to be a really interesting thing to watch I believe over the next
You're so
Because again
Make a break here for iot for a lot of these companies that raise funding in 2012-2013
So
Keep an eye on this you guys
Finally
Let's go to
Homekit
What you been playing with them.
So I set up a basic
Home kit installation
Text I have an iPad so that's going to be my
Like living at home
I didn't buy an Apple TV
Thai pads
Either can be a Gateway for the home stuff
So I have is devices right now I have an eye devices
Indoor switch
Sewing Outlet
I have Lutron smart Bridge
Which is
Controls now all of my Lutron.
Devices
I have
The Philips Hue
My Philips Hue Lights cuz the Hub is homekit
Compatible
I just want that out
And then I also have the elegado
Eve sensor
And I have a couple of them I have a motion sensor
I have the room sensor
That does I believe
Temperature in ear
And I have the eve
Light switch
I feel like I have one more that I haven't set up
But I don't remember
With those things
I've been trying some very basic stuff
Their new door locks or anything like that because I think the only door lock right now is August and he don't have an August on my
My door because my doors
My front doors don't actually work
My Backdoor
Has
So I may get one just to try that out though
Because it feels like summer
Set up on this
Is super easy
And what's important to know
Is in some cases you don't actually even need to install the app
For the
Correct
So
I have the Philips Hue already connected in the Lutron Hub already can
Connect it so those I basically opened
The whole map from
An iOS home screen
Oh that's going to be terrible you guys
And I was like add a new device and it actually saw that those devices were already on my network
Clicked on them
I added them
I could put them in a room
I can put them on
The home screen
Witches
This is this is ridiculous you guys the home screen
So in some cases I did like I have I have motion sensor setup for my laundry room in my closet
Through the Hue and I was like
Those are
And it only saw the lights didn't see the motions
Sensors for my
Queue system
Switch
That's important
It took
Maybe
92nd
To do all of my lights
From Hue and Lutron
Which is about a dozen lights
Name them classify them all of that
The active setting this up basically involved
Clicking on that
Button
Cuz it was self discovered in
Chase
And then
Lighting up the code on the bottom of the bridges and then AB sees it
Takes kind of a picture it's
And it's like
You're connected
And it was
Spokane
So easy so they nailed that
Yeah setup is
I did this with ecobee
As the only homekit device I have here
And setup was
Super simple just like you described
That was awesome
So
If something hadn't been connected
It already so with my
My other stuff that already been online
I also did the
You stuff
And
Basically I didn't download the eve app
Elgato
So I didn't download that at all
Instead I went to the home app and I've clicked
Wants to add the device
Because it was nearby and powered on
It was like hey
That's what I want to add
And then
I took the picture and boom it was on and then I got a notification saying hey there's a firmware update
So
Basically
Nail in it
On this side
On the outside
Getting things to work together is also
Pretty rudimentary
That's kind of where this falls down I wanted like some more
Options for
Cool style Integrations but
The pretty-much
Where they've been for
Two or three years which is I program like
Windows motion detector
Comes off Iran
Do this
And that works
Super fast
And this is all in the automation tab of the home app if I recall
Doing this like not like
I also I will tell you guys that
But I also have a challenge here
Because
I am not used to iPhone
Apple nailed it on the setup
And next week we're going to talk about
How well it is
When you live
Final tip for you guys
Remember last week I talked to you about stringify
Stringify was that app that basically is a software-based home automation Hub it ties into Lots
Some other things
So I discovered that they have a math function
Option as one of their triggers
Actually it's really cool because it lets you
Continuous Flow based on comparing numbers so you can actually put that in seoul
After this time of day
Turn the nest on
If it is greater than
This many took
Greece
Which is pretty cool
That's interesting and then you can perform math operations
Khon2 values
And that's like
Adding or doing other things
I'm not 100% sure how to use that yet
Cuz I haven't
Haven't found a use for it
But
If you guys can
They also have a text function
And I should tell you
That's basically continue the flow if the text
Says this
Continue the flow
If the text
Does not say
This is good for things like
Hey when I text the following
To my smart home system to stringify
Do this
Is a mattress
If that makes sense so basically it allows you to write text commands
Do so
Sometimes like for example
Because our
Like when I come into bed
Late at night
I don't actually want to
Tell the echo
But I try text
So rats like an alternative
Some of that sounds like what
Zuckerberg is done with Jarvis cuz I know he's got text controls built-in for that same reason he doesn't want to wake somebody up with voice commands so
Send a text to make something happen
Exactly
So I think this could
Really handy actually for
I don't know what actually let me think about this because right now
One of the things I commonly do where I'd like to tell the echo something but I can't
Is the middle of the night sometimes
He tore my AC is just
I wake up in a
I couldn't get
My smartphone and just use the app
Turn it back which is probably just as reasonable is creating a flow
To do the same thing
And then cuz if I create a stringify flow
I'm going to get my phone to text something
In Massachusetts the appen
Hours of fun in that
So today I actually
Everything else just
Okay
So that's it for this week's show
Stay tuned because we have an awesome guess this way
We have Susan Norris of Pacific Gas and
Electric
Who is going to talk to us about how the Internet of Things helps with conservation and energy-efficiency and what's
Startups need to know
What did companies about working with PG&E going to be awesome
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is
Does your host today Susan Norris who is a senior manager in Peach
Energy
Efficiency products organization
Hey Susan
Man that title timeout
But you want to tell people kind of Simply what you do
We're really trying to inspire and Empower our customers to eliminate unnecessary energy use
Which is still a mouthful
That is but at least makes makes sense
So you're one of the people behind the efforts to
Take my old
Incandescent bulbs out replacing with LEDs and maybe reminding me to
Turn up the air-conditioning when I leave in the US
And not just replace your light bulbs fit turn them off when you don't need
What's the elimination of it when it's not enough
Keyword there
You're in California
In California is he a Korean state has some very aggressive energy
Conservation goals
Do you guys have any official metrics that you're working towards internally or as a state
Getting Gold by our Utility Commission
To achieve
Each year
Demand which is measured in megabytes or gigabytes
You said which is measured in
Watt hours to kilowatt hours or megawatt hours
And sperms which is the gas side
Sing to me end
Reducing usage overall and reducing gas
And how are you guys doing
Start over
So it sounds like you guys have pretty big conservation
Does that conflict with your goals to actually sell it
The unique situation in California and investor-owned utilities are in is that we don't have that tension between
Revenues from
Selling our commodity to our cost
And
Ice cannibalizing that Revenue by doing energy-efficient
And that's because we're a public utility that is decoupled which means that the revenues are disassociated from
Commodity
If we get our customers to reduce their energy consumption we don't take a hit Financial
And that's a good thing because if you look at California that are cheap
Consumption since we started implementing Energy Efficiency programs our population has grown
That's not
So one of the things that people are excited about with the Internet of Things smart home however you want to look at it
Is it
Really has huge
Potential just cut down on energy use
Even in my house just having
Motion sensor switch is like the lowest hanging fruit ever
Turn off the lights after I leave
Leave saved me tons
And
You know things like The Nest Thermostat
Honeywell lyric they all just turn down the heat when you leave and turn up your AC
And that's got to be great so
Is that enough gets a good start I am both terrified and thrilled about where things are going
What terrifies me a little bit is that it a lot of this
Technology in your newsletter and in your recent podcast from CES you talk about
The proliferation of SmartThings and that is plug load that is going into home
It's also a lot of batteries
Switch
A crate for the
The environment and a lot of things getting plugged into outlets in homes and that that's a little terrifying for me in the space because they
That's where
A lot of those little hidden
Usage
Comes in
That in
In a 1D 2D cases isn't a lot but when you start to pile it on it becomes
It becomes extensive and it used to be that everyone had one television in their home
And now people even have televisions in the refrigerator than in their bathrooms and there are bedrooms and every bedroom
When you start to pile it on
It gets a little unwieldy for us when we're trying on our side when we're trying to eliminate that unnecessary and I
How to use and even those products
Don't look like they're consuming
If it hasn't always on feature
Like a smart TV or a game console or a computer
It's still consuming energy even though you're not benefiting from the energy of cancer
Those are the types of things that we're trying to
Solve
Forever either trying to solve sweat at
Consumer level
You Stacy can you just turn off the lights when you're not using them or when you don't need them
Can you unplug your
Computer or make sure that your
Set-top box goes off and really turn
Lights off when you
Can you do that
But it's better if we make it really simple for Custer
To do that and that's where the manufacturers come in
And so that's why it's exciting for me because I think a lot of disconnected
Stuff
Can help make it really easy for customers
To take those actions
So let's break this down a little bit
Because you brought up two things one is
More devices in the home
Because they're connect
Is
Using their intelligence
To help with conservation
So let's start with a
The first witch
You kind of alluding to this vampire power consumption
Challenge
In one of the ways you can deal with that
Maybe by installing
Smart switches so
You can plug your
Killbox which is a notorious culprit into
Connected Outlet
And turn it off when the TV is actually
Not on
Yes
Right
Some of that dodos devices themselves
Because they have
Southstate you know they have they have hard drives in them that aren't
Really designed to be completely
Kilt
Hi
So that's where we're going with manufacturers and and I think consumers have a pretty with we just talked about set-top box
Consumers have a pretty low tolerance
Spread out startup time
When you do completely power that unit off
I want to see the channel Selections in the guide instantly when I turn on my television and those
Device is currently
Many of them have to reboot
And so consumers don't have a high tolerance
We're going to have to figure that out and manufacturers are going to
I have to help figure that out but we're striving for is to have that device you
The least amount of energy is necessary
So let's go to the bigger issue
Which is using the stuff to help conserve
And I feel like there's kind of a couple steps here one is like
And you can totally argue with me cuz you're smarter and actually deal with consumers in electricity
What you're using and then
Automated
Ways to save
Or replacing
I guess replacing a device or automated
Something to save energy
Does that seem reasonable
It doesn't and the way I look at it I always break it down into these two different factors and ultimately there two different factors that
What is motivation somebody has to be motivated to want to take action
And the second thing is you have to have the ability to do something about it so seeing how you're consuming energy
Do your higher houses performing or how big that iceberg is underneath
The polar bear and that it's melting and things that motivate you
To do something about something
Are very motivational but if you
Really
Feel like the solution to that is out of your reach
You're going to get frustrated so so seeing consumption a lot of these
Devices can show you your energy
Consumption but they don't give you away to do anything about it
And after a while you sit there and you're like okay so my TV is using energy when it's not on
I don't know what to do about it
So I think some of this connected stuff
And that's where I've heard Kevin talk about we're getting towards the
Smart part of the smart stuff
When it really starts to interact
That's when you I think we will all start to see this conservation effect of the technology
You have two effects taking place you got what we call efficiency where if I get Stacy to take out an income
Doesn't light bulb and put in an LED
The Delta between those
2 Technologies is efficient
You Stacy the consumer still get the same benefit of the light
But it's using less energy
When I get
The second measurement is conservation
So I can get you to turn off that light when it's not needed
That's an added bonus
And a lot of this technology is
Delivering both of those things so smart light bulbs
Are helping deliver the conservation and the fact that it's an LED
And not an incandescent it consumes less
So what are some examples
Because that's what
People's brains go to
Where this kind of Technology
So we went from a top-loading washing machine
To a front loading washing machine
Lots and lots and lots of water you can actually wash way more clothes in it
Then you could enact in a top-loading washing machine that's great
Static Energy Efficiency move
The challenge that I have with these washing machine
Now is that many of them
Still default the user to warm water
Wash and Cold Water Rinse
That's great it's not a war model Reds but why not just default them to cold water wash and cold water mint
And then it's a washing machine was really smart
It could prompt the consumers say are you sure you really want to do that or it can show them their energy
Because once they're smart they
Exactly it's actually tapping into their rate
Order rate plan because if they're on a time of use plan it might say
Are you sure you want to start your washing machine now
It's costing you $0.22 a kilowatt hour
But if you waited until after 9 p.m. it would only cost
B12
You know I think there's a huge opportunity for the technology system
Start to interact
Together
In the home and
Some of those use cases are the thermostat registering that you're no longer there
Let's take down the lights for at least asked you whether
You want
The system to take down the lights that you've left on
So let's talk about the user interface for the consumer
Then we'll move to what startups need to do for you guys too
Proviable to do this and then we'll talk about what you guys need to do to kind of
On your end to make these sorts of
Cool things like sending XS power.
Your neighbor possible
Chicken
The user interface so right now I have to program everything to happen in my house
Which is a lot of work on my end and I do it cuz I love it
Most people are not
Weather and you know how
Right
So how do you get
Consumers and your customers
To actually
Program their lights
Terre Haute their nest
I think
Today it's a pretty big challenge
And I think that's one of the barriers that consumers have to really setting up these this
System
Approach I also think that some of the Technologies aren't
Ready for that system approach because as you described they set up these walls
Systems that unless I can see more dives into
A closed
System like a Lowe's Iris system
Where everything just will automatically recognize and talk to itself so that becomes a simpler solution but it limits your
Ability to add more stuff from that is not part of that system
I also think that experiences when if your your power goes out in your Wi-Fi or your Wi-Fi goes down
And all of that stuff
Loses its connection it doesn't automatically always come back together
And that's
Going to be really frustrating for somebody who
Decided they were going to take the time
To hack this stuff together and then
I have to do it again right honestly that is this
When you spend that much money on something that you're like spending hours
Fixing it or repairing it
Yeah they're over there maybe something
Susan I just want
I do think that it's you know it's getting there and I think manufacturers are recognizing it I do think that there are
Situations where consumers don't quite quote-unquote gat
That use case
And what really concerns me in if you do consider that diffusion of innovation model that innovator
Innovate and innovators don't really
Inform
The next
Group of
Consumers those early adopters because innovators will try anything
But early adopters actually have a strong influence on the early majority
And if we don't get this right for the early adopters
We're going to really struggle in this is that Chasm that they talked about Crossing
In the chasm things like that so I really do have
Something that space that we really need to nail this with the early adopters
And get it right for that so with that in mind
What do you want the startups
Or established
Tresor in the space
What should they be thinking about
To work with the
Company
Maybe it's just making life easier for
For consumers what are the things they need to take into
Consideration
One thing I would love to just shout out to all the manufacturers and developers and whether their existing
Organizations or whether they're just getting their feet wet in the
Space is
Utilities act across the country across the world
How to play
To help accelerate adoption of this technology in the marketplace
Many utilities across the
The world
Actually have programs like ours
That can can provide incentives for customers or can
Do things in ways that try to accelerate adoption of this technology in the marketplace
The challenge utilities have is that technology
Have to have an effect
A measurable effect
That's where it gets a little tricky
We have to be able to justify our return-on-investment
So we have in our Ally and that Roi shows up for us
As
Savings or conservation
We have to be able to measure that just like a bank would need to measure the
The return on investment in monetary terms
We have to register it as
Savings so
When I talk to manufacturers I often say
You know it's great that your device
Shows customers how much energy does consuming at this time and how much that energy is cost
If that doesn't cause them to go take action and persistent action that action has to be has to be sticky
Then I'm really I can't do anything with
That's where it gets hard to measure
And especially for talking about small loads but then residential homes
Score in small businesses
Those little tiny
Little loads like light bulbs
Better internet and then everybody uses them differently
Televisions and
Curling irons curling irons
We can help from a Utility side
It accelerating adoption of these Technologies in the mark
Place with the technologies that was cells have to come in with a way for us to measure the effect and the
How is it we have is that that process often takes a while
Because we have to do field studies
We also have
There's a temperature effect of that device like a thermostat we have to do it over summer and winter
We may have to do it in a variety of different climate zones
California is Rife with climate zones
Those processes take a while in order to really do the scientific study to
Determine the actual effect of a piece of technology or a
Combination of Technologies on a customer's usage
Got it now you also mentioned a couple things that
Like I imagine most startups or
Manufacturers are like okay
Then you have some other things like
I don't know how much startups think about
What else is there
That you're like oh by the way you need this to those things definitely help
To make sure there is a audio out there that has reviewed your technology and make sure it's
If it needs
Safety standards and
Other qualities that are going to be promoted we don't want somebody's house to catch on fire
Now what about security
Because now that becomes
Now everybody's like
Crap I'll just connect and stuff it may not be the best thing
Install
That is a big concern of a lot of consumers
And every time the news
Comes out with the latest
Breach and somebody's
Smart technology stuff I mean I just watched an old episode of Modern Family Modern Family where the
They were overhearing the neighbors baby monitor
To be fair that was doable all the way back in the
The 900
But I do I do
Do you think a lot of consumers are very concerned about the security and I think our responsibility I consider us it a trusted energy advisor
And I think we're moving into this space where we need to also provide cuss
Northwest
Information on
How they can
Keep their systems as a
Secure is possible and I actually just recently wrote a piece for our website so that that we could
Just haven't have some references for customers
To go online in and take a look at different
Buying advice
When they consider connecting SmartThings and then just
Fundamentals
Security things to consider like you know just make sure that you have your
Most secure settings on your wireless system that you don't identify your home or your family address
Or your family name or the device name in the
In the description
So that people
Can't hack into it make sure you change the password to something strong and secure don't use the one that came with the product and don't use
Something that you
You use for other things
Common Sense things
But we are putting up on our website
For our consumers to discover and we're trying to help them make
Good decisions on how they repair things together so if they decide to go down the echo route what works
Good luck with that it's a it's a pretty big challenge you know and I think
You seen some of that the work that we've contracted with to get this list of technology so that we can try to figure out these cross
Pairings that we might be able to help customers figure out
How does
PG&E
Prepare
Itself
For things like
Demand response that step one but then you think about the effect of Renewables on the grid how are you guys planning
When to use Chi
Coyote
Operations we have several different initiatives across the organization that I am not fully tapped into
Mattress pumps it's within our organization and customer Energy Solutions and said that Groot is always looking at
How do we manage load on the Greyhound that stature megawatt in kilowatt
That's your demand
And
Our demand is shifting
Where will you have pizza man in the middle of the afternoon on those hot days in the summer when all the businesses were
Hainan
Consumers are also consuming
With so much proliferation of solar
In our territory
The demand to shift it till later in the afternoon
When the Sun Goes Down
You don't have as much solar production I'm not sure how many people are actually aware of that that you're sober isn't producing when the Sun
Isn't shining
Which is an interesting
And I'm so the demand has shifted to later in the afternoon to like 6 at night
So for many years decades
Steven Wilson asking our customers to reduce their energy consumption on those super hot days in the summer when the grid needs some early
And now we're trying to ship everyone to realize that that
Happening later
When
The sun goes down
Consumers get home and start flipping things on
To cook dinner and to get ready for their evening
So we look at at
Did opportunities in end the challenge that the utilities are going to have across the country in the world and this is how
Having a lion you're up to with a lot of solar pain
Coming online
Where you're really moving from
Customers being passive
And receiving your your services gas and electricity
At what we lovingly referred to as
Cold beer and hot showers
Stop static gauges
Two more of a
Prosumer
Partnership
Where we may need you to react
And ask you to react to be a partner
Frost
Situation because you may have storage or you may have extrasolar that you can push back to the grid
And some of that is happening today but some of that is really just
Planning for the scenarios in the
Teacher
And pulling out together
And looking at how those
Integrated demand-side resources
Fit into the whole transmission and distribution
Infrastructure that's been around for a hundred years
All right with Susan thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you it's been a pleasure
That's it for this week's podcast thank you for listening and if you want more Internet of Things news
Sign up for my newsletter
Tecidos Bank
You can get it at Stacey on iot
Come once again thanks for listening and we'll see you next week