Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofu
And today we have an amazing
We are going to talk about security for a bit on the Internet of Things We are going to talk about a brand new homekit certified light switch
The Amazon Echo has some new skills
We got some chips news for people and connected lock story from Kevin and a nucleus video in
Intercom system review from me
We also have an ad from
Hewlett-Packard Enterprise
And our guest this week is Andy Ellis
The chief security officer at a cup
So
Kickback
Stay tuned but wait just a moment for a word from our sponsor
The days of walking into a sports Stadium sitting down and watching a game are over technology is the fans
Newest companion San Francisco 49ers vice president Sean kondu came to the arm techcon this week 2
Describe how his organization is leveraging mobile technologies smart networks iot Technologies
And software to revolutionize your in bed you experience streamline Stadium operations and build businesses are
Around those services
All right here we are let's kick it off with
Oh my God
Security
On Friday
Or lack thereof
It's not as bad as everyone thinks so here is the message from us for
Last week what
And was there was a massive distributed denial-of-service attack
Using open-source software
Found on the internet
It's called the Mariah
Chopper code
People used this
Create
A botnet
Comprised of a lot of network DVR cameras some routers
Some Critters
And a couple other kind of connected devices
It was a huge attack
It is
What are the largest ever seen
And these attacks represent a whole new wave like a whole new escalation
DDOS attack
These guys actually attacked died which is a domain name server
Service
Which basically accident address
For the internet
What happened is
A few people on the East Coast
Sabi popular sites go down because people couldn't actually access them using
All because it's being hammered by all these
Corinth
Iot device
The world
Mad
I was very mad being on the east coast and affected not once but twice on
It was Friday morning
Started out I couldn't access Twitter no big deal I can live with that but then my
Sony PlayStation Vue
TV streaming service that I use
Shutdown a problem with Amazon services
It was a mess
Heaven
Ground to a
Be wild and I wondered actually I wondered
Back on Twitter was finally back
I wonder how many people
Add iot issues and so many of those go back to the cloud
If they can't find their servers well that's a problem and some people actually didn't say
And that they had some issues
Yes actually August send an email to me
Explaining that
Their video doorbell was having problems because of
Here's the quick take and I've actually Our Guest is going to talk in depth about
So stay tuned for Auntie
And I've written about this
Basically
These devices
Have an open port to the internet
They're not
Your traditional iot
If Isis
They're basically Giant
Computers that have an open port to the internet
Your light bulbs are not really at risk for this type of
Attack
Because one
They don't directly connect to the internet
They don't have a lot of
Capacity and compute power to actually
Be useful indeed
Real perspective there for you guys
As part of this though I did decide
Hey we should really have a conversation about coyotes
Security that does more than like
And we
Like most companies are you asking about the
Restore York
It is accurate
Manor
You're like Shrek okay and move on
It's probably time to go deeper so I sent some emails out to companies like nest
Philips Hue
Ecobee Netgear
Chamberlain which makes the MyQ
WeMo SmartThings
And wink
To find out how they're handling security
We're not going to go into a lot of depth
Here
But I am going to post
This
In the newsletter that I do
Stacy knows things
So you can find out more about this
At a greater level
But the upshot was
These companies are actually doing it
A good job
Most of them have bug Bounty programs most of them are doing pentesting penetration testing
At least once a year if not
Almost
A lot of them actually monitor the status of their devices
Either if not through a direct
Network operations center
They do it through like
Heuristics on the data so
If the data is like a device stops
Recording they're going to notice if it starts behaving weirdly or group of them are they're going to notice
And take action
And I suspect we will find out when your newsletter comes out with the responses are I suspect however that their little bit
Better
At women they find a security issue that actual
Keep pushing software updates to your devices
As opposed to most of the devices that were used for this DNS outage
We're older and networked DVRs and such
That don't typically get updates
A large
Amount of them actually
Or built upon
Chips in a particular company as well
Yes and
A lot of them had hard-coded
Passwords which will talk about
I'll put it in the show notes
Also but I did a story for
Consumers basically telling you how you know if your device is hacked
How you know
Your what should you do and all of that and in some cases guys the news is pretty bad
It's basically you know
Set your device on fire and
Send it off into the great beyond
I can't I don't know if you talk about this
It in your story but I can tell you one thing I did immediately and that is I started monitoring the network traffic of
All of my devices when the outage was going on in my
Do I have any box here that are just
Turning in pinyin the DNS servers or what but I do not see anything out of the ordinary which was good
Yes and there are Port scanners
That you can use so that that'll be in there too
Yes monitoring your traffic is actually
Kevin you're so smart
I have a mind reader
Alright so
That's the security update news etcetera
Guys if you're buying devices from reputable vendor
And by reputable I mean they have a brand
You can Google them
Look for bug Bounty programs
Look for them to make you change your password the over-the-air updates if you haven't upgraded your router in a couple years
My Geico do it
Why you'll probably get that
So
That's that
Let's go on to
Find product news because we know this is not going to make a
Stop buying today
Connected devices
Pish posh
But I thought I probably will not be by the next device that we're going to talk about only because it's
Homekit
Not really interested
Which
I'm not either but I did buy an iPhone and I'm setting up my own home kit setup so
Guys stay tuned
Cuz I could be a lot smarter about home
Core
You're going to love it
Or you're going to hit
Tell us about this light
So new product literally ages
Hit our inbox is working for the show we actually know about this when we were planning
Elgato has the new EVE light switch
449 95
It is homekit compatible as we mention
And what's
It's kind of interesting about this one too I think a lot of people cuz
Sweet without so much about Wi-Fi
This picture Bluetooth low energy
Percy Sledge so
That's
Eternally I don't wanna sleep earlier naked it would be unique in my house cuz I do not have many
Bluetooth devices so
You might be Stacy you might have more than I do
I actually don't in the reason I don't
Is because there's actually switchmate
Makes a really that's her
Make savory
Nice bluetooth light switch in the benefit here is
When you get a controllable light switch but two you can actually put the switch anywhere so if you got a switch in a hard.
Beach Place
You can just be like
Hey I'm going to screw in bluetooth light bulb
Apopka switch on the wall
Wala
So that is Handy but
Because Bluetooth mesh has not been super satisfying
The remote control on these things
Isn't great so
The light will work
The switch
In the light switch to the light
Is fine
Because they're usually Within
A wonderful trip close by
Read unless you're going to do some
Crazy like programmable light switch to turn off
All the lights
To your house witch
Is conceivable and other switches I don't know if you
But that sort of stuff gets a little iffy with Bluetooth
If you don't have a stronger
Mesh Network
So this is a product that I'm actually going to order it by so I can
Tested my new
Hit thing because everybody really is excited
Connected light switch
Elgato also makes the sensors the homekit sensors so they've got a water sensor temperature sensor
An air quality sensor
And
I went open close sensor isn't these actually I've tested those they work really well
So
If your home cat person
This is definitely device
You should look at
And if you do look at it
Let us know because we have
Tested it yet
One quick question for you if you're going to get one of these do you have an Apple TV 4 or an iPad
I do I have
So you could theoretically set up as a home hub
And then
Remotely control lights drunk episode
Is the Bluetooth
In the iPad in the Bluetooth
In the light switch
That's the question
All connectivity you only go so far
New Bluetooth will go further
And we'll have better Mesh networking and we are waiting for that
So Bluetooth 500
Awesome
Maybe
Okay
Next newspaper
Also in the consumer smart home side
The Amazon Echo
Has
Kind of exciting
I'm surprised it's taken as long
Is that Amazon has brought
The echo functionality to its low-cost tablets it's actually reminds me a lot of like Google Now goo
Google Assistant because you can tap and hold
A long press on the home button on
A
Fire tablet
And then speak
Your echo through the tablet
Electrical little pop up cards like I do with my Fire TV so like if I
Ask for the weather I can get a weather card on my TV using the Fire TV
It's very similar just now is down on the tablet
Okay and you could also
Used to be able to tell
The echo to send
Data to
Fire tablet and it would show up
Right
Right now it's now it's native that's okay
Got it okay in my big frustration though with this and I'm curious how this
How fast does a
Load cuz I I don't actually have anything.
Kick work with us I don't know if you tried it
Have you tried it
I don't have any fire tablets
Delete ride with my fire TVs
In which case it is
Quick quick
But I couldn't speak to the tablet implementation
Because the
We're going to have to say the name
The Earl
App
On my
Phone is really slow to load
I'm like Cinderella
And I don't know if it's my Hardware it's it's all so slow on my husbands iPhone
I don't know what's going on
I would like it to be
But I like this idea I love
Because sometimes you don't listening to like if you ask the weather for 10 days out that's good
Will be painful listen to
Yes
Sending data onto a visual device
Is really it like a no-brainer
So yeah
The Amazon Dash program also got a slight boost in some more
Colleen meeting list
They're 62 button so now they've got over 200 Dash buttons these are the buttons you press to automatically reorder stuff
And
People are happy
Amazon says what do they say
5 times more five times more purchases
In the last year or in the past year
A95x Pro 35 x growth and I believe
Last year they said like a purchase was being made every
13 seconds or something crazy like that so apparently people are using them how many we have
No idea
5x more than
Which makes sense there's a mass
Expansion
Not too loud
And there's 60 more Brands added to the dash buttons
So I can go over 200 brands
You know I look at the dash buttons every now and then I'm like
Is there a place in my life
One of these and so far
I haven't gotten
The only thing I reorder on a regular basis are these like toothbrushes for my dog
They're like
Little toothbrush igbos that smell like Punk
Kanpai
I like pumpkin pie
Ghetto maybe a state they put that on the dash I would be
Be like yes
But right now I just
Turn to
And I say
However
Please order more.
And
You really should have a
And maybe they do I know that I have been have programmable Dash buttons that you can get in
Do your own tinkering but
Why not have a generic one that
But you select
We're sign whatever product you want to it
I imagine there's probably control over the brand
And maybe
Amazon has tax
Keep the product in certain stock
Maybe in its warehouses
Could be
Could they make sense
I need a restore 3 record as well
Which is
And finally
Folks who have the Logitech
Harmony
You guys are going to be excited because now it's
Swiss the echo
So I don't need it to send that cuz I tell people used to do it
Well I used to use you know me
Which was the software
Spoke to you know me
Spoke to the
Harmony Hub that then spoke to the
The echo
And then by the speaker
Lots of things are then everything
Went back yet
So it was no as you know me
That was the order of operations there
And it worked
So you'd say something like
However
Netflix and chill
Lo and behold
But now
That is unnecessary
Other than I sing about
The yonomi software is its
It comes preprogrammed
It looks of the devices you have in suggest
Recipes for you
So if you don't want to program your own Logitech
We have chip news this week I am an arm
Techcon in
Clara I have a hard time with
Please Bay Area
City named some like I didn't send sub place
Sometimes I even get a
This time
It's actually good show
I saw
You know the plans that SoftBank has forearm
Witcher basically
It's a bet on there being a trillion
Connected devices by 20
Think of a DDOS we could do with that
Well but
These are low-power their arm
I know well the cortex the cortex a series could really do it now
DMC use notsobot
Arvest done a couple things so
Big number of devices Masa who is the chairman of SoftBank muscle saint preux
Ejected The Singularity it was really fun talk
And
Kind of talked about
How in this is with art this is
What Kevin and I
Excited
All of these cheap sensors are just getting
Better and better and cheaper and cheaper and we're going to use them for sillier and sillier things that are just going to change our lives and really unexpected
My favorite example from the show
Was
From arm CTO
Mike
Mueller who said
That
Someone was working on a
Smell sensor for
For people's underarms that would
Talk to their deodorant until it went to work harder
This is not a real Prada
This is an idea of a
But
The chips are getting better and cheaper
And one day we
I have something on
I don't want that
Wayback attack
But it was just an easy
Kevin is stinky right now
It doesn't just freaking sensor to tell me
Does bring up an interesting ethical things
Look at that person's data the physical data for
But I personally was very nervous
And smelly
So arm also announced
Really unique service
It kind of baffles me
They announced embed Cloud which is their partnering with an unnamed OEM
Call provider
Arm is built software
Basically handle the first layer of an iot Cloud which is device management
Getting the information from devices
And setting devices up on
And I'm just kind of like wow
I should come
Heading into the cloud
Really at a chip design company
Yes
The same because arm doesn't create
Chips as we all know so it actually could create this in big cloud
I'm scratching my head on my way to actually making out
Physical product if you can call the cloud physics
Product they're not hosting their own data
Did write their own software though
So it's based on some other there is Sansa in
How old is 6 slope an acquisition
Sin City
Sensitive sensitive
Remember 6lowpan
That's crazy.
I'm excited about this because it's a really interesting new
Business angle forearm
I told it's a SAS software-as-a-service kind of bottle so that's interesting
It's also a
Opportunity for them to go
Up the stack from
Not necessarily providing the hardware but
You don't getting pretty close to the hardware
And now
Going up
They say that customers
What
The ease of use they also say that the links to their
McLeod and McLeod and their trust Zone in
Crypto cell
Security stuff is going to be really important and customers want that
I want it from one
Wilson
I'm not convinced that this is like
A home run or anything but
Do you think it's a really
It's a logical step when you look at the
Business transformation
And we'll see if it's the right step
It's it's interesting because they
Obviously known for their computing
This is pushing computer a little bit to the cloud which is very unique for them butts other countries obviously have done
I agree it's a very logical thing for them to do I just I didn't think about it prior to
Central Time
Intel launch the new atom 4
Connected cars and
Gateway's
So until causes fog Computing Asda Cisco
This is basically the idea that
You'll have some computer
Cloud computing Edge in the middle of a Gateway where a lot of like your sensor data comes in and is analyzed
Why is right there and then it sends data back
Because it's just too far too expensive
To keep going all the way from
The device
Too slow too much latency especially for something like a car what you need instant
Paneer instant
And if it's
So Intel chip is ruggedized and it's low power for an Intel chip
And still very capable and it also has some of the deterministic
Teachers that that help enhance the safety
Robotics and autonomous driving kind of applications
So that way it looks a lot like the recently-launched arm
It was at the r52 architecture
The r52
So the r52 that we talk
About a cup
4 weeks ago
This feels like
This isn't hugely
You're surprising but it feels like we're starting to see a coalescing around
What we need in these kind of
Gateway devices and four
Autonomous cars in
That's so it's it's like oh everybody agrees that we need these
Where are T2 Kevin story Kevin it's story time
So it is not a very exciting story let's not build it up too much your butt
It actually illustrates the difference I think between having connected devices and actually having a quote on quote Smart Home
So many people put
These products
Into a house
And then
Don't take advantage of the smarts behind them whereas
I actually had to because
Quick story of my son comes in
After work sometimes 12 1/2 in the morning
Is not locking the door
Orange and then yesterday he went to work everybody was gone he went to work at 11 the morning
And we came home at 4:11 in French
And again they did not lock the door so we've got wide open house all hours of the day and night
And I'm like you know what I have disconnected a lock that Stacy sent me and I
Hamden hard over installing but finally did
And it really
Use it in an intelligent way
When this is a perfect opportunity so sure enough
I went to my Wink app
And I'm like oh I can just make a robot that says
Anytime that the lock
Is an unlock status for 5 minutes I just arbitrarily chose 5 minutes
Lock it
And it works like a charm and
Lock the door when they leave the house
The house will always be
Locked within 5 minutes on that so
Just a
You know handy little tip that think about your devices
And use them in a smart while use them to their potential
Joseph
This is great A lot of people in this is a perfect example of
This is how the smart home will eventually work but it's hard for people because people do not automatically
Think about all the things things can do
I will warn you though
Do not like go out to Garden
And
Forget your key or your smartphone
Because when I have Auto
I I had a lock that I had auto lock on
It was a little bit faster but it's still surprise me
Crappie like
Watering the plants Abednego into
Add to go into the house
Well that is a good tip but I'm actually covered
Because this lock is push button
It's got the keypad
Correct which we don't carry keys to the house we have the push button
I love it I think keypads are actually way better
And that's a Kwikset Z-Wave
Lock right
Correct that is
Easy quick set
Z-Wave lock
Power through the wink hub
You could also do something like this using smart
Alright my show-and-tell for this week
Is the nucleus this is a video intercom
System
Could I showed it to my husband he was like
I don't get the point
It's basically like a dedicated Skype client
Which is what they literally everybody says
It is like a dedicated Skype
Client accept
It also doubles as an echo of sore
It does not play your Spotify playlist
And it does not
Play Pandora
But other than that it can control your Hue Lights and
Do a lot of things that the echo.can do
So if you don't have one and you do have
A nucleus
This is a device that works better in pairs one is about $250 the other
If you buy two they're $200 a piece
And people by a median of
3 according to Jonathan Frank
Call the CEO
And that is because
They're using them to replace these old school intercom systems
It is actually really useful for this
So
We put one in
Are upstairs one in our kitchen
We actually turned off the echo feature
And it's not cold
I love Auto
Consistent
Star Roamer future you can actually turn that off since we have an echo downstairs in
The kitchen we did
Turn the downstairs
But you can now we can now just when my daughter is upstairs pacing in my office or I'm up in my office working my husband needs to
Ask me where something is
Refrigerator he's just like
And you know it
You can set it up so it connects automatically
Four people within your name
It's like hello
Oh yes this
It does sound very much like Skype only if limited to your
Wireless network your own house is not like you could
Put one at the neighbors house and have a video chat with us
So you can
That's the other interesting
So now it's now it is interesting to me other place we have ours cuz we were at 3
Is my husband's office
So now whenever I want to talk to him
I just
Basically press the button.
There's a bun
The home screen looks like a button up all the
Call basically
And you go
I call my husband's office and
He's like why are you
But it's super fun and you cannot voice
Only if you were
And so grandparents you can give this to
Somebody wasn't text Abby it's very easy to set up on your network you basically set it up on your Wi-Fi network and then you enter a code that says your
You're part of this family
Family unit this nucleus
And it's
How to cool so the downsides are
Hear it outside
Things I'd like to see
One there's no missed call function
And maybe that's cuz I'm not thinking of it is it
An intercom truly
But I would kind of like
Purdue score
And
We had some issues with one of the devices
I don't know if this is representative it anything but
It just bricked itself
And then we had to restart it
And waiting
And it took a bit
To restart
Relatively minor issues are Kansai it's actually it's much more interesting to me now because it works outside
Another thing I just thought of it I'm guessing you can do this this would be an interesting feature to me
So Shaggy said you have it
The parents are grandparents house
Since you can set it up for Auto
Connect 4 Auto
Yeah
Yes auto answer
Could you theoretically use it as a
Remote monitoring tool
I
Auto answers
It doesn't
Have video
Sono Chi
Auto answers I believe it is just voice
Inow kind of
Oh there's one other thing though that's
That there's an app on your phone and that becomes part of your network to so when your aunt like I'm on the road right now but I
Call my daughter
Vici
So if I read my office
I said she heard it she can go answer it
We just established a connection without hurting a smartphone without
You know any effort on her part except answering a
If not it's a nice picture
So
I'm liking it
Kind of fun
Is it worth $200
In our house maybe not
But I can see setting up it would be worth
It'd be worth $100
Search for like a connection with
I think so
I will also say that
So if your family is TekSavvy maybe this isn't
Like the best for you
My mom for example I'm always like I have to call her
My mom will you get
Skype
Or I text her to like a mom let's do a Duo call
There is no spontaneity
And sometimes it's
How I would
Phone isn't plugged in
Skype's not on this computer right now because I doing something else
So this would be kind of fun for the
Yay
Okay so
That is the show for this week
Stay tuned
An interview on
Home Security
And iot security featuring Andy Ellis the CSO of Akamai
You're going to learn a lot of really good stuff in this
Or we do that
Let's have a message from our sponsor we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast
With a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Hewlett-Packard Enterprise
Can I have dr. Tom Braddock who is a VP and general manager for servers and iot systems
At hpe
Here with me today to talk about how HP handles analytics at the edge
Tom hpe has introduced a new product
Call The Edge line boxes
And they have 64-bit
Computing at the edge
Are these gateways
Juggernaut gateways
And that is the the difference here in fact it's 64-bit
Which as you know is Intel's high-end
Architecture that we can play
Gateway category and we have products and sucked my competitors
Atom Processor sometimes
No processor
What will you need to do deep analytics fast
Then you need the horsepower of proving enterprise-class
Such as
64 Intel Xeon cores that we have and therefore we had to create a new product
Category
And that new categories called
Convert 70 system
And in that category we convert several things in a single
Environmentally hardened box
And that chassis or box is temperature
Shocking vibration pardon
Q64
230 lb
And this has something
In the same box it also houses
Data acquisition
And control systems
Call my partner National instruments in the same box and then we also converge
Hpe ilo integrated lights-out
Remote
Management psychology
Because again what's more remote than the other called The iot Edge
Listen products
Vines
Amazing benefits in his conversion
Also
Amazing benefits and its ability to do
Analytics that's normally reserved for the Datacenter
And you come fast
Because they're out of the edge
Freddy turn around time in the response
Candy
What's quicker and many times a meeting
Do I still need a Gateway box
In the scenario
The Edge line iot converge systems can do the job of a gateway
Wechat customer applications now
We have
A gateway
Connected to the iot convergence
So you guys are essentially putting a mini Datacenter
At the edge
Why
Do we need some
What's a good way to put it because it has tremendous high performance Computing capability
And
I need a quick example in the world
Artificial intelligence machine learning and cognitive
Computing
There's a notion of building the model
Machine learning applications
Takes a lot of CPU power
To build
The cloud has a sensor and it's shifting
Which such
Bill demott
Augmentin and run
The banlist the security issues the latency in the cost issues
Are eliminated when
All done at the edge
Oktap
Where can we find out more about Hewlett-Packard in
You can find more by going to our website
Hpe.com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest we have Andy Ellis who is the chief security officer at Akamai
I'm doing fantastic
Sick today Stacy how are you
I am super great
I can't believe you're doing so fantastic
Play because
On Friday
The internet was under attack
I feel like you guys probably were noticing that
Had some opinions on
Yes
So we saw your the attack against dying it's worth noting that you're dying like Akamai Mini
Other companies your parts of the infrastructure that make up the internet and the web as we know it
Internet
It wasn't under attack the routing fabric with holding up fine
There were just a bunch of
Really popular websites that weren't available
The East Coast on Friday
So in the wake of this
Security researcher
Discover that once again this massive
Adidas
Distributed denial-of-service attack
Against
This actually was
Done by the sea
I don't know if it's the same organization but using the same source code that was used a couple
Weeks ago against you guys to attack
I think it was Brian Krebs
Website yes
Yep. There's the Mirai code which is used to build this botnet
Mostly of your network video recorder some other things in iot
Hard-coded default password
And we see some of the same devices showing up
In both the tax
That could be the same actors
It could be different actors now the source code is out there
And one of the things we have certainly seen in the past
Some other denial-of-service attack see when people are taking over WordPress sites
Is once it became well-known
Great source of botnet material
Lots of people in fought over that botnet
It would take different parts of it for themselves to go to attack
That's a pretty normal thing you see in the DDOS For Hire world
Okay so these people are basically they have a massive network of
Devices
They can use
The hammer someone servers
What you're saying is
Other people then
Take over parts of
They steal it okay
So it's Bots battling Bots
Effectively
I never seen a lot of
Scanning traffic in the background noise of the internet
People looking for machines to compromise
So let's get to these machines
I feel like everybody is attacking me
According to the Internet of Things
Really feels like it's a lot of these devices appear to be routers Network DVR cameras some printers
And they feel like things that maybe
But is it fair to
Call this The Internet of Things or should we maybe come up with better
Better terminology
So one of my calling
It's called it things on the internet
Which is probably a little more apropos
I like it how do we want to make a distinguishing lime
Two types of
So I'm not sure yet but I know where I draw the line between the things on the internet and the stuff that came
Before
Legal terms
Is if we think about everything that came before it was always associated with an entity
You think about PCS or laptops or tablets is being tied to a human
We think about servers has been tied to some business venture
Oregon
Rupert coalition
And all the sudden you have these
People die they put on the internet and they abandon them
And they're really not part of a network Fabric and not a mess
It's not like your fitness trackers we have 85 things monitoring your health that are talking
We have these devices to just get plugged in and put on the internet
Really associated with the person that bought them maybe it's the network video recorder at your local convenience
Store
Maybe this is your home router that you buy a new drop-in
It's doing traffic all the time that has nothing to do
If it's human there's no human sort of behind it
And for me that's where we've does become
Mustang on the internet
I guess I had to make a hypothesis
For where Internet of Things takes over
Is this really where those become
Part of something greater than themselves
Turn objects the truly is Network
Not just in the TCP IP centos
Who was in the day of an application there as well
I like to see I was making a division based on
Things that were
Modern design to be updated over the air
As opposed to like older stuff that they're like oh that's connect this
And it's kind of directly connected to the internet
Maybe just go through a cloud
I like yours better
I think the reason that's an important
Extinction is not just about modern versus Legacy we are still seeing devices put on the internet
It look more like things
Just don't have this
Over-the-air updates is over the updates are updates is really hard
What makes these old devices
Sister just sitting out there and attach to any
So
Problematic
I think what makes some problematic kits
So first of all is the fact of their omnipresence on me
Network video recorder
You think about its functionality
Is the ferry first version of the no network capability right you plug it in
You plug a monitor and keyboard and a mouse into it
And so you could look through all of your camera
Let's put this in the back room and we've got all these monitors everywhere
Searching for the web server on it
But it wasn't designed to be over the internet web server
MSA designed to be an amusing very liberal
I use of the word design apologizing software architect
It was really sort of Cobble together in many cases
He space and now it's there
Cassidy that just shows up
It is a fully functioning Linux server
You can login
You can do whatever you want
General purpose
Computer
No longer sort of very specific Hardware design.
Only do one thing
And that's where it starts to become a problem
Got it to send you have this massive
Capability that's no one no one is really paying attention to the
The to be harnessed for
All kinds of Shanaynay
Yeah as long as the cameras are still operating like
When a convenience store is going to notice
Well that brings me to my next question which is if I'm a consumer
How would I ever know if
Is my devices
Saudi really hard it's in that category of difficulty that moves
Small businesses and even medium businesses don't even look at whether or not their bandwidth is being used
To do
You have to do the monitoring
If I hold out of Hope
Why I'm fantastic
Wonderful idea if anybody wants to execute on it can totally take the switches
Parental controls
The monitoring software and Hardware that people to play for parental controls whether it's
Your Disney Circle or web nanny or any of these
Why does the opportunity to think of these devices as children
Adults and the way they use the internet changes
If I put a network video recorder in my home
It seems like the sort of thing that a small device that used to profile in traffic and preventing unauthorized uses
Would be wonderful and ensuring that I'm not participating in one of these.
Okay so I everyone should have some sort of software
It would be on their router that would
Possibly on your router's possibly as a home device I'm I got to order it circle from Disney
Cuz I got some Ayo to my house I'd love to filter out
There you go
Okay
So you wouldn't know accept it
Is being used
What can you do if
You do have one of these
Set it afire
Sadly that might be the best
Quotes for a couple of days
Do some of these devices that actually
Have hard-coded into their software the password
So it's not even as I can tell you to go in
And change the default password
Right and that means that it's written in the code the consumer can't change it it's just
A remnant of something
Can I say lazy
I don't like attributing malice or incompetence
The people put the user authentication is really hard to do right
And so once you start down the path of a will how would I do user authentication in this world
Your building these devices here and going to business to your Kickstarter
Are you going to ship devices out to all these people
As soon as you say
You don't want to have a default password
What's the initial password on this device
What are user opens up the box
What is barracks
Experience
Now you could build something
This says okay well it has to do autotune
Discovery Inn connect
Password
Like it
Impossible
Right password management software
Android user experience only friendly
That's really what the Internet of Things is about
Surrounding yourself with the internet in ways that makes your life better not worse
Soda biscuits
Sin 2 - what should I look for in the devices that I buy
Basically
There's no sticker in the box that says
Hard-coded password
Where
So
What are the types of
Questions I should
To be asking even a
Honestly even as a reporter when I'm
How do I curl them
Tyson question number 0
Is
Is this a server
Activate very different set of problems if you have a device that is only a client
It makes connections out
It does pulling together data
Did you have if you have a machine that is running a TCP server that people could fit with connect to
DP server into problems is where you are a service
Do people can interact with because that interact
If the only way you can interact
Uconnect out
I'm not saying you're perfect
Solve a lot of challenges you have how do you authenticate
Who you talk to their legitimate
But that would be the first Quest
Used to figure out
Is the server
And if it's a server did it really need to be
Okay so
A popular name
Device that people think of is a server is a nest thermostat
Does that meet your criteria
So I don't know how this did the implementation
The Google has a okay home I believe it is
Other devices
But I don't believe the original Nets needed to be a server I did sits here
It monitors your temperature it makes a call out
And it does stuff
Okay but do you run a web server that you talk to
From your phone didn't you
Your phone
No but did you talk directly to it or did you talk to nest
It was a client your phone with a client they're both talking to a server somewhere else
Such a different problem right that's it but it's not
This case where an adversary can login directly to your nest
Start sending out packages
Necessarily
Okay and I think architecture Lee
What are the things I've been hearing is that
Having a device that has a
Cloud interface so
Utah to
The cloud
It talks to the cloud weibo
There's cloud
Nothing is directly
Connecting out to the intern
Annette in that feels like
Probably a good way to go
Bradley
Devices
That's it
Great way to go to for this problem now on the flipside that means that if the vendor goes out of business your device stops
Alright so then what do I do
Except bricks in exchange for security
Doctor from within your home
Oh wait but we just said that's a bad idea
Butcher Trading
30 goal against security goal
So one is you want to have availability in the event of a failure or business model change on the part of your
The other is
Do you want to be a public health
Cash
So excited
So there is no middle ground
Can we put a hub in and have that
Be the brains of the operation at just the server in the hub
I could talk to the cloud but then there's local stuff
Never goes out
Isn't that what
Your Apple homekit and Google with onhub
And perhaps ultimately Amazon with Alexa are aiming at used to be that central point of contact within
It would broker these interactions for you
I believe it
Okay
So that's how I should be thinking of my
My new secure architecture that is also convenia
Got it so like what happens now
The I believe one of the vendors
Actually just did a recall of all of their devices it was a Chinese IP
Butcher its name
Hong's uchiyama
Technology
I gotcha by I feel like that's
Enough
So these guys did a voluntary
Should we be looking for more of that s***
Government get involved in
Bad actors get
They have a recall well it's going to be interesting to look into what is the effect of the voluntary recall
Because remember these two devices that mostly
Purchase
Deployed in a band
Oh my goodness mine is one of those
I want to participate interesting to look at
Details of the recall are they give you your money back
Acquire a new one
What are they actually going to do
That's yo question number one that's always been
Will it be in business
Or will they show up as a different company neck
Weed selling a slightly different product
Skeptical
The Challenger and regulations going to be the global problem
The Chinese manufacturer I want to blame all Chinese manufacturing buses run with this one for a moment
Let's imagine the US how to login
Something
That we believe that actually work for what was that loud really did what it is
Stop this botnet from being accessible to be groomed
Absolutely not
Most of the Bots aren't even in the Uso
It makes these devices not available in the US
What you'd also do is you would inhibit the production of a lot of devices by us company
Think about how many objects on Kickstarter would be affected by regulation here and would that have a net good
Negative for us
That's true and this particular company actually does
Software and other connected
We haven't even gotten into the fact that a lot of connected devices
Have a supply chain that is just really opaque
Very opaque and let's be honest
Ravens today
You probably only care about three things you care about the resolution of the attached cameras you care about that how much disk
You have and whether you could expand that externally
Can you care about the price
If you ever use one there they're all horribly on YouTube
Like the interfaces are not the most graceful and beautiful things because that's not what people are paying for
Give me a video feed
Make it as good as I can get at the Dollar Tree
That is true
Alright so we have to change some things the industry has to change some things in
People shouldn't be surprised sensitive
I don't know
This is one of those tricky problems where we have externalities in the system oh my goodness anytime you see
Systemic flies look for the externality the
Acquirers
The companies that make these
The Network's at their hosted on are not the ones that feel the pain
But they're the ones who make all the financial
People feel the pain
Are the targets
They're hosting Networks
And their fender
So we have this yoke
Beautiful dichotomy where
Do all of the
Initial costs are born by one group
But the secondary costs are completely born by the second group
We know from The Economist if we believe they know what they're talking about
Is it that leads to externalities were the first people act to minimize their cost of maximize the cost on others
Right so
Given this
Andy do you have a solution for us
Do you have any sort of recommendations on
How we can kind of make
Iot more secure cuz right now people are looking at this and going
Holy cow I want none of this crap in my
Or
Holy cow this stuff is terribly dangerous let's regulate the heck out of
First reaction might be slightly better than the second react
Which is the user saying I don't want to be part of that that's imrie internalizing
The externality and that's a Market Force
So maybe we will see people shift until I want to go to this Hub mode
And maybe this house mode will also protect you against devices doesn't
Like I said there's a market there
For parental control devices for your robots
So that's my that's what I'm holding out for the other thing I'm holding out for is
This is not something that is new
Even though it feels
Do we see harbingers like this
Every few years on the internet bill when we discovered all the empaths WordPress in Joomla site Severus like oh my goodness
Anybody survive that
The answer is not only did we survive those attacks
But by today's standards dos attack
Arbutus
Because the internet has grown so much
Defensive Brown
It's at the internet has grown so much
This is such a small
Percentage of the traffic now
This those when it's a big percentage of traffic it's noticeable
But my expectation and belief is that the internet will continue to grow
Will deliver you a larger and larger videos and more and more people that's capacity
It is important to be there for us to be able to handle denial-of-service attacks since well
But doesn't that capacity
Increase also increase
Pain
Power of a denial-of-service
What is a tax because as
As you're pumping out more internet content at higher resolutions
I is a consumer in tempted to upgrade my Broadband which gives them more bandwidth to
Intern point
It's I believe that you are the tax from the network video recorder
Well within a few years we'll tell why were we worried about care of it for second attack
Now we're worried about
But that'll be a world in which we talked about your pet a bit scale networks that are delivering huge volumes of traffic
Awesome I hope you guys
Can keep growing the network
I keep up with these attacks all right Andy thank you so much for coming on this week
Picture Show
Well that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again next week
On the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show feel free to stay
Sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com