Hey everybody Welcome to The Internet of Things show
This is Stacey Higginbotham and my co-host
Kevin tofel
And we are coming to you today from lovely New York city so I'm going to apologize if you hear honking or text
Tcaps in the background
I'm not in my studio
It Kevin
What's your excuse for the day
It's early in the morning that you woke me up for this ship
I have no excuse now
It's very early in the morning for Kevin so let's let's talk a little slower today we'll take it a little easier
Starting off with
The big news this is
The day after
Apple's big
Keto diet at
W is a WWDC
DC
It's WWDC worldwide and appleland is one Kit Kat needed word
Okay that's what I thought
Someone the other day was trying to tell me otherwise
It's not
So this is the day after
WWDC
And
I was looking for a lot
A lot of news around homekit
As you guys probably could tell having listened to our previous two shows
And Kevin
Do we get any news around homekit
We got bikers
We did we got
How do you say we got very little
And now you're right you're right
It's the bikini was very
Pactiv a lot to talk about but the focus was not on homekit for sure it was certainly on iOS 9
IOS 1011
Apple pay in Saint sauveur
Don't get really barely got a mention there was talk of the new devices that are currently available and then
They turn more towards the future and said here is what we're going to have funeral homes
Punk it will be able to support window blinds and
Other sensors and you'll be able to remotely access your homekit
Devices
Through iCloud
Which is interested in say through your Apple TV because we found out last week
That is one of the ways you will actually do that
True and actually there was no apple.
TV news
Again Butkus
Nothing
They did have the streaming media service
So
I actually talk to you
Stewart Lombard who is the CEO of ecobee because I was very
Curious
About the ecobee last show we speculated originally that the ecobee
3 which was going to be homekit supported
It would get an over-the-air software update cuz that
Made the most sense for my perspective
Especially considering they launched this thermostat in September 2014 after homekit was even announced
What we found out later and we had a correction on the show was that
Actually
You have to buy a new one and people were not
Happy
No
And I can understand that means spending a $250 on a thermostat
Install a gate in your house and then realizing it less than a year later it's basically not going to be
Compatible with homekit
If we get something that's important to you that
That's a real bummer
I I would agree with you let me here's a question and not and it's okay if you don't know the answer I don't know the answer either but
Yes we know that Apple announced the homekit platform look at last year's WWDC so last May or June I forget which month
It was last year
And it's been talking to her partners and so on and so forth and has the homekit certification program and there's a little hunk it logo for
For that certification program
Did ecobee and other Hardware partners that matter have the homekit logo on the products that they've been selling up to this point
I'm betting not
No they haven't
So ecobee basically it was one of the first four devices
I got certified last week
The others with a Lutron
Specific Lutron hub
Specific insteon hub
Is it alegado
A group of sensors
That will not be back out or they will not be on the market anytime soon
In talking to Stewart because
I heard enough complaints from people I was I was like I got to talk to this guy and figure out what's going on
He told me
But what happened was sometime after
After CES
Basically
Apple
Made up its mind and went with the hardware-based security solution which meant that the existing products
Existing ecobee3 products on the market we're not going to be upgradable
Obviously he was very disappointed by that he said
He said he thought about it but
He wanted to get his product
Updated it out and certified by Apple
And he was acknowledging that his other users are going to be kind of left out in
Nicole
But
They're still going to get
Updates for all the other stuff
It's just not home
It's definitely a catch-22 for any
Hardware maker or device maker this space because you
Don't want to upset your existing customer base they're the ones that are helping you move forward to begin with
But you don't want to miss the opportunity being one of the first quarter quell first people to
You know p
Certified and be in the Apple store and have
That wide
Range of availability at such a tough call
Exactly he hears a quote from
Storage
He told me
We could have held back on homekit and left our existing model in the market
But we wanted to involve the platform as quickly as possible
No matter when we decided to do the upgrade there is always going to be someone who bought the
The products last month
It's true
So the reason
Herb for anybody
What is this
It looks like it boils down to Apple security
Its or at least in this case Lombard said that
Apple required a security coprocessor to actually be in the device
And they open till
Currently January when they told
Ecobee said it wouldn't be
Supper a credible they were going back and forth like
Would it be software upgradable or would it have to be Hardware
And apparently Apple chose Hardware with his co-processor
And that actually has big ramifications because it sounds like
That wasn't actually known until after CES
So when I talk to Philips the makers of the hue light bulbs at CVS
They implied strongly that their customers would have access or their customers would be upgradable
They didn't come out and say it
But the implied very strongly that their customers who are their existing customers
Wouldn't have problems
Switch homekit
What's actually happen
Philips hue light bulbs
They're homekit certified that hoe
Whole package won't come out
Until September
And it is going to require new hardware
Black Phillip says
They will make sure that their existing
Hue light bulb
Holders will
Let's see what was there quote
All existing hue light sources will be made
Compatible with homekit
Apple's homekit support will launch this fall and Philips Hue will help existing users to upgrade their system
So I don't know what kind of help I should be looking for 4
Yas
I am turn on I doubt it's going to be a trade in program I have no idea what it's going to be maybe some reduce rates
Basically this is
This looks to be about security
Which is very important to a
And
From a user standpoint that's
Crate I was at a conference last week where the CMO of Home Depot actually raised her hand and asked a panel of smart home
Manufacturers
What is the deal with security
How can we
Sell these things to Consumers when there's a big concern about this
And if the CMO of Home Depot
Which is a retailer that stocks a lot of these products is concerned about security then
You know what baby apple made the right back here
I don't think they made the wrong
Decision here I think choosing
Tighter or
Security that you can control and some other way shape or form is much better
It's just that the timing of it and the communication to Partners and sew onto made it
We see this a lot it's not just that
I also don't want to pick on any single company in here but we see this a lot especially in this space
Plan people have great plans
The details are still murky when the plans get announced platforms are announced
And then over time as
Details come
Qunar workout
Ultimately
Consumers are either left flirting cuz they
But earlier products
It's something is change of the platform
Or something to that effect it's it's it's really really tough It's
Frustrating
Especially in this space because I've been doing this for
5 years old
Do-it-yourself home
Stuff
It's frustrating
It is so the moral here is the moral here don't be an early adopter
Well I mean I'm I'm always going to be one because it's in my blood
So it's hard for me to say that kind of feel like
I shouldn't say that but yeah
There's there's a lot of great products out there and they offer so much
Thomas
But at the end of the day may make sense to not go with version 1 of anything and then wait for v2 I mean that's that's pretty
And nodejs in iot space but
Phone watches wearables whatever maybe
There we go
Well out there was some watch news so that the second iteration of the Apple watch
Since you haven't
Apple watch are you excited what did you think about the
Futuristic
I think what we're moving real fast and we went from watch OS want to watch OS 2 in a matter of
6 weeks
Cuz that's what that one else watch os2 for their Apple watch
I am excited that the whole Apple watch experience has been
Mostly good for me it
Been disappointing in terms of apps because there really are no native apps
From third parties only from Apple
And the glances in the notifications and such
They can take time to get from the phone which is where the
Watch apps are really running now
So it's been a frustrating experience
Watch os2 should help that because it gave developers the Opera
Opportunity the tools I should say
To build native apps so
Some of the some of the interesting bits here there's going to be more
Customizable faces
Really liked actually the
The time lapse face I don't know if you got to see any of this Stacy but
You can take a time-lapse photo and then when you when your watch
Activate to show you the time
Time lapse washer take place so it's you know you might get a boat going across a
River really fast in a time lapse matter what I was just kind of Interest
App developers will get to create their own was called complications on watches Witcher
Little data points so
Instead of having just the
The Apple only type choices for what you can put on your watch face you'll be able to say put your
Your next appointment or your travel schedule for example or
They showed
The charging rate of your
Hybrid car
Just like the activity
Rings that they have on there today
So your car is charging little ring won't close up you know so you can have that on your watch
So developers to create that which is awesome
Whatever they want
And complications
Ventura watch
Compilations actually
That's a realtor it's a real watch Turbo I thought I think
It's like all the little
Any
Yeah any additional information other than the time
Libya complication watch the date
Today
The time zone exactly
So there you go so
Wow I just sent that early in the morning
Okay
So outside of app
I have
Because I was in San Francisco last week
Meeting with startups
I have an amazing
Start up that I have to
To tell you about
They're making an intelligent oven
So
Play The Jacksons can I just
Punch numbers in
Just have it's almost as cool so here's what they're did
These guys are making a countertop oven
And they
Instead of just being like I'm going to put some Wi-Fi in it and it's going to be smart
What they've done is they've added
A camera
On the roof of the oven
That
Looks at the food inside they've added
Integrated thermometer probe
Now that you can shove into the food and then they've added
Sensors in the feet
Of the other
So
The oven itself can become a scale
So what happens is
If you stick like a roast
You take a roast and you stick it in the oven you're going to pop
Thermometer in there so it knows the temperature inside
The chicken
The camera is going to recognize
That there's a chicken in the oven
It's using the same sort of
Computer vision algorithms that Google and Microsoft working on
It's a little easier for them because there's a lot
Fewer
Food classes that they have to teach the computer
Because everything taste like chicken
This is a bagel taste like chicken
Descale
Elements
Measure the weight of your check
So basically what you do
Ability as you can tell the
Open
Capacitive touch screen on the front
Of course it does
In-N-Out
I should say that but
I never want to touch
Spike my hands get so greasy I'm like I don't want to touch
You know anything
Any touch screen
It wouldn't be nothing without a knob anyway
So you can pop your chicken in
You say hey I want to roast chicken
Set your timer
It will set your temperature it will do all of that for you
Because it knows how much it weighs it knows it's a chicken at knows the temperature inside
As it's been cooked
Anna Scott
Panchos
Recipes and stuff inside and the ability to kind of
So it's pretty amazing
The other thing about it
And you can also do your own
You do not have to follow if you're like
I am smarter than you
Call the June oven so I'm smarter than you June
You can do that
And it also has
Adapt
But the nice thing about the app is with all of the stuff you don't actually to keep going back and checking on your food so even if you don't try
You can look at the camera in
See the food inside of you like
My chicken looks almost done
And you don't have to keep opening in the oven
So that's
Someone who is like
A little Taipei in
You know makes things all the time
And has a husband who
Petrified of food that's not cooked to the proper temperature
Would be amazing for me
So this it's on your countertop
It has its about 22 in across
The big Square thing so it
It would replace its large
The other thing
About this is
They built it of new materials
And they really rethought
The oven in a way that I think is amazing like
The heating elements
AR
Carbon nanotubes
Basically
Carbon fiber nanotubes
Steady up
Superfast for your oven to preheat to 350 degrees in 4 minutes
Which
That's impressive that is nice
And there's like all kinds of like
Oven features I'll call them Thursday consulted with Michael Mina who is a chef
About like
Oven features you need
Zoe's
Easy Bake Oven to.
Exactly it's a it's a fancy toaster oven
So
Considering that a wall oven
How much does it cost
Okay
It cost
$1,500
Well that's actually less than I
Expected but then again
It is small
It is small so you cannot cook a turkey
A traditional half sheet cookie sheet cannot fit in it
You have to get
Especial
It will fit a 9 by 13 baking
Which is the traditional kind of
Baking pan that use for cakes
It'll come with its own stuff too but you can buy special size
Cure for smaller ovens believe in
They're not it'll fit a tray that is 11 in by 16 in
That's actually about an inch smaller around a half sheet
A traditional half sheet
Trey
So
Is it
Replacement oven
For most things
Probably
Yeah
For everything know you can't cook your Thanksgiving turkey
Right right
Traditional wall oven does cost between 11000 in like if they can go up to it like crazy high things I've got a
Double wall oven that was like
3500 I think
So
Athens or not
Cheap but this is probably
Unless you're you know Young and Living in a small apartment this is probably not
Replace rubber
Yeah I put a burrito saying about being early adopters
Exactly
I really I really do I like that they
I like all the sensors I've seen that piecemeal
We talked about super mechanical waves you can Heather CEO in the podcast
Talk about the range thermometer and the intelligence that adds there's the meld kitchen knob the oven knob
That does a similar kind of learning thing that helps you it has
A knob that
Controls
Your stove start your stove top
And what it does is it measures the
Temperature of whatever you're cooking on the stove
And that it automatically adjust
Burners basically back or up to keep that temperature in the rate range for doing whatever you're trying to do
Is this a currently available or is it coming soon
You can pre-order it
Starting this week
You have to put $95 down
If it will not be out
Until spring of
I was going to say if it's out soon I give it a year before Samsung buy these guys
There you go well
Make it two years now
Make it two years I've seen I seen the oven at baked me cookies they were delicious
So
I am sitting
Really can I justify a 50
But I'm not my rule is I don't buy until so
Something's actually on
On the market that price point
A small
A small toy pet I will not buy
A $1,500 oven on sale right now I would agree
But hopefully someone will because
There's a lot of innovation here I like the way they're thinking about it
It's hard to read
I made it really is
Yeah I agree with you I love the idea that they have going on here I would like to see it expand
Tattoo traditional size ovens and to be honest and I'm not trying to downplay what they've done by any means
When I say this
I mean you could add these types of sensors and things to traditional ovens and that's why I said what I said about Samsung who does make tons more
Appliances
So
To me this is a precursor for what you met at Sea in a standard traditional oven
In
Your five
8 years
And did you just replace all of your appliances
Thank you thanks thanks so much for reminding me though
We just did that thank you so much you know if it makes you feel better I just bought all my appliances only 2 years ago so I feel like
I can't really buy a new oven
Probably
Alright so that's the June oven and I really excited about that partially
In other news this week
There is a
Wink
By my least favorite home hub is having
My understanding is that
Wink
The software platform
Has been for sale
Actually several months
And now I'm hearing that quirky
Which is the company that
Is producing a lot of
Hardware
It's the product development shop that produces a lot of the hardware for wing
Techquickie is getting out of manufacture
That is pretty
That's big
Big news
It's not necessarily surprising
But it is kind of
I don't know it's
Kind of sad
To see
Sunday that had so much support
Court
Are there still their parents are still available at Home Depot I know that
They are and they just had a couple weeks ago
They had a big sick
Security snafu
Where certificate
Some people's hubs
They couldn't even update over-the-air because of this problem
So they actually had to send their wings
Cubs back
Which you can imagine did not make
Customer is very happy
So
Yeah I'm clear what all is happening at
Winkle actually called them and try to figure out but I haven't heard back from anyone at Winker Corky
So
That is what we know now but
If you guys are in the market for a home hub do not buy a Wii
I'd be cautious
I'll be diplomatic
Speedway on Lake
We never you never know what's going to happen
Honestly I mean you know we've seen companies at 4
You know you thought they were down and out and then they get picked up by somebody else in the product line continues does it happen often no
But it does happen
Thirsty I'm sure there's a lot of people that have this product out there so that you know they're going to want
To keep using it in One support and so on and so forth so
It's it's hard to say what's going to happen
Maybe Samsung
Pick some up
And with the
Fix it there you go I mean it's a perfect example of what
Would probably be a best case scenario everything
Yes
So now we have Samsung buying another company we talked about and possibly wink
This is our speculation
Samsung is not actually buying us company
Okay
So I think
This week we don't have a guest
Because I was so hopeful excited that Apple would do a bunch of cool home stuff
Wentworth
I know it we did not
Schedule a guest for this week
Which now in hindsight I feel like
Why did I do that Tim Cook was just too busy today to come on the show on porchlight talk about on
It's true and you know I would have settled for Jony Ive
Sell aluminium
Say that all day long
So I think that means that it is time for our
5-minute review
All right
Today's review is ring
It is a $200
Connected
Doorbell
And I've had this on my
It's actually not installed
In my doorbell and we'll get to that in a second
What this is is
You place this doorbell
It's about the size of a smartphone
Either wired into your doorbell
Or you can just bounce it
If it is Wireless so it it talks to the internet via Wi-Fi
It what it does is it has a camera and a microphone in
It when someone rings the doorbell
It opens up a video feed of that
Person
And you can talk to them in
And say things like
Hey leave the package downstairs I'll come grab it or
You can even pretend to be home when you're not home
And
It's
Actually really need device I have wanted a video
Doorbell
Almost since I started covering the smart home because I have a
A rooftop deck in my house in
What we all
Go up there in the sky
It's more like the spring
We like to go up there and
Order pizza
I have friends over but we can't hear the doorbell Up on the Roof
So this way
We could both hear the doorbell cuz it brings to our phone
If you install it
In place of your existing doorbell it will also ring
If you wired into your wall basically it will also bring your actual name
Mechanical door
And then
Ring
Is going to launch a product this month called the chime
That for $20
It basically if you don't
Connect it to your mechanical doorbell it will still ring
In your house
So
That's kind of what it does
And here's some things I learned about it
Install
1 this works
Ring used to be known as a company called Orbot and their original doorbell
Having a lot of issues people really didn't enjoy
Using it
The video feed wasn't good
Appear very fast
This is much better this the video feed is almost instantaneous
The challenge I had with these and I have no idea how your doorbell is oriented
But my doorbell is not oriented on the same wall
Is my door
So
My doorbell
Is that a right angle
To my
Door
Yeah
Yeah so it makes the camera so basically what I'm looking at an Indian people also
When they ring the doorbell
They don't realize there's a
What you're going to see you
Depending on how high
Right it's probably a wide-angle lens I'm thinking but still here with the height
It is a wedding
So you can see a lot of
Not very flattering
Camera adds 20lbs best wide angle
I didn't install it to my actual
Doorbell so I don't know about it
Mechanical
Efficacy rate
For ringing the doorbell
So I mean I'm sorry you guys nor do I know how easy it is to install
From a wired
Perspective and you said it was mechanical so does it physically press your doorbell button if you install
Electrical
The electrical signal to the thing that
It doesn't actually
Sorry it sent it to The Chimes
What's inside your house
So I stuck it on the outside of my
Dorin because it's a review
Daughters are harder review
I had to like command tape that sucker
Is a lot of double-sided tape I had to create some padding
Even so
Famous Amos very changkyun ugly
But
And then I covered up my doorbell with
Ring The Ring
Which provided a lot of
Fusion at Birth
Yours doesn't have
To be set up.
Yours could be pretty
And
Although if your doorbell is Orion
Does your doorbell face out
Mine faces out we live in the sticks and really I don't think our doorbell has been running for years but it does face
So it was neat to be able to see
Cuz it's motion it has a motion sensor so when people started walking up to the door
Which trigger Inlet
So
If the UPS guy was coming and had a package I can actually make it down the time to sign the package before he like
Which is usually what
They have places to be I guess
So
$200
It's the ring doorbell
And you can buy it
Amazon at their website
Best Buy
And it is
You know if you're in the market for something like this
It seemed to do well I will let you guys know that I am getting a
A Skype
Which is one of its competitors
Very soon
So if you're
Want to listen to see how
That door.
Comparison
You know you have to mount the two of them together now so we can have a b testing for
You know video and audio and all that
So your chest but I actually have
Two front doors with doorbells
Believe it or not
My house is oriented so
I have two entrances
A front in the back
Can't wait to get into the house and they both look like a front door with a doorbell
So
I can actually
You won't choose which ones
You get to
There we go
So that is
Play
Review of the Ringling
I'm going to say sorry
The ring
I have one question about it.
Hit me
Cross platform support iOS Android anyting else
IOS
Android
Currently
I don't think it works with any it's not integrators supported into any of the existing
I could be wrong because
Staples
Connect
Launch with
The Rings predecessor
Doorbot
So there's hope
But
Because of the doorbot
Kind of
Reviews
I'm not sure how
Recorded
It is
But this is the new version
Much better
And that
Unless you got any other grape grape connected
Home news are great news on the
Internet of Things front I wish I had a connected coffee maker next to me right now that's all I'm going to say
Kevin
Timeout
There we go alright
Well thank you guys so much for listening I hope you enjoy the show and will be back next week