Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we are here with a bunch of stuff this
Just like last week we're actually going to have some Deja Vu talking about
Amazon Alexa
We're going to talk about insurance for the Smart Home
Or how does smartphone relates to the insurance Market
I took a trip to Marriott Hotels to see what the
The hotel room of the future is going to look like
It will be talking about
Experience of a 6-month point
Our Guest this week will be Darren samuelsohn
Who is a reporter at Politico who
Works on a massive spread that magazine did on how DC is looking at regulating the internet of
So stay tuned for all of the symbols
Great Kevin
Here we are
It's like
It's like it's last week all over again because our first topic is
Going to be Amazon
Yeah yeah I'm going to rub it in that I don't have an echo
See I didn't even know
Bring that up
You must be doing some serious angst because it's like
I'm going to make a bold proposition
This week amatar actually was last week
Amazon open.
It's voice SDK
And the kind of
Research and development in
Building
Voice recognition into the Echo and then it also opened up easy integration
To the echo for
Developers
Does a cherry on top of that Sunday
Created a hundred billion dollar fund
Support Alexa which is are startups using Alexa which is the AI brains
Can you find
The echo
Because makes
Actually better
Right now I think Amazon just outmaneuvered Apple
When it comes to the smart
You know what you told me that before the show and I sort of
Said I get your point but I'm not sure I agree but then you raise some really
Good points about people's recent experiences with Siri voice
Activation and
At home cat that just really haven't been up to par yet and
I think was
Frank Frank Fowler over at 2
He was returned
Yeah he was talking last week about how hung kittens
Siri together Air Canada
Just not all there
Just not all that
And
You got me thinking you might be right maybe Amazon has
Slowly but surely
Position himself really well
For the smart home with Echo
Here's my take on this and here's why I'm saying
Because I'm
I'm not I'm the furthest thing probably from an Apple fan
Fanboy out
I do respect
Stead
You know it has done an amazing job bringing
Really difficult technology to users and make it really simple
So
I was really hoping that
They would get there
I was really looking forward to
The issue with the smart home so far there's a couple
It's expensive
But it's also hard to
Get out of use each other you could put in one device
Two devices
That's hard
I mean that's what we spend
You know hours talking about of the show
What's going to happen to your and it's both like an integration standard issue but it's also a UI issue
Because you may be happy with
Carrying your phone around all day but I am most assuredly not
Before the show
Activate to wake up my nest
That was one problem but the same problem was
Physically left my desk
To do it
Because my phone was sitting next to me but it couldn't load the app faster
Then I could get up and
Which really is terrible
Slamming it that's got to be fixed
That is terrible
Maybe I'll reboot my phone
When you think about things like that
It's really just sucky to be a consumer right now this invoice
Is a wonderful way
For lazy people like me to stay in the chair
It's also a bit faster
To be like
Hey Alexa
Turn my Nest back on
All I need to do
And so what episode is done with Alexa
And then by opening it up it's created a platform
Where the standards don't matter
Because everything's going to go through
And
You control it all the invoice which is really intuitive and if you want you can
Get up off your butt and go
Musically or you can do it from
Eddie number of the apps on your phone but you don't
What the other biggie here is that
One device can be used by multiple people in the same house
To control whatever needs to be
So it's not like you have six
Smartphones everybody's got their own app and everything from nasty or whatever it may be
If you have one
Interface that you share
In this case voice
I mean that's that take a lot of complexity out of things
That's a brilliant point
I'm glad you that's why I'm that's why I'm here thank you
I'm so glad that I don't pay you to come
So
I talked to startups that are working with Amazon in the Echo Or Nah funded by Amazon
We're building these things
And we're going to see products coming out
Before the end of this year probably within you know a month or two
Discount alarm
Is one of them
What's a DIY
The orange chef
Which makes
Wait we actually talked about it makes a connected kitchen scale and it also makes a device called countertop
That you're going to be able to buy
I think next year
Waze off but
It's next to your Vitamix blender and some other things
Till like
Basically give you recipes and recommendations tied to like your job own app
So tied to your activity
What you have in your house and gives you recommendations I want to
Some other
Groups that are kind of interesting
AR
Dragon Innovation which is a company that works with a lot of startups
The CEO of Dragonair
Innovation
Scott Miller he's one of the
Founders of iRobot
I didn't even realize this at first but he was telling me one of the best things about what Amazon is done
Here's opened up
The physical Hardware the R&D day
Kind of created around building
The Echo and made it such a good voice recognition device
Cuz
I don't know if you guys remember but I've tried a lot of voice recognition devices in
Most of them aren't any good
So he's like hey of startups have access to this you can imagine you know somebody building a Roomba
That you can talk to
Heck yeah
I want that
It just doesn't listen
So again I think
I think this could be amazing I have no idea if like
What if you could get home kit India
I doubt it
Because I don't think so
But I'm excited
So that's that's the thought there
Yeah I think there's lots to be excited about and
And again I did not buy the echo because I didn't want to buy something for
Potential I saw the potential in it but back in November as like
Just doesn't do enough for me
And then they have the best DK come out in February and then we had if this then that support added a whole bunch of other things
As we talked about the WeMo support Phillips
Hue light bulb support now
And now they've got this Alexa skills kit which is really the SDK for for Alexa
And
Aside from the smart home aspect even on a mobile perspective
There's potential here in terms of apps I had read the Intuit StubHub
AOL and Citrix are already using the Alexa skills kit
I don't know what for but
This is to embed
Voice recognition I Summa to apps and services
Yes I can tell you what Citrix is
4 days
They bought a company called octo blue back in
December of last year
And they are actually enabling it so it will work with
Aqua blue is a
Code
See how do I describe October
It is cold that connects devices
Two other devices and devices to web service
So it's not it's like an if this then that
But it's actually
Code it's not
It's not a simple for the everyday user to use
But it's amazing it is it is very flexible
So they're using it to
Basically you tell Alexa you can say
Alexa allow octoblu
To check my calendar
In
And then it'll check your calendar for the day
It'll give you all that
So basically it opens up more services Enterprise
Glass services
Actually
Makes sense
But
They're also doing something with wit AI which is a startup that does
Speech recognition
And artificial intelligence around speech like getting
Computers to generate their own speech that
That makes sense
So they're actually
Running stuff that they tell the echo
And then the Echoes response back through with AI
In the idea there is to teach the echo via October
This is America
How to respond to better
How to better respond to Natural length
Cut that's all very far
Far-fetched but it's actually really exciting stuff I'm very excited in
I don't know
People who listen to The Show for a long time are going to remember that actually talk to Chris Matthews who is the founder
Who was the founder of October Lou way back in the day about what he was doing
It's really very flexible and very
Well I am looking forward to seeing this all develop and I said earlier I
Will probably buy the echo now inside
I put in a request
To get it and I had complained on on are the same
Well I blew it cuz now it's $149
The 99
Well once it came out for everybody
That request just got ignored and now it's 179 so I really missed out
The remote I didn't realize this
That's extra
Yeah and I I use the remote but it is a little iffy so if your house is really big
Cuz it's blue should be I don't think I even want the remote I think I'd rather have multiple echos because I don't
When I carry something else around or have something in every room
That makes sense if you get multiple echos because I'm very curious I've actually thought about it
Multiple echos on
Amazon
Does anything I hope so if any of our readers have multiple echoes
Let us know
Curious how it works together affect if it actually does
Yeah cuz like I know they don't have like a party load like Sonos does for all of your speakers to play the same songs at once
That's the only thing I know
So I know nothing Beyond
I think if there is there not working towards multiple echoes in a house I hope they do soon because I think it's going to be required for
Many many people
I agree there is there plenty of times
Dang it I whip
I wish I had an echo in the bathroom
I know that's over
But you know I owe you could instantly or you know order toilet paper when you're out
There is be ordering things like a lot of the stuff that you need to order is in the bath
They have to dash with the Oil of Olay products I'm all on that
Also you know you listen to music in the shower
You can
Add things to your shopping list
Think of a lot of good ideas in the shower I could
I actually used to have a shower crayon that I would write them on the walls with
Add this to my to do list
There's a lot of
I tell you I could see it now Sunday paper in the bathroom shopping at the same time no yeah
Cook
The bathroom
We're going to talk about a toothbrush
Oh goodie
Looks like one of the great segue there so we hadn't connected
Toothbrush company based out of Columbus Ohio
It's called Bean Technologies
Lesbianism Beam not being
And
What they
We may have talked about
Before for 2 years they sold a connected toothbrush that basically says
Is it's a toothbrush with Bluetooth
It's got an app the app is like
Hey you brush for 2
Minutes today good on you
Basically talk to the CEO Alex premiere
That was just a trojan horse to build an insurance company that can offer cheaper rates because they have access to more.
Data about how you brush
And because they
Build a lot of stuff
I'm more modern software infrastructure
You're so boring the cost by hosting stuff
So
That
Is pretty awesome
Yeah so I guess you would get discounted insurance rates
If you had their toothbrush and provided them information and so on so forth
You sign up for the dental insurance in he's basically promising that it's
It it's actually offered
So it's not offered
A company would sign up in the rates to offer the dental insurance
10 to 25% cheaper
And
In addition
They're changing the model a little bit by sending out
Every quarter a tuba toothpaste
Dental floss and a replacement brush head so they provide that for
Gotcha
And the idea is if they're doing that
And they're encouraging youth
Through gamification to brush
And then I see that you're visiting the dentist
They pay for the
Preventive stuff anyway
Should a pretty good sense of
That you're probably being healthy and
We're going to ask you little things throughout you know on the app you can ask
Ask you questions like
Hey
Sensitive teeth
And if they do we can make recommendations that will help improve
Outcomes for them
Can I see the game of vacation here the more you brush the more stars you collect and then you get rewards for different star levels such as
Healthy replacement heads or cashback on the plan
Yeah actually Our Guest
Are cast today later on in the show it was using a beam toothbrush and he said that
Keno brushes for 2 minutes just to get more stars
Four stars
All right
So
Bean is not the only company that's looking at taking kind of
The information from the internet of things and connected devices in
It helping users
Develop better habits will start there
Nest as we talked about last week
Has a program with
American family
Where
They give discounts they have a 5% monthly discount
A free Nest protect thermostat
Nest protect smoke detector
To their customers and
I want to get people to make sure there's smoke detectors are
Working so short
Just encourage them to
Custom once a month
Change the batteries when they're done
Is idea so it's not punitive it's just purely
I add an additive nice site
It's a good thing
So
That is what they're doing and then
A company called automatic
Which is they make an OBD Port so an onboard diagnostics
We got it right this time
Yeah I did
Yes Dondo that plugs into that port on your car to tell
Tell you information like hey driven this many miles are hey this is why your check engine lights on
I hate you speed too much knock it off
Yeah
Hey stop speeding
Go easier on the brakes
They actually got
Strategic round with a raised 24 million last week and they
The investor that led the round was USAA which is an insurance
Company
Based in San Antonio Texas
And USAA is interested also in kind of building
Smarter and better insurance
Policies for
People Based on data from things like that automatic
And I think
Progressive actually has a little plug-in module like that as well that I don't for a while and I'll give you a discount.
You agree to plug that into your car
Let that information be you know sifted up to them I don't know what kind of discount you get butt
So they do that and they also do it
They only do it for six months so they collect the data for six months and then you send them
Stuff back
I miss how it worked
In Progressive is like really they don't want to be in that business
The CEO speak one back in
He was like you know I would love to get that data
Car manufacturers I hate
Being in a device business shipping it back
The 4th to people
Nothing to note though is none of the insurer so far talk about real-time price
This is not something there after
I should also know that the second generation of the automatic
Not the current one
The second generation will have cellular
Apparently really big 4
Oh yeah that way they don't have to worry about
Recipe not to send any device and plug it in and upload data it will just go
Set the current automatic WiFi on
Next gen
Have cellular
I think it's a really kind of cool way of using the internet of things to rethink the way people
Business
Especially being I I think that's
I have no idea that
But I loved
You just want the Stars
So last night I visited a Marriott Hotel here in Austin
I saw the future
Really
Little little sleep pods like at the Google
No knots
Be honest it's a little boring
Because
Hotels actually have to pay for all this stuff and they don't see an Roi just yet on a lot of
What they do see is
Netflix in the rooms on the TVs which I have
Canker sore for a while
Yay
That's an ounce
They will have
Starwood has them already in Mariana's testing Bluetooth door locks that
You know you turn that you put your phone up to the door lock and it automatically opens
End
It's like mobile check-in
Yep
So you basically you can check into the hotel
From your phone
And then you're like you go up to your room
About to check in on her to tell you which room is you go up there
And you flasher
Phone up there in
Inside
Yeah I think it's a Starwood you don't even have to go to the
Desk to Check Into Cash
Yeah I thought it's all done on the phone and
You unlock the room whichever motels between the app and you're done
Starwood's
Was hacked
The Marriott people were very
Very excite
Knowing that
Over it I believe it was
So
That's at the other thing and this is
This is way far down the road maybe 2016 but they're talking about bringing wireless charging into
Well that's
Probably a good
Time for it to happen I don't think it's happened yet because they're just been too many competing standards too many groups
But you've had the
I'll probably get this wrong but I'll say the wireless
Power Consortium and
Welchy's the standard and I think the alliance for wireless power a
4wp
I believe they agreed yeah we can use the
The Apache standard Qi it is chi
That's really what we need because right now
You got multiple standard still so you're not going to embed
Spend money in betting these charters in
Furniture we're not everybody's phone or tablet's going to work so
Getting closer to the standard
And I could see in 2016 people financing okay there's enough of us
Have a standard here that we can spend the money and offer this to our customers
Exactly in
Marriott is looking at the
Cool
Good good good
So that was exciting I thought as
Who stays at hotels often
Talk about how
People consumers will see The Internet of Things First and hotels this kind of makes me wonder about that
Because other than the connected door locks
There's no plans there are no plans for like fancy dimming lights
Automated thermostats
Blinds
Again return on investment isn't going to be there unless
Unless you're the only one doing that and people want that type of experience and eventually everybody will do it and
Therefore
It's just Anna
You'll be a common thing so
I don't I don't foresee that happening
So it's not
Alright so now it's time
Kevin said it
5 minutes
So
We've got whatever returning to I'm returning to the ring
Connected jewelry
OtterBox
I know no I mean I paid about $130 for it but it actually sells for between
I believe it's 195 + 260 depending on the stone
So
I got mine in December and I loved it
It's for those of you guys who don't know what's a ring that's connected to your phone via Bluetooth it's got an LED
And it's got a little
Kidney stone
Install
Or under the stone
Rather in the LEDs and then it's got to happen
Sexy back
I'm so
And there's no screen
It's it's something pretty
I was very excited about it B
I leave my phone in my bag all the time and I need to know what
But before my ringler actually 2 weeks after I got my Wrigley I got a pea
And
Having used both
I've decided that I found myself only using the ringly when
I couldn't get away with wearing the watch and most of my day I wear the watch
I like getting the screen notifications
I will say that the Ringley is nice because it links into things like Slack
Uber
That
You know I don't
I just need to know that someone's painting
Me right or you just need a signal you don't need
Data
Right so
If you wanted to wear both you
But I've actually had
A bit of a challenge
With Renly so my first Ringley after
The three weeks it just stopped working
And
I sent it back and they've been very nice about
An independent right nice to other
It's not like
Hell yeah we get that all the time
I went out for dinner last night on the iot podcast
And I heard your voice
No we're not that
Date they sent me a new one and they said that it was a it was a one-off Luke that my box
Broken
So
They sent me a new one the new one was the wrong size so
I sent that back that was just in Arabic
I was in a system is having two sizes
Not
So I got my third ring
And
That one
Oh man actually
Okay so English
Words for about
A couple weeks
And then it stopped
Same problem as the first
Different problem this went this time it wouldn't hold a charge and that was a common problem
So are a relatively common problem so we set it back I got a new one
Did that one
The Box
Sad
The USB
Micro USB port was
Messed up on the box
So you can actually plug it in to charge it to the ring work
Boxden
In the Box in the ringer actually
Affected
Think together
Be a serial numbers so they
I couldn't just
Sentence using a USB cable
What can use a new USB cable but the box is actually the charger
That is actually a
Battery
Inside I got you
You have to put the ring in the Box.
And you can't use a different box because of the serial number tie
Because they link
What's the boxes
So originally I was like swapping out the ring that I had that
Wasn't
Broken
At one point in time I literally had three boxes
And I was just like
I can't make them work
So I said that back and now
I am on
That's at least four
Number for
And
So far it's doing okay
So we're going to check back again and
Another month because it looks like
They had some quality
Controller yield issues
Epic
Which is not uncommon
This is something I bought off of
Kickstarter
But
A concern that
Quality control problems
Our problem
Very good about sending things back but I also feel like I may have passed it by with like the Apple watch
Coming out there's a lot of other things I could do the same thing and more
So and for Less
But I mean you can get a pebble for 99 bucks
Half the price
Right so that's that's the question is there still
A market of women
It's mostly women
Be interested in a cocktail ring
This is connected cuz it is beautiful I get compliments on it from people who have no idea that it's
Which is good I mean that's a win in my book if it doesn't work it doesn't really matter
So there it there's there's the update on the Ringling
And
With that I guess we should
Call it a day and go straight to Our Guest
Sounds good
All right so stay tuned everyone because our guess is Darren samuelsohn
He is a senior policy reporter at Politico and he's got talk to us about what Washington thinks about the Internet of Things
Hey everybody this is Stacey Higginbotham and we are back with the Internet of Things podcast
And today I have are man and wife
Darren samuelsohn
He's a senior policy reporter at
Politico
Hey Darren
Hey sexy
So I gave him a little upgrade he's actually not our man
Washington he's just a guy in Washington who happened to write
Most of a really big package from Politico
On how
Washington DC weather
Explaining the internet of things to watch
DC highly recommend it to all of you guys if your
Sitting there going
What are legislators reading about
What's the Internet of Things
So good job Darren
Let's get started by
So let's get started with a sense of
What did you know about the internet of things when you started the reporting for this
Be stories that you were
You know I really didn't know that much at all about the internet of things I got a lot of topics in Washington has covered the Pentagon has covered
Energy
Policy and climate change and I had a lighthouse beat for about a year
Subpoenaed to things was kind of new to me I've actually spent I should say a year
Covering a political campaign technology last year during the
I got to see how
Sophisticated the Democrats and Republicans are in using technology to win
Election or to connect with voters
But this was totally different yet I learned a lot
In that previous beat that really maybe help me sort of just to start to understand how much policymakers and lawmakers and
And the administration you know I was going to be used
Technology themselves
To get it off
This is kind of an example of how much they are using technology while in office I guess that's what made it at 7
Awesome
Now that you've reported out the story
What do you think about the Internet of Things
What's today
It's pretty amazing I certainly started quickly seeing things all around me
That
Were part of my life or you know I was being choked
Watching on television commercials just my wife and I were sitting on the couch during the Stanley Cup hockey game
We're just kind of floored by how many of the commercials related to the internet of things I can find the best example
Was I think it's an Audi commercial where the guy is driving me
Kind of a classic
It just kind of floored me how many things are around us
Are being advertised
Directed at us
It was weird me
One of the projects I had was to get his wired up his
Cuz I couldn't
On the Metro
And there was an advertisement for the nest thermostat right there like waiting for me when I got off the train one day at
I'm a little bit weird like they knew that I was
Starting to connect my life up to the intern
I would say before long
Started to become aware of this issue and then
Started reading reading reading as many
Pieces of literature that could have been discussed whether Congressional hearing transcripts
FTC report to the Homeland
Security reports have been done on the topic
And you before too long starting to become a little bit of a dangerous expert on it
I love those
Consider myself a dangerous EX
So we'll get to you and your your personal transformation and dude I believe it was super Robo reporter in a moment
But let's
Let's focus on DC because
The tecknity often does
They're just kind of our own things
Washington's going to have their light-touch regulation there too slow
They're going to look at this forever
Hopefully we can keep them off our backs that is very much the sense I get for
Can the people I talk
So in reading your story
I was kind of strapped it what you found so I'd love for you to talk to me
About
You going around and interviewing people at the Capitol in kind of
What your take is on how
Legislator
View the internet
She was really interesting I just
Has been up in the capital for 15 years covering a whole range of issues
This was one that
I was floored by just how many people I had to do some explaining
Once I should have presented the question to them
Typically with a member of Congress you know you just say a couple of keywords
And they latch Andre quickly and they have sound bites in their own head where they thinking
You know they can take it
With this one you know I would usually start off with
Excuse me Senator or Congressman I'd like to ask a couple questions
About the Internet of Things
And except for maybe five or six members I got in a blank stares
People who
You would think would be pretty technologically savvy there's a quote from Congressman Sean Duffy
Wisconsin Republican used to be on the real world
Couple years ago a reality TV star who
Is in Congress anyway I asked him a question and he looked at me and said what the hell is that
I don't explain him usually what I would do without a quickly will explain another you know drones and
Autonomous semi Thomas cars in probably two examples that you're probably familiar with
And then a lot of members are going to say okay okay okay
What you're talking about
There's only been one hearing Energy company that was
Corning Court internet of things related to
And then there was only one Hearing in the Senate
Commerce Committee earlier this year so
For 2015
No hearings with you know the internet of things as the main driver
And then you have this internet-of-things caucus
Before we get to the caca
The hearings have only
There's been no hearings in
Congress because there have been hearings
In front of the f
TCM
I think so cuz I just want to clarify that far listener
May not make the
Congress in the regular
So absolutely yeah sure
Back to the Internet of Things caucus
Just because
Is it
So he's a he's partnering up with Suzanne.
A Washington Democrat who used to work for Microsoft who's been in Congress I think about 3 terms now
Bipartisan caucus immuno keep this in mind with
Respect
Powerless
Organizations are basically away
Four members of Congress to me to get together and
And host a panel discussion or
Trying to gauge but
There's all kinds of caucuses in Congress has ones on Whiskey Drinking
Little League baseball
So keep that in mind.
Gina one
Easy thing that members of Congress can do but it doesn't really
They don't write legislation if you're in some sort of like a club
High School
Kind of like a social thing again very few members are aware of it
Those are a couple their licenses and Bill Bean
In the house and then over in the Senate
You have
Small
Group of
Kind of I would say backbench senators
With respect to
Deb Fischer from Nebraska
I was thinking about this issue because of Agriculture and all the trucks that are
Flowing through the state of Nebraska
You have the
Brian Schatz from Hawaii
A Democrat who's taking his leadership on this issue
I meant Cory Booker he's pretty well-known New Jersey Democrat Saturday
And he's been
Front and center the former mayor of
In New Jersey has been in the Sun
Couple years now
Again
There's no pushing
More education than legislation
Okay and it sounds like it
It's sorely needed I think
In your story you had
Representative Isis saying that there are 435 members of the House
100 members of the Senate and most of them don't know what the internet is
So
It's kind of Grimm news
It is not the Congressional level
So let's let's talk about
The regulatory
Kind of side of the house because
Side of things
Don't confuse the issue
The FTC
Is actually already issued a report and some of their conclusions
From the report talk about
Increase data privacy
Making sure that companies don't keep data Beyond a certain
Threshold
The report also asked
Spore
Keto companies to be a little bit more transparent about the data they're collecting and how it gets shared
They've also
Tencent
Censorship bar
Find companies for
Violations of consumer privacy
Related to connected device
There's also the FDA which is actually doing some research into connected medical devices I have read some stuff from
Then you mentioned the Department of Homeland Security which I thought of where I was so I
I'd love to get a sense because
I don't know if it was one of your stories but someone
Brought up in this
Package of stories
The Internet of Things
Covers
A wide swath of Industries
And Congress
Regulatory system doesn't look at things holistically it looks at things in a very siloed fashion
And I thought that was a really good point
For like when were thinking
Yeah that was something that
Domino's in my main story that I wrote
And it was something you asked earlier you know what did I learn and actually that was something
A baby and it's been about 6 or 7 weeks
Digging in on the topic
Midway through
Did it occur to me that that is
The case I'll tell you where I came to that conclusion from up denim covering Washington for a long time
I cover federal agencies of cover the energy Department in the EPA very closely in the Pentagon very closely
And everyone does things very vertically Within
Their ages
Think about what
What laws
Allow them to do what they're authorized to do Under
Under existing statutes and they don't tend to think too often about
What a neighboring agency might do
And it's the exact same thing in Congress
Can you create a you have the Judiciary Committee and it tends to think within its own balance of what
It wants to do and it will fight like hell
With another eight committee
Over jurisdiction
This happens over and over and over again
Can you just fascinating you have this battle going on in Washington
Hanover who is
I get the Internet of Things
Just kind of wiped out all of those walls
And is designed to sort of have
One thing talking to another thing talking
Do another thing that typically
In Washington we erect barriers
Rancho that openly ultimately leads you to the White House
And you know the lighthouse is supposed to be the place where all federal agencies
Trying to take their commands and their lead and and you know the buck stops with the president United States who's in charge of the entire Federal.
Dancer that was a question
I was closing to the White House was okay
What are you doing
Be kind of came back with a similar answer to what you hear from industry
We want to light touch we don't
Really want to get involved we kind of want to
Stand back and let
The rest of the
At the same time they are being warned by their own Homeland Security Department you got a small window of opportunity here.
Talking if you don't
You know there's going to be some serious serious consequences
Security and sell
The White House is well aware of what's going on
If the White House has been telling people which way to row the boat
The Russian news agency that Justin start rolling in 30 different directions
And that's trouble
With that idea because the idea that we need a holistic view for regulating The Internet of Things
Or legislating it
And if the white house isn't taking
Charge of this
As you said
Where we going to
Get weird who should be regulating this should it be
Should we
Elect a president who actually knows with the Internet of Things is in 2016 should we turn to regulators and
I hope that they get it right
Should be
Start buying Congressman I don't know like
Where is our best hope of Regulation that may
It's a
Great question mean there's there's there's this tension here between the two and you know when I set out to teleport the story I was
Trying to figure out
How much do Congress and how much should be Administration no and then
How much were they ready to do and obviously what
What is industry telling them
They like.
Don't be wrong Amino President Obama is
Is no dummy on technologies that he's been wearing once a couple of months now
She certainly aware of it and he has made a couple of
Allusions to sort of what the Fitbit is capable of
Energy Systems
And he hasn't used the words Internet of Things
Please talk to me about today
Prospects of what technology
Conducive
He knows what it is
Some of these people actually told me that he just doesn't like to use sometimes
The nerdy terms
You know that that you and I are very familiar with it cuz he wants to kind of speak to the laminin
Internet of things is something that
Nick Milana is still struggling with her quite candid
President Obama
Use the
Use those words per say
Going forward I mean I think this is going to continue moving forward
The way it kind of is right now I don't get a sense that there's any
Effort underway to create an Internet of Things
Apartment or Internet of Things
Pacific law
Probably
Payback
On this like the industry is urging him to do
At the same time as I mentioned before having a lot of you ladies are
Competing for
And starting to get engaged on this issue summer doing it more proactively like the SDA
The transportation department
The FAA with respected drones in a lot of these are can actually be issuing rules that are going to affect
Decisions made by businesses
Usher
It sounds like that it's more of the same will get piecemeal efforts
That
Embody that light-touch regulation
For the internet
And I think that's to be expected I think in one of those things
Editor's would ask me to do and I really enjoyed this part of the story
Honestly one of the very first questions
I was asking if myself when I started out with
What about other big technological innovations how long does it take Washington to respond
And the airplane and Telegraph
And the railroad will it be before that I went and I started asking historians will you know how long did it take
It was that case I mean the railroad is interesting example
70s men
It takes another
20 years before you get the Interstate Commerce Commission starts to regulate
On that front door automobiles the great again Henry Ford pumps out the Model T at the start of the 20th century
But doesn't actually for seatbelts in the cars until the 1960s 1970s
Yeah so it sounds like we're going to eat we might
I might be in for a rocky few decades with the Privacy then it sounds like I know is a consumer that's a big
Issue
People in the internet of things and I think
Is there anything to the idea that technology moves
So much faster today I mean you look at regulations for the internet I mean
Not that the railroad in the car we're not huge significant
And things
And intent of milestones in
Both are economic and you know social
Development
But
The internet for example is already disrupting things is 25 years old
We are still trying to adapt our laws to deal with
Kind of the holistic
World of
Everything being connected right
And so when you look at the internet of things which is
It's been 25 years but we're basically saying hey you know what let's take the internet and like
Put it into light
* 1000
Yeah yeah absolutely there hasn't been much regulation on the internet and I think that's maybe why
It is
Do transform society as much as it has and hasn't really blocked
That many Innovations over the last
Two and a half decades and seems to be
At this point the lesson that
Graphic policymakers in Washington
Have learned
Is
Hang back and
And don't get too engaged in and let the market
Sort itself out when you have a company going and then having a big privacy here
Security breach
And that's something I heard over and over that company will probably be headed for the exits
Has people turning their competitors
To buy up whatever
An alternative they can so
I mean I think there's going to be regulation
You know what is a pointed out of the Peace
If something big happens if there's some Calamity of some kind that we can't quite Envision in the moment
You know I should have asked people give me your doomsday scenarios while I was reporting it
Pick up all sorts of crazy things
People envision
Happening because of the Internet of Things
And maybe a crisis would wake Washington uphill of course Racine
In a big crisis has on a whole host of other issues with IP infrastructure and
You're not replacing the bridge after
She's not doing big things after we have a major Bridge collapses
In Minnesota
Or
You know the fiscal crisis that we faced and all those deadlines
Drive Congress to act either
So you know Washington is pretty broken it's been broken for the last couple of years
Legislative front for President Obama he's in he's obviously done a lot of things
Reviews on executive powers because Congress
Subdivided
So I think it's as long as Washington's broken as well just another factor to keep an eye on
We're not going to see much on the
Passage of new laws
And that leadeth into the agency
So then I will tell people carry on and watch out for the Aged
Add
In terms of you personally
How do you view this because you did
You bought the sea it looks like a Fitbit at Dropcam
What else did what else did you buy to connect yourself to The Internet of Things
And what did you think about your
Really fun I mean
It was an idea that we kind of came up with how many things can I get my hands on in like a week
I ended up with a Fitbit to Fitbit
Bought a nest thermostat about the smoke detector and the Dropcam
I Got a Car connect which was allowing let me sort of Texas temperature of my car as I was driving around
I'll see what else do they have electric toothbrush the beam
Toothbrush was told me that I was the smiley faces when I rushed for more than 2 minutes
So yeah I was doing all of these things at Mercedes Benz dropped off a car for the weekend I was able to drive a semi autonomous car for
Sweet machine
I will say this is fastening so the Mercedes sent the car over
The guy who delivered it we were you showing me everything
You know the dashboard
I was asking about the
The parallel parking assist any kind of looked at me since man I don't use that I like to parallel park
And I just thought it was
So true because I tried to do it a couple of times and ultimately I just I prefer to parallel park myself and maybe that's the generational thing
So which of these devices that you tried
Did you find any that
You couldn't live without
I will say that I really enjoy the nest that one we didn't get rid of forked over the cash for that myself and
I've started noticing that I can I probably could go back to what I already have
I've already had the wires for pretty complicated to pull it out
Pull the old thermostat out of the new one in
Dropcam was kind of fun we've been using a time really to watch a cat's back in the day
You know I could probably live without nutmeg. They're doing cuz I'm pretty much sleeping
Are the toothbrush obviously it's kind of
Something now that it has replaced my old toothbrush
In my bathroom and
Your other than that I'm happy with the old 2008 Subaru that I drive which is totally unconnected except for
I do not hook up my iPhone iTunes to it but that's pretty much it
On the car
So you know I think I'm uncomfortable living in in
2012 here in 2015 but
I feel like I'll so it's just a matter of time before when I start buying the Next Generation and everything
It's probably going to be in minesing Schenectady
Voltaren thank you so much for talking to me about this stuff I appreciate your
Your look at your look at Washington DC and a sense of
What
What the capital is doing about the internet of things which
Sounds like it's not much and it'll be pretty reactive
That's how Congress off handles
Adidas react
Awesome alright well thank you so much for coming that's it for today thank you
You so much for listening