Hey everyone it is the Internet of Things show and I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
This your co-host
Kevin tofel
It is
CES time
And while I and pounding the show floor here in Vegas
Are but Kevin is
At home for the first time in ten years during CES week
He has earned his break but he did confess
To be that he misses the
Hustle the bustle the fun of hanging out
Baidu
Why do we always have such a good time at CES last year we hung out and it was a fun time on the plus side you probably have better weather cuz it's like
11 freaking degrees where I am in Pennsylvania right now
So
I'm good I'm good
I've technically because of the weird time constraints of podcast recording and editing process
You know we're going to do a little time travel to play a little
I have only seen
Like day one
Actually date
Day one and a half
But
I see the light I feel
I feel good
About what I said
So we're going to start off the show
With everybody's favorite platform the only true Internet of Things
Myvue which is
The Amazon Echo
She who shall not be named
Is playing a starring role
Addition show
Everyone
Is integrating
With chicken
So
The echo
Kevin what-have-you
Well I seen a bunch a lot of people are
Cortical planning to do Integrations it's going to take them some time but one of the biggest that I'm intrigued about
Is actually Ford
Ford is working on Amazon Echo integration
Which you like well why would they do that with their sync platform in the car what does that have to do with
That cylinder that sitting in my
In my house
It's kind of interesting it's a two-way
Connection and here's how it kind of works
You will be able to control your
Home Smart Home devices that you would normally with your Echo from your car so let's say your
5 miles from home and you're like oh you know what
It's getting dark out I don't want to come into a dark home I'm just going to tell my echo through the car
Turn on my lights
Obviously have had at 7 to dance but
It's kind of one of the core things that people do with Amazon Echo right now
So that's kind of cool you can modify your temperature and so on directly from the car through voice navigation
The only way around 2 if you're sitting around at home
And you like I wonder if I need gas in my Ford vehicle you can ask the echo
What's the range on my car right now and it will tell you how many miles you have to go before you run out of gas
If you got remote car starting in your car as well you can remotely start the car with your Echo it's a
Cool two-way sync to me it's not one that was obvious immediately to me
That sounds really cool so I actually tested something like this
Okay I'm just going to say it for my Tesla
It was a software program
It was a software program called
And it is Kali for Tesla
And it works through the website on the car
And it was an integration with the wink
Hub
And
Yeah okay there was
I thought it was actually pretty cool
Except
Because of the way the
Tesla update
It took forever to do anything with me
My smartphone
So
I'm actually kind of jealous
Because now I kind of want to have Tesla
Immigration
Quit Amazon
Do you hear that Eli please
Or I want these guys to make
Well if it's a Tesla issue
I want this to be a lot faster because I actually found it super convenient when it worked on time because I would live
Literally just drive away
In my garage door
From the Chamberlain
We just closed
Because it was like Hey Stacy's cars driving off
I mean I know it's this is voice activated but I would totally talked
So
I love it and I love it that it's
That's awesome
Okay so you guys
If you have an echo
Totally
And
With a sinking car
Yep and I should mention that they have not provide a timeline for this Ford has not and only because you mentioned wink they said there are
Also working on a similar integration with wink
So even if you don't have an echo but you have a wink
You're going to be able to do some cool things
Oh my God if you have the wink
When they integrate this
Go out
Get the garage
Because not using
Using your voice
To control your garage door
Or just using
Cartoon
Control your garage door without like having to press buttons
I'll be honest
Okay
So that's
Play Store
Again
Superstar
Total Superstar at CVS
There an alarm.com both announced
Alexa
DocuSign
Okay
Announce
Integrations
With she who shall not be named
Alarm.com
Did it through a skill
And so did
Didn't
It's worth pointing out you guys
We haven't talked about
Like skills
Skills yet for the show and we should
Because
Right now Amazon through it
You know straight up connected home
Paris in the settings where you go to discover new devices only really supports
Lights for the smart
So you can say things like
Switch on this turn on that
So what a lot of companies are doing to give you more kind of freedom to do cool things like
So it's so tell my house to go to sleep
They're using skills
It what you do to enable the skill is just going settings and
You go to skills in you
Enable
Like all kinds of stuff
And they have all kinds like when I told you guys about playing bingo that's a skill they have like a 7-minute workout you can able
Which I've done and it's
Kind of chill because she is not a great coach she's just like
Do jumping jacks
Jay
It's okay
So you can enable like the alarm.com you have a
A sentence that you say to enable it
And then boom. Action
And so through these things
People are actually enabling all these really in-depth
Kind of smart home
Challenges you have to have the code words remember exactly the thing to say
Which can be hard
Especially if you're going to bed
Or your garage in your waking up in the
But the benefit is
Like with Vivint you can actually
Close your locks
You can turn off your thermostat
You can
All kinds of fun stuff
With the alarm.com you can
Pretty much only control your I think it's your lights and
A couple other things cuz they were actually concerned about the security part
About the you control your locks
With your boys
I also heard
This is the gossip at CES
Amazon later this year is going to be coming out with some
Deeper cooler Smart Home
Kind of platform stuff
At the actual
Platform
Also not just letting you control your lights
What those will be
Percent sure yet
So if I'm understanding what skills are
Date
Can you cut your native features that Amazon is baking into the echo
That can work with other cloud services and such
But the skills seem to be third-party if Amazon is not doing it natively you can still add things and
Perfect one is AccuWeather has is a skill you know if you enable you can say
Echo
Singer named Echo ask AccuWeather what time the Sun will rise and
Because of a table parse out there that phrase and
Use the AccuWeather skilled AccuWeather is created
And return the information so
You know it's interesting
That we're seeing so many Integrations here and I think it's
It speaks to what we were talking about before with us
It's just a wide open platform
That's the beauty of the echo
It is
You have the option of remembering your complicated phraseology
And in some of it
It's not really
Pacific specific
And the cool thing is
You have the option of enabling the
So
If you don't want me there is a farting
Scale so if you don't want the fighting skill
You will
Forever free
The word fart around she Who Shall Not Be Named without
Ever having
The dangerous
. wonderful farting sounds
I can't believe that's the top skill in my list right now
We did it
For a little bit
Didn't
It's actually not very good I've got to be honest we were not impressed with the first results
So you know
Just so you guys
I think they're advertising its it's
It starts with a number
Okay
So other things are getting Amazon Echo
Commands that we saw
I saw a radio this is actually it's called
Chubby
It's my company called in
Noxious
It is a
Kitchen radio
And you could actually be one of the first devices using
The A's
Voice
Services
So it's built in
To the device
That you can talk to it and it uses
The Voice Services platform
Music you can ask it to do anything
Anna talks to the Cloud Inn
That boys
So
It's very cool
It's designed to sit
On your kitchen
Bridge Inn
Just be like
The school radio
And I'm trying to remember when it goes on sale
Because that would be useful for you
It's triby by invoxia
This is what happens when you
Gradually are going senile
It's a connected speaker for the kitchen
Is $199 and it has little Message Board to
That you can write on
It comes in blue
Red and green
I wonder how many products this year will actually integrate the
Echo voice services
Because it's
Kind of like having Echoes all over the place it's at some point you noticed any gives you that whole consistent user experience
I can't wait for it to be in my back
Iwata vacuum cleaner that I can
Like vacuum
Really that's all I
I'm a simple woman
Okay so other the final integration that we talked about is
Wonderworld little unclear on what is intriguing
It is
Lumos still around this is
2009 it had it was one of Ashton Kutcher's First Tech Investments
I know it's a winner
I just
Menarche
So what is up
Avoid
Don't copy came out is like
Back in the early days of weight
Hey
Let's give it a hand for still being around
It's a phone and a little
It's basically a hub
And
You can program
People's phone numbers in and you can tell it
And now you can use the Echo and say hey,
It's another skill
Hey so-and-so
Ask
Better call Bob
And
Lo and behold
What year does it happen is the question
Yes we don't know if
What I know is
Echo cannot
Or could not
Camp right unless it is change it could not act
A speaker
Like a Bluetooth speaker for hands-free phone calling speaker right
It could act as a Bluetooth speaker for your music but it could not
Act is a hands-free speaker for you
I don't know if that's changed my has done something weird
Using
The scales
Or if it's just
Like basically then takes your phone in like
Calls your mom
Yeah that's at the thing if it just does that if it just
You know it saves you from dialing and I'm like okay but
If it actually Taps into the microphone and the speaker of
The Amazon Echo hardware and let you complete the call hands-free right
Speaking to
The device
Venom I'm interested
Yeah cuz that changes the function of the device
Yeah exactly
Puma
Adecco
And wants to enable the skill and let us know
Interstellar
You're going to email it
Info
Call Me Maybe
Okay so that was our first segment
On really cool things that have happened with the Amazon Echo at sea
So far
Now let's talk about
Because
I love it
I know I've been shipped nerd and we have got a lot of radio news
Started with
Halo Halo
Hello Halo CE I ain't like the news here from the Wi-Fi Alliance about this new 802. 11n a h or
As I like to call it
Halo is the friendly name for attitude at 11 a.m.
You're not too keen on this and I want to hear why but let me just explain what it is
The Wi-Fi Alliance
Says that by 2018 will be certifying products that use the standard
It's mainly meant for Internet of Things devices because it uses
Low power
And will not transmit data very fast but
That's okay with
Are the small bits of data that devices in the house actually word
In the reprise actually yeah
Transmit
Can you use the 900 megahertz unlicensed Spectrum band
And that gives it better range than current Wi-Fi Solutions
I think it sounds like a win
But before the show you're like I'm not sold on that and you didn't tell me why so why
All right
Mostly because I have more question
So
Wi-Fi alliances
Talked about the 900
What you guys need to know about that is it is
Really awesome Spectra
It is currently used for a lot of things because it is so awesome so it
Microwaves
Baby Mana
Garage door open
It's a really crowded
So
Really crowded Spectrum lot of opportunity for interference
It also is great because it goes through
Walls
Which means you can stick stuff in your basement you're going to get an awesome signal
That's why they're really pumped about it
But in other countries
Like in parts of Asia and Europe actually
It's also part is like the is M BAND that is used for cellular
Guess so
Third kind of like wool
Is this unified for the rest of the world or is this us only so there's some questions about how that Spectrum
Going to be used for like
All of it
Where is currently the Wi-Fi
Bands that we have now
Arbroath wide
Everywhere
The Wi-Fi Alliance doesn't have
Great answer
So that's question number one we're like
And because it's unlicensed spectrum they really can't control it so that's that's an issue
It is
How big of an issue
We will see
Last year when I was talking to the chipmaker's about
They were really skeptical about the
Power draw and I asked the Wi-Fi a lion sound like
Hey
They're kind of positioning this to be kind of like
Competitor to Bluetooth
Not necessarily Bluetooth low energy but they were talking about using it wearables
And
That's a really big deal because
Syfy sucks
Power
I mean it's a great don't give me wrong
But you know there's always tradeoffs when you're
Engineering something
Because the alliance didn't
Give me
The power draw they just didn't have it
They're like nope
I really curious if in the years since I've last talked to these guys and that's that's what I'm about to find out
I'm talking to guys today
Is
Have they fix that problem
I mean a year is a long time when your engineer
Lyrics oh
Maybe they have
When I last talked to people about age they were like
Stacy
Is
Better
But it is
Not
Bluetooth
Bro
Better
You know
Better is good
It's not something you could put in the world
Or a sensor that you know you really want to be battery powered
That's another question
So those are my big questions about
I'm not saying that that's going to kill this at all
Has changed
It feels
Barry marketing at this point
What's the Wi-Fi Alliance has a marketing organization and they have to go into the Internet of Things
If they're doing this and positioning this is like a technology that you
You can stick on things that are like
Your washing machine that's down in your basement
The Great
This is great I mean on washing machines plugged in
You definitely do want
You're connected washing machine in your basement
Table talk
Or reasons we'll talk about later in the shower
But
If you're really going to try to
Compete with Bluetooth or
Superior thread
No
So the devil's in the details
Always
And I don't even care about like
The date eraser talking about
Are up to 80 megabits
Which I think is great
And at the small end is like 100 56 kilobits per second
I think it is
So that's a big range so I'm also kind of like
Yeah well that's like I think it's up to four channels depends on how much data per channel in someone's butt
It does its 1 megahertz to 4 megahertz I believe
Alright so
There we have it
Wi-Fi Halo
Very exciting
In case you're like
Hello
Excited
We also will be seeing Halo in devices in 2016 we probably won't see an official certification until 2
That's how the Wi-Fi Alliance works
You know that's not a surprise to anybody
I know and it won't be surprising to see some
Halo ready products in 2017 I wouldn't be surprised at all
There we have it
Next up
Zigbee and thread
Get married
I bet this is Vegas they could totally do it
What happened is back in April
Sydney is another Mesh networking protocol
There in light bulbs out there
RCP certified
And a lot of your sensors are it's a low-power Mesh networking
Standard just so you guys know what it is
Add back in April
We're going to work with the
Upcoming
Red
Wireless
Standard to kind of see if they could get together because
Underneath
At the radio level zigbee and threader actually using the same IEEE radio protocol
It's 800
15.
That's for you IEEE nerds out there who are like but for everybody else
Just think they have the same
Basic radio
Different different entirely
Okay
So they've got the same radio but they've got different software
On top of it gif
Protocols
What they said they would do though is
They would try to like see how they can make it easier for down the line
Things to work together
Because everybody was kind of like
Crap another radio protocol this is terrible we've already got zigbee Z-Wave Bluetooth
Wi-Fi
Our homes are a mess
So
What they announced at CES
Is
That
The upcoming
Zigbee
Three.
Oh
Standard
And
Thread with basically have the same
Okay this is complicated
They would not be interoperable
But
The device manufacturers
Through a hub the devices with share the same
Play notes
Communication in
Profile
Show
If you were building a device that worked on thread and you were building a device that worked on zippy
It wouldn't actually be able to talk
Directly to each other
But
If you had a hub
A light bulb that said it was a lightbulb in CB and a lightbulb it said it was a lightbulb
Thread would say they were light bulb
The same way so they could actually talk
Exactly are
Itachi how to draw
They'll start a certification program later this year I believe to
Thread + zigbee I believe it is
Yes that was really complicate
The two are pretty similar at at at at an underlying level to begin with so this makes them
A little more compatible even though they're not
The same things that make sense
But you're still as a consumer
And that's really what we care about
You're still going to have to look for them
To be compatible
All together
But if you buy a zigbee
Rio products
You will no longer have to worry about oh my God is it take me lightly certified
Or is it
You could just be like
I'll look this is Zippy 300 compatible
Yeah and this is it be 300 compatible
We're together
So going forward you should look just look for his MP3
Now
It's supposed to be backwards compatible
Gpha
Zigbee light Link
Sleepy all those things
But we all know how that's kind of a risky game to play
It is supposed to be
Nina
SEPTA's kind of good news bad news
Okay so
How is that
Better
Okay
Okay good
Next radio news
And they were through it
Bluetooth decks
I was really kind of excited about this
Cuz I tried
It's easy to install there's a lot of cool Bluetooth stuff coming out in the lighting section A lot of light switches and light bulb
Set up Bluetooth compatible so you don't have to do any wiring
You just like screwing a bluetooth light bulb and then you like literally
Stick a switchblade to your
Controls it right
It's awesome
The downside is because the Bluetooth matches not like
Super Gray
Phone sometimes
To be flaky
Discovery podcast
Introduced a Bluetooth Hub that controls 22 Bluetooth devices
I thought that was kind of a hundred feet
Which
I like
What they're saying Bluetooth range of up to a thousand feet in the open air or through as many as
3 walls
Cuz I and that's good I I know that sometimes I'm walking to my house I'm streaming music or doing something
I walked into two rooms away and that's it I'm gone
You know and then disconnected how to reconnect and so on so
This would solve that problem but
But other problems as well because they have
Other Bluetooth accessories
Bike smart home accessories
They do and this Hub is only
$100 and it supports Bluetooth low energy and classic Bluetooth
So I kind of look like if you're going to invest in a lot of Bluetooth accessories
This is like kind of $100 range
Yeah it supported more devices because I kind of feel like
You're going to
It especially if you're going to install a bunch of light switches
But
I still kind of think
It is an in 22 sounds like a lot in order for Bluetooth it is
But then again you know look at all the lights that we have in our houses these days you want to hide and
Switches and so on so I don't know if I would build hold
System out of this
You know you'll go through that 22 real fast
Yeah the facet my Hue Hub only supports 50 devices is actually kind of an issue
But the fact that he bolts kostek
I thought this was cool
That concludes our radios
And moving right along to
Services
Services integration
Honestly
If I'm calling a story for CES this year it is that the Internet of Things
Is moved from things
Two Services which is about
Time
That's what makes everything talk to each other
It's we're still not really there yet but
Let's hit
You want to talk about
Yeah, and they're not the only one but Whirlpool is highlighting some of their new smart appliances with guess what
Integrated Amazon Dash buttons
I'm almost surprised to see his eye when the Dash came out with the little $5 dongle
You press a button and orders whatever
Laundry detergent or whatever that button is for through Amazon
I was like yeah I know and it's cuz I'm kind of silly to me
Integrate into products it just kind of makes sense I'm starting to wonder will
How many products will actually have these kind of
Reorder buttons
This is the Amazon doordash fulfillment service
So it's not even
But miss
Kind of silica
It's really just an integrated like order from Amazon
Which is awesome
So
I love it
Recite
Of course a bunch of companies integrating with Nest my favorite is Chamberlain
Doing some Nest Integrations
With the nest Dropcam stuff and lot of stuff there
I also thought Lowe's doing a monitored security
Service through is Iris home hub was worth mentioning because
Again services
And they're still planning to do another service through
Helping to plug mic hook you up with plumbers and that sort of thing
I also believe Samsung
SmartThings is also going to continue a line that plan
Service announcement
Ginni rometty is giving
Jeremy the CEO of IBM
Is giving a keynote
@ces Witcher like with Enterprise
Crazy
Watson
IBM's cognitive
Picture of a dozen just play Jeopardy
Doesn't trust
Crazy and
Lake
Hooking up with all these consumer-tech players
Such as Medtronic
To help anticipate diabetes
Track
And predict
Wearable medical sensors there is a partnership with whirlpool
To help like anticipate needs in the Smart Home
Partnership with SoftBank
Robotics which is the creator of pepper
And a partnership with Under Armour so Kevin you want to talk a little bit more about the Under Armour and maybe pepper will Pepper
Real quick for those don't know what it's a little robot from aldeberan that's been around for a while they also make the now and I don't
I'm saying that represent a o
Like a $20,000 Little Robot that's really cool walks around and so on
So
IBM is going to tie into pepper what they're going to do is provide a little more smarts to the robot
Which I don't see that you can buy just yet I'm not sure if you can or not AIDS
Based in Japan through SoftBank so it may be a
Japanese thing only but I want a pepper also IBM is working with Under Armour and that sounds kind of strange like me
What does the people make like
All the clothes at the athletes wear that I can go buy at the store
And I have these products Under Armour Justin LCS they launched their UA healthbox
I have a health box and it is a $400
Kit that has a brand new
Under Armour scale with
Wi-Fi built in
Measures your body fat as well as your weight
Morgan update people need to step on it it knows who you are based on your weight and body fat
It sent that they dumped into the cloud
I thought it worked
No no no it's not that big it's a regular very well-designed glass scaler nice
There's also in the box and Under Armour band which I've been wearing for a couple weeks
Measures your
Steps sleep
You are activity or Fitness
And has a heart rate monitor Optical heart rate monitor not talk about that'll it more
They also include a
UA
Chest strap heart rate chest strap for those who would rather wear a chest strap
That's all in the Box
Not in the Box optional $450 I also have these
Are the Under Armour Gemini 2 speedform sneakers
With it looks like regular running
Shoes but inside is a battery and sensors
You wouldn't know it which I love it because it's invisible you don't turn them on or them
Just work
They measure your steps your stride your Cadence soup
Pace and so on
It all feeds into the Under Armour record app for iOS or Android
Addicts well-designed shows the four quadrants of activity Fitness Nutrition and sleep
I'm getting tons of data
But back to IBM
I'm getting insights from Watson
Which is using all of the big data that IBM has on health
And it's telling me how my maybe my fitness compared to people in my age group
Men in my age group for example actually goes at specific
Talks about health bits it just provides insight
It's not doing too much just yet but then again they just launched this but
I did notice the past couple days before the announcement
I was getting Watson insights in my Under Armour record app
Based on my data
And how compared to the big data that Watson has
Awesome
On Thursday
Morning when this goes
Let you know
Ask Watson for the Powerball numbers the Powerball numbers tell me Owasso
It will be at Watson plan breakfast which means it will be
You know as you guys know what's and not only anticipates Kevin's every need
ASCII exercise
Watson also plans delicious recipes
It's recipes before so
All right so that is kind of the services thing there is
The stuff also happening at the connect
Car front will probably talk about that next show
The partnership with whirlpool
Watson will actually be gathering data
From whirlpools new
Connected washers fridges
Other things which is why your wife I should be better in your basement in case you
You keep your Whirlpool washer and dryer
So
It's a little scary actually
I'm not going to lie to you
Vital thing
If we don't actually have a guest for the show so don't worry
You're going to spend the whole time
Is cameras
Because there were a lot of really good cameras and you know how
Actually we know how you live cam
Because
I'm not too sold on them except when they're outside
In this case in my fridge
This is me
So
Starters
It was actually here last year at CVS and they had a smarter coffee pot and hot water kettle that we talked about
Dissing your cake
Fisher they were showing off a connected fridge cam
It was $199
And I don't know if you guys recall this but I'm super psyched about the idea of a connected fridgecam because
Catalog in what's in your fridge
Boracay news
Grocery shopping purposes
That might happen but it's going to take awhile
And I need to know if I have no
So
This camera basically
It's a picture
And it sent it to you
On your phone
And that's it
And then you can be like
Hey
They also have a line of connected math
For your pantry basically it's mats with the weight sensor in it
And
You tell it was on that mat
It's like hey whatever this thing is
I'm loving that that concept
I'm loving the fridge cam
What is a little
Yeah I mean I'd rather just keep a grocery list and said pay $200
But I love the concept of
I'm out and about at the
Story of the grocery store
Cheese how much milk do we really have I forget
Pop open the app you look at your camera in your fridge now you know
Yeah I have to cut the tops
Set of my egg carton
I did get rid of my
Quickie eggs
And I'm
Now I wouldn't know
So I like that
I like this kind of like having you had a great idea cuz we
Is tiny little cameras I've written about them actually in my previous life at giga
They're called blink
They did a Kickstarter last August
Not this most recent August but August 2014
These are it's actually a
Companies
Started
They had a video processing chip that was really good
Really low power
And they realize that they couldn't make it as a video Processing Company like the margins were just too thin they could sell these chips
You know are actually $2
Tencent youku
Margins
Will Barton
To DVD Maker
DVD player makers
Blu-ray player
Instalike what is the Terrible
Nobody wants this
What could make
Connect to camera
So they decided to make a connect to camera they got out of the chip business and
When did the consumer product business and they like
Sonys cameras
Are $79 for one tiny little it's probably a 2 and 1/2 by 2 and 1/2 in maybe 3 by 3 in
And a wireless
And cordless
Yeah they run out of battery should last quite a while
You can if you buy these and both are even less than the $79 each because
And get to 41393 for 189 and 5
I like this because of the portability
It still uses Wi-Fi so it's not like using some funky radio protocol
You actually
Plug-in into an outlet with a little help it comes with it so it's not hanging off router
You can't use them outside or not waterproof but that's okay
But you could use one in your fridge
They turn up their not recording all the time when they see motion
The record that's the power conservation
Method obviously
So when you open your fridge door they're going to start recording
And you close it
The recording of what's in your fridge right
What about your friends being a giant Faraday cage I talked to the inhibitor
Behind what we thought that too
But there's a lot of like rubber gaskets and stuff that actually allow the Wi-Fi signal to get out so I was like okay great
What about you know the colder the fridge sucking the battery
You know what he's like
We also were concerned about that but you know
Tell battery life actually it's actually really good for the batteries up until you get to about 0 degrees Celsius
Then
The battery life
Maybe you could use
479 bus
If I don't use it in my fridge and I'm tempted because
These look simple to use during expensive
You can move them around easily
I like it
They're getting through their Kickstarter orders
And then they said by mid-January they'll be shipping
Comstock
So you don't even have to wait
So there you got blink for home. Com is where you can order them from
Two more cameras
That are worth mentioning
The ring doorbell launched
Stick up camera
Which Kevin these are the last two are outdoor cameras since I'm obsessed with outdoor camera
Price right now
The ring doorbell camera is the stick up camera is $199 of Kobe shipping in two to three weeks
You were looking actually for
A smaller outdoor
Camera this is bracket
Yeah bracket mounted might work for 9
What's neat about this is
It works with the ring doorbell
But two is a two-way audio
I'm so you can talk to someone if you see them running around on your property
Used to be like
Hey that my mom
Quite literally
Which
And then the other camera is the netatmo presence
Outdoor camera
And I like this
A couple reason
1 this is a wired camera
So the ring doorbell camera is actually not its Wireless
Battery power
But the netatmo is wired but what happens is you
You wire it into
An existing outdoor security light
Or an existing outdoor light
And it's got an egg LED light that turns on that actually gives the camera enough light to
Come by
And
Skinny
It's not going to be out till Q3 I don't have pricing for it
I've been wanting a camera to stick up on my rooftop
And this
I just seems like it might be the camera
I've depending on the price point
This is the camera in all of netatmo Welcome indoor camera
Are the cameras for you if you value
Your privacy and you don't want to send anything to
A cloud
All your stuff
On an SD card on the camera itself
Or you can send it to your own media
On your own
That's nice and I wish more people would know more products would do that
So
That is what you can send it is it your own FTP server and then you can send it to your smartphone
Like if you want
Little complicated but that's okay I mean for people who want total control of it yes
If you want Total Control you can do that with this product
And thinking
Instructions
They have no plans to ever offer
The thoughts of that is not there
I have no idea of being French
Is why they do that but I've talked to them
A couple times about this
Our audience really values
The fact that we don't put in the cloud
That's not her
So
What is a lot
Yes it is next like tip of the iceberg for you and was going to be running around Vegas all week
Exactly so I'll be running around Vegas and in the meantime thank you so much for listening and play
Please join us again next week