Hey everyone is welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
Kevin tofel
This week
Awesome stuff for you
We've got Amazon's new streaming music program we've got something about what the heck
It's happening with cameras coming out
I was just building an Internet of Things net worth
And this week's guest is Eric has cilia of AGCO the company is transforming
Intuit services
All because of the internet
All right
Kevin
Let's get started with Amazon streaming music service
Wechat
Roughly $8 a month for
Anybody if you're an Amazon Prime member
And $4 a month if you happen to have him
What do you think
Well it's it's interesting and we knew it was coming well we'd heard it was, I guess I should say
The interesting aspect is the 399 a month
Just have Amazon music catalog
Available on your Amazon Echo devices I still don't know if a lot of people are going to
Take Amazon up on that
Prime Membership
Store subscription fee for this is as you said 799 a month
Interesting way you can pay $79 for the year
And have the unlimited music if you're a Prime member on all of your devices
And then for all you non-prime folks
10 bucks a month just like everybody else
I think you'll get a lot of prime people here
I think $8 a month is going to be a peeling
There is a family plan coming soon that I was interested in cuz that's what I have with apple music
It's going to be 1499 a month
No matter what I say
Even if your Prime so
I'm a little less interested now so
I'm not going to do the echo only thing that just doesn't make sense to me because I use so many mobile devices but that's again
So what do you think
Well do in comparison I'm paying
1499 a month for the Spotify family plan
And is it 999
I meant or 599 a month
Score
Normal people Spotify
So I thought it was the same for Spotify
Yes
Yes it is
That my brain was getting confused cuz I
When I upgraded I was like
$5
$5 a month
Where on the music
Okay
So
I think
I guess I could cut back on in just have one Spotify account and then one Amazon Echo
Accountant that would be a Buckler
And my daughter could listen
Are the echo
You know to her music
Which is kind of where she lives
But now that I have Spotify on my mobile devices
But
Right now I have my echo set to have
Spotify as the default in If I Stay
Play this on Spotify
And that is not worth a dollar extra month
So I think I would stick with Spotify for the time being I will try this out because
Cuz what if there
Selectionism
And that's what it always comes down to I think my side from price for these types of services what's the catalog you how much music
Is there
I believe Amazon has three of the four major labels in their catalog so they may not have
Why does many songs or albums
Artist as the others but it's got to be darn close
The Beatles
I know it's important for you
Streaming everywhere song
Everybody's Got The Beatles at this point I think
Did you also have if you're interested in this kind of thing did you also have this new side-by-side feature
Which takes
Artist commentary
I'm sorry commentary from the tracks in the catalog and
View insights as to the music I don't know that's going to be a huge
Draw either
I don't know
It's kind of like
Emitra service right
And then let's make it
A little more affordable
And also have
Way to get it just on our devices for a few bucks extra
It's a smart play by then but
I don't know I just
Maybe it's me I don't know I don't know how much girls are going to get out of there
Fair enough
Cuddle with you
But
People who act like the ideas
People who are normal buying these services
It's possible that instead of a service like Spotify they're really going after a service like Apple
Their music service
Which
Feels like a little bit more
Porthole
And maybe this is a good way to augment that collection for people who are like
Colossians say you're right there. Maybe it is a different target audience because I'm sure there's overlap yes but
You think about
How many millions of echo devices are out there and how many cortical normals
Handsome
Yeah maybe these people aren't current music
Scribers at all
Yeah but
One taught the other thing I would say
I really
Excited
No I hope
Because baby there
But I really hope it is a Time
Keeps offering
The Computing Services
Cuz I think that's going to be really
Agreed important
Especially if you think about what happened with like Amazon not selling Chromecast
And given that they're going to be in an all-out war with all these other
Services
Like the new Google home comes with
Six months of access to like
YouTube
Red
If you're doing something like that and you know
Music from
Scott service
Sorry that it right
This is crazy
It's good people of music
All right
Movie Ride Along
Let's talk about
Ramah in the standard
We never have drama there
No
Only thing standard upstanders is drama
Okay so what happened with this the open connectivity Foundation or OCS
Has
That is merging
With the Ultimate Alliance
Actually it's not merging with you
Emerging the standards
Iotivity and alljoyn
Alliance actually voted
Just Dance
People yelled at me saying it wasn't
It was
This is not a merger of equals
You guys this is a merger of all joined into iota
Did it actually reason
The first one being
What happened to it's already in devices
The answer is
Ic3 will be back
What's compatible
Townsite is right now Ayo to be isn't much it's a little bit of hoses backwards
Compatible
Like their work out the backwards compatibility
There isn't a lot of like production value code out there to make
So
Forgot
We should stay with you standard to
Yeah that's a good question
That is too surprising for me. I need a lot more coffee for that
Got it
Okay so these standards are device
Discovery and interoperability standards
So what they're going to do
Is
Like
If your light bulb
H&M
I can do that
For televisions it might be here the messages I can display
Here's what you can do to me
That's kind of idea
Is this protocol let statements in the home talk to you
Each other and figure out
How to say
Puns aside in and that's probably why we don't hear too much about them like you don't hear about
Join product or this is Aniya tivity supported products
It's really big glue
That kind of makes these products work together
Which Southern on
Product specific
Feature
Seventies are like behind-the-scenes kind of protocols I think
Yes you were behind
Well I'm sure each of these people would be like like love to be the Wi-Fi if they're era
Call ideas just to make everything
Competitors to them is Ashley Google
Weave
What we're seeing here is
Or the merger of those standards is
We have existing alljoyn products
In the market they might be they will be backwards
Compatible
With
Coming of age.
Right now
It looks like I'll be stuff
It's really far off
Some people are telling me it's as far out as 2018
I have too many guys are like those here today
But that's kind of equivalent out where the code bases
And right now the code base is not
Production
It's already
Anaya tivity I think is newer
And then they all join
Framework because just last year with the announcement
They started musically if you want to
Mistreated by Poco
And then back in 2013 Qualcomm design
It in like a couple other companies are like we are going to
Christian standard
And then
There's licensing issues
2015 Impalas
Hey let's creator
Because that's what standards do
Then
They came out and enjoy
Push pins
And like Microsoft when she joined all terrain
This looks good
So all these companies kind of
1 /
And they decided that everything was going to work together a couple months ago
Honestly the death of Saul
Alliance was really
Written that when they all decided that everything should work together
Cuz you just don't need that kind of
You don't need to stand this
The same Tuesday
That's where we are
Is a sad day
Because right now I feel like we had a working standard but
Better marketing
Standard
While
Google superhero
I got weed
The funny thing is from new and users consumers I don't know
Even know what
Standards are used for the devices to talk to each other
That's the you know as all this churn
We're all sitting here going just make it work
Yeah cuz I mean how long has it been since we
Talking about this Markovich
Okay
That's the standard Smith
Let's talk about
Cameras
Kevin you want to tell us about the Netgear Arlo Pro
Oh yes I do so I didn't know this was coming you may have
But
Netgear has the Arlo Pro Wireless home security cameras
This is a camera that
You don't need to worry about connecting to existing power lines are in like that
You just stick it and go
Believe it is to
4999 does that sound right
$250
Base station and one camera
You can go hog-wild and spend a lot of money here
So this is
Did the station as well
It does have a base station in what I'm actually currently trying to look up on me really slow internet is whether or not the new or
Orbi mesh routers from Netgear
And so if you have the Arlo
The old lady
Yeah
The answer is
Orbi will not replace your Arlo base station
Bay station
Yes this is a new base station
All right well that's it that's it
Plug in my router
But I will save my Arlo cameras
I'm using the the older version that has
Irreplaceable
Batteries disc
When is
USPS
So you're spending Less on batteries
Complaint for the original
Singer sew fun
Good cameras you like
I mean honestly
Super magnet on the back
It's so great for like attaching it to things
Toss it in the air
I have this ability here
It's great
Even though there's a
So just
This looks like a more powerful
Uso
Yeah I mean
Quick Charge rechargeable battery so less time
Last downtime of not monitoring something when you had to recharge the batteries
Miniature two-way audio which is nice and the
Night vision and ultra-wide 130° field of view and
Like you said you can stick this thing anywhere
Start on something more
It's magnetic and boom
Yeah currently actually right now because I have glass doors at my home in my August doorbell or not
I replaced them trying to get a better
Version of its I have replaced it with newer Hardware in
So far
Are you guys
Yeah you have to
Please.
I'm using the voice before
We're back in town
Recording that before we left town
We were like oh
Where can you have a package so we just stuck in Arlo like
Right there
Magnetically
I have facing the door in
You know we got the motion sensor when
Someone came to the door and we're good to go
And for those of you guys who are like
Still there batteries in the sting
Talk about
Wireless charging which is
Not what we hoped it would be but is apparently getting better
Do you know why it's not where we had hoped it be
Standard you know
Don't want to seem but yeah it's standard different standards between
Reasons
Powermat
Consolidation over the past few years which is good
This point again people don't care what standard is used so long as they can use whatever it is they want to use
Seems like
A lot more devices now are adopting
The chi standard which has been around for quite a while
And or devices that support multiple standards again people don't care
They're just like I can use a wireless charging pad with this okay that's good for me
So that's really what's been happening over the past couple years so
While wireless charging has
Grown in terms of adoption and in fact
It was up 40% in
2016 according to IHS it could have been more as what I just said and I agree it could have been me
Figured out the standards earlier
Yeah it is important for people for like what she
Actually spelled with a q i many of you guys made
I did not
It is a bummer in
Haven't you tried a couple of these wireless charging things out
I don't charge it
Quickly
What do you think it's like
So
I would say just a year or two ago I would say that would be an accurate statement the difference between
Wireless charging times War
Very noticeable
These days we got fast wireless charging and again
Special chips needed for that special
Charging pads and so on but perfect example is my Galaxy S7 that I got back in May
I was able to find a Samsung fast charge wireless charging pad
Which will charge devices wirelessly at they standard
Slower rate
But the Galaxy S7 presidential causes Sports fast wireless charging
And it's darn near
Close
To a regular wire charge
Let me just add a car
I didn't want to go to there but know this phone has not
If it doesn't show it was nice knowing you off
But I I want to add a caveat there because don't forget in the wireless charging
Marketplace
We've also had
Quick charging Qualcomm quick charge
1 2 and 3. Oh now where you can
You don't plug in a fast charge wire
Plug and you can get like half of your battery back in as little as
15 20 30 minutes
Wiregrass wireless charging is not that fast
But it's as fast as standard wired charging if that makes sense
Got it
It is
But it does need to be touching the pad
It's good for like your mobile devices
I'm still waiting for a great wireless charging options
Fuller Lake
Sensors are things I mean like if you're going to invest in the Smart Home
You're going to invest in
Is double-sided tape
Justice everywhere
Is batteries
And you're going to be going through batteries like
Toddler is what
So
And you're going to also have
My recommendation is a screwdriver that can open all of your sensor back
So you're not running up and down
Yes
We should we should Market
Speak it for the show
Myiot breaking cases
Watch bands
Before you give up move on one thing that has not happened in this market
It would answer your or address your concerns and questions and that is
Having wireless charging pads built into furniture and other objects
Where is
Like I have a lot of
Devices that sit on a little table we know or whatever
They can't recharge their butt
If the wireless charging pads are there
All the time
And that's been a talk of me for several years now and I'm yet I really haven't seen much
Much play in that except for I give credit to Starbucks which put in a corset with the Powermat standard but
Starbucks wireless charging
Pads built into their
Little
Tables where you sit and have your coffee
I'm so you can have your phone recharge me just put it down there in your drink their coffee
That's about the only place I've actually seen that out in the wild
Wireless charging built into furniture
I believe one of the major hotel chains
Is investigating
Using wireless charging in table
The lack of Standards is released I need them because furniture
I mean think about
They remember how you used to go into every hotel room and there was a.
For your iPhone that is now lick
Or iterations at 8
30 pin connector
I mean Furniture should laugh
I mean I think having a little ballet
You know that you can get a charging that that you
That probably makes more sense
In all on
Because you'll know that wireless charging furniture sets a big time when it comes in
Ikea offers pizza and we're not there
There you go
Okay
Ml12 big news which is Comcast is doing its own low-power wide area network
Basically Comcast Building
An Internet of Things Network
Sometime last week I took a nap
Which is the maker of
Laura
Pandora is a radio standard for these low-power wide area Networks
And it Comcast said it would
Goldish Network out across 30 markets
Nextlink
80 months which is crazy because
Comcast has such a
Bigfoot prints
It's it's almost like how could they not do this right this isn't going to take a ton of bandwidth mean
Because Lora data rates are
50 kbps or glass of Minnesota
Iot MTM
Kind of communication so when you can
Leverage your big footprint with us why wouldn't you
Exactly
And either relatively cheap chips
They can work over a large
They are really interesting for like sensors
So you can see Comcast taking its Xfinity home which this is not part of the exit
He experienced it has medicine goes Network
You can see it
Why that took small business and Enterprise customers they're actually really hurting for these kind of
DIY or cheaper solution
Security in that sort of thing
To make sad
Inessence wireless network
Feel like we can talk about Comcast wireless network or like the last decade
There's a couple questions
Competes with standards like sigfox
Which is building
It says it's building a hundred
Cities in the US
Which is a lot in so far
It hasn't quite done that
Stop near me
Standard form
Will power wins
And
Nobody knows where that is proprietary
To pray time with you then
Comcast is really
You know pushing the envelope here
Especially in the US
Because in
Europe
In Singapore a lot of the major carriers
But here in the US with AT&T and Verizon
Laura Webb
They're looking at doing
Low-power wide area network based on the GSM standard so there
Cat 1M I can never even remember this
Basically cellular-based
Openstack
So I don't know exciting news we'll see Comcast does it feel like it's all it's going to it's
Could have asked
Hazit Market rollout nodejs
Contingent Upon a Child
Successful
But it's kind of nice to see come here
Yeah yeah
I agree
All right so I think that
Good for the show if you want to date you were going to have a little advertisement and then we're going to have
Church hymns
Who is with an agriculture company called AGCO
And he's going to talk a little bit about the interview is actually about how to trance
On your business
Selling products
Selling services
So it's worth a listen
Taking a break for the podcast for a few moments for a word from our sponsor this week sponsors arm and I have
Tom Williamson the GM of the wireless business at arm
I'm here to talk to us today
Soap
Paul
You're telling me that 18 months ago I'm launched a wireless IP radio division can you tell me a
A little bit more about this
Show that's right
18 months ago
Launched a new product offering cocodia which is
Radio IP rather than Price is Right
Which one now offering to arcilla campanas
And that allows them to add the connectivity that I need
Be able to address the rapid growth that was sitting in iot devices
What is your first radio.
The first product we launched with Bluetooth low energy
Beyond the initial version was the
4.2 standard but upcoming soon as the new version of Bluetooth Bluetooth 5 which introduces
New features that are really going to be important
For The Internet of Things
Key features that we going to see
Increase title right so
That's going to make the transfers between devices like
Your Fitbit 21
PetSmart Timothy wanted to getting that data to and from the phone
Fosta
And still win sorry live energy
I don't say things that I
Perhaps more mundane but really important for us to get secure connected endpoints into iot like firmware
Will happen very quickly
Clean swell
The other Kingdom
Featureless coming is where
Adding a longer range feature
The technology which means that devices will be able to cover
At the entire home rather than just those personal devices around you
I thought something that will be a supporting in the near future
Why would I want to
ARM version
Of a radio
As opposed to someone
VIP that we develop for radio is
Reddit really pushing the boundaries of low power consumption say
All radios operate at below 1 volt
Allows them to run off a pretty broad range of pass Plies and drive down the energy consumption flat devices
Korean consumer that means longer battery life by up 40% in products that use our radio technology
In addition to the low-power the other feature that were able to bring it along with the prices
Completely secure endpoint solution so you can securely about data from these
Embedded devices into
McLeod this guy to be more news about not coming up at the arm techcon conference at the end of this month
Awesome and as a consumer
I am excited about Bluetooth 5
What should I expect
24-hour toys mystery when these new features come out as to how people are going to use them I think
What you probably start C is a little more around the small time 6 please
Smart financing tablet apps
Devices that the need for these Bridges and gateways and I think I could bring
Even more Lifehouse NC
Into the home environment tell me how can I find out more about the products
Radio IP products
You just got to Omnicom Foods Kodiak
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higginbotham
Am I guess today is Eric Henson
Who is SVP of global cross cycle
And Advanced Technology Solutions for a company called egg
Hi Eric
Great thanks for having me on the show
Man I am so excited to have you here because I can
About Farm
It is actually
I don't I don't know what is
So let's get started Adco
You should probably tell us what it does because it is not a household
Yeah Edco is the largest pure-play farm equipment company in the world
So let's get people excited about bringing we've had guests on the show talk about Precision Acura
Culture talk to me about the future of
Farming
And
Why you guys are
Are doing this
Yeah it's actually an exciting time
When you look forward at the future of farming
The world only needs the farmers all around the world to double their productivity
There's no more land
And yet there's going to be more miles
The feed
You combine that with the fact that
Diets are maturing around the world
More and more people are
Adding more meat
To their diet at the multiplier and amount of
Food that needs to be done
Is just more bile energy
Demand sources
So that could be biofuel internship ethanol or soy diesel
And somehow the world's Farmers need to grow twice as much food
Nginx
20 years or so as they do today
With no more land
And and also managing the resources like water and fertilizer
Pesticide
Things like that
The farmers have to farm differently in the future than they are today
Farmers needing to be more
Proficient both because we've got more people
Because we want to use our resources more effectively and also because farmers
At certain points in time are kind of living on the edge in terms of profit
How much more efficient
Can we actually make
Yeah there's a few ways to look at that if we simplify it down
Kernel is
Seed has the inherent lipstick corn as an example
Eternal love
Corn if you
You take a look at them
Traits that are inherited it today
Any places that ideal condition
It can grow to
600 bushel yield
Africa
Whereas the average yield across the United
States is only about a hundred and seventy-five bush
Icebreaker
So not every single seeing every single Farm is going to be grown in the app to Absolute optimal condition
But there's still a tremendous amount of upside potential
On the farms to be able to farm more effectively
To raise the real
Certainly 20 25 30
Percent is
Within reason
In the short-term
And you guys started out with adding connectivity over the last decade to tractors and
Other farming equipment
And also I believe some sensors
So what makes today different like what brings connectivity to the next level
Precision
Guess you using a great turn Precision agriculture if you think about
What we talked about
There's no more land
And yet we need to somehow grow twice
As much as we do today
So we have to farm different
And in the phrasing around that is called Precision agriculture
It's intended to mean that
We need to be more precise with the way we use input
Seeds
Water fertilizer pesticide herbicide
And machinery
To be able to get
It's a different outcome a higher yield
And
The more efficient cost structure
A key element of that
More recently is
Connectivity
The Advent of
Telematics which allows us to be able to
Send the information from the machine
Boston machine
And remotely monitor how a machine like a tractor or combine or
Sprayer is operating or
Performing or how it
Set
Or Howard drivers
By remotely monitoring that machine we can then help the farmer with insights to say
Hey change how you're using that machine
Change how your settings
Change how you using one machine with another
Maybe a sprayers waiting for the water truck to show up to it
To refill it
Those are all
Solutions that we
We can provide
Now that this remote monitoring is available
And then you're adding
Sensors
So once you have the capability to know where you are
And the ability to
Transmit that information off board
Then two things happen one is you want to be able to learn more and more about what's going on
In the machine and around the machine
So that's where sensors come in
And second thing that you want to do is to be able to
Convert
All of that raw data
Into an insight
Okay so we're moving from notification
Action
That's right and it's just the kind of level set for those that aren't
Treme with the Baseline of where we are today
A lot of talk about driverless cars
In fact
Most of large equipment has the capability to be
Operated without steering it
So auto-steer within the field
So the farmer will typically come into the field
And let's say they're planting
They come into the field
They would set up there
GPS line their guidance line of the line that they want to start on
And then they took the steering wheel up out of the way in the machine operator
Allen Stone
Driving to the field on that line
You turn the machine around and then it will plant
And exactly parallel line to the first one
Offset by the width of the planter
Not only the steering itself on a on a perfectly straight line or or curved line depending on what you
But it's also having the ability to change the last
Change the speed at which it's running
And change what's happening on the planter
Change the rate at which it
The Planters planting season
Planting more in the high fertility areas
Lesson love
Those are just some examples of
Functions that are already highly automated on the machine
After your Stills in the cab
These things are happening
In an automated way
Soac is a seven and a half billion dollar
And you guys have been working on
Bringing the internet of things to your business for
Sounds like over a decade
Why did you guys get started
Addington
We felt this is one of the
The best ways to help farmers
Become more productive when you look at the
Technology that has recently become available on GPS
And then on telematics device
And then managing data
We thought
It would be a great opportunity to harness those capabilities
To be able about the world
Far more effectively
As part of the seven and a half billion dollars in Revenue
What percentage of it is
Based on connected services
Vs may be connected
Revenue generated from Services Estill
It's in the early stages
We're just transitioning
From
Selling the technology
To accompany this now poker
Gaston delivering services
Around that technology
Advising Farmers on how to change
Practices
But the
Scope it covers is
Most of what act
Cassell's
So do you sell
The connectivity itself
Or do you sell the inside
How do you guys sell
Precision AG
Yeah we're transitioning
To a company that sells
Subscription Service package
So what's the machine
And many
A customer can just buy the machine if they like to
But we're moving to a company then that will sell the machine Plus
Service packages around those machine
That can be based on
For example focusing on up time let's say
To be
Looking at
Indicators off the machine to be predicting when components will fail before they will fail
Or more precisely
Schedule maintenance
Around exactly when the machine needs
To maintain
Flex one category
Second categories machine optimization
Helping helping cell service pack
Optimizing how machine is used
Any category is helping with Farm up
Sensation
But we're going to be selling
Service packages to
Give insights to the farmer on
Different elements
Father Fermin
Today
Versus
How they could be
It could be and how
When is free application to
To attack weeds
Recommending
The timing of that
There's a number of different farming recommendation
I can also come out of
Inside the farm
Are using Wireless
Probably a decade ago we had this huge
Shift tonight
We're instead of companies buying their own servers they bought come
And it shifted
They're compute cost basically from a capex to an object
Situation financing
And if I look at
What's happening
In farming
And this kind of idea of providing Solutions inside
Do you see that same sort of shift
Possibly happening for agriculture or will there still always be massive
Expenditures that
Yeah I think there's going to be quite a Continuum there's going to be a certain segment of the market that I think over the course of
Time will evolve to the point where
Ultimately they will pay for
The outcome so it could be
Grain harvesting
Or seeds planted or Acres planted or something like that
And that
Someone else
Potentially AGCO would be
Managing
Not only the
Equipment within how they quit
Let's maintain our equipment operated
And I'm guaranteeing a certain outcome to the farmer
You see this happening in mining operations there more Bass
Navel
Charge the cusp
Play the quantity of War removed
Is the closest thing the machine
Get there
Much like
The technology Journey that
Technology doesn't show up
All at once it comes in steps
So we've been building the technology Journey
Now we're building the services Journey
MCU
Fill out these pieces one step at a time you get the customer comfortable and digesting the value that makes sense for their far
Piece by piece
Each one has their own
Coyote and wolf
Pieces are most valuable to them
And then over the course of time
You fill in the puzzle piece
Until
You know these leave users ultimately say you know what I'd rather
Focus on the other elements of my operation and
And let you manage
The machine and optimizing how that machine works I'm going to
Optimize The Other Woman
So a lot of the
Adoption of
The cloud computing model
Is Opex vs capex was taken
In the tech World by startups in kind of Greenfield operations because
Either there
Venture capitalist Preston to do that just made more sense based on their
Models
Or
They had no existing infrastructure even Creek
Oceans
So farming does not feel like
It has a similar level of
Churn and startups I could be wrong
It feels like a much more old-school industry so I'm curious how
You guys will push this sort of shift
In the farm
Industry
Persol one Farmers not the same as the next Dairy Farmers a little bit different than what they need and their appetite for
Change in their comfort with technology
We're trying to end up with a few different
Solutions for different groups
Customers
But
In general if you got to take a step back and
Simplify
What we would say is that
We're going to need to
Look at those customers that are most
What's a business-minded
And most comfortable with technology and end
Payoffs of value think of it in terms of an Roi
And work with them first to generate
A success story
Now not only do we need to work with our customers we also have to work with our dealers
Because most of our equipment comes to our customers through it
Channel of independent dealers
Hello and they hate
Well if there's a mixture there's well isn't there there's a mixture of those early adopters who
Embrace
This conversation about
I working
Not only with technology but with
Changing a relationship with a customer instead of selling them a machine and then waiting a while until the phone
Calls music
I need to know
24 hours
Remotely monitoring that customer and that machine
To be able to help the cusp
Make the most of it
Does a shift in the relationship
Doesn't that imply like if you have it you if you're delivering a service I feel like a middleman is a terrible thing to have
So when it makes sense
Look into providing that monitoring
Bring yourself as the company providing this Hardware
This is a tough transition
Yeah if there's going to be a mixture
Where we're going to do some of these
Services
Especially the data analytics
Some of them will be done Central look like they're done
Sexually
Interact with the customers directly from a
Some of them will be done centrally just because there's an economy is
Scale
Of analyzing large amounts of data storing large amounts of data and song we don't want every dealer trying to figure that out themselves
But we will deploy back to the customers through the dealer
So because the customer relationship is there and
Especially if it's around machine repair or machine maintenance
That's going to be done by the dealer
So the dealer will Lemay and the
Inside back to the dealer and say there's a repair opportunity coming up or maintenance opportunity coming up
But then the dealer will call the cops
Marceau look to the customer
From the dealer
In a third kind are going to be some
More local
Dealer generators
Solutions
Where the deal is going to be looking at
Specific issues with their customer base in their local geography
And coming up with some of their own optimist
And that will be directed
Between the dealer in Augusta
It'll show up in all three forms
I depending on the kind of work that's needed in
And this is a hard thing to do as a business
This is to transition from selling a physical product
Selling a service especially because
Your service is going to be wrapped around a physical
Co-product
So how do you guys think about managing your costs in your supply chain
Kind of
Adjust for the the way the income is
Yeah one of the things I say here is that
Diffuse strategy as a
Feud
We're not the only ones going after this idea trying to help farmers become more productive
One of the tenants of the few strategy that makes a difference is that
We have a
We're intending to be the most open architecture approach of anybody in the industry
Car that is
What the customer sees but then the other half that is the
The back-office side
We're not going to do all this ourselves
In order to deliver the competency and create the company
We're partnering up with a few different
Companies
To be able to
Leverage their strong EX
And given area and come to the market
With a package that looks like it's one package but was actually
Created by
A few different groups working
That helped spread some of this cost burden over a broader base
And it reduces
The inefficiency of trying to
Invent all of this on our own
Got it so can you give me an example of what that is
What that looks like
Will one of the examples would be our guidance
The guidance is the GPS receiver is made up of a GPS receiver
The signal from the satellite
And then a navigation controller in the middle and then
It actually makes action on
The steering signal
Steer the machine
Well historically you needed to buy all of that from one provider
And so the customer would be
Lockton
Two provider AR provider beer providers
But we've done is we've come up
With a system that we've launched in the market this past year
That is
Agnostic
Guidance and what we mean by that is
The customer can choose
It's an open guidance platform
We've partnered up with a few different guidance
Companies
And we buy
Their receiver
And so we we've got multiple choice
For the customer to make based on what their farming situation is on the
Coverage in their geography what are the machines they have on the farm
What makes more sense for them
And we write the software code in the middle of navigation
Control software
And and make it look like
1 Echo System regardless of what the input was
And how do you guys from a
Just purely from a business perspective
How are you guys measuring success
As you guys switch from
Hardware
Services
Old school to New School
You know there's a few different measures
But we need this to be a profitable business with an echo
Insofar shareholders we've got
Goals on revenue and and margin and growth rate
So I'm on one handed
It's like any other business
Degenerated song
Prophet Andrew
On the other hand it's
It's a significant
Transition
Phase within the industry and with an egg called
So we're measuring other things in addition to that
Like percent of machines sold with service contracts
Adoption rates on different
Regions of the world
Different machine forms
Different levels of the
And then
Activation rates of how many of those service package
Jahzare
Are activated and renewed
And then satisfaction on the back end so
When you're in a transition phase you have to
Focused on additional
Factors beyond just the financial
Performance
Because you need to cause the
Phase transition
And that's why we're looking
Some of those other measures
To make sure that work
Treating activity change the behavior change
And I own the company as well as with our dealers
Such that the customers make we make sure that the customer seen the value out of the service package
Yeah I guess you guys have to worry about chernow
That's right
Exactly
All right
Will Eric thanks so much for
For coming on the show this week I have learned
But I really enjoyed it and I appreciate the opportunity Stacy thank you so much
For listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news from this show
Feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com