Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have got an amazing show for
Are you today
We have
New Raspberry Pi
We got a new smart home plan from Telstra Australia
We've got home for Sonos
We've got
The future of retail
We're going to save some right
And if we get to it we will talk about my experience with stringify
Which is a
Really
How cool it's like it if this then that
They're going to hate me for saying it but that's what it does
We also have a sponsored message from
Cast an amazing guest
We have three amazing guess
I went to an event
National instruments and I managed to run into the CEO of PTC
The CEO of NRA
Alex Devereux
And
Their head of embedded systems Jamie Smith all of them are coming on the show this week to talk about
What is going on in the industrial
Internet of Things
No
Let's go to a quick sponsor message
This week sponsor
That's right you guys I don't have a sponsor this week
But I decided to use the spot to tell you about two things one if you would like to be a sponsor the space
You should email Andrew at Coyote podcast.com into if you can't get a
Enough internet of things news for me here you should sign up for my newsletter Stacey on iot.
It's also my brand new website
And sometimes I might surprise you by putting up new content there.
If you want more go there go to Stacey on iot, and if you want to advertise
Email Andrew
Iot podcast
All right I think that's it
How is my 32nd
Back to the show
Kevin
Weather
Let's kick it off with
Hi
I love pies restaurants Raspberry Pi
Yeah
So they got a new compute module is this is the
Third instance of it I believe
I almost feel like it's
No cuz they have raspberry they have the original
They have one that's better
And then they have the zero
It's like
V bucks
And now they have
The superpower
Right okay so this is that they're calling the compute module
3 which is based on the the latest
Raspberry Pi the pi 3
And what the promising is even though it's all the same
Broadcom 2837 processor
It is double the RAM and about 10 times CP performance of the original computer module which was
2014, three years ago
And before the show States I eat you and I were talking like
Does a Raspberry Pi as in a compute module does it need more
Power if it's going to be safer IRT maybe a person like that
Right now maybe not
But you raised a good point they're trying to stay
I think because
As
We add more devices to our homes
It takes more time to compute what needs to happen all the little steps to turn things on turn things off or adjust based on
Uncensored
So
You know at first I was like I don't really see the point is but based on your thought
Makes sense it makes sense to stay ahead of the Curve
Yeah I think
You're going to buy a hub
Probably
Every two to three years and for those of us who are shocked you like
I don't know you're not no it's it's a computer
You wouldn't die if you see
Expected to last
I think this makes sense
I also think if we're going to do more local compute
For your house it also makes sense for that
In this is actually really
Good use case for like the type of arm
Chips that are out there cuz these are very small workloads that are going to come in kind of all at once
And you're going to want to parse them up if you can
I'm not saying
Maybe we should have a
I don't know
Or multi-core
That's kind of my thinking he
So yeah I'm excited about this Plus
There's such a
Huge number of people out there building crazy stuff with pies
And no one no one in the history of the world has ever said I need less
Right right pricing is not bad at all
$20 for the compute module 3 they have
A lighter version for $25 so
You know if you just want to Tinker around
How to build your own Hub you some
Michelle software open source software
And that's that's a beauty the Raspberry Pi always has been and I hope they stick
And
Just so you know
The compute module is
Drop-in replacement for the first
Incompatible
Gosh this
Raspberry Pi print server
Can you make a pie Sprint soccer actually
I did
It doesn't make sounds
Alright so
Yay pie
Moving right along
This is some fun
News for me because I own six of these
And I have been very frustrated
But Sonos actually last week and we didn't address it on the show John McFarlane the CEO of Sonos
Step down
Replace with Patrick spens
Has been working at Sonos for a while
Is
This felt very much like
Great move for Sonos I mean
He basically he kind of missed the boat on
Voice and soda
Putting Sonos in the position of being not just the
Speakers for the entire car
Make it home
But also
The ears
Instead
Amazon created the Amazon Echo and boom they took that
In
For what it's worth
Sonos is still a great
I'm actually holding onto my Sonos is
Cousin sometime this year they're supposed to start work
Fingers crossed
But Patrick spens
Is really up
The Voice
He is like
We are doing it we are not going to do it ourselves we are going to work with others Sonos has always been really good at playing it
Ecosystem
It originally came out with like this vision of being like
We want to be the best darn internet-connected speaker ever so they never tried to launch their own music service to compete with other
Mother's Day just wanted to make all of your existing Music Services
So
Hopefully that's the tact
They take invoice I think they actually could have done their own
Voice thing but now it's
Too late
So
You know we'll see if it's
The way forward for them I guess
Yeah I wonder I mean it doesn't make sense for them to kind of create their own voice interface when there are options out there
And my daughter have been talking to Amazon and payment amounts anything
That may be the way to go to use the
Voice services from from Amazon
And it's kind of interesting yet I don't know if you caught this news or do we talked about it last week that Huawei actually has a phone with
Amazon voice services in it Prince all is well
That's why people are starting to do now just climb onto what's already available in working well
That's true in
Way back in the day cuz Sonos launch super early
They actually had like a $300 controller
You bought two controllers
Smartphones
Wait a second
People in app because that $300 controller while revenue for us is also a huge barrier to entry
In Dallas
Patrick Spence actually said that Sonos were in 20% of American households which
It's a lot
So
I think we can expect good things here
I am ultimately a little sad that they missed the boat
Last year on this but you know
There's still time in the got such a broad user base it's so you know I'm not saying it's easy but essentially integrates Employee Services
You've got a
Hannah people you know that I'm much happier now and then
Less likely to leave for different connected speakers
Cuz like actually ditch
Best Bluetooth speaker
High quality Marshall
Stanmore Bluetooth speaker we talkin about
I just
Bluetooth speakers
This is one of our
The Fight Continues
This is a quick bit too quick fix for you
One is Telstra
We're going to go International for a moment
HealthStream which is an Australian carrier
Is getting into the smartphone business much like Comcast or AT&T is done
They've created a service that's going to cost $25
25 Australian dollars
And you basically will get a starter kit
One for either security or one for automation energy
Take out their own hub
It's pretty much like what you would expect from other people
Like other carriers
I mention this mostly because
I do think
This year we're going to see a lot more carriers come out
With the sort of offering
And I think it's
A probable way
For smart home devices to get mainstream
One because it's easier
And people love easy
You're going to feel more secure with it and you're going to feel like most of your devices are going to be free
Those are some of the worries that
Customers have
Those are valid concerns
It's interesting you mention security and I know that
Last year
Telstra talking about using blockchain and biometric security for their iot stuff so
You know they're not
Fiddling around here in just putting products out there not thinking about the one of the most important aspects that we talked about all the time or just security so
At least they're they're thinking forward in that respect
They are and they're one of the companies that it CES
Add a smart home suite of products out on display
This is probably
Good I don't know who makes telstra's gear
These are the kind of things that I'm going to be looking for is to or the providers to the
Terriers and security firms
Chinese
Are they startups
Which startups are actually good enough to make it into these systems or being good enough
Question of some control
These are things that are
This this year is going to be a big
For iot
In this function
Keep an eye on it
Ok
Also international news
Nest
Has God for more European
Countries
They are now in
Germany
Austria Italy
In spades
They're already in the UK
And basically this just
Pushes them out
Further into
I wonder that end I'll just say yes this is part of alphabet which one's Google and I
Nashville time
Consult for Google so I can get that out of the way
I wonder what
Has taken so long as you think it's privacy laws in those countries that need to be mitigated or
I'm so glad you are
Fat look at that it's not even on the show
And I just asked the right question
Yuan
That's why you're the host
Arco home
All right
So I think one of the issues here
Where is
Regulatory
Not just privacy but also
Getting things through the
Different countries versions of the FCC
And the reason this is kind of interesting to me is because when I was at CES I spoke
With a bunch of
Companies from like the France Tech Pavilion
And all that
And they were talking about they're not available here in the US the products aren't available in the US but they're working their way through the app
CC's process
That provides a lot of stumbling
Gymnastics
Is pretty professional
They're not like a starter
They probably can get through but
These things take time
And so
I don't know what this is
Good bad buddy wants a lot of interference jacking up their existing system so I tend to agree that it's good
But
That regulatory hurdle can take
Obviously not like Hardware Supply there's plenty of those products being billed as just getting through to like you
Correct spelling of the regulatory agencies that are specific to each country
And I can't say I'm up on the latest frequencies The Clash over
Yogurt making me use I don't know
If there's something that
A typical Nest product uses that interferes with an everyday thing over there but
Still seems like a long time
Does an end you know they also have to hire
Company-specific support
If you're in Italy you probably don't do your customer support
PriceRite localization care
So
Challenges
This is a market
Where you're going to have to have a fairly large Footprints so you're probably going to want to go to places
Where you can
Build up your bar kit
Easily and quickly so that means smaller countries
May miss out on some products from startups
Eddie House
Moving right along
Let's move from International
Enterprise iot
What we have here is this week is NRF National Retail Federation
Conference event
They called The Big Show the NRF Big Show cuz I was there yesterday at it
Did you see anything
I didn't have a lot of time I did see a lot of I did see a lot of exciting things interesting no retailers
They're looking for ways to be in a booster
Foot traffic in stores looking for ways to
What do we attract customers
Where they are in the store
How much engagement they have with a particular product or aisle
Even emotions
Cameras that will
Take a look at customer spaces and try and
Determine
How happy were disappointing people are in products or displays it
There's a lot of stuff going on there you wouldn't sink
Retail is glitzy in that respect but there's a lot going on Beyond the Sea
Use the word glitzy there
Retail is glitzy
What we actually what was interesting here is the keynote for the NRF
Event was Brian krzanich the CEO of Intel
A hundred million dollars
Investing in retail
They also announced basically
It's a gateway
It's a Gateway lots of words but they all come down to this it's a Gateway it's a gateway
But the Gateway run software and idea of the software is Intel's trying to link these
Just for it retail systems into one intel-powered
Platform
Compute inform
Right now you might have
You know what Appliance or device that measures emotion
And you
That goes into 1
Place and then if you want that you got to go to that one
One place until trying to do is bring
The emotion track
The inventory tracking all of this into one platform
Support fraud
DIY spaces
I saw a lot of
Plays at that a lot of
Black puppies trying to
Bring cohesive solutions to
Manage and analyze all the data that these disparate systems
Capture
So that was a big theme I thought at the show
And that'll be a big scene
For everyone
Probably till the end of time
Cuz
A lot of
These systems right now
Are silos
Solutions
If I appoint device and then you're like oh no I want to get together with these guys have been
So
This is going to be
Increasingly important as
Retailers are
They're shutting down locations there
Having to really boost
The amount of money they make
Per square foot
They also are dealing with
You know hired labor cost
I said I really want to reduce
I'm guessing
But they will say they want to make each employee
Efficient and they can do that
Giving equipping them with more data and insights about the customer
So basically the goal is to make
The retail experience in-store alot
Higher ed
Mixer
80%
House off of Anna
And it's not because I haven't
But
It's just easy and I hate to shop
So
We saw Intel making this announcement I actually talked to zebra
Which is a zebra Technologies it's a
It's well-known for RFID
And this one is kind of tied into tracking inventory and tracking
Can customers
So actually they could end up possibly
Sending data to
System
This actually has some cool stuff
Because it's RFID tags
In the clothing or in the inventory
But it's also got these
Overhead
So
Right now
A lot of people think of iot in retail and they think of
Beacons Bluetooth based beacons
But basically in even talking to Intel RFID is still King
Because it doesn't need power for one thing it's small can be
Attached to practically anything you know all of your inventory so
It just economically make sense I'm not saying it's the best solution but it's one that still work
Intel also showed off something
Really cool which is a 3D printer for
That was kind of annoying.
My voice but I was really excited it prints
Prince clothing
This is business futuristic
And I'm really
Once
Retailers have this data am I going to get something crazy like smart mirrors that I look
I can see my clothes and
Suggestible things
Or is it going to be a little bit lower key
Would like the Apple Store
Play has like a tablet and they just come through and they're like oh I see you're doing this you know
This might also look good on you basically
Football scenarios because some customers want that handheld experience not handheld device
Not literally but
Store associate to walk them through and have personalized shopping
With assistance and some people just want to
Engage in the product themselves and figure out what's best for them and
And we saw that the smart mirror I think three years ago at CVS where
Literally stand in front of it and it would show you wearing different clothes of your choice based on your hitting a button
Superimposing the clothes to see what you look like in some people want that so I think
Retailers will Embrace both
I would like that in my home
Yeah
Amazon show me what this looks like
Sunday Sunday
Pictures are
All right
Hey you guys asked for us to talk about the Nvidia Shield
And I was kind of like
What
We can do that
But we can cuz Kevin went out and bought one
Incentive
Kevin such a sucker
I forgot it
That was the subjects I was going to say that out loud I think we all know
So tell us about the shield
I'm going to start off with something not negative but if I'm going to come out and say if you already have an Nvidia Shield
Shield because this came out 2 years ago originally
You don't need to buy a new Nvidia Shield
And I say that beat
Cause
Even though Nvidia at CES unveiled a new Shield
It's actually the same internals the new one in the in the old one
So if you have one
Don't
By 1 about a car to buy a new one because
With a software upgrade you going to get all the features that the new one has
And the reason it didn't really smarter than today I thought the reason didn't upgrade
They don't need to
The Tegra chip that they have in the original and now the new one again
Has plenty of horsepower to actually
Stream and show 1080p video no problem
4K video no problem 4K HDR video no problem
I don't have any crtv I do have a 4K TV antenna hooked up the shield
And the TV playback.
Fantastic
Television streaming in the house is done
I use PlayStation Vue for my
Typical channels in an Amazon Netflix and so on
There was coming in 4k in 4k HDR now for Amazon so on so forth so
So from that perspective it's good
It's
Interesting also because
A it runs
Android TV the latest version of Android TV
And so it's got built-in voice recognition we talked about that earlier with Sonos
So you can use the remote
Corby game controller and searches by voice
OK Google Now type information
But the interesting thing from an outie perspective I think
Is that a video said we're going to bring Google Assistant to this
And
Because you're not always in the same room as your Shield
We're going to sell these little $50 plug-in modules that basically are microphones that you put throughout your house
And some people say why
Always listening
Some people do want that those that do will have access to Google Assistant
3DS little plug-in module
Really really intelligent
Real intelligent so
Trent Lott
Eventually if I have
Is more things get connected to
Google home
I could be able to
How to control it
The Shield
That is the idea
Absolutely
Would be no different than having an actual Google home
Hardware device were using your
Phone is Google assistant is supported which strain has the pixel and the pixel XL so
Yasso
But do the phone version the home version or the
Aloe version
Well the phone version is the same as the home version by and large
I know there's a there's a couple little things that are different
And then a low as you mentioned
Cuz people don't know you can tag Google I can say at Google and any
Chat with you
Your friends on Allo
And you get the Google Assistant Smart in the conversation so like Stacy if you and I are chatting
And we happen to be in the same city and say it was get some
Dinner somewhere we can add
At Google not chat say at Google
Find me the closest barbecue restaurant that has 4 stars or better
And boom it'll just give us both that information that we have maps and reviews and thoughts
Real quick just in case there's a game around
They're just in case
The other reason I got I bought the shield is because
It offers
The Nvidia GeForce now
Subscription for $8 a month first month is free
Where they actually run
Console games on PCS or servers in the cloud and
Stream them to you in real time
No download
So I was playing at 1080p 60 frames per second
Version of Tomb Raider on the shield from Xbox
Indistinguishable between the shield and the Xbox all the difference is
On the shield it's all running in the cloud
It's neat
The thing is you got up
Here the caveat is
That if you're going to stream games from GeForce now at 1080p 60 frames a second
They look incredible would you also need an incredible connection for that base a 50 megabits per se
Second is what they recommend
And that's like
Even even with my 150 Meg service here
I occasionally see some
Some jagjit and stuff like that going on occasionally
So
Your mileage may vary
Your mileage may vary if it mean if your on something some slow internet don't even think about it
So how much is The Shield
The Shield is 199 which is the same as it was
A year or two ago
Debuted
The difference is another smart move
There including the remote and there are
Including the game controller both of which have a microphone
Before you had to buy at least one if not both of those separately for like
40 bucks a pop
50 bucks a Pop Evil
So
You're getting that now
Included
I'm glad you mentioned this though
Remember how I started by saying you have an old Nvidia Shield don't upgrade cuz you don't need it cuz you're going to get all the same software the
Voice remote start
Built into the game controllers you may want to get a new
Controller
For your old Shields I'm going to give him mine
Got it
All right
Feel like we're out of time
So I'm going to do a pretty quick review of stringify to tell you about it
And then we'll spend some more time another show
So stringify
Is
Kind of like it's a way for you to connect lots of devices together and create what they call flows which are
Basically recipe
Puppies for
Making something
So the reason this is
Cool are useful as they finally released an Android version
Now the Android version is still in beta
And so it's not as full functioning at the iOS version
If you're really into the smart home and you have a bunch of devices it supports a lot of devices like
30 or 40 that I have
And then it also supports more than one conditional statement so you know where if this and that you have to do
There's no limit
What you do is you
Bring all of the devices in onto what they call it
And if you do download this I really recommend you watch the video on
On how to do this because it is
It's not super into
So the video on how to make flows is
So you pick all of your devices and let's say
I want to do
Think of something to do
Okay
When my Nest cam
She's a person
And I'm not at home
Send me an email
And also turn on the light
So that doing that and if this
Would take
Multiple redis
So here what I would do as I pull in my Nest cam
I told him my location
Little icons for each device
Accolade my location icon
And I'm going to put those on
The left side everything
Goes from left to right here
And then I'm going to also the things I want to have happen
Email icon and then
What am I doing I'm going to pull in the light
So then basically set a trigger for each of those so location is when I'm away
When I see a person
On the other side
I'm going to set triggers for each of those
And then I basically link them I just remove
Click on that icon and then I move it over to each of the
Things that I want to have happen
When something happen
Decrease bass strings between them in
I created a fairly complex
End
This again
You're going to have to play with this I'm going to do a review eventually they will have
Screenshot
Really helpful
This is free
They support you know things like the echo the Aesop
Arlo netatmo
Nest
Like an amazing array of services I think ecobee
They don't do Sonos
So just
Telling you there
Skybell
Don't know if they do August
It's a pretty comprehensive system
It's free the way they pay for it is they actually do the same sort of thing for Enterprise customers and
Those guys actually
So yeah so instead of the Enterprise have to
Figure out all the apis for all these devices and
Sing themselves they actually do this for Enterprise customers they give
Like corporate it Department
These flows and support devices
Antos
Systems
So that they don't actually charge they just pull a PS4
Like for the Facebook and web-based ones they usually just pulled like the
Publicly available apis
10 + 4
The device
They actually usually
Conversation with
That makes it okay
Interesting model business model
It is like
I encourage anyone who's got multiple devices who's interested in
More complicated
Smart home programming to check this out
And it still bare bones
On the Android side
IOS is better and they're still features that they need to add
That'll come
Cool
Stringify
Now
Jose
Toodaloo
From our sponsor
But
Don't go anywhere because several guests
We're going to talk about the industrial internet
Where it's at today
How companies can bring in several vendors
And even advice for companies who are
Just starting to work with some of these big
Providers and how they can keep their pricing at margin
Staple it's going to be good
Everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor this way sponsor is dead
And I have Ivan O'Connor who is head of iot
Action point
Technology
To talk about
Action point and their partnership
Custom software developer
We also write all the software
So what are your tips for a successful iot partnership
What are the same size
Facebook
I would always trying that
Activity
Awesome what are some iot use cases that you're sick
Text
In the broad area of water
We have
Use cases
We have use cases
Waterfalls
Italian Festival
They're sending their Engineers into
Stop
What's the temperature
You are as well
Find example
Call me
Toledo Costco Palm City
Sausage
We also installed a Dell Edge Gateway so that will be connected to the cold
What we're doing is saying
Temperature
Ilocos Arenal alarm condition
Detailed reports can be Santa
To the line managers SMS alerts can be sent
Boston SMP Centex septic
Ivan it sounds great
So where can I find
You can put on information you need from
Dot-com
Which is our URL
We have a lot of interesting iot case studies from there too
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Things podcast this week in a little bit different for you
I've got three guess
From a visit I took to the National instruments
Lab
So this is an industrial iot lab
Where I learned about a lot of crazy cool things and I talked to Jamie Smith the director
Instruments
An Alex devron CEO
Alex had the lovely Irish lilt
Voice
So I'm Jamie Smith on the director of embedded systems here in Nashua
Aaron the Chief Executive Officer of
All right today we're here
Launching their industrial internet-of-things lab
Which you guys maybe like
There's actually so many people playing Industrial internet-of-things
Figuring out how to get everything to work together
Is
So let's kick this off with
Question about Partnerships
IC HP
So I thought until disco there's a lot of people here
How to companies
Bring you in
Are they bringing you in a massive conglomeration
Or
Are they bringing you in
That's a really good question
Because it is a large number of collaborators
These complex systems
And the customer engagements happen in a wide range
So what natural is expert in measure
Technology
Processing right there at the edge
Where sensors are coming into the
The industrial
Thanks
And all the collaborators we work with are aware of
So when their customers and their engagement
Additional sensing capability additional measurements or some form of advance
Troll right there at the edge still bring us in
Location
So where is
Your Edge
Because he could be a Gateway or it could be like that
Really good question as well that will redefine The Edge know if we think about or a traditional definition
And it's where the
Enterprise Network begins and is the barrier to the office Network
Home network begins or is it
Valerie to the internet service provider
That's the typical Edge boundary
I just got back from CVS
MSc industrial internet
Consumerism
Low margin
Blah blah blah
Where is the industrial internet
Where is it going
So the industrial internet today it's happening
Distributed systems in becoming more open
More complex
And collaboration of or vendors drysol
Inside
But the majority of Industries and companies
Have not adopted
So we're just getting started
Scratching the surface
But we're seeing a lot of interest
And
Indiana
Technology stocks
Becoming validated
Chest pains like we have in the lab
And if we can educate more of these and customers about
Then they can start doing a pilot
Program
And they move on
Broader adoption
Spaghetti.
Insights
Required
When you guys actually like to talk about your
Because that ties to a couple things he's mentioned already one is it
They didn't have anything
And now they have with a 30000 sensors
How did that come about
End
Is there a typical
I would say there is no typical yet
Industrial air
Duke Energy is the largest
Power provider
United States and
They
Realize that they can improve
Overall up time
All of their facilities they have more
They had
Experts in
Analysis of this vibration database rotini
Equipment
But they spent 80% of their time
Data collection
20% of their time analyzing
The database
They want to flip that
So they put an effort out to
Measurement taking
It's been 80%
Their data
Ensuring uptime
LS timing chain
How is the data collected
So the data was collected originally by walking around
Portable measurement equipment
Add capturing information that they needed to be transferred into a spreadsheet or another application
Now these systems
Online always acquiring
Connecting to the network
Defeat
Air plant Astoria
So there
Look at that data
Crafts to build on that to you know when we look at some of this aging infrastructure that's probably not on
The world
Part of the data collection process use that many of these large power plants
Is the human
And it can literally get a simple or a sophisticated
I'm going to touch
Machine to feel the vibration
And I'm going to listen to it
As a data collection and
Any customers in the similar situations are experts at doing this also
Tend to be getting a little older
And headed towards retirement
And they're worried about the ability to be able to replicate.
So as we
Deliver technologies that make it practical to
To be able to collect that data
In a synchronized fashion
Securely ideally
Future over wireless network
And then we developed story
Ability from a prognostic view
To record the symptoms of an impending
Future failure downtime
And that learning can be learned once and applied many times
In an automated fashion to dramatically
Iraq time zone
Answer the customer that also dramatically improve their use of energy
Which is an interest
All of these partners
How do you guys
Wright contract
Sell the product in a way
Ensures you guys
Get the value for what your
Massive numbers of companies
It just feels very.
We as a company Nestle
I've always
Operated as part of an ecosystem
Where are the ultimate end solution
Involved
Strom multiple suppliers
To be delivered
Tool supplier in the system supplier to scientist
So this has been our standard business model in r
Testing measurement market and we've applied this to as we've expanded our capability outings
That's a first of the business model is really clear
Hermosa apartments that we're engaging with
It's relatively well understood their portion in value chain
And ultimately the customer will decide
Some situations like Duke Energy the customer will choose
To purchase components from different
Kalamazoo Valley training
And that's a valuable use case
In other cases the customer want to
Just have one in Topeka
To deliver that complete value chain
And in that situation in a We have dealt with that is a business for many years and have a
I really clear way to to Castro Valley
City of tips for companies who are kind of it
There's a coming out this for maybe the first time
Well it certainly understanding your value and the solution is the single most
Understanding have differentiated your value is not have differentiated you'd like it to be or you might want it to be but a different you
It actually is
Can you get that from the customer to get that work
I think you get that from the customer absolutely
You know some cases it can get clouded
We have a great benefit because we also have a direct field Salesforce
So we have direct access to the customer
We sell to over 35000 different companies
Around the world every year
And we have deep relationships that the engineer to end
Engineer
And so our value
Is generally relatively well understood already
Two core constituencies within that customer
And that helps provide the frame of reference
House divided
A benchmark for us
To be able to
Engage with
A complete system level provider so my advice and Ensure
Would be understand your value understand how differentiated it is
Truly
And I would try to establish a price position
Independent
Selling direct to individual customers
To be able to validate my first two assumption
And be able to prove both to the End customer and my
Immigration partners
The value that I bring
Tomorrow
I would think also your relationship with engineers
Is important
As we seen in clouds
Developers are awesome
End
There's a lot more respect now for
On the industrial side is that same sort of
It may not be Grassroots but it might be respect for the technical
Absolutely
Ways we look at I-10.
Converging
The people will understand the problems and needs
Address of those on the fact
Where are the plants
In the field with the customer
So they understand
Needs what
Chang
But they may not have the insights in Denver
Information technology
Analytics Cloud technical respect
Pyside
Novation
Bad it's becoming
Clear that these groups
Together
And I would say that's the biggest shift I've seen
Look at the first part of my career
National instruments
There was
A desire for
Companies to provide freestyle over
Close systems to own the entire solution
And in some cases even hold a customer
Today those
Barriers are being broken down and companies are supplying to
Customers
Have a willingness in a desire to collaborate
And the customers are demanding
And so as companies are evaluating what move to make for the industrial internet-of-things
End customers
The one piece of advice I would give to down
Is 2 don't wait
Put down your biggest challenge your biggest headache your biggest
Opportunities for improvement
Start working to see how you can address that issue
That starting point can blossom real impact
And then to the next project
Izzy's Transformations are not going to be
Enterprise why all of
And some people have that view and
You guys are the people who are going to make a difference
And you should totally be
So sad
And now go to Jim heppelmann the CEO of
GTC
We talked about how PTC is acquired several companies such as
Xidan
Vuforia from Qualcomm
And kept where
Alta build
A platform for the internet of things called thingworx
Oh yeah
And it also
Acquired thingworx
So I checked in with Jim to find out
How a year later
Those Acquisitions were performed
Division is alive and well
Business is doing exceptionally well
Machine learning and Predictive Analytics
Find out what we need to know and then to be able to turn around using augmented reality
And kind of decorate your view of that will physical world
Important digital information
AR is less
Service technician
I think we're where the early days of AR
Screwing
Do this a scam
The big thing now is the digital eyewear
As the July where becomes better
And a little more ubiquitous
That will unleash a wave they are
And we need to explain it
And there's no better way than to make it visual
Linda put it in context of the physical world
So I think we're we're at the edge of the big toe
There is substantial breakthroughs happening with digital eyewear I mean the Microsoft hololens
Unbelievable
Snapchat spectacles
What we need is this going to be something like this smartphone which
Super spring in
Technology
Industrial-grade
She just heading to consumer-grade pretty quickly I think Microsoft is targeting
What's happening right now as consumers are using
Phones and tablets
As a proxy
4 spyglass
Do you actually get the same experience the downfall is it ties up your hands
Social service technician
Can I use a tablet or a phone to see what they need to see
They were just work
Fluidly
Without interruption because their hands
So in a sense I'm going to go crazy
Voice for the iot
Is Kai.
Telling you information for the Internet of Things
You're saying vision
Computer generated AR is going to
I like it
That brings up another point which is if the pictures on in contacts
Can you have to do a mental mapping
Is what happens to you in the car all the time when your navigation system in your dashboard says turn left on this street
Play was it
You look down to the windshield
And it's a
Process requires a fair amount of
And then if I could
You know hemispherical view of the world where I can look up down left right
So basically I'm saying is if we can figure out with smart glasses
How to decorate the world
Your aunt's room you're in
What information do you need to know about the
Your ability to ingest that information
Literally
It would be to read it off
Screen of your phone
It's a big idea of iot
Chris so much data so much knowledge
Physical world that you can't see
You look at it in the computer and then mentally map it
We just want to decorate what you see
What you need to know
So that feels like we need some sort of standard
14 Mattapan
I'm not a hundred percent sure if it needs to be a standard but I think we definitely need techniques
What did you think about
User interface development on computers
Microsoft has a set of techniques apple has a slightly different set of techniques and other vendor might be slightly different
There are good practices for developing grassley's Renovators in bed rack
If we move down with the AR prices
It's just the wild west end
Definitely
State-of-the-art
This well
And hopefully using familiar paradigms
From one device to another
Like I can move from us
You don't Android phone to an Apple phone and they're not really that different
I can figure it out
Pretty quickly
Problems
Is the Amazon Echo
I like
I can only imagine that if I switch from
Is it is not as big a deal in industrial
I think the whole idea they are is to make information Visual and a coil
What to put in contacts
So that you can actually process it without thinking
Driving your car you pull up to a stop light
Stop look and say oh
That looks like a stoplight
Shred
Red means stop
Okay there for me to stop you just do it what are some
Mercy
Directions
I didn't receive last thing first of all it's a powerful idea
Many many demonstrations approve that
People are far more productive
And make mistakes
So I think there are
Mini case studies now
From PC and from various others the show
Norma
Reason I don't see they are Belong Together.
Because they are Death Race
Physical world
Decorated with what
We need information from the physical world
An understanding
What is the
Addition
What is the status what is the action you should take
How do I convey that status in
Addition to you and then how do I convey to you
Right because right now
Information
I can tell you how many steps I've taken I can tell you
The temperature
That does me no good without being a
I'll take any sort of
So
If you think back to driving a car
You have a navigation system
Can you have the music
And if I could cherry-pick the information for the navigation screen and give you a heads up display
On the windscreen
Not to say
There are three roads coming up and you should take the
The second one
What to actually say see this road right here
Of course if you think now
Fighter pilots have had
Heads up displays for a long time
So if we could
Ocean of the
Heads up display
Put it on everything
People
Furniture
Industrial objects Farm
Give you a heads-up display on everything simply by putting on her glasses and everything you interact with
Has a heads-up display optimized for interacting with that thing
I think it's a big part 1
Savannah would be like this is a person
Business
Oh we don't have enough standards we don't have it
Anythink
Okay if I engage you in a social context
If I'm your doctor I want to have a completely different perspective of Stacy
Even though I might
Let's talk about
Security because
What we're talking about here
The number one reason
Companies say that they're not
What should baby
I think this notion of iot being a new set of security problem is wrong
It's the same security problems we have
It's just more things are computers
Right now and we're extending them to things that you didn't think of it
More and more
These things in our computers week
Play did you think of a power plant you know
Computer control
I think the security
There's no CIO that can save my data center is safer than it was 10 years ago
They just can't really say that
They might have invested a tremendous amount in technology and techniques and practices.
More secure
We just in an open-ended battle
What is going to be the big things
This year in a day
But I'm saying in our business is back
Has always been automated dirt or have been
What's happening now if people are saying
So much more
And get it so much more data
That would be useful in automation
And I could
Around what is this
Telling me
But I think I think what's happening is people are
Our business is going very well
And you ask what's driving most of that growth
Laser Pilots
Because people are just getting started a lot of the pilots are graduating
Into
Modified business you know real orders from real customers right now
I think I said that our last earnings call that last year half of our Revenue
Customers who were coming back for more
That's it for this week's show but please remember to join us next week on the Internet of Things podcast
And thank you for listening also if you do what more information don't forget to go to Stacey on iot
T.com and sign up for the Weekly News
Is letter
See you next week