Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And here is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And I'm recording the show from the Sonny &
Get still foggy confines of San Francisco where I am at Intel's developer forum
And Kevin
Where are you today
I am not at IDs I am in hot muggy Southeastern Pennsylvania
That's a real shame
San Francisco
I love it there
Awesome
Okay so
This week we've got a couple things to talk to you about we've got
Google's brand new
Actually I should say newly discovered
Operating system
Fuchsia
We got
Intel's iot strategy
I got a question about robots and we're going to do a review on my Brita pitcher that refills at
The Amazon
Replenishment program
We also have our guest is
A woman most of you guys probably know as lawyer Liz on Twitter is
Liz Wharton
And she's going to talk about some of the legal aspects of the internet
Things
But first we need to do a word from our sponsor looking for ways to keep your designs a step ahead of your
Predators learn the latest in iot in embedded systems design at this year's arm techcon in Santa Clara California
Three days of technical talks Keynotes and Exhibits begin October 25th at the Santa Clara Convention Center here in sites
Turn leading-edge designers in iot embedded software Graphics silicon design and networking Advanced registry
October 14th to register for arm techcon 2016 visit arm techcon. Com
Today on October 25th through the 27th now back to our show Kevin
Let's see
I think we should hit the fuchsia stuff first so we can get your disclosure out of the
The way what do you think I think that would be wise since we're going to talk about some
Newly discovered Google
Efforts I do work for Google I do not work on
Anyting development-related so I don't have direct knowledge or any impact of what we can talk about
But I'm happy to share my thoughts on what's been reporting what's been found
There we goes
Last week it looks like some
Or maybe it was earlier this week time flies when you're traveling
People discovered
The Google heaven
Dropping some code into GitHub
And
The phrase that they
Hit Upon was pink plus purple
Equals fuchsia
A new operating system
And so
The best article
We found so far is from the Android Authority
Who actually took the code and started running it
And they discovered
Couple things
The big thing about fuchsia is that it uses the little kernel
Okay
And magenta LK is a really tiny OS
I'm for embedded devices sothink
How small should we think it's an artist's right
I would say that's accurate
Okay
It looks like an artist
Which is
Is a real-time operating system designed to run on
Really tiny
Memory Footprints in really tiny battery
Powered usually devices
Okay
And
There is also a
It says on an embedded arm platform the core of LK is typically just 15 to 20 KGB
That's crazy
That's really small
Crazy smoke crazy tiny so we're talking
So magenta
Is bigger
It could
Even require gigabytes of memory
Don't know
Allow something at peripherals
And it looks like if I'm looking at this and I asked your opinion
It looks like Google has built
An operating system that could span
All the things from
Little tiny
Embedded devices all the way up to mobile 2
Computing
Does that feel right
That feels right that's what it looks like you know he's got
Google's built-in Stone Colonel which is interesting because Google has Bill price on the Linux kernel
Such as Android in Chrome for
And they're very obviously very popular
Used throughout the world
Is a small kernel like as you said
Decadron on something very very small and I'm looking actually on
The GitHub right now where there's documentation from Google and explains
Bok
Colonel Kush
Clearance small systems with limited Ram a fixator for a real Sandy bounded set of tasks
So
Small devices single-purpose devices perhaps maybe sensors who knows
Certainly I would think that's a good fit for iot type devices
Magenta the other hand
Could I get them ready traffic from GitHub stock notation
Target's modern phones and modern personal computers with fast processors non-tribal events Ram
With arbitrary preference during open-ended computation so
That way
Resume scaling up to Everyday devices that we use
So
You don't based on that I think your tribulations
Sounds good for now
But so let's let's think about this
Why does Google need
A new iOS like I mean it does need
They've talked about
Google had launched
Was it nest with weave and thread but Google had something that was also we've and there was another one
Hello
So
That looks like it might be kind of
NOS an artisan NOS for the in
Thanks so
I'm kind of like will cash where does this fit in with that
Going a step further with
With that thought I mean the whole Brillo thread weaved it was very IRT specific
And could not I would think scale up to running regular say consumer or business devices
Where is what I'm reading here on
This combination of Elkay magenta
AKA fuchsia would actually run on the smallest of
Devices all have two usable devices that we
Carry around
But you wouldn't necessarily I mean Brillo supposed to be Googled OS for iot devices on
With microprocessors
So
Is confusing
Inlets
Rillo actually I'm looking at some of the data from
Google
IO event
Brillo devices need a minimum of 35 make
That's it for today
Yeah so that's like a
Alright that's not the kind of thing
Yeah that is not
Okay
Well gosh I feel a little bit more
Confused I'm glad I know this is out here
I would love to have some sort of unifying code Bayside
I can think of advantages to that
I'm any other thoughts you have Kevin
Something else I noticed from
What gender is hard to get in actually anybody could use any of our listeners could go to get heaven
Build fuchsia and run it themselves at and its current state
Because it is open source
I noticed when they ran
And got it running rather got the build running
There were some included apps
And all of them were written with dart which is Google's language introduced
How to say about 2ish years ago
How to be kind of like a JavaScript
Type of
Platform I know you can
Cross compile Dart apps into JavaScript so there's definitely
Are some some similarities there
What is that mean I don't know does it mean everything for fuchsia will be written in dark
Don't know this is early days so I think we're mentioned since there are very few major dark
Limitations out there
Relatively speaking compared to Java Java script and songs
Yes and it's listening
Where is hainan
A scale of one of the advantages of Dart is it super scalable is my understand
I I do not
Code so I do not
Cold and dark
Or anything else
I know that was a big deal for Google
In a big deal why they use at sew-in we do definitely need Super scalable languages for
IRT if we're talking about billions of devices
So
I don't no big mystery a big fuchsia mystery
We will
Wait to see what's up
So
Next cool story is
Intel
Here I am an idea Finn I was actually
A little disappointed in some of the stuff that I saw a round I wanted to see more cool
Iot things from them but the two big announcements that
Have the most impact the first is that
Intel has taken an armed license so it can manufacture
Arm chips
Hell hath frozen over
That's
Without
I love this
Yeah this is I think this is great because I mean Intel has been trying to crack the
Low power
Mobile market
Superchips for a long time ever since they saw a scale 10 years ago or whatever it was
And McDonald
A decent job with their atom processors and I would have had surgery and some other things
Clarks
Now if I'm reading this right and you were you're there so you can
Tell me if I'm wrong but my first take was
Wow if I'm a Qualcomm or a Samsung who is an arm licensee building chips for mobile devices
I'm a little worried because now I got a
Big competitor building
The same types of chips
Yes so if I were Samsung
I would especially worried because Apple probably
Looks at this and it's like
Oh
Hey
We need These Arm based processor cuz they're my phone chips in our base
Processor that
I don't know what a word
Is Samsung is one of their manufacturing Partners For That
Chip-in
They've had some back
Can 4th in the past over
How
They're working together when they were
To each other so
I would say that
This is great news
It also makes a lot of sense strategically
From Intel
Because it's
I mean they tried was Sophia and Adam
Printer just cut it they shut it down
That's fine
In what
This shows us is it until ripe
I think it shows is that Intel's willing to let the 50 billion devices
They're on the very edge of the network
Have
Whatever let arm have that
The ESPYs on those are pretty small Intel's not a fan of that style of selling
And then what they're going to do is the Gateway boxes at those those Edge devices talk to that's going to be in in
Intel inside
When you look at their Network
Working strategy
They are building boxes for
Carriers
With software-defined networking basically carriers
Can put in
Like instead of this proprietary Cisco and Erickson gear they can put in like
Intel-based servers that run all of the core networking
Concussion
Even has a radio Access Network
So I ran
Kind of chip
Effort I don't know how well that's going to go but they do have it and then all of that data get sent up to the cloud wear
Once again we've got you
Xeon Processor
I think it's very pragmatic of Intel to do this and it gets I think it's a smart move
They've sunk literally billions of dollars in losses
Trying to crack the mobile market
And the kind of signal they were getting away from that about a year ago or so and and now they
At this point
Monkey with arm that's fine
But
Let's be a part of it anyway at least in the chip manufacturing process
And they have to
Intellicast
Billions of dollars in their Fabs they spent billions manufacturing it
Freezy tiny nanometer levels like
Just ridiculous
This is a lot of money and now
Making their own ships couldn't fill up
The capacity they have
With PCS on the
ISO
Investing billions in in these fantasies
You know it's just not smart so now they changed
Model
So I'm loving it I'm feeling really good about it
Now that they bought the butter
Github nervana systems I think it was last week
Week or two weeks ago
And that's a really interesting machine learning platform that uses gpus
So
When you start looking this it feels like Intel's getting to this point where they're like you know what
X86 is good for some things but
Maybe we're going to open up the world
Kind of again he'll have Frozen
Kind of reminds me of Microsoft's changing point of view over the last two years as well
Oh that's a good analogy yes you just
But if it makes sense you have to change in this world or
You just go Absol
Nobody wants to be
Obsolete
Okay so here's a question for you Kevin
And our audience
Aruba
Part of the iot
Might guy
I mean there's a lot of ways to answer that it's a pretty open question but my gut is absolutely just based on
Sensor data that they can capture and communicate
I would say rather that yes
All right
Good then we can talk about Intel's other really cool announcement
And this is something I could sound like robots really open us up to a lot of cool stuff
They're definitely quote-unquote a thing
Pretty loose definition
But until
Project Euclid
So this is a realsense module so this is there
Computer vision
Sensor kind of effort
What did you just say created a
People are calling a candy bar sized it's
It's probably smaller than America
Actually
And this has a camera
It has
Accelerometers it has all kinds of stuff in it
What's really cool is it has this embedded development environment
You can come by and see me with an IDE and you can program with our Arduino or turtlebot
Witcher 2 robotic Frameworks
And you can like
Literally
Quick
Skills that you want this
Euclid
Device to enable
And then
You can build like a little apps on it and like 22nd
It's ridiculously cool
This isn't going to come out until the first quarter of 2017
We have no pricing
And
It's it's just this little stick and if you
Put it
You can put one in and create this like tiny little robot that follows you around
I I like the idea of using it
Discreet liquor
Suitcase that follows
Syllabi
So
I asked about battery life they said they have been running it
For about 45 hours straight
On like a little robot
Easy robot
Fatso
Again that's not a
So I think it's another example of
Until being pragmatic because they've had their real sense
Hardware out in fact I think
What are the Dell
Tablets had real Santa's running on an Intel chip
I was an Android tablet and you can use it to
Capture sensor data Dex from
Intestines in San Juan
There wasn't very many
Could a permutation of it except for very specific use cases maybe you know you're on the field as a construction worker
You need an exact measurement or something
This is a whole new Twist on the Developers
Hands and said
Here take us see what you can do with it
And let's build some apps quickly which
Pictures to see what people come up with
Me too
We'll have to wait
It's in developers hands
So you know what's
Eyes open I think someone's using it
Since B
There's a robot that does Inventory management
It does this
It runs along
Shelves in stores
And
It
Season
Figures out
If the shelves are stocked
After beads people spending 8 hours every night going around with barcode scanners and scanning inventory retail store
Assistant to do all that to me
I think that's a great use case
See although it does eliminate
People and that's actually been an undercurrent that I've heard a couple times here is
You know a lot of these things are going to take
Very menial jobs
So
We should we should never say robots eliminate people made jobs
You're right
I'm sorry
DARPA
They have something
Big Dogs 2
Unrelated note
This reminds me a lot of what
Project Tango is for Google only I haven't seen very much too in a way there limitation there either
But it's the same concept of
Sensors and so on I haven't
Heard any about Tango being put in robots and slash play
It's interesting that we got two major players
Going down this path let's see what they do the same what they do is different
Yes we will keep our eyes on that and I'm sure someone a Google has probably put Tango in a row but I'm sure people are Google put
All kinds of crazy things on robots
Okay
Let's go because we are a little pressed for time let's go to The Brita
Review
This is the Brita Infinity water pitcher it is wifi-enabled
It is tied to the Amazon Dash
Replenishment service in for $45 you get what is basically
It's a nice-looking Brita water pitcher
That tracks how much water you're running through the little Brita filter and then went in
You've run
More than 36 gallons of water in the pills the filters now compromised it will order a new one
Automatically
So I told you guys about this I did make one statement that wasn't quite true there is
So what's an inside of it is
A little module that's inside the lid inside that module is basically
Wi-Fi
And a sensor that says go the lids open
Are closed there's no ultrasonic sensor nothing that's measuring water level
It's basically every time you flip open the picture to fill it
Accounts that is
Smart
Counter so to speak it's not really monitoring how much water goes through the filter
Yes so I would
Quest to make this is like accurate as possible I did
Everytime I filled the picture it puts about
4 cups of water in
There's about 16 cups
Of water
Can a gallon so keep that in mind as I tell you what happened
So about
Loads in
So 30 times that I had refilled it
All of a sudden it went from
Hey you're good
Crap it's time to order another filter you
Views 36 gallon
Lono
So I was like yeah that's kind of wait no I have not
I have not used anywhere close to that
The filter at like the the lid open a while to let the water filter through
Ask the
Pretty guys if that made a difference
If they had any experience of people leaving it open and it kind of
Messing with the counter
And causing some
Causing it to blink jump ahead and they said no
So
I'm not sure what happened the ordering process was nice in the sense that you do get an email from
Vim Amazon
It says hey
Cheer picture just called in a Brita filter order
You got 24 hours to cancel
So
I didn't cancel it cuz I
Wanted to see the whole thing through so I didn't cancel it in
You know two days later a Brita filter arrived to my door I still hadn't gone through the next 4 gallons
Between 36 and 40 is when it
Send out the
Help sidebar filters
It over 40 it starts
Blinking red and saying
So
I did just get to the red that was after another
Phil's
Exodus 28 pills
So
I don't really know what to make of this the fact that you could cancel it and you can reset it
But I just kind of was like
This is not a win for me
And I'm not sure what happened
I wish I could know
It doesn't sound as smart as it
Cooter should be to me
Yes right if it's just
Counting
They say that the top being open and close
And assuming that you're filling up with xcalar next cups every single time
It's kind of like
They do tell you have to fill it every time to the max fill line
Which I complain about earlier I was like that is super hard to see
Black on black
It's a glossy black so you're like I hate
The other thing is I had to
Like sign in Via an app and register it and all of that
And I'm never going to use the app again but I was like
Know the process of
Opening an app to connect a water pitcher
It felt like if you can't manage your Brita water filter
With the stickers or just a sense of
It's three months or my water now tastes funny
I think it's probably a better way
Yeah I mean you could you could get a
Just a little
Counter app
Every time you fill it and get the plus one on
Monger that way yourself
You know it be accurate than at least try
It doesn't seem like it said in value for the automatic process because the automatic process does not
Sound accurate
That makes sense does not sound that well
In my experience it was not a cure
I will say though if you open it real fast and close it like
It doesn't count those
There's a visible flash on
The top when it's like
I have registered this as I feel
So that's that's a little nicer but still
That is my impression of The Brita Infinity
Wi-Fi
Connect a picture
We don't need that in our lives
It's not providing a useful enough
Function I would say
Not in its current state
How many Alamo from pruvit
Consideration
If it became a
Accurate
A Brita water
Picture is like 30 bucks
So
Jennifer $15 more it's not like a
Raising
I mean it is 50% more I guess so
Sky crazy I don't know
Your mileage may vary on the
1 guys
All right
Well
That is it for this portion of the show please stay tuned for our guest
Who is going to talk about
I know you guys are so excited to hear about you was
Terms of services
But we actually do have a good time talking about
Legal implications for company selling iot devices
And how soon we as consumers can expect data privacy laws or something to change
Everyone this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast with a big month
Developer conference for people making the internet
Things happen
Is annual conference in September brings together technologist and designers who build core infrastructure for iot plug
Happy that you'll see two days of expert speakers including me
Giving talks on everything from Bots to Industrial Automation
Machine learning to time series data programming language
2ux
As a special treat their also bringing back the famous thing monk Hackett
Sponsored by IBM
Still have a short Watson and Alexa skills Workshop to kick things off with no prior knowledge required
To learn more about the conference please visit
Www
. figma
Dot-com
Iot podcast blisters get a 20% discount code for any of the days or a combination of all three days
So to take advantage use the promotional code iot podcast when you register back to the show
Hey everyone welcome back to the
Internet of Things podcast
I am your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
What is
Blair Liz
Or as her full name is Liz Horton who is an attorney
Hall Booth and Smith
And hi Liz how are you doing today
Hi Stacy doing well how are you
I am great
So
I have like two weeks in a row that we're going to have people who are at Defcon here but
I should also mention if you like
What Liz has to say you should check her out on her own radio show which is buzz off with lawyer lives at America's web radio
All right
So all of our
Marketing and exciting stuff out of the way let's get
Right into it
You
Are both a contract attorney
And dealing with all kinds of other things with the IRT and you're also really involved in this community and have been for
A decade so let's go with what you think the most important issue is
Companies today
Who are trying to embrace the intern
Infrasonic thank you for
Invited me onto the show today and for
Mentioning the buzz off show but
How many zits
Really getting them to wake up
Fence Pekin
Realize
That
Well everything is connected
That opens up
All kind of issues that they would have never had to
Look at Ford Imports
Upgrading the software on different devices patching
That
There are risks of now your network is exposed
3D devices
That the convenience factor and you're great
Connections with everything in the
Internet of Things by the same time there additional risk
Hidden Easter eggs hidden traps
So you and your last shower most recent show said
Used actually Delta and their recent
Crazy all of their computer systems
As an example of
I have one of these things
Do you want to explain that
Thanks it
Become one of those
Things where
Delta hide one thing went wrong
And
Where you would have been
Back-to-back ups and
Stale face
All of those failed as well
And
It serves as a good reminder
What happens when everything is connected and you're relying on one
That you need
To have
Segmentation
That
It with your home network if you're bringing your work laptop home connecting on
And it's the same network
That you're running your
Netflix account
The Rays that your coffee maker
That your printer is running through that
When one of those systems
Is or can be compromised
Impact all of that
And
Setting up at it really just setting up those separate
Okay so yes I talked to the security people in the past or like
You should have
Separate networks one for your
Security system
One for your work stuff and then to computer switch
Hawthorne heavy depending on where you're how you're carrying them around exactly
So
This is also a but this is a good point because Target actually had when they had their massive
Data breach of their point of sale systems
The people came in through the hpac system
Which
You know how to become connect
So that's that's a good thing to remember
Will from the legal standpoint to you as a lawyer and he does come out and play
You're now at risk
Yes
You're not because you're aware that
That's happened to other so now that everyone
Noah's battle Target was breached
That's how
Different companies have similarly suffered
Their data breaches
Do you then have a duty
Two pizzas for cautions
At the very least
In your office that you can't control necessary the environment
Outside of your office
But
Just a reminder that
Has it created
Legal liability if you're not
So speaking of legal liability
I have a question for
For you cuz this is something
I think
It's going to be a bigger issue soon
So right now we with our connect
Two devices
We tend to
Buy device put it in our house download the app
Click on a terms of service agreement
Arrow that says
It this explodes or if this does something leaks my data nobody's responsible
Arbitration
So I do not
But as I
Some of these devices like maybe my car or a security system
Really feels like
There's this other legal regime
Where people are responsible
Take the people making products are responsible for building things safely and securely so they don't kill you are we going to get
Get to a point where these two regions Collide and
How is that going to be media
If you already have an entire new anytime you turn on the TV
Depending on if it's late at night you get that
Commercials
Have you been injured by this product
There is an entire product liability
Legal Market
Universe
And
Dot is
Starting to bleed into
The direction you're absolutely right it's just
Federal Trade Commission
FTC
That FDA are looking at
All of these
Device isn't saying no no no no no
You have
Some basic
Duty
To create something that you know isn't broken it at all that you can't escape that liability
Bye
Including that in your eulogy
Clean out your terms of service
Ear drainage especially with people don't have the opportunity
Negotiate.
It's
Take it or leave it but same time there you had a basic duty to create something that you knew it was broken
Or want you to come to where you have to recall
Okay
Actually came out a couple weeks ago with this kind of concept
It was after the nest
Issue were Nest pulled the revolved
The people that purchased in basically just shut the whole thing
Think down the FTC looked at that and they cleared them
But they did write this blog post that talked about guy she'd are you selling a device are you selling a service how do you how are you
You guys marketing these
Products
I bought for you because I think it's
It's going to be a big issue
It depends on what we're talking about if we're talking about
A device
Failure for example you're seeing at some of the card
That is fair
On board
Systems are there
Systems fail
That was different than is usually what we could match work
You got multiple components
And you're seeing
FTC and FCC
Waiting into privacy issues as well
And
This two agencies are really trying to figure out
Who gets to control that then if it's
The device that
Feeling
Then
That I need to Trade Commission
Is it
The
Information that's being communicated
The data
Aurrera service
Connecting through being broadcaster
Through the internet
That's where you're seeing the fight between the two
Ever have to get to set the rules
And
I don't see it clearing up any time soon when you're talking about
Budget
And
Really a 40 cuz everyone wants
To have the final say
Because with the final stage of the bigger budget
Bright
How is a consumer
Do you think this will affect me let's go out 2 years the idea of
Product safety and what I'm signing what kind of Rights I'm signing away do you think that will change within the next
2 years
I think it will change
I don't know
The vehicle through which it will have changed
I didn't volunteer regulation or a lawsuit
Exactly
Then
Tongue and cheek joke
That
We met
When
I'm chatting with
Some of the Regulators on issues with drones
Is
Well
It's going to be the lawyers and the insurers who drive the chain
Because
As soon as something goes wrong an inch are going to have to deal with whether they're going to cover it what defense of the
Operation as soon as they're paying money out of pocket
And then
Unfortunately the lawyers
I'm going to jump in and say well we have
Quiet your injured
Order representing the interesting
This is your own fault
How will we hear you didn't text. So
The Warriors
The insurers
And through that will either push the regulators
To address it if it doesn't get fixed AR or the manufacturers
You're seeing in the automobile industry there is some
Slow movement with the
Auto manufacturers
Being willing to put in place
Certain
Checks and balances of system pictures how to report
Here's how we're going to do our six-year-old development
But that's taking years to get there
And all they've really done is just put out proposals
You haven't seen it
Surfing in Palma de chat so
2 years out
Is it going to be different I just don't know how through one of those mechanisms
Yeah I can imagine a law getting passed
10 to years
Okay
You mention drones and I know that's a special area that you focus on
And you were telling me
Just the act of flying drones and starting to collect data
We could probably I don't know if we could you can tell me can we play that two sensors like
How to clean sensors around
That opens up this whole area of
Legal responsibilities that
Udo municipalities
Normal citizens may be news organizations they just start thinking about that so
Any kind of talk about some of those legal issues that
You know might open up
Between drones and all the sensors
Collecting a lot of
Data
That you don't
Think about
And with that data it has value to
Nefarious actors are just other parties
And suddenly you're having to look at
Your
Cyber security
Liability policies because
You're downloading that data
Maybe you're deleting it
But
.
Because of right target environment
Or
If you're collecting personal and pii
And you're storing it
And somebody
Lease a laptop in their car
Suddenly
You're having to deal with a breach whereas
Before you were flying does
Aircraft are using a sensors you didn't have to worry about some of that
Okay so
Bigger surface area that you may not even be aware of
Is one of the issues and what about let's let's talk about pii because
What I think people are starting to become aware of is that really means nothing
Because as you get more data about
People
You can actually drive who they are
In create pii
From
Maybe a few data points that aren't protected under the
Exactly
One of the other
Probably if you have enough information that perhaps
Isn't considered as you
Noted in a considered pii onto itself
Because you don't have that other
Breaking that you can go on someone's Facebook on their Twitter feed
On any of their social media accounts
And collect the rest of it
You saw that with
Does my first seven jobs
Oh I glad about that yeah
You just
Told everyone perhaps if you've answered your security questions correctly
Or didn't create
Creative answers
Wow now I have enough said
Get into your
Financial account
I'm glad I did not do that
I also make up completely random answer
Answers to my security
Does Batman
But sometimes
Well it's a much better practice that I certainly recommend to folks but yes
I do I have stopped myself Madea time
What did I think my first concert at 10
Okay
And if your
You mentioned insurance policies
I'd love to ask you about
Contract
Because by Guy
Wendy's companies
This day.
A lot of them are working with others
You know I'm using this data to
Serve people or maybe they're just using it
Their own purposes
How are you seeing companies negotiate things like sharing data to deliver in and service
Are you sober part of Indie HIPAA
World
You had the hitech ACT
Which when it went into effect
Required at extended
Liability to
Business associate
So then there's your Contracting with
You're now responsible
Agreed to make sure that there
Taking necessary and
Appropriate precautions to protect it
Save
While not required throughout the entire business world
At the same time
If you do
If your data is breached through someone that you're working with at the very least negatively impact
Your reputation
And in a world where
If something goes wrong it can be instantly communicated
Nevermind
Hashtag
Deltadentalmn do you have to build that into contracts and
Companies are having to take a closer look at
Okay what are you doing
You can't just
Check a box
What to talk about before I give you this day.
How you're protecting it and
Are you taking us
Basic precautions
The likely answer is no
What would your advice be to companies
Who are trying to negotiate
Kind of connected devices
Interoffice may be brought in by employees
Versus connected devices that they bring in on behalf of their and
Employees
Take me back to that segmentation
Having different networks set up to it if I'm bringing my
Cell phone
From home
Dad
You're limiting
What data and what information what network
It can access
And on the flip side
I don't need to use my company laptop or my company computer
Oshkosh
Everything that I would want to from my personal devices
Into creating their segmentations and just being aware that
When you're bringing in a printer
That's going to be Wireless
Rate
But it needs to
I hate that you're used to have
Anything cricket
Take these precautions just as you would with every other device
Okay well since we circled back that's probably a good place to
To say thank you so much for coming on the show this week Liz
Thank you for having me it's been a pleasure
Well that concludes this week show thanks for listening and if you are so excited about the internet
Make sure you sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things at Stacy on Ajo
Jd.com will see you next week