Hey everybody welcome back
This is the Internet of Things podcast did I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And here is your
Excellent co-host
Kevin tofel
And this week
We are getting a started with some big news for
Google IO
Which is Google's big developers Conference held in California
Kevin
What do we have
Google sleeve this week
A whole lot of stuff Google typically unveils its latest and greatest version of Android which I'm sure it will do
I don't think I'll actually launch it that usually
Show it off and then watch in the fall
More important to the show though is Tok
Google
Connecting all the things with
Brillo
This is an android-based platform for the internet of things so
I would anticipate this to be a keynote announcement the keynote is on Thursday this week
Curious to see what they're doing seems to be a light version of Android my guess is like the communications and
Notification stack
And it would run on really light Hardware
So
We'll have to see
The funny thing is
Do you remember Stacy that
Google did something similar back in 2011 call Android at home
I do and
It looks like of the people
Who are still at
Google who used to work on Android at home I think some of those guys are still working on this
That could be because Andrea at home
In my opinion is generally a flop nothing really came of that and I
That was more of the timing you know I don't think IRT was
Getting to be close to mainstream then we talked about on the last show is only just now really starting to go mainstream and
I just think was ahead of its
Time even I mean even devices like Fitbit weren't even
Coming out
Until like 2012 I think is when we first started
I first started writing about
Connected devices in
CES 2012 I want to say
I was probably pretty early
I mean there were still connected devices
But people weren't like
Let's connect all the things
I believe in October of 2013 or maybe
Yeah I think it was like that's about right
Indeed it for years makes a big difference I mean just in terms of mainstream awareness of connected things
The fact that we've got much better Hardware that's low power and looks
Kind of getting some consolidation and
New agreement and what radios and protocols to use it
So I guess I think it was ahead of its time but
It doesn't matter now mean that that's
The Meandering home as a daughter
It's now
Going to be a presumably Brillo
You know
Scratch yes this is going to battle Apple's homekit platform in Samsung tizen
Well
So there's some things to know about
1 is
Michaels
Who is a smart home analyst
Has talked to people in the know it
Google and he says that the guy in charge of all this
Is Venom Craig Barrett
Who is Intel's Craig Barrett but
Craig Barrett who is
It's the former CEO of atheros which was a Wi-Fi chip
Qualcomm
And so
He's been at Google since 2013
And
Apparently Google has been talking to
Router makers to try to
Get
Grillo
Installed into kind of
Routers and what they're looking for is
What's called a real time operating
System
And it looks like this wouldn't be like a super
Blowing
Artist butt
Something
That would run
On a router
Andon device
Surround the home so they
That you wouldn't need a Smart Hub
Basically
We talked about the
Listen to past but the idea of getting rid of the
Hub is just
Crate
I would love not to have an extra
Device plugged in
Is my router
Or devices if you need multiple hubs
Exactly
The other important thing
Cure that we should note is
Google is getting behind
Craig
Possible that Google is getting behind Wi-Fi
And
Read Because nest
Which is owned by Coke
Is a big proponent
Of
Red
Which is a wireless protocol based on
B
802.
Turn it off
Which we're getting all radio wonky but basically it's the same
Radio that also power is zigbee
Sydney's just a different type of software that's running on top of
So
What we can take from this is like things like Z-Wave and zigbee are kind of getting left out of the newer generation of
Kind of connected Home Products because if you look at it
Google stream with Brillo
Ask Abby wifi-based
Probably
Probably Wi-Fi baby Bluetooth
Or Wi-Fi and thread
And then you got Apple which is doing homekit around Wi-Fi and probably
Bluetooth
So nosy be nosy wave I'm not going to say I told you so
Wait a second.
Okay well
Yeah okay
I don't I don't think these are going to go away
I agree
Yes there
Is somebody I think was Alex Hawkinson the president
SmartThings the CEO of SmartThings this was bought by Samsung
He called those he's
Psych gathers Our Kind of legacy
Protocols
They're at their old school dinosaur
The problem is now that we're getting too mainstream awareness of this Market
Those are not
Mainstream known protocols and radios Wi-Fi that's ubiquitous
Best Bluetooth most people even get that
I think that had a lot to do with this
I agree now threads going to be a tough sell
Totally new
And to make matters worse
Or maybe it'll make it better
Zigbee and thread have done this kind of co-marketing agreement
Barcode software
Agreement where they're going to
You're going to be able to develop
Red stuff will work on certain zigbee flat
That'll be kind of interesting going forward so maybe it's only a Z-Wave that gets left on
Kohl's
Yeah it's it's hard to say that
Give me know we're seeing consolidation here and then the approaches
I think it's also worth noting in in Michaels piece that according to what he's found out
Brillo is not part of 20 Fidel's Group which is the nest group
Over at
Google
And that's actually something that I
Had talked to my sources about
In in discovering what Google is doing
Along with
Mike I have actually heard the same thing
But not part of nest
That's a little surprising to me
I don't think so because
Google has made it very clear rather than S guys have made it very clear that they're not part of Google and I think that's probably a
Wise move because
Google is known for vacuuming up tons of data
And
Nest guys
Have the potential to vacuum a lot of data
And it's from your home and so
I can see the the need to keep those two kind of entity separate
I will also say though
That
Google fi pushing Wi-Fi and pushing the
Kind of
Operating system on devices
Especially if it's an IPv6 or like
Thread based in wifi-based
That's straight to the cloud
It doesn't have to go through any other device
That's a very Google Centric
Approach because it will send data from the device straight to the cloud
And they're huge fans of that
That because that gives them the ability to get
Get as much data
And that is their standard operating procedure I mean that's
Their whole Revenue stream is pretty much built upon that taking that data
And then delivering contextual ads
I don't think we're going to see ads on her door lock
But I do know no but
But it's all tied to your Google account.
The tie that binds everything together so my while you won't see ads on your door locked
If another could be information gathered by the door lock that
Put an ad relevant ad on your phone the next time you do a Google search
I think
More likely what we're going to see is
Google selling more context about you
Or Google providing services that you'll eventually
Pay for
Based on the data they have
About you
I don't think that it's going to be as simple as
Ads based on
Oru home during these hours of the day here some demographic
High-profile
Yeah that's a fair point
I think it'll be a little bit more in
God I hope
Otherwise you know cuz this gets into things like
You know how you can't
There's there's laws in Play Store
Protect children on the internet
Right
Advertising
So if your 13
You can't collect certain data about children
When the home there's a
There's no guarantees that you know you're not collecting data
About a child
Who's coming into the house
Right
You can't use that data for Mark
You mean you really don't want to walk up to your front door forget your keypad number and all that and instead just watch a 30 second video app
Add to get in your house tonight
You know yesterday it was yesterday that they were tornadoes so I guess they know
Okay now
No
Please Google no
New doorbell app
The Wizard of Oz it's on
Tonight at 8
Google well that's contextual it is context
All right
Let's go to the next piece of news that I thought was actually really good for the Internet of Things
And that is alarm.com on Friday filed to go public
I filed a raised 75 million through an initial public offering
Which
Significant for the smart home space because alarm.com
Says that it is the largest
Company
In this space
I don't know if I believe that
But
I mean I don't know either but you know I'm looking at the peace that you wrote and
They're saying or telling you that they've got 2.3 million subscribers
You're telling me a sec.
I think they can lie to me but
TCU getting
So alarm.com for those of you guys who don't know
Started out in 2000's
Security
And they could Abridged into the selling home automation just like all the other
But many of the other companies
And what I found most interesting in there
Their s-1 filing
Was a that they're profitable
They're actually doing
Pretty well for themselves they've grown significantly they reported 167
1.3 million in Revenue last year
The net income of 563000
And they're growing
And
The other thing is
Not sure how long that growth is going to last
They have this amazing churn rate
Which is
The amount of
Customers that
Renew
Service
Edit set the 93 to 94% of their customers renew each year
Their customer service provider
Oh not end-users
State the 2.3 million subscribers that they say they have are the end users
And those end users are locked into
The three to five-year contracts
Service provider
And that makes sense because typically they will subsidize the equipment for the house and installation with the long-term country
So yes
But what actually happens at alarm.com cases
Buy the equipment
They sell to the service provider the monitoring software
On an annual basis
So what I would be looking for is
Maybe next year and the year after that is for that
Keep an eye on their turn figures
Because I suspect
SOS three to five-year contracts
Come up the end customers are going to probably look
Like
Maybe alternative Solutions out there maybe DIY do-it-yourself do-it-yourself
Yeah
Even like ADT just
Launch they haven't
Stay there now
They haven't actually launched a new all-in-one
Kind of security box
Camera
Sensor
Package thing but
I think that's kind of a
Wave of the future
We'll see
Yeah I think you're spot on Watch the watch to see who renews after those three
Three to five-year contracts are up
Because they're just going to so many more choices everything will be cheaper
And you probably be confident enough and the device will be simple enough that you can do it yourself
Sure especially depending on what Google and apple lunch this summer
Yes
Okay
And let's see we've got some cool
How to say we got some cool back to school things for you
Kevin you saw a fun project
Kickstarter did you want to talk.
Now I think this is perfect for a back-to-school little gift for your ear
Curious child
I mean kickstarter's got tons of stuff that mean you could sit there all day and look at their projects with this particular one
Caught my eye
It's the microduino mcookie
They are small electronic modules that are
Compatible with the Legos of all things
So think of Arduino
But being in a smaller package and Metcalf
Be connected to Legos you can like
Make stacks of different devices you can link build your a little devices with Legos
And get them smarts
With the microduino
Income just double check with the
Delivery time is July so that's why I said back to
School
The initial early birds are all gone but here's what you would have gotten them you can still get it you're going to cost a little more
For $68 you got the mcookie 101 basic kit which was 4 modules and six sensors
Along with a bunch of instructions in the
LED microphone that lights up a Bluetooth Bluetooth controlled LED
Turn the little projects you can make with us I just love the idea for this for
You know again inquisitive kids
And it's it's actually so if you didn't catch
What's the
The $68 it's only 70
That's reasonable
I mean
I paid
I think 35 for my Arduino and I can't play with Legos and my dunno at the same time so right there that's a bonus
There you go in the fatter kits
There's there's one for $150
It's at 1:40
But that's the advanced kit and that gives you 8 modules 13 sensors
And a whole bunch of other accessories
And you can make things like a music box
Situation
Electronic puppy
That would be so cool
Yeah they have to go outside no that's good
Exactly
And you know the who the $258 kit
Get you a weather station
You can make a weather station or time lapse
Photography
Okay for that cause I'm thinking that's a Christmas gift
Well okay or you know it's science
I know I know
So that the closest analogue to this I would say
Choke there
Is little bit
It is very much reminded me of little bits but I don't think my little bits are compatible
I was like I was in
So if you're if you're missing your little bits and you really want to stick them with Legos
This is
A great kind of fun
Little cookies little stackable Lego cookies for everything there's an NFC thing or zigbee
You can have Wi-Fi you can add
GSM cellular capabilities
For crying out loud there's tons of different modules here
Oh yeah and you don't we actually of use the little bits in the cloud bit sensor to make like iot devices for a house and we tie
Tie them together through is this and that
Weather like
Will make like a
Pressure sensor or something else
This sort of thing is a really fun way if you have a
Kid or maybe you're just
Not
Totally comfortable
Building on your own like with sensors you can get something like this and you can make your own light connected doorbell or you
You can make your own
Motion sensor in
You can kind of start to have fun building exactly what you need for the scenario you're envisioning for
Are your Smart House
That's the key you got all the different building blocks with the sensors modules and everything else you need
Annies
Chet's obviously you pay more to get more modules and such
I look at the two or $300 LEGO Mindstorms robotics kit that I bought a couple years back
It's really cool as well
And it's Legos
But
The very few sensors that it really comes with
Universe has a wide range for Whiting Ranch
Yeah I mean
Dollar tip has like
21 sensors
I'm looking at these sound like
We can really have some fun with this
Absolutely
So I am
I'm game I I find these things a lot of fun
I will say with my daughter who is
She's 8 years old
Doing this sort of thing in the house is a lot of fun for her because she can see
Right in front of her when we build it and we hook it up
She sees the action right away and she's affecting something in her real life
Which makes her really
Like the sort of like it really gets here until like programming and building the stuff
In a way that
You don't maybe a more abstract thing doesn't
Yes sitting in front of a terminal and coding something again and again and again till you get it just right and they work
What's is one thing but here
It's a Mann's on one side Plug and Play because it's not quite that easy but it's pretty darn close
Yeah and she doesn't she doesn't equate it with like
It's play cuz we shan't
The other thing is if you're doing something like a haunted house or
You know any sort of project
Like that
We we do like little
Plays and sketches
This is also great for building
Props and that's hard
Throwing that out there for all the parents
Or just creative people in the room who really want to build an awesome haunted house next year
And because Legos
And because
Also like
And other news for this week
Let's just go into
Shall we do it
It's time for the
5-minute review
Ice Kevin
All right
Kevin's going to do the review this year
Okay this is my one review for the year that's it you heard it here
Yo no so what it what is it is it Cortana
It is Cortana because
This week
This week actually
Today is Tuesday
Microsoft
Announce Cortana it was going to be available on both IOS and Android in
I thought this was huge because I've actually never used Cortana
And I love you
And I was like Kevin you got to tell us what it's like
Because she downloaded
I don't know
Well I would say yes you should
Here's the thing you said you you never use Cortana I'm betting most people haven't use Cortana because
Unfortunately for Microsoft Windows Phone share is literally around 3.7% worldwide right now so
A very small percentage of the population of use Cortana
I have used it I do have a couple Windows phones here that I play with from time to time
Here's the best summary I can give of Cortana and we put it in terms the people may be familiar with
It's very similar to Apple Siri
It's also similar to The Voice Control actions of Google Now for Android
The thing is it kind of takes the Best of Both Worlds I find it far better than Siri
Because Cortana has a lot of contextual
Things that I can do
But you could
Say
Cortana remind me to wish my mother-in-law happy birthday the next time she calls
Now that's like
You can have location-based service type
Reminders on Siri but you can't do
What I just said I'm serious person
The flipside is
Do I Google now it does have contextual smart Square
Cortana will be able to surface information that's important to you at the right place and the right time
Even if I just gave it up a surprisingly perfect
So it's kind of a blend of Both Worlds I like it very much I think it's worth downloading
Installing on your iPhone or Android device when you can the thing is I don't believe and I could be wrong but I don't
Hopefully you can actually just go to an App Store and download it
It seems to be that Microsoft is putting out
An app called the phone companion app for Windows
And if you hook your Android phone or your iOS device to your Windows machine with this app
You can then use that app
To push Cortana
To your
Android or iPhone
I like it I find Cortana to be very useful bar more useful than Siri
I will leave it at that
Awesome but also a little disappointing
Because I don't have a Windows
Anyting
In my life
Well that's going to make it tough at least for now I mean bear in mind this is all part of the whole big Windows 10 push
So Cortana is actually going to be
Part of Windows 10
Sui voice activation there and such
It's early days for Windows 10 is not officially launched it's all inside her bills and so on so it may be
That Microsoft I would expect him to change this
I think they're just trying to get Cortana out there for people who are interested want to test it
On Android and iOS
When push comes to shove them Windows 10 largest later this year
They have to put it out there and in the app stores
Alright well I'm going to hope because
You know there
I love voice
Send
I I find the right now my favorite is still
Alexa
Who's on the Amazon Echo
Contextually she is she's not all that
And Google
Yet
And Google's is
Decent
A lot of we'll just say personality
Yep Siri has far more personality than
Google now and that's why I again I say
Cortana is probably the best of both worlds cuz Cortana has a pretty good personality
It's actually fun to use
Yeah yeah Google
Know their utilitarian
We will table
You know someone who is very utilitarian and pragmatic I can get behind that
So I'd rather my robot Overlord be pragmatic
Pretend to like
It's less confusing that way
All right
Well let's see I think that
I think that's it for this
Sweet show
Stay tuned for John Mann
He has a
Principal at
The artifact
Group
And it is a design consultancy
We're actually going to talk to you about brillo and homekit and kind of Designing for the Smart Home
User experience roster
Talking about
What we can expect from hotels in airplanes as users and how that can kind of help us adopt new technologies
Send to the smartphone and it should be a really good show
Hey everybody
Welcome back
2B Internet of Things podcast and we have is Our Guest
Today John man who is the design director at artifact
Hello John thanks for joining us
ICC
Thanks for having me
I am really excited to have you
You today because we have a lot of really cool things to talk about that I think
You're probably
Really going to be good at talking
We'll start with
A lot of news has come out
About
These are actually weeks they're not actual news yet I should clarify but it looks like the summer is going to be a big one for
The smart home in kind of how we're going to control it with
Apple's homekit
We're not a hundred percent sure how much we're going to see but there is going to be something at the worldwide developer conference
June 1st
Our second week in June apples going to announce something related to homekit
Possibly not the full range of device
But something
So exciting news there
And then it just came out
This last week
That Google
Is building
What looks to be a
Operating system for the internet of things that it is going to call
Brillo
And
The way that that is looking
And again this is all
Based on sources this is not from Google
Variety of news reports including
My sources including the information and in some from Mike Wolfe who is an analyst
Up in Seattle
Basically Google has Craig Barrett who
You guys may be familiar with as a former
CEO of atheros which is a Wi-Fi chip company
Is building out
Operating
System that looks like
It's going to be
Inside router
Edible
You won't have like a Smart Hub but it
Control a bunch of
The devices in the house
So
With all of that Exposition out of the way
John
Tell us
What do you think
About kind of all of this news and is this the way
Did the smart home should kind of evolve
As you said
This has been a long time coming Apple first announced homekit at WWDC last year
And everyone's really been waiting with bated breath ever since
And obviously eater does the flip side of that with
Android umbrella getting to the game
Hopefully this is where we start of cross that Chasm get out of the trip current crop of disillusionment
And hopefully start
To see some things that work
And really work together
And work it in this notion where we're not diving in and out of
Multiple app
Jamaica are smart home dreams come true
But it feels like a single solution
That's really the missing elements
Today
Let's go to take the smart home and make it feels sort of after
I think today's
Elements within the smart home and felt a little bit like multiple Islands
Either of icons
Floating around
Or at the very least
Stinks like SmartThings
Peking wings
A single app to rule them all but still an app that I have to get into and doesn't quite get
Take me to the start
A high-level access that
Apple's IOS or or the Google Android
Operating system can
Can do it only a swipe or a
Talking point away
I was all of that intelligent agents so
This is really something to do
Start looking pretty closely at
And hopefully we won't continue to be disappointed
But today is your day
Smart home islands are are not quite pulling their weight
And certainly not mainstream ready yet
So I'm going to sort of disagree with you because I feel like while these are
Islands because they're bigger they're more like continent
They are still separate continents and
You know my husband actually carries an iPhone
Icarian Android
And I look at this and I kind of like oh
Nuts
This could be today
Difficult think that's a great point in one of the things that we often forget
Is when we deal with multiple users in a home is
It's it's
More
It's certainly more personal
And it's our Sanctuary but at the same time at the sanctuary of us
Typically more said in the sanctuary of me so that multi-user components
And knowing that they could be on multiple platforms
Definitely an interesting point
The other point I'd like to bring up about this
Future
With all of these devices they still revolver on my smartphone even if there's like a Hubbard the Wi-Fi
Router is the brains of the operation or maybe it's like an apple
TV boxer
Whatever
But I still think
At the end goal should be a much more contextually aware
Home kind of like what Tony fadell from desk talks about
Which is
My house responds to me as opposed to meet ordering my house to do things
And I don't know from your first
How far are we actually away from some
Like that
Yeah I don't think we're too far away from
That's an excellent point and in many ways
Hopefully
What having these larger platform players involved
That will get us closer to
To make a great point
Context is important in 10th is important
And it shouldn't have to be
Expressed intent of pushing a button
What is that button is on my wall
Pocket door online read
Or even a voice
Command
There are things that the system can start to know
As they learn about us
Where it doesn't become a requirement
That we are interacting
And
The really interesting opponent that is how do you get that set up
How do you how does the user understand what those opportunities are or we would examine their own in 10 *
And
Anyways the role of
The system is in helping to
To discover those and present the offer
Because today with most many of these
Smart home systems
Weather
What we think we'll see from homekit or even Brillo
It's so much about the sea
Expression of
What do I want to do before I've done it
Understanding I like this current context
When we call this
This is dinner
And
Like to write the music and everything in that's what dinners going to be
Inside when dinner happens this
Should be what happened
In some ways Harmony did that a long time ago with certain that having things that are activity-based
Although we still have to kind of pull out a remote and head
Watch TV
But the sooner that we can understand those contacts
And
Do things on behalf of the user
In the beginning with their permission
Could it odd if you do something and it was unexpected
But after it becomes a pattern and repetition
And we can do those things and take something off the users plate
And I think that's where things started
To become mad
And I think on the way to that magic we're going to get a lot of these kind of
Autocorrect
Type feelings wear
Your house is going to be like oh
I think it's dinner time and it's going to dim the lights and you're going to be suddenly in the middle of trying to
Turn of work on a project late at night and you're like
No house no it's not dinner
Prince lights up
And house is going to be like
Sorry my bad
I do think we'll get there a very Optimus
Absolutely and it's one of those places where
Nemours data points
We have more information and awareness that the system has
The Laura can be a bit more accurate with those
Understanding those patterns in the nuance
In that part of having these systems at work
Together in unison
Rather than
Being their own islands of sensors
Input
And and output
That's the kind of thing where we need more cooperation across devices
I just interoperability
Data
Itself but the meaning
Behind that data
And that
Swear
It's going to be I think that the really interesting Innovations are going to come from
Is
That the company is trying to make
Expensive patterns
Machine learning is going to be
Exact what's going to take the
Smart home India
Smart not just a remote control that happens to be on the adult
Alright well let's think about
Bringing the smart home to the masses
How is it that we're going to
Can I bring this to the mainstream and you mentioned earlier before the show
Places like Disney and experiences in other business locales is being a good way to go
Get people introduced to this
Beyond just like
Blog posts
Marketing campaign
I'd love to hear your thoughts about Disney's Fastpass which is kind of right now the gold standard in the internet if they
Venetian Bay
Automation delivering an awesome experienced
I think one of the things at Disney's always done and done so well
Is they put us into the future
Epcot Center way back when I was a kid
Tomorrowland and everything they've been doing it is a full experience
And it's a great exercise and Industry of end-to-end service design
Is it a Magic Band
Is pretty remarkable in that in that sense because it starts from the point of
Before you even gone to Disney
You should have got this band in the mail you on talking it's already should have got your information and is personalizing you can do something
And the moment you walk into Disney
They know your name
And they can create some really interesting magical experiences when you make you just comes up to you and says
Hi Stacy
To understand where you are and how they can
Help improve your experience while you're there
Getting getting past lines or
Letting you know where there is another
A video of a ride you want to do that that is not as crowded right now and beyond all that so
And that's what
We want our smartphone to be in
When you see these magical experiences in this this world of Disney
You start to understand are you get exposed to what happens when
All of this intelligence comes together
And so
Their opportunities
In
Hotels
In the airline experience do you sort of really end-to-end
Service design Industries
Start exposing the consumer
To what
What's the value of
And integration of technology and and
That intention in the
Career your person
Personalization in York
EXO
If we think about
Hotels just starting to do this a little today I can
Go to a Starwood Hotel walk up to the door and in my my
Phone or my Apple watch
I will unlock the door and that's kind of a magical experience and there's opportunity beyond that as you start to integrate
Your content traveling with you your likes
And media and leaving your alarm clock automatically being set
Within the room based on what you might do on on your phone or your watching soap
When you think about an end-to-end Xperia
Airlines
Again this is sort of 4
For 2 hours for 6 hours work were captive
You know how do we engage the user from that moment they purchase their tickets even if it's
A day a week a month
Having that information on you
Smoothing to the checking experience
Sitting in your seat and having your favorite music
Your content
Got your drink type kind of all there
And it becomes an expected so hyper-personal to you and deeply integrated with technology
Into that swim start understand we'll look at my home do
Oh sure now what I think about getting on a plane
Especially for like a
An overnight kind of Trooper Redeye
Flying across the ocean to a different time zone especially
Thinking about
Doing some of these circadian rhythm
Light cycles
That would be amazing
And all you have to do is replace the LEDs on the plane with
I was slightly smarter LED and then you could run like a
You know I'm going from
Dallas Texas to Sydney Australia
Can you run a
A circadian rhythm cycle that puts
At the right time zone when I land
I look at stuff like that and I
I'm really excited
Absolutely I mean if you take that to that sort of
The full Disney contacts
If you had a smart home
When I bought that plane tickets and we understand the calculation that you're going to Sydney Australia and here's the time difference
Did circadian rhythms
Affecting that bealite can actually happen automatically in your home
Starting a week before the trip
End
The Serta Magic lyrics
AC systems
Are open to where the triggers being tentrr talking to each other
User should have to think about that
I put my Airline I don't know if I have enough trust in my airline that I be like
Yeah you know what
United you can have axe
You cannot
Annette
Kind of brings up
Issues about
Like when you
When do you start having this
Is very interconnected world
In your start sharing this kind of levels of personal data
Be not even personal data but access to
Your home
And control
Who are you going to share that with
Because I sure as heck
Is there companies out there that I'm like nope you're not getting any of it
Not
Not ever
Oh it's it's a great point and
You know there's a big component of trust
End
What's important when we do talk with clients is
Kid
Presents realities about where trusted currently exist
What are brands
Who do I trust with some of this information in
In N even there's an ocean of time limit
Which we don't really see too much today
It's sort of an all-or-nothing
Never or forever
How do I set a time limit on something United for this flight to get me to Australia and then make that a pleasant experience
For the next week and a half or starting now and
When does my flight land
I'm going to give them Trust
That within the boundary of what
What can they ask
Presenting that clear value proposition
What is a user get
From disclosing some level of privacy are giving some level of access
To their technology and their lives
It was in the things that brand have to get right first
User experience aside
It all comes down to is this worth the trade-off is it exciting
From me
We can't get overly excited just by the Techno
And that's the biggest challenge that
Technology companies have
Those are the things you have to focus on
Because that's what's going to drive the adoption
Anime boys
About in our industry
The killer app what's it saying where you're like oh my God I need that to happen
And that in many ways is the Serta missing
Proposition
For some of the smartphone I think we're getting smarter about it now
Yeah I think the challenge with presenting the Smart Home
And selling the smart time to people is that
Can you mentioned it before this the home is
Both shared but it's also very personal and so everybody wants different things and different people in the home
Want different things
Side of it so
It's very hard to Market this stuff
Alright
Thank you so much for coming on the show today I really appreciate it
Thanks Stacy had a great time
That's all for this week show stay tuned for next week