Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a great show for you we're going to talk about the merger of Qualcomm and nxp
Read about Microsoft's new security program and Security in general
We're going to talk about my
Brief visit to the beta store in Palo Alto
I've got some more low-power wide area network news for you
And
We've got
Brian.
Who is the chief security researcher at New Star
Who is the second of my two omigosh
There's an iot botnet out there
What do we do
So he's going to talk
A little bit about that
But first
A message from Mars
Sponsor
Everyone's favorite phrase The Internet of Things stem from discussions involving ultra high frequency or UHF
RFID
UHF is power the industrial iot for a decade but what else do you know about UHF
Have you ever participated in a marathon you probably had a UHF label on your race bib
UHF RFID labels and tags typically have a reed range well over 5 mean in Spanish
Specialty tags could even detect moisture all without batteries
Ready to kick off your own project
E-commerce team at Atlas RFID store
Dot-com has partnered with over 25 manufacturers and will help you choose the best UHF readers and
Antennas and tags for your project
Connect the Enterprise by visiting www. Atlas RFID store.com
And use coupon code iot podcast for $50 off shipping
Already
Headed we are back to the show
Let's talk about
The big deal
In the space
Closet
Yeah it is a big deal any most people know Qualcomm for their modems and Sosa's that are in
Most mobile devices these days
Nxpi ask remember
Then my first experience was as using X
Pea chips inside a phone for
NFC if I
Call correctly
And Qualcomm said hey we want some of that goodness that you have an XP they are buying them it looks like
It's a 39 billion dollar deal
Is it
Largest tech deal
Followed
Proceeded
Are you followed or preceded only by Dell EMC
Which was 67
So
Qualcomm here so
There's a couple really cool things that I think
Happening with this
Is Qualcomm gets nxp's car stuff every was really focused on
Smart to be focused on
We're talking about seeing like
It's like $1,100 worth of sensors in
So Qualcomm getting a piece of that action is good
Be great because they've been focused on kind of
The a task system so that autonomous Driving Systems
Recently
But not all the sensors I can your tire pressure in
There's their sensors
They got a little bit of this when they bought CSR actually
But not much
Answer this really complete
The other thing that's really exciting about Qualcomm
Nxp is now they have a microcontroller business
In The Internet of Things is all about micro
Polar seas are there really tiny semiconductors
They're here wearables therein
Where where else are they being there at they're everywhere they're basically anything that isn't the big
The arm cortex processors that are inside your phone that welcomes been working with
Decades years
So these are these are the smaller lower powered ones that
In 32 bit
8-bit 60
Correct me if I'm wrong Qualcomm does not actually
Physically
Fabricated chips it outsources that but nxp does manufacture chips
Oh that's a hard question Kevin
Oh I'm sorry
No NXT. Sorry it's actually not
I just had to take
So Qualcomm is Fabolous and XP does
Has some Manufacturing
I don't know if it manufactures all of its chips
So they do have manufacturing they also it's worth noting for those of you guys who remember they bought freescale about
A year ago
Which
Combines thereto
Steak-Out more car parts
They got some actually
With the freescale assets there's some
Cellular network radio
Chips that are
Like the chips that
Operate
Cellular
Networks like the network backend
So they got some of the network processors
Which will be good for Qualcomm because then maybe you've got this whole leg
And it Network stack cuz people in the industry
And really need
So all in all good deal
Qualcomm was always going to be challenged by the internet of things because it was such a wide customer
Suddenly this company that literally Qualcomm has dealt with
For most of its life it's dealt with like
The big carriers and
The big cell phone
Makers that's it and it's
Carrie different sales organization to support
Sub 100 customers
Anticipatory everybody who wants to buy
Chip for the
So this will help them there too
Business
And I don't know I have got nothing else to say about
I don't know I mean a little surprised that XP actually had more employees than Qualcomm which I did not
Plies until reading about the steel
Oh yeah
Again that's it that's a difference
Difference in sales organizations
I have a lot more excuse like a lot word tips
Nxp is
It is big
It's not fancy
But it is big
Alright so
Massive chip consolidation deal there
Very exciting
Now we should talk about
Security
Nxp
Qualcomm
Actually I was going to say nxpi no offers end-to-end security
But this is not that
Type of security
This is Microsoft creating an iot security audit program
Or it looks like it's
Cloud customers but it also talks about
Working with
Other standards group so maybe we're going to have
It work on
Devices that are hosted in other clouds as long as they eventually talk
How to measure
Yeah I was just going to say it first I thought this was as your specific but Microsoft is going to be working with t and a
Industrial internet Consortium
To assist with you iot protocols for the industry and best practices so
It doesn't seem too specific to
Azure iot efforts for Microsoft
It's just the name so the name again
Who doesn't love a good name
This is not a good name it's
Security program for azure iot
Yeah highly specific
And very descriptive but
You know I'm not like
This probably isn't something going to call it a door
Here's why it matters
It matters because
One Security audit please thank you
Add to cart
I love it
So a matters because after the drama
October 20th
First Citizen was this was a couple weeks ago
When people were suddenly like
Holy cow
We have a lot of
Connect two things
Unsecured
Insecure
That is renewed the conversation about this and that people in the industry been talking about this for years they're like
When are people going to realize this
So we may be there
And people may be willing to pay for security
But the challenge is because
Because there's so many moving parts you've got
The chips you put in devices like the microcontrollers and you got the radios and then you got
Maybe the connection to a Gateway in House at a factory
The Gateway myconnect
To the cloud and then you got the cloud back in like as your database security
There's a lot of stuff
Software firmware and then
It's a mess
Everyone has been saying someone should really come up with some sort of Unified
Like security
Service in people
I pay for it
On the Enterprise side that's kind of what it looks like Microsoft is done
We'll have to wait and see
But the working with the eye I see the
Industrial internet Consortium is pretty good and Microsoft being Microsoft
I really do think
They know what they're talking about
And they're aware of
The challenges
So
That'll be great
It's one of the first vendors to offer something
Like this
And then
I'm very curious to see what happens though
On the consumer side
Because that's where
I think a lot of other
Kind of a lot of these products are
SMB that
We're attacked as part of the Mirai botnet
Actually smbs
Businesses that Microsoft makes a point of saying that they will work with those come
Japanese
So yay for them
Put on the consumer side people are really worried and I'm curious who might
Solve
That guy Wonder it's been a question we've had for a long time
So we are seeing that maybe
Carrier I still think that
Carriers could it like isps could do it
I think that's a really good option
I also think that maybe if you're a hub vendor
Like SmartThings or
Wink or
I don't know
Your light
I mean there's a there's a bunch of hugs out there
Nexia
Maybe one of those companies will be able to offer like a security audit for the home is an add-on
Can service
Again
Click
Pay
So I'm curious
Would you guys be willing to pay for
Especially without any real
That's yes sir that's the tricky part and as you said with all of the moving Parts you know it's frustrating
Just getting things set up to begin with we talk about this
Yeah I nausea before just setting things up as a consumer
Is an exercise in futility most often
Actually understanding
And securing everything you're putting into place putting the burden on the consumers really tough
It's just it's just a challenge
You know
It is and I should actually say something so a couple shows ago I talked about
Credit to net worth
For my iot stuff
I'm still planning on doing that
And you guys have been
Awesome about sending me suggestions
I have been waiting for me to be in my house
And it'll to tear down my network
For longer than life
Like a day and a half
So that's coming in
In two weeks so stay tuned for that and
Already I realized
Just maybe an impossible thing to do because there's a lot of functionality that I want
Where's my phone
But my phone
Great
So
Are you trying to work my way around this by putting things on a tablet and just maybe giving up on go
No that wouldn't be the end of the world made I would take
A more secure approach as opposed to a more convenient one if I could
And you're moving away from the phone I totally understand that and that is the challenge
So maybe if he comes
I totally a voice-activated system for you
I'm awesome
There's also the option of doing something with if this and that and letting
Instead of my phone going on the net
Maybe doing something via
The GPS on my phone
In my house
Radius
With if this and that and that triggering
Me being home to
One device
Like the nest thermostat that controls a lot
Things I don't know
I might have to have a hub that works with its this and that. Which would be nybakke to SmartThings
It's going to be
Tricky no matter what unfortunately
All right
That's my little addendum cuz you guys have been so awesome sending me ideas and thoughts I wanted to thank you
Before it and tell you where that was
In my travels though
I have visited some very exciting
I went last week to the beta store in
Attalla Al
I'm jealous
It's exciting so anyone looking for this it's bait with a b8ta just so you know
I sure looking and this store is
Right now the only one of its kind it's their launching 1in
Seattle and
Santa Monica by the end of this year but
What is a place where device makers pay to get into the store and the company basically
Please shows you the devices in the store they demo the products for you there's video demos everywhere
There were probably
I'm going to ask me and I'm probably estimating wrong maybe 50 devices in there
And there were things like
A wide array of VR headsets
Some crazy
Helmet type
A lot of wearables
Whole counter of smart
Devices select
The Beyond light bulbs
Yes it be on bulbs with security on protection
Had a prototype version of the Luma router
Guys in this store the week relay with $70
I know so apparently
In that store something's get differential pricing as vendors want to try things out cuz people who
Show they're basically they get to control their demo units and pricing and they said all that and I can set it real time
Time if they want
Pretty cool
So I almost
To wink relays but I didn't because my husband decided that he did not want those in the house
And because they were too fat for me to bring home in
My suitcase
Thunder
Bummer
The boxes for
Yeah yeah
Dot-dot-dot all
I'm actually looking at all the products that they have on on the site
And there's a wide range mean there's a lot of
Consumer e
Fun things you know if you want to play with the bb-8
Droid by Sphero
I'll get there a lot of
Yeah toys
Actual toys
For kids not just Toys R Us
Define kids
Okay
They have one of my favorites which is cubelets I love those things they're like these little modular robots they're probably not for
Kids cut their soup
If you have a nerdy friendship
All my friends are nerdy what do you say
Well if you haven't heard from that you like a lot
Because he's
So I was in love with a store if you are in Palo Alto or
Before the end of this year when they open in Seattle in Santa Monica I recommend popping Bybee
Because
It was a really fun place
And all the people who live in Palo Alto your life
Yeah yeah
Yep energy
Okay
So I was going to talk about iot because
Harry Green wrote an essay over Harriet green who's the head of the Internet of Things efforts
IBM
Did an essay over it venturebeat explaining
How the blockchain was going to change iot
I'm watching you guys
It's not just the back end of a cryptocurrency
It's basically a distributed Ledger system and IBM has been flogging blockchain as a potential for
The internet of things for years like
Two or three
And the interesting thing about it is is because it's distributed
What you can do is you can have your devices create a network
And instead of everything being hosted back in the cloud
Things can be hosted
Online
Individual device Network
Work so there companies like filament that are trying to do this
Rural areas
IBM seem stood there when they were showing off a
Blockchain parking meter
Concept at the arm check show and it seems instead of doing everything
Kind of locally
And reaping the economics of not having to support a cloud infrastructure pretend years for a device that may not
You really require it
But it it's aren't paying the parking meter example actually did go back to Bloomix so I be a maybe now
What type of distributed Ledger in literature
I can host all the time
But the interesting thing about it is
With the standard
All the sensors in the parking lot can kind of know the status of each other
Can communicate that not just to the parking lot
Owner
Billing System
And
Even to a city
If the city wanted to eat
Grab the information and do something with it
For like events
Hey I just thought it was kind of a neat demo
I'm not hearing a lot about blockchain for iot outside of IBM
So I don't really know where this is at
Don't know I haven't heard a ton about it either and I message
Yeah but since then it just kind of has cooled off or we just haven't
I don't know what's going on
That means it's always been a question site is it replacing the cloud is it supplement in the cloud
What's the real benefit here
Aside from you know basically a public Ledger every single transaction between devices and
And such every single bit of data can
Theoretically we can trace back and viewed
But I haven't seen anybody
Demonstrate how they're going to use it
Did wheelie show benefit yet
For example what IBM shirt off you would mention that the parking meter
What if they did the same thing without using blockchain what's the benefit the day it was straight that I don't know that they did I mean obviously
Not
Yeah that's and that's probably why we're not here
I know that it is a does reduce cost
And for financial transactions it can provide an immediacy that is just
Preston
Correct so
But with iot we have things that are already relatively in
That is I am here
Making a Ponderosa near real-time
Near real
So
I don't know
I'm going to keep an eye on it because I'm obsessed with like
The potential here
But
I'd still like
Don't get too sucked in by the hype you guys because so far it's really only IBM that's pushing this
And showing off stuff
And they've been doing this
Other related stuff
Actually not at all related stuff
We've got a wide area network
Sperry different
Dairy dip
So
Don't be dismayed by the fact that I just drank a whole bunch of words together that may not make sense there's got to be some more
But
What is happening these are Networks
The cellular network
These are really low power
Like I said
Networks
Like usually they communicate
At less than 1 megabit per second of bandwidth in the case of
You know and they do it over huge distances in the idea is you connect sensors to be
Please
Because
They don't require a lot of power
So you don't have to change your batteries in your sensors for a while
And they're cheap and easy way to like
Play and send like State data
Back and forth so
It's 78 degrees
I'm on I'm off
That kind of information
A small amounts of data sent often
So
We are talking about this because
So you guys are going to love it
Eyes have a story about Singapore creating their first
Live NB iot trial
And I was like nb-iot what the heck
And I discovered you guys
Attendee IRT
Is a cellular standard so by that I mean it's a 3gpp standard
I told you there was going to be a lot acronym
What's a cellular standard
It competes
With
Hello Kitty mess it up again cat
So
The reason I'm bringing this up is because Verizon
In the US is doing a cat in one
So you're going to hear about it
And it's going to compete with some of the other networks out there like Comcast just invested in
Lauren
So when you hear cat and one
Or nb-iot
Tink
That competes with
Lauren net
Works or sick Fox
All these are kind of these low-power wide-area
So what's happening here is Singapore
Australia and Korean telcos are trialling nb-iot
What's also worth noting
Thing is that Singapura Korea both have
Lauren net
Brexit there were
Time to
So it's unclear to me at the carrier's think that Laura and the cellular standards
Compatible
And I might be
I'm running them together Verizon is
Not
Investing in
Up the carriers here in the US are like
Worth noting just a
If your if your network nerd
You can be like oh my God
More acronyms
More fun more standards more Networks
Finally if you have $300 to spend
Netatmo has an outdoor camera just for you
So this is part of the
Just
Rush
Of outdoor cameras we've got the canary Flex we've got the ring stick up cam
Forget exactly what is collecting that's right though
Is descriptive names they really hot problems
All right so all of those cameras Bay all range in about 200 maybe $250
Try to think about the canary Flex
But the netatmo
IS300
And this is a camera
Outdoor camera + security light
So the camera is beneath this big LED light
You install it outside by installing it where a security light had been
So it gets power that way so there's a little bit of wiring involved
The reason it cost so much put it at
Is because they don't
Actually store your stuff to the cloud
And so there's no subscription so they're arguing that over there a year
Your product is actually about the same
Which for the nest outdoor I guess it's $10 a month so
In about a year you make that up because your story on a internal micro SD card so
You can store an internal micro SD card which is what 90% of
People will probably do
The others can put it onto a
Internal Nas
Ntp server
Or you can send it to Dropbox actually just met
Is also integrated with if this then that
And
What I like about that at most stuff other than the Privacy features is that it's got
Really interesting
Image recognition technology so it can tell if it's a dog
This car has all these other things
And it won't record that stuff
If you don't want to
If you want without the noise I like that
Yes
So Nest also does that
Canary is working on that I don't know how effective it is
So in the nest stuff actually looks pretty good at it so
Basically
This is up to you if your privacy-conscious I would say
This is a good per
If you
Are compatible with nest and you have a bunch of that stuff maybe you don't spend
An extra hundred dollars on the net
There you have it
New devices
Available
For you
And now
Stay tuned
For a message from our sponsor
And
Our Guest this week who is Brian nox
The head of security research at new star and he's talking about security
Turn that up
That was just super fun to say all right
Thank you so much de to
Hey this is Stacy I'm breaking into this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Sponsors arm and I have dipesh Patel
Use arms EVP of incubation businesses earlier about secure
Charity being the biggest problem
Facing the Internet of Things
Armistead a lot of work with trustzone on its chips
It's crypto cell technology
And you guys recently launched another
Architecture
That will help
Secure even smaller
Devices
But you guys also did something really significant you launched a cloud service can you talk about why that happened
Did you know that biggest challenge facing us in
Connected devices
How do we make sure that the devices
A secure
And I managed to the life cycle
Let me explain what I mean by Manish first and then I'll talk about how the cloud offering that we have launched
Touching that to Jenny
So every device is best
Installed
In a environment
It has a
Needs to be unloaded and then it needs to be managed
To its life cycle and device management important
But one of the biggest issues with device
She's at the software that one has written for those devices
Tends to evolve over time
And you might have
Issues with
Versions of software that you wanted
Some of these issues with lead to security holes in the devices and in order for us to manage.
Do spices
To the lifecycle we need to be able to have those devices connected to a cloud service and be able to deploy
Different software update To ghost device
As part of that deployment this is where you bring into brand new and bet Cloud offering
And that's what I meant cloud is designed to
Text design to take the device
To a journey from the first time it's connected
2 to the time that we can actively manage the devices
In the field
With mbed cloud
An embedded OS
You guys are really branching out from
Silicon IP
Can you talk about the overall strategy for arm and why it's doing
As we started looking at iot
It became clear to us that the
So is 82 units
Scale and become mainstream
We were going to have to do something about the software that fan on device
At the moment the software that runs on devices is quite fragmented
And why that's okay from the volume Zello
In order to scale to a large-scale number of devices
That's Amore
Like the one we're doing with him by the West was necessary
And that was necessary because we think
A lot of the colon problems
I don't device
Software needed to dissolve
In one hit
And that everybody could take advantage of that
And spend their time and effort
On
Creating additional apps
Medications that ran on that sofa
Depeche thank you
I can't wait to see what happens where can we go to
To find out
Directions to Glen lawn mower parts
Is
Embed
Dot-com
That's the letter m
Followed by
Bed
Dot-com
You can talk more about MBH cloud
And by the way
Weather in America
Device manufacturer
Oh what are you looking to manage
Devices that are about to be deployed and in the field
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higgins
Today's guest is Brian up
Who is the director of security research for iot
At
New star
Hi Brian
Good thank you for having me
Thanks for coming on the show
So you are here
Because you have spent years
An industry that feels like it's only a few years old
You actually spent years doing security research for companies like Belkin and wink
And then you work with Josh Gorman over it I am the cavalry
Helping to create some
Frameworks for
Connected devices
For securing
So
I really excited to have you
Well let's get started
So
Right now we're in kind of what feels like a turning point for conversations about Security in the internet
Things we've kind friend
Deers about like hacking individual devices to all of a sudden we've had these major
Distributed denial-of-service attack
Text the most recent one happened
Friday and basically took down a couple actually
It can take down a couple websites but it affected
Websites on East Coast
And I would love to get your take
Did you expect this to be the Hallmark event or this type of attack to be the Hallmark event that got people talking about securing Iowa
Are we expecting
You know this kind of attack or just ready to start general service
Not necessarily distributed-denial-of-service but we were expecting these kind of attacks to be coming from iot devices
Because the security has really been locked
Such a long time
And the sheer number of these devices out
On the market
Gartner says there's 5.5 million devices per day that are that are put on the internet
It's a lot of devices
With very little security
That are just right for being used for attacks
Okay and when you said these kinds of attacks
What kind of attacks
What's this is a very different type of
What we've seen with
A normal
You know distributed-denial-of-service
Those typically Army send you a message to your computer or your device
And then it sends a request to somewhere that I've spooked
And what's really different about this kind of attack
What we saw on Friday
Is it used What's called the Mirai botnet
And that's it
Set of iot devices
They've captured
But instead of
Sending the request
Chi without devices
Making it
Trigger point there
They compromised all these devices directly
So they loaded malware on all these devices
And once these devices can infected they actually start searching for other devices
And there's a huge number of
Credentials that are
Store Dress Code
And so it's looking for
I will call NVR Network video recorders which is kind of like a DVR but for
It'll be connected cameras the cameras themselves
And then a small percentage about 4% we're actually router
Charlie's device
Cyst with a lot of power very little security were used to
Basically load this attack
Transdyne which is a Dynamic DNS provider
And
All the sites
Use dying
We are unable to resolve their
IP address
So what does that mean for consumer
When you were trying to get a Twitter and
Other sites
Sonosite
Become unavailable
Got it
This is a specific Port that is used for a certain time
Type of traffic signs
I'm going to nerd out for a minute here and we're going to talk about
The hotel nataska
And why
That's actually like
A good thing because
Well that's not so much that concerning me the problem with
Telnet is telnet is White Oak
Internet
Support 23 it's been around for a long time
In a lot of places
Suspend
Replace with a much more secure than called SSH
But the problem is that a lot of these devices
Wenger Manufacturing
Turn on telnet
Phone number
A lot of times they are used to telnet into the box so it's a terminal window you know For Those whom
Remember the old black-and-white windows
And once you get a tone at session you can actually look at settings
And so manufactured Jesus off the assembly line 2
Put things like the serial number
Set the MAC address at the IP address so they can actually program these devices
Unfortunately that means that a lot of times
Those devices never have toenail turned off
If 90% of the consumers aren't going to use that feature it shouldn't be on
Left of 10% that need it actually
Turn on telnet and use it
The other problem here
Which is more concerning is the password or that the credentials for telnet
The issue with a lot of these prices from Ryan back to all these places is there using default credentials
Which means he's
I wish credentials
Better in the user guides and
Document on the web for devices
And they're weak credentials things like all zero
Or admin admin
And so they're very easy to gas
So what Mariah does is it scans for
Devices
List of credentials
And they're all default credentials
And
One socket connection to telnet
It loads up malware
And then makes that device start searching on other devices
The problem you have here is
If a user goes into the web interface
Right just like their configuring router and they change the password
In many of these cases it does not change the tone at password
In some cases that toilet password is hard-coded which means you as user cannot change it
Got it which is why some of the
Are one of the vendors at least so far his
Recalled
Some of their devices
And that's a huge step that we shouldn't
Ignore I mean
To have a vendor
Find any record
Is it Theory have
Put such improper security into the device
But they need to recall it because they can't actually fix it
That's a big deal
And that picture vendor
The problem is there a white-label vendor
Which means
They're not selling their DVRs or their NPR's under their name
They're showing it to other manufacturer
So
That seem NVR kits sold to
10 or 15 different
Manufacturers
Then put their sticker on it and sell it with her cameras
Does that mean Isaac consumer have no idea if I've got one of these or does that mean
Those vendors that are at the actual
Brands need to do a recall
Well
I think one the coordinate through
The vendors that they were
But you as a consumer you can look at the Mirai list if you just Google for a Mirai botnet there's a list of the device
And manufacturers that are affected
Yes
That is true and what what if one of my devices is on this
What do I do
This is really where
Choices of consumers
Amanda cases
You can try and change the password
Look up the user manual to see if etenet password or the interface password can be changed
And if it can't
Then I would
Consider
Either removing that device
And buy replacement
We're contacting you manufacturer
Tell me the manufacturers have said they will be doing a software update
To change the
What is that means they're going to do another default password that someone
Figure out
Not sure
But if they just change the password to something else
Once people figure out that password
Unless every customer is changing their password to
Unique one
It's just going to be another way to attack
So the need to change their passwords
And enable consumers to
Change the past
Actually they just need to enable consumers to change their passwords and then consumer protection
Exactly
Got it
How likely is that
Well I would say normally
Not very likely
For a couple
You're assuming that the manufacturers actually have a contact
List of everyone who owns this device
So unless you register your device with an a
Account
Which song
Some of these
They don't have a way to contact them
Even if A2
It requires the user to actually do the interaction
So the manufacturer will come up with the new update
But they don't cash it out
It's cold down by the consumer
And this is part of the problem with IRT
We're asking average consumers to become it patching
Apartments
You know what you think of all the devices your house that may be connected
I have to go look for updates for each one of those and make sure you update them on a regular basis
Well this seems like a good time to talk about like things that
Companies can do to design security into their devices
Cuz a lot of my devices
Actually Force updates to me
And so
Patching for
For me it's just
Open app
And it's like hey
Firmware update
Do it
Or in some cases it's like boom
We updated yourself
Enjoy
I guess just this feels like something the vendor should be kind of thinking about when they're designing I mean isn't it possible to make this easier
Consumers
It's absolutely posh
Make it easier for consumers unfortunately security is one of the last things
I mean if you think of like a Kickstarter or Indiegogo type campaign
You're trying to get funding
And then you're building a team and you've got to build a mobile app and you better build the web interface in the actual product and the soft
So the nvrs are being provided
Many of these cases by a
White label manufacturer
But there's a lot of
Kickstart projects
Or cameras something that you need
Where
They may have to build the software for it
Or the
Firmware for it
Or they get part of the firmware for the manufacturer
But they're not fully
Thinking about security
From the manufacturer standpoint
Yashow Whiteley
Axure
They don't really think of the software layer so much as a firmware
And they provide that to whoever the eventual manufacturer who's going to put their name on it
So if there's not a you know starting approach of
Thinking about how you think you want to scare the product
It's too late once you get the device already you know down to
Consumer
And the last time I see
Is the tools that are used to it as I talked about before they're used to
Verify the product off the assembly
A lot of time
Actual vulnerabilities are in those tools themselves
And again they're used to do things like
Verify that
IP address is set correctly the serial number
And the MAC address
But those
Schools
Also have things like
Route show access or
Donut open
The manufacturers do this for
Convenience
They don't think like attacker
So
The manufacturer doesn't know it's there
What we call the original development manufacturer the person
Who makes it
Doesn't
Care that it's there because it's
Convenient for them
And most consumers window to check for those things
Or even how to check for those
And so the solution
If I'm a consumer and I want to buy products that are not going to
Become part of a button
Or are less likely to be compromised in other ways
What should I look for what should I do
So I think
Easiest thing for consumers to do is look up the manufacturer website
And see if they have a security light
And that's going to tell you a couple
Whether or not the company action
We take security seriously
To whether they have a bug Bounty program or way to submit
Information
If there is a problem
And those things alone tell you that they actually care about security
If there's no way to get to the manufacturer
About a security issue
10 if a researcher finds vulnerability
They're not going to have a way to get to the manufacturer
And it probably means a manufactured doesn't
And this is scary
There's a lot of opportunity for things to go wrong here and it feels like not a lot of
Ways to fix it
After the fact
So
Given that
What is your stand sign
Like what should we be doing should we should the government get involved in b-more
You know stick less carrot
Should
I don't know consumers just give up stop buying the stuff
What consumers really should be doing is using their buying power
To incentivize
Steel manufacturers who do care about you
There are manufacturers out there that
Run bug bounty
Set have Security Programs that are constantly looking to improve the security devices
So what about the governor
The interesting thing about the government is whether they have the power to you
Actually go after
Over the past couple years there have been some actions taken by the FTC against companies that are implementing what we
Sitter
Basic minimum standards
It happen against camera companies have happened against router
Unfortunately
They're larger company
With very large legal team set of fought back in
In one even when they
Violated
What anyone in the security industry worth
Would consider a basic minimum
An example would be a router with lap
And wife is a standard that has been for many years advised not to be
And there was a router manufacturer
ISP
Who is shipping devices
With back pain is
And after she went after them
And unfortunately lost because
Lawyers of this company were
Substantial
Where is most of the
Companies like that that that BC went after ended up paying fines for having two
Fixter devices
So
I think it's that's one way to do it
I just don't see right now that the FTC necessarily has the power they need
Be able to horses
So maybe this is where we look at other
There's an effort for something called cyber UL
If she works better with Underwriters Laboratory
This would be a cyber version of it that would look at
Border Collie puppies
There's an effort
That I'm working on with I'm the calvary
That is doing something
Similar to ones that the Cowboys release
It's a five star rating for
Devices
And similar to what you would see with a car
The consumers don't necessarily need to know all the tests that are behind it
But that a five-star would be much better than a 3-star
And that program would be run by
Government companies
We wouldn't necessarily want the government to run it
Probably more like an independent company
But think of it as a framework for researchers to
Use so that they can talk about devices in a Common Language
Every
Researcher you know goes to look at a device and
Has sort of different ways of looking at it judging
How good that
Practice
Compared to other cameras
Compared to other devices
If we had a common frame
A way to rate these devices
Or how they handle
Physical
How they handled
Network communication
Privacy
How they handle safety
I feel like we have talked about a lot of things
I would love to know from your perspective you give me some good tips about where to go and how to
Judge devices
Before I fall
The ones I have now
Do you have any advice for people who have a collection of
Connected devices in maybe there fine for now
How should I be kind of thinking about
Protecting myself
I think it's a taco
Before looking at the manufacture sightseeing if they're serious about security
There are number of
Defcon presentations that have been done on iOS device
They're all on YouTube
And unfortunately a lot of those manufacturers
Don't care or have never followed up to 60 issues
These are things like
Being able to
Call your home and then having someone who can just
Connect to that device
Load their own software on it
And
Really do whatever they want
Many of these devices are used for managing remote compsych rental helps
In the past there has been problems with
Companies like Mikasa Verde
Are they have a devices
The Gateway for your home
And it has very little security
There's a lot of YouTube videos explaining how to hack into him
And so is a consumer you have to make a choice on
Just the benefit you're getting from that device outweigh the risks of someone
Using that device to unlock your home
There are manufactured
As I said that you care about security
If you look at Google
They spend a lot of time
Security now whether you have a problem
The way they handle privacy
Is a different story
But
They do spend a lot of time on the security devices
Do you want to recommend any devices that are highly secure for us
There are a lot of spice I like
There's companies that I feel take a lot
Kerin
Their approach to security
But because I work on bug bounty
Crisis actor
Be very careful what I say
I will say publicly that
You know I like the products
Dictionary has done
I think they take a very
Serious approach to security
I believe the same with wink
I feel like it's a great platform to bring a lot of your iot devices together especially from the consumer standpoint
Google has done a lot
This pretty space
Whether you have an issue again about their privacy
Their products tend to be very solid whiskey
Prospective
Those aren't the three that come to mind I actually have about a hundred iot device
She's in my lap at home
How did I work on a daily basis and that means lots of applications
Looking at lots of traffic
To see how those
Devices work
Is that your home or is that your lab that is also
My home is actually a giant lab everything in my home is connected from my swimming pool
Turn my thermostat to my door locks
Now there are some
Protections like firewalls
Things put in place in front of it
Because I'm a researcher
Part of my research has to be using these on a daily basis to understand
The benefit versus security trade off
I love it
I also live in a living lab so I'm like
One day
I shall I shall visit yours
So
Thank you so much bro
Thank you for having me
Talk to you in
I really enjoy talking about it and special security
Well that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show
Feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
At Stacey on iot. Com