Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
This week
Actually was late last week
Shop to its very core by the departure of
Girlfriend
He didn't the part he was set to away mode
I screwed up Kevin
Bathtub
Yep Tony's gone stepping down
Stepping away
Apparently is invested in like a hundred small startups
The Pacifier 2
Including a go-kart company
Which
There's a lot to talk
There's a lot
First of all he's leaving after a bunch of
Bad press
Next
But
The Verge actually did a story I'm going to say it was Tuesday
Tell you about how
Fidel head actually told
Google
Larry that
He was leaving in
December
And wanted to transition out so he was kind of unhappy because it sounds like
When Google became alphabet
He suddenly got
Different marching orders
A little more accountability from a financial standpoint
Getting things done
Kingston Market
Less vision
Model the product
Selling
Let me ask you if you have a problem with that I mean you're looking at a company paid over three billion dollars for nest
I don't have
Have a problem with it I can see why I would have a problem with you
I mean especially if he was promised
He wouldn't taking it was going to be a YouTube style investment for
Google where they give you to
Like a decade
To get profitable
So if you're thinking along those lines than yes it has always been
Super long term I mean the man pushed a new protocol
That's that's not a short-term that right there
Right right
But but
Me play devil's advocate here I'll save from
Alphabets perspective sentence
I'm just giving my perspective on what they would think they spend a lot of money
And
How many new products really came out in what
3 years
Mastro's owned
There's nothing
I mean
Pipeline to The Nest Thermostat
Not really
I get it and also you know.
Google actually was in talks to purchase Dropcam
Like
They brought that deal in in May
A part of Nest Tony was not like searching around for the
Right that we know there was some some angst
There between the Dropcam folks and then ask folks based on reports of
Response to Tony fadell calling the
The real deal
So that being said there's a
Couple things to do
Think about here
Is the new CEO Marwan fawaz
Is a former CTO at several big cable companies
And
I believe it was Adelphia
Charter over there
This is a man who a has a lot of
Experience in the
Service provider industry which I think is actually a really interesting
Space for the smart home right now
And he also was a VP at Motorola Mobility
Managing their Motorola home business
The man knows how to hopefully build Hardware
Support it
And sell it
Which actually if your
Cheer consumer who wants to buy this product this may not be the worst thing for you
Agreed
The great I mean he's got the right background
You know I can't say I know of his accomplishments at those companies and whatnot but
Kiss My Bass credential Sandpoint
You know that's exactly what you would want everything in a nest group
Yeah it was actually the technical Advisory Board of ATT
Around the time that ATT was getting super involved in the Smart Hub
Come to
So I feel like
Alphabet
Is telling us something very clear here which is Tony fanelle's vision for the Smart Home
May have been
Where's the 3.2 billion dollars
But it's not playing out fast enough
Screw division
Let's just go with making a quality product
And
Get it out in the park
Ripe
Tri-tip as a nest owner
I mean I'm not concerned by what's going on are you
No no I'm actually a little heart
Now I will say
As someone who loves the industry
Fidel was
It's Magic here so we had a sense of how we
Get there from
Tactical perspective
I can't
You know it is kind of a loss to say
Dang it now we don't have this person I mean
Cuz it was an open but the worst with Nest program
Wasn't awesome
Way
To get people to buy into the smart home without actually
Freaking programming stuff
But here's the other thing I want to talk about cuz
ARS Technica wrote a story speculating that
Alphabet to put nest
I don't believe that Nest is up for sale
Was pure speculation on there
Park
The story is a great overview.
Forecast
But I was thinking about what is the value
Apple connected home
Today
Because you've got a device and there's not a subscription Revenue
So what you would be buying is
The device the Goodwill that sort of thing
But you also are buying the promise that you're going to support that device forever
Right
I just kind of started thinking about me and is that really a great model to
How should we start thinking about these companies that are actually successful
SmartThings for example sold to Samsung for 200 billion which is
A considerably smaller sum than 3.2
Yeah cuz you said there's no subscription model that could change that
Could Implement something but they have to provide more value than what
What's provided today
Obviously I think to a Google and alphabet or any other company in this with us
Getting the data is very important
Get that data
Nest keeps their data separate
From Google
And that's been
Promised forever
So maybe that'll change
Tony was really
Component of fat that would be
Keep an eye on rtos
Pandora.
Why shouldn't we all should
And you
Arbolino new home
So soon
Cool stuff that you're having to
Do deer like
Yeah that's
Will I be two or three weeks we can talk about that cuz that's what we make the move
But a none totally unrelated to the Tony fadell brouhaha
We're actually
Not buying a nest for the new home
I decided
Even before this news came out I decided in already ordered an ecobee
Because for the same price I seen a little less on Amazon
I'm getting a remote sensor and
We purchase a townhouse with
Multiple levels in my office will be on the second level thermostat up in the first level just like my current house and I'm tired
Being hot
In my office when nobody's home and
My thermostat doesn't realize nobody talk
So the remote sensor will go in my office and I can always add more sensors I think they're two packs are like 80 bucks
Does reasonable soft works with my wink Hub works with
The Amazon Echo
So
Apple unconcerned it
It's just a better product for my knees
Has been my favorite
Favorite thermostat for
A long time it's not the favorite thermistor of Wirecutter which surprised me cuz I was researching
The Weeknd
They actually still prefer the nest
But the ecobee what's the next best
Sorry I'm working
The people over at The Wirecutter and I actually had an argument with their smart home guy about that I thought your wife
No
Soccer. Stacy so this week
Because it's almost Father's Day
Which
1830 around there I don't know, Dad I should know but I don't
No no I think it's someone else's
The shop to remember
You don't have to do it
I thought we should actually run through some gift idea since we did it for the moms might as well offer some option
For the dads
So
Throughout the
Logitech
Home Harmony
Dad's like
That's my guy
It's actually the Logitech Harmony home hub
And this is 99 box on Amazon
I have actually
Massena personal I feel like I've seen it for sale for a little bit less so
Wait on that Chopper room
Shop around
But
If you have a smartphone
This is just a little Hub in the thing
We reviewed this probably a year-and-a-half ago
The thing that was amazing about it is
Logitech is awesome at AV
So you can pull in all your AV stuff
Super fast
Adidas just like this
Oh you have this receiver
Oh I sent the Roku
So that was
Super seamless I did have a little trouble connecting a couple of my device not connecting them but just getting everything to work
But once I did that
It was awesome
The added bonus is
You can connect it to you if this then that
If you're so inclined and
If you download the yonomi software and we've actually talked about this
Before
You can set up like
Amazon Echo commands
For like
Netflix and chill
Which
Will like set everything up for you
And I think that's
$99 get you the home hub
They actually have introduced a zigbee and Z-Wave home automation extender for it which
I have not tried but
I don't know either
That's also
That's a hundred bucks
And let's see they have if you want the remote
Troll
To go with this
There's $145 package that you like a standard remote control and then there's like a
$260 package to get you the Hub and the touchscreen pants
That's nice
That we know what Kevin Gates
Daddy bikes
I'm throwing that out there is good idea
Kind of pricey
Universal remote all that stuff
Why not give him more
Makes sense makes sense so as a dad I lose things all the time and I know that you just had the CEO of
Macaron the podcast last week
But actually saw a Tracker in the wild yesterday along with the tile
I talk with somebody on my team at Google as both of them he puts the Kyle
It is Google bad she never loses that
And his tracker is on his key chain and I
Would recommend this for any that I think and I actually did
Purchase four of them
Once I saw his because it's like the size of a quarter I mean it's the trackers really small
And it also has a replaceable battery which I don't believe the tile does I'm not saying
You got to send it back yeah post tiles the tiles bigger so
I like that you can swap this out with a coin size battery you know once a year or however often you have to do it they actually do
Do you have a current sale
Protect your Father's Day buy 2 get 2 free for 60 bucks
Plus if you know somebody who bought trackers they have it may have a referral link to my get another one free so
Which I did I actually dying of getting 5 for the price of 2
They're not here yet but I'm going to I'm going to do what my buddy does but one of my
What pads are my keys
Probably give one each to the kids I mean
I think it's a handy little device and it's not that expensive
It is not how much
It's thirty bucks for one but again right now if you buy two get two free Super 60 bucks
You got four of them
And that's what 15 each
Seoul
That's half price
Yeah those
Got Fitness One
Oh that's right I was like
There's something
There's something else yeah well you know he we dad's we like to stay in shape or at least pretend to be in shape
I tried this
Products
Way back before even
Launch a month before launch
Starting December January timeframe
And I got to say the most complete
Fitness tracking solution I can find an actually still used to this day
Is the UA healthbox Under Armour of all places
Again not cheap but
$400
What you got is a
Smart wifi-connected scale that does your weight and your body fat
Just nice
You get the UA band which is a little wearable device with a small display that track your steps
Accu sleep distance the whole genome
Pretty much everything you want you also get a heart rate monitor
For your chest
That you can strap on and go use when you're running
I think that is
It for the $400 the app is fantastic app works on IOS and Android
Very holistic view of your health you can track your nutrition because you a also owns the
MapMyFitness app
So you get everything all in one
I got $400
If you really want to go Hog Wild
And I do recommend these Under Armour does have a
Pair of running shoes that goes with this
Want to see the look a hundred 2000 $40
They have a built-in sensors
And Bluetooth
And you literally
You put these on
You don't
Turn them on writing you put them on
You go run and it automatically tracks
Steps
Distance and so on
And Pedro back into the system
And it just automatically syncs when you get back from your run you don't even
Do anything is a beautiful thing so
Again a little pricey but the UA healthbox is top-notch
If it were Mother's Day I would
Heart rate monitor
Strapped to your chest right
The heart rate does do it in a chest
IHeartRadio
It's not that I don't think it
Does a heart rate on the wrist
Yeah
But
Did you find it accurate
Because the rich ones are very
Free accurate if your
I tend to find the chest heart rate monitors to be more accurate than the
The LED sensor that were using on the wrist are few exceptions to that but in general
The heart rate monitors are pretty solid and yes I found it accurate
Cuz that's
Otherwise spending $400 on it
Not a cure
Heart rate monitor
The scale by the way works for up to at least four people so it's not even just for that I'm sorry up to eight
So that's a lot of people can they all stand on it at one time
Probably could but they better have small feet and it will probably break
Awesome so those are
Happy to hear others
Yes
But
I have a I have a husband that's going to buy for it
I don't think it's smart home Gadgets in the
And since he's a little skeptical of the whole Space
Yeah
Another product
It doesn't quite
I found
From Dave's
Super
Exciting I knew you would love this
So
Like almost a year-and-a-half maybe even two full years
I have been waiting for Hugh
To put out BR30 switch or the can the lights that
He put in your cans if your ceiling
In white
I have wanted this forever
And lo and behold Dave's at 2
Write something lovely blog
Scarfing through the FCC
Applications and he found
Philips Hue was going to do some white BR30
Yep yep yep
There is no timing on these there is no price on it
Hopefully
I don't know if is the type of company like Amazon is a type of company they never filed their at stuff with the SEC unless they're about
Out to lunch it
I think
Philips is probably similar in that respect
So hopefully we'll see this very soon
Like there will be a party in my house
It will not have colored lights they will be white and it will be awesome
And they will be tunable
They will be tunable and
I'm hoping that they go for about $30
Feels like they could go to $40
So I'm still probably going to buy them
Because ice
Believe it or not you guys I still have light bulbs that are not smart
Although I will say
So this happened to me
My Philips Hue's that I've had in my living room
For like 2 + years
Disconnected itself
One of them just randomly disconnected itself from
The network
I have no idea why
I'm worried after my experience with the cheaper GE lights that what about
Video fail
Not experience
But when it disconnected itself I realize that a
Putting it back on
Philips app was actually not hard
But getting everything
Back in track
For the echo
Is that required
Real relearning which devices are internet where I can possibly regrouping or learning improves yeah
Yeah
I wish there was a better way
I wish we could just save those
Remember that
Just be aware that you know it's possible that liked
Two years afterwards you get some wacky things. I don't know that was kind of glitchy
You know some people are like this is why I don't want smart light bulbs I don't know
Need extra glitches in my
12 it's and it's a big investment I'm in your you have a bulb or two that the radios are shot and whatever you paid for those bulbs
2030 bucks a pop it adds up
Yeah
The other thing we should know is the lumens on these BR thirties that Phillips
Korean is about 680
That is not allowed
Excuse towards the lower light output side
But I'm not too worried about it because
I have like in my kitchen I have six of these and my kitchen is like bright is freaking
Daylight all the time
Yeah
So and with a tunable stuff you can always tune
Down I guess
Quartz countertop
Have a a19 has 800 lumens
Chicken testing in
I can tell you about later
Another show
Super excited
Quick stats
August
The connecting door lock is connected its door lock to if this then that
So if you want to start
Doing things like hey when I unlock my door turn on my lights
It's done
It's done baby
Arlo which is the Netgear kind of home automation devices company has connected their outdoor camera
Stiff this in the
Which
I love because I want to put the outdoor camera on my route
I need to test a
And that way if there's motion up there I could set up a notification
Except a little siren
Your neighbors would love that
And then which makes welcome camera
And a weather station that I cut it
Also
An outdoor camera that I don't think is actually out yet to later this summer
So they opened up their death program
It's called
And you know I don't know if it's going to be is like widely used his works with nest for the cool thing about netatmo guys
If they don't store your stuff
Cloud Library privacy
Turgid
Alright so that was our last minute news any other things we should talk about
I got to find out how I'm going to lock my new home so I might be on the hunt free
Smart Lock
But maybe if
You should
You should check this out so I am starting a smart home
Advice column
Actually my first question because it's like the second most common question
Afterlights is what connected lock
Should I buy
There we go thank you
Okemos iot Manners I can't wait to read that
So actually I'm looking for a name for that column
And it can't be Stacy knows things cuz that's the name of my newsletter
That would have been perfect
You guys have any device
The meaning of my smart home advice column
You can send your questions to questions
Iot podcast. Com for now
Eventually wants
The column gets started will happen
End
It should be fine
Awesome
All right
Well
Stay tuned because our guest this week is Crispin Rose
Who is the
SVP of iot
For AT&T
He's talking about
Brand new Foundry that they started
AT&T plans to make money on the Internet of Things
And pricing so high this is Stacy and
I'm here with the iot podcast to tell you two things the first isn't I've launched a Weekly Newsletter devoted to the
The Internet of Things
That you can sign up for it
Staceyoniot.com
The second is that we're now accepting as on the iot podcast
We have packages for big companies and startups
So if you're interested please email Andrew
At iot podcast. Com
I'd also like to thank my devices and Callisto Communications who supported the show in the past
Hey everyone this is Stacey Higginbotham with the internet
Things podcast we are back with our guests today who is Chris Penrose who is an SVP of iot
At AT&T
Omad Chris thanks for coming on the show
Do you actually tell people that your desk VP of iot at AT&T cuz that's a lot of letters
Is a lot of letters
Connecting things that I've never been connected
And I am really hoping to transform businesses
Consumer experiences from that site
Less fun with acronyms
Actually was one of the first carriers in the US it was the first care in the US
Report over a billion dollars in revenue from
The Internet of Things
So I'd love to get a sensor
Where the businesses for
For you guys today and where your priorities
Yes
Today AT&T is been a true leader
The United States not a global stage Around The Internet of Things
We've been at this for
Actually over 8 years now
Where we started our first Disney
Amazon Kindle
Devices
We brought on
Interior space
An example of what
The new products and services
This might be connected at Hahnemann connect
Announce as a first quarter of the week
Are not connecting over 28 million
Devices
Title III AT&T Networks
Around the world and it's everything from
Classic cars
That's tianjin
Irrigation
The trash can
You know we we basically run the gamut across a number of different verticals
To make sure that we were able to really
Change the way businesses operating or change the consumer experience by connecting things I haven't been to
Okay
Are you guys today are in Houston to open up a Foundry which is
AT&T
I think it was like
Startup slash
Lab.
Kind of think about technology
And this one's focused on medical
Is this a new space for you guys or is it something where you were like you know what we just need a place to
The dedicated
AT&T has been creating Innovation space
A while as well
Foundry Networks
What we're doing uniquely here
Houston
Is opening up one
Pacifically around connected health
And we've been active in the space
Quite a while we actually is
Willowbrook
Companies in healthcare ecosystem
They were already doing
Text device
Your growth rate
What's with the companies were already working with
We think Daniel take
Facility in dedicated specifically to healthcare
Advice
Accelerate
Adoption of new technology
And really appreciate the way Healthcare is being delivered
Kiran Houston
The Texas Medical Center is largest Medical Center in the world they already had an Innovations
Any chance you're plugged ourselves right in the middle of that or we can deal with the startups
The companies that want to bring those new Solutions tomorrow
Okay it is just focused mostly on
The Professional
Health and wellness as opposed to like
Activity tracker
Absolutely
Not it actually is
We're taking
We're looking at really kind of four key areas
Some of that is actually in the home itself
How can we be able to connect
Patients and their information
With their Healthcare professionals
Dealer-to-dealer up
Location
Monitoring remote visits
We're doing work in the clinical setting about how can we make
Better experience
Ecosystem
Nowhere
Actually all the assets are the
You need to be
Patient
Working a lot around mobile caregiving as well as those
Yes we can take this
Not just her Urban but even then trolls marketplaces
And then there's another final Focus
It's really about what all kind of call the connected Hospital itself
About you're really looking at
What are the operations
Ava Hospital
And all the things that need to move
Coming into the hospital leaving hospital as well as
Fuel mixture
Running as efficiently in a text
And how does AT&T
Think about its role here
Because
SIM card in this
Let's go to hospital blood pressure monitor inside the hospital
And
How do you guys see your role because it feels like
With The Foundry efforts you must be
Taking on a much deeper role and I'm curious
What that role is and then what have you learned from
Like your previous foundries that you hope to apply here
Yeah really for AT&T perspective we want to enable
Activity into any solution
Beginning
Start of it
We also take a multi Network approach so that
You might be able to use
Biotechnology to put that in but you might
2002 use
Some other types of Technology
Within
I was in the hospital
Free Wi-Fi
So you can be wired to assets
An attacker just made an announcement
Hello Satellites
Danielle a while ago about doing it with kids
Yak activities places
Networks don't exist
But then once you're connecting it is what can you do
Yeah with the information from back
Several different platforms
Do we bring to bear
Where are we can
Begin to aggregate the data from these in devices
We can actually going to take action against the data
We called me
Flow designer
We also have the ability to
Really
Provisions these different services
Down to the individual advice level level
All this on a global scale
And let's talk about how that turns into
Are you guys because
Verizon
And kind of have a similar like
Supercloud
Activity portions
Seems like
They told me that
They come up with the idea that about 80% of the revenue with iot was going to come from applications 15% with come
Platform and only 5% would come from the connectivity
I'm curious
Is true for you guys or if that's something that you're like
Maybe that's there
SA
There are definitely different
Places where
You can generate
Valuing
Revenues are being created within the industry activity
Actually Foundation
I did it going to continue to
Your grow in
Anxiety can be created based upon
Services that are coming out
A lot of what we call these low-power wide area Networks
RR brand new that are launching
There anyone else
How to use r
Arctic macroalgae Networks
To be into many more devices because we can reach
Different buildings
Or we can reach further we have longer battery life
Well as well as we have lower-cost
What does Solutions and so I think that there is
There's a lot of opportunity in connectivity alone
And then I think it is about you
Wants to watch you have it connected
And what can you do with
Cheetah
From those connections
How can you either
Transformer business is operating
I will transform the consumer experience by connecting things that make snacks
He said that carriers
Would start to have to worry about the last meter
Where before you guys kind of stopped at the last
I thought it was actually really telling statement especially when you're talking about
Multimode on the networks
He was hopping across different Networks
Also thinking about
My provisioning each individual device
Is that kind of a ways to start thinking about 10 of the internet of things and you guys
Yeah it's I think you're going to see exactly what she do
Transpired
Example in that in that electric space is it
We have a lot of
Taylor connectivity to a hub and then I use a different type
Local area network
I am licensed a southern reach the individual meter
So you're going to have a beer and have some
Dedicated
Chevy straight into and twice as well
And at the end of the day it's a
It is going to be about how do we
Effectively secure
Solutions
Using that advice layer at the network layer
Application layer and using the visibility that AT&T has around all the
Traffic that goes across our Networks
To make sure that we can see real-time into the potential
Other things that you know as we as needed so I think
We are definitely reaching further and further into the various endpoints
Is there a Surface Technologies
And just
Last week actually Erickson
And I thought this was kind of interesting about 28 billion devices
This was down from 50 billion
What still alive
1.5 billion would be cellular
And the rest would run over
Other networks
Does that number feel right to you
But yeah I think that's Harrison
Report end and research
Beijing TV
Opportunity
Yaya Toure
Put together a fabric Network
Well
So depending upon
Royal
Rig in their Motors doing something agriculture
Doing something
Driving
Yeah you're going to need to make sure that you're putting
The devices on the best network
For the exchange locations
Okay let's talk about
Consumers
I am actually an AT&T consumer because you guys provide connectivity in my car so thank you for that
Excited
My car is actually paid for by the manufacturer so the connectivity
I don't pay for it
But if I
At some point in time it's possible that I might pay for
And get a monthly subscription
Or have to get a monthly fee
Subscription in without it I think my car becomes a lot less used
What do you think the pricing starts to look like for things
Looks like that to Consumers
Finally
Do they feel
Good about that today like okay I'm going to buy the car and I'm going to buy subscription plan
Or is it something that maybe
Follows the Amazon Kindle model because
Self-driving cars these things aren't even going to work without
Connectivity so that it feels like it might become
Yes I think this is a place where AT&T is really young
Pleasant pleasant world
Different billing capabilities test
Bringing to the automobile manufacturer
I am and all those models exist
Today
We all we got
And what we allow the automaker
What services
Do they want stay for and then which ones
What day does she like
And we have what we call a
Billing capabilities
So I'll give an example
You got a car
Where are the automobile manufacturer is wanting to
Pull update off of the vehicle
Two operating over the air updates
Make the vehicle work better
And that's going to be a wholesale relationship between us
About automobile manufacturer to be able to
Help AT&T records. Conductivity and typically not charged
Build a tan customer
Credit card
Or even adding on to your AT&T Mobile Share bill
Where you got a big bucket today to your article from AT&T
$10 a month
All right
Let's talk for a little bit about the Smart Home
Because it is a Hot Topic this week
I think what a lot of people are coming at their they're realizing right now that maybe the Smart Home
I'm seeing a lot of the smart home is stupid the smart home is dead
And you guys offer
AT&T Digital Life I've seen ads
What do you think about kind of the evolution of the smart
AT&T
That's a great opportunity not only
Security from a foundation
Perspective it then
Once you've got the kind of chilly for the home and how can you bring other services
Automation
Home automation Solutions
To bear
And so
More more traction
I am more accustomed to taking
Get well beyond the basics of conductivity
I'm getting into you a lot of these different services
But it is complex to manage and being able to manage all that through a single interface
Is really resonating with the end consumers
If you want that you go out to try to
6 difference
Solutions if you want to be able to stand up in your home and your six different applications
Do you need to manage in order to
Make it all work that becomes a very complex situation
AT&T will go out to your home
How do you install
Dissolutions get setup
Appropriate and give you a single interface
Solutions
That that is where we really have to differentiate our offer
And it raised our homes
Solutions
And with other things were doing such a
Connect a car
So you think about our AT&T Drive Studio we're actually demonstrating this
Today
Where are your car as is
The Neighbourhood
It automatically
It's over 8000 sensera and invisible
5 miles out
Automatically have your thermostat lowers
As you approach the driveway the lights come on out to go on
And in Sodus
Ability to seamlessly
Happy sings interface
Without you having to
Do anything other than drive to and from your home
Is another great value proposition that where we are beginning to pull together different parts of the ecosystem and make more coarse a muscle
In our consumers willing to pay for this
Absolutely I think consumers are always willing to pay for Value that they get
Okay final question
What are you most excited about when it comes to the internet of things and what
Turntable
I think what I'm most excited about is the fact that
We are beginning to see
How
These things
Darion networks are beginning to
Take care of ourselves versus Outsiders take care of her
I think
When we start getting into a lot more
Predictive
Solutions NM
Things are really enabling my life to work
Easier making a lot of my business
Operate more efficiently
Because I'm not having to worry about
Manufacturing Florence
The park
Might be about to fail
Yeah it knows that it's going to fail and it automatically doors replacement parts so it's sitting
Machine
Before the machine goes off
Beaver place
Yeah my doctor's alerting me that it looks like I'm about to get sick
Because if they've got information
It looks like things are trending the wrong direction I think this
Data science
The interestings is where it really gets exciting for
I think from a malpractice
The standpoint
Really stressed out
So Chris thank you so much for coming on the show
Thank you so much for having me here today we're very excited about overdoing it
That's it for this week thanks for joining
Will see you next week on the Internet of Things podcast