Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your hosts
Amanda
Kevin tofel
And today
We have
We have a show for you today
We're going to get started
Some talk about Trump
Because last time we recorded the show
Weah
We didn't have a
President-elect Trump an update to the routers a little bit about
Little bit about Verizon a new Wi-Fi water sensor that is
This is so new
People would like to know about
Bread connected even with a i
And
Solutions for my Google home problems from last week
We also have a message from our sponsor Bluetooth
And our guest is Rob Martin
A futurist
Porsche leg
The lock company
Talking about
You guess it
Doorbells
Locksmith
Before we get to all of that
I want to give you
This week's sponsor
Which is Samsung
Are you a manufacturer service provider looking for the fastest path to enterprise-grade secure interoperable in an
Intelligent iot based products and services Samsung artik Smart iot platform is that
Learn more about how to leverage Arctic
Arctic. IO I actually signed up for this because you can actually control Raspberry Pi
Send stuff through your Echo I check that out let y'all know how that goes
All right
Now onto the show
Yeah we recorded last week a little bit early because
I was traveling I want to interfere with my right to vote so
I think we recorded on Monday we voted on Tuesday and then the show came out later
Does the first timer talking about
President-elect
Kevin
The Battleground state
Pennsylvania
Yeah yeah
And then just to be clear we're not we're not here to trial up or talk about politics or left vs right views we want to talk about
El potential
Policy changes could impact the Smart Home
The climate and so on and I say climate only because I think my old house I had 41 solar panels and have a Chevy Volt
4 years and I miss both of those
Townhouse
But
With this
Presidential
Shange
Looks like a lot of the
I I would I suspect a lot of the subsidies
Is for those type of things are going away so I'm
Literally scrambling to
Change my car I think
Logo with us
Another vltor need a bolt
I know you love yours and I know why and I look for used ones and I couldn't touch one for under 49 or 50
Grand and that's just more than I can or want to spend right now
So
I think what I will do is look in the
30-ish thousand-dollar range that is Alexa a lot of option scares far more options than
Back in 2013 when I
I should say four more viable option
10 miles in 2013
Squeezable 2013
3 years and it was great for us cuz you didn't have any range anxiety you need to go 40 miles
300 some odd miles with gasoline
Now it's I think it's 53 miles on a battery with a new volt
And
Even further with the gas generator that's in there
But I'm actually intrigued by this new Chevy bolt with a B
I don't have seen this Stacy I have why is that better
Why are you introvert
It's a little more expensive right of the battery it's also not on any
GM dealership place as of
Right now at least when I checked yesterday I was looking into this you know
Because the size of the battery qualifies for a full $7,500 federal tax credit currently
I just like the volt in many other
Vehicles based on the battery size
By the way
So if you buy something with a smaller battery mean I got $7,500 in my pocket
It's 4154
Maybe a spark EV or a Kia Soul or whatever
Any case I'm the bolt is all electric
The cost of electricity to go a certain distance is
Cheaper than the cost
2 Diesel and gas than the math many many times
And obviously
It really didn't matter at all when I have solar panels because I was creating my own electricity so that was a beautiful combination right there
Don't have those but I still would like to go Electric
Not just because it's cheaper though but because of the emissions and
Literally just before the election I had seen
Before the Flood
A documentary from 3/9 go on climate change and whether you believe it or not
I recommend people go watch it at least just educate yourself and make a more informed
Decision on climate change
And since then I've actually made some changes in my life I've
Got rid of beef
You can watch the documentary understand why I did that
And also have thought about
The emissions that were put in there
Yes I love being an electric car in like
The fact that I can
But if I need to I can idle I don't usually idle ever
But like if I'm stuck at a traffic light on my car I'm not doing anything
Exactly
Nike with your solar panels back in the day
I do
My car does
Take energy which can be generated in unfriendly ways
In Austin
Yeah
For the premium
So that's one and I wrote in my
My newsletter last week I actually did a thing on
What Trump means for the internet of things and I should tell you guys
The cyber
I should tell you guys that I have this iot newsletter so please go to Stacey on iot
Dot-com to sign up
If that's your thing and you want to hear even more coyotes
But basically based on the things that he has said
And written in his like contract
100 days contract
What Kevin said is
Probably true
I would worry about my subsidies and get that in for green stuff
Solar electric vehicles
And get that in early
If you are
Thing about smart cities though I would say that he actually could do
A lot there because
He plans on making infrastructure investment
So I anticipate seeing a switch from
Smart cities marketing from things like
OLED conserving energy to
Oh
What's what grade are infrastructure
So
That could
Be good I talk to parents are the personal details and Rehabilitation obviously you know
Something new it feels like
Why wouldn't you start
Implementing some of these kind of sensor BAE Systems
We'll see the other thing is I was at a conference and there was someone
Cubesat
They're the tiny little satellites that are very cheap to produce you toss them up in
Into space in space
No Utah some up and those guys were concerned that
Trump Vice
Change the licensing agreements for how they share they sell their information all around the world except
Countries like Iran
North Korea
They're worried that that might change
So the data that they share their data green
Smite
Being finished
They were actually pretty
Bullish on a trump presidency because they said the defense spending would be
Phenomenal
There is that
And that's pretty much
Where things stand
For the smart home perspective because I actually just had someone ask me
Trump's economic policies
Make
Life worse off for the middle class
Then we're probably going to see people stop spending
Devices
At a macro-level the trends that are affecting
Industry
Really actually work
For the internet
It's because
We need to have more efficient
Production
So
Goal of putting sensors and boosting Roi by tracking things a little bit more accurately
That's probably still going to happen so
Hillside on the Enterprise side
We're still going to see Investments made
Connected devices robotics
That's probably bad for people
Since we don't have policies for
Ra training
Probably
So
I would agree and I would just add one other thing
And I don't know the answer this question then I don't expect you to answer to either bud
I'm wondering how many of the
Connected and smart home devices
Currently
On the market
Made in countries where there could be
New tariffs and so on which could impact prices and further
Reduce demand for them
Yes
That is actually
You're welcome that's why I'm here
Why you're here
Yes
So all of the terrorist if those policies going to place that will raise the cost of
It's possibly quite substantially
Can we didn't even get into the surveillance
State stuff
That's a whole another show
If you are concerned about that
I'll put some links in the show notes to like how to secure your
Better if you're really that concerned about it
You're probably not buying the sketch
This is my hunch
So if you suddenly have become concerned
What about it then I would recommend unplugging these gadgets
And not buying anymore
Which is
Terrible thing to say
But I'm going off the grid
That's it
Is my last show
This is it
Call me by phone now. I'm not even taking phone calls smoke
I'll send you a carrier
Iot podcast
Via telegram this week on the ioc podcast
All right
So
Smart home things that are worth talking to
Which is
What is this this is a
Mesh Network router
I have routers
Routers
Have three of them in my house
Covering tile 2500 square feet
The end they are
Basically getting an upgrade
So
It came out
About this time last year
That's about right
Early this year
Costa Rica
9 months having sex
Enough time to make
So they had enough time to do a giant refraction what's going to happen is your Eero router is if you have them
They're going to get about 2x faster
Because what they've done is they've taken data
On everybody's network connection so when you're having a
Good time a bad time
Wi-Fi is working is not working
They actually
Grab all that and they've figured out how to optimize
Their connections
Completely different type of meshing
And everyone's going to see 2x faster
A big complaint with Eero was that if you don't
Was that
Each subsequent hop on the network
If you don't have them plugged into your land
Actually degrades the speed and that is true
You're still going to get 2x faster so
Yay
Faster is better
And that's if you have the bandwidth
So if you were already maxing out your bandwidth and you were getting that all the way through your house that's not going to change
They cannot change that magically change your ISP
Tattoo Expo
They also did a couple things
Consider worth
They created an echo integration
And so now you can ask the echo to find a device in your home so any devices connected to Wi-Fi in your
You're home you can as of
Today
This witness podcast goes out if you are
Once you get the update
Because I think they're doing it
You can say
Hey she who shall not be named
Find my
IPhone
And it will say
Oh that's next to the router in the bedroom
So
You're like oh it's probably
In the bedroom now obviously
In my house I have that three routers so I've got more
Mark remson that it's it's only going to give me a general location but it's nice
You can also tell it to pause the internet based on family profiles that they rolled out earlier this summer so I could pause my daughter's thing
Talking to the echo
She could also unpause it by commanding the echo to do
The opposite
So
This is not a great strategy
And my favorite is you can turn off the LEDs
Your
Eros
Thank goodness
I say that not just to the folks at Euro but any manufacturer of
Smart home devices
Get that you want LEDs on your
Devices to
Show information
But sometimes we're trying to sleep and we don't need to see blinking lights and everything else in the
I have electrical tape all over LEDs on some devices just for this reason because it drives me nuts
Say about like a rest
All of mine
It's a multi-step process since we have so many
I suspect like short just be like
Is part of your like goodnight setting
All your LEDs power down
Oh my God thank you thank you thank you
Alright so those are the big
There's also
More information about your connected devices so you'll get data like if something's having a crummy connection you can actually go into the app and see
Hey it's not me
My TV really is struggling right now on the network
And it'll blame your ISP if that's the person play more it'll blame
I guess you're not
Sentence that actually super helpful that I do not have Eros I tested them I love them
I just didn't want to spend 499 for the 3-pack of the time
Silent music
Google
Onhub
And that app
Destiny very similar I've used it so many times to
Troubleshoot what's eating up all my data right now why does it have a bad connection and someone say before it starts
Super handy
And
In all of our news about security
All the mishaps with the Mirai botnet
Using your connected devices for today
Distributed denial-of-service attack
Not this update but an update coming out
They said enough
Weeks
They will actually provide in the app the ability to look and see if your devices are generating like way too much
I would like that to be notify
Vacation by
But yeah
That's a good first
Right now most people
Not easily anyway not unless you wanna look at archaic
No web pages can I get to your router
Getting around to find that stuff not + since you change your password
This is how
Reset the router
That's at speaking of security
Z-Wave which is one of those mesh Network
18 protocols it's wireless
Protocol like
City
And they have boosted their security
Or will
Booster seat
They as of April 2017 all wheat Z-Wave devices will have to have
A new level of security they're calling the S2 framework
So they're pushing everybody with a Z-Wave device to adopt this protocol
How to be certified
Open question
If portable devices have to use it
Yeah
But
It says
You know to pass certification to be in the mark
For consumers so my guess is your old devices don't if they can I'm hoping that manufacturers will update them
But
We'll see
Yeah it doesn't seem like this is a
Well that and or a
That it requires certain new hardware
You know like there's no new security chip or anything involved here
Instead they're adding the use of a QR pin code on devices for pairing
Set me your
You have been proven Authentication
And they said they strengthen their Cloud communication
For all a Z-Wave over IP traffic
Social Security office
Tunnel
And remove other vulnerabilities through like man in the middle attacks inside
To me that is not
Speak to
Hardware but so I'm thinking old devices could adopt
Yes we'll have to see
But this is good this is necessary this is actually been a standard was UA since the last
Upgrade
And now they're finally pushing it because holy cow everyone start
Security in The Internet of Things
So
Keep talking
Real quick
I just noticed something as I'm scanning through some of the information that they did send us
They say all gateways L Z-Wave Gateway 2500 series chips
And all devices that allow over there upgrades are able to add as to two existing devices
Well there we go
There we go
I don't know what chips are in my products but I will
Yeah
Let's see if I can find that I have some really old Z-Wave devices I'll be on
Honest so my dad
Confident those will not be there
My hunch is because those devices talk through a hug so I talk to my new wink hub
And because they focus so heavily on security
I will double check with them but I'm fairly confident that that's going to be part of
The wink hub
Okay
Okay moving right along
I met with Honeywell
This is not for people who are following
I don't know how many of the
I wanted to bring this up because I get a lot of questions about it
Honeywell actually is part of their lyrics
Program
Has a
Wifi-connected
Water sensor
That's battery powered
And this is and it's $80
I seen it for a little bit cheaper
In other places but you don't Home Depot has it for like 7
This is
Unusual because the only
There are only a few Wi-Fi powered water sensors in there
Do you think makes one
But it has to be plugged in which limits were you
I can put it
Credit sense makes one
What is $150
Which is a lot of money for a water sensor especially if you like I want to put one
Water heater
Seek
It gets it as a
So this one
Ebucks
And
This is the cool Part I
The batteries last it's three double a batteries they last for about three years they said it's depending on how often it checks
Cheetah cloud
Is no Hub required
And it comes with a 4 ft long
Chord
That also acts as a sensor
So you not only have the two kind of
Sensors on the actual
Box that is a sensor
But the board itself
Gives you like a lot of extra coverage
Cuz one of my big issues with
Water sensors is if your leak isn't where there's a detection
Didn't you want to
Guess where your leak may have to get really bad before it can
I thought this was pretty cool it also detects temperature
Humidity
So people can use it to the black wrap around it
Not where I live but where you live Kevin you could wrap it around a pipe on an exterior wall
Dysmorphic
Courts in
Basically see if your pipes going to
Fries
Yeah that's that's a big deal here in the Northeast so that would definitely be appreciated and of course I should say there about 8 bucks
Record and you can daisy chain
A lot of them together to rap
A lot of places
So
I thought that was really
A kind of meat product
I will probably get one for
I've had a lot of leaks but none of them are ever in anticipated spaces but
You know it's always it is comforting to have
I just wanted to tell you guys
What's a nice innovation
All right
Shear it's time
Cooking cooking with Stacy
All right
I reviewed
The June oven
And for those of you guys who are not familiar with
Let me wrap
Waxing rhapsodic about the June oven countertop oven
That is slightly larger than a toaster oven
And basically it's 22 inches wide it's about
13 in tall 18 in
It has
Everything
I know it it's it's a connected stove it's got Wi-Fi
The camera
So what's cool about it is it's got a camera in it
And a graphics processor and you put your food in
It's got weight sensors in the feet of the oven
So when you put the food in
It weighs it
It sees what it is
And then it's like oh I know what this is
I already have a preprogrammed recipe
And hit it
And it Cooks it and it Cooks It
Perfectly
So
Yeah I know you guys are like
Well
How much is this it's it's $1,500 guys it's 1495
$5 switch
That's a lot of money
But it's amazing
Like I could
Over a dozen things this weekend
And I would say the baked goods
They're working on it they're going to tweak the algorithms for this so they'll come out better but I don't know if I do a lot of baked goods in it
Anyway because I could only fit like 9 cookies on their tray
You can only fit
Things in it that are
I think it's 9
Yeah you're limited on size of
Baked goods indoor Universe some meat or something like that you know
11 by 6
CU tribute
Traditional Pyrex cake
Casserole pan
And stuff like that you can
Roast a 5lb chicken in it
But you cannot do it then
Guys
I wanted to sing so much and everything I made in it
Was so good
And you have a lot of money to spend
And I would definitely like actually even if you don't like
It's probably better for people don't like to cook cuz you could just slap some
Seasoned salmon on a tray with some vegetables and just pop it in there and
He'll be like hey dude
This is salmon
Or actually is a salmon in
How would you like your salmon cooked
Medium
And then
It does it
It's got a temperature probe is all that you can use
To really hone in on the right internal temperature for
For baking
Yes for rosacea
Resting okay
You would not I'm sorry my bad
I don't know how
Order out a lot that's probably I just evidence
So yes the temperature probe inside is accurate within 1 degree according
Pitchoun
I tried the temperature probe with my current
Digital thermometer
Kris cell
Either way it's still felt pretty
So this is like
My favorite and
My husband
And he doesn't like anything else
Yeah I mean it definitely is a compelling
Smart device no doubt about it
The price is obviously going to put out of
Reach of a lot of people
Although I mean you can spend a lot on high-end kitchen appliances obviously tsareena
Oven is 700
$50 for the
Doesn't do much no convection
My ovens in my house
Where $1,500
So
Their stainless steel
Are out there they are self-cleaning
They have to convey
I actually just have
There are Futures on other
And this is also a convection oven
Does toasting
I would say to someone
If you're interested in
This it will replace your toaster
Which is not an a
But if you don't have double ovens
And you want that
I would look into getting this because you can do quite a bit with it
And I mean I would cook dinner in it probably
Three or four nights
If I have it
I mean if you're not guaranteed but you're almost guaranteed to have a perfect outcome
That could make up for some of the compromises I tried to make in terms of size for example and cost and so on so
It's interesting the bacon that we cooked should have been
Better done
The chicken
The pork
The salmon
Kale chips
Potatoes
It all came out perfect
It was
And it came out perfectly without me having to check on it
Which is also nice cuz we had guests over cuz it was a
Inordinate amount
It was nice because I wasn't going back to the oven and checking it I was just like
Set it forget it
When it's play it plays a little song
I think the real potential here is the fact that the product will likely get better because it will learn overtime they will be more recipes out of
The food identification
Could improve
You maybe you'll be able to tweak it
And say you like I like my baking a little more crispy and it will learn to know that next time
By default it will just make it the way you wanted as opposed to the default way
Yes
And that's the beauty like
What I like about this is they took a product they made it better
They changed the material of the heating element so it heats up
Faster that's nice that got to convection pans in it
Where most happens only
That is also nice
And then they added this layer of Intelligence on top of it to make it really idiot
And it will get better with time
When thinking about designing a connected product
They didn't just say hey let's put a chip in it
Right behind thought about the
No I don't see this becoming like a huge
Widespread Panic
Definitely an oven of the future
Let's talk about
Google
Google home
Here's what we're going to say that Kevin works for Google
He does not work on the
Disclosure
Last week
Last week I talked about Google home in my issues of connecting my Philips Hue Lights
This was both like a
Dang this is disappointing cuz I can't test it
Infinity
It was just funny because of the Google support
So
Update on Google support did get back to me with an email
And the email did not
Actually help me at all
It was a seven-step email
In 5 Steps
It was basic troubleshooting and meet you Stacy add share the email with me and I looked at it a cycle reset this and repair that and try
Turn this off and on again
Very very
Standard
Personally
Credits and fortunately there was a very specific solution of this and nobody asked the right question in my opinion
Sub solution
In which
Someone actually suggested Ma
W
And Phillips also
Confirmed
For me
They actually reached out after
Podcast and said hey
So what the issue was is I was using Adblock as my browser
A block is not supported in either is Firefox so far
And you were using the browser to do what
So the way this is set up is
You
Give me
Google home app
When it comes time to add a device and you choose the Philips Hue Lights it takes you out to a browser
Ryuk
Complete
Authentication process
So in that
Process
My browser was like
And that's what broke thing
You have to use
Chrome Safari
Feel like there's an
Maybe Edge or ie
Let's not go there that's a whole nother story
Chrome horse
Safari RC
They just haven't gotten to supporting it
Sew-in and I get that
But I do think
So now it works I've connected my lights they work
Perfectly it's lovely
I did that by setting Chrome as my default browser for the setup
And then I swapped it back to Adblock
A lot of people especially on mobile devices
Use different browsers
Uncommon
So it felt like Google at some point of time should have asked that question
In
No one did
I completely agree with you I think that's a little bit of a real they're definitely area of opportunity
In that mean I don't want to defend but
The only thing I can think of is
Do the support people know which browsers
Are supported by Phillips web authentication which ones aren't I don't know
But that's
Really
Kind of a lame excuse
And I'm not
What is the brand new thing so I'm sure this is now a known issue that
You know
Possible if I called support today that
They would be like
Hey
What browser
Podcast
Shirley.
We spent also last we talked about the Google home a little work around for basically connected more things to it
That's right that's right we mentioned the Google Assistant channel on if this then that
And I actually just before the show last week and tried it but was having some issues
And I do not have a Google home
But that's okay because remember this is a Google Assistant Channel
Assistant is built into home but it's also built into the new Google pixel phones which I do have
So after the show I figured out what my issue was and
It had to do with the naming like
When you create
The new applet
It's a turn lights on when turn lights on through my wink hub for example of using Google Assistant
I was
You would have type the command that if this then that is going to listen for or Google assistant listen for
And I was putting OK Google in there and I didn't need to do that and I'm sorry if I just saw everybody's phones and Google homes by the way
So it was
You can say user on my part to me it's not really clear that you don't need to do that but whatever
I got it working really well and Ashley for the first time I can use my phone
Very easily
And natively to control lights in my house through this if this then that Apple that I created
There's only one downside and that's pretty standard I think with any
Cloud-based service would you give this man that is
There is more latency then
Using say the Wink app to do this
Dancing with my Wink app
If I do it through the actual one second delay for a light will go on or go off and I could
Be annoying at times I think
Yes it would be nice like if your phones by your badge
Turn off the lights downstairs
Which would be handy
But if you're like walking into a room
Presence
Yeah they're going to walk into something before Life Goes On
That's bad
That's bad and your lights
Attached herewith
They're a mish-mosh I have some
Cree bulbs in fact I just bought a
Four packs of
Cree bulbs are those are not connected bulbs
I do have some connected Cree bulbs
And I have the osram lightify
As well
I do not have any Philips Hue on my network my son has the Hub and does his own thing with those balls
I do not controllers
He was supported
Rights that would have worked
Natively
Okay so I could actually mess with his lights by voice
He doesn't listen to show I can say
There you go
Ed we have one listener question
Which
Good point Ithaca
Missy Brian Wood asks
Via Twitter
Why do smart light bulbs get so much attention
Is it a smart switch for Outlet more useful
I got a couple thoughts on that one
That's a good question it's a good question and I'm glad Brian it a steady just asked it on Twitter just this morning before the show so good
Number one
I think about it in terms of
Convenience choice
And cost Queen Elsa goes three things the three C's
There's no question a Smart Switch or an outlet is useful I have some of them might have a couple of smart outlets for example and then the way
Wink relay is a Smart Switch
That added smarts
To a non smart pot which is great
Switches typically cost roughly 40 50 bucks or more
Rapper that wears a bulb connected
Can be had for less than 20
I'm so there's a cost involved
There's also convenience I mean people listen to show
Probably okay with some
Swapping out switches and
Playing with electrical wires
Shorting out the HVAC systems like I've done but it's a lot easier to just
Changeable
Quite honestly so
For folks who don't want to mess with electricity
About is easier
And then a switch add smart stew
Dogs yes but
Some bulbs actually have more functionality just because they are smart bulbs whereas
You know that she was a pretty simple changing the colors
On your Hue bulbs are not going to really easily do that with most witches
That's one example
I also have those
Balls that are
Tunable
To soft light
Soft white rather or daylight
Again not easily done with just a switch
So I think you get more
Choice with a smart dog those are my
Three of the top of my head
Okay and mine are a little different
It depends kind of situation so
A lot of my lights
Our I don't have a lot of
Clamps so if I'm changing out all the light bulbs in my kitchen is actually cheaper
For me to install the switch
Install
And because that is a room where we lie
I only want certain functionality I don't need
The colors to change in my room
Are in my kitchen
So for their I'm like
A switch makes sense cuz I'm just going to dim it up
Quit
If you want the tunable wipes
There is no dimmer
There's no Smart Switch that can offer
Today
And they're made
The other thing to know is with a light bulb
You lose the ability to turn off your switch
Which if your label is connect
Because when you do you break the light bulb
It's off
So
Practical rooms
That's kind of my thought is
Uno swap out your switch for your mean
Jermaine lighting
Four lamps I think a connected
Light bulb actually is really interesting because
It's fun to play with colors and that sort of thing
So that's kind of where
I've come down on it so swap out your switch if you can
I really like Lutron
I'm just going to tell you
WeMo has a Wi-Fi switch
I was switched at
Is
Off on but it is not
Dimmable
And people are really iffy
That's
Most people do not
The best solution
And there's a couple new
Wifi powered light switches like
Sun Life is one
Are supposedly better but I haven't tried them there's the wink relay
But also no
If you put a connected switch in
You cannot have a connected
Light bulb
So you can't have a Lutron light
With a connected
Philips hue light bulb
For example
You basically lose
Those are my thoughts I think
It's not a clear-cut answer
No no it's these definitely not a perfect example that is I have far more lamps in my house than you do is what
From the sounds of it
Three lamps
Yeah we have a lot of lamps and
You know we just made sense to go with
Smart bulbs for those I'm not saying smart bulbs is a better choice for everybody who sang
In my circumstances made Morse
Yeah and you
Yep
Baidu
So yes
It depends
But there you got a little bit I think
So you can
What do I want to spend my 50
All right
That is a lot to show for us this week
Let us prepare for our guests Rob Martens
Who is a futuristic Schlage we're going to talk about locks
And before we do that we're going to have a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone this is Stacy and we are breaking into podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Bluetooth
Set a timer about this we have the director of marketing at the Bluetooth Sig
Caddyshack
I believe you are here this week to tell us about the imagine blue
What are those
ICC thanks for having me
Imagine blue Awards
Really high like the work and imaginations of readers
Of designers and for students
Who are using Bluetooth technology
To really push the boundaries of Wireless connect
Tivity we've seen things from Smart light bulb with built-in mesh technology
To automatic gear shift for bicycle
Spiritual words
Sissy are two categories
Prototype in
Student
With a Chance
To win cash prizes ranging from $5,000 to
The $10,000
So tell me more about the divisions and the price
The perfect category is for innovation
Markets
I want all the student category is for individuals
School college
Postgraduate
It's cool to have an idea concept or maybe even a working prototype on how life can be better with
The Prototype finalists
They'll be invited
World in March of next year
Where they can showcase their entry at our booth that'll put them in front of Developers
In front of entrepreneurs and even in front of prescient analyst
They'll also be
With the $10,000 cash prize
Finalist will be showcasing a blog post
Bluetooth Com
Ml
Receive a $5,000 cash prize
Awesome
Sahara
People apply
Two-ply you simply go
To Bluetooth
Is.com
Imagine
It's really open to anyone once you go to that website there will be information on how to submit
Either your prototype if you were
Submitting for the Prototype Awards
Or an overview of your idea of prototype
Or a video if
You're submitting in the student category
And what's the deadline to apply to apply is December
What have you guys
Listen to brilli exciting products come out from previous
Among the winners last year
Motorcycle tracker
It's an advance
Bluetooth Beacon tracking
System that improves
Food safety
So it makes it easier and more reliable
Follow suit
Foodstuff from Farm
Two tables
There's a reason
Smart app which connects your hearing aid
To your phone
Apple watch
See you can manage
Personalize your hearing experience every year the amount
Blue
Awards demonstrate that the Internet of Things
This is not just hype it's
Real and it's becoming
More important everyday
I were really excited to see what this year's award brings us
Awesome
Me too
So where can
People go once again
And to find out
People should go to www.
Bluetooth.com
Flash imagine blue to learn more about the awards and to apply
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
What is Rob
Martin's
Rob is a futurist and vice president of strategy and partnership for Allegiant
Which is the owner of Schlage
Probably really large lock
Company that you guys have
So hi Rob how are you doing
Hi Stacy how are you
So
I have you on the show because I love the title futurist
And I'm happy to talk to anybody who is a few
What do you do in your day-to-day life
Actually
Well my number one role Within
Wag and Allegiant is
The challenge old ways of thinking
So I spend a lot of time looking at new tax
New trends new processes and trying to figure out how to apply it
Back
To our products to benefit our
Consumer
Kenneth Lee to a big part of my job is to try and demystify things like the iot
Let's get started on that for your business
What is an actually we should stress that your business is both residential
Multifamily and Commercial so that's that's everybody
For your business
How are you guys
Looking at the Internet of Things how do you demystify that for your
Wilshire obviously you know a very complex space but probably the fast
This growing
Megatrend that that we see within our business
Probably you know the biggest thing we're trying to do right now
Is improve that customers
Experience on the residential side of
The market
Things are really honky right now
So when you buy things off the shelf some people are having experience
Is where you really need to be at a key
In order to I get the product to work the way that you wanted to work so
Our focus is how can we improve that in quite frankly
Falling to the Cadence
Somebody is today
Rather than being an interrupter
I like it
So let's talk about you guys and you're connected locks cuz when I first started my smart home dirty way back into
I think I had a choice of like a Z-Wave or maybe it was a zigbee lock from
You guys
Where are y'all today
Talking purely about the residential segment here for a second
We came out with our first connected lock back in 2008
And this was a little early was called slay bling
And that was
AZ wave
Connected
Keypad deadbolt
And so you would be able to
If still have to solve actuated another word that didn't have a motor you would get the permission to drop a pin and you could turn the deadbolt
I'll let people in or out
But since then there's been
Huge growth
So
We have a whole variety of
D-wave lovers
Z-Wave touchscreen deadbolts that have keypad
MNR latest
Creation has been what we call the Schlage sense
Which is the Bluetooth low energy lock
Right now most people associate the Schlage sense with Apple homekit
But in reality
Normal BP
Expanded out
The big differentiator between our
Z-Wave products sets in RB Ali-A products at
Is that at the ble products
Ship with an application
And the big deal about that
Is that
Before
We have all kinds of Technology built into these locks
Accelerometers in the example
That can tell you the difference
In the fourth profile of a Kickin at M purse has a dorsal
For example
Or we can set it
Such that for example my son is
Always
Late for the bus in your runs out the front door
Never locked the door behind them
And so we can set it so
30 seconds after the door's been open and up to 4 minutes after it can Auto throw the bolt for you
This
Graphical interface just makes
Easier a better experience to program the law
Programme schedules in the event that you have
A dog walker coming
I'm you have any scheduled events
And all that good stuff
All of our touch screen
Deadbolt
Have the penis keypad
Which is fingerprint resistant
They saw the heat and cold and all in a survive all the sledgehammer attack and all the crazy stuff you'd expect
Brea
A grade 1 lock
To survive
Let's talk about security and physical access in
Control
Access control I guess
A lot of companies in the lock space
Or who are getting into the locked space are viewing it as kind of a
As a home security play or possibly as a Services kind of play so there's like the August access serve
Service which is really interesting
Where do you think Schlage is going to kind of
I guess evolve in this world are you guys going to just be better locks which is totally fine are you guys going to try to move into some sort of
Other offer
No I think you're going to see us evolve in
And I think it
Really fantastic the whole crowdfunding
A movement although you know we've seen some crazy things come out right
Not all of them very useful
But interesting ideas that really helped to transform the station
Created a lot of opportunities within the category itself
I'd say the most important
Singing in our North Star is worth
Security company first
And we believe there's a small group of home automation Enthusiast made out of small group
You're certainly not as big as the main screen
We Believe
That there is a mainstream underserved
Gru
People who
Are really shopping first and foremost
Or
Security
Analogue
In a lock that is going to perform as
They would expect it to historically
But then has this incremental
Benefit
I'm in that could be connected it might just be the highest got a keypad and I don't have to carry he with me
But I think it's
Going to be an evolution towards enhancing
A better outcome
For the user
Those business cases
For the end users can be pretty complex today
You see a lot of people
Who want to connect
Different things within the
Home and what we're experts at is identifying
Which ones are those are safe to do
Which ones do you really need to think about more carefully before you do it so example of one that we would suggest
Hey Carson
You know who should be
You know some caution here
Would be proximity lock and unlock
So for example
People want the Star Trek to where you want to walk up
Have the door recognize you and unlocked for your convenience
Walt
We see some gas
In terms of the technology
Where is identifying Where You Are
Necessarily in proximity to the lock
Depending on where your garage
Example
Time you may be parallel to the lock or inside the home
And may inadvertently trigger The Loft open
And
It may be an infant a small a small chance
But you really have to ask yourself if your son or daughter or loved one is on the other side of the door and there's a
After Decline
And it unlocks and they hear it
Is that worth it
Sure and what I think about locks
That's a space where there might be some liability issues to
If someone wanted to pursue them and I don't know if that kind of
Obviously if you are a lock brand
That's your bread and butter is that your locked
Or unlocked at the person's will right
So having these
Potential for mistakes or uncertainty
Feels like it could be both a liability and a brand Issue 4
Are you guys how do you even innovate if you've got that kind of
A Culture of Fear there
I think
The easiest way to describe it
To say there's always a balance
Between physical
Security inconvenience
It's always try to do is educate the consumer on
This is the most secure element
And hear some choices that you have and you can diminish a little bit of your security and gain some convenience there
But understand what it is
In the balance that you're trying to
Get there
So this is just a physical like locking and unlocking
King future
But once you put something online so with your Bluetooth
Lock for example
Or maybe if i integrated my zwave locks to a wink hub
Suddenly I am now has thrown in another partner for you guys that you may or may not know about and I've also
Open up another Avenue of attacked
To the Internet so how are you guys thinking about
Could have internet
Absolutely enough
The big question or one of the big question
For me
It says you're only strong as your weakest link
Sounds cliche but it's absolutely the truth and so
We spend a lot of time with the Hub providers
And with our partners
Identifying
We're through that chain
Routine
Or robot or depending on your
You know when you're on your vendor they all have different names for it
Which ones will be allowed and which ones will not
The allowed
And quite frankly we asked
Spell subject matter experts for them on
What is
Appropriate and what is not appropriate
So
Pumpkin is a great example could you have your homekit lock
The homekit lock profile by August
And they actually recently had a
So it was on somebody said Okay Siri or hey Siri open the August door lock
And the person didn't have a password on their site
They're on their iPad and so Siri
Front door for them
Are you saying that your implementations are
Different from something like that or is there also a responsibility by someone like apple to say
Hey
Maybe we shouldn't have the door unlock verbally unless there's a password hint
Yeah I think there's a huge responsibility on the part of all the parties involved
Those types of gaps are things that we
Spend time
With them on
To try and identify again
It's that balance
Right
Between security
Inconvenience in our case we see those things as
As important gas that need to be addressed
I think it's also healthy to say and I'm not afraid to say it even as the futurist for a security company
Nothing is 100% secure
And anybody that tells you that it is
Is either naive or dishonest
And so I think there's a lot of things that
People have done
Especially people who are trying to Garner attention to a new brand
Or startup company or something like that
To try and drive it.
Perfectly secure for all these things and all that is as bait for the hacker community
You know I think another thing or subject that's tied very closely to your question
Chicken is privacy
Is well
And as we go forward
I think
Consumers going to have a lot of questions as they're comparing you know whether it's Google home and apple or SmartThings and
In Amazon
Yes they're going to have to make some choices in terms of
What information
They're willing to share from a privacy
Standpoint and what they are
In another way that we try and address some of those things is
What working hard to give options
As to whether we're going to play in a mesh Network
Does he know what that is you know Z-Wave type framework
Where
We're going to just
Share the information directly with your hot provider
Or in a cloud
Cloud type of situation where we have much work
Control over what is shared or not
But ultimately we want to put those types of decisions in the hands of the consumer
Okay and I know the cloud-to-cloud situation help me
Many years back I had someone hack my wink
And they were unable to control the Chamberlain MyQ because of the
But they were able to unlock my Z-Wave locks these were not yours
Because of the way that radio works
If I had had one on there
It's possible that it would have been locked at 2 cuz that's just
The radio the truth then you don't want you
Call Arkansas. Circumstance
What's going to take the command
From The Hub and so
I think people are Chamberlain deserve a lot of credit
For very early on
Yuan their development process
Figuring out ways
Hugh
Creatively manage some of these things without inconveniencing the consumer so kudos to them
Yay
All right
No there's been talk in Europe and there's even been talk among people here
Different organizations here about creating kind of
A sticker certification
Or maybe like a Good Housekeeping seal of approval for security
Like a security framework for devices
In the home
And I'm curious where you guys might stand on something like that
We have
Mechanical version of that
In in the form of bhma
Which you know are are
Hardware standards grade 1 lock her grades to lock or grade three lock and what those would indicate would be
You know it survive
This type of heat and cold to survive this type of
Sledgehammer attack
Kickin attempt to work
You know fire safety
We're very familiar with those texts
Frameworks and that's not necessarily A Bad Thing
What I would say is as I'll go ahead and say the expert across
A couple of different
Spaces in the commercial space
You find the standard
To be quite desperate you see a lot of proprietary Solutions
That claim to be more
Secure
And then you see a body
A group of people like Sia I'm trying to come together and provides standards not unlike
You know the ones you've been talking about on your podcast
You know all join you no excetera
I think we're certainly open
Time-in we're always looking
Shoe Drive
Open architecture and Open Standards because
We believe there's a lot better technology out there when it
Cher
I personally and in as a company we believe the proprietary definitely does not mean more
So let's talk about you guys currently support lots of difference
Cubs
Different wireless networks
Y'all are clearly out there
Doing a lot
How do you view
The lifetime of it Electra
So I feel like a lock is something I installing might like an old-school lock change those unless
You had like a break-in or something terrible has happened right this is or maybe you move
These are not
Things you
Upgrade on the
So
How do you see adding connectivity to this
Product
Changing that relationship
People have with it
So the hardware on our product
Is going to last
20 to 30 years at minimum
So
You do really get into the the question of
Okay so the hardware is going to last that long
You know just from experience the technology inside is going to change
We're trying very hard and I don't think obviously that we have this completely solved yet Stacy
But we try very hard.
What to do over the air updates
Updates
Create Headroom within the processors
And the infrastructure within the lot
Such that we can make it is viable as we possibly
And for as long as we can
So we're working really hard to try and figure out
What is an appropriate lifetime
What you also don't want to do is here
We're trying to shrink the size of these locks right they're not the most beautiful things to look at all the time especially on the interior
Terriers
But we want to have a strong motor and we want to have
Technology in there that's going to make it last
So
Your 2008 Z-Wave lock
I believe was your first one
Are those still in the market are they still working
They're still working
Yes I'm proud to say they are still working
So
We haven't
A significant enough
Drop off of some of those Technologies sale
Stacy if we see you know some of the match match Networks
You don't go away which I don't think we're going to see but
If we were to see some of those
You know Rod wife still changes
Gmic chef
We definitely do see a trend obviously especially in DIY Market
Towards a cloud to Cloud infrastructure
As opposed to let you know I'm a mess
Network infrastructure
But we actually see both of those products s living beside each other for quite some time
Alright this brings us to cost because right now A connected deadbolt
Even if it's not Bluetooth or something fancy
Still alive
Sometimes 5x the cost of a normal door lock
Is this a
Reasonable thing to expect should we see this go down
No no I think it depends on features and functions I mean
We don't know what the sweet spot is yet
To be candid
We're going to try and find that
Obviously you're investing a lot in R&D and development on these things and that's not cheap
But I think you'll start the
Sissy
Better and better solution
Coming forward with
Different features
The price points
You know somewhere people you know who might not be filled
Feeling comfortable about it today to get out there
In in to get one
I think the value prop
That a lot of people are seeing
And we have a pretty wide rain so we have a lot of
Non-connected Electronics
Deadbolt
As well
So they give you some contact
So in the last year we sold 1.1 million electronic locks
Electronic lock
A tremendous number those were actually
Lost it we're not connecting
So they have a keypad on them
You know some of the Innovation that you'll see from us that you might not necessarily expect from a company like Schlage
Will be on
How can we provide an enhanced capability for people with a specific need
For example like a landlord hey I have multiple properties
Can you
Organized he's in
But it makes me easier to manage remote properties
Reset codes all those things that you would want to do
Either a lot of other DIY devices in there as well you know you think about the
All these other devices
But you may want to set back to you know a different temperature or an original setting
Once your tenants of laughs
Oh yeah
I use the keypad door lock
Or that I use the actual
Remote connectivity
Aspect
Let's keep going
Real fast
Final question for you
Are you guys going to stick with being a devices
Company or are you looking at services
I think that
We are manufacturer
And I think that we believe
There's a
Really healthy
Land of the two
When you look at how we go to market today Stacy
We're trying to figure out how can we
Embed
The total cost
Of the device into
You know that.
Consumer another word
If you buy our product
We don't want to nickel-and-dime you to death with subscriptions and all kinds of other things
Thor trying to find a good blend
That is going to allow for us
You make it really easy
Really intuitive
It's just a good experience all the way around
Where you will see us
Yo I guess you could call diving into
Services someone
We're going to try and provide the type of app functionality over time that people are asking
The kind of what we talked about before
If you have a very specific need you know you're a landlord or no some other element
We will
Not only ourselves but with partners
Try and develop
I'm good kids that are very intuitive and easy-to-use
College was an RA a resident advisor
Benidorm
And I can tell you
Biggest pain in the butt
Was when people would forget their keys and I would have to
Either escort them my cells are called like
Somebody
Call a security person to come and unlock their door for them
I'm like wow how awesome would it be if you could just be like
We got you covered on that
Yes all the notes were capability to I need to start thinking about is when you talk about
City managers
Executive Sous job overtime
Has been to either audit doors you know for fire safety or for any number of things
Now we can really make some productivity gains for them we have a lot of what we call him no tour
Functionality where you can go and touch that lock
Without having to physically be there
I think it's also something important in a we start talking about
What's your plan
Not for if you're going to get hacked but when
How can we Flash the firmware
Quickly easily
Verses where if you had a master key solution
You know for a large campus
And if that master key got lost
You're going to go change out every single cylinder in that campus
Alright so the end of the master
At the beginning of
Omastar
Different types of security
Alright thanks Rob
Coming on the show this week I have learned a lot
And
I appreciate it
You're welcome thanks for having me Stacy that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and
And we'll see you again next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news
For this show feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
Jd.com