Hey everyone welcome back it's the Internet of Things podcast and I am your
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And Kevin I was apparently
Play feeling Grinchy this year but
For the holidays
We know that you're probably going to get
Apple connected devices
If you're listening to this show
We hope you get
We do we hope you get them unless you don't want any and then you know
We're glad you're listening to the show anyway
And since
Since this is going live on Christmas Eve
We wanted to do a special holiday podcast
In which we briefly spend a few moments with you to sing a few carols
Drink a little eggnog
I'm just kidding
Freaking out he's like there was no singing
I was reaching for my glass
You had me right now
No we wanted to do just a quick kind of like
This is our Christmas gift
Do you guys which is
Which is actually kind of a downer we're going to assume that you might have some trouble say
Merry Christmas
Yes so
In case
We're also going to assume that
We're going to try to help you out
Before you get into
So
We wanted to share advice when we're setting up connected.
Send devices what do we we've gone through all the pain point for years so that you don't have to that's our hope with us
So here we go
Starting out
Kevin you want to go with
With your your first
Tip for people
Right off the bat you've got to have patience and time put aside if you're going to be connecting your devices weather
Are there add-ons to existing system or just a whole brand new system I'm in I was joking with Stacy before the show this is now
Not the kind of project
That you didn't want to do it between say Christmas dinner and dessert
Make sure you give yourself plenty of time
And have patience
Is devices upon startup sometimes there they look like they're ready for you to add things you don't maybe you got a hubber bridge
Legend cycling headlights
Just make sure you wait sometimes babe
LED indicator sometimes it don't just be patient
And follow instructions when you should be fine
All right on that note
You need to read the
Instructions and you need to have your tools at the ready
So
So guilty of this I am often like so excited I grabbed it out of the box
A start
Trying to install stuff and then I've got like my hands full of stuff this is really important for like
Things that involve
Light switches
Locks
Actual physical installs of products
But make sure you have your tools ready
Like that include your phone
If for some reason is still like back in the early
Translate mm and has only a web app
I might need your computer
So read the instructions
Make sure you have your tools ready
I'm screwdrivers
If you need to
Turn off the power of my God turn off the power
And then
You know
Start your install
Don't be too afraid to do any of those things
Exactly exactly
And then once you really get going
The first thing I do with just about any device that I add to my house
I always check and see where in the app for where the settings
Firmware version is appearing
And usually will see a check for updates in there
Always check for updates before you even start adding devices to other devices
It's a simple process you might follow instructions to the T out-of-the-box for device
But it still doesn't work
What's usually the culprit
From where maybe something is changed and instructions
Haven't weeks or so on and they don't apply anymore because the firmware has been changed so I highly recommend making sure and every single device
Has firmware
Make sure you update that from her before you really get going
Also with this
Possibility
Make sure
Your device actually works with
Your device
So
I can't tell you how often I've been like in the Google app store or Play Store
Xiaomi
I'm looking for an app for device only to find out that it will only works with iPhones
And I'm like
That's not a big deal cuz I also have an iPhone but if you don't you're going to be kind of sad
And actually that probably should go before the other one because a bunch of open the box York
Going to be like now I can't return it
This is going to be the worst regift ever
Just to add to compatibility a lot of these products write on the box
I'll tell you what hubs and bridges and other products they work with
So just make sure before you even open it
Just make sure that
You know if I say will work with the base B if it says it's compatible on the box
You could open a keep going
Yeah cuz what if it's like
I'm sorry Mom
But what if they're like Clarity like connected devices so I got you this connected device
And then
Like oh my God but this only works with the
The wink Hub and I have a SmartThings Hub
I need this would not be a problem for me but for other people
This is true
So
I know Stacy doesn't want me to say this I'm gonna say it anyway
Oh yeah
This is so under duress you guys
So are we.
Stacy still upset that I haven't installed the
Bluetooth
Busy I'm sorry
I'm sorry Stacy is still upset that I have not installed the Z-Wave lock set on my front door
Actually I have tested it
And that actually is a good thing for this list of things to consider
I already know that the locks that works because
I took it out of the box I put the batteries in I set it up on my
With my phone
And I was actually using my phone to lock and unlock the door lock
Even though it was in the door and I say this because
Why bother
Taking out a lockset putting in a new one only if I know it doesn't work maybe you didn't put the batteries in right maybe you didn't set some
Something up right maybe there's a switch inside
So just test things before if you can test them before you actually install them
I don't think it's a bad thing I said under
That's because it's not hard
Install and uninstall lock change the batteries
Also because yes I'm mad at you for not installing the locks I said to you
Anyway moving on
Also
Kevin brought it this week
Which is really good point
About order of operation
And install
So once
When she performed are very dull and very serious checklist
Which will save you time and trouble
Start with
Especially with things like light bulbs
Start like
What was your tip there
I said start in the center Mortuary
Yeah