Hey everyone welcome to this week
Episode of The Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house
Kevin tofel
And today I am at CES we are recording this Wednesday morning
So
There is one
More preste
At the Consumer Electronics Show
But
We already have so much
To talk about
We are going to hit
More news than you can imagine
We're actually going to have a special CES
Edition of the podcast is going to come out Monday so keep a lookout
For that
And
We also because we're crazy have a guest this week we've got Tim Crawford who is basically a CIO for hire
Talking about
How cios need to think about the
The Internet of Things
So you got your Enterprise Utah
Sumer
We also have a sponsor best
Samsung
And we also have a message from this week's other sponsor
Level education
Are you prepared for the future iot is going to be huge it's going to be
So prepare for the future with iot training from Level education in Cisco they've developed
Program called iot core that is a 15-week blended learning experience for the foundational now
College associated with The Internet of Things there's going to be ample Hands-On learning opportunities
Real world examples online learning
Hackathons and project-based learning so you will emerge from this experience as iot
Ready
The course starts February 13th
And I find out more go to level edu.com
Okay Kevin
I don't even know
How are you holding up I am not at CES just to be clear
After 10 years I took a hiatus
So how are you holding up
I'm missing it a little bit missing the peeps I'm missing the the town and all the cool gadgets
And there are
Are so many cool Gadget
I have seen so much stuff so I have
Connected hairbrush
Toothbrushes
Scooters
Space heaters that are powered by CPUs that
Actually felt the compute power from them
Icing
Car stuff I've seen
Appliances that work with
The echo
I have seen
Other echoes
I've seen robots
Racine
Lights
Always sunny
I have seen the future and it is iot
Exact
There were there actually have been many cancer
Watches
I just don't care about
Basically if you can put
A chip in it
It exists so
Will kick it off with
Crazy stuff
First the craziest thing I was at CES unveiled last night which is a bunch of startups and
Keppra
Look at it
And the craziest thing I saw was connected
Grooming products
This is apparently a theme
So
There are connected toothbrushes and there have been for a while and I've actually tried it connected to
Thrush
Colibri
Never say the name
Is a French company and they're making a toothbrush
But now has a i
Help you brush better
And if you want to just come by and to macro-trends together
Iot + AI
It basically means that like this device is tracking all this data about you and it's
Trying to adapt
Become sentient and
Or breakfast
Let's hope
Monumental it's gone
This toothbrush
People that tells everything right there
I think they've had one for a while
This is $79 for this toothbrush
That's a special introductory price
I will tell you that there is a company that makes
A beam connected toothbrush that is actually the toothbrush as part of an insurance
So you buy your insurance
Invasive
Through beam and they send you this to
So
There is a business model here
I don't know if it's okay
Consumer business
No
There you go you let you know that you're brushing have
Even more ridiculous
Kevin do you want to tell them
Well considering I haven't even combed my hair yet today I think yes it would be a good thing for me to talk about
Nstemi
But I could be wrong
People may disagree and that's fine
To me this is just
A classic case of let's put chips and something and Paulette smart because we can
This is a new hairbrush
That is the collaboration of why things
Which is owned by Nokia
And L'Oreal
Which is very prominent in the personal care space
They've created a hair brush that has
Both Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
And of course it has an app
I'm not on the toothbrush on 50 a hairbrush rather but on your phone
Are there sensors in the hairbrush
Based on the sensors and
The hairbrush can determine if your hair is unruly because maybe you spend a lot of time
Coming or brushing your hair today I can tell if your hair is damaged
Has breakage is dry Tangled
How do you has a microphone
I mean microphone accelerometer gyroscope
The microphone might be useful because
The hairbrush was employed as a microphone
When we did our dance
Yeah but it's not really there for a karaoke
Hear your hairbrush patterns according to
Eric Stokes
It sounds
Interesting and interesting use of
Applying technology and sensors
Really do we really need that I mean this thing's going to cost I think over $200
As a lot of my
I will be out of
I will say the only thing the only Pro there and I wouldn't
Is my daughter has
Unruly
Tangled hair and I think part of that reason is cuz she doesn't always brush it
She's like me I asked
Also because I
And she doesn't brush her hair but she needs
And
Holy cow I would love something that's like
Brush your hair
And tells her
But that's about it
That use case makes sense to me
But I'm not even sure
That this will do that I think this is going to capture all the information of the brushing activity nut
Remind you
Tooth brushing activity
Will insult this segues nicely into another theme that I'm seeing is seeing
Witches
Data collection
So
Bye
Like so
L'Oreal I'm sure
I'm sure that the data they get here
From everybody's hair
Thousand times better than Market data
Consumers
They're like
I can sell you the exact
Conditioner and shampoo
And that kind of ties into
A couple other products
That we seen
Which is
There is a
Smart
Echo like device called the Aristotle
For kids and basically
It is a baby monitor you can talk to it
It also has a camera
What's interesting is its
It's designed to give
Your baby
Let's talk with your baby a bit
But
It also does things like if it's seizure child playing with a Mattel toy
It's going to the ideas that it will
Produce extra special effects
And then all of that data is going to go back
2 Mattel
So basically
You're spending $300 to enroll your child in the most intrusive Focus
Yes I know that's worth a lot to a company such as Mattel in this case
It's an
I want an easy way but it's an effective way for them to
To get
Product information on how
Kids use their products
What preferences these kids may have
And let's do some towards other products and so on
Yeah I mean it in a sense you this almost goes all the way back to
When I first started Loyalty cards reward cards in stores
Henry's like I always are great I get discounts on my stuff yes but you were giving up all your demands preferences
To the stores
And this is just I'll call her in a while
More modern way to do so
Loyalty cards
2.0
Ana titer the same thing because it's not just happening
In your home
UnitedHealthcare has a program called UnitedHealth
Ocean
And what it does is it offers
Employers
Your boss basically
The ability to gather Fitness data and set goals for their
Employees like walk 10000 steps a day
Where
Walk for 5 minutes
For 6 hours during the day
All of these things in the ideas of your
Please
Can earn up to
$4 a day in Lake health savings account
Money
So it be money that goes towards your age
HSA
And ideas that you know how their employees Cost-U-Less so this is a cheap way to
Can I push your employees to be a little bit
Do things that are
Incentivizes
Yes
So what they've done at CES is they've done it they've allowed fitbit's
So you can bring your Fitbit
Data in
And then they also
How to deal with Qualcomm
Coconuts Health platform
Recalled to life
And there are there working with that in the program itself has been expanded to
40 States of
12 States about a year ago
So
I really feel like giving all of these things
We really need to start having this
Conversation
About privacy
Is it make people aware that
Can you use these
Products right now
Your data
In most cases is going to accompany
And they're going to be using it and it's not negative
You don't know
To make a better toy
You know based on watching kids play it's not a
Bad goal
No but what worries me a little bit
Companies have been collecting data for years so that's not different
But
In this particular case Okay so the data
Is going back to United Healthcare and that can
Save
People money because they get the credits and so on
What is the employer
Is getting that information to and I do not know that they are aren't I'm just thinking out loud here
And eventually
Templar start putting that into like job evaluations
Will you not as healthy as you need to be to do well in this job I'm so I may be here
Mental Fitness is down because you're not
Getting a physical fitness
I mean I don't know what I want that
That's a real question I have tried it guys so many times to get an HR person on the show
We talked about this
Good lucks
The HR people that I have talked to
Art on the show
They said they don't want that data their company should avoid having that data
Because because of issues
But it is
At a certain point
It is like
How can we not take this
Stata
Because it will be so
Impactful
Wrecked
And that is a big question and that's why if you
Pop supplies in there
Standards
Maybe we can
Not even open
Is there a agent that's a door that you
Maybe I'm crazy
So I don't think so
So there was a lot of stuff for kids
There's there's the curry home robot that was roaming around in that
Basically
Visually recognize your kids
Let me tell you guys
Computer vision was
Baby sister
Which is is good it's actually very helpful
Listening is with
Computer vision I mean this the camera sensors have
Incapable
Quite a while to enable this
That hasn't been issued and that it's been the
The machine learning and the recognition
Are the algorithms in and sifting through the data to actually make the recognition that's been lacking and I think
Many companies have made great strides in the past I'll say two years on that front
To bring it to a defective but inexpensive level
Yes in this this robot which is not actually available but speed real clear it's not coming out till
Next holiday
So that's crazy
But it's
It's $700 at 699
Talk to your kids reads to them at Rooms around your house looking for things that are wrong
Cuz this is my thing about robots I haven't seen the laundry folding robot that has been touted
Being as being
I want my robot to do more than just roll around my home
Cuz I have a dog
As I say my pets do that just fine
So that's my thought
Holy cow
The service provider Market with iot is getting really interesting
And we're going to talk more about this on the special
Our special edition episode
Quickly
Alarm.com actually has introduced something called
It's insights program and basically
Any smart devices
They have in your house there pulling data on it and now they can actually proactively notify you when something unusual
Happens in your eye
So an example might be
You know if you if you guys
During weekdays
Leave
And your house is empty
And then the door open
Like maybe one of you forgot something
I'm back in the middle of the day
It's actually going to send you a notification cuz that's something weird that happened that doesn't usually happen
It takes into account weekends
Holidays that sort of thing so it sounds actually really interesting
The crazy part about the
Is there working with Qualcomm to develop a drone
Somehow
Your house would launch the Drone
When one of these things happened so you could get a visual
That's not real insights is real
Interesting I don't want to see all these drones flying up out of my neighbors houses when walking the dog or something
Why won't they
Where are the Drone landing pads
That that that is like a legit question
Answer
Absolutely I don't know
Did the other thing is going back to
When it notices using the AI insights platform and notices something different out of the norm
I think that's
Interesting but also in a sentence
Scary
Because I didn't talk about Haiti Security in
And a few seconds but
Basically it's learning the patterns of how you
Come and go from your house and
Do things in your house and so on and so forth
And if that information gets
Use buy some
Third-party dunnuck Nino
Stolen or hack or whatever
That's really scary because now it's like
I know these folks you know are gone
Every other weekend because AI insights is telling me that some
That's kind of concerning to me
Well yes but that's
I need the company will take
Security measures
But that
I think the challenge will be
If someone at alarm.com
They see that
Acme
Who's houses
That's a problem that alarm
People like I might
My mother-in-law never stops her
Newspaper because
She feels like
That person the carrier made
Shore shore an antibiotic cement
Kind of become accustomed to checking into places online anyway and telling people our whereabouts so
Without knowing the patterns you could
Look at somebody's Facebook page maybe they
Get checked into place new account they're not let me go to their house or whatever so it's
Unique
New situation it's just
I just worry about all that data on my
My living pattern
That are available in in one spot
And let's talk about the others
Security device
Yeah so I could swear that just one or two shows a guy said I wish the router companies would
Beef up Security on their routers to
Kind of integrate
IRT security right
Again I don't remember if I did or not if I
I should have
But it looks like Symantec is actually doing just that Mary have announced the Norton core
Router
Which does sort of look like a disco ball is a geodesic dome
Type of
Top shape
It has multiple USB ports
Onyx and
The big thing here is besides being a typical Wi-Fi router
It
Can protect your home basically it's kinda like the front door of all your iot devices lock
The front door and everything should be safe
So they're using data encryption secure DNS
Automatic update switches
T I think when it comes to iot security
He will help protect your web traffic
Give you warnings if there is some insecure or unsecure web traffic going through
Got parental controls
You can prioritize Wifi to devices
So it's kind of got all of the
Table stakes in a regular Wi-Fi router for the home
But also adds
The
Ability to update in case of sick of IRT issues or web attack since on a sofa
I think it is available for pre-order now I know they just announced it but it is approved for $200
Which isn't too too bad and that 200 includes a 1 year subscription to their core Security Plus
Program for all your updates regular price is going to be $280 so
I'm country by cuz I don't need a new router but this is exactly what I want to say I want to see more
Security at the router level four but all the iot devices behind the router
Of that Nelson ways to do that in Lake
There are actually protocols that are like trying to do that
By limiting what devices
Can talk to
What other device
Right so that is yet another in it that's not
Either or that's kind of an addition
So another layer
Okay so
More
News
We're just going to run through
Some crazy stuff
So speaking of security
The
Voice over IP phone company I don't know if you guys remember them
There
White terrier
They're still around doing well
I actually
My buddy and your buddy Kevin
Dave's that's noted a couple weeks ago that they had an SEC filing for some
And now it is out
It is a home monitoring service that runs on your
Hello
Smart Home
Service
So there's
Sensors there are
Basically just add this stuff and it's
Again monitored home security there's a camera with motion sensors
And
You know you can just add this on it becomes like a premium service
You can add to your voice calling so it's
It's like maybe it's the new double play
Security invoice
Security of broadband
Got to get your broadband
If you're a subscriber I would definitely look at this because
All monitoring is $6 extra a month
And if your premier
Customer of Ooma service
Like
So they have a water sensor that's going to be $30
I have to pick up a motion sensor.
It's $35
Indoor window sensors for 25
Hope there is no video
Okay
I think this is interesting it is legit and real it can be
Out in the first quarter of this year
Yay
Earthquake news
August
Door lock
Doorbells
Keypads
Actually now integrate with
The Logitech pop
Home switch
Andrew Logitech Harmony Home
You're not going to be able to unlock your doors with your voice
Guys don't try it
But you can
Hit the pot switch
Adorable
So if you have like a Goodnight Thing associated with your hot
Top switch now you can add your August door lock
Nice
So we mow has a couple of updates actually Belkin as couple updates on their WeMo line product line
EBay WeMo mini which is a sinner smart plug about half the size of the old WeMo switch witch
I still have two of the Insight switches and they are big and bulky
These are nice and thin
So you don't want you guys to have two of them plug-in dirty easily into a traditional Outlet
There's still a little button on there in case you don't want to use your app or use your
Voice controls if you'd be to use them
I think it is $35 available for
Pre-order now I saw an Amazon yesterday January 10th available
And it's called the WeMo Mini
Make sense cuz it's Minier
And then they all
I was going to interrupt you just to say
Tp-link has the same thing
Also works
Amazon Echo
Same style
TP Link hs105
People been asking me about that that it is a lovely
Spark plug and it is $40
If they're essential the same I'm going to go with the cheaper one person like a
They both work with my account so I'll be happy
Yeah and then we will also has a dimmer switch their next-generation smart dimming light switch has a night mode
Prevents heart
Harsh lights at night
And this also would work for with voice controls I presume so you could
You could Jim things by voice if you have
An echo which is kind of nice
Will be in stores later in
January
This is an actual wall switch that is not like a
Plugging kind of thing so this is something off to install I would say
Do you know what is so cool about the
Switch
I do not
Exists because people have hated the fact that the WeMo light switch
But to it has these lovely little LED lights on it and they change color based on what type of
Command
Triggered it
So if it's a voice command it turns Aqua if it if this then that Amanda turns an amber color
And I feel like there's some other colors but
I love the idea
Of giving someone a visual cue
What triggered it because right now
I have WeMo switches that
Triggered all the time by things
And I have no idea what you just did that
You know that's kind of a nice thing so if the lights come on in your room all of a sudden you're like
What just happened
You can glance over there and you'll see it
Someone gave a voice command to her
Why is this in that recipe must have been triggered
So that's actually kind of a really nice
User interface
So I like that a lot
Did you get to see this at CES unveiled or some other I did
But I got to see it now
They don't know exactly when it's going to be
Out there
Expecting it sometime
Later this year I bet early this year like
The plugs are out
Real life
Or not
And I don't think they set pricing it for the lights
So
We'll wait and see but I can't wait to get my
Hot little hands
I'm just I'm curious cuz they mentioned using the WeMo app to custom calibrate
Four different dog types of the day
Talk about that or show that to you
Yeah the lighting is always wacky overs
So other quick
News things I'm going to find out more about this cuz it's really interesting
And I don't have any other information
Cremation with zigbee
Thread if introduced
..
Twitch
Is ridiculous
Dot-dot is going to be a
Language for smart home devices
Communicate
And I'm kind of like what is it like a protocol that
Harris would like iotivity or alljoyn
Or is it
Just
You know like profiles
Cuz it be used to have these lovely profiles that made
Trippy things not work together
Somm, Lake
I need more information I asked for it
When I get it
Update YouTube it is worth noting that this exists
Yeah it and I noticed in their press release they say that
Etsy Esther dammerung prototypes
A products that speak..
Running on top of
Ipps thread Networks
Rate
And that makes sense cuz they're being thread
Same radio
Slightly different protocols but they've been working together to get things to
Phoebe running
I can't remember is it be running over thread or thread running over
Yes
That's a quick thing
Keep that in mind as we
We'll come back to that
Other
Is going to work with SmartThings
Yay
Nice
Was just a real quick it seems like everybody is trying to make
Amazon Echo
Yes
Lenovo made an echo
How do you make an echo
Yeah but we did talk about them until 1 but then the Lenovo one
Which is more expensive than the traditional Native Echo
It looks like an echo to me
It's a cylinder and so on
Bass boosted the
The speaker capability so it's much much louder
But it's just interesting that they're trying to make an echo now and all these other people making
Echoes by putting
The Amazons voice service
Package in there and then that's even equating to
Cars with some people try to put
Echo in cars
It is true in Rex
Which is a
Traffic prediction
Company
Out of Kirkland
Hasn't popped open car where
There's different
Things you can do with open car but like finding parking spaces it's kind of like a ways
Option 2
So they have
Integrated the echo into their open car platform
The other things.
The car is it competes with
Apple's carplay and Google's
Android
Kevin and I had a hard time finding
Things that actually use
Open
Car
Porsche
Yeah push it does BMW.
And Volvo does but they only use the entire open car platform for everything
Babe BBC use a piece of that like BMW has in their I3 electric vehicle
They use in wrecks to help find
Charging places nearby and so on and so forth
But what interests seems to be trying to do is bring in
The echo voice Services into their platform so you could
Basically control urine
Infotainment
Through voice in a cards on which again you can do through carplay Android auto and War
Whatever car manufacturer
Uses for their own systems
But it's interesting because
Once you do that you start bringing in
Ways to say at home I'm going to be going to such a such place get me directions
Send it to the car and it
Will work through traps for your Echo
And then return car parts
There's a lot of possibilities here but
Again as you said Stacy we looked around we don't see a ton of
Big partners
Car manufacturers using the entire plateau
Because
Most of them do not want to give their data to Google
So
That could be
Where is everybody
I know it's
Okay
So lots of Echoes
What's a computer
Weird grooming
Tons of updates from our traditional smart
Companies
So
We got the Lutron SmartThings which by the way you guys have to be big for y'all
Who keep asking me about
Light switches
Because now
You can you have it yet another platform
Which actually means I may try to
Swap back over and not use the link platform
So we will see
We've got
...
Service providers doing
Security and hubs all in one
Possibly
Drone landing pads
And you know what CSS just getting started
Is
We didn't talk about this so
Next
Episode
I'm going to do a review of the stringify platform
But in case you guys want to work ahead
Stringify is like
Suspend that
But it's far more power
It's only been iOS I've used it on iOS and I really had a lot of fun
Basically connected to your gadgets and then you do this like
GUI programming thing where you're like
If this happens and it does
You know
Then make this happen and you can control a lot
So
The news out of CES is it they just released their Android
Which I've been waiting for
So
Review coming next week
But in the meantime
See what you think
And I think
That's plenty
Yeah I take a breath catcher catch your breath because you've got lots of walking running around to do a next couple days
What to bring you guys so many cool things
Remember
Monday
Special
CES episode
Thursday
We will have
Back to regular scheduled programming
Alright Kevin wool
I say goodbye for now get back to the show floors
When I get back to my car to get back to the taxi cab line
Back to the taxicab lives and
You guys
Please stay tuned for a message from our sponsor and after that Tim Crawford
To talk about the CIO perspective on the Internet of Things
Hey everyone we're interrupting the podcast with the message from this week sponsor this week sponsor is Dell and we have
Have Jeff Brown who is vice president of global iot
Sales at Dell EMC
I'm more familiar with the center in the
Computer space
What is it doing with iot
What cell is trying to do is focus
Kind of the industrial embedded Edge
Environmental economist
Talking about
Traditional embedded
Computers that are cut
Long life
Rugged industrial when you think about some of the key application
Pacifically on that industrial side you really need something that's a little bit more rugged and robust
The kind of handle those environment
We're taking the hardware solutions that we've come out with weave
Come out for the entirety partner program that can really bring
Software
He sends to create kind of a hardware software solution
In that Industrial iot
You leave the sales team and your team is talking with
Customers
What do you hear from them
One thing that we here
Is there trying to figure out what they're
Trying to do two everybody understands iot
Teorias broader terms digital transformation
It's something that needs to be part of their focus
Some part of their strategy
Enter looking for Dal because
We do business with 98
Percent of the global Fortune 500
The really looking for us to kind of help me
Lead them down that path
So what customers really need to see
Is multiple layers of Roi
Yeah one good example of that is
In high-value asset
Mining equipment
Heavy duty structural
High-cost medical equipment
You know in terms of like predictive maintenance they're monitoring so they're getting that information back
Which allows them
How to make better equipment
The future
They're also trying to understand when things are going to fail so they can provide
Better service to their customers
Suning parts
Before that party
Tails
So what makes Dells iot Hardware unique
Versus all of the other option
What are the reasons I came
Citadel to lead this group
Is I really saw that there's a chance for somebody
Differentiated in the
Marketing
In Dallas really doing that
Speak taking their strategy around
PCS
And brought that
Two kind of the embedded Gateway Market
Meaning that we can deliver products
And weeks
2 3 weeks we can deliver 3 for 500
Noah Nelson
Market can do that and look in iot there's a lot of lot of
Face type solution
She's going out there so
Somebody wins the solution they need Hardware right away
So we can do that
The other piece which is key is Globus
You talking about
Managing
Critical assets
If something does go down there want to be able to
Get that swapped out really quickly whether it's
Science technician or get that product really quick
We have that
And then I think the
The third area is the manageability
We're bringing that
Server
Workstation manageability that Dell has
Throughout its products
And trying to bring that too
To the edge
So that when people have these assets
They can actually monitor them
And figure out the help
Configure them update them all of those kind of
There's a couple other ones but those are really the key that are kind of differentiate ourselves in this
Where can I find out more
Probably the best place to go would be www.
Key partners
Dot-com
And that shows our products as well as our partner Solutions
Hey everyone this is Stacy and I'm coming back to you with the
Internet of Things podcast
My guest today is Tim
Crawford
Who is a strategic advisor to cios with about 25 years
In the IT industry
So Tim thanks so much for coming on the show
Thanks Stacy for the invitation to join you today really looking forward to the conversation
Me too so
I've known him for
A long time I've been reading in Forever especially when I was covering cloud computing and
You're struck me as being
Very attuned to like
Real life
So we might all be over here thinking
Oh this is going to be awesome everything
Go to the cloud and you were like
Check you guys
Here's how it's going to have to happen and it hears what real people think so I'm hoping you can do that
With
How did the Internet of Things
MCI Airport
Yeah I'm looking forward to it I think that's
That's a great Segway is that you know there's a lot of great things happening
But I do think there is a dose of reality that we just have to stop and take a breath and
And recognize and respect
All right
RCI was coming to you asking about the internet if they
Things yet
They absolutely are
But I think a lot of it comes from an educational standpoint
I've had a number of cios approach me and say okay I understand what
Iot is
From a definition standpoint
What I don't understand is
How can it help my business
How does a
Fit in I mean I can think of some basic things
Such a sensors in Telemetry but
I really don't understand how this works and what they're really asking is
Help me connect the dots and
And that's a theme that that I often talked about his
This concept of connecting the dots
But
Help me understand
How this solves
The business problem
Did it come to you like having a mandate from their board or from their CEO that says
Hey
Go get me some of that iot
You know it's funny you mentioned Cloud earlier in the podcast
And I would say that
I have seen a number of cases where
Bored
Publicly traded companies
Have approached
Executive team and specifically the CIO and said
We need to do cloud
I don't think iot is there yet
At least I haven't seen it in Mass where
Executives
And
I would include
The board of directors of an organization in that
Are specifically calling out iot there's a lot of questions about it but
Not where they're calling it out saying okay we need to do this
For the most part
I would put iot
He's still in that
Experimental camp
So very few companies are looking at it on the hole on
I brought take
But
More so from that
Experimental or very specific
Use case
And do you think that's the right
Way to look at it I mean
I hear so much about
My coyote is business transformation
But you also hear kind of it feels like conflicting advice which is
Pick up small project
See if it works and then
Go from there basically to spread out through your business see what else you can apply that to so I'm very curious like what your
Tactical advice
Yeah this is where we have to separate the wheat
You know every technology becomes a business transformation opportunity
I've had startups that I've advised
That they've approached me with their pitch and their pictures
We transform businesses
Am I a natural reaction is without saying the words
This is basically hogwash
More
Eloquent words
And the reason for that is that
Turn my credibility standpoint they don't do that
I mean iot
Whether it's iot cloud
Pick your favorite
New technology
In itself
Doesn't do anything for you
It's how you use it
Is the differentiator
And so I think that's a real important distinction because
The company that build the iot solution whether it be an isv or consultant or
A Product Company
They don't do anything
For your business directly in fact
In many cases
Didn't even understand your business or if they do they don't understand the intricacies of it
And so that's why I think it's really really important for people to understand there is no magic bullet here
It's a partnership
You have to understand what tools to use
And then
How to appropriately apply those tools
And So eventually what you start to realize they're selling you on something that is
Not necessarily meaningful it sounds good
But it's not something that you can really cut a tangibly get into
And that
To me is a is a real problem that I see I saw it and cloud and I see it in Spades and iot right now
You've got a lot of folks selling on a promise that
Will never be fulfilled
Let's get into
Some of the deployments used
What are people doing that are successful
Nowadays
They're a couple of
Examples of app
One is where the technology hits the custom
The customer engagement opportunity I was having a conversation with the friend of mine who is a CIO
In retail in a retail business
He was asking the question about iot and how iot kind of fits in and said you know there's a great way for it to fit in in
And I'll give you a
A perfect example of this
Imagine putting Telemetry on
The baskets
Write the little hand baskets that you carry around the store or putting on the shopping cart
Now you start to understand the path
That Shoppers are taking through your store so you can kind of figure out what what are hot spots and cold spots
Within the store
Now if you were to take that and tie it to particular transactions like
This car went through this register and
That was tied to this
Frequent shopper because they have a loyalty card value can start to understand more behaviors about the
The customer and their buying habits when they're in the store
That some might say wait a second that's a little big brother
Baidu
If you can really start to understand
What is selling and what isn't selling more than just
A binary yes or no but rather to say you know they kind of went by the shirts or went by the pants but
It really just bought socks
I think that gives you some insights that you wouldn't otherwise have Acts
Access to
To me what this is all about is
Iot
Like Cloud before it gives you the ability to do something you couldn't otherwise do
Other than
Having an employee follow a customer around the store and say who they went to this one and went to this island this album
Not that aisle
Maybe a little creepy
Yes incredibly
Part of what we're talking about here is
Iot gives you the
The data stream the information
In an automated way
Without having to induce more labor into the equation which is as you mentioned expensive and error-prone
Okay so now
Cios are already in charge of like maintaining computers and I was thinking of Peters and everything and that feels like
Huge expansion of their you know
Purview
So
Who's going to be in charge of these things on the tech side is it still the CIA
And does that mean their role kind of changes to
Adapt to
Controlling more things or should they also be dealing with the business side more now to
I guess it's really what is the CIO to when we have
Like this Grand connected
Retail
I think the first thing you have to do is
Is take a step back
And
Let's just spend a couple of seconds talking about
How the cio's role is changing because I think that creates
The context in which to answer your question
The CIO
Historically has been a technology leader
And it's what I've referred to for some time now is 2
Traditional Cil
But there's a new type of CIO this come about
And that's the transformational see I am
And the difference between those two individuals fundamentally is one is very technology Centric the traditional one
The transformational one is very business-centric
And what I mean by that is that the transformational CIO did it 10 times
The transformational CIO
Is a business leader first
That happens to have responsibility
Before it
Letters that say it not
Technology
And the reason for that is that
The it organization needs to be more business-centric today than it ever has
Has been
So understanding that context
To answer your question the CIO quite often will not be involved in these technology
Conversations the
Transformational CIO that is
And so they're more focused on
If we're talking about the shopping cart example
How did this really solve a business
Problem for me
How does a tie
Iot into a business problem and I can't tie it into a business problem and it's just about who cool we can put dilemma
Metreon shopping carts
Okay that's interesting maybe but
Why are we doing it we've got a big huge heaping plate of things to do
It's overflowing and that hasn't changed
We want to throw up
Cool Nifty little thing on the plate
Without tying it to a business center
Problem that we're trying to solve that's going to be really hard to get
Support and funding for
Okay
And what skills
Do you think
The CIO needs in the organization needs as we start to embrace all of the
This is new sensors
The snoo
Ways of managing data
And I'm just trying to think about
The guy who's really good at like
Troubleshooting computer problems do you send him out to you know install the sensors does that change your
Types of people you hire the skills you need
The CIO needs to understand a couple of things
Number one
They need to understand how the company spends money and how the company makes money
And I don't mean
You know that they sell pants and sell shirts and sell socks if that's
What I mean is that
They need to understand how the customer in gauges
And the different opportunities the customer has to engage
Purchase those products
But they also need to understand the whole supply chain of how products are designed
The timeline that they go through for design to manufacturing to
Supply chain to distribution
And how all of that works
Soup To Nuts
Now that's
A very tall order but to a large degree these days the CIO needs to be thinking like
In the role of the CEO and I don't mean the CEO of it I mean the CEO of
The company
And so there's a much broader / view that
The CIO needs to have
What that means then is that a lot of these technology conversations
Because you will need to have those technology conversation
Those need to be pushed
Further into
The it organization
And so it needs to
Understand that and so of course they're new skill sets
With regards
Two new architectures around iot and I've written a bit about
You have some suggested architectures for iot to to have the conversation cuz that's
Whole nother thing right everything falls into the iot packet but iot is not iot is not iot
It's understanding that is really important
And so does new skill sets are required within the it organization
It is a division of labor
Even within the it organization
You still have to have some business sense today it still can't be
A technology Centric conversation
In line with this conversation about skills right now there is a lot
Of
Back and forth in the kind of industrial or Enterprise iot space about
Disparaging of
Information Technology with
Operations
Technology
And you don't
Itot divide
In
Salata
A lot of acronyms but
It's also kind of an interesting
Discussion because a lot of the IT people in the cio's are like
Oh my God I have to deal with life
Fike fire alarm systems
I'm I'm working on our email
So there's this like
Concerned about like where the role of facilities kind of management
Comes in here and if it does it all and I'd be curious about your take
You know it's
It's funny you bring that up
Because I can recall
A very distinct conversation I had several years ago
In past organization where the
Facilities organization had responsibility for the photocopier
No coffee Man
And
These
Machines guide
Really complex
It's really fast
They started connecting to the internet
Connecting to your network
They had a hard drive in them they had software that had to be updated
And the facilities folks
This is out of our wheelhouse we don't know what to do with it it's all technology
And they kept
Calling it to
To help address it
Help
You don't resolve it
Because we had processes we had
Means to be able to handle all of them
The functions we just couldn't deal with
Things like supplies and Ana type of stuff
Although arguably at someone
Like a printer
But anyway
It was interesting to have that conversation because
I think
The one thing you have to be careful about is
If you use an assumption that
As soon as it connects to a network
It falls under the purview of it
It becomes this massive organization is responsible for a lot of things that
It doesn't necessarily understand
And
Shouldn't necessarily manage
But rather other parts of the organization need to get more
Sophisticated to
And I think there's a balance
Destructor iron
And we're just seeing kind of dere the inkling of the pendulum starting to swing
Any other direction
And eventually it'll swing back
To something more neutral
So let's let's going to delve into this little bit because there are things like
Security that is
Probably very much something
I mean I know we have sex
Sisal ciss
Is that how you say it
Right Caesars Caesars
I know we have cesos now that are
Totally responsible for that and when you think about things like the target breach which was coming in through an a
HP AC system to the point-of-sale system to steal people's credit cards
That suddenly becomes like
Bully Chivas
That's on the network is that it
When you're dealing with
All of these devices that people are going to be plugging on or attaching to your network it becomes like who's in charge of that
I guess that's the thing that I often get pulled into is the conversation around security regardless of what
It's right you know we talked about
Comparing some of the analogs of iot to Cloud
It's the same issue
We had the same conversation about security when the internet came about the 90s
Oh we're not going to use it because it's insecure
Okay well today
If you don't use it
Your youre neanderthal
You know we had the same conversation about distributed computing we had the same conversation about Cloud we're having the same conversation
Json about iot
The bigger challenge that with iot unlike the other
Predecessor
Services
The sheer number of devices that were talking about in the intelligence of the devices
It creates
An exponentially more complicated problem to solve 4
That we don't necessarily have
A direct answer
What I mean by that is
If you think about every single device
In your house
And I forget about your office
Just think about your house from a personal standpoint how many devices do you have the
Connect to
Your internet service and if you start adding it up
I think on average
She probably have somewhere between 10 and 20 devices
Sprint average household
That's a lot of devices and that's probably not even everything that could connect
And so how do you manage those devices becomes the second piece of it which is
We're talking about sensors were talking about small
Circuitry and
Technology in small bits of software
That now we have to figure out how to effectively secure
And
That becomes incredibly problematic not just on a personal standpoint in our homes but
Think about it now in the office man the corporate environment
It's a problem
It's a personal conversation that they bring up which is
Okay I want to do this but how do I say
And even when they say those words
The whole concept of how do I say
Secure it
Has a whole nother set of questions that come with it
What do you mean by
CARiD
What does it what exactly does that mean
And how much
Do you want to secure it
Do you want it to be like for dogs
Do you want it to be
Just something that kind of keeps the riffraff out
It feels like we have to come up with a new model
First Security like a new mental model because like the firewall model doesn't work
Giant hole to dump your traffic in for it to be
I cleaned kind of doesn't work like it did for cloud
And just going back again to your retail example you're going to be putting connected carts in the hands of your user
Service which means
You can't even protect the physical assets
In many cases are going to be in the hands of other people and then you're opening up
Maybe not ports but
Opening up doors into your system be alike
Apis for
You're basically sticking a lot of stuff outside whatever wallet so you may have built in
Both physically and
Virtually so
I just don't I don't even know how to think about that
You're more spot-on than
You probably think you are because
The issue here is
The old adage of
Crunchy on the outside chewy on the inside that perimeter
Security Paradigm has long since been dead
More than a dozen years ago
I was with an organization that
It was an institution it was at Stanford University
And here's a prominent insta
Institution and one of the
Paradigm's
That we had to look at is we had to assume that in our in the world that I lived in there
We had assumed that our network was a dirty Network
Is the default thinking
Most corporate entities don't think that way they think of
Their internal network is a clean Network and you set up the perimeter and all the sensors to be able to protect you
As long as something's on the inside you're good
But when you're talking about
College students dirty dirty college students with
That's exactly right right
You know
Unlike a corporate environment where 90% of the devices you know about he have the random Consultants or whatnot that comes in
Cannon plugs into your network
In
An educational Institution
90% of the devices
You don't touch
You don't have control over
And so it changes the Paradigm and I think that's part of what we have to
Start to think about it it is
How do we start to assume that
We're not in a secure world
We don't live in a secure network
And so we have to take
Appropriate
Precautions we can't make that assumption that
Oh well if we just plug it on our Network and it's behind a firewall we're good to go right
Wrong
You know in the retail example with the shopping carts
How many times have you seen a shopping card
Out in some random parking lot somewhere that's nowhere near the store that it belongs to
Now imagine if it has
And iot device on it
And you get some kid that wants to kind of Tinker around and hack that system
Great so now they've got
The device
Is the devices connected into your
Your network
That they have full access to be able to Tinker around and play with it outside of your purview
That's just one simple example but I think we could go on for days and days talking about examples in
Just about every industry to and that's the other thing to think about is
What we're talking about today
Is not relegated to just retail or just certain industries
There are examples of this that cross every single industry that I've run across so far
Guys
This is very
Real talk
And if you want examples
From other Industries and other thinking
You're going to have to call Tim because we are out of time
Tim thank you so much
For coming on the show this week
Thanks Daisy I appreciate the opportunity love the conversation
How much for listening and we'll see you again next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get it
Coyote news for this show feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
Stacey on iot Dhaka