Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofu
And we have got an amazing show for you
Today
We've got
Ransomware
We got
An ISP
Defending against the butt
We got Intel has a new boss who is
What are the devices is the same as the old boss
We got a DHS iot
Tea report
We've got Amazon news and we've got some experience with some connected devices that we play
Like to talk about
And we have an ad from the Bluetooth Sig
And I guess this week
Nick feamster who is a co-editor
On the beach
Iot security report that came out last week
And we're going to talk about how to secure the Internet of Things
Let's have a word from our
Do you want to learn more about how to connect a building your home or even a battery Samsung sartaq platform
Makes it easy for you to get your devices online and connected to each other you can build new Services make your office more efficient
And start generating a return on your iot investment today to learn more visit Arctic. IO build
BS by to download a free paper explaining how to connect your business
Give it a whirl
Alright Kevin we are back and ready for the show after a wonderful
Holiday
Yeah lots of security stuff this we could talk about
So let's get it
Ransomware hitting San Francisco
Muni
I picked the story out because it
It's a trend which is as we start connecting things I think the biggest
Danger we're going to see is actually ransomware starting to
Effector
Devices
The ransomware I mean it
Obviously not new it's not a New Concept
It often helps individuals maybe you
Get a message on your phone saying I have control of your phone and all your data if you want to
$1000 whatever maybe
It gets really concerning
When
A municipal system
Thousands of people use everyday is taking over essentially
And that's pretty much what happened here
It is and it was infected
Theater
Computer so this it wasn't like a hijacking
King of
An actual thing
So keep that in mind but
Play with it was a ticket the ticket machines essentially it's not like they took control the buses are not like that like we have for me
The movie Speed
Let me write that could happen to us I'm not going to go there but
I don't think
Next true
Okay so what happened was
A lot of Bitcoins 100 Bitcoins
Which is about $70,000
They actually did not
End up paying for it because they had
Haha
Yay back up there like you know what
Take her date in Scrabble
What's the scrap yard
So
Plus one for backups and then the other interesting thing about this story is
Actually there's lots of interesting things about the story
Brian Krebs had a security researcher
Email him with information after he had accessed
The
Account of the extortionist basic
And so by reading these emails we discover things like
Oh hey
Most of these attacks were against Americans and those in the building industry
You can apparently negotiate with your Ransom
The folks someone actually was like you know what I can't pay you 10 Bitcoins to get my computer unlocked if I give you points
5 Bitcoin
A person said they settled
So
Yeah I told
At least a reasonable people
People taking your computer
It was interesting
Apparently some of the people who were attacked
With the ransomware
Basically said oh by the way
How to get in here and do you have any advice so this doesn't happen again
I got to stay asking the guy who mugged the situation
May not be the best idea
We'll set up a monthly payment plan a subscription fee if you will we promise not to hack you if you keep paying
So basically the the world of the
Cyber
Looks a lot like
Mob rule in Sicily
Yeah
Yeah basically
It's concerning that way
I think we're joking about it but it is a serious issue and
I don't think about it personally that much because I feel like I've got my stuff lockdown but
Services that I use I don't know if they're lockdown you know if I live in San Francisco probably be riding Muni
It's very concerning
Yeah well every time I
Created
Password forever
Two bit
Random sign up that I have to
I like
How secure is the
I mean every every time I'm like
And this could go
Yeah like that and if we talk more about smart cities and we see initiatives for that and mean
Again you could individually be attacked
For ransomware
But more than likely
Attackers will probably look in the future towards
Bigger
Audiences with bigger checkbooks
All right speaking of attacks
Deutsche telekom actually its customers on internet outage
Because
Deutsche telekom was actually attacked
To get access to its
Customers routers
And what happened
And they tried to do a reset and when they did it they bricked
Shut them all down
What do we learn from this we learn that
Isps will pay attention if
Their devices are all attacked on mess
And two it's probably still not easy enough to over the air update
Millions of devices all at once
You know they got a big user base saying they said about 20 million text line customers
Panda
Although he's only 4.5% that were
British actor that still 9000
Houses
Minutes
That's not easy to manage.
I'm curious if they
Routers like many isps to here
They do they do
And I'm also wondering not to lump them all together here but you know
How many people choose to use their own
Which I highly recommend
Yes this is
Let's let's put it a plug right now
Buy your own router
And then make sure it is secured by changing the password
Not just
For your SSID
And whatnot but also the password on the physical router
Demonstrative account yes
Donut people
This will help you
All right
We also have
Intel has a new internet of things boss
And they also created
A new automated driving
What do we call that
The automated driving group The adg
Yes
Self-driving cars
So
Where is the head of pets self-driving car group is done
Tyree the end of the year
That's what I thought back in April
Doug who was the former head of the Intel iot group
Was like
I've been here long time I believed it
I'm ready to retire
So you know
We're like right by Doug
But
Not retiring postponed retirement
He's going to be the SVP and general manager of the automated driving group
So
Yay
He said it was such a great opportunity
Stuck around
We'll see if that's
That pans out until is probably
It got a lot to do in cars with automated driving
Because
Nvidia has been kind of the big brains behind a telematics here because
Napping
Are self-driving cars requires a lot of
Visual processing
And then other car companies like Qualcomm
Qualcomm actually buying an exterior layer
The season
Was a deal for the sensors in the such
In the car's so Intel hasn't really had a huge role to play
As you said and you mentioned video and I remember it had to be at least 5
Years ago at CVS they started
Give me the Keynotes with Automotive companies do no glue
Audi in and others inside every year they made
Have another automotive-themed
Intel's
Behind here
Video has wanted to be in the cars and it's getting in the cars now
Intel says hey we can bring fide 5G connectivity to the car as well
You're fighting against the clock arms and the others that are already in that space
Then they're just behind some curious to see what she brings to the table
Me
You know I am
Of the opinion that Intel is
Rapidly undergoing a chef
They're really trying hard
Branch out into other processors
Other architectures
And really rethink what it means to be in till
Kelso
I agree with you but one quick question and I could be wrong so I let you correct me
Did they just scale back or even get out of
There
Wearables and iot stuff
Officially
Commented
Service reports
Reports that they were going to get out of
The wearable space
I would say make sense they
I've got nothing to offer
It's a very crowded Market lot of startups that
The morning bull has come to Market been very successful so I agree with you there
We should talk about
Tom
Which
Who is actually going to be the head of Intel's iot
He is actually from armed he spent 10 years at arm doing strategy
There at least bringing in people
That have the expertise and experience in
Market connections so if they can actually develop something that's
Compelling is a product here
That relies on Intel saying
Hey maybe x86 isn't the right architecture
Care for a small battery
Right
OC
Maybe they'll keep trying to shove them into that
But we'll see
I am excited
Two kind of I hopefully will get Tom in to talk to us at some point in time
To talk about Intel strategy here and that would be awesome
Ride Along
I don't have a snood Segway here
This is a difficult on a Segway I2
But it has to do with security
It does
Security
Industrial internet
And the Department of Homeland Security
Chess issued this was actually November 16th is when this came out
We did not get to it until now
They should report all about iot security and it's not
It's not a long report it's about 17 Pages willing to in the show notes
And you know I was looking for something exciting here
Like
How to do it all
If they had listened to any of our shows we talk about security I think
They would have found we've already said a lot of what they're saying here
You know that I appreciate what they're doing now I don't want to dismiss it by any means but
You know they're overview of strategic principles is kind of like a list of steps on
Iot security such as
Incorporate security at the design phase
Advance security updates in vulnerability management and Bill on proven security practices
Again a lot of things themes that we talked about before but
It is important that their outline and it readily available for people so that
That message keeps getting hammered home for device makers
Yes
And you know I got there last point so that got six
Points
But the last one was connect carefully and deliberately
Consumers particularly the industrial context should deliberately consider whether a continuous connectivity is needed
Given the use of the iot device in the risks associated with its disruption
Most companies
Probably do this automatically
Play because you got the IT department saying no
Every time you like snow
No but I would say for consumers this is actually a worthwhile thing to think about and I know that
It's going to sound strange coming
For me who buys like
Steelers
But
Think about
What you're buying
Do you need the connectivity here cuz in some cases
Connectivity is a one-off thing just to set up the device and then you can get o
Turn it off most of the time
If it's a good device and then you can you know turn it on every now and then for updates
So something to think about especially as we're getting into like connected sous vide cookers can
Connected ovens
Connective toys
Does it have to be online all the time
And if so
Is it worth
The risk
Expressing
As they say the intended purpose of any network connections to Consumers is something that I can see more of
Device makers that with our guest
Rihanna
Hi.
Amazon
Amazon UK
Million echoes
Since I bought mine back in December of
According to the
DIYs to get the acronym all back
It is B
Consumer intelligence research
Partners
So
This is not an official Amazon number
It's an estimate
So they say it's about 5.1 million Amazon
Echoes including two million so far this year and that includes echoes
Datsun
All kinds of other crazy
And that number
Beers going to go up big time I suspect based on the holiday season now
Yes
Because my gosh
Didn't you buy a new Echo
I bought another one
I bought a. That but this is my 4th Echo device I bought a. I did it
Through my echo by voice on Cyber Monday because a it was $10 off to begin with because they were discounting everything
And I think I got a $10 credit because I ordered
Through
The Echo by voice
So that's a.
30 bucks
Is that deal still going on
I do not know
Not no we're not surprised me because I think they're calling this Cyber Monday week or something on Amazon
Give it a whirl
I'm checking now I got it I got it
And no it is not it is 4999 interesting they're all not on sale
Want more
That was your Cyber Monday deal did you buy any other connected things on
Over the holiday shopping
I bought a car this is the first
Black Friday / Cyber Monday that I almost didn't buy anything but. Was at 8 p.m. on Cyber Monday
Did not even buy that
And I got my volt on Friday
Did you get a great deal on that pulled on Black Friday
Actually I did
I even got a great deal on my tray they valued my trade higher than the volt
So sales tax was
Nonexistent
On the car that saved a ton of money
I got my federal tax credit coming next year and I found out
The state of Pennsylvania go PA
We have $2,000 cash rebates for the first 2,000 people that buy
An Eevee
Each year and they were still 44 eBay stuff when I bought mine
Tell Pennsylvania get on the horn
Yeah I agree I agree some
Happy very happy
Sweet
I'm trying to think.
I almost bought Arlo's
Netgear Arlo
Decided
Against it because I wanted
The
Rechargeable ones and those were not
Grand sale
And so I cuz I I've been kind of in
I also thought
Maybe I should wait
Outdoor capable connected camera that has 4G
Because I thought
How awesome would it be to like park your car right and then be able to like set up a little camera in the Dasher
Somewhere in there
Monitor people coming up to it or anything like that
Maybe it's just because my car keeps getting hit in pek
What are we just talking about limiting or understanding connectivity and devices
Ficu
A camera in a car on be like what's up with that person
Okay
You're right
I will I will have to practice what I preach
It's your car you do what you want I'm just not going to walk around it
I wonder if I'd have to put a sticker on save these premises are monitored
Makes you wonder
Privacy
Or let it go anywhere you go anywhere these days
We have one more Echoes story
Speaking of privacy
Possibly
It's not about that it's about a possible new Echo device
With a screen which is soon as you say that I'm like we'll wait you know you have fire tablets that can do
Alexis stuff neighbor screen so why do this but
Story told to make sense to me to have like a
Very
Kitchen Eeyore bedroom me
Screen device width
Alexa voice service isn't sorry for saying her name there
Antenna better speaker which is the report better speakers I should say so it sounds like a 7in
Touchscreen device with better speakers and obviously will have all of the
Smartcell she who shall not be named
So remember when the wink relay came out
One of the things that we talked about with Nathan Smith
Quez
That there's some things that you just want to see it makes more sense
So like your Fitbit step count
Actually that might be really embarassing
Plastered on your
Although if it's right by your fridge that would be really smart
So there's some
Weather data there's a lot of data data plans
Capability and plus when you ask the echo.for cert
Things like Allrecipes recipe skill
It would be great to shove that to a screen
Actually in you
Kitchen so you can see it
I don't disagree in fact I've had some of this experience already because the Fire TV is I have three of them in the house cuz that's
How we get our TV content
There are the echo cards that show up on your screen when you use the voice remote to ask question
And it is Handy
So we'll see if that comes out it'll probably be more expensive
$80 cuz
Hey
Awesome
Alright here's a device that I'm a little unhappy with
The August doorbell
Earlier this month
August basically said
Hey we're launching our
Rick Cloud recording service so you get a week free and then
You pay for
Sudo access
Which month for cloud recording
Basically what happens is you get 6 months free if you're an existing customer of the August doorbell
And then after that you get a week free
With all of your
Recorded history and your video recording service is available for $5 a month or $50
For one year
Here's my issue
Basically they're taking away functionality that people have had now for like a year
I feel like August was opened that they would create some sort of cloud storage service
But if you bought into this you have no idea and they're kind of taking away this
Functionality
Not to mention that
They actually advertised a functionality
With the motion detection
Did they didn't actually offer
/ 9 months
Amman
I feel like
From a consumer
Like as an early adopter
These things happen
As a consumer and if I were
The FTC are consumer Watchdog agency ID
I be looking at them a bit Escape
Because
When you're selling a device
That also has a service associated
Suddenly charging
A service it was
Is once free
Feels
I understand why they're doing
I just think
Bad planning this is kind of one of those things don't get caught up
I almost wish they would rethink this and say you know what because we were going to have this before took us nine months to
Get it
And I will give you six months for free or something like a week
So they're giving
People six months
Of free service basic
Six months of clouds
Recording for free
Everyone gets a
If that makes sense so if you bought it today
You would get a week free
No matter what
And then you would have to
If you wanted access to those files after a week you would have to pay
$5
Right
It's tough I mean I think it comes back.
You're coming about planning any of planning ahead as a company with your product and your service then
Cuz they're at their going
Forever
In the minds of the consumer and
You know if you buy a product
You should know your bare minimum should be what you buy on day
Right you can't just
Clawbacks
Functionality
I guess right
So that's my take here
I could be wrong
I know that August was kind of floored by how difficult it was to make a doorbell and get everything working
So
Eric idle
Okay
This is Kevo
The Kevo lock
Which is a
Touch
To open Bluetooth
I didn't really like it
Initially
I thought it was the last time was pretty
Some tight like in a few
Had to come back and
Unlock a door that you just lost had to wait if
A few seconds
I didn't love it
Well now haven't if this then that in
Immigration
And
Because
That's my job
And I have to say that the lag time on the if
Integration was about
4 minutes
Which was what
I know
So this is may be fine if you're wanting to so it's a
Your options are door unlock door lock
Or you can trigger
I did a light thing so if my door you know was unlocked
Let's turn on a light downstairs
Just
Seems practice
Right because
It's late
Yeah
4 minutes later
That was that was not so lights
Just don't do lights in it
That's going to be the moral of all lifts
This should be like
Higginbotham's law
But
That's okay
And then if you're doing like a
Set up
You know like a different command
I was trying to think of other commands that my
Be useful even if there is a 4 minute delay and maybe like an arming the house
Lightworks
4 minutes is still kind of
You know
That varies
But it's especially with something like a lock
I mean that if you think about it
Take all the smarts out of it all the IRT out of it
A lock
Works when you use it immediately
So any delay
Even if it's two seconds in my opinion is
Making me
Experienced worse
Not better
Right here you're basically looking at a trade off of instant
Instant unlocking to I don't know
Have to get the convenience of
Right right right
Which is why I'm a big fan of keypad locks
Because you don't carry keys and
You basically punched to keypad
That's what we do
That's how we use our connect
90% of the time
Yay okay
And with that
It's time to
Close the door
Yes it is
Oh my God
Where.
State auditor of this
Report on iot
Security you're going to learn a lot of good stuff
And for a word from our sponsor
Hey everybody we're going to take a break from the podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Bluetooth
Yes.
Hagenderfer director of developer programs
About what
Everyone has
Has been talking about
Bluetooth 5
So Steve
When is Bluetooth 5
That's the million-dollar question
Stacy you and everyone else wants to know that's we've got 30,000 members in the Bluetooth signal 107
But the good news is that we're still very much on target for late 2016
The working group is putting the final touches on the spec as we speak
Okay so I know why I'm excited about Bluetooth 5
Why is everyone
When else so eat
It depends on who you are but there's a little bit of something in Bluetooth 5
For everyone
Lucy V going to get developers new features such as quadrupling the range or doubling the speed of a low energy
Connections it also has increased capacity for advertisement
Our connection state of broadcast
By 8 extra 800%
Achieves all this stuff
Alongside its industry-leading
Time Performance so
Hello energy still low energy
It was the major boost in broadcasting message
Capacity of the data being transferred can be richer
Great but as a normal end-user what does that mean to me
Bluetooth 5 actually going to transform the way consumers experience IRT
Weather at longer range for things like
Whole-home coverage for Smart Homes
Weather at faster speeds
For let's say updating firmware on your Fitbit
Instead of
You waiting for your device
It's done right the device waits for you for things to happen
The really interesting part for me is with the Advent of
Huge advertising package
We're taking beacons to the next level so you can have a much richer
Deeper
More involved experience with beacons in this kind of connectionless iot
Then was possible.
So let's talk about me
What is that going to
This is actually Stacey one of those things that excites me the most about 5 beacons today
Provide really interesting rich and immersive experiences for people to connect the physical
Digital worlds together
Almost everyone has experienced beacons in
And the traditional
Retail sense where you going to a store
And you got a message that pops up on your phone that says hey look we've got something that's 50% outside
Ford Beacon to give me much more interest
Because Bluetooth does so well and beacons do so well with proximity
Figure out kind of where you are in relation to something else
The types of snares at Beacon knable are huge think of
Asset tracking
In Process Management in transportation and logistic
Where you want to be able to track and ask if I'm
Play say to play speed in relation to
Other things that stay on your shop floor or in your office building or your fax
Beacons
Are a perfect solution for those types of problems of those taxes
I really look for beacons to actually explode
Where can I buy listeners learn more
You can get more info on Bluetooth 5
Vault developer toolkit and resource for building with Bluetooth
A bluetooth.com
Flash developed Dash with
Dash
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Nick fees
Who is
Man has so many things but he's on the show because he helped
Co edit a report from betag a government creep on security practices for The Internet of Things
And before you think that he's just some random
Policy walk
He's also a professor
Computer science
Princeton University
And the acting director
At the center for information technology policy
At Princeton
Nick
Thanks for coming on the show
Thanks Stacy thanks for having me
It's exciting to be able to talk about
Stop it today
Man
So you guys produce
Is it 40 pages there's a lot of footnotes in there and actually dies
You should read it or at least give it
But definitely check out the because they are actually kind of scarier than the report itself
So this is a 31 page report so not
It's all about how to secure the internet
How long does it take to put together
Please report to take about six months
Producer even working on this one for for the better part of 20
And I love this guy
I love the idea that we have actual people
With technical expertise in these the people who are working these are not
Like feet
Government lawyers at the big companies are actually
Technically Savvy people at the big companies
I'm working with policy groups ever
Everybody's so
I really like them
Because
Yeah one thing I think I'll highlighting
Because we're going to talk about this in the condo
Facts about the reports
As well as this the end of the report has
Quite a list of
Contributors
Twenty-odd contributors in
Therefore is committed by myself you know I'm an academic than the other co-editor
Is Jason Livengood who's the vice president engineering at at Comcast
So
That kind of gives you a flavor for the broad range of
Perspectives and stakeholders that come to the table and producing a consensus
Support like this
Let's get started with
Holy cow
What are the
Most important
Things
That can be done to improve iot device secure
Or iot secure
Just jump straight to this
Observations and recommendations
Can switch
You don't have to read all 30 40 some-odd cages of the reports to get their some of this is actually well summarized
In the first couple pages of the
Executive summary
So
Let's just jump
Best rated a high-level cuz you wanted the most important thing
The report talks about
Employment barriers
Portable desk
Current software practices
As well as various things related to in a supporting
Operation under disruption
Attacks
Other things related to
Preserving
User privacy
As well so
Any kind of jump into each one of those a little bit
Best soccer practices that mean some of these actually Echo some the other reports that have recently come out including
I want some Homeland Security that involves
This also recommends
A shipping with recently current software and another thing
Actually that
Did the we going to we going to a number of additional
Point that other reports
Touching a little bit less
Including deploying mechanisms
For automated secure software updates
Using straw strong authentication by default
And
Testing in hardening configurations
Dental abscess
Before there
Before they deployed
All of those I think like you said
They should happen quote about first
Meaning of things are harder than
They sound aminos as a computer scientist
Speak to
The difficulty of implementing secure software update Mac
For testing
Configuration
One of the things I think under the covers here is that
These recommendation
Is the group stands by then but there's a lot of work to be done actually 2 to realize
This I thought was really good as it wasn't just the ability to have over the air updates it was also the ability.
Authenticate
That the update was coming from a legitimate source
And then tracking kind of
The lifecycle I guess which I thought was
Way more deaths than I have seen in any of
Right exactly and I think that particular issue is quite nuanced
I mean you basically mention some of the challenges there
With regards to like pushing security software updates
There's a whole bunch of practical challenges which I can speak to for my own personal experience deploying
Frontier home routers
Many challenges come up there
For example is
It relates to no recommendation
In the report which is
You can push a software update but if you don't do it properly there's a risk of breaking the devices that are in the field in other words
Rendering those devices
Inoperable
And once your deploy devices are inoperable it's tough to recover from
So having mechanisms
Play Store test
Roll out of those updates
Is critical
Another thing that's like really tricky
Is
More and more a lot of these devices are relying on open source software
In particular open source software libraries in operating
One of the things of course that we need to
To sort of balance
Is the nature of these open ecosystems
Winston
Potential that a particular Library might have a security vulnerability or a back door and how do you want it how do you want a basic
Master check for those things
Alright let's get back to your list
Because I I took you off topic
Let's see one of them was
Privacy vs security I believe
Or understanding what your devices are sending
Jamming to privacy
What are the other recommendations that the report talks about
Is that the devices should ship with the privacy policy
It is easy to sign in under
Stand the report kind of stops there and I think basically that sounds like a little bit motherhood and apple pie
I still hard to disagree with the script
Insert talk about my own personal opinion on this
I think
Privacy policy
Infamously
Is Inderal cannot read byte
Consumers
I think this one actually is is
Interesting because
In a broader than the topic of iot
Python requests
Why we have private
I see policies in the first place
One of the reasons of course touches on
What is potential audience
For this report is groups like the FTC or industry consorcia
Who may have put into place best practices
One of the reasons have a privacy
A policy is that
If a manufacturer said something about how they're going to collect user share their your data and they do something else
Then maybe there's recourse
Through one of the structures that I mentioned
It'll be arbitrated
That's always in there too
Yeah exactly
Another thing that did personally interest me very much I know both of us have a little bit of history and in software-defined networking
To not to put people to sleep too much but you could take for example part of a privacy policy
By the way this is again my my personal can you this is not something we talked about in the report
It's certainly something at 7 like myself reading or recorded Direct
Say
Take a privacy policy
Data device
Exposes Brighton
Supposing that that is either machine-readable or could be encoded and something is machine-readable
You could consider doing something like dropping that policy
Into a firewall
Brighten the test will this device my thermostat says or less actually take
Let's take a different example let's take the DVR cameras
Write that work
Part of the Massive denial-of-service Attack
A few weeks ago
Well it goes DDOT cameras are only supposed to be talkin to
A very limited number of Internet destination
Right that could very easily be encoded
And such an encoding to be dropped
On the firewall
And it's all of a sudden we
We see those devices talking to
The dying DNS servers
Then we know maybe something
In addition to a privacy
A policy that
You know that encodes
What types of data is collected in
Where it should be shared
Manifest about
Like what types of
Communications
These devices
Are or should be having
Could be used also to improve the security of the network
Will it I know that some companies who make very popular connected devices actually run things like
Network operation centers where they
They see what their devices are talking to and if there.
Devices start
Connecting to weird IP addresses they notice it
And they investigate
Yeah exactly right I think basically it again this isn't something that the report talk
All that much
But I'm certainly another aspect
Basically
Is the is providing the visibility
That you talked about
For example a consumer
May want to
Be able to
Easily see
The internet destinations data devices
Communicating with
The consumer may also
Want to
I make decisions about which of those Communications are okay
Or not
One of the things that the report does mention
Play this is a good opportunity to get to mention another one of the wreck
Commendations
Is that
Iot devices
Continue to function and internet connectivity is disrupt
What that's getting at is
Your thermostat or your security camera or your door locks
Shouldn't have to
Assume
Continuous internet connectivity
Because
Broadband internet service may be interrupted
Another aspect is that
Which the report doesn't go into is that
Proxies devices
Continue to function even when
Consumers make decisions
About
They want their data shared or not
Is that something like
I don't accept the privacy because one of the things that drives me absolutely Bonkers is I purchase it
Something I read the privacy policy
Holy mackerel
I don't want
Change the device back
Can paying like a restocking fee
Feeding tube
Kind of invasive policy or privacy issues and just kind of going on because I really want to use this
Make a doorbell
Yeah that's it that's absolutely the kind of thing that that I'm talking about end
Just in a little bit more detail about that some things that maybe someone covered by the report's recommendations and then other thing
Things that aren't
As far as the recommendations write the recommendation
Talk about
Having a privacy policy
That is easy to find and understand
There isn't a lot of like you know it doesn't expand too much on that
But we can certainly talk about what that means
Right sounds like you've read somebody's privacy
Policies nearby
Probably putting you in the minority is
Consumerist
Oh man I read them all and let me tell you my favorite won the most recent what I had that was just
Terrifying was I had a smart connected oven I was testing
And the privacy policy I had to agree to it
The actual
4.5 LCD screen on the oven
I was like oh
That was exactly the type of thing that this
Did the dis recommendation
Getting it right is like
The authors of the report
Nice that many of these devices don't have screen
There are at least
Speedo screens that are large enough
How to display a privacy policy
In addition to like all the challenges we face is privacy policies
You know outside the context
The biote just on a laptop right
Now you put into the universe
Is the next piece
Really constrained devices with very constrained or sometimes even non-existent graphical user interfaces and the need for
Recommendations here is is
Pre-clear
There's three ways that people seem to talk now about privacy policies
Data usage basic
One is to create a nutrition style label for how your data might
Houston
Another is creating Lake
Oh this is for Sakura
This is
Like a lead style or a 5-star crash test rating for 6
Where someone doesn't actually know what it means but a group such as
Tiger something comes up with
Something that is reasonable
Can give it
And the final is like a Good Housekeeping security seal
Or a privacy Shield
I'm curious
You don't feel free to throw out another idea here or just
What are your thoughts
And the report itself
Facts about the third a little bit to the recommendations
The iot device
Industry
Consider an industry cybersecurity program
An industry back program under which some kind of
Secure iot device
Seal of approval or notation might actually appear
On retail pack
Quite get your question like I I I just wanted to mention that the report talks about the
Third option
The others are interesting to
Let me speak a little bit about the nutrition label
Idea
With regards to data flows
From a technical perspective like as a scientist I should say I'm quite interest
Sit in that particular
Angle
Tracking data flows is something that we have
Computer scientists do a lot we've done this in the context of online privacy
In terms of
Information flow and data leak prevention and
One of the big challenges.
It will face
I think
For that kind of in
Plantation
Is
Presenting something that
Users can reasonably Digest
And want to interact
Cuz if you think about
The number of devices that we already have or are going to have in our homes right
And now each one of those devices is going to have
A privacy policy and data flows and
Things that we might want to say yes or no to like yes this is
Yes my my Internet connected oven can talk to you know these places but not others and you going to do that for everything
Google device in the home
Technically we know how to how to do a lot of what you're suggesting
The challenge there is is
Presenting it in packaging in a way
That consumers can both understand
And recently act on without being
Incredibly annoyed
I'm annoyed by
Just having to deal with
Having to understand where all my data flows from each of those
Kind of scares me
What's going to
The roles of different
Parties in the system
So
This was one of the first reports where I saw a kind of a little bit
From the is peeperspecs
Maybe it was Jason your
Your colleagues are talking about that but
They have to kind of interesting roles one is
With the Mirai botnet
You know any time there's kind of a
Device has become part of a botnet you can see the traffic spike in
You know isps probably can tell that that's happening
If they want
Pay attention to it
So there's a rule that
May or may not be
Applicable to them there the other is
A lot of Americans
Get their routers from their ISP
And I think routers have a kind of unique place in this ecosystem
Kind of hear what you have to say
Why you guys focused in on the role of ISP in
What that role might be
The ISP plays as potentially very critical role in
Securing
The rest of the internet in light of the fact that many of these devices
Maybe
Participating in or perpetrating
Attacks such as the denial of service attack that we saw
A few weeks back
I think a couple of things to
Isps have been facing
Botnet threats for
More than 10 years
The cost structure is there in our challenges
Right because
The isps for reasons both
Technical and privacy-related
They can see certain types of traffic coming out of user homes
Can't always determine what devices are initiating
The traffic
Stacy right because
There
Observing traffic at the granularity of the city
What that means
Essentially is that
By the way this is public
Informational given example of
Comcast right they have a product or a service called Constant Guard
Where they can notify subscriber that there's some kind of infected devices
That notification just tells the
Driver's ed
There's infect
It doesn't tell them
What the device is
Potentially how to fix it
So
That kind of notice
Location of course it imposes a
The significant cost
On the internet service provider
Not just from the potential attack traffic at
Itself but also
The potential cleanup job there
So what happens when a consumer gets that kind of notification
They basically don't know what to do with it
So what are they do
Next they call tech support
They say hey
I fear have an infection
What do I do
Can you help me clean this up
And now that becomes like a significant cost center for the internet service provider
Partially due largely due to the fact that
Consumers are plugging in insecure devices
Provided by vendors that often have little to no hiding shall we say as far as best soccer practices
Is that security
Axis security
So I think this brings me to like
Sitting here with that as context I think this brings me to sex at 6 the reported refer people to that
And in the second part of your question
Just like hey wait a minute last piece
They provide users that you know they often provide users the
Show called customer premise
Equipment
Couldn't they do something with that technology to help the scanner mitigate
Is attacks
And the report talk
A lot about the possibilities there and
I'll talk a little bit about what
Report says but also called this
The same person again as it as a
As a computer scientist who looks at
Network security I think there are a lot of interesting future Direction
Sincere for what what the role
Technology might be
Let me just throw a couple possibilities for what that
You know so-called
Supercharged home router if you will might might do
Right it might do things like
Automatically
Discover an inventory
The devices that use
Connected to your home network
I think
Brand of your listeners I challenge them
If can you list it
Please can you provide it
Complete list
Every device that's connected to your home network
Oh and by the way can you can you provide that list for anything that might even connected to the network over the last 3 months
Including any guest
State might have visited and so on and so forth
Devices that you connected and
Phased out or thrown out and give it away
This inventory becomes
Just by itself sounds
Simple but it's incredibly complicated
Obviously knowing what's
On your network
In the first place is the first step to take to providing better security
I think it's far as privacy such a you know in home network device could
Could provide mechanism
Set present the user with clear information
About what date of the device
Setting to the rest of the internet and what other devices
Devices
Two smartphones in browsers have done this in
I think it's
It's almost a no-brainer that our home router should
Need a scented house that kind of visit visibility
Should be providing that kind of
Information to convey
UC Merced it
When you were I plug a toaster and oven or a thermostat
Internet work
We should have information at our fingertips as to what
Other places on the internet and what other devices
That thing that we just plugged in is trying to
And it's finally this comes back to something that we talked about a little bit earlier in the
In the show
I'm not home router could provide mechanisms that allow the user to prevent or disable
Communication
You know that they are
They're not comfortable with or willing to
Permit
So like you said if I don't want that
I've been communicating with other devices in my house or with other
Destinations on the internet
I should be able to say that
And make this decision then have my home router
Force those decisions that I'm making
Importantly
Without impairing the primary functionality of the
Device
Technically possible to make those kind of
Things happened in the customer premises equipment of the routers that the isb
Please provide
OKC
That was a lot
A lot of cool things that we talked about we didn't even get to the lifespan of devices but
We are out of time and I
So appreciate you
Coming on the show to talk to us about this
Oh absolutely thanks Stacy and I should mention there's a there's a lot more in the report as you alluded to things on
The lifespan of devices and
The lifespan of a which vendors should should
Support things like software updates I encourage your listeners
To go check out the report this lawn mower
Interesting stuff in there so that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and we'll see you again
Next week on the Internet of Things podcast and if you don't get enough iot news for this show
Feel free to sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com