Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Tonight's starting goalies
Wearables
Costume
The dresses are simple War
No
Walking walking the iot carpet
Guys did you see Claire Danes
Was wearing an amazing dress it was
It was like every Girls Princess fantasy
Was beautiful is white
And then with the lights were out
It close
I just sent a David
Fiber optics and 30 little battery pack sewn into the thing which I didn't see I mean not that I
Saw tons of pictures of this but
All the pictures that I saw I don't see any better backs
They did say that
The dress was so difficult for her to move around in it took her husband
And I think Zac Posen I don't know
The designer
To help her life
Maneuver
Yeah I think they built this around her
Panda
So for the most part I was really disappointed because all the celebrities were like
Hey
Fatima that fashion Gala which is held or the Met fashion
Just how old
Every year at the Metropolitan Museum of Art
Saturated is at the weather look for hosts
Appreciate
Really awesome
Why not Kevin
Sheepadoodles
Which Beatles t-shirt but then again what day am I not wearing
So I thought hers was also because it look like clothing
But
Dress that did have some kind of tech associated with it
Who's Carolina
Dakota
Wore this dress actually
Design
VnExpress
And
It was
White looking dress in this house little flowers embroidered on the train
And they responded apparent
You know it's funny you say that I didn't know about Carolina's dress I was going to say it would have been cool if
Claire Danes dress had some type of connectivity in it so the colors change based on maybe where she was in the room
Close to or someone
But now karolina stress had some kind of
Connectivity Tech in it
Yes so her dress was designed by is it March
Marchesa marchesa
I haven't watch Project Runway in a while but I think
So
Marchesa design this and it had a hundred fifty LED connected flowers
What they did is the
Sojoy patients excitement encouragement curiosity
Colortool
That uses color psychology to match emotions
So what's and shows colors
Also aligned with Marquez
Brandt
Of course
Mark s Allen
And
That actually on address because
A yellow dress
Your LEDs were like lighting up red
If you did a tweet tagged Met Gala or
That would change
Colors on
See that's the part I like I mean other people have influence over what happens that's pretty wicked
They say even the fabric
Which was tool
Was chosen through
People think would look good on this dress
Why don't we why don't we just say thinking now except cognitive
Those two were my favorite dresses
Is there a couple of nice dresses but
Overall for the sea
Maps
Immaculate
Man and machine
There was
Blade Runner
You know
Metal
Silver
Yeah that's that's that movies from the 80s 90s and so on but now you take a look at some of the more recent movies
There is no physical
Body you think of her
At work ex machina which you couldn't even eventually tell it was a
Android
So if we go with fashion from her all I remember is
Ridiculous pants
Well
That's that wasn't the best view of the future at least I hope not keep my Beatles shirts thank you
So right now
When fashion meets
Tech
I have to say that fashion is doing a terrible job
Yeah those two dresses were
Fine
I would love to see actually some people you know Adafruit always that the
Company in Brooklyn that sells kind of
Connected gadgets
They actually have some really cool designs I've run across some cool designs on their blog before
Things like
Clothes that interact with
The lights on the skirt with a round in the
Motion of the ISS
Which is kind of a fun way to
Right right
Think about it
Estimate does a similar theme wish they won't
I expect better
All right
So
After my foray the fashion there
Where everybody at
I'm not going to talk about
I have been promising you guys a review of this little
Pebblebee Stone
Which is
Two things
It's a Bluetooth tracker
Much like tile
And it is also a one button pressed
Do a couple things associated with your phone and theoretically
Also can I
Who is this
Send that programmable button
Nice
The size of a quarter
It cost about $30
And
It works as a Tracker
That's pretty easy it has a nice little nap in her face on it that you
If you press the map so it's not even making them up all the time
Depressant
Much to my chagrin
I could not get the if this then that
Functionality
So
You get to options
What does program
Press
And a long press
So I've done
Quick press being call my husband so
I don't know if I'm feeling lazy or attacked
I'll call my husband
Or you can have it ring an alarm on your phone
Which is nice if you're looking for your phone and you have the same type
Yorkies or something
And you can also use it to
Take picture
Which I was playing with before the show where if I did a long press it would open up the camera on my phone and
I was wondering
Yes
It was great
Glamour Shots
Be quiet
Busted
This is not a wearable device this is something you might
Clip to something or stick to something
Kind of like
It's like a little keychain thing
Yeah I guess
Sure these little plastic covers so
My plastic covers came
Blue white
Remind me of the Amazon Dash buttons only you have more control over obviously what
It can do if you want to hook it up with this pissed on that and also works as tracker and so on so
But the concept is is essential the same
Yes it is in
I kind of liked it because there
Really small and relatively inexpensive
Your home if you wanted
But
Here's the butt
I could not get it
Connect with my assistant
Account I verified it a whole bunch of times and even made recipes and if thinks it's verified but
Keystone doesn't so none of my if this and that recipes
It's work yet
So I'm kind of sad cuz I'm
I think it'd be kind of fun to have on my keychain
So I never lose my keys but then I'm also able to
Close at my house routine
Or if you're if you're cold
Just a one touch press and boom on your nest thermostat
I have is true it is limited
Information
Picture of a whole bunch of buttons
Buttons everywhere
It looks like I have some additional sensors in there because I'm seeing you can get notifications not just based on the Bluetooth range but also
Temperature in motion
So like like an example they're using you put in your car and maybe you want to know how warm it is in your
Your car
The baby want to remotely open the windows or something to cool it off I don't know but
You can put it somewhere and get notifications based on temperature in motion
There you go
I like this
Doing a press and hold to share your GPS location with someone
Since it's on your
You could actually have the one in your keyring
You can program the
Button press to be like
This is where I am
And you can only send it to one person
Right now where you at
So
You know
Yes no no no
Bakery
So that is
Sofar impression
Applebee's
End
Have been
I have a man that's because I don't think this happened till after the last
Show son
Disgusted but
Google onhub just got if this then that support a few days ago
Which is good news so basically anytime you
Connect a device to your onhub router
You could fire something off through if this then that
I will say this
Tried it a couple times once on Sundays over the weekend and then again just before the show
And I'm not sure where the issue is but it's
Not working a hundred percent for me and
I will keep digging to see what the issue is cuz it could be at any number things could be Beyond hub
Cashing what devices are still connected versus Western what isn't
It could be as I've set it up to use the wrong device who knows
But I thought hey this would be great when I come home
Nighttime can I use this as a proximity to
I get home I'm still in the driveway driving into the garage
But my phone will connect to the onhub so why not
Use if this then that that says hey if my phone connects to the onhub then
Runaway shortcut that turns on a light
Interior that sounds good I tried about four or five times and it's really only work one time
And it was
Very delayed
Is at least 30 seconds till 8 so I
Yeah that's
Surprise
Yeah
So I keep looking behind here we try to just before the show and I keep expecting the light to turn on 30 minutes later
The good news is there's if it's the nest
Support and it could be something maybe with
In a wink
Could be like I said with the onhub
Table
Could be me I don't know but it's not quite working well enough for me yet so I'm going to continue to play with
All right I should also bring up
Because this happened after we recorded our last show.
This
Is a big project
Did you see the guy who hacked
Tesla with the Amazon
I did not exist it would be starting with the echo
Even better
Actually connected his Tesla
To the echo
He
Is Tesla
Leave the garage
Ice Christian Park itself
So
This was actually a really neat video and I had a bunch of people send it to me like
What does
She who shall not be named
The keyword
What was the name of the car in Knight Rider
What's the resulting event
And
Connect to his Tesla
Echo Dot
10 called an unofficial Tesla API
Trigger the car.
Take action
So what it is
In the car
It open the car
His homeland
Tesla
Automatically open your garage
Summon commands that is on the
Trustable
Work on the Newark
Roku
It is a very cool hack
Yeah not for the faint-of-heart obviously if you're going to want to be a developer to really take advantage of this but
Also kind of scary
I think it shows a lot of promise
Although if you
If you imagine walking by the
Disguise house
You're like
Yeah
Chicago come pick you up
You like nice
I like that you remember to open
Garage door
It's all in the flow you know he probably flow chart of the whole thing out
Garage door open yes no
Which brings up a good point
When you were programming things for the connected home
More complicated
But let you get
Really complicated and even things like wink will let you build these robots
Have several actions taken
Place it's actually worthwhile to think before you actually
Program
Clean the stuff out because
Not historically done that and I found myself
Encountering things
Retrospect
I probably should have thought about
Yeah
So all right
Back to
Things
About things that don't work well
Survivor still on things
Which one would you like to have
Oh let's go with SmartThings
It's another show another week and where
Talking about
In fairness anywhere not making it up it's not like we're sitting here
We're not making this stuff up I mean this is news that is being reported and and we're sharing it and sharing our opinions on it so
I don't want people to think all these guys just bashed
It's not our fault if
Things keep happening in this
Most handsome
Some proof of concept
Exploit
Is letting hackers basically
Packing your house through SmartThings
Yes and
Basically the gist of it is
That because SmartThings has a developer program
And has to approve apps
You could sneak a nap in that
Police malicious code
SmartThings is at
But this hasn't resulted in any problems for our users
So where we're at
Working on this
So
In this actually ties into something else
Which was that it has
Hired a director of engineering
Amazon
So in part of what they were talking about in this with this hiring
Is Robert Parker
In an interview that Parker did with the Verge he talked about actually establishing
Guard rails is was his term for it
In SmartThings
Improve the user experience
What is part of that
I think what we'll see is also ways that
You wouldn't have quite as much openness around as being able to
Deposit
Rich in the good news here is at the basis of this
Exploit
Really has to do with the Privileges that the smart app
Smartthing apps
Are given
This is something Samsung
Fix I mean
Take a look at the ARs Technica story that
55% of the 499 smart apps available during
The research
Call fighting over privileged
So you got to violating a core security tenant notice Pekingese
Privilege principle developers may not even be aware that their SmartThings apps
Have too much privilege
You know it's not like the developers are creating this stuff to do
Malicious things problem is I guess in the SDK or whatever
To ask just have too much power
So to speak
It's like when you don't give your teens a curfew
And you just let them run amok
Yeah
Over-privileged
Going out at 3 a.m. nothing
What happened to you
That's basically what this is about
Alex Hawkinson on the show to talk about this
Because
They had so many issues lately
I know that
They're really trying hard what they're trying to do in terms of being super open
To challenge I agree
We hopefully will hear back
SmartThings
Met Gala
Onhub
We should probably talk really fast because we've got some corporate news
In the acquisition
So Microsoft acquired an Italian company called Solaire
I'm assuming that's how you call it it's Solair
Is it's about 5 years old
Which is provided
Device management
Device lifecycle management kind of stuff in the cloud
It really struck me that Microsoft with its Azure iot platform is going to go up real heavily against
PTC
Which I don't know if you guys remember
And
A rant
So
The idea is
Manufacturer
And
Say hey
Handle all the connectivity side of it and then
That's kind of
Adoption center
This company I mean they're not
I did not hear them prior to but I do see that they've work with the Italian espresso machine manufacturer rent Zillow
That's correct
And also a food processing Machine Company Minerva
Make a group so
I said PTC acquired
A ranch
Which is wrong
Acquired
Stacy you're over privileged
I'm over privileged
As I was saying and I was like wait a second that's not right
All right PTC acquired
That was back at the end of 2014
It provides Cloud platform for
So as yours actually going up against these guys
Which is kind of cool
Different model
Really focusing on both
Truant
Industrial
Enterprise
So there's that
Power
Which
Used to provide energy management software for utilities and they kind of have been
How to say pivoting
Because I haven't done a full pivot but they kind of switch there
Way of being
They started out with kind of demand response and now they're trying
Provide light
Data services
Boston this week
For 532 million
So
Great deal
And
You can see this working for the Internet of Things
The vertical Focus that a lot of the big companies that
I need to get
So
We should look for
Demtech wire specific expert
Batis in like
Manufacturing the internet
Utilities
Maybe medical devices in healthcare
So that was kind of my quit take from there
Now I will say
The oracles offer was half of our powers IPO price in 2014 so
This was not like
Possibly the best outcome
I think it was
Still at a premium
30% of the stock at the time
Escalate the deal
So
If I don't talk about is
Google
And the return of Rick
Rick osterloh
Osterloh yes
What a great guy in my standard disclosure being that I can I work for Google I don't know anyting
About this other than what's been reported
Just to be clear
But I do know Rick osterloh
Great guy
Ahi
Ran Motorola for quite a while the device is over there
And
When Motorola went to from Google to Lenovo he went along for the ride
And according to recode and it says it was it's been confirmed by Google spokesperson I don't know who that was
Whatever but
He's coming back
And whooping charges like
Everything
Consumer Hardware e44 Google
Yeah so some of the new divisions according to recodar
Connexus
Tablets
Chromecast
Consumer Hardware which includes Chromebook laptops and the new pixel C devices
Onhub
8 app
Which is the advanced technology
Yes and that's what good thing did the I forget what it stands for 2 but they did the modular
. they do some really cool stuff
Absolutely
And
Actually lost
The head of that
Facebook
Regina Dugan
Advanced technology and projects
That division was one of the very few that
Google did not sell
Telenovela when Motorola was Villanova
And there's
Class
Which
We must all remember from
Glass
It might have been 13 but the 14-year that sounds about right somewhere in there
Was given charge that's the CEO of nest
Was given charge of glass but
Apparently now it is he staying on his
This is not going to be
So we can take a lot of things from this
Just so Kevin doesn't feel uncomfortable I'll just start
Taking things
Which is
This is what a slap in the face for
Tony fadell
Because
They were the consumer Hardware
Definition
For Google in a lot of ways
And it sounds like
Google is
Limiting his fiefdom tremendously to
Possibly what they
They have
Seen elsewhere that like
Some of the
Reported projects such as Google's
Echo like device and
Other stuff that's developing
For the smart home might come under
This is well so
That's good because Australia was a good guy
It's bad for desk
Antenna makes me wonder how long that's going to be like what happens with that
Going down the road
Yeah well I will say this I mean
I guess you could say that Tony fadell was
Like the face of consumer Hardware but really
He had nothing to do with the Nexus program Chromecast
Chromebook
Tablets
And all that so
I wouldn't want to overstate what he had he had
The Nest group in
Glasses
Apparently so
Well there we go
Kevin doesn't
Retro
I'll be alone
I'm alright well I think that's pretty much it
Podcast
I will say that our guest
Coming up
Is Pike whites
Who is the head of openhab
I'm pretty sure that's an open source
Home automation can a software code
And we'll talk about what you can do with it why it exists and what happens when
Companies don't want to share their API how
Stay tuned
It's going to be fun
Hi this is Stacy breaking into the iot podcast to tell you two things the first is that have launched a weekly
Please let her devoted to the internet of things that you can sign up for it Stacey on iot. Com
Stacey on iot
The second is that we're now accepting ads on the Internet of Things podcast we have packages for big come
Companies and startups
So if you were interested please email Andrew at iot podcast. Calm and now back to the show
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Kai quite sure who is the founder of
Open house
Hi how are you doing today
Fine thanks how about you
I am super well so it is late at night where you are
Or later at night
So I appreciate you doing this show let's first get into
What is openhab
Because a lot of the project people might know about it I doubt like the regular users do
Open up is an open source software
Smart Home
Butt smelly
Target Salinas
DIY user so text every people
Who want to integrate
A lot of things
Alright so I will tell you guys that open have is even a little dirtier than than I am comfortable with
Because
What is basically is as you can put this on a Raspberry Pi
Or
We were talking about a couple shows ago on the pine64
And it's cool because in the reason cuz on the show is because this is a completely different model for building
Alta connected home
Which is
YouTube
In the open have guys
Their whole effort is around
Truly creating an open kind of home automation platform
Walk me through how we got to this place and why you thought the world needed open now
All started about six years ago when they started
Build a house on my own or for my family
I was really interested in automating stuff for already since childhood to answer for me
I have to build a house from scratch because I can put
Cables anywhere I like
And start really
Put in
Switchable lights are shutters or Energy Systems
A lot of Hardware was in there but I was somehow liking
Good software
And some
The problem for me was that I wanted to try some software where I can
Shorts
Future proof that I can
Extended even in the few decades
It's from now
And so for me it was pretty clear that's it
Must not depend on single vendor and their system at the business strategy
But that I'm really free
And open to Extended or four
Whatever comes up
Okay
And so you guys have built this
To make this work with any device out there
You guys just need access to
To an SDK or an API
How does that work
Yeah so it's pretty open up is running on the home Gateway as he said on a Raspberry Pi or some more
Capable of
Computer
And the integration are to the end devices Astin in whatever radio
And devices so quiet
Success
So there are f****** in many of the violence protocols like seawave CT
An ocean and others so are you having a USB dongle and so are you then integrate that's at school.
This supposed to call other devices have four
Normal ethernet to WiFi connection
And so they might have
Maybe I'll
Barry Austin.
Criteria API
Truck side steps
Answer for the mothers you might also have to go to school reverse engineering is he report call or whatever
In order to be able to communicate with these devices
Okay see you lost like half the people right now and it's a pretty tech-savvy Adi
But still I think they're like
Reverse engineering
The others are like yes
But
Commercially
Is this
Reasonable I mean or is what I mean is it going to break down that the smart home is really going to be only open in future
Approved for people who are able to you know
Reverse-engineer the data flow from their device
I think it's really the best
Best option for the Texans
People
It is so Technical and she or you have to know little bit what about you doing there
So it's nothing that you that you buy off the shelf and it's simply DirecTV
The good thing there is that this openness and
Freedom and Independence Aralia
Gives you
The chance to
App to be open in all the directions so as soon as you
Do a commercial product out of that Co
Getting into some
Business Direction than where you might
Disable okay maybe I only want to partner with that company but not ready
Competitor
And you're
Automatically getting not as open as you would be if you're really completely free of any commercial
Pinterest
And so I think that's really one of the year the major strong points of her open her up and
Something that I really want to keep like that for the future
But what about
Usability
Because I think I feel like that
Is
Not just about like business practices which it can be
There's nothing better than building your own and making your own thing work for you
To avoid somebody clutching her data or
Or pers
What about
Figuring out how to do something
And then keeping it is open as possible like
Have you found companies that are doing
Dissonant in a good user friendly format or
Yeah I wouldn't say that's open app is not user-friendly
Looking into that direction as well so there are a lot of new functionality is currently
Isn't there
That's like something to do or to Discovery so it's automatically scanning your network is checking what
Are USB sticks or you might have been there answer really
Discovered the devices that you have in place and
Make it
Very easy
Uber user interface to
Set up all your stuff
All together
So I think we're we're
Havoline
Increasing
The target audience their butt
At the same time
This is also the year the tricky part
Because as soon as you are
Making it more user-friendly
You also have four more people who
Can't help themselves if they come across problems
And so the more support you actually have to do on your standards or
You was a spatula
Not develop a sense, can look into things
Some how are you you have to balance or your time on such an open source project
How much
Sporty want to do for community members that
Joy uses
And how much time do we actually invest in after other are evolving the project answer pregnant for
And that's definitely something we're
Non-commercial project
Has its limits because
Then the time is Maria
Sky sunset
Jump the people
Working on it so I usually doing it for
The only use Kaiser so down
Happy as soon as it works for them
Is there any possibility that we could see this project go commercial
And have
Actual real best support or maybe more robust support
As for me
One of the strong process
That it's
Not, to the projects
Excel
But I'm currently
Doing this to create an organization actually a non-for-profit organization
Surrounded
Where it's at
Easier to organize people around that and maybe also then
Companies who actually
Do open hop installations for living
Capital of Turkey
Commercial companies out there
That's
I like open up so much that they recommended it to their friends and they are the immortalists.
Getting into
Business All-Star installing that and supporting it says that a job
And I think that says definitely a Direction Where We could build a kind of
Marketplace odoo network
For Professional Services
Person that puts us right back into like the x10 or proprietary kind of system days for the end-user because
Cuz you're still going to be at this place for like
4 light bulbs in daylight savings time
My program mysidia program
Wework Miami
My interest
I think the big difference is that it is mainly about
Consultancy Institute
Teach people body
As possible what can they do answer to
Besides OK what might be the best to devices
Stubai how to set them up and
If you consider or smart home technology is not only the consumer electronic parts but really also the
Classical home automation
You have to deal with heating systems and
Shutters
Docker automated
There's actually no way around having your electrician involved in that
Usually only for the initial setup
All the programming or
Let's not call it programming course that's too technical
But some lady automation Oklahoma cancer detection customisation
That can be done by the end she was herself
Got it
With this project
What are people doing with it that's neat cuz we got a lot of people who've asked us to talk more about
How to use in cool stuff that
People dance I'd love to hear
What's some of the people using open have have used it
I see many people doing a lots of energy
Efficiencies so they have for example solar panels that the heating systems and they they really optimize
This together
With
You was doing the
That might be interesting for you with the Tesla integration so they have actually
Electric vehicle charging stations
Directly talking to open Harper and Syrah
Holding 2 tesladin also
For the
Charging of the battery until alarm
Thanks all you can eat
Honk the horn if you like her to open up
I can honk the horn to the app
So in that situation
Tamir rice
You're right I can't I don't have the horn honking like
It would be kind of fun to have the horn honk
Extended security system
Someone someone breaks into my house
The garage that.
Tesla hangzhou
In that situation
Let's break it down for people I would need to hook my Tesla up to my home security system using open
Have I would need something running openhab
I would also need
The Folsom software that lets it talk to my Tesla do I need to have
Openhab the software running on my Tesla software
No sew
Open up itself
Comes with so-called binding
Set the bindings out then doing the integration to the
Different systems and testosterall
You would need us to install the Tesla binding on the open up so on the plants before for example
And this will
In the case of the Tesla or go to the Tesla cloud service
And connect to their so that's no local integration
That's about sums integration
Got it
And how would it work on a local immigration looks so
I'm trying to think of any of the local stuff I have
I'm totally failing since
Most things are actually not
They're mostly in the cloud
But how would that look
If I had an IP camera that was served
For my house
The local integration is the
Most important
Future open up in that respect because some
Only if you're having local integration
You can be pretty sure that your other independent
Of things
Just seen the case with the
Exactly the scenario that we want to avoid but open house sober ever possible
It should be local integration
Yes that's Farm
Most devices actually
Available seoul
All the stuff
It's installed locally you hook it up to your Wi-Fi
Stuff like Phillips you would like a Sonos speakers like
Lifx bulb
Bike
Logitech Harmony Harbor and saw
All these things are local and they have
Some kind of API
That was a much nicer because they are turkey discoverable for UPnP you to go to call
And
Really make sense
Possible to travel very reliable setopati together
What about security because
I'm trying and I'm thinking like as a user
SA
Less than
Technically Savvy user
If I build myself
The openhab
I'm going to be like yeah I'm so amazing
And I'm going to hook it up today that was awesome and I'm going to leave it alone for the rest of the bike Until It Breaks right
So how do you handle things like changing security protocols
I'm hacks fit univ older abilities that may get reported afterwards in need
Updates
How do you communicate that to users because that's
It doesn't feel like that would be part of your core function is
It's kind of a bunch of hobbies
Yeah well if they are willing to work with Latisse All Rights
Definitely fixed in the in the cold but we don't have an automatic update management
Inform people who have set up an instance
But they need to update
So that's definitely currently up with the users to make sure that they
Do regular crate so it is possible to just say
You have an older installation until you get the latest version without losing all your data and just set up
So that's something to be perfectly possible
Got it so where are we in the evolution of the Smart Home
Where we come where we going
In your your opinion
Smart home Technologies believe
Pretty old soul
I know it since at least two tickets I think we are still in a very early face
On the market
So I see you the the the marketing people saying since about
5 years at least.
Now
The big breakthrough
But some
If I look at
Their house
Easily breakable
Pink Salon Tower
Difficult it is for Relief beginners to learn to get started
Stuff
I think it will
Take a while
And some
I'm not saying that's the soccer part of the problem
Still
On the on the starting point of having really
Reliable protocol is Reliable Hardware
And saw
Thanks for the
Break too easily and
Communication is not not stable enough
And stuff like that
So that's pretty as to
Become
Better over the next year's
Software perspectives
I also think that there's a lot of hype around artificial intelligence and sore having smart home being
Your assistant at home that's a really knows what you want the traffic looks on Blue come out
El mencho favorite music playing
I really don't believe in that so becoming
True
Anytime soon
Because
It's really you need to laugh so much contextual information in order to
Levi's decision says an automated system
That's
All the possible sensors that
We haven't play snow already know.
Not enough to have that
Get the mood of somebody to get the whole circumstances in which something is happening
To troll the right
Cancel.
And I wasn't completely sure for you really
Wants to go the way to Atmore Center Center stop
Tool to make that contact
Available to the machines because that's then again also privacy issue
Assurance people might not feel
Compatible
So you might snow the analogy about The Uncanny Valley
And so I think this very much applies to artificial intelligence in the
Smart home as well for the listeners who are not familiar with that
20 minutes.
Or robots on automatic system
Fusible rear sensor
People are not compatible with that
As long as it's not perfect
I was at the actors in The Polar
Express they were just sold
Freaky Deadeye lookin
Dividers
3D version of The Polar Express from a couple years back that is The Uncanny Valley
Applied to your favorite Christmas book
I like this
So then what
Reasonably should we expect
I mean
Most people when they automate their homes if they're buying into this they're like
I want all this to happen right that's what they're kind of working towards both as an industry and even consumers is
What kind of work being sold
So
What do you think is a more realistic
Vision to sell consume
I think as long as the artificial intelligence that's just said wherever notes on the
Trophic level
You really have to go into programming and somebody else the only
Signal that I see there is
That you you make it
Easy to have
Complex logic setup for the user
So one day we were trying to drive that in
Open Office to a sable you have automation who was which is a piece of a logic that's execute
Butts
The
Normal user itself doesn't have to implement its butt
Can be a developer
Repair phone that
And the usertrust to configure SATA and
Customizes it's for his own purposes
So you can think of that a little bit like the Apes this man that approached
Where you have to use recipes with
So you hate that's a you case you want to use it at your
Creating this recipe
Using an X configuring it to your own
Set up
That's really what what is the
Most realistic way forward for the MoMA
And that's something you guys are implementing so in does that look like
You can do or it's automatically
Populated
The smallest a dream but definitely the interaction we're heading there so we're
Implemented the new rule engine that is
Capable off for having sex and play this week all that stuff all the rules
And strive for a user interface where I can easily instantiate the stuff
For coming on the show today
I cannot wait to try this out and if I if I actually do this
Which I feel it will be very empowering
And Kevin will laugh
I wish you much on offense
Thanks for having me on the show
Thank you for coming
Well that's it for this week's show thanks for listening and we'll see you back next week