Hey everyone you're listening to The Internet of Things show and I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And I'm talking about
Teachers in the Smart Home
Industrial internet Consortium testbed
Bliss hub
And the Brit
So Kevin are we ready
We are ready as long as you don't talk about a hub github
You know the article
Who says
Alright so we're getting ahead of ourselves
Express
We want to start off with a story from wired that I actually thought was
Really
Encapsulated a lot of things
The story
Is basically
It's my David Pierce and it talks about how
At WWDC Apple introduced a bunch of features that we've already seen before and how all the features on
Form separately coalesce
I think what got David thinking about this was
The the big one more thing Apple which was Apple music obvious that's not related
But it really hits the point that
Hey everybody else has a music service
To what why was this one more thing
As you said
Mobile platforms have matured so much
Pretty much
All the same in some sense may be different implementations
I think so I think about
But they're all the same so how does that apply to
Startups
It doesn't
Because nothing about any of my smart home stuff is
In thinking about kind of the news that we've had I think that there are a couple things that everyone's kind of gravity
And we're not there yet
Right now we're all at the end of Lake
One app to control multiple
Devices
So we see a lot of those being integrated where you can
Control
Your lights
From
Ihob
Like a SmartThings aura
Staples connect kind of
App
Where everyone is pretty clear that we're going is all these devices will eventually
Talk to one another
I think the difference is our
How they're going to
So
One of the big things that I've seen is
We're going to be
Fighting over
Services in the cloud or services in the home
And that's actually something that we talked about many times before because
Turn off we stand on different sides of that but I know from an implementation standpoint
I prefer to have my stuff
Local
Which on a device
Rather than
In the cloud
Where
Making my sins are program in the cloud
Can I have no
Internet connectivity for some reason and my scenes don't happen because the cloud didn't say make the same time
Exactly
The actual implementation will take place in both locally and the cloud
Like a light switches that should be local
Because there's too much latency
Right
You should have some of your basic programming
Auto local hub
Because yes if your internet goes down Sudley Road
Oh crap
Nothing works
When the sun sets or 3 hours before the sun sets
Take my shades down a notch
That's the kind of stuff
But you're going to need Cloud access for because presumably
The time of day that the sunsets is going to live
Maybe because I actually have that exact
I'll call it a recipe or seen
Had it on my insteon server and the server used
Anybody dress each day how many minutes before sunrise sunset
So could be local but I suspect yes most
People would would need Cloud for that
What is an architectural decision you can make you can actually download
Like once a day
Your server checks in and
Posen weather
Time
Point of light switches and latency and so on and
I mean I don't want to have to
Have a signal goes thousands of miles and then come back just to turn on the light switch
Being silly
I think
We'll see what happens over there
I think you're right where you had said
Could be maybe a combination
And by that I mean maybe you have all of your local controls will your controls local
And your rules local but sync
We're stored in the cloud as midi a backup copy
And therefore you could have come like a hybrid Model A
Depending on which made the most sense to use the time it would just
Alright so we got the hybrid model and I was thinking more control
Are you going to talk to your house or you going to
Show interface
Yeah
Interface
Wise guy said
Back in 2011 when Siri first came out because really that was the big first of all say
Boise personal assistant type software that hit mainstream
Tammy voice was going to be at some point in future the invisible interface
Because it's
Comment if the most common interface I think there is as opposed to
Dealing with touch screens and keyboards and mice and
Switches and
Wall panels in Solon
Also present some of the biggest
Challenges
In terms of natural language processing
Then again going back up to the cloud and there's a lot of things lot of moving Parts there that have to work
So
I don't think it was going to be an overnight
Interface
But I do think in the Long Haul
I think it's going to be voice
In the home
Maybe not everywhere
When you're out and about
Sitting around on a
Subway or bus
You're not going to use voice for everything
Examples for interact
There's lots of people around you and
And someone is just not going to work as well in the home though I can see it
Are physical
Presence is going to be a huge
A way that we interface with device
Even if it's like a secondary layer that
Voice or touch screens or anything else I think
Our physical presence is going to be noted enough in the home that
It will
Respond like oh is she's turning if she says turn on the lights and she's in this room
It's like a 98% probability she wants the lights
It gets axle that gets into the next
Peace that I wanted to talk about and it's contacts
Because contacts has a huge part of this
You got your sensors to gather the data
What is the context that
Case today that makes Intelligent Decisions based on the sensor data
But
And this gets back to the everybody's the same in some sense and in some ways they're not
Platforms and IRT
You got to give up information in order to provide
Contacts
And a lot of people are still not
Comfortable with that
Yes so there is
There's actually
A big kerfuffle today in the world because
We haven't used it yet that's a good one
Alright big kerfuffle right now in
Privacy kind of sphere because
With facial-recognition happening
More often in Facebook launching a platform
On this week called moments that uses
Facial recognition to Kinder
Auto tag
Your friends and help you share content among them
Which Google actually does to now with its new Google photos it does a lot of facial recognition stuff
Exactly
We anticipate the Dropcam actually Nest Dropcam uses facial
Recognition or has the ability to use facial
Recognition
And so does the
We're going to talk about later
In the Privacy Arena
What happened is the
Ntia
Which is a government
It's the national telecommunications and Information Administration
They were trying to work with industry and privacy groups to create this voluntary code of conduct around how people are going to use
Facial recognition data
And the privacy
Oriented groups basically left
Stealing like they weren't being heard and that the companies
We're not going to
Implement any standards
While
I can understand why the Privacy groups are
Concerned
But I almost think that you can't have it both ways you can't have
The intelligence that devices can provide
Without giving them more and more information
It should be out there not obviously I mean I don't think
People shouldn't just
Say I'm stuck with it.
You know you can not buy
In the end especially at the younger generation
Pretty much. He's convenience of a privacy as soon as I get older I don't think
I don't think it will be as big as a kerfuffle
In the future in the cities today
I hope you're right
I do think we should be having a good kind of in-depth discussion about this and I'm sure we're actually going to get someone on a podcast
In a couple weeks who's going to have this in-depth discussion
In the meantime
Context is one of kind of
The core things that we think are smart home platform will need
I think programmability like how we program it
Is going to have to change
And so I'm really interested I don't think we know how that's going to happen
If it's going to be kind of a
Data-driven model where like
When you plug in a device
Suggest like I see you have the following other devices would you like to hook us up and do this
Or if it's going to be more programmatic like
If this then that
So I think that's still up in the air
I think we're heading towards the former
Example though I do think that
The companies that really want to push IRT or trying to make the devices
Work with each other with
Far less interaction
I agree
The other question is how people get it are they going to buy it from a service provider or an alarm company or
Best Buy in Amazon
Actually really legit
We're all over the map their personal am I'm a DIY guy so I don't want
Companies that
Modern Fusion
And controlling and even access to that data potentially that
We don't want them to have some
Now it says convenience versus cost
Thinking about to get some input from you guys if you have any thoughts
At
Starcom
And
Next up is the industrial internet Consortium
Do you remember these guys
They are launched last year at
Was GE Cisco
The president the White House
Saying hey
We're doing this industrial internet Consortium
It'll be great
Nobody knew what it was
Including me
I first saw the news I tried to figure out what they were doing a conclusion that this was just a
The standards organization
Entrenched
How did you really feel about
That's true
Today
Are this week
Released their first
I guess we'll call a product it's actually a test bed that's been built by
EMC and Vodafone
And it's in Ireland
And what they're doing is there
Basically creating a virtual
33 data centers
And they're creating
The appearance of one data center basically so you could send data and it doesn't really matter where it goes
Switch Data Center
And idea
The first kind of use case is
Platform called Blue Light
And what it will do is
If someone is in an ambulance
It will take the data from
Ambulance and send it to the hospital
They're going to so you'll get the patient data
Water on
Route basically to the
Which is kind of a cool app
Location
Absolutely
Healthcare Providers on how to
Practically received information know what to expect and you can be better prepared
So exactly
And so
I think the end instead of just like
Like the patient's heart data and all their
Vital signs from the paramedics
This guy he was crushed by a car
So
I should be good
So that is that
Moving out of the industrial internet and back into the home
We have
Kevin years
Your thoughts on the
Homekit as the homeless hub
Publix sub
Homeless homeless
Nobody should be homeless
This was an interesting article over it that's not funny. Com
Apple's homekit and
Howard wheeler won't work with a hug
And Adam Bianca who wrote the article
Found something really interesting and he's been playing with
With some homekit devices the first
You have just launched in the past couple weeks
Co-create his Lutron caseta Hub and again I may be saying that
To the new homekit version
And then found out that
He can actually control it through the Elgato Eve app on his iPhone
So the EVAP which Eve we talked about in the past like those are the the sensors that you put in your house for a humidity temperature in such right
Yes
Right so
In the EVAP he could actually
Control
Through
So is interesting in that we talked about getaways Apple TV going to be a
Homekit hub
That all the devices work through we already know that
Apple TV will even though Apple did not announce us at WWDC it's on their support page for for homekit
Apple TV
Gateway for remote access
But in a sense it almost sounds like you don't need a hub
For the homekit devices to
Work together that was a key question I had
About how dissolving a horse
In Tampa because
I like things to do things based on what's Happening so if
One sensor see something maybe another device from another manufacturer might
Do something else and they looks like
There may be wasted at least control thing
So I thought I was quite interesting
He summed it up I'm going to read what he said
Because I think this really drives
Homekit is the ability to standardize the language spoken by all of your smart home things
So that these things can all interact with each other and
Can be controlled by multiple iOS devices
Without needing to be a central control
And they said it's finally a hubless smart home hub
It sounds to me this is very much the vision of
Join
Talk to each other
And communicate
Between devices
And using a set of standard
I guess it's schema
A standard way of saying
I am dis
I have the capability to do
The following sing
That's exactly what I'll do
It sounds also a lot like what Google
And
It's also what Intel has been pushing with iotivity
It's a lot like this
And isn't that interesting we started the show with how all the
Things are becoming the same depending on you regardless of manufacturer
Mrs.
Again
The same concept apply to Coyote and hunting snorkels now
Yes but these are not interrupt
Yet so catch there
I guess it's time for us to go to our 5 minutes
This is going to be probably a lot
More than 5 minutes
5 ish
You can stop at five
So what I'm talking about is the welcome camera
It was launched this week
Is the company that also makes the rain gauge system
Camera itself
Is brand new
It retails for $199
And the coolest thing about it
Other than its design
It's a very tiny Pringles can
It is this
It's the science
About the
It's smaller than a
Like a 16 oz water bottle
And it's even a little skinnier and it's
It's beautiful
Aluminum recycle paper towel roll
No it's
Is shorter than a paper towel roll but it's about that
Okay
It's a camera
It's pretty
And the coolest thing about it
Is that it offers facial recognition
So
When people walk in after you train it a little bit
I got it for day and a half and I'm Midway through training in it
Faces
Who is this person
And you say oh it's Stacey
Or in your case you like I was Kevin
And whenever it sees that person
It sends a notification to you in the cool thing is
The notification
It's no longer like I've detected movement
Which doesn't tell you anything it now says
Kevin's home
Kevin Zoe's home I don't get out much
In the kitchen
Can you connect me depending on where your camera is
He brings presents
So it's a way to bring
Presents
Minutes away to bring presents
What's even for people
Like my daughter who doesn't have a cell phone or Bluetooth devices on
I knew you were going to go there cuz I was just going to say
My phone can do that
T4 presents but you're right
Not everybody has one end
Yes I know I know
This is this isn't interested like bring presents into the home
People are going to be really excited about is
The camera can take video
And
Record of life
Motion-sensing
And pictures related to that
Are all stored on an SD card on the device
Sono cloud in golf
So there is a cloud
What did such a cloud is basically the timeline of events
Like so
Kevin has
NFL
Face basically so
Kevin has
Is entered the kitchen
Gets stuck
You can send your face to the cloud
And the videos that
Can generate
If you asked me to generate videos
Let's not go there we've already had one kerfuffle on the show
But that's the sphere is connected cameras in my home
Suddenly my home is now
Open to
Basically anyone who's like
Has the capability to
Hack into a server
In Amazon stock end
So here's a question
I'm not going to go not going to talk about the price 199 it is what it is
What can I do with that other than just being notified that I could I have certain things happen in the house
Trigger events
Because I walk in the door
With clothes on
Hopefully if you're coming in from outside you are wearing
Today
With all this other devices are supported
If this then that
This because it just launched his not but that is a priority
According to the CEO
Soon
You should be able to say when Stacy enters
Turn the Lights this way
And they will happen this way but when my husband enters a room where my daughter does
It would be
Turn the Lights this way
Kind of their first priority
We'll see how long it take
It shouldn't take too long
That will make it far more valuable to me
Yes yes I don't think I mean
It is always nice you can currently
Look into wherever the room is and see a live
It's delayed by a
4 second
Just enough to put your clothes on
Terrible
Sorry
So so that
Security
That's worthwhile to them
They can look in
They can also set it so people who aren't recognized
Tetrachords a video so if like some burglar breaks in
If there's definitely a security aspect in addition to presents I like that
Security
Presents
I wonder if the facial recognition works with animals cuz I used a webcam 3 years ago to figure out which the cat
Square
Relieving themselves on my Christmas tree
Facial recognition
You have to train it on
A set of
Faces so if you wanted to recognize animals you have to train it on a set of animals
I don't think they've done that
Probably a low priority for the company I get it
So I think that's it
Please stay tuned because our guest
This week is Dave Freeman
Who is the CEO of a company called
And they are providing
Background integration platform
A lot of really cool device
Sister being connected in China
So
We're talking about wechat's plans for iot as well as just the Chinese market
Bore of The Internet of Things
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
I have our guest for today it is Dave Friedman who is the CEO of Ayla Networks
Hey Dave how are you doing
I'm doing great sweetie how are you
Wonderful and
Just for a listener sake
Davis in China
And connections so we may get some
Interesting moments in this podcast I'm going to try to edit out
Be prepared
It's worth it he's totally worth it you guys
Alright so
Let's start out ala is a
It's a cloud provider
Companies who want to
Get products online
Yes that's correct we provide infrastructure
Manufacturers so that they don't have to
To try and do this on their own are our infrastructure includes a cloud platform
The manages the devices a device side software
That's running inside chips are gateways and application software
Awesome
And you are in China because you guys just announced that you are doing a deal where you're the kind of back in provider
Weather for
WeChat
And services their offer
We definitely work very closely with WeChat
A lot of us
May not know what WeChat is in the United States but it's massive
Pretty much everyone uses it here as a social network so the idea is
Of course
We're all looking for the super app and
A tailor we can't believe these Giants social networks
Sunshine in the US
Swill
Have the best
Chance
Provide that super app
Yes sir we are making it easy for all the manufacturer
Awesome services
Got it
So
Walk me through an example
Because I think if wechat kind of like
WhatsApp Meats Twitter
So
How would a customer use the
Well you know it's interesting that are really mundane
And they're not that
On their own
And yet when they can interact with
The Social Network where you spend all your time I guess it makes them
More interesting
But but
Maybe more importantly if you make lights
Switches or something
You can sell
Your own light switch app
But
Better perhaps if it uses the
WeChat apps
Maybe control the light switch cuz you might use the same WeChat app
Lots of other things in your home I think it's the integration
And getting closer to the super app
Is the most exciting part of this
All right
When you keeps you keep using that word
I don't know what you mean
Well you know it's funny when you start a company like Ayla you you can look into the future little bit you say
Do I want a door lock thermostat light switch app a refrigerator in a garage door
And I think we know the answer to rhetorical question
And so
The super app
I guess for us is
Start of the my home app
And we think we chat in the social networks have the best opera
Community to provide the super app or the my home app my question for you is how I as a user
Turn on my lights using WeChat and then again how I as a user would do something like set of goodnight set
Using WeChat
Well
Technical answered that they enable the ability to have HTML5
Control apps
It's not just a noun
Speak into the app like a standard WeChat
So they've built out the infrastructure
So that you can actually control light bulb you can build a nap inside WeChat the controls light bulb
Okay what are the benefits of using a social network
As opposed to
Your own kind of home hub I can think of things like
When you travel
Swift like your hotel room or
It is that even possible or is that just crazy talk
You know it's a broad question
In the case of
Little Caesars Entertainment there's this
Vast social network that they might want to tap
More of these
Great Chinese consumers into their hotel rooms now
In your home
Again it just makes it easier than the Chinese internet companies do so much more than say create a chat app
They do payments you can
You can help tax
I have an Uber like capability inside China to so they
Built the infrastructure so again if you
Have your device
Connected to WeChat there
Services that does payment and end all sorts of different things
Got it so
They have all of this information I just tell it what I wanted to do
I'm working within the app so I don't have to open my new app
That's correct
Got it okay
That does sound sleeper
So let's let's talk a little bit about where China is with adopting the internet
Speakers
You guys have been there for
Years guess maybe
Movie years is too long
It is all sort of gradually growing invest
Smith that's not so gradual
Yes funny I had a big dinner with our team we had a
The official opening we've probably been at it
For two years here of our officer was last year about this time and so
We went last year when we open that office
There were fewer people globally at ala
Then there are now in
China so I think there's about 30 people in China
Enchanted
What's happening right now is
I think it's like the United States only touch behind his ally awesome Kickstarter company launching products
And there's the big companies are starting to
The build and design their products
You're not seeing a huge amount of these
Things on the shelves
We'll see a lot more 2016 really 2017
Toby
The same of the US only the us maybe you know we'll see holiday 2016 Dobby
A good amount just a lot of
Design activity happening
Okay
And do these devices like
Right now I feel like we're the stage of buying one off devices
And I'm looking forward to when we get to the stage where we kind of start just building connectivity into things
Because it's cheap because it makes sense
Yeah you know I think you're right though but so what's happening is there's a product manager at these companies whose lawn
Launching a product it's not yet certain
Corporate at the sea level
A bunch of ayla's customers an hour or big Appliance companies and they have a whole plan of launching
Sexy
Devices that they don't just
Do you know they might say kitchen appliances in MA
I'll let you know the clothing type stuff
But it is right it's one off
So you know what they're great products
But everyone's starting with her toe in the water I think that's why like I said you're not going to have
Huge amount
Holiday 2015
You'll have a bunch more 2016 and you'll start to see the integration of all these things
And a lot more volume
Now
Stacy the other big deal though it's funny when we started the company 2010
The cost to add the networking like the hardware part ala dozen
We don't do Hardware but
It was probably about 70% higher than it is today
And same with info
You know it's amazing so
Amazon services
Is we run globally on AWS inside China 2
Aldo's
Also drop by about 7
80%
This is you know your set your question is will when will I see and everything
You're about to
Do because everyone is singing at the prices are now they say
Should I can put this in in the cost
The added
To my thing almost whatever it is
Is outweigh even by the ability to Serta
Understand warranty and service and maintenance
Let alone turn the cool features for consumers
Awesome so how much does the hardware
It is
Well below $5 now
You mentioned the cloud cost and I have to ask
Because
One of the things I'm really curious about is
How long you might want to support
The washing machine or something that's
It feels a little low value in terms of
Opportunity
And it's important that for like 15 years on a cloud
Does that make
Economic sense
You know it.
We don't necessarily do it if it
If it doesn't make sense and I don't think the manufacturer would either frankly now
You know what's interesting so today a lot of the product
That we work with
Are connected either by zigbee connect
One of the gateways
Or Wi-Fi
Now so you're at that that's a hardware thing that we just talked about but eventually because now you have
NFC that's going to be opened up an iPhone as well
You know you're at your washing machine might just have an NFC thing for you
You know you to be able to help troubleshoot
And hit a button and send it up
I understand what's going on with the product
But you know what's interesting is connected let's just use at a clothes washer
It doesn't have to talk to the service very often
It might talk to the service once a day
The ability for a thing like
The clothes washer to talk to a service once a day
It is
Incredibly efficient
To be able to do that doesn't cost a lot
Oh yeah
I agree now I would say
I think Bender should probably just stay
Wi-Fi or some kind of
Constant connectivity in there
Because I've never met someone
Who gets data from the internet
It says
Wow
This is great
And once a day is enough
I feel like what will happen
Is the people that every time I won
Run my washer is there going to be like
Hey actually we want to know every time she runs it
We want to know what's in there if possible and how it's running
And suddenly
What happens is
It's being connected more and more often
That's kind of how they
Internet works right
You know I think there is
There's not one-size-fits-all
The cost reduction that's half
Really it's a trade-off right it's the user going up to the thing and touching it with a phone and getting the data
Versus
It's slightly if you know the Edition
Cost of adding Wi-Fi it's really that simple
I think the cost of that is going down to wear lots of manufacturers
Would like to have that concert
The connection is true
How are your customers thinking about building these products are they trying to build in basically connectivity for
Coolest sake
Are they really trying to create
A new service
We have what we would call 1.0 company so what and what we mean by that is
Some customers want to have at least
Feature parity
With maybe a new entrance
The market
And when I want to say one. Do it just means
I want to also be competitive I I want to give
Similar capabilities that
Someone else has
One of our early customers
Is Johnson Controls a build a great
Thermostat
Using Amos technology where the underlying platform for that and Nest was in the market now this allowed them to
Get something on the market Havasu without hiring a whole cloud
Semenax semen everything
But some companies are thinking about the data much earlier and probably faster than we thought
Some companies realize
State if they understand
What's going on with the products
They can earn
More services
Or they can
Provide
Actually service and maintenance
Mortician
God is a bit of a mix
No that makes sense
And let's take it back to China since
That's where you are
Pictures this week with WeChat
Was
Consumer-oriented
But
Are you working with Chinese manufacturers or how is it
How is kind of Batman
Evolving
Yeah it's kind of only for manufacturer
There's really a so
Century one of the companies we work with his ozner it's a makes perfect sense they provide
Water filtration
Filters and they kind of do kind of the o2o type thing
You're the online-offline where they
They get people to your building or your home
And replace
The filters
David Kennedy getting these things connected so that desire need for them bad connectivity no the WeChat
And consumers are major Target makes it just
More cool more approachable
No not like some
Weird thing you have in the background by
People in China spend a lot of time on WeChat and this
Just makes
Maybe something of mundane
Perhaps like a filter
Just a little cooler
I see I can't wait for a cooler filters
With
With the Chinese market as a US company
What was your process in getting over there and what are the advantages and
Let's talk a little bit about that
One of the processes for being here was have a co-founder
Who has amazing relationships
In China
And by the way without that
Your China is all about relationship
Entrust first
And then you have to have great technology and Emmett and a business
This model that works
But Philip who I've worked with Forever Phil Chang
We he and I worked
Together in China at our last company and someone we started this company
We said hey let's give to go
Let's see if we can leverage these relation
And and do something interesting when we started by the way we chat was almost nothing at that
Know if WeChat had
Any users we start in 2010 our first customer in China was Cena
WeChat was smaller than Sina weibo back
It's much different right now
That's true
Things move fast
They do they do
As it is a back in provider
Asbys
As he's kind of abs inflows and popularity of service
Services happen
Do you see adding
Adding connectivity to your home being something that will help retain users and keep
Keep them from moving or is that just kind of an offering that
Can skip from place to place cuz now it's basically in the cloud
So
Fickleness I suppose of the consumer is less of an issue for a lice
We're just
The underlying
Infrastructure that it is using
So that they can build a set of connected pricing
Connect to
B2c applications are maybe the most popular at the time
Right now I'm thinking about for your customer base
Okay for so4 the a Lacoste
Base meaning manufacturer
Manufacturers
WeChat guys
Yes how easy is it
The consumer tied in
Pinterest
Once you've built it
It service
I think I guess if you're using data you can follow
I mean without
The data then you're it's very difficult but the biggest with or without ala by the way the giant internet plan
They understand consumers they understand your eyeballs and what you do all the time Amazon is amazing
At this
Your browser tells
Them everything about you
And so I think that's why these companies are
Beating against maybe the Old Guard they are great retailer because they understand the
Data
WeChat certainly understands how people use their services as well and now
Honestly we just see the internet is
Evolving
From PC to mobile two things
So you're getting a 1/2
You punch your customers are reducing their shirt and consumer users
Also getting access to this amazing
Set of data that they can then use to
Presumably improve their services
Yeah that that's right I need a WeChat these are giant, Adela is just to be clear not the only way
That they interact with internet
The things they have amazing Engineers we work with
They also connect directly to manufacturers
But we do provide also pasta
How to get a lot of Manufacturers onto their services very quickly and efficiently
And yes then
By doing that they
And I think where they will be much better than even a company like ala
Come is a WeChat can really understand what consumers want
They can aggregate
What consumers are doing with all these
Different devices
And provide a better and better experience
So you're manufacturing customers
Are they can
Concerned about that because they're going to get data from their what
Appliances
Where is
Someone like
WeChat
Can see the whole
What's the date at which
Presumably has more value
And what kind of dynamic does that set up
You know I
I think it's a good question that they manufacture at least in the case where a Le is there in
Infrastructure they get
Decide
Which data goes up to WeChat
So we have something called role-based access
Controlled the manufacturer
Who gets to decide
By the data point
I mean by all that you know that they can have a
An air conditioner gives 50 different date appointments and they can send 11 of them up
WeChat but they don't have the capability the realities
If you make air conditioners and that's what you do
Then you
Are not going to have data
From
Kitchen appliances
Got it
Okay
Anything else about
China
The Internet of Things
Ala what we believe in what you see is obviously
The population here is massive
The amount of mobile
Users is also massive
China seems to be
We thank in north then say North America in terms of
Since it's such a highly mobile population here
Creating services
Tailored for mobile is
Be something they're very good at here
That is
One reason we spent a lot of time here the other reason is our services for me any facts
And you know a lot of manufacturers
Weather in China
Whether they ship inside China or globally
It's a good place for us to be
Awesome yes
Lots of companies would like to
To be there so
Okay will do thanks for joining us especially late in the evening your time and congratulations
Great thank you it's good speaking with you again
Thanks for joining us this week
Will see you next week