Hey everyone it is the Internet of Things podcast did I am your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
We've got a great show for you today
If you are ready to just be
Just so scared of all the can
Connected devices to your home
Just so scared
Okay
So
We have iot security blows
IHOP
Couple stories
One is a non-story so we're going to briefly mention it and tell you not to worry
That is that
Your your nest device was
Transmitting your ZIP code
That you inserted in
Told the nest
So I can get weather information it was actually giving that to
Was called leaking this data in the
Packet header
Information
In some cases it was your ZIP code in some cases it was the zip code of the weather station
This has since been fixed
The weather station
So don't worry about it
A lot of people were
Mine is deleting my personal data
Sunday morning
Is not anymore
It's not dated this particular personal there were some bad security practices such as
Putting that
Information in
But you know
Nest is no longer doing that hopefully they've learned a valuable lesson
But there is maybe a little bit of something more
Worrisome out there
This happened a couple of days back and I had never heard of this particular search
Vengeance I'm just going to say it and
If it's not familiar to you will explain what it is
It's showdown
Shodan
And apparently a search engine for like iot things
What you can do with show Dad is actually kind of scary you can
Have it
Search for unprotected open webcams
Send their pictures of people's babies sleeping and so on that were found via show Dan in that
Really bad
Okay so
I'm going to do a quick reality check
This is going to be Stacy the geek talking as opposed to Stacy the worried mother of
So
Shootings been around since 2009
It is a search engine for connected devices
And for a long time people have used it as a way to
Find open ports on the internet
Check out
What they recently did was add an image search
And now you can actually search for sleeping babies
Yes
What you can also do is you go in and you don't actually
You actually have to
To type in passwords to
Kodak Kodak
Cameras and stuff
Usually it's
Basic default passwords for these things so like
Admin or password
Password one
Usually get you in a lot of these things
So it's maybe a little harder than you might
Think and
The other thing to know about shooting
And is it's not like just some sort of creepy like place where you can go see
Sleeping children
It's also kind of a neat
Place where you can go and see all these cool connected devices
If you're like
Myself
So I don't want it and I'm like a cool there's like weather stations you can
See your there's
View connected devices in
Actually one of our former colleagues yonko used it to track
Actually I think it was like
I was looking at app download
What's on Roku boxes
Is it again it is
It is like a Google for can
Connected devices
Right
That's just me
I know people are like
But
We don't have to freak out totally
Play freak out a little bit and change your password
I grew that I don't I don't think I should be freaking out it's just
Disconcerning number one
Mainstream people are not going to be going to this
Search engine in the end knowing what to do with it and so on it it's it's kind of the Geeks like awesome
I almost hesitated even bring it up but you know what I mean
Chances are people already know about the people who want to know about it already do so it's really I think the message here is to make sure that you
Your devices are secure as you can make them on the user side
And also from a
Turn a device maker standpoint
You know try and lock these things down give you some control some security control to the users make sure that it's not going through
Open ports and such
This is a good time to bring up a couple things
Thanks Cuz also in his arse
On once you get past
Sleeping baby wipe
Such a nice-looking baby though I have to say
Is it a nice looking baby
We can't see the
The baby
Light blanket in crib
It's a sleeping baby in Canada I didn't realize I was even going across the border here
So it's worth mentioning that we've had on the podcast folks from this group is called I Am the calvary
I'm here Josh Korman who is one of the
The founders effect
Since it's a bunch of security researchers and they actually
2014 released
Anything about connected vehicles in
It was a framework
They created with
The industry with the government in the whole goal was to
Kind of come up with again a framework
For how we should think about securing connect
Vehicles
And what they're doing actually is creating one for the Internet of Things
Which is been a long time
In the story in ours that willing to in the show no
Has a bunch of really awesome stuff in there so we're going to have to get
Them back on the show
The guy who's doing this is Brian nox
Have to have them come and talk about what they're doing here
It's pretty sweet
And with you
Took bunch of best practices that are in consumers interest here with internet security and privacy in
I do remember the I am the cavalry
Creed or Mantra that they
Check offering a couple years back and
I think it's great neck that's long overdue
That's ultimately
Picture here is Sweeney Todd
I need to start locking the stuff down a little bit better as an industry
Yeah and
Is all others
She's a little bit there's three under security so it's secure by default
So
No default password share between devices
Advanced features
That are used by only a few users should be turned off
That's under secure by default
Then you have
Secure by Design
And that's things like sperm or should be locked down
Other memory and storage nand memory storage medium should be protected with
Epoxy ball socket so the memory can't be removed in.
Obzedat's physical security
On the actual silica
Security is selca
So the devices should not rely on the network
Provide security
Rather
The devices
Security model
Summa Network
If the cloud goes down you don't want your devices on
Secure insecure because the clouds down
Bright
So those are under security and then there's some
There's four things for privacy
Quibble I think when we get them on the show talk about this but kind of privacy they have consumer Pi is not shared with manufacturers
Partners usage data on individual consumers is never shared with
Advert
Anonymous data for buckets of users on usage patterns is acceptable
As long as it's proven but not traceable back to the individual consumers
And then for data collection policy type of data collected in usage of data
Is clearly documented
On-site
So what's your quivalizer curiosity I know we'll get them on the show an answer
What is it
Well so it kind of the framework addresses this a little bit but
Buddhist concept of consumer pii which is personally identifiable information
I think that's kind of an archaic notion in a world where we have
Such advanced
Data mining
Because you can basically identify a person
From about three or four pieces of information has been kind of
Consistently proven
And so
I feel like Pi I could be really anything
Now in
3 they say
Anonymous data for buckets of users
Can't be traceable back to individual
Consumers which kind of takes care of
So maybe that's okay but it a lot of
Like laws are written
And they they just
Shove pii
And I'm kind of like
Okay but I hear you
Two-level said everybody this is not the final version of
Are the criteria this is preliminary
That brand Nelson in the group is not
Formally
I guess there was like a public with cuz obviously it's available but they're still working on this
Yes and
You know it is just a frame
You know it's not like
They they call themselves I am the cavalry
It's not like the horses are
Come charging out in anyone with anything
They also do note in the story
Which I'm really sad
Again
I'm really sad that the story like
If you don't read all the way down you're going to miss
A lot of really great stuff because
They talk about the ftce starting to consider how they're going to like
Are they going to do civil fines for this witch
All the way back
In 2013 when the FTC was looking at this
You know they had
People talking to them saying
Dude this isn't going to be secure and you
Find people
You know the rest into
And you know the people who are on the panel advocating for this for sale
Is it there's going to be nothing else
Do you need a stick
Yeah beat people with a stick because right now
Consumers don't pay for privacy
And they don't
Manufacturers
They have no incentive to
Put it in there
Tyranitar
And it's expensive
How to track an
Keep that going south
I'm not going to say regulation is the answer to everything cuz it certainly isn't
But
I can't think of anything else that can keep
The manufacturers in line
So I don't
Have a problem with this
Yet
If the FTC does really get involved depending on the details and what they're going to do obviously
What else is there
I mean the cost of your devices
All right
It's in everyone's best in
Because once we get past this like oh my God it's not secure
People normal people may feel more Trust
And by the
Okay sorry
I said we were moving along then what did I do I kept talking about it
That's all right
It's because I can't find my way back to Archie two things were still talking about
Cute cards
Cue cards Cayenne it's so hot right now
All right
So
I've been talking Kevin you talk for a little while.
Sure we literally out and talk about my devices not stay safe devices not my devices but
The company called my devices. Com they have some news out today that they were recording a show
I think they actually pronounce this in the past but I'm not 100% sure on that or what they've done is they are launching kayak
I am the world's first and I don't know if it's true but
It is a drag-and-drop iot project Builder
Not sure on the whole world's first bit don't think it is actually say she never talked about it before the show
Essentially this is very specific to Raspberry Pi devices
And that's interesting to me because I because I have a Raspberry Pi but be because
It's an affordable solution you can use it
For prototyping you don't need to have a ton of money to
Develop
I have two devices if you can use a pie and some other things such as
List some Dragon drop iot project Builder
Essentially
When is a dragon drop
This is a bunch of
Widgets
Tekken
Be viewed on a website or a mobile device through iOS or Android have an app coming it's a dashboard it's a dashboard
Set of sensors are reading data from sensors that are attached
Perhaps to your Raspberry Pi
You know it's
A low-cost way to I think development
A10 create
Iot devices so
I think it's interesting
Worth trying
I will say it looks a lot like
Freeboard
Rio from bug labs
Which is actually the developer platform that Verizon is using in it
Things space Cloud but other people can use it to sew
Looks like that the GUI interface that it has kind of reminds me of node red
So
And again I like all of this stuff so
Yes make it easier for everyone to play with the inter
So we like to Tinker so I'm in
You know something that's cheap and easy to use that we can just go
Have fun with for a couple hours on a weekend
Looks like that kind of thing to me so I'm excited
Yasso
Music let us know what you think
And
I will say
You know what we should talk about though
Now what we should talk about this because it happened
A week ago
But after we were
Recorded the show but Amazon did some news and this one actually doesn't relate to she who shall not be named
This is
Is Dash replenishment
Service
So everyone knows
Does the Dasher
You don't know
There are probably some
You guys out there I'm sure there are never seen a dash button
You know I've actually never seen a dash button believe it or not cuz I don't have anything yet
All Dash buttons
I'm your pretzel there internet-connected and it automatically orders one item so
A specific item that is pictured on the dash bus
But it also has something I'm far more significant
Which is the dash replenishment service which is basically just a
It's a backend
Cloud replenishment service to Amazon
E-commerce
System so
What it is is
If you're a manufacturer like brother printers
You
Basically have a sensor
And some code that connects
To Amazon's backend
And
When that sensor detects like that you're out of ink
In a Brother printer
It just
Calls Amazon it says yo I'm out of ink
In Amazon
Yeah I ate so it's it's kind of like a
The dash button from cells I think they were like $5 or whatever
Date of Easter Focus towards consumers you buy one like maybe the
The tide wasn't sticking on your washing machine when you're running though you just hit the button and more time is on its way
Getting disintegrated into actual products where it makes sense
Cenotes a totally different play
I like this better I think than the manual press the button for consumers just order one thing
It's a very specialized
Integrated Service say with the Brother printer that use bait you use as an example
So here's where I'm going to blow your mind
Hello my mind go for it
So this is for consumers this could be for businesses
But it really just takes
Sensor
And
Like 10 lines of code is what Amazon tells me last week they open this program up
Anyone
So if you are
A big-time developer like it
GE which has a smartwatch
Machine
Dance to this
Or you're like a hobbyist like myself
And let's say you have like
I don't know a Raspberry Pi
And a sensor and you want to build like
I would love to build a connected dog food thing
Instead of buying my own so you could actually this is open enough that you could grab the code yourself and put it on your pie with a sin
Answer to your dog bowl
Basically or my dog probably my dog feeder
Food storage
I got you I got
The giant Tupperware
So exactly
You could do this
I could do this
For big companies
She is doing this
So yes
So that I thought was really freaking sweet
What are the big companies are already involved
So Brita
They're doing it for their water
Samsung's one I think Samsung is one
There's a company called G mate
Which makes a smart blood glucose monitor which will reorder
The little
Prickly things in the
Testing strips
Spritz little
Glucose monitor Purell
Four hand sanitizer things
Cleverpet I don't know if you saw my CES video where
Play with the cleverpet device
I'm it's a pet food
August
The lock company
Which embedding is batteries but I do
For sure that make sense
Sealed air
I'm not sure what field are is going to
I don't know
So there's a lot of companies and hopefully we'll start seeing a lot more because it was a close program for now
I'm so so I know who I want to see integrated this thing and that is the folks make the
Keurig coffee machines
Always run out
And then I'm kind of
That would be interesting because
You have to do it on your storage
Pod correct it wouldn't be in the coffee maker have to be wherever the storage pods or maybe they make like a
A little container for those and monitor it and
You keep taking them out
Recognize
Hey that would be cool
So Kevin
You can actually
Temecula
Scale
Weekend project
See we get too excited about this dividing people
Because I freak people out about that Nina
We probably free
Just anybody
I thought was worth noting
So why do a couple
Quick newsie items
And then we'll end on a question
For everyone to think about
Alright Sony
Is buying Altair which is a Moto Maker for a 200
$12
Cuz it was 212 I would have paid sooner 13in
You're like I want to go to make sure I don't know why I want to have a Semiconductor Company
One for you and one for you
LG modems are basically cellular
Is there really useful for The Internet of Things presumably
What do you think Sony is going to do with this
Put modems in
What cameras
You know
I don't know I mean
So he's actually been struggling on the mobile side
These days they do pretty much
I want to say
Onda
Camera sensor market for mobile devices but it says I think that's actual
Pretty accurate is everybody uses
Most many many major manufacturers use them
They're not doing well in smartphones
Tablets
Xiamen
Is this the kind of modem that could integrate into say
System-on-a-chip from somebody else other than Qualcomm cuz right now these Qualcomm
Yeah they can
What about for VR
I mean would you use that you would want to use sedative for
Alright well we'll throw that up as a
We'll have to do something and let's let's do something and think about it somewhere I'm curious what they might do with us
Yeah I mean
I can
Connecting anything with lenses for computer vision would be really powerful
Okay
Johnson Controls
Band Tycho
We're like what
So this is an industrial internet
Also worth noting because
Johnson Controls competes with Honeywell
Competes with
A lot of Honeywell GE etcetera on the smart building side and it had kind of an old-school
Kind of smart building automation software package called medisys
It was a little bit more closed off
Meanwhile Tyco they actually own
Faucets I can never pronounce it but it's a line of smart home sensors
And they also had
Their own
Kind of it's called Tyco on
Which was a
Much more open
Fire & Security pack
CH4
Against
Building automation
Let 3rd party integrators
Integrate with them
And so I'm really excited about this
2 million dollar deal
And it's kind of a cool deal
In that
I'm hoping
We see Johnson Controls take a page from Tycho
An open up
It's also worth talking about only because
I'm really curious
This still makes me think about
The overlap between the operational side of building automation solake
All the sensors
In the facilities management aspects of it
And how that's going to bridge with the it side
Because
Both of these are very traditional
Operational companies oot
And I'm like
Or do they partner to get it
Because
A big rival of there
GE has been
Find databases
Bind database
Companies in
I'm kind of getting Cloud expertise
In building that up
Itself
Do they need to spend the money
To get the expertise the GE has or can you partner to get it
Where does that kind of
Need to take place
Thoughts
But that's not the question we want to leave you
No it's not
It's a good question
So
The question was it
The last show we talked about the potential for smaller Amazon echos
Yes Echo Junior
We don't know any
Baby
We don't know anything more about other than reports that it's coming
Should be about the size of a beer can can't tell if it's a 12
16 answer
But we were talking about how we wanted that
In the house in different rooms because of the voice activation
What do we have interesting
Comment
Flash question from Brian one of our listeners he says
Regarding the smaller Amazon Echo
The wearable seems like a better solution
The Siri function on the Apple watch is activated by a gesture which is slightly less creepy than always listening function
And still more convenient than hitting a button which
The
Portable Amazon Echo report illegal have to hit a button
If it's not.
Turning batteries
And he says princess
Also not confined to a room or a
Building and you know when I when I saw that I'm liking what Bryant that is a really good point not one that I have thought of
You could Amazon or does Amazon these are they thinking about
Kooding
Amazon voice Services until wearable that people would want to buy and where
And it's kind of a tough market for that right now if you're not a
Google or an apple or Microsoft because you got the whole software platform that
Typically goes along with that and
You know Amazon doesn't have that they forked Android
So that way they can have the
Fire stuff
There's no
Android Wear from Google that they can
In 4 coming out
That's kind of propriety everything that's not as open as Android itself
I don't know how they would do that but you know what if you could
Find a way to get
The echo voice services on your wrist
It is less creepy
Especially when you can just you know it's not always listening
And forget the apps you just do it through cloud services I'm thinking if it's an interesting point that Brian makes it where you think
So you could because
You can actually
Add Alexa voice services to
Other
Amy the Amazon Hazmat test
2K available so you could
Put it on
Device
It just
And it doesn't have to
So if Brian if you're really like excited about this idea you can make it
Meeting
Tens of dollars on Kickstarter I don't know
I should have worn Brian Stacy is very good at giving homework assignments
It's true
Hallmark
I would buy one
Yeah
Caveat there
So
I like this idea
If it's actually I wear at Pebble and people have told me it looks like a medical device on my way
Wrist though
Yeah yeah yeah so if you have
I mean that's the nice thing about an SDK
It's not as
Maybe nice is an API but
And you can add it to a lot of
So
It's not
Crazy talk
To Envision
Something like that
Knowing and it might give people more of a purpose to
To buy such a wearable because right now
Just my observation
Smart watches
Yes sales are growing but it's not taking off I don't think the way people attic
Expected and
The third-party apps are just
It's not there yet there isn't
A ton of reasons to go and get this type of accessory for your wrist
Holy cow
I just realized
What you could put
Alexa voice services on a drone
You could build a skill
And you could call it back
Do you actually would have to go to school you could just call the Drone back to
How awesome would this be
That would be cool
I'm good I'm in the
There's lots of potential here and then
You know this is why I keep saying Amazon I think it's one of the best
Position companies
Spore
I'll sail East consumer Internet of Things
Am I pretty
I have an idea Stacy
You could make one
Homework 2 Chainz
More I get more assignments
From Kevin
Yeah I will introduce Our Guest
Stay tuned for Scott Jensen who is
Ux designer on the Chromecast team at Google
But be warned
He is not going to talk
About Google on the show this week we promised him you wouldn't have to
He is actually going to talk about
Ux
For the smart home and some crazy fun cool ideas so
It's going to be an awesome show stay tuned
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And I have Whitney Scott
Jensen
Hi Scott how are you
I'm fine thank you
And Scott is a ux designer
For the Chromecast team at Google
And Scott is gracious enough to join us not because he's going to talk to us about Google
But because he
Writes a lot of really good stuff as a designer
On the Internet of Things
So getting started let's talk about kind of
What's wrong with the boring bits
Let me sell it to you guys
Let's talk about
What happened
When we start connecting our houses
We spent a lot of time talking about like
Hey
Really cool things we can do I talk about my lights all the time
You guys are told me to stop talking about my lights all the time so Scott here is going to talk about
Saving money
Let's do it Scott
So excited by the end of the things they instantly go to the hole
Automation side effects
Excited about is what the iot enables
Base level
So
Your house so that you only have power at the outlets and the ceiling for lights you can replace all the wiring to your switches
And you wouldn't even know is my auntie house
But it'll be probably 40% cheaper on
Listen to get so excited
And I think that's in a course you could do peyote like things
Turn on 17 lights
I was seeing you hate this concept of a digital Butler
You're like forget cheese I think
What is either the title or subtitle in one
Jesus must go
Viz idea is that
We are
So excited
About the idea of automation
And the factory
That we don't really appreciates
Weather makes sense
I just think that humans are
Sponge
Poetic Nessie
We can't be reduced down to 15 if then else clause
And there's so many things that people try to do that break down so I just think we need to have a little bit more
Humanitarian
Treat this with respect it deserves and there's lots of ways you can talk about
True I once spent probably a good for week
Trying to
Creative mode change an automatic mode change in my
For go to sleep
And it started with like a simple
When I turn off
In my house
About to sleep
Because
I would turn off those lights but my husband would be downstairs reading and then all the lights
So then I was like okay
When those lights go out plus there's no motion downstairs
15 minutes
And that didn't work
Because he'd be watching
So then I was like
Downstairs
And
It's after a certain time
Like a really late time
I didn't work for whatever reason
When I read your diatribe against
Digital Butler
Yes that's exactly because it never it never came to pass that I could
I could program a digital Butler
Or like an automation for this mode change
You're right humans are messy and it might work like 4 nights out of the way
But those other three it was
Absolutely aggravating for
Either him or me or
Maybe my daughter when she was sick and
You know trying to find us in the middle of the night
Lights were coming on ER
Good morning setting was coming on and she
In the morning and I feel sick and
DeSoto what's the saying good morning
Weathersby
In the coffee pot starts Brewing
Its 3
Forget or don't appreciate that with automation comes lack of concern
And it's usually even though it works 90% of the time you have to work 35% of the time
To be in your house and you have no control isn't terrible feeling
And so that's why I'm a big
Follower of Douglas engelbart who wrote years ago
An argument
That I think that we need to think about our houses as having different
Types of systems
Coeur d'Alene is fairly simple.
No one's going to get too upset before wedding comes on
What's ceiling
Or happy
The intention was to be a little bit more
Humanitarian
If no one's around
Then it should
Actually warned you work send a video to your phone or use voice commands Ark
Something so
Augmentation base system
Magic
I'm in control
Interesting
A lot about and you tweet a lot about is this idea
Identity and
Devices having identities
And basically
Because right now a lot of things
Connected devices are signed to
You was a person
And not like
Your family
Which would be probably preferable since that's tends to be who lives in houses
And you were telling me before the show that your house actually now has
Gmail account
Which
I would think the only thing I can come up with because if I'm going to hardwire
Smart lights
It's one thing to have an Alexa with you that's fine
So there's a rule on this show
Because so many of
So many of our listeners have an Amazon Echo
We cannot say her name
She is she who shall not be
Of course sorry about that
Amazon
Requires an account
With my email account so when I sell my house
What do
No sense
Printing a house
Email account
Gold Exchange the
Passwords on the Gmail account and
They will have access to everything and it'll work out of the box now
I'm not happy with the solution
I did Lutron
Light switches and they were actually design
The ground up
To convey with a house
So there is an account associated with Neutron
They're not associated with the switch themselves
Which
With the thermostat
I have
Actually had to learn how to reset the nest
Thermostat in my ecobee thermostat just so
EBay
And I was actually a debate we had actually couple years ago was like
If you spend $250 on one of these thermostats
Is that something that you
Take out and take with you or do you
In your house and then do you how do you
Say that to the owner that they now have to
Connect to thermostat they have
Think about your dishwasher your washing machine
It send
Yeah I was at CSN
And I was like oh like your Amazon account
And ordering their own
Stop
So imagine imagine the paperwork that goes with your new house now
Best part of the issue is it and how much it has to get reset because again I feel like this layering is
You think that we want to
Have some type of nuanced iot
Closed system concept
So that doesn't work
See certain devices now anything that requires
External control obviously sugar
Twerking in some kind of closed
Mechanism
And I don't think we talked about that enough
Let's think about this
Because
There's a couple different ways
You build a closed loop system
Around
The physical place
Like the house
Much like you have
Your power so your power is associated with
Your physical address
So you have to think about
Who's going
To manage that
Aarhus kind of the guarantor
Behind that right
Or I don't know how you would think
What you going to pay my relationship and you got to deliver relation
So the power comes in
Right in the end of everything work
The payment with delivery of control
Okay great
So then
So in this closed system
Possible
Maybe those are the same thing maybe they're not
Cuz I think we got to figure out
Right
Figure out what devices
Makes sense in that
Physical space
So light switches make sense
Do thermostats
Do dishwashers
MN
What other relationships are you going to have with them
Because like
And then how did those get managed
We can talk about
You can talk about my life
Wired and certain ways you could somehow create a closed loop
When these things are built
Together they each other in such a way that
There's are fine in their permanent than you bring in a new Samsung microwave and you wanted to communicate
Vanessa will call Nicole the Multi-Device Direct
Working America
And I want you to come to my house
I want you to unlock
The door by don't want you to accept
My file system
And again right now the answer is just giving you no account and you're done but it supposed to sing
Here's a residence of yours the owners of yours the kids
I need the controls that might survive the house being sold
Right
And So It Goes
Control and you sell the house
And I don't think it would talk about this act like how can we do what we funded for you and step it up a level
To actually provide
Access
Beyond belief
Pull a lot of now I see a lot of that happening at the network level so like I see a lot of companies
Adding data access layer
Would like a Wi-Fi router
In software accompanying the Wi-Fi router
Yeah
So that that is like a
Cited trend
What is happening
So
You know and being able to say
If you're a guest you have access
The following devices
You have access
Cast of The Following
Whatever permission
Which is very much what happens like
Corporate
Define gas
And then there for Augusta.
I said this and by default you are a guest
And that's quite a simplistic model that but it's so easy to break out of the gas
Open my front door
How do we handle a problem
Brain okay
I guess you could create different Airbnb guest verses
Hunting opportunities for identity broker
Stop being so for example Airbnb could easily become the Facebook of home automation in the sense that
If you had all devices can support Airbnb accounts and then you can just
Bill's got access in Beaumont to go but
Single monolithic identity
Struggling with
How do we have a Federated identity system so that you could
Poltergeist people
Well yeah because
There's identity for the people
Like there's my identity
Which changes obviously
Depending on where I am but there's also the device identity
And commission
And those are very different
And I know that I mean there's
Airbnb is working with various I want to say it's working with August but maybe
A different
Home company working with
August or a difference
Lock Company
Kevo perhaps I can't remember to create these kind of like
You know permissions
So like when you sign up
For Airbnb then you automatically get
Codes
Which is very happy
But yeah that is like
Pacific Market
Manufacturers of door locks
Say things like where you can give a key to your
House cleaner
And you know they can get in
Delegate
What's up
I'm questioning
I'm just questioning
What am I
What am I more famous
Articles talk about this idea of value greater than pain
Desiigner as long as
You know you'll do something
The problem is that's awesome painter sohi
Are nice things early valuable
Do it
Ramblin the space part of it is
I don't think you'll appreciate
Be quiet
Yeah cuz if you had like Universal standard
You could have like
A way to implement
Permissions with your life
Unlock code with your door
Which would be really interested
So
When you got your key from a Kevo or an August or whomever
Along with that
You could unlock a variety of experiences
You could customize as the
Omar you can customize that users access
As you were getting them
But that would require
The door lock company to build that experience
It would require some sort of standardization
Across all of their connect
Two devices
That would be awesome
It would be and I think of you are probably taking
One of the more difficult problems
And important part of my
Which is simplified wiring automated lighting
Things like that that would be really really valuable and not near me
So that's where I think
Appreciate
True
Let's pick a less
Problem I've already using
The wiring is
I'm assuming you're talking about things like Bluetooth lights
For getting rid of wiring
Yes
I'm going to to Bluetooth
Classic license
Baby always
You're going to
I am considering that right now
Jefferson Township
I'd like I'm Pro Lutron light switch
Although it's an old school standard
And I use them to replace light switches where
No light switch it says so I don't have to go into the walls and say
Hello
Let me do it expensive renovation project in my brand new home
So I'm already taking advantage of the boring bits
Yay
Okay
So thinking about
Other
Small problems
Sore
Things
I tried to take what have you done in your own home that you're like this is a perfect use case
Of low-hanging fruit
For the internet
Well actually what my wife doesn't hate is the thing that can and I will admit you think it's a little boring but
It's just simply being able to have light switches that behave like light switches
Like
Smart device
So that life with a light switch
Turn on
So I can kind of get rid of these for arthritis
Gang of four switches my kitchen
Turn on each of the individual Banks lights
Work 90
Percent of the time there's a
Two things I want to do
And so by being able replacing light switches
Get rid of that turned
And yet I can use the
So I am now in the process
Rewiring the
And stuff so that nobody even knows
This is a Smart House
It's important.
Having better lighting
And I love the fact that I can have
Sling plug into socket
And having a spotlight be controlled with
Australian painting with light
See guys this is why
I spend so much time talking about lighting on the show
Because it's it's one of the easiest things to mess with
It's really smart
So Scott you're not doing anything with Smart Lipo
Don't say anything like that yet
I am
Smart light bulbs
Spot because you're fighting the fact
And so to me I think I should be in sweat
My current
Siri
We can argue
Will argue about that
Okay. Thank you so much for coming on the show for making me think Deep Thoughts
Rather early in the morning
And
Conjuring identity and
Standards and
At the end of
My Jeepster
That's it for this week's show thanks for listening and we'll see you back here next week