Everyone welcome
The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Evereve
Excellent show to start off the new year we've got some
Hardware news on the consumer front
Iot
More stuff from
Going to be happy about
Big thighs and
A bunch of other news Plus
A canary
And a canary Flex camera he's going to tell us a little bit about that we're going to answer some questions from one of our listeners
We have
Chris Matthew of
Shoots ink
Talking about a new blockless blockchain
Coyote
As our guest this week
Ross going to talk to our sponsor Rob Munich
Flex products
And now
Let's go to a message
From another one of our spa
Spencer's
This week sponsor is CBT Nuggets
So how does the IOD change the way you do business for many organizations it means a proliferation
One of devices and tools
Which all require support
What is a mountain of requests for the it
Or Pilot devices that aren't being used to their full
Potential
But if everyone on your team knows how to use their tools
You're going to have fewer support request for it and get the most out of your material and vest
CBT Nuggets has been a top training choice for it Professionals for decades and now they're making the same
High quality online training for end-user topics like Windows 10 IOS
Salesforce and security awareness so your whole team can fully connect with the iot
Go to CDT nuggets. IO
To find out more about how end-user training can help your team
Get connected
To the iot
Okay
Let's kick it off with someone
Consumer-facing dues
Some of which there's two related stories one
In both actually happened last year
When is
Auto the $700 Smart Lock
We've talked about
They shut down
And then to was Amazon buying blink witch hat
Right before
Christmas
And I think these two stories are related
Is Nas played Wiseau Autos issue
Is that this company has started
Years before
Launch so it launched this
Last year in 2017
With this
Planned $700 lock
It was a very beautiful
Its claim to fame was it actually wasn't as bulky as all the other iot locks it all fit into the original
Is it the deadbolt hole
And was going to
The product launch TuneIn
Early this year
What happened was they said
We were in the middle of trying to raise money and then we got an A
Acquisition
Any acquisition offer
Was going to
The clothes in early December
Basically didn't allow Auto to continue raising money
And so when the acquisition fell through
The company was left with
Apparently the acquisition fell through on the final day of when the deal was supposed to actually happen
And that
Left the auto folks scrambling and
Yes they have
Shut down operations
I mean I can see where you're going to go with us being related
But I do want to talk about the lock itself
Because as I read the a medium post
By the CEO
About to die yeah
Sam's post explain you know how all this went down as you just
Mentioned
But some of it in there just made me
Scratch my head and he had mentioned that the
Turn beta testing the $699 price point you know challenge melted away
I don't think so
I'd be shocked if that was
Is traffic bad because
It seems to me like autobutts
They spend a lot of time working with
Somebody who actually was in the Swiss watch
Making industry and I mean very
Small precise
Components for this thing
And that's great I'm sure it's a work of art just like any say mechanical watch might be but
A mechanical watch high-end is not the same as a lock you know what you wear the watch it's with you all day the lock
How to use a couple times a day
It seemed like these folks going to be for lack of a better word
The apple of
Smart locks I think they actually wanted to be
It's an even higher
Well
I mean it's the Philip II
Rolex
I'm smart locks and I see this because most locks have Precision Engineering even August has they
Went through it there
And this lovely story about Japanese
Hi precision
Something something
Gears blah
Because
I kind of threw away
His
Swiss Swatch
I appreciate it but I'm like
Alex have very intricate little Parts because they're free
Picking locks
And if you're going to run a motor through it you're going to need
Bits and pieces
The two things I thought of
This is one
I'm very curious who the acquirer was because this actually happened not too long ago to Zana
Which also
Had an acquisition fault
Do and then Heather abruptly shut operations
And then led to
Hiring everybody had now the lawsuit again
It's raining
But
This seems to be a common
Maybe another time
This seems to be a thread
Did this happen
There's a lot of kind of cannibalization have
I would also say that August which was acquired also
Late last year
Was not acquired
In like
A very fantastic deal this was a deal that
The shareholders barely
So
I'm going to say
Locks not a great place to
Now
Trying to do this
Is Amazon buying blink
Blank is a camera company it's a low power wireless camera come
It's actually pretty cool it was started by a semiconductor
Company that had this great ship that was selling for like five bucks
Zapata Lake
Companies was it in Media
Amelia
They were like
Hey what's a better way for us to show off are really awesome what they had was low power
Video processing
Analogy
Tiger Mart
So they built this camera system
And it
What's a good camera
And
Very cheap 99 bucks for
A wireless HD
Cameron ice
And
They've been on the market for
I saw I first heard they were on the market
The middle of last year
So again this was
Last year was definitely a time of m&a and trying to
It's going to start cleaning up some of the
Success in the smart home space
So I don't coming along
That time
I'm with a really high price
Product was just
Late for that
And
I think in 2018 what we're about to see is the beginning of incredible commodification and
Addition and that's what I said with Amazon buying blink I think this is
Not Just Like Glue Amazon has security goals sure everybody does
But it's also a sense and
A validation that
Holy cow
Price and getting a price down India
Just going to be sued
I think you're spot on I mean there's going to be a
Tan of price pressure now on newer products and even some of the older products are coming down in price
Quite a bit and we'll talk about my canary in a bit but I mean I got it for a song
No pun intended
No no I did not mean that I did not mean that
Does that make them sick
Marion
Could be yeah yeah they could be but I completely agree with you
I think
And that's good for consumers for the business side that's a whole different aspect
The profit margins in sustainability but
If you're a consumer on the lookout
You can expect I think to pay a lot less in 2018 than you did
In one or two years ago
Alright so
Best debate consumer device story
Let's talk about something that
Amazon has sold a lot of
We still don't know how many
Exact number of
Man-made devices that have been sold but Amazon did say in a press release right after Christmas
Tens of millions of
Echo devices with
You know who
We're sold worldwide
The echo Dot and Fire TV stick with the voice remote work not just
Top selling devices on Amazon in the holidays but they were the best line products from any manufacturer in any category
Maria cross Alabama's on so that's a pretty good indication of how many a lot
In another interesting aspect
Because it brings more people using the devices
They say that Tamela Mann on Fire TV
The usage in the US is up 889% over the same time. Last year it so
We talked about this the Fire TV in the voice before it's nice to see the cards in the TV
I don't get into it that much but apparently a lot of people do so and that's all good for
For Amazon
Yes it is
And they seem to be
Add a story
This week
About Amazon they talked to some people at Big brands
Clorox and it sounds like
Amazon is talking to them
About bringing advertising
Sing to the A
Now
This is
This is basically it's talking to them about letting them promote their products on there
Early discussion centered on
Whether companies would pay for higher placement if a user searches for a product
Such a shame
Poo
Kind of like how Google
I would say
That's a dumb way to monitor
Another possibility could be with promotional bits on skills and such
So
That might make
More sense to me than just
Inner product placement and search ads and such as
Approach I'd rather see it on the skills cuz I have a choice to install the skill or not
Yes and I think skills could become like the Campbell's cookbook
Marketing bright so instead of saying
Let me put your search higher why don't you give me some functionality that relates to your product and so if you guys don't know what
The Campbell's cookbook is Campbell's basically put out books that taught you how to make things using their
Air Products
Is it terribly innovative
No better
Clorox stain remover
How do I get it out
I would do that
You can suggest how to do it and then optionally
Say do you need any Clorox
Sylveon
Place the order
I think the opportunity here
Where is Les
Direct like a search engine based at
Which is like
Shirley based on the intent and War around brand building and marketing like a magazine
Voice is not
I don't think voice is going to be
Good
This intent-based Mar
Because it's
It's a medium that Demands a
A quick information Exchange
So
Build trust with Brands you don't want to Brand taking of your valuable time telling you about
Disinfecting wipes while you ask
How long
7 elephants 2
Counter
So that's
My two cents
I'm sure that people will get it wrong before they get it right
I do think that Google's approach here might be a little smarter because they're looking at grabbing this data and trying to make
Products from it
And it'll be interesting to see
Anna Powell
Amazon figures this out
Yeah I think it's going to be a let's try a couple of different things and see what sticks and what people complain about versus what people are okay with
Plus how many more products to resell as a result of these
I would be super irritated
It already Amazon is pushing search results when I asked for like
Order more this
In
I know what I'm looking for so if one of the things I want is in a bundle
3 I'm not
I can see that
Yeah this is going to be interesting to see how this progresses and
Who does what in the space between Amazon Google I need a Microsoft
Okay let's
Talk about
Xiaomi
We shall we shall know
There's a report out from Navigant research that was talking about who is the
It's like a
Graph of who are the leading iot platform providers are
Gartner quadrant magic quadrant
McGrath and I noticed in the leader section IC
IBM
Okay that makes sense Microsoft okay that makes sense
AWS also makes sense
But then I saw no mention of alphabet
Google anime that doesn't make sense
Or does it
Maybe it does because where is and what is Google's iot platform
Oh my goodness
When Kevin brought this up
Ahead of the show
I would like
Will they have their serverless Computing option they have
Google Cloud functions
In beta
Witness
And
Then I was like
Cloud iot Core
Right
Do they have a job
That's that's where
Edge
Because you know if you got a w s has green grass
Microsoft actually has
Azure iot
Google doesn't really have an
I hate to say the word end-to-end option but they really do
Twerking
Yeah it's not mentioned
Very well on the Google Cloud
Site exora pee smell is not bundled
In my opinion
Can I talk to developers have used Android things
And they think it's actually really interesting
But I don't know anyone who's
Building Products
Exact
Yeah so this
Really does make
The question
Where
Like where's Waldo for what are you doing
Just to give some insight on because I did work
Google Pryor and I think I can say this without breaking any nda's
Google
Rightly things
Highly of itself and I seen that
Because
It's got some leading
Products and services with your billions of users
But
That is often the rationale behind we put a product out and people use it because
Google
And that's not a great strategy especially in this space which is heating up very fast
Hey Google does have a lot of the right pieces here that I would seek or
The guy Cloud Annex
Language in Cloud machine learning engine
And mention Cloud functions
People are just going to use it because well it's Google where they got all the best stuff
There's got to be a cohesive
Bundled
Story
End-to-end and I don't see it between all of those Android things and so on
And what's crazy is they have
Nest
Interrupt
Right so they have
Millions
Switch is very very
Millions of connected devices
They're so they're sick
Does Google home and Google assistant on most Android devices over Android 5.0 I think
So Kathy understand Edge devices they understand Integrations
So
Hey
Google
What's up
Talk to us
We would love to explain
What you're doing
We would love to know
And I bet we're not alone
Moving on from our plea for infer
What does talk about
Quick news
Arrow
Which is a massive Electronics distributor
Is buying e info chips this is part of their iot strategy
Which this one gets them from a distributor into more of a systems integrator there are thousands of iot based engineer
Beers from
This Indian
And
This makes a ton of sense we're seeing this both on Arrow as a distributor and also Avnet
Which is kind of a distributor they're all moving into systems integration for the iot
So we're seeing a bunch of
Consolidation
Up skills in
And the channel it's
Not exciting
I know but
Big and important
Nexa Roku
Wants to be your next
Voice assistant
Yeah I got a little surprised by this in one sense not surprised that they want to bring voice Computing to Roku
Power devices which are TVs they will be smart speakers as well
Is a part of this new licensing deal that
Roku Justin Bell this week but they're building the
Software themselves are not tying themselves to say Amazon voice Services Google or somebody else like that
They're going it alone and that may be okay because the initial push here is for controlling Home Entertainment
Such as your wireless speakers your TV sound bars and so on
But it kind of leads me to think longer-term like if you're going to do that why not go all the way in
Control Smart Home devices with voice and if they're going to do that on their own I don't know that they have
I don't say don't know they have the chops to do cuz they make a great product
But did I
Apple chopstick
Out voice
The others in this market I'm not too sure about that but
Regardless will get the chance to see this next week at TCL which is one of their biggest OEM Partners will be debuting a Roku
Connect power device at CES so we'll take a look
Nowhere Roku
Here is where
Okay
There's a huge opportunity in voice
To say things
Hey Shelby the yada yada
And
Gracenote
I don't I don't disagree with you and I don't know cuz I haven't used it but I thought that Xfinity's
Software remote may do something similar it may not be as robust as that
And I also be curious to see if
YouTube TV which is
Obviously built from Google and Google search I mean Google has I think the best search results
I wouldn't be surprised if you could even do that there but I have not tested it
Yes so that's
Intel CPU flaw
So quit State of the Union
Because there's not
Whole ton of details this is something that is likely
What will affect clouds
Rebuilder colonel
Is that
Yeah it's there's no way to fix this from a hardware perspective it is going to be software patches across
PCS
Devices servers Etc yes
And we were wondering if it was going to affect iot devices it could affect gateway's Inn
Industrial gateways basically that are running Intel based chips
But for most smart home devices are running arm
Chips and usually not even rm60
Afford it now
We did find out
According to the register that they're also
Adding updates to the arm 64-bit
That
But we're not sure
Newer iot devices like brand-spanking-new may use 64-bit arm chips don't know I mean we have to research
What is a little concerning in at the very high level that's law which goes back I believe about
10 years worth of chips now
As I'm going to do with allowing users
Access to Kernel protected memory and that's a no no
I'm insecure
Cortana still can't talk to me
Even though
They were clock watcher
But the thing is I still don't know how it's supposed to work that hasn't been explained yet so I guess we're just going to undertale here it is
Is an here's how it works
Demonstration
I think so
We'll see that
You recently purchased a car
Canary which is the all-in-one security device that I actually recently recommended as a
Do you agree with me
I would agree with you I would I not just cuz I do the show with you I bought a canary and I know you tested a canary
I added a canary Flex as well I don't know if you tested that
I did but it was when I tested it was brand-spanking-new and it had a real issues
Mywifi net
Work is it was running dual band
Because that Euros showed
Unified band
And Google Wi-Fi with your values also do a single band of 2.4 + 5
Gigahertz together but I
Didn't have any problems setting either of these
Yeah so that's that was very good cuz I do have a problem with my ring doorbell book schreiber's off
Similar issue with the Bands
Regardless yes I think Canary sells the home unit
For 349 and the flex is additional
I don't know 1:50 or some like that
So is it done once it's either
When he first came out
Yes a long time ago
This is the price pressure I was living
Regardless I got the canary and the canary Flex for 149 together
Wow
Yes Costco was very good to me at Christmas time this year so
Yeah so that Canary unit is a cylinder with a HD video camera
Speaker microphone
Has a little light underneath that let you know when it's 4
Recording or video or you
Somebody's looking through their app to see video which is
It's nice to see it also has some sensors in it to measure your air quality temperature humidity and so on so forth with your handy
I don't really need that but it's
Candy again
Italian
I think someone just took a shower
Humidity level rises
It's funny you say that cuz I looked at the graph of the air quality humidity apparently
We breathe out a lot of CO2 because every morning we going upstairs air quality tanks
I don't get it
To know you should get some plan
Yes we do need plants Virginia plants that's the gist of the canary unit and the canary Flex are they small
Little
5 in
Big Tylenol pill
With a camera and a microphone
It comes to the magnetic base so you can angle the video camera anywhere you want
It's an indoor outdoor camera I'm using it indoors only
And again no problems connecting it so answer for
What I like about the canary itself
The software I find is
Excellent
I love it
I like how you invite people to be part of the family and the reason you do that
Is because this
Auto arms and disarms based on geolocation if you want it
This is one of the Hang-Ups I had with the wink security system that I tested
There's no easy way to arm knit without
Going to the app
May I hear it just works automatically and even in the timeline in the app it says
Kevin just left home City just came home as soon as I work all of us are gone the system is armed if anybody is home
It will not be armed unless you want it to be armed like at night time and so on
I absolutely love that it's a little bit
Zealous when it comes to the notifications and I mean
It's sending me notifications for like when a car passes by in the lights are seen and so on and so forth
Even when normally dog runs around which I would expect there's some masking features that I haven't used yet but I also bump down the sense of
Nativity what you can do on a per device level
And that has helped out quite a bit so there's a siren I have not even tried that yet cuz I want to freak the dog out but overall
Yeah I saw the decibel level that's why I didn't try it
But overall I really like it ticks all the boxes for me in terms of the right notifications
Automatic arming and disarming is fantastic
Wasn't very expensive
It was easy to set up
And the software itself
Really found to be
Very well-made my PIN
It may have been different when you used it I don't know
I did like it there were a couple things but again
It was very early
So does it work with Madam or Google home
It does not work with home cats
And it does work with my wink
And I thought maybe therefore would work with the echo button
Did a search for
AT&T app and it does not find it
I'm not sure what I'd use it for maybe arming at night or putting in night mode by voice or something
You know we're doing the camera on a show or something which I don't have so
I'm not too
Upset about that
Incompatibility at this point
One thing I would like to do and this is
Probably insane you tell me
When somebody comes home or somebody leaves I'd actually love for the echo to announce
Who laughed
Who came cuz I said you could do that because you can actually do it
And if tablet that's what I was hoping
So Wink 2 asked to
Wink and Sonos
Cassano's Network Sunwing
You should be able
Can't create a robot
There's my homework
Kevin has homework
It's a good show
To a voicemail from
The IRT podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic lock
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & Security system so you can get the most out of your lock
Whether you're an Apple homekit user orlov Amazon Echo
To see what's possible visit schlage.com to learn more
I was just wondering
We were looking at getting my grandparents either
An echo dot or Google home Mini
For Christmas
They do not have a tablet or a smartphone
But they do have a Windows 10 laptop
What should I be aware of and do you guys have a recommendation
Either way appreciate the show thanks a lot by
Oh Adam
We have good news for you
Definitive
Your recommendation
What's an Amazon Echo
Explain why
There's a very good reason to go with an echo in this particular circumstance and that is you can actually
Configure and use an echo
To a web-based
App
On Amazon site
If you point your browser at Alexa. Amazon.com you'll have basically a Weatherford version of the
App that's used on smartphones to manage the echo devices
In fact I kind of think that the app is really built on web Technologies and they put a wrap around it but that's a guess.
Regardless you can do everything you need to do
Setting up the account and the devices right from there
Configure everything
You can type reminders you can do all sorts of stuff which is fantastic
Sex with no smartphone needed
You have to have a smartphone
To use the Google home or the Google mini that's the downside there's no
Computer-based way to
Work with us so
This site is a fine it's a gold mine I say
I think what do you think stays
I actually I was so excited because now knowing that
Type in reminders to go to my Echo Show which is downstairs in my kitchen knowing that I can do that
From far away
Or just to like if I'm not in town and I can just send
Reminder basically to Mike
Kitchen two people
I think that's awesome
Cuz I don't forget
Karate bag
I'm really excited about it
Why does her bag take karate
On that note
Sounds like a good time to go
To a word from our sponsor and then
T up our guest this week
Who is Chris Matthews
Of a new company
Quick compute Inc
Computes
Is basically
Gosh if you like combined
Iblocklist watching
For iot
With seti
I think that's where you're going to
That's the closest I can get
Aliens
Explain all of that and more in a moment
Everyone we are taking a break from this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Lux
Products and we have robbed muninn CEO of Lex products
Rob can you
Quickly refresher audience with
30-second overview of the
I'll do it in 20
We are a
A proud philadelphia-based
Innovator of HVAC
Trolls and our newest product to the market is the Lux Kono smart thermostat
449 bucks
She got a thermostat with
It's a great look at has
The coarse knob covers connects all the major Voice assistance
And has smart features like GFS
Alright so now
We are well aware that
Dakota smart is your newest thermostat
One of the things that makes it different is that it's easy to use
So what type of approach did you take when designing this product that's different from other thermostat
But what we did was we tried to come up with something
Thing that would be
Obvious
Unintuitive
We know that from our research
The other smartphone
That they may look easy
You know you can turn the device but sometimes
The user interface
Can become confusing that's what I research shows
And some touchscreen models are inherently
Not intuitive
Very menu-driven and Liars
Two layers so when we looked at the Kona we wanted
Did you something that
Lyft office
And it wasn't
So with the
Control knob
If you are hot you
Turn it down to the left
And if you are cold you turn it up
To the right
We literally have 100% of
Consumers that we've talked to
Have said
I get it
I know how to operate that thermos
So turning the knob is awesome
But most smart thermostats have other features so let's talk about
How to get to those
We wanted
You keep it really simple on the wall
So you can make it warmer and cooler and sofa
Forethought means taking a lot of the other
Features and put them into the app
Where it's a much more natural place
To do things so we have our scheduling on the apus
Which is so easy to use we have a variety of energy saving profile
House to help set up the schedule quickly
And more importantly easily
In addition to controlling the
The app also has
The future we call Smart
That will help him
Realize that
Direct impact that their action
Tap on their wallet
So if they are changing temperature and they making more energy saving
Choice
Will push out a notification
And say good job you're going to save
This much
Percent of your bill would you like to make that app
Permanent setting
For your schedule
Have a choice Obby
Crystal yes or no
Will also offer tippit have to do with energy saving
Friends
Sensing the change of season
It's always a good reminder to know she
Should you look at the caulking on your window and the weather stripping that you have going into the cold
And if you had to pick out one feature in the corner that's your favor
What would it be
I think what I would say is it's got to be tonight
It's just
Put it on the wall and
Even if you have Grandma
Come over who
Might not like connected products struggles with the smartphone
When she's cool
She'll know how to change the thermostat to make it warmer in the guarantee
Excellent and Rob where can we go to find out more
Well you can
Could stop by your local Home Depot stores
You could go online to Luxe products.com and you can shop all over the intern
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Chris Matthews
Hi Chris how are you doing
Hey Stacey great and you I am super well so you guys may remember
Hardcore listeners
Should remember that Chris came on
Couple years ago to talk about different protocols for Io
Now he's back with his own startup called computer
Ink and we are going to get into
Are you ready for it y'all
Basically
Blacklist blockchain for the internet
That's exactly a decentralized distributed
Supercomputing
Music
So before everyone freaks out his like
Quick
I need to get my brain in gear
We're going to talk first about your vision
Because I think it's important to start with
Why decentralisation
It's going to be so
Essential
Indeed I mean
Look at the numbers we keep hearing about 75 billion connected devices like by 2023
The cloud wasn't made to handle all of that
Machine data uploads and processing and
Go back down to things like driverless vehicles and all the
All the cool
Fantastic iot devices coming our way soon
Sure in
There's actually president
It is so in the data center
Way back in the day there was like
Like back and forth up and down
Traffic to the data center
But then as things like Facebook and Amazon
Things had to start pulling data for
From server to server
In the dataset
To like deliver the right
About
Became that was called East West traffic
And
The companies that were building big
Cloud computing and had big data centers
They actually had to invent a whole new ways of networking in
Software
To handle with a call East-West track
Taking the Datacenter
And what we're seeing now
Is a need to build that same sort of infrastructure
At the edge to handle all these devices sharing data
Between themselves in among themselves without going back to the cloud
That's because of latency it's
Cost
It is
Security even so
There is a
A big
You saw this need Chris
And then what did you say to
I should do something about the
How did we get here
What evil yes like you you look at all of these devices around us I mean they're idle like just like your laptop typic
Glee 80% of the time you're the fast room fast
Processors in them even GPU some of them
And they're idle 80% of time they chirp you know maybe every minute with their temperature status or what-have-you but
What is
All of these devices could just
Tear with each other even despair devices
Different manufacturers different machines
What if they could just
Pier with one another
And either requests work
Or perform work
For each other kind of in the secure mesh Network
It kind of got me thinking that we've got
A dramatic increase of more devices coming to the market
And at the same time a dramatic increase sperm or more computing power
For machine learning for AI
The cool automation
Things we want to do with these devices
Why not intersect the 2in
Make them Act
Stink like they're one
Interconnected peer-to-peer
Secure super
Okay
We're going to question such as
Battery life
Button
Beforehand
Your solution
Into this
Is decentralized
And
To take I feel like
Before we get into
What you guys are actually build
We should probably go into the history
Watching
Because
For people who are not familiar with it it's important to understand
And how that works with
Before we get into The Blacklist
Dip that's a great point of mean everyone seemed excited about
Bitcoin right like you can't turn on the radio or look at an article without someone mentioning something about the spray
Crazy price in Bitcoin wallet
That was
Built on blockchain technology going back
10 years now
So while it's a very cool idea you know it's allowing us to
Create decentralized distributed applications are currencies cryptocurrencies
That technology
It's kind of heavy and slow
All of this Computing that has to happen
Mike proof-of-work
Every node on the blockchain has to have the
Entire
Blockchain itself like
Copy of it in storage and
They're constantly updating an entire database if you
She will
Across each other all the time and doing this proof of work
Computations
To keep this blockchain Ledger in sink so
You can look at it as
Bitcoin or another crypto
Two currencies run on the blockchain in a blockchain is really no more than
Egg
Decentralized
Database like a database where every
Pier
On a network has a copy of it
Now proof of work
Which is essential for
Establishing authenticity
Correct
Want to make sure 4
And that's kind of the point of
What chain is it the distributor
Trust
Things
Which is really exciting
Coyote
And I always
It was like and it's scales
So what you're telling me here is that it doesn't scale
Or at least it doesn't scale
Very fast speeds and it takes a lot of power
Entire database
Yeah you know I think the Bitcoin blockchain last I looked at
The three-point numbers with something around 3
Three transactions a second theory emits biggest kind of blockchain
Competitor platform is
Somewhere around
A dozen transactions per second so
You can see that y'all
For the world moving all of these it devices to that type of
Technology
What's really cool is decentralized it stressful than a trustless environment
It is having some difficulty scaling to meet the demand of all of the nodes coming online
For reference
It's just so you
Case you guys want to know
Lisa says it handles more than 24
That's a big disparity
So when we're talking about
Visa is the largest
Payment processor in the world
Kind of what we're hoping for right
Let's talk about the evolution
Because
There's been a couple there's one that's huge in the internet.
Things called the iota
And these are so-called
Blocklist watching
Explain what
Yeah and computer is doing something very similar to what I owed is doing and I do truly believe this is kind of neck
Next gen
Blockchain like
Technology so
The idea is to throw a few acronyms at you and will maybe try to break them down but
There's this technology called a dag
A d a g and it's a directed acylic graph
It's not new developers that have been writing code using git and GitHub have been using gags whether they know it
For a decade now
The idea is that it's a bunch of like branches off of a tree where every
Commit or every update has a hash
A crypto hash
Is colic a 36 character Looking hash
That it relates back
To what its parents were
So you can kind of take one
Update in the system
And trace it all the way back through all the branches
Is the trees the parents to create
Basically a ledger
Of all of the transactions of happen
Intimidate
Without having
To do things like proof of work
Where you're actually having to track blocks and crate
Ashes of blocks to connect in the Dag
Automatically
Associate transactions with one another that allow you to trace it all the way back
Without proof of work
The other ideas at
It's very fast
Like
I'm kind of seeing the some of the earlier designs of computers being
Faster
5 more nodes you add
To the system that's counterintuitive how blockchain Works in one more other really important thing I think as it applies iot
Is that with the Dag
You don't have to maintain that entire database of transactions
On the iot device
They all just become
Computers that can read and write to kind of a
Mesh network of a dag so
Devices like
I don't know like maybe a hue lighting or
The Nest thermostats where they don't have enough storage to maintain like a
Blockchain
They could then participate
On networks like
What Iota is building and what computers building
And so you got
Very fast transaction
Very low storage if any
Basically an infrastructure less blockchain like technology
Let's break some things down
So what I'm thinking of
Is 36 character hash
I'm thinking
Would a good analogy be something like in Latin America for example
But you have people
You take your mother's maiden name
You take your father's name and you
Become to know
Crispy out Ramirez
And then your kid be
You always bring your mother's
So it's that
Now
How many
Characters like
How does this hash happen
And how does it
I mean there's only so many numbers and letters in
How is it unique
Can how do you follow that
Yes sir
You can also go back
From a security perspective decades
Thinking of how the Shah system works like sha-256 or Rochelle one what have you
Have you eaten
Talk to me
So there's this concept in cryptography where you can take
Any content it could be
A text new string or it could be like an address or could be like a
Encyclopedia
She will
And you can run
A crypto
Algorithm against it then there's a few there's like md5 and charges some examples of what I'm talking about
And what they do is they give you back at unique
Hash
A string of like alphanumeric
Text with some dashes in it
That always
Equate to what you just
Okay set a reverse so if
If you have
The algorithm that was used to create this
In Rio de Oro
Then you can read it
Then you can run your hash algorithm
And get all the info
Formation you need
Well kind of so it's not decrypt Apple so it's a one-way it's like a one-way hash but what's
Interesting though is that if you add one
Space near to that document and you rehash it the hashes are
So it is a way of always saying okay if I'm looking for
This file that says hello world
It will always have that same hash no matter if I right
The file or you right
Pedophile
It's a way of
I guess uniquely identifying
A resource on this kind of peer-to-peer
Infrastructure
By saying
We're all going to Hash it the same
Same way
And even a. Or space is going to give us a different hash it's a
Profile
Okay
So this is the day
We've got a sense of what the dag is
What else do we need
So
Like with
Computes anyway the Dag
Is cool everything that's a way of kind of creating like you explain kind of names are parents
In history
But there needs to be a way kind of like the blockchain works where
You need to have something that knows how to
Handle
Choose if you will like
With computes you can say
Like say the nest Princeton's could say
This is just totally hypothetical but the nest could say
Hey I need to do some machine learning on whether or not
This person that owns me is home or not can anyone help me
Maybe cuz maybe I don't have enough processing power do it all by myself and I don't want to send it all to the Google Cloud
Maybe I could have my Hue Lights and
My owners Mac and maybe some raspberry Pi's are sitting around
Like all
Join in when needed
And could do some computations to help me figure out
If someone's home or not based on these machine-learning algorithms
That type of
Process requires some type of orchestrator
Decentralized q-type technology that knows how to say here are all the
Yeah hundreds or thousands of computations that need work
Who's available know who has extra resources
Who can run JavaScript who can run python
Yo what have you
And distribute that work in such a way where there's really
No servers persay in this environment
It's just all of these piers
Know how to communicate with one another and
Help each other out
Tachevah
Yo computations and whatnot locally
Amongst themselves in a secure fashion without going to the
The cloud sofa
That's kind of another layer to this tag ideas that you need
Some other way of writing decentralized apps
That know how to run in this type of environment so you need a brain for
Decentralized app so everything has to have
A brain
Betabrand
Pretty pretty resource-intensive or memory-intensive
I would think so
How do you handle that
But yeah that's kind of the cool thing I remember and I can't remember if it was Cisco or who used to sneak this claim like
Ocwen switches were getting really popular they would say that the network is the computer
Hello is fascinated by that idea but I think
What we're building now truly is that the network itself
Is the brain
Like all of the nodes there's no servers they just know how to organically self-organized selfie
Real self
Collaborate with one another
To do various machine learning or AI related
Jobs
Okay
But what do
The individual devices need
In order to be able to
Participate in this
Dip perfect question so with computes they would need a very small little five megabyte size
Is very small
What we call a nano core or computes manticore
That gives them
The
Operations to automatically match with one another and
Join that Dag
And participate in that queuing
Brain
Technology
I feel like we're saying brains on
Okay
You know I have a fascination
For Skynet I'm always trying to build Skynet weather
Do octopus do or what have you been
You could almost kind of
Look at like
Relationship that it was
Global
Decentralized
Neural-net supercab
Right
I know you love Skynet but
What was the we're going to build a nice version of Skynet
So I can put this on the device is something that
You don't manufacturers will need to do is this stuff that like I has a
The crazy individual in my house want to do like how does that work
I like great example I think it's all of the above so we were talking with computer vision company the other day
And they were telling me that they're using cameras basically a sensors new iot devices as sensors but not for video stream
And they were saying that to do the machine learning they needed to Dubai on each camera that they needed like an octave
Core processor that was doing all of this machine learning
In real time on the camera
NetSpend
Yeah right right right
So what they were asking is you if there's a hundred cameras around a facility in office
Complex or camp
Could they distribute
The work two cameras that have no change in video
So that you could argana Klee kind of crate this message
Share the processing workload across the entire network
So that maybe you could get away with like a Raspberry Pi level
Processor needs
Cameron
So in that instance they would be interested in Gnomeo emminger
Deploying computes just basically inside of their cameras
But to your other point
I think we're near the whole Bitcoin movement
It's kind of got a lot of people thinking about
Uber
Supercomputing idea like
What if
You have
Idle City
Use on your Mac
And you want to earn some extra money by letting
Computer run on those the only secure fashion
That allows other
Companies to use your idle CPUs and gpus for computations but pay you for it so kind of like
Uber when you say
I want to drive for an hour
Well you can say I want to
Share my CPUs for an hour maybe you'll make
Now $5 an hour or whatever
Ambition the size of your processing power
Yeah you could earn you accordingly
How to say that micropayments
They're not quite sure
And I have lots
Talk to so many companies over the years who have tried to do that
Various iterations
And
Almost all of them
Have pivoted
So
I'm a little worried about that ass
But I like it
Yeah I think it's a good point I think we're focusing burst is really B2B so we're looking at companies you know that have
Was already thousands of servers thousands of workstations
Yo they see the demand for more more machine-learning computations coming at them and
Rather than
Buying more servers or more cloud services
Yo what if they could just
We could harness all of that
Wasted
Compute
In their existing hardware and give them basically access to the very own supercomputer
Without nail buying any additional Hardware so that's the first goal but I think to your second Point are your point about the
Micropayments
I think with the
Blockchain it's too expensive to do those proof of work and computations wear something like that
Which really efficient really fast
That might be the right technology to finally make micropayments work
When we get around to doing BTC type activity
Okay let's see
I feel like we've
We covered a lot of things
Is there something else you wanted
Well
I agree with you I think this is fascinating to me I've been thinking about this for a couple of years now
And this idea that
Any device regardless of operating system
Even using clouds themselves uidaho
Computing clouds
All connected together
Could be something very interesting especially as you know a lot of vendor iot platform companies are trying to figure out how to
Shift
From Cloud to the edge
A lot of them are taking approaches where your they're deploying new appliances on the edge I think this concept
Is a lot of Merit wear
Each
Device or each
Computing resource basically
Is an auteur is a core on this mesh Network
We
May reach a point where you don't need an appliance
Anymore just basically everything computes
And ultimately it's infinite
Computing I think
In this new world of
CEO of
Hockey stick number of devices coming to Market in
They're getting more more powerful I think this is just fascinating
You can be in and it's not easy I mean there's a lot of
Google problems we're having to solve
Computer science related problems
But I think that's what makes it
Even more fun and even more fascinating
Okay so we're not going to see you guys doing an initial coin off
I'm crazy like that
Stay tuned maybe I don't know
We'll see
Chris thanks so much for coming on the show
Thank you Stacey loved it
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week