Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Co-host
Kevin tofel
Did you show number 184 of the iot podcast and we have an awesome show for you today
We're going to be talking about do Wi-Fi branding what does it mean
We're talking about a new satellite Network for iot and yes Amazon it is in
Plus California Pasta reasonable security law for iot devices that we talked about a while back but now it's real we'll talk about
We're going to add IBM Watson to your smart home if you want
Annapolis rigging keyless door entry 2
Canvases
Plus
Kevin has some crazy ideas for door window sensors
Microsoft is bringing Cortana to noise cancelling headphones
Johnson Controls has bought a company and Splunk
Introduced a new industrial iot product
Speaking of industrial iot we're going to talk a little bit about Genies current troubles
This week we're going to hear from our sponsor
Cognizant
And our guest
What is Matthew prince who is CEO of
Cloudflare
He's going to talk about how to re-architect the internet
Coyote and
Basically Computing at the edge
You're going to want to hear it
It's super awesome
All right
Now
Let's hear message from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is
Chocolate
Your customers are not distributed are tracking system with 64% of iot users encounter
Performance issues you need chocolate The Edge first problem finding software that uses Advanced function
Analysis and deep learning techniques to identify errors and performance bottlenecks across your entire deployment
All that brings you the traces system metrics and environmental conditions you need to fix issues before your customers
Get started for free at Auckland. IO
That's a UK let.
IO
Hey Kevin
Start off this week with
Branding
The Wi-Fi Alliance
Is at it again
They have decided
But the energy. 11.
Acaax
Angie B I don't know Q
It's all way too confusing
Yente
Their solution
Is
Adverse
So the new ax standard is going to be called Wi-Fi 6
I guess AC within B5
I guess it would be and that would be
Cats they're doing a rebranding all those with numbers you will not hear about Wi-Fi one two and three cuz
I'm gone
We're beyond that although a lot of smart home devices doorbell
B r g
They do so that's going to be interesting
And that gets us
To public service announcement about Wi-Fi
You probably do not need
Update your system
To LAX
Not yet anyway
Don't don't do it
Don't do it I'm an early adopter of these things and I am not doing it
Yes
Because
It has to be really awesome and to get the amazing GBS
The 2.3 gigabits-per-second capacity
1.2 using all 8
Streams and apple be using 160 megahertz channels that's the biggest pipe I believe for ax
Okay
You will also
You said you need to do that
And then your client devices also
Have to have
Copper capability otherwise they're just going to use what they can do
Invited in
Remember what that is but it's
A gigabit per second
So
Upgrade your smartphones not using us yet
Which is probably the year most popular most
Commonly
Used device
Certainly not your iot devices
So if you think this is going to help you in that capacity
Percy routers that have us and I believe there have been already
Released
I don't recall who has put them out there but don't rush to get them because you're right once you have the router
Then you're going to have to wait for your client devices to have their Hardware upgraded
To take full advantage of this and that means yes your phone's your tablet your set-top boxes you two devices which again
Probably won't get this capability anyway because
Gabby cranmore antennas and older devices to get this so
There's just no rush
So wait for that APK or 32k TV with all the antennas and maybe then
Maybe then
So what other thing
And this is kind of annoys me and maybe I'm nitpicking here
Here's what I do not want to see happen but I'm sure it's going to anyway
Do you remember Stacy when
Neuer wife I came out and all of these companies said hey we got
5G Wi-Fi Wichita
Yeah
Technically that was correct because hey this is versus the 6th generation of life I standards for
Nostra news
Please do not call it 6G don't even call the old ones
5G because
You're messing around with
No cellular network naming conventions in that ditch
I will call at the first one it doesn't
This is so upsetting to me
I just can't
So let's talk about
Satellite.
Is launching an iot satellite Network
Amazon
Web services
This
Is designed to basically give you connectivity for things where there is no Cellular Connection
And
It is so cool
It is cool and I totally understand what they're trying to do because you know there are remote areas where you might want iot
Key devices or applications
And you just don't have good cellular coverage so doesn't matter if
You know he had an NB iot device
If there's no network
It's funny to me iridium is like the
Satellite service that just will never die
Remember
It was actually for voice Communications back in the day
For the same reason because of cellular coverage
Yeah when you were going to your trip to Antarctica
Crazy septum
You had your sat phone
Yes satellite is one of those
Expensive necessities
They've always wanted
Find use cases that
When you're doing satellite
One of the cost is
Launching a satellite
But the other costs are you got these
Really the modules that you have to have to
Communicate with a satellite or very expensive
Again
To be honest
IRT actually makes more sense than some of the other implementations for satellite Communications
The Voice
For internet you had like up to 2
Second latency
Highlights
So here's my question
They're talking about this is called cloud
They're talking about using it Electra
Makes sense
Another popular thing on a shipping container
But comes to buy
Most of those are going to function
With like normal radios that talk to a Gateway the gateway to satellite backhaul
But a lot of
Could actually just be done effectively be a lot
So you can say hey if it's a refrigerated shipping container
Yule log it like log temperature changes and if it goes out of range even if you could have notified
Vacation
It's unclear if there's much you can
Do
Lake in the middle of the ocean
There may be something
It has to be a high-value item to Justified
Cost
So I'm just thinking here
And it's possible when you go back into cellular range
Just uploaded
Again I think it makes sense for some high-value objects
If you're transporting diamonds then
Popping on this network so you can see it wherever it is
But I don't know
We'll see
Maybe third time's a charm for iridium I don't know maybe
I'm just such a satellite you know
I look satellites I just
It's a difficult business
California
Which is left and right
Crazy has left and left space of corset net neutrality
They now have this new law
That we talked about that is the
Cybersecurity law covering smart devices it is the first state to pass such a lot is SB 327
Passed in late August and the governor signed it
It's a first step
It's minimum
So we need
Work because it's just
Requiring that any device that connects to the internet
Has to have reasonable security features so we talked about this on Pryor show it's a first step it's not the end-all be-all by any means
So the law requires manufacturers to equip connected devices with quote
A reasonable security feature or
Futures
Designed to permit
Packers from
It does not define what this feature should be some people are upset about this but I actually think it's
Probably a good thing to keep this bag because technology and decryption Technologies change so quickly
It does mandated connected devices
Come with unique passwords
That users can change
So yeah I would love for them to say that you know you force users to change
That didn't happen
I think they are forced a required for Caesar to change if it doesn't
Come with a unique password I think it's an either-or
So
Some critics have talked about
Dealing with mean to bag which I've just
Praise but they're like it's not useful
And they also
Basically are like saying
Hey instead of forcing people to add security features why don't you
Insecure future
I wish that they'd spent more time deciding what those insecure features actually are
Device to the internet
Typically I think
Good practices or
Car security alert
Make sure every devices over there update and
Unique he's actually are really relevant
And I like
That's a good thing
That gets a little bar in
No hay
Okay so that is the new law
The idea is this only works for people selling devices
California
So do many other
The most populous state in the US
Chimpanzee
Has got
How do you want it
I think I might not sure yet
What is going to bring to the table but I think I might
IBM has actually put out a blog post
That's
Explain how to add IBM Watson services to home assistant which I know is a platform some of our folks
Home assistant is open source and it's something you kind of
Have to put on your own device like a Raspberry Pi instead of buying a Smart Hub human system becomes the Hub so it's more for the
DIY folks in the books like the program
I think it's going to be interesting to try and I think I'm going to do this because I want to see you again what Watson brings
The idea here is it
Platform-agnostic devices in your house and will provide a unified interface and then
My guess is based on what IBM is saying
They will help you
And developers make
Compose analytics visualization cash boards and new apps
I'm thinking
Will it bring some kind of machine learning Watson actually start bringing more smarts to the smart home as a reason
So that's the whole
But I will have to try it and see
Provokes a half home assistant it doesn't look too difficult to integrate a little bit of
I think that's something everybody should have anyway I'll get off my soapbox
And
Yeah it's pretty much
Bright out there and I github
Repository and add
Got it and
So are you looking for like visualisations of what's happening in your home like what kind of machine learning are you
Trying to do with your hair
Will know it would be nice if Watson saw that I'm doing the same things all the time manually if there's a way to automated Maybe
You could come to be like the
Amazon Padme hunches
I still haven't have you thought Hunters on your battle Bay yet
I got soul Hunters
All right. I don't know yet but I am very curious
Hey
Okay
Rooting
Right along
Let's talk about
Mox
Apple's bringing keyless door entry to campuses
And
You know
Why are there
Yeah they're in this is great and I'm taking classes at my Community College my daughter is taking classes at her College
Neither one is one of the three that Apple just added support to and I think they'd already mentioned that this was going to happen these canvases it's Duke
University of Alabama and University of Oklahoma
They can use that to you know when I need to show the ID that can pay for things using their
Student account with that really interested me was
Using that to get into their dorms the gym in the library
And told them through NFC and I'm like okay that's cool that iPhone has NFC and so does he
It's awesome
Why don't we have more NFC locks because to me this
Just makes more sense of remembering little codes like we had at my house or example
Punching arm
Kiko don't get in
Makes more sense perhaps than Bluetooth which has a much larger range in might be easier
Pack
Yeah NFC just put something close to the door open
I do recall that Yale had about two years ago some NFC locks
But I don't see them for sale anymore and I just wonder if the idea of NFC locks
Was head of it
Time
Because people wouldn't have phones and watches with NFC at that time but now it's becoming so prevalent
I think we need to research
Kevin I don't know
I want to think it's a power
Consumption thing or maybe it was just people don't use it and you know it
Is interference
Maybe someone has a really good explanation
All right
We're puzzled by this
But I am
Microsoft has brought Cortana
Too noise cancelling headphones these are $350 which is expensive
In the rain
Headphones
What why why Cortana
Well
I mean they did me this earlier this week after being Hardware event
Where they also debuted all new Surface products
Surface Pro's news
Sunset Ford so this kind of goes along with that in terms of new hardware
So you really going to add they're not going to have Google or Madam a
Now they're going to
Try and get people using Cortana
We put that thang up the partnership
They do and maybe they'll integrated Madam a
Into these with a firmware update later
But I'm not surprised that you was
Cortana the thing is to use them to use the Cortana bets you do have to be paired with a computer or a phone
Something that
Has Cortana already installed obviously and it's no different than Google assistant or Madame a butt
If you're not using Cortana any other devices
Likely going to buy these headphones
The one nice thing is normally on
Headphones that have an assistant built in
You have to
Tap something
To enable.
Assistant
You don't have to do that with these
D6
Kind of an always-on thing you can't set turn off by default yet but I presume you will be able to in the future but you just
Say Hey Cortana
And if you're wearing his headphones
He responds in your ears
So I am not buying this
All right moving right along to some quick news Bates Johnson Controls
Which
Thermostat
Control products
Industrial stuff that they bought a thermostat maker called
Lux products
Lux actually
I have a thermostat which is a
The talks to Google home
Set the nice-looking
It works
It works it's $150 people like it
Johnson Controls
So yay
Splunk
Which is
This is a data logging
Company they now have their first
Industrial iot product
Surprisingly called Splunk for industrial iot
This brings Splunk logging
Software
Machine learning toolkit
Visualization
Package
All to the industrial world
So this is really to capture and analyze data in a
Customizable dashboard I suspect on exmoor analytics that anything else
It's logging in and out
So you get all this information
Sponge has been involved in the IT world for a long time
Smogon all kinds
Now it is going into the
What was all the OT role vs. operational Technologies
Sensor controls Industrial
Hardcore stuff and a lot of that
Stop is on his own network that never deals and touches with it now
So spark is basically saying
Something just for you
Power
Energy Transportation these companies have these networks artist Abba
So it's a big deal
Asplundh
There are
Tough tools in the industrial world
So the competition there should be
Kind of interesting
But it's possible
As
Companies are pursuing
The internet of things and what they call Digital Trends
Information
The it guys are getting a lot
More say in what happens on the OT side so that maybes blocks weigh in
Okay
Speaking of industrial GE
Could have started
5 years ago with the industrial internet-of-things
I was there
GE just started talking about its jet airplane engine
How old is Cindy
Octave machine learning
Everything was going to be a service
She's been in trouble for a while
And earlier this week and CEO John Flannery
Was
Surprisingly kicked out
And replaced
So
No Larry
And selling various assets
So now
Larry Culp
The new CEO
It's going to be
Finishing that up and trying to
LG get back
Track
They also announced
The sale
Oh
Is intelligent platforms automation business
Emerson and this week I'm actually at
The Emerson
Annual country
Prince and announcements on Tuesday the day Emerson answers on Tuesday that they bought the intelligent platforms
Business sadly they could not say much about it including
The deal terms
That business did generate about 210 million in Revenue in 2017
So
Probably hopefully higher than that
Yeah
Interesting it's the most like this was one of the more successful areas in this space for GE because
Perfect example early adopters of their industrial internet control system
Saw a 40% reduction in maintenance minutes because of the predictiveness of Analytics
White and Emerson which has their automation controls business which is very much apart
Process manufacturing so thick
Anything like
Oil and gas chemical refinery
Even some food production
Those guys
Bunch of clients
It's this week that talked about saving
Gobs of money
Actually
Generating real savings from there
Installation of smarter
Sensors in predictive and using things like
So this DuckTales really well
But
It is still kind of like where I live
What is happening with GE
The answer is
A lot
But
Big companies are picking up the pieces
Export
Heart digital know how
To a lot of other places
Emerson already had plenty of digital know how
Other places
You can never have
Too much know how
I feel like some people might feel they have too much
They don't need to tell me how much you know how they have
All right
Speaking of know how
Kevin
You know how we can use our
Doors windows
Yeah
Yes I kind of feel like the door window sensor doesn't get respect it's like the least respected thing in the iot world in the smart
So
I had a couple sitting around so I
Different ways to use them cuz what do most people use it for
Doors and windows
For security
Total sense but these things are pretty inexpensive the batteries last a long time and they
Just make for a great trigger event for so many different things you can automate in the home so this week I wrote a blogpost
Explaining for unique
Use cases that
I come up with and I'm sure other people have come up with more some helping people share their own I know you have a favorite you can chime in when I
Say your favorite
My kids just don't turn on the exhaust fan in the bathroom when you take a shower which is not good for the bathroom
Terrible actually thought about spending some
Serious money for a
Exhaust fan that had a humidity sensor but the easier thing to do is to just put
The fan on a Smart Switch
And then use a door window sensor on the actual shower door so when they're taking a shower it just goes on
That's it maybe it's not the most
Slightly thing to see about having that sensor on a shower door I feel shower curtain obviously this is not going to work but it works
Pretty well in certain cases
So that's one way
Humidity
You know I haven't seen any problems
I know you're not like IP rated that I know of but
To be honest
There should be less humidity when they're taking a shower then
Biggest fan
I don't know
They're cheap and outfits 20-25 bucks for sensor
Also
I tend to after dinner had to my little comfy chair which is a recliner and I thought about this NyQuil
Why do I every night
Turn on the light
To that chair and
Turn on a playlist on the Google home
I just put
A door window sensor
Into the chair
I need the chair smart and nobody knows cuz you can't see it
To do it either
Flip my recliner over and where the footrest resides when the chair is not in recline position that's where you put the lid
Magnetic contact
And then on the inside of the charity but the
Centered self
Now when you recline in the chair you got a trigger event
And now
I sit down my light goes on in my music starts playing really really cool
That was my favorite one
And it's not going to have to have a certain
Want to talk about before but I'll mention again cuz what time is hey why walk into a dark closet
Sure you have a light switch for a minute walk-in closet to put the light on but we're leaving the light on all the time we walk out of the closet
I have to switch summer wasting electricity
Just put a door sensor
On the backside of that closet door and put a smart bulb in the
Cause it rather
I just open the door
Life Goes On
Close the door
So you're not walking into a dark closet and it's hitting electricity if you are like us and forget to turn that switch off
I do that
I do that in a couple places I do that on my closet door but I do it with a motion sensor
And then I also do it in my laundry
Because
It is awesome
And then again I use a motion sensor there
The other place
Master bathroom
I have it set to go
At 8
Lighting thing so it's not like
Makes sense and we often have our hands full bring laundry into the closet so yeah makes little sense in closet
And for his other tips you're going to have
How to read the article
All right
Speaking of teasers with razors
Spit at the terrible Segway so I won't do that
Septiceye
We have
The iot podcast hotline
I'm Into You with a question
About those razors and kegerators
Hey we're going to announce our winner for our September
Wendy's
Connect to Schlage lock contest
And that would hurt is
Derek
Surprisingly
This almost never happens
She's also our Our Calling
Percent for
So the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by
With a variety of stylish and secure electronic lots to choose from
Smarter homes start
With slaves
Learn more at schlage.com
Iot
Okay
Cemetery
Hi Stacy and Kevin
This is Derek
Malinois
I'm calling in regards
Question on a
Freezer that I
Modified to hold the
Keg of beer
I'm trying to monitor how freaky
Plant Cycles
Have a Z-Wave monitor but it
Currently only reports out about every 30 minutes
How are usages so I don't get a very good idea when it's actually running or not
Curious if you guys have any recommendation
End of a different product
Use that word
Allow me
Track my power usage
Frigerator
How long was that if you had a way to
Monitor the internal temperature
Of the refrigerator that would also be
Be helpful had trouble
Find nanny
But don't
Require mounting
The sensor in
Inside and it would have trouble getting out of this
Any help
Would be appreciate
Alright lyrics
This is a lovely
Question and an easy one
For the most part
So
My suggestion to you right away is using smart plug like the WeMo Insight or any smart plug
That has some sort of energy
Tracking on it
And
Put that in and you'll get a nice little graph of azure refrigerator cycle
So that's
That's one way to do it and ask for the temperature inside
We actually addressed that last week with
Variety
Temperature
Sensors
If you're worried about the wireless signal getting out of the refrigerator which is like a giant Faraday cage
You can put it on the temperature
Which is like
The probe
Connect to a device
An approach that is inside the freezer
Isis actually outside
The freezer so expensive
Or required
Required a hug
So you may not love it but
Someone else did suggest a cheaper alternatives you have
SmartThings and are feeling incredibly
Technically savvy
So
Listeners actually sent me an e-mail
If you guys have SmartThings
He's been using the xiaomi temperature sensors there on $9
Check his freezer
Temperature so that's an option
You do have to download a special device Handler
On GitHub
Orthocenter
And lieutenant
So this is not
I think I fully believe that everyone is capable of doing this but
Some people mean
But for 9 bucks
So it's actually pretty easy to install a SmartThings Handler
I had to do it for some fibaro devices for example and literally or just downloading a code from GitHub saving it as a text file
Remember that file format is for SmartThings
Images
Using your SmartThings app
How to install it once you do that then SmartThings Hub knows what to do with information from that sensor or device
It's not so bad
And you mentioned Stacy's a WeMo Insight switch
That was actually one of the first
Iot devices that I added to my house it's super useful
I wish we could do more than just look in the app and see a log or real-time energy use but and there may be ways
Listen to what I have not look at wemos apis
But there's no
Simple native way to like Mucinex trigger events to say hey
The refrigerator has been running
Too long or something maybe something's wrong as a result what's not running at all when it should be
Easy way to use that but still it is informative and I think get there on the right track
Yes it doesn't fibaro they also have
Energy tracking
It's ass eating
If you have a heart
Okay so Derek we hope that
Helps you and congratulations
Winning
We have a new contest for October and next week
Italy time
Feel free to give us a call at 5 1/2
To ask of your question
And you will be entered to win in the app
Drawing
Even
Even now
And it's not a bag of snakes
No snakes
Not even connected
All right
That's it for this segment of the show
Please stay tuned
And he's going to be talking about all kinds of new protocols
Ways to make the internet cheaper and more distributed
So
You're kind of want to stay tuned
Everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
And I have with me today Frank
Global markets leader
For iot
Frank
Tell me about cotton
Especially
A global leader
Large industrial companies today with all the beast that's going on
Instead of insults
Right from the sensors do I have which I would be platforms should I use what kind of business
And really we see our opportunity to help our customers
So as you helped
What are you typically focus on
What is
Hippie
What is becoming more connected
Helping
Every industry
Thoughts on business models and lead with beaches
Beast transformation
Especially for companies
How to be more efficient.
Jesus
We have at our Disposal today
Especially
Activity saucer
Are the baby look at iot
It's just that it is an accident
Doing iot
Architect
Alley Hotel customer
Cheap.
Using iot and other Technologies
Inox
Demystify
Simplifying
Advisory services
He told NBC
How did business priorities can make
With a solution.
Connection are physicals
That be a factory
Software platform
Denver Health design
Antoinette
Your service
And the focus on digit
It's all qunar
Exactly
Otakon
Absolutely correct
For the longest time
Large Industrial Enterprises
Really have two different words
The World of Tanks
The factories
Buildings and eating people
The world of the CIA
Glass blocks Lowe's
Alipay
And suddenly
To all the evolution in sensor technology
Network difficulty
Upcoming in cricket
Like metal
And the option that you can leverage this connectivity to drive actionable insights
Expedia experiences
Super exciting
Which is why
Enterprises
Leave it as fraud industry and Technology expertise
To bring together
Anthropology user experience
Hardware and software engineering
Stand up a complete solution
Allison Ables baidu
So is this
Real or Theory
Prime time now
Digital product companies in high-tech companies
It's complex when you begin collecting people processing Technologies in new ways
But it's anxiety
I just called to be working with the largest industrial companies in the world
Break the seal
You can go to a website and you'll find all the details about
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Matthew prince who is
Co-founder and CEO of
Matthew how are you doing today
Ccny how are you
I am super great
So we are going to be talking
Fun topic how to remake the internet
I'll call The Internet of Things
This kind of has been
Generation of the internet
I don't know so
4 people let's talk about why I'm asking you
You are with cloudflare
Explain what that is
Yasso cloudflare our mission is to help
Build a better internet
And
To do that we run
Wonder World Park
We have this morning
I think equipment running in the hundred
Eforcity is got it all around the world
And what
World Hinduism
Figure out ways
Make the internet
Orange alien
More efficient
And so what we're thinking about is how do you help
I'm sure that
You Candlebox
Exercise technology
You can spread them out very broadly
And make them available to anyone anyone who needs them
Art of that
Somebody has a lot of
When the internet first came out
It was a massive
Decentralizing Force
As you have lines
Companies like Google and Facebook
Decentralized a lot of
I've come out of those come
Wondering
Play Rolling is
For their decentralized that and I think iot exactly one major ass
Doug
I would probably agree with you
Before we get into like
Crazy nitty-gritty technical details cuz I think you guys are
Actually launching some products that make sense for the future
Internet
What is the internet of the
We talked about decentralisation Butler
How we think about designing this
How we think about the
Problem set
We start talking about
Challenges
What the
If you training at our how do you ensure that the best
Things about the internet
Virginia Beach Red Witch is that anyone
Anywhere an idea or
Business
More information can
And reach a global audience
To go through
Amazing companies
Creative
An enormous amount of value and they have a huge amount of
Technology which
Information on their Network
Easter basket
Security built-in from the beginning
Enormous resources
So had I think about the internet
How do you
Take those advantages
Is that the internet Giants
And make them available everyone
How can you make sure that
Even if you don't have an enormous Center resources
It's all about
How do you make
Sure that
The four billion people on Earth that still don't have internet
How to get online
Field have a great
Experience
NBA Bulls
To do so in a way that they
So much of the internet is really centralized in North America and west
The bytes call-out traffic
And that
That as
We get away from this place has the internet somewhat
Becomes actually much more expensive for those people who actually
Pay more for it.
Everything about how do you make sure that you
Creation on one side
And then democratized
Wow
All right
That's a lot to think about
What about old ways of doing
So
We have had
And actually this is something I've seen
Anglesey access and the kind of internet archive
Which is
Peer-to-peer Network
So we've had in historically things like
Napster
Original Skype
But then there was also really interest
Things about Distributing
Haitian with networks likes
One person had phone connectivity other people had this program
Your phone could talk to each other and backhaul using
Original phone
So how should we think about
Bringing those types of
Technologies
Forward or should we
Skip all that
And there's a new way to do
Yeah you know I think that
You know the nature of
Ecology
He is that
It moved in service
Sine wave
Overtime where you have a map
Dispersion
Validation
Networks will definitely
That went forward your network
Even when Micah
The way that's gay
It doesn't mean that
Life is always right
In those two things and constantly be fine
Disrupt whatever the reality was
Foreign and hopefully striving towards
More distributed more efficient
Secure future
The internet
Technology
Inside about
Is a protocol
Ipff
Interplanetary file
Is actually backed Limited
It means it was designed around the idea of
If you actually have
The internet.
Spam
The globular
But you actually had to happen
Planetary
That stops working
When you have to rely on be light because
Particle of light going from
Mars's
And so you can't rely on
Nutrition system
EBay net worth
Where continent
It's a trap
On an address
What ipff
Contact
On
The hash of the content
And then you can distribute
Tension
Some of the things that we were working on it with
Peer-to-peer Network
I didn't get a p switch
Not really interesting is when we
Two blocks
Chain and other cryptocurrencies
Could create some sort of incentive
I got a little bit of that
Striped bass
My server
Band with tears away that I can
Actually get compensated
There's been a lot of hype
Some of the cryptocurrencies and blockchain
That if you combine ability
To address
Contact
Actually content
With that it has
The current
The or other
Micropayment types
That might
Be away again
Democratizing
Internet
Protocol labs
Doing it
Really interesting I think you know that your body is around
And so
It's a
How can we
Together
I have the traditional internet
With now this
Weeks ago
Support.
Net worth
So that you could
Standard browser
That's the interplanetary file
And I guess I don't know that we know exactly what
That's going to go but if we can be a gateway
To make it so that more people can access these new technologies
Cheap things to make
Okay so we talked about distributed we talked about making things cheaper talked a little bit about some of the things
Let's talk about
Your birthday weekend
So
The last couple weeks you guys have
Pinterest drop Inus left and right
It's been kind of fun some of it
I don't care very much about like
For y'all but there are lots of things I do care about
About was actually the bandwidth Alliance
So talk to me just a little bit about what your goal is there
Yeah so what the bandwidth alliances
Citic group
A provider
Come together
To say
That
We should reduce
Cost of moving data
Between different providers so typically if you're using a cloud provider
Google Cloud
Microsoft and IBM
When you put it into them
Do you want to take data back out
Talk to you a lot
You're a fat provider
Alldatapro
Ashburn Virginia where you got
Your data center back the time user
Cruise in Sydney Australia
You got to pay for that
With a number of dividers
Is the markup on bandwidth
Are extremely high but
Barbie threesome
The cloud provider
They will
My hand that data directly off
I like pie
Connected over was known as a private
Literally
It goes from your router
To the top
Something
Beginning
Bike that has no incremental
Extending bandwidth
Link and throw
Was
Not paying for the data
No I think that the real leader here
What's Google + Google
2015 Prius
CDM
Intertek program
And Papa was
One of the
Members of Abba
Grayson
Or gathering all the other Cloud providers
Safeway
Together
Find a way that it
You're changing bit in a way that the
You
The long-term value
Is
That if we can make it
You can
Say I'm going to pay
Amazon
Everything in Amazon stock
What you know
M4ai and that the Microsoft
Stop
Google interesting
Stopwatch
Bear
Storage in database
Heap data where they
If we can make it so that would apply breakfast
Mack Oliver
Together without you have
Pay to move your data
Specialized
And instead of everyone the same
We get another thing them.
I'm going to build the best agree for this one particular thing
People will choose me for that
Overall
Open
Overall ecosystem
Significantly
Amazon Safari
Is the one major old out
Good thing to do
Okay and let's talk about another one of your
It is tied to something that you guys.
Spring
Beyonce program called workers
Really
Interesting
Been out for a while so I'd love to get an update on how people are using
And then you guys also a noun
Key Value Store
For workers
Which
I was really exciting like data could be
All over the place and accounted for but tell me about that
Yes boo
Today
Knott County
Three generations of how you've been able to deploy Network
Generation Y
Application
New bottle server
And that if you needed a new
The new application you bought a new server
Cancel the deployment
Time for that was measured in months
In 1999
The Next Generation
Occurred
Is VMware
Are there open source
Allowed
Electric at this point in time
Your mom
Bouncing baby
Coordinate with their people in order
But
You could actually take your unused
Beyond servers
On the phone
Utilization of the
The Next Generation
Which is Amazon web services and all the other
Cloud hosting providers
Let's take your you think you have me on that episode
Our infrastructure
And that's a bet
One time down
From days a week
2 minutes or hours
In order to be able to do
Still this model of man
Adwa
As if it was a verb
Securities property
Configure that everything else
Template
What we were doing with workers
Creating what is that
Generation 2 we all know what bare metal is
GM.
We don't walk around with a new idea
Exotic
You some everyday
VA
Delta standby
JavaScript
Wireless router
You need
Who are when you encounter
Start getting incredibly quickly
Cold start time
I didn't meet a very efficient and with
You don't have it
Giant
Super Bass
Feeling good in your laptop
Different pieces of code run
Next to each other
Isolation from one another and
The V8 engine
And isolate and we deployed that
As code running
What was amazing about that is that
Appointment time
Down from what now is
Flower
Cold Stone
Time Bomb what is
2 minute
Down
Workers you can write code
Quit urin
Iron Network
Running on every one of them
Machines out there and then you can look at it as if it is an individual
Function
Perform whatever
Valley unique
And it will be available as
I need whenever
With almost
Different model
And that you didn't have a weight back
So during our birthday weekend
The amount that we would leasing a value
Right
Data
You only one of our Philadelphia
Our system will figure out
Consistency
I meant
You letting it in Vienna then we did in San Jose
And it can be instantly available
Information
How did RM
Updated
The ability to write
One out of
Lakers
Expand in Boca Raton
Earlier this week
Mild webassembly
Then click languages
Go
A map of Global Network
BBW
We've now babe.
Exciting
I'm in the other dimension
Baked potato
Object
Store
Databases run
I'm at work
And I think that if you can combine the thing
Lola
Hyper
Combined with a very sophisticated data
Pipe tobacco
Locations that
You can build
I Willie
What we talked about the real value workers
Hake
Lady trying to drive down the building
What time is it in Dubai
What you now
I'm actually Megan
Boy ability
Take their legacy and then add things like image processing or boy
Voice recognition or additional intelligence
Update
Yeah that
Bye
New device
But every device
That we never stole
And so what if we date
The device is good at today
A DUI portion
In the network
Are we going to have that short latency and high efficiency
Gat5
Being a sweetheart to every night
Okay
We should talk about
Announce support
For an iatf standard
Quick
So why don't I let you defy
It's a quick really is a replacement for eggs
One of the differences is that
BCT Bank
TCP base protocol Callahan's
Send a pin
Signal
Set up a handshake
Fire-and-forget
When you get fired at
Align
And that is
Quit
Is design around at Uni
Emacs protocol
Eric Wright
Be able to fix any problem
Come across the line
And if there's any noise or anything
That might
Interfered with any of the communication
Where this really matter
Devices that are
Connected to a wire
And don't move around alot
More and more
Internet on wireless
Gcp is that
In those conditions where you see a y
TTP is actually incredibly low on
First of all it built
Security and by default
Wait really designed around
Mobile
Experience where we know that there's going to be lost.
Is overwhelmed
That could mean because somebody
Turn on the microwave or
Google
Willie nolita
Team building original
Python
A used car
Stancil Mount of their own property
Back protocol has been adopted by
Bmchs
Finally got ratified by the idea
That will again be that Gateway
Where is a mobile device
Will be able to talk
Duet
Quick
And then behind
Will still
PCT in HDPE and all the things that standard web server
The Wire
We hope to bring the back
World
Connection
From the device
Wandering around
Reebok
Dude the Clown
Out running
The address of the internet
And then
Eubank
Traditional protocol
Do you think of this is again something that help make the internet
Make it more on again tomorrow
Is it something that previously
Okay
Think of your network
Where can you register your network
Is
And I believe you said 154 City
So because this is all tied back
To you guys
How do you answer the charge that idea that well are we just centralizing around
Innovative
Places
Really
Bride-to-be
In terms of
Pushing the internet over but doesn't require
Beat the only provider
Ipff
Gateway between
Browsers that don't
What IP path
Write the world
But if you have a father
Down
People that use
In awhile today
Together
What each other
Thanks
You know
Connect directly to digital
Great
Stand-alone entity
Protocol
It's on
Call what is a chicken-and-egg problem on the internet
The browser guys don't want to
And what we found it
If we can be kind of the first mover and solving the problem
Standard
I'm not going to give it enough
Anything that we do
Support on business
Back more than
And
Then again
The only way that you can get online
Awesome
Alright thank you so much for coming on the show The
Thanks for having me
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
Remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Will see you next week