Hey everyone Welcome to the
Holiday Inn
10 of the Internet of Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today since we are pre recording this in the early early days of December we are not going to be discussing
This week's news
Presumably there's not a lot
If there is will cover it next week
Because
How we doing
Instead we're going to tell you about crazy iot prediction
Our biggest
What's up 20
And our biggest
Auntie
Our guests this week will be my family
Let's go to a quick word from our sponsor a place it's a Feeling
The feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT helps keep you safe
So you can feel protected wherever you are introducing the ADT Security starter kit everything you need to get started
Is ADT Pulse including a camera professionally installed for only $49 visit att.com
Slash podcast today to learn more requires 36 month monitoring contract installation and activation fees
Did Roman and qspec pay required certain markets are excluded licenses available at ATT
Dot-com Florida ID through f0001 121 Louisiana Ave
1:6
Okay
Now we are back
And let's kick it off with our
You want to go crazy
Predictions are biggest
Let's go with biggest disappointment that we have good stuff new Happy stuff to talk about a fan
Already
Let's kick it off with
My biggest
Where
Oware
My presence today
We have been talking about this
You know like
Gosh for like 3 years now
It feels like a really long
I keep wanting to be able to go into a room
And have the room know that it's
Me
Not somebody else in my
But also that I've been there so when I say turn off the lights
It knows
We got
We got closer I mean we do have cameras with video recognition now but they're out there on the market but
Yeah I agree I mean I always thought it would be
Either a little tag
Maybe it's Bluetooth I don't know
Guitar phone
Whatever but it probably will be
Cameras and facial recognition and that's going to be interesting because a lot of people may not want that
See I want a Bluetooth Beacon
Things I thought that was the ideal way to do it so you
Phone
Also
We also
Kind of got there
In a sentence with like the Amazon Echo letting you group things in a room although that
Not exactly
Perfect it's not perfect and it's more
It's Annie's of use thing it's not really a presence thing I mean it's putting the presence of the objects together but I think we're
Song about our presence
That's right for a 1R smarthomes to be smart enough to know where
Kevin is in this room and
Stacy isn't that room and someone
I really don't have the
This ties in with actually a corporate
Or Enterprise
Kind of effort which is
Beacons
I was disappointed this year because I feel like beacons have no
They're not all that people are not I don't encounter them
Very often
Spaces
I have the physical web in Ableton
IPhone 4
Couple years that's
Google
Beacon
Project
Cash nothing ever pops up
The only time I saw things pop up
Was when I was working for Google in the Google New York City office
I never had anything pop up in a store or anything
And I'm actually okay with that cuz I really don't know that I want the store hanging meat but it would have at least told me
I've only seen
A few or news of a few implementations and a lot of planned Abominations but
A could be the people ruin them out and we're just not aware yet but I tend to
Beauty the beacons are not yet all that
Yeah and I really thought there was
Interest Airbus on
I'm working but things like wayfinding I thought would be
Be really helpful in building
A lot of cool talk and there have been so pilots in like Stadium
Sports Stadium
To help people
Get to the shortest line the fastest
Indicate which
Bathroom decor
But overall
Would be farther
So
Maybe that'll happen
Let's see what else is disappointing this year
Consumer protections and data
Retention and Salon that's been a continuing problem and no longer has a problem the worse it is for this Market at the whole I think
A couple shows back we talked about some legislation
Here in the US that might add some consumer protections to iot devices but
As we sit back on that show it was like a six-year time frame at best
Apple keynote basic legislation
Willets Point
Committee and then we'll do the next step and I will do the next step
Task force of a committee to create benchmark
Protection right right right
I didn't even
Take up space in my brain
Guess so consumer protections I'm actually disappointed that we haven't seen somebody lost
And I'm betting it's because a lot of this
Well could be that it could also be the
People when you say. Attrition meaning in the terms of service that people agree to or
Yeah okay I was going to say that's probably why there's no lawsuits cuz people are agreeing to the terms of service but you're right
Buried in there probably have arbitration Etc Elsa and I'll be the first one to say I don't read
Read the terms of service
I'm almost at in your eye. And I should I'm setting a bad example so
Don't do what I do
People read your terms of service and decide you often don't see the terms of service to you bought
A product and that's an issue
Yes I would like that song
Also in consumer protections I would say we also have not achieved any sort of forward momentum
Round things like
Setting a product life cycle settings
Security parameters we did see
This last year the f
PC
Sue
Couple router makers for having hard-coded passwords and still trying to advertise as being safe however
TC decisions were actually
Appealed so were and I don't feel that our current FTC is probably going to be as active under the
Ministration
So yeah
I would say things are not great
I would agree
They can only get better let's hope they do
And speaking of getting better or rather
It's opposite since this is the biggest
Section
Cash Baker I think
I feel like things are getting worse
Army integration
I need not into separate
We have not seen a coalescing
Billy around standards except for madame
Possibly Google home
So they're still too many hugs out there
There's still a lot of options
And getting things
To work together
Is not seamless you're like enabling skills and logging into like 16 different accounts
Get stuffed working and then even then it doesn't always work
It seems like we've got
Solution it's a bolt-on solution we just keep adding adding adding little bits not cohesive
Solution
James Wright & Filippis
Amazon text alerts
Get the skills and I forget what Google calls them but they have something similar and then we also have
Yeah but their party Services I can
Rap all these things together with apis
It's just everybody's trying to put
Stuff together and why do they do that because it's not together by Nature
By default
And that's
Yeah you're right it's kind of getting worse in that sense
And what's making it even worse and
My best example of this would be
Amazon Echo Show
And Google's YouTube video
Now the people are actually like the big manufacturers are actively try
Tear things apart
So one it's all I need to begin with but in some cases
Since I'm just never going to be
Write and in that particular case you bought something with the
Unexpected feature
That you no longer have
Which brings us back to consumer-protection
Badda bing badda bing badda boom
All right
So I really like honestly biggest disappointment
This year might be so far in the Smart Home
Still freaking
It sucks even though we said it's not for the last
3 years
I'm very disappointed with the end of
Asheville
Angry about it okay
Emotional
That's okay no you're entitled to admit it's been a challenge has been issue I don't disagree but I do think
It's gotten
Better it sucks less
Depending on what it is what product or what service or whatever it is you're trying to do I think it does suck less we have more options
Which has its pros and cons
I think it's getting easier to set certain things up just a mesh Network
For example can be very easy to set up and do a world of Wonders for devices in your house
But you're right it still kind of sucks
No no
All right
Finally on my biggest disappointments are
My gosh
Cellular providers where are my flexible cellular
Transfer business
And startup iot f
I still feel like
We're not seeing a lot of it
Innovation therein
And it's still hard for a smaller company
Kapil products with
Cellular-based
Wireless Solutions in them
Yeah I don't disagree with that I think this is still pretty nascent Market
In terms of using alternative networks for iot devices
Luckily one would hope that the carriers and operators have learned a lot from the mobile broadband Revel
Lucien you know starting tennis years ago in terms of what they need to provide on the network
Kind of demanding to have from devices and so on
We seen figures and other.
20 billion device
So I'll cut them a little Slack
But by this time next year
If this is still on your disappointments list
That's a major fail in my pee
Another disappointment
Is
The Trump administration's decision not
To continue with the vehicle to vehicle
Communication standards 7th grade to like 5 years ago
And not to implement that
Which
There's concern over the cellular in Hawaii
HiFi guys
But I really thought
We have this solved
Yeah
I got a lot of people
Possibilities
Screeching halt
I can't argue with you on this one I'm disappointed as well it's just it's something that took so long and get going
And
We even had you know an official protocol standard for it
And we were just about to get
Rolling out here and now it's like nope not doing it
So that kind of sums up my biggest
As always I'm disappointed that I don't hear more from
Companies that are actually implemented
Cool iot stuff
I know that you're out there I know there are pilots and
Sensitive
I'm a little disappointed that I have
Heard more
Successful
Scale
And that could be partially because companies may think we just implemented is one thing that was a mess of undertaking and it gives
This Thursday that we didn't have before
We can make more sense of it
But part of me says
Are they thinking that's not
Big enough in there for not reaching out or shouting from the rooftops look what we did
I don't know
Either
So that's our
So now we'll move into
Are crazy iot prediction
Let's talk about
What we think is going to happen
So
Let's kick it off with me on the smart home side
I think price is going to become a
Huge honkin deal to cancer
We're seeing so much interested really cheap
Iot home devices I think that's because people have realized that
Like we said earlier it's still kind of sucky
And I'm not going to spend a lot of money it's a lot to ask someone to spend you know
250 bucks on a camera
If they're not sure how it's all going to work together
What other products
So I think
Cheaper devices are going to come
If that's actually tied to another prediction
Air quality in China
Some Chinese manufacturer
It's actually getting really good
There's a lot more emphasis when I talk to you
Suppliers and
When I talk to me
Facturar
They're telling me that in China
Quality is becoming a big
Issue
And tell if you tie those two things together we're going to see some cheap devices but
Basement of quality and I think that's going to be
A lot of pressure on other
Providers in this area
I hope so because I just
Started pricing out motorized blinds
For my house and oh my goodness it's ridiculously expensive
Oh yeah
So if you do motorized
I will tell you that
Part of the challenge is he want quiet blind
Mostly
Those quiet Motors
They cost a lot
Yes they do
Yes I do so little me at a prediction in here I think after
When it's been
Since 2014 I think it was 2014 that Apple announced homekit
So was 2015 going to be the year of homekit while it wasn't 2016 no 2017
I think 2018 will be able to say yeah homekit has finally
Cortical arrive
Siri
Will probably just be good enough
I don't think
I made this prediction back when they announce the homepod in fact
Saying I then feel haven't proved serious that it will
Compete better with
Amazon and Google's offerings but now I'm I'm rethinking that I do not expect that to happen
Still be good enough
Yeah I think
The big change here
Was Apple's decision to go with hardware-based
Security Authentication
And they have really thought that
Through now we can be software-based where we staying out said it could be so I think that will ease the burden on a lot of these
Device makers
Which they were kind of going in circles for the
The passenger year-and-a-half in my opinion so 2018 I'm going to call it home kit
Is it's a deer
I agree with that
But it's probably because I've been burned by
And the people I talked to have also been burned by him
The vendors
And manufacturers are certainly
Losing faith
Or have lost faith
The consumers
It's still a very popular request
People email is questions
Fewer things do work
Don't get that is true
Let's see what happens this year
So yes
I do see some
All right
I also think in this is kind of a fun way
Actually going to see some Smart Homes getting built
Sonu belt
And
New apartments
Smart features
Added to them or going on them
The new-build market
I think
Connected elements are going
Package
So what kind of like granite
I do think that's happening
Lennar
Katie Holmes
All those companies
Investing in it I think we should keep our eyes open
It's a lot of these are investing around
Particular
Product
Like home kit
Where
Why is a non homekit
Are non Apple phone user I look at that unlike
That is useless
So that'll be really interesting
Developed that because the two ways of
I seen so far is homekit or they go with Ken
Proprietary app
That uses like a Z-Wave or zigbee and then a hug that the apartment community
Provides
And then you just have a nap and that's usually in the apartment
Stormcutter
I tend to agree with you I think you'll see more of this
I think homekit will be the
Not that the factor standard for this kind of option but I think it'll be the one that's
Offer the most
And probably chosen the most then I say that because the people who are buying homes in the future are the younger generation
Right man I'm a downsize yet
You can live there for a couple years maybe and stay there but whatever
You're not going to buy new construction again is
My guess neither am I
If I buy it
I can't get any neutral wires every true I can sympathize with that personally but
Again.
Generation X
Up-and-coming
Spell remind vinegar properties
One thing I think they're
Probably more iOS than Android
And
They're going to want this
And I can't believe you just called me
I didn't say all that young girl
We're no longer
Up-and-coming
AARP card online
All right
After Kevin's called me old let's move it move ahead to new prediction
Oh I like this one this is a good one
Always something I alluded to in a post
A couple weeks back
I think we will start to see in 2018 very slowly but we will see it
More offline or contextual Smart's in the home
Thanks to more localized machine learning and AI this goes back to some of the
Products that
Amazon announced this year back in November
I'll soon Google has some products around this time talking
Specific about green grass for Amazon and
Tensorflow Lite
For Google
I think it was a beer to bigger players in this space
And
We'll see if it's going to require new hardware or not I'm hoping not
It just amazes me for example that Google's pixel phones can be offline but still tell you what song is playing in the area
So there's some
What used to be in the cloud is now on the phone
Right way to see that everything going now to the home this last in 2017
Intel
They launch date
Device called the
Movie Diaz
I think was the neural network dongle
Had again
Capable of machine learning capabilities on this
Portable little
Stick USB stick it was
Crazy
So this is definitely a trend and I think what we're going to
I see is now that all this is out there
And people have started using it or going to CC
Some really cool stuff
And the added benefit is when the robot overlords rise up again just pull out their AI dongle
Hi
Also
This is more on the Enterprise front butt
Pink tour 2018 we can safely say that the race to the clouds
Everybody in there
Dog
Everybody in their dongle
Industrial space
Pretty much over there giving up that
We're now the cloud is over
The it guys
So we got a sure we've got Google we've got Amazon all offering really competitive and compelling
Iot services
For Enterprises
Industrial class
And related to that
Next year we're going to see
Edge has already been a big
This year
But it's going to be more so next year we're actually going to see how companies
Are implementing it
Where to see a lot of startups
Come in and solve for some of the
The problems of
Computing at the edge such as latency
Security issues
Ambient
So I'm going to look forward to that
Pill finder
Call me if you're
Cool startups in
We'll talk
And
Hussy
Oh last week
But Kevin brought up a very good
How much is business
Voice
I think that's going to be big next year
But it is also
I think I T has a lot of nightmares right now and I forget what survey it was with something like 62% of ITP
People surveyed back in
October November
Didn't even feel confident they knew about all the devices on their Network in their
And that's a
Huge issue a huge issue it folks want to know
Everything
Because they'll be held accountable if there's an issue and they certainly want to keep control of all that and the whole BYOD movement kind of
I took some of that away
I think the only reason they just got their hands on that
And wrangled those cats
But this is going to be a mess for them
Now here's where I'm going to go
I think next year it shops are going to reassess
How they're implementing
I think very much like a guest
We had earlier this year they're going to be looking for longer are Eliza's
The short-term
Because they realize that you truly do a business transfer
Information you actually need to think
Longer-term
Bigger
And just you know
These very easy automation projects at
So I think they're going to reassess their role in
An iot developer
Think we're going to see some local can
Control start to develop because a lot of
Value in iot a cruise where the sensors are
And often times that's going to be at
Your branch office
Start a retail shop
I sent that is not where I T is today
So I think
Go Kevin
I was
Right there with you I'm like yep I agree I agree I agree and then when you said local control
I just don't see it does not want to give up control anytime it gives up control
It feels it's opening itself up
For accountability when it has no way to be responsible number one
Into
It people and I was 1/4
For 15 years and
Maybe it's changed since I was last in the night eShop
They don't want to offload things be
Because they feel it
Many of them feel it
Reduces their value to the organization
And sadly while I understand that
You know it isn't just a very specialized you need roll anymore it permeates everything in today's modern
Businesses so
It's a balancing act
For these folks and I sympathize with them.
They're going to fight
Tooth and nail to not give up
Control okay so maybe our fight is
It fights
Business
Over
Chi-Chi has always fought with business and it always will
All right
Well those are big
Predictions
For next year feel free to share your own
Predictions with us
I'm sure we'll get lots of cool ones
And then we decided to end it on biggest questions
Because
I don't know about you Kevin but
There's a lot of things happening that
Malik next year because I'm not sure how that's going to play out
But I feel like it's going to happen
So my first in this category is
What is going to happen
With GDP
PR and that is the
General data protection regulation
Yes that is the eu's act
It goes into effect May 25th
2018 it's basically instilling some
Privacy and data
Protection charges
Across the European Union but also
For EU citizens
So that means if an EU citizen is renting a
Here in the US
They actually are protected by this which means
Companies in the US will
Undoubtedly and other parts of the world
Have to deal with
Many companies already put
Yeah I have a feeling they're going to
They're not going to be prepared for those kind of situations and
The other aspect to this is
We got the whole brexit vote
So
UK folks you're not covered under gdpr anymore unless
UK passes something similar on its own
Yeah you guys are like
Dip with no privacy
SC Productions
Now I will say looking ahead at this
We'll probably see a Spate of lawsuits
Very soon after its path
Most of the big tech companies
Totally on board and have been
Forever In terms
Getting their house at 4
So we're going to see some really interested I think the lawsuits
Will see you're probably going to be
Smaller companies and maybe some of the sketchy data Brokers that have
Historically been in the shadows
Is there going to start
We're also probably going to see some newspaper articles
Who are like
Reporter saying
I just ask Tinder for all the day that they have on me and holy cow
What they have
So I think there's going to be a real public
Accountability
Challenge
That's going to come out
And actually I'm glad you mentioned that this is probably something that
You and I should
Consider doing as well as to the listeners every once in awhile go and download
All of your
Data that's available safe from your Google account
From Facebook or whatever
It is and go see what they really have
Because there's been a lot of interesting stories in the past year
About
You know Shadow accounts and so on so forth and let's
Probably
On us-22
Really dig into that
All right
Just giving ourselves
More work
Next big Quest
What will the end of net neutrality mean
For iot assuming
That net
Neutrality
Does go by the wayside from the protections that were put in place two years ago
I don't know I can only because I don't
Know that we have all the details yet
Split
I don't know what I'm sure you have thoughts on this
We don't have to that's why it's one of our biggest question
We don't have to know
We just have to
Bring it up as like
Hey
It's possible now we're recording this
Before the December 14th vote
So we don't know how
Tamarindo or if it's going to happen
There's also will that boat stand after
Comet Pride
What kind of a judge don't know
That's going to be stuffed
To be decided and then
Also just how are
Isps going to
Treat things
My Comcast has a very big
Smart Health effort and they also
Have been historically pretty aggressive
About
Walking things on their Network
It will be interesting
To say the least
Another big question we have is
Security
I don't think security is an issue is going to go away
I am not really helpful and I would love to see a new security
Model developed for connected devices
In the home
And Enterprise
So
My big question then for next year is what
And also just because we're talking about legislation I wonder if we will actually have some real legislation
From a security standpoint that's passed here in the US
Because every said earlier it's just been
Nonexistent or on the very very slow Rhode
And my final big question has to do with cellular network
Lyrics I'm curious of NBA
Katem
Will win
Actually
Probably should brag mat for low-power wide-area
What will win
Probably
Is there still Laura there sigfox all those are being deployed and I'm curious if we're going to see
What networks
Become popular and what locations and for what types
Business situations
Yeah I was going to say
What I think
We'll see is different
44 winners in different Geographic
Regions based on operators and what they've already started it deployed
Bro they've already started down
Well and I have lots of
Peter probably a good place to stop
And give you guys some food cuz I feel free to
Seriously
Episode
Scary difference
And stay tuned
Because
Is my family
Talking about
What has changed in our house what they like what they
Normal person
Perspective
I don't know
Hey everyone welcome back
Back to the internet
Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
AR
My family
So I got my lovely husband
Andrew
And my daughter Anna
Hi
And
As usual
Around this time of year they are here to join us
Did give you a mainstream perspective
On what it's like
Live in
So let's kick it off with this year
I feel like I personally have
I've tried out fewer devices and spent less time changing
Do you guys think that's true
I would say lately that's the
Case you know there's still some things that I wish would be tinkered with so they would work a little bit better but I think that's
It's probably true because you've got
Kind of a baseline together with all of our light temperature
So this year
I brought it in
A couple
New devices
I know everyone who listens to the show
Understands my husband
Affection for the June
Yes
In addition to that
What else
That you guys are like
It's not so bad
That's not so bad that's
What hasn't been so bad
All the Alexa's in the house
You do have quite a few more now don't we
They seem to increase over time
NAU
Previously told me that you did not want any smart devices
And now you have an Amazon Echo
Why was that the device
Because
Once I'd gotten to know a little bit better and feel how it affected me everyday
Since they were pretty much all over the house
I realize that
I would not mind having one of my room
Because there were some things I noticed about my house
And that Alexa could fix
I like to listen to music when I'm doing homework or studying or playing and
Designed to play music
No not really
What if I put a smart light bulb
Well maybe I'll sneak one in there and see what happens
Andrew what have you added or what if we added that
First of all in the Echo
I would say that they are helpful I'm not a huge fan of the Echo Show I believe there was this year
Compared to the regular Echo mainly downstairs
Because we have
Kind of the bank open downstairs
The Amazon Echo you know that big
Ring on top lights up
When it's listening for the echo show yet to be looking at it to know if it's listening or not
And I've also found that the sound quality isn't as good because it doesn't have the the speakers going all the way around
I'm also
If Google home had all the connections at the same time as early as Alexa I would say the Google home
Is better because it's so much better at search
Write them in there so many questions that I think are fairly simple that Alexa can't answer that Google can and Google seems to
Understand
My questions better than
The Madam a does as well
As far as new things in the home while the June oven obviously is nice another one was pretty simple.
Share but it's a huge help which is you put in that
Connected
Switch for the under cabinet
Kitchen light
And connected to a pair of fluorescent bulbs that we have
Several fluorescent bulbs
So we had on our kid
Right and so it did two things for us one is
And when you've got your hands dirty with food and instead of reaching for that switch
Turn on the under cab lights you can just ask Madam a to turn them on at the other thing is
Bad habit
Leaving house lights on
And since they were connected where is the rest of kitchen lights were connected I got yelled at by
Not not yet
I got in trouble with a certain someone for leaving those lights on
When she would be going to bed and ask matamata turn off
The lights downstairs knows want to go off and then she'd have to walk over and do it so
That was help
All is well
All right helps you with your bad habits
And also
Just make life
Yay
Okay we also this year went through
Couple different thermostat
I say we had a Honeywell T5
For a while
And
Have historically had an ecobee smart SI
And then I just put it in a thermostat
From Luxe products which is a sponsor of the show
To try that out
And we also upstairs have a nest
So given that we played with a lot of different thermostats I'm actually curious like
Does it even matter what smart thermostat you have or do you even care if you
Your thermostat smart
I just want something that works
You know it and frankly even if I just have to program it
If it has it's kind of a smart away future that's enough for me that thing that bothered
Me about the nest is when it decides on its own that would be more comfortable at a certain temperature
And it plays with it and then the middle of the night you get really hot I guess there was a bug on that this year fire caulk
Correctly
Slasher
I guess the answer is the basics I need I need an app on my phone so I can adjust the temperature
They were out of town
It needs to be easy to program when we want it to be certain temperatures
And
Really that's that's about it as long as it's working that's good
And I feel like we should do it connected toys this year
We've kind of spent most of your time just hanging out of the car
Computer instead
So are there any features or anything
Exciting that you like you actually like the Echo Show
Yes I like the Echo Show because I feel like it's a bit more interactive send
Other lights as because
You can ask
Steve information
And it gives you prompts for what to say when your just like
Well what else can Alexa do
And you can actually
CM Punk's and you can just look at it
Are the time instead of just
Having to ask
Madame payforit
And it's also helpful when you got like recipes or something that's pulled up because you can just
Look at it rather than
Haven't got you other
Trouble because
It's just
Like a voice programmed iPad
A couple times I called you guys while I was out of town
And I drop in on you on the echo
How did you guys
It was
Strange to see the sudden transformation of like a screen
Intuiface from distances away
And
It was kind of strange to know that the camera on Alexa
Stampwithbrian
Casting us
To somewhere else but I thought it was a nice feature because
We could talk
/ serial
No
You know they took the Amazon and Google who owns YouTube are in a fight
Which is why we can't watch her Corgi videos do you feel like this out loud
I know without that
Do you think
TV show is still worth it
That is a very tough question because
What are my priorities on it was that I was able to watch
Crazy videos on YouTube
I feel like the other stuff adds up and makes up for it
Because
Even though
Madam is having some conflicts with
Partners and stuff it doesn't limit its abilities to full extent
All right what about things that didn't work
I can think of one Gadget
It is driving my entire family
It's currently driving us crazy
I'll give you a hint
Cleverpet
Yes
To be fair this is
Cleverpet
Pet feeder
It's designed for people who are not at home
For their pets
Still like entertain themselves during
But since my family is off at home since we had it over the Thanksgiving holidays and some other days were
Still in the house
Treatment to find itself unplugged
Quite a bit
Well
Once or twice
But it is very annoying if you're sitting there in every
10 to 30 seconds it's making it
Loud mechanical noise
And our dog doesn't seem to appreciate it either
Okay I don't think she's learning
Skyrim
It's possible that our dog is
Okay what other gadgets any other things that we saw this year that
You guys were like
I want some of that
Why don't we have this installed
Or
Please take this out of my house
One thing I have noticed this year is that our internet seems to be working well and I think
I don't remember when we play
Put the first-generation erosion in the second generation but and I don't know if that's it but I was having lots of connect
Tivity issues before that and it seems to be going really well the past
6 to 12 months
Will give ear of the credit for that
Cuz yeah you definitely have some
Your computer does
Did not like steak
It didn't another thing to is a device I rarely used
But when I do use it it's extremely helpful and that's the Chamberlain MyQ for the garage door for example when your car was in
Rashad we had the loaner car
Didn't have the garage door opener or the
The Homelink
And so being able to open up the app
And select
Might see you in just open the garage door that way was helpful especially because we have such
A sloped driveway so to actually park it and get out and go into the garage and open it isn't all that easy so
That was very helpful as well
And speaking of the Mikey
Do they actually have added
A feature that would integrate it with like if
Or even like maybe your Google home and what it is is you would pay
Buck extra each month or
$10 a year
Right now we don't subscribe to
To any of these things but I'm very curious if you think there would be value
In
One of those types of subscriptions or maybe
Cloud-based camera system
It's a good question you know one thing we've done recently as go through look at all of our subscriptions in because they do that
And see which ones were actually using
I need to keep I can't think of anything off the top my head with the MyQ where I'm like oh I wish I could do this or that
That that said a lot of times you know I didn't think I needed voice activated stuff before the Alexa camera
So you know sometimes it's what you actually get it that you realize how valuable it is
Security cameras
I guess if they would record for a little bit longer or keep it store longer but for the most part
We would know if we need a recording pretty quickly after it happens right if we were robbed or something like that we would know
No I can't think of anything off top my head run like
I would pay a monthly fee for this at the same time
I'm sure there are some things that
Would add value that I
Say yes let's pay for it
Okay
Because you are young
You are the voice of the future
Can you come with your own theme music
In your Ideal World
What do you think the house that you live in
Like 20 years
10 years
What do you think how do you think it reacts to
In the future
It really depends because I feel like the way technology is going it's going to be
A lot more customizable
Journey
Brilliant light
Being in control
Troll
Less than being able to
Talk to things
So
I like
Having easily access
Too late
And control
So
It's pretty clear that this year was The Big Year for
Voice to become a smart home interface
Since we've been
When is it worked and when does
Well it's very helpful I think for lights
In general
Especially when your hands are full or in our case now we can we're going to bed we can just
Come upstairs and say turn off downstairs we also added the television
Thing this year what is that called
Logitech Harmony Hub which is kind of nice when you
You having a glass in your hand and you're heading over to the living room to watch TV to tell it to turn on the television
And have the TV and the Roku and everything just kind of boo'd up
I will say that it still seems like
Matinee
Miss carries us
A lot
And it's not getting any better in fact I feel like as we had more devices it gets worse because she gets confused
Between them
And so you know a lot of time she asks
For clarification and it just seems so far off from what we were asking
Well let me ask you this guy's
What if I swapped out Madame A4
Haji
I like the idea that the one thing I don't like
About the
The Google
Is that
It has soy
I mentioned the Alexa has that ring of lights on top so you know and it's listening
The Google home on the other hand has a slope top
And it lights up a little bit
But if it's facing away from you
If the slope is going the other way you can't tell if it's listening
So that's one downside but I'd I totally be up for trying like a swap downstairs and seeing how it works
We did it for a little bit
Hugh
Well was that
When we had the regular matinee
Yes
Cuz I think my big complaint with the Google was that I didn't know if it was
If it hurt us or not
Where is the matinee we could see that it was listening
Alright any gadgets on your wishlist
Oh I have one
It's about the
It comes in and actually sets up the expensive thing we have that
Makes our Shades go down automatically and allow us to control them
Every year
I just I just want to give you something
The house of 15 or 20 years from now it'll actually be set up
In anything that you're excited about or think would be fun
Onion
Smart toys these days
They're getting more and more interactive and I really
Appreciate that because it's not just so if I press
This
Something happened
Get you deeper into like
So if I do this combination that it's going to interact with me that I can interact back and it
Billy tentative sets Your Horizon towards a bigger goal when
You're playing and learning about tech
Was it last year that we got the
Robot
As I would call it the 7 minutes away
It was kind of a sentence like a
But yes
Yes
Cosmo
Yep the kids toys that you continue to play with the specialist
They cost over $100
Because when it's aimed towards kids
The main goal is not to show off the technology that's behind it
Its 2
Use that technology
And utilize it to keep
The buyer or purchaser Entergy
Because
Cosmo had some really advanced technology
Where it was using
Multiple codes to get
A full body function over robot so that could do all these tricks
But it really do
Keep you as entertaining
Because
It was more about
Wow we figured out this Tech words
Info control everybody in it can do all the stuff and lasts about
Let's interact with that let's play with it
Hey you didn't have fun playing the cube stacking game with them I thought it was just that he didn't have enough
That was
Also part of it because in the long time run
Could not keep you that entertain because you did have some interactive things with it
But a lot of the time it was last
Let's interact with it let's
T-shirts.
Amor
Let's go over the things that learned and see
How cool they are
You guys think so much for a talk
Living in a smart home
The last year
Again
Are we don't have a choice I mean I mean our pleasure
Great
Pleasure can I have a corgi now
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news please sign up for my
I newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week