Hey
Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and Jericho
Kevin tofu
And today
We have an awesome show for you
We are going to be talking
Talking about
Actually sensors on planes
All of the AWS iot news that we have
So far
The ocf
Iot standard is now an ISO standard
And could we have crammed more accurate
I don't know we'll see when we talk about it later
Mg
We did all right we've got a new Google Assistant
Speaker
Kevin's going to talk about smart robots and Jarvis he's building his own Jarvis
And it's cute
And
We've got an update
On Amazon smart device sales that will talk to
Just to give you a sense of how the world
Does going this week we have gone to
Limerick from UL
And she's going to be talking about these cybersecurity standard that UL is developing
I have some tough questions and she mostly answer them
So all of this is sponsored by a pharaoh
You're going to hear from them
Then later and
In a few moments
So let's get the show started
With a message from our sponsor
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot
Deplatform find out why Kenmore and D-Link
The pharaoh
Affero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99% pure support calls
M10x higher activation rate
Bus
Bakery use 90% of their work from one project to the
To learn more visit a pharaoh
Dot IO
That's a f
Ero
Dot IO
Okay Kevin
Let's get this started with
Sad story
So this is really sad story
I felt like crying but it was also hugely important to talk about I felt.
Because of the iot Inc
Girls here so data from the Black Box recovered from The Lion Air flight
The crash into the Java sea
Last month
Is now available
And basically what it shows
Was that the Boeing 737
That was being
Flown
Had bad censored
Reporting bad sensor data which made the autopilot behave in
Terrible way it kept try the nose of the plane kept trying to go down in the
The pilots kept trying to
The correct it
They
Actually did
Correct it
More than two dozen times
String deflate
But
They failed to
Maintain it and
It crashed in the ocean
They actually corrected it manually
Like you said more than two dozen times within 5 minutes I'm looking at the timeline.
5 minutes
They had to fight against the automatic anti-stall system which is why the
Clean cab
Putting its nose down automatically thought the plane was
Stalling
So they're two things that I thought
We're really important here
Kevin's has got his own things that are also
So one is
The sensor data
That was causing the system
Fail
The sensor was
Reporting bad
And I think it's important
To notice that
Not just because
Why did they replace the sensor
How to replace a
But there is a lot of research right now going into malicious attacks and how to spoof
Censored
In
I think it's worth noting that there are
Things like physical attacks like
Certain frequencies of noise can
Confuse accelerometers for example
There's no evidence
This happening in this case
But you something
Researchers are looking at
And having this sensor
Report bad information
Funnel that through the system
In a way that took control of the
A plane
We have to start thinking
About those
Hack Avenue
And I talked to
Their biggest on the show Alistair Allen is
Who talked about
Reading like a truss system
4 sensor
Basically having sensors on
Our automated systems
He talks about doing it
The black sheep
Basically what would happen
When is Every sensor
The report's information
Into the system gets
Credibility
Basically like
What's this
Yes or no
In overtime the system would
Would learn
Whether or not
You can trust that
So in this case it may be that every time the
Pilot's manual
Corrected the data
Import overrode descent
And that's the system with stop
Pay attention to that sensor
That didn't happen obviously
I did not have
So that's one aspect
Does like homie iPad sensor data we need to start.
Designing for
The second element
Isabel
This was a soft
Software update
Boeing issue
And bowling basically said
When they did the software update their like
Everything is going to work the same way
Used to work
But that wasn't actually the case
To fix this error
The pilots did what they had always done
It didn't work
Boeing later issues
Correction of clarification saying that Pilots actually
How to manually take control head to do
Two additional step
When I looked at that I was like
I was frustrated because
Assume that soft
Where is just soft
But when we start letting software
Garden sensors
As the input into the real world and controlling the real world
We actually have to think about
Software
Isn't just software
It's something we could actually cause an actual event like
The plane crash like a car
Crash
In the case of a smart home
Am I allow someone into the house and I don't think
Corporations are really thinking along those lines
Just yet
How software will
And Kevin you have a Corollary
Yeah you kind of stole my thunder because this is the first thing I thought of
Is wilty this is a plane it is awful but we are seeing some progression in automated Vehicles cars
And all these threat actors and sensors all exists
Any Vehicles as well and
To totally turn over control when the systems
Maybe shouldn't have control
Or reading faulty data and therefore are basing their control based on bad information
That is a huge huge challenge
And I just
Granted a plane obviously has more passengers it's terrible how many people passed away in this
Plane crash
There's so many more cars on the road in a sense I I look at that as a bigger issue quite honestly for future
Purposes additionally unreal
Boeing response
It's like saying
All this information was in the user
Pilots flight manual
And I think they had updated the flight manual and
They follow the flight manual the Pilots Dead
But the system kept overriding their overrides and I said my question is and I asked is because when I first IT jobs with us
Software tester and
User manual
Documents are used to create user manuals for software
Who tested it
How did the test it I mean
If somebody is tested in a real plane that might be dead to right I get that but
Simulators
What is this
Tested / the manual not how do I get to work
But how does the manual say it works
And how does the manual say to proceed when it doesn't work
I want to know who Tessa that but
I'm sure we'll never find that out it's just
It's something
Has to be considered
Trinity smart system
And let's not forget that underlying
All of these issues in this is why it's so important
189 people
I mean and they died I don't know what it's like
The fall for the area
But I imagine that it's not
And so
This just drives home that we are
Putting a lot of reliance
On software
On sensors
Automated systems and I'm not saying that we should
Because I mean planes have been drive-by-wire
For decades
And there are lots of safety protocols in place but I do feel that
As we are
Pushing
More friendly
The plane automations
And drive-by-wire systems have been built
In
The vacuum it were built
Hainan airline
Regulation
Right so very safe
Where is now we've got a lot of
Companies building
Their software
Tech review
Which
Has been kind of bad breath fast and break things
And those things are colliding in a way that
We need to borrow
From that highly
Highly focused testing
Kind of world
When we start applying these things to
Cars
Airplanes
Medical device
And so on
So breaking things is fine I get that it's part of the process but not when those things are people
And maybe it's move fast and break things
In a simulator
Maybe it's an emphasis on testing
Kevin said
Maybe it's
Now it's probably an emphasis on
We should focus on
Is unfun and as not exciting
I think that's probably where we need to
Pause slow down
And take a few moments to
Get it right
Because it really matter
So that is our take
On this plane crash and
Yeah iot didn't do so well there
I don't know if it's happy
It's interesting it's interesting
So this week
User conference
Non-stop so much exciting
First up we're going to talk about a WIC
Space Network
They have a new service called AWS
Ground station which is basically
Providing you satellite
Antennas on the ground
They will work with iridium
And
You will have a satellite connection that you can buy on demand
Through AWS
Which is pretty cool
Especially if you think about for iot
Services so you could actually
Maybe you've got a connected
Okstate dog collar but you probably don't
It's a sad life her that
Attract Norm where's where's Norm
I'm going to retest with satellite to find my dog
Let's talk about container ship
Becomes an interesting option where we go
To have
12 in operation by the middle of neck
Skyr
They said they're saying that you can ingest and process your data from the satellites
Direct to AWS very cool. I am curious about the cost that because I mean we all know about
Everybody
Probably knows about iridium and how it's been a spectacular fail so far and is pivoted at 3 for different times
Which was originally going to be satellite-based phone technology
Over the cloud anywhere and there's only satellites up there
Really don't do that
They still developer
Now it's not making any money because we have great cellular network
Brightwell and you still need satellite phones for super remotely
Location
It's super expensive
For the data connection because
I can't scale relay
Is expensive
Require special
Radios
Search
Huge
There is no Moore's Law
Fitting satellite technology right now so you get these massive phones
Right
Can you set them up
ICM
Takes a second or two for that voice to travel up and carry back down
When does space
So you know
This will be an interesting
Pink
The pricing will see so also in relevant
Coyote
There's an update to security for AWS
Coyote green
Green grass is the
Service that lets you run
AWS
Beer AWS instances on
The edge
Basically
So now what you can
Can do with this is you can have connections to
Use third-party app
Location that other AWS services that are secure they're going to have Hardware root of
Trust storage
The isolation of permission settings that lets you
Basically just take
More control
And this is really important
Because there are a lot of
Enterprises
And even Industrial
Using AWS Greengrass
And
Necessary service
More secrets
Moore security
Yeah it looks like they also have another service that's
Password related it doesn't necessarily require green grass but I saw this IRT sitewise which was interesting
And
Sounds like it's a piece of
Hardware because they said there's an on-premises Gateway device.
That collects data
And far is it to AWS or further processing so then you can build representations of production lines and processes safer
Industrial iot
Yes
The big focus seems to be here on AWS
Really making sure that they have something
Industrial and
Plant cell in addition to sitewise
Which australians
They have 8.
Events that that you do iot sensors
It's scale
So that's
And then they have AWS iot
Things graph
It's basically letting you do
Locations for Edge gateways
So
It's basically like
Would I look at this and I see
Microsoft is done with
With Asher
In iot
What kind of screw this up guys cuz everybody Nancy Rio.
Hardcore
Score
Before I believe I think it's core
So this is
Play to get some of that business cuz Asher
Just owns the industrial
Because
Microsoft
And everybody in the industrial World works with Microsoft
It's hot by my bad it's not core Google I think it's core
FC
It Is Ash
Is everybody pick one and stick with it
We'll just you know pick something different in
Instead of iot Hub parkour
Function
Brain
Green grass
Skynet
Okay so those so far are the big iot related
AWS news stories out there
You also found one that you like
Yes I saw this
On the AWS news blog this is the AWS robomaker service and
You can go
That is read to you by a robot or a robotic voice if you'd like
I found a press release which is kind of cool it is a service to help develop
Simulate test and deploy the robot of your dreams Amazon says
I doubt that because they're open My Dreams or something to talk about little bit later I think this is more for heavy-duty robotics
Companies
These are packages for the robotic operating system that
People used to build robots and it supports a TV services such as Lex Polly as I just mentioned recognition
Which we talked about before the
Facial recognition
Yeah
Natural language processing
Kinesis video streams
Don't use that never heard of it
Just for videos
And Amazon Cloud
I don't either
But you can watch the clouds that's not true
But anyways because of interest in robotics I thought this was neat could we see this
Move into the iot space so I think we might and we'll talk about that in a few
Yes
Alright before we get too excited
Talk about the ocf
The open connectivity Foundation
Which is now
Holy cow you guys an ISO standard
So we talked about ocf
Before they've actually sponsored the podcast
A couple times for a special CES episode
Which by the way we're going to have again
So
These guys build
Universal standard for connected devices is there
And everything will have a data schema
And everything will be
How to talk to everything else as long as
Sports Asia
The challenge
Has been
Did they really delayed issuing
Version of the standard with security in
They recently did do that this summer
But we haven't seen a lot of devices
It support it there lots of
Companies that are involved in Asia
But we haven't seen
Devices
I don't know if
Hopeful that we'll see some this year at CES that are not just rehashes up
The old stuff
What they had
I think we will in the only reason I say that is because it's the ocf
Standard
11.0 spec that has been ratified and
They are working on two. Oh and I believe you can correct me if I'm wrong cuz I very well could be
That the two. I was back really brings more of a cloud into things
Smaller device
Abrams security
And the ability to run it
Plus
Make smaller
Not
Fletched
Smaller chips
Dumber chips for
But they're still smart they just useless
Power
Yes but they're not as
Between like
Nmcu
Andar May 7
But yes
So that's
Kind of WhatsApp
To be inside
ISO standard I just thought was interesting because you know
ISO is actually a very legitimate very powerful standards organization
And
The fact that they ratify this is
Probably
It means
Basically if
I so want it could develop a standard that didn't
Appraise ocf
And if it does then everyone has to do it
Ocf is pivoted someone
On the smart
Home Space 2
To focusing on
Automotive
Medical device
Standards
So
That might be I don't see this impacting the smart that much if at all
It used to be very smart
Home focused in a lot of the companies that are involved are smart
They have
Home Appliance devices like LG Huawei
Samsung
So but they're all using other things and there's such a big audience already for the Eastside
I don't know
Okay
So
But since we're talking about I so we should talk
Hey they just actually ratified a drill stand
Is not crazy
Set of standards for drone operations this draft
21st of January and they're expected to be adopted later
Some of the things that are in there
Are no fly zones so drones won't fly into airplanes
That's a big deal
It also talks about
Like sensitive
Locations
Yeah they could actually shut your drone down if it comes within a certain geofence area for example
And actually in the USA law was
Allows the government
To shut down
Drones
That is actually
A little bit
Controversial because it's unclear
What areas might be deemed too sensitive so you could see something
Very good reason exam
Trying to
Fly a drone over the tornado
Camps where they're keeping the
Undocumented
Children
The government may be like you know what media I don't want you looking at
To close it that
And they could just shoot those down which would be
That's a different story
We're going to want some clarity in that law
Probably
It talks about
Flight logging
Training maintenance requirements so that would be
Really useful cuz I don't know how often you've been hit in the head by a drone but it's happened to me once it was
I haven't been you know I hope to never hit anybody because I had to register mine with the FAA so they would know what it was
My hair for a week
Not that I didn't think this was a big deal because it is but this surprise me
Currently the head of the UK's air safety board
It said that half of air traffic incidents now involve drones
Is
Surprising
Cuz that's a lot but I also
Recall unit
The firefighters not recently in California
Probably last year's firefighters talked about like they had to stop helicopter flights because drones were in the way
Siri call Dad
This is shared airspace
We got to figure this out
All right
Sogo ISO
Working on that if you have comment
You should tell them
Let's talk now
Let's talk now about a new Google Assistant speaker
Just came out of nowhere I did not expect it but then again
Pretty much any speaker these days it's on the market anybody's making them
I'm betting they're coming out with models that have
A microphone and some smart sync connectivity cuz that's what
Klipsch has done
They make high-end speakers they have for years and years
Eclipse
The three now has Google assistant and being a high-end speaker system it'll cost you 409
$9
Which is an awful lot for a smart speaker but
If you
Want that mid-century modern design and
Pig sound
I know
There you go last minute
No cuz I'm not an audiophile I always like
Does it sound okay
I'm not an audio file for say cuz my hearing is starting to go but I do
Like
Good speakers you know I'm not going to get this because I don't like
Good speakers under $500
So is your
What qualifies
Just a good speaker in your
What's your favorite
Good sounding speakers the best sounding speakers in my house are the Sonos
Call my dad
Which still still has not Google Assistant which we mention I'm thinking the last podcast it's not happening
Hopefully early 2019
He'll let us know
Oh I will
Okay
Speaking of assistance we should talk about Amazon because
They put out a press release
Talk about
There
Turkey five
Black Friday to Cyber Monday which day
Turkey 5 holiday
We will turkeys turkey from now it's not a thing don't make it if you don't ever be a thing Amazon
We're not on board
What's that but
We are on board with
Finding out
You know and just do this with a big heavy load of salt
Which is Amazon's press releases are notorious for not actually
Real information
Astounding
They give information but it's nothing compared to because they're not providing that extra bit that we give you the comparison
So let's see but they did say
That
They sold
A lot of echo dots the best selling products at
The Amazon pop-up device
Kiosk
Over here is that where it's at
35 weekend
So basically Thanksgiving
Black Friday
That weekend and then
Cyber Monday
It was the echo Dot
In the Amazon smart
Which
By the way
Was on sale
25 bucks
Was crazy cheap
Sounds great
And it's sold out
Which is
Amazing
And I saw a
A tweet
From Ryan
Ramallah
Who is a voice first kind of
Person
I don't know how else to describe
He's an expert there but he said
The source
Told him
Did the sales of the echo Dot
More than a thousand units
Hersey
Witches
It is
And just we can put some minor perspective around this
Because Amazon said that
Customers ordered
180 million items about those five days obviously they were not I'll.
Of course not
But the best selling
Products
Cyber Monday for example
What's the new Echo Dot
As fate was in the kiosks as you said
So the only kind of idea they gave us on
Total sales for Echo devices was Millions sold worldwide
And that the all new Echo dot was the number one
Selling price on Amazon globally from manufacturer in any category
We know they sold 180 million items and they sold millions of
Echo devices
We don't know how many millions obviously less than 180
Yes which is still
Other things
The ring video doorbell 2
Makes sense
But they also sold the iRobot Roomba 690
Robot vacuum
That is not the one that actually Maps
Your data and can send it to your
Google Assistant
They sold a lot of TP Link mini Wifi smart plug
And the Amazon smart plug
This is part of hopefully the mainstreaming of the smart
So yay
All right
Let's see what else do
Speaking of Amazon
And the robots that we were talking about it is now time
To talk about Kevin's
Tri Merle.
Well
The next thing on my
Want less I guess so
This is not mainstream are going from mainstream to just what Kevin wants but I think
Other people will want
They just don't know it yet
Yes
Wait before you
One day
YouTube
I want an iPad mini and guess what
They did
People don't realize that but that's another story
Anyway
So I mentioned vector
The little robot from Anki that I had bought in October last month
He's gotten some software updates he is much
More expressive
That's the new thing for him was when it's
It's cold outside on the weather when it's below a certain amount
Please got another update coming and this one gets me really excited not just for the near future but the
Faraway 5-year future
He is getting
Amazon's matinee integration
And
The funky folks shared a video
Of
What it looks like and how it works
Because you don't have to ask
Vector to ask Madame a something
Nature's literally at Amazon
Echo device for all intensive purposes with this update
Is coming in a few weeks and I'm super excited to get it
It made me think about though is and I proposed to
Earlier this week
For people who are familiar with the Iron Man movies which I suspect most people are you know about
Jarvis
If you're not familiar Jarvis is basically a
Bodiless digital assistant just like matinee
Eventually becomes
Put into a synthetic body and he's a robot in a sense is real
Yeah you're right
Geek cred for you
Oh my God was that a spoiler
No not well it is for the Age of Ultron as well being
What I saw with the doctor and Madame a integration and then
In reality and then the movie where and digital assistant becomes a movable object
I'm thinking
Why do we want all these speakers and microphone throughout the house okay speakers yes we want to music
Do we need all these microphones I literally have more
Smart speakers than I have rooms in my house right now and I just bought another one I just bought a Google home hub over the holidays for the kitchen I'll
Silence we can watch YouTube TV or coffee
But I'm tired of buying them and quite honestly
It doesn't make sense in the long run
Why not have
Movable object I a robot
That can definitely humanoid is enough to be enlarged
It is a bit bigger than Vector because Vector only lasts 45 minutes on a charge but just had that microphone near me when I want to
Near me
Robot go stand in the corner I'm going to watch Ironman for the 10th time
Whatever you know what I mean because it takes away a lot of the Privacy things now
Because you can be a way you can be in a room that doesn't have a microphone or camera Decker as cameras I presume
Robot like this would have cameras to
Yeah I can go into the non robot and do my thing and be private and then still have the robot within earshot and I can say
What's the weather or whatever I want
Thomas Martin
I don't know I know it's a radical idea I never most my ideas so I can use a radical and some of them actually come true
And I like the idea
Like following me around
And you know
Hanging out doing things
Look it over in
Imagine like a Sony aibo like a little robot dog
Having yes
Oh my gosh
That would be so fun
I do think Mobility will add a lot
To this experience I don't know that everybody is ready for the right now and I can't that
You know the update on the smart speakers have been ridiculously fast and granted
I love my pretty inexpensive fat it certainly helps
I don't know I think there's a lot of value I didn't mobile virtual assistant such as this
There are privacy
Questions about this
If it's something that can
Can follow you around you to lose elements
Privacy Law
Like if you only want your digital assistant in certain play
Places but I guess you could say
The kitchen
Having dinner with my wife in candlelight dinner
I think that's manageable it's more manageable than it is now these speakers are just there
I have one of my back
Gervais get out of the bathroom
Slave
I'm going I didn't want to be
Future from
Kevin
Let's answer some questions
From Riot podcast
Which by the way is sponsored by Schlage
And guys
Do not miss your chance to win a Schlage
Connect smart deadbolt
Which now
Comes in as a certified version that will work with Amazon
Key Program
You can upgrade your smart home
What the safety Simplicity and style of
Schlage
And if you want to be entered to win
Who is call us at 5 1/2
XVI
742 4
This month's drawing will end November 30th
At midnight Eastern
Give us a call before then
We can only ship them to the US
Canada
So sorry rest of world
It's a great lock
I like it
And
Now
Let's hear our voice mail who is
From somebody
But I'm guessing they're from the south
Just like me
Stacy Kevin how y'all have a question regarding
Using the most
Current
Intelligence which is but in an old building
Helping my daughter and son-in-law do some updating and their new house
And he wanted to automate a couple switch location
Today they're using Madame age connected direct Outlets
So Gateway
Stinky shoes I understanding this
Building was built and we're guessing the
60s
This wiring it is two conductors no neutral
And that's just about every other ladies Racing shirt
A suggestion for wall switches
We could use an old house
Thanks for being so nice in the right direction
Oh this is such a common question
Unfortunately for you I have
Literally want ants
Because it is the only one
So the only option they have
Is a dimming switch
From Lucia
And you will find this it is
Lutron caseta switch
Which it is model number
TD
-
6w
CL
And there's going to be another
Series after that that's going to denote color in this case it is
6wcl - wh
That's white
It comes in Black
Almond
Some of their
So this is a
$55 switch
But it does not require
It does however require
The Lutron
Stop the smart Bridge hub
And that
Right now
Is $117 sometimes I see it on sale for as low as 80
This is ratehub
And if you're going to buy a Lutron switches
This Hub is going to be
Your best friend
Makes it compatible with Madame a show at the Amazon Echo
The Google Assistant ecosystem and even home
So
It is a hub
But it's a really useful
And it's going to work with all of your switch
This particular switch does not require neutral wire it says so very clearly so make sure you do see those
The downside of this
I just called you to switch it's actually
Is if
If you don't have dimmable bulbs this isn't good
So for example if you have a fluorescent bulb
You're not going to be able
To use it
And
That is
Frustrating
And I
They used to have a switch that didn't require neutral wire now they do not
And I suspect that these aren't going to be around that much longer I'm not saying
Days are weeks but I don't know about that
Keeps them on their website they talk about it being a perfect option for
An older home
So I don't know
Which year there's obviously there's plenty of older homes out there
It's only words
Dimming lights I mean it does have an on-off two buttons one for almost four off at the top and bottom
Turn off the dimmer in the middle so
If you use a dimmer though with
Incompatible lights
Liquor in
Yes
I was just thinking you're saying this is a dimmer which it is but it could be used as a switch
Only on lights to the caveat is
Your lights have to be
You can't put non dimmable lights with this
I did not know that
Yes I have done that
I have not
Obviously
Don't do that
So that is the caveat if you have weird if you have normal
So
Dimmable LED
I think like lights that won't work or fluorescence
Halogen light
So
Those are going to be a little bit more difficult
But normal lights
Yay
That's my
Are you so easy answer
It is expensive but
I recommend Lutron lights
Everybody who asked me
If they're installing switches I know it's expensive
These lights are
They just work
The work well
And the Lutron support is amazing
Also
I know you guys know I love
How do you spell
For this case it is literally the only option so
Problem solved
Okay
Well that brings us to the end of the News segment
Of the show and now
We're going to be
To our guests who is
Honda limerick
From ul and we're going to be talking about the UL cybersecurity standard
Gosh where is it
Why does it cost so much
What are you guys trying to do
You will like this especially if
Like standards and certifications it who does it
Get started with this but first
A word from our sponsor
Everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a
And I've got Joe Britt who is the CEO of a pharaoh here to talk to
So first off would you reminder audience who afero is
Fair was fundamentally
A platform for connecting all kinds
Sensors and devices to the cloud but the most important
Vocero is that
We put together everything just works
And we also feel like
It's very
Design
Easy to use
And very very secure
And our customers tell us that it's
The best choice for great end user experience
And developer
Productivity
You may remember that many of us out of pharaoh came for
From places like apple nest
Google Android Netflix
And we really wanted to bring the best of those engineering and Design District
To the world of iot
Excellent so who are some of your customers and why do they pick up
Customers like hemorrhoid
D-Link chose a pharaoh really because of three key reasons
Time to Market
They can cut down their development Time by as much as 80%
Technology reuse
Their Engineers are able to reuse over 90% of their work from Project to project
For example
Kenworth connected more than
The 25 Appliance
In less than 2 years
And finally custom
Experience
Our partnership founded
The Pharaohs substantially increases the number of devices that are actually connect
Thanks to our onboarding technology
And substantially
Reduces the number of conductivity related
Customer support calls
So what is new since the last time
Time we talked
Great Wolf
I'd like to highlight
To really excited
The first is around our patent port
Few weeks ago we were identified as having the
V large
Just patent portfolio in the iot space
Find large companies like Samsung Qualcomm
Intel and IBM
Now this is a really huge test
Funny to the quality of the engineering talent that a pharaoh has a
But it's also a test
To the market
Get Gap that existed for a fully integrated and secure iot platform
Are patent portfolios
Reflection
Of the benefits that are custom
Get by using the affair of platform
End
What about this Bank of things
We've also been doing some really inspiring work
Work with Mitsubishi ufj Bank
And this is fundamentally about enabling
Billions
Of tiny micro Tran
Micropenis
Through smart devices all kinds of
The project is called Bank of
Because
It marries iot with banking
And also really lays the
Groundwork
4 things to pay each other
Directly
Sarah provide CIA
Party platform
A Mitsubishi Bank provides
The payment processing
And this kind of solution demands very secure conductive
And very secure payment processing with minimum over
Each device
Then becomes its own payment
There's no need for the traditional paint
Terminal is an add-on device you get insta
Step response
Highscalability
Reliable operation
Low overhead
Payment Processing
And all of this has to be there to create this
Very unique solution
That sounds really cool so where can
Can people go to find out more information
Dot IO
Flash
Go - big
Is the best place to start
If you're a developer
You can also see.
Developer.
Arrow. IO
And make sure to just check out all the resources
We have on a pharaoh. IO
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And I have with me Don't Tell Em bury
Who is the senior business
Development manager
4 Cypress
Security at UL
How are you doing
Aggressive
See how are you
Excellent
So I'm excited about this because
I actually when I
Purchase many of my products including all of my connected Outlets I look for that UL certification just to make sure my house
So excellent work there and you guys have
Since
Oh I don't know a couple years ago we've been talking about
An iot
Security standard
So talked about
Why you all decided to get into this
Game
Like you outside
In the face ego names
Sunday making sure your car can catch fire
When you think about your product that using your home as many products have Network
Connectivity
Device
TV
Your door lock
Baby monitor
And that actually rings
Additional risk
Safety razor
Security
To ask you out what are you guys doing to protect us from these new risks
That's why we have been trying to engage with industry
Around security thinking about security requirement
Cabana some of these security risks that have been
Paramount life
For example
Losing control of your device
Having someone reached your data
And related types of risk
So that's where we have gotten involved as physical product
Senior home
Computers Network connectable products
We want to network with industry I'm with consumerism smart homeowners
Managing director
Associated with those products
Okay so there is a little bit of a
Prince here historically if you follow the rules of various physical
Sex right so if I want to create an outlet
PetSafe I have to follow set rules about you know the amount of voltage that goes through that sort of thing
Testing
In the product stays relatively the same but will be start connecting things to the internet
It almost becomes a
Impossible 2
Secure it because things on the internet
Always changing software is always going out
So how do you guys think about
That because that is
At the core of iot security that seems to be
Biggest issue
Extremely relevant
Indeed speaking about your products
Check your TV that's no longer
Screams with a wire
It's actually a software and most of its functionality
Mannix
Add your TV product level
The cloud sofa
Services
It's no longer Hardware itself and then the risk
Scenarios
You think about it
Scenarios they evolve over time but they are more
Static
How to break into
The combination of on the one hand
Same-day auctions
Warm or suffer and suffer and be updated
What is manic
At the public library
Science
And how we help industry
Ready Set Go
Email leaving the factory
That's where I stopped caring about it
You know it has to be
Miami Heat Reddit shooting turn left and that's where you all need to step up and help
Ultimately
Society as well
What does ongoing
Insurance that products are being used
So that implies a continuous
Testing process
So something like more like a nice so kind of standard
Approved and then you go back in every now and then they come in and
Certify you again or make sure that
Up-to-date so is that something that you all has done in the pasture does
The plan to do this
For the cyber security program
Want to be nimble to
Customers needs
To be a enabler to business and to maintain a
The quality of products in the past we have collaborated
What industry to make it happen.
Calibration
Has gone beyond
So let's talk about
The broad Strokes of what you guys are thinking about when you talk about coyotes
Security what is the program
That we have done a few things are actually has
A lot of experience and also strong reputation in markets that are currently
Redlands I mean there is
Standards that have options and adoption
Credit cards
End-to-end security requirements
Secure process
Credit card
All of that is secure
Internet of things not just your credit card
Fendi everything
That you use a life
Is becoming a digital electronic product
Michigan eat
All of those products and communication from those products to
Networks
Ecosystem
My building
100 standard
Which is aiming for a high level of soccer
Security Assurance testing
To think about how come
Security do you envision a company having to get WL certification so if I'm making a connected
Kitchen product for example
Fire safety kind of aspects but then I'm also going to possibly need a
Cyber security
Certifications
What is that look like for a company that's like
It's going to cost too much
Feeling of course you want to avoid to the extent possible
Products need to be
Celtic Woman
Companies
See it that way and I call you
Security includes
Wireless connection
The cloud
Products for today is
There's no such thing as one
Do you want to work with
Customers and Industry as much as we can as a one-stop-shop
Different elements
Performance
Wireless connectivity
Interoperability
Manufacturer
The care about the brand
I'm going to Market with a
Level of quality and they see you getting there
Let's run down some security features and let's see where they fit into the UL scheme so this will be kind of quick and short
Hopefully so in corruption
Necessary
Where
Very important
For example you think about day that other thing, decayed it's from a product
Example of a IP camera security camera
Is protecting a building
Tamarack sheep
Is sensitive
Information and if it's traveling from the camera
To some clouds environmental environment
Stanley should be able to intercept today that has a hacker and get access to the
Good Life cheats
For example.
Coccidiosis
That is data that ideally you encrypt
When you communicated from the device
Okay what about encryption of data at rest
On the cloud
Very important as well
Addressed in the cloud or data at rest in the device sensitive data you should be considering
Adequately
Program Spencer
Data protection data at rest
Think about
Spy Store on a server
What about password
Default passwords on devices
That's what's important actually useful password those are not the greatest security practice so I having you
Sports is important
Okay over the air updates
Critical as well to maintaining overall Total Quality seokjin able remote software update
She's going to be very important making that very secure
Is going to be open
Clear privacy policy
Critical as well
Degrassi kind of go hand-in-hand
Some more and more data
Used in devices and also and devices pick up user-specific data
Devices you need to give up some of your data in most of the cases.
Your username
Or your name the general
It's very important that has you interact with devices and with iot that those data architect
Clearview holiday.
I'm Sedaris a responsible policy
Okay what are some things I missing
What else is
Important
That I don't know about
Do you mention encryption
Oh yeah update
Privacy
DDOS security
You hit the major must haves
Security items
In general when you think about software
One thing that is important
Considered as well as whatever functionality you enable with it if you want to protect yourself or adequately
Any insecure functionality
Albuquerque accident
Grenadine in the right way
Operate a certain function and if it's not needed
Why am I enabling
For example remote
And maybe have a mindset
Disabled and stops Networks
Security in general even though it maybe
It's still important
To consider and it will remain important
Lansing Social Security office and forms and devices you can consider
Whatever
Device is your navel make sure they're behind a router or a firewall
And I think about Network segmentation
So do you want your computer for example to be linked
Are connected to the same network as your device
Maybe you should apply some smart
Organize your device
That is something that I think about but I'm very curious because
That is not something my company's
Who I'm buying the products
Tell me to do so that feels like not something
It feels out of the UL Lane
Is that
Increasingly though when you buy these smart Spotify
Devices there should be Industries user guide
Insecure Protocols of protocols being used
How to
Example use your router together with the product to make sure that it's not recording session is still secure
I look forward to that okay
When did criticism of UL
Is that in order to
See the standard you have to pay to get a copy of the license
Which makes it really difficult
For companies to evaluate
Program
And I'm curious how you guys
Like when I talk to the security Community they're like well I don't know if it's
Straight or not I don't want to buy it
So how do you address that kind of
Need for transparency and security with your business motto
That's a good question
Dennis r u l i p where they're also belong to the community so typically like
Standard
Requirements and working with industry in the way
General Studies
Okay and when should we see a finalized version of this
Do you want a 900 as a standard and design to it
So we gained some traction with that program with that standard and addressing it security
Security number of various products
And embarrassing
Stop there
So when you really think about it you know adoption
Security in a
Scalable way
I really want to work with in this
Leveraging industry programs
Example of
Program
We Are One
Drive adoption of the program
Then Amazon
Example
Building Alder Alexa
System they care about device
With Alexa and the security of those devices
Speaker devices for example we work with Amazon to test those devices
Industry initiatives to get to gradle
Windows
And we also proceed you know developing multiple programs that can really comfortable wide
Variety
Products that manufacturers
Centaur building
Security Insurance on Baseline all the way up to
Hirelevel
Security assurance
Okay so if I wanted to look for a
UL certified cyber
Secure
Product so if I'm working with my echo devices or something like that I should be looking for
UL 2900
Yes currently that's or certification program so you can find any you want to know how much
Certification database and then
Including collaboration within the
Awesome alright we'll come to thank you so much for coming on the show today
For sure
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter
Stacey on iot