Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Rocket ship
Man self-driving cars
Spaceport
Lawsuits
Moore security
Holiday II Plus
News 4
Logitech bricking a device
Send a voicemail from one of our lives
We have a message from our sponsor
Sparkcognition
And
Our Guest this week is Grant Erickson who is the head of the
The red group
Talking about
News
On the spec
You're going to want to stay tuned for this
It's not what you think people
But first
Other word for my
ATT
Home isn't just a place
It's a feeling the feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most
Weather for your home or business ATT helps keep you safe so you can feel protected Wherever You Are
Introducing the ADT Security starter kit everything you need to get started with ADT Pulse including a camera
Professionally installed for only $49 visit att.com today to learn more
Requires a 36-month monitoring contracts installation and activation fees apply enrollment qsp in ezpay
Acquired certain markets are excluded licenses available at att.com
001 121 Louisiana Ave
1:6
3 9
Okay Kevin
What started off with
Self-driving
It's so funny you said minivans because all the people talking about the new waymo self driving taxis are like hey if you want to be a sock
Your mom just jump in the waymo van cuz
Girl Vans I'm kind of surprised
Cuz you don't make sense for you no
Taxi
Because she can get more people
Look at you
Can get all kinds of stuff plus minivans have these awesome features for self-driving cars which is the doors opening
Close on their own
Right right right right
That's very true and in fact we're talk about the Phoenix area and waymo and their self-driving taxis
Of course and we talked about this before but they're actually kind of live now which is kind of
Crazy you can literally within a hundred square miles of Phoenix
Fast travel in a waymo self driving minivan
For now
There will or maybe a waymo person
There is a waymo person
In the van with you
However they may not sit in the driver's seat you may have nobody in that driver seat
Is what waymo is saying
So it's pretty cool I think and I think it's really smart that they're doing it where they're doing it
For a couple reasons
Why don't people realize that but just outside of Phoenix
In the area of Mesa there's a massive driving test track
That has been there for like 30-40 years
Now there's like they're building solar panels and stuff there but the track is still there for testing so
A lot of companies use that it would not surprise me if waymo use that early on but now they're obviously in the city
And that environment that
Topography the weather it's all I perfect place and I tweeted out the store yesterday Stacy and somebody said
Well this isn't that challenging Phoenix is just a grid
It's flat as dry I'm like but that's what you want to start you don't want to start with the most
Challenging
Garments yeah yeah I mean
I think it's actually a very wise choice
For waymo to do this in the Phoenix area because it is very grid-like
Streets it is very flat
So
It gives them their foot in the door here so
This is I think this is level for driving as soon as not quite level 5 but
That's pretty darn close
It is it's one number away
I was going to say that it is smart that they still have a person in the car and suddenly I realized that
Holy cow if there isn't a person in the car eventually will have to develop systems for preventing vandalisation
Vandalism
So we'll have to
Figure out a way
Play scarves are cameras everywhere
Yeah and I guess you'll have a credit card UK
They'll just lock the doors and pull over until the police come
And other Automotive
News
Has partnered with NASA
It's not autonomous
But it is a filet
This is just a fun little
Video willing
I don't have a
I have to say after I mean the video that people should watch this basically
It's almost like the fast pass line at Disney World literally would
Scan your phone for barcode with Uber you request an Uber air whatever
Can you go up
To the top of a building where maybe they have today helipad and stuff
Enter these
Small little things like glider planes
Is what they're envisioning
And they have propellers that would
Tilt horizontally and vertically so they
Takeoff
Vertically
And then drive or fly you wherever you need to go
And it's interesting they say they're theorizing that you could go from
The LAX to the Staples Center in 10 minutes in one of these things as opposed to an hour and a half
Driving your car
So
Huge Time Savings and all that there is actually a pilot in the Drone like
Vehicle
It got me thinking
It's only a matter of time once they get this off the ground no pun intended
That they do this autonomously as well
And that's going to be a bigger challenge than autonomous vehicles because now you have a whole nother
Dimension of
You know up and down and
What not so
I just think it's worth watching is my
Okay I will keep watch
I will keep watching the skies
All right
Outside of car news
We have some exciting news
God we're going to talk about
Home Security
So here goes
We've got a couple story
Ring and ADT
Fake news
End of last week
ATT was granted a temporary injunction
Against rain
So when can no longer sell its ring protect
Product
Because
And this goes all the way back to March when
Ring hired
Almost everybody from Zona
And
As part of that
Was like the security system yeah we have gone off but
Zone of had taken
Funding
Alone from ATT and also was working with ADT to develop a smart home
Security system
ATT so ATT was like
Turn off that you just kind of sort of took with you because all these people that work for a ring
That's ours
And the judge basically
Agreed with ADT and that's why this temporary injunction
What is
Scary face
Users or perhaps a great deal of people seem to be really excited about it ring basically said if you ordered one of our
Products
Ring protect
What's going to happen is
Ring is going to offer you a $50 promo code that you can use towards any ring doorbell or outdoor camera as well
Well is an additional $100 off
Ring protect once it's re-release
Sell this injunction went in place before ring actually got any product out the door right
Yeah cuz I'm just thinking if I ordered one before and Ashley
Got it
Can I still supported do I have to send it
It's probably a very small number if any
I got out there but what terrible timing we're going to the museum
Shopping season of the year here in the US and I'm sure some people going to buy security systems
No they don't make great stocking stuffers I just received
Okay then how's your smile
This is true and the pricing
Get this was a $199 system if I recall correctly.
So that's also going to appeal to people who may not want to pay
For 500 more
Yeah
So this is big this is sad
Will cibor also
In the security space
This is a super hot area right now
We've got pricing came out for nest sonesse launched
Nest secure
The couple weeks ago and it is 499
I think it's two sensors The Hub
And to text activate the Hub
Arm and disarm the system
So they launched that and they also said that they would offer a monitored security
Package
And lo and behold
Now they do
And it's kind of pricey
Yeah and it's also
Separate from the
Nest aware subscription if you pay for that so if you already paying nestegg IM $10 a month
Nest aware for your nest cam that's totally separate going to keep paying. So they're working with Mony Mony or money
I don't know
Capital m o n
Yeah I know the second largest
Security monitoring company in the country last I checked so they're huge they also sell their own security systems
Similar to an ATT and so on and they have obviously monthly packages I'll give you the hardware for free and so on
Obviously with nest
You're not getting the harbor for free but the monitoring is optional
And you can pay
2499 a month if you commit to a three year plan
Or you can pay 3499 a month
On a month-to-month basis with no plan and I just find that super super high because again you're paying for the hardware
Right so
You know maybe give the nest
Oway and do the
Obviously that's not what next wants
To do so if it's just
Nest has
Just hold me in the past
Sit there still very delicate
Heated to their DIY
And the DIY people may not want one
Monitored security
Sure
So I think that's kind of
Nest also now
This is a little
I don't know if Nest is being actively
Part of this but Nest now works with security systems
I'm a company car
Call notion
Innotion actually makes a really interesting system
It is
Set of sensors and then a bridge
And they're $0.05
Plus a bridge
That's $300
And the sensors are really interesting they're cute little circles that you just stick anywhere and they measure things like
Vibrations of the
Tell if your doors open
How close they measure temperature they can do Leak Detection they can do a lot of things and so now what they do is they all
Also can detect they work with the nest so if you're
Door is open in your air conditioning
I'm not sure if it'll let you arm and disarm
Based on
Presence detection
Turn The Nest Thermostat
Which would be Tycoon
But it's yet another Wrinkle in the
Security world
It's good to have the integration I mean that more Generations are always better in my opinion so that's good
I hadn't seen this before I'm looking at it now it almost looks like a plastic August lock
It's smaller
And their peel and stick
It is
Pretty much as they use a proprietary version of 802. 15. 4 which is zigbee
I know I thought
You almost lost me at bridge but now you're really lost
Proprietary
It makes sense you can't have a battery-powered sensor
That doesn't mean
You can't have a wife
That's just great
That's just
That's the
But we also have
Almond
The Almond router switch many people may not be aware of there by a company called securifi that actually all the way back
Back in like 2000
11 mm 12 was launching mesh router
Because every
The way routers work
It's terrible so they were like super early in the
They now
I have created
Security package
That
It has some sensors in it it works with the mesh routing system they
Long had a security offering
Are they have for the last year had a security offering
For ten bucks a month
He basically
Have a router that works with sensors
From this company and
So I'm like
That's yet another wrinkle
Yeah and I said I could see more of this
Jack built into routers
You know it's like so almond actually did the Almond routers when they launch they had like a
An LCD screen in the Next Generation had all these radios
They're pretty good and then now the
End the latest version
It's the almond
3s route
The third router plus that stands for security
It has a battery it has a SIM slot for cellular backup
And it has all these great
I lied to you it's
Professional emergency Mana
Is $20
And if you I guess do it
Through the Indiegogo the secured
There you go cool stuff from them I
Just like their products so
Always worth a look if you are like a security maybe I also need a mesh router
Why not
Now
Moving outside this
Let's go to Congress
Edit security-related Act
Because we're talking about
New legislation that was introduced in the Senate
And the house
Call the Cyber Shield Act of 2017
I haven't seen the actual legislation Norton space I don't think you have either so we have a write-up on it and I think it's a good
Step it
Does a lot of teeth
Two at a sickly
They're talking about setting up a voluntary program so that device makers can choose to have their products evaluated
And certified for meeting certain benchmarks on Cyber and data security
They got the right buzzwords in there but there's too many qualifiers such as a voluntary and Ken
Choose
And so on and so forth
It's going to take time to get these Benchmark settings put together
You're looking at a couple years before I think anything really
Happens here if it
At all quite honestly
Yes the legislation basically sets up
The committee
Hey Kennedy
Over a period of 2 years to set bench
Parks for cyber security
Yay long time
And then one size benchmarks are enacted
It's voluntary
Yeah so it feels like
Let's talk about iot security without actually doing anything
To dress what is really actually a quite
Two plus two to three years from now the landscape will be very different anyway so
Tentative
Figure this out the next three to six months in my opinion
Yeah, this isn't going to do anything
We should talk about
Decipher
Because this week there been a bunch of reports
About cyber secure
From a bunch of
So in the newsletter I will highlight a bunch of these
Because there are so many
But the big things to take away
I think are pretty simple
The first thing to understand is
What's happening is there active groups targeted
Industrial
Systems so these are your skater these modbus all these old school industrial system
Running power plants
Yes nuclear plants
Dams
Manufacturing
All of this so these are all being targeted which is not actually news but
What is worth noting
Is that most companies right now
Are still under the belief that things like air gapping their Network
Works
Not only is air gapping not enough
The Based on data coming
Cyber X
There's a lot of unpatchable stuff
They're so
According to the survey more than three out of four sites have obsolete Windows system
Yeah this is actually a big
Ideal hospitals have
Gotten
Ding by this when they're
An upgradable machines like MRI machines
Windows operating
Systems which is best five things like XP in 2000 things that are not really supported anymore
They also have
Crappy passwords
It's nearly three out of five sides
Have plain text passwords traversing their control Network
No no no u
I know you think those networks aren't online but people can get to them and they can be sniff
And
Half half
At least one unknown
Or Rogue device and 20% have wireless access
Points that
Are unknown
And you don't want your wireless access point
Because anything that
Connects to them will be vulnerable
So say I think anybody's implementing the system just needs to binge watch mr. robot and
I think they'll get a kick in the pants right there
There we go so really you guys if
You have
Automated systems
Monitoring systems
You feel like they're secure
You should probably
Double check
Statuses
Target got hacked
This way it was
Let us
So that's all the bad news
About 4
Z saber
Front
Let us move to
A giant M&M
As an Old Ship reporter I was
Really
Excited is not the word
Kind of ostrich
At the idea that broadcom
Offered
This week
Hey
100 in
Pie five
Billion dollars
Billion with a B
To acquire
Qualcomm this is an unsolicited takeover
Offering
70 bucks per share
And
This isn't the middle of
Broadcast
Trying to buy Brocade
After it said it would move it
Back to the US
And in the middle of
Qualcomm
Trying to finish its massive deal
Nxp
Yeah this is huge
Broadcom is a
Big player just in a different way than
Qualcomm broadcom Zamora verb Bluetooth Wi-Fi
Very low-power type chip
So here's
We all think of broad
Tom is one company but really it's not that
So broadcom that Kevin's talking
Is a Bluetooth
Powerhouse components and all sorts of
The phone spot
Couple years ago it was acquired by a
Which was created by a private-equity
The pot hp's Agilent
So this is like super embedded
Detailed stuff and then they bought a bunch of network
Alyssa
Plx
Please crazy ethernet
Storage Network
Working all kinds of stuff
So what we call broadcom
Today
Is actually a mishmash of a
Bunch of really deep cut
Conant level
In networking
Right foot
When we say networking level
What I think broadcom gets out of this but it doesn't have today and you can tell me if I'm wrong
Qualcomm modem business is huge
And not just for phones
I'm also thinking ahead to like
Capital M and
NB iot and such so
Art person
Respective
I think this would be a huge win for blood
Yes it would it would get its communication stuff so the bass Man in the Moon
Right
Also gets the Qualcomm
Application processor
Rich
Broadcom when it was
Actually Brad, Nut Bra
Avago actually was talking about doing
Arm-based servers and some really interesting and they had application processors to we should
Desperate
This is a deal that would basically
The new broadcom
Qualcomm
In every single phone
In the world
Iot devices
So it's
Pumpkinhead
Huge deal
The broad, Clayton she said there may not be known for their application processors
But they have them for sure I mean the Raspberry Pi 3
Runs on a beach
Township so
But you know it's not a new space for them but it would greatly expand the capabilities and reach of that
Yeah I mean Qualcomm is
Their application processors are the creme Dela
Yes Man unless we're talking about Apple's application process
That is
That deal
I wrote a bit about it
Include a link
Put out a newsletter alert
Because I thought it was such a
And
So we'll see what happens
We'll have some ship drama
And now
Let's move to
Holiday iot
Because
Why not
Amazon has been
Partying hard it did a great deal for
Lutron devices I think was 120 bucks got you
Hub the Lutron hub
Two of the switches
And
To the little Pico room
Switch that basically threw in the hub for
$80 value so that was actually a smoking hot deal
I believe the SmartThings Hub is now 50
2% off for Black Friday
Beyond are going to be doing deals on the Amazon Echo all the answers
Hardware and
Released
Is there a news
Which has a nest cam
Call for a hundred
30 bucks that's one of the doorbusters
They also are going to do an echo.
30 bucks the new version
A little shorter
$80
Brighten up the place with the Hub
And then fo-sho for a hunt
By the way the Echo Show release
Really sad
My daughter told me no because she likes looking at she plays music on it she like seeing who
Did the song in the
And personally like
It's not worth that much money
What's 220 bucks that keep your kid happy
I don't know about you but I think it's a lot
So those are the big Smart Home
Deals for
Hargett
Okay
Like I wear a Fitbit
But not everybody
He'll be more will have probably more of this next coming shows I have left
Oh yeah
IJustine
In case you're like who I want to buy one of these things
Now you can
Okay
Let's move this show right along
It might be a good time to update your Logitech Harmony remote to
Well so this is not the harmony this is the Logitech Harmony
Link
Vegas
I don't know if you want to update to Harmony maybe should get like a Chromecast and
Google Home Fire TV
Anime
Logitech is
Ricky
D
Logitech
Harmony link which is a device that you can buy
About seven years ago and it
Was it basically converted your IR signals
To WiFi
So this is not the harmony home hub that was introduced a little bit later and connect to madame
But plenty of people did buy this device in Logitech base
Basically said you know what
Guys in a couple months
We're going to send a software update and it's gone
Poopy heads
I don't know what else to say I mean it I said the Stacy before the show or talk about this these guys are not doing themselves any favors in order they do
In the industry any favors here
How to get back to that question I keep asking are you buying Hardware are you buying services
In this case you can keep your hard work it just going to be used
Servu
I won't do anything and I sort of don't understand why they're doing it with this particular product because
It's nothing more unless I'm missing something
Then it rich to convert wifi-to-ir
I'm assuming they don't want to keep
Hoarding
The software
Logitech sent email to the link
On March 16th 2018
Logitech will discontinue service and support for the link it will no longer function after this date
They are offering customers a 35% discount on a New Harmony
And it's basically the same sort of thing IR Wi-Fi but you also get connected
So my hunch is they just one
Consolidate
No
But not everybody wants
Apple Smart Home
Some people just want to be able to control their TV
Product know and let's face it
Keeping software up to date on a device that handles IR codes and Wi-Fi it's not like
Guess you could say we're kind of going away maybe it is but
But then you go I mean that just
I don't like this at all
In this ties back so a couple of months ago I wrote
But I really do think
We should be talking about smart
Devices in the car
Expiration dates
So this would be avoided
If
Wenzhou
Released a product said hey you know what this product we're going to support it guarantee
After that
That at least gives customers the Opera
Opportunity to say no
It's some will some won't and I think
As we move from
Straight up Hardware to Hardware that's supported by software we're going to have to
And at first I was like no I don't agree with you but then as I think about it
Especially as it relates to a totally different industry that we're all
Involved in smartphones
You
So did you have that
You have
Companies Google for example we promised software Android software updates for
2 years on the new pixels
And
Security updates
3 years
Do you know what the shelf life of that is going to be
So I guess I do get it
Not saying I like it but I get it
The shift in ownership
I've never really are
Your in software does
Requires constant development in upgrades for security
Requires
Someone to support it
All of those things cost money and
It's possible that you won't want to have that happen
For the rest of the
The rest of the physical life
Right
So I think we're going to get into this I think
The industry should be
Really rushing
So guys in the industry
Think about this
Really think about this and start discussing it and buy
Gosh
Start Ashley in
Because in the industry
It's already in Enterprise iot
You get a device with
Asset
Expiration date asset support
We need that is
It's going to suck
Real quick that one alternative I can think of I'm not saying it's a good idea is to start making this
Ace Hardware
Modular and or agreeable that look at this little hug device you know maybe I should be able to pop it open
Grab the board out of it pop new insert a new board that
Bring me new wireless Technologies and new capabilities and so on
And that way you
Kind of res to replacing it but
It's more of a
Update to the device already have
I think that would work on some devices
Unsung
Answers to Penny I mean most consumers are not going to be like
No you have to make a consumer-friendly. There's a plug-in type module again
Yeah but I'm not trying to
Who your idea
Let's see we have we have a party
Kevin and nobody was invited
Yeah that's just a funny story actually leads into our listener voicemail because
Car related
An Amazon Echo in Germany that started a rave
And nobody was home so the police had to actually break the door down
Because of all the noise complaints from Neighbors
Nobody knows how long this person's
Echo started the crazy music party but it did on the six
Open window
Does not like somebody could have
Told madamaiyada
Crank up the
You know Electronics
Pump up the jams yeah
That's what I don't understand how this happened but it did
I just think it's funny
That is fun
And that brings us to our
Question of the week
For the iot podcast listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of Alexa
China clocks
Schlage electronic lock
Offer unparalleled
We all on there
Right out of the box
So you don't have to have a smart
To see what's possible
Schlage
Jacobina Stacy
Atlanta
I'm loving the show I did have a question actually this
What company was last week show when you guys
Talked about
Google home
Does a night mode feature I haven't tried it out yet but I'm definitely
Get out but what I've been thinking is
Usually and I know this is especially
True with the
When I would whisper to the echo
It would usually responds
Obviously Amazon has a profile
Whispers
Does he know when you whisper
Obviously does not sound
Like a regular and irregular speech
So I'm just wondering why
They are not able to identify that
Body is Whispering
And then
Taylor response as it pertains to the volume
Accordingly
So it fits
In the morning and I said
Why can't Amazon recognizing I'm whispering
And then
Just automatic
Anyway
I don't know if they are complications that I'm
Not aware of what I would love to hear your take on it
Thank you guys
Odoo weight
What is a brilliant idea
Although I will say that when I whisper to my Madam and she never respond
But she does respond to my
So I love the idea I think it may be a bit of a technical challenge because you have to figure out
Somebody if the voice levels are low because somebody just further away or they're actually whispering
Right because if you're further away the noise level to whisper like
Sound level so
It could be tricky but I love the idea I hope that they could
Try I mean let's try it beta test it let's do it
Yeah well it it's a very human thing to do because like if
If I suddenly whisper to you
And I will respond at the same level
Exactly
So it's kind of like
My electronic device
Is my AI is now
More like me
So
Charlie
Amazon
Get on it
What did happen
Just let us know why
There might be
If you
Want to leave a message for the internet
Kings podcast
You should call us at 5 1/2
R24
And we
Mets
Answer your question
Yeah that Raspberry Pi server is always running
Now we are going to
Take a small break for us
Message from our sponsor
And when we get back we're going to talk about
Thread because there is actually some big news this week
And it doesn't sound good for the thread standard
So I could Grant Erickson coming on the show 2
Talk about what's happening
And
And what is it
What isn't happening
So stay tuned for all of that
Haverwood we are taking a break from the podcast for a message from this week sponsor this week
Sponsor is Spark
Cognition and I've got Guzman
Shuja
Who is general manager of the industrial internet-of-things effort
To talk about
Sparkcognition
Respond spark ignition is an AI company and you guys are really working to help
Industrial iot companies
Improve their efficiency
And improve their safety
That is correct we are drinking
Together a lot of different capabilities with an artificial intelligence and data analytics
B1
Caviar dressing
Use cases such as predicting failures or catastrophic events
And also automating a lot of the process
She's been in the industrial world
Looking at security data Within These industrial environments to make sure that no
Activities happening
Show data analytics is a big
Peace effect
But we are bringing different people
Pictures of artificial intelligence to make that analysis and make that
Application
More robust
Do you have an example of maybe one of your clients and how they used AI to change their business
Absolutely closer
Which is the largest pump
Manufacturer
And the US is one of our client
Take a break
The failure in a bump
A few hours in advance
They applied are algorithms
And now they can
Extent
Forewarning of a pump failure by 6 days that is fundamentally changed their business
This Mortal they can sell prediction of the service which is really supercharged
Aftermarket
What are some of the critical steps to ensuring a successful
Plantation
To the key to successful implementation
Could be the pink bag
Strategically
An act
Tactical
What that means
Addressing the big picture problems
Concerning the Border
The c-suite
And the dressing
The business
Outcomes
Building a good Roi story at the end of the day that technology
It should be tight
Clothes liquid
The the second thing that very important
Is the people Astor Cafe
Because it's new technology
And fix
Controller technology or Lord
The client's feet got to
Engage the people and get
Goodbye and so they don't feel nervous about it and their stock price
Technology
I can deliver the business outcomes that are looking for
Okay
And what are some of the risks of limitations
The biggest restaurant
Seen as people jumping to conclusions about what the technology can do
The dog building the right foundation
Safari examples
The organizational structure could be something.
It's not supportive of an AI implementation
It could be the lack of data or available data within the ideal environment to be able to support some of the artificial intelligence
Algorithm so between the organization
Structure in people
And the
Technical
Infrastructure needed to deliver a i Solutions
Dota 2 big things that I've seen
Penn State majorettes
And where can we find out more
To find out more
Visit sparkcognition
Dot-com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Grant Erickson Who is the
President of the thread group
Hey Grant how are you doing
Good morning sissy thank you so much for having me on this morning
I am super excited
Because
How to say you got news today and you guys are watching something
But I want to hear you explain in your own words cuz I'm a little worried about the
So
Let's talk
Thread
First offer people who are unfamiliar thread is a wireless protocol
It's like zigbee Z-Wave Bluetooth all those Wi-Fi even
Except it's a little different because it is a mesh base protocol it is also low power
And it's
IPv6 compliant which means
A device can talk directly to the internet as opposed to going
Rahab
So now that we know all of this about
Fred letzter
Talk about your news first.
Good news
Thread is used in more places
Let's talk about that
Aptoide
So we have an exciting pipeline of products coming into the marketplace today we have just shy of a dozen
Components
Facts of people in use build exciting iot products
Today
And because of this actually spending the number of places that you can go certify thread products and solutions
Spanish
Including a locations in Southeast Asia
And your looks to be closer
Mazar
So we have
Two categories of
The people who really want to
Tell the world
We have something to talk about for quite some time which is our thread certified products
One of our first and most prominent companies in that category 0 who announced their stuff
Next generation Wireless products
Stutter hopefully soon-to-be thread certified
We have a second category of products
What is a member-driven organization and we have people who are really excited about touting their uses red in pots
Even though that maybe not all the way quite there
Program called shred ready
To support the interests of members who really won at out
They are using thread but they're not all the way to
Completely open trade system
That's one of the first example of that it messed
With a recently released
Nest
Acure product line
How's it's been running designation for their nest
And for their nest guard.
Okay so
What we're seeing here is threat certified which means
Ian Fleming
All parts of the
Thread protocol
Exactly
There is a second category which is
Thread ready
Which is implementing some parts
Exactly
Okay
So let's dig into this cuz this feels like
China
One day
So let's start with ness
So they are thread ready
What makes them
Thread ready
As opposed to
Thread certified
Stacy
Average of being a sponsor of the friend group is super excited about friend technology
And we're Liam wants to get to the end game of the vision we've all been talking about the last time we're
Couple things to do to the nature of its products and getting to Market
In which
Induction of leave application layer they want to do
Stout but they're using thread
Real Marketplace problems
Become a signal to the market that they're going to get there in terms of kind of this full open
Designation is really a way of saying
Network perspective everything we do is completely compliant
And meats.
Application
Commissioning
OtterBox
Experian score for the time being doing things a little differently
And offering them or close to
And so the ideas apps it's sort of a signal to the market Marketplace problems today
And it's a signal for company to say
Will get there
And because celebrity of time-bound
Here's the time in which we will like to move our products along to kind of the full red certified
Okay let's talk about the timeout
What aspect of it
And how you would go about becoming
Shred ready so how does a company
Goes to the process to say add-on to be certified
I want to be ready
And how long do they have
How to get from ready
To certify
The first stop is approaching the choice
Any one of these six that we're just identified that are open available today and in conjunction with talking to the test house
Tom Shirley application saying here is the bread ready
And the certification director of the certification committee and the board of directors or visa application
And figure out whether or not it
The spirit of thread ready which is a company that is really on its way to being fully thread to formal complaint
And whether or not the exception again
Minor thing or major thing
And in addition Delgado
Indication of how long they have to get their implementation
Okay so it's a case-by-case
Exactly
And the time window is
Anywhere from 12 to 18
Okay so within 12 to 18 months then we should expect Nest to be fully thread compliant
Okay
And
What are some of the things that are okay
To be so you could be thread ready but not
Trade certified
Commissioning apparently is not crucial enough
That you would be
Will let you be thread ready
What else could I change to be
Thread ready
I think mission is really the one that we've really thought long and hard about says that
Probably be the acceptable extent
Unique advance in changing some cool things about how they act
Publix
All of our years of experience with other alliances and other technologies that making changes and compromises there would be less than desirable
And such really more around probably those things that affect the out-of-box experience that might be very
Specific or unique
Tamar of a closed ecosystem
Alexander nevsky The Nest secure product is today
So if I wanted to change
I don't know the device management aspect
Probably not going to Grant an exception
Okay so from the perspective of a consumer
If I going to see something are there going to be two labels like thread certified and
Thread ready
Tell me a really really with this program wanted to limit that kind of confusion in the marketplace
Suspend ready participant
Can't use any low going they may indicate it's ready and Prince but they certainly may not use
But don't unfriend or thread certified did again
For the artist
Market excited about it and we're on our way to being fully Spencer Define interoperable
It's really there
Brand that is really the key Brannock
Perspective
If we look
Products that are in their ecosystem like the
They'll be Burlington
Looking for the logo
Estrada courts
Opportunity guarantee I'm looking for
And not necessarily Focus
Omni broad open
Okay so in 18 months
It'll have works with nest and also presumably thread certified
These devices that
Work with what actually Nest devices
Now
Or something like that Yale lock which presumably will also be
Become thread
Ready at some point in time
They also have the choice to step up
To this certification level
Exactly
All right this to me feels a little bit
Like
Zippy which Bratz I really was stuck
Cuz
Zippy was like oh we're standard but they had different
Location lyrics
And so you could
Buy a zigbee certified product
Really guarantee that it would work with another
Certified
So how is this
Different
Differentiators
Programming in front of learning from history you have an IP layer
Cancel that I can really carry and transport
Multiple application layer
In fact if you think back to the demonstration that you saw at CES 2017 and that wall that we had
We actually have enough products
What program is running a personal strength
We're talking about here with friend ready
I knows we're on the very same networks as...
As well as the oci products that were on that wall
It's a really even though the method of getting those
Devices
The thread network was being shared difference between
At the end of the day once they were all on the network all three of those application-layer simultaneously work together harmoniously
And that's really the beauty of Ip and thread and ability is
Perspective
It's really great because you can have a comic
Today I want to be..
Tomorrow Mayra
The device has the resources
I want to upgrade with the software update
Justin Bieber I want to update
Okay and so let's talk about thread within the context of other Wireless Pro to
Call speakers
My gosh is getting hot and heavy in the wireless
So Bluetooth just
Bluetooth just
Came out with mesh
For a while
Capable
Not everybody implemented on the chip
So there is that but it is capable of doing it
Same thing
And
They also
Arlo power
Kelley Blue
Bluetooth low energy
So to me that feels like
The biggest
Predator
The red
How do you guys
View kind of
Protocol
Battles
Actual question Stacy and I think
Lykke Li I think we're kind of to some extent in our mind
Past the particle battles I think there's a link
For every application there's a network for every application
And generally speaking it's red we kind of see if spread is
Aswan + Wi-Fi
DSL DOCSIS for your kind of coupling to the internet connectivity
I need with Bluetooth
If you can play the Pick 4 do you look at Bluetooth
Remember partners that actually have ratted out of box
Solutions
But use Bluetooth today for that kind
Repairing another box
I think MacArthur perspective but we really love to see
Is working together with members of the Bluetooth community
To really start to standardize
How thread and be illegal together
If you look at our silicon partners
Define. Almost all of modern chips and components that are being offered
Actually
Dual stack
Joel thread
Ble radios
Use cases in terms of how you could have point
Interactions
The periphery of the thread
Really using thread is kind of that backbone steady-state Network
Actually
Business
Alice fredenham
Again
Again I think that really is a complementary view of
House red and Bluetooth can work together in the future
Billy Mac's Asbury Nathan
Billy IP is very nice and
Solution of cheer in the market today available today and open rule problems
And I know your ship partners are obviously doing a lot of the work to Bluetooth and thread together
Are you guys at the
Actively talking to people at
The Bluetooth Sig
To try to make something happen much like you guys did with
How many ducks
But we do have many members in common between both the Bluetooth Sig and
And those common shared numbers are
Doing a lot of work in the background I try to bring those two worlds together and show the marketplace how easily can be complementary
Augusta Technologies
And final thought
Thread is
I know that Nest is obviously a big prick
There's the Eero routers I've talked to LaGrande which makes
Beautiful switches
And those cool plugs
Pop out of the wall
Are there other players
Using
Threads that are worth
We can mention by name we have confidential agreements with all of our members and partners that do go into the store
Certainly do now that they are there they are actively engaged with her greatest test labs and tough houses and if we kind of
What to add everything up that we see in the pipeline and I'm Horizon we think by end-of-year CS
2018 time frame we should definitely see certified products
Numbering in low
Okay so CES
The year
Coming on the show
I really appreciate the time-space it's been a pleasure as always.
Look forward to everything I try and things podcast remember if you want more
Or iot news please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week