Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a
Stupendous show for you this week we have people who
I don't know how to say this their abusers and they're taking advantage of Smart Homes to make life for their
Spouses are partners
We're also going to be talking about the new wpa3 security for Wi-Fi
Tesla's new pricing model for data
Which I think is
Relevant for the rest of the iot
Madam a
For iOS
Games voices
We've had some really cool news bits like
Smart stent
We got a sensor company getting money that helps
How to prevent pollution
We've got smart Park
Benches in Australia
And I'm going to tell you about my experience
With my new Delta faucet
That talks to me
Madam
We're also going to hear from ceruse Farva
Who is the author of Who
Habeas data on surveillance
Metadata
Iot stuff
How to even
So
Stay tuned
For all of this
After a brief message from our sponsor
Today's podcast is sponsored by Leading smart home provider control for their smart home system connects all of your smart
Devices to make home control is easy as Alexa turn on movie time to lower your shades
Dim the lights and start Netflix on your TV or when the doorbell rings you can go into one app to see who it is
Turn on the porch light with control4 you can automate the devices you already have and keep adding new ones
Now that's smart head to control4.com Pest Control the number for
DACA
For more information
Okay Kevin
We're going to start this off
With
Justin
Really Grim story in
Honestly
I didn't think about this so
This weekend the New York Times did a story about how
People worrying
Abusive relationships how their abusers take advantage of smart home
Technology tool
Make their Partners lives even more difficult so they talk about setting the heat to lie
100 +
Locking people out of their house in
It sounds like a nightmare
This was
A really sad started to read it and it got me to rethink how I Implement devices in my own home with my family
Happy family there's no piece of relationship here
But
I again I rethought how I do things and how I communicate what devices I'm putting in place and why
And who has access and so on and so forth but if you're in an abusive relationship like this and
Your home is being turned against you whether it's
You're being listened to all the time monitor through your microphone enabled webcams or is she said
Thermostat changes that
Make the
You know you're home environment miserable or you're locked out of your house you know
There's no easy answer here to
Stop that from happening if you're in that situation and that's the scary part
Yashow Kevin is put up a story on the website
Talked about this a little bit
You know you mentioned
Best way to
Do this is have access to your router
So you can
Yeah because it's a control thing this is all about control and if you don't have control over the devices if you can get
I control over the centralized point of communication for those devices
Meaning the router
Then you know at least you can see what devices are on the network and you may not even know that's the scary part.
Could be being monitored
And not even know it
There could be hidden networks like we're putting place in you again don't know so access to the router I think
If you can and you would suggested
Even
Hard resetting the router to stop devices from
Having access work at least temporarily
Yeah and this is
Maybe
I don't know maybe you're packing to get out or something
I looked into hard reset
Isis and
The best option for someone who doesn't have access to the
Router or the apps are going to be
Things that
Don't require you to have the app so
Nest for example
Are there thermostats
You can hard reset your nest which
Erase all your settings never
And this is not a great solution
Because whoever you're living with
You can just press your thermostat
Ring you open the
Under settings
Reset it
So
I'm pretty sure I can do that with the ecobee I have install as well and the whole point is you're looking for ways to reset these devices
Either without the app
Without access to the the app you know you may have the app which might not be able to do certain things to do administrative privileges
And if your Echo device you just pop a paperclip
Into
The reset button
It depends on the device
But there's a little hole and if you stick up
Paper clip in
The light Rings going to turn on and off
And then
You can't actually re-registered if you
I have the app on
But at least that
Deregister
So
Factory resetting your loxism
A little harder you
I need the app for
August lock
That's because he's our outside
Your house and they don't want somebody
A thief could come in
Reset your lock
From the outside right you could it mean if you have the right tools you could actually remove and replace
That's a pretty extreme step with baby that is useful in
Your particular case it's hard to say
I mean you can rip out all the smart home care I called it the nuclear option but again
Crab repercussions when
The abuser finds out which they certainly will very quickly
So yeah
Heidi Lynn
Kevin and I
Because we have so much stuff in our homes I'll tell you my husband actually doesn't
Apps forever
Iinstaller
I offer it to him
He's kind of
And I joke sometimes that he calls me
He can't
He's calling me when I'm out of town cuz
The lights don't work
Never thought about that
Using that so Kevin came up with some
Basic good practices for
Partners
It's not going to solve the main issue but
Youku
Potentially proactively avoid this issue if
Like I'm going to start doing more of
I plan to talk
About whatever device I plan to put on the network with my family
And offer them you know the same rights that I have first of all I want to make sure they understand what device is going
What it's going to do
What information is going to gather and send to me or to them you know if they choose to
Accept the invitation the app and that way they understand exactly what's here
Because he'll know what
Could potentially be used against them
God forbid something happened in our relationship
Yeah I just want them to have the same information and rice that I have
Again I would never plan to do this but I want them to
Joe comfortable with everything in their house
And if they're not I've decided you know what I'm just gonna start putting stuff in my home office where they typically don't go
Man that's fine for testing and I may not be able to get all the features and so on so forth you know but that's okay they need to be comfortable in their own home
So proactively those are two of the steps that I'll be taken with my family
Yes and I've always done that
Like my daughter actually doesn't want smart thing
Bedroom she's told me
Looks like no just don't install it
Okay.
Not until she does have an echo
Because she wants
And now she has a smart
Because she
But she had to come out
So yeah
There's no easy solution air
Yeah this is
People
That is on that so let us talk now about
W
Re
Wi-Fi Alliance announced this week
A new security protocol
Free wifi
It's about time since WPA2 has had its fair share of soles for quite some time in
It was back in 2011 that the Wi-Fi protected setup that button you would hit that would scan
For devices you hit the button on your router and pet access to all the new devices on network that could be Brute Force
Pact with as little as 11,000 guesses of the PIN
Which
That's not very secure for a
Protected secure
Set up so this is long overdue
Yes
And
Vacation
And it's actually been used in mesh net
Other people's
Now
This is going to
Address of The Brute Force attack issues so that'll be nice
And
The downside to this is
Chant
It's not an existing router so
If you want this
Going to have to buy some
Which if you just got it Like Us excited about mesh routers
You just bought a metro
What
Terror
Two things that I would say one it's a perfect time for her router makers time
Introduce Smart Hub Smart's two routers because now they're going to have a whole upgrade wave of routers
Even if you
Buying new device that supports wpa3 and I believe LG smartphones will support
This year it's okay because that will always fall back
To WPA2
So you won't have all the new security features of wpa3 but you don't necessarily need to
Upgrade your router to still use the device on your home network
Yes and if you buy these
New Riders
Nothing else to think
It is backwards compatible
But
Someone to what extent
Fluorite
But in other news for iot
People the Wi-Fi Alliance also introducing the
Easy Connect
Which is really nice
Because basically you snap a picture of a QR code
And then you can
Connect a device to
Your WiFi
And that's that's good that's actually how you connect certain devices to your network today I know that
There's a QR code on the bottom of Google home Mini
Homekit devices have a numerical but also you can scan a QR code to app so that makes total sense
Sakura witch
They say it is we will see
I'm sure someone
How long till attack
All right
Tesla
They have a new
Pricing model
For data so anybody who has a test
Mary called it
You basically had
I know when I bought mine they would like to have four years of data free
And then you'll have to pay for it and I'm like how much is it there like we don't know yet
Okay
I hope
So I've been actually Loki worrying about that for a while cuz you know the
They kind of have me over
Barrel I totally need internet
Connectivity for
My car
A lot of the functions that has relies not just on Wi-Fi
In my garage but also cellular
So
How's it going to work
Apparently people who bought their cars will not have to
If you were buying a new one
No you get a certain amount of time
Use basic data
And that will always be
But if you want to use like real time
Traffic
Views if you want to do
Do you like Street View maps
Data-intensive app
Applications
Then you will pay
$100
So for the basic you'll like still be able to get maps and routing you just won't get say the traffic the real time
Hondata
So your car will still function and do lovely things for you it just won't be
I'll tell you that
Traffic
But you do have it on your phone so
Yeah I mean
If there's something I couldn't get on my phone then I would consider getting this if I had a test what would I do not
I wonder
If you can connect
Your car to your phone as a Wi-Fi hotspot
In which case you don't need to pay the $100 a year but it is a little clunky
Now also
It includes the fancy package
Including car streaming
Media and music so
Prior to that it's been
And also the intern
Which I personally have
I have never used in my
But
Yeah
Let me know how many people drive without the phone I know I don't think there's a big push to move certain smartphone
Activities while you're on-the-go
Saline to the car so you can leave the phone behind
Nobody's more conveniently
Like being able to skip a song
You know and have it
Run from 1 places
Supposed to on your phone
It's kind of nice
There's a huge screen in your Tesla so
If you're navigating
When you want to look
For real-time nav
You know for real time
Traffic
It's nice to look
17 in
Sitting right there
Bissell you're going to pay $100 a year for
Is a convenience factor I'd say
But I like this model I think it's good because there is a lot of things that were unlike
How are you going to prove
Activity for these things
Is it having
Some of these devices it's very easy to say hey it's a water sensor it's a wake-up this many times
X many bytes of data
So for that
I
Could price that into
Vice really well
Right I have a good sense of
What's going to happen
With some of the devices that have screens or
Things like that
It does become a little dicey
Like you can't really effective
Sleep rice that
Into the hardware cost of the
Device when someone buys
So this is kind
Gives you the functionality that you
Expect for
Your device
Then offers you
It's your things
Yeah and they're not limiting how long you can use those fancy things if you want to stream
Audio near car over the web
You could do that
Theoretically 7 by 24 not that you would and you're not paying like overages or anything like that
So
I like this
Nautica
Crazy thing I like
Tiered structure there
I think we'll see
I don't know how many subscriptions I'm going to end up
Okay
Yes finally I mean I don't remember when
Amazon announced that's what they had said prior that they're bringing Madam a voice support to iOS
And they did this week and I tested it
So in the matter of a app there is no a button that you just tap and you don't need to say matinee or you just
Ask a question or say a command and she behaves just like she would in an echo device right on your iPhone
It's not always listening thing Apple will probably never allow that for right third-party digital assistant
I totally get that
One thing though I think
That Amazon is missing the boat on and hopefully there's an update to do this soon
A lot of iPhones have
Force Touch where you can
Hard press the screen on an app icon and get alternative options in all kinds of different things and if I do that on my
Google assistant app for iOS
There's a button that says speak to your Google assist
They don't do that for
Manamea on the anime app so I think it would be helpful to you just don't have to open the app that way
You just push press
So other than that
Works great
Took him forever to come out with it I don't know what took so long
Got it I don't understand
Use case for this but maybe it's cuz I don't have my phone
All the time I'm like I just shouted out
I guess it's 4 p.m.
No I mean if you're not at home and you want to turn on
Things that are connected to a matinee
You know or see who's home or you know what there's a ton of anything that she's connected to at home and you want to access remotely
We should be able to do this way
OkCupid
That is like
We talked about this
A couple
Weeks ago the wise camera
And
After I wrote cuz I was just
Appointed that I couldn't
Turn it off
I have like five people
I just plug it into a smart outlet
Then I
Sounds like
Target
Who is like me and just
Didn't see that
Thank you
Twitter
Did see it and
Kind enough to put it out
Smart listeners
Smart listeners and connect
So let's talk about basic news
. actually I think
We got a smart
Stent
This is the device you stick in your
And it
Holds your arteries open
Text several people
They are
Lovely except for they get clogged up just like your arteries do in
How to come out
Another surgery in
So this one
You this is wild this tent was created or designed to actually act as a large antenna
So
The stent itself the tubular stent is made up of wiring that just goes around and around around a form
Understand and there's a pressure monitor
Attached to this and that measures
I presume you the blood flow or the pressure on the artery and because of the antenna
That pressure information can be monitored
Exactly exactly
I look at this and it looks like a caterpillar to me because of the way it's designed with the whole design is an antenna that's just amazing
Research project
Not actually out
You got to see it
Okay
The company called
Gets
24 million in
These guys on my podcast
They have their sensors attached
Google Street View cars in
And we're measuring pollution in
It was a great project
I loved it because it talks about
Having air quality monitor
Ring sensors
Lower level is really
Because a lot of cities put them
Way high up
People are breathing
So
That's one into being able to track
Very granular
Air pollutants
AR
How cities planned
Better so you can say oh my gosh this intersection is
Horribly
Let's see what we
We can do to improve traffic flow
In this area for exam
Maybe we just plant more
So
I like what they're doing
They
Raised
More sensors are more cars and more places in
I love it
And
That is what I
Very cool
Meanwhile in Buda
He municipal smartness
Yes Meme
In Sydney Australia they are
Linksmart Park
Benches and I love this because
All of the benches and surrenders tables as well
Have sensors in them
That basically determine if the bench is being used if it's broken
That allows the local municipality to a keep track of
Any upkeep they need to do and get it taken care of faster but also
Tell them
How to better design public spaces right
What about that says
It's there's no user data collected Noah I'd personally identifiable user information it's not saying that Kevin is
Sitting on this bench and sat there from this time to this time
It's just saying that someone did
And that's pretty rare that we have
Batters new security issue here from a personal privacy standpoint
So that is brilliant
I would love to see more places to this I don't know how much it cost but it shouldn't be that expensive to add these
Pressure sensors and such to park benches and tables
Very curious to see what kind of data they get out of it and one for me how they use the data in the future
And now we'll move from smart
Park benches
Too smart
Faucets
So
Delta
We got very excited about this
As we saw it
Imat ces
Delta makes a
Bi-weekly means face
No it is it is it was cooler when I actually saw it
Retrofit kit
Touch2o faucet
The retrofit
Vitamin A
Faucet so this means it will talk to you
Everyone's like what why would I care
But I'm going to tell you why you
So I did this in
Back when we talked about it originally the
Pricing was about five hundred
Dollars was
Plan pricing
For this for a total faucet
And adding
AC replace your existing
Faucet with this
Touch to Dada
Capacitive touch faucet
Which I also
Just means to turn it on
So I happen to have a capacitive touch faucet
He said it would be about
$120 but it is not on the market
Get this is a beta
They really wanted
Let me try it cuz I am soaked
Crazy about this kind of stuff
And by they wanted
Stacy really try it means Stacy really want to try and they said okay
So this is
Is not something you can buy
Eventually
I think it could be if we're going to have dealt actually to come on the show in a cup
The faucet
Installing it
Looked so scary
You guys cuz you had to turn off the water in
And you need to have power underneath your sink cuz
This is wifi-enabled
Wi-Fi sucks juice like
Business so beforehand I had batteries
Power Ranger
Batteries
Not enough
So
I put under my sink
I do have power
Because I have a
Garbage disposal
In the dishwasher
Running off of
That's so yay for
I turn off the water in basic
Glee you just
I just remove
One module that was in between
Pipes and I stuck two more
Then I connect as a little ethernet
Because thanks need ethernet now you guys
And
Can you basically
Tested
And then you connect it to
Remind me account
And
I had a little trouble
Connecting
When it's set up a soft access point
And basically was like trying to
Connect the faucet itself
But I work through that
It was a weird glitch
And then
I was able to
Tell Madam a
Hey so hey. Ma ask Delta to turn on water
Turn on
Turn off
And there's about a 4 second delay
So this is not a great option
You know you're saying supper
May just run over faster
But is really cool
You can do things like
Hey Madam a ask Delta to dispense to
Does it does it does it accurately
It's awesome
You actually just heard the problem with
But this Witch is it's really hard to
Number to ask Delta
Yeah that's a problem with a lot of these skills
Yeah
So I struggle with my
Words
I struggle with my words like your words use your words
Once we got it down
Using it
Not as often as I thought we
But we do use it to
Phil
Things that
Are large
And you don't want to
You know like I don't want to stand there
Like a gallon of water
So I can just stick the bucket under there and just
Tell it to dispense a gallon
You can also go to the Delta website
There is not an app
Go to the Delta website
Dragon / 2
Home screen
But it shows you your
Check your water usage history so
So you can see how many gallons of water
Use for that sink
Canidae which is kind of
We'll see if you're building a new house I would
Totally put this in
You can do custom
Type Phillips to like if you have a water bottle that has x amount of ounces capacity you could
Shortcut that
Yes so I did create a shortcut I have a vase that I used to fill
Are fish tank
Water evaporate
Take it slow
Can you treat the water in the
Right now I have a big face and it needs
11 + 1/2
Cups of water
So instead of saying 11 and 1/2
Half cup Cypress to set base
As my
A program database
And so now I just say
Matinee
Ask Delta
To fill
Face
Nice
I have one question
The ethernet port
Is on the module that YouTube retrofitted
I'm just wondering if I need an ethernet port in my kitchen or something they connect to each other there's a module that controls
The capacitive
Touched and there's a module
Controls
Okay so no concern there of not having total airports in the kitchen you do not need
I liked
My family so far seems to
My daughter thinks it's a little silly but yeah she thinks a lot of the stuff
Banana silly song
There we have it and you'll learn more about it
I'll have a review up after living with
More days
Make sure that nothing terrifying happens
Sand
Also have
Before we go to our voicemail you know what your daughter won't think is silly
That the Google home can now speak Spanish and I know she speak Spanish
Yes
Expect can habla Espanol
And we know this because
WeChat
Right before the show
Trying to speak Spanish and it did not go well but the Google home doesn't work that way.
Available in May
Now Google
Speaks French
Spanish
Elsa speaks
English
Good news all around
North America actually
Okay let's go to a voicemail from the eye
Podcast hotline
Remember that hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Don't miss your chance
When a Slave
Sense
Smart deadbolt
Wifi adapter
Soda energy win
And this is
Through June 30th
At midnight
Eastern
You just need to call us on the hotline at 5
1 2
6 to 3
7 4
And
At the end of that time
We will
Pick randomly from all of the
People who called in
We will try neat
They will tell you on the next show
And now
Let's hear this week's color
How is from Shannon
This message is from Shannon
I'm interested in getting the Abode home security system
Just wondering if you had any recommendation for sensors
Sickly store sensors window sensors baby garage door sensors sunlight
Anything that you guys could recommend that goes with the systems also have apple homekit
Thanks
Oceanian
This is one of those
Why is the smart home so hard
The questions
It's a good one
Wonderful
At home security
Yeah we're going to tackle this into pieces
Because
There are two pieces
They don't work together so actually will just tell you to give up on the home
KIPP dream
Talk a little bit about this as we
Used
The Abode
Worse with lots of devices and they have a wonderful
List
On their website so I'll put
Link to that
In the show notes
Of the devices
Is it safe to test
Works with both
Z-Wave Danzig
I noticed on there that they had the
Aeons
I love those
I think they're really good
Dancing very attract
They have
One of the and or sense
Gen 5 in that is a recessed door sensor
Answer so you can actually install that
Insider
Torso you
Holypop
And then you don't have these like we're
Weird things on it
Exterior
And makes
Water sensors door sensors
They do make light bulbs
Wouldn't be excited about that
So I wouldn't go there
For that
But I also saw that
That they have
The linear
Garage door
Which you would
About that
Kevin
What do you think about it
I like it it's very easy to install it's literally just adding
Plugging it into a power port
Jack and then connecting two wires to your garage door opener
You made a ladder
Probably
Unless you're really tall on like me but it's not a daunting install at all
It works very well
Correct
Is easy you mentioned door locks they have
This works actually with
Kwikset door
Blocks the Z-Wave
Kwikset door locks I have those
They're fine
It also works with the Schlage door locks
And I'm not saying this because they sponsor this
Their door lock quality is better
So
I would probably go with that if
That you're seriously concerned about
But it only works with the Z-Wave
So this is where it gets can
Using because Slade also Mesa
Louis Facebook swell several of these vendors make homekit devices that are not compatible and the reason
People understand
Very simple reason
Homekit only supports to radio protocols WiFi and Bluetooth
So you're never going to find
At least today a Z-Wave or zigbee device that works with
Myself so that's the issue
It is
And
It also works with Nest devices ecobee devices
It works with your Amazon Echo
It works with Google
So there's
A lot of things this is going
You're not going to have
That cool ability on your iPhone
Look and see who's at your
So that is
But that's what it works with
And it actually seems really
Good in
Again a lot of people
Like the security system so
Good luck to you Shana
And sorry to burst your bubble
Remember if you
Do you have a question for us
Or he want to be entered
Dutch League
Door lock
Give us a call at 5
Now Kevin
Secret pretty good for news this
We could summer it's a little late but
State
Cuz we
We have
Bruce varvara
Who is the author of
Habeas
Data
Privacy and the rise of surveillance Tech
And we talked a lot about the legal
Background here
Tok also about what it
Ginsburg
Your devices
Inside your home
And how you can
Try to
Make
The world around you a little bit more secure
Kiran bedi
Encourage governments to spend less on
You can look forward to that after a message from our sponsor
Fastest route to you by Kevin and Stacey and we want to tell you that if you like what you hear
And
Want to advertise with us
Just shoot an email to Andrew at iot podcast. Com
And
Aspirin
We'd appreciate
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Syracuse
Barbar who is the author of a book called
Habeas data and a reporter with ARs Technica
Hi Siri how are you doing
Hey what's going on
Man I am super excited about this be
Because I spent a lot of time thinking about all the crazy Gadget
Json stuff that I can
Can put in my house and I spend very little time talking about
What this means in the big picture for people's privacy and
What it means with the lawn for
So I am happy to have you on the show quickly
Tell me a little bit about what the book is and why
Chores for the book yeah it's called habeas data privacy vs the rise of surveillance Tech it covers 50 years of service
Valence law history in America so the book is mostly about 10 legal cases
Mostly Supreme Court not 100% but mostly starting with chapter 1 which is a case called
Cats versus United States which the Supreme Court decided in 1960
57 or we are getting 1967 engine take
And this involves a guy in Los Angeles and Sunset Boulevard who was using pay phones to
Make illegal gambling phone calls and the police put a recording device on top of the phone booths
That he was using
To do that they didn't have a warrant for that
They captured his voice
While he was in the phone booth and ultimately the Supreme Court ruled that this was not okay
Mistreated this phrase
Call a reasonable expectation of privacy
Cease of the Supreme Court sad
That when you step into a phone booth just as when you are at home or in a hotel room or in a few other places you have a quote reasonable expectation of
Privacy to be free from government surveillance and if the government doesn't want us to reveal you
They need a warrant
To do so that's part of the legal underpinning
For a number of cases that I write about in the book
And many others that have provided
Sort of a framework for understanding how the courts think about
Surveillance over the last half-century
Biscuits case
Set up this idea of this reasonable expectation of
Privacy and the rest of the book
Spend a lot of time exploring how that intersects with technology so you talk about things like
Real-time location data you talk about thermal imagery applied outside
If homes there's wiretapping there's a lot of technical
Innovations that are currently still being addressed by the
You actually in the book talking about a case that just was decided last week at the Supreme Court
Can you tell me a little bit about that
Yeah so that's a case called Carpenter vs United States and it involves a guy by the name of Little Tim Carpenter who is
Is involved in a gang of men operating
Primarily in Michigan and Ohio back in 2010 and 2011
That were sticking up Radio Shacks and cell phone stores they were after the latest models of iPhones and Android
And the government in that case was able
To go to a company in this case MetroPCS and Sprint
And require them to turn over to the government the phone record specifically What's called the cell site location information
In other words we're Littleton Carpenter's phone was and by extension where he was
In this case over the course of a hundred and twenty seven days
I got they didn't have to have a warrant to do this and so the question that the Supreme Court this time was being asked to answer why
Is that okay is it okay for the government to obtain such a large volume of data about somebody more than a hundred and twenty
20 days worth of data about somebody
That not only show that yes he was at the scenes of the various crimes but also you know that he was at church on Sunday that he was at
At a relative's house on another day and that he went to buy coffee in a different day and you know he did lots of other things
That had nothing to do with the crimes that he was accused of committing did the government
Need a warrant to get all of that
Data to find out all of those things about
Tim Carpenter
The Supreme Court in a five to four ruling
Said yes the government does need a warrant that location data here is different
Then other kinds of data that the government might have been able to previously obtained
So now presumably law enforcement agencies all over the country are now trying to figure out
How to adjust their policies and practices
To deal with this new reality
Now
This feels like yes
Awesome
But in reading about this it sounds like there's actually a lot of limits in the court didn't kind of didn't talk about Gathering
During the state of
Overtime or
How long they would have this data they left a lot of things open
Open so I'd love to get your
So yeah so if you read the decision and it's long it's about a hundred and twenty Pages including all of the descendants
So in the majority opinion which was written by Chief Justice John Roberts
The court seemed to suggest
You know that the government
Certainly needed a warrant to obtain data that was more than over the course of more than six days so the government wanted to come out
After myself at location information for more than 6 days they certainly needed at work Beyond.
Before that they probably need a warrant but they so it was a little bit fuzzy in the way it was written
The dissenters sort of seized upon that and said yo the Six-Day rule is very arbitrary why is it take days and not 5 or so
7 we don't know
But
We don't know yet
Exactly what that's going to mean in practice
Presumably you know presuming that law enforcement agencies are following the Supreme Court's guidance here is that it just means that it
It's a little bit harder now for law enforcement
To get all of this
Information right now they have to show probable cause which is not that hard to get right judges sign off
Off on probable cause warrant
Literally every day around this country so it's not
Difficult but it certainly requires the police to do a little bit more legwork upfront
But you know it's very early still this issue just came out a few days ago so we don't exactly know yet what the full Wrath
Ramifications of Adar
True okay let's break some Concepts down from the book
That I think are worth talking about before we actually get into like smart home
Which is what is idea of
D orders
Warrants
Super warrants because these are all like the standards of
Proof that
The right government establishment has to show Buffet
For getting the data
So talk to me about that
Sure it's a deodorant which is named for a particular section of the store to medications act which is a federal law
All that governs
How the governments in Access
This particular data and what standard they need to show a d order merely requires relevancy to an Envoy
Going investigate
That's pretty low and that's pretty broad generally there's no real issue there
So we've gone now with respect to cell site location information data we've gone now from this do you order standard relevancy
Too probable cause right side that's a standard well-known framework that is in 4th amendment law
Criminal defense unit going back for a very long time right this is a well-known understanding of what that means
That the government has to show probable cause
That there is evidence of a crime that if they search somebody's home or somebody's phone or whatever it is that they're going to find evidence of a
The crime a super warrant as you mentioned a moment ago isn't even higher standard right and
To be clear the term super warrant is a nickname that lawyers have given
For what the government has to show when it wants to obtain a wiretap order
So if anybody has ever watched
Universe TV shows or movies
The most notably the wire you probably remember that the character in The Wire of Jimmy McNulty spends a lot of time go
Going to this Baltimore judge
Asking for wiretap orders
On particular phones that the you know fictional criminal gang in that show
Are using to conduct their drug-dealing up
The reason why they're called super warrants oftentimes in the real world is because
In order to get a wiretap order
The police law enforcement has to show to the judge
That conventional surveillance either has already failed
Would fail
Or would be too dangerous to undertale
Right so you can imagine for example
Trying to infiltrate like a gang or a mafia-type organization or something like that where it would be extremely difficult
If not outright impossible for them to do that and they have to swear in a document write affidavit to the judge that really
Play this is the ultimate Last Resort
And this is the only way that we're going to be able to bust these bad guys is if we wiretapped
Stop listening in on somebody's phone calls
It's pretty invasive I think all of us kind of inherently understand that
So the government has to clear a pretty high bar in order to be able to
Be granted a wiretap and in the federal court system the federal courts actually publish annual statistics
It's showing how often
Set wiretap orders are granted
Wiretaps have been allowed under the lawn out
For 50 years and we've lived under with all the wiretap ACT also known as title 3 for 50 years now and so
So we have a pretty good sense of how that works and you know this guy hasn't fallen right the fact that the government has to go
3D Dexter Hoops doesn't seem to be
A big barrier
Okay and now that we talked about warrants this gets into possibly the big macro theme
The book if I'm thinking about it which is this idea of metadata versus content so a wiretap for example
Is getting my actual content of my
But in several of the cases that you write about
What government is actually getting is just a record of the phone calls like the numbers called or what time someone called
The courts seem pretty okay with
The government getting access to lots of metadata
Talk about that sure so if we go back to the 1970s
There's a famous case that I read about the book called Smith versus Maryland Smith versus Maryland is one of two cases that form the under
Painting of another fun super catchy legal phrase known as the third party Doctrine
The third party Doctrine comes out of this case
Smith vs Maryland and also case called United States vs Miller
Richmond vs Maryland basically involves a woman who gets
Bugs on her doorstep at midnight in Baltimore in the 1970s and the man who robbed her
Also decided in His Infinite Wisdom that he also was going to make harassing phone calls against her from in some cases
Sit home and in other cases
Nearby payphones
Hopefully the police in that case were able to obtain a court order to get his car record using a device
Vice called a pen register
Again we would maybe today call this
A call log or just metadata righteous essentially showing that he called her at these particular times for you know the
This number of minutes
You know he challenged the fact that the government was able to obtain these call records again without a warrant and also
Julian Smith versus Maryland the Supreme Court decided that no that's not a violation of the Fourth Amendment you don't
I need a warrant to access these types of car records as you say this is a sort of metadata versus
Just content type of Distinction
So that the idea there is that you know the third-party in Smith versus Maryland was
The local phone company in that case and because he used that company to effectuate his calls to call her
That he had given up a privacy interest
In the fact that he
He had called her because he used the phone company
Need to do it and so then the phone company could give up those call records to government or to anybody else
To type you don't more to the modern-day right this is exactly the kind of question that this room Court was facing in Carpenter
Was was this an instance where has the government argued
That accompany could be compelled to hand over Hall records or in this case location records
Of carpenter
In the Supreme Court's decision in Carpenter
The majority found that
The csli the cell site location information
Was basically to private and too personal and you know went too far it was more than just a couple days
Call records
It was in this case 227 days
Literally everywhere this guy went and so they said that that's too invasive
So in this particular case they said that the government had gone too far but the court took great pains to say we're not
Overturning
This third party Doctrine we're not saying that that is
Not good law they said you know it still persists
In other areas but in this case
Where were talking about such a large volume of location information coming from a cell phone we're going to say that the third project
Doesn't apply
Alright so now that I feel like we've gotten a basic legal education which was probably a bit much for every
But worth it
Let's talk about
Smart Home
Because to me everything that we're doing
In the internet today
We're obviously leaving these
Digital footprint says what
What people liked called
But it's scary because
This is a huge amount of data about individuals that is stored in perpetuity or for however long accompanied
Deems it wants it and it's accessible in searchable by
Apple computers which is on
Resident
So keeping all of that and we're bringing it closer and closer into our homes with
Very little understanding of what
Doing so let's talk about
The devices that scare you the most or that you think are
The most rate for
Government overreach
You know all of these
Smart home devices and I'll admit I don't know nearly enough about the Myriad of devices that are out there in comparison to you
But from the ones that I am aware of you know the Amazon Echo or the Google smart home devices are the Apple smart home device
Is or even just something even more basic like a video you know baby monitor for example
To me there have been you know numerous instances of
Certainly questionable situations where whether it's
Some miscreant out in the world you know hacking a baby monitor to say awful things to a young child
All the way up to you know there was a case
Just last year I believe it was we're in Arkansas in a murder trial the government wanted Amazon to turnover record
Heard from an Alexa that was present near the scene of a murder as a way to try to get at what either the victim or
The alleged perpetrator had said in the minutes prior to the murder
And you know this came up a little bit in some listeners may remember
Just a couple years ago there was this so-called FBI versus Apple Showdown that involved a locked iPhone in the wake of The Sandbar
Bernardino terrorist attack here in California and one of the arguments that Apple made was you know sort of what I would call
OB If You Give a Mouse a Cookie argument and this is in her some listeners may be familiar with the children's book
If You Give a Mouse a Cookie and it's just a never-ending list of things that the mouse will want and so basically this is sort of what Apple
Who argued if they said look if we Apple agree to what the government wants
Today if you want us to break our own security and get into this iPhone that was owned by or used by you know now
Now dead terrorist in San Bernardino tomorrow you can ask us to turn everybody's iPhones into tracking devices or you could ask Amazon
How to turn into Lexus intuitive snooping devices in everyone's home we write you know and on and on and on and on we don't yet have the answer to
Do the legal question as to whether or not the government does have the authority to order companies to do their bidding
It's not clear yet
How far the government can go and with the prevalence of all of these kinds
End of devices that people have
Voluntarily brought into their homes
If you are an ambitious FBI agents or local
Police officer
It's easy to understand I think how those types of devices
Could be useful to law enforce
You know I don't know about where you live in Austin but here in Oakland where I live I have many neighbors that have you know surveillance video camera
Outside their homes that are pointed literally at my own driveway and also for the public Street and I know of
Another neighborhoods here in Oakland up instances where local neighborhood groups have voluntarily handed that information
Over to police to bust
Robbery suspects or things like that burglary
Chica understand how that would be useful
But at the same time it's
Very different when a company is being forced
To hand that over and it seems to me that we're rapidly entering a world if we're not there already
Where those types of requests those types of court orders
Are going to become you no more the rule rather than the exception
What kind of precautions do you think
Companies
Need to have in place as they start putting these devices
Yeah that's a good question you know so I think there's this phrase that many people may be familiar with known as privacy by Design
And that doesn't just mean how do you design the actual product of what kind of data does it collect but also a few steps.
Down the road once your products are out in the world what happens when your local police department calls up with ring or a
Any other company and says hey
You know we think that
The data from this device would be helpful in our investigation
And you know I think all of us want
The police
To do their job so I would say if
Accompany
Not to pick on ring in particular but you know what, do you like that that is selling a product that collects you don't visual data audio data on
All kinds of other things
If they don't already have a policy in place as to under what conditions they will
Comply with the government and also it's important
To remember you know are they going to notify the customer who has generated or who is associated with that pitch
Particular device for that particular account
So I would suggest two companies that they really need to think long and hard as to what kinds of information they are collecting
And what they're going to do when the day comes that a government entity wants access to that data
So just to pick a technology that I know we're thinking a lot about and has a lot of surveillance capabilities
What do you think about
Drones
Drones are a technology that I think a very very interesting but also
Very problematic in some ways
Elegant we have to distinguish between the actions of
Private persons are regular individuals like you and me and the actions of the government right because drones are so cheap lawn
Enforcement that traditionally could not afford
Sade have
A fleet of aircraft or helicopters are even one
Can now afford not only a drone but perhaps most
So if you run a Google News search for police acquires drones you'd be surprised
It practically every week somewhere in America you know some County Sheriff for some town
Is now you know buying or expanding its drone Fleet and in many instances those towns or counties
We're cities
Don't always have clear policies as to again and what circumstances they can deploy the drones in what circumstances they don't deploy
Play them what happens to the data that is collected what happens to the videos with the photos that are collected are they allowed to mount
Extra devices on to the Drone such as an infrared camera or other kinds of things are they allowed to loan it out
Two other agencies so a lot of us I think we're just generally unaware as to what kind of surveillance technology our local
Law enforcement have
And if you don't know I would encourage anybody to file a public records request
You don't have to be a lawyer or journalist to do this every state has public records laws and you can you know send an email or a letter
We're to your county sheriff or your Police Department and ask them for a contract purchase records things like that policies regarding
Drones or anything else
Okay so it feels ambitious is a person who
Likes having the convenience and even a little bit of safety associated with some of these devices like I love my smart speaker
I don't want to give it up I actually left my doorbell cam
But how can I take my love of Technology my understanding of technology and apply it towards better
Why so the government doesn't use this kind of stuff
Against me
It feels pretty daunting
It is daunting you're right the first thing is to you know check the Privacy policies that none of us read
Yeah we don't read all the time if you have let's say
A smart doorbell or a smartphone
Security camera or whatever the case may be
Go actually read the policy that the company had laid out
If it's done by a reputable company chances are very good that they will have one of these policies up on their website
And go actually read it if you don't want to read every word just search for it phrases like law enforcement or subpoena or Warren
Or things like that and see
If the terms that they have laid out in that document comport with what you think
Is fair and reasonable for the company to
To do you know and also I would say if you are
Again whether you're a reporter and attorney and activist
Just a regular you know citizen ask your local law enforcement agency
How many times they have you know tried to get at somebody is Alexa data or something like that file record
Request ask
Because I sensibly these agencies are supposed to be accountable to us
And it's hard for reporters like you and me to find out and we rely on individuals to come forward and
And tell us you know hey this thing happened to me or I found out that my County Sheriff was doing X Y and Z and I'm really worried about that
That so I would say you know asked around and if you don't think that you're in a good position to tell the world then you know
No contact me or you or any other reporter that you think would be receptive to that type of information
All right well service thank you so much for coming on the show today I really appreciate it
My pleasure
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at stays
AC on iot cam will see you next week