Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have got
I said amazing show for you today
We are going to talk about Amazon's new drop-in feature adding more context
Typical home
Applebee's tracking firm
And we're going to do some thought experiments on ransomware
Plus we got a new phone for the iot and I got to review
Woohoo I've been you Eero
Routers
Arabic songs for this week is TE Connectivity
Guest Daniel elazar
He's going to explain how to build and manage
Products
So
State
And now a message from another sponsor
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about Affiliated monitoring
In response to a trigger from any connected device affiliate is professionally trained live agents can follow up
Protocol and reach out to your customers
Their loved ones and local emergency services Affiliated works with hundreds of smart home security help
And other iot businesses visit Affiliated.com iot to read a case study
And how they help to connect guitar startup turn an idea into a thriving business with a hundred-million-dollar exit
Affiliated. Com
Splash iot
All right
Let's get into our shows
Speaking of show next week we're going to have the Amazon Echo Show
But in the meantime we should actually talk because some of the reviews are out
And
I know I felt like they were like
It's got the screen is desiigner
It was a mixed bag in the reviews and it's funny because the hardware itself
People did complain about the design felt it was chunky block Etc
And it actually brings me back to the very first Kindle device which was also
Very angular and odd you know Jenna was remember that the page Kindle
About Amazon website
Yellow
It's blocking a junkie
Amazon
They are not here to design things to sell you things in the most efficient and cost-effective
Way possible
That they are that they are
Again I did not order when you did and you should have one like
Probably right after the show it's going to be delivered
UPS come to my house at 1:45
Oh I'm sorry
What what you're getting
I'm not
You know I get to see you again from going back-to-back the original Fire TV
But has the
Cards for
Madam a
On the screen that there's a benefit to that especially for the bedside device and so on
And for people who maybe you're not tech-savvy want to keep in touch with family
Tweety's Echo shows would be
Would be handy but
I don't know I will say this
Amazon continues to evolve the whole Smart Home
Product line
Far faster both hardware and software
Then anybody else on the market today and I'll give him credit for that
I agree with you and
Working
Hard to
Say hey is this working
So there are really actually moving
And I love it
Some features that might make the show work for some people with Smart Homes
So they brought in several camera
Suzhou Logitech
Cameras and
My August doorbell camera actually can feed into the show
When I get it
Those are the kind of things that you know
Might
Mater to
No doubt no doubt right rather than have you know
Paleta smartphone and look at the feed whatever it mean it's just easily accessible you know if you have that show in your room
What I imagined Google will do in response is
You know the Google home doesn't need a screen because you can
Chromecast use the Chromecast on your TV if you have that always on
Sunday now you can just be like
You don't need a device with a dedicated screen to send it to your television
I will show up.
So that's kind of where I see probably Google heading in that direction there's pros and cons to this
I mean obviously if your TV is on watching something you don't want to be interrupted with
Bright
Order pizza
But then again I mean it wouldn't be a stretch to see a little picture in picture pop up
Did a programmatically appear as soon as
If somebody's at the door so it doesn't take away from the viewing experience of
Whatever you were doing beforehand so AT&T I never very clearly
Like 15 years ago show this for Smart Home
Digital Life was part of U-verse
So I'll go
Yeah
So if you're right picture and I always forget about picture in picture
So
That could
Definitely
We should mention
That we
Talk about the Google home stuff
Because Android police did a teardown of the latest
App update for the Google home and they noticed a couple things they notice bluetooth support which
Pair more devices to the stadium or speakers
Yeah
And then you can also set
Default help
Put devices so you
You can actually say
Hey
This guy the Google home in my living room
I want you to talk to my living room
Which
As the default
Yes as a default which means it's automatically going to
Go there so in that
Future that we just talk
You might have to set your defaults but then poop that's where they're just going to send it
Yeah nope
Android Police
Does a lot of Android app teardowns and some of those things pan out some of them don't have the code is in there
Where to enable those two features that you just mentioned
But it's not
Active
Right
And Google did talk about this though at
Their last
That I oh I oh I was so excited
Everyone else was like no product
Cohasset vision for context
Andrew
Kevin was writing about context
Yeah I was Google Now on my wrist I said I want to see it and lo and behold we got it
Alright Amazon also announced a fun new feature
I personally wanted like women
It launched so I'm excited about
It's Erica
And isn't this will work on your show this work on your dots this work on your
I don't know if it would work
Taps who has a tap you know what it actually I tested I have a tattoo I have one of each type of echo
It does not show up as an option on my tab
I might at brother
Okay so
Kevin has answered both questions
Kevin has the tap and it does not work
So there's a couple ways you can use this I actually used it from The Madam a app on my phone
By going to conversations
And that's where you can see the
Voice calling that you might have done you see a history there in your contacts
But the very top of that screen there's a blue bar that says drop in
When you tap that it shows you which Echo devices you can drop in on
I have three right here if I tap any one of those
That device will actually make a sound like an incoming call but little
Ring light
Turn green
And it now becomes an intercom
So it's an intercom between my phone through the app and that Echo
But I think you can do it
Without the app as well
Okay one thing to know before you start
Dropping in on people in trying to make this work
This is based on the name of
Your Echo
When you install that you had to give it a name
If you gave it a cute fun name like
She who shall not be named
You're not going to want to keep that you're going to
Probably for the intercom feature what I keep it as the name of the room that it's in
Who is your go-to one of your echos
And you'll say
Madam
Drop in on
Bedroom
And then
It will the light will turn green up there and
Chime will sound and
You are working
If you can drop in and you can talk to whomever
You can actually also do it like a formal phone call
If you think that someone might be busy
And so then you would say
Madam a
Call
And then what's going to happen is the person actually has two
Answer you
Two ways to do a drop-in is like
I'm here
And the other one is like
Oh
I'm trying to get
Attention
I like both approaches and part of the reason is when this was announced a lot of folks who wrote it up as
You able to spy on
And listening on people in your house and so on
And you made it sound like they wouldn't know that you're doing this but
It's so far in my usage it's very clear
Between a chime and the ring light
But you are either, glistening talking Etc
So I don't
I don't have that concern of a from a privacy standpoint
And I actually so my husband and I tested this and he was able to walk
All the way across the bedroom
And I could still hear it just fine
Can you
Well I have my stepdaughter is a low top
Then she wasn't facing the echo
It might have to understand my family does not like to test things with me this stuff they don't put their all into it so
It could have just been that she's a low talker
I don't know
I suspected it work for you and your husband I'm sure it's going to work fine for everybody else
You know I feel like kids voices
Understanding my daughter sometime
Redis clear
Okay
Let's see what else do we have that was so much like a personal assistants exciting
We got apple
Confirm
That's it
That's the report I mean you never really know
What two apple has purchased until usually long after the fact
But I didn't use shell companies and so on so
The report is that
They purchased sensomotoric
If I'm saying that correctly
Which is a
German company that has 1991
They have developed a range of eye tracking
Hardware and software through 4 lotto verticals
And it sort of makes sense if this is
That this might be true
Because there's been a lot of discussion about Apple getting in on
AR VR
Wearables possibly although so far that's all just
Speculation
Because at WWDC they were showing a rnvr through
AR kit
Bearcat which is been very impressive from what I seen so far
Many of the people who work in PR that I talk to
They're like this is really powerful and it's really easy and
It's already on everybody
When I was 11 right
Isn't this company makes glasses
Peoples Natural Gas
In real time
And it is up to a hundred and twenty hurts which is super fast
A lot
That's a lot
And
The benefit here is
If you know where someone's looking it's a more granular
Data field
For you to actually
Zhu Zhu it's it's less jerky
Fluid
Yeah I mean that you're getting analytics that
You might not think you could get a sense
But they would be very valuable for a developer to have
These type of analytics are pretty useful and in fact it was earlier this month at YouTube
Was actually showing off video analytics through VR
And of course
Are being owned by Google alphabet.
Probably more for
Add sewing thing for ad targeting
To see what people are looking at as opposed to a developer
But either way I'm into to be able to get this type of granular data on what people actually looking at is it school
Going to open up new markets
And
Possibly
Confirm that people are ignoring ads
That's true
Let's see
What else do we have we have a hundred million dollar fund from Trent
This is Jennifer.
We don't know a lot about this but they said this week
And this is the typical corporate investment strategy what it looks like is
Dollars to invest
And they're trying to get an understanding of how
To think about Security in the eye
So this looks very strategic for
We've had we shared some thoughts on
Security iot in the past
Oh gosh I don't think I have a day doesn't go by that I don't think about security and iot
So yeah this is interesting I too am looking for a threat model like a way to think about securing the internet of things which is
It's just completely massive
And it's really probably
It's more a model of thinking about how to secure
So many highly distributed
Devices that
Are really relatively dumb
What are going to have very complicated permissioning
Between them
That's kind of how I'm thinking about it I however do not have a hundred
Million dollars to invest so you should probably talk to
At first but then you can call me
I could start a $10
Oh yeah
I'm sure I could make it even to hunt
I mean let's be generous
410x already
Speaking of security
There is a wannacry variant running around
Hitting everything
This is a ransomware attack
Which is basically where companies are like
They wake up one morning
They got a message and it's like hey you can't access your data because
We've got it and we've encrypted it and if you want the key to unencrypt it
You got to pay us X number of Bitcoin
So people freak out this is Ben
Ongoing for a while
What are predicted late last year
Included in my annual predictions
Is this is going to be a big deal for iot
Not necessarily for
Attacking
Individual consumers
Protagonist company
Hey
If you want your thermostat to work
Pay this meeting points maybe it would attract consumers I just feels weird.
Especially
Cloud-based iot service providers that are at risk
And it wouldn't be hey do you want your thermostat to work it would be
Do you want your
10 million
Customers thermostats to work
Right
So yeah
Way better
Please don't use it
As soon as I read the news about how this new variant I think it's called Pacha
It's hit
N64 countries
And some of the various
Companies that it is hit I mean the major shipping company
Maersk is it
The proper pronunciation
They they were only able to
Send out like one of their shipping boats
Only one
Then they like one of the largest shipping providers around the world
As a result of being hit by this
You know
It got me thinking about
Boy the IRT service providers better
Better not get lock out
Just think of it again the scalability of how many
People be impacted if
A Samsung
SmartThings
Platform
Was locked out of the top
A wink and Nest mean there's just so many
Especially if it has a ransomware
Kind of
Attached to it it's one thing if your device doesn't
So if you get a message
My device doesn't
You're like
Son of a gun
And you get kind of frustrated
Hey this platform has been compromised until Samsung pay
You know all your data belongs to us
And then I would say
That's a different level of freaked out cuz you're like
Yep I got who has access to Lake
When I'm home
When I'm not home my security alarm
That is a berry
But if they're attacking
Provider and not the consumer directly
That's going to freak people to hack out
Is it true that
Is it is it should I I think I mean this type of attacks or less about getting the data although I
Share your concern
I'm sitting here going I walk up to my house and I can't unlock my front door now
And neither can any of the other three million people or router many that have the same lock as me
Yep that's true
I don't carry it
I have my watch or my phone that has the app
It's a Kwikset
It is just use a screwdriver
I can't believe you went there
It's true
I have a Kwikset lock
Vanitas Z-Wave screwdriver
Thanks I'm changing my lock now
You're like great did you send this to me you did
Not mocking it locks anymore
This attack is really scary it's spreading very quickly
It's part of a new type of attacks just like wannacry was
They call them network-based attacks
And we could go into that
Stop that
To tell you that this is actually a big deal because it's hitting
Infrastructure
Not just computers
So
This attack picture or variants of it
Which confusingly is called
Not not yet you
Is
It's running a muck and the way to stop it do we have a way to stop at yet I don't
You know what that there was a report
I want a security researcher that if you created a read-only file with a certain name
That it would stop it
And I know that
One email provider
Tank in Germany
Has disabled
The email address
Of we're supposed to send the Bitcoin but that's a problem because
Now even if you want to pay it you can't so that it doesn't seem like the smartest solution to me
Yeah that I saw that and I was kind of like
You have a good excuse but if the hacker still doesn't give
What you doing
Still kind of screwed
So that's a very legal
Kind of
Weight attack
It's a big
And
Once again is highlights
How unready we are to actually move
Everything online
And how the old security models
Are now being exploited
Because we haven't adapted
To this agreement
So things like
How do you patch test
How do you deal with
Problems when they occur
How do you get people to upgrade to the latest version of os has on their computers because a lot of these
Types of attacks are on
Older
Versions of OSS
Industrial or even Medical Society
Yep
People who manufactured this
They don't support
Upgrades to a nice early
Which means if you're if you bought like a million ATMs you don't want to update
Beto's in potentially
Break all the stuff
You really want your vendors
Help there
I just I just had this conversation with my son who works at Wawa which is a convenience store chain on the East Coast
And we were
Discussing two nights ago on the deck I said what
Systems do your point of sale
Systems take baby touchscreens for ordering at the deli and all that
Windows 95
I said I said you know I mean
If I knew what I was doing I can come in there and you know a taxi sings of the virus he's like well you just have the point of sale
System that that may not be connected to our corporate system
But what if I held them Ransom across all 665 stores
And you couldn't take orders at your Deli how much would that cost your store
And then all the sudden he got silent
Yeah not to mention stealing people's credit card
Why will these you don't pay at those terminals okay
What are point
But they think they're safe and they're not
Exactly
And that is kind of
That is where we are today in that we
This is going to be a giant
Honking bass until
We get all of these old systems
Updated or out
I talk to people in the medical industry and they're like God we are like 15 to 20 years out from that because
Those purchasing Cycles
Even today people are still
At the board level or the purchasing level
Turn on Tech stuff so things that they perceive as being non-tech
Point-of-sale system
They're like
How do I really want to pay the extra money for security
And the answer is often no
I don't think they look at it I don't think that's the question they ask themselves or like do we need to upgrade a point-of-sale system know it's worth
Working fine how much would it cost how much would it cost to upgrade
Tiffany
Really not whatever MyPay
Guess what you could pick a cost you more lost Revenue by not doing it with another new from the Securities and they're not
Not looking at it that way
Not the equations
The people are
Making in their hair
That's all be terrified
And talk about the
Like
I have the new Eero routers that we talked about
Couple weeks ago
I have been testing them but I will admit to not testing them too long because I came while I was in Costa Rica
One does not test routers
Vacation
This one.
Other people
So these are the
And Eero Pro
Routers
And they
Are more powerful the beacon is smaller
And plugs in
So it's kind of like a
Flume say it
Oh I need a little bit more WiFi coverage
Send
There's two things I can't
One is I could go all around my house
I did go all around by house testing like Netflix streams and that sort of thing which seem to be
The biggest test
I could come up with
I did not run a software like JP
Detest
The actual
Signal strength
6 megabits per second
In the
Clear reason
Like I did think about doing it and I was like you know what
Wi-Fi today
In many homes when you have sufficient
Connection and I've got a 305
Bit per second connection
So at that point
I don't actually
Care about getting
Even bad Wi-Fi is good Wifi in your house
Right so that the real issue is coverage it's so
Where can I go in my house
Inexperienced
And I think honestly that's how we should start testing
Because
Especially when you're a lot of the reasons people upgrade their Wi-Fi networks is because you know you're
Sticking up
Connect sprinkler in a garage somewhere in the garage has crappy WiFi
And you know that sprinklers only going to need like a 1.5 megabit per second connection
Right it doesn't need to Speed it needs the ability to communicate
Reliably in
Consistently
Exactly
That was my thinking
In this you guys can
Call and tell me
That that stupid
Ectasia Rock
So
IWatch all around my house
Everything worked I had a challenging area
It's actually worth
Contesting doorbells so I have this challenging area right outside my backdoor
So I went out there and I spent some time
With some connected doorbells
Those
Had better
Wi-Fi signals as measured from the doorbell app
Based on the DBS
So
It seems like these actually offer better
Pepperidge
Then my existing which were the old school year
Is this going to work for everyone
That's becoming the question with
By any answer is
I don't know
You really have to install
That's it that's kind of crappy answer
But it's it's a fair
Answer because everybody's
Infrastructure is different your house or townhouse your apartment your office building
It all depends on the layout depends on the materials
That are used to construct it
So you can't say it's going to work for everybody
Nobody can
But
You can eventually I don't know if they do it yet
You can add the extra Beacon
So if you have really crappy coverage
You're going to be able to buy a beacon in just be like
And plug it in
So
The Eero beacons $149
Enable ship in July
It also doubles as a night light
Mine is currently up mine is actually in the roof
On the roof
On a roof
In a cabin
It's so
The night light does not
Really
Help their the idea of the night light is actually one so you don't stick it in the cabinet like I did
Depreciate
Appreciate is not the word
Where do you usually
Negative negatively impacts the signal
Thank you Kevin
But
You can put this in your hallway
I actually thought about putting in my hallway because I always right about those doors weren't testing those doorbells and I thought
Good way to add connectivity there
There was also announced that they were going to launch to Services when is a security service in one is a parental control service
Those are not available on my test app
So do not test those but I'm really eager to test those cuz for $10 a month it's something I might actually buy
Yeah
Well that's it on the Eero
It's time for
Kevin
How to say sayonara in for us to
Take a message for my sponsor and then
Come back
For some really cool tips on how to build and manage connected products this is a product manager who's built
Any iot products were going to talk about
Sustainable business models
How to talk to your engineers
And more
Stay tuned for all of that
And we'll see you next week everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast
Message from our sponsor sponsor is TE Connectivity and I have Nick Langston
Head of Business Development at TE Connectivity to talk about the smart
So let's kick this off with a quick reminder what is TE Connectivity do
TV connectivity mix
Sensors
Antennas
Huge variety
Connectors
That appear in all manner of device
Message from consumer electronics to Home Appliances that Aerospace
Medical devices
We're here today to talk about
How I can get a smart kitchen
What we see happening in the
Today is
Device manufacturers are adding sensors that take advantage of
Increase precision
To enable
Usersub make meals
With
More consistency
With less effort
They're also really focused on using this increased Precision in sensing to improve efficiency
We're in the business of manufacturing
Watches that can get those jobs done for everyone
And when you think about it there's a lot of different places in the kitchen that are really rather harsh be
Because exposed to extremely low temperatures extremely high temperatures
Exposed to a lot of moisture
A lot of motion it takes a particular skill set
To design
Sensors
Connectors and things that can withstand assorted
Environment
Precision sounds really awesome but it also makes it sound professional
How can the smart kitchen
Actually help everyone
We think about the
Smart kitchen
As being
The area in the Smart Home
That
Really begins to deliver a lot of value
To the public
Early on
People on connected home things
Because the kitchen is the place where we really begin our lives at home
It's all about what's cooking what's going on how we talk to each other how we gather as a family that'll happen
In the kitchen and if we can leverage sensing
And connect
Activity
With all of the data now available
What about us as individuals
And What Makes You mistake online then we can leverage that to live healthier and happier life
For example if we think about a week when
Weave
Just nailed it and everything's gone right for us we can look back on that week
It's okay I had two healthy meals I didn't know reason had a lot of junk food that I had good activity
Think about a bad week
Maybe you say I am
Too much junk food I was traveling a lot of fast food
With the smart kitchen
Your appliances
May actually be able to
Know about your current health they may communicate with your
Wearable device to know what kind of activity you had during the day and they can leverage artificial intelligence
To understand what
Sort of Neil
You should be eating
Hear a t e connectivity we want to provide the
Sensors
Activity and even the system
That helped make that possible
In appliances
The Senate May look like something like a wireless
Power and data trend
Ignition system
Some new cooking appliance whether it says sous vide circulator or
Smart coffee machine
Where can people go to find out more about TE Connectivity
We invite the audience to check us out
Ged.com connected home
Hey everyone about them to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And today I have an awesome guest for you guys his name is Daniel Elizalde
He is the founder of tech product manager
And today we're going to talk about
How to introduce your own iot products to the market or how you should think about that if your company is trying to do this
Thanks for coming on the show this week
Thank you so much for having me and really excited to be
I am too I'm excited you're here because
My gosh I see a lot of companies saying Hey to the mix
We're going to watch a connected product
And then they do something and it's terrible
So I'm hoping that maybe this conversation will
Stop a little bit of that from happy
Boston I come up to you and I'm like that
We need some IRT
Is that really the right approach
Yeah that's a really good point because
That's what I see a lot of
Company
Today pay here that iot
He has all this potential
Opportunities
And then
We need an iot
Aetna really not understanding
Iot is just a tool that can help
Solve the customer's problem in a better cheaper faster way
So by understanding what problem did really trying to solve
Then you can analyze if iot with all these components and all the benefits
Actually the right Solutions
And once you have that understanding you can go through
Process to understand all the different pieces
How they fit together
If there's a business case
Jump that step I launched into
We're building
So let's have identified
Problem is it safe to say that there's probably a few more steps once I've identified that problem before I should launch into
Yes there's actually a lot of different
Places that you can go through to
Valley Faith with her. Problem is
First of all that's a traditional
Weather. Problem is worth
I'll be
But then once you figure out that your company
That's found a problem when solving
And they are well suited to solve it
It's not the same thing
And you can go into
The process of understanding
What it would take to do it from an iot
That's where
I think there's a lot of
Confusion between companies because iot sonido and it has so many different components
Even if they're able to identify the problem
The transition from
Strategy to
A lot of things get lost bear
Alright so
How should I
Think about this
Cuz like
For a while
A lot of connected products were coming on the market and they basically were like you can control XYZ from your phone
And most people are like
That sounds great
Actually I don't to pay three times as much for something
Like to turn on crock pot for my phone
How do I get people to think about
Connectivity and really applying it to
I guess useful make sense for their business
The way I think about it is that
Dislike song
What are the problems that companies
Particularly are trying to solve
They already have those problem
So companies are coming up with
New problems
Barefoot products
So bad
Are the ones that
Falling to this
Not enabled
But let's say that you are a manufacturer that sells
A particular
Type of
Epic Motors
And then your customers
They are
1 C to
Get more value out of those Motors because they say that they are discussing the money because there's
So the customer already has. Problem
And you have been having that problem
Forever we discussed
Society doesn't really opening
How can you apply this new technology to solve that problem in a better way so that
You can provide
More value to your crush
Ultimately they don't care about iot
People don't buy a
Customer doesn't really care about how
Take care about
How you going to help them
Bottom line
About my opinion
I don't like
Problems with companies
And how can you enhance that
Caballo tea to bring more value to your customers
Okay so
Maybe I should think of this is
Classes of problems that the internet of things are adding connectivity consol what would those be
Challenges that we have with the term biote is that it's all-encompassing
Anything that connects to the internet
And 1/2 component on the difference
But there's a big difference in the car
Solutions for healthcare
Consumer products like wearables
Smart buildings
Smart TVs to military to energy
So I think that
The class
Problems
Are going to be dependent on the industry that you're serving
You're going towards the industrial manufacturing setting
The challenges that they have always had have to do with up time
Reboot of their production line
Purchasing cost
If you're looking at it
Call Darius
Convenience
Give me five different systems of data
So that's the kind of problems you can solve
Kindred Healthcare well that's a highly regulated area so
Problems that have to do with
Ensuring Precision of instrumentation to be single time
There's no one killer application for iot
One solution
Classes of problems
Which detergent
Solving approach
With the corresponding Eye Institute.
One of the things that I see
It's a different process
Understanding
Who are the customers
Anubis digging into what
Text problems
So sometimes
Even if you were focusing on a specific vertical let's say
Black building
And
You are creating a product
Connected
A device that controls the air conditioning to say
Energy
Buildings need to save energy there for dissolution is going to work out
But it turns out that when you actually do
Some user research
Care about serving energy
That much they really cared about the other colors not be running in there cooking
Or their security in the building so
All the sudden you have this companies that come in with IBS
Back from the customer
Could be okay if I cared about that problem
Let's get into this idea business models because
I think a lot of companies throughout connected products and services without thinking about
Supporting them over the life there Prada
So their business model doesn't necessarily match with
Product that they put out there
I think people are realizing that
They made some mistakes
Child services on a product
But
How do you advise companies to
Identify their problem and then before they even start building
Product to think about
How they're going to
Pay for it or how they're going to charge cup
Converse all these different areas
In order of
Understanding
On the way aye
Set this up is in a way that is Progressive
So once you understand your users and understand your data
And having a date
Ticketfly see a lot of companies doing is that
They say we're going to going to
Add sensors to whatever we are selling
And that's it
When you probe deeper text what are you going to do with that data
I will figure it out later
And it turns out that later Never Comes
A lot of fees in the clouds
Space
Storage Etc
By going through a process that can
Help you understand
All the different components of a solution
How long do you intend your system to be on the field and therefore
How long do you have to
Be able to get revenue from that customer can make it
Bible all those things
Is what I see is important
What to do
Even before you start for the types of before you raise Capital before you launch
I understand your data strategy
What is
Is model support that strategy
And that all of those things are interrelated because the technology has to be at a price point
And that's what all this change
Play together
If you add more data then
Cost you
Marcos Torres so therefore you going to have to charge more
And by being able to understand all these different
Complexity
Then
I'm more realistic
Memorial Estates
Road map
That actually
Pictures of passports profitability
As opposed to just
Cool
Technological solution
I'm sitting here looking at your iot decision framework and for folks who care I will put it in the show notes
But you got
You excited
So and that's actually less about like
Ux it sounds like
Well it is still your ex but it's more about identifying the need of your customer
You got the business model that you're going to work from the technology
Then you move to security so a thank you for having
Security in there
Is a lot of people feel like security something that should be designed in from the beginning
This is obviously a I think still before you put anything together but can you talk about like how you think about security and house
Please back with everything that you've talked about that comes before
Yes that's a very good point send
The reason I put security here
After technology
The way
I use this framework is
It's a matrix
So you look at each of those items
At each layer of the Earth
Iot technology stack support example when you looking at business
A look at the business implications
But then also
Empathize Hardware perspective
Application
You're going down then you have
Technology so
What cigar did you going to use to solve V
And then
Security cam player because
Unless you understand what the technology
What you going to say
Security risk management
It's a located that you should be able to
Beginning to end
Before you
Start developing anything
So in that sense
It is baked into your design
And then you have to understand
What security
You need a device Hardware other device off when they are a Communications
What's the worst that can happen
That's true and understanding your customer base is in
Port near to because
A medical device is very different
From a security standpoint than a consumer thermostat
Or a Bluetooth
And that's why in the framework but I have a case
Starting with ux witches understand your user
It's so if you understand
Persona 4
Different user involved throughout the life cycle
Then you can say you know what
Security
Even though we might be in a highly regulated energy
Well
Security is going to be most important for us at the device Hardware because
Physical tampering
I supposed to the car application
Assessment
And you say
Might different users care about Security in this difference
Layers
And I am comfortable with this levels of risk
Now here's the fun part of all
All this
This
Is a real
And I think it's it actually is a very nice
Way of thinking about
It's also this is a very fast-moving area
And so
How much time should a company
Take on this
Put everything
Together so
All teams should be looking at you like salty should be looking at 8
Ed
But I do work substitute teacher
A week or so working with your team you can actually learn the framework
You should be able to fill this out really quickly or so if you spending too much time on this
So that you understand all the different things and you make the fish
And my
To go with a minimum viable product
You always going to be learning
But at least
And then turn right on
And the other thing is that
Isolation because the industry moves so far my recommendation is
Look for Market fit before everything else
A lot of companies that are coming from
Having hyperthyroidism having a lot of experience there
They thrive
Forecast
They want to have the cheapest product
Smallest products in Market
And I
Paint that is actually
Putting the cart before the horse
Do something even if it's broken
With other types of components from third-party vendors
So that you
Verify that the
Traction in the market
Watch contraction in the market then you can actually start by finding your offering
To make it faster
Cheaper smaller etcetera
And
Here's a tough question
Cuz I think a lot of the benefits that
Connectivity will bring to businesses
Is an Ashley in a physical product in some cases it might be a service
And I'm thinking of things like you know being able to order a Domino's Pizza
Amazon
In this this feels very
Physical product oriented but I'm curious if this can be adapted to
Just probably thinking about how connectivity everywhere is going to disrupt
All kinds of businesses in
Thinking about using this
Even to deliver services
Azure software
Yes I can see that's a great observation in
I think this
Generic
It has all the different components that you can eat
And then ask your realtor Progressive than you can focus on a specific area
Example of the echo
The echo have all these components
But as you continue to evolve it into stay now the echo
Orders pizza
Well that is just
Focusing on the device
Software area
In the voice recognition and artificial intelligence
So you can actually have
And then it just touches
Sum of the parts
You don't have to do everything every single time
What are
Sir product mistakes
They have gone before so
What are some some ways that people have not
Follow this
How to fight them
The first one is not understanding who your users are
And what problems are you really looking
Salt for them
So that it's a combination of
Not having user
And also the technology
Leading the way
I think a lot of companies
Think that iot is going to
Open your doors from a technology perspective
The temperature to Dollar Tree without really understanding that you
Another
So the idea is that you can
Add sensors
So that you can collect information
2Pac somebody
If you don't have a clue what the value is going to be
Going to be really hard to
Justify
Cost
Later or change it to your organization
Or anything else
Business
You have to think that
Other couple of my area that I think are
Often not understood correctly security
Speculation
Companies don't really take the time to understand what regulations are going to eat
Especially if they're going to go to work
Like energy or Healthcare
You know what they're getting into otherwise
It's never going to
Adoption or purchase etcetera
Other types of
Examples of smart buildings
Now
You have to deal with building code
Exchanges in different districts and municipalities and you have to have all the different
I completely outside of the technologically well
A lot of companies just
Don't think about that
So my recommendation is
Think about it
I get the rice counseling to make sure you understand
What the regulations
And in the
Area
Regulation changes your back
How do you ask your users what they want especially when we're kind of in this place where we it's like your users don't even know
What they want
Give them what they need not necessarily what they want
And that's why I'm a big proponent uaccess
Techniques that you can do to observe your users
Their uses
Won't be able to tell you
What solution they want
But they can tell you what the problem is
And it's your responsibility
To come up with something.
Salt. Net for them in a way that make
Makes sense
There are a few of my favorite things
To observe your users in the wild identify who uses our first of all
And then go out there and spend the day with them and interview them even how they interact with their environment
Problems first time
Then
Costume
Identify the problem
Keep that
Discovery and research mentality swap
And other
Types of Technology
But they need to make it deeper into
Iot is what
To be a part of everything
Needs to be part of the toolbox if any product manager
So that we can understand
And then
Only then proposed what solution to fit them
All right
Thank you
Thank you so much for having me
Really exciting
To be able to have this conversation with you
You just had it with
Carlos Nursery thank you so much that's it for this week's show thank you so much for this
Listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things at stake
Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week