Hey everyone welcome
To the internet
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
At your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
We have an Aloha shirt
Aloha
We are going to talk about Facebook's plans possibly for a smart speaker
How Google took sensors and Ai and saved a lot of money and data center Cooling
A new survey about how scary iot is Plus
A couple exploits that
Show how scary is he his
In our news this week
Some Acquisitions to talk about
Industrial iot and
Be Fitbit charge 3
And
This week
Our Guest is Tyler Baker who is the CTO of foundries. IO this is a brand-new iot
Platform from the
The people who brought you lindaro
This is
We'll talk about is basically offering security-as-a-service
Interesting points there
And we're going to have a message from our sponsor Netgear
Talking about
Inside wi-fi system
So let's get this show started
With a message from
Another one
This week sponsor is a pharaoh are you looking for an iot platform find out why Kenmore
Angelique picked a farro a farro customers have experienced as much as 80% reduction in
I'm too Market 99% you are support calls and a 10x higher activation rate
They can we use 90% of their work from one project to the next to learn more is it a pharaoh
Bro. IO that's a f e r o. IO
Okay Kevin
Let us get this
Party started
Let's talk about Facebook
Aloha
I don't know if they mean Hello or goodbye
That is there
Voice
Service that they are
Planning to do there's a Code out there for Aloha even leading to additional code talking about a smart
Speaker called
Portal
And
I think
We talked about a Facebook speaker in the past because
They were supposed to be rolling out
Speaker earlier last year
That is high 1 and 2
Yeah she makes sense because Facebook doesn't make any hardware so I don't know what kind of
Economies of scale they have to build off of it.
Point right so that's
It's going to be a challenge for that Miss fat is
True on the price
Yeah
Lynch
Pink is
Privacy
Facebook
People don't really trust based
And that was why
Put their plans on hold it sounded like originally
I don't think they've actually solve their problems
Sweet People worried about privacy I know that people are still on Facebook
But think about how prevalent the rumor is that
Your Facebook is constantly listening in even on your phone people take this all the time cuz they'll be talking about something
Sunnyvale CA
Yeah that's a good point in fact the whole speaker plans
Seem to fall
Part last year when there were major privacy concerns brought up by the US government with the election and
Other consumer issues there so yeah and it made sense to back off on that up
I'm not even sure it makes sense to
Continue it though you tell me and I do use Facebook Facebook for my private stuff we have a Facebook page
Stacey on iot
So we use it
Mail from business standpoint
And I use messenger with the family because that allows me to be crossed
Platform since I switched phones
SOI Theron on iMessage
Set reminder on Android you can't get me there so
I don't really see the
Point of this because they want to add voice to their
Messaging apps
And
Perhaps
Through your posts even through Instagram is a chat service and I don't see a huge benefit they're from
An end-user standpoint I certainly see a benefit for Facebook cuz maybe we'll get even more of our day.
What do you think even though you may not use Facebook as much as I do
Will it might be because when you talk to Facebook
Messenger
You're actually using
Google are apples
Speech to text
Yes because that's the keyboard will pop up so whatever keyboard you're using and it could be a third-party keyboard in fact on Android
Somebody else is getting the data Facebook is not
The only thing you can do natively in the app is record a voice clip which then gets sent as an audio file
Okay so Facebook probably wants access to that sweet sweet voice data
Because then you can build all kinds of
Another idea in this does not throw me at all but
Die-hard Facebook users might but imagine something like Google's
Flip camera that uses machine-learning to understand when to take the best pictures
Maybe imagine like something like that in your home from Facebook and then you could just send those pictures to your loved ones
I would again never do that
But I would never do that either but your point makes more sense when you even think about the patents that Facebook
Has which also came to like this week via TechCrunch reported this story they have they been Facebook as a pet
For a smart
Speaker as well as a
Smart camera and a video
Camera so
Doesn't mean you're going to use those patents for actual products but you're right they could
Facebook with
And so when I can people
I guess I mean
It's really a shame that we don't have unified platform
Farms for video chat
Thanks apple with FaceTime
Hangout I guess
I'm just kind of like
You know the telephone at work so well right now we're adding video
We want to share so much more with our loved ones in
The telephone was great except that little rotary thing with numbers on it and it just doesn't make sense to Millennials it's actually kind of funny
Chords
Okay
Let's talk about
This is an iot story
Sort of
It's been
What is why you put all these sensors in place
It's not because you're like
It's so you guys should do cool things
Lake Google basically save 40% in cooling cost or electrical cost for there
Data Center
Beihai
And again the sensors that.
People that data
So every time we talk about businesses and iot we're talking about this idea
Digital transformation
This is a really great
And scary example
Doing that and moving from
The AI making recommendations to people
To actually
Take action in automator
This is a really scary step whenever I talk to Industrial iot people there like
That's a terrible idea will never do it
Well they made
Google did
And again
Energy-savings
And see I think this is what people lose when they talk about IRT because it means so many things to so many different people weave
We've had data collection and big data for several years now
Analyzing data is not new
Doing something
Automated
Based on the data
That is new
The new wish in a way that people can have a bad day and I noticed something
And then you can make even finer
More finely-tuned things when you're automating based on machines
I'm excited about
So this is a big deal it almost actually
The Energy savings
Garnered from this almost made up for
The cost
Energy using
Kris of adding new data centers
So is a big deal because
As you guys are
Crusader digital footprint
Connected devices best we need to build data centers and eventually we could be like
Data centers are sucking on their power
About 1.8% of all electricity generated according to a report in 22
Is a long time ago
That actually that report was saying that by now would be
We almost be screwed but
So far we're using things like Renewables and
Techniques like this to
Keep it
Relatively flat
Which is good now we just need the Bitcoin miners to stop
Yeah a lot of areas have you
Speaking of what type of scary
This is a survey from dynatrace
Over half of consumers worldwide are using iot devices
Two-thirds of those
I've already encountered
Performance issue
And
SLO with lots of devices
True statement
Consumers experience on average 1.5 digital performance problems every day
And 62% of people fear the number of problems they encounter in the frequency will increase due to the rise of iot
Just call that glitches
This ridiculous that was interesting as well 72% of consumers Faith likely that glitches in iot apps will cost
Serious injuries
Yes I could
Of course
They're including in the survey they talked about self-driving cars and so on
Support so yeah you have a glitch there
Certainly you
Probably have an injury but
Regardless
It's a valid concern performance issues they're worried about RB
Because of bugs in them
Technology
It has not been part of the reason it has not it's because I
WiseWay two years ago we bought this house
I've never carried a key to this house
But the Smart Lock I bought
Has a
Keypad as well
So the only way I can be locked out is it the battery
Actually die
That is
However however
Just like people use the little high-tech he's actually hide a key somewhere
Somebody smart locks
Have 9 volt terminals
Hidden underneath them if you have a 9-volt battery you can give enough
Juice to actually get in your house
I'm not saying I hit a battery but
You never know
Karaoke I carry a knife
Little steel wall I can start a fire
Yes
Absolutely put steel wool on a 9-volt battery new and turns into flames
Very handy for camping
Life or death situations
Okay you're my friend I'll carry steel wool
You carry your battery and
And together
When we conquer the world
We're ready for the Apollo
Okay
Zombies
Let's talk about some another performance problems associated with the iot
64% of customers fear not being able to control lights in the
Okay this is happened to me
Insomniac
Vacations all ask madame
Somehow
My
Get connected light switch
Become disconnect
From something
Or they'll get reset
So this is a legit
Agreed
Senior
And this is kind of a
This is why we think trust is sober
81% of consumers are concerned that technology or software problems with Smart Meters will lead to them being overcharged
Forecast electricity
In water
So
I never thought about that but it's valid all the time both from like
You know your electrical provider all the way from
Like Verizon in your phone bill and
This is not necessarily a function of like sensors and iot Tech as much as it is like
Billing systems on the back end everything is automated
Why do things make
Crunches
So
I may start going out to my meters in manually recording because
I never thought of this
Two-sided
I guess it double-sided access to some of these things
There are
Devices
Like curb or smapi
Or I can sense
That you can install on your phone that measures your electricity
Consumption
So you can actually check that against you
Entirely
The same like one-to-one the same but it should be right
Yeah yeah some of those they go right into your electrical panel
If I recall
And so something like that or having a water flow meter
Are there so many
You can actually double-check that so I actually think
Yeah you get the added benefit because a lot of those water flow things will
Actually shut your water off because they're smart enough to know there's
Water slide when it really shouldn't be or normally isn't
So would prevent leaks and then you get the added benefit of being able to monitor
The actual slow as well
Yasso
While I agree that
Iot
He's going to add another layer of complexity to are already comp
Complex systems
I don't think it's
Will get more glitches but
You know we still don't have
Systems in place really too
Affect the glitches we have already in our existing systems look at like what happened with
Verizon employee not turning
Not not throttling
In California
That's something that actually
Automation
Yes
One would think yes I'm working on this fire for Emily weeks now let's not throttle the fire
Men and women that are fighting this fire
I don't know
I feel like
Doesn't change it at
But
It's because people don't understand all the things you can do once you've connected
Things like
That's me what it is they haven't thought through every possible use cases there are so many it's not until something bad happens like
We could have prevented that we have that data
And then the problem gets off
Yeah but that's kind of how
I know enough
Speaking of
Scary
This is an interesting article
Wolfram bleeping come
Computer tell you about flaws in smart irrigation system
And in this is actually
A team of Israeli researchers
Showed how
If you attack a couple
Irrigation system so smart Homer
You can actually use them
Campuses use them all kinds of
Please use them as well but if you attack enough sprinklers
You can empty a water tower
So
Dtac sprinklers
From Blue spray machine
And they found me
The sand
They reported all their vulnerabilities
But in drought-stricken areas this is actually a big tissue
And a problem
So
Do I tell people not to connect to their sprinklers
I don't know what's
The solution here
No I mean I wouldn't not have the product if you need it and you're aware of the vulnerabilities and the fact that these
Bardos are reported and likely be fixed
I wouldn't say don't do it
But it's scary that if it's almost like a denial-of-service
Like on the internet if somebody had control it
Theoretically here they did a damage calculation of 13550 sprinklers they could get rid of
1787 cubic meters of water in
6 minutes from a water tower and that is what they say typical water tower capacity
6 minutes
You would drain
The local water tower in this actually ties that something I put in
My newsletter
I had talked about again it's like a DDOS attack on the electrical grid basically
You can overwhelm an electrical grid if you pull
Too much demand
On the system
So the idea was you just use you know what your tacoyote devices and you
Increase air conditionings for example air conditioners to all run at the same time
I called it like flushing all the toilets at once in a door
Again this is
These are real world impacts from
Insecure devices that we might not think about like I may not be like
Soma air conditioners
An extra 20 minutes
If you time
Play across all of
That could be a problem
That's a brown out
So there we go there scary things in the Internet of Things a popular connected device
You may own it has been
I guess we'll say has been hacked
Again
We talk about these things all the time this one is pretty
Chicken dip
So I'm not unplugging
And it's only the WeMo Insight smart plug which is an older model
I know this
I have two of them as well in fact I recommended people use that
Plug your Hub into it because
You could get your hand goes down you could remotely start your hub
With a WeMo Insight smart plug
Yeah you're right this is that very particular attack I wouldn't want you to panic over it but the McAfee folks essentially down
Downloaded or extracted the firmware off
Open insight smart plug created their own little
Smart plug on a board
And then hacked it and then they can punch holes in your router and all that the thing is they would actually have to be on your
Neural network to do this
Be physically present is not a
Thing that you should worry about per se and I'm sure that WeMo will fix it
But it should be
But yes it
Another
So if anyone
When comes into your house as
Your Wifi password
Don't get it don't give it to
This is where I'm going to just stress the importance of guests
If you're going to build an iot this is another thing.
And you put them on a guest Network and that's the same network you give to like
Your kids friends
That's a bad idea to
Just use the rule that I use at my house when you come over it's BYO I bring your own internet
Just use your for cheap
You're getting nothing
Zippo
Terrifying
Let's talk about
So if you guys are familiar with Vera
Z-Wave hub
The company has been bought by a company which makes its own
So what can we expect for this
Z-Wave hub
Well it's interesting what easy yellow and I don't know if it's that works as a little but whatever
It's interesting with Z-Wave hubs they make
They are super small and one reminds me of the Samsung
SmartThings link USB stick that I have in my Nvidia Shield which add zigbee and Z-Wave to my
Shield and it makes it run the SmartThings
Software so it becomes a hub easy yellow makes really small Z-Wave only hubs
One is a USB stick
One is actually a plug you just plug it into your electrical outlet
And I love that idea I love it cuz I don't want to see boxes all over
Correct
Avira soft
On
Yeah I don't know about
Okay
Never use it
No idea
So
C3 is another tire
So C3 which is Tom siebels company they started out doing smart grid Smart Energy Management
Slowly transition to iot and
Of course AI
They have
Done a link up with the Google Cloud this means they support now the cuckoo
Cloud Amazon and Azure what's interesting to me here is that Google has
Really beat up their industrial iot efforts they did a deal with company called
Foghorn
Dayton
Others with industrial companies on the last Light
I hear maybe since CES
They've really started digging into industrial iot cuz they have been very far behind
An Enterprise is
Yeah we've talked about that a number of times but what is Google's iot strategy which is not a cohesive message and so I'm but I agree
This year has been a big year of catching up I'm not going to say they have caught up or haven't we'll see but this is definitely
The year they have made big strides and just real quick to plug something
Not smart plug but just plug plug
I was on the twit network
Know-how show which they cover IRT
And I was a guest
Talking about Google Android Android things
Industrial iot so I don't know if what I said make sense but if you want to listen to it and go to twitch.tv
Did I do okay
I don't like you did all right
Yes I did
The other person was a homekit person with
Enterprise industrial iot and I
Didn't agree at all with
What he said I didn't hear it until after it was
Published so I couldn't reply that so to speak but
Yeah that could just be me
Okay
Let's move on to Wi-Fi for airports
Security I know this is a Wi-Fi story is it an iot story only reason I put it in here it's cuz we talked actually
About various systems in
The home
That use Wifi as a security system
So
Wi-Fi is radio waves you guys and if you analyze those ready you can see things
And apparently you can see the
Very clearly
According to this research
You can find
Dimensions of metal objects or estimate the volume
Liquids
And this is a 95% accurate system
And this might make it so you don't have to do things like pull your laptop out of your thing
The TSA line
War
Toiletries
3 oz
Containers in the ziplock bag
The wi-fi system had a success rate of 99% for recognizing dangerous objects
98% / metals
And 95%
Now here is it perfect
Use for something that
They wouldn't use
Because it's
Kimpton products
Google Glass
If you had TSA agents while you were standing in line walking around
They could be getting a feedback from the Wi-Fi signal
House and seeing individuals and who should be taking stuff out of their bag
Looks like a brick and I want to know what it is or you got
Too much liquid in there
Actually you could disable the Google
Last.of.the couldn't take
Screenshot switch
Indeed
Yasso though although although
That would also be useful for known Travelers and people who are on the do not fly list
Oh yeah
What can revive Google Glass on the Shelf
I still have my
That's why you want
But here's my cautionary tale for those of you guys who are like looking at this for a sec
Security system and maybe feel more secure because it's not a camera
This is pretty granular
So it may not actually be
Camera
But it's going to know a lot about you
So
Keep that in mind and
Because Wi-Fi signals are not contained unless you live in a faraday cage
You can actually read this outside your building so people can actually
Using this type of gear see what's
Like motion and what's happening inside your house even if they're not in
Insight it
Alright so
That's my a lake
Before we get all excited about this technology
Which I do hold you or
RAB
Fitbit
Has a Duo device
Reduce the Fitbit charge 3
Which
I'm excited about
Because I have a charge 2
I love it I wear it almost everyday
But I don't wear it it means I'm losing with my best friend cuz we have a competition going on
Who can burn the most calories in
Take the most steps
So I think I might get this I'm going to be due for a new Fitbit probably in six months or so this one goes on sale after
First
I might pick it up
This one is $150 I don't know what you paid for your charge 2
As far as what you're going to get if you do upgrade
You will get app notifications what you don't currently get on your charge 2 I'm sure that's optional if you don't want them
Not
Easy to no problem
I thought I would think you would because you don't carry your phone
More often than not and as long as you're in range of Bluetooth of your phone you would get notifications I could be a poor
What's eating out
Applications are actually useful for me because when I'm not near my phone
Animal my Apple watch and you pay me via Hangouts chat which happens we talk during the week
A chat on hangouts rather I get that on my watch has a notification and I know that you have a question I can even see the question
And so the question you don't know I'm not far
Computer you can't do that
I don't know
Okay I don't want to know when Kevin wants to know something
Really need to get me you should probably
Or you should actually
Or
Hack into my WiFi
System and dim my Philips lights
Yeah okay so Stacy isn't one of notifications but everybody else can get them on the charge 3
On your charge 2 you have an OLED display that you can tap
I know the charge because they
Touch screen so I can you can do more than just tap and you can scroll around a little bit easier which is
Probably better navigation
You can't go swimming with your charge 2 cuz it's splash-resistant charge 3 is water resistant up to 50m
Kneaders so if you can scuba diving
You know With The Stingrays
That's useful
You should get 7 Days on the charge 3 what do you get on your charge 2 right now
Roughly actually I get about for 2
Depending on how much
Bright and that you don't get app notifications that's even
That's helping your battery life to I'm sure
Yes
Since I'm such a curmudgeon
Who hate us
Yes so I'm
I'm all in on the
Arnott
Because I need
GPS on my wearable because I run everyday and I need to track her
How far in Payson
Splits and so on and so forth
So you can do heart rate on the charge devices which I can do on my Apple watch but I have a built-in GPS as well
And
This has a GPS
It's not a cyst it's connect
Is your phone
Yeah you can I was like you can get that huge
I don't want to run with my phone
So I don't run with my phone
So yeah and you know Kevin and I were talking about
What you want cuz there's a lot of options out there in the
Instatracker / Smartwatch / whatever world
And it's kind of nice to say you know what I really need GPS cuz that's going to narrow your
Options
Considerably
Very quickly yes for me I want deep
Sleep tracking stats and I also for some reason I'm obsessed
So those are
And I get that I mean I would never pick a device for you and vice versa
You know what I want what I want and need someone so forth but
A lot of people might be saying why aren't you running with us because
If you have a problem you need to call somebody in emergency that's another factor that
You should consider
I opted
Did for the LTE version of the Apple watch
So my family can call me text me
I can call them an emergency
I can call the police very quickly with the SOS feature and my
Peeps can find me on find my friends
Because when I leave the home
That starts tracking to watch not my phone
Oh and I should tell everybody
Remember back in the day
Win Fitbit
Pedal
Some of the watch faces that you
Get on the Fitbit charge 3
We are the pedal ones that we have not seen for a while so you know if that's true that you can actually get
Just out there it's still lives
A little bit
Kalettes
Smoove on to just a little congratulatory note
Because
We follow Cee Pro
Which is a industry magazine
For this is the professional installer Market
Start up stuff so this is where I go to learn
About
Control4 and savant
All these fancy brands
They were bought
This week
Emerald expositions which is the company that actually owns Cydia
Which is the show
All those professional installers I went last year
Had a lot of fun I'm not going
The emphasis on audio
Steffes
Audio at home videos
Was kind of too much for
But you know
Congratulations to Julie Jacobs
Send Whois counter
Eminent
The Grand Am
Grand Dame of smart home
HomeStar seasoning
Yes
Open doing that Cee Pro
24 years old
It's
Crazy
Yep
So yeah so good for her
Good for
Media organization
And
I guess
Hopefully having truly says it will become puff piece kind of company I can't imagine her participating
Fantasy jewelry
Sophia Revelations
And
Who's that
Cheap
Okay
Now it is time
Voice
Smell
It's not our personal theme song
We have a great voice mail for you from the iot podcast
Listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Tell you not to miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart
Deadbolt and Wifi adapter
You can only enter to win if you are in the
Us--or
Canada
I'm so sorry
Rest of world
623-7424 and leave a voicemail asking us your iot questions
Remember smarter home-start
Schlage
And this week's voicemail is from
Mark
Kevin Stacy my name is Mark Butler come from Cleveland Ohio
My question revolves around
Trying to track
When one of my children arrives
Or leaves home
I know there's a smart things
Sensor
So you can do but that's something I guess you made it look like
Sharing The Backpacker here am looking for something that might
Work with
Location of the song
Ridin through my wink Hub or buy Amazon Echo
Ecosystem
Could be possible
Feel like it's the Holy Grail I've been doing some errands
Thanks so much guys. The podcast
You should be doing twice a week
Oh mark this is an eminently reasonable request and you can do it so many ways we can
Can I tell you how to do it
Free to
Oh my God now I'm buying it
Entire home security system
Let's get started with three
Because we all
You want to start with the iPhone version
So I don't know which
Phone platform
Mark and his kids
Have
AR
And is to use the find my friends with you
Your family
That is free
If you're on iOS
There are downsides right off the bat when you
Set up a notification for let's say notify me when my kids
Come home
Basically
When I come home you'll get a message
The problem is it's a one-and-done thing
So I don't recommend it
Turn all the time you
But it is possible to do if your on iPhone you could do it also on Android they have a similar feature
With Google
Maps sharing
I'm not used it for notifications though
It's more of a
Looking
Where people are in a set
You may be able to notification I have not tried it yet but those are two
Options not ideal but could work
But
Still keeping with the
Free but now we've got maybe some more ideal stuff
You can actually put if
Service that
Ties web services together
On your handset
Be there a iOS or Android
And you would put it on your kids phones to and you would actually
Create applets
It would say when this phone
Either geo-fenced
Or gets into connect to the
Home Wi-Fi
Get a notify
Vacation so then you get it
Like a text
So
That is free
Your kids do have to have that on their phone
So this is not surreptitious but
Your kids probably know that you're trying
When they come here
I wonder though is there a trigger event for when somebody leaves the Wi-Fi network because Mark wants to track the arrival
DeLand
Departure
I think there must be an Android I believe there is because I have one when I leave
My phone
Android phone leaves the Wi-Fi net
That's a trigger that I can use to take certain
Actions
The natural work
That also means
When
Your kids turn off the Wi-Fi net
For whatever reason
You're going to get a
Gravely disabled WiFi radio that's correct
So
If you want to move up a layer
There's a couple options you can add
Camera with facial recognition
Ignition so doorbell cameras I actually have a doorbell camera the nest
That recognizes
People in my home and when I walked by it there like
And I just passed the door
Or you know they say Anna's home
So
So this is good if you don't have
A camera in front of every door that you
Your kids are going to use
And that may include a subscription fee I'm thinking Nest aware
10 bucks a month
Another option
Is you just have a nest camera and like facing
The front area or an area that you're
Your kids have to pass through
And you'll get the same sort of in
Information that you get a notification that movement has been detected
And you can go back into the nest app and look and see what the movement was in there for you could then see
Who is it and which were they going in around Etc
Slightly more proactive options include
Lighthouse camera where you can say tell me if you see my kids
Which is kind of fun
But it's pricey and that actually has a subscription
And
If
You're worried about like your kids sneaking out
We're trying to figure out every possible about your kids sneaking out my assumption is you're going to want install
Call something on there
Their phone that's going to
Biggio fence to your location or your Wi-Fi network
Cuz they're not going to leave without their
Right I actually have the canary
System which you can find now on some decent discount
Quite honestly
I think I paid 179 or 199 for the base camera and one extension camera cuz I got it free
There you go again not for you but not too expensive either and it's the home security camera system it also measures
Air quality in your home but it also does the geofencing for you as long as everyone in the family has the canoe
Canary app installed and they actually want that installs I'll tell you why because when they come home if the alarm is
Active on the canary they can disable it on their phone before they walk in the door
Otherwise you may have a siren go off where you may have a police get called back
System so we have
The geofencing it set up so every time somebody in my home
Leaves the geofence area or arrives I literally get a notification on my Apple watch and on my phone that
So and so is home
So-and-so has left
So that's exactly what you want Mark and then again there's a cost
And there's a subscription it's 999 a month I had pay for I think the two cameras but
It has the geofencing which is
Probably the best way to go if you don't mind spending a little money
Markdown options
Options for you
Various price ranges
And I'm sure actually
That we didn't eat
Oh yeah
I would try the free option
Tiffany work for you and which case you know you don't have to spend any extra money
Good luck and now stay tuned
For our guests who is
Tyler Baker the CTO at foundries
Which is a new company that's launching
Iot
Security platform will talk more about that after the break we are taking a
Break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Netgear
And we have John McHugh who is general manager of commercial networking
At Nick here here to talk to us
We've been talking a lot about how Netgear has adapted the inside line for the internet of things and no
You guys allow
Companies to control their power over ethernet devices over the inside line
Do you want to dig into that a bit
The Internet of Things
And appeal we
We are like
Perfect companions one of the things that has more people
Putting out Solutions like monitoring
Cameras or security lock
Or
Speaker
Various other Internet of Things
Controllers and monitor
Defining one of the
Wonderful attributes
Network connect
Wired network connection is you can power that device
No having to worry about batteries and other things
You can power it with a cable that's easy to run and doesn't
Represent an electrical shock hazard or require a specialized person to install a
What and so what this means is it's kind of a do-it-yourself thing where you at this
DC driven power
It is now making all of your internet stuff operate there's a lot of efficiencies around this one of them is if you can
Power your network
Would like a backup generator in the case of an emergency all of these devices are going to function as well
Off the same
Network cabling
So what I found most interesting
About
Your control of power over ethernet devices was actually that it's not just control
You let customers handle automation tasks
Stutter normally handle
Completely different software
Can you talk about that
We knew when we were looking at the application so we're going to run on the
News networks that this power thing was
Very fertile ground and if you look at most
Competitor
Devices out there
I mean I'll let you turn power on
They let you turn power off
We thought a lot about what how customers work
Going to use this
And softly created a bunch of features
To enable the models that we thought sit with these devices
For example I can power cycle apart so right it's not turning it off and then waiting and then turn it back on
Push a button
A power cycle
That's something we need to do to remote devices
Regularly is part of the troubleshooting
Process the other thing is people said
Going to be really cool if I could just
Turn off my WiFi
I mean turn it completely off from when I leave at the end of the day till the next morning what could be more so
Secure the net
So you can
Schedule that your all your power devices are certain
Shut down a certain time
Turn on when you show up the next day at work and so it provides you with this level of Direct Control and phone
Functionality to frankly standard Solutions in Computer Solutions just don't have
Where can we go to find out more about the in
Www.netgear.com
/ inside
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Tyler Baker who is
CTO at
Foundries
Dot IO
Hi Tyler how are you doing
I'm doing well Stacy how about yourself
Great
I almost said Lennar okay
Cuz that's where half of you guys are from but
You guys
Just launched your company this week
Quickly
Let's
Talk about
Just very briefly what you're trying to
So we're building a secure iot platform they can be leveraged by many many customers and
The idea is that is
Is minimal and is updatable
And we have a couple different platform
1 for a deeply embedded
And the other one would be for the nice class devices
Okay
So for some of us were like why what was that
So let's talk about stories for
What
Is the problem you are trying
How to solve
That is a great
Really what we're trying to solve
Is distributed denial-of-service attack
That's have a higher bandwidth
Throughput and we never seen before some even
And where they're coming from our compromise iot
Cameras but it
Router
Providing a
People or companies that would like to build IO
And allowing them to be
Sure
And allowing them to have
Update capabilities
Security is our biggest concern and being able
To have the latest software available for a customer
Let's talk about
What it take
Cakes to create a secure iot
Because that's the everybody's in gold
Let's make this more secure
So what are the steps that need
What is the bare minimum
Yes
Images
Cryptographically sign
Image into a device
The second thing is
The solution that is provided needs to be threat models
Innocence that we identify the attack vector
And we decide which
Tigers are not in scope
And the ones that are in scope we model them and we say here's the medication
So we're under the impression that our software offering here is
Completely secure in fact I don't believe any software
D'usse is
We use
The Upstream software and we basically
Continuously
If you want to look at something like
Spectre meltdown bug
Turtle very quickly
However with older LTS kernel
You can use
Many many weeks
Is distribution
Should be updated which means a lot of the cloud
Inspector
So our goal is to provide the latest software that's
Imitation
Is transmitting data to an educate way
So that sounds good I understand the kind of
Platform that's always updated with the latest most secure
Version
Of the software
But you guys are
You're supporting a bunch of different versions of soft
Because you've got your artists you've got basic Linux
And then you've got container
Focused
Locations so
Explain how all of that
Works together
What we do is we are actually we work Upstream with those projects a lot of us on the team or maintainers at them so we have a good
Advantage
Able to understand what's very important
Security patches
So
Wallets very complex systems
We have
I believe the right expertise in the right places
To help us achieve these goals
So let's talk about this from the perspective of someone building a
If I'm making a lipo
I need to put your Zephyr
Artist
Micro plaits
On the way
And then
I got to put your Linux micro platform
It's going to be on the Hub or Gateway that
Stocking a lightbulb and then
Talks to the Wi-Fi
And then if I got servers running in the cloud
That's also going to have the Linux micro platform on it
So none of those pieces have to be there you could use the platform independently of our Linux microphone
The way we've designed the software stack
Is that there is no law on open source projects
If you choose to use the micro popcorn and maybe you've developed a proprietary Gateway standard
TT
All your educate Wings Temple Modesto
We use standard there as well
To allow people
Plugged in
Any clubs
It really depends on the use case and where you see
Ideally we'd love you to run
Okay
So talk to me about how I would make
This decision
Because actually first tell me your Revenue
So am I being charged
For every version of the micro platform
No sew you paid sensually a year lease
Army Zephyr micro platform
It is $10,000 a year
And there's no per unit
So it is a per product
If you have a stalker build let's say
Light bulb
Hardware that is only
It's $25,000 a year
Steampunk
What is it is a paper product
Okay so then what are the trade-offs and reasons I might run it on the edge
So on the light bulb versus on the
The Gateway or
So what would I do
Is we realize that
The enterprise software Concepts
Updating your software
Using containers in virtual machine
Is really good practices
These concepts are widely known by developers in
When you go to embedded it's kind of a choose-your-own-adventure
Beyond the Edge
We can standardize
Some of the stuff for deployment
And the way people deployed harappa
Locations to the edge
Using containers using virtual machines and using tools at the Enterprise
Already
You don't have to learn new tools or create your own
Already managing Enterprise
Trucks today
Okay so one of the challenges with
Connected devices is
Companies don't tend to
Update them
Forever right I might expect something to sit on my factory floor for like
20 years
Or even Thirty but the idea of supporting software for that long is just
Anathema to the IT guy
So
With your experience from the embedded world
Is this product
Going to
Help
Solve those kind of
I believe it is
Intestinal problems
Just an industry
I think there's a two ways how this product helps
Enterprise developers that want to maintain a product or
Building Products
Especially when they're based on movies open source projects like Linux
And you're probably
You're onto the next project
Working on
There's no time for you to really
Keep up-to-date
What's happening of streaming the security things that are Basics there
So what we provide
What is a summary every 3 days every 5 days
Where are small bits of information that are easily digestible
30 minutes and understand what's happening
Software
The second part of that is
We're doing a lot of fasting
Internally
And our partners also do a lot of testing and feed the results back
As the suffers moving forward it ideally it gets better and that's how it's
But we're constantly offering update
You have the Machinery that's on
Automation floor where
Processor like a consumer device like a refrigerator or a light bulb
Necessarily the companies don't need to update it
Because there's no exploit but what an exploit is found in their product
They want to be able to make a move
Latest software
Updates
So they can make it there right now
So if I'm using something like this
My device isn't automatically
Secured I still need to handle basic cracked
Encryption between
Storing data in database
Provide
We've done that like work for you
So we provide dtls on the
And we use mqtt S
Between
In device
And the Gateway rain so we're able to show you this is how you use encryption to move your data from the edge
To the cloud
And provide you the best price
And we
So when it comes to security
One of the challenges is
Is that a lot of these companies
456 years down the line
They don't have the infrastructure to track and monitor
Hey what's happening in the security World in their exploits
They don't actually know how to track without in the world and actually roll out the security updates to it so it's
Still a pretty complex
Big thing
To ask
A manufacturer
To take on security so do you guys kind of
Help absolve them
Yeah I think you're absolutely right so for your question a
Do provide
All the information
On a regular basis about this
Security exploits and the fixes that are going into our platform
So you're at least notified at that
If you still have it
Practice this weather that security or opens for soccer practice
They have
Nothing else to do other unresearched
They're able to Leverage
We built and built on top of that as part of their
All of the software that we provide
Is open
Able to cancel it anytime
So if they decide that they want to take on managing
Create appointment
All right so let's talk about other security efforts so you mentioned things like you have to have a secure Boot and this is not something you guys
Provide this is something the underlying Hardware that
You choose should have
Correct
Don't let friends do have cryptographic managers that store keys
Write a we will our software will allow
Product makers
Use that those Hardware devices
Those are the security measures that benefit the low level
Assurance
And send them at the edge
How much overhead do you guys need in
Yeah so where does that
In Our Lifetime we need to optimize
Yet we plan on offering multiple flavors something
It doesn't like 500
And then the image that we provide today is kind of got everything
Things like that is right around
For most applications but the
The way to configure alcohol
The extra stuff
Designer
Cytosine
Har Ram
And a really minimal not a slash
And that they can be verified by the bootloader and then booted
So we're working on optimizing it there or not
Our customers guide us there
Thank you so much this was super helpful
Tyler thanks so much for
AC not a problem enjoy it
If you'd like more iot nose sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com