Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higgins
Botham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have anime
Sing show for you
We're going to be talking
Belt curables
One of our favorites
Lakes where can we talk about Apple joining the thread group a new report from Bain Consulting about the industrial iot
Plus
A new
June oven
Why people are buying stuff on the Amazon Echo
Arms making
Shenzhen acquisition
We got them
Security tips that we thought we'd share and we've got a new
Home robot
Talk about Plus
Many men
Any horse
And
Our Guest this week is Matt Van Horn who is the CEO of
June
They make it oven and they just launched a
Randall
Product that is way cheaper he's going to tell us how they did that
So
Stay tuned for that
For a message
Netgear
Or we get to all of that
We can talk about the news
And
Hear from this week
Other sponsor
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform find out my Kenmore and D-Link picked up pharaoh
Apparel customer service experience as much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market 99% fewer
Support calls and a 10x higher activation rate
Plus they can we use 90% of their work from one project to the next
To learn more visit afero. IO that's a f e r o. IO
Spooky Kevin
Let's talk about
Hearables
We've talked about this before we had a guest in April
That was a fun conversation
Talk about perception
Sounded
All the kind of things you could actually cream into her hair bows and then you pointed out this
Fast Company article on Doppler Labs switch
It's no longer around but it's not it's not but it had a lot of influence on what's happening with
Apple
Google and Amazon these days
For those who are not familiar with Doppler labs they came out with the here one wireless earbuds and
News for traditional music
Earbuds
Also they could amplify external noise could even
Translate languages in your ear so you can have a conversation in another country
Criminal law
Into these little earbuds
But they face the challenge that many new hardware devices
Space battery life is
Really tricky when you have such a small things that isn't your bud
And you're cramming all kinds of processing power into the earbuds so you're right they're not here anymore even folks friendly with
Froggy or Froggie
They had the dash headphones that were very similar and just like the here ones the reviews were just terrible bragi
Is now licensing Airsoft
Are so but yeah this is a good article because it really shows the influence
What I think is
And I don't know if you agree but
Maybe the next big wearable type device that
We are
Looking at once week workouts
Some Kinks yes I totally agree in what
More I think
This is kind of the few
Future and not just because I loved
The movie Her
I think
We've been very focused on screen
For good reason
And we still are I mean even if we look at things things like Google Glass
Heads-up displays it's very screen Centric
But I think
We could do a lot
With
Information
Delivered
Audibly over-the-ear and maybe with like a
Companion haptic
So
Maya mean
Think about things like directions like when you're walking around
The city and you're just like
You're hearing from the phone that you're looking at the phone to see where you turn right or left but
Having a device that
I can just say
Turn right here
That's amazing
Having
A device
You can just ask a question of
Then get the answer we have that in our homes so putting that inner ear for travel purposes
Makes a lot of sense
It doesn't actually work getting there already and those two particular instances
For example when I wear my Apple watch when I get directions and walking around town where you when I'm driving
When I get to
Turn in the direction C it will give me a haptic feedback
In advance of it will be like two beeps
Go to buses for laughed and three for a ride so I'm already starting to get that in certain places with the Apple watch
And there are
Various headphones
What's that have built-in Google assistant or Madam a
Siri for example that give you information
What's nice about it is you're right it's like a whisper in your ear nobody else knows that you're getting that information I think that's part of the next step
Stop here right we don't want
Distracting type interactions
Yes baby will stop walking
In the manholes
Because that is a thing that happens
I'm excited about this and then there's the next level which is
Hey I'm getting kind of old and
My hearing is maybe not
Is awesome is it
Used to be
So having a device that can
Help me hear what I need to hear in May
Fade Out background conversations
That's really
Compelling
And I'm raising my hand because I actually fit into that category I have problems hearing things when there's a lot of background noise
So when my family watching TV and talking to me
I can't understand them so I actually did buy
Acorn horrible from nuheara earlier this year the eye cubits and
Again they function as a music player
And they also amplify sound so I can like sit and watch my TV in my office and not have it blurry
Hearing so I can hear it because it drowns out the girls watching TV downstairs and I turn to a normal level
I just wear the iqbuds
What
Yeah
Except
I had to
So the point is in the reason why were talking about it on the show is cuz
I really believe that this is going to be
I'm just saying the Next Generation
Computing platform
The challenges we're going to have to come up with is figuring out battery life
Things like wireless charging
Only go so far I have some wireless headphones that do last for 5 hours cuz they don't do anything
But
Charging them in the charging cases
It's fairly simple so figuring out a way to
Compensate for poor battery life doing things like
Betteredge kind of processing
Power that Stila
Thing that needs to happen
What else might we need
I think better life is the Big Challenge because again it's it's just
Space limitation
Write the computing
Either you're going to need to cram more and more into smaller
Chips
But that's a given that's happening that's pretty standard with any Computing platform
There is a technology
For hearing aids
So it's called probabilistic
And the idea is instead of computing on every 011
You computer to slightly less
Accurate rate to save on energy
Very simplistic way of
But it is a known technology that
I've been researching
The challenges
Doing that at
Scale
Requires a device that is sold at
So I'd be curious as we see major manufacturers
Like Apple
Ace Hardware Samsung
Will they find enough use for something like that to basically create a whole new type of
Computing platform
I think so and I just say that because
Have your very first point about getting away from screens voices the new user interface these days but there are times when voice doesn't make sense
Cenote if your assistance going to announce
Personal information now so the world will that kind of
Stinks so I think we're getting away from the screens and this is the next
Spread your next
Step to add information to you in a non-intrusive way
So I do think there's definitely
And I suspect there that's appealing
And additionally just
Going back to the hearing assistance new hearing aids
Expensive
You talking several thousand dollars I didn't look and see how long the batteries last I know they all have replaceable batteries with us app
There's a whole new category for these horrible is called
Personal sound amplification products for peace out
And that's
What I bought that's worth a lot of these things are
They're not
Subject to FDA
Regulation
And that's important because
Anybody can buy them over the counter
I wonder what the impact is going to be for
The hearing aid industry as a result
You should listen to that podcast for back
We do talk about
Is her name number
Yes she was
Okay
Well
I don't think we're going to solve the hero's power problem anytime soon but
Keep an eye out I know Kevin and I have been for a while
Just keep an eye out for these kind of innovation
Cuz they are coming and they're going to creep up on us
Who called the iPhone
Echo
Okay I don't think we never talk to each other again
Maybe we
Next up
Apple
Joined the thread group
What did you think about that
I think it's
Big potential news for homekit because it opens up
The door to other
Radio protocol
For homekit devices cuz right now it's just Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
It's
I mean apples every deliberate they don't join groups or standards that they don't plan to use
I didn't just join the third group they are a sponsor top-tier level they're on the board of directors now
The pan of sum of money each year now so
I suspect
They will use thread the question is with what and how
Yes so in this
I was super excited about big
As you've mentioned before Kevin
Right now punk it is only
Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
And that leaves out a chunk of devices and that's why we've got hubs for like our
Hue light bulbs
That sort of thing
With
Thread which uses the same underlying radio as
Zippy
802. 15.4 what could happen is maybe we'd Co
Apple supporting
That radio protocol which means maybe we could get pure hubs in our lives
The alternative
Because I have seen
Arm actually a couple years ago showed
Thread over Bluetooth radio
And I talk to other chipmakers
To have experimental but don't have
Production stuff
Read over
Wi-Fi
Radios
So it could open us up two more protocols but it also might just be like
Same stuff but now you've got direct IP access
Which is one of the things
What's the thread is both a mesh protocol
It's low power and its IPv6
Capable
Which means you go Direct
Write what I
I would hope for assuming
Apple does
Use this for zigbee devices
What that would do
What is manufacturers would not have to make
Two versions of devices right now there are some door locks
Example there's a virgin
There's a home cover
That's a challenge for the smaller device makers right so it's limited
The number of devices that you have available for
Choice in home care if they were to adopt
Zigbee
With thread
Then that would make life a lot easier for
Consumer stand for device
Yeah because I did a lot of
Consumers have to choose their like
Yes a limited class of device but I also have devices that they may not work with other smart home hubs so
Let's see what happens
My hope is that we're going to see some interesting things so you know I dog an apple
A lot for
It is Well executed but it is so limited and it is
So brutal to be at home
Kit partner
They're slow and steady approach the the smartphone market has not evolved
The way I thought it was
In the way I hoped it would because I am an open internet
So it's possible that
Who is still come out from this sin
Be just fine
It's taken a long time but here I agree
Very possible they will
Really expand homekit more than they have in the prior-year so
Yeah we'll see who knows maybe I'll be Maricopa
It is
So let's move on from the Smart Home
To some
Industrial and
Enterprise
Okay so this week Bane
One of the big consulting firms
Put out a report noting that the iot
She is
Hey it's a big deal the most notable number that you're seeing everywhere is that it is going to be a 502
20 billion dollar market
That will be by 2021
It's going to be more than double the
235 billion that was spent last year on iot Hardware software
System integration and
Telecom services
Like everybody they believe that the Enterprise and Industrial segment circuit
Experience the most Revenue growth and they also realized that
Most of the executives they interviewed
600 they are admitting that
Adoption rates
Are pretty slow
And as someone who follows the space this is
Natsu
Pricing for the last two years I have seen
Many of
The company serving the space offering me the exact
Same
Customer win
What is happening is I see a few of those customer win
Expanding their stuff but I don't see a lot of new customers that are actually expanding so they're still stuck at the
Concept
They call that the pilot purgatory
Yeah and I mean I work for two companies I had over a hundred thousand employees and it was
Any major change or implementation it was like driving an oil tanker you know you took forever to make a turn
There's just so many pieces involving so many
Business units that are touched and you got a test everything and get buy-in and also I sort of get that cuz this is like a new frontier
Here for Enterprise
But what I found interesting in here was
Security is on the minds of these people that were interviewed and that's not the surprise of it it's
The fact that Bane says
These folks would buy more iot devices
And pay more for them if there's
Security concerns for address
I just asked him how much more would you pay and they said about 22% more on average
Obviously Securities important if we are pain that I ever show
But the fact that they're willing to pay a premium for what I think should really be table Stakes is a very interesting
Can I sing
It also speaks to an issue with security
Which is people would love to
Payforit
To go away
Unfortunately security is not something you can throw money at it's actually a
Process is much as it is a technology
Socks
I'm not making light of everyone's problem here but it's true you have to train your worker
How to behave with this kind of information so they don't get finished or they don't pick up a USB stick in the park
You have to train your vendors to
Issue update said you have to start thinking about that
When you start sourcing
Technology
It's not something you can just
Play 4
So I'm glad people to pay for it but at the same time I think
It's misleading and I would also say another reason
One of the other big reasons are not adopting this technology because they don't see a good Roi
In quicker
And I think again this is not the type of
Yes there are things that you can do to
Get an Roi
And Technology
This is actually
How much more foundational shih
So you're going to be putting in technology
Overtime but only if
You understand how
So
I get why this
Is taking a while
Technically hard
Security concerns but it is something that everyone is going to have to
Carlos say
In a couple of weeks we will have actually someone
Bane on to talk a little bit more about this so you
Stay tuned for that in the meantime will include a link to the
Reports you can dig in on
Euro timing
Share your thoughts
F sharing thoughts
Paul a lovely Lister Santa
Iotc
Securities
Tips from meek
Magazine
So Paul thank you so much for doing this
Play Love make
And this is for people who are building
Their own
Smart home systems and
Reddit homebridge on a pie
Will include a link to it some of its really easy
Hey all raspbian OS installed
Password for the default Pi use
You should change that
Another
Keep your OS up today
That makes sense
It's going to be secure
And some of these are a little bit more
So disable password login with
SSH
I was kind of like
That is not something that I thought about
Yeah I had to be honest
I hadn't thought about that
Nor have I thought
Or tried I should have thought about having tried setting up a firewall and
Punching a couple holes in specifically for devices I just haven't had the time to plan that out
Intuit
It does make sense
Yeah you're running a lot of pies
And so that's if you're going to make your own for all of the devices
Prayer things that are not your own device we talk about these all the time
Which is ya change your passwords
Keeping us up-to-date this goes a little further it says disabled services in protocols you don't
Sometimes you get in trouble when you're trying to do that individually on certain
Iot devices
So your device funk
Nationality Maybe
If you do that but
You know if you're using a VPN
Is also a lovely
It is and I don't think it's a bad solution but if you
Depending on how you implement a VPN and what you use like if you set your whole home
Internet off on a VPN and you do streaming services like if you watch MLB TV for example I watch
That's only available in the US so if I have a
Different IP address I from Canada I can't watch that service so there's pros and cons to that one
That's true and sometimes with automatic time update
If you're in a different view if your VPN saying you're in a different
Time zone U
You could have your lights wake you up an hour early witch
They also talk about things like using a guest Network
Talk about that
I don't love it I actually
Daycare is an Advertiser in the podcast
But while we were on the phone
Doing the ads
I did ask about the
This I was like
You know guest Networks
Don't work
Look for iot
Actually said that their work
To make easier
When that comes out
I don't know but it does give me
A sense of
Hope that
Maybe the Wi-Fi vendors are going to start taking this seriously
Create easier ways to do guest networks without actually doing
So
Let's move on thank you Paul for that everybody will include a link that actually offers some really good how to
Make magazine
Let's talk about
Some quick new stuff shall we
We shall
Okay
Big news
On the show The June oven with Kevin and I both own and bought for 1495
And $95
That is no longer going to be the June
Gentoo oven that is out it is right now
9 for an undetermined
Period of time
Or you can buy gourmet package which is
699 and I can chew a bunch of trays
Recipe service
I think additional warranty services
Eventually the price of the
David will go up to 5
It hasn't yet
So we're going to talk
Much more about that but I just wanted to give you guys like
This is a smarter oven that we all know and love and if you don't know in love it it basically
Has a camera in it it recognizes your food
It has preset cooking programs it basically makes
Cooking
Yeah we still use ours
At least twice a day
If not more
Barely use a regular full-size oven as a result and it when I tell my wife about the shoes
I think we pay like $1,500
Yeah
I said but you know what first-generation product relay doctors
That's life I said the question is do you feel it's worth
I just like yeah we use it all the time that's great
So she's not even upset about the price. I don't know if that's how you feel about it
You know it is what it is
You know I haven't talked to Matt
I feel okay about
I understand
We held
Kevin we helps make this possible
This is true
So
Look at us
If you guys buy it you can
Okay so arm has made
Acquisition
Last week but now it is a done deal arm his arm has a chip license
They bought a company
Called treasure
Data and the idea here is that arm
Seems to me they also bread
Company called stream
Data
Stop the stacks so instead of doing just
Semiconductor design and Licensing
They're starting to think about life
Black data processing in the closer you get to the solving the problem 1 it's going to have a good virtuous cycle on there
Chip designs are going to understand what they need to build
More butt
They also
But this was not a lot of people are using it but they also launched a cloud service
Especially I think
2 years ago so it kind of makes sense
Sit there
Getting more into Data Manager
Spencer treasure data does data management
Pulling data from a bunch of iot devices and they help you
Normalize it
So you know
Since it is also adds another Revenue stream for arm
And that
With treasure data for the data analytics and
Stream Technologies and arm and bed people who subscribe
Forest Service
Through those
Entities
Will be able management take devices over the clouds so that's a whole new Revenue potential stream for the
Oh that's true
All right so that's the arm news
Any smart home news we have a fridge cam coming out from a company in the UK called smarter
Here in the US I don't believe we could order it yet
Very disappointed I saw this at CES
How do you know if it was last year if it was 27
But
If you're in the UK
You can buy it for
You can buy it for a hundred and fifty pounds
Or roughly a hundred pound
If you buy a
Fridge
I love this because it is a camera you stick in your fridge that also has
AI is part of it
They're working with
UK grocer test
Costco so you can
Get a shopping list based on your
Fridge contents
And they send that to Tesco and
Jessica will just
Chocolate
Pick it up I just really want to be able to open
My free agency
I can't open my
Message and see what's inside
I want to be able to get a picture of what's in my fridge so I can
I just want to see if the light really goes off
It does
How do you know
Okay so let's see what else do I
Kevin I can't believe we almost didn't talk about this
Let's talk about
Anki vector
Oh yes the Anki Vector which was announced earlier this week
For those who are not familiar maybe you are familiar with the cozmo also made by Anki that
That came out I believe in 2016 if that's small little robot is small
Sister I don't know 2 or 3 in wide by maybe three maybe four in long is smallfoot
It is the cutest little thing I know it's Stacy you love the
The cosmo personality
So wonderful
It's so endearing that funky I met with them to talk about the new
Devices called Vector they said that people
Sending you know there
I'm sending their Cosmo because it needs me up some maybe something broke on it
Plastic parts
Do I get it fixed
And they're like my nephew is miserable at his
Cosmo had to come back and please hurry and people get really attached to this because aside from it
Being just at home robot it's really
A companion
So much so that onky has hired somebody from Pixar and they animate
Thousands of expressions and movements in
It just didn't
Those into the robot it's really like a little personality on tread spray
It is and it actually so when you are games you play with
Cosmo
We'll talk about the old one
The old one and what it would lose
Was too many times in a row
It would get mad it would like
Jamis little it has like a little bulldozer front and we just go
To beat it on the floor and it was
I mean it was kind of hilarious but
Also
Just so much
Okay facts about yourself
Vector looks a lot like
Cosmo very very similar maybe even identical it's hard to say exactly I know that they've doubled the amount of parts inside
Lights on the inside cefaly different
Back on the inside is very different because with
Cosmo you had to connect
Chi robot via an app on your phone or tablet and
A lot of the processing
Was actually done on the phone or the tablet that big difference with Vector is
It's all on board and when I say all
Division is on board
The neural network is on board
The mapping is on board natural language processing is on board
It does have a connection to the cloud over your Wi-Fi network
And that is to access its Knowledge Graph
Companies such as Google Amazon have knowledge graphs that their devices tap into for information
Well Vector does the same only its monkeys knowledge
It moves just like
The old robots
It actually can tell when it's
Battery is running low to like 10 15%
And it will go back
By itself autonomously to its little charging base
I asked them about that makes so you can only use it when it's off the base right
They said no actually
Once the battery runs out goes back on his charger
He still available to listen speak
Ask for information give you the weather will still recognize faces
It's just that
If you do any movement with a Treads those suck up a lot of juice
And he may not
Come out of his charging pad if you say go across to the front window and tell me who's outside he won't do that
There's person recognition
And there's the everything in there is
All on board
Running on a Qualcomm Snapdragon chip and it's a reasonable price the
Cosmo device was 179 this is on Kickstarter
You could have until September 6th
Tobacco
It is 199 is the early bird but when it hits stores in October
It will be 249
Even so yes it's a small little thing is not going to lift
Picked up things on your house to bring them to you per se but there's so much
Groundbreaking intelligence in this for the price in my opinion that that's why I thought that's what you were talking about
And
Are you going to buy one
I am seriously considering I have till September 6
The early backers will get there
Vector by October 9th it will hit retail stores buy a
October 12th
There is an SDK that if you know some python
You can program it yourself
That comes out in December and that's kind of why I'm interested
Just how much is onboard as well as the SDK because
What got me interested in talking in general was I saw a video of somebody using a cosmo
Pairing up with Google tensorflow and training it to recognize the difference between a cat
A dog and
Assure example and there another Cosmo go around and say cat
Dog cat networks go to the shoe and he would someone directly saw shoe and to me that's fun tinkering and that's what I'd like
I'm leaning towards yes getting on
Okay
Well then you'll have to send me my Cosmo
Two other quick bits of news the FBI is warning
Hospitals that their iot devices are being targeted by cybercriminals
This is not surprising we've been talking about it
Sears now but
The FBI's finally Lake.
Reboot your devices
They talked about using antivirus
Isolate your iot devices from other network connection
Basic secure
The other piece of news
It's worth talking about just
Because we wrote about it in the newsletter but we haven't talked about it is Charlie Kindle
The guy behind
Madam is Smart Home
Efforts
He's now at
Control4
Which is a
Professionally installed
Home automation
ABK
So I was really excited I talked to Charlie about this
And one big takeaway and you can see the interview on the website but the one they take away I thought was interesting
When I asked him
Why go to professional when you've been DIY your whole life
And he was like
Look there's just a bunch of stuff that
It's just too complicated for consumers that you just can't do
If you
Are trying to do DIY so like
Whole home audio
Video of those kind
I just really difficult
And I appreciate what he said about
The fact that both
DIY and
Professional Home install
There's a place for both
In this world in it
You know what I think he's right we focus a lot on DIY stuff
But you know what we'd do this stuff we
Elizabeth
A lot of people are like
I have no idea where to start and I wouldn't even know how to install it
So yeah there's definitely
Placerville
Oh yeah and then the second thing he said
That was worth noting is I asked him
What kind of
Technologies he was
Excited about still where the future was still going
In
One of his
Topix was voice not recite we got a lot of room to run there
Not surprised
But the second was actually high quality content
So we pulled out he's like
You know
Kind of sucked
Petco dachshund
Compression Technologies for audio and video for a while in the
Experience has it
Shipping crate so he's looking at things like for Katie
TV better audio codec
And he thinks that's going to actually make a big comeback
So
Maybe I mean my daughter would rather watch something on
YouTube and
Stream
Her Spotify list through the echo so this is not a
High quality experience
Enough about
News
Let's take a moment and go to our voicemail
From the iot podcast
Which as you guys know is brought to you by Schlage
Do not miss your chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt and Wifi adapter
All you have to do is
Call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
24 and leave us
Question and you will be entered to win in our August drawing
So call us before August 31st
And
Therefore being
And remember
Smarter homes
Start with SLI
Alright this week's voicemail is from
Noah
Big eyes
I was wondering if
You know what a federal
It is too large
Harmony is
Use it or automating a lot of
Like
And then air purifiers my
Old school
TV and I really don't want one anyway
Irregardless
Yes
Like how it's based on profiles and I have to turn one profile
Before I can
Another one
On it gets really messy when I have more
Places that I want to start
Or stop at 1
So if there's anything that you guys can see
Think of or know of
Thanks
Big props to you for using
What I would think
Unconventional technology for this particular use
I our lives like I was like
Instead of a Logitech Harmony he should go with the
Amazon
New Kindle block thing this out but then I listened to your voicemail and I was like oh no
No not freaking
Ceiling fans
Instead I'm going to direct you to
A device that I was really excited about probably really last year but
I'm not as excited about now but
It's perfect for what you want this is a device called the bond
It is
Is a $99 disc that basically uses Wi-Fi IR
And has RF
Capabilities so it will pair with your ceiling fans existing remote
Control up to
6 ceiling
Score
Six devices
It also works with fireplaces
The idea is
That you
Lincoln to this device
And then you can control it via Madam a or if
Or
Dap the bond app
And you don't have to put in like the fancy
Retrofit kits for an existing ceiling fan or replace your entire ceiling fan
So you know
I don't know it works people seem to really like it I hadn't tried it I was excited when they
Started initially.
Talking about it because
They said it was going to do more than just
Ir and RF they were going to do other
Radio frequencies
And I wanted to pair it to my somfy blinds app
Patozon
Cuz I hate my
My current some people I knew
Cementation butt
It doesn't have that yet
So I am sad
Yeah they are looking at bringing support to other devices as well though I say
Think like garage doors and some others
Yes they are right now they only have ceiling
What's in my hunches
Be on or off
You do need for an IRA if your fans are IRA
Not RF you're going to have to make sure the bond
Has a clear line of sight to the fan
Which means it's not gonna be able to
Troll
IR fans
So that's one thing to know
But it's relatively cheap
If you
Could use it for a couple things then
Crate
Ceiling fans
Controlled by Lutron on off switch so I can actually control the speed this will let you control speeds if you have the speed
With the remote
So yeah
99 bucks
And that about wraps up the show this week please stay tuned for our guest
June CEO Matt Van Horn he's going to tell us how he
Cut so much money off the price of the June and talk about data and food plus he shares a smores recipe
G4S
All of it
Coming up after this message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Spencer is
Netgear and I have John McHugh
The senior vice president
Of commercial networking at Netgear
Last week
Well we all know it for home routers
You may not be as familiar with the commercial
Do you want to talk briefly about that as I said we target
Small businesses
Especially ones that are like do it yourself
Small office home office business
The it
She department
It's actually the business owner and we're the best networking
Company allowing those people to be sick
Successful
The point frankly fairly Advanced Networks
What about security
Because me and
Routers like
Frontgate Interiors
Tire iron
Yeah that's a really good point
And in fact
Did you look at
Some of the other Solutions are out there the customers
Required
Set up complicated
Cardinals
True there
Security
To make the cloud
Connectivity work at
It's a terrible
Formula that's going to end bad
And so that's why when we designed inside
We did it from the ground up to be
Self Deployable
Absolutely
Secure what we did was we drew on the same technology we've been using for our readiness
Ready Cloud Solutions the last
Six seven years it's the same architecture we use with Arlo cameras
So that means there's
Literally
4 million of these agents
Purely running day-in-and-day-out to buy choosing an architecture which was already
Simple little boy abs
Absolutely robot
And time test
We knew that we would get in
Experience for customers wouldn't be compromised
Which is on
And you guys have notifications or maybe some sort of
Machine learning that understands when bad things enter the network
Absolutely and that's one of the
Neat things about Cloud connected
Devices
It's because what that does is
Is create a very close relationship
Between our customers
And that's your
So we can do a couple of different things for you one is
We make it very easy if you ever need help
Support with your device
Forget that we also can immediately alert you if
Through our network of paid hackers
White hat hacker
Hurst if we find a defect we can mediately let you know that there's a
Problems and help you get it
And of course customers
Set notifications and alerts
To know what's going on in their Network and the message goes right to the phone in their pocket wherever they happen to be
Anytime
Subscription for this
What we do is we provide you a to base level connection
Devices anywhere in the world you get the ability
To do all this
Cool stuff if you scale beyond that if you're starting to get to a bigger Network we do charge a nominal fee uniform
Check connectivity gets $5 a year per device that's more realistic
Continue to invest
The infrastructure and make sure that it's a rich
Performance experience
Awesome alright and John where can we go to find out more about netgear's in
Of course www
Netgear.com
Slash
Inside
Hey everyone welcome back
To The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Matt Van Horn who is this
The CEO of
June
Hi Matt how are you doing
Hello hello thank you for having me
This week
You guys
Announced what I feel is like
Pretty big deal you announced
Brand new
Cheaper June oven
So there are two versions of this
Can you tell me
About them
Absolutely
So
This is
The seven and 1
June
Cooking appliance and we Sunset the prior gen one product which is 1495 and shipping today
We have a new product
499 + 6
Okay and
499 is
Justy and ikey
Keep calling in an oven
Some of that but
Okay good I feel better
The 429 is $100 off promotion for the 7 and then you have another package
It's called the Corvette is it a package
Additional accessories
A longer wire
Warranty and bundled cookbook recipes
Got it
And that is a subscription
You get it free for the three years included with the
Package Mercy
A monthly or yearly
And I'm ashamed to say since I was such an early and
Enthusiastic a doctor that you have and I still have not tried the
Terrible
Free trial
Let's
Kick it off with
Men
I really want to know we should
How
House
Did you cut this
Greystone
So much
Kevin and I beforehand we're looking at this it looks like there's no scale in here
It looks like they're still the
Computer vision aspect of it
Looks like there may not be enough
Break it down for me
How did you go from 1495
2 499
Lots of little things
Is the best way to describe it
Particular examples
So one of the really nice things
For all of our customer
Where is that
90%
We're able to learn usage pattern
Figure out what the most important teachers are on the tree
So for example
Our automated
Cook programs
With Summer by the Cameron some U2 summer menu
Those make up 42% of all cook session
Single largest
Whale
Not to people cooking
Is by using
Are automatic
And so
When we can
Dug into that a little more
We thought about when you were the most important aspects of that and
Two of those aspects are
Able to do Oliver
Automatically
No preheat
And so are coming
That's one area where
Easily could have saved a lot of cost and
Decided not to
Based off of
And then
Camera another easy ways to take money off of our bill of materials are bomb and again
Very important
Feature to shortcut.
Access record program
And so we have that.
Those were not
Good things
Save money on and then we started looking for other place
And so one of those places
A weight scale
Report load cells
And we're able to look at the data
And see how often
People were actually wearing their food
Some people that do it a lot
The majority people
Never ever use that feature
And
So why should we have our customers
Have to pay it
That Hardware
The future that is not very used
And so we were able to actually use data on usage pattern
Figure out that that was an okay teacher
You're too removed from the product
Wait so I thought
Oven automatically
The cooking time
Haven't use weight as one
Variables
It would be a more
Valuable sensor that actually was that we would one day use it as
Of value to
Adjust cook Bergen
Fractions
I always thought you did
Colour Me surprised
I use it every time
It's automatically doing it
Temperature in the different temperature sensor
Okay so
You took out the scale
What else did you
That's one area to another area
That
Great opportunity save a lot of money
Can I lower quality
Display
Touchscreen work
Computer
Empress
I got her homework and
That was not the place to cut corners
And so we still have a
2.3 gigahertz quad-core computer on the June oven
An area that we did see that people were using
As the primary method
Communicating with their June oven
Versus using the knob
And so even though we were
The feature that
Weatherford fire
Gentoo does not have a knob on the front it's just a touch screen
But you can also
Control your voice using Alexa
Okay so that feels super controversial to me
Maybe because I'm old and I do use the
I like having that
Interface
Because it makes me feel like the oven will still work even if the
Touch screen goes kerplunk
And is that just me kidding myself
I mean if the computer goes coupon
True okay
Limited edition original
So you can brag call your friends and one of the amazing things also about softer
So you've been
With a lot of features that
I barely got any press
I'm getting a lot of press on today as
New June Gentoo features but in reality
Same operating
Platform so you've been
Getting all these features over the last year-and-a-half
Her free just as
Software update
Our new customers will get to experience all those as
I love their intro to Judy
Overwhelming
It kind of feels like
I don't know what to do with that
No I love my
Okay let's go back to cutting
Cost
Scale knob
What other things
The primary features from other areas there is a lot of simplification
Designs
So taking everything that we've learned from
How to make a
June oven in gen 1
What type of
Decisions can we make
On the second generation
There are
Variables and you only get two
Focus on two of them
So
All those variables
Quality
Quality of the product
The Nexus calling
What time so
Crunch to ship
We should go first June oven
Literally on
And then the
Would be cost
And so on
1st June oven we optimized
Quality Inn
Speed to Market
And
But this time
Basic qualities
List of most important thing
But we Orient ourselves and knew the importance
Getting a more accessible price point
And so we made sure to build that in
The shipment ready
Excellent let's talk about the plans for
June going forward I was always intrigued by you guys because
You built this
Product it was arguably smart it wasn't just connect
It was actually smart
I really appreciate it
Since I see lots of terrible connected stuff but it was expensive I was I
Constantly asking you about your business models
And I paid for upgrades in the form of
I bought an air fryer tray
Gourmet package
You know what felt like you guys had an interesting
I don't know if it's
Stainable or not model
Also adding a new lower price
What does that say about
What the business models are anticipating going with
For the next however long it takes
Where does the
From our perspective
The most important thing
To the last business I was involved in
Focused on
Getting lots of
Musers that we didn't sell a product what was the social networking
Social news site
The general idea was get lots of eyeballs
Figure out how to monetize it later
Work together
The Social Network
That's what I think that we can like about that business model
Because in that world
You can only have two masters
You deserve customers are you sure
People keeping the lights on so and usually that you know what the advertiser
And so for us we want to be able to surf
We want to make a product that's high quality that's worth paying for
That was the one requirement
When we were
Work together before we even that decided
We wanted to make something that was
HEB business
But that is hard and I say this not to be a jerk but
Because even things like Roku which sells Hardware also
Most of their money on advertising and you look at the fate of like GoPro and Fitbit
I'm thinking everyone points to Apple with nuts
Great place to be
It's really hard to be a
So
Should I expect you guys I mean are you sustainable just as selling this product
For the rest of your life do you plan to Branch out into other
Kitchen products I know a lot of companies are now looking at
Trying to talk about a hard business. Sounds like a really hard business
Every few weeks
From our perspective would focus on
We have
Relied on that in the past
Look for today when we're not relying on that
That's a big part of taking a risk
Company like June to be able to ring
A product like the June intelligent oven to Market
Bring a lot about your first shareholders
Great product
Let's flip to your subscription business
Because you guys launched the recipes tell us a little bit about recipe
Is how that's going
Herzing to try
Chicken eaters
Nope you need to work on
Cuz I want the feedback
Walkthrough
Can I was out there
And the most part
Recipes online are YouTube videos in
X-Files
Sometimes
Get some fun
Tasty or something like that but we didn't see any experience out there that
Was actually
Guided
Dress we have
This opportunity
Do guided cooking
While also having
All the right hooks
Into this
Enso
When your
Cooking in the
Recharge 499 a month
And you're doing a program where
Teaching you how to perfectly dressed up
Your iPhone or iPad
We ask you how you like your salmon
And I wish you remember
This recipe before
Otherwise it's not medium rare
And then
By the time you're at the last Avenue
Distressing
Getting it ready to go in the oven the ovens already
Expecting salmon
And already know she wanted medium rare
So you didn't have to do anything other than
Put it in there
Walkaway
For us it's about how do we
Great great experiences that are inspired people to cook more and more
Are you looking to broaden that I mean
What are the challenges with cooking is people have their own recipes they want to find stuff everywhere
I feel like it'd be impossible to
Create these awesome recipe experiences
I searched bon appetit
Cooking Light
Ione
Publix 30 cookbook
So
I look at something and paying $5 a month for
Something that I can't bring all that a digital content into its
So are you looking to be in Bordeaux
Platform play therapy
Possibly
Suppress we're only in RNA
The current plan
Crossword making new content on a
Weekly basis
Thai recipes cookbook
Really nice
We're cooking our pictures of habit
Most people cook the same things every week
And I know for my own behavior
I actually wish I was trying
You think more often
Discover something and then it just enters the routine
And so
Are you with the cookbook
Two recipes that
Weather in my regular routine now from the gym cookbook one is that are fried chicken and
Know the recipe mostly
Stewart
Watch the looping videos on the iPad of every single staff because I
Sorry I tried to cheat on the June cookbook
Fried Chicken 14 times I really don't need to watch blippi videos again
I forgot one of the most important
I literally
Room dinner
By skipping
And so even though
Following the steps
Keeping me honest and making sure that
Forget anything is really powerful
Air fried chicken
One of those dots to my regular routine
The other is this amazing
Salmon dish
Something that I I need to watch the steps everyday
Talk to me about some of this data that you've got I know that you guys for example you told the story to me
Cooking bacon in there
You realize that the most important variable in
Cooking bacon is how many slices
People use
So I'm curious what kind of data are you seeing both friend
Recipes
People were having bad
So we ended up taking all that data and those conversations and returned one bacon program in 264 bacon
Another really cool thing that
We're able to do is so now we have over
Automatically program
I'm all of them
No preheat and
We would get
In the app people can talk about their cooking
Cooking spray
Customer experience team
Things like restate program
Which in the beginning
Required
In the early days
And it was a three-step program
We would prompt you to look at at some point
And so we took it upon ourselves and our culinary team to how do we create a cook program
That
What's good or bad
Better
To do it
And we signed up for that challenge in our state program is now an eight
Step by step
Include the rest
In the middle of it and
People love it
It's great another thing that
Data wise was
We're able to look at
All the
Food that have been cooked in all the June ovens in the world and figure out what
And Lily stack rank
The top foods that we didn't have
Automated cook programs
Works we can create them
So actually I think about it
Reheating of tortillas
Was a top
3 use case that we had no cook program
Now we do
Cannot wait to try it I've been away from my June for far too long
What are some of the others
Pizza was always very popular in the gym and we have
A pizza program but we did not have a yesterday speech
Pizza
Program
Which is totally what you need
Some people do
Cookies in the oven
The pizzeria
On the oven
And we were seeing literally receipt just slices of pizza just sitting on racks
That we have yesterday's Pizza
Does it go in the rack
I always put my
Michael Mina recommend
Putting on a pizza stone under broil that's his official recommendation
I was like I was like a piece of stone that's pretty specialized stuff right there
It's already a lot
Ashley Reed
I just shove it in my mouth
Sometimes I am
Okay let's quickly talk about some of the
Gachas are things that have happened with
The oven so far so I was surprised to see that it's running
Android
This was back
Can a day are you guys still using Android or Android Things Are
Did you use
Something else for the
We
Have
And
On top of that there certain
Frameworks from Android
Design perspective
User experience perspective
There's no hint of Android with in any of the amazingly bill
We stretch the limits of what you can do with embedded Linux and certain Frameworks from Android
Create
What we call junoesque
So I don't need to worry about me
My Juno s not be
Supported in
Battlescribe
Okay can you share with us
A sense of
How much it cost
To support a June oven
Annually or how much you guys are thinking about from
Cloud security cost I know you guys spend a lot of time and effort programs an update
Appreciate
I don't have a specific dollar answer for you but
From
Perspective
Design goals when we were
Designing June is we didn't want it to not
Work
Your Wi-Fi goes down
That would be the worst experience ever that you can cook
Cook dinner because your wife I went down
And so
We spend a lot of time engineering
An experience that doesn't actually require golang
The cloud
For example
Detection
And yes we download
Updates from the server
That makes me a better butt
When all the food recognition all that happens locally all ETA or
Take the Baton.
And so is the most intense
Processing
To save money on card
George Bush
Music store
So could I bring a June oven into my house
Sand
Connected to my wifi once and then
You know check the app and just use it normally
Do that without even connecting to wifi
We have customers that have email.
Taking it camping
Running recent software
Any software updates because we're always constantly
I have many questions about getting the June oven to work
Since I am in fact
I haven't done at 5.
But I know someone who has
I really enjoy that they
Brought it with him
Yeah is there a s'more setting
Let's get real here
So there is not a
Smart setting
Something you could do
You can
Put the oven on broil
You can actually
Dissmore's an accident few weeks ago and it was
Pretty amazing election
Better than a campfire
Okay every
On that note
With Matt Van Horn
Secret tune smores recipe
I will leave you
Somat thank you so much
Coming on the
The show this week
Of course
Play for having me that's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter
Stacey on iot
Will see you next week