Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host
Your co-host
Kevin tofel
Are you guys here
Talk about
European
Appliance
Bad bottoms from AT&T
Cat M1 testing and after
And a big philosophical debate about what makes
Brother
Receipt
Keep them coming
And we've got
A message from one of our sponsors for track which actually just raised 88 million dollars this week
And our guest
Landon borders Who is the
Head of connected products at I can't say the full name of the company but is the big
Beep fanco
You can talk about what they've learned
By jumping in early into the
The connected Prada
And it's a really good interview
Stay tuned for all of that
But first
Another message
This response
Did you know on average it takes companies 18 months to lunch and iot connected product
But it doesn't have to get your product into the hands of your customers faster with cycling
Go from concept to connected in 4 months or less and get everything you need to run your connected product business cycle
Play offers everything needed to get up and running including Hardware integration a launch ready mobile app
And if I stayed up and prebuilt Integrations with tools like salesforce.com that's
I v e l y. Com for more information
Now
Moving on
To Eva
Oh Kevin I wish I was there
You know I feel the same way I have
Turn down going so many times
In the past and this year I think I'm good at most
Of all just because of all the connected products
Disappointed
So having never been this feels like it might be even more fun for a smart home
You know
UCS was always I think that big show to go to 4
Phones tablets and such but even that has bled over into
Even more this year and then because the smart home and iot categories are growing
There's just tons of stuff at you for this year and in that segment
So we were going to talk about.
The Crazy Ones
Since neither of us
Woot Germany hearing
All right all right
I was excited
Because higher
French
All right
If you know me
You know I'm super psyched about this
Kitchen talking about
Bridges I'm like I don't want to touch pad on it I just want a camera so I can see what's in there
So
Higher history
And this is their link
Cook series / 4
The next cool thing they did is not just attic
They also
Let's see what's in your fridge at offers you a recipe
What's for dinner tonight
I like that because then you don't to worry about
What ingredient to do or don't have
You can just say hey fridge
You know what I have what can I make
Right so the freaking come with 10 ideas that you would live on your own and you don't have to go run out and buy anything else
See this is where they
Like even I'll just say it IBM's Watson
The chef
Contact would be really interesting
Although many of those recipe
Having
I'll take you guys I own the shuffle
Time into these kind of databases feels fun
My concern is in
There's no details on pricing
When the sun be out so right now consider this kind
But what I'm worried about is
We're going to get these stupid like limits on
Because we don't have like a unified recipe format really yet
You're going to have to use the following
Place to get your recipe
And really I want my recipes from
Wherever I want all recipes
Recipe
Annie Frazier
Open source recipes
So hopefully that's going to happen
Right now it's
What we're getting today is things like
Drop which is the maker of a connected
To do the recipes for all of ge's connect
We just got news this week that sidechef is going to
Do the recipes for sharps u.s. Appliance
Is swelling good
This is really a first world problem
Like oh my God
A recipe online I'm not going to be able to have my oven
Automatic
Two things one yet I'm glad you mentioned drop because I was going to bring it up
Because
Drophead me that Bluetooth connected scale
Maybe 2 years ago
And it would do something sort of similar in that
If you didn't have
Maybe sugar for a recipe
It would recommend what you might have instead and it would
Yo Gotti wait and tell you exactly how much of a substitute it was
Not to the scale of a fridge that could
Do all this obviously
Number one and the other thing is this gets back to that question that we asked a show or two ago are you buying Hardware or a service
It's so cool to have a connected fridge with a camera and everything else
What is the service light that goes with it who runs it where's that day to come from and then all the other obvious IRT question security
Personalized data Etc
You got to think about where they're going to get this information from her recipes
I wouldn't buy this fridge unless I knew it had a broad range of recipes for example
I agree
Because otherwise it's just to be like tonight
I see you have a cat
Crunch cereal
But I want
Captain Crunch crusted trout
I don't actually
Also in really cool and random
Bridges we have
Panasonic
Connected sake fridge
Which is basically
I feel like anybody who
Was an engineering student in college probably built one of these it's a fridge that you can
Call to you
And it will come to you and bring you your
In this case
Sake I'm sure it would also
They sold in the us to bring new cold beer
Just tiny little fridge looks like it sits on top of a Roomba
Has voice commands and
It's got lighter so it can map its way around your home
Just feel like Africa
Yes yes yes
Yes I had a R2D2 programmable robot couple years back and I actually
Metal extendable arm I read program the route from the fridge to my
Temperature in the TV and I would have it
Bring me a beer
Unfortunately it couldn't reach into the fridge to get a beer or store and everything so somebody
Put the beer in the armpit
Get the
Idealist
Since this looks like a concept or talk to anybody been putting like
This isn't actually for the Fret set
Have Mobility
Yeah my son has parties all the time
It's a sucky fridge but it's for people with Mobility problems and I'm not saying the people with Mobility problems aren't drink
Sake
So okay that probably does it for the
Crazy
Fridge stuff I just got to restate for the record that I do not think a fridge really needs a giant touchscreen on the front
Even though manufacturers are really trying to sell this
Alright just you know
If you disagree
Can call and let me know
I'm or Justine
So I also saw I didn't see
Coverage of
A washing machine that looks pretty cool
It is the AG 9000 series from
Okapi
And it is a
Combo washing machine and dryer
Not the US market
Because we are giant space pigs who have room
For both
What this does is it has all kinds of sensors
To detect
Your Washington is
How much
Washing is actually in there and then it also can detect
The type of clothes
Fabric
And we'll wash it based on that
I'd be curious how does this and I'm actually interested in something like that because
From my running gear which is snow all
Berkeley polyester Dri-Fit stuff Nike or whoever
You're not supposed to use fabric softener on those
And sometimes I forget
And it'd be nice to have this stuff automatically
Detective don't put in the fabric softener you know cuz it'll just
I'm thinking they'll just dropping fabric softener automatically but you know if I need a shower or not suck
Yes 4 all that money
So I'd like to hear a curious how they can tell the different Fabrics apart
I talk to people from like P&G and they talk about you.
Either having messaging
Indications on the tags
Or just being able I mean if you think about a camera it could look at the fabric
Other option because then you could really tell Lake
The Weave based on maybe not later but at 3 DC
What that feels like
Also you should not dry
You should always
I know I know so I don't even know why you're sticking
Dryer in the fur
All right but this is
This is not a show about laundry
Let's talk
You know what else happened
This is not even news
Cool stuff from
Juicero
Down last week
And guys
Sweet wine
You may recognize juicero we talked about it
A couple times it was a $700
Cold pressed juice machine
They later dropped
Price $400
But
Really what it was
Is
Service
That was trying to bring you
Fresh
Vegetables get you
Eat your vegetables
Convenient easy way
Fortunately
Crazy expensive
Very tough distribution model
Because
These cold pressed juices only
I kept for like 7 days
And
Is very expensive cookware
Yeah it's almost like they took the
Razer Blade Pro
To this by saying we'll make up a lot of money on
Description in the juices and saucer with the hardware itself was just so darn expensive
Hardware was not
I don't know
So yes and
I caution companies were building connected products
Hardware
To think about this are you really selling Hardware
If you aren't
Don't spend too much on it
Because
That is sadness
I'm not surprised
So yeah
If you have it you Sarah though
This is not a product that can be really replicated
So you bought something that
There are no other things to fit into it
Keurig when they stop producing cake
Cups
My life would not go on for me
Yeah okay
Now into
A little bit of
Industrialist news we've got this is not Industrial
This is
Security Eros
Kevin Wendt
We are so if you have AT&T U-verse
Service and you have an Arris modem router or Gateway that was provided by AT&T I guess where you could have
About yourself listen up because no motion security
Has said we found five laws that are so easy to
Pax that we just go public with it
Fact they didn't even go to the vendor like I normally do with a waiting. To see if Eros would fix it
They just went public with it so there's a couple of issues here and I think we should have a link to the new motion
Blog because they
They show how you can close some of these holes and that's what they are there holes
Cute cute cute
And to be fair I think some of these
May have been included for
AT&T 2
Provide customer service get logs and things like that that's not an excuse I think this is inexcusable I think regardless of Harrisburg
Reducing is modems AT&T is the service provider and they are the ones that should be on the hook to fix this in my opinion.
That's just me
One of the issues is
The exposure of an SSH
Shell
Remote access
To the internet from these routers
And
Username or password is hard-coded right in the firmware so you have
Access to have access to the mall so that is not good there other default credentials that are sitting in there that are just
Available for people exploit not good Motel said I see basically it just too many ways of poor
That's open for remote access that shouldn't be open just not good at all
Indeed
And you got a little rule in here saying you shouldn't be renting your modem about 80% of people in the US
Apparently do get their modem
Straight from there is
Please stop please stop people from 2 that there's actually some interesting things that are developing with the internet of things here
Will just take a note 2
Talk about it if you are a Comcast customer
You actually have to get their modem and Gateway because it's got software that
Works with their Pokemon
What's happening there is Comcast is like
Trying to make that
I think it's up to $10 a month
A little bit more worthwhile
But
If they're doing
They should darn well make sure the
I'm I'm okay with paying a modem rental fee if you're going to have those additional features or years we paid a fee for just
Access Electric
Terrible
Not to mention the other reason I had this rule is as one you can save money by
Getting a cheaper modem never launched
The third-party routers
Offer features
Far faster
For earache far faster than what is provided by the isps you know today we got Mesh networking through various
Options that are out in the market you got faster speeds I think up until a year or year-and-a-half ago
Verizon was trying to get me to rent at 8 to 11 for a while get out of here
Very few reasons in my Pinto by rent a motorized if you can help it
Yes
All right
In the show notes
So
Let's talk about
Cat 1 Test
That's right
You really like cat M1 for some reason
I just
Actually I like it be iot
What is
One of these
Low power
Wide area network
Technologies but it is a cellular
So
Think of it in the same kind of mental space
Sort of as sigfox
Lorawan nb-iot
The difference is it actually has
Way bigger
More Gatorade so this is
Better
Cellular
Right in the news
This is not
Earth-shattering news but I want to bring it for two reasons one the first reason is that
MTN in South Africa is trialling their new cat M1 network with Ericsson and Qualcomm
That is the first test in the continent so that's kind of cool importantly I
Notice this little nugget
In that
They're adding Erikson's added support for voice over LTE
This platform for cat M1 that's been implemented trial
And like why would they do that
Will Boise is relatively low bandwidth so it's
There's enough speed enough pipe there to handle the why would you do it it's all for Internet of Things what Erikson said is that the
Addition of
Voice over LTE on Cottman Ave Network
Let's telcos
Connect to iot devices in the apps and services
They could benefit from these boys services such a security alarm panel
First aid kits
Wearables digital lock
Disposable security garments
I'm like that's actually good idea so if you have a security system that's using say cat in one network to have its constant connectivity
G2a monitoring service
You could actually
You know in case of a break-in
Make a call
On that same network
Or to those people I never thought about that
Okay
And I don't disagree with that and I see
That's one way that Cellular Connection Ali win in this area cuz I think right now it's pretty expensive like for example and a half
Africa I know of several
I feel like
That's going to be a hard sell but
That's a good way to try to
Yay
I think it's time to talk about
Assistance
All the philosophical Quest
Question
So yeah
Antifa
Everybody had enough
Assistant
Baker, Laura
In Kevin and I were wondering
When do you need a smart speaker
What features do you need
Assistant speaker
Do you need a speaker
My gosh
What kind of features do we need in these smart
Home assistant
Should be calling them
I don't know if we should call them smart home assistants not all of them because you have and I haven't most people that was in the show
A digital assistant integrated to their phone already weather is Siri
Weathers Google Assistant
Whether it's Bixby whether it's
Even Amazon Echo Services because that is coming on more phones so
That's not a smart home assistant that's a digital assistant what I'm asking for information
Contextual information popping up reaching out to me that kind of thing
Like the number of times I use
Google Assistant
Is Winn-Dixie
And I don't know why I really don't know why
Let me ask you a question that may give you an idea
How often are you away from your Echo
Your Google home and other things like that
I am away from it but then I'm usually in
In public life
Stepping out so the only time I use it was probably in my
Okay
So I talk to my phone whenever I'm out of the house
And want information
Because there is no dedicated assistant around I mean it's just
There isn't there these are all fixed
Assistance in my house
Right
And I guess
State is not very social outside of the house
So you just walk up to people and say hey do you know how far it is to the Moon
B6 don't often come up when I do I actually usually
No it's a it's a different anything wrong with that seriously
Beijing ribs
We are sure you're not no you're not weird there are people who still do not want to talk to devices
Outinpublic not to their watch not to their phone and so on
I get it I don't judge that's fine
No I might go
I might still judge
Alright so
And it just a friend of mine actually just asked me if they should buy the Echo Show
The echo
And I was like
You know it's kind of cool
Show me some
Corgi videos
I don't have anyone really to talk to drop and capability
Right
I don't think I would spend that much money on the echo show again
So I feel like I don't need a video screen
Because I don't
I got a TV
Really functions
Perfectly
If you have a Chromecast you can
Use Google to say hey
Show me this on the TV. Easily anyway
I think it's an intriguing product but I don't
Think it's
How can I be a speaker hit as maybe the original Echo devices quite honestly because it requires to get the most out of it
Requires more than one
So you can do the video call and so on
But that kind of stuff I just do over the phone or computer wherever I am anyway
I don't want a dedicated video box
They're definitely use cases
With kidney touch with his family that's far away that maybe they're not very technical I get that but
That's on me
I would love to have more Bass
What's a Google home
Things I would love to
Hey
Speaker assistant
Person add such-and-such at 12
I think
That kind of interactivity
In the ability to affect other apps would be really cool and no one's really
I breathe I'm hungry
What else do we need
We need good quality
I think it's fair I mean a lot of people buy these things now because of they're tapping into music services that can connect and they want
Voice Control music music
Chola people
Summer fine with say the standard assistance are available today that you
Echo is your Google home and so on so forth
New Google Assistant
Enable speakers coming out soon
Now that you Frozen play we got
Whole list
Of
Smart speakers and I've noticed something very interesting
They're all coming from big-name audio companies such as Harman Kardon
Sony
Panasonic
Onkyo
Their stuff is typically not cheap and sure enough these quote-unquote smart speakers or digital assistants are also looking.
Gucci prices look much higher than the echo products for example
And that's because
They have more robust speakers maybe some more features and so on and I think it's also because
They're getting in because they saw Apple's homepod for 350 and figure hey Apple can make a good sounding speaker
With additional assistance
350 we can do the same for two three four hundred dollars Etc so
It's just interesting the number of
Large audio companies getting it on the skin PPL is another for example
Fourth is expected to announce their digital assistants be
So it'll be
And whether or not my existing
Chris compatible through the echo is supposed to have
Cross your fingers on that way you know it's really nice though about all this
There there are
Smart
Home digital assistant speakers for every type of budget
And every type of listener right now
You couldn't say that a year or two ago
Now you
There was only one
But even even so even the ones that have come out since then have been relatively inexpensive and some munchies
I know we talked about the UV before I think it was actually on sale for $29 but you know your Echo dot is $49
We talked about one called the fabric
With a Q
And that was like
Ridiculous
Low priced it was like
That wasn't one
Yep right wasn't always listening you've got more great choices again for every budget every sound level
Tell the speaker said I'm seeing that we're now sativa
This could be your whole sounds
System for your house and you get the added benefit of the connectedness
So this is
I think
You know it
I like playing music
Over my existing speaker
I don't want to
I don't want a constant
It is kind of a pain
But
You got the Amazon is built into
Lighting it is built into things like the ecobee so you've got a bunch of products that
Their justice system
They're not even not speakers exactly
Exactly they are the interface really for your smartphone that's what started all this and I think that will still open
To be Central to all the types of products speakers is a big one because
The dual purpose of listening to these Music Services since most people are now streaming music not no uploading or playing CDs or
Vinyl Runner
I have my. I have the entire Beatles collection on vinyl thank you
Once a month or so
Versatile
All day everyday on SiriusXM
That's what I thought
We should do a
Minor quiqup
I got yelled at so badly by my child
Because I switched the multi-room audio on the echo
Just try it out last
Are you guys on Amazon music settings
Spotify didn't
And she was getting so frustrated cuz she was trying
Play her
Music she's like nothing is available to me
I realized
Leominster dog
It's still broken yellow
Until I can play the music I want
When I want it it's just not you
Especially for everybody who still trying to build off these clothes Chico CA
If you don't support everything
Hi God it's like you support nothing
Are at this point
What's a good sex
Ruined it into
Voicemail
Okay so last week we started
Highline
Can dial it
You know the number I have
6 to 3
742 4
We've already had a lot of gall so thank you guys
We will play some some we're going to hold off on
Just for now
And some are actually lovely
Questions that don't want to be on the air which is totally fine
We had a voicemail from Jonathan
Then and he noted that it's kind of interesting with like the Microsoft
Amazon Cortana speaking to Madame a
News
Connected speakers are
Now talkin
And he didn't really have a question he just threw that up and I was like you know he's right it is and I think this is actually a disturbing
Worrisome trend
Because what we're seeing is Brands getting in there and saying
Hey this
Smart home stuff
It's going voice
Okay if voice has been extra why I need to get my brand in here
And how many do that
Yeah and
It is interesting I drew Jonathan it's concerning to me because I don't want to do prison with Jonathan
Said he'd said that there's an Amazon Echo skill that talks to Google
So you would ask the echo to reach out to Google to get information but that's like second and third hand
Commands and I don't want the interface
Just gets me my information I don't want to have to think about who I'm asking the question to an how to ask it right
And probably this means that we should have
Oh my gosh you know we talked about open recipe standard
Voice UI
Getting access to this data should probably be something like
XML
Or HTML and not
Controlled by
Central
And I say that because I'd rather just be like
Computer just do this for me
Right as opposed to
What's happening now is one you have to pick between the Amazon Echo Google home
Apple's homekit and then those guys are going to have their own skills that
Can't wait so right now GE actually has Geneva
Will tell you how
How to cook your
Cakes
Roast chicken in your ovens
That's well and good except you got to be like oh hey
You know mattimeo let me talk to Geneva Geneva I want to cook something
Preheat my oven
When really you just want to talk to
One thing and say hey
And then you were at at 2
I agree with you I think it's going to be a challenge until we decide that we want to separate the interface
From the data if we have a standard interface for voice perfect and then everybody can compete
Who's got the best data to answer the question get the best recipe etcetera but I don't
Think that's going to happen because everybody's push for their own natural language processing technology in addition to the data
So
It's kind of a mess
We broke the open
All right here
The lovely Quest
Craig
Hey folks this is Greg here first
Time caller long
Time listener
Feel free to embed my message in your show that would be awesome
Question about a bunch of light switches I've been putting in my home lately
They're made by a company called homeseer I believe that
The New England area maybe New Hampshire
Vermont
What do you know about these folks
Have you experimented with the products before
And you have anything to say about the Hub that they build I currently want to wink hub
At home ear would sure love to see me used on HUB I'd love some comments for you about that
I do I have an opinion I guess I should
Did say I'm because I'm not used homeseer
Ever and I don't think Stacy you have either a couple questions so I just told Kevin that we should get a hug
Start playing
Which I agree we should definitely do that but in the meantime just to give an opinion on Craig's question I think
Hamster has some nice qualities
Is that you know your data can be local now.
The cloud so you know maybe your internet connection goes down and you know all your stuff still work
The problems that I see though with homeseer even though it may be a stellar solution
Is a couple things one it is not cheap the cheapest
Smart home controller right now from Home Series 19995 and then there's a second one that has more stuff in it
399 95 and then the
Best one is $899.95
So it's not cheap compared to a wink or SmartThings or some other hub
In addition to that not all of the service Integrations are free in fact if you go to home Siri
Site
You can see that you can purchase plugins
For homeseer
Some of these are free which is great you know you can say work with Z-Wave and insteon
No problem
But if you want
To add Lutron caseta
Yeah it gets expensive and
I want to go throw them cuz there's a whole list of plug-in
Summer free
My fear is that you really have to think ahead what products you want your husband support before you invest in a home syrup
Because you're going to
Implement this and then if you want to add something later is that going to cost me
Were you $50 as I get the drivers and they asked
Will say that you get to try all the plugins for free for 30 days so it's not by have to keep buying
Get to try stuff but I just worry about that it's an interesting business model but it's not one that I would personally want to
Go for I would go for something that has much broader product range that is included or included at no extra charge
All right
Next week more listener questions and in the meantime though I did want to do an update
To me this week we lost internet
Access we lost power and internet
Access so as a reminder to everybody who's dealing with connected
Homepro
It's important to understand how these things behave when your power goes out so for example your hue light bulb
ABS because your switches on they will
Power goes out they all and comes back on they all go back on
Everywhere in your house all your hue light bulbs
Turn right back on max power
There are other things like the Amazon Echo Power and Boots back up
It will also go
And I believe
So
As a fun little test
If you want I can do this for you by turning my house off
I'm telling you what
Brakes
Hit your power button just to see what happen
Because
You're likely if you've invested a lot of smartphone
We ran through
Because we didn't want to wake up
My daughter and turning off the Hue Lights at the switch that we
We remembered we had
And I think we still were surprised by some
I don't remember what it
Oh it was our air filter but that is not connect
So it just talks to us
Just for fun
So not even connected products
And then the other thing is a couple nights ago
We lost internet access
Normally The Echoes will let you
You know if it has no enter
Access but
It doesn't
I guess in the middle tonight I'm not sure what happened there
Put my WeMo
Dimmer switch so that the product
To put in my bedroom
To my chagrin
It started blinking
Bright red
And it was very bright
Is a very bright LED
I was like oh
Is Boogie bright red what does that mean
So at 4 a.m.
Consulting my WeMo app
What is this
Psycho it needs the internet's out I don't care I'm sleeping but I couldn't get back to
So I
A washcloth
Because that's how I
Where is painters tape
But I did find out that I could actually manually hit that
Even though I swear to God I did on that button
And it's supposed to turn it off
24-hours so should your I still think this is
Little baby don't have to Blink the light in
Maybe I'm sleepy
Agreed
If this happens to you apparently if you hit that button
It will
Turn it off for 24 hours and
You don't have to
Shuffle around for painters tape
All right
That is all the smart
Dick and Let It Go
From one of our sponsor
Before we do stay tuned for Landon borders from big
Bleep fans I can't say the name
And still retain our PG rating on iTunes but it's
Big butts
I really don't know what
You guys fight
I like big phones and I cannot lie
Like big fan
You really got to sing this
Not going to happen
Okay
Landed is going to tell us
What is company learned by building a connected product all the way back in 20
T12
Which is you know ages ago in Internet time
Re-echo so stay tuned
Hey everyone we are breaking into this week's Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Forgerock and I have Ashley Stevenson who is the identity technology director at Fortress
If we're going to talk about what companies are doing with your digital identity management solution
So let's just get started with what you guys are doing with TomTom
Identity platform to secure and manage a business asset that really is becoming an increasingly hot commodity
These days and that is digital identity
Manager growing range
Including those of iot devices
And I need to understand the relationship
Between
Their customers
Across the different business
The spine and how they relate to those device
See this with many of our customers they had
Digital identity living in a lot of different places
There's a lot of different disconnected places
Which made it very difficult for them
Single picture of what their customer is doing what their customer needed
And it made it difficult for them to give their customers
Experience across their different offerings
So what does that mean in practice
They were able to connect with the Ford rock-a-dundee platform all of the different psilocybe ID
And that would enable them
Provide different and better service
For their customers
Single sign-on across
Services
And the ability of their
In-car device's
This is actually have digital identity
The identities of the devices
Customers
Cross all of the
Difference
What's the identities of the devices
In the cars
And the customers wear
And give the customer the best
Possible sign in
User experience possible
So what does it do to add to it
The business value
Personal single sign-on really is the culmination
We talked about on the back
Ties together integrated
What sites done
It really does ADD
Three main business benefits for the customer
Experience it's easier
It's more efficient but the other one is
It's more efficient not to single sign-on but bringing together all these identities
Springs more business efficiencies as well because now
TomTom
Doesn't have to try to understand their customer and their data across all the
Silo's lacrosse
Alien
They actually have a more efficient method of providing services to their customer and understanding their customer
Last but not least
Security is another large business benefit of
Single sign-on
Capability because it effectively reduces the attack surface
Compromising one of the TomTom customer
Because when there's only one account to authenticate and if you're up in any one of them
Push authentication where you don't even have a password now you only have one
Places open instead of 15 or even more
And where can someone go to find out more about
Definitely recommend for draft.com where we have this and many other case studies lots of other information about our
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Landon borders who is the director of connected devices
So this large fan
I'll put it in the show notes
Landon you guys make
Ceiling fans
Residential or commercial you guys also actually have a bunch of other products
Right exactly you know we started as a
A company that makes large-diameter ceiling
Dan's but got into the lighting business and we sell lights
For industrial applications and for the home and
Residential ceiling fans
Things we do controls for our products so yeah we kind of branched out a little bit
All right and I first discovered you guys actually probably in the pages
But it was back in
How to say the 2013 2012 time frame when introduced
Haiku can you talk to me about what was going through your mind
Back in 2012
Cuz you were doing this
What were you guys thinking about
What was the impetus for logic this
What we wanted to really provide our customers was a fan that just
Knew how to keep you
We wanted to get rid of the pull chain we wanted to get rid of the dimmers on the wall and
We wanted a fan that was
Smart enough to just keep you comfortable based
Two ponds the room temperature whether not you were in the room
And so forth so that's when we launched the sense
Give me technology feature for the haiku
Okay so up until 2014
Your products
That's correct
All right in this sense me though was amazing
Because like you said it was kind of like bringing that Nest mentality of algorithms and intelligence happening behind the scenes
To just be like oh
It's warm in here we should totally turn
Yeah
Exactly and you know really we also launched app
Control and it was
Was primarily at the time we saw that is up
Configuration tool
First scheduling
In setting the fan
Settings just as you wanted them but ultimately
You know our philosophy was get our users out of the app as soon as possible
We wanted the fan operators autonomously is pause
Batman that was actually kind of novel
Because I had a lot of companies I would be trying their devices
You have to remember that this launch before the Amazon Echo
So it came out the end of 2014 but the
Voice control for smart home devices
March or April
I just got to set the stage for ever
All right so back in this history
And what happened
What
Did you learn
From this process
Yes we launched
The sense me feature
And it wasn't for us it was never a you know we're going to launch this and make it available to our customers and then
And that's just what it is we had a very ambitious roadmap we were working on Partnerships with
Companies like nest and others
We had a plan and we wanted to
Continue building and can
Continue providing value
To darkest
Tremors through software updates and through the launch of
Integration
As frequently as
Sweets office
So that's exactly what happened
And you guys were also
As soon as part of your roadmap but you actually helped
With the development of
The thread protocol
Which is a wireless protocol with nest in Samsung
Now
Your first sense me did not have
But how did that go and how did that align
Yeah it was all part of our strategy
And we works with nest
What's the early stages actually pre-acquisition
And as you noted we shared
Very similar philosophies
Somehow these products
Working operate
And
We got to understand the vision For Thread and how it relates to the home
So we invested
Eveleigh in
Helping to
Develop
That specifications
I believe it's red just was
Wildly amazing
In terms of
Membership and in terms of
Contribution
So that was a pretty amazing adventure
Okay thread has not exactly
I know the formal specification took awhile to come out but it's been out for about a year
And I still don't see a lot of thread
Products
Does that disappoint
Yes or no
I mean I'm very proud of the work
That's thread group
Put into building the specification
I think the technology is great
It's designed
Quite well by a lot of very smart people but
Thread is more analogous to Wi-Fi
Then it is to Bluetooth in what I mean is
Frozen Network
Lair
Templates the networking layer stack only it does not contemplate the application
An application layer is what end users
Understand and know so I think
One of the reasons why adoption is not
Widespread is that this industry is still trying to solve for the
Unified application layer
Problem if you will and so there appears to be a convergence
Chinese ecosystem
Such as the one
Provided by Amazon
And
Google home and
Homekit but
Again the adoption of those ecosystems if you will don't include
Fred as of yet so
Because that's just
My opinion is that
You'll see
Larger or widespread adoption
Kenneth read once it includes or is included by those he goes to
Well maybe the new Echo will have a
Thread radio eyes closed
Okay
So let's talk about your CEO did an article
The Harvard Business Review that I read in
I said I was part of my newsletter in a lot of other people
And he basically we're talking about the lessons you learned
From connecting
Your products with this idea that not all of your consumers really wanted
Connectivity so
Is it only half of your users actually use some of the sense miracle
Connected options
Yeah that's correct so at roughly half and
As I mentioned we were
Extremely proud of
Listen to me products that we launched and we continue to build and introduce new features
As time went on and what we decided was
Well you know these
Other half
Of our customer
Base they would
Really appreciate these features to and use them if only they had access
Rather than
Charge extra for them let's just make this
Standard offering in all of our Haiku fans
I thought that was great now
You also talked about the adoption curve like
Who is getting curious
If you can talk a little bit more about
That's because like for ceiling fans are really interesting product
Me because they are something consumers
Yours are
Kind of expensive
But there
Well worth it
But I haven't installed them
Because it's a big job and I already have some that work just fine and
Extra
Seamlessness
Is it really work
No so I'm curious where your other customer
Why you think they are
Adopting the
Quite as rapidly
I think what we learned
You know cuz we made this a standard feature the beginning a toy
In launch today
CES
But since then what we've learned is that nothing has really changed the p
People that really want these
Smart features on our products are the ones that use the mullet
And there's
Just a large portion of our customer base that
Values
The beauty of the fan that values the energy efficient
And all these other features of the fan that make it a great product less the technology
I think in hindsight and when you read this article that's the message that were really trying to
I convey here
Is that thrust
This is a feature that we build we thoughts
Your people had it they would adopt it but in hindsight is just
Some people don't want the tech.
And which is fine with David are we still value those customers just as much as any other
Of course
Unlike your ceiling fans
So exact
This is another element of connected products that I think a lot of people
Belt connector products may be ignored it
First but this idea that
If I buy a ceiling fan I expected to last for a really long time which includes maybe software update
It's overtime if I'm using those pictures
So would you change anything differently and maybe it's
Budgeting for software development over a 10-year life
Maybe it's introducing a an expiration date for software updates I don't know
Anything about the business of building a Connect
Good product that you've learned in your life
We should adapt this way
Yeah I think
Let's face it we are at Midwestern
Product,
And
This was
Speedo blue ocean for many of us
And we know we're isolated from binos
The San Francisco technology braintrust and we're learning a lot of things
As we went along
And you don't understanding where the market wood trim to and
Cost of the technology over time as we
In the background you know pay for PRI AWS bill
And so forth right so I'd say that we didn't have good foresight into that but we certainly do now
I know by the way that market is changing
Quite a bit right it's getting a lot less
Expensive for manufacture
Like ourselves
I think we wouldn't change much I think actually our philosophies
Still a great
And I think the only thing that we would change in hindsight would be to just simply
Make this feature available to the people that want
What's in the people that don't we still have a great product and then
You know I think that
A very unique
Approach to this Market
What does it mean to say make
That feature available to those who want
I know that you guys talked about making only one
All of your products are
Because otherwise you're carrying different skews in that's complicated so what is it mean when you say
We talked about the modularity of our
And we designed them in a way such that
The technology
You can be easily added or removed
The technology that
Ads cost
Basically to the product
Sofa manufacturers
Perspective
As our products are going down the assembly line theoretically then we can add a removed
This technology before it goes right custom
Send it doing this
The customers that want these features
We can provide those to them by just simply adding
This module
If you will and then those that don't want it
Just get the same product when I'm less the technology
So we see that taking this modular
Approach works really well for our cus
Got it
Have you changed to start doing
Yeah it's been a work-in-progress you know starting with
BL series fan that we launched
Superstar to take
Approaching not to give away too much but we've ever as you might expect lots of products in development
And have been taking this approach to designing New Prague
Over the course of the past several months
And there's an idea about you guys had
Common in there about dealing with customers
And customer service
So what have you learned
Has you've introduced
It's starting to come into
To the market a little
What if you learned there
Well starting with your first question
Regarding
Customer service
I think some Growing Pains
The early days
We had to become networking experts here
But you know that was anticipated
When did we adapt
Quite well to that
But of course you know there's a
Expense associated
But we have a very unique
Sales Channel
Soho cigar products
Sold directly
You are customer
So as a product developer such as myself
That provides us with
Very direct feedback to and from our cost
What we've learned
To do and to value is to really invest in
The customer
And we're in at because of our unique position we can
Can do that and adapt
Quickly whereas
List lot of manufacturers in the
Space really rely on retail partner
So they lose that connection
As a customer start
Using Integrations how does that change
Customer service
It probably does
Yeah it does
So you know we did launch our integration
Chicken with Amazon
And
The Voice
Control features in again it was
Huge success
For us and our customers loved it and in fact
They use it a lot more than we
Originally anticipated to control our fans and lights in the
That mean it's quite amazing
So that he knows we course correct when these types of things happen in
When we look to invest in
And similar Integrations as you might expect
Now let's homekit
Specifically you know that is as I mentioned before we have this direct line if you will try our customers and that is something
Thing that are customers
Want
And ask for a lot
But frankly it's not been
Azizi
To develop
Homekit integration
As it has been
For sale
Nestor the Amazon
The integration
Is complicated I guess for manufacturers and
I would venture to guess that's why you haven't
Cny
Brand adoption
At home care by other similar me
Okay yeah well I was Casino, kid it seems that there is kind of a moving Target
And it feels like just
Recently we got a lot of good news from Apple
Quit home-based voice can
Supposed to just Siri Bay
On the phone this
Doesn't have to be a hardware Serta
Vacation ship
Was I think a big deal for companies for like
Modular home kits Pacific lines
Terrible so it feels like that's been
A bit of a moving toy
Yeah I think that's
Fair to say it has been but you know just as well
Everyone's learning center
Exactly what I was going to say and even here just is
The little guys if you will like us or learning
On the way does the big guys are too and
Dark Horse correct
That's just how this
Is going to evolve
So how do you build a product that's flexible enough to
Course correct
Because I do think in the past and even going forward I think we're still we are not at the finals
Someone who's got a
Like a semi-permanent install in someone's home
How do you build a product is flexible enough to handle that course correction Dothan
Hardware but also in software
You hit the nail on the head you have to treat both of those
Differently in
You have to have strategies
And so on the software side I think that
Companies like ourselves and most iot
Companies provide a means for updating the software in their Prime
Typically over the Internet or through an app
I think that's how you
Accommodate
Implants
Tour
The future on the software
But the more difficult
Thing to plan for is only Hardware
So it wasn't that long ago that we all had
802. 11 B
Wi-Fi routers that are
Our home and those are now obsolete
And then you have other technology such as
Just thread that are up-and-coming and you know how do you plan for that
And
For us
Especially
Our company the products that we still have very long
Life cycle
And are warranties are conducive to that
So
We have to be thinking 30 years
And
With the way that we've
Accommodated
The hardware that I've it is
By taking this modular approach
You know just as
We can
Add a remove this Hardware feature in our product
Internet on the assembly line we've done it in a way that
It's simple for customers
To do that so that
If yours to come the neck
Great networking protocol comes out than week
Develop that
Portion of the hardware and shipped to our customers that I want
Okay that makes sense no a 30-year warranty on the hardware are you prepared to offer like 30 years worth of likes
Security update
For those fans
I'll just so that our sales team
Doesn't kill me
For saying that
Sitar lifecycle I mean
Fans are expected
The last 30
But our warranty is
15 year war
So
I wanted to clarify
I don't get in trouble
All right
Warranty on these things doesn't mean you're going to warranty or software you guys have plans to update and do all of that
We're still all in
And you know our plan is to
Continue.
Support these customers
And
They are the products that they bought and they know as of right now I don't we have no other plans other than
N to continue to
Support these customers
Provide software updates as the world around us changes as
There's new iOS
Update or new networking updates we continue to
Provide that extra value.
Our customers
Okay that's a tall order
Because like if I think about you guys
Just spending
$3 a year
On AWS for a
Example or 8
87 million fans
You've got a $3000000 line-item
Every year
For the next 50
And that feels
I don't know
Balance sheet
Cuz your private company
I feel significant
Yeah well you know it's not for everyone
And you know IR
Again premium fans that were selling to our customers in
Materials
And Technology
And performance
And so you know we have that affordance
But you know if we were
Not to pick on anybody but if we were
Selling at a light bulb then that's a whole different ball game
So maybe it's a different ball game but they have the market will dictate what they're willing to pay for these products and
I think we've all seen the smart light bulb market is
Continue to go down in price
And more manufacturers have gotten to that game
It may not make sense for those companies to offer that level of support for that.
Alright Linda take so much for coming on the show this
My pleasure and always enjoy speaking with you
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can
Can sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
Dot-com will see you next week