Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham and this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
An amazing show
We got
Apple
Is it really need a series
Speaker about the Amazon look
Because
We're actually also going to talk about a new iotc
Security products
Samsung greeting Bixby voice
To South Korea
Google home getting more
Device support
ATT
Do a lawsuit against
Company XIV
An interesting little factoid from one of our listeners
Our sponsor this week
Is
If
If I have an exciting news announcement there too
So you're going to listen to that and then stay tuned for our guest
Bjorn block
Of Ikea
HomeSmart
We're going to talk about traffic lights
Meatballs
Ikea smart home strategy
So
Jam-packed full of goodness are you ready
Before this
I'm ready but people probably have to listen to my landscaper
Do I apologize
First
We had another ad
Is Samsung artik you have a great idea for an iot business Samsung artik and easy interop
Purple and secure iot platform lets you focus on building your business rather than worrying about technology
Arctic provides fully integrated Hardware cloud and services interoperability with other devices
In-service clouds and system-wide security Samsung Arctic coyote gets down to business
More information visit Arctic. IO that's a r t i k.
Alright Kevin
Let's get this show started with
Does Apple need
TeleStaff
We can talk about the question but the news or
Licor remember how we want to put it is that apple is coming out with a Siri equipped speaker
This information comes from
KGI Securities analyst ming-chi
Quote was actually one of the better
Predictors of what apple is doing he looks
At supply chain like nobody's business and
He's thinking that
Maybe at WWDC or Apple's developer conference in June that they announced this
Siri equip speaker with
A subwoofer and 7 tweeters to provide excellent sound
Map of the question
Do they need it
Well I think they do but they need something else first
I need to improve Siri
They need they need to improve Syrian it and here's the thing if I'll be watching the the developer event
Live keynote which is where I would predict
They would announce something like this if they're going to
And the first thing they
Should be doing if they start talking about Siri and improvements to Siri
Then I would say
Chloe's on
Target for this
If they don't
I don't know I mean
Siri is just
In my opinion does not nearly as good
As Google assistant and the Amazon Echo
I can't speak pretty good about Bixby because I don't have Bixby voice that we talked about that a little bit more
But serious just not that great it just has
Seems stagnant
It is
Not that guy
I don't spend a lot of time talking to Siri my husband does
Not in
Crest
I guess if they can get Siri cuz yes I would be super frustrated shouting something across the room and
I'm not sure I can help you
But just keep you very limited information not be very conversational to have follow-up
Iteration
Amazon Echo is like
Agreed
Who created
Saudi Arabia it's not perfect. I totally agree with you there when it from
Conversational standpoint the echo is not there
It is something I think Amazon needs to address
But the echo has a lot of other positive that make up for that shortcoming
So what would let's assume Apple has the same
Model word
Has a limited
AI
What would it really bring to the table here well
Homekit
Right homekit device
Control
I would see this as an attachment for Apple music subscribers if the sound is really good could even sell more Apple
Music
Subscriptions and I would not anticipate it works with other services are easily
Amazon's Echo
Guys okay with that Google home does not
Premature Google play music
Play I can get Spotify
Because we mentioned that she word
We should mention
Oh yes I work for Google as a full-time consultant
Touch it more there Enterprise area with Android in Chrome not with
Iot devices
Direct
I would say
Where we could see some cool stuff from Apple is things like healthkit integration
So
What if you can ask your I think you can actually ask
Your Fitbit data from
The echo
Where is it
A scale for that although I've never done it so maybe they
There isn't but being able to say hey
How's my health
But today might be real
Could be could even listen to see if you're snoring at night
I stuck so update you all I have not gotten my mice
Snoring pillow
Not yet
It's expected to come I think
Like another month
All right yes
Sew in
Pricing
Sure
Corset well
At least as much as an echo
Which is 189 although you mention right before the show there some refurb units
On sale like right now for 130 something
Yeah it's just really almost too good to pass up if you want an echo
As far as Apple pricing Shores it certainly a
At least 199 device if not
A 249
Device
Yeah now it would be nice if this device actually
Replace stored in replace augmented
Apple TV or an iPad as a home
Hub
Homekit wire
Yeah that could that could work in which case you know
There's a definite Advantage there
And an even I could see them
You know sell multiple ones that stream music simultaneously kind like a Sonos
Exactly
I think there's an opportunity I would love for these things
Play nicely the one thing I am sad about with Sonos and kind of missing this boat
Is there whole mission
Was to be this neutral
Kind of
Delivery device for the internet music
Tell him I'm kind of like
I don't know if I really want to see this fragment
And it's so much especially because I used my
Echo Dot
My television
Right
We'll just real quick related but not on the show notes
We mention saunas the Galaxy S8 and S8 Plus
Phones at
Launch last week
We're two weeks ago rather
The first phones with Bluetooth 5 Ashley
Use the feature that allows you to stream the same song over Bluetooth
Two different speakers I do with my Amazon tap and my Amazon Echo
And actually works pretty good it's not a saint I was
Of course but
If you have multiple bluetooth speakers that works pretty well
Okay
Good to know
Celine cheaper alter
Speaking of voice
Assistant
I have to ask Kevin
So recorded the podcast last week
Amazon
Free Amazon book
Echo with a camera
It is designed to take pictures of your outfits
To give you style advice
Is it
What's happening
Really I thought I thought you'd be all over this thing
Will you be like this
I did Aspirin
I'm not going to lie I told my husband
Right now anyone from Amazon listening to this
I would like
An invite so
I have to get your thoughts on this so
A hands-free voice-activated selfie camera that tells me what I already know which is I have no Style
Me personally
Not interested at all however
It's interesting to me would it do you think would be fair to say this is a
Product targeted at women
Probably end
I put something out my newsletter about
What I thought was great about this and what I thought was just
Beyond weird
I think Amazon's pushing
The envelope
Are people ready to have a camera
I just in their home but this is if it's checking out my outfits
It's like a bedroom
Closet
Bathroom tile
Getting personal now
Feels like
Those are not places where
Right now I'm even
There's no mechanical closed
Camera button
Which I thought was like
Please add that
But Amazon's been trying for fashion for a while
It's the flight one of the last holdouts of like
Retail for them
Where can I get a sense of exactly what's in my closet if I own some
I guess they're going to know all of me
I think it's a great idea for a service once it has information to be like
Hey Stacy
It is cold outside and you have an appointment
Maybe you should wear this
And my brain.
Yeah I know I mean it brings the assistant
To another level
So I can
See that
It's going to get some information as you said that they don't have today about what's in our closet
Knight start suggesting
Items to buy
You know like hey your you need an update in here which
Tell me it is a spell I haven't
Yeah I all you have is Beatles t-shirts and jeans and high tops
You need some help
I'm not saying it I don't see this as a viable product I think it's
Targeting particular audiences
So it's less Universal then say their Echo products are current Echo products that's a lot
I also talked to somebody
Who does
Craft block
And she was like
I don't care about 4 outfits but having something where I can put a
A camera like a mount above my hands while I'm doing
She says
Sewing project and then say take a picture
It have it take that
Picture that would be really great for me from a blocking
And I thought about things like
Cooking
And showing people things for like recipe blogs instead of having to stop what you're doing take a picture and then
I don't know
Oh I thought that was kind of interesting although again
A very niche
So
I'm excited I was speaking yesterday and it bent and they're like 250 people in the audience that I said hey
Is anyone going to get the Amazon look
Like literally
Interesting interesting
But it was
In fairness this was
Maybe not
Its fashion
And I also my talk
Privacy so I asked
Yeah well now that's a fine. The target audience site I would agree
So this is 199
Amazon
Have to beg to buy it
Sarah now
You know you may not have people may beg to buy it
If you like up too soon too soon
And personal assistant news Samsung
Is bringing Bixby voice features to South
Korea
Latam country
Maybe it's it's getting ready
We make it two voices
I hope so
Galaxy S8 and S8 plus got updates in South Korea
To enable
The voice command feature which
Kind of weird selling all these phones I have one and you can't use it by voice even though that's one of the big features
Wasn't ready for lunch
And
I don't even know how well it works because they really haven't demonstrated it that much so
They did say the us we should have it
This spring
Which means I got about 7 weeks or so
I would say maybe 6 so
That's a good question I don't know
I would ask my phone but I can't do that by voice
Yeah so we'll see what happens again
I think I mentioned it prior to on a show when I did get this phone is got the dedicated Hardware button
For Bixby
I'm sure was you Google Now like cards there hit-or-miss for me
And it also has Bixby Vision that is enabled right now where you take a picture of something and it's just like the Amazon Fire Phone
Where you at
Scanner
Picture take a picture of something and it would magically
Determine what it was and then say Hey you can buy that here on Amazon for X dollars so
Also has an Amazon hookup in Bixby for that so
It's pretty limited right now so I'm dying to try the voice thingy
I'm not going to go to South Korea to do that
Sponsored
The other news from the personals
Is Google home and assistant
Is getting more divisive
Leviton
Amber light
Artik cloud
Smart home devices
IHome
Which I haven't
I haven't seen
No me neither
What is veal
Crazy but I will say it Cloud the Samsung stuff
Actually
Connector
For all kinds of
Depending on how this works and I'll have to go play with it
You might be able to connect it to all kinds of other things that
It's like another mediating layer so you
You could be like two hops away from a device that you really want to come
Yeah I think I don't know because I don't have any Samsung Smart Home things in my house
I think it's kind of limited right now in this particular implementation to Legrand smart hubs
The Simpson arcade
Okay I see you're at Sola Grand who
Makes
Really nice light switches
And I think these really cool
Plugs
They've actually been working I talked to them before about their smart home efforts
They're big on
Thread
So that makes sense because
Cuz
And
Honestly
Most chip vendors that I talk to and most people that I talked to her like thread is a dead standard
This may be like a
Come on thread
Effort
Trying to build up momentum
Because
It sounds like it needs
I would agree with that
So how right
Will test that out
All right
One more
Kind of news bit
Totally unrelated
Personal assistants
Now you are very lazy we love our assistance
Last week cloudflare
Security cam
I know for over baggage on covering like servers and all this other fun
Kind of it
Take it cloud computing efforts
Uber happened is cloudflare launched a
Iot security products
Orbitz
And so I had to talk to them about it because I'm always in search of new ways of thinking about IO
LT security
And the cool thing about orbit
Cloudflare is it
It's designed in such a way that it
Prevent something like
The Mirai botnet
Everybody listen up
Your devices that are unsecured today
Have a potential
I'll say a potential for being secured using this so what it is cloudflare basically Acts
The way they've always worked is
You point your
Your computing
To them
And then
It's basically like a filter that's like
You don't want to go here
You know where you don't want to download this packet because it's from an owner
Right
So what it does is it
Taxes that filter for iot devices
And
Right now a manufacturer has to
Put this in
And so it's not going to be everywhere it takes efforts and
It's not like if you were like a sea so at a hospital and you're like oh my God I want it I want to scare all my medical device
You can't right now using that unless the manufacturers elect
There's going to be
Hopefully
More adoption they're already protecting about
Is that about 20
5 customers and they're protecting about 120 million devices now
Basically
What happens is anything
This coming from a malicious place or trying to get your device to download malicious
Content
That's going to be
That's the
So the right and IRT gatekeeper of sorts from a security standpoint
Yes
And
I was really just a
Appointed that
You know you had to put this on your end device
Manufacturer eventually up there hoping to have
And SDK
And some other tools
And they haven't solved like
Like we just don't know how to solve
The problem is you're not a manufacturer secure
Thanks for working
We hope to
But they're they're just not there
So
That's what it is
For those of you guys who saw this announcement it was like hey what's new with iot security
It is new it's
It's actually very
Compelling
But it's pretty limited so far and we're hoping it's going to
Bigger better again I should also stress
This does not
Cluj you needing to actually secure
Your devices
Physical level
Other security steps that you need to take but this is just for
You know this can help make your over there updates more secure
New things are talkin out
The internet
And downloading things if this helps there
But that's about
That is cloudflare
Let's get into
Real quick bit of news
We got an update a story that we've reported on it
Weeks back
I actually
Purpose tour
What disease is
Zara which is a company that makes software that connects and integrates not the devices they were behind the Staples connect hub
They worked with ADT
On their pulse product
An ATT was actually an investor in the
What happened is an acquisition went South so not needed to sell
It didn't
Sol ring
Basically came in and hired everybody that worked at Saint off
Or they offered them all jobs most of them went over
And one day they work
One day they worked at Sonic
The next day
They worked
So this was a weird deal
In the theory is that ring is going to use the sauna team to build and integrate their products into more places which has
Hasn't been a huge priority
So this suit
Tiles in Delaware last Friday it's a 10-count suit
It's accusing them of all kinds of terrible
Lake Perris the CEO
It's saying that he downloaded a bunch of
Miles before going over to ring that rightfully belong to ATT
So this is a 9 piece suit
They're calling
The damages
Real and imminent
And they cannot be calculated
IT services
High drama
Hainan
And they're asking the court to find that ring and hair is breached
Orated breaches of fiduciary duty
Tortiously interfere
The contract
Unjustly enriched themselves in
Converted adt's assets to their own purposes
This is
It's always tough when you work for a
Technology company and then you go somewhere else
You can't forget our unknow something that you know
I know it's always a challenge with IP
I don't know if ring
New how much is on off
I done in conjunction with ADT in the past I'm sure they did but
Balagan how deep a level
This stuff gets messy
It does and I will say it
Majorly Messi
Because
Was a big investor in saint of
But they stopped caring after being acquired by private-equity firm about
Other kind of home automation
In this field there's been a lot of legal wrangling
Write like in the last year or two so there's I control that was purchased by
Comcast and alarm.com
There was actually a suit with eye control
I believe it was Honeywell
So what's happening is a lot of these security firms are like
How to keep r i p
For while we didn't know what was he
Happening with the Zone off IP
This is not really a sip
Price
In-N-Out also keep in mind that when you file a lawsuit you got to paint every what this is your your complaint is your chance to pay everyone
The biggest jerk in the face
Murder puppy
Paste a poison schoolchildren I need that's the level of drama
So take it all with a grain of salt
Singer follow this case though assuming a ghost kitchen use on
I assume
We'll see what happens
Exciting news in the lawsuit
World Air
And let's follow up with
He was last week we talked about a company called
Hubble
Idevices
Skip and Kevin and I were like
Who
What
Why
Yeah
What
But
Thank you Robert
I don't know if it's hafer Hafer
One of our loyal listeners who is sent me
Minion email not in a negative way but Justin
The K by the way
This happened
He sent me a wonderful email
About
Harvey Hubbell II
Who is the founder of
Hubbell Inc
This is a man
Who way back
Like
Guys 1890s
I like over a hundred years ago
He holds patents for the pull chain light bulb socket
The toggle light switch the two prong plug
And the duplex Outlet
That's really cool
So I was I was excited to know this so now it makes all
Heinz
A sense that this company being
In this deep
Building space
Would buy a company that is
Taking advantage of all these things and making it
Even smarter
Anybody's ever on Jeopardy for the airt prehistory
Category
Now you know the answer
Harvey Hubbell II
Alright so
What's today's date
I feel like this is a good place to end
Cuz I always like learning a random
And we are going to
Learn more random facts with our guest Beyond block of Ikea Home Smart
Bralorne about meatballs
Lights and some of Ikea's future plans
Right after
This message from our sponsor
Hey everybody this is Stacey Higginbotham and I am breaking into the Internet of Things podcast or a message from Mars
Sponsor
This week sponsor is if
And today I have with me Ann mercogliano who is ifs VP of marketing
She's going to talk about a new way for partners to think about integrating on
Hello Ann
Hi Stacy
Yes
Typically the old adage
Has been that anybody with an API
Rihanna
But we decided to make it even a bit easier and think about
If you have an RSS feed we're happy to have you integrating how to be a service on it
What are the interesting use cases of why we decided about this still see many people are still in the kickstarter fundraising stage
They're saying API we say come on to EFT and really think about the idea of
Keeping in touch and growing your user base by putting in updates
Your social media
Everything about a Blog
Being able to grow that user base
Even using it as a form of feedback in R&D for what you're developing so when you're ready
You can already have a robust user base
Sit on it and start using your service right away
So what do you think the most popular way that people are going to
Use this new feature at these new news feeds
One thing we seen from the user side is that a lot of people like to use our news feed services
Just be able to kind of author information overload so the idea of saving for later so it's not just about getting an email or have
You know every piece of information go to your inbox you can say things to things like pocket
Evernote
Dropbox Google Docs whatever is your choice
Essentially want to be able to catch up on information
Digesting you're only getting what you're interested in being able to use some of those filters is another really compelling way
Everything people use us
Also just alerting a group we use as a test around the office is all the time we love to have in our own slack channels
What's going on with different news is there interesting breaking stories
It's a great way to kind of keep everyone informed what's going on throughout the day
All right and
Everyone this was so easy I actually made one of these with if
So you can actually enable The Internet of Things podcast RSS feed service
And you can
Tweet for example when there's an episode or your Hue Lights might blink when there is an episode
Have fun play with that in an
What other cool Outlets are there
Share well with your service I think
Some great things would be alerted when you have a cyst
Coming on your show
So you never miss an episode on what's important
Do you know other great things that we thought about is
Saving episodes of Pocket
Posting it to your slack Channel being able to
Bring us to work or share with colleagues
Just a touch of getting notification when a new iot podcast has
Stopped so
Being a partner is really easy
And how can we find out more
Taylor Moore better partner platform about integrating with your API or your RSS
You can visit if. Com backslash iot
Which is
Ifttt.com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Bjorn block
Who is the global business leader for Ikea
HomeSmart
Hi. How are you today
Hi Stacy I'm good how are you
I am super
Awesome
And I am so excited to talk to you because
You will not know this
But many of my readers have sent me in surveys I sent out to them they're like can you get the Ikea head of the head of it is
Smartphone efforts on the show
I like
Baby
So yay
Everyone
Great likewise I think we are equally I am equally excited to be on the show so thanks for having us
Yes
We're going to talk about all kinds of things today you guys are going to talk about
I'm going to screw up the pronunciation
Traffic
He's pretty close to him saying is that correct pronunciation but I think yeah I think I got it
All right we're going to talk about the try to feel lights
We're going to talk about Ikea's be with a smart home
And
We're going to talk about
Combining Smart Home Technology and Furniture and Things
Probably going to live a lot longer than the technology itself
So
Let's get started with
Ikea
And it's view of the smart
What is it
How long have you guys been thinking
Good journey Nike Elite we started the Journey about 4 years ago
We got the question come from
If there was an opportunity of
Integrating technology and digital Solutions in tar
Home Furniture range of course we
Answer yes or no
Tell me where I stood
Leave that project
Project inside Ikea Bay schedule
Startup
Asking to become and get business in Ikea
Nothing Jordan really stalking me
Doing
What we always do
Meaning of we are curious about
License
Better everyday life
So the tallest self is not something different to to IKEA
It's just the difference
So we have different to what you know two bucks
Digital Solutions
Can you Technologies the weekend used to dissolve the
Okay so I should not think Ikea
Flat-pack furniture company I should think Ikea solving
Life dilemmas at home
Exactly
Okay
So you guys actually about two years ago released a smart kitchen video that was very forward-looking
And you guys also have the wireless charging
Embedded in furniture
So are those kind of projects that came out of this small group
Y'all created 4 years ago
Yep the wireless charging it collection of Lowenstein in the April 2015
Actually the first
Collection of the first branch of products that came out from
Initiative
Now that's starting point plus
Around the charging in in life at home
What are the landmarks that you have
And a lot of people came back.
Said that it charging my
Mobile devices or tablets
You know you can't find your charger the cord is too short to waste the charger or someone has stolen It. Whatever might be
And that's what we got yours about the
The wireless charging technology
So we didn't at all
Invented
Stupid gesture
Captain to the existing technology
The chief technology
Incorporated into our bedside tables or desk lamps
Made it part of Home Furnishings
Stand-alone
But we can help a lot of people to
Easily charged at home in a nice and good looking man
Definitely starting point for HomeSmart
The kitchen concept was still strong.
Different poster constellation within Ikea
Public golf course
It was more of an experimental and more of it
Concept
That we showcase thing that email on that 2 years ago
We got some great lunch from
That project and I think yet
Aloha Del Sol
Inside the concert that we tested there
Generate a lot of pictures
Will we see some smart Kitchen products come out to
The good thing with with HomeSmart inside Ikea Easter we have no boundaries
Which rooms are areas of the home that we can go to or we can talk to you in so
Right now we are collaborating
With every part of the of the home inside a Kia Soul
Only businesses that you see the news
Go through the store the living room
We are basically working with all of them so good
Kitchen stuff coming out soon
All right
I cannot wait
So let's go back to the tradfri lights
Which recently launched
Why did you guys choose
Lighting
First of all we know live
We know the importance of life
For the life at home
We know that a lot of
People want to change
The atmospheric layer depending on that
Activities at home
Because basically you want to do
Homework around AA
Dining table if you want to have that cozy Friday night dinner on that same dining table
You should have completed except
Lighting setup in order to be
Yeah prepare for that setting
And we know that that's a huge potential in you proving life at home
Using lighting
We took a bold statement a few years ago
Going all-in LED
Autumn 2016
Meaning that we had the precondition to explore the full potential of digital lighting
So
Eagles
I shouldn't say easy but at least
Daily blast from the past or golden from
LED torch
Smart LED
Need for it
So we understood that people really want
Feel safe at home and a great atmosphere using lighting
So that was a
Starting point for us
And what are some things you learned in building
That Prada
And maybe even building the wireless charger
Call Lee learned a lot of things
Project versus initiative
One of the greatest
Importance of
Simplicity
You take the connected home massage
I think it's been nuts
Possible
Quite a few years
Stop looking at smart lighting work or whatever type of connected home that were looking at
Testing a lot of frustration on
How complicated is today to set up
And also in terms of how
Insidious 2
Guiding principles
How to make it super simple
People to get curious about the connected home or connected devices
Alarm contacts
And also how can we make it really for
So I think the
The greatest learning here was to
Finding the starting point so we can start with a fully connected home
We believe that people buy a smart products
Then add another smart product and
Suddenly God created your own
Rancho Park in the home and you get
More exploratorium edu connecting them together
Suddenly you're evolving towards a connected home
But you don't start by buying it for me
Connected
I think you're right that seems to be the journey
Hopefully soon to be less fraught
Frustration
Now
In looking at
The lighting
Kevin and I were talking about it a few weeks ago
I was like
Very concerned about security cuz I'm like yeah I hope you did this rate I hope you did this well because there's so much bad
Iot security
And it turns out you guys did
But in part one of the ways that you did it appears to be
Keeping it a closed ecosystem for now
I'm just kind of curious about
How you guys approach security
And the idea of the
Yeah I should start up
So thankful for having you
I think it's a we took today
Security aspects of Courts
Very seriously and we enter that dilemma with with great respect
And I'm the team put a lot of effort into
Finding the best
Apartments all dogs how to take the color out to make it to a
Secure systems
User-friendly
So I think
Really good job and yeah reading the reviews
Forever grateful that the music turned out well.
To the extent that we thought so real happy for that
Also saying that
Our intention is not to be closed
We we think that's the one of the major success factors in the connected home Easter.
I have good friends
K24
Seamless user experience in the home so
I think the more we can work together with with partners and and other players that use you're in a better way
It's on our journey for short tube
To make sure that we eat the open up in that direction
Okay any time frame or mechanism for this like an API
I compliment to give you a time friends but just to say that we are
Very good sir.
A good partner to collaborate with in the NHL standings in the states
Got meatballs
Okay
So
The other thing that Kevin and I talked about actually
After I was like please don't screw security up
Was
That you guys really have the opportunity in your stores to showcase
A smart home in a very compelling way that I think
Is lost
Actually
I shouldn't say lost a lot of retailers been trying
And figure out how to show off
The Smart Home
To their customers to get them
Interested in also just to educate
So how are you guys thinking about building that experience into
Your stores
Well I think it's
Fantastic opportunity man we have
More than 900 million visiting customers every year trust or Sunday
It's a great opportunity of course to have access
And of course we we will try to build there
Living room sets where you can experience the smart home and that we know that touch-and-feel is
OSHA when it comes to
The last message we just released for example
It's almost in that feeling when you switch that little nugget and I'm using the lights go
So we will try to build it
Intuitive any drafted station as possible in the store environment
It does take you quite a bit to
Walk you through the phone store so
It needs to be there if you want to play with it will give us some play areas and that we will also make them
Easy to grasp and use it to buy if you just have to grab them by in
Before coming to the store
But it's a great opportunity and we have to
Barely started yet
I agree
How to customers in the store in maybe online in general
How are they reacting to these
Kind of smart products
Do they see them in the store and buy them do they do their research ahead of time
What are demographics look like
So far we have seen that a lot of people to the
Homework online
Prior to the storm
The majority of customers
The know about the Detroit Red Wings before they
Sheet in the store
Bubbles Salon
Not exclude the ones who are
Maybe looking for
Just a lightbulb going to come to the store
And after
Sympathy 27 LED
Maybe they progressing there and
Knowledge level and the Curious stand there and see how they
Might get interested in
It's most likely just
Wendell buying a lightbulb so I think there's a little bit of a difference
Customer Journeys if you are
Curious about the
The Smart Homes from the starting point
Say goodbye
She's at people can man
Engaged
Coming from Los Angeles
And as you open up the platform
Are we going to see other devices Maybe
In your retail experience with your partners and that sort of thing
Will you go deaf
More products coming out from Ikea smart lighting is nothing in destination for us I would say that
First of all
Smart lighting Products.
Is in the store today
Is only the starting point we will of course expand base range
Get more rich
In this range
But that we will tap into the same TracFone
If you're asking if we will see
Third-party product or products from other vendors inside Ikea.
Highly unlikely we are quite strict about only selling Ikea parts stores today
That is true
That's why I was like
Dad in the meatballs in
And Lincoln buried
Delicious
Chocolate could be good for you to know that we are selling 2.9 Million
Okay
That is a lot of meat
As you guys
Build connectivity in the more products
And even with the tables that have Qi wireless charging
How do you think about
Putting technology which may have like
Three to five-year lifespan
Into
Your furniture witch
I assume has a longer life
It's a good answer that you bring up on me let me develop
Ikea Warehouse
Formula call Democratic design
Wait 5S
The Equalizer
Function
Quality
DeAngelo price
Those on the side
Always
Judging evaluation we developed
And of course I thought I can be recycled and and also what the chair just made up
The one aspect of course also
Table top cradle
Clicking no kick-out
So that's how we see the wireless charging
Solution
All the solutions that we are put out that mean you can basically mean it's almost a replaceable part that you can upgrade overtime
So you can keep the piece of furniture in MD
Work with the electronics SM
Usher more than module
When it comes to the
Connected products
We see a great opportunity
Using the Ikea Gateway because that's how we can
How you can download the latest
Firmware with the latest software from Mac Thomas
So hopefully making sure that the products are always up-to-date with the latest technology in the latest
Play the song
So why we hope that the lifetime of the product is going to be
Appropriate weight needs to be in order to being a sustainable product overtime
Along with sustainability
How are you guys thinking about
Reducing waste because I know that is a big function for you guys
When
You got these electronic components that often times have heavy metals and can't be
Tossed easy or shouldn't be too hot too easily
Are you guys thinking about programs to take that back or
How are you going to communicate that with
Your customers
Yes it is something we are
Lily Garden
Boats in every aspect of the value chain
Less every year
Recycling fossil have programs in place so we can
Recycled products or we use the products that at the end of life for when you are at the end of their life
You have a big program out
Alarm circularity we're looking into aspects of how we can take back
Mattresses
Whatever you can be
Okay yes cuz
I'm sitting there thinking about like my smart light bulbs that I've already had some of the LEDs that should last
3 years
Eminem like
I throw this out
Now I have to stem light bulb what do I do with it
This is
A first world problem
But I think it's also interesting
Opportunity for thinking about the LED light bulbs that you take YouTube
For 25 years
Ikea
If you open 2 years ago
20 years left on them it's a great
By and it's a great little
Secondhand opportunity
All right
Guys
I'm going to start Stacy II headlight bulb store
Just after this
All right
So you talked a little bit about extending the range of your light bulbs line
Does that mean
Colored light bulbs or different
Formfactor so not maybe the traditionally nineteen's or what what can I be
What should I expect
Planning my smart home
Around Ikea
Yeah so first of all you want to make sure that we have every socket size 2
Survival apps
Chick 63147
Exploring
What type of color temperatures are we we should have for a home furnishing a state
Today we are
Having a ball
Three levels of
Whitestone going from the lights to the neutral White
We are extorting you
If that is sufficient
Just play around with these three tones
In home furnishing context it makes a huge difference
We'll see how we go there
Right now I feel like there are a lot of really cool Technologies
That are being
Incorporate into the things like Fabrics or
Haptic research there's a lot of
Is a lot of cool stuff going on and I just be curious what kind of Technologies are you guys looking at in thinking
Wow this is exciting
Well I think
The luxury of working
Inaki I used to have our own
Material Development Department department for new technologies and so on
So we have access
I agree with you
Fabrics and textiles and
Smart textiles
So what we definitely take to explain that area
One thing we are very hard on him
Seville custom
So
Chico State
Technologies
Want to play around with
So we are
The Reel made for it before we launch
And also we compare
A solution with an analogue Solutions
So it makes sense that whatever we put out there
Eco bedding
Cool technology digital solution
That it is
Superior
Look Solutions out there so we are exploring
For sure
Sensors and how we can get the how we can get some Architects dolls
Evaluate this woman two and three times before we actually
That's probably why
There's a lot of things out there that I'm like
Way to calm down and hold off on that
Protest it
I will have to stop by my nearest Ikea
And
Consume some meatballs and also
Check out
Your future smart home stuff
Thanks.
Okay well
Left abruptly with Bjorn over at Ikea I hippie stop recording button before we set our final goodbyes
Thank you so much for coming on the show I had a lot of fun and for you guys for listening thank you
You so much for listening and if you want more iot news please subscribe to my newsletter at Stacey on iot
. com as always I'll see you next week