Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
We have a lot of news for you
Arms new architecture
Machine learning at the edge
Amazon making its own chips
Google hiring a Samsung exec
Plus
Wechat new wearable news
Smart glasses
And a homepod review
Kevin
All this Plus
We have our guest alexandros Marino's
Who is going to be talking about the
Best
And fastest growing iot Hardware platforms for both
Consumer prototyping
Consumer products at scale
The industrial internet
But first
Let's hear a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Ring
Ring the connected doorbell and security camera maker Rings mission is to make neighborhood safer today
They over a million people use the ring video doorbell to help protect their hopes ring nose at home security
Who's at the front door but it doesn't end there so now they're extending the same level of security to the rest of your home with the ring floodlight cam
The floodlight cam is a motion-activated camera and floodlight that connects right to your phone
With HD video 2-way audio and more so you can see and speak to visitors and even set off an alarm
Rate from here I have tried the ring doorbell but I have not tried the ring floodlight cam
And I will say that I really enjoyed my ring doorbell it did its job super well with ring
You're always home so for listeners of our show save up to $150 on a ring
Ring security kit when you go to ring.com Stacey Stacey
So go to ring.com / Stacy
As you can get $150 off your ring security
Okay Kevin
We are back
With what are we going to
Machine learning at the edge we have to start with chips cuz that's your thing
I love that
Meet you
Potato chips
Keauhou
Yeah
Corn chips
Okay I'm sorry
I'm sorry
I am a little hungry but we're actually talk
Talking about
Doctors because
Who doesn't love a good semiconductor story
Basically what's happening is this week arm said that it is going to build a new architecture
For machine learning at the
The edge
In
This is
You don't just like mess up your architecture
For no apparent
But what they've decided is they need massive parallel processing
At the edge
At a very low power
They're doing this in a couple different ways
They're going to launch two different
Flavors of this when is an object detection flavor which is
For computer vision specifically
And then the other is just generic machine
The Edge and
Ho Kevin
Let's talk about why machine learning at the edge isn't
Well let me kick that all sin with a question to you
In terms of
Edge devices
What do you think these will find their way into
Cameras
I think also maybe some smart speakers
You probably will also see them
What cameras and smart speakers for the first initial
Wave of them
And I'll say that because cameras need to
If you can do object detection at the edge
And the other thing is we should say
There's two flavors of machinery
There's the training portion where you
Train the computer how to
Nice something in that takes
Typically is dead in the car
Because it takes massive computing
King Power massive parallel processing you should
Peter thousand
Thousands of images in there like
Learn how to recognize a dog versus a
And then there's the execution the inference
And that basically
Once you've trained a computer you've built a model and then that model gets executed at the end
So it's important to know that what are missing is they will actually be able to do both execution and some info
Prince at the edge
It is because you mentioned that you know the cloud
Approached I noticed in arms documentation
They have discussed neural network Frameworks and they
They say there no network software Translate
Google tensorflow for example
Which is
The big machine learning
Backbone of Google nearest tensorflow everywhere you wouldn't see it or hear call tensorflow
But a product delivers is coming to a lot of devices so I'm wondering and I know we don't discuss these on on the show
Show that much I'm wondering how many phone makers will integrate this and we see it first there
As it
Comes out to Iowa
T-Type devices the only reason I say that is because I know that
I said Huawei with their Kirin processors have
Some
Aai chip
In the now as well as
Who else is working on that
I want to say Samsung but not have any products right now
So I'm just wondering if
Bissell filter out through phones first and then float further to the edge
I imagine they will I also would say that we will see these for sure in 6
And possibly drones actually drones has a really interesting use
Case for something like
So I should correct something though because they have the two
Machine learning and then they have the object detection processors
The object detection processor will only do
Inference so basically that's not going to be training
You can't train enough
Section at the
Right so that's going to be providing the information
Royal
Rap
That's okay though
Weather saying this can do is they're going to have
You can show
People the direction they're facing
Hindu gesture and pose
And this is all based the object detection is based on their acquisition of apical
Colwich
I had
Talk 2 years ago was like super excited about him so pumped when are
I'm glad to see that acquisition finally met
And I don't know what else to tell you guys about this other than
They're not alone there's a lot of
In a moment this is called project Trillium so if you see
References to that
You guys we should see the object detection processor
We're not going to expect any silicon-based on this
Until mid-to-late 2019
At the earliest
So that means it's not actually good
B&N products
Until like
So this is far-reaching
Right because arm doesn't make chips they just create the
The architecture of that
Jamaica reviews
Call Apple
Immediate acne
Aura Plano license and they will
This might not sound like it's related but I'm going to it is something to mention it
Apparently the hive
Camera uses a first generation
OD chip from based on arm
This is the second OD
Generation chip from arm or architecture
From our mission say
Alan just wondering I'm not familiar with the hive
Camera
Send wondering what kind of object detection that has Hive is from British gas it's there
It's sold in the UK and that's because this isn't actually from our mats from Apple
Which is the company that
Icing
Yes it does have object detection
It is
I think it's
Facial
I think it's facial
Ignition
But I don't know beyond much beyond that
Curious hi-vis actual
Planning
They're trying to build their US
It's a subscription-based service.
That was so it's you get the hardware and you
Pay the money
It's lovely
Little bit about that okay
Let's move on to
Amazon
So
But Amazon is actually so the big news this week was
Last December when Amazon acquired
Blink which was the wireless the battery
Empowered
Camera
And they also make a doorbell
So when Amazon acquired blank it was a deal valued at about 90 million dollars which
Pets
The interesting thing is and I said this last December is that blink is not just a camera maker
It actually made a
Add imagery
Ignition chip
Ecology a video it's actually a video processing
Chip and
It did it at super low power
Empathize
Buy the chip company
Me and we're selling these chips for like five bucks to like DVD Maker
And this is
No prop
Just terrible business for
So they were like what else could we use this more and they decided to build a video game
I want to make use of their technology
And that's how blank was for
So Amazon when they bought link they got that shipped
In addition to that
The information is reporting that Amazon is developing a chip design for artificial intelligence
Twerk on the echo
Other Hardware
Powered by Madame
So is story if any information is talking about Amazon's acquisition of a
Company a couple years ago called Annapurna
Annapurna was doing networking chips and they were dealing primarily with a software layer of
Networking
So creating basically they call it a fabric
Fabrics are used to manage
Moving information around the chip is probably the
Best way to describe it
You think that's fair
Lancaster
Okay so Annapurna is a fabric
And when you're talk about machine learning
This is super important because
When I talk about machine learning it keeps saying the word massively parallel processes
And that's exactly how these jobs are divided up so you
You send
One job to One Core another job to another core in
So on and so on but you need a fabric to manage all
Until annapurna's good at that
And then we got it
The blink
Video processing so that makes sense
And then Amazon has its own chip design
Singer sew
I think we're going to see is some
Intelligence at the edge
Happening
And it sounds like it's going to happen both from
Companies that are traditional ship providers but also if you're going to be building consumer Hardware you're going to need to do it yourself
And I'm wondering a couple things about this
Totally see where this is going on agree with you
The first thing I thought I could ever was talking about Otis
Speed this is going to bring to Matt amazed responses is going to be amazing
Everybody kept focusing on that and like
Oh yeah but also I think there may be something here when you push a lot of that intelligence away from the cloud down
The edge
You improved
Perception of privacy
And that's something that right now all of these smart speakers
SAR fighting
You know nobody wants these always on microphone send me all the information on the cloud
If you can do all of it with ML at the edge
And not rely on the cloud
That really helps with that area I think
It does the question then becomes what data does get
Pushed off bridge
Cuz you do need
And eventually when you can actually do
Training at the edge then you actually
Get the opportunity
Personalized Services until then
Depersonalization.
Right right
And the other thing that jumped out at me on this is a definite Trend you're obviously I didn't know about the on Trillium when this
Amazon news came out
But it relates back to that everybody seems to be making
Chips for the edge for their own products
Such as apple is using its A8 processor from the iPhone 6 or 7 I forget which
In the homepod freezing
Now you'll see Amazon devices eventually have this
Google has been
Talk about with
Creating their own
Soces and such
Need the visual
That's right they did they did which is
At the TV is exact
Exactly so it's definitely a trend and I'm wondering in Amazon
Case particular
Will this be limited to Amazon Hardware only and I'm going to guess
Yes
And the reason I'm saying yes
As a guess is because they let you freely use
Maddie Mae's voice services but there are very specific features and functions that are not on
Non Amazon devices with matinees voice services
I'm just under the wondering if Amazon keeps that chip
Feature set
In the house
Well it but then again they also cut off potential Hardware partner such as you know the Sonos example has Madame a in it
I can't do everything that an echo can do but I do
90% of it
What date
Want to
Check all these Hardware manufacturers off
So
That's a good thing to think about Kevin
All right I will I will think about it
Meanwhile
We will move on to Google
Hiring a Samsung executive
To focus on iot
Specifically
In the cloud
And not just any executive either this is the guy his name is in John R E
He used to be the EVP and head of Samsung pay
This goes back about two-and-a-half years ago and he was instrumental with Bixby
So
And it's interesting because I
What did I read I read something this week oh I don't know it was
There's an interview with Google Rick osterloh
There's a really good interview about getting Google AI into all of Google's product
The one question I didn't see asked or maybe was asking was an answer his
What is a think of Madame a in Bixby and other
Named you no assistance I want to name them all because I don't set a resources up
I'd be very curious to see what Google thinks but now that got somebody who's coming from the Bixby fold
Indeed
So
I think this is a good
Story Samsung actually has built
A really good
Cloud business believe it or not
There used to be Arctic now it's SmartThings cloud
Their focus on connecting everything
Is a neutral third party
It is really easy to use even I have actually use
I'm kind of stunned by that but it's a good implementation and I know I talk to people who are
Using them
So
To the extent of this guy worked on
The Knox security system
Spigen Samsung
How much time he spent on their Cloud stuff
But
If you can bring that Samsung really is trying to be this neutral
Play right so if you can bring some of that okay coming from inside
Google and I know I can talk about this plus my own just
Research into this
Samsung is very very good at
Acting neutral
But
In the real world at the end of the day same songs in it for Samsung and I say that because
They often recreate things that
Android already has
Maybe doesn't do well
A lot of what's in Android actually did
Come from Samsung split screen multitasking on a phone
Samsung did it first with their Galaxy Note 2
Eventually
Android just accepted it
Samsung's Knox which is there security system for Android devices
In the Enterprise
That was competing head-to-head with
Google
Android Enterprise stop
Sure enough after about 2 or 3 years of competing
Google said you know we're going to be working agreement out
An integrated Knox
Features into
Android not to still separate but
Google
Subsumes a lot of what Samsung does and obviously Samsung
Compensated for that
And I'm wondering in this case
I'm wondering if either part of their Cloud business if they got some expertise that Google doesn't have
Or with their digital assistant
If there are some things Bixby does more efficiently or or does that Google Assistant doesn't do
You watch give it a year or so and it'll get subsumed into Google
Okay well that's
That doesn't
Sound terrible
Oh no not at all not at all
No knocks when I say this I don't mean don't expect Bixby replace Google Assistant
Probably still live on its own on Samsung devices
Or unless
And best case I think for users
Bixby and Google Assistant just become the best
Read in one product
And that product would be Google Assistant course and it would go on all Samsung phones and
Bixby would essentially disappear inside of Google Assistant
I need weather
I have three in my room right now so yes I agree
Netflix PS3 controller systems
You could have four
Galaxy S8 yes but I'm not going to do that right now
Okay
Moving on from
Google Samsung the Mysteries they weave
Let's talk about a new radio in Wareham
Yeah this surprise me I don't really know too much I just got a press release before the show from Altair semiconductor
And they announced their collaboration with Ericsson and Sony mobile
What they're going to do it
Mobile World Congress is demonstrate
A new wearable device
Well it's a wristband for diabetic patients that connects to a continuous glucose monitoring device
The interesting part is we seen these kinds of things before they're using Altair's lte-m chips
Set for cellular connectivity
Without so you can
Center data back
Cheetah monitoring system
Without having your phone
It's always interesting because when we talk about
You know Cat 1 ml tem Etc
We talked about a lot of devices at the edge that
Run for long time on a battery so that's why
You know they use low-power radios and so on
Not wearable devices so this is kind of interesting to me
I agree and you fight
I mean you got your Apple watch with its own
Sim and
Is 4 G
It's not yet said at least 10 with an LTE connection
It makes sense to have this direct line out
You got to send that data
To the cloud to be monitored
And I assume
Especially for like
Elderly or children
You actually don't want to just collect in store for a while cuz if something's wrong you need to be able to
Writes the funny thing is he just only cuz you brought the Apple watch
Apps and really not been built to take advantage of the LTE Connection by that I mean I leave my phone at home and I'll go
Go out for a few hours at a time
Sure I get messages I get phone calls I can chat with you Stacy him
Cetera
When I go run for example all that data is captured with GPS heart rate and so on
I have to actually go back home and
Think it over through to my phone
I can't do that remotely
You can't go to it may make sense for now from ABBA
Perspective
Not a lot of data
People use anything set for phone calls use it for a phone call I can tell you
You lose 1% per minute on a phone call that's why
If you are not spending our on the phone you're going to lose 60% of your
Apple watch battery life
And I mean that is another example though
You're still get it's not much data but every little bit counts I mean if I start thinking
At the data that just goes back
IPhone to the cloud
Right as rain
True beauty but even so you could optimize like in a health situation cuz it's modern my my heart rate
It doesn't need to send all that heart rate data back to the cloud or anywhere until I get home anyway
Unless maybe there's a some smarts in there says hey
This guy might be having a heart attack or something right now
That day and you ain't get sent on the always-on connection
You don't have to send all the day
That's true and that's where we're
See some really cool stuff
The hierarchy
Activation
Is what they call it and it's basically you have a chip
It senses something
And that it's it takes the next action so
You have something that says oh this is a trigger I recognize that that is a trigger
And it's important and I'm going to wake up something else so I can wake up the
Modem and say
Home
I got to bring back the machine learning in the chips back into this
Okay
I know you're disappointed with
Apps
Let's talk about
Something fun that we missed last week
List two things last
We missed Intel smart glasses which were about to talk about
Into
We miss celebrating our hundred
50th Park
That's right we did
So let's talk about those glasses
Yeah and I was very interested in this only because I
Purchase. I was reimbursed for it through work
Google Glass back in 2014
Still have them don't use them obviously not a successful product at least in the way that
Google might have holes
It has been used in
Certain verticals in Enterprise right now but
Other than that
Nope can't buy everything
Intel smart glasses are similar but different and are different enough
To have a lot more potential in my opinion
Because they do less
What I mean by that is
They
Willie r a
A notification
Open system for the most part
They're also don't look like
Anything from futuristic they look like regular glasses frames
Are all of the chips and battery and connectivity inside the side of the frames
You can't even see them there's no prism display actually sticking out from these things like Google Glass head instead there's a prism
Built into the glass
And IT projects
Using a low-power laser right on your retina
From the prism notifications
It does one thing and one thing
Very well and it doesn't look
Outrageous
So I'm looking forward to seeing what
Might be done with them this isn't something until it's going to sell that you're going to have a developer
Preview where people can try and write apps for it later this year
And
I'm countries have even come to Market because there was talk about until selling off its AR
Group elements I guess I will have to say
Do you know to me this I know people could be like Oar but I'm just like
Let's just talk about the
Power of a heads-up display for
Ito think about turn-by-turn directions
You know when you're walking around the city
Right now my phone will vibrate but I still don't know if I'm supposed to turn right or low
I just look at the Sun
How awesome would it be to be talking to someone in
Have some sort of indication of
Who this is
That's just me cuz I
Faces really well
Well you even also need a camera for that nice have no camera
Okay that is true
You know who people are based on their
Pair Bluetooth or Wi-Fi
We're not supposed to
Best part of that privacy of
Okay so no camera
I will be sad I will be sad
A little while ago speakers no mic
Oh so I can talk to
I don't believe so
This reminds me of the Amazon Echo cuz when it came out very early all it did was you
Yeah
I remember the search engine so it couldn't answer that many questions I couldn't control Smart
I'm devices it just basically played music and
Set timers for lights why I didn't buy one man
You didn't buy one but enough people did in the use case became gradually soap
Compelling
Look at us now
Oh yeah once once they made it smarter you know switch on the troll that's when I go bowling absolutely
And so I I like
Having some of my favorite devices just do something really well
I think there's a lot of power
So I'm Nina on
This
Especially someone who wears glass
All right
Let us move on to Z home pod
Because
Kevin
Neither of us really wanted to order it
But we decided we had to
Because you guys
Really have a lot of questions
Either it's funny and it just goes back to what I just said I didn't
Want to buy the Echo and first came out
For the same reason or reasons that I
Don't want it by VIN by the homepod when it came out
There's two things to talk about with alpine obviously there's the sound
And then there's the smarts
Unfortunately in my opinion the smarts actually went into the sound meaning
Sonically engineered
Apple did an excellent
Excellent job
It doesn't
Doesn't blow me away like it did the early reviewers and a lot of early reviewers
Got a I'm just going to say they got a dog and pony show from Apple
An apple showed off the speaker and compare it to certain other speakers but I have since found out the set up on those was not the same
I'm like one of those speakers with setup for Bluetooth
Instead of Wi-Fi I mean so
I get why Apple does that and appreciate that but
It just doesn't blow me away it is really really good for a single unit device
I don't want a single speaker because it has multiple speakers at 7 tweeters and and 1 woofer
And it does sound good
It's got the smarts the intelligence to auto-tune itself
When you first put it down it will sample sound in the room you don't even hear it
And it will consider yourself for the room that you're in which is great
It'll do that again every time you move it
Unfortunately
I don't see the benefit of that because you plug this thing and you're not going to move it that much so
That's neither here nor there
Okay
My daughter
Takes her Amazon Echo it's in her room
And she brings it into the bathroom for getting ready
And bats
So
She actually moves her Echo back
Because she doesn't have a tap
That's what I do I use the tap the tap I move around all the time
The point there is it psychic
Case where someone
No doubt no doubt I don't think the majority of
Imposter going to be moving
Is my point
But anyway
So
Just one more point about the sound before I talk about the smarts
I did a blind listening test with
Different music genres
I did the best I could to make it as equal as possible
Setting the sound levels to be the same now I did it with the homepod and I did it with a pair of Sonos ones
And one of my
Tech savvy friends came over listen and he's like
Using two speakers
I am
Musical ly
Because they're the same price and he's like when you can
Put that into the equation instead of course you can
I said you have $349 to buy a
Homepod
Then you need to compare to what else do you get free money
Temperature in $49 you can get to sauna
He couldn't really tell much of a difference nobody really could affect people who had a preference
Amazon
It was the best speaker but it was
The preferred sound for them
Was actually the pair of Sonos once more often than not
So I don't know that surprises people or
Whatever but Sonos is the pioneers of smart speak
They've been doing
Similar things to this for
4 years
Yeah they have and I'll say I'll give Apple Credit here
Insulate improve the experience in terms of setup it's very simple
In terms of
Using integration with apple music obviously it
That's all integrates with right now
That just works with Sonos it does that but it kind of
There's like Steps wooden steps to do that right
So they offer more but still more complicated if you just want to drop dead simple plug it in and start playing Apple music
From a smart standpoint I am shocked
And I said this in my written review
Siri is fragmented now
Siri does not work the same or does it have the same features
From an iOS device to the homepod
And that just boggles my mind there are things you can't do you can't set two timers you can't
Access your calendar create an event
It's just really strange
It just seems like it's Half Baked and the kind of goes along with some of the other features that aren't there that are coming in that is
Multi-room audio and
Blinking Twitty's for stereo
That's coming but
It's just odd to me but
Siri is very responsive as you'd expect
Besame
A trip inside
The
Microphones for listening
Apple Mail. You can
You don't have to yell even if the music is
Is crank way up
It's really good
But again
If you aren't in apple music if you're not
On iOS if you're not using homekit
This just isn't going to be able to buy the father
It does not appeal to me
What the funny thing is I actually do use iOS and I am an apple music subscriber family is
But I still wouldn't buy this right now
At this is again it's just like the Amazon Echo I wouldn't buy when it first came out
It wasn't compelling enough for the time
Alright well if you have homekit questions for Kevin
And gosh I bet you do
Call us at
Are iot podcast listener hotline at 5 1/2
6 to 3
And
Let us move
To answer a question from
Sinners
The iot podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage electronic locks
Schlage electronic locks off
Unparalleled convenience and simplicity
All on their own
Right out of the box
So you don't have to have a smart home
Benefit
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
All right
This week
We have a question
From
Intellicast
Some sexy hair
Selena Quintanilla
What question
Teenage suicide walk to the younger one
When I went to go and set up the calendar
Spotify music
Unlimited
Change it
And then music
At the moment I'm stuck with
Oh my God
Is there a way that I can change.
Music
Sitel
I'm playlist to calendars on Outlook
Okay Sam
This is a
Pain point near and dear to my heart
Heart
Because I have been trying to use my Spotify account on Amazon Echo
Without using only mine
I've been trying to let my daughter
Use hers cuz we have the
Premium Spotify
Has multiple accounts
By golly it doesn't work
So I hate to tell you this you're going to have to either lie
Or
Supper
Depending on their ages
So my daughter is under the age of 13 so the only thing she can be
In the Amazon Echo universe
Is
Part of my household
But she can't actually
Have her email affiliated with anything except for allowances
And her Kindle like
The free time Kindle Freetime stuff
So
I can't
Associate her email address with
The calendar or with
R Spotify
Because she's underage
After she's 13
Cuz of the Copa act the
Children's online
Protection privacy protection
Danny Amazon can take her email
I guess start
Mission Mater
Then she can use it
So in that case all you have to do is register those devices for each of your daughters
To their account
So you would have to have an Amazon account
You would register those devices and then you would link
All of your accounts is a
Family
Kind of complicated but to register the device you go into the
Anime app
You going to settings
And you're going to see all of the different Amazon Echo devices in your
Household
There
It's Going Down Under about it'll say the device is registered
Burgess Owens
If it's registered to you
Because which it probably is if you bought it just deregister it
When you do that
You're going to
Connected to
Your daughters are
And I did actually brings up a point that I
Probably should have mentioned in the homepod
That because
This is a lot like iCloud in Family Sharing iOS I wanted to mention that the homepod only supports one
User One Voice one iCloud account right now so multiple people in the home
Will not be recognized
Everybody's one user
And that's a problem for your personal information
Oh that is a problem
And you find the
Household like you find the area about who you're at a household with
Under the same settings menu
But instead of going to each and
Official twice she keep scrolling and scrolling until you get to
There's a section that says in a household
With these people
I believe you have to set up your household
From the Amazon account itself on the web
You can't do it for
Fitness app
So that is
That is how I've done it I don't see a way to do it otherwise
I may be wrong but it makes sense actually the
Tear
And I believe it has to be mutual
Excommunication but
About setting up
The benefit is you can share your Kindle books
Guess that's
That is our answer for you
If any of you have questions
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And now
I believe it is time for us to
Say goodbye to each other Kevin and move along to our guests this week
Who is Alexandra spiritos the CEO of resin IO
It sounds esoteric
It's he doesn't his company does containers at the edge
Basically
The whole conversation is about what people are using
To build their iot devices on
And what it takes to actually create
Something that's resilient enough for the Internet of Things
Musical guest so stay tuned
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Is Alex burritos who is the CEO of
Resin IO
I am super excited because
Is super pumped because we're going to be talking about development platforms
Industrial Enterprise
And there's a whole lot of stuff change
Like a whole lot of stuff on the market now
Before we get into that
We want to let people know who you are so why don't you tell us a little bit about resume
And
What you're doing there
Tono Rosario is a
Containerized payloads
Two embedded devices attached devices
So we built all of it to again
You need to really get
Golang for structure of the way
And just deploy code to your devices wherever they aren't
The big idea here is containers at the edge
And we should probably explain a little bit about
Why that matters so much
Coyote
Oh absolutely
We were
Developers at work
Focus on cloud Technologies
We kind of had landed on this project
What we call today as confused and this was a biggest problem with sound
Updating this device is managed
Incredibly difficult
While in the cloud we had this
Credibly
Great experience
Wish you no single command so if they ever
Everything at the same time
The devices we actually we're back
The eighties we were literally going around
USB sticks
Egg containers
We found essentially the loop
Well that allows us to
Through that half all of us
Toddler clothes that we know and love
Tootie's devices
So which containers we can update the device
Without rebooting them if something goes
What's wrong
You can put update them again
There's a host operating system underneath
If anything goes wrong
And that level of
Virtualization react
It's for my personalization that we
We're never able to have
Previously on his devices
It really
Changes development
Entirely
Feel while not identical
To Cloud developments that's feel a lot more like it
Flexibility a little bit of
Comfort
I want to say certainty because nothing really
Miss World
Who are they
Who are our customers with
Colton Fleet owners they are people
We're like
Used to be house
$100,000
They need to manage and they are
Geographically
So they have this problem on their hands and honestly they don't want to focus on if they have other things they need to
Development of the machine learning or the digital signage or
Tidal turbines or whatever it is that
Pair device
To do that software
Not
Focus on how do I get my
Container from A to B how do I make sure I keep running
So when you guys started out one of the cool things that you did was reported a doctor
Container to arm basilica
Talk to me about
Is determined
What does audience mean
We were very privileged
Because we
Really we're building for RC
So our initial Vision was actually we need to build Heroku variety
We need this one command
That you
So baidu
Pulling on that thread will realize the Roku was using
Innerstand docker
Was very early days anyway
0.40
6 I mean
So we found that
When you that this was going to be big but it wasn't
Support arm
So
We essentially
Are we going to do our own thing or are we going to try to make
We decided we were a small teams in
Want to really reinvent the wheel
So
We decided to just
Primate Docker work
That's that's what we do
Time again
And that's really how I
People start noticing
Because of her
Got sort of
The first Sterling better container
It's okay if working
Of course in the beginning
Confused about why would you even
I want to do this
I like now we know why
Cuz now we're all
Absolutely
So right now you're in a unique position to see
What people are put in your platform
As they try to start building
So what kind of development platforms are
Using
So we would definitely see something that I think a lot of people are seeing but maybe you're not realizing how intense it is
Which is at the Raspberry Pi is just in
Incredibly
So we will see you at
Of course I mean
Basic projects
Makers
Universal students
I will also see it in the biggest companies
In the world and prototyping
We will see you then
In startups
And then we see it in product
Tamuct production
Let me see it a lot further along than anybody ever imagine
So that's definitely something that if you
UCR for athletes that start with B
A very visible
But stand out
There is definitely
Another Trend there around the in Tillamook
Which is something that Intel did
Thinking about it exactly this way but this is
To the space if you just things that nobody thought cut that way this is used when you want more power
More processing power
Look you know what size 5x7
Computers
Yes in French
See
Exactly I think it needs a next unit of computing
That is exactly what it mean
See another very exciting
Picking up which is
Around the Nvidia RTX
Pontiacs to family
So you have it
Essentially a fairly powerful arm chip but then a very very powerful GPU there
Baidu deep learning
These ones haven't scheduled yet
So we have a lot of people were
Working on them
First stage of the project but
Velocity we see behind that is something
That's a mistake
We do not see that other device types other than
And the on the pie
And so if I tried
Divide these
If I'm doing a
Prototyping early stage
Device or is this something that's actually being used
Real production
Me realize is that
People will push prototyping
Out into
Production as far as
While yes canonical EBC it in prototyping we actually do cereal product build battle
Include a Raspberry Pi inside them
Multiple Raspberry Pi's depending on the
But we do we kill the people going out with hundreds
Sometimes.
Raspberry Pi
This is
Surprising but I never left
Are there downsides to that I mean like when I think about Raspberry Pi
It's a basic arm chip I don't think of it as
Particularly Harden
For a security perspective
Right I mean the issues with the Raspberry Pi really are
Three and they're kind of big
There is the
Working aspect
Support 5 gigahertz
He works a lot of busy
Is a power aspect
You know you have a USB
Mini
High voltage
And then of course there's a story.
Take whatever you have an SD card and I might get lost
Corrupted you know all of that stuff
Which all of these
Perfect sense what are Raspberry Pi Foundation
They're trying to make an educational classroom
Spread the love
Computing we should have succeeded
Exactly
On the security front
Yes there are three high does not have you know that
TPM Awards
Computing
Extensions
I mean exposing at least to the users
But then again
It's not like
Most others in the mud are in The Spinners
Play
Appetizers capabilities but there are subtle flaws that make them
Usable I think over the next few years will
Phoebe thinks I'm out I really
We're really excited for them
But I wouldn't say that they're at the Raspberry Pi
Significantly worse State than
Most of the classes
So that's the pie so
People are using it
Little walkie
With the the Intel Nook
Have you seen this
News from the early days
People
Really
Industrial context you know if your in the universe
Press your arm you probably will grab a Raspberry Pi
If you're in an industrial setting in
I literally call it the Raspberry Pi of the Industrial
It's it's very accessible price point which is like
Get it for me
$300 or something like that
What's the basic models are out
Is very accessible for an industrial pump
Set reminder
The number so they make him available to their engineers
Send a lot of
Project.
Also for
Digital signage
Which needs
A lot of GPU power
One screen to screen in a 4K Graphics all that stuff also the Nook is very very popular
Oh that makes sense that they just in January
Said that they were doing a new one with the graphics card
It's pretty impressive that can do 4K and
Some other fun stuff I was wondering why you needed all that
Machine learning but
I didn't think about this
Weather
But a lot of the cases that we see in resin are actually what I kind of
Call
Time it's just
Already there
Digital sign smart meters
Industrial Equipment that's been there for decades
And just bring it to the next level
In the next level in that
Internet-connected having containers
Operating a lot more like a server in a Datacenter than a old-school embedded my
Efficient
I remember
How many people it took to manage
1 to a hundred used to be amazing
Lord only knows what Google
It's probably pretty
Exactly minutes that. Same curve is playing out at
Yes we must come at the edge
DS
Exactly it is either or you to
Guitarist Ora
Let's go to India
And machine learning because this is
This feels very much like the future so I really want to dig into
What types of applications are they doing that with who's doing it
What can you do
Coming back to you.
German what it means
A lot of people
Essentially started
Because they wanted to
To filter data between
Small and cheap devices that work
May be dispersed
Around the factory or something like that and Cloud so they
I couldn't eat it all.
Too much they would put these the gateways in
So where's the Nvidia boards come in and really make
Another
Is
When you can do learning
Or at least deploy machine learning model that you have pretrained somewhere else
Because you can actually intelligently choose what the
The cloud needs to know you know what is interesting out of all of these
Closest Mission I got
You can compress if you can filter it without a technology
But I using Universe kind of
Rotational power
You can actually start doing applying models to it and doing a lot more
Before it ever reaches the cloud and sometimes
You can't even make decisions on
If something is looking really strange
You don't have time
From the clouds you can make a decision yourself
Anzac
Yusuke's
Is actually one where we live the tx2
Tupac running boards really well
Is for driving in a smart cars and all that stuff
You caught really think about it
Very intuitive
Call Kuwait
To decide what you going to do
With your car until there to the cloud
You have to make a decision on the spot with
Serious intelligence if you have was in the car
That is true
And that
Latency
Everything would be terrified
Tariff
Exactly medicine going into tunnel vision connectivity and then
Where is Ski Apache
To travel really slowly.
Like you could only go to take you places
At 20 miles an hour
Exactly once people start deployment
What are some of the pitfalls the things that they're trying to do
Walden University
Sweet sweat
You're going to have her Roku for the edge what are the things you're going to first try to do
The first thing you do no problem you haven't actually won one of the place
I'm so happy I found you guys because I was really not sure how it go
Going to do this is in the fact
Even for you get out there how do I
Classes device
Each one is unique
Which one is
Tagged in a way that when it starts up in my customers
Factory
Or wherever it is intended to go buy it actually checks back in its
Authenticated I don't have to do
Maneuver
What's my customer
Show all of that died of the
Work clothes
Can get really complicated if you haven't really built it.
Timer
And then in production it's really a lot of the same things you kind of want to do with server spread you want to
Unless you want to bring them up in an orderly fashion
You want to make sure that is
Something
Goes wrong either in your code or maybe so
New Linux kernel exploit gets published
You need to update yesterday
Do that really well
Having button down
The next thing you wanted
Application performance
Is anything unexpected happening and that's where you want to see
The logs and as you figure things out
You learn things you don't no plan survives contact
Also
Software and devices to ask you learned you want to keep
Evolving that software
Update my devices
Something that is
Is one of the core
How to use S4
Okay how is it not
Like servers what is unique about industrial Eren
Enterprise on fire
Commence this is actually one of the questions we get a lot and then one of them
Because I really don't
You can't really just
Hate technology
Transplant
Resync it for the edge
Think about it
It's like you're taking
Machines that lets say they would be in a Datacenter but you are standing at the center to call cover the whole globe
Turn Down The Walls in your sort of
Growing at 5000
All the sudden you have
Challenges one is at the machines themselves are not as power
Muffuletta server
Is not as powerful as what runs innovative
It's further away
How much longer can you could also be you know some kind of dodgy Wi-Fi connection
Which Yukon
So you have to start thinking
For yourself
Make sure
It can react
Do opossums
Situation without knowing that I can get back
Then the other thing is
Climate
You don't have guaranteed powers
Pull the plug on me all the time
Which again are sings that are
Unheard of
So there's only sort of environmental situation
You need to think about it differently and then the other part is more so
Philosophical
Heard before of the cattle versus
Analogy where you know
We used to have our servers like they were pets
And then with mutual's now like kubernetes
See the message
Undifferentiated CEO
Purchasing power
And if one goes down it doesn't matter we can bring up another one
Etymology doesn't actually
Work for the edge right when I have a Smart Lock
My house
I don't want
The container that's on it to have less
And it's gone somewhere else because the somewhere else
Free actually want
Zap device
Specifically to keep functioning all the time and if something goes wrong with it
The company that told me that lock
Cannot
Press the button
I make another one up here
They actually have to ensure it's working
All the time NZ small
Perspective that we should have higher regards
I'm not sure
Maybe somebody
And then you're out
It's kind of that
We should also be nice
Nicer to cows
Okay well Alex thank you so much for
For coming on the show this
I really appreciate it
Thanks for having me that's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy on
Coyote
Will see you next week