To The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin Torres
We got a great show for you today we're going to talk about Intel selling Wind River what the heck that mean
Can I give some advice to Spotify by golly
And Kevin and I are going to have a debate
About robots
Plus we've got lots of little news bits including a smart radon detector
Amazon
Sigfox and Louis Vuitton working together
Little bit of news on the Google Assistant
And the future of
Your
Fridge
Plus I did a little bit with the nest hello doorbell and
We got some advice for you on that and we got a new sponsor this week
Ford truck
Plus
Our Guest this week is Eliseo
White she is an embedded systems engineer and we're going to be talking about what exactly that is
And play it's so much more important now that the iot is everywhere
First
Let's hear from one of ours
This week sponsor is ring
Brinks mission is to make neighborhood safer
Stay over a million people use the amazing ring video doorbell to help protect their homes ring nose
The security begins at the front door but it doesn't end there so they're extending that same level of security to the rest of your home
Phone with the ring floodlight cam just like Rings doorbell floodlight cam is a motion activated camera in flood
Next right to your phone with HD video into a audio that lets you know the moment any Wednesday
Property you can see his speech of visitors even set an alarm right from your phone so when ring floodlight cam
When things go bump in the night you'll immediately know what it is
Ring floodlight offers the ultimate in home security with high visibility floodlights and
A powerful HD camera that puts Security in your hands so with ring you're always home you.
Guys can save up to $150 off a ring of security kit when you go to ring.com
Stacy that's Ring
Dot-com Stacy check it out and help support our show
So let's get this party started with
Intel
Edwin
Alright earlier this week and tell said it would spin out Wind River systems
PE firm tpg
Undisclosed
Price
This is a big deal because Wind River systems in Wind River was in bed
Systems and software
So when I bought it I remember being very like
Wind River for a long time was very
Independent
Because no one seemed to know what it was doing with Intel
2016 so
Autolover 2 years ago
Intel really brought much closer
CEO of
Winter mobileiron and
The thought was
Now the Sea. Of time it started like
Shutting down some of its smaller
Turn off low power
Energy efficient
They're not really
It's low power chips
It started
I don't know
Coyote
And now
Looks like
Winter Garden
Actually help Intel sell any iot
Teechips
And because they're so many embedded OS has
Are tosses for embedded systems
And they're free it's
Unclear what river really had to offer
And it's probably worse even though we don't know the sale price the acquisition price in 2009 was 884
4 million dollars that was a lot of money back then
So
Curious how much of that they got back and as far as what
I think I don't know I'm so I'm not going to say a lot or a little but I suspect it was
Not enough because obviously they sold it but
As you just said Stacey
There's so many different
Embedded software platforms out there
And there's so many more
Come about since 2009
When in tell me this acquisition so
I don't know whatever really came out of in a positive way
Introduced Intel to some of the Industrial
Customers I mean Twin Rivers been around for
Decades
It software is inside Manufacturing
Implants
All devices
Planes Railways all kinds of places
So it's not like it's
It's a nothing
Company it's just true
True it feels very old school in
I feel like we're getting to this kind of
Newark
Modern modern
Yeah so just to your point I mean I shouldn't say nothing came about it because I know that NASA
Sjpl
Curiosity Rover Mars
That was powered by wind River
I did not know that
Now you know
Who's where
I guess the Rover Market isn't too hot AC
It's a shame
Moving from
I guess
Embedded systems
Let's talk about
Spotify this week
Republic
This particular
Sigmund is not
Related to it golang
This is just
Me complaining about Spotify
You have special Musical
She's complaining about Spotify
This is something
Encounter quite a bit in my home
From various different
What is this
Spotify has a premium account
Where are you
There's a count for one person
And then there's a family premium
Which is what we have
And access
For up to 5.
People can play
Spotify
Which sounds really awesome if you think about it as five people playing
Crystal Lake phone
2 something
It is terrible in the world
Smart speaker
Because all of my Amazon
And Google
Speakers are under my account
And
That means if my daughter is playing Spotify
In her room
Amazon
I can't play it anywhere else in
And part of that reason is because she doesn't have an Amazon account because she's not old enough yet to have one
Legally
She is she can't have it when she's 13 she can have
It's still a little irksome cuz even if I gave my husband
What room is he in
He's in the Saint heat cuz he has
Access his emails
I can put his email on certain echos but then they would pull from his calendar and that sort of thinking
That would be aggravating since
Amazon still doesn't recognize me as an individual in my home
And yet it recognizes him
So
The issue here is I would like
To allocate devices
Not email
Dresses for my Spotify
Playback
Actually used to do this on Sonos
If you hook your Spotify account up to your Sonos you can play up to
Two streams on the same Wi-Fi
Which was
A my house uses Sonos because they have to turn onto an app
The Sonos one
Not that fancy
It's really frustrating
Spotify
Please make a device
Focused they cannot just use her Focus but make a Multi-Device
I wonder if
Company service companies are getting away from per device type things because
People are buying so many more devices now that are capable of using these services
Maybe
But
I'm not giving them a pass I'm just trying to think this is not the way it used to be
If you have a echo in every room in your house most every room have 5 6 8
And
You know I know you
Limit 2 concurrent streams new se5
Concurrent streams are song
If you do it per device that kind of
Goofy when you have too many
I don't know
I knew her voicemail hotline
Question has to do with something
Disorder related
And this gets to the way things are design in the home now they're designed for
Individual users
Or there's design for individual users and not for everybody in the home and that's that's something we need to resolve
Yes there's definitely a question about identity who gets it who doesn't
How you allocate
Services
Yes
Good preview for shadow
Question
Plea for help from Spotify
And yes I can put an email address for my home
And then put all my
Home devices
And honestly if you were going
I'm trying to say
Should you set up like
Your home email address for all of your devices
And then just send it to your
I guess you could
Some things would not work
I think your Google calendar is
I'm going to work unless you also tie it to
Tresor
Yes
See
You just tired
If you guys have advice
Kevin sent me this email
About
The links
And we started getting into it like
Conversation about what we want in a robot
This is
This is what we do over the weekend we talk about robots over email
Where exactly the people
Exact
So
You know I keep up with what's going on in robotics world because I just want
A robot that does everything for me pretty much
Interested in the space
And I noticed that there's a new human looking robot
As $800 it's called The Links
What stood out was that it has
Smart's built into it
Got me thinking
These types of smarts and why are they all trying to recreate the wheel with
Their own personal assistants I saw another nice forever
$1,600 on wheels
House for 8 hours a day
It's got its own personal assistant even
What's could be a smart home hub that's great but
Why are you doing the whole
Personal assistant on your own when the rest of the world is kind of
Adopting
Several other ones I take for roughly
Between Apples Google's Amazon's and
Samsung I started thinking about this I'm like you know what I'm just going to maybe
Kabul my own thing together just a small
Couple wheeled robot that has a
Camera on it so I can
Follow me around tomatoes are not very expensive
And then I'm going to just put a Google home on it with a battery
So that battery lasts as long as
When I said that Stacy was like
You have a very different idea
For what
You want a robot and then
What I want
What did you find
I don't want something that follows
Site I'd rather have these devices
In each room
Stationary
From your robot has to
Mastiff
I mean
I'd rather shout at something
Just another thing for me to trip over when I
Trying to get stuff done
Needs to be able to like unload the dishwasher
Transfer laundry
Those are the things
Like my house is pretty automated
As it stands and I can shout and get
Things done
The next level of tasks that I want to take out of my
Grind are those that
Require
I know and I do get that in fact over the weekend I was looking at
Camera modules for robots
Things like that
They are not cheap
Unless that she
You can get cheaper ones but they only can lift anywhere from 8 to 11 ounces of weight
Is next to nothing that's not good.
So
Yasso
Cost is not
Where do you need to be for that yet
Let me next Monday snow object I'm sure you could buy a robot that does everything you want to do but
I could probably just buy a house
Pikachu
And that's because it's kind of a robot
It does a lot of
The mass of cooking for me
And that's kind of what I'm looking for
Tasks that otherwise
And that's xmnx
That's fairly, that's what room has done since day one
Great Titans
There you go
Oh you know what
2Go unstick the room but when I go
Gets stuck under
I need a robot to unstick my other robot
I don't know I mean yes I mean I know I don't need a robot to do what I wanted to I could have a speaker in every room
Sancerre for 3-g Speed
Nice especially as these things start getting anticipatory
And
I'm sitting there watching TV I wouldn't mind having it
Podcast
Yeah I know
New
Long story short I do wonder why a lot of
Robotic type companies are trying to do it all
Especially when it comes to the personal system space
Dentistry
Jibo
All right
Spa music
Let's talk about
Smart radar detector
Yeah I came across this over the weekend as well there's a company
How are things
That has a smart radon detector
Actor caught the wave it is $199
I don't know if right on the big deal
All the listeners are here in Southeastern Pennsylvania it's a very big deal
Discuss the rock formation is underneath Pennsylvania
Radon is bad so
Well we had a lot of issues here every home has to have a
Radon inspection before it's purchased and so on so
What this does though it's kind of like a carbon monoxide detector
Water detector for Radon
It works with
If this then that and the company
They sent me an email as well because
Hook it up that if they're in your house
You know you can have your lights turn red
Turn on a fan or AC
Stacy I would like my son
Play like a nuclear war
Sound
It would freak my family out
But obviously there's a lot you could do with this because it is a connected radon detector so that was kind of dressing
I like it I do not have radon issues
However
I'm all for you not getting
How much is it
At 199
How much is a note on the second floor so that way
How much is it normally how much is a normal
I don't know I mean I don't I don't have one usually people come in with radon test kits
This isn't like a CO2
This is just us radon Uso
It's another $70
The wave + measures indoor air quality plus radon
I don't see a smoke detector and radon
Alright let's see in a move to bring it back
Google home
Amazon has taken its Echo and it brings music
By the way
So it's not to set up your
This basically means like
If your
Good morning or good night
Have a good night routine
And I can now add
Play
Spotify
Yeah you probably can I actually can't because my
Madame a app for iOS has not been updated yet
So what
Feeling it has four
Android I'm just taking a wild guess on that one
Streaming services supported for this are Spotify Pandora Amazon music of course
IHeart Radio in TuneIn
Cuz we are on
The internet
Kings podcast
Respond
Speaking of Google
You can now finally control your nest secure from Google
Assistant
Which is nice because originally
The Nest secure security system
Arnot from your app
Or using the tags or the keypad
And I thought that was kind of
I actually wanted the nest cameras to be like I recognize your face I will arm it
Disarm it when I see them
Google Assistant can just say it instead of
So
You can even ask the status of the security system with at 2
PNC login she just take things I'll never buy for $500 Alex
So sigfox is working with Louis Vuitton not a company I purchased from just cuz it
Expensive
They have a new luggage tracker using sigfox technology
It works with certain Louis Vuitton Horizon luggage bags and I don't know the price of those I'm sure there's
You have to go in the store actually find out how much cuz you can't find out online
And
Track your checked luggage in major airports and there's a whole list of supported airports
And why is that important
Stacy why is it only certain airports
They have to have some sort of
It's the equivalent of a cell tower
It's not a cell tower
A radio receiver so when you're in those airports
Your luggage can talk to
The tower
Basic facts main gateway
Outside ever far from the airport but it will track
It while you're at the airport
It seems the sigfox Monarch service
Teresa
And it's got about
25 US airports including all the big ones that you would expect
International
If you're going
And yes
Seems exciting
I wish I knew what the price was
I personally just stick a tile in my bag actually my husband sticks
He tracks it
There
This is yet another
Let's talk about the future of our fridges
It's kind of scary.
Do you think
I went to take a piss
I'll tell them what this is Nancy if you have some thoughts interesting article in
Venturebeat this week talking about emotion AI or affective computing
Basically
This is a way for a connected device to determine your emotion
And the example was a smart fridge
That would suggest Foods based on your emotion or your mood
And I guess that's I think that's a good idea because there are certain
Turn to comfort food and such and that's not necessarily the best thing
In the world
It gets to the question do we want
Our emotions and
Bluetooth devices tomatoes
I would say yes because we're always talking about context right
This is like the next level of context in actually
It's something that people have been thinking about
For as far back is to
I remember talking to
The people about this city
Freescale
And they were talking about how to
Detect people's emotions from their voice
On their phones
And
Assigning those emotions to be
Trying to figure out what they could
Julie emotions are just
Again more contacts so if you walk in the house angry
You don't maybe your home
Play some soothing music
Fridge could offer you some ice
Then that makes sense I guess
I'm stuck on trying to put this technology into every single device I would rather have it centralized
Maybe in my robot that follows me around all day
Or my assistant whatever
Digital assistant
I'm using
As opposed to each individual thing like I want my house to know but I don't need
AutoZone points
So you don't
Calculating your emotional score at the mo
Yeah I mean it is a lot of a computing power at the
Right
Here's my heart we're going back to the robots
Coming back with this sort of skill
In baby
The context in brain of your house is like a cute little robotic pet
Companion
I can live with that I could to be kind of fun
Hey French this person is really sad
Offer them some chocolate
Enter test that I could take my
Idea of the robot in the Google home sick
And just put a Google home on my dog
Yes that would I would like video
And how we smart
So Google story
Google
Might make its own smart display
Oh
I was so hot for that Lenovo one that we saw at CES
And this is our friend
He's the best
Yasso
I don't know
Cuz this is coming out in the summer the Lenovo one
Right right so hopefully within the next three months or so
Cuz I would like to have have to say
Like I just
Talked about this a minute just installed a nest doorbell in one of the things I'm looking forward to is actually pulling that up
On my
So but having just a little
Google display would actually be
Yeah I do that today with the shield as a crumb
Cast capable device I do that but like on a 50-inch TV and I don't need endoscopy inch TV
It'd be nice out on a date or 10 in
Tablet display like this like a Lenovo one
I suspect I don't know obviously but I suspect that next month at Google IO
We'll hear more about smart Display Devices
And other partners cuz I can't believe it when I was the only one
And as in treating Zone Hardware brand products
I could easily see them by maybe by the end of the year 900 but talk about 80 or introduce a
You know a home screen
Google home screen device or something to that effect
I am with you
The best takeaway from this article
Is Rishi Chandra who's in charge he's a
VPN
Home Products
He said the simple truth is we need to become a must-have
He's looking for daily use
Cases so basically he Home Products
And he said they're not
So
I guess I can see that I mean, the old adage say the best assistant is the one that you have with you
You know what it's on your wrist in your room
In your car whatever on your phone think of how much I actually use my
It's not like multiple times an hour
But it several times a day
I use mine
More but I did have to make a concerted
So
Final news bit is
Iot platform provider electric in
Just going to work indirectly integrate with Microsoft
Asher's program
Managed services
This is like just a small bit of news
Electric imp provides
Secure
Radio
Compute platforms for iot it's probably one of its biggest clients
Pitney Bowes I think side axle
Physical fitness
Equipment company uses it
You basically stick Electric in pinyin
And you got a connection
That's the
Pitched companies
With AWS and so this just extended to Microsoft azure
And we totally expect these things to happen
It's always nice
It's interesting that
Few companies iot tech companies are relying on a single
Iot Cloud providers
You stay say something more and more of this
Oh yeah that's because they're there in customers want
A choice in AWS does not have
The lock on my
By any stretch
Rizzo okay quick settings
I was prepared to talk to you about my experience with the nest hello doorbell
Nest Yale lock
Sadly
My experience is paused because I went to install the nest hello doorbell
239 doorbell very excited
Because it's got
Great reviews
And
I love Turtles
I'm not in love with my current doorbell but
You know I'm always up for something new and something
I've had a little bit of a challenge installing it Nest actually recommends a professional install
Actually very proud
The doorbells
Maybe
Is a recognition of the market
Installing door Bells is maybe harder
I have not got my to work yet
It says it's not drawing enough
Power
Can I find that confusing because
Just a few months back
Replace my doorbell transformer
From a 16 volt which is what most doorbells
Transformers are
In your own 24 volt
And I would recommend install a video doorbell
Do this
Because a lot of them say that the work
Between 16 in
But 16 is really the bare minimum
Struggle
And that means that you get
Higher latency
The picture doesn't always Roar
She's not as good
Transformer
I cannot
Emphasize
Are reinforcements and Elsa and I think a lot of people
Smart
It's very common to have
Change your transfer because the power requirements
And it's not expensive to do that it's not
Difficult to do that either
It's going to cost you ten or fifteen dollars at most of the Transformers
You shouldn't take you more than 10 or 15 minutes to replace
But just be forewarned
Going to get a smart doorbell at least look at the box and see what it says about the Transformer and the energy requirements needed to do this
Because I C
Countless support for on the same network
And almost
Cheese I can't tell you how many times it's the power it's just not enough
Part of this is on the doorbell company
To do it
I think
Vanessa's house is yours every 16 volts
You don't fit
Right now it's just
Here and I do have a weird doorbell setup so
We're going to troubleshoot that because I really want to get this work
Awesome
And
So far I will say that it is
It is lovely
Installation instructions are very easy
Making sure that the device compatible
With your product
With your existing doorbell setup
So that the video
10 solitaire
You know
So far so good
Now it's time
The iot podcast listener hotline
And you guys may remember
That we had contest
For a wise camera people who called and left us a message or enter to win
And I'm happy to say that Chris
Winnetka
Camera ISO
Chris that camera
We're coming to you
Do you have a question
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And now
People
Go listen to this week's voice mail
Broadcast listener line is brought to you by Schlage
Schlage electronic locks offer unparalleled convenience
And simplicity all on their own
Right out of the box
So you don't have to have a smart home system to benefit
To see what's possible
Visit schlage.com
To learn more
Isolation Kevin my wife lie has the Google homes and socialites and S
Google started recognizing our voices sometimes but it's been pretty annoying
Sharing routines or scenes are flows
So what's the best way to program something once
In one place
Available to my wife's on the Google home without having to do anything on her phone
Thank you
Zach
As we said earlier in the show a tenant
First off
This is not something I can count because Google does not actually recognize me
As an individual person in my house
It only recognizes my husband
My voice is just weird
Show
I cannot physically replicate this problem
For you
I did look around for solution
Yeah again it gets to the way things are designed to work in the home is it for the home is it for the user
Short of replicating the
The routines which is what you don't want to do obviously and I don't blame you
I think what really has to happen here is for the software whether it's for
Google home or Amazon or whomever
There needs to be some
Global or home routines
That everybody can use
Straight so that there isn't that she said so there's no there's no way to do this yet without
Replicating
So we're sorry for the bad news
Even something as simple as saying I'm in a family with this person
You know
Can you commit a shareable routines
Just click their name next to the
Routine
You know
I don't know
The Google please let's get this work
Also
If you could figure out how to recognize me that
An added bonus
Okay and before we go this week
I have to ask you guys
Many of you have already completed it because you're awesome but we are running a survey on the iot
Podcast
And the newsletter
To find that
You can go to Stacey on iot. Com
/ survey
We're just asking you to answer a couple questions about the show about the newsletter
About Kevin
And
Tell us what you think
This is useful for us for advertisers which helps support
What we do
Which actually
Do support what we do so big thank you to all our advertisers
And to all our listeners
And
Believe
That's it so we will know
Go to a message from
This week sponsor for truck
And stay tuned for Alycia White
Who is an embedded systems engineer
Talking about how that role has changed in the Internet of Things
Podcast for a message from our sponsor
Strategy and innovation
So let's kick this off
What is Fortran
Iraq is a digital identity
And what we do is we create a platform
That allows us to do
All the traditional stuff you would think about when you think about identity whether it be
Provisioning of users management of their data
Sportmix for track really fun and exciting is that we take those traditional Technologies and we bring it to New
Awesome digital you
And so if you think
Customers of ours like hospitality companies that when you show up at your hotel room
It's personalized for you it knows who you are
What you've done in the past
I don't understand
What the type of experience you want
To be able to do that at
Scale and do what the flexibility that a lot of
Digital transformation project
That's what for. Specialized
Awesome
To part of some of those use cases
Is personalization but as for Discovery right now personalization requires that we share data with
How do we
Do that well in a
Post Cambridge analytica
What's a great question
I need to think if you look at this
Kind of
War of disintermediation that's
Occurring right now where every
Company is trying to be closer with consumers or trying to get direct
Consumers
Possible
And everyone is competing with Amazon
I think one of the advantages that keep
People forget about Amazon is people all created their Amazon account
15 years ago login and haven't logged out since
Amazon just been collecting all this data ever since and so
Everybody else now
Getting on that
And try to collect as much data as possible in order to
Give you a great personal life
Experience I think it's becoming more and more important that people
Understand
What these vendors are doing with their data and I think it's important
For vendors that want to offer a personalized experience to make a fair deal with their customers
About what they're going to do with the data
And make sure they give them the appropriate tools
To provide consent
And how does forgerock
Has built into our flat
Builtwith
Tyrosine
Consent in mine
And so we were the first vendor
To take advantage of
The standard of the user managed access
It scored or products we allow an end-user taxi determine
Which of their personal data they want to share and with
And so it allows a vendor that is
Is one stick electrician
Those levers built into their product
Becky but user control over what type of data they're staring
Awesome all right so then where can we go to find out more about 4
So is it good or website
You find some amazing stuff about what 4:00 and 4 drop test
Arguing
To protect their crops
Privacy
And so you should go to for draft.com
Glass privacy
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Alicia white who's the founder of her own
Company logical elegance and the host of the embedded
Hi Lisa how are you doing today
Hi Stacy so nice to talk to you man I am super excited to have you because guys as I said before earlier in the show
Alicia is a
Embedded
Systems engineer
And probably going what
We're going to solve that first query by saying hey
Alycia tell us a little bit about
What an embedded system
Dictionary
When I talk to people who aren't engineers
I tell them
That I write software for things that aren't computers
And I've gotten to do some pretty neat things like
Children's toys in DNA scanners
But it's a simple is
Your microwave or your car or even yourself
Listings
Aren't the same as writing on big web
Servers or even laptop
Cuticles
Until we call them embedded systems it has a lot more to do with the hardware and software working
Together to do
And so as you guys may have surmised
This is really important in the internet
How
Have you seen your role as an embedded systems engineer changed in the last I don't know 5 years sio tbk
Came all this
Cheesecake
Pirate he's been coming for a longer than that
But it has definitely started to hit that hockey
And it has changed
Before
We had
The dumbest possible devices
Talking to a hub of some kind you think about your Hue Lights
Will you have tiny tiny microprocessor is inside light bulbs
Talking to a hub that then can translate so that it can get onto the internet
And yet a few years ago these
$4 Wi-Fi chips came out
Things could connect
Directly to the internet
And
Olive
These possibilities opened up until we had
Way too many things directly connecting to the internet
Insecurity problems
And all of the
Changes
All about the dress
Connection
The things that go behind the gateways in the edge
Or fog computing
Those are a little simpler when you think about wearables
Fitbit in going to your phone
But when we talk about
Wi-Fi
Then
Those things are kind of unprotected for the deep and scary see the internet of
Okay you've brought up a lot of things and we're going to get to some of them but first
Let's go back to this idea of what an embedded systems engineer Spencer
Their time doing
And how you get to the
Roles in an organization or maybe just in your life
So I don't know if you want to tell us a little bit about your history
I went to school at a small engineering school and
I took all of the applied computer science courses and all of these theoretical engineering course
That left me with a lot of
Series about signal processing and a lot of time writing code
I didn't know that this would be the perfect degree for doing things like audio processing and motor control
But it was and I was lucky to fall into that I love
Making
The world change through my software
The first time you get your motor
To move because you wanted it to is just magical
Stop pushing bits over the internet and you start
Moving
The world
A lot of people come from the computer science
Almost an equal number company electrical engineering
There's a problem here
Most of us only
Went to school for one of the
Perfume or embedded and computer engineering degrees coming out now
But still it's
Pretty tough to know both of these disciplines all the way down
And yet that's what we do
You have to learn the other half on the job
Wow okay so
That's a little scary because that implies that
Well maybe a lot of people coming into this field
At first they don't
No entirely what they're doing so you're either going to miss out on the
Taking care of the motor side or you're going to miss out on the
Taking care of its side
Yeah it's easy to be afraid of the hardware and actually touching
Bored
On the other side the electrical engineers don't necessarily know
That you can write your software to be far more efficient if you know a bit more about data structures and algorithms
The things that computer science people that's what they do and so it is definitely a
Specialization
This isn't the thing you go into right after college
Unless you were on the robotics team or or already had some experience
Disciplinary approaches
Instead of something you
Kind of look out for a while and say
Well I'm writing software now and that looks like fun and then you get a little bit closer in a little bit closer and then suddenly
Pics of your life
Actually sounds kind of like a good analogy for iot as a whole which is this whole real world meets the digital world
All the cast that can ensue so
With that in mind
What can you see about things that
Maybe you seen in your
Professional life
And how this is going to play out with
Coyote
Again real world meets digital world and things that people aren't really thinking
Prevention security is
Yeah security is
Is a constant battle and it's
Scary because
We are connecting medical devices
To the internet
Things that can
Truly affect lives
A car
Qunar traffic light
We can't just leave those open
For some kid to come by when they're bored at
After school and yet we're never going to get to the point that it determined hacker
With physical access
Isn't going to be able to do whatever they want
Did it balance
That but you're such a balanced how much does all this cost
When we buy
Internet-enabled
Light switch
So you can plug something in and then you can control whether or not it's on remotely
And yet
When you go when you buy them on Amazon or at the store
There's the $4 one
And $30
Go get the $30 one
Because what does it say on the Box about it being differ
Nothing that you can understand
I mean
Wapk 2493
ISO 44 blah blah
How do we convey to Consumers
So this is important and as consumers
How do we recognize that yes
Is worth the extra money
To let me talk about security we have to talk about price
So the last two decades that you have been doing this
Things have started connecting to the internet and that's
A big change but it's also big change in
How long we think he stinks need to last cuz it used to be you could buy something I have a bread maker
Like the 1980s that has a computer in it
Instaworks
Paperwork connected to the internet
I feel like maybe it would not have lasted
Oh yes
And there are so many reasons for that
And it's
Hard as a developer it's very difficult
To try to plan ahead
Medical devices is a good one because those are often long lasting
Thanks
Cars are another area where we have embedded software
I made design something to go into a car and he won't go in for two or three years and then the car is expected to last
After 15 or 30 years
How am I going to search
Work.
That long we hear all about these firmware update to how important they are for security reasons among other things
But if I'm supporting five different cars
Over 30 years
How do I test
D I did not
To update your firmware
But then you end up with things like we heard about Apple where their batteries were
Being throttled
And party music or will that totally makes sense another part of me as a consumer was like no that's awful
And you have the
Push and pull again about
How do you make it so you can
I think last long
But also act fast
NB cheap
Beyond the market
And support all the device
I think
Ventura technology is one that we're going to end up having to learn front because he's printers
Came out 15 years ago still have their driver up
And it's a lot
About the standardization of their interface
Zombie see more of that in the few
Oh that's really interesting about course printers are some of the most hated machines on the
The planet
Yeah
Yeah that was an unintentional parallel
Okay
This is actually the Apple thing is a great example cuz this touches on something that I think we're going to see more
Which is this engineering mindset where
If you talk to an engineer
It's wonderful
Because
I understand trade-offs in every decision they make is basically
Optimizing against trade
Yes for some particular subset of
In consumers we don't think that way
We want it all
Or the cheapest price
Possible
When those two kind of things come into play It's not that Apple was necessarily being
Evil they just were thinking like an engineer
And as we have more technology.
I'm very curious
How you see these kind of
I guess
Conflicts I don't know if they're really complex just differences in point of view
Getting resolved between
In the business world but also for
Consumer I
I have to admit
I'm an engineer
I'm so an engineer
And like I said I understand why Apple did what they did it made sense
But
We can't
Be that close minded
Impart
Because we have an obligation to work us
And
It's going to keep happening
That there's this
Butting of heads between engineers and customers
A good marketing department
Can figure that out
Can mediate
Between the needs of the customers
And the
Goals of engineering
I don't
Think there's going to be an easy solution some of it
To me because I am an engineer and this is all
Normal to me
I think everybody should be technologically literate
Yeah people say that to me about
I don't know Macintosh
I can't
I'm sorry
So now we're getting kind of into this idea of
How do you communicate
The people about the functionality and how
Tanks work
But let's talk about what it takes what kind of team it takes to build an iot device
Because I think a lot of the company's coming at this tend to be like oh
I've made a nap
00 hire someone and I have this idea for a product so I'll build it out of a pie and then
Open a Kickstarter in Macon
I think we're kind of over that now but what do you think
Company really needs to have
OnStaff to build
Well I should say build a connected device
When you ship software you're sipping Electra
But when you ship Hardware you have to ship the protons to and they're much heavier
Far more difficult
If I got to build a whole team like I was we're going to build a
A hundred thousand of these things and there's going to be enough money to hire all the people
You want a systems engineer to look over all the peace
Is to make sure that they're all going to fit together
And
That person
We'll talk to a mechanical engineer that will help design the Box
And make sure that the boards fit inside the box and the box is pleasing to the customer
The electrical engineer will Design boards
And make sure that they're manufacturable and their parts are all going to be available at the time that we want to ship this product
Give embedded software engineer
Who works on the software inside the product
To make sure that these
Security the connectivity
The firmware update as well as all of the features that you're actually building into this product
Are there
And are there on a processor that is cheap
Cheap enough to build
Dimension Raspberry Pi
You know they have some of those that aren't too expensive and so it's a good way to go if you're going to build a hundred or something
Thousand something
He wants to be more
Motorrad
I think maybe resource
Strained because
It only needs to do the things you wanted to do your building a product you're not building a
Computers Raspberry Pi
Computer and you can hide it inside a product
But
If I was going to be cheaper if you actually
And then on the other side you still need the software
And you likely still need the back end and web developers and all of the other software Engineers you need to do to have a good
Good app and good Prada
But you have this whole other team
And
Why do Consulting
And I enjoy it and I know
Many people who are good at it
Going to a
Professional Services firm with a napkin sketch
And idea
They may do a great job
Many of them do
But they're not going to love it
If you wants to build this
You going to have to at least be that systems engineer who can talk
And that means knowing a little bit about all the p
Enough mechanical engineering to no other problems
Enough electrical engineering to use the right words
Enough embedded systems engineering to hire somebody
You can balance your knees for
Speed efficiency
Power optimization
Cost and getting to Market on time
The last person in the
Chain is probably the menu for
Fashion engineer the person who at the end
Make sure you can build
A hundred thousand of them on a line
Whether it's
In Mexico or China and United States wherever it is that person is going to optimize it so that
The firmware update step that took 20 minutes now only takes 5 and that means your throughput is
Pastor
And your whole system cost
I keep bringing up cost because it is something that is very important with internet at
It's why we choose the $4 poorly security systems instead of the $30 Wilson
The amount of software in the amount of harboring them isn't that different
It's just how well its design so if we can get these $30 designs to be
$10 then maybe we can start convincing people to use the good stuff
I like it to use the good stuff
All right
You're making a great case for meeting
All of these rolls and
Especially in embedded systems
Do you think
This is a job that's going to become more in demand as we add
More smarts to everything
I hope so
I think my job has changed over the last 20 years and I think it will continue to change
I used to work more on 8-bit process
Json getting the last
Little psycho out of
A processor so that I could use it
To do something
And now that's not as important
The prices are so cheap and they're so power-efficient only occasionally have
To really worry about
How long thing
I'm so much more memory than I used
The onboard memory where the code lives and the RAM memory
We're at the code executes or or can use variable
But I worry more about power efficiency
Making sure that if things are wearable
Or even plugged in and need to be energy STAR certified
That's a good thing that we didn't used to have even cell phones used to be bigger and now they're smaller and they
I keep getting more and more
Timmy x changed a lot
And
I'm glad
I like learning thing
I think
That we will never quite make it go away
Because there will always be a need to have it be more power efficient
Or
Have it be cheaper and more functional for one purpose
On the other hand
I don't think people will need to worry as much about
Smaller detail
I haven't needed to worry about
Car detail
I think it would be more approachable job in the
And how this sounds cool
How do people get into this job what's a good entryway
Well if you're in high school or college
I say immediately go out and join the robotics
If you are a software engineer and want to learn more about Hardware there's this platform called Arduino
It's fun it was originally designed
For artists
To use to make glowing and interactive displays until there's a lot of
Orioles out there and they shouldn't be
If you are a little beyond that because it is a little bit of
Hobbyist only platform
Look for the end beds
These are a series of boards with online free compiler also that Teddy Torres.
The good stuff
And then if you want to go into it for a career
I wrote a book
Making embedded systems from O'Reilly
And it talks Natalie about all of the things I think you should know about making great software for embedded system
Also talks about getting hired in 10 minutes
And mostly I would say try it
If you get one of these boards
You maybe spend 30 bucks
China doll that
You may find the
This is really fun
If you doing all kinds of
Weird interesting pads
Where your life becomes as much about the application and the customer as it is about the soft
That's a really good time.
To I
Of course
I meant I would second that I actually have an art
Order ahead
I didn't find it as fun I found it a little frustrating just because I didn't probably know enough
But the worst case scenario is
You can donate it to a school robotics club and
Will welcome it with open arms
So
Worst case scenario you spend a little money
You find you don't like it
And then you get
Goodwill
From your school
Alright well at least you thanks so much for coming on the show this week
I really appreciate it
It's been wonderful to talk to you that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if
If you'd like more iot nose sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot