Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy hey
Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have an amazing show for you we are going to talk about Rockwell automation's
1 billion dollar investment in PTC
This is all about industrial iot so you're going to want to hear it
Has bought a startup and we're going to talk about that plus we're going to go into some standards news
Thread group has
Need some Milestone announcements
Tell you what those mean in the consumers about Wi-Fi Pumas offering a Wi-Fi subscription
We'll talk about that
I have a very controversial opinion
Plus
We are going to talk some
Stuff about security
It looks like we're getting some price wars in the
DIY security Market
What about that
Verizon's new CEO and what that means for iot
Plus I got my wyze pan Cam and we're going to
Do a quick little review of that
I guess this week is Garrett Miller Chief digital officer of current
He's going to talk about how GE shifted its
Current business
From
Selling power generation kind of electricity on demand
That's a lighting because that is where the market is at
And much more
Are podcast today is sponsored by praetorian so you'll hear it from them
But first
A message from one of our other sponsors
Control4
Today's podcast is sponsored by control for a leading Smart Home
Provider delivering support for nearly 12,000 connected devices professionally installed by a smart home
Lighting security thermostats door locks music TV cameras and more
Work together to provide a smart home that's built for smart people you're home and all the connected devices in it controls
Simply and easily
Now that smart head to control4.com that's control the number four.
Dicom for more information
Okay Kevin
Let's kick it off with
We're kicking it off with industrial news you guys which I know some of yall might be like I don't know
But it's a big deal
Rockwell Automation
They have entered into the Strategic partnership with
PTC
For industrial in a
Station
Mptc you may remember they are a company that used to do
Design and Manufacturing software and then they started buying up iot companies like thing works actually Bots Lively witch
Clock me in
Mommy and Dively and then sold that but they
Are doing really cool stuff with things like AR & VR I talk to the CEO Jim heppelmann a couple times
As part of this partnership Rockwell Automation is making a billion-dollar Equity investor
And there's
CEO and chairman will join the board of pt
This is going to be a really deep partnership they're going to integrate their smart Factory Technologies they're going
PTC has thingworx kepware all of that's going to go in with Rockwell Automation
Factory song
So my question about this is
Where does that leave
Other companies like Johnson
Controls
Cement
Compete with raw
Rockwell Automation
And I don't know how exclusive
Pussy
I think to answer your question but I don't know the exact answer but to answer your question I think it's going to depend on pricing because
Where is subscriptions
It is
In which case it's going to come down to like in any Enterprise
It area how much is it going to cost me so if those other competitors can still provide similar services
At a lower subscription price that may help those little guys
It might it actually I'm talking to Jim heppelmann
Later on this week so you'll see more about the
Send the newsletter
But it's
Pretty big freaking deal so
We're talking about here
Arm
The semiconductor license
Company that you all know and love
They make the designs that
Make yourself own chips
Other chip
Like the tiny little chips
Surrender SmartWatches
They have bought a company called stream
Technology
And
Their goal here
Is
Extreme Technologies does device management and
Iot connectivity
This is a little weird because arm is a
Chip design
But what's happening is they really focused
Hard on their mbed OS and they launched
Probably a year-and-a-half ago I feel
Cloud offering for iot so
They're actually trying to
To build
The same sort of cloud offering that
Amazon
And others have
To help their customers basically offer
God I hate saying these words end to end
Cloud iot offering so basically
They need a lot more though they can't they can't compete with like an Azure and AWS
It got the basics down which is getting your devices online and then managing
No I don't think it is I don't think it is because our magic says they chip designer they don't manufacture
Nitro chips instead they license their designs to
Apple Samsung
Mediatek
Qualcomm etcetera
And there's only so much more growth left in the mobile devices that
Run on those chips that yes there are newer types of devices and some iot devices will need these
Smart as well but
They can't rely on the big growth
From their biggest
Revenue generator these days they have to do something more than just be a chip designer that
Puts out intel processors basically
So I don't think it's all that
That weird
Okay I know that this is like I get it and I know that they're in this position
But I think it's
Crazy for them to think they can come
I guess is where I'm going
SA
I get why they're doing it
But
I just want to be successful either I'm not saying that at all but
At least they're giving themselves a chance in a new market
Is right now without this and I think they made one other
What was the reason I thought was weird acquisition last year I don't recall what it was but
Really why are they doing that now
They have to
They just have to otherwise where's the growth going to come
So I I get this in
You know arm
Has done a lot actually
Advance fee
Try to advance the overall iot Market
Easier
So a couple years ago they launched in bed which is their OS for it's their real time
And they did that because everybody else had their own OS is it part of
I called the chip fenders
License
Iris designs
They had their own
Operating
And it was terrible because you
As a developer if you wanted to build an iot device
You had to learn like
A variety of embedded operating so
It's basically so they were like hey let's have them all learn mbed OS and that'll be easier and then that'll work on
Rochester
That hasn't embed has not the adoption curve has not
Gone the way we thought it
Doubtful but
Only according to an eclipse
Iot developer survey that came out in April
48.8
8% of
Developer survey
Actually use mbed OS
Compared to
I'm a 72% using Linux
And then
About 20.4% using
Free artist
Just be
Most pop
Artaste
Set Linux
Too fat for life
And Amazon bought free art Osso Amazon right now has that same
And they didn't buy free
Asset open source
I don't know how to phrase that properly
Anyway so now they've got this
End-to-end kind of system
Really interested to see what Amazon does
Too deep in that
Meanwhile arm just feels like it's really far behind
So there's there's art
In other
Is it industrial it's just kind of catching up with p
People V
Red group
I remember them
The thread group they're using
Iot standard for
The radio
It's mesh Network base it uses 802. 15. 4
And
The same thing is it
Same radio underneath
And then they connect directly to IP
IPv6 switch
Unique about it so they did a milestone release
This week
It's worth mentioning that
Nordic joined which they actually announced way back in
February
Zeidman's also joined which means thread could actually find some
Some credibility in the industrial space
Face which I thought was
Worth mentioning
Thread still does have
Definition
The issue is with
Google and Nest they actually were one of the founding members of
They built a version of it that is not actually certified by the thread of life
So they have there
Own
Thread
Lamentation
The group that's in or the companies that are part of thread group right now I'm in with all the Heavy Hitters are in there if Samsung are
We just talked about Qualcomm nxp
Somfy osram
Evendale
Even yeah
Even you got out a lot company and don't forget
Say it the big butt Fan Company
So that's that's kind of the thread stuff there's
Lots happening there
Yay
I'm actually might my goal is in the next week or two to take a look at
Both red
The open connectivity Foundation
Because
It feels like
There's a lot of nothing happening in
If I remember correctly The Nest connect when it came out
Was there was a mention of thread and this kind of gets to that dichotomy of
Using full thread and knot thread in fact I remember we asked a grant Erickson president of the thread group about this
And I said I was quote right for me nasty text relies on threads low-power architecture
Place for long periods of time A-1 Battery Nest connect is a thread router
Which seamlessly extends
Bo3 cheat activate a thread Network
I think we later found out that it doesn't use the full
Angered
It uses what
They call thread
Ready
In what
Google has open source
Has open
Yes and that is exactly
A challenge that the thread group faces which is that
They basically let Google
Google nest
Use
The version of thread that they built in the very big
Beginning for all of their stuff
Right is not actually
Compatible
With the thread certify
It's just thread ready
It's a little bit of a
And that could be why we have
Not heard much lately
Indeed
All right
So Kevin
Hard question for you
Do you pay for a Wi-Fi subscription
Or an add-on to your
Listing of a service on top of your Wi-Fi
I do not my family pays me because I am the IT service guy for the network
Okay
So plume which we talked about in the past there the company that has the
Plume pods they're little
Hexagon shape
Pods that you can
Just plug in
And they actually
Dynamically control
Your network
In the cloud
So you plug these in wherever you need in your house and then they start to
Understand what's happening on your network and then
They
Kelly
Pod what to
Describe that
It's kind of like Mesh networking yet all the intelligence is done the cloud as opposed to local
Right
So
They now are charging
When you buy a plume pods they're going to charge you
60 bucks a year
Wi-Fi service
Literally
Or $200 for a lifetime membership
So
Where do you buy this though you get reduced pricing on plume sweater
And a warranty for each year that
Sew in
The lifetime is 5 years
With a subscription you get a 3-pack
For $40
You can't buy them without us
Used to be it was $180 for the bathroom
So
If you
Don't have the subscription
You can't use them
Right
And said they accept if you already had
If you have already bought your plume pods previously
You can still yeah you're fine
Flights going forward
But going forward you're going to have to pay 60 bucks a year
I am actually okay with this they offer the discount on Hardware
You also get parental controls security stuff
The collective management
Describe what the
What does is basically saying
Hey Wi-Fi in your home
Is no longer going to be
Hardware base
This is going to be a service
I'm kind of okay with that given how much drama I have over my Wi-Fi network
In my house
It was all of my connect
If that gives the company accountability
For actually
Solving some of the problems I have with my devices
And it makes them update
Things that
Might like
Any issues with my router
You know
That's kind of worth it
I think for some people yes it is I'm not going to dispute that
For me personally I have all those features
In my current router setup
Parental controls guest networking
You know being forming at the right place and time so that the signals going to the right devices I can prioritize devices
Search for Wi-Fi
I'm not I'm not paying for that
Unless unless I have no choice in which case
That would mean all of the vendors in this space to do this
And that's going to be the big question so what it what we do see in the space right now is companies like Eero offer
A subscription option
So
I could pay 04
Additional parental management
Additional
Security
A VPN password manager all attached to the
In a security office
I have not paid for it yet even though I was actually like thinking about it I just
Justin get to it in time before it
Expired
So
I don't know I and I really
I also question how many people buy their routers at retail so plumes big business is actually still going to
To be through
Isps so things like the Comcast deal and Comcast is not charging people
11 bucks a month for a router
Which is said to be insane
Here's the thing
I don't have a problem with subscription for
Extra services
But I don't even have the option with this one the option is to not buy this one and buy a different
Router brand
Yes I'd rather see it as an add-on option
Look at it this way this is hardware this is
Just a little bit
And I'd rather be part of the hardware
Because that's at least a sustainable business model like you
I mean again
If this was the only choice out there I'd be like
And I know a lot of people very much a lot of our audience is probably like Stacy you're so crazy
I can do this myself
They're going to be people like you Kevin and I respect that but
I think this will be interesting to watch to see if
Accompany
Actually
Move from a product model to a Services model
Keep an eye on it
Okay
Google home has a new skill
Where does it where does it
Yeah so remember I wasn't but a couple
How to say we should probably months ago
They enabled the ability to use a Google home with
Multiple commands in
In one sentence speak one sentence and have two things happen
Apparently now you can do it with
Three things
Google
It tweeted something about this
And then pulled the tweet
And if I go to the support page at they've linked to in the poultry it's still just shows two things
However some people are saying that it still works at 3
So we've actually tested this booth on our respective Google
Devices and has not yet work for us so I don't know if it was a rolling kind of thing where it's coming
We just don't have it yet or maybe Google pull the toys because
It's just not ready for anybody yet don't know yet
The mystery will not be solved today
Okay let's work at home security there are two notable stories here the first is the nest security system is
399 so $400 this is
This is a reduction in price by a hundred
Box so
Annie's get YouTube
Presence fobs
Security sensors that are multi-purpose sensors and
Round thing that you
And the keep
Is there a
You know it's built into the Top of the Hub
A little funky design
Right
Your father over it to arm and disarm it it's
When is it still thread ready
So
That is
Notable
Because people liked the security system they hated the fact that it
Cost so much
But
Perhaps
There's a reason to this
Which is
Rings home security system is going to launch
Next month
And when it launches
It's going to be
The 99.
Remember ring was purchased by Amazon
December
So
This is
Ring / Amazon
And it will include
A single motion sensor
Single door window sensor
+ 8
Keypad
And this this one you should melt to a wall I would think
I guess you can have it
On a table but I don't know
And it's got this weird iPod
Click wheel looking device
Yeah
I don't know about that either but that's okay I mean it's sticking out $200 less
$200 list
I'm in the centers are relatively cheap you buy a motion sensor
Next door windows
Are you surprised I mean we knew this was coming because of something else last year but then they were lawsuits until when I think this was
Back in October was supposed to be out for was announced back then
Are you surprised because since then Amazon has purchased ring that there's no Amazon branding no
No
Bundling with a Amazon camera ring like that
No I'm not actually surprised because
Does Amazon has
They fought
Plenty of companies in
Twitch
Zappos
Some of their bigger Acquisitions that kept alone
And bring has a great brand record
Ignition in in
So
It makes total sense to me
That people might buy ring
Not realizing
I would like to see
You know
Ring has the doorbell camera that have outdoor cameras
I would like to see a package that includes some of that be
Because I think it
You know
It will take
But I wonder if we are not seeing it be
Because
Amazon also bought a company called
Link and they have some really good video Pro
Processing technology very low power
So I'm wondering if we'll see a new camera soon
That goes with
The Amazon key system or the
Ties into this that uses
That hard
That
That's a good point and possibly need doorbell cuz I believe the blink doorbell
Yes they're still planning to make that
Right
So you don't maybe they'll have a
A higher antenna Lauren like amazonbasics
I don't know
Okay
Other final two little stories worth mentioning
Microsoft hololens
Is coming next
Your whole inspiration
And I put this in here because
The Holland is really interesting for a R&B are in industrial settings there's a couple companies
Already using it
I know it's a little weird
I'll be honest you know that's not
For us but I have it
Several
Industrial
Iot events I've actually done some
Repairs in VR
For like industrial process control systems
Guided by you know
I put on the hololens and they would guide me through the steps
I can see how this would be really useful
And that sort of setting
For that for emergency services all kinds of
On the field types of activities yes
So
I know and you know
It's a beauty good experience the hololens is actually.
Cool
There we go
And then finally
Hans vestberg is now Verizon's new CEO replacing Lowell McAdam
And I brought this up because I have known Hans
For years because he was the CEO of Ericsson
After being
Kicked out of his CEO role at Ericsson in 26
He popped up last year as a CTO at Verizon
So
This was a surprise to Wall Street this was a surprise to pretty much everyone when Verizon announced him it is
In this role a couple analyst for like
Yeah it wasn't that great over at Ericsson
However
I will say
But he was very Visionary about the Internet of Things
Turning Erikson's product-based business into a Services business
And
He knows a lot about 5.
So
I think those are really good reasons to put him in
A Verizon I think
With Erickson originally he was trying to turn around a company
When the Telco equipment Market just
It was
Killer it was
Broken
And he was really pushing 5G a little too early
In
That the market
Fertel, equipment hits
Consolidated
Tremendously
Martinsville
West End
And he just
It's a little too early on iot and 5G
That's that's my take on his tenure there so having him at Verizon
We're there already investing in 5G
They need that Visionary plan for how to build services around it
I think he's actually a good
That's that's my take on that I wish him the best of
If you want to hear
Vim Hans
Hans was on the podcast in
2016 before he was kicked out of his job at Eric's
Senso
What episode number 56 you can actually hear him talk about iot and
And what matters
And that
No that doesn't include our show today
I was I was all excited but know we're going to talk about the wyze pan cam
Which is
My new toy
This is a
Camera
You do pay shipping and handling
Think so
But cheap camera
Lot of fun
All the functions of the wise to camso it
7 sorry
720 or
1080 HD
And it moves
It moves 93° up and down and it moves 360 degrees on the horizontal
It doesn't go around in a full circle it goes
Around all the way and then
Comes back the other way
And
The daytime video is about 15 frames per second
So it's
It's a little choppy but
Night vision
10 frames per second
Awesome night
And two way
Audio
Plus
14 days
Alert videos
So that's 14 days for free
Yay
And
The stuff is
Independent
Caption
They do use AES when
So it's not quite Bankrate
But pretty good
And there was question about where the data is stored where it goes I remember some
Listeners asking about that
And I think originally wise was working with a sum
Vendors in China but now
From a cloud perspective the date is all kept in the US the cameras are manufactured in China
And the
Why is people are really focused on the software experience their use
Razor thin margin
My stuff in the cloud stuff is hosted in
Aw
So these guys are former Amazon
Some software is built here
Stuff is hosted here
Karim rashid
So
That is
Really I mean
The overall
Experience with this is
Really good
But you can set it to track
Motion so
The camera will like pan wherever it sees motion which
Just totally
Be creepy
Just walk around your house
I'm some people did ask how loud the motor is
It is not that
And
The downside is this only works with wise and if
Services
So
This is not like a homekit thing this is
With anything else it's just those things right now
So
Yeah and then the same applies to the non pan-and-tilt version which is $10 less expensive
Which is the one I bought so
Very similar just you're getting
That creepy but cool tracking with the pinto
Yes and you can also set it up so it'll actually go through
Through
Traumatologist like
Goes around hits all four points
Of the circle
And you can actually set custom point
So
If there's something like in the way like a pillar if you can actually set your point
To not stop at the
Pellerin stop
So with a battery pack and a Roomba I could actually make a little robot that
Scans around the house
Yes this is wired so you plug it in
And
It can take an SD card
So you can store your stuff
On an SD card should you
And
That's the product I like it if you're in the market for a camera
I would say
This is really cheap it's really easy it doesn't do facial recognition or anything fancy but
30 minutes
So or 20 if you want the smaller one
Are the non moving
The non-motorized one
All right and now
Let's take a moment
To visit with the iot podcast listener hotline
Today the hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic lock
Schlage electronic locks offer unparalleled convenience and simplicity
All in their own right out of the box
So you don't have to have a smart home system
To benefit
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
And I should remind everyone that if you call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And leave a message before midnight Central Time on June 15th
That's Friday
So before Friday the night
You'll be entered to win my old ecobee SI thermostat
It is a lovely thermostat
It talks to everybody he wanted to talk to
And
Apna TV
Does not talk to
Just Google and Madam a
But
I like it
That will go out to you if you send us your question
Before midnight on Friday
This week's question comes from a nameless individual and covers for alarm system panel from quality
Hey want to know what you guys think of the
Qolsys IQ panel
They both
A lot of
Z-Wave and
Security compatibility yunnan compatibility for things like
Blood Centers in
Security sensors in
You know everything in addition to
Email to connect with alarm.com to do cameras and doorbell video cameras and
CCD getting a lot of attention but wanted to know your thoughts on it
Okay
Heaven
So
Should we talk about her suspicions first
Well I do find it interesting that there's no caller name and the
Phone area code comes from the same area code where qolsys is marketing department is it
Yeah it's still a good question and I learned a little bit about this panel which I have not heard about before you have though this is the IQ
IQ panel 2
Yes so there's two qolsys panels there's the first generation IQ panel and then there's the IQ panel
It's a good product
I'm I'm not going to say that it is not
A good product
There's a lot of caveat
But let's talk about some of the cool things about it the software looks
Really good it works with
Z-Wave stuff
And it also works with it
Proprietary line of sight
Take their
Has cellular backup
So yay
And it has Bluetooth disarming so
You can leave your phone in your pocket and
Disarm
So you don't have to enter your code
That sounds like a camera so you can see pictures
The people who try to
These are really nice feature
But
There's some
There's something
We don't love them
Such as
Will you have to choose your wireless service provider for the LTE backup in advance
I'm so if you ever change providers that's obviously an issue
So you can go three or four models one that works with Verizon
One that works with AT&T and one with Telus
Also you can install this as a DIY but you're going to need a service contract
For this to work
There's no actual app for this that we could find
So you
Send you actually to the alarm.com app
Which makes
Because alarm.com
Large.
Of
Monitor dolar
So
Probably your ideal forever
Can I get the business model they work with Distributors and dealers in
Service providers such as alarm.com and I'm so
My first thought of my always feels on Android
It's got Z-Wave it's got LCD Wi-Fi Bluetooth on like this could be My Hub
I went that's when we went searching for the app and found there's really no app for it you have to
UC
You know an alarm.com app and I have a subscription to that and so on so forth so
This is
I wouldn't self-install at this point because I can't do anything once I install it
It's a good Hub I have actually
The two
It's a it's a similar
Panel hub
Called
2gig
So
And I never used
Is it at all because
Cuz I don't have
Amana turtle
There's another tub
Called the zipatile by zapato
In a couple people have asked me about this this is
Z-Wave zigbee
Home control system
And that actually has its own app
It's about three hundred and eighty bucks
And
You know that might be a better option if
Keep that
Invite
Remember if you have a question for us we are happy to answer it at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And for the next day or two you will be entered to win an ecobee SI thermostat
Okay
Hey
Kevin I think that's enough for the news this week stay tuned for our guests Garrett Miller Chief digital officer
Current
He's going to be talking about business models for the industrial
An Enterprise iot and
What works in
Maybe what still needs a little bit more time to develop
This week sponsor is praetorian
Praetorian provides end-to-end iot security test
Helps organization
Balance risk with time-to-market
Praetorian Engineers help you strengthen this
Security of your iot products
From Chip
Cloud
Turn security into your competitive advantage
Third-party certification
Praetorian
The leaders
Microsoft recognize
Praetorian as best-in-class
So what do you think praetorian
Iot security
Check out the case study online 2
To see how praetorian
Strength of acid
Security vazaios
Stacey on iot
Jd.com
/ 6
That Stacey on iot. Cam security
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Garrett Miller
The chief digital officer
Officer
Buy GE
Hello Garrett are you doing
I'm even while Stacy how are you
Super great thank you so much for coming on the show I remember the
The formation of
Current way back
My gosh was it
That's right yeah we're we're coming up on three years here
Okay so before we get started let's tell everybody
What it is
Set current
Show current is a the business within GE we're born of our lighting businesses
Transition to an LED business
I so we use LEDs as an opportunity to lead into our customers
And follow that very quickly with a digital offering to create what we call and intelligent environment
Okay that sounds super exciting
Let's drive a little bit deeper in
When you guys formed
Current
It was a
Understanding that both lighting
Easy way to get into
Businesses
Because everyone was
Transitioning over to
But also
Opportunities
Not just
Lighting
Power generation
And other services
SoCal
How all of that works
Together is part of
Absolutely
So we find
Our conversations with our customers often times most the time I would say
Really start with LEDs
Which is a great way to get in and save about
Your electricity cost
As it relates to lighting
So that is a really good starting point for conversation with a customer around energy energy
Efficiency Energy savings the carbon emissions associated with that and what we do very quickly from there
Transition the conversation from one Focus solely on lighting
The one that's looking really more holistically at
Complete building envelope so being able to access monitor and improve the efficiency of the
Operations of all building subsistence are going from lighting and hcac to plug load
And so forth
So we do that in a really interesting way so we'll go in and as I said we lead with lighting from there
People then get pretty interested in managing the rest of their building subsystem
And so what we do is put in place
Edge technology that allows us to tap into the different assets that exist
Ennis in a particular customers environment
Or to go in and augment
That environment
And so often times a place that people start is with lighting controls
We need use a monitor describe our architecture
Call that we refer to as open on the top and open on the bottom
And if we really start with that open on the bottom concept the key word there is really interoperability
So we can go in and leverage whatever type of edge infrastructure investment our customers have made
If they have existing sensors or controllers and place
We can reuse those
If they don't have existing infrastructure we can certainly put that in as as part of the
Appointments
Sweet hurry holistically sense and control does building environments to drive energy
Efficiency musing are all Sites
Application is a cloud-based application
Idolizes to not only gain insights but to develop
Optimization
Strategies as well as been pushed control back to the edge across an entire Enterprise portfolio
And it seems like this came along
Just the right time
Using
Lightning is away
Control
Thanks and I say this
Because LEDs are so efficient
Any company that was making lights
Suddenly had this
Moment of life
Holy cow we're selling these bulbs that are going to last forever and now we've got a
Switch our business model.
Cuz selling light bulbs that died
Every
20 years
It's very different
Was partially a response to turning
Product business
Listen to a service
Yeah that's right and I think you're exactly right LEDs have really turned
It really changed the the industry so they're really great for people like you and I infer for our customer
What are there cities or building
Have you said they use 50% less energy but they do tend to last quite a bit longer which is a big part of the volume
Position in addition to the Energy savings that did put us down the path of trying to reimagine what can we
Now I think LED is is in a good spot you know when we talk about the LED conversion process that's happening
Out there the industry today
We like to say we're somewhere in the second inning so I think there's still a lot of Runway left
As it relates to getting in there and helping customers have better Energy Efficiency better lighting solutions through LED
It's certainly as we start to look at the evolution of our business model
Digital is played a big role in that so we talked a bit about the Energy Efficiency components
That are part of the business model
What we're now doing the same that's a really good place to start but there's a lot more that we can do to add value
Due to our customers
If we think about using
That digital infrastructure that I described earlier as a way to deliver energy-efficiency
You can also flip that into live there other types of business
Productivity outcomes
For our customers using that same infrastructure
The way that we do that
Insta take all of that data all those insights that were capturing in generating created
Stream those out to a 3rd party ecosystem
So we've recognized our customers of recognize the value of that data coming back to that idea
Open on the top and look on the bottom is open on the top really means that the data that were capturing
Is
Readily accessible by our ecosystem or directly by our customers
And that opens up tremendous opportunity for customers to go and do things like space utilisation or
Retail Analytics
Or workflow management in industrial environment really a preamble set of opportunities
I know it's so cool
So when your customers start understanding
What they can do with this
Are they doing it
You guys are they doing it is a
Pull from
Other platform
Azar software
Cuz this gets into this
Iot is an ecosystem
And I feel like
It's such a vast ecosystem right now.
People are unaware of the
Potential of some
The things they can
What they can do
So how do you guys cut
Market
To that
With your partner's out
Yeah so we approach it with our partners absolutely hand-in-hand and I think you hit on a couple of different trends
Are happening out there that people are really starting to wrap their heads around about what they do about it
So one of the really wonderful statistics out there in the world of Statistics is this
By 2020 you'll have about seven and a half billion connected business in points
In this whole iot world and that's growing at about a 33% kegger from today
Which means there's a tremendous amount of intelligence
It's being created and I think our customers are starting to realize
Hey this all of this data out there is really great but we actually have to be able to do something with it and so what we've
Recognizing what we readily admit is this
We look at all of that data where we do a really good job of capturing it of transforming it of making it avail
Edible and using it ourselves to our own software applications
To deliver Energy Efficiency
We recognize though that the opportunity so that data to deliver other types of outcome is is real
Satan bound
We go hand-in-hand with our partners in our ecosystem to go to our customers to help highlight
Like the opportunity of leveraging
A single digital backbone to create not on the Energy Efficiency opportunities
It also business productivity opportune
And the way that I see the market evolving right now is that
You have customers who understand that value proposition that this whole
Connected in points the the growing iot space is going to create lots of opportunities for the
Historically for customers that have been forward-looking and and and identify that opportunity
They really put in place Point Solutions
The cast of the data to power the individual applications at their interest in pursuing
What we do though is something that's quite a bit different
So think of it almost feels like
The mobile phone for your building or the mobile phone for your city and you've got a single set of Interest
Structure that can be leveraged the power
Any number of
Actual software applications to deliver different types of outcomes to our customers and so
We absolutely do that hand in hand with the with our partners that leverage that data to deliver those other types of business
Productivity outcomes
Okay and you mentioned that you got you think that
That lighting
Is it second in
So I'm very curious
Where you see
This going
And how far baby
A part of this
Throw in there
Some of your competitors in
Lighting space
Also
Just made some
Acquisition
Osram body
Lumens
Siemens jobs
Enlighted
Both of these
They seem to be catching on to this trend and so
Where do you see it
It going
Where We Are
Yeah so I think the market is really going to evolve pretty rapidly I think it's in the next couple of years where we
Reduce the other people identifying this opportunity which would take it as a great compliment
We did our own acquisition of daintree which was at its core a
Serves as the foundation for our intelligent building
Portfolio particularly to the edge technology
It was really born out of a lighting controls play
But it allows you to tap into hundreds and hundreds
Literally thousands of types of devices out there to deliver whatever type of outcome someone's interested in whether that's like
Controls HD AC controls or
People counting
And I think we start to see more of our competitors going in that direction as well
Well I think one of the really important parts as this industry evolved
Other people are going to identify as
It needs to be an interoperable
Open system to be able to take advantage of all of the new innovation all the new technology
Whether that's a new sensor type whether that's a
A new software application
The making sure that from an in customer perspective
They have a single
Digital backbone that they'll be able to leverage into whatever type of business outcome they ultimately wanted to cheat with
Whether that's something they want to do today
Next year or five years from now they've got to make sure that they've got a system
To allow them to flex and grow as we all discover what the future brings
Okay
Let's talk about
How you guys
Pair for that
On the business side
You are a chief digital officer
When current
First came out
It was a slightly different
Opposition
There's talk about price
Things based on
The Energy savings off
And I feel like it's
It shifted
Bearden ever-changing world so that makes sense so where are you guys
Today when it come
Pricing
Where do you think
Could want
Yasso current has been a story of evolution and transformation absolutely when we
Said the company was really very much focused almost exclusively around the energy play
Which was really interesting and you started to think about some really far Out Concepts as it relates to Birch
Power plants
Peer-to-peer energy trading and how do you pull in things like that how do you price those types of offerings
Switch because not a lot of time talking about that
By itself I think we're wheelsamillion landed was that those types of markets
Are going to be a little bit
Farther Along before they fully mature
Which is fine I think we're positioning ourselves really nicely to be the behind-the-meter in points
To play in those types of business models in this hexoskin does Market opportunities
When they come to fruition
But in the interim we're running the are intelligent environments play which is also an interesting time
Business modeling and pricing scheme so are we mentioned that you have a mobile phone as
It is an analogy for how our model works and I come back to that n**** just
I'm break it down a little bit more
Where if you think of the mobile phone is as your Edge Hardware that's something that people are used to consume and then
Game 4 and they buy it they own it it's it's their phone or in our case it's it's our sensors controls Gateway
So far the service is pisto that sits on top of that I think is where it starts to become really interesting and
You know if you would step back and just look at technology Evolution over the last
And yours are so I think we're not in a spot where
People are very comfortable with with service offerings in particular software-as-a-service so when we think about the business
It's fine that we now all the sudden have
A recurring annuity that gets put in place
I'm with the different applications that are being purchased for those are things that we built ourselves like also
Whether there's a partner applications that our customers are going to ultimately be consuming
In this model I'm going to test how far we can take
Take this analogy
If I am a building owner and I buy
Relating to Center
Where's the Gateway
In many cases this is technology
It's going to be bought
Two maybe three
So think about it from that in
There is some replacement Happening Here
But it becomes much more
For you to also have
Something on the services side
The business
Yeah that's right I think swing back to that the hardware piece of then we can go Services next
I think I'm Hardware side the nice thing about it is that you're not just buying a single iPhone and stick in your building
Replace it when the next iPhone comes out what's really nice about having the open architecture is that you can
Upgrade
Your Edge hardware for the building you can upgrade the quote-unquote mobile phone for your building as new techno
Knology comes online so you're essentially future proofing your Edge architecture by putting in place.
Interoperable
Capabilities
In-N-Out on the services side
There's going to be continued Innovation as it relates to the different types of applications that come
I'm online and leverage. Data whether that's the date of this being created and generated today
Or if you look forward you know couple years down the road when
The new whiz-bang sensor comes online that nobody's even thought of today
I ain't coming back to you if you've got an interoperable open Edge platform that can take that in
Consume it now all the sudden you can access that new type of data
Let's go into this
The idea of increasing size
Occasionally
What kind of flight current started out
Because
I loved it cuz I'm a journal
I love that it was so forward
Cool and like all my God is amazing I can see the future
I can see why people were like
So how do you
Get the market
Get ready for that
How do you know
Time and do you have a
Evolve what you sell
Into some
Like that
That's a lot of questions of
But it's basically how do we get for
From here which is in a
Crazier in
So I'm glad you agree I think we're crazy cool what's happening now and I think
Even brighter
Is simply Market preparedness and bringing customers along with the journey and
Evolution
A couple years ago if you were to go into a customer and you'd say
Okay are we going to do an LED retrofit you know half the time the customer would say well I'm not so sure
And now when you go in everybody recognizes hey doing LED is no brainer and saves 50% of my
My lighting energy it's got a tutu for your payback
And it makes a ton of sense to go do
I would say we're in a similar point where the LED Market was a couple years ago
Today as a relates to the digital adoption cycle where
Not every customer is convinced it's something that they need to do that said I think we'll give this a bit of an advantage and
Co-op from a market adoption perspective is it
Number of the types
Solutions as a relates to the software applications that we want to enable
Are out there today and people are consuming them
What we're doing is giving them the real-time data that makes those Solutions even more powerful even more
More valuable to our customers
And do you think you'll ever
Reach that
Partnership
What kind of role
Where you're sharing
Swear you're actually really moving the needle
Consumption
Yeah you know I think the other all of these ideas around as a service models that will pop up
Which I think fits into a little bit what you're talking about there but do you think about energy as a service or space suit
Realization of the service
There's a lot of really interesting models that are coming up and is part of those new models are coming online
Customers are looking at shared-risk models to go along with it so you know as an example of
Are there a lot of s goes out there
Energy Services companies
It will go in and and their business model is to take a portion of the savings energy saver
The day enable for their customers
Not today that's not a model that we are are
Lighting you're pursuing it's really something that we've taken a look at and I think
And we'll have to see how the market evolves in terms of where is that right balance
Perspective simply
Giving the tools and enabling the capabilities but ultimately up to the customer to achieve their own outcome
I or will it evolve into something where
Your service is really starts take over and it's
The outcome that's being delivered as opposed to the tools to do it it's going to be interesting to see how eyeballs
Man is it I am excited to see
IFit app
You and me both
I would be remiss if I did not ask you
Cuz GE right now
Is in the headlines
With all kinds of
Selling assets left and right
Kinds of drama and a lot of that seems associated with it
Digital transformation
And so
GE lighting and
Current are both
For sale
So I just wanted to find out
From you
Where that process is
And understand
Did ge's transformation is that
Formation of
Well I'd say a couple of things no one right now GE is really needing to
To go through eye refocusing exercise
And where they've landed is to say there are going to be three core businesses for GE going for lb 80
Jason Aldean
Healthcare in OB power and current today doesn't fit into that
Inside configuration
So we're going out on our own as it works income will be finding new home over the next couple of court
Which were excited about
I think she is got to focus right now they don't have time and effort and resources to focus on current so will be
Going to a place
It does have that capability and capacity in uniform it from a digital transformation perspective I think
Is really led the way for GE we are the first
Truly digital industrial business with Angie's portfolio where we are enabling new types of
Outcomes by combining both
The historic Hardware business in this case lighting and augmenting that to create new types of business model
Those with the digital capabilities that we've been discussing their so we're really a first in that regard and we're really excited about
Stop taking that Ford in a new device
Alright thanks so much for coming on the show to talk about all this
My pleasure thank you for having me
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week