Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And this week
We have a suspect
Tacular show
For you we are going to be talking about all the news
WWDC that matters
We are going to be talking about madam
Amazon
Digital assistant getting on PC
Smart sensor Kickstarter project
Maybe worth a look
We've got updates on Microsoft they have got this great smart building software they've been
And
Kevin and I have been purchasing gadgets and applications that
You may find you
So I guess this week
We're taking things too
A little artistic level
She is Anya
Chapala with synth Babe Records
And she's going to talk to us about bringing iot into musical performances
We also talked about VR AR end because you can't have it
Blockchain into
We got all of this
From our sponsor
Praetorian
More
So let's kick it off
With a message from another one of our spa
This week sponsor is Bosch interested in all things iot the Bosch connected World blog
Covers a wide range of iot topics from around the world such as industry 4.0 Mobility Smart Home
Black and a jack check out blog. Bosch - s i.com for
Articles case studies interviews and more I read this blog on the regular and
I will tell you guys I love it it has some
Very useful case studies in thought processes on iot this is not a typical corporate
Blog at all highly good
Okay
Kevin
You
You watched
All of WWE
Yeah I kind of
I had it going on in the background
Work cell
We're going to rely on your take
Most of this
So let's talk about the biggest news
From this I was just
Frankly I was too not just cuz I invested about
2 hours and 15 minutes waiting for something really exciting but
When they finally got to talk about Siri at home kits a little bit of a letdown
Granted
This is their developer event they being Apple
So they focused on software this time around no new hardware whatsoever talk about
IOS
Os10
TV OS
Aaron's
Hof I forgot I forgot about that
I wear that every waking moment yes I forgot about that
But homepod was only mentioned one time and passing first of all so there's nothing to say there
Hands
Siri yes they did talk about Siri
And I wrote up my thoughts
The blog and I said she got smarter
But not in the way you might have
Or maybe you had hoped
They're still a knowledge.
Between Siri and the offerings from Amazon and Google I don't see much
List. Forward there maybe half a step forward
It was more about
The usefulness of Siri in your everyday life which is good
They introduced this was the big feature
What is shortcut
And
If you're familiar with
If this then that it's very similar to
Shortcuts
What you can do is you can
Record a
Trigger phrase
Or Siri
And
When you say that phrase you can actually configure
Siri to do any number of things
Using various apps and services on your phone
Which is kind of cool the demo was kind of neat with a woman on stage said
Heading home and she had pre-configured that phrase to
Fire up
Apple Maps and find the quickest way home and to send a message to everybody home saying I'm on my way home then
Fire up the radio station so she can listen to NPR on her phone
In her car
Do one or two other things that she oh she said her own thermostat
The 7D young and so on
Kind of cool
And again reminds me of if this and that and also how
Homekit sets up the automation very much
Drag-and-drop kind of experience
This actually reminds me a lot of this is actually something I've built using both stringify and yonomi plus goo
Yes
So yes
Extra
Software platform player I guess you could actually do this
Yourself
Using any number of other
Yeah it's funny you mention that because you want to know what the first thought I had was when I saw this
What was the
I recall specific memories
Setting up
Microsoft
Voice command
Where you would record a voice command
I pocket PC in 2001
And we can figure that to do certain things
Scranton you can do nearly the things that you can do today backwards
That's exactly what they were
Yes
And I thought of that and then the other thing I thought of was
Shouldn't be assistant
ELearning
And
Know what my habits are in just set the configuration of sort of for me like surfaces at these kind of things
And to be fair
Siri will start doing more of that they did
Show
Circus Casino if you constantly go to the gym at 5 p.m. everyday and you open a particular running app like
Which I do not
Everyday at 5 but whatever
Eventually Siri will
See that you are there and before you even open the app it'll say hey looks like you're at the gym ready to start running at 4
It'll save you a Tapper 2
It just felt weird because the assistance were supposed to be getting smarter but in this case
You're teaching
Siri to get smarter on your own you have to configure it
And I wonder how many people are really going to take full advantage of this
How many Siri users
I don't think it's going to catch on where everybody's going to be using us who has an iPhone
I just don't see it I'm actually curious cuz like you can do this with routines
Or I think it's routines in Amazon's world and in
And I've set up
A couple but
You know they're kind of
Pain
You have extra thing the whole point of the assistant is it supposed to do things
For you know this is kind of like programming your assistant salary
Simple fashion in a way that anybody can do but you're absolutely right these are like routines and in fact
One smart thing apple is done here is
The way you
Do this you have to link your apps with Siri and
Siri hasn't worked
Tremendously well with a lot of third-party apps Oye Apple for opening it up
And now you can link your app so that way another stage demo was a
Can't find my keys
Shortcut for you say that
And because you linked
Siri Twitter
Tile app
Siri would Buzz the tile Bluetooth tracker for you and pop up the app
So that's good but
I don't know it is since
Apple is not going the
Amazon Google route with skills or actions and routines it's just using apps for those purposes I think
Yes and a friend of mine who's a Big Sur
Supporter of
Apple products
He pointed out that learning is really tough
And when you get it wrong it irritates
People in that actually brought me back to and I wrote about this but seeing Google's
Head of connected speaker products mark space
And he talked about
You know when you're doing
An AI model
If you're doing it for what he called a corrective experience so that's when a motion sensor doesn't detect motion for a while and it turns off the light
Automatically
It is a black at 85% confidence interval
Because it's really annoying when you
Sitting there in a room
And if you're actually going to start something
Lectern like
I'm going home turn on the oven or order a pizza
And it has real world applications that are
Kind of bigger than just waving your hands around
Then you got to have like 5 9
Which is why a lot of
Black people fight with their advice
Like learning thermostats
Can I come see you know apple does not want to build
Sprite
Right
Yeah that makes sense
The only other
Aspect that our listeners might be interested in
The Apple home app which is typically on iOS devices
Will also be available on Mac OS 10 this fall
With OS 10 Mojave
And that should be out
What they tested for
Suspect September issue
The public beta will
Probably kick off soon so
You'll be able to have a home on your Mac
Yay
I could actually play with it
Without but you wouldn't get to your fence
No no you have Siri built into the Mac already and then you would gain access
Your back was always
What's a good question they did not mention that didn't talk really about
Remote access and hubs and all that which I was actually hoping for him and they did have a whole Apple TV bin I was like oh please
Suzuki DRZ way radios in a new version
Didn't discuss
Sub-Zero
Okay
So that was what was new on
WWDC
That was very muted
You know I know we weren't expecting
All right so let's talk about
Homekit is coming to a computer
Are you suppose
Pacifically a map
And Madame
Amazon
Echo assistant
Is coming to a PC
Near you
Kevin what do you think
Well I think it's
Candida have these assistants
In and around
Us everywhere you can have in your home and such to me this is kind of
Probably
Something Microsoft is not too happy about because they want Cortana and all their Windows machines
Big partnership with him
Exactly exactly what Amazon is taking play out of Microsoft
Display book now because they work
Three different odms original design manufacturers
PCS
Compound quanta in Wichita and they all
Create PCS for PHP sadelle's and song they build them
What they have is for
Actual
Windows PCS that have Madame a built-in
And this will lead
Hardware makers just
Work with these designs and just have Madam a integrated automatic
Play there's nothing they'll have to do so there is one PC and three laptops that will cover makers can choose from
To build off of
I will have matinee
I think it's good I just I don't think
Yeah because they were trying to make this weird fine line that that I
Originally think was strange between
Matinee
Cortana
And Cortana was for business and Padme was for home
But even figuring out what was what
Didn't make sense
This would be a more Nativity
Screen Sunday Cortana asking
Padme to do something you know s
One assistant asking another so this would probably be a better
Amazon experience
What would help
I would hope
One of these days
You know what these are just
Again neither like design
Reference models
So
It's going to be up to Acer vs. Lenovo HP Dell etcetera to decide if they're going to use these
Reference models are not so I don't know if or when we'll see these
All right
And
In the
Maybe more exciting
World of crazy connect
The gadgets you can buy you found
A sensor that
I've seen it
You thought it was
Yeah we have seen
This type of sensors before this is a Kickstarter project
It has 8 days to go it's only halfway to its goal and if it's
Not funded all the way it's not happening it's one of those All or Nothing which is actually good
If it doesn't happen if you back that you'll get your money back this is called the oval and it's actually the second generation over
Basically it's a small 5 in 1 sensor
It can measure or tell you about motion
Light temperature
Water or humidity no video camera no microphone Rising like that there's no subscription fees
You just kind of stick these anywhere you want
There's a little Gateway device of these things can talk to each other before the show station I were comparing pricing to
Something similar I think it was the notion you would said yes it's the notion sensors there
Colorado company
You can find them on Amazon or at their website getting ocean.com and
Pizza been out for a while they're just circular sensors that
To measure a bunch of
Different stuff temp
Humidity water
They don't measure light but they have a decibel tracker so they can measure things like
Glass breaking in that sort of
Right you know if you already have a smart home setup these are probably not for you I would say these are in fact
Ovals campaign is targeting apartment renters Airbnb host
In a roommate at College Maybe
Pricing isn't
Terrible you can literally get one sensor
And one
Gateway for 99 bucks
Join two sensors it's 129 price goes up from there
It was interesting to me I mean that they run on a coin cell battery so you don't
I have to really worry about that for about 6 months you just stick them anywhere you want there's double-sided tape included
Is subscription fees there's an app for
For IOS and Android
You obviously get push notifications but it can also send text or even emails
If you'd rather get notified of things that weigh
Integration wise
Currently only with if this then that
They are looking at homekit certification but they are saying upfront you know it's kind of costly so may not have
Okay
Yes and
Notion the other
Desensitize most reminded me of this is an Kevin the one that came and found us a novel
Do not have an if
Integration they do work with nest
So
You know you can actually like
Detect temperature and then turn on your
Air conditioner
Yay
That's where they are
Let's talk about kind of
Some fun little bit
7 News
Sweet got Lenovo smart display that Kevin and I are both really excited about these are the Google Assistant smart display
Well I can
Pre-order it now
Doesn't shift
Well I'm going to make it even sadder because
The LINQ
Was working before the show
And now
Page is down for pre-orders
Sounds to me like in this is B&H Photo
Yeah sounds to me like that went up a little early and they
Gave away the shipping date or rough
Estimation of when it will be available which was September 3rd so I don't know
What the deal is but
We haven't heard squat about this
Mustang shipping
What is the first time in the summer
So
Technically
Now it's right after
It's still summer so yeah
All right you know I can't hold it could be
This is not just a standard smart display running on Android wasn't this
We later found out Android things
That could be part of the issue
Find
Let's get business
Microsoft
New iot core services
What are they Kevin
This will make you happy because they already announced the iot core products so the services at their nothing today provides
10 years of Windows OS support through the windows long-term service Channel
And
Obviously that means you have
Your devices will be support for 10 years but also if you're using that release you won't get feature updates
But that's not a bad thing because that will let you focus on stability if your device make
So that's good in this is actually super important in the industrial
Where patches
Can break like
Everything
If your patching a piece of equipment that's like
Gear manufacturing processes
Dependent on
You know you're looking at
Millions hundreds of thousands of dollars of lost Revenue if your line goes down I mean this is
For most of us in the consumer world were like I'd hate to have this but a lot of these big Industrial
Companies are Enterprises that
Epcot
A lot of things set up on
Or if your medical device manufacturer you don't want it like sending update to the FDA this kind of stability is
Really am
In Microsoft gets it
This is why
Azure cloud is doing
Sowell in Microsoft iot services
I wish that they had
More customers to talk about they still using the same reference customers in Sam George at Microsoft had told me
This is partially because a lot of customers are trying things out and if it works
It's so good for them that they don't want to share
And if they're kind of like I don't know what to do with it yet
Tentative
Stan pilot Purgatory for
I agree with you but I did notice I was very happy to see it that one of those customers using this
Misty robotics
Yes yes they are they were at build
Actually that's where I
Yeah
Two other things with this slick or Services they it works with Microsoft device Update Center so that way
Is your centralized way too controlling and send out updates as needed you can even Target a small group of devices
Testing updates that's good and then they have device
Health attestation
So you can enable the trustworthiness of a device at boot time
Free trusted iot system so that is awesome
That is
Okay
Also
From Redmond Microsoft announced
This week that they are
They don't have a name for the service yet but
We'll call it
Spatial intelligence
So understanding of where things are in a building
So they released this
They actually showed off
Kind of a sense of this at build
A few weeks ago
When they did a conference room demo in the conference room understood who was in the room
Based on their ID that
And kind of
Where other people were in the building
So that was pretty cool
This is the service that enables this and it can do things like detect occupancy it can understand
If you have tags on furniture it can understand what Furnitures and what rooms and
All kind of
It understand how people move around the building and interact with
With the space
This is going to freak a lot of pee
If your employers like
Hey
Why aren't you in the office more
Do you spend all your time at the bathroom or at the water cooler that might
You know you might be like
But the goal is to understand how buildings are used
Where stuff is if employer needs it you know you're like I did the paper cutter
Where is it
We had this issue
Newsroom speech
From home person I love this
No, I'll never be monitored
Is my points
Well actually so you used to have
Used to have this idea when we were at gigaom together where you wanted to tie your chair
Your butt being in your chair to your I am status
Yeah see people would know when I'm available when I'm not
So you can do said yes
I was being facetious there's a lot of cool applications for the Senate when I was at Google we worked on the smart office
Projects in spare time
This is very cool stuff
Yes and her customers using it are Steelcase
And CBRE
Which is a
Huge
CB Richard Ellis
It's just a bunch of
Just a bunch of letters
Real estate
I'm a little surprised that maybe they are using this but I'm a little surprised that Microsoft
Seems to have abandoned all the technology that it Acquired and invested in with the Xbox Kinect
Yeah so they actually in the
Gemo
And this was a big thing at Microsoft build they had you know where the polycom speaker
Conference Center was
Cone and I wonder if
The connect
Hardware could be in the cold
Everyone was like what's in the cold
Nobody knows
So
They may not have a band
We'll just have to see where it
I mean they would be silly not to
Incorporate some
Pretty high bandwidth
Data so
True Faith at one point
Maybe
I mean I have to use all of the
Sensors you know the cameras and such
Time to do what they need to do
I remember after I bought the Kinect
They actually had an SDK
Kinect SDK for Windows and I was using it to kind of
Create a way to turn my lights on when I walked in my office when The Connect saw me and will not miss this goes back quite a ways
But all the pieces of the puzzle were there
Make a list
Who knows
And finally
Find a little bit of news Sierra Wireless has
Launched a new version of it
Mango
Open source
Hardware platform
For industrial iot
And so
The mango yellow is the new
Device it is a super sensor
The mango yellow has
14 sensors and actuators on board
Which is
Yeah
And it will function with
A wide variety of cellular-based low-power wide area networks such as cat M1 and nb-iot
So this joins the mango
Red and green Prada
That are out
And basically it's just got
More sensor
This is used by companies who want to try to build and prototype
Connected devices
Business processes
So you can buy a couple of these Papa around your manufacturing facility if you want and see like
What does it make sense to measure here
That's what these are
Pretty cool
And
The mango yellow
Is not going to be available though until May 2019
And now
Kevin and I are going to share things that we have spent our own money on
You spent more
I spent a lot more so I spent $99 on an aware glow this is a
Really interesting products that I've actually been looking at this company that used to make it bigger one there's a new one coming so the
Old one is being discounted
It was like $200 now it looks like
It might be on sale
If you get one but you may not want to get one cuz there's a new one coming out or you can spend
$99
And get
The glow which is what I did
It measures
Chemicals in the air so vocs in the air
Humidity
Temperature
And also carbon dioxide
And
I got it because I wanted to test the air quality in the Portables in my daughter's school
Because she has classes in them and she says it's so hot and stuffy
And I was trying to get data to like
Understand
How hot and stuffy
And the school allowed that which is awesome
He did now I had a hard time connecting it to their Network
So this is a Wi-Fi product
Power products they just pop it in and the coolest thing is they have a
Pass-through
Plug so
You do take up an outlet
When you plug this in
But you can plug other things in it and
Also acts as a smart
Plug even cooler is
In the app you can actually pick
Like if you plug in a fan
Or a humidifier
Dehumidifier
Or in my case
Air purifier
You tell it what you plugged in and it will automatically turn that device on
When it's needed
So if the temperature gets too high and it knows there's a fan plugged in
Intuit it'll automatically turn the fan
I think that's
This is basically in
This is good for anybody who's got who like lives in a New York City Apartment
Or has
Window air conditioning
You can actually take your old window air conditioning unit
Plug it into this and tell it hey
When the temperature gets above 90 degrees
Turn the sucker rod
Or
If you don't want that to happen cuz
At work all day you can also sets
I think it's a really nice mode
I'm not 100% sure it does not tell me how many parts
Vermillion is measuring for the boc
Short interest
There's a lot of
How sensitive these really are but it is very good for noticing
That's what I have to ask
What was the trend in the classroom
So because I had a hard time getting it on the Wi-Fi network I never actually got in
But I can tell you
It's right now in my car
Kitchen when I cook
Holy cow
I really should leave Italy
That is what yeah
I know
I can save you $99 and just tell you to do that
Fair
I should also say you can set preferences if this is kind of fun
It will tell you your air is bad with a little glowing light on the device or it will also send you a new
Vacation if you will
But you can set different priorities
With you basically tell the device
Like allergies aren't
To me so it will tell you
It's a little bit more sensitive to
Humidity
Chemicals if you want productivity
Carbon dioxide in the air
Becomes
Born critic
So I think it's a really fun product
For $99
They've got a promotion right now going on Spring 10
And then you get like
10% off which again
Huge but nice
I like it
So smart plugs
Also tracks my hair
Very nice sell it works with a bunch of other devices like Madam a
And I think
Hey
So I spent a whopping $2.99
As for my
Hey Big Spender
Yeah but I had to I had to have this
I'll tell you why
Because I couldn't believe it was true
Seriously
I found an app
For my Apple watch
But apparently allegedly
Reportedly
Put some anime
On my wrist
I'm thinking no way Applewood never allowed
Just can't work not possible
Turn off
It works
I'm not going to say it works
The way you would hope and I'll explain why in a second but it does work so
The name of the app is voice in a can
And maybe we can put a link in the show notes not just maybe to the app in appstore but also to a video demo
Tattoo developer
Chose
It works
Basically this is really clever
You open the app on your watch and I have a complication on my watch that is a shortcut to it so I have to tap the watch obviously
And then I also have to
Tap the screen to
Tell the watch to start listening
So now I say my
I don't have to say Madam a I just
And I say my command
That information that sound bite is then sent to Amazon servers just like any other Echo device
And she responds and does or does whatever I've commanded
You know just like you would to an echo
So there's a little bit of lag in terms of the back-and-forth communication
And the fact you have to tap the screen
But it does work now and that it's not unbearable lag I mean it's just
Not as quick as using an actual Amazon product so
I'm impressed it does what it says it does and I did not think it would
That is rare in the
Yes very true
And now it is
Alright listener hotline
And guys
Andros
We are still doing a giveaway I am giving away my
SI thermostat
So this is not the cool looking ecobee that
And if they launched in response to Nest but it is a perfectly good
Connect a thermostat
It talks to Madame a and Google assistant and has a lovely ecobee app
So you'll
You got all the benefits in just
An older model thermostat
So that is what we are giving away if you leave a voicemail at 5 1/2
2/4
And this week's voicemail comes to us from Dan in Charlotte
Hi Stacy and Kevin
This is dance with Charlotte
I got to be honest I am really struggling
Smart lighting
You both know a lot about the space
Stacy particular seems
Smart lighting
Chinato
I've thus far stayed away from Smart bulbs
Because balls are expensive and they put the burden on my wife and Young
Kids
Not to touch the wall switches
SmartThings user I've already installed about 5
GE smart
Which is around the house
Delete my basic GE smart switches I can schedule lights to go on and off
SmartThings
Turn on off groups of Lights
For example when we're going to bed
I am planning out a bunch more switches
And so I wonder what I'm missing out on
Should I honestly consider smart bulb
With Lutron caseta
For switches
Be much better for me than my tea
East Witches
What else would I want to
Regularly do
Gianna current GE smart
Switch features
Thanks very much for the recommendation
Oh damn
I kind of wish I knew a little bit more about your light switch but we are going to guess that it is the GE Z-Wave either
Either the demo
Switch or the on-off switch
If it is the on-off switch
I'm going to recommend you go for
Dimmer switches
I am not going to recommend you go for
Car bulbs
Unless you are doing
Actual
Lamps
Between lamps and bulbs
Perfectly except
But in terms of getting more
Out of switches if you are happy with those switches
Then I see keep going
I will say by switch of choice
Is the Lutron caseta
Only because
Cuz
With the Lutron
Hub they will work with homekit
And
A bunch of other
Site Google
Padme SmartThings
Wink
Yes so if that sort of like level of future-proofing and interoperability is important to you
Then
Yes gopher
That when you sell your house I would recommend in that case you sell the Lutron caseta Hub with it and then they
Nature's can do it
What they want
With the current
GE things you probably
It's going to be hard to convince someone to use SmartThings you know what I'm saying
It's a little tough
But those are really the only thing certain Kevin can you think of
Things that he's missing out on by
Going or sticking with it
GE
Either dimmers I would go with dimmers over the switch
Right because that way
Ciq the bulb route because I do lamps more than overhead lights and such in my family is trained that they'll get a small
Small electric shock if they touch any switches in the house
I can't think of anything the only other thing I would consider and I don't know if
The investment is worth it
We talked about a couple of switches and light sets that will kind of create the scenes for you
Things like new
Citracal that's the one
Noon does an in this is better for open floor plan
Plants this is not good for like individual rooms but
If you uninstall
And actually someone else will come out in
Install a bunch of noon switches for
Then they create they have a lighting designer whose pre-configured a bunch of options like movie time
This is what all the lights should do
Movie time
Some other things to think about
Lutron bought a company called catcher that also does this
So we may see that coming to luchon
Baby
I'm guessing maybe it would be nice but
I'm not holding my breath
And then only other thing that you might want is
There's a couple light switches that have like motion sensors
And ecobee4 example has a $99 light switch that has a motion sensor and Madame Abe
Belton
If that's appealing to you
Pretty expensive if you're going to replace a bunch of them
I don't know if I'd go there
But you got those do exist
And I couldn't help solve the whole
Use the switch or not use the switch
Issue because you got the motion sensor and they're granted
A little more than two times
The price of
The ge's that you have but
You know when you get mad at me so
Easy way to put an assistant in a room without buying another
Device itself another Standalone device
Make your bathroom
All right please order more Charmin
Instant delivery please
I need a drone
Potty humor who knew
Okay
The iot podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage electronic lock
Schlage electronic locks can make life so much easier and more
No more keeping track of extra house keys each member of your family can have their own access
To see what's possible visit Schlage
Dot-com
And now
Stay tuned for our guest
Anya trybala
Which synth Babe Records talking about how iot can change music performance and
How technology
Can really
Change the equation
For artists
Stay tuned for that
But before we get there
Let's hear a message from our sponsor praetorian
Praetorian provides end-to-end iot security testing that helps organizations balance risk with time tomorrow
Market pressures praetorian Engineers help you strengthen the security of your iot products from
From Chip to Cloud
Turn security into your competitive Advantage by earning a third-party certification
Praetorian the leaders in iot secure
Microsoft has recognized praetorian as Best in Class
So when you think praetorian
Think iot security Expo
Check out the case study online to see how poor
Praetorian help Samsung strength of the security of its iot
By visiting Stacey on iot. Com
/ security
That Stacey on iot
Dot-com
/ security
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
I know tribe who performs as
Nanoosh and every couple months I like to bring someone who is an artist on the show to talk about how the internet if
Things in technology can transform art
And I ran into her at
An event in Sweden
And I'm super excited to have
Overcome talk about everything that she's doing
Taipei RB are connected suits
NBA
So hi Anya how are you doing today
I'm good we have some
Suisun finally
Sweden
Very exciting
Let's get this started I saw you
Perform in this connected suit
The created a
Virtual
Polar bear
On stage at an event and you saying
You danced
Polar bear dance
List with you
On the screen it was a really surreal in
Cool experience talk to me about
That performance in how it all came together
Quick Lacy with J which is a digital media
I'm usually from Melbourne Australia
And we connected about a year ago
They help
As the first time I Tibet
Try the glass
AR
Stances that kind of stuff
It's kind of been in the back of my mind
Do something as an extension of the music that I could use
Again about
She wants to know something and
We had this amazing Workshop actually
Basically with all these Amazing Ideas that we want to try and
What's the one thing
Right now
They just pets
Cool suits
I'm basically
I was like okay well maybe I can perform in this week
Something we can create
Kind of surreal
Experience
Into my into my songs and which song I wanted
Performance and
The bed sometimes
Smart Switch
It's credit personal songs to me it's with I wrote it just after my grandmother passed away
Then when I certainly went into a really lunch time
Which is why
Oh there's my eye
Because I deal with bipolar disorder and
Carnival
Spirit animal
Polar bear with dance
Different theme
Sorry that was a really great team
Fugees my vision I suppose so I gave them the conception they kind of morphed
We filmed in that are we feeling
At a club
Onion
Lovely experience
Came out so you guys I'll play a little snippet of the song for you and a link to a video of
Parts of the performance in the show notes in
In case you
Want to see
Alright so
Let's talk about
You as an artist
What do you do what do you focus on
And then we'll talk about how you think about bringing technology
I mean I know it's been a musician since I was quite young I played the trumpet
So many years and then black moose more and Chip quiet
Japan
And then now finally on
Play music
AnnaSophia code Ableton Live
Which is really intuitive
It software actually
Because you can pretty much orchestrate
As many sounds
Lively
Kind of things
Your software to my music so it can be quite emojis
I love chicken
Technology
Has the potential
In a creative way to be
Really magical
So then let's talk about
This suit for example that was using lotion
Capture
Create this VR experience
And you have this idea for a VR elevator that I think is
Really interesting
Yeah yeah
I think it kind of came about
Initial Wikipedia
Create
Is that true
Stay so you can like
Choose where you want to go
Inside an elevator came
You know what shop
Black creatives
Virtual space so we can release Music Week
Have interviews people can go in and try instrument
Bavette
To space so I don't really really excited
It's something they were actually working on
And ideas what I'd love to do is to release my album
In the elevator
It does that make sense
It's a little bit
Big wild
Each floor could have
Find song I suppose you can like cheese
Selection
Maybe the top that be like a interview going on but I mean
Jose might Collective
Facilitate all different than Keurig different floors cuz I have a lot of
It's loud stated that IDK
Came out in the light wow wow
Have a whole system
And you just randomly pick a
The floor I mean
Technically that's what day would come
Yeah and let's talk about working and we'll get this in Spades in a moment
Let's talk about working with
Technology as an
Artist
How do you
I know that you're like oh I think this is need how could I use it how much do you have to collaborate with
Partners and what do you look
Yeah
I mean when it comes to the stuff we're able to have been using it for about 6
And I use it too
Sketch sound
Interscope
Sounds
Two different forms
Exemplify recorded
Snake like one of my Stones new country
Actually recorded
Snow
Steps to take on the snow and then
Transporter
Ableton
And I messed around with it to make it sound like a song
I said I do
Just on my own and I love doing that but I also really love
Clever
Expedition stickers
They add so much
Text Jen death
Cipher example my friend Looney she's
A trumpet player
Spreadable chocolate
And when she played
Ilovesukie
Trumpet Wild play
Lives
Stuff
Took sketch's real texture
Imitation in my feelings electronic
Music
Think she knows technical it's very like
Maybe a little solace in some way though just to check my banking music that actually
It's kind of like having an old
In your computer that you just
Launch different sounds
And when you're thinking about doing like these VR worlds
How do you sync that collaboration
Works do you like SketchUp
With someone
Yeah I'm not I love the idea of you
Eating a live animation
Analytics different
Phoenix Artisan that way
Visual artist salary
If you in mind commissioning other artists
She create there in floor
The sequence
Which BRS
The accessibility some people
So maybe you could be cool types
Estates
Arcade
You can come in and try these
So let's go to this concept of descent babes because this is something you are passionate about and it's
The unjust use
Talk to me about what that is
Since paid records about 2 years ago
Editor's Pitchfork Jessica Hopper
Kum & Go
Business ideas
Because
Traditional
The music industry is very
Enchanted
The leadership structure sounds like
I really want to create this
Collective
Basically of women
Gender diverse
And also I wanted to release my own album
And that's always been the core I think you stop sitting
Having
Dynasty of my music
I'm not handing it over and not losing the copyright to it and then
It's kind of evolved into
More of the collective more of a startup
Because I wanted to
Have impact
I wanted to change the electronic music
Representation is so loose women
Biggest scale and it stinks one of the main issues is accessibility to
Expensive music software
I think
United stilettos
Gatekeepers
That has many female artists because maybe they just got different biases
About a year ago and how and why and those are the kind of reason
Create
Can a very cool online face
With the funding you're trying to raise
You guys are going to create this online space where
People will have
Access to the discounted software
Yeah kind of
I think I was really inspired by
The
Wow
Revolutionize the way you GPS me to basically
I was discussing his concept of offering up the software
Time I suppose
Omnicef
It takes a long time to learn
I mean I had to Ableton
6 years before I actually bought it myself
Idea of like being able to share the stuff way around
And then just being charged with what you used
Taxi really cool concept
That could be a really
Cool idea where you could
Try it out and then you can
I had this idea
Because cost of the way such as
Thing that came up
See my research
As to why
Why you do by the software
I'm like well you know average and less than men
Gender pay Gap
Clean the world
You know women on average have more
Customer service
You know some discounts you can also do you use the platform that's the kind of
Thinking that I want
Next to me feels like it was
Create more impact
Got it
Okay and then the other part of this so after you got the online space you're also creating a festival
Correct
Exciting
Gene study
It's going to come from
Conferences check music feminist
And some of this money that the raising will go towards that and then we basically
Cities around the world
And yeah just inspire
Basically because yeah
Women have really interesting
Ways of approaching technology and also making using it
So I think it has a
Potential to inspire
Got it all right and
Let's talk about the blockchain because yes
Wouldn't
After the conference when we went out to dinner we were all very excited about blockchain
And I keep talking about
Have you thought of ways to use it and music
Seem like they might
I know you Imogen Heap
She's an amazing artist
How do you
Create transaction
Assess streaming cost because the way I see it
Have their own
Justin on the Block
We can see exactly how many
Streams weekend
We can see it's a nut-free put really subtract
On a particular date that way
Cuz right now
If I
You know I'm a
Distributor
If I take that down there
What happens to the
The song like I just think the permanent
Of blockchain mixit
Very exciting
And you can really see exactly
How many streams
Did you get how much money you are
That's what makes me
Meetfighters
Okay so more is a payments
Payment seeing the other than ulcers smart contract
When you working with Odyssey
You know you
You want it to be as legitimate as possible
And sometimes
Where did I put that contract
Quite exciting and then that's the stuff we're sharing
System
Would be in the blockchain because
You know you use it and then it sits there as a wreck
But this is kind of things that I'm
Planning on thinking about
And going forward
How do you think that connectivity and Technology will change
How we experience music
That is a head of a human pillar
It's like a it's a
Play that is a Bluetooth cooler
And had the speaker in it
Jesus
Flashlight
50s music
And they had beef United displays
And it's just amazing
Killer Bean spacing
Enfamil enspire
Can watch a movie on your phone or you could
I can sleep
Something old list
Listen to music
I've been listening to it
Vibration
So I think that has
Containment salon
Will be a big
Change when people stop to get all these
Cool little gadgets
Kids music
Whole new way
When it comes
Forming like the way I talk
Performed
The order
So I can
Is my audio system
Is motion sensor
And when I move spinner
Different
Different different sounds can come out just
Remind me
Rather than me
Ashley
Maybe I could
Control the music with membrane
And I think that's really
Very very cool and fun
Hiking sweat
I think it's kind of messy I think you know even stage cough like
Microphones and mic French
Stems and things like that
Analogues
I think the evolution of different products
Can use on stage
That maybe didn't exist
Music
Oh so like we ditch the microphone and we go for something
Yeah I have this idea of a
Say
Kind of follow you and
You don't have sexy hold
But she likes
When you hold the next
How to tell your whole performance
Anna Kate Bush was one of the first people to request a headset mic
You want to feel this moment
She was one of the first people to do that
Beside you is like a
Train that could
American flag in front of your face
You can sing into it and then like I said about the elevator part
Entertainment at home
Feeling like
And that gives access to a lot more
People
The people that
Experience life
Could be thousands
And then
Sew-in that gets to a big challenges right now it feels like the
World for artists
Is both wide open with crowdfunding taipei
Opportunities and
Patreon
Yes
Yes is a lot of
Construction happening
Because he called music
Industry model. Working
Really
Reclaim the in Independence
Anoka
Is to be able to send or the creative projects that we want to do and not operate like a like a not-for-profit
Something actually operate on a business
Stitches
This is social cause
No I think that's PayPal
When that happens
Okay well I'm here thank you so much for coming on the show
Thank you
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week