Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have done an amazing show for you today we are going to be talking about the big bad
Amazon in
Google Feud
Are you talking about a huge 61 million-dollar fundraise from a smartphone
Company
Pekin faucets you can talk to her finally here
Wechat
Crazy story about
Madame de and her
Evil laugh
Plus
We're going to be talking about new features coming to your Wi-Fi router in the
Probably sort of District
Future and we've got smart
Dorm room
Johnstown Inn
Arizona
It's not your beauty school
Yes it is
Okay it is
Plus
We're here from Kevin who tried out a connected car device and then
Will hear from
Sponsor this week Samsung artik who's talking about security
Before going on to our guests who is Rob Martin's Who is the
President
Of allegion Ventures this is a newly-created venture firm
For The Internet of Things
And we have the exclusive on what it's looking for
So stay tuned for all of this
But first
Another message
This week's episode is brought to you by the yonomi platform for the makers of the free yonomi app the yonomi platform
Is a cloud-based platform-as-a-service that enables developers to build a more connected open smartphone
This week on iot podcast part two of their five parts
Theories on what the next billion-dollar smart home startup will look like hard to add
What is the point of no return in the smart home that is what is the iPhone moment when adoption skyrockets in can
Consumers can no longer imagine going back to the way things were before
You can read all about that today at platform. You know me. Co / Stacy
Beyond iot once again that's platform. Yonomi
Co / Stacey on iot
Hockey
Kevin
What
It's getting worse that's why
Oh
I thought we patched things up
You are right
It is getting worse
Kerfuffle
If you like it movie on
So Ava
Initially
Paid attention to this because Amazon and Google
Tennyson the kerfuffled and
You no longer plays YouTube videos on your Amazon
Shell
Order Fire TV
My daughter being one of them
Yes my.
Now
Amazon has taken
Nest
Off of it
Website well they're still there for the moment
Only remaining inventory that Amazon has on Nest products I'm looking at it right now the Amazon site and they still show the nest
Thermostat and security camera
Anything they've been selling
It's still there but when they're sold out
Apparently they will not be replaced
And no new
Nest products
Will be put on Amazon and this all came about on a conference call between Amazon and Google apparently and people
That were reportedly on the cauley-stein The Nest side feel that it came right from the top of Amazon
Jeff Bezos and
This is just getting ugly
I mean
I think I bought
I mean you bought a nest cam
Continued
I bought mine
Yes I did I know that you can go out to like various stores retail stores
If they are
With so many people do shop
On Amazon either for
A better price the free shipping whatever else you know
I think personally Google should be trying to work with Amazon to figure this out because I think that's going to hurt
Google more than hurts Amazon
Guess I never blame it when a product isn't available on Amazon I don't blame you
Although
In this case I definitely do
I would not be surprised I want to say I do
Believe it's Amazon's pulling the plug here so to speak
But you know when you Google pulled the plug on YouTube from
The Fire TV products and the echoes
You know Amazon probably was not very happy cuz that hurt the customer
Experiencing what we have to do is with install the silk browser
On the Fire TV and then go to YouTube on the web and
It's a pain in the neck
And Amazon surely didn't like that so this
Appears to me to be retaliation
Well let's see how far this goes
Right now my nest
Secure still works with Madam a
Do you think that could be
If they want to continue this fat
What is next I would think that would be
Yeah we don't want that
And this actually speaks little problem of bino the silos that
Can be built in iot instead of the interoperability which I know what to talk about with him or the different products it's kind of worrisome
Incredibly worried
Potentially worrisome things
Interpolated ecobee the maker of
What used to be my favorite song
Smart thermostat
And is still
Turn sign
Smart thermostat
They've raised 61 million dollars
And part of that
Meditation
I was going to say it.
So this is really interesting timing
Because the press release that they sent out
Really focused hard on the fact that Amazon just bought
Rickford
A billion plus
And we talked about this last week that fell to us kind of like a weird anomaly
I'm kind of the end of the consumer iot
Play it on
I can see if Amazon wants to take this all the way to the
Peru
Buying a thermos
Thermostat company
Could get you
Like more of the complete package
Distend
Really what they would need is an indoor camera
I guess
Maybe locks maybe not you know
Google doesn't have a lock
I don't know what do you think
Yeah I mean
Two things pop out at me ecobee
Already obviously works
Anatomy voice services on the newest model
So there's obviously a relationship there
Okay so their newest model
Doubles as
Anatomy
But their old stuff also
Works with
Describe your other stuff
Iveco beef
3 Sol
I'm not
Surprised that they have some backing here
What does it mean in a long-term because we talked about this a week or two ago about
Companies that get
Backing from the matinee phone and all the sudden a competing product is out and buy Amazon leaving the original
Company wondering what the heck just happened
I don't think that's going to happen here
It's entrenched yeah
And I think building a
Right
The other thing Amazon could get out of this
Ecobee does support motion sensors and even remote motion
Sensors
So I don't know what Amazon would do with that date or they want that data but it's a proper they could get it where is none of their other
Let's do that
Right so this is actually interesting cuz it could do occupancy
Sensors do occupancy and they also
So this gives
Again we always talk about this context so Amazon could do something with that
Context if
Could be something as simple as
Maybe you don't have to have it. And ever
Maybe you could just be like turn on the lights and they don't know what we
Beer in Hog Wild and you know watch a movie where they're on a frozen planet on your TV and it turns you
Your air conditioning on to make it really cold
I'd say that the same but
The hue light bulbs
Already work with
I know I love that for you
Here I am an ice Planet Hoth
That's exactly what I had in mind but I didn't know if
Reference
I'm pretty sure I'm pretty sure most
This is true
Okay so that is
And other thing that might be worth
About is ecobee because it has a link into
Power
And utilities
Theater smart thermostat and kind of demand response programs
Is Amazon you know this week they were talking about a let's get into banking
This could give Amazon
Yet another bill that you pay and
Another facet of
Transactions since they want to be a part of every
Free transaction
That feels a little out there but
Never Say Never
All right
Moving onto excited by this
Excited
Because Delta we talked about this
@cs because one of my favorite devices from CES was the Delta faucet
Madam
Installed
Did you get it
And basically
I have these Delta touch faucet
And now they're offering
The touch faucets
Plus you can say Madam a
Dispense 8 cups of water
Crash of the fossa
So I'm really excited about this because I love my Delta touch faucet
$549
That's the faucet included
It is a lot of money but is there a retrofit package
All we talked to them and say yes about a nice ago you know they were thinking about it
So I don't see a retrofit package cuz
And my touch faucet was about $300
Just to give you a reference
It is a nice faucet
Capacitive touch on your faucet
Go back
Awesome
Yeah but now
So break this out what how much is it
When is the additional expense now for the smarts
$50
80%
That's why I went back and looked at it
Sofia
What so it's it's a lot of money
And you know they get the benefit of all of your
Exciting
And this is almost I think this is exact
Deceitful touch2o
Essa touch2o
The only one you can buy as a
An Arctic stainless finish and it's
Only this one pro
Particular one
This one particular model
But this is my exact
Yeah one thing that could be contributing to the cost here I had forgot about this feature
They did tell us a
That's it yes and I just noticed it on the on the website for the faucet
You can ask matinee to warm up the water
And that's
That is an additional piece of Hardware that's got to heat up a certain amount of water so that way it's instantly hot
I will say is
These faucets
I don't know if Delta is going to do the same thing for this one but one of ours ours had like some sort of
Leaky gasket or something happened
And they just sent us a hole
Which
Yeah I was like
Is this expensive
Remodeling my house
Yes
Rip out my exhaust
Ashley hard
And replace it
Yes
Yes come on your body June
The rest of you guys
If you do buy it you have
Have to do some
Video demonstration for
The folks on the site
Yes
Also color I should tell you
Also makes a faucet
Is madam
I don't know if it's
Which
Again
Black magic
I love it
Okay moving on to things that are not exciting but
Actively creepy
Madam
Has been
Laughing
Or just laughing
Not sure if this is it Kevin and I debated putting this on the show this
It's such a quirky story we felt like we had to but
I also want to note that the stories that we found in this topic are based on either a Reddit thread
Or tweets for me
And nobody's actually gotten Amazon
How to talk about what this is nor could I replicate
Campus
Just happen spontaneously
Yes
Apparently people's madhumeh devices
Just random times middle of the night
Whenever
Just start laughing like an evil laugh
Well that's what these people have said
And I have seen even a video of it
The person didn't say
Madam a laugh
Started laughing
And it's like
Why is this happening
Cuz it shouldn't be happening unless she's running around skills now we're going to see if
If you can hear this video
Yeah that is
Yeah I don't get it I just don't know what would cause that
Amazon hasn't spoken to anybody who is
Is reported on this
So we don't know
I was thinking I am sitting here going
Man is someone hacking like a certain skill maybe all these people have a certain skill involved
And this is Kai
Benefit Big prank on them slash
It's funny you mention the hacking aspect because
Obscene
Numerous reports over the past year of people
Seeing
Phones and other connected devices connecting via Bluetooth
To their Echo devices
Even though the Bluetooth pairing wasn't on and
That seemed to be a bug
I don't know if it was addressed or whatnot so you know maybe this is
Some kind of hockey thing
See that's
That is my
Hopefully
Hopefully we'll get more information
Oh my gosh this is the kind of story that captures the imagination
Negative
Maybe Google phones
Hahaha
The feud
Alright let's see what else do we have that doesn't
Webcams
Should we talk about
A crazy new plan from
DSLR
Yea nice webcams the network of intelligent camera ecosystem
It's a new alliance and if I sound skeptical
It's because I am
There's a startup called cinarra that is that put this Alliance together
Nikon is involved
Sony is involved and some of the folks that actually make
Devices over in China for
Just about everybody wished Ron and Foxconn for example are part of this Alliance
That is trying to start up
And I looked through the Sonora home site
And seems like they're trying to create a
A video of interoperability
Platform for webcams and include AI
So that way people who make devices don't have to worry about what the webcams are seeing the platform itself will have skin
Standardized ways to determine what's important in the video and so on so forth and I just sit here and shake my head because he's
He's kind of alliances don't often Works number one
The number to it sounds like they're trying to out a i the AI companies and I don't think that's going to happen
I'm with you on that
It reminded me and I cannot for the life of me I start googling in a
Back in the day when did Apple App Store came out probably here later
And the Google
Android play store started happening
Cell phone carriers would like
Hey there at stores actually work what's happened let's all create our own app store
And they got together to do this big
Multi carrier App Store f
I can't even remember the name of it so clearly that did not go
Nominate to the carriage of had their own like
Verizon had vcast for example here in the US
I don't remember what the
Croup
The terrorists tried to adapt stores they also try to do it mobile payments
I remember Melville
Isis yes
Yeah not smart there
Surly they didn't realize
So anyways this is
Keep this in your mind if it happens
Kevin did mention that this the guy who's behind this though
Who actually has some
He does he push forward the HDMI video standard which pretty much is an acceptable standard so
He's been able to
Get different players to
Come together on a single standard that we do use today
Possible that
Nice works out but I again I'm a little skeptical
Yes
Let's talk about
This isn't cameras but it's
Kind of like
This is part of my
I did a story last week on why your Wi-Fi sucks
In the house
Why your wifi isn't fixed yet
And if you want a link to that so you can
Go see it
Talked about all kinds of crazy things about
Basically your router's are getting smarter and your clients are going to need to get Dumber
Fish can't have two SmartThings fighting it out
Is part of that reporting
In talking to Qualcomm
About kind of the future Wi-Fi
They also mentioned that there really are working with
Five different companies to bring presence detection
Motion detection
The home theater
Wi-Fi
And as an example of this I've got to deal with a company called cognitive systems
And that company makes
ARA the ARA Wi-Fi security
And
That basically says
The whole technology is built on this idea that
People walking around disrupt the radio waves of the
House and
Now.
The chips can
Tell they can paint a picture
So based on that disruption they
See
What's kind like radar in a sentence
What cabin
Traffic
Welcome
Which provides the chips
Almost every
The really
Dublin
Technology they're actually working with five companies to bring that into the home that actually gives me a lot of Hope
Ferg presents
And maybe even like
Better security inside the house what do you think
Yeah I would agree I mean when you have a call, then we just like you said the Behemoth of the
Mobile one
Atheros
They are huge so that's a good sign for this technology but then again
Had a chair failures as well they had their
Displays
I forget what the name of it was but they kind of replicated The Butterfly Wings
The miracle
Mirror something is
Yeah they try a lot of different things I give them
Credit for that answer but they don't all work out but
I like
I like that
Potential is a tense because of what you
You last said improve security and the reason I say that is
Unless you put a camera in every room of your house you can't
I see in every room of your house so with this you could sort of quote unquote see in certain rooms because of the
Disrupted Wi-Fi
Media weather
You know emanating from the router and
Flooding
Every room of your house
So you are getting
Information from rooms don't have a camera so I see a lot of potential are
I am curious though
So there's a couple things it's not a camera
So you can walk around naked and
While it may notice that there is slight differentiations
It probably
Don't care
And it's not like a human can see that does that make it better
Like it will still be able to see what you're doing
In the sense that
If they run the right algorithm
Right now
This person is
Beating a child picking their nose
Whatever
Yeah I mean it you so you're not going to get the
Detailer of a
I've seen something on a camera
Maven
They're working on that day
You're not going to see the detail you would see in a video camera sound like if somebody walked into your house in a room that doesn't have a camera this wi-fi think-tech
Text them your alarm goes off you wouldn't have a picture of that person right so you couldn't
Picture of the Nala
Yeah
The knowledge is important it's basically
It is just presents
It's not identification
But presence may be good enough obviously we will use
Sensors on our doors and windows and things like that for detection
You know presence detection
And that's good enough to tell you
For allergic something's not right
I just bring this up because it's kind of
It's part of that ever-present privacy surveillance
It's kind of a spec
What do you want
Yeah exactly it's a choice it's a personal choice absolutely
Okay
Let's talk about
Here comes a little news
Yes
Across the pond or folks
Saracens will be happy in the UK because
Google home calling is now live so you can do hands-free calls
It will
Make a call from your Google home but use your phone number
So that is really cool that's added to the US and Canada which already have the
This feature
Even though I have it I never use it but hey
It is a very isolated
So here's the use case that actually has worked for us
Is
We tell our daughter
Because she doesn't really have a cell phone
Where's the house cell phone but it's never
Procharged
So
We tell her just to give us a call
When she's home by herself and she need some
So it becomes kind of kind of
Yeah
There's a used
Case it's more
It works
IBM has a new service called pears
Geoscope
It is a
Cloud-based service that they've launched
Basically you put in
Any sort of data with geospatial data
And it pulls the geospatial data act
How to create a map
And it's apparently super easy
I bring this up
Because I am super excited about environmental law
Monitoring so I love the idea of being able to pull data from Lake
Maybe it's weather stations you can and see around you
And get like air quality data or weather data on a map
It just seems kind of like a fun
Easy project
And
It says it can even
It can take anything from
Geotagged
Weather data Census Data aerial imagery
Tweets or news data
Nickelback g.
So I don't know how many of you want to make maps but I just thought it was cool cuz a lot of my iot things and like it would be headed
Need to have a map
Function for this
And what am I
My favorite college is ASU go Sun Devils they're getting smart dorms in the engineering
Ar40 engineering students
Kind of sets AC off before the show engineering students
Requested
Some students should have
I hear you but they got that Cronkite
School journals on there I know
I love I love you
But the engineering students are getting some
Fancy new rooms in one particular dorm
Some of the things were just smart usage of furniture and things like that not connected Furniture 9 that but I did
Didn't notice and there's a video that we can link to
If you want to see me
Every room gets an echo Dot and the students
I have four different custom wake word so that way each individual student can speak to the. Not confuse who is speaking
They can control their Smart TV with it as well
And what I thought was a really cool only because I
Doing laundry at college
She's like one of the things of my existence
They made it so much easier for people to ASU in this particular dorm because the laundry machines are connected they sent me a
Bluetooth which I found kind of odd
Because you're not going to be within range of
Laundry machine for the future but
You can
Use your phone to see which machines are open
And determine if your wash is ready or still in progress which I thought was awesome you don't need to sit there like Wii U
I have to do with
Rolls of quarters because
All the laundry is included for free don't have to pay for it
And then wait and see when she becomes open they can do that right from their room
Yes I loved
And I was with your Bluetooth cuz it they showed him like going downstairs
Yeah
The Hub
So that weird but
I mean
Apartment
Should offer this as well
I feel like
Any apartment complex that I would live in now
I would expect
Set the sort of feature
Because my goodness
Actually I would expect
Washer dryer
Along with my June oven in my Delta faucet
Yes
So I like this I'd like to the other thing is in the Echo.
Rent it and I don't know if they'll swear
Custom butt from Amazon or if they just made those with their 3D printers that also happened to be in the engineering dorm
They look really nice
Give me the name of the doorman everything in multi like a geographic design on it look really funky
Kevin
You try that again
Yes
So I tried out the Raven I'm going to call this a preview because the device actually doesn't become available for shipping and
Tomei to a lot of the features unfortunately we're not working
For me to
Test yet the company is working on adding those features
The basically with the Raven is it almost looks like the old
Microsoft Xbox Kinect
And what it is is it say connected dash cam for your vehicle
Either place on your windshield or on your dashboard I put mine on the windshield and it's got a front camera so you can
Do your drive and so on so forth
If there's an accident or something you recapture that information
It also has a rear-facing camera so it's looking inside the car itself
Which and even capture sound in there so I was singing to The Beatles While I was driving and luckily
The microphone doesn't work well yet they're working on fixing that
So you can't hear me sing in the video which is very good
What's unique about this I mean that you had to connect to dash cameras at GPS it's got LTE it's got to display
Blaze on if you can see real-time turn-by-turn that occasion
You can see your Telemetry from your car because it plugs into your onboard diagnostic port
In your vehicle as well get his power as well as information from the car
Seated speed and fuel information and so on it was that'll work fine
But the really interesting thing about this is there's a security aspect to it because there's an accelerometer in a processor
In the device
When your car is
Park but gets bumped
Or your car here is glass breaking
Or somebody tries to open the door
You can actually
Get that captured on camera
Again I could not test that because those alerts are not working
And I also
Question how well it will work with the video
Camera
Is the first thing I'm going to do when I get that alert is I'm going to go look live right in my car what you can do because there's an LTE
Connection in this
The thing is
If somebody bangs my car
As you're looking for the
Cabin of the vehicle yeah you can see a pretty wide angle but
The vision is kind of limited because of you know things in your car and the pillars between the
Doors in the roof so I don't know if you like be able to get a license plate or not like that so
What it does today it does well
What it will do
I don't know if it will do well
Because again
Those pictures aren't there just yet this is $299 you can pre-order early and save 30 bucks
And then of course there is a service plan because it's got LTE and
Real-time connection to your phone so you can check in live at any time in your vehicle
Those range from 8 to $30 a month and the
The main difference between
How many times can you
Look at your vehicle or look out through the front
Camera it also captures everything on video and you can pull those down
I'm sure those which I've done it in my review so
Kind of price
Missy and I should also mention that there's actually another device
Very similar to this on the market is called the owl car cam
And it is available for $349 it is going to be available
Call the end of March the estimated delivery is ma
March 31st will see if
This actually
Comes with a Year's worth of LTE service so you get the 60 Minutes of live 24/7 video or 6
Tags which I guess is
Checking in on things
Threatening
You can buy more data
For ten bucks for
What they call 66
I suppose
So that's just
There's apparently a big Market
Here for the
Dash cam
Damn baby
Popularized by all those Russian dash cam
Videos
Maybe I see the thing is
Even if these products do what they say I'm not in the market
Before it gets first of all
My car already has LTE
I mean I can use it as a Wi-Fi hotspot so the only thing I can't do right now is the camera stuff
You know
I can remotely close the doors on my
Car I can get telemetry
Find out how much gas is in there or how much battery charge I have so it's a toughie because
These only work with cars at least the Raven only works at
2008 and up and a lot of newer cars come with
Too much all these features except for the camera
So I don't either be market for this I don't know me either
I
Just bought a new
New car we just want to
We did not do it then do
And really the only feature that we were like
Play dead set on
Was having a backup
Which car is actually a starting this year all cars are going
Anyway
So I don't know
Everybody's gif
So this
It could be really exciting to
To some people
Let us know if
And now
Will move to the Internet of Things podcast
Listener hotline
Chase hotline responses bread maker of electronic
Which leg you can have a brand new electronic lock installed in minutes
With just a screwdriver
On your own two hands
Panther Easy to setup and use
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
Hello Kevin and
Stacy
This is Ed
Are the questions I never hear this
Discussed on the
Radio any of the podcast
Is if I set up my
Lights
Home to Beach
Activated using Google home
Should I never touch the manual lights
This again as at my
The sequence
Thanks
That would be a big problem normally
S I can't always
Talk to Google home
Turn lights on
So hopefully you can please address
Question which I never hear anybody talk about
Thank you
Lobster Pot
Oh
Men
Ed this is a great question
An end probably obvious to any of us
I need to know
So
Good good on you for bringing this up
So the answer is
It depends
Definitive answer it.
If you're working with a smart bulb
Then if someone
So if Google is controlling a smart bulb
And someone turns off the light switch that controls that lamp or those bulbs
Then yes it will stop work
Correct because you have basically turn
And this is why I've told everybody in my family don't touch the light switches in the house
And now people actually make fancy light switch covers that you can
You can stick over them
Billy hack off your family cuz then they can't ever turn the lights off
Switch
I'm not going to die
Instaff
Tape or you can install a Smart Switch if you have a Smart Switch
Google is smart enough to understand the state of that song
Twitch and so
It doesn't matter if someone
Turn something off
Right and by using a switch you can actually use
Old original be the point of contact for
Control
And
Tissues old pubs
And there are some
Parameters that you want to make sure you
Handle like they have to be capable of dimming
If you have a dimming switch
That's actually most of my house is wired up to Smart Life
Switches
The only place I have
Smart bulbs is where I want
Eye color change
Bulbs
And so
And those
Price of a terms of office which they don't
So that actually works
Nodejs Google Assistant
It also works for any smart home hubs that you might have so if you're like any automation
That you have those bulbs
Part of that group
So it's pretty much just
It's the same prayer
All things
If this is one of the benefits of going with smart switches
And I have not done that I'm completely opposite of what you have Stacey I have dumb switches
And all smart bulbs so that's why I told my family don't touch the switches.
Recommend to Lutron
Because they're made
Favorite of all time
Fees which is work like they're intuitive so you don't need
Educate your family
Which is nice
And the downside is they do require
The plus side is that how it works with Madam
Text with Google and it works with
So I feel like they're pretty future-proof
They work really well they're nice
If you don't want to do something like that Leviton makes a
Decora Smart Switch that
Is
Amazon Echo and
I believe Google Assistant
Enable do not get
WeMo
Smart dimmer switch because
It glows in the dark
And its related
That's my thought
Okay so
There's your question
Good question
And remember if you have a question and want to ask
Call us at 512-6223
7424 we will also
Tell you that
Moving right along to our next segment is Going to Be Our Guest
Rod Martin's who is president of the newly-created allegion ventures
He's going to be talking about
What they're looking for in a new 50 million dollar fund
Before we get to that
Let us take a message from this week sponsor Samsung
Ask for a message from our sponsor sponsor is Samsung artik and I have John Jefferies here to talk
Tell us about Samsung artik
Insecure
Hey John
Hey sweetie how are you
So we last had Samsung artik on the show a while back
And since then you guys have made a few changes
Can you share with me
What those are
Absolutely
Does Samsung has really focus on
Security in the last 6 months 9 months and really
Invested heavily in both features in the cloud
And on the hardware modules
We have Unified
ICloud
Into the SmartThings Cloud offering
Which includes all of the
Previous article cloud services
And we've introduced our line of s modules
Gosh asthma
Tell me more about those
First of all the s stands for
Security offer Hardware protection
For your eyes
Modules which include all the computer communication in the software you need to build or your audience needs
To build iot devices
That are safe and secured in really provide
Three essential elements
Device protection
Data protection and
Protected communication
Iot devices
Sunday ads
Do the clouds going forward
Leaves as mulch
Those will be included
In all Samsung Smart refrigerator
What are the benefits of using the S module over something else
One of the primary benefits is rapid time-to-market we also eliminate the risk
Rolling out
Security including things like secure boot encrypt
Data
And you thought education out of the box
As part of this
It's critical that you design products
Security at mine which means
That you need to think about
At least 10 things
That are serious and important with respect to the pioneers
We create a list of these 10 things
So it's critical that Developers
Design Security in
The early phase of the development process
At Samsung we have
10 cor 10
That we think are absolutely essential
Develop
Secure iot device
Awesome
And guys
If you want to learn more about what Samsung artik can do for you
Especially on the security
Visit www. Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Slash
Samsung artik
That's www
. Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Slash
Samsung artik
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Your host Stacy and her guests this week is Rob Martin's who is a futurist and president of
The newly-announced allegion ventures
Hi Rob
Hi Stacy thanks for having me today I am super excited and for our listeners you probably noticed that
Rob through his
Parent company Allegiant
They actually sponsor
The Internet of Things
Hotline
But we are here to talk about
A new Venture fund that
Is set up by Allegiant is called Allegiant dentures and it has 50 million dollars to invest
And Rob
Why don't you quickly tell us
Why Allegiant started this fund
Sure Stacy we started the fun
Because we felt like there all these
Fantastic ideas and
Technologies out there
That are yet to be discovered that could
Contribute directly to the
Security and safety space
We believe if we can connect with the right Founders and the right companies with the right business models we can help
Help accelerate them
Market not just in the traditional consumer iot space
But in a variety of space
You know whether that be multi-family or
Commercial institutional spaces
That they might not even be some other what's yet
Okay so you guys have 50 million dollars this is a corporate venture
Petrified which actually historically has gotten a terrible rap but with the internet of things that's actually where a lot of the doll
Others are coming from
So what is your goal is it to make money
Is it to
Find cool things that mixture of both
I think any Venture fund obviously you ultimately would love to make money but our focus is
I'm much more long-term view we think things take time to percolate so
It's much more about finding what's the next
Technology that is going to contribute to a breakthrough
In terms of the consumerist
Experience
Or a
Frictionless
Experience for people when they interact with Safety and Security devices
Hopefully
Udo long-term organ contribute to a safer environment overall
And you guys illusion
Has both residential
Sounds like we all know the Schlage Locks but
You guys also have a very large business
Set is
Commercial
Correct that's correct so
Allegiant is actually a 2.4 billion dollar company
We have 10000 people across 130 countries around the world
So most people know us
In North America by the Schlage name
But in Europe you might be slower with cheese
And we have a number of other brands
Example portable security like Kryptonite that people might be familiar with but actually the Lion's Share of our business is not
Not in the residential site it's actually on the commercial and institutional side
K through 12 schools
Higher education medical applications in the light
Okay so you guys are looking to invest
Cross that whole Broad
Portfolio of
Absolutely
We just see that
A lot of great disruption
Comes out of the
Consumer iot space you see a lot of
Unique design unique development
Very focused effort
That sometimes draw out interesting and new approaches
We also think the type of
People that are bringing those for
With our assistance with our
You know expertise within the space
We may be able to help to accelerate bringing their products to Market
But maybe even more importantly
Bring them to some new markets that they might not even be familiar with were manufacturer so we know how to build stuff
We've been building stuff for over a hundred years so when companies struggle to
To figure out
Even
You know very basic things not only are we security and safety experts
But we also know how to Source things we know where to go
Where lean Six Sigma experts
We have all kinds of
Unusual skills and expertise that people might not know
Okay so that gets into the let's take some Nitty Gritty fun questions first
So are you guys looking for
A particular series like series a seed
Maybe later
Shirt we're looking for early-stage companies that have good growth
Potential
We do look at seed
Series A&B to a degree
There's really no limit we could
Go to see but we're typically looking in that series a series B area to start
Okay in
Most corporate Ventures don't have a lifetime of their fun
Do you have a sense of how long you want your investment how many investment you'd like to make
Per year
And how long you play
What does investment
We really don't know but I would
Tell you from our thesis
We think it takes probably
Between somewhere
In 05.
7 years for something to really mature
Into the space
Sometimes brownouts or failures take up to three years for that to happen
And so we're taking a very long term review
We think in order to be successful
We need to really work and help Foster
Are these entrepreneurs and Founders so that's not an overnight
Activity
In any sense
Sofi investment
We don't actually have a set
Target we wanted do it in the most organic
And intuitive way we feel like if we were to set
Specific targets at somewhat arbitrary
And what we want to do is we want to reward the best ideas the best technology the best business models
All right and who are you
For this site there is yourself
Sure there are three of us you can find us an Allegiant ventures.com
Wade sheet who is our managing principal he also happens to be the deputy general counsel for our business
And then our chief marketing officer OSHA Stewart
Yellow Bass
Carmel Indiana
We are
Okay
Best part about
Is there startups
Let's talk about your thesis
So Stacy the thesis of the find is based
To a large degree in two things
We obviously want to Foster and develop new technology
By investing in tech companies
And we also want to partner with these Founders to make the world
A safer place
So that is quite Broad
But I can give you a tangible example
Which is a company like you know me
So
You didn't know me is an Austin in Boulder based startup
That many of the listeners may be familiar with from a consumer iot standpoint
They've a very popular application
That aggregates
In automate
Lots of
Routines
From your favorite
Iot devices
But what you might not know
About you know me
Is they also have two other enterprise-class products
One called that you know me spin cloud
That actually provide a very cost
Effective solution for
Large companies to get their products
Online
And to manage their
Messaging and
Conductivity
Infrastructure
And then another one called the anomie one
Which is essentially the ability to embed a software development
On a edge device
Very interesting company
That has a whole variety of different ways
Is 2
Interact with
Security devices in other things
But also has the ability
To manage
Flow
So
People flow
Through the house
It's the routine that you go through it does it in a very simple and automated weigh that is very appealing
A residential consumer that same level of benefit
Can potentially be brought across
To an Institutional or more commercial
And user and also that technology itself has great productivity benefits
For large companies like
Allegiant engine tax
Got it and by the way I should mention that you know me
Is actually also an advertised
On the show okay so that is a good example so it's a very wide swath
You guys are
Absolutely
What you know
In one of the other podcast I think you and Kevin talked about
The fact that
Security and safety security in particular is kind of the gateway drug for the
Consumer iot
It really is because if
If you think about it
The door
In the areas that Allegiant typically plays in which is
Play around the door is the launching off
For many many recipes routines robots what-have-you
And so
We're in a very fortuitous position to launch all kinds of other activities
Let's start with
Where you think
Investments might lie
I know that we have had guests on the show and I'm
I'm feeling like we are at the end of the
Consumer iot
So I'm curious
How you view that space
Sure so
I think
I align very closely with
Some of the comments made on the show of late around
The consumer iot in a little bit of its demise
We're obviously very bullish
But I think you need to have a balance
Portfolio in
Perspective when it comes to the consumer iot
Allegiant is very fortunate from the standpoint of
We've been in business for well over a hundred years
And we have
Both mechanical products
Ian connected products
So when we enter new markets with
Electromechanical and now fully digital product set
We're able to
Balance some of those elements out
Without having to
Bet the farm for lack of a better term on one or another it allows us to experiment a little bit it allows us
To plan and
Cover some cost
Where
Within an iot
The framework the ongoing
Maintenance cost of some of those things are something that a startup
Might not
Be able to absorb so for us we have
Some advantages there
When we look at that to my
Adventure fun standpoint we see some fantastic technology
And
In some cases it may be introduced within a consumer iot
Frame but we believe it's the founders
Had the Opera
Trinity or the exposure to some
Perhaps institutional
Or commercial application
They may find that
To be far more appealing from a financial standpoint which doesn't ultimately lock them out from
Working on
Consumer side but they might want to address that later as
Making money as a startup is a good thing
So let me ask
As a consumer
I feel like
We had amazing strides
It's in the last few years some very cool products
Some very terrible products
Even some good products that were been discontinued
Have also come up
But do you think that there's going to be a wholesale abandonment of
Of the space especially as we're seeing consolidation
Chinese I don't think they'll be a wholesale abandonment of the space I do think / 2018 + 29
19 we're going to see a lot more Brown House
In a lot more fire sales
And we have seen in the past
However I look at it like a wave.
Saint Stacy
You know the wave tank
For the last couple years has been
Great disruption
Fantastic ideas
Tons of energy from this
Consumer electronics almost gadgety side
Flowing across
Into multi-family and then ultimately
Beginning to impact institutional and Commercial markets
Well I think it's hit the back
And I think the way the starting come back
And I think you will see
Some mature
Casted maybe not as
Cool or maybe not as sexy to use that work Solutions but very practical applications of iot
But I think we'll bounce back
Can rebound back and you'll start
To see them
Coming the other direction back in so I don't think it'll be completely abandoned but I do think we're going to see some
Some consolidation in the
Space in I think it's necessary
I think when we
Get to a level where
You know skepticism is high enough when people make claims
Skin
People aren't able to deliver on those to the degree that we seen it gets a little sketchy and consumer start to scratch their head
How to make loose face
I think the
Inclusion of the Meg attack
More and more into the iot
Will contribute to some resilience there though as they expect
For these larger businesses you know whether it's an Amazon a Google and apple whoever it might be
Making these Investments
You know what you expect
You know those things to work and to do
What day are advertised and designed to do
Does Allegiant or Schlage look at the big consumer
Companies getting into the hardware space
Like Amazon's deal to buy ring I am think about Google
Bring nest in house
Looking at those deals do you guys worried that you're going to have to
Compete directly with those guys one day
Stacy I think the megatex are going to deliver
Amateur product offering
That is in line
With
Not only consumer electronic
Expectations
But also with
The basics
Security and safety elements
That people need to have
So that is comforting
Intuos
We partner with them very closely
So we do
Spend time with
You know Amazon
Apple
Andina the other Mega tax
To ensure that
You know our products
And how they're used within their
Ecosystems are done properly so we're actually
Excited about the
Participation it's an accelerant for us rather than a detriment
And then on the industrial and institutional side what are some technology holes that
Could be felt
That you might be
I think the number one hole
Sounds
Pretty basic across
You know both consumer
Multi-family in commercial which is
People don't want to carry anything
Wisdom to get in the door they want the door
Or the product
You know the portable security device to recognize down
So how do we do that
You know today everyone carries
The phone with them
They may have a wearable
What if you don't have those things
Yet you still want
Secure
And say
Solution
To give you access to
To your bike
Or to your home to your office
It's a weird looking for
Technologies that can bring a more frictionless experience
Into all of those areas
While at the same time still
Addressing
The real legitimate
It concerns
That people have
You know we experience
This terrible tragedy in park
And
We
Have a lot of product
In k through 12 schools and higher education
How can we secure in Hardin
Those
Schools
Wallet
The same time
Not make our students and teachers feel like there
You know behind a TSA security line
How can we do that those are the types of technologies that were looking
To bring in so that we can really give the Peace of Mind
But don't have people feel like they're swimming in
That's a tall order I can't wait to see the investor
Thanks for coming on the show this week
Thanks so much for having me Stacy thanks so much for listening
Moraiyo chinos
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week