Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
I am your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have an awesome show.
Addendums on Google Assistant support
Amazon Echo says we're going to talk about tensorflow Lite
For those AI folks
We've got wink
Lookout
Impression
Plus I bought a $20 camera
And we got some news about
Blocks
SmartThings
Or we'll have a message from our sponsor sparkcognition.
Talking about how people can interact
With a i
Aunt
We've got our guest this week Michael Sherwood Who is the
Technology and Innovation director for the city of Las Vegas
We're talking about something really cool projects
So
All this
And more
After message
From our sponsor
Home isn't just a place it's a Feeling
The feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT helps keep you safe
So you can feel protected where ever you are introducing the ADT Security starter kit
Everything you need to get started with ADT Pulse including a camera
Professionally installed for only $49 visit att.com today to learn more
Requires a 36-month monitoring contract installation and activation fees apply in Rogan and qsp and easy pay require
Certain markets are excluded licenses available at att.com Florida E300
01121 Louisiana f163 9
Okay
Kevin let's just get started with some quick news bits because there's lots of
Quick news bits to Happy
To go around
So Google Assistant
It finally got support
Ecobee
Speaking of Google Assistant
I got an email the other day from the desk crew I imagined many of you guys got
Jane basically that
Before the end of this month
I'm going to have to reconnect
My
Nest gear
To my Google Assistant
And
The reason for this is a little unclear but we have our suspicions
Yeah what message saying is that Google search voice actions and Google Now are essentially part of Google assist
Which therefore also Google home
So I guess this is a Google thing that's being changed innocence which is affecting us which is there for fighting all the nests
Customers
They're just pulling this
Part out of Google Now which
Seems very strange to me because you've always been able to tap the microphone icon on Google noun
Essentially like a sister
I guess you're kind of going away from that
Google Now
Cards
Yes
So it sounds to me like Google Now is becoming more of just a contextual card-based
Information-based system
And
Assistant
Will take the place of the
Voice searches and controls and things like that
I'm seeing this happen
It's like they want to separate them
Make a very specific for different use cases
Also
While we're on this topic we should also mention
And I put this in my newsletter last week
And I
Kevin
Because it's my friend Michael Wolff over at the spoon
Notice that Google had applied for a patent
Four chimes
Unique Chimes that were specific to
People locations and events
And this seems right on par with the idea of using
Your home to notify
I might have my own purse
Personal chimes
Stacy
Oh my God get out the door right now
And that would sound like something where is my daughter might have a different time that says
I don't know
You should get up
I thought that was actually really interesting
And
Very on-point with actually getting rid of
The smartphone in your home
Which
Designer Carrie mine
India
No I agree it's actually ironically it's actually taking a feature from smartphones and moving it to the home because you
You can customize
Notifications and ringtones for different people are different types of alerts
But if you don't have your phone with you it doesn't really matter but if those kind of alerts come from a smart home
What are your in the home you have to carry the phone
That makes sense
Yeah
So I think that's
Really
Really cool
And it's worth talking about in the show because
How many of us have two Google assistants
Google homes are Google other devices in I like it
Yay it's just they filed for the patent they don't have the patent
Pet disclaimers
Check it out if you want
My little tiny Google mini it's actually smaller than I thought
So that's the first thing it's probably maybe
3 1/2 across
If that and it doesn't sound great
And
I find it very difficult to control using the Taps be
It's hard to orient on the device
My daughter is fascinate
The lights George that makes sense
So I think a question a lot of people would have I don't know if you can answer or not book
Sound quality and microphone
Pick up of your voice any better or worse than the echo Dot
I think it's
Probably the Mikes are better
The sound quality
Probably on
It's really
Quiet
I mean
That might do it I could I was listening actually the podcast in the kitchen on that thing
Write this is just me personally everybody has their own way of approaching us
When I think about what devices I want in my house from a voice assistance perspective I think about what do I do
I do in that room Dua
Need an input device with better Mike's or do I want a consumption device with better speakers and that's why I put the.
In places where they don't listen to music like on the nightstand for examples perfect and it's fine for listening to light music when you're
Fall asleep
But I. Where many would make sense in that use case for me so that's my Approach input sources that puts
I agree and I like it we put it down in the kitchen
Mostly because it is now our backup
Amazon so when
Meta Mages pumps on a question which happen
Where are you ever dinner now I can just be like
Sorry you guys
Haji
Okay done with Google
Not really we're going to come back to it
Other news
This works
About the Amazon Echo is now available in Canada
Yay
And India
It is exciting
This year in Canada radio
Well yes
And it reminds me
Report neighbors to the north
They get nothing
I feel really bad for them.
But they don't get
I hear you they speak English
Something speak
Alright let's get back to Google see I lied to
I told you the truth cuz I think I said we're going to come back to it
Not
Associated with smart
They have their tensorflow
Will have chips they have
And they now have machine learning for embedded devices
Big trend
For next year so
Oak Avenue
Yasso tensorflow Lite is what they announced this week
It is a developer preview basically the lightweight version of tensorflow do they use for their Ai and machine learning
This is specifically geared as you said Stacy towards embedded devices also mobile devices
So your Android phones in particular
I'm more interested in the iot type devices embedded devices because
We think about adding machine learning to these things now instead of
Theoretically you automating things based on potential trigger events and so on
Things can happen based on an event
That machine has learned
Essentially
Perfect example I think is I forget the name of it
There's not a platform built on tensorflow that does image
Enhancement for example
And it starts to
Take an image that's kind of muddied and it will apply the machine learning to a tank
Clear it up
So basically what looks like a fuzzy picture becomes a crystal clear picture of
Exactly what it should be
Sewing machine has learned what something is supposed to look
So I'm thinking for image recognition maybe in the Smart Home
This could be
A tremendous tremendous value but that's just one of many possible avenues for this
You don't have in your Roomba have
Processing
Actually recognized
Furniture
I know it's Pat but I can tell you that
My cabinets definitely have little Roomba
Ruffles
Bam Bam
So that kind of stuff
Would be helpful also things like learning who people are in their emotions around the house that's definitely something that you
What companies are investing in
All kinds of
So I'm excited about this
I would tie it to
A couple things one
Intel bought a company called movidius
And status
Computer vision on the device which is really in
So they have an effort and play here and they actually launched a dongle it's a little
Basically neural network stick
They can train things at the edge
And then Qualcomm also has a very
Big effort income
Computer vision at
The edge
So
What we're seeing
When is
Trend in kind of a shift in thinking so we used to think
With machine learning there's two elements Thursday
Learning part where you're training a computer model and that's done on gpus and in the cloud
And then there's the execution site
Which has been done
At the edge
Andon
What we're seeing
Is this idea that maybe we can do some basic training
Even so build models on the device that's where the industry is trying to
I don't know if we're ever go
Can I get there but
I think if we're going to get there they're going to need this type of
Technology where that comes from Google or somebody else is irrelevant that's what's needed for sure and just to set that one second
Deep dream that's the computer vision program I was thinking about you look it up
But if you take a look online at Deep dream you can see visually what I was talking about Google uses the tensorflow for the smart reply
I seen lot of its messaging applications
And that reason context of a message and provide you with your three possible
Are multiple possible responses that actually make sense contextually
This is true this this is true but think about this
Instead of just getting
Smart home notifications for example that are just
Pretty cans
And are always the same
How about something with more context
Casino such as
Well I just
I get tired of the door has opened or disclosed kind of things
Maybe it should say so and so just step through the door
What is home
I said that's where we're going
I think I agree with you
Superfund super inter
Christine
Supra eKEY
All right
There's some
SmartThings
SmartThings is getting an update later
This week
Actually
Local
Because it has
Spell but even if you don't have cellular backup
What's going to happen is for your lights and some alarms they're going to be able to run locally on the Hub
Which means if your internet goes out
You will still have your lights turn on and off
But this will only happen
If you have it on a schedule
If you're like me and you have a lot of stuff to set to sunrise and sunset
It's not going to
Is that actually
The cloud
Sprite well that's kind of a shame because
If a device is still on even though it doesn't have a connection is not like the
The time has gone down the time just continues on the on the Hub
That's really weird
Well it's because they have to pull out
Get the different the different time every day I get that
Awesome
Here's where we should be going
Pull that time down
Store it locally
And then keep it for a day
24 hours
That would be
A fun way to go
Maybe someone
And it's kind of complicated
They've got child apps
The SmartThings app
This is really
I'm getting back into smart
Set of a hiatus
Maybe we'll do a special segment just that
It's a good idea so that's actually a hub update
Yes
Your house
That's a later this week there's actually been an app update this week as well
Which hopefully people happy about interviews and getting back into smart thing so maybe you can give it a try
They've added scenes
Which is nice to have
As well as visitor lock
Code-switch I love the idea that
I don't think I have that
Today on my system so I would like that
And also a fingerprint authentication for the app
Which
Alicia already have that anyway but
The scenes in a lock code
The two big he's here so you can go update your SmartThings app
Codes are
I can issue lock
That's correct you can because in the developer notes of release notes it says create unique lock code for visitors to a
Access your home
Very funny
Speaking of locks
I should let anyone know
If you're using the Comcast Xfinity home
Set up
And services
They actually just added for different
Kwikset locks
To their plot
So
Yay
Stacey's happy
Kwikset locks on my game
If you're going that route in the August locks but
This way
It's all in the same place
It's fine we should actually maybe we should
You talk a little bit about
Lox B
Because one of the other stories that I saw this week
Was
John Cena
Which two thing up coverage there is latches teaming up with
The company called
Comelit
4 Apartments
And latches a lock
How late is a intercom
Picture and I actually get a lot of questions for people who live in
Apartments about how they
Can integrate their smart locks with control of the internet
Any answer right now is
You really can't
But
What this does is there saying that this intercom
Company is going to work
With these smart
Lakme curso comelit
It's another intercom
Company is nelo
They have said in the past that they're going to do something like this but
They haven't
So
I thought this was interesting cuz I get so many questions from
People saying
Hey
I want to be able to Grant entry to someone and not just into my apartment but all the way up to
My door
Wish I could be
Kind of it feels like where we're going if you think about
Amazon key
August in the
Their access program
Image taken
Talk about this
Dislike
What you need to let people in
You know Amazon needs a camera
As somebody point
In and out
Fraud detection
And for you to know who's coming and going
August is the same thing they use their doorbell
They also I think
With Nest on that
Do we really want
I mean
In general or I mean if I lived in an apartment complex
Sexy I think I would want this
You know I'm not home somebody buzzes
The intercom
Person that the
Front desk
Says they're not home and sends me an alert and I can decide to let them in my
Apartment or not
I kind of like that
As for my house
I don't know I mean
I just mentioned before the show that I'm thinking about getting out
Ring doorbell for the front door
And I may have to figure out how to make it work to
Unlock my door if I want the door unlocked like maybe I want the UPS guy to put something in my house cuz I'm not home
I can just unlock the door for me
I know it's him
Die, I like it
But I managed case
Yeah and I'm still like
I think about the number of people who don't want like an Amazon Echo in their home because it's always listening and I'm thinking those people are probably not going to let
UPS guy in
Warehouse
No
So we definitely wouldn't I mean it's
To me it's if you bought into the whole smart home especially with cameras
Lifestyle so to speak
Then
Yeah you would want this
Otherwise probably not
Well here we have it yes I'm still puzzling over this
I'm still
That's okay
Let's talk about
Your review of
The wing
Cuz we both got
Toys
Okay I'm scratching my head a little bit over the wink Lookout
So let me start off by saying that
And the reason scratching my head is not because it doesn't do what
It advertises
To do because it does basically
In the lookout can't you get a Wink 2 hub
You get two door window sensors magnetic sensors that are Z-Wave
You get a motion sensor again
Aussie wave
And you get a siren
Also see
Pairing everything
I did struggle a little bit and I find this a lot with Z-Wave devices I have to be really close to the hub
And I don't know if that's your experience Stacey but
I really loved when the wing
Cub went Wi-Fi
Special
I liked that about the wink Hub cuz I would just bring it with me to wherever I was trying to
Yes
And that I did that exactly that when I did my zwave door lock
So that's
You're right
In this case these
Little devices are all
Small enough for me to just walk up stairs and go next to the wink Hub while I'm in the
Setup program
Once I did that cuz I
I was trying to do it from a couple runs away was not working
Once I got close
Everything paired fine
The motion sensors
Are super
Super super good my opinion there are at least five different sensitivity settings so you can
You know if you got pets and things you can reduce the settings
You can
Say don't send me alerts unless there's motion for more than
1 2 5 10 minutes whatever you like that I like
The door window sensors also work well no problems there
I will say in this is not specific to wink
I have like traditional molding around my door so the molding is not flat which makes it very difficult to attach
A door window sensor of any kind
To it
So just say that for people who have
Similar molding
Have some issues there
But again that's industry-wide is not a
Knock on wink at all
The siren
As a chime feature which I like or you can have it now
Blaring really loud alert alert you know
Three different volume settings on that which is
Just good sided forgot my dog is everything connected really well
And there is I think everybody should have this now in the Wing Cap there's a new look out Prada
But it's not a product per se because it's more of a
I'll call a platform or a way to get into the
Lookout settings
So
When you go in there you can actually see what you can connect and even though they didn't send me this I was able to connect my nest camera
The lookout settings
What Lookout actually does it's an alert system
And that sounds like will shortz a security system
What I mean by that is anytime any of these things
Text motion or a like that
You will get an alert
When you get the alert on your phone in the app
You can choose to sound the siren
You can choose to call 911
Choose to
Call a friend
So it's
Taken all of the security aspects and giving them to you and you decide what you want to happen
That works
But it also introduces some
Challenges and if you have a traditional security system obviously you got a keypad or way to disarm the system by a
Maybe with a new nest for example you can use an RFID tag
Swiper NFC tags
Parmer Dessau
There's no way to do that here and that I think is going to be a challenge because it's all at base
And one of the particular challenges in
I've set this up to automatically
Go on and alert for things
From 11 at night
Until 5:30 in the morning so overnight
Somebody walks in the house through my front door
Or the door window sensor or motion sensor
Text the siren will go off cuz that's what I want to happen
What is my son
Works late comes in at 1 in the morning doesn't know
If it systems on or not
Doesn't even have the app
I got to sign him in as me
And he's got it basically turn off the alerts before he walks in
And my family is not going to do that
So that's going to be a challenge
Yeah you're coming
You're starting to know that they're actually starting to now and that's
Actually why they don't have the Wink app installed because they don't need the app
Because I just tell
The lights to go on and off as they need you now
So that's crate at Amazon
Yeah which is great but now as they're engaging in that which is awesome
Now how do I get them to use the security system
Oh
I would say maybe voice recognition
Analog one day and then you could be like it's just me
And that would work but that's not going to happen
Cuz the false positives
Non-recognition
It's still pretty
Yeah
Speaking of
Amazon still doesn't know
Who I am
Really
Really it is the saddest
Satisfy
No personalization for Stacy
I haven't tried it in my house because again they just use the
Lights on lights off kind of stuff
What are the challenges is everyone has to have the
Their own
Mattimeo
Each of them on their own app
You have to log out of you
Re-login is that
For each one
It's a little convoluted
Identity management
This sounds
And I was looking for a presence detection.
Tobias Forge
Disarm
You're right
I kind of feel like that's the missing piece here
And I understand why wink went this way because their feedback they've got
What they tell me they want people to be in control of their security systems
A total control
And you do if there's no question them succeeded in this
This is perfect for somebody who lives alone
If you have to worry about those
Scenarios that I was talking about
Not right and you have total control but
It just feels like there's a
Piece missing
Truly arm disarm
And
You can do some automation bits and I've done some butt
It almost feels like they don't want you to in a sense cuz I don't really tell you how to set up robots
Their schedules or anyting
With this kit and I mentioned this to that man like I get who this kid is game four because as a hub you're talkin about first-time smart
Home buyers
But if you're talking about the buyers
You got to tell them how to do the automation bit
We've had to figure it out along the way we got good at it but connecting everything is fine but then how do you make it all work together
That's kind of missing for a new person I think
And again I just maybe some stuck in a traditional security mindset of this arm / disarm
But I think that's a lot of you think
Stihl.
Well and I would say that in some ways that's
Because like when I was a kid growing up my parents had an alarm and they kept it
On
So they'd hear the beep beep beep
When I open the door
Same here that you could hear it beep beep beep with the siren and the chime sure they're also potentially going to get
Notification after notification after notification on a smartphone
Like every time somebody walks past a motion sensor
Which is a good price and there's no monthly fee or anything because again
It's not
Professionally monitored it's
Immaturely monitored by you I don't think it's a bad product I just think it's probably for a very specific
Type of user
That makes sense
All right well if you're that kind of user you like hearing your smartphone you like notifications
You want to really know what's going on in your house this
Happy for you
All right
Before I get to my toy
We're actually going to take
AR
Voicemail
From the
Internet of Things podcast listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of electronic lock
Schlage smart locks work with most home and security system so you can get the most out of your lock whether you're an Apple homekit user
You love Amazon
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
Alright this week
On the iot
Iccl Kevin my name is Hugo and my calling from Montreal I sent
Tuesday
Asking her what she thought about
The wife
$20 1080p full HD night vision two-way audio camera
$20
Reviews from cdnuts last year
Call tmw my question is fairly simple is it safe to use
Secure where are those image going and more generally what should I look for
Or if I want to get any type of camera
The outside can is a little bit less worrisome for me but inside cam
Could be something that they don't hold it
More something I would think more about to wear
Data is going obviously there is an account be saved
For 7 days
The things that are recorded
So it's all good and it's very cheap
However I don't know if it's a
Thank you so much guys I will be looking out for an answer
However you wished
I will about you
Okay good news for you Hugo
I just
Bought and received my wyze camera
My $20 tiny cute camera oh my gosh
It is adorable
And it works
And for your accused
It has a slot for an SD card
Which means it doesn't have to
So
If you are interested in where the stuff goes and I think it's smart of you to ask these questions
There are security breaches
Time so
With this
Can set up motion detection I set that up it seems pretty responsive so
And then when I open the app
I can see the live stream
I can record
My voice and talk to people
Over the cap
Camera so that
That's good I can hear stuff
My sound off
I can hear stuff if I want
There is night vision
That seems to be pretty good although I haven't
Play with it in the app
End
If you go under settings
You can send
Vocal recording to a MicroSD card
So for twenty bucks
Sounds great Scott the SD card slot if you
Don't want to send the data to the storage card
Where can you save it or does it get sent to
It seems it on the app
And then it shows
Photos on
Okay so it's not going to the cloud
Does not appear
Okay then there's a reason I ask this
That's because
I don't think we've yet figured out what the
Portico best and safest practices here for webcams because why don't we send the data to the cloud
Well cuz we don't want
The companies to
Have it
Can hack and so on and so forth
So you want an SD card slot okay that makes sense to
Which this. Is which is awesome
But if I'm breaking through the house and I see this thing
And I noticed there's a little
I'm making that card out
Rob my house
I mean I know it's an extreme example and I know what most people
Breaking into a house that probably aren't going to notice this but
I just there's like no guarantee you'd have the date at that point
This is the same debate I had
Like 10 years ago when I started uploading all my CDs
Is 2
My
Terabyte drive
I was like I have converted all my CDs to you know
Flac files
And it took a long time it was a lot of work
Working then
I put them on my
Local hardware but then I was like what happens if this fails
So then I was like okay I'll buy Carbonite backup
This is
It's the same kind of situation
Yeah but it's a dilemma that I think is it's more personal here because now it's pictures inside your house
So I think people need to decide
Am I going to trust
Any company with this
And if so pick that company and get a camera that works with that company
Or no I'm not going to
Trusted company have an SD card slot and manage it myself and hope that nobody takes the card slot or just walks away with a camera
And I'm in if they walk away the camera then they walk away with the SD card
Portable
It's exactly
Yes I mean it's it looks like a camera
You can tell it would have signs you can tell it's a camera I mean ultimately what I guess what we really want is
Hidden camera so to speak to that way
You wouldn't have to worry about somebody walk
And or the data on it
Well then you can turn the indicator light on or off
So I could put this in and out of
See I returned that indicator off if I'm going to store to an SD card together
I will also tell you guys
I rather you go I will tell
Netatmo
Welcome camera also stores data to
Either an SD card or your own
To be server
Which might be an interesting
Way to
If you set it up to the store to your server
Someone
You have to take your server
Yep I'm making that again
So
It's a nice camera I like it alot I like it actually more than the
Best camps
So
Although some people complain about that Atmos customer service and they are not wrong to
Is there a French company and they tend to be
Less responsive
They are eventually respond
They're not
That is
Really all the news
To print this week
Cabinet
You can say hi to us
PCS around
Too at the end of November November 30th I will be
Hosting an event at the Target open house
Talk about iot business models with
Schlage
Canary
And
Hi
So we'll be talking about how to establish trust between
Can users
Why companies may need to charge for things and I'll come
So if you are in San Francisco November 30th
You should come to that event
Will leave a link in the show notes
I think
That is it for
Are section that stay tuned for a message
Our sponsor and
An interview with Michael Sherwood who is the director of technology and Innovation for the city of Las Vegas
He talks about some really cool stuff
And if you're going to say yes you'll be able to see it in person
From The Internet of Things podcast from our sponsor
Cognition and I've got Stewart killing here to talk to us about
Promise is critical infrastructure
The powers
Just about
Alright Stewart
Sparkcognition is using a improve safety and reliability
Can you give me some real examples of ways that utilities
Are using
To offer more advanced
Capabilities
Absolutely for example we're working with
One of the largest
Producers of wind energy in the country invenergy
And we're working with them
To be able to
To help.
Specific
Donuts on their wind turbines
Very specifically on there
Gearbox
On turbine and what we're doing is we're taking the same techniques
Facial intelligence
Machine learning algorithms
Using our Technologies in art
Tools and what we're providing them is
Lead time
In terms of failure
Prediction
For the
Gearbox
Does AKA
Opponents of the
Turbine are about to sail
I love it so how can machine learning improve equipment reliability and
Performance
We're working with some of the leading utilities
We're looking at operations on their gas
Part of that what we're able to do is we're able to identify
Operation
Conditions that
Their subject matter expert
Want to wear a
Before implementing an AI tool
What this allows them to
To do is run
Machinery more efficient
Understand better
When it needs to be taken offline
Scheduled
Maintenance and really this helps
Improve their bottom line both from
Keeping the machine running
As well as reducing maintenance
Cost from unexpected breakdown
Failures
Okay so you mentioned humans
What is the role of human subject matter
Machine learning
We still find that there's a tremendous value in the
The subject matter expert
As you mentioned them humans
May I at least in
Some of the industrial world where it can be sort of Celsius
Sustaining
There's still a lot of information about
We might come up with
The result
And we really need the humans
To help us understand
What does
Results are telling
So our goal isn't necessarily.
Replace the humor
Can we augment their capability
Instead of them taking a shotgun approach
Looking at every
Machine all the time because they really don't understand
If we can help them with a i
Focus their information Focus
Is there knowledge
Specific use cases
Pacific problem
Seen and then allow them to
Is there expert
They can augment
The outcomes
Lisa thinking about
Facebook
If we can start showing examples
Mudding to humans
Hit the like button
On
Titan Machinery to weather a
Results was good
More bad then
The machine can start learning
And eventually it can improve its results that the humans are
Where can I go to find out
Tsac your listeners
Can go to www. Smart cognition. Com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Michael Sherwood who is director of technology and
An innovation for the city of Las Vegas
Hi Michael how are you doing today
I'm doing well thank you for having me
Excited because
Cuz I went to Vegas a couple weeks ago
And Michael took me on this wonderful tour
Around central or Vegas downtown Las Vegas
Downtown is correct
And I got to see all kinds of crazy street lights and things that most normal people would not be excited about
The thing that most impressed me though
Was
Is it you
You're the coolest job in the world so you are thinking about how to make cities smarter
Not just any
Stereotypical hey let's put a lot of sensors and cameras on lamp posts
Switch we will talk
But you seem to have a broader vision of how to make the city
So let's
Heart with your overall what's your pervy
What is it
That you're there to do in
Willis
To connect the community
And provide new avenues of a fish
C4 citizens and I like to call people that come to the city consumers
Whether you live here
Or you're visiting your
Assuming our product
We want to do is really have
Your experience
In Las Vegas be one-of-a-kind and if we can do that
Through iot
Technology to LP transversal
City a little bit more efficiently provide you with locations
Parking
Make the air around you more enjoyable or healthy
I just provide you a level of safety that you have while you're here
What is extremely important in
We really believe
The iot and The Internet of Things in general
Play a major role in that experience
All right in a lot of people are really
Stoat
About smarts
But it's also a huge
It's a huge project you can't just wave a magic wand
Or if your Google I guess you can buy 800 acres
In Toronto and just rebuild
But
As someone who's working with an existing infrastructure
What do you think are the first things a city should
Maybe
Connect or maybe it's just the first things they should consider
I think the first thing to consider is starting something have a plan
Understand what your priorities are we have
5 priority
But I understand what those priorities are
Have a plan but I think a lot of my peers the thing is they don't start anything they talk a lot they have a lot of plans
He never actually X
Anything I think what we do uniquely here
Is we do lots of pilot project
And try a lots of
For technology
Find out
Nothing like in a real lab environment
Knowing
If something works or doesn't you really don't know
You put it out into the field the downtown Las Vegas area we really set up as a
Technology we caught the Innovation District
Are we set up this area we can really
Test
Improve out things
Before we make large investment
In any one particular technology
People tracking in The Innovation disc
To count things like hay
There are x number of people who walked by this place
In a given time. And that's great for the economic
Chotu
Like Starbucks
Yeah that's that mean we've had really good
Exceso
We have now 50 of Those sensors throughout the downtown area
And we're counting not just people but
The difference between Motor Vehicles
Pedestrian
And cycle
So now we're able to
Take that data and show Developers
And local business owners
Here's the amount of people that foot traffic that comes
By weather
Vehicle and it's important to know if it's in a vehicle or walking by your location and in the past
The city would only send a surveyor out maybe once a year and it was sitting in a lawn chair in
Everything manually now we have these sensors that are constantly on 24 hours a day
7 days a week
And now we'll start we have these traffic
Patterns now that we can actually see the number of people and then if they're in a vehicle versus pedestrian versus a cyclist
And we really think economic wise
That's going to be so
Great data that are Developers
And other business people will be excited about as well
So let's go back to the Innovation District
Because this is what we toured
Part of
And just talk to me a little bit about
How that came to be
What you're doing
Sure so in March of twenty
16 to the city council designated
A large area in the downtown Las Vegas area so for those of you that
Are familiar with
Las Vegas to Fremont Street
Experienced witches
Original
Las Vegas and
Incorporates several different
Areas around it
So when the city council built this Innovation District obviously we've included the Fremont Street which is all the casinos and hotels
That everybody knows and loves
About Las Vegas
But it also includes our Medical Center where we have our County Hospital A Private Hospital
Throw in a bunch of medical
Support facilities around it
Which we consider that our Medical
Subdistrict within the innovation
District we have some
Business districts as well
Business supporting the city as a whole
We have an area of social economic
Do we want to improve
We have all these little mini districts
What's in this Innovation District
And
Stay purpose of the Innovation District was to
Use it as a living lab
Truly test technology to test iot based
Tools and services to see how they work in a real environment
And if they would be
Scalable
To be able to move across
Or the pool across the entire city
Some of the things we are doing in the downtown area as we have
Cameras at intersection
That are actually analyzing
People will believe a bag behind for security purposes was more of a security functionality we're using
Video Analytics
To look at parking spaces.
Occupied or unoccupied
Hide we're doing air quality to imagine
89 cars at a light and it's red we're looking at sampling the air quality
And then based on the carbon emissions
Does Vehicles changing the light to Green
So that we don't have carbon buildup in the downtown area
Where people are obviously outside walking
From venue to venue
So we try to manage all these different
Aspects
We're doing other things with
Radar now and lidar
Where
We are scanning intersection
Looking for people walking into the
The street that they do
Then we can turn the light red
Lots of Pilots around that
But the data that we collect
We make available to the
The public as well and hoping they find ways one of their businesses or citizens
Those are all really good in fact I learned several things just talking to you
One was
That you can't have one camera that does it all
You've got
I think I saw three cameras on a light post each one of them had a different job in your very
Helpful in explaining why that was so
Let's talk about some of the concrete things that you
Learned so far
Because I feel like when we talked about iot
We tend to get excited about
Really cool things that can happen but we neglect to think about all the Practical learning
Going to place
So things like oh yeah you need three cameras
So I don't know if you want to pick a project that
Changing the light for
Cars that are idling the
That might be an interesting thing
Everything she learned
Shirt woot
Probably the most fascinating one and I get the most
Questions on
Stuff the most complex one in the one we probably learned the most
As we've gone through this journey and continue our journey
But you would think the very simplest sounds
Sensor reaches
Is a certain level
Sends a signal
That signal turns
It changes a light green
It sounds simple
I penciled it out we worked on it at
It seems very easy but no we started learning quickly was obviously there's lots of little things that we weren't even
Paired for
One just getting the buy-in of everybody around you think it sounds really good and
People would want
Partaken nut
But as soon as you start talking about it there's a lot of
Well do we want to do this why are we doing this
So we had to break through Jess
The internal politics
Around Prague
Just like that
Tacitly
Is
Who's going to be the installer
Obviously the city hits
City traffic lights
We don't want a 3rd party installer doing it so you
You try to accommodate
That component of who's going to be responsible who's installing who's touching what when and then when you start getting into
Just more of
The actual interface
So
The air sensor Caesars we have
How to send it to a legacy
Traffic system
That's not current with what we could say current
Software standards
So we have to write an interface
In order to for it to do that and then add fail-safes
Into that interfaces
As well and so before you know it's something that I figured would be a 3245 damp
Implementation is now we're at 5 months
And we're close now to actually
Having it
Fully work the way we intended it
But the
Amount of time in the
Enforce
Seeing things
That came up
Constantly required us to go back
And evolve the project revolve to specify
Applications
To get to the point where we are now or we ask
You have
We consider a functioning
Project same thing very similar with
Hazard light are intersect
Project you can use the lidar radar for two things one seeing a
Pedestrian
Walk across the
Street on a green when they should be waiting
The other thing would be for wrong way driver 210
It's on a one-way Street if
Cars going the wrong way
This radar lidar system would be able to
Have signage
On the street
Saying hey wrong way
Flash of the driver host
Reseda and stop
And realize you're on the wrong Street
Again sounds very simple
In concept
But it's actually taken
From concept
I'm putting it into the
Street itself and then seeing how it operates in making all the connection
Is a lot of it
Just the ticking this
Newer iot technology and have it work
With more Legacy taipei
Systems that just weren't designed
To accept the input that were trying to give
I'm working through that it's just takes a lot longer than in
What about so that's fair I deal with that whatever
Can imagine
When Public Safety is on the line
How much time do you spend thinking about
The rules of
This kind of
So I thought it was kind of funny
Just thinking about oh my gosh
There's too much traffic building up
The air quality suffering
Turn the light green
Oh my gosh there's a pedestrian in the middle of the intersection don't do that
I just got to start thinking about how complicated that kind of
Rule setting
Might
B-but we discuss internal I mean so and then some of the fun things about the discussion is
Where tacotaco at the light or in the fishing industry
The kid was
It's kind of a troublemaker
Probably still in Canada
Troublemaker you were discussing
We actually had to come
What ifs
Kid on the sidewalk find out about the
What is lidar system
And jumps into the street and then jumps back over
How do we
How to prevent a bunch of people from jumping into this
Rihanna Jump
Back over
And not having all the lights on
The city turn
Red
Could I be a safety
Concern
Some kind of prom suits
We actually do have some deep inside discussion and again we try to go towards
You're the reason we're doing a pedestrian goes back to one of our five principles which is
Public Safety
And so
We design around us but there's a lot of
People who know is there a problem
Accessories getting hit why are you doing this and answer is no we have a pretty low pedestrian fatality rate
But the same time
One fatality is one
Too many
So let's talk about dealing with citizens
Because
That is a
Challenge
To say the least there is concern about their concerns about privacy
Surveillance
They're also
You know concerns about your taxpayer dollars and where those go so someone once told me in smart cities
If you can't provide a citizen use case
The city council will not
Even listen to
Which is probably true
So how do you think about
Selling this and educated
The citizenry
But you brought up a lot of me a lot of great points so
Obviously privacy is a big deal a lot of people
Have no trouble
Going on to Facebook other social media application
Tell everybody I'm out of town
Having a great dinner
And don't think anything about
Privacy
In that regard yet in the government space
If I
Put out information
Before immediately suspect of that we already have a huge barrier
To overcome
I think a lot of what we're doing is
Around education right now and letting the
Actual population know what we're doing so
A lot of what we're doing is not
Users
Pacific yet we're working on some identity manager
Programs
The lot of what we're doing right now in the iot space
Is aligning what we believe our citizens needs with city council priorities
So when we talk about providing the temperature
And weather condition
Google say at a city park it's not just about providing that the citizens will see that part of it and will
Purdue sat on a website and on her mobile app so that people
Can get that data but we're also using that data
To find out when we need the water
The fields
And
What makes sense based on
Actual
Conditions at
The facility rather than just using the sprinkler timer
And timing it daily
So what are you saying
Different sensors
To achieve
What we consider multiple successes
But then the other piece on that is how do we use that data that were collecting
To help better the
The city internally
So how do we take that
Weather information and use it in our maintenance
Find better patterns on when the water knowing how many people are coming to
Parking at what time
So we can schedule maintenance
Mission operations around
When there's the least amount of people
At the
Facility a lot of data at a high level
And then looking at how
We can make it
A better experience
For all that are there
Now we are working on other products
And programs that use your specific
Identity inhabit
To build a better experience
But on those type of
Ideas
One you have to opt-in for it to privacy is a very big
Certain the laws here in our state
Still haven't caught up to the touch
Technology
So that's going to be a major challenge hopefully next legislative session
Will be able to have some additional protect
For the consumer as far as how we can use their data or not release it
So that there is
Privacy
For the individual at the same time that they have privacy
They get the benefits
What does technology
You can do for them
Let's go to your vision of the city of
The future cuz you're putting together some crazy stuff there
Let's visit Las Vegas in 10 years
There's a lot I mean so we'll pick some of the bigger things off I think that I'm going to say that
Do we really want that Amazon experience and what I mean by that I would say Amazon experience with a little touch of
Nordstrom's in there
Look at delivering City service
In that same way
Meaning when you login
My mobile app lets you use
Parking lot 12 downtown every week and we know that we're going to resurface that lot
So now that we know that you use that lot we're going to now send you a push notification automatically this is hip the next two weeks you
Use lot 13 because 12 is going to be research
Another idea would be we noticed that you
Sign up your son for daughter for baseball or softball
Every year
And bring it to you
Additional
Sports programs
During the off-season
Automatic
If you have any go research and find out we would send you
Apus notification saying hey
This is for you
This will help you
Get additional classes at maybe
You weren't aware of
I'm look at that is helping Drive our Revenue
As well as providing the end
Consumer additional information that they wouldn't have had
How many goes on from
Using your phone to pay for your parking to pay your sewer bill
Weave
Used and started to build applications for the Amazon Echo platform
As well as
For Google home
And now the Amazon show
Which is an upgraded Amazon
Product with a screen built
Intuit
So now you can ask
AC
As well as here
And so really is making
Government as transparent as possible but very
Hi touch
High service oriented
Where you really feel connected
And if you're able to get the
Information that you need in the most timely manner
Vanessa from everything
From a safer environment your street light goes out on your
Street
As soon as it goes out
It's not about you having
You call us we already know what's out and hopefully
We replace it before you even know that the lights burnt out of those a type of things that were looking at
Do you really
Going Beyond
What
Traditional government that I call up and I never get a response to
Hey I didn't even have
Call they called me and help me or they message
Instant messenger
Give me your day
Send me an email or automatically alerted me on the app
So it's really about that service
Level
I mean we're looking at doing fiber optics
Downtown
Where we would look at providing internet Based Services
Everybody not just
Two selected area stole a lot
Really give our city a competitive advantage through either education
And Technology
I don't see any limit the sky's kind of the limit
As far as what we're looking at implementing and
The technology just we will
Yo testing
Actually
Deploy at one point in the future
Alright I kind of look forward to that
Nature vision and let me ask you one final question where does the money for all of this
So right now
Majority of it comes from companies that want to be here and obviously
We have a huge technology show called CES every year so we kind of have that as an advantage more companies will put their technology and down
Downtown at no cost
Sublime we can test it to they can show customers
That come to
CES in January
This one
Obviously we do have a budget set aside for innovation
This past year was $1000000
And we've been
Leveraging that as we do these Pilots
And
Additional testing
But really down the road we kind of see
The ability of
Proving
If we're able to put a technology out there
That actually saves money so we're looking at trash can sensors right now people we have
Physical laborers that go up and down the street
And look at all the trash can if they're empty or full
And no matter what right now they drive up and down and they checked
Well if we were able to put a sensor in the trash can to say if it was empty or full
And we didn't have to go to Every trash can ever
Everyday
That would be a savings
We're looking at that those savings mechanism
2 then be funded redirected
Back into the Innovation fund and it would be a fun that would eventually pay for itself
Through efficient
And we think that is one
Great way of long-term
Sustainability
A lot of what we work on with all the technology
We're talking about
Is sustainability how do you keep these
It's going to just
Can't put in 10000 sensors
And then
How do you keep from going after 3 years when the batteries die or you need to replace
And what are you get the money to do that
Exactly all right
Michael
You have been a Funt
Information
I love it
Thank you so much for
For coming on the show this week
Thank you but I'd love to come back again it's been a real pleasure in
Obviously Vegas is open to everybody so can we hope to get everybody out here and
Enjoy it and see
The technology we have
Yeah if you're a CES
This year guys
You should actually go
Stop out that's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Is please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com thanks for listening at
I will see you next week