Everyone welcome to
The Internet of Things
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a fantastic show for you today we are going to be talking
About the latest stats on Smart speakers
We've got an if
Integration for Sonos
A 6.7 billion dollar chip
To talk about
Welcome
Latest
We're chip nxp
Actually has AC
Security chip for Google
And
We got a new iot security bill
It's on the governor's desk
Just so you know we're not talking about Apple because we're recording like
A few hours before it happen
We've also got a lot of little news such as
Samsung launching its
Iot tracker
We're on the LTE network
We talk about the past
Updates on my June of an issue updates on
Kevin's Nest Yale lock
Issue
We're going to talk a little bit about what we know about the Ikea blinds and we've got a message from this week sponsor
SAS
Plus our guest this week is an Bocce a baby who's going to talk about
520 billion dollar industry that iot will be
In 2021
When and who gets it
And as always
What is her
Voicemail from our
Listener
So let's get the show started
With a message
From one of our spot
This week sponsor is chocolate 64% of iot customers report problem
Problems with their iot products don't waste time and money by manually identifying
Web server aquatrax architecture Regional patterns system
And your application to identify when where and what cause beer
Stop settling and start fixing problems before your customers find
Get started today and chocolate. IO that's chocolate auk
Let
.
IO
And speaking problems I forgot to tell you that we're going to talk about the brilliant
Smart Switch
Which I did have a few problems with
So heaven
Let's get started
Which
Voice
We got some new stats from Adobe
None of these really surprised me
But I will admit to having
I think I hard voice
Smart speaker user
In Seattle came out
The big thing is 70% of people report using a voice assistant
Music 64%
Museum for weather
53% use it to ask fun question
All of that is true
Children laptop
The I don't ask fun questions me maybe before the show is we're just kind of goofing off or something
Not so much in everyday life
Not so much I know that on my Echo Show sometimes it'll show me
Questions to ask
Ask Madame a
What we call Amazon Echo
Ecosystem
Assistant
So we don't set off yours so it's like
Ask Madame what the big news is today
My daughter in heaven
Oh
What is the big news
And that's usually
Yeah and you're right about this report from Adobe they asked 1000 us
Smart
Speaker owners what they do with their devices
It wasn't anything any new activities or like old I should try that but what was interesting is
Be kind of rank the usage patterns
And those stats you just
Phone number for primary activities the ones that I use
Are the emerging use cases
Which is weird because I've been using these for so long and I guess
I don't know I just weird but
I'm looking at things like only 31% use them for smart on the commands
Yeah or
36% from making calls
That is more of an emerging use case because that's
More
Relatively new features I get that one
The people actually asked about their calendar.
Schedule for sports scores just as much as I do smart home commands
I'm like wow maybe just cuz we've been doing the smart on things so much
Longer than most people
Yeah I think this
Said we're definitely
But we are definitely
Yeah
And I was actually curious so
Food delivery
Domino's has had
A skill for a while
Hotel and flight research
Are you doing that
No not there
Okay that was my thought
Set a temperature to be like
Maybe just maybe it is a really good feature that we're not using because I mean we book travel and when you do it
Later I do it I typically go through an app or through the web
Yeah I'm almost all web
Because I want to see all the options in right now
My apps are all like
That's just crazy
Yeah so other things to know is 32% of consumers reported owning a smart speaker in August 28th
Looks like a third of
Consumers
Here in the US this is compared to 28% in January
Of this year so it's a 14% increase in 8 months
And
I don't know I didn't think that makes total sense to me people are constantly sending in questions
Stop the show they're like
Hey which one should I get
For I just bought one
What should I do now
Basically people are more
Comfortable really curious
Cuz it talks about
How people who have these start becoming
You mentioned
That your family doesn't
Like talking to
Smart speaker is that changing at all
You know
If you were to just ask me and I can think of that I take that is not changing and all they barely use it
I have to admit
As I think back
Oversaw the past
Seizure year-and-a-half
They probably do and I think of cases like
Are downstairs lights come on before dusk every night
Automatic just have
But if it's cloudy out it's a little darker before that
So my wife
Is sitting in the living room and it's dark and she will say Madam a turn on the downstairs
Not maybe that's because there's really not much of an alternative for her because
You know she knows if she messes or touches switches in the house
That's going to mess things up
So maybe it's by
Sheer lack of choices but yeah she's doing it she doesn't seem as self-conscious about it
Voyager wife
Pretty much
It's forced adoption
Okay
So
Not really speaking voice actually but this is the other side of switches
Something else idevice talking to you
Maybe instead of you talking to a device
If this then that or if
We talked about it all the time
We use it till I connect web services to devices or web services to other web services
Using simple if this happen
Do that to me
They have an integration now with Sonos
Yay
So
Michael was to create
I have a right now I'm testing
Nest
It is sometimes the doorbell chime
I think this is the nest issue
I think it's tired
Is that a legitimate
Excuse I don't know
But I was like when people press the doorbell
Let's have the Sonos make
Unfortunately the nest is not supported and if that particular
Aspect of it
Cameras seem to have support
Vanessa
Ecosystem
And I just been playing with my weird motion sensors are things happening
X
You do need to be careful
It becomes really irritating really quickly
Like for example when your phone gets into your Wi-Fi
Zone
Having
George theme song play
It sounds like a lot of fun
But
It kind of sucks when you come into your wife
It's like 2 in the morning and everybody Sonos comes on
Yeah I could see that being annoying so coming home from say travel or something yet were even like if you hooked it up with
They supported webcam that one
Camera saw you
Walk in the house
It would play your songs or whatever
If somebody taking a nap or something like that that's probably not cool
You can set time limits oh
Unless it is
Between
10:00 at night
Sexy morning I have to be careful because my daughter has a Sonos in her
And she goes to bed earlier than everyone
Just little things to think about but you can't have a lot of fun with this
I think an interesting use case would actually be a button
So if you have their lots of
Logitech pop buttons I've tested
Pebblebee buttons a lot of those are supported
On if
And you can actually create a button that plays your
Your favorite song
Your favorite playlist
I feel like coming on
Quick
Aside from choosing like a predefined
Centos favorite
Song album artist cetera playlist
You
Get quite a bit of functionality here generation aside from basic playback controls
Pause resume next previous you can even control the volume so
You have a doorbell and supported in the doorbell rings Maybe
They couldn't mute
This I know so you can go answer the door and peace and quiet
That is actually one of my favorite things that the yonomi software did
I just started this I'm glad you mentioned that
Whenever my phone would ring
It would actually mute my Sonos has that were playing
Which is kind of sucky if
Like my daughter
My phone re
Insert news cases this is actually really nice
And
You know you could actually set that up on your iOS or Android
Easily
I wonder I haven't looked at the new if denigration but I wonder if you can
Set this to
Specific Sonos devices so that if you have multiple ones
Maybe your daughter is doesn't mute button
The one in your living room
So I kiss you
A lot of options
Moving right along
Okay next we have a ginormous
Semiconductor deal
You guys know how much I love my semiconductor
So this is Renee sis
It is
Agreed
To buy integrated device technology Inc
46.79
This helps
Renee says get into
Semiconductors
Sand
You guys may not be
Here where this but today's cars have
So much silicone on them it is a
Huge deal with
Qualcomm CSR
And
Then later when
Tried to buy nxp automobiles were actually the driving
Shell Manassas is second only to nxp in auto-related chips and it's got about 30% of the market
Kit for microcontroller
So
It does need the analog chipset integrated device
And just so you guys
Analog chips are those that can
Convert analog stick
Signals like sound waves
Analog day
Any sort of physical
Happening in to digital
And that's really important cars for like pressure sensors
So this isn't like a super secret
Kind of deal is part of a larger Trend in
Consolidation among semiconductor manufacturers
Part of this is
Because
As you get into iot
Average selling prices of the
The chips
Are much lower
You are selling a whole lot more
But they're cheaper
So you really need a lot more
Is a scale associated
He had two quick notes to the store a man it's good news
For Sure Fit industry
This is the second big acquisition
Vanessa says made this year and those two Acquisitions including the 6.7 now total 10 billion dollars
That's a big chunk of change they bought
Intersil witch again
Yes analog ships
Free sample but the other thing to know
And I know this IDT which
Okay yes they have chips that they can supply for the automaker's
They only generate 11% of their revenue from Automotive
Industrial businesses so I just wonder if
It's a big price to pay for
For what they're getting we'll have to see
I don't know
Global did put Renee cesana negative credit watch
A lot of crazy stuff
S&P
Did not monitor my
Let's see
Qualcomm introduced a new one for wearable
Devices
And
Kevin saunderson
So it's good that they are introducing this but I am a little mitt on it I'll tell you why
So for those who don't know just about every single
Google
Android wearable now it's called where OS I apologize
Wear OS watch
Runs on a Qualcomm
Snapchat in chat with the old 2100
It came out 2 years ago and even then it was
Kinda getting a little long in the tooth
Now
It's good that Qualcomm Snapdragon wear
3100 is now
And there are no devices out with that yet although Montblanc has announced that they will have one very soon and I'm sure
CES but
Two thoughts here one is that it's really not that
Chip
Hardware that's been holding
Google smartwatch
Back
I'm sales is really been a kind of mediocre user experience with the interface which is changed majorly 2 or 3
Now so that's
Part 1 of this
Part two is
The 3100 chip
It
Is good in that it offloads most of the low-power stuff to a low-power
Processor that's also on this chick it's like a big little architecture there's two chips one that's heavy-duty processing and
One that's like processing
But it's not a major change in that chip technology from the 2100 it's really meant to boost battery life
Be smart watches so don't expect like
Major Performance gains although there probably be hard to measure in General on a smartwatch
The apps are so small but it just seemed like a very incremental thing for them to do when they could have done it a while ago to be honest
So that's why
Me mail
I am
And the reason why
Why is because
They
Qualcomm with this chip
They've introduced a low-power coprocessor that uses
What's called near threshold design okay
Are you guys ready
To get nerdy
This is a big deal so
Near threshold design
Has been buried
Early-stage Cutting Edge
Is
That you are basically giving the chip enough voltage
You're getting it
Plenty of voltage so you know it work
It's going to flip the switch
Which RAID is going to happen
Plenty of house
Your threshold says
We're just going to give you
Just enough
It's really hard
To do tight transistor design
Things like leakage become really important
So
There's no margin
And
It's pretty cool
And the fact that welcomes doing it because they do a lot of there
Manufacturing process
That means this is going to be accessible
To a lot of company
Significantly
The power
I'm going to tell you there's another chip company
And they actually do
Sub-threshold design
Just like this
Even more so
And those guys
Are in
Huawei wearables
Aspire
Wearable that you basically tape into your underwear
Tracks your activity
And other stuff that lasts for like a year and a half
So this is a really
Big deal
What Kevin sizes of matcha
In that is going to bring
Lower power
Coyote
Devices
I'm a little less may now
Okay
My Buddy Lee Ratliff who's an analyst he explains it really well he says power consumption is
Proportional to the square of the
So even a small decrease in voltage
Have a really big impact
If you slept through all of that
Wake up
Because nxp has announced a security chip for
Google iot Cloud
With an exciting name
Bissell wave people
Can I say
Let me see if I pronounce this correctly this is tricky
A71 ch
Nailed it
Thank you
So we don't have practice
We don't necessarily care about the name of the chip so much as we care about what this is this is linking
Security keys
To Google's cloud
This is very similar to the design
Microsoft azure
Project Sopris in the
You're linking
Particular cloud
Cloud OS
Security hard
Onnit ship
That's actually a lot of people look at that as the future of how we're going to develop
More secure iot devices
The fact now that
An excuse doing this for Google
Hey that's worth something
So that's why we
Now this this is a big deal named kidding aside is this a big deal nxp says that device credentials are pre injected in
Into the chip
And public keys are sent to the end-user through
Whatever interface is required etcetera
Security
The First iot Security bill
Has been approved in California
And is waiting at the governor's desk to be signed into
This is SB 327
Yeah so basically the big provision in this bill is that a manufacturer of a connected device
Shell
Equip the device with a reasonable security feature
Four features
That's a little
So that's concerning to me because what is reasonable security it just talked about authentication procedures such as
If it connected devices equipped for the means for authentication outside a local network there are two criteria that they Authentication
Systems must meet so unique passwords for example
Or it must proper user to set their own password
So this is
A good step forward
That's true in things like reusing Keys looks like it may not be
Acceptable
Under the sea
Password is 1 1 1 1
However
This is not an end all be all week
Because it does not deal with
Show me
TC security
But it is a start
We'll see how it is and
By the way we should update you on
Internet of Things cybersecurity
Improvement Act
Was in the US Senate
I didn't think this bill was all that other piece of cake basic
We talked about what devices the government should buy in the security standards
Pretty minimal but that isn't going anywhere right now
This is what we have in California's laws do actually 10 minutes
Enchiladas
Developments around the country B
Central State
So keep an eye on that
Okay
Moving on where security
Morbidness actually
Well one of them is the same button
And the other one
I think it's gasket and obviously everyone is Mariah and I
I tell you I'm wonderful ever stop talking about Mirai
Maybe in like
We just like
But tell us about
What's happening now
So the Palo Alto networks unit 42 has a new report out
MRI and
Gadget
Are basically moving beyond
The typical Target switch in the past we talked about such as connected cameras
And
Security systems and routers now it's moving into the Enterprise
It's because
The open
Source
Framework
Apache struts
Which is used for Java platform Enterprise Edition there's your Enterprise hook and was also what way
Was attacked in the Equifax breach last year they still unpatch Samurai is now targeting those systems
So now it's getting into potentially Enterprise job apps
That is not good so that's an expansion of targets there and then
Gasket
Which is also known as bad as light which is probably easier to say is attacking unsupported versions of
SonicWALL Global Management
System so
This is bad because it's going
Again Beyond
Yeah that's firewall product for networks in Enterprises and such so that is
Also bad
Extra bad
Okay well
Alright so any
Good news on that for
Not till these things get patched
UNF it just speaks to a bigger issue here
Add button that's another iot device
Hacks and attacks
They're not limited to a specific type of device or a specific client or a consumer or Enterprise
There were widespread and then we'll just keep
Looking for things to in fact
And it's really scary when you think about how many connected devices are out there we talked about this all the time billions and billions and you know it just
How do you patch everything is the question
Bummer
But let's talk about some quick updates
Newspaper
All right
Kevin I'm going to give this to you cuz you're the guy who found it
You know nobody seems to remember that but you're right and that we talked about in the podcast
Yes probably early August maybe Late July
Yeah I noticed an FCC filing for Samsung SmartThings tracker
And it was going to work with both Verizon and AT&T s
LTE
M1 Networks
And sure enough it just got an ounce this week
So think of this like a
Bluetooth tracker
Only doesn't use Bluetooth but if you have a tile or
Some other similar tracking device this is just like that except it has a GPS and it connects to
The in first case
AT&T network
It will cost you $99
It's real-time tracking again because of GPS you can set geofencing with it works with SmartThings and there's even a panic but
Just nice so you can use it as a personal tracker if you don't want to
Attach it to your luggage
$99 includes AT&T service
The first year after the first year you're going to be paying
$5 a month
Or $50 a year
Available later this
Tweek actually at select AT&T stores and
Samsung.
Compsych resume my Verizon model follow very soon because the FCC tested also for Verizon's
Those prices
Cesare kind of insane for tracking my luggage
Put
I mean in your kids backpack
If I were kidnapped
Which I am not doing if I were
The first thing I would do is throw away the
It might work
I would actually my dog used to be able to escape my fence and run all over the place I would put it on my dog
I love these case for it I mean
Again because it's Tyler and so expensive you really have to have
A high-cost or high value
Item
To attach this to
Exactly I probably have to put this on my
Keys to my car
Even though that is a high-value thing because I have a spare key and so on so forth but I'm one of a kind item that it is
How to replace or has
Things that you need for an essay trip in your luggage yeah I would do that
It's just that $5 a month through
It's me
The first years included
I paid $10 for that what I get for that for me personally is
My family knows where I am all the time because
It is tracking the GPS and so on in there and they in is uploading information to them if they need it I also get
Get all my calls and my texts
My notifications I don't care about that when I'm out and about running or something but it's nice to have the ability to even make it
A call from my wrist without my phone
If I get hurt while I'm running
So you're buying
I'm not buying peace of mind because darn it I'm worth it
You are worth
Maybe 15 a month I wouldn't I wouldn't do it
59 net worth
Alright here's an update I complained last week
Two weeks ago I think about my June oven
And
How
I felt like it a chain recognize my toast anymore
It turns out
That June check the logs because they can do that on a
Device and they're like Stacy
You have a giant
Greece
Which is exactly what Kevin told me
How to say that Kevin
I checked your logs to just so you know
John Kerry
You know exactly how many waffles
Is a little disturbing to know that if June wants to they could be like
Ayo Stacy
You cook a lot of
Eggo waffles
But you know what they always whenever you
Request support help they asked
Commission
To view your logs
Are they doing the behind-the-scenes I doubt it could that yeah
But I mean any company could look at the date of their getting from the device
You know I'm making a baked potato or
I'm not cooking anything
So you also and complaints we talked about the nest by Yale lock
Yeah that was our complaint show a week or two ago that's right the Google home integration with the nest by Yale lock
I know we talked about it cuz it was
Announce right before the podcast
A week or two ago
I couldn't get it to work no matter what I did and
Stacy it sent me a
Great set of troubleshooting steps from when she had works with nest for troubleshooting something similar in the past
I was just about to do that
When
All of a sudden I went to my Nest app
And it
Said there's a new application permission that we'd like
Access to
Really what is that and sure enough it was for
The ability to see the state and information
In from the nest by yella so the integration just hadn't ruled out to me yet so I did not have to do anything
So my complaining was kind for nothing cuz I was impatient but it does work now and I can speak to my
Home devices right now I'm not going to cuz I want to set PeopleSoft
And ask it
If the front door is locked I can tell it to lock the door and
I think that's it you might be able to assign specific codes cuz it is a touchpad lock
And two different people and then I could tell you who's home
Think that's a possibility but I want to check on me
Can you couldn't create a routine with it now though too
Oh yeah that's
Set up
Movie times
Lower the thermostat
Turn on my Sonos
Businesses
No it doesn't work with
All right
Okay quick update for everybody who follows
He connected blinds
Story it turns out that Ikea has submitted documentation to the FCC
Did blinds
Okay you guys have everything
The most common show question but we do actually get this question about
Hey I want smart blinds
And so this being Ikea I expected to work with the truck
I also expect it to be cheaper than the current options which are
Are kind of expensive there is my smart blinds which is one of the cheaper one
Works with wooden slat blinds
The big one
And that is $99
Window
And there's a limit
How big that blind
Dang it will move
There is a Lutron Serena Shades Hunter Douglas has somebody has some
Soompi
Has Raquel expensive
Which is why I don't have them
Will post the motorized shades are expensive
Adding connectivity to motorized Shades is not
A big cost Sterrett
Motorized
The shade coz motors have to
In some cases a lot of cloth
And they have to be
And
In some of the fancier iteration so I have motorized shades
To my house
Ginormous
Windows and those were $10,000
Which is
Bonkers so
But they cover
A 10 x 40
So
There's a lot of fabric to move they actually plug into
Dedicated low voltage
It was a quiet
But most people are good
Agreed well I'm not so that's why I don't have them and Ikea products do tend to be less expensive I mean
Look at the Tron freeline it's
Cheaper than most other smart home device lines
So I'm hoping
And I don't think we'll have to wait too long because IQ usually announces their new products in
Stay
Real quick
Question about the trophy
Hub
The radios that supports
I'm assuming it's zigbee FaceTime looking at the FCC report and based on that frequency that they tested High assume this is
You can
The custom music me I can't remember if Sha
Something else yes
You have to have
Particular hub
You can't link it I could not link my
Tri-C lights to other
Even if you have a zigbee hub if it's not
I tried freehub you won't be
Able to use these person
Boo
So yeah
Okay
Let's talk quickly about
The new brilliant
Light switch and
Smart home control devices
I've actually been testing it
It came out
Not a good time for us cuz it was after his last week's podcast
Live
We can talk about it
But I have been testing it
It is a
Light switch
Which one switch panel so that replaces when switch is $300
And it goes all the way to 4 switch panels
So what these are they replace your existing light switch you do have to be
Comfortable turning off your power and
But it's not hard
I'm not going to recommend these just yet
We're going to have the CEO on the show
And we'll talk more about WhatsApp
I think
In a few months this is going to be a very different product
I would recommend
But for right now it has a lot going
And DUI is in
It's not great yet
So I think it be confusing for most Norm
People if you are dedicated smart home user
It'll go ahead you're used to
Playing around with stuff
Things improving over time
This is fine
What it does is
Access a light switch
Also acts as an intercom
Taxes
A Madam a device and it ties into a variety smart
Products like the ring doorbell
The Sonos WeMo
Hue Lights
Nest
Coming soon
And also smart thing
So
That's a lot of things that you can do with it
You can set scenes in idea is
You walk in and you can use this
To control your home via voice or via a touchpad
Touchpad
Screen
What I found
The touch pads too small to control all the devices
Really easily
What I think is really interesting though
Is you could install this in
A couple places in your home and actually control all the lights
Which
When they figure out the user interface in
Easy I think this could be real
It could be anyone shown me we did a video hangout you show me a little bit of the usage in
It reminds me of the old wink relay in some regards which had a touch screen and was able to
To literally show that your wink shortcuts in your devices on there
But I still think there might be a little bit of work left on the southwest side for the brilliant
Okay so now let's talk about the integration
I started out just played with a plane
And
I will say one of the nicer features because
Casitas way it was being able to upload my own photos
Taranis panel so it's like this neat little digital photo frame
You can only do 25 and it's kind of time-consuming youku
Individually upload each photo
But it is really nice to like
Walk by the slice
Pictures of my
Some things that were
Hard is once I brought in my Hue Lights
There's a little glitch Inus in bringing in
One of them didn't show up
And then to control all of them is
1 unit
Was a bit time consuming
Like to actually create
Make a schedule for my living room because there's no way to group
Light bulbs yet
There's no way to group light bulbs into
And that's
Kind of frustrating cuz I don't no one really wants to control
Not in the same room
So
That's one thing they do say that that's coming in two to three weeks
So is a non hacked
Nest integration
And they're just waiting for
And you can create scenes and those are interesting in the Sonos integration
Is actually doing really well for them it only likes to
Favorites R radio station
And if you need to control for like deep dives into specific songs
So
Do I love it
It's all right
Do I think it's going to get better
Yes oh and SmartThings the SmartThings integration is
You can't control all of the devices
You can put into your smart
And then with the Amazon Echo
Croatian
It actually sometimes
It won't play music
But it does do things like when you ask it for the weather it'll show you the weather
It doesn't do all the things
Very much reminds me that wink relay cuz you could do a lot of things
Similar things in
Displace
Interesting Lee the photos is nice
Having to manually upload them somewhere is kind of
I don't know mm Forest to me but I understand why you need some kind of integration I only mention this because just
Earlier this week
Google opened up its Google photos API and that means apps can men have Integrations to
People's Google photos
The other reason I mention it is
Because for the next podcast you're going to have something that will automatically pull in your Google photos for you you want
Upload them it'll just be there
You know I'm talking about
Set me a Lenovo display
So that's what we'll talk about for now and how much is it that today
9 for the
1 gang
So the one switch
Which comparison like The $99 price for the wing
Yeah I was 99 and even came down in price after
Not install they still have
2 switch panel which is probably the most common
Is 340
And they will bundle stuff
Oh and also works with
It looks
I mean I've only seen it on the Hangouts
But it looks like it's
Work that money just really pretty
It's a very nice device in the microphone on it is crazy
Search for
Kingdom anime
So
Actually turn that potion
Because
It was fighting with my other
Batman that a debate does more things so it's like
I want you
That's just me
Okay so let's go to our listener
Be iot podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Do not miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wifi adapter
You can enter to win
By calling us and leaving us a question
That number is 512
To 4
Note that we will only ship the lock to
Canada
And the US
Unfortunately
So
Remember smarter homes
Start
Which lay
And this week we have a question from an unknown individual
But it's still a really good question
So let's hear it
Stacey and Kevin
Long time listener and you guys had an episode while ago where Kevin talked about using his
Hue bulbs the color ones
Show different shade of
Colorlink
Red or blue I think Bass
On whether or not
Kevin stocks were trading well
I want to employ similar use but with temperature
So when I wake up I'd like for one of my color bulb to display
A blue or red in Greater intensity
Gymnast
Based on
Current temperature
I would love to know if this is possible
Philips Hue bulbs I use Google home and
And willing to do pretty much anything
Alright thanks so much
Okay
This is a great
Question and Kevin and I have actually both
Dumbest or variations of this in our
I've actually done literally what
So
I'm going to give you the easy answer
Kevin is going to give you a hug
Bez more fun
Yours is more fun and it has the potential to be
So my answer is
I set up my Hue bulbs
If
And then I just set up a
Basic rule that if
If the weather is
Above
You said do it in the winter so I do if the weather is above 40
Turn red
And if the weather is below
I did this in a light
Closet for a while cuz then I was like oh now I know how to dress in the morning
Is it perfect no cuz you have to set your temperature parameters
You're lying out of Weather Service that may not be directly outside your house you could if you have like a netatmo device you can link directly
The weather station
Right outside your door
Sometimes you have temperature sensors
Doorbells
Access them
So that's ways to get
Granular
At your house weather
But you also then after that you have
Reset the light
Or create another recipe.
Beckett
Go back to Norm
But that is an easy way to do it it doesn't cost you a thing
It works with your existing stuff
Play around with it till you get something
Luther's Cafe
The hardest way to do something simple that's my motto
So
What I did just to refresh everybody I literally created a
Python program
That
Reads information from an API
Other side Bitcoin cryptocurrency Trading
Services
So it's constantly every minute getting up-to-date
Numbers on the actual
Currency prices
And then I use another API based on information
And said hey
Turn on my lifx bulb to Green if
The price is up and even increase the brightness if it's up over certain percentage
So I have a super fine granular amount of
Control
Where
Yiking
Literally get
More precise India notification
Obviously
This is
A program exercise and you need to have something to run that program on I use a Raspberry Pi for example
So you know you have to add something to your smart home you would have to do some programming
I've shared most of the code on our sites
It's a good stub to get started
But you also need to make sure that apis for your products are available
And in case of Philips Hue
Yacht there are
Apis
How to control lights
So it literally you could get temperature information using
The program and set parameters out of those will be your trigger events
If you
Compared to F and then what you want to happen
Would be an API that sends data to your Philips Hue Lights
It's going to require some effort on your part but it's
Stacy said it's something like a
Do a lot more and could be reused in many other cases dirty easily just changing a few lines
Zip code could information from another
Source
Maybe it's stockmarkets maybe it's
If your mailbox
Have been open in your sensor on it for example
You can get a light to Blink when the mail is here
Okay okay but I'm just coming up with
Random examples
But you're right yeah you know there's lots of ways to do this if it would be what I would recommend from us
People yes
So I would start their shirt into programmer you want to learn about apis
You know it's a fun experience
Two ways to go
Just in case
You're that kind of purse
Yes
I hate to be that guy but I don't want to be the only bad guy so please
All right
Now
It's time for
A word from our sponsor but stay tuned because our guest this week is an Bashi
She's going to talk about why
Iot providers need to focus on just a few use-cases what vendors need to do to mm
Prove
Their services or companies buying iot Solutions
And
Who's going to get wet chunks of the 502
Million-dollar pie
For the internet
You're going to like it
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Is that
And I have json Van
Who is VP of iot
With sass
Last week we talked about SAS creating a new division for iot
This week we're going to talk about
The edge
So let's kick it off
What is the value
Us the edge
In The Internet of Things
I think the value can change
Based on use case that the first element is
Just a reduction
Encaustic
Transport and storage of data everyone sees
Projections
The number of
Sensors that are going to be deployed in the edges
The amount of data
It's being generated in the fact is even
Commodity transport commodity storage
If you move everything to the network
Into storage
It's going to be quite expensive in the fact is most of the data is not valid
The first capability is reduce that footprint of data you movie
Through your network and then it really gets
Listen to the youth cases
Surround reduce lighting
Ucn decisioning failure identification
And yield Improvement
And then within our cuss
Centric Industries I like
Betel or Healthcare it really provides the
The basis for a unique engagement model with
Unique messaging based on what you know about your customer
Where they meet
There you go
It really does dairy buyer
So everybody's talking about the edge these days
What are the SAS differentiate
So I talked a little bit about this
In our last topic but it really has been about the invest
And being able tax
A lot of people talk at 10000 feet around the ability
Push
Assisting to the edge but it's quite
Duplex
Davis-standard
Device configuration
Invested
Chablis in that
With this verification validation effort
To make sure that when we say
Push a robust set of Analytics
Capabilities to the edge that we can ask
We do that
And we talked briefly about them but what other industry verticals are working
We're starting to see adoption across multiple
There are those industries that have a long history with sensor data so we
Racine early adoption
Spaces things like energy both generation and distribution
Transportation
Is an area for wide adoption bothan
Fleet Management and
Autonomous cars
So it's really not one industry that I
.2
To say they are leader in the space
But there's white adopt
Great if you want to learn more about what's ass is doing at the edge
Where can we go
We had a great landing page setup
Or additional information whether it's Industries
Specific or more horizontal capabilities that can be found at stats.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is an
Vashi
Who is a partner and leader in the iot practice
With pain in calf
Hi and how are you today
Angry Stacey thanks so much for having me on
Super excited you guys have done some great report
I just love
Wow
Lots of money and iot you talked about all kinds of really challenging issues
So let's just get this started
A level set where are we
Industrial
Enterprise
We have done Recent research
Over the course of the last two years in Time series to understand what the big changes are that we've seen in iot
And the first one is
It still is
Really attractive
Which I think most of your
Listeners would agree with the market Revenue
Circulation providers
Thor Solutions
2 / 500 billion dollar
Aa2021
Which is more than Java
Today but that is a tremendous thought
Also what we found
Customers are really planning
A lot more
Contact
Kidding
Contacts
Fantastic it's really accelerate
The other thing that we found out is that many
Temperature
Haitian so it's really interesting that they could do anymore
But really
Location of
Piece of rolling out and the pace of
Inexpensive implementation
Has actually Fallen
It's a lot of energy but I see
September
And so some of this is really adjusting
That there was probably in mm
Birthday today
Continued barriers to adoption but people are finding
As they're starting
And engaging on Twitter
We can talk a little bit more about those
Okay and we will
But first I want to dig into this 500 I think is 520 billion
Was the number that
You guys
So who gets that
Because there are a lot of different players happening right now
In
The industrial iot in Enterprise iot
Teethers the big kind of
Traditional it guys
There's a bunch of steps and then there's the traditional old school
Honeywell emerson-johnson
Zeidman's all of these guys so
How does that money kind of
Divvy up yeah I guess
I would say there's a lot of
For many different pocket
The first one is
There is actually very interesting opportunities for the traditional technology players especially when it comes to
Kill a couple of things conductivity obviously for the
Cisco's in Ericsson but the world as well as the
Spiders obviously this opportunity
The cloud provider
Microsoft
As well as the private
Providers that companies like idea
For example and then
I think the other is
Providers
Now I think you've mentioned it so there's a lot of
Point you kids application
And then there's also application development
Integrators
And then of course you can't
Leave the felt that you were talking about like a Honeywell or
Schneider or GE that are providing Industrial Equipment because they also have
Unity to music operational Technologies
Stand not to use iot data
Really there's a lot of money
Starview at Bain is that there is not
Billy broad-market Steve
I would say there is many
Vertical here and there's opportunity for many winners across is vertical
Awesome yes I would be terrified if you said one
Get it all or even to really
Funny baby I feel like we get that question a lot who's going to be the winner and IRT
Everyone does love a winner
Just a singular winner so
Okay what's the point of this concept of
Pilot purgatory
Because it's fun to say and you talked about maybe reality setting
A little bit more
In this field soap
What exactly is
Going on as these projects
Get halted at the pilot stage we're going to stay there indefinitely
Yeah sure
So I think that
There's a lot of
Obviously
Search with customer
And our findings at the
Billy around mm
About 40% of the executives that we interviewed
More likely
Getting proof of concept
20%
In the number of tfv4 happening
Let me talk with the band
They talk about how expensive
Backpack
When you say how extensive the asks are
Do you mean like
The number of companies a ski or do you mean like they want a whole heck of
Save-A-Lot
Exactly
Okay so these are happening
And what's happening inside these companies as they're doing them and they're like oh
What is a learning
While they're learning a few things so the first one is that there's still a lot of beer
Adoption that haven't really been broken down
We found at the top
3 issues that customers are facing
Into the barrier
Feeling pretty
They were 2 years ago
And so the first one is around Sakura
It's the most acute
Challenge that customers are facing
They might be okay
Contact that is a ringtone
But then thinking about
Scaling out
Without me
Security capabilities on the device or the app
What concern
Protecting the data is something that keeping them from
Probably at least
Extensively I think that people are implementing
But there's
Probably.
Practice security
Challenge
Concern
To increase the number of devices
And actually even probably
And for those of you guys
Who don't speak chart in ASP is average selling price
The second one is around
Return on it
And so I think the safety you might have heard that
Folks that are implementing
New kinds of ukases that you dial TJ.
Problems on both sides
The Returned
Inside
Lack of clarity
I got on
What
In terms of upside and I think benders-hadi
To really characterized
What the value is
Buying
Customers are buying
Decision
The ability to
A producer's be there for increasing the velocity of their supply chain
Enfield vendors need to translate the data
Allowed
Customers make better decisions and showed up in the prison
Cut that flips on The Returned
Lack of clarity of
What kind of
Turn that should expect
MMA
Cute is that the investment
Zhuhai and that's for a couple
The first one
Really around
How much cups
Station is happening today each of these implementation Austin
Is very
Develop to deliver
Have less repeatability been in a more mature
EXO vendors really need
Hate to drive more repeatability across
Keep it so they can understand some more
Common component and you really get them better
Out of the box but I think that would help on the
Investment side
Is that ladder bit
Possible because I feel like a lot of the customers are the ones that demanding this customization
In part because maybe their workforces and is familiar with it so they're building these highly complex Dash
Words for people or it could even be you know just their equipment is so
Particular to them and that
Particular
Figuration
Between
There's no way that you
Sinnoh customizer are always different
There's actually value
Standardization
And so
How to trade off right
Can have a lower investment and more standardization
And so I think they're just actually
The challenges
There's not really an offer yet today
I think there is some truth in what you say
To all I got
There's going to be
Elevation here
Rebate application
Vibe and then stomach pain walkers on sale software
Relationship manager
Tool
Paradise more than there has been today I just think the vendors haven't had a
Cato's in a particular vertical
With a particular type of equipment
You know they need to actually identify those little cheese
Parts that actually could be
Okay
I feel like the vendors
You have some strong feelings about what they are and are not doing
What would you be telling them right now
Kind of funny
Because
Same thing just like you said you know pilot Purgatory on the cusp
When we talk with vendors
All different
Pollution
The concept that are going on and they're trying to figure out why
Which one is actually
John Deere trying to figure out
Can be repeatable because from their economic
Doesn't work either
To have something that's custom
Time and so they would like to also reduce the amount of customization but they're having
What's challenging about this
So bright
Play it's like an opportunity
And so
Aiden Mesa technology
He market like the horizontal technology
Vendors that are capturing that 520 billion potentially in the future right there so many of them
I actually need
We spoke at
That I
That's just too many you can't actually figure out how to
A particular UK If you're focused on 80th
Wait
And so what we suggested that vendors really reduce the amount of verticals that their focus
Initially
Look at what their customer base actually looks like we're to have to go
Where could they have some repeatability and that they're delivering
How many verticals should a particular company try to focus on and is it dictated by like
If I'm a startup maybe I should pick
Three if I'm someone like Microsoft maybe I should
5 +
Work with dedicated Partners how does that actually look in
We would actually say that even for a large company
Microsoft
Good night
Probably two or three UK.
Target
And then for a startup Austin
Repeatability
So we suggest I guess
If they take a particular
Just on the horizontal component that they might so you know servers Ark
They also looks
Or how do I act
What are the challenges that we haven't talked about yet is this idea of
If I am a big industrial manufacturer I may do a
A proof-of-concept in one area
And be like this is amazing and
Roll it out fully but then when I start doing things in other areas I realized that oh maybe my two
Solutions will never talk to each other or
Maybe they're not designed to be as flexible as possible
So how do companies kind of
Handle that or how should they be thinking about is future-proofing there
Iot efforts
Customers are actually doing many proof-of-concept the same time
Any given company is
Two or three different type of concept for different UK
Exactly what you're saying
She working with Microsoft and then application
Provider to actually look for something like an HVAC
End
You're standing pal.
But I might have another Bender that I
To think about the transport within the belt
Contact
Realized
We think about
Some industrial providers
Like a Honeywell or GE
Interoperability across
Types of equipment
And so you know I think one of them think that customer
What you do is really think about the choice of vendors that they have
Whether that be a provider like a Microsoft or an Amazon
Industrial Equipment provider
And how could they ensure that the data that they have
Different kinds of devices
UK that might be usable or shareable I think about it
Initial proof of concept
And probably
I need to think about potentially due to the concept
Othello
Okay
I'm going to call you good news Anne
From now on all right and thanks so much for coming on the show.
A cart that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week