Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and her co-host
Kevin tofel we have an awesome show for you today we're going to talk about the death of an OBD port
Company
Explain all that in
We are also going to talk about iot an industrial setting and how much it can save you
Plus a little bit about Wireless Industrial
Free to talk about
New transistor designs for iOS
Bear with us
It is going to be
Be interesting anyway
We also have lots of news such as how much
People are going to spend the night
7 years
We got a merger we've got more homekit gear and some special tips and tricks on your Google home and Amazon
Echo Plus
We each installed new devices to talk
We've got
Awesome guests for you it is Nick Langston
TE Connectivity we spend
A lot of time tell you about smart fabrics and what the future holds
It's a little slow
Plus we're going to hear from Lux products
A sponsor on
Their news
At and Design
So
Let's
Get
Started
With
Message from another one of our sponsors home isn't just a place it's a feeling the feeling that you're safe to enjoy that
Things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT helps keep you safe so you can feel protected wherever you
You are introducing the ADT Security starter kit
Everything you need to get started with ADT Pulse including a camera professionally installed for only $49
Visit att.com podcast today to learn more requires 36-month monitoring Khan
Contract installation and activation fees apply easy pay required certain markets are excluded
Licenses available at att.com Florida ID through f0001 one to one
Susana F-16
Already
Let's talk about the death of yet another
Roddick
We got an email this week from one of our listeners
He writes us to tell us that
A company called
Mogio
Canadian company that made
On board diagnostics
Port products
So that's like automatic you shoved this into your car attracts things like mileage rate
Are you are you
You can tie it into
Like channels like if
And track
I actually think it's kind of a cool thing to track your mileage to a spreadsheet if your
Driving a car around for business purposes
This company
Put out their product back in November of 2014
But
End of January the generation
1 Mojo device
It's not going to be supported anymore
Kevington upset because
This is not a very long
Life cycle for a product
Such as this because it's not like the pores have changed on the vehicles number one and number two
This was one of the
First state was the first was one of the first
Modules that had built in 3G and GPS connectivity
And that hasn't changed so
What's changed
Well it gets a little bit better
Apparently in the email it says they've said we carefully ensure that every customer on first generation products
Has received a minimum of
12 months of service
This is a device that cost $150
And
How does subscription fee
Your poor the cellular connectivity so this is a device that
You know in some place did it alright they
Accounted for the cost of
You know sending data and
Hardware cost that was actually fairly expensive I think the original automatic was
Like 99
Cellular one is more
And
Yeah here's the thing this reminds me
Of like a smartphone that you might replace
The fact that this only lasted about three years
A car is the typically a longer-term investment it's not like you
Recycle through cars like smart phones in most cases the second thing is it's not like a cellular technology has changed
They had
Produced this device with a
Say a 2G chips that you know and those networks are shutting down as we transition
The Operators you know moving forward
LTE 5G Etc then I can sort of understand it
But
That hasn't happened so
Why I still wonder why
This is no longer going to work and there's no
Valid reason in my mind
Here's what they say
They say the first generation OBD2 devices
Incapable of communicating
And because of the way they've been manufactured we cannot
Install alternate SIM cards
Changed the could be and we should probably know that they have kind of changed their business model overtime as well
After this product came out to basic create a product and let the carriers white label it
So you could go to in fact they mentioned that you may we recommend if you know
I forget what it is but
So it seems like they're getting out of the Direct business
What's the direct-to-consumer
This is this is another example of what
We talk about when we talk
Talk about it looks like perhaps these guys
When they launched this in 2014
They probably didn't think ahead about life
Like what happens if we pivot
What happens if
This doesn't
And I think any company that's launching a connected product needs to have those contingency
Hanson Place
And it would suck to have to use them but you should still have
And
Communicate that to the customer so
It's only words you're going to hear a lot more about this
The year ahead
Because it's a topic we strongly believe in
Very propensity
And I think we're going to see a lot of other companies hit the wall
It's going to become an issue
So
Psy
Let's move away
Consumer for a moment and let's talk about
Iot in industrial setting
Cuz
I did a field trip
Well it was a distillation
Not whiskey distillation but like Refinery distillation and it was a little pilot plant that
The University of Texas has on
Their campuses
And
I went just to kind of learned
And see
Connected sensors in action and I learned a lot
Cool stuff but the coolest thing I learned
Was
The challenges of Wireless in industrial environment
I said I did put this in my newsletter so if
If you read this forgive me
That was cool
So can I talk to you from Emerson was telling me that in
The initial setups things like trains and trucks that are
Moving into load up
Refined product
They would stop the wireless
Signals to the RF environment
Is super challenging there
One because it changes in the release large metal objects moving
But it's also changing
As the
Chemicals inside these giant metal Vats
Go up and down so as things are refined the volume inside changes
And Wireless in water They Don't Really mix so that causes
Problems
There were talking about like why mesh needs to be
Why mesh Wireless needed to be
Be created for the
And
I just thought as companies are starting to roll out
More Wireless
Networks things like Laura
Things like sigfox
In there
Maybe not why does industrial but he didn't like a warehouse in Bayern
Some of these things are still going to be the same
You're still going to need to answer
To those problems
So
It is pretty cool at me we sit around our homes and complain that we can't get
Wi-Fi signal in a room you know but even when nothing is moving and changing dynamically in a warehouse I mean yeah
I can't wear production facility
All the movement of things I can
Affect wireless signals never thought of that to be honest
That's going to be half the investment tool
Change out from older generation
Wireless networks to new mesh networks or whatever solution they use but
I think they're going to have to do that
Well yeah and if you think about things like robots right those are usually metal and they're going to be moved
Around so
Woohoo
It's going to be a challenge the other challenge with mash that we should mention briefly
Is that when you
Install a mesh Network unless you're working with like a standardized thing like these Wi-Fi mesh networks there's no standardized wife
Imesh
So what we get
Is
Proprietary just going to say semi proprietary it's like there
Proprietary implementations of a standard
Is what it really is
Yeah
Sync
Head
Industrial mesh for
Wi-Fi
Bluetooth is working on
Yeah it just to clarify
I'm sure people understand but for a few who may not
What you mean
Liquor my own perspective is like I can't take a Nero and attach it to my Google Wi-Fi mesh for example and vice versa
Yeah
They all still speak Wi-Fi but to each other to create the match they're using their own
Software
Maybe that should be stand
Get the best out of Cheyenne Gilgamesh Network around the entire planet
All right
Also industrial news
I did I found an inch
Interesting article from an MIT Sloan management review
I thought there'd be more data in there an unfortunate wasn't but there was some very interesting information
What's a good cover
It has to do with facilities management and IRT so semi related to our last story
They took a look at some of the
Data that has been collected from large
Commercial buildings and Facilities over decade
And figured out that these places spend about a hundred billion dollars each year just a repair and Main
It's work right
The thing is
What they're saying is hey you know what
If we could use iot devices shenzhen AI
To Ghana
Figure out in advance what might need to be maintained what my break down and said we could actually reduce unnecessary Maiden
By about 20 to 25%
And that adds up I mean if it is a hundred billion dollars and you can achieve that returns 20 25%
$10 a year save just by using iot limitations in these facilities so
Rather interesting when you put in that respect
Yeah we care a lot about preventive or predictive maintenance
Which is about to break down quick
Fix it first
What we don't talk a lot about and what
These case studies don't cover is
A lot of maintenance is just routine and set based on
Every 5,000 miles you should get your
What this element is is
Hey
It's been 5000 miles but you know everything still humming along so why don't you just wait a little bit longer so this is
It's preventing me
It's so it's proven
It's not predictive it
Preventing
Preventative
Yes yeah I mean instead of using just guidelines General guidelines which is kind of the way we had to do it
Before we had
Big Data
You know saying cars like the present but yet you always do the 3000-mile oil change and tire rotation cetera but
People drive in different areas people have different weather patterns people have different road conditions
So you maybe it'll go 5-6 8000 Miles to the guidelines kind of irrelevant
When you have the data
Discount on individual-level weather person or a facility's plant or whatever it maybe now you can actually not spin
Minutes money when you don't need to
All right
Now
We're going deep into the nerd hole
It's so worth it
Ivan old Shepard
Kevin is
You're not old but
You previously
Kids
20 years ago
And I've always been fascinated by this because to me are underlying silicon and Hardware
Are the parameters for what we can really do
And I know software is eating
The world and it's awesome but it's still constrained by the
Capability for soft
And one of the challenges with software is power consumption
So I have been
Constantly fascinated by
The ways
Companies try to
Reduce
Power consumption
And I just read this article I linked to it
On a startup called
Minima it's out of Finland
And they're doing
Okay guys
They're doing near threshold voltage
This is kind of weird but basically you got a little electric current running around on any semi
Are any transistor that
Right
And you want to make sure
They usually run at a higher level so you can make sure it
Completes the circuit
Candidate against
What this does is it
It takes it
Is low to the ground is pause
And
They basically
Will modify
The performance
So how much
Electricity is shoved through the chip
Based on
Performance team
So they can get away with a little bit they do
So these chips are becoming smarter
And reducing the power
Consumption
So that's what it does
There other companies such as ambach micro which I have covered since
I want to say like 2012 or 2011
I have left this come
And edit compute and they're also working
With low voltage
So I think this is a really cool concept so this is how we're going to
Continue pushing forward with chip design and capabilities
While also reducing
Our needs and being very custom to the job
Things are trying
Yeah I sent her saying it just to give a frame of reference Huawei mrs. noted in the article but it jumped out at me
Huawei actually uses ambucs microcontrollers right now and they get 21 days on a single battery charge now
Granted maybe doesn't color screens
There are other aspects
Contribute to that
But
You compare that to a traditional say a smartwatch or other wearable in my last a day or two
Free sample right because it doesn't use the low threshold
And last week actually profiled a company called spire
And they make a
Stick on
Health tracker it'll go on sale in January
Where I said this is a activity tracker tracks
Heartbeat respiration
Sleep
It's a sticker
And you peel it off and you stick it in your underwear and you can wash it
And it just stays there and works for
Two solid
They're using
Micro can
That's a 2-year battery life on a device that
You actually can
I think it's crazy
And it's always on and always on it
Something right now
What's crazy is
Waking up in sending that data some
Now there's no screen on
Which is a huge
Powerhawk
Screen
Like nobody's business
But waking up a radio to send that data and processing that
Is just insane
Hello
That's the future and so we need these types of companies because
Otherwise
We're going to be like charging everything in sight forever
And that's a
Now it's time for
Are some rapid fire news
IDC has said that Global spending on iot will grow 14.6
Percent next year
And they think it's going to hit 770 2.5 billion dollars
They're going to assume that by
20/20
Iot
Spending is going to be at a trillion dollars
That is insane
They also think that most of the money in the beginning is going to go towards
Ace Hardware
Modules and sensors
How long is spending on infrastructure
Security
Services will follow hardware and then some
Which makes
Might be worth noting also that the industries that they see the spending manufacturers
Slated to spend the most in transfer
Rotation and utilities
And then you find consumer
Iot spending which is interesting so I focus so much on consumer that often forget it's really a smaller part of this
Big pie
Did you say that by 2021 more than 55% of the spending and iot projects will be
Before software so if you're starting your company today
Software y'all
Software
Alright in other news a french company called atos has offered to buy gemalto
Four Points
3 billion euros
Gemalto is a company that makes SIM cards payment chips there inside things like your passport
Credit cards
They made the Nano Sims 4 like
IPad.
That was cool they make the Eastern actually for the Apple watch and possibly the pixel phones as well
Yeah so this gives atos
Hunk and payments and security and sim cards for the iot and since iot is so hot they are so
They want to get in on
5 billion dollar offer
That's that
Oh yes
We don't get to talk about honking that much because there haven't been as many devices are supported but there is anyone
I didn't see Honeywell lyric
Controller
This is not like the lyric thermostat this is the actual controller panel that
I think you have to have this one professionally installed
I'm almost positive you can tell me if I'm wrong on that one
But it does have homekit support now as of December 7th
Yes this is their security stuff I think it even speaks with Oprah
Proprietary Wireless thing so this is kind of a gateway to talk to them
Proprietary Honeywell security
Except which is
Indeed
All right Google Assistant
Now supports device sync
My voice
There's not much to say here
Well
What is device sync
Some people may not
Understand what that means when you're adding devices to your smart home hub or a digital assistant usually have to go in and out
War II
Just a link accounts on a server
Now what you can do with Google Assistant once you to add something to your smart home hub a new product for example
You can just say to your Google Assistant hey sync my lights cuz you just had a new lights
It'll just do it automatically you don't have to go into the app or anything like that so
Little less of an obstacle to do that
It
Next Step
You can wake up to music on your Echo just by simply saying that
Set my alarm for 6 a.m.
Beyonce
Recurring you can choose from different music services such as Amazon music Spotify Pandora TuneIn
Sirius XM
One of my favorites cuz the Beatles Channel and iHeartRadio
I can just get blinds to show me the sun on the cheap I've been good shape
Well that brings us to my neck
Topic which is
I finally installed
The Ikea tradfri
I just like to say it
It is fun to
So
I had a botched initial pack
So this took me awhile and
And I replaced it
And now have them so the one thing I liked about the Caesar $80 from
Ikea the setup requires a hub
It has a remote control and then to light bulbs and they're white tunable
It does work with Madam a
And it also works with
So those are the things you need to know about
Now when I installed it I love the fact that I did not have
Have to sign up
There was no app
There isn't a doubt you have to install that I didn't have to
The password I didn't have to
To do anything
Just just
Took a picture of his very much like the homekit setup I took a picture of the device in the back
Your phone's on this network this is on this network
I've now authenticated this to this
It's a very localized non cloud-based
Solution
Yes but there is a hub so I know
It's okay I setup the remote control
Sitting at very close to the Gateway and saying
Connect
And then
That's how you add light bulbs to stick
Light bulbs into the socket and then you
All the remote
Control next to them
And
It all worked
Pretty flawlessly
My challenge
Is now that I have enabled the echo skill
And have that working it recognizes
One of them
And turns it off
But it doesn't
Recognize
And it shows both in your Madam a app
Yes but one is glowing and lit up
The other one is not and when I go to it
I can turn it off
From Adam
It just says it doesn't recognize that
Set device name
Which is weird cuz it's the same device name
That the outlet that lamp was originally plugged into was
HEB
So I'm still troubleshooting
Can be exciting
I wonder if
If you use a different device name as a temporary
Just to see maybe there's some confusion there with the reusing an old device name
So that was my initial thought but I rebooted
So I put these in our bedside tables
Lamp so I replaced
A hue light bulb called Stacy
With a Tri-C light bulbs now
Call Stacy
I rename my hue light bulb
Anna for my daughter
And then I took
A WeMo Outlet
It's called Andrew that his lamp
Plugged into and I replaced it with a bulb
The tribe people
Called Andrew
And I named the new outlet
Christmas tree
Because my Christmas tree
So so much about my house
So
Stacy work
The Andrew does not
Just out of curiosity does it work with the home app or do you guys not have any iOS devices
My husband has an iOS device but making him
Play with the homie
Then he should not have a lightbulb
Next week
Will find out
What happened
What went wrong
Help
Beat lights
What is the point
These lights are really expensive for what they are
They're kind of nice like the remote control is nice when you're like oh
I don't want to wake up my spouse by saying turn on Stacy or
Turn off Andrew
Cuz he's asleep so that is nice and the fact that they have Madam a integration
Makes them work exactly like they used to
When they work
Witching is not happy
We'll figure it out
It's a nice way
To do this
And so
Is it
Do you need this
The answers
Is it an easy
Painless kind of smart home thing
Is it fun to say tried fee
Yes
There's our thoughts on
Well it's kind of funny that you have a
Troubleshooting
Issue with something new as did I
I received from I'm not going to name names but I
Fabulous podcast co-host I work with
I received a ring doorbell Pro as an early Christmas gift
Thank you Stacey
And
And before we hit our
12 degree windshield weather today I went out yesterday and when was a little warmer and installed being new
Ring doorbell
It was it was easy to install like this is
I think very simple for most people to do
I had a challenge in that my doorbell transformer
From my old doorbell
Is literally attached
To the very top of my circuit panel downstairs
There's no breaker for it
It just seems like it's just attached
And so I'm like
I'm not to be able to turn off the power
But it's low voltage
I didn't even once crossed any wires or shock mice
No problem
So
Ring includes two little
What should I call the little jumper so to speak or do you have to go into your current doorbell and
Attach the wires to the jumpers and a little ring box that they include very simple to do did that
Took off the old doorbell put in the new ring attached to wires
Perfect getting power to the app and set it up
So far so good
This literally took me about 30 minutes and I said part of that time looking for the breaker to turn off power so
Not a lengthy process
However when I got through the setup process with the doorbell
And it wanted to connect to my wireless network which I use a Google Wi-Fi that's actually an old onhub and one
Google Wi-Fi
Am I nice Network
It said it was connecting to or connected to my
Network and as soon as it got connected I could use the app I couldn't do a lot of you I couldn't do anything other than
Ring the doorbell
This is weird why can I not connect to you
You said you were connected and in the actors that device health button and you click that you can see the power when I had more than
Power coming into that was not a problem
But just sitting at work offline and like what are you talkin about
So I spent more time than it took to actually install the thing to figure it out
And that was
My home network name has a special character in it
As a hyphen and I probably don't need the hyphen I had it in there from way back when I used to run multiple Networks
What I would name my network on the put a hyphen
Jeor -
And
Bryson a fool my different
Bands
Don't need to do that anymore
So what I did instead of changing my home network name which would host of about 25 different devices right now
Exactly I got creative and remembered oh I already have a guest network setup on this Google Wi-Fi
And it's just a regular
Network name no special characters
Let's see if that works
Sure nuff it does
It kind of bothers me
Now that I have all this work
Cloud before it gets too
It's not Nino
No
No it's not going to the club
When your doorbell rings
And it's going to
Put your phone instead of going over the Wi-Fi network
Because they're not on the same
Network but they sorta are
I checked the seven head and the IP addresses and the way Google does this it's
The guest Network
Is
I want to see the same network cuz it's not but
It looks like it is
It's very interesting out there done it
I'll have to dig into a little bit more but I'm not seeing any issues or I can still
Access things when I go my guess what I can access my printer and so on so regardless Reddit
It said it soon as I got rid of my special character at work
And that's why I did it as a workaround
But the thing is
Rings troubleshooting for this
It's like okay
Connect to that Network on your phone and do a speed test
And is it more than one megabyte per second yeah it's 150 megabits per second
And I tested that multiple times
There should be something in the troubleshooting
Texas
Make sure you don't have special characters in your home network name because for some reason it doesn't like that
So
Seafood please
If I'm wrong and I just got lucky with the Yes Network and that's not the real issue with special characters let me know what
If it is I think
Yeah the app
Troubleshooting music
Excellent regardless of all at once it's working
It's working great
I set up motion zones and
I told Stacy before the show we have a side unit townhouse so people to walk around the actual front and come around the
Side front entrance
And there's a long walk way and
And I can see them as soon as they make that corner and I'm like hey 10 steps before they even ring the doorbell
I get an alert right now it is awesome
Lovett thank-you skating Stacy
Really great
Ye all right now it is time for
As to answer a question for the iot podcast listener hotline
Tautline today is brought to you by Schlage maker of Alexa
It's late you can have a brand new electronic lock installed in minutes
With just a screwdriver and your own two hands
They're so easy to use and set up
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
All right
And here's our voicemail
Hi this is Denise
I really enjoy y'all show
And I have a
I own a commercial building a small commercial building
And
I'm always curious specially this time of the year about pipes burst
And I was wondering if you had any information about
Actors
If you do I'd love to hear about it
Thank you
You are in such
Luck
Because Miss is like
Water
Management leak sensing
Season
Right ahead of CES
There's a lot of products coming out on them
There also existing products
And if there's one thing Stacy likes more than lights it's
Leak sensors
Does weeks have been
A constant part of my
For the forever actually
I once had a pipe burst
In the apartment above me and I came home
And like there was a stream of water that could feel like a 50 gallon trash can
Like every 5 minutes just
Pouring down into my mouth
It was sex
It's very exciting
Elite sensor
Fortleaks sensors
I really love the
Honeywell lyric
Leak sensor
Because it can wrap around your pipes to text both leaks
Because it has a long tail as a 4-foot
Cord that you can actually string a couple of them together
And
You can wrap that around your pipes and it will detect if they're going to fry
Fries so as they get close to freezing it'll let you know and if it bursts or there is a leak somewhere around there
It will also let you know so I love those because they're Wi-Fi so they don't require anything special and they do temperature
And we
Detection
Undertale gives you a
A lot more surface area
So that's probably a great option
Now
The downside for that is
You got it like when you get the alert you're going to be like oh
Oh crap not going to drive down to my office
So what's really interesting
When are some of the things coming out so their products from a
Call Finn
Spin out from Belkin
They're actually tracking
Weeks at the water valve and
The cool thing there is there going to be
Looking for
Weeks anywhere in your
Basically so you don't have to actually rap any
And that's going to be an algorithm that says oh my gosh you're is a lot of water and it appears to be coming from your
So those are cool
The most advanced seems to be a company called
Slow and what this does is it has that kind of algorithmic
Detection
Like Finn
But then it also
Can shut off the water
When a leak occurs
So if it sees a major leak in water
Going through the system
It's like oh no
And then
Atlas shut off the
Internet Sandy
Those are really excited there's a lot of shut-off valves happening
So you could create like a
Take your Honeywell and then happy
Water valve connector
True like a gift but
Honestly for something is important
I kind of wanted to
Yeah it's got the functionality to
Shut the water slow down
Either at the main or whatever the week is that's actually very very useful I did well with paying a premium for my opinion
A lot of these though I'm going to tell you you have to get them installed
Professionally
You're going to be messing with
Which
Yeah but the for the basics the lyric is only 7999
Yeah and that is does the freeze detection as well which is actually
This time of year here in the USA that's a good thing
Exactly and there's tons of leak sensor
They're so like every
Smart home platform
When there's SmartThings has one root which makes a
Smoke detector
After 2 they have won the challenge with those that I don't love not all of them do freezes roosters dufur
But they're also just like one tiny little sensor that
You stick next to something and you just hope the league
That's the thing standpoint
That's like you got to decide in advance where the leak is going to happen
I don't like that
No I don't like that either my
Apartment situation back in college you know
I don't have access to some
House of Hair
A lot of these would be really interesting in things like
Multi-family dwelling
Because
Of like what I just described
And they don't want
Denise that may have been more information
Honeywell if you just want a quick leak sensor in rap
Your pipes
Or
You can go and Vance
And put a flow system on that tracks all the water usage in your building and then can shut
It Off
So if you
I have a question
For the iot
Cast feel free to give us a call at 5 1/2
To 4
And who knows
You might get your
Your question
All right
Kevin I feel like we have done
A lot of work lot of good work today with the show so
Lettuce
Move on
Guest
Stay tuned
Because I've got Nick Langston
LTE connectivity
Discussing Smart Fabric so
This is everything from Lake
Crazy smart socks to crazy smartsheets
To carpet with LEDs and printed in it so
You do wayfinding so it's a fun interview
Hey everyone we are interrupting this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is flux
Products and I have robbed
Here to talk about
Is Kono smart thermostat
End
Cool design feature
Hey Rob thanks for joining us
Can you start by quickly telling us
What it is
We are a
Trout philadelphia-based innovator of HVAC
Controls
And as you mentioned our newest product in the market is
Is the Lux Kono smart thermostat which has all the features
You can imagine
And some more I hope we get to talk about a hundred and forty-nine bucks at your local Home Depot store or of course he
You can shop online
Excellent
So the first thing I noticed was that
There were a bunch of different options for me to change out the faceplate
On this thing
Can you tell me a little bit more about
We believe in personalization out-of-the-box are
Decor snap cover what we call them
Is in a great black
Stainless steel
Color which is very popular right
But as you know people decorate differently their walls look different
They might want to match something or contrast with something
You think so we have
A bunch of other apps
Since we have a hibiscus Red Sea
Deep Blue
Of course we have a black and a white
And as you mention
You paint it
So when you're
Spending all that money
Dressing up your living room and
Changing the colors
You can now
Customize your own thermostat with large of course not covered where you can have your kids draw something nice
What other designer
Taken to consider
Duration
If you look at the product you can't help but notice it has
It's great big
Brushed aluminum knob on it
And that's the control knob that's how you get into the user interface
How you make the thermostat warmer
And cooler
Very easy to use
It's part of the reason why we came up with the
Ancona because when you
You see it you're going to want to touch it
So I love that you're focused on design in person
Ization what other features have
You built into
It has
A lot of smart
Teacher so works with all the three major voices
Assistance Apple
Amazon
And Google
It also has geofence
Sing we call that home-and-away aware and
We also have something for IAQ indoor air quality so there's a lot of different built-in features that work through
Through the app and through the storm
Thermostat to make it an excellent entry point
For any Smart Home
Can you tell me a little bit more about IQ
We have a long history of understanding the need to
Remove air
Sew weave
Come up with a product we also call are smart IQ
We connect with a third party
Air sensor
And when it detects a pollution event
It'll through the cloud to Cloud integration
Tell our thermostat to turn the air on
And automatically you have
IAQ event we will circulate the air through your filter and through your air quality system
Something awesome
Where can we go to find out
You can stop by your local Home Depot store or you can go online Deluxe products.com
Of course you can shop online and learn more about the Kono smart thermostat
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Nick
Langston who is in business development for
TE Connectivity
HD
We're talking
Outsmart
Hey dick how are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing great how are you
And I am super excited we have had this conversation I feel like over a year ago
You got to come on the show and talk about this
It just did
Open until
Better late than never
Exactly I feel like by waiting a little bit longer
We just come that much further
We're talking about smart Fabrics today
So explain to me what these are what this entails
Where We Are Tour
The definition of smart
Probably depends a little bit on
Who you're talkin
But I like to think of it as
Sensors embedded into
Fabrics
There's also a place
We're just delivering
Power
Ortygia
Through Fabrics but I really like to think of it is textile based
Sensors used for biometrics
Mostly
Okay where are we today with
Like the development of this
Yeah we have more technological capability
And we have
Business case
That is there's all kinds of fantastic things we can
Do with textile base sensors in
And smart textiles
Or clothing but there isn't a fantastic way to make money at it yet so what you can see if you look across
Kickstarter or Indiegogo or go do some of the hardware accelerators
Different ideas on what could be done
With sensing in
Soft goods
But you find very little of them really making
Can a big impact
Market
I think some of us are probably familiar with what we've seen in
Sportswear
That is workout
Clothing that's really quantify your activity
Hope you understand how many calories you burn to help you understand is your posture correct
Your emotions correct
And give you that kind of feedback
What we haven't seen yet is something for the commercial Market that really solves a very big problem
And I think we are approaching a
We're going to begin to see some things happening in the medical in
Where you'll begin to see patients sent home with
An item
Smart clothing that they can wear that'll take their basic measure
Heart rate respiration
Temperature
The three most critical and they can take them
Constantly
So you don't even have to be involved in
Anyway and just simply send that data back
To your medical practice
Keep tabs on you in real time this also has
Utility for
Pharmaceutical trial
Where they often rely on people to do self-reporting
How they feel
When trying a new truck if your getting some of these basic
Have to rely as much on self according to
Beware
Some sort of change
Gym shorts
There's a lot of things we can do
But very few ways to make money
Okay
It will talk about some of the
Cool health and safety stuff
A little bit more in depth later
Let's dig into
The tech
So I feel like conductive Fabrics
Are all the rage and thinking about things like
Hey there Google Levi's Jacquard jacket thing
Honestly is a little bit disappointing
Partly because of the business case
What the heck is a little
Disappointing
What is the tech
Inside these things
What is it really in
Well usually involves a conductive alipay
Historically that's been things
Conductive Yarns that are either
Cotyledons
Silver ore
Somehow plated with conductive material
Can you can imagine that
Any sort of fabric you put three that's one of our process
This is not going to be
Extremely durable
They do we honor the fabric shrink as you wash them or change shape as you watch them and that's not good for these
In Alaska
Conductors
So that's a limiting factor right there
A lot of work has been done by
Companies like coupons
In creating
Conductive ink
It can be very easily silkscreen
Who owns Annie's
Textile Laura
Piece of class
And be able to wish
Damned
The flexing in the strain
The Distortion that goes along
Being embedded in
Flexible substrate
And that seems to be the next generation
They can be used both for data transmission they can be used for
Fencing
It can be used even to a certain extent for low-power tree
It's got a lot of property
To improve what we can do and there's a drive cost
Wait
As well okay so when I think smart Fabrics I should think things with
Conductive thread
Now what about
I have like
Smart socks
Github conductive
And then there's like a little
Power Radio
Computer pack
You stick on
Is that the goal is to have
This soft Fabrics that conduct electricity and then some sort of hard non washable computer pack
Clicks into it
That's certainly not the goal
But that is the state of the
Technology
Today the elect
Chronixx
Generally
They are not embedded
In the fabric itself
I think there's work being done on
Making
Semiconductors on kapton substrates
You can truly imagine
Flexible
I see that could be
Embedded in the Fab
But I think we're several years away
Actual production
Such a thing for the time being it is going to be
Spencer's
Or
Los conductores
Inside a text Tyler their substrate that have to make a physical connection
To some sort of
Small PCB with a microcontroller chip on it
That can actually process with
Incense
Okay and you said caps Trump
Substrate
I missed
Captain
Well if you've ever seen a flexible printed circuit the substrate material there is typically something called cops on
It's basically just a type of thin flexible plastic that offend you can scroll traces
Alright okay
So if I'm thinking about
Clothing
I feel like
We talked about the
Athletic Market we talked about
Health and Wellness
I feel like there's also opportunities in like firefighters and military operations made
Yes and that
Seems to be where the sustainable businesses are focused
Today
Show me some much smaller
Any more chat warehouse and safety or the end
Goal you can actually command a reasonable
Price to build a small business
Is a few companies
Working in this area for a long time and they deliver things to the military
Vertically called smarts told your sister
And this can be anything from a way to
Distribute power around a soldier's vest
So you can imagine.
Many different devices
Clipped or pocketed in their vest
You need to keep them powered or charged
The way of the
Distributing that power throughout the best
Or way of Distributing
Throughout
So that a remote operation unit could
Our particular
Squatter team
Is behaving really going to take it to heart rates and respiration in that sort of thing
To be able to monitor the condition
Each individual
It's also got a lot of application
In Aerospace
And there's a one of the Pioneers in this area is a Canadian company called acts of skin that's long been involved
And
By being able to deploy sensors into
The suits that astronauts wear
That's been one of the key areas that
Smart Fabrics have been involved in 4 years
But I think the technology is progressing to a point where now it can be much less than
Intrusive
And you can probably
Understand what's going on with the astronauts in much greater precision
Any previously
Okay now what about taking this outside of
Of clothing
So clothing is awesome
I get the
Utility there
But there's also a lot of opportunity it feels like maybe embedding it in
Furniture or even like my sheets
Track my actual sleep patterns in a way that maybe is less intrusive than a Fitbit
What are they doing outside of
And smart
Yeah that's
That really interesting question
When you think about it is
It's one of the new
Implications
The consumer iot and wearables in general is that now we get to collect a lot more information about ourselves
The question if you're going to be sensing all this data about her
Cells in all these varieties
Products what's the best place to really deploy
Particular sensor for a given
In a use case
I do think betting is a place where we're going to see sensing appear
Just by default
And it will be sort of a common trait
In mattresses or in
Full bed assembly
That they will be able to
To report to you
Your sleep activity there's a product that t e was involved with
That is now used
It's called sleep tracker
By Serta
And basically what that's doing is sensing the heart rate and respiration and lotion
Of anybody who's on the bed
I believe it
Spice enough that it can even identify
Individual
Based on their heart rate
Because we all have unique patterns in her heart
That
Sensitive
And it's totally untrue
You'd never know it was
Floyd in the bed unless you went looking for it
Specifically that's one place but we all
Sidon automobile
There's bin sensors in
Car seats for a long time
But now with the Advent of smart textiles
You can actually deploy soft
Sensors in the steering wheel and with two hands on the steering wheel you be able to measure heart
With sensors in the seat you'll be able to measure heart rate as well as respiration you can tell if an individual's awake
Upset
You can tell alot about
What's going on under those circumstances
Even in an industrial setting in the
If you even conducted Fab
You can do things like gate to text
So that you won't need to carry around.
Key card
The building will be able to identify you simply by the way you walk
You can also do things
Give people directions throughout a venue
Their next meeting
Imagine embedded LEDs
That recognize your dates
And then like the pastor
Wherever you need to go to your next meeting
You have a lot of impact
Weed control in large areas
Oh my gosh Nick I went from
Oh my God terrifying
That could be really helpful
So
HIIT isn't it
So let's talk about a factor let's get into the Privacy factor and
All of these sensors seem to be
Deploy to figuring out what's happening in a person's body or health reasons and I know that's lovely but you know
You know I don't want my bed necessarily recognizing that I'm on it with someone who isn't my partner for exam
Because
That's scary
So if I think about that how do we do this without dealing with like identifying people are there other useful things that could
Maybe it's like light sensing
Sensors in your car
Curtains
Automatically
Open
Or things that are less like
Scary to me person
There are things that can
Be done with
Fabrics themselves this is another genre
Smart Fabrics words not about biometrics
About environmental science
So you can imagine shirts
Or clothing
Brick that has interaction with the outdoor
And in big cities
Places that I traveled
Do you like Shanghai
The air quality
What is she wearing a jacket
Something that
Would have a small section of it
That would change color
To give you some indication of air quality and let you know when you should be
Concern there's things like that
It could be done there's also
The opportunity now we
Research being done universities to
Actually use Fabrics that can generate a little bit of a charge
Kinetic energy
I guess we move in s
We walk either things that don't have any applications
Privacy
But they do provide a certain utility
I think another interesting option is things like haptic feedback for wayfinding for example
I've always because I can't tell my left from my right I've always wanted to have
Sleeves or
Maybe in my shoulders
It's like hey turn left here
I seen
More than one startup come up with
Products shoes
That will give you a half on the left shoe or the right shoe depending on where you're supposed to turn
That can be used
People who are visually impaired
Where we're trying to go
Let's talk about business models not just business models for the
How many starting this but how this stuff gets done
I think what we'll see is that people will come up with certain technologies that will get lice
Intersection between technology and fashion
Which for me as a guy who is not fast
Lesbian
Fascinating Journey
To see that
Not only can this technology be useful
Can provide really valuable insight into our health
Adorn fireman
But there's an aspect of the technology that can be used
To be beautiful and I think it's in cases like
Is that
Where
The fashion industry will
And it would then become much more acceptable
Unless avant-garde
There's been some people who have experimented with
Kind of social
Smart Fabric
You can imagine going to a football game
Where are you wearing your
Favorite players Jersey
And it has haptics built into it
Every time your player takes a hit you feel something
In that part of the Jersey
Or if your team scores a goal that shirt lights up
You can imagine the rest of the fan
In the stadium having their shirts on ladybug
The same time
To get these kind of shared experiences
That's another issue
A real useful case
But it's
And I think it's that combination between
Technology and fashion
They can really
Help push this
Forwarding
Real viable commercial
Enterprises
Yes I think the fun stuff especially like the football jersey is a great example
Because people already spend too much money
I could totally see how something like that
So where are we with the economic
So in terms of
How much these Fabrics cost per
Are yard I don't even know
Certainly
In electronics in technology
We're in
Slow mix
High volume
What is produced
The same thing in extremely high volume
Lowest possible
In fashion it's
Much different
You're providing
Clothing that changes every season and even if you have us
Successful line of clothing
Sizes so it's really much more of a high mix low volume
The two
Diametrically opposed
The good news is
As Mobile Electronics proliferate whether it's wearables or
Smartphone
The cost of all those Electronics
The incremental cost to look at a new industry like
Smart clothing
Is slowly decreasing
The challenges
With the integration of the sensors
And the electronic
There's a few players out there both jabil and Flextronics
No flex
Double stem sinking
Significant amount of effort into being able to deploy
Smart clothing and solve these problems
Brands
Any bothan some.
Projects
It's still very early days
You Netflix has some partner
Better traditional
Textile manufacturer
Investing in this area have we as well
But it's still very early
And without
Big money tree
Really
Focused effort
It's going to be a lot of hit and miss
Projects
That's it
1 as we see continued
Investment and things like firefighter safety
Body cameras on police officers or decreasing the technology of the military and
Space exploration that investment is going to
Continue and Nick
TTC
Does technology going to continue being developed in North Carolina and NC State and Raleigh has a fantastic
Body-worn sensor
Particularly Amy a textile in a
Even so you're still basic
Problems
The connector
The coast between a textile and electronics
That's funny
That has yet to be solved
A TE Connectivity we've looked at that end
Simplism
It's actually a very significant challenge to go from something
Soft and pliable to something
Hard and firm
Let's talk about
What other big problem
For that switches sustainability
When I think about
Smart Fabrics I get really really excited but then I'm also like
That's going to be horrified because right now you know
Clothing does get recycled
And I feel better about tossing away a cotton shirt that I might
Something that's covered in Silver Sol
How do you guys think about designing for sustainability or do people think about that at all
I think at this early stage very few people
Thinking about it they're thinking about survivable
But the sustainability is an issue because
In
Fashion industry overall
Sustainability is really an important question that a lot of companies are struggling
So I think if we do look forward
The electronics
People like cheese
Could you play into an extent the raw materials area this
We've looked at conductive inks for a long time
Finding
Formula for
Conductive ink that is biodegradable that would have a lot
As long as you can still meet the bass
Requirements of being deployed
Textile so I think there are going to be advances like that that will
Current parallel but
Very little of it
Before
We start seeing
Really good
Valuable businesses emerging in
Syria
All right but Nick Picks so much for talking to me about this as a fashion lover and a tech lover I am excited
Terrified
And back to excited
My pleasure state
Happiest people
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week