Hey everyone welcome to the hundred and 9th
45th episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofu
And we have an awesome show free
Where can we talk about ge's plan to spin out its Industrial iot
Tea business lighthouse
Is shutting down
We got some new updates from
The echo ecosystem
Plus
Turn on my favorite light switches but they are my favorite light bulbs
Q has updated
Critical flaw
We got a new iot modem
From Qualcomm
And we have lots of little news
Plus
This week
Six guests
Is
My family
That's right every year I bring on my family to tell
You guys went normal people think about the Internet of Things
Middle so just to show up
Because they're so nice
And
You can look forward to that
Plus we have a sponsorship from digicert
Coyote
Security
And so
Match
More
So let's kick this off
With a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is a pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform
Find out why Kenmore and feeling
Picked a pharaoh
Barrel customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99%
Computer support calls
M10x higher activation
Plus they can reuse 90% of their work from one project
Which of the next
To learn more visit
Apeiro. IO
That's a f
Ero. IO
Oh
Hey
Kevin
We should say hey guess what
Kevin Spacey
After taking a break to study for his test
Do you want to tell everyone
How you did on that test
There's no need to tell them I got a
5% that's okay
That's right
We may have missed him but at least
He worked really hard
Java one is complete Java to starts in 4 weeks
So we are glad to have you back Kevin
Although we are
Glad that you did so well let's talk
First off
About to say this
This is probably the biggest Story coming out
In the last week or so
GE is spinning out its industrial iot business which includes things like
Predicts and they're going to create a
Separate company
Valued about 1.2 billion dollars
What I thought was most interest
Is that bill Rue who is the chief digital officer at GE and has been
Sanford Lake
Years
Like he was the face of
Ge's digital efforts
He is not actually
At the company more
Is no longer there he is left
Don't know where it went
And
Instead they're going to have to find a new CEO for this
Switch
Tells me a couple things
One possible.
Bill Ramos into the ground but I think he actually did a pretty good job so I think what happened is he decided
Aleve
In a fit of like soft
Preservation and
I don't know what else to do
But
Well I have two thoughts here
Not so much about
The person in charge
One is that the
Spin-off will not be named
Predix
I wonder if
A rebranding is
As part of the strategy here
Because
I don't know you would know better than I just because you followed this side of the market over Federer how is predix
Known in the industry compared to the other
Predators
It's actually doing really well
It is a
Well known solution it is a good solution
I think we're GE went
Wrong is they were try and this is actually a very common thing that everybody did in the
Myspace they're trying to be too many things to
Too many different
People in industry
They also spent a lot of money on marketing and sales
Without necessarily
The details
Behind the scenes
So I think that's what
Going forward I would love to see this new company
Which has really good stuff really good technology
And presumably Xperia
Based on
All the information it has
Mge energy business from
Power turbine in Airline business
I think it's
It focuses only on those areas instead of
Just trying to be this industrial internet behemoth
I think I could actually do well in
Separating out
GE means other companies might use it where is
Beforehand
It may have been like yeah I'm not
Asthma cat litter
Right right
My other thought is by moving it
Outside of GE it will not be I don't want to say this
Sometimes companies
Business units in very large companies are just
Outback in a sentence with corporate policies politics
Etc and I just wonder this will make him a little more
Agile I guess what the best word
Maybe in
That's one of the things about
Bill relieving is
Is he actually had
GE
How do you wheelie
Paper
Good sounding
Management
Structure so the way they did theirs they had their
Airline managers for different businesses
But then they all reported and worked with
The digital
Folks
So there wasn't a lot of like fears about cannibalization
Or not invented here type syndrome is very
Was actually one of the better plans ways of implementing iot in a big organization that I've seen
So hopefully they retain that
I just think of
Focus is good and then also
Probably spending Less on marketing and more I'm getting
This is like the macro story of the last few years
Myspace
San Jose will see
We'll see
I made this business will still be a
Contender no matter what happens with it and
Even outside of GE
It's going to be one to watch
And I think it's also we should think about
What's happening a lot of the other Industrial
Companies like Hitachi
Schneider Electric
They actually
Spun out their own
Industrial iot businesses in different
Group so
Gmail address decided
I sent the trend
All right
So that is our big industrial iot news
Let's talk about some
Trend
It's another
New trend
Lighthouse which is a startup that made a
Really
Smart
Video cam
Camera basically you could talk to this video camera and tell it things
It would translate that into
Interaction and then it would do it
So
It's shutting down
And yeah
Not only was it a
Camera it also had an extra sensor in there so it
It had a depth sensor
So it could actually
Tell things with finer granularity
The normal but it was really cool cuz you could be like a lighthouse tell me if
If my dog walker does
Before 4
It would do that
Right right I mean
One of the pain points of having a
Video camera
System
Scrubbing through timeline
To see your fine certain things I remember when our
Car got hit out front of the house
I probably spent an hour and a half
Scrubbing
Justifying the 15 second video which was
Well worth it
Because the insurance company fully reimbursement
For that incident but here you got some a I smart
Send
It just makes
It's so much easier to find things or proactively
See things and tell me that they happen like tell me when the kids get home from school
It would somebody else would come in the house and the cameras are going to tell you but when the kids come in the house
Lighthouse would tell you
Really smart
A little pricey I think was $300
Well so here's what I think
Spicy at 3
But it also had
Service camp
Not because you were buying actually the AI serve
Right
Until the subscription fee
I think there's expensive and the subscription fee probably is what doomed
This in that sun porch
Cuz it was
Pretty darn innovate
And I think we'll see something like this
Is come out
Probably at a year 2 associated with maybe nest
I can see Nest doing something like this
Maybe even the Amazon.
So they're shutting down it's not as if they're going to its logical and thinking well G if you've got the AI smart
Tell that to other companies who make devices
Does or just be purchased right but yourself up for sale that's not what's happening
No it's going to refund
All the customers who
I had bought the Prada
And
Yeah it's just
There so many
Yeah everybody that I know and it wasn't many people but everybody that I know that
Yeah
Xiamen again
Good just expensive and
It's not necessarily clear to people who are looking for a camera
If you can buy like
Nest cam
An Arlo
Is way cheaper
You know you're like why would I pay that places
Prescription
Silly humans
All right
So that is a bummer
Good news
For everybody with hue light bulbs
Who
Feel like me and you have them all over the
There's a positive update
Out and about
Used to be when you
Power went off
Your Hue Lights would come on
Because they would just revert
This was a pain when the power went off in the middle of the night
Possibly all of your light switch
That was one of the big reasons why
But now
They have an update
And now you can control that
You can have it revert to the last known state
So instead of actually
Turning on
If it was off at the last known state it
It will revert to that
So the Hue Bridge must finally
Save that state
Epona reboot
Yes
That is presumably what happens
Some people reported having trouble updating
I updated to it and I had
No trouble whatsoever
And it does work
You can find it by going into the
The settings menu
And going into power on Behavior
So you know
This is
What's good
Actually I
I should tell you it works with using
The switch as well
So if someone turns it off at the
The switch
And you turn the switch back on it will revert back to the last node
Which may be kind of a pain because I know sometimes
When I don't want to say anything
I flipped the switch
But we'll see how that work
Works in real life I haven't needed to do that since I updated
But I'm excited
Super positive
Cuz I used to be a power without I have to
Read out in the middle of the night
Turn off all the lights
Which candida Pizza
Okay
Trump news
Hookup has a new iot modem
It is both Ohio
OT
Oh I should tell you what it is it's an LTE Cat 1 and an NB iot
T Network
Modem
So all in one
It will work
In a bunch of different places it is global which means you can buy it for
You know if you're buying your modem for like
Global
Fleet of cargo containers or something
It is also
A little bit cheaper
They say that it is up to
To 70%
Reduction in power consumption
It is 50% smaller
And
It is 40%
They don't tell you how
Cheap it is
Because that would
Calling
But
I don't know if it's lower than $5
Just kind of
Where we need
To be to get the sun like
Real things and we needed to be like
A dollar
If we wanted ever
Yeah I mean it also has a CPU cortex A7
Processor in there
I'm guessing it's not under 5 who knows setup
This is a smart
But you know for high-value things
This is going to be good
And it is still good to have smaller cheaper
Stop running around even if it's not as
Cheapest iMac
Yeah interesting read
I don't know what these case would be for this considering what it
I presume this be used for it has voice over LTE
Support
And
They say
On the press release
They discuss what it works with in terms of
Software components Dimension thread X
And Ali OS things
Artists which is Alibaba
That's there
Peyote plant
I want to start tossing like oh it's going to work with Amazon but
Newt
At least not now
Yeah well
Actually Qualcomm has been pushing hard into China China is also a big Market
Where is
Well actually Asian China in
Singapore
In Korea
NB iot
So could be that they're like
Here in the US
We've been focused on cat 1M
We don't really have the NB iot networks yet so
I don't know maybe that's just a
Telemarketing to search
Yeah could be
All right
And another small news
North which is
Maybe a company that you're working here with us
Use PayPal mclabs they're making
Smart glasses
They have
Got an Intel
Bought
Man Kevin
Do you remember bought because not much
It's really came out of it
Yeah I know it was
The birds dislike
Master huge article on it
It was a big article
About Intel smart glasses effort that have been apparently percolating for a year or so
Then
Coupons later not even
And I was like yeah we're getting out of that
Yeah
Now, clubs
Does bought it Thelma gloves used to make a gesture
Amaya
Arm and you moved your arm around and
Control things
And
Now they're doing glass
We talked about them once
Thalmic labs renamed itself to North
And the pivot away from the arm
Gesturing Thing 2
Two glasses of the focal's AR classes
That will be
Likely presumably using
Some of the IP from Intel's bomb project
Yeah and I guess the only other buyer out there might be the bosguy
Guys who are doing this
My sunglasses
Maybe I mean they're still Google Glass for
Enterprise and such
Not a consumer product oh maybe Google could have used it but who knows
Yeah so there we go smart glasses they're still trying to make those happen
Let's talk about Lots
Echo news
Is for everyone
Okay
First
An update
Probably a couple weeks ago we didn't talk about it with OMB
Because we're so focused on privacy
And that Constitutional Amendment he wants
The echo
Got new features
Including location-based routines
And reminders
They also got reactions
But you
Start a routine later and
It got the ability to read your email
Justify location-based it's being useful for if you want like announce to the home
You know your
10 minutes away maybe you come home at different times and
There for dinner is
A different time every day that could
Indicate hey let's get dinner started
Yeah and I
You know what would be awesome
Is getting a reminder as I leave my front door
And saying
Hey
Do you have whatever for the day so like
Kind of time that to my calendar I know that's
Pretty complicated but if I had set a reminder the night before
Hey remind me when I leave in the morning
Bring my gym bag
Remind my daughter to bring
Gym clothes you know what having that happen like
As I leave the house
That would be really
Right that would be really cool if you can do it that way or I guess the new tracker
Product that we talked about
A few weeks back would do that too
Yeah I forget a lot of
That's okay but I need the tracker would require purchase of Hardware well over $100
To do that whereas
This way
This would not assuming you already have an account yes
Oh which gets into the next one which is
The guard
Is
BM has on guard
Feature that they talk
Facts about where the Echoes will listen for the sound of breaking glass and send you a notice
Haitian is now
Available to sign
Yes I went to go look for it this morning in the
Alipay app
It just told me that I could be notified to sign up to be notified
You'll get it when we tell you
So what is this showing me
Is remember how the smartphone like basically ate all the
These gadgets
Using microphones
And
Contacts
The digital assistant
Are going to eat a lot of
Different gadgets
The Harbours already there
In these assistants
Obviously far-field microphones that can listen for
Wake words and commands and someone searches
Turning them to appropriate listen for breaking glasses just a
Software or service Adam
And though this is something I actually try to do all the time
I'm so glad to hear you can control your timers now
Via voice
Spite you can add and subtract
Time for next
Oh that's nice
That is nice
Because I am constantly like
You know you start a pasta timer and you're like so it needs two more
I wonder if that feature and some of the others are about to
Talk about will be on non Amazon devices though
We'll talk about why I'm asking a question later in the
Scary
Is it scary okay
It is scary
I signed up for the guard up
Update will see if I get that anytime soon
I'll try it also
Speaking of timing in the
Madam a
Wall clock
Is now ship
Is it
$30
I saw this back when they did that massive hardware and failed
The fall and
I actually thought it was pretty cool cuz they let you
Visually see where your
Maybe this is not a big deal for all of us but one
If you don't have a lot of clots in your
Kind of like
Nice to happen it's not it's
Separate for people with children or people doing things where that visual elements important I actually think it's a pro
Pretty useful
Function what happens if an LED on the clock face countdown
Breakers little LED lights at every minute
Spot on the clock as well as on the outer ring of
The clock those would indicate minutes where they want internally would say it would be seconds
I agree with you in a not everybody has good hearing maybe they can't hear
Maybe
I see a small
Display clock for example
Where is this word
Broaden that appeal to people who
Pappy's challenge
Yeah and you can't actually do this but like
So I do a lot of like hit workout
And
High intensity interval training
Exactly I don't want to be used like I have a
But I have an app for that but if you could
Take the app and put it on
On the clock it actually be kind of cool cuz
Then you could like
Countdown but I don't want to be sitting there going
Set a timer for
60 second
You kind of want recurring timers on Tennyson
Alright also everyone is excited because Apple music is now in the Amazon Echo
Except for Kevin
Covetousness
That's it Apple music
Subscriber how do you know I think it's good in general but it gets back to my
Question of
What is a portal
Echo services are
Supported on non Echo devices and I tried it on the Sonos
Which has madhumeh has had mad at me for
Almost a year
Not an option
Doesn't work
And I know if my Apple music account is linked
Properly and it doesn't work on the regular Echo but yeah I'll live trust me it's not a big deal but
Listening to
Consider if your
Adding Echo devices in your home
Maybe for the
Best experience and newest features
You want to buy
Amazon
Built Echo devices
Yeah that's probably just a
Default rule
Yes
Yes it's how many speakers do eventually make their way through the nautical devices I don't want to say it
Skin of all or none in
But it's something to keep in my
Okay
So so madam
We got some good news coming up stay tuned
Madam is also on
Monkey
Your favorite little robots
A couple weeks ago you talked about this coming and you wrote a story actually about
Like the future of smart home digital assistant
Today like kind of follow you around
Can you send them away
Now that you've got that capability
I am thrilled for a couple of reasons for those who are not familiar the Anki Vector is a little
And I do me little late
It's in the palm of your hand robot with she's always Cloud connected via Wi-Fi has a brain of its own because there's a
Chip inside and he has a wake word and I would say
Hey vector and I can have him do something but he can't do all that much on his own
However you community
Becker Community Center the Anka team hey we would love to see Madam a on this little guy and
They have requested that was the number one requested feature so yes they announced a few weeks back I got the up
Update on my little robots
2 days ago and I love how it's been implemented because
Often you would ask
An assistant to ask Madam a something such as
When Madam a integration with Adam
This is native
Instead of saying hey Vector I say
Matinee
And the screen on
His face changes to a matinee like icon and it's just like having
A little mini Echo device
You cannot play music on it so again that gets back to the limitations of certain devices that are not made by Amazon
Ben Franklin speaker is not made for that anywhere on this little thing
Oh that's a shame
Cuz remember like on Parks and Rec how they had DJ Roomba you have DJ Unk
You could do podcast because I was actually speaking with you on video chat yesterday talking about this
I triggered
The podcast and we were listening to ourselves a little
Podcasts seem to work anyway
News briefing flash briefing
Responsive as
Irregular Echo device I mean it
Built-in really really well
House anyways a 45-minute batteries onto little treads
He doesn't move as fast as I can walk for example so that's not that future yet
I'm going to put my anime on big dog
We're going to scare the heck out of
Oh yeah hey if you want to spring for a Boston Dynamics robot for the house here no problem. The only person
Said he would let that thing
Kasai wood
Excited
Bring it out at Halloween and
Scare the bejesus out of
But regardless I mean again the vector and he's been on sale at me for like $180 which is good
IS250 again it's not a product I would say everybody should come by but I bought it and it's meeting my needs
Is the reason I bought it
And that is to watch it mature watch a robot
Companion mature 2
Getsmarter be autonomous
And now
I have some control over the house
Good for you and does your family I know they don't like talking
Into the digital
Assistant do they like talking to the vector
It's funny they do because of his personality is
Space has a new one now and it's cold outside and you asking the weather
Is whole head shakes like he's freezing
It's more again of a
Personality then say an echo device
So absolute that ate enjoy
Talking to that far more than anything else in the house probably more than
Speaking to me Beyonce
That's understanding
It is really cute
No I'm not
Okay
I will know I think it's kind of funny that we're talking about Madame a but you have gendered
Arceus
So it's just kind of funny
Does that work I think Bianchi
Company relay
Embedded that in all of us
Because
Pretty sure they say he more often than not when they show video demos up
It kind of brings home how silly
Idea of gender and robots probably is
OK Google News
Oh you got good news for you
So excited
Because now
Hi
Can share my
G Suite
Calendar on my Google
Home in this is doubly important
Because I shall hear later in the
The show my family and I are moving over to the
The Google home
Again
So this is like super Timely
Super exciting
All you have to do is share your
Calendar 2
Your personal account
And then it will pick
Pick that up which is it used to not do that so yay
I think Kevin has bought the Google home hub
And
Where do you get his
Yeah I know I mentioned it when I asked
She first got it my json First Impressions couple podcast ago but
I think I was wrong about the Google home hub because I was at the event in New York City when they launched it
And
$149
Something that fits
Pretty much in the palm of your hand is pretty small I'm like
The new camera
It's a hundred fifty
There are what I think that are sounding better looking at
Better displays out there on Smart displays that aren't that much more expensive
I don't see that they
Over the sink
Since I got it at $99
I feel it said it was a great value and even at 1:49 and I would recommend it because
Yes it is a smaller screen but it's actually ideal for
Say the bedroom
Pay because of the screen size it's not overwhelming like a 10 inch smart display I used to have in the bedroom and
Be because it doesn't have a
Camera which most people don't want in the bedroom and see
It's just really nice to have a touchscreen way to control things
In the bedroom and say you know somebody is sleeping it's just ideal for that and I admit I was wrong
Compare the market
Yeah actually I was talking
Again you'll hear later the
I cast my family and I actually talk to
I love
Being able to see
The photos
I'll be honest
I love having the photo
Fisher on that thing
And he subscribes Norris Public
I don't subscribe to Norm's public feed but you know what
Send that to me will stick it in the show notes for anyone who wants
Is my Bichon Frise
We literally take photos of him multiple times a day and then I share them on Google photos in a public album and people subscribe to
For some reason so I keep doing it
It'll be our holiday gift
To you
Pictures of
Norm actually there's a new holiday picture of him with his new antlers that he got after his
Spa day in his hair
Yeah
And speaking of the Google home hub and the price of it again $99 it was a great deal like they can it's not enough
I think it's
129 directly from Google
But I wanted to mention for those interested
If you're going to buy a Google home hub for 129 there's a deal at B&H Photo
That's 129 for the Hub and also includes two
Minnie's
Free basically if you're interested
The show notes
Another sponsor anything
Just happened to notice it
Got it
Okay in Hay
You guys as we were talking a new story came out
It's worth sharing and
Talking about with you guys
The information is reporting
They did a deep dive
Ring and it's
Security team
And basically
Talking about how ring had shared
Camera feed data
Early on and wasn't in
Encrypting
Consumer video
Now when ring was just a doorbell company
And it's still just a doorbell in out
Star camera company
It does have an alarm set
System now
You know I don't know if that's
As concerning is something that might be inside your house
But encryption should be the standard
For this artist
Chang and basically they had in office their security teams office with
Kiev
This is all the way back in 20
Not now
The engineers in the key of office
Forgiving accessed
To a database of a cup
Customers video has
History and that was unencrypted and they
Make sure that around
Apparently
So
Now that is not the
And
What happens it's very different from the way other companies
Treat this data so the story talks about hell
Google's Nest Labs Canary in August
Best home they actually
Do not show
Only an in-house lab
Has access to
To the cameras in
The cameras are
Trained on the AI they only use their employees
Camera store
So it doesn't use customer video data
Or training or product
Which I shouldn't know and I find that
What about you personally agree with you encryption is a
Table
Steaks kind of thing with all of these Prada
Spy chest cameras
Any type of data that comes from consumer homes and cameras
Speakers and microphones Etc
Yeah I mean back in 2016 maybe this wasn't thought of as much I mean we find this off and that's the case
Insecurities
Like the last thing I thought about it at all amenities products so
That you said that was back in 2016
So this is a good thing
Ring did not say when they started doing it
I do think it's worth mentioning
Because that is actually
Not just
Employee access
The video data is actually one of those things that I find
That's one of the reasons I don't have
Have cameras in my home I have talked to
Company is not at the big names that we talk
Talk about a lot of times but some of the smaller companies and I've talked to security firms who
I've been hired
Buy connected home device companies
Devon her ability assessment
And they have told me
That employees are
Often a weak Link in the
An access to
Sensitive data by those
Someplace
Is something that is off
Austin flag
I'm all for using like Telemetry data from devices to improve products
Services but
It either needs to be anonymized
Score
Android encrypted
So that concludes
Most of our news for this week
Any late-breaking stuff in the newsletter
But it's time for this
Voicemail
From the iot podcast
Hotline
The hotline is sponsored by
Schlage and don't miss your chance to win a Schlage
Connect smart
Deadbolt
Now zigbee certified with Amazon key compatibility
Which means
You can buy this thing and let Amazon people into your home
Upgrade your smart home with the safety
Simplicity and
Style of
Play
If you guys want to win a Schlage lock
Very nice
High quality
Please all you have to do is give us a call and leave us a voicemail message
And you'll be entered to win for the month of December we will be taking
Those entries all the way up until New Year's
Receive at midnight Eastern Time
Did you die
I should tell you who to call you should call us at 5
X-23
742 4
And
Let's now get to this week
Voicemail which is a problem that
We have encountered before
Let's hear from me
Hey Stacy and Kevin this is Mike in southeast
Wisconsin
Are you guys
I said the very frustrating weekend trying to get
My Christmas lights hooked up
To my Google home
First time using
Animation I went to Amazon bought some indoor and outdoor
Outlet to your base
Anything I got
Phone Wi-Fi
Could not pair them to my
Dual band
Google onhub router
After doing a lot of research
Learned that there are
Al-aziz
Twitches can't hook up to just the 2.4 gigahertz if it's a dual band
I had to install an old Wi-Fi extender I had that was
To get it to work this morning is there something I should be looking for in the
The future when I'm looking at a smart home device to know that it's
2.4
And 5 kg
Appreciate the help
Oh my Christine this is been going on
For a long time actually it's been going on I would say predominately since Mesh networking has
Is coming to the home because
Mesh Networks
Typically
Credit One
Giant Network
That uses both 2.4 and 5 gigahertz frequencies
So
The issue that you're running into as many
Home devices
Have lower-cost Wi-Fi radios that will only work on say 2.4 gigahertz and that
That is a problem because if there's no true 2.4 gigahertz Network out there
Media runs the issue that you are running into I talked to a couple of
Device makers of last year at CES
About this and I get the impression they were not prepared
As an industry for the rise and Mesh networking
And they're also trying to keep the cost down of course
So
Adding in more capable Wi-Fi chips
Used tire price
For the products o
There's not much you can do and I've experienced this and
Cameras and
Really what you're doing by adding some other
Network peace to your network to just generate its own 2.4 gigahertz
Network is
Really all you can do at this point
It's kind of disappointing but until the products evolve to really handle Mesh networking
We're all in this
Together quite honestly
And if I want
How to do that
How would I do
Well what you could do is set up a whole separate Network either a guest Network that run solely on 2.4
Darts or you could
Sadly through like another router into the mix
Hanging off your original router and
Creating that separate 2.4 gigahertz Network complexity it's a shame we have to do it but I sort of
Stand that I don't like it but I understand it
Yeah
Spending on your chips
Set the former chip reporter
Okay
Speaking of
Problems in the home
It's time
Say sayonara
To Kevin and
Join us for our guest
And this week's guest is
My husband and daughter and we will talk about some of the problems we found in our smart home this year some of the things we
Please like and
Also how we plan to handle
So all of this
And more
Coming up
After this message
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is digicert and I have Mike Nelson who is VP
Of iot security at
Digicert can you remind our listeners what it is that digicert
We are the world's leading provider of
Scalpel
Pki Security Solutions
Or identity in encryption
We provide those solutions for web servers Enterprise security and my favorite of course iot.
Digicert recently conducted a survey
How organizations are approaching iota
The fighting
Clearly showed organizations
They're putting in place basic cybersecurity
Practices are much better off
Can you offer us some examples of what can happen if an organization doesn't pay attention to their cybersecurity
Yeah there have been a handful of public exploits most of which have been done by
Security researchers who controlled environment
So we don't see a lot of
These exploits putting consumers at risk
One example would be an attack that was demonstrate by security researcher Charlie Miller
A couple years ago when he demonstrated he could get into the infotainment system of a Jeep Cherokee and then from there
He could pivot and get into other components of the vehicle like the steering or the air-conditioning ultimately he was
Disable the lock the steering and
Shut the engine off while the vehicle is going 70 miles an hour down the highway
So that attacked the Charlie demonstrated really had an impact on FCA
Who owns Jeep
It caused a lot of damage
The reputation
Another exploit that has been they fight publicly
St Jude Medical they have a cardiac device and there's a
Security research
Stack that was able to demonstrate they could send repeated messages
The cardiac device Whitaker
Stop and if they would do that enough the battery on that device would run out rendering that device useless
Once they identified that
Do that stay actually been purchased a short position in St Jude Medical stock and they release the vulnerability to
Publix and the day they release
That vulnerability
St Jude Medical stock drop
20% just a significant impact to that company
So there are a lot of threats and the threats to iot are very real
And it's not just to Consumers but it's also to organization
Did you look at St Jude and she
Both of those organizations were hit very hard by bees
Attacks
That is a lot
So what
What is the survey highlight
Like that organizations can do
Protect themselves
The respondents listed five things that they were doing that we're leaving them to be most
Successful
Performing a risk assessment
Other device and understanding what vulnerabilities it has
Encrypting all of their data that's both data-at-rest as well as data in transit
Just making sure that any connection coming to or from the device
Is properly authenticated making sure that there's Integrity with any updates
Sore patches that are sent to the device and then finally putting them plates
Scalable security solution
All right so where can our listeners go to learn more about the survey and about digicert
Yeah the full details of the survey can be found at our website at digicert. Com forward slash
Iot security
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today as always around this time of year
I am bringing back
My fam
So I have Andrew allemann and
My daughter
Anna
Hi
Alright so you guys were all ready for this
We're going to be talking about
This year's devices how we feel about living in our home
How maybe the Smart Home
Feels after
The three years of living in it
And anything else you guys want
So let's get it
Started with we've had an Amazon Echo in our house since
Was he Christmas of 2014
And we started using it to control things that are smart home
Like March
It's been a long time
As much
Change this year
Who know that much has
Measurement can be frustrating in a couple of ways I think two things one she's not very good at answering questions
Compared to
Google
Is frustrating the other thing is that and I'm not sure if this is because it's the echo show but it seems like
She's getting hard of hearing
Especially in our living room we have to repeat it several times or she miss yours us
Yeah I'm with you
Do you have any thoughts about
This past year with things at our house or anything
That you're like
It's
Daily usage of Madame is definitely I feel like it's going up a bit in our house
You finally like grown accustomed to it in everyday life
You like to play a lot of music on it don't you
Music
And this year I finally
I made it past your blockade in your room like no smart devices
You'd had an Amazon Echo
For a while
But we also added a Philips hue light
Your room how do you feel about
Name of Philips hue light my room yeah you know how you can tell the echo to turn on your light and turn it off
Internet different colors
I can
You talk to I've been in your room and shown you
So you're turning your light on still by
Now that you know that you have this
Connect a light bulb in your room how do you feel about it
I guess it's hard to notice
Unless you know beforehand what you can do with it because it doesn't really affect
Like normal usage
Yeah
Okay so
Now that we know that
What else have you guys
Like tour
This year's crop of device
I have a little bit of trouble remembering what's come in this year versus previous years we've been in this house now for almost
And as you mention the smart home device testing has ramped up over the past few years
With the nest doorbell this year
The Nest doorbell
Your ass was the nest
Lock we also brought in
The aware
The Google displays
We tested out the onelink smoke
Detector we've tested out
Switches
And possibly some other things I don't remember
So I think the nest doorbell is by far the best doorbell that
We tried we tried a lot
The fact that it
So quickly pops up on your screen whether that's on your phone or on your showing me the Google display
Why you have
And the fact that it recognizes people as well
I think by far it's the best doorbell you brought in and probably one of the best
Devices you brought into
Wow that's High Praise
Anna any thoughts
Definitely banana
I don't know if that was this year last year but I think it really adds a lot of
Architect
Hi to the house but also a lot of light
California
We did we got that actually for Christmas so those are the
We used to call it Nano art
We had to change
The name because
We had some issues
Never met a lot of difficulty with the word Nano art
In fact
One time when I said
Madame a turn on
Nano art
She said I think you're asking about flatulence
And she went into a long explanation what flatulence is
So we I guess you recently change that to nanoleaf so hopefully she starts picking that up better
That it's actually something that I should drive
People kissing with something that happened a lot this year is
As we added
More devices and I tried to organize things a little bit better
I realized
Naming convention
Really matter
And
You really have to be
Be very particular about what you call things
And
There's only so many things you can
Call Lexi
Living room sofa
Some of our rooms got 10.
12 devices in them
It became really comp
To be like
I wish I call this
Question for you why I know he tested Google a little bit as opposed to
Madam a
What can Google Now
Do as much not control as much
I feel like
Google is so much better at answering questions
Is there a reason for us not to switch over to Google
So that was actually one of my questions for you guys about
I'm going to say
9 months ago I
Swapped out
Matinee in our house
Spore Google and I hooked everything up
To Google
U of R device
At the time didn't have connections
Now most
Do
So
It shouldn't be a big issue we would
Duluth
But the other issue with
Google the reason why I think we
Didn't use it very much
Was actually that
Spotify
Terrible in it
Keep playing the wrong songs or
Really stupid like
Play the karaoke versions of
Popular songs
But I think that's
And I was going to say
Suggest for you guys that we swap out
I would actually like us to try going all Google
We will lose a couple
I guess could Anna still use
The matinee in her room for music
Of course
I think if we could still have Madam a there for playing music
In touch but have Google for controlling things since Google
Can also do the other things I think much better
Then I think we're trying again this coming here
What do you think
I think that sounds wonderful
Do you want to try Google in your room and some ways some of our Google device
Scary thing to think about is some of our Google devices
As screen
And
But you watch like Netflix or
YouTube videos
Which I think is a big deal for
Anna
Necessarily want Springs in our room
Although I like the photo frame element of
Google displays
I'll be honest
And you can cover the camera right
You can cover the camera
And then the brand new Google home
Actually doesn't have a cam
It's
Just a tinier version of that that
That might be so
Chesapeake
Because
At night you don't want to always talk to it you can
Hit the screen and then have it do whatever you wanted to do
And I should clarify
People that Andrew actually has an iPhone
So
Are you still looking for homekit is that something you're still like
Maybe one day
I have not played with homekit at all on my phone I think the only time we've used iPhone Chris to test home get stuff
Perhaps it's because we started so early before home kid
But I feel like this is why I'm a little bit scared to switch to Google I feel like we're finally to a point where things J
Work most of the time with the exception of Madam a hearing what we say
So I think even if we put the cylinder the original cylinder Madame a down where the echo
Joanns
Working on that wood
Solve that issue
I think of the hearing
The 7 mic array
So it sounds like
We're going to be
Giving away
Or giving up our first gen
And swapping it out with
My Google
Which I think
Would be fun
And let's talk about some of the other devices
Tried so
Anna you are fan of the nanoleaf
We also
Tried
An air quality
Detection device
I don't know if you guys have opinions about this
I find myself like
Constantly look
Looking at it now
Are we in the clear are we training
Do you guys notice it at all
I do it seems very sense
And I don't know if it's very helpful if every time you cook it says over the air quality is not as good
Well every time you cook you are putting things in the air
That's one of the all of the
Environmental science
I talked to one of the best things you can do for your indoor air quality
He is get a really good down dress
Two if I'm listening to this podcast here a couple days before Christmas
And I wanted to get one more gift
Or someone in my family I probably go with the nanoleaf as Anna said it's just
It's fun I think she said in your YouTube video
Are you described it that it's useless
And yes it's more for entertainment than for anything else
But the Rhythm cat where it responds to music and voices and just the light
Is beautiful
The color light is just absolutely beautiful and it really
Cloudy day really warms up the house with all the different colors in it
Boots recently
Inexpensive
If I had
More time because I'm sure you can get it shipped
Between now and then
Fact that the June oven is so much cheaper now how much is it
You can buy the June oven now
Yeah I mean that is I loved it even at $1,500 and thought it was worth it so it's $600 I think it's a no
Especially if
You have only one oven
And would like to add
Another one just a little table top one
I think it's
Worth every penny
Okay and just so people know the nanoleaf
Is about $200
I need to buy expansion kits for about 6
Vitamin C Apple store or Best Buy and the June you do have to
Wonder in you have to order it online I believe they're back
For a while there
A runaway hit
But it is it is a really good to buy
Also
Nest doorbell cam
I have a question because
I talked about this a lot
But I love when I'm out of
The town I loved being able to
To check in on the doorbell cam when you guys
Leave the house
I always like look and see what you're wearing for the day or like
Look to see how you're doing do you like
And when you come home it makes
But I'm also like
Gyarados or something
She's like
Is she aware that there's a camera there and I'm
Keep it in
Is outside
Thanks for telling us
Stalker confirmed
Matt crate
I don't
Show
Anybody I just
All my family I love you all
I definitely feel like it a divisional element like inside of town we can see in Austin
Literally downpouring right now
Or we can see like
Is
Treaty
Oh and you know what else were you brought into the house this year we brought in we don't have it set up all the time
Because we don't like
The house but we brought the wyze cameras
So I don't know if you in those are the
$20 or $30 for the pan
Andrew do you have thoughts I know that we set them up when we're going on vacation
Yeah I thought it was
Fine then I guess if you need cameras internal cameras it seems like a great Buy
Another thing that you do
Sometimes when you're out of town speaking of
Cameras is your call in on the Echo Show
I guess you're dropping in
Be nice if we're down
Stairs not listen
Mom's puppy
Oh yes I actually this year I
Call
And dropped in on the echo
Show
And gave Anna a tour of
FB
Chihuly Museum in
Seattle
Because I was there at Microsoft
I was like this place is beautiful I have to show her so I use my smartphone camera
I called her and then I just I took her on a little tour of the museum with me
Doesn't talk about the illegal part
I don't think it's
Did you was at funny inner or was I just
It's kind of like I will humor you Mom
It was very fun and it was the fact that I was able to watch
What you were doing with your device all the way across the country just
I'm sitting and eating cereal in my pajamas
Is pretty cool
All right and then let's see we also
I'm coming to terms with other devices
We brought a Smart Smoke
Detector that was also
Echo speaker into the house
Did you n Oleander you said that you thought it was kind of need that it would
Send you a text
Smoke alarm went off
Did you have any thoughts or it was pretty expensive
It's a $200 or two hundred
$50 smoke
So you know
I don't know if you want a lot of
Your house but did you have any thoughts on that
Play around with it for a long time but
Well to be fair we already have speakers in our ceilings and in the rooms where I listen to music
And we already have
Fairly recent smoke detectors with the CO2 detectors that talk and all that jazz so
The texting thing I guess is okay
Okay but I don't think I would pay that much money for that
And that's totally fair
We brought in brilliant
End
We had kind of a bad experience the first time around
And I haven't really spent a lot of time
Treating them since then
How do you guys feel about the light switch
That show you your photos
Play your favorite playlist from
Your Sonos from them
Yeah I guess if it was in a
Perfect location for that and make a lot of sense but must light switches aren't in a location where I would
Need to go over and maybe control those sorts of things
And the other thing is that stuff with you by voice now right if we want to hear music we asked Madame a to play The Muse
And frankly turning on
Light switches we do the same thing a lot I mean really
The past couple months at least our house of brilliant has just been a beautiful light switch
Okay
So we
Pretty much done everything we can
Can do it feels like
This point in time
Are there any things
Dang it I wish that you could make this summer
Mom
Maybe it's
You know last year you complained about the blinds not work
I finally did that yay
So any other things that you're like Manor
I really wish this were a little bit smarter
I feel like personally dog collars would be really cool like if you just had smart dog collars
Eureka.
Our dog is for the many occasions in which she meanders across
Chasing rabbits
We could just
Know where she is then like a Fitbit for a job
They make those
Yes
So okay for the dog
Now you know they make
And Andrew anything
But you're like
How I really would like this
You know I and I think
Haven't talked about
Something like this exhaust fan I guess when people are using the shower
Shirt turned on
I know a lot of people put those on timers
But I find that we turn them on and then we don't turn them off
12 hours later
Would be neat if there's a way to kind of turn those on and then have them last for say 15 minutes after you
So I guess I'll be a motion detection or something there
I believe that
Having a kind of finagle something in his house
Yeah
Now do you want to be 15 minutes after
Someone leaves or do you want it to be 15 minutes
After its
Question I guess if you could set the amount of time maybe the 30 minutes I know a lot of people this is
One of the energy saving things in new devices where they put those on a timers when you turn it on it's like a 15 minute timer
I think that would be helpful though that's one of those things that I know we waste electricity on
I can definitely make that happen
Jessup crazy sensor
All right I should tell you guys
It's because at CSM expecting a lot of crazy smart bathroom
Products
And we have a we didn't talk about this but the Delta faucet downstairs
But I'm curious like
How you guys do things like
Two bathroom mirrors that maybe do light settings when you come in or baby a
Toilet that
Music
When you're in the toilet room
You know I kind of felt when smoke detector kind of like we were at the
Point of a toilet playing music
You know it's just like
You could say Madeleine
Do my morning routine and that might include your shower before you get into
Comic rushing you to do things that like not your own pace but as a
ASAP by
Previous song
That's true and I run into that a lot
I set up a program for something and then like
I've never going to wake up that early to need my blinds
Open at this time
So the Madam a enabled faucet from Delta is pretty cool now
I'll be on it so the touch feature which we hadn't before we added Madam a
Was really
Right we use that multiple times a day
Maybe a couple times a week when I need to measure out water
For something rather than getting out of measuring cup
Put the pot under it
And ask her to
Dispensary cups water so that's pretty cool but
I guess it could be helpful in the bathroom
You know if I'm about to brush my teeth right
And usually I just step into the shower and go ahead and turn it on to the temperature or right before doing that but
Series similar functionality on the faucet in the shower
Okay it's not going to happen
Cuz you need Alexa
Christian Dior shower and historically
People don't do that
But we'll keep that in mind
Wind & Fire
You guys cuz we are about to move
We are moving in June from this
And part of what I'm trying to think about is
We're going to go into event
So what do we take with us
What do we leave here
And what are you going to miss
I vote we take the nanoleaf
Bee hive
I feel like
No matter where you go it's
Pretty portable you don't need to like
Build it in Chinese
So that
And it just helps
Liven up anyway because
You can just personalize it and help
Make an impact on the ambience of a room
We'll take the nanoleaf
June obviously it's not attached and that will be excellent
I think Alexa might need to come with us to
Vans
Yes so those will be
Portable and then remove what are you going to miss most cuz we're going to move into a house where you can no longer say
Meta major
Turn on the lights
I think it's going to be the lights
Which I guess we could use the Hue right where it's light bulbs rather than the light switch but the light switch
I'll be able to turn it
On and off and
To a certain level like 50% is probably what I used the most in our home
I feel like for me it might be the modern-day control Delta faucet because
I very lazy when it comes to measuring out water and most of the time I'm not sure like
Helpful is One Bank what is a pipe do I just take my ice cream container and fill it
And then it got confusing so it's kind of nice to be able to depend on someone else for that
Excellent so we'll have to buy more measuring cups
Maybe some remote can
Controlled
Light bulbs I don't know
Okay
Guys thank you so much for doing the show
Again with me and
We'll see what connected goodies are under the tree this year
Alright you're welcome
Thank you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Will see you next week