Hey everyone welcome to us
Episode of The Internet of Things
News podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Edger co-host
Kevin tofel and we are calling this is special episode
Because it is brought to
By you
We got so sad about
All of the voicemails piled up we decided that this holiday week we would
Answer a bunch of questions from our listener
So that is our plan today
This show is brought to you by
Control for their smart home system connects all of your smart devices to make your home control
Is easy as Alexa turn on movie time to lower your Shades dim the lights
Start Netflix on your TV or when the doorbell rings you can go into what app to see who it is and turn on the porch
Porch lights with control for you can automate the devices you already have and keep adding new ones now that's smart
Head to control4.com that's control the number for cam for more information
And because this show features all of you guys is also brought to you by Schlage and
The iot podcast hotline if you want to get a chance to appear on this show or have us answer your
National Air give us a call at 5 1/2
623-7424 don't miss your chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt in Wi-Fi adapter you can enter to win by calling us and leaving a question and no
It's smarter homes
Start with Schlage will be doing that contest for the rest of July so anytime you call
Call between now and the end of July you will be entered to win that particular lock the Great loxo
Carlos asks your questions 512-262-3742
In through the month of June which just finished up we were
Giving away a Schlage Smart Sense lock so we're going to announce that later on this show take believe one of the colors
Questions that we answer on Today Show is our winner
It is it is so
You can find out
Who won
That lock
All right
Kevin
Get it started
Our first call is from
Frank
Yes
Really good question
Penn State game
Homeowners insurance and the guest you had on
Naomi Campbell Technologies
Homeowners insurance
Places that offer discounts or some kind of antenna
Houses with Smart Home
Unlike other than just alarm just wondering if you guys had any information about
Camino
Frank this is a great question
And
I'm sad to say that a lot of them still Focus mode
Mostly on home security
Not
But we got a couple
In all of the sensors in this case are basically here
Nest
Smoke detector
Actor so American family
Insurance offers discounts
Four people have a Nest smoke
Tractor and who opted into sharing if their batteries are
This is a big question for ensure
Liberty Mutual does the same thing
And I know this is security-related
But American family also offers a discount
For people who install the ring doorbell and then ring actually offers some Disco
Counts to people as well
And finally
State Farm has a deal with Canary
Where they will offer you
I think it's $20 off
The purchase of a canary but then also $20 annually
Off the
Canary subscription
Right and that's a $10 a month subscription I know because I have the canary and I pay that so that's like getting two months of the
The service are free
So we're not get to the place where Insurance firms are saying
Hey we're going to subsidize your water sensors and that sort of thing
But I will say
I think we're going to get there and I think we're probably going to get there next year so 2019 I think we'll start seeing policies
Is start seeing more discounts but we may even start seeing some of these
Policies built around
The insurance firms are really into this but as we said
Before they need that data
All right
So
Stay tuned in your life
For insurance discounts on Summer
Homegear
Next question
Hey Kevin and Stacy my name is Jeremy and I have been thinking about getting a
Smart Lock
But sometimes you know when somebody shots
The door they don't
Closing all the way
And some wondering if you guys have had that experience where maybe it's not shut all the way and then you're somewhere else like
Maybe you know I'm not at home or
Using the app to lock it like do you know
Door doesn't lock
Because of that boat can go into the hole because the doors not shut all the way
Man
Jeremy I have
I've tried like half a dozen smart locks and I literally have
Never thought about this
It is until August actually introduced something called Dorset
Which is basically a magnetic sensor that you stick near the deadbolt
Or inside your door for
And it will actually detect if the deadbolt has been engaged
The door is actually
Still open this is literally never happy
But it's a really good question
And right now
That's really the main
Option out there so you could buy the August door lock
With doorsense in it
Has it integrated as part of the package or
Kevin came up
Well it's clever that August has done that's because they have integrated the sensor with the lock
However the center itself appears to be just a magnetic sensor and you can certainly buy any one of them
The number of
Magnetic sensors that use typically zigbee or Z-Wave
Which would replicate exactly what door sense does so if you don't want an August door lock you can certainly try a different Smart Lock
And add your own magnetic sensor it may not look as pretty because most of those are not in recessed options so you'll have a little
Sensor on the door and the door frame but still that would work and give you more options to choose from if you
Like that actually makes a lovely recessed sensor that you do then have to drill the hole in your door
Mordor and
Put it in there
But it is recessed
The final option I'll give you
Is pretty low
It's pretty easy pretty cheap so you can
Can get a wyze camera
And stick it so it faces your door and then you can always check in
With this $20 camera and be like oh hey
My deadbolt engage but my door is actually still open
If this is
Like a big concern of
The downside to all of these actually is if the door is still
Open
You do have to go back home and
Close it
Or maybe it's just call someone
Right I would probably set up some type of automation that triggers if the door magnetic sensor
Is showing open
For more than a couple minutes or something to that effect when you're not at home that way you're not too far from home and you can just go back
There you go
So if you do the external door sensor
You're going to need a hug
Cuz they are zigbee
If so you're really getting into
Investment charity
But then you got a lot of fun with your
Alright next
Stop is a question from Rob
Who is from Austin
Shoutouts
To Rob
My hometown buddy
Alright Rob
Let's hear your question
Hi Stacy
My name is Rob
I'm a retired electronics engineer
Here in Austin
I got into Electronics
In the early 60s as a kid
Now after several years of retirement I want to get back into it
Funeral makeup
Sonic game
Home automation gadgets
Seemed like a fun Avenue
But I don't want my gadgets to be too dependent on
Proprietary protocols
Or
Access be on my own local
What tips do you have
But you can give me to find DIY friendly devices plans parts and protocols
Singson
I can have sole control over
A lot of fun
Thanks for a great podcast
Okay Rob
This
Is I think I actually really common desire among the lot of our audio
Yes you guys do not want stuff sent to
The cloud for the most
Parrot sounds like
Mike and
You don't want to have the compromises that come with the incredible lack of standards that we have in the
The industry today
I get that
But
We don't have a lot of
Options for
So
You want to control it all on your own
You could do something like load openhab
Are home assistant or
Homebridge on lyca
Hi it control everything
Locally from your pie
That's pretty complicated thing but you do say that you're doubly so you might be totally comfortable with that level
Love
Effort in
Granularity
I will say that I put openhab on
Can I use pine sol
Xt4 who's difficult to get it on there but man the level of control I had was
Awesome
And sky
But there's a downside
There is a downside if you do any of these things
You have a problem
Which is if for example your door isn't
And you're like my door is unlocked I will remotely control it from my smartphone while I am at dinner
You can't actually do that
And that lack of remote control
That made
Ear problem for you it kind of depends on the things you want to do with
Secure Smart Home
I would like
To have the remote
Access myself
I'm the same way I like my remote access
But I
Don't know that I want everything going to the cloud and you can do that you can have a local hub
Still have remote access so it sounds like you don't even want that so you can pick and choose what you'd like to do there is another new
New Option out there which is no cloud
Data an app
Is the habitat
Hub which we have a review in it
Hopefully coming soon so we'll be able to tell you a lot more but I know it's at least on paper it would meet your specifications
Because it is totally in your network does not go to the outside for its Smart Home Smart
Habitat where do they come from
Beef Elders actually built the rules engine
For the SmartThings
So
These guys they looked at SmartThings Chevrolet
Like I like where this is going
Pretty granular
Can go as deep as you want to
But they
Did not like a lot of the aspects of the
Cloud connectivity
So
They were like hey I want to control all of this on my own
Yeah well once we have that in-house we can
Tell you more how it works one other thing I'd like to mention if
Rob really wants
Tinker and not have a ton of different apps because obviously certain devices that not necessarily certain protocol
Close but just kind of use their own app
Controlling things like that you could actually get into some very light coding and use apis that are available from a lot of
The different device makers I control a lifx bulb using a Raspberry Pi and some python
It's literally just a couple lines of
Code to actually enable of lighter so on so forth so if you don't want a ton of apps as well and you want your own controls you could do that too
I will warn you and I will warn anyone who says I don't want to depend on proprietary protocols
I will say that it's not just the
Proprietary protocols that
Okay let's go with another question we have got one
From
Eric
With kind of a doozy so
Let's hear it
PlayStation Kevin Dwyer up some wise cameras
Problem before today would make a
Small USB
Tension wire
Power only
With a
Plug in the middle of it
Very small such said I can go maybe a quarter inch hole
Ancestry
We connected on the other side of the wall
Minimize the hole size
Of course.
Most USB
Hey connectors are pretty big in the night camera connectors are still fairly big so I want a midpoint disconnect
Push it through a hole
Anyway thanks for your help and love you podcast
So Eric I look
All over the web like the entire web
4 USB
Cable that has a disconnect in the middle and I struck out and I don't know if that's
Because there's no demand for them or the USB spect
Not allow for those
So the short answer is there is no cable it's going to work for what you want to do and I get while you want to do what you want to do
You want to limit the hole that you're drilling to pass through Power
A wyzecam in another room
So
I came up with some Alternatives and I'll let you decide if any of these are workable one is that
You could if you have an outlet within 5 Mi of the wise
Camera that you're going to put up what you could do is swap at Outlet out with another Outlet
That still has three prongs but also has additional USB port
Sports and these are inexpensive maybe $15 I have a couple of my office that are easy to wire and what that'll do is
Is it a let you use a regular USB
Cable from that outlet unfortunately you're going to see the wire because that's going to be in the same room but that is an option and I
I said five meters because that is the spec USB for length
Shouldn't be more than once you get repeaters and all but you wouldn't need that I'm trying to think of some other options there just aren't too many I know
I know Stacy you thought of something if
You want to have an electrician come in the house and drop a new outlet
Because of my life I need more outlets in weird places.
Under my sink
So you just have the electrician come out if there is a light switch or an existing outlet they can run some
Something up the wall down the wall anywhere on the wall
It cost about in Austin it cost about $25 to get
Added onto your visit so there's usually a small visit fee and
That so
And while they're out there they could
About all your lights
So that's really the only option I had
Which is not proper
Okay sorry bad news there but
We have some good news
Next color
Who is from
Canada
Hi Kevin
Work
A girlfriend
Canada
Affordable
Lucia Nutley
Hear from you
First off
Your girlfriend with the SmartThings Hub she's a keeper
Because it's hard to find people who you love and who
One day you might live with who like
Having the destruction of a smart
Courthouse cell
We went and looked for this particular product I used to try smoke alarms out
End
The challenge was my dogwood
So I stopped trying
But I did go and find
A First Alert one
Because I know that they actually work with lots of different options
Kitty
Kidde I'm not sure how you say it they have a
Proprietary radio so not all if there's work with
Other devices that
Don't have that radio in them
But I look for a First Alert Z-Wave smoke detector
Because the Wi-Fi ones 8 they need to be wired they require a lot of power
All seem to have secret surveillance
Cameras in them which kind of fruit
Is that real
I went searching for a Z-Wave smoke detector
On Amazon
Canadian site
By golly I found one
I found a
Lovely one that actually does work with smart
It does not work
And
It costs
Roughly $88 Canadian
So it felt a little expensive
But you know you can do the cool things like when your smoke alarm goes off
You can set a program and SmartThings so it
Like turn your lights on and off
If you want
Text you can do lots of fun things
It's a bummer that doesn't work with wink I know it'll work for this particular call or would not work for me my
Family is awake
Maybe I should be on your Tinder profile do you like SmartThings or wink
Your profile
No comment node of course not
Of course not
Like I'm going to have to tell your wife
No no no she's awake
There you go
So yes and Kevin I think actually before the show
He pointed out that
No because you know I looked at The Nest smoke alarms and see you know you can spend a hundred $2,250 a month
More for each one and that adds up quickly and 88 Canadian dollars is roughly around 65 you
U.s. dollar so it's a lot cheaper than the nest options that we have here so I don't think it's too terrible but again I don't know
This particular individuals budget
His first girlfriend he's going to spend the money
Spend the money
Yeah she's
Scrapy she's twerking
She's worth it
Apus next
This week's
Winner I wish we
We have little bells
I should really invest
This is Robert
And
He
Has a question that actually surprisingly
Easy to answer
Very short answer
With a very long explanation
Exactly
So let's
Tear it
Another time but I'm just getting into the home automation thing
I was looking at the home assistant
Be my first project
Start in a new home on 3rd
Getting
I just want to know if
First timer into the
World
Okay Robert
Here is the short answer
No no
And why is that
We don't have any sense Robert of how Adept you are technically
Play End like I was saved when I installed
Openhab
Home assistant
Looks actually a little bit easier to install
Then openhab
But it still requires you to be familiar with having a Raspberry Pi and
Loading software onto it
And the interface
Looks amazing
But man I'm going to tell you getting the software on these things is like a
Journey ended up
Yeah this is one of those that you would install on Raspberry Pi so that's why we're leaving towards you know but Robert if you can name for Lee
Linux distros off of top of your head that would tell me you're Savvy enough to make this happen
So if you are then yes would be our answer
Is your not then know this would be similar to as you said Stacy the hoping to have Mozilla things Etc
Probably better off as a first-time smart home buyer to get a smart home hub such as SmartThings or
Wink work will say more about habitat
Once we have that in-house it can tell you
If we would recommend that so that would be a recommendation
So on the one and you have openhab you have home assistant
Homebridge
Super powerful
Requires a lot of expertise and it also requires a lot of time like
When I was playing with openhab man I could spend an hour
Setting up one light bulb
Because that's how much greater than it was
Wonderful for anybody who ever like played D&D and spent hours designing their character
I mean that's kind of what I felt like
Now
The next level above that I would say smart
Switch gives you a lot of programmability
It's a little less
Is that a lot with the reliability but still there sometimes
Some issues
It's a little less user-friendly
I think it was idiot-proof and then wink
Is just
To me it's the gold standard of hubs for
Cuse and then
Homekit is
Also super easy probably easier than wink but you have your than in a tall Apple
Ecosystem
Which doesn't work
Right I would agree also have some limitations and that
Would be in the device choice because
You can't using Peter Z-Wave with homekit you're stuck with Wi-Fi and Bluetooth type devices
So that is our
Gradient of home hub
All right
And congratulations
You in the Schlage
Lock so that's actually a good start
And now
A question
From Twain
Atlanta
Stacy I just saw your twin
The post referring to Kevin's article on the routers and smart home hub
I have a question
I'm actually looking
Getting the Samsung connect home 3 pack
Actually for
$99 which is unbelievably
Just low and I'm wondering what are your thoughts
Is it a good unit I'm considering also get into the Google wi-fi system but I just wanted to know your salt
Samsung
Prices
Thank you
And thanks Michelle
Dwayne we are really sorry that we
We did not get to you in time
For this deal because it was a smoking hot deal
But
Is Kevin will explain
We're a little confused as to what you're asked
We think you're asking too diff
Right you should mention the Samsung connect 3 pack
Which is a mesh Network and you also mention Google Wi-Fi as a contender which is also a mesh Network
So that's fine those are on par right there there's a some subtle differences that I mention II
But there's one key
Prince the Samsung connect is also a SmartThings
Hub for your smartphone
Google Wi-Fi is not a smart home hub so it is strictly a network
Set up for your home
So if you're looking for just
A network
In your eyes
Either would do the Samsung connect uses slightly faster Wireless
Radios that are up to 1300 megabits per second theoretical real world is not going to be quite that fast.
Google Wi-Fi is 1200 megabits per second you probably wouldn't notice the difference
You may not have it
Right exactly it all depends but even for internal transfer from computer to computer that's where you would gain some benefit and see the fast
Speed regardless though if you don't have a hub
And you're looking for a hug the only choice of the two you mentioned would be the Samsung connect
Because
SmartThings is built in
Hopefully that helps
Hopefully
You see that awesome deal again
Keep decided you were
What do you pull the trigger on that $99 deal on save two hundred bucks
If so good deal good on you
All right
Final
Question of the
Week is
About our favorite smart speaker
Madam
Let's hear it
Play Kevin Spacey I just want to say really in
Enjoy your
How many Educators and IB
Been doing a lot of workshops
Temptations on using Alexa in
Contacts
Classroom
Just want to say really enjoyed I really don't
Any
Questions but certainly
Enjoy
If you
Add or know of any
Skills at
Teen to
Educators and if
You've heard of anyone that is
Using
Mad at me
In the classroom thanks so much and
Thanks again for a great time
Oh I am so glad you asked
This question be
Because we had so much fun
We as we did yes we did The r4000 Madam a skills in the education and reference
And I wouldn't say we went through all of them but we went through a bunch
And we installed and use them
To come up with
Five recommendations here granted you can go through yourself and find additional ones but we really enjoyed using these
Yes and
Smarter and
We weren't
So first up
Is the National Geographic
Wiz
Skill reputable name
And
A very functional quiz so what this does is it every single day you get 6 dude
Geography based question
And the Americans
This was good Kevin and I however
I believe we scored 6 out of 6 on AR quiz
And there's a range some of them are very easy and some of them
We're a little more challenging I wouldn't say any of them
With your liking
Jeopardy champion
Quiz Bowl champion these are probably not going to stump you but
Definitely good for the classroom
Then we have
NASA NASA Mars
Yes That's Amore as I thought it would be
Good and it was
However it
Was very information dense it sometimes we'd asked what we thought was a simple question and we would hear a 5 min
Answer so there's a lot of detail in here this is me by JPL
Who would certainly know what's going on on Mars
That's correct
And you can get information about Mars but what we thought was really cool you can get
What is a real time but same day information
On the
Curiosity Rover
And when we happen to ask about it
Curiosity
Actually did not go as far as planned on Mars that day
And we found out exactly what the problem is and exactly what NASA is doing to resolve it I mean it was
Serious information really really cool
It was awesome and they had you know we asked I didn't realize this but
And we found out
The Moon's name
And we also found out
Why they were named
Complete mythological history very very very
So if
I was just asking about how many moons it had we got all of that information
Yes
We did not have to
It's actually probably a lot
Why does this work and then I'm like
Let me explain it to you
A half an hour and two drinks later you'll get your answer
Exactly
So we like that is probably for older
Patient people
We also tried for younger
Kids smart math
Which there a lot of smart math
I was looking for a math fact skill
Basically for my daughter
Because not too long ago we were in that realm of like
Hey what's 2 + 2 2
2 * 2
2 / 2
All of those fun things and
How cool would it be if you could just ask
Mate for your man
And it's
Pretty cool but it's also
Bus RTC it starts really easy
And this skill basically gives you 40 seconds and
Matinee will ask you math facts for that
Amount of time
I really wanted to go like
All out super fast but Madam is not super
But I did get 40 seconds
Which was 8 questions and they were like
OnePlus 4
Kevin heard me
Answer this at first I was like
Nervous about doing math
Nothing from the Kevin but it was not hard
But you can level up but I
I think it's a Time
Ruidoso baby for younger
And then
Kevin and I
You want to talk about our secret shame
Yeah I'm very disappointed in my performance on the periodic table quiz because I just
Went through the periodic table in the big history project
Switch I highly recommend for people if you could have big history project
X.com
I screwed up my alkaline metals in my transition metals in this one is really
Really challenging but educational
Tons of
Good
Good tough questions but I learned so much
I forget how many questions it asks
Fastest 5K
Sweet By the way
Only got
Two or three
We were not great but
Will be better next
I'm actually I kept that on there cuz I'm like
You will not pass
Best me.
But it did
But not again
And it's also better more for the sciencey kids that are in a folder or
Higher grade level so it's not Elementary School obviously which we had some pics in there if this was more towards the middle school and heck maybe even
High School
Or adults
As we sold our
All right in our final one is educational for anybody
I just liked
This and hopefully you guys will too it is the Autobahn
Bird songs
Scale and
You basically you ask madam A2
Ask Audubon
What a Mockingbird
It sounds like
And it will play
Mockingbird
I just thought this was needed it's not like Shazam for birds
Which would be even cooler but it's still for anybody who likes the animals or
To hear what's around them
Yeah you can ask it about any different bird I forget how many it actually has how many birds that actually covers butt
There are 2,000 bird calls in the skill and anything is with the Mockingbird and obviously with several other birds if
The bird has multiple sounds or calls it will play all of them I think for the Mockingbird played for different ones all in a row
Rose we can hear the different calls of a Mockingbird for example
Because that's what my king
Yes
Super cool
Those are some skills I recommend going digging through that we found a couple
Like we found a spelling test
Skill that we thought was great
Because it let you import your own spelling words but then
If you spelled something incorrectly it was like
Yeah
Didn't say anything
Nix that one
That was disappointing because I had such promise because
Stacy created around list online with the skill and then
Matabei regurgitated the list perfectly
But when you misspelled something you just didn't know
Didn't say anything
Kids with low confidence well it might be good for them but yes
So I would recommend all of these skills
Look for what you want
And then I would say test them out
Because some of them are of dubious quality
The ones we kiss
I feel pretty confident in
Because we've tried them out but
There's a lot so
It's so easy to enable the skills right from Amazon the website to so it's not like I could go into your app
Testes
It's also easy to any
Kevin was like I'm not getting my
Or I'm not
I don't need to do that
All right well this was super fun you guys think
Thanks for sending it
Great questions we had a good time answering them
Hope you enjoy the show
And we will do this again I'm sure
Because
Another
Another contest for you so remember
Call in
5126 to 3
7424 for your chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt
Nyfi
Kevin that's it for this
So if you guys want more content please check us out at Stacey on iot
You can sign up for the Weekly Newsletter for you can see great content from Kevin and I and as always
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week