Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Today
Lucky
I am not
We're going to talk about the latest news from Apple including.
We're going to talk about
And some new Services are launching
Where there's more phones with more personal assistants on them
And the internet
Things
Man there's a new study out and it says
Terrible things are headed away
I bought a brand new device will tell you more about that
We also have
A message from a brand new sponsor TE Connectivity
You're going to learn a lot about connected appliances
And this week's guess
Are actually three people
We got Scott Harkins from Honeywell Adam justice of connectsense and nuala O'Connor
The center for democracy
Technology all talking about different facets
So
It's going to be a Napoli show
But it's going to be awesome
Let's Get It Started With the passage from
This week sponsor is Affiliated monitoring if you are hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business
You need to hear about Affiliated monitoring in response to trigger any connected device Affiliated professionally
Follow protocol and reach out to your customers their loved ones and local emergency services
Affiliated work with hundreds of smart home security health in other iot businesses visit a Philly
Plated.com coyote
Turn an idea into a thriving business
With a 100 million dollar exit that's Affiliated. Com
/ iot
Alright Kevin
A is for apple
Let's do that in Sister Talking Letters we can throw in WWDC because the worldwide developer conference is going on this
With apple and Michelle Obama
Yes yeah
Yes
The most
Obviously there lots of
Software news for developers which is good cuz it's a developer event
They were Hardware refreshes on the
Competing side
And then there was a new product and I think a lot of people
Don't quite get it
But that's just me
What is a name
So it is a
Smart connected wi-fi speaker called
Homepod
What do you think of homepod
Anthony
Show me the name
Don't love it
What were they going to do I Spy
Speaker kit
Is it those are kind of software kits so
Yeah yeah
Just
They didn't call it the Siri
And I think
We might get into wide
Why it's not called
So
So what do you think
Beyond the name
So beyond the name just
Quick high-level this is a $349
7 in tall
Cylinder speaker
With us I think 7
Wattpad readers and so on speaker since I don't recall the exact numbers
Speakers
But it's interesting from a speaker standpoint because
It has
Beamforming so it can adjust the sound based on type of music
Placement of the speaker and so on and so forth
It's got wifi in it
From that standpoint
If the Apple application of currently existing speaker technology to me
And everybody says it sounds good I'll be over there listen to it
Set a timer better than the echo
And I would expect that
Couple reasons why because they're selling the $349 speakers sound better than $180
Ecco Aurora
$120 Google home it's much heavier than those devices about 2 and 1/2 pound so
Speakers and power have a lot to do with the weight in the magnets and so on so forth so I would expect that
Everybody kind of shied away from the fact
That it has or will work with Siri
And I think that's because of Apple marketing and the reason I say that is
Siri is not
Still
Great
By comparison in my opinion
They're working on it and they talked about that on stage of
What technologies are using to improve Siri
But it's not ready yet
In fact the demo speakers
Siri wasn't even working at Aulani
Everybody is focusing on the speaker the music and so on
But here's the thing
Don't neglect that this has
Apple A8 chip inside of it
This will also act as a
Gateway for your homekit devices
That lets you remotely access them away from home
So to me
Apple
Get the big win here from marketing standpoint
Great sounding train $50 speaker
Come September October iPhone event
And they tell you now in my opinion that Siri is much better here's how
Now of a sudden
Everybody's like it's coming in December that speaker for 349 sounds so great
It's got Siri smart and works really well as an acid
That's what I think the play is here
People talking about that sound
Yes I think you're right and I think there's a lot that Apple does need to do on the series
And we'll talk about this with our guests because there's also
A really interesting element they talk about with homekit
I'll just ease that there for you too
Means that maybe we'll see more homekit
Get devices in the future
Certification
And
They also emphasize the
Privacy
That's worth talking
Because
Nobody else talks about it this way
Apple is basically saying that
They were not going to send anything
To their server
Until
So all that's on device processing
Send it
They're going to send it out
Encrypted
And they're going to anonymizer
Cancerverse
Rich right now
That's their differentiation Point that's how they're trying to stand out for these other devices and services
Saying hey even we don't know
Yesterday that is on our server but it's a non- we can tie back to you and we're not selling that data or
Or matching up with advertisers so you got total privacy
So what I think is interesting is will have apple selling
Privacy
Shell
It sounds like
Google home be selling
Actual smart responses to things
Ecosystem
We got
Amazon selling its developer ecosystems
You can control just about it
Skills
I don't know what Microsoft
We'll see
I'm sure they can do something
Alright so
What are they saying from the news
I thought that Apple adding support for speakers
Did you notice that
As what are they
Yeah they are
I thought that was really cool though I didn't see Sonos in there
And so I don't know what Sonos is like all in on cuz Soto said Apple used to be Thai
Yeah
Now
Actually as I was watching the
Keynote
Streaming from work
A couple times in my quilt this company's not going to happen I hope that covers I can be happy now
Synonyms for because
AirPlay 2 and the homepod
It's all supporting multi-room audio and
I might go a couple things they announce today
I've been core products or product features
Their party is that people to be like well
Guess I'm not going to
Buy that now Kannapolis
Give me the natively
That is always happening
Is it is the way of the
Cupertino
Just for a little bit
Because
Smarter people tend
I'm not ashamed
All right so right along
Two more smart home
This is a hug but not a voice assistant this is week
Lync is adding
Some services to its platform
And these are free so if you have
You're going to get to New services
Debility it'll it'll
When you're not home
So I thought that was pretty sweet
Because yeah
Recycled in any other one
Moonlight
Relate so basically it's funny because I have robots that do this now I don't need to have those robots
Turns your lights on or off at predetermine
Time such as
Sunrise sunset that's the default actually and then you can
Also adjust Moonlight have the lights go on or off
Different times as well but
Yeah so there's my
My robots that turn lights off at night
Mandana. Asking someone when little
Yes it is just
A recipe
Annapolis
The scheduling thing
I I don't care for that
It is what it is so on
In Exile so introduce a new
Kids call wink bright
Rick lights actually
Yes that's okay
So for a hundred I think it's $119 you can get yourself a wink
Hub 2
Included with the packages to Sylvania smart a19 dimmable bulbs
It's kind of an inexpensive easy way to get you started and of course
When you start adding lights it's like a gateway drug and
You have a Gateway cuz you have a hug so you can just keep adding lights on other things
This is pretty like I think this is noteworthy for the Nerds
It's going to
And seeing a lot of action so
There's a couple of efforts on the standards front to
Make sure that things can be prepared
You're not prepared
Pair to the hub
Yes
So there's a lot happening there because provisioning in
Pairing
Difficult
We have so much technology yet
This is still hard
And wait till you have to
How to reset Alexa
Ctrl-alt-delete
So you're counting to five in the process
Discovering your devices if you have a neck reallocating yourself
But it's all so simple
So I asked the wink folks
Because I saw this and I was like this is great this will be at these are nice
You know ways to make yourself smarter very easily
And I also asked are you going to offer premium services
And they told me
Patrick Mahoney a spokesperson
Send me the email that said it is in the pipeline
But in the near-term they're rolling out free services
That tie back to home safety
And that's because home safety is number one reason people buy into
Automation
So
44% of Americans who have purchased a connected product did so to keep their home safe according to wink smart Olympics
I talk to I control about
Distance like roughly 33%
We'll see
Boom shakalaka
All right
We'll see more of that from
I'm going to say everybody who has a
Product on the market and is trying to maintain
Basically stick around
Because
What we're going to see next year or so is a lot of companies that have Smart products realize that holy cow
Afford to maintain
Their customer base
With the server cost with the security cost all of that adding
Putting out
Additional service
Yay
Kevin
Another phone or back to assistance
Yeah back to assistant-san and I don't want to give too much on the phone cuz I know we don't do that but I'll mention that the newest HTC phone
Mbu 11
Which
Has been available for pre-order for $650
It's a flagship phone
It comes with
Google Assistant because it runs Android of course
But like
One of the
Recent Huawei phones this also has
Native built in
Hace Amazon Echo but you know I'm talking about
She who shall not be named
She can be your assistant right on this phone as well now
I say native it's coming in an update after the phone launches through Google
The Google Play store within 30 days of launch
IPhone launch
But you'll be able to use assistant you'll be able to use
Matinee
And of course they also include HTC Sense companion which is
Intelligent type of software the HTC is developed which really reminds me of Google now because it
Services contextual information so at least two if not three
Really looks like a big push
For Amazon yet
Echo
Integration into phones in a big way this year
Which kind of surprises me because
Just don't see it on a phone when you already have
Google Assistant but that's just me
Hey because we mentioned
I work for Google
Full-time consultant not on IRT things
Any opinion is that
Isaiah
I always up
But last week we had a huge huge shift
In the force
The caverns are show which is Kevin weekend
How do you feel
I do like it
I mean again a lot of the functionality are already had with Google Assistant that's not like I added new functionality
And as I said before one of the things that I
Kept me from buying it
Cuz my music services that I listen to Arms
Supporters on it
But
It's actually really easy to cast audio
Or video
Watch it from your phone
To any
Cast enabled device which Google home is so I just listened to my Beatles channel on SiriusXM in the app
Cast it to the Google home speaker so
Yeah it's it's working well it's
Turn lights on
But that's
Google home specific as Google Assistant
Specific
We're getting there
Yes it still doesn't work with locks in
Actually going forward I'm kind of curious about the fate of
Has as a gem or Stephen to assistant anyone with an Android phone is probably like
I could actually do this with the Android phone
So
Alright by the way hello
And you actually carrier
Okay
So
Moving right along
We have a big meeting
Port to talk
I title this at our show notes
Because that's kind of what it felt like
So what happened is Pew Research Center
Report all about iot
And basically
You can tell from the title they're like The Internet of Things connectivity binge what are the implications
The implications are
That you will never not be connected
That's my summation of this
Entire report witch
Everyone should read because it is
Excellent and covers a lot of things that we talked about
On the show
A lot
So if you are connected
You can expect
Exploits and attacks is basically what I cut out of
So
You're going to be connected because your life is going to increasingly demanding
And we're almost there today like you have to be to get a job
Right that's that's just that's why internet connectivity
An argument is
Uber time your devices are going to have to be
Connected in your home because otherwise you're not going to be able to
Function or do things with
Feels a little crazy but
I could see it happening
I could I tell you I just
I feel so sad reading this report I mean
I'm just going to read one sentence
This reminds me of Terminator
What used to be attacks against data and information have become attackers against
Flesh steel and concrete
Which is true I get it, infrastructure and
And even wearable devices
I get it but wow you don't have to say it
Well so I actually did a
In my newsletter last
Play the Shameless plug for my newsletter
I actually did a
EU report that was amazing
On
Data security so they were talking about iot security not as a privacy issue
What is a safety issue
And they compared it to you once you start and it didn't notice what you start connecting infrastructure
Attacks bear have real impacts on
People's lives
Actually
I just
My data was stolen
Report
It's like 7 minutes long
Summarizes
Points
They're not wrong we're putting all the stuff out it's
Highly insecure
I will reach you
My favorites
Because
Also something really well
Resistance is futile
Penalize those who disconnect
Social processes
Reward those who
Fully withdrawing
Maybe
You will plug into the Matrix is what they're saying
Is there again
Not wrong it's going to be harder like especially in things like
Appliances it's going to be harder and harder to not
Buy things that are connected
Not just for your benefit
But for
The appliance maker
So to get warranty service on something
You're probably going to have to connect
Because then they can see how things are were
Right
Until once you start doing that
Then they're like
Hey
Here's a service we can offer you why don't you
You're connected washer why don't we offer you
Euro results
Amazon dash button service
And so then you're like
Oh that sounds great
Except
Then you're locked into
Buying a certain kind of laundry
And get we talked about this the guardian
Did a
An article on this that they took the report as its theme so it's like you will connect and then really dug in
How we're kind of unquestioningly
Allocating more and more of our buying decisions to these products
And how the number of choices presented to us
Are becoming more limited
Think of it is the idea of network neutrality
In search results on you
Amazon Echo
Rate
So
Companies pay for shelf space in
In the grocery store
Eventually they might start paying
You don't first listing in
Your Amazon Echo
In the question here is Will consumers be aware of
Will it recognize that that's happened
And that's
Probably a no
Yeah I miss animal not not unless
Their major
Media stories about it explain how this works
You listening to the show
Paired
Soho
I think that the good outweighs the
The bad
Thanks
Baidu
Debbie lack of transparency here
Is going to
Both cause a loss of trust that makes people
Not buying
To this which is fine but
Sad because
More data
Market insights
For everyone
And I also think that companies need to be
Aware of the influence they pedal
And help build trust with consumers that they're not
Abusing that
So that's beyond transparency that might be things like letting you set your
You don't make it very easy to
Cast something to her
Send something to a screen so you can
You can choose you
What you're buying
If the price changes there
Very obvious like
Hey by the way
Usually that cost 699 but today for some reason
There's a storm in Malaysia it's up to 788
These kind of things should
Be a pair
The grid
None of this is controversy
And I don't know should you be able to buy this is going to be interesting should you be able to
Disconnect
The products and I asked is because you know there's things like predictive maintenance but there's also things like really interesting Energy savings
Benefit societies
Yeah I mean I prefer connected products over non-cancer products
When it makes sense
But I don't think it should be either or binary choice I think people should have it
And we're not there
This report for
Computer really makes it sound like
It's inevitable
Resistance is futile
But I actually think you can
What's your dollars
And that could
Is
How people react to things like the homepod Apple is reselling privacy
Keep that in mind
Go read the report
It was scared
Ed
You mentioned homepod wood
Which has to do with music and I think you just bought something
Music
And it just says no reply
Apart
Alright Jack
I did I bought
Okay longtime listeners of the show will be
Be rewarded with a shot of dopamine cuz you're going to remember that I talked about this
80 months ago
This is the mighty
MP
Somebody MP3 player
This is a
Spotify is a dedicated Spotify player
Oh and iPod Nano
Sorry to shuffle
It hasn't been updated in years but it's
Hey
Cuz it doesn't work with Spotify
Does even work with apple music so you have to put your own MP3
Alright nevermind
Alright so what we have is the mighty
This is a
Tiny little
Device
BICYCLE stores your Spotify stuff
Offline
So I can take this
When I walk the dog or go running at stores a thousand songs
What's 5 hours
35 hours
And
I saw this on Kickstarter
Again
Like
18 months ago and I was
Super excited
I didn't buy it cuz I was like
I still burnout on my
Kickstarter's
In the pebble
Announced
Was that what it was
Pebble
Announced a very similar product in since I had a pebble
Can I trust a pebble
I was like I'll get my money down for that
And then
Fitbit
What pedal
And I was very bad
No court for you
No car for me
So I went back to my baby and I was like are they going to make it and just
Or last week
They announced that they were Spotify certified
And
Product will ship June
XXX
So I
I put down
$85
It turns out with shipping
$95 or
$94
In about an orange mighty
Tennessee
In July you guys
The test is puppy out
It will see if it answers
All of my prayer
Or at least the ones I had about listening
Can we just talk about the Spotify certified thing
Yes
So also regular listeners will remember I said
That music services are now becoming a part of the lock-in for wearable devices
Because you want
Add Apple watch to exercise which I sometimes do
I can only get music from
My Apple music
Service
Onto that
I want to
Using Android play
I got all that but you know
These things are tied to services
So this is the first that I know of
First device that allows
Spotify offline playback
My Samsung wearable has
Spotify Spotify app
But all it is is a controller
For Spotify my phone so
Doesn't store the Spotify
Music
Spotify certification is interesting to me makes me wonder if other
Wearable
Device makers will be
Getting Spotify certified in the future
We should clarify this is be first
Wearable
Device
But you have Spotify
His
Sure sure sure absolutely yeah
Correct
It's too early to say I'm curious to see
If any other devices get certified for Spotify now
Or not again I'm just concerned but I want more choices
I'm a music selection
For my whereabouts when I go running listen music
Can I listen to music that's tied to the
Device itself
And that's one of the nice things that both Amazon and
Have done and
I'm curious if
Which is
A pic from
Music service
And you can eat them
Yeah
Doesn't really give you that many choices I'm missing it
I didn't give you that money
But they do get on Google choices
Noah Spotify is set as my
Really
Maybe because I know the Spotify app
It's not picking up on that
To say there's a link that you can add their
Certified this you go into your device settings
In the Google Assistant settings there's a section called music
Music
Your choices are Google Play Music
YouTube music
New default provider which is account
Preferences on share
Pandora
So they recently they have
Fanatics but that's good
That's getting your vehicle has
Had many many services for quite some time
That's good
That actually raises the question as you said
Will Apple allow
Non Apple Music Services on
Don Potter
And there was no mention of that
At WWDC
My money says no
But after a word from our sponsor
Can expect
Text you this week's guess we've got Scott Harkins of Honeywell
Connectsense and O'Connor for the center for democracy and Technology
Stay tuned for much more
Everyone it's time for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is TE Connectivity
I have Nick Langston from TE Connectivity here
To talk to us about what the company does
What I want the audience to understand is that
And you look at all of these
Interesting pieces of Hardware that are appearing
In our kitchens and in our home
Every one of these
Full of different
Pieces of Hardware that allows
Sensing or data or power
Moving around
Between these devices
Does little connectors that allow that to happen
TV connectivity is in the business of Designing the sensors and connectors
Possible
Can you give us some examples of
What you're talkin
For the example that most of us
It is something like a USB connector
Those
Plugs
Are the types of connectors
That allow the tree
Data and power to and from certain devices
There's a huge variety
Of connector
Inside your average laptop
Let alone
Your average refrigerator
Dishwasher
Car washing
And then you also introduce sensing
What temperatures are we going to have to measure
Do we need to measure vibration
Need to measure humidity how do we combine
Dos War
Works of features and capabilities in the smallest possible package
That's what we're in the biz
What are some of the Innovative things that we can expect coming forward especially when it comes to things like the smart
Smart kitchen is an exciting place
It really does
Seem to be the focal point of the connected home
We all know how much time we spend in
Kitchen now
And what we're seeing is a trend where people are adding precision
To all of the devices
If you see products like smart ovens
Read a new types of device
Like sous vide circulator
All of these are using increased
In measuring data whether it's
Temperature or humidity or
Weight of food or evaporation of material from
It's
Really about increasing Precision so that we can make
Fooda prepare things
What consists of
That seems to be what
Ace Hardware Aspen
Check that the Internet of Things is really a neighbor
Is that
Everyone can become an ex
Through the use of high-resolution sensors and to some extent artificial intelligence
Well
Precision is important
Reliability is also
A big challenge
How do you guys think
We're in the business of making sure
The sensors are ready to survive
Extremely high temperature
Or the wet environment
The inside of a dishwasher or washing
Or that you'll be able to control the efficiency
Nothing like your refrigerator
Which consumes a huge percentage of the electricity in the average household
Nick that sounds awesome
Where can people go to find out more
We invite you to visit our website you can CSS
Ged.com connected home
Alright the big news this week
Was the Apple homepod
Which actually isn't coming out this week it will be out in December
We can't just let this
Slibuy
We're going to have a couple experts this week
To talk to us
What's a homepod
For the smart
First up we have Scott Harkins who is AVP
Connected home
Hi Scott how are you doing
Doing great baby how are you
Loving life
So
I don't know if you saw it yesterday but
Apple introduced
The home
And since you guys
With apple producing a homekit certified thermostat
I thought you'd be a good person to talk to you about what this might mean
I did
See I watched it live like I do every WWDC I was pretty excited
About it I think
It looks like a great
Product great looking product that the reviews I've read seem to make it sound like it
Some great sound quality to it
And
The fact that a polite
Think with a piece of Hardware efficiency
Turn yourself into space is a
Is a really big deal and you and I have talked
The four about
Like the impact of just voice control
Of the home and so
Let's tell other people like what voice control the home has meant
For you guys what have you seen
Produces these products
Stacy we introduced a voice-controlled Connect
Is thermostat a few years ago to pretty rave reviews we immediately saw and recognized it that boys like havoc
Play in the consumer Market
You know that the Amazon Echo came along with its voice
System
And I think really revolutionized
The space
What ID for Honeywell
Specifically or at least for some of our perspectives
In the market
It proved to things that prove that
Consumers actually
You can get it and understand voice and can understand different things and
Semantics that they have to say to make something work
But more importantly in the connected home world
It proved one of our key perspectives which was
Consumers actually want one kind of user
Experiencing
Much of the industry for many years was talking about Halo on one app
Emby amazon echo
Stepped in and probably by Design. I guess we're not sure
Did it with voice we're going to beat the Spire products
Please different protocols
Communication techniques
Can I be controlled by talking to
Speaker
And I think that's a
Really big deal as an example of
How Amazon Echo has really become one of the key drivers in the market
Place
We can look at 1 24-hour.
Midnight from Christmas Eve
Could midnight Christmas Day
More than 10000 consumers connect
Amazon Echo
Two-way Honeywell thermostat
In one 24-hour period
So
Since this isn't actually due until December
Which many months away
Looking at what you know now
And the experience that you guys have had
What would you suggest
They could do to make your life
Consumers
I'm not so bold as to
She just asked what they ought to do but
I do think some promotion in the meantime it's get word out there about Apple and Hope
Getting this product would be beneficial when it comes to the market
Selfishly speaking in the greater connected-home world
The more they all do to promote this face in their product in the
Connected home aspects to it
The batter off
Awesome
What is your take on homekit today
Like our consumers
Really interested in home
Another really good question Stacey I think that most
Consumers probably dozen
Really know what home kit is yet
Unless
They're setting up
Pay Home Depot
So if you were setting up one Honeywell
T5 thermostat
And you had an iOS device
Missing you were setting up it would recognize iOS and it was prompt you to set it up
That in some cases might be their first real
Exposure
Right and at that point you know we actually see the fair amount of customer say yes
50% but
I offer my customers that have iOS devices
To say yes and then go down the route setting
Clean up as a homekit enabled
I'm not
Senior as a kid
Nazi
Investment in advertising
Into the General market riding not seen anything about
Unless it's driven by
The device comes
But it isn't
With your Apple user iOS user every
Device that you set up in that setup
Process it will recognize whether you're on an Apple device or not
Impromptu you enroll it in home
Which is a really interesting way to get
Connectivity in the marketplace
And I think also makes that home
Pod when it gets dropped in right it's going to drop into an existing
Ecosystem
Devices in the home
I'm excited
The homepod actually works like
The other Apple experience
I can imagine just bringing that into your house
Having it recognize everything and you don't even have to do this
Space discovery
Weird
Tying things together that happens in
That could be
Because people will be like
Holy cow all the sudden I can control my thermostat with my voice
Wow
Yeah
The privacy pop
I swear it's not listening until you wake it up
Which is very different than how both Amazon
And Google went to Market and
And goes to
Kind of their commitment to private
Part of their rights
Key Market
Strategy
Tell the quality sound I can't wait
Hear it I have
Sonos in my home and I love it
I would hope that it's at least not good
If not better
And in the fact that it unlocks that were
Remote connectivity really for the first time in a way that doesn't require right Apple
TV's not that there's anything wrong with that
But it's
I think the speaker approaches to
Just eat better
Go easier price for the consumer to get their head around
I'm with you all right big Scott
Next guest is Adam Justice who is the founder of the connectsense brand which is a lie
Sensors connected outlets and other good stuff that ties into
Homekit and other ecosystem
Guess Adam
Yeah some of the other ecosystems stuff is still still coming but yeah we were very early player in the homekit space
So what did you think about the Apple homepod
Just basically some of the Apple news
Yesterday
Always good to see homekit mention on stage and
Looks like some new device profiles and things like that coming to homekit so
That was
Interesting
And then home pod
Definitely
Apple's entry into the smart
Home assistant Market to compete with Amazon Echo
And the Google home and I felt like
Before the show if they were going to do something here
I hope they would differentiate it
In some ways and
Differentiation
It's the really lean in on a music and sound quality
So to me and almost felt like there more going after Sonos then
Then really some of that
Smart speaker alternative sent and really playing up the music I think that's
Time Warner places where they felt they were strongest and so they were going to lean in on that they also think there's a lot
We don't know about these devices
So far so I had a chance to see it in the Hands-On area yesterday
It looks nice
I wasn't functional we couldn't hear it
You can touch it but
It looks nice
Doesn't have a screen on it
I have a similar white aesthetic to like what's going on with the Google home
And yes Mother good things it's got Hub capabilities for homekit so it runs on the same
AA chip
That's what's in the current Apple TV generation was probably why they use that so it'll be another Hub in the house and further
Extending
Homekit devices
Which I think is a good thing
What would you like to see
Between now and December what would you hope to hear from Apple as a company that builds home Kik
Yeah I think that's a big
Point to its we got seven months to go before this thing ships
So
I felt like they were maybe two reasons why they
They showed
What they have
Today
And what they showed yesterday and one maybe that maybe they have some
Really cool features on this
And they just didn't want to tip their hats
To the competition and show off something and give them 7 months to catch up
The other one was
They got seven months of software development still to do on this until
You know that's a lot of time and I'm sure they are putting their best and brightest on this
And so
You know what we see in December definitely is going to be greater than
What they talked about on the
Stage hear about yet
I would say my biggest one is
A way to handle multi users
I think Google home does this a little bit
And kind of the basics beginnings of that but in the Apple ecosystem individual user accounts
It's so important for everything you're going to do
And the fact that it had messaging capabilities listed
Made me feel like maybe this is a thing that they're going to have
I think for this to be a really great communal device it needs to be a have a way to differentiate
I'm with you on that
Okay
Anything else
The other one that I'm not quite sure on yet is
The other thing they talked about in the homekit slide yesterday was
The
Homekit profile
And so
That feels like there
Could be some cool things we could do with speakers
We have a water sensor for example that'll be on the market later this year
And it would be great if
The result of a water sensor could be something coming through a speaker of
Hey there's water in your basement
You should go do something about that
It does in the Press materials after the
Big WWDC Keynote
Apple Help
Put in
A little
Felt like a throwaway line that talked about
Making it easier for developers and makers of smart home devices
To connect into the ecosystem using software
And that
Struck me as import
What about you
I was surprised this wasn't mentioned earlier and I think we'll find out more later this week but that's certainly interesting
Change of tune a little bit
It said you know
New ways to authenticate devices using software
And then even in the session description there was something about some support for hobbyists and Things 2
To be able to play so
CI as of today
You know you need to have a apple authentication chips as part of your design and so that's been challenging
For some companies who have devices already out
Maybe why some people have not adopted Home Care
You know I think
Certainly interesting and we'll see you when we learn a little bit more but
You know could certainly changed
Gay men
Certainly
To me feels like
This ecosystem is important to them and they want to remove some barriers to help as many manufacturers adopted
All right I am excited
Thanks
Connect to talk about privacy and the implications of having an always-on
Listening device in your home
You're still O'Connor
From the center for democracy and Technology
So I'm curious
About Canada privacy application
In general for these types of the
Well I'm glad for saw that
Apple is
Concerned about and is continuing their strong history of
Thinking about data collection of
All of its devices and I think I reapplied them for a the strong stance they took obviously in
Protecting data encryption on the iPhone
I think
I've looked a little bit of the echo I've looked less at the Google products
All of the companies are thinking about in are aware of the fact that you are entering into someone's
Home
And I think the boundaries in the protections for privacy should be even higher than they are obviously on the street
Sayonara
Kitchen laws United States there's a Public Square in a private Zone
These devices blur the line between what is truly private and what becomes somewhat Republic
Carlie shared with private sector companies so suddenly all of our most kind of intimate
Details of our daily lives
Are mediated or shared
Through
Companies on their way to the recipient of the phone call or of the email or the text excetera excetera
And because of that I think we're really calling a company sit to take a stronger and stronger stance as they are further info
Further inside the cartilage inside the boundary of the home
And I think you know what I'm glad to see companies competing on privacy at the value
From a person who cares about privacy and things pretty deeply about it
What we know so far about
The homepod
Is that
Until you say the phrase hey Siri
Nothing is being sent
Apple and then when it sent
They're doing an optimization
An encryption app
The data so
The company actually isn't able to view your data on its server
First title
And that feels pretty different from how both Google and Amazon see the tree
Is that something we should expect
I think those are all terrific projections and I think they really nailed it on the issue of what is
Collected and when
And then how long it's stored and in what way again I am not
Strong confident
The comment on the differences of the variations between the three
7 major Home Products right now but those are all really compelling
Things to think about it's look for as a consumer
What information is being collected when does it say device
Start collecting it
How long has it been
Stored and in what way
Encrypting it and Kennedy identifying it as if our things that we here at CDT have long pushed
For in Fallout 4
And those are the kinds of protections the fact that the company simply can't see it or can't read it or can't interpret
What it is you're saying and doing online
That's some of the highest level projections again that's why we need a we was really think Apple's the very strong and other companies as well on encryption
And that's really what's going to be necessary to protect
But only some kind of law enforcement requests in National Security requests but
But from hackers in from Attack
As we become more and more reliant on these devices and our daily lives
What seems like
Credit mundane data
Can be actually created you don't put together in a way that can create a very both nefarious or very innocent picture of
Your daily life
The same fact
Different ways you could be used for against you in a court of law or Court of public opinion excetera
Example I use there was a case in the midwest involving a whole bunch of Home Products even something as mundane as a smart water
Water meter
And there was a murder in the home some of you may have heard of the story of nothing with an arc
And
That's a huge amount of water with
Used in that home on.
Night in question what are some visitors to the home ended up dead at the end of the night I'm very tragic circumstances
But the same detail the fact that a huge amount of water was suddenly use could
Interpreted as
They were stealing the hot tub because they were having a party or they were washing away the blood right and you can see lawyers in Atlanta
Court of law
Arguing both of those
And so not having the state available not having it online not having it in a human readable format
Is very very strong protection
Awesome so then
How do we educate consumers about this like the fact that Apple seems to be talking more about encryption I
Pink is awesome except I don't know how many consumers really understand the technology
How do we help them
That is such a great point and I'm constantly saying to that the folks I work with
When we are talking about are very nerdy kind of wonky
Concerned about VPN
Door
How encryption works or what kind of
Cyber security protections exist around your devices
We need to make this understandable to people who shouldn't be forced to understand the inner workings of every device they own in order to you
I think was Walt Mossberg and into his last call and recently said
If we don't expect people to understand the combustion engine in order to drive a car
They shouldn't be forced to understand me to take you have a PhD in computer science in order to own a phone or a laptop
And I think and I said
Ben Franklin out for decades to come because I've worked for and Weston
Against
The onus is on the company developing and introducing new technologies to be an educator
To be an explainer
And I did not an a scan of spend more than not only 1/8 we think our product is great but she obviously expects but this is
How the product works and impractical
Simple terms for every user every consumer to understand and to make educated choices I think we've probably
I need to get to the point where the same words mean the same things and consumers can make educated decisions
Clean different devices
Based on real
Understandable differences and I think
Some of that is explaining privacy policies that some of it is actually in how the devices work I know
I must have been out for several more years
And it lights up when you talk to it it circles one way when it
It's doing one thing at Circle to the light circle another way when it does another thing
These are kind of
Inherent or kind of in the environment
Disclosures with I would be a big fan of not making someone go to the privacy policy on the website to understand
A device that is sitting on their kitchen counter
They also saying
More information should be available to the users who want to dive deeper
Into the inner workings of the device so it's contracts on layered notice where there's a short notice after device whether it's
Lighting up or it's flashing or sexy
Speaking to you which would make sense for the device that speaks that you speak to
It should speak back and say
This is with who I am and this is what I'm doing in this is kind of what this happening with your data
But then you can go to the website there or elsewhere and find more information and again in it and easy
Digestible format
Okay so my next feature request is going to be
You know having the Amazon Echo
Just tell me it's privacy and security practice
This is when I ask it
That's okay
No thank you so much for coming on the show
Thank you so much for having a satellite
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more
Iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Will see you next week