Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
In your co-host Kevin tofel
And we have got an amazing show for you today we are going to be talking about
Some big industrial news both Dell and Salesforce are re-upping their iot commitment
Amazon is doing something with Walmart will talk about it
Kevin's got some advice on the Google home Mini
And we are going to talk about some autonomous vehicles
News there from GM and Nvidia
I also have some thoughts on the August Smart Lock that came out last month and
Have sort of been testing the doorbell will talk about that
We also have a voicemail from
Sally
And a message from our sponsor
Qualcomm
Plus if you stay tuned
You can hear from Tony CPL who is the CEO of Vitamix
Talking about
Yes
Smart blenders
All right
Let's kick this off with a message
This week sponsor
This week sponsor is
Sap
Sap wants you to come to Leonardo
Sap Leonardo live you will walk away with a game plan instead of brochures for dealing with
What's the Internet of Things
You're going to experience these Technologies rather than just hearing about them
Insurance
You're going to
Innovate instead of just talking about it you're going to get hands-on experience with Innovations from iot machine
Machine learning analytics Big Data blockchain data intelligence
And all of this is enabled by sap Cloud platform and design picking services
You're going to hear from customers such as caterpillar UPS HP Bosch
McKesson
Monsanto
Parkwhiz and wow even more
You're also going to hear from Andrew McAfee from MIT best-selling author Walter Isaacson who is
CEO of the Aspen Institute also wrote a wonderful book about Steve Jobs that I enjoyed very much and so
Many more self to learn more you can visit sap.com sap Leonardo
Water live in a sap.com sap Leonardo
Anime
And now back to the show
Skip this week we'll talk about Dell
Which is it
Best billion dollars in iot
R&D over the next 3 years
Around a couple different projects
It's also really trying hard to integrate all of its
Business units into
1iota option
10 / customers
Prior to this gel was really involved
Selling gateways
And it did work with a lot of customers individually to set of solutions
But now it's got this
Unified approach to Route it
Many many products so we're talkin
Dell EMC stock
VMware
Pivotal
All of that
It's also made some investments into a bunch of IO
40 startups
So when I talked to Del
Last week
About the snooze Leon
Green
Distributed back into the
So they really wanted to focus
At the edge not necessarily the sensors
At the gateways and then in the
Concept in some places you're going to have data centers
You're not actually
Data centers on site
So that's kind of their focus and then some of it goes bad
Obviously
Companies in Inwood VMware
AMC
Docker project Nautilus
Which I think is in beta right now just ingested
Queries data from the iot gateways
So you're taking that edge data and mash it up and see what they can find out
And that's really important because obviously
There are so many situations of
People are realizing
Coyote
Dealt with
In real time
To be like you
Admittedly
Actually
Real-time because of someone's operating like a smelt
Machine and the temperature gets too
The high that needs to be
So I think the IT world is kind of waking up to the fact that when they started selling the stuff into some of the many
Passion planner
Do you not understand what we do all the time and how dangerous that can be so that's why the other is data
So much data center
Doesn't make sense manufacturing Park
Generate like a petabyte of data a day
Nobody needs all of that nobody needs all of us
To spend it the money to send that up to the cloud storage
Do stuff there
So finally there's a
Security company
It's a lot of this is very critical data
And
So that's what those doing here it's a smart
Makes sense
I don't have a lot more to say
Well I'm glad you mentioned security bit because it's a common theme in our shows
And they actually is part of this initiative project Iris under the ribs
So they are working to provide certain disabilities in Monterey out to the edges what they're saying so that's good to say
Yes yes
It's a hyper-converged platform
Part of the VMware family
And it's basically going to let you do
Software
Consistent
All the way from
Not the sensors
Probably the Gateway
To the core area which is to be that little mini Datacenter all the way to the
Cloud
So it's just going to make life easier I know we're talking very much in generalities
And the devil is in the details on these
I don't want to
It is
High-level framework
So here are the devil's in the details will see what happens if I was playing buzzword bingo hyper-converged
Yes
I should have Piper
Basically your storage your networking
Computing it's all kind of in the same
Please possible
Allocate resources on the flights Ferry
I'm going to stop
Because
Salesforce
Another kind of industrial iot
They came in
Big
And then we didn't really hear
So what they did at dreamforce this week they basically said they've created
Summon call the IMT Expo
Explorer Edition
And this is just to help people deal with data
Better
And it's doing it in a way that doesn't it
Kodi
So
You guys maybe
Salesforce what the heck
Important thing because
WeChat
Overseeing staff
But you have to eventually evolve
So that's what Salesforce is Hope
So all of that
To be analyzed
Anixter like think of service calls examples
Disturbing company
It service call
There's going to be service required
Potato
From the turbine to figure out what's going on
What happened what went wrong
Rather than go after it after the fact that you're getting real time reading
As a service calls coming in it really cuts down on the time it takes
Solve the problem
Exactly
If you don't believe that this is a thing
Go back in time to November
GE
Bought servicemax
Or 900 in
And I think it's 950
Million dollars
And that was a deal
Basically to bring people into the predix GE predix infrastructure
Service calls me
Managing all of that Salesforce obviously wants to get in
And it'll do it
I want to say this cuz I haven't looked at servicemax to my
Might do it like a
Comfortable for the Enterprise way so maybe we'll see
It is the more OT side of the GE way and for the it side
Enterprise spokes go
More Salesforce
All right
Let's talk about Amazon
Yeah
So I think we talked about
What's good weather
Yes
Walmart was work
Google for
Rihanna
That was that yes yes yes I forgot it was a Google home or Amazon
Certainly don't want to be shut out of this concern Adra
Shoots Walmart competitor
Can you use a Smart locks in your home to get your stuff in your house also
Smart license plate Josh and deliver things to your car just put in your trunk for you
Frame is the name of the smart license plate maker
Part of frame is a license plate frame
There's a little
Space to store a key for the trunk of your car in there
You can remotely open now
Provide access to your trunk
It's kind of interesting cuz there's such a focus on home delivery
Guess what you're not always at home
So if you were at work and you want something over there
Actually just drop it off in your car trunk
You don't
I feel like they were talking about that earlier
I filed a patent for the info is it now real
Or is there a box with frame
Anything yet but that's the reporting is that they were talking with frame to make us a delivery service
Okay cool
I'm all for it
Make my life
Okay now
Speaking of Google home
Google home Mini
Sao Paulo
It was last week
Yes
Oh yeah
Of course some of it was
Google home
Product family
The reviewers actually
And found out some trial-and-error and some wacky
That it was listening and recording and sending everything up to the cloud which we know
But it only supposed to happen when you actually trigger the keyword this is happening 7 by 20
4 and that is a very very bad and so
And replace it exactly what they should do as a response to review really reached out to Google
Record the issue Google and they have already
Exit this problems if you ordered one on don't worry this is not
I don't understand how this happened
The Google home mini has to be sharing and reusing tons of the code
It's already in Google home and ordering Google assist
So what happened somebody
I just understand
Well and
This is like everybody's worst fear about bringing these in
So you would think that
Google would be like
Hey guys
What's me
For real sure that this doesn't
Happen
Apparently that didn't
QA test manager
This would certainly be one of the use cases I be testing that's all I mean
All right
Option
We don't actually have an official thing
Call game
No no no
No you can go in and erase this stuff
That's doable you just go in
Your privacy settings
You should be able to see you can hear everything that it's hard
Do you want to get rid of it now when you get rid of it
Will tell you this
You are
Messing with this effective
Everything is learned
Is Tatiana starting from scratch
Okay let's talk about
GM
Company called stroke
Make it slime
Better
I don't know what else to say about that
I can tell you what else
I think this is awesome and I'll tell you why let me give you a very quick little backstory
When I was working at Google
Spaces group
And we
Set up a booth at the Google Cloud event
And we got a $25,000 lidar sensor
We were showing
People who may be on retail stores
How you can track
Motion movement Etc
Amazing
It's basically sending
From top to bottom 30 thousand lines of
Weezer's and that way you can get the depth and width of everything so I'm support does that every second
But again
$25,000
The report is by GM buying strobe
They will reduce the cost of lidar by 99%
Actually do that
Scale
And you can start putting the cost out of these things
That's when it's going to be
Attractive in London market and become more useful
So that means the big think reducing the cost of lidar
Computer vision
3D depth sensing which I've written about we're all very excited about
Computer vision right now
It's weird because we see one way
Everything everything
That is not true
Computer vision is
It is flat in doboj to contacts
Except
We can figure out
Oh I see these things
Pixels in when I get this arranged
Pixels it is a cat
What is
Cool about text
3D 3D
Until things like
If you put a white box against the white wall it can actually say
Not This Is Us
White Walls
It can actually sit here
This is really
Cool stuff
Because
I can put that
Places
Computer skin
Well they can analyze more information see more of us in oh my God our privacy is dead
Okay and you should see how much data that creates these letters
Lee County Jail space Weaver doing
In a car
It's going to be the same thing you're going to need that though for
Seeing all around me
Turn 60 degrees
It's going to be awesome
You're going to need a lot of gpus
Just so happen space
Step somebody Makes You music video
Says it's got a chip
That can take all that data and bring what they call level 5 autonomous driving
This is the new Drive PX
Xbox One hunting video
That will deliver 320 trillion operations
And it's going towards Autumn Acres of course
In the second half of the year
Nice and level 5 Nvidia mean
There will be no need
Gray steering wheel
Petal or pedal
Or mirrors
In your self driving car if you choose to implement this
Holy crap
I need a mirror in my car
How to put makeup on
That's what your phone is for selfie mode
Can you be able to do that in this car because you won't have your hands on the wheel or anything just hold the phone up and put your makeup on
Give me an extra five minutes
How far away
They're saying second half of 2018
Here's what it says
Starting the second half of 2018
The chip is just the beginning
Testing
But
Alright listening from excitement
Clarification
Weeks ago
We were talking about
Vehicle
Two vehicle vehicle infrastructure AKA
Vehicle to
And
We're talking about it
I don't remember why but you
Sunset Ford
Come on I got it I got an email from one of our
Smart
Conservators but you're actually all listening
That will call you listeners and
He pointed out
That
We were a little unclear so let's clear things up
He says there are two
Competing standards for v2ex
That is
802. 11p
Standard
Dedicated short-range
Communications
And that uses the attitude at 11 radio that we
Wi-Fi
An acellular
Cv2x
So
The cellular one is it
Variant of a
P
Wi-Fi and both of them are going to work in
Inseam
Spectrum
It's the five point
Gigahertz
So
Basically we're trying to figure out which one
And
Ideas
How are we going to do the infrastructure the cellular structures are
They're so maybe that makes sense
But WiFi
Paper license
You have to build infrastructure but then you could do it
If you want with it
So I want to say
Thank you I don't have permission to say who sent this to me
But thank you
Wonderful person who sent this to us in
Clarify this
We all know
Yeah I have no idea
Cv2x
Cars are coming with LTE
You can make them Wi-Fi hotspots as a result
Horsetails have Wi-Fi for that
Pick and choose my car based on a stereo
Yeah they're going to have to
Figure something
Cuz I don't
Drivers are not going to
Alright let's move on to my thoughts on
August Smart Lock
That has
Z-Wave
Doorbell
IXL. August Smart Lock with Z-Wave
I've been traveling
Forever I'm traveling right now
It is hard to
Best home devices
Actually when you're traveling so it took me awhile to get the August Smart Lock
Installed
But
I'm happy to say
But if you like
The book of the August
This lock
Madeline
Yente
So I tested and all those things and it works and it's exciting
I don't know what else to say other than
Hey
Connect to locked it does a lot of cool
Now it is
Technically not a lot
It turns the deadbolt door lock stays the same so the install is super easy
I have some
Some glitches with the sauce
Are partly because I have
Tested song
August devices
It is hard for me to figure out
What account to put it under I apparently have 15
416 Augustine
Mount switches
Ridiculous
Hopefully you will not have that
I would think not
So how much is this one because it's the new August Smart Lock Pro + connect
Yes this is
But it also
A little
Bridge
That you plug in that gives you WiFi
It is a Bluetooth lock so if you want to do anything
You're going to be
I need the bridge to talk to the
A home can't work without the
But if you're buying is like you're getting a
Just don't even want
Now
They have a lot that is cheaper it is 149
I tell you this locked works very well it's Bluetooth and then
If you buy the
Connect Bridge
You can add the wifi to it
And what it is
Very substantial
Good lord it's so heavy
And boxes to the batteries is real
Easy
Doorsense which is
Basically the ability to censor that you stick on the side of the door and then it
Knows if the door
Close all the way
And so
Sometimes if you lock it
Door and you're gone
It can be locked
Not right
So this is how
Someone asked me if you could see
Dorset
I do not see it separately
S*** I'm curious though if you installed something like
Homebridge which is a little bit more
Simple
So I don't have her
Homebridge install
But I did not see it now
I could not use
Motion sensor
And this
Smart Lock the $149 one is not something you put over your existing deadbolt practices natural replacement
Really interesting I only say that because it looks
Bigger it has a bigger faceplate
I don't know why it
It's the same it doesn't have a deadbolt
Just
Mounts over your existing
Watch
It's
And it's not that
Traditional
August
And then if you like that circle look
You can still have it
And that will be there
The whole cat version / $200
You're like
I needed to talk to the echo
Keewaydin there
Lock that is Bluetooth
Wi-Fi ready so you still have to buy the bridge remote access
At that point you basically should just
That's
.
Now August also in
Doorbell
I bought the August doorbell
I hated it
It was the worst purchase I think I've ever
Cuz I have
After first and second worst
Bro
Couple Improvement
It now has
A light on it
Prior to this they actually did not have a light that you best in low light
Gamer setup
What if there was no light
You can see who is at your door
Which my husband would like
Dear killer
It wouldn't affect
Street lights
Your house you probably
But this has a flood light
It's very bright color HD video
In the dark
Yay
Here's where we get to the park
I have installed
Actually a dozen doorbells
House and I was
Because
The original August so terrible
And then I open this and I was hoping just to kind of
Slip it back on
Mounting plate
Different
Make it more reliable
And
So I was like okay so I took it off and then I realized
Schools on the mount
We're different
So I had to drill two new holes to install this thing
My house
And at that point
I was just build with
Wish I could I get I get the most people
Probably
What would be the first
Doorbell
Camera
So this is your fruit so
If you want to upgrade from the original August
I'm just warning you that you're just going to have to
Bust out your drill again
Put the holes in it
Difference
Existing holes are hidden
But I still hate the fact that my
Looks like Swiss cheese
Can I have two dispatching
But that's me
That's not everybody
Unless you try out a lot of doorbells
So the doorbell works much better
It is
Probably
I only tested it a little bit before I left so I want to do some more
Is way more responsive
Faster
Quite a bit of
So sometimes there was a little
Consistency it was about the same as what I felt with the original ring
The ring Pro is actually better
And I think the ring Pro is probably a better
Doorbell to this
And both of them have a subscription fee
So I kind of wood error
Preside
Unless you just like the look
This one
Go for it cuz it is so unique looking
College Square
That is my
August
I'm still very bitter about it
Yes they say there's one in her door just like I don't want Bridges and hubs in my house
There we go
So
Does a little gremlin
You can reach it and please do call us
What's your question
But
You make the app
Call Leslie and play it on
The podcast so you can call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7:40
Toopoor
And leave
Your question
This week's question
Comes from
Sally
Hi my name is Sally and I have a question about using my Sonos Play 1
With If This Then That app and wondering if there's a way to
Connect with you
So that when my August Smart Lock unlock my home my Sonos to turn onto my purse
I'd love to find out if there's a way that I can link this last piece of technology and with
If this then that internet thing but I have happen
Thank you
Okay Sally I have
The bad news is we can't do it
What's he want us to do
So
List
Doesn't work
Directly with some
That's okay that's okay
Cuz we found two
Alternatives What alternative
It's going to SmartThings that requires a hub
So we were like
And SmartThings also requires you to have the August lock with Z-Wave
So we kind of just automatically cut that out
Cuz we're not sure if you have
Latest August lock
But
You don't have to do any of that because
You can download a free software app called
Do you know me
That's why I O
Am I
And that work
With August locks
And it works
Solosis
Especially very similar to
Create routine
So the same thing just using a different tool
And my favorite part about it is
You can actually set
Limits
So I went in
Do you know me
Started doing this because I was like
Me at every time you unlock
Your tour if your Sonos plays
Your favorite
You're going to suddenly like the time you come
I'm home at midnight
And your I don't know if you live with people you live with people
The time you coming home at midnight it starts Blair and you know Joan Jett or something
Your phone is going to be mad at you
I know
Because this has happened
So what you basically can do is
You can say when something happens
The August door unlocks
Run this action so I had mind saying the kitchen Sonos
Take a couple option
And I had to play throwback Thursday
So I said only if it's before 10
10 p.m.
And then you could even also say and only if
I'm there
In the important
Part about that
It will only do it for you based on
Can your phone be
They're so
Your husband comes home
When you're not home
It's not
And I don't know
Is someone else
Sometime I realized
And
You're not home
Which I think is
Customizable
If you live alone
Fine but I always find it
Really fails
When you start adding other people in
So I'm always looking
Welcome to my world
Is it
Goalie challenge
It's just me
So Sally that is the option that we found
Best for what you were
Police calls to go out to buy Oliver any like that
So
We wish you luck
And you know me I like it because
All my Sonos is Mew
Automatically
Which is super cool
Cuz then I can listen to music
While I'm working
Phone calls
That's like my favorite thing
And it doesn't right off the
What feels like
Good stopping place for this section
The show
We're going to have a message from our sponsor
And
We're going to have Tony CPL
Who is the CEO of Vitamix
Talking about
Adding Bluetooth
Two blender
That was kind of fun alright stay to you guys
Breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is Qualcomm and once again I have Raj talluri here he is the SVP
And GM of iot
We talked a lot about cameras when we talk about the internet
Why is it so important
Or such a good opportune
The cameras are becoming an increasingly important part of
Different diets
Because now the camera
To do a lot of interesting features that help consumers like facial recognition objective
Malaysian people
So you are not going to be seeing cameras
Things like
Spend a tell you your pie is baked or not end security cable TV
Cameras that I
Actually you can take out your house and some strangers come
And also 360 degree cameras
Where are you now able to record a concert
And send it back though someone was not in the concert
Can watch
Aviara
Awesome cool, is well-known for smartphone
So how applicable is the phone camera
Back in the intern
Smartphone cameras really fantastic now they've done a lot of work in making these cameras better and better
Most people now just take the
Pictures of this month
And I really a great source of camera animation
Dab dab sensing
Multiple cameras
Ultra HD recording and so on
Sadistic Knology is actually very applicable to iot
Because we're not able to
Use the smartphone camera gorgeous
You actually got to work this kind of
Innovations
Into lots of other cameras
Example into home monitor
Security cameras
Action camera
Wearable camera
The beijinger technology applies
Sue Qualcomm customers they're just putting smartphone as Oh Sees into these cameras
What is one more than that what we do now is
To take the technology that we have developed
Smartphone camera button customized
For the various iot applique
So for example
The security cameras require
Start the amount of low light performance because these cameras installed where you know the light can go down to like one lumen
Until then you'll have to use things like infrared
So we are doing a lot of modifications
And a lot of innovation
Top of a camera technology that we built in phone space to make them more applicable to this kind of tired
So what's out there that
Currently using
Call contact
So the new nest camera you just said welcome technology
In that has built-in smartphone camera adapter to home security cameras
Rico recently
Introduce a typha a newt
Eataly
360 degree camera
The fuses are snapdragons
625 processor
But this is actually at 3
60 degree camera
Peacocks in 4k
Another example of how we were able to adapt and modify the Snapdragon
Camera technology for the consumer 360
That is an awesome camera
So we're can listeners learn more and get started using Qualcomm
Products for camera
Ulysses can go to qualcomm.com iot
And look for the camera section
It's a lot of
Information
About technology and diet
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Tony
CPL who is the CEO of vitamin
Hi Tony how are you doing today
I'm doing great Stacy nice to be here with you
Man I am super excited one because I love my Vitamix
Everyday I use it into
Because if I can make it smarter
I feel like I might be a healthier better person so let's talk about what you guys are doing to make Vitamix
Grout Stacy we're very excited because the first of the year we launched a new
Platform of products called the ascent series
And this new Ascent series really redefines hype
Performance blending
Form and Function
So for a long time the Aesthetics of our blender
People would say it's not that aesthetic
Replacing so we did it
Total redesign of the product and it has new
Euro curvilinear lines
And very high-tech
Aesthetics that people would be very proud to
Kitchen counter think of it as kitchen candy if you
The more exciting to that is the way this new technology integrates not just the
The form but with the new function
And it's a query
Invented our whole Vitamix platformer
Historic operating system within our blunder was a singular operating system
And now the new system has five different
Operating systems like
Actual software or like things
It does help me
Yes it actual software that's system that's kind of controlling how the motor runs a system that is controlling
Doing the program's system that stalking
From the base to the
The container
Assistant it stalking for the unit
2 apps
In a system around security
Because we wouldn't want anyone to hack our blender
By the way
That's true cuz sometimes I reach in there and that would be
Okay so the blender is connected
To the internet and to your
Just let me clarify little bit so we have a number of new technological advances that are part of the redefinition of the
The function of the unit
The first one that I'll highlight is the use of near field communication
Can NFC
Which is all around detecting the container
And so the new line of products
You can run an 8 oz
A 20 oz
48 oz a 64 Oz and even some new things in the future and the unit will automatically sense
Do near field communication the blender base what is on it
8 oz 20 oz 40 an ounce
And it will reprogram
It's also all the programs
Operate with that appropriate size container
Got it okay so the recipes and everything
Can then be adapt
That's exactly right so for example you wouldn't
Want to make soup in an 8 oz container might
Not be a safe thing to do so
Will limit the recipes that can be done in the 8 oz
Sounds like wise if you're doing a 40 an ounce or 64 Oz
The way that programmed
Develops in terms of it
It's ramp and speed
Induration
Will be different than it is
It is 60
All right so let's talk about what connectivity enables you to do
As a company both
Consumer services and then also as somebody who makes
Really high powered
Crazy blenders so just to talk a little more about that connectivity
Each of our units in addition to having NFC or near field communication on board
They also have Bluetooth
And this enables the blender to work in conjunction with the
So currently we have an app called the Vitamix perfect scale which is a scale that can detect which container
It comes with an app that has over 500 recipe
And once you put the container on the scale
Zero's out
The container and now you can build a recipe
With no measuring tool
And it will automatically take
That recipe and
Send a program to the blender that's appropriate for that recipe
That's what we've been doing since
The first of the year we're about to launch our new app
It's going to be with our new platform
The sensor
And this new app comes with 17
Program
So if you have any unit that has no programs like
Peanut butter or frozen dessert or soup or one of the big favorites
That everyone has self cleaning it will automatically take that you
And send that program
To the blender this is
What will help people be much more successful
The app also includes
500 recipes
And you can scale the rest
Recipes either by volume or by calories
Show picture of your finger going up and down kind of scaling recipe Sally 120 ounces I really don't want 32
It will on the Fly we can't calculate all the nutritional information and display it for you or send it to your nutrition
No app and then it will recalculate
The program to blend
Tencent
The unique
Program for what you just caliber
To the blender and blend it
Awesome so it also sends that you mentioned something that was really exciting to me that it sent it to the lake my nutritional accounting
Is that so you guys are working
With everyone or is that like an open standard Zephyr
Yes we have an Open Standards effort that connects to a number of different apps right now but we're open to connect with anyone
And we are doing that now in addition the app includes meal plans so you can create meal plans for yourself it'll create
Create shopping list and probably in the not too near future will generate your grocery order and maybe even placed
Very exciting and ambitious so how does all of this connectivity
And Technology bit into the Vitamix
Vitamix is purple
Is 2
Liberate
And nourish
Your zest for life
So the liberate part is really to reinvent the way you currently prepare food and beverage
And change the way you do it make it much easier and faster
The nearest part is really we're interested in making you high
And your zest
Your life is our customers they live with gusto and with that what we want to do is help them achieve
Their goals
If you won't think about their in the process
Exploration in
Transformation
And so we consider ourselves a transformational
We want to help people get to where they want to go
We want to make them
A better me if you
Whatever that might be for some it might be a mom who really wants to give her children the most nutritional diet that Sheikh
A healthy snack
For others it might be a high-performance athlete that wants to reach his Peak Performance or her Peak
Performance Brothers they might be a foodie and they want to
Create
Dish
That will really impress their friends when they entertain on a Friday or Saturday night
And so we build track
Within our app within
The way we map the customer Journey
To help people be successful
And as we go forward as a company it's all about being intuitive
What do we need to do
Help people reach their goal
We don't have to be intuitive cuz you're going to get a lot of
Data so let's talk about how you guys want to use that data to build better products but also maybe I don't know this
I had my blender forever and it's never broken down knock on something
So what else does that do for
So is it company
We pay a lot of attention to what
Our customers do both here and around the world we sell our products and 140 different countries
For example we track
Blender usage in 9 countries every month
Both what people make in home away from and what ingredients they use how often
And what they buy away from
And where they buy it
And what do they buy what
The commercial side wework the largest chains in the world
And so
We're constantly bringing them ideas on menu creation
So
When we know that
New ingredients are popping up
Buy turmeric
Caffeine
Our customers are typically early adapter
And so when they start putting these things in
And we can bring these ideas
To the major chains and say look this is where
Menus are going
Likewise for recipe development for the household we start developing recipes around what we are seeing people use
With regard to Ingrid
We're garnering a lot of information
2 hour Vitamix
Perfect Scale app where we Now understand what's actually happening during the day how often people are
Making a smoothie
What day park
Soups
Frozen desserts
And it's very insightful
How to know what people are making what ingredients are using
What day Parts they're doing and we use that to influence
What we created
In terms of the experience within the app
And the recipes.
Could you sell that data I would
Like if I were like Campbell's I would be really interested in like
What's the trend in healthy soups
So I can make some
I suppose that's possible that's not really our aspiration we do it primarily just
Insights in terms of the macro Trends and where things are going
We don't even have the ability to look at it on an individual basis we look at it in macro terms
And we look at the trends and then we use those
To direct kind of where we go.
Directions a lot of people talk about the monetization of data I'm not sure anybody is actually doing it and it's
It's not something that's a high priority for
Building a connected product
Can be super dangerous
Because there's a
Security risk
But there's also this
Does the customer really want
That's so how did you guys approach the idea of bringing
Intelligence into
Something that work really well
We have a very robust business insights team
And they do various types of qualitative and quantitative research as well as ethnography
Epic research so we spent a lot of time in people's homes
We spent a lot of times with shafts both in fine restaurants in large chain
And we really understand how they use the prop
And then we create our controls we can
Create are apps the whole experience around the way people really use the product and what's most of
All right and
One of the challenges of building a
Product is
Suddenly you got this thing that might last for
7 years or 10 years out on someone's counter that's going to constantly need to be
Updated
Costs associated with
How did you guys think about
How to price it and how to think about that bring that aspect into your business
I'm glad you asked that because Vitamix typically Vitamix owners consider their blender Vitamix blender is
Asian heirloom that they're going to pass on from generation to generation and so we spent a lot of time thinking about that and that was one of them
Main reasons why we put Bluetooth technology into are Prada
So that in the future
I downloaded Vitamix app that the most current APP can actually update
Your blender just like a Tesla can be
And so that's the infrastructure that we put in place is one of the operating systems that I talked about earlier and one that we're copping
Didn't that are Vitamix owners you know will well into the future still have that heirloom quality
An heirloom type of perspective about a product and it will be able to be up to
Awesome alright Tony thanks so much was really nice having this opportunity to chat with you
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot cam thanks for listening and we'll see you
Next week