Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Kevin tofel
For you we're going to have a
Secret
Secret launch
From Andy Rubin
Kevin has some big news for everyone
We got some chips news
We're going to talk about the WeMo dimmer switch and a few other
Plus
We have this week sponsor which is Eros and
Our guests who is Brett Greenstein
From IBM
And some other cool things about
So
Let's get this party started with
Quit message from one of our sponsors this week sponsor is Affiliated monitoring if you are hunting for a subscription
Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about Affiliated monitoring in response to a trigger from any connected
Is a vice Affiliated the professionally trained live agents can follow-up protocol and reach out to your customers their loved one
Guns and local emergency services Affiliated works with hundreds of Smart Home Security
Health and other iot businesses visit Affiliated. Com iot to read a case
A study on how they've helped connected car startup turn an idea into a thriving business with a hundred million dollar
Surrexit that's Affiliated. Com
/ iot
That's actually a really good idea
There's a lot of businesses that
Benefit from having a trigger
Actually do more than just send you a notification
All right
Unto the show
Let's go
Start with Andy Rubin
And the essential
We can't we have to talk about the essential phone and the essential home
One punch
Is only here the essential phone
So
Kevin do you think this is essential
Well they would like it to be like for those who don't know Andy Rubin is the
Creator of Android
And has left Google a couple years back and forget when
But this is his first
Venture outside of
Life after Google it isn't Android
Powered phone and it's
Iron specifications
And dealt with
Printed materials such as titanium and ceramic
Pretty much an edge-to-edge display even more so than the
Galaxy S
8 but Samsung makes I don't know if they see if you've seen the because it's edge to edge
Here's why this phone is not
Essential for me
I do not like the front facing camera cutout
On the display
Did you see that
I did
That separate that separate the top of the phone just like you would have
But since the screen goes all the way to the top Edge
It's almost like there's a hole there in the screen as you're looking at content
Oh I do see it
Looks like a keyhole or something like what is bad
Took to not essential for me personally I sent you would be to not see that
But regardless regardless of that it is all high-end
Specs on a Snapdragon 835 and
4 gig of RAM and all the typical high-end features
You were leading to the backside of the phone
Has these
To Pogo pins
Where you place a 360-degree camera you would it attaches to the phone
And then I believe it actually
Since the data from that 360 camera over a 60 gigahertz Wi-Fi gig
Holy cow
A new devices
Found it
Possibly
Maybe bring this technology
Like 2002
Ultra wideband
Ultra wideband that it was something else
So many chip companies went into this and fail
And
The standard is always been there basically Superfast High data rates you can send over 60 gigahertz but you can only do it when it's
It's really close proximity
Yep I totally totally it's a perfect season I knew because I knew you would cover the since way back
I knew you would love that little aspect of it
As we said it runs Android it's $699
360 camera
I would imagine not a lot of bloatware I'm suspecting US Stock Android or slightly tweet
Yoga wear
Very no logos
Yeah yeah minutes it's a nice-looking device
Now
Competes against a lot of other night so I can give Isis and this is a relatively unknown company because it's
Essentialism
Ribbon startup
So
We'll have to see it does it doesn't work well with security updates and so on and you know there's a lot of question
To be asked
We are not it
I thought you were going to leave the fact that we are not iPhone
We are
Iot
An iot compono
And it's very vague and fluffy so we're going to go with what we know
Which is
This summer
This is they call it home it runs something called ambient OS
And this is my idea is this will work
With everything
The product itself is a tiny round
Device looks kind of hockey puck Asia Terrace light
It reminds me of
An echo Dot
More wedge-shaped because the top is slanted is you had said and it has a touch screen display
Emma's wish that's what the. Was from Harbor perspective
Touch lamp
True true
And we don't know how much this is going to cost is coming out summer times
What's the time
So how does it work with everything that it works with homekit
Products that are very handy
It's apparently doing so that reverse engineering public apis which
Not ideal
I mean it's nice for like
But what happens if those public apis can change in
What will happen is it a break
Your product before
Fake necessarily fix it
Right
Sony demonstration
It's always better from
The end-user
It's Andy Rubin I can't imagine that these guys can't get
You know when the time comes
Cam specs
Since everyone else isn't that competes with like
Google maybe they won't do a nest integration
Play hard to say
One of the other aspects which is very important for our listeners is that
There's a privacy
Function I guess you could say or design in that it tries to handle as much data as possible locally on the device
I'm not sure how that's going to work
Because if it's tying into all these other
Platforms
It's going to be sending and receiving data in
I possibly giving giving data to those platforms so
I'm not sure
Not sure how that's going to work
It sounds good on paper but let's see
And
Just for funsies
I'm interested in this because
Playground pictures
Which is also backing this
They funded something called lighthouse
And lighthouses
A smart home assistant that has an image
Comment so computer vision components so it can actually see things so you can Chester to it
It sounds really cool this is also not a
Cool products
Bill's pretty competitive
With
What is this
I don't see a camera or mention of a camera on the
This device so
Anticipating no Machine Vision
Aspect to it which eventually help
Its first integration
But that'll help keep the cost down number one
And to it kind of leads back to the hole
New Amazon products which
I'm still scratching my head over I know you ordered
The show
And I seen the discount packs
Before
I had ordered my first one I would have
Cuz we need it cuz we need another way to talk
That's essential will find out more
We'll stay on this
Cuz by dali
You know I love Andy Rubin he's a big
Open
Kind of open web Guy Fieri consumeristic
I feel like his attention to the phone with some things of kind of
Tragedy fetishistic which I don't think is going to work
Actually in the smart home space
Because
Most normal people do not care if their stuff is made of titanium
And that's that's for the phone
I do have some concerns there
Also the fact that it's going to be doing everything local means it's got to be
Pretty robust
Processor on it
When should you add to the cost
10 tube
Be cheap
Again
We'll see
I would love for there to be more
Competition in the space
Jason actually
This was something I was thinking about talking about
Before this came out
I actually feel that my smart home works really well right
Weird
Because I spent so much time complaining about standards but when's the last time you guys heard me complain about like zigbee or Z-Wave
If I happen
Right or something or something that doesn't work with something because of some other particle maybe not
Messerli radio but
Maybe apis sdks
We're getting there
Yeah cuz with the Google will actually with the Amazon Echo and now with Google's latest Integrations I feel
Basically I just say what I want
And then there's also those super powerful tools like stringify and if now that it's
Scott the maker
I actually can do a lot
So this brings us to
Such a subtle Segway but oh so timely yes okay so
After
Almost there
Here I guess I guess Google announced the Google home be at last IO 2016
It wasn't available
That's true so I get a pass at least until October so
Longtime listeners will know I
Cast on the Google home because I have for Echo devices in my house
Mainly for the reasons that you just said because things worked
Write everything I needed to do eisworth well with the echo
However
I finally caved
I ordered a Google home for two reasons
It actually has not arrived at its comes tomorrow so I can't speak to how else working for me
But one of the reasons was all of the new Integrations
With the Smart Home Products the ones that I particularly use already
So it will essentially replace
An echo
Turn my smart home purposes
Additionally I do feel having use Google Assistant that when I want information
I get a broader range in more detail information more specific information from
Google
Knowledge Graph as opposed to the echo I think Amazon's made improvements but they have a ways to go there
So
The second reason I got it
3 reasons
The second reason I got it is
Because
I got rid of my pixel
A few months ago about a Galaxy S8 which has as we know Bixby
I have the assistant on there however I cannot
Use the hot word
To trigger the assistant unless the screen is on or the device is plugged in
Where's the pixel I guess I could just use it
Getting frustrated by that
Finally
There was and I think there still is
A $30 discount on Google home if
You
Purchase it through Google Express switch
I've never used before
It's for new Google Express customers
There's a coupon code which may we can put in the show notes we put the link to where I got this information
Said hopefully it still available for people making use it
So
I sign up for Google Express probably won't use express anymore. Cancel that service but I got $30 off the homestead 99 box so
For all those reasons I caved
Got to Google
Okay
After you've had it I want to hear your experience with
Music
Because I find the Spotify
Integrations if I ask Google to play a song
Can I ask
The echo to play a song
Metal Place the correct song
Cool seems to play like
The top voted karaoke version of the song
Well I don't want that
I may not be the best person to ask however
Because I don't use Spotify
None of the services I use are actually on Google
App for music
Are you Sirius XM
And unfortunately because my family all has iPhones we have an apple music family plan so neither of those work with it
Best I'm going to be able to do is use the free version of Google Play Music
But at the fact
Your music library
We have gone
So far
It doesn't work across many devices I kind of feel along with smart watches
Music is actually a lock-in
Assistance as well as smart watches
I agree
I do not Apple
Apple though
Is getting even more
Locked in
Vertically integrated
There is a report out
Last week the apple is designing its own a iPhone chip
This is pretty exciting news totally fits with the Apple ecosystem where Apple was be
The first phone manufacturer to release
Decided to sign its own arm-based chips for the
The phone
Those are the
Slash number processors
5272 that's area
Oh okay I said where to the A9 Axor
So
Apple does that
They also design their own chips
For their Wireless
Headphones
Actually
WW1
Yes and
They were one of the first to create a
A sensor unit sensor processing
So that
It's their m
This is not crazy that Apple would say you know what
This whole day I think this this basically execution this inference of artificial intelligence algorithms
We got a separate that
We got to put that someplace else in
Design something special
For that
The reason they can do this is because they sell so many darn iPhones and because it's going to be a huge savings
Maybe not huge it will be a savings on battery life
It's really important
Cuz running these algorithms can take
A lot of processing power and also it needs to happen really fast and
You don't want that competing with you know
Trying to load your website
Your browser
Magically happy
You know what really sing
I'm going to say this and you can correct me if I'm wrong
Is maybe I do have this around the world
In my finger really seeing
I must March toward Asics application-specific integrated circuits for
Just about everything now every used to be that the
The phone processor would just do everything but now we've got
And we had digital signal processor
An hour
Building chips for AI
And building chips for this and billing chips for that
So we can optimize
As you said the processing power for the right task in the battery life for the right path so we can
Get a good mix of a battery life in a Daiso
I think you're going to see a lot more this especially with a i and assistance
Apple certainly not the only one working on this in my opinion
And
I'll be curious to see what
Advantages they Tout
If and when this comes out
Yes and we talked about the sun previous shows but this is
What we talk about is the end of general purpose computing
We've come to a point where battery life is so significant
The volume sprayer
Not just phone makers but even some of the big wet companies means that they can
Build specialized not just equipment
What's silicon
This is a huge existential
Threat to Intel
So I'll just bring that up
Yep it's pretty big one
Kevin we actually forgot
Something we forgot your
Closure sew
Retroactive oh yes I will yes so I do work
Google I do not work on anything iot related
Then all opinions are my own
We do not question
Kevin is
Speaking of chips
They finally announced what they're going to do with it dynamic
Architecture that they announced probably 3 or 4 months ago
How much so they have a new cortex a75
55in a brand new Molly chip
Only the cortex chips use the dynamic
Which is basically a new way of
Parallel processing multi
Keith reading it's it's better for AI
There's that word again
So all of those
They're at the more energy efficient
Really Nifty
And then the Maui chip is just
It's it's my better graphics chip
It's more power efficient
It's
More powerful
So we talked about the dynamic
CPUs I kind of pillow is a little bit of marketing fluff back in March
I
Kill a little less so in that
Instead of comparing big and little chips in terms of
High compute and high battery life with
Less computer lower battery life
You can mix and match a little bit so you can go up to
Eight-course believe
But you can say six or seven of them are low-power and only one is high-power you can
Do whatever you need to do for whatever device you're designing so
I'm a little bit
You're impressed by that so maybe you can have a record medicated just to machine learning for example
And again this is that much
This is chi you guys
The theme of the week
Bachelor
Moving on from chips
Verizon
Hub
Sorta
Yeah this is my
Okay well this is marketing
Can I just say that right in French
Okay
So Verizon put out a press release last week
Turn your house into a Verizon 4G LTE home with
Smart Hub
That's the name of the product smart
Capital S capital h
I fail to see the Smart Hub capabilities of it it seems to me like it's basically
A way to bring Wireless
Broadband to your house which
There's Merit for that
People out in rural areas at maybe
They don't have
Cable choices FiOS isn't there and so on maybe the other using phones with Hotspots for their primary connectivity
I get it
At this place makes sense it's a $200
4G router essentially
But Verizon made a big to-do about how it's going to work well with all of your
Smart devices including more than 200 Wi-Fi products and so on and so forth
So I'm thinking before even though it's like a router with
You know it's that acts as a Smart Hub
But it doesn't seem to be that doesn't seem to have those kind of smart that just seems to be a way to have
Connectivity for your devices like maybe like a Gateway at best
Am I misunderstanding it
Well it looks a little smarter
I mean this is still not something I would buy because
So basically it's $200 it's got the backup to the 4G network
Works on Wi-Fi it connects to over 200 Wi-Fi devices it's got a tiny little OLED screen at the top
Tells you how many devices are on your network and some other things
And in the app it does let you control
In schedule
Like routines and that's worth
So
You can tell anything to
It reminds me of the
Routers
Become red in in just imaginating 4G
The idea for cheese basically
It also has a backup battery so when your power goes out
You still have
Cellular connectivity to
Two things that run on batteries
Right now it's only has cellular connectivity if I'm not mistaken
Well not this early but again for people in rural areas I think it's
That's good because I don't have many Broadband choices
Yes
Okay so
You got your cellular to Wi-Fi connection
That's yay
But if your power goes out you know you're not going to be able to control most of these devices cuz most wifi-based devices which is what this works with
They are plugged in because such a Powerhouse
Right
That's where I'm kind of
It seems like a mish-mosh of
A lot of technology that
Doesn't
Yeah I don't think so again
If you don't have good
Wired Broadband nagpur
Opportunities at your house
Then it this might make sense you write will be expensive
But at a Smart Hub I just
I'm just kind of questioning
What kind of man
Oh but we do want to talk about so
One of our listeners John
Send us an email John
Morse he actually sent a comment on one of her last blogs that was super helpful so he introduced us to
This
TI has a technology called
Captivate
And it basically is touch technology that
That works through
Wood
Wow that would be so cool he points out the
I agree
Real estate like
That I'm I'm very excited about like touch technology that works through Fabrics because I'm like
Passive touch screen an arm of your couch
Is here there like you could put it on your coffee table as long as it's
The MC use can sense their laminated plywood that's up to
2.75 in thick in particle board this one inch thick
So I don't know I think this is kind of neat right Kevin oh absolutely am it if you can't agree
Capacitive touch into wood
Products furniture and sex it would be
Great
Do you have to plug in your furniture to make this work a minute this says it can run on a battery for a certain amount of time
Exactly exactly so ideal weight yet
You probably want a dedicated power source but if you do that then you think of the possibilities of adding integrated wireless charging to the furniture
Is available today but
You know this just makes sense.
How to
Go hand-in-hand with a capacitive touch
Element
Sound like
Again my my sit-stand desk is wood
The top and I would love to not have
Physical buttons underneath it to raise it or lower it may be great to just go to a
Section of the desk itself Express in heaven
Do its thing
I would love to see you.
We're actually love this I'm like my dining room table
Control my dining room light
How awesome you'd be like
It's a little bright in here at the sun goes down
I don't need wireless charging in my
Kelso that would
Writing rice
Okay so there is one downside
Would you like to tell
Oh yeah
That's the dance I almost forgot about it because it's
Barely mentioned
Yes I'm just going to read this flat out from the Press race touch technology embedded in wood might also be subject to moisture
Penetration
Send me from a spilled drink on the arm of the chair or rain on a door frame
So if your knees in your dining room table don't put your drinks down on capacitive coasters
There you go
So
Really cool technology
TI's got it
I thought this was great
Thank you so much
Kris Kristofferson
All right
I promised you last week that I would talk to you about the
WeMo Wi-Fi
Dimmer
Switch
And this is wemo's first dimmer switch
They had a normal wifi-connected switch that was on and off and
Some people like that some people do not
The dimmer switch is $80 so it's
Prasek's
My favorite switches which are still Lutron
And it's pricier than the Leviton WiFi Decora series
Play switch I also have installed cuz those are about 50 bucks and they work with the Amazon Echo without a
Cuddly trying to work you need to
My install process was a little wonky because I've got some crazy wiring so I ran into some trouble
In the first spot
So I stuck it in a different
And I put it in the bath
And this is a
Really nice light
It's got a capacitive touch dimmer
So you just move your finger up and down the dimmer which is kind of need to turn the lights
LED in it that turns on
When
The light
Is triggered by something so it turns different colors based on what product has triggered it
If that is something really
Cool cuz if you set like
If you're like me you said a lot of different recipes or
Things up and then suddenly your lights are going on and you have no idea why
Believe me guys
Happens to me more often
Be able to look at it
Blue and be like
Hey. That means I just turned it on with the Amazon Echo
Which
Is maybe not a weird thing but if it turns orange that means I've turned it on but if if
Which actually is a nice thing because
You know that might be an automation then
I like
The light
To feel it's expensive and then the other things know about it it's got the most
Wonderful labeling
Squires
Lovely
I got to say
The switch itself is
Freaking huge just so big
So if you don't have a lot of room
Like I initially try to install it in a
3 games
Switch and there's a lot of wires crammed back there
It wasn't
It's bigger even than
So it's bigger than electrons
It's bigger than the Leviton
It goes as bad as deep as the Leviton but it's also a live
That's going to be an issue if you don't have a lot of room in the
The back of your switch box
Or you can just hire an electrician
You know it's interesting because all the the boxes and all were designed for a traditional light switches for years and years and
Years and now we're adding
Smart sand
Chips and
Things radios and such
Into the switches that I wonder
You know how we run out of room in a sentence
Man
Okay that's a hugely certified product thank God
Because you don't
Standard standard for a reason
Toads
I think so
Yeah yeah
That's going to be
A challenge but
But yes it is something to think about
If you don't have a lot of room back there
You're going to be folded wires
I anticipate embedded speakers maybe even cameras and such and switches
Yes there's a lot of weathers motion sensors
There's microphone switches
Your relay switch for
You have
Stick out a little
Yes it did
So it it moved forward
Fred
Which means you could install it in
Cycling switch
Soda challenge
All right
Cheapest to think about
Alright thank you so much Kevin
No
We will
Stay tuned
For a Our Guest this week Brett Greenstein for my VM
And
Before we talk to him we are going to have a quick message from this week's sponsor hey everyone we
Breaking into this week's podcast with the message from our sponsor this we sponsor is Eros and I have
Z Hussain who is the CTO and founder of Eros
Here to talk to me about
Hot markets for The Internet of Things
So
Quick Refresher
Tell people what areas is
Eros is a company that provides a complete solution
From the devices that are located out in the field all the way back
Netflix
To the storage and analytic functions that are necessary
Support iot applications
From small medium and large Enterprises for their customers or friendly
Markets for iot
What are the most rapidly growing areas for
What are the natural things about cellular which is what we do and provide for connectivity Services is
The fact that devices that need to be mobile
Can be on our networks are roughly half of the units tend to be in the automotive & Fleet Management space not surprisingly
On the other hand one of the largest markets that is
Coming up to speed is the healthcare Market because of the impact that iot Solutions can have on the cost
Problems that are being encountered in the healthcare Arena that market is exploding
Those are both
Really good Industries
So how should they think about the trade-offs between
Wi-Fi and cellular
Surly Wi-Fi tends to be a very ubiquitous solution if it's available in a given
Residence or given business or given building the only issue is that you have to do a fair amount of configuration
To be able to use that Network
And not all applications can take advantage of that or the maintenance and debugging and support
Can become an issue so people like to be able to use
Networks that are dependent on someone locally providing a support activity support system
Netflix
And to be the method of choice because the network
We'll manage that for you Eros managers the device behavior on the network
Because they can reach out and see the device
Completely independent of any local setup issue that might
So now I know what's hot and how to connect
When should a business
Think about
Beginning to implement in Iowa
Beauty solution
The best time to implement an iot solution is when you know the problem you're trying
And you have information that you're trying to get remotely
And you have an understanding of what
Value that information
Has for you your company or your potential
If you don't take advantage of the fact that data is available and that the solutions that are being implemented in the iot space
Can provide you the necessary information in a way that will make meaningful sense their business action
Then that's not the right time to start
Where can I find out more about what Arris is doing
I want to find out more about iot Solutions and how to deploy
And iot solution for their particular problem I would highly recommend that a download a copy of the
Free ebook that I have published this available on our website
Www.arris.com listen to a copy of this podcast another part
Scott Stapp
Www.arris.com podcast
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And we are joined this week by
Brett Greenstein
Who is vice president for Watson iot
Over at IBM
Hi Brett how you doing
Very good nice to talk to Stacy
Actually we've talked
You guys and Brett is a font of information
About this
But that
It's not really
Talk too much about today
Instead we are going to focus
Watson's iot business
And also a broader question of
How do we go from all of the sensor data to actually
Taking action or getting valuable insights from it
So let's
Let's start off
Set the hard question
I got gobs of data
Tracking everything
How do I take that
And get from
Data
I think you have to recognize that most of the iot data that people collect today
Is probably useless
It's only valuable fur
Microseconds
It is awesome noise
And finding the signal from the noise
Certainly the hard part
We found
That having model
That Define
People
And places and things
How we think they might work
Palm is a necessary starting point
And then we leverage analytics to look for
What's normal and what's not
So that could be something
Gets rid of some of the noise
Right away for example you can look at
Jada coming off the thermostat
For the most part doesn't move
But if it spikes to 900 Degrees
There is probably a serious
Or if it drops really quickly is another series
Being able to know what's normal what's not
Give me done with machine learning algorithms to assess
Anomalous Behavior
And I could be something that happens in a moment
Three happening something happens Trends over time
And it has to be based on having some
Hypothesis of what's normal
But then using analytics to look for the variations in day that I would tell you when those
Moments happen
NFL really looking for is not the date itself but the moment
I just realized that you're going to be a great person to have it because you can probably help me break down
A couple concepts for peep
Because right now we talked about analytics all the time
We also talked about machine learning
And then we talked about things like
In a lot of people I feel like people kind of just throw those out there
And there he was very interchangeably
I probably shouldn't
So maybe you can help us by
Helping us set up definitions and how we should
Think about each of these
Concepts
Of course I probably will not use whatever
Textbook definitions exist but my own sort of simpler way of breaking it down into what I say three categories
When is
After data has happened
There's
Plenty of analytics tools that go in and look at how you can visualize it in pivot it in
And sort through it to find
Correlations in patterns that you expect to be there and that you're looking
You looking for particular moment you know what you're looking for so you kind of sorting through the day that glancing through it and providing
Are different different ways of organizing that data that sort of astronaut
App
Now
Things that happened
Wallet
Recurring you may have some
Real-time analytics something that is looking for a set of business rules are conditions
That occur as date is flowing in and you're looking for moments are you looking for variations
Here's where machine learning can be used to help see if things are trending in a way that is
Anomalous
So you have you build a
Picture of Baseline
View
And the Machine learning is watching the day does it's coming through every day so that thermostat data
Everyday 7 a.m.
Probably changes because I change the thermostat
It varies with season varies with things and you sort of know what's normal because they machine learning is watching it
Animal attacks abnormally you catch
So you got the what happens after date it was generated. What's happening as it is being generated
City of Learning System
Those are two different types
I'm not an expert in either one
But you got started this assisted learning this is where
The machine is catching things and then you're telling
Too human interaction
Whether these things are correct or not what do they start to approximating model
This is how you might training system for example with images
You might see that
Fifty or a hundred or a thousand images that say this is
You know a dog
And
Each time it has exceeded in and it and then based on that you can correct
The next picture you shall it's going to say I think is a dog it might be a cat
Incorrect
Say what it really is and you keep feeding it and it will continue to approximate
And get closer and closer to accuracy based on the wide range of things
You see it
So this is where this
Human intervention in both what you decide to feed it and of course what feedback you got
Any of our systems that are
Amor vincit that learn on their own
And has recently been
Several articles about systems for example I just get fed
Procedures and things that people do it watches what people do and then learns quickly from that
And that's less of the assisted part that's more than the Deep learning Park
I would say that the range of these different types of system
People tend to lump them into one category
Golden Corral
Yes thank you for going I know that's a scary question to answer me
But you just like rocked it
So thank you for that because I do think that
When it comes to business
It's all lumped together but really
For most businesses probably only the first two are really in
Important today or the 1st
What are your thoughts
What are the most practiced
Definitely the more dominant themes today
We've all been doing analytic Sunday after his creator for a very long time we
Italy called analytics and we called a big data cuz it was more buzzworthy
But also effectively visualizing and pivoting data in different tables and different structures so you could see it
And to look for patterns or looking
Before but I think this idea of
Systems that can learn that are assisted is is clearly grown is almost every process and every industry
Primarily
Because we're really bad at doing something more than a few times
Wenis
And if you can bring the very best at what you do into the systems and they can learn you can improve that you can improve the repeater bill
You can do it at scale
In ways that people can
But we're still unique and be able to tell a dog from a cat
Until we teach our system and then it can tell
Not every time not perfectly
The better and better than my teacher
All right
Let's think about
From a business perspective
Because
Is nothing if not
Which I love
How are customers trying to use
Assisted machine learning so
Will call Watson
That feels like an assistant machine learning
Kind of Technology
How are they using that for iot
Why was
We got some really great clients for using visual recognition to help manage drones
In a particular leveraging
Training of different things you might look for in a drone that might be inspecting power lines
Example
If we can catch
Defects and problems
Was it your own operating from perspectives that people can't
And catch things
Are more subtle
And it's faster than people can
It makes our jobs easier cuz we can direct people to go fix the things that need to be fixed
You know exactly what's wrong
Things
And it's a very powerful technology so we're using visual recognition
Unmanned drones over Powerline
And we can use it in all the variety of settings
Where that perspective is unique with a drone has a
A bird's-eye view that people don't have
Well season
So we done a lot of really great work with several companies bringing
An image recognition to help do defect analysis
A manufacturer
And my very first job
A really long time ago
I was doing visual inspection and now there's a Semiconductor Company using Watson to do that
Probably much better than I ever
And faster
But the other part is it can also learn and change over time you may find that this machine
10 Siskiyou Loop celestin Island
She doesn't over there
So instead of paying people to catch all these variations you can also train systems in
Deploy different models to different tools and manufacturing line
Say something unique that's as well
What's a very powerful way to scale out
Speed up
We're doing similar things with acoustic Analytics
I'm listening for the sounds that are normal
Knowing if a machine is about to
Break a bearing filling is in a house
Brookneal glass broke
Siamese
Actually break into something like that
Anything we can do that sort of listens and understands acoustic data
And learn from that what
Things are good or bad
And then knowing what to do with those moments and we do similar things with boys
Personality assessment
Damn I tell you a lot about the feedback of your customers or how people are feeling in an elevator we find it all that unstructured data
Really lends itself to these cities Learning System
Just go there cuz you brought up a cyst
Should I talk to all kinds of assistance in my home I talk to companies who are trying to bring
Voice assistant to the Enterprise it feels like
This should be a perfect place for Watson or the Watson technology
It isn't I never people do not talk about Watson
In that sense so
Should they be or is Watson something else
Now they should be and they are but you'll often see that we're the technology inside a lot of things
So that makes it harder
I also think that the consumer
Excitement and energy around assistance you can buy in a store and bring it to your house
Is very very high and it sucks a lot of the energy on conversation
It's on a bad thing because I think it's also
Created
A level of comfort
That voice interaction and assistants are part of our lives
You said you have many in your house I have
One of everything
More than one of everything
In my house also and
I like their differences
Different things
Maybe I'm working early adopter but I think for all of us we're going to realize that there's going to be
You know the systems and different places we're going to be more comfortable working with them everywhere
Because I couldn't be good at something
Will IBM we bring a watch in a natural language and Enzo amore
Deeper view of understanding people
Dental assistants that were doing in hotels in concierge and
In various settings and you'll see much more of it in a publicly
The programme call with Watson that has watching embedded in things
You'll even see if you go to the weather company app we have watching embedded down the weather at 4
But consumers were introducing more and more
Dialogue-driven insightful Services even into the weather company
This is something that
That we felt that we could bring a dialogue and
And engaging kind of service with Watson
Get a consumer that we can do it in cars we can do it in hotels other places so we're working with clients all around the world
To bring
A deeper understanding of people
Using watching in those settings
And we also obviously do it in the Enterprise at so you won't see
The same level of
Chatter
About what we're doing in the Enterprise
But watching has a rich set of engagements across almost every into
We talked so much about the cognitive era
And
1 things I like this
The thought that
This is not
A passing thing
It's one of those things that a eyes now and see using the way we work
The systems we use where you can comfortable with Chad and the faces
Half the time you talk to somebody internet you don't even know if it's a real person or or chatbot or something else helping you
We're getting used to it this is the beginning of an era
More so than a passing technology face
Go smart phone may come and go
I don't know
Come and go
But cognition and these are things going to be with us for a very long time only improving over
Alright so we talked a little bit about assistance
Watson
As an assist
Just in general
Where do you think all of this is heading
These voice-activated assistant
Throughout my home
I think we're moving from a place where people were doing fairly difficult home automation stuff
If you were using you know hubs and things and setting up rules and stand
Very complicated for most people in early adopters did it and everybody else looks at it like it's a bunch of wires and
And scary stuff
But I think we're moving to a point where assistants are trainable
I already use if this then that
With several assistance where I can create my own custom dialog and words and
And stop doing people come over you know I can say hello Stacy and Stacy it's been a long time since I've seen you
It feels as if you're understood
I think it's just an illusion
But it's the beginning I think of the expectation people have cuz I tried that recently
That someone come over and you look very nice today
They looked all around where's the camera
How did how did that sting on my desk know they look nice today
And then they wanted to answer
That didn't have a response
But I think
We leap
To wanting to be understood
So
Quickly
That if anything can understand us
Really understand how we feel build respond more dynamically
We embrace it
And I think that's it that's where the future is headed is much more of these assistants and interactive capabilities that
We will Embrace as an extension of the family
How many people do you know have a Roomba
Annabelle is how many of them named it
IWatch
I think she will get very comfortable with this idea there's something they're taking care of them listening to them understanding
I got a bunch of experiments in my own house that that replicate the feeling of that
And I'm amazed how quickly even non-technical people
Yeah kind of excited about it
This idea is
Device has been and what I want
Before I
Absolutely why should you have to ask to turn on down your lights when you come downstairs
Your home should turn your lights on for you it should say good morning Stacy it's nice to see you it's going to rain today don't forget your umbrella
Your car is low on gas
Not all at once
You should get it should understand you and the state of your home and where you are where you're going and
Offer things rather than waiting for you to keep asking
Lights turn to Blue unlock front door start car you shouldn't have to say all this
How far away are we
Something like that
Could happen faster than we think just as the smartphone became
Something that we
People embraced much quicker than we expected cuz it's basically a computer in people's pockets I mean it was a time when that sounded ridiculous
And now not having one's ridiculous
I think we're only a few years away from from having a much more Interactive
Home Hotel car environment that is
Proactive
And anticipates our needs and suggest things at the right time and
Feels like an extension
BB do
Not
Sucking it in
It's invasive and not something that is going to have to ask for all the commands to
So how do we get to that point cuz right now stand
I always thought his inconsistent
And the thing standing in the way worse things like the expensive getting these devices in
And Holmes the lack of standardization
Concerns about privacy
And I don't even think we'd actually solve the UI challenge
We also need to know like
Who's wearing a home and getting some of that information out
So
Are these that
Metal water bottle pieces
But it is kind of cascading now
What started out as
Would really like to have it like that was in every science fiction movie for the last 30 years
And yet
We didn't have anything in our home
Back to us
Now there's millions of people who do
You know you can buy at any store
I could do some very very basic things
So we suddenly now have these endpoints
It will be more cuz every company is working on some
Level of end point whether it's cars in
Places
I will be able to at least have a thing to talk to
But they're not generally very smart yet
They're more like a mobile app for The Voice
Instead of an actually understand
But that's coming through all kinds of different work we've got some really cool work around modeling a people we did it
Starting fruit from work on Aging in place
Helping people to live better and safer in their home instead of going into
I'm Healthcare
Facility
We started building models of people understanding the better think so we're trying to extend that into some of those
Solutions
Can I see other companies building voice recognition so that they know who's speaking to it
Icsolutions around proximity to know based on a mobile device you have who's closest
Might be the one talking
Together since it might be issuing a command
So it's kind of all the parallel I think it's just a matter of
Building up critical mass
Some of these Technologies and enough
Microphone
Speaker kind of interfaces in people's lives at the Comfort levels are high
Incremental cost is low
The cloud services are very very expensive
To deliver this
They just require some Innovation some companies to really step forward and take
A little bit of risk
Introducing the new technology
All right and what I think about these
In this future
I think about the Amazon Echo
Google home
Atlas Siri
What's wrong in there
Apple
I don't think so where is Watson
Well watches working with the consumer electronics companies around the world as well as
No cars and then
Telco providers in others
So you'll see us maybe you'll see it so differently than you might see others
Don't this is a rule for all of us in this and I think for companies that are trying to deliver deeper engagement between their products
And users
Just keep those and watching don't exist
Did any of the others
But I'm also pleased that there's others out there because they're also bringing the ecosystem of developers to bring me a comfort level with
Voice interface is there helping Drive improvements
Just if nothing else to do
Competitiveness
In speech to text
Which basically hasn't changed much for most people you know in decades and suddenly now has improved dramatically because of
Competition
Machine learning volumes of users things like that so
I think you'll see watching in many
Things you buy that directly engage with consumers where
Engagement is the value proposition
Car manufacturers in others
And you'll see home assistance whether it's Google or Amazon or others I'll be seeing lots of homes
I'm hoping there's some
Emerging standard to happen here I'm still have yet to see it that would allow application developers to build things that are fixed
Environment
So I still have yet to see
That kind of sanitization occur which is what happened in
Open HTML in
Job and everything else for Bixby to build for one web server move to another I think eventually you'll see
Expertise and skills and applications in a voice interface be a little less
Stuck in an ecosystem in more open so we're obviously aiming for openness
And I'd like to see iot devices be
As open as possible how they integrate
And which I'm seeing through
Things like asking others that are not tight anyone
Tickler system
All right Brett thank you so much for
You're very welcome cuz you talking to Stacy as always
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more
Aot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
Come
Will see you next week