Welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and Jericho host
Kevin tofel
And today we have
A happy thanks
Giving show for you guys this is only
4 people in the US
If you're not in the US you're not celebrating
Thanksgiving but I'm going to wish you a happy
Or podcasting
So I hope you're eating
Wherever You Are
All right
We have got an amazing chauffeur
This is episode 191 of the
Cast ready to be talked about Lowe's selling its Iris business
Apple buying a
Smart Home
Hub business
We're going to be talking about Black Friday
Slickdeals
We've got a bunch of news associated with
Amazon digital assistant
Other news associated with Google's digital assistant
And a new smart home security device
Plus
A new LG smart
Display
Out in the park
We're also going to be hearing from our sponsor bitdefender about
Crazy printers
And how they're not secure
Aunt
Our Guest this week is Mike
Nelson
Who works for cyber security firm
But who is coming to us talking about his role as the father
I'm a diabetic daughter
And what iot device
Security for medical devices means
To him
So it's a really great show
I hope you guys enjoy it
Let's Get It Started With a message
From another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is
Cognizant
With demanding customers at the center of today's value chain delivering engaging products and experiences
Even more important
Cognizant a global leader in business and IT services helps companies engage
Customers
By envisioning Innovative products and experiences
Or inventing disruptive new business
Models with those insights cognizant collaborates with clients to build smart products
Disruptive strategies
A new ways of engaging customers across every channel that uses the power of
Iot
Learn more about cognizant Scioto services and solutions
Atkinson. Com
/ coyote
Okay Kevin
Let's talk about
Lowe's and this is kind of crazy because we actually had
Someone calling into the show and asking about
What was happening with Lowe's Iris business this was their smart home business that they started in 2012
So way back in the early days
I guess the Resurgence of the Smart Home
Automation
This was a platform
Designed solely for the retailer and the
All kinds of zigbee and Z-Wave
Compliance sensors
That works with the
And those actually charged a monitoring
C4
The devices
It actually had a battery it had
Cellular connectivity if you needed it
But
I don't think it did so well because on its earnings call this week
Louis said that they were going to is part of a decision to
Close 20 US dollars
27 Canadian store
They also said they were going to exit
They're alacrity renovation services and they're
Iris smart home biz
And as part of that smart home business
And the alacrity renovation Services they're taking a 14 million dollar right
That which is not a terribly large amount of money in the grand scheme of things
Furloughs but
Regardless I agree with your comment
You said you don't think
Set the iris platform League
Tidwell least relatively speaking
It started out in an era
DIY stuff
But it had a service component
People did not want to pay a subscription cost associated with
That was the biggest complaint
I had and they also weren't going
To support
Other devices so they had a whole brand of
Lose
But when it launched it didn't support
Anything else
And I think that's the bigger
Challenger problem with
The whole strategy that they put into place because
Weconomy
Tell me the past two to three years of very siloed
Closed
Smart Home
Ecosystem
Too much more open when you look at
Are digital assistants
How many Brands and devices that work with
Example and granted voice assistance
You know just a user interface
To get things working
So that's not
Truly smart home to me
But I think yeah
Keeping it close the way they did was definitely not the right approach
So just to be clear even though they're exiting the Smart Home
Iris smart home business
They will still sell Iris
Devices which I'm not sure
Why but
That's irrelevant
They will also still sell other Smart Home Products at Lowe's it's not like
When they say exiting
The business will still be able to
Purchased
Very smart home devices in fact I think 6 weeks ago or so on the podcast I talked about
Healthy store-within-a-store at my local Lowe's and I
Presume
I know a lot of other people see them as well
Were there filled with
Smart home devices such as there was
From Google
Amazon
Venezuela's
Nest
Who else received
Phillips and Samsung all
It's just
I guess this herbicide they're kind of getting out of
Yes and owning their own
Makes a ton of sense
So I will say
Lowe's header
PR reached out to us and she did say
This is important
It for now
They don't have timing or additional details to share
It remains business as usual
There are no changes
Hello support of the brand product or service as we search
For a buyer
That's really important to know
Because right now your stuff is still going to work
Depending on who buys it though
Who knows
It's a
So there we go that's the
I guess that's the big Smart Home
And kind of a sad
Close to this
Dussehra I guess I mean if we think about it Staples
Did they launch their own platform they got out of the business Best Buy had
Pete they got out of the business
Now we got
I can't think of anybody who's got anything now
We're kind of you said you know when Iris came out with more than do it yourself kind of
Era
And to some degree that era still exist but this is
Alexa Smart Home
I don't say too. Oh I'd rather stay 1.1 at the step forward from then
Where
You got very capable major
Platforms that are mostly open
Pumpkin is the one I would say is not
As open obviously because it only works with iOS devices and such
But
I wouldn't want to be in the business of
Creating
Servicing or owning another platform right
Me either
Okay
Let's talk about
Another acquisition in
This is being portrayed in the media as an AI aqua
Position which I think speaks more to the idea of what's hot
Right now but this is Apple buying silk labs and
This was reported in the information
And
When I saw it I was like Silk
Glasses in an AI think they be too smart
And they did it was founded by Andreia skull
The former CTO
Mozilla
And we actually had him on the show
Episode 46 so way back
Early 2016
Talking about
They built
A hub
It was a hub to Showcase his ideas about building smart
AI services
Respected
Privacy
And
You know I have thought this
Company had died
Because a lot of these smart home
I guess we're going to do this were amazing and then
2 years later you check back in there like
Nowhere to be found
Yeah that's because they actually started with a Kickstarter project I remember seeing the
Small little Hub box with this curved front and a
A camera inside it
Zuri
I love Space Odyssey
Space
It was like super curved
Yeah yeah
Anyway it's not that it was even
Are there a closed system because I think it worked with just Wi-Fi and Bluetooth devices
Words with ya Sonos at work with smart light
Yeah
And a couple of other
Non lighting device
They just never really took off in
They cancel the product
Josh Maybe
Actually the same year that the kickstarter
Yes
Remember
To developing AI software so that's kind of
Probably where the AI Bixby
Comes in as well
Sew in
The key Focus I would say on this is they had no image recognition
We're doing a lot of things
They can play your music based on your taste
The idea was all of this would stay on advice it wouldn't go to the cloud except for
Key things that
You know you might want
Hey the picture of the guy who is breaking into your house you might
Want to keep that in the cloud
So
The whole end
And when stuff was sepsis
Cloud it was an anime
And that was actually very unusual
In 2016 so that focus on privacy is
Hollywood app
Is after
Being able to make
A smarter home experience or smarter
Overalls
User experience
Without
Having to break it
What is now a differentiating stamps are
Privacy and secure
Yeah and if you have
Time
I would say go hit the silk Labs website while it is still up cuz
With the Apple acquisition I don't know that it will be at much longer
Because you can get a good
I feel for what apples
Getting out of this
Basically went still pivot in 2016
It was a way to a Bergen
A table
Cognition for any device
But you make will bring a smart so you bring a device
Best Buy
And there's a lot of interesting information
Cool go check it out
Hopefully screenshotted Kevin
Okay we are in the midst of
What I'm no longer going to call black fur
Because you know I've been getting deals all week
Sorry to call this Black Friday week
Now
And I just want to let everyone know that if you are in the park
First smart home device
Spice they're actually really amazing
Deals I would say
A lot of things you shouldn't buy on Black Friday
We're going to just kind of a little bit
But a lot of the smart home stuff is really
I'm telling I'm not going to run through
Too much everything that
We looked at was on sale and what we looked at were products that we talked about the past
Approximately
Just purchased ourselves
Heather Holmes
And these are like Kino $5 off some of these are 50 or more dollars
Whatever the devices
Yeah so if you are in the market and
I will give a plug for this this week in the iot newsletter
Stacey on iot
We are going to be sharing our list of
10 connect
2 gadgets that
We think make good gifts
And some of them are for the
Your parents
Chefs your industrial iot designer there's some weird ones on there
Any other list
Because of Who We Are
So you can sign up for the newsletter or you can see it
But
A lot of those things are going to be on sale so yeah
Go out and get your hip you're on the fence
You like me to buy it this is actually really good time of year to buy your smart
It my thought is if you had
Smart home items that you were thinking about buying
We're just holding off
I'd say pull the trigger now
You know
Do it and then when you have questions you can call us and ask us
All right
Let's get into some big news for
Batam
Padme is what we call Amazon's digital assist
So we don't set off
All of yours
So
Couple news items biggest one probably this week was
We now have matinee on Bluetooth headset
Watches
All kinds of other things which is
Basically way to
Bring Padme to everything
Yeah this is and all the technical details are on it
The developer blog over at Amazon
They talk about their
Madden 18 mobile
Accessory kit
Which at first we were like is that Hardware but it's not
We dug around it's basically a list of
Hardware requirements for you to
Actually build in this protocol and service
So that pretty much any Bluetooth device that meets the requirements
Can take advantage of this
So call, actually as a reference design of
Headphones for developer you can Tinker with these but $300 so I wouldn't do
And what do we mean like so
Are you guys here
What does this mean it means that you
Could you know if your watch has Bluetooth
Andis
And sports at basic
You could be like madam
Unlock my door
And then you have to give your PIN so that's a terrible example but better be
Turn off my lights
And you would say that your watch and it would happen
You can do it on your headphones you can be like
Oh
Add dog bones to my shopping list
And some headphone manufacturers have already integrated
Madam a so this may just be how they used it I don't know but this
Again opens up the doors to
Any device maker that meets the hardware requirements their device Mason
It is neat how they implemented this because you don't have to have a device that has always on listening
Have that obviously listening for the Wake word
But if you want to save battery life as a device maker you can use the
The push-to-talk implementation as well
Got it in that makes the Tennyson
That's because sometimes you're like oh man
I don't even change the battery on this thing on
It's kind of like the tap
Okay
So that's out there look for that I will say from my perspective
Amazon is just
Helen it
When it comes to
Creating a really compelling voice plan
Smart Home
For everyday use
I mean it is doing what
I really
A company like apple to
The apple is totally behind on
Bringing this everywhere like
This is kind of like apples mfi program
Rambler it's. Criteria for what you need
To work with it
It's trying to
Ring battlebay everywhere but do it in a way that
As long as you meet these criteria
You can do it so
You know there's a number of reasons they're killing it can I totally agree with you
I just found one out last week one of probably many
You may have seen her
Everybody else did
Do you know how many people that Amazon has working on the mat amazed
Oh my gosh no I don't
As a lot of people
I do not recall or I read that but I
Hot it last week and it just blew my mind
That is a lot of people okay yeah
That would do it so
More
Mattamy news
Kevin
You're going to love it let's just let you talk about it
Yes yes I'm so excited so
If regular listeners recall
I bought
The vector robot made by Anki
And I did that there kickstarter's I got a small discount
And we love
Can I use very animated
Heroes around is autonomous so he gets bored if he's just sitting his cradle is charger it'll just go out and play with his
Bluetooth Cube and what not and we can have them do some fun things
Kind of limited sofa
However
I have seen a video
Of the neck
Speak feature that factor is getting
And he's getting it in a couple weeks
And that is integrated math
And I love it so far based on the video
It's very responsive it's very quick
It literally you don't and you don't have to say hey Vector like you normally would to wake the robot up and do stuff
You just say hey matinee
And then you see her little icon show up on his face and
Ask her whatever turn lights off get me the weather do this
And she does it
I am super impressed by how it looks so far
Cannot wait until it comes out
Yes and I'll just give you guys one of our
10 items that are gift guide is the
Because
I think we're saying is for the kid or the kid in you
And and and
Come back to the Black Friday deals
You can actually get the vector less than I paid for
As a won the first Kickstarter
Packers I paid 199 he normally goes
For 249
It's 179 right now
Oh my gosh
Stop on that because that is actually a really
I have a cosmo
In I thought it was adorable
And fun but it was not as capable
And now I'm like
I have I have
Okay
One final bit of Madame a news
This is pretty esoteric but where you throw it out there
Now
Madam
Can power on devices in low-power mode so this is like your TVs are
What not if they're in low power
You can
Speak directly to them and they will turn
It's called Wake On LAN controller
If you want to Google that and
Figure out the details but I thought it might be interesting for low-powered sensor
Because these are things that are in sleep mode a lot of the time
And
Now
Yeah man Jamaican basically wake them up
And get
Details of something that's happening
Right now a lot of time with
Low-powered sensors that will send the details to the cloud and Madame a will look
State
And be like I would like 20 minutes ago and reported this was the state but now you could actually
Get it to wake it up directly
And get the state
Which might make sense for something like a something open or closed at the moment
Or something like
Detection if you suspect a week and you don't want to get up off
Off the couch to check it out you should be like meme anime
Yeah it'll be interesting to see who implements this and what devices because her now
Amazon work with three partners and got some very low hanging fruit in the
Television market with
Vizio LG and I sense they're all going to get this feature in the neck
Next couple months I be rolling out
And yeah TVs are often in the low-power state and so you just send him a little packet over the
Wi-Fi network wake him up and then you can
Do whatever you need to do but yeah sensors and other things
Curious to see who implementation
Yeah that's just me talking
Find a little bit of Matt of a news there is now Skype calling on Madam Ave Bay show this off
Actually back in set
September 3rd
Massive
Unveiling of so much stuff
So this is just saying it's now out there
If I were at home with my mattimeo
Kevin but you know
For anybody who's using Skype
Yay
Alright now let's move on to Google Assistant
Because
It's an interesting tie up with
Siri
Kevin try this out so Kevin what do you think
Yeah I mean
So you can now
Include
Google Assistant the app
A pin
Siri shortcuts
Which sounds great
The implementation is very much like the way
Microsoft
Implemented Madam and Cortana where you ask a boy
Assistant
Tarasca Voice Assistant something
And that's what we have here so I did set this up
When I say am I
Song I'm sorry if I wait anybody's iPhone
When I say hey Siri
She will start listening and I say
OK Google
And it opens up the assistant app and Google starts listening
So it's kind of a shortcut to a shortcut
IOS users
I can't really do much more unfortunately but
It's there
It gets you to Google
It doesn't get you faster it get you their hands
It's free because right now you can't
Actually haven't always listening OK Google kind of thing on iOS what I do is I take the assistant
Widget for those who
Play with iOS and I
Just put the assistant widget on my widget screen on my phone
Flashlight over and
Tap the microphone button
And that opens assistant this is hands-free though
So that's what you would do if you were
To get somebody who could actually answer your question
I'm waiting for somebody to
Do assistant to an assistant to an assistant
And I mean that sporadic
Okay GS
What should we call Siri
Should we come up with a name for that
Guy sending your suggestion
Maybe we'll take a
Lady s
Too close to matamata
I don't know
Let's talk about Google Chrome
A snooze at Canal sync music
With home speakers
Switch
Yeah but that's just a little thick
Some of these are like little
I'm like yeah that's
It's handy
We like it
I don't know what else to say about that
You got anything else to say about that you can do as you can
TVs and speakers together in audio group
Ipso
If you're playing say something on your Android TV or on
On your Chromecast audio wise you can have it strange about the house now which is kind of nice so yeah it's just another way.
Movies that music round
Who that music
Alright Google cloud iot and microchip
Actually security to
Microcontroller switch
Yay there's a lot of
In the space
Without Microsoft doing some cool stuff with
They're Azure sphere product and what is Google doing
So they have
Partnered with
Microchip
Which is a company while it is also a thing is
Company
They've created the
Avri otwg development board and all those things actually mean something
IRT obviously
We know what that means WG stance
4 Wi-Fi
Google so this
Is a cloud connected 8-bit
Microcontroller development board
That is connected to the Google
Cloud platform
It's a $29 devoted small it's not super powerful but it does have
Connectivity to the cloud and they want to help jump-start
Cloud-based or Google cloud based out of
So can I look at another developer
And it died is that it will
Securely
Back to the cloud
Easier you see these all the
I mean like
Every microcontroller in a lot of things
Sancerre like arm-based chips and even some Intel stuff for iot
Usually have some
Option to link directly to
Big clouds azure
Google or Amazon
And actually you see them with
Alibaba
And I do as well
So
Yeah two little interesting bits about this
They have a co-processor on there it's a
Cryptographic coprocessor
Trusted and protected identity for each device
So you can have Sakura indication
Medicine
And the devices are pre-registered on Google Cloud iot
So you can
Get them out in the world with zero touch
Auditioning
Yeah that is very cool that is all part of
So sweet
Okay
Moving into cool gadgets that you may or may not want to buy
Abood
Has a new smart home security device
Called iota
And this is
Edible mix
A really compelling
Sensor
The sensor and hub kit
DIY
Home Security
This is a
You know what the closest thing I can think of is kind of like a
It's got a camera and it is
Github sensors
You can add other Abode sensors to this
It comes with optional
Cellular backup and
Connection plan
So
Security device is to
Mexican
Black Friday pricing if you want to put it with a
Connectivity plan that's going to be
That's your 4G connect
Searching for backup and that includes
Yes
For one year
The cool thing about the Iota is it's going to have
Sea waves
Zigbee connectivity
Camera that's 1080p
And
Again integrated backup with 6 hours of battery life
If you want it
I mean their stuff is their original dear is
And this will also can
Next back to their original
Kirra swell
It is very much like
The canary I think which is what I have
Is part of the
Yeah this whole security
Like I feel like we are
I'm surprised we haven't gone further
Better yet but there's been like
Security has often been thought of
I need a sensor
This is open is closed but
Comedies like Piper
Troll
Sucked into
Walmart.com
Canary and now this our
Can I get a little bit at a different way they're like
Pictures one or two devices you put around your house
Activity sensors
Camera and they like listen for Stuff
It's different
And it's wrong and then let you know
And that also included there as the echo
Guard
Vanguard versus can I listen for breaking glass and such
I forgot about that yes
Which if you have an echo it's going to get that but no extra
So
And I think a smart
I think that's a better way to
So that's just
So that's out there if you're into that
And you want a different type of home security or if you got a boat stuff and you want
The camera functionality
Answer
Okay other things that are out
That we care about
Kevin a new smart display
It is a
Yes Google Assistant
Built-in so it is a
Smart display similar to the
JBL and Villanova once that
I've been out for
Couple months we both have the
Lenovo
And this is from LG
It's the xboom AI thinq you smart display how much longer they can make that name I
Don't know but
It's very similar to the existing ones in the market so assistant is built it and it's got a built-in
Camera for video calls which
They also comfortable Google home hub is not headache
Russell
Just worth a mention as a difference
Chromecast built-in it's got an HD touchscreen Bluetooth streaming support I think the
Big thing here for LG
Stephanie not design it kind of looks like a tissue box on its side to me but
That's beside the point
Pictures of two big speakers
With Meridian Audio zedvance
Technology so
Probably a better speaker than some of the other ones that are on
On the market it's normally prices brand new
29999 for an 8in display in those speakers
However
Since they just launched it they've got a promotional price of 199
So that's where the Boom
Comes in I'm guessing
The High Castle
Cuz I'm telling you it's a tissue box on its side
Piano speakers
They're not the fanciest design
The bamboo backing
I think I like mine more than you like
You do love yours I mean I like that
I love my
Sister watches TV on it all day long
Kevin's going to be in Byron
That's my
Prediction
All right
So
That's pretty much what we got
But we have an awesome voice mail that ties actually into
Holidays
Because
Well loving father who wants to outfit his daughters new
Iot stuff on the iot podcast listener hotline
Which by the way is brought to you
Bye
Slade
Don't miss your chance to win
Schlage connect smart deadbolt
Which is now zigbee certified with Amazon key compatibility
You can upgrade your smart home with a safety Simplicity and style of
Schlage
3 enter to win this awesome connected
Lock and it really is
An awesome well-built
All you have to do is call us at 512-6223
742 4
And leave us a question
Automatically be entered
We are closing out the November drawing
End of November November 30th
At midnight Eastern Time
So call us before then and you will be
Automatically
Enter to win this Schlage connect smart deadbolt
Okay and now
Let's hear from
Scott
Play Kevin and Stacy this is Scott from
Cincinnati
I am interested in getting
My daughters
Started in home
One has an apartment one has a condo and was looking for the best
To get them started
They're not programmers are do-it-yourselfers
I just want something that they can
Shut up and
Basically forgot about
We have a lot of Apple equipment
But I'm
Insurance that
That's for The Voice automation they would
Caesar phone
Tablet
And they don't always have those
Listed in your ID
What would be a good
System or young people in their first
Apartment or condo
Thanks for your help
Looking forward to hearing your ass
Oh Scott you are a good dad
And I don't know how much money you want to spend so where
We're going to go all the way in
We really could okay the first thing that we think
You should buy regardless of what kind of digital assistant you might have for your child
Or children rather
Is
A canary
We just talk about
Despite it is a really awesome security system is
It's great for renters you just pop it in there you could have
The camera facing the front door
The cool thing is it not only has the camera it has all these sensors that
I can tell you what's going on
House even
When they're not there
And so you can see like oh
There's a weird noises
Maybe it's not a Robert
Maybe it's your dog going
I don't know but you'll know about it
Which is kind of nice
And it is
The canary right now how much is
So now is the time to get a canary because they are
Free
With a membership
Yep and I should tell you that I do pay for a membership on my canary Goodwin or is it
All of them
Wow
So I have the $170 all in one
That's the camera and the climate monitor that you are
Alerting to but they do have just a regular camera only without the sensors 99
Endoflex
Is 199 that's an indoor outdoor
They probably don't need a secondary camera but if they do
So right now they're all free with the membership
Holy cow
Go get to one for each of your daughter
Okay did you have reduced prices if you don't want to
Hey you know the service fee and
Salon so I think they're all
$50 the all-in-one is $50 off the view is just the camera that's $50 off
Endoflex is $30
And you pay for the subscription and you find it worthwhile
I do although most of the alerts motion detection and the snapshots of what's going on my house are my dog running around
I'll be in class and my Apple watch will buzz in the middle fast
There is normally around the house
And
In case you're wondering
The
Terry has home kits
But it also has
Limited Google in Amazon
So what it does is it can tell you like
The temperature but right now it doesn't give you
Visual displays for
However Canary says that
Basically
They're working on
They are talking to Google and
Amazon about
Deeper integration
Mary
But for now they support
Mattamy on the Echo Show and spot for displays
And Google Assistant
Google home
But not with the display
There you go
So that'll keep the daughters
Safer
What can I do for
I don't know seeing in the dark
Seeing in the dark
I like that
Lady
We decided that
We didn't want to
Send you down the Hub
So
We are going to recommend you by the
Tp-link
Casa that's Casa with a k
Smart Wi-Fi
LED bulbs
I am going with
I kind of want colors for them because they're
Post-college
Just having some colors is kind of nice but if you just want to if you want to get to
Japan CD
Dimmable are tunable White
Range from about
$20 to about $30 depending on if you want dimmable or tunable White
So
Those are
They're good lights
They work with Google Assistant they work with Madam a don't work with homekit
So
Keep that in mind a couple bulbs there
In their lives or in their fixtures
Define the downside is
They will have to leave their light switches on all the time and if the power goes out
In their homes then
Yeah the lights
Lizard like the downsides
If they have homekit
Probably would
Say maybe the life
Text bulbs
Yeah but they're super expensive soap
Yes indeed so there you go and then we also
It'd be nice and
For them to be able to connect there
Devices
But we haven't actually talked about it
Mitchell sister
I don't recommend Siri
You're fine with that
So I would go with either of Google assistant or madam
I would recommend on the cheaper end with a display the Google home hub
That is the brand new
Tom Hudson Google branded smart display
Google branded smart display right now it is
$99
Black Friday
Normally it's about a hunter
$50
So that's one option the other option is going with the Madam a universe and in that case you
Who would get probably an echo.
Unless you wanted to go all fancy and get an Echo Show with this player and Echo spot
What's the display I would just do it.
Honestly
Yeah unless they're going to listen to music then maybe get
The full-sized Echo
There you go with the second gen II
Which is very nice so
Those two and now that you've got those
Bunch of picture ecosystem
How do you say
Give them away to make their television
Smart because they can build these routines around stuff like
Movie time
Impress their friends
Lights dimming
TV turns on to Netflix
So for that you're either going to go with a Chromecast.
Like 35
If you're in the Google world or an Amazon fire
TV stick
Anime inside
That's about 25 bucks so
But that in and you should be able
Control your television using those options
If you wanted retained
Neutrality
I have a $99 Logitech
Harmony home hub
And that also
Covers things like
Speakers
If they have external
Speaker smatswich
So it's like it's on the basics and it's not terribly
It is not you got television lighting security
And a digital assistant
Which you know and if you want to throw in some spots
Spark plugs
They range from
Ridiculously cheap like right now for Black Friday Amazon has their smart plug for like
Like five bucks extra with
If you buy a.
Warren Echo thing
Otherwise it's $25 and for any Google related smart plug
You can go with WeMo or the tp-link
Casa Sol
That get you started
And hopefully your daughters will open those
Love them
And feel safe secure
And
And they they can't even communicate with each other
Using the smart speakers because there's calling built-in a boat that
Yes unless you get one the anime version
The other the Google version
...
So don't do that don't do that
Just get your whole family sucked in on one device
All right and all of those can move with them and their systems that
Ingrosso
That's
Apples for long time to come
If they want
All right
That concludes this portion of the show
And if you stay tuned you're going to hear about
I will
Printers with malware
And
Diabetes
How The Internet of Things is changing
Care for diabetes and also
Why security is becoming so
In medical
All devices
So stay tuned for all of this and we'll see you next week
Hey everybody we're taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Fender and I have
Alex Gallant Whois
Chief security researcher at bitdefender
You're just talk to us
About printers
Alex
Statistics from about 2000
Defender box units running in North America show that
Half of iot Gadget
Identified as
Had a weak password
This could indicate that owners never bothered
Factory access
Or they just chose a really bad
But really
How much damage could a printer do
Access
Wow
So it sounds like someone
Could use this printer
Privacy how could that have
This is why we're actually
Unsecured
You should probably get
Scary so what can I use or do if they discover that
Best and want to secure their printer
First of all
Especially
Make sure.
Awesome so where can I go to find out more about bitdefender
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Mike
Nelson
How are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm great
Thank you thanks for having me
I'm super glad you're going to be on the show
Because you have a job
Will probably
Touch on a little bit
What is a talk about using
Two devices
Which
It feels like a really big opportunity
Talk to us first a little bit about your history
With a disease
Absolutely I'm excited
Discussion with CIA I was like nah
With type 1 diabetes at the age of
So I've had it for
Coming on 24 years
And it's been amazing to see the evolution of treatment I mean what I was diagnosed
I had to poke my finger and weights
45 seconds
To get a glucose reading that I have
How to take a shot
Insulin about 45 minutes
Before I ate the lobby on set
And today
You compare that to the technology and the benefits of
Evolution that's happened
Today I
Get a glucose reading from a sensor that sits on my arm every 5 minutes
High insulin
Also this thing
Dramatic improvements in the info and then I can take a shot right before I have to leave
And the insulin gets into my system and
Becomes active right away so just a dramatic
Change org last 24 years
And the technology is doing a lot of things to make the management of diabetes
Much easier
Awesome in
For your parents when you are 16
Imagine that's a really overwhelming
Like oh you got it
Be responsive
For the 16 year old boy
Maybe amazing
That's a lot. So what kind of tracking
Was in place
What was your life
It really wasn't for my parents
Terrifying
I think that a remarkable job
Responsible
Stay on top of my blood sugar
You're not really responsible but you're getting into that age
Encourage me to
Weather I was playing sports
Make sure I check my blood sugar still there if I was
Sleepover at my friend's house to make sure I check my blood sugar before I went to bed and making sure that wasn't dropped
But the truth is they had
No way of knowing and
The technology is such
Today where
You know I travel to work
Regularly
And I wear this
Continuous glucose monitor that has a Bluetooth connection to my mobile device Linux
Cloud and I can share my what's
Sugar levels with
My wife so what I'm traveling with my blood sugar
Drop some middle of the night
She'll get him noticed
Call the hotel
Help me get
The attention that I need
The Peace of Mind
It comes from that connectivity has been just like janky
All right and now
As a parent unfortunately
You have a lot more experience nausea
I just personally but
With your daughter
She is also been diagnosed with
Type wooden actually
Before we get to this we should talk to
Skip a little bit about
Type 1 vs Type
Type 2 diabetes
Yeso type 1
Pretty easy
Type 1 is a disease where the pancreas actually completely stops working
It's an autoimmune
Disease that's caused by your body attacking the pancreas
Your body just stopped
Producing insulin completely
Type 2 is typically triggered by
Whether it's obesity or women during pregnancy
But it's where the pancreas
What's effective
And there are oral meds
We taking
Treat that whereas with type 1 insulin injections
Are required
The pancreas
Completely stops working because the body attacks it whereas with type 2 it's just
The pancreas can't keep up with the needs that your body has
Okay and when there's a problem like when there's too little sugar or too much
Can really injure yourself in both case
Fall unconscious and
Yes
If you were to take too much insulin what happens if
Please let me know some of your listeners may have felt a big workout you get a little bit light-headed a little
That's typically symptoms of low blood sugar
And your body does a really good job naturally regulated
Because your pancreas only releases
As much in Salinas
But with diabetes
You have to act as your own thing
What type 1 diabetes
And so you have to know how much insulin
Put into your system so if you put in too much
And then you don't eat enough.
Cover the amount of insulin that you've taken it could be catastrophic
It can put you into what's called a diabetic
Tacoma where you lose consciousness
It could become very damaging
Okay so just not till like belabor the point here but this is something that
Is really
Tough to manage
It requires
Paying attention to a lot of
Different Factor
And
Consequences are pretty dire so
Your daughter
She is
Yes to turn 4 this year
And renamed
Olivia
She is just
The sweetest little girl
Last year's a little over a year ago she was
3 I was out of work
Scrapping
I got a call from my wife
15 minutes
What are the signs
Type 1 diabetes
Did you try to actually your body's natural
Responses to try
Watch the sugars out of your system
So you get really thirsty and try to consume a lot of water to try to
Disperse the sugars that she was having that symptom in my wife called and said
Yes I took him to the doctor in my heart
Knowing what
The Simpsons aren't you know I hope for the best but
Probably the worst
4 blood sugar
I was really high and so we kind of self-diagnose training took her into
The doctor and they confirmed that
She was a type 1 diabetic
And so what does that mean
For a child
What does that mean you have to
Just start doing
Yasso
Diabetics require insulin
Before every meal
Olivia and myself
Take the right amount of insulin discovered
Food that we're going to eat
And so my
Sweet little four-year-old
We started by doing a finger poke and she's now emerging is now using connected technology so she no longer has
Fingerpoke switches
Been amazing
But we look at her blood sugar and see where she is and based on the readings that week at we will administer a certain amount of
Going to try to keep her blood sugar in the right range
Cancel
We do that and then it's
Continuous monitoring
She goes to school
Season preschool and so when she goes to school we send her a little meter with her
So that we at all times have connections we know what her blood sugar is at all times
A friend's house
When he goes to tumbling we send her little meter with her
And it gives us the Peace of Mind
Shandong time
What her blood sugar is and so
Still outside from the
Insulin injections and
That it really is a disease that you just have to monitor
And you have to pay attention to and do the right things to keep your blood sugar in the right range
Okay in Fright now there are lots of options out there I know that
They're definitely
Connected options out there that
Let you monitor your own
Or someone else
Is blood sugar
Surely not
Basically
And then there is a whole subset
Parents
Some people out there
Together their own devices to do this
Talk to us about the options that are out there
What kind
Factors you think about is
Yeah so you don't from me it's really just
Knowing that all times when her sugar is
And
The fact that I could put my phone down right now Stacey
And pull up and see where her blood sugar is
Is
Dutch I can't tell you
Peace of mind that I can't visit
I didn't have that she goes
Tumbling if she goes to a friend's house or she goes to
Glucose reaction and she goes low
Jenna Bentley could pass out and nobody would know what's going on
And so having that
Data in front of us
The track it at all times and it's not just there but it my phone will start beeping at me
If your blood sugar starts dropping
How to quickly and so it's almost a preventative way to
Channing Frye
Extract
Continuous glucose monitors are a great
Innovation
Aside from glucose monitors and I think that's the most
Exciting innovation
But I've seen them last 20 years the next is really what's happening with
Insulin pumps right now
Insulin pumps have been
You wearing like a pager on your belt and you program the amount of insulin that you need and it administers it through it
Tube disconnected in your belly at all times
And
Insulin pump
But insulin pumps now are starting to develop
Where
They have the capability
When your blood sugar starts to go up
The insulin pump is smart enough to
Send a text that and start to
Administer insulin
True
A connection that has with the glucose monitor
So
Glucose monitor in addition to sending the reading to my phone
It also send it
The pump
And the pump
Reads that and then makes a decision based on the levels
And can help you
Self correct
To keep you in the right range and it's just amazing technology
And you know
Benefits
Open up the madness that disease with those types of technology is just
Awesome
It's probably comforting to have this level of data
Available to you
You on your phone
Are there things that you
Are concerned about Earth
You're kind of like
Who did this
Yeah that's a great question
Everytime I pull up my phone and I look at is glucose reading
In the back of my head
Because of what I do
Professionally I think
Integrity
Is that accurate
Inaccurate Stacy as if
Glucose reading
Comes to my phone and it says
Their blood sugar is really a hundred and I administer
Her insulin based on that reading
That event
Can be catastrophic
Utilizing glucose monitor
That's my boy
Integrity
Data
And making sure that the readings that I'm getting
Valid and so that when I
Creeper and give her the insulin it's going to be the right
Right so that data doesn't get up
Go to the cloud and then
And somehow get sent to the wrong
Play Store
Your data is mixed up or anything like that
Yeah or a man-in-the-middle attack
Of course somebody manipulates the data and you know it ends up with an incorrect value
Cast true crime stories I can see these now
Okay
And I can't even really rely on my
Home automation systems to work in concert like
That's so I still have problems making sure that when I
Leave my house
Lights actually turn on
Like they're supposed to after 7
So the idea of relying
Something for
Your safety and your daughter say
Especially
That feels very fraught
So
How do you evaluate
Disease are connected Prada
Yours connected to the internet or do they have a cloud connection
They have a clock next
Bluetooth
Amanda wifi-connected
Okay so you are the head of iot security attack
Company called digits
So it's not like you're
Not like your normal person running through life
How do you evaluate the
Security of the state
Yeah you know
Consider myself a unique consumer in that regard where
I don't think most consumers when you go and buy these devices are thinking about
The security posture of them
And if they're vulnerable to malware or man
Getting in and taking control of the device
Have to worry about that
I'll tell you the story I mean I went in
When my daughter was diagnosed
They require diabetics
Go to the hospital and they get the blood sugar under
Education
Medical devices
Some of which I
Had Direct knowledge of Canada security posturing what they're doing and you know it occurred to me how
Personal
Spices can become for consumers very rapidly
And
You know I've been working to solve these challenges
4 years
In my profession
It all
Different vertical
And all the sudden I was hit with this
It's very personal dilemma
Mike Ashley
What if something were to happen to this device while my daughter
Let's get control of that infusion pump
Edward to manipulate the amount of
Trucks that is being administered
Those things in the results of those kitty cats
So as a consumer I tried to take a deep breath
And say I don't believe that their malicious actors in This Hospital
Daughter
And even though I know the security vulnerabilities in this device
Had to take a deep breath and say you know I don't think the rest
Because of a lot of
Factors
But those risks
Depending on
This circumstance
Risks
Can be real and so it's consumers I think education and under
10 things that they can do with personal device
Good password crack
Making sure that
Hardcore
Credentials
Part of devices are you know those types of things
I think education is important
But ultimately Stacy I really think that the furred needs to be on the manufacturer
I don't think when
You are to take your kid to a hospital or what I took Olivia
I don't think I should have to ask hey is the device
Connecting two
That's being used to treat her is that at
Secure device
What doctors would look at you like you're crazy
Yeah most doctors wouldn't even be able to know
I mean maybe like
Yeah there's no way they would install
I believe it's consumers we have the right to assume
Security and safety
And if that
Security and safety isn't better than manufacturer
Just need to act responsibly
To get into a place where they are secure and safe
Sure know let's talk about is a consumer not just in the
Hospital but when purchasing
Insulin pumps
And glucose monitors
Continuous glucose monitors for your daughter
Did you
Were there lots of options I mean
Prescription device so unlike Could you actually
Legitimately
Security
Yeah
You can I don't think most consumers
Can I mean you can call the company and you could ask
And they could tell you about the different types
Communication
Protocols in what they're doing
Data is being encrypted
You have to get the right person on the phone on the other end
Yes
Cuz I can tell you I talk to people all the time and I'll ask these questions
And they're like
I don't know
It typically takes a couple phone calls to get connected to the right person
I do believe that that's going to be
Become more transparent
I think that manufactures and we see this manufacturer
Starting to disclose the things that they're doing around data encryption
Hostler practices those are two that are really low-hanging fruit
But you know I think consumers need to be aware of those and
Either go to the website to look to see if they say anything about it
Or ask a question
I'll tell you the Food and Drug Administration FDA
Is getting stronger and stronger on there
Requirements
Connected devices
It's because of some of the exploit for the Papas
And so I think the FDA is
Working really hard
To provide assurance
That
I talked about that consumers should know that these devices are safe and I think the FDA is working really hard
Figure out
What mechanisms they can put in place
Attest
Send checks to make sure that the connected devices are going on in the market
What kind of messaging
How do you think
Manufacturers
Start trying
Bay what is really complicated
To Consumers
Like is it like a Good Housekeeping seal if
Approval
Some people talk about
Nutrition label for data security
I really don't know it all seems kind of dumb
Yeah it is
Heard a lot of discussions around what
Spam and really there's no
Clear I would not say that there's any
Strong evolution
On a medical device
Is the stamp
Safety that people are looking for but challenges a lot of
Devices that work
Approved by the FDA 5 years ago are now getting hacked and so
I think devices that have been cleared in the last
Couple years have a lot better
Security protection than one
Five or ten years ago that they still being used
Hospital
Okay I'm going to put my faith in the FDA
Meanwhile
You can put your faith in
Globally
And that team bear that just working on medical device security I think they're demonstrating
Four other regulatory bodies in other countries to follow
Excellent and
There is really nothing more personal than
Hearing about
Your story or
Water store
Clearly people's lives at stake
It's worth it
Okay
What makes thank you so much
For coming on the show this
Hey Stacey think so much
It's an important topic and I appreciate you giving attention
Thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week