Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And today we have as always
Boy howdy is getting good
We got news from it
We've got some Amazon Echo Integrations worth talking about and
I'm going to do a little
The wrif on light switches
My God
Exactly
Is Michael Bell the CEO of Silver Springs who's going to talk about
Smart grid and what we can expect
Our Generation and our utilities in the future
And we have a message from our sponsor Arris
But first
Let's go to a message from another one of our sponsors to sponsor is be smart Kitchen Summit it is the old
Only event of its kind of tackle the future of food cooking and the kitchen with decision-makers and disruptors across food
Cooking appliance retail and Technology there two full days of content discussions networking and
And product showcases the 2017 Smart Kitchen Summit will be held in Seattle on October 10th through
I will be their listeners can use the code Stacy that's Spacey
25% discount on the tickets at www.dot smart Kitchen Summit. Com
Let me know
We can meet up
Okay
Kevin
Let's get started shall we start with Google or should we just start with something
Easy like Ikea
I kind of feel like we should start with Google because the last
Show we did we recorded a couple hours before the Google IO Keynote
And there's so much stuff
That was discussed
There was
First
Let's get
Your disclosure
Oh yes I work for Google as a full-time consultant not in there
Anything related to its smart home or iot or anything like that
Syria
Now we know Kevin
You get my honest opinion
How old is so honest
Are you going back that should tell you everything
At the
Keynote
With Sundar pichai and
The assorted cast
Google favorites
There was a lot of people who are like
That is true
I didn't think it was
Cuz there was a new
Processing unit
Really nothing gets me more excited than chips
So
Custom architecture
Fight for our audience
I went through and watched a lot of B
Presentations after
Edwards
I said I was super excited
This show is all about
Contacts so last year Google was all about artificial intelligence
And how that was going to be the foundation
For everything that Google does
This year they put that to work
In ways that are pretty compelling so the idea is when you have Computing everywhere
And we as mere humans are like
Well
How can we interact with this stuff without giving complex commands
Things without screens
The answer to that is
How did the computers figure out where you are or what you're most likely to do in that situation and then
Present a more limited kind of choice.
Is that a fair way of saying huge
I think it's a fair way saying that and I think
There were people that thought though
Keynote in the show itself was kind of boring because there were no devices and what those people I think have forgotten is that it's a devel
Ella prevention
Granted there have been new products released at Google IO in the past
But like you said this was really all about
Advancing the contacts that type of information right place right time
Kind of thing and
That's
Ingested
The future sokolov you were like other showing as a future that's always right around the corner
You got to start somewhere you know when you got to you got to put the platforms out there for the developers to take advantage of
In a sense they actually did really quite a bit so on a smartphone
I got really excited because they
Talk about how you can build apps easily
For Google Assistant
Which is the brains behind your phone it's
It might be in your car and it is most importantly the brains inside your Google home
A speaker that competes with the Amazon Echo
What they've done
Apparently
They've created
Smart home apps
Which is on the actions on Google platform
Going to be a lot of words about to happen
Actions on Google is
The
It's the platform for building
Things for the
Google Assistant
Basically
Short version of this is hey it's really easy now to build
Google
Home app
Creations
And they said they
Have now 70
App integration so if you go to devices for your Google home you're going to see a lot more stuff and he said that in the last 6 weeks most
Those were at
Which is amazing
So
Right now the Amazon Echo has over 10000 skills
Like / 200
20 of them are smart home related
And what I'm saying is like they're not there yet
But holy cow
They just need a really easy to do it
And they have
Nothing about this is
They've done it a couple different ways so they've got
Your device types
They got their overall structure
We just kind of like
What is this stick out the room they think of it in three ways so structure room into ice
Room is
A label you put on your device
And it knows what devices
In the quilting is
Devices are basically device schemas
So
What words will
Change this aspect
I said has trades that has state it has all of this information
And they got stuff for that already for lights
Thermostat
Cats and they're going to be adding a whole lot
Hopefully for locks too cuz I still can't see my locking
Google assist
Oh yeah you can
Isaac
Like I know
I asked the echo all the time and then
Same here
So this is really cool I really highly recommend you go check this out and
If your developer trying to build this stuff because it it almost looks so easy like I could do it
But probably not
And other nice thing is it's super easy to do this
But they also require you to send them a device but
Prove your
Integration and that's great cuz they're going to do
Lots of testing there testing for latency
Adjusting that works
And that can be kind of like a certified
Vacation
Program there
So
It's not just two apps it's actually bring assistant putting assistant invoices third-party devices
So yes
Status status
What I was taught
But yes
That is also a thing they talked about you want to talk about that
Google Assistant SDK in other devices
I didn't watch
No I don't want
I didn't I didn't have to I was working during the
I did not see that
I just knew about
Guess
So yes
Much like Amazon
Adesa KC
Plus they actually have done something with their microphones
So they have a hardware reference design so you can build your own
Echo like device
Google has
Beliefs and SDK so you can put Google Assistant
Other things
Thanks right
There was a lot about
Android
And I'm still actually thinking about some of this and I'd love to talk.
People so if you're working with Android pay
Come tell me
What you think
Because my goodness
There was a lot
And I
I didn't know if I should be excited about this
Or if it was just another kind of
Bifurcated universe that I don't really want to
Google home cuz it's like we will work with everything
Even they are not Android
Although Android things does seem to offer some
Ankle supports
Nice secure
Dirty stuff
And speaking of Google home working with
Lots of things Google Assistant did come to IOS as had been rumored
That was announced and launched a Tayo
So
Get an iPhone
Have you can use Google Assistant with your school and I don't know if you saw this but just some basic updates to home
Itself
Calendar appointments reminders
A proactive notifications are coming
Also interesting because we just talked about it for a week or two ago hands-free calls with Google home similar to what they are
Echo is doing
But like this
But I was going to save I think but better some could you could you could argue against that there's Simplicity in a
Echo to Echo
Video or voice call I get that
It's different than a phone call which Google home actually will do it will place a phone call
Hands-free to any of your contacts and you can choose to actually have your phone number
Sean today
Person before they pick up so you don't have to do that but that's always nice as well so
I would say it's better but
I don't know
No I I saw that and
That's way cooler
I thought so end
You know how the Amazons Fire TV
Platform if you have a
How to hook up to a TV and you use the voice search features
It shows you cards on the screen
Assistant will do that on your TV with Chromecast later this year they're going to visual responses
So if you say what's the weather and it can actually show you the the weather cards on your
Screen via Chromecast
The Google home voice
Calling is
Later this year to
You are correct it's not
Out yet I think they showed it off
And some of the limitations it's going to be in the US or Canada
No cost
But you're right it in the coming months I'm looking at the official blog post now
Okay I was like
I don't
I don't have it
Yeah. We like to try the echo calling
But you're right
That's coming
In
When the rumors happened with the Echo Show
Which is the
The video
Touch screen screen
I said
I'm not super excited about
I bought one but I would be more excited if my echo screen
My Amazon Amazon released an echo
It had contextual awareness and sent
Data instead of to a dedicated screen
To the nearest or most appropriate screening
House in a way that's kind of what Google did
So like if you ask it for
Commute times it will actually end you can or directions to a place
You can tell it to send it to
Your phone
NFL
Which is
And same thing with the
Sending stuff to your TV
You can tell it to send it to your teeth
So it's not as automatic
Write this is bestie
And that's that's why
What I thought was super cool and super powerful
Again going back to this idea of context the Google home device can recognize up to six different voices
It's so when I tell it to call Mom
It's going to call my mom from my
When my husband says call
It's going to do something to
That is the kind of
Powerful interactions that we're going to need and that's all based on
Having
Contextual ability that they showed
This is the world guys that we
Waiting for
This is the world
You and I and many listed my family see that's the whole thing if I
Thinking about getting a Google
What you described I think is an awesome feature that multiple people can recognize
But nobody will talk anything in my house
Except for me
So
It seems like a waste
You have it you have it
Teenage daughter
White
He's in college so yeah he's he comes and goes but yeah
Nobody talks anything
That doesn't the voice recognition is really good it's not that good yet
It doesn't
Recognize wolf wolf
No
It's probably for the
Although I wonder I wonder what the the shortcuts feature in Google Assistant I wonder if I could
Train it to Tucson
Let's talk about shortcuts
Yeah it's funny because
One of our listeners
Forwarded you I think the this information
And shame on me because I saw it about
Maybe week ago week and a half ago and I neglected to mention it
Yeah this is
But yeah it was the middle of May
This actually showed up and assistant I don't remember a blog post or any news about it but
Basically if you do have the assistant app and you open it up
If you go into your settings
You can actually see a bunch of options in there the bottom option for me anyways
Shortcuts
And what you can do is create what it says
But you crave faster easy ways to do your favorite things
And make a bunch of recommendations
Hilton already and I like you can say stock update
And
You would literally tell
Google what to do with a certain should do if you see a stock update to it
In this case
Talk to CNBC about the markets
So it's it's Ukraine custom shortcuts and actions for those shortcuts so
I haven't used it yet
I don't have a home and I hadn't sought to do it in my system now
Halibut actually you could for four like voice commands to your
Your phone too
Hi I just realized
So when this arrived I had broken my phone
So I haven't tried it
It out yet
Because I guess I should have downloaded I'm using an iPhone instead of my Android phone
But since I'm only using it for a couple days I did not download
All of my hundred and something out apps
So
I'm looking at the default
Shortcut examples that they give and maybe this is how I get my girls to start talking or something because they are
There always been watching Gilmore Girls I don't know why but they do
And one of the shortcuts in here is you know what to do and the action is
Start watching Gilmore Girls on Netflix on the TV
Yeah so it's kind of it look
Looks like a cut
The powerful
Malmo stringify app
Yeah
Exactly what I was thinking
Example that Derek sent us was now he is asked it to
Stop saying ask
Harmony
To Transit that's not Logitech Harmony to turn on the
MattyB
Sorry to change the volume
So now he can just say
Turn down the TV
Turn down TV
And
Turn down TV volume and all these other great things
Looks like he
Traded
Multiple ways to say it
To turn the volume down and
Cuz that's how you you
Usually asked
It's too loud is usually what happens
But there's a shortcut it's too loud
There you go
So I had to play with this once I get my
Exciting things will happen if I may have to get a Google home after all this now
Well you don't maybe you wait till
Maybe I don't
I'm not a waiter
Now you know again I feel like you should just be able to cruise through the Google offices
I see air fresheners all over there yeah
Now that's an interesting idea those in office environments
I'm like that's that's a little
All right that's for the recognition of his speaking really comes into play otherwise you'll be running in the Halls setting up everybody
Google home
Google
My bad
Hopefully because it was whispered and because it didn't finish
And I can do that to you
Other things so that's that's a lot of
La Taqueria
Let's move to
Ikea
Yes
Google and we were so excited about Ikea and there's more
Chad fee
I was wondering how you say it
Oh did you not listen to my Ikea home dude
I'm sorry I didn't
Stratford
That's the we also learned on that show that
They sell
2.9 Million
All today
Oh yeah
Tell me the biggest seller
Probably
Those products are going to work with
Gosh everything
If you don't talk to it it's going to work with it
So Echo
Are we should say
Before you ask that question
If you have Google assistant on your iPhone
You cannot talk to yourself without talking to
Siri
You just have to
That is correct
That is correct so you can't
Unlike an Android phone where you could set it that always be listening for the hot word and
You know hands-free all day long
You got to actually open that that's correct
I'm still Pro using
Echo and Google home over the
Cat stuff I have
TNN alot of the news of
Assistant
Coming iOS came out
I saw on a lot of
Sites that cover Apple stuff
I told her negativity that I
It's not going to be
It's not native you have to open it
You know it's not going to sauna catch on
I begged a differ because
If you look at what Google photos has accomplished on iOS in 2 years
I think it's is a 500 million users and like 1.2 billion photos a day
A lot of them from IOS I mean
I don't see it as a barrier
But we'll see
Well end
It's a great way to try it out and I think if you really like it and you want an always-on out
$129 which is
Cost of the Google home
That's not
Crazy
Especially if you've already linked stuff to your
Right right right
So you were going to say something
I was going to ask you a question
How is this going to work with homekit is homekit certified
Well
It must have
A special chip inside saucer chip
I don't recall seeing
On the
The device has a
That's where I'm going I don't
This just seems like this week news that I would be leading with this product if that was the case and yet
I'm not saying that
Any homekit device
Should have on the back of sticker that has like the little homekit logo and a number and that's what you used to actually hook it up
Wi-Fi network
Alright so
I don't have a truck for you
Because Ikea is like an hour away from me and I haven't gotten out there yet
To pick one up
You don't look on the back of yours if you have one and
If you do then sure as homekit certified
I don't know Kevin
I'm at a loss I mean I rather
Official press release and then they allude to working but they say that it's going to work with the home app is going to work with Siri and they say
Home cats
But it's other
The wording is just odd to me
I just wonder are they going to have some kind of bridge device
Coming later
You know I'm a big
I felt so much better
Once I bought the
Are actually Lutron sent me a smart
Home their Bridge which is at
Think $80
Cuz I had I have all these Lutron lights in
Having the bridge makes me feel like
They're very serious despite having a really awesome proprietary protocol about integrating with other products
So once I bought that I was like sweet now I can buy a whole bunch more Lutron lights
So that's just by thinking
So if I was going to go all in
Platform that wasn't using Wi-Fi or
Bluetooth
Having that bridge I feel gives me a lot of
No it's okay I mean this but this is why I prefer like Wi-Fi and Bluetooth on other devices you know
Yeah. I just gravitate towards them because I don't want
Bridges in the hub center lappin
Totally understand I'm really thinking they're going to offer some kind of bridge products by I just not clear
But coming this summer or Autumn Place
You'll be able to do this
Alright so other immigration
The Amazon Echo
What is kinetic energy
Dish
I thought this was cool because it's going to be this sort of thing where you say
Hey
Change the channel to ESPN
Find The Big Bang Theory
And all of this is just going to happen
If you're disgusting
I would love to see
Every
Provider like Comcast has their Xfinity home and they have a speaking remote where you can talk to the remote and do this
Supposed to the echo
Why not
I think I should I should play a little bit more with the Nvidia Shield
Android TV that I use I don't use the voice kids
Well yeah sure I don't use the voice capabilities and part of the reason I bought it was because they were going to offer
They still plan to
A shield spot
$50 mic
Earphone
That basically let you talk to it like you talk to a Google home and then
Would interact
The TV
I just don't know if they're TV controls yet for any of that
So
I should
Does the Nvidia Shield
Well I don't know if I don't have a good one
I don't know what the remote itself has a microphone on it
Oh yeah that it does
Yeah yeah sure so I should use it more
To do list
Okay
Let's see
What else do l
If this then that
Every time I say that I do a mental
It's his lunch it's
Megaplex
And they were sponsoring the show a couple weeks ago and I actually used to make a platform to create the
Internet of Things podcast channel on if
Which
If you guys don't know
Is
Available to you and you can get
Things like
Save my articles on Stacey on iot
Or
You no send me send me a notification when
I think I have my lights hurting
Red in my living room window podcast publishes
Fun things
It's like it's like a red alert
Siri
Your podcast is life
I know
You know sometimes I don't
Question is always
Publish
There we go now we're thinking
And my hope is I'm trying to figure out how to
Launch a channel that actually will send you a notification if I mention in the tags a certain
Hair product
Which everybody who's like
I really want to listen to it when you talk about you know
These light switches cuz he's are what I have in my house
Then that would be good for you
That was like a little ad within the show sorry I'll but
Ifft
Is doing its own maker Channel and this is kind of cool because a couple
Well I was a year ago a while back that they took out the ability to like
Publicly share
Applets that
Yeah late last year I think it was
Disappointed cuz I I
Stop
Hey don't bother me I'm making Annapolis
They took that away but now
New capabilities that used to be that you could only like tie two things together right which is fun
Yay
But now you can build applets with multiple actions
Turnt
And that's actually pretty exciting cuz you can do some of the
Some of the more
I don't know
When this happens turn off the lights and do this
So
That's going to be fun
Will be playing with that
And
One other feature that's probably interesting to you guys is you cannot create a tablets that work on any connected device
Even if you don't own it
So
It used to be that you had to link your device before you
Create an applet for it
Which
Sense but sometimes your wife you want to expect like for this show for example
We want to experiment with
Can I possibly do this if so I'd like to buy this device right
And so
This lets you see all the triggers and
Play with the
Full Outlet before you actually maybe go out and buy a device
You can see it it works for you
Can you actually test without device or no
It can run it
If it's like
Yeah
But it's nice because there a couple times when I'm like
Oh I'm looking for a particular trigger like one
Popular thing that I like is I have a netatmo
Camera
And I can use that to see it recognizes people
Because it recognizes people
I was hoping to build something that was like basically
If you see the following people
Do this action
Right or if you haven't it more and more
Reliably I want to do if you haven't seen
The following
That wasn't actually a trigger
So that netatmo has it
Gift
Immigration
But it didn't actually include people recognition is what
By the trigger so it's like
Hummer
But I would have been able
Will see that nessus
All right
That
Is that
And
If you make something really cool
A big name brand might pick up your applet and showcase it on there
Hey make something for the iot podcast
Maybe I'll publish that
Hey hey hey
That's about it on the issue
I don't know I feel like we've done
Hutong a good show today
Lots of news lots of nudity
Leinenkugel Lodge
WeMo dimmer Wi-Fi light switch
It is
Pretty
But it's $80
Which is a life coach
Especially because I had just tested the Leviton
Wi-Fi light switch
Which was
I think it's like
It ranges between 45 and
$50 and that is both
Google home and Amazon Echo capable and it's got dimming functionality just like
This is why I go bulbs every chance I get not switches
Switch off I know you are
All right we're going to argue about that next show
Because I have his massive mapping projects where I'm actually swapping out lots of light switches
So
Real talk about what that means
And how much that costs
And either time or dollars
After that our guest
Michael Bell CEO Silver Springs
Who is going to talk about
The smart grid
And they have over 25 million devices
Added to their net worth
Which is a lot
Hey everybody we're taking a quick break in The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Eros and I have Evan whitelock who's a product marketing manager at Eros
How to talk to us about iot and Healthcare so Evan what is aris doing in health
As a connectivity been a connectivity management provider what we're really providing to a lot of customers that are there
New solution providers that are entering into the healthcare space are really how to fold I think
The first is at 4 customers that today have an unconnected product will there be
A sleep apnea machine or in-home medical device
They're moving from an unconnected product
QA connected service adding extra value of that service
Enable them to increase their revenue from the devices that are already selling
One of the challenges there is to keep those operational costs as low as possible
Given this new connectivity that there including into their product so the tools it
Customers are leveraging from our connectivity management platform really help them bring their operational costs to level to the lowest
Possible to ensure that
The margin that they're gaining from the other revenue on these new recurring Services it is great as possible and then second
We look Beyond into the larger scope of the iot world in and where these Solutions
Can become ocean pack for
We have a lot of partners that are working to bring Advanced Healthcare Solutions into the maybe some of the underdeveloped
Parts of the world for example sweet scent is a customer of ours
It is leveraging our Global connectivity to bring Water Treatment Solutions
Various parts of the world specifically in
In underdeveloped areas where
Where water quality is a very very large issue
I think when we look at what I can do for the healthcare space specifically it opens up exponential advancement
In-N-Out only the efficiency of Healthcare systems for example reference the ability to provide a connected Home Health Care
Solution for patients with chronic conditions can actually have a device that that allows them to communicate directly with their health care provide
Lighter instead of having to schedule trips and leave the house and oftentimes for patients with disabilities or chronic conditions that's amaze
Adopting iot by making it connected solution
They're able to provide a much more efficient solution for that customer I think what it also does is it enables healthcare provider
Riders equipment manufacturers to move from just selling Hardware to a recurring Revenue model opening up a
Brand new Revenue stream for their services that they provide what are the most rapidly growing markets
Beyond health care we see tremendous growth still in in the automotive Market even though that's been one of the drivers for
Form a society adoption with connected cars and consumer Automotive but as we moving towards a more autonomous
The world which is one of the buzzword there that's why we've invested a lot into the bleeding edge of autonomous and consumer
Technology but even beyond that we see a large possibility just about every vertical for every device that's previously been
Non-connected possibilities are really endless there for a Wiens who historically provided non-connected products to move
Toys that are connected world
If I want to learn more Evan
Where should I go
You should definitely head to our website eros.com that's a e r i s.com podcast
Hey everyone welcome back to the
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host and today's guest is Mike Bell the CEO and president
End of Silver Spring Networks
Hi Mike how are you doing
Free Stacy how about yourself I am super well and I am excited to talk to you today about
The smart grid
Smart Energy
And
How you guys
Because you've been doing Smart Energy for so long
Are more like
A top industrial iot company
This is the case you're going to try to make and you're also going to tell me about
Energy generator
Nothing too hard
Alright so let's get started you guys have been doing this for a while and you told me you now have 25 million devices
In the field
Which is crazy
That's a lot
Absolutely
Cisco's predictions for Lake Tahoe
Exactly
Take me through kind of because this is I think a really good microcosm for iot
And where it can take
The rest of the world
Give me energy mark
Can you take me through what it was like in the late 90s then smartcric came out and then
Tell me where were
Mercury little people think about smart. And they're like oh you know you read my meter for me in
I sure that that's
Probably where it started you know it's it's easier to automate meter reading than sending armies of people on the field and
You can argue that it
Who's better for the consumer it was better for the
Utilities because it took
It made the process easy and it took you know trucks off the road and that was great
The really we're headed I can't imagine a modern utility right now
Without having a smartphone implementation I mean it would be like the Stone Age because
It's going so beyond your once-a-month reading meter
I mean if you live in a part of the country
It gets hot and experiences brownouts aureus
You live in a part of the country with bad weather I mean right now the smart grid is responsible
Keeping your lights on when things happen
Or keeping your lights on when
Electricity demand get so high to the otherwise
The blackout
Areas
Modern utility lives and dies by the data they get off their smart grid Network and that's how they're able to function
It's such a complex environment we have including things like
Micro generation from solar and other things in Electra
Vehicle charging I mean
Utilities have a really
How to deal with a lot of stuff since you know even even the past 20 years I'd say their job
Keeping the lights on has become more and more
Complex
As we've added a lot of these new technologies
To what was otherwise a pretty stable kind of business for a hundred years
So
If I'm a utility and I'm looking at I'm using more of my data and my deploy more sensors like
It used to be smart meter
2 point x end
Now what are they playing
Wait a second
Yeah you know it's actually a couple things
So it turns out that your your smart meter is actually a sensory know and it and knows all the other information
And it's kind of like your people talk about crowdsourcing so I'll call it crowdsourcing for meters
When you're able to take a look
Look at the data coming off
Thousands or millions of beaters you can put together some really interesting information so you can tell whether you're properly balancing
Voltage across your distribution area
You can tell if there are trees on the line but they're about to take out the power lines
Ephrata area
You can't even tell
If the electric socket it's somebody's house is something
Call the hot socket so corrosion build up over time
Resistance goes up in Franklin you can actually have a fire because of the socket being dirty Based on data coming from the meat
Either you can actually tell us a problem
On top of that you can
Deploy other sensors
To take a look at it other areas of the grading and something even worse.
Mating
Call distribution automation we're essentially tell you this big electric grid and a storm happens that takes out part of the grid
The reason your lights flicker and come back on is
The electricity
Rerouted in a minute
Instant
The smart grid technology does
Only read your meter and tells you when things are going to go bad and by the way when storms happen
3 is what actually helps
All right but this is still despite the intelligence that is being deployed
Utility Networks
It's still a really tough business maybe a little bit boring how can this kind of intelligence start helping
Utilities maybe add new Services is that something they're interested in
Yeah you don't think so our Utility Partners
It turns out that they really do want to help the consumer figure out how to save energy although you know what that makes them look crazy but
They really do they really treat
Customers more as consumers and not repairs
So Princeton utility customers
Instead of reading
Kneaders once a month
15 minute turns out if you read the meter frequently enough there are a few startups out there they can take
Look at that data
And tell you exactly what's running in your house
So why your bill so high
So you
Call up your local utility and say in a why is my bill is $1,000 this month
If they've done the right thing with a smart meter they can say what with your permission I'll tell you why
And they can go in and say well
It looks like you have a old
Refrigerator from the 1960s
Someplace in your house and it looks like it uses about $250 worth of electricity a month
Spelling Magic
Promise of service marketing
People look like in that big data
It's real you know there's there's actually something if you have enough of this kind of day that you can
You can do things for the
Server that the same like that
So let's talk about demand response because this is an area that I think there's
I live in Austin so Texas has its own utility grid so worried of a special special
Case
It gets really hot
And
There plenty of times in the Summer where you know my Nest thermostat on eco B thermostat is low
Hey guess what
Utility is like
We're going to turn you up a notch
And I'm thinking about places where
God how can we make that
I don't know
Better more efficient
Maybe less disruptive cuz I notice
Almost immediately when my AC goes off at 4
You know summer day when it's a hundred and ten degree
But maybe I wouldn't notice like my water he
Shut off my dryer
For your pool pump
Silver Spring I demand response has always been an important part of what we've done and there's there's two really interesting things
News about it as you mentioned right the ideas that you shave off
Why is it important while the first thing is because
It's tops potentially up
Rolling blackout right
The other thing which is kind of cool For Those About to work in this space is
One of our big customers is Oklahoma Gas & Electric
Are they little they have the same issue gets really hot everybody comes home before they turn the record
Turn the air conditioner on
Quantify
They've been able to quantify that they have avoided building two new power plants by implementing grandeur
Cedar Point
There's no reason actually why you couldn't hook up
The same technology to a pool pump or to a hot water heater and in fact
It's one of the things we're advocating we could easily put this technology on your hot water heater or your pool pump it really just
Takes a utility to say hey we want to go do
Okay I was going to say how did what do we need to do to make this real because I had it you know
I Dubai
Do I need to buy connected washing machines or
Take me through the largest energy consuming products in a home
Tell pool pump Maybe
Yep pool pump you up to some extent washer and dryer that person hot water heater
Here for the most part it depends what you have gas or electric
But yes that's released a lot of electricity
Yo it's interesting so
The reasons man response is usually done with the thermostat is because it
Easy to talk to the thermostat
The thermostat controls
Thing that uses electricity
As you say if you had something like a pool pump or another device like a washing machine or something
You would have to actually you know have some way to control that but honestly
Technologies come to the point where you can pretty easily build a little box it's not that expensive that you know plugs in between
Device of the electric grid and that we turn it on and off
It's not really a matter of Technology at this point it's really a matter of just
Wanting to do it
Is it worth doing I mean
Obviously turning off my lights
Sephora
Even if they're on
Probably
Machiavelli Deez Nuts
In the fancy
Exactly so it's something like that or is it
Will you know I tell you
Certainly if if you live in one of those affected areas you are remembering in California some years back when you're having rolling blackouts rolling brownouts off
Samurai
Technology
Yeah I think
I think it all depends if you take a look at that return it's a lot cheaper to roll something like this out than it is to build a power plant
Okay
And let's let's talk about two other challenge
Just that I can think of
1 is
Microgeneration oral
You know my solar panels on my roof
But if I did
Excited
How should we see like solar is becoming so cheap now
Now it's awesome
Jeff when we get more of this sign
How should we think about
How we've architected our Energy System
Cuz now it's like push out to the home as opposed to like the homes pushing up and maybe this isn't a deal I don't know
It's interesting solar generation in general is this points most
Presents the same sort of issues to it to utility reverse that they were talking about with the mannerist
Because imagine is safe
Sear in Hawaii
Crazy penetration
Every day at UNO
7:40
3 the Sun goes behind a volcano and
It's like a light switch shopping so you have
All of this energy is being put on the grid solar power plants are kind of idling
Literally it's like somebody flipped a nice switch boom it's gone demand suddenly spikes
And suddenly that utility has to figure out how to jam enough
Energy generation from traditional sources of the grid
To prevent blackouts
Spell
Take a look at the kind of Technology we provide you know you could imagine a case where
Utility says I know that
Time
Today because we know what it is
A sense of going to happen
We will gracefully
Turn off some of people solar so it stops
Putting stuff on the grid
Double ramp up our production at a reasonable pace
So there's if not like this race
To see if you're under the grid fast enough to go get blackout so
Really you need a smart grid to manage the sources said his back for the same reason you viewing is smart grid
To manage the number of EV Chargers there going to be put on the grid over the next 5-10 years because those
Considerably more electricity
Send
That was my next question for you so I don't
Like 2 years ago I had
Power plant manager for Austin Energy
On my show and we talked about the coming EV electric vehicle crisis
And so
How does
Having
Connected
Utility
Help with that
Mitigate some of that
Yes it was so having a connected utilities
EV charging
Really there are a couple ways to look at it the first one is
Able to quantify having the Chargers be connected
You know when they're coming on and off
So that the utility can
Balance the voltage or wrap up the power delivery or what have you
Is required to really provide
Seymour service
The people going to expect
But frankly there are places in here in the United States a lot of them
Set the current design really just
Going to handle the fact that you went over your neighbors
How would he be charged with it everyday at 6 you get on at home
Unplugging your supercharger and suddenly you know the demand
The Roots
I would argue that there probably in order to
Balance disease the needs of
All TVs that are becoming online or the next few years you're going to need to have these Chargers
Be smarter
It's height
Utilities
So that they can make sure that everyone gets their fair share of electricity and it doesn't create
Sir problems nearly tries to charge their car
What else do we need cuz you need more than just a smart grid
Or connectivity on the grid in these sensors
Or smart Chargers you also need some machine learning algorithms to understand
Habits
You need probably some business rules put in place so
Consumer can override it let's go beyond just
Activity on the grill
Utility used to work with us now they're all at the Silver Spring Network and the smart meter is in the
And the ways
Did the censors of quantify what's happening
The fascinating thing to me is you know everybody that there are two big buzzwords
These days right internet of things and Big Data
So if your Internet of Things Big Data company
You're flying high
I think there's a huge up
Opportunity
Four companies
Need to come in and apply machine learning
To the data generated by the utilities to really provide
Unique services and provide
Even services for the utilities themselves that'll really help make
He's probably just talked about much easier to deal with that I think it's a kind of a very lucrative space I think right now you know that
There are a few companies in the space but I think it's it's something that they really has been overlooked and it could be a fantastic business
For someone who
You'll has a machine learning
Algorithm
Swift's attic
Keys to apply to something good boy
Really have a pretty big impact
But utilities make pretty lame customers
Your startup because they've got these incredibly long sales cycle
Obviously very risk-averse
Because you know you don't want to mess with somebody's life
What should a startup have how should they think about trying
How to get into the space even if
If they are
Well I tell you don't like her the horror stories of the utilities
And you know how slowly move it so on and so forth I have to tell you I think many of the kill he's certainly ones we work with have gotten the relay
And
We have
We're lucky enough to win ConEd
Building New York utility for for York City
This past year
And I tell you today are really
Pulling up
For pushing us
To come up with these carsolutions I just talked about it I mean they understand that they look at all the things we just
Disgust
And understand what their customers expect and understand the challenges going forward and
The fact that you know the generation
Is goody limited so they have to do more with
With what they have
Other believers
So
I would actually say that some of the more
For looking utilities are really right for this technology and immuno
We are actively looking to work with partners
Help create solutions that we can jointly go to market with
Let's shift the conversation just a little bit and talk about
What it takes
To deliver
More than 25 million connections
In an industry that is so risk-averse and so important to like
Our economic well-being and even our physical health
Electricity is the lifeblood of Industry
How do you think about issues like security resiliency
Walk me through some of the architecture and Technology decisions you guys have made
There's a couple things about the technology Silver Spring provides if that's kind of unique
We like to talk about
If you don't even called Smart Energy these days with sparkly Because The Internet of important things
As opposed to the internet if you know connected talkin
Animatronic dogs remember people
For selling these days
When it comes to
Wake up to something like
Smart grid
Security
Is Job 1 2 3 4 and 5
Yeah you can't just put stuff out there and you know
Was it help a couple months back were a bunch of
Security cameras with half the denial-of-service attacks I mean
You can imagine if that was a smart created with just being a
It would be
You just said so
For us
Do we have built multiple layers of security and it's not just
One thing that you start with
Secure hardware and secure software then you layer on top of that encryption that you layer on top of that
Medication
From the beginning
Our entire set of Technologies has been based on
Standards-based
Things that are the same technologies that the internet
Was created on
So
You know I love the joke that the
Graveyard of networking Technologies littered with the dead bodies of people
Thought they were smarter than the internet
We've taken with all the founders of the internet for together and we have essentially
Put them together into a very reliable very
Cure
Wyteria
So not only do we have this
Security layer we also
How to apology
That is different than most people be called a mesh Network
Essentially
So unlike your your cell tower yourself at work
Result hour goes down
You lose connectivity
Our devices all talk to each other and they talk to multiple
List all the facts
Points
So is anyone touring number of them goes down
Home network
Switches over and find a different way to communicate
It's a very lowest level we have this
Picture highly
Reliable
Way of communicating
Against all completely standard space
That sounds really good and it even sounds like it might be applicable beyond the smart grid and I think you guys are working
Ninesome
Optical smart cities
I hate PetSmart in front of everything but. Where else can you take what you guys
Size of done in
Utilities
Do you think about this so we've designed this
Highly secure
Highly reliable why your area always on networking technology that connects the most critical things on earth
Why not connect everything else we've made a big push into smart lighting we have
If you go to Paris all the streetlights in Paris are controlled by our hardware and soft
Many of the boroughs in London
I'm cooking in Glasgow Bristol
Closer to home like Florida
All right I like your good
Let's talk about more goodness
Let's talk about
Actually the reason that I kind of got excited about talking to you
You guys have this really cool project town in Florida do you want to tell me a little
And I think you're referring to the story Which Wich know they love to tell which is kind of cool so they
The rolled out not only our smart Grid in our distribution Automation and
Everything else that we
We make
They rolled out our smart Street lighting
Every kind of tissue
We're apparently turtles hatch at some point of the year and
Before
We humans came around with lights the turtles hatch
See the moon and
And walk
Into the water and all would be good
And apparently what's been happening in parts
The Florida are
Turtles with hats
And see the street lights on the other side of a highway and walk across a
The end would be quite as good for them
So
You know you wouldn't put
A smart streetlight the Flaming out necessarily to
Safety rules alone chemical thing to do
Will be really expensive things
But it turns out you know one of the nice things about technology Is You U2 play a technology and then smart people kind of figure out
Really cool uses
And somebody said you know
Turtle hatching season we could turn those lights off between
Say 980m at 4 a.m.
My gosh guess what happens but Turtles don't get squashed
So again it's just one of those unintended consequences of Technology you know you you find a great use for it
And smart people will find things to make and eat
That's why I'm really optimistic about the internet
Work
All of what we're doing here is
Once you add sensors and connectivity so sensors actuators
To the world
We start looking at that data we can actually start making some
Really cool things happen.
Either one of those things so I
Yo it's it's kind of funny at the other thing FGL did I just want to make sure this way quickly you know
Hurricane Matthew hit
Karbolyn this Devastation like that
The factory of the smart grid let them get the electricity back on
Record
You look at it when you
You just talked about you know I don't know what's going to happen when you
Suddenly have enough sensors
There are two environmental sensors tell you something
When you have hundreds or maybe
Thousands because it
It's easy enough to do that
I think we're going to start seeing
Do donuts have to be just can't picture today cuz
Your people just
Can't imagine
Yet what they can do when that kind of date is available
So optimistic that the enabling technology you know iot is getting table all these things that we just can't imagine kind of like
It would smartphones were first day out
I don't think people ever imagined because ecosystem the speedometer on that
I think you're going to see even
Yoga is great that I'd argue that maybe it isn't
Critical for life I think you'll iot could actually
Improve my little baby live backup of Steel
Some of the challenges that are coming with
All right Mike
Thank you so much
For coming on the show
Anytime that's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and if you want
More iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy those things at Stacey on iot
T.com
Will see you next week