Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Eddie V extra bubbly today
Today is our what
Hundred
Apus
You know we did some digging and
We've been doing this a long time
We have we've
In fact
We'll insert right here
An example of our Show from
2 years ago
It's one of the last shows when we were the gigaom Internet of Things
Podcast
Take a moment
Hey everybody is Stacey Higginbotham
Good afternoon we should probably start by just getting it out of the way
No I haven't installed to resole the insteon system
So it's like you knew I was going to ask
It's true I like the worst most horrendous bag
Kitchen makeover going on
Are some kinds of
Craziness
All right
But now back to the present
We've got an arm report
We've got LTE
For The Internet of Things
We got things to see at mwc
We're going to talk about the problem with all female personal assistant
Maybe some Google home shopping
Connected lines with something
I also going to talk to you about my experience with orbi router because people
After all this we've got a message from our sponsor spin dance talking about voice interface
And
After that we have our guest
Who is the CEO of a company called venteon
Talking about the internet of moving
But wait
There's more here's a message from one of our sponsors
The Network's is an Enterprise internet-of-things platform that is empowering the world
Leading manufacturers by simplifying the inherent complexity of the
The iot enabling them to turn their products into smart connected systems and transforming their businesses
Game changing world of connectivity iot platform abstract the complexity of develop
Connected products
It is trusted by some of the world's leading Brands so they can focus on what they do best
The internet of things so you don't have to download the white paper 8 tips to help you accelerate
Hear iot product development at Stacey on iot. Com
That's a y l a
Well he excited
You said
It's something kind of music
It's not really on her show notes
But I have to say that
Celebration of our hundred episode
I bought my wife a gift
Actions for Valentine's Day but it works either way
And it arrives
Just yesterday actually
And she said it up this morning while I was still asleep
And
Something kind of
So I went downstairs this morning for the show before the show
I put two Toaster Strudels in there
Oh so bad but oh so good at the same time
And of course the June oven recognize their Toaster Strudels and
Coping with your professor
Better than a toaster does because
Custard never gets the Frozen middle part without burning outside
Anyway
Point has
I just
Took them out of the oven and I get a message for my wife
Just like your food is done
Menchie's
She's at work right now and this message
Came out of the blue I completely forgot that it's connected to her phone she set the whole thing up
But it freaked me out of my is she going to know every time I like cook stuff that I should be eating
Yes
Oh no where's the privacy
If I should mention that June has sponsored the show
In the past
What I purchased
I think you could probably turn some of that off
Vacations
But yes Whoever has the app on their phone
Made it so you can actually
Pair to differ
To the Jew
We just happen to have a couple of songs in
Yes Amber Alerts must be
But anyway I just thought it was hysterical.
Using it for the very first time
Amazon I got a message from my wife right before I take the very first bite
Am I substitute oh my west side
Basically I know what you're doing
Eating the forbidden fruit
Yea High
I asked my husband
Hey
How's a baked potato
Kinkos how did he
Ice cream so we'll be playing with that obviously for the next
Couple weeks
I think we're going to keep it
Alright so I have
Moving from the smartphone to the
Industrial internet
I have
An excellent survey that came out
Actually Tuesday
It's from The Economist and arm
And it's basically an index tracking how businesses are adopting
As
Little worried about indexes they can
Compare a time frame now to time frame
At some point in the past
You're measuring not based on like percentage gains but you're
Measuring based on
Games in the App
Dex from
The time before previous run the Baseline
Yes for the base that's the word
That's the word
And
What they found is
Companies adopting
The industrial internet-of-things are actually adopted
Fairly slowly
I'm slower than
So
Monastic orders
Surveyed said they strongly agree that their progress has not happened as quickly as expected
And another 33% said they some Whitaker
So only 10% said they disagreed
That their progress has been
As quickly as expect
So
That's one kind of sense
And the survey and it's 825 senior Business Leaders including
About 400 c-level executives are for
And there around the country
30% Europe 30%
America
30% nature pack
And the rest
Everywhere else
It's kind of like a smart home to me
It's going to take time for
All these different possible iot solutions
Spore Enterprises businesses small businesses Etc
Chevrolet China
Consolidate
A little bit
Has to figure out the business cases
What kind of struck me is they talked about where people were in the process like
Nonexistent in research and planning early implementation
No it was an extensive
Fermentation occur
Around the world
Companies went
From being in research to being
Planning
But in North America that actually went
Down
And that was kind of an odd mix and it could be that people have gone from
There was a lot of companies doing research and then some of them abandoned it
I did think that was an interesting finding
So
Yeah there's one other aspect all this said that
I don't think this
Survey really talks about and that is
Instrument things you Bring iot into your business
Are gathering data so that way you can make data-driven Solutions
Rap that's a lot of data
And I wonder if a lot of these companies are prepared for that that's
An integral part of the research in the planning
What are they going to make a slice and dice
You know there's so much
Beyond the actual physical iot stuff
All the data
That what are they doing with that and I think that's a big chunk of their
Time investment
Why Kevin
You are right
Because in
Questioning about which parts of their business have seen the greatest positive change
The iot
Where is percent said their data
Analysis
Pikachu
The other thing to note is the chief obstacles currently
Preventing an organization from using the
30% said it was the high cost of
Investment in
Infrastructure
The next largest
Group was concerned about security and privacy 26%
Of the respondents
Wer
Worried about
The next was the lack of Senior Management
Acknowledging
Which shows that this really in in this is true we said this before
It really does need to
Okay
So this is also a little bit industrial but still very cool
The Internet of Things is getting LTE coverage thanks to
Google and Qualcomm
And then also
New chips from Intel
So what happened this week is Intel lodged
It's called its liquid
Or it's but it's liqd
Because we're out
We're running out of owls
In The Internet of Things
And what they done is the cat carrier proof boards which means that you no longer have to if you
Use one of their boards
You don't have to go to get certification through
Carrier which is a login
It is probably less for startups
You could use it but
It's
It's any company that really just doesn't want to
Get that expertise or learn to deal with all that
Is it it's a
Process
The other cool piece of news
And we should say that
Kevin works for Google right now
Right this very second but I do not work on anything I would she related or smart home or anything like that
Specifically Android phones
Qualcomm Snapdragon
210 chip will add support for Android things
Later this year which brings it along with the raspberry
Tnxp Pico and the Intel Edison board
This is cool because this is a board that has LTE on it
Yay
So Android things now has LTE
Yeah I'm curious to see what happens with Android thinks it's a relatively new Initiative for Google Pinkalicious
A few months ago there was
Rebranded renamed relaunched
But yeah you're right it wants to compete against the Raspberry Pi and other
IRT type boards and all that but
Is Android things
Is actually an
Olestra
Metastatic
Gosh what does it mean
These are boards but they also have
Basically
Actually would be a
But but anyways
I digress
Leadership support for LTE and really help you
Connectivity challenges witch
Obviously is key for iot so
I'm very interested to see what people do with
This chip and his platform later on this year when they can do something with it
Obviously
Probably
Ideal for things that are not in the home or in
Things are on the Move Realty
Having a
Connection anywhere
Expensive things
Cameras that's a good one
I don't think you'll see it in cars
There for that but
Bring some little like smartconnect and scooters and such
Dutch oven
Sweater Segways
Well what would be really interesting
Actually is
Not LTE
Which gay
But getting something like LTE cat 1M
Or
Nb-iot Witcher
Versions of cellular radio
Cellular standards
Design for small data
Those chips are just now coming out where to see a bunch of
Congress
When that happen
A mad rush to
Cellular it all kinds of
World Congress
We got some cool news actually
Next week
Is Mobile World Congress
Congress Kevin is not going
I am not doing
So so
I found a couple things to look for we've already talked about some of the new network
The new Chips
But
There is a blockchain platform
I'm actually talk to these guys
A long time ago
But it's called iota
And basically
It is a
It's not a cryptocurrency but it's it's a distributed Ledger
Is going to allow you to
Track stuff that happens at a low
Low power low data rate
Kind of slow as soon as a result stand in terms of processing how many transactions per second
It's interesting that they
Do 7 / 2nd where they say Visa does mm
Some scalability that's got any work out there if it's going to
Really take off I think but
It's interesting
Yeah so this is things like if I were at mobile world
Check this out
And they also the developer
With nautical
Is canonical has iot core
OS kind of platform
So maybe
This is for microvilli
Doing kind of automated contractor charging for things
Crazy small scale
Tails so
Yeah maybe you're by your washing machine can buy
Detergent
Those kind of things
Amazing
That would be nice
Will find a use desperately
And we also saw coming out at
Mobile World Congress
A new
Everything
But I guess I can understand why they need a new hub for this because this is something called
Tabs
That's kind of like a play on keeping tabs on people it's a solution for busy families
And they're using that's the real Laura and that
Wi-Fi and Laura and therefore I can understand why in this instance
Stay With Me
So they're washing are they
Off
Bubble Rock on
Okay okay
And they're doing
And for those of you guys who
Do not regularly follow the show
Laura is a low-power
Wide area network so you can send
Small amounts of data
Fairly cheaply over really long distances
And it's
Predator 2 things like nb-iot
And
LTE Cat 1
That's that
So look for a new house in your life
It's not just a hug cuz they have a bunch of devices that you can actually wear for kids could wear that
Attracting someone so poor that I didn't want to just focus on the
Smart home devices kid trackers
So if you haven't
Already started outfitting your
Or if you're just crazy like me and
Hey I don't have a lawyer Network in my home yet
I have a dog that runs away
Keep tabs on the dog
Can I get the name I do
I just need for The Hobbit
All right now it's time for a
Debate
Joanna Stern at the Wall Street Journal
Read an article
Explaining that she has a problem
With all female personal assistants
She thinks going forward we should be maybe a little bit less
Research shows that
Prefer
I guess dictating & Hearing responses from a female
Voice so I'm curious Kevin
Do you think I Robot should be both
I think
Choices good in all things
I realize I don't have I don't see your customized
The Voice the way you would like to know you can already do that with different accents or language packs and such
So why can't you pick male or female you
That's a good question like why isn't there a Sean Connery skills
I'm guessing because it
Mutation that just
There are some like voice
You can get voices of specific people for certain apps and things I have seen that
The password can have you know
Batman read you your to-do list whatever
Personal Computing is it's personal and this is all part of personal Computing so
I should have that choice
You're dodging the sex
Question
Thank you
What what's your thought I really thought about this a lot
Because
I'm a woman who has strong feelings about this
Strong feelings about you know feminism
ViaSat
In our culture
This doesn't bother me
As much and I really was trying to let it bother me
It didn't bother me well you know I really gave it a lot of thought
Yeah it is kind of
I feel kind of
Ordering a female voice to do something
This is not a battle I feel like
Really strong
Yeah I don't I don't see it look at a phone or a
Echo or NC gender I just don't know and I guess that's why I don't really
It does not bother
I want the choice
It doesn't bother me
So many rescued baby towards female voices at beginning
So there we are we are
For now I'd love to hear from you
If you're like
Speaking
Personal assistants
Google
Home shopping
But it feels pretty Limited
I would say
Rite Aid
Which is why
What you can buy stuff online
Allows users to order stuff through Google Express and more than 50 retail
Partners
Doubt I have never use Google
Express I don't know if I even
Access to it
I have not used it I would imagine that you do I mean
You asked that's was going to say
How is the bulk of
States song
I'm sure that you could use it but
I don't use it I don't use any of the Amazon fresh or any other those types of
Express-Times shopping services so I couldn't speak to it
We use the CPU something
What do we use
We use Amazon pantry
But not express have used Amazon now
Buy stuff
Order from Google Express
I've never done that so you can order from Bed Bath & Beyond
Buybuybaby
Nine West
Pier 1 Imports PetSmart
The Vitamin Shoppe
The shop
Nevermind
My dad
To shopping list
At Whole Foods
Insolent
Stack
It would be fun you know it is only through Google home I guess that's your Google Assistant because I could do this on my pixel
I don't have a Google home
I'll try it on
Okay I was going to say try it soon because I'm on the
Google Express web page it says through April 30th
This year when you shop via Google home
You don't have to worry about additional fees like ship
Woo
So now is a good time to try it
Okay
If you follow me on Twitter
You probably have heard about my trauma with the Logitech
Harmony Home
I'm going to talk about that next week
Because
I think some of my drama maybe like
User error
So I have to spend some time with Logitech 2
Work that out so
We're going to talk about it
Anytime
Oh and I don't have any connection blinds but I can talk about them and I'll tell you why
Because
One of the folks I work with that Google actually I report to him
He's been getting into the smartphone
Has been asking me for suggestions how to smarten up his home
Heaven
On call
I mean really that bad
That's just great
Yeah I could be like the kind like a Geek Squad, come to your house
What do you want to do all right let's make it happen
Let's go to eBay you can rent me
So anyway he
He's got a hug now and they did not listen and do not
Github recommended
Instead he got something else
He's got some light switches going to be like you know
I just got her how to do my blinds I got these the song FeFe radio
Frequency controller on my God will probably not her megahertz
Hey did you know that sound P makes
Interface Walmart that basically takes the
Radio frequencies and converts them to Z-Wave
Just kind of
It's an interface except I guess you call it a bridge
Yeah it handle 16 channels and
Since I do not have some people lines that you do Stacy you educated me before the show
Explain how the channels work
My kind of phone is like what one channel promoter but not necessarily to most like
You could do scenes of
3 blinds
Let's do a quick breakdown of motorized shade
Because some of this is generic
If you're using like the automated Hunter
Neutron star
Arena
Motors and Shay
So
What you'll do is every individual
Has
A motor that's going to go up
Down in it you know it depends on the size of your
Windows and all that somewhat like I have really large windows
So I have
Boaters kin
So it's not necessarily,
And you might
Want something where oh I'll my windows
Go up all at the same time
As opposed to Lake
Having two commands
And each individual one
So
Every time
You're going to group
Downloader
So depending on how many windows you have that's how many channels you should
So that's generic
With the salty stuff
I mentioned to Kevin
I have the sea wave
Module
Have an older version of it that has a literal click wheel on it
It's kind of a pain to setup
So
If you're working with any sort of Z-Wave thing that's going to control multiple
Channels are multiple devices
You're going to have to set up
With your hug you're going to set it up as a
Brain
So you put it on your Winker you're smart
As like
I am a brain
And then
You have to use the other channels for
You know all the individual
So it's
It's not into it
But the pros
Right
That's handy
Yes that's what my husband
But he's fast
For Christmas
Will you you got this module a couple years back the one that you can get the older one
And it was a couple hundred bucks
At the time
Dealer beeg
Because they didn't sell it on the in
Right right but now they sell the stuff on the internet
So I'm looking at Amazon right now and
For 289 the newer song 16 channel
Walmart juul is
Sounds like a pretty good deal
I'm going to recommend it to
The person that I'm talking to and trying to help out so
I don't know how many blinds he hasn't haven't even details at Sitel know if he'll need more than one of these
Because 16 channels may go quickly if he's got a lot of motor
Yes now I would say
If you don't have a lot of
There is an easier solution
Which is something now makes
It's out it's a
I think is Wi-Fi it's a salty radio protocol which is like art
Yes
Is what they call it
To WiFi
And they call that the Milan
This is expensive this is like $175 on Amazon
Instead of buying
I have like a remote
Blinds instead of doing that
My closet
But it was me
It actually integrates with Echo I believe
It also talks to iPhones
And Android phones
And is kind of actually if I had seen this
I probably
Cuz I would need two of them
I probably would have done that
Honest
If you have
It starts adding up at that
EXO
Because you did three of those replace all the channels this one
Unit cell
Well I'll give him both options and see what he does
Okay now it's time to talk about Wi-Fi routers
We love
So I have been trying the orbi router from that
This is in contrast to my house router which is the Eero mesh
Your some pots
The orbit
Is
Not a mesh Network
Is traditional
Traditional bassinet
It is
Network extender that just happens to have the same name
I basically put the main orbi router
In the middle of my house and I put the extender
Light socket to satellite in my office
At this end of the house
And I tried it in a couple places
My results were not
Is this is actually really great WiFi
It is a very powerful
But I think I would need another
Down at the other end
My house is my house in Spanish
Skinny
I can't stress this enough when you are picking a Wi-Fi network
Router basically
You are going to
Your house is going your mileage will vary
Without a doubt because the materials because of the the design
There's a lot of factors there's there's no way
Exactly so the orbi routers they cost
$400 my Eros cost 500
And so
You know
Is that for one base station on satellite
Churros cost
In my bedroom for example at the other end
My office
The network would slow it was slower at that Inn
It wasn't I still have 150 megabit per second connection so it wasn't me
Killing me
But I could definitely
Now
This did push out an amazing signal to my outdoor Wi-Fi
Camera
Which I have
The canary Flex running
Which
Hey doesn't actually play nicely with
Mesh networks right
Even though they're working on
So the orbi definitely made that cake
A lot better
When the satellite was in the middle of my house it did not work as well
Pretend camera
So that's why I kind of pushed it closer to the edge
And the other things to know about the
B router are
There is no app
You're going to have to go to the web
Login
And some people feel that this is a security
Issue is actually something that the FCC is got
Madelene
Jesus
How many spark is there
Hey you shouldn't have that open
Web-based login
Not secure
Did you make you change your password
So that's nice
And the features are okay but again you have to go
Login
Log into the router
Where to change
Switch
But you do ever you can do a guest Network I presume
Crucial
And
What supports lots of ports on it which I like in my
I have the Google onhub that I bought
And I also Google Wi-Fi unit
Check on a mission together
And
Kind of skimpy on the porch I think you have four on these guys
Baidu
Brothers Subs
Are all my husband
I know I know
And he has good ratings
Cena and
Actually it's the favorite of The Wirecutter it's the favorite quote-unquote mesh Network for them
Even that's not technically
I've seen it give it 4 stars PC
It does have
Three ethernet ports
Kevin was saying so that is a
And that's
Router and on the Hub itself
It's super easy to set up even though
Do you have to use the weather
But you know
I think
For my house set up
Eros going to
A little bit better
Literal end-to-end
Bridgeprep went into my house
Right if you added a third unit
Second satellite in your case
Match what you have with the Eros is your three year old
Then maybe
Actually I think they just shoot me
More patlak more consistent
Signal strength
Throughout the whole house
$50
Yasso
Yeah
This is why I downsizing living townhouse now
Delete all those
My house is actually
Because of
What I do
My roof
Yep
So that is all the news for this week so
Until next week so
The hundred episode
Happy
What if
I need like a little party
Aspire to get a noisemaker
If we were a
All right
Message from our sponsors
And stay tuned for our guest
Schwab
Who is the CEO of
Videon
To talk about how we're going to build an even more distributed internet
Hey everyone we're taking a break for the podcast for a few moments
To bring you a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is spending
And we have Brian
Toll from spin dance
Good how are you Stacy
I am great
So okay let's
Reminder audience
Who is Ben dance and what are you guys do
Sundance is a consultancy that helps organizations design
Develop and manage
The software for their iot products we work with Fortune 500 company
He's like whirlpool
Ford Motor Company along with smaller manufacturers and startups
Within that space we help with it strategy and we also
Do embedded cloud and mobile programming
Increasingly were asked
To develop voice application
Inspire customers to
Voice is indeed hot
So what are you guys see
Spin dance has actually been developing voice
Integration for the automobile industry
4 years
Amazon Echo and Google home
Are making that sort of Technology much more accessible for a typical iot product
Yes I've heard that
You can't even develop a consumer product now without some sort of voice
By our company's interests
Yes they are we're seeing more and more industrial and consumer customers looking at voice to improve the experience in places like
What kitchens are warehouses
Or even the fact
Before what should I be thinking about when
When I'm designing
First of all don't be afraid of it it's much easier to prototype a voice application that it is a mobile app
For example
Instead of a GUI with a G
You're really developing in Bowie
With a V and it's much easier to get in
You can build a prototype in just a day or two
It's also easier to do user research for voice
The flipside though is that testing and fine-tuning the voice app
Can be much more time consuming
Bennett mobile application so you definitely want to leave time for that at the end and in our experience the gooey part of
The application
Is the easy part. To your back and
Can be very difficult
It's not designed for voice integration
What should I be thinking about as I building
There's two things you want to keep in mind
What is
What is your back and look like and is it prepared to integrate with
A voice interface
Secondly if you're serious about it you're better off engaging Amazon and Google in developing the Africa
Patient getting their feedback
Sooner rather than later
And you worked with a couple customers already
What if they giving you is their feet
I think most people are aware of the skills
But you can write
For voice
Integration systems
And skills are similar to apps free
For mobile phones
But what they aren't aware of as you can actually embed the Alexa service directly into
Your own Hardware
Which is pretty cool people learn more about spin dance
Including voice
People can visit spin dance.com IRT to download a free whitepaper I'm building end-to-end iot products
And if they're interested in boys they can drop us an email at hello at spin dance.com
Let me be more than happy to talk to them about integrating voice into their iot products
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is
Jumperoo
Who is the founder and CEO of
Evenium who says he is building the internet of moving thing
Well basically you know we look at
Cars trucks and buses you know not just as machines that carry people and goods from one point to the other but as
Active nodes of the internet
And also as critical elements for smart cities
So once you look at these machines or no as mobile Wi-Fi hotspot says access points and network routers on Wii
I've been a lot of changes and that's basically what the name is doing is delivering a platform
Is he able to deliver this internet of moving things
Because all I can think of
How does this actually work
Is there going to be a software on my
Car for the users it's completely transparent
So you will use this
As any Wi-Fi hotspot
At home in in the office or in the cafe but essentially you know the network
Manages itself let me give you an example veniam the company I found it in the end manager
Actually
I deployed the largest
Vehicle mesh Network in the world
So we did this in Porto Portugal where we have
All the buses and some taxis garbage collection trucks
Serving as Wi-Fi hotspots and connecting to each other information to the internet
And today we actually serve free Wi-Fi to about 400 thousand users
Alberta hind the scenes are veiny arms Hardware software and call Solutions art you know making sure
That all of these devices are connected to each other and basically are not only providing free Wi-Fi but actually
Gathering all sorts of data for different types of applications
So how does this work from a technical perspective what is actually
The Venom is actually a full-stack company in that we owned the hardware the software in the cloud components that make
Networks of moving things possible and also
But allow us to offer no managed services
And so typically our customers are companies that own and operate large fleets and they come to us and say for exam
You know I have 400 bus has 200,000 passengers a year
I want them to have an excellent internet experience I want branding and advertising but I don't want to worry about
Hardware software SIM card cell data plans
How much does it cost me per month for a vehicle
To be able to offer a service like that to my customers and so we take care of
All of that in that hassle-free way
And then we are able to add other things like
Footage from surveillance cameras on board diagnostics Aldi's
High-bandwidth applications and ultimately you know the big advantages that are able to move
Massive amounts of data between the vehicles in the cloud at a very affordable cost
What is your back
For something like this cuz I can see the Wi-Fi on the buses I can see the
The management challenge
How is it actually can
It's a multi Network approach very much in the spirit of 5G in that we have youngboy devices
Is with wireless interfaces ranging from Wi-Fi to 4G LTE
Dsrc which is the standard for vehicle to vehicle and vehicle-to-infrastructure communication which actually use this
A frequency band The 5.9 gigahertz
That's in the US than in Europe has been reserved for intelligent transportation systems and it's so far underutilize
Until we're actually able to grab 75 megahertz
Spectrum that nobody else is using
Experience and so basically the device is choosing between these different networks and is also doing all the handovers
Between all these different Networks
So that you can jump on any bus start a Skype call or a YouTube video and even though the bus is switching but
Now I connect to this guy a call now I connect to this access point now I go back to Cellular
Your Skype call and YouTube video never break down
So we could actually be doing this interview in a moving bus
In Puerto or in Singapore or in a shuttle in downtown New York
I would like I live in Austin
I have no clue
This is really hard when
When Comcast in
It used to be Time Warner Cable within Cox they created this
Wi-Fi network for
The Northeast Corridor for trains and that sort of thing that took a lot of
Technical brain power to do handoffs over Wi-Fi
The cellular guys have done this for
A while
So is your kind of magic software the ability to
To manage all of this
Precisely
So the salad carriers I have done this for
Long time but this is in from South Station to seven
Shell station in the network.
Decentralised in which they control entirely
We're able to do that across different networks using different Technologies managed by different people
It is actually
Sadly most people will just be like
Dang it my Wi-Fi on my buses
But you know that that's because they don't have to build a network themselves
Let's break down the idea of now I've got Wi-Fi
On city buses
What does that enable and you know maybe I've got Wi-Fi enough
Let's just stick with the city stuff
Also.
On my city Vehicles MyCiTi bus
What can I do
Well most of all yours now transformed these vehicles
Into active nodes in the network
That is constantly moving and constantly evolving and so now everything else that you can do is actually software
Beyond providing fully-managed mobile Wi-Fi you can get tons of data from the vehicle to the cloud
At what do we want this for well for one we want to be able to know exactly how the vehicle is doing predict
If it's going to break down before it breaks down
Know the fuel consumption driver behaviour safety profile you want to get footage
Security cameras
Are high-bandwidth applications that are only possible you know where the network that is able to scale to provide that
And in the future you know with autonomous vehicles coming much much faster than anyone imagined and where mobile
Melody services are going to be provided you know on demand in the in a network like this you are going to have to move you
Many more terabytes of data between the vehicles in the clouds
And so ultimately you know the Wi-Fi applications just the first one that justifies
Placing an on-board unit in a vehicle
But once you do that you have a new network infrastructure that can allow you to do a lot more
Things on top of that
So you're providing basically
Cool mesh pipe
Cobble together
Is it
Are you guys also going to provide things like the data
Analysis for vehicular maintenance or does that actually go to some other
Once you have this Wireless interfit infrastructure Vehicles do you still need to bridge the gap to the cloud and make sure
Sure that you have very low latency mechanisms that allow you to actually capture the day to process the data locally decide what do I say
Immediately what do I send later so that then applications can actually do something about that those data streams
And so what we provide is that these data API
Some of the applications we do ourselves
Like mobile Wi-Fi doesn't mention but also mobile advertising so the ability to place contents in digital
Walgreens inside of buses
But then other applications like sleep management or telematics and be built on top of our platform by
Other players who have done this already for for fleets worldwide
Awesome so
What kind of
City services can you provide once you have this network
So let's kind of dig into the idea of you know being able to provide bandwidth for cameras surveillance cameras
Sore
Maybe I'm trying to think if there's better wi-fi at bus stop
I don't know
So beyond having
Better connectivity and internet access for lots and lots of people in and also as a means to
Bridge the digital divide in in our cities
We can actually leverage all of the data that the vehicles are picking up not just to maintain the Via
Michaels or manage The Fleets more efficiently
But also to learn about the infrastructure about the city climate and and the
Any other things that are relevant to make our cities smarter safer and and nicer to live
At one example is that Porto already gets a date Avaya Venom's data's API
Two-time the traffic lights to
Smarter way
And that's just a few of the examples of how a city can become much better provider
Quality of life
If its uses
All these vehicles and we're talking essentially about
Fleet vehicles
As mobile sensors
Capturing Urban data at large scale
So where else
Provided the
So we have it at commercial level already in Puerto Singapore and New York
And we have a number of other cities right now that will be rolling out throughout this year
We like to partner with Telecom operators big
For three main reasons one is
The fiber in the cellular network we enable them to do more with their infrastructure and we obviously need the back hall
The second aspect is that they have access to a large number of customers that own and operate large fleets
Send so they can also help us distribute the solution
A number three Telecom operators are themselves
Owners of very large fleas
That we can use again for as as mobile but also as mobile sensors for urban data
So right now our strategy is to partner with with Telecom operators and and leverage these three
She makes a lot of sense
I'm it also gives you great Network effects cuz if you were going after individuals
I'm like
I think it was cool
Having my one car roaming around
Does nothing
Are very low
If you think about it there are 1.2 billion vehicles in the world and only 5% of them are connected to the internet
Initially we did think about a consumer approach and adding it to private vehicles but then we realized that
No private Vehicles go to work in the morning and they come back in the evening so they're limited network effects there
And on the other hand fleet vehicles are 26% of vehicles worldwide
And that percentage is growing every single day they traveled more than 50% of the deal
Miles
And so as you think of Norman's disruption in which the transportation sector is right now with
People taking Uber and Lyft and leaving their cars at home
Then you're saying that the percentage of fleet vehicles is only increasing and once the autonomous vehicles come in
Which most people predict to be around 2020
Then we are actually going to see that most of the vehicles are going to be pleased
And so looking at that
These fleets
Mobility as a service providers
As part of the infrastructure I believe this the right way to think about
The future and how cities can become
You know more efficient wave iron mentally sustainable and provide an even better quality of life
Right because actually these people
Living in dense urban areas where this makes the most sense are the ones most likely to give up their car
Switch to an Uber and automated system
Bringing in something like
Drones in I just thinking crazy thoughts here because I love drones and I think it's kind of fun so I'm trying to imagine you know
Could you much like
Google and Facebook are trying to create connectivity with like
Everything from balloons tula
Find airplane solar powered airplanes
What about bringing something like
So Google is looking at balloons Facebook is looking at drones so venom has its feet a little bit closer to the ground
So please locate vehicle and we started with vehicles because they're everywhere
They have batteries
That keep recharging so we don't have to worry about energy
And they even have their own Vehicles can use but it's just the beginning
What we call the internet of moving things
We have a market segment
That shows us points as to what
The future of cities going to look like which are industrial environments like
Ports and airports in construction sites where actually the internet of things in my view is progressing the fastest
Type of rhino industry 4.0 approach
Actually connecting everything in the controlled space like that makes a lot of sense in and our first customer was actually a container term
Why we have not only trucks but also cranes and boats
And other
Mobile assets
That are providing connectivity but also Gathering real-time data to make the operations more efficient sober
Bring ships faster in an asteroid loading and unloading them with with greater safety
And so I think that there we can see that you know in the future
You're going to have
Yes not just beer in Connected vehicles that
That build internet of moving things but also
Robots drones all of these things need to be connected and that's where you know we have to
Be real and accept the fact that the current Internet is actually
Not ready
For the massive
Mobility and the type of machine-to-machine connectivity requirements that all of these mobile
Acids are removing things are going to to need
And so to be able to scale we need the network
Effects of mesh technology we need the ability than to process all these data streams
That they arrived at the cloud in a way that
Ensure is the best operation mime on all of these
Moving things
That's why I do things
Drones are a part of the equation but think robots
The future of autonomous vehicle which is not going to look at all like the vehicle we have today
What are some of the big challenges of building basically an autonomous Network that's going to be made up of
Hundreds of thousands or maybe millions of thing
Well the key is to move towards Distributing also the intelligence and decision and not
Just the device
In the sense that you know if you expect
All of these devices to have the connection to one Central brain that is basically orchestrating the whole thing
Then you run into problems of latency security single point of failure
All sorts of obstacles to actually making
Leveraging the network effects that you get from having more and more devices
Essentially the technical challenges to the find the local rules
I buy which these devices interact with each other and engage with each other that ultimately generate the kind of emergency
Behavior for the network
That is desirable in ensure is that it doesn't break down
And so defining this local rules that's a lot of the work that we do as many again vehicles
Good way to start special leaf lease because automatically the vehicles that the buses trust each other they belong to the same Fleet and survive
All of them competing for the wireless access they can actually
Coordinators wireless access among each other
And share those network resources in the
Smarter better way
Until we work a lot on this notion that
We have local clusters of nodes that
Help each other
I make the best use of the available network resources
Private are for
Running around at the same city do they share their connectivity yes only occur
When you actually have those interactions
And so you have to insure end-to-end security so there's no privacy breaches but at the same time at the network level
These are nodes in the network that's basically cooperate with each other
And also the access points are multi-tenancy in that you have the same infrastructure but they are used by
Different operators in different Tennyson so that's also part of the platform
What is the Temple of this is exactly how many key Global players are thinking today about 5G
With 5G I'm seeing a completely different attitude it's more about
Ensuring that you know all these different networks are able to work together
To ensure that everyone has the connectivity there Nita and I welcome this approach because I do think that
The future is going to be
Using in different ways
A big hurdle to overcome actually has nothing to do with technology that has to do with finding the right business models that also
Autoscale
How much is this going to
Cost because right now Cellular's expensive Wi-Fi quote-unquote free so
How do you think about building a business model around all of these Technologies in
For an ecosystem
So today the revenue for mobile Wi-Fi comes from to Maine
Sides one is the preservation companies themselves who want to increase ridership provide a better quality of experience and so
So they are willing to pay for the the extra connectivity they're giving for free to people
The second is through advertising
So you have a captive audience that is ready to receive the content and not just on the splash screens but actually on
Digital screen put inside and outside so that's one model
But then there's also the monetization of the urban data picked up by the vehicles
Which is interesting nachos for cities and municipalities is also interesting again for all sorts of
Players in the private sector can pick up a lot of local data
Set the saddle as I'm not able to pick up for example you know the pictures of the the windows of certain shops
Start counting the people in different parts of the city all of this is anonymized so that you don't break the user privacy but you're actually able
Call them tomorrow. Very valuable data
That many players say for example foot traffic in different parts of the city in different parts of the days valuable
For the huge number of Industries high and so that's the kind of thing that will enable us to fund the connected
Give it to you later on once we get to critical mass of connected vehicles and and the critical mass of users
Okay
I can't wait to see this everywhere
So hopefully
Feel like I can't wait either
I think it's a necessity for future life
All right I shall enjoy thinking about what can happen when my car is both a sensor and a hotspot
So thank you Joe
Perfect thank you so much space it's been a pleasure
Things podcast thank you so much for your support over the years and please if you are looking for more IO
Haiti news subscribe to my newsletter at
Www.dot Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week