Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And you're Cohoes
Kevin tofel
And today we have
Buncho for you we've got Amazon
Your house
We got week
Launching a new security bundle
And
We've got something new to fear
The Reaper
We've also got some news about
New Google assistant device
Crazy Cheap
Speaker and a voicemail for one of our listeners
About
Working with
Android
Our Guest today is Phil Skipper head of iot at Vodafone
And our show is
Sponsored by
Sap
Let's go to a message from another one of our sponsor
ADT
The Internet of Things podcast is brought to you by ADT
Who is it just a place it's a Feeling
The feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most
ATT that you take that feeling with you wherever you go
Whether you're in your house your business or online ATT helps keep you safe and secure with security system
Automation alarms and surveillance
So you can do at home
Wherever you are learn more at ATT
Okay
Heaven
Let's get started do rocks and hugs and botnets oh my
Actually we are talking about
Security
Because every good home automation
Company knows they've got to get into security
We've had Lexi's SmartThings partnering with
With ATT
We've had
Ring
We had
Next
And now
We've got
Amazon
Looks like it's getting a
Into the space with a grin
New
Security camera
What do you think it is
Actually we should talk about what it is
Before we ask
Yeah so this is a smart move by Amazon they're offering actually to new things and they work together one is
Is there new webcam which
Just cause 1 1999 and we'll talk about some add-ons that you can get
Options you can add on for that and then they also have Amazon
Key which is a way to use a connected lock or selling you the lock
And that will allow you to let Amazon
Prime deliveries
Right in your house
What do I think of that
I even work from home so I don't think I would
Need that
But I could see why people in the 37 Metro areas that thrilling us out in
Some of them might like this I probably would have a camera with the key
Amazon Keys what they're calling us little bundle
Just so I could see
The people that come in and deliver
Smartly Amazon also partnering with
Bunch of their home services so if you use Merry Maids or Rover or whatever
You can allow those people in your house as well as much as
And I
I feel like this is a totally logical extension you can only actually get the key
Integration with Amazon
I'm Prime so the idea is
Yes Amazon's just
Shipping stuff left and right
Do you you put more stuff
Through Amazon Prime because why wouldn't you
Assure yourself that never
Rockets lost this is also good for Amazon because you have to deal less
Package theft
Shrinkage or leakage
Then it's a package I don't know in the retail thing it's shrinkage
Can I call it fast
Alright theft
So this is
It makes sense
If I were a security company that's hosting on AWS
And a lot of them are I might kind of
Be like yo Amazon
What are you doing
This is our busy
But that's kind of Amazon
Cross to bear especially with
I want to buy Whole Foods all the retailers are like
Let's get out of this
Yes so just so folks understand the locks are actually
Existing locks you could already buy but they are two of them Yale and Kwikset are working with Amazon
Ski-in home kit cost to 4999 for the lock
And also that includes the Amazon Cloud cam
You're getting the whole bundle there for $250
There's also free Professional installation which I think it's very smart of Amazon to offer
Yeah but it's okay
Everyone stays
PSA
Install your own lock it doesn't take
I put a video up on the side yard
It's not hard
And
Kevin you came up with this brilliant idea with
Is probably accurate
My lock
Currently cuz I have a quick
Set Z-Wave lock
I don't think that's going to work with this
It definitely
Is not
In my opinion it's the reason I say I say definitely in my
Definitely in your opinion
All right
Definitely not
The reason I don't think it will work
Oreck is because I look at the Kwikset
Lock that is included with the cloud cam
And the in-home
Kitty cat and that model does come in two flavors
One with Z-Wave
One with the sticky I have a Z-Wave on also
The reason I don't think is going to work is
Because the Amazon Echo Plus which is a hub does not support
Z-Wave
So
I presume Amazon a smartly using the zigbee once we can work with their hub
Stubs not required
You can have any other hub
That's fine but I just
Leaning towards it not working
They have a new stamp works with Matt Ma
On this as well so we'll see if it was lock
Fox github
If that's works with Matt Emmaus
Really into
Ectopic so I've talked to
Listen to Philip Rivers and this stamp is
Is relatively new
And it's something that Amazon has
Pushing
Partners
Affairs
To work with
Amazon Echo Show side what it means is your
To get that sticker you're going to have to
To show your video
It's on the
Show
Some partners are like
And some of them are actually
Concerned that this is Amazon's
To get more data from
React be true
It could be it right now some of them are like
You know do I really need a works with Madam a sticker I have a
Skill that's fine
That's efficient
This looks like a little bit more than I want
How to take on right now so this is kind of an interesting there's a behind-the-scenes thing happening
With Amazon and it
Its partners
Well and that I totally understand on the other side of the equation from a consumer stand
1.5
Showing this little
Works with Madam a it gets rid of the whole conversation of
Which radios
Zigbee Z-Wave you don't need that on there anymore
Confusing keep on saying what works and what doesn't
Kind of like
Dunkin logo
So I think it's rather clever from a consumer-facing
Totally agree
All right
So this is Amazon's move into
Security I wonder if we'll see them pop out
Sensors later on our part
Week
Wink has a new
Security bundle
For $200
It is
Smart Security is
Kevin as a wink owner are you excited this has
To open close
Got a siren and it has a
Camera light
Looking
Motion detector
It is not actually
And all this is for
Did your 499
$500
Yeah so it's interesting that they're bundling all this and
Also they're not requiring or adding on any monthly fees this is definitely for
Somebody wants security on their own they want to monitor their own stuff through their apps and whatnot
So I think it's clever of work to do I don't
Really need some of these things but
Let me grab some of the
Door window sensors to give them a try
The next thing is Wink works with so many things I still
SmartThings
Of course
I already have some of these products just
You know there's a way prices you can get anywhere
Good for first time buyers
Percent that seems to be a big
Keane everybody's aiming towards first time buyers
Yes I think that's actually why
The Amazon Echo Hub that we talked about a minute ago
Doesn't matter too many people that it doesn't
Work with
Z-Wave because
It's not meant for people who already have a lot of Z-Wave products
It's meant for people getting started in Smart Homes
As with this wink Lookout B
I would argue that
Patterson
And we'll never know
You'll never know
Good for that
So yes I agree with you
I think
Are some interesting pricing here at
The other thing I would
Be interested with is
Other than
Security I've actually tried to mess with
Emotion sensors
Pulled motionsense
Answers into my Linksys
I was got a little frustrated because they could do open close but a lot of these sensors have other readings
That wink would never pick up so
I'm curious
How
In adding these if wink is going to expand the
The capabilities for
For all of it
Because there are definitely some things that I would like to
I have existing
Window sensors that I would love to add to
Weak sister
Yeah no I totally understand that and I've seen what you're talking about any depends on the product
So I don't know if it's an all-or-nothing thing with wink I've actually gotten temperature and other things from motion sensors
It does depend on the product
It's basically if wink is done
Wink and
Device manufacturer
Exactly
So also on the security front
People have been asking
About this this is crazy and I have been
Looking under rocks for all the bad things
This is a camera for $20
From
A company called wise labs
Actually based in
Seattle
I am so suspicious Kevin will tell you that I liked was
I was clicking through on the terms and condition for the
The price
Home theater
Website somewhere
Just for entertainment purpose
But they don't appear to be at least
So the camera actually the hardware looks really good
I do I'm surprised
And your skepticism is
Well founded I'll say that right up front but I don't see any morning flag cic nice Hardware
I see a 1080p camera full HD night vision two-way audio
It's $20
It has an app
That will alert you with motion and what not depending on how you have it set up it has an
MicroSD card slot if you want continuous recording on your own which I think is
Great
Because if you control that but it will work with a
Cloud services running on AWS
And for no extra fee will actually record 10 to 15 second Clips whenever it sees motion and whatnot
My issue or maybe why it's
So inexpensive it doesn't integrate with any
Cubs everything
This is strictly I got a camera cameras
And I use the app that comes with it to get my alerts and so on and so forth so it's kind of limited in that respect maybe you can work with
This the night or something but
I don't know for $20 I may actually
Grab one or two or three of these
Too late
I just bought one Kevin
But it's on backorder
The okay so you didn't buy the last one
Okay
Keepin On
So yes
We're going to buy it
And tell you what we
Please take and if I hate it
Perhaps I'll even give it away in the
All right
Let's talk about
Oh that's talk about noon
Guys
This is very exciting this is a startup I actually broke the news about the start of
Like a month ago
Gansett actually
Yeah the CEO is Eric Charlton who is
Before I had a business
At nest
And there's a bunch of Nest folks there
And this is a lighting
Smart lighting
That is
Actually really interesting looking
You guys know that I love
Love lights
And what his company is done is they've created a
Light switch that you install
And it has
Croisette
Has a couple thing
It says
Oh hey what are the lights in this room so it detects the bulbs and what they're capable of
Once it's installed and then it also has presets
Burberry is like relax
And daylight and other
Three settings
And then it automatically hand
Is all of that
I think this is
Really interesting
Because as a person who's invested in lots of crazy lighting
Schemes colored balls
LEDs of various Hues and warm temperatures
Whites
So many
Light switches
I can tell you
Most people do not want
They just want to hit a button
And have like
A couple options
It look good in there
And that's what this is promising to do
Yeah that's I think the big drug you know a lot of people don't want to go through the rigmarole as you said of setting up different scenes
I don't really know what's up
Good lighting setup you know so if these are
No professionally-designed you know maybe they're going to just wow you I don't know but this interesting approach
It's actually a common one
So there's a startup actually in Austin Texas that works on super high-end
It's called ketra and they actually make
Crazy awesome lights
I would love to have them in
But I am not that way
And it's actually also something that like a Lutron
If you get like a professional
Install Nautica set up at the the fancy Lutron if you get that they'll have
Lighting design
Program the
So basically it's bringing that idea of having a
Professional lighting
Installer dude come into your house at
The program your stuff
Except
This company is going
To do it with
Is it $399
Piece of hardware
Yes
And the package can
Pain
Will you get one room director switch
Two extension switches
And three wall plates
For 399
99 if you just wanted room director switch which is the main smarts that's
199 99 storage room you going to add
Cost of two hundred bucks and then each extension switch for that room is 99
9 so it's not an expensive by any means but
There's a definite convenience.
Oh yeah and again
If I look at all that I've spent
If I look at my Hue bulbs
Four of those at 6
D-box
240 bucks so I'm halfway there and then I still had to buy some
I did install a switch that
Kept it on for me
So that's another fifty bucks
So now I'm at 300 and
I'm still doing the work of program
Price put it all into perspective and the master switch you put in your room
And then the extension switch
They talk to it via some
Proprietary wire
Of course they do
And that
Controlling
Is it like a three-way set up or is it like
All around the house
Build-A-Bear focus on room so you maybe you could have like
1 Portico master switch control in two rooms if you want the same Lighting in that room
But it seems to me like you're going to want
One of these in every room 101 master switch
Yeah alright this doesn't include both people should be very clear that does include both but it works
Text with regular ball
Your bulbs do not need to
In fact it's probably better if they
Arcsmart
Because a grief I test these things
You don't need to SmartThings
Vying for control of your lights cuz
They're going to fight
Smart thing plus smart thing equals dumb things because yeah they fight
Terrible why can't they just get along
Alright other quick cool gadgets
Linkee which is a
Touch screen
Smart panel thing for Google assist
Reminds me exactly of the nucleus
Which was a touch screen
Smart panel intercom system thing for
Madam
And it kind of reminds me of the Echo Show and that it is
Very
Attractive
I see why you're saying that it does look like a mini
Echo Show to me
Because it's a 5-inch touch screen so small and it's got the speaker Grill along the bottom
I'm a very small iMac
To me because it's the
That black and silver look to it
So you write it works with Google Assistant
It has a far field microphone array
WiFi zigbee and Bluetooth
Wireless built
10 +
Yeah I mean it's only interesting to me because it's the first
Google Assistant item with a
A touch screen
Answer my phone it's Unique
Wakes up your phone while I've said that Furlong were carrying all these things right around
But that's okay
And it comes with an app so you can still integrate
In all that it's $150 it's on Indiegogo we should be very clear about that
It's a project on Indiegogo early bird special start at $99
The full retail for 1 days is going to be 150 any ideas that you might put one that's standing on your living room coffee table
Turn on your nightstand light mounted to a wall around your house
Because the intercom
So
There in fact are two versions of the desktop version it stands up and there's an in-wall version see if they can pick and choose and
Plan ahead on this
It's only 13% of it
$30,000
Flexible goal
So I say flexible because the campaign will get all the funds raised even if it doesn't reach its goal there's a month left
You want to think carefully before you backup
Even if they don't deliver the product they're getting them
Your money will go up in
Okay
Yay
Alright let's talk
Such enthusiasm from Stacy
I like sorry sorry guys I just
I'm not excited
But I am excited by now
So there we got we all have our
Let's talk about
Security
Because by golly
There's a lot
Is here
Let's talk about
The Reaper
Forget the song you should fear this Reaper
I think it's bigger than my right eye it is a
Botnet is
Everything
But it's
It's not good so this
It's got over 2 million it
Webcams so IP camera
And digital video recorders in the past
Month according to check
So it is growing faster than Boracay
And the
Concern is that these
Devices have enough
Computing power they have enough access to bandwidth
The date
Create a massive DDOS
And that was
Kind of the concern with Mariah
This is very
Similar only it's a little more advanced
Because
This thing can really it said it's like changing passwords and having
Control this can install additional software on these infected devices and we don't know what that's awful
4 can do
Depends on what the botnet controller
Wanted to do
This is very
Concerning perhaps more concerning than Mariah in my
Yes
Cuz you could actually reboot and then
Patch and then where I was
What's going on in
Can attack you
But here because it can actually install things
Run on that device
Netty persistent right
Thank you that's the word I was like they'll stay there even after it
So this is concerning and I would say it's concerning for two reasons one because it's
Could unleash
A massive amount
Bandwidth
Target but two
Because this is another thing that's going to
Tar and feather
Tea and these devices are old-school devices these are not the modern devices that we
We talked about so some of them
Passwords
We've got it all
Either not going to be updated over there or they're just
Out of service
These devices can be like 10
Years old so I think the more
Current modern
Companies are learning
From this but
I think that we still haven't actually in
Encountered a true iot attack yet that actually takes advantage of
United States
I feel like this attack
Yes it targets
Computing devices that are
Connected that are not actually
Computers but it is still very much in line with the old models of attacking
Computer system
I think we're going to start to Sea-Doo
Attacks
They're going to be aimed at true iot device
So sensors that light up
Other
Types of
The physical world attacks
I see again
Bluetooth
Subwoofer like sound waves
Can disrupt your accelerometer
All of that it's going to be
Happening in
We're not even
Fear the Reaper the only thing I would add is
I think we're in a better place now because of what you just said those other devices are very old not to be patched
Yes we still have some issues with iot Device makers
Not offering security patches as quick as a cooler they should
But
Mostly
Are updatable
Pretty easily so we got that on our side it's just going to come down to
How quickly do these device makers react
Yes
Okay
So there's that
And then there's
A possible Solution on the horizon
So this is really interesting
Arm
I am actually here at arm techcon this week I gave a speech all about iot
Talk about some of the things
We always talk about on the
You guys remember that
But they introduced something called the
PS
And that stands
4 platform security
So this is really interesting because arm has gathered up
A bunch of big names in the industry it is basically saying we're going to Setzer
Things in place on the hardware
And then you guys
Here is a framework
For software developer
Work with
Our hearts
And that I think is going to
You can't what are the issues
We have right now is companies on the hardware side sell chips with
Like secure modules and all the school
Cool stuff in it but a lot of the companies don't actually turn it on
Know if they're working
Correctly
So this framework
Will address
Yeah that the smartest thing here is that are MS
Kind of using an open source
Firmware
Call trusted firmware m
And that's going to support this PSA specs so by doing that instead of making something
Proprietary
And sew on a it will allow people to contribute
Updates to that code
Theoretically make it better
And be it'll be easily usable by more
Company said that's what arm once I mean if they're expected to ship 200 billion chips
Spy I think it was 20 21
And Atman 200 billion chips running in
All kinds of computing devices but a lot of
Obviously smartphones and so on but
Tons and tons of little Iowa
Multi devices
You're interesting a wide base of
Product markets and you're making it easier to do so in a secure way
Which is awesome
We're excited
Bye
Farms PSA I hope this
Is it good step
Forward and
I guess
I feel like we talked about a lot of stuff Kevin do we have anything else we want to share
Do we want to take that listener
Voicemail
I do want to take a listener question Kevin and
For those of you Dies who may not be aware of it
We have the Internet of Things
Hotline where Kevin and I will endeavor to solve your
Toughest
Or better yet easiest iot
Problems
And you can call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7:40
424 +
Now we have our voice mail
From
Derek
Hey Stacy and Kevin
Their fruit
Tuscaloosa
You have permission to
Use this in your shower if you'd like
User iluv homekit but i've been looking at that new google pic
And I was wondering
Is there any
Phone or any other operating
System that integrates home automation into the actual ecos
Besides home
The Google assist
Or we'll have to have
A bunch of different
If you haven't asked us
Please let me know
Love the show
Love you guys
I'll let you know
Old Derek
We love this
Question
What because
The kind of fits into the easy
Although as always with our questions
The caveat
Your mileage may vary based on the devices you have
Change your comfort with technology
Which
It's basically a huge disc
What I was expecting to see when I saw that $20 cam
So all right
There is a lot of software out there
It won't do it
Exactly what
Home for iOS does
So if you want it
To be persistently available on the home
Home screen or what is that little tray that
On your iOS
Command Center
Is that okay yeah if you want it in the command center
But but
But it's
It's hard to answer the question without knowing
You know all the details of this system The Hub and so on and so forth but I use wink on my
Phones Derek with IOS and Android and
That is my central repository for controlling everything seeing the sensors and so on
It's certainly not as clean as home which I also have install oh I don't have a lot of homekit devices
One thing is lacking for simple there's no rooms
Like home has like home I can see what sensors are doing in different rooms and someone saved
What is very clean an nli
However if you have a SmartThings
Hub
Which would work with either iOS
Or with
Android they do have room support and I find the interface
Cleaner
Then Wing kits
Closer to what home offers
Again if you don't have a SmartThings Hub it's at the obviously not going to help you sound like you
You can use it with other hub
Please have you seen anything any third-party type things that just suck everything in like this
So there are some
And their limitations
So I've mentioned one before called
You know me
I don't
No I don't
Thanks.
It has
Was kind of the room support that you would be looking for the ability to control it
From a nap there is however a company that used to be called Alfred smart
Comedy called Gideon
Smart Home
So you can download this app on
And
It has the room capabilities
You can create scenarios
Controller
Huge variety devices
But in some cases you're going to have
Have to have the Hub
Select
Controls a bunch of insteon devices
For that work you're going to have to have the in
It controls
WeMo devices
You don't have to have
So it's got nest
Set Philips Hue with
That Apple gear but not all the nits out
Ogier
Sonos
It will control
Pink stuff tp-link gear
It actually control some of the week stuff
Through the wink hub
So it's
Pretty promising I tried it last
Probably about a year ago
And
It works the interface was different than what it looks like now but I can
Kind of expect that because he was newer in a little
Funky but it did do the
Controlling there was a little latency
But I would also ask you
Why do you want
What to do this
In them not trying to be a jerk but I really try very hard
Did not pick up
And I do that thing
Things to do
Amazon Echo or the
The home and that is
I feel like I use an app
You know maybe one out of every two
20 *
And I I totally I get your point
Say hi to in defensive Maybe by Derek might want to do this when I look at the whole map
I get information it's not just about control maybe I want to see what the temperature is upstairs without having to speak
Or walk upstairs or so on so forth
It's just right there like I'm looking
At the Home app
Occupancy detected you know when the dining room well that's obviously my dog
We probably shouldn't be on the dining room table I can see the heat down there the heat up here the temperature and so on
It's like Ike story
Get that it's the getting of information
As well as
Got it okay well now I understand
And now I say Gideon will offer you some of that in
Yes on a
Semi-related note
What I think
Andy Rubin essential is promising is something like this when the essential Home Products come out
Because he just wants to apparently make it all seem listen pollen
One repository one app and so on
I haven't heard anything about that I do have an essential phone being delivered today
I'm going to see if they have any
Smart home software included in that as well but
That's something to keep an eye out
Yeah I'm excited about I know the essential phone was a bit of a bus but I am a
Excited about
And hope those are still
It's less of a bus now they dropped the price $200 that's why I bought one
Go Kevin always on the prowl for
All right
I feel like that was a really good show and we should pause here
Take a break
And then come back with our guests feel Skipper who is the head of iot
Tea at Vodafone and we are to be talking
About nb-iot
The possible convergence
Other cellular low-power wide area Networks
And some fun things that are happening
Expanded connectivity stay tuned
Everyone that we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor
Where is sap and I have
Gil Perez who is SVP
Of iot and digital
Supply chain
We're talking about sap Leonardo live which is a big event that you are having November 2nd through 3rd
In Chicago
Can you tell me what this is
Leonardo live
Is SCP
Brand name for
I'm going to get a vacation
And this is a global event which were going to have
People coming from all over the world to see how
Sat
Technologies come together to really create that system of innovation weather is going to be blockchain
Machine learning
Of course iot and other things coming together with sap customers
SCP partners
And of course
SCP themself showcase
Aldi's
Amazing
Okay so I could see some real-world things
Exciting
What are you most excited about
Working on two really interesting area
One of them is
Connected vehicles and in that space
We're really seeing the
Continue
Conductivity doll all the cars in the Telco.
Where they are offering
What we called the OBD
Uncle Phil making any existing cars that is still on the road
Today connected with an OBD dongcopter going to have a great
Company called muccio presenting how's that working with FTP and really offering
Today's
Which is the T-Mobile offering
Which is powered by
SAP connected vehicle
So that's going to be a really exciting question
Another
Is if course blocks
Boxing is another
Amazing a new technology that is evolving quite quickly everybody knows them in the context
But in the Enterprise is going to be used in other ways
Pacifically in the compass
Pics of track and Trace
And accountability and ensuring that drug
Which are beans
Distributed are affected
We've been working with
Mark
Island example and Amerisource
And where
Showcasing those
Technology
Innovations
Really with
Sap technology being used in Veep today out there in the field of being piloted there's going to be a lot of info
Christine
With multiple
Customers
That sounds great so there are a lot of shows
Right now
Focused on iot
What makes Leonardo live
Leonardo like it
Forward
Customers
Actually have hands on
Experience with all these
Technology so I really urge
Anybody who is interested in these kind of Technologies on blocked in machine learning
I8
To come and visit us Leonardo why because you were going to be able to
Interact with
In real time
Alright this is coming up on November 2nd through 3rd in Chicago
So where can we find out more about Leonardo life
You can find all the information
Animation on wwd
Jcp.com Leonardo Ma
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Who is head of Business Development
Coyote
Excellent
We've got you on the show to talk about a couple things
One is to give us that European perspective
We so often lack
Yashow into
Who is to talk about everyone's favorite
Low-power wide
We are all excited about low-power wide area Networks
Worth a few seconds
Explain
What the heck are these and why do they matter
For the internet
This technology
Play penetration testing building
Traditional
Play ball
Lpwa action
It has to do with it
Revolution
Okay and now you guys for your particular Network
Market shows in NB iot
Why did you guys choose that over
We spend alone time
Elope a lovely weekend in the NBA
Penetration very low battery life
Witches NPR cheeks
Infrastructure
Enterprise
I need China it's a big Market
Rechargeable
Convergys
He has like
A very low data rate
Which I'm wondering if
America picked
Cat m
Because we're like gluttons for bandwidth
What about things like when we talk about over the air updates
And
Those sorts of needs
Do we need something
Better
In terms of
I think it's in the US
Knetbooks
Preseason football
You don't actually need to get
Information
Traditionally used to things like
Go to launch detection environmental monitoring
I choose Joy
Security technology
Okay so
Let's talk about this idea of convergence because I am
Very curious what you mean when you mentioned
And nb-iot conversion into some sort
Single standard or wheat
I think it's
Angel Food Network
I think she might well see these things becoming similar
I think you'll see them become
Let's talk about some of your
Connected device
Use case
Spitter using
Either end
I don't know something even fancy
Connect to call and internet services
Tiny devices that you might use
Chinese inventions
Use cases
The interesting
How
The
Technology wings
Let's talk about
Because
I saw an article
Talk about the module cost in
I believe it was someone from Vodafone that was actually saying the module costs are not low enough
So I'm very curious
When does it become economically
To actually put this in more
Places
How much money is January
Don't have the power to do it
When you start looking at
Applications
Something small tracking devices
Cheering in Chinese
Caldwell
Applications come to Market
Actually
That you're going to see come out today
Cuz what we're seeing
Today is
Mostly Subs
Corruption based beak
Has bee stings have
I think that's because that's how
Consumers and even businesses are used to
The Simpsons that I did not see where the chips
Windows being broken
Spell baby baby
To replace
I think when you looked at
Look for instance asymptotic changing value
When something goes something
It's going to cost you a few hundred pounds
Looks like
It's at that point that you can charge the device
So wishing momotose where the hardware
Where is Stitches
Is the initial value so you think of the customer list of connected
Places to call
Animal Collective
Election monitoring TV event
Or the outcome
Okay that's kind of
So in that case payment comes to you
From the glass maker
Let me tell somebody
And that is like
It's at that point where
Tavares High
Stolen vehicle tracking
If you can get called stolen
Luggage being stolen is of no use having it returned to you
Used to be hot
Totally see where you're going in that makes a lot more sense
Pay a monthly fee for a glass break sensor
Cuz once it's broken I'm like
That was my security okay
Here we go do you think
Consumers are going to start
Ending up with
And of course
Everyday to the way we operate
Looking at something where you'll give me action
Whether he wants
That becomes much easier to manage
I think
It will be
Psychiatrist being sent back
The television show
I think it's your care
Reading Country Club
I know customers privacy
Everyone benefits
Disagree with that I just feel like there's always a lot of community
Location
And you touched on security which is something
I think license pants
Generally have
A little bit more of
Sandisfield
So talk to me about how you guys are
The connectivity in the network
Also the
Customer data on the backend like what role do you play in
Something like
Volume teachmore
Security
Cool business
Skills
We get the economy
Escaping security
Because security something you have to invest in
2 into a number
So how do you make the device
People
How to make sure that the taking out knees or something else
Turn on network
Insecure
Ability to use different techniques that we use to secure that piping
Large complicated system
Control over the conditions
Unemployment insurance
Distributed
So if I'm buying
Connectivity it sounds like I have to keep everything
Your world so if I am on AWS
A different Cloud platform provider
Chant
Will it rain July 6th I do today wsj
Medical City
The best security
Elizabeth
Coyotes in ecosystem play
Security
Okay let's go back to this window maker
Because I feel like there are a lot of really
Technically Savvy folks like the AWS guys like you guys
In the it
Now we bring in this window maker who's like
I have one at this module
Concrete this other line of business which sounds awesome
But then let's say
Maybe it's
Processor inside
The censored
Broken dick
Gets hacked so there's an element inside
Window sensor
It gets packed
Vulnerable
You guys might see this long before the window maker
Probably isn't
Sword
I'm not saying they shouldn't
But they probably are
So what is the role
As
Technology expands in the
More places with
People who are maybe not Azteca
Wasabi
For a company like
Windows
Looking off the remote sensor
Usage
See
Information that you can use on
I'll be able to come
I said Managed IT provider
The network
So we can just avoid him to be input
Centerpieces prices that he wants too long
Existing
Our customers
Into that if you like
A lot of people are like hey the most accurate
Will be to build it
Ourselves and then there was this Evolution were there like
Oh that was a dumb idea
Let's not build ourselves as good as somebody else
But now it feels like
They still want to monitor
Set data so is this just a continual Evolution back to the egg
Do you think there's
I don't know
It feels like it's not
Not many people are doing it.
Depends on
YouTube
The large multinational
Unable to manage those connections
Galaxy 7
With all platforms they cannot change location
And see everything that is actually happening
Simpsons people that might be making connected clothing
Do not have
Coming back into the business
The company that makes the jacket work you have to have service centers around the world
We have been servicing to alarms
Depends on
Dissimilar
Businesses
Production orientation
Babies quite a large market for these are your team
Barometer
Raleigh
What was most interesting
People are deploying iot Solutions
WhatsApp
Number of
Organizations with y'all
Actually increasing the sky right now
A good indication that people seem to benefit
The second one
Changes in
The perception around security
Example
Security
We understand how to resolve it
I don't think that means
She sang we know that security
With that you would keep the understanding
Ready
How customers are increasing the volume
How to become insecure
All right we turn this whole conversation but we haven't actually talked about
Threat
Unlicensed or the rule of unlicensed
Low-power wide area
Parks and I've got to ask you because I hear a lot of companies are deploying
Network
Works especially inside there
Encana creating this
Private low power
What is your thought about
Laura there sick Fox
Subway
Wide area network
These nuts
Are you already saying that with some of the deportment shavings
2g or NB iot
Will coexist in the same way
Now carriers have been working now for the last
Gosh
I want to say almost a decade
I started reporting about you no like
The carriers
Wi-Fi app
And they're definitely strategies
5G coming
What kind of blend licensed and unlicensed together
Seamless
Consumer Packaging
So is that what you see happening with some of these
Is unlicensed
Low power
Yeah I think you just too
So how do you say
What you'll come down to me it's not necessarily the technology
Konosuba Syracuse that you got
Where you can get it
Under the security that comes with the offer
Service-based differentiation
It will be around technology
I think that sums up the iot
It's service it's your work clothes
Technology is
All right
Thank you so much
On the show this way
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news please sign up for me
My newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com thanks for
Listening and we'll see you next week