Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
Awesome show for you this
We might call it
Vitastiq
Because we are going to be talking about news bits from Eva we've got a company that just raised a lot of money to help you in your home
Ares God of course smart speaker news because this is a day that ends
Why
And Kevin and I are going to talk about some
I don't know user experience
Challenges we faced in the last
That you'll probably want to stick around for
After that
We've got a message from this week
Sponsor of pharaoh and our guests who is
Chris Young this
CEO of Chef
What steps you can be talking about the
Joule sous vide cooker
Why it doesn't have an interface and his strategy about
Weather today
Go to load or license
With someone else
All of this
What's a good recipe
Now let's hear from
This week's weather
Looking for an iot platform
Find out my Kenmore and D-Link
Picked a pharaoh
A pharaoh customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99% pure
Support calls
In a 10x
Higher activation
Plus
They can never use 90% of their work from one project to the neck
To learn more visit a pharaoh
Dot IO
That's a fair o a f e r o
Okay
Heaven
I know it's Eva
But first
Actually let's just talk about Eva
Let's just get started this is a giant
Home Appliance
And houseware show in
In Germany
And up until a few years ago
It was not even on my radar
But
With the era of
The connected Home Smart appliances and even things like
The Amazon Echo
If I had become a
Huge trade show for us
I would have gone but
I'm actually going on vacation
Tomorrow so I'd
Yeah it's
I've actually follow it for a long time because it reminds me of like the
International version of
CSN degrees held in Berlin every year and aside from the stuff we talked about on this show there are laptops in
Mobile devices
And so on so forth
Things that I cover elsewhere so there's a ton of stuff I made when I get out there
But no
I know now we're still going to hear if I just started so we're still going to be hearing news
Will cover probably neck
Score in the newsletter
But for now
With some smart speaker news
Harman Kardon
Which is now owned by Samsung actually announced a $600 Google Assistant
Speaker at feels like a lot of money
Yeah but
I mean it
You're buying is for sound quality the Google assistant is kind of like
Well I guess it's becoming table States these days for speaker in a sentence
You know when you can get a Google home Max for $200 less this has
200 watt stereo speakers
Support high definition audio streaming has an LCD
Touch panel at the top so this is definitely a high end
Device I assume it sounds good haven't heard it obviously but it is strange to me that
Harman Kardon is making a Google Assistant speaker when they are owned by Samsung
I guess they in a good way they're keeping that line still
Semi agnostic
Yes although I would say this is
I'm a little concerned because remember when Sonos was talkin
The information actually did a story several months back about
Sonos being able to do both madhumeh which is what we call the Amazon Echo as a
Assistant to avoid setting off
Assistant everywhere so they wanted to add madhumeh and the Google
And to do that they shared a bludgeon Google with
Patents
And
What I'm
Certain about is you might have several speakers but you're not going to have
Voice assistant
On that one
Speaker even though technically it is very doable
What it is very doable and it becomes I think a political battle between the companies that provide the voice services and
Have they said his son has said that they're not doing the Google Assistant know cuz they did say by the end of the year so I'm kind of holding out
You know they are
They are still doing it but
To get get the ability to make a madame a speaker and a Google Assistant speaker they actually asserted their patent
Smart speaker technology
The series The kooples using it in the Google Max
I don't
Those are deep inside or negotiations
So I don't know how that exactly
It does make em like
You know I don't want to have to
To pick and choose
If I really want awesome sound
You know that's expensive
To have a matinee version and a
Google Assistant version
Absolutely
No I don't either but
Hey if you want to spend even more money you can because did you see the Bang & Olufsen
Speakers with the Google Assistant built in
Yes
That was
Neat looking
Like all of bang it all
Did it look like it was worth $1,750
No no didn't know this only get you
Google right
That is correct
Yeah
Sono
I'm going with them knowing
We say no
All right but
There is another option
There's booze
Which also introduced a new smart speaker and Sound Bars
And I really don't know
Like
This what does Amazon
Matinee
And
Leader voice assist
Since we'll follow
And
Also AirPlay 2 for simple streaming from
Apple devices
That's going to happen next
As well write the interesting thing are there voice assistants to follow
Now the question is
Will it be Google would it be Bixby would it be Cortana
Yeah I don't know
And I look
Looking for prices on these
And I don't
$100
Dollars okay
So this is our mid-range
No that's her low-end actually right now
Speaker for a large speaker area
So large speaker in The Sound Bars there's a
The small one and big one
Retailing for roughly 550 + 8
Yay
All right we're not a speaker show
Train to Busan 2
Crazy stuff you could do in the home front
So
Eve
Barry
Sensor maker for homekit
Devices
They actually launched a homekit air quality Mount
A t v that
Measures temperature humidity
Air quality it's actually really tiny like
Lot of their Eve sensors it's about
I don't know half the size of a cell phone
And this is their room to
And it's going to cost
$100
So
Kind of
Actually that's exactly how much I paid for my oh where
Glow that measures all of these
What I like about this is that it's a small
Units and
Doesn't run on
Power cord
And some people might say well that kind of sucks
Because
Charge it or change batteries yes you do that's correct but
You can move it from room to room much easier I think that anywhere
And
That makes it very handy
Yes and worth noting
That this is the
First thing launched since Eve actually
Split
Gaming Division and ditched it Salgado
Saudis used to be Elgato Eve
Interstate in June
Banda June
They actually created Eve systems
Only focus on the
Worth noting so this is the first one everything else is old
And moving right along to
You crazy
Stuff from
Bosch
Holy moly
Okay
I got so excited by
Weird Ibiza so we turned into Rai
Oh I never know
It's Chris Christ he is a scene at home reporter he's a lovely fellow
We read about the time he's been on the show
So he actually
Tweeted
Cannabis presser
A bunch of stuff
Including
Induction cooktops with intelligence
So you could understand if you're
Burning stuff
For cooking stuffed
Too hot which
I thought was really
And he also showed off
Schecter
And it's basically a projector that projects
An image that you can interact with on your countertop
Okay
I thought I sent
So excited
Because I actually saw the
The semiconductor that made this possible in the Bosch booth
Yes
I did a whole story on it
Super stoked because
This thing was amazing UK
You
If you put this
Since they're showing is a standalone unit but if you put this you've put this on like an Amazon Echo or something like that it actually could show you
You video
You can show you video on any surface
You could move your hand up and down and the resolution changed
Seamlessly and then you could interact with
So imagine if you could say if your doorbell rang in
You could turn and put your nest
Doorbell camera
Image into this
It could just show it to you on your counter
So that's cool
Write absolute
What school is you could actually all the controls right now like we're very excited about the
Controls on the Lenovo
Smart display for things like lights
Because you can take
Haji
Turn on the lights
And then it'll show you
A control
4like color tuning or thinks
Like that to me if you imagine that popping up on your counter via this type of
Splayed then you just
Like to it right there on the counter
Yeah this is it's interesting
Because there's a whole Suite of apps that you can have it it really looks to me like they've taken the open-source version of Android and crew
Created their own little interface with it but I mean you could even use
I mean they're showing a video not a video picture of
Yeah the Chrome browser in Pinterest and all that
Do all that without a display because the Earth countertop is the display and I presume there's some kind of
And what kind of sensors they would have in the projection part itself but to allow you the interaction refit interact
With these apps and so on for recipes or
Who knows what I meant I like the idea of it I don't know that I would just
Put this on my countertop but I could see it as a future thing especially as they
Tweet this idea and implementation
If I get reminds me of the very last CS that Bill Gates was that he showed the quote-unquote home of the future
And they had projection balls so you can
Change the look and feel of you know what your view is like
Pretend you're in the middle of the ocean
What is all interactive and they had a projection on the countertop that you could you know through recipes and so on
Okay so don't just think about recipe
Is think about something like an interactive cooking demonstration
That if you
Put something underneath it
It could tell you like
Hey
Here's how to cut the chicken and it
Show like lions where you
Chop your chick
So imagine kind of like an
AR on
On top of
Your actual
And that's along the lines of what he showed it was kind of like you put a certain amount of food in a spot and a projector wood
Visualize it the density and someone say you need a little bit more that's too much of this recipe
You're right when you start melding
AI
And sensors and
Get rid of the screens have projection there something you can do
Yeah I'm super high on projector
I have been
So I love this guy
If it's like a r without the glasses
Yeah basically
Although in a limit
Like this
You'll have your induction charging spot and then you'll have your projection spot and then you'll have your I don't know what's
Bosch also shut off a washer and dryer that basically you just
Throw stuff in it it senses what it is and it says this is the type of wash you should do this
This is how much soap I need
Dispense this feels like something I have to
Maybe tahini laundry is not
This could be like a revelation
Remember the June and when I got this I was like even might toast taste better you guys
And that was a function of like really opt
Optimizing for that part
Everything with
Washing
Baby there is better washing and I just don't do it no notice it overtime that my clothes are cleaner and maybe they're less
What's the word I'm looking for
Born by washing
But it feels like
I don't know that I know
What I need
Jhene Aiko
Right and this is a big part of
The IRT conundrum we don't know what we don't know yet it's almost like
Until you implement something
You want don't know that it's better or maybe it's not it will save it that's a big Challenger
Self-hating wouldn't Bosch
I want to test this out
See if it acts
What color
That was the fridge any of the fridges come in different colors that are replaceable doors as well
Cuz it's not really technically iot but Bosch also did show off these
Refrigerator doors that you can swap out in their different colors
I love color so I was really a
Excited by this
But again there's no spark
Associated with this
I know I brought it up just cuz you were so excited about
Not as excited
But that's okay
All right
So let's move from FIFA those are the big things we've seen so far that
Exciting let's talk about a 50 billion dollar funding for a company called pulse
Technologies
Pulse
These guys basically come in and
Hang your television
They even program your smart lights
Send apparently this is a bang-up business first
Yeah they got about 2500 vetted professionals
In 50 Metro areas to get them kind of like the Best Buy Geek Squad what they are
Train to do pretty much anything here
A smart home
Service is
Part of the deal so they can set things up for you probably help you with routines assistance Etc
Send some people leave that enough
You don't even know where
Still more oven DIY kind of thing with these devices available you know if
She's at Walmart Target and everywhere else
Some people still look like
I don't even know how to set it up
So you got to think about like
What was it we had Charlie Kendall who was the head of the Amazon Echo smart home platform
For a long time go over to control for which is very much a professional answer
So you know I can see how
There's a limited layer of us
That are willing to go to
Later and there's probably a lot of us who if you can make it affordable would totally be like you
Please come in
I'll give you you know maybe I don't know if the prices like closer to like $2,000 to outfit my home and make it
Get smart you think that's a reasonable price
Maybe it depends on the home how many devices what you want the waypost as it is that this is
Flat fee for the service depending on the type of job
They must be doing okay though because apparently their text
Between 70 and 80000 a year
That's Not Unusual I mean
You're messing around with lots of stuff
So I'm on their website and it looks like
The way they do it is
If I want to do a smart home thing I basically pick a zip code so we can get the
Pricing I'm assuming that New York cost more than Austin
And it's like hey
Do you have a thermostat
And I'm like
Yes I want install that
Do you have Smart Home devices
What kind
It looks like they don't have
Electricians
Because they don't do any
Lighting
Aunt that is like a light switches
Which is kind of a pain cuz that's a lot of the problems
People have but they do support like SimpliSafe
Security they have a bunch of baby monitors
Cameras
August door locks ring doorbell
Detarius hubs
So that's kind of a bummer
Yeah maybe.
Expand that cuz if I recall these guys are actually like
Smartphone repair
Best internet expanded into this
Sector
So maybe this is a future Edition for them is to add Electrical Services
Because that is actually a
Competitive advantage
Or like
Comcast when I talk to them about their installernet
Working like that's awesome you have this
It's a very big deal but they don't have a
Electricians and
That
How is a really convenient thing to have someone who can install light switches
Just for you order Outlets
That's just my take one of the more painful things I have to do is install Outlets
So maybe that's just me
Maybe that's just me
Okay
So
These guys got a lot of money
What else is
Oster some changes coming to the Google app
Assistant 95 Google took a look at the latest
File installation for Google Assistant
I don't know if it's nothing released yet
They're seeing bits of code revealing household family mode and downtime
So it looks like we got some adjustments coming there or some improvement
Since they're so that's good
I'm chasing household will let you kind of
Put different people's personal information together in the home you know
I appreciate that
You know they got it right and do this
But I will say every time they update something
I have to
Like they're adding basically a new user interface
Austin away and then suddenly like half the time I find it I have now
If I want to use this new functionality I have named my devices
Does poorly or maybe
Put them in the wrong
Rooms
Or I need to put them in rooms
So the sounds terrible this iterative process I'm not sure it's working really well for
Are people and I think they probably just give up
Cuz I know that sometimes I just look at this and I'm like oh
I'm not going to connect this
Google home because I already have something called the front door and that's the lock and now I've got to have a doorbell called
Light called this
Synonym like
Yeah we're going to talk about this little more later but I'm right there with you with some recent challenges on these
Updates and changes in the First Reactions
So yeah I don't know the answer because it's like
Don't do it
Wait install it professionally I mean I do want them to iterate on things right that's a
Jumping ahead
Last little bit of news for us is Google Assistant now can control your nest by Yale lock
Organys
Because
I tried this and perhaps it's just not
Rolled out yet
Maybe it's a rolling release
But
My home app is not even
Show the
Nest
Buy a lock
It does show my Nest hello doorbell
And it shows my nest
Camera
So Stacy suggested wisely you know what
I think you've got to unlink
Your nest
Products from Google home a demand account back and then it should appear
So I did that
But in doing so
I need to get the verification code Nest will send you free SMS when you add an account to Google home
And it never came
Okay well I should say never about 30 minutes later we'd already given up it came so I finally re-added
The Nest back to Google home
And guess what happened
It's not there
It's still not there so
Maybe just rolling out with the whole fact that you have to unlink accounts just to add new devices
Is Eminem
Maybe will magically disappear
Google home for me
Mine has not met so I have one
And I have linked to my Google home account
To my nest
Account it is not magically appear
Okay what when it does
If and when it does you should be able to
Query your Google home
To see if the front door or the front door any door the lock is locked or not
And you can lock it by voice
For security reasons
They have decided to not allow voice unlocking at this
Before start complaining
Kevin would you like
To talk about the new device that you tried
I would love to talk about
I tested out and still testing out the Phillips
Hue Lily spotlight
I'll tell you right up front what you get they are
LED outdoor spots
And a low voltage
Plug-in Transformer so you literally just plugged into an outlet they are weather resistant so they obviously they could be outside
It's $280
For these
If you would like to add additional
Spots
They are $80 each and I know that sounds odd because you're like what wattage is by
Free
Regular spots because you don't get the
A Transformer with a single
LED
Spot
Transformer can handle up a 5 spotlights
Being from Philips Hue
You got your choice
16 million colors
The nice thing about these you can control each
Color
Honeyspot individually
So I kind of celebrating Christmas for example with one red and one green eye
Last night which everybody was walking by going what are you doing and I said okay I'll put it back to White
So you got all your choice of the colors and regular white
Set up pretty easy I like how they've done that they've made a wiring heavy duty and these connectors will you
Connect and
Screw in the
Wire to the next wire it's very simple you cannot not do it correctly it's impossible to do wrong
So that part is easy
Is about 15 ft in between each
Anywhere
Scrapy
However I don't know maybe it's my home
I could not
Connect this
2eather matinee
Google assist
I was successful with
Siri and
Home Care
So that worked out fine but I don't know why I could not connect this
True either my other assistants for my wake up
So
Not sure this requires the Philips Hue Bridge which is not included so hopefully you already have one
If not I can take over about 60 bucks
And pre-teen just like any other
Set of bulbs you know it's very similar just meant for outdoors
And you had a hue Bridge
I do have a Hubert sent to me all these are loaner units yes
One Challenge
That I had during setup I said it was easy and it was but for some reason not the bridge but the bulbs themselves
Needed a firmware up
Update and it said right in the app this could take up to an hour
And I told you say so you're like I haven't felt I'm sorry quick
It wasn't quick it was like 30 minutes
30 minutes to get that firmware update pushed over I guess because of the zigbee connection
Yes signius
Is that happened but that is a constant Source actually for me
With my shoes
I very rarely going
NBA app
Cuz I have home
Factory automated
So it is inevitable that when I want to do something
Like a little
Fancy
I turned it the app
Inevitably there is an update
Waiting for me
And that I can't do what I want to do
Until I
Download
The update
I kind of wish those were automatic I understand why they might not be
Because sometimes when they do an update the lights to flash
For example dated at 2 a.m. and I was sleeping in my lights only flash tan I would be
Upset so I can get where like
As a manufacturer there when do we let the
Control passed to the user versus us doing it
But it is
And that is a long time
And speaking of frustrating
Let's talk about some frustration
So this week I have had
Two devices do software update
Broken functionality
It makes me sad
The first is my Tesla
I don't know what
There is some update and now
My garage door won't
Open the Homelink
Functionality does not work on
And I can't reprogram it
I can't do anything
And so basically
This is very much a first world problem probably a one percenter problem
Not actually 1-percenter but
I get this is not something
Is attic about
I don't have to use my garage door opener
My car does not automatically open the garage door anymore
Because
Can a lot of money for this car
I don't really have a lot of recoil
Of course I called the Tesla people in there going to
I'll look into it but
It's a little frustrating to have something work one day and then the next.
Yeah software updates in general it's
Hit or miss you know you'd hope things are tested but is every single function tested somebody test the Homelink feature
Probably not because it changes are likely not related
To it but something broke something is what it sounds like
So the other asp
Is
Frustrating is my June oven
Y'all my June oven
The device I thought could do no wrong
And I still love it but
It didn't update to add some
Actually really good functionality that's more instructions for people like where to put the
The temperature probe when you're trying to cook
It shows you a picture
Nice
Because some people that were like
My food isn't done and I'm like
Kitchen start at deeply enough in the right spot and they're like no insert the probe
So that was good but somehow
I don't know how
It no longer recognizes
Does my toast
My brand of bread
So it keeps telling me I put my bread in the oven
To toast it
And it's like
Is a strudel or a poptart
Is Pop-Tarts and salmon one of the other cuz they're both kind of square
Oh yeah yeah
So it's not strudel it's not Pop-Tarts
It's toast and it used to recognize it
It needs to be all cool if you like oh
The bread and
Four pieces of it do you want me to toast
Lately or
Medium or whatever
But now I have to press
Again
Not the end of the world
Nobody
But it's not functioning the way you expect as you are was functioning
Totally agree
I'm going to take a wild guess here though because I actually had a problem with my June oven as well Reese
Mine was not preheating anything you would literally
Set a temperature in normally would say
Pre-heating
But it just wasn't preheating
They would just start cooking
And that's not good because that's not the right temperature yet
The good thing about the June there support people are fantastic
Tandoori over there help me out
They're all good they're all good but somehow I always get to where the thing is they can actually
Delete with your permission
Go and look at the logs
Of
The oven see everything that happened
Which is awesome for finding problems and they found a problem with one of my heating elements one time before and
Literally just sent me a brand new oven
You know they paid to send that and send back the other one
So they found that out from the logs in this case
The problem that I had anymore wondering if it's related
Christine
Camera up top of the oven
Gets eventually covered with
Stuff
You have to at least clean the camera off and I'll tell you why because the June my June was functioning as
Design it doesn't see any food
In there that's how it goes to preheat
Because they were struts on the camera said we must be something here I don't know what it is but
Let's start cooking
So
That's what happened to me and sure enough
After checking the log
We determined that was my issue I clean off the camera
And I got my preheat function back
100% of the time so it could be the food ID is not quite right because you're not giving it
Best data
OKC and that's a very analog problem
I love it okay
D'usse try that and then go down the South
And I was thinking
Another aspect of
Especially with
And you'll see because I have the CEO of chefsteps
Which makes the
Joule sous vide
I was thinking about some of their recipes so
June
Creates these pre-selected
Recipes for you so you just
Pop salmon in and say
Hadist I want it done and it just does it
But those things get tweaked over time
I was thinking band what if I really liked
One way they cooked it and they change that recipe over time and then
Suddenly It's just slightly different and maybe not as good
And you may not there's not a lot of
Transparency
So
You may just be like huh
What's happened here
I was thinking about that
Because I was thinking about changing
The sous-vide and suddenly I was like I kind of have lost all control over how things
Thanks might taste
But most of it is better so that's an okay tradeoff
I don't know these are things
Yeah I know you're right it's not transparent because the algorithms get tweet
Is all the information from device owners
It's crowdsource on the cooking results and such
So
I guess when we took a stake it tastes the same for everybody as a June oven
Cooking a steak
And I would love I'm pretty sure I suggested it on the
User forum
He let me save
The cooking method
Because that's how I like it
Right you did it right but all the sudden it changed and all I wanted the way that used to be so let me save that
Yes
Basically your own personal rollbacks on
I like it
Okay which is only useful for
Things that are not security-related that's
Probably have
You got a patch
But other than that
Okay
Well this was our
Yes weekly complain session
We don't usually complain very much but
Monthly
So let's go to Riot
She podcast listener hotline for a question from you guys
The iot podcast
Listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Don't miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wi-Fi at
We are giving those away through the end of this month to enter all you have to do is call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7424 and ask us a question
And we will
Are you into the drawing
This month's drawing actually ends Friday at midnight eastern time so Friday August 31st
Pikachu
Basically a day-and-a-half
Tacoma's and remember
Smarter homes
Starfish leg
As of last week we answered a question from the a listener about tracking his
And we gave many options but we kind of forgot a really obvious one in
A bunch of guys called us on it
So thank you
We forgot about life
Which is a really good app that it is an app that you can put on your phone it also integrates with lots of services like if this
Send that it has a deal with BMW has a deal with some
Security companies in basically this app lets you see where your kids are
Where any of your family
And it can be really useful and if you use it with f
When your kids get within your house range they can actually give you an alert
So David include some nice pictures like a group chat
Fear family and such within the app
So
Guys we didn't talk about that
Because it's not a thing but we should have because it does talk to things
What is a thing
Is the thing on your phone
Okay
So this week's question comes to us from
Donna
Hey guys
Doncic
My question for you is
Is it against
I'm wondering
Is there something you can think of
I could either make
Or by
The budget of
Lesson about fish
Dollars
Love you good gifts
For someone who is moving into a college dorm
So the money is leaving home
Moving into a dorm
I'd love to hear your ideas
Project
Show
Oh. Free question and Kevin actually just wrote a story last week about how to out
Take your kids to worm with some smart stuff so you should definitely check that out
But it sounds like this isn't your kids are just trying to be a thot
4% witch
Amazing
So we try to come up with some equally thoughtful
Ideas for you that are
Beyond Justice
Plant sow
Kevin came up with
I really don't want
Well it's a potentially good one it depends on the person that you're buying for
This past weekend I move my
Daughter into Kutztown University for her
First-year College one thing I noticed
A lot of the kids
Walking around with water bottles
There was a hot day I will say that but you know they weren't carrying a Starbucks cup they were carrying their own water bottle
So I thought you know what Stacy has a bunch of water bottles I'll bet you there's an inexpensive one
It's kind of connected to help you track your hydration for under fifty bucks and I think you found one
It is called the hydrate
Hi
Dra.
Spark
To. O
There are two of these
One is $50
But that's right
The edge of your price range there so I say go for the $45 one
Is Bluetooth
It links to an app
And it
The Lowe's
When you need to drink more
So it starts blowing and it also integrates with Fitbit Apple watch
Other things
So basically as you drink
That water's going to get transferred into your Fitbit data and
As you need to drink it'll start
Chloe which actually might be kind of disruptive so think about it in a darkened classroom or movie theater you may want to turn that glow
Low functionality off
Oh I wouldn't
I got a battery-powered Hue Spotlight I'm taking with me to the movies
So that was one option another I was looking for a bluetooth light bulb
That had a remote
Because I thought it'd be nice to have a
Light bulb
That you could put in something like a lamp
And be able to turn it off
Even if the switch is across the
The real or
At night
But I couldn't find a Bluetooth one that had a remote
So if anyone else
Found one
Let me know I did find some on Amazon but I can't say that
Use them or heard of anybody that uses them and almost all of them they did have remotes
But almost all of them also had a speaker built in which actually might be nicer
Tazewell for playing
Some music
But I cannot speak to the quality of the morning like that
So I found
I recommend
The
Ikea
Tradfri
For $50 you can
Barely get away with it
So there is a dimmer and a bulb
And then you have to buy the hub for $30
If that appeals to you
It's going to have a Wi-Fi component I was trying to avoid
But I couldn't
So those are the two things that we thought might be a good gift for someone going away to college that are under $50
We also found one other thing that you may love or hate
T Phillips
Makes a wake up light alarm clock
With a sunrise
It also has a clock in there
So this is
About 50 bucks on Amazon there are more expensive models
Colors that basically you set your alarm and it can make noise but it doesn't have to
It can also
That is that it would
Light up
Instead so this might be good if you have a roommate
That you know
Doesn't like
To wake up as early as you do
And it might also be a nice way for someone who may not be used
Used to getting up in the morning on their own
Kind of
Set up an alarm that's loud and also a force function with the lady
I don't know
There's another ID
Okay Donna I hope that helps
End
Guys if you guys think of any
What is that
All right
I think it is
Now time for us to
Take a break for a bit
Message from our sponsor and stick around because after that we are going to be talking to
To Chris Young the CEO of chefsteps
About why he didn't put it in her face on the Joule sous vide cooker
We're going to tell you about what the heck sous vide
Actually is
And
His decision to
Go it alone as opposed to licensing
With large Appliance vendor
Aldis
And more in a moment
Hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Cancer is a
Pharaoh
And I have Joe Britt
CEO of a feral here
To get started why don't you describe a pharaoh for
A pharaoh is a sensor to Cloud IO
Party platform
We really take a lot of pride in
The fact that it really just
Works our customers tell us that it's the best choice for them for a fantastic end-user experience
And great developer productivity
I think a lot of this comes
From the fact that a bunch of acid of pharaoh came from places like apple nest
Google Android or Netflix and we really wanted to bring the best of engineering and design disciplines from the
Those previous
Experiences into iot
We've been talking for the last few weeks about a pharaoh and how some of its customers such as Kenmore and D-Link
Camping using your software to cut 80%
Off their time-to-market
And giving them the ability to reuse 90%
Of their works
Someone project
This is really exceptional
So let's focus today on what you guys do with the
Back end of
Iot system
You can really think of Artie and three big parts
There's first the supply chain
Which is all about the sea
Security and efficiency
Actually
Building a
Then you've got the
Device in
Which has to do with the security and Wade that particular device communicates
But then we reach the part that you
The back
And the backend device
Is really the engine room of
The system and it's all about how
Responsive
Scalable and how resilient the system is insecurity has to undergo
And all of that
Many end-user complaints that we
We heard can ultimately be traced
2 problems with the back end the back end is the part that guides the
Policy and business logic and is triggered by different events that translate ultimately into the vital control
And asset data for an application
So what happens to device
Stata when it arrives
This is critical
The data has to be processed instantly
So the end-user feels like they're just using
Normal or traditional remote control and he can't be something that takes seconds and seconds to respond
So we've got to take into account
Whole round trip
The traffic
Plus acting on whatever the
Particular command was and implementing whatever the
The policies are there relevant to that command
We have to squeeze all of this down in
2 millisecond
This demands
I truly elasticum
Implementation that is extremely optimized
In terms of processing
Achieve that
The data also has
Be structured properly
So that once we retrieve it we can easily feed it into different Analytics
Machine learning tool
And then we have to scale all of that
Up to thousands
Millions of devices
Without sacrificing any of that responsiveness or security then on top of the whole thing
We have to make it super reliable and that means High availability
Multi-zone multi cloud implementations
That sounds like a lot so where can people go to find out more
In about a pharaoh
The best place
To start is a pharaoh.
Slash go big
That's
AF yarrow
Dot IO
/ go
Big
And if you're a developer
Please also check out developer. Afero. IO
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is
Young who is this
CEO and co-founder at
Chefsteps
Hi Chris how are you doing
I'm doing great
You're having me on today
All right
I am super excited because
You guys
Not only are you a recipe site
But you are also
The maker of the Joule sous vide
Booker and I've been playing with us for a while
Okay let's kick it off with why you guys decided to basic
Invent a
Internet connected
Cooking device
Sure it's not the most obvious
Project that supposedly we didn't start as a Huntington recipe
Late 2011 early 2012 and we had a real Folk
Modernist approaches
Cooking because I had been too cooperative.
We started this
Videos up on YouTube
Cookie recipes
Stuff.com
And the real point was to see if anyone
Interested if anybody you know
Would follow what
And that was about as far as
The really good news was it turned out there was a huge Global audience
Dewberry very quickly
And a lot of
Custom content videos
The information we were providing
And there was a real
That we were clearly serving
Okay before we go any further we should probably tell everybody what sous vide
Chevy cooking is I think about it is just the way of adding a measured amount of
A recipe for that food is never older cook
Or under
And it's a technique that used and many of the best restaurants
Around the world and even many restaurants does it surprise you
Usually in some sort of flexible food grade plastic bag of your vacuum sealed bags
FoodSaver you didn't put the food into a water bath
You have some device
Marquesa Jewel suvee cooker
Temperature for the doneness
You want so if
Do you want your steak medium rare you might put it in the water
The water might heat up
Tuesday 122 degrees 124 degrees Fahrenheit
The water and when you're ready to eat you can take the food out and give it a quick
Beer and you're going to have a steak this better than I would say probably 95% of all dressed
You would go to
Because the food is actually going to have no risk of being overcooked and it's relatively simple
Okay
So from the website
You decided that people are interested especially in sous vide
Yeah so we decided ultimately
We recognize it was a real
I'll need to have a better p
Piece of sushi Hardware that we could see that no matter how much cost
After we put in education
Should we give people the most accurate thermostat
Ever had in their kitchen before
The problem is
Nobody else
Set it to 2 degrees difference
A pretty big difference in the final outcome
Or that chicken
And you know what we saw was everything
The time was a direct descendant of Laboratory
Gadget
Intimidating
And we need the benefits
Tremendous
Professional
Habits to be tremendously helpful to Homefront
But you're going to need
To have a piece of Hardware it was designs in the ground up
Be more helpful to home
Not forcing
We did spend some time talking to other Hardware manufacturers about this because
Our eyes were recently wide open about whatever
Make a hardware device
Ourselves but after spending several months
Leading Hardware manufacturers became convinced that they didn't see the same vision that we did for what was
Possible
In terms of creating internet-connected devices
It would actually be there till
Help them get the most out of their tools
We're going to make the device
We safe to be an actual cooking tool that's really going to empower
That was supposed to be goal and it was
Still pretty naive about making
You opened it right up
Let's talk about
One of the things that we thought was important as we didn't want it to be a gadget
We wanted it to be
What is a professional chef
The knife for example
Play the tool I reline a tie
Use it all the time it is
Central Perk
Do my job
You might look at a bread maker
Who bought one maybe comes out once a year and then it goes to
The back of the cupboard and never get
It again
We didn't want to be
All in the back
We knew how beautiful
Holiday today
Understand
People's Kitchen
And you know
Countertop real estate or top-drawer real estate
Really really valuable
And things need to be compact
CB devices wait about 9 or 10
Towns they were relatively enormous
Reskin Laboratory
We set out with the
Small enough that it could fit in that top drawer easy to grab
Quick to use on a Wednesday night
But one of the challenges
Sous vide is your heating water
And anybody who has a background in physics
Tremendous amount of heat energy
Teresa Teng
The power of a light bulb
We're dealing with you
1100 Watts
Power Wiki
Maybe about 80% of what you can even take out of an outlet
Please check the device down.
Small enough to fit into a countertop door needs to be about an inch and 3/4 deep
You're sinking
Huge amount of power
Smaller
Smaller surface area
Tiny heater core
80% of the water
A nuclear reactor core
Actually pull that off
We had to invent some
Proprietary New Heating technology
Even make that possible so these are in retrospect there was a lot of goo
We thought we could do that those are just some of the engineer
Let you know we wrangled with
Trying to figure out how do you be a hardware
Actually want to tell people I'm cooking with nuclear fission
I know
I'm right
Let's talk about one of the controversial decision
You guys made
Because I'll be honest when I pulled out the jewel I was like hey there's just this one button on the top and
I don't actually I'm not a huge lover of screen to my smartphone to
Pest control things so I kind of looked askance
The fact that this
$180 or $200 device that had no interface without
I will say that was a contra
Botanica
Wasn't taken light
It was polarized
In fact I think when we first launched I remember reading
Comments on the subreddit
Sous vide
This decision should be dragging the
Shotwell
Whoever that person was
And the person you want to go out
The reason for that
We did as good a job as we
Lights up.
Explaining your customers why we met
This goes back to
Werecognizeyou
Keep things up
Luke heat energy around the real opportunity was to
Devices
Because if you think about it
Every technology we have
The average home kitchen
Is actually recognized
It hasn't changed that much
And all of them require you to translate what you want I want
My check in Taiwan
Christmas Canon
I want it done at 7:30 you have to translate that into
Engineer parameters like should the oven be
How long will it
This is where a lot of
Fusion comes up
Opportunity
What's the actually create a way of interacting
What devices does a fundamentally more human weigh
You could express your crap
Princes of Hell won't mistake to look like this I want to eat it
This time and you didn't have to translate that necessarily into knowing that that means
Probably want your water Bassett
28 degrees Fahrenheit
Putting a manual temperature
Or you can just look at the image
Which of the following human vocabulary
The one I want
The texture of that short
Rib that looks right to me
Here's how my food is that
Geometric information
It looks like the food will be done at this
Pulled over
2% right
We also
Depersonalized
Because different people would want to post advice in different ways by moving all those
Bulldog
Ability to make the device better over time
It gave us the Opera
To think about new ways to interact such as
We have now
Because voice when your hand
Voices of phenomena way of communicating with your device
Baby apple juice phone there's information
Another way
Preverbal
Why we know some people would like to have that fish
We basically felt it
The trade-offs
Worth living things
We were really interested in finding the customers who bought into this idea
More devices
Create new features we can get better over time and that's really the long-term View
Just about Joule sous-vide device there will be other Hardware there will be other services
We wanted to demonstrate
The kitchen can actually leverage software in a way
It allows you to
More
Make it more human not less human because there are things
Computers and software can do they're just really hard
Skilled professional set
That was kind of a decision behind it
And I think on some level
We could have put us
That really would have been
Thai chicken the pressure off us
Really think very hard about how to make
14 function that required us to be really good at
I need to be really focused on reliability
To really think about user experience
How does needed to work
We could have laid out but you know
As far as we can tell where the best-selling connected to be device now where the number two in the market the leading devices is large
Actually not Reliant
And that gives us
Going relationship with our customers
So that we keep getting better over time so it looks like that
Asian accent
Panned out pretty well for us
Havaianas
Totally honest
Continue to demonstrate our customers that was a good decision I continually shipping updates
Okay
So what is your thought process around if
The company goes out of business
Do you have actual things in place
Sword is everyone sous vide
To stop work
One of the nice day
Think about that in there are we've actually had
I'll be able to security pretty seriously so there are aspects of
The device where we would have to
To make it possible for other developers to support it but there are plans
Do that the infrastructure is in place simply we're using our own internal apis to do
Do these kind of things that would be relatively trivial press to open that up this is kind of the end of life for Oscar
That would be something we could do and we have seen enough
People attempt to reverse-engineer some
I'm going to basic
Acordeon Sol
That's a tricky question
Still an internal discussion of where those boundaries are how do we
Spectre customers data privacy so we're not quite ready to do
But that is something we're actively thinking about how do we
Encourage more people to keep innovating with soccer in the kitchen
And connecting your device
Put that software
Apache Corp
Along this line
Let's talk about business models for the smart
Because a lot of Kinect
Set device maker
There's a lot of innovation have
But there's also a really big establish number of vendors out there who make
The traditional home appliances
When I look at what they're trying to do it feels like
You're a pure software the intelligence you guys are built
The years might be
Well suited for GE or Whirlpool to come in and buy in
Maybe make part of
I know they don't have a sous-vide option yet but make part of their own
Kitchen ecosys
What are your thoughts around
How that's going
These companies
But we haven't yet results
Questions we have
Allow us to go forward
One of the first
Issues X
Pragmatic
A lot of the things we really want
We will have more announced
Control over the hardware the sensors
Calibration
Be able to
Provide clean data
To our various cloud services
To do things like
Cooking times
Significantly or make predictions about how the
Do you think you certainly see how they would be a
But those device manufacturers
We have to get on board
Much much better sensors in the device make the best of it
The market
$10,000 rack
If you actually test
And we did for love
You'd be surprised to find that the app
About plus or minus
Dad
It's terrible
Right
Humidity control is well so these oem's of
Kitchen Hardware
We have to get really serious about
Pretty much better
The hard work of calibrating to get
Usually reserved for
Precision lab equipment
You could imagine we could work with him on that but
Distortion everything for us
All the sudden we're really having
And most of our time working with these licensees to bring them up to where we're already
How much is
What is teams
Other issue is
We're building our own Hardware
Software
When were citic vertically integrated that way
We have real Clarity over
Lacoste
There's no ambiguity of how we make money there's no ambiguity about like whose needs are you serving
Change it
Licensing organization well
Is Electrolux a customer
Is there any
When you start to get ambiguity
In particular we want a very low structure and Bayern
Anderson in a company
Customer is always LED
Problem bad decision-making about
What's a prioritize what's a really work on
So does that
You guys kind of has a niche product or a luxury product for a while to come then
I don't think $100 a day
Without disclosing numbers and we have customers
In the six-figure range and growing rapidly
Free to continue to grow out from this week
Can't wait to grow our Revenue fast
Goodbye license yet but that's never been out
Yeah we are really focused on making sure that we are
Retaining our customers engaging them and serving them
Well over time so that they continue to be customer for years
And let's talk about additional Hardware I'm sure you're not going to
Disclosure product ramp
But let's talk about where you might
Go pure products
Lot of companies who build Hardware looking
Milky Chance
So
What are you guys think
There's a few things
Hardware's Apopka
You're always under margin pressure
And that's never going to go away and you run the risk of having your business kind of blown up by
Politically on Fallout trade Wars
Be careful of
You sign up for
When we look at it
As a professional chef I've been
College 2001
We have a long history that but we would all say
Great books
Only thing
It could be smarter in your kitchen that could actually
Do a better job
Looking out on the hardware key or act
Sibley developing tend to be complementary
Technology so for example went on a Wednesday night TV may not be fast enough or you're just not in the mood for something that might be a protein
Teen dominated milf
The ark
Free Technologies
Do heat a meal that we think can be Mass Market that can be made shame and that you can deliver on some of the same core
4 Promises of
We guaranteed Foods
Guarantee it's going to be relatively convenient to do it
And we think there's
Real meaning of ways that
Better interfaces
Facial interfaces machine learning
Actually put
Human Experience even more and make it easier for you to
Which is really dark or metric Azara
Customers choosing a cup
Or they call you
And we are looking at
Bass we are saying how can we make it easier
Pictures to cook on a Wednesday night we were playing with meal kits back in 20
Tina's Chester
Prototype then we beta-tested them with some of our community
To love them
We should have listened to we don't know when these
Economics address look right side up
So we had a team that's
Started working on that bumper few years and they had a real break
Late last year and in fact they've been building a pilot production
Facility in Seattle
1011 manufacturing the way they want to and we hope to have something to announce
In a few weeks
Ella comes out of beta but we really see this as a product
Consumable space
To choose to cook more frequently and have a greater diversity of options and have more compass
Caviar
I like that's your stand
Okay
Before we go
Let's see
What is your
Favorite thing to sous vide and give us a recommendation
For anybody who's
A novice
Austin saying
So tell us what you like to do
As a super duper complicated Chef person and then
Maybe something to convince everyone else
Sous vide might be
Okay so for the meat lovers there's two things that are free
Goat cheese for me
Beef short rib
You really want to get from ribs
4 5 and 6 that doesn't mean anything to you go talk to a butcher it will mean something to them but that's the thickest part of the short rib
You take that short ribs
You cook it at 54 degrees Celsius or you pull our visual Douglas guidance
Pictures of textures
Little wind up with this for three days
That sounds crazy
3 days book
I promise you this is one of these dishes at tends to change people wise the first day and they have it
Especially
Is just so much more flavor
In a short Redmond sale ribeye or especially a flaming yawn but three days of cooking in a very low temperature Converse All That
In the short rib
The tender gelatin without making it
Play Ear braised and you end up something is very steak like
The tender filet mignon in
Ugly delicious
Play something more easy
Weeknight you usually can find in supermarkets
Pork shoulder steaks that usually at uppercut
Flavorful but you drop those in the morning when you
You go to work and
Cook them they'll be
Incredibly tender when you get home
Perfect medium-rare
Really it's hot pork should be cooked
I really recommend adding up
Char sui sauce to the bags
Candy at the end for those who are not
Beats
Lentils and
Asparagus
Are just vegetables or grain preparation
Can really benefit from CBD cooking chicken with the grain
What's nice
Leave them in the fridge
Easily up to a month
So you can have a really quick meal for together
What you want
And to get The Machinist out of them
They're really great
Beat you retain their natural sweetness
Earthy flavors
Little goat cheese for salad
Maybe some toast it
Conn's
Classic restaurant
Starter and it's delicious
Asparagus
Is one of these things where
It really just needs to be lightly cooked you wanted to snap but you don't want it
He stood
You don't really want to cook it in anything other than it
On juices maybe a knob of butter so asparagus is one of these things where
It will be much better.
Asparagus you typically getting a restaurant that has been steamed
Color now in Gilbert
Christmas and precious. I love about you
Okay
You guys didn't know you were listening to a cooking
There you go
All right
Chris thanks so much for
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
Remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week