Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have some awesome news starting
The end of the Qualcomm broadcom Intel
Wechat iot devices set a new legal presidents
We got a new Edge Computing platform Google Assistant routines are now alive
And we have a smorgasbord
I've new devices including
A sprinkler a security camera
A new Raspberry Pi and
A light switch that
Fox 2 madame
We got some funny stories from Kevin
Any creepy conclusion to this segment of
But then
We light it up with our guests Toby meet up from bear
Who's going to be talking about iot and agriculture
Put lighter and how it relates to insect
And we'll have a message from our sponsor Samsung artik
Add how it secures
The internet of things so
Let's kick this off with the message from another one of our sponsors
Iot world you're invited to iot World premiere event for iot business and technology
It's May 14th through 17th is Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon Valley and cellar
Prettiest fifth anniversary in the show welcomes over 12,000 iot professionals
450 speakers and 300 exhibitors and startups
Where is all about putting iot into action how to build a winning strategy Implement that strategy effectively
And drive results to learn more and register to attend visit iot world event
Rent.com
Okay Kevin
Man
I should warn everyone I have a cold so Lord only knows what's going to happen to my voice this show
Bear with us
It gets too bad I'll just make him do the rest
Shamanism
Oh goodie
Let's kick it off with
Qualcomm and broadcom
The deal
Is
Dead
It's done the deal is done but not in the way people expect
Give it to me
So Kevin and I have actually been going back and forth
Before we record the show actually talked about it this week
I know
So we held off we talked about it when it first was announced back in November of last year
Because this was a huge consolidation of chipmaker's especially related to the
Broadcom makes the chip
In the Raspberry Pi
WiFi chips
Yes they also have networking
Capability
He's a swell but
Our purposes
Broadcom iot
Qualcomm however has been getting
Into
The iot and most of its chips because they were focused on mobile for so long and
Did so well there
A lot of its ships have just been
Popped into iot devices are actually working really hard to make things like
Embedded module of snapdragon
The Snapdragon 820 that we talked about
I think a few weeks back
This deal with
Consolidated
A significant amount
So
I'm actually glad it didn't happen because broadcom is
Private Equity play they are just mooching together lots and lots of Chip companies in
Frankly
I don't think
Did they have the focus on innovation
Qualcomm has had
Forever
Broadcom used to have big focus on integration but
That is
Subsequently
Died the most of their I don't want synchros but I use it for lack of a better word has come from Acquisitions and
Just getting into different markets as opposed to developing
Existing markets
Such as IRT in Solana that just agree that electing qualcomm's no more innovative
Their mobile chips
I can prove that but those are too powerful to use too much battery for
A lot of IRT type devices and sensors so they need to re innovate in that area which they're doing
The whole reason we didn't even say why the deal is off is
Because
The u.s. president has said they would raise security concerns to have a Chinese company with that typos
Power in this particular segment
Yes which is ironic
Because prior to the deal being announced back in November
I believe is the end of October that President Trump actually met
With he appeared on the podium next to
Broadcom CEO
Hock tan and talk about jobs growth
Trump broadcom in the Uso
I'm sure
Right because this deal for cording to broadcom just you would have brought more jobs and because
And this is happening anyway broadcom is going to re
Established
Headquarters in the US which it had done about
Three two or three years ago and moved overseas
So it meanwhile
We should just introduced this meanwhile
Qualcomm
He's still trying to buy nxp
Major semiconductor
To get more it be more Automotive capabilities and that microcontroller
Welcome is current
Yeah there's an XPS billion NFC chips as well which I would use the most mobile devices use NX
P4 NFC
Yes
Right
If that weren't crazy enough
Broadcom deal where to start looking serious and tell him I come in with a
It's owned by iota
Which then begs the question of now that this is done
What happens
Intel is it content
Just sit there and say you know what we're good
We don't need any mobile chips
Because we're
I don't even know
Cuz we had those with exhale and we sold them off right before mobile phones came out
Yeah
So
This deal
The broadcom Qualcomm deal
Not happening
Xvideo
Who knows
Intel
Also who knows
So we'll leave it at that and
Yeah
I would also talk about anymore they store debate over should we talk about
Yes
No more debate
Okay
So moving right along to
Oh this is a really fun story you guys
Except
Scary story
I shouldn't I shouldn't set you up
Like that
To worry
It's so scarier than we talked about before
It's true
All right I was reading in ABA Journal
Which is a business law publication
The panel occurred last week
And it was basically
It was called
Madam is this evidence
Savannah News madam
Mystery
Basically these guys talked about law cases
Where Internet of Things devices such as a Fitbit
Vitamin A and
Other things other connected devices were used
To Arsenal's personal devices insurance
Device in someone's car
It was used in
A murder trial
And this is a murder trial in Wisconsin the victim was a woman named Nicole vanderheyden
And her boyfriend was a suspect but
They looked at his Fitbit data and they decided that he didn't do it
However
They found this other guy who apparently
Was suspicious sending those data from his Google Dashboard
It placed him at relevant locations
Around her death
And they also looked at his search history which is not
New and
The woman who is murdered actually had snapshot which is
Connected car devices
Progressive Insurance
And
They use that to
Please her whereabouts prior to the murder
So
The attorneys noted that this was not
Direct
Cooperative
In
Yeah but it's still a little scary so
Yeah it is scary. I will talk a bit later about some probative evidence that I gathered
For an issue at my house
But
You know we talked about how these types of devices that data goes into the cloud the
Companies
Yeah that the Privacy policies but they're going to comply with local laws and and subpoenas and so on and so forth and
I don't think it's going to stop people from wearing smart watches fitbit's talk into their Echoes and so on
But we need to be aware we is as consumers need to be aware that
Even if you're not cortical giving up your privacy with these devices it still can be used against you
Yes and he suggested that lawyers actually asked
Consumers what iot devices they have when talking to them so they can understand the possibility of
Evidence basically what could you come out against you
And they also said that this might lead to a new class of
Expert Witnesses
Where people can be disputing like how accurate is the Fitbit data I don't know which that could be fun as well
That's a someone I don't plan on committing inverter anytime soon
Whatever
Let's be clear
But it is a little disconcerting because as a journalist I'm not doing anything
Controversial now but what if I
Decided to get into some
Controversial I think my iot devices might be the first things out the window in that case
Keep this in mind privacy fans
We got a new type of edge Computing out there cloudflare which is a security company
They help protect against DDOS attacks that was there
Original
Incarnation
Now because they have such a massive network of
Edge
They call it Edge devices Edge servers there really more like Edge in the sense of a CDN being an edge they're not
The edge
Of
Like a little tiny nose and sensors
But they're actually offering
Shooting
At their Edge
Which
Pretty compelling it'll be deployed at there at just called cloud
Workers in
I bring this up mostly because it's a cool offering but
It really drives home the point that not everything is going to happen in the
Cloud when it comes to the Internet of Things
It can't
We talked about this a lot
But it's worth bringing up
One more time
And this is also
Very similar to what the telcos are trying to offer with their Edge computing
Efforts which is at the edge of the telconet
So you can kind of look at those as parallels
And
You know I would
This is kind of interesting to me if I were a true developer I'm a newbie developer but
I mean you
Mention CDN is just to further explain example like if you watching Netflix
You're not watching it from Netflix as main servers they've got servers all over
The world
That have the content so you're going to the closest server
What cloudflare is doing is they're putting
JavaScript processing at the edge kind of like Netflix does with its content
So if I'm developing an iot device
I can get to the closest Cloud Player
Server to process things
In a process sensory information in return a result or making action happen
And they claim you know that no latency is like
Practically not zero but pretty darn close it's much quicker
You don't have the processing on the device you don't have the processing at a centralized cloud storage place
But it's all over the place it's kind of interesting from a developer standpoint
I agree
It does look to be some smaller developers are complaining about the prices
Because there's a $5
Covers your first 10 million requests and its / domain
So I can see
Okay if you're going to if you're going to have
A massive user base
And devices that are doing something all the time with data I
Get that but it was I thought it was actually pretty cheap
I think some developed if you have multiple domains this could get
Crazy fast
Yeah
So I think that
That's the issue however
It's awesome
Earth
Let's move to the home for a little bit
Because
Google Assistant routines are now
They are live in the US and you may not see them yet I actually do not have an older version of routines in my Google
Just an app from what I've seen if you don't have it yet you can go to a Google support page that we are linking to in the show notes
I'm a little disappointed because it takes a lot of customization and flexibility out of it
The routines are really
Preset 6 different options such as good morning goodnight and so on and so forth
When you configure these in your app
You have a set of checkboxes that you can choose from
Siri it's not like you can
Customize completely to your
Needs I don't know I haven't used it yet cuz I don't
Haven't yet but I'm a little disappointed by that but you raise a good point Stacy or just here for the show
The reason for this
I mean
One of the big
Complaints we've always had about
Programming your smartphone is oh my god it feels like programming your smart home
Checking off boxes is far easier than saying
Okay when this happens let what should my good night routine be
Is someone suggest things for
It's a lot
True very true
Now I don't have it
Either
And I will say if you want to do my suggestion to Kevin was if you want to do
Something super custom
Go with shortcuts which is the Google option where you
You say what you want to say and then you
Just tell it what you
Wanted to do
The downside there is
I have shortcuts that have never run it will never run
Because they don't work
Google doesn't actually tell you
What does work about them
Fixing them is
Yeah well and hopefully they'll develop this further expand it no Google Iowa is coming up in May
I really do expect to see a lot of
New information features and functionalities on the IRT side from Google
I'm going to hope so because
Men Maybe
Maybe we'll get boring Google things
All right
Let's do some quick news events fitness app Strava has decided that maybe it shouldn't
Joe Whitesell
How much data
You guys might remember
Couple months ago
Strava did is heatmap in
Suddenly everyone realize that military bases in other clandestine operations or kind of obvious
The areas where there weren't a lot of Strava users and
Yuka's in
Third world countries in the Middle East in
Suddenly you could see o
Here's a couple Strava users
Going right here
End
That was no good
So
Now they have a new version of the heat map
And in the bars access to street-level details to anyone except registered Strava users
Right and if you set your
You can do this in the app if you set your mapping to
The private
What they'll do is they're going to wipe those
Private
The private data every 30 days
So it won't be a long-term history of this type of information
Yes and Roads and trails with little activity will not show up on the revised map until several
Current users upload workouts in that area
So
Pretty good
And
It's a step
Latest Apple series
We'll see what happens
And you know in the meantime I think the military kind of
Came to a wake up call
Maybe we should check with RP
People are using
That would be a shame and very ironic if we got better privacy thanks to
The military
For iot device
Alright other news
Samsung SmartThings
Hoof
And well I think it was only in North America so this was not worldwide
But it was earlier this week around 2 p.m. eastern time and it lasted
Depends on who you ask
Sun and obviously different users in different areas might have
Experience the
Issuing While others did not as it was being fixed
But to me it looks like the last about 18ich hours and
I mean if this happens if I get it there outages for every cloud Base Service
Known to man
People were complaining about Samsung's transparency
The other issue this raises is
You know with everything being done not everything but a lot of things being done in the cloud for iot
That's a chokepoint that's a problem and
SmartThings outside some local
Things that can run Onyx Hub as does wink
But it really
Priests of the question
To me of you do we need hugs and why I think we do
And I made a case for Google to actually make its own Hub earlier in the week
I got some interesting responses from that
Some people said hubs are just hacks because
That you know people are using standards but I don't I don't agree with that at
Hubs will help
Bridge different radio protocols for examples that are using standard
I hope so also have the processing power and stores to actually
Store your
Automation
Things like that and when I said that's the cloud for that and I said
So well that works so
I think we still need hubs
I don't know what you think Stacy but I think is a good example of why
I think it's ironic that you of all people
To hate hugs
In bridges
Baidu
Blackmore hubs
But no I only want one
That's the thing I don't want multiple hubs
I'm happy with what I've got a wink of I'm happy with having one
1 is fine as long as it works with all my devices
But
To get rid of it completely there are ways to do that but it's a challenge
I am I in the conversations I have with people on this is all on Twitter and Google Plus I said
So you want every device available talk to every device
How does one device know what devices I have in the house
Does every developer
How to know about all these other devices that are on the market because once I add one has to talk to that one
So that's a challenge
I think a hub can do the work
I agree I think the challenge we've come up with is
We never built
Standards for the internet
We have yet to do it everyone instead decided to build their own standard
And so what we've got are these little silos of information works with programs and
We will be there for probably all of time is my feeling
I don't know baby I'm just
Pessimistic so we will need a hug
Given the way the world
His evolved
Didn't have to evolve
Chopra
Here we are all right should we talk about all the new toys out on the market yeah let's do that I'll take the first one
Because I got me excited there's a new Raspberry Pi
Pi
The Raspberry Pi 3 Model B+
It is on sale for $35 which of the same price as the old
Raspberry Pi
3B
What's new here is Nevada dual band wireless so you have a tour to 11 AC
Both in 2.4 and 5 gigahertz you got Bluetooth 4.2
You've got
Gigabit Ethernet
Now and also if you add on a module I don't want the prices going to be
You will get power over ethernet support
What you want to ask about a second
What else do they have I think those are the main things
So I guess I'll just ask her right now
Power-over-ethernet why should people be excited over that way this Raspberry Pi
Pro community
Power-over-ethernet is something
That Pro installers of consumer electronics
Usually ask for
Because it's more reliable
Get your doorbell cam it's faster
Until
Cameras
Doorbell cams those are kind of the things that end up going on
Also alarm type systems
So I would think that if you were
Interested in building
Something custom
That has that kind of reliability this would be an awesome thing for you so I think it's actually a really interesting
Option for
People who are interested but smart
I agree
So that is the new
Which by the way we are recording this on Wednesday which is Pi Day
Yes it is Happy Pi Day
Next item
Is actually one of our
Listeners
Brought this to my attention it is the Abode
Iota
And this is a
I'm just going to call it a canary like device that
Is built for the Abode
System so upload is a security system
I've had several people
Talk to me about this and they love their boat systems
It's about a $300 initial install it's a Gateway and sensors and all this other
It's super easy to use
What they've done now
Is they've created a
Camera device
With sensors that you just plug in and it acts as a gateway
You can use it with your existing about stuff
But I think this is actually to get to the
The rental market the layperson who's like
Checking out something fancier
Involved so this is like hey there's a camera
Funk it down
If you want to get fancy or you can start buying some sensors
Works with zigbee Z-Wave
And
I'm actually kind of excited
It's $329 which is Kai
Anniversary
It's not out yet
It will ship sometime
They say the first quarter of 2018
No matches
So
Yeah I just thought this was a really interesting device I may actually try to
Pick one up to play with
I wanted to try out the original Abode security
Based on all the positive feedback that I have gotten about it
But I never did
Security systems are not sending a
I'm probably boring these
Chunk it down
Forget about it
It's some folks might be excited about this as opposed to the canary because this has a MicroSD card slot as well.
Presumably
Not everything has to go to the cloud or could be at least retrieve and stored
Locally so
That may be of interest to folks
Yes
All right
There's also a brand new light switch out
Switch
It has
A motion sensor and Madame a
You guys are probably familiar with ecobee
Cuz
Holy cow
It makes a thermostat
Including one
Now it's just moving into light switch
Send I have a theory is
Would you like
I would I would love to hear
Okay
Light switches are ubiquitous in your room if you want to get good presence detection
Having a light switch with a motion sensor
And
T-shirt matamata
Great is a great way to go about
Because
Again light switches every room
They have power
They are in a compact form factor so if you really hate the idea
You don't have a nose
Hockey pucks everywhere
You don't have to
Just be like
I am getting one to review so I'll let you know things like hay
Does it really work
Something in your wall and talking to it
And getting response
Dancer
May surprise us
So
I thought this was interesting ecobee did just recently get 61 million dollars in funding including
More from the
Man of a fund
So
This makes a lot of
Yeah interesting although matinee has built-in as one would expect since they built into the
Tend to their last thermostat
Just like the ecobees recent visit work with homekit
Also works with Google Assistant SmartThings and
EFT
So it's don't feel like it's an Amazon only kind of thing that you could
Use this if your
Not using Echoes for example
Yes now it is $99
Switch has a lot to pay for a light
Well you're getting a light switch getting motion sensor that can automatically activate that light and you're also getting
If it's important
And you can have that in every room
And this fact when I saw this
It reminded me
Again to harp on this
When is NVIDIA coming out with their little
Google Assistant microphone and speakers that you just supposed to plug in every room of your house that was to see Elsa's ago
14 months ago
Another
Cuz that's what this does is that in the speaker and the microphone to every room
Maybe they're busy
Making chips
It's for cryptocurrency mining I don't know
But that's probably more profitable
All of the market sound but still
I'm very upset that there's been no news on that but so this appeals to me for the same reasons actually and I'm not a light switch
Guy on my balls
But I am interested
Maybe I should send a
I should also mention that it does.
And humidity relief
There are some
Constraints to this one
It will not work
The 3 way switches which means wherever you have
Multiple switches that
Control
One light will also need a neutral wire
Shop and it works with LED and CFL lights and also
At work with that
And then it works with incandescent light
There you go
It doesn't
I'm looking to see if it's a dimmer
Because it works with CFLs I wonder
Yeah I don't see that it's it doesn't say that it's a dimmer I just see on off so it may not be a dimmer
And if that's the case
That may or may not
Right
And we have this week
It is
The rachio
3rd generation
Sprinkler
And rachio smart Sprinkler Company
You actually install this at your
Where your sprinkler brains live
And it controls things and you can control stuff from your phone
They had talked about adding soil moisture sensors
That process is still incredibly complicated so I
Now they have the rachio 3 smart sprinkler controller and rachio 3 wireless flow meter
And fees
Will sell for 249
The irrigation of things is not cheap
Nowell the actually I think the second generation was about that much
Much my father-in-law actually installed one and has it and he loves it
He thinks it's just fantastic
AC is not
He is not perhaps the most sophisticated smart
We did
Tie it to a Nifty integration for
For weather but that was about it
And he was just kind of
I think I made it
Now the insulation of supposedly easier there's 5 gigahertz wireless
Compatibility and
A new long-range radio to connect with the first-ever residential wireless flow meter
So basically this tells you how much water is being
Used and it will detect when leaks happen
And it shuts down your water supply
This is really important cuz sprinkler leaks happen all the darn time
And you don't know about it
And you're just like unless you get a swampy patch on your ground to your like
So this is really important
Is fits within roggio's whole we want to save the Earth by using less water effort
And
Also I mean
I helped them install it the second generation
It was easy
The biggest challenge actually for us was getting wifi to the garage
And once that was taken care of we were all good
Pre-order
And like I said it was 249
So
249 99
Hookah
That is all the new toys out this week
Well it may not be all of them
Those are the ones we saw
And got excited
Yeah one of my old toys actually help me out big-time this week
Tell me more Kevin
So I won't get into all the details but essentially we woke up
Late last week
I guess was Friday and my wife went to her car which is parked on the street and our townhouses complex
Inside big tent
And scrape in her vehicle
And lots of Parts all over the ground not from our car but obviously from another car
And nobody left a note or anything but somebody hit the car
So I went back and scoured all of my Nest cam footage cuz I have an indoor Nest cam
Winking Outdoors since we're not allowed to have outdoor cameras
And sure enough
At 6:11 p.m. the night before
We saw a neighbor pull out of their driveway Quest
Street and back into our car so I got the evidence
I work with the local authorities and talked to the neighbor who isn't really
Sure that she
AR car
She thinks somebody hit her car but
Saturday
Whatever hot
No big deal she doesn't have video and I do so
Yeah we're using that Nest video footage with the police and also our insurance agency so big help right there
Well there you go and
Clear desk purchase has
If they claim is covered by their insurance company
And then some
Okay and Kevin
Kevin took a trip on the dark side we were talking about it this morning
About this the story I'm sure many of you saw it
But it was MIT technology review
Road about
Is a y combinator startup
Can you upload your
Yourself
But it is 100% fatal and
This is Freaky Deaky what the heck does this have to do with the internet of things other than
You're right other than its
Just to clarify the startup
Is preserving brains for the moment that's what they're going to do with the hopes of actually
Being able to upload all of them
All of you in the future
And the reason they
This is fatal is because they have to keep your brain Preserve
And alive so to speak so you kind of pretty much got to be dead
That's one
Whole freaking out about it but
Normally I wouldn't even brought this up
But
You said something pretty profound once before on the show how many times but in particular
You would said once your data is uploaded to the cloud or company etcetera
You don't control what they do with it
And I thought about that as it applies to this and if
Date this company actually does succeed and I'm not saying they will but what if they did
My entire brain data would be
In their hands
What would be done with it I got no control over cuz I'm already
Ted
And that's really scary
Yep
Alright so now none of us are going to sleep tonight
And I'm sorry
I lied to
Because we're actually going to end the note
On one of our
Iot
The star hotline
Instead of a hotline this week
Nobody called us
You guys
512-262-3742
You for overload us with
With your questions
However
We do get lots of email question
So we took one of those
Fantasy podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & Security system so you can get the most out of your lock
Weather here in Apple homekit user or love Amazon
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
And this week's
Email
Not hot
Michael
Ask
What are the best books to read are other forms of information I can learn from for someone who is new to the world of iOS
Multi sensors
1 Starter book would be great but also a few follow-up resources that will take me from learning the basics
Like an introductory book
To having a good understanding would be
Depends on what you want to do I think
And I say that because if you
The center that you can purchase today that work with iot hubs and such
Are pretty easy to use pretty easy to install and so on so forth
However do you want to learn how these things work and make them work yourself
I would do one of
Two things I know you got some recommendation Stacey but
I would get an Arduino kit and some sensors
Very simple
Sensors could even be buttons
And walk through some of the
Step by step instructions on how to make them work
Literally
Make magazine is a great resource and actually have a book it's a little dated
But they have a book from 2011 called getting started with the Internet of Things
And they will walk you through either using a pi or Arduino board and some sensors to
Literally make events trigger events and make things happen so that's that's
One thing I would look at
Do you have any other thoughts depending on how
How advanced you want to
Just to get a feel for this if you have sensors
I always agree this is actually what I do with my own daughter is I just take sensors and light bulbs
And I
Hook them up together via if
Or via the SmartThings Hub gift is beneficial because it's it does
Does it cost money
We just show what happens when you trigger thing
Thanks right so that's
One option the other option is if you want to get a little fancier this actually works
4 kids and I'm not trying to insult you
I actually use it this way to is little bit
If you buy a little bit
Can you get
A lot of sense or so if the idea of an Arduino scares you and it should
Some people do get scared with arduinos
Start with a little bit skid and
You can do it meme
You can pick them thermostats with those things
They're very capable devices starter sets of devices absolutely
And the other resource I would offer to you is 8A fruits website
So it's a d a f r
Uit
And they have if you go into their learn section
You will see so many
Products and they're really what the lessons that they have
Explain what's happening
Explain how to do it and you can buy like
The kit to get started
So this is a great way
To just
Start playing with Hardware
If that's
What's interesting
So sensors is a huge cat
Like I don't know if he wants
Like Arduino level stuff or if he's just like hey I want to play with my life
So this should get you started I wish I wish there were like a book that was really compelling but
I so far haven't really
Found one
So
I would say
Start with those kind
Those are good resources to start
I agree
Okay and now
We shall
Hear message from our sponsor and then go to our
Guest this week's guest is Toby Mena
From
Bayer Ag and we're talkin about
Agriculture in The Internet of Things in
He's got some great startups that he talks about he talks about
Building a new business model for iot and he talks about using lighter
What attract insects
So you're going to want to stay tuned because it's pretty cool
Everyone we're taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is Samsung
Can I have John Jefferies head of iot marketing for Samsung artik
How to talk to us about how they handle security
Remind us of what Samsung artik does
To focus on
Samsung artik provides
Comprehensive security
From the edge
To the cloud
R modules
Numerous
Security and safety features built into them
And they are also tied to the SmartThings passed through mutual Authentication
Last week we talked about as much
Trustmark for iot devices
That idea comes from both the work that
Underwriters lab is doing
And what I saw at CES I noticed at CES this year many of the OT devices were sporting
Works with Alexa
Under boxes I think that consumers would benefit
By looking at the boxes if the devices that they're buying where infection cure
And one of the things you talked about was
Securing over the air update
Why is this important
Well Stacy this is important to me because the very first iot devices I bought
I've thrown away because they were not upgradeable
Okay
And
With over the air updates
What do you need to do to make sure that there's
Daisy over there updates are more complicated than they sound soccer package itself needs to be created sign
Protected by the manufacturer
Send a message to be sent
Received in a secure Manner and once it's finally deliver to the device
The device itself needs to verify
That it was signed by an aesthetic
Creator of a software
The manufacturer that device
Let's say an OTF isn't secure what are the risks that that
Until what are several points of risk
Stacy
Even when the
Software packages in motion
If the implementation of SSL or TLS
Doesn't include for privacy ideas lesson 1.2
It's acceptable to eavesdropping it by man in Middle attack
So in addition to the concerns about authenticity and integrity of the software package
There's also risk of a downgrade attack
When older authenticated software update can be rolled back
Enabling vulnerable versions of Wi-Fi or Bluetooth protocols
That were
Officially sign
Yet are still vulnerable
At a fundamental level
Manufacturers should ensure the authenticity and integrity of
If there's no way to verify that there's no way of
Verifying
Sadness after you received
And just upgraded your new iot device to is in fact
Genuine
And created by the Minnesota
That all sounds great and a little scary so
If you want to learn more about what Samsung are takes doing on the security
Is it
Samsung artik
That's a r t i k
That's www.nhanow.com Samsung
Artic artik
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Minna from Fair
What is arsenic
And we're talking about
Farmers
ICC
I'm so glad you
You drive me today
So let's just get this started
The Internet of Things
Agriculture
60 miles farmers of facing a lot of China
Resistance
E-waste
Visiting
So our ambition is
2 letters, perfect you know
Where would we
Growing My Wish
Diseases spreading in which context of finalists
Without traveling Moss master
We have a couple gas in the show
Who are in the
Increasing the efficiency of farms and helping make
Workers more productive
In from your point of view what needs to take place for that
Farming operations
Things happening
Unbelievably
Little short of him
Million Acres
In Ukraine
And we have tremendous problem
Really bring home
The complexity of
Good economic decisions
It is very much around
Lifting
Good decisions and making them available across field
Increasing labor machine efficiency
As well as other input
Efficiency
Hey and hear it where Bosch connect
Here you guys are demonstrating so
Something you're working on with botched
Is computer vision identifier
And then sprays it
Little bit different
10 technology that we talked about
Blue River
How are you guys different from them
Teresa Pharmacy
Applying Ruby slide
Needed and we're supposed
Withdrawal
So exactly where the weeds are
Existing equipped
Our technology so they can operate their existing equipped
That they can go with their existence
And
Safe input
At the same time
People to
You know stay with their existing equipment
No
Are you guys
We talked about
Some of the things
Doing with startups because you're not just doing
Weed management but you're working with a couple other
Projects
For example
Together with Bayer with you laughing at
Technology
Accountant
Determining sex
Call Chief
Miles and miles away
I think that's really cool stuff
And especially helpful
Visit the field everyday
But there's really no
Which insects are there
If they are hung
And how many are there
My favorite part about this guy
Is how
Do you identify
Insects using lighter
We understood that
Love you to measure the wind
Frequency of individual insects
Turn out to be more strict than we expected because depending on what incited
Frequency is slightly changing
To Ephrata Library
Waldo's wings
Love that there's like a dog
Pieology around swing beat frequencies that's crazy
Okay
So and then
Working with other companies which ones
Pandas update
Jack stauber
Especially focus on
Radar technology
From satellites
And here we are
Measuring
The soil moisture
From space
Realtor helping Farmers to come to
Drug identifier
Free sample and also to understand
If I'm Just Brakes, spreading on
A lot of companies doing soil moisture is in the ground
Talk to me about why you guys
With space instead
10000 or 20000 times cheaper than
You smell sap
Baseball stats
Soda
Average Nicole Smith combine this data with other rain data
Understand
Somos Tres developing in differ
Leo
How much do
Does that cost
Essence
What is the cost
From my farm we did some experiment
Salt sense
First of all
In like 30 cm is 69 cm
We needed several for 10 acres we were digging in Twin
You have permanent problems
With Collective
We had problems when
Acropolis drawing
So all of this
You get away with when using data
I'm imagining you know what happen
Sprinkler heads
Run over them with the lawn mower and I'm
Just like that
Okay
These are some of the companies you work
Working with what
Other things
Looking for what
Companies that want to work with you on this
Where the holes where the gas
Good-looking reefer
Crazy and unbelievable data sources for agriculture
Come from existing machines
Could come from
Different date
So anyone listen
Great idea
I love it
You guys have made a distinction about the different types of farmers that
When is Big industrial guys
The other smaller
Can you talk about
Those two types of farms
Traditional glass
Rossmoor Acres
We believe that with did violation this drug will reverse
Small farmer
Introspective
Big Pharma
Liberty store
It's our ambition is to bring the
McMillan small farmers
What's today only producing 20%
The calories on the planet
Global Act
What percent of calories
4 calories
Air quality
Veggies we're looking for healthier food
Remove balance
Diet
Especially across Africa and Southeast
Small farmers in the spaces they are the same
Our future is now window tint
3 Villages weather
White
Smartphone app
Just helping those just by taking a picture
Which weed which disease and evening
Need some nutrition
Oldest
With their existing smartphone and an app called
Just pictures of
Cheetah
Also
For years we've been going out taking
Pictures of weeds in of insect around
Planet
Built those recognition
One of my biggest things
Thinking about how the iot can actually
How we can actually make things better
How are you
State of trying to think about
The bigger picture of us on this
Explain it
Proprietary data
Ruby Savio scouting app with a hundred thousand users
Across a hundred countries
We're donating all this
Proprietary data to a data and Geo
Planet
25 makes the stator available for open
Sapore
Better agriculture
Sustainability
I bet you could also see
The new Super Why
Universities approaching
You guys get a
Fluoride
No idea what you having fun
Because
Can you speak
Can the yield
Company that is trying to do
Incredible it is an end-to-end
Understanding of
Basically all the way
Sumer
Holy cow that's the Internet of Things
So
This could go at how this could connect Beyond
Isaac
Reading the right
For my body and I will be confident that what I'm eating
Healthy for me
Information
This
Soap
Convinced that this data is regenerating gear
Is not only good for
Coral Springs
Please
Circumference of a consumer
And how far would it be
You guys
How much do
You guys want to do versus work with partner
Very beginning of his journey
And we are
About 30 companies
Very big like Bosch
That's a lot of small startups
And we re gorillas refined
And how long to
We see real changes in the way
Farm
From the source
Innovation
Are you see you today if you're traveling
Uganda
And you see how
Swope Park
Unbelief
And we also
Formation
Information on that finger
How do you say
Ultimately change
Your products
We are perfume
Where is that
Cathay business model
Face on
Selling gallons
Are a kilogram
Call Doc's
Is not carrying us death
Our ambition is to sell
Protection ultimate
Used as a service
What is your process is
Forgetting
That's clearly a very long-term thinking about working
Deeply with your customers
Are we don't have any
Perfect son Stacy
We have this Grand ambition
MP exactly know what we're going
3 Orkin 12 and 10 maybe 18 months
Bath & Beyond
Cycling and having a having
How can a company that
Wants to also do something like that
I'm selling a product
Tuiservice
How would you advise them to start
The process if they're looking at this going
Customer segments understand that some farmers are very satisfied with the system as it is today and they want to carry
So weird
Stop
We are in parallel buildings
New business model
Which overtime
We're replacing
How do you identify
Set my
Interested in that how does that conversation
I need to go
Different Pharmacy
Fantastic experiences
French dairy farm
Very hot
Earn money in Dairy operation
Incredibly open
Tower new outcome-based service
When people are reluctant
They are real
Because season farming for 40 years
Adhesion
Farming
Reedy for that for the sake of farming
Because he loves
Driving a
His machines and he doesn't likely to
Full day with my mother at home
He would end up spending more time with your mom at home
And he slows to do this
How does that change their life
Customer fraud
Customer segments
And they're really really
Gradle
Crop protection and economic decisions
To someone else
Thank you so much.
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot