Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
And this is your co-host
Have to tell you that we have an awesome show for you today we're going to talk about
Galaxy 8
Andy's Market
Acquisitions in the states to talk about Google
Voice recognition
Spotify
Autonomous cars
And Microsoft
Latest iot Suite
Scary security stats
Message from gif
What are sponsors
I guess this week
Jason Shepherd
Tell is going to be discussing their age
Foundry platform
Pictures of pig
Toi the industrial internet
We get to that
Whataburger
Samsung
Got a great idea for an iot business
Benson archery
Easy interoperable
Wuxi focus on building
Rather than worrying about technology
I survived
Integrated Hardware
Cloud dancer
Security
It's how iot gets down
The more information
Dot IO
AR
Tik. IO
Okay Kevin
I have to warn everyone that I am in New York
Recording from
A hotel room that is high but not high enough to avoid the sirens
And has bad Wi-Fi
El terrible Wi-Fi
Kevin is my savior this week
Yay
Get started with your
Surprise purchase
Oh sure we can do that so West folks know the Samsung Galaxy S8 and S8 Plus
Officially became available
On Friday last week
Did not expect to buy one
My main SIM card has been in an iPhone 7 plus for quite some time
And I've had various other Android phones for my project fi Sim
But my main send is now in a galaxy S8 Plus
It's the big one
Didn't expect like I said to get one but I made the mistake of going to BestBuy just to look at that nice
Mostly bezel-less display and
I was sold her that and some HDR video just sold me on this phone
So
Snagged on a Friday night
Thank you T-Mobile because
State paid $600
Gave me a $6 promo card when I ported phone numbers over back in January so which I didn't pay a lot of pockets
Overall I know we're not a phone charger say overall the phone is
Really really impressive a beautiful screen
The immersive news of that near bezel-less display really does make a tremendous difference
And just about everything that you do and Samsung I have to give him credit they've done a great job
Getting apps to work with that
Funky new aspect ratio of 18.52
So it's very tall that
Not so wide phone
R2r Shore two things
When is Bixby witches
There
Version I would say of
Almost like a Google Now
And 2 is the fact that this phone works with the SmartThings and such
Now I do not have a SmartThings Hub ideas people probably know from listening the past I went with a wink Hub but
Stacy you test a lot of things and I think you do have a SmartThings Hub yes
I do and I'm actually one of the reasons that in New York
At this event with Honeywell smart thing
Skybound
Business Development
You showed me
The Galaxy S8
You showed me the new
Integration
Call home
Holy mackerel
It is
Gorgeous
Automatically discovers everything on your WiFi
This is actually an update that SmartThings
So if you
When you download the app it looks Infuse everything it can it can on your Wi-Fi
But it automatically pops
Wichita
You will have to manually add your
Things that I can't see
But
It's also
In this house
Stomach really nice shot at the Dairy Queen design
Really nice job
Can quitting Lake
Where things are
Obelisk
Smart home so anything on
When you when you bring this phone into your house and you should actually maybe try this
See if you can get with discover some of your wifi-based
Divisive
So in essence
Do you still even need a SmartThings Hub if you have this phone I guess that's one of my questions cuz I don't have the Hub but from what
You're saying I might be able to use the phone
In lieu of a hub
Yes for Wi-Fi device
That is my
And that would make sense because this thing doesn't have Z-Wave this phone doesn't having all the different radios at the Hub would have
That makes total sense
So
You said you had to download the app and I just checked the app and see if is pre-installed it is not
OK Google device
So I probably have to go into the Samsung apps app and download this app which is fine
You also noticed that the design of it is
Pretty nice and I haven't seen it
But I can't say for folks who have shied away from Samsung
Devices in the past because they have the TouchWiz
User interface over top of Android
This is now called
The Samsung Experience it is no longer called TouchWiz and it is very less
I don't have a lot to say almost
I find TouchWiz gaudy
I find it Gotti
What does Samsung Experience
Find job redesigning us
Leaving I kept the phone with me to Google New York City yesterday
Where I work I should disclose that that I work in the devices and Mobility group for make money for marketing
They were all impressed with the redesign of the software in general so you know I'm a
I made download this app and
Play with some of my Wi-Fi devices with the phone I have multiple ways to control them now but
I'd like to see what Samsung is done here
That is B
Latest news on Batman
I did mention there two things in one is Bixby
I think I think Bixby will be forgotten in the near future by many people
You forget about it because they have a dedicated Hardware button on the
As you hold the phone in your hands on the left side of the screen is you looking at it
Hit that button and Bixby open
The Voice interact
Infer Bixby
Is not
Available yet
However you can use the
Bixby cards if you are familiar with Google Now
Swipe right
On a Google phone that has Google now you'll get your Google Now cards
Contextual Karzai show maybe traffic and weather and
Information that you're interested in and Dixie does that now which is
But
It's not
I'd say fully baked yet it's pulling in information and putting it on cards for apps that installs hitches
Play CNN
So show me interesting CNN stories
March
And I don't really care about those anymore
So
There are some good things about Bixby there are some not-so-good things about Bixby I would say it's a work-in-progress I would not buy this
Phone for Bixby
Because Bixby is a promise that is not yet been capped
It's probably the best way to say it
Okay
Unveiling
Avalanche Ranch
That's correct. They're still working on the Voice interaction bit so I use then this phone obviously because of
Has Android 708 has Google Assistant built-in so I basically been using them
Amanda and I just use a Google shortcut to tap and then I get my Google Now cards so I'm
I've done some workarounds to get the functionality that I want but you're actually correct
Samsung headset at launch
The Voice
Peace is not very red
The cars that will improve over time as well
Internet
Come back to you later Kevin
All right
Since we're talking about Google which way
Because you work there
Let's talk about the other news
Google home
Google
Is it Google home or Google Assistant
Basically what we say voice recognition we're saying voice recognition for multiple people
Right start this is so here's what's the idea here is up to six different
Recognize
And unfortunately I have not tried this
Out of town
Can I have a Google home
Write an integer
It is it is exciting it in sores I know it is specific to Google home not Google assistant on your phone
And that that actually makes sense to me because your phone has your information
You might share it
Calendars and other information with other people but
You don't want
Other people making calendar appointments using your phone on their account and that's busy with this.
This is
Allowing
Multi
Account
And user access to Google home and I have not tried it I've seen some people say it works great at seeing some videos show
I seen some people saying it's not working great for us
So
There might have to be some tweaks involved in terms of this
It's hard to say I don't have one so you're right I can't say
Start in a little bit
Yes
Basically I'm excited because
Idea of being able to have my husband say
Versus mine is awesome
And it also
Amazon Echo
Which I really thought would have better
Voice recognition
Baidu
But I mean think about
About being able to say that I'm not sure I'd want to do that cuz I don't know how closely aligned
We have to eat in Minecraft
That that's one of my Baker
Concerns on the Amazon Echo
There is a passcode
Right so I think
You're right in some sense this puts Google home ahead of the echo ecosystem for now
At least in this Regard in general I find the echo to be ahead of Google and many other areas in this product
Category
But
It's interesting
Curious to see if Amazon responds
I like the idea that yes you can like I can check my calendar maybe my wife went to check her traffic on her way to work
Our way to work
Baby the kids want to order a video on Amazon Prime for their account
So there's a lot of different usages and that's really what we want in a home assistant unless you live at home by yourself
You want everybody to be able to use this product otherwise
You spent a lot of money just for a single person's usage nuts
It's not ideal you know
Idle by washing machine for myself and one for my wife and one for my kids right
Set point
Chest pain
Okay
So
Yeah well we're talking about Echoes and Holmes notice I just got an email from Amazon yesterday
That Amazon Dash buttons for a really good deals going through midnight on May 2nd
If you buy one dash button you get two free and
You still get the
499 credit $4.99 credit when you purchase make your first purchase so basically
You getting all three for free once you use the first button
I already added to my card I'm going to add a third I don't have a dash button so it will be new for me I got to find a third pie
Gatorade G2
I look for coffee I couldn't find coffee that I wanted and greenies for Norm
Oh okay
Yeah I was hoping
I still don't have the
Flashlight
Brush my dog
I have a virtual one on my Amazon
Web page do I just go to the web page node like
Which is almost equally
Okay
Actually I can
I was talking to the Honeywell people
And hopefully sometime around
They're planning on releasing
Immigration
Whitney
You can actually honor thermostats
The day that you changed your
They'll just basically automatically reorder your air filters
From Amazon
Nice
Which is actually really nice
One of those things where you like
It actually
I think I don't think about it a lot but I do think about it four times a year with the change of seasons Every
Official first day of
Spring summer winter fall
That's when I
Change my filter so I kind of have reminder set my calendars to reorder or go to the store
Yeah they're not to work around this would be ideal to have a meeting with the replenishment service built in
I was just about to
Make fun of my husband
If you can
But
But now I think you're a jerk
It's there
So the cooking there isn't just that it is a
I slept around for people who are not
On top of things
Reminder Center calendar
I keep making money on their connected
It keeps ending
A portion of Revenue Paraguay
The cost of having a
This is something we talked on a lot
When you device
Money everyday that you got that device
Money in your development cost
Custom Construction
Call down or something
Not going to call and get back up
If you're hooking up when you haven't started
How to support that device over the Long Haul
Start
One of your subscription
It may be like
Punishment
Those things are
There we go
But I'd also I'd also add
All kidding aside the what Andrew and I do
Nerve manual replenishment attracting these kind of things
It's actually smarter to have a device do it because a thermostat can see
If the usage has been super high in a given time. Maybe if it needs a filter sooner as a result of that right
Yes
You have to trust
They're just not trying to like
Questions I should make an extra Buck Uber with it
Nope nope they're trying to get more money out of me I know it
Honeywell
All right
Hitting a little
Shift because I read something
So excited I read in fortune
Spotify
Fortune medicine that's not funny
Hiring for someone to make
Suffice
What are the stars will remember that
Really excited when
The Pebble watch
That they were going to make a tiny little device
Store Spotify songs
So when you're on a run
Something without
You have
So this is what I want
We don't know what
Idea is
You need a device
You're happy about this I totally get why
I shook my head no no no when I saw the story
Because
Hardware is hard
And it has become the downfall of many good service companies who have try to do things like this
I don't
Personally think it's worth the risk to Spotify to try and do this and I'm saying this of course without knowing what it is they're making
However
You know
You got a great service out there
You got a lot of subscribers and a lot of money flowing in through the service
And you can integrate with a lot of existing and then future Hardware
Do you really want to make your own
Hope they do well with whatever it is they do
I'm leery
That's all I'm going to say
Directions
You work better with their part
What yeah that would be ideal because we've seen so many different
Wearables another device we have
Spotify on this and then you go to use it
And it's like well it's really just a controller for Spotify on your phone that's not Spotify on my wearable devices
And it was actually I had a Samsung
Wearables I forget which switchgear
I had but that was the one of the big things at lunch it's got Spotify cool
And yet
It was just a controller for Spotify on the phone and I don't run with my phone so now I can't listen to Spotify
I'm tracking my running
Kind of feel like oversold and underdelivered there
So we'll see
Yes if anyone out there comes across
Tiny little device
Is it my phone
Spotify
Glass now
Why does it why does it have to be Spotify for you I'm just curious
Because that's that's what I
Music onto
Flash
A flash drive but if you subscribe for example to Apple music or Google play music
That's fine that's fine
But if you do don't forget our people who do use Apple products we can we know that
Google play music using Android phone Android
Those will sink over music from those
Services that you subscribe to to that way you locally
Carry those chains on a wearable device
And then go run exercise and stream
Over Bluetooth just like you would
With the nails that don't have to be manually
Pushing MP3 files over and then that whole complicated process if there's
There's options out there I was just curious that's all
Okay
I would like
Spotify Spotify
Yeah no and I mean I was a Google Play music subscriber until the whole family went and got iPhones and they're like
Apple music
So I I subscribed as a family plan to Apple music
Luckily Apple music works on some few things Apple makes it worse on Android so
I can you know
Stream stops
Okay
All right
Picking up devices and Hardware
Idevices
Which is a company that is very popular
Open acquired by Hubbell
It is not the telescope
Anna and I thought it was humble at first in like a little figurines
Yes also not that I'm so Hollow
For people who don't know what it is
Is a 3.5
Billion dollar
Company picnic
Electronic products
Square
Residential
Construction
Industrial and utility
This is an interesting purchase that because idevices is very consumer e
Yes now that they have
No they don't if it's
Non-residential residential
The forgetting
Show me a picture of
I hope this makes a lot of homekit accessories such as they have a thermostat
I don't even know what to think about this maybe it's because
It is actually gaining popularity in builders
When are taking over actually building houses
Purina products for new residential buildings and such and maybe even commercial bills I I guess it's
Just seems like I don't know what they paid for everything but
It just it just seems like
It's a very specific application of
The products and
I will see
Everyone knows that I'm not Super Soul.
I'm not loving
I didn't love my
Testing of it
Second love
I don't like the fact that it's only Apple in the device universe is so limited
Add more than user experience
Behind
You are stuff that's out there in terms of like
Helping
Pinecrest
I like I would not buy a home if I was out buying a new home and it had a home kit
Absolutely new
No value to me whatsoever
How about
Weymouth
Yasso
This is so ironic that this news just hit because last weekend I was in the Phoenix and Scottsdale area
And we saw
On the same day in two different areas of town may have been the same car
A Chevy bolt EV all electric
With lighter on top of it so is when I go self-driving Bolt
What's up with that
And then I get home and then a couple days later
Which is a Google company
Announce that citizen testing is gone live in Phoenix
They have 500 looks like minivans I'm not
500 vehicles that are equipped for self-driving
They are
Signing
People up in the Phoenix area so if you live there
Good for you cuz I love it there
But secondly you can sign up to be a an actual tester
How's the self-driving cars and
There's a
Maybe we can let you in the show notes the way most site that shows a video of one of the first testers it's a family like five or six people and
That size family with kids that are at activities
Running the kids to friends house to activities to school to whatever
You just get in the car
Robert needs to go where they need to go just go as soon as
So it's saving them already time and
Effort and
Less traffic
I'm so
It's kind of interesting I saw this this is happening quicker than I thought I did not expect to wake up public
Testing of waymo this soon
Is it
The car drives itself with there still a person
Sitting in this
Behind the wheel
It's ready to take you should say that because as I was sharing the video with people at work yesterday
They asked the same question
And unlike it doesn't show that the video I'm like
That's probably because they don't
Really want you to see that in the video but I suspect it still required
Right so they're trying to show that
Excel driving you don't need it
Benihana Wheeling song by Sting for a regulatory standpoint a safety standpoint
Somebody probably a licensed driver still needs to be behind the wheel
That would be awesome
You were like a kid she can be like
Eventually I could see The Happening
Yes it probably won't look as much like a
I don't know
We are also going to be for this next item in the show notes which is a semantics
Surely report
Hold on it really great information
Reading 15 pages on the Internet of Things
Bat
I have a DDOS attack for an hour
I am not in the market for a DDOS attack but now I know that
Less than an hour
All kinds of useful
Okay
This report talks a lot about everybody's favorite button it the movie
And had enough
Oops
Actually run
And that man
Routers and network DVR system
This is Dad let you
Stein and French toast
Terabyte
Per second
She's crazy
We all learned about aliens
Carolina spices are
Yoshi rap
Distinction between
Devices and iot devices
Because a lot of things
Score
Routers network DVR
Five or six years ago
Most connected devices
They do not have
Password
Did you allow for over the air update
Stop
From the report
Besides attacks against a Honeypot
Today's setup
Where I am
Much of the attacks were coming from China
And the United States
Coming from
China
Got a quarter
So this is actually got kind of surprised
It's not that
USF
The passwords that were used
Spices
37%
Batman
3% use route
And others the rest use some variation
Text
I suspect
You know it was a leopard surprising to me that 17.7% of the
Attacks
Honeypot attacks were from the US
I'd look at it as we probably have a higher density of devices connected devices than many many other
Trace
So it's just a matter of having the device population more than anything in my
Oh that's a smart thing to think
Is coffees working today
If you like sitting here going home
Talk about this
Here's some things
Disable telnet login and use SSH
You should
Use on your network
Actually just wrote a little bit about Healthcare
Episode
Healthcare iot I'm shocked to find out that a lot of people
Actually have any idea what's on your network
You should know what time your dad
And
You know change your default credentials on all of your devices
Wifi router
Are camera everything it should be one of the first things you do when you install it
Yes I am
Those are kind of the big takeaways
Thai soccer
I don't know if you saw anything else that you
Oh yes
Now there's this thing is chock-full of information on
Security online security in general there's a whole section on iot which we hit some of the highlights so
This is definitely worth a read I think it's almost 80 Pages this report
But like I said
Afterwards you'll know how much you need to pay
All right
Quite a bit of news for people
Microsoft
They did
Products including iot
Which year
Microsoft Azure is there their infrastructure-as-a-service offering for everyone
They also have a coyote which is a wafer
People who
To configure
Iot
About iot Suite
Call Microsoft
I need some
Microsoft
We don't have a payment
That don't want
Get Smart
I understand
Cities in other places
They're trying to
So I think this is a really smart
Yeah I would agree
You know when you're offering a whole package not just an iot product I think we offer package that you want to
You're going to find some businesses Enterprises that find it compelling because they don't have to manage all that stuff
So obviously Azure is Microsoft's big cloud play
In addition to
They also announced Azure time series insights
Which brings you the whole manage data latex
Analytic storage visualization so you can you know Annalise
The tons of events that all these are two devices
We presently create so
You know about that Insight how do you actually apply the information that these devices catcher
So really smart play buy buy Microsoft and this is kind of minor but
I never knew that they had an iot blog which is where they have been announcing this news so I'm just out of this to my feed reader
Take an Internet of Things blog didn't know that
Baidu
People who
Probably
This is a big deal for the Internet of Things
The time series data is basically
Time
Temperature
Time in States
Time in anyting
But if you're and iot if you're dealing with Device data
Amazon
Actually don't know what's going on
So now that Microsoft has something that's awesome
A couple other things
They're worth
Thinking about
Battery operated soap reconfigured
Basically this is again
Already done for
Accompany
Call Microsoft
It's because they care that works with everything
Pretty awesome
Microsoft are actually doing some really awesome
And now
The show
Eventually
Which is Our Guest
Jason Shepherd to his
With gel
Discussing the edge boundary which is something Joe
Announce this week with the Linux Foundation
It's basically like middleware for the Internet of Things
Really cool
Iot scale
Shave him for that
Before we go there
Hey everyone this is Stacy breaking into this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Where is it
And this week I'm talking with Mark space who is the head of
Product for home automation at Google
People kisses on Google Wi-Fi and integrating it with if
So hey Mark how you doing
Good thanks for super excited so why don't you get started and tell us
Why you guys chose to integrate with
So we decided it was on the reading platform
We want to make sure that we gave
Consumers
Connected to any device
And that let us do you seem
Great new features that we had never thought would happen
And also being able to allow users to do things like schedule causing devices their schedule
So now you've been on the platform for a year
What type of success
Have you seen
Excited about that
The other thing is
We had a couple teachers that we didn't launch
When we release the router and things like being able to
Schedule
Prioritizing devices schedule
And
Are you just turn into a stew lever step platform for those features as well
What do you love that Google WiFi can do
The one of my favorite
Examples is there the engineer who came up with an athlete that
Allows a user
When your device connect to Wi-Fi
Start to play music
And the entry music
So far really use some good entry music I like it
What else can you do with your if denigration
Well you know what we saw a lot lizard became one of the number one use case it's so being able to connect
Lighting connected to your thermostat
That people were asking us to integrate with because if you think about the signals that Google wife ideas
My device connects and disconnects
It sounded great signals for when I get home
And we saw a lot of people leverage to connect disconnect signal
To find out more
Visit www
Dot gift.com
Coyote
Www
TT
T.com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Katie Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is Jason Sheppard director strategy and Partnerships
Adele
Hi Jason how are you today
Good
Good morning thanks for having me
Good morning I am excited to have you because
Several months ago
You talk to me about something that wasn't called project
That job was working on
It is no longer called project use is now called
Ajax
Foundry
Alright so
Edgex Foundry
It's a big name but it's
It's just a name
First off why don't you start telling us
What it is
Is that you guys are
Trying to solve
The big problem right now and
And IRT is this
Fragmentation
I mean this Market is
It's always going to be heterogeneous there'll always be
You're different standards for connectivity all kinds of different domain experience required
It's really important that you partner on new Solutions
Very important that we push standards
But that the challenges there will never be a single standard there will never be a single choice for operating
You always need to partner
Promise to mean Experian
And so
What's needed is something that drives more interoperability and in
I'm cooperation between all of the
Different things that are inherently a problem with
Feeling anxiety
Scale is important
Cuz
An example I use all the time
Scale the cost $1,000 to connect
Matt's basically the market right now and it is it
It's really fragmented
And how LD Solutions come together and it's great that there's a lot of
True a different diocese out there.
Technology spiders in general
Services providers
I work with them every day but
Defragment
So together we need to get to wear it
It's more of a consistent foundation so then we can go solve real problems
Analytics
Services
All right and this is design for the industrial internet or kind of Enterprise iot this is not something for the
Consumer
Yeah yeah it's definitely focused on Industrial
You make it industrial-grade
You really fit the bill for commercial and Industrial use cases
Say people won't use it and consumer. Definitely interest on that side
It's built from the ground up to the industrial grape
All right and the focus is at the edge so
The idea here is that I can bring in
Any type of radio standard
I can have all these different sensors out there I just need to add a driver kind of to this platform
And it is going to
It's a framework for me to build to that like
Lets me insert all this extra other stuff on
So it's just kind of this middle layer
And now
We're going to delve into what
The components of this middle layer
Cuz it's pretty
What are we really focused on
With Ajax found
I'll start at the end of a high-level are good
Text
It's similar to Cloud Foundry
Super popular for building
Platform-independent
Scale Solutions cloud-native principles
Loosely coupled microservices you've done through open source
Your polyglot
Which means that I can run it
You like and run a python service right next to a Java service right next to a JavaScript you any number of applications
Slot together with d
Containers
You can deploy on a device
Or spread out across the
Devices
You all communicating with one another so that's that Loosely coupled nature is very important here
Because I have 2 solutions
Going to spread out all over the place at the edge of the network so he's anything that's not the cloud
Whether it's
The Datacenter or down to the various things
Call spread out this is designed to run on
Gateway's so the device you're talking about specifically it's like a little bit computer hanging out somewhere
In a factory
The devices would you typically connect to a Gateway at the edge especially if they can't talk to the internet native
If it's a legacy system like that communicates over
Mudbuster
Bacnet or Canvas OR propane at or whatever that you can't natively talk to it
Navigate
People also use Gateway
Ways to do local analytics you like that they want to filter data that's coming off of all these sensors
And then you'll see the like normalized
Results of the most important data up to
You're the backend whether it's a server or
The Cloud everything can go to the cloud substrate key to
Our strategy at Delavan
The industry of people talking about the edge not so yes it's designed to run on the Gateway
But that really just any device at the edge that does kind
Computing for
Sings
Bringing data
Make it interoperate with other data
Do some local transformation of the data and push it out of the box
You for your choice of protocol soon as your kind of icky layers
In architecture
Loosely coupled with a
I can run on a single and what
Are the things you talked about it bringing in the data
You talked about
I think it is Data normalization but that may be the wrong way.
Yeah that's basically
Your normalizing
You pick your standard
Nothing it's very important here to understand that this is not trying to Creighton
Talk about it
With people there like
Oh man you're solving the standards
Your fragmentation problem with another stand
No that's not that's not the goal here in the goal is to solve the problem with a
Really sucks
That makes it all work together so that's that's
Generalization is basically
You know what that lower layer does
I can come to talk to you about a little bit
Go for it
We're at that spot you should talk through it
All right
Start at the bottom
So basically you have all these
Things that communicate over a variety of different standards
So
If I'm in a an existing
Situation at brownfields
Situation
I'm kinda told what protocol I need to talk
Maybe I'm in the building and I'm talking to bacnet
Ormond bus
You're the problem today going back to
The fragmentation problem
I mean there's literally if you left it a hundred different plots
Storms out there
They basically all right
At the application
The device interface
No for that particular bacnet
Thermostat
Where that particular modbus
Flow meter for note for the water
Be alright the drivers different
So even though modbus
The standard
At the Opera
Json layer
Kind of like your keyboard driver
Everyone treats a differently
Because I just kind of writing drivers to make it work
Just to get the data so then
Analytics
The platform
Really have a hundred different
Drivers for that modbus
Water phlegm
That's the fragmentation that makes it really hard to scale
So what are jets fans
Is it provides you a common way to write
Drivers
Devices
Is done through enough
BK for the device services and so each device service is a
The container
You can point through Docker or anime
Turn to snap you to play a service kind of like
The keyboard driver
It's done
You about the OS
But it's also agnostic that's another key part of this architecture is its platform-independent
Both in terms of
Hardware
So any CPU arm or x86
Even though we're doing it through the Linux Foundation of course it runs on Linux
Windows keep running on Macos
So that device servicenow
How can run on your choice of cyst
You write the driver once
4 using the SD
Hey
And now it works
With the core services in the edge X architecture
Common way
So I do not modbus
Driver once
I do the bacnet driver once for that
Device
And I can start to build a library
Consistent
And once that libraries
In all application
Topside
And use a common
What
And the chief for years that you get a bunch of companies involved and you put it through open sores
So that
There's a very consistent way and in terms of how these device drivers are so I can be back Matt and modbus
Zigbee temperature for energy
Gtt or some sort of
Coyote protocol any number of
Choices
It could even be a proprietary
Standard
As long as you use the device service SDK to write in
Consistent format
Alfie the protocol support plasty
Metadata above that
Describes
The details of that particular device the core of the architecture knows how to talk to
Right it's like
Crowdsourcing the one ring
Everything can talk
Yeah
So the middle is the secret decoder ring
That allows you to
You talk to that. Devices
Okay
This is a Dell
Created
Project but it is open-sourced we talked
You were about to basically.
Hey we're doing
So what has the result
At this point we've engaged with
Hundreds and hundreds
The companies that are interested in using this this code
As a foundation
Further
There is clots
You said they build a Gateway platform today
Even if you
You do those device interfaces today out of necessity to get the data
We have a lot of companies are like you know what
I'd rather
Drop what I've done
Necessity and use this
That's a Sunday since we've got lots and lots of companies are interested in doing that
And the other important thing is that there's a lot of companies that build things like
Complex event processing engine
For a Gateway for the edge Analytics
Security service
That can run at the edge
System management tools with backend console
Databases you any kind of value out around
The data ingestion
A lot of people are struggling to
There's no center of gravity to attach it to that that's kind of industry adopted
Unit in the tangible way and so that's why we're getting so much interest
Not only do we have
Hundreds of
You're when we launched the project last week
You we had right around 50
Your founding members for the project
Lots of people that want to
The code is amateurs and open source
You'll never go from there so it's a big launching and we're looking forward to it now being you cannot truly 8/8
A community effort
I'm going from there you guys are signed up companies such as Google sap
And others
And what I'd like to know is
Why are they getting info
Companies of all sizes
Are really just looking for a way to focus their time on invaluable
And so so rather than Reinventing
You know
For The Hundreds or so times
A single type of device
Let's all use a more common way of inner operating
Sensors
Systems
And then let's go build value-add on top
So those those types of companies
I see it as a way to really
You prioritize
Timeout
On the real value
Your analytics and services and
Security in system management tow companies
A large like like
You Google an SAT and
Electric lighters like Chronicle
We've got a smaller startup
Doing really good stuff in it that it's actually built a lot of this time
Kind of stopping their own platform
It'd be much better use of my time to use a common
Core and then focus on value so
People like Kimi lacity and
Henry layer
Docker Networks
Edge analytics company called foghorn
Home security providers like no Kana
Device Authority
Forgerock
All coming together
Go to
Add their value
Around this common
Foundation
Got it
And you kind of answered one of my questions was
Which was about will this hurt others that have
Really built a business around kind of
Bringing all the stuff together and it sounds like
Most of those companies would rather not
Spend some of these extra things
So let's talk about these extra things
I think it's worthwhile
You have a vision
Where
You got the score use the estoque and then various apis and you can plug like
Your security
Efforts and your data analytics what else can you
Bring to the spa
No system management so
Example like I'm trying to manage a bunch of sensors yuan in their firmware updates
Youku
Connecting two gateways or just a network in general
It's really different difficult to do because of
Yours all those different
Standard so this provides a center of gravity for those types
Play I'm a database
Provider and I offer like a time-series database
You collect data on a Gateway and then I do it like a really good fashion
Preston
Oakley
Send out the stuff that matters to my business and pay for it over the network
Yeah you could be that type of swim-bladder
We've even got company
Interesting
It's the so much value the
We added
Around the wheel
Companies that are starting to
You add
Training services around it
Your dad will be a certification program in the Linux foundation and we thought
Your certification
Houses
Instant signing app
I'm speaking about extension of
Part of it
Does a company is companies that do kind of logging
Services for letting an 18 attached to it
It's got a framework on
On the top side of that. Interoperability layer
Describes how data comes up and comes back down
To those devices
It's got a bunch of
Place holders that are all reference
They all communicate through exercising
On the platform
Your rules engine
And there's a database in there it's mongodb
Oh you don't like that database you can replace it with your own
Does reference services
Give you something that works out of the box
But all these different types of
It providers
Can
Commercialize their versions
News about the platform in their plugin
Alternates that they sell
Okay and then
How does this fit in with some of the other efforts out there like there's project quora
From the eclipse Foundation
I don't know if some of the other kind of standards are going to try to get into here
There's kind of some
Reference architecture efforts for The Internet of Things Consortium
So how does this fit in with that kind of wider ecosystem of trying to make the world
Yeah so we
Yeah that was that's part of the
Alignment that we've been working on all this time over the past
A few years that we've been building the project is
I don't want to reinvent standards there's plenty of really good standards
No we don't want to
Dell New Consortium like where we want to align with them the Kura project we've been
Indirect contact with
Eclipse Foundation
It is overlapped
I was Sakura project
We seriously consider joining prayer with think it's a great project
We saw the market needed something that had a little bit more flexibility in terms of being Loosely coupled
Your polyglot I eat
It's not just Java you can run all these different code bases together which is important when you're trying to unify partners
Developers cuz they all have different preferences
That's why I
What's the different architecture
But actually you could take a career based Gateway and plug it into a jack
Infina K10 you can have a service that.
Gateway to Gateway so you actually think that they
Play some good collaboration potential with a variety of different
You open source projects that is
Solving similar needs in different ways
In terms of Standards we've already got folks like you Ellie and notion signed up for working
Foundation on a on a liaison agreement there so if you're in manufacturing opc-ua is a very important
That we want to promote
Call ideas
Use good standards
You know if you don't have an opinion
But if you have to use something at least use a common way to write to it
Talk to it
So and we're working on
Just invited to Malaysia open connectivity Foundation we're building a liaison agreement
We've been
You working with IC
Two same thing
About the liaison agreement
I actually last week when we are there we showed the edge x one of the demos was part of an iic security test bed
Bunch of people at participating
Open fog Consortium
If you read the reference architecture that was put out recently it's actually very similar to an infant
A lot of the elements
To the edge X Andre architecture
Yes we were founding member of openfox or working with a bunch of different
Shapewear
Edgex Foundry can be used as an ingredient in open smog test pek
We've really been trying to
Bridge to all these different efforts
And we get this kind of PC model
Industrial internet-of-things are just
Internet of Things
How much time do you think this could save
People trying to
Implement
Connected battery is connected hospitals connected
Yeah minutes time-factor there's also a security Factory with you not going to talk to a couple things but you just in terms of time
And I'm going to start by saying imagine if
If 50% of the brain power give or take wasn't
You focus on reinvention today in the market writing device service
If you need to write new protocol support I can take weeks to months to do it
You depending on what platform you are working in
Some of the best
Glassdoor the proprietary platform
Once you know a little bit about a protocol you can do it very quickly
So
You know it's not like it's saving you.
Time for say you compared to maybe the best in class
Silent protocol
But I have to redo it for every pot for
Form out there
Hear it saves time because once I do a device service I can reuse it
With anybody's application on the back end so maybe I want to
Connect to
Your thing works in a deal in one case and then I went to connect to sap Hana
You know or or IBM Watson or relayer or
Any laxity any number of different providers
I can do the work once
Are the prime factors is
You way better
Everything is just
Trying to sell
It takes a lot of
Time to sell
Embedded Solutions
And the challenge today is when customers look at the market they're like
Man there's a lot of platform
Literally search you iot platform
Google
Incredible number of
A lot of people adding a lot of value but also a lot of reinvention
Fuses Customer Center
Time to revenue
Customers are like
I don't know if I want to make the wrong decision especially at the edge where you have to update it
Because I made a mistake on my
I'm rolling a truck out there today
Will fix it
Should I said
And everything
This time on development
Time to revenue
Not only because of the it on the time but also because of the
Decision time for customers
You're not looking at so many choices
That are very confusing
Did the security side to you very important
I would argue that
Impossible to really
Shell
You like smart city solutions or anything that kind of crosses public and private boundaries
Or even
Private surprise
Businesses sharing data
Without some sort of
Trusted openkore that everyone
And take a look at
Everyone
Godzilla Security Administration pass
And also if you're trying to share data between
Three different companies
Difference a public and private entities
Having that open Trust
Corvette
Exchanges data between things and applications
It is really important that we think it'll actually help
You there as well
Ip true internet
We always dress start
With your your things
Start with with a small and a domain
And then it'll be like a series of increasingly larger Intranet
You saying everything's going to talk with everything is probably a bit of a misnomer but you're having that open crust and core
I love it I never thought I could spend so much time talking about drivers
I can keep going
You
I've done a great job Jason
Thank you so much for
For coming on the show
Thanks for having me at this might either well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast
Please join us next week when we have another amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are
Hankering for some iot news sign up for my newsletter it's Stacey on iot. Com
Thanks for listening