Everyone welcome to the internet
Things podcast
Does your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Are you today about Microsoft's
Azure sphere
A new security product
Ross can we talk about you secure
Purity standards for the Enterprise for the online trust Alliance
We're also going to talk about
Apple acquisitions
Possible acquisition
New details on
What your August locks
Can talk to
Twilio has introduced a new
Iot product
We've got a crazy idea in transporting small pets
Kevin's going to review and talk about the fibaro homekit sensors
And our guest this week
Zeke is gay
The hunt
Was actually
The Mastermind behind
Azure sphere
So we're getting a lot of detail on
Plus we got him
From our sponsor for sure
And now
Will hear a message from one of our other sponsors
Is you know me so you know me platform from the makers of the free you know me after you know me
Is a cloud-based platform-as-a-service for companies Building Solutions for the connected home
You know these offerings include a cloud a server list iot platform for device manufacturers
Get their products to Market quickly and securely and also you know me what a powerful integration engine that connects
It's more than a hundred top smart home devices this week on the Stacey on iot podcast
Hang up their five-part series what the next billion dollar smart
Home startup will look like you can find part for it part 5 today
By visiting platform. You know me. Oh Stacey on iot
Okay
Heaven
This party started
Microsoft
Yeah it's going to be fun to talk about Microsoft and not
Talk about Windows
Yes so everyone was very excited about this
Probably the most common headline I saw was
Microsoft
Yeah I doubt they did that pizza
Yeah they've actually done a good chunk of
Work on bringing Linux to Windows desktops recently which is great to see
Obviously this has to do with iot devices and seizure
Would you say that there
Using a you're creating a Linux embedded OS
Not exactly
This is only for the address fear is only for security
So I think that's a really important
To note so this is
Obviously going to talk about it later
Gary Bradley
Is a secured microcontroller
It is secured OS layer
On top of that my
Microcontroller
It handles the back and forth between that
The MCU and
What is a
Secure
Cloud Elliman
So the OS is really just handling the back
And forth between
The hardware
And kind of
Brains and
The cloud seoul
What's Happening Here
Is the MCU
Who has a lot of the elements that you would
Expect
From
Trusted
Cute environment secure boot Olive
What is also
Has is
It also has the certificate based on the
Sanitation
He's going to
Communicate with the certificate granting
In the cloud
End
Also in the cloud
His threat detection so when new
Viruses
Abilities are detected
It's going to be able to
Basically
The check goes in
Tell the chip and get having a secure patching ability
Back down to the ship
If that makes sense
Yasso
Product self is the Azure sphere and then the cloud service that you mention that the security piece that's the address.
Security service in the cloud so this song
Which would not always understanding is there secure at all times
When they're not secure
And how to update the security on them
It has been a challenge so this should help with that
Yes this gives you 2
Detection audit
Zation
There's a lot of things that gives you
Now
The issue here is Microsoft is doing this for
It's open sourcing
That's so it's open
It's trying to work with all the chip vendors to get this on
I'm bored and
Will people take it that's really the question there's plenty of
Chip companies that have their own security standards in them anyways that's part of the problem
Is it
Fragmented Market
You'll never hear someone say
It's not
This feels more in line with something like Samsung
Arctic which has they have their secure module
I'm curious with Amazon could probably do something like this
The free artist if it wanted to Overlay security
Some of those
Thanks right so
They would have to do a deal also with
What the Chip n
Letters to have the hardware
Comment sold
That's a little
But
This is a good
Model
It feels like a good model
And
I am excited to see if it works it's not retroactive though so
Right right
You mentioned chip makers and trying to get them and Microsoft already has mediatek is one of the first
Companies to make peace microcontroller units you mentioned Arctic and that's the one challenge that Samsung doesn't have
Samsung does made chips are these designs chips and have some produce
So
If they wanted to do something similar
They could without
Bering
Chip makers are going to come on board
Secure
So
I don't have the block diagram
What
I can't get this
Come back to you on that
We'll see ya
Problem
I'm sure that our guess is going to get into the details even further boat in one thing is worth stressing Riverfront is Microsoft
On the security aspect of this through address fear but the date
Sent to Microsoft azure
Yes and we talked about all of that and we even talked about
When you see this
And
How
Little bit about how the trip is made so
Stay tuned for Galen
Because he is worth it
Also
On the security front
We have the online trust Alliance
Switch
Cool stuff
James a ringing endorsement
They actually created
Several years ago
They created a checklist for what to do when
When you move from your smartphone
So how did I remember
They've created an Enterprise iot
Security check
Quest best practices for
Things if you're going to have an iot Network
Your office and I won't call them to it
I won't go into all
There's about
11 or 12
You probably should have a guest Network or separate iot
Yay
You should update all your passwords and don't use products with hard-coded password
Some of the more interesting
Is
Don't allow or severely restrict automatic connections via Wi-Fi or other be
This will restrict the ability of other devices to
Infiltrate
I don't know why
I feel like
That kind of defeats the
The purpose of
Some of these iot devices I don't know what
Well
I mean deployment of a society devices is always a challenge
It's simpler to Adam but
Obviously that's not a good security practice so I get what they're saying there
Enterprise as opposed to home so I can understand
Cover up all my
Disabled
So in my favorite one which we should all do
Although this puts the burden on the consumer
Enterprise or
Consumer consumer
Is closely
From service when they are no longer updatable
More secure
So in this actually you I'll bring back the Microsoft thing cuz in my conversation
Michaela
He mentioned that
The
MC user supporter for a 10-year
Cycle
So
I was think
Supremes my washing machine stops being secure a sphere
10 years
But this
In the Enterprise
You've got similar sort of
You got some Thor gear this could be running around
7 to 10 years is usually the longest I've seen
These connected devices in their support
Contracts
Chilling at reasonable
It's reasonable but check
That's a challenge
If you'd like to see what you should be
Skipping riddle
Home security news
Called nice out of Italy
Is buying a 75% stake in
Abode
Which is a home security system
Lots of pee
Love
The value of the 75% stake is 18.75
Million
And
De stijl
Is
It's a good one
Fits with what
Aldi
Smart home security companies getting purchased by
Barter companies
Such as
Ring
Who else has not been
Where she did see the iota
Gateway
Fromm adult at CES
We did we did and then plan to sell that for $329 and would ship
In late q1 well
It's now early cute to and
This acquisition but no updates
Right it turns your Bose system into something compatible with
And if you don't have an existing
About system
You can buy that at
Add about pieces on
Security system
Supposed to work with nasty Kirby Philips Hue and lifx right out of the box I will see what happens if and when that shows up
Alright also in a position
Lucci
The maker of
Favorite light switches
Tetra which is actually an austin-based company that makes
Really fancy high-end
Commercial lighting
Tetra is a company that was actually
Created by no suits
Who was one of
Founders of silicon Labs so school Austin
Guy here
Are the chip world
The cool thing about technology
They make
LED
Chips that
Are in there
False so this actually give us
How to do it
I'll say it
Lighting
So they can make the
The chips that
Make LEDs
The bulbs
And then the
Radio protocols that allow them all to talk to each other
And catchers
Unique because
The chips actually
Controlling themselves so
To the right color that
The company or the
Resident wants
They walk
Always stay that color
So apparently LEDs can pop
In-N-Out us
Dismiss apparently
So
Do you think we promised to actually get into the business cuz this is a very unique
Technology in LED
I
Sync
So I've been to catchers demo
Maroon and Kesha's lights are in like
The Museum of Modern Art in Chicago
Some very fancy high-end
Fun places
Lot of nice retail stores
I think this gets
Flu shot into the
Commercial Lighting space
More so than
D
Cherry Crest Market
Yeah so
I think this is a smart move for them
They know what they're doing
In terms of like
And I think
Bringing their expertise from the
Consumer world
In the high-end home in dealer
Which is why they started
I think this is really
Esprit Market
Competition
I guess
Phillips
Other big
I think it's a smart
Trap mix
No word on how much this cost
So sad
To hear that and I don't know if actually Lutron will suddenly have an outpost in Austin
We should be super cold for me
Granny backyard
This is true
All right
That is
We have
Touted as someone who
Might acquire
Nokia's
Health division
Which we all know and love
Are used to know and love is why things
A little convoluted but
Leukemia
Now in February of this year they were like yeah
This isn't for us
Yes the internal memo explained the digital Health business did not look like it was going to be profitable for the
The company and they were evaluating what to do in February
I forget the quote something about failing fast isn't failure to accelerated learning what they said
Terminator was failing fast because things for $100
In 2016 and I suspect whoever guess
This part of their business it's coming
Be a lot less bright
A lot
Google makes sense to me
Only because
It could tie into their nest in the hardware teams
Also because and this is just my experience I try this several times
Google is not that great with Health Data Google fit in particular has just been
Wonky for me does not work and not synced with other services so maybe
Why things I peking come in there I don't know
That perspective to me I don't know what's going to happen obviously
Write another I think they also floated Amazon as a possible acquire
Which would be interesting because Amazon is launched that health initiative
Southwest JP Morgan
I believe
That we don't actually know what the heck that is but you know
Sew-ins
We have
Watch Dora
Yeah if you have an Apple Watch like I do I don't have an August lock you can update
And now just tap on your watch to unlock the door keep in mind I know the August has
Walk up to your door and have it unlock when you have your phone with you
This does not do that if he has cold smart unlock
This is not that this is actually just
Tapping on the watch to in the app to unlock your door so it's going to be clear about that
So you have to tap
The Watch
Yeah but keep in mind you can set to complications on Apple watch to be shortcuts to apps
R show data
So 1 tap to open up an app or two types of is pretty quick
Waiting for 5 seconds
Also
Twilio
It's now generally available
Programmable Wireless
Basically this is the ability to have a
Connected to
Places with a SIM card the last you provide SIM cards and service and they have pricing plans that are
Pretty reasonable
Maybe you want to create your own little iot sensor that connects to the
Weber something for whatever reason and it's remote he can pop a Sim in there and you know I have text messages sent to your phone
People who are do-it-yourselfers number one but there have been some companies that are using this they mention in their blog post
I did eat a bit and
Not a bit snow just kidding dwelo
Which is a cellular connected Smart Hub for apartment buildings but even the folks are just
Connected dashboard camera
They talked about using trulia's programmable wireless cellular
Iot devices
And Kevin has a brilliant idea
Maybe we'll send him
Bunch of mailboxes all together the front
Ascensor in there and then have it send me a text message saying your else here we could all do it
People
I'm sure Kevin
I'll tell you about it
I'm going to patent and sell it to the post office
Hugo
All right oh also
Now you can
Astra products
Yeah this is interesting I haven't taken it for a test drive but this is their VMware pulse iot Center
State of couple of Hands-On Labs where you can actually remote so you can explore
For the polarity center consoles dashboards you can manage simulated IRT
So this is a way for them to educate people on their product to manage devices
Latex free to access the lab zombie run through
These things
I thought it was kind of cool looking Kurama
And
Prayer since summer is coming
Kevin also found
The video is cheesy
Peta safe so this is how to transport your pet
Safely
Yeah safely right it'll actually help you if you have not said you're moving across the country and you were going to take your pet on the plane
Unfortunately
Or you're going to have a transportation service take your pet will digipak for example has a company that uses this
Technology and use RFID tag tracking
To basically monitor where your pet is
Temperature yeah they can even help you
No smoke
Not everybody transports their past but I just thought it was a cool Easter Vallarta to the summer sometimes
That's nice
Bring your dog with you
So
If I use it I'll let you guys know how I found
All right and
Kevin this week you reviewed
Homekit sensors from fibaro
It was time to look at home kit stuff since I just moved everything over to SmartThings so I have the $60
Sbarro door window sensor and the $70 fibaro motion sensor the eyeball
They're pricey but they're very well-designed
They are very responsive easy to set up in home app
For iOS for automations I have the door window sensor literally from 7 p.m. to 11 p.m.
In the office and shut the door the light just comes on
Can you open the door to leave the light goes off
Obviously you can use that for security as well very configurable
I'm a little concerned about the batteries only because the
The knot standard like double a triple a kind of batteries that sort of unique
Tomorrow said they should last two years so
If that's the case then it's less of an issue I mean you pay a premium for good design while working
Cancers that don't just do what they claim to do the motion sensor and the door window sensor
Also report temperature which is Handy and the motion sensor can tell you the brightness
Set a room in terms of Lux so you might be able to make some custom automations based on room brightness
Open my shades
Mapleshade's and I believe you actually
If you want to do something like that
And you can see the Lex on the home app
Yeah then you could do that with Lutron Serena shades
Hunter Douglas also has a shade that works with
So if you're
Eager to try something like that out
Which
I would be
That's actually kind of
I think so too
Allright basal temperature actually
Bring the sheets.
All right well now it is time
Are iot podcast
Listener hotline
We would like to thank Schlage for sponsoring our hotline for the last five
That sponsorship is now.
Becoming available so if any of you out there
Would like to sponsor The Listener hotline
Please reach out to Andrew
But for the time this week's
Ashley
Maker of electronic locks
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & security systems
You can get the most out of your life whether you're an Apple homekit user or you just love Amazon
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn
All right this way
Hotline
Question
Comes to us
Hello my name is. I live in Louisville Kentucky and I've only been listening to yourself a couple weeks now
Into the home automation
I love you so
But what I'm wondering is
Is there a
Video doorbell system that work
Being good for someone in an apartment building
Who does not have the ability
A wired system because there is no existing wire
Thank you for your time
Okay Scott I wish this were longer answer
Because
Then you have a lot of choice but
There's really only one choice out there for battery powered doorbells today
I'm going to recommend you don't go and buy
What are some of the no name brands on
On Amazon which
Are out there but don't do it
A Lot of Things Fall Apart
Genki to have terrible apps
So your options
I really rich
Ring the original for $100 or the ring video doorbell
For 200
And the video so what that price difference will get you as a slightly different camera
On the video doorbell 2
It doesn't have his wider field-of-view
But it is high resolution
The other thing is
The battery pack
For that one is
Rechargeable
So
You just take it out
And you can actually buy an extra battery pack
I want just like alternative
So some people find that way more
Convenient
Lie by Rihanna
Original video doorbell is also rechargeable but you have to
Take the whole thing off
Retarded
It's a little less can be
Yeah if you're not in a rush Scott I would consider waiting to see when the
Blink video doorbell arrived it was coming out in 2018 we last heard still says coming soon on their site
Blank was purchased by Amazon so I don't know if there's any changes
That will also be a battery-powered option I know they announce the price
Previously but now there's no price listed on the site so I'm not going to Hazard a guess that may change
So there you go
You can wait
And you don't mind a little inconvenience
You can always swap it out later
So there you go also
Nest
Hello doorbell speaking of doorbells
I found
It difficult
Because
It just was not connect
I have the
Darkness time
Connecting my Android phone
To this thing
Which
We did get someone who
Call Dustin said hey
I get that problem sometimes too
Doing what I do is like
End
That person I say you are so right that is it
Exactly what you
When you have an Android phone
That is not
Turn off
Mobile data
Usually
Horses things to go
But I would also say eating with iOS because when I had problems with my ring that's what they had suggested originally
In the case of the nest
Do that
It did not help
But other people have said that they installed on an Android phone
No problem so I am just a special special
Which does not surprise me
Okay
Do you want to call
To The Internet of Things
Hotline
Please dial 5 1 2
37424 and leave us your question
And now
Because I'm feeling like I'm
Cleaning Out My Closet
If you guys
Call and leave a message
You'll be registered to
My old camera
Got an SD card for those of you guys who don't want to send your stuff to the cloud
Thursday
And some sensors that you can actually connect to it
And
Have the camera go on when the sensors go
Or off or however you
You want to set it up
So that is
Yay
And now
Stay tuned
For our guest
Break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week we have been Goodman Innovation at 4
What is 4
Our scale flexibility lets our customers move Beyond
Traditional Enterprise I-10
Typically people use identity management tools for things like provisioning employees
Is access to corporate applique
We like to do a lot more but we also do things like the authentication security for your bang
Cellular network or for connected cars or even things like connected
People doing really cool things
When it comes to digital transformation by leveraging for trucks technology
Okay and what are the challenges with identity management today is that it's applied
To so many things or maybe it should be applied to so many things
How are you guys looking at that more
It's a great Point there's this Rush right now
How to get technology to mark
And I think as technology just keeps moving faster and faster
The reality is that securing identity is Austin after I thought you know you hear these stories about
It has thousands
Sensors on
Collect all this data
Enjoy your day start with
Something like that
And they don't think about okay how am I going to secure that day. How am I going to secure that
And we're also seeing is that you know the government and the regulatory
Climate can't really keep up as well and so you see things like
In Europe they have gdpr which is
Privacy regulation
In there and it was probably yours too late
Yet it's ahead of
Pretty much where anyone else in the world is
So how does identity manager
Actually
Identity if used properly is like magic
It's one of the few technologies that can actually improve customer experience
Why actually making their interaction more secure
So I didn't he is also one of the few technologies that is future proof
The reality is
In order to
Secure something you must identify it first
And if you think about it no matter what the device is identity persist
You always are who
Who you are and your thing always is who it is
And so are people realizing this and building their products
With that in mind
I think this whole concept of identity in
Security being an afterthought
Is starting to
And quite frankly
We're working with
Consumer electronics companies who
Are now thinking about
How they create an end-to-end identity driven customer experience so from when you order it when you put it on the first
They provide a better customer experience but they also make the device more
We're working with large Industrials that are building
Command-and-control iot Networks
Stutter making sure that
Since Inception that they ensure that everything is secured all the way from the chip
The Clown
Sounds good so where can we go to find out more
To learn more about what you can do it
What our customers are doing with identity
Visit www
Dartford rock.com
Flash
Digital
- identity
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
And today's guest
Is Galen hunt
Who is with Microsoft
Hey David how are you
Good
It's great to be here
All right you guys are at RSA where Microsoft just announced
A pretty big product
Azure sphere
Coming for a while cuz we talked
Last April about some of the core ingredients
What is azure sphere
Azure sphere
Is an Ambien solution for device manufacturers
Who built
MCU micro
Controller based devices
Allows them
Build devices that are
Connected
The internet
Highly secure
You might ask you what's an MCU or what kind of devices use those are museums to use our
They're in everything from
Toys to Home Appliances Industrial
Factoring equipment and basically none of them are connect Jets
Huge transition
Over the next couple years of all these devices
All right
So yes Galen as you might imagine is correct
Guys out there we talked about computer usually talking about processors
Your phone
What we're talking about with microcontrollers are all the as the arm m-class devices although there are plenty of
Things in your washing machine and and yes they are getting connected to the internet so you guys are created a secure
MCU
There is also a secure OS
In a secure cloud
Opponents of the idea is that this microcontroller
Who actually used to explain
What is happening
If I do we need all these
Well if you remember but when we talk back
We talked about the seven properties
Highly secure device
That was a paper that we wrote released
The year-ago
Basically we looked at from our experience at Microsoft building devices
What is NASA
Build an iot device
Stanolone
Internet device that is highly
To address those seven properties
You need three pieces you need Hardware support
Software support on this device
And you need
Collaboration with
Cloudtail Pecos
And that's what we've built
We built azure
Sphere are these
3 LM
So there's a new class
MCU sphere certified MCU these will be built by our silicon partners
Is not getting the business of building
Sailing ships we do however have
Pablo Acosta silicon IP blocks we have Microsoft
Security technology
Developed
That we put into every single one of these Azure sphere certified ship
And that gives a hardware rooted Trust
And the second element is the
Spear operating
System
Defense-in-depth multi-layer properties
System that
Create a very secure environment on the hardware
For the song
Temdan the third aspect is the
Azure sphere security service
Security service
A broken trust
Between hydrosphere devices and other devices
Cloud it monitors for emerging then to text emerging security threats against the devices
Across the entire ecosystem and it renews this
Security on the devices through software update
It's new security challenges come out
Okay threat detection and then
Renewing Security on the chip what's happening
Well okay so we'll talk about
Software update
When a device is out there
And it's some music 33 it emerges or maybe even someone finds a bug in some peace
Coats on the device
You want to be able to
Create a patch for that and
And get it out on the coast
Devices
Do it reliably do
Attentively another every device you build it out in a field
Is now running the latest
Software
Security service
Provide the
Does it also do things like signed update sign patches does it
Check for that
It's all apps
Yes so it
I'll just talk about one of those
Vulnerabilities in which town
In Microsoft experiences
Version one of your software is out running on
Sounds like you figure out
Security vulnerability
Guitar version 2
Well Packers will
Try to trick the device into instead of running person to the rollback version 1
Bill Clinton
Is rollback
Protection in a way that we can
Physically Modified by blowing some fuses
And the chip
Say hey
Don't ever run version 1 ever again
Vulnerability
Wow so it's kind of stone self-destruct button
For a particular version software you
You guys originally worked with mediatek
On this hard
How can other companies become Hardware Partners or is that
We have a program
Working
With
As many silicon partners
Over a dozen companies were working with right now
Detecting the first partner
You're the first one that's coming
Market
And what we do is we go out and
We are licensing royalty free
AR
Security technology for the chip
And that's so that
The Spinners can use it
MCU Market very different from like the PC market in the regard of
Maybe you can I come at 3 silicon providers for the processors in the MCU
Market 32
Jasmine
And so in order to provide app and
Breath and get a solution outfits
It will be an everyday
We realized we were going to have to life
Give them
What's called an IP block that goes into their device
We get them
Sports teach them how to use that
Appropriately
And we also work with them.
Validate to take
Put it in writing put the rest of the architecture
Ship correctly together
It really is
Secured and then we certified
We let them put the address
Sphere brand on that ship
How does this compare with something like arm has their trust Zone that they recently extended to MCU
There's nxp has I can
Remember what they're
Secure module stuff is called for their kinetis lines
In the MCU world
Everybody right now has as you said roll their own
Compare
Coexist with
Ours is a solution that we have
Built based on the Learning Zone
15 years of
Security
Game console
And in that game console business Microsoft concert
Three generations ago
Consul
Justice
Significant
Amounts of money
Security
Console
Clear Lake to prevent piracy
But in the process
Doing that we learned a lot
About
What determine hackers will do how far they will go
And what kind of defense mechanism
Eaton Place
And then we took that learnings and created this it block that we are using I think one of the things that stands out
Compared to some other Solutions is that
It really has based on this
Many many years
Experience dealing with very persistent very determined
I guess another way to describe it is
It is built
Shoe function with the address Pier operating system
And the Azure sphere
Security service
Optimizing
Fire system in the end
So the all the pieces work together perfectly
So if I'm a customer and I'm like hey this sounds awesome I totally want to go and get these devices
Never worried about security does that mean that I
If I buy
This does that mean all of my date that these chips are generating get sent to
The Azure iot Cloud eventually or could I use
Another
Or keep it on premise
That's a great question as I mentioned before you were really committed to open this
But we don't actually
Hold your data
Connect to whatever cloud service
So if you that you're running proprietary servers
On-premises Enterprise
Will you connect to them
Are you connect AWS or Google
Or I am or Azure iot hub
Shroud
Obviously you want to make it as easy as possible
Thatcher
Created a fantastic very easy to use while buried and freeway
For people to use Azure cloud services for their date if they want to but we don't
Let's talk about Azure sphere
But I buy it
Have you guys would I buy
The chip Inn
Can force from the chips
The way you
We would purchase address
Fear is you would go to your
Distributor
Spirit certified ship and whip it would come bundled
The license for the Azure sphere operating
Come pre-installed on the ship and
The rights to use the azure
Security service
Or attend your lifetime
At the one-time transaction
One-time pay one cost
You get the operating system
Security service
An ongoing service
Prices for that
Okay so let's talk now about
Macro iot thing
One of the big things that we
We talked about a lot is this oh my gosh are we going to do everything in the cloud to do everything at the edge
It's probably going to be a bit of both
Depending on your use case
This feels like a very cloud-centric model
Because
Sending my data from the secure MCU up to
The cloud security
Development
How might I build this to work in borovan
Distributing in Bayern
It may not have
Always on or even reliable connectivity does that break this model
We have to see the clouds in a very important element
Microsoft message
Talk about the intelligent cloud
Intelligent
Azure iot
That allows you to take computation you normally run the clouds and bring it down locally in the environment
Stare
Container ship that's offline
The time
Factory you don't want to shut down your after shutdown your product line
Just because you have lost your internet can
And so have the capability bringing this coffee tastes very very vocal as well
Am I correct in understanding that this will work with Azure iot Edge
Yes absolutely
And
Would it work with some
Other
Edge Computing platform
I'm not using
Iot Edge
It could be made to work with enough
Platform
We got it
Chicken got an operating system
And we provide an API
Programming.
Chips and
Or giving you internet connection
TCP IP connection TLS connection
Programmer to program
The actual device
They're open today
Program
Execution
Local device they're open till
Whatever local devices are other things in the environment as well
In why is Microsoft doing
What is
Obviously we care a lot about iot security
White in Turkey
What is a hardware platform in a Linux distro which is kind of crazy for you
But you don't participate in the it
Think about I guess Jeff back and think about
Descendants you
Billions of these devices
Coming on
We look at it cuz they that the Technologies of people are using right now
Free azure
Those devices are not going to
Security nightmare
And we looked at it
Start this project
4 years ago
Looking at that eclipse
Future that looks like a very scary future and saying
Yeah we have the technology
We have
A lot of
Experience we could that kind of do almost started the research
Could we take everything that we've
Learned a Microsoft about
Security
And figure out how to package unit
Such a way that it could be used on these very very small devices
So that we lived in a secure where
And that's what we create with that
What year was kind of
When I talk
It was reason is Galen wants to live in
The security is out there is out there for him to use
I could not get it
So we're bringing the Technologies to make those
Microsoft
Ultimately a corporation
Responsibility
But we see is if there are many of these devices and their
Picture and people
They will be part of Cloud solution
So they will use cloud services
Are all of the Azure service
So we see tremendous economic benefits there
Okay so what are the things that you cited several times in relation to the creation
This is your seven properties of Highly secure device
Just briefly letsrun
Okay soda
7 properties
Margarita Trust
Then defense-in-depth
Small PCB
A trusted Computing base
Dynamic compartments
Certificate-based Authentication
Online are recording
And renewable security
Yes okay
So
Let's just dig into a couple of those that people might be like what
Compartmentalization what does that mean
Okay I love this
The compartmentalization is actually probably almost one of the oldest
Security Technologies
Known to man
And this is the idea of
Having multiple layers of Defense
Having
Separation of concerns
Example
Compartmentalize with Floodgate one part of the ship
Because there's a lake
That doesn't just fill up the entire ship
Buildings where we have firewalls inside a building if there's a fire
Prevent it from property
Lego Back to the Future cast
If you think about all that s***
One of the most important lessons we've learned at Microsoft about security or less
20 years is that it isn't a matter of
If I will get her
You will get high
Make sure to buy some version of your device
Question
When your device
What are the medications and what how prepared are you
It's a building compartment actually end of the chapter
Self and the operating system
Allows us to if
Partnership becomes compromised in summer
That compromise
Compartmentalize they can't go any further
And then we can use the rest of the ship and the rest of the operating system and software
To build restore
Security.
I'll even go a little bit farther because one questions you might ask
These chips are different
The traditional MCU
We brought in a cortex a class
Processor in addition to the cortex M class
Non-exempt to use for the very first time
The reason why
Because it gives us Dynamic compartments
Traditional MCU
Aesthetic Apartments I have like
Maybe at TruStone and then one other Lakes
Willie two compartments on the chair
And so
You can't change departments like after you've been out and employment if you figure out the
You custom music
Security vulnerability or some news form of attack
Like with a device been out with you
Light years
And some new
Security attack is
Embedded we can actually change the compartmentalization
In the device by years after it's out in the field and mitigate against and prevent that attacks will be you
Wow
That sounds awesome but it's also brings up these are not chips
Battery-powered devices the song
It's going to consume
More power
Glass chip
Well one of the innovations that we get so we partnered very early with
Arm
Building
Figured out
Scout II with their help to construct an a class
Processor
It is much lower power and
Smaller area
10 people traditionally associated with the cortex 8
And so we will see battery power
Address to chips
All of this sounds
Really intriguing
My biggest question
With this is forever
Going for
Is there a way to retrofit some
Space force
Are all healthy
Millions
Hundreds of millions of connected devices that are already
Well it turns out
In the empty space there aren't that many device
And so we're really kind of worth it
Perfect timing rainout address
The problems before they can become problems or all of the new devices as they
Can created become
You know it's like right now
Every Appliance in your kitchen is
You have not been to my house
Is your kitten
Oh yeah
Okay
And these will be on the market
Like physical devices
The first
Azure sphere certified ships will be available in volume this summer and we expect
See the very first
Azure sphere base
Products on shelves
Devices on shelf
Alright everyone for Christmas this is what I'm getting
Alright Caitlin thank you so much for coming on the show
Oh thank you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week