Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey
Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
Awesome we've got a great show for you
Do this week
I am in California at Bluetooth world so I'll give you a slight update about what's happening in
Seattle theme park
With the shortest rides
I don't know
That's a terrible thing
Okay we're also going to talk about Ikea's new smart home efforts Google home getting a lot better
Compact dishwashers what the smarthome can learn from
From Cars
And we're going to talk about how Congress just sold out your privacy
When it comes to isps and what that means for iot
Kevin's got a story about his quick set
Z-Wave lock
And our guest this week is Dan herscovici of Comcast
Plus we've got an interesting case study from Samsung
And now
Let's take a moment for a message
From our sponsor hey this week sponsors
Me that's right it's me Stacy
So I just want to tell you guys if you care so much about the internet of things that you listen to the show check out my newsletter
It's at ww.w. Stacey on iot. Calm and it's actually the stuff we don't talk about it
Osso whole new perspective on the Internet of Things the other thing I should say is if you're interested in advertising
You should email Andrew at Coyote podcast.com and that's why
Are ready Kevin
After that inspiring ad
Let's talk about
Yeah I did not realize
Shame on me but you knew about that several months ago but it's now public information that's new Prada
Alex from Ikea
Connected
Bulbs and sensors
On the cheats really
Yeah
So this is the
Prodigy
Yes I actually pulled this as an FCC filing back in December
If you got my newsletter
Hartsell right there
All right
This is a zigbee
And Wi-Fi
Wireless lighting kit
Basically
That Ikea sewing for is $85
It works out to about $85 however you can't get it unless you're in Sweden right now so it's actual prices
Swedish krona
749 4
Gateway remote controlling two bulbs
Which is
Addison DeLand
I'm hoping this will come to the US
Because they did file actually with the FCC which it does indicate that
They want to come to the US because otherwise why would you go
Go to that effort
And this is kind of his part of Ikea's actually
Been creeping into kind of technology for a long time now they've they have wireless charging on Summer
Moser furniture
Which I was just concerned they have 14 different wireless charging options some built into their furniture and some you can
Module and apply to room furniture which is kind of interesting
Actually I didn't realize I had
Yeah it's it's 30 bucks and for those who keep up with a standard Caesar all the chi
Wireless charging standard is what's used
Which is
Pretty much the winner right now
That's the one people
Apple's going to use
What Apple actually does I believe use it for the Apple watch so that that's if that's any indication
Yes
But who knows
We are not saying that that's how
We're just saying
Really cool video a while back
If you search for Ikea and smart kitchen video I bet you'll see it
They basically showcased
Sensors in
A projection
Tiny Pico projector that projects images down on a counter
It was a really neat like
It's not real it's something they may never do but it was
Clear that Ikea is thinking about how to bring kind of
Intelligence into the home
And I feel like this could be like a great
Gateway
For mainstream
I just mainstream America and mainstream Sweden
Well I mean I can get such a global presence
So they got a huge advantage of a lot of these
A smart home product companies that don't have their own storefronts right there just a single or two or three products and
You purchase eyeliner
Amazon
You walk into an Ikea store and you you live in the rooms that they sell essentially right that the showroom
The make it walk to the show I mean there's little hidden shortcuts turn off
You actually care
Yes yes
And I think that really goes all huge Way Forward for people to understand why these products can be beneficial
When you can just walk into a room and Ikea
And put your phone down all the sudden your phone say it's charging and you say oh well that's kind of cool
And then there's a little Maybe edematous
Turn off or whatever it may be
And when people it can experience it and it's not that expensive to add
That's huge for I cannot have a huge advantage
Maybe they should
Call up Amazon in
And get mad amazed voice services
That would be really cool
That would be cool
Picture frame with that
Let's do it
That's a very exciting
Also in Europe
And here's actually something I was thinking about with a key
There's a story about milk which is a
High-end Home Appliance come
Having a hat dishwasher
The challenge here is
It's actually the big point I took away from the mule story
Wasn't the vulnerability because that happens
Was this the statement that because meal is an appliance company and not appear play it come
It doesn't have a process for reporting
Are fixing bugs
So the people who actually did the research and noticed it
They sent an email but meal never respond
In this is something that I'm hoping that Ikea's thinking about it really anybody who's doing this
Is
These products you can't just
Create ship out to the world you have to think about security
And you have to think about an ongoing relationship with the customer because that's really what this does this creates an ongoing
Relationship
Between you and your
And
It's got to be a two-way street which means you can't just suck data from their dishwasher
You have to
In return
Give them value
Which
Probably includes not having
I agree with you it's really an extension of the existing support business model you if you're in a support your product or supporting everything about
You can't just selectively say well if the nozzle inside the sprayer
What year did the song
You can't have it both ways
Exactly and I should say that this is a professional
Dishwasher
Commercial level
These are sold into you know Church's kitchen
These kind of places
And the vendors response so far is
Take it offline
Or firewall at offer
Nothing else
Which
I'm sorry
The shaft for the penetrator
Restaurant
Hey can you open up a socket I need to clean some dishes
Yeah
Going to happen so
That's the lesson I took away for
This
Hopefully that
Ikea
Pay attention to this
Do this
All right
So other big news
Google home real quick I'll disclose that I do work for Google as
As a contractor consultant more in the Enterprise area with
Chrome in Android such not been any opinions are my own
But I'm really excited that that is my ping is really excited about this one
This week
They basically said that they will support a bunch of new
Products in the smart home section so these products are
Wink
Lifx bulbs rachio connected sprinklers
Vivint
Which is a smart home alarm platform
Frigidaire
First Alert
Tp-link
Best Buy insignia
Geeni smart bulbs and Anova
The maker of
Suvee cooker
Of those Brands probably the biggest for most of our audience is going to be
Wink lifx rachio
August
Sa August
I don't think it did but it's in there
It's also a sew in
Was it let's let's kind of work this out
So to connect stuff
What you're going to do is you would go into your Google home
App
You go into the menu
Connect
Be smart
Earth smart home settings
And you basically see a little plus sign you hit that plus sign
And you're going to get the list you
Click on the item you want to add and then
Your ticket to an authentication screen
Right that's how you link the IRT accounts to Google home
We should know what this also comes to Google assistance not specific to Google home so if you have assistant on your
On which
Shaw Android 6 & 7 devices now
It's very similar to the process
So this is really
Interesting
And
With August I have to tell you guys if you're like yes I can see if my doors are locked you cannot
Unlock your doors from
Google home
You also will need
A August connect
Which is basically a bridge to give your August access
Wi-Fi
Yeah
Now August is working with companies to get if you have bluetooth support on your router
One day
You should be able to control your August
Build your router
If there's bluetooth support
That actually reminds me that Google added support
For certain Smart Home Products months ago
Through the Google Wi-Fi
Devices
Which do I Bluetooth so I wonder
We can check
We'll check on that will come back to that
Like next
Okay
So that's exciting
Frigidaire stuff
Pest Control
Conditioning the other thing is actually the tp-link
Outlets are the other thing that's kind of exciting
ESPYs are
We're going to get into something
This may seem
Virtual pet
I think the best bang for your buck
After you get
Any digital assistant
The echo
Even Siri
Oracle home is to buy an outfit if you want to test smart home stuff
Because this is like a $40 invest
You're doing Siri you're going to have to do a
Idevices
But if you're doing
The Echo and Google home you can actually switch between a WeMo
Or the tp-link outlet since both
Supported
End
You just pop those in I think it's great to have it is your bedside table lamp just plug your bedside table and then been to it
Name it something
Ghetto nice and when you go to bed at night
You can tell your
Smart home device
Provided it's in your bedroom
Hey so-and-so turn off the light
Book that's so nice
And I feel like is everyone
For 40 bucks it gives you a sense of Mike
So I don't think that's controversial at all cuz I actually agree with you 100% And the reason being you can take that switch
Weather whether it's a WeMo switch on tp-link whatever or not device
And you can move it around your house and test different thing
It's not a single thing you can take you can use it to control anything that you plug in essentially
So you can start getting a feel for what you might want to automate
Add insulin to a Smart Home
For very little
So I agree in fact
My WeMo switches is literally my
Night table next to my bed just as you would setting
I told the echo at night you know shut the light so
Jewelry
So
Here's here's where things get a little
I don't think is it controversial
How scandalous
But here's
Here's the
WeMo security
Always makes me feel a little
Little iffy
And they're very active when they discover bugs but
They discovered bugs a lot
Nemo products
And their software has gotten so much better
There's a lot of people out there who
Who hate women
There's a lot of people are like God sucks
I think it's much better
I actually
I like my WeMo switch I think
It works well
But I am very careful about firmware updates because
Because they have such a big footprint
There's a lot of attacks
People of hacking their WeMo switches
The other thing is
The tp-link switch is I guess I'm concerned about the security there because tp-link
Has got so many products
+ 4
Some of their routers have been
Implicated in some of the heart
Put a password
Hacks
I just
I don't have a lot of questions about 1
How do they feel about security
Into
They have a huge portfolio products
To maintain and I worry that
Smart home Outlets are probably not make
No soy routers and such more
Winter nails
So that's what feels kind of controversial
Did you talk a lot about security
So if you are really panicked about security
Maybe this isn't
The device for you
Unless unless you have a
IOS device and you get an idevice switch
Because I'm your car
The homekit security built in
Right.
Haymeadow mess
Turn off my bedside table
Alright so that was our digression away from
Google home let's go back to it and ask
Heaven
This is change your mind about
I knew you were going to ask that
It's funny because people at work I was at Google New York City yesterday and
Hi I've known about the news like a day in advance so
We were talking about it internally And Then There Was X going to get a Google home right I'm like
The thing is
I don't think so I mean I've already invested in for echoes
So
Really
What am I gaining
But I can't already do
That was the big thing I stuck with the echo because it had wink support and it might
Smart home hub is built around wink
I mean I'm having real good wink support is now on Google home
But again
I think you're gaining
A much
More
Intelligent
Assistant
Better search results if you use your Echo
If you want to use your device that way
I find the Google home to be much better
I've heard they're very similar
Sentiments from many many people
And I think
For the audience the dead search histories things
Yes I would agree with you I'm not one of those people
So you could be because it's
Really
Very useful
I think so here's my thought
Because you have the
You could always add a Google home to your setup and it's not like
It has to change anything
No no it's just do I need a v
Voice interface in my house right now when really
I have Google assistant on my phone
Which
Takes the place of
A Google home
For these purposes
Twist
Google assistant on your phone
Okay
Then you're fine
I just don't have it I can
Okay
You carry your phone around with you so it totally Miss
All right
I'm going to say for anyone who's on the fence who's like
Echo or Google
This actually
Unless you have
An unsupported device in
I'm going to tell you right now there is a big handsome
Put a device right now that I know is coming soon
We'll talk about it next week
Intrigue
But
I think
You could go either way
And I would probably
AdWords Google home
At this point
Because the
The ability to talk to it
Is so much
Better and semantics for like things like turning on your lights is actually
More user-friendly
Cuz when I tell my Google home
I can basically tell it to turn on living room lights I can tell it to turn limit
Lights on
I don't have to have a specific phrase where the echo is very
Ulta points
Call FairPoint I'm a little surprised that you personally because I know that you like your Sonos
They've announced
Echo integration
You're back in November
And I have not heard any integration plans with Google home
Well dang it
You just made me think
Boom
That's true
Will have to
Keep listing or keep
Okay I'm keeping the app
Okay
A lot of factors here
Alright so
It's okay it wasn't like I was going to sell my
Sonic
I am going to switch my Google home
And my echo
So my echo right now
The kitchen
Main living area of my house
Google home
My bathroom
Swap those out
And live with it for a
There you go
All right so that's Google home
Let's talk about
Let's talk about the other big story of this week
Texas
Consumer broadband
I have a seal
Laws
I cannot believe you did this
So
I totally can
So what happened is Congress passed a law the president has not yet signed
Congress
But you probably will
Revoking
Obama era regulations about governing your
Internet privacy
So
Basically Tom wheeler FCC
Couple years
Was it last year
2 years ago
Basically said that isps could not look at your broadband data and
And then use it for Mark
Purposes
And sell it
To third parties
In this data includes
Places you go on the web so your url history
That's all tied to actual
Information about
I think even the apps that you use on devices I think
Yes actually even the apps that
Devices
What this means
For all of us were like
Cow the first thing it means to me and I already did it just last night and plumbing I should have been a long time ago as I install a VPN
Participe and service and install on my mobile devices
I went with OP Rochester a couple last night
And I ended up going with surfeasy VPN
Which I believe is part of operas
Sweet of
Products I'm going to double-check that's why I'm not getting bad information there
Design and development
Canada
Which I think is $50 a year from
The five devices unlimited data
They have
Smaller plans one device unlimited data
And so on
But I've got a tunnel to
Use my ISP and they cannot see
What I'm actually doing
Got it and I
Have
Viper V
Vyp
DIY videos
The last night
Vyp
Eat in this day and age we ignore valves yes I remember now
Hawaii
That's the one I use that's also available
Everything
Including
Your router
Is it frustrating
It can be done
And we're going to
So
When we saw this news
We wondered what does this mean for your iot devices
Kevin asks a really good question
Inside Out 2
Emails to people
If this happens what does it mean
Can what can
Myspc
Yeah cuz I mean a lot of people frame the whole
Issue as well it's it's my browsing information out there getting and songs over to put my question and
Sasa never talked about this before the show
Just kind of tree has to come a little bit right now
Does that also mean
Include
Data from my iot devices and a good example at Stacy
Can an ISP determine if your home or away because they can now see that information
Or can they see your your thermostat settings at any point in time or have a history of that
In which case if they do when we don't know the answer this question yet but
Wings worth asking
Let's assume that they do for a second
Could they then sell that information to an HVAC
Provider that says hey
But these guys on your list to hit up for new energy efficient system
Based on the use of our devices
Pets
Obviously not what we want so
I need a lot of questions here
But I think they need to
So
We came up with
It is certainly possible for them to know what devices are on your
So that is
That is
Unless you're running a VPN at your router
They will be able to see like a
There's traffic coming out of her house coming
Email from Nest from
Wink from all of these other places
Stowaway2
Ensure that that
Data isn't more exposed is look for products that have end end
Encryption
To the cloud
And
That's a hard thing so cuz I when I when I talked to come
Companies about their staff
Security products a lot of them will say
Hey
We have
Encryption
More information please.
Caption in a lot of them encrypt your data
A good product should encrypt your data
To the cloud
For example lifx got in a lot of trouble several years ago
Because they actually
They were sending your Wi-Fi passwords in ssids and
In plain text
But
People notice that in real life x what are you doing in life exercise
My bad
So
These sorts of things are getting fixed all the time but I would say to anyone making a product
Hello cloud-to-cloud encryption
You should probably start talking
About that
And consumers
You should probably look for that if
If you don't want to do
This kind of information going
To your ISP
Correct correct
Cheer is
To sell you things it's always
Oh that's true
What can I say and what can I do with it is better the two questions so I completely agree
I'm going to go a little tan gentle hair just for one second
I'm just going to say that I will never
Put a VPN on my router
Amazon Echo
That is one potential
Think about that
Sorry
Because it may not geographically in
You're from so it's going to
Boom
My main thought was
Very related
I get all my television content
Through the internet through PlayStation do and as soon as I put my VPN on my mobile devices
Even though it's on my network
The service will not work it's like I don't know where you are I don't know if you're allowed to watch this
Space TV shows
You're not
So
That is a a bit of a hassle like soap
I put the VPN on my devices
Not on my router
And I
Using Android TV Nvidia Shield TV.
Can I install a VPN software on that because then I couldn't watch TV
Oh so this seems like a really great opportunity for vpnmakers
Allow you to
I don't know
I guess it wouldn't be
But maybe authenticate your real address
No no that they don't want to provide that information I mean you know I'm 10 spoof locations people do spool okay
Patience to get like overseas content viewable here for example
It's going to be messy as more people cut the cord if they're going to use vpns as well so
I'm not sure how that's all going to be handling
But that's my reason for no VPN on the router although I would prefer the VPN on the router I will be honest
Yeah cuz you can't put a VPN on
On your nest
Or maybe you can I don't know
Guys twerking
That's that news
Let's talk about Bluetooth world
Because it's where I'm at
So I'm in Santa Clara right now and
I came to this thinking that I was going to learn all about Bluetooth mesh
Because that's my latest obsession
Put in 5SOS
And sadly we are going to still be waiting
Forbush
And that is
It's not not happening this year
But it didn't happen
Connect Bluetooth
And Magic is not a Bluetooth world
It sounds like it'll be
A couple of months
And the other thing that I heard
Is there are
Go in addition to mash
The next big effort from
Bluetooth
The Sig
Is going to be bringing audio
To Bluetooth low energy
So there are actually two radios happening
We talk about when we talk about Bluetooth is a whole one is Bluetooth
The classic version
And the others Bluetooth low energy
So a lot of your devices that do audio
Are using Bluetooth
It's classic
Because
Bluetooth low energy
Was too small
Too small for audio
Great
So what I'm worried about
Or what I've been kind of thinking about what my brain automatically went to when I heard this was hey
Are we going to end up with
Bluetooth classic being kind of useless as we bring
Everything into
Ble Bluetooth low energy
I'm kind of like
I asked the guys that is
This was a marketing guy
No plus this is like 2018 stuff
She's like over the long-term though
It does become
Question
Bluetooth classic
So
Going further down the road
We might end up with you don't Bluetooth low-energy and Bluetooth mesh
And we'll kind of
See what happens to the old.
I should also say the exciting thing about Bluetooth low energy
An audio is they're going to get a chance to revisit the audio codecs
That's the compression
Because some of those
Our Lake
10-15 years old so
We're going to get some more modern
Kodak switch make car audio sound a lot better and that would be
Good for everybody
So I can actually speak to that from product I'm already using that takes advantage of higher Bluetooth audio streaming quality
Which I believe is being incorporated into
Some
New devices and maybe minutes the standard foot
Love to see how that plays out
Basically ldac is a high-quality wireless audio via Bluetooth mechanism that's the date
Need a transmission of a standard Bluetooth which is the eighth
2dp protocol
That's 328 kbps
Cenizas 990
Kbps you get more data
In the Stream
Through the Outback
So that's kind of like I don't know
Bluetooth is the Sadies going to adopt that or not but
It's already available in Sony's
High-end headphones which I happen to buy as well Sony's mobile phones
Pensive
Alright before we get to Kevin's installation dramafun
It is time to tell you guys who won the wink Hub last week
Auctioned off is not
Not the right word
We are the giveaway of my version 1
Link up
And
We got lots of awesome responses and I'm still going through the questions some of you guys are like
I want to wake up and I have a question for you
I'm circling through
Your questions because
Because time
But
Doug Schreiber
Is our lucky
Winner
Come on down
Giardino's
Send an email
And you know
We can totally do this again
If you guys thought that was fun and
Moving right along Kevin
Your Kwikset
This will not take long but it's disappointing my purchased
Kwikset Z-Wave lock
The 910 I believe
On Amazon about
2 months ago
The reason I purchased it even though I had one as I had to swap out the Finish iodide
Meet my HOA standards here
I need a brass and then just had my front door replaced last week
So got the front door replaced but in the new lock
And for the life of me could not get it to connect I mean I tried dozens of times
Couldn't get it to connect to my new wink Hub to sound like
Is it not supported anymore what's the deal but no supporting like it still supported
Crazy me I ordered another one of the reason I ordered another one
Too late
To return the one I bought from Amazon so I'm kind of disappointed in that but
That's life
Got the new one
It too is a 9/10 but the
Box is actually different
So it looks like I got a newer
Version of the Kwikset
Insure another pair right away and I'm all good
I had to buy two locks
It is what it is
I thought it might be because the new Z-Wave plus I'm on the wink Hub 2 but I don't think it is
Did you do next
I did exclusion zip
Natural
Pro tip for people who are like listen to this voice
Which I listening to
Kwikset
If you encounter the first thing you should do
If you have a Z-Wave
Device that doesn't pair to your hub
Is run the exclusion mode
On the Hub
And it basically unpair the device
So Z-Wave once you've paired a Z-Wave device to another Z-Wave device
It's
Are there for Life in
Excluded
And usually that
Solve the problem
But
This case
Not
Don't know
Dona could just be a bad block on the production line when it doesn't matter
I still think you should be
I think so too but
It doesn't matter what I think
Clearly I bought a second one from them
All right
That feels like
All right that's enough for this week show
Stay tuned
For our guests who is Dan
Herscovici of Comcast talking about its purchase of icontrol
Why
He doesn't like Z-Wave
And a lot more
Comcast plan for smart home world domination
That's going to come in
A word from our sponsor hey everyone we are taking a break for The Internet of Things
Podcast to bring you a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Samsung artik
And we have Curtis Sasaki of Samsung here alright so let's kick this off with just a
Quick sense of what
Samsung artik is
Samsung built a hardware platform to make it easier to actually build
Iot products
Harborside
Who's also built the cloud for years ago we noticed that none of these
Products actually work together
So we sat upon a mission to build the cloud that actually makes improper buddy much much easier
Interoperability is a huge problem I know you and I have talked about it is it
Consumer
But for businesses that actually has to be really hard
So how can using Artic help a business
Because we built the Cloud solution that makes it easy to connect lots of devices
Services we've already done that we're working with a company called Breezy who has an elder Care Management solution that works
Tablet so we can take advantage of an elderly person might be wearing a heart rate
Wearable
Or
We may actually see that the light skin
Houses
Turn on and off
And without information they can know
Way more about what's happening in
Someone's home normally if you were to try to do it yourself you have to go and talk to every single manufacturer make business
And then do all immigration
Because artik cloud has already done all of that
Please you can take advantage of all the work that we've done
And create better solutions for elderly people
So this highlights that you can't build these products alone
So what have you guys learned
About building an ecosystem
When trying to build
What's an iot
Well we figured out on day one that
Even the sides
Company like Samsung
It was really important to find companies you could really bring
Their technology their expertise
And work with us together
And by building an ecosystem it actually helps
Other companies
We're actually trying to build iot Solutions
And get those products to Market much much easier
So we're very excited about the partners behalf who bring in
You technology
And we're very excited to also work with new companies
Ideas and capabilities
Great thanks for your time Curtis
Aging parents I definitely want to look into how iot can transform Healthcare
You can learn more about how Breezy
Valtech
Curtis mentioned leverage Samsung art
Cloud Builder solution
Quickly and securely
By downloading the case study at
UW
Arctic
Dot IO
Slash case study
Again that's www
. artik. IO case study
Hey everyone welcome back to the internet.
Thing show this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and I have Dan herscovici who is the head of Comcast
Xfinity home business
Hi Dan
Hey Stacy how you doing
I am doing super well today
So
You're in town for South by Southwest
And
We just did a bunch of
Conversations about voice which was super
So why don't we start with idea of
Where is Comcast now
With Xfinity home
So
If you go back to our founding we found the business in June of 2012 that's when we launched
Xfinity home
Nationwide
We offer home security and home automation solutions to all of our subscribers
I'm in as the business has grown dramatically the core of our business has been home security
I'm really the thing that resonated with customers
Was this evolution of home security the migration from an unconnected security system to a connected security system in what is it
Connected security system
Give you it allows you to arm and disarm remotely allows you to receive push notifications that allows you to see
History and tracking in your home but even more so the Xfinity Home Solution allows you to add
Not only life safety security like Solutions solutions that call the police call the fire department call the ambulance
Which is traditional but we will buy a home security system
But also
Peace of Mind automation what I mean by that is layering cameras leering and door locks
Play to not only does does the Xfinity home connected security system layering all the things that you
Expect the security system to do
But also
Ads on peace of mind it's
This is where
What is very popular today cameras door locks doorbells garage door openers
Things that
Aren't necessarily emergency services but provide you peace of mind did the dog walker
Girl arrived
Did the babysitter arrive
Do my kids get home from school okay
Did the Amazon package that I know was delivered
Move
After it was delivered
Is it still at my front
These are all things that is do I have a water leak
These are all things that
Don't necessarily need to call the authorities
But I'll give you
Comfort and peace of mind in a connection to your home
That you otherwise didn't have
I think
That's where we evolved to when we continue to grow we can talk me to go to the ecosystem
Please continue to grow the experiences we offer
And we continue to integrate them across our service
So why would I get something like this from my ISP as opposed to ATT or another service
That's a great question when do we get as a spur
Only I think
That only Comcast can go give you experiences that are integrated across your services so from Comcast for buying
Video
Internet
And Android security solution
So first and foremost you can interact with and control your security system from cool things like your TV the biggest screen in your house
We offer a kind of end-to-end
A support installation in a way that nobody else does I that you know
I know that sometimes
Isps or mso's might get a little bit of a bad rap but the reality is
We deal with
The less-than technically inclined
And were used to handling those those types of calls in the fact that we have
People that go into your home and
And repair and teeccino Justin you have a phone number you can call single phone number regardless of the device at senior
Are home seems comforting to people that are perhaps
Concerns about not knowing what to do when a device is offline
Alright so
We've established why am I want this
You guys have actually brought in a number of Partners
I think 9
Was was the last count I had and maybe that's different now
But
How do you choose what companies you want to work with
Our philosophy is to be open
And to be as easy to integrate with
As possible so we want to make it
You want to make the integration process the the the the the work required
To join our system to be very easy
That said we believe in a curated
Ecosystem one where
Comcast
DP test and evaluate these devices not only
Did this company do the integration properly but is this a great door lock is this a great garage door opener is this
Is the right light switch for me
And we test those devices we test those devices in our labs
Once again as in their intended environment in
Noisy WiFi environments in ways that consumers might use them everyday
And so
We hand-selected you know we'll deal with large and small companies as long as
They pass over yours quality
And
We stand behind those quality test so
If your inner ecosystem we will support your device
So when you call
Comcast
And you have a problem with your Chamberlain garage door opener your Lutron light or your nest thermostat or your
August door lock or Yale door lock Schlage door lock
You know we will help you
In probably deal with 80% of the questions that might have otherwise gotten
Bounce around to different vendors and frustrated you know
As a frustrated individual on many cases I thank you for that
I do not live in a Comcast area so guys I've never experienced
Okay let's go by the business here because
Right now I feel like we've got a lot of crap in the market
Just crazy stuff happening
You guys are creating
This
I'm going to call it it's expensive
Like from a DIY mine
From a mainstream perspective I don't even know if there's really
Is there a demand for it
What's the business here
So it's a to think about it this way let's let's let's take a step back
Depends on what you're calling expensive right
Each of these individual devices
You know if you take them to the garage door opener in the door lock on the door bell and the
Camera
What do you get from us or not is going to end up costing hundreds and
The dollars the question is
How do you bring those devices together
I'm in a way that lets you get the most value out of the money
I think of Comcast is
Developing an underlying base platform
And that platform is
Automation in
And
We're going to put that platform in every house
On top of that platform
We will
We will sell Services we will offer you services that you find Value
The first disarm security it's the one that people understand it's the one that's the most
The most compelling to Consumers today
And we sell the home security service but back home security service still sits on top of this underlying
We will sell a video service so last April we launched 24/7 video recording
As attached to Xfinity home but soon it'll be
Sold as a standalone
So now you have
Video recording and video analytics and all the things that come with that type of experience
That's once again a standalone service sold on top of this song
And will Laren
Energy management and other services along the
The key is
That we are in Bedding
The underlying platform in that in everybody's household we're doing that
By placing the software stack in the control in the Gateway
And there's a lot more to come on that but it's a it's a quite exciting development and then imagine
You know our
Scale
Quite impactful so
So when you talk about deploying the solution
And everybody skate we are talking about tens of millions of households
That we can affect very very quickly
You guys just
Well I don't know if it was a big deal for you guys but it felt like a big deal for the smart home space
So
You should probably Define press what part of I control you bought
And tell us what you guys plan to do with it
So I control service to Major consumer
More customers
To say who then service
One part of eye control
Call call converge
I serviced mostly Comcast and other
MSO
The other part of eye control called connect
Their major customer with ATT
And so you know some other man
So essentially split the company into
I'm we bought in the end of the development organizations everything was
Was very separate so it's not that difficult to separate the
Which organization was based in Austin
And the other connect
It was based in
Redwood City
So we bought the the converge business
The Austin team
And it's been it's been a great experience we
Yo I control has been the
Core software engine behind their security system since the day we launched
We know the team really well we work with them every day
And having them part of the Comcast family
Allows us to
Just accelerate development and accelerating
Innovation I'm also excited to
Being Austin and crate up
Create a Technology Center of Excellence in Austin
That kind of attract employees that we otherwise wouldn't have access to
I'm and I'm excited to come into the wholesale business so
Everything we talked about for the past few no
Few minutes here
It's been about service and consumers
Pretty soon with this acquisition we were servicing other
Cable companies in there
Security solution so we'll have a you in a bigger reach to consumer that we otherwise would because
Cox and Charter and Rogers
In Canada
Oral going to be on the same platform
And all the things I've talked about all the features and functionality that we've discussed
Will then be passed on to those
Now other than yourselves I feel like a lot of the isps
Have they started
Like Verizon had an effort to do a smart home
AT&T had Digital Life
Time Warner Cable which is now Spectrum
Also did but
They really backed off at
Will Time Warner and Spectrum are
Continuing forward under the charter brand I think
I think you'll see more there
But you're right
And
I think
The challenge has always been
The business
Prom is the business opportunity in the Smart Home
Versus the business reality
We stumbled a bit too in the beginning because we placed equal weight
With
Business opportunity on
How fast will smart home technology grow will the consumer
MyPay
Is there value there
Versus home security and we quickly realized the way
To win in the short-term
What's the laser focus on the home security experience
Add smart home and automation capabilities underneath that umbrella but really focus on
Home Security
It wasn't until recently by recently I mean
You know April of last year
That we really started to
Your venture out again
Could we turn down or stand alone
Offerings
Into the the automation space namely
24/7 video recording
And you're soon to see
You know other launches from us around thermostats Energy Management so
We're tiptoeing our way back but we're doing so in a slightly different way more
Focused measured
Experience so we know that consumers value video so let's nail the video experience
Let's Nacho
Offer hundreds of devices that people can
Potentially by
Let's really nail a singular experience that we know people love
So once again it's kind of like think of home security is a vertical that we've focused on and then we're going to layer in other verticals along the
That's
I think the more better recipe for Success versus
What we seen previously and why others kind of stumbled
By which is vomit up some sensors and devices and hope it all
Right
All right
What about standards because this is a huge thing that
God we are still talking about 5 years in
Or longer really
Do you guys feel like you need standards for the Smart Home
So I struggle
With the database
I see a need it's beneficial it would be helpful
But I don't know that it's holding back innovation in
Look we because of the nature of how we build our
Standards are valuable
If we want to just essentially allow anybody to join the ecosystem untested
And so that it would just work
But what are approach
Has been to test and evaluate and cheery this ecosystem
So what you know what are you connected over Wifi or Bluetooth or zigbee
Is invisible to the consumer it doesn't really matter
You know there's some stand popular standards older standards that we don't support namely the
The one that comes to mind when people talk about us a Z-Wave
But other than Z-Wave
Amway support everything else and everything just works and I think there's a lot of
Reasons why we don't support Z-Wave that have to do with it security and coverage in the home and reliability all the things that
We talk about when we
Talk about you know
Having a curated solution that we know is reliable
I think we are from our point of view
We made the right decision and we support the devices that matter most
The big debate right now in
Smart home is actually security
My God I cannot go a day without some stupid connected device getting hat
So how do you guys view Security on the Comcast platform
And security overall in the industry
Look I mean security is top-of-mind
For us and for the consumer we find the consumer asking those questions more and more lately
I'm we take obviously we take security very seriously
Frankly we have a dedicated
It security team
Just an Xfinity home in addition to what you might expect as being a very large eyes p a large corporate security team and we all
Work together
The encryption standards we use for our video product than any other
Solutions are similar encryption standards for
Bank and financial transactions
I think that there are
Without revealing too much there are benefits
To being both the ISP and the provider that manages your your devices I mean
We if a device is behaving
Badly
We can see that faster and quicker
Because we are the ISP and I think that provides a layer of security that
Perhaps others may not may not be able to
And what about your partner's how far do you check their security
So that's once again I mean it's a really great friend with a glad you raised it because
The third pillar is not only do we test do they do the integration
Probably not only do we test are they good
Door lock for garage door opener
But we do our own penetration testing we do our own it security testing and
And we've found vulnerabilities that we've been gone back and asked the manufacturer to correct before we were willing
22 undisclosed unnamed
Light bulb manufacturer
Had challenges and we wouldn't launch their lightbulb until they
They address them and I think they appreciate frankly they appreciated it just as much as we appreciated their react
Action their speed of response
The fact they took it seriously
I think there's not there's benefit the ecosystem of wrong the way we're approaching the
You guys have a really cool advantage and being an ISP and also having the router in there because I think
There's a lot of talk about doing security at the router level
Is that something you guys are thinking about it
Launching for Xfinity
Yes
Stacy
That's a good plan we are looking at it we take it we think it so it isn't very very interesting opportunity as long as the
There's horsepower in the router
To do all the things that you
A lot of people
Talked about this idea
Having a company come in and being
Security provider for the smart
And it seems like an ISP might be in a really interesting
Place to do something
This website is
Got Junior ISP maker
Make sure everything secure anyway if they're offering this
Maybe it's maybe it's password management maybe it's
You know authenticating devices I I don't really understand how people think this might happen but
UC Comcast getting into some sort of business like that it's like malware for the whole my dad I mean I think that
Look what's what's but whether or not we're going to get into the Uber going to charge customers
Decide cuz that's
There are a lot of things we can do
Some
You should be likely included at no additional cost and some might be a premium feature that maybe
I'm have some real cost that we incur
That we want you know and only like a subset of the Cavs
Super Bass mic
We are seriously looking at it we think there's a lot of
Of opportunity there
Personally I use a password manager
Or I don't know I have
Edward as with most people have dozens and dozens of accounts
And you know I won't you know advertising here but I use a great password manager
And that that's an interesting
An interesting space but more so
If all of a sudden an iot device that for the past year has always spoken to
You know camera.com
And all the sudden starts talking to camera. Are you
Not many people can see that immediately and that's an interesting alert that something might be going wrong
I have a router that does that
All right
Will Dan thanks so much for coming on the show this weekend anything else you want to tell me
Next pleasure to be here and thanks for joining me it's out by
Well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast please join us next week
When we have another amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are hankering for some iot news
Sign up for my newsletter it's Stacey on iot. Com thanks for listening