Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
We have got lots of on the voice activated
And supper
We got to focus on China this week
And a really cool example of Sensor Fusion
We're also going to talk about light bulbs
Believe it
Some Industrial iot
T news Plus
Holiday Pro tip
From me
A
Question from one of our listeners about homekit
And Belkin products
End
We're going to talk about why the war of the future
Baby Phat by something that's
Kind of like
Voltron
We also have a message for this week sponsor sparkcognition
And now
Before we get into all the good stuff let's have a message from one of our other sponsors home isn't just a place it's a
The feeling the feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT housekeeping
U-Save so you can feel protected wherever you are introducing the ADT Security starter kit everything you need
Need to get started with ADT Pulse including a camera professionally installed for only $49 visit ATT
E.com podcast today to learn more require 36-month monitoring contract installation
Activation fees apply easy pay required
Certain markets are excluded licenses available at att.com Florida a through F 0 0
01121 Louisiana Ave
1:6
Okay
Let us talk about
Let us talk about talking
So good news for people who
Bikes
Google home
Actually before we get into talking about talking
Any cool stuff
On the Black Friday deals did you partake of any cool smart home or can I
Home stuff
I did I really held back I should bought something that we had on our
Iot gift guide list
I really like that Sonos one review and it's so much that I bought my own which I got like $50 off
IDE
I did not get
Anyting
I just couldn't pull the trigger
I looked at all this stuff and I
I'm feeling a little bit of Gadget overload in my
I think it's a function of headache
Too many cables too many apps connecting I just kind of got tired
So I have more than most that I understand
Yeah I think I've hit a threshold
I didn't but you know
There was some great deals to be had so hopefully
You guys part 2
Or have you checked out our
Gift guide
All right
So back to
About talking
Google home is actually getting
Really valuable skill
So like the Amazon Echo Google home has
They don't call them skills they
Call them
What do they call them
Oh that's
Kakashi's not schedules
Cannot remember
Soon with the Google home
Instead of saying Okay g
Talk to
My LG Smart to turn on robot cleaner
To make your LG Vaca
Dinner start cleaning
Susan able to say
Okay g
Start the robot vacuum
And she's going to know what
Which is awesome because the biggest challenge I currently have with my Amazon
Echo
Is
Madam a
You know ask
June to preheat oven to 450 degrees
Theoretically should not be hard
But is
Kind of
Bright red
This is actually this is a key reason why my family doesn't buy into all the voice command stuff that like what did you name that late again
What's that called over there and I
I recognize their frustration so when Amazon actually added the
You know turn on lights to the localized groups
Not too long ago
Define on using an economic interests a matinee lights off
Yes
They're using it now
So this is great because I don't want to remember names of companies and products are ninjas
The thing I just want the thing to work
Exactly
Google has released this
Which means that
Comedies just now we need to
Create their New Boyz
This
If done well
Could
Make
Brands
Like give up the fact that we're going to buy all LG appliances in our home
And instead we could just have a crack
Optical interface with them
This Is My Hope
Samsung's actually the first to implement this too by the way so if you got Samsung appliances
You might want to test us
Yeah apparently you can say things like pasta dishwasher
I don't know why anyone would do that
My favorite
How much time is left on my dryer
That's really useful cuz my dryer is upstairs and if I'm downstairs I have to walk
Are you guys
This is life is tough life is tough
My life is hard
So
That is that
End
We also have
News on Amazon
Madame a skills notification
I'm a little leery this but Kevin you want to tell us what it is
I woke this is actually already in place but it's been
Expanded
I believe how should I don't know exactly when this year it was
Amazon said hey we got a developer preview of notifications for Alexa skills and as of
Today in fact they are expanding that to a wider audience
So this is going to be
A way for you to get personalized notifications in
Save
Peekskill I don't know maybe we have an iot podcast skill and maybe we have a notification that your echo says
Does hate there's a new episode would you like to play it
Whenever we have a new episode so
This is what's coming or going to get hopefully not bombarded with notifications from are echoes but hopefully some valuable ones
I would like the defaults
To be for me to set
Those up as opposed to having the
Will and that's fine I don't know exactly how it's going to be by default it's going to be opt-in for user
There's before Easter vacations
So if you don't help in you'll never even get
Notifications
And then even if you opt-in you can disable or suppress notifications
Hearing your app where you can put devices in Do Not Disturb mode so
Alright then I feel a little bit.
My
Amazon Echo waking me up at 5 in the morning to tell me a new iot podcast is dropped
I actually have
How to make sure my things
Polish I have a Nifty
That
Turns one of my hue light bulbs red
So I can always walk downstairs and I'm like
The pietasters
Quick why is it red red is usually bad make it green
You know what the old school lights
And they don't do
I almost was one of my Black Friday almost
Your lights are on sale should I get the newer version and then I'm like
Stacy you spent sixty bucks on these bulbs you are not spending fifty bucks on Brady bulbs
Yeah if there's a notification I want I know this is unique to me and other people maybe live in a townhome Community like I do
The mailboxes are down the street obviously not at the houses
And I would like to know when the mail gets here and I would love a notification for that in fact I was actually thinking of creating a little dirty
Board system
That pings me when they open the mailbox
So the challenge actually that's actually very easily doable
Just a basic sensor
But exactly
The challenge is getting WiFi
Or connective
Yeah I was going to buy an NB iot Dev board
Okay yeah like I think particle has
Sorry I don't nobody else cares
Actually wanted to set this up like when I first got my smart thing
Original
13 and then I was like
Is like wait a second
Maybe we should even talk about this maybe we should build it pat didn't sell it to the US Postal Service
They got money
Maybe we should build a patent and sell it to Amazon
All right speaking
No not speaking of Amazon
We just spoke of her
Waze
Get a wake word and voice commands
You are surprised that
Waze is that still a thing
Will innocent is the implementation Waze is great
Don't get me wrong I know a lot of people use it
But after being purchased by Google and having some of the ways functionality integrate into Google Maps I kind of thought way
Please as a stand-alone was going away
Clearly that's not the case because so many people use the app Waze app and as of today you can on
On iOS or Android use the Waze app to say
I think I can say this because I don't think he'll say anything law
Okay Waze
And basically it's kind of like turn into a voices
Distance so now you can
Initiate your drive get a preview of the route you can send reports at a pitstop
All by voice which is
Awesome love it love it it's in the Waze app you going to look in settings
Sound and voice
Talk to Waze
And then tell the okay Waze function on
Wow
That's actually pretty cool cuz I don't use it now but now I'm like oh but I could
Okay
Voice
Let's move on to China
Because
China has some news
Rather
Actually China itself has news
Is China itself
So
Two things here
It has two interesting bits China is
Beginning to set standards for the smart
This is the
Okay here we go the China Light Industry Council
And the China household Electric Appliance Research Institute
They have released a white paper
Tell you about nb-iot in the smart
And the cool thing to note there
Kevin Bob is that there
Choosing nb-iot over Wi-Fi which is interesting to me
They're saying we're going nb-iot because
Lower power consumption wide area coverage and low cause I all of which I agree with but I wonder
Why
Because
And I don't know is
Broadband penetration in China very low and therefore people don't have
Home netwerks and therefore WiFi
I don't want my appliances connected to a wide area network but maybe there's a good reason in China for this I do not know
It's a really good question
When I think about you
What's so I'm like having your stuff all connected
Dwyer is at work
Easier to
Control4 in circle
And it's probably better for the manufacturer's because one of the big challenges with
Connected appliances today is most people don't actually connect
Connecting a device like a washing machine to Wi-Fi is actually for
Pretty hard for most consumers one because they're like
What do I need to say
Which is totally legit
Question
Even though you just answered it how much time is left on the dryer
Or
They've got it download the app on their phone and that's irritating
Coyote
Some of those
Especially if your vendor
Paid for the connection because they get a benefit of saying I owe this about the breaker hey you need a new filter
Do you want to buy one now
So there are reasons
To do it but
It does feel like
That's ask
The surveillance thing which I don't disagree with your comment but I'd like to they really want to know when I'm frying Foods when I should be baking them I don't know
Think about things like controlling power
Lake
What if I think about this is water such an issue in my neighborhood
Neighborwho like
Runs the sprinkler on off
Off days what if your ration power like we ration water and
Sprinkler system or sprinkler with telling you
Be like hahaha you can't run now
Ratted out by the water company
We live in a freaking desert and we're in a drought what are you doing
It's not just you
These guys are doing is they're trying to
Set standards
In connectivity
Aren't we all
Did we do need it
But also in human machine interfaces
And the cloud computing
So from 2017 to 2019
They're going to
Create
Standards in organizations for smart Manufacturing
From 2019 to 2022
They're going to create the smart home use
Standards
And then from 2022 to 2025
They are going to plan for those things to eat
Actually used
In the smartphone
So I think this is a good
Perspective like
Hey let's start with manufacturing let's get that
And then when children place then we'll set the stage
Smart home and they will actually like
All
That's not a crazy
That is
Hope that's only part of the
Here yes
Is there other companies
In China
Where am I
They are working together on iot and Ai and by they I mean
Baidu and
Xiaomi
Which if you're not familiar with Baidu is like I can search the Google of China quite honestly I think it has over 75%
Sent market share and search there in China
And Jeremy is one of the largest handset Sellers and manufacturers in China you can get some of those phones
Outside of China
We don't seem too much here in the u.s. not much detail here it's just an announcement that was made at
Xiaomi's first developer conference in Beijing
Just saying that these two are going to start working together
Don't know what
Are we going to
Do yet
I know by do does have like a
Voice control
OS called do OS so that's available in some of those yummy Harbor you can buy today so maybe they're going to interview
Great that with whatever they can with Baidu I do not know what
It'll be interesting to watch
Because this is going to be the big coyote
AI movement that we've seen here
Over in China these two large companies
Yes and Shelby has a big Smart Home
Effort they make outlets and
Bose outlet
But I bet there
So
We're keeping an eye on
Yeah they work with Smart TVs smart watches and all that as well home appliances
Baidu
Hopefully they will be better at it than Google by the way you guys the Google pixel buds that I got
My back
Not a fan
Too much
I didn't see anybody who was a fan unfortunately
I read a lot of battery is messed disappointing
Google
Come on
Okay
To a really cool story about Sensor Fusion
PID of Sensor Fusion is you take data from
Multiple different sensors use algorithms and you get different data that's even better
Pretty cool concept
This is
Kind of like that I guess it's not technically sensor
Fusion it is using cell signal so the performance of your cellular network to detect
Weather so
This is a way to detect
Weather more accurately without buying
Moore weather station
I already have tons of sensors and radar and so on and so forth I thought this was an interesting Twist on
No leveraging
Traditional technology that we already have the cellular networks themselves to actually
Improve weather at a local level and it's climacell which is a boston-based weather company they raised 15 million Siri
Is a funding and again no sensors or anything else
Measure how weather is impacted by wireless communication networks therefore you can use that information to
Get more accurate
Detailed weather app
Look alive
Which is awesome and that reminds me if there's a company from Israel called
Breezometer
I've heard about them a cup
X
They actually use a measure
Weather patterns and then they use existing weather sensors but they're using like crazy events climatological
Models
To predict whether locally without using more sensors
So this is actually
Tide of a trend
I'm probably the smart one because
Maybe we
Have the data we need we just need different algorithms
To get to it as opposed to like spending more on sensors which are awesome but you don't require maintenance
Car batteries
Require all kinds of other things
So
It is there's a third piece to the weather aspect
It's not covered by this company but
Crowdsourcing and that's how I get my weather actually through an app called dark sky and it's uncannily accurate because they will tell me
Rain is starting in 7 minutes
And I show people that when I'm out of an event or something like that or bundle up or get your umbrella out
Turn off
Almost to the minute
The rain starts falling it's really impressive
Yes I feel like there's a thermostat company that's actually working with
Either dark sky or another crowdsource weather app
Weather underground or somebody
Now only I could remember the thermos
But it's actually a really cool story
So the pointier crowdsource
Sensor Fusion
And
Algorithms
West Ada
Making lives better
But maybe not as a
Who's a good tagline
What is the inevitable decline of the hype phase of
Iot
I should have mentioned this
While back but a company called emberlight
They need smart sockets
So smart light sockets
And possibly
Stopped selling
They decided to shut
Don't they couldn't make it in the market
Which
Cool product but they were like
It's too competitive
Too much
We're shutting down so they have a cloud service so there light bulbs will continue to work for
Three to four months
And then
They won't
Yeah that's this gets back to what happened to every buying Harbor service and in this case
The service is going to stop working unless somebody wants to pick it up open source somehow or whatever
This was actually a Kickstarter
Project
It was and I would say
It's not if you're buying a hardware or a service product I think
You are buying a service product
You have to recognize that there is an inevitable service product
Associated with these things
Maybe we hadn't really
Recognize before
What I asked a question knowing the answer
You're right
Absolutely but I asked it's the people think about it
If you guys I think
Yeah so also and other lighting
Stack lighting
Which
This is really disappointing and my friend Richard our friend Richard Gunther
Who's over at the home on podcast
And the digital media Zone actually reported
Is first so kudos to him
But Staffing
They've gotten out of the consumer lighting business they sold their bulbs
Looks like
They are now moving into the managed
Aging-in-place managed Beijing
Care
World where
It makes total sense
They have built algorithms that understand where people are in a room
Yeah based on sensors in the light bulbs and
Vacancy basically oh grandma got out of bed this morning awesome so it's less intrusive
Our people feel that is less intrusive because it's not a camera
So it makes a lot of sense but it's also an indication that
My God don't feel typo
Well there's just so many players in that space right now
Honestly I mean not you could probably name 10 light bulb companies off top of your head
I'm sure really need that many I mean up competitions great I get that
But really do we need that many
Well in the challenge also with lightbulbs is these are when to replace your light bulbs
They're supposed to 11 if you got LEDs. Going to last for a long time and it's really hard like with me
Paying another fifty bucks for
Better Greens in my Philips Hue color lights I was like
Not worth it
I would say there is a sengled is a lighting company that seems to have this that has they make bulbs that
Meatballs with different functionalities built-in domes that someone has speakers some of them have IR for security some of them have
Cameras it's very interesting
But they keep them pretty cheap
And what's interesting there is there model is that you will spend you know 12 to 15 bucks and a light bulb that's connected and
Then in a couple years you'll be like yeah you know what I need a different personality
Let's try this
I don't know I don't know
No I I don't think it will personally but
Good luck
If it does seem happy for them I just don't see it I mean I'm a one-and-done shopping when it comes to light bulbs
I think getting people dragging their mind here is going to be
Tough So Good by Amber light
I stack you had
What stat to be clear is pivoting
Who's Ember lights they were
In retail stores
These are legit companies that made real products that actually work
It's hard out there man
All right
Lettuce
My holiday Peru tip from Stacy
Okay that's a terribly nice
Reading music for that
We do need music
For my holiday
I for the fourth year in running have
Pulled out all of my Christmas lights and
Connected them with
Various
Some of the Mercedes some of them are Z-Wave and some of them are Wi-Fi out
But my pro-tip to you is for your outdoor lights
Label
Your Outlets
So I take a giant
I'm using a
Silver glitter pen
Because that's what I had on hand
But you can also just stick a piece of tape on it and label it on the tape if you don't want to
Put silver
Glitter ink on your house
So I have upper balcony I have
Snow witch
I have a snow lamp that shoots out like
Pretty snow patterns on the garage
I have a
Roof and I think I have a little balcony and then I have my eye twinkle lights so all of those are permanently
Is labeled so I can just pull them out and put them in the right spot which is awesome it saved me like an extra 20 minutes cuz usually what I did
It is I have to
Hook them up to my Z-Wave stuff
Jeffrey hook them up
You don't spend the time figuring out which Outlet
Work
So that is my Pro tip
Name your
Holiday lighting
To something it can't even be kind of generic
But just give each one a name and stick with it
That name on the outlet
How to make it easy for
Good idea
That's my Pro tip
My other pro-tip is guys
Amazon Echo
When do you group things into a room like turn lights on at cetera
Does recognize now the Lutron
Which is awesome except for two of my Lutron lights are ceiling fans and so now whenever I turn my lights on my ceiling fans
Turn on soap
How to ungroup at
And that is also information you guys might
A neutron
Kind of a bummer because I really just wanted to be like turn on fan
What it's like
That's a light
Cuz we have stupid names for advanced we call it our downstairs when is big fan or if there's one is Master fan
I always forget you know my turn on the fan is like there are several things share that name
I get the same thing
With the certain lights are rooms and whatnot so I want to get away from the whole names thing let's have some contacts in here and you know
Screen on the contacts
But let's make it the right time
Cuz that is going to light switch
Okay
Let us move to the iot podcast listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of electronic lock
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & Security system so you can get the most out of your lock whether you're an Apple homekit user are you
Madam
To see what's possible visit schlage.com to learn more
Adhere I'm going to warn you guys this is a
Good question that is
Given to us
Bye
A speech to
A text to speech robot baby what do you think
How many grams
This is not an act
Maybe a good reason for that
I believe strongly there is a human
Did actually ask this
Stacey and Kevin
I'm calling on behalf of Michael from Brisbane
Australia
Announce the bridge to provide High
Have you heard anything from Belkin recently regarding me my timesheet
Compatibility
Like it will come out on December 4th
But
Kevin
Yeah well for folks who are not familiar with the actual details Belkin actually announced back in May that
WeMo devices would be homekit compatible through a WeMo Bridge
Piece of Hardware that I don't want another bridge but okay I get it
The reason was because Home Care
Required hardware certification
An actual implementation of a security chip however that has changed
Apple now that does not require they can do it on the software side so I suspect Michael that the WeMo Bridge
Will never come to pass which is fine by me
Unfortunately
Dokkan hasn't announced anything yet
In terms of this so I don't know
Really
When they're going to I presume
That CES in January which they singing I will both be attending and we will certainly be talking to the Dunkin folks and visiting the
WeMo area
Dad
Maybe that's the time that they announced it I can't see if they haven't announced it by now
I suspect CES is really good
The big thing the time in place so
Hopefully the second week of January we will have a definitive answer for you
I hope it is not a bridge I hope it is something they can do on the software side and just make it sew
Yes I'm actually
Because the homepod
Was the Apple homepod was delayed until early 2018
I'm actually hoping we see a lot of really cool announcement
At CES
Even though Apple.
Historically
They don't go I'm hoping we see a lot
Partners or hear from people that this is going to happen like I hope the homekit ecosystem coalesces
Sometime after that
Because right now it's not as compelling or as rich as some of the other things and
Are other options out there and I think that's a real shame
Because
Yeah and
Just looking back at prior CES is a lot of the announcements have been we're going to have this it will
Come this year
I think we're at the point now where you will see more actual
Implementations and products are available
Like immediately or
Student not sometime next year we're going to have
That's so that's my hope Michael that
Belkin says we got it as of today
Boom
Yeah I would like it is past time
Together
Poop or get off the
That's what I said
You did you went there
I went there because I am so frustrated
Now
After that
I feel like we should take
A moment
For a word from our sponsor and then after that stay tuned for
The internet of battle
How we are going to connect
All of our robots are drones are soldiers are sensors
To create the battlefield of the future this is a fun conversation I had with
Someone from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign so stay tuned for that oh and before I go I just want to remind
Everybody that Thursday that is actually today Thursday November 30th if you're listening to the podcast in the day
Andrew in San Francisco
Target
Open house and we are going to be talking about business models for The Internet of Things
You kind of want to go if you're in town because you know
It'll be a cool conversation and you can meet me or you can watch it live streams on Facebook
And I'll be sharing a link for that
And that's the one across from Moscone Center
Cool gadgets
And now a word from our sponsor hey everyone we are interrupting
Message from our sponsor sponsor is sparkcognition I have here fellow
Sparkcognition
To talk about
The Pie vs Bill deliver
Implementing a AI in
Many companies have internal data teams and they're looking to implement a machine-learning solution internally
What are some of the factors they should consider
In doing this
Your first question typically comes from the executive
What is the company's core competency
And how is a line
With the idea
Building a team
How to create cognitive analytic Solutions in house
Another aspect
When you assess what is it
Strategy required
For me long term
And how far can you really go in here
Thinking about implementing machine learning
Solutions
Seems to be
Speedy attractive at first
Then you realize it is sex
She just the tip of the iceberg
If you try to build a cognitive solutions that is it
Scalable
And finally implemented it starts
With executive team sponsorship it propagates throughout the stakeholders
So what advantages and services can an external vendor provide
One an AI company like spark ignition
Has tested and evaluated existing and available tools
Algorithms
Techniques that are in the market or any research
Knowing the best product
And having access to the right tools can make a significant difference in how long
It takes to complete unused case application sometime to value is one Bennett
Second computing
Middleware platform
OS algorithm
Continue to evolve
In change
Rapidly maintaining and upgrading applications
Quickly become a bottleneck so we that long-term
Court is a great benefit from vendors that are specialized
And finally that was argued that vendors are exposed like no one else
2 hundreds of used case
And this know that
Out of the box
Is extremely beneficial when leveraging that knowledge to support a particular client
So what would a partnership look
Like what does
The internal and external team which responsibilities would they have
So I would like to
Start saying that we becoming
Ascension of our clients capabilities
Distance to engage
On the pilot project refers to
Agreed on a success criteria
LC's ability for the project
Then we break
Project introduced
Specific and manageable Milestones that both sides
Quiet
In our teams can understand
Influence and drive
In summary
The internal team on the client side will provide us
Subject matter X
Richie's to fine-tune Diablo
Vacation
Define the usability of
And that is actually
Critical because Ximena cases
The same application
Will be used by different parts
Organization on the client side
We will do the end-to-end effort to do project management
Will do data ingestion where do dashboards
And we do the final deployment
Follow the sounds great
Where can I go to find out
You can look at our website for cognition. Com
Hey everyone welcome back to the inter
Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacy and today's guest is
Professor Oak
Shooter science
At the University of Illinois
And we are talking about the battlefield
Future
Can you show me and I am super excited
But let's break this down
Alright so you guys recently won
Grant from the Army research lab for
Helping develop
Battlefield of the future look like
Vision for this
Game from
Cheer. Concern in the future
The US
My face
Adverse
And after college
Need to be ready
Technology Warehouse
Cr1tikal logically Advanced 1
Will
Net worth all the answers
Add that well
Allow them
To work dynamis
Intelligent player
Mission
Without
Okay so I have so many questions because
The stuff of science-fiction
Is the ID
In the future
We're going to just send out drones
Fight for us
I think the idea is that we want to really put the people out of Harm's Way
If that is something that we can do with robot
We should definitely do it with it open
Not everything we can do it all by example
Issues
In this project
Is BattleBots shalt not kill
Without
Somebody has
But there are many other function
And the question
To what degree we can push the economy
How practical that is how safe that is how ethical
Intelligence
Turn into septic safe
Okay so today
And then we also use drones extensively
And so
What changes
Are we
For this project
Because I feel like we already use a lot of
Definitely.
And in fact
Idea of the
Filled up
Future P&G net worth
Leverages what the US is already liquid
We are in fact
Good act automation
Artificial intelligence
And this takes it to the next step
We want to Network all the
Did not individual entity
That are working
Southside controls
Individuals now we want to see
Think of them as
Beast 2000
All Phase
Cinco distributed
And perhaps the analogy that comes to mind
Yes with Transformers from the
Transformers
We have that thing
Shapes into whatever you tell it to
Except
Hear it filter
CVS at little
Digital component
But they work together as a
Joint Commission
Activision
Intelligent
It has to
Think on its own how to accomplish it
Mission
It should not be micromanaged
I don't want to tell all the Thousand Parts what to do
I want to be able to tell that in Seattle what to do
And it should be able to
Figured out how to do it somehow
Distribute the jobs
Now the individual Parts could be anything
Could be the armor
The people wear
Is the weapons themselves
It could be very dangerous
Krispy Kreme
Mobile
Golang
It could be sensors that
Deliver information
It would be even algorithm
AI search
Components all of these
Net worth together all of these are part of the mission part of that
OKC that sounds more like Voltron as opposed to a Transformer
This is not an 80s
Cartoon show this is
Real life
When you say things
Might work in conjunction
Which information
For my drone can you put me in a bind
Commanding the battle
This could be one of the types of missions
Is a Tax Commission
Disaster Response
Mission
Lots of recent hurricanes
Endorse definition
First environment is hot
What deity denies
Team of machines and sensors
Going fine
Survivor
Stay in the aftermath
Hurricane
Find out there
Where they are
Accessible they are what is
The best way to
Come and get them
Perhaps
Steven Universe
First state to them
Until
If you want help comes in
Now to do that
Configure in the right answers how elegant
When you do
Park when you took her house
Configure Linksys
Computer supplies we as a
Battlefield Commander
I don't want to have to make those decisions myself
Sense8
See your face answers and 5
I want to leave that
Decision to Maya
Palace Mayan
My intent
Is 2 safe
For example survivors
Gulf Pointe
Rescue them
The machine
Quit be able to understand what that's
Sensory devices in terms of actuation
To be considered
And they would go
Do it
They can eat
Give me some status updates
I made
Manage them but at the high level
Okay so in this idea
I feel like a couple of possible weak links so one is right now
Connected devices
In all honesty and update
Crack them all the time
Peps Lake
I have to do is go to war with someone who's really good at computers and
System
Resilient and then also is aware that
This is a wonderful question
And in fact this is
Exactly why we need
To be informed
Research project
Deployment exercise
Security integrators questions
Alien
Ask question
Safety and that's why
That's why we have 10 years
Play Century figure
Indeed
Security is one of the main source in the
Everything we do has to be
Your everything we do has
Safe has to be
Brazilian
It has to operate in a very hot
One of the ways that this is
Is different from
Similar Technologies for the internet of things that are
You was in
Civilian life is that we are operating
Demanding
Break up
Is it going to rain
Infiltrate
Components
Indication
How do we face that has one
Let's talk about how to break that up because I think there's some
Obviously
Right now one of the big thing is you know cracking various protocols
Electronic
Components that actually perhaps
Do as much manufacturing of our electronic
Components
That we can actually control so I'm curious what you
You guys are thinking about the
What one of the very interesting aspects of a project is that division
Conan
I'm not entirely Trust
Not all the components
Other
Not over components
Yeah some of the components perhaps a drastic but some of the components are what we called grey components or even drive component
Gray is where you don't quite know
You should trust this
Rather sweater is actually
Maybe DeLong
Does animated mean when I see if you can somehow
Exact value of it anyway
But the point is
We do not
Are all 100%.
Supportive
Security
The mechanisms that allow you to pretty quickly
Power components that are not doing what they're supposed to work.
May have been in
And eliminate them or isolate them
What is that prevent
These components
What do we learn from technologies that are already out there about
Security cameras
Especially when it comes to things
Using machine learning
Do detect
Security
Stanton in network
Is a heart problem
Clearly the more components
What's internet work
Told me she was at all this
Components
Palestine is bad
Sometimes
There is benefits
The more components you have
More
How to be resilient
Because even if some of the components go bad
Compensate
I think one of the
Get network
More
The enemy will have to go and
Hawaii is one of those to get to the other
However
Resilience mechanism
Are in place
Evil twin
Really clear despondent isolate
Then that's it
Mitigated
The other part is we
To make sure that
TSM
And I think that
One of the
Critical lesson
Trump
What I want to call the field of
Cyber-physical
So the physical world
Subway's learn how to
To build for example
Plane
Passenger airline
Computer operator
Be safe of course that I asked
Spent a lot of the time
We can learn from that
One of the
Cheaper happy
Lesson
Is this skillet
Allows this
To build systems.
Continue to operate correctly even when a part of this
System has been compromised
This is something that
Need for a lot of things
Automated systems like economist
Plane
Autopilot
And I think we can chat about along for the bathroom
Because components will be compromised
Distance have to operate with those things
Components will be shot.
This is Denise to be engineered in such a way that at our age.
I agree and hopefully some of this will apply back out to
Commercial projects
Connection factories in other autonomous systems that we're trying to build today in real life
I do believe that some of the lessons
Let's learn from the
Project
Chucky be applicable to
Industrial demand
Disability application
Let's get a little deep into this because you did also mention ethics
And I imagine that's associated with
With soldiers
With the button which is already happening today
It's some level
The idea of sending drones
Robots
There's an economic cost but part of the horror
Deterrent
Against War has always been the high cost
So I'm curious what it means
As we automate
War
That's a wonderful question I said
IID Electric bill
Think of it that way
If we don't do it
And others
Do it with Whitby
In good shape
My guess
She's not we will not be in good shape
The question is do what degree do we want to push in an hour and I think
There is an important role of for ethics
Here and in fact
We do have
I'm looking at hotels at 6
Design and that's the practice
That is done in many larger project because a lot of them
Design decisions
Do
Beautification somehow
The product
What is enable
What's the weather
OpenTable
Empowering
What we want to happen or not
I think
We need to think through the implications of what it means
Install Network things
Delegate certain decision
And
What's a machine
Should follow as far as ethical code
When I make a decision I make it
In accordance with Lauren
In accordance
Ethics
In accordance with
With knowledge that I have
Make me laugh
Well
Wicked
Impart that knowledge on the machine
But we also them
Make the machine
Stan's the Lost
I think it's
Wonderful design problem
It's something that's
Bridges
Is the technical
And the social and ethical and illegal
And we need to make it
Safe
We need to make sure that the machine
The knot
Perpetrator fences
Got
Be liable for in a bad way they're not going to go kids
Another question
Tied to the ethics
Is
Right now if we look at what's happening
With fighting in Syria for example
What you see a lot of is civilians
Are left
And what becomes interesting to me is this idea of we have our robots fight
Worse for us it feels like a lot of civilians could be
Caught in the
Crossfire
Quite literally
I don't know if
We're really thinking about so I am curious kind of how you guys think about that are also
Not actually about
Their cities
Jen homes
Neighborhood
I think what you said is one of the important motivation
Theaters of operation if you will Insidious
Most people
Today live in City
Future Wars will increasingly be in
It's pretty hard.
To fight a war
He damaged
Collateral damage right now is
Huge problem
Say something
We cannot improve
Idea is
Is that
If we have Smart than welcome
Maybe they can if
Tell your story and this happened to a friend of mine so they
They were driving across the bridge
And there was a fight
Any fire and fighter jet
Flew over the bridge
And I circled circled again
Until my friend got off the bridge
Just driving around
And then that just
Saved my friend's life
Gateway to the
Away
Now today we have
Maybe your check go there's nobody there so I can fly fly fly fly
Civilian
There's no way to stop it
What is the Rockets
Maybe the Rockets
Until what that fighter
Jet Pilot
Little bit
Jefferson
My point is we tend to sing
Bob's Market weapons
More dangerous plants
And that isn't it
To explore How can I
Make war
Safer
For the civilian
With less collateral damage
So I think that is.
Can we create an FAQ
Environment
Can we create system
That was you just clap
Damage to zero
High School
Try to
Future and I think maybe with smarter Technologies
And
What about our military hardware is going
Two places like
Police
Specifically
Because last year
In Dallas the Dallas Police
We're faced with a shooter
And they actually
Parking garage
And took a bomb disposal
Robot and then
Is weekly kind of
I feel like there's a lot of questions
Around something
We have in the USA history of our military
You're going to
Police gear
Can you set down the chain
And
Are we prepared for that as we
Connect stuff
Make it even smarter
Maybe just a couple of things
Things that I should mention one of them is.
And this is a big
IPhone 5S
Project
We are not
I think that's an important
Distinction to make because
Robots fighting
Weather
Kill anybody unless I push the button
What's the weather today
How to make
Vacuole function
Is a completely different level
And it's something that we are
Not going to do it
Now there are lots of other functions
Example data
You know I need
Sensory data
I want to deploy my sensors
Somewhere where they can
Can see the enemy and I want them
Tell me what the enemy is doing
I want them to report when
Something happen
Requires my attention I want them to
To do that for the magically I want them to
Automatically understand
When the enemy is doing something that might
Star. Delivery
Function of those alerts
Mason
Is
Lena Paul website
Do Automation and Tool
Splicing their intelligence and autonomy of them
Worry about people
Okay
I have learned a lot
I'm intrigued to see what we can learn from this project so thank you
Very much for coming
Thank you very much that was fun
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com thanks for listening and we'll see you
Next week