Hey everyone welcome
Go to the internet
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a stupendous show for you today we're going to kick it off with news actually from last week
This was the
Proposed IPOs for Arlo And Sonos
So we can talk about that
Then we're also going to talk about prime day Bargains you might want
The hunt for
Some details on Google home product discounts
And some updates to Google Assistant
Nest software and Sonos
Plus we're going to talk about
Space-based iot and Smart City efforts
From LG CNS
Finally
Will include a link to how to make your own indoor air quality monitor if you
You don't want to buy one
We have our guests this week
Is Randy Schneider who is
Delta faucet
And he's going to be talking about the creation of the Amazon
Echo enabled kitchen faucet
Going to be
And we'll hear a message from our sponsor a pharaoh talking about how they worked with Kenmore to connect their Appliance
Now
Let's go to a message from another one of our sponsors
This week's podcast is brought to you by Avnet and it's podcast when you guy today's ideas into tomorrow's technology
You need a lot of changemakers along the way to bring their stories to life after it has partnered with not in pause
Possible labs to create a new podcast series about spectacular people harnessing the power of technology for the sake of
Humanity each week they'll reveal new life changing technology and the story of how it came to be sold
Listen now to podcast not impossible to find the podcast on your favorite podcast app
Just searched not impossible
Actually sounds
Yes
All right
Let us get started with some financial news
Takes out now
Nevermind
Okay
We have last Friday
Netgear's Arlo division
Filed for
An IPO
And Sonos also
Filed for a night
That's an initial public offering it means they're going to raise money on the stock markets and that money will presumably go towards making their prey
Products better
Giving them
Forward and all that good stuff
The fun part about IPOs is you get to read a document called an S1
And those have all kinds of financial aid
So we know now that Sonos has sold
Over 19 million products
In almost 7 million households around the world
And last year they actually
Reported a billion dollars in
Almost a billion
In income cell
That's actually pretty cool
They did have a net loss
In
Bisco 2017
So
But that's a lot of devices
Sonos has been around for
A really long time
13 years
Now there's also Arlo
From our lows we have figured out
That
They have sold
And they have made
In
Physical
370 million
They don't have a
Prophet
And that is because the separation expenses to get them out from Netgear IndyGo public are costing them more money than
So they do something called pro-forma
Numbers that take out those
Extraordinary events and those numbers actually show that they are also proper
Which
Is pretty amazing for hard work
Incredibly proud
But hey
Yeah it certainly helps that if you look even a year before the revenue growth from 2016 to 2017 at the report
40 is 100% growth I mean there
Just gangbusters growth
Right and they are growing from a small
What is 7 million devices
Really good
This is Arlo
I'm pretty impressed with that because they've only been out for just a few year
So
Coyote doing well
But
These documents are full of risk statement
And that's
3 par for the course Very
I used to read these all the time
What I'm noticing though in
There's a couple things to notice big trends that
Are worth
One Arlo talks
Quite a bit about its relationship with AWS Amazon web services
And that's because it's cloud is hosted on there and that's an integral part of its business Arlo make security camera
Ascend
That date I get sent to the cloud
The camera footage and
The fact that Amazon
Now is one of their competitors is Broad
I'm curious because they don't talk in there about
Rethinking their Cloud strategy but I'm curious if they'll find their way over to
I guess it wouldn't be Google because Google has nest
So maybe Microsoft or some other cloud
Yeah it kind of does leave it to Microsoft Azure because there are no
Hardware
Competitors in terms of
Products from Microsoft in this space
So I wonder if we'll see that and I also think this is an interesting
Given the rapid m&a happening in this
Area it'll be
Interesting to see if other
Iot device makers decide to dump Amazon is it encroaches more and more into
The smartphone business
Text Ashley that's what I was thinking I mean right now you don't have a full Suite of competing products from Amazon but we know they
Several companies are two camera companies I can think of or camera component companies
Between blink and ring
So
They'll compete even heavier in the future I think with Arlo
Yes so that's one Trend I'm going to keep an eye on it
The next year
I also be surprised with Arlo they had a really tremendous emphasis on
Engagement
Weather app
And they try to compare themselves to
Facebook and I don't know if this is like
Padding because you know you wanted
Investors think you're sexier than you are which is very common in these documents
But they talked about
Our spin
Monthly active users
And so I don't know what is your thigh feel like
I don't want to buy a device that
It wants me to engage with
Therap I want to buy a device
Performance Smart Home
Function for me I almost never want to be
Cameras are a little different
But still
Yeah I completely agree with you on trying to compare the engagement of a security camera app
To a social media app or other even they compared to Candy Crush and I'm like really you know
You go to a candy crusher go to Facebook when you make when you have some downtime right
Kind of pick and choose one that is safe for in your notifications coming in at you like I want to read this but with a camera
You may be getting a lot of notifications sooner like anytime somebody walks up to my house I get a notification it's not the
The same type of Engagement
At all
So that's just me
As weird I don't know if I should read more into it because usually that engagement in Social
Forms is too precise both users and
A potential for
Add dollars
Yeah and social you're engaging
Because of other people you're engaging with other people maybe not in real time maybe even real time with messenger apps that are related to
Direct messages are not engaging with a
Person here
It's not just don't see that as a comment or metric is comprable
Little weird
The other thing that I thought was super interesting
The Arlo
Was actually
The strength of
Retailers that they
Disclose so their cameras are sold
In
Three main places Best Buy Amazon and
Costco
In 28% of their 2017 sales
What's the best
Which
Well people are still shopping at Best Buy with my first thought
16% were at Amazon and 13%
Costco
I don't know Kevin disaster
I thought I was crazy
Crazy in what way cuz I actually do go to Best Buy
When I got to have something and or tip
Piccoli it's on sale
Right so if I need something immediately I won't get from Amazon I'll go to BestBuy unless I can save a ton of money on Amazon
Best Buy would be
First and then Costco is really interesting because that is like for mainstream America that's where like
Your mom shops right so having
13% of their revenue
From Costco I thought was
Guys in a smart home space get your product
Good Lord
Well yeah I mean we go to Costco probably once a month and I have seen the Arlo products as well as many other electronics and it soon
Soon as you walk in I don't know if it's the same with every Costco but I've been to a couple in my area
It's like as soon as you walk in that feel like chronic sex
It's right there
You cannot not go through it
And
I don't have any
It's hard to just ignore and walk past it so I think they get a lot of decent sales by
Having products in there for mainstream
Consumers in your right what companies to get their iot products in their I have seen some others obviously but yeah
Brighten your face
In your face
All right
So the only other thing that
People
Hash this out quite a bit and it is worth tok
Talking about his friend the sonosite
Cuz it talk about how Amazon
Can pull their functionality from the Sonos 1 speakers
Really with limited notice to Sonos because it's an AP
And I looked at that and everyone's like
Freak out
Yeah
This is not great but this is something we've been living within the smart home Community forever
Talk about it later on
Only answer a
He's our question but this to me
Points to the need
Data scheme
A unified data schema like alljoyn was supposed to be
Like ofc is supposed to be but is really not
So far
For the home
And for these devices because right now
Everything you buy is at the mercy of these supported apis and they can
They can go away
And they also change on a fairly regular basis as I've seen just from tinkering with
Coding stuff
Something breaks because the API was changed
So I agree with you I don't know that we're going to
Get to that point I would love to but
Everybody seems as a run
Proprietary solution to this problem
Happens it's going to be terrible I mean I guess it gives a lot of negotiating
Leveraged
Thing like Amazon
I mean imagine the first time someone stands up to this people are going to knock
I agree with you I also think
The first
Product makers at
Loses compatibility for the functionality
He's going to make a big public stink
And blame Amazon rightly so
I don't think
Amazon will want to tarnish its
Brand with that so
When I saw this and people worrying about maybe this goes away
I make don't be silly because
Frankly Amazon doesn't make its money from selling Echo products
It makes money by
Getting the data building you services on that data and getting people to buy things and use the services
Through its Echo products and
3rd party Echo products
It support
The Amazon voice services so
Amazon one
Padme everywhere and
If other companies want to help them do that they're going to continue to support a tie
We'll see what happens
Inside again I want my unified data schema still okay
Let us move on
Amazon Prime day
Play I'm not a huge
Holiday it's not really a thing but we did notice
One remember last week when I was talking about that crazy new
Madam a powered sink from Delta
Hey
That's actually for sale it'll be for sale to the general public for the first time as a prime day launch
For $500
Chrome and then
$525 for
Arctic stainless which is basically like
It looks like stainless steel
And if you want to see it before buying it you can actually go to the Stacey on iot YouTube channel because
I actually reviewed it
So I'll link to that review in case you
You are interested in
Learning more about it or just seeing one of these in action and be like
Wow Stacy just is a little crazy
Which is
So that's probably our most notable
Gadget
Madame Amazon
Products are on sale so some good deals on Kindle Paperwhite
And I feel like I should keep asparagus
Lose them all the time the Echo Show is like
That's a pretty great deal
If you want that
And I also saw an ecobee3 with 3 sensors
Or 219
This is not the most recent ecobee4
But it's a really good thermostat and having three sensors
Is actually really stellar
I don't even know what I
Yeah that's actually the thermostat that we use here in the house
I have
Two sensors I take that back I have one remote sensor
So the unit itself is a sensor and then you can add these additional little sensors in other rooms
And I've literally I should really buy another sensor because what I do is
I put the sensor in the bedroom when we go to sleep so that way
The bedroom is comfortable
And then
Penny the day when I get out of bed unless another bed
I put the sensor in my home office I just carry it in a minute
Just a little stinky thing that runs on a coin cell battery in that way I'm comfortable now office
There you go
So we could get Kev
We could Splurge an annuity
Okay so those are some of the products that we saw the receipt until we saw the
Tp-link
Deco mesh networks if you're in the market for a mesh Network that is also
Launching apparently is a prime daypart
Not to be outdone
Buy Amazon
Google home
Is also
Doing some say
Sales
Yeti sales are actually through walmart.com
And I say that specifically because you
Cannot go and get these deals in the Walmart store which is kind of silly I live a mile from the Walmart store but I
Order things through walmart.com just to get the rebates
And that's what they have on me so
This is through the 17th of
July which is
Coincidentally the last day of prime day
Sandy Moore there
You can get a Google home mini on sale for $34 and then you get a $15 rebate so
It's $19 net
That which is a really good price
If you want the full size Google home which is normal 129
It's on sale for 99 and there's a
$30 rebate on
Top of that so it's $69 net and if you really got to have bass booming sound for music along with you
Google Assistant
You can get two of the big bad Google home Max units
We tried to leave Earth
$350 normally you can get
Two of them
498 after a 100
$50 rebate witches wow
That's too much down for me
Having one of those fills up
Yes yes
Okay
So pretty good little Google Assistant
It's very little but
I'm not sure what Google is trying to do here
I know we talk
Talked about a Google assistant voice there now 8 voices and you can
Why does he hate the man I don't know that it's so funny but I changed our Google voice to a man and he was like
Okay well I don't use nobody in my house uses the Google Assistant with me so I could free rein to go male or female doesn't matter but it use
Used to just choose
Invoice number 1 voice number to Voice number 3
The description
Now and I'm not sure I understand why
If you go into the update assistant app
You not use them by color
So
Yeah
Red purple green
I have mail
American
Female I don't know
Sean Connery
I really don't know
But if you change it on one it's a universal change that hasn't changed at all so all of your
Assistant voices will change to the new voice on your phone and other devices Etc
What should I do
Weirded-out cuz
Right
Yeah so curly I use orange for what it's worth you might want Amber to green or cyan that's up to you
It's not weird
Go Google
Keeping it interesting
Is Nest aware customers can now set in manage activity Zone
What's on IOS and Android
Devices
This is something you could do for a while with ring
And
Pink's mother
Camera makers
So I believe even on the wires I was able to
Yeah I know you needed the computer to do it right
I'm in as to where this just brings it down to the mobile apps
I have never play
I try not to but I
Once I got this news I updated my Nest app on my iPhone and
Yep you just have to
Give your camera in the app
Make sure your
App is in landscape mode so if you lock it to Portrait this will not work
Put in landscape and then just
Drag little handles around the area you want so
Hopefully I will no longer get notified anytime somebody walks past the house across the street on the sidewalk as I have
Limited activity Zone not adjust our front walkway
Although
Does this mean you won't catch your neighbor if she backs
You know I might want to change the nest aware Zone
Activism
Tiny tiny tiny news
You may care about
Sonos
Now supports AirPlay 2
Kevin you've got her you're a resident Sonos user
Yeah I'm not to Jazz by this but I'm sure other people will be basically yes UFC
Support for AirPlay to Solana update your Sonos app
I did that right before the show and then
When I open the app it said there's an update for the app so I can send me back to the app store which didn't have an update cuz I just got the update
Blue paint so hopefully you have better luck I was not able to test it because of that looping update issue
What this does is you'll be able to say Hey Siri play such-and-such on my Sonos water whatever song
Don't know Survivor room yet or Sonos setup enable play Apple music
That way so
Why I'm saying like it's not like it add Siri to the Sonos devices
It's just
Adding Siri support on your phone for your Sonos devices switches
Sure nice to have but I'll just stick with you and Madam a
And we're still waiting on updates
Is the homepod which
Oh my gosh
We bought you in December
Pretty darn early only when a new function comes out quite honestly
I'm it's just because it's limited to Apple music which we do subscribe to but I also listen to The Beatles Channel or
Are the coffee shop or coffee house rather on Sirius XM that's all supported by Madame a
So why have that card
Okay
Hey let's talk about something really cool
Space base
Iot
Not to be confused with
The space force
This is real and
Happening well sorta
Kevin you want to talk to us about space
Space coyote I did not know about this but apparently there's been a project going back to 2014 with the
Development of cul-de-sac
Which was low cost
Machine-to-machine communication services
Space-based infrastructure for iot
The deal is this is actually spinning to terrestrial iot using the satellites to communicate and then go
Actually have
2 billion low power
Wide area network
Devices connected to Satellites by 2022
I have written about satellites
A lot
It's a weird sub-genre that I
I am really excited about
The challenge with us and answer we don't have answers
When you're looking at this kind of satellite stuff you need to think about it
Things you need to think about simultaneous connections
Because satellites
This one actually
Handel's billions
I believe so it's a lie
You also need to think about
The cost of the radios in the terrestrial
Devices to
Talk to space and their battery
Consumption
As you can imagine shouting all the way out to space is
Battery intensive
That's one of the reasons why these satellite
They're huge and
Expensive
About two batteries and very expensive radios cuz
There's not a lot of use for them
Rights of operations
Xiaomi scale
But
This actually sounds really interesting so I'm actually going to try to find somebody who can talk to us a little bit more about this because
It would be really intriguing to have these would use the same frequency is sick box
I'm all about new networks for iot in
Having a space camp
Pegasus Global coverage and waited
We don't have today
And it gives Elon Musk another use for space
Yes
All right
Smart City news
So
LG CNS which is a
Iot
Division of algae
Stepmonster a new
Smart City platform
Called City Hall
And
It's going to focus on Korea
Or maybe not.
Which is where they're based
And it basically is a way to
Collective
From iot sensors Oliver
The place and bring it in and analyze it
Deliver services
So
It supports the
1 M to M Stan
As well as 98 other iot standard
Yeah there's a lot well that means they're doing all the standards
For you the downside is
That you're stuck
As long as you.
Got yourself sew-in ideas the platform will serve as the Unified
Takata control tower
4 smart cities
This feels very similar to some things I can do saint
Also in South
Korea they have a similar
Effort by 1
Carriers
Singapore has it ever
For like this day forth with
I believe it is Accenture
I'm a
Connected City platform that pulls out all the state and and
So I don't know
Just throwing it out there
There for you guys
Yeah that one M2M standard I probably should have heard of it before but I never did so I went and looked
And they're tons and tons of white papers and standards documents there and I looked at the security one would win
211 pages
And my brain exploded as I can even look at the other standards
Apparently it is
Aquatica worldwide global
M2M standard
If it is I'm not sure why I hadn't heard of it before
About my global
Maybe it is if you're in Europe
Europe I believe Sutton Asia
Which skin out
Is what we would call arrested for Elder row but
Everyone else would be like
Yeah that's global
Global can just sometimes meme
More than
And before we get it
Sucked into the
One M2M standard
Let us talk about something Kevin
Which might be useful to you guys especially if you heard me talking about the aware air quality
Sensor
Couple weeks back
This is how to make your own
Indoor air quality
Yeah I just found this right before the show so I can't type
Follow this project and everything you know about allegedly this works fine basically somebody ate a fruit has
Put their own air monitoring sensor
Together
Measure various particle sizes and temperature
Relative humidity there using a dust sensor module temperature humidity sensor a little
Whatscall hackable board hack a b l e as in Bluetooth low-energy so that's how they're getting the data moving around
Around using a Raspberry Pi as a Gateway with the python script python
And a Taproot dashboard display so they can
Look at the data again it's a project that I did not do pretty technical onto because everything is explained what does
Sex a good thing
Infinity chest want to follow the directions and copy the code
You could do this I would imagine it's knocking
After that much I didn't look at the pricing but this has to be Camping World modern dollars that we spend shock is more than 50 Cortana
This looks like
They say this is a
Beginner level
Project fi
Folks interested in Bluetooth
So
You know
I'm looking at this sound like
Code you can download
How you know if really good
I probably wouldn't do this I would spend $99 on a
Device but
If you're fun project for anybody
Nevada high school students
Bored this summer
Tell him to go yeah
I think looking at the instructions it's overwhelming because
All the base details of how the sensors work down to you know the different bite in a transaction in
The dust sensor for example is listed but that's good for people who want to know everything about it but if you don't you could just follow me
It's a little less overwhelming if you look at that way
Yeah and I would say
Indoor air quality sensor running around it's actually really big deal and
There's a lot of
It's kind of interesting to see like how certain
Products are
Use patterns in my home
I'm really affect the air
So we started using it
Downdraft for oven because I saw this
Every time I cooked
We just get like all the
Does particulate matter
Hey dude I should totally
Suck that way and so now we do
Using like an oil diffuser can really suddenly like spike your
Pollutants inside so
Maybe don't do that
So I don't know what I found a very educational
Yeah just a Bluetooth sensor by itself is $20 I mean again this is not going to be a huge investment in terms of cos
Okay
So let us go to this week's voice mail
This is from
Are Internet of Things podcast hotline which is brought to you by Schlage
And you
You
Schlage sense smart deadbolt and WiFi
If
You call us this month
At 5 1/2
742 4
And ask us a question
Not only will you be enter to win
That Smart Sense deadbolt but you might also get us to answer your question
Smarter homes
Start with
Schlage
So this week's voicemail is from
Josh
I like your podcast by the way thank you
My name is
I have a Chamberlain
Garage door opener that I'd like to make
Smart MyQ enabled and mostly interested in
Daniel Tiger
Open garage without closing it
Gainesville close it remotely
Sorry I looked at the MyQ add-on
Cannot big fan of all the limitations if you wanted if this then that
Description if you want to add Google Now.
Description
No matter what I'm assuming that we'll have a subscription to ever get it
I want to
To look at other options but I think
Conflicting information online and working on a TV
Coffee
God
Anything else
Put the Chamberlain
Do you know anything about
Whether third parties work with Chamberlain garage door openers do you know any of them
Good
Thank you very much bye
KJ
This is
There's a lot easier
Because it's a SmartPhone question
Haha yeah because there's no unified data schema for smartphone
Most of the other garage door
Don't actually want you to be able to open
Boise State security
Issue so this is the same thing that happened in the lock
Community a couple lock makers now that you do it if you also give them a
A passcode verbally
So that's
Aspect
Why
It doesn't work
I do have the Chamberlain MyQ I think it's a great option for people who just want to see if their doors open or shut
Take care of her
Remotely so I gave this to my in-laws
For someone who wants to get more into home automation
There's only a couple things I can offer for
One is if you have a wink
It does work with the wink hub
Not to remotely close it
Use like opening it as a trigger so I have a robot in my wink that
If we open the garage door after search
Time of
Night after
Basically.
My porch lights go
So
I did that without if I did that without having to
Subscription
So if all you want to do is use it like
What is a trigger
But
If you want to go further
You're probably going to go with something
Kevin
Yes I actually don't have a Chamberlain MyQ
Garage door opener
When I did put in with my garage door opener may work with
Myql explain in a second
So it goes by several names
When is the linear gd00z
The garage door opener the one that I bought I think
It's available at Lowe's for like $65 under the name gocontrol which is
What I have to again if the same thing as just rebranded
Essentially it's a Z-Wave
Controller
With two wires and those two wires get attached
2D
Terminals where the wires from a hardware button garage door
Open and close
Ghost so I attached the
Go control to that and it works perfectly fine with wink
There's also a tilt sensor in the kid that you put on the garage door and based on the tilt
Controller tells me if my garage doors open or closed
So I too have a robot that if after 10 or 15 minutes the garage doors open it lets me know
Via wings
And then I can remotely close it via wink
Now the MyQ models
According to the maker of the module the Z-Wave module they say they are not compatible
That seems to be true based on what I read in various forms and such
However we can add a link in the show notes if you don't mind soldering
Little Liars
To the hardware
Controller in your garage that you likely have
If you want to do that
You can make it work
You can't solder it directly or connected directly to the MyQ
Like I've done with
My garage door opener
That will not work
Additionally if you're not on wink and you're on SmartThings it looks like SmartThings support has been pulled
In the last 6 to 12 months
Buy Chamberlain so you
Really out of luck if you have a SmartThings
City of wink
You got an option but it's going to require some solder
And our final thing
Have not tried this
But we did find it
A device from
Comedy called nexx garage nexx
Garage
And they have a $99
Module that you stick to your door and a sensor
And
This actually they say it works with Madam a
So
And it also works with Google Assistant
And if
So
That might be the way to go I looked at the reviews
Some people it looks like it's a little bit more complicated install
But
I don't know this looks yeah there's no really good solution here if you don't want to jump into the MyQ space because of
These changes that Chamberlain has made an adding subscription fees for if this and that and so on
I don't know like I get why they do it and I know we talked about in the Shogun Steel just not a fan of that
And
Just before you buy if you're interested in the next garage thing
Before you buy just go to the website which is
Next garage.com
They have a list of the
Garage door openers it works with so
Chamberlain Bunches of them I don't know
At which one you have
So you will have
How to check that out
All right
Josh I hope that helps you and you enjoy your tinkering to get your garage doing
What it
Wants to do let us know
What you ended up
It how you feel
And now
Stay tuned for our guest this week
Who is Randy Schneider from Delta faucet
Talking about how they connected the faucet why
And
A bit about how they programmed it to understand words like
Decanter and glass + Tumblr
So stay tuned for that
And now a message for this week sponsor hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things
That's for a message from our sponsor sponsor is a pharaoh and I have Joe bread
CEO of the Pharaoh here to
What's really quickly
Tell our audience
What is a pharaoh
Fully integrated
Fully Interactive
Fully secure sensor to Cloud iot black
Our customers choose us
Because they can
Market buys much as 80%
Of course that cuts down on
Cost and complexity
Because it's so robust and they can reuse 90% of their work
Project project
First love how easy it is to get their devices connected
And how fast and responsive they operate
Awesome so Kenmore use as a pharaoh to get its appliances
What are the benefits
The Kenmore as seen from connecting fridges and dishwashers to the internet
Are two main category
That's the first one is in customer value in customers get value features
Amiability to control their devices from their smartphone
But also they can integrate Kenmore
More tightly
Traditional lives
Kenworth
Because their product managers
Appliances with cruelly competitor
Differentiation
And devices that are easier and less costly
Maintenance service and they use real data from these devices
The field to understand what features are popular
Kenmore is an incredibly strong and trusted brand and they had the foresight to start very early to lead what was at the
Time an emergent connected appliances
They had multiple projects
With existing solutions that they just weren't doing the job
It took him too long to get a Kinect
The place to Market
Experience too many outages
Generally the solution
Runner 27
Connected Appliance model together now
And a pharaoh is a true platform
So everything works with everything else
What are the hardest things about eyes
Is that you have to
Develop for embedded
Mobile and the cloud but a pharaoh has created a unified
Click the configure developer
The process that radically simple
And as a result
The first pharaoh powered Appliance
The Kenmore built
The previous one
The outages that used to experience stop cold
Because we built a lot of resilience into the system
Device if nobody connect
And too many company
Go through all the trouble
Justifying the customers aren't signing up
Because the onboarding process is too complicated
To fly with a pharaoh
It's a very simple
Process started to see
A lot more customer
Actually connect me
Appliances and then once those appliances were connected
Manage the entire fleet of them
Using an overall single-pane dashboard
Let's see the data that
It's coming back from their machines
Topline analytics and machine learning
Finally I want to touch on
Security a pharaoh not only secures all the
Potato Patch
Devices or appliances in this case in a cloud
But it also secures the manufacturing process
Where can we go
The best place
Is a pharaoh
Dot IO
/ gobig
That's a f e r o.
Slash g o b i g
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your home
Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Randy Schneider who is a product
Electrical engineer
Delta
Hi Randy how are you doing
ICC I'm good thanks for having me on the show
I'm super excited
To have you here
We are talking about my new favorite Gadget
Which is the
There's a lot of words here but it's basically a Delta faucet
That talks
To madame
Call Amazon
Assistant
Play so we don't set up
Let's get this started with I saw this
CES
I could talk about it ever since
Very excited
How did it come to pass that you guys
Hey
Text hubby and
How did madame
Yes that's a great question are
Joshua Fawcett
Turn around for almost 10 years
And adults are always looking for ways to innovate and add new technology to our devices
So where the invention really of Amazon Echo and
Other smart speakers even ableist add voice activation
To some of our devices
So we wanted to look for ways
We could add it on to existing product offering and bars are electronic
Arabic seller so adding voice activation made sense
People could do some of the tasks that they normally do with a touch faucet but this house when able
New features
Express base
I guess we should probably explain to people what the touch
Yes sir I said she'll faucets use
Cast of Simpsons
Technology so that you can touch
Deposit anywhere to turn it on and off you has a handle on it so you can
Install control temperature and then you can even touch the handle to turn it on or off or on the spout
Enable you to do tasks
Very good and as someone who's owned I have had a capacitive touch faucet
Ever since we moved into this house
And it took that it was a little bit of
You guys but I would never never go back
Now even though every now and then
Oh my God
Turn it off
Turn off the faucet at the faucet
Supposed to
It's actually a lot like
Smart light bulbs
So you guys actually started selling this
First through you
Website
Two people as part of a beta program
What kind of feedback
Yasso
This year we sold a small quantity to some user
And we
Lots of interesting feedback really
Learn about use cases in which
People use this
I got some
Good feedback about a week
A teacher features
Product stories as well about a person
Has a cat
Lights to turn a faucet off so they
And they would give it to me and then your voice
Turn off
I like it
Imaginext cat
Okay and I noticed you guys don't have it
And I was kind of curious
Why that way
Yes that's a great question and
It's actually an intentional decision that we made
With the testing center on voice activation
Pretty much all of the user interface is through voice actor
So there wasn't a lot left 4 and 1/2
Necessary
Customer first and customization options could get a user interface to customize
The name of a container
Core 2 processor remote control faucet
Also as updates are pushed out
Something that we learned at you
Get the updates right away to the web app you don't have to worry about are you running the latest version of the app on your phone
So that was a nice
Have you seen any pushback from your customers about this or do they even
Never use the web app
Yes will you does a question me specifically asked are you
The weather
You should just minimal because most season her case is to voice
But it does have some music
Features you can check to see how much water are you using and then like I mentioned you can customize some things like the name of the cancer
Inner Light coffee pot or dog bowl
And how much water goes into those containers
Let's go to the actual installation
So
There's a lot to think about
Once you got to deal with
I mess with everything in my house and
But it wasn't actually that hard
H2O faucet
Man of a module
And they have to have
Power underneath
And that's because Wi-Fi is a big Power hog
Capacitive touch
Did not have
What's a little bit of an adjustment
I'm glad that I had another
Do most
So yeah you're right Stacy with the Wi-Fi module on the faucet you have to have an AC adapter
Turn Outlet we have found the majority people have an outlet and they may not know that they have an outlet Austin times together garbage
Disposal under sink
Or if you have a dishwasher nearby
There be an outlet under the sink as well
And if you don't
Typically an inexpensive addition
Electrician come out or if you're DIY type person
You cannot live without
Okay
And let's talk about
The actual
Skill with
Because I find it a little bit
To be like the way this work
I will say
Madam
Acid altitude
Dispense
Types of water and
But I do find myself stumbling
Over
So I'm curious about
How you employ
Yes I can be a little bit of a mouthful.
Once you get used to it and the routine it
Becomes
A place for you
But it's something we're looking to improve right now it's
A limitation of the
Profiles that are available
Within
Ecosystem so they have profiles for light switches and door locks
But there's not really a profile for a faucet
And that's something we're working
Consumers Amazon
It's that next stage of development
Oh yes okay that my
Makes a lot of sense
It's kind of gets into this challenge that I see in which is there's no data schema I know Universal data schema
Smart Home
In devices in it
So everybody has to build their own
And if native skills basically in bed
I would think becomes a challenge for a company like you guys especially
Do you have plans to go beyond anatomy and moving to like Google or some other ecosystem
When we start our development
We
Took a step back and looked at
The landscape to figure out what's assistance out there and what we see
Systems are people using
This goes back sometime maybe year ago and
Looking around we saw the Amazon Echo was
Can we erase a little bit and was popular
Consumers
Would also buy a touch faucet
Partners Amazon and wanted to make bar
Voice activated faucet
Works
Within their skills
Available since then
Pulaski exchange a little bit
So
Google has
Come up
Apple has their homepod
And I think those are both platforms we are looking ticks
Blur to try
To add voice activation
To our faucet
Work with those platform
We're just not quite there yet
Let's talk about this issue that a faucet is something that people don't necessarily think a lot about
I like when you move into a new home
Has a faucet
There's a bus at great
There wasn't one
But people don't necessarily spend a lot of time
Upgrade cycle
But I imagine that you guys do
So how long do you feel like your boss it should last and then how long from when you start adding technology to
How does that change that occur
Yes people will typically think of a faucet has an appliance when they move into a new home it is
Just something that they use
People replace a faucet
Is something goes wrong and
Copulate or they want to do a remodel and update
Stylist
I saw sister design
And they have lifetime warranty on their
Are electronic faucet
Have a 5 year warranty
You can
Expectantly
On time
After the electronic Spark
Where's outer brakes
Maybe there's an upgrade cycle that needs
How do you envision that
Telesis Electronic Component that needs to be replaced we offer replacement parts
You can definitely reach out
Delta to an 800 number or an online
Contact and we can send you a new part if you need that
One of the
Biggest questions that I've got
People about the
Beyond
How do I know that the faucet isn't going to be turned on in Waist gallons of Honey gallons
Water so most people were sitting here telling
Oh I need a notification system
Dispense this many gallons of water
I don't actually know do you guys have some
So
Kohler touch faucet
Actually have a 4 minute timeout
And so that will override not only a touch activation but also a voice
So typical flow rates
People's homes are
About a gallon and a half per minute what means
Really worst case scenario if somehow your faucet
Catalan
Distance about
Water
Okay I couldn't even fill up my fish tank without you
You guys
Another issue that we've encountered
A couple times
I think it's probably was Madame SOI only there was some sensitivity around
So I started out calling
Something
Fish bass
Because I have a certain base I like to fill
It's forever that I used to film
I tried to do that
Was not having any
But she's like I couldn't understand this
So do you have any advice
Are people on
Hey baby don't call it
Fish bait
Just call it bass or something else
Yasso
One-word names
Definitely work
Better you can use more than one word
You know Amazon has their own
Machine learning that's going on in the background and interesting to do during development when
We have to train are still on what kinds of objects looks or will you provide a list of
Common object names
Star Developers
Actually went to The Crate & Barrel website and got a list of a lot of different
Akinator names
Anywhere from Facebook
Decanter
Kind of
Train it on types of object
An object name
Cold water
And so
The scale uses that information
Trey cross reference
I name you might have with
Common name for container that hold water
I like that
Are you guys planning to expand this to other areas
I think this is awesome but a lot of people are like
Hey I want to be like Madame a run me a bath
You know that's something we're looking to
For we right now have the voice activated kitchen faucet
And it would be an area that seems to make sense
To explore as we continue to grow the offering but right now is
Justice
And what is the price you
About launching this product and how people
So far
What was most surprising was how people use it in their everyday
The once people get used to
Naming an object
Like
They begin to use it
Tilly's Chillicothe / se have abs
Secret recipe that they make
For me it's making oatmeal for my son
In the morning
Assertive change my
Routine in the morning instead of reaching for a measuring cup out of the cupboard I think a voice command and feel confident it's going to depend
Right amount of water into the bowl with oatmeal and then
X-ray to go
So it's
That kind of learned behavior that
You see the shift
Four people were doing things one way and now the technology enables
How to do it anyway
Okay well I can't wait for the future when madam
Myrecipes
Dispenser automatic
Well I'm off doing
That's going to be like
My uncle
Randy
Thank you so much for
For coming on the show
Yes thank you Stacey thanks for having me
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week