Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's co-host is
Call Malik
Yes we have the awesome
Malachi
They're talking to us he is a partner at true Ventures he's
Investor
And most importantly
He has been my mentor
And
I'm really excited to have your room
I'm glad to hear it's been awhile since I saw you
Talk to you whenever enjoy your pain
Cast
Which is gone from strength
Two strap
Just like your business in
Makes me very proud
All right for those of you guys were like who's his own fellow and where is Kevin
Kevin will be back
Studying for his
Computer final
So this week we have an awesome show
Privacy
We got Google
CEO Sundar pichai
Who is testifying before Congress
We have a New York
Times investigation on
Location
Tracking
Surprising to anybody who listens to the show but we're going to talk about it
And
It was a little news about new Chips
Spore
Cellular modems and Z-Wave and
A funny story about the internet
All of this is brought to you by our sponsor
Digicert
Hear from them later and this week
Guest is
Bianca Wiley who is
A smart City expert and activist and we're going to be talking about
What we need to do to make smart cities work
First Citizens
Stay tuned but first a message from another one of our sponsors
Arrow
Are you looking for an iot platform find out why Kenmore in dealing picked up a pair of
Apparel customers have experienced as much as a 80% reduction in time to Market
99% pure sport calls and tedx higher activation rate plus those customers can be used
90% of their work from one project to the next
To learn more with it a pharaoh. IO that's a f e r o
Dot IO
Okay
Let's talk about this week's big stories
Want to start with
Sonora testifying before Congress or
New York Times investigation
Pistons location
Choice
You do that's why I gave it to you this one this is a democratic show
It's like democratic
Singapore
That's right I'll take him under the table that were sitting at if he picks the wrong
How about we talk about the New York Times story
Alright so for everyone who did not read this New York
And story what they did is they looked at location data coming off of your ass
So when you
Tell an app that can track your location
You think that it's doing it for various reasons like geofencing
But in reality that dated
Can get
Told to advertisers and others who are interested in
Finding out demographic
The New York Times
Took that and they basically
Look at some of those files
House and saw that they could identify people
And they had a lot of quotes
Our people were like I am shot
Just drop
Did this happen
So old what was it take
Well I think I'm glad that
Story first of all it you no yes
It's just like you said
Your listeners may not be surprised
Just like my
Theaters on my personal blog
Won't be surprised that this is happening because
I think
If I remember correctly I've been writing about this for 10 years
I think I started writing about data and privacy van
Facebook launch
Beacon
Essentially
If you think about it
This is just
An extension of that idea crossed
Every little lie
Unfortunately
What is that
New York Times
A writing about this
After
Megan has happened so
Long ago these things started happening
And so now to talk about it
Is actually taking
Some
Action head is much more difficult
Because it's a little too late in Insidious
Attractive
Virginia's widely spread
I mean they just looked at
Summit
You know
There's not a day goes by when Piano Bar
Reaching some unknown
@nina Android store for example as you know
But having absolute unique information
The other thing is this has been happening for a long time
I'm not focusing on the fact that it is
Chrome extensions which doula
For a long time
You remember a long time ago there was a coming call report
And it was a plug-in
Legacy
Guess what quotes. DW used
Plugins like that
Extensions like that
Nicole
Recedes from
Amazon are they can
Figure it out like
Just a metadata going on forever
So the question is
What can you do about
Looking back we can't do anything about it
Looking forward weekend
Show my view
You know it's just my opinion is
That we should be looking to
Very highly regulated
All the data around
All the applications in privacy around
Watch devices rychcik morning our homes
They should be higher
Standard
Sparkles make Alexa type device
Absolutely you the next time you feel I think
You know
Amazon cannot get a vivid
Saying that all we didn't know
Looking Glass time for so long
Even app
I think Dad should be
National
Data privacy
ICB no
Quality should be
Another amendment to the car
Rihanna
Actually beginning to
See the merging of the man and machine have to change
NBA
And the cost
Execution has to kind of
Adaptive at the time and it needs to be in my mind around this notional
What color person data is invalid
Can be used
Right now all our personal data has no sense of pain
It is basically up for grabs
And for Abused
Nina from Manas air down to all the nefarious
Latest very little light control
What are our rights as Citizens
Okay so that's going forward
I don't know if I should be a
I'm not a constitutional scholar but that feels like
Such a high hurdle to pass
Because you have to get
So many states
I do think there are things we can do retroactively
Help with
Privacy in apps
With our devices that were wearing
Filtering out or data places
So what would you say
I mean I look at things like apple and their privacy
Even things like the loophole disease
Apps are explained is the fact that
When you give permissions in an app
Holistic
Permissions they're not telling you everything you're doing
I think
Popeyes
50 Constitutional Amendment
It if you don't start the conversation now
20 years from now
I think it did it needs to be
Some
Conversation with diesel
Today
Saying that enough
I have all the answers but I think your feet are smart people.
In the market today
Because going forward it would not just be
Largest yacht
Devices you can be
Rinaldi's connect
Which is it
Verbena robot assistants all these things
Wales become part of society
They are part of
Society I think of them as inanimate object
Text but they are sending data they are translating us
So we need to kind of thinking about these things
It's not just privacy
A larger
Stop
Insurance
Companies decide
That you don't deserve insurance
Senior master go out because you forgot to wear your
That is like humans
It's all carpet rights and what they can do with the data
No one is actually talking about
Peace about this about 2 years ago
What's call
Service no terms of trust
Yes
Basically actually eggs
Explaining to people
Howard this week
Collector
Unfortunately
No one wants to do that because the lawyer have put so much
Yuno constraints around
I don't think it's just the lawyers I would argue that the easiest way to make a buck
Is to sell information to marketing
And I think that's a really big challenge
When they're trying to do something
Right
Maybe they've got investors
Who am I
It's very easy to give that
I mean that is definitely market for data looking Facebook and Google.
Facebook Tina Carter used to abuse
Privacy and data it continues to be used to knock
Civic Society
We can send a few more hours
Registering
Exactly the same thing
This is my whole point
Talk about the fact that
Dangers of bleach
Marriott 500 million
The cost to a human the time
Cosme
Protect my son
How is Maddie are going to
There was just a government Accounting Office
Report on the Experian app
And they were like this was so eminently affordable
And if you read that report it
Joe Ingram
These guys basically had and collected all of this
Some of their
Coliseum
They were aware
Good Security in place
End
They just really
Jackie and I think this is where I feel that if you have us
Stronger
Privacy Amendment
Answer the call
You know I like to see
The other US government impose like a 5 billion dollar
And I think the next one
Will be like overall we can't do that
Impose
Find
The Bible in dollars on. In the brain
Using diesel
So the environment pollution is
Solution
Data privacy leaves
Okay
From that standpoint needs to be regulated just like
Yarn company.
Automobile driving regulations
I'm just say
These are trying to do something about our government doesn't do anything about
Okay so you're
GDP
Do you want something
Stronger
Okay
Business
Needs to happen baby
Is people
Netherlands government
I think there's a lot of
Partizan will have to be taken care of
Gdpr is a good starting point for Europe
I think you would have to come up with
Changing battery
Okay and that actually ties into and we
We kind of talked about the things I wanted to talk about with Google CEO
Testifying for
They talked about algorithmic bias they talked about the data breaches
And what I didn't see was this kind of conversation
About what we need to do in privacy in till
Constitutional Amendment
Capricious
I think the basic tenets would be.
Companies like Google and Facebook should not be at the
For the conversation at all
Okay so you lost your seat at the table
They have
Whether it is
I would go as far as
Including Amazon in
Companies of flights
I would say that as
Access point
The Trust on these
To advance
Mega platform
Alarm concern is you
I assume the worst before
Anyway
When it comes to Google
How to say taxi
I would throw in
I would throw in companies that we don't even think about
Actually have a lot of information and I would also think about things like
Kirby feels like can I just put my data in an escrow somewhere like a last
And I can use that
Retail stores
Hotels in
Things like that but maybe the solution there is really just tired
Those guys to make it
Play there's nothing which teaches you a lesson.
Five Below
A lot of money and security
Ming tombs
Everybody spending money on making things
Sakura
I think this is all nonsense to say that
This cannot be done as most of these people
Don't spend the money
Don't know there's an idea that you can't ever be security
Always be
You have to upgrade your sister
You have to start somewhere actually care about security
And I think that's the key thing is like
The idea that you
Xperience Fitness
That's all they business is number one thing they need to do is four-pack data
Facebook forgot say
They have a deal
The whole business is
In English
Seriously
How are you
Talk about dereliction of Duty
Do you have to be
Okay
Sandra said we were going to talk about the app
You know what apple and
To make it mandatory
Perhaps just explained
Policies and data collection in a simple English
In plain English that is actually one of the things that we talked about
Digital standard reference
Currency around iot devices
Components there is
Aceite in English
I think that requires a lot of effort
Shimmer
The media needs to be
We have to get better at explaining
Things to people in
So
So we'll see
Next story I picked this because
Don't know
It's like the 18th time as somebody's video cameras been
This is a story from USA Today and someone
The camera had been
I went into this
Because it was Ness
NASDAQ actually has a really good
Google yes
Google
Alphabet
They have really good
Devices they do a lot of things
You have to change your password
Make sure that your device is not behaving weirdly and sending things to China
Is there supposed to
And so
I was surprised to see this
And what happened it looks like if somebody was using the same password
In multiple places in there
So 1
Happy stories are like panties so insecure
Really this isn't an iot device thing this is Jay
Or password practice
But
Nest actually pointed out that
Hey this is a
Good reason to
I have to factor out there
Haitian on your device is especially
Cameras
You iot companies that
So how this person had to factor
The camera wouldn't have been
And I would basically say hey device makers
Especially for
Matt amazing speakers things that really have a presence in
People's homes
Camera audio
Lock that down on my echo device
Yeah I mean do I disagree with more
I think
Idea of two-factor Authentication
NIU
Usable two-factor authentication in front of a human being
And they have no idea what you're
Play hockey at the show my mom house
Once she saw it she knew how it works
What time to gation and I think this is the biggest challenge we have is the technology
Has become so complex
And so pervasive
Ss80 but I mean the company than the brand
Taking the time to explain 2
Xi'an customers like what they can do
They should be doing
And everything is very different
Just be nice like by techies for tacky
Even if you explain it
It is okay
You're like I want to get to this I want to set this up I don't want to mess with it
I will say that I've seen some really in
Interesting incentives
Curso MailChimp office
Doctor
Fortnite did two-factor Authentication
Free dance
All right
Special dance whatever
So you know if Nest said hey
Two-factor will give you a month or maybe two months of the subscription
I think people would be like
I'll do it
Maybe
Plastic idea
I think
You know everybody should do it like at the more security we can provide
I like
Mostly Apple ecosystems
I use face ID
You don't like fingerprints and
Still time to get devices I kind of see how they made it all the work release
So I appreciate that
Knox
That's true and there are ways to say hey
What devices are in
Another op
To see that
Okay. But I think you should keep writing about it I think that's
Give me a writer on iot
It's your job to kind of sad
A little bit of a standard motor standard form
Because media is not doing this then the companies will pay no tax
There's no incentive to spend an extra dollar on
You see that is Ole Miss still the side of me
My story isn't it
Spend years I am not
Assign UNF
R&B I'm glad to not be signing anyone anything
Alright let's take a quick moment
To talk about
That mean ride home podcast
Switch Kevin and I have been following techniques
We have used it to keep up-to-date on our technique
Tracker standings
Sometimes we would just
Go in even on holidays to see what was going on in the world
Check me now has a podcast so you guys love podcast
I said the daily podcast comes out every weekday at 5
Really helpful it's like 15 to 20 minutes of
Whatever has happened in the world of today
Guys give it a listen see what you think
You can check out by looking for the
Acme
Ride home podcast
Your favorite
Okay what if you don't write
See this is my thing so I actually listen
Send to it when I
Big confession
Workouts
It's a van while I'm taking a shower
Showers are great
By the way
What can I getting today
Zoo hours today
Coffee break
Yeah that's how you make
Yes he is
It's okay I don't want
All right
So here's some basic news happening
World of iot
Silicon Labs has a new Z-Wave
Notable mostly because this is the only place you can get Z-Wave stuff right now
Silicon labs
Sigma and so basically next iteration better
Securities lower power
Pretty standard
Other news sites
Exciting
Is essential witch
I think Kevin was one of the few people who had an essential phone
We were mostly
Caring about it because
Plants for the home sounded really intriguing
They are
Still around
Essential
It's an email
Because I caught a business Indiana
Okay
Movie Ride Along
I don't know I wanted so badly for Andy Rubin to come in and like change the home environment
He's a smart fellow
I don't see it I don't see it happening
That is the nicest human being
Since I've known you this like that is why
She's been very kind right
Horrible
Sexual harassment issue
You know I talked about that
This happens all the time
I don't agree with that ass
Aspect
I can't divorce the technology from the person but in this case
Smart person
Let's talk about backpack
Coyote backpack
Because
I thought this was a great story and misfits and we talked a lot about Smart Home
Surveillance
And if we can grab
Places we can improve the world
And that's really Pollyanna
I do think
Be able to understand what's happening with
Culture
Temperatures around plants
Is a really big deal in Amarillo
So
Pretty cool
Data to educating farm and garden
At some point
Utopian do you get to view
Okay well we're not going to do ads
Is the University of Washington
His dying
Steve
That is true we have to start separating
Chrissy ads on Facebook
And Google
To be fair the ads on the podcast really transparent hand
I'm not taking any information for me
So this is at the University of
You're really adorable they're little
Backpacks are iot sensors they put on
Actual bees
Is that a yes
I have to double-check this cuz I'm like peanut robot bees right no there
Tiny little sensor
For real B
So yeah I'm like indecision to research thing
These things weigh a hundred to micrograms
So very very tiny and I guess
These are really strong
I'm not sure about
The radio
That was the biggest
Unsurprisingly the limit here is
Honeycomb
Bet that is it is a mess
I don't know what they're going to call it but
It's
Somebody I can make that joke might as well
There you go
So I thought this was cool in the show notes for anyone who wants to watch the video on it
Is adorable and
Again better information on the world around us is going to help us live in it better
I can just say IBS mean exactly 10 years since I met you
And you are
Way more Narnia now that you are
JustFab
Story Piccolo
Has me inside yeah
You still there
Nothing is change
Just a little bit more and dance
Alright this is also super nerdy but this is nerdy more in a
Economics way
Which is a company that does Cloud Server
Surprises they finally announced
And you guys
I'm not going to get into like what the heck serverless is but think about it as if you have a
Man that you need
Give like your sensors like I saw something now I'm going to go
Is super common in the
Serverless it allows you to spin up a server in the cloud that you
You can talk to it
Trigger that command without actually having that running all the
Which is
Prosthetics
So this is part of any
Expanded
Functional program
AWS Hadoop
4 years with Lambda
Google has it with iot function
Microsoft has something called
Azure
And now pivotal has it
Which is
About darn time because this is be platform for
Enterprises
Is when they're trying to build this
So I have no idea if you want to talk about service soon but if you have something
You know
Adventure
The whole cloud is like
Basically abstracting resources and
Making them available when you need them so
10 years
You know 15 years after
About 15 about 14 years after Amazon
Stocks that evolution
AWS cloud
Okay
I'll Trust You Man
So either way I think this is just the next evolution
You know he had to have made an investment in a company called
Solo
Richardson's Ice Computing space vs timeout
Maybe I'll profile
Talk to the phone.
She's pretty amazing
Alright amazing people
She's also
But I do believe that the edge Computing is
Talk about it
What timezone yashow Eureka Nevada
I think a lot of people
Understanding
Take me to be going forward and I think
As you see that become more and more prevalent and you'll see more and more
Ideas
New ideas emoji
Cloud 19
Sara Lance is going to be right.
No pun intended
Are you sure cuz you did bring us
Bee honeycomb
Earlier but this one was like not intended
Honeycomb mesh that have funny on come on
Okay and yes
I was actually this week at an edge Computing thing
I'll probably write about in the newsletter I will not
Deal with this now because
We have to go to our voicemail
Without Kevin here I'm intrigued to see
You don't really want to do this
Alright so
We take these questions from our listeners hotline
Play podcast hotline is sponsored by Schlage and you guys
Schlage lock
If you
623-7424
And ask
Question
We take a winner every month
Schlage smart deadbolt
And it's certified to work with Amazon
Ignored all of our conversations about privacy and
You do want Amazon
Upgrade your smartphone with the safety simplicity
InStyle
Voicemail is from Scott who is a SmartThings
User
Practice car
Stacy and Kevin this is Scott in Houston
I've been using the family cell phones as presence sensor
Control automation
Samsung smart
I really wanted a way to make my car reliable
Presents to buy salsa
It would be nice to be able to
Track the location of my car and initiate
At home
Based on one or more geofence
This location
What is your recommendation
4 pi to do this
So Scott
The answer is
Actually really simple
And depending on how much money you want to spend
So I did this for a long time I put a SmartThings
Presence detectors
Is it a zigbee or Z-Wave sensor that just basically says
The range of the Hub right now
I used it actually to tell me when my husband was coming home so I can run downstairs and watch the dishes tonight
So that is about $20
Cheap option or you can go with the fancy hundred-dollar Ops
Which is a
Acellular
Connection to detect your car wherever
It is
And this is $99
And you will have to pay US Cellular
Subscription fees so you're going to
Really really really want to track
If you're going to do that
And
If you happen to have a Subaru or a Tesla
There is actually a
A program called
It does have a monthly fee but it's
It's cheaper
And we get into your house you can actually control your
SmartThings stuff
From
Options for youth
I mean you could buy a iPhone for like 50 bucks
Find my phone
That doesn't coordinate with SmartThings
I'm just saying there are other options
Simple life hacks
So yes there
All right
We have reached the end I want to say a big thank you thank you old
And stay tuned for Bianca Wylie we're going to be talking about smart cities
Including
Alphabet sidewalk labs
Stafford in the city of Toronto
So expect more updated privacy
How to be a better Citizen and now
What do a word from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message
From our sponsor digicert and I have Mike Nelson
Security here to talk to you
Hi Mike how are you
Hey Stacy good how are you doing
Excellent all right
Let's get this started by
It's a little bit about
We are the world's leading provider of
Scalable pki
For identity encryption and we use these Solutions
Or web servers for Enterprise
Security as well as iot devices
Last week Utah
News about this survey that
And how the respondents were divided in the category
There's a top-tier
With organizations who demonstrated more of a Mastery peyote
Security and a bottom tier
Which were organizations that were released
Struggling to implement
Can you tell me more about the differences
The survey found between these two
Yeah we asked the respondent about the iot security incidents that their organization
Inside experience from the past
After years and the difference between the top and bottom
Unmistakable
The company struggling most with iot implementation or the bottom
We're much more likely to get hit with coyotes
Security answer
Every one of them
The bottom tier responding
Experience in iot related
Security incident over the past 2 years
Compared to just 32%
The Top Gear
The bottom tier were also
More than
6 *
More likely
I have experience in OT tonight
Service attack more than
6 times likely to
Experience
Access to the device they were also much more likely to experience data breaches
And 4 and 1/2
X
As likely to occur
Experience malware
Ransomware attacks
Comparisons rmb
Steak
Shows that
Those organizations that are working to master iot
Security are much better off
Wow that's
What were the top tier organizations
Doing that letter
We are still
Talk to your organization
What they were doing that was leaving them
Successful and their response is really I don't
People shock you
Are the basic blocking and tackling security
Practices things like
Encryption of data
Open transit in that rest
Authenticating their connect
Performing risk assessments on their devices and putting them play Skillet
Security Solutions so that there's
Security
Scale not just for what they have today but for what they'll have in
325 years
Excellent and where can our listeners go
To find out more about the survey
More information about the survey can be found at digicert. Com
Flash iot security
Everyone welcome back
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is Bianca Wylie
Who is a fellow
At the center for international governance Innovation and the co-founder of
Hack reset
Canada she is more importantly
An expert on Smart cities
Sol Bianca thanks for coming on the show today
Thanks for having me
I am super glad
That's so quickly let's tell us what you do in your
Day-to-day life
What does it mean to be all of those
I need a lotion
Friend it's writing and thinking about data technology procurement
And how those things work together for government policy and in the tech reset Canada world
Advocating
For public good in the Innovation economy which means looking at
What is happening in technology how its effect
Our lives and
Our economies
Insertive
Understanding how we can
Participate
And make sure it is happening
With as much public good involved as possible
We talked a lot about
Smart cities
On the show and really any time at the Internet of Things is
And what we don't usually talk
Talk about is this idea that
We are bringing
Private companies in
To gather data
To analyze data for cities
And in a lot of cases
There's a big tension between
What is civil government
So asking citizens what they want telling them
And bringing these private
Companies in to do
What hasn't historically been the role of government but is it kind of like an entirely new role
And that tension is something that
I don't think we have
Policies for I don't even think we talked about it
So I'd love to get your
Take on
What the challenge isn't
Tensions are between Smart City
Please and governments and citizens
Absolutely
Yeah and I think
What's really surfacing
In the Smart City discussions right now is that we don't have
Great mechanism
Democratically in
Formed technology policies
We have
Historically methods to engage people in urban
Planning and even that isn't great
It's not a very inclusive
The process is not accept
The bullet ends
To be at least in Toronto the domain of
White homeowners
Urban planning and public counsel
Station is already problematic now in terms of how we're going to bring technology
Into that the history of
Procurement of Technology definitely did not involve public
Consultation
Right like it's operational for a city
If he needs to buy.
Technology
That's something that's done
Tamina weather
The CIA
Depending on the city but it's
Not something that you
You go out to the public and say hey were thinking of
Procuring some technology
What's happening I think is as these two things
Come together as how he use that technology actually impact
How you're using urban planning tools
Another
We don't have a way to have
Discussions about this in this
Standard public consultation method
That we had
For years and years and years and so this is surfacing this real tension here in that there's an oversized info
I'm coming from the technology side right now because it's not just
Selling software that
Support
A standard City operation
Now it's beginning to
Potentially influence and drive them and the outputs of some of that maybe data or maybe they don't know
And these are things that we really need to understand like
Who's receiving those things how are they being used
And I think
One thing that is really important
Products to think about with vendors and
Technology is that I would argue it's being 20 years
Really bad
Technology procurement within government
Memphis to sweeping statement but a lot of vendors sell to government and it is
Extremely difficult
For those vendors
To stop selling
Anti-government so once you get in with government often
You become
Whether or not the solution
Good cities and other government
Relinquish a lot of that powering
Control
So I think you put all of us
Think together and you have a recipe here for trouble
And where we need to assess
How do we return the start of Technology governance piece
Do something that's more democratically inform
Yes and I became aware of your work on these topics
Lakes around the city of
Toronto
The Waterfront development with sidewalk labs
Google /
Alphabets
Siri and that seems kind of like a microcosm for a lot of these issues that
Talking about do you want to talk a little bit
About that
Kind of drive this home for
Certainly and I think what
Critical condition
Stand is that this
Project is not happening
With the city of Toronto directly
It's happening with
Public corporation that's in charge of Waterfront revitalization and so while the city of Toronto is an actor
This is not something that's happening
Between the residence
The city in the vendor
Another
Waterfront Toronto
Is the partner in his
Is the person who put out the proposal
It's a nuanced but it's important understand because it's
City of Toronto dealing
The way that this is really come to a head in Toronto is that from the time they are
P was
Put out and
You know where we are now
Which is more than a year later
Is that it
Incredibly clear
That people generally are unable
To weigh in on
How technology might be used in a neighborhood
Because we're lacking the public
Education layer that we need and I think this is emblematic of the last
20 years
Technology is that it has not
Attained
Is social license required
To go forward with
And so on the heels of this great enthusiasm for Innovation and economic development we stopped asking what
The impacts are of the resident
People who live with
Ecology and I argue in some cases and places
We are
Entrenching
Essentially a surveillance
Society
Because
We're not
Interrogating
Enough why are we putting
Technology
Who is it benefiting and
Do we really need it is this even primarily the core of some of the issues that were experiencing in cities and we know sit
Cities are really facing austerity you know they don't have a lot of money
So I think a lot of the stuff here
Really needs
Apod
Thoughtfulness
And thank you for going to go forward with technology we really need me to make sure
A good number of people understand why we're
Doing it and really are on board with it
Okay there's a lot to unpack
So let's start with maybe something
A little bit specific
Because I think that'll help
Talk about will talk about your ideal process and we'll do it with something that I think is
It has a lot of ram if I
Asian so smart lighting is one of the more popular options
Because cities have to replace
Street lights with LED
Clear cost
And they have all these cool projects
But it's also a place where you know you could add Wi-Fi but
Also add cameras
There's all kinds of
So talk to me about what an ideal process
Ferb
Adding smart
Tierpoint
The reason for the replacement
Is because there's a better technology available
And so that makes a lot of sense to do
Which is something that's understood 3/3
How people can get on board with both cost-savings environmental benefit make sense
Now these other things you get into this world of just because you can doesn't mean you should
Write like and I think this is this moment where we say
Is putting WiFi
Public space
The
Pressing urgent
Policy issue in cities
And I would say
No
Just as a starting point in a city in Toronto and now we all need to
I think about City to City what the differences are and you know how you would prioritize
Decision I think you have to look at some of these other bits and pieces and say okay hold on yes we could do all of those things
But we don't have
Have to do all of those
But if there's a real reason to do those things of course we should do that
So this is when you can enter into
Kind of conversations a public at
Education piece
Prior to doing the rest of that Edition
And to talk to people and understand like a is this something you would like to have in here are the benefits.
The potential cost
Is always a trade-off
Discussion and policy
So
How do you go about having those conversations in a broad enough way that's difficult right
Exactly and that's very difficult to do a consultation about
Public Wi-Fi seems like
Not the worst idea
But also I think it's also the time right now what I think everybody is scared
To do
For me is that is a responsible move right now
It's just stop putting more stuff
And until we have had a bit of a wholesale discussion
About many of those components
Because you can't go off doing one off one off one off right you can't be doing that
Street lights
Cameras again
That's why I think it's a really good time for
People that pause and say hey
Weaning calves
A digital and data infrastructure
Plan for City and.
Something that we can talk about all these
Components together
You know what the public
With stakeholders with industry
Then you take that plan and you use it to inform a whole set of
Procurement if we would have had that done
A lot of the issues
With the sidewalk Toronto project wouldn't be issues because we would have already
He had set out some policy guide
The problem with this particular project
Bring it back to it is that we don't have that
And so now we're freestyling
With a vendor
Which to me is not how you do good
Policy so I think this is really a point in time where you don't try to do little one off stuff
We need to think about that we have a digital and Aiden fish structure policy
Four cities
And that that is something that's done with good Democratic process
And then you're set up well to go ahead and do lots of
If you
Sedona wholesale policy it enables you to take advantage of those opportunities for you're going in and email adjusting into
The structure but then you make sure it's all aligned with your Paula
What is difficult for everybody to do right now
Is to take the time to
Stop
And do that polish
So with that in mind
Let's talk about how we create
Digital infrastructure
Because I will tell you I live in Austin and we just did a
Got it was like 5 or 10 years
Code next
We're basically trying to like
Identify and improve housing in the inner city of
We're having a portability
And holy cow we went through this process for
Many many years
Many people wait in any people had strong feelings
And in this last election they were like
You know what
What do a boat
To see if we should have
Scrap everything we just did with
Devil didn't pass
But
The point is
Doing anything at a policy layer is
Hard and it's
Uncertain
And it's expensive and
The people who
Complain the loudest are often
People who want things
How to say the same
So very curious like if we stop this
What should that
Digital infrastructure
The process look like and how do we think that's
Going to unfold
Klepto
A couple pints and I think one of them is that
We already have
City policies in
Implants right and so
It's not like those things don't exist
And I find that this is part of where the Smart City narrative is very
Its aggressive and overconfident in that it
Forgetting
That cities have
Plant City
Plant City top priority
Cities have long term
We're not starting from zero
What we're doing is we're looking at what is already prioritize and what is already the policy for the city
Writ large
And then you look at that and you say
How can technology
Support
Those priorities and those plants
And you're using technology in a small
Tool fence
To say hey these are the things we're trying to achieve
How can technology help get us there
The second thing to me is that
Right now is not the time to
Minimize or pretend as though
The impact
I'm all of this data collection
I kind of act like head in the sand or like well not a big deal we already have a lot of
Attack so just put a bit more and you know like this is the future this is how it goes
This is really a really important time to stop and say
We know we're
Getting to volumes of data collection where
Free diamonds are going to be more at risk
The freedom to participate in
Society with that what you're doing being known to others I think this is also a time of
Great unintended pun
Consequences for what it means for some of the players in technology
Have a lot of data as it is what is it looks to be creating
More power asymmetry between corporate actors and
The state does that little talk
These are fundamental element that have to do with power and
Control and
And these are things where we want to exert
Right around
Our freedom
And taking and maybe walk
Getting back some of the decision
Bands that were made without
Consent abroad
Social life
This is the time to do that but in order to do that
You have to make sure that you got a bigger set of players out
At the table because right now it's all you bring in
It policy people and academics
And vendors
You know you're going to keep having
Missing conversations
This is the point in history to bring in
Everybody like this has to become
Social issue where the public is at the table in large numbers
We need to make a comfortable space for people who don't have a tech background
Participated
Because things about democracy control Freedom privacy those aren't
Technical issues
Deeply
Social and ethical issues
So we need to figure out a way
To make that space
Comfortable
Way more people than
Currently is
And if we don't do that
We're treading ahead with stuff that does not have consent
And the public and I think what we seen in the last year is it high time to stop doing that
Because of all the unintended
So I think we're falling into this
Surveillance State not just because it's easier in the public may not quite realize it
I think we're also doing this just
In general especially I'm in the US year in Canada
Because of
X
Political leadership
That we currently
We have
So I worry that it's easier as a government
To say
Yes we need this
Stoking that fear and that feels
Not a technology issue
Tissue that feels kind of like a
Overall political
Climate issue and I'm not sure how we addressed that because right now we're in the state where we
We have all these
Crazy tools available to us
Bixby used for something like what
China's doing with their social
Scores
But I think like two points on. The first one is
People like to point
China there's a lot of stuff going on in North America that is profiling
On people using social media information
Whether it's a bank looking at it
Whether it's
Employer looking at it
We're doing a lot of this same
Stuff but we're not doing it
Necessarily is National policy
I just want to say that because I think a lot of times
People liked
2.2 China and I think that furthers
This misunderstanding that is a lot of bad stuff happening in North America to
In some ways worse because
It's not so highlighted as state policy it's more
Again like various actors
Freestyling
I think the other thing about the political climate we're in is that it's not just that we have the kind of actors who my
Pro surveillance
Because of for me a significant moment in time with post 911
Winspear
Became
A driver
And a rationale for many
Including technology but the flip of that which is
Older the 9/11
Is efficiency efficiency efficiency
Until when governments are make it you know they're being
Sold that they're going to save a whole bunch of money so
Magical they got some Hobbies
Technologies
Great times of efficiencies
Without
Interrogating
Kudos
Efficiencies impact
Politically is a whole nother round
Trouble because that's happening
To write and I think this is where you look into the work of like a Virginia Eubanks with the automated
Quality
Roblox glitches that you know where you look at using software to create a fish
To be sure but you know who it continually in trenches and accelerate
Discrimination of poor people
And
It's not like it's benign
It's done intentionally but it's
Sounds very defensible to say well we're just using technology for efficient
But we're not
Sing ourselves efficiencies mean when you look at how are those deficiencies applied
And so I think
Completely right about the first Realm of the political thing but I think there's this other longer
Political issue which is who in the government doesn't want to think they can
Can buy their way out of things like
Affordability or sustainability like for me but this is a persistent
Interrogation of
Quite a bit smart cities
Stop the saying it's technology what we need
Or his political leadership what we need
Right so we as people really need to be involved in this stuff because it cannot just be left up at that political level
Because there's way too many disincentives
Actually Act
That's right with this business such a alluring short-term
Jobs
And efficiencies Merida is that what is that look like in 10 years
Which is what we all have to live with
So with that in mind
I'm coming up to the end of the interview
Give me some concrete things I should do one as a citizen what should citizens be pushing for
Thinking about in Dewey
Start encountering some
And then
I guess as a city manager or a
Politician what are some concrete things
Each participant
Can do to improve this
To have these
I think I'm the first one in terms of what can a resident do I think we need to be really aware of
The demands on people's time and elitism of Technology like one thing we have to do is we have to realize
Not every residents going to be able to put Smart City policy at the top of what they're worried about
So I think we have to think about if you are engaging with
Politicians get in touch with you
Officials are more friends than just a
Smart City
I think you're a non-resident technologist and residents. Should be just getting in touch with their elected officials and saying hey
I'm getting alot about data and data collection and how my data is being used
You have to start
What concern you can start with like how much
What do we know about what's going on how much
Are we doing this in a way that is aligned with stuff that we've all participated on in Polish
Right now it's just signaling to politicians that people care about
And to my earlier point
A lot of people can't
Care about this because they got real
Lots of other things about survival to care about so if you are caring about this try to think about it in a way we think
What are the implications of data and Technology on poor people on racialized people on people that are being surveilled
For a long time already
And also
How do you engage with people who aren't showing up
How do you make sure that people in
Community housing aren't the ones you're getting more surveillance
Because they're getting something for free
Like we always have to think about that I think is a really important time to remember what are Civic responsibilities are
In terms of
What a city manager might be doing or an elected
Official I think this gets back to reminding everybody who's in
Charge the government
Charge and what is the government have
They have pre-existing policies
Until I think we have to turn this conversation around
How to say the vendors this is what we're trying to do in the city
How are you helping us do that
Not what is your shiny new thing and how do I find a house for
It's right it's the other way around it
Here's what we're trying to do if you want to be part of our
Procurement these are requirements that we're looking
Free to me and to have
Technology
Nothing really being formed by pre-existing democratically inform policy
That would be helpful as the next
And I think that's a good interim step before we necessarily have digital's and data infrastructure planning or not
Master planning whatever
Procurement
Is a really really
Garden place for everybody Ted Turner eyes right now
Because we don't have
How to change
That much like you can do a lot with an existing
Procurement
To have it operate
In a better way in Mark's pants
And you know and looking at are we looking at open source stuff rather than just proprietary are we looking at in traffic
Mobility can we share Solutions with other cities like cities need to start working together a bit better on this stuff because even in Canada
We got cities that are doing way better than Toronto and we're not really
Implementing their work
And so we should be thinking about that as well like as elected officials
City managers how do we accelerate the best practice
Implementation there is I think a room to be sharing more into me
Like learn from each other more in a pint
Awesome alright well now I feel like I have to go out in
Possibly a better citizen
What Bianca thank you so much
For coming on the show this
Sweet I really am
Thanks
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week