Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacy Higginbotham co-host
Kevin tofel
Awesome show for you today
Baby talking about facial recognition moving into
Terrifying
Territory
The echo spot
A cheap doorbell
And a lot of other news including
Sonos not working
With wink every have a conversation about iot and privacy with Janice I
From Mozilla to stay tuned to see what you should look for
When it comes to devices that may
Sherwood
Now
Let's go to a word from our sponsor home isn't just a place it's a feeling the feeling that
That you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT help keep you safe so you can feel
Protected wherever you are introducing the ADT Security starter kit everything you need to get started with ATT
Including a camera professionally installed for only $49 visit att.com
Splash podcast today to learn more requires 36 month monitoring contract installation and activation
Beauty Supply in Roman and qsp it easy pay required certain markets are excluded licenses available at ATT
E.com Florida a through F 0 0 0 1 1 2
Louisiana f
1:6
I know it's a week late
Because we knew the FCC last Thursday was going to vote against
For repealing
Neutrality
And see what everybody's hot takes
As someone who's covered this for almost a decade I kind of felt like
God is there really anything new to say about
The answer is
Not
But
For people who are wondering
Net neutrality
I think is important
To the internet
Mostly because we don't know yet
How iot is going to play out in one of the things that I've been thinking a lot about
Is
In talking to people that keep asking me about
Low power
Wide area network
Soaking cellular companies really screw around with net neutrality if you're working with like nb-iot
Eeyore
Cat 1M
Am I answer to this is
Maybe
And the reason I say this is today these things are low data rate
Works never
You can always
Always use more broadband no one has ever said wow
I have got enough
And so
The things constraining devices on the edge right now are mostly power relay
And it's
Completely possible that we will have Innovations in the next 10 years it will
Allow us to not have to charge things all the time or change the batteries which then suddenly with all of this power
You can actually leave this on a lot more often
And once things are on you wanted to be communicating
Which means it's going to consume
And so
This is how I think about
I look at it as a resource
And right now it's finite because
Power stuff
The Edge is fine
But if that turns incident or
Then we're going to want to come inside
Increase in bandwidth
And that's when we could see carrier start messing around
Data and collinear networks congested
And all of that fun stuff
Charging people for access to
Do certain
In this is where I think
Don't need net
Neutrality
I agree with everything you said it's not necessarily a problem right now but it is something we need to be aware of
For the future
Because
Most of these devices are
Creating small bits of
So it's not like we're pushing gigabytes of video for example of we need enough of a pipe for that
But we probably don't yet know everything that's
It's going to be connected
And we can't then imagine how much data I think is going to need
Right so I agree with you
John that is very pragmatic I think about it now
The other thing is
Looking at it from stay-at-home perspective
What happens when a PSP has its own security system that it sells to customers and you don't want to use
You want to use your own
Morty when he's around Hub instead of their Hub and what if they slow down the Gatorade
To your Hobbit
Kind of push you towards their product so that to me it's still another problem that this is going to cost
Exactly
I totally agree
You're going for immediate issues I'm going
Essentially
We have to just ask ourselves do you want Broadband to be a scarce resource
Which is how the telcos want to create it they wanted to be scarce because then they can charge more
For it and that they have the
The power
Totally rational
Business perspective
They have adopted a scarcity
Now if you could argue
And I would argue
The Broadband actually shouldn't be scared
It is like access to
This is terrible but gasoline and electricity back in the day
And because we had abundant access to those resources
What happened is we built entire new Innovations
We are reaping the consequences
But we got all the way from
Electricity
Air conditioning
Two refrigerators
The frozen dinners to being able to store vaccines I mean
Look at how
Abundant resource
Changes the
Just added that picture at this air-conditioning itself is what help
People
Migrate in the United States down south
Really
I'd like population areas and we created massive cities down there in
So it's a
Probably picture stamp
The impact is huge
So yes
Broadband should be an abundant resource I think we've moved past the time frame when it
Could be scarce
Resource and also look what happened with
Cellular carriers I mean remember how is a great example of be texting in Europe
Versus text
We because texting plans were charged per text we never developed much of a texting culture until they be
Unlimited plans
Where is in Europe
It was actually much cheaper to do that then
Roma data
So people texted me
Economic incentives are huge
I think broadband's probably in a place where we will develop around it because we are getting closer with things like 5G and
Buy 5G fixed Wireless over millimeter waves
But it's worth thinking about you guys and
It is frustrating My Hope Is that there's two last chances for the repeal to not happen and that is one
Many many states have filed lawsuits to kind of block it
And to their
Could be a congressional review of it as well as which could overturn the passage of it so
Best eyewear We Stand today
And Marsha Blackburn did
Introduce a bill
It is not a bill that is actually helping
Preserve net neutrality
It is
Gary Career Center
Keep an eye out for Chuck Schumer a Democrat has said that he will also
Try to file a bill
So maybe we will see actual Congressional legislation
Around
Net neutrality
Which is a direct result of a lack of broadband
Competition
Now
Let's talk about things that consume a lot of broadband and frankly
Are tariffs
What is happening as part of a Crackdown in
Dissident activity
Ivy
Uyghurs
In China
They have
Put digital surveillance systems
With cameras
Using facial recognition
Addition to track people and then they detain them and
People disappear
This ties directly into Chinese efforts around
Lissie when was it
Kevin we talked about this earlier it was in China where your
Considered a loyal truthful respectable person versus not
Yes and so this is an example of the power of the Internet of Things used I would argue for
What happens if you do now because of the compute power the sensors and
Computer vision
We have the capability to track a citizen
Everywhere they go
Endnote
Everything they do in
That
We have to establish rules are
Because
My God it's so
The word
Severe
That
In the article anyway
They say as soon as you stepped foot in
The city whatever City it is that's under surveillance
They know you're there
Like almost immediately that's how
Instantaneous this all is
In this implementation you have to engage with these systems to do everything from buying gas to pass
Not volunteer
End
It is not necessarily even
Visible
To the citizen
Yeah
It's a long but well worth
Reading article
Rather scary unfortunately for the IT industry
This is going to be another one of those horror stories of people say this is why we shouldn't have everything connected
That's unfortunate
But I can understand why people would say that
What a downer show what a downer show this is yesterday Facebook
Our government is creating a database of faces
As part of
New license
Shepherd so the FBI now has a database of it
Many people's faces because of new state licenses
Driver's licenses
Now
What is also interesting in parallel to any state
Efforts we have
Facebook
Which just announced this week
That they can
Recognize you in pictures and
They will send you an e-mail when you appear even if you are
Which many people will be like
That's nice because sometimes I just don't
Me to find the victim of stalking even if I'm not tagged I want my picture off Facebook
What is scary as all get-out is Facebook nose
Who many people
Pilar
That is also
Quite scary
Facebook is not using this necessarily to Tamp down religious beliefs but
Start in town
State activism but you know it could be an agent
On behalf of a government if it wants to work
Country okay
The scary part is and I have long been a Facebook user so you know I'm I'm guilty as well
We've been providing
Facebook the smarts the data itself
I previously tagging people
Right it's to the point now where it's recognizing
Yeah my wife isn't it
Picture and you know it's just kind of our own fault
It is
But I would say
Facebook is providing one thing
Community whatever
When it's actually monetizing
Building a business
I'm completely
And that's actually a really interesting element
Wishing this
They're usually do lames in any product so a product
Invisible Hardware
Consumer perspective is trying to serve you by offering
Who sings but you are
Also
Helping
The development of that product
And you may not understand exact
And that doesn't have to be bad
It doesn't have to be
Evil and it's not clear
There's a lot of distress right now for Facebook
They're not picking up
You know dissidence off the street and putting them in prison or killing them so
Cello bar
But they're building the tools and supporting the tools that they could be used to do that by somebody else
That's computer vision
It's something we really need to start talking about
About and we need to talk about it specifically
Around these issues
Also data correlation
Once we have all this crazy data
Computers once I can see more things
They can
Amass a lot more data
Wish that can be searched and correlated very quickly
And that is a powerful thing I think we have
Another example of that is Google Street View
Apparently now Google Street View can determine how areas vote based on the cars that are
Yeah it's
I read through this article is very interesting and it's not facial recognition but still recognition of something about people
Their choice of vehicle
You know and then
Basically using the data
From the street view car as I drive around seeing which vehicles cars trucks
Etc are in a neighborhood
They can pretty much estimate if they lean left or right in the u.s. democrat-republican Etc
And it's uncannily accurate
Yes and this isn't actually all that new like there's been surveys in the past likes
Democrats drive Subaru
In general
So Republicans generally drive pickup trucks and we can actually
That is not a crazy
Correlation to make
Maybe not 100% accurate at the individual level but at the broad level
It is in
So this is just basically
Pulling this data
At a massive level
Correlating it and then
Sending out
Useful insight
Siri
All right let's do something a little less distant
Where did he born
And
Iota Iota which you've written about blockchain many many times for the past several years so you are probably soon
I know you're with Iota I was not until very recently because I start a little altar
Coin investment strategy just for fun
Tell me to disclose that actually own
.025 5 Iota tokens right now
Which is worth next to nothing but
By investing in it I learned that
It's rather interesting use of blockchain because it's device-to-device transactions worth
With
Currency all currency that uses blockchain is typically
People transaction
Buying something for somebody your exchanging currency at cetera
But this is device-to-device so this is like the blockchain for IRT apparently it's
Stun over 10 billion dollars worth of
Transactions already so I did not know about it but it
Been around for a couple years now and recently they just earlier this week rather Robert Bosch venture capital
Invested I don't know how much but invested enough to make news
In Iota token so
An example of how Iota would work would be power a car with a ton of sleep
Pay for Town parking
So take our two parking meter transaction for example that would use the Iota blockchain and
No human interaction needed so it's something that I'm looking into a little further but against a so you probably heard this
Before I have
No
What's interesting is I've written about
There are two things that are really great about
Just probably the black sheep
Wishes that it's distributed
Countability so
The distributed nature of it is scalable which is awesome for iot
Trillian
Billions of sensors
And the accountability is good because I passed her security and Trust which is important
Things like Mike
So is far back is like 2014 I've been
Talking to people
Like IBM
7 Samsung
About
How to develop
Blockchain based Technologies for
Device to device
Microtrans
Actions
And IBM had a platform for this
I think it went anywhere but it is part of
That demo that you saw her
The parking
It's also things like your washing machine
Initially
At CES in nice
2015 Samsung and IBM shut off a washing machine that can order its own detergent
Based on their
Technology they're watching
Which was not
There's also a network
Company called filament
They're using it to share data
Cross very small
Proprietary Wireless net
It works and they do it
As a way to
Distribute
Signals when there's no cellular
There's also a security company for the industrial
She called sage that I wrote about this week they're using the blockchain to track
Data requests across the system
And then there's an algorithm called
Shamir's secret sharing
And that is another distributed way to scatter data and then reconstructed
Set from different now
Notes
What's important to note
For any of these to be useful these blockchain-based kind of Micro Center
Security whatever
You need to combine the blockchain
And there's various forms of that iota
Bitcoin ethereum
Whatever
With other technology
You just can't just be like black magic
File transfer
Yeah you need
No it's eating people verified
Directions and keeping track of things and misses what the miners are doing when they're mining for Bitcoin for example their cream
Reading more blocks
On the chain
Or verifying am I
I should say it's more technically accurate
And you have to pay them
Because
They're using their electricity Computing time so
It's a whole infrastructure needs to be built
Nachos you can decide use blockchain
Well so some of them are
And I guess
Iota works that way
Some of them are actually
Like hyperledger is actually internal to a
So these standards are the company can develop in
Control
The issuance of Tokyo
Because they don't want actually
External
Different ways of doing
And I was actually just tell you about the tech
This happened
That's basically
Kids keeping a record of something happening
So
There's a lot here in this was kind of maybe not the world's best over
I have long believed that watching has an important role to play
And IRT
And I have kept an eye on iota
And now that Kevin's invested High
Ask him all my questions
I think it's worth $0.07.
All right he's not quitting his day job
Or his
Wednesday morning Joe
Okay let's move on to some news
Let's do this really quickly so
People really like the echo spot
Echo spot is the hundred and $29 camera I don't know what it is right now cuz Amazon probably has a smoking hot deal ahead of the house
This is a tiny little
Screen that shows you what the weather in a clock face
Curly videos but not yet YouTube videos
Nope
Don't take that show Amazon Prime video
Yes
In IMG
Surprised because I would never want
A camera
Because this thing has
By my bed
Well I'm in the bed
Inside is a good place for a device like this yes so the camera is an issue there I mean you could have this
Maybe in your kitchen or somewhere else it would be okay
There we go
This is a round 2.5 inch display and
Amazon is touting it as hell you can watch Amazon video on it or you can view your webcam and so on so forth
I just don't see the point of that on a 2.5 inch display but
Chances are you have another better display for that you had your phone in your hand which has a
456 inch display
Maybe you bought the show
Video of tablets
Around the house
Tell me this is more of a solution
Persuasion
Yes I do
Let's give that to him
And
Blink
The maker of a
Smart home camera that we talked about
They have created a $99 video
Doorbell and
This is part of this influx of Cheaper Gadget so we talked about the wise camera that was
Matthew 13
Basically the doorbell will cost you $99 or $129 if
If you need to Blink sync module so I don't have a lot to say about this people seem like
It's a
Good
Deal
Everybody has a doorbell
Typically they've been priced at 2:50 or $200
So this actually really is going to put a lot of pressure
Ring skybell
August
Nest
Who's got a Toradol coming out
But worth looking at
People apparently it's got a live video stream motion sensor two-way audio and night vision
And it can't run
On batteries or
Two Double AA lithium batteries or you can hardwire
So it's pretty awesome
Actually yeah I know it's got all the features that most of the other
Smart doorbell
Cameras have and it is at least half the
Price so you're right it's going to put pressure on the other folks maybe they'll say we've got a better service or
Peanut because lotteries have monitoring plans and so on so forth capturing the data saved in the cloud making clips and all that will have to see but
That's your right is going to put pressure on it reveals
Is a strong
All right
So that is available
Pre-order
I want that chicken
Electricity consumption of iot devices I'm putting this in the panic
Except
There is a
Computing cost for
Listen we should pay attention
So the communications industry could use 20% of all the world's electricity by 2025 according to
To a nuke
Paper by us researchers
It is not yet published but this is from the guardian
They think that
Information and communication technology ICT to create up to 3.5% of global emissions by 22
20 surpassing Aviation and shipping
Is huge
That is
The
Global Computing demand from Smart TV surveillance cameras video streaming
Blah blah blah is increasing by 20%
A year
And just to add to this one because we talked about blockchain earlier in the show
I haven't seen a different article that said blockchain mining right now is
Do you think
More electricity than five
Nations in their small
They're not dirty
Totally understand that but still it's a scary Prospect me start thinking about how much juice is being used in the emission
Airport
Okay we also have news for wink
And sodas lovers
Which is
Me
Kevin yes now works with
WIC
And Kevin
Tell us lyrics
Yeah it works really well I mean it just like any other connected device in your wake up it will appear once you're at it
And then you can create
Triggers and robots and things like I said a robot up that when I come to my office at night and
Voice control my lights turn the lights on that the Sonos automatically plays
What turns into one of my favorite XM radio channels and just starts playing
So I don't know we had a question on the voicemail couple months back about somebody wanting to do something similar
When she walk into her house she want her son us to start playing well you could do that now if you had the right locking
Dwayne can do it
She had the August lock
Which means that she actually could
Now integrated with wink
And have herself
So there you go yay technology will provide
Let me ask you because most of my Sonos Integrations only play like a favorite station
I assume
You have to set
Does it automatically play
Just whatever the default favorite is or can you set a favor
You can set a favorite for that robot
Let's move on
Question Public Service answering mood answer
A question from The Internet of Things
Hotspot
The iot podcast listener is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic lock
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & Security system so you can get the most out of your lock
Whether you're an Apple homekit user or love Madam a to see what's possible
Dot-com
Hi Stacy
Kevin
Angeles
Love your show
The only podcast I listen
Religiously
Here's my question
And please forgive me a
I've got a tiny apartment in LA with
100 square foot
That's far it's outfitted with Hue lighting
And WeMo smart plugs and switches
Which I control via no less than
Three Google home devices
Occasionally enamel
Yes there are really
This mini digital assistant
In my small space
Everything is integrated and occasionally alternate
To ask for stringify to fill in the gaps
My question is this
What would the advantage
Set up a Smart Hub
Be in my setup
If any
Is it just a matter of
Speed
That is rude
Reducing latency
She or are there other benefits
Smart home hub I should get
At this juncture I don't see the necessity of one
Hoping you can shut
For me
Thanks in advance
Happiest
Holidays today
Okay Chris that is an excellent
Question
It's at
It is so good that I'm going to tell you you don't actually need
Itsmarta
If you are content
What's your setup do not bring in
More devices more complexity and above all more hubs
The only reason I would do it if I were you is if I wanted to do something with sensors because hubs will open the wide world
Have sensors so if you want to automate your lights
And have them turn on would like a closet door
Opens for if you want a temperature
Change to set something up
Ascent
You would need a hug
Yeah I just I literally just had this conversation with a neighbor the other day
And
He was wondering why some things he could control through his Echo
Where is other things he couldn't
And I said we got to have a hug for certain things so
Going to your point Stacy if you're going to add other things such as sensors or maybe a smart door lock
What you want to simplify and there's nothing wrong with
Iftin
Stringify
If you want to just do it in one app
You get an app with your hug when you can
Create your automations that way
So
I agree it's probably not necessary unless you're going to add more things
Okay now if you want to play and go a little nuts
Go right ahead
It might be a question is Chris
Why do you have so many smartass
In your eyes
That's more smart assistance per square foot than I've ever heard I'm impressed
All right that rounds out the news portion of Today Show
Please stay tuned
Conversation on iot device privacy
And a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is FSG if you make iot devices and you want to sell a whole lot more you should really come
Consider partnering with FSG
FSG offers in energy management
Platform
FSG past clients include Starbucks
Ford Rackspace Circle K
If you want FSG to sell your stuff to their clients
Sign up for the works with clarity
The program will be included in fsg's portfolio products and you also be featured in co-marketing initiatives
To learn more
Visit Stacey on iot
Slash
Clarity
That Stacey on iot calm clarity
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham and I am here with Janice Psy
Who is a research scientist
With Mozilla
Hi Janice how are you doing
Thanks for having me on
I am super excited so you
Are a human
Computer
Interaction
Research scientist specifically
Specifically
What's called usable privacy and this means
Privacy and how people interact with things
Got it this is going to be a fun conversation because
In general I feel like The Internet of Things is a privacy nightmare
It's not even waiting
And it is
Right now
So in terms of privacy
It's one of these things that she
Really difficult right cuz like when you are trying to go out
Buy some connected
Device
It's probably because you have some kind of use case
Like you want to make it
Easier to turn your lights on
Control your thermostat
From upstairs but having to come back downstairs
So usually there's a reason why
People want to buy a bunch of connected things
And
Trying to figure out
The Privacy that goes along with it is pretty much a
Because right now we have
What kind of a legal regime
For privacy in the United States
Space
And so the way this works is
If a company posts a privacy policy
At three matches all they really have
Legal perspective
Government normal person perspective
We know that no one reads privacy
Trying to even decipher or understand anything about leaving
Did the Bison
What is connected to the internet
You know where it's going and who's using it
So the way I view
Privacy is really looking at
How can you explain things
Normal people
Can understand and then make decisions
Where's relevant in context
And actually have some real control over your data and
Space
Okay so let's
Dive Right In
With the big challenge
Because
I think you did a good job explaining like
Oh my gosh if I'm buying a Kinect
The thermostat and I'm going to see that notice and consent thing on the thermostat which is a terrible place to read 40
Is right
It's also I think
You hit on something a little bit more subtle witches
If you're buying these things in their use case to
Dependent
The Privacy impact of it may depend on
That particular use case like I may not mind
The company that makes
My light switch knowing that I got up and
Turn off the lights at 8 at night
But then there's another layer to that which is if I connect that light switch to light
My garage door
Then that company
I might also know when I've actually left
My house
There is this concept
I guess it's a changing use case as you connect more devices this sort of
Privacy in the
Data that's available to pee
People about you be
Becomes a lot
I'm curious what you're thinking about
How to deal with
Yes
You're absolutely right
He's just having one single data point like light switch on
In the whole ocean of data that's available but that's not
Usually the goal
The goal of most companies as well as
Everything else that you are interacting with in terms of the iot platform
The gold companies
Typically class
Information
Overtime
Bacon do fancy machine learning things
Nowadays
Remove docker from Jessie
Having
Now everything is artificial intelligence
And so
But they do that's collected
You may think it's pretty innocuous
Or low risk
Combining
Aldi's differ
Sources of data
That begins to help other people
Accompanies developer really
Detail picture of the going-ons inside of your house
Right now consumers are worried about the
Their privacy
Why do companies
Wanted
Information
There's a couple goals
What are the goals obviously
Is make money
By either selling more products
Or selling services
To go along with your product
For example if you have an S
Ask him if you want to save your videos
And you have to subscribe
That you have data storage
Further down like
Bigger picture
Issue is
Making money through being able to profile you and or sell you
And I think it's a lot of data
Now is
It's kind of based on a
Hope in a
Figure out some cool things to do with it later
And that's kind of like the worst way to have dinner
You don't have a specific goal
Is just by collecting a lot of it and
Get around
That's where you open
Companies open themselves up to a lot of risk
Because everyone has data breaches all the time
As a counter argument to that a lot of the current advances in machine learning
Been made
One because hey we got more powerful in a parallel processing in gpus but two
Because we have a lot of this data of
Available
And so in some sense and I'm curious what happened
Pens as we
Double down on AI and machine
As we definitely are
Does that kind of outweigh the need for
Privacy
I feel like there's a lot of things that you can do to be a responsible
Company
In terms of the day
And then you could have mentioned some of it now
You mentioned the word
Right now I think it's a matter of
How did is
Win tickets to words
And
What is attached along
Cheetah
And a lot of companies are working really hard at figuring out ways the kind of still take advantage of collecting lots of date
Doing
Either transforming it slightly
With mathematical methods
White differential privacy
The kind of guarantee you a little bit more
And also still being used
So if I am a company striving to
Napa evolve
For example
How should I
I think you should first of all have a good understanding of
What you want to do with the data
And the ones you collected figure out what needs to be
Stewart
In terms of
From an identifiable person
My Windows machine
Is Sunday at 2
And that is usually attached with
Several really unique identifiers like a machine ID your device ID
Along with save my IP address
And so
When the things that companies can do is decide how much of a story
Jenna specifically
Or just someone in the Pacific Northwest
Is using a computer
And be able to start
Lopping off the data that isn't needed
And you mentioned things like differential privacy
What are ways that companies
Treatdata respectfully and still have it retain it
I think that's one thing that's really important
Is for companies to really kind of
Treat their own responsible did he use
Policies inside the company
This is kind of separate from
Differential privacy
It's being able to have
Methods and systems in place
Attract
Does it have audit mechanisms
So bad
People can't access the other not supposed to have access to
Or if they are and it's kind of
How many companies
Play they're doing it more and more now
Thank you
From years and years ago there was news about people searching for likes
Celebrity taking Ubers
Or someone like Britney Spears going to the hospital and people within the hospital system
Funny people
People who are it system administrators are more of these issues
And they have
Probably done more in terms of access controls
Here comes a challenge cuz I talk to people about connected devices all the time
In private
How do you communicate
Good data practices
What matters
And all of that
To Consumers and maybe we should even start that with like my God which is
Primary things a consumer should
Care about with Rick
Let me think about this
And I think that we
We need to have a whole bunch of different
Ways to Die
If I were to go to Home Depot right now and I want to buy a Kinect
Probably half a dozen
People are companies are manufacturers offering things now
But there's nothing that packages
Unpackaging
For any of these products
That actually says
Anything about the date
Right and so there needs to be something that's
Imagine all the different points
Upsell
Physical packaging or
When you go to Amazon
There's some kind of disclosure around
Hey you either need an app
Or we're going to share data with
This many companies are these types of come
Some kind of nutrition label
Provide some
Let's talk about you
Because you guys did for the holidays
Of things
Well may or may not
Tweaker date not leak your data cuz it's not
Kits and intend
Sharing
Intentional and unintentional
So talk to me about this
Sure so we created this guy again
The kind of their permissions
That would be
Whether they act
Or your microphone or track your GPS location
And it also kind of
Did a little investigating whether you had what kind of
Information about
Whether it requires you to create an account
Or if you have any privacy control
Or she could delete your data later
And when the kind of the funny thing
Things about
We're not funny but tricky things about connected things
Is that
Everything isn't just
The most obvious
When I buy a rubber duck
That is called
What is a connected rubber ducky
Please music in his LED
It's not just
Cuz you're also usually have to interact with
To get your thing to work
I had to download an app
I kind of said everything
So you have to think about
Device
Which I hadn't really thought about
And each of these things
Bye-bye Dropcam
The camera on the outside of my house
It's obvious that hey it's probably record video cuz I just bought it
But when you're buying like a
No electric toothbrush and you have to use the app
It might be weird or kind of like
Not really make sense why
Collecting your GPS
Location information
GPS information to use the app
Pastor askew
And I don't understand why he needs
In some of these cases you can just not
Say yo
But in some cases you can't and that actually brings us up to a really good
Kid point which is
A lot of these things you have to purchase it
To find out that it's going to
Have objections all data
And that feels terrible because sometimes
Can you return it
What is that sort of
Consumer rights issues
Army figure
You're the only person who's talking about this
Because
You just don't know
Until you get home and you open it and send oculi
Why is my thermometer
Reply
Be right back by that time it's too late
Unpackaged giving it away is a holiday or birthday present
5 year old child
I want to take your present away from you
That's hardcore
Because in 10 years time he don't want those naked pictures of you in the bathtub going anywhere I promise
I need one good thing though that people do do now
I think a lot of people do they look things up online
Or they look through lots of different reviews like
You know the ratings for everything
Maybe this is a called that two people who really like doing product review
But when you are reviewing something
Somewhere else that you can
Something about her
I returned this because it was really weird that I was taking my picture all the time
Words of advice for
For people who are like
Man
I really think a lot of this like I'd love to turn off my lights from
Using my voice for my cat
Do you think they should buy into this
Switch they look
Or if they
When you are making a purchase
Just spend some time going to
Through all the settings and controls
And the permission
And just turn off the things that you don't think
For example on the rubber ducky if you don't want to
Have your location
Turn off the location permission
Ender settings
And sometimes our settings are in the actual
Like system settings
And sometimes those settings are in
So just check out both areas
But if we can just do it once
When you're for sitting up your device or a port or what not
There's other simple things that you can do like a lot of people put tape over their webcam
Laptop
So if there's something physical that you can do to like or unplug your Echo
If you want to go ahead
Try that
But check out settings
And
I really hope
And thought that
The state of privacy would be a little bit better than where it was
Currently
In terms of
The iot connected things
Most things did not have any privacy
Controls
Mustangs
We're very opaque
In terms of what data was being sent when
For what purpose in hell
And so I think that
Still have to be a lot of
Work.
Before things are really
I think
There's a lot of really interesting things
Special 2018
Is the gdpr
Are these new privacy regulations that come online
As a result of his privacy regulation
Regulators are going to start just going after
In terms of their data collection their transparency
Where do you sing it now
With regulators and the really big tech companies
And I think that it will just get more and more interesting
Okay so I'm going to go down a list of popular iot device
And you can tell me
Would you put this in your house or no
How's that for
Your own personal like utility like
Is it going to be valuable to you
It is there's a
You just tell me so here we go
Connected light bulbs
And I feel perfectly capable of
Turn on the switch
Also
Want to make sure I get light bulbs that last long
So anything that requires firmware updates
I probably try to avoid
Especially because typically really high in the ceiling
Okay
Connect two thermostats
Programmable
Pretty happy with just setting the different times on it
Daniel Lee
What to see how cold my house is
Any particular time when I'm not home
Smart door locks
No
Smart
But I would get one of the ones where you can type in a code
Okay
Not have it connected to this
Okay what about a connected doorbell
I probably wouldn't get that
How about outdoor cameras
Yes I would get outdoor cam
Indoor cameras
No I would not get into
A smart speaker like an Amazon Echo
Google home
I would but I have no eyes
I unplug it or my husband unplugged it when we're not actively used
What about Seth
That he's concerned about it like
It comes on randomly
About Alexa
Talking to you
We don't say her name on
On the show
For that reason
Yeah connected toys
Like your boyfriend Edwin
I probably wouldn't get
Connected toy that wasn't
The purpose
If you didn't have like a real Beast
Nintendo switch
I want that connect
Into the internet so I can save my progress
Hi scores
But for other things like rubber duckies or
Or other things
Probably not get the
Because things get destroyed
Fair
That's all right
Janice thanks so much for talking to us
It was a pleasure to talk to you that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember
If you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week