Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have a
Fun show for you we're going to be talking about ge's digital unit
We're talking about a bankruptcy and the world of the Smart Home
Apple
Who's got some homepod news that we should talk about
Got a new crazy device for dedicated hardcore smart-home people some news on cellular modem is turning a
The gateways for the iot
Bonobos got a new smart device
At the SEC
Control4 has introduced in intercom function and we have a new device
Sportrx
Crazy wacky iot product of the week
It's
Something you're going to want to stay tuned for
Plus
Kevin bought the Lenovo
Google smart.
Display his first impressions
My first impression I want one
This week's podcast is brought to you by our sponsor
Netgear so you're going to hear from them
And I guess this week is Christmas who is VP of service Innovation at Otis elevators
We're going to be talking about
How to build a connected elevator
End
He answers big question we've always wanted to know which is
Oh my gosh does pressing the door close button actually work
All of this
And more
Let's Get It Started With a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform find out why Kenmore and D-Link picked a pharaoh Pharaoh customers have
Variance is much a 80% reduction in time-to-market 99% fewer support calls
M10x higher activation rates plus they can use 90% of their work from one project to the
The next to learn more visit afero. IO
That's a f e r o.
IO
Alright Kevin the big news this week comes I'm going to save for the Enterprise and Industrial side which is the Wall Street
Journal reported that GE
He was considering selling off some of its a digital businesses
V
Proposals here are at servicemax business which helps get service Personnel in installers in people to fix stuff
Out into
To the field managers those employees
Therapeutics
Business
Might also be on
That's a time-series database analytics and all sorts of good stuff that they've been marketing for a really long
The industrial average
And a couple other Acquisitions they made
Radium
Which was a
Audio Analytics
Company that does Predictive Analytics
Prediction machine's fail so there's a lot Happening Here
We haven't talked much about it but GE for the last year or so is really been
Oh struggling is not the right word
Coming to grips with a new reality might be a good way of putting it
Basically they're like all of that marketing dollars
Can I spend a lot on
Digital transformation
It was just too rich for their blood
And basically there
Slimming down there selling off all kinds of division
And it's not a huge surprise but it is a sad thing
Because
GE really created the industrial iot that in actuality but in terms of Market
Probably
4 years ago there like a virgin spend billions on
Send by God they did
They didn't think was like 2015 so maybe
3x years ago put
They said they want to be like a top 10 software
And even closed but that didn't get close to being a top 10 software company but they
Had a huge software
Right
It's right but the thing is in this is interesting at the eclipse Foundation had a little study for cloud services do you
Use planning use or any of the following cloud service offerings for implementing your it solution was the question
Of course AWS docker azure
Private on-premises cloud
Google Cloud the top
4 and like my own vast majority
The very last one with a 2.1%
Choice was GE fridge
That was probably in
LGE custom
They learn a lot of things
The hard way like they started building their own data centers to host the products analytics stuff and
Everybody was like
G I don't want to talk to you
Amazon
It's a reinvention of the wheel at this point as well
And then they also were very ambitious in terms
Is hiring people to
Sell this so like I don't think it was a mistake
Because I think there's a lot of there there
But I do think it was a bit early
And they spent a lot of money
On the marketing side
Did they couldn't necessarily backup
On the other side
I mean
The really interesting thing
If they sell this
And still they're not we're not sure they're just said they were selling digital assets and it's not clear which one
One second a cell
But if they sold something like products I think of you
Who the heck's going to buy products
You know that's it's a
So would it be would you want to see like a Microsoft or someone
Come in.
I don't think they want to but
This is what I think I'm going to explore this weekend
Epicurious cuz
The people that come to mind
There will be some overlap there but I'll be curious what you
Did you
My deductions
In other sad news
Is for the internet
Oh man it's like
Everything's coming home to roost
Way back in 2014
I read about a company that I just loved it was called
Well the device was called mother
The company was called cents
Send that essien
Dot SE
Azusa French design company
And they put out a smart home hub called the mother and then they
About little sensors called peanuts
That you basically program to be like asleep detect
Motion detector
Or any number of things
And
I loved this is
I thought it was it didn't give me the programmability cuz I was super nerdy on
Yeah I was like the smart thing
Person back then
I was like I love spending time tweaking these things making these weird recipes to do weird stuff in my house
Before everybody else
This was a really well-designed pretty in
Cute
Cute cute
Cute device
And sadly this company
Apparent
Yeah the little
Mother Unit looks like a little
Squash bowling pin videos remind me the current Google home
In some regard it was a cute product
Yeah
I mean and I love the fact that he
These things where you can buy these peanuts in
Program them
Basically the
You flash them
So they have the algorithms they need to
To do like
Truck sleeper truck stop
Really well I even
Remember putting
Through the wash
Yeah so if you have that product
Tell you
You might not have it working for me
What is that cost back in the day I'm trying to think
Cost
It cost 200
$99
And I should tell you that the creator of this system
Was it
We're going back in iot history he's the guy who found the
Now that's
Stacked I don't know how to
It was a connected rabbit and it just
Glow different colors and people loved it
So yeah
Bye-bye mother
Bye-bye
There we go and I still to this day would like just a sensor that I could
Stick on top of like my dog food container and just have it be like
Has anyone fed the dog
I wanted to tie into metal made
Okay
So that was our sad news segment
Of the show let's talk about
We don't talk about homepod that much why is that
Because it's not good
Okay then
That settles that
There just hasn't been much in the way of
Development lately I mean week through AirPlay 2
Was announced maybe a month ago
The latest IOS 12 beta beta version
5 which I have not upgraded to yet however it includes
The ability or at least the setup ability to use the homepod to make phone calls so this
Has to do with the way Apple
Uses continuity that's the function where you can spread data and activities around on different iOS devices so
You can pick up a phone call on pretty much any iOS device is it
It's tidy your iPhone and so on
So that will come in homepod with probably I was 12 I think it's a fair
After Beth
Really it's kind of table Stakes to
Do this kind of stuff that I think you're a little late here but
It's coming so that's good nothing else to talk about though cuz nothing else has happened with homepod
And
I only talk about it
Ann's Apple just had their quarterly investor
Chicagoland
No reports this week
And homepod is lumped in with their other category which also includes
They're your phone's there
Watches Etc that's a growing segment
They did talk about
How strong those products are for the other category
Not a peep
Of homepod
Not it's growing not its meeting expectations
Zippo
Read into that
What you will
Okay guys
We're here there's going to be like a hundred of you
Maybe more I don't know
We're going to find a center
But it is heavy duty heavy duty but very specific in its there is a
Okay it's either
Mackinaw
Moschino
Or, do you want to go with the pronunciation
No I'm going to go with one of those two I'll say
Mackinaw
This is a device that has
Mini input
And you pop it into a pie and you can control
Your smart home
These are four devices that you actually
I can wire them into it so
Like maybe you want to
Create like a special breaker box
Used to measure electricity consumption your house or even Italian to some
Appliance somewhere
This is too hardcore for either of us
But I would agree
If you are a doubly or just really into this stuff
Baby
Perfect for you and
Is it out yet
I don't believe it is out yet what you can do is you can sign up to say you're interested on the the website
Which is makinen., she puts on the show notes cuz I don't want to have people type it based on a pronunciations
What could be wrong though it's not available yet
Yeah it's
Built on a lot of Open Source
Raspberry Pi read E46 input outputs
You're right that you're going to be hard wiring a lot of stuff
But if you're that kind of guy
This might be a great product for you so
Check it out if so far if we haven't scared you out feel like
We'll do it live
You know I'm thinking about you wouldn't have to hardwire a lot of things because your pies going to have Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
And I'm only saying that because now that I look at the web interface for the switch axe looks very pretty
In terms of controlling things you know they've got a light
Is one of the switches and their temperature sensors
You're not going to hardwire everything in your house this one little box
So there should be Wireless connectivity through the pie
Okay but there is the option
Control wire should you
Oh yes there is I mean you can
Home and there's analog inputs that
You can configure for all kinds of currents and resolutions oh my yeah
So
Check it out if you're interested sign up and
If you get it
Tell us know what you think
Yeah
All right
This is for the industrial people out there
Your cellular modems are now Gateway
Sierra Wireless just introduced
The airlink lx40
And
You don't need to remember that
Specifically but the idea behind
This line of products from Sierra is that you get the cellular modem
And you also get
A gateway
Weight is part of this
And that will handle things like analytics of
The information coming in so basically you don't have to send every piece of data up to the cloud
Which is important when you're at a cellular connection because by God that band with this
Pensive
So I know that we talked about this in the home like why aren't our routers
Also
UPS on the case of the Enterprise world
Your router's are indeed at home hubs but
Enterprise Hobbs that can do some
Fairly reasonable computer
Seems good to me
Yeah I'm going to Pick n Save on van with costs on a cellular connection that can be a lot of money depending on how many devices you have implemented in
And so on so forth
Seeing it supports LTE
Em&m dirt both
So that's good
Power over ethernet
Battery Master
Pretty nice
Okay
And
This is in the
What the heck
Category Kevin
In his
Search his regular perusal of the FCC database found
Wait a second
No no
You make it sound like nobody else check the FCC database two or three times a day
Oh well
Sorry I meant
Surely there are other people who
Check it more than I do but you're right and then you were going to say I found a Lenovo smart bulb
And when I found it I'm like
Who
Emmanuel Lenovo
They make phones computers and so on so forth
But a smart bulb and I checked I could not find a single Lenovo iot product maybe I just didn't look hard enough but this
This appears to be there first
Foot in the door
I guess it was smart home if a wifi-enabled smart home and I only know that because they have
CC tested the 802. 11bgn end
Make it particles on it so
I guess it's exciting for Lenovo but
Not really for the rest of us is it
I saw the sign
Miss Marple
Yeah
Why
I don't know why this is everyone's intro product if I were doing an intro product for the io
I probably would do something highly Spa
Pacific just because
Try to integrate with others because we're so far into the
But if I were going to be like a giant
Smart outlet because they're so much more versatile and because
I mean I'll keep looking maybe they have a suite of products that are coming I don't know I mean this has not been announced yet
Clear on that maybe two days for results
Indicate that
Tickets an outlet and a hub in
Lord only knows what else
I don't know but I will keep looking
There we go we have
This is not DIY but in the world of coke
Control4 which is kind of Defense here hiring
Connected home stuff
We have
Suntrup Hyundai introduced an intercom feature
End
I thought this was interesting because it basically turns your control 4 system
If you have it any touch panel that you have turns into a
Prudential screen that you can talk to from your smart
Which and you can also to see video clips like from your connect
Doorbell
So I thought this was interesting for anyone who has these
Systems
And I also went to a dealer to actually check out the
Control4 system because they
Launched
With their dealers a very comprehensive
Smart Home
Showroom
So if you have one of those fancy high-end
Home automation
Dealerships
Pop in and check out
The control for stuff cuz they
Created a really compelling
System
It's actually cheaper than I thought it would
Sol cerveza
And
Yes this is difference when Elsa
You're buying it all at once and someone's going to install it and then
You know there's I think for the intercom it's part of like a $100 a year
Service fee but if you're like many people in your like I do not want to
Program a smart home I do not want to install all this stuff
It's not an unreasonable thing to do
So
I'm taking a guess here that this intercom
You said be thinknear use your phone and communicate to one of the panels
I guess I'm going to be on the same Wi-Fi
Don't you can actually do it from your phone when your remote that's what I was going to ask me what vehicle feature
So you could actually I could be
You know at work somewhere and
Intercom back to my house and talk to my wife
It's basically the same way I have used the Echo Show with my daughter when I'm traveling and
The way you might use
Google
Duo program
What's Duo
Sorry sorry sorry
So actually this gives us a choice
I like your new product that you just bought
Or should we talk about these silliest iot product
Tricky Bowman suspense a little longer
It'll keep them in suspense
Alrighty
Let's talk about your first impressions of the Lenovo smart display
All right so I ordered the Lenovo smart display the 10in Honda del Sol at 8 in Persian
Late last week when I was first available and I'm going to say
If you haven't ordered one yet and you're a Costco member
Take a look at Costco because I paid 199 for the larger one which everywhere else that's the price
For the smaller one normally it's 249
$50 savings are there a derived about 36 hours ago so I got some more
Testing to do my first impressions remember Stacy when you when I saw this
Sexy yes in January and like we pretty much fell in love with it right away
All those feelings came back
Right away you didn't regret your field
Not at all
Not at all I am super impressed so far with it
They're easy to set up you do all the setup with your phone
Through the Google home app
Get off that your Wi-Fi password is just a code here or there
Very very easy to set up
Display is fantastic it's a full h
Pictures of full HD display the larger one but it's a 720p display on the smaller one so you get a better resolution on the large one
The speaker as I know a lot of people are going to want to know
I'd say it's better than the
Stand-alone Google home but he's not going to compete with a homepod or Sonos it gets loud
Like those but the face is just not going to be there it's more scooters that the higher end of the sound
I don't see any microphones on this thing but obviously it's got a microphone array
One thing I've noticed
This is really meant to be facing in towards the center of a room so to speak Lee I put this on the nightstand in the
Bedroom we'll talk about that in a minute
Most people would not put a product like this there but I'll explain while you can
You know it's the screen it's not something I can sit in the middle of the room because you can't see it then from the other side
It's the same issue we have with the echo
We just going to turn it around with
But I will say though I mean I got a tangled
On the corner of the nightstand facing into the center of the room and it's been pretty good
About listening
But obviously I'm not behind it so
That helps
ABC's built-in with
Google Assistant some of the features
Are cool
Wake Netflix is actually built in so I can just say
AG play such-and-such on Netflix
And boom it just starts playing on the
Awesome 4K videos on YouTube
Actually
YouTube is also built in
So that would work
What's not till 10 but still works
Is YouTube TV which is I switch my service providers now from PlayStation Vue to YouTube TV however
Smart display is a cast Chromecast basically it's a receiver so anything you can Chromecast
To the Chromecast you could send to that so I did that with my phone Chromecast and YouTube TV
I was watching the news and then I put huh I wonder if I can voice control it so I said Haji change to channel
On YouTube TV it sure enough it did it so even though YouTube TV is not built-in and other services are not yet built in
Is casting you can voice-control it just like it was made over there
That's awesome down here this is
Really nice but I'm
I'm very curious
I have too many photos on Google photos
Is it possible for me to set that up
In spare time when it's not being used
Corgi videos in my house
Could I actually just have it run
My Google photos
You absolutely could because there are three options for the display when you're not using it
When's the next standby mode I'm just using the base clock display because
At night in the middle of night I want to see the clock
You know I want to see anything else but another one is Google photos
And then I think the third one is just kind of like what you have on a Chromecast like a backdrop future worth
Google just provides photos
Nice
Okay
Now
Let's talk about
The nest
Let's talk about that so
I've been tested everything but I would say anything that integrates today with Google home
Should certainly work with this display and that includes video streaming I know somebody on Facebook asked us if
Pekin Stream ring
And wyze cameras to this
You can't because you can't they don't agree with Google home today
Is problem with a platform not with this
If that makes sense
It's on sand
It's possible.
I did test messed my Nest hello doorbell camera and
Just you know it's a Haji show my front door that's the name of the camera
And what did you say about 6 7 Seconds of latency from the time I asked it to the time and actually showed it
Yes we got
Few seconds like maybe two seconds of like
After you ask where it's like sending it to the cloud
Thinking about it
Okay and then you get before second Subs
Spinning Wheel pulls up
And that's on the same Wi-Fi
It is
I mean it's not instant
It's probably the same performance as I see with my Nvidia Shield TV when I'm watching TV and I can just voice command because that's a crime
You can also pull up
Was that your nest
That was the nest doorbell
I have another nest camera
But I didn't test that
I just presumed it would work because one did
Never assume in
She part of my testing
Challenge now is
I got to go home we can so dependent on
Amazon for controlling the harm that I really never set up the rooms and devices in Google home very well
So now I need to do that
So part 2
Will be
More in-depth on how the Google home
Works with the
Which is
Today
Bye
Not by who
Let's wear this way if you are already into the Google platform for your voice user interface
With your smart home
I think this is great if you have a
Play sport I mean yes could be in the kitchen where you can do
Recipes and other things you want to watch YouTube or TV in the kitchen
We put on the nightstand and as I said
We normally don't put things like this
In the bedroom and I say things like this meaning it has a camera
Yes I was going to tell people I'm like
Yeah I know it does have a camera
Does Kevin actually now with this I could call
Kevin on Duo
And it just like
Pops up
Write in fact I said Haji call Stacy and it says
Video call or voice call and I just say video and it called you on Duo the devices typically best in lands
The only thing that works in portrait mode because you can switch
This device is kind like a dual stand the only thing that works in portrait mode is Duo
Can't have it set up
Fuse in portrait all the time
And when I did do that you said my video got a lot better I wasn't
Extract
For a little while
Yeah which may be a good thing but anyways going back to the camera itself
There's a hardware built in switch
Shutter
Hover built into this device you just flip it down and it a little
Red indicator on that says hey I've covered up the camera right now and
And also an impact the device itself will say the camera is now off
Just like you if you muted the microphone it will say the microphone is now
All right
Real quick it's touchscreen to even talk about all the voice stuff but
You can navigate through touch
Like when it said you want to call video voice I could have tapped the screen so there's a lot to his prerogative
So far I am loving it
Okay well I can't wait to get mine
And
Will come back to you in a week or two and check in on the home performance
Aspects of this and I'm sure you'll rights
Something up at some point
That was an assignment
That wasn't
Okay
And let's see
Kevin
Good Pro tip from you and then we'll get into a crazy idea
All right
So it's funny because it's before the show Stacy you're not at your home your way right now and you would said my hug at
Home is not responding
It's so funny brought that up because I was going to share this pro-tip
What do you do if you can't
Access your hubs in remotely maybe need to be rebooted etcetera etcetera and on the wink
Facebook page
People have
Talk about this and that first thing people said was
Plug your Hub into a WiFi smart
Outlet and I never thought of that but it's
Brilliant
Because you can remotely access
Bat Outlet
To reboot the Hub
Yes
And
I talked to people who actually have their routers plug into a smart outlet and they actually schedule so it just
Power Cycles through at like 2 a.m.
So hey
Good idea
Okay let's talk about I'm calling this
My silly iot product
Haven't you actually it do this
I am are you ready let's get naked
Not you not you and me not I'm not listeners
The product is called The Naked home body scanner
It's not what you think
You don't get naked on this you still can wear clothes although it's probably best to wear
Minimal clothes
Maybe underwear whatever it is a
Scale that you step on
As well as
A mirror
That has the top of it one of Intel's
Prosense sensors
Sensors for 3D Jap and
Descale actually rotates you 360° wireless sensor checks you out
Yeah
You have to howl
How else would it get your 3D body composition
I mean I guess the mirror could go around you but no
It's okay
Okay so I'm on this turntable in my
Skivvies and it's
And it basically uses the infrared sensor to scan you and
Attend will create
3D
Map remodel in a Connected app
To show you what you look like
And it does body fat composition weight
Azure sizing
Body parts
Well
I don't know what to tell you I mean if that's the whole point is to measure and then the idea is it's for Healthy Living and as you transform your
Body by living healthier you get a better sense of your progress
And I think that's actually great
I don't know if I would pay $1,400 for it
But whatever you actually raise a good point before the show with this
Isn't used for but
Should be used for an I love this life
Yes this is the only reason I would ever shame myself into getting on 80
Table that would
My body fat composition
Which is
If you could use this
Actually send those measurements to like a shopping
Excursion select Amazon or to Nordstrom's and then they be like oh well in the following Brands you're a size
And then the other bands are a size 8
And that would be amazing cuz then you could like
Buy things online in Ashley try it on virtually and it would actually be
Supposed to
Now what you're just like all by two in different sizes and send one or both back
I wonder if that infrared scanner could actually do that could it detect
I measure you so to speak actual converted into inches and so on
Converse sizing
Oh yeah
Judging by the
Judging by what it offers now I think
I guess I just because you're going to stand on this little turntable
And you may place it further away each and every time and it's going to have to
I mean I can measure the depth I guess so yeah I guess I could work
Yeah even if it's going to tell me that because it says it offers you measurements of like your biceps
Waste India
Hips and all of those other body parts
Play tabs but I only have one I have an app
You mad
You got it
But yeah
So that is our crazy product of the week
If you have $1,400 and no dignity you go right ahead Just Like Heaven
And let us let us know I'd be curious to see how it works
Somebody I don't know if we could ever get a review into this and I'm not putting naked pictures of my
Pictures of model where I don't blame you but they're not pictures it's kind of like bringing the TSA security scans
Oyster House bad for health
You know
It's enough
I would want to see
Alright let's
Go now
Our question of the week and also it is the end of July which means
We have a winner
So as you guys know riot
Listener hotline is sponsored by Schlage and Eric
Was this month's winner for the Schlage
Sense
Smart deadbolt and Wifi adapter
Curso Eric
Yay
For you
And the rest of you guys
Just because you didn't win this month
Donot
Spare we are running this
Contest again
For the month of August
I do have some more rules
Anyone can enter but you can only win
If you are in the US
Haneda so I'm sorry Europe
Sous vide sole
And I don't know how to say it another language
Okay
So
Let's see this week's voicemail is from
Dan
And he has
Question that we actually
Hi Stacy and Kevin
This is Dan from North Carolina
I'm hoping you can help me with an idea I have for using my wyze cam
I'm pretty mainstream on the smart home I use
SmartThings to control lights
A few other things in my house
And I bought a
Cy scams recently because of the Great
$20 price
There is not a wyzecam the SmartThings integration yet but both of those system
Do you have if immigration
I want to use the motion
Answer on the wyze cam
Trigger a SmartThings connected light
Turn on
But I can't figure out how to do it and I don't
CNS
Stop with the Dozen
Can if Bridges got for me and if so can you explain how I do it
And as a side note
Assuming that there is a way to do it I wonder if there's a way for the light to then turn
Turn off after few minutes
Thanks again guys love yourself
K Den
I have good news
I have mostly canoes
Which is we can actually do this
So the way you would do this
Is you go to f
I went to
Austin sauce look up why
So the wise motion is a trigger
So when it senses motion we can trigger something
And in this case
We can trigger a SmartThings device to turn on
So
This is very easy for you to make yourself
And
If you were having troubles just email us and I'll make an applet for you and send it to you
You basically
Turn on
Your
Light
We can't
Get it
Ted turn off after
So
That is the
Imitation
A vest
Which
It would be nice if you could say you know after no motion detected
Per 5 minutes Etc
Can you turn it off but I don't see any trigger done for that
So you could try and I went into SmartThings to see if there was
They have app
And SmartThings
But you could use since wise is not supported yet by smart
Now it's
Possible
That you could create an app in smart things for the state your porch light
Turn on if the porch light has been on for more than
10 minutes
After a certain time
You could create a SmartThings app that would turn the
So then you're looking at creating an if tablet
And then a
SmartThings
Automation
So
You know what this is an interesting use of the wyze camera any camera that has motion detection
And I guess
The dance trying to do is innocent because the why is cancer so darn cheap I mean is 20 bucks
Because what you could do
Throw another alternative out there
Buy a motion detector
Motion sensor that works with
SmartThings and what are you say they would cost
40 bucks
Yes it probably like a Z-Wave
And just use that because then you could actually have not just light turn on but you could probably set it to turn off as well
That's pretty typical fare for a motion set
Yes
But it is
Because basically everything
Cups of coffee and tea
So bad
Is our answer for you
And
If you have a question for the iot
Podcast
Hotline you can call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
I have to tell you again
The podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage and don't miss your chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt and wifi adapter for the month of
August
Dinner to win that you just have to call and leave us a question the end of August we will
If you are from
Do you a store
Canada and
We will reach out to you
I'll give you the information
So just think
Smarter homes
Start with c
And that concludes this portion of the show stay tuned for a message
Shemar sponsored Netgear
And
An interview with
Chris Smith from Otis Elevator
You sure is there story about building a predictive algorithm for the elevator what went wrong
Eventually went right
Annie tells us
If the door close button
Actually works on these things
Stay tuned for that
Everyone we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Sponsor is Netgear and I have John McHugh who is
A senior vice president of commercial
Parking at
Most of us know what is but
Do you want to give us a short summary a lot of people do no nut here
But they don't know that they actually we have a very important
Strategic role in commercial networking for small businesses
Especially for kind of do-it-yourself
Business owners and small office
Is home office business
And before this we were talking and you said the networking needs to change for the internet
You talk about
What you mean by that
Yeah you know it's so funny because
The internet
Saints runs over networking
And the ironic part of this whole thing is networking hasn't changed
In the last 10-15 years and it's not taking advantage
Of all the power
Potential that is brought with good Internet of Things implementation
What is that mean for Netgear and how you guys design your product
Like I said
All networking devices
By definition are connected to the network
They can be connected to the internet as won't be iot
But nobody designed them to do that thing back there two things that really I think make
An Internet of Things
Things to buy one is
Did user interface
Hilton connected to the cloud
And it's remotely accessible a drawers on the internet to do
Really much more advanced user experience capabilities
And the other thing is
Did it immediately can find the cloud
And get connected to the cloud NFC
Cure in a reliable Manner and those two things haven't really been address
Networking product until today
Designing your products
How did you implement a better user experience and this idea finding the cloud
And that was
Exactly what we start out to
To do cuz we
Other people that were kind of doing internet-of-things networking sort of connected and where they made
Things that jumped off a
The page to us
One was
A bunch of cloud connected network devices
Don't work at all without
Cloud will guess what
People's internet goes up and down
And especially small business owners
There's a lot of
Complexity of getting something up and rounding that doesn't just
Turn on and run for you
So the first thing about our inside
Cloudconnect
Is when you turn them on
State-run
Exactly the way existing products
The other thing that we wanted to make
Extremely easy was for this thing to automatically home to the cloud and get Uconnect
Without local
Servers are Cloud keys or
Weird things you have to put on your network
You just discovered the device with an app on your phone
And boom
You're connected to the cloud you're connected
Sebastian Vice
Those were the two things we really
Wanted to do differently
Okay sounds good where can we go to find out more about netgear's
At www.netgear.com inside
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Christmas
Who is VP of service Innovation that
Otis
Are they turkey
Hi Chris how are you doing today
I'm doing great steaks
Thanks for having me on
Man I am super excited
Because
They're like the thing that allowed
Skyscrapers actually
Steel with that but then we also need Adele
Water jet
You guys
So you guys are now doing
Connected elevator
And you are very clear.
So tell me a little bit about the role of
Communication
Sure so you know it's 30 years ago when we transition
From older relays called relay logic Tech
The microprocessor
It was a big change for our mechanics
And the mechanics
Needed some help literally instead of tracing wiring diagram
GrandStay had to there's this black box a PC board that had all the in
So our engineers said you know what
Let's come up with a way
How to remotely Connect into an elevator using a
Dietary homegrown REM system we called it Ram remote elevator Bonner
And analog phone
So we would dial in and help troubleshoot the information
It was designed to be read by a very senior experience
Engineer and
Was for them to help and kind of thin translate back to me
Pentagon hey this is what the issue is
So for 30 years we've been doing that
And evolving.
Technology and then of course the new technologies came along called The Internet of Things and
Industry 4.0 and we said we need to do this a
And that's where we are today
Is product called Otis one
And you still use microphone
So what exactly is changed
You're swapping out your analog phone lines
Borgia cellular initially
You know we'd eventually
The landline or buy firewood
Comfortable with just yet in their buildings we will
Use that but initially our initial product
Cellular and we're not building this ourselves
Parking without a cup
Tell you about another's work
I can't right now but
We didn't take the data off the elevator put it through a gateway
Do some Edge computing
With some of the data those that which we need to process and then we send it to the Azure cloud
One of our Park
Is Microsoft and Course once it's in the cloud that's where you
Do all your big data analytics and get all these different Insight switch before it was for that engineer
But now it's insights that we can give it directly to a customer
Biba directly to our mechanics
In it to anyone else
Reporting. End-user the passenger
You can even start connecting
The elevator in ways I can say
So it's done in a very different way with partners
Okay
We're going to dig into all of that
Temptations project to do but
What does enable your customers to do
What are they excited about when you offer
Yeah tour customers actually have no we done extensive
Research over the
Jerry cancel
Customers tell us they want
Predictive
Proactive and Tran
Predictive text
The first thing is everyone's heard about it hey I don't want things to break
I want my elevators to be up and running we call that up.
So that's the first thing we do
You can do with that
So elevators are the outside doors with
Proceed actually
70%
All shutdown
So one of the advantages of doing this
For 30 years connecting elevators
We have a lot of data
Elevator shutdown
And so we did the Pareto chart and says okay if you're going to come
What are you
First and we said okay let's go after these door calls
How do we prevent door calls and so we took all this data and working with vendors and we have a research center
Because United Technologies Research Center
Bunch of really smart phds
We came up with an algorithm that helps us
Predict when the elevator maintenance should be
It actually was an interesting Journey when we started
Predictive Solutions
We were trying to figure out a
Exactly when the elevator was shut down
In quite frankly it wasn't very sick
What we were able to then do is when we went to our Research Center they said you know you're looking at the problem
Wrong way you really can't predict
Like your doctor can't predict you know you have 27
Years and 3 months to live
The doctor can predict your health
I can't your health your numbers are going up or down and keep doing this change this and that's what we are able to do
Squishies
We were predicting now we predict
And therefore
Time when to send a mechanic to get there to do the preventive maintenance
So instead of saying when is
It's not feasible
Is it not feasible
Well at least four doors we went through successfully shifted that mindset
Again I don't want to say we can't get there
Someday but you know now it's within range
We know below a certain
Score week
Score at we say that's now in the yellow category and we should get out there within
21 days
And when it goes red we like oh no now we need
To get out there with something
So it's not as
We were trying to get it really precise
But when we
Talk to health
And trending health
That's when we started
Great results
Just help me out here how many factors
Are there in an elevator door close
Closing play into the
Well dozens and dozens
Because the elevator doors ride on a sill you mites
See that when you walk cross news
Ridges in it and so there's
Call Gibbs that keep the elevator in the seal and that still can get dirt in
Which has nothing to do with the elevator
How to do how much dirt is being tracked
The building was there contractor
Building the elevator
Doors run on roller
And the rollers you know again in
That's on a track
Back in the game
Dirt and debris in Elevator Shaft
Similar to a chimney so everything is where's the building located
What time of year is it where's the
The front door when the front door is opened is all this wind coming in and going up the chimney so
Different job site conditions are
A critical time of year is critical what's going on the building so we will see you don't see a nice smooth trend
Building a
Office building three stories we should see the same Trends know it's all
Mothers of Aries facts
Geography
So now let's we talked about for your custom
What is connecting your elevators
In this fashion
Do for you guys
Oh so ultimately if I can when the customer say I want predictive I want pract
Xidan transparent obviously if we can
Keep our customers
Inform and give them all those three things they don't want to leave
Sprint so they want to stay with us
Notice you're giving doing a great job
I will continue with under a maintenance agreement
Can you having a service you
Competitive industry
We have anyone wants
Product with a good reputation
Competitors would love to have our
So then you start getting into a price game
Yes you can
Chilton like why would I leave for
A few dollars cuz Otis's
Lighting X
And we should point out for people that
You might buy an Otis Elevator
And put it in your building
Over the years you also have two choices
Choosing contractors
It's not right
Some people might think
Clearly
If you don't work out your own
Duct a c if I had a nickel for everytime
Someone said to me you don't have any competition do you you're the only elevator come
I'd be very
Now we have plenty of
Listening people do on their elevator
Okay so continuing on
With your
Benefits to you
So the other key benefit to us
Is we can start scheduling
More practice
So in my example earlier
We now
Return day
Reactive
Murphy's Law
Situation where is Murphy's Law
For a mechanic I was just in the middle of doing it
Detailed maintenance
Routine at this one building and then I got a service
And now I have to leave pack up my tools and
Drive
And driving is the most unproductive timing
And get to the next building inmate
So obviously now when we can say no
We think in the next
5/7 days
21 days
Elevator a
In this building is going to shut down
The doors
We can now schedule that
Put it into his maintenance
When he's going to still be there so think about it the customer was going to have a shutdown they were going to have someone come and look at
Shutdown ended
The doors but it's going to be after a very
Tinsel events
Now we are still getting that same service
Beginning a corrective
And we can put into an ice maker
Schedule as opposed to being reactive
Totus more efficient
What metrics are you implementing
To account for
Things that don't
Because it's really hard
As we start making things more efficient
It's harder to say hey this terrible thing didn't happen and it was because of us
Exactly until that's where the transparency comes in place
What we're doing is for sharing with
Sonic custom
Portal for sharing with them their health scores available
Lyrics to show them and then when we do do a proactive
Close to react if we also showing them that as well hey
We came and did maintenance
Because your elevator door health
Sending negative and therefore your main
This is being done
Before we only shared with them hey we did a call back and we only shared kind of the bad
So now we're sharing
The bad news in the good
And so that hopefully of the
Scentsy while you guys are
I do have 99.9% uptime which
But there's a reason
Write instead of just
Just unlocked
Because I can see the maintenance you're doing in the timing that you're doing it
And my building is in the
Our customers tell us if
If you could delimited one thing for us
Illumination
Shut down
Okay this overarching trend
You know I see it in my connected devices I see it
Industrial
If we leave Eliza
A lot
People having trust with
Because I can see a lot of people being like
What is this
Came out did this right
Feeling like
Padding your numbers
Does people wear
Playwright
Transparency is key but how do you think other companies trying
How to do this
Create that trust
Have their bills or insert some sort of
Yeah yeah
You know I think the other keys
You saying is to share with the cuss
Tomorrow at the line of sight
Where they will have to
Most mechanic
Trevor Wright elevators will not last
The building is now a hundred years old original elevator
It needs to be upgrade
Great there's new needs in the building they need to move people faster in the building so they can have to upgrade the machines and make it faster in the
Brains to make it move faster
So when you can give
And it's all good
Apparently but give that customer
Because of the data you're getting
Usage information
Like your car hate my tires are going to last
So many miles between an oil change
That's the same thing you have to start giving that customer
That line of sight that
Customers understand hate I know eventually
I know we got to change my
So here
With data you know what you're going to get another hundred thousand trips out of that door
Operator before scot-free upgrade
Cricket in this is going to cost
This much
And it's three years out to want you start putting away some
Any of the next thing that's going to go is your machine but that can last a million trip
And you're so many trips out from that
Start investing
You're putting this song
I think that's where then you're truly are
Kiss I hate surprises
It's right no one wants to hear
Hey I guess what you have to spend $20,000 on this system
And just like we didn't budget.
Well feel sorry
But you need to do it
That's true okay that's a good point I like that okay and finally
What is his offer to
The people who ride in the elevator
The people who are waiting for
Is there anything that
You can build off of
You're one platform to
Yeah so you know what you're saying and that's
Passenger experience we are talking a lot about it in our customers are talking
How do we improve
Audi can you make it seem
I don't have to
Presents
Security badge and then go up in
Identify myself Uniden pick which elevator
So I can check myself into
To the building using my phone which 10 knows that it's
8 in the morning
And I work on the 12th floor
And if therefore seamlessly assigns me the elevator to get on
So that kind of seamless pastor
Elevators are knock
Straight people don't know where to look
Where to turn should I talk to somebody who I know but they're
Three other people in the elevator
It's so giving them some infotainment
In the elevator cab
Your music different things like that we actually Alex
Recalling a talking elevator
Integrating Alexa
And Cortana
And when we
Put this at a trade show recently the amount of excitement
Star Trek
4 Captain Kirk would get on and say you know Bridge
And the elevator were just taking to the bridge and you know
The idea of going into an elevator and say take me to mister Smith's off
Instead of having to remember
On the 12th floor so it's things like that that you start making the ride a little more fun and more
Have you actually tried out mattimeo
China Inn
I just feel like it would be super awkward to be shouting out
Take me here take me there
Take me to my divorce lawyer
I don't know
So we've done it demonstration
Big trade show
They got a lot of interest you're right they're developing
Believe It or Not developers of the
Most interested but
Particularly they saw an initial application and let's say in a residential
We're in the Residential Building typically there's not too many
People riding elk
So that could be very helpful in a commercial building where there's any
12 people on the elevator one time you're right I think we have a ways to go but the only certain applications
They can see this
Speed working out
Okay cool
So let's not talk about
My goodness
How have you are
I thought it's a little nerdy but you know we talked about Edge Computing and
Predictive Analytics I don't know what you're doing
What is this look like from
Physical
Technology
Perspective
So you know for Otis elevators obviously we know the language right
With the brain and how it talks so
Those elevators we can pull information directly off
The controller and we like I said we put it to an edge Computing device where some information is just in from
Usage things like that you don't have to say
Send that up every elevator
Is it for a bank of elevators
Yeah that the Gateway can be shared between monks
There's a limit but the Gateway can be shared
But every elevator itself would have
I so wanted to buy spur elevator but then the Gateway can be shared
Okay so
You're sending it to the Gateway some of it goes to the cloud
So we send it
And in the cloud
That's where we
How to State a witch
We can share with whatever information we need if it's an immediate shutdown
Elevator
We know it's a meter
Right that'll make this meaning this isn't going to
Self heal
Do we have things that at
Kind of grocery
And that we meet Lee
Send notification
And we've actually been now informed the customer that you know
Instead of you calling us
This is where practice
Which by the way
In the old way 99.9% of our customers
Call this a couple
Use an app
Say hey Malibu
Shut down
You say really who are you where are you
Okay we'll send a mechanic
DayQuil with this now we know when the certain fault codes are it's a hard shutdown in the only thing it's going to fit
The sound of a cat
So instead of waiting
You can imagine in the building
Sometimes hours we work
Say we just found out her elevator is down for 3 days
We now know me
Be much more proactive
We send the info so we kind of
That
Computing says none of this is really important data
Information I need to send this up immediately and it's
Straight the eyes we didn't notify differ
Systems and say this is a shutdown
Send a trigger to the customer
Senator going to mechanic
Everyone know that
We need to get out there and fix it and then other information is just
More like I said
It was more kind of
Useful information how many trips did it make on Tuesday afternoon what's the most
Know how many trips
Did it make in a day and that's it
Information now
Help us with predictions it will help us with
Estimating how long
What is not critical information
And like I said earlier we use cellular technology to
So how much data does
Elevator generator
How much data
It's less than you think and then month
Probably about
When is less than 20 megabytes
Really it's not that much now it depends on if
If you move into voice and video and things like that
The date is
When it's just
Regular data just deleted off an elevator is not a lot of data
Okay and that you're sending
Powdered is 28 overall
Yeah that's much less data than
Yes small packets
I've been conditioned by the GE airplane
Tangent example
So what other
Technology iot initiative
Are you guys in
Stacy was a pleasure you know we were part of a society or this one is bigger part of a bigger service transfer
Cremation and we started with giving all of
IPhone screen
So
That is a plastic
Which stem weed adult apps
So now that we have this
Common platform we can share information with the
Mechanics
Much easier but I'll give you an example of one app that are mechanics really low
It's a party
So 106
55 years
You can imagine there's a lot of different elevator
Anatomy course all the competitors
So imagine the parts list
And it literally would take
Hours for
So we built an app where
Steak and
If I start typing in
Product you working on
Name it I know it's I know that
It's a relay
And I know it's on this type of elevator and then it starts shorting it
4 man mechanics are saying it's saving them
In the field
Which means our customers elders
So the oldest
One in the iot is just
Is part of a much bigger
Transformation with your by the way also
Involves the culture
You know that's
Animation
Begins and ends
Culture
And although
Digitalization that we do
It's just the support
So that was 51
And my final question
Are you close by
On the elevator
Actually
So the answer is it.
And it does
Some buildings that doesn't in others it does so it really does
And sometimes buildings can turn it off there some code issues about how long an elevator door shoe
Be open
And then some people just choose to say no if it's going to be open for 10 seconds
I want to hear it and other times they
Allow it in this way
So I guess the answer
It depends
It's okay
I've always wondered I'd like I've actually never
Can make it to the door opener
People outfit
I have no idea
Put your hand out
You stick your hand out
Good elevator
Exactly
Thank you so much
For coming on the show
I really appreciate it that's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot