Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
Are you today I think we say that every week but
3 week is totally true so we got some news about Lutron and Google home
We can have a really good discussion about the Amazon Echo and voice everywhere
Where to talk about iot developer trends
It's a survey that's just out
The eclipse Foundation
System installed on some Honeywell gear so we're going to talk about that
And there's some other news
Plus this week sponsors after work and get a little update there
And finally our guest this week is sean moss pultz of bitmark
It's company using
Blockchain for establishing digital property
Kind of a fun philosophical discussion we have so you'll want to stay tuned for all of that
And now
A quick word
From another of this week sponsor a great idea for an iot business Samsung
Arctic and easy interoperable and secure iot platform lets you focus on building your business
Rather than worrying about technology provides fully integrated Hardware cloud and services
Interoperability with other devices and service clouds and
System-wide security Samsung artik is how iot gets down to business for more information
Visit Arctic. IO that's a r t i k. IO
Okay Kevin
Last week you were sick so we're glad to have you back although I have to say Richard Gunther was super helpful
He's over at the home on podcast
So
I don't know
But I know that's great I'm glad you found a great
Co-host it which was sort of last minute so thank you Richard cuz I was really sick I'm still sick but at least I can
Jumping around these days
Yes
Are you guys he was willing to drive himself and
The break up.
Just to talk
Just in case I said I'd be here
What is Richard came through which I appreciate so that's awesome
It was awesome
Now I'm going to say that you did miss our big discussion which is I had a week with the Google home
In my own little
I did not go back and listen to show yet so
Give me the skinny if you can so quick
Take was it's not quite ready for a couple reasons
Biggest one for me was how the Google home
Divide
Rooms it asks you to do a room for every
Device doesn't have another set of
Relation
Something I like having
All of my lights for like
My living room
To be called the living room
And that is rightfully possible
With the Google home
But then in my Amazon Echo I have another set of categories
Gory switches downstairs
And in the Echo you can put
Devices in a double categories
In the home you cannot
Another limitation yet another reason Kevin does not have a Google home
This is something I just started playing with we hooked our Netflix account to it
And I'm actually seeing some really good stuff with the Chromecast stick in your Chromecast in with your Google home
TV is important to you
You can actually do a lot of things that are
Pretty compelling pigs for the Google Assistant
I don't know how much of it
The Netflix stuff does go over the Google home
Turn on
And watch
Try to take a show that's on
Stranger things
Sure
Watch stranger things it'll actually pull
All the way to
Stranger thing
Right
That was one of the
More compelling features on Google home was announced how you could use it to cast
Audio or video
Be a voice right so I suspect that
If a third party
Service or provider
Supports chromecasting it probably will work fine with Google home as long as long as you have a
25 $35 Chromecast
Hook up to a TV or speakers at the Chromecast audio so that's actually a
One of the biggest selling points
As opposed to an echo because for you to voice control your TV
You have your Echo working with that via the
Logitech write a Logitech home Harmony which
Second $90 Edition uses IR
If I'm not mistaken
I also have a controlling my Roku
So it actually brings him
So it's unlikely that Google
But
Yeah yeah I mean that
Yeah gif
If you do look at
The integrated services
With home it is very Google Centric obviously so that that is a good point
Disclosure time
Don't just close your time thank you see I'm still sick so I forget that
I forget to tell people that I do work for Google as a consultant it's my full-time job
I don't work with them on the IRT type products in such a word with chrome in Android so
There we go
Let's be quick
Experience with one other thing that you can do that I thought was pretty cool
You can actually if you're using
Google photos
Like I am
Yep
My dog
On living room TV
And holy cow it shoots photos of your dog
And Olivia
Which is pretty
You're like
Computer yeah
That's actually one of those
Most impressive
Recent software apps that come out of Google in my opinion I even use it on my iPhone on my my SIM card currently in an iPhone
To be honest and
Google photos I use that too for the free storage because backs everything up into the cloud but the search capability
Image recognition I really
Impressive and then when you're tied into
That search functionality to voice and casting that information to a screen
That's pretty cool I agree
It's magic
What do you still say but you still real quick but you still say the home listens better than your Echo as well
Amazes me
You know something
No probably probably but no not in this nothing relevant to this
It just amazes me because I was always very impressed by the
The microphone array in the original Echo
And
I know Google home has an array I don't think it has seven microphones I don't recall the exact specs
And I'm just I'm just really surprised that
Pitbull listens well you're not the only person I've told me that so
And maybe it's got to do with the timber of my voice survey
Maybe Amazon listens better at certain frequencies
Google listens better at others
This is a Christian actually into some big news
Wichita
The Amazon
Folks
Have released
A madam
Hardware development
People which includes
The seven mic array
And basically if you want to build
Exactly an Amazon Echo
You can you can
Pop that Hardware into your particular device
And you can have the matinees voice services
And Wallah
There is
An echo
So that
Brings the question
How were people building Echo like devices before or were they doing it with
Fewer features like they couldn't have seven microphones there's an apple
They had one
2 microphone
Phone so Lake
The nucleus
They have
I think it's just one
1 FedEx
A secret
But they just put it in the Amazon voice services
What race really is is
A better listener
Device
It's also I look at this and I'm like
Yeah
Basically Amazon so I can't voice is going to be an essential UI of the future and we want people getting
Used to using
Our voice system
Sure
Just to add to what you had said about
How that can now make
Devices with the 7 Mike's it also supports beamforming noise reduction Echo cancellation so
Something like a nucleus
Probably don't need that
But
Home assistant type devices which
Seem to be cropping up every week now
That I could see why
Harbor makers would want you know the full feature set
No I'm
Curious bee
Because I don't know if this has it
Amazon has
I feel like after Google announced
Because Google has something that basically
Pics when you are in a room and you talked to something at picks the closest available
Assistant device that can
Panda lyrics
Quest so Amazon has something called ESP in that stands for
Echo spatial
Perception
That's basically
So if you have a multiple Echo devices are. Surround
Your house
The closest one
Bright and
I don't know I assume that the
If it's a software update but I assume that your Hardware
Implementation would have this in the reason we bring this up is because holy cow we're putting Madame egg
And everything
Right
Just real quick I don't think
I don't know if Google has something similar like if you had multiple homes and the only reason I say that
I don't have a home so I can't say for sure
I keep hearing from multiple people
When I say the Wake word for Google home then my phone which is also set for the same wake word
Is firing up in responding and then I have
Seen that with multiple Android phones that I have so
I'm not sure if there's a similar Solution on the Google sign
You don't
I talked about having something
But I have had that problem I actually talked to her
Weeks ago cuz I was trying to
Get something started and I
I had to leave my phone elsewhere to get it
But
Pretty sure they talked about having a way to do that other than and I should say
You can always use
Okay g
For one device and Haji
Pretty
True
Well that's a thing and then I don't want to do that because I don't want to have to remember it sounds stupid but
Eventually you know when you have like
Today I have four five things listening all the time
I would imagine I have double that number in a year
I don't want to remember their names I can barely remember the names of my two kids so
I don't want to
Popular wake words for everything
Yeah well that actually so
What are the news items that were talking about this week
Because our buddy
Steve's at work
Who despite having a
A young child is still
Breaking stories
He found that the next version of ecobee 4
It's going to have
Metal May hanging out in there he actually found this information out prior we weren't sure about
Vehicle before I think it was another FTC filing
I'm sorry FCC find my phone
Camping difference there
But now
He's actually got a picture of the a blue light
Bar on the top of ecobee4 Witchwood
Simulate the blue
Light ring of an echo for example
We already saw the potential for speaker on the back of it I would say obviously there's a speaker on the back of it now
So
It's interesting I don't know we don't
Knowing anything about pricing or than cuz
Ecobee has an announcement so it's just this is just
Foundry ICC testing
You know what that's going to add in terms of cost
Do people who already have
Echo devices
Are they going to
Buy this and have another microphone and speaker that they need any
So it feels
Additive
Person
Who's like
Oh maybe I want to get the smart home to try
I'd love to save money on my air conditioning
And this Adele also has
Diego
And it's so
Maybe in depending on the price point
You know
Havasu mean it's more than 250 which is the
Kind of Baseline for the high-end
If you don't have either of these devices maybe this looks good if you have one of these devices
I don't see it because
You can already control these devices through what you already have right
And it's not like you're going to buy this is your first Echo device and play music on all day because of speakers not
Going to be loud
But if you are getting into the smart
This might be a tree
Interesting way to do it cuz you could just buy
A smart thermostat + a light bulb
You know you've got
We talked about
Buying someone a. Plus a little
Switch module and how
So now you can buy them
Two connected
Devices the thermostat and the connect
Are the connected
Switch module
You know why I can see
Especially if you don't
Want
Speaker in your house
Like
45 Blackstone
I'm pretty keen on that personally but okay
Oh thank you so I can see that but
If there's other plans
GE has that weird glowing light
You know I can see pudding
The Temptation and the goal is clearly to put the echo
So in everything
Where to put Madam and
What do I really want to talk to
Do I want to talk to
Every single individual device or do I want to talk to like a butler
Lakeside Grill
Exactly
That's the key right there and I
And that's why I think
And I can put it very well be wrong
I think this'll
Probably not be as big as sellers
Oaks my
Extinct
Because if you already have the cylinders around your house
You're not going to buy this version of an ecobee4
I don't think
I agree with you
And so the big question is is this is the echo
Orem anime
Compelling feature that pushes someone over the edge into a smart home
I think it's probably however
Yeah
Let me put it to you this way you have multiple homes
That goes I keep doing that
Is not home
You have multiple echos as do I
Throughout the house every week pretty much outfit at our homes
With echoes
So would you
If you need a thermostat would you buy they go before with
Voice and speaker
I'm guessing not
Hohhot
3x speaking of ecobee
They just did a deal where they
Now that you could be late which sells for about $170
It works now with external sensor
So the reason that the light was late is because I didn't have this
Sensors
But now for 80 bucks you can buy a sensor Pack 4
Toby in that kitchen
Koala
You now have
It's not lighted
So just in case you guys are looking out there for the
Smart thermostat work
Maybe go that way and
Keep your
I go I don't know
Okay
So that's that's a little little bit of each of the news there
Let's talk about
Should we talk about developer trans or should we keep going on thermostat
Let's keep going on thermostat sticking up thermostats
Why not temperature
Control is so exciting
Anna and I have a temperature control story from my weekend so
I like it
OKC were planning to hear you're watching the sausage get made right here
Yo I installed two weeks ago a Honeywell T5 thermostat
Breaking the great thermostat band
Of I think it was like 2813
No more no more
Big deal
So
I had some thoughts about
And I installed the T5i also
Got a version
Of the lyrics
Which is there voice control
Round
Thermostat what was interesting here
Is
Honeywell makes a universal
Plate that you install with your wiring against the wall
So you can actually pop any Honeywell
Well thermostat
Just write on
Which is really cool cuz as long as you're the Honeywell ecosystem
So
My call is
By God
Let's get a stand for
Call thermostat
We might be off
It would be very nice if
Because you know when I left my home
When I sold it last year and I had the The Nest down there I took the nest off
And like well because I painted around the plate and now they're going to have different colored different size plates
Are there thermostat I just I just left the nest I made such a hassle
I would be so mad if I showed up at the house and they taking the
Thermostat
Billiard
I suppose you're not supposed to listen to this technically wired to the house
Thermostat
This is a big debate
Oh no it's not making bag
I'd like that now I will say
That I've installed an ecobee
I've installed
The
Nest
The Honeywell was the least forgiving in terms of having Room 2
Pop my wires in
So I was doing some serious jam and some wires back into the wall
And some fairy
Delicate folding to try to just
Get that on there
But
The experience with the thermostat
Was good
I did call support
I'm at one point in their support was just bang on
Awesome
Good
Am I tip for anybody who's installing a thermostat because it's been awhile since I had done it
Is how the information about your existing HVAC system available to you
I feel like in the instructions for all of these devices they should actually put
A little questionnaire like
You have a heat pump
Debra, Dwyer yeah that forces you to go through this
Because
Every thermostats going to ask you these questions and if you have it if
If you answer wrong
You're probably going to
End up like spewing
Hot air when you want
And another tip
When you take your old thermostat off
Before you remove the wiring
Take a photo of how it is connected via the wires
Adidas for two reasons one it makes it easy to transition the wires to the new thermostat so you can measure everything up
It sometimes the colored wires are not the correct colors and someone other than that label correctly
What to if you
For some reason can get your new thermostat working to get up hook up the alarm again
Is there any easy to redo it
Yes
And actually in the Honeywell install
They actually give you
I took my picture
But they actually give you a checklist where you
You're supposed to match your wires like
Before you do anything exactly
Where does your yellow wire
It goes to the White
You know you're coming about standardized
Plate System
Ashley resonates with me because
As I mentioned selling the old house it was a hassle with an S do I keep it to another what do I do with it
Imagine how many people
Don't buy these things
Or don't invest in Smart Home Products in general because they're
They may be
Continue moving in next couple of years
Well if you have a standardized Plate System you can make the investment and not worry
In a sense that the other the new people can be kind of screwed or whatever
Exactly
Really want it once a month
Said that bad but it's cool
Thermostat probably every two years but like
Every five years may make sense for
People in this is a really good thing that this would be great for the industry I don't
Bakery
This is this is a way to
To resolve
Boats
Industry if you're listening this is a good idea
Take it
Okay
Let's see the other Honeywell device that I had
So I did the T5
And
I did the water sensor we talked about this is an $80 Wi-Fi power
Water and leaked it
That has
Both the sensor
Module things
Square
It also comes with this for footlong
That you can wrap around a pipe or just extend along so it gives you more surface area to detect
Weeks cell
Apple
It is I love this sensor
So I got that I installed that
And you can daisy chain actually
Four of the
The cords together
Sulekha July 6th
That's a lot
So there's two things to know about this one is because it's Wi-Fi and battery powered
You have to actually spend
It only checks in once a day to see if it's a check like temperature and other
You can set it for more often but then your battery is going to
Diminished
Broccoli
But
When it gets wet
Only way to shut it off is basically reset the device
Batteries out
As a as a tester this sucked
Because I was like how much water does it take not a lot
That's great
I got to be added to my
But
It does make sense because presumably this is not a device it's actually gonna
What it does go off you're probably like
Oh crap
My house is leaking
You know
You'll take it you'll shut that off and then you'll deal with your leak and then
That's true I wish I hope that in the future they caught up
I would like a beauty
They say they have
Okay
So
So this all ties into where I visited this weekend which I did not plan to visit
But I'm glad I did
Because this place could really use some of the stuff we talked about on the show
I went I went out in Arizona for the weekend we were visiting colleges
And on a win we drove two hours from Phoenix to Tucson
And then the answer to Tucson
In Oracle Junction
At work like
Is the biosphere
To which
For younger people you may not
Remember this but I do remember
People living in the biosphere for two full years like 1991 to 1993
Which at that time was it completely closed
Ecosystem
Yeah yeah
It was noted there was no Netflix
No
No it would life was tough kids
This is an amazing place I highly recommend you visit if this is your thing it's just
Interesting science experiment and they still run
Lots of science experiments to determine
The impact of CO2 on climate and so on and what not because
It is literally it can be a completely closed
System
Meaning no outside air or water or anything get in
And none of the stuff is inside gets out
Right
So
What was interesting and relevant to the show however
Was
I got a tour and we got to go underneath the biosphere which is multiple I mean a couple hundred acres this place you know
Glass domes and whatnot
Because there is
A rainforest room there's a desert room then there's there's a
Literally you think you're in a desert or the rainforest could they be simulated
And they paid
They actually built it that way
But to do that they have to control all of the air the water
Everything else is air pressure
And it's all done by computer controls through a control an energy center that's
Obviously to attach via wires but it's a separate building
And a single person
Because it's all computerized can actually
Monitor and change things so
They could use they have some
I'll call Early industrial iot stuff because up there a lot of computer control valves and such to do all this
I can easily see the meeting water sensors and maybe they have them and just didn't show them
Because
All the water inside the biosphere is already there
It literally
They put water into their ocean room and evaporates and then they condense the air and they recapture the the water
And the recirculated and solids
Auburn
750000 gallon tanks of water in this place
I got two prisoners water leak sensors in there but again I did not see any
In any case
It's just it was really amazing to see what I would
Consider early industrial iot on such a scale
For an interesting project like that so
Just something that
Kind of tied in with the show I thought I mentioned
That's like old school
Yes it is
Today would be less custom
Cheaper I don't know
Snooze beds
Logitech pop
They make a
Button
It is literally a fun button
Or $60 they now make a
Homekit
Button
August
The original Legend
Might be
And you can do three commands on this thing and I think there's a 1-tap a to tapping a person hold
Press and hold
All right
Messi
August locks
Has done a deal with HomeAway which is one of those vacation rental places
And now you can
Basically if you stick a
August lock on your door you can
Do an integration it's kind of like the integration they've done with Airbnb
So when someone signs up and they're running an app they can get into the house using the August lock
Handy funny that you say that because while I was away this weekend in Arizona I had my front door painted here my townhouse
And I didn't know I was getting it painted needed a second coat
And I didn't realize that I was coming back this weekend so
Literally as I'm having breakfast in Arizona
He sent me an email says
Hey I'll be over 20 minutes to paint front door and give it a second coat in like no I'm not there
Sure enough I was like just text me when you get there cuz I want to give my code
Cuz I have a keypad code as well
And I'm like I'm just going to go into my Wink app and
Slide little slider and unlock the door when he gets there he was awesome
He knew about that already
Cuz I told him
When was painting the first time I gave to the lock locks on you
Your painting don't freak out
If anything was behind the nest cam going as well so I could see that he got in and didn't do anything nefarious to the house
And why not
It was a nice application biote
Yuriko IRT guys
All right
We should let see
Let's talk about the iot developer Trends survey
Cuz that
That's
I thought so they do this
Every year
Well they did last year
2015-16 and 17
So the big thing that I thought was probably most interesting for our listeners is that Amazon is the top
Cloud is the top iot Cloud platform
MRSA when you're hosting your iot stuff
You're hosting an AWS
Let's see 42.7% of the time
I'm actually not surprised by that
I'll tell you why
And it's actually has to do with what I do at work
Because I work with the Google Cloud team
And I'm often looking at
Who is cloud is being used the most for what purposes and it is
AWS without a doubt is bleeder in just about every area that I have researched so far
Microsoft is a strong second with Google being third
Microsoft is big in the
Yes
So that's that
They also had
IBM bluemix was still hanging out in there
GE predix is way down the list
So
The other thing that I thought was really interesting is they looked at
Connectivity protocols
And
Thread
Is seem like
Nothing
Tiny tiny tiny adoption at 6.4%
It was just this year I feel like that it really came out with their actual
It's definitely does not have first-mover status
The biggest protocol is TCP IP
Which
Makes total sense followed by Wi-Fi
Cellular is actually
The next most common
And
Way down there is like
Zigbee which makes sense cuz there's a lot of light bulbs running zigbee out there
And then
We get into like cereal
Lora sigfox and all that
Those aren't those are way down
It will include a link to the actual
Report in the show notes
And then security is the top concern
Still good if it wasn't as high as I would have thought though
Not about security
But it is in the follow that's followed by interoperability
So we're still not there at
Fertility
We do have lots of middleware options were going to see some more stuff coming actually there
In the security technology cuz I asked about the top security related technologies that were being used for iot
One was basically TLS and dtls is the
The top option which makes sense
Skip test
Everybody I know is like yes
Start there
In data encryption followed that
In a pretty closely
What I did think was
We're talking about is Hardware oriented Security Solutions were less
Popular
Yeah that's surprising to me too
Now
Homekit uses Ace Hardware
Oriented security solution yes
It does
And
Now I will say so I talked to the head of
Now he's got a crazy title but he's at nxp and he's head of he basically works on security platform
He said that they have like they have secure element
It is one of their that's there
Where based security
You said they put that on there if people buy it and they think they're using it
But in a lot of cases the way they're writing their firmware or their OS
It doesn't take advantage of
Because the software developers working on somebody's project don't know how to tie it back to the heart
Okay so I can see to things here one is what you mentioned in that
There is some level of effort required to integrate your software to work with a secure Hardware
And to I would imagine any Hardware security solution would also add cost
I wonder if these are part of the reasons why this adoption other usage is lower
So cost is coming down I actually so it's about $0.50 to a dollar so I talked to another chip
Person I talk to someone at silicon Labs who's working on the iot
And he said it's 2017 he anticipates
The cost to come down
Quite significant
Because security
Such a concern
So I think that's going to go away but I do think
The knowledge required to connect these two
It's going to
I have to work on
It sounded like like when
You say he would talk to the CEOs of these
Company
We got a hardware element
And they think they're
Can you sing it
Imagineers think they're you
But they're not actually
That's that's actually pretty scary
It is
He's a call we work with him
But so
Yeah take that is
Scary
Which is why I actually Microsoft
Comedies like electric imp are looking at a platform approach that actually tie those things together
Which
I wouldn't that actually
Yeah cuz security
Yeah
Feel like we
I talked about a lot of things this show
And
Feel like we should probably get to our sponsor message and our guests for this week
Which is
The CEO of
Bitmark
We are going to talk about creating digital property rights
And how we have perhaps
Done everything with the internet
Wrong
In the past
So yeah I know
So stay tuned for that because it's actually really fun and interesting conversation hey everyone this
Stacy breaking into the Internet of Things podcast
And I have Linden Tibbets here
Taylor Swift
Lyft allow
Anyone
To get their services and devices to work together
We want to be the standard
Or data access
Can I use it all the time so thank you
When did you're in a unique position to see so many iot devices
Are there any Trends you can share with
Absolutely what's really fast music
If we seen from talking about hardware and devices
The talking about services in API every device
To the service
Whether it's your phone your car your watcher
Thermostat refrigerator from our perspective
That Hardware that physical device is just
The starting point
First service
Experience that you can have
With your cuss
Whatever the internet touches
It tracks in it empowers
I'm changing all of our stuff
Every noun
Into a verb
Software is truly eating the world and see the World in a really good way
Experiences are getting
Much much better
Overtime
For all of these new services
Where should they be trying to reach
What's your bet on the next interface
Sza voice
Two voices going to elderly be a huge deal if it's already
We're still just kind of in this almost like this
Free iPhone remote for voice imagine in 10 years
It's going to be one of the primary ways
Which we interact
With the internet in our services
But what's so fascinating
Is that interfaces are really additive
She didn't kill the radio and in fact we're on a podcast right now
Free free right there every new interface is really a new way in addition
Call the current ways that we interact with the internet and we have this huge wave of potential new interface
Is coming down the pipeline voices one of us but there is everything related to arbr
We talked about chatbots
Your TVs are becoming more
What services and in devices
Think about
How do they have
Presents
How
Does Derek
Experience extend across kind of this never-ending March
Interfaces
How do I set themselves up for successful experiences
Given that
New interfaces apartments.com
So then what's your advice for iot companies trying to stand out
Try and see this future of more more devices more interfaces more data as a huge opportunity
From the get-go develop an integration
Unless you're the very first serve it that your customers invested in
It's very likely that your customers are going to have a
Big question as they're making a purchasing decision or whether or not your product is going to work with all the stuff they already have
Still working
Incredibly
Proud of our partner platform
Has over 400 services on it now we got hundreds more coming soon
Helps our partners
Integrate
Incredibly quickly with each other and that coolest features
For their end users
The sounds great where can I go to find out more
Anyone with an API
Any iot service any service at all
If you got an API you can become an ex-partner
We encourage you to visit if.com iot
If
TTT
Dot-com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Xiaomi
Moss
Hopes who is the CEO of a startup called
Fitmark
Hey Sean how are you
Chris Stacey thank you so much for having me on the show
Man I'm super excited and I didn't know if I would because
You reached out to me and you're like
What is kind of cool
Cool idea about property
And digital ownership and I was like
Hello
Let's not keep people in suspense
Let's talk about kind of
Your thoughts about
How we're treating
Property
In a digital era
So on today's internet and this involves also Internet of Things
It's individuals that are creating all the value
But we're giving away almost all of these assets for free
The two companies that then take these and use them for
Quote-unquote Big Data
Which is really
Selling the analytics to other companies for profit
Okay and you're talking about my content like the things I'm creating on Facebook or
Maybe it's my
Camera data that
Submitting
Two-ness
Yea or it's your playlist to make on Spotify
Like if you just look
Kind of
Completely analytically at any one of the evaluations of these big companies
And you say what does it cost to license all of the world's music
And what is the valuation of say Spotify for example and there's a massive gap between the two
And then you go to a school where is that value coming from that justify such a high valuation
End
We believe that it's because
The accounting so the value that's being created by individuals
Is off the books
Yet
In the eyes of a adventure capitalist it's absolutely on the
Okay so your thought is as a user of all these services
My data is worth something and we should figure out how to act
Account for it yes so our vision if you will the perspective is that
Data is the next major asset class
And
Until individuals can assert ownership rights over their data
That on the power that can come out of that asset class in terms of freedom in terms of wealth in terms of privacy
Realized
Okay so how do you propose we do that
So this requires like a really brief history lesson right until property is this kind of strange abstract things
Michael's back hundreds of years
Property came out of
Land ownership
And something known as the enclosure movement
Square Farmers
Literally he said
I'm going to start
Boxing in my land
Before this happens only kings and queens in churches could own land and so there was this
Not very smooth in a very radical process.
Came to a conclusion in 1801 when Parliament created
The notion of individual private property
A very similar thing happened with knowledge with ideas with patents and trademarks
End
After
The democratization if you will
The ownership of land as an asset or knowledge as an asset
The moment individuals could own that it was a very short period of time before
The Agricultural Revolution happened
The Industrial Revolution happen
And so it's this theme if you will of
Democratizing who can own what an out of that
Comes
A massive growth
In Market
And so we look at
The 3rd
I'm stuck if you will is
Data as an asset class
And if individuals could own that
Then
You could have
I don't actually know what this name is called sometimes we call it information revolution but people think that's what I've already happened
But there's going to be something that will happen once individuals can assert ownership over their data and it becomes an asset
Class that generates wealth for them
This idea that is transferring this concept of old-school title Spacek
My data
Yeah that's right
I feel like
We shouldn't be talking about property rights at all we should be talking about
Ownership of data which
You're saying should be treated like
But it's really not
About property
It's really just about owning
Let me come back to it this way right so if this this relationship between titling assets
Ownership property property rights are all intertwined and
I think the
Simplest way to think about this is that
You need
A record of who owns white and from that record
You have
Titles that are being stored in a property as a title plus an acid
And now you want to say okay what what are the rights to
Talk about water rights are rights whatever you want
At the end of the day what we're talking about is
The ability for an individual to assert ownership over something such that they could then transfer the ownership of that in a way
Play it safe
Respect their privacy
That they can
Capture some of the values
The things that they create or they generate
Solo printing
Renting my data you can run your data you can lease your data
You can donate your data actually I think that donating side is particularly
Strong
All right we're going to get into that but first because you keep mentioning
The distributed
We should probably talk about how you do this
Everybody
Who's listening
Yes we are about to talk about
All right
Yasso
Without digging into the weeds too deeply
A blockchain is
A really new technology that allows two individuals
To exchange something of value without going through a central intermediary
And why that's important for property system
If we think about how
Humans
Behave in terms of exchanging property
I can sell you my car
That's a really a peer-to-peer transaction it's a decentralized transaction now
You could argue you have to take the title go to the DMV they update it
Fine
But I'm Toyota is not going to complain if I sell you my car
They have no right to complain if I sell you the car whereas
In the digital environment if I try to sell you the software that runs on my phone Apple could say no
Adobe could say no there's all of these people that
Have structured the digital environment to wear
The transfer of things
Do not look like property they look like
License agreements in renting which
From the perspective of
Somebody that purchases something is radically different than owning something
Ideal you're saying here is we should have some mechanism of ownership cuz right now we don't actually have
Even wait a license
Stacy in some ways we are granting license all day long to our data so when you use Facebook when you used to
Twitter when you use these different services
Within the terms of service is some Clause that resemble something like you are granting
That platform and non-exclusive royalty-free irrevocable license to use your data to
Create derivative Works your data to sell your data
Big knock against creating individual datamark
Places
Has been
Individually my data is
It is only an aggregate that it becomes
Worth something too
Yeah so how does what you guys are doing
Supply chain
Give my individual data is some sense of
Value to
I'm revisit this from like a historical perspective
On land also had no value before
There were titling of land and individuals could
Could assert their property rights to land
So it's like the Indians trading Manhattan
Yes
Yeah
I don't know if you want to yes
Strike we are giving up our
Freedom
Without knowing it
Cuz we have bought into this argument that our data is not valuable
But our perspective is that
That's totally wrong
Your data is super valuable and the reason it's not
Economically valuable right now is because there's no way to assign property rights to it
Okay
What is this look like in practice and I think you mentioned that donations
Yeah probably the place that this was going to start
So can I
Walk me through an example of
Best example of this
A public health researcher
That would like access to
Tell me if your photos and your location data and what's interesting is that
You can run algorithms on photos now to
Figure out what the
Pollution levels are in certain places
The number of
Really interesting applications that you could do for public health benefits if you could
Crowdsource
If you will
I'm photos with locations with individuals consent
Can use that data and Anonymous way for
Tracking pollution or air quality levels a lot better
So how would that work
A researcher would broadcast
A study
You as an individual
Wood
Opt-in using your phone
And you would be able to donate your data and so technically what we're doing there's a company in Silicon Valley who are partnering
If Tom if this then that
And they provide ways
Is of automating
Date of rule so like if you upload a photo to Instagram when you can
Save that photo in Dropbox
And so we have something going on with them where you could say if you have a new location Point than bitmark that or if you haven't
New photo
Then didn't want that or if you have new sleep data or Fitness data
Then bitmark that end
Now there's an index
Pics of who has what
Indexes the blockchain as a database
And researchers now would be able to
Have
Structured information of who has what data
And individuals could donate that data
And do so in a way that the consent is automated the privacy of the individual is respect
No
Go with us because I have connected if
All kinds of
Looks like Michael Pitt
And I already signed
So I can't not retroactive
What do you like
Or can I see this is this is where things get like who this is fun in theory but when it meets
The road what happen
Yeso
You wouldn't be retroactively going back and getting all your data off that site again
What you would be doing is that
If can extract the data from Fitbit
Write on your behalf
And that is entirely legal
What you're granting again in the terms of service is a non-exclusive
Royalty-free license
Stew what you're creating
What your generating
You're not actually transferring ownership
Of all the abilities
Create
Additional licenses
Haha
Tesla in their contracts
With buyers of cars with autopilot
They say you can't use their cars
Or that service
For your own kind of
Rideshare
Cramps which is very smart
We're looking ahead and saying hey we want to do this ourselves
That feels kind of like something
It is
Moving is more towards this subscription model
Unless towards an ownership model so I wonder if we're like
Too late
Kind of pull this back a little
The good thing is right now all of this stuff looks like the Wild Wild West and that's why companies can
Claim
Statements like that
High-end
So it's so early
The way that we live in the digital environment for so many people is still so unclear what are those rights
What's what's going on there
How does the Constitution how does the rule of law protect me when I'm in
Environments where
The data the assets
Global
So these are all
Really early really unanswered questions
And so we just kind of try to look back at
Historical
Perspective end
Yes there were plenty of times where
Companies kings queens churches whatever
Unclaimed
Ownership over a comment claimed ownership over a lot of different
Things that arguably
Should be owned by citizens in all should be owned by the
Nobody individuals were creating them
End
Time and time again the courts
Side with individuals
I feel like Sean that I should be a lawyer
And we should have a conversation based on like
Entries of case law that I could say
For most of history in Outlook a book printing that resembles
Copyright copying
Throughout most of History the average person never ever ever hit up against copyright law and this is
Predominately because none of us are book
In the internet the way that technology works this is Internet Internet of Things
Same thing
Our devices are constantly making coffee
Copies in the cloud copies into local memory
And each of these copies interacts if you will with copyright law
And so
Whereas nobody ever hit up against copyright law and now all day long were brought up against it
All over the
End
Our perspective is that
Copyright law never should have been applied
Things like data things like
That the binary outputs of programs of musics of movies these sorts of media
Once you apply copyright
Right to it
The ownership of that goes away it gets Stripped Away so the freedoms of an individual in terms of
Things like for sale your ability to sell something
Your ability to share it with somebody your ability to use it to create new works
All of these get removed
When something looks like renting
As opposed to ownership
So this
This is a big philosophical thing
It kind of scares
Bejesus out of me so my big concern with iot is everything is becoming a subscription
We don't own this
Yes what are the repercussions of this and so what you're saying
Right here is
When is we won't be able to
Generator wealth we won't be able to
Accumulate stuff over time pass it on etcetera
Yep and we can go really
Kind of far in this direction but there is
What is the number of books
6 famous book that says that
Making money with property
Generate a lot more money than making money with labor
If you don't have the ability to assert ownership over something
Then you are a renter
And with renting you are right
To create wealth are just
How much is create wealth but your
Privacy rights
Are also
Incredibly Limited
You don't have a right to privacy in public
In public places
This is what you do have a right to private
Mercy in your home
Because you own your own
Because it's your private property
But you don't necessarily have a right to
Privacy on your Facebook
Which is you
Yep
End
We think that
As these two environments look
It's not fair to say anymore somebody is online or offline
We're always
And the digital environment is intersecting completely with the physical environment
And it's just no longer possible to separate these too and to look at okay in the physical world we have these
Liberties we have these freedoms
In the digital world
Everything is different
It's just not right
So this is an
Awesome intellectual argument
But because you are starting a company I have to ask you
How are you guys planning to make money
The way we'll make money is
By giving you
Simple ways hopefully
To monetize your digital assets
Demonetized
And then you take a cut
That's right
Or I pay for
That's right so we would take a commission when you sell your data
So it's like
A real estate
Yeah or Merrill Lynch
Stock broker
You know you're going to sell some assets that you own we're going to help you find a buyer
We're going to make that transaction
Painless for you
And I like it
And we're going to take a small piece
So to see how far this
This analogy extends let's talk about liquidity
Because any good Market has
Liquidity and right now
You got zero the
You have no market and
How do you make Market swell
Marketsource
First made through
What are known as like over the counter transaction
So you
Transfer ownership of something to
Another party
And over time you'll see
Exchanges you'll see marketplaces
But
Until the property rights
To the offsets
The property rights to the data is clear
And people can assert ownership over that end
Courts can look at that and they can say yes
Stacey homes.org
Shawna
Unless that's clear
You can't have these sort of
Economic models
Alright so what you feel to the titling system
To test this kind of titling system for my personal data
Need both Embark it or I need something to go awry so there's a court case about
And nothing that you've described to me makes me feel like there's
An opportunity for a court case because I'm
I'm granting these non-exclusive rights and I'm talking to companies that are going to pay me buddy I'm just donating it to
Court case would come about if you wanted to revoke some of those
Rights that you've granted to the parties
And so that's not what we're at
Where after
Giving you new ways of using your data to create wealth
These new areas are things like
You can donate your sleep data you can sell your location data
You can
Pass your
Photos down to your children in a digital estate so these are things that
Right now are incredibly difficult
To do if you can do them at all
Okay so walk me through this
Let's talk about what I can create
To pass down to my children as part of a digital estate email is probably a really good exam
Or maybe a Facebook
Wallpaper
Yeah you know all of these ones are really good examples because they're behind terms of service or something no one dies
Fiduciary duty where if you die or if you become incapacitated then
The court can appoint a lawyer
The process is known as probate
And the lawyer can
Get access to your assets they can call if your bank if it's Bank of America they can say hey
I'm Stacy is dead whole system work
The banks
Stockbrokers they all know how to deal with
The ownership can be transferred passed between Generations
About the tech companies
Tech likes to say that yeah we're way ahead of law has to catch up
But in this ownership perspective
I think that
The tech companies are totally wrong
They're waiting
Find very elegant Solutions of how you protect wealth how you transfer wealth how you move assets between
Individuals
That have been set up for hundreds of years that are very simple very elegant and
That's what needs to be brought into the digital Empire
Okay well I love what you're doing Shawn
I have no idea if this will be successful
Really appreciated the chance to talk to
About it
Thank you so much for coming
Michelle
Thank you so much Stacy it was really a pleasure to be able to come on your show and speak to your listeners about
This problem that we think is
One of the most important problems that nobody looking at right now
Smoke Shop digital ownership
Well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast please join us next week when we have
Another amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are hankering for some iot news
Sign up for my newsletter it Stacey on iot. Com