Hey everyone it's time for The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacy
Kevin tofel
Are you today
First off
We should say that
Hey welcome back
Good to be back
Rite Aid
A run for your money
I heard that
First off Kevin's back today and we have
We can talk about
Cool uses for
Lighter
Rings
Security
Roomba
Iot design Manifesto I learned about at South by Southwest
You're going to enjoy it and I still can't get my SmartThings and Lutron integration to work
We'll have a message from our sponsor Samsung
And our guest this week is concerned who is with Hogan Lovells
Oh Law Firm
And she specializes in
Class action suit can we talk about
What the iot is going to do
For class action lawsuits and
Product liability and deceptive trade practices
She actually taught me a lot
Before we get
Another one of our sponsors
SSO
The world's top three automakers use wolf SSL to secure their vehicles and they aren't alone
Wolf SSL secure is 2 billion connections across a multitude of iot devices including Automotive
Connected home industrial military and medical devices with the Mirai botnet in the girl
Rolling threat of ransomware attacks on the Internet of Things companies have to pay attention to security or wrist litigation
Bad PR and their brand value securing the iot is hard but wolf SSL has he
Sperian specialized expertise to help
Shouldn't you be using both SSL to find out more
Visit wolf ssl.com and yes you probably
You should be using SSL because as we learned later in Today Show security is a big part of
Risk
Management
All right
Kevin
Stacy
Let's just get started with Intel
Three billion dollar acquisition of mobileye
That's huge well I mean not as Huges other Acquisitions until has made but I didn't
Not see this one coming and for those who are not familiar
Mobileye is in is really based
Company that started back in 1999 and
Their technology Powers a large percentage of
SA
Vehicles
That's what was using them for quite a while if I recall correctly
Yeah and then I know other automakers are
Are also using mobileye for their
Self-driving efforts but yeah
Deal
It was $63.54 per share
Which was a 33% premium to the prior day closing price for mobileye
That is up a chunk of their short-term cash they see you and I were looking at until
Recent balance sheet
Just before the show minutes it's almost like all of it
I think was 17
2.1 billion
Are cash and short term
That's not to say they can't raise me
More cash they can
We sell a lot
Or chips
But it's a big deal
Tide like
It's actually almost as big as their recent acquisition about Tara
Which was about
Two years ago that they announce the
Still I think it closed last year
And this was Intel spending 16
7 billion dollars
Company that makes
Programmable
Chips
So I'll tear with an F
So you guys might be looking at this
Hey Intel has just bought
Mobil ISO
Computer vision for cars
Then they also bought a company called movidius which was computer vision
On battery power device
And prior to that
Nervana systems which was all about AI
And there's a company making an AI chip but also an AI kind of software-as-a-service layer
And then I'll Tara so what's happening here is Intel is really try this time around 2
Get ahead of where it thinks
Computing is going
Can I just say
Spending a lot to get there but
I want that again I will never bet against it
Cuz they have money and they have
Know-how and
Brian krzanich the current CEO is just like
For a long time until was hobbled by a
It's dedication to x86
Picture witches
And now they're like
You know what
It's in the past
And when you say Havel they mean
It was always up for a large
Curative time until was focusing on
Processing speed and Power
Just at the time when we were looking at
Chip efficiency
Hence the rise of
Arm architecture and mobile devices which
Sure power is great in your performance
Empower a great but you need to be efficient because everything's battery-powered so
We kind of lost out in a large
Way on mobile
So far
What's notable
Is wise chips
Their IQ
Their chips are the IQ
They're basically
Massive supercomputing type
Power for doing
Computer vision
325 Watts
Really
It's not like
Cell phone
It's definitely loafers
Power that is
Pray I mean I think even Intel's Adams back
Time my last used one was probably more like a
5 watt chip
So
I think that
Yes Intel is clearly getting into cars in autonomous vehicles which is going to be huge
Ed koehn Ford
It's also just
Look at it as Intel continuing to invest in lower power
Computer vision
Or even lower power arcade
Rail
And for scope of the other potential here
Goldman Sachs has a projection for Advanced Driver assistance systems and autonomous vehicles
They're saying they expect that market to grow from about 3 billion dollars in 2015
296 billion in 2025 and 290 billion
20:35
Predator
View out and lot of things can change but
You can see why
15 billion dollar investment
Is chump change with a potential error
Now the question I have
Built its dominance on the fact that
The x86 architecture license
Inside out
Intel's now moving into markets where it's going to have to be
Competitive
This this type of silica
So
It will be really interesting to see
Howard
Only
Agreed and it's funny because it's competing against the same folks that are it's competing Us in the mobile market medicine video call, so
Citrus soap
It's not like it's competing against
Players here at the same
Players and you're right this is a different
Environment for until 2 to try and succeed in
So we'll see
In other exciting news
About
Kevin actually
Told me something today that had me
Oh my gosh
I have Associated a technology called lighter
With
Drive self-driving cars only self-driving cars
Forever Kevin shared with me that when he was gone last week he was doing
People with lighter
Before I talk about it I'll just
You might standard disclosure that I do work as a consultant for Google and it's actually work
I was last week it was working for Google at our Google Cloud next event in San Francisco
And I was Manning the booze for my area which is
Cloud devices and Mobility
And we had in that Booth I didn't realize it at the time or beforehand
We had a $25,000 lidar sensor there
Nami by velodyne
Which of the same type of sensor you see on the self-driving cars that unit sits on top and spins around
And so on and so forth
And yes you're my most people associate that with self-driving cars for obvious reasons
Put together a prototype demo
Of using lidar to basically instrument
A space that could be any space
Some of the ideas that we had we were sharing with customers were hey you could put this in
A retail store for example
And
You can then get a physical heat map of your store
Showing where people are walking you know it's late to traffic patterns where people are stopping and looking at product etcetera
Manufacturing in office environment
How many people are standing by the printer right now and why are they standing there is a problem with the printer or you can start gathering this type of
Space data and apply in totally different ways from the self-driving vehicle application
It's kind of interesting
Yeah that's the exact same sensor yeah we just had it mounted up high
And you know people are walking by it was tracking
Weatherlock hanging over there standing
There's no personally identifiable information which makes it a very interesting application so as opposed to a camera
Example in the store
You just see these wireframe stick figures essentially people
And whatnot but you can't really see who's who
So I think that's
A kind of advantage of a camera and
You think about the data that you're capturing a man
Tons and tons of data because these things take like seven hundred thousand
Pieces of data per second
Because that thing spins around there's multiple lasers in there
It's just
Amazing amount of data that actually
Generate so
I'm just an interesting number of applications that maybe people haven't thought of
I like it
Anakin versus Cameron
We might be having
Until the end
All right
So
If you have a ring doorbell
Because
This is a security challenge for the ring doorbell
What happened is somebody noticed that
Was heading to a server in
China
And they said
Why are some of my package getting diverted to China
And they wouldn't read it
They posted it which is exactly where I would go if I notice some highly technical
The response actually
To their credit the VP of security at ring answers
He basically said that the
End of a live color motion they lose connectivity
Occasionally
Rather than abandoning the entire call
They said the last few audio packets that are
Corrupted
A non routable address on a protocol that
No one uses
Okay
The plan is that they're going to update the firmware
So this doesn't have
And he talks a little bit more about why they're doing that kind of architecture design
What I don't think they talk about and what I imagine is also taking place here
Is ring uses a camera from China
Ring does not build its own
I'm wondering if this is something that was
Basically part of the camera architecture and they just for like
Don't mess with that we'll just leave that is it is
I could be I could be
It's interesting to me in and I hope we post the link to this conversation in the show notes because
Is this actually the whole conversation went on a lot longer than we have time to
Cover
There's a lot of back-and-forth
UDP packet
So long story short
Conversation went back and forth this was a technical user
Going back and forth with the VP of security at ring ends explained
It's a really good conversation and I'm glad that's person knew what she was talking about
Doubly glad that ring is finally said
Yeah we're going to take it from her since no longer happens
Yeah the point here is
When you are building connected devices
You are building
On top of infrastructure that is
Already in place
And you need to evaluate
Every piece of infrastructure
To create your product
Ridiculously hard
Or we need to come up with some sleep
Unified certification layers or levels
For each layer of
Kind of a product
You don't understand how this happened
Happens if your sourcing in a products from someplace and
Ear like this is good
Put it here
Yeah you don't know what's in the firmware
The point root beer need to see here
Is you need to learn
Exactly
Where your
Cloud-hosted service provider is
Is putting your data
You need to understand what kind of security practices accompanies you contract with
Having place
For example the connected
Teddy bear hat from a couple weeks ago
Part of the issue there was it the toy company had contracted with
An outside vendor to set up
Therap
Which
Relied on
A mongodb database that had it like 14 month old security flaws oh shoot
Right
You can't do
Black Sheep tattoo
It goes back to what we said many times if you're going to deliver a product or service
You have to
Evaluated from a security perspective from beginning to end an everywhere in between
That means every
Server touches
Every
Network
Part uses
Cameras any parlor
The databases
It all has to be secured and evaluated
And now we're going to add another layer into that be
Has Kevin found
Some crazy
Crazy research that puts the physical in the Cyber visit
Call security
Yeah I never thought of this but it totally makes sense so
University of Michigan
Research esthetician
Different research
Earlier this week
That shows that
How you can use
Sound frequencies
Kind of wants a hack but I'll say
Yeah
Creek
Accelerometers that are in common devices that we use everyday such as
Watches Fitness tracker smart phones Etc
I didn't make sense when you think about it
Because accelerometers I mean they're measuring movement
And sound waves do
Have movement
So what these folks did was they actually just
They use a $5 speaker
And injected thousands of fictitious steps into a Fitbit
Just by playing
Particular sound frequency
They also used a music file on a smartphone Zone speaker
To Pilot a toy remote control car
And he
They took a different music file and got the word Walnut spelled
Autograph
On a Samsung Galaxy S5 because of its accelerometer
I just never thought of it but sound waves are
Vibrating
Chinese memes
These accelerometers can be affected
Basically a meme is a digital component
Physical world
So the accelerometer is usually like tiny little Springs
The digital component Translate
The movement of Springs into
Footsteps or whatever
Whatever algorithm
The company is putter
Here it's just
Be somebody
Springs
What's crazy is if you know the types of algorithms used you could do something like
Fake a seizure across a wide number of the population
For example
Aziz accelerometers if they've got
Devices that track Falls right
You might be like Wyatt
Would that matter but then
Emergency resources someplace
Right
I don't know I don't think like someone
If I could but if I did
I guess that's that other layer that
And I don't know from a security standpoint how you would protect against that that's that's going to be challenging
Okay
So that was a little bit of
4r
Habits of Happiness we have any happy news today
I was at South by Southwest and I didn't do a whole lot of stuff there
Because
It was really raining in cold and terrible
I did
Design workshop for iot
Devices and I discovered the iot design Manifesto
Manifesto
And it was basically
In this Workshop we actually built
We designed it
In the one thing I notice there are 10 things to think about with Society design
Manifesto
Privacy of data there's a secure
Charity
Element
There is
Parties parties associated with an iot product
Explicit
If your
Send your data to someplace else that they're using
And all these are awesome but what I didn't see
Is
Anything about business model
And I thought that was really kind of
Huge oversight
Cuz I think
I say this all the time so you guys might be sick of it but
We don't know how without a business model
You can't
Allocate the resources you need to continuously secure something or you can't tell customers that their device isn't going to die
In
Because I think it is
A great
Start
So are you suggesting maybe they need to add something that says you know
If you're providing a device or service
Promise to go open source if you go under
Oh that's a good idea I don't know how to think of
If you're designing a business model you probably also want to think about like
If your business model is selling data Maybe you
Have to add a clause about how you deal with the
When you sell it
If you shut up you don't but if you do
Put the source code in escrow
I don't know I just thought you know it's worth thinking the nice thing is
If you guys think it's worth doing you can actually
Submit thoughts and ideas to these people and maybe it will
Captain
That was that
Which is my favorite store
They don't pay me to say that I just like store
A San Francisco location and an Austin location
They already have a Seattle
Palo Alto
But
They're coming to my state
For my house
Very nice
And it turns out they're already in Seattle you said
And I am going out to Seattle in June to run the Rock and Roll Marathon with my other podcasting but
My mobile tech Roundup show
Just to get in through the hole
His first marathon and I think I will have time to go visit
Because it is
In each store stocks differ
Devices I should say
You could you could go to one in one place and see
Certain devices
And then go to another place
Play something totally different
Cool thing is they don't actually care if you buy it there
There gold the companies pay to be in the store
And it's basically
Additional mark
Go try to be our
Let's see we also have everything
Which
Doesn't have any vowels in it
This is
I like you're not going to find this company if you search for it but it's everything
With no vowels in it except for that first to eat
Is an iot platform
Based out of Europe
Gotten 24.8 million in series B funding
This is an Enterprise kind of corporate platform
But it's got deals with like Avery Dennison which is bigger
Crown holding
And westrock
So these are all big packaging companies and what they do is make smart Packaging
Dave provide the platform
For these guys
Put
No NFC or RFID tags on stuff
Shipman
Monitor
Train Transport
It's platform is used to monitor things like
Where to buy citizen the shipment
It gives consumers product information if they
They want it
And it also sends data back to
Like when I buy my
Liverpool Football Club Jersey there's an authenticity thing on and I can scan that and register it so it sounds like that's one of the things I can
Theoretically do
I actually had a conversation with another company
There's some really cool stuff Packaging
And I think I'll probably be ready
Stay tuned for that
Feels like something we probably shouldn't
Talk about 2
It's a little nerdy not everybody
He's excited about the
Packaging
Let me just leave it at
You will be
Get air
Echo integration
This is only the 900 series which has a
Wi-Fi connection
App
The idea is that soon you'll be able to tell your
Or ask the echo to start your Roomba
Which is
Pretty awesome
I have long wanted
Fly my pretties
And have my Roomba go because I am
A strange person who
Deep affection for The Wizard of Oz
You don't remember seeing the roomba's flying around in The Wizard of Oz but maybe in the
Yeah they're they're like the flying monkeys all day
You thinking about
Bratz
Or track poop
Whichever
Depending on your situation
So
Roomba is been really vocal about this in
I'm excited
I don't know if it's
Reba spent a lot of time talking about how they can be
Rooms
But they're not lighter
Twitter
Sensors
But it is an economical
And sharing that information back to other products in the home
Because of where the Rumba is I'm not 100% sure how
Useful that's going to be a me the stuff my Roomba normal encounters isn't stuff
The whole lot
Right right
I'm thinking this could be
Maybe you want to vacuum is very specific room
Maybe you don't want to pick up the room by bring it in there at the Starbuck whatever
You can just
Tablet
You don't go vacuum the dining room
Gas coming over something
And it will learn what room is what room and and therefore through voice control you can
You can do that
Yeah and they're also saying
Since the Roomba knows what room is
The kitchen
Eventually
Yeah
Information to
Other devices and then you can just say turn on lights in the kitchen
And you wouldn't have to program it in your essay so it so that I get it so today like when I I have
Lights in my kitchen I have them specifically labeled as kitchen light so that my
Want to turn them on to have to say that but
Element that naming programming Park in the setup
Because the information of
Kitchen would be found through the room up raps
Everything to make life easier it's all good
All right
I feel like that's pretty good for this week
It wasn't a whole lot of news
The Neo Smart Car debuted at South by Southwest and it's pretty
It's far offs
We should mention this because we have a lot of people who like their echoes
AWS has
AWS promotional credit
It's for
She who shall not be named
Basically you're saying it's free for Echo and I'm just going to say instead of
How to say Echo
So it is now free for Echo Developers
Echo skills
Using AWS
And they're going to offer
You can apply to get
An additional
$100 promotional credit each month
That you know you encouraged
Use your scale says you're skilled
What happens if it's free to develop usually it's free for life
Like a small number of users but if it gets really popular
Which is fine
Is prison
This way
You can apply and get an extra hundred dollars in
From
I will put the link to that so you can
Can I apply for that
They're letting you scale
On the cheap or for free because what they're saying here is if your skill
Surpasses the AWS for usage tier you may be eligible to continue receiving promotional credits in
I think
To get pass at 4 usage tear it was 1 million AWS Lambda requests in a given month
And or up to 750 hours of the Amazon elastic Cloud compute or easy to compute time
So if you're still really takes off
Don't panic and think I'm going to have to pay a lot of money to continue scaling
Does not look like you will
Exactly you know this make sense they want to get developers on board
There's
Increasing competition
And if you have all the skills I mean cuz like if I've developed
It will work across any hardware that's also using that platform which is actually really cool because a lot of other companies are
Building devices that have
If we should make an echo skill that so you can just say
Her name and save play the latest iPod
So you can actually do
Play that latest I know you could actually
Play The Internet of Things
Because we are
Yeah
But I have been thinking about a recipe of the day skill which I think would be kind of fun
Or maybe it's recipe
I like that's a lot of recipes to come up with
I just haven't gotten to the point
Okay I'm ready to do an echo skill
But
I'm talking to the Amazon team tomorrow so
We'll see what happens
I have a complete
So
Lutron
And SmartThings integration between the two platforms where you can control your Lutron lights with
The SmartThings the Samsung SmartThings platform
Super excited
Because
I was like because which one is awesome
Samsung actually works with the Google home and
Currently the wink doesn't
Oh yeah
Now I can control more stuff for the Google home
Well
I haven't gotten a tour
So last week I told you guys that for some reason I was having
Itachi issue
In touch with me they deleted my account
SmartThings
So I could restart from scratch
That did not solve the issue
What was happening as I could
Connect
My Lutron
Bridge
To the SmartThings app
But when it went to this
Discover my devices
It didn't work
I kept getting an
Send that to them
An
They
The first was like okay
Try again
Because
Networks
It didn't in this case and then they they looked further they said well we don't see your buchon Bridges connecting
To the server
It doesn't look like it's actually connecting out to the intern
But
That's not true
I
Next ACT test
I was like turn off the Wi-Fi on my phone
Text my
Bridge turn my lights off
That sounds like
Nope it is connected
Soul for some reason
SmartThings doesn't see
Miley Trump
And I've now reached out to
Bouchon
Maybe next week
Cuz I really just want to test this integration
If anyone is experienced this issue and knows how to solve it
Please let me know
If you've experienced the integration and you love it
That's also a good thing.
She said I can tell
I can tell all of our listeners
Hey guys
Maybe
I mean I know I have a lot of stuff I always I always test the stuff it doesn't work
There there are more variables in your environment than most people's I will I will grant you that
But
I don't really see why this would be an issue
On this case anyone it feels like somewhere
Somewhere there's something getting lost
We'll see
Alright Kevin I feel like
Wechat
We should probably move on to our guest
Phoebe Wilkinson
Who is a partner at Hogan Lovells
And we are going to be talking about
Lawsuits and the internet
Stay tuned
For that
And now a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone this is Stacy and we are taking a break in the podcast for a message from this week sponsor this week
Sponsor is Samsung artik
And today we're going to learn about smart lighting and
Building automation
Friend Thomas
Let's just get started by telling me what Samsung is doing in smart lighting
What we're doing is
Connect
Different lighting devices
Aesthetic system
Silo's
Today
In the cloud
Imagine a building where your sensors and light switches your flight fixes Luminaires they're from different men
The factors to operate on different connectivity protocols
And they do not talk to one another
So what you do is
Build a platform that allows two
Connect all this device
McLeod
And interoperate with one another
And smart lighting is part of
A bigger picture
Actually building automation
Why are people investing in building automation
That's right lighting
Heart of building Automation in the building you have
Traditionally
HVAC systems UFC
Security systems of data center North Coast lighting system
All operating in
Silo's today
And by
Connecting these different disciplines
You can optimize the energy used in buildings you can also
Connect the lights
This remotely
And operator
Building
Any place in the world hangzhou smart
How do you bring this together
Using art
Brings all these different devices
Together such that third-party devices
Interoperate
One another
In one place
Securely
Easy onboarding
It's the one place that brings Hardware software third-party devices and services
Together
So that they can truly interoperate which is the true meaning
Off the Internet of Things
Now that I've taken my building automation
Thumbs all through Samsung
What kind of Roi
Yeah that's a great question so the ROI can be brought down to half a year
Maybe one and a half years which is significantly better than
The four years you have to have today
Traditional building management system
Consider that
Traditional building management systems you pay a minimum of $2 50 per square foot sometimes after
$7
Square foot
Modern
Iot
Base building management system you can bring this down
2 hours
75 cent
What's it about five times less than that of the traditional
Billy Madison
And this week Samsung
Has launched a new e-book
Unconnected lighting
It's called iot connected Commercial Lighting solution
7 questions for achieving optimal value
It's an insightful look on what it takes
2 connector lighting
And you can find it at www
Slash connected lighting
Remember that
Www
. artic
AR Tik
Dot IO
/ connected lighting go download it today
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy
And today I have a wonderful guest for you guys this is Phoebe Wilkinson
Who is a partner at Hogan Lovells
CD
Why don't you tell us
What your specialty
Thanks Stacy I'm just
Really pleased to be doing this podcast with you
My area of specialty is that I represent manufacturers of products
In court litigation or perhaps sometimes in arbitration
With a heavy focus on class actions as their litigated here in the US courts
Basically she tells people how to make things that won't get them sued
Is that a good summation
I do I try to make sure they do not get sued working with people you know as they bring products to Market but
Also to the degree the inevitable happens and they they do get sued
Routinely in their defending them and
Trying to make sure classes never get certified against my client
Exactly so I thought it would be really awesome to have you come on the show to talk about the Internet of Things
Because it feels like a really ripe area for
Gosh class action lawsuits
I see a lot of people talking about how the government is not regulating this area so maybe it will be regulated
Quartz
And I would love to just get your sun sign
Big picture
What role do you think the Court's going to play
Kind of making the internet of things a little bit
Maybe more secure
Baby
I don't know
More consumer-friendly
Given that these devices are so new and
Regulations always sort of lag a little bit behind
Technology and advancement that you often find that the courts when they're faced with lawsuit
It's often become the first area where where policy or laws or
Howa manufacturer needs to operate in terms of thinking about the risk
Of operating in the space that courts play a pretty big role
And shaping how we all operate before maybe regulators and legislators ketchup
Got it so when we talked to earlier you actually gave me this awesome history of class action lawsuits in the first I was like
Why are we doing this
But as you explain to me
This actually helps understand what's a class action lawsuit and what isn't
So I'd love for you to kind of explain that to her audio
Sure
So the class action
Mechanism in the tool really came about I want to stay in the 70s
And it came about for a very logical reason
So you had an airplane that unfortunately perhaps
Crashed
Or maybe a
Skywalk fell
Before they had the class-action rule in the procedure
Every person who was involved in the crash or the Skywalk that fell
They have to sue
The manufacturer or any of the defendants one by one and what someone came up with was you know what
I shouldn't really have to
Prove
That the engine was defective
But if there was a problem where there was a liability 230 times
I should really only have to do it once
Because if we know the person was on the plane
There's really going to be no question as to causation
The plane went down
Liability was determined to be the fault of
XYZ
And then everybody on the plane
You should get the benefit of all that work and not have to do it
230 * an individual lawsuit
That made a lot of sense
What's happened however since that time
Is that
Lawyers and even technology and products
Have started
Look to that tool and they said we'll meet him in it maybe I can use that tool for other loss
And at one stage
They were used against the tobacco industry against the Pharma industry
The world of el diseno that's really too many individual issues there so we can't really use it for those
Personal injury type cases
But then the next advancement was
Famous lawyers or litigants who said well
But I have a deceptive trade practice or disc
Deceptive thing that a company did
In connection with how they advertised
The product
Or whether they made it safe and reasonable for youth
And the class action tool is actually
Really the right tool to use in terms of an action
That goes after what those activities were
So for example
Do you secure your data
How do you use your data
What have you told people
And that is sort of I think the New Frontier 4
Manufacturers are people who are in the
In the world of Internet of things and just think about that because it does present
A challenge
Going forward but when I think that they can at least think about how to mitigate some of that risk
That was really helpful so that the challenge has become
Inks Lake
So deceptive trade practice that's things
I'm saying my device does something that
May not
Or maybe I'm overstating it
Abilities
Could it also tie into devices that
Consumer might have an assumption that they'll be around awhile but then they get
Richter
Turned off
This is actually happen
Find a lot in the internet of things with devices
That you know maybe the company goes out of business and they're not going to support it
Or music company gets acquired in the new company isn't going to support it
So
I really trying to figure out
What cases
Might come up
For class-action status
I think there's a variety of them and I think you've identified number
But think about a very sort of straightforward one
And we've actually seen this play out recently with respect to to a manufacturer of a smart device
Smart devices collect a lot of data
And
It's a manufacturer is going to do anything
Set data so for example maybe they'd like to
To sell the data
To companies that
Track advertising or track audience measurement
Or track the successive advertise
If the manufacturer of noctis
Closed
To the purchasers of the smart device
Hey I'm going to be collecting the data
And
You can opt-out if you'd like but also I may use that data that omission
Not telling a consumer about what you're doing with respect
To their privacy their viewing history
Whatever it is it the smart device
Does Tracking not telling them actually is actionable in this
Because every state
All 50 states
Pretty much have what they call a deceptive Trade Practices Act
All of them in essence a manufacturers
Or sellers of products cannot engage in
Deceptive trade practices which includes advertising
What you say about a product if it turns out not to be true or what you don't say about a product
Internet since that's my omission
Example and the danger of these
These statutes and the way they can be used very
Aggressively is that
Most states allow you to bring a class-action using that statute there's a few that don't
But they carry treble damages often
They carry the right
For the manufacturer
Have to pay attorneys fees back
To the planets
And in some instances provide
Punitive damages
So the stakes are very very high
And the actions you take as a manufacturer
Can very much be
Implicated because if you say something but you don't say everything
Or if you say something but you don't say it
Sweetly truthfully
There's a lot that can be done with attorneys who say that is a deceptive trade
It also frankly can come up with a to Securities if you don't secure the data
And you have a big reach that's not going to be a deceptive Trade Practices Act
Per se but they're either can be class actions
That are lodged against you for failing to
Secure the data that you've collected
In a way that is reasonable
In terms of your obligations to secure that data
Okay so we've got ate a security
We've got
This idea of decep
How to trade practices
Are there other issues
That
Might be risky
Kefir manufacturers of
Those are the primary ones if you're going to collect data you have to
Secure it but if you're going to collect data or if you're going to do anything with respect to the information that you obtained from your
Are consumers connected to
Smart devices you really need to make
Disclosures
I guess there is one other risk and it's not
Pacific to say a cause of action
But the reality is
That
Data izax it's not expensive to hold we know that these days right
It's pretty actually cheap to hold data in the cloud
But if you're involved in a litigation
And then you have to produce the data through the court process
That can be an exception
Soleus pain
Addition and severe say I think companies need to think about if they are going to collect data is
Do we really need to hold on to it for any particular period of time
In legal parlance we call it a document retention policy
Birthday tarp reservation policy
Where you sit beside you know what we really don't need to keep anything for longer than x years
Let's go a little crazy here
Because
What you're talking about artificial intelligence
And how people are using data collected off to train
Models in SoHo
That becomes really interesting be
Because the data
Is used to create
Basically a model that says like this is a dog this is
The cat this is whatever
R4 Leica camera
For example
And then that algorithm
Lives on four
Forever
And then it gets gradually retrained with more data
So if I'm thinking about like
Data retention
Do I need to keep the data that becomes part of an algorithm especially as algorithm start making things happen so a
Actually eating things
I may not get a notification on my security camera
If it thinks it's a dog
I'm in maybe someone breaks into my house because of that and I'm
Timeout money
Maybe there's a fly in there
Product
I don't know I'm kind of
I feel like it's a little far out there but then I'm also like
I don't think there's anything that's far out there and in this evolving world of smart data smart technology
And I think you've identified a lot of things
The people need to think about
In terms of the retention there's no question that if the algorithms that you have or any of the technology
LG
That you have that operate
It's the device
You're going to want to keep that right because you're going to want to make sure that you have the ability to always create the history of how we got there
And keep it updated
But there may be other data that you decide is not necessary to maintain in terms of the Opera
Recent
Of the business or the or the operation of what your business is doing or what you're looking at
And so it's that day that I was
Suggesting that they're up there can be instances where companies will not want to keep that data
Because it's expensive
Down the road if there's ever any sort of it
Disputes have to
Producent
But you're right there are there going to be categories
The data that you're going to want to hold onto
For the viability and for the progression of the business
Okay well that makes it so maybe they don't need to keep that it's my cat but they should probably keep the record that it
It's a cat
That is great
So
Let's think about
Disclosures because you've mentioned this
As a risky area for companies
I'm very curious because I buy a lot of connected devices and I
Click through a lot of terms of
Service agreements
Where a lot of these devices will say hey we're going to sell your data.
Make algorithms
And
Enough
I feel like when I'm clicking through a terms of service on a 4-inch screen on my oven or maybe it's the 2-inch screen on my
My thermostat and like
Is it really reasonable that I read a 40-page ulloa on
That particular time
I don't know
So
Any any thoughts there
I think if you want to be
Really
Prudent and manager risk
You consider identifying at the top
Of those
Documents
Or somewhere prominent right where and then user starting to use it
That the
30 page or the 40 pages
Contains
The following types of disclosures
And identify them by category and say
You have the opportunity if you'd like to opt out
And if you do want it
See more about this right away
To create that link that maybe they can go there right away
I'm a defense lawyer and I tell my clients all the time it is always safer
When you start out to anticipate the worst
And work backwards
And so if you think about ways and terms of the
Disclosures
That you make
The especially if you are going to
Use the data
Sell the data or you want to do something with the data that you capture
From a person smart
Device
I think it is prudent
To be pretty clear about that up front and if you give them the opt-out right and they don't
At least if there's ever a problem down the road
You can say if your face was some sort of a regulatory inquiry or a lawsuit
Hey I was very upfront
Early on as to what this document contains
I just closed it and I gave them an easy way to opt out
And they chose not
It does depend on the type
Of disclosure and probably the type of device
So your thermostat
It's probably not collecting
What people would consider what should be a
Private data essay
Your television viewing
Or either we have seen even recently there was some case involving
Data involving sex toys
So there are there's a
Whole spectrum of privacy
In terms of water
Particular device
My capture
The probably will also dictate the degree to which
You should make your disclosures
Very prominent
Does that make sense
It does so my sex toys they should probably be saying
We are collecting this information and we will share it
Also with probably my television or my Broadband viewing history
Maybe my thermostat
On the idea of opt out
This is always kind of irked me because I usually read these things and then I'm like
And to opt-out
You can not use our software or device
And
In many ways
That feels eminently reasonable especially when I'm
What is essentially a luxury
Thermostat
But
As we kind of put
Technology in four places it feels very strange like
If I buy a car for exam
When I sign into the app for the first time after I've taken possession of
The car
Probably not the best time to tell me I can opt out
Play not using
So I am very curious like
Do you think we'll see a shift in
Maybe when were offered an opt-out or how those might work
You raise a good point and I think we probably will and I say that because
In other areas
Where we have faced opt-out questions we have seen
The law of evolved to a place where you have to make it pretty easy for the consumer top doubts
The specifically I'm referring to
Mandatory arbitration
For example
The law has developed over the years where a mandatory arbitration Clause may have been buried somewhere
Are in a warranty document or in a manual
And then you know Court said no you got to be prominent about it and
What we saw was that manufacturers
Said okay will make the disclosure of the arbitration
Claws more prominent but we're going
To put conditions on it and say
If you return it to us
Then you can opt out and by the way there's a Reece
Restocking fee
And Court said no you really can't
Put a burden on the
Consumer if they want to opt out
Answer the manufacturers have been the most
Successful
Getting arbitration clauses
To be deemed valid or the ones who have said very prominently
There is an arbitration clause in this document
And if you would like to opt out please call the following number within 30 days of purchase
And so they've made it easy
For the consumer
They've made a reasonable amount of time 30 days and courts have said you know what that is appropriate
And if someone does not opt out by making a phone call in 30 days then yes
We are going
To enforce arbitration
So I can see something like that happening
With smart devices wear
If it's litigated
I suspected the manufacturers who make it easy
For someone to opt out
Are the ones who will see
The greatest success
And having
Chorus or Regulators say
That was a reasonable step
They didn't do so and so you were free to use the data
Thank you I'm glad that that might have
Because I I've been thinking a lot about that
I almost never give something up
Let's tackle one more issue that I think is really
I think
But we'll see what you say
A lot of these devices we're getting to a point where they're not just tracking data and notifying us there actually taking action
Action on our behalf
Something at things like
When I leave I program my door locks
Tlaloc behind
And this gets really interesting because like insurance companies are paying for people to put you know connected smoke alarms and things in their house
So
When you have a connected device
Styx
Controlling the real world
Does that introduce new levels of
Caution
Baby
Can you share a duties that I don't know the legal terms for these things but as a manufacturer what should you be thinking about
When your
Actually
It's a great Quest
And it's one that is undeveloped yet
In our legal system but I do think that
To the degree that say it doesn't work
Write your
House doesn't lock for whatever reason or becomes unlocked for some reason after it was locked for a few hours in
When you are away
And something happens
Or for some reason
The device doesn't give the warnings it's supposed to say it's a thermostat that actually operates also
So it's some sort of us
Security or fire hazard
I think there certainly is risk
That a manufacturer will face
A lawsuit in that regard for
Basically the product didn't work right or there was a malfunction and it'll go then to was it designed appropriately
Or if something happened
Remotely that
The company somehow there's something happened at the company that caused the device to
Turn off or to unlock
What were the safeguards
That were
Use of the company to make sure that that didn't happen did they have warnings had it happened before
And there you get into very straightforward product liability law
I think you're unlikely in that instance
Sia real class-action risk
Because those are one-off event
Is it a risk of liability for manufacturer sure
Because either now they're not just
And think about the old days they didn't just sell the product and they weren't they were done with it they're actively now interact
Staying with the product even while you use it
To the degree that it's connected and
To the manufacturer and that
Things are happening or not happen
Running right so it's
Created a relationship that's almost day-to-day
Goes beyond
The point of sale
With the the old way that devices
Where sold
So do you think it's going to be interesting to see how the law developed
In that regard
But I don't see that lending itself to class action
Treatment or risk
As much as I do
The security of the actual data
Disclosures Etc
That's that's over the large
Large pool of people versus individual action
And although
I could imagine if my connected pet feeder you know stopped working in
Till the whole bunch of cats
Interesting
In terrible
I should have terrible
Okay
TV I feel like I have learned a lot
Are there any other topics that you're like Stacy
Just for all the people making smart devices out here
You should also think about this
I think the big ones are
We started touchdown them indirectly but just
Assume as you go down the road of new technology and advancement and the more connected your
Becoming
Two people that you're nowhere near
I do think think about work
Work from the back what are the risks
What are the risk of something goes wrong what are the risks of what we're doing
And work backwards from what anybody see this
As a infringement of some
Sores that would cause
A whole bunch of people to be able to in one Fell Swoop say that we had done something wrong
And I think working backwards like that
It's just a great risk management technique and I think
Is important to always think about risk mitigation
And risk management
At the same time that you're evolving and developing technology because
The companies of Osteen get in trouble or the ones that things get too big too fast and sort of the infrastructure
And the thought process about how to manage risk and how to
Mitigate risk
Doesn't keep up with the Amazing Ideas in The Amazing advancements in technology
And that imbalance
Can just create
A lot of problems down the road it only takes one
You know bad class action or one really bad regulatory fine
Manele hits
Your bottom line in terms of whatever you have
Hey
But it's hugely disruptive to the company to go through that kind of
Litigation or regulatory oversight or regulatory investigations
And also you take a hit in the media and in all of those things I really think can be mitigated by a little bit of thought they had
All right so I made all your techno razzle-dazzle cheerleaders in your smart home companies also hire
A few Debbie Downer
First happens
Exactly
I never popular but you love them down the road when you realized oh thank God we put that clause in there the way that we did
There you go
Alright thank you so much for coming on the show The
Well it's been an absolute pleasure for me and thank you
Well that's it for this week's podcast to thank you so much for listening and remember if you want to know more
More about the internet of things please sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
See you next week