Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey
Higginbotham
Entrecote
Kevin tofel
And we have an amazing show for you today we're going to be talking about nest
CEO being at a job he predicts in Microsoft
Coming together for industrial iot
A new smart microwaves that actually has some cool features we need to talk about
Should you upgrade your Echo
UPS is taking on Amazon and we've got some Smart Lock
Plus
Self-driving car news
And later on we will hear from this week sponsor
Pharaoh and we're going to have our guests who is Mark Allen
Jacuzzi
Talking about how jacuzzi
Out of connectivity
Mm hot
Bubbles
Alright so
Let's get this started with a message
From this week's Ponce
This week sponsor is half Net podcast when you guy today's ideas into tomorrow's technology
Give me a lot of changemakers along the way to bring their stories to life out that is partnered with not impossible labs
Create a new podcast series about spectacular people harnessing the power of technology for the sake of humanity
Each week they'll reveal do life-changing technology in the story of how it came to be listen now to podcast
Not impossible to find the podcast on
Your favorite podcast app
Just search for
Not impossible
Okay
Kevin we're going to start the show with a disclaimer if you have a thing against
I think they're crows they may be Ravens
This is not the show for you
Because I am
I'm doing this for the Pacific Northwest and there is a very
Excited black bird that really likes
So you're going to hear it throughout the
He's a fan of the show obviously but
I have to actually add a disclaimer to
Before we talk about some of these thing I am currently doing some freelance Consulting writing for Google a
It is specifically with Eric
Chrome OS Enterprise team has nothing to do with iot but just wanted to mention that cuz we will be talking about Google today
So much Google
Let's kick it off with
Next CEO
Out
So
Marwan fawaz
Joined
Google in 2016 and took over as CEO of nest
Aetna
Plus
Is part of the reporting on the story we learned it
Google did try to sell nest
To Amazon
So lot of stuff here
Yeah it all comes back to the same
Central theme that many of us had when Google bought nest
2 / 3.2 billion dollars
Back in 2014
Yeah that fart was
They paid 3.2 billion dollars which is a lie
And ever since then that's has just never seem to
Fit for whatever reason from a financial standpoint Google has a new CFO as of 20
That's Ruth Torah and
Having worked at Google Underoos not directly obviously but Google is very much more held accountable for its finances
Now and
So that's an issue right there if Nest is not making
Enough money to
Recoup the investment
Shirley doubted us then you've got
The issues that
Adele had with Google and
We say he stepped down but I think he may have been forced out that's just my thought
Yeah because yeah his management style was
Google
Too much
And if you remember Google also have their own smartphone
Same time so they were like parallel tracks
Set development Tony was focused on developing this
Crazy new thread protocol
Right and it wasn't focused on products
And they were forced to integrate Dropcam
It just it was naughty
Copacetic
So he was forced out
Then
Well and then
Marlin came along and they put him in charge but as we're finding out he really wasn't around that much he lived in
Denver and the nestings in Palo Alto I believe
So there's some rumbling on that fact
Change in leadership may be the leader
Vision is an issue or wasn't if I don't know all-in-all what's happening hours
As you said I wanted out
And the
Nest team is now moving under the Google home and living room area
We just part of Google Hardware which is run by
Marlins
Motorola Powell Rick osterloh
So Nest should be under
In my opinion
The Google Hardware division
Because I need to be sharing the information and their efforts and projects with all of their hardwood addict
Cohesive line of products right now they don't I mean I still can't
Use Google home with certain Nest products for sale
Sample minutes
Weird yeah and nest
Had been pulled back in February that's was pulled back
Talking to
Google from an alphabet company
From being its own independent alphabet
And so this change that because if you're going to be pulled back in as a hardware company
Google you don't need your own CEO so this makes sense
It also made sense back when they
Hired
It felt like they were going to try to sell nest
Figure out what
To do with it
So in some ways this is good news for people who love nest care because it means that Google is not going to try to sell
They're just like okay we've got it
How to make the best of it
Start pulling all the stuff
So I agree with you there I can't help but wonder what would have happened if Amazon had bought it
Then we'd only have
Yeah I did I don't know & Shirley
Plank
And Ringwood
I'd still be there possibly be their own entities that I don't think they would be purchased by Amazon at this point they only
Right might have blank
As blank I think was much more of a hardware
Technology Center staff
Right here we go
Give so that's the latest on desk
As if you owned a scare I think this is good news
One more time
3.2 billion.
Okay I'm done
Remember that he D fun days
All right
Let's talk about Industrial iot
GE
Microsoft Cloud
So I talked about Microsoft Azure 4 years it is
Top cloud of choice for people building
GES
Decided
So they are going to be pulling together much more integration between the products appliances and software in
Services
And software
You're going to have more integration between Microsoft Azure Analytics
Azure iot
This is
Part of an ongoing seeing that we're seeing in the industrial iot which is
All the Defenders have realized
There's a couple realizations one
They realized
Way too hard to pull all the stuff together for
Companies that are not used to dealing with I
So GE has to work harder
Original GE was like
Hey we can do the it side too and they were building
Critics cloud and all this crazy stuff in
That's gone
So they realize that they should let it guys do the it
Do the industrial not stop
Work together to create the
Really tightly integrated pack
About calling this an end-to-end solution
But in this case it actually works
So that is
WhatsApp
We're seeing it happen all over
We're seeing companies like sap and
Sazon
Xeomin
All of them
Tying at these Cloud assets and even doing so
Some Partnerships
Vertically specific companies as well
So it's a big deal
Is another
For Microsoft
Credibility in the industrial
End
That's what this is
I don't claim to be an expert in Microsoft Azure cuz I'm certainly not
That's not anything I've looked at in detail but one thing I did note in here and I don't know how true it is or isn't but one of the other benefits for
GE is to enhance the product
Platforms
Security layer
Thrasher
So that is always a good thing assuming that is true
Alright we'll speaking of GE we're going to move from their industrial stuff making jet airplane engines and all that
It's tough to
Their home appliances
They announced on Tuesday that they had created the GE smart
Microwave
This is a microwave
Is wifi connect
And is integrated with Madam
You basically can scan
3000 different microwavable products from Hot Pockets
Studio Cuisine and it will automatically know the instructions
Cooking time
Is popping in the microwave
Start the microwave
And then poop
What's amazing about this
Historical price
That's what Kevin thinks
The price is 125
Actually the MSRP
Which is the manufacturer
What is actually
Suggested retail price
There we go
So MSRP is 139
So my God
Oh you got to keep going
You feel like this is a
I think this is a great College thing although her college requires you to rent the microwaves that they provide but that's a whole nother
Absolutely I mean it's not a huge microwave at 2.9 cubic feet so
It is perfect for like a dorm
And
Yeah yeah I made it
And it's also not expensive
No it is
MSRP is 139 and then
As part of prime day they did a deal where they bundle this with
An Amazon Echo dot for 125
Now that's a visible
That deal will be
Today is not Friday
But it's pretty sweet
So here's what I'm excited
Kevin is rightly excited about the price but I'm excited because it's going to have What's called the
Cooking and time
Controllers with
Matamata
So consumers will be able to
Directly to her
Without using GE
Appliances
Basically natives
Cooking and time controller
Where's the Amazon has now added
So you no longer have to say
Anime
Ask
Geneva
To start the microwave
If you could just say Madam a start the microwave
So this is
Huge
I agree
Is signals one the creation of a new type of
Native skills
Matamata
Intuit signals that GE recognizes that asking Geneva for stuff is sucky
Well now I wonder I wonder how many other
Partnerships will come about once people start
Enjoying the fact that they don't have to name the skill and their command
What's up that's what I like
SP exclusive to GE
Opportunity for Amazon
This is just become
Everyone else could use it
Number two is that Delta faucet is working on an
Amazon integration
4 faucet
Which means you'd have native
Support for
Turning your wife us
We talked about that last
So a lot of Hope in my heart that Amazon is
Trying so hard
To become the standard Slayer
Smart home and
This Market
J&D time if they can come up with standards that will eventually let's say
Have met him a work with
All
Madam a enabled voice services
Not have a skill for it all just have a API layer that will work with different brands and so I'm behind the scenes
That could be big
So not only is a microwave cool but how you talk
Speaking of the echo
Kevin
Do you want to upgrade your Echo
I do not
However that is a question we
Commonly hear from Friends colleagues and countrymen and women around the world and
I feel like we should give us
Special shout out to
We should he's in your backyard there because
Season
Washington State
Our old house
Yeah probably
Mr. Chris Albrecht who has
We work for them in the past to go home and
I know he's doing some podcasting work these days as well
It hasn't been
For a while but
Every once in awhile mr. Albrecht
Ping us and say Kevin Spacey
Can I get a new Echo is it time to upgrade my ago
Is there a new Echo coming out
Checking account now
How about now
So
Yes I'm making fun of course but it's actually a valid question and Rye Crist over at CNET
Poses that question in an article that both looked at before the show
I don't know let me try make some good points I mean you have to understand if you're going to buy a new Echo then you are
Committing further to
Being in the Amazon Echo
And that's fine
That's totally okay
Security guard
Without a doubt you and I are both happy and as are many other people
However
I like flexibility and I'm glad where I pointed this out
That's why I was kind of hot on the Sonos one because it came with Madam a
Out of the box
But he's also getting
Google Assistant
At some point this year.
Plan it did recently get AirPlay 2 as well for
Controlling music
Interior
IOS device by voice
With Siri but so I'm not interested in upgrading my echo I would still have an original one and
Any
.
And I'm fine
I don't see the need
Even the newer one with the Hub is just liking some radios for me so I can know thank you
And that would you recommend they buy this
-1 is a
If you have nothing
I would say yes but
Cause you're not locked in
21 platform
If you want to be on the matinee Amazon platform you can do that today
If you decide I might get some things that might work better with
Google Home Products
Then
Can I give you an out
You can have both
That's what I
Confusing
Okay so yes and I have the original Echo that I bought
December of 2014
It still work
Sounds good
Why is making the point that maybe Amazon should update it
Is the market has changed significantly but I actually don't think
I think it's better that it hasn't changed significantly because it just becomes this based of ice that sits in your home and can
Controls everything
That's kind of the point of having software-based update
One of the benefits
Connectivity
So hungry. What should they upgraded to any women that have had newer versions
Come out they have upgraded it yeah so he's saying they need a new flagship line I say no this is like
It's almost becoming an appliance in your home that you just set and forget
Parks
I would like that a lot
All right
Let's talk about
Where Amazon
UPS
Is taking on Amazon key
Sort of
You want to talk about
Yeah UPS
Has announced that it's got a pilot program with latch
Smart Lock
4M building deliveries
To multi-unit homes AKA apartments in such in New York City this is a trial program pilot Pro
Basically it's very similar to the Amazon key in that you know if you have a package and you live in it New York multi
Home UPS can now get in and leader package
It's not going to leave your package in your apartment
Or you're living
SpaceX
Just leave it in the building
So it's kind of limited in that regard it's not meant for single-family home such as what Amazon key is doing with their cat
Ameren Smart Lock and door there
Access to vehicles
Trunks as well so this is very limited by comparison
But it's a start
And it's great for this user
So I wrote about this
Does company
UPS working with the idea here is
There's a lot of apartments that don't have dorms
I went to New York City I had a
So
Apartment building
But the apartment building basically did not like a bail closet
You can
Get it and get your package
But the time comes
I think it's great
Is going to be useful for a lot of people
I'll have the traditional
Family homes
And it's a beauty big deal for latch
What is a startup
And
So I think it's really
I like it
Yeah two things come to mind one
I never knew you lived in New York City
I live here right after college
I didn't know you were deaf
To this could extend to other delivery services I'm thinking like pizza Chinese food etcetera
Is very common
Yes yes yes
The latch door locks they control access in and out of public areas in these apartments but they also
Can be placed
Residence
Stores
As well
So what can happen there then
Is this could go further
UPS probably doesn't want it to go further cuz they don't want their delivery guy having to go down an apartment making all these deliveries that seems
Crazy when you dump it in the mail closet
But yes
Spur
Service providers
Pizza delivery whatever
Grocery deliveries
You could say latch has a foot in the door
All right also in the luck news World a similar startup this is a startup called open path they just raised 20
Million dollars in
Instead of residential locks you guys are providing
Smartphone-based access to building
Offices
So they are
Very similar except
I think of it kind of like August
It's partially because I went to Oz
Blocks
Officers when they were starting out in these guys give
Smartphone access to
A building so the say instead of having your like
NFC card
RFID Card
Whatever
I've only worked in one building where I've had a card
Situations
But this election
Large amount of money
Doing this for
About two years
So it looks like
We're kind of slowly upgrading our access infrastructure
And we actually have a lock
Related question and I are listening to voicemail a little bit later on the show I just want to point that out because
There seems to be a very big difference between industrial War office Enterprise locking and unlocking
I'll leave it at that for now
Yes
Okay find a lot story for you
August
Says it has
1 million users
Users
Users not
Customers with law
Yale locks sold
So
I don't have an August lock on
But I am technically an August user
Because I have a
And my husband is also a user
Because he is
Are you sure on that doorbell as well so
We are at least 250 million with our August doorbell
The question is
How many locks
All right it's a milestone for them for trying to downplay but I'm trying to keep it in perspective as well
Yes and Nesta sold more than a million
Mystats we found out that the Arlo geyser
Just sold more than 7 million Arlo products
Sonos devices
So what do you think about those numbers in the context of the us having a hundred million households about 310
10 million people
You know the Smart Home
Got a lot of room to grow
We're not yours
Speaking of the August doorbell Apple Insider has noticed
Apple his
Purge the doorbell category from the homekit
Accessories
And it is indeed
True
So it suggests that
August and ring doorbells that
We were promised to give us homekit support which meant you could open the home app
And see what was happening on those devices
It seems that may not happen
This is a big deal for people especially on the ringside because the ring folks have been
Promise homekit support
4 years
And they've just never gotten it so
Apple has not commented yet
On the story it is unlikely that they will say anything substitutive because it is
But this is worth noting if your
NFL fan of these doorbells and homekit
I'm a little surprised that apple
Elvis just wondering what they had in mind because it is not like them to have a suite of products and have a gap in that sweet
Yes but it could be that the security implementation for homekit just doesn't work on basically what is a battery pack
Powered wifi-connected device that supposed to
Glassboro
It does feel
Wired
I don't know if you could be power that is you're absolutely right I kind of feel like Apple
They want Simplicity with their protocols but as a result
They have limiting options
Okay
Moving from
Locks
Let's talk about
Cars not the movie but cars that we drive or the drive us I had not heard of this company
I'm about to talk about Bruce Lee
It's called
Zoosk
I hope I'm saying that right it's a z
Oox
Basically it is a startup
That believes autonomous cars should be built
From scratch applying sensors and everything else that we need all the smart summer planning
You currently available vehicles
Is not the way to go it's a very radical take
He was a very good profile on this company and the CEO
Add Bloomberg to learn a lot from reading it
They're basically trading robot taxis
Autonomous taxis the ticket of very different approach again they are filling from scratch
And
It's a bidirectional
Taxi it literally we can go forward or backwards at the same speed so that's kind of unique in some sense
Compared to today's traditional cars they have to do other testing with
Currently available cars that can tow
Put their own cars on the road yet because I just don't have
Penis look like
Sand dune buggies right now just frames essential
It's very interesting though they're going to have the sensors actually communicate to other cars
Are there drivers I should say
With a long LED strips and such
To suggest that hey there's a problem further up ahead that I noticed you should be aware of it or
I'm going to make a right turn now and
It's all clear ahead of me Etc
It's just a unique take on things and
Kind of interested to follow
Especially because they really stepped out
Not about papers 800 million that was the other big news for them 500 million in early July
Very recently
That is an evaluation of 3.2 billion dollar so clearly the investors
Support them and see Vision here
It'll be interesting follow
There's a huge Market
A huge market for a delivery vehicles for
Industrial
Self-driving car so why the heck not
Alright also in the car world
Light
Which is a camera company has just raised another big round of funding 121 million
Self-driving cars
Yes light is
Probably better known if you know them at all that is
As a camera company in their camera looks like a smartphone innocence but it has
16 different sensors and lenses
And most smartphones today at best come with
Maybe two rear facing cameras this has again 6
The reason they do that is because they use software and AI to create the best possible photo using
16 different viewpoints in a sense and sensor for me
All of these sensors
And it's really a cool idea that camera alone is $2,000 again for 500 smart
Price on DSLR like that it's just a handheld
$2,000 intelligent camera
The weather doing has
And why just raise money
They are planning to sell the camera technology
Tu connected car
Companies because a lot of these car companies are using I would say off-the-shelf camera components but they're using things that are red
Readily available lidar obviously is not something that I would say readily available and inexpensive
But from a camera perspective
There's not a whole lot of amazing new technology being used in can I see cars
So this could extend the vision capabilities of are connected cars which in turn would obviously given more information at be
Smarter and perhaps even cut costs
Because maybe they would need to use as many lidar and other sensors
Wow that would be
Pro getting rid of light
A $10,000 Tesla
Okay
So that was our
Smart Car news
Kevin you want to talk about the ticwatch
I do we don't talk about too many wearables these days just because that market seems to have slowed down in terms of energy
Vacation but there is
The ticwatch
Pro is now available and it is an Android Wear OS smartwatch
Personally I'm not a fan of where OS I got away from the Android Smartwatch platform once
Start use a nap a lot to me and I just was more consistently
Stable for me added features usability was better Etc
So I think Google has a lot to do with wear OS
However the ticwatch pro is
Kind of unique in that it sells one of the major issues with wear OS watches that is battery life
So what this device has
It hasn't what you'd expect like a 400 by 400 resolution OLED display
But on top of that
There's an LCD display that's
Transparent
So
It has two modes one isn't always on mode with that low-power LCD display that can show some basic information and the other
OLED display
For using you don't certain apps that work
Android Wear OS wechat music app store
Exercise app
And so on so
What does does it really resolve the whole issue of really poor battery life cuz I have not found it
Two or three day battery
Life watch with wear OS
Typically Monday at best
I just buy Apple watch I can sometimes get too so I don't want to you know too many conclusions there but
You can go for days and days on this two days on Smart Mode when it switches back and forth between the displays
Multiple days
30 days and just what they call Essential mode
So that is the LCD watch face always on
So it's a nice balance I thought it was an interesting use of Technology
So
Good news on a possible watch Aldo
Android Wear but you also have
Yeah real quick little Pro tip if you have a Fire HD device the current one the tablet I actually have one so this is how I feel
Found out with a software update
I was a week or two ago the Amazon said hey we could have Fire HD tablet charging stand
And that will turn your tablet into an Echo Show when it's
In this
Turning Stone
Will turns out you don't need the stand
You just need to have your tablet plugged in
And I found that out again through software updated explained all that to me so
I have a case that doubles as a stand for my tablet I just leave it in there and plug it in and now I feel Echo Show capable
Without having to buy Amazon
Starting to see how you feel about
Special capabilities I'm not 100%
I never was sold on it to see if it wins me over
There you go
All right
Thank you for that Pro tip and now
Let's get to other tip
Basically in the form of the iot podcast listener
Star hotline
So this hotline is brought to you by
Slate
Don't miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wi-Fi
This month
So you'll enter to win by calling us
6 to 3
7 4
24 and leaving us a question
You have to do this before the end of
Dual ISO midnight ET
On July 31st
Remember
Smarter homes
Start with
Schlage
Okay this week's voicemail is from
Rob
Hi Stacy this is Rob Lowe in Chicago
We are doing a commercial build out of her office spaces and looking to do some kind of Bluetooth
Door lock for both our offices as well as other folks in the building
However
I know a decal won't work
Ana commercial space
Need to be able to push it open
From the inside
So wondering if there is a commercial version of a
Schlage archival or anything like that
Thanks have a great day
Rob
This is a good question
Really glad you asked it
And we came up with a couple Solutions
You're very expensive
One of them we think is actually probably opt
Which is buying a
Bluetooth lock
From a company called
Ultraloq that is ultraloq with an l o q
Actually if you have a deadbolt this lock won't work because
It
Cover up your Deadpool
So this is waterproof so you can do indoor and outdoor
You can use a fingerprint
A cold
Or a key to unlock but you have to
To pick a fingerprint or a code you can't do both
And it is Bluetooth enabled so that means you can't do it remotely
Does wifi bridge but
People seem to like it except for the fact that they don't love the
Functionality so I would say go key code
Yeah definitely that would be the way to go get rid of biometrics
So that you said say say this does not require attack it won't work or the Deadpool it works with a traditional lock
Door strike
Doesn't look like it belongs in an office because it's
Satin nickel hits
Believer and
Battery powered obviously because
No power to your door
And it's only 199 from
Smart Home
Cam
Which I think is pretty reasonable considering this is really a very unique lock and that its Bluetooth without a deadbolt
Oh and I saw its
145 99 on Home Depot
Who was out there you go there you go it does work with Android and iOS
And with the app
You can knock on your display screen if you have IOS
Or you can shake
Your Android phone to unlock on either one of those platforms
Mexican Andy
Until
Any other weird
Category
I don't even know how to think about this
There is a
Comedy called haven
Is Hayden lock.com
And this is instead of a
Door lock
This is actually
Bar that you either screw into your floor
Beer fluoride
Little unclear about the install there in this bar actually has a little
Thumbs up
Pops in front of your door and prevents it
From opening so this is smartphone tested
This works with a smartphone
And
I don't even know what to say
Save-A-Lot when it's unlocked when it's unlock a little pop-up art is down into the base of it and the door can freely
Is Bluetooth enabled
When you
Want the door lock that little section pops back up
It keeps the door from opening it's been interesting it's like a
Extending the Seal of a door
Are door frame
And just having something that blocks the door from opening so
You can step on it to lock it
Kind of interests
But it's not cheap
And it is kind of odd
It's 349
So is this is important to you and I can't imagine how this gets installed in carpet but
If this works for you and you like to look at this it's
They say it's 10 times stronger than a Deadpool and it sort of makes sense because a deadbolt is rather small compared to the large Center
Pop-up section of this that has more surface
Knots to the door
Yes they do have a tape
They have a tape install
So you use
3M VHB tape
And 3 m is like
Secret winner in this market
You guys I mean how much
3M double-sided tape have item play them
For me it's command strips but that's because a lot of things are temporary for test
Yes so those are the options
I also was looking because I saw this in this house
Fairly common
I think I saw it at csrc. But a magnetic lock that
They're basically electromagnetic
Things that you use to replace your
Lock cylinder and then also the key stripe
The inside of the door frame and those basically when you
The clothes when there's electricity running through activating these magnets
And then
Turn off my electricity and then I can unlock the door they do require
Power and they also I didn't find anything that was bluetooth enabled
So you may look for something like that if you
Do you have like an existing smart home system cuz a lot of
Companies offer that but otherwise and that's actually cheaper you can buy
Something to replace you
Door cylinder for like 60 bucks
Assuming you have liar power available to the door
Yes
But you got to have power in
It's not going to be blue
So those are the things we found
And
Hopefully
Actually call us back let us know what you chose or if you hate all of your apps
That does it for this segment
The show
Stay tuned for
Mark Allen
Jacuzzi he's going to talk about how
Company
Has connected their hot tubs
What products be used and a lot more
In the meantime
Here's a message for this week sponsor a pharaoh hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's I
Iot podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is a pharaoh and I have a pharaoh CEO joke
Albert here to talk to us
So let's start with what is
A pharaoh Pharaoh is a fully upgraded fully Interactive
Fully secure sensor to Cloud iot platform
Our customers choose a p
Because they can cut down their time-to-market by as much as 80% which cuts down on
Cost and
Complexity
The affair of service and how they can reuse 90% of their work
Project in consumers love how easy it is
Just to get their devices connected and how fast and responsive they operate
UK and last week we talked about the work that you've done with Kenmore at this week we're going to dive deeper into the security you guys
So tell me about your secure
Security is a big deal and it's only going to get more important both for businesses and consumers
The challenge though
Is the iot is an end-to-end kind of Technology
And so is secure
Jamaica
He trustworthy
Not only do you have to
Secure all of the data path
But you also have to see
Your identities
Build security with
Resilience and then you also have to secure the manufacturing process
Supply chain
So what is it mean to be able to ensure Trust
Throughout the supply chain
If you think of your PC
And their firewalls also
The place in malware still continues to get
So we know you have to go
Beyond secure data path
Devices
Don't have a lot of love
Processing power
So we really need a different strategy
Compared to the PC or smartphone
Also have a much longer life
PC and you have to ensure
Did their secure
5 years 10 years 20 years on this will be the next Battle Ground
When you have to go beyond just securing
Potato Patch
Formatting mine
Text one
Building Trust
Kitchen Hardware
In the right place is in the process and to
Integrating them into the rest of
Decentralized iot stack
Across multiple
Protocols if you're using a communication protocol built on TCP IP this is relatively straightforward
But if you're using something else like Bluetooth
It's not straight
To dress this we came up with two very useful inventions
One something that we refer to as an
Estem
Coyote
This is similar to the SIM card in your smartphone but it's a hardware root of trust for
The device
Second
Something we call VPN for iot what are the shortcomings of
Historically has been that it works only over TCP IP network
So this is not totally appropriate
Propriety
We've developed technology that overcomes these
Okay so in practice how does this process work
There's a hard word of trust
It's built in a secure facility that enables us to build the rest of the system at not secure facilities and then we use that
Cryptographically
The device is who it says it is when it connects
That sounds great so where can we go to find out
The best place is a pharaoh. IO
/ gobig
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Mark
Alan who's VP of it
Add jacuzzi
Hi Mark how are you doing
Good how you doing Stacy
Man I have to say I'm really excited because
Where can we talk about connect
I also
So before we started recording I learned a little bit about hot tub
I'm going to give you guys the same
Benefit so
Mark briefly tell us
The journey that you guys are on a Jacuzzi when did you launch your connected products and
Refit on why
We've been looking at this iot Plaza
For quite a while back when it was you don't machine-to-machine and trying to figure out when the right time was to Diamonds.
No pun intended but we wants the initiative back
In June of last year
And it was a really quick production cycle
We dedicated a few people from the company and partnered with particle
Man from Jason partner perspective
And a very rapid implementation
Cycle
And launched our first product went down a manufacturing line in November of last year
Wow and you now told me that they're like
500 of these guys
Out in the fields that are
Thousand out in the field
And half of them
That's correct
Yeah we're still names
Itsy bitsy. So far as
Phenomenal
So we're going to talk about what you guys have learned from this we're also going to talk about the
The process of
Connecting these things
And get into why
So let's start with what are the benefits for a consumer
Who is buying a connected
And then what are the benefits for
Yeah from a consumer perspective we've had an Apple mobile app
In the past
That you can control your hot tub
And that's obviously the first dentist said if it connected hot tub is sick
Consumer can control their hot tub
So from a vacation
Homer some
Monster on their way home
From work and they want to eat the hot tub up a couple of degrees
Let's ready for when
Make it home they have that obvious
Above and beyond that
The true iot hot tub
They get the additional benefit of the hot tub unit
Communicate back
So maintenance reminders
I have to replace
Filters
As well as
The ability to
To get air noise
Application so happy
Don't forget something
What's wrong with that
That are notification
To them as well as
Comes to us
As well as notified
Local dealer so action can be taken on the
And your initial thought maybe
How important is air notice
Vacation in a hot tub
But with a hot tub is in an area where it freezes and it's a vacation home
Someplace that you don't
Visit on reggae
Basis in a power goes out
Or iot device
Asus battery backup
Got that your notification
Because now you only have a certain amount
Time to drain a hot tub or restore the power
Before damage
So the dealer or the
Consumer can take Act
Prior to damage
Wow
Okay I'm like sitting here
Like I know nothing about
So you guys sell your hot
People not
Right here we have an independent dealer Network and we still are hot tubs today in Des Peres theater
So some of your thousand
Connected hot tubs are probably sitting around
Inventory dealers as opposed to
Consumers not coming
Yeah it's true it's the right now we're in the process
Assuming those hot tubs.
What's the dealers in Salinas
Supply chain so all of those hot tubs 1000 hot tubs
The $500 right now
Disconnect consumers backyard and the other five
Okay so let's
Talk about those 500 hot tubs what have you learned so far I don't know if you've seen a lot of Arab
What do you learn from
The 500
We've learned quite a bit about the process of iot
So we are on probably our I would say 8
18 Federation
From lunch
I've just fine-tuning ever
Everything from
The firmware upgrade advantage
Price of doing coyote
Keep us on the way we did it is
Firmware
Servicing from the firmware to the
Marshall application
So we've learned a lot about her
Consumers in the we're also
Have just launched
In-app purchasing
So the idea being that when a maintenance notification is given to a user
Result
Replacement for example we know exactly which
Hot tubs
Summer house
So they don't have to hunt around about which filter fits their hot tub when they get a maintenance notice
Application that they need a filter replacement they can immediately click on to
And they are directed it exactly
It is that through the dealer or is that Direct
ESO
The way it's set up today is it
Direct from us and then we do a pro C
Feedback to their local
In the future we'd like
Like to set it up
The point where it seems
Soaked through the dealer and then they will also have an option
Pick that up in there
Okay cuz this is a really interesting
Conundrum for many
Companies when they're dealing with the dealer Network
And attract
So how did you guys approach your dealers
When you were watching this in
Cut them into
The process
I don't know what
Is it still important in this day and age to have
Yes absolutely important for us
A couple of different
This one is our dealers not only seller hot tubs
But they also service
And then from a tumor perspective hot tub
You know it's an important
Purchase it says
Significant
Much like a
So we encourage our can
Somerset actually do what we call wet
Physically go to a dealer to sit in a hot tub into a wet
Hot tubs are very different
Not only by brand but also by model
To encourage them to go into a dealer and actually do a wet test
Before they purchase
So do you or critical in that sense and they also are the ones that
Do the actual answer
Installation of God
To the approach
To our dealers was at this
Benefit the dealer from being able to
Provide
A connected hot tub and then also from a dealer for
We give the dealer a portal that enables them to
Co-star
Disconnected hot tubs
What's the status
And then also any error message
Respect
Station quickly
CNE hot tubs
Have errors and then they can also run remote
So from a dealer perspective
Huge fan
In the past they would get a call from
Consumers
And they would roll is an was going to everything in it
I hoping that they have
What's needed
Now they run remote diagnostic
Annie's got a pretty good idea what's wrong with
Hot tub before they go out
And I bet there's actually some really interesting things
I'm assuming type Geographic
Custard so if I sell
I got X number of hot tubs in my service area
There's like
If it's going to freeze break
You could send out a friendly warning
Establishes relationship
Ongoing relationship
That's exactly
And what about you guys because I know in some Industries like the insurance industry freaks
Temple there is also
It's not exactly a dealer network but there's there's a middleman and they're looking at connector products
Bypass them but get more information on their customers and understand what they need and establish a direct relationship with
Securities if you're looking at
Doing that somehow
All is well
We see the value in the data
Right so yeah that's
Phenomenal
Solana park for eyes
So looking at the data.
Coming in from all of us
So in the past
Any data that we were receiving
The hot tub was warranty
You type data in that warranty dated
Was coming in
From a
Technician that was out in the field and repairing a hot
And say hey here's what it heard in
Right to his only when we receiving date it was
And that was a human interaction
Certification for
Now the day that we're getting in the hot tub
Is not only errors but it's also any type of that
Activity that's going on in
Hot tubs we can see FaceTime temperature how much the
Just turned on how much
Turned on when there are errors week
Correlation between
Between those errors
And other things that are going on in
Hottub usage temperature all kinds
So the data for us
Scream lyrics
The other part of it too is
Nunnally correlation
But then also
Future product
So in the past we would go out with
We would survey
100 users
Hunter customer
What's important in a hot tub
Now we have that data and it's not only a hundred.
Will eventually be Oliver
So will definitely Drive
Product
And that's a
Huge mean that the value of that is
Unbelievable
Oh yeah and a lot of people tend to say oh my gosh that sounds amazing I would totally use that
And then
Okay let's talk about the process a little bit
When you guys made this decision you said you worked
Particle
I mean it is not as simple as saying
Someone calling up and saying Hey I want some iot on my Jacuzzis
You're like who talk to you about this wear today
Order come from and how did you start approaching this as a
Problem to solve
Yeah like I said we had a review of some application mobile app
Controller Hut
And
We had been thinking about doing some type of connector
Hot tub
So we were looking at doing long before we knew really what I was he was
Thinking about doing a machine-to-machine kind of
And we've been thinking about that
3 years and we had approached two different companies
Thanks for doing something like that and it had just never found
The Wright company
Need a partner with
And then we actually was our CEO had that I think
Been sitting on a flight neck
To one of the CEOs
Vertical and just had been talking
About it and that sparked interest
And that's what beginning
Discussion
In the particle partnership was it just was a perfect
Fit from day one
When they came in to meet with us and we started talking about what we wanted to do and where they were at
Process it was a
Okay and I have to ask
I'm really excited
Zach who is the
Must have said you guys using Wi-Fi or
Cellular cellular and it was important
We have used Wi-Fi in the past
Center previous product
And Wi-Fi for us
Dad
Some issues
Because of our product being in the backyard
And because our product
Is under the
Covers in a hot tub
So we have electronics that are under the covers
We have water and then we have the backyard the disc
The backyard
So we were dealing with all of those things
Estranged
Connect to somebody
A consumers Wi-Fi network
And that just
Percentage a lot of issues
So we decided that we wanted to go
Cellular to alleviate those issues and also make
Easier on the
So that was one of the
Score of ordering with particle
Is we really wanted to you
Taylor number
So I'm very familiar with particle
Do you just
Did you buy the boards and just slap a mind as part of your electronics or how integrated and how much work did you do
Do with them
From the Ford and physical stuff all the way up to
Your hosting
And building the app
I wish it were that easy
We wanted more of an integrated
We have a lot invested in our
The structure that
So now the partnership
Particle was really taking their existing or
And cuss
Mising that and allowing
Particle
How to do a lot of work in interphase
Infrastructure
And then building out the
Particle cloud
Customizing
Oracle cloud and then Doling out AWS
Infrastructure
Jacuzzi so that we had a
Really tightly integrated
From Indian
And how do you guys connect
Ford dealers
Thor dealer portal is provided through
Salesforce vs Salesforce
Community how was the activity that are notification and everything
Comes in
From AWS
Salesforce
So are notifications
Country style source
As well as all the nodes
Any Tire Dealer portal
So what would you
Like to see
After you've done this and you're operating this and you
Hopefully will see it grow to
I don't know how many hot tubs are sold a year
Thousands hundreds of thousands of hot tubs
What do you need
Yeah I think the one thing that makes me the most nervous
Is not so much on the jacuzzi side is it is on the consumer privacy
Issues
Things like gdpr
And castle
Those things make me nervous
I don't know if they do you
Comes to iot
And especially with the fact
The California
Just came out
Announce that they're pretty their own version of gdb
PR what Hoops are we going to have to
Jump through in order to continue to advance this last
In the future
How are we going to be able
Continue
Do business
With all of us
Deregulation
They're going to exist in the difference
The world would you like to see one Unified
Maybe one unified regulation is kind of absurd but maybe
Three or four
Absolutely
I mean it would be
Astounding right would be abs
Absolutely amazing
You have one Unified
Version of gdpr
I think that probably it probably will never happen
Our lifetime
But even if we had three or four different Unified gdpr
Thai policy
To start getting to the farm we have
State-level
DPR policy
In my mind that's going to win
Nightmare
And to be clear your issue isn't necessarily with the regulations with ideas
Giving users controller
30. It is more just trying to implement many
Conversion 10 variations of
Those types of regulations
Describe
Yeah I have no problem with
Consumer privacy
I've completely believe in
It's more of trying to implement that
Across
Different Geographic
Hilarious
So if you have a different policy
In California than you do Intex
Trying to make sure that
You treat that data differently
California for those
First thing you do in Texas in designing your application
Around that and then
You know that balloons up into
30 different policy
Then doing the development
Around that
Keeping up with
Since we're in privacy let's talk about our other favorite
My friend security
So how are you guys
Dealing
With six
Security
All the various levels cuz I can see a hot tub
So we were very careful from the very beginning working with Oracle and Pandora to make
Make sure that we use the industry best practice
Straight from beginning
So we do it a whole
Variety of different
Security measures depending on you know what devices
Communicating
So depending is particle stylist
Communicating with a w a sore ass particles
Device where is the mobile app is
Communicating
Directly with particle you know we do different things
Cherokee's all
Great measures
Spell our consumers
Rest assured that there when they communicate with their hot tub kits
Right and also that no one will get boiled alive
That's exactly true
Well that's also handled
Within our controller
In the hot tub
So if that hot tub
Decides to
For some reason try to overtemp it goes into
Andover temperature
So that it does not allow the
Cuz people you know they get into these and maybe they're not their best
Selves who knows
So okay so
Let's talk about what all of this cost
Because this is very different
I imagine it's very different to build a connected product
Just kind of some ongoing overhead
Be crazy expensive
Last a long time so I'm trying to think about how you change how you sell these things how you
Projector
Liabilities for these things how does that all
How does connectivity change that
Ma
So right now we're targeting our Amir products
We quickly hope
Platform will
Easter Sunday
Quickly plan on having the iot Plaza
Wheat bran
SmartStyle on all of our
Prices and
It should vary
Quickly be a revenue generator
Through the driving
Additional hot tub
Sales because of it being
Product we believe that it's a differentiator
In the industry as well as
Accessories
Accessory sales
Or the app
It's also when somebody is
With that mess
For a
Or for chemical
Mike that that additional sales footage
Brandon
Products with lead
It's also will drive.
Recently I read about GE Appliances
They are doing a smart fridge and
It actually
Won't dispense water if you
Don't put a GE branded filter
Into
The refrigerator
As you can imagine that did not go over well with
People are you thinking about
Doing any sort of DRM associated with
Aker jacuzzi filter only works
No I mean that's I don't know that the we could ever get to that
You know our warranty states that you should be using your
Yeah jacuzzi branded filters
How everything there are aftermarket
Out there you know we believe there's definite benefits to using your
Jacuzzi brand
Filter
As well as other
Person accessories but we get to a point where we
Physically turn
Are hot tub off
If you don't use one of our products
There are no plans right now
Okay I'm all freaking
Outside like if something comes up and
Stacy you need a new filter clicker to order I'll be like
Does bargain hunt
Okay Mark
I have learned a lot about hot tubs which I have not experienced a whole lot up and the whole process so thank you so
So much for coming on the show
Absolutely thank you for having me that's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy on
Coyote.com will see you next week