Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Kevin tofel
And we have an amazing show for you today
Starting with the launch of the Amazon
Echo Show
And makes it iot purchase
We've got Microsoft news we've got some exclusive on a brand new product from a company
Set is
You know it
Really good
And we've also got a new start-up
From
Andy rubin's playground Ventures
Cut some industrial iot news and we are doubling down
From our perspective
With
Three more people talking about
The Echo Show including
Jonathan Frankel the CEO of nucleus which kind of just saw its business
Take it over
Buy the Amazon
Fred Meyer
We also have
A message from this week
Play sponsor Arris
And
This is a good time to remind everyone
Did this week show
You need to turn
There's just no way around it that we're probably going to say her name
Normally we are really polite
What is this week
Is not going to be that
We'll try not to say her name but boil boys can be tough
And I'm going to tell you right now
When we get to the gas segment
The guests were not as
It just got to me
It was too much
They were name dropping huh
So
Take this moment
I hit that like button if you got one year
Okay
So
Shall we get started
We shall
Okay
So Kevin and I both
Try.
The Echo Show we should
But what it is for
Well just to clarify we didn't try the Echo Show we tried a feature that comes with Echo Show
Because the news is that
Amazon launched or introduced the Echo Show device which is a
Screen
With a speaker and
8 microphones
It will cost you $229.99 available black or white
It will be released on June 28th
And I should note that if you buy two Echo Show devices you can save $100 with a promo code
Amazon is posting it is show the number two
Pack
And you might want two of these because it has a new feature which we did try
Saying the called she who shall not be named
Calling
So it's video and voice
Yeah that's what it is one thing I think you
Forgot
Show which
Probably will make a lot of pee
It has a camera
It hasn't always on camera in an always-on Mike that actually cannot be turned off physically it has to
2B only
It can only be turned off
Digitally
There's no physical shutter
On the camera
Interesting
I just threw that in there because
Cuz how would you do me a call
Without the video
This means we've got we talked about the other one last week but the echo look
Which is the
Hands-free selfie
The thing that were like
I ordered one
I could I could suddenly feel Washington
We tried the calling feature and just so you know everyone now if you have an echo device
You update if you update the app you're going to see a brand new app icon
On your phone
Google Voice cloud
And you have the ability to
You should see in your home screen
Conversations
And
That's going to let you set up the ability to
Use your Echo as a
I people
It doesn't do a video on the phone does it
Kevin and I just tried this in a brief interlude here inspired interlude
And what we discovered is that you cannot do video from
On the phone so this isn't going to compete with you know
Skype
Order
Hangouts
Duo or FaceTime
At least not yet
But what we did discover in
What I thought was kind of interesting as when Kevin called
My echos
All of my echos in my house when
Any calls me ring
And my phone rings
Now it'll be interesting is if I'm away from home
What happens
Because my husband is also on our Echo
And
His number should be associated
It with this device so I'm like
Could he answer my phone calls from
That could be a minute is all tied to a phone number because when you set this up
You enter the your phone number into the app
And
It didn't send you a confirmation code so it ties or links your phone number to your devices
Great butt
It also allows you to be in a house
So I'm
I'm curious
I will try that
Be kind of
I don't have
My other household member has a job that is not
So the question then becomes Kevin
You of the Isle of the echo would you buy an echo
Did you buy
I did not
And the main reason is I think the biggest use case here and there multiple use cases
The biggest one is the video
Calling and
I have so many devices that already do that
Mean yes
I would say this is nice from a hands-free perspective
But I don't really
Again to have that use case I want to do have tablets with
Stan's in things that
In computers
I just don't need another way to make
These kinds of calls
However I do like the fact that the screen shows you you know flash briefing videos and
Weather and so on just like
If you have a Fire TV and use you know use the intelligent assistant
You get visuals of what you're asking about so it's kind of nice but
For $229 I'm not sure what this replaces for me it's why I didn't buy one
Got it
All right
I may send you a
Just for fun
Listen I see
People infected in the marketing video for this
They're showing me no moms on the road calling on home
Talking to her daughter and the daughters grandfather who are working on a
You know school project together so Mom can check in and see
How it's all working
I can see people wanting to certain people but
Big enough for me
I thought the baby monitor like the look in on the babies
Was kind of in
Interesting
Baby monitor
Because the babies are probably not
Aldo
What if your baby's first word was Alexa
What if your baby's name is that
I don't know
You right you right because this does like any other equity-based tie into all of the smart home goodies and things that we
Musicals for today
So yeah you can turn into if you know the camera
Of another show for example I would have imagined
Could I use it to look at a nest camera don't know
It does say that you can shut
It says she can show you the front door monitor baby's arm is compatible cameras from ring and Arlo for example
Well I don't know about
Then right but certain things
That's exactly
So you could have like your own security system
I like it
Okay lot of cool stuff Happening Here we will talk more about it in June
When you get one
When I get one
I did only order one now I'm thinking I should have ordered two
One for me and
One for Kevin
But you know
Find a friend on the internet
Are you my friend
Also
We should say that Microsoft is planning a home hub function for
Windows 10
Shooters
I'm okay with this even though
I feel like the market is
Yeah I mean so this is
Returning from The Verge who has
Some what they call internal documents that they
Obtained
To show how Microsoft's home hub all one word Capital H's
I will work
And
It's
To the ideas it's going to be a place where you can control your devices
Where you can
Collaborate with family on calendars and such
I just don't really see it I don't see people using the PC for controlling smart home stuff
It's always got to be on you have to be in the home Hub app
I don't know
I'm with you
The only time I'm in front of a PC or PC like devices when I
Working at my dad
Granite people have laptops
How often
Now I open my laptop so rarely when I'm not quoting
Creating content
Register
Yeah for folks who are curious what the tentative plans are according to these documents support for hue
Nest insteon wink and SmartThings
Use Cortana of course for voice
Controls and such
I am just
I'm not Jazz but
Also
We have a really interesting
Start up
Coming out
It's called lighthouse
It's backed by playground Studios which is the
Adventure fund
But Andy Rubin
Of Android and Google Fame started
And also is like
Is he psychic or danger
Danger
We've had this conversation before
Sorry
The lighthouse is a new startup
And what they're building is a personal assistant
That has 3D sensing technology
That they built as part of the DARPA Grand Challenge and it lets you accurately distinguish
People
Embarrassed
Actions
And so what it does is it adds this layer of understanding
Both who's in the room
But then it also has a deep layer of understanding in it
So you can tell it very complicated things and it will actually do them
So to make this
Real
You can tell it notify be at the babysitter doesn't get home
By 4
And think about all the tablet that will impact all this happening
So you just hold in plain English
A person that has to write
I'm your set a time so you've done kind of Summer
If this then that programming
Location
And location
That's really freaking
Powerful
Well this is what the promise of a smart home is to me and if they can deliver that's great because
Very few devices and platforms are delivering
At this level yet
Yes we can take our existing assistance and we can tie our own if this then that recipes and so on to make this happen
But this is a native solution
And
I
Suspected will work better but we'll have to see
Exactly so but we won't see any time soon
Assume
This is really expensive
This won't be available until September and when it is available
Getting a device is going to cost you $400 and that will include one year of the lighthouse intelligence
Service
Look at that point your intelligence service cost $10
Right you could pay more Upfront for 99 to get 3 years of the service with the device
599 is an interesting bundle because you get 5 years of the television service
And the device
Well it says it renders the device free
Which makes me wonder is the device
I feel like the device is probably
Or thereabouts
I mean
That makes sense matter
Exactly
The cost of the Dubai
Nice cuz like this is one of those things that I actually
People may not love this
I like how they're trying to get people away from paying for a subscription if they want to pay more upfront
Doing something like this is going to require a lot of constant
Computing and support on the back end
So it makes sense that this is going to need
Some kind of
Your subscription fee just to help pay short
Absolutely
I'm pro-life idea of what they're doing here
Pro having a business model
I don't know if consumers are going to be stoked
I'm stoked about this but I'm a creep
Chongqing
So I don't know if real consumers are going to be stoked about this when
Make something like the echo is out there doing crazy things
True
Truing and you have
Developers that are climbing onto these different platforms that are readily available mainstream people have and they're always knew
Skills coming out a new intelligence and so on
One thing that might
Appeal to
People fought for the lighthouse device
They say that
Lighthouse customers data is only viewable by the customers themselves and never by Lighthouse employees or part
That's a big deal
Oh so you can pay for
For privacy
Which in a sentence
Is something
Is a thing
Yeah you know if you know what I see I see something like this getting
Is something like this would make home
Just
Miles better
Miles in apple already understands this they brought
What about the guys
Define Siri
IC
That's illogical
That's all right because I I don't see it actually
Speaking of Apple Apple
If I accompany called
Barrett
Didn't see that one coming
I've never tried a bit it although I have I have
Graze
Browse thank you
I think what scared you away from
Bet it is
The technology that uses because you can't say it
Oh Kevin
Go for it I'll give you 10 points
Ballistocardiography
10 points
Kevin
Yeah at the end of the show you'll have
I'll give you a trinket
Sure
Yes words are meaningless but I'm winning
Gamify all the things
What is ballistocardiography
Well I better get more points than 10
So it measures the mechanical activity of your heart lungs and other body functions which shall not go into detail what does MyPay
Because I've no idea
It's actually
Along
Sensory thing
That you place under your mattress and it measures your
I'm very intrigued by this device but I've never been
So Apple bought it at this will be amazing
Data for
Okay
We don't always hear a lot about healthkit but you know the people I talk to you for using it
Researchers medical folks it's a very credible platform so having kind of granular sleep data
Makes me feel like
This could really adalah
Makes me think that that is if you want
Really good sleep center might be the way to go cuz I'm assuming Apple that at all the other company
I can't I could see one other function that Apple would use
So every time they announce the new iPhone I have to get up at 3 in the morning to order it because that's when they order stuff on sale and Lease
Coso
Just a little alarm
Little little nudge for your bed
They work you that
Say that means by it
Yeah
Yeah that way there's no alarm feature vibraciones just a sensor
That's awesome
All right we also have this is kind of exclusive to us so we'll talk about it company that I followed for years
It's called you know me
Yonomi
And there
Consumers you can download it it connects to all kinds of things and
Establishes what it calls routines with
If this thing called applets or other companies called robots
But the idea is an in they do it automatic
So what they've done is they've created a product called that you know me thin cloud
In this isn't for consumer
This is for
Manufacturers of
Connected devices especially those working in the smartphone
The first customer is Schlage
DJ Norm
Complete so you know me think loud is basically a way to
Get your devices online
Connect them manage them
Do all of that but it's it's very thin they're using the AWS
Lambda functions
So there's a couple key things here that you need to know
Is
That
A manufacturer
By this
Once so
They don't have to pay yonomi on an ongoing basis adding to their own ongoing cost
Turn off all the provisioning and fun stuff
But there they will have to pay for the AWS cost
So there is still an ongoing
Right but
This is where we get into this concept of server list and I feel bad that I haven't talked to you guys about this
4 because it's actually a really big deal for iot
From an economic stance
Disappear With Me
Because later on we're going to come back to Target
Take a shower
Serverless computing
Things like AWS Lambda Google functions
The Computing instance only spins up when it's needed
Really important for iot because a lot of times you don't have like a constant
Compute job you have a sensor that wakes up and is like
Oh my God
Quickteller home hub my door is open
Is it a ghost
So if you had a server running all the time for that
That would be just disliked ongoing tiny little cost
But if you want you serverless computing
It wakes up
Perform that function charges you only for that function and then goes back to when it goes back to sleep
It's been Stout
So that's the concept we're talking about here so serverless Computing is really important for iot
Because it keeps your cost
Only when you use it
And I know that's what everyone told you about
Cloud computing
But that's not actually true
What is becoming true now
The way this approaches
Yes
And it's not the right approach for every
It new
But Netflix isn't going to use this
It's a really big deal for iot so now you guys have this
Amazingly nerdy
Party talk that will actually make people run away from you
So maybe picture
But in your management meetings
So what you know me does is they've built their platform for
Another server list kind of function Basecamp
And they did this to help
Cut costs again
So
What we've got with a Janome send
Is software the manufacturer buys once a one-time cost
Can pay for you no service another
Other things
If you want but you don't have
And then you've got the
Most as-needed function of AWS run
Basically you can run a smart
Hallmark
Connected device
Basically you can run a connected device
With
Minimal
Overhead
And that's what's so cool
That's what Schlage is excited about
That's what other customers they have are excited about so
I don't know I think this is really into
I agree it's it's far more efficient and specifically tailored to
The iot industry because as we
Just said
These devices aren't
Requiring
Qtime
All the time and so why pay for it
And why not make it more efficient so that
Computations take place as needed on demand
So yes the other things I should say
Because this is really important
If you're building this stuff
Is
When you buy the license to the thin called
You get the source code
So
You're not locked into it you
And that's a big deal because I have talked to many
Connected device companies who've gone with a
A cloud provider
Maven like
Crap we want to change our luck in this sucks
And that also is a benefit if a service provider for some reason goes out of business but not that I'm saying
You know me would or whatever but we talked about this
We talked about this in the past what happens to the the customers you know at that point well somebody can
Take up the torch and continued on with
Because they already have the code and they can
Obviously as you said tweakin to customizer do whatever they need
But still I think that adds a level of
Insecurities not not
The typical
Definition security not like device in data security but security that this
Service will be
Around for a long time
Exactly
So
Retrieving into kind of some industrial stuff I've got one more industrial news bit for us before we move onto our guest
Plural plural
Also for people who are building as opposed to just buying
Connected devices
CB insights the
Oh how do I describe them
They do Venture Capital data
They
Earlier this month put out
The industrial iot stack
Where they looked at
What it takes to build the industrial iot
They highlighted 125 startups transforming
All kinds all aspects of the industrial iot I can see that they forgotten some they
Put some on there that I'm like what
Their stack is really interesting
Because they break it down into sensors and connect
Edge device isn't connected
Objects
Universal platforms and Edge intelligence
Applied sensor networks which are very vertical specific so thank boiling glass
Cleat
And then Advanced analytics protection
Which I'm kinda like everything else
If I think about the way that business is going
Feel like a sensors and connectivity side
Are going to be pretty high leak
I would agree
Now some of the companies here
They've got sigfox Center
Engineer those are all connectivity side that got
In the censors of monitoring side they have companies like electric and power
What I see those companies doing is actually going all the way up to the
The topper
The analytics and Security Site
Height of the stack
So
When I look at this I disagree a little with the order but I see a lot more movement between the
Companies in these classify
Locations in the show notes you come look at it
I'm also going to include this in the newsletter on Friday so you
You can spend even more time with it
If you want
And
I'm glad that someone did this because
You don't even I sit there and try to
Create a stack
Industrial Computing iot industrial iot and I'm like
I give up
And it's hard
So it is hard I didn't even noticed they say while some companies may fit into multiple categories and parts of the stack
Weedmaps companies based on their primary use case of these sort of
I think I agree with what you're saying
A tendency right this is a challenge this is not to
And there's no
Correct answer here
To build a stack
But looking at this
There's like over 700 Industrial iot
This really reach we talked about this but the newly-launched platform Edge X found
That the Linux Foundation is doing
And we had a guest from dalian
Police are talking about
This is
Part of why that
Because they want to take
Some of these companies and push them together and then let
Push them together
Let them linked together without having to write individual
That's the Technic
Pickle side happen
They're just pushing them together
And then let people really focus on some of this exterior stuff so they're trying to come out if I the stuff in the middle
So not just sensors and connectivity but
Just at middleware where you just
Connecting
With that
Let's
Take a momentary break
Get into
Guess this week which
Are Michael Wolff
Jonathan Frankel
The CEO of nucleus
Mark Rolston the head of argodesign
For a message from this week's sponsor this week sponsor is Eris and we have
Z Hussain who is the CTO and founder of eras here to talk to us today
Let's get started with an easy one
What is Eros
This is a company that was founded on the premise that people needed to get remote information
From equipment and devices and applications out in the field
Process them and take some business action
That's what we've been doing for the past 20 plus years providing these kinds of services for our
Enterprise customers
Why should a company think
About implementing
One of the first things I tell people is to understand
Exactly what the outcome is that they looking for from a business perspective meaning
Is there some basic
Cost advantage that they get by implementing an iot solution
What is there some kind of enhanced Revenue that they will generate because they've implemented in Iowa
Lucia having said that there may be other drivers as well.
Create the need for deployment IRP application
For example if a utility company wants to do
Time of day billing and they have to measure and take him
Information from the electric utility meters and that creates the requirements of the opportunity for implementing and iot
Solution even though it's in perhaps
Santander Consumer
Meter reading app
That sounds great so what does it take to
To implement some sort of Iota
They need to understand what
Data Vinnie together what control functions they might need what business action are they
Going to take on receiving that data
What are the worst things you can do is gather data for the sake of gathering data and create
But I will call Haystacks of unimportant data that actually has no
Relevance to what they're the problem is that they're trying to solve any to understand exactly what it takes to get that data
And what day does it need now
Transport of that data if it's a remote
Device is very very important how do they need to get that data back to their facility where is the device locate
Then they need to go beyond the conductivity portion of it I understand where they're going to store the data how reliable is that storage
Do they need to perform an analysis of that data so what areas does is when these companies are look
Looking for a iot Solutions Paris provides them guidance right from the start as to what their solution is
Things to look like
And then once the Enterprise has made a decision that they needed to play an application
We provide them the network transport from the cellular device at my PR
Filled all the way to the cellular system where there's within the United States or overseas internationally
And provides a data to them in a in a massage Orem
That they are expecting to see
Where can I find out more
About what heiresses
We want to find out more about iot Solutions and how to deploy
And iot solution for their particular problem I would highly recommend that it download a copy of the
Free ebook that I have published it's available on our website
Www. Eres
Atrrs
Dot-com
We can also listen to a copy of this podcast another podcast app
Www.arris.com podcast
We're doing something a little bit different this week on the guest portion of the show because we are
So excited about the Amazon Echo Show
I got a few people to talk about what they think this means
So
My first guess this week is Mike Wolfe
Who is a smart home analyst
And who has his own site called
The spoon
Where he covers smart kitchen stuff
It's not as the spoon. Tech
If you're really lucky
You'll be in Seattle for a smart
Kitchen Summit
So
Mike
Amazon
Show
What do you think
Well
It came so fast after the walk it's like the looking show
Was in what two weeks in a row
But I'm not surprised because I wrote a piece I think early
About 2 months ago saying
Amazon
As a whole bunch of connected Home Hardware coming this year
I'm Thor's I've been hearing out of the Doppler side of things
And I just out of out of Amazon for my sources is
They're not done
After what they showed up that with Echo with a.
So
I think they're just going all-in on this thing
What do you think about Amazon
I think it's
As doing everything they can to get you to buy more stuff
Does that still fit in with this Smartphone Vision or should I expand
My Amazon is going to take over the
I think they're just trying to like find of a fit with Alexa for every type of user
Modality every type of preference in whether that's a
A touch screen
Were you going to show some things
Whether it's a
A camera which you know as we know people love
Some people love cameras either one I don't know if I want a camera in my in my
My bedroom
But
There's they're just different looks in different use cases they're trying to
Fit into and give people
A way to use Alexa
Really what it's all about
And I think it's over taking everything in terms of their connected-home Vision including I think it's in a way replacing
Dash I think the physical done for Dasher starting to go away you starting to see them just went to Virtual buttons are they really think they're going all-in
When is an Alexa has the weight of the century by stuff
And and get people like you said to interact with our conversation
So I'm with you on the dash because I always thought those buttons were stopgap
And I thought the real story was with the dash replenishment service
Because you can build ERS into anything and that feels so powerful
For any maker of some sort of like razor blades or
Pet food or whatever
Brita water pitchers
So the idea of
Having
Different
Echo form factor
Who is most threatened by alipay
This is it
You know Google home with its me to speaker is it maybe
Apple with its I don't know if it's going to launch a speaker
What do you think
I don't know if they're not knocking out of the park
Either
The walk
Or the show
I feel like
The go-to big winner still is the
Backhoe the primary product that started it all I mean we'll have to wait and see I don't necessarily feel like this
One factor is like a huge winner
It look when I first saw the picture I thought like
Okay this is just someone's
Physical
Idea but it wasn't going to be the final products I was kind of surprised the final product look
So 2007 quite honestly
And what surprises me is like
I'm wondering if
If Amazon is using there are lots of fun to invest in companies
The price for discovery mode because this looks a lot
It feels a lot like the nucleus and also asking a lot of ways like that the tribute which is it another company busted in inbox yet
To the kitchen speaker
They've invested in comes with Alexa fund that
The ultimate creative practice very similar to
So that's interesting to me
And we have Jonathan Frank
Nucleus
Is coming on in a
He shares your opinion
If they are using this is a Discovery Fund as opposed to an actual advance
You know the platform
What would you advise startups who are looking at taking money from the Amazon
The city Alexa voice
Get a great lawyer
To write your agreements although you may be at the mercy of whatever they want to do
But just go into this with full understanding that
Amazon
Is never going to be
Someone other than maybe coopertition then maybe ultimate your competition
Like they're ultimately
In it for their own
Motivations
Step back and say I do think they want it have Alexa distributed among the different devices
There's going to be categories that they don't go into
But I mean you can never fully right off the fact
The idea that they mailed maybe your competitor even if you had their your investor
Where won't they go
I think
Most everything has to have a Commerce orientation I don't necessarily see them going into
Connected
Sprinklers or garage door openers or those types of things at
You emailed me get some sort of
Level of adoption but it's never going to be like this massive
I don't think they've ever going to like low-volume
Niche products
I was going to ask so there's this idea that it like
Roughly 5 to 6 million Amazon echos either in the dot or the echo format
WhatsApp have been sold
And usually when I talk to people who aren't interested in it they're not interested in it because they don't want to have a speaker always listen
I kind of freaks them out
So
Do you think the
Telenovela can
I can't find anybody who wants to
So do you think the show is
Going to bring Ian that audiences so far is kind of worried about privacy and that sort of thing
Maybe
I think the main motivation for the shows is a video screen
I mean Wilder you receive platonia natural decline in in tablet shipments I mean iPad numbers Court
Continue to go down
I still feel better
Our people are very visual
Want some sort of
Touch interface video interface
What's interesting news
Remember we were at 8 on the one of the podcast when I talk about the cabinet project cabinet that talk about a rumor kitchen computer
From a couple years ago I think this is what they told me was this Maybe Might their kitchen computer
Cuz you can do things like video
Demonstrations of a cup
Like Buzzfeed video recipe how to
I think
Basically the kitchen use cases very visual
There's just certain things you can't do
With a voice interface like I may ask Alexa
To tell me how to cook
But I can't show me how to cook with a video
Dennis it's has somewhat Limited
Usefulness I think so I think this kind of sauce for that
Okay and what about the voice calling
Again this kind of
Tizanidine nucleases stuff
I was kind of excited by the fact that
Looks like it only goes from
Do you have any thoughts there
I really liked video calling I don't think anyone's going to necessarily replace FaceTime
You know Skype video calling
Or even
Google Hangouts with this thing but I can see them
Sewing
These and then maybe coming out with an app much like they did with the Kindle app eventually
The Royce attraction
Video calling maybe they've go that direction okay so after Amazon has released all this Hardware I'm looking at it and you know what I think
I think it might be time to relaunch the Fire Phone
Phone now
Now you serious I'm serious think about all the data that they could get from being able to
Put this
Basically think of
Alexa on your handset
And there is definitely a market for that today but now that you've got you know calling
Now you can create this entire ecosystem around that I don't know either
What are they did a killer
Wearable
Like no one's really done I think Apple watch
It's kind of like okay are people done with that boy that you did this really great wearable with Alexa integration I'm just Breeze from
Just kind of spitball in butt
I feel like big Commerce
Because of Commerce being so big to them I don't know if a wearable make sense unless we think about it as like a bio
But what if what if it has
Some sort of like scanner in it or something to tell you when you watch Walking to a store if you just scan a product
It goes into your Amazon account
And I'm let me advise or something I don't know
Just thinking out loud
I like when people think out loud Mike
Thanks so much
For coming on the show
This has been a lot of fun things Stacy
Alright I'm here with Mark Rolston who is the founder of argodesign and he's here telling us about how
The Echo Show
Was inevitable
Hey Mark how you doing
Good to talk to you
We have spoken
Several times in the past about
Amazon Echo in the voice as an interface
So can you kind of break down what you mean for me when you say that
This designer this product was somewhat inevitable
Yeah well when you look at the echo
It's fantastic
Devices you can imagine talking to
Soon as you start doing that
You realize
You really not
Look for it to read out the answer verbally
For you
The time
You can start talking back
Now you realize that I have a list of restaurants
A grocery list
Store what are my points
Anylist that's beyond one or two words any sample of words
Just not tall ago.
Tablet computer
So
You realize you need a screen
Anywhere and everywhere but
Queens
Super useful for any kind of like the concert so it wasn't a glamazon
Obviously the show is there
Response
Alright a lot of people have said that this thing
Is ugly
I think someone earlier in the show's 10th it look like it was a design from the
2007 so as a professional product designer
Give us your take
Agreed
Ugly because
I think so read on it as soon as I hear
Is Billy twofold wine is
Quietly into my home
Cincinnati
Does
As much as I can
Given what it's doing today
Does it look like a gorgeous objects
First run
Consumer
Introducing everybody
I understand why they didn't
Sasori what they're trying to do is say
Form around it
Just look
It is
In the nursery speaker
I really don't mind I don't think it's a silly silly
Got it let's
What's your profession
True and I feel like we are kind of to this point where we have fetishized
Electronic objects these white plastic
Maybe they're space gray plastic
Things that we stick out our home and I'm kind of like
I don't know if I need any more like UFO looking like things that control stuff in my house
What do you think of it
Unnecessarily
But as a stepping stone it's an all-in-one device and it has
Thing that is causing it so much
Mass is
This microphone and speakers
Vim screen
But that's just because that's when we are
I'm really look forward to this answer when
I've got a set of
Potential screen
Microphone array
Organic part of a well-equipped home
The speaker's Maybe
The same way that were starting to hide
Speakers that we listen to music with
The device speaker
We're not anywhere near that yet
Kind of hardware stores on come on
Breaking news
Find
Because it's introducing a lily
Magical 7 features
Everyone recognizes how complex that scenario
Understand this is really pretty successful design and it took a lot of engineering
Well let's talk about those other ideas kind of us the final
Bit of all of this
You once showed me a prototype when you are at frog
And it was his concept of house that understands context
Adapts to you and show you information kind of where you need it
It was really kind of cool
And so
From
And I don't remember how long ago without pus but from that time
To hear
Where do you see us evolving
When it comes to building these kind of contextually aware smart
Elsa Rumi was our future mission to imagine instead of devices
That we got a lot of this
What is low-level functionality
What time is it change the temperature turn on the lights
I almost died.
Devices that will help you with that
Which required
GoDaddy pocket unlocked
Go to Red Lobster Vine app
And such
But we imagine that the home
Itself
Was equipped with all the necessary for
To do that for you orthodox
Any environment that humans
Commonly existed within them could be equipped
With the level of computing where you would say the room is
The computer in the corner
Is really
Beautiful example of
First product
Way back into a guy
Chesnaught
Was thinking if we wanted to build this
The first thing we need to do is essentially make a box with some of it
Then we thought maybe the first box will be the projector
We want to quit
Field that product
Be kind
It's obvious today
Got answer so.
Amazon go
I'm extremely coffee
We will get
Back to that
Instead of these discrete boxes you have
Corner yoga
You instead
Put the next one up into the ceiling
I like all.
A can light
Socket you put one of those dogs will be your max
We kind of see this today with if you look at like the ecobee did with the
Alexa powered thermostat in there actually doing light switches with both of microphones and speakers in them
So that feels close to this patient
Cats getting their rights
They're basically
Exploiting existing
Appliances in the house or existing affordances
Alexa light socket
To sneak in another mic
More control service
Eventually you have a an overarching system
Something Amazon Rhymes or Apple
Google Now
Back to the room
Into other room
Cost of laundry room
It's really one conversation one
You'll stop thinking of it is that thermostat
Calories
Black
Monolith in the corner
I'm really just talking to the room
Go back to the question of what do I think of
Echo Show
It's a great stepping stone
All right
Well thank you so much
Can you have Jonathan Frankel who is the CEO of nucleus
Which as you can imagine today just found out
That the Amazon show
Looks kind of like
Bear pride
Hi Jonathan how are you
So we talked for years I've tried out a nucleus I thought it was actually pretty
Pretty sweet what was your reaction today when you saw the Amazon show
I thought hey that there's an eerie resemblance to product
And how is it how is your day been so
Let's ask it like that how is your day been
It's been a rollercoaster
I like it.
Elf crystallized thing
We
Having a
Yeah that this was
Coming
But
At the same time you're under the impression that it was
Not overly
Competitive by
Signal leak
Nothing video this morning yeah kind of
Different direction
But
Panda strategic part of my brain
Working as well
And
As I'm watching this as much as I make
Straight in my chair thinking about the future of nucleus and
Call the Family petrolina
I also think about the
Ordering.
Walmart
Target
Comcast
Google
They also have
Wondering
How do they remain relevant
Amazon has
Potentially
Shopping cart
Every room in your home
The reason
Why I think Amazon is willing
2 +
Directly with
By the time you were the single largest investment from the
Why would they
Shut the marketplace that it can't be trusted as
Sandwiches
Ecosystem
I think it's because
DeGraff Butler wheatgrass glitches
Using communication
Is the pat
Ticket
Normal everyday people to put devices throughout their home
And exact their homes out of people's houses
The Amazon has this once-in-a-generation
Opportunity to get their shopping cart
To every room in millions at home
And logout all the other retailers
Elsa
Interacting with the customer
I guess is Al Pacino's too good to be true
And if I was a teenager retail today
Okay
Well let's break that down because that's that's a pretty big strategic threat
How exactly do you feel that this is us
Threat for these guys
Now that Amazon has a shopping cart
Video and Communications access in every room in my
So
Amazon Pennsylvania Plaza building blocks
Price of a minion
Stair look
Heather Cameron has
Image recognition Technology Building
And now that has Echo Show which all sides are always on camera and no private
Imagine typical family
I wake up in the morning
There
Preparing breakfast
Ever since the milk
Fans on camera see if the milk is empty
And immediately pops has a message and says hey do you want to deliver milk later today
They were in the office
YouTube
Why would you ever step foot into a supermarket ever again
When you can physically have this
Automated delivery system Rainier kitchen
Thank you mention Google in there
Why should they be scared
Tell if you're italco
Tacos today mean that many lines of business
Internet phone
And entertain
So song
Amazon announced the ability to do phone calls together with
Ecuador
Tell you if they turn your
Each Echo device
A whole home
I think I've taken that pillar out of the the triple play
Set entertainment
Lights out
Cable bundles on their taxes
Lots of different type of Amazon
But now that you have
Amazon Fire stick that plugs into your TV
Did Billy
Use your voice to turn on your as your show that you want at anytime that Amazon Prime video
Screen in your kitchen so you can watch shows while you're cooking or getting ready
They're going to lock you more more
Enter
I can't take it one step further
Netflix
Is renowned for using data to help them
Programming
It didn't have a microphone or camera in every room
Amazon Uno
Who is watch
When they're watching
That's what the camera that can know when you're watching the screen or looking down your phone
Amazon has better data
Any Android can play in the industry
To create better content for the La Quinta
The entertainment portion of the bundle kind of Falls away
Taco becomes an internet line
Is
It's lucrative but but it's hard to sell additional services
I don't know what if they killed it
That changes
But we're not going to go there
Now for you guys
You mentioned that you were rethinking possibly
I think about your business in light of this
What is this mean for nuclear
This is still fresh
We have thought deeply about family communication for
Chillicothe R2
Tens of thousands of people
I understand what movies does he look at Arden Heights versus Amazon
Different devices offline store
Shopping
Optimized for family communication
Physical properties
Because he wanted to feel comfortable in your own home
Inland Steel
City Center cuz they want the camera recording
Look into partnering companies other Industries Antonio's auto companies that are threatened by Amazon
And we can help them
Yeah by putting nucleus devices
Potentially with or without Alexa
Action
I didn't ask to be great partners
Help we can find
Threatened by Amazon
And our
Don't want to find a place
Device that will offer
Consumers
Even better family
But also not the relationship that they have in it
With their customers of a billion dollars and decades building up
And finally because you guys you mentioned this you were the
One of the largest Investments That
The Alexa
Voice Services Venture van
Headed back
How do you feel as kind of
A startup
They took Amazon's money
And now
He's kind of faced with this
What would you advise other startups
So I kind of have a
Split personality
I'm not
Like I understand it right it's business and we're big boys and girls and we've got it
Opportunity put shopping cart
They're an example of to do that
I'm not
Spy with it
Interesting case study for anyone else thinking of partnering with Amazon
The weather
Start up
Weather at Spotify
Pandora
Stone services
Amazon music happy to partner with you
Quality time
And then I'll switch it up
Which is kind of the way business gets done
Yes I understand it really I'm not like they had to do
Nas
Monopoly
Athena
We don't have to stand there and let them do it
Which company is that
Chaoyang district Shopping
All right with Jonathan thank you so much for coming on the show today that's it for this week
Thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy
Snooze things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week