Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Kevin tofel we have an excellent show for you today we've got big news Amazon making an acquisition
Smart cameras and how smart they really are
News from Mobile World Congress
Bunches of little news bits including some fun
Submit in the space Samsung news
Plus
Some gear
We're also going to talk briefly about my visit to Bosch connected world
Our Guest this week is Dominic
Cheater
Of Iota
Which is
It's a boy
Isn't just about
Cryptocurrencies
Which
If you listen to the show
You already know
And now
A word from our sponsor
This week's show is brought to you by the platform you all have probably use the free yonomi app
Or to control the smart home devices in your home or you've heard us talk about it on the podcast well it's January 8th
Project they've been working on behind the scenes for the past 4 years
Cloud-based platform-as-a-service that allows developers to build a more connected smartphone
Essentially you know me is building or parsed of consumer iot this is really exciting
This week is part of their sponsorship of the iot podcast
Concert series on what the next billion-dollar smart home startup will look like part one is available
Today for listeners if you go to http colon slash slash platform
Don't you know me. Co / Stacey on iot there you're going to be
Smart home industry might be stuck in what we need to change before we have more billion
Given this Rings announcement so go to http
Colon slash slash platform. You know me. Co / Stacey on iot
Include that in the sponsorship link part of the show notes as well and for those who don't remember or no
You know me as yonomi and now back to the show
Okay
As referenced in our ad oh my gosh you guys Amazon
Just this week said that it would buy
Ring the maker of
The ring doorbells
Ring lights and ring outdoor security cameras
Maybe the ring security system
Which is currently
Being
Cancel because of
Civil lawsuit
Yeah that's that's part of the story too but
I guess there's a couple pieces here to unpack one is how much we do know how much Amazon has
Buying ring for
River was 1 billion but then people saying it's the second largest amount
That Amazon has spent on acquisition
So maybe a bit more than a billion
Second largest
Largest was Whole Foods at 13th
2.7 billion
Zappos
Appears to be the second-largest at
2 billion
8 billion +
That's a pretty
After number
They said they estimate there are about 1.2
Million ring doorbells out there
So if we use the one point
2 million
Ring units sold
And we say on the low side is a 1.2 billion dollar deal Amazon's paying like $1,000
Hours per customer per doorbell
If I ring and I know they're not just buying customers
The buying new Rings assets and IP and I get that a wow that's a lot of money
It is a lot of fun
You know I suppose
I suppose it's
I know it's just a lot of money
It is a lot of money
We shouldn't ignore the fact that in December Amazon also bought
Which is a security company that also makes security cameras and doorbells
The interesting thing to know here Amazon seems to be
There's a couple
Thanks this gets into what I wrote about when the deal was announced but
Review at quickly
One home security is essential
For the Smart Home
I know we talked a lot about automation cuz that's where heart lies most consumers buy into the Smart Home
Which home security systems is the number one reason that people buy stuff
Number 2 is Energy Efficiency
So you can't be
In a smart home without
And
Amazon
As its
Falling into this magical Madam a place where it's okay we're
Play double down on that I think what's happened is
They bought blink
For a technology powers
Has it started out as a chip company making aloe
Power video processor
And
That kind of technology is going to be key if we want these kind of sensors around the home at a low price and being batteries
Empowered
What is getting with ring is
Market share
Ring is by far the leader in this market is according to IHS it has about a 45% share of the Americas
Market in
Video doorbells
So
That's number one the other is there is Nest just lunch the doorbell their skybell there is August had a doorbell
Like really
Ring was
The contender
So Amazon gets all of this
Classic hits
We can't see Aqua hired
Lawsuit with ATT
Because ATT had invested in off and was security products
There smart home kind of security
Product
And they were 44 ring
Well that that's what it gets me through the other thing Amazon is getting here lawsuits
What happens with the prior tsutsumi obviously they're not going away
And Amazon has deeper Pockets than ring does obviously
So
What does X Change
What happened to nest in the Honeywell lawsuit after Google acquired
My gosh just a few months later it was settled
Yeah well maybe that's all part of this big number
Somehow
Yeah and it's so it also in addition to the ADT lawsuit it was also being sued by skybell for patent infringement
Darius doorbell
Video doorbell
Right
So
I don't know what happens to those
I reached out to people
It's so new that people are kind of like a shrug
Right
We'll figure that out
We may never find out unless I'm going to assume the saying that these suits will be settled no hear about it soon
The next coming months
And I doubt we'll ever hear the sums that were
Presented for settling these suits
I would love to know that because taking back in that money out of the purchase price for reading
That's really what Amazon is paying for ring in my opinion
Has raised a lot of money they were actually going back
Again to the market
With around that would value them in a billion.
Color switches are around billion dollars it was just some
So it makes sense the price that people heard it makes sense it was around a billion and then it also makes sense
Right they went through six rounds and raised about 210 million dollars and they're looking for more
And that kind of speaks to how hard it is to profit in this market as well
Right you know
We traded company that was the exit and
What happened is it just
It couldn't get there
Fast enough
It was selling well
But the doorbell my understanding is has a relatively High bill of materials licensing fees on their video
Testing machines
There's no scale potential there
There could be now with Amazon buying it
Casinos blinx technology
Well you can put links technology inside and
Amazon video processing
Itself
SoundCloud it's not AWS
So there are definitely economic
Advantages to
All at all
It's a good deal the other thing that I think is really important to know
Well there's two
Is if you have a ring doorbell it is going to work for now just the same as it always has
So that means it will stay in great
With other platforms
Amazon
Ring says they are still can't
Doorbell
That's not out yet
So keep waiting on that and
Then
Will that continue
I hope so
I would hate to see the Google flights
Especially with Google launching their visual display stuff I would love to be able to look at who's at my ring doorbell on my
Google
I want to call it the Google show
The smartscreen like spaghetti sauce
I can do that today obviously with a nest in a Android TV
So I would hope that
That kind of thing continues I'm pretty sure that ring will continue on its own
Brandon all that so I don't
I don't expect massive changes
As far as what it's going to work with him but it won't work with I think we'll just be highlighted how well it works with Madam a
Yeah I don't know I feel like getting to this point where everybody's got Amazon is almost feels
You're going to have to have your own
Ecosystem
So like the nest gear going into Google
And being more closely tied
I can see Amazon looking at that and saying
I guess we got to get our own dear to
Questions what happens to other partner
Canary
Or Skype
Those who are working with
So lots of question solidation it's going to be a mess as consumers
I'm kind of consumers
We could be host a little bit with our
Are devices that used to work in multiple ecosystems we may find them getting
Crunched which is a shame because we bought them
With the
Understanding that would work with multiple ecosystems
Other
Companies get squeezed out now
MN
You know the products that you bought that don't have a big-name partner may not have a future
Send it
That's sad
That is sad
I'm trying to think of all the devices
All the signals the end
Rush of startups
That came out in 2013 2012 All Around the iot
We saw this huge massive amount of kick-started in French
Crowdfunded in venture-backed companies in
Even a little in 2014
If you weren't out in finding America by then
You were kind of
Addalock in
We're seeing that with the end of a lot of devices and it's kind of sad so
We talked about this early on with Matt turkey was a guest a while back
And he was like yeah
There is over
I think he's right
Teresa
Very sad
What else would we talk about
We can talk about a new camera
Yes let's talk about it
Clip is finally out
This is a camera they announce the Google IO and it was a
Yes that's correct
Is pizza
You said it somewhere and it decides the right time to take
Picture and it takes it
And what kind of it outside the button so you can
Take pictures yourself but the idea is that
You're living your life in
Google decides what
Yeah which it's actually intelligent idea because Google has so much data from Google photos about you
You know who's in your family who the people you care about that you take pictures a lot of what pets you know do you have it in you take pictures of
It takes you from behind the camera and put you in front of the camera with those
People and things and
And intelligently
Captures that we supposedly captures you no meaningful memories
Did you read the reviews at all by the way
Yeah did you see any good ones
The surprise really excellent story about
Google clip in Lighthouse which is now out
Lighthouses another intelligent camera
In his his reviews weren't like these are not pictures that I used to taking
But it captured some really good moments that I would never
Captured or even noticed
Which is that good I think it's a totally different type of
So I think you expect
Much like people poo-pooed smartphone
Pictures
For their DSLR
DSLR
I think we're going to
This type of
Innovation for a while but I think we're going to start getting used to seeing them and then
Start treasuring these Lake
Little moments
It captures
What degree is early days this is like the first
Camera of it
Kind so to speak in a mass-market level and it's going to take time for it to become smart enough to truly become Valley
So
I agree with you I wouldn't write it off I don't think it's quite ready for everybody to rush out and buy one based on what I've seen
And I'm not used one
But I read every review out there from people that I know and trust and I'm like yeah
It's just not
Not enough value for the turn $49 yet
The other thing to note is Google
You choose what images
So if
Google Clips catches you
Running across the living room in a towel
Work without any clothes
You can just delete
That would be a moment
It's doing its job it's capturing the memory I think the key here is recognized
Job of explaining this
Recognizing
This is a big thematic shift
Imaging technique
Beforehand we had cameras that were dumb
It just you know to make a judgment call a human had to be involved
Normal cameras but now the cameras are making their own judgments
Computers
Which these are
Are so much
More scalable we're going to have the ability to make judgments about pretty much everything
Every second
The day and that's actually really
Yeah you know I would say
Cameras actually a pretty smart even before this came out and I took away a lot of the
Human judgments in terms of
Composition near things like laser autofocus
Multi-point Focus so it can determine what the actual subject of the photo is
And these are all
Technical things not a I type things
Now we're adding a AI
You know that point and shoot type features of many cameras today are so smart that
Arrival at completely manual camera so to me this is the next step is just
It's a very first step
Sure so Aesthetics
We've been using AI for Aesthetics for a while now
Keep that in mind
It's a little freaky
Will probably talk more about this at other junctures
Let's move on to World Congress
The show of shows
Congress
Is it
It is in Barcelona
So and also we should say this weekend is also happening in Germany
Not seeing a ton of great news out from that but check out the newsletter if you want
Some when it comes out
Back to Mobile World Congress
Qualcomm is doing couple things that I thought was interesting
One is the guy
They've taken their snapdragon
High-end phone chips and they created embedded versions
The important thing about these embedded versions
They're going to have support contracts for
5 years 7 years however they're going to be made for the embedded
This means that they're going to have a longer support life and be around for longer if you want to build them into your products
Yeah I need these are also very capable chips that the newest one is anyway because it's built on the Snapdragon 820 which
What was powering Flagship phones just two years ago
So it's not like a low-power type
Chip that you might see and say a smart plug or something this is going to have a lot of computing power
Relatively speaking front of to device
And computing power
All the connectivity that you would expect in basically
Longer support
Mostly lock support
They're going to standby some design considerations
Pokemon different types of pre-configured modules one is for LTE
Which is great because you can
Is a software development kit
And module
You buy it and then you seem connected to a variety of different LTE networks around the world which is just
Easier
If you're trying to build something
And then they also did
Pre-configured multi radio
Module 4
Alkota homes
Bluetooth Wi-Fi
All kinds of fun stuff
You're actually two different versions of that one has Wifi one does not
Yes
When is super low power
The other thing that jumped out to me
These two that were talking about now actually
Come with pre-integrated support for homekit
I'm like electricity
Yeah I'm still
I hear you
Okay good for them
It's Not Dead
Yet it won't ever
I shouldn't say that
No AT&T
They are
Powering all the connectivity for
Caterpillar
Which is
They make all kinds of industrial and farming
Equipment
What school is they also had a very nice story and a SIM card announcement around
Google house in I pay attention to this because AT&T actually led the way with Kinect
10 cars
They are by far the dominant
Provider for connectivity in
Vehicles
They've got in the US
Or the cut
So they picked the right Market there
And that was good and I'm interested because now if they're really doubling down or focusing hard on medical
Then maybe it's actually time for medical 2
To be a thing
I feel like I've been saying this for a decade
You know it's funny because I remember - this goes back about 6-7 CSS ago
Seeing the
Little Pill cases that had
Connectivity in them
Adding wood
Take your medicine and then
It could determine if you didn't if you didn't it could use that connectivity to like
Reach out to a healthcare provider say hey this person I don't remember
There you go
Yeah so
It's time again for that I can talk with
Yeah well okay but see take the Qualcomm
LTE bass modules
And that's the kind of product a
Medical device manufacturer
Watch so red
High-powered snapdragon
You know capabilities with long-term
Ish support
And so
We could be seeing
What we need to make
That happened
Okay let's get to Bass news bits
Yeah so this kind of came out of nowhere just happened to be the person in charge basically out of
MattyB
And also the person who created The Madam a prize which is a million-dollar prize to create a chatbot for
I can interact with a human
Buy sell for 20 minutes
His name is Ashwin Ram
And he has left Amazon is now the technical director of AI at
The Google
As a bonus to this Kevin has found a really interesting about conversation
Because you should read this conversation
Yeah these are the actual conversations that the people going for the Madame a present as a million-dollar prize by the way
We're trying to win so these are there people testing the chatbots
The conversations are sometimes scary but also very interesting
By the way question from one of our listeners who was
British spelling
We're talking about
The Amazon echos brains
EXA
We try not to say it because we don't want to set up
One day we will have access to Amazon's medical High free
Mancino and said they play beforehand and maybe we can get our
Our own versions bat
Can reverse engineering
Kevin
Get on that ass
Alright in other news
Dismiss a company that is selling Enterprise
Intelligent WiFi
Is raised 46 million dollars I really wanted to talk about this because missed is changed its
Marketing in the last probably 18 months or so and I think it's worth noting they started out actually touting
Virtual Beacon
Location basically so you could actually run their software on your access
What's your Wi-Fi access points
And use it software to
Place
Virtual Bluetooth beacons to interact with your employees phones
I thought it was awesome but apparently the market was not keen on this because now
They're touting themselves as
Intelligent Wi-Fi event
For the Enterprise
Hyacinth
They're using very similar
Spectral analysis is how they're doing this capabilities
To say
What's wrong on your network how many devices are on your network
So they
A couple months ago or maybe a month ago announced that skill for Madam a that basically
You can say hey Madam a
Why is Bob smartphone
Not on the network
And it would tell you
So how many iPhones do I have
And the answer is more than you think
Now you know
So I just thought this was an interesting shift because
One of the things Kevin and I were disappointed about last year
As a good context
And it sounds like location is still
Not yet in there no I actually like the whole virtual Beacon idea but
Honestly I'm not hearing a lot about beacons in general it's like that technology that's like
It's great it's just that nobody's using it
Yeah so
We'll keep an eye on it
Apparently
No one else has no one else has
Welcome to our world
Merced news
Staples connect
Is finally dead
So Staples connect timeout
Cash in like 2013
I was really excited about it actually showed it one of our first conference has that we hosted his eye
Happy people
And it was a
Zana built it
And it was a back-end platform plus a hug that connected lots of different things including
Smoke detectors Lutron lights
All kinds of other products
Nobody really bought it
It was actually one of the best and well design platforms out there especially for normal people
And they stop supporting it
You know when Zara Flint to ring
Staples decided to shut it down and now
It's probably
You can't pronounce the service at all I don't think the problem was the platform because you said it was one of the better ones around it
What's the time
Ain't nothing against Staples but I don't know if that was the right
Place to sell it
Here's a good thing
The fibaro smart plug is shipping this is Kevin really likes
You like it you tell
Sure sure I saw it at CVS and shared a picture on her Instagram page talking to you Attleboro folks about it
So it's you know it's your typical smart plug
Just takes up one Outlet you don't obviously it itself isn't outlet but it doesn't cover up the second one which is nice
Have a really nice LED ring around it and that is
Kind of cool because you can change the color of it you can use it as a night light
But you can also use it to determine how much power is coming
Through the outlet in a given time
$50
It's a Z-Wave Outlet if you want to spend an extra ten bucks and I probably would because this is cool
It has a USB port to it as well so you can charge something
And then you can monitor both the output of the outlet itself as well as the USB output
Pretty
Other news
Bixby speaker
Push to the SEC
Yeah they were hoping to do it in the first half of the year and then it
NWC earlier this week they announced their Galaxy S9 S9 plus and of course it's got the dedicated
Bixby button so they're Bixby smart speaker isn't quite ready
They're talking about approving Bixby calling a Bixby 2.0 at least internally
And I have a feeling that's why the smart speaker itself is pushed out because I want to improve the
Voice Assistant something that other companies
Don't you want to have a
You would want to have a $350 speaker that's not too smart
Just saying
There we go
All right
Well
I
Also I meant with her I meant I was at Bosch connected world this weekend I'm not going to talk too much about it cuz they'll be more of this in
The newsletter
It's cold I think the big trend for Enterprise and Industrial iot
Where is last year we focused a lot on security and proof of Concepts
I think this year we're going to focus more on culture and making these things actually work with your staff and how to get your staff and
Employees on board with it and training
That's kind of
One day take away the other big takeaway is we're going to see a lot more competition
As people build services so
We'll talk about it and future shows but basically I talked to bear
Which is both a drug company and make sex
Cultural supplies
And they are trying to do agriculture as a service so
Growing plants as a service
And they're building a
Connected weed killing machine that
Basically identifies weeds and kills them
It sounds like what John Deere bought when it bought a company called Blue River Technologies last year
That's because it is
Exactly the same concept
What's interesting to me is both companies used to work
As parts of the supply chain so John Deere sold equipment to Farmers
What's happening is they're both trying to offer agriculture yields as a service which means they're both going
After the same
Market now
And we're going to see this this is just one example but we're going to see this play out
Again and again and again
With iot
So
Keep your eyes peeled for that it's going to be fun
And now it's time for
The iot podcast listener hotline
Is brought to you by Schlage
Picture of electronic locks
Schlage electronic locks
No more keeping track of extra house keys
Is each member of your family can access
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
If you want to leave a message for the IRT voicemail
Please give us a call at 5 1/2
To 4
It now
Hi Stacy and Kevin
My name is Christopher and I'm calling you from Broken Arrow Oklahoma
I was wondering
Good idea to segment all of your iot traffic in your home on to a specific SSID on your router
Segregating it from your computers
Wifi-connected TV devices
I'm thinking of segmenting at off onto a guest network from a security perspective but I don't want to lose functionality and
I think so I haven't started setting up smart home devices yet
But I plan to do so
In the near future
We are an apple household so my preference would be to use homekit
I have a router that can handle multiple guest Networks
So I can do this and still have a guest network available for my kids friends to use when they come over
I would love to hear your thoughts
Oh
Christopher this is such a good idea
It's so good
And
I'm very concerned that you're going to get frustrated
Which is exactly what happened to me
I decided to try to
You can do this in setting it up on a guest Network and ability to have multiple guest Networks
Great so the challenge comes in
When you want your
Phone2action
Sni4 geofencing
If you don't
Care about things like that
You actually should be
Okay cuz the challenges your phone's going to come in and connect to your regular Network as opposed to your
Gesnetwork
And in a lot of cases that can be a trigger for events to have
It's not always a tree
You will quickly find out what devices use it as a trigger
But if you're not Super King
It is actually possible and fairly easy to do
The challenges you won't encounter the hiccups until you
Get a particular device and I'm
Sorry to be so vague
I remember you went through the Senate
It did present some little
Challenges you know I I wonder about will I get my notifications can I still control all my devices from the phone and all that is around
Different networks that It's Tricky It's Tricky
So they were on the guest Wi-Fi network
Which basically turn them into when I was in my home
On my phone instead of being
They're my phone read it in the video doorbell extra seconds
Right
Those are the kind of things where
Didn't have the time
Which could be fun is if you have like the nest doorbell and it ties into your
Google home thing
Or your Android Television then you might actually get
Those are all in the same local network so it's going to bypass your phone anyway
If that makes sense so that actually might
Be a way to solve for some of that wood
Additionally
Yeah you're going to have to really think about this to see which products talk to each other and how you want to be notified
Use these products I'm in my Android TV does get information from my nest
Camera they are on the same network
I don't think it would work if they're on different Networks
Right but the key is if you have your computers and phones in the phones are really
The question
When I have Spotify playing on my phone actually
Can see all of my Sonos has in my Amazon echos and my Google homes
It can actually cast essentially to the I know it's not casting
Another ecosystem
But whatever
If it sees all those and I can just cast it to that
Which I couldn't if I was on a different
So again it's very huge case-specific
I say give it a whirl the worst is going to happen is you're going to have a couple devices you're going to have to go through those set of processes
Change the SSID
Which you know is it fun
It's not the end of the world
Yeah and I think
It's a question of balancing
Security vs. convenience
Really can you got it that's a personal decision at that point I pretty much have everything on the same network but I do I have
Security concerns so that I can start late
Recognize the importance of Christopher's questionnaire
Yes we are not
It all denigrating
New we can have the ability to hop onto
Networks
Not sure how that would work
Okay
Well
Christopher excellent question remember
We are here for you
We have probably made similar mistakes as you guys are trying to make a solution
263-7424
And now let's go to a message from our sponsor after which we will have our guest
Dominic
Sheena of Iota
He is on talking about
It is a distributed Ledger
You're going to find out
What is 4
Why we talk Blacklist and why we're trying to not focus on cryptocurrency aspects
Buy Internet of Things World dollars
World's largest coyote event taking place at Silicon Valley on May 14th through 17th take your iot strategy
Implementation to results as you learn from industry veterans and real-world case studies the agenda cover
We've got smart cities Industrial iot
Smart Home
Smart Construction and building energy and utilities connected cars and more prices
Midnight on March 2nd and if you're listening on Thursday know the prices go up to now
Night at midnight that's midnight March 2nd to learn more and register to attend visit iot world
Event.com back to the Internet of Things podcast
Is your host
Cheater
Who is the co-founder
The creator of
Hey everyone
Probably aware of what I owed is
Quickly Dominos
Oops
Jeff Corso is basically different
Improvement
Stupid technology
And the main focus of an IRA
3D unleash the full potential
But first
Let's talk about
Everybody who's familiar with black jeans and things like
Pointing at cereal
You guys are
Little bit different because your text
What does that mean
We are
Technologist
Realized
Issues we have issues
We have to minor illegal
It is really not helping us
Beaufort improve 2 blocks any soft
3D make a scalable and bring it to Industry
N2 production
When is we we looked at the Block
It shouldn't just be like the sequential change
What are some
Ways to achieve
What is consensus of what is true and what is not true
An executive
Dad we done came up with this Dakar
Know every
Participant in an effort to execute
Participate in his validation
And Confirmation Transaction what is music
Iota
When you executed for Zaxby's
To confirm to transaction
History
Blue Datsun two transaction
Increasing
You have to pay no transaction fees
What is miso
That transaction
Because now we can truly do micropayments but
Scalability issue
Limited to the block sizes
To the Block in troubles what is real
Okay so we're going to bring some of that down because with
Bitcoin and other traditional blockchain Technologies
The more information you have the
Longer it takes
How are you need to actually valid
Cheer
I am saying hey if I wanted validate something I also
Scepter promise
We're actually validate
Behind me
That's awesome
Right exactly
So we can look at this
Nothing
And everything is stopped
And the beautiful thing about I already said we are no longer limited to a single pipe
Midas a new architecture
And the main reason why are you
Horizontally
What is means that now is
Okay now I keep reading that the number of iota's out there
Have been set
And so I'm trying to understand
It works with the
Validation
Behind us in so I think there is
There's a mix of
What Iota supposed to be doing and
Cryptocurrency world
It's a little confusing for me
Reading for anyone
Participate
Dish Network
What is osmosis
Currency that is intrinsic
What is protocol
Bitcoin today
For you to be able to transfer
But the thing is now the beautiful thing about this that you can utilize
True things
Is cryptocurrency dead
And if it contains data
Use case that comes out of that
Different sentence structures
So the children was just a way for you guys to raise money
Notes
Exit right
The token for us
Cuz all vision is this machine economy and what is machine economies now
Machine
Future
To hold
But the thing is now when
He comes to this machine
Participate
Can contribute
Reconstruct
Earning money by
Capitation to a car dancing
Or something like that
Meetup cryptocurrency
There's no censorship
Is nobody controlling it
Undisputed peer-to-peer pushing machine
But this gets into a deeper issue
Almost all blotchy
Chains
Effort out there which is
Are correlated so strong
The people are focused on the value
You're choking as opposed to what
You can do
Entire blocks
Exchanging new money streets
Everyone join two blocks
Images to make money
This is Teresa
What is technology
Fundamental issues in society
What's Sophia should we trust
What's the name of new business
At this point
To Pakistan
Circulation
Sick of it
Which is why we're really focused on his pregnant
We want to bring a Yoda ink
Industry
Focus more on
Concept
Accomplished
3 first of all an education about the
Concrete work on a product
Roadmap and strategy
So we can really bring this
Angel production
Purchase are useless if there's no
That is true
Need something to allow machines to talk to each other and transact
At least information is not act
Talk to me about
Customers your users are looking
And the first ball is over the air updates
Example
Over-the-air updates
Today has over there
From now on
Police investigator
On the vehicle
I did not have problem
We can read it and able to secure transmission of data
End-to-end verifiability
Dirt bikes
Security
So we know we stopped at what you started
Each point in time
And we can really make sure that this audit
Canopy security
Investigation
Brisket
First witches
How do you say
Please
Right then is part of your ass
What kind of software needs to be running on
Verizon iot
Look into the blankets all because of you could solve has a secret shared with
Antibiotic
Books on payments payments
The most important
Components for vehicle in the future sister wallet
Once a car has
Autonomous
It's not what your car can do is to Juanita
Can start earning money
RadioShack
Mobility
Uber like Angus place that has wallets
Automatically
Micropenis
Tesla
Will not allow me
With my future automated Tesla
Ecosystem
Infrastructure
PlayStation 4
Electricity
What is a very interesting
Focusing on is
Start collecting data to cancel it
Open Marketplace
Screw that have
New Revenue stream
To relearn
Money
I love this idea
A lot but it also gets into this
The world seems to be with iot moving to subscription-based
He is very transactional base
Awesome
Company I don't see
I would much rather have
Beriberi
The thing is all about
And if there's a business model
Behind the motivation of data
What's the most efficient way to actually be able to earn money
And so there's always a
Different business
What time is it
Unleashed
Pencil
Eddie Money
What is an interesting or interesting
Completed
Now if you do micro
Payments
You can read it at the spine granularity
You can pay per use this unit
And now we're truly Edition
It because I T
Machines
That makes sense
Directions
MTG Pirate Bar
Which ecosystem
You don't know when it's going to need
How long do
You think so we get there
What's a long time to move
Models
For software for example to subscription models and now
What you're proposing / resource unit is even more extreme
The question is
Look at the cryptocurrency song
Because
The biggest problem we have today's we are not
Ecosystem
Adoption
Difficult Odyssey is
I think of some different solution how we can actually anybody's mic
IndyCar
Chico
What's even more important that is it to rethink about what
In which areas of
Everybody's first adoption
Payments
When it comes to
Computation
Asian market places
That's where we going to see the person
I've been covering datamark
Play Systems Lake
I want to see 2008
Lighting
Loving day tomorrow
Forever
And they never happy
At first it was an infrastructure issue
Antitrust issue
The marketplace
Don't actually want to contribute their data
Main difficulty becomes.
What is date of birth
Bicycle
And nobody has been able to solve
Subscription services
But that is not really an issue for potential
I saw think now everything is kind of
Coming together right
Git
ITX become United
Walking Dead
Tell me remake
Impossible machines
Collecting data in stata
On the market
Different Technologies
PEMDAS convergence now
I do think that
Now is the right time for a market-based establish yourself
But the difficulty August
How do you make a pot
Entire Industries to adopt
B1 bomber
Speakers
If you have peace pregnant
And that's why
In my opinion we as a non-profit
Supination
With no electric incentive other than
Foster and ocean Marketplace
Bring it to the mall
As long as it's open source and we have
I do think the Gnostic
What about
Privacy that's been
Corporations against
For a while
Because it's so transparent
We have some
Wonders
American taco
What is Albany
You still up just called
Mosque of indicated messaging
Toyota de Mexico
Encrypted data
You still got the same
Immutability
Authorized
Can we decide Taylor
Gordon State College
Okay final question
What do I need app
The edge
To run
Toyota
Right now
We still have his longer product roadmap to actually make sure that I ordered wanted
Best Buy
Frosted collaborate with bigger companies like boss like boys
Is Ricky Schroder green green
Ecosystem
Because we should interpret the iodine Note phone
Where are you
Integrated personnel
This machine
Coffee machine
I need to be able to do is to sign
They can have a wallet
Send it to Zach
Processor
Boston basics
You know I run a bunch of different gateways in my house
What ones could I install
I have the
Openhab
How can I do this
With the manufacturer
So we want to send
Toyota standard
For example
But today's Almighty
So so I don't think it should be
Songs you can run Java
How can I get Iota running on my own
You can just don't get it
Four clients can run
Good start
Big goal right now is it
Reupholster this innovation
We want to emphasize
New applications
The sandbox is super simple to build
Application with iota
You can have this
Easy install in your app
Nuckols
Might have to start thinking about that
Myself thank you
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy
Coyote
Will see you next week