Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel and we have
An awesome show for you we're going to get messy
Bluetooth
Which just announced their.
Mesh networking standard
We also got to talk about Google class baby it's
We got the Amazon echos features in an alarm clock
We've got a security
Got a big funding for an iot development platform
The FBI warning people about connected toys and some
Low-power wide area network
Action
And
Our Guest this week is
Can colder above the Bluetooth say we're going to get even deeper into what Bluetooth mesh
Memes for you
We also go to a message from our sponsor to discuss
Why you're connected locks
Don't always work with
With the Amazon
And now
Let's take a moment
For a message from another one of ours
Affiliated monitoring
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about Affiliated monitoring
In response to a trigger from any connected device Affiliated to professionally trained live agents can follow
Call and reach out to your customers their loved ones and local emergency services Affiliated works with hundreds
Smart home security health and other iot businesses visit affliated.com
Coyote to read a case study and how they help the connected car startup turn an idea into a
Depriving business with a 100 million dollar exit that's Affiliated. Com
/ iot
Additionally we hear the podcast our booking ads for
Before so
If you have any questions or want to advertise on the show
Female
Andrew at iot podcast
DACA
Alright Kevin
Let's not going out
YouTube
Yeah we've been waiting for this for a while
Yeah yeah I know our guest from the Bluetooth Sig is going to really get into
The news here but just to
If you belie level Bluetooth
Will now support Mesh networking
Show Bluetooth devices instead of being
Peer-to-peer or one device to one
Prettymuch introduces many-to-many which is crazy
A good for
Oh geez I mean Smart Homes
Industrial industrial
Yeah this gets Bluetooth into the industrial world it's been
Excited about
The one thing we don't address
In
Interview
Is
What is this mean for Olive
The other stand
So stay tuned for all of the stuff about it
Things called mesh models we talked about
How it does intelligent routing
We talked about
Use cases and will even talk about things like
IPv6 a bandwidth since
So there is a lot
In the interview
Well I haven't heard the interview yet I'll hear it after the show
But so if you guys have talked about this that's so we can skip this but I'm curious about the
Power requirements I'm curious about if this will require new Bluetooth Hardware devices which I don't think it will I think it
Will actually work with
Bluetooth 4 and 5 devices
Better already exist
So am I correct in that
Kevin you're spoiling the interview
Yes you are correct
So it's only going to work over Bluetooth low energy
He's not going to work over classic
What else did you want
Power I'm curious about any power
So we get into how it conserves power that's actually a huge portion of the interview
And then
When it comes to how it's going to be implemented
That really depends on
Yourself
So it goes all the way back to Bluetooth LE 4.
So it's backwards compatible
Provided your silicon provider update their chip
With the software needed to R
Gotcha
Okay okay well those are two key questions I was curious about before we actually answered the question you originally asked which is
What does this mean for
Other Technologies because
When I saw this news hit was the first thing I thought of and
I may be wrong I'll let you tell me
But I merely thought of Z-Wave because he waited always had National working as far as I can remember
And
What so happen to Z-Wave
So there's three Mesh networking technologies that matter in
The Smart Home
Lesso the industrial
Definitely the smart
Zippy
Z-Wave
And
I feel like Z-Wave is a little bit on the outs in talking to people
You have seen things like Eero supporting
Thread in their routers
Comcast is actually supporting
Thread in some of its Xfinity home gateways
So I look
If that is
Part of that so I'm like
Yeah I know
For the longest time I was at on-site anti Z-Wave and not against any technology that solves a problem effectively
But I've never felt confident of Z-Wave would come out as a
A leader
In the space
Just because mainly because I should say
It's not as prevalent in devices and by devices I mean the phones and tablets and things that people use to control
Other things
With all those devices have Wi-Fi all in my Bluetooth
And the Bluetooth was lacking match so does he weigh
I started warming up to it
But now that Bluetooth has mesh it's almost like that whole Advantage is negated to me
Right and I think honestly
A bigger
Question would be what is this due to sick because he pees really popular
In lighting
It is the radio protocol behind like
Your Hue Lights and a lot of other
Even industrial lighting
Thanks
It is a mesh Network
Work as well as a low-power mission
And
Bluetooth is coming
That's where we stand right here
Any advantage Bluetooth is going to have here is that it's in all these phones and other devices
Today
If they can be updated
And many of them can be
Then you're going to see
If you're in an industrial setting
Probably actually won't
Control lot of stuff
From your phone
Rihanna Stay
But
There might be an advantage to having someone
Contribute
Using their phone
I can see cases where
Hpac system
Someone could be like hey
They're still I'm not writing any of these other Technologies off by any means
Because I think there's still some advantages
I know the zigbee is really low power I I don't
You know about
I'm sorry Z-Wave I was thinking cuz I looked it up earlier this morning
I'm so there may be power advantages
To have
AZ wave
Chip inside
But that's not necessarily a bad thing that is
Doesn't necessarily a bad thing because not every application needs
You know lots of megabits
Is per second
Trooper
And there may be some cost advantages in terms of the of the chips themselves it again like I haven't seen any compare
So I'm not writing it off yet
I just
That's kind of where my head's at right now
I think it will remain to be seen
Honestly
Bluetooth is going to
Conquer all
Just because
This is still very new
There's still a lot of unanswered questions even in the current spec
About how it handles some of the
Routing requirements and scalability requirements
I think it about
5 months maybe 6 months will
Kind of start seeing how this is going
The industry
Actually think
The more interesting question
Is how does
Bluetooth
Thread kind
Because one of the things Bluetooth doesn't do
And thread does to
You can talk directly to the internet
Bluetooth
Could do that but it
Doesn't nimesh situations
Won't
So
I'm kind of thinking about this and I'm like
I think this is an excellent technology
A lot of devices are already going to come out and support it
Today
And
It will be awesome because like right now my Bluetooth switches for example
If I'm not on the same floor as the light
I can't control
Commensurate
That's just
Cell
We shall see
Let us move on to other
Exciting news
Google Glass
Google class which is also Bluetooth capable
Google glass cutter because I thought it was dead for
Good reason it was very
Consumer-focused
Google did the whole Explorer Thing 2
Early adopters Peyton want to pay $1,500 for
This
Camera and small processor and battery and sensors to
I didn't want to admit it but yeah
I still do an in a dresser drawer somewhere I have the original Google Glass
Edition Explorer Edition
Yes back when we work for a gigolo
Google home actually
Purchase that was for me to cover because we thought this could be very interesting space
And it is an interesting space
Suggested develop the way Google thought it would back in
I don't know 2013 or so
But quietly Google has continued to work on Google Glass for different type of customer
Mainly that is Enterprise and Industrial cuss
Mercy
They just announced that
Hey we've been doing this and it's actually working pretty well so
Companies such as GE Boeing DHL have all been using it doctors have been using it
DHL for example says that they've been dating Kris their supply chain efficiency by 15% where is
In healthcare it's reduced paperwork
Got loads by 20% and allows doctors spend more time with patients so so there is a glass Enterprise Edition that it's
Targeted towards I think the Right audience for that product
If your consumer nothing's really changed here but
Amateur
The workforce that you want to enable with some type of AR
Or additional information that they
The glance of an I know it's it's pretty interesting stuff
Well so this
I think remember how computers personal computers started out in the workplace and migrated out
I think this idea of heads-up displays
Arso
Both high cost
Originally
It's a very big
Difference is a huge social
User interface ship
So I think starting at the Enterprise make sense for a
Don't think of this Justice
Glasses right they just heads up display and not having to look at a screen is really compelling
And this is technology that is
Floyd
It's also technology
Microsoft is using
With manufacturers
Using its hololens
That's Amore
One of the big questions I have about things like a r is
Do I really want to look at
At the world through my phone
Play now
I was shocked actually when Google launched these for consume
Cuz I was like
This is this going to violate all kinds of social contracts in
Did just what you did
But but but I think
The way I
Look at the product when it first launched for consumers was
Very much like I look at Android Wear and other
Smart watches
That is
Contextual information at a glance
If you look at it that way it sort of makes sense unfortunate did much more than that such as recording people
A video and so on and
We know light indicator that people knew you were recording them
This Enterprise Edition actually does have a little light so that people are aware
So
I got it just was the wrong
Form for that concept
Yes and this has
Better networking
Faster better processor longer battery life
It's got a camera that's 8 megapixels
So
Icing
In Enterprises are also going to be able to pay this price and then when we get economies of scale
Come down
I was at the Snapchat glasses sold
No we don't I don't I don't
Exist
Elsa real quick just cuz you were mentioning some
Inspect I noticed that there's an Intel atom
Inside witch
Surprise me
Yes yes because the original glass was kind of built
Apollon smartphone gots
Which made sense low power
But it was capable of doing what needed to be done
This actually has an Intel atom inside
Well in that might be because of software can a lot of enterprise software is an arm
I'm compatible yet
I don't know
And you know these guys
Presumably you can charge your glasses every night if you're in a workspace here
You don't think they take them home I employees use the method asking or on the
Production line or wherever they are doctors in the office
So you got it you know
As long as you can get
I don't even know a full 8 hours or baby
I mean if you're on a production line you probably have a
Prescribed luncheon
Probably charge
Okay so that was exciting
I am stoked about the return of glass in what feels like
Immortal dragons
Gradual rollout
Tell me about
This alarm
Because it looks pretty
Yeah so that's a Kickstarter I say that right up front that has already exceeded its goal
So it is going to
Continue
It's the
Sandman Doppler and I had not heard of this
Sandman company before but apparently they came up with a guy Kickstarter or successful Kickstarter
Previously
Turn alarm clock like a Smart Alarm Clock
That did not have
The Voice services that Amazon Echo
Rides
I don't want to say miss a Disney and that's why I said it that way
I'm so this is kind of interesting to me it's it's literally an alarm clock that
When you look at the screen or the display
It looks like an old-time LED or I'm sorry LCD
Alarm clock
But it has a pair of speakers I think 14 why so they probably
Allowed
And it's got the boy Services built-in as quick buttons that you can program to do
Cast
Instead of using your voice to say can you say
I think it's great miss a turn the lights out
In house
You can just program that to a button or several of those buttons
The screen display does show your your weather
Which is kind of nice the day of the week
It also has a little light bar which is customizable
To indicate certain things so you do you want to know if the stock market up or down you can program that light bar to psi
Show green or red
Obviously it's got a microphone built-in so you can speak to it
And what I thought was really smart of these guys
They put in 6 USB ports in the back of it
So you can charge your
Mobile devices off of this thing
And even more interesting Lee
You can pull three of those out at a time and replace them to a different form factors have the old USB a
Words you can put those in it
USBC you can put those in
Really really clever design
It's been funded
It looks like it will not be available to backers for about a year
Unfortunately we're just kind of a bummer
But if you want one on the cheap you can beta test that you're not going to get final Hardware ever
Beta test
Hardware in design for $89
You can still get
Essendant Doppler for 119 in advance
Don't know if they said the
The MSRP
At this point they have a
Now I will say that feels
I got a.
Then it's great So for 50 bucks
I can tell it to do all these things so I'm sitting here wondering
You know having a clock display
Is nice in the middle of the night I'm not going to ask
It feels like a lot of money just to get additional
Port Saint.
It's certainly going to sound better to
Okay well that's true okay
Yammy just has a pair of 14 watt speakers where is if I had to guess the.
You probably looking that more like us almost like a smartphone speaker week maybe two watsapp best
Oh and the quick access actually can do several
Thanks it's not just one thing
Okay so
Basically I don't
Dubai another device
You're really get it
I get it believe me I'm all
Newport Centre mall tapped out myself between the Amazon tap
Couple of God's Echo Google home
So this would have to be different but it appeal it was different enough to appeal to me
At that price
I haven't backed up yet but
Think I just might
Okay
Well
You know the other thing is
This looks pretty bright so
Hopefully they got it like that like most smartphones it has a sensor in there that can read the ambient light and
Dims automatically based on that so
Oh and it's powered by the next things chip
I love the chip
The southern
Has become the next thing
Makes a $9
Development
No chip Pro is a little bit more but
I freaking love that come
All right very exciting
Justice
Let's talk about
Now that we're done with her
Gadget fetish
Let's go into
00 security vulnerabilities
Devil's ivy
Oh my gosh
And this is something is a vulnerability that affects
IP base security
Cameras mostly but
Don't they all
That's the security cameras have been connected to the internet
Are long time forever before we even thought about all the stuff
So this one is
Particularly nasty because it is a vulnerability in open source software that is used by
A lot
Southeast security
The prevalence
Of the vulnerabilities
However
It doesn't appear too easy to exploit
Redken
That yeah that's that's correct time in its
Once a device is compromised you actually have to have the user like uploader or get it like a tool Big File
It's not likely it's going to be exploited it's more of a buffer crash type thing
Overrun
But it's still not good
So it's not as nasty as a lot of other things we can make the Mirai bot for example
Talking about months and months ago
It's nothing like that but it's still concerning
I believe it was axis Communications
They say that about 249 of their
Camera models
Perfected they've already patched them
And they have
Shared information with the
Industry at large on how to fix things but it's going to be up to each individual Hardware
Maker to update firmware cuz that's the only way to fix
Speaking of the FBI
People about
Connected toys
This is like a recurring theme with them I feel like it's once a year if I got time to other people about those smart toys
Or just smart things the FBI has done a
A warning about
Devices in general
This specific device is about privacy
Which
It's important it is important
But it basically goes in and it's like hey consumer
Lays out why iot toys are vulnerable
Why you should care
And then it's got a section called what should I do
And I'm really
Hat
I'm cheesed about this because the wind should I do section
Can is incredibly long
It is
Just
Mind-boggling that you would think a consumer would do this
So some of those things are research if your toys can receive firmware software updates and security patches
If they can ensure these
Irenic that's great
Right
Research where user data is stored with the company third-party services or both
I am
Quarter have asked Mattel for data on
This type of thing
Including they also talked about
Do they use authentication when pairing a device via Bluetooth and do they use encryption when transmitting data from the Wi-Fi access point in
Why is reporter have sent this data to me
These questions
Mattel
Mattel was like
Feeling like a consumer can just call up Mattel and be like hey I want to buy this
Connected Barbie doll for twenty bucks
So
Yeah this this to me points out
That we've got a big dick
Pinhole in consumers
So I totally agree with you as I look at some of the other questions and I'll read the disclosures and privacy policies to see if a company is victim
My Cyber attack
What will the company do if they were you know will they notify you
Where's your data being stored
All great questions but just as you said
People are not going to call and ask about that in the few that do
Where can I get the answers
So here's a thought just a thought I don't
Like to get into
Regulations and policy and whatnot but in this case I'm going to throw it out there
Should there be answers to those questions at least a high level
On the packaging for all of these devices
Yes this gets into this idea of having a some sort of labeling
First Data
And I totally
We should have
Basic consumer
Info for the stuff
And I feel like the FBI saying
It is not like Congress is going to
Hawaii
Thinking maps
I do think maybe the industry could get together in
You know some basics
Encryption
To the cloud
Today within the home
Where is the data stored
Your TOS is actually going to happen
Information about
Is it shared with her
Third-party data
Companies
And you don't even expecting people to read through all of that to get there as kind of
Not right
That's her
Fallout 4
Quick bits of news
Particle which is an iot developer
The platform
That offers
Wi-Fi Cellular Connections it's a pretty
We talked to them before Zach's Apollo the CEOs been on
Show
Erase 20 million dollars from spark capital
They are
They're doing really well
I was surprised so particle has built
Is easy
To put in development
And they have about a hundred and twenty thousand people that are building iot products
That's pretty significant there in a bunch of products
Ideo uses them Looney lunar design
Mindtribe
Actually power that Met Gala
IBM Watson
Dressed LED dress for the
Costumes
Yeah so they were there and uses them to track their
Campus bicycles
Pretty cool
Lot of money for them
I am very excited
Because
My gosh building iot connected products is hard and
2 days to a company that has started up trying
Easier and in
Donald learned a lot of
Las Vegas has a
NB iot Network
That is building when conjunction with people
So I thought
Vegas fan
So I thought this was interesting they're going to use it for
Smart cities efforts in there doing a partnership Las Vegas is doing a partnership with call, derickson
As part of this nb iot Network
They're going to
Disconnect flood in storm
Drainage sensors
LED lighting and some
Weather temperatures
An environmental Network or a sensor for the weather
Hot hot and hot
Sometimes it's cold and rainy
But yes normally
All right and then
Final bit of news in the
Iot wide area network business Comcast
Has launched their machineq
Product which is a lorawan
A worldwide
In
12 more cities
So
This is big news about a year ago Comcast took a chunk of Senate
Which is a company that makes the Laura chips
And they said they were like Hey we're going to try this
Basically they are expanding it to Seattle
A bunch of other cities and the idea that is not to create a city-wide
Lauren at work but to create these kind of private Lauren that works in like
Manufacturing spaces
For warehouses
I think it would be kind of a really interesting
I guess thing to watch
So Kevin I think we've done a great job this week on the show
And in the coming weeks we actually want to do
Consumer-oriented
We answer your questions
Segments
I would love
For you guys if you have questions you guys are really great about sending them
But keep sending them to info
At iot podcast. Com
Kevin and I are going to try to answer some of your questions on the air
And now
A message from our sponsor haverwood we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast
But the message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Allegiant the makers of Schlage
Locks and I have Rob Martin
Who is the futurist
OverWatch League
Here to talk to us
About the smart home by Rob
Hi Stacy thanks for having
I am super excited so
Let's dig into this idea of things in the connected home
Working with Eva
Everything else
How do you think about that
Well
I think there is a lot of
Misconceptions around
How things actually work today versus what's advertised
And media
The truth is is that Integrations the fancy word for the ability to work with other connected stuff
Our kind of fickle
You're best off select
Testing devices that are going to suit a very specific purpose for you
First
And then looking at
What types of recipes routines robots whatever you want to call them
You can connect with
Later on
Now you guys so far has decided not to integrate
With the unlock function on your
Can you explain kind of your thinking there
Stacy Schlage is a security company for
So we're a little different than some other people who are focused on simply the convenience
And comfort
Of the Smart Home
We're concerned
About the
The security of anyone behind that door
And we want to be certain
That your intent
Is to unlock
So what the voice assistance or next Generation technology
We support things
Dislike door status
Locking
But unless we can
Can be 100% certain that is you
We won't unlock the door
Do you think we'll ever get there I do
I think we will get there I think there's lots of
Nursing technology
And as a futurist it's my job to explore that
So I can say
With some certain
Going to eat we're starting to see some really interesting technology come for
That is moving us closer and closer
To be able to do that with great certainty
Do you want to tell me what those Technologies are
So Stacy there are so many exciting new technologies headed our way
It is a futurist it's my job
Explore all of them
Weather at the
Facial recognition
All different
Types of biometric
Shoes
Both persistent and non-persistent Technology
There is just a
Wide variety of Technology
See that you're going to see
Embedded
In many different types of
Security devices that are not only going to make it
Easier more convenient and simple
But potentially even more secure than it is today
Alright Rob where can I go to find out more
You can go to slate.com to learn more
Or if you're
Interested in our thought leadership tour want to learn a little bit more about what I do
You can go to slate.com
Thought leadership
Or follow me on Twitter on Atchley Pinterest
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Ken kolderup who is VP of marketing for the Bluetooths
Hi Ken
How are you doing today
I am doing very very well
Thanks for the opportune
I really
We are super excited because we have been talking about
Bluetooth
Mesh
For what feels like
For two years
You guys just announced the Bluetooth mesh Spectre
We are so excited
This feels like
It was made for the Internet of Things
So
Talk to us
What is
Guess you're right it was made for the inter
And so specifically it is we are adding an additional Network topology
This one happens to be a Mesh networking
Topology so now what that means it allows
You'll have many to many device can you
What that means
Is it really suited for applications like building automation
Wireless sensor networks asset tracking things like that new
Have up-and-coming Market
It's where you have
Tens or hundreds or
Or even thousands of device
Is that somehow need to
Securely and reliably connect
So it builds on all the other capabilities Bluetooth has
Which is already supports a kind of a coin
The point Network topology
Broadcast topology
And now with this we are adding
A mesh Network
Anthropologie
Okay in a little bit we're going to get into
How you guys are doing the
Before that
Let's try to
Focusing on
How this relates to
The other flavors of
Bluetooth so now we have Bluetooth
Classic Blues
And then we have Bluetooth low energy
Where does MASH fit in with
Actually there are only two flavors of Bluetooth that stays
True with the introduction of mass
For those of you that or where we started Bluetooth
21 years ago in the initial
Labor a Bluetooth is something that is called basic rate enhanced data rate
Or breeder
And that one so it was a really good technology and still is today or crazies kind of
Continuous wireless connection
Stream audio over
And that's what's the technology today behind
The whole wireless audio industry
Weather in headsets
Speakers are in car systems
It also supports a simple
Point-to-point Network topology for one to one device
That's a really really good Mark
Then back in
2010 timeframe
We launched the second
Flavor of Love
Which is
Cold low energy
Or Bluetooth LE
It is a yellow wire breeder was for
Continuous Wireless connect
Bluetooth LE is form or short bursts Wireless
It really was done to enable
Really really low power
Consumption it was initially targeted at at what the time was this nation
Connected
Device Market
Wle came along and they also supported that
The same point
The point Network
Topology
But now it was really for
What kind of data transfer services rather than streaming services and was
Again targeted that connected device mark
Interesting thing about Bluetooth LE is when we launched it
Not only did it also
Support point-to-point
Bre Dr
I mean also introduced
Another topology called Broad
Really around one too many
Medication
What does evolved into over the last couple of years left
People are really using for that or is this whole kind of Beacon Market
Yeah those kind of point-of-interest beacons there's item fighting deconcilis Technologies you now.
See out there that use Bluetooth is a way to find your lost keys or your wallet or your phone or even using deacons as a way to find you
Your way around an airport
Or Conference Center or Stadium
Broadcast
Last apology
For one too many
And that leaves us where we are today with mash
What mesh is
It's not another flavor of Bluetooth
It's just an additional Network
Pieology Austin
Available for Bluetooth low energy
So does Bill on top of Ellie
So mess is all about how you can enable now
Dementia before tens hundreds or even thousands of Bluetooth LE devices
To be able to exchange messages together
Anna Faris
Usher reliable in
Available way
All right
So Bluetooth classic
No mesh
Bluetooth LE
Jasmine
And it's going to go back
How far to what versions of
I decided to develop the Bluetooth mess Fest
Medication such that they would work back to you
Any Bluetooth LE that was 4. O or higher
This is really helpful
And for those of us who are super excited
Fashion I'm going to include myself in this category
I'm looking forward to it because I am
Excited about being able to control lights in my smart home
Bluetooth light bulbs
Without having to go to the floor there actually are
Which is right now.
Fireball
That's just me but what else are people thinking
Think about using
A lot of it
But let me go a little bit more into that so building Automation in general is an area where we see a lot
Olive activities that's looking
Bluetooth mesh to there
Then there's the wireless sensors O2 sensor Market in general
Especially kind of in industrial use case
Where they're looking to evolve their sensor Network
Wireless or economic
Endure being able to add more devices
Really helping out in there and they also NASA
Certain areas where
This technology really makes a lot of
Those are three big bucket areas where we see a lot of act
Building automation
I use that term relatively
Broadly there cuz there's residential which is
Is the smart home when what you kind of brought up
And which will be right in the middle of that as well
But when I'm really excited about is more than
Commercial area.
Where there are a lot of companies now that are
Targeting that for
Whether it's lighting or heating cooling or security or so forth
Aurelia doing a lot of sophisticated automation
Control
For the building
And in their we're seeing a lot of energy where the initial thing is I'm actually on Commercial Lighting
We're seeing a lot of movement
In commercial lighting
Because the business case is pretty straightforward therefore
People wear
There's this whole other changes of what right now people going from complex fluorescent
And those buildings over to LED
At that time going over to wireless
Control makes a lot of sense
Is a lot of kind of governmental and local regulation going in for smart buildings and energy efficient buildings and so forth
A lot of things and planets aligning right now for that commercial building Automation and lighting specifically
Getting a lot of traction so you'll see a lot of activity in there
A few questions
What and these can be quick answer
Bluetooth mesh because it's compatible with Bluetooth low energy that means it is
Lord
Erase or rather
I won't be able to do audio
That's right these
Mesh networks not just
Just Bluetooth
Despedida lobbies low-power mesh Network
Really intended at those kinds of yusuke
Amounts of data around facilities in math where the domain of other other Technologies are
This one is really a
In these areas we talked about where it's at
Building Automation and sensor networks rehab
Lots and lots and lots of devices
They need to communicate with each other but that's generally not
Streaming large amounts of data
It's kind of command-and-control have a net
Will Bluetooth mesh take advantage of the greater range
Bluetooth 5
The initial set of specifications do not look to Leverage
Some of the princess
The broadcast data capacity enhanced
Incurred in five
Are not part of the initial messed up
Doing four or Mash those aren't imperative
Sure
The biggest complaint
I've heard
About Bluetooth as a mesh Network
Up until this moment in time has been that it is a flood based as opposed to a routing
Bass network
End
Basically what that means
It's just shouting his messages to everyone all the time
I'm in that can get
That can overload assist
Right as opposed to having intelligent routing which
Is a little bit less flexible you have to plan for it there's
There's constraints on both sides right
What you guys are
Done is y'all have
Created this
Intelligent
So explain to me how this is going
That's right so you a couple of years ago in when the group started this
Zephyr to create the mess specifications that was absolutely Abby imagined
What's the message
Transmission
You do around it approached or you do a flooded
And when they went
Through the whole exercise of looking at the requirements
Sports
Dale and reliability
Simplicity and everything else
It was really couldn't get there
With the route is broke
So I'll go I'll go back to the example of
Commercial Lighting where I have to have a
Switch
Turn on
Hundreds of lights all the same time massive multiki
Yelp
And you really can't get there with a router
Show is agreed that applied approach
Wireless mesh Networks
Very very unique
Fundamentally different
And so have the
Requirements in different capabilities
It was determined after that the flood base approach was
Was uniquely suited for that
The kinds of scale the kind of reliability so it's inherently
Multipass
It's inherently selfish
Inherently no points
Failure rather than trying to engineer those things
Now you mention you got to be careful though
In a flood approach this deal with some of the power Quest
So those are those are things we done into what we call a manager
Blood approach for message
So for instance simple time to live counter
To make sure that message
Propagation doesn't
Go unnecessarily
Message caching so you don't get into an unnecessary looping they're looking a message
We have the relay function itself
Is actually not mange
Date when you provision device you declare whether that's
It's going to be relay messages or not
You wouldn't have a an on main power node for instance relay message
It would be too much energy
So is a developer I can set my
A device to be
Router
Have router functionality versus
Not or
Provisioning a Mains powered device
You would probably
Give that the real
Here's a message
There's not for itself
Then it will then retransmit that
QuikTrip is a sensor
Hanging out on battery I don't want that
Stop by when
Heavy duty cycle over there would be associated with having to have that on and listen
For those messages
OU more than that you mentioned a great one there like a sensor that sitting here in a coin cell battery
Even if it's not real aim you need to make sure that doesn't happen
Sit there and have it
Your radio all the time even listening
So there are other additional
Functions that can be
Provisions into any
So if you are a battery-powered
Sensor
You be given a look all the low power notes
And there's also a
Companion function called a friend
What you would provision into other main power device
Surround it
Low power
Node wakes up with this function in it first thing it does is look for a friend around it
They set up a relationship
And that one Indian down messages that are busy or Destin
For the low-power note to friend hold on to it and then that that low power
Minutes
And then retrieve this message
Messages from the friend
There's techniques in these other Solutions use not yours
Somewhat similar techniques but it's all around allowing for these
Battery-powered nose to operate for many many years on this
Single coin cell
Oh my God that sounds
Very useful and totally applicable towards
I'm surprised you're selling but it also sounds so incredible
Is this something that I now have to figure out is part of the spec
Or is this something that you guys are going to do for meat like
How much of this do I need to do
That's right there along with the Bluetooth
Your radio you're going to get the mess stack if you
UL weather yeah there's many ways
The source that whether it's from the Silicon provider Independence
Within there
And then there's a provisioning tool that is provided to you as well and that's what's response
Possible for when you provision a device making that a very straightforward
Exercise
How does this handle IPv6
There is work underway to allow my pecan Chevy with a Bluetooth generic
But what we're trying to do with this is us
You know that I could get for use for many many use cases
That's not what's getting you so for actually enabling a mess
Based messaging
So how do I
Yo transmitter
Messages for command-and-control purposes
Many many many devices
That is not leveraging ipv4
Rb6 is part of that
Bright so I won't have a match that spans different IP
Snow
Got it okay
So
There's been a lot of conversation about different
Profiles
And I don't think you guys you call a mesh models
And there's one for lighting that's been developed
Tell me a little bit about what this is because it feels a little
So if you're used to Bluetooth you've heard
The car the profile turned
Before that's how we talked about whether they were gapped profiles or the traditional profiles for b r e d r l e
That was proposed to find how Communications happen between
Do devices using that simple point.
Wing connection
Now when you go to mash that hire kind of app
Application layer
Now if you will
So what defines a node on the network in the behavior of that node on the network that's done with something called
Model model
And the way that we approach that
Is really a very powerful way where there's a number of generic models that you use to them to find what the big
Behavior of a device on the network is Caesar buried
Very simple things were talking to on and off you up down those types of generic definition
Define envy
Library of math models that were that are beans part of the specification
So if I have a mesh model for and you can have one for like lighting
What other models
Generics that are just for buy everything and then there are some areas that have been gone into more
4 of theirs lighting is a big Focus
Did we mention
Sensors the whole set of definition
Surround sensors so that's the other
Really really big initial use cases
So you'll see stop an asset tracking and other other areas
Is well okay
So now
I hear the phrase mesh models and I think
Zigbee profiles
If you are
He may not have been a huge student of zigbee profiles but you know there's like
Home automation lights
However many datos that they had
And it was very confusing because not all of your Zippy devices would actually work together
When you brought them home
Unless they were part of the same
Profile
And so when I'm hearing
You talk about
Mesh models I am getting
Flashback to zigbee profiles and JB did away with them
7-Zip III
It still scares me so I'm worried that I
Bluetooth which is
Works really well
The Mind trust that has done that it is
Do they come up with an approach is
Incredible power
Incredibly flexible and addresses the
Concerns you have about interoperability
Right so
For instance just to talk through this
54 seconds
Which is actually when you provision a device on network
It goes and does
Theory of all the capabilities of that device and then that makes
Just all come together so it's it takes the
To the actual person who's doing the provisioning weather that's
Consumer rated commercial contacts
All that it's all that end or the developer that's all in place that does come together
If I got a product that is running running a lighting Bosch model
And I've got another product that is running a sensor measure
Can they talk to each other
Isn't that comes into the role of the provisioner that the provisions that will not a person so this is the provisioning configuration tool to get the
You get supplied with when you
By this message the system
These are system
Institutions are being presented to you
Aquarius device ID knows what kind of device it is okay it's alright
What's a thermostat
Thanks and then it also knows what capabilities.
And then is responsible for presenting this in a way that allows it gave you these things can work
Together right so that's the burden is put on the provisioning tool to make that very very straightforward and
The end-user
Okay
So let's talk about how long it's going to take
To get
2 mesh Bluetooth in
Commercial
Products
When there's changes in the Spectre effect
The radio layer
Like witches 5 did
There's a natural. Time it needs to have
For those products to
It developed and tested in
At the market
That was his message that we said this is another radio flavor of
Valve software layer the network
So things can happen
More rapidly
So y'all are normal answer here is typically on within 6 months you'll start to see products in the market I think here you'll see stuff
What happened pretty quickly based on the amount of
Of activities has already been going on here for quite some time
In the maturity of some of the solutions that are already out there so I think you'll see things will certainly this year and hopefully pretty quick
Awesome Ken
Thank you so much
For spending so much time
Explaining
I'm glad to do it thank you for having me on the show
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can buy
Sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see
Next week