Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have today
Zuv speaker and assistant news that we're going to cover including it
Amazon Echo multi-room audio in Google Assistant coming to
Josh
So we're going to discover GE trying to fix it
Predix Industrial iot
And
We build a special project just for our listeners
You're going to love it
We've also got a message from this week's brand new sponsor for truck
And
Our Guest
This week Alastair Allen
Who is a geek reimagining
How to secure the Internet of Things by having devices
Lie to each other
Going to be exciting
And before we get into all of that let's have a quick message from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is Lively did you know that on average it takes companies 18 months to launch and iot
Connected products
But it doesn't have to get your products into the hands of your customers faster with side li-po from concept 2
Connected in 4 months or less and get everything you need to run your connected product
Lively offers everything needed to get up and running including Hardware Integrations a lunch ready mobile app
Systems to manage
User and device data and pre-built Integrations with tools like Salesforce visit Zylie.
That s i v e l y
. com for more information
Okay Kevin
So much news let's get started first with GE and it's predict stuff
Because
In the billions of dollar category I feel like this
This is the biggest item we've got
So what happened it is
Rare's discovered that GE
Has
Shifted its
Focus on the
Industrial internet-of-things because
It was crazy spending on its predix platform
And accountability
So
In Spring GE called a two-month timeout to tackle these
And now they're focusing
Only on a few Industries as
As opposed to
Iot
Opportunity so now they're going to only emphasize
Sales to existing customers in energy
Aviation
And oil and gas
Is this make sense
Because
I actually
Talk to a company that is
Competing with
Critics it's called flutura
And they were
Napping customers because a lot of customers who had Industrial Equipment data didn't want to give their
Proprietary data about how some of their Machinery work
Route to Geb
Because GE my
So there's that issue so people worried about GE trying
Compete with them which makes sense then that she's got only try to serve its existing customers that are already buying their
Equipment potoo
It also kind of emphasizes
How in the wild wild west of the Industrial internet-of-things
GE wanted to be
All things to everyone it wanted to be an IT player it wanted to be a traditional industrial Powerhouse and then it also
202 develop the algorithms needed to like do
It wanted to be IBM
Yes
It's not easy to do that and basically what happened is G Building Stone clouds and last year it said
You know what our own cloud that's not a win for us we're going to work on Azure and AWS beak
Does that make sense
And what it seems to be now is
They're like okay we're also only going to work in certain industries
Not only where we have customers but also we have our expertise because
Frank Leo I don't think we figured out how to scale in industrial iot platform I don't think there's one platform
That's going to work across all Industries
I would agree I would agree there's there's too many individual requirements for different types of Industries so
By focusing on these three core
Verticals it makes sense for GE to you know cuz I can focus on growing the customer base that they already have
We're not competing with those Industries so it makes sense
And
Huge Industries
It's going to be
That's kind of the GE story I think we're going to see we're already seeing it like samsara which is an industrial
Iot startup
It's doing very well
They wanted to do the same thing they wanted to build out this massive industrial iot platform and what happened was there like
It's pretty hard to do Fleet Management and cold
Supply chain
Because
Doing everything
Is it really pause
And I still talk to companies who are like hey you know what we're going to build the first scalable
But
I don't know if it's good luck with that
I want to hear about it if you think you've done it
So that's our industrial iot this is pretty big because
As part of this
GE is also expecting
12 billion in digital Revenue in 2020 and that includes its products stuff
That's compared to
15 billion
Previously talked about
I remember getting that prediction for them
A while back
How much years ago
That's amazing
But apparently it was a little too amazing
So
But they're not backing off
They're just
Refocusing perhaps
A little bit more
Where we are today
All right
Moving along to
Crazy
Smart Home
News before we move on
I have to tell you guy
Little Harvey update
Hurricane Harvey strike Houston which is where I grew up
Add lots of friends and family there everybody I know is safe some of them have lost things that are precious to them
But everyone is safe
And
I am safe and for all of you guys who've been sending me nice messages
Thank you
And
I'll let you know next week after
Still ongoing as of now so
I don't know what to say right now
And can appreciate the help
And good thoughts
People are sending
That's good to hear on your side there still so many people that will be affected and that's it just tragic to watch quite honestly
Going to be insane
So
Okay
Oh I also have a
Correction
Right here in the middle of the show I have a correction
Two episodes ago we talked about the super sensor
This is a
Sensor that was developed to
Analyze sound and other information from the house and
Basically say oh hey you turn on the faucet in the kitchen
Or hey
That's your bathroom shower
Which we all thought was
School it is
I said it was from
But it is not
It is from Kearney
I know
Idaho
My apologies
MIT you do some very cool stuff Carnegie Mellon
So do you you also do really
Lake. In this case
You guys
Developed
So
Noted
I did send the link to the right place so if you ended up there from checking it out
Probably realized my mistake
Okay
Yeah we live on
I want to
Digital
Assistance
Dash
Should we start with
Multi-room audio from the Amazon Echo
We can do that that's that's something that you've been looking forward to and it's it snow here
It is
It's a little bit more difficult than I thought it would be
It's challenging it's it's also very a little bit limiting it's not on every Echo device yet so my tab
Sitting in the corner like it's being punished because it is not supported but
Echo dots and the original Echo and Echo Show devices all support
Multi-room audio
3rd party
Indeed indeed job you can also you can use this to play songs in different rooms from Amazon
TuneIn iHeartRadio Pandora
Not yet for Spotify with you Stacy listen to end SiriusXM which
I listen to you too so
Unfortunately what kind of
On hold for that
Securus a pro tips that Kevin and I have
I figured out
Trial
Which is going to hell you have to figure out a lot of your Amazon Echo
Not great
So
First
If your Spotify or Sirius XM is your default
You probably if you really want to get into this you're going to want to change your default to like Amazon
Or Pandora One of the services that works because your other alternative is to say something like play
Beyonce on Amazon music in this room
Which is kind of a lot
Let's talk about room names
Sopac when Amazon introduced calling and drop in
I actually changed the names of all of my
Echoes two things like
Master bedroom or
Color Kim
My daughter's name
Her name is not Kim
So what I would do it.
And the echo in a room
Woodwork
It was awesome
But when I tried to say
Play Beyonce on
The echo was like
Nope
So I actually have a change it to
To Kim's room
It seems to have to be location
Based from a context and point
Which was a little weird for me and I had a
Dot that I hit
Creatively named Dottie
And I actually ended up having to change that
Living room
Because it would not play
In Dottie it would not play in Daddy's room
It would not play on Dottie and it would not play on Daddy's room
So it's kind of a strange way of doing it and also when you do this you have to set up
Groups of speakers
And a little challenging if I don't where you actually do that I think we found two different places and they have to do that right
Yes
I did it in the smart home sec
Where are you at Creative Group
Or maybe you can grab some light bulbs for example by room
In there when you create a new group you have the option of what device group would you always had
You now have a multi-room music group option and that's where you set up or what I wear I setup my
My multiple speaker
Groups
And if you go under settings
You can scroll under all your devices
Two groups and if you click on multi-room music
You can pick
Your
Multi-room music so you can take create group there
You can only put a device
Into a single group
See you downstairs and upstairs
And you have all your downstairs ones in it
If you do that then you can't have one called everywhere that includes
All of them
Right
So it's a little limited there
Java group you have to have more than one device
We actually trying to
Get around to the weird naming by creating a group called the proper name
But that did not
It does not work
Car Bluetooth streaming
So if you're streaming something
From your phone
It's not going to play
In Minneapolis
Strictly that the streaming directly through
Amazon were connected services
I'm kind of bummed about the tapping
Supported right now because
It's always like the one that gets featured the last
And I get that it's maybe not always plugged in for people but come on they did it with the
I'm always listening option A later added that
It also gives the option that included in a multi-room audio group
That's why I don't like that
No I take my tap out on the tech I take it you in different rooms that don't have an account for every room
In fact
Because of some news when I talk about the minute I may not buy anymore Equus at all
Yes
In fact I will you
Use my Sonos on the routes because
Sonos is set to announce its multi-room audio at features or a speaker rather
With a microphone is smart speakers smart speakers
On October 5th so we will let you know how that goes
Related to that
I don't know if you caught this in the Amazon press release on multi-room audio
Amazon has added an SDK for multi-room music and it connected speaker API
And guess who they got a quote from
The VP of software at Sonos
Yeah
Disconnect
Scrappy dappy Doo
Ambidextrous of working with Bose sound United and Samsung so
Tell me interesting to see by the end of the year I suspect we'll see lots of Amazon Echo
Voice service speakers
Excellent but
What are you don't really love
Madam
What's
Here it is
Which is the giant Appliance in
Consumer
Home show
In Germany
I wish you were there
Google Assistant
Said it would work with
LG
And other things right.
Yeah since you returned my speakers I'll go through this first Google Assistant will be coming soon to
Zillow
Best speaker the take-home mini by mob boy
And the ga10 speaker by Panasonic
So there will be more speakers coming but
You will have
Google assistant at least it was three speakers soon
I believe it's by the end of the year that's coming out later this year
Most of it up on the US UK Australia Canada Germany and France
More interesting to me is
LG appliances are getting
Google Assistant
And my appliances I just don't mean like
Fridge I mean washer
Dryer's vacuums and more
And we didn't realize this at least I didn't before the show started looking around and LG I didn't know
Makes a series of Roomba like
Vacuums they call it the humba twice
Not called the homebodies probably Stacy said to me before they probably already is a home.
But these are from 679 to $999
Robotic vacuums
With cameras and security features and so on
It would not surprise me if these get Google Assistant later this year
All right
Should we call this amount of Zurich
Cortana news
Yes
Call it yes cuz it's both
Microsoft Cortana
That is going to talk to Madam a
Is can I talk to
And
I don't have a Windows
Machine anywhere that use Cortana Kevin
I still do I still have one or two slider on Asia
Has very good it's just I
I just don't use those machines that much
Yes you can say
Madam a
Open
Windows 10
Deceive it's a little clunky how it's going to work
Microsoft says you'll just say
Hey Cortana open matinee
And then you can ask matabei to order something for example
And vice-versa can say hey madhumeh open Cortana
And
Maybe get your
Office
Next calendar event or something like that Amanda thinking I would do that but
Just as an example there's a little bit of clunkiness here
Internity interface
I think that's
Partly because voice is still so
Unusual
Relatively new and these kind of Partnerships and figuring out
How to position your brand
In voice command cuz that's
Part of the challenge
Right here like
This is probably a win for both companies but in my opinion is more of a win from Microsoft
Because
Originally Cortana came out on Windows phones and those are no more.
Product line is essentially dead
So yes Microsoft Cortana into the newer operating systems Windows 10 and so on so forth
Good
But it hasn't found a growing
Market to add Cortana to expand its base because PC
Market is not growing
Phones are growing but they don't have any
What is growing
Digital assistants
So now they've got their AI into
I don't know I'm going to guess tens of millions of
Amazon echos
This could be very interesting
Sing in the Enterprise space so if you guys are I would love to hear from people who are working in offices
What this means for you
You guys because I think that's where this could get
Interesting although a lot of people are building and putting Amazon Echo into offices I think there's
Real advantages to having some of the security and admin
Elements that Microsoft
I would agree with that and I go a step further and say this is Microsoft's
First real step into the Smart Home Market
Because
What can you do with Cortana from a Spartan perspective right now probably not much I don't think
Feeling it too
The echo you can then
Voice control that stuff
No I have been hearing rumors that Microsoft is going to announce something
Really big
Andy's Market Market
Would not surprise me
Actually it is a little
It is a little surprising because if I look at where Microsoft is not just traditionally been power
Powerful that where it's reaching and pushing
IT services
With azure
It is
Definitely pushing more
Enterprise Industrial
Data analytics
So it is a little odd to me that it would be like a getaway
Let's let's go back to the store
That just seems bizarre to me
But they've had two versions slimdown version of Windows to run on arm processors and Raspberry Pi
Pies and so on so they haven't
Totally overlooked this area but I would agree that Focus has been warned Enterprise
Asher is doing a great job
So
Smart speaker news story for us we have a new smart speaker
Slayer
This is a startup called
J-Stars company's name the product is Josh
Dot AI
And it is
Josh
Micro
Is this
Particular product so Josh has been around for a while
Doing
Professional installs and voice activation associate
Professional installers so you could have called like your CDA guy
Install basically a computer running Josh that
Control
Your control for your
Lutrinae or whatever else is installed in the
What this is it CD of this year
They're going to be showing off
In launching
Echo like device it actually looks would you say it look like Kevin
I said it looks like an upside-down bowl with the top cut off
Yeah
It reminded me of the eufy genie
We don't know how much it's going to cost
This is Wi-Fi the cool things that this has
Sitar
Worth thinking about
Is the top of it
Top of the
Which I guess would be the bottom of the bowl but
It's facing.
Top since it's upside down
That part has a motion sensor light sensors temperature sensors Etc
So you can do things that knows when you're in the room so you can do things like
Josh turn on the lights and it will actually turn on the lights of the room that
Has memory so it can retain the conversation
Been having
I don't know how long
But you know if you say turn on the lights
It'll turn the lights on and then if you say dim lights to 50% it'll be like
Yeah there's a light that just turned out I bet
So that's cool and then it also accepts
Multiple commands at 1
Which
Yes please
So I think this is really interesting without pricing
I'm going to see it when I'm at CDO by the way you guys I'll be
Next week
And we will have a special CD podcasts
Will get a double bonus
That's forever
I know you're cheering right now
That's only speaker
We got some Home Care
I think that's what we do as homekit devices again all this news coming out of
Dife orifa show
Elgato has some new homekit devices
I want is actually a refresh of an existing devices really for new devices
The eve Thermo is there connected radiator valves the way that's a second-generation so that way you can control your
He threw the scheduling and someone's got the password touch control
What temperature display
Bridgeless architecture and mornstar shipping on September 26
And then the new products are the eaves smoke smoke detector
The eve window guard the evelock which is done conjunction with Yale
And the eve Aqua connected irrigation controller
So these are all
Products that you would expect to see for the smartphone market not like anything at totally outrageously new but again these are all home kits
Supported so that is a big deal for them
It is end
I didn't love their original motion
Which I had tried
It wasn't very fast it didn't
It was big
Didn't love it from the sensor perspective
But things like
New lock
That's actually pretty exciting
870 euros
Roughly 60
So that's the homekit news out there's also a homekit light bulbs
How-to geek
It's most colors
It looks like a candelabra bulb but it's actually like a regular size bulb so it's
Rather large
Unwieldy
Sylvania smart a19 light bulb that is shaped like
Looking for normal light
Homekit enabled does not require a hub
And that actually works really well the colors are
Rich it works
Motion detector in homekit I've programmed that light to come on
Quickly
Pleasantly
I've run to the colors they are bright they're not as bright as rich as the
Second gen Hue richer colors if you guys are taking notes on that but they
Did you look lovely
Book lovely
How much is that bulb
45 peso this one is also how does homekit supported and it's 36 so it's even
It looks a little like I said unwieldy if you have it under a shade or something you wouldn't really see it then
It displays more than 16 million colors which is nice
All right and we're going to take a listener question
So our question this week is from
North Yarmouth
Name
And mr. young asking us about
SmartThings
He writes
Thank you for bringing me into the iot world I'm concerned about SmartThings not sticking around most everything is on sale now in
Including their newest hubs
Homes are being cleared out what is the successor
And this person really enjoys using SmartThings in two different properties
And there
Little sad about battery life
They would hate to see them
Well
We have an answer for you they're not leaving me
They were purchased by Samsung
A couple years ago
And what is happening is
I think it's part of this overall movement away from hubs because most normal mainstream consumers
I want to invest in a hub
So they'll still make those but Samsung is embedding SmartThings in smart TVs
And also into
It's Wi-Fi access point
Poinsettias make
So
That is
What is happening
SmartThings they are innovating they actually earlier this year
Did a major back-end redesigned which
But what it does is it gives it a lot more agility in
Inflexibility for building new services
And Kevin any thoughts from you
And it's certainly not going anywhere as you said they're going public yay I love that anywhere and everywhere that they can
Put SmartThings into devices appliances and so on they're going to continue doing so I would have no concern about smart things going anywhere
All right
You can keep your SmartThings stuff
And will
Yay
Kevin
You built us all a big surprise
Blisters
Everybody
Well
We build a voicemail system specifically for the iot podcast and while we could have done this
Just by using Google Voice or Skype voicemail
We decided to take it like a little iot project
So
I'm since we love getting your questions or comments and so on what we have is let me get the voicemail number out first and I'll explain what it is
Palace at 5 1/2
623-7424. Message
In your message
Let us know if it's okay to actually
Embed your question you're coming in the show if we don't have your permission we certainly will not do that
What we did is we have the response system running on a Raspberry Pi
A headless Raspberry Pi meaning there's no monitor keyboard or mouse attached currently
Set it up I did have to connect a monitor to it
We're using the standard the software that comes on Raspberry Pi and got some Python scripts
They're constantly running
We tied those into twilio and Stacy
Yeah
There you go I was couple years back so we decided let's try to really again
The apis are very easy to use there's a nice little console on dashboard that tells us when you called when there's a message
Play your message and record it and save it and all that
So basically this is just a little like a set of inexpensive Raspberry Pi running
Python scripts
With the chulio so if you call it
You can leave a message and we will actually
Get a text message that we know that you have left us a message and then we'll go take a listen
Ye all right so let's get that number again
Yep it is 512
6 to 3
7 4
2/4
Because it was a little iot project it might make sense for me to write this up
For the new Stacey on iot blog we can get into it more that details for people who want to know how to do this
So
We're also going to put it on the website
Call the iot podcast listener hotline
Woohoo
And I have an Android app
Actually if you search for The Internet of Things podcast on Android
I actually think it's Stacey on iot
On Android
You should be able to find it and download the app
If you're happy that way
And there is a link in there to call the show
So
Guys
Send us your question
Girls also send requests
I cannot wait
Kevin thank you so much for
Yeah it was fun
Yeah we look forward to your write-up
And now
Let's talk about having our devices
Lie to each other and how that might enhance security for The Internet of Things
Stay tuned for our guest
Alistair Allen
Up next
On the Internet of Things podcast we're breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with the message from
Our sponsor sponsor is Fort Rock
And I have Robert Humphrey the CMO of four truck here to talk to me
So Robert
Fort Rock is a digital identity management
Why does Fort rocks platform matter for the internet
And what digital identity does it help
Companies monetize customer relationships as well as dress regulations that are filled front and center and everybody's
Mine our own privacy
Sense things like
European Union's gdpr
HIPAA regulations here in the US FCC privacy regulations Etc digital identity
Alias the enabler in the
Center of all of that digital identity initially it kind of its Inception was all about employee
Identity in grew into customer identity
And now in our differentiation
And where we were founded was all about
Identity of people devices
The difference
Between employee ID
Customer identity
Growing into
Peyote is the issue of scale
Employee identity is limited to the number employee somebody has
100000 is a lot of employee
Customer identity
Is limited to the number of them
Customer somebody has so it's in the Millions
Iot identity in the identity of things is
Almost unlimited but clearly it's in the billions
And billions identity and that
Is why it's important to iot
And that's one of my biggest differentiators
And how do you guys help your customers improve their businesses using
Digital identity
Start with one that people probably haven't heard of a company called Amer Sports Hammer is the owner of Wilson Sporting Goods
Salomon skis Atomic skis Precor exercise equipment
Except
And like a lot of companies
Didn't know who their customers are
Didn't have a relationship with the customers because of the nature of their products
Has done
Is
Using iot is now
Put sensors into many of their products or today you can walk into a sporting good store or buy from Amazon
Wilson X basketball
Has a sensor in it that allows you then to do really cool things with a basketball now I can play horse with somebody
In another country
Let the ball is telling me
Where to shoot from
Excedrin is tracking all that stuff
Interesting from a
Amber perspective is they now because they're connecting
The customer
Good at basketball
They know who their customers are and they're able to them cross cell in Excel
Basketball football soccer Balls Etc
Because they know their customers much better
Doing two things from the Amber perspective there knowing the customer
Unable to do all sorts of interesting things
From a customer's perspective
They're building more in interesting engagement
Approaches
Because of what they can do they can extend that Plainfield for the sporting equipment
Across borders across continents countries Etc
By connecting those ball
Awesome
Alright Robert where can I go
To find out more
Go to www.ford.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
He's Alistair Alan who is a former academic
2 hacks make
6 and rights thing
About the internet
So how is your welcome thank you
Great to be here thanks I haven't
I am really excited
First because you're British and you're going to sound smarter
All of my other
Even if you're not
But
You actually are pretty smart so let's get started
Briefly
You have put forth some ideas about how we should secure the internet of things and how we're thinking about the way we
We design Hardware kind of wrong
Can you describe this as like a few sentences
Sure so
Recently I've come across some cases of what I'm calling maldita malicious dates are being injected into
Internet of Things sensor systems distributed sensor systems
And that serve kicked off a line of thought
Tell me about
How we're designing
The architectures
Things itself in about how
Those architectures affect the security
Fun fact
The the Felicity of the dates are going around those systems
And just didn't like it before I bite smart devices
Essentially
These days
Hardware is just software Raptor
Symplastic
An idea I think has done
Real harm
To the way with design
Devices
Let's break that down because what does it mean when you're talking about
Hardware just being software
Does that mean we're ignoring
Security on the hardware side
What's happened is that we've inherited in architecture from our software
System so when you
Ask a device to do something you'd say turn on or turn off
You're essentially just telling the device
Effectively the API the devices
Presenting to the world
Is just
The software on donut are delaying it so essentially your calling a software subroutine to do something
On the device
Which means
That
Very much is a command-and-control arkit
All the devices are presenting
Direct access to the physical things they do
So a light switch or a light bulb
Turn on or off
A sensor can be
You can get the value of the sensor
And I think that actually quite harmful architect
Patrick is sure as a person I should be able to tell my
Light bulbs
Turn on and off
But increasingly are smart devices are controlled by well other smart devices
So why should another smart device have the
Control over my thing
Did I do
So what I've been thinking about
Is
Howell devices should talk to one another Rob
Okay and that that makes sense because ideally we're building something that's scalable
It doesn't require me
To sit in the middle of
Tell everything in the world around me to do anything
So your idea here is that you will program things to lie to each
So how would that work
What are the problems with the Internet of Things always the consumer side of the internet of things right now is
That
Pretty much all of the systems that are commercially available assume that there is a human in the
That is part of the conversation with the device or the system
There is a human
Making decisions or at least monitor
Bring the system in some way
And I see said that isn't going to scale
What is this new way to scale that
It's it's if you look at your iPad right now I mean I have this problem
If you must have this
There must be 50 apps in your iPad right now to
Even more
Yeah okay I have a whole folder these
Exit it Scrolls page at
And 0 with we are outlined cases you and
We are not the typical consumer
It anyway
But the problem is
That's where the typical
Consumers going to be in
Time
So very obviously
We all know this
That's going to have to
But if you imagine the case in the future of say a smart heating system
And you can tell a smart heating system to turn off
Okay that's fine
Until Tim and Tina a temperature
Okay
But say you're in a kitchen
Your oven is smart on the oven
Should be able to tell a smart heating system
To turn off
Because it's turn the oven on in the heat
The kitchen's going to heat up because the oven
Or say the ovens turned off and it tells the heating system
How to turn back on again
At the same time the window is open
The windows smart
So the window tells the heating system
To do something else because obviously now you've got the kitchen is open to the outside in
I need to waste money
Heating outside
Or
You have a son sensor to tell you how much I liked is coming through the window and it
It's the middle of the day
Once the system is told you to turn the heating on in one system tells it to tell the heating
To turn off
What does the heating system listen to
Well in this is something I as an individual
Most of us will not work
I don't want to be it's hard enough that I have to set priorities in my
Is my internet
Skype calls prioritize this
So I can imagine saying
Hey listen to my window sensor
HVAC or
Oh no no listen to my ceiling fan
So you're
Solution
Your thought here is
The solution is that it shouldn't listen to any of
They should be able to talk to it and it should be able to talk to them but they shouldn't take commands from other objects
Why should my smart window are my Smart Oven be able to tell my heating system
Demand for my heat
System
Did it turn on the roll
They should be able to to provide information
Or request
Hey I turn on you might want to think about turning off
So all of this would then be mediated where
Because
The benefit of having a truly smart home is having these
Things have this kind
Conversation
Exactly the conversation is is exactly the right word right now what happens
Those apis are very specifically tied
To the function of the device
To turn on or off
Set this temperature
Imitated the architecture them separately currently playing with RR what a cold agent architecture is there they're actually truly
Smart device
And
What happens if you actually have negotiation
Ansel
The smartness if you like
Drop side of what's called emerging complexity did the negotiations between the various devices
So
Effectively there isn't one place where this is mediated
Eights mediated in the exchange of messages between all the devices
So what does that look like cuz I'm hearing you and I'm picturing
Some sort of
Butler inside my home
A computer that is
Tracking all this and making decisions
But that actually doesn't sound
Quite what you're
That's not exactly what I'm talking about that's that's only one architecture where
Where you have some sort of central point
Negotiation
Send failure what I'm talking about is more distributor
Intelligence
There was a case recently in California
Of a Vineyard
Square
Malicious data was fed into
Distributed water sensing system
So this was a system setup
To check the moisture in the soil
And automatically triggers some sprinklers if the moisture in various places
What's below us
Levelland militia States was fed into the system
And that automatically triggered the sprinklers in the the crop
Was massively overwatered
And farmer was fine
Quite a large amount by the state of California for
Too much water at 4 actually triggered this whole
Line of thought
List exactly what happened
It was one single
Piece of data that was One commands to go
Hey I have
Low-moisture reading here
Turn on the sprinkler
And
What was happening was he sprinklers was sitting in the middle of a large distributed sensor net
And it was one single Auburn
Piece of data that was saying turn on
Sprinklers
Why did that single piece of dates a trick of the sprinklers while because of the way the architectures work
It's like if you got this sensor reading
You should turn on
On the sprinklers
But I also have a history if there is a history
O2 sensor readings
Fine
It was the only piece of day so that was that was Auburn
It was
Why should that particular piece of Beto triggered
The water
Shouldn't of done
So what should have happened was
If they should have looked
WhatsApp history
The sensor readings in Gone Wild
And then should go die and asked all the other sensors
Hey
What's going on is like do you have those Vizsla readings
Initiative intensive negotiation messaging should have happened and it should have been dead and gone
Well that's at Auburn piece of pizza
It's not
Something I should pay attention to I'm going to ignore that
Are the same thing
Should happen of a consumer level
In your home
So
If I'm thinking about building and architecture like this
Is there enough
Computing power on a sensor to actually handle this kind of
Pulling for certain data and then say what
How does this work within the systems we already have or do we
Rip and replace
Right so
That's a great question
Because you're right
You can't do it everywhere
So I guess the way I'm modeling it right now is is a series a tiers of Architecture is so the
The lowest level
You effectively have sensors
That's
Just get out of there
Moisture there measuring temperature there measuring
Humidity
Whatever
There's no real need for them to
Have the sort of intelligence the result of a decision making
Because they have no actuators they're not going to affect the world
They can provide readings readings can be requested from them
But that's it
At the lowest level in the
The really power constrained devices
There's no real necessity to have
DeSoto decision-making
Ability that's necessary in this earth
The mid-tier where you're having
Devices that
Are have a single actuator
Yes is problems there
So your sprinkler
Yes it was sprinkler system
Is this the real
Necessity to have
High end computing
It just turn the valve on
Why would you have a high in
There I don't have a quite
As I said these are
Ideas and playing with
They're not solidified yet and yeah that's
That is definitely
You could see it being mediated by
Higher-end devices that have the capability to do this sort of reasoning
Dedicated Gateway or is it going to be like
Oh heck I have
Extra compute power right
Where so I'm just going
Can use that
My turn ID with the latter
That you have
Computed nodes
Distributed so for instance warning things you seeing is
Gateway devices
Between sensors
Right so
You have zigbee systems Gateway into IP systems you have
Ble systems Gateway tint eyepieces
Shenzhen
Vice versa so this pretty much always
Extra computer
Available at those Gateway
That could be used for this sort of stuff
And you also have
For instance
YP
Accessible Gateway
TED talks to her
Sick pieces
Princess run
Sprinklers
But on top of that you find manufacturers often
Massively over spec
Stata CPU
Necessary
To do these other things
I was just simply because it's actually notes
Any more expensive to use a more powerful CPU in a lot of cases than it is to use a less powerful CPU
Simply because of the full light for the smartphone
I agree and I think
Figuring out inefficient and
Secure distributed architecture
Accountability
He's going to make a huge difference
That's why I'm really excited about what
Thinking about
Are there
More things to talk about here have you figured out
Anything else or are you playing around with other ideas around this that we should talk
Do you want to talk about blockchain
So I was going to make a little pissy fun, hey what is this
Watch it
Cuz I know it's there
Alright let's talk about
Yep so blockchain is
Massively missing
It's not about digital current
It's not about
The exchange of value
Essentially blockchain is just a way to write to record a log of events
And it's designed to be immutable
If you discard the height
It's a mechanism for reaching
Consensus regarding the states of a shared database between multiple parties who fundamentally don't
Trust each other
Write this is actually why I think
It's so
Powerful
For iot because it's both scalable
And gives you a kind of build
So I'm like yeah
Alright so how does blockchain fit in
You're talking about
Well
The whole concept of
Visa decisions
This is that you have to have
Some sort of accountability between the devices
In the architecture
Brightside
When we talk to each other you have to have some sort of memory about what this device told you last time
I just actually turned out
Trick
And you need a way instead of shared consensus
All keeping track of that
And so that you can also tell all the people that hey you possibly shouldn't trust if you trust me you probably shouldn't Trust
This other person
By this other device
Essentially what you could do is blockchain could service TripAdvisor
That was a big jump there okay
So essentially it's a review site that the blockchain is it is it immutable way to store reviews
Sensor readings
Reliable actuator
If I hey I asked
I ask this thing over here can you turn the heating up can you continue make this
The room hotter it never did it
Never ever responds to requests
This sensor heater continually reads High against all the other senses I know of
Some reviews shouldn't
So for instance if you go to the real TripAdvisor
There are a whole bunch of reviews in hotel rooms in London.
Complain about the lack of air conditioning
The rooms are really small
For anyone that knows about hotel rooms in London
That's just how things
Work so you should
Push any reliability reviews
So for the same thing for the blockchain reviews all the sensors
If
There's a series of reviews that are obviously unreliable because they disagree with
Your view of reality
Then you ignore them
The way I said
Plum blockchain into this the city of Architecture is
It's bear as a shared record
Of whatever one thinks of everyone else
So what happens when the one-off malicious data so let's go back to your
Vineyard
I don't know why this
Censor decided
To tell the sprinkler
But
Let's say I was
I wanted to hack this Vineyard
I would put this data in
How would that can at work
Can practice with you
Obscure architecture
Call everything has a unique identity and in the case of the vineyard it was a hack
And
They effectively
They injected a piece of malicious data onto the the zip beanie
And that was forwarded through the zigbee mesh to
The edge
Where the
The computer that drove the sprinkler system. Stop beta I went out there's a little moisture reading I have to turn on
The sprinklers
Add a course
The problem was that it was injected for all
It was a piece of data that was injected with a randomizer
There really was no sensor
That existed on that net
It was creating that piece of dates
The shadow sensor
It was a shadow sensor yeah
So the obvious thing to do in in this area barkitecture is while I've never heard from that device before why should I trust it
What would happen in our cases
The computer driving the sprinkler system would go
Hey can I have a sensor reading from all the senses I really trust about what the the moisture levels are and say we go
Do I ask for for the sensory
It wouldn't ignore it cuz that would be that
Because I effectively what you're doing is you're trying to
Responsive effectively in this case of an emergency right it's like
It's an emergency I need to water so
Even ignore it but you would ask the clarification
Seaweed mask
Ozen sushi nearby hey can you tell me
Is it dumpster
And it would get back to reply
Shirts
Spine here come down bring beer it's all fine
Out of a pony with dead
Proceed to login to the blockchain hey this particular sensor I which I've never heard about
Seems unreliable to me possibly you shouldn't
Any notice
Got it all right
Now
To build this architecture
I feel like we need a lot of things are you actively
Trying to build mock-ups of this where are you in terms of me
Making this reality
I'm at the point where I am
Software
Demos so I obviously have software simulation
Signs
It's a 1/2 thing I'm playing with a model of the vineyard that started me down this track
In the first place so I have sensors and I have actuators and I have bits of computer
Flowing documents between all of these so right now I'm not Resorts limited I'm not
Putting on Act
Mitchell Hardware
Deploy
It's all sitting all about
Half-a-dozen ec2 nodes in the cloud
I think that this set of malicious Tater injection is Mal de to injection something we going to see moral
When the it becomes
I think
Right now the security problems we've seen
Things Are
Should we go with unsubtle
Yes but
If you think about information warfare that's essentially what this is you're going up and giving bad information
To someone something
And they've got to figure out
How to handle that
Alistair thanks for giving us this
New way of thinking about architecture for iot
And thank you also for coming on the show this week
Thank you you're quite welcome really great to be here that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and
If you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things at Stacy
1iota.com
Will see you next week