Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacy
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
We are going to be talking about Amazon
Security offering
Facebook's plans for the smart
Fitbit and Health Data
A new SmartThings Hub
A dead company
A company that is trying to be resurrected and plans in the UK
So
All this
Plus
Our Guest this week is going to be Chris Harrison
He's an assistant professor at Carnegie Mellon and he actually built a smart wall project
And he and I are talking about human-computer interactions
You're going to want to listen to
We'll also have a message from our sponsor machine
Cute
Comcast service
And what answer a question for
So let's get it on the road with a message
One of our sponsors
This week sponsor is twilio twilio programmable Wireless makes it easy for developers to program
Connectivity whether you're working with a few devices or thousands get connected fast using no shenanigans
No contract and pay-as-you-go pricing you can connect devices in over a hundred and twenty countries around the world
Grandpa Wireless offers you the scale and strength of the twilio network trusted by millions of developers all over the world
Check out twilio.com Wireless
Because I have a super secret
Coyote
You guys were here
We actually use twilio for the coyote voicemail I don't know if people realize that that's the back in service that we use not that cellular
Part that they're talking about but
We trust it
You can too
All right
Let us move
Ahead
Exciting news this week biggest news we thought
What is Amazon's stock
Maturity announcement
Which
As far as news goes was kind of
Not very exciting actually but we'll talk about it because it's worth talking about
Yes so last week Amazon said that they
Are going to
Provide smart home services
Insecurities
For users
And this fits with some of the purchases they've made
Plus
The fact that security is so far the best Gateway Inn
Just about anyone
What is
How to surprise about Amazon's thing is they're actually not doing any monitoring
They're basically Packaging
A bunch of devices
And they're going to install
Is this exciting
It is if you don't want to do like a DIY so
Is still
What I would think of it as a DIY system is just a DIY system
Cheapest option is a $240 option that includes an echo.
And some lady outside
And that's $240 for
It runs all the way to
Super smart
$140 and you're going to get a siren motion control contact sensors
Safety sensors
Cameras
A.
Video doorbell
An outdoor light
And a hug
Not
Not The Hobbit Amazon makes which is the Echo Plus
Yes so Kevin astutely noticed this
I'm glad she did
Instead of the Echo Plus which is the
Echo
Citic
Amazon sending people
A wink hub
The wink Hub 2
Which is Kevin's
Public choice in my Hub of choice for anyone who doesn't want to deal with
Complexity
It has a pretty basic setup
So
This is really weird
It is
It is really weird and you know what I got
Not trash but people when the Echo Plus Hub came out I said
Turn on starter for me because it has no Z-Wave radio just said Cindy Bluetooth and Wi-Fi obviously easy way Bastille
A big part of this market for many many reasons and
By doing this by going with a wink Hub 2 in all of the packages that include a hub
It just illustrates to me I'd want to say was right but
Amazon news
Easy way to steal important a lot of these products are Z-Wave products
Yeah when you look at the sensor Market you're looking usually to Seaway sensor or maybe
Azzip Pizza
But most of my sensors are actually see
So this again makes a ton of sense
Do you want all this stuff
To work your
And I also think
Maybe there
The goal is
Oh hey
Yeah it's super complicated to program all the stuff to work
Work together let's get an expert in
To do it and that's basically what Kevin and
And then you just tie it to an echo Dot
Which said you tell the customer you're like
Hey
If you say this
The following things
Set it all up
Couple weeks ago I had someone from Lennar on and they talked about how
They set up
Be home with the Amazon Echo and all this smart stuff and they do it basically by sitting down with the family doing a Q&A ask
Asking them
What they like to do how they likes
Things to work
And then they basically program at forum
It's exactly
The model that
You have
As a it's a high-end when you're talking about
Like some of these Crestron and
Extend these big fancy system
Print it was also interesting to me that these are actual Amazon employees that will come to your home that they're not Contracting this out
So obviously they're making an investment there
To educate the employees on the Smart Home Market
And Brooke with customers directly
Yes
And that's awesome
Because
We need this
Most people are not going to be
Ryan's
And yeah and will hear later from heaven
He's involved in one of these projects
Right
I am one of those
Quick snow just because they are making or are using they being Amazon using the wink Hub 2
Underwood Amazon
Potentially acquire wink
You know
It's gone
2 startups quirky
It's too much
So when quirky went bankrupt they sold wing
The company owned by William
Add Flex
You're right I miss that right they sold it to flex
And then after about a year Flex was like
And so they sold it to the company owned by William
I will say
WIC hardware and software
It's really good
It really works well for most people so it would be a real shame
The market Lofts
True I mean even if they were to acquire a wink a minute doesn't mean you couldn't buy it and use it
With your Google home it's on so forth
I don't think it would go away in that regard
In fact I feel better if a company like an Amazon actually owned it because it's not like they're cloud
Center which provides lot of services it just kind of disappear mean that's their bread-and-butter right now so
I would actually feel better in a sense in that regard
When we recommend the wink
I often see questions
Listeners
And readers on the site saying
You know you guys were worried that it might disappear because been sold so many times
Yes and that's something that has reported your purchase decision but it hasn't gone away yet
So I
The wink Hub 2 for $99
Honest website
A couple other places
And oftentimes
I see this on sale for
70 years
Okay and other
Amazon news
Charlie Kendall
Who was the head of the
Madam a smart home
Project
Has left
And we had Charlie actually on the show a couple
He was fantastic because he's one of the only people who I've encountered to have more connected devices in there
Their house than I do
So
Always find it
Talk to him
He joined Amazon
In 2013 so far
5 years ago
And now he's leaving
Just to hang out
Sounds like
I mean the innocent personal blog post he was saying he just wants to take a serious break from work I can totally understand I mean Amazon
Has made huge strides in this market over the last five years Charlie obviously has a lot to do with that
He mentioned he's got a car restoration project that hasn't touched in 2 years he hasn't updated his smart home
Since 2001
So he said it start getting very crusty
So are you not some people are trying to read into this but I think it's exactly what he's saying he just needs a break
So thanks Charlie
For all that you've done
Connecting stuff
And I know that he has been very proactive
And reactive to
Requested
I've made to him
And try to ask him questions about
So I am sad
But maybe he's got more free time to talk to us now
I'll have him come out
Teak restify mysmart
Get a chance to Adelaide
Everything's changing
All the time
In the smart speaker Market
Facebook which is doing
Basically said that they are going to take their smart speaker
That is going to include Emmet smart assistant
To International markets first
Or at least that's
What's CNBC
Yeah well we had reported or read reports of them postponing this smart speaker couple
Four weeks maybe in a few months ago
As a US base company sword made sense to launch it here
But with all of the brouhaha over Cambridge analytics and Facebook data and privacy
Wouldn't surprise me if they do this overseas first
Those people people outside the US have been less affected
At least in the headlines so
That was so far
So far
What I actually thought was interesting is I thought Project M
Which is Facebook's AI program
You guys may remember it because it was a chatbot
Just asked to do things it would have
Happened but it was
Both
AI plus actual
On the back end
In
It sounded they shut that down
The chatbot aspect
Shutdown
Because
It sounded like it wasn't
Scalable
And Facebook is all about scale
Thereto
So I thought it was interested that they're going to have a smart voice assistant
M and
That it's kind of
Part of that program
Although I
Doubt there would be a real person
On the back end
Because man if someone was like a real person on the back and listening to some of my Madam AR
Google request
And I would have a serious problem
Asking a chatbot to flip the switch on my lights and actually have somebody overseas were in
Imechanic Datacenter flip the switch yet
That would be
Everbilt
That's what we know about that
We'll see if that happens if you're an international market
One day you get a chance to buy
Let us know if you actually would I have to say that I wouldn't
I would do the same I've heard and this is just hearsay that Japan will be the lunch area
So
We have to bring up China all the time
Because to me it's just baffling and it also looks like the worst case scenario
For a lot of disk
Technology
Building
Maybe it's just a cultural difference but
China is now mining data directly from their workers
Prince
Caps on their heads to find out
How they're feeling
What
Yeah
Industry
To measure emotional responses to things
Things like tiredness
And there
Aggregating all this data to see
What they can see
Well it's sort of gay people
Approach they're using that information to say hey this
Employee is maybe overtired may not make the best decisions right now let's
Rotate this person out as a result of that it's no different than say industrial iot and a machine maybe the machine is going to
You could have a breakdown soon I don't mean the person would but
What's the best analogy I can come up with
So I get that but
Wow Chinese just going
All out with
Personal monitoring
I mean we talked about you know that smart cameras that capture jaywalkers and the points that you can earn by being
A good citizen based on your social media posts and
Yeah I mean if this is where we're headed I'm not so sure I wanted it's not a future I want to be a part of I don't think but
Wow in a while back I had someone
Talk about things like Fitbit data in HR so if your HR gives you a Fitbit for maybe health insurance
Some of the interesting use cases
Is the pop up from that
What is it
What happens
If
Your company can measure how well you slept less
And maybe they look in there like I was Stacy you only got 4 hours of sleep
This guy
Got six
We're going to let him have
Where is Maple Avenue
Maybe
It's not to say that
I should be penalized
So there's a lot of privacy implications yes obviously
This is happening in China but this is something that could conceivably come into play in your life
Or in the not-too-distant
Not my life and not today
I don't know Kevin I'm going to start monitoring tell him we can't record the show and tell
Dangerously
I'm wearing this ankle bracelet you sent me Stacy what's it for
Now
Basic news
Why do Jews this week
So first.
SmartThings
New Hub coming with
Thread support
Twitch
I actually was a little surprised by this because the
Older
Actually the SmartThings Hub 2
Has zigbee support in thread is basically
It's a slightly different variation
On the underlying
So
Basically you're talking about the same
Radio stand
It's the 802. 15. 4
Stack
Esso radio specs
So you take one of these in
Most of the newer
And probably chips from the least the last two years ago
R backwards
Compatible end
Can do a software update
Date to get ebooks CPM
So my hunch is the radio in the SmartThings to Hub
Wasn't capable of doing that because
This is why they need to launch a new one
I guess that makes sense to me because
The SmartThings Hub
2 does not
Support zigbee Pro
And I just wondered make that may have something to do with the radio of choice that they put in there which
Would potentially then cause a knot to have
Weave thread support
You know with a software update so we should probably mention this actually this information came from somebody on Twitter who is
Scouring the FCC database
And the SEC has tested a new
SmartThings Hub
Acrostics radio
Transmissions in Swansea horsefeathers new announcement of a SmartThings Hub a new one from Samsung but
Obviously one has been tested so therefore it is very likely coming
Looks a lot like the current one
Has a ethernet port on the back as well as a USB port and then
All of the major radios inside so that's good it's not losing anything looks like it's only gaining something
Alright in other news smart luggage company is shutting down
And it's sold office
Technology
Travelpro
The reason
Because it has
Smart luggage
Has a battery for charging plus GPS
For tracking your luggage batteries are not removable
And
The airlines in December
Basically said you know what
We don't like the smart luggage it could blow up in our holds those Lithium-ion batteries are terrible so if you can't remove them
You can't carry this look
Yeah but does but so
Me and Mike so why would a company buy them when the current company Bruce mortgages
Redesign with removable batteries
My hunches bluesmart didn't have enough money to redesign I mean that's a pretty big project
Yes and so they decided to sell off they sold about 65000
And basically they're no longer honoring warranties on them
And
You're pretty much hosed
Say probably about the
IP for cheap just
In case they want to do some patents in case they wanted to launch their own smart
Luggage that
Doesn't have
A non-removable battery
Dessert
It's not uncommon
Bluesmart
Did have a lot of stuff they have the GPS tracking that weight sensors
Are the batteries for charging devices
Tulsa
Cool stuff
Too cool for us
That is blue smart
In other
Possibly dying
Whiting's
Has been sold back to it
Original founder
Bear with us as we explain what Whiting
Nokia
Brought whiting's turn it into a toy
We talked about this
A couple weeks ago on the show because we had
Heard that perhaps Google was going to buy
So this is
Baby monitor
Give me the flight tracker
I think I sleep stuff
Basically Nokia said
This isn't doing anything
Press
And so that the company's original co-founder and chairman
Eric
Korea
Has now purchased it
And it's expected to close towards the end of June
So if you have the stuff
It's unclear
Sinclair
Yeah I'm sure
Eric Carrillo has made some good money on this because Nokia purchase this
Company for 204 million two years ago
Another selling it back
I'm sure he's getting it for a song at this point
I mean this is presumably
Sported
Maybe he's got some great ideas.
Come to fruition so we'll hope Google
They have rolled reviews for assistant actions and apps
Yeah this is new you if you go into the Google assistant on an Android phone cuz I tried it on iOS and did not
Not work for me
Put on Android phone if you search for an action or an app
Which they've already had that functionality
They've added the ability to submit reviews and even see reviews and I think this is great because you don't know
What you're adding to your smart home speaker until you actually install and use it
But if you can crowdsource review information and get an idea of you know what's worthwhile and what's not
That saves a lot of time and makes experience better so
I assume that the Google assistant app on iOS will get this
Very soon but for now if you hit the Explorer
Tab in Google assistant on Android
Do a search for any action or app
You will start seeing reviews
Because they just roll this out there aren't too many I didn't find any reviews but I've seen some online for people to dig around and found some
That's good you got to give it time to
To populate I presume
All right
And
Big news for zigbee
We're talking about how big Z-Wave still is
Yeah the zigbee alliance has been chosen for smart meter role as to every home in Gray
Great Britain
By 2020 so that has a big win for the sigelei folks I think this is great to have a standard protocol
Standardized
Smartphone meters and so on so
If you live in Great Britain you will be able to I assume purchase this maybe they install it through your power company.
Don't know how that all works
Alton in the UK but this is great for energy metering energy management
Their first outing increase savings for utilities and customers Etc
So again Big Win For The zigbee Alliance on this one
Yes And Hive witch
It was created by British gas is a smart home
So they offer it they started with
With a smart thermostat and they've moved into other products
There actually is
EBay system
So this makes
And Hive just by the
Okay and now
He's working or doing to opine on the state of the smart
I wrote something in my newsletter
Last week basically
The bottom line is I'm
In a smart home
Any further
Then I thought
We are still solving the same problems in 2018 that we had identified all the way back in 2012
So things like a lack of standards
High-cost
Use cases
Blah blah blah
These are all still issues today and voices helped but it hasn't helped enough
And
Brinkley
Disappointed
That's that's the short too long didn't read version
Of my story
And Kevin
Is living this
Yeah I am right now because I'd miss on the last
Show that was going to switch back
From SmartThings to wink
And I started to make that migration thinking it should be pretty easy I had one before
No problem and even though I disconnected all of my devices
From the SmartThings Hub before I shut that up down instead of re-adding back to wink it's been a frustrating experience some of the device
Cesare still there just having problems linking back to wink at even reset some of them and it's
My bulbs in particular that I go to the reset process and depending on the bulb
It's you know what off
On
Sequence
You know anyone from a half-second to 3 seconds and so on so forth
And the Wing Cap walkthrough that for each type of bulb you have I have some lightify bulbs that I have some Cree bulbs and some
Time three sets working sometimes it's not and that it's just so frustrating I literally to this day still have a couple bulbs
Are no longer smart they're just dumb bulbs because the reset process
Isn't resetting
You know and it's just really really frustrating and
Is it also have
Exodus
Particular ones are Cree bulbs but some of my other Cree bulbs are
Okay
So I don't know that it's a crazy thing I'm thinking it's more of a
More of a hub thing I don't know yet
I don't know and I got to figure it out
Additionally because everything was linked in the Amazon mattimeo app
And I told her we discover devices even though Ivory added these devices through wink
It's still showing the SmartThings implementations of them and saying hey this server is not connected or not responding like
Because that's not in place anymore
So I had to manually delete and figure out which ones are working which ones weren't in matamata and manually delete them and re-add them
It's just more hassle than it needs to be
It just it's just so frustrating you know makes me wonder how smart Amazon actually is by doing all this
Installation and configuration for you and me and if we have problems
I know you're I think you're going to talk about another problem you've been having lately
If we're having problems and we've been doing this for
Years
And maybe it's not us maybe it's the devices
Words I speak
Hahaha
Yes
You didn't take all the steps
Spring cleaning
You're going to do something crazy like
Like this
I would tell you
Do the formal uninstall of each device
First selfie
Disconnected formerly from your house
Actually I guess your first step should be unlinking
Your stuff from Amazon
Whichever or both
The formal uninstall
Of the device
From The Hub
Ben
Reset your hub
Delete everything
From Amazon
Even the existing stuff
It's still on there
And then
Slowly
Had it all back
Now if your lights do not reset to the hub
That is
The problem is the best way to do it without
Weird glitchy mistakes because
You're otherwise,
I'm sorry
And it takes it takes
It is not
It's a project
Which
I'm cursed so I went to install
Nest Yale
Smart Lock
And as part of that I was resetting
Everything on the Google
Home
Hub
In the Google home app
Because I wanted to die was trying to go Totally Google if I might
My house is much as I
And taking everything off Google home
And then putting it back on cosme
Some drama much like
Kevin head drama
And then I also had some struggles
Connecting my Nest by Hill lock
Yale by nest
Because the hardware side was not work
The end result was that I installed it
And
I never actually got the chance to add the app
Because
The touchpad never
Lit up and so I rechecked everything
I checked on my connections
Reset the device just in case
I changed out the batteries
In all the comment troubleshooting
And
It still didn't work
I spent an hour
Like 15 minutes on the phone with
Nest and they were finally like
Basically they told me to do all the things
And then they're like yeah I think this isn't a software issue is Hardware issue so we're going to send you over to you
And they sent me to you
Any I was like
Yeah that sounds like a hardware issue we're just going to
Has a long time to get a replacement what I will say is
This process did
It worked in the sense
Fitness had a warm transfer
To Gail
Which method
They handled my case seamlessly
From my perspective
When they transfer
And that is how these things should work
It's kind of unrealistic to expect Nesta
Dale's Hardware
Problems but it is totally realistic as a
Customer to say hey
I ended up at nest
Your job is to get me to yell without making my
My life miserable
It'll take a while
But that's customers
No that is the right process and I'm glad it worked out it's it's a shame it takes that long but I can understand
Why that is
In my situation I got to believe most people don't switch hubs nearly as often as we do so it maybe I'm whining
About a problem that nobody else has or will experience
No because it is hard like sometimes things break
And I have had to uninstall everything and put it over but I have had two I've had glitches
Where something stops working
Didn't work so I had to uninstall
And try to get them
Work with particular
And so
That's I think it's actually fairly calm
Sadly
All right and
Think about this
When you move
Holy cow
Or if you decide to replace all your bulbs just buy Smart Switch
And I leave them at the house
That's my advice to you
Now let's go to the iot podcast listener hotline
And good news
Continuing to support the hotline through the end of the year so
We are so glad be
Because I think it's actually real
I really appreciate that
So everybody go out and buy a Schlage lock
If you want to Schlage lock just go right
By 1 and if you want to see what they have to switch leg
. com to learn more
And we also today
How to announce a winner for our April drawing this is for a drawing for my old
Netatmo
Welcome
So this is the one that goes inside recognizes people and you record actually to an SD card so you don't ever have to send it
Cloud
I love this game
And now
Steve
Can love it too so Steve
You are a winner
And you're
Actually asking a question to
So
If you have a question for us give us a call at 5 1/2
742 4
And we will be happy
Or we will be happy
To tell you
We have no answer for
It could work both ways
To be honest
So let's hear from
Steve
Stacey and Kevin
My name is Steve and I
Trying to kill two birds with one stone and looking for a smart lock with a built-in camera
I have no desire for a smart doorbell am I currently out there
Really great for one anyway
I don't want to have to buy and install a separate outdoor smart
Camera eater
So far I've only found the gate
Smart Lock
Which was an Indiegogo
Some serious if you guys have any experience with that one
Or if there are any others I should know about
You're in the market already or possibly coming out down the road
Thanks so much
OC this is actually a
Tough one because cameras
Require wifi and wifi sucks battery is
Like nobody's business door locks usually
Their batteries are kind of a pain
How to change so
It's very tough to find some sort of door lock
With a k
That being said
Kevin has found the closest thing possible
Well I did a bunch of research and unfortunately I came up with the exact same single option right now that's tea
Steve himself came up with and that is the gate Smart Lock which
Will cost $349
For the reason that you just mentioned battery life mainly
Nobody else that I can find is making a door lock with a camera in it and you know it
Technical challenge for sure
It's interesting the gate Smart Lock
Has a
Removable and rechargeable battery on the back of it
And you can even purchase a spare battery for $59 that recharges in 5 hours battery
Should last you about three months they say but that's
Probably going to depend on how much video streaming you actually do from your doorbell so
That's that's going to
Very true
Yeah that's actually very very true I see the same thing in my car which has a battery in it to run the Electric reels
Yeah I don't know what other options are all right now and it's started on Indiegogo as Steve it said it is now available.
Directly from the company so I've even seen some Amazon reviews and need kind of there than many
And they've been a little bit all over the map one was
Terrible and two or three were good to excellent
I will save some people did not like the quality of the video itself and I should note it is a 720p video camera
So it's not a full HD video camera
That may be important to you may not
But
Right now looks like the gate is at
On the plus side you want a free camera
All right
Now stay tuned for our guest
This week's guest is Chris Harrison who is an assistant professor at Carnegie Mellon University
We're talking about
Human-computer interactions
We're talking about his smart wall project
About digital paper
So it's actually really cool
As a nerdy person who loves this stuff
And so hopefully you will do
A message from our sponsor for this week's Internet of Things podcast
Ask for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is machine QA Comcast
And I have Alex
From the GM of machine
So let's just kick this off with
What is
I think he was Comcast enterprise-grade network
Specifically Belfry Mt
Wework of B2B and b2c use cases
You want to leverage our Network
So they can focus on building on the application for them
We also have a growing and robust portfolio Business Solutions and we're providing to and customers as well
In a lot of cases people looking for iot networks are looking for iot
Teen that works everywhere in minor
Comcast
You guys have
That is not everywhere
How are you guys
Handling
Public Announcement made regarding AR-15 City metropolitan area launch and we cover hundreds of cities within those areas
Any of the customers that are looking to us provide i a t e connectivity do have needs as you would imagine outside of
Trisha
So we've done is
Effectively allow them to either
Bring their own does login device
And I can connect back virtually to our Network and we end up managing these gateways for them in the field so whether it's in a farm
Garmin Iowa or it's a warehouse on place in Detroit we have clients who are
Point solutions for their end users in these locations where we might not have particular sort of coverage in that particular location
DirecTV On Demand service
Which allows us to Shipley's lorawan Gateway
The location they need able to sort of virtualizer network for them in places that are not in our quote-unquote traditional hook
Excellent and one of the customers that you guys recently announced was Victor which is a
Pest Control
So how are you working with Victor
Which I assume
Pass coverages a nationwide issue how are you working with them too
Create
Connected pestka
Did ISIS
Where will help Victor add additional access technology to some of their connected Pest Control devices
List case of low-power device
Which solves our problem for coverage in hard-to-reach locations like attics
Or basements
In terms of making sure that their own footprint clearly in the places that we have built networking we pronounce
It's not a problem that works out well in other locations throughout the country were clearly they might need to have a need and we haven't built there just yet
Reside outside of footprint a couple
They're checking out shopping or Laurel and connected mousetrap with one of our machine Q lorawan Gateway
So we can drop ship them anywhere they want and make sure they can
Work cited work with it Solutions companies
Havanese low-power devices anywhere in the country
I need loyalty cranenetwork and that were provided by Comcast to support them
Awesome if you want to build a better Mouse
Or something else
Where should
People go to find out more
About machine
You can start our website at machine chew.com is some great white papers there
Including our latest on dense Network studies
Tactical business level
Aquatica Services info
A conversion guys are resources to help on machineq including network coverage details
And how you can get service both in and outside of the Comcast footprint
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Chris Harrison
Who is an assistant
Professor
I Carnegie Mellon
Horse with human
Computer interaction
So hi Chris how are you
I'm good thanks
I am super excited so
Last week we actually talked in the show about one of your projects the smart wallet
And I want you to stay
Quickly remind everyone
What it is
With a smartwatch
Well we realized
About a year ago that there's no one thing that is truly ubiquitous in and home exhausted and pretty much every
Human environment
Waltz
And the slightest
Incredibles
Computing technology we really haven't transformed the wine of the walls of today we're not surprised that you know a Roman or Greek
Babylonian
2000 years until we decided
Advanced technology
Wanda's waffles
Smart
Got it and the end result was basically creating capacitive touch capability and why
False if I'm
Couldn't really
Basically
Well that's one part of it actually actually the product of
Two things one is it let us add touch
We might be able to use them that's for that gesture
Bi-Lo
Contractility on a wall
Entire wall surface
By splitting up our hands up and down on any part of the Walk
I sent this
The second part of imbued walls will be his face the antennas or electrodes just like you would have on it
The smartphone
Is we also realize that they're really good at sensing
The electrical noise that comes off of appliance
So everything that runs on electric
I'd like a little tiny radio station
Your microwave or your laptop
TV lamp
Everything emits a little bit of this electromagnetic noise
Start poncelet just what they do
And we found that our walls what we documented that
Really good at picking up the signals
And so we can actually
Has machine learning or artificial intelligence
Look at those signals next to gas
What things must be on in your alarm
Tell if your walls are not only fencing or touches but also what
Are you making dinner or is your TV on and we can feed that
2 smartest
Things like Alexa or Google home
Let you know what's going on around
Okay
Where can I get back to that Concept in a
But you also have a smart
Talk to me about what that is
Yeah so the lab is really keen on trying to bring in tractor
New object
Activity
Thermostat
True ubiquitous and be everywhere
And paper is another one of these ubiquitous mediums
It has no inherent
You can digitize it by taking a photo of it up with your smartphone
But it isn't really truly attractive
And part of the same reason why
Have not received and paper
And they're very low cost
Hey I can make you a smart wall but it going to cost $2000000 upgrade your home
You're the interactive sheet of paper
$100 for those are no longer wall
Respect
Something different
Become interactive abused and thought of in the same way
Smarter versions of themselves very low cost
Especially paper which we literally
Looking through out after single-use
Something to be surfaces
Lacoste effect
So cheap that you can put on everything and not really think twice about
So when I saw your video of this my first thought was actually
Not cost
Holy cow
This turns something that's recyclable
And everywhere in two
What
Is it environmentally feasible to do this
Wechat out
I really hope that we can still keep those properties
Because if we made a paper
Going to keep forever
Give Essentia dismayed
And not very good either
So we want to talk about
Paper
Underpass recyclability
Using a single-use
You get this
Screen paper touch-sensitive paper
And you can write a little bit the Sharpie and you don't feel bad about
Well obviously there's
More
I would respect recyclability
Requited
Recycle
As a regular sheet of paper
We assume that there are ways to recycle things that have been laminated
Packaging products
But have the ability to be recycled
Processing facilities better than code in a very similar
So I think the reason
Certainly more work to be done
Would using this approach
Could be compatible with
Recycling process and below cost
That you would truly enjoy that after single-use
And this reminded me mostly of Livescribe which I don't know how
How old you are how long you been
In the world of tech but it used to be a journal
Or
Paper that you used in conjunction with a Kinect
Obviously this doesn't require special care
Active pen
So I'm guessing
The smarts there were more
Independent
Right to this really two main approaches that have been used to do
Digital paper attracts paper
One is going to have a special Booker volume that you clip something to and it'll track the pain with
Sensors that are operating
Another person
Have a smart pen that has a Centre a camera built in
Keep track where the pain is writing
Virtua back in that you digitize
Things like letters
So this approach is different
The paper itself
SO2 having cannabis
Post-it notes
Cardboard
Printer sheets and loose leaf
Anything could work with Ara
Especially printed
I don't think you work with just fingers
Do we actually have a demo that we have in our demo reel
Paper can be interesting
Something special like a camera
In order for it to work
It is different ways of attacking sprouts
Alright and going back to lift me out the most about this
Yes I think was this idea
I have in my mind that this picture of walls in it
Connected homework
Are connected offices being a place where you shoot a screen are you shoot information that can't be conveyed
Sia audio
Maybe by some sort of ambient light kind of happened
So more complicated pieces Amanda
Information
When I saw the wall I was like oh
That is a totally different thing to do with the wall so I'm curious why focus on touch there
Play with you could you screen
Obviously Tire technology into a projector screen and projector that static
We can actually have a b a touch-sensitive
Read on your wall
Aesthetically
Gables wallet
To have this
Seamless
Experience but we don't want to have to
Badger hole
Smart environment look like it.
Have to be from like
23rd century
Like the notion of keeping your house looking like it is
And a technology being somewhat invisible
And when you walk up to that wall I need
An okapi ubiquitous capability
Subscribe to that sort of notion that Mark Weiser
And we definitely subscribe to that belief
Walls are greatest while this will be kept
Haven't replaced
Something crazy we want them to still be walls but the impudent with x
This is a nice polite way to do that
We can remove a lot of
Milo's of Iota
Smart smart wall now
It's very much taking an iot
Computer
And then sticking it to the wall
Exclusive WOD South being the thing that smart
I liked it hopefully it will come with incredibly dirt resistant
Fingerprint
Yes we're leaving after the pain song
It's this all that's awesome
Second
So let's
Getting to this broader idea
They say it's your special HCI
You've done some projects that also deal with
Connectivity in the
Peterson Twitter
Places so as we put Computing everywhere
One of the things that
I've been thinking about
Is how do we make them smarter
And
For that I feel like we're going to need a lot of innovation
Around providing
I would love to get your thoughts about what are especially in the home or in the office environment what are kind of good examples or what do you
Think makes for good examples of context
The computers can
Used to identify people or died in
My actions
All those things
And I think you could bring now these devices that we say you're smart are really quite dumb and I think it's important for us
I think about technology
Sitting on your kitchen counter
I think like an Alexa or Google
Apple homepod is sitting on your kitchen countertop
And they have no idea there in a
Let alone
What you're doing in this
I have no idea
I teleported you into my kitchen to tell when I blindfolded you
Listen to The Sounds going on around you
You called be able to identify that you're in a kitchen
And you probably won't even get a frying on a pandora cuz clinking of
Silverware I'm running a blender
Instantly now
If you're in a kitchen and probably will be going
Do we know that the signals are there and you don't need to stick
Camera
Kitchen to be able to do that
Understanding
Selectivity and right now these devices
Ignore that
What this wall project is doing it
Getting one extra piece of information while using sound
Electronic
Emissions are coming from electrical Appliance
Interference Re Mi because electrically driven
Motors and
Pictures of all kind of appliances like
The keypad on your microwave a little bit of this
Being very nice large antennas
And we just happen to have in our environment can pick those up
Feeding that to a local
Smart device
Whatever for my baby
What's going on
Don't for me like the great examples and we've got to put one of these antennas
We can actually monitor not only when the laundry machine was on
But also what kind of psycho
So that I can have to get a proactive alert saying hey Chris
Your laundry is done do you want to put in the dryer so that to me right now
Oh really practically engaged
Example of theme
Actually happened
If these devices knew more about the
Context
Just talking about what's going on in the room that the devices
I have spent a lot of time thinking about this focused on
Who is in the room
But do you think that really matters and then that gets into some private all of these getting
The Privacy implications but maybe that gets into more privacy
All these have to be I think
Privacy is going to go with haddock
Consider the same time if you can deliver value to people
Privacy
NBA
Invasive device
Really could be list
Everything that we do
I guess we happily carry them around
Because we extract so much value
Everything has to realize
Let's get that.
So I think through this
Sota technology to be successful as they have to really deliver on.
Iot is having a problem right now
If people are
Immodest
But if not
Monetary outlay
Mia formulation correct
In this case
Yes we are we can probably talk
People that we can track
August Appliance used in Navy that would have
Reveal things that are they are the kids watching too much TV are they spending too much time on their computer
It is complicated
And the more information of a give you advice
Okay and then let's talk about knowing who's in the home or who's in the
What is the value there.
Do you think we could
Look around
Azizam in the best examples
I'm going to a ventrac
Target
In the same way that your Netflix account
All the shows that you get 5 * 1 * 2
Definition of collaborative
Leverage
The taste
Millions of people that find people that are sort of like you it's recommended shows
Spotify
Everything you can imagine if you're asking
What's a virtual assistant
Recommend
I'm some ingredients are interested in the gredients
That you only search for spicy food
Whatever it may be
Anyconnect you recommend this practice
It may get the wrong message
The tailoring know what I want to hear the news that plays news that I'm interested
Topix
I know this means
Examples of personalization
A real human
What do f
Obviously like the way that I like Mike
Right now most these devices are pretty agnostic
Who's asking
But that's amazing
Hummus
System versus a lot of machines right now they're all
Depersonalize
Raq-c we probably
Are very close to having a personalized
Experience
Okay and then my next question is which do you think we'll get to
First you think we'll have environmental contacts
Or person
Personalization this much
Because we can use this answers that are already on these devices
At least do those products I know already do person
If I have two Google homes in my house right now
The call Mom
My mom
Depersonalize again
But obviously
Prince Among Us
Environments are
Tricky book
It's hard to do with sounds alone although it is possible we're doing some research on that now, there's so many things that happen
You know in homes
It's hard to do that really really robust
Personalizing itself
But you need to work on
Car and you start breaking the experience and
Complain
There's more work to be done
Environmental knowledge and how to
Glabrous that in a very use
What is it
That doesn't know that you're
People haven't really been able to articulate
Sure and I think
Data camel tie back to personal preference
It's like when I'm cooking I want no interruptions
Right
Other people
I guess it's social it's fun
Okay
Let's talk about the next
Areas of things that your
I meant so I run the lab at Carnegie Mellon
And collectively we're working together
To the Future
Prototyping the future at science fiction
Battlefield
Technologies in Italy
Put them in front of real people
Actually
Gator experience
You can't just describe a technology
Would you like
More often. That sounds pretty cool so we like to build everything and everything you seen her videos is very much real
And we run
Standard
And so on
Looking at the cost
How about these boys would be a minute facture excetera recyclability talked about before
Could I think about all these issues
Holistically
Agreed
So what else are you guys work
Each of my PhD students has
Collectively the lab is very much
Technologies and machine learning
And it turns out those are very powerful combination
Because tuman
Signals
Our very best
Like right now in this call
I am
Moving my hands around
Testicular move my hands when I speak
And if I had smart devices in this room looking at me
And they're trying to decide whether not to activate
Brighter or dimmer whatever it has to make a judgment
That's a very lofty signal
0 or 1.
Mouse click timeout not click
It's somewhere in between and humans are really good
Resolving an ambiguity
Traditionally
And machine learning is this
Really powerful
Perfectly well suited tool that we can resolve
Very complex
Innocent
Statistically viable results we combined
Sensor data
And machine learning
Build new and novel and crack
In terms of new resources
We are still doing a lot with
On body
Computing for the notion that we won't have small
Computers that have big
We have been with no screen potentially and things like projection or augmented reality to co-op
Space from the environment or even from the body
A SmartWatch with that
Pathetically tiny screen which means that you can't use it and then really kind of fundamental
What happens that attractive experience
Spilled Out on your body
A computer which is many times larger than a knife
Ultimate change
Our point of view point on wearables
Also there's another names red looking at you if we are going to have things like wearable sitting on her arm
Just acting like
Comma before that
Voice Assistant speaker
New ideas in the kitchen level of what you're doing in the kitchen
In the same way I look at smartwatch
Right there on the very end
Position right there on your wrist
I got to have no idea with your hands
Arguing but seems like a huge mess.
Theories of Technology
Smartwatch knows not only what you're grabbing object
Together we can get this really rich context
I like it although I'm not looking forward to the battle for my wall or
Alright Chris
Thank you so much for coming on
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Will see you next week