Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your
Your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And today
We have an amazing show for you I am here at the
Parks
Connections smart home Summit
So we're going to be talking to you about stuff from there
We were talking about new updates
Madam
And Amazons
Selling facial
Recognition
Plus he's got more details on easy mesh tied to
Comcast selling
Everywhere
New Arduino boards for iot projects
We got a
Lighting company that focuses on
Selling light switches to builders raising money
We've got some
News about Google
Cloud and wheat
Completed our own iot project that you want to hear.
We got a message for this week sponsor Comcast
Machineq business
And
Which Boeing CEO of Sears
Services is actually our guest at
You talk to us about
How serious is using iot for things like predictive maintenance and then also
What you can expect
You're connected
So all of this and more is coming up
Kik message from our sponsor
This week sponsor
Where is Bosch
Are you interested in all things iot the Bosch connected World blog covers a wide variety
Iot topics from around the world such as industry 4.0 Mobility Smart Home
Blockchain and
Agtech
So check out the blog at blog
. Bosch - ssi.com for articles case studies interviews
And more
Are you ready I am super hyped because I am in California
It's very early in the morning but
I believe it of the show it's only been going on for half a day and I've already gotten
That's a great information and data
And
I am really angry angry
Pyside
So far
Big topic is
Hey
We're kind of not going as fast as we thought because
People are
Flying into this in
Hidden among this is
Value proposition for users expense
The big thing is
Probability
Nothing
It's hard for them to figure out
Works with what
They're talking
About this at the show
It's this mystery force
Like not every single one of them has had
A goal of creating their own platform
You're ready to give that up
Actually work for Sammy's
Spell standards
That's the thing aren't these the people that are creating this industry
And they have created this mess themselves by trying to do it all internally
In their own brands
Yes
Yes that is true
So
I will not harp on this too much because we all know it's frustrating that are devices don't
Work together in
But
The first panel of the event officially
What is a bunch of guys who
Came up from Cox from ATT
There's someone from Vivint the result
August and someone from the beta store
Basically talked about
Interoperability
Yeah like it's hard
And it is hot
But it doesn't
I have to be hard
You know this is something obviously we've been harping on for a long long time and I don't see it getting any better soon
Partially because
This industry has
Gained momentum
Without the interoperability and yes interoperability would certainly
Pellet further faster but that may mean that people might have to replace devices hubs switches
So here's my
Does Hawaii have
In this is something I don't know if it's actually going to happen but
I've actually talked to two companies recently that are
In trying to implement OCS standards
These are data schema score
Different devices so basically think of a data scheme
You can
Automatically generate that
From their stuff and this is the open connectivity
Foundation this is
You should be Intel's group and then
Maybe that's going to happen
I thought that was going to happen in 2016 but they didn't come out with
Good reference back but now that's
Stout
I don't know that's really kind of my only hope invoice is not my only
I'm sorry people who feel like
Chernobyl
Yeah they do it all the time
Your voice voices of user interface it's not the back and that's the thing and people kind of confused
Potoo
I mean voice is just a way to interact with your devices but it doesn't help necessarily the devices interact together need back answer
Nervous system made that happen standards Etc so
I'm glad people are realizing my voice is not the answer
Interesting label two points coming out a little bit and the challenges of it
Voicemail
Listen to voicemail this week later in the show so they just highlights the challenge right there and also
This is almost like
We can talk about using matches well but this almost reminds me of the whole ezmatch thing we talked about last week
So what is the incentive for these companies to work with other products it makes more sense
With a device as opposed to the router guys because the router people have their own
Things that work their routers work today
Interbrand
They don't want or need
To work with other brands even though consumers would benefit from that
The device side again
So much of this is already rolled out so this should have been done already
Now I will say and I'm going to write something up about this
Spell so happy
Mark Spitz who
In charge of Google
Did Speaker business and that means Google home in the Google Max speaker
He was talking about AI
Products in what was really kind of
Compelling and interesting is he
What about the levels of
Since you needed to deliver certain AI experiences and can we talk about this
Be more intuitive
So he was saying
If you want a curated experience
You have like a 70%
Confidence interval
Hey this person seems to like this type of music
Let me just play
It's highly likely that that's going to
Right
Do you want a corrective mod
So something where they
Think of a motion sensor
Sitting to Silver
It's okay when that have
Just a little irritating you got to wave your arms around but it's not the consequences
Not too huge
For that you need to be 85
That you're going to get
And then predicted which is where we kind of want to go is you have to have a
Confidence level of like five 9 to be able to deliver this experience
Because otherwise you're going to get clippy their real-world consequences for
Like money make change hands
Smart assistant
Hey I think
These signals all result in Stacy going to
The airport
What she always does
Let me just send that
How to do those kind of things
Probably need to be
User
Supposed to add
Quite some time
I thought that was really interesting it's good food for thought for you guys as you starting to build you know
AI products in
I'd be curious to hear what y'all
And that is all
All I've done so far
Fox Home Center
I'm sure I'll talk about it next weekend I'm sure you'll see more in this week's newsletter
So now onto
Anime which is what we call
Amazon's personal assistant Just So to avoid setting off all of your devices
So she's got some new
Cheetahs and this is a talent that Google Assistant doesn't have is beyond me and you'll understand
Second Sole
What happened this week is Amazon announced their Madam a smart scheduling assistant
And what you can do now is ask Madame a to schedule a meeting with one of your contacts and she will actually check
Check and see
When you to have time available which is awesome
So I could say Madam a schedule a meeting with Stacy and matinee would say you would say Siri available from
3 p.m. today
5 to 7 p.m. on Friday what day and time should I schedule social actually check and then ask you
You didn't respond the time
You can give her the name of the event and she will schedule it and she'll send an invite
Email invoice to
The other party
If you already know the time you can just schedule the meeting with that person at a set time
And she will still check
To see if there's availability and
Will say if there's a
Conflict or something
So that's kind of nice
This is already out there for Amazon's madhumeh for business accounts
But it also is available for consumers as well
And it works with links
Calendars from a mixture have it right Gmail
G Suite
Microsoft Office 365 and Microsoft Office exchange 2013 or better so
Again this is one of those things that I'm like this with my Google Calendar but it doesn't work with my Google home
Either way I think it's an awesome use of voice
Assistance
Both parties have to have their calendars huh
Hooked up to
That is correct you actually have to add either your work or your personal contacts to the matinee app
And some of mine are already in there like you are
Because
Talked
The drop in
So
This is awesome
This is Mike this could
So much relief
Cuz half of my life is scheduling
Meetings I swear
So now everybody who wants to be with me
Man put your calendar on
Yeah please
You know what's really nice because managing these events also can be a time-consuming thing
You can actually say Madam a move my 9 a.m. meeting and change the time
It's like magic
Okay this is where we're going
So exciting
Okay
Is
Amazon the ACLU
Put out some data that Amazon is selling facial recognition.
Technology to police depart
Which
Is upsetting because
Give me clear signal to the world
Hey we have all this camera dude is picking up our faces we have the ability to recognize
In
Now we can sell it to a lot of horse
I feel like the story
It's not overblown
Exactly it's a great example of everything that Kevin and I
Talk about in the abstract so I think it's important
Forgot birthday
But it's also important to know that what Amazon is selling is
The recognition and that's a recognition
Computer vision
Facial recognition
So
This is not taking
Verdi. This is applying their recognition to
Cool to
Cops
Data
I say this because a lot of us are freaking out
Because Amazon sells
Because of the blank acquisition
Cameras
And they have her
They still sell this but the Amazon Echo look
Which takes images of yuan
Cool outfits
Person tells you how to be more stylish
So
Big data Amazon
Reply it's facial Ricky
You should stop to that
For all I know it does
Question to ask
But they're not selling your
Which I think is in a
It's a huge distinction as a consumer I'm not overly concerned that my cameras are using facial recognition
Mission sending out that data to third parties this is dated at the law enforcement agencies I think
Particularly sperm ACLU standpoint Washington County Sheriff's Office in Oregon is using it that mean
Had a database of mugshots and other
Things to cross-reference faces so they were using facial recognition on the day that they have
Not scanning webcams for
People which is very different you're right
Aunt
Now
Just two
Put this into like hey the future is coming
Apply this with ring
The ring doorbell
The neighbors app
So Amazon now
They've got the neighbors out
This is actually your ring doorbell data
Going
The police if there is an open
Case File
So the police
File to get some data from
They have a case they can actually get dataforma neighborhoods ring doorbells
And from there they have
Facial data
From your smart home stuff
Which then the police if they
We had recognition any number of services that are similar
Other vendors
They could actually
Find a perpetrator or maybe find someone who's innocent
Just is in the wrong place
So that is something to say
Stop being a little paranoid and then we have to think about the ramifications of putting
Cameras everywhere
When we also have access to really good facial
Recognition
And I don't think we've actually talked about that
Societal level noretta regulatory
Maybe we should
I think we should
All right
Let's talk about
Easy mesh
The cracks are already showing
PS so we talked about using match last week and just to recap this is the Wi-Fi Alliance standard
That
Will allow interoperability there's that word again
Of mesh
Networking routers and access points from different
Bender so instead of today you can buy all Orbeez are all those are all Google I-5 whatever maybe
In the future you may be able to mix and match
And I had said
I don't see any incentive for these router makers to really adopt this and packets disincentive
But that was my thoughts
Sure nuff Fast Company reached out to several router makers
At some of these are Wi-Fi on its members
They say they are not rushing on interoperability
And in fact an executive at Qualcomm which makes the chips inside these router as an access point Express skepticism
Non-coding now
But the current standard will bring down prices or aloud
Competing systems to work together so even the folks who helped devise the standard
I'm in the alliance are like
I don't really think so
I just got to
Too fast
Yes I need the Wi-Fi Alliance was behind the ball on this
Finishing the hat and now they have
No reason
The standard
So maybe
All right
Titus Comcast
It's part of their xfinitywifi
These are not the actual pods manufactured by
There going to be a 6 pack of these
Hi switch basically you plug in
Apartment
Where you have poor connectivity
Six-pack Acosta
199 which is cheaper than the plural version
Comcast is ginormous
And
I try these out I thought they were good they did suffer
Prince of the sea
Speed test
Traditional
Magazine
And that's because
Their focus is on
Average
Fixing
Issues
I think we're going to be moving for me
Hefei
Lasted in a small radius kind of
Check the speed
World 2
Hey
Can I get decent coverage everywhere.
My house doesn't have to be the fastest because how many people are really
How many devices are really going to use a Kegerator 300
4 seconds
Really probably just
And you should really hardwired
Okay
So that's the
Cast news
All part of Comcast
Wi-Fi is super in
Our plans
As a broadband
And without good WiFi you can't do anything
They can't sell their Smart Homes
Services
Chandelure good Internet Explorer
These are really smart because they don't have to send a tech out they just send out this tiny little device that you plug into an outlet
Your wife I magically gets better
Stop assuming that you were using your car
Comcast Supply
Modem
Router
$11
Craziness
So
This is giving you value for that
Can you be
Nope sorry you can't tell me I'm using their router
That's okay
I'm not trying
That's all that
Yeah little bit of iot maker news now in the Maker Faire Bay Area event
The Arduino folks announce to new iot boards
Stacy you're a chip girl you're going to love the first
Is the mkr Vidor 4000
And it just the first Arduino board based on an fpga chip or field programmable gate array chip
You're excited aren't you
That
Is amazing
And we want to say why it's so amazing
I really love to hear you I would love to hear you say why
Oh my gosh this is time it is something that I actually want to write about
Which is
We're entering the Sarah ship customization
And it could be through fpga
Architecture
But what's happening is Ashley at
Computing to everything
We no longer have these
Call Nautilus
Smart Home
PC
Server
It will still happen
So we have this additional
Market
Or chips that
Optimized to do something very specific
So maybe it is to be very good
Empowering
Water sensor
Or
To be powering
Camera
Recognition
Retail store
So you're going to get a lot of these more
Customize
Scale-out
The production of
Alien ships that you
We need to do it
Traditional chip pan
Manufacturing
Process
Programmable
Or adaptive
Economic
So that's what the fpgas are
That's right
Yeah he's awesome a lot of what you describe is
What I would call like an Asic or an application-specific integrated circuit
Annette
Just like a Bitcoin miner uses an Asic it's at that chipped as one thing and one thing only in it mines Bitcoin
You should say yes these are changeable on the fly in the
Reason for that
I was like
I didn't talk about an AI
The reason for that is because the jobs are going to be doing the AI job search
Spot on
So I thought you would like this board
This looks
A lot like a Raspberry Pi board like if you're familiar with the large Arduino boards and it's got Wi-Fi built in and different ports and so
Salon I don't have a price on that I think it's going to be available next month
So we'll see what happens
And then if you need a really small
New Arduino board Wi-Fi revision to which I mean it looks like she's half a board almost looks like
Memory module inside a computer for crying out has a really small
And that has like just a miniscule amount like 6K of ram 48k of Flash
And that's what microchip
Yeah this is really freezing
Cloud-based
Iot devices that they say it will work with AWS and Google Cloud for example so
That also comes out next month so we'll see on pricing
Okay I'm going to let you guys know that I'm
Hotel
And it's starting to get a little noisy
703 distance
Ignore the background
Yay do Arduino
A company called eco
Million dollars
And Nico is a really interesting company to me because they make a light switch but they've optimize their sales
The builders
So what happens is it's for new construction
You go in and you say hey this is exactly how many light switches
And you say what rooms are and everything like that is
Builder
You send it to decal
And they said
Send you a package that is like
No brainer install
Disguise
He put it in the right room
It's got the right
Intelligence associated with
Nothing has to be
Programmed
Without
Any work
I do all the work on the
So there's no configuration by the consumer which is nice to one aspect because they don't have to mess around with it
So it's going to come with different scenes and so on pre-configured
Does that mean you can't change them in the future
Okay that's good
Guy ideas to make
Make it as easy as pie
Gotcha
So it's kind of like the new lights
Except those are a retrofit option
Channel established
So with the new lights
You can buy them you install them
They have these programs being so you should never have to do it
Right if I recall correctly the decode lighting system
Is capable matamata on Google home already
And Google assist
You can add those
Don't worry
All right
Let's go to next
Next little bit of news ala who is in iot
So companies like Hunter Fans I feel like there's some Appliance manufacturers in there
When they want to build a Knex product
Famous cloud
Play pop it in and all their data goes to Eli Eli manages the device data
It managed everything for them
So they now have a dad
Google
So
Yeah and this is actually worth noting because Google doesn't have a great device management
They've got lovely insides and pitiful but they don't actually
Deal with
Telemetry data as it is
So this is actually Win 4
Both
Because they said their customers
We want to know.
Stinger stuck on AWS
They don't have to
And speaking of Google Cloud
Evan is going to tell you about our latest iot project
Which is moving our voicemail platform
Yeah so we
Guilty party voicemail hotline using Python and twilio last year and we talked about
Put it on the cloud back then but me being a very very
Amateur developer
Work for so we put on a Raspberry Pi
And that's worth
Mostly pretty well any issues after having been with a pie with a code it's been with
My dog pulling the power cord on the local Internet outages things like that
Outside of Genoa my control
So I started digging around and looking at different Cloud Solutions we could have gone AWS Google Cloud Azure whatever
But I already have a free account with
Google Cloud platform along with
$300 in credit and all that was good for a year and I highly recommend if you want to play with
Using the cloud
This is a great way to do it you can sign up for the free trial account and not paying anything
A year which is awesome
My years almost up but we still not going to pay anything because
AR
Voice mail server just barely uses any CPU cycles and not too much Network bandwidth it's only when you guys call in so
I mean calling you know anytime
We certainly got the van with the handle it decided to Google cloud and a post
Marty Explains It All
Basically I didn't have to change my single line of the Python code I just had to get it up on Google Cloud using there
Cloud console which is very easy to do and just add two other little files for configuration purposes
I also had to create a virtual machine
And you can choose the all really small virtual machine which is obvious that we did I mean it's literally 600 Meg of memory and
Just like one CPU core
But mean if you're on Netflix or somebody you obviously have hundreds and hundreds of cores
Tons of bandwidth that you needn't sound so the cloud makes a scalable that applies obviously to Google Cloud azure
AWS etcetera we probably won't ever have to scale this but it's good to know
In any case once I got all the files up there
Literally I just spun up the
Virtual machine and toilet to deploy
My app
And that was it and all I had to do after that because we use twilio and twilio needs to know when you guys call in on the
Trulia phone number
Where do I find code to do something with this information
URL
Configure Trulia wetsand naturally appoints to not the pie anymore but to Google Cloud
And that's it that whole thing was seamless you guys didn't even notice any transition because it just
Happened
And so far it's been working great
Yay
Thanks Kevin and he said we in there but it's really
I like to Tinker
I love it
Would you like to Tinker
So
Speaking
Voicemail
If you would like to give us a call and have us answer your questions
7 4
This week's iot podcast listener hotline
Which leg you can have a brand new electronic lock installed in Venice just a screwdriver
And
They're easy to setup and use
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
And this week we have a voicemail from
White
Perfectly illustrates
All points that we have discussed so far
Hey Stacy and Kevin this is Dwight from Atlanta
Actually calling with a question
I want to know if there is a way that if there's a device that I
Use
Physically cut on my light bulbs I have a mixture of Hue Lights and
And I know that Hugh makes a product
That can allow you
Toggle light switch off
But I was wondering if there was a device that works
Both lights anyways you can make that
If you know of a device that might be useful I would appreciate that thank you
This is a wonderful question
The state of the
You should
It's hard to answer your question exactly because we don't
Actually know what you
So we're going to run through a
Apple scenarios
The basic architecture is you're going to have
To run each of your lighting things through some kind of software
Hug
And then run a button
True that
So there's a couple ways you can do this first way
Is probably in the best ways probably
Kevin can tell you a little bit about that
Right so
If you have homekit the lifx all the lifx bulbs actually support homekit so you're good there and Phillips
She was only have the second generation Bridge you're good there what you could do that and maybe is look at one of the homekit button such as the new
Button from fibaro and you'll be all set
My lifx bulb is the only thing I have on homekit so I can type tested this but this should work
Again if you have Home Care
What if he doesn't have Home Care Stacy
So if your home can implementation doesn't work what you're going to have to do
Use smart
Don't have SmartThings
Proposition
Because you're going to have to buy the Hub
And her to probably going to have to buy something to act as your butt
And there are wide
Range
$30 buttons
Button to
Take these tiny little Z-Wave
So you'll hook up your lifx bulbs
3 SmartThings you hook up your
Free SmartThings
Create
Recipe receipt
Little button press contact
And that
Is how you're going to be able to do that
Tennessee
The only thing I can think of on the wink Hub site even though it's not natively supported
The lifx bulbs I mean
Maybe using a third-party system like if this then that or you know me could work with wink at it should work with
As long as you have a button that would work with wink
Center operability issues
But that's how it work
Thank you to answer your question and everybody remember you can call five one two
6 to 3
Have us answer your own
Smart home question
And stay tuned
Midget bowling
CEO of Sears Home Services
In a message from our sponsor we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast
Our sponsor
Comcast service
And I have Alex Crum
To talk about how machine
Is evolving
So Alex
Remind us
What
Fishing Q is Comcast
B2B and b2c it business
Focus on providing network connectivity
For switching partners
We're also growing Andrew bus portfolio of points Pacific IT solutions
Awesome so last week we talked about how customers will
Use machineq to start measuring some aspect of their operations
But then they quickly
People try to add more
Can you offer an exam
For singing The Marketplace
Many of our initial solution providers are able to go in there and solve
Particular need at Syracuse
I'm going to come back to us
And ask hey by the way
This additional services that these people looking
For so perfect example would be looking to go to a restaurant and provide temperature humidity for their Cold Case
One of our solution providers have provided in the full stack solution
That's what they sell for that they might want to do predictive maintenance all the refrigerators as well
They come back machineq and say is another solution provider in your ecosystem they can sell for predictive maintenance
Portland only see you there
Terms of private Enterprises but an example of beat for what we did a Comcast cares day
We went to a local Garden Philadelphia
And they asked us for swelling monitor sensors
Freezing a partner bars called sensoterra
After they realize that we had network coverage in that area and they were able to monitor their soil monitor with that device to ask this with anything else
Air quality that might be used there which of course we happen to have decent labs
Another one of our solution providers and they installed a decent labs are monitored
They said for the indoor Greenhouse
Use cases we're also trying to measure temperature humidity as well
There something that can be used there we said yes we actually have
Our own device called the answer
Q Flex that can do that for you
In the market is while many users have a particular need for one iot solution that quickly come back once
Recognize what that's done for them and they're seeking additional services at scale quickly but having to go and do an RFP
Where to go down as particular Pilots
We talked about this picture customers interested in working with machineq worry
If they aren't in a
Comcast service area
The song for our clients needs outside of foot as well
With a service call connectivity on demand
That is a particular need or the location that's outside or trishul footprint were able to drop ship them gateways
Provide coverage in a localized area
Search go
To find out more
About machine key
The best place to start will be at our website
Thank you.com very can find the latest information
Honor network coverage white papers
Capital M business details about how to develop on the machine cannot work
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is Mitch bowling who is this
CEO of Sears
Home Services
Hi Mitch how are you doing today how about yourself
So well so thank you so much for coming on the show I know we talked when you were backing
Comcast doing some of their Xfinity home stuff
And I'm excited to talk to you again
Yeah same here
It's been a long time
So let's kick this off with
I just ate brought over
What are you doing
Sears Home Store
Cancel good questions
Sears Home Services is
Appliance repair we've had that business for decades we also have a home improvement business
Wally home or Wally Labs as part of Sears Home Services
And we have a new exciting service
Call service line
So that's what we do we serve customers around the country
No matter what brand of Appliance they bought where they bought it we serviced it
I imagine so
This is a business that's tailor-made for The Internet of Things
I can think of my gosh predictive maintenance
Cats understanding
From a connected Appliance what's wrong see if the right parts on the truck
There's probably a million other things but can you talk about what
What you guys are doing here today
Will go into what you
Are thinking about doing
Yeah I mean you hit on some of the things that are happening today
Are Kenmore appliances that we sell our
Working web connected their smart Appliance
A lot of the appliances we work on for
Some other brands are also smart appliances so we're faced with those are we
See those everyday
We're able to use those Diagnostics to
Help solve the problem faster
For consumer
We also
Use technology to help our technicians
Turn the home solve problems faster
We do that by connecting that technician to an application to our effectively a tear to where they
They can call if they have a really tough
Situation in the field
Where they can send them live video then
Shenzhen pictures
We can send them back schematics to a product so
We're seeing
Connected devices
We're working with those were also using technology to be
Faster smarter
And help our customers
Okay
It's actually something I talked about was Sears at CES you guys were actually bringing this concept of using video to help repair
Turn appliance that your texts are using today in to hopefully
The consumer home so like someone like me
Steals fairly confident and mucking about with the stuff my
Also have to chance
Yeah we're working on that we have a lot of customer
Merced do DIY which is great we serve those as well
And as you said
We use the technology
Today 4 Hour
Technicians it's it's sort of our
Proving Grounds For That
Technology but we absolutely right
In the process
The ruling that out
We've tested that
We're making some change
Just to wear that what we want to be able
Things to do is
Give that DIY customer
Are the ability to call us if they just need a little bit of help troubleshooting
Where they can
Using their phone which
Practically everyone has a smartphone
And show us
Exactly what they are seeing
And we can help them
I think that is so cool
I cannot wait for this to become
Actually do you think this would become
Standard in
The service world
I think it's possible that it can work very
Excited about it the cusp
Feedback
Been very positive you know in this day and age is everything
Comes more and more automated smart device
Applicable
I think
If it's
I think it's almost
Impossible for it not to be very common
Play sand
Future
In other areas where I am
Well you mentioned predictive
Maintenance
That's something that
You know the industry
Sears included
Is working
Whether it's
My group from a service perspective or are Kenmore
Team from a building those products and other competitors as well but that is the future I think of
Appliances for sure and more things in the
Many things in the home as you know are becoming smarter every day
We want to be able to get to a point
Where
I'll just use an example your refrigerator can tell us
In a proactive
Give way whether it needs a water filter change
Origin
Maybe it has a part that's going bad or is using more energy than it should that's an indication is that something is
Wrong with that client so that's what you know the industry's working toward their real working examples of that
Today where that information goes to a consumer app on their smartphone
But what we're working toward is where we can
Look at that from
Service perspective
Proactively
Contact the cost
And solve a problem before it
That means that their inconvenience level drops
Refrigerator
Cuz
You know you have now you have
Food that can spoil and
That's not good for anyone
This is such a cool and compelling vision
As someone who's you know how to dryer breakdown
Right as I'm transferring my white clothes to it for example
Yes I lost refrigerator
How do you convince customers that you're doing this for their own good
And build trust because
There's also this sense of like
This is about to break down are you sure you just don't want to sell me another part
I think consumers today actually
Past that and understand that predictive maintenance
Part of life
As I mentioned before there are other
Devices in our lives today that are trying to be predicted
Some cars are trying
To be predicted
I mean if you think about it the check engine light from
50 years ago
Is an indicator that
Nothing is wrong with taking the check engine light to
A whole new level in this digital age
So I think consumers understand that it actually gives them an opportunity
Key to save money
From early detection
Versus
In a waiting and waiting when they may not know something
Problem creates additional costs
I think it's a positive for consumers I think it allows
Them to do things on their schedule versus the schedule of their Appliance if it breaks which it needs to be repaired
Now
Preventive maintenance they're going to have a window that they can
That's okay I think it's
Going to be
Very positive
Consumers when this becomes
Commonplace again
We and others have
These devices
Appliances in the marketplace now
It's making them the norm
And you know it'll take awhile but
Is there a lot of Legacy applying
Out there in Appliance last
But the changes everyday and
Percentage of
Smart appliances goes up
Literally every day
So it's
The future is exciting
You mentioned that you guys are working on this
What needs to happen for this to
Become
I guess common place or
Real
Well
Smart appliances are real today
They are
In consumer homes today
Connected to
The web
Connect to the cloud by a better way to say it
And customers are getting info
Information on there
Where I think there's a real opportunity is
Moving that to a proactive state
With a Service Company like ours
Where we can proactive
Contact
Customer maybe they missed the alert on the
Their phone
You know maybe they didn't Lodi Athena's there could be reason
They don't see that where we could help
Buy proactive
If we contacted them and I think what gets us there
It's time
Because we need more Ubiquiti
When I say we the industry
Needs more ubiquity of smart
Appliances
And that's happening
Just the way you know
Color TVs eventually overtook black and white teeth
It takes time for those
Things to be replaced
But that's part of
The evolution of
Smart Appliance
All right and let's go to one of my
What are the topics I've been most eager to hear about which is
Wally home Sears bought this a while back
And
It kind of went under the radar so
What are you guys doing with Wally
So yeah well he's a very exciting
Product anyone I came onboard
Sears giving my
Comcast background check
You know you're very smelly wet
We move that business into Sears Home Services
I've spent
Years of my life in the iot space
But it's a very exciting product
See all the product itself I believe
What's the best in the industry
Between the water sensors
Are hogs
The water valve itself
You know I have all of this in my house and
I feel protected
From a water leak
Water damage is one of the highest
Repair door
I guess damage claims
Industry
Because usually when those things happen it's hours before you know if you're at work
It's pumping water all day so we protect Palms from that
Again I feel very protective
Could I have that product soap
What we need to do is continue
Expand that so
We are working with
Several
Insurance companies
The same way we work
You know I work with insurance companies when I was
Comcast
Security in home automation
Devices
Where we were able to
Help consumer save money
We haven't
Are solved anything at this point but we're in great conversation
We're also
You know in that idea of water damage
If you think about it
As a
Individual homeowner
It's bad
But sink imagine you are in a high-rise where is
Apartment on the top floor has a
Malik well everybody Bulova
Then probably has a
2 because of water flows downhill
We talked to a lot of property owner
And or property managers that
If that's one of their biggest
Concerned soap
We're in
Several trials
Those with multi-tenant high-rise buildings today they're seeing the value of the products so we're excited about a real future there too
Not only provide
Vistana
Consumer basis but also on
B2B basis
And in addition
We have recently
Started using our Sears home service
Appliance technician
There now
Selling the product in a trial base
Selling the Wally product when they go into homes especially to go into a second home for a consumer
It's a perfect product for a second home because
You're not there
That experience that you had and others had of
Water
Pumping out all day imagiknit pumping out for
Multiple days or a week or a month who knows especially if it's an
Winter Wear
Freeze software testing that now
We just roll that out to
Another three hundred of our technicians to sell so it's something we're moving across the company and trying to help consume
Numbers in different ways
So with the Wally product this is a zigbee
And
Play face Enterprise
Search for anyone who's in in can you buy this
Somewhere else
PS on Amazon
You can go to Wally home.com it is zigbee and Z-Wave
Both are Hub zigbee and Z-Wave so our devices
It really made up of a hub water sensors and the water valve it
And zigbee and Z-Wave
They're so and we can kind of
Operate both ways it also sets us up to be interoperable with more platforms which we're in conversations
For that as well
My goodness
You also
Are in charge of
Service
Live business
Switch
I think it's really interesting because there's a huge hole in the market
For installations for a lot of these connected devices so talk to me a little bit about
What is
Yeah yeah servicelive
It's very exciting
Self service line
Is website servicelive.com
And you can come to the website
And today we offer plumbing services
Electrical service
Plant Services
The goal here
Is there any service that you need at your home
You can rely on searshomeservices weather that's Wally or are traditional home appliance or Home Improvement business
That we can serve any needs you have at your home
Or your prop
Civil service live
We are building
A network
Suppliers
Four different types of service
Today at 6
Say we have plumbers electricians and home appliance repair
Will be expanding
Into HVAC very soon
And we're already doing some work
With iot installation
Thermostats cameras doorbells those sites
Thanks
Stan
Really the
Great thing about service live
An infinite World of solutions
That will be able to provide
Because the
Needs of
Homeowners are essentially infinite
And they change all the time
Example I use all the time
Is 10 years ago
Very very few
People would have ever knew
Needed an electric charging station
Electric car charger
Sensation in the garage
Today
The car almost everyday
And that's something one of our electricians
Could
So
It's just one example
Of this ever-changing world of needs at your
It doesn't mean that something is
Broken here servicelive can provide
DIY charging station isn't
Problem it's a no
Opportunity
It could be something as simple as you need someone to come out and hang your
Lights the holidays
A seasoning
Come back out and take them down
So it's not
Doesn't have to be all hi tech
Servicelive is
A broad array of services
But we are excited about in barracks
Excited about
What can happen
Because
I think everyone would agree iot is a
Exciting but a lot of people don't understand
Homeowners
They kind of know they want it but
How do you put it together
So
On both service live as well as our
Home Appliance Tech
Conditions are vision for that is that we could be think of it as a trusted advisor
For this model
When we could go into someone's home which were in millions of times a year and
Help guide them through do I need
3 cameras where would I put them do I need a door lock
Do I need a door
Bell
Do I need a Wali
In my home of course you do
And that type of
Are trusted advisor type of
Assistance is where I want to take us we're not there today
But we have to have that Vision to go forward and that's where we're headed
Okay let's talk about some of the opportunities that you're seeing
So right now
What are the most common installs that you
You get for smartphone
Devices
See if thermostat
Thermostats
Very common
And now the doorbells are bad
Becoming very calm
And how much training do you need me this
As someone who is installed a lot of this stuff
And tried to get it all to work together
Impossible soul
How do you train these people
This feels like
Just a huge area of
Previous angst so I don't know what it is for
World Service live We Are
Creating relation
Recruiting
Third-party provider
So we'd intentionally go out in
Chic
Providers that
Have these skills are
And what we are is a connection with
Consumer that need something need something
Installed
And the provider that is there a resource so will you create
The connection between
Supplying them
So we're not doing that
We go find people to have that tree
You can connect them with
Either our cost
Timer for service live also has a a white-label aspect to it where
We have Partnerships with
Companies that have these
Devices
More than just iot device
Anything that can be installed
Several things
Looks to be installed at home
And we create the connection
Queen that company in providing
A resource for their custom
Burnett case
When you go inside
What are they at
I feel like I get bombarded by a crazy use cases all the time
But it's
So far the consumers are not like oh yeah
I totally won
Well yeah I think
You know every day that education
Improves by
The smart home space is still a little bit of a mystery to a lot of homeowners so a lot of the questions we get our
What connects with what
Because
Does my camera connect with my thermostat which connects with my
Wally let's use that
And I think that's a mystery for a lot of people I think bull
Moving that direction we're not there yet
To be able to be that trusted provider but that's the vision that I have
And that's a big question
You know people that I know just in my personal life
As you know I've had a connected home
Home for a long long time now
A lot of people that I know don't and that's one of the reasons
Stay it's
A little confusing so we want to be sort of an educator and
Trusted advisors what I usually call that but
Where we can educate consumer
Rumors of
How it all fits
Cuz once you understand
It's more than just having a camera is what the camera can do for you it's more than having a thermostat is what
Thermostat can do 4
Thermostat can save you
Money on your energy bill
If you have it
Install properly and setup
But if you don't have those other two pieces it's just a therm
We want to help people get the most out of
Iot devices
As well as
Understand
How to put them all together
Okay
Well I feel like I've learned quite a bit
Today thank you so much
For coming on the show
So thanks for having me on the show I appreciate that we're really excited here at Sears Home Services about the future
Probably more involved in iot and
Helping consumers in new and different ways
So thanks again for having me on
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week