Welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higginbotham as your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we of course have an amazing
Take a shower for you today we're going to be talking about a Rebrand of a popular tracking
We're going to be talking about arm
Dropping acid
Low power Bluetooth
IP
We've got up threat report
And we're going to ask an existential question about
Your Smart Homes
Security
Plus
We are going to hear input from the Property Brothers
End
We got tons of news bit such as a really cool consumer premise equipment from
A French is
We got new smart devices for the bedroom some
Crazy glass
A $10 smart plug
Hi-def cameras
And so much more
Plus I'm going to tell you what I think about the
The First Alert
Onelink safe and sound device
That
Is expensive but might be worth it for some people
And I guess this week is the
Ctio of the City of Calgary she's going to be talking about how these City
Created its own Vortec
Sensor Network and what the heck they're doing with that
And what a message from our sponsor digicert
All of this
Is coming up
After a
Another one of our response
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform
Find out why Kenmore in dealing
The Pharaoh Pharaoh customers have experienced as much as
Is 80% reduction
And in time to Market
99% pure support
Antenna
What's higher activation
Plus they can we use 90% of their work from one project to the next
To learn more visit afero
That's a fer
Oh
Dot IO
Okay Kevin
Let's get this
Party started
Boo boo
With
Tracker
What is happening with tracker
You may be familiar with to make
Bluetooth tags for
Locating items you put a tag maybe on purse
Dora backpack or computer whatever
And
Ticket believe it behind you can
Use crowdsourcing technology from other tracker users to find it but not doing that anymore
They're still going to support the old tracker
Devices
But they have pivoted with a name change they are now called adaro and they have a new line of products
Which
Is a Twist on what they used to have so
I kind of find this interesting what Ed Darrow is going to be selling it back they already are
Are a bunch of
Small Bluetooth items
Such as tags
Tablets
Key Rings lanyards Etc any idea here
Is that you make a smart
Container
The container might be again
A purse a backpack
Duffle bag suitcase whatever might be a briefcase
And you basically use the smaller tags
Too attached
To all of the items that you normally
Carry in that
Smart container that back and when you leave the house if you forgotten one of those items
It will notify you before you leave
Right away
So I like the idea of this it starts at $119
For three tags and three tablets on a charger
So it's not cheap
But yeah
So I think there's actually
A gem of a
Really great
And maybe it's because I'm a parent or maybe it's
Because I
Personally
Have
Crazy lifestyle
But if you could bring something like this in
And make it washable
And then also make it connect
To your schedule
I think you start looking at something that
Really change like that would be worth
So imagine if
I could put
Like on my daughter's gym clothes
These tablets
And I can dissociate that
Tuesday
Thursday and Friday
Is right
That kind of stuff
Do you like kimchi
Same thing for me if I could stick it in you know my gym bag
We're pretending I go to work in this scenario
I don't but
I could do that in
Especially for things that are
Variable is that the way to think about it
I don't know
Like I like where the
This is going I don't think it's 100% there yet I mean I know people who do forget their sunglasses their keys and their
Smartphone in their wallet
Very common
Is here but you walk out the door typically with the same X number of items and every once in a while you forget one of those in this week
Prevent that they do actually have a way to set up
Customize
Recurring reminders
So if you have like an event at 5 that normally go to and bring
Certain things you tag them
It'll remind you hey your yoga classes coming up
Your yoga mat is not in your bag right now don't forget it
Etcetera etcetera so
Ender portal
They're part of the way there
Awesome and this is part of a trend I mean
In tracker actually that was
Does your
Favorite one out of all the Trap like there's tiles there's a
Oh there's one that starts with a c and I can never remember it
There's a bunch of these out there but you liked
The tracker
Yeah we still have them and literally I just
Use one right now can I have two more sitting around we have it on the mailbox key
Because we have a mailbox down the street or after I go to it soon a townhouse community
And whoever gets the mail usually wasn't putting the key back where
Didn't we go so nobody could find at the next day so we put that on there so that we could find it
And I think
Where can I see a lot more of this
Tile even his
Diantha sized
Individual tiles and is working much more on basically creating a Bluetooth
Tracking Network
Work through
Is Partnerships with like Land Rover in
Steripen companies and other things
So
But I am kind of
It makes them
It makes sense I mean to smarten up non smart object so that way you know you don't live in behind
I like that idea I don't know if I like it enough $420 minimum purchase
Will get there
That's the earliest
We're very familiar with
We pay that all the time make it down this case
Spell usually
Alright in other news
This is a little bit more
How Deeply Tech
Arm has dropped its
Cordial Bluetooth
An arm is the chip design firm it is the brains of almost every
Smartphone out there
And has a big iot
Division
They'd actually created this IP around Bluetooth and narrowband cellular network
Technology
To help you it was extra low power it
It was going to be the
Special
Highly optimized
Arlo power was very cool
They basically a banded it
And
My hunch is they abandoned it because
Cuz
It was
Untested
There's plenty of other
Bluetooth face stuff
Barely low power
And I imagine that
The buyers of the stuff for like
Do we want to go with something untested not so much
So
This kind of sad
Because I thought it was actually a really interesting technical solution but sometimes really interesting
Tactical Solutions if you don't solve
Play huge enough problem in a big enough way
It's not worth it
So my hunch is that what
It's interesting just run a business perspective they actually made for Acquisitions in the last 3 years to help develop
Concordia prom
Yeah they did
And they had funded some of these
Self sow
Philadelphia punch
Sound
All right here is
I guess here's a question
Get some feedback from one of our listeners
When we talked about
We answered a question about
The guy who has a
His two daughters in their condo
What should there
Our first home basically have in it from a connector
Until are connected devices
And somebody was like Stacy and Kevin you guys really missed the mark by Knotts
Suggesting some sort of
Security box
So this could be like
Tattoo Joe service maybe it's
Weather Network
For the network
And you know we had an Advertiser bitdefender there like I heard about it
Just like the bitdefender Box
It came on right after
I got to think about this and I'm like
I don't
Currently have
One of those Services I'll be honest
But I don't actually run one on my
What time and I don't
Feel
Unprotect
But I do feel like
There is more information that I
I could know about my network
So I guess you're taking
Well I don't have one either right now I have a Google WiFi mesh Network
Connected directly to Verizon FiOS which is available in my area so that's
Pretty much it
You know it
Set up appropriately I don't think there's any more I can do in the Google app
To add security I have look at some VPN services
And try them but that causes problems because
We subscribe to
Online television and
You start having no
Geolocation issues
When you have a VPN so
I turn VPN off
I know there are some boxers that can
Not sniff the traffic what sort of monitor the traffic and see if devices are inappropriately
Accessing the web and so on and those have to go behind my Wi-Fi
Networking
So that seems to be an issue as well cuz
I don't want anything behind the network is that causes other set of problems so I think it's a good idea I have yet to have found the right
One for me and
I prefer without a
Subscription I'm a look at some that I can install on Raspberry Pi
Pihole that project on fenkell I really block
Herbs and things
Give me any security so I'm all for it
I just haven't found the right one
Fair
Yeah and so I guess
We will amend our answer to say
If you're really concerned about this
There are security services and box
Does that come I actually do check
My Eero Network every now and then to see if any devices are
Like sending more data than they should
But that's about the extent
Extent of it
So I'm not really
I do the same in in the Google Wi-Fi app you can see it anytime the history or real-time what devices are on that
Network that IP use the Mac addresses
How much traffic they sent over time Etc an indication like if my
I don't know if
If your doorbell start
Sending like 30 GB
The traffic a day you're going to be like
Different video
Does heat up a bunch of maybe I should look at that closer cuz I typically is one of the higher used devices but like my June oven is using
30 gig
Then I'm like
That should not be
If your doorbell is using 30 gig I want to know how many
Coming up to your door
Take Norm for a lot of walks couple times a day in and out in and out
Norm's life is good
Okay
So we'll leave it up to you to decide on that way
When I'm not sold
If you are
Super concerned or if I noticed
Ad networks slow down
I would probably
Splurge and get one just to see what's going on
But I'm not sure if it needs
To be there just yet
But maybe I'm wrong because according to
Nokia
Excellent Segway
According to Nokia iot Bots
In 5 minutes now make up 16% of infected devices
Observe
On
Just general Network
In the world
So this is up significantly
According to them from
3.5% of 2
This is there
Malware
Report that they put out the
And basically
The big story here is
Holy cow
Iot
Art infected iot devices are now huge
Horsham
Iot bot activity represented
At 78%
Networkx
That they have seen in carrier Network
That's more than double the rate
In 2016 after the big Turning Point
Mirai
So
And to put it in perspective for additional perspective Nokia breaks out
Different device types
Classes of devices
An Android is
Basically the biggest Target right now they say
Leaving notice a Android device is responsible for about 47.15% of observed
Maillard effect
Windows has 35% so right there you got
At seventy 82% of those two device classes IRT and then
The iPhone is like less than 1% cyattie basically the other bit here
I think that's going to change if you think it was jumping from one year ago to now give it one or two more years
When
There are billions more iot devices out there
And what do the bats go after the Big Easy targets
And that's what iot is becoming
Well I think it's worth noting that these iot devices are basically anything that's not a smartphone or
Computer and one of the challenges
Is there is
There a lot of iot devices out there that
We don't necessarily think of as I am
They might be
Printers
Or networked DVRs
So while this is a real
Rhett
Probably less of a threat for something like your thermostat one because it doesn't have a lot of processing power
Into because I'm good company is going to
Handle things like API limit calls so it's not going to reach out
Try to talk to
To offer
So that's just something
Nothing about if
You're going to pick a device that scary
I would look to video doorbells video cameras that are connected
And I would really make sure when you're buying those devices
Buy them from reputa
All right
As many of you guys know I'm planning on moving
And well it's still like 6 months away but you know it
I'm still thinking about all of my devices
And you can expect to hear more about this but I love the fact
Property Brothers
Those guys on
I don't know is it Bravo what channel is
What channel are they on
HGTV
Oh
Yeah that makes
So those guys
They actually did a panel where they talked about Smart Homes and
Selling your smartphone
I'm so of course I read it
And didn't tell me anything new
But
They did say that
Look when you have all the
Play smart devices they become
A feature
If possible selling point your home so don't take them out leave them in there
So things like your nest thermostat
Or your video doorbells or even light switches
He says they can
Raise your home's value
Yeah I could see that man
It is an investment as they say number one in
It's a value to the new buyers potential I mean not everybody wants a smart home but
Becoming very prevalent
The thing is little and I kind of realized this when I moved 2 years ago
If you're going to leave everything
You still have to actually factory reset everything and leave instructions for people have said all this
Stuff up
That was going to be my play
Holy cow
I'm in the process
Figuring out what I will leave
And I realized that some of my device
Is our Echo only
For example and so nice person comes in with a Google they're going to be like
I don't need this
Which is fine
They don't have to have it
Are they don't have to use it but like my echo powered faucet
And the other thing is
When you're showing off
Off the house
And you mention these things
The stuff better work
In I don't know about you but sometimes I will
Hotel
Padme to do something you were even Google to do something
And
Nothing happens
Maybe they didn't hear me
Right or my favorite is like
Wind
I say something in
Madam a thinks I said something else and provides me with
Completely different answer
It does but if you're trying to sell someone on the
Mustafa it's a little less ideal
Agreed
So I guess that's all I have to say about that you guys will hear more and I will definitely do a definitive guide to
I guess my particular smart home and
Decommissioning it
But in the meantime Kevin and I want to talk to you about
Tech Meme and the tech meme ride home podcast
So Kevin and I follow technium.com
Years since it started
Basically yes
As journalist is
Is the crucial tool we use it to
Up-to-date on
Daily News and
They now have a daily
It comes out every weekday at 5 p.m.
We find it super helpful
It's like 15 to 20 minutes long and it really gets you
You could see the scoop on whatever happened that day in the news
So
Cuz you guys probably like podcast
Because you're listening to us
Give it a try
Try see what you think you can go look for the
Tech meme ride home podcast
On your favorite pie
And unsurprisingly
If you start listening to it you're probably going to hear them talk a little bit
About us
That would be nice that was always the gold contact me if you don't
Not that way Kevin
Okay so let's go into some
Quick news Rundown
Thoughts on new devices
Okay
Over across
The pond
Free which is a very innovative
Telecom in is
SP they've created a
New device a new consumer premises
Device called the free box Delta
It is worth noting that
S1 because
I started covering
Isps in
Broadband
Free was just
Innovative as all get-out
Just super crazy
They're still doing it so now they have this
If you sign up for their
Service you get
What they called the free box Delta
It acts as a zigbee hub
Is Scott Madam a built-in
It's got a really fancy
And it's got six
Cox connectivity
Which is a proprietary low-power Network for things like
Old smoke detectors in
Random
Sensors
Need long battery
So they're putting that out there
It's also a media player a 4K
HDR multimedia box
And
I'm kind of excited
It's a fancy thing
What doesn't it at
It doesn't have Z-Wave
Oh okay alright
I mean it's like everything in the kitchen sink there
Yes it really does so
It's pretty fancy
They're going to charge you
10 euros a month
For this
Device
After 4 years
The pain that you
Can keep it forever
And
The CEO of
A free he hinted
Selling Reebok steel toe.
Consumers in other countries
Even if they can't see
Subscribe to the eyes
So I don't know
It's kind of like
Roku * a million I don't know
Yeah it's I mean I have the Nvidia Shield Android TV which could be a
SmartThings Hub as well there's a USB stick to add
Zigbee and Z-Wave
And that's kind of a similar all in one box
There's no
Subscriptions paid but the Box itself is typically $180 is not
Are they cheaper set-top boxes out there but he's one of those it's got a whole bunch of everything in it
A whole bunch of
You alright
Move on down smart accessory maker idevices
Yes
I don't have any idevice
Devices but
For those that do they are now integrated with
If
So you can use if this then that to create recipes for your idevices all I devices are
Supported except
For the idevices thermostat and there
Customizable LED night light
Other than that any connected smart home idevice product you can
Work with f
Another i-news iHome has launched
Vanity mirror and alarm clock
I
Yeah let's just go with music and movement
I know Evans gets into what I said A week or two ago and I was saying it's just at some point it's going to
Stop making sense of microphones and speakers and every single thing like I don't see why you need it in a vanity mirror quite honestly
This is why I want to know this my little robot
Follow me around or whatever listen
Is my assistant but
Madam
Who is the fairest of them all
Yeah well for $180 I will not do that for this spending year
That's how much it is
That is how much
Also
Other crazy new products
Bose
Has created gosh it's another glasses out the
It is a new wearable it is
These are sunglasses
And I don't even know
What's it look like normal sunglass actually look like snaps
Spectacles
With just a sunglass of the minutes
They're $199 you can pre-order them
There's some AR apps actually coming next year so they're not just
Smart glasses
Speakers
Yep there speakers
Is there microphones
AR
And yeah and you can access your virtual assistant
I mean it's kind of like her except it's sunglasses not that your thing
Yeah
I don't have the nice thing is you won't hear or people around you won't hear the assistant
Through the speakers because they're kind of
Patched into the arm of the glasses or no earbuds or anything
So I don't think of using like bone-conduction Witchwood
Give me a little more privacy as well but they say that
It's pretty discreet
And they will run up to
3.5 hours
Playback of music
And 12 hours on Steam
So you don't end up considering their sunglasses
I think it's a little weird
Just because
I mean like
You're inside
I don't know I mean I get it
You're outside you're away from
I'm stuffed but are you even connect
You probably going to Bluetooth to the phone because there's no assistant built-in so to speak it's going to leverage in assistant on your
Your phone so I'm very can I have prescription sunglasses so I'm not the market
Get there going to be $200 pre-order start today
They're not going to be out for a while
Let us know if you buy this I'm really intrigued
I think it's neat and I'm like oh I can't wait
So they work as a Bluetooth
Headset for phone calls as well
You can take calls make calls I mean I don't
I'm not in the market for this and I think we've kind of
A kind of gotten over the whole smartglasses thing
But maybe
Sure I mean
Let's give it a throw it out there soon
Ikea
Has announced a in addition to its
Triad
Line of products
It is a $10 smart plug
To go with it
Lights
There's nothing much
To say about that
Arlo has
Updated
Wireless security camera now it has the Arlo Ultra
It is a 4K HDR wireless security camera it has a built
10 spotlight
And
It's $400
Well 4K doesn't come cheap got to pay for all those case
I just
I don't know if we'll get there with 4k on all these devices over time in the prices will come down
So somebody had to be out of the gate cuz I don't think any other security cameras right now
R4k
Do you need that
Definition will
Are you know if you have cameras outside for example maybe something happen to your car like mine did with the nest cam
I could tell that a car hit it I could see my car move when it got hit
It was hard for me to exactly determine the type of vehicle and I certainly can see their license plate because zooming in
A 1080p didn't cut it so
If you can get four times the pixels
Then maybe there are use cases where yeah zooming is going to be useful
I'm not saying it's worth it I'm just saying
Hey
Speaking of nest
Did your camera go down again I did not get any notifications that my Nest cameras went down but apparently a bunch of
People did
Last week
I think it was
The overseer was just a couple days ago my bad on December 3rd
Nest went down again Booth third time in less than a month this happened on the 15th of November 27th of November
And on December 3rd and no root cause has been identified but it has been
Obviously
Where everybody would know about it
What's going on
With a cloud services on Google Cloud
I don't know
But if anyone has any clues
Let us know
In the meantime I do appreciate that whatever my Nest devices go offline or have trouble
I do actually get an email notice
Application that's like by the way
We're not working
So you know that's
Kind of a bare minimum but it is nice
Not all of my device
Isis do that
And actually I should give a shout out to downdetector.com because that is at one place too
Search for any services that are disruptive and actually right now
On the east and west coast sewer are some
Issues with nest
I don't think it's
Ton
But I see the map and it's got some yellow and orange
Dots on it
No
Let's see we have
Are lenovo's
We have to
Each of us has a Lenovo smart.
Play whe
They have new features
Too and I do
New features in fact they are getting cooking features
Such as
Your cookbook and how save and retrieve recipes you can make save
Certain recipes maybe that you use on a regular basis
They have the nest hello doorbell two-way talk
Which
I have on my
Pixel 3 phone so that way it just pops right up the doorbell shows music
All the way downstairs and my display is Right neck
So that's going to be and when I tested this on the pixel it was so much faster than having to open the app after getting a note
Vacation and by the time I did that to talk to whoever was on the front porch they already gone
So this is a much better way to do it they have touch alarms in the
Quick Settings now the time out to go to a dark screen is actually faster when in low light which is good at night time
You can even Now by voice I turn off the screen I don't do that so if these sensor isn't quite working at night to your side of
Faction you can say hey
Java spring
And then
I really like respect my white loves us the bigger dark screen clock face have you looked at this lately
Yes I noticed that and I was like
You have the update and me with
Terrible eyesight
Even with the smart display on my nightstand right next to my bed I could not read the little clock
At night so now I can
Well I must read this one my eyes are really bad
Lee's Summit
Suppose sunglass
Then you can have an AR
Who needs good vision
Just use AR
Let's talk about your new toy you got a Google home hub
Yes yeah
Speaking of smart displays at the last second while the Google home hub was on sale for $99 direct from Google
I ordered one
It is so small which I knew because I saw it at the laundromat but I
Took it out of the box as soon as it arrives and I send Stacy a picture of this device in the palm of my hand
And what did you think when you saw that
Cute butt
Again with bad eyes I like a larger display on things
So we actually because we have a 10 inch smart display in the bedroom I stopped watching TV on that
Facts about TV on the wall there I was using it for you to TV from time to time
But it's big on a nightstand so we
Suave I bought the home hub for the kitchen island
To watch news in the morning or coffee with my wife
But actually the smart display is better the big one the 10-inch one so now the Google home hub is on the nightstand
An array it's a good fit there I think that's an ideal size for the bed
It does all the same things as well whenever one I just does not have a camera that's fine
But Duo calls actually work
The same I mean I didn't know my son was going to call you about having to be laying around in bed and I got to do a call on me
I'm up if you can only do Audiomack I don't care and pick it up so I pick it up I explain to him that I got no camera here he said that's no problem
He was happy to show me his
Happy face so we had a great call the experience was fine yeah I mean I think it's a nice device at specially 99
149 it's a little pricey
All right and I think
It's a good bedside tables
I also have a
Talk about I have a review unit of the
First Alert onelink
Safe and
Sound
That is a mouthful it's actually device
We recommended on her gift guide
Play parents
Just because
So it is expensive it's about $200
But this is a smoke detector
A carbon monoxide detector
And
The crazy part
It's a really good speaker
Bitconnect
To Apple homekit
And
Amazon's Echo
Ecosystem
So I can
Talk to this
Speaker and I tell it to do something I can talk to it just like I would talk to Madam a
Controls all those devices it also will play my music
From anime
And it will also make phone
So and it sounds amazing
The only issue I have
With it is because my smoke detectors and I think most smoke
Actors are set by the doorways of rooms
I kind of want this thing in the
The center of my
Has one big
It also has a night light that is a multi colored LED that you can
Can set so I can set it
I think right now it's set to
So you know in the middle of the night or whatever it is
Detects a lowlights
Setting it's like
What turn the night light on
Socket has purple glowy light in my hall right now where I'm testing it out
Setting it up with
Super Breeze
I have
Kidde smoke
Detectors
So
It's a different brand
They have a comes with three different connectors
And a mounting bracket
So I unscrewed my mounting bracket
I took Olive like
30 seconds
Pop the other mounting bracket
And use the little connector shove the wires up
Screw the sucker on the hardest part
Was actually screwing it
Into
Mounting bracket
Not a hundred percent sure I
Got all of the things
I say this be
Because this is a very heavy
Smoke alarm it weighs like
I don't know pound and a half to pounds
It's not something like
Cuz like I really don't want to
First of all because it is heavy
It's a decent speaker
Indecent speakers
Are heavy weighs 1.76 lb
Oh I was good but
Check Outback
Yes that was a good guess
And it does have like I said
The homekit compatibility sew-in is going to have AirPlay 2 coming later on
So you can actually
Play your Apple music
Through it if you set it up as
Homekit function
Functionality
I didn't do that because
Didn't need to but you know if you wanted to
You could actually set it up as a homekit devices
Control it from there
I tested it it works
As a traditional smoke alarm so it will go off
And will also set off all of your other smoke alarms
If they're inert
Does it send you an alert on your
On your body
Thing says you are hallways
In case you're not at home
Yes cuz currently none of my
Alarms do that but none of your dumb smoke alarms cost
$250
Well it's on sale for
Amazon right now
A list price is 24999
There you go
Yasso on sale at Lowe's
But yes
It is inexpensive
Which device and for most people you're probably just going to be like
Why don't I just buy an echo Dot
And I would say to you this sounds better
But
It is 4 * 2
Your microphones and speakers I sent the trend
Yes I still like it
For anyone who doesn't want the stuff in their house
Like it doesn't want it
The clearing up things
True true
It does sound really amazed
Yeah well the heaviness suggest that to
Not yet I have your speaker typically would sound better not
That's not an exact statement but it's a good General paste
So there's that device if you're in the market for like
Ceiling mount
Speakers that work with Madam AR
Homekit
This
It's not bad
It's actually good
Altitude
To have
Apple music
And you don't have one of these
There's a tie up now between app on Amazon that you're going to be able to listen to Apple music
Play on your Echo devices
Starting to
December 7th
Will let you know
Kevin will try it out
And
We'll see how that work
Vector my little robot may have his
Madame a feature
By then I bet you he can play the music
On that little itty bitty speaker
I know I can dance
There's like three different links
To get that one thing
Oh man that's crazy
Okay
Now it's time for our
Voicemail
The Internet of Things podcast
Which
You guys is sponsored by
End
Do not miss your chance
When is Schlage connect smart deadbolt
Now
Zigbee certified and
Working with Amazon
Compatibility
You will be able to upgrade your smart home with the safety Simplicity and style
Slay
You can do this
Because
Pick a winner for a Schlage Smart Lock
To win all you need to do is
Just call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And
Leave us a voicemail with your question and you will be entered
To win
Is luck
And let me tell you guys
We have the November
Winner
Provided
As always that they are not located at
Outside of the US
Or
Canada
So let's hear for this month's winner Kevin who is it
It is David and based on his area code I suspect he is within the US
He actually left us a good question in November that we didn't get to he's looking for a Smart Switch
I work shop light but he has to fluorescence and no neutral wire and
We looked and we didn't find anything
There was a product that you sweet made
That would work for that
But
We came up empty so
At least you're not empty-headed David you you win the Schlage Smart Lock
Yay
All right and I should note that last week
We talked about
Putting in a smart
Light switch without a neutral wire I said that
The only option out there was Lutron
And a bunch of people who use insteon
We're like jalapeno
That is not true
Is insteon actually makes a light switch that also works
Out
A neutral wire
You will need
In NC
However you also need a Lutron Hub so you know
Similar
And now
Let's go to this week
Question
Which is from
Clarissa
Hi guys this is
I have
Question about
Smart Talk
If you guys
We're not concerned about privacy and anyway
My tech would you be using in your bed
Thanks have a great one
Okay Clarissa
This is a good question
And when we can totally help with
So
Clarissa
Let us explain it
We actually probably have more devices to suggest than one would want in their bedroom and working
Keeping in mind that maybe privacy doesn't matter enough
That's fine that's a personal choice
Some useful items we have in here
So we mentioned the smartest plays earlier in the show
I definitely think that's a good
Place for a smart displays in the bedroom is Stacy and said
Because you have voice control of all of your smart home devices you can also
Touch screen control them if maybe
Somebody sleeping in the room you don't want to use a voice
You can get weather information York
Calendar
You can do
Cameras from other devices in your home
Really handy
You probably want some smart followers and or switches
We could
Decide on any single one there's so many options out there
So did want to make a plug
There a couple lights like Philips and GE make lights that are designed for better
Sleeping better
Throughout circadian rhythm
Circuit anyway
Start out with bright daylight
And then evolve slowly into a deeper orange as it gets towards sleepy
And when you wake up you can have those kind of come up like Sunrise which
Kind of nice
And then we also have
Amazon look with Stacy you
This is
Kind of interesting because you can use it to help get
Clothes selection
Yes it is a camera where you basically put on an outfit
Take a picture
Using the web camera
Snap a picture
And it snaps a picture
And then you
Put on
Other outfit options
What's it basically looks at those and says
This one's better
So
This is a really kind of silly thing but I threw it in there just in case
You
Have doubts about your
Watch over need a friend
If my wife ever divorce has met with her fashion degree and go somewhere else I will get one of those because
She dresses me basically
Photo app that doesn't happen
Let's hope
I'm always thinking ahead I want to be prepared you know you know
If you want to monitor your sleep you could obviously do that through wearable devices there's so many of those that do track
Sleep such as the fitbits and smart watches and such
Why things actually makes
A nice
Relatively inexpensive
Solution for this
You basically put a little pad under your mattress and it
Tracks your sleep sleep stages heart rate
Snoring the whole shebang
And you can get that for about
$80 on sale list price as a hundred bucks which is not too expensive as a nice smartphone app as well so you can look at the graphs
Send all the data
If that's your thing and then we also came up with
Monitoring your air
In your bedroom
Because you want to be sleeping in clean air if they see you mentioned this before because you bought one
To monitor the
Classroom are
For your daughter's class
And it's the aware glow which is kind of like a smart plug but also with sensors to monitor
Different aspects of the air quality
Yes it
Temperature humidity
The
Carbon dioxide
Oxide in the air and also
Quote on quote
Chemicals
Which are
Volatile or
And I didn't know until you mentioned it before the show that
You can actually use that
Data
And have the arrears plug actually turn on say humidifier this Plug-In or a
Air purifier or a heater or air conditioner
Yes you will tell be aware what you plugged into it basically
So if he's plug-in in our case we plug it in
Air purifier
When it sees
That the air quality is degrading it will actually
Proactively turn on the air
Which is
Cool feature I think
So you just tell it what your plug again and then I will use it to proactively adapt Fiero
Around you
And I think that's
Awesome picture
And since we have an air purifier that nobody wants to get out of bed to flip the switch I am going to go by myself in a where
Glow because
That is perfect for what we need
Last thing we could suggest that this is really going to town if you don't care about privacy we talked about it before the 1400
Dollar 3D body
Scanner mirror from naked Labs yes
The naked so you could see how fit you are or not
Well I didn't want to say that but yes
Yes because
Gretchen you probably wouldn't have that in your bedroom that might be in a bathroom connected to the bedroom but
I think it's really interesting product I just don't think it's
First $1,400 when I can
You take pictures or have my family just told me I'm getting fat but that's just me
I think it's
Venus Project
And I would not want it at all in my life
I don't even like that it exists in the world but
Close because of privacy or because you have
Because I don't want to know
Okay
I can do something else
Without the aid
An artificial
You can pay me $10 a week
For you as well.
Cuz I like you I think you're my friend
So I am biased yes I would not want that information from you cuz at the end of it I be like
Screw you Kevin
So much for that Revenue stream
All right
So hopefully out of all of these devices oh and I will throw this in
We talked about having a connected bedside table lamp
Which I think is great but also why not connect your bedroom light switch
Because then if
Those lights have
And Beyond
You can turn them off with your voice without getting out of bed witch
What time snug under my covers I do not
Want to leave that room so
I would throw that in there and maybe a smart outlet
Letter to to control fans or anything else you got going on
In the bedroom
So all of those
Really
Actually have most of
And I thought you cared about privacy and I do care about
Privacy I don't have any cameras in the bedroom that's the only thing I don't have the look is in my closet facing away unless I need
Facebook portal
Nope
All right
Well
That is it for this segment of the show please stay tuned for a message from our sponsor
And our interview with
Cit
CEO of the City of Calgary
Talking about their laurel-ann
Sensor Network
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is
Digicert and I have Mike Nelson who is VP of iot security
Here to talk to
Let's get this started by telling us a little bit about what digicert
Where certificate Authority or the largest certificate
30 globally in our services are
Protecting internet connection
And that raises everything from SSL TLS
Certificate for website security to Enterprise Security Solutions and
My area ZIP code
Courses with iot
Security and we have robust Solutions using visual search
Give the kids to secure it authentication
Communication over the internet
Excellent all right
Well you guys recently did a survey
About coyotes
What did you guys discuss
Yeah earlier this year was selected
A survey we reached out to over 700 engineer's for iot
Manufacturers
These were people on the front lines
Security in their organization
Other respondents
Divided them into
Three tier
The top tier
Would be classified as organizations
Sunset have fewer iotc
Security incidents they've demonstrated
Mura Masa
Tree and iot security doing things like encryption authentication risk
Assessments there's middle class
The bottom
The bottom tier of Courts
For the organizations that are really struggling to get
How old am I
Security and to put those practices in place
So we're there big differences between the two
The results were surprising
So we have to respond
About iot related security incidents that they had a
Experience
The past 2 years
The difference between the top and the bottom
Here were a mistake
Of the bottom tier organizations
Every one of them
Reported that
Experienced
The security incident
Something like monetary damages or loss of product
70 compared to just
32% of the top-tier organizations
Experiencing an incident
Comedian shows that
The things the Topsy organizations are doing those things like encryption and I'll send it
Vacation
Risk assessment other devices
Those things are working
And they're leaving those organizations to be much better off
Okay
So let's talk about those on the bottom tier
What type of damages
Did they
Yeah I think
Most surprising was monetary.
25 /
Percent of the bottom tier reported iotc
Security lock
At least 34 million dollars in the last
2 years
And those range from
Monetary damages
Loss of Prada
Activity
Legal penalties that they're having
Pay and impact to their stock price
So where can we find out more about digicert and the results of
Our website is www.denniskirk.com
And there's a link there that
And take you to find more information about the survey
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Heather
Read Penske
Who is the CI to at the city of
Alder tree
I'm just Gray Station thanks awesome. I should tell u c i t o mean
Chief Information Technology officer which is a title I've never heard
Is that really common
I guess in Calgary or in this Municipal business
No I think it was
Just a combination
Heo so it
Takes a basketball to put them together or possibly just two jobs in one day
So the City of Calgary has deployed a Laura
Network and I thought this was really interesting because
One there not alot of city-owned Laura Networks
But I'm aware of so I want to talk about that and then you guys are doing some really cool
Cool things with it
So let's just start off with
Your approach to this networking
How this came to be
Sure and I have to go back in
In time because
And City of Calgary we've always had a vision
Turn around connected
City and. Started
You know more than
15 years ago and we've been building out communication
Structure to a fiber optic Network
18 years
We really saw that is the foundation
Send up Dan building a pond that
Forest Park
Obsidian to the Future
And innocent of knowing what was
Coming into
Future in terms of
Depot access devices building
Being connected
What that would
Mean for a city operation
Versailles
We wanted to make sure we had that Foundation
Spice so
We have used a fiber-optic Network
Carrier-grade Network which we built
In
Nickelback 2013
Which shirts all of our trip a product Network for the City of Calgary and all our offer
Water skiing
And then from there we you
Use some of the infrastructure that we had
Play so we have
Radio towers
That we use
Responders for their Radio City
And wisdom tooth at Biltmore the last mile
Components of a fixed Wireless which helped us to get to a few
UCI
And then from there we challenged our innovation
Technology
To go about researching
Spell to do that
Awesome
It sounds like there's lots of things going over that Network
We can run many different services on it it's
260 City facilities
City operator
Is really important in our a lot
Has been that is a city we need our own private Network we be everywhere we
Sure we need it to be available for our first
Responders
MCC Public Safety situation
And that's always been
Our
Call Envision
So why did you choose Laura
When they're kind of some other proprietary Technologies out there there's the
The cellular stuff was it part of the being city-owned aspect
No it was just our team really analyzed
They reviewed
Lora technology and
It really felt it had some of
Advantages
Security functionality the implementation and operating cost
The real ability to have
True that coverage
Performance
And
Knology
One picture they have flexibility and better
The system that was
The technology
She that they decided on and started to
To install
Radios on
Some of our radio towers and were able to get pretty much the whole
Geographic area
Cool okay so you guys were doing Smart City before it was even cool it sounds like
I like to see
You got it
Lot of stuff happened in their soul
Talk about some of the newer things that you guys are doing I was most excited
I think because
Sounded
Really beautiful and also complex
This devonian Gardens
You guys
Haven't you should probably tell us what that is first
And I will talk about what you've done
Devonian Gardens
Is the three-acre
Like this
Peaceful Refuge
Depends on the top of the shopping
It's one of the largest
Indoor gardens of its kind and it was more than
10000 ground cover plants
Square foot living wall pond
Children's play area
I really kind of this Oasis
Stat targaryens
Go to in the middle of
The downtown
It's really impressive
Space has imported exotic plants
Tropical trees
And it's really been
We go through so there really precious asset that are in this Garden
This unit for the main challenge for them is creating that healthy environment
Or all of the
And all these
Tropical
Interior plant
These tropical plants life is hard for them in the middle of Calgary even if it is a nice and close to area so it's
It sounds like you guys built out a sensor Network
Work in
Curious
So the sensor networks measure soil moisture at measure
Late for these plans
And there's a feedback loop this getting built
What does it look like
Build something like that
And how do you make it economical for the city
I think the main thing for us
Because we already have the
Infrastructure in place
Having that foundation in
Place it was absolute
Will be Paramount for us being able to
Launcher dorwin Network
Write in a lure when Network
She'll really was not that it's
Expensive
Cuz we had that sound
Place so we spent about 45 K on radio
To be able to have the network
And then
Writing about it
Software platform tools that were you
Collect the data
For the team itself there really are innovation
Operation
Citgo in try again
Products
You know they were crate closed
See with our local
University here and
Next race in the field as well Jacob
My GF
The main Center they were looking for was a soil Monitoring Center
To measure the water content
And at some of the Electra
Conductivity in the soil as well and so that way they
Some kind of the understand the irrigation performance against the required
Plants
And that's where it's really helping our
You know what they should be doing and how they
Watering plants
In that area or anybody
The light the temperature is required to keep
Keep some of those
Exotic plants
Healthy so how does something like this
Change the job
Of the staff in the gardens are they
Now responsible for the censored networks are they still doing
Like I just trying to think about once we add this
This type of connect
Activity and get more information out of things a lot of times that changes the job just
Descriptions of some of the people
The stuff
I think this is an evolving thing I know it is in our organization is that Evolution around
Havana lyrics
And yeah really making sure that in an organization we are training
People in that area
And then I think an area like devonian its they could be much more precise
About the work that they're doing
Very very much more precise
Excellent okay well let's move to you guys have also in addition to
Hopefully making it easier and healthier for your plants
You've also
Done
Project with noise pollution and understanding kind of the acoustic profile of you
I'd love to hear more about that and what does that entail and how much of the city does
Yeah we just done and most of these cases for tubing in Pilot mode and
We really
To be honest with you wanted to try
Some Pilots were they weren't
They weren't going to
Impact and essential service necessarily right
Turn the noise pollution and I think there's a few cities that are looking at how they monitor noise and
I think one of the goals is really to get to what's the type of noise
As well
Cuz I can help in terms of
You know what kind of
Services are operations need to respond if there is something
Teenager happy
City project
Noise monitoring with a partnership
With
University of Calgary so between the City of Calgary in the University of Calgary we have the program called the urban.
Where you know if we have
Knee problems that we're trying
Thank you
She might be
How fast
Ravens put those on the table of the UFC have some research
To conduct and it would like
Real time
Problems
Access
Some of our facility
Networks
That they're able to do that too
So it becomes a partnership
Some of these research projects
Umbrella so we worked with a robotics
Central Network group
Out of the Department of electrical and
Computer Engineering at UC
And they really collaborated to help
Should have built this
Sensor
To initiate this pilot
She tried it on a
We have different sites
Weather Sebastopol
Typically where we get
Complaints from citizens who live nearby about noise and we also have new ordinances bylaws
They wanted to have an ability
To be able to
Understand what the noise level was
I think in the future again
Precision
Why do we need
Send Paula out there if we can actually get to the place where we
Distinguish the type of noise it is
I need to be able to have onboard so they use
EBay sensors and they were placed at a carnival
Circle Carnival actually can't remember what
That played
Apartments
September and the senses were programmed
Noise level over a window
3 minutes
The noise of a rose above
E85 gas
This actress sent a warning packet
Through the lorwyn protocol and then
Provided to concert promoters
Sure
You in the future is that
Get that feedback to the car
Promoters
To ensure the noise
Compliance
So it was that happening in real-time so you can get like an alert on your phone and be like
It was it was in the pilot we didn't quite have the connection where we were then saying
Hey mister concert
What's happening right now at your Festival
Use cases going forward
Kids that get up having a bunch of it
Possible people who are
Sitting there with the noise monitors were able to send them alert
That say hey you're over the Bible
So noise
Sensors
Have been
Somewhat controversial one because of the idea that they're recording all the time and that makes
People kind of uncomfortable
Comfortable like can they hear conversations we don't know
Some can some
Can't and then the other idea
I talked to somebody in the city of Busan
Korea and
They had an interesting problem where they did noise profiles in the city and in areas that were louder than
Then others
They publish the state on their website in the
Citizens got upset cuz their property values were
Declining is what they
Said and I thought that was really interesting and doosan decided not to publicly
Publish this data anymore in the website as a result
How to bet but there's so many
Unintended consequences so can you address
First off
Privacy
Are you recording all the time and then to talk about maybe potential unintended consequence
Yeah I like your question cuz it's something that we think about quite a bit and it needs use cases I said they're fairly
Contain
Not in
Critical
Operation
The whole idea of pride
Is she and where we're heading in a world of sensors I think it's something
Cities as we are deploying the
Sperone operations we have to make sure we're not
No privacy for a citizen
Is Paramount and that were not
To your point
The hottinger
Unintended
Is I don't know for these ones I don't believe for the test that we did in this one Carnival it was to the level
Where you could get
No individual conversate
I think some of them value
Looking for it
You don't have comments
311 noise
So being able to
Karachi addressed some of those noises
Complaints may be one
Future
Use case
Support some of those
Noise bylaw violation
Some of that data
I have heard about
Not being able to
Lexus
Nowhere the noisiest part of the
I'm really glad that you shared that
Example cuz those are some of the things we really need to think about you
Impacts of that kind of
Could be or the employee
Okay until you guys in Calgary because you've been doing this for so long so I feel like
You guys must have thought about this
Do you have
A digital infrastructure plan one of the challenges I think is municipalities
Start putting technology in places
They don't actually have a plan to make sure it all comes together in the end
So maybe they don't have like
Unified data schemes or
You know interoperability between vendors
So that's it
Technical side but then on the
Citizens side they don't actually have
Policies about privacy
Or how they're going to use the data
And I'm curious if you guys have built that
Already
And I would say because of the track I think we're all on his City's those
Strategies and need for some of those policies evolve right along the way
So yeah we've had a few different strategies
Things that work together we have a digital strategy where we really are focused
On Digital Services
Square citizens open data card.
Did holiday
And then we have another strategy
Which is more round
Information management
Right and how are using our data.
Privacy piece
Lisa's part of that
Yes for the processes that we go through before we have data out on our open data catalog
Legacy Challenge and if we move forward into this world
If we're trying to go
Slow
Enter learn from it
They'll be more that we need
To think about and can
Consider through some of those policies
So what is your neck
Spec project
For the Smart City going to be
You know we're at city that
Foothills
The Prairies in the mountains
Planting trees in urban canopy is
Really really
Golem strategy
Until recently we really didn't have a Dependable way or measurable way
Confirm that the teacher
Water
At the correct interval
So we worked our parks
Apartment 2
And idea to have a water flow sensor
Already have
Portable GPS
Cellular modem
In there
Which gives that wireless
Activity
Potato flour
And Daddy was simple but
It was complicated
Haswell
And to what we
We did is we actually have
Watering trucks that now having industrial-grade
Water flow sensor in them and then a gif
And allowed
Viewing of
Amount of water that be
Tree in real time until they can actually see from the
What that old world tree watering
Progress per day
Temper Trap
Works like
And that really helps
Disability
Yashow
Tree watering
Number one
Reduce
Jerry water can
Nutri actually reduced
The death of nutrients due to overwatering or underwatering
And what they do
To have all of their truck
Did it for these water flow sensors
That they can really use their resources
Water and staff and contractors really effectively and efficiently
To the point where they can
Sure that their staff and their contractors are doing what their
Supposed to be doing relative to the urban canopy
I feel like we've covered a lot here and I appreciate you coming on the show this week Heather
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
Remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Nginx