Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Christy from CNET
That's right we got right here
Because Kevin is
In California at the Google Cloud
So
Rai is going to be awesome with us today we are going to
Have a message from our sponsor
Spin dance talk about it training
We're also going to have
News
Tons about things like the CIA hacking into television
Amazon
Update on that murder case
Lots of rumors about Echo and things
Become
Some issues with Google home
A new smart home Gateway
Brand new first-time home
My experience with
Homekit
And an update on my time with Lutron and SmartThings
Things try to get that too
Will also have
An awesome guest Ross Harvey of the yield
It's an agricultural company based in Australia and she talks about things like
How did you
Data-sharing
And making money off of
So it's got to be a good interview
You stick around
And now a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Wolf SSL
The world's top 5 Industrial Automation companies use SSL to secure everything from Factory floor
Devices to their power beaters and they aren't alone
Including Automotive
Connected home
Industrial
Military and medical device
Places with the Mirai botnet and the growing threat of ransomware attacks on the
The Internet of Things companies have to pay attention to
UTI medication
Bad PR and their brand value
Securing the iot
It's hard but wolf SSL has experienced a specialized
Expertise to help
To find out more visit wolf ssl.com
Well let's just get right into
Because
Got a lot of new
So first up that everyone
Probably think
Is
The CIA
Hacking
Well all kinds of stuff so they were Revelations this week that the
He has a program to hack
Smart TVs
And a bunch of other devices
And I thought of this and I was like oh my God
Yes it is true that I thought it was the NSA but it's really the CIA
Probably listening
So what do you think about this guy
I think that
As long as you got cameras on our phones and microphones on our phones and computers and
Stability idea of cameras and microphones on their body and their home
Smart model
But
Tortas Ya
Not just a Samsung
Specific
Confirmed
La Santa Cecilia isn't confirming anything but
I don't think it's a stretch to assume that the CIA is going to
Microphones in
Cameras inside
Probably
Cameras and microphones in their home in general
Because I think the
So I don't know that there are really strong guidelines
People are aware of the people
When it comes to devices in their home and in what the government is capable of what
Just got a new frontier that
People are figuring out as they go
That hasn't dissuaded people from buying devices that have microphones and cameras
I would remind people
Not to commit crimes
In front of their Amazon Echo or they're smart television
For example
There is the case of we brought this up before
Cut the hot tub murder
Scandalous
This is a murder investigation actually that the police
They were seeking the suspects
Amazon Echo files because they wanted to understand who was in the home
At the time
And Amazon was fighting this
Which good for them rightly so
Saying it was over reach there other ways to get that info
Formation
And
What happened
Now is that
Suspect basically agreed to let Amazon
Pass those files
So
The good news is Amazon was really into fight the bad news is we don't actually we're not going to get a legal opinion anytime
Time soon
Weather this is
Prosecutorial overreach or
Legit
What's a really good point I think and
Sort of interesting
In terms of
Didn't hear you know that Amazon was going to turn it over after
Suspect gave the okay
I wonder if the conspiracy theorist in my young
Could someone use the Amazon Echo to create an alibi
You know could you sort of second voice command remotely or something somehow trick the echo to thinking that your home while you're out committing a crime and
And tell the police
Turn the lights off
Go ahead Amazon show
So I guess it's interesting
Tac being kind of ahead of where the zeitgeist
I like the way
Oh
Alright on the topic of the Echo Man
Are worse
Medi
Rumors
You actually put out
Moments of brilliance
We'll call it this is the Amazon tap
No longer being
Red-headed stepchild of the
Echo family
And so I'm assuming you're talking about
And take it with you and still be able to
Hands-free
Chatting to
Yeah yeah
Point spread
Before you couldn't even
Activated remotely
Now you can say
Awkward wake it up and use it just like an echo
I'm not quite as strong as the echo is
So as a middle ground between those two
You can't do with the echo or the echo. I think it's going to be a pretty intriguing option going for it I'm kind of curious to see what happen
People get the memo that that the are the top in a lot better now and will see it'll be interesting
So
Now this raises the question should I buy a tap which cuz I I feel like my home
I don't have enough of them
So I'm like should I buy the
Or should I hang
Tight for a little bit because rumors last
Where the Amazons going to unveil some
She Who Shall Not Be Named power devices
That will allow you to initiate
Calls using Voice
And it could also work as an intercom
Comp system
And this is from Rico
And I'll be honest I was actually following the story so I
Believe that this is
Totally accurate
So
Should people wait
That's a good question
Especially if I already had him
Echo or Echo dot access to Amazon cloud services
I'll be stealing at my home with extra devices
Just right now it's just
Kind of the perfect
Bad time to do it
Because there are so many rumors out there
Beltone call functionality rumors
Also talk of media camera
That might be voice activated in some way there was a week images that someone found
Lycoming through Amazon.com of a camera that looks a little bit like
The canary Flex a little table top camera
With a very familiar blue ring around the lens so
Yeah I don't know that
We're going to want to rush into a product like that that is so
ISO camera Focus
Especially in light of everything going on in the news so different
Expand what they've done so far
And I will have a fun time seeing what actually comes to comes to life
What are your
Favorite features
I'm assuming
I do yeah yeah I was one of the lucky ones that got one of the discounted ones in the very beginning at 7 to pay tobruk
Yeah I was so happy
Iran time I felt like I was a winner
Turn lights on and off my lifx bulbs that work really well with it
Check the weather every morning on my way out the door you know I ask for music all the time through Spotify
It's just a convenient
Neat little piece of the future
But yeah there's definitely a lot more of that
It could do and I'm kind of excited to see what comes there could be some really big steps
Olympics
The intercom feature because
We put things around the house
I guess I have to re-up my
Speaking of hard
Since we're talking about these with Bruce Sterling once on my podcast called talking donkeys
I kind of like that phrase
Google home
I don't know if you have one but I do and it stopped
Working for me this week
I went over to CNET and lo and behold they had a lovely story explaining that I was not alone
That other people were having this issue
First came out and then I didn't feel the need to pick up a Google home but we do have
Peanut smart home as well
Places about
Difficulties with Google home that it kind of been bubbling the last month or so
Especially with Google home controlling Philips hue light bulbs I'm not sure if you were using it for that in your home
People that
Work
That have no problems with the Google home otherwise
Or just totally unable to control their lights is really weird
Performer when it comes
Smart lighting so that that was sort of
Eyebrows
Verizon
Because we're not able to replicate the issue on our end
Able to confirm that sun
Users are crazy
How cold is right now and just put only tell us that they're working on
I am one of those users who had issues and
Actually last
For 2 days
These cloud dependencies
A huge number
People listen to the shower
Probably right now are gleefully playing it
So it was remarkably opaque and that was actually really frustrating
As a user
Because I did go online and I saw a lake
I saw it
Couple issues but Google's help was not
So
What is happening
Yeah I know I think that the frustration
People have a really telling the really indicative of how much people enjoy and
Come to rely on using
Voice control Platforms in their home
Unplugging the router and plugging it back in
And they've already come this thing that you know when the clock goes down to get frustrated but that's just sort of the way it is
I don't know that makes Amazon like
Time Warner Cable cable company of the future but but we'll see
I think there's
Actually this spring.
So I have a question for you
Because my Google home is in my master bath
And I love talking to it when
When I'm in the shower
Play music
What's the weather for the day
News for the day all of this stuff
It was kind of chilly here
And I was
Oh
I should totally hook up
My little shower heaters
Have a little
Heater light heater fan thing
For my
I forgot to turn it on and I was like I'm not getting out of the shower
Water everywhere is like
Slightly warmer bathroom
When I get out but
This is a perfect use case for the smart home because I can be there and say
Google turn on
What
Do you recommend or are there
Switches cuz I I don't want to stick like a normal switch on my
Heater fan because I feel like that's probably a different
Different device
Do you have any recommendations there any knowledge about
I got Standalone Appliance
Heater that you plug in or is it true
It's in the ceiling
If you hit the button on a little
Warming sand
It's just a basic on off switch
You can use a Smart Switch to turn a ceiling fan
Smart Switch
Should be able to handle so you can use
Belkin WeMo light switch
Pretty sure is Google home compatible
Imo's products and
A lot of smart switches coming out this
CES in January
So I'll ask him more often hopefully the coming months but right now if you want to do it I'd say Just Go With It WeMo light switch
OC I was going to go with
Can I go with the Lutron
But that's just
Okay
But we were almost getting ahead of ourselves
Is the Segway Direction
You guys
All right
Before we go into some Lutron stuff
Jesus has a new smart home Gateway
And I looked at this and the first thing I saw was it didn't have
Z-Wave in it
And I was sad
Because I have a lot of
Running around the house
And I also looked at it
Said holy cow it is a ring of
Light it looks like that GE Echo Power
Latex
See I don't know I feel like it's it looks a little too futuristic to go in my
It's not it's not a devices
Yeah
Yeah I think that's a good point and I think that's smart
Figured out that line
Certo
Between futuristic and inconspicuous
Probably in Arizona
Besides I think some people like Tech like that and some people don't
And you know it's the type of thing that
I think you could probably just hide behind your TV or wherever if you don't like the look of it
But yeah
Dimensions of it but that ring
Looks looks
Pretty sizable as far as how to go
It looks so it's right next to in their Press paper
It's right next to
What they done is they've launched
The Gateway
And I should give you
Spax its support zigbee Bluetooth and WiFi
It manages all of the other Asus Smart Home
Isis soda can Outlets I got some sensors that got blocked
The guy that looks like a siren
And the Gateway is probably the size of their lot
And these are going to be launched on March 16
So not quite
There yet
I kind of feel like
Dear God do we need another
The first criticisms a lot of people will think of when they see it you know we already have
Several houses that are pretty well established
Point you know I think
Got a hard time catching up with wink and SmartThings
Not there for a while
Things you can do with it
This point is going to be a market mover I think people are looking for more devices and more things that can do things and actually have a tangible
Experience in their home
As opposed to devices that just
Can control
But I don't know if you need
Give a little bit
Now I will say I think this would be cool
So Jesus also announce this was
Hcso
Xxv
Robots
Zhengzhou
And that's actually being produced
You can actually buy it it's a
It's like $600 but
This is supposed to be a smart home robot and I think if you stuck all the smarts that are in the Gateway
Is it also does robot
Things like
Talk to your kids and reach them
Dancing
Headed back companion robot idea
Crazy expensive
Compared to like just by spending like $100 on
I don't know I'm like everything in a hug
In a robot
We saw a couple things like that
CES this year I I don't know I think
I think that idea
Very nips
Very much like a very specific kind of product
A lot of people
Wouldn't necessarily want
And there's any practical sort of
Questions about that informs of how to get rid your home of the upstairs
What you step on it what if your dog plays with it
Pinchos
I like that you were the
Practicality
All right
If you knew
Small pieces
Your Nest Thermostat now has two Factor
To which I say
I mean it is good from a security
Prospective anytime you log in you're going to get two-factor you have the option of having to pee
But if I'm thinking about looking into all the devices in my house that I'm constantly logging in and out of four
Testing purposes or just
Something glitches out
I'm kind of like
Okay
That's a lot
And that ride you got
Adelaine camera
Homekit compatible camera that will actually show you the seed directly in apple
On your iPhone
Onyx the D-Link omna
Which is just a freshly out
Reviews from
Who's our camera crew
And she wasn't totally whatever
Appreciated The View
Has a lot of the basic features done right but it was shocking
To me at least that there weren't more
Interesting things you can do with it because of the whole cake
You can't even pull up the Apple
Apple TV app
Have to watch this
You can do that with an s
But this isn't the first Apple TV
You can't do a whole lot of things of it through home I think it just would have revealed that homekit
Despite having taken
Next step forward in the last 6 months
I still have work to do
Interesting experience that makes
Awesome and we'll talk about that in a minute but first we're going to talk about IBM and Salesforce
Doing a
Partnership
This is on the industrial side you guys but
This is a portico day I partnership
Where
Basically
Be human
Reading capabilities of Watson
Will be tied in with salesforce's
Einstein
CRM
Basically what I thought was most interesting
About this is the fact that the two of them
Are not doing a revenue-sharing
They're actually just going to be
Cross-selling
And reselling
I thought this was interesting because
The way they've got this partnership structure there
Doing a reselling agreement
Agreement based on 10 of their algorithms and data that they
Are using for this
And
Because data is such a
Crucial element
How you
In The Internet of Things
I thought
Man
I was hoping to see these big companies kind of start to model for us how we do these data sharing contract
But instead it seems like they're sidestepping the issue
Entirely
Which might be smart
But it doesn't bode well
Personal startups
This one actually be
Real until
The end of the show
Headline generating stories
Testing time
Speaking of homekit
So
I've been trying
Come in as a non-apple user this is been Lake
I don't know this is like learning how to walk
Grits
My toes or something
Just feel so utterly for
Foreign to me
But I've been giving it the old
College try
And I said everything up working with my
My phone and that was
It was so lovely I didn't feel like it was anything revolutionary it was super easy to set up
Totally one at that
But I decided I wanted to create it I wanted to use the Elgato Eve motion sensor
Serta power my Hue Lights in
Closet
Because my
My Hue motion sensor is actually a
I bet you do this
I needed to
Run it through the Apple TV
Or an iPad that sits in my house be
Because
When my phone is out otherwise it
This was my challenge
My iPhone is registered to me
The iPad that lives in my house is registered
Husband
So after
Some Googling and some sad noises on Twitter cuz I have my Google searches word
Coming up
I realized I had to
Prove
ICloud access
On my devices which is something I never wanted to do
Hate iTunes
Hate this
And then I needed to
Fight
My
IPad basic
To The Honky party
And I did that and then my husband had to approve an email saying yes I do want
Then
Ocean Center
For some reason I can't
Included as part of
My automation here
So I'm just I'm flummoxed
I don't I don't know why
Yeah this is a nice
CNET Smart Home
We have a
Product line
On an Android phone that we
Android apps
Access between each other we need to sort of
Step on each others toes a little bit it just
Almost
We had weird ones were notable instance where
The office
That's her at the home
And we were trying to get this to work
Describe your husband
Would not work at a drive out there and then figured out in person
But when she gets home from work that night all of the requests that we have been sending
Your iPad and not her iPhone
And so did so many little hiccups
Especially when you have multiple users to share control
It's still a big sticking point to the smart element
So my request is
Now that Apple has made
Onboarding devices super easy
If you live alone and you are going to be Soul commander of
Tennis is probably
For now with
Trying to share access
It did not I still things are still not working
Offer that to you guys
If you have suggestions about the
Elgato motion sensor and why it's not showing up on some of my stuff feel free to email me because
I don't understand
And here's a little update for you
So I promise you because this week
Last week
SmartThings and loutribe you talked about this partnership but now you can control your Lutron devices
From your SmartThings Hub and this is done is a cloud-to-cloud integration
And
I was super excited about it because
The wink
In my house
Does all of my Lutron
Actually pal my Lutron Bridge does all of my
Stop
It was on the way
And
I was super excited because then I could
My baby consolidate
Onhub 4p
I will never actually consolidate but
Tell other people bacon
Consolidate
How nice for them
So
I set this up
With the intention of trying it directly through SmartThings and then trying it through both Google home and
Amazon Echo because both of those devices
Scientist
The sad news is
When I
Hooked it up
I was able to authorize Lutron on my SmartThings account
But when it started searching
For devices
It gave me a glitch
And I uninstall things I reinstalled things
Felt like I tried everything to get this work
And after about an hour I have
So I said I sent a note into smart
Sporocyst
And I'm still I've heard back from them but
There's this lengthy process of like
Can I look at ROBLOX
What's the username on the account so I feel like
I've had every 24 hours I get a request for
Can I look at your information
So I don't actually
Resolution yet
We have a ton of stuff in the smart home that we
We test out of anything
I will tell everybody
Please send me your it works fine for me
Funny stories because
I feel like my house is such a
Cluster of devices
Integrations that a lot of things breaks
It would not break free
That is worth noting
Absolutely
Alright well
Write thank you so much for
Taking the place of Kevin
You did an awesome job
Kevin will be back neck
Courage ride please
Next time we need a guest host
We're going to bring you back on
Hey thanks a lot is great to be on
Alright guy stay tuned for our guest this week
Which is Ross
RV of the year
Which is an
Agricultural
Issues
With this in
Fabulous Australia
Sexy should totally stick around to hear that but first let's do a message from our sponsor
We are taking a break from this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
And I have Brian tollefson
About
Hey Brian
Hey Stacy
Alright so remind us
Finans designs builds and manages iot software
Fortune 500 firms
Smaller manufacturers and even startups
And over the last year
We've been developing and delivering iot training is well
That's really you need for a software developer
How did that come about
It is unique
But it's been a great
Set for Engineering Services
It came about
We kept hearing the same technical questions over and over and wanted a systematic way to answer them
We kept getting the same questions about how to add wireless connection
Your product
Or what features were important when picking an IT platform
That's interesting so how is the training struck
It's a modular setup presentation
Class of 2015 in 45 minutes
And we can combine them in a variety of ways
Sometimes it's just an hour
On the phone with somebody but often it's a half day workshop
Where we cover a variety of top
We always start with a session that introduces
And defines iot
I can go in a lot of different
Directions we have a number of technical presentation
Including iot topologies embedded Technologies Wireless protocols cloud
Computing in war
It's definitely design for engineers but we work really hard to make it
Accessible to business
Does people designers marketers
Really anyone
Involved with develop
It strategy
Tackling coyote
The first of firms that have
Some sort of traditional software back
Maybe they've done firmware before but they've never
Developed a wireless protocol
Or an over-the-air update
Are training addresses the
The needs for that group
The second group that we see increasingly is his group I like to call corporate makers
These are electrical engineers or mechanical engineers tasked with creating
An initial iot
Prototype
They frequently are using maker grade Hardware like Arduino or Raspberry Pi
These are awesome platforms we love our arrest
Replies but they're really not the type
Used to go to market
So we've designer training to help penicillin the knowledge gaps for that group
And help them figure out how to go to market
Do you need to be on site.
We can do it either way
A lot of organization
Have remote employees so we made sure that our training works well over Google hangouts or go to meetings
But it's a lot of fun in that
It works really well on
On-site as well
So where can people learn more about 7 dance in your iot
They can visit our website it's been debts. Com or send us an email at hello it's been
We'd be happy to preview
Training with anyone who's in
Any more. Iot
Awesome thanks Brian
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Ross
Harvey who is founder and managing director at
A company called
The yield
Hello rise
Morning Sky see this morning in Australia or anyway
I was going to say it is afternoon where I am but definitely morning where you are so today's podcast
As I said about
Agriculture
But more about the business side so bras
Why don't you tell me what you're doing
What we do is take the guesswork out of growing and Simon Jacques
Christmas Day
Tympole and knowledge hungry
And using Internet of Things technology
We can help Growers make better and faster decisions
This feels almost kind of akin to something like climate Corps
Which measured weather now that was for insurance purposes
Is it correct
Actually not
Went really genuinely and I are teepees nuts and we coming at it from completely with different front end of
So we focus on intensive irrigated
Where are the difference between microclimates not even down to a plant with
Can they
Absolutely critical
At margin per hectare of an irrigated praying
What fruits and trees and plants
40 times what it is in Russia
And really that's where a lot of the American egg parties which they are very inspiring
Every light, cut their teeth in that mold broadyke are dropping in the five young cool cross
Which starts at very different
Technology because it's not your guy that it's huge guy out
Looking at remote sensing and long-term public Doctrine and leveraging that wears wig
Actually
Putting Harbor on the ground so we do enjoy
Hardware platform analytics user interface and really focus on the more common with us
Okay so Rose can you give me a use case or an example of this
Really real one of that
I know the customers that we work with it produces bagged lettuce
And they wanted to strides because it produces
And so what we do is using our technology when measuring 9 environmental parameters at
Agriculture things from
Temperature humidity life witness fools of blight soil moisture temperature
Ranger Prime
And then what we do is we use these to help Growers make decisions on found decisions about when to plant when to irrigate
Play Swing to protect
Went to feed and when to harvest
So we can together with Houston
She's one of my customers
It can take 4 weeks to grow lettuce
In summer
From plant to harvest
Butthole bleaching winter
And effectively they know that there's a difference United from Farm to Farm Road Road
In terms of the time and distance that it takes from in terms of planting and harvesting
But they don't have to
So what I do is just have one Girls quiz
And so what this company does he suggest
Overproduce to make sure
That it can make it
Enter if we can just reduce their production by just one percentage point it's literally with
With hundreds of thousands
Is business
But more interesting as well is
We also use that same Dark Side to deal with things like she'll fly
So when you cut lettuce and put in a baguette stops decomposing for the minute.
And the thing that drives it is actually or continent
The plant
And so we make sure that as a by-product
The work we're doing reindeer guiding and spring
And then we can find that two got data together with processing data and
Retail data and we can actually work at the
Perfect time
To have a sex
And again we just take one day extension for that one day
Then it's really really worth millions to the business
So I think
So maybe that's a really important thing about what the hughleys doing differently we think about the business problem
And we think about the
50 Cent problem through the value chain
Then we design platform technology
That allows us to
Basically impact that
Across the value chain and I think this is
Really important
In terms of Sam getting uptight goodbye to you see it's very difficult I think to get
8 return on investment I'm just a single-use Kiest and I think that the value in artery is actually
In half. Circulates in how you analyze it and how you can Bond it
That's perfect because it's listening to what you just said
You hit on a bunch of issues
We talked about a lot
Twitches
You're dealing with different sources of data so not all of its your own some of it it sounds like
The retailers
Free public data sources
You're also trying to
Follow
Supply chain all the way down to the
Consumer even though
You're not necessarily the company that can
The consumer relationship
I'd love to break this down a bit and talk first about
How you guys
Jet
Your data and how that whole process of
The retailer
The suppliers data actually
Best thing to say and this is
Heights Taxi
Boosting
Is you
To have
Reliable
Accurate
And
I think just like you want to know that
Covenant to be food in the quality of it
You need to know.
Providence in the quality of Hadassah
Because you can't do analytics without it
So
In our case we do hardware and we partnered together ird partner is boss
Global business
Potatoes in sensing technology
And internet of things so we partnered with them as well as partner with Microsoft
So what this gifts
Is reliability and accuracy
And
If you don't get this
It's really trying to the analytics art as I said you were using artificial intelligence to predict
And in the case of art what's the solution which is a different product we have in Market
We get 95%
Accuracy 3 days app
Hauntings like Slinky temperature in Deptford
Critical to growing in
Supply chain
Really
The important thing to understand is you must control calling the daughter this is why I get so frustrated
Because
You just do not platform fit right in. If I don't know to call you back.
You don't know where they've just go garbage in garbage out
I think that's a critical issue
So then
Second thing is about
This is
That's so we do Hardware
Because we want to make sure that we have good reliable quality.
And then
Really the person
Understanding the business model and the problems along the supply chain is really important
Because what happens on Farm
Ricochet
Through the supply chain just like that example I gave of Life Witness
And she'll flirt
And so what main really matters is how you actually understand and stop
Pieces problem and the value chain and how you been collaborate with others
And I think that's really going to be incredibly important in an industry like Agriculture and food
No one company can boil the ocean no one company can solve every problem
What you really want to have to do is Glyburide
And that has a whole lot of
Passions about
Your architecture
The way you
Design technology
The white that you should upload
Business model
The white that you can recruit
And the sub skills that you looking for
It really has a very significant introduction on how you actually approach this and that's been very big learning
So let's break that down even further
Let's
Because there was a
I I wish
I covet that roll
So
Actually what's my bow Target
Want to
How do you architect or how do you plan
You're assuming this is both things like data normalization and also things
Like apis and
Terms of sending out
So happy planner Arc
Architecture and then
Look at
How you can establish a business relationship with
Needs to share data
Animal finally talk about the skills
API Centric architecture
Pretty cool and you not based on Open Standards as much as you can
The other thing that we try to do is be agnostic
Different types of technology and I know you and your listeners and explored issues about things like anti-war and
Galaxy fox in NBA RT
Really what we do is from Taiwan design
Ethnocentric
Picture design
The God of destruction
Madonna rockitecture to facilitate
I'm sharing
But we really
Very very careful that how we do that and I'll come back to that
Because the final thing that you really go to do so stinky patties
Contract senior legal Arrangements
As a business
We are very focused on giving our customers
Transparency
Control and incentive to share
Because fundamentally
Really what you want is much more like that.
Cooperative
The market rather than terminal
And the back to work
Reply to Shannon episode
But they also
S2
Be confident that their daughter is not going to be used against
And so it is much around
Cultural policy and privacy and security issues
Messages about the technology
Now let's talk about the skills that you look for then in the people you hire
The people that you were
What we do is
We are very strong value spice business and this is really important to us when we founded the
Company
We had a very very clear purpose and that was
How are we going to see the world without
Wrecking the planet
Not a time where
You've got unprecedented
Constraints
Climate change
Loss of arable land at the same time we have
Have to purchase 70% more food by 2050 just to feed everyone and so having a very strong purpose and value
Attracts a certain sort of paperwork to the business which is Christ
Thai Spice and the other thing that we really really look for is collaborative skills
And not being
Fabulous technologist in doing really really cool things with.
That's a given we do that
Buckets
But we also need to have people who can actually work with each other and communicate because
And also the pieces matter what we're trying to do
It's just
Make it simple tightly complexity why
And that means we do everything
And and we
Deliver a product.
I know it's product as a subscription service
That means you've got to have
Making Janine's electrical engineering
Systems engineer software Alabama what's the main exports yuan
Design is
Oldest working together
To make the experience into a
Beautiful thing
Totally imagine
I'm trying to think about what it means to be a business that is actually
Delivering insights
As opposed to
Hardware solution or even software
End the ability to figure that out is
It's going to be what separates
Successful iot come
Companies that use iot
From
Unsuccessful
So what
I seriously can't get that he's really the issue he it because
Coyotes Dream by technologist anyhow I love technology
Because my thing I adore it's not really
United
Bro has a very round and round
And you know they running a
Complex system
Rimini things interesting all the time
And seriously
Target customers the knowledge hungry
I just wanted to check in to deliver kind of value proposition from Taiwan
And you just got to focus on this
And you know in some ways that
When we
We started the business we called the business the yield for racing
Become effective that in agriculture, so you don't have a business
I really thought long and hard that will how do we make so that's really embedded in our culture in the way that we go about so
Sleeping problems
Tonight
Good name
How do you think about
Charging
Fair
Insights because that's
There's a lot
As you said a complicated things going into it there's relationships with
With other companies
So
How do you break that down
And figure out
A price and one that's sustainable
For your business
Essentially what we do is we create
Different digital solutions from the same knowledge infrastructure and we monetizing different light so let me give you a really concrete exam
Optimus Prime
Was it annoys registry
So
When it rains going to get runoff from the soil
Because of oysters at filter animals like she may like contaminants that make it dangerous
And so the food safety regulator says
Shut down when we get
With the risk of runoff
The way that they were doing that in the
Past what using rainfall which could be coming from
Thomas White
Is putting real-time sensing into the water that that way strengths
And
Been using
Parental Guidance down we got 30% reduction in unnecessary closures just do that one
Something
And then using artificial intelligence
Predicting it
94% accuracy 3 days Upon A predictions of salinity
Then what that means he's Growers can get product out of the water
Felicia
So effectively what we doing is giving them back
20 days
30 days a year harvesting
Which is a big deal
What's that noise infrastructure reduce in Enterprise
Set of tools for Growers
Ducks things like
Fly fishing Chelan
Actually Megan Harvest it does food safety and tracking end
Consignment reports that happening
The conditions of my necropolis
Harveston to orders and purposes only certain things
Entirely different digital product
The regulator
And we have two different safety Regulators using the product in Australia
And so we take that same data but now what we've done is doing
A view that allows
Opposite the rules
Malachi Croatia differently series 2
Mama said conditions to use
And then
It is too bad I don't give it to researches
Different nice guy so together they want
Exit out of the cracked egg right through that
Will give it to you free of charge
But we really loud music
Tripping into a product
Imma things like disease management and animal husbandry so you can have better impact and we can get
Something's out of the labyrinth
Antipasto
So that's sort of the wire that we approached it
And then you know I can
We already having discussions look to pick Lock and Dam the value China vat have that.
And I mean I ate to lose weight working it out as we go how we might as well so that the bottom line is if you can guess
Enough of the Thai prepositions
Not everything on top of that is obviously
In the mix here is
Your algorithms
Your data
Mixed with other people's data
Other people's algorithm
And it sounds like there's some
Quid pro quo happening with some of the
These maybe it's exchange and date
Is there a monetary absolutely absolutely
Absolutely looking at the bottom at the end of the day you've got to come up with a Y that everyone feels good about it
And that's really unique businesses that that when you boil it down you go to delivering value to different people working together
And so what that means he's pulling back insane what's your eject
What's Market
What are you good at where we go. And if we work together can we buy Queen and how do we share the risk and reward
It's just a different way of thinking
And so what's been really interesting for us as a small fast growing business is
Wishing someone
The world's Giants in
Technology and food how you make that relationship work
Text example
Huge company
Imagine it's kind of like two little
Coldwell South Korea
Living in a different spice how do you make that work
How do you serve
Mitchell is Italian prepositions a box and now there's a lot of
That's my stupid wife thinking about how to approach the business model
To make that work you don't have signal things with Microsoft
Ibogaine understanding incentives and drivers of people with lopsided what brake light City KPMG
I think that
Example with
Food safety regulations retailers it's really a bat
How do you
How you put together Arrangement that Sky we're going to pay the bill
The Christ value
And then I lied on that is always late than they Tonight Show that I customers
Current control what happens if the data and it's not used against them and they shine outside
So do you have any advice for a companies that are trying to
To work with
Bigger company
Mediate
The types of companies you should look
Characteristics
Cuz I think this is a really tough
Sting for a small
Yeah it is it's really hot
And to get it right
And
I think
My advice would be
Obviously you want to look for strategic partners
Partners that
Provide something you don't have any no I think it's a very good agricultural sign that good fences make good neighbors
Showing people who got complimentary soda
Technology in capability
So that would be one the second is really
Typed out you seriously
Because when you're inviting
Business broker
And so you want to work
People with his trust and trust is built on similar values
Because it's nothing you can you know you have to pull back on that when you never got him down now it
I think that's really important
Do something
Workout
Business model how it might work
And then sit back and say okay had a waiver take this out of Scouts
All right
Thank you so much for coming on the show this week
This was awesome
Greatly enjoyed
Picasso I feel very privileged to be yet
Gastonia program sites
I can't wait to check back with
Put you in a little while.
See how things are
Great thanks
Well that's it for this week's podcast thank you for listening and as always if you'd like more iot news
Please sign up for my newsletter you can buy it at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Thanks
See you next week