Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Add your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have anime
Anything show for you we've got the return of Sony aibo
San Diego Smart City plan
Siri
Maybe a little bit disappointing soon got a funding for a
Iot
Pause company
Updates
And we got some data from Mozilla about how consumers
Perceived
Plus we're going to be reviewing the echo
Plus
And all of Amazon's new interfaces
We also have a comment from one of our listeners on the
Iot
Podcast
Which is now by the way sponsored by Schlage
Message from
Sap
Andar
Guess this week
Is Joanna Soh
Who was the CEO of the Chamberlain group
And yes
We're talkin about the
So all this and more awaits you but first
A message from our sponsor
The Internet of Things podcast is brought to you by ADT Home isn't a place it's a Feeling
The feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most ATT let you take that feeling with you wherever you
You go whether you're at your house your business or online ATT helps keep you safe and secure security
Home automation alarms and surveillance so you can feel at home wherever you are there more
Pat adt.com
Okay Kevin
Big Show Big Show Big Show
With my favorite
The Retard Estonia
Aibo
Robot.
And if you were not around in
Thoughts so 2005
Mm
Sony introduced
Cute little robot dog called aibo
It was crazy expensive I did not own one
And then in 2006
They
They put it out yes they pulled the plug on
Add people were sad because
Cuz there were lots of
Who loves their eyebrows and back
They were actually people who held funerals for the
Big things
So I was really excited
But then I
So is planning to be less excited with the new aibo
Wow
I think it's cool that they brought it back
I mean I'm not saying everybody needs a robotic dog and Stacy you have a dog I have a dog
Sometimes you can hear them on the show in the background
Put some people don't want to deal with
An actual dog and I get that
But you want to companion so that's what I though is before I get to the
It's actually an interesting product itself I mean
This is everybody dog that can move around 22 axis it's got OLED panels
Expertise issues expressions
Sony makes a lot of computer vision products so all those Imaging sensors and
Products like the iPhone
Sony makes
It's really cool to see Sony saying hey you know what computer vision is now a real thing happening in the world
And we got technology for this let's put it in this
Aptoide and see what happens
So it has
Yeah I mean it is impressive from a
Technical standpoint
Right
Is it though cuz here's where we get to
It reminds me of
Cosmo which is $150 connected toy for kids that is just a door
And it has
Image recognition
It rolls around
Small Earth
Send the dog and it doesn't
Move is
It doesn't have the
22 access web movie
It cost 150 and I
Yeah
This is not a toy
But even if it was what's a $700 a thousand dollars less
I still would not be interested this is why
On top of the purchase price there is a monthly subscription
That is going to cost you $26 a month
You have to have that for like 3 years
And that's giving the dog Wi-Fi and LTE connectivity
Cloud backup cuz you know
Because you want to
Remember where he got his bone you could
There's an app that goes along with it I mean
A subscription for a dog I don't know
Should I buy food for my dog
Yes yes
Guess what your dog doesn't have life he can't be used as wifi hotspot
I don't know I mean this is just that it's just a stretch
To me a lot of money
It is a lot of my
And I will purchase
The original was too early for its
And I think this is now the right time for something like this
And
I actually think there will be an audience for it even with the $26 a month subscription fee
Although
Kind of like does my robotic
Nini Deli
I mean I feel like we're going to start seeing people ask
These questions because right now
Cellular costs are still very high
Compared to you
Wi-Fi which is basic
And so
I think
Maybe they could have chop that subscription fee
And the bill of materials to make
A dog
A bit
Okay I was just making Wi-Fi
If you wanted to
Take your dog to
You have Wi-Fi at the Starbucks but getting to and from the Starbucks you have to
Healthy I guess but it's kind of interesting I agree that yes there is an audience for this I remember reading about older folks
Lived alone fat companion
And I'm not going to judge on that that if that helps those people then so be it I think that's great
But this is not
Mass Market
Product in my opinion now
You know nothing
Well let's talk about San Diego
Because I've been there twice this year and I love it it's a lovely place
And it is getting smarter
This is not
Exactly new we talked about San Diego in the past
Because it's had a pilot Smart City
Graham now that pilot is moving into production
And they're working with cheese current to manage the LED Street lamps in the city
They also are
They put in 3200 sensors and they're going to stick
3000 more sensors
In the city which is
Quite a lot of sensors
Yeah I mean this is a whole city wide after this is not just like sections of the city there
Spending 30 million dollars to deploy this
And
I think it's good I am a little worried because they are working with ge's current they're throwing everything into products
Cheese products
So I'm kind of like what happens to that data I do feel like
A lot of Articles focusing on the Smart City don't think about who has access to that data how it's managed in
Even inside a city one of the challenges that
Cities have to deal with in it's worth it for the citizens to know is
How
The data from different sensors
Is shared across
So
Do police have access to you no surveillance cameras or do they have there
And those kind of things become really important
When you think about
Qatar privacy app
Locations and
Economic
Considerations
Right right some of the services that AR
Rolling out actually touch upon that in fact is they're looking at installing shotspotter which is affecting
Location of gunshots in real time and at first I thought I was a good idea about
Before the show station I was talking about and she didn't mention to me that the last cities that use shotspotter
Are actually getting rid of it and I did not realize that never definitely privacy implications there of sensors that are
Listening for gunshots that
Can also record conversations and so on so forth so that's
Definitely something that needs to be considered
Yes and
It's probably not a lot of cities taking it out but several cities are taking it out the
Because they felt like they didn't San Antonio is one
They're talking about it Oakland is another concern to that you know it's a little redundant people will report gunshots
Pretty much
When they hear the
Sometimes there's false positives and that was a problem
932 privacy concern
Shotspotter microphones keep recording
After
Detect shots
So please have use that in
In court to try to invite
People for crimes now
If those people committed the crime
Probably okay but if not they just have to be at the wrong place at the wrong time
Recipe you know
So there are definitely some
Liberties
Things to think about here
I hope the cities are
And speaking
Of a lack of privacy
Let's talk about Apple
Because it is
Cell focus on user privacy and I think that's probably going to be a problem for it going forward into the smartphone
Basically
There's bad news for homepod
Lovers and lovers
I guess you can't love it yet it doesn't
It's not out by the homepod speaker when it comes out
There's
Kevin yeah I mean it's for the homepod comes out next month for $349 and
Apple hasn't really said much about it so we're all kind of guessing what will it be able to do with behave like
OK Google Home Products on Amazon Echo products
Not out of the box
Is what I can tell you right now and that's because the SDK for it Apple has just provided to Developers
Say hey here you can start making apps for the homepod
But
Only in a few categories such as messaging list
Endnote
You'll be able to use
Homepod to control Apple music by voice but I don't see any third-party Music Services coming anytime soon
Because
There's no way to do that Apple hasn't provided a way to do that so it seems like it's going to be a very limited
Experience and the shame of it is
And my opinion
Siri is already a limited experience because
It's not as smart at getting information in my opinion is some of the other assistants out there and of course it is within Apple's wall
Olive Garden which there's pros and cons to that I
No issue there but
It's just an observation you know he's going to work with homekit
But what else
You know I ain't just
I think this is going to be a very
Limited product when it first comes out
Well in that was very much like homekit
And homekit is much better now
But even today
Developers are still Lake
Where's my homekit support
They've been promising homekit products and haven't actually released them because of challenges working within the
Ecosystem
And so
I was really excited about homepod and I thought this would actually help push
Homekit to the mainstream
This does not make me feel like
That's going to happen
And it's frustrating as a reviewer someone who talks about the
The stuff because so many consumers are looking forward to homekit I get so many questions about things were
Working with homekit and people have been waiting for
Literally years and
Feels like
Apple has promised them
Something that works in
So far
It's pretty minimal
Everyone else feels Miles Ahead
Will it does work
It's just Luke
You don't have to breath of options
That you had with other platforms
PreSonus support standpoint
And you had said that a lot of these
Product makers
That deal with challenges not only challenges but changes because Apple went from a hardware base than occasionally
Security bit to software-based in I mean that stuff to these companies can't change in a diamond
Producing Hardware
So that has caused delays
Thanks and maybe some people just like you know what
Like you said others feel Miles Ahead such as Google's and Amazon's ecosystem
Maybe people just throwing their hands up and saying we'll get down get when we get to it
Yeah and I would say from a developer side that makes a lot of sense from
Consumers
I don't want to say look Amazon's really good it's easy to work with
Do that or Google if you're already on a bunch of Google services Google home has
Over 6
Christie Partners right now in the smart home section it is definitely a
Do you want to keep waiting
Good waiting and I'm in Apple's ecosystem
I would say it's not
So I'm sad
Well I think a lot of people will purchase this
Even with these potential
Limitations just because of the bus sound
Quality is my gas and they will feel it
And Apple's technology they are getting a better sound system than what's available
That's just what people may think and that's fine
And it will work with her
It has Siri support
For built-in but if you want to control Spotify for example by voice that's not happening you have to do it through if it's
Play Spotify through AirPlay 2 and control by voice on your phone not through the
Speaker itself so it just seems
Talk Dirty to Me
Awkward
Yeah
Okay here's some fun news bits before we get to
Arvig review of the Echo Plus and Amazon smart home
Which is
Coyote
Form as a service
For companies that are
Usually selling products
Consumer so think big name brands
Are selling connected products to Consumers
Girl who stood on
Ala and they just raised $60 in a series D round
Stay
The capital but they're doing it
Because they are going
And they are creating a joint venture in China with sunset
Communication
Telco
Telecommunications
In China
And I think this is gray tail has been around since before the iot was
Even a thing
Really they've been around
Which
Holy mackerel that's a really long time ago
What house what else was happening
Can I have 2 years that's a long time
What's before Nest which was when everyone was like oh my God
And I've got a crack update for everyone
We talked about this two weeks ago crap is a
Vulnerability in the Wi-Fi protocol itself with client devices and your router's so all of your
Phones
Smart ovens smart whatever's
Are all affected
Wi-Fi and most companies have done a really good job
Either they are not
Vulnerable to the attack
That's because of the way they structured
Their products
Which is Yay good June nest and feel like wink
Is in that category and then others have been updating
Like mad
Crazy Mad personally my Nvidia Shield got an update for that address this as well as added other features
I bought an essential phone last week and got an update through them
From Google with that address McCracken chorizo
I was surprised how quickly on some of my devices
That actually showed up
Yes
What didn't get update
Is actually pretty stunning to me so
Two big names in the iot space and in their outer space
I reached out to Belkin
The day of and they were like yeah we're working on it
What's out there
So now two weeks later I felt like
Okay let's just check in
They still haven't released a patch for their devices and then the other is tp-link which is another big router maker but
Also makes the casa and other connected devices
They have light bulbs
Kasa smart home app
And they have not done an update either although they do
Did say hey yes
Yes we're aware of it
So
I don't know what to say
I look at this and this is why
Hive historically been
I don't know about 2 p.m.
Alex products
Worries me
I am also a little worried about the security on wemos products just because of the
The way that's built
It's a known fact that you can walk into someone's house if you're running
A WeMo
App if you walk onto their Wi-Fi network
You can actually control their WeMo devices if you have access to their
Tp-link sort of surprises because Google partnered with them for the original Google onhub router they were two models of that
Tp-link made one of them
I'm sorry it's not that they're not
They just haven't
We have
People working
And
Mozilla
Because they're still around
Music
Ouch
I love Mozilla because
What they're doing
Work on the open
Privacy rights I shouldn't
I heard they're not as prominent as they once were for various reasons I agree I agree
I need credit is iot effort that felt like
If you just like
So
But they did survey
The people
And
Discovered how people felt about
Privacy and smart devices and Kevin
What jumped out at you for
This will have you obviously a lot of people are concerned about privacy and this is global by the way this is not just
190000 people in one
Region of the world is global privacy and that kind of filled to some degree that ship has
Assailed
But I totally understand that people still really don't understand
Peyote and all the difference
Things that make it work
They said fewer than 30% of respondents said they can't explain IRT or botnets
Blockchain
RFID for example
And fewer than 40% could explain what a DDOS attack was so
Yeah people still have a lot of
Learning to do and I blame kind of the industry and
The people like us to degree who explain it I mean we need to
Get the message out more to get people to understand what they're buying into if they're going to look towards this future or so
I agreed
The thing is it actually sucked me what is Brazil
So resilient
They have both in Brazil in India they have the highest rate of connected Appliance ownership at 15%
7% for the rest of the
And Brazilian respondents were the most excited about how quote-unquote easy as Martin
4% selected
The top benefit
The world being more
So the Brazilians are like
Super Pump
People in the US France the UK
Canada there were less
I don't know I just like
Go Brasil
Yeah I wonder and I don't have like Molly I should you have a survey data out there so I'll go check it out shorts I wonder how the
People in Brazil feel about the privacy and security as a result
Are they
Kind of like saying I don't care just get me connected baby I want to live this life
That would be very interesting to see so I'm going to go back into the rug surveyed and check that out
Yeah cuz
I want to go to Brazil now
Adidas fun
Just because why not
Sure is something I enabled and I thought was really cool you guys
May already know about it be
Because it was report
Earlier this month but
The Google home if you're part of the preview
And you can go and become part of the
The pretty version of the software
You get something called
Google home
Night mode
And if you know what this is
You are ahead of me
How is awesome
Basically what it does is
When it's night
Nighttime
You can set particular hours for the Google home to lower volume
Intimately
Which
Yes because
Like my daughter runs around in this is less a Google home thing but she does turn up the volume
Turn music loud
So you know sometimes
Play tonight
Turn off the light
And holy cow
Okay I have a similar situation the girls go to bed a lot earlier than I do so I'll send
In my office I watch TV and we talk to the Google home either to turn the TV off shut the lights dim the lights whatever
And it is so loud because I was listening music loud during the day time so the LED is really
I'm the only one in the room but boy oh boy every time I go to bed pretty much wake everybody up the Google home so I'm going to get in that bed approach
Why didn't
But I want this
I don't know why you didn't either
Anime
Go get that
Prettiest
Okay
Speaking of matinee
That was like
Gluteus
I got the
I got it yesterday
And started play
It's there two parts to the
This one is the Echo Plus is Hardware itself
And then to the stuff that Amazon has now recently done to make it smart home interface
Is it better or just different
We're going to go with
Different right now but go ahead
So.
Hardware for the Echo Plus
Is
Excellent
Substantial piece
Equipment
Sounds good it sounds a little bit better than the echo it's probably not as good as the Sonos one
And it
Has a zigbee radio in
So initially I set it up
In my own home but since I have a hub for most of my zigbee bulbs
Because they're
Philips Hue I was like
I don't know what is happening
I took it off
I reset it up on my guest Network
With the pulpit actually came with it which was a
Philips Hue bulb
Is a white bulb
And I set that up and let me tell you
Super easy
So the Echo Plus is not something you need
Unless you don't have any
Other hubs that
Zigbee in
So and
If I could just add I think that is why they did not include a Z-Wave radio because this is targeted for people who do not already have Smart Home
UPS
That's my takeaway
You probably don't need this most of people listen to the show
Fridge is fine
If you want to give you know your parents
Or someone
A lovely gift
Smart Home
This actually might be a good price
So I tested it with a Philips Hue bulb
I also had an osram bulb and it worked
And
I don't know what else to tell you about this other than
Yeah don't by your heart
Yeah I reckon so somebody that way just get the list
Expensive that goes if that's what you want to do because you also said they changed the software
And I have seen some of this
Last week in factories are newsletter
Bird was a support page
That showed how you could add Echo devices to your smart home groups
And by doing so instead of having to say the name of the lights in the room with the echo you can then just say
Lights on or lights off and based on
Proximity
But the group setting essentially
The actor would know which like you're talkin about without naming them and it would take that action which is a beautiful thing
I should point out it only works with Echo devices so if you have a smart home speaker that has the voice
Services
Then it will not work
And it only works with
Bulbs as we found out where the WeMo switch in my group and Stacy I think you two have a Wiimote and something else
I have a WeMo Insight switch I have a Lutron fan
And I have a
A WeMo Insight and WeMo dimmer
Right so those wemos make gumballs
Smart
And this setting will not work with those with only work with smart bulbs
But it is a little sad
Because I have a hodgepodge of
Different reasons
Places like so I have my WeMo Insight switch to test like how much things
How much electricity
But it's also nice because I can set sunrise sunset
As my schedules on the
Insight switch and I like
As a automatic
So I don't think I can do Sunrise scheduling yet for the Amazon extra
You can't do schedule
Because it's not
Not really a homo
Automation platform
So we're probably seeing is Amazon moving into a home automation
Platform slowly and surely and I will see you interface
On the app so if I go in
Any devices I see all of my
50 Cent my devices
Arrow in two columns it looks very much like a SmartThings does with its devices even
Actually wink doesn't
Into
But SmartThings has
And I actually like
So but
Hard to say I mean for people who again our first time buyers of a hub and they buy this they won't have
Have anything to compare it to
So
You and I miss you it's a little more complicated than it used to be but they'll never know
Yes
You can also add scene so remember how we were talking about with the software developers were going to do with
In a Philips Hue if you don't have the Hub do you need the app with is
The answer is you do need the skill so you will need to log in on the app
If you want to
Control
Lots of stuff
I should have said that earlier and
I couldn't get any of the scenes that it pulled in for
From Phillips to work
So
I'm still trying to figure out what I did wrong there
Since I
I've had it for like 12 hours and some of those hours were Halloween and sleeping
I don't have the new help but my wink shortcuts
Showing up in scenes and are still working
Cuts of always showed up
Shortcuts have always
As they were in the device
Craigslist so now they
I now have a
A lot more
So I have things
Arctic Aurora
You know what that is
Color Loop
I have also
They don't really have them
Cuz they don't
Yeah I wonder if they would with the Hue bridge in use
Could it sounds like that's where they coming from
No
This was me testing it
Unknot the
Plus
This was me testing it on the other echos
Not the Plus
Got you
Oh it's okay
I'm going to buy a shed
In the shed
Look for it because soon I'm going to be rationalizing Miami
Echoes because I have way too many
Maybe we'll
Give away the Plus for someone who needs a smart
Happy holidays to our users
Stay tuned for that neck
Comments and questions
Bruno Mars
This is from The Internet of Things podcast
Listener Hut
Which now has a new sponsor
Schlage actually it has a sponsor
That's exciting
So thank you
The Internet of Things podcast
Do you now by Schlage
Maker of electronic lock
Swishly you can have brand new electronic locks
Installed in minutes
It was just a screwdriver or your own two hands
They're easy to setup and use
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
And now
Comment about the Amazon
Key
A very smart one
Might I add
From Brian
Ecstasy
This is Brian Denver Amazon
Amazon delivery service
I believe it Amazon Cloud cam
Actually there
Check Amazon fraud
Talk to him is actually required feature of Amazon in terms of service state that must be facing the door you
Use for delivery
Arizona ski happiness
Amazon music player photos for videos
Stinky cream to demonstrate
August
Say snitcher someone can't blame the Amazon delivery person
For pre-existing
Which probably explains why Amazon is getting
Sojourner
In the prices Key bundle
Camera
Free insulation
Anyway that's my two bits
Already
That is a super astute observation Brian obviously the Amazon Cloud Cam and the key tool
Livery service
Sandlock
Helps consumers because you know if you're ordering from Amazon Prime and
It's getting delivered in your house where you want it
Delivery people are not running a muck in your house
You know watching TV while you're gone and whatnot
But yes
Shame on me for not looking at like
The terms of service and all that kind of requires that cloud cam because this does protect Amazon as well you know you not to be able to say some
It was not delivered
LSA the delivery person
Threw it on the front porch
Now it's damaged
Send me another one ready that soup
It really doesn't make sense
Photos the consumer and for Amazon to require that cloud cam for the key delivery service
Agreed
Let me have such smart
Smart
Listeners
And before we go I should offer you guys Hotline in case you want to call ask us a question or
Make a comment
Numbers 512
6 to 3
7 4
Too far
You can also find it
And now
We're going to take a momentary break
For a message
Sponsor
Stay tuned for Joanna
Sahovic was the CEO of Chamberlain group
We discuss
These subscription plans
What's behind it what
You can expect next from Chamberlain and some insights about
How to build a connected business
And what that's going to mean for any other consumer products companies out there
Hey everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from our sponsor sponsor is
Sap and I have Gil Perez who is SVP
Iot and digital supply chain
We are talking about sap Leonardo live which is a big event that you are having November 2nd through 3rd in
Chicago
Can you tell me what this is
Leonardo live
Is fep
Brand name for r
I'm going to get a vacation
And this is a global event which we're going to have
People coming from all over the world to see how sap
All these come together to really create that
System of innovation with its going to be blocked
Machine learning
Corthaiyou tea and other things coming together with sap customers
SCP partners
And of course
SCP themself showcasing
Aldi's
Amazing Grace
Okay so I could see some real world things which
She's really excited
What are you most excited about
Trust me I'm working on two really interesting area one of them is connected vehicles and in that space
We're really seeing the
Continue
Conductivity of all the cars in the Telco
Where they are offering what we called the OBD Uncle so making any existing cars
On the road today connected with an OBD dongcopter going to have a great
Company called
Emoji of presenting how's that working with SCP and really offering to days
Which is the T-Mobile offering which is powered by sap connected vehicle
So that's going to be a really exciting question another
Area
Is if course blockchain
What team is another amazing
A new technology that is evolving quite quickly everybody knows them in the contacts
But in the end of ties it's going to be used in other ways
Specifically in the condo
Pics of track and Trace
And accountability and ensuring that drugs
Which are being distributed are affected
We've been working with
Mark
Island example and Amerisource
And we're showcasing
Windows
Technologies Innovations really with sap technology being used in the today out there in the sea
Children being piloted
There's going to be a lot of Entry
Christine
With multiple
Customers
That sounds great so there are a lot of shows right now focused on iot
What makes Leonardo live
Leonardo like it
Forward customers
Actually have hands on
Stansted Aldi
Technology so I really urge
Anybody who is interested in these kind of
Aldi's phone blocking machine learning
IRT
To come and visit us
Leonardo live because you're going to be able to interact with those
In real time
Alright this is coming up on November 2nd through 3rd in
Chicago
So where can we find out more about Leonardo life
You can find all the information on www
Att.com Leonardo light na
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Joanna stahovich was the CEO of the Chamberlain
Hi Joanna thanks for coming on the show
ITT thank you for inviting me I am really excited because
You guys have been doing
It product or products rather for a while
And I'm
Eager to learn what you guys have
Is it also talked to you about a recent decision that is
Controversial
Among some of the
Let's just kick it up with controversy
You guys in the MyQ garage door
Which I own an actual
That awesome
You guys recently decided to start charging
Your users
Reviews of
I'm curious why
Fac
We have had them IQ application which works with are Chamberlain and LiftMaster garage door openers for more than
5 years
Andaz
As a durable goods manufacturer
We initially looked at it
How does this increase our bill of
What's the cost of the Wi-Fi chip
And the related
Components and what sort of a price increase
Do we need to put on her
In order to recover our car
Over the last five years
We have realized
That
Are MyQ app
Among its user base
Is it
Extremely walrus
If you take a look
Look at the rating
Other some of the highest out there
It comes with a huge response
Stability
People expect 99.9% uptime
Otherwise they're locked in or locked out of their garage
They expect for there to be a level of security
Because for almost 80% of us homeowners this is the front door
Because their garage is attached
To their home so they don't want it
To be able to be hacked or penetrated and anyway that doesn't get lease
Equal if not exceed
Regular garage door open
And then to see they like to have ongoing
Features and functionality
Such as integration with partners
Or new features that continue to be dreamed up once you have the capability of a connected
Garage door opener
And so we found that really there were to invest
Since one was making the product connectable to the internet and
In the first place and the second one was the ongoing investment
Of creating
Uptime
From creating security
Continuing to upgrade it was features and functionalities that are users would like to see overtime
And when did you realize
This product that you were pushing out into the market
It was eventually
Was on its way to be
More of a service
At least in terms
When I arrived about 20 months ago
I came with background in the connected home
Connected building
Connected fact
And so I came with
The benefit of understanding
What do
Ongoing value
Created by the
Company looks like
As well as the ongoing cough
Responsibilities as a supplier
Call that service or that
Good and and what I found was
Gem
We had created something
That had
Agreed amount of reception
But not a lot of understanding or thinking
How we were going to
Continue to evolve
The value of this product
And pay for it
So it's probably with 20
Months ago when I joined the company
That we started having conversation
All of these Partnerships that were requested by customers
Partners all of these things that we could do to the app
But we really couldn't afford because those things work
Competing with the core business
Witches products
That brought Revenue
The profit and we began to look at it a different way
And so
From your standpoint I thought this was interesting as this idea that
It's kind of cannibalizing your existing business
Put development cost towards the ongoing Security in the ongoing maintenance at this program
Because normally those resources are
Reviews for selling
The physical Hardware
Product
So have you guys shifted the way
Ization
The biggest
Conflict that we found was in
Engineering resources
Software developer
And we did
Change our entire organization
Structure
To better align
With where we saw our grow coffee
Opportunities in the future so one area that we ended up creating was a line of business
It's called the emerging businesses
Lob line of business
Just that would allow us to focus on
On some of these new and disruptive
Things
That we wanted to
Store
And that we wanted to test and that we wanted to incubate and bring it
Critical mass before we put it in the more mature business
And they have their own engineering resource
They don't have to cook
Compete against
The more mature businesses that can guarantee growth and profit right at the outset
Still allows for some risk-taking some
Experiment
The other thing that we did and
We separated are
Businesses more by end-user
Standby Brandon Channel
So we now have a residential line of business we have a
Commercial line of business
We have a premier access line of business International line of business and distribution and Automotive as well as the emerge
Line-of-business
Talk to you about before and that does allow
Focus
The end-user application
Right now
Maybe
Hardware durable good base but may just as well be
Software systems and services
Like we're discussing
So let's get to this if service because there's been a couple things that
User soap
The first was a few years ago
When
Chamberlain promised homekit compatibility with
The MyQ system
In the thought was they weren't going to charge
Turns out that
Homekit requires an extra search chips
You have to make new physical Hardware
Go for it and
Then Chamberlain charged for
Abridge
This rubbed a lot of people
And now
Those are other users like them are really looking at the charging
Integration
Promise that she
Other services
So I'm curious
How that happened
So I'll refer back to the earlier discussion where when we started this journey
Nobody else has really done much as a
Before and we were looking at it as to how much can this
Chip Coffey
And how much does it cost to just enable if
Service in the fur
And we thought that we could recoup our cost
In the initial sale price
The product that we've been on this journey for almost 6 years now
We've discovered again
Send that to deliver on the uptime Promises
Security promises
The partnership integration promises the extra value added services that
Consumers are asking
There's an ongoing
To the service
Start as week
Continue to add
Features functionality
Partnerships
Integration
Then if we feel that there are customer segments that are willing to pay for it
And other customer segments
For whom it's
Completely irrelevant
Then we put that into the premium tier
Where we charge
$1 a month or $10
You'll see more and more going into the premium tier and you'll see more and more going into the base pre-service but ultimately
This is something that
We wouldn't be able to
Afford to continue
Investing in the business if we made everything free
And how did you guys come about with that price
We have several different we came out at
Several different directions
Analyze
First off
We wanted to understand
You know what are are caught
We don't price based on cost
But
You do have to have an awareness
Of what sort of cost are incurring
Because if the value does not exceed the cost
Then maybe it's not so
And then we did
Some very detailed analysis
Customer
Around what
Value are we delivering and what is the willingness to pay for that.
And we came back with a variety of different options that
Equilibrium approximately a dollar a month or we got $10 a year might and sent people to sign up for
A year at a time
What percent of your user base do you think
Will sign up for something
Well we've had a large percentage of our user base sign up for the F10
The homekit integration particularly during the 30-day.
Where there's a free trial
And we're continuing to monitor
The participation rate as the free trial.
Spire
NetSpend
In some cases
Triple digit growth day by day by day
Small numbers admittedly
But then the other thing is that
As I mentioned we do intend to keep adding
Features functionality services in apple
Locations to that premium tier
And so if people value
And enjoy if
And or homekit integration
They find that they get other features and functionality that
Continue to validate that invest
Or it brings in new segments and new users who
Initially weren't willing to pay for the action homekit integration but they would
For future applications that we bring to Market
So what are some of those future applications
Well I think my product manager
Strangle me
If I were to
Pronounce
But one thing that I can tell you about that would be available but
Time we are this podcast
As many people don't realize that we have an automotive component
HR business
That we license our technology
For the Homelink application
Is the ability to use an integrated button in your car to open and close your garage door rather than
A removable trans
At the CMAs show
Which is one of our industry shows
We announce our partnership with alpine
People who own select Alpine navigation or entertainment
Would then be able to use MyQ
On Alpine
Connect to open the garage door as they're approaching rather than have
Physical
Transmitter like
So it can further
Allow for integration they can activate their home mode
That would turn on lights for their house is lit
Put their nest learning thermostat so that the house is it a comfortable temperature all from
In the car and so that's
An example of
More and more applications
Become available once we can have
HD devices connected to the internet
And that we can create more value for our user
This idea of charging for subscription
I believe that we're going to have
Pay for subscriptions for a lot of Arc
It's just part of the business model that
You just talked about
Baidu
About kind of death by a thousand subscription
So I can see
Chamberlain
Ring 30 bucks a year
IOS security thing
X number of dollars
Plus maybe some share cloud storage etc etc
So when I start looking at that
I wonder how you
Your subscription
As part of an entire
Fire systems
A subscription that is going
So I agree there is a little bit of a
Consumer paradigm
That stuff is free
But people are beginning to realize that
Stuff isn't really free
When you upgrade to the latest IOS you
You find out that some of your free apps
Haven't been updated
And may never be up
Jaded and it's hard to complain about that cuz
They were free in the first place
People are beginning to learn that if you want a service without advertisements or commercials or things like that
But you have to pay for it
Some people are also beginning to learn the notion of a freemium model you get the base
Version for free maybe LinkedIn
Evernote or something like that
And then if you want the premium version
Name something that you may value
And you have to pay it
Subscription model
And so customers are beginning to realize
That if you want
Premium
Service B. Noka
Commercials are extra
Features are
Or somebody
Updating it making sure that it's upgraded and secure overtime
You're going to have to pay some dollars
That being said
Competition for recurring Revenue dollars
Fierce
Everybody wants a piece
Piece of the consumer's wallet
And the consumer only has so many dollars
That they're willing to pay
For a monthly fee
Description your home alarm service is competing against your cable
And people have to do
Decide what's more important
And so really it's we're relying on our ability to create value that the end users
Want
And are willing to pay for
And ultimately there are some that will survive and there are some that won't
Survive but right now it's the Wild West
You know everybody wants to have
Connected
They realize how much it cost
To maintain a Kinect
The device
Further subscriber base over a long. Of time and they're trying to figure out how to get paid for it
At the same time
That these ecosystems are trying to
Consolidate and some of the consolidators
Are looking for
How did they assemble Partnerships but
Keep the recurring monthly Revenue to themselves
Two very exciting time I can't tell you where the equilibrium will balance out
But in order for us to control our own destiny we
We have to continue to develop
Things that
Consumers will value and are willing to pay for
Sure I'm just wondering is eventually they'll be kind of like
Like a cable package
For the smart
Provider ISP
Some third-party
Whereas security
A system just I no longer know what
To you guys
In particular
Part of a package of
Cloud storage Plus
You know if dinner
Decorations Plus
Absolutely
Possible
And there's so many different directions at that taking
You can see the security
Providers taking a lead on that you
Home automation Partners taking a lead on that you can
To see the cable and telephone line companies taking a lead on that
You can see that damn
The world taking a lead on that and that the home assistant
And we're not really sure where it's at
To settle out
But the good thing
Is that every single one of those partners
Want garage
Well maybe you guys will get to be the ESPN
Let's talk about
New stuff
You guys have
Expanded from
You've obviously had
Business outside
Consumer but I know that
Roughly a year ago I talked
Tacori Cerise over
About
You guys starting to create a service package for
Commercial customer
Merced actually helps them
Understand their business better based on like
Like how much time
Trucks are spinning at loading dock
Bassinet sort of in
Information
So I'm curious
1 how are you guys evaluating these new Hopper
It might be that the business
That you guys are working on
And where do you see you guys going next on that
So you're right to our reorganization
Did create a commercial line
Fitness now we've always sold commercial door openers
It's part of our core comp
Trauma residential line
And so they're heavier Duty and they do a few different things
Take advantage of our engineering Act
Toyota open
Commercial doors
Maybe for a disc
Warehouse the issue is is that
The biggest
Competitor
In the commercial line of business is do nothing
Unlike
Residential homes
The commercial doors
Are often manually power
Do you have a worker coming in the morning
And they roll that
Hang up in the morning and maybe
They might close it a little bit throughout the day
But in large part they remain open
For much of the day
Are they closing at the end of the day
And for years we've been relying
On a value proposition that talked about injury.
And workman's comp
Claim avoidance
As one of the reasons for why
Owner-operators
Distribution center stay
Should invest in
Commercial door opener
But the reality is
Is that
A cost avoidance
For whose cost it isn't even in your operating plan
Is one of the first things
Should be cut it really
Resembles insurance
And when you are resource
That's one of the line items
And so by creating this
Line-of-business where the group
Really focusing
On the End customer
And what are their problems and what are their offer
Judaism
It's all for them
We gained a lot more insight
Around
How their business works
And how we can
Better contribute to that business
Through an automated and connected
Commercial Door operator
That can contribute to things like
Energy saving
ASPCA at the Spaceway
Climate control
Or
Safety
Plaintiff
Say it's a pharmaceutical
Warehouse
They need to
Cooperate
To a regulatory
Security has been in force
Or efficiency
If you think about
Many people have a certain number of doctors
For their distribution warehouse
I think that they're all being utilized equally
And then there are capital requests add on more
If we can provide the data that shows them the actual usage
And the trends that they
Can understand when the right time to invest in then the back of a p&l on
Real insight as to how they can operate their business
More effectively
It doesn't trade on
Fear
And cost avoidance that really isn't even in their planning at 4
Yay
Let's wrap it up with others in your position
Or rather in a similar position
Products
And it cost them money over the long term
What would you do differently if you were building
MyQ today
And the ground up
Well if you reference
Starting to charge for some
That has been free for almost six
Sears has not made me the most
Most popular purse
It's been a
Small butt
Vocal
Group of detractors and if I had to do it over again
I would have
I could rewind to 6 years ago I was in a company then but if I
Somehow travel back in time I would have done more thinking
About
What value are we creating
What service are we offering
And what do we want to offer free
But what do we need to charge
In order to help keep the investor
Going if anybody thinks that they're going to start out
Free and once people love it
Then you're going to start charging and people will be happy to pay
Dog probably end up in
The same boat that I was
Once we did start charging for certain integration
Beyond RV services
Got it
You guys build your own cloud pot
Correct
Yes we absolutely did
Being a company that is rooted in
Security
And making sure that we have
An offering
That controls
Security of what for most people is their front door
The garage door
We wanted to make sure that we
Had full control over that
Okay so
That's still
From your perspective
It's still a good decision
We can
Monitor
And we can make sure that we understand what's happening
100% of
The time and
For us
The other opportunities around commercial or perimeter or other applications just continues to make that a good to see
Vision is weird
Word branching out from
Are base residential business even further
Excellent
All right
Joanna thank you so
Much for coming on the show
It's my pleasure it was nice talking with
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Is please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week