Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And it is
Is been a long time
But we are here with episode
Is 7 for you guys
And we are going to be talking about
Our predictions for the year ahead and what we plan to see at CES
Plan probably what we think we're going to
We're also going to be talking about smarts
Speakers because
Cuz you know
It's a day that ends in y
We got news on Google and their projects
Solely which is their radar-based
Gesture
We got
100 million-dollar fundraise
Is 4
Iot platform company that
Value City at three points
6 billion dollars making a
Get an iot unicorn
Plus
We have to do a
It's not a correction it's just a
We're idiots and we didn't see this
So we're going to do something on one of her answers from
Last week's
Episode
All of this
Plus we have got Scott McDonald who is
A managing partner at Mack Rock Capital he's going to be talking about
Trends in the industrial iot for the year
I had so we got can
Consumer we've got Industrial
And we've got
December's voice
Smell winner
And
We're going to hear a little bit more from digicert
And they're iot security survey
And before we get to all of that
Let's hear from another one of our sponsors
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform
Find out why Kenmore and dealing
Pick a pharaoh
Affero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction
Shannan time-to-market 99% pure
Support calls and a 10x
Higher activation
What's Bakery use 90% of their work from one project to the next
To learn more visit a pharaoh
Dot IO
That's a f
Ero
Dot IO
And
If you want to meet with the Pharaoh at CES
Just emails
CES at
A pharaoh
Dot-com to sign up for a meeting
Email saying thanks for sponsoring my favorite podcast
All right
Kevin
Let's get this party started
Happy New Year first of all to you and all of our listeners
I can't believe it
2019 already
I can
2018 was just
Bear of the year
This is true
For many many reasons
Somaya tea related in some not but yes
I'm very glad to put that calendar
So here we are flipping the calendar first thing
Probably going to talk
Talk about
Because next week we're heading there
Actually later this week we're heading
We're going to Vegas for CES that's the Consumer Electronics Show it's a big show for
Consumer electronics
I thought we were just going to Vegas we have to go to this show
Hey
It's like a hundred
Twenty thousand hundred fifty thousand people Vegas is that showed
Yes yes it is this is what your third Sia
It's actually going to be my V
Your 50s look at you should get a special star
Oh and it's like your 20th
No I think it's
12 * 30
Teens I can't recall but I'm looking forward to walking the many miles around
Vegas the convention
All the hotels and of course I will be tracking all those steps like I always do to see if I can
Break my CS record which I think is like 52 miles at week
That is insane
You go right ahead and so
We will have
Next week's episode is going to be
On the 10th
Recorded at CES will be talking about cool things that we
Racine and then we're also doing a special CES episodes
It will come out the fort
And on that
Episode
You will hear
From people we met at CES talking again about consumer trends
But
We're going to do it
We kind of have to logistically is her tricky because CES is still going on as we're going to be recording the show
From CVS Oster maybe new things we find out
After the show for example again
Interviewing and talking to people we've got to edit and so on and so forth
I think that's a good approach
Two weeks of CBS coverage
Yay
So just
Real quickly
We'll go down some we won't go too much
Listen to it but I think it's worth
Giving you a heads up on things that I say
Super nuts
So 1
Connected bathroom
You guys
I
Expect I told you this and I was like I regret to
We are going to see smart toilets at CES
We are we are going to see them from
Many of the major brands and
They're going to have
Some crazy feet
And I can't give you too many details about all of these
Plus I'm sure I'm going to see
Evenboer
But
You should expect some smart speaker toilets maybe some flights may be soon
Interesting
Cleaning technology
It's going to be wild
I'm going to let you hit those boots
Cuz that's not my jam that's all I'm going to say
We're going to shoot
Video
It's going to be fine
So that's it in in addition to toilets
You're going to see a lot happening in the bath
So smart mirrors going to be a thing
Lot of smart Health technology that
It's going to try to
Incorporate things from your scale and
Mirror's Edge
Other new devices that are going to be out
I hope all is
Bathroom essentials in the smart home are
Battery power because I don't feel like rewiring electricity in my bathroom
Or something like a smart
Mirror for example
That is a point
So and we saw this actually
It was a two years ago that Moen launch there they had a smart shower
Thing in the last year
Kohler launched
Couple smart bathroom thing
As well
The challenge with a lot of these is people do not have electricity like you have to
To put
To put the Moen smart shower thing and you had to
Install basically a touch screen in Your Shower
And you had to wire electricity to your shower
And that's
Yeah do that with the water off is my recommendation
I would have sent you
Hire a professional for this
Particular
Insomnia
So that'll be kind of
I said not to do it
Another thing I think we're going to see are some really crazy cool headphone
I think we're going to see a lot of
We talked in the past about getting
Google Assistant
Madame de all of these in anime
Amazon
Getting that into headphones I think we're even going to see some
Cool sensors
If not at CES
I think we're going to see it
This coming year in
You know what there's a bunch of
Smart headphones incurables
Out now
And it's early in this market for sure and companies have integrated assistance
Listen to headphones
Cordless headphones need to be connected by Bluetooth to some
Smarter device
To get the information from the
Cloud I wonder you think maybe there's a wave
For these
Headphone makers
To make headphones almost always connected but not with Bluetooth met with Wi-Fi but
Get the Wi-Fi off when you're not using the assistant parts
Just cuz of Wifi battery drain I mean
I'll try to think of what could Advance this
I'm thinking more of the Thai
So I think it'll offer Health and Wellness
I'm thinking we'll probably see you know you can actually get a lot of really interesting information for me
Ear
So I think we're going to see something
Like that
As opposed to an always
On
Individual I think you're right when you frame it that way but I'm going to
Say that I don't think they'll be a big thing
And the reason I think that is because headphones aren't something you wear all the time
Like my Apple watch for example
Take an Android Wear watch doesn't matter
That's
True now I could see it for more accurately
Like a heart rate monitor
In your Apple watch actually
For people who don't have
This may be in a baby more power efficient or better place
To put it I don't know
There's definitely in it and accuracy benefit in certain
Thanks no doubt about it I just I don't know
Maybe four people don't wear watch
Watches or other wearable
Keith Whitley
Interesting
Yeah so and they are way more accurate
Speaking of
Icing
In 29
And you know also at CVS
We're going to see
Sea change
In the number of
Appel
And wellness-related devices
Algorithm
And we're going to start seeing FDA approval
On a lot of
Thor on some of them
And that's going to be really
Cuz we see right now you know some of its
Snake oil right you're like
You can track this it'll be amazing but
You don't really know if it's actually doing anything or
You know what this heart rate monitor is actually
We accurate enough
But
With Amazon they've got actually Omron is a blood pressure cuff
Apus monitor there actually making
A wristband that's going to
Check your blood pressure constant
So if you look at something like that
You can now ask
You know Madam a what
My blood pressure
That becomes really
Kind of exciting and then I also see
A lot of research
Husband going into things
Looks like gate detection for various illnesses and then things like
Using your voice
Understand if you're
Depressed
If you have Parkinson's if you have some other medical condition
And I think we're going to start to see that in FDA-approved Fashions on our
Smartphones and device
And that's going to be
Freaking awesome
Splashtown
I think you're right and I also would add to it
I hope they say I'm not going to text back
PC but I hope to see more
Simple ways to
Share this data with
Your health provider
I think that's going to take a little bit low
But that's okay
And I think I could stew actually the next thing
That I have on my list
Privacy
I think we're going to have to come up with ways to understand how the state is being used and
We're going to have to
To figure out
How to protect
Consumers
And how far we want to go
With like health insurance and pre-existing conditions
Because
This is going to
Exposed
A whole new area
Risk
And that's scary for health
And I don't know how we're going to handle
That I mean if you can tell if someone's having Parkinson's symptoms
Super early this is not something that
Security camera
Managed right
What does that mean
If you can detect it
Early
How does it affect rates coverage
Can you get coverage absolutely
I think this is more of a long-term
Problem
We're going to see those things
Start to happen
When we vote me out because we've started to see this already
In terms of with driving Percocet
Safe driver
Monitoring
Devices that you put in a car first
You can get ready to sit down or up
Based on how are you
Try for 60 days or 30 days
But you're right
The reason I say it's a longer-term
Being is because
You get into it
Policy now and governments and
The healthcare industry is so slow.
To change as are the laws that regulated
Where it is regulated so but you're right this is
Where we start to see
How that's going to shake out in the coming years
Yasso in John Hancock for example
Bill has a
Insurance policy that requires you to have
Connect
Wearable device
Yes it is so
Not to
Crazy
Also the privacy
We're going to see some sort of Regulation I guarantee it
It's going to be
Probably pretty crappy
Lot of negotiations back
Back and forth but I
In 2019 we're going to get our version of
PR
Close enough
I passed like a
Or maybe
Let's just not even talk about that
Okay other two big things
One is mvnos for iot
Connectivity
I think
There's a whole effort
Taking place
With the platform companies like
Like a lion particle and those guys are introducing
Cellular
Platform cellular services for iot device makers in their acting
Kind of is an mvno
You're seeing them
Bucket a lot of options for
Carrier so
You don't have to do that yourself as
As a client
I think we're going to see an advancement on that
From other new entrance
Set the market like twilio there's some interesting things happen
And you're up here so I think we're going to see
Canada Slayer
This abstraction layer on
On top
Cellular connectivity the basically
Allows
People to connect your devices without having to
Negotiate
The carriers
And that'll be
Worthwhile
I agreement already seen twilio for example start to do this
Put a data SIM cards at
You can use
Variety device
Testing and so on
This is definitely
A shift from
What mvnos have done in the past which is offered
Were you would they would bundle up maybe text
Talk voice and
Data from
Bigger carriers Envy cell and smaller chunks
Fourier
Cell phone plan for disabled
This is more I think you're towards industrial towards device makers
And so forth so
I would think
But that service would come with some devices and fat
I don't know if you probably pay a monthly subscription but
Yeah maybe they you don't have to provision
And some companies are basically saying hey
What connect your device
As long as it doesn't do more than this if this many mags
Data
And this is the
And then they just
That allows come
To say all right
We're going to charge you this
And we
Got to stay the same
So that'll be good and then there's also things like satellite
I think we'll hear a lot about in 2019
I'm curious how far will get into Act
Well Services
But they're definitely launching satellites and hoping to
Provide some sort of iot
Key service I just don't think
But I still question was busy
So
Just for me power consumption from a demand from
Armacost
Yeah
Well and then and I'm going to say and you're going to
Cringe
I got a mansion 5G cuz
If the big HuHot the end of 2018 with the first devices and hot spots and so on and so forth
And how it's going to change the out to world
No I don't think so in 29th
The world is not
It'll get gradually
All right and then my final prediction which will be really interesting
I think or in this is
But I think we're going to see a lot happening with voice program
Not necessarily for consumers although we seen that actually in the smart home but I think we're going to start seeing it
In like Amazon's AWS
I think you're going to start to be able to ask things of
Mattamy or maybe even Cortana
And you ask the assistant in the assistant will give you information about like your cloud
Settings
What not
And that's going to be
Really
Fun interesting
We'll see
It's interesting to me a minute and just from a programming standpoint
Can you interface a voice interface for
Making things happen better not
Let's say
Static information
Is there any interest
Probably not for like your typical consumer but
Ouija collector stuff
Yeah well and I think consumers like it too cuz it makes me
Easier in so I'm interested like how is the syntax going to develop how do we actually implement this
Will there be a standard
Yes yes yes
Those are interesting I have a
Couple that I'll run through pretty quickly things that we may hear see etcetera at Cas and maybe some
Hopes and expectations for the year in the
I have to mention like we do every year
Siri and homekit because maybe 2019 will be the year for these
Do you think
No I don't think so
Mention something just before the show and then neglected to put in the show notes but one of the Google headhunter
Just went over to Apple to work on
Voice interface AI
Yes yes John giannandrea
He actually had gone over there while back
I think he joined Apple
It was in April
A 2018 he went there from Google but now he's been promoted to their executive
So I think Apple's getting
Serious
About
Siri
Yeah well I have to say 2018 was a bust
On that front for them
Because couple reasons I think most of them are obvious
And there's one that's maybe not so obviously wouldn't think it is the speakers and digital citizen cider
Proceeding aren't is the smartest ones
Are the most widely available
Yes
Not everyone has
And iOS device for a homepod which
Really I mean I spell for a year now folks
Yeah
Yeah that's almost say about that
Something started do I start to see in
2018 actually has been happening long as I suspect
I'm kind of
I don't say worried
About to be in Z-Wave but I'm seeing less of a place for them in this
Cloud connected API Centric
World of the Smart Hub
And it's funny because somebody just asked me the other day
I think I'm going to get the new
Echo hub
It has that extra radio and like what are you going to use it with
It'll do you have something to eat
ESAT radio
You like will know what do you use
For unlike
Yxz1000r
Sensors and things that are low power but
You don't have those no plan add those
Why are you buying the subpoena
You think I'm crazy on that
No no I have been
I've been thinking this
4 years right and it's still I mean Vivian Z-Wave silky
Trucking along but I do think they're going to find themselves
As mortgage
Especially
Especially is Bluetooth
Izhmash kit
Yep better
And integrated and more sensors cuz that's where you see zigbee and Z-Wave is in
Lights and sensors
Because you need low power in
Wifikill
So
Yeah I know some people would be happy to hear that and hopefully I'm wrong
Maestro's people that's on my side
This year ended with an interesting twist
On the smart home user interface
It's not just voicemail
We're really getting more into
Displays and I suspect
In 2019 will Seymour home dashboards
It may not just be like a smart displays from Google or the
Echo shows and so on
More integration with TVs and other display
Will Ferrell
Yeah and I think
Contacts
Just going to really
You know we've talked about this for like
Using context is going to be the key to make
That work
Feel almost match
Ability to say oh this is the
Kind of contents
And that I should leads to another
Thought I have and I've been single for a couple years now.
The smart ones we have are actually not that smart
They just respond to things when we tell them to respond the things that respond to her voice with
Somewhat canned responses in
Skills and so on and so forth and actions
Yes you can set up routines and
Things like that I get that but
Where's the machine learning
Where is the Smart Hub getting
Smarter where maybe it notices a trend or pattern
Like you come home every day between 5 and 5
15 Saudi really need to have a
Smart light routine that turns the outside lights on at 5
No you know maybe you don't
You don't need to manually do that at
I can start doing things
Right now the smart home doesn't do much on its own
So I think
And hope that we'll see more in the AI and ml area
Here
And then laugh
Will two things
Smart speaker overload I'm already sick of it I have more smart speakers than I have room to put them in that
Could lead towards
Other devices
Mobile devices robots and sex
But have a speaker
And a microphone so we can get rid of all of these speakers
Don't know we want microphones everywhere speakers
Microphones
I don't think we need that and I'm not lying
Sorry
Okay I'm going to trust me I'm going to I'm going to be all over that robot section c you looking for this
You know I may come short but if not I'm going to say huh
Last week
Something that we talked about our last show
I don't think a lot of these smart home device makers were really
Prepare for the fast
I'll take a mesh Wi-Fi
So I really think this year
Newer products
Are just going to work with mesh WiFi and the reason is
Allow these devices have
Less capable Wi-Fi chips maybe only 2.4 gigahertz support
And so on and then you have dedicated network name and
On that channel or on that
How that would match so
I really think
That problem starts going away in
I hope
So
B2
Me too
All right
And I also
We're probably going to see I mean we've already seen this year I don't think
Less consolidation now I think we've established that Google home
And Amazon
Anime
I pretty much the King of the Hill when it comes to the
The kings of hell
When it comes to the consumer
King and queen
My
Yeah alright you could send you could have changed the voices
I was thinking of Google is but he and Madame a is but she I don't know why
We should not
It's hard to do when you have a robot though they can actually speak to one of these
Delta Fire
IRobot
Okay
But
You don't Bixby
Cortana
Who else is up
Siri
So
Who is our best and smartest
Smart speaker and we actually talked about this the newsletter. Last
Because we didn't have one last
But the way
Prior adventurous today
What color did i q test for
Smart speakers
And they discovered that
They tested both understanding of the inquiry
And then the ability to act
And Google
One out
Lake in a major way but
Where that bad I was actually pretty impressed
No no
I mean
When it comes to understanding the queries all of them at 99% or better which is good and just to be clear
The same questions were asked of each of these
General assistance
Hundred question so I think that's a pretty reasonable
Sample size actually unimpressive they did this
When it comes to answering correctly that tells you a lot
About who is truly smart and who is not in the
Space Google Assistant led the way with eighty seven point nine percent
Incorrectly
Siri was actually second at 74.6
1%
Surprise me
And then Madame a 72 and 1/2 in Cortana unfortunately 63.4%
Questions were answered correctly
But this leads
2y the big two are the big two in general
They have the biggest knowledge
Crafts I think
And they are against
Sinner lyrics
The most widely available to capture data as well so
Bixby is not even part of the conversation here
Will Bixby has been out on phones for well over
2 years
On a Samsung phone again you're limited just like Siri or limit iOS
So that's a problem for Samsung
Additionally they don't have a search engine of their own they have a browser
On
Samsung devices but I don't
Tingting capture
Nearly as much data as anybody else
Honestly they have new
I'm going to say this is both a new business being in the space
They just don't inspect and in fact that Samsung Galaxy home speaker that looks like
Fondue pot
Coming soon I said
Which presently was before the end of the year I'm pretty sure they said before the end of the year
It is not available for sale yet and it is now 2019
A top of that
This is very telling to me
It was reported just
Last week
Apparently
Samsung may be partnering with Google to add Google Assistant to its
Smart TVs
Instead of or I guess
Alongside of Bixby
That's
Waving the white flag with right there
Yes
That is
But I mean it's kind of necessary
Yukata
If necessary if your
Google assistant is junk yes
I mean I know I sound cranky about this but I sat
Through a 90 minutes
Samsung CES press event
Last year and it was all SmartThings
It was all
Bixby
Higher primate
Lifeline ovens
Bridges
Sode and 28
18 did
Switch from the original SmartThings to the new integrated SmartThings that can talk to lots of
Samsung
You're so they did in a great and that's
If you think about it they had special apps for the refrigerator special apps for their
Televisions and they brought it all under the smart
Plan was bring it all into SmartThings
In that app
I don't know if
Everything is very yet
But a lot of it is
Well I haven't looked at the app in a while several months I should say and
Just transitioning from the SmartThings classic app to the new one was
Horrendous
Horrendous user experience
And if you look at the reviews of those apps
A lot of people are not happy we're not happy at the time with the new app
So it's probably worth a revisit I'm going to wait until
The dog and pony show at CES
And then I will take another look at it
Take a gander
Yes I have been playing I played with SmartThings
Just a month.
It was
The transition was horrendous
Yes you're right
Things
Still work as anticipated I don't have any smart Samsung appliances so I couldn't bring anything
I just don't have anything that I could have brought over and I was going to buy a new washer and dryer or anything crazy
So it's a little hard for me
How to test exactly
What it's like to break in the news
But the old stuff they smoothed it out
So it works
For the most
Right and I'm not
I want it kind of exclude like a SmartThings ecosystem and the Hub and products because
It's really good
It's not bad it's the whole Bixby thing that aspect of it
Has rubbed me the wrong way since they launched it
And all of my experience with it as backup my
You know I guess you could say preconception
Which maybe isn't fair but still it just isn't
It's good they cannot yet compete I don't see how they can compete again they don't have the back end of information
Google or an Amazon have
Okay well
That was a lot of cranky
Kevin we don't see a little cranky Kevin
I had to get it all out
I'll be good for the rest of the year I promise
Senior and Kevin
Okay well let's blow through some news.
Real fast
So we got a test
Or drone deliveries
And oh people love the fact that they can get their stuff in
A few hours
And other people who are not getting their stuff
Few hours hate
The fact that drones are noisy
Yeah the funny thing is this is happening now in Australia
These are up past
Program from wings
Which is a subsidiary of alphabet
And I've had drugs before and one of the things is yeah they can be a little noisy but I think the bigger issue and some people are
Complaining about it
The ultrasonic frequencies
From a drone motor
Tribes
McCann Drive
Pets
Crazy
Scares the bejesus out of
My dog for example I actually got rid of my drone because
At the dog I couldn't hear what he was hearing but boy he did not like it
Yes
We also have
Research for the University of Singapore on
Power saving
Powri
How would you describe
I would say that this is a addition to sensor technology that could
Allow the sensor to wake up when it's needed
Basically cut the power consumption down
Apparently by at least
1000 time
Down to the Pika watt range
And that's because
You don't in certain use cases need a sensor on all the time it doesn't need to be drawing power from its battery
Turn electricity Etc
You just need it when it's needed and I know that's hard to predict so I don't know how this is going to be
Implemented
But the technology seems to be promising
Thanks for that if we can figure out the right algorithm
Sensors will be using nearly as much
Battery power
Always
It's a good thing
We got some new samsara
Which
They launched a while back they've been an iot platform they were going to be very generic
And then they really honed in on
Honda vehicles
They have raised
A hundred million dollars
At a 3.6 billion dollar valuation
This is mostly for fleet manager
And cars and trucks and
It makes a lot of sense the guys who found a Sims
Sorrow with the founders
Meraki in the idea that they had there was
You basically
Wife I was getting really complicated as people
Brought more devices into an Enterprise
Corporate Network
MBA Rocky they built
Special
Router Xanax
Plus software that made that a lot
That's kind of the idea with samsara
Oh my gosh will bring you all these connected
Sensors on board and we need both a new
Radio technology in
Software to manage the
Ended up going with was saying okay
That's too big that's
Debride
We're just going to do this for
Fleet manager
So
This is a good thing it's
Glad to hear it I have been cut
I have worried about them but there's a lot of iot platforms out there that are not going to make it so I'm glad to see
These guys well-funded and apparently doing really well in their selected
They aren't they are very well-funded because this
Raises their total funding UPS 230 million
And the company says they haven't even used any other previous round of funding
So I don't know what kind of plans they have it must be big
Yeah it a lot of
Companies are anticipating a
A big Market turn down
So it's probably wise up
Get the money while you can
Especially in an area like iot platforms
Okay and another news Google they got FCC approval at the
Fairy end-of-the-year witch
Good actually cuz the FCC is going
Part of the government shutdown
They got RCC approval for
A project soli which uses
Radar
Is a 60 gigahertz
To detect your gestures so the idea that used it
QQ sisters tag gestures
On fabric
Skin on whatever
You want and you can use it to control screen
This was actually launched at
Same time project
Card was
Wei Wei Wei back in like
The 2015
I think so I think so at the Levi's jacket
Yeah and so
So we haven't gone places and one of the reasons is
That they couldn't get it at a high enough power
Experimental license
Search for the SEC to play with this
But they couldn't get
Enough power to get accuracy
The Chester
So this
Latest
Approval gives them
Basically
Moore DDS
It lets them transmit at a higher power so hopefully that will improve the resolution
Of
The gesture
Understand
That's being nice
I can see the
Immediate use
For people who have
In fact in the news release dimensions
This could benefit users with Mobility or speech impairment cuz
Can you speak to the great you are but not everybody can use it
So I get that
I wonder if it has to be
Combined with something physical like a
Jacquard project
Jacquard jacket for example
I'm thinking not
I'm thinking because it's right are you could literally have a virtual on off switch
Ukraine yes mr. fingers in the air and
Something turn on in your house for example so it's in a sentence
Like voice as always said as the invisible interface innocent This truly is
Invisible interface
Yes and
Right now they're using 60 gigahertz in a couple
I think last month I wrote about likewise 60 gigahertz was so interesting for The Internet of Things
And I talked about like fall detection and some of the other
Cool things
The companies are doing with this
Can somebody actually pointed out
Comments that project soli
Uses it
As well so you're right
And it's a very prescient statement this could be like the other invisible
All right and now
It is time for our
Iot podcast
Hotline before we get to
This week's question I have to fix an answer
From last week's episode
Our answer was
Drawing a chest
It was like the wrong way
And I apologize
Price for that you guys I
I don't know why my brain decides to
Things to post difficult way except it's
It's on me to both of us neglected to recognize the native
Madam a says function that's in the matinee app
I will defend myself
Anime app
Experience is
Horrible trap rap
Mine even the guy who I
I hired someone from Amazon to come and play with matinee at my house
Probably a couple months ago
Wow you're a prime so slow it's
Terrible and I was like I know
But
The question was
Basically how can I have an audible notification that
Like my door is open or a sensor status is
And the answer
Is
You can use a routine so a lot of people are using
SmartThings
For like
Their sensor management cuz Madame a does not handle a lot of sensor
But you
Basically use SmartThings for
This sensor has
Change state
Right so you put that in there
As part of your route
When this happens
SmartThings
That's your trigger event
SmartThings motion sensor triggered
Then do this
And then do this you just go to
It's called I'm going to say it you guys
Cover her ears
Alexa says
So you so like that and then you say
What does she say so you can write down
The door is open
I saw a dog whatever you want
How to say and you can set the volume
End
That's how this works
And it actually is easy yes
Samantha River before
Like notifications we hated it
We thought it was clunky as all get-out
And realize there are some pre-canned
The responses in there you have to use the custom command if you want
Something like he knows the back door it's open
This light was left on for more than 15 minutes excetera this is a great feature yes we missed it
It gets back to my smart home really isn't that smart
Thinking out this stuff chew just happened in a sense
LOD irritating
Felix shut up
Cadillac the alarm set
System that beeps whenever anything happens and you
And thank you guys
We had a bunch of you
Send it in
Really nice messages like
Hey
I don't know maybe you guys didn't see this but so
Thanks for letting us know
Oh and thanks for everyone who sent that in
It's like High
You could do it this way
They were very gracious to us
All right
Now
We will go to
Two more things
This week's question but first before that
We are going to announce our winner for the Schlage connect
Smart deadbolt
This month
Tsar actually last month's winner
December's winner is
Chris
Go Chris
Yeah yeah
Get your walk on
So congratulations to you Chris
And I will go to the question
For this
And I have to tell you that
Once again
This week the iot
See podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of electronic lock
Schlage electronic locks can make life
It's so much easier and more convenient
No more keeping track of x
Oyster house keys
Each member of your family can have their own access
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
All right
This week's voicemail question is
From
Heaven
Not this Kevin
A different Kevin
Let's hear it
Stacy
In Raleigh
South Carolina
My questions really about
Ecosystem
We have the ring doorbell
And now as a
Scarcity
Everything else in the house
Is Google Assistant
Parts for the iPhone but that's
Question is my going to have to
Amazon Echo
At work
To actually be able to do things like
Go in the back door
Podcast
Kevin this is such an important topic that I asked
She was going to write a post about it be
I'm so frustrated
The short answer is you
Can't connect your ring doorbell
To your Google
But you can't do what you probably most want to do
Which is C
Who's at the door
Right now
Google
Support
The ability to
Take a video doorbell in
Connected to
What your Google home device
And even Google displays
And Google Chromecast
But ring
Does not allow for
So and I don't know if that's because
Has Google and ring are talking
Or what the deal is but ring right now in ring actually for a while did not come
But the Amazon stuff easily as well so it may be a
But ring will let you
Talk to your ring doorbell through Google home you can ask it about
When your doorbell
A string
You can ask it starting to
Recording
Ask it to turn on motion alerts
But you can't see who's at your door
Right
And I suspect
It's less about Ring not talking to Google then it is about
Amazon not wanting to talk to Google about this since Amazon bought ring last year
So yes the short answer is you can connect it
The longer answer is you can connect it and get
Some basic information
Probably not the visual and
Information your look
Dissolution
I hate to say it you guys
Is Topeka Niko
Google home
If you're going to be on Google home
The Nest hello doorbell which is an awesome door
Both the ring and the nest
Storehouse RS
Excellent I think the nest is actually a better doorbell because
It's a little bit faster in the
Facial recognition on it is
Phenomenal
So I'm actually
You're looking for the best video doorbell and that's your focus I say go with the nest hello
Which means you'd be a Google Echo
Ecosystem
And so if you're in the Google ecosystem already
Take back your ring man
Captain's get the nest hello
It's going to do everything you want
Are the echo ecosystem
Yeah don't get a nest
Because
Google is not going to
It goes so far and I don't
Time soon
Will give
The video app
AP Iced Out
So
Then you want to be in the ring
Which is a really good doorbell in
They have to be getting closer on the better
Facial
Recognition and understand
Yeah it's
I mean it's just disappointing though that you have to pick an ecosystem for
Akira lock your
Doorbell
I would say
It's really only for those.
Like video cameras
If you want to see it on your home display
And your door
Like sensors you can pull in through a variety of platforms
Even Arlo if you want to
You know maybe
I want to get the video doorbell just
Popping Arlo out there and
Then you can do a lot of things
I don't know
It's not everything
It's just those thing
Store
And at the shame that all while it could be an alarm system
To but the shame of it all is
We should have seen this coming because
Google Nest came from Google and then went back in to Google
Spun out
Alphabet and then went back to Google and then
As we said Amazon bought ring that's when you start seeing the sideways go up
And that's that's the disappointing
So yes we are in Silo territory
Kevin I'm sorry to tell you this
That is our advice on this
And
Guys if you have a question for us
Please
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
The answer may not always be what you want to hear
It would guarantee an answer we just can't guarantee one that you like
All right
Well that concludes this portion of the show
And stay tuned for Scott MacDonald of mcrock capital who is going to be talking about
The big shift
Leptin
Enterprise and Industrial iot
Basically
The last five years have been one thing and now we're getting ready for the next five years
And will you guys be per
Prepared
Find out
After a message for this week sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Sweet sponsor is digicert and I have Mike Nelson who is VP
Of iot security at
Can you remind our listeners
What it is that digicert
Dad the desert is the world's
Leading provider of
Scalable Security Solutions for identity and encryption and we provide these Solutions
Search for web servers
Enterprise security and my favorite
Of course iot
Mike we learned a lot about the survey.
Theraclear benefits to organizations prioritizing and implementing iot
Security
Can you tell us about some of the ways that the
Successful organizations are benefiting to a handful of group
They were talk to your organization's that demonstrated a Mastery of iotc
Security middle-tier and then the bottom tier of courts are organizations that really struggling to master coyotes
Security and the difference between the top and the bottom tier
Was shocking
Every one of the bottom chair organizations have experienced a security mishap
Things like denial
Service or malware compared to just 32%
Of the top-tier
The bottom tier was much more likely to have reported problems
In those areas
They were
Nearly six times as likely to experience
Data breaches
And unauthorized access to iot devices
Compared to the top care and spell the survey for my perspective it really highlights that
The things of the top-tier organizations are doing
Priority security are working and in protecting their organizations
So where should organizations start when building an iot security strategy
My recommendation for organizations is there looking to stand up and iot security practices first of all to make
Make sure that they build
Security into the DNA of the way there
Developing their products and that would mean everything from making sure that they think about cyber security in the architecture in the design
Testing for cyber security man in the
Employment making sure that you're doing the things that are continually
And keep your devices secure
So we asked to talk to your organization's the things that they were doing that were leading them to be successful without you
Security and they gave us five
Sphinx the first was
Scalability
Of their solution to making sure that the scale of the solution they put in place will just meet their needs for today
But also five years down the road making sure that they're doing Integrity check
On any package that's being sent to the device
Doing authentication on all connections coming to and from the device
To make sure no unauthenticated connection or person can get into the device
Reviewing and Performing risk assessment
Is always important to understand the vulnerabilities of the device and then finally and of course
Encryption of sensitive data
And making sure that you're encrypting data both at rest and also in transit
Thanks bike that's excellent advice
So where can people go to learn more about the survey and Digicel
Yeah the full details of the survey can be found on our website at digicert. Com
Forward slash
Iot security
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Scott McDonald who is a managing partner
And co-founder at
Mcrock capital
Hi Scott how are you doing
Eddie Stacy I'm doing well how are you
I am excellent I'm excited to kick off the new year with you as our first guest on
On the show
Partially because you have a great theory that I think it's going to set us up nicely for a big trend
In 2009
18 and also because your firm invests
Heavily in industrial iot
Let's just get this started
Talk to us a little bit about what you've been investing in in the last
Few years
And what you think is
Is going to change
In the coming year
Well I'm excited to be on
Thank you for having me and what weight on my shoulders
Takeoff
2019 talking about all things iot
You're right mcrock capital has
Exclusively on the industrial side of the IRT
The past 7 years
Was raised in 15
70 million-dollar spoke exclusively on the industrial side of the iot
2 back then
What we really were looking at
Was the collection of data
Machines
And the conductivity of that data so I have an analogy that I use
That the coyote
Can be the body and the Brain
Are there two different portions
As we evolve through the iot
And the last five years has been about
Data from equipment machines and sensors and connecting it and in some ways
Cleansing data
But it really has been a data play
Setopati
And in the next 5 years were singing
Just now
To the real disruptor side of iot which is the analytics I now that we have all this
Is dark data
Start to do things with it using machine learning and AI
General Analytics
It's going to drive
Huge disruption in Big Industry and it's going to drive
Productivity
Okay and you just use the phrase dark data
What does that mean
The dark data is
Unintelligent
It's just
Tech data
Is a building block of some value creation
But until you do something with the data and
Recognize
Patterns are deaf.
So what
Which is dark data
State of it's not doing anything it doesn't have any meaning to it that's where analytics comes into play
We've been hearing a lot of
Machine learning
But we're starting
Really see a lot of connection technology
Become intelligent
So that's me
Take that dark data
You apply Analytics
And now
You know but she was are not only being able to send their actually becoming aware
They're starting to
Make predictions are starting to act
So it's one thing to have a recognition of what
Call it
Current state
Telling people they suck
So you think about a machine that's running
It's not optimized
It's not doing a very good job it's that your production line is not very efficient
Is there a y
What you really need to do is now take corrective action and automate the whole process not swear this
Play
So we go from
Learning
From the data from the machines what's actually happening as they talks to us then we need
Better way to operate them through AI
Now the finals
Feedback loop is when software also then take the autocorrect option
And changes the way that they're behaving in this is not using the word machine
Traffic light so that you can have it
Control in a city
And start to figure out how many
Cars are at an intersection
2 * 2
In real time
Traffic lights
I like that
There's no Roi in telling someone that they say
I like that a lot
So if we go by the story which I think is totally accurate
Which must be why I had
You come on that show
The last five years have been about hooking up
Machines getting the data
Getting the body
Of the iot
And then the AIS pek
Back to being the brain and then starting to do something
What that what if in the last 5 years you've been reading about the
Maybe we should try that
Kind of dipping your toe in the water but you're not there yet
Are these companies that have not built out the body yet are they behind
Skylark
Companies that build up the body
You know we speak a lot
Large corporations that say things like
We want
Cuz they have the angle they know what they want cuz there's r a y
So they go to the
Thing that they need
What they don't have is
Everything
Equipment
Connected
Whether it's wired on
Leflore weather it's wireless
Pieces of equipment
We've been monitoring
Will high levels
Statistics try to map out where we are in the evolution of the eye
For the first time have dropped below 100% kegger so
This year they were about 91:4
Sam Insidious years they were
Hop in the hundred and thirty
Percent growth rate now
Other areas like monthly Revenue
As it relates to machine machine is still in the early days and it's
Just starting to grow
Is that monthly revenue for providing cut
Activity
To these machines
It's hard
Coppell glass
Be careful with that one because it is hard to tell whether it's just connectivity or that serve
But it is M2M Market Revenue
Is got 12% kegger and you know we're still at planet in the
300 billion range
Which is again I suspect probably has
Large number already
Your question around where are companies
That may not be
Including instrumented and sensor Dell
I think they're not
Far behind
Because of technology and Innovation now
Shekinah
Walk-in different ways to access machine data and a lot of equipment is being built with sensor
It just wasn't used for different
Again I go back to my turn
This there it's sitting there it's sort of
Trout
And now
Dilaudid
Spiders that are helping me
Operations
Connect
An access. Data
So you could catch up really quick
I don't think anyone is
Materially behind the best
If I'm thinking about making Investments
And I'm looking at
Getting to the dark date or even maybe
Doing something
Is it too late for me to invest in those
Company should I be starting up an analytics company this pointer
A data cleansing company where should I be sinking
If I'm doing something
Now
Going forward and looking into the future and that's sort of our prediction that are from
Seeing a lot of Hardware a lot of what we would call the body type in Destiny
We dabbled into the brain side into
Analytics
With a company called noodle in Montreal
We were waiting for a lot of people to
Septic systems up and running before they were ready
Sirius Analytics
They had to get the body though
Looking forward
You're crashing but we're looking for in the future
I think we really looking at the analytics I
Looking at companies that actually can
A call that dating now in a lot of these companies
Will be at your place awkward
Some will still have a hard-working
And there's also another area that I kind of put
Andaman with analytics which is
Cyber security
And that's a whole nother area but
Need that is
Analogy body in the brain
Cyber security
Analytics
Are the brain
And they are becoming more and more important as one cementation
Elmer conductivity
Got it and let's take him to some of this
So what's important if you're going to be the analytics or the brain side
Let's break this down a little bit
Got to have
I talked to
Dozens of companies each week that
If they're like we're doing AI for iot your AI for business transformation
What do they do
Be able to
Tudo how much room is in there for a variety of different
Well
If I broke down the Analytics
Landscape
There are number of companies that are doing well almost call Professional Services
So
They have hired
Very intelligent data scientist
And they work with corporations
Analyze data sets
To try to
Understand what the angle of the customer to say why do you want a eye what are you trying to accomplish
And there's a few different reactions in the biggest ones come to
Well we think there's
Value Adder productivity gains that can be hot if we analyze how our operation
The other one is usually around people and how people interface and maybe customizing the way someone engages effect now
Ecology on a personal level
It's a different people at different angles for Yai
But when you look back at the pipes
Companies there are
You have a
Handful
Of Technology businesses that are developing software
Not very many
Which are almost plug-and-play like jamming to dataset in
And it's going to go look for pattern recognition and it's going to start to discover things
There are other companies that have
Really sophisticated teams of smart people
Where they are at
Assisting in the learning of the AI
Solar still
Humans are still handling the data and the touch is still higher than everyone believes marketing wise you wouldn't know that but
Experian
And says it's very
Hand holding
AI data analytics
So we're getting there
Denver RC
True revolutionary
The Shelf software technologies that are designed for here let me give you a real example
Something around
A specific type of
And so it will have an agent machine learning agent
It starts to recognize certain situations and correlate
Failure
I'm a piece of equipment based on things like temperature vibration
The different sensor readings
And it will start to map
Predictions on
Tell your time
Weather 7 Days 15 days 30 days and it's a
Self-learning algorithm
So and it's run on
Bunch of different machines
Across the world
Pacific time
And every time there's a new state that identify
Turtle runs parallel experiment
To see if it's just a new statement the new operating State that's fine
Or if it's actually a failure mode and indication of failure mode
And so
That truly is
Predictive Analytics cuz you're actually running
Algorithm that constantly learning
About every different type of sensor
Be back and then trying to the
Text when there's an anomaly
That actually
Can lead to failure and then
True experience of data
Figure out if it's 5 days or if its 50 days
And then she can start to take real action
Got it
Okay
That does sound actually really cool
So now let's turn to Cyrus
Security
It's kind of the same Quest
Which is when we're thinking about industrial iot or just
Iot in general
Cybersecurity is a huge field what are the types of
Solutions that we really need what is different
About Cyprus
Security for industrial iot that we should be thick
Thinking about
Well the one area that I'm really excited
2019 S10
That anytime a device connect
Turn Network
And you see the devices we see that are vulnerable the ones that are outside the firewall of Noah traditional
Security system
Inside of a cyber kind
Security perimeter
To the network wireless
Whatever way that wireless
I know everyone thinks wife I usually when we say Wireless
There are different types
Analogies in the Spectrum
Just like a new open window any device connected the new open window
That hackers can get into and call around and what we
Seen so far in the last couple years
Is that the weaponizing devices
Just anything from routers the back of police cars 2
Smart TV
Those can be used
Kind of tax where they just tryna
You just trying to
Clogged
The internet and take down certain
So they're trying to be clever and sneaky that way in there as I call it weaponizing iot device
But it's not really trying to hack the device
So now we're starting to see more
Pacific
Cases
I guess attacks
That are much more professionally done
And there
Dedicated and targeted
So they know what the device is
Listening to be really simple like
Taking over the screens inside a airport
Taking it down and then holding them for ransom to say
No one knows what gates are going to Orlando flights are leaving our departing in a large Airport
Because
We basically take control of all that displays
And again Wireless
Tends to be the area of vulnerability
The word
Wishing very little
Quickest way most companies don't even
Have an idea of what the wireless
The structure that they're running the networks have no idea
What devices are connected to the network and it's pretty interesting when you start to have technology
But then looks at the types of devices that are connecting people surprise
It's just even in the audit
Of what they even have a wireless perspective
Even companies that don't think they have much find out
That people run spy cameras that there are
Drones in the vicinity that hook up to their Network
We had CEOs that have found that
You know when they're
Automatically hooking up to their you know they think they're hooking up to a Cellular Tower
From there
Cell phone
Someone can actually replicate that cell tower
In a device in a car parked out Sun
Update seniors home
And now you're going to start to put data directly where you don't think you're putting it
The whole idea round Wireless
Cybersaint
All these different devices that are connecting it's just fascinating
And something that
To be done
A lot of the companies
Putting Warren Moore
Wirelessly connected devices into the universe
Will probably making our last investment in someone
In a wireless fabric
Good company for this day
Got it and you guys are raising fun too
And that is where we're going to see more of your AI
And analytics Focus
Christian vestments correct
Exactly
In the new year will be finishing up the last
Investment fund 1
And will be launching the second
The same strategy
Sandusky industrial side of the it will be working with a number of corporate groups that are currently investor
Continue on with us
Our sun is largely made up by a dollar amount
Institutional Financial investors
We're looking for strong returns but we do have
Select group of very strategic limited partners
Cisco Systems
Caterpillar
And electricity de France which is the world's largest
Power utility
As we go into Fun
2 will decrease the size
Spike Lee
Up from 70 million and fun one to a hundred million and fun too
The focus will again start to
Shift a little bit as we see the IP of all things
I'm going to start to move into a little bit more of that
Blaine Anderson
We've been talking about where we have
Few more companies on the analytics side
We have been mapping a host
Cyber security companies that we also think are going to be urgently needed us
People develop a variety
She strategy and then
They start to realize they have
Have cyber resiliency baked in so that they make sure they're doing it safely and that they don't have embarrassing moments
What about things like Edge Computing this
Does people talk
So much about
Does that fit in with your current pieces or is that kind of a side project
Are you guys just aren't Focus
Stacy I mean clearly Cisco's very interested in
Anyone that makes a box
It's it's remotely somewhere
Wants to put computer power on and have it make decisions in
Crate
Increase Value Guide for it and I think there are applications that make total sense
Right where you don't want it
Descending
Tons and tons of data
Into the cloud when
There's not a lot of changes on
You know and so
You need the data but it doesn't itch
Is pretty static data now when it does change it
Usually catastrophic
Second Sole
You want to know about that so I think there are a lot of
Locations where you can have Edge compute
And devices will kind of do their own software analysis on the edge and if there is that where except
Russian. Ghost
The cloud or starts
To be alerted to people
Independently but yeah I know
I just think that use cases are very
Pacific Ranch Computing make sense
Got it all right
Will Scott thank you so much
For coming on the show today I feel much smarter already and very excited
About 2019
Hey Stacy I really appreciate it
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot, will see you next week