Hey everyone this is the Internet of Things
Podcast
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel and we have an awesome show for you today we're going to be talking about
Matinee
In toys
The dangers of Amazon
Breezy smart sensor Tech
And why Bloomberg
Will have asthma
Even if you don't
Rough going to do some quick news with Google by anxiety
Google predicting
Heart disease for rent
Scans wyzecam updates
Meta-man
The car
And more on self-driving Cars Plus
I got a review of a
Mirror that understands
Who You Are
It gives you
Valuable data
What's our guest this week
Is
Mahler
She is VP of innovation
At Fort Rock and we're going to talk to you about digital identity
How to deal with so many different
Personas
Kids in the Smart Home
And
A unified
Identity management
System for the king
All this and more
Adjustable
And now a message from our sponsor
This week
Ring
Rings mission is to make neighborhoods
Safer
Trey over a million people use the ring video doorbell 2 help
Protect their hosts
Ringo's
Home security begins at the front door but it doesn't end there so now they've extended that same level of security to the rest of your home
The ring floodlight
Just like the doorbell
Floodlight cam is a motion-activated camera and floodlight that connects right to your phone with HD video and 2-way audio
It lets you know the moment anyone steps on your property
Which is a handy feature of these doorbell
I know cuz I tested the ring doorbell I enjoyed
How quickly was how responsive it was
And it was super fun actually to watch my kid when she would leave wave at me
As she walked out the door while I was traveling
So you two can see and speak to visitors and even set an alarm right
I'm your phone and
For our listeners you can save up to $150
Offer ring of security kit when you go to ring.com
/ Stacy
Ring.com
Slash
Stacy
If you're in the market for this
Go check it out
Heaven
Kids are almost too old for this story but I was really excited
To see that Madame a is
Going to get a
Starry
Appearance at
The Toy Fair
You guys
Before Kevin tells you what he thinks
You know me so well
Because toy fair is awesome I went
A couple years ago
And I was
Prepared for like high-tech toys
I was not
Prepared for what toy fair actually is
It is like
Soulmate dolls
Stuffed animal
Very low text at the high-tech stuff was actually pretty relegated to just a few
100 square feet in the Javits
Vengeance
So it was in 2014
So very low tech industry
Trying to get
More high-tech
And they're doing it with matinee
Kevin your thoughts
Well
I mean I think there's there's Merit in some of these things like there's some interesting trivia type games and box games that
Add some smarts
But for the younger crowd I just worried about
They always listening type
Microphone stuff and kids privacy we seen so many connected toys for this has been an issue
Those were smaller companies Amazon
Maybe they were protecting their databases and servers and so on as much as Amazon does but still
I went a little when I hear about
And to be fair these are companies like Mattel and Hasbro building the sin
Using Amazon stuff it I think actually
Amazon as opposed to having them do it themselves
Tell me the smarter move because
I feel like both Hasbro Mattel it had some
Issues were they
I didn't think all this technology
So
And I kind of like the idea of adding
Some of these
Gaming Elliman
It's to the ecobee
Because it is kind of a fun thing
To do with your kids
Like my daughter and I play
Would you rather
And we also play Jeopardy
So some of these things
Especially
Especially like trivia games I think
Would be fine
In this isn't Amazon
First for a coveted toys
Last September
The echo button
Which is like a $20 pair of button
You hit the button
And you're like
It's like a button in trivia so you
You get to go next
Right right they work with certain
Skills Witcher
Game oriented
That's a little more interactivity that less voice but still smart so yeah
I get it there aren't too many of those
What's 16 of those right now
I thought that already
The other thing is they talk about most of these being things like
It will play a soundtrack
I'm sorry it is so lame
I'm not I'm not excited about that but I would like to
Be able to interact
Morphwiz
Amazon
I do think if you wanted to do that though
You would actually want to build like a Persona 4 Madam a
Laker game persona
So
When you were playing with her
That would be great by daughters only child
She'd have more of a
It's more fun as opposed to like
The score
Right right
I thought it was interesting that the
Travel trivia game The Voice Originals When in Rome which is
This morning's choice
It uses voice actors for some of the questions and some effects and such and I think that's great that's a speaker
But then
You know
Maturbation keep track of the scores and provide guidance on rules but
That's a part of the fun of the game just and it's Dino just adding scores up and I'm not having fights with angry sandwich see that score
As opposed to just saying
You know you're winning 7 by 7 points
There's no questions asked at that you know there's no math involved
I guess I was thinking like when you be fun to have a monopoly arbitrator because like I don't know about you
When I play Monopoly with some of my friends it's like all out War
Different rules
House rules in Monopoly
So you can you can definitely see like
An opportunity there but then I got to take up
And then I'm like I don't explain to Madame about like
My family is like oh
You can you can give people instead of paying the back you can give them like
Returns when they land on your property
Wichita
I think my husband and I almost divorced over
Chase book this may not appeal to all our listeners but I would say the best use of a smart speaker pair with a game
What do you have the smart speaker whoever it is
Dungeon master in Dungeons & Dragons
Okay speaking
Dangerous
I could have been somebody either I could have just said
Speaking of matter bag but I
Play next weekend
Traveling it's crazy it makes me the information is reporting that
You should not take money
From
Amazon's Madame a fund
And the reason
Is because
They will screw you over
That's me too long didn't read version of this
They pulled a couple examples
Really the point of the story isn't don't take money from Amazon it's just that all the big
Platforms
Really trying to win
It's a consumer Smart Home
Consumer Hardware
Which means
They don't have time for your
Efforts to build an app
They're going to turn you into a modified hard
Fast as I can
So
Example what are the examples was Amazon
Had made an offer to buy August
Locks
Apparently end
August
Said
No
We don't want that and
Then they were like well okay fine will work with yuan
Amazon
Deprogram but it turned out that Amazon kind of wanted to take
The software experience away from August
August was like no I want to send people to my ass
Because that's what's valuable
Me neither
Usernames I neither
Data other email
That makes sense
Yeah it does and this is the danger in this race in general
Just before the show you drop a good example of
What's the Apple home app
That's the unified experience for a smart home and now I'm kit world
But all the individual apps they're still there and still install if you want them
But the thing is once people go to an easier CMAs
Experience of
Then these companies that sell the products and create the software for it
Who's out of the sufferer experience
Once actually Jason Johnson over in August to the Sea over dog is
I'm about
This sort of like
Commodification
And he was like you know the poor always going to send people to rap to
Things like you have to download the app
Install it to calibrate your
But that's that's not making that customers life
Isaiah Wright
This didn't feel great
This makes sense
The lesson to learn from this is
My God
If you don't have some unique and compelling a pin
I'm with you
A lot of the value of these things is to do not ever have to use the app
I mean I can't tell you how little I use my phone to control my
Back to devices
And that's great for maybe Amazon
Google
Music now but it's not great for
Hello sir tune
Any others
Yeah. I don't use my Wink app
Very much at all even though I have install my watch my phone's Etc
It's all voice
Tell me that
Absolutely
Gel and then the other samples when we were familiar with your other show which is Amazon had invested in nucleus which
Which was making an inner
Cam system using battle
And then they put out the
We had Jonathan Frankel on the show talking about how this
What yeah they can see why I can say it was not just intercom systems video conference type intercom system with a screen a display just
Like the Echo Show now has so
I don't blame him for being upset
Indeed RI
This is not this is
An ongoing
Do you want to be valuable I think you have to Center yourself around Gathering
Useful data from you
Your device
And you don't companies that do that really well
Please like Kenzo
Connected thermometer
Basically
Creating
Epidemiological
So close you guys
Unblock where diseases are spreading
And that kind of stuff is
Really compelling in the other side where I think you could get
Value is
Something like
I hesitate to even say that you love and be
It's really expensive in G he's going to come in and try to do very similar things
But that's something that provides
Value without
The app
But it's just so unique in the market you're like yeah okay
This makes sense
This is why everybody wants to get out of hardware and this is why we're not excited about the Netgear Arlo IPO
Why were concerned about Ring
Raising money at a
Billion dollar valuation
Just us
Realistic by the way
As you just heard ring is a sponsor of the show
In
Obviously does not change your opinion on anything
All right
That's the hard life for Hardware
Let's talk about something
Cool and Future
AC
There's an event this week called the international salad
State circuit
Comforts which is like the nerdiest place in the world
It is awesome
For people who likes
Imparted what team out of this was a bunch of cool new sensors
So when you guys probably heard about was Sony did a low-power CMAs
Ucmas just means
Manufacture a low-power image sensor that does motion detection on the scent
So basically
It's like
Something's moving it doesn't it just needs that sensor
And you don't need to have like
Crazy battery or crazy bandwidth
In Texas caviar
This is interesting cuz it does take
The need for two sensors and turn them into one you don't need a motion sensor to set as well as a camera
This has like a stack
Structure where one piece of it
Can do the detection and it doesn't through each individual pixel on the top sensor
When the pixels detect movement
I kind of think this some of this technology sorter used in phones today with pixel focusing features
It's just a way to make this cheaper and smaller
Inside of device
Exactly that's all you need to like change the game
Cheaper
Smaller lower power
This does the motion detection
At only one point one
Ashton Kutcher
Crazy
Qualcomm has there they have
It's an image sensor that does
Do like 3 to 5 machine learning models
Just the execution of them
But it can do those
Sub to milliwatts
Not this year last year
End
Talk about it okay
So Microsoft also showed off
New time of flight
Sensor
This is actually a type of sensor used in the lighthouse
Camera that we've talked about a little bit
Basically it just gets death
So instead of just seeing a flat picture the computer season
What something is based on
And gets a sense of death
This is
Useful for all kinds of
And
Microsoft
Basically making it
More accurate
Conception because once again
That's the name of the game here
So let's see what else
What else do we see there's a couple things I linked to anytime storage
Talk about this including 200
Meter race
Imaging
Get to Bloomberg
Which wrote this week
Story about how everyone will have
A smart home
Is this story actually disappointed me a little bit because
Is very much focused on the gadget
In
I don't know about you Kevin but
I have so many smart gadgets but I still have a very dumb hole
So I don't really
Appreciate that
Every ship like the idea that guess we're all good except these gadgets to make our lives easier and better but I don't
I totally agree I said this for a while now I've had a lot of smart home devices in my house but that the data is not used
Contextually and together
Home itself has not yet smart
And so
I think we're getting there and I think we're seeing the Growing Pains of that obviously with
These stories like
Don't let Amazon invest in your startup
Bloomberg appreciate you highlighting a lot of relief
They're on the same page as us with basic
What things have to be
Provide additional
Function they can't just be
For no reason
Or for just room
Okay let's
Do the news Rundown
Last week
Google bus idly and Kevin
Has something to say
I had something to write actually I put a blog post up late last week after
For thinking about the whole
Intent to purchase
Google isn't
How to purchase thyroid
You know we talked Stacy you and I talked about the
Google's iot strategy marketing message
Platform save tools a few weeks back
And said
Its competitors
Talamore
Helen cohesive end-to-end story
So the purchases Island
Actually will help Google because I really has a very compelling end-to-end story to talk about why you should connect your products
Why and how you should connect your product how do you create business value save a whole business process Services team
To help people go from prototype
Two incomplete projects
And I don't see that at Google so
Google's going to get that Google's going to get
Zaxby's
Existing customer base of which Lutron is I did not know that fact I took Lutron Just 4 months of working as I wait to get there
Products connected
Which is
Super impressive if you ask me how long does it take Google to do that I can't even name a company that's done that with Google yet
I don't know
I believe there's 45 employees from zyber that will also become
Google says well so I was getting a lot of smarts a lot of
Experienced a lot of business
This process management when it comes to iot
And I think it's a great idea for them to do this a lot of
People wear poo poo in his whole deal with a lot of an adolescent like you understand
The whole story here so that that was my thought
And does Ivory and I have no idea how many people are still there and how much of the original platform is
But when seikaly started out it started out
Basically in mm
So way before it was very forward-looking
In the biggest thing you probably would have
Recognized it was called patchbay
And it did radiation monitoring in Japan
And after the
Big earthquake in the nuclear disaster
Fukushima is at Fukushima that sounds right now they actually had a crowdsourced
Radiation
Pittsfield
Very Google
Fairy Lake
We are Tech
Where is we want to try to change the world we're going to build
Some crazy platform and just have people crowdsourced stuff on it
It just
That's his Heritage so what
Feels like not only do they have a
Telling story but it came from a very Google
That sounds it's a good fit
Okay other news
This elicited 204
Kevin so
Kevin
Yeah that was really really impressed by this is another Google thing and has to do with machine learning where I'm sorry artificial
Intelligence
Google Verity
Which is their health
Osteria they are able to
Take retina scans from eyes
And determine with 70% of the time
Accuracy
If you're going to have a cardiovascular event heart disease issue
And the way they do this is they scanned
Old
Retinas
Look for patterns that isn't there AI
And then check
The results of the AI predictions against
People
Five years later or within five years did have health issues that's how they taught it
And that's actually amazing because
To do that today
The method requires a blood test and so on
It only is
Accurate 72% of the time
So with a i and retinal scanning is almost as accurate as blood test
That's it
That is and
It ties into two things one is
When people are talking about health
Data
I think it's really important
We talked about
Like electronic records
I think I could become increasingly important for
Training
Do you have to have
Both
Potato that you're looking at but you also have to know that diagnose
Gnosis or what have
Listen to the patient
It says you're going to need them or
Picture to get these
That's why we see a lot of x-ray
Kind of AI efforts
Because that's like
Yes
Or that person is having a stroke but some of these other things
School requirements
Longitudinal
A patient over a p
Right
Just related I actually just yesterday joined the Stanford heart
Study program through my Apple watch
So I'm confirming my own
Heart rate data to that program which is the one where they can
Predict if you're going to have health issues or heart issues
All right
Maybe one day we'll see her
I'm gay
This is for me
Why is Cam
So they're launching a second wyze cam I got an email last week saying hey
You got your first wife campuses the $20 camera that we
And apparently a bunch of you guys were really into it cuz a lot of
I don't know if y'all bought one
I really enjoyed mine
Superfine
And
It's like disposable because it twenty bucks it does a lot of good stuff
Second one's coming
And they're getting an ifta integration integration
Coming up which is what they said they would do
Yeah if you have a show for example you be able to say Madam a show my wyzecam excetera new
Stream at 4.
It is and
I'm not sure what day is it
Functionality will provide
So that's what
You don't know what this new one has motion tagging a better sensor
Still the same price
It's crazy
These guys
For Amazon people their whole model is to
To sell something
Barest minimum margins they can it's just sell
We'll see how that works out for
Hey we are commodities
Accepted
Duvin design your product for that reality
All right and do you need
Madam
In your car
I don't
I would just talk to my phone or carplay or Android auto
Your car is still that maybe don't have Bluetooth or USB ports and whatnot so
The Wirecutter said hey if you need madhumeh in your car there's a number of plug-ins at you
You could get
Like 60 bucks or so
They ran through all of them
I think the general take on this was he here they are
They're okay they really need it I don't know
Do they link to
I would imagine they'd have to
Did you have a subscription or
Yeah I know it's you it's is probably it would choose
To the phones again I guess you should just use Google Assistant
You can use your phone
If you have a matinee happening and she's always listening on your phone sometimes do have that built in now so
I don't see the need for an atom but again I have a newer car that has
No carplay and Android auto my choice so
I can just speak to the car
As opposed to plugging in a little
Gadget taking up another spot
If you do have some gadgets
I think you're testing a camera system
I am
Will have more
Reminder Kevin
Homework
Also cars
Alphabet song
Getting a little closer to having a self-driving
How long will it be till we're riding around
I don't think it's going to be too much longer we knew that waymo was testing there
Sweet of
Self-driving cars in the Phoenix area
And what they've done now is they have gotten
Approval
To operate as a TNC in Arizona
Which TNC is a transportation Network company
That allows them to legally charge for rides
So at this point from a legislative standpoint it
It's kind of like they got their ducks in a row there because Arizona is one of the more liberal states when it comes to self driving car testing now.
Okay
These guys to Paisley
Take on the Ubers in the lift some song with us
With WeMo
Self-driving
You can charge money
All right
And now for something totally
I have recently been testing
Bicycle Domingo
Mirror and this is
This is America
This is a mirror that has a 7-inch display in it and you can
Basically
You basically program widgets and all the widgets are pretty
HealthWorks
Weather in
News oriented so it's it's like
Dashboard interior
And I program
Mine with
Yeah I connected it to my Fitbit
You can also connect to an Apple watch
And the deuce things
Are some unlimited that I found lots of things I have the Virgin Wall Street Journal
I want to see the BBC
What's cool about this mirror
Where is wenzhou
You can set a general settings
And then you said
Your own personal
What is it does it takes the information from your
This is only your iPhone for now
But your phone
And it
This is Stacy's phone so I'm going to show her dashboard
Can see Mike my Twitter
And it's nice because it it's personalized
To an extent
You have to get within about
4 feet
You can change the rain gif
If you want to before feet felt
About right
So people didn't
Set it off while they were walking by
And every other time when people walk by
It just shows you
Like the weather
Which also is nice
It reminds me a lot of it first came out
Text information is personalized
But this obviously Idaho health component because of you said you connected
Did your Fitbit so you can get
Your statistics on
Wigs body mass steps and so on and so forth for the day
I love that it's
A multi-user.
Display
Although for the iPhone
I think I'd only works with iPhone as you said
Nobody my house character phone saying to the bathroom which is typically what I would see this
Part of this
So how practical is
First off
Comes in two sizes there's a regular 24
$500
So this is not cheap
And then there's a
32 High by 24 wide which is what
Initially I stuck it in the bath
But that's
I was like I never have my phone
So I was just getting the generic
What's playing
That felt like that
To the hallway
In there
People pass by
That's good
The other Flipside
Is
If you have a child
Again they're not carrying a phone
They don't exist for this
And you know it
It in the hallway
Can see like how many calories I consume
I can't remember if I put that in there they can read my Twitter feed
So there's trade-offs
And the other the final thing is
Do you really need this
Yeah probably
What it is fun
Yeah I mean it when you're away from your phone
You're in the bathroom your brush your teeth, to her whatever it is do you need that if you needed that you probably bring your phone in with you and stay right
Read it while you're doing yourself
But it is nice that's why I
Actually one of my most common bathroom
What's the weather today
So
I think it's kind of like whatever user interface works for you
Senior Lifestyle
And it does I asked if they would ever use
Something like the Fitbit cuz I wear that in the bathroom
They're taking my identity
Turn bluetooth reset that Fitbit has
Security things so they they aren't they may one day do it though for the Apple watch
So Kevin
You
Get Lucky
I have the darndest time
Keeping the sky up
Because I am on
Eero Wi-Fi
It does not that's only 2.4 gigahertz
Band for Wi-Fi and so
It would basically whenever my network was like you should try to fight it
Just drop off the den
It was intermittent and pain
I know you can't see me but I'm shaking my head back and forth
In frustration because so many of these types of devices are
Single bands and the
Do not
They were not designed with Mesh networking
It is very frustrating for you.
Maybe not a whole show but we are tok
About that later
Because this is something I'm spending a lot of time with
Stay tuned for more on that but now
Now you guys
What is take
A listener question the iot podcast listener hotline
Is brought to you
Ashley
Which leg you can have a brand new electronic lock
Installed in minutes with just a screwdriver in your own two hands
And they're easy to setup and use
To see what's possible
Schlage.com
To learn
And if you have a question for the IRS
Podcast listener hotline
Give us a call at 5 1/2
7 4
To 4
And now
This week's
Question
IStation Kevin
Questions /
Is
How in my case with multiple Google home devices in Android device
Don't have an iPhone
Courtesy of work
Not wanting to carry two phones
Really trying
Transition
2 using iPhone with all these other devices
And it's a struggle
Similar to Stacy's
Switch from Alexa
Any tips on
Interacting better
Appreciated
Thanks Kevin
That is an excellent question
Better question for our very own Kevin to answer because he actually lives in a house
Acts like what you're describing
Exactly exactly how use just for reference I'm generalizing a Google pixelbook
For my main computer
I have
Google homes in here various sizes and kinds
I have an Android TV
Which is also Chromecast capable and so I answered in the same boat
And it might be challenging during the transition
Kevin but I don't think it's
Long-term an issue and then here's what I say that
Just about everything I do from a voice standpoint
I'm signed into my Google account so the Google homes work obviously just fine the iPhones not affect
You can install the
Google home app on your iPhone to manage it and so on so that's useful
One trick is to install the Google assistant app for iOS on my iPhone
That will give you a piece lyrics
System capabilities with the easiest way that I found to get to that since you can't make that a default
Listening agent
An iPhone
Is to install the widget on your iPhone
And what that does is
Simple slide over from your home screen and you can just tap the microphone button and then say the hot word for Google
And there you go you have access to
Ashlee Simpson everything from an iPhone
As far as other information I mean I can Chromecast things from
Generally not a problem some apps.
Still supported the most of them do
So it's really not too bad again ice cream from
Play iPad to an Android TV with no problem so
It might seem frustrating because you can't make Google Assistant the primary listening agent on your phone
But you can always do the widget after install the app
I'm going to say yes
Because I do not have an iPhone
What he said
Kevin Spacey
That's why he's on the show
All right
Well
It is that time where we
Have a message from our sponsor and then guest in this week's guest is Eve Mahler
Who is VP of innovation at Fort Rock and we are talking about identity in managing the
Complicated identities for The Internet of Things
There will be children
There will be gdpr and there will be
Stuff about personas
Stay tuned
We are sponsored by iot world
You are invited to iot world the premier event
For iot businesses and Technology
It's May 14th through 17
Santa Clara Convention Center
Silicon Valley
This year iot world is celebrating its fifth anniversary in the show
Come over 12,000 iot professionals 450 speakers and 300 exhibitors and
Start up
Fisher is all about putting
Iot in action building a winning strategy implementing that strategy effectively and driving results
To learn more and register to attend visit iot world event.com
Mahler who is
VP of innovation and emerging technology at
Ford truck
I'm great thanks Daisy
Man I could ask for this
We are going to talk about
Digital ID
It's the new new thing
The new old thing
You think I don't know it's been around for a while but it is getting increasingly complicated which is what we are going to talk about
So
Quick
Talk to me about your background
Thinking about
Digital identity
Absolutely so you know I've actually been doing digital identity and
Access management forano 15 plus years
Used to be about
Web applications and then we entered the API economy
When it was all about mobile applications and getting them to work
And now in the iot economy
Which grew out of the API
Economy
It's more important than ever because we have to worry about
Device identity
And application identities and identities of piles of data
And identities of people all interacting
Each other
Let's
Talk about
This concept of personas
Because this is
This is what I run into
The Internet of Things
I have devices that I a certain people before the internet of things this was even be
An issue which is I have
My sense of self
Like IM Stacy and I am always stays
Actually I'm not always Stacy when I'm
At work versus what I'm hanging out with me
Prince and so
We think about that as personas
Talk to me about the different kind of personas that people can have
And then we'll kind of talk about how we should be thinking about dealing
Yeah indeed
So
There's some advocates in the world of digital identity and gentlemen vendors for example
Google say well you should really have it exactly one identity digital identity that you bring
To every digital service
Every device
PetSmart
We do live our lives presenting different facets of ourselves
Two different
Circles of people and different services
So you know you have a work-life
I found home life and you might not
Sail the same thing
Stall those same circles
In fact it was quite revolutionary when Facebook started
And try to get everybody to present the same face to everybody in there some researchers that kind of proved there was an article about this
Pointing out that researchers proved
That it's maybe not such a good idea to present the same face to everybody in
Maybe even reuse your Facebook login account your identity
To every other server
This is what we call social sign in
Now where you can reuse
A social
Identity provided by Facebook
Forever
At other services
Although it's quite convenient
Pattern to reuse
Your social login elsewhere
Leveraging it
At these other services
Means that you're actually sharing is not just sharing a credential as we just defined it
But you're shining quite a lot of data
That comes with that
With that relying party service
Fraid so yeah but not privacy-preserving so much
So right so it's not just that
Like oh my gosh I want a different
My boss doesn't see me partying on the weekend
But it's also
That maybe I don't want Facebook to have access to like every recipe that I've downloaded using my Facebook identity is
Login for that site or
And their real-world consequences I mean I actually know somebody who was
You know considering taking a job with being considered for a job
Add a health-related company
And when they saw that he like
Posting recipes
Cocktail which is very good at
They actually we're not so interested in
Which is kind of creepy if you think about it
Yes
Especially
Recipes
It's really means
Doesn't prove how much you drink even but if you're over a certain age
Okay
Maybe he shouldn't work
Actually
Shut up
Okay
So there's fat ass
And now let's take it to
The device level
Because
What's nice about Facebook is it is my Facebook
But when I start
Dealing with shared devices like
My car
If I have other people in my household use it or let a friend borrow it
Tickets to devices it gets a little weird
So what does that look like now and how should we start
This is where
We start thinking about
Call identity relationship management
Talked about
That there are no people identities and there are actually
Mobile device identity
You know my phone actually has a unique ID
And they're actually identities
For each of the applications on my phone
And
Your average car has a lot of identities
The car itself has an identity
Each of the sensors
In a connected car
And there's a lot of them
Has a unique identity
And
An owner of a car
Has one identity
Each of the drivers of a car
Cookie money has my identity each of the passengers of the car and when you talk about the scenarios today of
Let's say somebody driving down the highway
And having your average
You know EZ Pass or something like that
Which is connected with a payment instrument so that they can you know easily get charged tolls
Well
Now you've got somebody being surveilled on the highway
Or you have a fleet vehicle and you've got a police officer
Has been assigned a fleet vehicle for their shift
And you have another voice
Are coming onto the next shift
Neither real life scenarios pretty much today
You want to have the right data being generated about them or the right payments flowing about them
For each time that you have
Particular driver
Store owner
Associated with the car
That period of time
And then a disassociation
To happen
At the right time again
So this is why I talked about
Identity
Relationship management
So that there's a bringing together
OD identities
Practical purposes
Angular use cases at the right time
I'm going to disassociate
Okay and we just saw the disassociation
When is failing
International Airport in February
Talking about how right now when
Peopleconnect
Their phones to their rental cars basically all that.
Just stays there
Is no one on your rental car takes it away
Oh my gosh
So that's just an example of
The lack of disassociation
How should that
Happen where does The Purge from the device and the backend servers
Well one of the ways that I think would be
Super powerful to do this is actually and I talked about relationships
Sometimes the best way to think of this is to actually look at
Technology like graph databases
And you know that's actually a very
Powerful
And performant way to manage relations
I'll give an example
Thinking about smart home devices
Let's say you got
Now you're smart dishwasher and you kaieteur smart light bulbs and you got a whole bunch of things made by a bunch of different manufacturers
You might have a part of your home that you rent out
2 something like Airbnb renters
And you got family members
She's got somebody coming to the family cuz they married in something like that
And what you want to do is
What we would call
Constrain delegated Act
Access
To certain parties
Like
Cruising Airbnb renter
Today
And
Kruse family
So those are relationships that could start to sort of creeped out into the world and
Get complicated
What you want to do is share access
To those home associated
Things
Only with
Family members
Only who hasn't been divorced yet maybe and married him
And only with those currently in the Airbnb rental relationship
With me
Those things can expire what you want to do is have them
Actually go along with who's in that fuzzy boundary relationship with you and have them expire naturally
That sounds lovely but how does that happen
Well it can't happen so you know one of the things that I think you and I talked briefly about the past
Is a standard called user managed
Which is based on technology called or which of the standard around authorization of permissioning and consent
And there's actually a growing
Number of standard
Around
Security and consent and privacy
And
Authorization
It comes from
Well the API economy from the old web
World it's actually starting to be more and more applicable
To the iot world
That's quite exciting to me because
It's funny that you know the web world is actually more of a
Mature in this respect
But it's more applicable
Does new world and username to access is actually a standard
That allows you to
Delegate constrained access
Basically any API along lines like this
So that looks like
Is that like what I sign into my nest and I'm like
I'm attaching this device emulator on an app and like
I no longer own this device I'm going to detach
Kit to make this a whole account
It is
Possible to apply to those patterns
It's now I would love to be in a position
Listen to talk to Nest about these patterns cuz what we see now is
You have to implement those patterns
1byone like sulfur example
I downloaded
Kevo app
Because you know might I know some people who have Smart locks on their homes and they
Invited me to get access to their homes and you know this is how we do it
So I think you know one by one
These smart devices
I've had to implement the pattern of sharing access with others
A way to do it
In a Multi-Device multi manufacture environment
Would be to be able to
Add share buttons and add access approval Loops in a more standardized fashion and this would be a way that you
How to do it
Oh so this is like my dream of one app to
Control my home
And then I can just
Deal with it
It enables you to have a kind of a dashboard of who you've allowed access to what
Okay and we kind of Gliding Over this but I think it's an important thing especially
Example with
Your family of divorce in Airbnb
I don't know what happened
But
It's the idea of
Rights that go along with
And so it's not just enough to say Hey you have asked
Cespedes
But we also have to make
Provisions for
Hey you have access to
Despite
I don't actually want you turning my thermostat in the winter up to anything about 70
Because that's just absurd
Or turning off the entire interface of the Smart Lock so that I can't see
You know who's coming to my door even if I'm out of town
Yes
So how do we are there Provisions for managing
Access
Right now I feel like
Probably half
Access my devices
Do consider
And then the other half
Durka durka
Can do it and some of them don't even let anyone else
It's only
One app
Right well it's all as it starts with a matter of what
Granularity does the API
You want to start with you know some good granularity there be
Because apis are about making money now and it's sort of
The host of the API gets
First right of refusal on what Granite has and you want
Those to be respectful of what the buyer of advice can do but at that point it starts to get really into
Especially
I know you've been talking about
General data protection regulation
In your podcast
And in your newsletter
And this is where it gets
Kind of exciting for people who are in the position to buy devices because
They're starting to have more rights
And
Framework for how they can get more rides and we're granularity is basically coming for those who either are EU citizens
Indoor travel to the EU and a services
And you know services in front of devices are going to need to start respecting
Yes if you buy devices from
People who are based in the EU guys
This could come to you soon
Yes
Okay so what does
So I've been mentioning you have access Uma
And a fact of the folks who work on the samba standard on the cheap Amana Therrien
We've started to develop a legal framework
Where you could actually
Start to have
Kind of standard contracts and even licensing Frameworks
How you roll out your terms and conditions and how people can set up
Policies
Around what they share with others
And it could even extend to well if you want to make available data
Coming off the devices
To Let's a marketing company
Then that should be possible
With a kind of privacy preserving bent
And let's go into one of my favorite favorite topic
Switches
Kids and I
Because
I have kids
And my child is 11 which means in the US she is governed by
Copa
Which state
Child online privacy protection act
And basically
Companies can't collect data
Which right now in my smartphone
Come means that she's like
Yeah
Difficult doesn't it
She can't get her voice recognized by things she can't there's a lot she can't do
Can I get why this is there but let's talk about
Identities I guess you
Parent-child
Queso
I feel like I have no identity
It's just
Stacy who controls
Rosanna's account
Yasso
Yeah in a lot of the laws in oh this is where I talked about you know this is
Especially sensitive data and gdpr has a whole set
Section for it and a really odd thing is
Under capitalized
That the age of majority is 13 under gdpr
It's largely 16 +
Four different kinds of data
You find it on every state in the Union you'll find slightly different laws about which kinds of data there's different age
Actually even more
NetSpend
So imagine that there's different kind of
Clinical devices
Is farina generating
Different kinds of
Miti Behavioral Health Data
Or you know pregnancy
Testator for example
And you know not to scare you
Age 11
Hopefully way too young
But there's no different ages of consent in ages of majority for all these different kinds of data and you know every state and every
Jurisdiction has a different ages in his nuts
So
Can I see a wrinkle in there
I'm going to make it even more
There's also like
F13
I'll child protection under like Google for exam
Apple for a while
What's 0 / 13
No parent protection
What you doing
Want necessarily kind of ignores the fact that I want my kid to have access to something
Then they can
Get further access
Okay so that's my
You did what kind of a sliding scale if you're to be a responsible parent and yet it
Brightline is for the easiest so maybe some of these things words
Different age of majority for different things is more reasonable
Because it kind of admit
Set a responsible parent wants to have a role in their child's life
For certain things
So
I do only what you want to have
Is
An ocean of some
Management
Over
What a child can do
In a
Responsible
So
Typically what you would want to do in the view of digital identity Solutions is an ocean of
Accounts
And this
Shouldn't be I mean that the solutions that you been
I think we're just know they're not
Taking advantage of as possible
So here is what we typically see
In my world
It's the notion of
A full identity account
For a parent or Guardian so you know in law and might be somebody's not a parent but a guardian
Cancer kind of the proxy
Freedom child
And that
Full account
Would be able to for example set up the account
A person could set up the account on their own so let's say it's
You know Alice that's pickle
In my world is Alice and Bob and Alice wood
Set up an account on her own should have a process where she
Proves that she's a beige
The permissions on the account would be.
She can do lots and lots of things
The schema governing the information
That's stored associated with the account
Would be very full with lots of
Information so that
It's not blinding certain things it's not disallowing certain information from being stored
And then
You would be able to
Set up
Alice would be able to
On behalf
Of her child little Susie or even younger Johnny knows maybe two years old and can't operate any devices or
Or services
And little Johnny would have
A managed
And a managed account is very constrained and what it can do
It has a limited schema with a very simple set of data
That would adhere to you know that the applicable laws and the jurisdiction and it had very limited permission
Effectively be
Change
To Mom analysis
Now what are the things that you can
Excitingly
You do with the notion of identity relationship management is
Reflect
The fact that they
I have a parent or guardian and child
Relationship
And if you know Little Johnny's age
You know when he times in
To certain ages of majority
And start to give him full rights
Under
The jurisdiction
Kinds of data
You can start to collect more data
And you can start to be able to build
Amore Digital Life for
With the with the notion of a digital twin if you will
And then the
The eventual idea
OBD2
Transfer the account
I'm kind of like co-signing on a
Car loan goes on your credit report with
Your parents with you and then eventually be
Becomes part of yours and you
You go off into the world
Exactly it's sort of like he starts with a thin file in credit language and then he starts
How to build more of a file as he reaches age of majority
For certain kinds of data
And it feels like the Enterprise has
How to unlock more
How are we going to see this coming to the consumer World anytime soon cuz it feels like we're years behind him
Desperately
Better
Options here
You know I think so I mean this is where
Consumer scale I almost done with a consumer it's just there's a Sturm Scion with stance
Customer consumer Inc
Were there we've been there actually for a while
Has certain properties
Scale
And
Performance
That requires
Over and above
Employee I am world
And house for a while now so it different is
In quality and quantity
From what we had to do for the employee or the greater employee population
For a long time now
Employees and partners
Of the Enterprise
Because you know a lot of those
Big companies have or even small companies will have
1000000 or 10 million
Or a hundred million
Customers or end-users
And when it comes to devices
That they might use will you know
Multiply it by
Another 10 factor or a hundred factor or if you start looking for sensors
And I'll keep multiplying
I don't have to be in a relationship again just keep multiplying
Bright but I wanted
Call my relationship
Things in this case not have
Company and that's there's no real framework right now
Does that
I mean we are seeing
That
Not only the standards that I was mentioning
Do account for that
But I mean
This framework is very real for what I see everyday
What we do everyday
And this is where
Particularly that graph database
Slayer
Does
Managed
Tackle
Performance needs of you know what an individual person has to
Deal with any one individual person I mean how many if you imagine that you're sitting policies
For who I want to share with
You know Our Brands tend to explode if we
We have to jump higher than
527 anything's at one time
So I think that that that notion is probably pretty well accounted for but the Frameworks of the kind of Technology
They were talking about I think
I think it exists
It's stuff that can be done
So then the question is
You need a business model
This because yeah
So
I think about my digital identity who would I trust
A
To have all of
In feet what I pay for it
And how am I going to pay for it out of pocket cuz right now I pay for it like
You know a lot of people trust apple and they have a lot of
Digital identity associate
And they pay for it
Face painting
Exorbitant
Devices
So you see like a breakthrough possibly happening there especially as we have so many more things
So you're asking a question you know how many digital identities should we
And
It's so tough being so I use a password manager so I can certify
Count how many logins I have and it's not pretty
Who have hundred
And you know the average person to do any studies an average person has in Odessa
A dozen
Or several.
They're lying there totally lying I'm really counting them up and you know I do think more people are using password managers for the
Still in that going to probably
Low
Doesn't
Percent something like that
Did the right answer isn't one
We're talking about persona
The right answer isn't one because
Then
Song
Identity provider node
Everything about
And there's
There's a theory now about self
Sovereign identity
That you're going to somehow hold all the information about you on let's say a mobile app
On your client device and then somehow you'll hold out by Disney information about you
And you'll be in entire control
And the reason I don't think
At the end of the day that's
Harley viable is that
Anybody who needs
No information about YouTube get Services going and have you know offer you into
Sting services
They need some of that information Vital Information about you to be
Asserted by third-party
Like there's not going to trust you to say well I'm a citizen of
Country
They're going to rely on
Next country to say who you we are citizen of
So it's got almost a lot of things
To come from third-party so those third parties count as
Multiple sources
So
It's a multifarious problem
So between all of us has multiple sources does that mean we're still stuck with
That many logins
Zoe's
But I think
Here's where I think that we might
Be able to consolidate I'll give you a little olive branch of hope we may not be able to consolidate source
Identity
But I think ultimately someday
Maybe someday soon
We can consolidate
To a short list
Baby County
You know one hand
Of
Places where we can manage
Our preferences for
Could we share with
So you know any user managed access Lan we would call that an authorization server you know
Maybe the dashboard the privacy.
Because
Ultimately
What preference is we
What
Authorization policy we have what privacy settings we have
Our only source for that should be us
Like if your preference is smoking or non-smoking or
Aisle vs. window
Can you trust anybody else for that other than yourself
Like I've trained my husband
He knows that I get the Isle
Exactly it's I mean you can store it someplace else
But it has to be self-assertive
Well this is
Again
That's a small Olive
French meadow cafe
And
I will also thank you for
For coming on the show
It was a delight
Thank you that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot cam will see you next week