Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And today we have a special co-host
Richard Gunther
That's right we got Richard Gunther here from the digital media Zone
He does an awesome podcast especially if you like lighting
Call Dad home
Richard is my go-to guy
I am a bit lighting obsessed
He is
That's okay I am too so for all of you guys were like Stacy stop talking about lighting
This may not be your show
We do have an awesome show for you we're going to talk about the Bricker but
Ikeyless lights again
Because we found some information about their security
A bit of Microsoft Sopris project
A new hub
From Sbarro
New mesh Network
From tp-link
Some other odds and ends of news and
Matinee
And how to use it to change
Your lighting
I also have an install to talk about
We did the Google
The Google home vs Echo swap in my house and I'll tell you how that went
Richard has a smart blinds installation
You guys are going to want to hear cuz I know you love this stuff
Our Guest this week
Kevin Ashton
Who coined the phrase internet of things and he tells us all about that
And what he thinks about it today
Celtics
Let's go to a quick message from our sponsor
Got a great idea for an iot business Samsung artik interoperable in
Secure iot platform it lets you focus on building your business rather than worrying about technology
Integrated Hardware cloud and services interoperability with other device service cloud and systems
Charity Samsung artik coyote gets down to business for more information visit Arctic
Dot IO and that's a r t i k.
Alright let's kick off this show
Let's talk about
Bricked devices
Because we actually had
A couple weeks ago we talked about
Somebody had developed
A virus basically that went around shutting off
Active devices this was theoretical at the time
Thanks to people
It's called
What is this is
It goes through and it finds things that have the Mirai botnet in them
Or are accessible
By the Mirai botnet
Because it's got a hard-coded password and
Deportes breaks the device
Which is crummy if you own this device and suddenly it's
Not working but it's also kind of like
Vigilante justice on the internet of things trying to keep the bride button
Shutdown
I don't know
How do you spell
Yeah this is really really weird and the thing that's interesting here is am I correct in understanding that this was.
Discovered basically by setting up
A Honeypot
To try and find stuff like this
What is
I think it's nice in the sense that
It's going to really Force manufacturers
Is there consumers
What the heck is happening here and they're going to call their company in the company's going to be like oh crap we should have spent money on security
But I got to admit if my router
Well right and so that's what I'm really wondering about is as consumer and you know that's what I focus mostly on
My show
If I'm a consumer and I have
How does this impact me
Is it just that my router shut down
What is
My indicator that I have this problem and I need to do something about it
It breaks your device so
You will know because your device will
It flushes all iptables
And all the network
And then it adds its own rule to drop all out
It tries to wipe all the codons
So that's a pretty like there's not really
Way to come back
Do we know what devices are impacted by this
It is devices that are attractive to the Mirai botnet so they're running Linux
Those that are running the BusyBox toolkit
And it
Apparently according to the register has a particular affinity for Ubiquiti Networks
Yeah I saw that cuz I run Ubiquiti
Here's the solution guy so to block the attack
You have to disable telnet
Which many people tell you to do
You already
Change the devices factory set
Also something that you should be doing already
And
The company that discovered this radwear also recommends using intrusion prevention systems to lock down device
Coincidentally
Pappadeaux's
I will say though if you are running
Infected device or device it's likely to be affected
You should be doing taking those steps anyway because it's highly likely that it will get infected by the ride.
Anyhow so
Yeah yeah
Messi
Messi Messi
But we have good security News 2
We do two weeks ago
For the two weeks or last week
I think was the last week you guys were talking about the Ikea Troy tree lighting
Exactly is is that how you say it
Cuz I've been
You have just
Proven your worth
Right there
So we wondered
Gosh is Ikea doing this right or they just opening up a giant
Security hole ever
An answer is
I can't do this right
Yeah so it looks like from some independent research
Into the platform
Some really in-depth
Analysis
Diarias in
The Hub itself
And in the communications
And the bottom line here was that says it seems like one
One of the most
Secure iot style devices
I've looked at
A quote
Doubt
He does mention one
Potential problem
And that's that
At the time of initiation the hub goes out and
Things at Ikea server and says hey
Let me know if there are any updates I should get
And it gets the response back in
Clear http which is probably not a good thing
And that's something that they could
Clearly fix at some point in time
But he also indicated that really the only way of hacking this thing
Is if you had physical access to it
Right in the reason is because there's no remote
DIYs
Which also means
It looks like this might not work with other device
Yeah
That's the downside so it's
Highly secure
In part because
It doesn't talk to any
Which is a good way to say
It is a medium hope I hope they're able to get beyond that at some point
Because I'm very excited about this platform
We talked about this a little bit on
Our next episode of home on and I've been
Eagerly awaiting what Ikea is going to be doing because
Stacy I think Ikea has the recipe to sell this stuff right in retail they know how to do it
Experiential storytelling in retail
I totally agree with you it actually
I've been in touch with Ikea and they should be on the show Suits
We can find out
A lot more
Yay
Security
This is going to get a little deep you guys but you should know about it because
Security is
Animal
Microsoft introduced last week
A project called project Sopris in what does is basically a way to bring security
Two microcontrollers which are the tiny little computers that run a lot of
You're connected to
Spices so
Tiny kind of dumb processors are
What these are
And
There's a million different flavors
It's not like the Intel
Kind of world where there's one flavor
There's pee more now
But what they done is it put out this research paper
And they basically came up with seven concepts for security
And put it on
Afford a development boards that they're giving to hackers
Later this month in May
So they're getting hackers in May
Try to get them to test it and play with it
So here are the seven things
That you need to have
In Microsoft
Worldview-2
Make a secure system
You have to have a hardware-based Reta Trust
Small trusted computing
We're stuck in a loop
Do you have to have defense in depth
Basically that means is the device still protected if the security of one layer
Device
Is breached
Clark
Compartmentalization
And so that means does a failure and one component at the device require a reboot of the entire device to return to operation
They don't want that
Certificate-based Authentication
That's what
Renewable security which means the devices software can be updated automatically
And then failure report
Does the device report failures to its
I'm actually surprised when
I sometimes test devices and there's no failure
Reporting and I'm like really
Music
So these are the seven properties
I look at this and I actually talked to his some security researchers and some people in the industry
And they look at this actually this is a really good frame
My concern is
That Microsoft is pulling all of this in
And there
Already chip vendors who are trying to
Create this type of platform or some elements of this platform
On
Their chips so
Nxp has sicurella
Which is a designer
Facturar
What is that mean for those guys is basically what
Microsoft's kind of
Perspective seems to be
Or basic
Well I mean this is what Microsoft does best right they come out with some really great
Approaches and
Frameworks
And they're usually late to the game
Awesome experience
Right exactly
So
Who knows who knows if
This is going to get adopted I mean I'm wondering if Microsoft is doing this
In some way
As a way of saying look this is what we're going to expect
Run
Windows for iot
On NE
Device
We expect this
Level of security
And maybe that's where they're going to cut
Draw the line
I don't know how they would do that exactly
Is it could do that programmatically or if it would have to be something that they in a case-by-case basis
It's interesting
Frank Lee work companies need to be thinking about this yes I'm super glad it looks like the elements
Exactly right
And it feels like because of its a lot of the industrial internet so the Enterprise players and Industrial internet come
Please turn to Microsoft azure
Another cloud
Compute
And storage for their iot stuff
And they do it because they Trust
Microsoft to actually
Provide slang
Their it departments are like yeah
Microsoft
So
That level having
Having influence at Fortune 500
Tundra companies
Feels like this could be a good way
Get adopted maybe not in the smart home but definitely across connected devices
Enterprise
So
We'll see
All right
I know
A new hub.
You know what this is
This doesn't seem too though so fibaro has been talkin
For quite a long time now
About
Version of there
Home Center
Sbarro is a company that
Primarily does business in
European countries
And they are now bringing
A light version of
They're Z-Wave based hub
The US
And this is good news this is a really good product
From what I've
Racine
It has
Significant
Capabilities very granular
Programming capabilities energy monitoring
All the good stuff
That you want in a high-end helping this is a high-end
This is a $279 product this is not
Something that you're going to buy at your Lowe's for $60
There you go
And the other thing that
I love about
Sbarro
And I think you know we've talked about this I think tomorrow has
Some of the best
Physical industrial design for products out there if you're looking for products that are going to look cool and home
Dyson small and 9
Trusova
Particularly for security type products
They have a really good selection
Products available
And I'm excited to see this finally happening they say they're shipping
It's also going to be compatible
With systems like
Sonos and Logitech
Russound and Phillips restaurant surprised about you don't see a lot of folks integrating with that that's
A bit higher in but
Remember this
Origins of
Sbarro's Friday
In many cases are in
Irn installations
And they're planning Amazon Echo integration to so good stuff
Yeah oh and you can control 230 devices
Which is
That is a lot actually and I don't think even I have
230 devices
Now my echo 230 devices but that's cuz it counts everything multiple times for some reason
You may have multiple
Every time I read
Discover things
Discovery
So
That is
Quickfundusa
There's a new mesh router
From tp-link
It is The Deco M5
Mesh router
What are we calling these are these the new mesh router of the week
I don't know
We don't have a name but we do talk about him a lot so
The router will settle for $299
And I supposed to cover between 2400 and 4500 square feet
Individual units are going to be
So that's cheaper than Eero
It is
Right in line with Google Wi-Fi and
And actually I have not tried this to have you tried the velop system from Linksys cuz that is there mesh wife
They have I have not
But now they have
Yeah no I have not
And yeah I'm glad to see companies get into this Mike Wolfe and I were talking about a year-and-a-half ago about how it's
Wi-Fi routers were just kind of becoming commoditized
Really glad to see companies
Coming out with
Innovative
New Solutions in adopting this newer
Mesh technology since I adopted mesh
In my home
Granted I mentioned I'm using Ubiquiti
So it's a bit of a more industrial solution
I don't have the problems that I used to have
These things
Do work these things do solve
The coverage issues that most folks
Particularly with iot devices
Around the fringes of their home
Typically complain about
Industrial designer this tp-link is a little weird I don't know if you can see the picture Richard bit
It's beastly
Round circle pucks but then they've got like this
Triangle sticking out
Kind of
Of the side looks like
And you're like half
Pulling out
Piece of the pie
Is she had her you know I was joking on Twitter earlier this week that
I think it's a bit ridiculous that all of these products are designed as if you're going to put them out on your coffee table or something
In all likelihood this is going to be shoved in a corner but every company is trying to come up with
Something that looks
Unique and special and makes it something that you might want to put out for
Visibility
Of course
Any cords you have for power or
And ethernet backhaul on any of these things you're not really
Why do that
Here's my brilliant startup idea anyone can have this
Okay so Kleenex boxes
Have covers and if you're not a girl you may not know this
But they have these fancy covers that you can buy the stick over your Kleenex box
So
You don't have the app
What we need
Is that it
RF permeable
Netease 3D printed custom
Router cover
And that it could be pretty
All right I just don't want it to be knitted and have it look like a chicken or something like that I have
Okay
Ring added
An unlimited device plan because it
It has so many devices
Ring has been
Coming out with more and more products with cameras on them
Are intended to secure the perimeter of your home
And more cameras
Then the more you end up paying in
Video plans
To store and access
All of the videos that they're recording
So
At $3 a pop that can get pretty expensive if you have a bunch of these things around the house where
Expecting that there going to be coming out with the floodlight soon
That's also going to have a camera on it
So they've introduced a plan in advance
Of that product release
That is a universal or unlimited cameras plan
Edis called ring protect
Four ring
For $10 a month
You can get
Any number of cameras
All in the same plan
And you can also pay $100 a year
If you want to pay that way
And if you have any more than three devices
Your
Definitely going to be saving some money I think this is a great thing
I'm expecting to get the ring
Flood light when it comes out
And so that's going to put me over the edge
I'm definitely going to be getting
Wow so
That is good news for ring because it means that hopefully people like you
Are buying
More than three devices
+ 3
So good for them
I don't know
I don't like the looks of it
It's a little bit
Chunky to put on the side of the house
Okay.
But so with a battery
How often do you recharge
So I
End up recharging about
Every two months I would say
Batteries get a workout
Because the one camera that I have is on
The side of the house where I let the dogs out
And
I'm doing that
Pretty regularly
So I'm pretty happy with that I don't really have a problem with
Pulling it down
The camera is made with a nice clip that it's easy to pull down
Just stick it on USB and charge it up for the day
Oh okay
So yeah I was I was wondering
I did the Arlo cameras in when I tested those
I put one like way up in a tree and I needed a
A ladder to get to it and then the battery died
This was dumb very dumb
Well see what you need there is a kid who likes
To climb trees
This is news that is tailor-made for you mister lighting
So we have some news about
The Amazon Echo
It has a new capability
And we have some new light bulbs that will work
With the Amazon Echo
So the new capabilities you can tell the echo
To turn
Tp-link +
Lifx light bulbs
To turn to a specific color
So yeah
Madame a turn bedroom lights
And that will happen
And that's really cool
Is Google home
That already so this kind of brings it to
Feature parity
And then
Tp-link Kasa
Are these new bulbs
I believe that the
Color changing
Bald is new but I'm not sure about the other ones I know that
They were showing
At CES this year
So I'm not sure if this is the introduction of those for real
Or if they already had them
Okay tp-link basically also said hey
You can change your colors
And are tunable white lights
With the echo
Which might be the same it is a skill
So
It's all part of that smart home skills so it's
Well it's a skill
It's built into the smart home section
Of
The app where you would configure this stuff
This is really good I'm glad to see that
Added color control this has been missing particularly if you have white tunable
You didn't have the ability
To address those and if you have
Then
You really care about the color of
Pure white light
So having this ability is going to be important
To you and then for the color tunables
You always had to revert to
Whatever app you
Control these things
If you wanted to change the color like if you had
Hue bulbs around so
This is a really good
New capability
I'm curious how this is getting rolled out though because I tried it and I think you said you tried it to and it isn't working
Fortis yet
It isn't
That doesn't mean I'm I'm sitting here looking in my Google Play Store to see
Have I updated the app recently so
I don't know
But I don't have it yet I will test it out for next week I'm excited about it because you know even things like make the lights warmer
Make the lights cooler
Will be
I think nice
Cuz I am absolutely
So
It's install time you guys were going to talk about our life in the Smart Home
Mine
Is last week I promised you that I would switch my Google home
And my echo
Downstairs in the living room of my house
Our kitchen is where
Elizabeth
It's open
And
I didn't actually do a full swap
Because the Google home is still a little iffy
So they're both kind of sitting there hanging out but we did use the Google home
And
Here's a couple things I can repay
When it comes to doing the smart home stuff
Google home is not quite
I had hooked it up to my Logitech Harmony
That plus the wink integration gave me everything I needed to control all the devices that the echo
Can we talk to the echo
So it downstairs
Buy the Google home was fine with the harmony
To do a couple things
What's 1
It wouldn't reliably play music
I'm not sure
What was going on but we would ask it to play
Play Beyonce
And it was
Play Beyonce on Spotify
I'm sorry
There's been a problem
And I even asked at one point I was like what's the problem or what's wrong
It was like
Sometimes I'm a bit buggy
Like immediately after ask
Google home I would ask the Echo and the echo
And this is very intermittent
It just
You never knew when it was going to work or not work
Which is
Video killer for my daughter who loves listening to music
So that was one the other thing is probably just me but it's super weird
I have this crazy integration
With my
Lutron lights
They go to the Lutron hub
To SmartThings
And then through that too
Google home
I have two lights my dining room and my kitchen
Google home will turn on and off my dining room
But when I ask it to turn on or off my kitchen lights
It says it's doing it
And then nothing
Which I think is super weird
Yeah
No
You have these lights hooked up to
Other
System tray these are your Lutron light so
Are integrated with
D
Echo.and
With
What these Logitech as well
No they're not integrated with the Logitech
To homekit
Set up
Okay
The echo
Into smart thing
And are you able to control those lights okay from
Those systems
Yes
I did my favorite thing to do when my Integrations don't work
Which is pull everything out
So I pulled the
The Lutron to SmartThings integration I broke that and then I
Pull the
Google home and
The SmartThings integration
I broke that
Thinking maybe that would solve
But it hasn't solved it
So
If anyone has any ideas
Gilfre Richard
Yeah I mean something
That I would try is
To set them up temporarily so that they're all in the same room
And then see if
Your Google home is able to control them if you tell it to turn all the lights on in that room
Okay I'm going to do it
And that actually brings me
To another thing
The frustrated me about
Google home
When you put it in like lights and stuff
It asks you what room you want them
And so I put it in the appropriate room
Psychiatry
My various my for living room lights are all in the living
But
I want to be able to say
Haji turn off downstairs
It right now
I can't actually
I can't group the grouping
Into another group
So
In the Echo you can actually
Sayo I want to create a living room
Setting
And then I want to also keep
These lights in also it downstairs setting
And you can do that but in Google home you can't have
One device at 2
Rims
Yeah that's
Seems like it's something that they're going to have to fix it was funny
The echo gives you the ability to
Group things anyway you want to
But doesn't have the ability to know
What room anything is in
And then Google home
Knows what room things are in but doesn't give you any other group incapability
Is there must be a happy medium somewhere
There will be I have total faith
So
My verdict so far is
Is the Google home can't live on its own right now downstairs
And it's awesome
For talking to for asking
Questions of
But it's still not quite there in the
This is terrible so Kevin was out sick today
I'm trying to convince Kevin that he needs a Google home
And he's not sold yet so I don't think this is going to make him
Rush out and buy one
Maybe not
So you have an integration
And it's actually a really good one
It's over not integration and installation
I'm really excited about this so I have been looking for a way to automate blinds
Blinds throughout the house
And
I have a Southern Exposure
Part of the home and
So I get quite a bit of
Sunlight
And I want to be able to block that out at
Times of the day
So
Most of the products that are out there are there
Very pricey
Or
Still
Crowdfunding
And when I was at CES I ran across this company called mysmartblinds
And mysmartblinds creates
A $99
That you can install in nearly any
2 in or
Wider blinds
Installation
In the top rail
And it comes with a bunch of adapters to fit it to different manufacturers in mine wasn't one of the listed manufacturers but it were
Worked anyway
Too much
Weider
Is that right blind slats or is that the headspace
Yeah that's the blind slat so if you buy a
2 inch blind that's a pretty
Typical wooden blind nowadays
It's not going to work with mini blinds
So if you have something that's like really really thin
But with the wider wood blinds or wider vinyl blinds metal blinds it'll work with those
And
You just installed at the top
Rail
Comes charged but
You could charge it again through USB if you wanted to
Charger supposed to last for a proxy
Smitley
Six months to a year I think they said so will
See how that goes
And all it does is eclipse blind
It's not trying to raise or lower
It's just flipping the blinds either open or closed
In
Quarter
Anchorman
Not all the way from clothes to open but close to Parkway open and then open
And then
Parkway open and then closed again the other way
And I am really impressed it took less than maybe 20-25 minutes to install the Kit
Chainsaw the blind
Hooked it up to the app
It works through Bluetooth
It works on
IOS
An Android
And having hooked to Bluetooth
On
One device
All my other devices were able to know and control it
So there is some
Cloud stuff going on there to make all that work
The only thing that I have a problem with
Right now
Is the because it's Bluetooth
The range is kind of limited
That's my beef against Bluetooth lights
I like I want to go downstairs and turn off the light
Junction is a smaller house
Yeah that
Yeah yeah well
Someday
Maybe we'll actually get Bluetooth
Toothbrush for reals
In the meantime
What you can do
Is you can set schedules
And it is also aware of where the sun would be
Where you're located at different times of the day
So you can
Basically say at a certain time of day but
Dependent based on what time of year it is and where I am
Then close the blinds and those schedules
Live locally on the device
So it will still work on its own without any sort of controller nearby which is a great thing
They also sell a
Just a little
Remote that is Bluetooth and
You can install that just like you would install a light switch
They have
Solar charger
That you can install on the outside if you want to use that
I am really impressed
With
This kit how easy it is to use
And
I don't understand why I can't buy this in every single Lowe's
And Home Depot around
But you can get it on Amazon
Awesome and it's $99 in actually how wide
How does it deal with the with the
The Blind Side
It's just a thing you stick on the slats right
It's not like I'm 12
I mean if you stick it in the top rail you're basically putting this mechanism in the top rail
Turn the little mechanism inside that top rail
The adjuster
The
Slat angle
So you don't see this at all
End
The wave that
It works
Is
Then by
Turning the crank inside
Then
Your blinds turn and it doesn't matter if you have 2 inch blinds or if you have 4 inch blinds if there is such a thing
Lake Ozark banks
Awesome
Well this is a good
Like the sounds like a good product I'm excited to thank you for sharing that will put a link in the show notes forever
Richard thank you so much for coming on the show today I will confess we did this twice because
Because troubles
Kevin is out sick this week but he'll be back next week
Hopefully
Fingers crossed
Once again thank you Richard for stepping up
Guys stay tuned because after this I've got Kevin Ashton
Who is the guy who created the phrase internet of things
Talking about how that happened
And going forward
Why he's so optimistic
About
What we're doing here with iot
So stay tuned
We would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and today
Is Kevin Ashton who is the credited creator of the phrase
Internet of Things
And the author of how to fly a horse
The secret history of creation invention and discovery
Which is a really good book
So hi Kevin how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm good how are you
I am super great
So in case my editing skills don't work out as well
Kevin and I are in Austin where it is thunderstorming and we both have dogs that don't like thunder
So they stray
Whining / barking you here
If you hear it
All right
Canon
Let's kick off with
Creating the
Which is a big statement it's like inventing the internet
What did you really do
Well
I was an assistant brand manager
Procter & Gamble with and
I just launched
The new range
Charles Kylie Cosmetics on makeup
This was this was kind of my suspect product launch in my career and ice packs
I defecate frustrated when I went
My local grocery store to get my weekly groceries
And
Noticed
My most popular products with no.
Michelle
You hear a lot of fantasy
He talked about marketing
The most basic thing is if people can't buy your product
It's about trying to sell
I started a
It was
You're horribly out of stock
Protect me the most was
People this was in
Did you say 1996 or 99
So this was in 1998 and so people understand this is before smartphones
Etnyre
Pause Spotify
Yes
It's funny for those of us who are old enough to remember what life was like in 1998 it's kind of funny it's almost like
Black and white world
End of 1994 beginning of 1995 and
Most people have not heard of it until then
Yes I was still using a dial-up modem
And I have got my first
Email address
The way you access the internet
Computer
Dakota motor
But you're plugging joke
Computer plug that box into your phone line which are the required a splitter on the phone line
On your phone line
Your phone line was that busy to everybody else
If you had cool waiting you had a problem because the cool waiting
Guitar with mess up your internet connection
You would get online and what could you do online
A lot of what you could do was
Bulletin board
Your wife
2 minutes for a picture to
Wireless internet that was years away
Really want the internet
Like in the
Mid-to-late 1990s
Say yes with that context
That is actually relevant
Because the other Solutions this out-of-stock problem turned out
2B information
The really big thing but I should have discovered
That was not the only person
Was that
Are computers needed to start Gathering date
Is that all the information
It was human and two data are ugly
Until really I mean I guess
Nike rally 1990
You started to see the beginning of
Automatic data capture
The UPC barcode
Is the most visible example
Of a technology that was trying to
Start
Tonight
How date was entered into
Chicken Tortas
It's interesting to Crothers because
For a lot of people who use computers in the 20th century so that we people who
Probably in the forties or older
Now the idea of human in today Taurus is so
So much the natural paradigm
Computing
But it doesn't seem
Orange
Not sure if you were born in 20
First century
You're very very used to your computer gathering at 7 a.m.
Pencilmation
But the one I realized was looking
Out-of-stock problem
Was caused by the fact that
Stores
Had moved to more
Computerized Information Systems
Fidelity information they had was being hinted at the checkout counter and in a few
Stop code scanner in the warehouse a few other places and not men
Very detailed real-time like is a particular color of a particular lipstick
On the Shelf in a particular store
Was
Riddled with inaccuracies and errors to the point where it was kind of useless
The stores had sort of a big picture of you
But at that the grill detailed level
But she went into Data was
Was too limited to really be precise about what was happening
In a retail supply chain and then it turned out
Zygote into this mall through instead of 1998-1999
Any office supply chain
The way you live in this world a physical thing
Everybody was very enamored with what was called the information revolution in the 1990s
The information we really needed was about these these physical
Cata how can you order tonight
The capture of dates were about stoplight
Little lipsticks on shelves so I need any other thing in the world
At that time there was
Emerging technology called RFID radio-frequency
Z Nation
It started to look too
Tumi light
This Mason RFID technology
Could potentially be embedded and sings like lipstick Packaging
As a way to know what the
Shell
But the other piece of artwork
Which was
Kind of a berry
Niche technology in
In the 1990s and the reason was
It was much more useful
If you could connect it to the network
Because now I'm the the lipstick is on the shell to keep it. Example
Meticulous
If that date was being shed on Broadway
And so
The emergency
Public internet at about the same time as the beginning
Specialization of RFID
Was I buried
Technology-wise because what we've LED Subs
What was
But not in great detail inside 1999
Was it connecting sensors
Like RFID tags
To the internet
Gooseberry powder
Because suddenly
Gather information automatically in one place and know it in real time and some other place so you can
You can gather information all over the place and not real time in one place
This idea of connecting
Consensus to the internet
Soda
Machines to gather their own
Information
Was
A really revolutionary paradigm
Time shifting computer
The only person he was thinking that way
But I do remember it was very hard
Define other
The people
It was thinking that way
I say we get to 1999 and I have
Crystallize this concept in my mind
That Proctor needs to lead a kind of a worldwide effort
Initially chips but then all the senses
Insane
Unconnect
To the internet
So we can have this
Incredible new visibility into what's going on in the world
Senior manager
Instead of 5 minutes or less
Icicle
Because
You know you had people who were very busy
Who didn't know if this is going to be interesting to them
Most importantly
Wooden on techno
Release for guys who
How to started
Working at a time when Company still had things like typing pools
So I guess my thought is
Because this is
Focused on things that the P&G guys while the technology is difficult
It's probably much more accessible to be like
Hey you could track all your things as opposed to you could put
Stuff on this magical place called the World Wide Web
It feels easier
That's that's why I said
This is happening
I mean in 1998
John Chambers who was the CEO of Cisco
Chambers guide run around all the CEOs in 100 CEOs with
PowerPoint presentation
Explaining to them what the internet
What was and how important it was that
It was kind of internet or. I was kind of
Raised right
50 60 something year old white guys
Who
I've been told in a very compelling way
If I needed to get on board with the internet
So the way to get
Attention
Was to find a way to join the wood Internet to the wood thing
Bicycle
To describe this idea of network connect connected
And so the PowerPoint presentation
At least through the company with this PowerPoint presentation
I had to coat something like small packages
Just kind of a horrible dead-on-arrival kind of name really
To really grab the attention of these people who
Newton's net worth important wunschel what it was
Answered
Tubidy
Make my idea pitch my idea was an internet strategy
RN about I think it was probably about April 9th
99 change the presentation
And I knew I wanted to use the word internet and I do I want to see use the word things
So I wanted to get them both in the same type of the PowerPoint presentation and there was no
Easy way to do that so I came up with this this phrase into that all stings
As far as I'm aware nobody'd ever
At least not loudly and publicly
Out of Internet all's anything
If all right there was just the internet
Preposition that went with internet
I'm here looking back I probably should have called it like the internet for things
Saw something
But whatever reason internet all stadiums had some kind of ring to it
So that was a typo.
Impatient and earned me to MIT to make it real at some point
During the
Sodalite to mm
It became a common
Common phrase people used
So let me ask you
Now that we are in 2017
And I feel like the Resurgence in The Internet of Things has been around for
11 2010
Where we started seeing a cheap sensors
Data everywhere
WeChat cloud computing which made a big deal
And so where it where do you think we are today
You thought we would be or did you think we'd get here
Here faster
If you'd have asked me in like 1999 or 2002 predict 2017 I would have been
Wrong about most things
I think I was
Network sensing
An automatic data capture was going to be a huge thing
Look at me trying
Inspirational I'll give you some examples in a minute
RFID tags with B
Would be everywhere at right now
And it's interesting why that no
By the way
And some of its structural
It's like
Gives you his day to you you haven't got because you haven't got that you don't necessarily know you know
Need it
So I could be buried
Nicole is still kind of
Working our way through the 20th century generation of senior managers
These are people who
Grasping the idea of
Networks and
Intuitively
There's some kind of
Fort imagination
Has better see the value of something like
They got to know where your stuff is all the time through a technology like RFID
Add another thing this happened
Pacification I mean one of the assumptions I made
Through my whole time at MIT
Was it you needed something like RFID because something like Vision Machine Vision
Was never going to be good enough
I'm actually happy
Softer
1952 about 2000
Machine Vision was horrible
I was a really struggling field
And then
Episode of 2000
2010 it suddenly
Became very sophisticated
And the reason why is interesting from the internal things perspective by the way
But she got good suddenly
Because of network sensing
So digital cameras all senses
And then uploading pictures to the internet is kind of
Caprice of network products.
I want happen
Was
The dataset
That computer scientist had available to them
Algorithms
Dinner went from a few pictures to a few
100 million pictures
In a few years
See I credited two gpus in
Having more compute but you're right the training data
A big deal
Write machine learning
Is
Patton Wrecker
Basically
You have a hypothesis about Wattpad
She might want to recognize to Beartooth for example identify a face
Hypothesis
Some mathematics
But you need to run
Thousands or Millions
But also your algorithm
How can I prove itself
Ride it can start to look for
What oldies station
The same face what do they have in common
I'm one of the ones that I sold what I say
Butt off my face what do they have
What don't they have
So
Burger
Unimportant
Is generally
Didn't happen until about
2000-2001 is Seroquel
A lot of things we do today without thinking about it like GPS and
Smartphones in your pocket
High definition
Digital cameras in your pocket and you know broadband
Downloading hi-def movies and things
All those things
Pretty much
Declared to be impossible
The early 2000
That was some
Supposed to be
These physical limits or technological limits of man
It would never be possible to
To scream high definition
Movie into Ohio
Peter have a GPS sensor that work indoors in your pocket
It was supposed to be all these reasons why those things wouldn't work
Elderberry important
Technology invented in the two in the early 2000s the transformed
You could do with radio
Radio sensing
Which lead us to where we are today
Any type of things which is like you
Does GPS
So
There's a whole bunch of star
And the GPS space in the digital photography space
Health sensing from your phone
A lot of things that were
Maybe
Should have creamed off by a few wild-eyed dreamers like
Met-Ed
Late 90s early 2000
But we were told we were crazy and frankly we weren't being crazy enough
That is awesome.
There's stuff that you like
And then it doesn't
It happens way later than
Absolutely
It's awesome
That's why I love it
So let me ask you because I know you said you were working on a new book
And you also told me that you are inherently an optimist
Look at the internet
As a tool that can be used for great evil
Is he all kinds of
Set a bad but I can also see like
I talked to a company that it's a power company that once they connected their infrastructure they were able to turn off
The lights at beaches when sea turtles were nesting in so sea turtles are actually now
They just have to dispatch Crews to actually physically turn off these lights
Four seater sea turtles can come up to nest on the dark Beach and it's very sad
I look at that and I'm like holy cow
Cool things
So you can do with this so what does the future hold
Oh
Spiffy wonderful
42 optimistic because history teaches us to be open
Domestic
My lost book how to fly a horse was very much about
The human creative spirit
But I think one of the things we we can mess because it's
Everywhere is
Another thing that's unique about human being as a species
Is we all have an innate drive to create
Not everybody is going to
5th Symphony
We all have an innate drive to create two
Improve things to make things better so
What we do is a species
Is
Approve also
Improving on technology and we've done that forever
Anat has led us to a place where
In
People were worried about growing population
Because
The world's population of China just about reached 1 billion
But today at 7
An 1800
Average life expectancy
See probably was about 38
And today it's about
So
We know only
We have been able to sustain a large
Most of those people live longer Fuller happy alives
What's changed
Strangest we continually improve. Technology
So when you look at what's happening
Now
You see some exciting things going on in
And Technologies
Space traveling
Space exploration
Things like self driving
The things that are happening in microbiology to improve
Angel
Revention smartphone
Earlier
Amazing
Rarely told stories about smartphone
Cell phones is
We're taking us from a wild wear in mm
About 1 billion people
Had access to a telephone
So that was probably about 20%
Today that are more phones Than People 120%
Population has access to a phone
Bats
Powerful change
Does happen because of Technology
And it means that
You know some people can't talk to their mom or whatever
But they can access information
In places where they can attract
Consummation
So what hola amounts to is you know whatever challenges we see
Did one of the big ones people talk about now is climate change
Example which is Real History shows us
Credibly likely almost certain
We will overcome and mitigate the effects of
Climate change
By proving on technology because
On that note
What is the biggest obstacle today
For your vision
The internet
Oh I mean that kind of has really
But I look when I look around the
Consumer applications in like things in small firms that use GPS so that the sense you're hot right or whatever
I'm sorry business
Incredible
Largely unseen
Revolution around Network sensing so there another no autistic
Post to my page
The Internet of Things
Happening cuz it's already it's already happened we are now surrounded by
Network sensors and the benefits
Subnetwork census
I don't see any any particular all the schools are always new problem
Yeah that the frontier for the internet of things today
Is definitely
Machine learning
Because you eat cycle this diet
This coming from
Census
And you need a new way to evaluate and analyze it because there's so much of it but
The 20th century
Types of paradigm
Was was kind of the Excel spreadsheet
Clear coat turned into a pie chart
On a PowerPoint
In the mind of a lot of CEOs and Senior executive so I gather these 20th century white guys
That still want dangerous right you ever report that comes out of something like an sap system or
Salesforce.com or something
And some kid
Into a spreadsheet
Add makes up pycharm
And then I arrange a meeting in the Outlook calendar 3 weeks later and they sit there
I'm stare at it
Try to understand it decide to have another meeting
About state or Dialysis in the 20th century
In the 21st century
It's ultimated using this technology for machine learning
So either one of them
Sweetheart
People's rehab today
Is
Developing Alpha Beta algorithm
To do machine learning analysis of
Huge amounts of real time
It's a lot of things
Another challenge the
I don't know how we're going to solve is
The wild have this
Really old fashioned
Approach to radio spectrum
Kind of like
Bright House Spectrum
Is kind of still allocated
Everybody watched analog broadcast television
Listen to analog broadcast radio
There's barely any Spectrum
Digital computer science like application
You know you got more 20th century white guys running the world governments
And then you got big old fashion companies that give them bunch of money
And tell them what policies to agree to
It could be hard to get them
DeGraw
You know how we need to make
More radio waves available full
Internet of Things type applications
I like your thinking
Alright Kevin
Thank you so much for coming on the show
Well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast
Please join us next week when we have another amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are Hank
Praying for some iot news sign up for my newsletter it's Stacey on iot
Dot-com thanks for listening