Hey everybody this is the intern
Things podcast with your house
Kevin tofel
Stacy Higginbotham somehow we switched roles
I decided I decided I'd I switch it up a little
Because today I am a
Recording for my hotel room in Aspen and Kevin Ware YouTube
In the home office in Pennsylvania
It is truly wonderful I am here for Fortune's brainstorm Tech event where I've I'm hoping to bring back all kinds of insights
About the internet of things that I would share with you next week
I should also note that this week we don't have a guest
Because travel uncertainties and we have
I guess a lot of the guests this week or traveling
Try really hard to become but
People were just like nope can't do it
Gone
Vacation time so you're going to have to make do with Kevin and I
Cuz we we ate are Wheaties this morning had a little too much caffeine
Say a little hyper
And you also have less oxygen than I do being at a higher altitude so this ought to be interesting
Superfund
Alright so this week show we're going to
Start with some news we're going to move into Target new Internet of Things store and we're going to talk about the wide world of
Sports in The Internet of Things
All right
So
News
This week
Red
We talked about it a little bit last week
This week
The red group
Which is
For those of you guys who did not listen last week
Is a wireless protocol kind of Bluetooth
Connecting devices in The Internet of Things
And these guys are announcing officially that they are
Launching a certification program
Suggest like Wi-Fi products are certified
Going to be certified
That certification program will be out
And developed for September of this year
They also announced that Qualcomm
Is joining the thread Group which means that
Companies like
Guest
Freescale
Silicon labs
Samsung
Everybody is everybody
Yes lots of people I'm I'm I'm drawing a blank
There's Big Ass Fans
Since mother company
Where to but Qualcomm
You know is it me or is Qualcomm
Trying to
Do what they do with wireless charging throw the best way to say it
We had three wireless charging standards and Qualcomm got involved with all three
Separate standards hoping to
You know I guess pick the winner
Can I get to the about on everywhere's you're bound to win something
I think they're doing this as well here because they already had all seen all join and
I'm going to stop you right there because
Austine
And all join
Qualcomm is a founding member of the all seeing Alliance
Call doll join
So all join is actually further up the stack
It's not a wireless
So it's a little bit different
EXO thread
Is a wireless protocol
Also that's just the radios and how they talk to each other
Is
Housing
How how once the radios are talk to each other this is actually how the software way up there
Talks to each other like how devices talk to each other
Alright so they're getting involved in a different layer in the stack but
Okay I get it
So thread competes with zigbee
Z-Wave
Bluetooth especially Bluetooth mesh
And
Wi-Fi
All seeing
Competes within
Games like iotivity
Probably
Brillo
We've we're not sure cuz we haven't seen that yet
Yeah probably homekit
So that's that's where those off
Right right right
I know
It's funny because you know one of the things that we said for years actually before we doing this show is this just so many stand
Nerds and
Methods and protocols and all it's all very confusing to the
For the young product buyer
It's challenging if your do-it-yourself or because you got a hope you're picking the right
Particle products and Salon
And
I like to see consolidation
So I guess in a way this is good but it really doesn't
Consolidate much at all dozen
Will wait
Okay I'm waiting here comes some more news that honestly if for the normal and consumer is it going to be
Mean much but
Silicon labs
Also this week is announcing
Pet products
Better made using silicon labs
Zigbee chips
They're releasing software that will make
Those chips
Updatable
To the
Thread standard
Through an over-the-air
Cell phone case with a safer bet if you go this route
So yes so it's possible that very soon
If you have zigbee chips and things
Those chips will be using
Threat but you as a consumer will never know
Right and because there's a certification process
You shouldn't have to worry about standardization in the Prada
Right and you as a consumer aren't going to actually be looking for assertive
Vacation until after September
Because while they announce the certification program
It doesn't actually
This. This is another case
Announced thread-like over a year
So
Again it does not pay to be on the
It's just very mental
It's new and it's very expensive that I can attest to and nsu's head
We don't know nothing about weave and Brillo because that's
A token question of a will
That work with red
Or not
I imagine
It has to
Because they are working with nest
It's separate from
But
I can't imagine that Google would spend 3.2 billion dollars on nest
West Indies
Was one of the founding members of
Thread for you would be like
Yeah you know what let's
Let's do something to totally does
You would think so I agree with you that makes sense however I wouldn't have expected the big nest news
The month ago to be
We've branded are cameras with Dropcam cameras is nest dropcam's and we've got a slightly updated
Well I would expect that that is Tony fadell all over
That is like
I have learned so much from my dears at Apple
Let us make a baby
HooHa
Overall apus
+
You know kind of geeky kind of nerdy
Here's some less nerdy
This is
Sort of if you like these products
The Amazon
Echo
Now works with
Which we talked about last week not knowing
They were going to do this
We were actually talking about will you mention that you spent I think $180 on
120 on
Lync light bulb switch work with wink
And they also work with the Philips Hue so with your Hue bridge and your Echo you could
I'll say
Unofficially control you
Wink bulbs
But now you can officially to it
Right in doing that actually
Also last week or maybe the week before noticed
Wink support was listed on the Amazon Echo website
I didn't think it was a big deal I just thought oh hey
There's wink support there
But then I made a hoo-ha about it last week
I had a scoop and didn't realize it
I did not get it
Will update the although
So after I guess over a week of turning my GE link
Light bulbs on and off
What do little
What I know I'm going to go out and buy some
What's going on
So what's happening is I'll tell Alexa
How to turn the light kitchen lights off
In all but one will turn off
Let me stop you right there
Okay
There's something I did learn and covering the non scoop news last week was
Where do you have some groups because you can't group them in the Wink app you have to group them in the Alexa app
They are grouped in the Alexa
Oh that's a glitch
It is it's
Popping up more and more often is a Different Light
Every time
So I have to tell it to turn off twice
To get all the lights off
I'm kind of wondering
If there's kind of like you know how it in your browser settings or something you might clear your
Cash
Just clean everything out
I'm kind of wondering if there's like a the equivalent in a smart home likely work settings
Or in Echo I have no idea cuz it
It kind of feels like that
Terror
I would say it's worth a shot if you don't mind
You know unlinking all of your lights and and rediscovering them and regrouping them
I'm going to bet you that works
So again in Aspen now but this is this is the reporting
The tappening
EXO next show I'll have regrouped and see if that pops up again in
You know if this is something I have to do every week I'm going to be like guys
This is
This is not
This is no bueno
Don't you actually don't sweat it while you're in Aspen I can use use the backdoor that that hacker created on the
Was it Nightline I forget what TV show
They never stopped they never got my
We didn't tell you that they got to be honest
I could I could do it except for I have to have a physical a person physically there
Button
Or maybe a Roomba with an extension
That's what I do I need to build it like a little Servo motor
You don't have it set up to hit the button for me
Little bits
What you don't have a telepresence robot like the rest of us
I do not
Alright so
Next news item which is something cool
Spending a lot of time
Target
This
Is what I've been waiting for
I think
I have to go to San Francisco to see it but it sounds like what I've been waiting for
Which is
Target
Has introduced
A store concept called
Open house
At the San Francisco
City Target which is on 4th Street
Crossing mosconi Woodbury always get the clothes we didn't
Remember to pack on a trip to San Francisco
Exactly
If this is a retail concept for selling the internet of things and right now they've got about 50 company
He's in there
So if you listen to the show you are familiar with a lot of these
Companies like
Yonomi tile August
Ring Whiting
High IQ
Keep going on I'm
Sonos Philips Hue
Mimo which is a baby monitor kind of concept
Jawbone
I got the whole lineup in there are so many
It looks
Amazing
This is a story-within-a-story concept right kind of like how Samsung
Puts in their little mini stores in Best Buy's and such
Yes now this is the only one
This is not a concept that is going to expand for now this is a in the basement of this
The single Target in San
The idea is there working with these vendors
To show off connected devices you can go in and buy them
But what's really cool
Is a setup
Scenarios where you can see exactly how the stuff
Can work
Singly and
Importantly
How it works
Together
So it won't show you
Onesti's partner so it will show you things like how I always talked about like the works with Nest concept
With like the Philips Hue Lights that I like so much where if you're
Nest set to away
Your Philips Hue Lights will just
Turn off
Or if it's a two-way for more than a day your Philips Hue Lights will go into like a random
Keto on and off pattern
Should I boil burglars
So it shows you those things are shows you that
Sonos working in
Conjunction with the mimo baby monitor so if your baby starts stirring the Sonos can be turned on to play White Noise or
Lullaby so maybe the baby will go back to
Asleep
Maybe you can make your phone ring
I was like that is actually not my phone ringing that is that is Street noise
Permit Aspen
There's apparently a
But they had a pray for you very nice very nice
I love this idea for two reasons one of the obvious reason is it shows and expose of the cancer
Consumer to really what's going on in the iot world premiere
A retail level of a real
Use case experiential kind of
Kind of thing
More importantly though
I see these types of
Concept homes every year
At the Consumer Electronics Show
The difference here is
When I go to CVS I go to one vendor's Booth such as
Spell can they show me their home field with WeMo
Going to go to somebody else's Booth me show me all of their products
This is showing all of the different vendors working
Gather and that's really key
So the closest I've come to this is Donna which is the back-end behind Staples connect
Possibly some other
Products
Where they located are located in Pennsylvania I believe
That's right I do remember them asking me to come out I guess I should go over you should go see it it's it's this concept in Pennsylvania
It's actually really
So you could see this without going to Sanford
But it is so powerful to see this
Because most people
Do not buy these
Product you're going to buy a device
The one-off reason
And the one on his case and sometimes that one-off use case
Is really not that compelling
Paying 60 bucks for a light bulb because it changes color
Or because it's connected to your phone
Ridiculous
If Stacey doesn't weekly sorry
It's because I have all of these other people's voices in my head
With other people
A lot from a person to be like
Yes I know that my connected doorbell will flash the lights when it rings
Alerting me to who's at the Emmy that's
That's just
Angry people have it in their head up a smart home is
You know something like The Invasion on Star Trek for example where everything does work together
All these different things going on
And yet then they go in their buy one product or like this isn't what
Gene Roddenberry promised me this is a light bulb that changes colors what do I do
Showing the whole home showing how these things work together is
Really the value at
And showing which things
Work with which other things so the only other place that does that is Amazon
Because it's online you can actually separate in their home automation Channel which products work with which other products
I spend a lot of time
And it's one of my favorite places to buy devices because
A good prices
It shows
What other things can work with what other things in
Most retailers don't have the resources to either constantly update that
I mean like when I come into Home Depot a lot of the time
Is like the cencap jumble that is like hassled out
Spot it hasn't been updated
3 months am
So target has basically combined the information
Hopefully it stays up to date
Did Amazon
Can provide
With
Feel like demos that CES off
With like some clear lucite furniture that
Looks cool I guess
And like the ability to play with all these products in real life
In real life in this
The store experience
And
It's supposed to be disliked living lab so if you buy stuff and you hate it or it's glitchy like
My GE link lights are right now
You can bring them back
And there's no restocking fee
When I talk to you David Newman who I'm hoping to get on the podcast
He was like
You know we're going to look at that as an opportunity to do consumer research you know you bring them back you tell us what happened and we're going to talk to the
Manufacturing be like
Hey what's up
Awesome
I love it I love it guys I think this is just amazing
It's a lot of work
But
I think it's a really interesting
I'm telling right step in for the startups
Hopefully when you man comes on the show Hill talk about how startups
Can get involved because he wants to actually have
Startups come and show off their products even before their maybe even available to do consumer research which would be gracemore
And it's March
And this is at the Metreon Target in San Francisco and it's in the basement you say
Yes in the
That sounds dank and dark but it's not thinking
If they have a glass stairway I mean you know there's a good chance it'll be successful
It took last year
Just saying if it's lucite
Clear acrylic Furniture everywhere
They Stitch you stuff looks great
All right so I'm excited about this I can't wait
To go and see it
If you guys are in Sanford
Francisco
Check it out report back
Can let us know
And
When we have to
Keep listening because sometime this summer
David Newman
Who's in charge of this is going to come on the show and tell us all about what they've learned so far hopefully
And how you guys can
Thinking about all right final news item for the day or not
Just things
We're talking about thinking about is
Wimbledon
Or specifically tennis
I guess it would be tennis specifically with
Yeah that works too
Yeah yeah I don't play tennis
Well I did one
What about you
Play on occasion I'm away from the ratchet tennis courts down the street public tennis courts so every once in awhile when running
Get some exercise will go and I'll head ball
Really that's my problem I can never hit the ball
That's kind of thumb the most important part
That's that was my
So is there something in the iot world I can help you with the ball
Maybe
There is there are connected raqqa
I think my general hand-eye coordination
Even the information
Connect
I was reading this
Put out a piece of content marketing
Antenna
And
Contact Marquis
This was actually really interest
And
He talked about
And I don't know how to say this
Babolat
Belittle
So this is a I believe it's actually a French
Direction compass
Connected tennis racket
And because they make
Connected tennis rackets they believe that by 2020
Everybody will be using smart tennis racket
That's because they are just so amazing and what they do
How you move the racket
How the ball hits the racket the strength of your serve all of this
Information
And they're transmitting it to the players
Real-time but also making video analysis immediately after the matches available to them
Yeah this is a this is actually a
Market that we
Probably should talk about more when we talked about IRT and and big data and such as a sports Market
Because there's so much information
Available or
Well it's hard to get that information
Without sensors in you know the tennis ball soccer balls whatever maybe
Golf clubs now on tennis rackets
You know that's all feedback to athletes didn't even Spectators I mean like I'm always watching golf
And they have the little ball Tracer that shows where the ball is going after
It's been hit the swing speed the height and all this
It's just amazing and it
It's more immersive experience both
Observer and probably as an athlete
To travel information it's just we don't
I don't think about it that much
What I thought was really kind of interesting as IBM talks about giving some of this data out to like
Coaches so you could actually coach someone playing against arrival
Based on this data
Yeah so
I mean if you feedback in the incredible
Inside
That that to me was just kind of
Crazy so
Idea was imagine playing against big Champions like Rafael Nadal
Which
I don't think that's possible and so
If the other thing is
This kind of information from the racket
Befuddled real-time 2
You know a smartwatch which could deliver
Haptic feedback to a person
But I know that on Wimbledon you know they don't allow coaching
For the sidelines
And I don't
No sale of smart watches at Wimbledon but you know
You can get coaching almost immediately
From a smartwatch
Watch which means
I think they would disallow that in competitions but it you know it's 4
Amateur
Regular people
That's pretty useful
Yeah
Well it is not just your equipment
I mean equipment is the first thing
Because you know you
You've got
It's obvious that the instrument equipment
PocketInvEditor
It's also something that people already spend a lot of money on if you're even a amateur
Actually if you play a sport very seriously
You're willing to spend a crazy amount of money on it
Oh yeah
So we're going to start seeing like sensors in clothing
You can already buy
Sensor embedded shirts
Socks 511
Oh yeah
How do you make the
Best
That has sensors and it to monitor my heart rate
And my respiration rate and so on so when I go for a run
It's real time sending that information right to my phone
Did it help you
I got tired
Give me good feedback
All joking aside I like to work in certain heart rate zones for certain types of workouts like my Speedway
Working at Temple work
And I'm going too fast or I'm working too hard. I shouldn't
Be running out fast for temple workout
I can keep that speed up for 3 miles then obviously
It's going to be a wasted effort
So long-term yes I can help absolutely
Did it give you feedback right away
Pick it up later
No real son
I would think some sort of it wasn't a screen or was it have
On screen
So haptics
Sure if I if maybe you could set Target zones for the heart rate and have the data sent to the watch and when I
Too high new mattress too high you need to slow down
How do you get a double tap if I'm going too slow and get a single tap Shore
Cuz that's that's what I think
Really awesome
Absolutely and you know all these sensors don't have to be embedded in these things going back to the tennis bed and I and I said
Because there was a Kickstarter That was supposed to deliver in January still hasn't so
I'm not advocating go get this by any means but
They have a company came out with a shot stats Challenger to a way to make your tennis racket smart
It literally is it it looks like a
A racket dampener for people who do play tennis and what that is
Except it has a small screen on it's got sensors inside and you can
Measure you know the speed of your swing the speed of your servant
The angle of the racket when you hit the ball and so on so
Yeah you can add these to regular tennis rackets
I'm sure it goes for all types of sport II I've seen things you can attach the golf clubs for personal information so
If we don't have to embed all this right in this equipment is what
I'm really intrigued by a kind of all of these option
Where they might come from
Eventually you should be able to stream all this data into Lake
Android Fitbit or Android Wear
Is it a better way
Which one which one
Google Fit
On Android
Google Fit Android Wear or
Healthkit
And perhaps
You know
You could use that to track you know your burgeoning shoulder injury
Who knows
If that's a potential
I wish I had more to say about the
But since I don't play tennis or
I don't that
Let's let's be honest Thrillers were talking about is cuz it's kind of cool name babala
Baba black sheep
I was excited
Window tinting idea
Play ideas like how this changes
And how it changed
Because
There's a lot of ways that Sports
With the Advent of
More data like it changes the way you
Plan your defense
It also changes the way that you could
Potentially
Compete
Can a single person Sports so Lake
You know what everyone has SmartWatches coaching them
How does that change the nature of the game does it make it faster does it make it
You know more precise I don't know
Will sit in some sense once you add the technology
Kind of brings a different way of competing at if you look at you know formula
1 cars and all the technology they have in there I mean these guys
Are constantly tweaking the code of their cars to make them
Have an advantage over other people's code in their cars and
It's going to be very interesting to see how that develops in terms of competitive Sports in general
You know every time I've gone to a supercomputing show I always see the Formula One guys
Actually there it's like the the racing teams
They're there because that's
Important
Cardiff
Competition
It would be very interesting
Sensors become such
An important part of
Cheating because these Sports don't normally kind of give a nod to technology
We need to link change sensors on the NASCAR so we don't have any accidents no no
I don't know if you are
I am just going to date that you're very more mechanical and electronic in those car
It's very
I still use manual
Tachometers for example they don't even have speedometers so
It's very much a mechanical sport compared to say Formula One
I don't people like the exit
Isn't that part of the
People in them certainly do not but
Yeah I mean I'm not going to lie there's a there's definitely
Portion of a Nascar fan base or racing fan base that
Watch it for the big one
It's kind of a Bittersweet saying I don't like you probably don't know this
Mention it
I'm not this past weekend but the weekend before there was a
Terrible accident where
At the finish line
Karwan
Up and over to other cars and into the catch fence at
Daytona
And literally the entire car
Went to Pieces the engine flew out for example
The front end was gone
Basically nothing was left with the roll cage in a little bit of sheet metal and
Thankfully do the safety
The driver did not get hurt he walked out of it but it was
Touch and go for the first 30 seconds after that happened me people thought this man was dead
And there were actually
Spectators that
Were injured from debris that didn't get caught by The Catcher And so
I mean it's nice to hope for these accent
Sputnik
Can be careful what you wish for yes
Well gosh that is such a grim. I kind of don't want to end the podcast I will send you that the YouTube video this crash and you
You will be will be scared for this person's life
Of course you know at this point he's okay but yeah
All right we'll add that to the show notes
Maybe
I'm like
I don't even know rather Grim so let's let's bring finish the show on an uphill and say it one more time
Pop-A-Lock
Or father later
No actually I
I realized
Time 45 minutes
Device
Review
All right
This week's device
Home connected doorbell
It's actually
It's the doorbell.
And to get the doorbell you actually have
To sign up for their monitor
Security system
But
People likes this
Doorbell so much they actually got 40,000 new sign ups
Jasper the freaking doorbell which is amazing
Just so you know what you're getting into
What you do Vivint offers
Connected homes
This is not a DIY project
Normally I don't mess with these but
I thought it was either I was kind of going through a connected doorbell phase
And I thought it was so interesting that
They were one of the first to offer
A video doorbell
I did I decided to happen
Install it so they came out and installed it be
Because this is that kind of product
They charge between 54 and $70 a month for a monitored home security product
The pricing differential there's three levels
It basically offers you can feel
Levels of storage
I'm in different levels look like
Connected devices
So they work with
Z-Wave devices
So they will also connect you up with other Z-Wave devices in your house
Nice which is kind of cool
Actually set up my SmartThings controller is a secondary
Controller it will actually go into that
Completely different podcast
Because it's it's worth talking about
The doorbell
Because
I liked it
It's a nice-looking doorbell
The most doorbell
Video connected doorbells it is the smallest of the
Ring
Skybell
Didn't
Doorbell trifecta
It is
About an inch and a half across
It's about 3 in tall
It looks like a doorbell
Which is really important
Because
Sometimes people get to my door
And they're like
Button
What do I do
The other nice thing about this is they come in and install it
They also is installed with a
And again you're going to be paying for it every month
So when it's installed
What happens is
If someone Rings your doorbell
It comes up on a security panel that they install in your house as well so you could video honest
On the security panel to touch screen panel
You also get it on any of the phone's you hook up to the doorbell
So I get a notification on my phone it rings on my phone
I'm in it sounds like a doorbell chime you can
China variety of chimes
And it will also bring
Your
Manual doorbell chime if you want
At 2 actually
No it does
It only rings through the
Doorbell chime
Sound through your touchpad
I like you guys
Forget that forget the
Ndk
Video it is instantaneous
So
It's pretty sweet
I will say because I spent a lot of time on the phone
That feature is less exciting to me because
I'm on the phone so
I'm not able to
You you can open Allina conversation with someone
You know what they're at your door and be like hey what you doing
Upstairs come on Inn
Hey
I'm busy
Leave the package at the door
Can you do that through the the display panel you can
Okay so you could you know hope put your phone call on hold or whenever mutant
Kind of. You just can't do it with the phone when
And I particularly can't because I have some weird phone issues
Attleboro
Well I have
I have the Moto X
Second generation
Verizon
Which
What's Mia it takes me off of the data Network when I'm going to
Recess
But that's a very
Unique it's a Unique Ink although if you
And everyone in your family has on the Verizon Moto X 2nd generation or a
That's better get fairy
What is interesting though
And if you hate
Having if you don't want to do if you don't want to go DIY
This is a crate
Product because they will actually set up
Garage door open
They set up a garage door opener so it's like the UPS man
Ring doorbell
You can actually from your phone or the control panel
Open your garage and tell the UPS due to leave it in your
Garage and then close the garage door behind the
You can do that from your office like 20 miles away from your house you can do it
Inside your house
It's pretty sweet
Sandy
Attendee
So
Night vision on this thing is nice
Steel division on it is nice
What other questions do people have
About connected doorbells Kevin
Is it hard wire
Or is it is there a battery it is hardwired into my existing doorbell
And that was a nice thing about having them
Install install took about an hour
Yammy most people have a doorbell wired doorbell anyway I would think and so it's a replacement for that direct replace
Yes
If I'm not mistaken these are the folks who also
They're did you a whole package here I mean like as you said you got the doorbell and they have
The garage door opener they have connected door lock
Calm have in house wifi cameras
But I think they also offer internet service
They do they have actually internet service in some places
Yeah
And they have a whole home automation f
I'm thinking
And this is important
Unofficial open
Internet home automation service although they are
Planning
But they don't have it now
So while they actually hooked up my
The secondary key
Control
So I could tie my SmartThings in through this
I don't know what they would do that for every
Ketchum
Did you offer lotion
Motion sensors door window sensors
It all of it's based on Z-Wave
So if you're a Z-Wave
Send or have Z-Wave stuff they can link your existing Z-Wave stuff in
Got that
You know what that's it is not bad so if you're like
You're kind of like
I've been gandaras monitored home security so if you're getting your like
I like monitor homes
Security
And if you if you decide to go with these guys
And you're going to pay the monthly fee
Do they give you the hardware cuz that's a pretty common
There you go you sign up you pay this and think of you I think it's up to $1,500 worth of the hardware free
How to control panels like 9
Hundred of that hard
Wow
Yeah the sky control panel is $900
I'll stick with my iPad thank you
Yeah it's a nice nice piano
So
Gay that smoke alarms carbon monoxide
Video cameras
Thermostat
Why did their offer no package just like a lot of the
Traditional isps are starting to do now
Yeah and it it's got cellular backup and it's primarily a cellular system
Which is what a lot of
The modern ones are which is great people like me who don't have
Yeah that's we still have the old ADT system and no landline now so
We haven't used ATT system in years because of that
That is that is our
Our product
I like it
I think it's kind of fun if not convinced enough to pay $54 a month
Ford although my husband in this biscuits into something and we're actually talking about paying
The monthly fee for monitored security
So if we do that
I will probably use Vivint and I will do it because they have this doorbell product
So
I'm not in their target audience I'd rather do it myself but you can even with the struggles and
I was getting things to talk to each other but there is there's definitely a big Market
Yeah well and the fact that I can bring in my SmartThings stuff I'm kind of like
Hey
All right
Well that is this week show so
Hopefully you guys
We left on a higher note then
Hopefully
Let us know if you stop by the new Target
Open house
What's in San Francisco
Or if you see anything worth it
Talking about on the show or
Questions
We are in
At
Iot podcast
Dot-com
Please tell friend
Listen to the show
And leave a review or something like that
A friend of a friend
I don't know if you want to tell a friend of her
And
I think
I think that does its what do you think Kevin
I think so and remember don't bother little bubble.
Babolat
All right
They are
Don't stay tuned for our gas
Because this week
Nuggets
Come back one year
Come back next
Come back next week thank you so much for listening and have a wonderful week