Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and this is our co-host
Kevin tofel
We have got an amazing show for you today we're going to focus on Defcon hacks
We've got questions about how
I could driving is going to work we got a bunch of news bit
Including week being sold
To William
We got a Q&A from one of our readers
And we're going to highlight and improbable iot product
This week because
It's really improbable and after all of that
We will have a message from our sponsor Hyksos Solutions
I want to hear about them
Our Guest this week is Sam George who's in charge of Microsoft Azure iot efforts
About a lot of industrial and Enterprise iot
Information
So
Stick around for all of that and now
Another one of our sponsors this week and they are launching their
2nd generation mesh wi-fi system these new aero systems contain one
KIRO that is in the older square shape
And when did you begin switch are mesh access points
They also have cool features like a night like they're smaller and you can put them just about anywhere you just plug
Right in there is no pork
You will also be able to buy individually rozar begins to add to your current system they are fully backwards compatible
So for example I spend
$149 and I bought additional Beacon to put in my hallway to improve cover
Average for my Wi-Fi doorbells because they needed it
So the original system containing one zero and two beacons
Starts at the 399 again this is for people who are in the market for a mesh wi-fi system
I have one I have the Eros I have loved them for a long time and the new system is faster so
You may want to start adding New pieces I don't know what I like about them it's just so easy to extend your mesh Network
So you can see just like you said saw them into an outlet
And boom got insulin coverage
Cuz you got backwards compatibility if you have the old Euro
So if you are interested you can go to www Eero that is eat
Ero.com
And with this code Stacy and I encourage
Go out
Grab some of these and tell them that we sent you all right
Back to the show
Lots of hacking to talk about
Besides
Actually
Big hacking conference in Las Vegas
And we learned a lot of things
Such as
I think we learned about the Amazon Echo getting hacked
I don't know if that happened at Defcon but
It was definite there's always a lot of Newsroom
Yeah it happened around the same time as death, don't think it happened
During the fire at Defcon but
This is
At first it's concerning but it's a little less concerning once I explain what the heck actually is and what it takes
Actually a security researcher has been able to
Show
That he can take over
The microphone of Amazon Echo not an echo dot or an echo
How are you going to vacuum the only on the Amazon Echo
The original one
And
He can listen in and have the audio that it captures sent to a server Elser and you don't even know
Now
Again that sounds concerning and it should be
However
Newer Echoes are not affected by the hack so if you have an echo
Check and see the
That is packaging with the device itself and if there's a 2017 on it and the model number and ending in 02
It is not vulnerable
Anything else he's vulnerable
However
To actually
Implemented
He or somebody would need to
To have physical access to your Echo and we need some time to manipulate the files on it
There's a root exploit that he would need to use
So if nobody's coming out of your house
Oh my God it's like it's like the 21st century version of like having the Russian spies come in and plug your place
There you go
Dapsone
I would say
Fret too much about this I don't know if Amazon can actually fix this with
A firmware update though that's that's the more concerning parked me some the older Echoes witch
Mine was bought by
Before this year's I'm sure it's vulnerable and Stacey I'm sure yours is to
Mine was first off the line
Yeah I'm not sure that can be fixed
I'm okay with that
I figured
So in addition to
Your Amazon Echo could be hacked freakout
We also have car washes could be hacked this is actually from Defcon and
These researchers
Showed that
They could find access to automatic
Car washes online I bet they're using chaudin
To be honest it what happened is
They can find these car washes
And they could gain control of them lock a vehicle in them and then beat the vehicle with the robotic washing arm
That's very it is a very scary thing to have happen I am sure
But the reason this is happening is because
These car washes are online and they didn't change the password so like if you own a car wash
And you invested in the automated thing maybe change your password
That's going to help a lot
Which then brings us
Oh my God it's 2017 and we're still having to tell people to change their password but maybe next year we won't
Because there is new iot security legislation
Proposed Hindi
Send it
Go Far Kid
I wonder if they're listening to us because I think it's the last two or three episodes we've been
Talking about
Potential consumer protection legislation for
Smart devices
And
This is a step is a baby step in and there's no guarantees that the legislation is going to pass but it wouldn't surprise
Crazy because it's very minimal
What is a bipartisan legislation
That would prohibit vendors from offering up devices that have unchangeable password switch
It's good you should be able to change your password if you purchase something
And or possess known security vulnerabilities
I dread that separate article about this aside from the Reuters one that I'm looking at right now and I believe it said
It would also
Require the devices to be firmware updatable
Remotely
So
Again
That's kind of a given her mostly
Devices today but still
Tire vendors that provide internet connected equipment to the US government to ensure their products are patchable Income form
Industries
Well G look look out for the government not for the people
Allows federal agencies
Ask the US Office of the OMB Office of Management and budget
Buy non-compliant devices
If other controls such as Network segmentation
So most of these I'm like wow this is like the bare minimum it doesn't hurt
It does expand
Directions for cyber researchers who are working in good faith to hack
Which is a big deal because
You know I don't know if you guys remember but Oracle used to sue hackers
Like all the time
Regretted
There's this whole kind of idea
I don't know if these are controversial still that they used to be because people would be like
Why don't you just tell us where
King of Thieves hacked
Why do we have to pay you
In kind of felt a little extortionist
2 News
It's a good incentive though it is it's actually one of the things I tell people to look for
If you're going to buy a connected home product or a connected device
Look for companies that have bug bounties because it does mean that they are serious about
More serious about security
J4 getting on board I would like to see consumer protections I would like to see the FTC and able to expand consumer
Productions in this area
This looks like it's only the
Yeah I think you're right
But it's a start
So you know who knows if we're going to get anything passed Congress has been kind of
Analysts call it divided
This is legislation in the Senate they're going to introduce similar legislation in the house will have to happen is they're going to talk about it send it to committee
If it makes it out of committee
Hold on versions of it who knows what else will get stuck in there
And then maybe
Maybe it will
There's a lot left
So it may dying
Haley StarTalk
Yep
Let's move on to other
Specifically how are
Cars
Talk to them
What will they talk
Well I remember way back when you and I were for gigaom I remember our colleague Katie foreign-backed listen to a bunch
To research and stories on cars
Using a specific
Wi-Fi protocol to talk to each other member that
Yes it was the vehicle to vehicle
Communication
I don't remember which
80802 something something I don't remember but obviously since then
345 years ago since then
Autonomous vehicles
Have really
Jose taken off you know there's a lot of momentum in that area
Which is awesome
But there's a lot of other things on the road that are not cars on the side of the road which yes
Carson see them
But you also have
Bicycles especially in a lot of urban areas
You have scooters and motorcycles so on
And none of these things talk to the cars the cars may even have problems identifying number of deserting them from pedestrians
So there's a researcher out of Carnegie Mellon
Who says hey you know cars have a regular pattern with the way they move
People right when people riding bicycles
The chain between acting like cars on side of the road or they might
Look up on the sidewalk
Journey Don't Stop at stop sign
This is true
I know I know I know I'm guilty
I myself am I my road bike
But you're actually right there they're not as predictable
As a car
When you look at it that way
What the researcher is doing is he actually loaded up a bicycle with lidar and radar and
Cameras everything else and he's trying to
Create data
That maybe they can add to the algorithms to the cars that say hey
That's really a bike and here's what you need to be careful for it may not stop at the stop sign
Everything But Water
You know it's not a pedestrian so it might have different rules that it has been applied to it and so on
So it's kind of interesting
I'm intrigued by this because I do ride a road cycle quite a bit I'm actually going for my motorcycle permit
Probably next week
In hopes of buying a large scooter
And
Part of me says he has a great idea but the thing is
Bicycles are not battery powered
And you're going to need battery power constant battery power for
Bikes to be able to speak to cars
Free sample if they want to say hey I'm over here doing come in my lane or whatever
And I don't know how that's going to work
Me either
So
Disappointed
There are lots of USB powered bike
Accessories
So I can see a couple
ICU addon
Very curious about
Like motion kinetic energy harvesting from a bike
Possible short
So could you power something that way
It's kind of got to be foolproof if for example eventually and I'm thinking far ahead here
Eventually there's a
Alert on your bike at says hey there's a car coming
Very close to you from behind or something like that you know
Is it bench I could see all the sensors that are in cars
Mitchell way down to
Motorcycles and bicycles
But the latter work you've got to have constant power
Champion sometimes I power and sometimes I don't
You'll have is constant power
From a battery
And I was just
You'll have that constant power for a set amount
Time
You'll be able to go on a 4-Hour bike ride with those features
Tonight anything else you're going to be back in the Dark Ages
This is Mike my hunch
I think it's think about it they had like
You know where they were trying to do a heads-up display that was all powered on a helmet
You know so that was charged and then
I don't know how long it would have lasted
I can see this happening I think things like electric bikes like in China right now those are surely
Super big so I think those kind of things might
Become part of that
It honestly because those are valuable safety
Repeaters
It does kind of get into this bigger discussion about
How will Design the roads are they
The future in life
Right away who will talk to whom in that sort of thing to think about
The rules for cars
Nice purses
Baby bikes and pedestrians insomnia
In terms of
Population
So cars with autonomous I'll just slow the
Cuz I have
Not your second power but
Add a longer battery life I can totally
Afford taking of slow down where's the spikes got to get where it's going so
Recharge
Right right I mean I think we're way ahead of the curve on this discussion because
We got to wait for all the cars become autonomous
And that's going to take time
And as you said
We may not we may not put
Maybe a Tipping Point where most of them are or something to that effect
Then I think it trickles down to the smaller vehicles I think we are ahead of the Curve
Related only because we talked about it last week member how we mention Google Glass making a comeback and Industrial and such
I'm actually thinking of on retiring my Google Glass to wear under my motorcycle helmet
Pacifically for a heads-up display for directions
Oh that feels like it was going to hurt your Bridge of your nose let me know how that works I have customized custom lenses
Is already inserted into custom glass frames for glasses
Sony came out
Oh yeah. Yeah you couldn't wear glasses with
But now
You can do that so
I look forward to hearing back from you on your both motorcycle test
Experiment
Let's get to the news bits portion
The show
Real quick
Eero
Hey we talked about them earlier
They are sponsored they acquired the thing to do it so last week
We said
Dington
Add shutdown
Kind of wanted to be an OS for the smart home well it turns out
Tom Coates and Matt Build-Off
T2 Founders and the only two employees I know of is
They have been
Aqua hired
And no one's talking much about what they're doing their butt
I look forward to it cuz
Like I said those guys are super smart and very thoughtful about living in
A connected home and how people interact
The connected home and how it's not a one-to-one
Other news tracker
Jose track r
The Bluetooth tracker company
I don't know what else to call it it helps you find yourself
50 million dollars
They compete with
Sceptile
I am interested in them because they have this product called tracker at
This is not out yet it was supposed to be out this summer so far
Not out yet but you plug these little plugs in there like Bluetooth
And they have an echo skill
So what happened
You plug the sit-in then
It knows what room things are in so you can say hey
Anime where is my wallet
It'll be like it is
Set the living room
But you know
It's great know where to start
I mean we'll see what happens when this product comes out of still available for pre-order as you said it's not out yet
But I'm scratching my head on this one because
I'm all for using Bluetooth as a location device I have some trackers that I purchased before SM tiles as well
But moving everything
To these two outlets
I just don't see the point of it because it really replicates what you should be able to do with your phone and a Tracker app
Meaning
You got the processing power on your phone
Two algorithmically figure out the
Signal strength of where a Bluetooth tracker is
And she kind of navigate you too
Great room without these things might
I think you might be right I think there might be like a Powertrain the people might be upset about also you've got to sell more Hardware
In the iot connected business model
I get the I get the business model
Don't know that makes sense and I would also say
I read about this company a couple of weeks ago it's called switch
They make Outlets
So I actually kind of like
One day we're going to have all of this in our outlets and by God that's going to be a beautiful day
Until then we may have to buy things that we
Plug-In or in Kevin's case we will just hope
What you downloaded
It doesn't for us
So
That's tracker other news
Wink
Was sold
William
Who is not just a rap star and
Outkast I was like
Not the Outlaws
Not the Fugees
Outkast
I was a member of Outkast and he also used to work for Intel as they're like creative
Technology Ambassador guy
It didn't go in
William has bought wink
The smart home platform
Flex Flex
Kevin
Is not happy
Did I say that out loud
Especially my inner monologue
Sorry about your inner monologue
Look I mean as a very happy wink owner
I mean I could have gone with a bunch of different platforms but I've
I'm stuck with wink because it doesn't work well for me
That was already sad when flexbot
Wink
Is a maiko what's going to happen now you know but everything seemed to be okay
And it was and now it's going to William
Who just my opinion does not have a very solid track record in the tech space
I remember when he came out with its wearable and I'm like please
Come on it was it was terrible
Minute you can't even get it now so
That tells you everything you need to know I I just I don't have confidence in
Disability and hopefully he's surrounded himself with
With good people
And
The wink
Hardware and services and software
Continue to expand but I just was not happy when I heard this news
Nathan Smith the former CTO a twink who is in charge of
He's actually gone over to Amazon
Another fellow that
I won't say his name
He's nice but he's one of the
People who
Have been a twink forever
Just left
For another job
I think we are going to have to I mean I'm willing to see but I think we might when people tell us they want a hub
We usually said if your
You're not really into like playing around and working real hard
Wink is the way to go
We may change that recommendation going
Forward back
SmartThings although it is
We'll talk about this in another show cuz we're running out of time but
It is also an indication of where the Hummer
It is
So
Lot's happened
Speaking up hugs
We asked you guys for questions and by God you delivered
So
We're going to take
A question
This week from
Tom brincefield
And this is a good question summarize at a little bit
So he's got a Google home and he is
Currently looking for things to automate
So he's got a Google home Philips Hue hubs and three color bulbs and a WeMo switch
Farmers porch lighting
So
He has
A problem though he wants to automate a fluorescent light over his kitchen sink
But it doesn't have a neutral wire so I can't use the WeMo switch
He wants is getting voice control
And remote control of that light
Second
He has a dumb monitor plasma TV a Samsung Blu-ray player and an older tuner that he run sound through
As well as the Chromecast audio for music
None of these work with voice control
Also is there any method that we know of that could give him the ability to turn these things on and switch some settings
Especially on the tuner
So
Tom
I feel like we got really good news for you
But it is going to cost you
That's usually how it works
Self
Your lighting question is so common that I actually knew automatically where to send you and
I did it myself
Sort of
Because
You want to have voice control and because you're dealing with a fluorescent which a lot of the kind of automated immersed
Don't
Fluorescence
I'm going to steer you to the Lutron system
For there on off switch
Because this is the only thing I know of that you can use without a neutral wire
It's still get voice
So what you're going to need in this is really important
Is the Lutron pd5 WS
/ DD / White
Actually the wh stands for white
So if you need an almond
But it's the Lutron PD 5ws
Slash TV
The five stamps
For 5 a.m.
And this is important because they have a 6 amp
26 AMP one requires a neutral wire
So you have to get the V amp
And you can order this Amazon has a really high price on it right
I ordered by and for
Like 65 Amazon bright now showing a hundred bucks for the
What you'll do is you
Pop the switch in
You're also going to need the Lutron Hub which is about $80
So
Then you got voice control of your fluorescent lights and I have mine for my under cabinet lighting
My husband always left on and I love it
I also have a lot of other Lutron switches
If you want to go that way
Go that way
I will tell you I am very hot
So that is the answer to your lighting question
For your television
Question
This what I thought was kind of tricky
But it actually wasn't
Stacy figure this out
Before the show
It looks like the
Only way might be to add yet another Hub and that would be the Harmony Hub
This is about
This is a
Little
I have one
I saw this conversation
Now before you buy it
You can either buy it and see if it works
Logitech has a list
Oldest tuners in stuff that support so because you didn't tell me what your tuner was I couldn't look it up
But but but
It does work with
Most
IR compatible devices yes
It has an eye it actually comes with a little IR blaster
This makes my husband go nuts
We had to put the
GoNoodle
It goes in our
AV cabinet
Under eye television
Total Wireless
Next to it
Because we don't have a
But it won't let me drill a hole in
I can fix that little
The other thing to note is for your Chromecast audio. 100% sure this is going to work
Kevin found
What did you find
I did find some support
Questions and answers about the Chromecast and Logitech Harmony Hub and
The only mention Chrome Cast audio which suggests to me that it does work is
That Harmony Logitech rather suggest you create a
A shortcut
Play music
And so on therefore it should work and in my opinion but it wouldn't tell you to create a shortcut
Chromecast audio play music if it didn't work so I suspect it does work
Probably support Chromecast
Audio it should work
But he has a Google home so you should be able to
Voice activated Chromecast audio ady
And control
Oh yes without even doing
I will say that I have my tuner setup
To play
Okay this is complicated but my Sonos goes through my tuner
To some of my speakers
I have set up a special thing
Special shortcut
Display Sonos living room
And so
The other nice thing is when you connect your Logitech to your Google home
You're going to have the option of naming the shortcut
Again for the Google
Or your Amazon Echo
For anyone who's
What do I do
So
Those are two things for you
You are going to pay
Let's see what brought it up to 280 so
300 box
I don't know if it's worth it
I spent
I have not
I'm crazy
Okay so that was a question for the week and here's our
Iot
Improbable device
Of the day
Is an Indiegogo campaign is for something called
Smalt
And Kevin
Would you like to tell us what the small tis
Yes we are talking about the small
Which stands for smart
Salt dispenser because of course everybody needs a smart
South
Dispenser
But it's more than just a selfish Spencer it's a centerpiece according to the Indiegogo campaign
You can play music through the
Integrated Bluetooth speaker you can set the mood with multicolored lighting
And of course the Spencers in any amount you please
I'm sorry but
There's just no place for Texans
This is going to be $99 for the super early bird special
But the actual price of a 199 when it hits
So it ships
March 28th
So we're going to have to wait awhile
I don't think it's going to shift at all
You're probably right my favorite part is
It is
To dispense
A tablespoon of salt but if you don't have an echo you can go in the app
Hindu gestures
Because I know when I'm dispensing salt
I really want to open my phone
Solutely
Absolutely
And I've seen decently large salt shakers before this is big
I'm looking at a picture of it right now and it's like a two-handed device
It is yeah this is
It looks like a slightly smaller it looks like a bigger tap
Actually
Yes
Solace
If you've ordered one of these sentences explain why
That is stupid
Telus
Why if you were one of the backers of this product
Is it
For this week show
Hico Solutions
Sam George of Microsoft
Lots
About it
Other teas
Now I'm just getting silly
Stay tuned
Hey everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Foster is Hico Solutions
And I have Jeremy
YouTube Mitch here
From haikou
Who's going to tell me a little bit about
What Hico is
Jeremy
Quite simply actress Lucia
Advanced iot engineering firm
Our mission is
To really messed up
Product owner
Cyanide
Executive here in the United States
Are really trying to sell some the bus
Coyote engineering problems
We bring in some of the brightest software Engineers embedded
Systems engineer
And data scientists out of Eastern Europe
And several hundred Engineers that we have on our team
Over 60% of these Engineers have
Either am I
Serious or a PhD
Degree many of them are still lecturing
In the University system in Eastern Europe
And actually out of all of the employees at
We have an Ico over 60% of the degrees are in mathematics if we have some of the brightest stars individuals that are
Really working on cutting-edge research and development in the area of iot
And it's our job to put them in touch
And how does an engagement with haikou happen
How does that get started
Generalist
Peking a client is going to start with a smaller
Call it a pilot project
Where they're just going to get an opportunity
Is this going to be a good fit for us
And then really for us to why should we be working together
Because let's face it I can
Sit here and tell you how great we are in
Provide you with some really solid documentation that
It's super technical any Bill to see you like well can maybe these folks know what they're doing
But the reality is you need to get connected
And get some knowledge from them firsthand
Communication
10 strong
You can just
We want you to be comfortable knowing that you have a good partner
And until you interact with
The team that you can be working with
It's just really
Difficult to know that so you know you got a small piloting
This how we would get started
Jeremy that sounds great so how can I get in touch with haikou solution
Go to our website. Www.
Hypoglycin solutions.com
There's a lot of that great information regarding our service
Against
Tyco - solutions.com
Text Jeremy and guys.
Haikou
Hi
200 - solutions.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the
Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Sam George the director of iot for Microsoft azure
Hi Sam how are you today
Great Stacy thanks for having me
Me and I am super excited we have had several conversations
And every single time
We have
Yeah I learned a lot so this time I'm excited to bring the rest of you guys listing
Along for the ride
So
Let's get started with
Conversation about
Iot architecture
So
You guys when we first talked
We had a big conversation
A couple years ago
You're a half ago about pain
A lot of happening in the cloud
I think you were looking at head of the middle area so not the edge but that
Middle Gateway area in your life
I don't know if I'll be there
And how is that change
Because it certainly has
Yeah when
We didn't realize
Really early on that
Is iot got going that there is going to be the Natural Balance
Natural
Equilibrium if you will
Between
Processing that happens in the cloud
What happens at all devices
And so that's always been one of that Central Central tenants
We were looking at
Reintroduced
A Gateway a c k
Last year
Just now
So you capabilities as well for a joke
Definitely
Definitely a
Beacon Central
Docker iot
Strategy
How are you guys
Defining the edge cuz when I think of the edge I think cloud
Then I think
Gateway that usually on-premise and then when I think of edge I actually think of
No it's not necessarily sensors but maybe so
Will you find edges anything that's
Capable of running
Intelligence
Located on physical
Outside the cloud
That could definitely be a gateway
Could definitely be an iot node or combination of the two
It really just depends on capabilities
Mean
As you look at that
Spectrum of device
Ituc everything
Sensors all the way up through
Oblong gateways
And everything in between
And so when we think about Edge
We think about you know there's these waves of computing they're happy
This Cloud
Coyote
Leverage
Cloud in an edge leverages Cloud II
And we
Slightly different and iot is about sending signals from those devices
Attacking on the signal
Betches about
Pushing cop intelligence
Into the devices themselves
Silicon man
Offline
Are low latency loops
Fail-Safe systems in cases local network outages
I mean another big trend is simply just minimize any amount of data that's being transferred
Between devices in the cloud that's part of that equilibrium
Everything about between edging
Okay and you just threw in like a whole new
I don't even know what to call it
So
I got you
So when you're tired iot just being signaling
Can you help me understand what's your talk
Looking for example no customers doing predictive maintenance
Industrial Park
I don't want to smoke or service that are under service
If a device is simply just sending
Sheepshead sedated
The cloud and your doing
G'morning and analytics Fair
Need to determine the maintenance window and maybe even your shut down the machine in case of a pending failure
Yeah I kind of classify that usages
Pretty straightforward and Vanilla Ice.
Edge's for the vet next week where
Instead of
Sending all of that data to the cloud
I can't
Or processing
I can take
The processing and move it to where data is
Because
As machines at Society really gets going
These devices generate more and more and more data data has gravity
It's much easier to move
Computer where data is
Cutest
So
In this example that was
Just giving about industrial equipment
Much easier does take that cloud intelligence about
When do I need to shut this down or when the maintenance going to need to be adjusted
Tickets on the cloud and just
Right right on the
So on the IRT thing I'm thinking this is a differentiator here is there's not a real-time element
For the edge stuff I thinking
Real time
I'm thinking maybe a conservation of data
It's not making decision
There's no decision-making happening
Some intelligence
Fighting to take action
In an unsupervised manner
Okay so when I look at all these iot edge things that are
Coming
Count you guys have yours
Their competitors have
That's the decision
Exactly
Exactly now you guys work with a lot of
Big Industrial
Most of the big players that I talk to you there like Azure all the way
So I'm very curious because you're probably dealing with this right now this divide that they have between the it side of the house
In the operational side of the
And
I'm wondering how far the it infrastructure
Can actually stretch cuz
If I talk to someone like Honeywell
They have parts of their Factory automation
It's on their gear
On their private Network
And a lot of wire
So
I'm curious how far into that infrastructure you
You can go or you even want
But I think that's a big
Part of why
Weekly schedule such an important concept
Because
There's many many times where you want
All about logic
Then you want to be able to
El Pollo Loco
In a local itot teams
You're a lot of people especially in the commercial and industrial iot space
Want to make sure that their data saves resident
I think that we're doing with iot Edge and also with Azure stack
Billy about in England
Who is managing these and buying them
He's inside these
Because
I talked to these OT guys and they are
Very smart
They're very smart about different things
What I think the typical Azure customers
Iot is the
Anchorman that really forces
Itot games
To work together
And
Your customers that have worked that out
It worked out that the balance between the two
OT teams realize
I keep going to be managing
And it teams respect the OT discipline
When that really works
Can you can have iot
Enabled for that business
What are some best practices that you see in your customers who are actually able to
What are they doing today like
Right chest pain
The most successful customers they don't think about it
Disciplining an OT different
I'm thinking about
And what happened to different phases of the car
And we'll wind up happening is it both different 1/2
Coordinate those rolls
So for example
There's a role for
Designing software
Designing a software that runs on a hardware
Updating that
True
It what's the top-rated going to be running on it and what's her update strategy
Taking people from both discipline and having to be accountable
Designing that process together
Helps break down some of those barriers
Okay how often does that actually happen
It really depends on the cusp
Some customers that have been around for a long long time you know for OT has been around a lot longer and it
That can take a long time to break down
It really starts with
Leadership and will
Commanded the next two teams are going to work together
Waterpik 150 Prime
I'll bring the other one along
It is the
The prime one
Is it usually OT
I think it really varies I'm starting to feel more more it
Actually
Anthony industry
In a world where we've got like
Breezy security breaches happening
And even when you know you're dealing with like compliance issues at big companies are
Maybe your tracking hazardous chemicals and
This whole iot ecosystem
How do you
Track
Your partner's both
Appliance perspective or just bring them on board for lie
Tracking
Materials I mean is it's very tough
So
What are you seeing developed
What are you guys thinking
To make that easier
Let's pick on security for a second
That looks like for example that you know I'm a customer I'd go pick solution and eye solution
And I had some partners that were involved in helping me with that are that are still operating
For me
In that situation you know you've had many hands touch their iot project
I'm so nope I'm at customer and I want to
That's the question which it should
Life Solutions
Cure
It's not a simple answer because there's been so many for so many different parts
Absolution
Do we handle that
Is with Security Programs
Security program for add royalty
With third-party auditors
That you know we train on every key that
You can come and inspect
ONN solution
Import of what we're doing there
Is
And we work with standards bodies around the world
And a very important one we work with this industrial internet Consortium
And so we recently introduced
Security maturity model
And the reason why
Is it security maturity model
Is
Answer the question of
Which security
Techniques you need to bring to bear and iot for which
Types of something
Because
We hear a lot of customers asking us to
Am I secure
And can I say that I'm certified to be secure
I like the Cure
For what
What specifically until you have to start talking about
Different types of techniques that were employed and what the security maturity model
Is a way of
Everyone agreeing and that's why we're doing it in a standard body
Is everyone agreeing in a hay for these types of scenarios
This level of security is
Appropriate
The things that we're doing on
But that sort of touches to your question about Hugo 6
Square
If there are a lot of hands and balls
You need to find a way to certify the thing
How to make sure certified the solution and make sure that it itchy the level of
Appliance
Security
Date of residency
There's also this
Idea of
It's ever-changing
So is new vulnerabilities
Pure or maybe someone shifts
I've talked to people who've had one of their
Your partner switch their underline Cloud Player
Right or maybe their database provider
All of a sudden
They've opened up a hole that they didn't
It may not even be security it may just be breaking some functionality further down in the chain
Chasing all of that
Is tough
But you can't tell people
Thou shalt
Change
And that is where Auditors come into play
Play this word you know there's an expert
Bet you make a living doing this
Do your partners proactively have to notify you
What does that so
Many of the solutions that we see and IRT
Is you'll have a partner that will develop
Solution
Coyote
Where
The partner secures devices build the solution
And many times operated on
So there's not
You don't get into a case where there's no lots and lots of vendors that are
Words that end in solution
Is iot
Industrial iot in particular
Enterprise
Really scalable yet
I need it feels like everything is still
Fairly
Custom
Because Industries require highly specific
Because you have these kind of
Custom built Solutions
The bear may not be hosted on
Your cloud or somebody else's
But still
Yeah yeah
At this point
There's still a tremendous amount of vertical specialization
And I think that there's always going to be
Yeah like that degree of
Your vertical specialization
The thing that you see all of us stealing is
Providing more and more functionality
That reduces the amount of vertical specialization that
If you were to do an iot Solutions say 5 years ago
You would have
Painted some virtual machines and build something custom yourself
Now we have platform services
Where you don't have to worry about scalability
We handle that part for you
You can connect devices in billions of Massachusetts
That reduces the amount of vertical specialization
And then
They have
You like we've introduced
Assassin
So that you don't even need Cloud solution development expertise in order to build
And so
Yes you're absolutely right now the iot industry is still
Pretty nails
So what you're saying and I think it a pretty rapid pace
You're seeing
Provide more and more functionality so that
There's less specialization required
I have to ask this question
Chi products deep billions
Millions of messages
I was talking to somebody who's up for a diet
T solution and they were actually frustrated because they couldn't find one that could handle
Hundreds of millions of synchronous messages
I like what that seems like a lot
He's like well consumer Products Company
I want
I need to be able to do that
I understand that
What's the kind of technologies that
People
Need that we don't have yet
So what are you guys looking for that your customers are like
August 1st
That would be cool
That's a great question
What are the challenges
Imagine for a second that you know you could all tonight
Solution
And you know you're going to add
What's a 1090 device
Typically that what you see is you know
Contact
Pilot
Great limited device that you know you do your scale test
One of the challenges after you get all that in place
Shift from being getting a solution in place
To provision
Impala saying software staff
Things are slow
You can put Asian
Capacity for handling
Billions of messages in minutes
But to actually your provisionals devices and make them operational
Cat cakes
That's where you at we look at problem like that we say
Hey that's a great example where we need a service it does that
That's why we introduced a device provisioning service
Tysons Corner
Contact it
Give permission to the right
After service
And then no download latest software operational
Ice provisioning
If you have something in the sexy sexy
No it's it a lot of the stuff is is
Spacek
Tackling it feels like for computing problems
You know a lot of people
Managing hundreds of thousands of servers
And so
Okay let's take all of that
Running
How to do the world where we have no control over things in their devices
Have not a lot of
And maybe not even great network connection
That's right
Do you have any cool favorite things that people have built that you're like
I can't believe they did this
It's crazy
My favorite right now is what Hershey's is done
You know top of
Add Realty
If that's something they call the internet a Twizzlers
And
Actually
Connected Twizzler production plant
Azure iot
To optimize it
One of the challenges
Someone like Hershey's faces when they're producing Twizzlers
Is when
Put a bunch of Twizzlers in a package
It says it weighs 3 ounces
It has to wait at least 3 ounces
And
Tuning your
Factory
The bad you know
It produces a predictable number
Twizzlers
Cancer in the mouth
Turns out to be a heart problem
Tibetan example where
They used
Machine learning
As well as
Connectivity to the cloud
In order to monitor
Production batch
Spell the liquor she's being
Mixton
And so they can tuna production bat
Any extruders
To generate
Precise
Face of a bunch of money
So we just bought some the other day
And I was telling people on the team
This is using our stuff
I mean it's just an amazing thing
Be part of an industry
They compared those kind of scenario
Okay that is awesome in on that sweet note
We shall end
The show
Sam
Thank you so much for coming on
The show this week
Casey Oliver pleasure thank you that's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more
You can sign up for my newsletter Stacy who sings
Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week