Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofu
Hey we have a champ at
Show for you
Are you talking about
So does his new terms of service
Talking about a lawsuit
Regarding terms of service
And we're going to say the phrase TOs
Google's got some new headphones that my
Assistant
Can I ask
What happened to the Nvidia spot
Do some news bits take a reader question
And talk about a new project that we built here at the show
We also got a message from our sponsor Hyksos Solutions and our guest this week
Nick Dawson
Who's the head of innovation at Johns Hopkins Sibley Innovation Center
We talked about building a quote-unquote
Road Network for Consumer it for hospital patients
A message from
Another one of our awesome
This week sponsor
Eros
Arrow makes a mesh Wi-Fi
That is
Awesome I have it in my home it is
Currently Powerade over 50 connected to places they just launched their second generation mesh wi-fi system
It contains 10111 beacons and the beacons are basically access point
Plug-in around your house and they just expand the coverage and this isn't complicated to do like a tradition
National kind of network extender where you got to have late at work
D-rose recognize each other and they're like
You can buy individual heroes or
Word that begins to add to your current system if you're a first generation Eero customer I bought an additional begin for about a hundred
$49 because I needed a little extra coverage for my Wi-Fi video doorbell
Start at 399 410 into begins now ships
The Canada and for listeners of the show if you go to ww.w. E r o g e r
O.com you can buy your Eros for 399 and get free shipping with a code
Stacy
I love my Eros and hopefully if you get yours you will love them too
All right now back to the show
Let's get started with a meeting
An intense
Topic that
People have very strong
My feelings about
It is not
Politics
Sonos is new
Terms of service in this is part of an overall trend that we
A lot actually
Are we buying Hardware are we buying
Services for
We pick up its neck
Kevin you want to break down 10 of the Sonos drama for us
Yeah
And I do not have a
As soon as I know you do something curious separate
Now
Alright then overachiever
So I am not
Affected by this
Basically Sonos has said that users must accept the new privacy policy
Weather devices the Sonos audio devices May cease to function
They're not letting you up
Out of their new privacy policy
And that's not good I mean it's pretty much a
All or none situation the way things
Are looking right now
I am very curious what you think about this because you have a
And I have some just hide
What is your feeling as a Sonos customer
So
I was so disgust
I
Understandably miffed
At the idea that might
Devices
That I bought
I bought my first Sonos back
It was like
Yeah it was
It was a weird mm
Baby 2009 my first one
And then when we moved I spend another $2,000 by
I can't remember the part names but little connectors Ono's things for my
In-ceiling speakers in
That wasn't
12 Sol
As an existing Sonos customer I'm probably going to
Well I am going to
Except these and I would accept it almost blindly just be
Because I want
Dysfunctional
Play Lose My Soul
But
For people who are
Upset
I understand they're upset in this
Because
Buying something
Even if you just bought it last year
One of the questions I have is how long before they
Degrade the server
Best rate
2 years
Terrible if it's
10 years
I feel like
Maybe a bit more reasonable although this is why I think
Connected devices
Expiry date basically
Appoint over which you would not support the software because
Front about this kind of thing
From Sonos is perspective I understand why they're doing
If they're going to start offering Integrations with other devices
And if they're going to
Do these Services All In
They're going to have to have a measure of control
Over how they purr
Pro-Med customer relations
Soto says you don't have to send all of your data
But you will have to send what
Functional
Email address IP addresses account login information
As well as device date information about Wi-Fi internet
Other Hardware
Information
And
Location is in there as well
Okay
You can't opt out of it
You can't opt out of the functional data
Right
Privacy people are
Understandably
And I get it
But I also see
Why sodas wants
If your Sonos isn't
Performing well
With another device
It needs to be able to
Now the question
Personas dispersed
Is if no one wants to add these additional features and just wants to use their
Old Sonos has
Until
Brake switch
How to play five
Almost eight years and it's
Looks great
Works fine but
For Sonos sub
Sporting those devices
Plus another set of software for the new gradle with other connected devices system
Good become cost-prohibitive really quickly
So I think that
The challenge
And I would agree that
What song is this
Trying to do at least partially is
To lack of better term control the experience or offer a guaranteed minimum level of positive
They need to have some control over the devices to make sure
Everything's working the way it should
So that its customers are happy
Flipside is
Support
I use the June oven as an example you and I both purchased one
I had some problems with my first one
And when I reach out to support they said okay
Will you give us
You're okay to go into the logs of your device
So we can troubleshoot it
Absolutely I said
They normally would not be looking at that
So it's a way to do this on a case
Space spaces from support standpoint
Yes but they were collect
Data
So
Do all these they're just saying
Hey we used to not collect
This data and now we have to
Now we want to
I would say there's a couple things they could do he
The closest example I can think of
What is Google when it bought revolve
Call Cyn
This revolver was a smart home hub that Google bought
Mostly for the engineering
Revolve worked on a completely different set up the nest
Which is Google's other Hardware
Platform
Thing at the time
Google shut revolved
It just didn't make sense to operate those two things and have the move them over
Have those soccer teams basic
And so
When they shut it down they did so very poorly they were more than 10,000 customers
People freaked out
And as a result Google said okay
Will do
So they did
Refunds I don't know if they were hold a partial refunds
For this device
Sonos has a
Heart problems
Because they have way more devices
A full refund
Do a partial refund
Coupon they could do something for the customers
Don't
What
Their sister
And they should
Also
Not say that it will cease to work
In some nebulous future although I understand why that's
EOS
Are privacy policies
But they should actually come up with a plan
Say something like hey your devices
Spell failing
We pledge to
Support these devices
Till this time frame and it should be
Reasonable time
It should be
These devices in this service as you
No
Evolve
Pretty quickly
New hardware features
New services and so on anycast 2.4
Carpenters Tipping Point
Hey I just got a really old one of our products
We're just we just can't support you anymore because we've always you Advanced features in the newer products and so on so forth so
That's a little concerning me but that's the way this industry is right now
Well it would function they would have to pledge to keep a functional version
Of what they offered
Today on those device
I don't think that's crazy although with like
Eventually
Sonos works on your wi-fi system
But it also has appropriate
Network
And I don't know but if you could support that for an additional 10 years beyond your
I think that would actually
It even say that
I think that would go a long way to curbing some of this out
So that's just the sort of stuff
Another challenge
Experiencing right now
How is this
Oh my God what am I
We are still working that out
And there are not a lot of Protections in
Place for consumers as this happen
And Kevin and I talked about this
Ear when you buy a Kinect
It does behoove you to read the terms
In conditions that terms of service to privacy policy
Pretension
And not every company has that
I will call again
And for some sort of standard
How
We communicate
Data practices
To consume
In every device should come with a label
That says
In plain English we followed you
Practices
Right maybe something as simple as a Good Housekeeping seal of a
Although you can buy
We are but something something before
A consumer makes a purchase
They need to understand
For they make the purchase of my penny
Right
Because once you've made the purchase
You opted with
It's clicking on this thing and then you're like
Rap I've been selling my
My grocery list every week
That sucks
That's what
And then to
Is I think we really need some legal protections
Probably a few class action lawsuits to settle this
So in other news on this front
Anti-consumer kind of
Device Services challenge
The second court of appeals for the southern district of New York
Actually overturned a lower Court's decision
About Uber
And it's terms of sir
Basically a complaint
Was made
That
Uber's terms of service should be valid
Because you get it on your phone screen
Like I need a ride okay
Click yes
And you don't read it
And basically the court said
You know what you have
How to read those so
It said that
The arbitration clauses
Uber's terms of service
We're actually fine
They were legal in
This person
Click through to it
And said yes
Search two things that are bad
About this one
Terms of service
Terrible
They can take
Literally
Over an hour.
Like I will be to turn the service
Because legal jargon
By forcing
Arbitration arbitration clauses that are in these terms of sir
The court has basically said
All of the litigation or
Maturity is a litigation that we're going to have around the Internet of Things
It's going to happen behind closed doors
And that's terrifying
Yeah and any
For one thing you may have
Similar situations arbitrated differently so you'll have different outcomes
Secondly as you said behind closed doors we don't know we as consumers don't know
What's really being
Disgust
Decided and so on and
These are products
And services that millions of people use so
We need to know this
So
Sonos perspective
It's someone's like a su about this I think this
It's a sucky that they're breaking my device
If they had a terms of service originally that says hey you're going to arbitration
That could happen
Replicas
Customer support
Waive the right to sue the company as a result of agreeing to the terms of service if they have arbitration clauses in there
So
What are we saying to you
Find connected Hardware
You should read the terms of service
And
I'm also saying that we
Probably need to come up with more consumer-friendly
Explain privacy
Explain data retention policy
Also
Understand that there's a reason companies are
Selecting some of this data
If a company wants to change the terms of service on it
An existing device
I actually think that's
Because I get why they're doing it
If you're going to break some
You know it's funny because
A lot of this
Has happened in the past and it wasn't really highlighted people didn't realize
The computer world
If you're on Windows
There's a lot of telemetry data captured by these
Computers and devices
That's not new
That's actually
Happened four years
And there's a reason for an estimate the products better and see
Maybe people are clicking a start button windows
Don't need to because they have what they want is already
Shown their you know so that tells Microsoft
Tweak rui and saucer with make it better
It's a little different I think with these very personal type devices though
I meant I think that's why it's getting more attention now
Agreed
Okay
Skip ahead to some fun news
Google
Offering headphones
That's the report and this comes by way of a teardown or
Viewing of
The newest Google Assistant
APK which is it an Android X
Executable settings the app itself you can look at the code if you have a
A program that can open the APK and that's what
Books 495 Google
There's a lot of code strings in
The
Google assistant app
Alluding to on device called Bistro Bistro
My name is spelled
I don't know but
Regardless
The deal is all these
Code Snippets point to headphones that will
Have Google Assistant built in
We just got interesting at school because actually I just
Qualcomm
Play survey
Interested in wireless wireless headset
Connect to the internet
Baby Alive
LOL and I was just going to say that it's a trend growing friend because
More devices more Mew device
Particularly are losing their 3.5 millimeter headphone jack so
Going Wireless
I'm okay with it
Smile couple pair of
The Bluetooth headphones so I
What I like to have
Magic word to the Google Assistant get information
This will be
But again we don't know yet and there's no official
News from Google on this is just people being around in the
APK
And the other speculative
Google News
Compete with
Either the Amazon Echo dot or possibly
Oh okay well there's a homepod
News 2 so
I was like
What is happening
Google homepod or Apple
Right and I I don't I don't think it's a true
Apples to Apples comparison to punto because the homepod
I believe is going to debut at $349 where is a smaller Google home would be more like an
Can Echo dot work
Where are you feed we talked about last week
And
Should I hope cost $50 or less
I would have
Show Kevin
You doing some research here whatever happened to the Nvidia spot what is the
What a great Segway because I just talked about
Home assistance for $50 or less
I don't know if folks remember but back at CES in
January Nvidia
Debuted its newest version of the Nvidia Shield TV which is an Android TV set-top box
And you haven't
I do I bought one and I use it all the time
Fantastic
Sky 4K support for streaming HDR support
Android
TV apps and games
Controller
A voice remote
My TV my game is everything through it
Part of the reason I bought it was because the day they debuted this
Sexy as they also said coming soon
Will be our Nvidia spot
Which is a
$50
Little microphone
That you plug in I believe to an outlet and you buy multiple inputs
And basically turn your whole house into a giant microphone
Nile Clinic do that my whole house but I thought
I can put this in a couple rooms that way I don't need to be
You're my one single Google home
Get information song
They said
Coming in months and months and months are past now because we're now into she's almost September
I don't know what's happened to this it still
On the website the website you can still cook to notify me
I just think it's almost a missed opportunity each day goes by in this video is not available
Yeah
So you don't actually know
I just saying
If you find this service
Okay
Tucson news
Speculation is that AT&T Digital Life Division that is there connected
Home automation and security offering
Is for sale
AT&T Apple back on this couple years ago Verizon's actually
Nickelback
Animation
Meanwhile
In the ISP world
Comcast
Des Moines
It makes sense
AT&T separately
So we'll see
Who might buy it
Gosh
Companies
We talked about 1
Couple weeks ago called perdia that is
Offering the back
Software
For this type of
Service
I don't think they would want
Actually manage the footprints oh my
I'm just someone like ATT
Which are also really bacon homeschool
That makes sense for purchase and interesting
Glen
Blurry
From AT&T
He is
Stepping down
Yes the president CEO of AT&T Mobility operations I believe that
Blake suit next month or two
What would I find super interesting he says his house has a hundred and sixty-five connected devices
So I'm curious who does by this because
I'm sure that his all-round AT&T Digital Life
Cheese
Combined
Although it may not be more than Charlie King
Tesla
Hot robots
I love the now robot
It is 6
Good thing
No amount of money can keep you safe
Basically
What they did
Basically control the arm of a collaborative multi-jointed
Robot
These robots can extend as far as
Lift up to 22
2 lb industrial setting
Is airsoft
Caesars
These robots that use what's called a buffer overflow attack
And that's basically so you send all kinds of data until the
Did Isis like
And
Then they overwrote the safety file
And so then you could make it they could control.
Richard Scarry
That is a problem
These are the robots that use in the game soccer robotics soccer games on TV ever watch those
Music
I have no
Control Alexa remotely and make my team win
What if someone had a hacker
Okay
You want to know more about the
It's pretty creepy and videos
In the show
Project this weekend
I don't want to tell you about it this week I'm going to tell you about it
Going to tell you about it
Because we're almost out of time but first
I want to answer
A reader question
And
Some of you may have this problem
So it's a question
This guy has for security camera
This question is
Dave
Upstate New York
Hello Dave
He has for security cameras installed
And they're all power over ethernet
Are HD cameras three of them having to be pause cams in one or trend
He's
Tie them all together using software called I spy which is a
Open source software
To make them all run together
It's on Eazy-E
But he really wants a unifying platform
Form for security and iot devices
And so he's got the hard wire traditional alarm system
He's got Google home Google Wi-Fi he's got SmartThings
She's got cameras
State wants to integrate
And he wants this unifying popcorn
So he's thinking he might use a Raspberry Pi to create a web server so he doesn't
Computer all the time
Yay
But she's wondering if there's another
It sounds like it really that the sticking point here is the cameras themselves getting
Using camera things to trigger
Kemmerer events to trigger automation
If I'm understanding it
That's my boy
It's a little Leah this is what
We're going to recommend Blue Iris
Softer and I know there are issues with blue iris but people have loved it in the past
A lot of Peter questions actually it
And blue iris has an integration with the Amazon Echo
Google
Now
The Amazon Echo integration
Is actually an official Blue Iris skill
And so
The link to how this works
Accurately
So you can do that day
There's also other services that will tie together
Blue Iris with Google home
Called Dash Runner
That's her voice commands for both
It will it will I use blue iris
A couple years ago with the couple of Ip webcams but at that point I didn't know how that automated system here
The only thing I could do is actually a kind of automated that it's like send a tweet
Every hour of what was outside my window just for
Profundus I was hacking kicking things around
But there may be
Some scripting that you can do with it might even be some ways to tie things together with
Honest-1
Well so I also found a blue iris Fusion software this is on the SmartThings platform
So if you search for Blue Iris on SmartThings you're going to find
Actually says it ties everything together
It's going to be a little complicated but
I think they gave you were up to it since you were going to build your own
Using the pie in
All this yourself
Set rich with IP camera this is a challenge
If you go with
Say I nest
Or another similar type device that is more of a service-based things cuz IP cameras too.
Get a camera and you make it work yourself
Where at
Nasty they have a service for you and
You can build off of that or they can go outside so that's
That's the tricky part that's kind of getting away from IP webcam
So that's our thought on that
My sponsor and
Foreign
Awesome guests
This is Nick Dawson who is head of innovation at Johns Hopkins
Community Hospital
And he is going to blow your mind with cool stuff he's doing using things like Amazon dash button
Philips Hue Lights and
Even Sonos
Hey everyone this is Stacy and we are breaking into the podcast for a message from our sponsor this we sponsor is haiku
Do Solutions and we have Martin mauersberger who is the CEO of high
So remind me again what is high CO2
We are in
Advance Auto
Lucky engineering Solutions provider
With Development Centers in Eastern Europe
We have primarily used Bass Lines by providing engineering teams
Help them
Design artist
With heart radio
And not ending
With mathematical data flask
The data they collect
So let's dig into that a little bit more can you explain what the service is that your
Providing
Requires
Real world data to be sourced from a thing
Or not
You need to transmit
Through the internet to some form of backend
Were you practicing
You also
Time to activate a phone
On the side of the object based on
Giggling
Sunday sounds pretty pretty
Easy Button
Entails a variety of operation
Baleful requires number of
The first
Resource from a sensor and then transmitted either directly or through a gate with a Q
System work can be analyzed or visualize
The other way around Dayton
To be transferred back to the object
Where it causes
A desired app
And that's usually outside
Wow that's going to cover a lot of things so what kind of skills do you employee
Provide
Disservice
We have experts
An analog and digital electronics
An embedded software engineering
They focused on
The size of the thing
Orgeat
Then we need to cover
Communication
And that was done by Engineers who understand
OSI stack
And then we
Various
Data scientist
Mapreduce algorithm
Which analyze the data
Front-end software developers to create the user interface
Is Rudy a range
Back in Turkey
That does sound like a lot of interface
Is that something
Concerned about
Well you have the coordination of different skills is most
There are differences
Language or terminology
A good example would be an electronic in
Together with him
Visalia Dental
The mathematician
Expresses the imaginary part of
Complex number as the letter i
Where's the electronic
Give me will understand
Current
Port a tectonic engineer
An imaginary number is represented by the letter j
So we need to make
The date
Understand
Speak the same language
How does Ico a
Address that
Over the years
Training programs
That makes sure the teams collaborate efficiently
This is also
Why are combined experiences
Cindy found in areas I was incredibly valuable.
We remove this learning curve
And where can I find out
Go to our website
Hyper solutions.com
Www.icsolutions.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest we have
Nick Dawson
Who is the executive director of innovation for the
Johns Hopkins Sibley Innovation Hub
Hello Nick
Hey good morning Stacy
Man I am super excited to have you on the show beat
Because
I'm really excited about what you're doing for innovation in iot and hot
Herself
Let's just get started with telling me a little bit about
What you do
For the Johns Hopkins community hospital in
But you work
I have tried for wieden here for about 4 years and I tried for four years to come up with a really short pixie way of saying
Saying this and I still stumble on it but
In short we are a team of human-centered designers and technologists
Sand
Project people in the heart of literally sitting in a space in the main lobby
Of a hospital
In our job
To constantly look for
Ways to reinvent reimagine improve and fix Healthcare
Mostly we try to do that Through The Eyes of patients and Families
That was pretty good
It's hard to be pissy when you're talking about the lives of patients and Families
So you're on the show
Because you and I've had this amazing conversation about
Putting
Technology into patients rooms
Let's get started by it with you just sharing what your journey
Maybe two years ago two and a half working on a project
Try to give patients more control over their room in their experience in your laying in a hospital bed
You don't have a lot of control even over the physical environment let alone what happens to you and in this is right about the time the
I guess I got to be careful about it I can't say the a word the
Padme is what week
Matinee
Had just come on to seeing it we said alright let's experiment
Let's just prototype
The concept of giving people voice control
Over a root and so we bought a couple of them and that's when we said oh my gosh how are we going to get Madame a connected to this
Highly secure
Appropriately secured
Corporate Network
And you can imagine that inside this corporate network is
Highly regulated
Protected patient information and
Clinical information in medical science information and then there's also the all the gear there's MRI machines that are network
Connected
IV pumps and sore pretty particular about what can go on to a hospital Network
Working what can
We got no problem with a guest Network
Work we can get this thing on the guest Network
Work but the guest network has a captive portal
And there was no way without an interface to clear the captive portal we can we talk about
Spoofing the MAC address and he said you know
This is our chance to do something a little bit
And so we ended up
Running a completely separate line
Call the local ISP and said would you come install a line in our hospital that's separate from the hospital Network
Set up our own
Infrastructure in here and
It kind of laid the groundwork to say oh my gosh what can we do now
That we have this
Separate
Air gap
Non-clinical Network
On which two
To start innovating in and open the door to saying all of these consumer things
That we said wouldn't be need to try that in the hospital oh yeah but we can't
Now all the sudden he said well we can't Miss Israel easy we can put
Hue Lights and Sonos in Chromecast in a room and start to see if that at least provides a little bit of Creature Comforts
And kind of gone from there
Okay so did you ask
Permission before you installed the Sip
How did that go over
With corporate it
This is just between us right
Pegasus
Nobody will hear that I said all of the 25000
So we did
We're we're having a lot of those conversations now and it will
Beebe Road we didn't say work
Explicitly not going to have
Conversation
But we were tapping into I think
It's really special
Unique about our setup
Is we're chartered by our CEO
And part of that Charter was
Do things differently
We looked at it and said we're not
Substantial risks
One of the members of our team is a cyber-security researcher from DARPA
Zoe
We had a pretty good
Putting stand on
So we didn't we kind of just built this separate Shadow Network
End
Instead of having the conversation about is that okay
We had the conversation instead about what can we do for doctors nurses and patients
Add value or make your jobs or days easier
In
Those things
Became
More of the story than this separate Network
It's workout mostly we started to
Like any innovation
I think there's a point where if you
When you start to
Really create a lot of value and change
You got a bubble up over the surface a little bit then people start poking around and see will hang its make sure everything here is kind of copacetic
Enterprise in Byram
It's a good conversation to have
Okay well let's not skip ahead to that
Conversation let's talk about what you guys actually have done let's start with
Patient rooms
First of all just to say I keep going back
What does it do to say we've got this high speed
Robots
Non-clinical net
Networking once we started using that phrase in our own heads is it okay that opens up a lot of opportunity
In that same
That we were originally prototyping some voice stuff around when I
How do we get madhumeh connected to our Network more
And became this design-driven project who he said
How could we give somebody
Device an interface to do two things
Let's get
Real-time feedback
So if something is going well
We're not going well
We know in the moment
So we wanted to have this
This way of getting
Real-time feedback
There's also something else really powerful as we were interviewing patients and families in
That deep design-driven works
We'll just have to learn what's wrong we can give people the tools in the services in the ability to control
And have more empowerment
Turns out when you get
Choice and give them control that leads to more dignity and there's this incredible halo effect
Comes with it
And so we were setting out from this path we said
The thing that makes sense is some kind of tablet interface and we didn't know if that was going to be like
Custom thing built into the bed that we would build me a box that up in
Belittle 3D printed version above of an iPad holder that
Baby clip window bed stand and ended up finding kind of fortuitously
Is this incredible
Partner
Who's a startup company
Makes these tablets and custom interfaces for hotels
So you're
Checking into a hotel you walk in your room and they're sitting next to the bed stand is a
Is a tablet
It says welcome Stacy to your room
Can you tap it and you can say I want room service at this time I need a new pillow I need an Uber to come pick me up and it
Knows which room you're in in so it'll buys you when you were gets there
It has Pandora built-in inside had some entertainment stuff and I had to delete order Postmates and headed Bill directly to your room and he said
If we trying to coat our own version of this I will take us a year to not even do half as men
Many things is they figured out how to do at a hotel
So
We said would you ever come work in a hospital
And they said we don't know anything about Healthcare it
It terrifies us I know it's highly regulated
By the way
We can get our device on your network
Working me Centro that's where the magic comes in we're a team that can help you Shepherd you through so that was the thing that really became
Our biggest use case was he's tablets in patient rooms
To give people the ability to give us real-time feedback and have control over their experience
And it kind of snowballed from there
So you got this tablet
One of the things that we
We talked about previously was this idea
That you are not solving
Medical
Problems
We talked about iot and hospitals is being
Part of patient care
But what you guys are actually doing is taking the load off
From nurses
Spike reading the side Network
Requesting
Yeah that's exactly it in the clinical care is in
Credit report
And their people with high levels of domain expertise
It ought to be able to focus on just doing that
But there is so much more
About being a patient
It gets not being able to do the things that you would normally do during your day in the grief you might feel of having
The ability taken away from you. Because
Cuz of the hospital
Just your illness
Air condition taking it away
And so giving the separate Channel
To have more
Controlling your life whether it's
And we look at reset if somebody's not on a restricted diet why can't they order Postmates
Why can't they get their favorite food delivered if your 2 days out of a knee replacement you're really in pain
Face but you're not
Appreciably sick
When I get your favorite meal
And little things like that
It's not clinical care
But it is care for the patient
In a way
It has a profound effect
It's beyond just what we might think of this country or service in a hotel
You mail the other part of it is
We're taking that burden off the nurses so they can focus on the parts of the job that
They find really rewarding that's the calling of being a nurse
It's the bedside care stuff if it's a win-win for everybody
So in the patient room experience
It feels like we've covered a lot of that
Now you guys have also
Done some things inside the hospital with
I think it was kiosk
Maybe there's a slack integration somewhere in here
Outside
The patient room
Banneker it'll tell you started in the page
And it just kind of blew up in a good way from there
We saw we recognize that if there's a number of
People because they might just
Did you sick or tired they don't want rap
Turns out it is not a Jew
We have plenty of older adults who are every bit it's not more tablet savvy
Then younger people
Some people
Just want to push a button
Swiss re
How can we create a non-clinical called
I want to push a button to have somebody come
And that person then we'll go get me food or get me a blanket or get me something
Like a newspaper we look around you said we need a Wi-Fi button
In the Amazon dash button
Was perfect
How are we going to know
If somebody pushes that button
Are technologist on our team said no problem I will give each button the unique identifier you will know which room it to sign to
And it'll peanuts in Slack
Are we going to know who to pick any sorry we're going to create a Google spreadsheet
And my code goes and checks
The spreadsheet says
Kind of who's on call amazing are quotes but we all take turns being on call
And so it's somebody in the room push that button
It says okay right now in the spreadsheet
Nick's on call
I get a pic on Slack
Everybody
I can see it and it says Nick
Patient in room so and so
Is requesting services
And then we get to go answer that neat and then we started saying what where else can we use the
These buttons and this is the cool part about having a
An integrated team
Arlene engineers said
Are you kidding me this is data collection in a way we've never been able to do before
Today started taking Moline buttons and mocking up of the IP pot
And mocking up
Ways to collect data from a patient
And the staff
One of the first things they do
It was made a little kiosk
In our x-ray department
It said
Were you running late
If so why in one of the buttons is labeled traffic one of them is I got lost one of them is Mickey
The other something like that
Play more like
Because you're late you're not going get your point and it was more like let us understand what were the barriers to getting here
So we can start to fix them
And every time we hit one of those buttons
It logs an entry into a Google spreadsheet
And concise on Slack
It's amazing to watch this data
Coming in real time
And it's one of those things that
Healthcare
Traditionally doesn't have that
Skillset internally
We're really good
Really complex it systems
But this idea taking something and
Kind of quickly cobbling together a little bit of python a little bit Google API a little bit of it eight of us
And a network that's designed for non clinical care
Made it happen in hours
And
You can really valuable really quickly
That's awesome and
In addition to doing all this you've also
When someone's on call for like
Patient care needs
Sometimes I think you said some of those are met by like interns so is by your staff
You've also brought that out to other people in the
I love these Ripple effects that
Can happen when you move really quickly
We say it's how do you go from years to weeks or Days Inn
What's next
We're getting pretty good at answering a lot of these patient care requests and
He said who else would benefit
We realized it was filling our souls
Holes in a way that was really special it was giving us a reason to be in a patient's space
And to be of service to the patient
We looked around and we said
There is a
A small percentage about 20% of people who work in the hospital who are not clinical
Or his main job duties
Play but all of this
People talk about coming in to help
All care for calling
And we started to Seroquel how could we onboard them and so we asked a couple of our
Executive
Alex if they'd be willing to take call
We added to the Google spreadsheet
And wish we had a prototype that so we hold their hands and we had to Shadow them so they never
Garfield
Houston
To delivering Care at the bedside but
Bape head for the same response
Don't swear
It's instead of going in in feeling
I feel like I'm going in and being of service to somebody and I hope it has a
Cultural impact
That we haven't even started to see yet
Okay
What have your Executives what's changed because
People are interacting with patients in it
I am not saying that
People don't care but
It's very different to make
Decision
Running a hospital
Versus fetching blankets
And in one of them had that exact moment of okay I followed this project Nick on paper
We were unsure about this it thing
And we've been looking at the data coming in on this real-time feedback and then holy cow I had no idea I was
Went and delivered a warm blanket in this it changed my whole day and I had no idea
I was looking at this
Is a system is a data thing
It's not it's much more than that
It's this whole week in fact it's where we going to tournaments this whole non-clinical ecosystem of care
So what do you want
Wow
We're piloting a couple things that feel
Kind of pretty practically Within Reach so particularly in
The outpatient Cancer Center
And if you're going through chemotherapy
For cancer or you might go through infusion therapy for some other conditions
You might sit in a room
From anywhere from
228 hours
The average of 46 hours a year ago
Outpatient infusion rooms on credit
They private rooms
I have recliners that turn into sleepers and each one has a private TV and each one has a view of the outside with
Greenery and by the end of the day
You're sitting there for eight hours in the middle of the day in
Daytime TV is still Judge Judy and cooking shows and you can only watch so many of it
I have nothing
But love for judge
But there's only so much of that you're also reminded
You're F Where You Are
Right you're being pumped full of medicine that may cause you discomfort in
A lot of success
Some of this stuff in that setting
Because again it's just giving somebody
Just a choice a binary choice
Do you want to watch TV or do you want to watch net
When is taboo
People will often just look through nest
Because it's a choice
Cast in every room
It's starting to turn a couple of those rooms into basically Smart Home
Rooms
And getting people full control just like they have it home but with somebody like standing there and showing them
How you can change the lights here's how you can
But your favorite music on it's a really cool thing in
Is
Playing around with VR
So
We said alright let's get a couple VR headsets we have done this before
Before different
Setting where we are talking to a patient in a room and they said it's not that I mind being here I don't mind being interviewed about how you could
Improve my experience I just don't want to be here
Anywhere But Here
Where would you want to be
And she said they grew up on a Seaside town
Croatia
One of my colleagues said I've been there I know that
And so we went down and got
A Google cardboard
And
Aspera phone
And use Google Street View and pulled up the
The same town
Took it back
To her and said
Would you would you look through this
And she said I don't really want to do anything technical related in simple just try it and she sat there for
For 10 minutes looking around single I know that restaurant
I know that oh my gosh I know that that
Little shop in
It was this really profound emotional experience
For 10 minutes
She wasn't in the hospital room
She was in this town she grown up in
Wait a little while and then now we took
Tianjin got some VR kits in first thing we thought we would do is get people like
Guided meditation
Mother going through chemotherapy because
Because you're going through chemo you must be fragile you're probably queasy and
And we want to give you something to be mindful about
It turns out
People want to play games
There's a great Vibe there's a bow and arrow demo
People have more fun with that bow and arrow demo
Then
Anything else so the next thing we try
We're just beginning of prototype it is
What would happen if you had a surrogate
So where in Washington DC
We're full of incredible Monument
There a lot of still very beautiful parts of beautiful things about this city
So what if somebody was only to go down to the National Mall and walk around with a life VR camera
360 camera
Envy your search
And you could lay in your bed and say I really want to go to the Lincoln Memorial I really want to go see the washing I want you to go in that museum
And we're just
It's not even going to Monument maybe it's like go to your favorite restaurant with your family
If you're going to be happy in the hospital but your family is out
I do need the regular Friday night thing when I'm done with them
Basically borrowing a terrible internet connection
This over
Over the mile
Right yeah
Transmitter
Cool so how do you guys
Pay for all this cuz what you're talking about is
Not cheap
We're lucky in a couple ways
1 is
We're
Part of
The heavy very small part of the operating budget
The hospital with less than
.01% of the operating budget
Which is a
A pretty small amount compared to things like life-saving
Equipment
All the stuff that goes into clinical care
Have a little bit of philanthropic support but the be honest answer is a lot of this stuff it's expensive from a consumer
But it's not that Out Of Reach
From
For prototyping in this kind of setting
So to get
Philips Hue starter kit
To get a VR kit
The ark it's one of the more expensive things we buy
But mostly our costs are
That hottie
Turns out to be a very expensive Endeavor to try some of this stuff
And if it has a return
The return in one can of little Healthcare nerdy Nuance is our reimbursement what we get paid
Is is affected by
Patient experience
If
A lot of patients have a negative experience
We lose money on
And patience have a really good experience
We stand to benefit
From that and so we look at it as saying all we got to do is affect that
Needle
A little bit and wheel offset our cost
Several times over
And have you
We're trying to measure up for the first couple years we
You can put off measuring it we knew that
We would
We were going to have to be temporarily lost in the wilderness to figure out what it is we're really good at what it is we can do
And so we're just at the point now starting to pull that data and then saying
Because we did these things
We affected
The patient experience measurement in this way
And that's worth XML
It's on early days
Let's get back to this this idea
You're bigger
And people are paying attention
What are the worries that you have to dress with your corporate officers with your it
Do you have to make this enterprise-class
Yeah this is one of those places where
I have a foot in both camps
And
The
Optimistic
Enthusiastic country
Rebellious sometimes a little
Rogar Maverick
Innovator in me
Wants to go hundred miles an hour against every roadblock and every Norm in in question all the things that we are conditioned
Career
The last thing so Hopkins is one of the top three Health Systems in the world and our patient data
Includes
High level
Research National and international level research data
Includes
Hundreds of thousands of patients treated a year
It is in
Credibly value
Not just from our clinical you stamp
Magic imagine
Target
Adida breech for us
With
Be incredibly expensive from a regulatory fine standpoint it would be it would be caustic to the organization's
Reputation in
Frankly it's also we have a moral obligation to protect
Patients privacy
People's privacy
We have to kind of balance that line and say
We think there's no
Rainbow putting this tablet in front of somebody
Itani non-clinical net worth
We think it's relatively safe
But if we're going to roll it out Housewives
The cross every bed in the hospital
And then maybe to every hospital
In our system
And then hopefully get other hospitals to follow that are works all open source we want everyone else to
Try the same things were trying
If it works great if it fails let's learn together
So we're going to push that model
We got to make sure it's
Free
And it's great to have
DARPA research on RT and it's great to have somebody who says
I do pin testing against government government hardened systems
I can do this on our Network
To ask the question of
How can we in this is this is the way we ask it how might we
Innovate securely and innovate with our Enterprise partner
But make sure that it's a partnership so that we're
Valuing
The risks and
Their conservative point of view in their valuing
AR
Innovation
Ends in priority of speed and testing
It's a delicate dance
To say the least
Wow alright Nick thanks so much
For coming on the show this
That's it for this week's show
Thank you so much for listening and if you want more
Iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things
At Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week