Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
Awesome show for you today
We're going to be talking about the new easy mesh Wi-Fi standard
Six foxes brand new
3 as a service
Plus a crazy sensor
Borsuk box
We're also found a hob
That you're going to want to hear about because it allows for local
Control
In your house
Aunt
We got a bunch of little bits of news including
New lights from Philips
A cool intercom system for families
And data on who owns a smart home device
Kevin is going to share his opinion on the wyze camera V2
And he also got a Yale lock
So we can talk a little bit more about that
Our Guest this week is Chris Myers from Misty robotics this is a smart programmable robot ended
Developers
And if I had the money I would totally buy one
Our sponsor this week is machineq
A Comcast service
And you can look forward to hearing from them
In the middle of the show
And now a message from one of our new sponsors
Bosch
Are you interested in all things iot the Bosch connected World blog covers a wide range of iot top
Topix from around the world such as industry 4.0 Mobility smart hold blockchain and
Agriculture Tech check out the blog at blog. Bosch - s i.com
For articles case studies interviews and more and I will say a lot of fees
Corporate blogs run promotional this one is what I actually read on a regular basis to see what's happening and what cool thing
Things people are doing so do go check it out
All right
Kevin
Big news of the week
Wi-Fi
The Wi-Fi Alliance has certified something called easymesh that is
Like the Easy-Bake Oven only it's an easy mesh Network which means your mesh networks will
All going forward
Work together
Regardless of brand or vendor
Yes and this is a big deal cuz right now if you buy it like an orbi
You had to buy the orbi
Main thing I can't remember the Colleton to orbi satellites
And you cannot like swap Outlet
Acer satellite to work with your orbi satellite
You know
Biscuits sad inhibits price competition
So now we have the ability for everything to work together which is actually something that Kevin and I
What about a really long
But
There's a fly
Attwifi
There is and that's because there really has been a standard for Mesh networking and it is
AAA 802.
11s
End
Current mesh networks either use some of it or
Create their own stuff and that's why things aren't you know compatible these days between say
Google wifi
Or be a Nero in a plume Etc so now with
Adoption of the standard
Turn the Wi-Fi Alliance you think this is great news and in theory it is
But I'm a little concerned because
I've seen some research from last year that says the global market Global spin on wireless mesh
Networking has already talked over 5 billion dollars and it's expected be about 11 billion by 2025
So there's a lot of non-compatible much stuff out there I don't see any information showing this
Stuff is all backwards compatible
So that means if you already have a mesh Network system I don't think you're going to be able to mix and match in the future without
At least upgrading your router and that's not something I think most people do on a regular basis and it's not like a smart light
A switch I mean that's
Yeah we all did it
Like 2 years ago
We did it before that freighter 211 you know AC or and whatever you might have chosen up a tie
Time a ex is coming that's going to be even faster which is great but
Honestly I don't see this as backwards compatible
And I sort of wonder what's the incentive for these companies to
Open up the walls and say yeah now will work with anybody here
I don't see the intended to that
It may be because of mesh has an important aspect of like a good smart home system and a lot of these companies are getting into those other
Other devices
It might also be
Pressure from
The isps which
For a while
Consumers
They went with
ISP routers
Incredible Never Their Eyes Pete gave them so maybe
They adopted this because they realize that that's
That's the way of the world
Going to go now
Baby the isps then adopt this
And for many people you're right that would be their new router that they the rent or buy
Directly and then compatibilities
Bonus I get that
So yeah if you wanted to sell an extra at like it I mean basically allows them to get into
Easier extender market for
Crappy wifi routers
But your eyes peep
I don't know why it just it sounded good when I saw the headline it didn't feel so good as I thought
Through I just I don't know
You know
I don't know I literally just replace a router actually so I mean it is rare but the only reason I did it was not to get faster speed
Need sorting like that
It was because it just happened to fall off a table and broke the antennas can be soldered and some pieces fell off and
Question the Integrity of it otherwise I'd still have this router that I bought in 24
But that the Google router
That was the original Google onhub which was software flash to become essentially a Google Wi-Fi unit
So yes and I replaced it with a Google Wi-Fi units now I have to Wi-Fi units instead of a non other than Wi-Fi
Cool
Speaking of network
Let's talk about a low-power wide area
So these are the
Big networks ethernet Works cover cities or big Regional areas
Countries possibly
There are two flavors are the unlicensed bands and then there are licensed
Bye
Those made by cellular
Pay for the other flavors of this our cat M1
And nb-iot
Now what we're going to be talking about is sick. Such as doing their own proprietary Network
In
Set
Six-axis launching a new sensor device called the sensit discovery
And
They
Not as part of this but a week ago also launched
A
Assuming they are calling connectivity as a
The service or cats
Please no one ever use the phrase inside
So basically all it is is there going to ship you
A base station a subox enable base station
If you want to try using their Network in your
Farm fields or perhaps your Warehouse
So it makes a ton of sense because they've been trying to cover the us but can't cover the whole us
Just randomly that takes billions of dollars so what they're doing is if you're like
Hey you know I really like the look of your network
But you don't have coverage area
How can I do this
Is there like
You know what if you got Ethernet or 3-g will send your base station you plug that right in
You are good to go
It's almost like the base stations that the carriers usted provide when you had poor cellular service in your home
You would connect that to your ethernet connection of your Wi-Fi and that Pam credit many cell area
That's it femtocell
Yes and this is actually what our spots are machineq also.
So in there doing a different version of a low-power wide area network they're doing Laurel
But they do say they're not working
But anyway this is going to be a common thing for getting these Networks
Spread out over
Some more places
Ton of sense
It's basically built it is
If you need it and Kevin do you want to talk about the sensitive I switch
Looks pretty cool
Yeah I like this it's a really small sensor weighs about 2 oz and it detects up to five different things temperature
Pictures of light motion humidity and vibration
Oh and also has magnets and it's easily
A door open close sensor for example
And it just clicks all that data and sends it to you through the sick Fox network and then you can
Presumably do whatever it is you like me know what some animations or things like that or maybe just want to let you know stare at the day today that's up to you
I don't know how much this cost
You can sign up for it now it's kind of been in beta for a while
But yeah I like it's a nice little little sensor
Yes and presumably he'll need a
Sigfox Gateway
For this
Yeah I love to put this in my mailbox down the street
Well so this actually we weren't going to talk about this
This is not an issue
Some TV rating for the show notes
You guys but I just bought a device
Because I want to measure temperature and humidity at my daughter's classrooms cuz they're in a portable building
And she complains that it's too hot
Too stuffy and the school is like
I'm sure it's just find me tired
Air conditioning out there
So I decided Well is he
What it's really like
And
Look at you parent with the sensors in the Nevada
I know I'm not a helicopter parent heat triggers for migraines
Terrible
Anyway
So what happens is I was like Oh I thought I was going to actually
Sponsors the twilio
Sim
And actually just
Use that as a connection for
An Arduino that was going to
Sensors on a
Because I didn't think the school was going to let me
But the school said yeah you can come in on the Wi-Fi network that's totally fine
Now I just bought a $90
Was $90 on sale and aware glow
So aware makes a
Air quality
That's her that's $200 but the glow is like this night light
Outlet
Plus air quality sensor and that's only I think it retails for like
$105
So I bought that
It would have also worked for that there was a long way of telling you guys about this and
Just out of curiosity I still want to hear about it next week but it does I don't know why I'm not familiar with the device so
Because it's called glow is there any visual notification of with the
So
There's a night light component that
Turns on and off
Control it through Google home
And then there's also a light
On top that glows
Green yellow or red depending on the air quality
And I was just thinking it would be interesting for the kids to see the information you're going to get the data but it would be nice for them to see some
Wellness
Thread in the
Muscovite unplug it
Could you already have the data so
Problem solved
There we go
Your classrooms get an upgrade
So that's the sick Fox
This is I think really cool
Especially for a lot of our listeners who write in every week to complain about having their data in the cloud and there are a lot of
So this is a device
Cold habitat
H u b i t a t
And it's $159 Smart Hub one of the founders is actually
One of the guys who created the rules engine
Or SmartThings
So this is a
Device could have built
I have the SmartThings experience in mind
But
The owner controls it so
You plug this in
Extra devices
280 create the network and then
Data stays local
It doesn't go
Anywhere
And if you want to update or grab some
Maybe some new apps or
Something for your habitat
You pull it down at your request
I like this and I look into it a couple weeks ago as I was researching hubs and I should note that right
Right now I'm on the site actually down $215 in the US
Yeah it is the Hub or USB stick
Which includes zigbee and Z-Wave on ethernet cable
So yeah I kind of like the idea of this and I know a lot of our listeners will as well because of the local aspect
David
So for this hub
What's also cool is
While everything can be done locally it also can go out and talk to cloud-based
Applications
Which means it will work with Madam a witches are shorthand for
Amazon Echo digital assistant
We just want to set off yours
So it works with that it works
I believe with if
And
Things like your Lutron
Hub if you have that
Your Hue Bridge your Sonos is
And a bunch of other existing devices that you might have
So it's pretty cool I think
Yeah I love the fact that
Aside from the date and not going up to the cloud is your internet does go out
The still works 100% I mean it's cuz it's all local and your wife I obviously still going to be around noon.
Have to go do anything else with your internet or your network of the move files around but you still have everything working here
Yes and it works with a lot of the brands we talked about like lifx
Donkey
Schlage Samsung
Aerotek
Bosch
Sbarro
I don't see ecobee on here
And I don't see nest
Obey Ducey nanoleaf
Lots of products out there
That this will work with and where will be coming
All the time
As people build device driver
I was just going to say it you can build your own and absent device drivers with this and that reminds me of the candle
Fillers for SmartThings which has a pretty active community and I know you can just take SmartThings handlers but I wonder if
50 Brookside
OC so I wonder because the fibaro folks
They provide some device Handler stores ampleforth SmartThings
That you can download that's how you get your fibaro devices work with SmartThings
I wonder
Is there doing the same thing here in which case there's a lot of potential here
On the cheap
On the cheap so
If you guys are interested in that and I should warn you
They are very clear in saying that this is for people who really want to play with this stuff this is not yet for people who want
Something that they can set forget that's easy
So most of our peeps
So most of our people
I just want you to everybody
For the people who are like
And Kevin
I know you're excited but you did not love your smart
So I'm curious
But that wasn't
For the
It wasn't because I had a tanker
No I don't mind tinker and I love to Tinker Bell movie
But that wasn't it it just
Didn't Do It For Me
The Experience wasn't there for me
Well either Kevin or I will try this out
Will fight over
You can try it if you're going to buy me a misty 2 robot
Don't get ahead of yourself my friend
Those are a bit more expensive
Alright so
What are big exciting things this week let's talk about some of our smaller bits of news
Such as
I ran into this device that I thought was pretty cool
Republic Wireless which is a company that makes
Well the word
Cellular mvno I don't know what they're doing now but
They launched this device called the relay
And it's designed for kids
And basically it's a speaker with a button on it
When you press the button
It'll send a
Short voice message to your parents phone so I can get that message in SMS form
And I can respond via SMS in the device will read the message
Switch back to your kids
Or
If you have two of them
You can actually just have them set up as like a little
Intercom system
Between the two
Which
I think it's really cool
We have actually used are Amazon Echo and Google homes as this
Kind of thing for talking to her daughter both when she's upstairs but also
When she is
At home and we're away from home and we just want to let chicken with her or she wants to check in with us
A single one will cost
$99 at tu casa
Ouch it is kind of pricey
But it's nice if you don't have a landline in but they sit me up
Home phone
Well
Yeah I mean it's but it's almost like an SMS CB radio to me it's not the voice
Device
That's true if you don't have
Fred I should say they do have a service fee
$5
Because this is this is basically like a cellular
Sure you know what this reminds me of an I don't know if you recall it to remember that Peak
The small email device
Did nothing but email
Yeah yeah yeah
I'm not I mean listen I don't have younger kids these days so
You're obviously not the Target customer and for people who are the Target customer
Okay I get it cuz
Probably aren't
A ton of great options in this space so I get it I do
You know you don't need
Every kid to have an iPhone 10 and paying you $46 a month if they're
6 years old we just need somebody
Some way to talk to them in their homes I get it
But I don't know
Okay Kevin's not spending the money
I don't know if you guys will
Synchronicity
Maybe you save your money for Misty or maybe you save it for this summer because I was talking with someone from
Philips Lighting
And they're going to launch a colored outdoor light this summer
So nothing more than that but I got very
Excited about color
Tunable
Outdoor capable
Philips Hue
Pothead
Then I was going to buy like a fire pit Meme and just get some colored bulbs to flicker like fire
Yes
Yes that is
Definitely
Cheaper solution
Fire pit
Nothing that is warm
But that would work
Alright Kevin you got some survey data
Just for those
Yes it's not a ton here but I just happened to see this
Infographic and survey from metova
They have survey people in the US and these numbers are kind of Staggering they say
From the survey respondents 90% over 90% of consumers in the US have a connected home device not
Resume playing like a router or something like that
Yeah I exactly although even the new Kindle tablet I just bought one has hands-free Madame a built-in to
Crazy speaking of Madame a the results from metova survey say that nearly 70%
Already have a voice control system such as Madame a 58%
Kuoni connect new device are concerned about how it may impact their privacy I would hope it be more than that
And 30% who do not have a connected home device
Currently do plan to make a purchase within the year
So these numbers
Sounded hire me except for the
Concern about privacy I thought that would be higher than 90% in the US have a connected home device
Okay
Exactly 30% of the 10%
Apparently growth is done there now we're just
Can I sell more connected device
And mesh Network routers
Here's how we're going to do it
Mattamy is coming to more stuff
This time TiVo
I never had a TiVo
Idea
I forgot about it but hey if you have one
Now you can control
Yep this is I was looking to see what you could actually do and it's pretty
Full feature mean you can skip commercials by voice with the TiVo skip mode you can launch apps change channels by name
Amber number
Course the regular controls of play resume pause fast forward rewind
So that you know this isn't just like turn on the TV this is a bunch of stuff
It is and if you would like to spend even more money
I'm connected devices
Arlo Netgear
Smart home brand is
Going into
Security lighting outdoor lighting for the home
So they already make
Cameras both wired and wireless cameras for the home and I think they make a baby monitor it's adorable that has little bunny ears
Okay
Now they have lights
Also change colors
Holy mackerel
Not Justa Phillips
You can now buy outdoor Arlo lights these are security lights so you're probably going to have them on bright white most of the time
You know if you're being
You enjoy the stuff
Maybe you do something else
So you can buy the system which is
One camera plus a
Little converter Hub thing
It's a bridge or low bridge
If that's
I got a bridge to sell you
So yes a bridge 440 999
Or
You can buy two
For 249
That's a lot of
But this Compares with things like the ring floodlight cam
And I feel like there are other netatmo make
Is a present scam that also has a flood light on top of it
So
More options in the
Lighting the outside of your
They're very modern looking I couldn't get this past my HOA here unfortunately who still seems stuck in the 90s
I like the looks of them and their wireframing they have rechargeable batteries to it's kind of nice
Yes in
Is there anything like the cameras
There's so much fun because I got this magnetic Mount you just like
I'm stuck on this
It's
And they work with Madden may as well
Baidu
So in the bridge is a nice touch
Because beforehand
I had for my camera I have a massive
Bridge device that is plugged into my router and it's kind of large and cumbersome
So this looks
Smaller and cuter
Sadly it does not work
The Netgear routers do not
Interface with this
And now it's time
For another camera
Oh that's right yes the wyze cam version 2 I decided to put a camera in the back window of
Are townhouse I already have a front camera
With a nest indoor camera behind the window unfortunately I can't put cameras outside so I have to
Do with screens in my windows
That the cameras looks real but it's okay
20 bucks I mean
Long story short if you need a camera for 20 bucks you cannot go wrong with the new wyzecam
It's very similar to the old one it's got a matte finish on the outside instead of glossy
Otherwise it looks the same they upgraded the sensor inside
They have also added motion detection tagging so you always had motion detection which would tell the
Camera yes capture this video somebody's walking past whatever but now they actually show you in the app
Hernia video
A little yellow
Border
Where the motion is because maybe there multiple things moving and you need to know what's at the camera off you can do that
I did not test the SD card functionalities cuz I'm out of SD cards but just like the old version of the camera
You can keep all of your information local for that
Or you can use their Cloud which is actually run on AWS I found out
It's
14 days of history for free there's no subscription charge the twenty bucks does it that's it
I don't know you tried the original one do you recall if you could daisy-chain multiple ones on a single power cord
I don't think so
Cuz it's got to
You daisy chain amount of power
Strip
Can I come together
So what they did but this one
Is they have a micro USB port
For the power brick that comes with this you power to the micro USB slot
But there's also a full size USB port
And you can daisy chain
Through that up to two more cameras so one power cord can power all three cameras over USB
But I only bought once I didn't say that
That's actually kind of a neat feature and like you could create a little ring of security
I'll be looking at
Well you can call her ring security.
I couldn't have
Was literally talking about a ring
Security however
There are come
Yay wyzecam
I really like the camera I think it's a great purchase for anyone who just wants to experiment with what you could do with camera
And they actually have added if this then that
Compatibility
So yay for that you can now use it till like if it triggers motion it could set off a light or
Alarm or
Something else
Whatever you could geofence with your phone and if this then that turn the lights came on when you leave for example
Yeah
I look for the good in every product
So you also bought something else
I'd love to hear your thoughts on
Yes I bought this
So
I bought what you talked about last week or the week before that was the nest X Yale lock
I already have a Smart Lock it's a Kwikset Z-Wave lock
In lovely brass thank-you HOA
But the motor was insanely loud on that thing
So I decided let me try this nest
Add wow it's like
By comparison whisper-quiet it's so much quieter and yes you can hear the motor but it's so much quieter
Put another way the Kwikset was so loud that when the girls are watching TV they would pause
Weather watching because they couldn't hear the TV while the lock
Motor engaged
No problem now so
I know you had a hardware
Bad Hardware I guess multi Hardware Co descenders back you got a new one and twerking
I thought I did too because I put it in the door to call 20 minutes
And fired up and it says
Press the yellow button to your computer that's locked
And I did it and nothing happened on the touchpad
It happened to him miss you
Wouldn't know it was a legit issue I guess you could call it installer error I decided let me just make sure the key
Cable is fully seated because every one of these locks has a cable from the
Front keypad area to the back
Smart Serie the board and sure enough it was angled a little bit so obviously during the installation it came
Conceited
So I
Seated it receded it put everything back together and sure enough it works just fine so it's working great the girls are very happy
I'm happy
It's a beautiful
Even in brass
Yes
I guess I am bitter about that
Yeah it's really really nice it's very sleek
It's much nicer than in the Kwikset that I had and I feel like it's a little more robust of a lock as well
Yes that's it there higher-quality
Yes and I checked just for you guys who are like
Stacy it was that what happened to you I did check the cable see
The connection between my cable
3 *
I will note that when you're installing it should you buy this and install it it's not a crazy error to get because
Putting the cable into the lake
Like wire guys that they have
It's a little thick in it
Requires a little
Nothing around very easy for the cable to become a little bit
Disconnect it so you have to watch that when you're
Yep but it was an easy fix and I didn't have in the past the nest connect
Now you got that included with it because for two I thinks 27999 for the lock with the Kinect
It's 249 99 if you already have a Kinect
And I'm not a fan of hugs and bridges new extra ones anyway but this is unlike anything else that I have because it looks like a
Small module you just plug into an outlet in your nest products and it didn't even need to be plugged in for me to configure to my
My Wi-Fi network
Yeah
It's very nice I like it I like it alot so
I was also excited the very day I installed this that Yale announced
Support for Madame a voice unlocking
For their locks you could already lock your door with matinee on the Alaskan now you can also unlock and when you do that
Ask for you to
Recite your PIN code
So that way somebody can just shout hey unlock the door and let themselves in
But then my enthusiasm was temper because this is not for the nest which actually thought it was
It's only for their Usher locks
Oanda
Schlage also
I want to say last week or the week
The four
Also announced unlock features
Bear
Connect
Incense
Locks
So
Through anime
So same thing that you got out of pain and actually if you miss
State the pin more than three times its
Locks you out
So there you go
Esther security measures there
Speaking of Schlage which is the sponsor of The Internet of Things
Podcast listener hotline it's time to take a call
From one of our lives
The iot podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic lock
Schlage electronic locks offer unparalleled convenience and simplicity all on their own right out of the box
So you don't have to have a smart home system to benefit
To see what's possible is it schlage.com
To learn more
And we have a message this week from
Heil
Your message
Hey guys this is
Kyle salon Pensacola
I'm calling about
The
When they calling about
So I just want to give you what I thought was a cool the team
I recently received my connecting a long panel from ticks are elderly Kickstarter backer
I got my connect alarm panel I'm really happy with it cuz I can integrate my pre-wired alarm
What's my Samsung SmartThings Hub what are the things I did was I bought a bunch of cameras and put them around the house
But I really don't want them
According
When arms is away mode when I leave the house
Automatically turned on all those parts which is turned on on my cameras inside my house
In this recording on my alarm
I'm outside the house and then when I return home at all
The alarm disarmed itself and all my cameras turn off that way I have them going if anything happens when I'm away from the house but they're not recording
When I'm inside the house pretty cool
So could you eat the shell
And have a great day
Way to go Kyle for using the cheap wise cans to do something fun
I love this idea of playing with
Connected alarm system that's connected with a k or those of you folks who are out there going
How can I make my older alarms
System smarter
That is how
If you guys have a question or you want to share a smart
Tip or trick with our users
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And now
Stay tuned for our guest
Chris Myers
From
Misty
Robotics Misty is a personal robot aimed at Developers
Doing right now for $1,600 at 3 crowdfunding
And campaign and that won't ship until December 4th
To hear more about it is it
Pretty freaking
And now
A message for this week sponsor hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from Mars
Sponsor sponsor is machineq a Comcast service and I have Alex Crum here
Talk about machineq and some of its use cases
So Alex
Remind us one more time what is machine
Excuse enterprise-grade Network
Specifically deal for iot we're working with B2B and b2c iot solution providers to help
Then get their products faster the market by providing the network layer for them
So Alex
Who are machine keys end-users
First let's define what we mean by end-user
Machine Keys customers include iot solution providers who test and bundle art activity is part of their go tomorrow
Plants some have new devices are designed to be lower compliant
What others are actively converting cellular Z-Wave Wi-Fi zigbee devices to our Lord at work
Mission Q also sells connectivity
Directly to SMB mid-market and Enterprise businesses who need Laurel and iot network connectivity
To deploy their latest iot applications
These customers cross nearly all market segments
Agriculture industrial to retail and Beyond
Once an end-user then chooses one of our solution providers at
Is working of us
Recognizing machineq has
Many many different Services were being built upon this platform
Rather than having a bespoke
RFP we're going to a contract manufacturer to help them out with their new use case they look to us in our portfolio of
Solutions that we can provide
XYZ as well
And as we continue to discuss on the show
Once they have this connectivity
That really enables them to do a lot more with their business can you give us an example of that
Yes
Pansophic is one of our solution providers
Who purchased connectivity from Comcast
What are there any Zara customers the New York Housing Authority
Has been deployed the pansophic solution using a machine to network
Pansophic first installed
The empty flash device for machineq which is a multi-use device
Current temperature humidity
Vibration
And other monitoring capabilities
The begin monitoring temperature humidity first
Dinosaurs adding air sensors to detect mold then they started adding Leak Detection sensors
Throughout the building as well we often find customers starting with one particular need
I've been learning on additional sensors and services as they grow
Most of our solution providers are certain single-threaded and they go in and
Their end users ultimately one thing they've identified as a hero use case
So we say what's a temperature and humidity detection is East case number one
Once they're in there with our connectivity
Viennese are my comeback
2 then
Bose the landlord and say by the way I also need something for Pest Control to my building and it goes from there
Excellent alright Alex where can I go to find out more
About machine
Start of our website machineq. Com
Play some great white papers there including our latest on dense Network
In addition to that we
Tactical business conversion guides and network coverage details well
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Chris Meyer who is head
Developer experience atmosphere
Robotics
Hi Chris
Hey Stacy going to be here
So you guys are on the show
Settle cabins in my debate
Over robots in the Smart House
That's not true although you
Totally way it
Isaiah robot without arms
He wants to camera that he can talk to
Juvia
The framing of the debate
So what we're going to do first is have you talked to
What is Misty
Misty is our attempt to try to democratize
Robotics so we realized that
Robotics
Industry is still
So we're trying to give
People a robot that is sensory
Okay now you guys just launched the Misty there's a Kickstarter
I'll put that in
You guys
Give us the parameters of what is
What kind of robot
Talking about
Got it so Misty is a you know like I said sensor Rich robot that we're trying
Work so you don't have to No Control
Mechanical
So it's programmable via JavaScript and python
How would you describe me
She's cute
She's round
No hard edges
She has a track drive system and
3 degrees of freedom in the neck so I can do that
The role that had songs
Is really sweet really cute
And then a 4in
Orange LCD
Verizon
She looks kind of like Wall-E
With a little
Runs around
Tank treads
And
I think our actual spec is
27 meters per second to a fast
Okay in the vision is that this robot is
Roaming around
Holmes and maybe small office
Doing what
Well that's why we're trying to enable people to figure out
Everybody uses a computer differently than we know that every
Nobody's going to use and then wrap the robot different
So one of the things that I use mine for is it a wait in the foyer
If it recognizes myself
Or my wife
First
Then it'll play my Spotify playlist
But if she's there first
Play her Pandora
Goose I'd like a race to get in your front door that's exactly what
But it is trying to get off work early
Nice we have that in my house but it's for the air conditioning
Cold pack
So they're going a lot of
Smart home robotics
SmartThings
So what did you guys learn
From head of the previous
Experience at small things and I think somebody has
Spiro
That you're taking into this project
I know when the smart thing side
Trying to do something just developer focus and kind of
Programmable
You
Have a hard time putting that towards the consumer Market upfront
With maintaining the program
So with Missy what we're trying to do is really focus on
Developers and makers
A programmer's especially
For them first
When we figure out what those consumer applications are there
How did Misty
More consumer-friendly
Got it so guys this is not necessarily
The robot
You want to get to your
But it hasn't
Cool stuff so they showed me the robot it's got like a
This little backpack areas are in the back
Can load all kinds of stuff
You're talking actually about an Arduino and what are some things you hope
People try to do with this
Yashow because it's focused on
Program
The hardware store
So we haven't
Arduino backpack
It plugs in
To the back of the
And we also have open source connectors for the arms and antenna
AdSense
Route that all through your Arduino arrest
Berry pie
To make it accessible
If I want to add a barometric sensor
That was run
Through my Arduino and then take barometric sensor readings around
Hayden Ponder why you would want to be
Around your house by
12v temperature would be a better
Kids having a heat map of
Why my bedroom is always cold
Is a little bit more interesting
The barometric pressure
Got it okay this does make more sense
So
Let's talk about robots in general
Cuz we seen a lot of activity right now
Not just right now
Over the last few years in robots
You talked about it being
In its infancy
What do you mean by
We've been trying to crack robotics for
40 50 60 years
And there hasn't been a
Real
Application
In the home or office
Utility base or single-purpose
But the problem is robotics today is people are continually building robots for a single purpose
Set the draw the parallel between
Computers in the 70s and 80s
People were in the garage is Belen
Computers
Opticians I can build a computer chips
This is where robotics
Is today that's why
What we saw with personal
Computers is once physical
Was invented
Then people started to have
Real use in
Office for
Cheaters you started
To see that awkward escalation
Adoption
So what we're trying to do
Do is make those things accessible
Thinking about what they
But instead of worrying about control system
Charging
That
If those things are
Given
What do I do with it
Indeed
What do I do with
Hands versus roaming 2
So where do you fall in Ark
Physical manipulation of objects is a
No problem so obviously is in
Robotics company
Do you want to bite off of
We can swallow
So we made a deliberate effort to say okay let's not
Tackle physics
Frontlets start
Thinking about
How do you change the recipe
When you have something
It's physical
It's mobile
The same way that when your programming
Computer there's different
Do you consider when you programming
Mobile device
So those learnings with
Physicality
Duration of
Robotics so we want to start there
And then we have the ability
Grab things and say like hey that's a Red Bull can or that's no a balloon
That I can move those
That'll enhance
We've already latex
Okay so I should
Just give up for another 10 years on the robot
Well I mean there's laundry
Right right I'm not spending that kind of money for a single purpose
62 hours to full
Cycling shirts
Whatever their actual
True Okay so
Let's talk about some of the competition
Because we've had
Geebo
Is the most famous
There's also
Curry
Now
Random robots running around
Do you think what happened with Jibo
It's going to hurt the market for what
Find offer
Is kind of a double-edged sword on one hand it's very clear that the
People wants
Robots in some sense I mean a raise
I have to go there actual dollar value was
It was a lot it was a lot
And then you know
3 years delayed
In the things that were
Kickstarter video
We are really hopeful to get to that point where
Everything
It was shown
Is possible
And what we realize with robotics
This is not a linear complexity
Scale
You can't add
Movement in
Physicality and then all these other subsystems
How to be like
3 *
More complicated
But it's actually
Factorial
We're very glad that she was in the space we love
But people
Call about some of the promises
Robotics Army
Yes so you guys speaking of promises you're doing the kickstarter and
You expect to ship some
December
And it's not text
Kickstarter
It is a crowd
Campaign but we're going to
Build it regardless
I'm already hit our goal so
So let's talk about designing a robot
And the types of things
State you put in
Like you said before it's cute
Its or maybe ice
That is adorable
When
Designing it
How much do cuteness matter
Personality
So we realized it personality is
The long tail
When you start to have something that
People engage with
And meaningful in Rockwood
Has some of that
Characteristics
It really make it lovable
But that's going to be one of the
Sequel to the robot
In the short-term
It's really about programmability and getting
And itself to work and function
Auntie very difficult environment
Office
So when we came
The design we wanted to enable some
Flexibility and experimentation
And then figure out what are those elements
Apps that make it
Cute personal
Personality
Heavily and was
We have three degrees of
So instead of just
You know up down left right we also have roll that is
Spaetzle
Oh yeah
Is that your psychic
Yeah yeah absolute
And so this is such a powerful
Motives
Capability
And then
We put the with the screen
Behind a lens
Because we didn't want
What we call tablet
We don't want it to look like
Droid phone
Inside the robot that that adds like a
Another layer of
Not so much mystery
Butt personality
Tell me a cross
Uncanny valley or
Live on the other side of it in a cute way
What about
The nail room
Trauma
Did SoftBank ESV Alderaan Alder body
Pepper robot
Danny very much so
Misty
And its eyes
The fact that it was aimed at develop
Clippers
Are you guys
Competitive
I mean it's a different price
If I recall
When you have to fill out the application to get it
And I believe there
The more than seven
And it's just it's just different it's multi-joint
Scott legs
Scott fingers
It has the arms I'm
Yes button
Doesn't pick things up
It does the Macarena
Had it very true
But it doesn't have I mean the differences
Crosses doesn't have expressive eyes
It is leg day
They use a proprietary system
Choreograph
Which
Is a little bit
I'll leave it that
We talked about earlier was that
Programming a robot is not what people like
So if I like bought this
Versus like maybe another robot what was that experience
Be like
My role is that the head of developer
Experience so I'm trying to mitigate that cognitive dissonance
The way that you expect the programmer
So Misty's Bergamo via JavaScript
Python
So
And anybody that can build a website should be able to
So you can do things
Go to the
The kitchen
Name XY location
Go there now
The
What do I do if I encounter an obstacle
What happened
And if I hear loud noise
I can stop
Or trying to make it as easy as possible
For anybody
Be able to do the things that you want to do without worrying about
Lower level
Programming
What is it lower level programming
For let's say that we take it out another Wheels
If I wanted to say go to the
What I have to do
Without the subsystems I would have to
Generate a map
Do the path
And then go down to
Low level of
Drive my Motors in a certain way to turn left turn right
Avoid
Build the entire system around
To where
For you
So you can operate at the high level
Go to Kitchen
Without having to do all the stuff down
Do you like easy
Simplicity
Okay so
I have to ask you
Throughout this because
Apparently
Okay
I have to ask you because we had a conversation about
Party
And flatulence
And robots
So
Why do robots fart
Which is one of the things that makes robots
Extremely personal
Very very
It's one of the things that the biological function
Unexpected
Lititz
Really kind of funny
I think it's one of the things that
Eagle
When you know the whole concept
The robot
The room waiting until you see an individual
You'll make an apartment
Leaving the room I think it's just
Juvenile
I would
You're right okay and because kids finest
Let's talk about kids
Robotics
It feels like we're in this
Weird like
What do we do how do we train them how to be around the robot so
What are your thoughts there I don't know
I have a 2 year old
Yes I mean I personally think
The robots are going
A very powerful
Driver for
People to live the life they
Encouraging Behavior
Moderated making
Do your own awareness of how
You live your life
And then
Being used
So when it comes to kids getting them
Familiar with it
And then
How they work
Is going to be really
What's the standard equation
The program ability
How to program
Kids just behaving like total jerks
And I don't know if your 2 year old is
I'm sure he is a very nice person
But
How does he react
Your robot
Is he getting to the point where he's
Using a door
Taking it for granted
Speak one of his first words exactly
Robot so maybe I'm an outlier in a lot of
It's more curiosity
I know that every time that is sitting on and
Messing with the Devil
Wave at it
Which is really adorable
It does
He hasn't my son hasn't been to
I think in scenarios where there's
Groups of people
That there's going to be you know more about abuse
You know you see the night sky in summer
Stuff like that
I think we're hoping is it summer
The personality
Will come through and see where it's like
If you kick it we have it
We have an IMU
Detect when it's being Joselyn
React
Like out
I whip my heart might break
It's like
IRobot
Just like my dog
Okay so I think this robot
Cat roaming around my home
But is that the wrong way to think about that or is that how you'd like to
I mean that's kind of a difficult question because it depends on how you expect interact
I like the idea of having some
In the Bronx around be like hey Missy did I leave my
David on her like he misses my dog
That element of hellofresh
Fascinating but I know
People that have
Large families
Did the last they want another thing
Quiet
Might be
More desirable to them
Good cheap setting okay anything else you want to tell us about
We got two weeks left
For you to sign up to get your
Misty 2
For $1,600
That are
Oh gosh you guys I don't know if I should tell you to buy now or
$200
Be sure all right
So there you have it thank you so much
Chris
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week