Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host Kevin tofel
We have an awesome show for you today
We're going to be talking about a step back
For privacy
Big funding for a smart window maker
Couple new iot related modules from gemalto and Sierra
And
Bad security news
Dealing with
Madam
The Amazon Echo and e911
Shecup / Cortana
And some bad news for everybody hoping
Google assistant on Sonos
Plus we've got Andy wilson-thompson
Talking about the digital standard
Which is a new privacy security and device safety standard that
You're really going to want to hear about
And
We have figured out something pretty cool you can do
With your Amazon Echo
And notify
Applications
All of this
Plus we'll hear from bitdefender who is our sponsor for this week show
And
Will discuss the digital standard
So let's
Kick It Off
With
A message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Cognizant
With demanding customers at the center of today's value chain delivering engaging products and experiences
Is even more important
Cognizant a global leader in business and IT services helps companies engage customers by envisioning Innovative products
Experiences
Or inventing disruptive new business models
With these insights
Cognizant collaborates with clients to build smart products and disruptive strategies and new ways of engaging customers across
Every channel that uses the power of iot
Learn more about cognizant iot services and solutions at cognizant.com
Iot
Kevin
All right
I feel like this week was late on certain types of
Snooze like cool connected products news
But we got a lot of big news relating to how
The internet
Things is
First step
Is
Maybe a blow for privacy
Last year the FTC came after dealing
You
Are building products that are not
Actually secure
And I was like what
We have to see this like I'm going to still find you because you're talking about your device is being secure but they have these hard-coded passwords
This is all in the Waco
DeVry botnet and things getting a
Infected
And
People realizing that a lot of their routers at other products
They weren't really well-designed very well
So
D-Link
Dislike
I'm not going to be made up an example here and they fought back
And
The district judge in this case basically said
I am sending this
2 quart
Neither of you are going to get summary judgment summary judgment
On a case is when the courts basically say
Yeah okay this isn't even a case
You're in the wrong
Or you're in the right
Whichever
And this is kind of interesting that is happening in California
I know this is a federal thing in California has a state law
That was recently password talk about on a number of shows it's as we said night time
Does a lot of keys it doesn't have
Honda of different
IRT security aspects that we'd like to see or the kinds that are in place recommended in the UK
As well these are all the things that we say
Where did ice makers that is
So we have to cease problem is Haven aside from the hard-coded passwords you had command injection vulnerability
Steve got misplaced security keys
And even worse plaintext password storage
You know basically available to access
I said so
I like to see all that go away I think you would too and
I hope it's where we are heading
I'm kind of disappointed it was a summary judgment because to me it's like
Yeah these are all
Bad security practices that you should be held accountable for especially if you're selling these products to Consumers number one and number two
If you're telling consumers yep
Secure with us
Yeah in this case this is a little weird
Because both parties actually asked for summer
Judgement it seems like the FTC was kind of trying to walk back his arguments in a way here
Usually
1 party
Chelsea Kasper summary
In that case it would be logical for
There is no case here
You are so it's a little weird that the FTC which one after dealing was like yeah
Let's do a summary
And the judge was like
Yeah. There's a lot of information that we need to go through a tree
Dial soap
I suspect D-Link
Wanted to summary judgment because they are surely not the only manufacturer in the space that has
Similar issues and they didn't want to be the first
D-Link actually recently just got called out by Consumer Reports
For not having
Great security associate
It's products as well so you know maybe it's just feeling like
Punching bag
If you're a D-Link
Device owner just so you're aware of the scope of what is in bounds here for this it's the security response
How to see which is obviously not your voice but that's just d-link's practices but also their router security and their IP camera user
Interface security cameras
You know this is kind of an play for you
Oh know that some of them are hard coded nevermind
Do you think
Depending on the case and I think I'm sure that we're going to watch this one because it's kind of the first-of-its-kind that I can think of
It is do you think this will push us forward
National
Type of legislation with
Again maurkice and say what California has include Jose California at least they have something
Nationwide we don't have anything
Well this was brought under
The FTC deceptive trade
So the FTC has the ability to
Call companies out for being
Basically saying something that isn't true so that's actually the authority under which the FTC brought it
And because
Steelix in California that's why it
It's there this isn't under the brand new
New California law
Although cuz that doesn't actually been going to a
There's a lot here that is literally the only
Hammer that the FCC has to go after this right now
Maybe not the only
I'm sure there are lawyers who
In general
That's the hammer the FCC has so they're trying to
Yeah I don't see the FTC moving forward in terms of trying to push a legislation as you said that's not their role or anything like that but I could see
See some lawyers
Start pushing for the sun maybe even some legislators
Probably in California that try and bring the snow to the
Rule of law in US
I mean California did just pass that law that would affect
This case
Isn't that right
Right
Yeah so it's past it just isn't going to work
So I think we'll see more here
This is again
Maybe we'll see more of the current FTC is a little different than the FTC the brought this so
I don't know that's the danger of having your
Pause kind of having agencies do all of the enforcement
But you don't
That's
Moving right along
Artesia scope we'll talk a little bit about Good device security and privacy with
I guess so stay tuned
Cuz that's basically what
Does the voluntary
Goals not
Federal so
We're getting there we got big big money happening
Hey smart window
Glass manufacturer
Actually
It's over a decade old
It's called View
They just got 1.1 billion
Friendly Saudi back
SoftBank
Vision fund
Which in its own way has some controversy
Associated
Let's just go with the big side there and let's talk about the smart windows
Because these are
Pretty cool they've actually been used in
DFW Dallas
Fort Worth International
Birthday pin used in
Overstock's headquarters I remember when I was at Fortune
A colleague of mine wrote about them teaser
Basically two cool things
Apus One
When the sunlight hits it
It can turn opaque with the push of a button
So you can
Duke radiations in
Capacity on the window which is me
Into they're using software associated with it
To detect how people move around in the office and make the windows more
Restaurants
Parent based on
Temperature
But also the needs of the
People trying to
Yeah and this 1.1 billion and Sunday actually follows 800 million that view it already raised from folks
Corning which makes sense Corning Glass madrone Capital Partners TIAA Investments and the New Zealand
Sovereign wealth fund so
I got nearly 2 billion raised here
It is technology that's been around for awhile
It's kind of cool because that's there's like metal oxide films in between the panes of glass and you said you would
The Press of a button and technically you're right
If you remember at CES last year we saw a very similar product
From halio
Which is smart tinting glass and it took about
Channel 3 minutes for to go from
Fully transparent to fully dark so it's not like an instant thing I don't want you to get the wrong idea
It is very cool and aside from the fact that
Do you have this in your business your employees might be happier than an athlete blind as much getting less UV light Etc you can save
20%
On your
HVAC bills which is huge when you outfit entire massive building with them
But they also cost four times as much as regular glass
Yes I've seen
Twice as much to four times as much so I think it probably depends maybe
Volume
I don't know but I would love this I actually have these massive Westward
Windows
Had this been an option for me in the residential space
Totally down for it
But this is for now
So yeah if you and they're going to use the money to
Selma
Let's talk about
Modules
Oh my gosh so we got two little bits of
Module news for y'all out there in the world
Connected iot devices
Gemalto has built
Highly efficient
Secure NB iot platform
Gemalto is one of the companies that makes
Someecards
And does all kinds of
Crazy Security in your credit card
And their new NBA OT simplex
Is
Basically the
Super low power
Howard butt
Has
Is it December 7th
Yeah it's easier so there's no physical Sim in these gemalto disease and Technology
And it makes sense because you don't want to actually he want to have
The flexibility to
Transfer these around
And the security didn't want to swapping SIM card like putting my phone SIM card and some Wireless module Taking Over Control
Call the device you're right but it's okay and I may not at 5 never done that I'm just getting
I said that very quickly I don't want people thinking I did it before
Theoretically I could have done that
That's what I'm saying
When to do that
So in this case we're looking at this in again
These are going to be for low-powered sensors that don't need to send a lot of data nb-iot
It's not even a megabyte
Couches to put in perspective the downlink
Is 27 kilobits per second and the Uplink is 63 kilobits per second so
It's a baby
So yes this is designed for temperature may be sending a
Location every now and again
But we don't know how much this costs and that's a big
Issue here
Again this is going to be 30 modules are usually more expensive because they're cellular
If we don't know what the cellular plan affiliated with this one
But the emphasis on security makes sense because this would be
Good for
Tracking some high-value device
Our product
Or
Temperature
Or anything associated with
That and you would want that to be secure so
These are small to women
Musical artists models might think it's a large bit of silicon but it's not it's 27 by 18 mm
3 mm thin
So it is really inside some type of device
All right and Sierra
They also
Now they're announcing the first lte-advanced module
Poor
The seedrs space
If you guys are like what this is a Citizens broadband
We haven't talked a lot about this because it's not
Yes it will be in Connected device
This is what this is is this is for the 3.5 gigahertz
LTE network
Worx what's interesting is these networks don't actually have to be operated by a
Exterior they could be operated by
A private company
So what
We're seeing one of the use cases that we seen
We seem like the NFL came out and support
If this is the idea that a stadium like set up their own private LTE network
What to do
Any sort of
Data
Inside the stadium so
Concessions
Yeah all kinds that there's some creative stuff have
They're so this is the first module for this it was FCC approved so
Yeah this is a big deal
In the sense that this is going to needle
This it's the underpinnings of this new
New type of Technology
So these modules have to accept two of them I say are available now for commercial deployments I don't see a price but if they're
Available now.
Find a price set curious
I'm not buying any but
Okay so that's our module news
Now let's go to Crazy security news
Because
Freaky Deaky this is so not good
Alright Kevin
Scare everybody
Go okay you've already probably been scared by the fact that there are basically databases out there
With IP addresses of
Wireless
Webcams
Oh yeah
Exactly
So of course
Let's make it easier to find those wireless devices those webcams with this little scrap that was written
Uses data from show Dan and you can actually I looked at the code it's
Pretty simple to use I have not used it cuz I don't want to see people's webcams
You could search by
Address
In this database now and find webcams in a particular radius of an address a home business Etc
They just making it easier and easier to be bad and I all
I'm scared
Creepy
Yes so did you put in your address
I don't know I don't want anything associated with this tracking to me no no
Got it yeah it feels kind of
Natchez crape
Paralegal
Okay so
Come and you could install it the code is available on GitHub you can install it
Query show dancer with an address if you'd like but I just looked at the coat just another curious but I'm not using it
All right
But in positive
News let's talk about Battlement so bad today is what we call the Amazon echos digital assistant so is not
Turn off for you guys
AR
To become a friend I feel like
Absolutely he's been to my house I've had for dinner
Patent for dinner
It's amazing
Andy Abramson
And who we've known forever
Because he was good friends with
Are former boss at kygo
And he's a smart dude
You know
His expertise is voice
Which used to be a big thing back in
Get out 2010
And now it might be coming back around
Innocence innocence I mean Andy
Read a blog post that will share in the show notes and it's kind of a response to
A news article in the Wall Street Journal
And the German was talking about Madame a and emergency 911 calling how
Amazon's Echo can do all these great things but you can't call 911 for you
And he's like no no no hold on a second
He said I think they can solve this pretty quickly and I like where he's going with us
What you could do he says his Amazon knows your address cuz that's usually issue
When you call me on a mobile phone or something tonight with one where are you right
Amazon has your address for deliveries and they know which is your home address perhaps
Snake versus a business address Etc
So we can link that up
Right away so that
Stable Amazon devices meeting Amazon
And then he said you know and for people who move those Echoes or whatever maybe you have a
Amazon top like I do when you take it to the beach it's on obviously you're not at home anymore
He said hey
People done this before with mobile devices and basically you need to re-authenticate your home address after
You know 4 hours of online or a change in
GPS or whatever might be
So I think he's right I don't know that many people would call 911 using Amazon cuz we all have mobile phones but
Tell you if your phone is upstairs you downstairs you falling down to call 911
It speaker to do that yes as someone who again
I know you always carry your phone
I do not and I called
Guess I was referencing you because I know you don't carry your phone not about the falls
Yeah
Exactly
That would be
Nice
Let's see if it
Amazon Prime
Responsibility
I don't know though because it means they are all about providing service through the Echo and it is a true digital
Assistant so why not I mean
As long as the customer has
Previously set up an address or Lincoln address they could allow the call and if
You haven't then they just don't allow it to call on
DACA
That way they're in the clear
Assistant
News Microsoft Cortana
Boss Javier soltero
Is leaving in this is really unfortunate because after seeing Xavier
Speak about Cortana integration with the Amazon Echo
How to work in with smart offices
I wanted to have him come on the show and
Talk to us about this
But that's what happened
That's not going to happen
And the reason is Microsoft is bringing
It's
Cortana research project into its
Coming out of the aif
Basically
It's experiences and devices
You know
I don't know either I mean Microsoft as well as many other similar companies Shuffle everyday
So often the Chevalier organization
I would have been curious to hear his experience at the shame and he's not coming on the show only because and nothing again so I never met her
I'm not sure how we got to be in charge of Cortana
Microsoft buys startup
It's a mobile mail startup in 2014 was a complete
And then he was part of Outlook mobile and then all of Outlook and then head of office
Hop2
He's a very like we actually
Talk to him a bunch of gigaohm and he's a very smart
Forward-looking
So I can see
And he's very good
Thinking about
Business sauce
And how to make that more user-friendly
So if you think about Cortana as being
Business digital assistant
Then
It makes a lot of sense and I wasn't saying
You know he shouldn't have been injured I was trying to understand the path
But you just make sense right so instead of office as the business application
Service he took that
Mindset to Cortana and
Use the Cortana service in that regard
So that is the Cortana shake-up
As it were
I still am a little weirded out by the idea of going into an office and switching my digital assistant but
We'll see how this works
We're not there yet
We're probably four or five years away from some sort of seamless strategy on
Who we talk to and who helps us in different
Aspects of Our Lives
And where we even go to do that
So we might instead of having
Cortana in the office we might have like a bring your own assistant
Kind of like we had your bring-your-own-device policy and that would be
Wacky kind of crazy
It would I don't think we'll go that route at systems and networks are getting locked down for good reason
Personal devices
Are typically allowed in if you let the organization manage them
Yes that's true I did hate that I had a separate Fortune phone that I literally never used my birthday
It was and there's also another aspect and not full of just six of how an office is set up today and in the future
If you got an open Office
Area where no cubes and whatnot do you want to hear people talking to you know when thin air all the time I'm not sure how that's going
Don't you work in an open Office environment or even you know just
Any office because
I'm itching to be more like
A headphone situation
Which having been an open newsrooms all my life
You know you very quickly get used to people talking on the phone and you just ignore them
While you're talking to other people on the phone
Persistent
We've talked about this before but we're seeing a lot of Madam a power
Earbuds for example
So
Maybe it's all going to be like her it's all going to be in her ear
Yeah
All right
Let's talk about Google Assistant
Since we're on the assistant topic
Bad news
Bad news for you
I know
No Google assistant on Sonos this year they said it's going to be next year
Well we were getting close to the end of the year said it would happen and I don't know if they run into technical issues or what
You're right they've announced this the good news is
And it's just 2019 we don't know when it's coming
The good news is if you're interested and I am so I'll probably click this link
You can sign up to be considered
For a private beta of Google assistant on Sonos
However it's pretty tough commitment they want you to
Commit to at least 14 hours of listening a week which is fine I'm listening
Music all the time
Use 10 voice commands daily and respond to surveys yes you get homework
Within 72 hours so if you're willing to do that and you get through the screening process
They will let you in the private beta to test this
Holy cow I use digital assistants all the time but I don't know if I use 10 times a day
I do for a lot of music playback and pausing and volume and whatnot and occasionally weather and things like that so
I use Vector to check weather like five times a day so the robot
Picture
What is the weather to be slower but yes he tells me he puts the temperature on a screen and then if they're
Are clouds are rain they show up over his eyes
And it rains in his eyes get sad and it shakes at all off and the clouds go away
That's why I do it because it's
Yeah cuz that's why
This is not on her show notes but I just remembered
Because it's very related Google Assistant
Is available on
Chromebook devices
Yes but it uses
Basically you have been able to Google Play Store so Android apps in a little people don't want to do that they just want their Chromebook to be a Chromebook
So what Google is doing its now available in a day
Version of Chrome OS they have a native
Google Assistant
Coming to all Chromebooks
Don't require
The Play Store in the Google app and all that so that's coming for people who want the Google Assistant but don't want to have to
Use
Like Android apps on their Chromebook
It was that is super cool
It is it is
Dedicated Google Assistant button on the keyboard
I never use it
Talk to vector
Oh that's right
I'm going to throw out a random device just because
Why not this is what we do on the show throughout
Random devices
This is a new smart plug
From a company called
Current currant
If you were trying to
Bluetooth smart outlet and a Wi-Fi smart outlet
Bluetooth Outlet is 50
The Wi-Fi is 60 what does this measures your energy consumption at that
Outlet and tries to use AI to optimize Energy savings
Interesting
So it sounds like a more modern version of the WeMo Insight switch that I've been using for probably three or four years
The funny thing is
I never look at the energy
Output
On that
You know why know why
Because I usually use these with lamps
Anna's lamps have very low power LED bulbs
And it may calculate the cost everything it's like
You spent $0.14 this month
I don't use enough energy to make it worth my while to look at the data
I use it to test different things so I used it to test like power consumption
The June oven
Which is a like compared to like a crock pot cuz the June did their Crock-Pot setting guys the Crock-Pot is way more energy efficient
Lejeune
Based on
The energy consumption
If you feel like your food taste better maybe it's
But yeah in general
This might be and it has one cool design
You can actually flip up
Prongs so you can
Slip the outlet
There's two outlets on each
Switch
What do we call those out
But you can flip it
So you can flip
The outlet to fit more
Are plugs if that makes sense
Yes that makes sense
You should probably just go look at it
Cuz I was a terrible
But you could see it being used for something like you know the set-top boxes if you didn't want it to always be on
Prioritize Energy savings
It could be like oh
At 5 she usually turns on the television so maybe at 4:50 it starts
Turning back set
Topics on ghost
Boot up process so it's ready for
Or maybe after three hours of TV I shut it off on the kids
Yeah I used to have
Smart outlet that turned off if I didn't make my Fitbit steps
And that was the TV was plugged into that but my
Walk more I want to watch the football game
Get out
Okay
So
Let's move now to our voicemail
We have an awesome voice mail for you today
This is from the iot podcast listener hotline which is brought to you by Schlage
They have a variety of stylish and secure electronic locks
Statues from
So you can have smarter homes that start with SLI
Learn more at schlage.com
Iot
And enter to win a new Schlage
Sense
Smart
Block you get an option you have a homekit one you could have your
Other options out there
There's also a Wi-Fi smart Bridge
And to do that you just need to call us and leave your own voicemail
Question 512-623-7424 is the number to call to ask us a question
This week's voicemail is
From
Cheese
Kevin and Stacy this is
Teas from Lewisville
I am wondering if there's a way for
The
Madam a to tell me
That something is going on from an ex
External source for infants
If the cameras pick up
A person in the backyard
Could she
Alert me inside the house
By saying someone's in the backyard or
Who sings Something
Suppose
Be having to have the phone in my
Thank you so much enjoy your show
Okay chief Kevin and I spent an hour trying to figure this out and it was a
Our well-spent I think
Kevin rizer I'm so glad we do because our initial
This was like nope can't be done can't be done
And then
We stumble onto a skill called notify me
An Amazon
Madame a skill
It does require some configuration on your part
You don't
Need to be a programmer but it would certainly help if you were
However if you can get through it
And Stacy I would say you're not a programmer
You're smart and you got through it right
And I feel so excited that I did
So
To enable this you're going to go
To the skills in your Madame and you do have to have a matinee
We'll see if we can find something for Google on this site
Notify me
It'll send you an email with
Very long
Cerakote
So once you enable notify me and get your access code which is something that allows the skill to
Tire
Amazon email to your
Echo devices
You will then
Go to if this then that
You can actually use this with a couple other services such as is why Indigo homeseer and Tasker but we got to working with
If this and that so that's kind of all we're going to
Talk about here you can try it on your own with the other services
Basically though
If you
Want to
Have any type of trigger event
From a device that you have
And that
Devices supported through if this then that and we tested this with just added an email as a test also with a y
Wyzecam also with a smart light switch
When
Something happens to that trigger device
If this then that
Well then send a notification to your Amazon Echo
It doesn't just speak it aloud like any other notifications you may get a notification light on your Echo
One sanitation comes in and you have to say hey
Read my notifications
We did this and you can customize the notification message rather
And
Stacy you got the wise kind of say hey I saw something on the
Outdoor wyze cam or whatever
And I had to say I saw something
And then I realized that I should totally if I was going to do this on a bunch of
Things I should have
Let's label I saw some
Something on downstairs
DC that you can customize the notification text yourself very easily
The basic notification is just a hello world
It's kind of like pre-filled which is a programmer thing to say hey this works
Just change hello world to whatever it is you want to hear from your Echo
And once we went through the discovery process it actually work really well and is awesome
So I'm going to go play some more with that just for fun the latency on this was really quick
It took like
Two or three seconds before I sent the notification
It was kind of fun
Keep in mind
That
There is a restriction and it's an API restriction on Amazon's part you cannot
Get or send
More than five notifications within a five minute. If you don't want to use that safe for like a door that's People concert going in and
Cease to work until the next five
5 minute increments
And it is proactive it is you have to be proactive about getting your notice
Applications this isn't just going to shout this happened
Over here echoes
So
I'm not a true fan of the way that Amazon does notifications because
First of all my Amazon tap and my Sonos devices with men aren't
Beeping or lighting up to show me or tell me about notification my
Regular original Amazon Echo does
And at that time I say I have a notification so I'll say Madam a read my notification that getting that
Bit here on these devices
Summer
It's okay
Alright so
Have fun with that you guys and
Stay tuned
For a message from our sponsor and for any wilson-thompson who is from the open technology Institute
Who is going to be talking about the digital standard
Which is a Bren
To think about
Privacy security data transparency and even talk about things as crazy as business bottles
4 connected devices
Conversation
If your user a manufacturer or just somebody interested in
Security and iot stay tuned hey everyone we are taking a break from the internet
Set of things podcast for a message from our sponsor
And I have Alex belong here
Who is a chief security researcher
Bitdefender
So last week we talked about
Stopping bullying
With the bitdefender
This week we're going to talk about
Curing your
Router
How would I know if my router
Where is safe
Easiest way to know if
Was
Most people that I know
Don't really have any clue
Old how to update
Everything
How's that for a deal identified
The people using the device
There's nothing
There's Note 2
Is processed
Some point
A lot of us have antivirus apps
Protecting our
Computer
How do we protect against the
Threats that my router made
Unfortunately you cannot be stolen
Solutions like
Can you play
Is it like
May be used as an adult
We knew that
A solution
Maybe
Hours for somebody else
Will be present in each process home
Example
So do all routers
Manufacturers
Summer
Each night for example
Piper's Auto successful
We can prevent the attacks
Even being
Home Depot
I don't have the password
Oversee something
Being outdated
I do not want my router
Can I do something to
Fully updated
You can get
What are the front of your house
And then Fox would they care
Excellent so where can I buy listeners go to
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Andy Wilson
Thompson who is a policy
The open technology
ICC
You guys are working with a couple different groups to create something called the digital
And I
I'm so pumped about this because
We got to start somewhere
And
I really like
Consensus-building and
What does Sol
Let's talk about who you're working with and why you guys cry
So I'm actually going to roll back
10-second
They're six organized
I felt the standard
That did the initial development
I got the test in the content
We did not
We came in
When it launched
To do a sword
Kiara
Convening campaign over the past
You're so
It's great
But this thing was built for us to work with
It's also great that we have sir
Serva third-party Rowland
Companies can say you know I really hate this I really love this and we're a safe space to have those conversations
But the digital standard
Is open-source
Collaborative
Set of tests
An evaluation methodology
Used to test the security and privacy app
Consumer product
Detest
Cigarettes everything from encryption to the hard security we can really talk about
Two things like transparency reporting and privacy policies
And so far they've
By Consumer Reports one of the
The six organizations that helped build
Standard
To evaluate
Smart TVs and payment apps like venmo and
The standard is open-source however switch
The be used by anyone who wants to look
Yes okay and
You kind of Duty this up into a
A couple different areas so under security
You guys have things like those quality of data security app user safety
Which almost feels kind of like u l territory in some ways
And then you have
Privacy
You focus on
Accessing
Troll
Data retention policies
Collecting
Too much
Third-party tracking
And then
There's also the question of what happens after you purchase this
Idea of ownership
Governance model
So there's a lot of
Unpack here
The most complete looking part seemed to be tied to security
And privacy
Correct
Yes I think there's the most
Consensus among you know organizations that you just kind of stuff
That those two
Privacy features are kind of
That you wanted
Have you want to have a mechanism for reporting vulnerabilities those types of things are more
Agreed upon
Three categories
Standard because it's open source so it's a lot of
Collaborative creation
First set is
Done
That is
I seen
Well understood with
Developed testing approach
The nursing staff
You know colors like a stop light yellow things which are under development
But still have some else
Standing questions
And then ride is a TARDIS
So nobody's using those under discussion wenzhou
The test yet
They are really complex issues that still need to have
Debate between the people developing the standard
I said they're sort of in their infancy but
You know I know you want to get in
And two things that are not
Quite ready for lunch yet
Antarctica
Yes but
We'll talk about what we know
Because I think it's really
I feel like a lot of people when we start talking about security and privacy of these devices
People just kind of throw up their hands
That's too much information is too hard I can't convey that I can't build it
I can't do anything with it
Let's hope those people relax
You got a section on the best build
And what is some of the things that that in
Best build prop
The standard
Sort of talk about industry best practices
Paradiso when the software
Product development
Industry best practice
Things like safety features not using unsafe
Function
Orcutt Library
It's not to come
Complex
That one is
When you create this product did you do the best
Did you consider privacy
Insecurities as a build in or is
Rental companies that's where to stay when they're creating their product you know
This is something really important to us and we wanted here.
Best practices
That's sort of an A+ from us
Broadly so when we start moving to data security in your authentication that used to be
A lot of these are really like we talked about these on the show all the time
Changing default passwords making sure people have really
Good passwords and encouraging them to make them
I like
The idea of multi-factor authentication is another big
ATL I wish I could see that and actually more
Home device
Are there other things you want to call out in the security section that are
Relevant or
Probably
Worth mentioning or new
So
Just for passwords
Interesting because
Companies actually
That one of those things my colleagues and I have been doing it
Cashier speaking to stakeholders like
Companies in non-profit
Privacy and security are really important and we think you should
Do them better but also here
Discerning tool for you that you can look at you know here sort of a hit list of stuff that
You could
Next product
Supervisor current products
Include
To get certified you know checklist
Privacy and security community
Companies that are doing a great job come to us
You say.
Authentication test
Is actually cheap simple it's not cooling
Consider things like
Fingerprints
Or other
More complex indication
And it just sort of
Originally said be able to change the password require a long password
And I think it was require a password
Because companies that are really good at this
Actually this is too easy like
There should be an expectation that people do something
Better is to
Kind of a big issue here
You guys do a really good job like
You kind of talk about the test you talk about
Criteria
And you talk about the procedures you can use to test
For this which I think is really helpful for companies that are looking to implement
I was just speaking to a group about iot devices
Security and I was talking about you
Of course this is a normal human being
They don't know what encryption
So you can do all of this on the back end
But to communicate with
The buyers of
How do we bridge that Gap because I don't think it's fair.
Require people
Understand
Encryption
I told her she was willing to understand it
It does feel like
Pretty big lies
Shopping app
So I mean everyone who works on this
I spent a long time trying to draw cool diagrams of what encryption means or coming up
Analogies for the public
To say this is what encryption
Especially in the Google Apple
Conflict with
Congress
About
Encryption default
But I think 103
That we are
You know my call again I came in through the window
The standard was developed
So we're giving a thing into
Could you work with us
And one of the reasons we really like it is
Because Consumer Reports is used it twice
And Nicole is not really
Provide
Consumer web
Here are the results
F-35 test
It's sort of
Mortal list of judgment of like is this Securus
If it's not secure
As poorly but this is never meant for
Consumption this entire consumption cool like
If you really want to read what happened
When needed an identification test on the newest light bulb
But we're not
Consumers understand that when
Purchase something
All right and now we're going to get into some of that
Ohio
I'm going to call them
Hotspot issues
Is because we talked about them I think they're really important I also think they're really hard to solve
So thank you talk about things with no necks
Play resistance which people are very similar
Potato put a product on the market
Get that you know is going to
But then
We move into this concept of security over time
And you know
The Kevin and I my colleague on the show talk about
I would love to see an expiration date
Providing security is not
It's not an expensive
Freight updating your software.
Things up to date
Is available resources Q
UA testing all of this so
How are you guys approaching that
Ocular issue
I think for iot that's it in some ways unique challenge because when people go by really X
Home devices Like Home Appliances which
You know all of the companies want to build
Fun things into them you expect to have this for 15 years
Be 2 years you want to have your
You're not going to throw away
Refrigerator
Quickly because
See that you want to have
I like the idea of
Both have an expiration date
I will not support after whatever
I think that could be available for consumers
It's not something
What is Belton
This is a requirement
But I do that
Think that I could be released
Effective way of communicating.
To Consumers when they spend a lot of money on
Something what are device makers telling you about this concert
SEPTA security
What time like maybe they have some gradle
I think a security overtime
Casino Consumer Reports
Companies in the same way that you know they don't have a
Here's how the srk
Conversation with vendors
Or manufacturers
Not the way they're all he's worked a chilly day for us
And say
I think you should do this better
Share the way
Testify
Security overtime is one
That's what if we thought like assertive hand wave on a bye yeah yeah like that's
You know we're going to keep it updated
Rather than
IClear Wrecking
That's not something we can do forever and we're going to
Explicit
I think that's a real challenge
Just because the
You know specifically smart home industry
Is
Built on
She was very
What type of seals model
Redis built on to
You by Selena cost
$2,000
And keep it forever rather than
You know I'm more
Cool Tech toys
Sales model
Brakes
Network
Pretty soon
So the ability for company
Today and we're going to
Stop servicing it after
Time one of the discussion
We've had.
Scariest Birds
Was what about it
There are third-party
Repair people who
So. Gets into
At the start of ownership and right to repair
Is good
Cuz that's where we're going next
Soufeel
Yeah let's move into that
Maybe if
Company why who makes her expensive
Refrigerator says they can
Can service it after 5 years
Smart person
Men with their own Scrappy
VTech company
I could come fix it for you
Solution maybe not a popular one for companies
Yeah so you actually have a whole section on ownership
Digital standard in that whole section is
I know people can see
I see colors but it's basically
Red which means like
Nobody else
We're just throwing this out the hip feels like
And in that you guys have things like hay
Interoperability
Ownership
End
Resale
And this actually gets
Something I would
I'm thinking about cuz I'm
Going to put my house on the market eventually
How do I
Freecell Vista
So what are you guys pushing for what are you guys talking about
What people would have
So
When it comes to having conversations
Resort at the very
High level of a lot of people
Start a startup
Easy lift
Generally agreed upon
Security Experts
Elementary
Preschool level security everyone will tell you
And it's not
You might not want to do the work or spend the money
But you know
Hair products
But
Stuff like
Interoperability
Companies that day
Really
Don't like things like resale or right to repair ideas
But when we
Working
Besides
Agree to disagree on this right now
Please don't
Not have
Good passwords
Because
You disagree with us
Okay so bigger fish to fry now
At the end of October the US copyright office actually said
That certain set of products we do now have a
Which felt like a step forward and maybe maybe this is something that gets determined in the courts
It's a design process
That's part of
Cuz of the ITC based in so
We do work a lot with Congress
And
Regulators and things that Seto on all of our policies
And so
Places
Slice copyright office
TC
Are interesting
Touchpoints
Or you know how what role did they play in
Maybe it is the Court's maybe his Regulators that are going to
Be that big finger on the button
Like you're not allowed to do
PewDiePie
Anymore you need to
Steamers better way
Take ownership and I'm not
Obviously
People who advocate
Security advocacy community
Can say this
FTC penalties or
No legal challenge
Well that gets into
Red
We don't know what we're doing
This point on this whole thing which was
Business model
So what are your thoughts
It's about where you'd like
To see that go
So when it comes to digital standard you know when you start to talk about the things about governance
Privacy
Supposed to use a lot of it is
Not so much about the
The policy it's about making that really clear defense
Consumers what the policy
So
You're so far the business model
Pasties
Nowhere it's it's listed as a placeholder in there saying there's going to be something about it
But it's really important that they make clear
Two customers
Whether they make their money through advertising
Subscriptions
Basically when you buy some
Something should be transparent about are they making money through
3 selling your data
And that ties into something that we constantly
Crocodile
And I hate because I actually read all the TOs has and privacy terms but
Do you really
Yes yes it's really a lot
But is there anything in here
Don't want to say I didn't see it
But maybe I missed
Because there is a lot here
About how we should present
These kind of terms and
Cuz there's a lot about terms of service
Enforcement of them
Is there anything about like
How to make that intelligible without forcing people
David disagreements which are
Oh my gosh you guys
Really
Really ice cream
Looking at this
I really am
Appreciate the focus in terms of
Privacy policy the things that digital standard
Asked you for
Are that they are presented in an understandable manner which isn't super clear that's pretty
They should be in language is most commonly spoken by the
And the company clearly discloses
Which policy is applied
The thing you just bought and that
So they're in
Huge focus on
What the terms of service should
Look like but that it should be clear
And a field goal
If someone wants to read them
It's not
16 tabs in legalese in
Cheney is in a place where people are
Scrolling through on my other
When your oven oh
Okay and so
Along these lines I'm just going to
Throw out some wishlist I have four connected to
Devices and see how plausible are where youth
We might get on some of these
1 is
A lot of these
The terms of service and privacy
Cease we actually see when we download the app is
For installing
Vice which feels like
A really big missed opportunity be
Because then I'm like
Crap this device is not secure enough
It doesn't follow all my
You know I don't want to get them
Can a permission then I have to take it back I might be subbed
Restocking fee
Are there
Protections in place or things that we should be advocate
On my separate personal opinion
One of the greats
If you have cancer
Ideas
It's still under development open source
Regular people
Actually makes it
Birds and components of it but
Personally
Yes I do
Beverly gradle
People could read the terms
Service earlier
Encouraged
To I don't know
Accept terms of service maybe once they put something in their cart
Online
But I think
You know we still face the problem of someone buying something
Wanting to
Use the fun new feature isn't going click click click through
Whatever is between them in the funnies
Social adjustment
Every in terms of service as much as I did sign
Yes but I was thinking about you know
With the GM story
Text back I was looking at that in like hey you know what if I got my
My boss my car
I wanted to turn on Wi-Fi
Pretty useful
Features to have in a car
And then I'm like oh
Wait I'm giving them access to all this crazy data and maybe they did say that they were going to sell
That's awful
At the same
Sports
Definitely not
So those are the kind of things are in like
But I swear that
I mean one of the
Reason set
I think I consumer-facing standard is really important
People already read things like
Consumer Reports
When they want
To buy a car
And if
Expectation.
Terms of service
Included in the
Consumer Reports
If you buy this
Scar it could
Require you to give over this information it could require you to sign up
Terms of service questionable
And so you know what third parties evaluating that
And informing customers about it at the same time as informing them about
The annoying turn signal flippy thing
Part of the overall package
Medication
Great maybe
Yeah I know I actually thought I'll tell you guys as my audience
I am looking at this and I'm thinking hey as a reporter
A lot of these things I do
Or at least ask about
Sometimes
And that's kind of where we are
But I would love to see more reporters
Asking
About that sewing
Candy
Reporters are great
Distorted by carrot and
Stack and bonus
But I think the goal is you know anyone who wants to
I think we're deeply about this any company can do it and he asked
The organization
You can do it and I mean it be great if
On a major data breach of some
I Was Here by someone says
Hey you know
Maybe if they'd adhered to something like the digital standard this wouldn't happen
Right and so normalizing
Best practices
Could be a useful tool in moving the industry as a whole
Will get there I mean
So if you guys want to find this it's at
Www.
The digital standard
. org
And it's
I encourage you to look at it
You can download
I don't get help so yay
And apparently make suggestions there
Andy do you want to tell us anything else
I think that you know I want to make sure that I give
Credit to the
Help build the standard led by Consumer Reports disconnect
Etre conditionnel right by the Cyber independent testing lab and with us
Aspiration
My colleagues and I don't see I came in at a later date
Spread this information around the country and collect feedback
But we were so happy to
Have you no really
Kristen wonderful
Set of test to work with
Thank you Stacey
I really appreciate this conversation
Yeah thanks so much for coming on the show this weekend e that's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will be next week