Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we've got a
Rip roarin show for you
You today we're going to be talking about Microsoft in their 5 billion dollar investment in iot qualcomm's brand new
Vision intelligence chips
Kevin
Has some insights about
Voice assistant
What's that you should hear
Plus is the Apple watch losing its apps
It doesn't matter
Comcast is adding stringify
We've got some exploits again
With iot
It devices
And some news plus we're going to talk about me installing the nest hello doorbell and what I think
And I dumped a device for my home
Because by golly it
Find out what that is
And hear from our Advertiser this week for a truck
And learn about the future of hearing
From poppy Crum who is a chief scientist at Dolby labs
It is a jam-packed show
So let's get it started with a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is the yonomi platform for the makers of the free you know me after you know me platform is a
I'm faced platform-as-a-service for companies Building Solutions for the connected home you know he's offering
Include hidden Cloud the server list iot platform for device manufacturers looking to get their products to Market
Quickly and securely there's also you know me one a powerful integration engine that connects more than a hundred
Top smart home devices this week on the Stacey on iot podcast
Part three of their five-part series on what the next billion-dollar smart home startup will look like
You can find that today by visiting platform. You know me. Co / Stacy
Xeon iot yonomi is spelled y o n o m
I
Cake
Man
Great episode
I realize that I say super all the time
We can start a drinking game with me being super excited or super happy
Or
I don't know
So I'm trying to stop that let's see how well I do
Yucaipa
Crap a beverage and see what happens
All right
To get started
Microsoft
They announced last week that they were going to spend 5 billion dollars over the next 4 years
Where's on the internet
Thanks
What do you think about
Well maybe they're there a big player we probably don't talk about them as much as we should
But cuz they're behind the scenes of a lot of things and what I liked about their news announcement witch
I would say the light on details on how they're going to invest
Even see anything
Earth shattering in there was a continuation of their efforts
What I like in there something that I've noted
With Google's IRT
Press announcements
Is often missing there was some
Real actual customers in here
And discussions of how these customers
Use
Microsoft platform
4 IRT
When I say customers I mean
Steelcase color Chevron Johnson Controls United Technologies
The Alaska Department of Transportation which
That was kind of cool cuz they're building smart roadways to monitor weather conditions
So
They actually Microsoft
Their iot stuff and azure
Are you spy
Buy Hershey's
To make
Twizzler packets
Twizzlers candy
That's my backyard Hershey
So
They use it to make sure every Twizzlers package is packed with
The right amount
Whistlers
Because before they added sensors and analytics to this
Process
They actually were like
You had too many Twizzlers in a bag
That was fine but if you didn't have enough to meet the weight requirement
You had to just Jam more in
So they were
Are Twizzlers were not uniform enough
And so
They managed to save money by making them more uniform so they could
Dirty Woods of licorice production
Microsoft has some really good
Smurfs here and
I actually emailed them to get a little bit more in
Information did I get a lot more
But
Put this in context
Microsoft has spent
One point
5 billion over the last 4 years so this is a huge increase in their spending
In
They really talk about it
They're going to add
More people
They're going to do more in R&D
They're going to work more with
Their partner so a lot of this is going to be training
People and partners
Some hiring
And some cool stuff
And apparently this is a really important sentence to Microsoft because they sent it to me
Me twice in the same two paragraph email
But according to them
Quote by investing even more in iot we are committing the resources and Innovation to empower companies to
To take advantage
Iot and intelligent Edge
What does that mean
But
It does mean that Microsoft is a
Excited about iot
They actually also this week
Partnered with Tom siebel scump
Nac3
C3 is a platform-as-a-service that does alot of data analytics
And they got started in the energy space Benadryl and monitoring
Data for
Mini mini smart grid devices
And they really branched out into iot
I actually just last week did a deal with
Is it all in the industrial Enterprise side but
This is where the big money is so we were
Moving right along
Qualcomm
Has New Vision intelligence chip
These are a new line of chips
They made
Television intelligence
It is basically
It's kind of like what
Nvidia switch Intel bios
And a couple weeks ago we actually announced it arm is going to have
Machine learning platform for the edge and Invidia is actually using its vision
Processing
Engine on those
On the arm design
So everybody is really excited about computer vision at the edge
We can talk about it here
4 years
And so it's finally coming
To fruition
With cheap low-power silicon
These are the
IQs 603 and 605 chips and I actually got really excited when I read about where they
Are looking to apply the technology to where they expect people or companies to apply at
You'll see why in a second
Obvious example of security cameras Sports cameras wearable cameras
Virtual reality cameras here we go
Robotics
And smart displays
I just got excited with robot
Yes
The ones with arms are the ones that you're
Speaker on and have fun
The smart speaker on the Roomba I think I'll just wait and get one with arms now
There you go smart speakers
Smart speakers
Arbs and
That's what we need
Okay these are wifi-only
Only chips
Just so you guys know
Oh and
Qualcomm has been doing computer vision but they have been doing it on there
Snapdragon
Processor switcher actually design person
So having something specifically designed
The edge
A lot of sense
I'd actually
Because it's Wi-Fi you're not going to see the sun
So I guess the Snapdragon stuff will still be on
Oh I don't know about that cuz like a lot of the drums
To use like a peer-to-peer Wi-Fi to a connected tablet or phone for
Connectivity
Favorite
Okay well maybe I will see this
You. We sure might I think
Black people use drones for the vision aspect obviously
The 605 chip that the more capable of that you can handle simultaneous 4K
And 1080p feeds at 60 frames a second
Suck your battery
Small drones generally do
Sure
And I guess you know if you're thinking about staying in a room that's not
Okay so that's qualcomm's
Let's talk about
Kevin's story this week yesterday Kevin posted a story that was on Wednesday
About
Adding context
That's the big thing that's what we're always
About
Is really
I think there's an opportunity for home assistance and I don't know if people have thought about this weird people really want
Yes I know I do but I know I'm weird so that's okay if you don't want this
Are voice assistants are good at providing
Contextual information
When we asked for it but
Context means right place right time
So why it aren't
Our assistance
Feeding a set of formation at the right time
Meaning
An extension of their existing notification capability right now on your Echo
There are notifications
Damn you make it your little
Make it a sound when somebody calls you you may see the light ring change a different color when your notifications
Then you have to ask and say met him a tell me my notifications
I thought just seems like an unnecessary step
Google home has limited notification support and again if you're not looking at the lights
You're going to miss a notification it supposed to like on your phone you'll get a buzz a beep and all that you pull out of your pond
Mocking someone
That works on a phone notifications
Such as
Buzzing and beeping and all that
Our assistance have voice capabilities that seems to be a much better medium for me to get that information from the
Those devices
That's what I'd like to see is eventually
These devices
Speak out loud say hey it's time to leave based on the traffic in the fact that you're going to work right now I saw that on your account
So that's one example I can come up with a hundred different examples but
The question is do people want
Proactive
Voice notifications should are smart
Speakers speak before being spoken to is the question
You know what it can
I was just out of it so we'll get into this but
The Nest doorbell
Which I installed
Actually gives you an option
You're going to love this
If I'm using
The face detect
Is my doorbell rings
I have the option of turning on a setting that says notify me
The nautical
All devices
So it will notify me on my
Home that somebody that my doorbell is ringing
In addition to the chine
Right what's even cooler is
Is it recognizes
The person's face
It will just say
Stacy's home
Exactly I knew they had that feature and
I think it's awesome that's a perfect example of the value right there
Okay yes and I see this too and so
This brings me to
Epicenter recommended listening
Is sleet
Future tense so will oremus did a podcast
Cast without Lindsey who's the chief of Amazon's
Voice assistant
And they talked about what Madame a here's a took
Laughing
It was really interesting is
Will like Kevin and I really wants more context because that's going to make
Madame is life a little bit easier
But we're in in
Allen's he's all for it
He says that
The big challenge is how do we make
Madam
Contextually
They say they're doing this initially
Bye
Having devices listen so it can determine who's closest
Figuring out if
When you ask her to stop
Do they want you to stop music or the
The video that's on your fire
So they've worked on those and saw that
The idea of kind of gathering ambient information about your environment
Willing that back to the echo that's not have
But he does think
That's how we're
And if for people who don't want that I hope it it's configurable
So that way you can
Yeah you can disable those type of notifications I realize that not everybody wants that
And there are other pieces of the puzzle that need to be in place such as presence detection
Like if it's time for me to leave for work
The echo next to my wife downstairs in the living room while she's watching TV shouldn't say hey it's time to leave
For work
Yes
That is NC in those are the kind of features people will give up
Privacy for
Think about
Think about how freaked out we worry about Gmail and it reading our email soon
Serving ads
That went away so fast because we have free email
And it's not just things like
Free it's things like
How many people get over the worries about Amazon listening to your conversations
Because the echo is such a
Valuable device to them
By the way the
Podcast has talked about
How the echo works so you can
Get a refresher course on
How it listens and triggers the Wayward and your privacy set
They are still the same
They changed I would have led with that
So yeah
I recommend you listen to this if you're a huge Echo user
Will
Drop a note in the
Show notes for y'all
Let's talk about o
One of my favorite
I guess apps
From a while back stringify was bought by
Comcast
In Comcast just this week said
Did they basically relaunch stringify
Are there users of their expected
And
Twitter Kevin Durant
Comcast subscribers
I used to be a stringify user
And Comcast is basically created all of these they call them flows
What is a recipe on automation
Comcast is gone in and created all these flows for
People so they don't
In themselves
It's awesome
So there's a movie night float
For example that says when I ask Madame age to rent movie night
Set the brightness on my living room light.
10%
Pause my son's iPad
Change the channel to Starz kids and family
Do that for me would be family
So none of the flows are is, they're usually about
For devices
They're not as complicated as
I used to try to do
But if I was a mess because making a flow with so hard
And having all these pre-configured for you is actually real
So yeah
Totally agree and again neither you nor I have
Comcast for
Video provider a lot of what they're doing with stringify
Tying into the Xfinity X1 video platform so
Well you may be a stringify user
You may not have access to everything it can offer if you're not a Comcast X1 subscriber so
Yes now as a
I recommend so stringify
Competes most closely with yonomi
Which is a
You know he's a little bit easier to use and they're they're both going in the same
Direction care so
Load one or the other
In start playing around with
Famous the best way I
I can tell you to
Are both free
Comcast still lets people who are not Comcast customers used
By the way they also added
Lutron support So now that got support for casetta lighting Serena shades
And the carrier
Cor thermostats
Yeah there
And folks who use Android where they have a Android Wear watch out for the first time as well so you can easily one tap or what
Voice control your scenes inflows
I will not be able to
And you shouldn't be able to on that small screen so
Those flows
They're really powerful that's the
It's kind of like the choice of
Really simple user interface Limited
Keto options
Kind of more complicated you could do a lot more stuff
Okay speaking of watches
Let's talk
About something that people have noticed
The Apple watch
Is losing apps
Yeah and that's kind of why I said what I just said you shouldn't be able to set up
Smart home flow is on a watch because it just doesn't make sense on that screen
And yes people are getting a little
Worried about the Apple watch
A platform because now they saw Instagram
Is going away from the Apple watch
And other apps have gone away such as Twitter and slack and
Couple of others even Amazon I don't think they're going to be upset about as far as the
Because a lot of those apps really had no place on the small
Screen on your wrist
To begin with
I mean I'm not going to go to an Instagram if you don't know you know 1 and 1/4 inch
Screen Flip Flip Flip Flip and liking flipping foot
It just doesn't make sense
No not Twitter I mean anything with a long float
Certainly doesn't make sense to no notifications for those things
You can still do that without those apps because the way the Apple watch work says you can mirror the notifications from your phone
To your watch so
I don't have
The Facebook Messenger app on my Apple watch but when somebody
Messages me it creates a notification on my phone which is then creates a notification on my watch
Can I get a reply from the watch as a result of that you don't need the app
A lot of cases and notification still very actionable
Again Instagram
Do you want to get notified everytime somebody likes your photo on see that on your watch I can you could probably still do that but you don't need the answer
Give me a map to do anything
Now your rest if it just doesn't make sense
I don't
I don't think it's the right place for these apps to begin with
And that makes a
And so Kevin is not
And I think
Maybe if we get cool stuff like
The watch today
Airpods
And having more voice cwise maybe that'll
Compensate for the screen so maybe having your
Smart
Assistant be able to talk
Talk to you and me
More context oriented and notify maybe that make
For now
No
And we moved so much to the vision
Get on
It's insane
I feel
When I surf
The internet today
Maybe I should
I should tell you guys it's my birthday
Yay I just turned 40
So that might be
All right
Let's talk about
News
Okay
Little bit
Lifx has new controls in feet
Yay August now works with SimpliSafe
FB
Smart home security company so your August lock integrates it now with that
And then Kevin has in x
Will stop my exploit but I'll report online
The other was an interesting article over in Wireless
We cry red
It's not what I thought it was going to be because the title is a long-awaited iot crisis is here and many devices aren't ready
So I assumed it was like IPv6 or something like that
New itsallaboutyou P&P
Which is universal
Plug & Play
That's
I guess it's called a protocol that helps devices on a network find and
Work with other devices
Typically tan media streaming devices
Like if you want to
Use a Chromecast for example
That uses UPnP
To find
Other devices working get content from
So basically the exploit
It's something that Akamai researchers found and they said that there are about
4.8 million devices on the open internet
That would improperly return a certain query related to UPnP
And nearly a million of those
Another issue that would create
A network communication vulnerability
And they have a number of exploits that they've seen out of that as well
A lot of people turn UPnP off because it's not the most secure thing in the world is pretty open thing hey
I'm looking for devices on the network who's out there who can find me
So security standpoint it's not the best
Problem is certain devices require it
Such as a Google Chromecast
Even a Google home because that's how Google home finds
Devices such as other Chromecast so
I'm not suggesting that
Your Google home isn't secure or anything like that but
It does kind of make me wonder I'm trying to get turn around my head around
What the alternative is to UPnP for iot devices in home assistance in such so I don't know what that is yet
I don't know what
Everyone is using so
Not panic mode but this is something to be aware of
All right I know just who to call and ask so maybe I'll
Later this week
Video
All right that's enough news for now
Talk about
Should I go with things I've added or things I've done
Take
Let's go with me dumb cuz I'm really curious as to why you dumped this
Product plus I like to hear you say the product
Oh okay so
I was house cleaning I think I told you about myself
Spring cleaning
And basically I have dumped my Ikea
Triad 3
Tradfri
How is it supposed to be
I think you said it correctly
Okay my Ikea tradfri
And I'm sorry Ikea I'm sorry
Worked really well
In their own little ecosystem of
Stuff to the hub
Two bulbs that I had
Incredibly well
They did not play well
Madam
One I never actually got to
One worked
London
And then the one billboard wood
And one ball just
It would be recognized by as a device on Madame a but it would never actually be
Controlled BMI
My voice
Except
What's so weird about it
Except when it was included in a routine
And that would work
That's odd
Isn't it crazy
I assume this is done through a skill
It is it's Ikea has a skill
And I will tell you guys that I deleted it off the echo
I deleted the skill
Alright disabled the skill
I uninstalled the app
I reinstalled
I redid the Gateway
I re-added every
Instilled
And going through the
Comments on the app
Apparently this is not an isolated incident
I found several things in Reddit about
This being
No problem
So
I just got sick of it it was my bedside table lamp in my husband's bedside table lamp
I laugh at this but
You know it was so nice to be able to say
Turn on Stacy
And poof
The Lamplighter
Turn off
You know those are
Really nice use cases in my husband was just his it was his that didn't
Of course it was
So basically
I did it out of him it was like a mercy killing
So these are no longer in my home
No longer installed
I may try to give them away so we'll see if that because I give away later on
Take my broken iot devices
Broken
I know I
But yeah they don't work with Madam a
And I don't believe they work
With Google home
I don't believe so
That is where those stand I'm leaving them maybe Ikea will get its act together in this work but
Until then they're not installed
That is dumped
Alright well what did you ask
Oh you guys
You know that I love doorbells
Or if I have a love-hate relationship
So I had gotten a review unit of the nest
Hello
And this doorbell
Is amazing
It is a very good
I don't know
It is on par with the ring Pro
In terms of the level of installation
And
The quality of the video
I think it loads a little bit faster
And then you have all these Integrations because I have a Google home and because I have a
Pixel 2 phone
This is definitely the doorbell I would choose for that type of setup
I also have a Chromecast
I have not
Casted
To the Chromecast yet I'm actually in the next week I'm at
I'm going to come to you guys after having Google fi to my house
It's going to be fun
That's where we are right
I will be very curious how that works with your Chromecast only because my Nvidia Shield which is also my SmartThings
Tub
Has Google assistant and
When I'm watching TV
I would love to actually
Get a notification
Of
Somebody at the door and door
The video
Pop-up mode I don't think that's
An option right now but
I'm thinking ahead I would love to see that cuz all the tools are there just needs to be in
So we're going to see what happens when I Google fi and I also have the Yale lock
It's not installed on the same door
Where is the
Doorbell
Because
The doorbells on my front door
Front door is weird
So we're running some experiments to time how long it takes me to
It'll be able to remotely unlock the door so we'll tell you more about that but
The doorbell
$239
Install
Like the physical install
Pretty easy I think we talked about it last week
I did
Resolve the wiring issue
And that was mostly a Stacy's got weird wires kind of thing
In the end
Getting it connected
Was a challenge from my
Pixel 2
It was a snap
On the iPhone
That's weird
Yeah that was how I feel
It took me a couple customer support interactions and then
A reset
And it never connected
So I'm a little frustrated by that I find at the
Adding devices experiences always if your
On an Android device so
If you were able to connect your nest
Hello with an Android
Tell me how you did it
I spent
Probably three or four days trying to make that work
It's kind of longer than I
So those are my products
And now
What's answer somebody else's
Question
From the
Internet of Things podcast
Hotline
Coyote podcast listener hotline
Is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic lock
Which way you can just have a brand new electronic lock installed in minutes with just a screwdriver and your own two hands
And they're easy to setup and use
To see what's possible
Schlage.com
To learn more
If you guys want to leave a voicemail for us and have us answer your iot questions
Ring us at 5 1/2
623-7424
And Kevin actually has another ID
Even if you don't have questions you can
Call in with some of your favorite home automation routines I had written a post
Earlier this week two
Suggest some to my favorites and some of Stacey's favorites and we're getting some really good suggestions in the comments
But I would love to have people call in and provide us some of your
More unique
Home automation routines
Yes super actually to do an episode that is all
You guys
Your comments
Your automation
What's your question
So
Send them in
512-262-3742
Okay
This week's question is from
Derek
Hey Stacy Hey Kevin this is Derrick from California
My question is around smart home devices it appears that you know zigbee and Z-Wave are still kind of duking it out
I'm wondering
Is there a
Stand-alone hub
Or maybe a starter pack
You might recommend
Somebody to connect to their router
So that you know I don't have to worry about which protocol eventually you know when's the game so again just look
Looking for a way to break into it with maybe a
Mandation on your part thank you guys great show love it by
Oh Derek this is
Like you could have asked this question 5 years ago and you know what the answer still probably
The same
Pretty much mostly mostly the same
What's the Atari
So yes this is
Lady Eternal question
And iot
Your answer is
Uniqlo
The best hubs we find 3 Kevin
I found we found
3 SmartThings support zigbee and Z-Wave as does wink
As does a router that you point it out to me
The almond 3 router by securifi
That actually
It's kind of an under-the-radar product but you can buy
This is both a
Smart home hub
It is a router
And it can actually act as a home security system with
The proper it to have a home security system options so you can have sensors and stuff
Talk to it
One of the routers is $150
3 cost
$400
And
I tested these out actually there
Quite good
It's a good Hub it's a nice user interface
I don't know why more people don't have them
In all honesty because
I don't think people know about them as much
Yeah so that is out there and it's a mesh Wi-Fi router system
I don't know
So
And Derek if you're wondering why we didn't include the new Amazon Echo Plus which is an echo
A smart home hub in one
Because it only supports
WiFi Bluetooth n
Zigbee
Not Z-Wave
Yes
All right
That is the answer to your question
Hits by a hub
I'm sorry that that is the answer to you
Your question
It is what it is
Alright stay tuned you guys be
Because our guest this week puppy Crum is Avicii scientist
Dolby labs and she's going to talk about hearables
How we perceive music and what it means to give computers hearing
From The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is for truck and I have
Ben Goodman
VP of strategy and Innovation here at Fort Rock to talk to us
About ringing consent
To the edge
Superman
Remind us first what it is
Active digital identity
We have a platform
Tools that allow us to do things like
Authentication and authorization
Manage user data and one of the things that's really exciting about our platform is
Is that we can take that platform and use it in ways that people didn't traditional music
So outside the Enterprise to the edge
And I think that's what we want to talk about here
So last week we did talk about this idea bringing consent to the edge
How do we do that
Generally speaking has really been about things that you do inside of your computer or your mobile device so it's been about
Authentication to a website or authentication to an application but more and more
Especially as
Taipei
Organizations are trying to compete with
Your native digital organization
It really is about
Instantiating all day
Controlling capability that I have on the web in the real world
And so what we believe is really important now is to take
The concepts of digital identity Weatherby Authentication
Or data protection or Access Control
Elections
Bring them down
To the physical world
What we've been doing is working with a lot of really interesting
Vendors like Armin
Samsung Intel
And making sure that we can take
All the capabilities
We have in the web
And bring it down
Into the real world answer some of that may be as simple as
Utilizing a trusted element or a trusted environment inside of a chipboard inside of the device at the edge
And actually making sure that
We can control the flow of
Personal information
As it goes to and from that device
It may mean around how we
Create secure channels and how would you ask
So what you really the key thing here
Is that
More and more people want a bridge
The physical world
And in order to do that
You need
Addition identity
And he destroyed any vendor that understands how to push that and that's something that has been focusing on really expensive
So what does that look like for the End customer
It's important that for the end
Customer they don't see this kind of jarring
Separation
What happened to the physical world
You seem very organic and so
What that means is that behind the scene
We have to
Create an identity for a thing
And manage relationships with it just like we would manage relationships
Between two people and
Give them the end-user levers
That makes sense to them about how they share data just like they would share data with
And so I think it's very easy if we say that I'm hey
You know in order for me to personalize this hotel room for you
You're going to have to share a certain
And make those very clear concise and
We provide the plumbing that allows that to happen
But it's still the responsibility
Of the vendor that wants to provide this personalized
Make sure that they're surfacing that in a really user-friendly way
Alright where can we go to learn more
Please look at our website
4j.com where we have
A ton of information on privacy and really interesting things that are cost
Dealing with it and specifically checkout.com privacy
Hey everybody Welcome Back To The Internet of Things
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Poppy Crum who is the chief scientist at
Toby
She is talking to us at South by Southwest
Just part of the IEEE.
Hack for Humanity
So hi Papi how are you
Feisty
I am super excited because you work on something that I am super passionate about which is curable
Because I think this is
Perfect example where like
Technology advancement
Meets actual
Better
So let's get right into the fact that
I am super optimistic about hearing aids incurables
How do you feel about this
I really think that you're is going to be a transformational place with regard to both Ai and the
When did reality Hub in the future there's so much information and learning about an individual that happens in your ear we can
Talk about that
But there's this also
Lot of movement that's happening
In this space right now
We're seeing huge converge
Between entertainment
Lifestyle
And
Hearing health
I'm a True Believer that
Our Technologies are only going to be as good as we
Can get them too if we have personalized devices
Annie really becomes this amazing
Hub at
Information
Between
Individual and the external world
To really think about how we optimize our experiences and make these devices and enabler iot devices to be
What I would call an extension of our agency
Wow that was super deep okay you brought up
The whole bunch of stuff for me so we're going to break some of this down
Cuz I was thinking
Hey hearables their medical devices but then when you talk about AR and BR in like oh my gosh in at Dolby I'm like
Peasant immersive experience
Is false breakdowns for me should I be thinking of hearing just
Bradley and we should apply it everywhere
That's a great question
I think there's a lot of waste
I tried to break it down
Where is a device in my ear might actually be able to enhance
My life or ways we even use them
You can separate and let's start
With the way we're already people are already using hearables might be as assistants I think that's a pretty
Ubiquitous use that showing up
Are you can talk about hearable both as a static character
What's the price of an Amazon Echo
Go home or a wearable device
We should listen we talked about the wearables right now as an assistant you've got something intersecting other app
Applications
Ways of
Causing things to happen in my world that I'm actually
Requesting
In your ear you've also got information
It can pick up on you've got within their system
Really rich set of biological signals
That having sensors and that one particular place in your body
Tiny
Certify call it will dime-sized patch you can pick up
Up your heart rate
You can pick up the electroencephalogram pick up EEG you can pick up
Blood oxygenation
Your galvanic skin response
Internal information about
Kathy is our state
So how do we use that to sing
But you've also got the devices
It's listening to your environment
So now you got it for
Coming in and information about you whether it's for your voice or through
Reading information about your state that's going out
And that interplay is I think will really important part of the future
Wow I didn't realize you could get all that for my ear so that's actually go bad
And talk about yours for a second
And hearing and all the information like
Maybe it's not as simple as how it works but if I'm thinking about taking information what does information that's
Good to get from
My eardrum and what makes sense to
Happen it
In your device
Great questions and if we look back five years things have really evolved
That's why the way we might have described him Taken 2 years ago different than how I'm talking about them
Today
We are in the last few years people have been able to in a lab and you're just with your sensors capture
Picking up and decoding
My attention
Attentional my cot where it's being directed
The Who
The what
Aware
And you end up with these inferences happening in a lab might be
Somewhat noisy but suddenly you pair that with environmental intelligence and contacts I know I'm at a restaurant
Because the device can tell or I know I'm
I got certain stalkers I'm trying yo that are in my social network in my device knows that it knows who those people I care about are
Answers and start painting this really rich
Picture that's going to ask
Actually
Truly enhance my experience and not just be feeding me again that you have a text message to go check your email
So I can literally mute people
Don't we all
Completely possible that your device in
Getting out of the lab is one thing that we're really moving towards that your device would allow you to have
One conversation listen to another
Multitask
Let's do that in a effective way but it's a can make you more social again it
We already do that
In our attention at the cocktail party solving that kind of
Problem
You're aware I'm in a noisy environment and how do I make sense of my
Acoustic environment
Someone who has hearing lots of fun of hardest problems in for someone that doesn't have her
Hearing loss that's still a hard problem
Let me go to a restaurant that's popular it's really noisy and it's something that
Greatly impacts
Our social club
Communication
So what we want our devices that enable us to
Better communication with
Each other without us having to break that conversation and go you know
Turn up the cell phone or
Intersected and police things that you want your device to know so what am I device that can pick up one on my cock.
That's a fairly robust thing that we can track quite easily it can tell if my brains having to work harder and it responds
How do we change that technological Lube
Because you've got
You've got these different devices you got
Information about me
These things that are happening in the world of AI and machine learning are we becoming much more intelligent
The environment
You're in the military they call that situational awareness and
When you think about what
My situational awareness for my contacts that's really relevant
To my devices
Sing to me
I want my devices optimizing
Their signal processing
And their capabilities to be intelligent to that without my having to intervene
Type of intersection and so that's what we're really starting
To see in especially in development especially in sort of what I would call bleeding edge Technologies for hearing aids as well
Okay so you're actually talking about customization both to my hearing level and then also to whatever environment I'm in
Has a lot of computational
Power so
Or it feels like it should be a lot of come
Computational power so what is happening
Justin the physical Hardware side
It's making this pause
Football today
I think there's really a beautiful Resurgence in Seoul
Working development that's happening
If you look at the let's just talk
Carrying out front
Because the richness of what's going to happen
Or needs to happen to truly make a hearable device
A significant one that we all
Benefit from
Is Convergence of both entertainment and lifestyle and this hearing Health space
Sharing Health space UCI
A lot of
Hearing aids in
Make use of the same so I can make use of the same signal processing and it's really quite
Constrained but
In order to get
A lot of this
More advanced machine-learning nuts and things that are going
To enable more intelligent experiences
The Silicon development has really started
There's been a big Resurgence in that development to be able to miniaturize computation
In Tucson
Into a small enough
Form factor for hairball
Now form factor is a huge
Yeah you look at it
Hearing aids they really haven't changed much at all
And there's a big stigma
Associated with some of the
Four factors that currently exist Things Are
Behind the ear
Come with a medical branding on them they say you're old
And people hate that
What I see that's really wonderful about how things are going to transform music
Everybody's wearing horrible to destigmatize is it
For everyone because
Unlike Vision where people might say not wearing glasses you
You have a muscular a muscle benefit sometimes and
And I would question that but there are reasons with the
Case of hearing if you actually don't innovate your hearing
If you have hearing loss and you aren't stimulating people wait to get here unless there's actually an increased deficit
Neural deficit happens
All through the pathway so there's this
Very important
Aspect of getting people to
Not just preserve there. But actually intervene when you have hearing loss as soon as possible
The reality is we all start having hearing loss when
Dinner
Early twenties and its mission
Things from our environment exposure to noise ototoxicity aspirin soda toxic
A lot of things we just
Julian just
Avatar
Okay so my life is a rock critic
In my college Years and
My incredible ingestion of aspirin is causing me some eggs
Now I'm like oh my gosh
Okay but
Let's go back to what it takes
Before you freak me out more
Too many tries this
What is the ideal form factor do you think or what is a form factor we're working toward
And then what
Just be something we have everyday that we just wear and we listen to music and we
Go talkin
Pop it in when we're like of a certain age I mean what is this look like in the
That's a great question.
Because it's evolving and
Think about it this way
I don't like to
To think that having hearing loss there was a statistic I came across 19% of
12 to 17 year olds
Already have some degree of noise-induced hearing
And that's a pretty terrifying statistic but
Movie think about hearables
I really do feel
We don't want to talk about it with regard to hearing
We want to talk about it disregard
Personalization
And how do we we all have our physiological systems are all differ
Environment
Irrelevancies and sensitivities that are environments demand of us are differ
So we went processing that is capable to adjust to that and learn those needs of us
With regard to a form fact
That's a really fun question because
They're a lot different ways you can go and things you're seeing happening
There's no question a small device is interest
If you look at it
Where are the Haribo company's are right now it really is it runs the gamut
Let's it's a hugely heterogeneous in terms of form
Talking about devices
Like your go who are trying to be assertive
Disruptive I love their form-factor they're sort of a disruptive they still considered
Call themselves the hearing aid but therein are almost entirely hidden from the world there's nothing that goes off
Warrior versus a company
There's a Hero
Human
But has he started Elston
Devices that fit
Completely over here which I also think is beautiful you're trying to
Create a very different in both cases a different landscape than what
Historical hearing aid
Fourth doctor
Whip It
You'll have a lot of devices like
Like nuheara
Former Doppler where you have
A near device but it's
Wanting to point out here is it's fully exclusive
And everything you hear from the world
Is Electro acoustic layer
Representative
Which is just some level of philosophical conundrum I'd like to think of it
So instead of the analog signals we're getting the digital interpretation of the analog signals
Precisely
And we can do that pretty well
But it's a funny thing so it to me and this is my personal belief that
Ideal form factor something that leverages our natural physiological capabilities and then
Gives us things on top of
Rather than just recreate it so it because
You think about going to wander the world if I would you wear a VR device if I tell you everything you're going to experience is
Entirely an accurate representation of the world
I will be able to give you more but you're still it's all going to be sent
Did you go out for the rest of your life doing nothing
No I would not
Which gets to this idea of perception and you've done a lot of Standards work around the concept of
So let's talk about
Let's talk about your philosophy there actually that
So in this case you're talking about letting someone else mediate how you experience the world but you also work
And standards efforts to establish baselines for how people
A different
Levels experience the world correct
So my background I'm a neurophysiologist by training but also I've been in the technology space for quite some time
I really
Like to think that I spend my time trying to identify
Anafi
Ways our technology is going to best intersex
With
Austin's depending on both an understanding of our biology but also a
Are perceptual realities we each experience the world and very unique ways some of those we can track some of those
We haven't been able to but
And we're learning more about how we can actually objectify what someone's XP
Prancing and use that to informed
Technology
No I'd like to say we're building
Technologies that are
The way they intersect with us it feels like a true extension of our agency
And not the technology telling us what we have to expect
Answer what we are going to do
Anticipating
How
Yep we would naturally
For me the world going at every moment is and this is I think
We are thinking about
Things now it's a probabilistic
Experience
And many features come together
To determine
How we experience how we each differentially experience perhaps the same
Piece of
Cremation your and UK
Can probabilistically model those things weather
I go back
20 years I spent a lot of time thinking about probabilistic inference for how we experience auditory and visual information to four
Where it is
When it happens and
You can develop very intelligent models at this
But now you get into this
Transition where
The device
Needs to
Understand those
Perceptual reality cuz if ice is going to have a lot more information then
We ever experienced
We don't Xperia
And having a device tell us things in the wrong place or intersect Us in the wrong place that isn't consistent with that
Is jarring and actually think will make us less if
So it's how do we
Bridge that Gap
So it's like we've been doing a lot of work we read a lot about computer vision
This is kind of computer hearing and understanding
What different things mean to a person when we're actually perceiving
So I always know that if I hear a car in my
Like behind me
I always look in check and I know exactly where that car is based
A computer may not have that sense until we program it
Is that kind of close
Yes on some level
Computer hearing
Is very relevant
But it's more than
Write it needs
There's information
What it tells you
How it informs
How it makes use of that information so something as simple as I want to
Inform you that their car right behind you there's other things I have to get right because now I've got to create binaural represent
Tatian maybe I got an inner tube I so I didn't synthetically
If I'm
Trying to do this and it say an inclusive environment at the synthetically recreate
Information that informs you in the right way
To make sure that you reacted
That's indicative of
What would be the most successful for you
In fact that's a pretty tough problem
In that case because I got a saint if I didn't
Patient meaning
I need to identify what's the best Q I could give you
How to make sure that every single time you experienced that
Or someone else does
It's in the accurate location
And that's something that the industry has not been able to get
Cracked
In the variance is based on what
Are hearing loss over time or just
Totem multitude of Futures because it one thing we each have
Unique what I like to call cookie cutters
Our bodies are at anthropometry of our ears or head
Create a very unique filter of continuations and excitations across amplification Center
Continuations across every frequency in sound in
World that is unique
Chimichurri sauce
But we also have very unique
Hearing patterns and different physiological
Call changes that happen to our bodies and we also have them the context of information of the environment
Those three pieces come together and no
You have a knack
Accurate representation right now what most of the world does what most of
The technological space and
Offering to the market do is assume
We're all the same
Wow
I just learned a lot and
Now I have a sense of
Both house
How hard it is
To develop
Reactive responsive hearing aids responsive
I don't even know what we should call this we probably shouldn't call it Heroes what do you think
I am happier with hearables in hearing aids for sure I'd like to say
It's all about him
We can
Have assistance
Enhancement
We can
Delivery information out
Meaning understand our bodies and have a device that helps us
Connect to our environment to make us more effective but it's how we bring information into in an effective way that it actually helps us
Make our lives more augmented and enhanced
Awesome alright
When can I expect to see things like that are this cool
Some of them are already coming out there
I think there's
Awesome thank you so much Poppy
Thank you Stacey that's it for this week thanks so much for listening to remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week