Hey everyone it's time for The Internet of Things podcast this is your
Tell me about the latest and greatest
News
Well we're just going to stick to things
Yeah there's a lot to talk about
To Ara
Yeah this the first podcast we've done
Together like in the same room
We just want to see us like 3 or 4 years ago
Yes it's weird
Because I just
So we actually realize that we've almost been
I don't know what anniversary that is
The diamond anniversary
The transistor
All right
Joanna Salinas
Astoria CVS
Is my
Goodness Amazon
Madam
Purses
Franklin
All the other boys
News about voice assistant
Alibaba's as well so we're going to talk about Bixby in a few minutes as well
Bixby
Didn't go to the Samsung
We're also going to talk about
Rihanna
Smart bathroom
New chips for Z-Wave
And losses
We also have
The CEO of arm Simon segars
On the show he's going to be talking
To us about
Future of iot and Spectre meltdown so you're going to
How will your phone's going to work
We got a message from Lux products and
Now we'll go to message from
Another one of our sponsor
This week sponsor is CBT Nuggets
How does the IRT change the way we do business for many organizations that have devices in tools
Does devices require support request for the ITT or a pile of devices that
Start being used to their full potential
Phones tablets excetera support request for it
Choice for iot Professionals for decades and now they're making the same high quality
Find training
Earnest
Go to CBT Nuggets. To find out more about how any training can help your team
Connected to the eye of me
All right
We're going to catch kevin mitchell
Let's talk about that
This point is the question because I'm seeing
Google and Amazon voice Services being put into anything and everything
New devices
Partners
Google is here
Every billboard
Monorails that had a nice display over at
NC is much Amazon
I seen Amazon's obviously they also have
They had a giant
To display we like
Gumball machine
Upstream
Having a game with people using Google Assistant
Show
Just make sure that they're in the conversation
House Outdoors at Las Vegas
Shut down
So what we seeing
Matinee is going to be in
The exciting for anybody
I would actually
Garmin is also showing awesome
Prada Supreme
Add on straight into the car
I would still like it
It seems like a lot of
Voice Services position as Solutions
Car manufacturer example
Just an all-in-one solution
Which of the Samsung company
Shut off their vision and
It wasn't you the voices
You just messing
Alright let's talk about Bixby
Because I mean other than I should say we talked
People
In one of the things I found really interesting
That the retail channel so the Best Buy's of the world are actually asking smart
Homemakers
Adwerx
Shelf space that way
And so if you don't have that
They're kind of like
Which I thought was pretty
Not smart because
Consumers are in the Best Buy in LA
System test taking time away from something else that person
EXO
Packaging that explains all this
Yes and
It's basically ended the standard
Forever
Nobody cares if it works with Madam
So like we said
Seaford over all of that underlines
We're done with that you guys
Is a lot more work for
Honeywell integrating with whirlpool
And getting these like silly features
Custom integration
Tens device by device
They're everywhere
Talk about Samsung
You and I were at the Samsung president
3 years ago
Laughing a lot
It was precy at 3 Oliver coyote craziness it was right after the Bots
And oh my gosh
Everything
Work together
Do you remember what it was
Did you hear anything
Mention
In the Press event
And I would say
35 minute timer
Very different
For us and our listeners
SmartThings
Bixby
So it seems to me and I have not been able to
Samsung
And you know what good for them for realizing it when they have
Netflix.
Stihl brand
And that's what it was
They are
Coming out with things on their watches
Which I think is
Great for them and make it award
They probably will because
Message. And other people
Washers that still work
I would expect them to you as well my take on it is
If it works with smart
Things today
It still will work on forward
I don't think they're going to
Limit.
Underlying
Federer
Did not know it was another thing I was waiting for them to
But that's good
As consumers don't care about that you know
Everett tweakers
I just want to
You think together
And that was really promising to hear
I mentioned Bixby in the car that has Harmon showing of 13
Autonomous cars
Disable Bixby
Drive me to 7 South
Their clients as well they showed their start fresh again
Expedient
It would recognize two different people voices together different morning briefing
Stop that we have with others
Nice to see them
War
Because I'm a
Industrial iot
Memes
You guys are like what
These are basically like analog
The Internet of Things
So they had
Really low
Power accelerometer
But this guy
Microwatts
Which is so small
Tracking
Instead of using magnets
So you start
See you later
It's not just what the sensor measures but also like
Inference
Really. So I'm excited to see what people might
That's the other thing that I thought it was
Wicked cool
Was they have a memes
What is
Zoom in and out with a projector HD
How to do it
And it's small enough
Millimeter
Fit inside like an Amazon Echo
Semiconductor
Because they
Chauffeur
New display
Especially when
Z-Wave
Z-Wave ships out there I should talk to
They offer
Your battery life
Z-Wave sensor
So awesome
Used
You can color better managers sleep basic
So those are coming out
Andrea
Crazy low-power in r
And speaking of Z
Which I really like that does like my WeMo Insight switch to your energy
We also have a USB
Something else
So I don't have to go by the
Not only that but
Energy
Drawn that us
Sbarro
It got me thinking about
Use cases for
Devices
But when
You turn on your
Bedroom light in the morning if your lamp
Waking up before the sun comes up
Power draw that's now being modern
Good morning
I never thought of using power fluctuation as
Everything in my
They don't like using voice that's fine
I do I do
His voice is not the right contacts at 1
Good morning
I know she's not a new
Probably going to be tomorrow
Jester
Describe that a little bit better so what is the fibaro gesture thing Hill
I forget the exact it looks like a small
Picture frame
Just Chester like the other four stroke oil it uses
Some kind of radio waves and by using your hand
And that's how it knows what the gesture is I think is about 6 different chest
Swipe the magic
Albus White
Because that
Situation
Whatever is going to sleep you know I tell that I made a gym
I can just
Wave my hand over this thing one way and dim the lights
I can
It is also
Howard or white
Because that leads into where I might actually put it
I may I have a little
This actually works to wake up to an inch of almost any
I just literally wave my hand one of six different ways over my little table and
I need to get out of the voices for everything
Because it is
Exactly and that's why I took
Coveted
The challenge
Doesn't work
Call hubs
Right we did chat about that
If you're going to use for bar prices
Probably better off
With a SmartThings Hub
USB device anyway
Which has three different options
Shoes that just came out
D-box
Sbarro
In your house
I think Evans
Check this out homework for Kevin it's been awhile it's been awhile
All right
Hbase is
Skybell is
Ring for patent
Frenchman on video doorbell
I feel like this year 2018 is going to be
We all need to get to
What year
You're probably a start sooner
Scribe
So this is
Not surprising
First loss
They're suing them over their security system
Stole some ideas from them
Tired vazzana
This actually reminds me of the Apple Samsung lawsuit
You know I
Let's be honest
Anybody here
As I look at this from
Video doorbell as
Scott
Chicano speaker wiring
Speaker
I just hate to see this
I'm with you
Okay
Look at you
Text more in this market
PetSmart
Bathroom
This is an extension of the smart kitchen so
One of the coolest things
Is a
Delta faucet Kohler also excuse the feature to
And
Jackson talks to matamata
Cast metal
Turn on my faucet which
Could be handy but it's probably not that great
You can also tell if
Feel something up
2 cups of water in it and it'll just dispense that
Stun
To fill up so like I have a big spaghetti pot
Spaghetti pie
Oh my spaghetti pie
That will happen
So this
Is awesome I'm sorry you guys
Is super awesome
Because these are like
Intelligence
Remote connectivity
So color also
Makeup mirror with a
Feel like shower something
The smart bathroom which I'm not actually sure I'm ready
Ready or not
Let's
A listener question
On the Internet of Things
Podcast
Podcast listener
Schlage
Maker of electronic locks
Schlage electronic locks off
On their own
Right out of the box so you don't have to have a smart home
See what's possible visit schlage.com
If you have a question for us
Give us a call
6 to 3
7 4
Hey iot podcast
So I have a question
Actually the market to buy my first home and finally stopped print
And I was wondering what
Kind of iot solutions should I be looking at
Kind of an iot Lube right now
Basically I'm just still into the
Anime
Some with
Echo that I was gifted and
29 Echo dot Black Friday deal
Other than that I'm not really interested
I was wondering
Where should I start looking and start doing my research
Two iot of Phi my house
Also
My real estate agent got me thinking when he was talking about one of his former clients
That had moisture sensors in the bathroom
So when the Marshall ever got
Hi it would automatically turn on the vent
I was wondering
Are there sensors that
Can determine
Almost like a
The stinkiness level ntaganda fan to vent out the smell
Just wondering
Love the podcast
Okay Kyle that wasn't a different direction that I thought I was ready for like hey I've got an anime in what do I buy it
Interesting use case
Smarter we always suggest starting with e
Please case
A couple different ways
And we can partially stop it
Another way
Right there are
There are bathroom fans that has built-in sensors
Running until
Humidity level drops
That's a non-smart
Doesn't communicate with anything other than
I'm going so you could do that
Home Depot
I thought we put it in
Probably want to get a switch
Wifi switch would probably
Just Finance
Tp-link make slime soda
Spine
And
Like there's plenty of humidity sensors
As far as smell sensors that's a little tricky
Yes so
Kevin and I had a lively debate over
What makes a bath
Consensus appears to be
Hydrogen sulfide
And I was thinking about you as well
No no
You know I was talking
Actually someone from
And they actually had in a where
AWA
Sensor
Next to their cat litter box
They would trigger an apple
Turn on the smart outlet
The concepts are similar shows some sense
We just Alaska measure vocs
I don't know if hydrogen sulfide is a Voca
You can buy a Hydra
Gas sniffer for like
Internet status
It doesn't feel like something
Be excited about
If you guys
Anyconnect
Nobody advertisers
This particular
Teacher
Market
Worst case scenario
Smart Switch
Could always do
Do something where
Seether Set It Off
With a motion detection
Stop
Determine what that time is that
Or
$30 bottle of
Which is
Recommendation this is a little
Into the toilet
Chris is oil film on top
Trade It
Actually
There is a
Really big
So if you didn't want to connect
Lowe's for your
Humidity sensing fan
Your grocery checkout aisle
A little vial of free
As far as other things for a new house and just getting started I think
You don't have to do more switches unless you want to
In a thermostat
Should you get certain thermostats Plus
Caesar detected in your home
So
Birds with one
All right
Tocayo
Thanks for calling
And again
7 4
And now
Conversation
Simon segars
The CEO of arm
Hey everyone we're taking a break from this week's iot podcast from our sponsor this week
Lux products we have robbed
Here to talk about thermostat
And how it works in the smartphone
So Rob
Can you tell her
A little bit
We are a
Proud bunch of philadelphia-based innovators of
HVAC
Controls
We've been around for over a hundred years
Our most recent launch
The Lux Kono smart thermostat is a product chock-full of
Smart features it has
At the core element with Decor snap cover so it can match
Any environment and it works with all the voice assist
Which is a pretty competitive price
Animation was a big deal at CES this year
Bunch of devices we're still focused on
A big thing was everything that had to work with one another
How did you guys attack
We stay in the channel that were in
Sandwiches
HVAC
And so we know that we have to be able to come
Communicate
With all the major voice
Assistance
Because we view that as the
The glue of the Smart Home
So
Coming out of the gate we have the big three
Google Apple and Amazon
We work seamlessly with those so we can be part of each of those ecosystem
And right now you guys offer three generations of Kinect
Two products
How do each of those fit
Within the home automation
That's a great question
We started our
Smart thermostats with the Lux Geo in 2015
And it's feature is that it is
Battery operated Wi-Fi products
So it works off of
2 lithium
Double a batteries or of course with the famous C wire and
Parnu power Bridge
Which makes it have connectivity forever and ever
Second generation was more of a pro product
We called the g o x
And that has
Superior humidification
Control
And of course the most recent
Our third generation is
Dacono smart and
We've just launched the
Kono
Smart zigbee version which weave Julie named
Konigsee
Excellent
Having all of this experience what are some things that you think manufacturers need to
To remember
Moon embracing the Sun
What are the things that we differentiate on
For the Hub basis
I'm with or zigbee product is that we
Are a thermostat company
May 1st
So when we designed or zigbee product for the hubs we made sure that you happen to lose connectivity to the hub
You're still going to have your thermostat working on a schedule keeping the house comfortable and even if you had
Two for those devices
You can put a schedule in at the wall on the device which is something that other people that are in the smart products
Business first
Thermostat 2nd don't think about we've been through this a lot for the past 30 years we have over 15 million
Thermostats on the wall we know exactly what to do.
Keep the home com
Alright Rob that sounds great
Where can we go to find out
What we'd love to have everyone come to Lux
Products.com there's plenty to read there and if you want to learn more about the Kono smart thermostat you can stop by your
Local Home Depot store or shop online
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Who is the CEO of
Our assignment how are you doing today
I'm so excited and as you guys all know
I love semiconductors
I love Arm
It'll make semiconductors they just make the brains the instruction set and then the license about every
So in my brain
Simon knows everything that's going to happen
For the next 5 years
I like to think that's the way we was way we develop a technology that way we were upon us
Us to have some insight of where at least of all the processing you've got
Can you snort see devices
CSG seeing exactly what everybody else with the technology
You think about the supply chain with rain
Developing processes and everything else people used to build chips we license them to chip companies they design those into
Play put the rain stop around it
He's on it into an end product eventually get ships that is a really long time gap between
Ostomy. Especially in the very early days of new technologies and it ending up in a real Pro
You make it sound like a takes a long time but it's actually gotten a lot shorter so
Point in time that you guys start designing a chip for your
Oh my gosh I think we need voice recognition
How long do those
Jimmy Walker audience may not be
This process through house
If we are
Thinking about
New architectural features then that's fine from
First thing about what we might need two products shipping in a store that you can actually go by
Could be Chinese
Play Somebody architectural features that all shipping now in smartphones by small V8 technology
Another word come that happens
Probably 10 years ago
So in some places
Light radiates how long time
Thinking about maybe it's Origins on top of that specific
Processes
4 different Performance Point
Applications
If that can be for male product concept 2
A ship
Products can be anything from to use to
4 years
It is you guys must be really smart
Having to take about this stuff
Let's think about
You and I first met
ORD a half years ago when
Chicago CEO job
When I asked you what you were excited about what you're going to do next week
Internet servers and you didn't really give me much more than that so
Looking back on that now
Do you recognize that is like a transition
. what did
You guys where do you guys see our
I see what you look like that.
And if you took to anyone in this kind of semiconductor industry
Huge amount of semen
Comes in
Huge amount of R&D huge amount of economic value
The growth rates for mobile was going to slow down
Everyone was thinking about snakes
And it really wasn't clear and
Yeah I talked to a lot of CGI was in this industry
Franklin
Now United
That the
Technologies of iot
The price is incapabilities Academy nivel artificial intelligence
These are
Cherokee building blocks that can get deployed in Lutsen
Different wines weather
Self-driving cars
Recognizing your voice and ordering
Pizza for you or making the lights in the room go off a few
Workout
So I've learned looking
Had this idea that these Technologies would going to be useful
We starting to see the first deployments of them in
Real products
I think we just going to Seymour MO
So some of the features that
We talked about
I don't know if this has Hardware implications for you guys
Voice
Computer vision
Which I feel is still kind of early
Machine learning at the edge
What else is there
There's some communication
Everything is low power
Hear what we're trying to do is cry Wolfe Ali I'd like to either and when you went to Gracie that was really well together a suspicion is that
Energy efficient
Teen memory in the Danbury Mall pal
Black people forget together
Integrated technology
Is Seattle a few years we've seen things like voice
Things like visions.
Yum yum application
Want to use because it said
Cancel them
There are new features that we need to develop you look at the algorithms using to to machine
Learning processes
Run them prices for the Run even more efficiently and other types of
Accelerator new starting to CP
Boston Market
People using gpus Bigler developing a custom acceleracers
This whole Space is very alive at the moment because he's
You the hours of the changing the oven
Being developed
And I think you know
Cigarette another phone off use time
Yeah you look at all of these Technologies
We producing
It will be addressing in a little
Okay it was me
Just a moment ago
You guys are recent just by SoftBank
And massage
Has this big vision for a trillion connected devices everywhere
You doing
Vision board
What Master is doing with the SoftBank group is creating a an ecosystem
Square
Really want to lose them all together is Taissa
Investments that they making their businesses which can use data to glean insights for the Racine
How people use Office Space how people
Omega rounds
Status is going to be guided by
Iot devices is going to be
Leaves across the network
Process
Some of that in the age of Summer
The Clown
The network
Who was that relies on
Efficient energy efficient semi.
What's devices
I'm weak right in the building box for that
So you only view what we doing now is really at the house
Hope everything Master is trying to achieve cuz he's all that data
Capturing it moving it
Using it process again getting the inside from it
In that kind of vein of data
Machine learning
Specifically
I'm super excited about this cuz it's been awhile since there's been a lot of chips
He's running around
There are several of those is that something you guys might look
Acquisition
Is snow something out have a rule out there a little C
Chip companies are getting building
Pictures
Pakistan
We're Young once we have activities
Ian Axel starting point is more th
Machine learning algorithms applied in
It's devices in this microphone
In it devices
Lots and lots of a processing he's going to start
And we see that was a huge
Where dementia security
And specifically
Everybody's big panic
Spectre & meltdown
Initially arm-based processors
We're not
But now it turns out they are
So can you talk to us about what you guys are
So when the this particular type of responsibility cup discovered a bunch of research is over Google
They contacted us then I contacted Intel and AMD
Because
Any processor
That uses advanced phone to speculations
High performance
He's potentially
In this way what we did was going to analyze our products
Because she is typos
Attack
Is brand new
And it really is
Very sophisticated very calm
Flex and utilizes features which nobody could ever
Utica security
So we spent on analyzing that was ever a time when
Affected over there they all because it when this news broke
Yeah we were very much out
Public very rapidly
With ears are analysis and situations of the Saints of all communication with our partners about
Which products are affected with y'all and we've been probably taken out streaming issues and fixes that are required and working Pro
You guys are in a little bit of the unique spot because
Licensing a
The check to somebody else who sells
In products
How do you insurance
Asbury Broadway
How do you ensure that
What year did
To solve the
You're it
All the way up
It controls you say we're in a supply chain away quite a long way down it but
Web developer roles
The architectures developer
Princesses
Using
We spent a lot of time thinking about the subway that's going to run on
Even if we don't end up shipping
So we do a little work in open source
Kali Linux kernel
I'm subbing this issue particularly we spend time making sure they will pass useful Linux
Are we would sleep on his online
We make sure that was available week
EOS fenders
To understand how these Thunder abilities do pertain to
Kohl's in
So you really refuse all relationships up and down the street to
Try and get everybody doing the right thing and being ready for the day when this take their life
So is my phone going to run slower
Since
That really does remind to be seen but one thing I would advise you to do absolutely is
When the path gets pushed to you download it and install it
The only thing I say is
What is security issue like
Oh my soul
Can I get exploit III malware on your device sorry if ever there was a time to be worried about your no kind of that Dodie website
Accepting my email that doesn't quite look right now is the time to
Really really be
Aware of that
The boss in the first place
So yeah I do the software patches and continue to practice Can I have
Safe cyber security
Good hygiene okay
Spectrum
Actually
Was it just like it was
Thought about
How do we try to
About security
And then also implements
Going forward as we
More and more really important stuff
Yeah they wanted
Really important
Concept
Head around is the insecurity isn't
Are you saying
That you saw
They have social security forever because people will find you why he's all second
Writing systems
Spectre meltdown
I said I all abusing
Take me to the pin used in micro processes for decades
And what everybody considered
Asakusa
Hawaii
You do speculation
If it turns out you should have done it saying
No 6 States
In the process of
What turns out they're awesome side effects
Texan eye side effects
Explosive
What's it all for 27 years. A lot of people with a lot of experience in my compressor is on everywhere and I was looked at this has just been
This technique
To get exploited
There are going to be more things like that
Insecurities an ever-moving
And as we move toward us billions of connected devices
Benny
Gazillions of art things
New ways to attack
That will come about
So we have to consider that security
Lewes Ferry on the lookout
Elsa shoes
We going to have ways to fix issue
The come up
Redis Spectre meltdown
Fixing to haul away
Many many Display Devices yet ready is announced
Fortunately you don't need to because the software mitigations do work and I all the right way of approaching other selling a tissue
In a world of iot
Are many things you can buy to die OTC things
Connected devices for your house
Don't have any way to have to suffer
It is good. Most Computing devices that are
Spectrum
Call Ricky end of an operating system
I see devices logged in many devices
I have a run is in it when it leaves the factory
New software
That might be okay but I think
Actually the word loyalty is going.
That's those devices can be managed
And of the software can change of the lights
The securities
Depressing
Depend on something a little bit more cheerful
Let's talk about we are here at CES
I know you haven't traveled the show floor possibly as much but
What are you looking for what
The most excited about your head for technology
Every year
Is just extra
Check on the Rapture of how old is technology is used in put into
Cole consumer products
And we spend our lives going to be in the transistors thinking about
Chinese down the road
How much compute performance you can be needed in
Seems generally
When I come to see yes I see how people actually use them
I put them in
Ayala glossies or
Drones for the weather this week that the demo of a
What time is TC to drive out there
Zerorez technology
Presets UC
Jesse's mom's every year
And every year she was like a race of his own son is fosta
And that's because the cost of accessing the technology goes down and down and down and mow people can experiment with it
And you just get more Innovations results
Awesome thank you Simon
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter
Stacey on iot cam will see you next week