Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higgins
Mathematics is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And I'm going to let you know that
Today Show is going to be packed full of exciting news and also some Home Improvement
On Kevin side
So
Not really
Smart Home Improvement although I do have a new Z-Wave lock on my front door replacing the front door as we speak right now
Rotted wood frames and whatnot but
Yeah
Sorry
So there may be a little background noise but
Bear with us because Kevin
All right
So here we go
Today we're going to talk about
Samsung's new
Voice assistant
We're going to talk about
I missed it by Google's voice assistant on the home
Tell me about the news about the Amazon Echo
And
Then we're moving out of the assistant territory we're going to talk about what happens to Zona
A company that was bought
It wasn't but we'll talk about it
And arm has some news they bought an NB iot company and they introduced a new architecture
So whoop whoop
And finally
Will end it with some SmartThings news
Because
All right
This week we have
An awesome sponsor in Samsung artik
We also have
Vint Cerf is Our Guest
Who
And I'm not saying that just be
Google Play
Yeah I kind of don't know what's causing
You know he's
She's one of the fathers of the internet he's also an evangelist from Google and
He's the architect of the Matrix
There we go
That's what we'll
Alright so
Before you get to him
You got to go through us so let's get this show started with a message from this week sponsor
This week sponsor is Wolf SSL
The world's top five Industrial Automation companies
Floor devices to their power meters and they are not alone will pass Adele secures 2 billion connections across the
The multitude of iot sectors including Automotive connected home industrial military and medical devices
The Mirai botnet the growing threat of ransomware attacks on the Internet of Things companies have to pay attention to secure
Charity warpas litigation bad PR and their brand value securing the iot is hard but
What does a cell has experience in specialized expertise to help
Visit wolf ssl.com
Okay
She'll get it started with things that talk
Bruce Sterling came on the show a couple weeks back
Did he call these talking
And I kind of like the name he's like
Ghetto his idea was that
They don't do much
I don't know if it was
They're stubborn
He called them talking
Chalky spray really did like the
The phrase
So
I don't know what do you think
I mean there's been a big push for voice assistants obviously since
Say sincere restarted although you feel all the way back to like
Windows
Cee days are pocket PC with Microsoft ad voice actor
Washington Pediatrics
At that time the tech wasn't there for natural language processing
You had to literally record yourself saying a command and then assign
A command to that
Recording
Canal days
Yeah those were the days all right
Yeah but now it's obviously much better because you have natural language processing week.
Siri we've got Google Assistant
You got
Echo devices letters lots of
Voice interface says I keep coming back to it being the invisible interface at something
Works for everybody
Buying large
Now Samsung wants to getting on the game although it's really
That's a second attempt because they already had S-Voice which was their version of a
Your phone assistant but now they've got
Bixby and
Bixby isn't quite what I expected it to be I don't know what you thought
But what did you think are you surprised by what Bixby is
I wasn't actually surprised because Bixby one I really like the name
It makes me think of like some friendly alien or something
Bixby or puppy
But
What it does in kind of reminded me of which was
Created by the guys who actually did Siri
When you talk to the guys who created Viv they were thinking about building this kind of back-end infrastructure to help
Applications talk to each other
So having something that basically it kind of reminded me of Google Assistant
You could that ties things together
Hear your voice
Felt like it made a lot of sense to
Yes
It looks like it will do that it looks like it will also
Kind of
Take over some of the touchscreen interface of gotten used to over the last 10 years so that way
Anything you could do by
Touching a controller button on your phone or an app
Whatever might be
You should theoretically be able to do with Bixby via voice
So there's an interface aspect of it there's also what you would talk about
Which is the
Getting apps to talk to each other which I think developers will actually have to
Kind of an able but I don't have the same technical details yet
But it seems more interface e to me then
AI to me
I supposed
Sational
Contextual
Yeah I think
Meaning of assistant that does things
That or gets information contextual information right time right place
That's what I think of more often with assistant but you could also say assistant will help you interact with an app or apps
And it seems like
It's
Maybe a bit of both but I think more
More the latter
Yes
In that makes sense cuz that was the expertise they bought it wasn't
About like having a conversation in that way I mean
I think Google is
Probably the farthest to head on
The more conversational in assistant
Level stop
But it doesn't have kind of the chops on the
Controlling a variety of
Thanks site
That's her
So Samsung went the other way
We should know something
Casa
Yes
Yes I don't work on the IRT team but I do work as a consultant for Android
Chrome Enterprise type things so yes
So my my opinions are my own
Yes
And you know
He probably won't say anything
Play nasty about
Android Enterprise
Hopefully I won't say anything about it
Non-sequitur
All right so that's Samsung Bixby will find out more because it's next week that they're going to announce the
Air show at the phone
The alleged I said I can neither confirm nor deny
That's correct so Samsung is having an event might be multiple locations I do know that they're having an event in New York
City I think it's the 28th
Might be Wednesday of next week so
Unfortunately will be
Right around the time you record our weekly show so
What that may be put off
Talking about that till the following
Okay
So that's talking donkey number one
Talking donkey number two
Is the Amazon Echo
Now is
Final
And to be honest I mean we've already heard that some phones will have
Echo integration
Built in such as the Huawei maybe the mate
9 May 10th
That was enough CES I don't believe they've implemented that yet and I guess that's a take the place of Google Assistant will give you
Options
But this is actually Amazon itself not a harbor partner Amazon itself saying hey
Replay
Echo smarts into your
Strange thing to me is they put it in the Amazon shopping app
Which makes sense if you want to track orders by voice or order things
But if you want general information like right before the show I used it to get the weather
And it works
Fine
But I had to go to the Amazon shopping app so why not just just have it in the app
That has her name
I have like a dozen Amazon apps on my phone
I have
Let's eat let's try calling or madam
So the day app
I have Amazon Kindle app
Stop the music app
The Now app
I think I have the shop
How is it going
Fastpitch bat actress
Wrong that's just wrong
Okay so I get I see where you're going
I get it
I have multiple Amazon apps as well just put in all the apps they're all going back to the same servers I'm in
You don't make it contextual in that I want to check
Shopping stuff via voice
Okay I'm going to go to the shopping
I want to control Smart
Home things
Voice
Put it into the one that does that
I mean
I want to control music
Through Amazon Prime music
Put it in the app that does
I don't understand why it's all in the shopping app
You seem silly to me
It no I'm with you
It's also very confusing
I don't I can't find it I don't have it so
If you're looking for this
Amazon shopping app which if you like me
Maybe you haven't downloaded it
Go download it so you can talk to
I'm kind of like
Okay
Next up
Google
Google this week actually may have been last week
On the Google home device
Had kind of a
Because it feels pretty intrusive what they did is as part of
People's daily briefing
That you can get that tells you you're like weather traffic
Basically like your
Your morning radio kind of thing
On the Google home
They inserted
An ad for Beauty and the Beast
Yeah the new movie
What's
Really crazy is when someone called them about it cuz somebody posted it on Twitter
Google decided that it wasn't
Correct correct so you're right it was part of the my day feature which kind of summarizes everything for you whenever you ask
And it kind of
It went at the very end it was a
Literally
This is the tech
That was spoken
By the way Disney's live action Beauty and the Beast opens today
And if there's a little bit of information about the movie
I mean
I guess I see but I see both sides are clearly if I'm a user and I do not own a Google home at 4
Echoside that's the route I went for various reasons just better support of the products I use
It's going to sound like a nap without a doubt
Google says was intended to be an ad it was just trying to write some helpful information about your day and
Was kindly content
Yeah I mean
If it's not clear to the users then you got a question the decision to do it I think
Well
Baseline did money change
Don't know so nobody knows
Google has not said
Disney has no
That's it
That's the first question right because the FTC
Even
Even if users
Eventually the FTC would be like
What are you doing
But you
I think the shows a couple thing
Thanks one
It shows that dealing with ads in a voice assisted world
What is going to be
Really hairy
Annoy people
If it's not done well
But if it's done too well I think the FTC is going to be like
Did you really think you were serving
Sponsored
Kind of like they do
Instagram
So there's that there's a very fine line there it needs to be clear to users
Weather as you said you know it's sponsored Penny changed hands basically is this an ad or is this not a nap
Write it needs to be clear to end users
And I will say that there are ways
I am sure you guys don't
The Harry Potter
Fantastic Beasts movie came out
Google actually did and I think it still works
You could say lumos
You can say hey G
Lumos
And your phone flashlight with
Right
That lumos by the
Not Harry Potter
Very clear we don't want people thinking they can actually do this
It's magic
But you can actually do it on your
I thought that was really fun it was clever
And I assumed money changed hands
I mean it felt kind of marks
Nothing but it felt like something a user opted into
Enby
I guess
Mostly they felt like something a user opted into
So I guess
That's the first
You Can Be Clever ads and I think we're going to have to see how that gets
It's done for
This I really think Google needs to think about
Switching from an ad based company
To a product
And I say this
Rather a services
And I say this because
Google's ad Revenue comes from the web
Predominantly
And we're going to stop looking so much at
And when it
Goes into a world where data matters and services matter
I think it should really start to position itself
Not as an ad
Because people don't trust
And you're not saying anything that many analysts haven't said in the past I mean that's
Something that
Not an original
I'm saying that
A lot of people agree
And the fact is as you said a lot of those
Ads come over the web and now
The web
It's bigger than just
Something in a browser
The data from the web is coming through devices
Through
Wearable devices
Home assistant
Connected other bands I mean there's so many more places
That the web is touching
Right
So now it becomes do you want to see ads on all those things
There's a whole mindset that needs to be
Figure it out here
Traditional old ad model
Will not work in a connected to a connected world with
Multiple screens or
Other interfaces such as voice
Yeah and having that data
Has-beens that could provide super super valuable services and
I guess maybe maybe the next step then is how to monetize
Ads for Beauty and the Beast at the end of
My day
Is probably not the
Keep thinking
Okay let's move on
Wouldn't really quick
Purple
We'll try this in audio category
A smart home
That was
Controlled by an Ocarina which is
That weird
How much is a pipe
Hey I guess it's an instrument
Yeah well doesn't this will have to be electronic I mean in in the Zelda games
Electronic butt
Sounds like they have electricity there
No no
So he basically created a smart home that was controlled by
Ocarina
Because he has a huge Legend of Zelda fan
And he basically built
You put a microphone on a Raspberry Pi
How many plays in Ocarina certain
Sound phrases
Trigger certain things.
To happen with Wi-Fi control devices in his house he built all these himself so this is not something
Yeah you're not going to go buy this
But
How fun was that
And
Talk about it interesting parking app
Opportunity that actually what we're saying
What's Google +
Opportunities to tie into
Movies in
And products
With
Baby smart things at different commands and remember how when I got back from Harry Potter world and I was so sad that I could
Can use my wand
Okay I was going to bring that up because they're to go there's a perfect do it yourself just pointed at certain smart
Home devices and have him go on and go off the lawn to know you could do that
I can't because it's the one has
It's not NFC
I think it's a
I already
I think it's
But it's proprietor
Cannabis
So so think about that marketing
There might be some fun to be had there
Alright let's talk about arm
Because there were two things
What has more relation to the iot than others
So last month arm acquired two companies that provide NBA
Technology
For those of you guys are like
Is one of the low-power wide area network
Works so basically you can send small signals small amounts of data
Over
Huge areas
Cool thing about NB iot is that it cellular
So the cellular companies are looking at this in AT&T Verizon orange it said
Everybody's looking at this to provide like
Put your sensors in your smoke detectors talk to the cellular
But it's cheaper
Your mentioning cellular have they changed the name of nb-iot 2
How to say LTE
Andy one
Oh so there's two
Two versions
Of course they're Hispanic
And then herself
Cat 1
Okay
Nb-iot
Is the download speeds are 250 km per sec
I'm in Uplink is
Also too
Until it's y'all
Very very
Very small like it'll tell your device state or something like that I mean if they were talking small bits of information
It's on us
It really love how
An LTE cat M1
Is
1 megabit per second
So that's
It's not video but maybe it's something a little bit more steady state
BiggerPockets
More price
Little bit different they're both incredibly low power both designed to go over wide areas
Both going to be implement
Bike carriers
And we're still waiting for pricing form
AT&T and Verizon
For both of these
Scratch
Set alarm purchased two companies then
Two companies
They are
Next
G
Cam
They do
NBA
Coyote
Software
And
Missed base
Which does the actual chip
The physical layer so
The lowest part in the stack
What does the radio stuff
Together these two basically give arm
The ability to design in NB iot
This matters
Because
There's also a bunch of other stand standards out there in the low-power wide area network
World which like Laura
We talked about all the time on the show
There's things like sick Fox
And there's other
Proprietary things like ingenue
I think wait list is still floating around out there
The idea here is
Nb-iot that the back of the cellular carriers if they come up with a business model it looks like arm is like yeah we're going to support that
I was just going to say me nothing against the
Competing standards and product makers but
Arm already has such a big
Footprint in the mobile industry's got the backing of practically everybody
If anybody can push towards
Fewer standards I would think it would be an arm
You know there's other
Big news
But I think it's fake
What time it is
Dynamic
And that's like
Got super
The last IQ
The last
Yeah the last two letters
Know the last two letters of the word dynamic and they're brand new
IQ
And there
Basically they're saying it's Works painting possibilities for artificial intelligence
Tell me why you think this is a big deal maybe you'll convince me
Okay so
What they done here is arm has actually changed its architecture
So
They have
Redesigned the way they're going to make their
Cortex a core
These are their bigger fatter meteor
Chords for smartphones for performance
Not the M class which is what
Shut all that stuff aside
Sha
So what they done
When is
The architecture they chosen is going to let you run eight different
Horse in a cluster
That are all going to be able to run at 2
Clock speed so different frequency
So you can have one that's like
Super high-power like 1.2 gigahertz going
Chugging full out then you can have one you know what 500 gigahertz that's like
Only waking up till late
Listen for a voice
Anderson
Alright so I'm gonna stop you there and ask a question
To me it does not seem very different from their
Big little architecture and they already had
Multiple corre processes running at different speeds
So big little was introduced in
2011 that was there last
Forehead what that does is
Impaired
A big core
Like the massive
Powerful one with a
Metalcore
Less powerful
The big core wood handle like mobile phones and stuff like that
So the difference here is in this feels very slight
Is
With big little you had one that was on or off
And the other
It was on or off but you couldn't choose like different frequencies for
Taken throttle them based on the performance load required
And also you can only put four of them in
And
You can individualize
Every single one
So do you guys have all
A little
So
I think the the cores in the cortex is now.
Throttle
Based on performance load
I could be wrong
I'll give you some more
Cuz now we're getting home
So are you didn't actually give a whole lot of technical
We're going to see that later when they actually introduce a new cortex design
With this Ark
Temperature later this year
They also did two more things
Mentioning
Changed it so
The bus now works
An accelerator
Much faster
And they also added some
And this is real nebulous are like some resiliency thing so it works for automotive in robotics
And I don't know if you remember they actually introduced a core
Last year
A core I think was a 57 or they 53
That was more resilient in design for these kind of industrial
Situation
But they're also changing the instruction set
And this gets into the AI stuff they're adding some instructions to the instruction set to make it work better for
Intelligence
That is the final amount of excretion
This was more of a press release in a product launch sandwich
It's fine I had no issue with that
They just seems very evolutionary to me in that
As we said big little architecture which was a big step forward
Back in 2011 this just seems like
Again maybe a half step forward on that
Andrea Lee
It's yes there are new instruction sets that will help with a I I don't know what those instructions will be in and what they will bring us
Sweet we'll see
I mean it's almost like we're taking our old architecture to adjust a little bit and say Nathan is Rai
I'm just not I guess I'll wait and see
What Hardware
Manufacturers do with this
Just to see how much of a big deal is really is but it again it seems very evolutionary to me
This will end up more in phones
It does feel kind of Apple
I can see why you think that
I think we'll see it first in phones
Because you can actually dedicate a lot of tasks to specific
Processors in a way that
I think would be compelling
The other thing it'll be good for is
Networking
On the other networking site cuz you could really amp up your
Networking in because you're dealing with so much for so many more flows of information
We're going to see
The accelerator side of that also come
That is the arm
Wait and see
Text hubby and we'll move on from the deeply nerdy to the
Deeply sad
All right
Last week
I broke a story
I'm Zana which is the company that
Does software integration for lots of other companies
Including the Staples connect home that is now the phone
The song FeFe Tacoma home
Automation stuff
Several Lake
Common products
So
Zana
I had heard that they've been for sale
For a little while and
Basically at a deal had fallen through Honeywell was one of the potential requires that they were in talks with and and that
That did not happen
But
After a deal to buy them fell through
Ring the maker of a connected doorbell basically said
Will extend everyone who works it's on us
And most everybody is on olfaction
Kittens on us former CEO Mike Harris
Has confirmed to me that he is now a
Head of the
Ring Philadelphia office
Which
Now exist
Enough was in my backyard in Malvern if I recall correctly
Pennsylvania
Oh so is that where the ring Philadelphia office is at sitsa Philadelphia suburb that's why
It just
Exist
There might
Presumably right now
For the 80
Or so the 70 to 80s on us employees that are now
Every
So really interesting story
Really cool that ring came in and offer these people jobs and really cool that they all wanted to stay together and take it
Because you know
People who understand device integration which is what saint of does
It's actually a pretty valuable skill right now
They could have found jobs elsewhere
And so this feels like
Good news for ring
And
The people who used to work at sauna
My big question is
What happened
Tazanna which is what I don't know
I feel like
There still an asset out there they still have products like sawed-off was
Still supporting all of the people who still have Staples connect devices
No one comes on off no one from its investors
Has called me
Dark rather I called them and they haven't returned any of my calls
I don't actually know what happens to those customers that
ReliOn sign up support
That's a good question and as the mean as you alluded to the Staples home connectors got into Funk so in those people
Already in the Lurch I don't know what's really going on there
Indiana will they continue to do that that's going to be up to ring I suppose
I know it'll be up to Zana
Ring only hired
So who's left the question to actually make those decisions
Xander support these things
So everyone
Asana
Got a job
So who's left at Solana
What's left is that of might be the right question
Now not everybody took
Looks like everybody
The people who didn't aren't working at Sonic
I've been trolling Pacer to find out if there has been a bankruptcy
So we'll see
That is an open question if any of you guys want to tell us what's happening feel free to
To drop us a line Casino
I used to love the Staples today
I thought it was the best home hub out there
For a really long time
Because
It was user-friendly
It had a lot of Integrations
Interesting
I like the display because the display showing all the products that Staples actually had put together through TV is on off
Because it showed people how these things interact in a very simple to understand way
So there's that
Finally
Two bits of things for smart
If you guys have gone in your SmartThings app lately
Or if you're a new buyer
Perhaps
Discovery now is amazing
It just goes through your house
Echo Steakhouse
It goes on your Wi-Fi not working it basically Auto discovers anything on your Wi-Fi network
Which for me was a lot of stuff
Including my Sonos is
Or is it so nice
So it discovered all of that
It discovered
A bunch of stuff it was really nice
So
Discovery is way better at it that's a brand new
And
I finally got my SmartThings and Lutron Thing 2
Work and I have to tell you
That
I apparently was the only one who had
Problems
And it was not because of SmartThings it was because
I had a ghost Lutron hub
On my network
I know
Solutran benezra like why do you have two Bridges I was like I don't have to
A Darkness you do
Here's what I think happened
It's because
I actually discovered that I have a phantom will call it a phantom Logitech Harmony Hub
I'm a phantom Nest Thermostat
So I was like as I discovered all of these weird Phantom things in my accounts
I thought it might have to do with the fact that I took my Wi-Fi network
Offline
And
To test some new Wi-Fi networks in
Then I brought it back on
And so I'm wondering if
That process created
Alternative
Bridges
I have no idea how all these came about
The companies themselves.
How old is
So this this emphasizes how weird my house
Now that I've tried to smart thing
I can tell you that it is awesome
It is a cloud the cloud
Integration and I was actually really worried about that
I don't know what magic
Blackmagic Lutron and SmartThings have done but
There is not
Noticeable
Latency
In commanding
My stuff
From the app
Through Google home
And through the Amazon Echo
All of those work
Seemingly at the same speed maybe a millisecond slower
But not so you
Interesting that you mention latency because I didn't
Say I was going to do some of that show but I did do this between the last showing out I
Got a wink Hub 2
And I noticed much less latency which is very good
Nope Anthem devices rounds afraid that when I transfer all my stuff from the one to the other
Create issues
Oh yeah that way
So what are you going to do with your old wink
Cuz I have a wink 1 and I don't know what
I have a teammate out in Mountain View who wants to know
Smarthomes I'm like hell just send you a link
Send somebody awake
Go for it
I have a spare wink hub
Okay we're going to do this for a week
Send me an email at info at ioc podcast.com
And
I got a bunch
I will do a random generator or I will randomly pick one of y'all and you can have my old
This is Wings version one hub
So if you want it
Send me an email
And will
Do it before the next show so
Actually let's say
Before the end of the day on
Monday night
Which is March
And then
U2
Could have a wink one
That feels good
Let's do the guest
Kevin thank you
Everyone else
Stay tuned for Vint Cerf talking about what the problems are with
The Internet of Things
And how he thinks that's going to work out
But first a message from our sponsor
Everyone we are taking a break for The Internet of Things podcast
For a message from our sponsor this week sponsors Samsung art
And I have syrupy chair
Samsung
What Samsung is doing
Hi Sarah ICC I'm so glad you're here today so can you tell me what Samsung
In the industrial internet let me start by saying that Samsung is a very large manufacturer
Connected products today a lot of people know Samsung through the mobile phone to tablet
Wearables and many more connected products
Samsung video
Chasing and understanding a lot of the challenges that other manufacturers have
Trying to improve off by guillotine for json downtime
And deliver reading high quality connect
Json pretty demanding customers
Samsung manufacturer
And with all Arctic iot platform we're helping
Manufacturers like Samsung to get better
Insights into that productivity
Boca helping industrial OEM
To deliver connected products
And connected services
Awesome see you
Perspective what is the future of manufacturing
Countries already created
Massive quantities of data so that's not something that's new I think the s*** that we going to see is more in the usage
All that data
Pink shed more effectively between applications
Beautiful and also shared with other parties to have outside
The factory
Medieval efficiencies that haven't been delivered yet and also we going to see that day to being shown or delay
David down to the machines or to the people
Really need it and they're going to be getting that dates of when they need it most
So what are some common mistakes that you see people making is they try to add intelligence to their face
I think one challenge
Industrial iot implementation to security it's always a big concern or industrial customers
And it's important to design that security in from the outfit
Rather than added in as an afterthought
Security is a big issue
Also a graphic shifts that make automation
Manufacturing
In the manufacturing and production for teaching in the US says there a lot of very highly skilled and experienced workers who going to
I'll be retiring this problem
Patisserie challenging for petroleum Engineers of the utility worker
Big fraction
What does what forces are going to be retiring
In the next 5 years
And with that big of a cold
Great shift change
We potentially going to lose a lawsuit
Intelligence and knowledge
Expertise in industrial processes so we need to find ways of capturing this expertise
And one way to approach it is to
Collect more data and analyze that data more effectively to try and codify some of this knowledge
To find out more about Samsung
Arctic
And how it can help your iot development strategy
Go2www
Arctic
Dot IO
Slash build or buy
That's
Arctic AR
Tik
Dot IO / build or buy
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacy Higgins
Bottom and today I have with me Vint Cerf want to be
What is called the father of the internet
One of the fathers of the internet here with me
So - are you doing
Well right now I'm absorbing Austin reign
Unexpectedly
It always rains during South by at least one day before it turns beautiful again
That case I don't feel like anybody dumped on me but it's a pleasure to chat with you today
It is wonderful to talk to you I'm really excited
So
Let's just get it started with
How do you define The Internet of Things
I think that the most Broad
Is generalization would be anything that's programmable
And perhaps something with
Also has communication capability
This extends well beyond the classic sorts of appliances around the house and around the office
Sir in the car or on your person
I even think of
Fast training systems on the stock exchange is it kind of Internet of things as piece of software that takes real-world input
Juice it up for a while and then does something which has a real-world effect
So I'm very general notion of communicating software that that takes in real-world information in
Has an effect on the real world
For most people whoever is a device
Programmable
All right
And
Why would you say that this is a big deal
Right now forever
But perhaps the biggest deal about the Internet of Things
Is that our people are rushing to build
Products
They have these
Characteristics Communication in computation
Kobe mentality
The trouble is you're not paying as much attention to access control security privacy safe
And frankly autonomy by which I mean
Ability to operate successfully even if the Internet isn't available that what you don't want is your house doesn't work at
The Internet isn't connected
That would not be a good design
But already have
Sense to me on a daily basis with my internet
Flips out
So
What's actually skip to architecture
What kind of underlying technology
Do you think we need to
To think about
I guess scaling out this distributed
Intelligent Network
Well first of all there has been and I would say
Anna parents
Common
Choice to use the Internet Protocol is
Circle fundamental
Mechanism for moving database
Back and forth
IP version 6
Is preferable because it is
Scam
But the underlying transmission systems could vary all over the rod and they do to slow pan
Why fine
LTE not you can rattle off lights in Germany's Bluetooth and Bluetooth low energy so we're going to see a proliferation
Variation
In the underlying transport mechanism and that's okay cuz the IP protocol
Amor
Critical question is what happens above the IP layer
And here we also see a lot of variation among the producers
These devices
And we're probably going to see that variation for a while to come
I think it's important to achieve some standard
Especially when we get up into the space of semantics
What can I tell what device what can the device tell me
If I have to
Somehow managing Ensemble of devices that come from multiple
Manufacturer is more
Brands
Standardization is your friend here
Because then you can write applications that
Consistent
If you have to write something different for every possible manufacturer
Equipment is going to be hard fixing things that don't work is going to be
Speaking of which
Another big challenge is how long these devices are going to be in the field
How long will they be maintainable
Will the companies that made them go out of business and leave you with a house that doesn't work anymore
What if there's a bug in the software that causes a your malfunction or a breach of privacy or some other thing
Who's going to fix that
How will the software get downloaded into the
Did you buy sell the device novocaine from a legitimate Source how do we know if the update hasn't been modified
Integrity
The list of questions
Is very long
And most people who are doing these devices are not thinking so much about that they're thinking about I have an app
And I have a device and that's it
End of story
And at some point even the consumers are going to recognize that there is more meat
So right now at the kind of
Device Communications level
Upstanders like iotivity
We should all join now we have
Got. So that's that layer
Some of the other thing
Things that you were talking about
We really don't have a standard zeffert around them to
To my knowledge and I
I'm thinking of things like
I guess authentication of a device all the way through the network or even
Being able to monitor changes
Do we have anything like that on the internet
Not anything that's so so so
Pacific to the device
I think advice should be
Paranoid gently
Not accepting control or updates or willingness to release
Software release date
Unless it has good reason to believe that the party that is asking it for the data or commanding it to do something is
Legitimate
Which means probably in almost certainly some kind of cryptographic Exchange
Digital signature style thing
It has to be workout but then that leads to all kinds of questions about how easy or hard is it
Configure the device to do that
I worry about
Scenarios like I have a house full of this stuff
And I've invited guests over
How long does it take me to introduce my gas to the house
And give the gas the authority to
Turn the lights off and on and flush the toilet
And then when they leave how do I make sure that I revoke the privilege is so that the fifteen-year-old in the family doesn't do something
So there are these scenarios
I think you're not adequately
Address
We don't have
Not coming agreement see at the even that these are the right problems
Solve it alone how to solve them
So my guess is going to be chaotic
For a while
But the consumers eventually are going to get
The point that they don't want equipment in the house that isn't reliable
Did they don't consider it
To be safe
That fails to work at the Internet isn't available in the old series
Expectations
Will eventually rise to the surface and either the producers
Will have to respond
Or their products won't be
Purchased and they will go out of business
So
There will be pressure in the long night
To solve the problems you achieve standards and everything else but not before a fair amount of turmoil
Experience
What is everything didn't talk
2B internet
What is each house had its own internet
And then
Your platform
Provider let it out
And did something like that does that feel like a viable solution
It's not an open web thing
I think it depends a great deal on what it is you were expecting this
Classify
To do I mean if you want remote monitoring for example when you're away and you want to be apprised of what's going on
Turn around in an emergency
The house is on fire the fire departments on the way should they have access to the webcams and the temperature sensors
In order to
Find people who have collapsed or places where the fire is obviously burning
The brightest
And then you don't want them to have access app
The fire is out in summer
So I can understand
Local communication which I think is needed
You don't want to have to go all the way out to the public internet and back again in order to control the house so they're Cleveland
I need to be an internal
Communications capability
And that introduces the possibility of a hoverboard
Control over something
There's an organization that's called iotx
Which is trying to help people
The disparities
Protocol
Find a way to allow interaction to happen anyhow maybe with protocol translation which everybody gags at including
Me or with some other mechanism
So that
Even in the presence of all the diversity it's possible to organize things in a
Maura West
Consistent
At somewhere
In the Arctic
So I don't think that isolating things in the house exclusively it does salt
The problem and certainly doesn't satisfy many people's expectation
What this can do
What about the industrial iot
How should I think about that differently than
Make it the Smart Home
Well several things occurred to me one of them is it in an in an industrial setting you may have
Tens of thousands
Devices
But you're operating at a scale where you presumably can have expertise in the company or accessible
The company that can help organize configuring maintaining update
You also could have some discipline within the organization about access
You might insist on two-factor authentication really times a mechanism
That limit the potential hazards
Abuse
Or invasion
Of the system
And so it's the usual thing in an in a corporate setting in a government setting in an inch
Situational setting mothers in top-down control
You may be able to and introduce
Practices
That makes system a lot more safe and secure
In a household setting though
It's another story because we're ordinary Mortals and we're not very disciplined and so the system has to help us
Behave better or at least prevent our Worst Behavior from damaging
Ourselves
Arlington
It's true sometimes I use the same
Change password
Two apps and I feel every time I'm like that's the wrong thing
Okay
So
This is felt a little not dark but just hard
Let's talk about what makes this worth it so what are the opportunities what is this really enable
So there are several things that I am
Firmly convinced will make a big difference the first one and obvious one is that with the right kinds of equipment in
Monitoring and sensing
You could do a better job of energy use and other resources in a house or in an office building and you see
GED and I'll lead buildings
Are getting more and more popular these days
Probably because there's some tax advantages and other things about investing
In this kind of structure
So at home
You may save money
On your resources bills
Another possibility is remote monitoring
For safety
Here we get into whether it's Access Control security or fire prevention or fire detection
The third possibility which is perhaps a bit more in
Is that tell you may be able to use it home which has been outfitted with this capability
How do you monitor your angel
And here we got the notion of continuous monitoring where the information
Where
An estimate can be made of your normal condition so that if you drift away from normal that can be a signal
You should go
Go to the doctor call husband Larry call 911 or do something
So take your vitamin pill
So this idea of being able to gather information and assemble it and make it useful
Even to the extent of your own health is it is valuable
I often wonder whether or not
Having the house is fully instrumental
Can also make it a lot more comfortable on adaptable
There are lots of attempts now meme
Voice interaction
To control my house some of it is almost certainly as stimulated by one Star Trek episodes where you could say
Malaysian play Beethoven
I am
Still a little unsure about how successful The Voice interactions are going to be but some of the applications
I am being able to get the house to adapt to your preferences in an easy way it's supposed to running around pooping
Ip65 dimmer switch
It has a certain amount of appeal to it
It is totally awesome
I have many
Voice settings better
Like party mode
Dinner mode
So
We talked a lot about
Cool things that happened
Standards in architecture
Let's talk about
How we're going to pull this together in a way that works for the consumer and the possibility of Regulation
Because
There's a lot of data running around
Security issue
What role
Should the government play
In this whole Realm
Well Chris the normal reaction in the private sector is the government
Go away
I think that's not going to be
Possible
To sustain
People are going to be relying increasingly on these devices. Where
At some point they're going to have to be some kind of certifications
The software level on the hardware
So we need
Cyber Underwriters lab
I think that there may also be potential liabilities associated with negligence
Deployment
Equipment
Breakfast
For example the situation that Gaming Corporation found itself in
When whatever was a half-a-million webcams were all aimed at the same destination
How could this possibly happen while there wasn't any access control built into the devices or the access control was widely known
Username and passwords were constant in the same everywhere
To assembling a botnet was no big deal
I consider that to be near your responsible
However to be fair to everybody people made those things probably weren't thinking about the possibility that they were all online
The same time on the internet and therefore
Compromisable
And we saw what happened
So just go
Seat belts
Warren until the law said if we catch you driving now to seatbelt over there's an accident without a seatbelt there will be time
Same as smoking
So you find all the Persuasions about good behavior
Are backed up by some kind of incentive
And I want to use the word incentive here and not necessarily legislation and regulation
When we have incentives
To do the right thing
Then
Generally speaking the right thing happens
The question is how do we formulate the incentives in order to get that to happen and how do we agree on what the right thing is
I thought you were going to tell me
One of the other things
I think it's worth considering here
Is
Those cameras many of them were manufactured in China so even if we had
The right incentive
People in China they don't have necessarily so there's an internationalisation
I don't know what to think about it
Well there have been a lot of discussions about International cyber
Agreements
On one side you agree not to attack each other's basic infrastructure and on the other
Not to ship you know hazardous gear
A couple of thoughts come to mind one of them is the the certification question
I actually have some
Saline Ciara suppose you couldn't sell a product unless you could at least reveal the source code
Some party who agrees
Private boat so handsy
But Sadie credibility to have said we ran into a series of tests we did and everything else we believe this
This device to me
Say
Another observation is to
Inhibit the device's ability to communicate outside of the of the house except
This gets back to you earlier thought about today
A local conductivity that doesn't extend outside the house
So I think that there are are serious
Supply chain question
That arise an example of a scenario that really worries me is somebody building a device throwing in random pieces
Source operating system
Code
And not particularly caring about whether you'll ever be maintained or not just I just want to sell the device
Answer that leaves another open question in my mind about commitments to maintaining
These kinds of devices over. Of time cuz some people will buy them with the expectation that they're going to work for
Period of a decade or more
And what is the company goes out of business
You know within six months because it wasn't the popular product and yet you want
To keep it in use it
So maybe they're asking Arrangements
With regard to the source code
There I think there's room for quite a bit
Domestic and potentially International exploration
Of agreements
The United States because of his
Extraordinary
Consuming power
Isn't it is a place where they will be even
Higher risk factors just because we acquire all this stuff
Music
That's West true and places that are not spending as much of their discretionary income on gadgets like this
Over a long period of time
All these gadgets will become available to everybody
Things to reduce cost
Unless of course attorney sounds we've all concluded these things you're so hazardous and dangerous and annoying and they don't work with
Supposed to anyway
And we all decide to hell with it
Go back to the light switches
You can pry my light switch
My cold dead hands
Alright so
Given all of this
Do you have any smart devices in your home
I have a few
My wife
For frankly they have a 747 worth of light switches and dimmers so that she knows exactly which ball butt is itchy
Controller
On the other hand I'm not a few Lutron programmable things that I like a lot because you talk about it
That's not up for you
I have a custom Entertainment System
And that's a good example of
Hazardous right because when it doesn't work have to call up a guy that lives on in miles away to come out and fix it
It's a good example of why customization may not necessarily be the smartest thing in the world
I have some of the
Alphabet Nest thermostats in the house
And I also have a system to monitor the temperature humidity in light levels in every room in the house is a mess
Network money
6lowpan
Every 5 minutes
Information to a server in the basement
And
The Wine Cellar is instrumented so that if the temperature goes up to 60 Fahrenheit
SMS in my mobile telling me my wine is warming up
So the next step is to put RFID tags on all the bottles so I can do an instantaneous inventory make
Make sure that when I'm away no bottle is left
Seller without my permission
So the answer is we have a little bit
Automation
Did you build your light and temperature sensing in your wine cellar stuff yourself
No this is not me in the garage with a soldering iron I actually got commercial equipment
Every case
Use for that
Yeah I mean whose equipment did I use
Well let's see the thermostats come from there
The temperature sensor Mesh networking from archrock which was acquired by Cisco Systems
The RFID detector was a startup company
Where I bought it in and bought some of their equipment
Lutron controls are commercial
RN program by the same guy that did mine
Entertainment System
Entertainment System itself is a kind of a dog's breath waste of equipment coming from a variety manufacturers all
Wife together
I am being driven by
Fairly sophisticated
Software package
So is it all commercial that some of it is
Let me say cuss
Don't
Awesome thank you so much
Happy to have a chat I'm just hoping that we have a chat 10 years from now hopefully I'll still be around
10 years now to to assess where are we in the space in which which one could we driven into this.
I'm hoping we're flying free and easy because I'm That Kind of opt
Tumescent
Well so am I but I'm trying to be
All right
Well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast please join us next week when we have another
Amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are hankering for some iot news sign up for mine
The newsletter is Stacy
Coyote.com thanks for listening