Hey
Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we are doing episode 187
The Internet of Things
Kings podcast
It's going to be amazing
We're going to talk about some brand new smart glasses from the former makers of the myo armband
Qualcomm wants to put more metal May powered bluetooth earbuds into the world Google home hub reviews are out
Look at the launch of a new chip
Company that is
Going to do amazing things for low-power tensors
Plus
Whole segment on privacy
He just so much to talk about there
Hand
We have
A solution for people who don't want a camera in their bathroom but they want to check
False
Our Guest this week is going to be Hugo fines who is CEO of electric
We're going to be talking about iotc
Security +
What's going on with cellular connectivity that's popping up on every platform out there
And we have a message from this week
Sponsor
Cognizant
So
Big Show
Lots to talk about Let's Get It Started With a message from another one
Keep your iot Fleet growing and trade in the days of remoting into your customers devices to identify and resolve bugs
Upgrade to Aqua 10 minutes and let it
Edge first problem-solving software do that heavy lifting for you
I'll quit automatically find performance issues then tracks them from released to release
Collecting all the Intel you need to rapidly identify root causes for the errors plaguing you and your customer
Register for free today at auklet. IO
That's a UK
Let
Dot IO
Hey Kevin
I'm sick
Today so
What's going to happen on this show
Feels like
Anything Could Happen
But
Shake It Off
With North
This was surprising this
Happened super fast we talked
I believe last week
Weak about the maker
The myo armband which was a gesture-based armband
Deciding to
To kill that
And
Start something new but we had no idea what the new thing is
And now we do
The company that made the Maya
Armband
What has changed its name it is now known as
North
Which kind of makes sense
Canada and it now has launched a new Prada
Cold vocals
And Kevin
What are Focus
Coco's are glasses coming from North and this is good because now they have three more pivot Points if they want to change the
Secondary name is east south or west
If this doesn't work out
Vocals
Air smart glasses
They're not cheap at $999 you will be able to get them in
A North
Store they're building one in Brooklyn New York
Right now
Of course they are
So soon you'll be able to go to Brooklyn and get measured up because you do have to get
Connect scan your head has to be scanned for proper
What's different about these glasses say then
Google Glass for example
But I still have don't use them there's no camera here or anything like that
These look like
What they look like the glasses that I wear today just kind of
Hipster looking glasses and to the right side
Of glasses hidden from anybody
Who's looking at you is a small projector
And what the projector does is it bounces information
Off of
A spot on the lens right onto your retina
Like fun and that's this is not the first product
To do that I forget who maybe it's Intel has a similar technology until does they started a smart classes
Unit called vaunt
And then promptly shut it down
Oh I was going to say perhaps North is using the until technology but
Qualcomm Tech
Really interesting all right so what can you do with these things for a thousand bucks
Honestly you can't do much but you can get some information which I think is actually a good thing
I'm all about context give me the right information in the right place at the right time and making it so that it's not
Disruptive
So if I'm having a conversation I don't want to be like look at my phone every five seconds from new information
You don't have to do with vocals
300 by 300 pixels
Viewing area is 15 degree viewing area
And
You can view messages you
Can send automated responses to messages you can call an Uber you can also get Turnpike
Turn directions to your calendar check the weather and I presume more functionality will come to these but the point is
These are not
Highly intensive things
That is giving you or letting you do
What I thought was really cool
Because I'm crazy
Is you can actually see information like a text or get your turn by turn directions but you can also then talk to
And say
Respond to Charlie
You know and
Charlie I'm running late
So I actually thought that was
Not only are you getting basically at
Tiny personalized screen
You can also interact
Yes I was actually surprised to see
The matinee integration quite honestly and I think
It's really smart rather than North creating their whole own special interface or
Assistant or anything like that it just makes sense
To integrate with something that's good and already exist
I thought you were going to say that you were really intrigued by the little
Accessory that comes with it did you see the loop
I did not know I did
Machida Loop yes that is
Yes Loop is I got plastic ring with a joystick button looks like a regular smart ring they might
Benefind
It may be from
Motive or somebody like that yes motive
We just added an NFC authentication chip to theirs but that's only the story you can use the little joystick on the rink s wipes
Through the interface on your classes so it's not like you have to again with Google Glass sound like you have to
Touch the glasses to do anything
You know I had to cancel a swipe the side of my head and I think I put a dent in my hairline there by doing that so much so
This is really really cool matinee integration also makes sense for another reason
Amazon actually was a lead investor in the series B funding for North
Yes
These look pretty interesting to me I don't have $1,000 to get this I don't think I
1% and its current state because I wear Smartwatch and not generally does the same stuff plus more but I'll
Lakers are going and I would do it if they had so here's
A lot of people are like oh got $1,000
That's crazy for glasses
I'm going to out myself right now I don't buy a lot of
Jewelry but I do spend a crazy amount of
Glasses
Because I love like really unique and
Frames and sometimes those are
More expensive
So
Well I have spent $1,000 on a
Pair of frames
Are my glasses they look awesome
They have actually
Are big sunglasses that have
Swarovski crystals in them it's
But
These are not those glasses these do not look as cool as I would want them
$1,000 so that's just me
And I think that's because they want to appeal to a wide audience
You know these are pretty generic looking hipster doofus glasses like eyewear
I like that there hipster doofus glass
I like that
All right
Is another reason real quick just that I could not get these even if I wanted to
Did you obviously work with
Prescription lenses if you want
But
They don't work with bifocals which I have progressive lenses so that
That might work okay with these
However
They can only handle prescriptions between + 2 and -4 diopters
And I'm well beyond that both eyes unfortunately so
It's not even an option for me
So it's not for old or blind
Got it did you just call me old
Weird lines and line
Are you being right
I'm like hey I might have bifocal soon to
Or actually I'm getting progressive lenses for
For the first time
Good luck getting used to that the first days
Might make you nauseous
Okay
So
Related
But not exactly so we mentioned the Qualcomm chips are in these glass
These are not the chips that are in there but Qualcomm has launched a brand-new reference design
And for smart audio
And this is worth noting
Cuz I really think we're getting to this point where we're going to have that interface from her
Write the movie her where you
You're like you got your phone in your pocket and it's super smart but you also have a relatively smart headset
TED talks to you when you interact with
Actually
I feel like I just saw an ad for this for some
Other madam
A powered headset
So what county is created
Reference design for its qcc5100
Series Bluetooth audio chip
Yay
Is for Android phones obviously
You put the
Anime app on the phone and you pair to these earbuds
And you toggle mantle made with a simple push of the bike
And they actually have decent quality
Features for music listening as well so they're going to active noise-cancellation they use the
Qualcomm app
X codec for high definition audio and qualcomm's true wireless stereo I'm not saying that thing better than
What those are so many rappers use but
Now these are not just
An assistant in your ear not just a hero
They don't actually have the hair bow
Functions
But maybe we'll get
It's so much computing
It's funny you mention that her movie cuz I've seen it probably 20 times I love it
Do you know that I cannot get my wife and daughter to watch it cuz I think it's
Creepy
They will not watch that movie
Huh
If I will not watch The Haunting of Hill House
But who neither would I but that's creepy on purpose this is their interpretation of her is creepy
They probably see the p
I bought those pants
MLB him for Halloween
No I'm kidding about that but
I'm worried because we're going to this he Robles
Future and
You have to accept it
It better get on board
Hassan Whiteside
We're going to talk about something
Along those lines out of
Remember creepy
But now
Glucagon
Well maybe not I don't
The Google home hub reviews are out
And
People think
Yeah and
I read all reviews
They're obviously the devices cheaper so that's a plus
But you get a better experience on the larger smart display as in general yes they cost more so you're paying for the
The sound quality on the Google home hub is not up to par with those as well and you know I
Still
I don't know I just can't get over the size of it. You know what listen it's not for me and that's fine there plenty of other people who are fine with
With a little home interface and a photo frame
That 7 inch screen no problem I just like the additional feature of a bigger screen for my YouTube TV and videos and
They're totally fair
But a photo frame
Right now is about 79 to a hundred bucks so
You could send people like your Kik pictures and get this for like a family member if you thought
It doesn't have a camera so it's
It's kind of creepy
What it does actually take Duo calls that I just found this out the other day
I thought you couldn't use Google Duo on this because it did not have a camera Google says it supports Duo calls
Better voice only
Oh
Yeah so this actually might be great for like
A grandparent
Yeah it is
People won't be able to see you on the other end of the call but that's okay
That might be a bonus
It depends my for my friends yes they're probably very happy about
All right and Google home hub features have started rolling out to smart.
Displays I have not tested it on mine
It started yesterday I believe
And Kevin has not tested on his
Well I tried to force the firmware update by resetting the Hub and it didn't do anything so we're talking about it
All of the features that Google
Demoed on the Google home hub this month at the made by Google event
Are trickling down to the other smart displays which makes sense so the Lenovo that you and I have Stacy this marks
Display is getting at the JBL is getting it
And this will add the
Slide down for Europe
Whole-home interface feature
To allow you to control things by touch little bit easier which I love that future but and this is another reason why
I probably wouldn't get a whole lot because if you're just getting for that feature you're going to get it on the on the better Hardware anyway
Alright well hopefully
We will get that soon I will say that I did enable Matt Amaze new whisper mode
And
It was super easy
I just started whispering to her and she said
I think you're whispering to me
Would you like me to Whisper back
Or something along those lines and I said yes
And then poof
It happened
This is notable one because he was promoted
Pretty useful Batu
I had this whole voice interaction with
Metal Mayhem
That's historically somebody
Probably would have done in the app
So
It's subtle it's great that you can actually enable this by voice it's that's
Smart use of the
Microphones
Yay
If you're listening and you're on the matinee team someone did actually ask us
They're like hey I'm hard of hearing is there a way for
Recognize my voice
Which yes there is and when it hears me it
It just speaks up
A little louder
And I cry just for that person
I was like that is a brilliant idea
So Madden 18 Folk
Or the Google team phone
I'm actually not fussy
Go for that
Can you still use case
Unless they're whispering and then don't shout really
All right
Let's talk more about Amazon
Amazon is pitching immigrations customs
Horseman
On using its recognition face recognition cloud service
2 track
Immigration
This is
Unsettling it's related to the use of the
Face recognition service
By police officers and now they're just
Ice
Which currently
It's a super controversial agency
A lot of reasons
We don't get into politics much but
I can say that
Isis one of the agencies behind separating
Families from their children at
At the border and a lot of people think that's a problem so Microsoft Salesforce and other
Called in
2 question
Allowing their technology to be used by this agency in
Many people feel is
I just can say it's the pursuit of people you shouldn't separate families
And just to be clear this is not a done deal yet
Yes this has been a pitch and I guess demos
Still under consideration so it may not happen
Without again getting too deep into the politics
I think what we need are
The right
Policies in place first
And then look at whatever tools are necessary to help
Support those policies
So I'm not saying I'm all for this painting means
But a piano to me this is putting the cart before the horse
Basically this is allowing for things like Mass surveillance and when you run
The images through it
It will recognize
We don't have any rules
About this
The and it's not it's also not foolproof
No no it is
And you might be recognized as a escaped convict when obviously you are not
And it's worth saying that
We are more concerned about
Dark people
People who are brown people who are black coming in and those are actually the people who these facial recognition algorithms
Tabby biggest problem
So
Lot of things to think about here most of them
Kind of dystopia
Send a lock that note
Let's talk about privacy in the Internet of Things
Because we
We talked about this a lot we think that in the US were about to get some
Privacy regulations
I think that is
Good
As we are leading up to drafting some kind of legislation getting something implemented we're seeing a lot of
Companies come out talking about it
None more so
Then Apple
Which has constantly said that
Did they keep State a private
And
You might argue that that actually hurts it and its ability to create
Great day I based experiences but it's also something that it is definitely
Trying to pay
Pitches a differentiator between Amazon
So Tim Cook
The CEO of Apple
Give a speech recently in Europe where he basically said that when companies are misusing quote deeply personal data
He called it
Weaponized against us with military
Efficiency
Comet surveillance
And the entire speech was
Those are strong words
From a CEO
Yeah he's all in favor and In Praise of
What's the new gdpr regulations in
You obviously I see a point in
We talked about privacy in the past and we're all for it
I also wondering you kind of alluded to it you know
Is this perhaps why
The
AI in
The iOS world is not
Up to Snuff
With Google and Amazon in terms of personal
Information
Helpfulness I guess it's probably best word as well as
Homekit not having the launch velocity that the other platforms
It's almost like apple is back itself into a corner in these areas
Try and improve them
Without sacrificing privacy which is up
Great goal
But it comes at the cost of products that are less useful
And it's really unclear so there's a lot of reasons that Apple may be perceived as being more behind it
1 is
For a long time it didn't let researchers talk about what they were doing a lot of the data science Community is very open
And they want to publish research
An apple does not work
To happen so part of it may just be it's not attracting people who
Want to share what they're doing with the word
The other aspect is definitely really
There are those things too
To think about
With this and
I think we might be veering too far into the
Innovation is awesome Innovation at all
Cost is
Awesome in this particular realm because
Average height
There's kind of conflicting things
There's the idea that
Customization
AI can lead to
Awesome customization
And a better user
But
Up until now the web has been built on
Using an AI
For better Market
And those are two very contrary
You're either going to sell the user or you're going to sell the user
On something
Historically weave
So the user
And
It's unclear actually even if the user wants these
And that's kind of where we are at
At this moment and I'll give you an example of something
Kind of
Ties into this
Last month
James director of global
Additional information gave a presentation
To the association of national advertisers
In it he described the company Gathering data from
90000 GM owners in LA in Chicago for
Three months last year
These people were not aware
Of this happen
Basically it was sent into what people were listening to radio station satellite
Etcetera
And
It took that
Title to vehicle
Data and location data in basically was packaging this
For Advertiser
There is so much fear right now like whenever I talk to somebody who doesn't have an echo or a Google device in their home there you
Usually concerned about it listening in
Can we have this
Actually happen
And with the scariest part of
The presentation I think
Place to me
Was that the GM executive said that since of a quote
We sampled
The behavior every minute
Just because we could
Yeah that's not good
Interested tie these two things together and elaborate something else
Some more on what you said
You're right Innovation for the sake of innovation is
It's not the answer and
People sometimes fail to understand that when you innovate and building Technologies
That allows you to increase your Innovation and
Bill Nur Technologies so the rate of change and innovation
Is increasing
What's not increasing is the level of privacy
Security that we have
Yeah but you need to be in lockstep for this Market
Otherwise you're going to have while you're going to have what we have today you're going to have
Devices and device makers that are doing things like this because
They can
Injustice 2
Drive this home
Because
By gosh we're going to
Call the spit dystopian episode sidewalk Labs which is alphabets
Company building a smarter City on Toronto's
Waterfront
Area one of the advisors
An
Cavoukian
Who is a privacy expert
She actually resigned
Last week
Is an advisor to sidewalk
Because she didn't like
That Sidewalk labs when it released its privacy and digital governance
Proposals and we actually feature those in the newsletter last week
They decided
That the
Could not make
All personal data
D identified
At the source and what that means is all of your city public data that
It's coming from you as you walk around the city
Will still be associated
With you
Did you talk about how people could use that data and when people use that data they need to make it
Clear what they're doing with it and then
Talk about creating a civil Trust
To monitor that data
But they did not say
Is that it had to be
Take it away from you
And part of the problem here is when you create these type of smart
Platforms
You obviously open them up to third parties
And one of the issues
Is
At least with sidewalk labs
The alphabet company saying is
You were committed to D identifying data but
We can control with their parties do
You can see how this
Could play out negatively for
Also take for example the recent
Selling of
People's wireless data by the carriers to third-party data brokers who then turned around and sold that data to
Two law enforcement agent
So then
They actually had access to Lake
Individuals movie
Which is kind of creepy
Because you know we have lost
Protect
How police can get that info
Information they just kind of sidestepped
Frightened rabbit
Just by going to
Now the carrier said they stop doing
But
You know these are
You have to rely on someone to figure this out and then
Shame the company and then they're like oh okay I will stop
It's always after the fact
So all of those stories taken together
I'm going to say they make me feel dirty
They make me feel really uncertain about the world that we're trying to build
And the conversations were
Having a bout
Are connected products
How use the data from those
And our monetization play
So
I'm going to be like if I had to claim a big Story 4
The coming here
Which we don't really do those kind of things
That's going to be
A huge story next year
And
A couple episodes ago we talked about how we're getting the smart home ready for normal people
And I believe that is truly happening
We need to have those conversations
What's before everyone starts putting
Olaf is crazy
Stuff
So this is me calling out
To everyone
To think about this
To talk about this
Start
Figuring out
How we want
How to handle this
And maybe it is maybe it's like
OK I don't need this in my
It's not providing me enough value
I don't know
That's enough on that
About something
I don't know is it more creepy is it less creepy
Everything
What's creepy this is the walabot
This is a
Sensor you can put on a wall they
I think it's good for your bathroom
And what it is is it detects Falls
It's a $249 divided
And you
It doesn't use a camera it uses
Radio waves so it's tracking basically
It's not like it's
It's kind of like radar or sonar
It's basically creating not images but information about
Waterfall looks like
Through and it will work through a shower curtain of a war
Works for all of this sort of
Thin layers of
Materials
And basically it'll say hey
This data pattern looks like what it looks like when someone falls in the shower
When someone Falls stepping out of the tub
And it will call an emergency personnel
How late is wifi-only nuts
It doesn't have a subscription fee
Probably because it's wifi-only
And if you're concerned about
This is a problem
It might be something you're
Interested in looking at
Yeah honey that's another way to help the Aging population or anybody trips in their bathroom whatever
It doesn't seem too invasive to me because it's not like you can
The camera
Because it's using Wi-Fi it's obviously voice over IP which Emergency Services aren't going to your local
Patient through that however I would assume that you set your home location in an app and it just
Provides that
Information
To the emergency services so that way you don't have to tell them where you are now you're going to carry this thing around and you're always moving so that
That's good you know for the Right audience I think it's
Probably a good product
Yes
I'm kind of interested in someone
I coming to you this week with a broken toe
That's okay
Baidu fall
Anyway so let's move on to our final Story 4
Witches
A couple weeks back
Probably months ago actually
The New York Times did an awesome story
Talking about how smart home devices can be used against people
Who are victims of
Vuse solo
How people could be controlled
By the connected devices in the
They're home so maybe their husband installs connected locks and locks them outside the house
Or maybe a wife uses a camera to monitor the husband
Don't know about it
All of these things
Super creepy
And
There wasn't a lot that we could do we talked about
A couple things that you
You could do but really it's
It's a tough problem to solve Kevin talked about how he always checks with his wife and daughter before installing things in the home
I talked about giving my husband Adnan
Access so they have
Access to this but
The Wirecutter did a story talking about
Other things
They're good suggestions in that they
They help they don't help
The issues
Like if you're not prepared to leave the situation or you still live with your abuser
These are not
Really helps
Tremendously
But
It's a start so they give instructions on how to log into your router
And see what other devices are on the network
They talked about how to reset devices and
Call the manufacturer
The two-factor authentication suggestion is awesome I'm very big into two Factor authentication for all of my online
Accounts as well as my devices nobody can login pretty simple to my Chromebook if they don't have the special
USB key for example
So I'd like to see more
Smart home companies during the setup process offer two-factor Authentication
Because that could completely lock somebody out from changing settings on you
Without your knowledge
Corset could be
Agreed
And another idea was to disable remote access
You can avoid applications that track and store location history
Turn off geofencing on
Devices
You know so again this kind of put you in
Back but we are talking about surveillance
In a lot of these devices and
You know it can be used against you
I'll put a link to that for everyone who is interested in checking the
And
I'm surprised wait a second I'm surprised that you skipped over one of the most interesting exciting chips.
Rays of the week
Oh my God I didn't talk about it
Now you know that's my point you guys I'm terrible
This is what happens
Okay she was so excited before the show about this okay there's a new
Chip company out there called at mosack
It launched this week
And
Here's what
Any new Chips
Japanese automatic
Cuz I'm a big nerd
But this is a chip designed to solve
The battery problems with
Connected sensors in low-power devices
Out there in the iot
Because my dad if we're going to put a trillion sensors anywhere or even fifty billion sensors we can't be changing the battery
So at mosaic what they've done is they've created a tiny bluetooth module
And
This Bluetooth chip is notable be
Because it's designed to
Do some really Advanced things on the sleep and wake mode
So that's good right
The way it listens for
Data packets is slightly
And more power-efficient
50 most exciting aspect
About it
Is
It Harvest
RF energy
Show
Basically this doesn't need to be powered by a battery
Sorry it can be powered by harvesting
Wireless
Else and
You have to be kind of close to things for this to work
But this is not inductive
It gathers energy from the RS
Signals so basically
Any radio waves out there in this is actually
Radio
Powers
Other things so Wireless power like we talked about with a Qi standard
That is actually
RF power is
As well but it's sitting directly on top of something and so
It can power things that
Require more power
Like a cell phone
Cuz if you send too much energy through these RF waves to power stuff
You end up basic
Microwaving someone
So you cannot send massive quantities of power wirelessly
But you can't send tiny amount
And that's basically what the sensor. Is it's basically trickle charging
All the time
So I love this
I love the design
I'm very excited to see this come out into the world
It will not be out into the
Volume until 2019
And then we probably won't see devices at the earliest until the holidays of 2019
Probably more likely we'll see it
In 2020
But
Yeah this is interesting
For so many reasons and
The application of this obviously you think sensors right away because they generally have low power requirements to begin with
But
They're saying there are multiple applications here that we could be using his for such as wearables asset tracker
Beacons remotes
Keyboards
Mice
So there's there's a lot of potential here in terms of
What we could see this in
Yes now what you will need
For this kind of network
Work you're going to need
If a mesh situation because you cannot be too far away and still gain
The power
So
You're going to have it like
Your phone cannot trickle charge this by talking to it
Phone is downstairs
Check the sensors
Upstairs
Yeah I wonder though
What the range is like I'm walking around
With a wearable and I'm not
My phone with me would it be able to harvest energy couldn't possibly get some from the cellular network
What's that are around I don't know all the frequencies that they're using to get that yellow electromagnetic
Energy
Will Kevin I can answer some of the
So it is
About 10 feet
That's kind of the optimal range that you should be
So
I mean that's not terrible
It's also know so my phone would always be within 10 feet of something I'm wearing
I'm carrying my phone as well but obviously I'm almost always more than 10 feet away from a cell tower
NFL stand under that just to recharge
Things are still very interesting what they could do it.
Yes thanks for reminding
I was so eager
To get to our
Voicemail
Iot podcast hotline
That I forgot about
And it's really
Yay
Now
Let's go to the iot podcast hotline which is brought to you by Schlage
With a variety of stylish and secure electronic locks to choose from
Smarter homes start
With Schlage
You can learn more at Schlage
Dot-com
Coyote
And
We are giving away a free Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wifi adapter
Turn to our listeners
All you have to do to enter to win
Is Colace at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
Ask us a question
We may answer it and
You are automatically enter
Two twin so we do our next drawing
On October 31st
At midnight eastern time so call us before then
And you'll be in the drawing
This week's voicemail is from
Isaac
And he
The question actually
About his Schlage sense lock
Hi Kevin and Stacy my name is Isaac
I'm from Colorado Michael is actually about the
Schlage sense
Lock you probably seen in the web.
Ever since I was 12 was released
We can no longer control the
Sexton
Locks remotely
Sections were actually my favorite locks have been using them
Years
And I have to my house
The other day I almost said to gets locked out of my house
Connect keyless remote case I was traveling back home
Cisco
So I was hoping to ask if you guys know more from the rectum
Is there an app to type
60 shoe
And it's not
What are the laws
Star hump
Compatible
Would you recommend
To replace the
That's probably not going to be selected
It to be on the air because
Complaining about Schlage sense a little bit but
I was hoping you might be able to
Thank you
Oh Isaac
We do not
Let our sponsors
Interfere with our editorial
We would never do that
Because all of our sponsors actually
Really want the iot to work out
And so they really want to solve
These issues
In this case
You Are Not Alone
Schlage
Has acknowledged
This is an issue
Dealing with it's also an issue that August locks and even some light bulbs that are Bluetooth
Baste her face
Schlage has given us an official statement
They acknowledge that this is an issue
People are experiencing remote
Connectivity trouble with
And they are currently working with apple to identify and resolve the issue
In a timely fashion
They do want to stress that customers can use their
Access codes to unlock the
And you can manage the lock using the Schlage Sense app
Or the Apple home app if it is in Bluetooth
You just can't do it
Remotely
Now this is probably still super inconvenient
People hate this
They hate having this problem
LED light bulbs
Problem with other
The issue is the update
IOS 12
It appears that
Something about that update
Broke something
In the homekit Bluetooth
Implementation
The
Challenge that a lot of these companies are dealing
Here is
They don't always have
Full access
Beta versions
That might be
Locks and so they are working with Apple
Kind of
The challenge here
For apple is there
Completely changing the OS versions of major
Release of iOS iOS 12
And sure you know
DeKalb
Unit testing regression testing Etc
He got beta testers I beta test iOS 12 I did for a while
Before it came out live but they're just so many moving parts and you
Fix earned Edition
May go back and break something in this case perhaps it's something in the Bluetooth stack or who does what
You never going to catch at all unfortunately
Guess I don't understand you give Apple a pass but I mean I used to manage a QA software testing team just that one Corporation
It's a challenge I know anytime that you have coaching to such as especially when they're massive
So I hope that it gets fixed
It'll for all of that manufacturers that are affected because it's obviously not Ashley
And
Favorite kind of sucking Windows you know early adopters and IRT people until it happens so
Hopefully
You know Apple certainly knows about the issue so my guess is we'll see it fix much under the rather than later and we're just
Going to be inconvenience
That's what happens
And the plus side is
This sort of thing
Will probably prompt everyone to look at how they're evaluating
Software update
SRO SF
So this voice mail came in actually
I was 2 weeks ago
But
It's still not solved
The most recent update as of Wednesday morning
When we recorded this from Schlage is quote Apple continues to work on finding the root
They're working daily with r and
And other companies
You can tell that that's an official statement
Because I use the word app
And that's the first thing in finding
The solution is to replicate the problem
So Apple needs to do that first
Then that should help them determine what the issue is then Fix-It test the fixes make sure the fixes don't break anything else
Anywhere in iOS 12 and then push it out to everybody at that point
So that
All these locks now work the way they used to
It's going to take time it's just going to take time and the good thing is as you said I mean
They should now have a test case going forward
To retest
All baby lock
Functionality going forward with each new iOS update so
Hopefully this does not happen again
Something else might happen
Because hey
It's a whole new world out there you guys
All right
Thanks Isaac for a good question
Thanks late for
Feel free to give us a call
All right
Kevin thank you so much for
Talking to me this week about all of this guy's
Stay tuned
For our guest
Hugo finds the CEO of Electra
He's going to be talking about how a device
Made by a bankrupt company
Is still working for us today
And
You'll hear from our sponsor
How does it stay tuned
Everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Cognizant and I have Frank entities
Conscious its Global leader
Of the iot
Frank we have covered a lot of ground in our previous
We talked about how it's not easy for companies to build iot Solutions
But how you guys helped
A bunch of your customers in retail in manufacturing
Now tell us today how cognizant is taking it a step further by using a human Centric approach to
Solutions
Moschino iot applications are changing
Atticus of this customers demand more than the Enterprise Windows lock the speed
Scale of the coming transformation is massive and cognizant is helping building
But it's also a challenge that comes with graphic Technology Innovation
Some companies try to solve the problem but using a technology
Design new technologies without
Clear understanding what problem different song
What we as humans
S customers Factory workers
Service technician
110v that is widely believed in a human supposed to propose to solve this problem
Followed by the technology
That is a big challenge
What do you recommend to your class
What we recommend to our customers is that before
Legal
Solve the problem with the technology first approach to look at what people really
It's example
Apartments
Date we can get all kind of data
Some cars we can have
Show me the different features
At the disposal of the grave
Depression videos
Just need so many features
Arconic features
Well crafted features
Swappa thinks that we work with our customers interest example if still
Understand what people really need
Like I'm having to use
Dimensions can make that experience or driver most
And how does composite do that
The way we look at
Least problem says to
Play on key principles of ethnographic
Rochester
People say they want
Example in this case
The way a driver
Answer the question on a survey about what they want in a thug
It's very different from what they actually want
Doctors established by observing and that is why
The principles of
Ethnographic research help
Companies legatus
Qualitative understand
On what customers really want
On top of potatoes
Improved outcomes and iron auction rate
The iot to vote for people we need to keep human eats at the 4th
Your team sounds like they're doing a lot of grapes
What is the Outlook
For iot
What's possible with iot is already been experienced in a personal life
With Alexa
These new digital experiences
Continue to grow
I just installed a diminution work
Debate unprecedented efficiencies
Transform business model
Drive New Revenue
Douglas and can help you get started
And where can I listen to
Go to find out more about car
You can go to cognizant.com Coyote
And tell me about newspaper
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is
Hugo finds Whois
The CEO of a
Hugo how are you doing today
I'm good times
I am just
Fantastic
And I am excited because we are going to talk this week
About one of my favorite products
For the iot of all time
The quirky
But before we get to that
Let me give you a chance to tell everybody what Electra
So Electric
Provide security on dimensionality devices in the field by customers to build
Aqi easily integrated long lasting
Devices
4080 to deliver the daytime control wherever you stay
Which brings us back
To my favorite product
The quirky egg mine
We spend a lot of time on the show talking about business models and about security
We floated ideas like hey we should have in
Expiration date
For connected ID
Adams because
By golly
After certain period of time
You may not want to support it if you're a manufacturer but does a consumer you need to know that your device is not going to be supported and get ready
The updates so you can possibly
Take it offline
End
You've been thinking about this
Probably from the beginning
Talk to me about
When you are developing Electric
Kind of how you were thinking about security
Devices
Xiaomi
Going way back
Coming back to the
480 * 2
Specking
Play 90s MP3 player
But I'll tell you we got a quiet by Rio and they love consumer MP3 player making cosima devices
What's something I did feel like sawdust ideas and I sent to you MP3 players with almost the ultimate this place welcome
Every year that was much better delete some bands haircut better
Intellicast
Fusion so
Either you develop
Continue to work on a product
Really
You never did Summer
Takes off her that will the bugs were out generally
Product development team would move this is kind of
Chi products
Adult by Thrice some of the development team so similar
Construction
The company is either bring its new product still finish it with software on it and I'll get it working though ship it
And the chances of Danny's xidan capable
Could you sing a software update for this make in five years time a very low
Just simply it's not that serious Nowell it's everything to budget
Scheduling
That's the engine is made absolutely desperate won't attach
Tatiana stock if she were Hubley typing ability but unless they actually had given QA results
Retirement money
Do this
And that's really a structural
Consumer product companies
Maintenance
Cancel 20 years in advance whatever at least and so that was very much my mind with
HIIT
How do you make some other work how can you make
Devices remain secure even if the manufacturer is not involved
And the way we do separation operating system
Add the application unit tiny device White
Yakima
Okay and that brings us
Reminder
So talk to me
About that in the
Main steps that you take
Keep this operational
Even though
The company behind the Crooked eight
Is now defunct
Interesting things
Cookie OC Henson
Kwikee products
Innovation
Some people decided that I next trade
It'll tell you how many eggs you do if you don't have in your fridge from anywhere in the world by the powers on your teeth
The promotional
Suprax possibly
And by golly
I do have any eggs and I actually thought it
I didn't think it was like
Eminently useful
But when they
The salad is an idea they said it cost like $15 or
And at that price I was like that isn't
Excellent gift
Like
Quirky kitchen gadgets
For Christmas or holiday
Right so I was like yeah but then when it came out it was $50
Which probably gets
KissAnime expensive iot when
Like whatever
Moving
Now that is defended by
Quirky
If I still had it
It today
Message to my son
You would actually stay
Yeah it should do I believe since you bought a new one you confirmation and now they turn off the pilot
Pretty much still around
Play Store devices online at least still working yes
The one thing series
Essentially
When they decided
Patience of Wilton
Successfully
Cookie cookie
And since that point to him is pretty they don't test
Chicken place on the Southwest Center in 2013 to 5 years ago
To advise
However the device has had
Pretty night time
7 the right OS updates
It's been patched.
2 in
Secrecy
It now has
Very sweet to trust improvements
Pieces good stuff
And no one
Quickie head
Essentially
The gold standard one of the oldest
Security in its radio
Should be using
Unity Chan sotl Essex
Security
So now
We're familiar with that
So
You guys
Basically Courtney Stefani
And there's
These existing products
TLS updates and all kinds of other up
And so
Listen to it works cuz I rock
Oswalt radio operating system underneath
Most people
Don't have an iOS update on that
Phone or laptop whatever
Windows
Retest all your applications as well as testing done by the operating system Benda
. concept has never really been cold all the way down to IRT you know my jio TV
But that's what our system has done we have the separation between application and then operating system
Essentially that allows
Testing
To be able to update Yelp rating
Christian without the involvement
Vice Ganda
And so
This is one way of
Thinking about securing iot
Devices and then keeping them operational for a long long long long long
Time from an economic
Perspective
You guys have to update the OSB
Because
You're providing a service to
Customer so everyone gets
Joanna meaning
Kind of works Lacoste aswell
The huge cost of building and testing and maintaining your braking system
And every customer runs the same OS
So did you try to work that goes into that to make sure that it's stable and bug-free and we do a whole lot of other stuff
What about you
Remote Diagnostics
Something is going weird or whatever
We can dig into problems are deeply and find a recording pics
Yeah we kind of ducks
I'm sure they can stay online and stay secure
So let's try this to some big advances that have happened
I should say big
Some advances
Security
Microsoft has a product
Azure sphere
Which is a
Connection between the hardware and the OS layer
And it's actually also tied back in
Cloud
You guys have a cloud
But I'm trying to chill
This is a little bit of a
It's actually pretty interesting to see we've been doing this sweeping shipping store devices
2012 on
Existing commodity Hardware in the best features of the existing checks
Microsoft
Is city market sell steak
They have
Custom Hardware
Deployment
Security update
Application
Recycled things so it's good
Good things to have
However if you look at the comparison between the two this composite
Application
It's not sold in trouble tonight
Mystic Lake so security
Show the deployment
Mutations Grace
So
Busiest day stuff really does nothing
Integration
Traditional IRT in Diamond have to run in for my certificates on my device
I'm going to have to run my standard
TTT or MCPE rhcp stuff
On the device like usual
And like that.
Vici
Wes Electric in every device in the field has to be in the clouds to be in the clouds deals with
They transgression
Huge amount of flexibility
If you got the battery life
Concealed
Level eight
Actually and needed
Applications of spray primer
Well you need middleware
Uniqlo
ASAP database import custom record album.
End up with
It's always beautiful stuff which is architected my sleigh time in some parts
Conscription decide to tie stuff together for
Would you like to come system the education
HK security console
The actual standard system you ship so it's scales
Chick one product
Okay
So that's a lot about
And now let's move over to
How we get these things to talk to
The internet
Because in the last few years
I know that you guys lunch with
The Wi-Fi board
Some other
Lots of other board
Filtered out
Overtime
It was mostly Wi-Fi maybe Bluetooth
And now we're starting to see a lot of cellular
Modules
And I think that's
It's indicative of something
Talk to you since you guys recently launched
Bored talk to me about
Why
Is now the time
Show me the
Applications
Which she cannot find Wilson Leather
Additional line in 10 reasons why the sign text narration with his hand in a tree
Too bad Wi-Fi
Text message
Quite a few customers
Even when they products are pricing in office environments reference weatherall Wi-Fi
The problem is is that the amount
To talk into an IT support person you need to actually successfully deployed one of these device
Customer service
Is
Expensive not always productive and so becomes Justina doing and run around the whole thing and just
The police are there instead
He's actually a really horrible snake
Directions to many applications
Visible applications for a remote
Connect
Shipping right now it coming
In two environments with every sexy wife are you just not allowed
Top right now this is a few reasons.
1 is
We moved from
TD treaty networks 12
Nokia snakes in the IP
Because of that it actually has mammal characteristics make it much more like Wi-Fi
In terms of its very fast break latency by Foster son dates
Construction alt works alot better
Volume to data quickly
Tell me about devices typically if you want to send dates
On the backhand
Sexy stove Essentia switched connection so we will bring you a date to session
When nothing seems to happen
American X
Coming up and then you haven't used
10 seconds to Terry with tear that down so you could give it
Someone else
No Trace Adkins Finance no thanks. Doesn't want no slow fish.
Satisfying to use Nano
Trophies better like that
Variety specific
Sandwich Fair Oaks
1 which is about 10 megabit down saying it's it's
Open the same family is that okay that your phone use
The cooking guy.
It support
Contemporary
LTM
Undandy IRT
Which design
Realize the applications you never going to see these on the phone
But that smooth
Flower power
Simpler and cheaper
Antenna key has better range and penetration due to the motivation teams that the one they use but it's ready this this is opened up now
To do this
Her friends about it now
You're eating a lunch on iot devices going to try to make sure that
All City devices you actually can pay the carious money as opposed to being sick.
Couple things
Would you ever do a Lora board
It's probably not a 6
Stress petechiae
Me accidents on IP networks and now
They're essentially
Message based Networks
That's fine they're definition
I don't see a thing that I wear
Advice for customers
Very simple things you know we have customers who have
So they can monitor the TV networks remotely
What about me
Cast this is been something that I've been following
For a couple years now but even in b i o t
Still pretty expensive they're not at $5 which is where I think
They really want them to be
I would like them to be even cheaper
$5
Which is easier one of the problems there is he still coming on ready to sell it can I miss
Point
Just nb-iot silicon radius of people making the sandwiches
So is God
Bad stuff is coming
It will take a little while but I think
Bear in mind
Network early right now
Several
6 months ago
Pizza
100 devices
The carriers realize
The actual product development
Volume
He's coming down
So right now
Gigi fullbacks
Really really
Volume
Flexibility
I need
Okay and
In line with cost what about the
Costs associated
With delivering service
I feel like we've seen it
Couple
Couple Innovations here like AT&T launched in LA
TV button that instead of charging you
Pecan consumption you just had a
Max number of button presses
And it feels like for iot
Subscription models
Mini Prada
For those products they need some sort of
I guess built-in model kind
With the original Kindle
So you seen carriers
Get to that point
How are your customers
Problem
Asylum applications
People voicing this has several parts
The suffix run the application in the connectivity and a carry relationship
A list of neck dinner with moving pieces there what we trying to actually get rid of all of that
Can you give it power
Come online
The building is right
And to do that with hearts
Between the carrier and the customers just provide the
It's really really simple
Demi model deployment model
So people can actually get
Continue
Okay so
I feel like we talked a lot about
2 billion Ford
Tennis shoes 1
Security and making sure that devices stay secure
Even if
Your company goes away or maybe you don't want to deal with patching it anymore
And then also the issue of
Cellular connectivity and how
We're trying to figure out the best way to pay
Pay for that
These are big things
From the consumer side
It may not make a whole lot of
But from the manufacturer societies us a lot of
So with that
You know I would love to hear your favorite current iot device
What is it
Oh okay
So
Trump's wife
Not a commercial device
We have various things in our office
Connecting to Slack
So we have some speakers that I hit above us
Ceiling tiles in Connect
Tootsie Keowee drops
What's next for access points
Are we can now
Play Samsung pool
From the ceiling when sad things happen
So we actually have Arnold Schwarzenegger sound samples
Trance at 4 p.m. we have a full p.m. planking thing where
The office you so inclined can someone for applying for
She meant whatever but we have money to get down
Which comes out for me
Because all about ceiling tiles
If anyone mentions cookie the cookie
Swedish Chef
Chef rock 720
My favorite device is actually some of the random things we have in Iraq
It's very single uses of a mass-market thing but the interaction with the real woah
True unconventional memes
I can kind of like Siri and Alexa and Sonos beam of open up the voice in space today
Actually free convenient
Athena parking barrier
You need access to the right section
Employee
Access Control apart from hearing the channel
This is so exciting right now ATT
We should get excited about you
Who sings because
Yeah it actually makes your life easier and it's nice
Alright I look forward to planking one day
40 m in your office
Hugo thank you so much
Becoming on the show
Thank you very much that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more
Coyote knows sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot, we'll see you next week