Come to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house Stacy
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And please
Have so much news
News for you
This week we're going to be talking about all the new stuff in the
Security system
Ring
SmartThings ADT
We've got cool stuff for your car we've got a mood changing smart
Listen
We've got
A brand new os4 wearables that can track what you eat
Possibly
Got some driverless Taxi
And some stats on the industrial iot
We also have a message for this week from Qualcomm and
Our Guest
What is yodit Stanton
Who is the CEO and founder of open sensors
And she's got talked about how to scale infrastructure this is really good for
Your boss
Whatever and of course we're going to eat
Voicemail call from
One of our listeners
So
Let's get started with a message
This week sponsor
SG
What does g has been specializing in building automation for close to twenty years this week they've announced a bra
Brand new Clarity Gateway it support zigbee
Seaway
Wi-Fi
Bluetooth
Bacnet my bus and more so if you work with these protocols you're going to want to work with clarity
What FSG to Market your devices works with Clarity compatible just email energy in
Info at fsgi. Com
That's energy info at fsgi.
How to join the works with
Clarity
Thanks FSG and if you want to sponsor this podcast please visit Stacey on iot. Com
Slash advert
Okay Kevin
Let's get started with security
This week
Ring
Watch it security system which we were totally expecting
And
I find myself a little underwear
What about you
You know it seems like everybody's got their own security system coming out now or maybe they're partnering with somebody to
Panther security offering
Hey with an ounce compared to everybody else last week we talked about the new Nest secure
Security system
And another one
But later I kind of like
Ring is doing her because it's not expensive
Some of the details
Their home system is called
It retails for 199
A cheat code for arming and disarming
A contact sensor for a window or door
Passive infrared sensor for detecting motion
And a Z-Wave extender for adding range to smart
So
It's not a ton of stuff
Get you started
Yeah there's not a lot of sensors now in contrasting Nest system
Cost
Includes
I don't know what to call it
But it also has sensors
Serious and you can tags that let you
Swipe in and out of
Motion sensor
What column to extra fancy
Sensors
And then
There is another thing out this week SmartThings
Is working with ADT
BestBuy to Launch
I almost don't want to because this is really disappointing
And keep them
Samsung has you said working with ADT is an ADT monitor do-it-yourself security
Solution Power by SmartThings it'll be available exclusively at Best Buy
On October 29th you can pre-order it now if you're going to pre-order it's going to cost you 504
$49
And it's kind of basic to you don't get a ton of stuff and it's a starter pack
What's got a panel touch panel so that you can check in and check out the arm disarm etcetera and as far as sensors
Comes a 2 door and window
Sensors are detectors and emotion
Base station serves as a SmartThings Hub work with other SmartThings devices
Just great
Buy 4999 for olives
That which is not a lot
Seems
Like a lot of money to me and that's
Again that's the starter pack does not include monitoring
Get back to the ring monitoring and then talk about Nest modern as opposed to but if you want to have ATT professionally monitor
It starts at 1499 and safety
Meyering and then 2499 a months is for security services so I kind of thought for 5:49
The monitoring service for maybe a year
But I don't see it that way
Appear that they are don't know what Nest will charge for monitoring
Ring is going to charge
100 a year
Serene's pricing is actually really good
Get $10 a monthly fee gets you
All of your video
According
If you bought into the system
You probably wouldn't pay much
4 month
Highly significant
Compared to light
ATT offers or even something
You know like
SimpliSafe they have monitoring to I think that's 10 or $15
That's all so different from the nest
Security monitoring because it's
Going to be separate from the nest aware subscription which is now $10 a month for my recordings and such
Right the nest security
I think that's going to be
It is
Funtimes okay
So I was talking to somebody in the industry cuz I have written a lot
About how security is the Gateway
To the Smart Home
And so it makes sense that
ATT would get in on this
Pulse was home automation Plastics
Security really didn't do much about
And they also were suing
Because
To help integrate
With the security system
And
Ring was like
We Investments are not taking her IP
And so that lawsuit is still I don't know where that is it's still
Glasses take long time
It's worth noting
Employees
But they didn't buy the
It's very complex
Fairy wax
But having those people on board
Means
They're going to connect with other things so the ring security system
Additional outside
We don't know what those actually really encouraging
Don't do it right so
Yay
This is a lot of confusion there's a lot of
Stuff happening in the market
Are because security issues such a
Place to start selling
Hannah smart
Most the time I hear the stat
The 20% only 20% of America
Let's have some fun
Sakura
Which is really low
It is it is but I think you're right as far as a gateway drug
Because
It's something that people can equate to easily make security systems have been around for years and years and years
Where is the Smart Home Smart Home is a relatively new phenomenon
So I guess people can quite understand what it is I think they're also used to paying a lot of money for security system
And I wonder if that is playing into some of these packages and pricing plans
If I just securing my home
A security system
Nestor smart
Are things you know plus the
Dr200
Camera
Yes
Crazy but it's also
It's also going to cover your whole home if you're going to spend that much money you're going to get a ton of sensors right
Where is if you start with one day is like the ADT SmartThings package
For $500 you're monitoring one or two maybe three things
So you have to
Then spend hundreds more on top of that
We should also say that there's been companies doing this for a while
SimpliSafe is probably
Smartest
A friend of mine the SimpliSafe
Effect and basically they're saying hey SimpliSafe
Plus monitor
Very little
And
Another company that does very excited about
But they love their boats
354 the basement a moment
They can go out from there
I feel like there's one other company
Worth mentioning
I can't remember
Well that's okay while you're thinking about that I've got
What is this due to like the canaries and all the others that are
Home security cameras
I'm glad you asked because I'm very worried
About them so
Canarian pipe
Where to home security come
I love to pieces
You brought them into your house
Camera and a bunch of sensors
You
Punch it in and if it noticed something
You no emotion it would
Notify you in
Oh my gosh
Someone's at my house you could check the
The Cameron say yes there is a person
Could activate lyca
Really loud siren on the device
I thought those were really
Interesting and they were actually
Like they felt like a step forward
Home Security
Leslie
Let's let's insertion
Device
Think about how your home
Behaves and let you know
When something is different
But I'm not sure they're doing well for example just this week
Canary
We saw a lot of video on the cloud and it's not really tenable financially
Play for us so we're going to have
To ask
We're going to roll back some pictures and I thought this was really
Unfortunate
Because nobody wants to
Teacher's butt
Also
If you don't have a business model that sustainable
Business
So there is
In the future there rolling back
Is always
Recording
They said that they chose that one
Because
Most people turn their canaries to private
I would imagine so yes
It is probably the least
Sure I can understand why they're doing that and I just think in the long-term day and
Similar products are going to be more in a niche
Market than those who are teaming up and coming out with their own Solutions
Broader Solutions I should say
Security space
What do you think
Alright so lots of new things
What's up
Speaking of Piper
Which is one of those security
Piper Russell
Yuri
I don't know
The score podcast
Russell
Meet the piper
He left when Piper was sold to
And now he's doing a comedy called Clash
Works and
They make a product that will be out next year
Just a quick thing about this this is going to be a product that you stick on your
Car dash like the piper it takes a picture it also has sensors that plugs into the OBD port
Your car too
Gather location in Geneva
The idea here is to understand what's happening in
Around your car so you can check in on people as they're driving so
Tesla
Where's my husband and daughter
Are they are they stopping to get dinner let's see
Where they parked
You can also
Check in
See the road from
And then it also when your car is parked it has like glass break monitoring sensors and
Like Notifier
You something
So
All of that comes it's 299 for the device and then there's going to be a subscription fee for the LTE
Connectivity associate
It's going to be
At its lower-end
$5
No idea how high that
No I think this is actually really
Cool device
Mostly because I like getting my car data
And also be
Because I like the idea of having a camera in my car
Car that can turn on when something happens around it so late
I want to test it because unlike someone
Right I agree I think that's the
Most attractive
Here to this product
Plug-in modules that you can just get your car data today without module for a hundred bucks
Data coming everyday on my efficiency
See if somebody thing me when I'm parked or something like that I like the idea that
Are you going to pull the trigger unless you were actually look
You know I don't know about the T-Mobile syncup Drive
Yes I am
So I actually stumbled upon the syncup drive from T-Mobile
I noticed that this is not April OBD plugin module for car
Arsenal to check to make sure your car is
Actually compatible with my phone is not I was shocked to see that so all of our other cars are
Same thing it's a breeder that diagnoses vehicle issues
And so on other things as LTE built-in
You will pay for a 2 GB data plan per month for this and that lets you turn your car into a hotspot for
Idevices again to share
I don't need that aspect of it
The device itself also includes with the to get you get roadside assistance
Vehicle and
A support service from Allstate Motor Club so that's included in your monthly fee
It's only $2
A month
For 24 months for the data plan that includes the roadside assistance as well as all the time
Getting an app on your car
I think that's a heck of a deal
I don't think I've ever used
Nice piece of mind for people who don't have Roadside Assistance
So they have
It's the same sort of thing
Roadside assistance
Different
It is a subscription starting at like 10 bucks to Fifteen bucks
Plus that Verizon activation fee
Just makes me want
And then there's like a $30 and
So wow
That sounds like a smoke
Alright guys so connect your cars
No
A crazy light bulb because it's been a long time since I've talked about lights
This guy is worth talking about this is the he light
It is a Kickstarter project
And this is a smart bulb that does two things
It listens to you
And then to
It has easy pre-programmed
Including things like Halloween
Because it's October
Makes it close
Flickers into
Astro be effective
A spooky flickering can
And my
Personal favorite which is
The romantic
Witches
A pink
Elsa coming
So I think this is cool but I kind of
Freak out
Why because it listens to everything that you just got to pounce it
Azure making noise
Slickers from
One kind of pink to a stronger type of
FaceTime
Which
Curtains
I don't know I personally would not but I think it's an interesting
Melding of
A different type of sensor you don't
Often have with a lightbulb right you don't typically have sound
Is the trigger
A candlelight mode and then you can actually blow on the light
Just like a candle and it will cure your breath in
Shut up like a regular Candlewood if you've got
The music playing it can
Colors and whatnot.
Shoe People
It's not as interactive right this is
Cuz you got to use your smarts
The sound 2
Music translations
On your smartphone
Your smartphone has to be
So this would be smartphone free because the sound module is built into the bowl itself
Crazy sensors in
Bucks
Oh that's that really
So that really 60 bucks for three bulbs problem
More realistic pricing is going to be
No that's that's still not realistic
Now the 3-pack it looks like the estimated retail price of a 117 or roughly $40 of
Color changing
Yeah Usher assassin
Some of this is also
Really interesting so it looks like his blue toothpaste
Because
You actually it doesn't have a hug when you change the bulbs color you're doing it by sound
I'm not says without Bluetooth Wi-Fi
You can do it with or without from what I can see
It isn't
I'd be curious to see
If I had watching a movie or something
There's like a door makes a like a movie mood
Kind of like what she was dumb a certain television shows I remember I didn't have Hue bulbs at the time but I was watching some things on
Syfy
Change the lights in your room to match the scene
And all that
That would be a cool mode I don't see it
You know she was actually doing that they have a hue entertainment features and they're working
With entertainment companies
By providing them
STK
And
It will actually allow
Companies to
Basically created
Surround sound for
I don't know what entertainment company is
Yeah let's make that have
I will admit that I watch Sharknado
Set the Hue Lights on and it made it like that much
So when that was in the water
My lights would turn
Red
Which I was like
Yeah
My other favorite
Was when it was thundering and
Lights with strobe
What article
Wasn't cheesy
Oh yes
Did it work with the movie
Definitely
They also did it with us Syfy channel
The show that was actually much less
I don't recall which it show I was watching on Syfy
Syfy
You can possibly look for it
So cool Kickstarter
Fun lights
Let's talk about
Passive information collection
Because
I don't we love that
So there's a company that just launched this week called clue
It's clear with a k
And for the Apple watch
This software
Magic
It
Isn't all software Magic
Software is Magic
This one's especially Magic
So these algorithms
Basically detect the Motions of your hand
And use that to determine
You're eating
If you're drinking and slightly more specific
Versus
Cutting steak
Braces
Reading Eggs
Super sandwich
So I can tell those kind of things that also tell based on how you're holding the glass if you're drinking
Water or
Grant
Kevin
Kevin and six-year-olds everywhere
Using a straw
It's my juice box
So I thought this was
Cool because I love that ideas
Having something at the ideas that would promote mindfulness around
It's less about calorie count
You can get
You know you can't log exact foods but you can get a sense of life
Wow you know what you eat a lot of food
It can also
Act
To vibrate
You're sitting there eating tortilla chips
What else does this but you know you just got
Reaching the bag
Yep during football games
Yashow she didn't want that to happen
I could tell you you like by the way you're still eating
You like oh so I am
This is an interesting Twist on like behavior modification
It reminds me of some of the early SmartWatches that would just eat
Text what
Exercise you're doing or some really intelligent algorithms
Detectamet doing a push-up
You're doing it maybe you shouldn't be doing it as much
I think it's a very interesting concept because
And see what I can find out about it
Excellent well I will say I'm a little worried about it
Not because of
This particular thing I have no
Problems and I talked to the CEO and she is wonderful and she is like
It stays with us when
Elsewhere
Your data
I look at this and I'm like
My hands
And you know some things I don't know if I want
People to know about
You know I don't know if I want that logged forever and software somewhere
Think about what you do with your hands
Every year it's a good point and it brings me back to the not-so-long-ago episode of
People are the police using data from
President Echo
Or a Fitbit
To determine
If somebody
I've been home when their spouse have been killed and so on
I mean that's just more data that could be used
Against you not that I'm saying
People are worried about that
Inherently good
You're right that's the tricky sticky
Situation Sticky Wicket
Latest hits
So that's that
I
Just throwing it out there but
Transiting about here privacy
So software running on
Like an app model for
Wearables cuz that's kind of what this week
Depends on
And then three
Passive data collection
Switch
As ye
And also can
I will also say
Before I move off
Devices
Too much I ordered the Amazon Echo Plus with
That will arrive
October 31st
Which is a Tuesday you guys which means
The first podcast in November
We can be
Works I'm dying to know how and what it works with
Me too
Will let you know
All right
Driverless Tech
So this is just a quick news item because we know the alphabet has its way more division for self-driving cars information says that
So is getting ready to bring driverless taxis
Resume actually in Arizona
Specifically I think they're looking at the Chandler area which is a southern suburb of
Phoenix they're having some issues right now
In that the cars are struggling with left
Turns and not every intersection has the left
Yeah gonna make it
Obviously I've always made it but you never know
So they're looking at doing this in the Phoenix suburb
Actually saw these
When I was out in Scottsdale Arizona and back twice in one day I saw
Self-driving waymo car
We're at visiting ASU so they've been trying this for a while and
Arizona's pretty light on regulations with self-driving cars
Testing and
I guess implementing an actual business model
Taxi so I'm sure the Lyft and Uber drivers are not happy
Because they won't be needed
It'll be interesting to see if people actually take WeMo up on these when they don't become available in the very near future
I would
Yep
Courseware are freaks
I mean if we think about what we've done to our houses
Just by virtue of
We're out there
All right
Let's take
A voicemail from RI
Kevin
You want to share that number with everybody
Absolutely please call us with your questions or comments leave a voicemail at
623-7424
Unless you're coming as Stacy
Cuz I'm just not
I leave that one all the time she just delete it so don't bother
Kevin Kevin
So this week
We have a question
From Charles
Sacramento about
Hey Stacy and Kevin
Charleston Sacramento it's okay to use my message
On the podcast
Thanks again
For this wonderful podcast
You guys make
And the one question I had is
Withhold
Switches
Are all home get approved
Controllable when you're away from
From the house
Thanks for
Taking the question
And have a wonderful day
Oh alright Charles this is a great question I bet a lot of people wonder this
And the answer is
Remote access to any homekit
Devices
You have to have one
Thanks either
An Apple TV
Or an Apple iPad
And I think it has to be running what does it have to run Kevin
IOS 10.3 or later
On an iPad
I do not know what the Apple TV version is but I do know that the Apple TV must be
Duration
Better
Which is the most recent one
So you have to have one of those things you also have to enable in this is actually where I got tripped up at first on my
Annotation iCloud
The kitchen
And you
For example
The iPads are using as somebody else's iPad your going to have to
So
That iPad
Can talk to
Like your device
So that's a little wrinkled are once you get all that set up though
It works like a charm
And
You probably don't want this to be an iPad that your
Your kids play with
Because
You have to leave it on all the time and you're going to want to leave it plugged in most of the time
Obviously, Apple TV is for most people
What purpose would be plugged in all the time it might be in sleep mode but it's still on for all intensive purposes
If you shut it off and that's your gateway to your home kit
You can't remotely access because the Gateway is effectively down so you can leave that iPad
Yeah
So this is all done through the iCloud
Account
That's what ties all this together
And then again yes iPad must be powered on
All right so suggest about switches I just thought I'd throw in a
Couple quick switches so because
I have tested mosto
Thought
So if you're going to do a home kit
Installation
Want to swap out some switches I still love
Lutron
They have a bridge can
The bridge
It's 80 bucks
Turn on the switches which are
I think they're perfect r65
Are between 65 to 10
And if you can buy some
So that's my
Favorite but if you hate the Hub
Which people do
Spell. Oeave
Oak snake
Switch it is only on off it is not a dimmer
Lutron that is $50
Actually works with Bluetooth
Capacitive touch screen I tested it
I found it a little
There was sometimes
Possibly because
Bluetooth
All in all I thought it was beautiful it was very pretty
And it were
So that's that
Idevices makes a dimmer
Or a switch so you could buy either on or off
Where the dimmer functionality for a hundred bucks I haven't helped
But I devices is worth noting because they have a Bluetooth based
Kemper remote switch that you can actually use
Three way
Lights
I don't think anybody else can use theirs for 3
So keep that in mind there and then Levitan
Makes a Decora iOS switch that you
That's actually $50 for the gym
I think it's 65 for
I don't love
Without switch
It's
Kind of feels sticky when you toggle it and then the dimming function
Is a tiny little knob on the side that
Just doesn't do it
Switch ratings
I have not tried any homekit switches although based on
Charles is questioning
Probably should so I can
Do that
Go grab ones I think the Leviton Maybe
I'll send you something
Okay okay
That is the news this
Weak but stay tuned
Because
Yodit Stanton
Talking about
How to build out a scalable sensor Network
A lot of these things felt
How do I common sense but there were a couple of them
I would have thought of that
Before that you have a message for this week sponsor Qualcomm
Hey everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with the message from our sponsor this week
Welcome and I have Raj talluri Whois
What's the SVP
And GM of iot at Qualcomm
How to talk to us about the edge
And AI
Rush
What is
Edge
Post NC weather industry hasn't quite
Definition of the edge easiest way to think about it is the counterpart to the
Cloud this is Canada last box on the last
Do I spell the internet terminates in your house on an officer
And we
Typically referred to Edge computing
As a price
Testing and Analysis that's done on this last
Devices so that they're much closer to where the sensor
What are the benefits of Edgecomb
What is Qualcomm doing there
What's the benefits of computing something at the edges
You know when you have a product that's connect
Think of the clouds
You can't usually wait
For a long time
Information to the go to the cloud and come back
Turn your computer on the edge
You know you got much shorter later
How to make X users don't want to send all the information to the clouds like for example if you had a camera that's in your house
Depressing locally and not send all that with you in for
Back into the clouds that's another advantage of crossing a ditch
And lastly it reduces
The total cost
Because sometimes starting all this video and I don't
Information on the cloud cost a lot of
What is qualcomm's roll
Easter think ahead of this kind of problems and make
Chips that have a lot of processing can really in them
So that we can do things like artificial intelligence and machine learning and
Camouflage
On this Edge devices
So the customers can take advantage of
Can you maybe give me an example of a consumer product
That uses Edge computer
Yes I recently one of our customers Nest launch
The camera and discounted Ugg a lot of Frost
Sing at the edge
For example
Discount on looks for things like motion listens to
It just sounds like a crash up a window breaking I think like that
And then
You know you sent a message back with another 20
Things happen also
It's going to look nice
If your family members are the ones that came with your house then it doesn't send you an alert what's this someone who's not
Houston to San Diego
Daddy's doing a lot of process
Sitting at the edge
Do give intelligent
This sounds great so we're can listeners learn more and get started using caulk
Sportage computer
Go to qualcomm.com Coyote and get a lot more information about Edge computing
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Yodit Stanton
Cheap CEO and founder of open sensors
She is amazed
Thank you so much for coming on the show this week
Thank you Stacey tramvai senior honors
I am super pumped
So
You are here this week
Because
You have built actual sensor Networks
Know how to do this
Tell us a little bit about your history
Yeah sure is so
I guess my history
Music careers
Muslim time
Manchester United
Came from.
What happens when the whole everything physical
Has been around for about three years
Started as
Pretty much a community project
I started publishing
Name of thing in an organization in business
So we kind of came
From the environment
Need nowadays we focus on helping people to Troy
Manage
Switches
Start
Category
Buildings mostly
A bit about what you guys do
What you've learned
Deploying sensors and environmental
Air quality sensors in buildings
Play all kinds of
You have said if someone calls you hey
Give me a price
Is customer
Prayer for us
Talk to me about what you're trying to
To get to when someone calls you up
How should people be
Be thinking
About
There's a lot of hype and froth around.
It is very cool
But when you're investing rs 50000
You know what that has to be clear
What are you going to do what is the value of thought
Even like $10 percent
And this year investing people kind of stupid
That's not a trivial thing
To do
First question is actually like what is about
How does that change what you do now so beautiful commercial projects is really like how does it make
Ferocity how does it make you more efficient and I think there's a lot of inefficiency
That are hot
And the physical world
Trade-offs Roi
So the second question is do you really need
People have some other dataset
The weather information can we use that exist Within
And then layer the sensor data over
Business
You know it doesn't really make sense
Always keep the train
Infrastructure
Can you give me an example of something
So wooden buildings
Already some sort of
Temperature sensor
Actually happened instruments
You see what happened
Maybe the landlord has access to it
They might have life
When people come in and out and so this already
I'm making a little bit of
Supplementing What's missing
With the sensors
Is probably like
The right thing
So it sounds like so far first I need to clear
Yusuke Circle
Then I've got to think about
What resources
Already have
4M like
Yes
And then when you read it
Actually like thing around
Like one small control site
Just a few sensors
Initially we tested
Sui generis
Depakote to walk across it
He's such a huge deal
Verifying
The information
With five sensors 10 sensors or whatever saves you so much headache
Because that's so everyone
I'm going to test elasticsearch
Cats cats cats
Testing
Independently
Verifying
Do you do that to expect my consultant
Firing someone
We do that a lot
So there is
A number of
Things we test
One is the data quality like
Another
The difference of your testing weather
Is sampling
Parts per billion
Doing obvious changes
People breathe on a air quality
And you see the CO2 readings go up and so forth
Is not like a defined way because they're so many variables for the day
One thing she's next
Does it say
In terms of if it's like Nora certified
Or Plainville organic
Does it actually perform in the way that you expect
Does a join in a correct way
You know what happens when
Gateway goes down
Because this matters because
To go down and then there's other stuff which is a little bit more nebulous around
Battery life
So does it it's a real
Live performance
Kind of confirming the specs versus the
Let's talk about this
Concept of scale
Because
People don't
I feel like people are like
How many sensors can I put on a single Gateway soda
But they don't think about it
The boring stuff
What configuration management
So let's talk about
Even something as simple as
The Personnel cost
Flying sensors
When we start talking about operating the sort of
Infrastructure at scale
How should we think
There's two sides does the deployment cost
Of the personal and the maintenance cost like how much is it going to cost me and how many times do I have to get the battery change
You know in a given year
What we had
To do
Training programs for
Facilities manager
3D abstract away the
So our aim is to get the sensor install time
Down to
Around 30 seconds
And I think
The last assignment we got to round 20 seconds but I'm not
Counting my chickens
Somebody's going to have to physically take a Gateway put it all
Way to know at work
Because they're not
Software engineer
That are going to be the joint
Support
And training
Software
The people need to know this kind of
Make these projects
Because myself eating house like the health and safety certificates to be able to go up on a roof
But I think
The IRT from my perspective is going to be much more operational facing them
So you really need to be able to
The operations guys your friend
Deployment size
And it's a lot of detail
So we have to upload things like the drawings in the schematics of build
Next
If you don't know if a sensor is
Go badly wrong
Moschino that needs device ID once in a particular corner
The interface is that
Triple-A batteries
Country Queen to Real by through other than people trying to figure out
Clients are getting
Looks like PCS on phones in my mind
Expense because who hasn't run around their house at like 6 in the morning are actually more like 2 in the
Are smoke detectors going off and they're like
Standing in front of one going at this one
CNN
Going to the next one until you find it
Celtic Women in a giant building with sensors
Need a battery check
Where can I find this
Let me just look it up
Rather ideally when I get a notification of a battery go
It's like
It's this one right
Right ear and then think of this scale
Where it's usually not going to be in one
Location is going to be most of our clients have multiple kind of in different countries
So really challenging
Maintenance
It is that custom
For every client because that feels like
Seeing a scale that
For any of this just
Can't scale yet
Because it's just
It's too custom
I mean that's all we had
The decisions that we made around what problems do we end up solving
Rainy drawings
Dockside
How to do stuffed crust
Because
The cost just goes out of
Also
You know we focus on buildings asset mantri environment
You know how to do this
In a repeatable way
That's for me the realization.
A lot of variety players are going to
Define themselves
Just pick a vertical
Make it work without vertical
We know exactly what to do
Boiler Room
Factory
Northam Healthcare application or widen of the other million and one things that people are doing
So where can you stay
Let's think about
Like what kind of Technology
Have you guys develops
Actually helps you streamline
What matters for
Making these
Hundreds of sensors
Thousands
It's really been about
The deployment
Maintenance
So I mean
What the Ensign ends up saying is
Considerations in analytics and they're like
The effort
That we put in around
Maintenance
Because
It is just me or even for
End up doing 20
Really hard tonight
When you got so many moving
And so we've taken
Should be people that have
Deployed you know these
The old phones and PCs
The 90s and early 2000s
Super streamline
We need the drawings in the schematics of
The floor and we're going to kind of Sanju
Set register's office
The project is done
Life
Because that status information you should be able to look at
Battery status
That's integrated into your slide
Or you're going to hell
Comes from experience
Because I need to head line items for iot
Super hard
Let's talk about
Who is going to be doing this and there's two reason
You mention this is operational
Operationally focused
But then there's also the concept of how to
Network and security sensors that
Becomes maybe relevant
Pick 4 SC
Or anxiety side so I'm very curious
How we should be thinking about Mary
Those two things
Yeah for sure so funny stories in the early days
Using kind of short-range rf4 stuff that connects to the
What we had was
What is
Like are you serious you want to have like
1000 sensors
Connect to the human network does not never going to
So it has been
Interlock
At least four 2017 something like 60 or 70%
So what Laura gives yuan standalone
Gateway has a
We have furniture
A couple of tacos
Remotely manage the Gateway
Defense
So that's kind of a private Network.
Basic workouts
Everything else
Probably much more
Common
Now you might have
A situation where the sensors talk to some monitors
Laura net worth
Fox network Whatever Bud like you know you can have the human hour
These sensors cuz security
It's just a nightmare
I suppose built-in security
Makes sense
Keys and all that kind of stuff so you can
Elise
Take steps to war
It is secure
Well even if you've created the separate
Network so it might be Laura it could be a season
All your devices eventually something
Costume
Talk to it
Information has to hop from one network to another and maybe it's over
Gold and that's more secure
Kind of seems like
That's going to be a really interesting area
Pay attention to
Yes
Perspective I think the way I look at
Securities
A friend of mine
Describes
The way she describes it as you look at security
There's mold
The different elements
The layer between
The unnoticed the sensor to the Gateway and that would be appropriate security like for fedora
You'll have more than one day
And then you have stayed over between
Gateway's for example
Those gateways behind
And then
There's a security from the gateway to
One appropriate
Suppose that industry wire Industries not having
The conversations of
The best practice
Just because I see people doing
Funny things
Approach to security
Could these layers are correlated are they industry-related are they
Sensor
The way I look at it is
Sofa Laura for example where so their teeth
And you're not necessarily Reinventing
Create like the running joke
Somebody trying to roll their own crypto wishes
AB really bother
There is a consideration of
You know how much memory is done this
Like what is the
Worst-case.
Maybe they can get
Access to
Doxycycline
Answers I mean
Access to the
Then on the Gateway level is again
What is atopy
In your mind
Architect sing Against what is possible
And how people are going to
Lesser interfere with it
Alissa Hopkins
More sensitive it is
Put in a lot more effort around
Tamper proofing like people can manually touch it
Is Larry's but it was appropriate there is based of what is going to be gone
Security stocks I can cover all these use cases
What's a wearable just very different
Architecture
Because
People just one
That's a bracelet or something
To a very dumb sensor last
10 to $20
Thank you so much for coming on the show this week thank you very much
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Yes please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com thanks for listening and we'll see
See you next week