We would welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is the July 4th week Edition
This is your host Stacy
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
This week we're going to be talking about the Amazon show
Myra
Reportedly building its own Amazon Echo
Google home has wrote last week
We got a discount
Iot executive
Low power
Everytime boy
We also have two other reviews for you
Are you talking about
Kevin's brand new purchase
MMA News
Which iot is changed
Case in point
Today
We're going to have a guest segment with fahri Diner who is the CEO of Wireless about Wi-Fi
This is made possible by Schlage
Who salutes the innovators of the internet
Dunton done as you guess they are
One of our sponsors for this week
With our second sponsor being
Affiliated monitoring
So let's hear from them
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about Affiliated monitoring in respond
Cons to a trigger from any connected device Affiliated to professionally trained live agents can follow protocol and reach out to
Are customers and local emergency services Affiliated works with
Hundreds of smart home security help and other iot businesses
Is it Affiliated. Com coyote Derita case study on how they helped a connected car start
Turn idea into a thriving business with a 100 million dollar exit that's affiliated
Dot-com iot
Okay Kevin
Let's talk about the Amazon Echo Show
Before we do that
How much caffeine have you had today
You're singing your dance and I can't see you but I know your Bebop and everywhere
Hear it cuz my chair squeaks so that's that's
What's happening I'm glad I have not had a lot of
Surprisingly
But you do have an Amazon show and I do not
I did see if you had we could be doing this
On the show
That's actually
Good reason not to have a show
The Amazon Echo Show it came out it was delivered on June 28th to anybody who pre-ordered the
Device this is a
Amazon Echo so mad amazed inside
And
It is a 7in touch screen
On this
Funky bass
Is it is not the most appealing
Looking design
Out there
And we'll talk about a little bit more on that in a second
It cost $229
You can get $100
Offer to buy to go correct
Yes
And
That's why I titled the show what I titled it which is the Amazon
Michelle makes me feel so lonely
Because it does
Because I have one
And the biggest problem with the Echo Show
Is that
It's really freaking hard to call people
It's hard to find your friends
It's hard like
I've only got out of all of my contacts
Tax
I think I have 10 people I can
Another was our people who have a show or who have an echo because I know you and I have had a voice call
Those are people who
Who have
Actually it's an echo it's the whole Echo interface but I don't mind not being it
Caucus
Could I call you
Skype
Google Hangouts
I sent you a postcard
Yes all of these options are available to
But I can't I can't just drop it on you
So so let's talk about
How this work
Show with the Echo Show I can do to differ
If someone else has an
An Echo Show
I can
Call them
We would essentially have a video call
It looks nice it works really well actually
Or
If we're really good friends are like your parents or something like that
You can actually drop in
You can
Label someone is being okay in your contacts list to drop in and then they can call you
Any point in time in the actually
They can do this from
Madam ASAP
On the phone too
Kevin you could actually if I if I said it was okay
From Madame ASAP
Youku
Call me on the show
We could do a video call Ashley
To show
That's funny you say that because I was actually in the app as you were described as Mike I bet you I can
Have a video call with the phone and I could
Yes
Or if I said
It's okay for
Kevin
To drop in on the show
Kevin could actually just use that drop in function
Pinterest
What happens then
Is
He would
Actually start seeing
Right away he would see a blurred version
Busy typing
Eventually it comes clear and clear
So this is time for you to put on your shirt if you're dating
Then suddenly would be like
And
We can talk video conference hands-free
Gotcha
Okay
Tell a couple things
Amazon
Pics the people in your contacts it ask for permission when you give it permission to look at the people in your
It's going to look for the people in your contacts 12
Phone number that's registered with
Amazon
If that is the same number registered with the
Echo
Or there a account
Then you'll see their name
Gotcha
So it's like it's your mom
The Amazon account is in your dad's name
You're going to have to have him
He'll beer
Pssi telephone number essentially
Yes in the phone number that they registered their Echo devices
Weather
Padme stuff
Amazon
Okay
So that's
That's one so it's really not easy
To connect
It's not as simple as sending out like an email in
And my mom is like to have one of these and she's I can't be just talk on Duo
I was like okay fine
Hide and then she's like I don't want Google to have
Have my phone number
No no no I don't want to talk into
So we're going to Skype
Stacy I don't want to talk to you anymore
Tall
And that's what my mom and I are no longer talking
So some other things about the echo
The show doesn't have the capabilities you want
I'm just going to say this to be
Totally real
The potential is really there in like doing things like
You can tie it to some of your video cameras
I wanted to tie it to my August doorbell
But so far that doesn't seem to be working for me I'm not sure why
Cuz I would like to be like hey
Animated show me my doorbell
Which cool feature
I'm you can also if it's linked into like
It's temperature sensors inside you can paint show me the indoor temperature
Edible show you that it
It's nice for features like the weather cuz you can see the
It is also nice for Amazon Prime this is a use case I didn't really think about that my daughter and I were
It's my show is in the kitchen
The other thing is
We put
The original Echo
Away from her
The kitchen at used to be in the kitchen and now it's not
But
The show is not as good
For two reasons one
You can't tell
If the screen is not facing you you don't know if it's
There's no light indicator of any kind not on top of it
In into
I don't want their Mike's all around but when it's not facing me
It doesn't seem to hear
So it's hearing seems to be a little bit in
Compared to the rake
And this is an exact same position
The other one was
Right I think the original Echo has zika 7 array microphone
Or 7 microphone array I should say I don't know what the
Show house but they are far field mics
So it was It was kind of surprising to us
So keep that in mind
And then
The scream can be a distraction
Cuz as long as it thinks you're there
It's showing you stuff it shows you
They're not actually ads
All the time there's like trending topics but they sometimes could be an ad
Also something.
Consider I like the fact that shows me the weather all the time
You can use it to show
Photos if they're stored in your
Amazon
Photo account
Apparently is a thing
Yeah it is an and I believe I got an email
Maybe 2 weeks ago that Amazon was getting rid of the lower-tier very inexpensive
Storage for photos and they're going to bump everybody up
With a higher-priced larger
Tierce I don't know if people are aware that or not but
Yeah
But you can also put
Some photos
In there in into I think the app to show is like you
Your home screen
I did that with a photo
It was granted it was a photo that I pulled from WhatsApp
It did not cover the whole screen
I don't know if it wasn't high enough resolution cuz I pull
Pull it from WhatsApp
It is just keep picture
Vacation
But could be but also that that touchscreen is actually I believe a lower resolution than one might think
1024x600 it's not even a 720P
Yeah so like some people I had read their lie
Watching videos on it and like you don't want to watch videos on this really
For any length of time you can watch a movie on it
Maybe a YouTube video with a recipe or something but not
Something detailed
And that gets me to recipes
And yesterday I was making
A really complicated
Recipe so
I actually pulled up it only pulls recipes for
Allrecipes
I wish I wish I could pull up the web on the
Now so when I pulled up all recipe skills
Basically I would
I was looking for a Cajun spice
Snakes eyes like
Show me recipes for
Cajun spice
And it pulled up a whole bunch
And I picked one and you can either pick up with your finger
Scroll through and pick up with your finger or you could say choose number 9
We totally hands-free
I was like okay show me ingredient
Show me the ingredients
But after about a minute
Outright
It stopped
It was like if you want to see
The steps
Continue
And it's a Spaceman
So I didn't say anything
Go back
But I had to do the search again
For the recipes I wanted it to stay longer because
I wanted to stay until I tell it to go
Because that's all right
Could be alone
I don't know if there is a setting in
The app for that
Terms of going back like the home screen or something that's possibility
I don't know
But I totally agree that wouldn't want that to go away on me
I would think it's got an it's got a camera obviously so I would think if
You're still standing in front of it working your
You know spice mixing whatever
It knows
You're there
It does
It's just kind of like
Not to backtrack on the the device actually does have an 8 microphone array
What
It doesn't sound the top
Under 3 hardware buttons on the top of the
And it's that
Ring of dots at
Elliptical ring of dots around those three buttons that's where they microphones are
Exact same space
My other Echo
So
Not good
It does sound better though
I was just going to say it's got two speakers since the first Echo device has two speakers I would suspect
Bellatrix handled better
It does
Okay so that I felt like there was one other thing I wanted to go
How do you say I watch videos on it so it's right there at the
How do I get a breakfast bar that we have in the kitchen
My daughter and I were watching
Amazon
Cuz we're Amazon Prime subscriber
Possibly obviously
We were just sitting there a breakfast ghetto paging through videos and and watching trailers for movies to see what
Where can I watch tonight
Lights out
That was actually kind of a neat
I don't know if I can
Check that out why didn't we
Why didn't we watch our usual
Okay so that's the show I would say
It is not a need to have device
The coolest thing is probably video calling but there's no one to call
Everything in the first fax machine
Exactly what I feel
But but but but I remember when the original Echo came out
I felt the exact same way there's not enough here to make us I must have it wasn't until
46 months later
That Services became available
Psychic reading things for it
Then I'm like oh I got to have it
Now I have four of them so
I give it time I think you know I think what you're saying is probably accurate maybe now it's not a must have but how long until it becomes
True and
Like if you have a video camera that works with this thing it would be great for you
Show me what's happening upstairs
You'll be able to see
That's the show
Alright
Alibaba
Reportedly planning to challenge Amazon Echo
Not much detail here but that's what they're planning according to the Wall Street Journal and the information
It's at possibly as soon as next
Week which would actually be this week based on when this article was written
So
MN
How many people we have in China listening to show but good for them
Is
I'm assuming that
Google home is certainly not available in China
I'm assuming Amazon echos aren't available in China in either but that's a guess it's going to make an Amazon Echo
Bike
Anna story
Man whatever happened to xiaomi
Remember
It was coming on strong without weather
It was as me line of Smart Home Products they had all kinds of stuff and
And they were the big thing last year and I don't think it's a yes I saw
I know it will also mention its article is Baidu
Which is a big
Rival in China and apparently they launched their own voice controlled home robot
Call Little Fish
Which is interesting back in April
Yeah
I like the name but I
Is it or is it what it what is
I don't like it says it includes a tablet screen so you can
Turn searches order food play music and movies
So
May 2nd show
Without
Alright also in a personal assistant
Smorgasbord
Google home
Is rolling out bluetooth a little earlier than
Well
There's nothing official from Google saying this is rolling out yet however at Google IO back in may they did say Bluetooth stream
Available on Google home
And
Because
A lot of the Music Services I use are available on my Google home so which one of the reason I didn't buy one
But if I get Bluetooth streaming
I can imagine
Stream something from my phone to the Google home like any other Bluetooth speakers so that's that's a bonus I think
Did you can still cast
Things but it has to have
The opposite house
Support for
Tom Cassell casting
Yeah and
This is also something we talked about cuz it was in the Android AP
BK
Correct
Some people were seeing speakers
They were seeing access to some of their Bluetooth speakers
It was not an option
What's happening yeah they must have gotten
They that firmware update I'm sorry that the software update for the Google home app a little bit early or it's just being rolled out
Gradually my check ready for the show I don't have the update yet so
I cannot either
Yasso
Well maybe this week will hear something official
News is out there
Wouldn't surprise me if schools
If it got it ready just says yet
We have two kids coming this week
Eventually go up
For what it's worth
All right
Bad news
Pearl
I can't believe it in Taipei
Does last week cuz it did
My bad
So Pearl
Backup Vision Care
Rear vision camera
This was a company of Engineers from
Former Apple dictionary
Camera
And they
Have decided
2 shutter door
Yeah then raised about 15 million dollars in VC funding the backup cameras integrated into it like a license plate
White frame
And I guess
It was a good idea but not a good idea
The ship now we've been a good idea to ship 3 or 4 years ago but they only found themselves in 2014
Selling it for $500
And
Correct me if I'm wrong that you would output the video camera to your connected phone
Yeah so it's not like a building solution which at this point
Most car makers are already integrating an
And why is that Stacy
Because
The National Highway
Castration says that my
2018 all new cars sold in the US have to have
Instant killer for pearl
People's old cars but a lot of people with old cars probably are not spending $500 on
No I mean
I said this right before the show if this was like
5199 maybe 249 solution
It wouldn't have some traction but
Not as $500
Very sad that they actually were there apparently were some offers to act
Acquire them
An act
Higher
Not enough choir
They didn't want to be
We'll probably see some other cool stuff
So
That's what you know
This is what we're going to see this is going to be the year of a positions in the space especially in the connector
Kind of consumer Orient
Space
End
Deaths
There's no other
All right
Which is a low-power wide area network
Dedicated Networks
The Internet of Things
Long long distances
Cheap cheap pricing
So this is ingenue which
Actually
Was formed by some former Telecom
Some guys
This is John Horn who
Joined ingenue in 2015
The company actually used to be on
And Horn used to be the director of
Machine-to-machine services at
Mytmobile
Basically this guy is out
My hunches in this is reporting from fiercewireless by
This is State they figure this out so good on them
This is going to we're going to see this happen we're about to see a consolidation in
The space because I think
Sigfox ingenue
There's Laura that's in the space now Laura is in a company that's
Smartstandard there's something but he's like Comcast is working with Laura
Other startups are working with Laura
What we're going to see here is
Increasing pressure from the cellular guys that are
Creating these nb-iot in LTE cat 1M
Basically
Cellular guys are creating their own
And so
There's a number of reasons why pregnancy pressure but I think the biggest thing we'll see is a bifurcation between
Cellular networks and then
Things like lore
That's my hunch so
Sigfox should be kind of worried
Ingenue
Also should be worried
So we'll see what happens
And related to this I just read this morning that one of the carriers
Vodafone New Zealand
Aveda playing a narrowband or NB iot Network really next year
Crosman Zealand they done some testing already there and do some more testing with some customers later this year but then
Phone network rollout
Next year is what they're saying
And you know any of our listeners have this
Of where the stuff is out so in the US Verizon and AT&T are doing MBA.
Works and they're supposed to be out
Next year
I kind of been like
Really really are they really coming out
Cuz they all started actually pushing the cat one in which are a little bit more band
Out first but
I don't see a lot of
Fat people clamoring to
To use those just yet and I think the pricing still needs to kind of come into
Come into the picture
That's a lot of like
Well we don't know
But
We're see it the way things are coming
I would agree
Now
Kevin
Yes a rare purchase I haven't bought any iot stuff
Well took my Google home but
This was some kind of crazy
But I ended up buying
A Home Security Suite as it's called from gocontrol
And it contains one
Passive IR motion detector
And two door or window sensors
Kerstetter magnetic
And
Most people would buy them for what's in the name security
I didn't buy these for security however
I actually bought these
To have automatic lights go on when you open or close a door
A closet for example because of my bedroom closet we have that wink relay just outside of it and actually turned a dumb light in the closet
Smart light as a result
And every morning around 5:30 a.m. I
Kind of hear my wife I'm still in bed I hear my wife no going getting ready taking a shower
Then she goes to the closet
And then I hear her
Quietly cursing so she doesn't wake me and I'm giggling under the covers because
She presses the wink relay so hard that it kind of comes unconnected and then she can't turn the light on
In the closet
And I think
I know what's worse is that it's been giggling about it for 6 months now
I decided to research
What works is my wink Hub that way
Solve this problem so to speak
I can turn the wink relay switch on the promise no
Where to present where not to but that's only the store
And I thought about magnetic connectors and sure enough the gocontrol Home Security Suite
Does work with wink
Arrived just this morning but it's so easy to pair with the Hub and so easy to set up a quick robot
Master 2 robots one for the door opening to turn the light on and one for the door closing to turn the light off
That
I was already able to install it be just
Breaking for the shelves
Working great which comes off rotation got to be thrilled
I'm going to mention that when I researched this
On Amazon I saw one of these motion I'm sorry Wendy's door window sensors for like $35 a month
That's expensive
But for $42
Just $7 more there was a kid with
Two sensors in the motion detector is also I sperm for that makes sense
So
Also easy to install is the infrared motion sensor witch and now have in my office
So that way as soon as I walk in
I already have a robot set up to turn the lights on
Not sure when do about turn the lights off yet
And propose to have a wink Hub instead of robots
You don't have to have the running 7 by 24 like it when I walk in my office in the middle of the day I don't want the light on
There are settings in the wink robots
How to say
Do it from this time to that time
I'm so that's what I did for like Sunset to Sunrise
It will turn my lights on so
You right so far they are working right
You should be able to motion detected
Turn it off now I don't know
I don't know I kind of CSE I kind of sit still and watch TV or something on my iPad or something and I'm
I'm not moving around so I suspect at night time the White Witch shut off on me
I'd rather
Not deal with that
The exciting
Moving your hands
I'm still here I'm watching a movie
Okay well that's that's a good motion sensor
Several
Places
Motion sensor
This is actually an open close sensor that's on the
Okay answer you have another one
I'm decided yet though I don't know yet about to figure that out
Liquor cabinet
That's always open
You must have a hue motion
Sensor
Baidu
Okay
2 PSI promotion do they
Offer anything else because
I didn't realize it when I bought it but this gocontrol does
There's a temperature sensor inside but it's not at
Tied into openhab
And then open have picked up the temperature sensor
And he doesn't show it to me
But open
Will wink shows me the temperature on this motion
Sensor which is kind of nice I haven't actually another motion sensor
DigiTech temperature now in my very warm office so I might play with some robots for that to see if you had an Echo Show
You could be able to like show me the temperature inside and it'd be like
Bullet for the Wii
I don't know what that
I'll just send you pictures
Theoretically that should happen
Siri
All right
Well let's see I also have something
To tell you guys about
Because
I didn't buy it
They sent it to me and then
I sent it back and I bought one
Is it was already installed
Long story short I have a Leviton
Wi-Fi
Decora switch this is a
$50 light switch on
And it talks to the Amazon Echo without a hub it also talks to
The
Yes
And
I wanted to like this lights which I really did
Because I'm a sucker for smart switches and
It's not hard to install it's not hard to hook it up
What it is hard to do is turn the freaking light on
I hate that
Isn't that kind of a
Primary purpose of it
Exactly so you only have one job switch
End of the dimming switches this little
Dimmer on the side that's not an uncommon design even for none can
But I didn't like it
I hated it
I don't like touching this light
So
I feel that as a connected product it is
Fine
It works
What is a product that occasionally I'm going to turn on and off with
Natural fingers
I hate it
This is going to be your mileage may vary
You may love it
But I didn't it's it's not it's not that
Play sand I just
Tell kind of Dewey when you
Press it it's not it's not a click it's more like a
Cinemagic
And it's $50 so you really have to like it my pen
Come with almonds
White and other color so
You know if your
If you have other Leviton switches
You know this could be
That was that
I feel like we answered this but I'm going to answer this again for p
What did new Eero router stick
TL DR version of the says it is backwards
Compatible with your old stuff
If you have the old Eero routers
You shouldn't have to upgrade unless you're going to want
Thread Network and then you can just buy a beacon
And that it's your old system
Yes so
If you've already got the Eros
You don't need a spring for a whole new system
If you got coverage hole that you want to make better
You know by the $149 Beacon
So
Just making that Crystal Clear forever
Okay
That's a lot that was a lot for this 4th of July week
I hope you guys didn't blow up any of your appendages
Shooting out fire
And I will also
End
I think that's it we will
Have you guys stay tuned for fari
Diner who is the CEO of blue braided about Wi-Fi
Making it better next Generation Wi-Fi and business models
Get ready to love your ISP
Okay
A word from our sponsor
Schlage is proud to support the Internet of Things podcast
Cast for more than a hundred years their commitment to innovation has created smarter and safer homes around the world
Their latest generation of connected lock options
Leafy industry and safety Simplicity and style
Learn more about schleichs plans for the future of technology at home security
I finally get to futurist Rob Martin
Sun Twitter
You can find him at Schlage futurist
Schlage
Open possibilities
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
And today's guest is
Fahri Diner Who is the
CEO and co-founder of plume
Hi Siri how are you doing today
Hi Stacy
Great thank you
Excellent
So
I got to talk a lot about Wi-Fi switch is
Basically the lifeblood of
Get home
People probably no clue as the company that makes these
Plug-in pods that will improve their Wi-Fi experience
You however
Call yourselves in air traffic control
Can you kind of talk about
What you're actually trying to build with blue
WiFi pods that
We make give you awesome coverage around the home
But the key challenge is how to optimize the performance of your Wi-Fi across
Not just space
These things
Wi-Fi access points or pods
Will give you a good coverage around the home but you want to optimize your performance across time as well so you're
Wi-Fi not only has to work everywhere around the home but it also has to work all of the time and across a
Changing side of load so we think of it as more of a three-dimensional problem
And all of that requires a fairly sophisticated control at management plain and that's really the piece that
So this is the software that's in the cloud and it is
Actively managing
Network loads across my
House for exam
Also if my doorbell rings things are going to change
Is that how I should be thinking about it
Yep it deals with things there are a lot of things why are they
And Wi-Fi
Particular as you know is a non-deterministic medium unlicensed Spectrum things change
And you want to have a system that responds to these changes both dynamically in Rio
Real-time as well as preemptively and predictably
So the conclusion control plane be call it
Adaptive Wi-Fi
It deals with things like
Both Wireless and wired backhaul management and these multi-node environment so you have to worry about what the backhaul can be
Migration looks like
It deals with things like handing off client
From one pod to another in a smart algorithmic way it deals with things like interference management both in
Inside the home and across multiple
It also learns
Client and
Device behavior and patterns
To be proactive and predictive
Optimization the power of the cloud
Alright so there's a lot that's happening in
And people like myself work
Like crazy Network
Oh my gosh it's up where to find Wi-Fi
How did you come to this idea what was your core philosophy
Especially given
Your history
Clone myself
My co-founders
We are a team of
What's a telecom industry veteran
We worked on in Pioneer things like ultra-long-haul ultra-high capacity fiber-optic transport system
As well as be caught really high performance Wi-Fi into literally billions of devices
And the realization became to maybe about 3 years ago Stacy was that
Oldest digital stuff
It's piped into our homes today at a pre-trial fast and reliable and consistent rate but today what happens is older
Stop after going through a lot of fiber Networks
Kallax Networks
Etc they come to our home
Before reaching our devices in the living room something goes terribly wrong
That has to do with Wi-Fi
And also many of internet service providers
I told us
That this is a primary source of
Subscriber dissatisfaction
Leading into incoming service calls
Turn which is a very expensive problem
Bananas you know
Let's talk about that because I have peas
Have historically
Well I shouldn't say historically
Play because they've done a lot of things over the years
Important
The Wi-Fi point
Alone The Edge stopped
At the modem
And now what's happening is they seem to be interested once again
And going beyond that
Talk about
They have to because in our networking days until not long ago open Ben Meade Rudy's Network diagram
Routers and switches in fiber optic Transport Systems on the end of the network
This little picture of a cute little home
With a nice little roof on it
That was the end of the network in other words that was the
You have the Broadband Gateway if you want
In the home
Service providers are responsible for providing services to the home
What has happened now over the last
Let's say five years or so is that now they're providing services to the devices in our homes and example
Comcast is now saying what they have been saying for a while now you can watch your TV channels on your iPad
There's a little Comcast app now if you're up in the bedroom
Can you click on your app
And the Xfinity is not playing on your iPad
You have now on the right
Call Comcast
Complain you're not particularly complaining about your Wi-Fi you're just saying look Xfinity doesn't work on my iPad
Dinosaur is a service that I'm paying
If you know what I mean so
That last
Peace in the home the last 2 or 5 or 10 what have you is now whether they like it or not
An extension of their broadband
Infrastructure
Now it is just as important I might argue in so many ways that is more important than the two thousand miles of fiber.
They use to bring the Broadband to our home
Because that's the piece that the consumer is interfacing to
So this is not an option of saying
For service providers moving forward and we're seeing that
They have to own and control
The Wi-Fi peace otherwise it said it's a section in the middle of their Network
That they don't have
Visibility to and they get blamed for everything okay
So with that in mind I remember when
Wi-Fi
First started coming out
My cable provider the time was Time Warner
And they actually had a
They had a fee
4 Wi-Fi
It was I think it's like $10 extra a month for
Wi-Fi I remember looking at that
Why can just go buy a router
The Best Buy
Pop that in
Why would I pay Time Warner
Credit they do have equipment rental fees now so we'll
Cable providers seek to tack on
Additional service charges on top of
Can a better wife
I think some will
And for some
Customers
We are engaged with many of them
As you know
There will be additional fees from some of them I believe for premium go to Whole home Wi-Fi
They may also look at it
In tears if your subscribing to ex-
Or second or greater maybe your whole home Wi-Fi
Will become as part of your sex
Scripture some service providers might very well I'll sell you
Devices like pods
Google home coverage
So I believe this is an area of that they're looking at both
I would say defensively and offensively defensively in the sense that they're very interested
And they must
Highly reliable WiFi
Offensively in the case that I think the retail in the
Street has pretty much
Demonstrated
There's value in people are willing to pay
Whole-home reliable good wifi and service providers will take advantage of that
Now I believe from there isb perspective the defensive part is
Probably more important
To them
Which means when they go on the offense
And even if they were to charge you for this
I think it's going to be
Much much more affordable
To get highly reliable whole home Wi-Fi
From your ISP then
It will be to get it from the retail Channel
Imagine one of the reasons you're saying this is because you guys have this deal with Comcast this is one of your big service
Provider deals Comcast has made an investment
And they're also reselling and I think
Even helping manufacturer the
Can you kind of go into that
Pretty please
Of course Comcast is one of our service provider partners
I will be launching with them this year as well as a number of other tier-one operators
In the case of Comcast our relationship involves two element
That's one is better managing and optimizing their existing Gateway
So that is a very important
Art
The whole infrastructure here whereas when you go out to
Can you go out and buy retail access points
Everybody asks you to turn off your service provider Wi-Fi
We think that
Soulja Boy
Waste the Comcast has very good gateways
And there's a piece of Clone software in those gateways that connects it to our cloud
Amanda is an optimizer
And then we will also license
Our
Design of the pods
To our manufacturing Partners who will be able to make and sell them
Directly to service providers like,
We don't really want
To be in the middle trying to get an additional
Margin from these Hardware all in the interest
Making
The pods and access points as affordable as possible for the office for the consumer
Okay
That makes a lot of sense and it also makes sense with
Comcast and other service providers getting into
Home automation and security systems because those are definitely things where you want to be able to control the
Network all the way through
Absolutely
When it comes to retail though let's go back to that
Because there has been in the last probably three years just
Scads of new companies coming out with better
New improved WiFi
Erode securifi
Room is in there and even the big vendors of followed suit
And their focus has been on
If he's mesh net
Works
And I am curious do you think that consumers are going to go buy their own routers or do you think they're going to turn to the
The service provider
I know your
The Surface Pro
But it seems so far that consumers are turning to
Do these kind of
Off-the-shelf
Retail system
I don't think the retail
Segment will disappear
There will always be a certain portion of the consumer in my
Opinion Google buy their own routers and access points and nationalism song
Statistics
That I know
Are there in the US
About 70% of people get their Wi-Fi from their internet service provider
Places like Europe that percentage is even higher
So I believe though as the service providers get into whole home highly reliable life
Fight at retail Market segment with string
A lot of them have been launching
New services on top so for example
Eros launched a brand new service that does parental controls & Security for
$10 a month
There's scads of devices all the way from Disney Circle device that does print
Control through a box at
Attached to your network
Another security device
So I'm also looking at those and I'm like hey is that a real or is that something that's going to get eaten by the service
Is providers
I think the retail players
Who rely on Hardware margins are going to see
The price of these things become lower and lower
There are no now many players in this market and they're naturally looking for more margin
Some of these customers what companies are startups or other companies
Obviously they're in it for profit so I believe they're looking at these over-the-top additional services
Ass-kickers to improve their margins now
Problem again there I think that's a good lineup
Thinking about service
This is really the bread and butter of the service provider's whether it security or parental controls and so on that
Will all the sort of bundled into are available through your internet service providers
There is peace
Like I can't see give unless you're like in a very small
Sonic out in California
Most people find
Verizon so how do you think that might affect how people
See this shift controlling more of
Network inside their house
Everybody knows we all love to hate our service providers
And we blame the forever
You don't even if you are retail Wi-Fi doesn't work
An average consumer Bill calls offense at 11
Consumer it in a lot of times I don't even know if they don't even know the difference between tsar of your broadband and Wi-Fi and all that
Somebody says lock the internet
The phone and call wife
Call Comcast for service provider
Obviously
Discuss before the service providers are seeing this
Festival de technology
Whether it's the Silicon or the software
Etc so
I think there are many other reasons
Not be happy with our service providers but
Yavapai think Wi-Fi performance and Broadband is not going to be one of them and not system
What is the other things that I think is really fascinating about Wi-Fi as we've moved from like this
Is I don't know if
It's like a machine gun
Routers just like I'm covering the whole home by sending out message signal
To this mesh approach where you like we're going to cover the whole home by having everything kind of work together and then
You guys are taking that too late
WiFi 2.5
Actively managing it
Cloud
But I feel like like Wi-Fi 3. O was going to be
Wi-Fi embedded in just about everything
It's going to need a connection so I'm going to buy
TV and it's going to have a Wi-Fi
Repeater
Perhaps or maybe it's my cable box if it's ISP model
How do you envision that
Into the world
We want to enable it
As I mentioned plume is ultimately a control and management playing and you need something like plume to make all of that
That's been our vision from day one there are a lot of Wi-Fi resources that already exist in our home
Your TV has WiFi
If you have a Samsung family Hub refrigerator it has Wi-Fi
Your
MacBook or iMac that sitting on your desk has WiFi in it
And largely who using them as client
They don't contribute to the network
Our vision rvu is that many of these existing Wi-Fi resources that are in the home
Should not only be clients but also should be these
Repeater points are Hotpoint
Pasar Wifi to other clients
And that requires
Unified control plane and that's what is all about
We are also partnering with Samsung
I think you're familiar with this product that they launched recently
In home product that has
Really nice iot capability and also
Bestop mesh WiFi
That device will soon be powered by Klum
Where you'll be able to see let's say a Comcast
The Gateway a Samsung connect home
Access point Igloo parts
Starting point all working
Coherently on the same network
Go to the beginning of this Vision that you just
Describe an in the future we want to roll in
All these other devices
To become
A part of the network
How does it work technically
Because I know in the case of Comcast at that I have firmware
On your gateway
He could have firmware on the
Device
Hear it sounds like there may be something like that happening so are you guys going to be
Software that's going to be at any endpoint and a variety of gateways that just met
Makes this
Seamless Wifi between devices
That's right so there's a there's a piece of software in the Gateway
Your service provider Gateway
Obviously there's a piece of software firmware in r-pod
And we can also put these for my are into other access point or other wifi-enabled devices
They all talk. Cloud
And we do the coordination across them in terms of treating them as either access points or clients
I'm doing the backhaul configuration among them dealing with interference and so on all from the cloud to the cloud
Gloom cloud is the element that enables Oliver
Okay what else do you want to tell me about
I want to tell you more about how we
See the control plane right now
We have focused s on Wi-Fi
Lte unlicensed Spectrum
Focused and in the home
The control plane will also
Stacy extend into other
Unlicensed
Protocols like
Zigbee Z-Wave Bluetooth and Salon
To really make these protocols at least for my power consumption
Expected as you know how many devices on the iot world are very sensitive to power consumption
And they do their own measurements on
In our concept you have a Wi-Fi access point literally in every room
Either by way of quads
Or other devices that exist in the home
Imagine a world where you able to actually do a lot of networking M on other protocols over Wi-Fi
So that would save power consumption because you would have to
Our devices would have to
Do quote-unquote shout at a lower DVT
To reach something
Exactly image thinking about doing kindness zigbee
Z wave over wifi
So instead of these low power
Devices having to speak to each other and mash and do whatever they need to do
Beatrice sang let him just talked to the nearest pot in the room
And then one another networking
Larry few old we can do this communication and anything quote smashing a month
That will save a lot of power
And beyond that
Y'all let's not forget about the license
Spectrum
So license spectrum is very expensive and it's not really available
So we also see this control plane expanding into
Author of coordinating across both the license
Spectrum
As a unified converged control plane
Sold a lot of exciting
Wow
I Wireless
Wireless
Very sad
Okay thank you so much for coming on the show this week it was
Really Illuminating
Thank you thank you Stacey
My pleasure
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listen
And if you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy news things at Stacy
C an iot.com
Will see you next week