Hey everyone welcome
Go to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacy
Your co-host Kevin tofel
And today we have a scary show for you
We are going to kick it off with the Defcon hacks
We're going to talk about
Google
Behavior around the
Location we've got the first easy mesh router
Refresh your memory on what that is
And why it matters
And Samsung has partnered with plume to do something
Pretty cool
Also
Samsung has a new smart speaker
We're going to see what you guys
Plus Microsoft's Cortana and Amazon's Echo art
Into each other
Hand
We're not sure what
But that Kevin's going to finish up
Is Lenovo smart display review after living with it and I for the first time tried sous vide cooking
I'll tell you a little bit about that
Plus we have a message this week from
Netgear our sponsor
And our guest this week is Alison cliff
Jennings
What's a filament
Who is going to talk about
What block
Chain does for The Internet of Things
It is not your typical blockchain discussion
Do not fret
You're gonna enjoy
And now for a message from one of our sponsors
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform find out why Kenmore and D-Link pick a farro a farro
Customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market 99% pure
Your support calls in 10x higher activation rates plus they can we use 90% of their work
Check from one project to the next to learn more visit a pharaoh
. IO that's a f e r o. IO
Okay Kevin
Let's get ready for Defcon is your Wi-Fi turned off
Scared of we talked about Defcon cuz it's crazy with the hackers of Jews there just
Prove that things are not as secure as we might think
Just to make us
Little more insert
Actually because of Hotel policy
The big story at a Defcon is not the hacks
It is the management at hotel sending security guards in randomly to check
People's rooms which is
Not a great thing forever
So we're not going to talk
That we're going to talk with the devices that are half
Including our favorite the Amazon Echo
But researchers from tencent they spent months
Trying to
Figure out how to convert the Amazon Echo smart speaker into a surveillance device
What they did was they use multiple bugs
In the second generation
Show that allows a hacker to remotely stream audio from the devices micro
But those researchers
Did
Notify Amazon
And Amazon has
That's why I like ethical hackers
Ethical hacker
Should you be worried that someone else is going to come
Come do this to you
It also requires access to your Wi-Fi
And so
Most of us are not
We don't have people coming around trying to attack her
If you are that person
You know that
And
It it actually though braces are good point I mean not cortical front door to the smart home is
You know your Wi-Fi network
Innocence
You really want to focus on keeping that secure
Routers updated Etc to talk more about routers later today but I think it's worth the mention to your point that out
Yes don't give out your wife
My password I know we used to all casually B
You like
Gesnetwork baby
I know it's not I Ortiz
Specific related but I tell you what voting machine hacking by the kids that are really scares me
1 well folding machines are supposed
These aren't button
Instead
What did this 11 year old
Here there was a bunch of enterprising young children including the 11 year old who was able to
A control mock-up of the Florida sec
Terry of State website and change the voting results
And guess what it took him all of 10 minutes to do so that's
Concerning an even though voting machines aren't supposed to be
Network can connect Etc
There are processing
Bits inside them and they have firmware and some of the kids
Scott's is voting machines to change vote tallies they uploaded their own software the machines
And even had a looping gif file on the screens of one of the voting machines so that's
They're just old
Not the kids the machines
Yeah
Keep a paper record you guys
Another thing
That was hacked
Police body cameras
These people device waited live stream footage from the
So
Basically hack into a police person who's Maybe
Monitoring your criminal organization and be like
Look outside everybody's play it cool
He also could put
Malware on the camera
And then you could bring
That into the
The police department in
Go to their other databases and allow you access to
To their Network
Which as we all know is the beginning of the end
Okay
Voicemail
This one cracked me up because it was like
Hacking into voicemail but I'm like who uses voicemail
Yeah I mean
Probably very happy because people don't care about as much although they probably should
I'm like what are they
Be part of my endless parade of
Your prescription
The pharmacy is now ready
We are confirming your
Appointment at the dentist's
There was another
Kind of freaky
Freaky hack
I don't know it was a hack McAfee hackers basically showed off the ability to hack into a
Hospitals Network and falsify a patient's vital signs
And this gets into some of the medical device hacking we've talked about that a lot on the show
There's a networking protocol used by medical devices known
When is
RW hat
I'm not sure how to say
Rwhat I have no idea
Exactly
So basically what they did is they hacked into this protocol and let other devices come on to the network that looks like they
They were monitoring patients to mimic their vital signs
This is again an example of
A case where
If you were in a position where someone is really after you and wants to hack you
This is that kind of scary
Most of us are not in that position
I don't know if many people are going to want to freak out hospitals by creating imaginary patients or
Overloading people's actual vital signs with
But
For me
Government let's see here and ex-russian spy purse
Rhapsody
These sorts of hacks confortini
From that perspective
This is an interesting way to murder kill someone
Poor kidnap them and make it look like they're still there in the heart is beating normally
They just took that another level
Sorry
We're going to see this and you know
The next batch of movies
TV shows I'm sure
But it is something that we should keep an eye on just because
We're connecting all this stuff and it's providing a lot of new ways to
Falsify information and also
Allowing people access to
Things like insulin pumps in that sort of
Too many attack vectors
Too many
Access
Okay
Speaking of attack vectors
Speaking of attack
Amazon web service introduced
Their iot device Defender
Actually they didn't release it they just made it available
Kevin
Right at AWS invent
Equus November last year they announced the iot device
Defender for AWS but it is now available basically it is another service that they have for their IRT offer
And What it lets you do is
It lets you create audits
Of all of your fireteam devices you can schedule them excetera and you can look for like
Cat doesn't different things like certain certificates that are expiring perhaps
There's a policy that overly permissive
Is a whole bunch of parameters here in the idea is that you can cut a check
I would say real time I would say and I
Schedule regular basis if all of the it devices that you were managing are doing what they're supposed to do
And or
Maybe they have been hacked maybe they are getting too much information but they don't need so this is a way to help manage that so it's
Iot device Defender and again it's all part of the AWS iot services
Okay so
Let's get into another big story this week which is
AP working with some
Princeton researchers discovered that Google
Share your location
Even when you
Don't
That's
Yeah that's a fact
I was going to say that
Kind of the story but that is a fact it is true the issue here is one of transparency because Google
Says hey just disable location
Settings on your phone or whatever Android device or Google devices
To cetera and your location history will no longer have your location that is technically true
However there's another area of
Your account that
Tracks your location
It is the web and
Activity
That's where you need to disable also the location information you can manually delete it if you want to go in your account
You can do all that now retroactively but I just find it very disingenuous of Google to say the name something location history with an O
On off toggle essentially it's not all of your location history that's bothersome
Yes and we talked about this all the time but trust is so important
With the internet
Thanks and with
Mobile devices and
With all of the data.
It's been collected about
We is users have to trust that the companies are
Doing what they say they do
And maybe this was not nefarious on the part of Google maybe it was just you know
Engineers making decisions and not thinking about the UI impact
Privacy impact
We can't do that anymore
The information that is being gathered here is so personal
I really think all companies have to pay attention to this
And
Start being
Way more transfer
By the way
If you want to turn this off you have to go to on your phone do you go to Google settings in the Google account
And tap on data and personals
Station that's where you going to get the web and a peck
Then
Utah the blue web and app activity slider
Two off
Google's going to be like this is going to limit or disable more personalized experiences across Google services
In
Then
And it will
Every now and then I turn off
Or change my privacy
And sharing settings
And I can tell you the experience degrades tremendously
I mean that's kind of to be expected
If they don't have that information they can't deliver my weather without me asking
My commute
Yeah I mean that's the thing we have
I want to say treated privacy but I guess that's
Probably the best word for now we traded some of this data for very personalized useful Services Bureau
Don't want their services
That's fine
You can turn all that off
But
I'm kind of can't complain that you're not getting your commute times anymore and you're not getting local traffic cuz it doesn't know what local is for you right now
There's so many things that will disappear
That we've already just
Become accustomed to
All right
Let's move from Wiki security and privacy topics to
Do Wi-Fi Eros
Almost all of the cable
Out there
They have made the first router that works with the easymesh
And if we remember easymesh we talked about this a while back
This is the Wi-Fi lamp standard
To allow different wifi routers
What's Wi-Fi routers from different brands
Is beforehand if you wanted a mesh wi-fi system you had to basically by
These were all heroes or all whatever
Phillips
So
That's still the case with those systems but now Harrison this make sense because it's possible that
If I bought
My cable provider comes in they want to be able to
Adopt whatever
Mesh systems they were
Or maybe are already know
True but I kind of laughed when I saw this
Because this is like getting the first fax machines and then saying what okay what do I do because
Even though this is the first
Certified easymesh product
No other
Of the brands that you just mention no other ones
Work with EZ match so it's still only
It wasn't working
This one it will if
Yeah
So I mean somebody's got to be
First I get it and it does make sense of the terrorist who can sell these two
You know home broadband providers by the pallet load but it doesn't matter until somebody else says
Networking it allow using mesh to
All right
Also in
Wifi router news
Samsung
They have what they're calling the new SmartThings mesh wi-fi system
What it actually is
This is
Looms
Service
Rebranded
And
I feel like we talked about this in the past because I talked a lot about the
Future of Wi-Fi
Basically all of your Samsung SmartThings hubs
Will have this technology
Built-in +
Basically this is a rebranding of the Samsung connect
Home
Mesh Wi-Fi systems to become SmartThings Wi-Fi and Samsung had added the SmartThings keypad
Ability to these Wi-Fi Hub so it's not
Unusual they also are taking the time
Because they had
But this operation I'm guessing
Add a new and improved SmartThings Hub sensors and out
These
Are cute
The new SmartThings Hub is actually cheaper it's only to be 70 bucks 6999
The sensors are bad
20 + 2
$25
And the smart outlet is
Ya know it's this good for SmartThings admin for SmartThings users or somebody wants to upgrade or what
Start there's hard on why I get ahold mesh Network system with smartphone capabilities and
The only downside to me is
I'm not a fan of the mobile app but that's
Just me
Oh and they added
Button button
Basically
This is
It's a button
So you can have triggers on it and you can control various things around your home so
Yay
That is the one thing
With SmartThings I had a lot of automations but I am almost never in the app so if I can't talk to my
It's not already automated
Write it one question I haven't seen Samsung or plume address
Because I know the reason the plume middle layer to integrate the
Temp service on this Hardware we just talk recently about plumes
Subscription fees
I don't see any
That's the question yeah there's no mention of it
So I assumed not since you can buy this I would imagine it would tell you when you buy it and I'm not saying
So basically if you wanted to you could get the
Flume capabilities
Without the subscription
That's if you want you then get this exciting
That also
Has additional radio
That also work with zigbee and Z-Wave and Bluetooth which
Actually kind of a smoking good deal
And does what Kevin wants which is hay puts All the Small Things
StubHub
You just got Wi-Fi
Why so it's functional
Exactly
Alrighty
Moving right along
Samsung has
Also announced
Galaxy homes
Speaker
Quizlet of the Amazon Echo or the Google
And
This is bixby's version
Looks
Like a fondue pot BBQ
Yeah it's just almost like a teardrop
Shape with the top of third cut off and has the
3 silver legs
Maine
Looks like some of the modern lamps that we had in my home when modern in the 70s men lots of chrome and
Pretty shapes
Can finish it but whatever
There's no price yet it's
Coming soon cording to Samsung they did use it at their Galaxy unpacked event where they did do the Samsung
Galaxy Note 9 and the Galaxy watch they had a hundred sixty days playing some of the presentation and
From my perspective I was watching it online I couldn't tell the difference the sound sounded great but I don't think I'm going to buy a hundred six days for
I'm not convinced that Bixby is
For me but
That's what it's going to run
It also also
Also works as a SmartThings
Hub that's actually
It is
So it's got
It should because it says works as a hub
Core SmartThings
We don't know but has a smoking good deal but if you hate extra
Alright I can see that Samsung is going to stick SmartThings
Actually
SmartThings is the basis of
Are there apps that actually switching a lot of their lie
Washing machine up in the fridge app
Are becoming the smart
And Bixby of interface for a doll
Speaking of things that
Talk to each other
Cortana
And Madame
By the way I get this question a lot matinee is just what we call
Amazon's Echo assistant
Because we don't want to trigger it
But we can say Cortana on a bet it's fine
Bixby Bixby
Cuz that's what we don't say
The hot words for those
Yes and
Why do you call it something
Dancers
Anyway
So back at Microsoft build
Microsoft showed off
Cortana
And me
Together so basically you take Cortana as matinee
How to turn on my lights
That would happen and you should also
Do it in reverse and say Madam a ask Cortana to find this
Particular email
It was awkward to ask
To do the others
Who's going to do whatever job
And it was really high latency
It's rolling out to everyone so everyone can
Yeah I just think from a user experience perspective I don't want an assistant asking another assistant
To do something the only possible benefit I see
Is Windows is still very entrenched in the Enterprise
And why you could use an echo there you probably wouldn't use a
Google home because
Business data
And
Maybe use the
Integration to ask
Madame a to set up a
Calendar event for your work people on you know without looking so on wherever you using Windows and maybe there's something there
I'm not a fan of this and I don't understand why it took a year they announced this last August
It took a year
The basically make this
Skip yeah I don't know
There's a lot going on I think there was probably also some inviting
Back at the event
Satya Nadella the CEO of Microsoft was like Hey Cortana is for business and Madam A is for home
Maybe there was some like
Calling an Uber
Is that a business
I don't know that could be and there could have been some debate over who gets what data because the way that this works
Today is
As I understand it when you use
Madame a Amazon gift the data when use madhumeh to
Ask Cortana do something Microsoft gets the day. So there may have been some pushing and pulling there and that will tug of war
Yes so that's out
Etsy
Now it's time for the part of the show where Kevin and Stacey try things at
And tell you about them
Kevin last week talk to a lot
About the Lenovo smart display
He did a pretty comprehensive review now we've got one up on the site which are linked
But Kevin did you have
Having now used it for more than 30
How do you feel about
I really like it is not for everybody I guess I'll say that right up front if you are a homekit
Person this doesn't do anything for you
If you are all in on echoes
This doesn't do anything for you it is basically a Google home with
Screen which I find very beneficial for viewing information just like the Echo Show does
Also for fine
Tuning your smart home controls because if you say satellite to 40% it'll do that
You can say that my voice but it then we'll show you a little slider on the screen and says 45% and maybe you're in that room and
That's not enough
You just touch it you don't need to speak again then just touch it and drag the slider that is actually coming to the
Google Assistant
As well I've seen that rolling out as of last week so you'll see what I'm talking about on your phones and tablets
If your
Thinking about switching over to Google devices this is a
Great great device and if you watch a lot of online video content
Fantastic
Because it comes in two sizes 8in and 10in I bought the 10-inch one because it is a full HD display where's the other one at 7
20p you can voice search
And give commands to say watch
Cat videos on YouTube and there it is is your Google Play music you can save play songs by The Beatles whatever
It does not
Work with as many Music Services
But that's typical of the Google home platform
So that is a limitation
But I love it for watching video as well as YouTube TV which I switched over to about three weeks ago not because of this ice
Switch in advance of this
And
It's just nice to have a little
Nightstand TV to watch a half an hour of something
In full HD the sound I think it's better than the regular Google home
Play Smash it's much better than the Google home mini there's two 10-watt speakers in here and I like the fact that it just
Looks more modern than say a competing product like the Echo Show as a nice bamboo back if I
Curved back so you can stand the device in portrait or landscape I will admit I've only used it in portrait one time that was free
Google Duo call with you Stacy
I have not made another one and that's the only function that works in portrait mode
This is meant to be in landscape
So I got my photos from Google photos on there all the time I've got the
Time on there
25 hours a day get my weather and so on
I love it I got to be honest there are things that don't work yet such as Netflix
It's on there even though I link my Netflix account but it's all in the work so I'm very very happy I'm using this far more
More than any other smart speaker in my house just because that screen add so much more value to me
I can't wait to get my own
And we shall say this is all specific to the 10-inch one because I don't think the 8-inch one can you switch it from porch
Landscape
You can't and both of them have cameras to use Google Duo but I should also mention the smartest thing they did was putting it
Physical shutter cover on this device
And you just slide it and the camera is off its block there's nothing
Vatican City
EXO $200 for the 8in
215 to the 10 in
Yes and
Kevin Lee
I'm actually
I kinda want to get to it he didn't actually talk about this but like
Facts about Alaska
But you can see things from like your nest cameras
On the device
Another sibling
So exciting
Already
Let's talk about my experience with
Sous vide
You guys know that I am
Crazy person in the kitchen and I met the CEO of chefsteps
Mexican Heaven
Come on the show soon
They make a sous vide cooker
They're one of many
Cemitas
Cooking under water at a set
Temperature basic
Play so you put one of these circulators in its got a thermometer it circulates water ideas you stick your food in a plastic bag
And
You cook it at a set temperature at
Takes
A little longer or a lot longer depending on the food
And
Quote on quote perfectly done
So
They're right
Perfectly done I will say that I would not cook something in a suvee I would not suit
Need something
A suburb
And then serve it to someone I would want to
Put some charna so fry it up afterwards they tell you about this in
So this Tuesday GIF cooking I'm not
Super keen on
Like one pot Stacy
It really makes deliciously
Jimmy eggs but like eggs with the proper yolk that is not like to renovate
Not to
Hard and then it does a great job
Beach
And for anyone who trying to meal prep
In advance it's actually really good because what you can do is you can stick in
Couples it has to be the same kind of meat in roughly the same size but you can flavor it different ways so you can have like a
Mediterranean flavor in
Southwestern flavor and you
You can stick those in individual bags and you can basically prep different types of chick
Different types of flank steak
Which
Actually
Does the juul have any connectivity or mobile app or any other
It does in fact
It has
Nothing on it
There is no interface
Without the app
Which is a questionable thing
Some people are not going to let this
Others like the Anova have that capability on the device
Schedule without your app is
Shell
The app that
Is really good
Chefsteps has
Comprehensive
Recipe site
In some of the things you don't even have to sous vide
So they have lots of cooking guys that show you how to make
But then they also like
Have a visual indicator so when you're trying to
Cook something
Like I put meat in its like hey what are you cooking and I'm like I'm going to cook a cow
And I like yours the cut
And then they show you
Video basically
Tidy
Video or GIF but it just a quick shot of how would you like a cookie they show it to you
So you don't say meme
Pinkness of the meet basic
They show someone cutting into it so you can see like the juicing as that all of the stuff
It's kind of terrible twos
Are you in Siri when you're hungry cuz
Can take an hour or two or three
Except that is
You know what would be neat
Well I see something on the site that has a hands
Free mode
Were you can
Kind of talk to it and
You can't you can't talk
Okay
So if you can do that
Would it be cool to at least see the temperature or anything else you want to see on that
Smart display or something similar that I was just telling you about it mean it's got Bluetooth and Wi-Fi just temperature information it and or timers
Simply
Small bits of data
I see a lot they could do with this in terms of integration so I guess is what I'm saying
Yeah they could
Integrated to work with the show
It doesn't work
Google assist
So
Sorry Kevin
That's okay
If you're interested in
The
Juul which is what I tried is
179 for the
Cheaper version and then they have an industrial one
The bigger clamp that is 119
On Amazon
So in there are others like the Innova it goes on sale regularly for
Like 17
So
Pick what you will that's just the one I used but I was actually Pleasant
I surprised in this is very much and I.
In the sense that it's using the processing power on your phone to make these kind of decisions about
And the sensors in the particular
Suvee cooker
To figure out the most appropriate way to
Your food which
Awesome
Kevin
I believe
It is time
For our voicemail
It is
So this week's
Voicemail from the iot podcast hotline
Is from
Jessie
Any deals with fans
The iot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Do not miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wi-Fi adapt
To do this all you have to do is
Call us at 5 1/2
6 tooth
742 4
And we randomly pick
Every month
Someone to win
So call us
Ask us a question do it all before the 31st of August at midnight ET
And you too
Could win a
Schlage
Sense smart deadbolt and Wifi
Just remember
Smarter homes
Start with SLI
Alright let's hear from
Jessie
Accusation Kevin this is Jesse from Connecticut here I'm currently building a house and had a question about Smart Control of
Overhead fan
Can I have a fan in my bedroom and I asked my electrician to wire separate
Switch for both the lights on the fan and the fan itself under the assumption that spark
Be easier with sex
I am having Lutron caseta switches style throughout the home for lighting control
Set SmartThings Hub brother control and have a number of Madame a and Google flights
What would be the best way to
Trolling motor
Specific make and model of the fan on getting
Thanks spot
Jessie
This is
A good question
And your luck because I have Facebook
Myself
And I
Have all the devices you have
And the best option is
The GE Z-Wave
Plus smart
Speed control
Device so basically this is a
On Amazon it is a
3782 device
$37.82 and you want to get the paddle fan control
Vice this is going to turn your fan on and off and
You do a long press 2
Control the fan speed
It works really well at use a Z-Wave plus so it's going to work with SmartThings
It also will work with
Wink and madam
And
You were smart in dividing up the things I will tell you
We actually last week talked about a device
Call the bond ir and RF remote
For people who have existing fans
Control that's actually a really good option if they have a remote
That goes with their fan they can use
That remote to program it to the pond and then it would work with
Madame a and
An app
So just throwing that out
Are people who
Maybe we're not as smart
2 divided
Lighting and the
Air fan control
And Jessie and anybody else
Has to be careful if you do go to buy this on Amazon
There are several switches there
And this looks exactly like the paddle light switch but that only controls the lights
So make sure you get the
Paddle for fan control
And on the bus it says easy smart fan can
And shows a picture of a
Really look forward
And is a really easy answer for you Jesse so hopefully
You can call us back and let us know
How it went
Okay
I think that's it
The new 2nd of this week show
Stay tuned to hear from our guest
Who is Allison clift-jennings the CEO of filament discussing
What blockchain can do especially around microtransaction
And it's a really good we actually get a little philosophic
In there so
Is that your bag
You're going to like this
It's not listen anyway because
You can never have enough black
And now let's go to a message for this week sponsor hey everyone we're taking a break from this week's Internet of Things
Podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Netgear
And I have
John McHugh who is a senior vice president of commercial networking at Netgear
Alright so we talked
A couple weeks about Netgear which
Not only has a
Homebase router business that a lot of us are familiar with but also a commercial and small to medium-sized big
Business Solution
So let's
Talk about how you guys make that
Easier for
Commercial customers
Setup and operate their Network
You know one of the things Stacy the Netgear really takes pride in
Is
Making networking technology
Accessible to folks
Who have little or no networking knowledge
Kind of taking rxp
Ortiz from home networking
Where millions and millions
The people rely on Netgear for their home networking Solutions and most of those folks aren't really technical specialist
We do the same for small business owners
Okay so as someone who's dealt with this are we talking about oh now I've got a router and then I've got access points everywhere
Where and how do you make that process
Easier
Let me give you great example orbi Pro
Right or be Pro is a solution for a small maybe four or five thousand
Square foot retail outlet or bed-and-breakfast even a hosp
Fatality Ben you like a restaurant or whatever and what it allows you to do is
Stand up a small business Network
Turn on guest user access the able to log who the guests are they
Use your ecosystem
Have a bunch of ports
Wi-Fi
Business-oriented stuff that you don't want the gas to get access
And it does it all in a way that somebody who's an opposite networking
Turn it on to make it run
Okay so that's orbi problem we've been talking about your Insight line so how is that different
Inside
Kind of plays the next roll up orbi Pro is really designed as a turnkey for a do-it-yourself net
Working person
I like to say or be broke
Is for people who don't know what a VLAN is
And so can you can set up a grade secure business Network
And not know anything about networking whatsoever but if you want to go to the next level then inside
Bridges that Gap it's both simple to use its
Common English
Straight boards
30 let you get in and start dealing with a real complexities of
More scale-out Network
What are some of those complexities
You're the most common one is that people like to think about structuring their networking isolating various
Is domains one common thing I hear for my customers is
I want all my
Internet of things on a separate VLAN
So that my home network my base business network is
Completely isolated
Well that requires vlans that requires Port assignments on
Switches and a lot of stuff that kind of goes to the next level inside allows you to be able to go to
Full Security in Attica
Where can I go to find out more about insight and
Orbi Pro
Www
Netgear.com inside
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your home Stacy Higginbotham and today's guest is
Jennings
Who is CEO of
Hi Alison how are you doing
I'm so well how are you
I am excited
Because we have talked for like years almost about
How we're going to use the black
So let's Orion people in
And tell them
Where
Filament darted in the iot
Originally
To think quite a while to get into this realm
Having an engineering problem
Salishan
She was problem and then from there it's always hard to realize
And now we're squarely in this marriage
Between the blockchain and the internet
Awesome
We should probably talk a little bit about the hardware problem that you encounter
I think it's important only because there's a lot of us height in this phase I mean
You taking and everything for just barely IP
And you had blocked
You got to get this like
Meda hajt
Originally address that we were
We had a lot of customers to pay for Internet of Things
Product they wanted to pay for it
Korea score per month
Princeton
Upfront
In the technical in the financial world who called capital
Or capex versus
The common terminal Airlines
So what we ended up having this
Orangewood company saying what they want to pay for this
Topic
Requirements
Is it that way
Didn't have a good way to
On the device
And so it is a fundamental engineering problem
Any physical device that isn't always online
It turns out that this is a very large problem
Century there's some famous
Problems
Sybil attack
These are well-known.
Talk and it turns out that the block
Happened to be a recent
Invention that had address
Does
When we start looking
It's called
Sales problem with some aspects of
OKC
You guys
Your solution
Build your own car
It was because we needed to be able to store
The cryptographic keys
For the block
And the only way we knew how to do that
SPX
The Cure
And so that's where we went down the throat if you know originally again only happy
Aspire
She asked if I censor device
We moved now squarely into bring it up
Security of the hardware aspect of making
By having the heart
Secure element
That we built
Okay but that's actually not what you got
It was nice
Talk about is a startup
I'm going to solve this problem
Now I have
Exactly
What were you trying to do 6 years ago you saw this opportunity
Wow we could do x what was so cool about those ideas
Write this a good question to the pathway
Industrial
Ceviche like Sportsman 1000
The world in the Ford motor
These were the companies that we thought wanted Industrial iot
Coming iot
And it's
Partially true
The truth is that we found out
Hard struggle
There are
Several people in the company who do want it but there are also several people who do not
Can often be towed Enterprise
And the only one way to learn this lesson
And then have the field close shutdown
Sanya Let's Ride
Because of the startup
Everything is based
Clearly
Industrial
When we solve the problem for having a little device
Payable on going contract or peruse
Economics
We've been had that moment
And which one
We can do this part 5 what happens if we allow our
Officetel
Their products
Another words what happened
Product
This could also be economic
And if they could be does it allow them to have him
And more importantly does it get
Those who use the veto it
Now say oh heck yeah
It's about sweater
Thule rack today but through a lot of hard lessons by trying to sell Industrial iot
Stacy very difficult
Okay so what turns a little bit more so when you say
Product
Economic machine
Giving it economic
Capabilities
Is that simply like vending machine have the trust
And value
Store TUMI
How would we
It's a great question it's an important point so
Stoneham thinks about making machines economic
I can make sure what we mean is that machines by default
Can't our infrastructure Maybe
Car trucks
Carpal
Those are awesome
Not economic nature meaning they can't
Transaction value
Some people value is data other people
Value is
Now what that looks like it's when you start Splenda forget it looks like a cryptocurrency
But if those infrastructure pieces or less machine
Could
Transact value
Or trade or exchange you know even
Can musically be built upon a new business models that allow us to do
Simple machine to have the core components required
In order to
Transact
Extension
Hair be paid or a test
True that the minutes happened
Cryptographically Exchange
Aggregate
Together so let's actually
Take a step-by-step because this is a pretty
I think it's not a hard concept but it
Examples totally help
Let's go with something
Listen Vision something we know and love
Now with
The machines having this inherent
Capability unit comes from
Implanting
Write in cars in
If you take Vehicles today are usually operated by
People usually own the vehicle or pay regulation
And usually also pay other
Entity to operate a vehicle
Insurance
Or sometimes a ticket to a highway patrolman
For a toll road these are various aspects of
Payment.
Need to make
In order to use music
So when I start talking about how this might look differently with her
As we see in the future on the horizon of autonomous vehicles
They'll still need to
Transact on behalf of
Either their owner operator the writer
The manufacturer
Somebody will need to pay for the fuel to recharge
The ticket
Find
Toll road fee and so these are all
And there's just not
8 weight
To do that today
This is like a coyote today is literally like
Me too
We had gray background website sir Tim berners-lee invented the world wide web and we're all excited about make your own web
And then came along.
E-commerce which allowed the internet
2B Transit
To be transacted as well because what happened when we brought e-commerce the internet
We got companies like Amazon
Alibaba
EBay
How old is amazing
Exactly could not have existed
Of the internet
So when we can bring the future Alibaba
Amazon eBay
Could be built upon the machine
The Stick of payments for a moment longer
A lot of people look at this
This is like a way to enable macros
So
I feel like in some ways that's a bit limiting but we
Do need a way to do my
Transactions so can you
Give us your vision
Yes microtransactions are funny
Because they are buried
So many ways but the technology
In the trees
Directions for
He almost empty Commerce
Publishers
You're going to pay podcast
We were going to pay a lot of people a lot of things
Never really
And a big reason why
Did the minimum transaction fee to make
In the traditional credit card or electronic
World that we had up until 10 years ago was still
Too high for microchip
Do you like going to the ATM
And clean out $0.30.
$2
It just doesn't
I didn't know in this actually going to do that so there is an aspect to this that we're looking at that cryptocurrency
Allow for the pie
Possibility
Have microtransaction
Capability
This isn't always
Spaceballs
That public blockchain such as Bitcoin and ethereum are quite expensive right now
Taxi transact on internally want coffee maker conduction test
Luckily there are some new technologies in that state
Network that
Requirements
All that is to say that this technology
Along with
Development is setting up
The situation
Very nicely
To actually be able to
Could you microtransaction
At the hardware level
Finally
It only took us like 30 years ago
That's how I feel about a lot of
Now it's actually here
So
Let's talk about value
Because this is
Cryptocurrency hype
I think a lot of people
Don't think about the idea
Attestation
Update on saying hey this came from here
It's a really important thing and I'll just
Sherwood
Our listeners
I was talking with someone from Bosch and they were talking about
Connecting trucks please of trucks
And it would be really beneficial to have some sort of decentralized way
For those trucks to identify
Car self driving
Identify that they can join
Time it take advantage
Cartoon VR so
Machines being able to
Data or Truss
Absolutely
Because you know a lot of
Networking
Machine learning
That's better
Detective chief
And I think that economics
Not even when people sell things are always after the data
Catchphrase
Expected we think of it
If you look at information or what
Definition Theory data is the Bottom Rung of this
Definition
Because data and then on top of that
Information which is data that
Organized
And then on top of that information
Categorized
And then you have your wisdom which is overlooking based
Previous knowledge
Proactive
Siri and Alexa kind of think about how we
Deal with data
Is it similar thing that we
Headed to dig into the economics
Is not data
Economics
And then on top of that you start to have
Party or participate
Cinemark
Look up. You start to have things like
Transaction demand
Reputation is like Wednesday
Like I will trust you again cuz I trusted you in the back
Every time
So it's interesting because it's parallel
Field
And both of them are just as powerful as the other
But we spent a lot of type of data
In the tech world
Talking about values
Requires
Trust to be absolutely rock-solid
If you can't trust the other party
Your reputation for the park & Market Apartments
Don't know
And I thought they were most attacks happen
Today in the cryptocurrency
Space is like trying to steal cheese in the Trap
So when we think about this we really do want
Established
Really strong roots of traffic and then on top of that let others build
Their applications
Let's break down this
Concept of trust from
Economic theory
Because
What you're talking about is just that it's
Sure it's trust that it's secure in your stuff won't be stolen or
I can't be value cannot be
Temperature
Correct
Because there's also an element of trust in
Reputations like what I think of is a person
Trusting another /
That's more reputational
Incorrect
I think so
Okay because the tech companies
I would look at them and I think going into eye
Abstract for a lot of people as machines being
Transaction
Build it
A lot of companies
The reputation Trust
It's becoming increasingly clear that
If you're going to say
You're going to hand
Company the keys to
Creative me
Some sort of aspect
Business weather
Partner with
That relationship
In the reputation entrust their beak
So much more important and I don't see a lot of companies thinking that way
I think that maybe
Completely agree in concurrence I don't even see it in our Clinic
No fear in other areas
What happens when trust breaks down
It can be pretty dense metal can be able to trust
Perspective
And I completely agree with you.
Used trucks
URC
Then when losing out on possible future capability and
Quite frankly
Payment issue later because we have trust based in
We don't have it yet we're not quite there I do believe it starts with people reconsidering what trust means
Okay well that got deep real
It's something that I'm not sure we can
But if you have any tips
Stephen Thompson
Blase about
Really so important
Ways to establish real partnership
What are the kind of things that a company should be
Communicating and also internalizing
Considering this as a first class property
Property
Fire today
It's not unlike
Traditional
Security office
And then we had the Home Depot
Target another hacks where
This is a requirement this is a necessary thing for
To take seriously
I do believe that you know
Sir I'm not sure he could probably fall under CIA
Regardless
Somewhere where somebody champions
I need to be treated
Because it will be one of us
Lightable area
Where are you again
In some ways
Traditional human or social
Spearfishing
Gmail
Nfcu
A breach of trust at the end of the day
People assumed that they could
Email coming from
Westside Pizza
Stop
Text Lee
Much more broken up
Treated with respect. Whatever type of I don't want cause a liability but
Responsibility
Of companies
Connect
Religious Wireless World or
Connected world
Where's that they must also
Have some aspect of responsibility around the
Festivus
List of people you know
So it could be as simple as
SM Plaza
It could be something it has
Proactive is the key about
Training your algorithms to handle adversarial at
Tax
Which exactly
Is kind of crazy hard
I think about
Grateful
Currently attached
The question isn't can you
How do you know when it's actually Act
Attract the Great Plains
Okay well
We have talked about a lot of things
Analysis
I appreciate you making me think so hard this after
I really enjoyed it
Thank you for coming on the Shelf
Thank you for always like to join you that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember
If you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Next week