Hey everyone
Welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin Torres
We're going to talk about data protection
In light of Facebook's
Here hmmm
A scandal best smart home login problem
I did a smart home sprinkler
We got a bunch of news from IBM
Some shopping tips for Google home
Bunches of small news items from Smart Home world
And the industrial internet world
We got a
Wonderful guest for you today it is
David Kaiser
Who's going to talk about the smart home of the future that Lennar thinks is going to happen
Homekit for
Amazon
We're also going to have a message on iot
Security for my sponsor Samsung
And now
Let's go to another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is iot world are you thinking about going to iot World in May if so used to
Code to get 20% off for past you are invited
Event for iot businesses and Technology May 14th through 7th
At the Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon Valley this is the event is anniversary in the show
12450 speakers and 300 exhibitors
Sounds boxers this year is all about putting iot into action building a winning strategy implementing
Strategy effectively and driving Revenue so to learn more and register to attend visit
Iot world event.com and remember use coupon code Stacy 20 that's
Stacey 20 after checkout to get 20% off your path
It is
Jeep
Deep winter there for you but here in Austin Texas it is the first day of spring
It is not the first day of spring
What about you
I'm feeling tired because we're getting pounded with snow and we shovel like every 2 hours
Where is our smart snow plow version of
The snow plow
Let's talk about data protection because
Because this week's big story
Misuse of
By Cambridge Analytics
US election
And this is
Use of Facebook data so they actually use data that they didn't have permission to you
Used to Target people
Well
A lot of people originally said this was a data breach it was not a data breach the system
Facebook system
Platform work as intended
However
Cambridge analytica
Putting out like a quiz app
That approximately 270000 people took
It got data from
Friends of
Yours
And as a result the report is it actually was able to creep
Profiles of 50 million people
Even though not technically people use the quiz app
And again that is
Within Facebook
Acceptable
Or technically possible Facebook
For many people
Think about
Your craziest Facebook friend probably your aunt
Who you're just like
What are you doing
That person
Is opening you up to all kinds of craziness
And also Cambridge Analytics
They did live right about saying
When they had
Correct
Correctamente
For you is
4 very specific
Targeting of Facebook ads
And
The targets were built on the profiles that they created for everybody
Also Those ads
Well well say steak using Those ads but then again political ads
Often have
Information that is questionable or
It's designed to sway
Yes
The dark
Did you know
That candidate X
Let murderers loose early
What look like legitimate news stories in that same tone
Witches
It's harder for
The reason we're talking about this isn't
Because
Facebook
It's because we think the story helps
It helps legitimize what has been a long-standing concern that we had about
All of the dated it
Uart connected devices
Everything from Cars to light bulbs to
If you're at home if you're not when you typically leave the house so on so forth you
We don't have
Good protections for this and a lot of data is
Please
So this story presents a really calm
Concrete evidence of
Why that's
Something we should be looking at
Tell that much
But they can actually tell us
And they can I share this with a lot of pee
And so Kevin and I were talking about our Smart Home
Kevin was like
So they
Are the Camp Hill Democrat
Profiles
Pretty interesting
Kashmir Hill actually did a story about
I have some of that might develop
Kind of Lifestyle
Most of the devices we do talk about you can't use unless you are willing to provide that information to
Whoever the service provider is
That is true
And that's one of those things like the gdpr that European
Regulations about privacy
Actually talked about
If
You are providing
A device or service indeed
Is part of that
The person has to be able to opt out
In some reason
And I think that's going to be
I really enjoy I'm interested to see how they actually improve
You put something on a package before
By the way that we're going to collect
I guess because I would like
Actually I would think
I really easily
Understandable
Sharing
Sticker
On the device
Helpful
And then I'd be like
I don't want to buy this
It's one thing for Google to say
But it's pretty easy to switch over some
Purses
Once I've installed something I brought it home and packed it from
And then I see that they want
All this extra data
Restocking fee
Aha
Yeah it's definitely tougher with physical devices to know that in advance
What happens
And this is a really interesting
Because it might become relevant for life
I bought my
In terms of service
When Nest peking
Google Google
Those receipts
But
Let us know if it changes
If they change it
How likely are people
Jack to this
Thermostat off
Off the wall
It's basically a
The barriers of change
New updated terms of service
Art
Now that's what I call them
Amazon
Just a few weeks ago on that and like
Oh well
Dice clicked yes but
Took them for my wall several months later and try to return
I would like to see these companies along with the
Neely's of a terms of service provide a simple checklist of what's new compared to what
You know what the original tale as well as
Get on it dies
Okay
So there
And let's move to another anti-consumer
Qual work while we're on this
Smart Home
Lockn
Kevin this is a really good article over on Fast Company that willing to in the show notes
Jared Newman wrote it and he knows his stuff.
Google and Amazon in the past and he talks about why that is
And it has to do with standards and such she has to do with apis which article on last week one of his
Key
Areas in Antarctica
You can talk to me but I won't talk to you
It's interesting how the approaches that different
Smart Home
IPhones have taken like will provide you can talk to us but we're not going to send you anything back
It's really rather interesting
Jared has spoken weapons in the Articles you can read it but he has spoken with some of the
Standards groups that we have
How about we talk about a new one which kind of poo poo in butt
No it's an option in that was the network of intelligent camera ecosystem nice the alliance that just came about
But also the OCS we talked about before the open to be Foundation
They're all in here and they're trying to
Can do
To try and make this a better and easier so that way we do have standards and we don't have lock-in
You know
Say with homekit I think it's the most lockdownd ecosystem and that's why
Devices to choose from because the manufacturers
Don't want to just Target a certain demographic
Sonic racing
Yeah yeah
Change it
Your device
The capabilities of your device switch
Probably frustrating
Absolutely
Something a Google effort that kind of reduces
I will call it
Strong
Competitor a strong service provider in the sales everywhere talk about that
One of the things in this article they did a lot on the ocf
Which is
Connectivity Foundation
Where they're trying to focus
There which I think is really good so get
This is what a light bulb is so every light bulb will come
Basic
I would like
I have dimming capabilities maybe it'll
Encompass the color capabilities
And that'll all be standardized across all of them
Something like Google or Amazon
Or any of the other plants
Pomsky just tired to that
I would love to see that
I've been wanting this
Or
Decades
But it's
It's incredibly
It's a device capabilities
And I wonder
I wonder how
Don't know this will happen I wonder if that will obviate the need for a
In the Smart Hub
Theoretically
But yes will it well actually I don't know
I think you always need a hug because you'll need the extra
Shooting because this isn't going to solve the issue of life
Like reading like this Unified
Platform everything that you should have power
So you're still going to want a hug for local cab
Computing of tasks prop
Automation
Which
Kevin you wrote about last
So
Yes so you're still going to need
Which is fine
But you don't need 20
Thank goodness
Ziggy does have some
Call.
Ocf is working on something
We was going to do this but
More so
Maybe maybe there's an OCS
Standardized
What they put their seal of approval on
Ocf
But you would also have to buy ocf
Lights for
You know they said they were going to have stuff
Last year
They didn't
So there are no but this year supposedly we are promised ocf products
Coming out so we'll start seeing this and we'll see
Actually works
Will let you know
Because
Right now
It sucks
My criteria for connected devices now is it needs to work with Amazon Echo
The Google Assistant
If I were a iPhone user
I probably wanted to work with
Trinidad
That's like very low on the totem pole since then
Homekit implementation is not awesome
Also I don't have a knife
I'm getting from the station isn't bad it's actually
Quite good baking really kept it simple by staying with just Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Because
Device makers and not put all their products out
It support
That's true
Kevin is going to be a resident
Kiddush home
Good luck Kevin
All right if you're I I want to talk about this cuz this is something I
I am in the middle of
Probably talk a little bit more about this but I am doing an iot Smart Home Spring
And I'm going to recommend that if you're like me test a lot of Criterion capabilities
Did you look at this
So I've noticed in the last couple months that things are just
There are things that just don't work there devices on my network
So what I did is I went through
I looked at what I had in my house
Anything we didn't have
Like that was
Anything we weren't using
I deleted the app
I deleted my in when I delete the app I delete
Authorized every
Everything I try to delete as much data as possible if it's possible
And took a device unplugged
Set it aside so once I have done all that
Appleton East
That wasn't working
Write this down
Deleted all my devices for the Amazon
I deleted all my devices in
Google
And
It is part of re-adding them
Implemented I spent like four hours doing some routines on both systems
To make life a little bit more
More fun for people
And it's been kind of a sucky
But necessary process it's taking a while
Have two more things that don't work even
Through the massive reboot a couple things actually did come back
Because
You may be asking
Maybe moving stuff around
In
It's kind of nice to have a fresh slate
I don't disagree with a question though
Did you hard reset the physical devices that you took off even light bulbs
If I took
Them off and there was a hard reset button
I did the order of operations for this was I looked at the app
IDI Thrice the app
I did a hard reset
I deleted the app
Okay I'm just thinking because even a lightbulb
She don't
Oh yes you can
I don't have any Philips Hue but like my Cree bulbs
Am I awesome bulb there is a process to reset them
Oh yeah yeah yeah
Would any device still have say my Wi-Fi credentials somewhere
Buy some device providers don't take
Your Wi-Fi
Information
So deleting the account or removing a device from the provider should do that
It's a reminder concerned I just wouldn't want somebody having like the MAC address of my router you know by poking around somehow and
You can poke around in the code of the bulbs
So if you have the
Google how to reset
AG smart light
Sometimes you can reset them by accident
Can children because
Most of the receptor
Put the lights on and off really rapidly 6 times
Do it again
Amazingly
My child
A couple times
It's possible rare
Smart home screen
Clean
Couple hours and
Your home is not going to work
Like it should
Family or set aside
And
At the end
You will have a brand-new shiny
Less glitchy smart
That's what you're working
Anything you don't have glitches right now
You don't need to do it
I ready
Speaking of
My first thing I added after all my routines
Amazon
Echoes
Barismo
Yeah you might have heard of its record as a follow-up mode and what it does is if you enable it when you
Speak a command to madam she will chords
Do not come in
But if this mode is enabled she will also listen for additional 5 Seconds
So you can just
Say another command without saying the Wake word I think it's
Super handy some people may not want it to continue to listen for 5 seconds
Because of privacy concerns I totally get that so Choose Or Not choose this mode based on your preferences
You do this in the app there's in your device settings in the united pay app
But interesting what you did it in the app
This morning Stacy
I didn't do it in the app
What freaked me out when this went live when I went out to go for a run at 9 one night nobody was
Awake so I just told me today to turn the family room lights down 50% I didn't even at full Blair because
Nobody was in the living room
And she said to me
I have a new follow-up mode
Would you like to enable and she explained what it was to me
And I enable it by choice
Yeah I love that
I must be special
Please to her
Maybe somebody Will Smith
She knows that I'm spitting
But it works really well
I have it on.
So I don't think it's being held back
Specifically to Amazon bill devices obviously it's not because the sun has has it so
It's in there you can enable if you like
Awesome alright speaking voice assistance
IBM
Has a new smart assistant it is
Watson assistant
Go figure
Talk about
Emma Watson
No but it's actually pretty good name if I had like
Holmes and Watson
So what this is is this is an ID
Voice assistant
I didn't have a ton of cool Watson and
Products
Conference
IBM news
Watson is not
Design for
Consumer-facing stuff
It's going to be mostly operate behind the scenes for other companies so
Which is working with Watson Kindle
Commands for cars
And Watson also wants to do it now
Hotel rooms
Stores
The store in retail setting
It's a little confusing for
A Watson
Store assistant master store planner
What engine do I have
In Spring
So I think this is kind of interesting
Hockey
Two people
And probably
Really unlimited even though it's trying to do Amazon for business
Business on the side
Right cuz there's a lot of things you think about like admin access was access to certain
Information
You know anyone can walk into a room and asked
So I'm sure as hell
RPM sticking
About the architecture of the back
People access
Emission control circuit
Isis
Interesting to see what comes of it
Yeah I don't want like my passenger like sometimes you know you're driving
Time with your kids and I
Friends
My car
A lot of types
All the time
Maybe doing a voice assistant in the car letting them change stuff or painted cooler
Nope
Air condition is just fine
IBM also announced
Type
Chip that is designed to
As part of its crypto anchor program so
It's basically like a digital birth certificates digital watermarks for devices the quilting here isn't that a
Super super tiny
Although it is
The cool thing is that they're talking about it's selling for what is like $0.10 a piece
Which does put it in the realm of
Many applications
Call zlata X
You should
A5x the cost of
For the hardware is
Just Fur
All that stuff that goes around the hardware integrated
Get into
But that's still
Let's go back to the home for a little bit
Because you can now
We got details about how
Google is thinking about shopping
And I was going to respond to the Amazon
Which is pretty huge and Google already got some big retailers lineup because
Amazon is the scariest thing ever
Shopping
Assistant
Yeah I think this is brilliant it's a very defensive play on Google's part against Amazon
Search Google for products to buy
Apparently 72 80% of those searches need you to Amazon where people make
Purchase so since Google
Antitrust concerns and such what they've done is they've integrated
Google Assistant shopping
With Google Express
Interesting way if you do say to your assistant I like to buy whatever I'll coffee cup
Amazon results are little scarce there
Very interesting so what Google doing as they work with
Retail Partners
Show up in a search results
And then use Google expressed actually
Complete the purchase
I think it's
Super super smart because obviously for using an Amazon Echo
Or any matinee device to search for Crocs to buy
Where is it going to rain
Amazon
Can't do that with Google Now you can I just I think it's a brilliant brilliant move on Google
Yes I do too so
Do you want to talk to people like I was a little fish trying to figure out how
Because
Well I mean you do a search through Google Assistant for a product and you'll get various results and she like you can add any of those
Google Express card
It doesn't look to me like you can actually complete the purchase
Google assistant
What happens if you
It gives you tells you
After you've selected something
You can slide in your life that's pretty cool
You can add it to your cart and then it gives it says
Okay this is in your cart you can find it
At this URL or it gives you the option to check out if
Except checkout is going to send you to the Google assistant app
The express app
Where you can't
It's not a fool and then purchase implementation yet but I got to believe that that's the next step
Which is good because
He just bought five things that you really don't need
Women's short sleeve red t-shirt
The first result actually was from Amazon
And it told me that
Periodically
Search result is from Amazon.
Which was unlike any of the other search results
Interested
Maybe it mean depend on the product
In which case they don't have a retailer with a grape
Deal or or stock or who knows what
I don't think they're locking Amazon out
I think that would be a problem
Yes alright also in Google News late last week after
Done
Recording the show
Is now available
The video doorbell
Is the nest hello doorbell it is going to be 200
$30
So much money for a doorbell
You also will have to pay for nest aware cloud
If you
That it is a wired doorbell
So
Note that
Not battery power
Does the service fee does that count with your nest aware
Or he has to pay extra
IMG
So what will happen is I will ask
So whenever we talk about
Hello doorbell which should be either next week or the week after depending
When it arrives when I get it installed
I shall have it answer
Also
The clock is come
Well
A little sad because this particular version of the Yale lock
Will not work with
So it's not like the August lock which works with
All of the
Yeah I'm seeing the same lock come out for different plaster
It's the worst absolutely the worst
Don't
Try that and we'll be able to look at the Google Assistant smart display stuff
We're out in the market
Because I'd love to be able to
So I guess I could try to
You certainly could because I tell my
Nvidia Shield
TV which is an Android TV and Chromecast
Assistant built-in
Show my Nest Cam and it just started up on my TV
Because the Chromecast devices can actually turn the TV on so you can if you're not
Watching TV at the time you can just
Letv model and show it
OMG
Also going to break all the sprinkler
I did probably but that's okay
Because that's my life
Stay tuned for
But if you don't want to wait for us to talk about it you can just go and buy it cuz they are
Alright let's move into the
Quick
My stuff
And we talked for a really
So here's an interesting Google Project Pat
Sidewalk Labs which alphabet
Smart City effort
Map of San Francisco's parking rules
What you be like will why did they do that well if you need to know where you can
Stop for deliveries or maybe you're an Uber driver need to know where you can sit for a few minutes and not have to pay
Pay for parking
It's all there in this information
Unique
Because normally
Disable apps tell you
Has spots available
This is not that
Could help fill with City
Planning for
Different parking rules in areas
Speaking of
Cars we would be remiss if we didn't talk about Uber self-driving
Car killing a woman
This week
In Arizona
So we don't have a lot
To say about this but
Well you know obviously so very sad statue
And for that individual in the family so far the preliminary results
There was no way for the car to avoid this pedestrian
There was a driver in the car not driving a car they were in the driver seat in Uber person
So far based on the information
Not even the smart technology of The Economist
Vehicle could have avoided this point would be
We can't just assume autonomous vehicles will
Completely eradicate these type of
Of incidence
It's unfortunate but we can't do that because some things just happened so fast that not even the computing power in the car
I can handle it to make a change of swerve etcetera so
I don't want people to think of time this car will make everything safer 100% of the time
Right there real world physics
A car going is going around 40 miles an hour
If you step in front of any car
Going at it will try to break which this car did not
But there's a bunch of random this in the world that cannot be predicted and anticipated and
Yep all right moving to Industrial iot
Shofar horn
Startup has partnered with Google's iot core
To do stream
Data processing at the edge
All Google Solutions
Basically so
Does have Partnerships with Microsoft azure
And AWS this is a little deeper integration
Basically
And it's important to note Foghorn systems does so it has built a complex event processing engine
For the edge it's kind of like Apache Spark
Only instead of
Run across so many
Compute nodes it's designed to run in
One-place Solana Center
And
Bunch of different machine learning models
On the Foghorn software
It's nice
I believe GE is a customer
Incel
The partnership with
Google basically makes girls offering
A little bit
Deeply integrated
With for industrial
Clients in this is a big deal for Google cuz right now
It feels like
Very few
Industrial players are using
Google's iot
Yeah we talked about Google's iot strategy and how it's a mishmash of products that don't
Are presented well as a
Has one solution
This actually is I hope Google is talking about
They're using Cloud vaping Foghorn they're using Cloud iot Core
To gather information
But then Google Cloud pubsub
Is Kathryn dating
Data studio is all used for the analytics to make sense of that data
So this is a whole bunch of Google products
That please Google should be shouting off the rooftops
Yeah it's basically Google's got all the smarts in the cloud
Certain types of smarts at the edge that need
We've all talked Ad nauseam about the
Right so
Google doesn't really have much of a
Play here
Yet
This gets it
Joshua
So
In other Industrial iot
Has
Put out a piece of Hardware now this is a company resume software
It allows you to run containers at the edge so things like docker
Can run on laser-based systems
What day did the original
People got excited
About the stuff
And it basically lets you
Easy to implement software across hundreds or thousands of
Devices which is really important
And really hard so it makes it worse
Cloudlex
Brake calipers
Yay
Necessary what they've done is a hardware
They have created projects
It is a board that stacks on top of a Raspberry Pi
Compute module 3 Lite
And basically it gives it
Industrial
Capabilities
So some of those capabilities are
Separate
Bluetooth processor that can send data even without waking up the main
Model so it's low power
It is designed to work in industrial environments which is
You salty cuz these are
Crappy environments there loud
Vibration
Hot
All kinds of stuff
It will take an external antenna for WiFi
And you can have power from 6 volts or 30 volts
Titus Industrial
There's even a SIM card slot seafood and I got a cellular modem not something you can easily do on a Raspberry Pi buy sell
So lots of cool stuff
They will still work on a bunch of other
They just wanted to offer this because they saw companies
Meeting
A different solution
Customized solution for industrial
Without having to spend
And a lot more
In Industry already
Put out Raspberry Pi's throughout
It might be limited by their capabilities this whole beef up those capabilities and be an add-on to their resistance
Solution which is actually rather smart
A lot of companies develop
Achieve3000
It helps a little bit
Possibly
Can one really interesting thing that I noticed
The processor
For the sin is actually an Arctic o-200 to model made by Samsung
How much is a sponsor
Thought it was interesting cuz he don't see Arctic mentioned in in products that often
That's true
So
We'll keep our eyes open
All right
Industrial Enterprise
Jose Enterprise
Comcast in
Cox cable guide
We talked about getting into
Lorawan Networks
And these are low power wide area Networks
They're usually for like
Private
That works for like warehouses or made
Personal
Works as opposed to like a cellular network
Comcast announced a bunch of
Science
For their machine to Laura when Network including my favorite
Example of
Connector products
Which is a smart
Mouse trap
This is actually really cool because
I've encountered
Connected Pest Control
Three different use cases so basically this is something that says
Hey
In your Warehouse in the middle of nowhere. Something
You can do that without checking
Which actually is really cool
Company using Comcast Comcast
Whether it's about 2 years old but
It's getting a lot more attention
Now
Customers
Cox is also
They have their own
Laura
And they signed a deal with
Cox Automotive which is a giant Fleet Management
Laura as well as
2 track
Where cars are
So these are just too quick examples
One option
Cars with the likes of
AT&T and Verizon
And even
Startups we're doing
These guys want to provide the network
Work with systems integrators but
Yay
Okay let's go
Voicemail from riot
Podcast
Listener hot
The iot podcast listener hotline
Is brought to you by
Speaker of electronic lock
Which way you can have a brand new electronic lock installed in minutes
With just a screwdriver and your own two hands
Using setup
To see what's possible is it schlage.com
This week's voice mail
Is from Clare
Import
Hi this is
Is Claire and I'm calling from Portland Oregon to question about how I can make my smart home
You're awesome for my
6 month old baby
So far I have the August Smart Lock
I have Sonos speakers in his room but I would love any suggestion
Since you have on how I
Suggest
And what we can do
Thank you so much I look forward to your answer
Where are you
Love this question
Because I love
Peoples were actually thinking of
Cool things to do
Connected devices in
Real life scenarios so
Apus
Is a great singer
Here's some crazy idea since you're just
Santa visit ideas
Face it sounds like
Kevin's first idea
I think it's a good one
1 for where your
Where your kid is now at 6 months old
So Kevin you want to talk about the.
Yeah I would
Pinterest the only Amazon Echo device you have in your house
The reason I would do this is because you could use the Amazon app on your smartphone
To drop in and listen to
The baby boy even talk to the baby
And you can
Insane anime
Play
You know if you want some soothing music in there for the baby
Hands-free
However this know that even with the volume on your Echo dot turn down
When you drop in on something
You get an audible charge
And the green light
So if you're trying to check on your baby when
It's sleep
That may not be
Okay so what
I also think this is. Is a great
Take because you can play sound like what does a dog say
And there's a ton of skills that
You know kids will enjoy
Play Silly Songs
When the child gets a little bit older
Probably like 18 months to two years in your thinking about things like
Hey now that you can sleep and handle things on your own
Tell your toddler you want to get out of bed
There's a device that they sell for
Called
Like an alarm clock
Turns different colors
When
It hits a certain time
This is design for parents who want to get their kids to stay in the room
So they can sleep in
These devices are fun but you could do the same thing
You could set it so
At 6:30 in the morning
Or 6 the light bulb turns yellow
The light mobile stay on and stay yellow
Up until like 7 a.m.
At which point it will turn
Sounds Draconian if you don't believe in this sort of thing but we did it with our daughter and it was awesome
We did
Get a little bit more sleep that way
So we always seem like
This light is on
It better be
Emergency
The others since you got a son
When you start potty training
A really useful thing to do
Do is stick a water sensor
By your toilet
Yes
It's actually really handy
I would use one of these
Corded
Watersense
Rinse it off
As opposed to
Some of the others which
May not react well to
This sounds disgusting that all parents know
And
I think those are probably some good things to start with also wants you have the echo dot UK
Can put in things like connected doorbells and you can tell
Hey Ma
Turn off the chime on this doorbell
And then you don't have the doorbell
Bringing drinks
You can have it all
Tell you stories are read audiobooks to you
And baby
Those are all options
Those are all good baby things to have
And hopefully that gives you some fun ideas
OneNote on that sensor
You're going to need a Smart Hub
How'd that you work with that sensor
To my knowledge right now there are no
Dedicated sensors
The Amazon
But then you can just get the whole house or tomorrow
And then once you're doing that
Like you're going to want to set up motion detector outside their door so
Wander around in the middle of the night
You know all sorts of
So that is our suggestion
Remember if
You have an iot question for us
Call Santa Hotline
6 to 3
742 4
And I will tell you as part of my sprinkler
So if you call and message
Before March 31st I'm going to enter you to win
A wise
Camera and we'll just ship that out you have to be in North America
Unfortunately
Next month we'll do a different giveaway
And just to do that just leave your email as part of your
Voicemail
That sounds crazy
We won't run your email on there
And
And now
I feel like we've talked a lot
Let's move to our
Cast David kaiserman
And from Lennar Homes talking about what they're putting in their smart the future
And why they decided
To go with Matt of a as opposed to Siri
Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Samsung artik and I have John Jefferies of Samsung
Arctic here to talk about the identity of things
So remind us really quickly what it is that Samsung art
Samsung artik is a complete
Edge to Cloud platform
That delivers holistic security from the device
To the cloud and makes it so that
Device manufacturers don't have to learn
The Depths and intricacies of
Security
To the point
Secure IT solutions
Got it
So
Why does identity 4
Devices
Matter for the rule of identity and access management
Is expanding rapidly
Because it's no longer just about identifying
People in the New iot World Order
I am too. Oh must be able to identify
Devices sensors monitor
And be able to manage the access to the
Data and you guys are calling this
The identity of
What is that
The Diary of things is the ability to firmly and definitively identify a device on the net
The identity of things matter
For several reasons
First of all you need to be able to trust
The identity of the device to be able to trust the data that it produces
Furthermore you must be able to identify the device
As it's accessing your cloud
And sharing data in the cloud
You and I talked about this and you think that public key infrastructure is the best solution
Why
Public key infrastructure pki
Is proven technology
That creates and unforgeable cryptographic key
That firmly identifies its device in the same way
That publican
Is universally used to identify insecure websites
We are now using that to universally identify and secure iot devices
And their data why is it the best
Because it has been
Developed and proven overtime to be uncrackable and Unbreak
How does Samsung artik pull
Pki and
The identity of things
By building Hardware backed identity of things
Technology and tki management into the Arctic
You make it easy for Enterprises to enjoy the benefits of DKI all of our devices
Burned into them at Birth
If you will
We enable customers to
Bring their own certificate
An automated provisioning of them
And rotate their keys
As may be necessary by their screw cost
To find out more about Samsung artik
Public key encryption and Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Slash
Samsung art
AR Tik
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Dave
Kaiserman
Who is president of Lennar Ventures
Hi David
And I am super great I am sitting here in a linear model home and I've just been taken on a tour and seeing
Holy cow
Lutron
Sonos
Philip stuff
Amazon all kinds of crazy things where to find out
What your future new home
Might look like
Alright David
Talk to me about
Why when are
Is getting into the smart
And they protrude
Sure
Soyo
I think at the simplest level
We build a brand new home
And new really means
Is best-of-breed state-of-the-art
And so what a perfect place from a blank canvas to actually construct
A home that
Works seamlessly.
Wireless
It has all these devices connect
Get together for manufacturers
Entrust
Into
Feels like a
Combat under the hood
Really operates like a fine
Sports car
I9 Sports Car I cannot say that about my smartphone
All right
So
Throughout this process you've been talking to me about experience as opposed to the technology but
My listeners are super into the technology so just run down
Some of the devices and things that you thought was important
Introduce the rest of the world to the
Trick to it starts with a wireless infrastructure and we're proud to work with a company called Ruckus Wireless
A trillion RV was in the Bentley at access points
In the much more Enterprise in Byram
And it brought that into the residential environment
And include a wireless solution with Ruckus access
Appoint as a standard feature of all the homes
We've also worked very closely with the Wi-Fi Alliance
Which is the international standard-setting body for Wi-Fi
In
Cheap mapping our homes like you wouldn't office
To ensure that we have sufficient coverage that there are no dead Spa
The base of the home
Is an incredible Wireless environment that allows things to interconnect
And then we put together best of Ray products from companies like Honeywell and their lyric thermostat
Lutron and Erika Sato lighting product
Sonos
Ring video doorbell
Kwikset and their new Kevo lock that's embedded in Baldwin
Is the higher end
Form factor
Among other things
And really put them all together such that you can control them seamlessly from button
Better on the wall or maybe Pecos that are remotes to applications like the Samsung SmartThings application to your
Your voice by using
Alexa
And so for us
The ability to indistinguishably work across
Voice button
And
Applications of soup
Guys he just said off Madam a
That's good
Actually want you to a little bit more basic like lights they're really important
People so we thought we were going to prioritize connected lighting
The door is important so we priority like
So for people who may not have the chance
Maybe if they're like trying to create the biggest bang for their Buck how should they think about approaching a small
I think it starts with
Great Wireless
And I think
You can't think about the way you
Live your life and you mirror that so
The front door super important
A door lock
That can be controlled both
Remotely and Power
Your voice
A video doorbell that lets you know who's at your front door whether you're at work
Or whether you're in bed
My wife
Love's
Because it's technical or because it
Connected
She loves it because she tells me it makes her look good in her jeans
When she goes out if no bulge in her pocket
Alex Supertramp
On the flip side my wife
I always wonder what would happen
If we needed to open the door in the middle of the night
Maybe our kids were sick and
We need to let somebody in
Would we have to go downstairs and open that door but now we don't have to
So the technology is really faded into the background
But more importantly the stories of how it impacts in your life there's so many of them and we hear them customers
All the time
People have now been moving into these homes with this package
With this all of your homes have this it's not even
So what are the bumps that they found in then
What are the
Experiences that you're like oh my God I never thought of it
So the bumps clearly have been in and around how you activate
The products and how you make it work
For you and one of the things we announced
In June of last year with a partnership
With Amazon
Where they will come to everyone our home
And spend hours with every one of our customers
Chalk everything up
Customize it for the wave
Cancel service has been
By far the most in
Important factor
People's excitement and actually
10 using the product
And then the products
Some cells in terms of be like a door lock
Echo Show in the
Music the notion of how they all work together seamlessly
So that
One voice command
Trigger a bunch of different things
People have been much more interested in
How do you set up a voice command
How does everything how to work
Together so
We've been very
Focused on
Establishing
Suggestion
Write up voice commands like movie time or party time
Or who's at the front door or lock my front door and getting people awareness around
What they can do not how it works
Does Amazon dildos or do the residents build them after they move in
And you together
So we had a list of recommendations
Amazon sits down with our customers
They share a starting list
And then they sit down together and they customize for what they need so if you're a working mom you met
Want to be able to give someone access
List your home during certain times of the day
That may be different than an active adults
Cool watch
How to get their grandkids access less frequently than a millennial
Who wants to be able to let nobody in unless they bring the
Until
We show them the
Tools that they have and then we listen to their life
And we have a real human conversation about what you need
You know what we can provide and we trade a custom solution
Every single
Is this the future of Home Building the future of life
And I think if you look around
When's the last time
People put a
Key in their car door to open it
It's just
Some are expected today that
Cars have
Keyless entry
I think homes
It will be expected if they have keyless entry automated lights
Technology
And I also think that people will expect
Home builders
Not only focus on the mechanical systems of the home the electrical
Plumbing Systems
The Architects will begin to
Provide Wireless
Just like they do mechanical electrical and plumbing plan
I'm at
Homes going forward
Won't use extenders in
Peters
Go use really architected
Wireless solutions that will come down in price as they have
And provide this experience where you
Whatsapp
Sometimes even faster inside the network
In the public internet
You guys did with the Wi-Fi
You guys did the Wi-Fi certified home Stan
Clearly this is the Bedrock
For your home but why choose Wi-Fi
Over maybe some of the other standards that are familiar in the smart home and does that preclude using
Sacre question it doesn't preclude it at all in fact Lutron use as an internal
Proprietary Network clear connect
But the ability to access
Those devices from outside of the home
Is dependent on Wi-Fi so there are
Many different
Marriage is a different
Standards
I think
We pick WiFi for two reasons
One it's brand
And it clearly the world over is recognized
Half of the internet traffic
We know today is over Wi-Fi
And I think the second reason to is
We seen
Most manufacturer
Adopt some form of Wi-Fi integration whether it's
Remotely controlling it from the outside or even internally
The network include things like BL
Wicker front door lock Odyssey uses
Or clear connector
Tricare standard light
Lutron system
We think the unifying
Thread throughout all of those is Wi-Fi
And then on top of that layers different standard
This was a hugely controversial move for you guys I remember reading in
Ice Pro oh my God
Do you get better everything over wires
So
Practice how has that played out and then also how you convinced you know the CD of community and other people who are
Hardwired
I think a couple things one is we have not thrown out the wires in the
I know that's been reported but
That's not true we have
Continue to provide a balance
Amount of structured wiring
With a much more robust Wireless in my
And from a consumer perspective which I think ultimately defines
Many people's perspectives
When's the last time you took your laptop in
And plugged it into
I do it every week but I record a show
So so
Ever the app
Everyone else mini-computers don't even have any
My computer doesn't have an Ethernet
That's right
I think we're finding that it's not one or the other
But it's a healthy marriage about that we still have cable Jackson
Coax in our rooms were pulling out things where we're going
Super extreme environment
Work cry and Ice balance but we do now
Is that people come think of their home at the place that they make their memory
Whether family grows up where they have parties where they do things
I'll be in their minds forever and the technology that they have around them if it different in the home then it isn't
Every other aspect of their life
Brings the home down
And what we want to do is kind of bring the home back up to
Speed
Your car is super technology-enabled it still drives like a car
Just like the office
Is super technological
Still your office your home is just kind of falling behind it so you look at
Companies like apple and Amazon and Google and Samsung
They're all making huge bets on home
Because it's that
Can a gaping hole
In the world where
Life is different inside your home that it is
Almost every
Let's talk about Security in
Privacy
Because you guys set this up and
Do you manage it
So we allow eats
Persons Network to be managed by themselves
Provide them access
Simply to Amazon if you have any questions for adjustments or
We actually provide a 90-day happiness guarantee that
If I need tweaks
The first 90 days Amazon will continue to come out in
Do that for them
But their home is their home
We're not managing it we're not listening in on it
But we're not a technology company and we partnered with people
We take these matters really really seriously and we place a lot of stock
In their level of Neo scrutiny
Security but what we do is build we have a canvas
From which people can actually
Bring all these pieces together now it's more than just
People who live in our home
Turn many people
Come by our model home centers
Want to
Decorating ideas we have a bit of floor plan ideas we have maybe the home automation
We're starting to see that the influence is not just directly to people that are buying home
The people are
Curious
About how all these things work together
Until you go to Best Buy it's very very hard
Understand how the whole system works together
You sit in the couch down our living room you say movie time
And all the subsystem
Scarifier at once
And you get that experience and people are beginning to see that
You know it's about the sum of the parts and not the end of it
Okay
And what about Security in terms of
He put all the stuff in here
Let's say
My Lutron lights get hacked
So far not
However
Let's say there's a vulnerability that
Discovered
How do you ensure that Lutron does this so people
Where's the responsibility first off
And what are you doing
In the beginning
And I think we've been very careful to pick people that have demonstrated to us
Significant resources behind not only security
Customer service
Liability in everything
And instead of having 30 different manufacturers in this home
What heater 9 but will have very
Deep levels of
Conversations in relationships all the way to the senior levels
To make sure
That what they put in our homes
You not only works but it's supported and they're aligned
Towards that with us
Because as they
Look to sell their products
And they look at the deficiencies of retail
When I say reach I mean that aisle at Best Buy
Retail
They want to be able to tell a story about how their product works
As much as anybody
Lennar has more model homes in Target actually has stores
Until the notion of being able to
Having to get it right
Is
Bo tables
And supporting it when things go wrong and they will go wrong
Play Everything Is Not Perfect
Having the infrastructure in place
Really defines the universal
Okay and then what kind of things do you suggest to your users when they
Common in terms of setting up
Like the commissioning and let's talk about the decommissioning of a
How does that process take
Who just started this sub
Decommissioning
Isn't something different
Experience
How to take the commissioning of the home
It's something that we actually wanted
Take away
From the
Perspective of the consumer and do for them
And we want to do it for them in a branded way so
Amazon has just launched its new experts business which is
Amazon employees that come in
To help both activate devices that we
Include with our home
And sell you more devices
That you want to add on to your home
They are super trained
In not only how each device works but how they
Can grow
And we believe that a white glove approach is absolutely essential
At least now even though these are DIY products
They can get very complicated
And so in order for them to work reliably
Together and for the experience really to shine through
We think has to be done in all white clubwear
Okay
Tell me you do have a plan for Deke
Surely you may not have done it
Like what I move out what happens when I move out of your smart
So
Our plan is
Probably the same which is Amazon or
Some bread Partnership of people that have dedicated experts available to you
To do so
Intercourse can people live in their homes for
789 years
Things are going to change
They're going to be new technologies
Our homes today don't include things like Wireless blood pressure
I put the code in the future or maybe Wireless medical devices
There are going to be things that are going to be
Added change
Take it away from the system
And again our belief is that with those changes comes
Sphere and uncertainty
Doubt that should be best delayed by
Sardis
White Glove service
Branzino
So in this model because I mean a granite countertop for example is going to last
Gosh probably forever
I might eventually I might get tired of it and I'll renovate my kitchen but
There is no equivalent yet for renovating your smartphone
Pulling out your old Gear in
Adding new gear
So it's just it's an interesting thought
I spend a lot of time with his I've got devices my home for like 5 years
Json like
These are predictions are not sure that would rather be right or wrong
But I believe the world is a wireless
And that in order for us to
Change
Sayings
Bike locks and lights
Is the fable
You have to think whether it would be a wired world or a wireless World in respect of those
If you believe it's a wireless
Which is the premise
We're starting from
Then you look at the Box
That's on the ceiling that's a Wi-Fi box
The Rock
And you say what what about
What is the radio frequency
What if the
Software
There's a combination of hardware and over the air updates
Can be put together
That will change
Wireless signals that made
But it won't change the nature of what you
Which is Wireless
And it's all
And then you also think about things like the control center
Are the panels where we put all the
Relevant pieces of Technology like the hubs
And we think about things like
Should I be metal
Historically does a Bento Box
Metal and wireless don't, go together
We have a plastic one
Do you have enough room inside of
Do you have enough structured wiring run to other places in the home edit
If you had to attach some sort of wireless device to the network
Those are all things
We think about
And while there's no Assurance of a
Will be perfect
Going down
Future
We got as much as we can
Future-proof
Right to accommodation Not Just Wireless
Wireless infrastructure
To the end devices
Wired into
Structure
To various
Awesome
And if I am a company and I really like this idea and want to work with you
How does that happen how do you pick your part
So the first thing we've done is we've
Partners
Have
The depth of resources to support their cause
Security customer care
Replacements manufacturer
That really limits the world
People that we have work
Because there's so many cool interesting
Technologies out there
But
They don't have the maturity of the industrial manufacturer
And so for us in order to have
Some reliability in this market today restricted ourselves to those industrial manufacturers
All those resources in place
I'm at overtime as people want to bring in their own Technologies that's where Amazon comes
Seldom different things
So will give you the base but sort of the infrastructure that we think is
Solid and reliable
You got to change it as you want
To be clear I could buy it from someplace other than Amazon and bring it in
Okay and final question for you because
Many many many months ago you guys were working with apple and homekit
When are we going to be at home kit come
And then
Les Paul
No I guess it was June
You said
Amazon
Madam is the way to go
So we have a lot of regard for apple and their engineering Carlos and we've been
The products of a plethora
Our decision in moving forward with Amazon was really based on things that app
A service work
The ability to retail additional products of real size
Greater scope
The ability to work cross
Multiple different devices
And still work together with like a Samsung
Right kind of together the strategy of matinee as you call her
Be incorporated into Sonos speakers and incorporate into other devices
We looked at those principles and he said
As we try to sell a different way of living of reimagine way of living
The degree of flexibility that allowed for
Alegria service
That's being provided for
Was very different
Apple was
There's nothing in our homes that couldn't be hooked up the home
Many of the devices we have
Happy happiness
Compatible
But we believe you have to sell a single way of living
A single brand
Partnership
And one that's
Able to kind of stand
Service all the way
Pair device
Awesome alright David thank you so much for coming on the show today
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week