Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we haven't
Kicking it off with the big news which is Amazon
Then we're going to talk about a super stealthy secret startup
IND lighting business that was founded by a former Nest executive
We've got some drama between an
Amazon and Google
We've got the FDA doing some
Cool stuff with companies
Kevin's going to talk about his experiences with the Apple watch and
He's something he's doing
You guys are going to Super Love
Answer voicemail question
From Australia
And we're going to hear from our sponsor
Qualcomm
And
Matt Rogers
David nest
Is Ark
I guess this way
So let's kick this show off
With a message from another one of our sponsors
Eero
Guys you have heard me talk before about Eros 2nd generation mesh wi-fi system
It is awesome I have it in my home
I do enjoy it
The new system contains one zero and then 1/2 too small
Beacons and these are little things you plug in that double as a nightlight and they basically
Mesh access
Spit make your network bigger so I have one in my garage I used to have one of my roof
Hallway you can buy individual Euros or begins to add your current setup even if you got generation ones
Stop and the system start
410 in
And we have a deal for you you can buy euros and get
Free overnight shipping with the
Code Stacy
Free overnight shipping
With Stacy
Wi-Fi routers
Go check out the Eros and
If you buy them
And get free overnight shipping
Shake It Off
We are actually adding to our original recording
Because Amazon
Secret secret
Our secret
Where they talk about
Whole bunch of
Echo products
And of course they did that after we recorded
But we love you guys so much
That we decided
We are going to do
Just tell you what we thought
You kept
Keep us down
Can I tell you what
So I
There were two things that like
There are two things I was super excited about 1
Okay and then one thing I was like what
What day was the Super
The echo
Plus
This is 100
$49 device that
This means it has an additional radio it has
Zigbee
So obviously it has Bluetooth and Wi-Fi because the original one did
Yes
I should not neglect those
The one aspect about this is
You
Can't get rid of
Your hubs that speak
Z-Wave
If you have Z-Wave devices
Because this doesn't have it
But if you're only dealing with
With zigbee devices
You could
Write this is one of multiple devices they announced today and this is the Echo Plus model which is Jesus
Said 14999 and that includes a Philips Hue smart light bulb
Included with it while supplies last
I'm kind of curious and I'm not sure if you know Stacey but I'm kind of curious on the Hub itself
Because obviously I have a wink Hub you fuse Dwayne give you SmartThings
I bought all these works with wink things now I guess we're going to buy
Works with
Echo thing
And they're actually probably
NSA works with
Okay well you either way
I think bad news for the Lincoln Samsung folks in general
I'm just curious I assume I don't have to
Repurposing my old stuff cuz I can control it now
If you've got the
All the existing stuff that
It's a lot of it's done over Wi-Fi
Anyway
Now what might be interesting
Is if
You don't Phillips decided to work with them and they actually
They put their zippy
Bulb switch if this comes with it
It just did away with the
Philips Hue hub
Right right
Does that mean this is good news for people who
Weight hopsewee
Which is which is me I don't want like extra hugs extra Bridges and so on I'm still curious the devil's going to be in the details for me because
Cuz I want to see how the
A smartphone
Companion app works with this because obviously he's my Wink app quite a bit
I'm also wondering you know some of my things are going to get some of them or not is that good
Pékin issue here I don't think so but I'm still curious
Yeah this isn't going to support
It doesn't say that it does
They would have said
So
Now
So that was my Hulu that's exciting there's also
A new Echo
Which is 99
And this is
Just a better speaker smaller
Cloth cover
Kilby processing this this to me is the
Late competitor to Apple's homepod because that's going to focus
Salon sound quality and
Siri
So this should be sound quality and Madame a
And then
This is the other devices
Here's the device I'm also a
The echo spot cuz it's super cute
Askew
Echo with a little
Alarm clock
The little clock face
Did question
It's like a modern chumby it's like I'm not as jumpy it is exactly
But how bright is it going to be
That's what I want to know I don't know
I'm totally buying one
It's $130
Right right now
This is true
This is true so this is I guess I almost a replacement for a. In that it's small
But it also has a display so it's kind of combined the. Show this would be there if their baby
So you can see things on the little screen instead of 2.5 inch display
I thought I read and I'm just double-checking
You can get your camera feeds and you could even take a video call this at somebody on your little chunky like device
Looking at you and you looking at them
Then if there is not a manual cover on that
My camera I do now
My bad my bad
Give up a lot of my
Right right
Sound-wise at 8 probably isn't much better than the. The current. Because it's only a 2 watt speaker very small acts like a smartphone
On speaker
All right maybe I'm not going to buy this
It's all good
Camera
Amazon have a heart
Shutter
We could probably like make one and a 3D printer market and make noise
Low-tech
It's not a sexy
So there's also a new Fire TV which
Not a big deal
OIC I like because if they've added they already have a 4K
Support in the current Fire TV which is what I use and they've added
High dynamic range
Which brings out more color pops wider range of color and
Better contrast I have to 4K TV so this is it
Ostomy
And then
We got lots of new
Skill so they said the vehicles are coming
Your Fire TV
You could tell Matt
The play catastrophe
On the
Weather Channel
Showtime PlayStation Vue
All access NBC Bravo etcetera
They're integrating those
Video content partners
Sport
Control
Okay
Aunt
Two more things
One we're going to actually talk about this later in the show but we were
We didn't know this so
Amazon's introducing routines which allow you to control multiple devices with a single voice commands
All of this. We'll have
Later is actually how to do the Sun
Home so
Prism play Battle
That's still a relevant answer
Button
4 people
Go to bed at night
Turn off this
Now you can just be like Madden a good night
Final item
Calling
And messaging
To a phone
A
Right-of-way / landline
And so this is a box that you
You buy it reminded me of
I remember
It's still around its magicJack 2.0
There you go
So yeah it's 35 bucks
The echo
And this sun like Google will dial91
Because this is a landline.
Text spacing over. Voice over IP to
Cellular you need to have a lan
Right
If you're like me and you don't have a landline
Same here but
You know this is good because so there are still some people with landline that's that's fine
Second as you said $35 is not expensive
And it
Broadens the range of calling because
Before we could just do like
Echo to Echo type calling you those are Echo devices or two
The Echo app
Now it's actually going through cellular other
Landline phones you can make phone calls
And
Condition of this
They're adding we're rolling out
Voice calling
Puyallup
Play Just Like Google home
Yes
Yay
All right so that's all the Echo news that's fit to
Well talked about
Moving right along
Rastelli start
Let's start
Off by tooting my own horn
Yes
Last week
I have been working on a story all summer long
Try to figure out what a company called logo
What's doing
And I knew it was some former Nest Executives and who is consumer products
Finally last Friday
An FCC notice
Application and basically this is a smart lighting startup
So this is from
Eric Charlton
Who is a family member of the Nestea
Former head of business he's got people on there from GoPro from
Fitbit Kathy Sanders who was the former CMO it August is actually
Part of this team as well
In what way
Is it as a lighting Prada
It is a wifi-enabled dimmer switch
Which
Is there two of them
Elvis and Wanda
Sativa and
I also
Heard so this isn't in the story that I wrote
Time but I also have heard that this is a smart lighting switch
Doesn't
Choir
Neutral wire
Is really interesting
And also in the FCC filing this also has bluetooth support Dimension Wi-Fi but it says both right
It does
And
Assuming
I will assume that it will have mesh capabilities cuz that makes a lot of sense for lighting
Because your phone's name
Phone won't always be close enough
Turn it on or off
So yeah
Again we don't know the details we won't know the details until
Sometime hopefully
I'm really excited about it but should be soon because typically want something go through FCC certification it's usually
Within weeks or one or two months at most before
Prague is actually launched
Formation Apso
You know Jose
Christmas almost over so we'll say I
October
Maybe November
And as a lighting aficionado
Iams you need more ways to control your thoughts
Like I still have some dumb switches in my house and
Got to take out my
WeMo dimmer switch because I have decided that it
WeMo dimmer switch
Do not put it in
In your bedroom
Very bright
Not just when it goes off in the middle of the night be
Because it has no internet access but also just in general
Little indicators
In a dark room
Universim
I just to be clear we say dumb switch we're not judging
Number one and number two I agree with you on pretty much
Any device or switch or anything that hasn't LED I've actually used electrical tape
My sister shut off for cover of the LEDs in the bedroom in particular
You're just too bright
If I let it it would look like
Like a little like
What is glowing
All right
Next story
Is it a question
Issaquah
I guess my question is to you because I can't answer it because I do not have an Amazon Echo Show and you do so my quest
Question is do you watch YouTube videos on it
Baidu
So I
We watch gory videos all the time cuz it's right there at the
I called the breakfast bar it's where my daughter and I will sit in
Breakfast sometimes
More like hey
Madimak show us some Corgi videos and
Pick one and we watch
Well I guess you're not doing that anymore because Google has basically shut that service down
On the Echo Show
So no more videos on Echo Show from YouTube
I know
End
Why
What's that's the thing nobody's talking about
Companies don't play nice together you can't buy a Chromecast
Google lets you know support certain Amazon services
But I think is
Amazon uses a fork of Android
And that is there fire OS
They are not a licensee of Google's GMS or Google mobile services that's an agreement that all device maker
Your sign if they want include the official Google apps so this is no different than the Fire tablet that's the issue
Eric and I don't think it's going to change anytime soon because I don't see Amazon
Signing on as a GMS license
I don't think it's going to happen I think you not going to get you two back at least not an official capacity
So Google shut this off
Because they were just waiting for
The official statement is at its
Ifrit technical problem then I guess you could say well technically
Amazon is not a licensee I don't think it's a
A true technical Pro
Obviously you can get YouTube running on just about any device and Google
So this is not unprecedented by any means
But I don't know the stories that I read everybody
Open today
Nobody's talking about the GMS license which to me is the core issue here
Believe you because
Sounds very
Not ever
Consumer but like as a business person
And I think we're going to see cuz Amazon is also pushing really hard on its part
To work within its show ecosystem
Do certain thing
I think things are getting kind of dirty
Smart speaker assistants
Looking good
I'm feeling a little down here about this
So no more Corgi videos for me
But
I might
Get better wearables that are
Tested by the FDA which
I'm kind of excited about I don't know
I am super excited about this for a couple reasons one is I think I'm the last show I mention I got the Apple watch
Three with LTE and I'm already seeing
More
Informational Health Data being sucked in by this thing
Metrics that I have not seen before which is awesome but
Secondly
When
We can start getting these things certified as medical devices and you'll cease consolidation you won't have people have to wear a sir
Turn device to measure save it
You know heart rate because
Cuz they have me be at yours me or whatever maybe when that can be approved
Certify into an existing device such as
Device you want to wear song
Yay
Yes that is awesome and I'm super excited because I would like more
Accountability on a lot of these device
So you know how I was always looking at these studies from places that talk about
Hey
This heart rate is actually accurate or this calorie burn
Is totally inaccurate so I am looking forward to having
High quality
Jada and then is someone who
Who I actually
For a while had to
Some heart issues that my heart was fine
But they're trying to figure out why
I kept fainting all the time
Let's put you on a Holter monitor which is horrible
Battery powered Giant
Thing that you strap on
Where all the time
24/7
Uncomfortable it's cumbersome and I decided not to do it
Because it was so cumbersome
If only I could just
Actually use my
Fitness watch or something
Like that
We here
We're close
Close
Yes I mean the deal is it that certain products such a
Those from Apple Fitbit Samsung Etc can get pre-cleared through the FDA
And I agree with you on getting some kind of standards for the data because there isn't a smartwatch or
Exercise tracker that I haven't tried
And the variance in heart rate for example it's just
Massive still and we need to have some type of certification says we'll take a little tolerancia no not a wide
The data that we have
Several times in the past year
However
They announced health
Way back with the Apple watch 3 issues ago
They've done a lot here
And they should be commended because they're the ones that I think have really pushed
More so than anybody else for this type of standard
They stopped at every closed ecosystem is sometimes a real pain to get your data out of apple health
I give him credit B
Because they have not
I'm going to throw up
Cool little monkey
I would be excited about this not just for like the fitness and
Heart rate
But there's also a
A whole.new
Kind of class of things called
Shareables
And it's a stupid name
But the reason they call it that and not hearing aids is because the FDA certified
But there are a bunch of classes of devices that you can plug into your headphone type devices
Put in your ear and you can actually hear better
I would love to see some certification moving
Forward I'm hearable Zora
Being able to actually call them hearing aids and seeing a lot of innovation in that
Area because there is so much Innovation happening
On the chip side
And on the product side about audio processing
The old hearing aids
You just going to stick like your airpods or something
Be better
And so I'm actually
Maybe not the first thing everyone thinks about when they think about FDA
Pre-certification
Or getting some sort of
Leniency and developing these things
I think that will be a huge area
I'm also going to the audiologist
Worried about my hair
Used to cover music
Can the day
Covered it's just a little too much to do we did it
Honestly
Let's talk about
Autonomous cars
Because
Because the sooner I stop driving
Happier
So
Ford is teaming up with
Lyft
Tell us about
Yes please
Yeah this is interesting and recently announced so therefore it has been working in autonomous cars for the better part of six
7 years now they are partnering with Lyft
To try and figure out how to effectively
Dispatch self-driving Vehicles so if you're a Lyft driver
Where I can send Uber driver to you in the future
Cedar Tavern
Partnering with these Ride On Demand services but
Basically just trying to figure out where should we do this with cities what kind of infrastructure do we need to maintain the fleet
And so on and so forth
Customer experience
Kind of interesting on how a big car manufacturers starting with a
This ride on demand service it's also worth noting that for was one of us
First feedback
2010 to work on the Wi-Fi connectivity between cars not Wi-Fi in your car but
Car talking to another card using WiFi they demonstrated
Structure it doesn't use Wi-Fi
Uses I believe a spectrum band that is also allocated for Wi-Fi
But it's not
Correct
Vehicle vehicle
Structurescan Point Smart City it's all part of the same
Pay myself yes
Yes they did do that
Actually Qualcomm put out a chip
Probably
I'm going to say
Out there sponsored by the way
Two months ago it's actually one of the first pieces of silicon
Embed allof
This vehicle to vehicle and vehicle infrastructure
Connectivity into
Which is a big step because
Beforehand
You know it was all talkative silicon
So now they're silicone
People can actually start
So that's a big deal
So we're actually going to start seeing cars that communicate something to other cars
Relative
Yeah if I'm not mistaken that Qualcomm chip with a 9150e cd2
Which is the first cellular vehicle to everything solution as they say
Yes
Yes I never remember the
Ship names
I'm surprised it's so aptly named
Like because I'm a
All right and now
We should move to Kevin
Your secret crazy cool project
I called your
Play my secret lab haswell
I'm just starting to work on this
Sad and it is basically a way to use
An Apple Watch or actually any iOS device that has Siri to control non homekit device
Faces by voice
There's a project out on GitHub called bridge and are plugins Google or for home
She set up the homebridge project on a Raspberry Pi
Plugin for wink for example so I could then say
Tell Siri to control things on winky another not get certified so that's something I'm working out
Future but in doing all this research
Kind of transfer how to do this I realized with the Apple watch
People probably overlooked Siri if they don't use homekit Smart Home devices and here's just a little tip that I found
When I
Want to use my wash to turn on the lights or turn lights off or whatever I actually have to go and open my Wink app on the Apple watch
Watch and that's not the quickest thing to do because you got to press the digital crown and a little wink icon in the
See your bubbles of apps it's so easy to just tell Siri to open wink or
Open SmartThings when I do that
It literally just shows my shortcuts
From my Wink app to turn the kitchen light on turn the kitchen light off
Don't go talking around on your watch if you're using wink or SmartThings just say
Tell Siri to open the app
Chicken much faster for you
We'll have more information on the project I really get that working
Good luck bridge is probably in the same scale is openhab which is my pet
Been working with on and off
And I haven't really talked about it much on the show
Is getting it up and running
Was just
Not user-friendly
Their intention of listeners who are probably
Really Adept at coding
Loading things onto a pie or
For most people
This is going to be 2
Much so that's why we haven't talked about it but
I should probably write it up
Put it out there
Sometime in
We each have our secret side projects
Kevin is probably a little bit
I'm not a coder I just love tinkering so I'm learning on the way so I don't want people to have an expectation that I can just go
Whip up lines and lines of code it takes me some time but there's tons of great
Create documentation out there
Once I had open have running
On my way
I
Could spend
Hours it's like a PowerPoint presentation where you start moving things
Adjusting stuff
You have that much granular
Control over your device
So
Kevin you should actually tell us a little bit about because when we last talked
Have your Apple
Watch with LTE
Oh that's right
That's right I've only had it for about 5 days so real quick
I am very impressed I think it was well worth the upgrade for me I had an Apple watch
Series 2 that I sold
Privately so I have tested LTE calls quite a bit they work
Really really well for me I was actually out on a 3-mile run using Apple watch
Offering to play music but always to track via GPS and heart rate what you can do with the series 2 model
And
Friend of mine called me
It's about 8:30 at night as I'm running down the street in my local little town and I just
Tap the watch to pick the call
Did not have my headphones on
It was a little challenging for me to hear him because there was traffic going right
Next to me I was on the shoulder he said I sounded fantastic I was
Shocked so we had a 5-minute chat while it was
Keeping up about 8:30 mile pace and I'm like dude there's a hill coming I got to go
So I hung up
I later tested the next day a call to
That same person while I was taking the dog for a walk out on the trail and I'd this time did have
I had set on
He said I sounded the same which was surprising that that speaks to how well the microphone is on the Apple watch
I could obviously hear him much better because of being pipe cancer my headphones but on the plus side those are all good things I can connect
I can reach out to my family make a call in an emergency
I need to work on my notification
4 second
Things to watch and I'm like it's not important
Side detriment here
Vacations but all in all
Okay and
Do you get a sense that this could be the future of devices like
The future compute
The new model for it
I would say so and connectivity is liberating when your attitude
So from that perspective yes
Obviously we have battery life challenges a 10-minute phone call took the watch battery down 10%
For example so this is not a primary phone device I've read reviews and
People that sang this is going to be like
And it shouldn't you shouldn't expect that when the Box battery is 10% of the capacity of a smartphone battery
Literally so
We have to figure out a battery problems
Challenges there but yeah I do think you know having that kind of connectivity
Are you all the time we had it with the phone today
So it's just moving into wearable absolutely
Computing and accessed
Intelligence as opposed to phone
Phone calls cuz
Phone calls most
Phone
Applications
Information so
To that point that's really good actually have tested Siri a couple times
Just as on a walk just to get information because in the new watch
She will actually sweet back to you
Which is nice to look at your screen that will only work if you have Kinect
So
I could try that on an Apple Watch to when you're out and about and don't have your phone with you
Siri is not going to work
So by all means this could actually
Bring more intelligence to your wearable because it's connect
Write that to me is excited
Cuz you know how many times do you pick up
Your phone's like
Look up the weather
20 minutes later
Twitter
This is my personal challenge
Well let's pick up
Voicemail so
We have
Voicemail
Jonathan
Who is wondering how to handle multiple action
So let's
Hey this is Jonathan from
Australia
Listening to
Stacy on
This week in Google thank you
Not really
Planning to be noisy person but now I have the Google home
I'm wondering
10 MI
Get it to do two top with one
I want to say to my Google home
Lake my life
Civil and for the Google home to turn on
The TV in my bedroom
I don't say maybe play music on Spotify
In the kitchen
Not really able to see
Figure that out I know that's probably not
Technical questions but if you can get me through this I'm going to stop buying stuff
Thanks Stacy
All right I love getting Australian
That's my site
To I
Have done what you asked I done it will talk about it both for your case.
With the Google home
And also with the Amazon Echo
Because a lot of people have those and might also want to
Create basics
What are scenes
Ways that I
The first is or the Google home
It's company called stringify we've talked about it but
Have been purchased by
Comcast
So I feel like will this be supported
But what you can do is
Yoodownload stringify
Uconnect whatever devices you
Want to it so your Google Assistant
To go home and what you end up doing is you create a command so like movie night and then you pull in all
What's the other devices
That work with that
Make basically what stringify calls
Flow it's a little
It's not complicated but it is a little
Weird to do
If you don't know what you're doing
The flows flow from
The left rights
We do
Not everybody does
So the flows will come
Pull the devices onto the screen
Basically
Then you're like soap
When this happens
You can do
Possibly a dozen I've never gotten more
Loso and basically
You just say
Tell stringify to
Start move
And then poop
Your scene has been
So that software is current
Play free and it works really well sometimes there's a bit
It's not a lag exactly but sometimes it takes a while if
If you have a lot of stuff
Look for it to all happen
So be patient there it's not
Instantaneous
This is all happening on the server side like after 8
Like a good night scene
Can take like a man
For everything today
It's a lot of time to me
Yes I mean
Yeah maybe you don't do it for things like
I had one setup for when I
Yoga and I would have it
It's still very handy
Tell stringify to
Start yoga in my
Shades will go down
My
Hue Lights with turn to the
Take out soft
Color at 50% my Harmony
Would come on because to Amazon video that I would do it would come on to
Do the Amazon
Prime on my
My television
And my AC would go down to like 75
And that was
All of that happened
I didn't really
Tell you what this I wish we had a localized
Version of a string of fire and if that we could run a server at the house at the device so it wasn't cloud-based but that
It's just me your next project
Olivia other option this won't work for you Jonathan because
You don't have an echo you
You have Google
A similar sort of
Effort can be done
Untrue a site called you know me yof
Vendo MI
They support the Amazon
Echo stringify also supports the Amazon
Echo yonomi does not support
Google home
That I can see
Yet so same set of action
Very fun
Works well and
You can also do things with
Gift
You can actually so you can do it yes recipes to set some scenes
Set scenes
Through stringify
With
Which is a little weird
But if you
You really want to just bring that in
I don't know why you were
I would also say it cuz you've mentioned the word and it's the right word you mentioned work scenes many times
And that's really what we're trying to do here in a sentence
And what I would do I would keep an eye out on the Google assistant app because they have
Listen to past they have
Shortcuts
They support shortcuts where you can customize what
Your command is what you're going to speak and what it does
But you can't do multiple actions with those yet
I would not be surprised if shortcuts becomes word Racine do multiple
Thanks
If the gas on my car I don't have any inside information
But that's
Truly missing from Google home and I would
Meet
You know I still can't get the actual shortcuts
Work well for me
I'm cursed you guys man I try to install all kinds of
In like this week I was going to tell you about the August smart locks
But so far my installation effort is
Great big brick wall
Star Wars their butt
For some reason it
Just can't find
In the app
It's always something
So yeah this I say this not to throw August under
The bus
Because you guys
Sometimes this is hard and I do this all the time
For a living
And I still
Hit these weird walls where I'm I
Like what's happening
The people who sent me this
Persevere
Let us
Take a break for a message from our sponsor
And then after that
We will have Matt Rogers who is a co-founder of
Nest
Talking about Nest security
Google Assistant it's going to be a good
State
For all of that
Hey everyone we are interrupt
AT&T internet
With a message
From our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Qualcomm and I have Raj talluri here
Who is an SVP and GM
Iot at Qualcomm
Hi Raj how are you doing
Breakfast
Call, Ms
Well-known
As a semiconductor
Hair designs
You guys are getting into the smart
So people have been talkin
About the concept of the smart
Four-decade
When do you think it'll be realized
Actually very gradual
Single event in time
You have to come look at the whole ecosystem
Most of us
Funeral homes
And I don't just buy like
Smart home setup one time you'll be by
No one at a time like this
Smart TV yellow speaker
Light bulbs and so on so what happens is that gradually your home
Get smarter and smarter
Problem is the fact condition
Because you don't buy them all at once you may end up buying different things from different manufacturers that have various kinds of ecosystems
Psychedelics
Make them all work together is really dead
So what is Qualcomm doing
Approach is to build
Products that can support multiple protocols
Add multiple videos
1 SOC
For example recently launched
NSLC called UCF 4020
I do that she the first
Chip that support multiple RadioShack Wi-Fi
Bluetooth
15.4
So this device can
Connect to different
Protocols
Different
F-35 customers
Make a product
Then what happens is all the different products
Different radios
Each other and being something
No
In addition to the physical layer
We also put in
Enough memory
Time in Australia
Austin power this chip
So that it can support multiple
And so on so that
Different
Products from different manufacturers
That support different profiles can also intraplate
And how do you handle
Security with device
But why does Noah connected
System can be
2% + 20
Security Incorporated lot of Hardware basic unit
Features in Terraria
Set so that when customers make products using a chipset they're very secure even though they
Connect multiple
Where can listeners learn more and get started
Qualcomm.com
Flash IRT and get lottery
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's game
Is Matt Rogers
B founder
Product officer
Over it
Hi Matt how are you doing today
It's super great to have you
Alright so last week was a big one
I asked you guys
Launched a security system
Upcoming doorbell and made some product updates
So we talk about those
And we'll get started with just the first Big Sean
Can question that everyone's
Asking which is
Nest security why
Go there
That especially since it feels like
Everybody is
It's goin down
Don't think about building new product want to find out
A lot of people actually everyday problems that you have
Energy
Home safety felt like the next natural extension
A lot of our cameras are Nest cams are used for
Security license
Is really unnatural condition
I'm already there anyway and you thought about building
Security out in Chicago
Why use umbrella
Okay so what are the holes that you
You saw that you see
I think you're feeling with
Is it still too hard
So we serve a lot of people have security
The ones that do they feel like
A pastor remember the PIN code
Did not reach out the door
Yeah because of race against the clock for the alarm system goes on when they get back to their home and the middle tonight
Around 90% of time when you're just living with it everyday
As opposed to that 1% of time and you actually I need to use
And what kind of features in body that
Do we think about
We purchase it from several different angles
You make it easy
Go to the pin pad if you want to use that
But we don't think most people use that so we created this mess
For kids
Everything that could be
It is there.
So you can open up the best app and disarm you on that way and if you forget
Which is xur paper play
Did you forget to arm
You're on the road are you already at work
Will send you notification saying hey
Do you want on your system
And
Right now you guys have the
Tags you have some sensors that have
A couple capabilities built into them and then you have to
The guard The Hub
How other Nest products
Work within
People use our Nest cams today for security
Flying drone
You're not there
So integrating our cameras with Nest secure was our first priority
About the whole experience
What things would you want to know end
We've learned
Is that the video feed is IQ the most important thing for them
To verify that something thrown into home
Those who have security systems today usually have false alarms
And the false alarms can be caused by any number of things
Having that video to know what's really going on
So
Do your phone notifies you that notification itself
What's happening in your home
What did you learn for the robbers
And at the most basic level they don't want to be caught
So they look for homes were doors unlocked and it's really easy to get in
Look for master bedroom
So if they see a camera
That's already a big barrier that I can work on that house I want to be on sale
I want my face overseas
With this I talk to some people and they're at they're looking at this and they're like
This is
Neat I like
DIYs
Security this week
What's compelling for that perspective
But they're looking at the Price Point Inn
They're saying
Expensive
And I know that when the nest thermostat came
That was a big deal
For many teeth
So do you think this is
Price for the Main Street
We think about pricing
Total cost of ownership with all of our products as well as something that you buy one value over time
There's no contract no walk in those under think so
Yes
First point of purchase it says on the high side and frankly wanted to build a premium best-in-class
Those things always change over time and you want to start at the top and build the best experience possible and things
The premium version
That's the only kind of the value of the product
Is immense compared to cannabutter
Of course you get lots more valuable
Okay I am looking forward to being able to
Unlock my alarm system
Which I feel like
You guys could totally
That's My Hope
You're right we could probably do it today
This is anything that we
You working a lot of beta testers and field testers of our current
And facial recognition technology
Is not ready for
Today is a lot of situations where we still see every once in awhile we'll get it wrong
Especially comes to your home security and safety
Uncertainty but also user in
The one we created
Play explicit that the users taking the tag
But that doesn't signal enough user
Have you want to ask
That way song
All right
Let's move to the other I thought this was actually a big deal in the announcements
So you made which was putting Google Assistant
On the nest cam
Indoor IQ
And
So it feels like nesting Google are actually
Maybe trying to work a little bit more closely together for a while
There were two weaves there was
Google home and then there is nasty
It felt like they were
Working together basically so what
Can we take from this
About how things
I don't know how have they changed it Google and nest
Are you guys working
More together
We are working very well together
Virgo
We really do working quite closely together
Delete the Google Assistant Nest cam IQ
But we could do in terms of
The eyes and the ears and hands
What you want to do with your voice
Your people use their Google home a lot for music today
Google play me some music
What more things can you do with it
Partnership
Can I check a little bit further
Significantly
Device to device Communication in town
All the way
Okay and then
There's really became Android
So
They're still
Give me an offer exists
Android things is a great package.
I have to do
So it was really important that allows just started to go and
Grab this
Operating system get some software by some still working
Get up and running size heated
Are you guys using that in your new devices or
We are see my end up in the brain
I'm sure they appreciate the advice you guys
Okay
So you talked actually about feeding some of the nest information
The Google home and I think that's a really important thing
Back in the day I remember
Talking to Tony
Tony fadell about the site
Siri context aware
It feels like
On one side Google has a lot of the machine
Learning ability
To make the sort of context aware home
Possible
And you guys have a lot of the physical Hardware
So I'm curious if that Vision still stands
How its chain
20 left
Setting up my job to keep it going
Admission is not changed at all we are still looking to build the conscious home
To take care of
Turn the World Around It that has not changed
Is anything actually
How do you build that given
The market that we
We have today which is super fragmented
And Boolean products
From a bunch of different places and maybe different operating systems
Mobile devices in the
I don't see them
Yes there's a lot of different varieties of Technologies out there
But at the time the most important level witches have a user's level
That you were able to tie them all together so
Fireworks at Nest program has
Even now
Things to Google assistant so with the apis for the Google Assistant
Michael Anderson
And we'll start school
Most homeowners never have to worry about that because
It's our jobs
To make it all works
Okay and how do you think most homeowners are going to interact
Because I agree with you that a lot of this
Taking place it still feels kind of far off for like an easy user interface but voice was a big deal
So how do you think
Will call
Intuitive homemade I don't know what to think about this
How are you
Peking that will exist
People winter
Voice is great but you can't use it for everything
So the reality I think we need to have
Variety
But people use phones don't really important
Watches
Interacting with something
And that one day hopefully we will use our watches to tag in and out of her house
An example
Del Sol TVs are greater face
Actually watching video
Everything about having
3 cameras in your home for cameras watching the
TV
Is a fantastic experience
You want to be able to tie all these things together
We have to have teams working on all these different
It's worth it
I don't disagree with it being worth it
Okay what's a homekit the biggest question that I see coming in is about
These Multi-Device household
Or should I buy homekit
Or should I limit my device
Purchases only those that are
Our home should be locked into anyone platform
You changed
Smartphones every year every two years
But your home is probably most expensive purchase
It's your longest turn asset
Tire home
Switch phones
It doesn't make any sense
So you obviously have a great presence in Iowa
And we're always talking about Apple
Integrated home care experience
We're not there today but one day we will be
All right Wilmette thank you
You so much
For coming on the show
Thank you
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more
OT news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week