Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house and your co-host
Kevin tofel
With a lot of Amazon
Fit for Microsoft
Put not her suit and tie
Plus we've got a spat
Between Google and Amazon
Walmart
Shopping for iot sensors you're going to want to hear this and
The things I learned at an event last week at Target
Discussing sustainable business models for The Internet of Things
Kevin has a quick review of a device that he installed in his home
This week
So all this and more await us sponsored by
Lux products
Who you'll hear from later on in the show
We're going to also have as our guests who Paul Basu from NGP capital
And he has got
A really insightful view on what people need to consider
When investing in The Internet of Things
He thinks we've been spoiled by the cloud
So life is going to get
Pretty hard for IT department ever
And now a word from our sponsor home isn't just a place it's a feeling the feeling that you're safe
Enjoy the things that matter most weather for your home or business ATT helps keep you safe so you can feel for
Protected wherever you are introducing the ADT Security starter kit everything you need to get started with ATT
And putting a camera professionally installed for only $49 visit att.com
Splash podcast today to learn more require 36-month monitoring contract installation
Nation piece of pie easy pay required certain markets are excluded licenses available at 8
Att.com Florida ID through f0001 121 Louisiana Ave
1:6
3/9
Last week
I was in California
And watching
AWS
From my computer for part of the time in
Amazon
They did a great job
Watching a bunch
Of iot services
Rent out the list but we're going to focus on a cup
It wasn't actually a bunch
If you read their press release it was the slew
That is a fairy
Cinnabon
Who is more than 3 and a slew
Yeah
Maybe we should ask madam
So what day do you want to list
Some of the things they now
I sure some of these are available in preview or coming soon so I'll know that right up front
Breath about bad AWS iot one click
Which is available in preview
That's to enable single button devices to print to do whatever you want
Dash theme shopping like this way it's more of maybe you want to call customer support
Jesus is a suite of three things I'll just list them out and talk about them
AWS iot device management
AWS iot device Defender which is coming in the first half of next year in AWS iot
Analytics
Alright.
The other two
Two things
Go back and talk
Amazon free artist
So let's tackle
Device Defender device one click
And Analytics
These are basically
Some of these have actually been around like device management
Amazon has had for a while
Company a while back in added a lot of this so
They're just beating up some of their Chi
Capabilities
Device Defender is interesting
Because
It's going to allow you to apply to wristox2 any iot system
That you've got hosted in
Amazon's Cloud devices
Behaving oddly
CBS network
Say hey why is that
Or rather it will say
Yep and I didn't I did not see the event
Unfortunately my take on this was that you could apply security policies to devices
And this would be monitoring those policies of the compliance those policies at the device
Yes in actually this is hell
A lot of
Companies were doing
Managed air
Devices out
Field today they just had to build it
Custom
So if you think of companies like a large thermostat vendor that sells men
Any thermostats to consumer
Xiamen other
They have this sort of thing
So this is actually a really
Useful product
And it makes total sense for Amazon to launch this for
Device management
He had a lot of this so they're just kind of packaging it up
Great Clips
I was intrigued by Adele
We've had this
Kind of with
The dash bus
It is something that
Prior to this you did have to program your dash button
So you had the iot
Amazon Islam
Song Happy
I think they're just kind of making it a little easier and
Kind of getting rid of some of the obstacles so that developers are hackers tinkerers can
Get started with them I don't know if they already had the pre-configured Lambda instances
That work with 54 so that's that seems to be new to me
Again removing obstacle see if they can figure a Lambda instance
And so on
So yeah they had it but I guess you could say that beat it up or made it a little bit easier to use
Let's go to AWS Greengrass
This is something
Gosh so much earlier this year
This is an edge instance or Edge compute the time
Which is better functional programming
Switch
If we lost all of you
I totally get that
Lambda is Amazon server list
Computing
Effort
I guess it's how to think of it I always think about it
In plain English terms as
You know
When you have
Compute instance with Amazon
You have to have a server that's ready to be spun up
It is there
And if you're doing whatever you ask it to do
You don't want to have a server just existing
Throughout the house
Parody of time
Because it's costing you money and you have a device it's going to wake up
And it's going to say hey
I want to send some information
Innocence information
With Linda
And the circle is architecture
What you do is whenever you call it up
Amazon
I Spit It Up
And that cost less
Really brilliant for
Coyote stuff
Yeah absolutely and the only thing I would add to that is
I believe that as a computer service you just said you know anytime you needed your call Lance there that's true but it can also be a
Event-driven so it's not like you have to do something
If your devices need the computer
They can reach out to AWS Lambda and get that compute
Yes
So green grass basically ties the functionality of Lambda back to
Pushed a lot into green grass
I'm just going to add a link
In the show notes that explains this little bit more because it's really complicated and most of you guys probably are never going to care
Macro perspective
One more news
The other piece of news is Amazon is done
What it called Amazon
And
Our house stands for real-time operating system
It's these
Tiny little os's that run on microcontrollers
So
You don't like you that the OS for your phone
A computer
Microcontroller are top of the world is free
Amazon
If I could just go back one second and just
Only because again I did not see the event but going back to the green grass bit and the edge compute
Just this is jumped out at me and I don't know if they'd had this or discuss it at the event but out of the press release and said
Greengrass ml interface ml machine learning
Models
To perform inference locally get results in and make smart decisions quickly even when they're not connected
So this kind of goes back to that
Piece I wrote on the blog about
Making smart and smarter with machine learning and AI I have a feeling that's where this will come into play
Yes
Kevin will be happy
There's a reason you are on the show
Yes and back to free art is basically every connected device needs to run an art us
Or at least run some kind of operating system
If it said
Tiny dumb device
The Big Challenge here is if you are a developer
You're trying to build for so many of these right now cuz back in the day everybody who made a microcontroller
There are a lot of them
Call Heather
If you wanted to build something
Software for something
Then you actually have to start with a custom OS in that sucked
And developers to make a good flat
Developers you want to have as few
Operating systems is few platforms for them as possible
Arm launched one a while back there others like
This is actually free
An Amazon now having this
Means that I'm assuming
Don't make it so easy
If you're running this on your device
That you're going to be tied and almost automatically with one click service
AWS which is
Right now
A lot of the other Cloud vendor
Have deals
Mysterious like
Sudbury Centre,
Needs to link your stuff automatically into their cloud
So
By getting into the game
An artist
It was some kind of like sidestepped all of the individual board efforts that it be
The efforts to connect individual boards
Specifically
And I have a question for you and because I don't know the answer and I
And if you don't that's fine too we can look into this would you say this is comprable to
Google's Android things
I don't know
If I could
Nail someone from Google down on Android things
I might it might be but I feel like everything's might be for
Requires maybe larger memory
Venda traditional artists
I would have to
You should look into that we should take some time to look into that because to me this is Amazon's big iot push and it made me question
What are the competitors doing
To the person that is like a big competitor so what are they doing
But maybe it's not the same
Comfortable exercise for bigger stuff
You need 500
512m
Jeffrey Artis
Yeah
So yes that's the answer
Okay
But even though
Which event happened last
Microsoft
They have iota
Cloud news
I do not know why this
It's fine
They actually Microsoft
Has had an iot presents for a while in a lot of companies
They use it
Because no it manager gets fired for buying
Actually I'm pretty sure that's not
They have iot Central
They've had an iot Hub platform
It was like platform-as-a-service
And now they have iot Central which is a software-as-a-service
So basically they've taken everything they've done
With all of their iot analytics device management
That you had to customize and they said you know what we're going to build a couple scenarios in Bryn off of that is a spur
I saw the demos there very compelling
If you
Want to start something
You can start there
There's going to be a lot more features coming over time
And I don't really know what else to say about that other than
Basically everybody and their mother is trying to
Make it easier to put your devices on
Promise results
In fact along with that to make things easier they have made the Azure iot Hub device provisioning service
Is generally available
Is pretty sure that was out in like a preview for quite a while now
Yes in you know between you and me I can never figure out what's app
What's today what's
Yeah what time is it
Well this is definitely
Yes as a
Okay so that's
That's not all
That is not all
Because a tree
Amazon also discussed
For business
Yes
Big picture
Amazon wants to move into the office
Open talk about for quite some time so it makes sense
We have lots of questions
Because
I'm just going to save as a madam
I'm trying to like
My biggest challenge so far in my life
With my smartphone
Has been
Making my Spotify app
Accounts
Work on all night
So I signed up for multi-user
Spotify
Which is not based on devices based on people
And my daughter
Who is the most common Spotify listener
Cuz she's 11
That's all
She actually isn't legal
In the Amazon
Amazon
Doesn't really recognize her email address
And she doesn't get
Mattamy functionality basically
So then I had to address for my home
Associate that with my
The point
Is
That's complicated in my family
When we bring this into
Office
It becomes wackadoo
So
Yeah it's going to be an IT logistical
I want to say nightmare about this a challenge for now
Because I don't know how this is going to be implemented and I can see why they want to do this and then there's some of the examples are saying
I'm sorry
Hey Madam a you know get me a conference room
Or
Give me directions to the right room
Piece of broken equipment
I get all that
But the challenge that I see
It's the same one that Google actually faces
Because you
Typically can't use a Google Apps account for like Google Assistant Google home
And that's because of businesses
On their data
And the way these
Assistance work is they work with that data
So
How is Amazon going to manage that
Businesses
And misses are very eager I talked to lots of businesses who are very
Madame a into their offices
And there are certain companies that have built skills to do
Things like
Hainan
What were sales
Q4
Facebook
The questions I still have I've read through
Amazon stock
There's no mention it like
Microsoft active directory
For example
Which
I kind of like you can
Blanket to Office 365 Microsoft Exchange
It lets you made it so people come in with their personal Amazon account so this assumes that everyone's going to have their own personal
Amazon account
It's probably not a crazy assumption for most people but there's going to be people who don't have this
I wonder if they will have
Atty the the work email addresses to Amazon business account so to speak for this
I don't know don't go personal
Reading through this book Kevin and I are a little confused because
Rockets
Divvied up
You can invite
And users it says to enroll their personal
Madame a account
With your mad at me for business account
So there is some
Teacher there to allow you to use a personal account but
I don't know if people going to want to do that with her employers number one
And secondly in one of the case studies that actually work they say they build a skill
And it called a private still see what they private skill that we've built
Matt American Reserve conference room style help tickets for Community management team and provide important
So
Maybe that's a way to get around the whole you know having access to the business data
You do it through
Enabling your own skills at your corporation
I don't know a lot of different ways this can go and I don't know if it's really clear yet to anyone
We will see
What challenges related
What was it called
That was a nightmare
This is bad times more so cuz it's more devices more skills
I'm in a household with people who do things I have no one in my house loves the fart ass but imagine you know your boss
Apps
And the other see there's a lot of lines crossing between personal and work there and additionally how
Amazon handle
Recognizing people through the voice Services here
Because it's struggle sometimes
Should someone who just happens to be in your conference room have access to all the data that's available on your Amazon Echo
Probably not
So those are the things were curious about
Pretty sure or if you're piloting
That's my Insite for that
Battles
Battlegrounds
With Amazon
And now Google YouTube
Has been again
Code for the echo show after
Brief moment when I could watch the Corgi videos of breakfast also
They pulled it from the Fire TV
And Amazon is now
No longer selling
Products yeah I think the nest ceasing of selling nest
Product has been a couple weeks if not more
But this whole YouTube getting pulled from the show and surprising with a Fire TV
I hear you have a show you had then you lost it and then I seen you had to work around to use the web version
Can you can access
Reinstated it
This is a big battle right now it really affects Amazon's products the show I kind of get
Because
I don't think
They worked out whatever deal they needed with Google in advance at the Fire TV I mean
It on there for a while I mean
And that's
Not an iot device theoretically it's
I'm surprised
I like guys get over it YouTube has the audience so you need to be on the television
Amazon
Retail stores so you got to sell your product
Yeah
We can I mean
Apple products
Amazon sale
I'm used to that but it's still really darned
As a normal consumer not like
Waiting up till 3 in the morning.
IPhones or what
So this is just a mess and it's
It's a mess
Consumers ultimate
The price for
It is extra frustrating because when you buy these things
You think they're going to work one way in
And now they're not because of the stupid Court
Fights
Remind me
Arguments for the last couple years when you're like
Yeah it's that same argument all over again just on different devices in a different content delivery mechanism if you do have a Fire TV
How big is start singing notification morning saying that
YouTube on no longer be available on the Fire TV as of January 1st 2018 so watch it
Nginx turn
Okay
I just hate everyone
That's frustrating
What is move to happier news
Corporate excitement
Walmart
Walmart AR
This is a great story
So Chris Ensley
Who is
Head of a team in
Walmart is 500%
Walmart so he seems like
He basically wants a
Sensor that cost less than a buck
So he can stick it on all of their products track of around the world Etc
She wants it to sense movement Keepin vibration
He would like it to be energy harvesting
And
He wants to get it really cheaply
Vigilia
Yeah I mean
He said we have nearly 12000 stores
And they've kind of done at initial rollout of iot stuffing about 5000 stores
So
It's not like they're
Starting to play stuff
But it's obviously expensive
Actually made a really good point is I just changing our light bulbs is a huge undertaking in terms of cost and effort and songs
I get it
Talk about using LED bulbs Beacon somehow soda
That is something that people have talked about for a while so that makes a lot of sense cuz they're powered in
People that consumers can access them
Great article I will link to it
You can learn and you know if you have this
Apparently Walmart wants to talk to you
Coma
All right I was in
Another guy was at an event at the Target open house actually was
Last week and I had a panel
On
Building sustainable
And
Hives
Which is a subscription
Connected Products Company
British gas
Rob Martin's who is from Schlage
And Matt van
Horn who is the CEO
And I learned many things
And I'm going to send them up really quickly
The June oven which cabinet I love
Stop for the holidays
Because they did is crazy pricing paint with Williams-Sonoma
They charged some $1,000 for this thing and it's Norm
$1,500 an hour
They have no more to say
Niedermeyer
Early adopters that's a tax I paid all my life
That's terrible
So
More related to the panel topic was this idea that we should be selling Hardware as a service in
A lot of these guys actually really resisted the idea
That
This is actually what they were selling
But the more I talk to people the more I'm aware of the fact that every connected device you buy
It's not a product that you buy
It is a service that you
You're going to buy
Now whether or not
You paid a monthly subscription
For the service
It's still a freaking service
And they have to
Manufacturers
Educate consumers as consumers we need to think about these things this way
Because right now
We're buying these things thinking they're going to last
The same amount of time an unkindness
Active device with
And that's fine if it's a
And it only last 3 years but
If it's a door lock
And you want that thing to last
Expectation seen numerous updates feature.
Missions like every couple weeks we get something
I got an email today
Yes thank you I love it so these things they have to build
R&D to figure out how to add these new features
Continue to support the old teachers
Hopefully into perpetuity quite honestly and then
You know you support them through questions
That's the second
And this is from Roy
Operations prayer hive
He was like
You really need to consider when you're building this product
The timeline you're willing to
Because that's going to affect
What you charge for it up front but also how you're going to monetize it over
Overtime you can't just stick a something out there and be like I will figure it out later
Which is exactly what happen
Because people 90 world in the computer world were used to
Things that may be last for 3
Well they tend to lease a lot of things
I thought that was really a good point
Because if you're designing something to last for 10 years
You're going to have a very different cost equation then something for 3 years or
Our customer
Rather
Maybe we should lie siriano to devices
Something somebody should be looking into
There's a lot of questions I have about that like what it means to start
Paying for things monthly that used to own because
The form of wealth
Eurasian rights
Can I get equity in my door lock
Yeah but once you start
Are you sore
And having things taken away that's why we shouldn't have to pay for anything at all
Not so fast.
That is not true that is not
We feel
Or that's how I feel
Apparently
Okay so
Let's Talk About Kevin
Has he got a new Gadget
Yes we'll keep this kind of shorts cuz it's not super
Glitzy but I finally got around to installing the controls
For those who are interested it's model number G
I think you can find it online for 80 90 bucks actually bought a refurbished one for $61
So it's just a big Square module
That has a light
And you literally it to me tennis install this thing
You literally plug it in near your Z-Wave Hub witch
My case is a wink and tear it up using the Hub app
That way you can make your connection
Didn't unplug the device
Garage door garage door opener
Mine is an old Genie
It's probably came with this house which is Bill 18 years ago
And literally you connect two wires from the gocontrol Z-Wave controller to the garage door opener
If the same screws that your push button control for garage door
Is so easily stimulates a push of the button and then
Tilt sensor that you stick on your garage door and that will tell the
Controller if the door is
Copper down and that's pretty much it I mean I have it working with my wink perfectly
One thing I will note with this particular controller and this may be common
It will only accept one command every 30 seconds if you open the door
Remotely then you got to wait at least 30 seconds
How to close a tanning spray safety
Tradition which I can understand that but
Working really well I've created a robot 2
Shut the door for me if I
Leaving based on GPS Android
I'm not sure what you got
For my garage door is when the garage door opens after dark it turns on
My porch light
Very nice
Yes I like that
I like that
I will do that
Anyway
Very easy like I said
The 10 minutes to install anybody can do this quite honestly
Very inexpensive to I thought what it does
No that's awesome
Got it feels like decades and Internet of Things
Garage door
The challenge with all of these is for security reasons a lot of them don't let you do like voice control for the Amazon Echo
Google home
And some of them don't let you control asthma
Play things from Hobbs
Curse my thanks
Price Rite and I did check I cannot voice control this through either my echo devices or through my Google home it just isn't
Supported yet
I believe I can
Control the mic
Fee
South Jersey subscription
Hainan
There you go
All right
Let's go to this week's
Voicemail
Find The Internet of Things podcast listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage electronic locks Schlage
Xbox
So you have to have a smart home system
See what's possible is it
Already
Let's play the voicemail
Hi this is Ray calling from Daytona I'm having a difficulty now that I've added Alexa to
They're getting confused with multiple living room notations for the
Various iot devices
WeMo switch home
Etcetera
Naming convention
All these devices
Shave
Fusion
Appreciate your help thank you
This is a
Great question
And there are so many ants
The basic
Problem
Okay so there are many ways to tackle it but I'm going to give you a philosophy
Because that's what I think
Is going to help them
I pick one thing
What I'm naming devices
I pick one thing tickets the name
Lake of the room that it's in and it's usually the
Dominant lighting Source in
So I have living room
And then the for ceiling can lights teacher living
So it's like
Left shelter
Easy chair
Or whatever and then they're all grouped together under that name
Everything else in that room
Get something that does not have the name
Living room
So there's a fan that's
Big fan
Is that a yes
It's named Afro Circus because my daughter named it after
Something
From Madagascar
When that was hot
Years ago
You can name it whatever you want I was suggesting that do not sound like others
Thanks
And I also have
Batman lose all of my downstairs downstairs
Which meant that
When I
Added my
And stuff
I used to call them downstairs blinds and upstairs blinds but
Diffusing so
Lower
So
Right and I'm shaking my head because this is a great question and it's a common Challenge and
I take a similar approach to pretty much everything that just obviously makes sense
Name some things by room office lights but I have
Office middle office bottom cuz they're on
Vertical lamp so yeah it's really tricky so I do it by placement and room
I try to be as descriptive
Possible
I think at the end of the day what we really need is what's taking place right now such as the
Grouping of things we don't even need the names so so you can just say it lights off
In the room that you're in free sample
No the challenge
My fans are on
Technically light switch so when I turn on my living room
So when I say
Everything is pink sza light
Even though some of those things are not lights
Stair fan
Or if you have a switch
Associate with
The fireplace
And that is because this is still very rudimentary
And we need
Had to go back to that article from last week we need some a i and some ml to say
You know these things are lights that's a fan even though it's on
Hydra light switch may be the assistant needs to say would you like the fan on as well we need to have that contact with
Don't have that yet
Actually
You know what it's pretty chilly in here
Yeah that's either either way that's fine too
I would say pick your dominant
Pick one thing and labeled
The most sewing
Many cases it's going to be
And then from there
Descriptive
Crazy however
Children
In your life
There you go I actually find Afro Circus to be my most easy thing to
Remember because it is
So very different
Yes it is
When people visit
When you meet us to putting name tags on your devices that's usually a bad sign
Exactly
So it's
If you're not busy answer
If you have questions
Please give us a call on our hotline at 5
R24
We would love
To try to help you out
Or
Hunt
For this week's
News portion of the show that's
Get ready for our guests who is
Uppal Basu from NGP
He Capital Partners capital
For implementing
Any kind of system
And how
We've been spoiled by clouds
And how that's going to set us all up to
Stale
Good interview
Superfly
And now
Our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this
This week sponsor is Lux products and I have Rob unit here who's the CEO of Lux
The company and its position as a leader in Home Comfort and can
Trolls
So Rob
Can you start off by telling me a little bit about Lux products
I sure can so the folks at lox we are proud philadelphia-based innovators of HVAC
Control and we've been around for over a hundred years
You probably don't know this but in the middle of last century
We came up with what I jokingly call is the world's first home automation device
Which is the luck
Minute minder kitchen timer
I'll bet you have one in your Homer
Your grandmother told me your mother
Terrific well I'll jump ahead
2 about 30 years ago where we started focusing solely on HVAC controls
And I'll jump ahead even more to tell you that we've just launched our third
Wifi connect
Food product called Deluxe
Kono's
Smart thermostat
Ancona was a Hawaiian word that mean
Inviting
I think when people see the product they'll know why we need to Kono it is something you want to touch
And get to know
We focused on personalization
Design and comfort
Tell me a little bit more about
The kind of smart thermostats Wi-Fi so you can
Control it obviously from wherever in the world and it's equipped with all the smart features that one light
Expected has
The geofencing we call that home-and-away aware it has
Smart scheduling
Ford with utility cost us
Estimated
We have energy runtime and usage reporting on the app and it connects with all the three major
Voice assistance all at what we believe is a great affordable price
149 buck
Another thing I'd like to talk about fricano hazard warranty
We Stand by our products we've been at this for a very long time
For the DIY channel it's a
The 3-year warranty
If you have a pro install it
He got two more years that's a
5 year warranty
And we also have a service for HVAC Pros
If they become a lux
Sprouts bacon at
Another two years on top no one touches
Just that sort of Warrant
Okay now it sounds like you guys have really embraced the startup mentality since you've been around for so long
And you made such a wide variety of products
How is this influence how you develop
We have the drive and exciting
Man and the creativity of a
The startup but we have this established company mentality there are over 15 million Lux thermostats on the wall
Walls throughout the country already
Throughout the past
30 years and we build on that knowledge
And that experience
Of knowing
What the mainstream of America want so we design our products and develop everything
That will meet the needs of the mass Market
We're trying to get past that I owed
Key bump of early adopters
To get really through that and into the main part of
The marketplace
Rap sounds great
Where can I go to find out more
You can go of course to luxproducts.com and you'll see everything
Thing you need to know you can drop by your local
Home Depot store and find out more as well and you can of course shop online
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Who is a partner at NGP capital
Adventure firm back by Nokia
So how are you doing
How you doing
Super well so we're here to talk about what it means to actually dig into the Enterprise I
Iot world and what you actually need to do is a business to make the
Successful
So let's get started
Quickly talking to me a little bit about why you think
We have maybe misled p
People about iot and its
Complexity
Secy CIT coyote like
Dashiki
Onset of high expectations
And sadly
Numbers astronomy
Jose Enterprises and consumers
Excited and we do believe that eventually
Come to fruition
But I think
Significant
It's amazing how you
You transfer me
The physical world to the digital world
And I think because of the
Technology has been moving in the last few years
Sometimes server to clouds to mobile
Expectation is that this is Magic
Call Alexis.
Looking for
Unfortunately that has not been the case
Coyote
And enter the number of factors agenda
Why We Sing
Coyotes defense
Mi tienda
We need to adjust
Okay well let's dig into that you took my Segway right away from me I love it so
Let's talk about why
Iot is different from it
So the first
Singing it recognizes via connecting
Assistance
Physical environment a digital world
Conversion from one Environment Canada has
Not being the 30 of IT department
The first step to even connect
A physic
Raquel Welch
The decision was
XYZ sensor
And I Network
Play gateway to be added
To watch a movie Once
Monitor
AR measure
And that is labor intensive
And the marginal cost of that does never become
1001 Lakes officer the Morton's Uconnect
Mosto Uconnect
More elevated Uconnect
The mortgage
Did you connecting the
And additional labor has been
The IT department
Fox and Hound
Cognates
Chucky
Olympics
Phone number to is
Second connecting the distal to the physic
Request
Citizenship historically not talk to each other to be connected
LBC
Operation Technologies
Text surveillance
Cameras LED lights
Control Systems inside factories which annies dry cleaning
You need to open this up and connect them to the Box
Operational excellence
Erp systems again
Is a front in car
Caustic Bible
Look at these two
Taxes alone
Is an Roi
Which is going to be lower than traditional it
When you use the same Roi Benchmark I need
D-backs
Wednesday 12:15
Did those metrics 11
It Department
Disappointed
Who justify
Call Jack
Because the payback period Has to be longer because
Discontent
Labor and capital
Investments
Send it a couple more points I just wanted to admit
Enlightenment
Complex
ID technology Industries
Enemy sometimes we have too many standards
Netflix
Platforms
Which car introduced in the last few years
And what is that done is paralyzed
Organizations
Consumers can play with gadgets but Enterprises
They need
Predictability in standards and networks and protocols when they see this
Huge number of
Election choices
Daisy actually gets
Houston
Often do nothing and I think the last one is Archie's hyperloop
The benefits center
Weather
Defenses are being added and
Typically weather Valley Springs
It does not corporate headquarters what's happening at the branches at the retail stores at the factories
So git Department which is almost all decentralized
Does not
Vicky see the tangible benefits
In front of them so they often
Thai Taste project
Visible to them and their bosses
Okay and this reminds me of life back in
Kind of the late 90s maybe the early aughts when I T was very siloed
A lot of integration work
You know life was just a lot harder
And there was debate over should ITP centralized cost center all of these fun thing
And cloud computing came and changed
A lot of that as did like the SAS software model
So
Right now a lot of solutions are coming onto the market with the same as more modern biz
Business models attached in
The ROI that you're talking about
Should we be going back in time or should we be trying to bring the standards and everything
Up to
Modern times
Interesting
Change which has happened in
Assassin bug
Chicago fasciitis
Inception
Because you started making a lot of
Purchasing decisions without doing
So what we are seeing is
Is it Department actually have been outsourced to shrink in size
Because bedroll is much more Gemini's for likes
Boston Market
The weather in managed by
Call Fidelity
The organization that she much smaller than the 90
And then on top of
Dad security
Beaches in opposite of existential dread
Have kept them so busy.
This new project quality.
Doesn't get
Supported deserves
And then
Some organization
Utica College
When we actually interview simatai
Videos
We find it actually busy
Strategist
Did you have this
You have this you understand
How to connect Asus
Dakota Digital but they have no resources
Are people and projects really under them of any
Size 2 actually
Execute project early strategies for trying to advise
Golden seals on how they should think about the future a future of digital start writing what we find is this
Iot
Challenge
Really
Global mindset
A longer-term Roi
He's not getting
The attention it deserves
And hence
Concepts WeChat
Tom Dooley by champions
Local champion
An oil and gas
Decides to
Digitize their leg
OSIM retail store in California decides to
Interesting things into the cameras
Prediction tracker
Tends to be
Gravidez
Reasons for doing this
Corporate headquarters
Not as engaged let's do it
Blank slate
I am a company that wants to get this right or maybe
Uno's Viera
Or a big company for the description look like
What was the organization who handles iot
I don't know what the title should be but
Should be an individual who
Is butter
Senseless
Carpet function notable
And this person needs to have an organization p&l which allows them to
Deploy
This obviously this individual event have to be Matrix
To the be used because the Auto I
From iot benefits
Business units
So they need to work closely with beans they need to work with it Department because
The date of each comes out of iot have students
So this individual does have the challenge of having
Organizational
Liters to make this happen
But this individual needs to be a stand
Leader who reports into
Levels of organization
The second point is they need to have the
Flexibility of longer-term Roi
Given the mandate to
Sun experiments which have
Five-year-old device
So that they can actually deploy these yet
Because the labor and the Catholics required
To make this book
Is that because everyone no one else is going to do it because they
Demon Cycles
It companies which actually exist
Because this I going to benefit
It's a bit like her Amazon
Building Warehouse
It's a little bit more like that
Think about how did the world look in 2025 in water
Investments
It's competitive advantage and I think that's the mindset of an iot
Key project
What's the ROI in the next 18
The last point I think
To put some of this problem back to the
This applies to vendors
I think to get send you can find supplies for wedding
To the deployment
Education and
Mention the software
Subscription monthly basis I think that's a better relationship than trying
Shifted out the deployment
Bead installation
A more complex deployment environment
And how do you think they should handle the local asp
If I'm at the edge
I have a business how do I
Report back to this digital officer
Push project
Yes I'll give you a real example of
Just to make this year Leslie back to come
LED control Solutions and direct selling
Beihai quality
Solutions to
Taxis in New Hampshire
North Carolina's and
What they found was
Stanton local
Facilities manager
Because their budgets were highly.
Localized
MP3
Monitoring them against
The cheapest solution
Chinese supplier
Width of a Sharpie back because the
The building facilities
Incentive was to just control an annual budget Evernote thinking about strategic benefits to the
Headquarters
Budget Inn
Incentivization
And so the way.
Connect the edge
Actually tell the building
Facilities managers
That's
Ubud dog shelter
Solutionreach
Which is not just about the cheapest
Dissolution
Light up your buildings but which actually gets you act
The data and then
Which can be used to run this
Back to you
Weather for the next 5 to 10 years
Do that then
Given the budget
As I said in a 5-year fashion Nova
So the local managers with it
Retail store manager
And at your local hardware store
Local Target
Needs to be
Wendy
Securing lights
Example
Cameras in their stores
Dania
HQ
Did you sell right now.
Is not the case
Today incentives have to be aligned
They have to be the largest for doing the right thing for the corporation not just for the
Got it okay and all this sounds really complicated so what are the first steps
A company that wants to benefit from a digital transformation
Should I just like fire this CDO person should they what do you do if you want to get to the
So I think the only time of year
Scene Solutions
Coyote sightings
Ian has been where
The CEOs organization has
But we made the decision that they're going to transform the organization
Digitized dog medication and twin
And they going to
Footaction
Resources to go to the first step in my opinion
It's not the title
It's basically putting
Somebody
6 + 2
The CEO and the CFO
On this project
And then
Give them
Elegance
Environment
Franchisee
Like pasta
Where is very hard for example
4 corporate headquarters to tell franchises
What to do in DC this in McDonald's and hotel chains where even though otherwise way clear franchises
Which effectively on this hotels and restaurants have no incentive to spend money
Different than where the
Crunches actually
Bullion by headquarters of the organisation structure
The difference
I think Sanchez
Completely on the accident.
The edge of your neck
Like useful so that would be nice
Genovesi
The second thing you would do
My technician
By the ocean and tricycles everyday
Addition problem
Pick one use case with
Chinese food
Could be security could be
Predictive maintenance
Could be
Customer satisfaction
Just pick one and just run with it on a national level
Opposed to trying to sell security maintenance customer happiness
Everything in one massive project
I would try to
To just run
One single use case with the base year value
Across the country
And then once
Stats exceed
Send
One by one
Alright Island
If I am evaluating
Project so let's say I put the infrastructure in place to actually do this
What kind of projects tend to generate
The most value
I think
The team switched into Jen has the most strikeouts at least tangible value tenths
To be
I would say
Operational effectiveness and labor count
Labor productivity basic
Please show if you can get more work
Square foot of space
In a factory on the retail store
You can sell mortgages
Inside Fry's Electronics
Private lesson number in Plaistow Central
Get the quickest
Feedback
Receptionist
English basically makes
What Cosmo Collective inside
Building
Car and get more work done
I think those would be what I call low hanging fruit
The next one I would say
I would say predictive maintenance
Trying to figure
Phone sin
Environments before they happen so that you don't have to spend enormous money
1 sound system breaks down
WWE
Would be the second level
Customer happiness and satisfaction tents
To be
More intangible and takes longer
Trying to figure out
Shareholder value
I just lost project to standard
This would not be my first phone
Productivity
Magnifica facility optimization as my first project
This is in line with your long-term vision
And where do you think things like sustainability
Set in because I think iot has a lot of it offers a lot of benefits from
Inefficiency standpoint and that goes all the way
Through two things like
Reducing energy
Reducing materials and components
Tracking them across their life cycle
Baby making
Things are recyclable etcetera
Chill
When were talking about the big picture and digital transfer
Formations when do we go or should we go beyond Roi and talk about others
I discussed this the Lord you know
If I was building a brand new
New house
If I was buying a brand new car most likely
Has all the features but if I have an old home or a legacy
Sikar trying to connect everything
Which is an expensive proposition so I actually make
Brownfield sites
Science groundskeeping Legacy environment
I think there's a notch
You cannot Transformer Lego
Legacy environment where tens and thousands of years of
Legacy Investments have gone in
Facility training efficient environment
What you trying to do is
Make it more efficient
ICD-10 sustainability value prop in an old facility is going to be tough
On the other hand if I'm building a new fact
Can you retest
Anything's a new healthcare facility
Look for Latina Platinum LED environment
Idiot
Try to make it out
Sustainable as I could
Because I have the ability
Do that fresh and the interesting thing which I learned
In my thoughts
Construction engineer
What I found was
Six buildings against
Earthquakes
In the mid-nineties in California
And what I found was
Fixing a
Building
Making it earthquake compliant is far more expensive on a per square foot
Good bases and to build a new
Building from sky so I actually worked in
Old Hospital building
Does Kaiser
Permanente
Design new Kaiser
And on the square foot
Dimension index
Environment
Without dislocating the employees in the
What is inside the building
And thinking in
That building up to
Who was Far farmer
Expensive
On the first page footage faces and a new building
UA test
The cost of doing that is going to be much more expensive
And that's what we say
Nrt2
Retrofit and exist
Sing environment
Space pen
But you must sometimes do that
To conceive
A blank
Looky looky
All my new car
Construction in online USA
Kylie digitize Hialeah
Invested 20 years bag
I can only be selectively able to do that
Okay
Be the most optimistic note to end on
But I think it's a good one
And maybe you'll come back sometime and talk about how to change that how do we deal with Brownfield
So much for coming on the show this week
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news please sign
For my newsletter at Stacey on iot cam
Thanks for listening and we'll see you next week