Hey everyone welcome
Go to the internet.
Your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel and today we have
Awesome shoe for you
We are going to be talking about AT&T new indie iot
Network Madam eggettes a hotel job
We got some
Enterprise AI bot funding
We got new smart home routers HP Enterprise is going to invest 4 billion in the eye
Iot Edge
And a bunch of other news
We're just not even
And
We have a message
Praetorian Plus
Our Guest Gabe halimi who is the CEO of flow Technologies he's going to be talking about insurance
And smart home stuff
You're going to want to hear this if you have hopes of ever getting an iot device covered by your insurance
And we have a brand-new giveaway plus we're going to announce the winners of our last
Giveaway
So all of this and more ahead
Stay tuned
Now
Let's take a message from our sponsor today's podcast is sponsored by control for LED smart home
Delivering support for nearly 12,000 connected devices professionally installed by a smart home expert
Lighting security thermostats door locks music TV cameras and more work together
Provide a smart home that's built for smart people you're home and all the connected devices in it controls
Simply and easily
Now that's smart head to control4.com that's control the number for. Com
For more information
Okay Kevin let us get started first up AT&T
Has launched
Or says it
Launch a
NB iot Network
For those of you guys who are like what what what what what
Nb-iot is a real
Low-bandwidth
Low data rate
Relatively cheap
Cellular-based
Low-power wide are
So it's
Blake sick Fox's Network
Kind of like ingenue
It's on par with Laura
So very small
Dancer theater
Little very small
Bits of data
And presumably very cheap
Nb-iot has what I call crazy low data rate
It's like you can only send 250 kilobits per second
Compared to
1 megabit per second
LTE cat in
Network
And gosh I don't even know where we're at
It's the dial-up modem for iot
Yes
There you go
But it's supposed to be super cheap
The challenge with NB iot
He is you do have to buy
Modules in right now the industry is aiming
For $5
For a module
That's still super expensive
Compare light cost
Wifi chips with Bluetooth
Chips with your liking me
Dollar
50 Cent range
Really cheap and when you're thinking that there's any billions of these things connecting
That's a lot of money
So they're working
I don't know when
She is doing this
This is worth noting.
Because Verizon
He said that they're going to do it
T-Mobile said that they were going to
Initially in the US AT&T and Verizon
We're focused on doing LT
PCAT and which has
Like I said
Hire date
So
Europe
Asia
Like yeah nb-iot let's make it so
But in the US not so much
So much so now that
These guys are actually piggybacking on T-Mobile
Announcement doing this
It's worth noting
The big questions I have
Are again about module
So you're going to need this for like high-value devices that are moving all over
The place to think
Shipments of
Computing equipment
Pandora jewelry or
Medicine
Things that
Are going to travel
Possibly even around the globe
But definitely
Around the country
And that it won't be cost-prohibitive
Like kind of a more expensive device
And more
Data plan
The other element here is the date
So how is AT&T going to charge people
When
Historically
They want to do these
Individual deals with
Companies in people there are
Companies out there like particles
Twilio that
Can support nb-iot
But that's
Again
Question
I mean they can't use the traditional
Pricing that we use with consumers for phones and Neo data rates are phones and such because as a consumer we we have some
Super fast Wireless at this point
Pandora streaming
Big things like video
This is not that so
Yeah I don't know how they're going to do this and the kind of
Burns my bottom that
I have to pay like $10 a month for LTE service on my Apple watch because they're kind of using that old pricing
Even though my Apple watch
Only uses I checked
About a hundred
Bytes per
Month and yeah I'm paying $10 for that sewing up her database is it extremely expensive they cannot do this
It's never going to succeed if they do that
Auntie says they're going to launch vim in the US
In 2019
And they're going to follow it
Mexico
Verizon
Plans here
Are similar but they're doing their NBA team
Filled out
This year
And they've said they're they're going to cover
The whole country by the end of the
So
Yeah that is all the news we have on
Nb-iot
Low-power wide-area
At work so far
Let's go on to our next story which is
Play spots
Who is the big news this week was
Madam
Bro she is going to be in Marriott
Hotels there
Tons of Marriott brands that are going to have this
Not that I'm going to stay at
What cuz it's Marriott Hotels Westin Hotels Resorts st. Regis hotels Aloft Hotels in autograph
Hotels
If a hotel has more than three names in it or three words and I can't afford it so yeah
Okay
Some of these are super
Rims for
In a couple that lived
And I've been wanting this for
Forever cuz every time I walk into a hotel room
Dust begins to search for the light switch
You're like where is it
Because we don't look for them at home anymore that's why
So yeah so I've wanted this
There's a couple things that are interesting about
Marriott
Was actually the first company to
Hook up Netflix to
Your Netflix account in your hotel room Marriott
Over the last few
15 and I was a big deal
It took a lot of logistics
Actually
Make sure that
When you left
Deactivated
And that's actually going to happen
In this case so instead of attaching to your individual Amazon
This is going to be a generic
Hotel
Count in the recordings are going to be deleted every day
In hotels are giving it access to the Boys Room
Andrew Madoff
Directions
But they will actually get
For the matinee for house
Fatality we sounds kind of like a whole little skill or action or
App even
They will
Yep the hotel will actually
Be able to measure engagement through analytics or they can do some customization by choosing like to fall
Music stations and such like
Amazon
Give an example of Marriott offering TED talks on Echo devices for example Selby pre-configured which
You don't want just access or nothing
But eventually
This kind of concerns me eventually they're going to let you temporarily link your Amazon account
Better running he's mad at me for hospitality
Blueprints
And that's
Really nice as you get customization but you got to trust that when you check out your account is automatically disc
Schenectady cuz that's what's going to happen you're not going to disconnect it it's going to happen
Or is it
One hopes that it will
Because Marriott has experience with
Like I remember talking to Marriott and the Nets
Looks guys and they spin
A long time
Making sure this
Properly
And was safeguard
User info
Information
Conscious
Spent a similar amount of
Worry is
There's a couple
Battlements
There's a lot of questions in
The consumers mind about privacy
Around this so I think
But there are plenty of people who will see this in their hotel room
If I were walking into a hotel room
The explicit purpose of having
Affair
I would probably look askance
And that's because there been some weird glitches
Like the echo randomly recording people in
I'm thinking it hears things
But it doesn't hear
That's actually a little worrisome
And even actually in one recent case sending that conversation to contact
Yeah and I try
My data believe it
Don't trust
These sorts of
Weird errors glitches at the stakes in some of these
Glitches
Could be high
Especially Fingerhut
But maybe that's a good reason not to have your own account linked
Isn't the hotel just yours
Amazon
Yeah that's the thing I don't know that I would like my own account but I would just look at it as
The TV that they put on there with the channels that they offer right I don't think I would log into my PlayStation Vue account
For example
Have access to my channels in my DVR stuff while on vacation it would be nice but I can do that on my my own device
Yasso
And if that's
We'll see how that works but I think this is a
Really
Good use case for the echo
I know Amazon has really ambitious plans
I'm talking to
Across a wide variety
Industries
And there are tons of Industries everyday that
What do you think about getting the echo at restaurants or in industrial Factory
So voice is going to be a huge
Huge deal
Everywhere in
Amazon's really doing
Good job trying to
It's funny you say that
Because
That was a great segue right to an article that I wrote this week
On basically The Madam a everywhere strategy
That I think is really helping Amazon keep its digital assistance leadership
Animes that they're doing it because unlike their competitors such as Google Apple and Microsoft
What do they have at Amazon doesn't have
They have desktop and mobile software platforms are there
So how is Amazon doing this right how are they stay
Granted they have first-mover status so that helps but doesn't guarantee success obviously it gets back to something you just
I said about the hotel bit
Utrust
Amazon with your data
And when you look at the companies I just mentioned
Apple is up there with trust
Microsoft
I would say
But Google
Many people are not as many people I think Trust
Google with their data
As opposed to Amazon with their data so I think that really really helps
The other thing is
Amazon's being very open and they have to be because the only way you're going to get this
Platform is a platform Developers
They've got like 11 developer kits that you can buy where is
The other folks don't
They have the most skills out there depending on who you ask and they've about 30,000 Madame a skills Google says
1000 * 1 million
When million actions to try
But that's use case if that's not actual developer actions there are only around 2,000.
Directions
So young again Amazon is making a good play here to attract the Developers
Herewith building skills or routines are actions whatever you want to call them the other thing
He's really been talking about this I'll just raise it and I'm curious what you think
Biggest populated country on the planet
Is China
Who is persona non grata in China
Google
Yep
Amazon
Granted Amazon will be competing in some very
Aggressive and widely available retailers that are looking to their own boss and such
So it's not a cakewalk for them but they have an opportunity to work Google have no opportunity so
I think that's going to go a long way in the future towards keeping Madame a front and center for sometime so
So that
Okay well there you go
Did not argue with you on that
So
But not some people might not be curious to hear some comments on a voicemail if somebody disagrees
There's no right answer here obviously I would love to hear people
Yes
Let's talk about
Enterprise
So let's try to make as looking at the space there's definitely some
Actions that it's taken
Still kind of TVD on that that the Cortana example is when wearing
That's both interesting and
Sanitize into some of
The things you mentioned
Only it's like that frenemy
Territory
Let's talk about
Yes I have not heard of Jan until I found her mention on voice bot. AI which is like my
My new go-to site for voice stats
It's really good size check it out
Gene is a company started by David karandash
Who is the former CEO of answers.com what do you think about it makes sense that somebody from answers.com
Working with an AI bought these days
Jane is that a I bought she is a high-powered office assistant
And launched about a week ago
The company raised 1.5 million in January 2017 to get started but they just got another 8.3 million dollars are 10
Enterprise a iPod
It's interesting because
With Jane
She can tie into your enterprise system so like you could just ask Jen what's the status of the Purina lead
That we've been working on
James Bond here's what I found in the CRM marketing department sent a proposal and expected to close on March 3rd
I mean you could go into your CRM system look all this up but if you can have a voice
Assistant do it for you it should be radically save a lot of time and again it's a very Enterprise AI Focus there's
What happening in this space all of a sudden
Hey voices
It is not the sole
There will be others
Prepare for the multimodal future Pep Boys
That's a lot of it
The invisible interface that everybody knows how to use
You just yell at it
Cheap the Enterprise
What's
HP Enterprise
Because they
Heaven in
Unquote intelligence
Edge Technologies
And services
Over the next
Here's I bring this up because
I am super excited about
Edge computing
Element for iot
I know even if you're focused on smart home stuff and not thinking
About Enterprise type
Examples
Not everything can go back to the
We obviously tok
Sollozzo a lot of
Computing
In processing
From all of the sensor data is going to happen
At what they call the edge
And this is a rich vein of opportunity
A lot of startups and big
So everyone from Intel and Cisco to hpn
I don't know just pick another big-name
Gear that is optimized
Data processing really quickly
They don't have to be low powers
Cuz everybody's definition of the edge is a little different soompi
People are like it's a sensor but most of these guys are thinking about an aggregation
That sits on a factory
Floor inside
Closet and
Like a lot of this data shouldn't go up to the cloud
Because of security or
Tradesy
Rules some of its latency Centric so you can't have a factory that's like relying on data to dictate once and
Nothing turns off
Any latency there
Quite honestly deadly
So either why it's important
This is YH
Investing here
Now
The question is
What is an investor
Steak picado
Everyone makes season
3 years ago IBM was
Earlier this year
Microsoft was like we're investing 5 billion in it iot
Insulate PS4 billion at the edge
Does that mean
It's going to invest in R&D
And it's going to focus on business models
Which would be
A lot of it's going to be security AI machine learning
And
Again
Talked about this isn't highly specific
But it is worth mentioning
Cuz we're all cloud
And the four billion is going to be invested over the next 4 years so roughly a billion a year
So
Yay more money for
All right now
True that smart home
Tp-link
Tp-link is adding
Deco
Mesh routers
Along with
They're going to be able to have your router
Aunt gift
So
Kevin
I love it
Because all these extra hubs boxes gateways Etc that were plugged into the router just never made
Sense to me just put the dawn radio chips for smartphones in the router to begin with and that's what they're doing
They had a this is there I think they're second mesh router The Deco M5 which is a dual-band
Router no other radios are the Wi-Fi maybe that Bluetooth
Now they got zigbee in a deco M9 plus mesh router to tribe instead of Dual Band
Yes more of this please
AR price
All right
Let's talk about
Smart
Fridges
DRM specifically
Smart fridge
This is a
Twitter thread that I somehow got through
I'm really excited about
This fellow was complaining about
An RFID reader on
GE
Appliances so this RFID reader basically measures
If you have a
Branded
Water filter in your fridge
And if you don't
The water dispenser won't dispense
Really
Yes
It's not good for the lovely
It's red because it encompasses everything that you would have
In the sky being
Doesn't work
We might hack it but most mainstream consumers know
Yes but it also includes GE Appliance
Weighing in to say
He's like hey
What is this and why are you doing this
Angie appliances says what this refrigerator requires this
Particular technology to work
Direct lease please see the following link for details
And then
She is like
The guys like this is unacceptable I don't like that and then
This guy
Geappliances says
Well we recommend only using geappliances RFID
Filters as they are designed for your refrigerator specifically
Usual a non-genuine filter
Guaranteed to work properly and may damage the area
This Is Not Unusual
Any company that sells branded
Toner filters
Whatever else that
Comes with his stuff
They're always going to say hey user
Branded stuff
But
If we think back to Keurig in their pickups in
ERM associated
K-Cups
It becomes harder
When you connect a device to the
To do this
That's
Yeah me know I have a Samsung fridge and
Usually I buy the Samsung water filters but every once in a while either not available River and I'll get much cheaper
Third-party filter
I know it will work with my fridge
It will not work with this guy's French
He does not have that option and it's not
Disclose when you buy the fridge that it will only work
The persuaders DRM on the filters essentially
Yes and this is actually a really prevalent
Idea in the appliance industry
Because
They're looking for ways to
You know creep do services
Right so reminding you that your filters do and then being able to let you order One automatically
But
For the people who are like brother saves
This guy saying
$50
Reminder usually 40-ish
So yeah
Where is a third-party one might cost you the $15 or less
And in my case I actually have a water filtration system
Full House
So I don't actually use the filter in my
But in that case GE does offer up iPad
So it just
If you put the bypass in
So your options here in this case are we
Return the fridge
Buy the GE part
Orbit whole house water filtration system
I guess orange shoes
It looks like he is going to return it from the thread
Yes
This guy is like
I am returned
Interesting bit is talking about 2
Disclosure the filters typically last at least 3 to 6 months
Which when you figure this out when you run into this problem
It'd be well Pastor return.
Yes
So we're going to say if you were making a smart Appliance
With your product in this
You got it exclusive
I feel like the FTC
And other organizations
What do you like
That's not cool
Sorry Green Revolution
Tigres
CRM
Mark Bridges
All right
Let's talk about other
Things that have gone wrong
Google is going to fix
Their location
Google home
Yes it's a bit scary to me that this is
Just been found but krebsonsecurity reported about it
You can inject some JavaScript in a website if you are at
Evil person I guess and that script can run and find out if you have a go
Google home read Chromecast on
Your Wi-Fi network
And if you give it about a minute to run the script that is it can get super precise location.
Lake County Within
10 meters I believe
That's really bad
So Google is aware of it now and they are going to fix it I haven't seen when it's getting fixed but
Really really bad
I just I'm surprised I mean that home product is not brand new I mean you expect these kind of
Remember that
Incredible data
Consumption
Yeah that's fair to say I don't know if you wash it but there's about a minute-and-a-half video of somebody actually doing this
Script
The maid to actually exploited
And it like opens up a location in Google Maps to 239 close radar
Yeah it does take a minute like I'm staring at the screen like watching paint dry but you know that's not the point
What's less scary scary
Dependent be called bsh has partnered with techstars to develop accelerator program for the connected kitchen
If you are like me this is
Super exciting
TSH is 8
So one of the German iot
Countries that we talk
Satellites
Basically are going to create this accelerator with techstars
The focus is going to be on digital business models and
Analogies for the
Home so something that we are super interested in
And and super excited about
This will start
In Munich
In
And it'll be a three-month accelerator program they've committed to finding it and making it happened
Looking for 10 companies
So if you are excited about this
Keep an eye on techstars is website
And
I am sure you're going to see something about their partnership
Esh
Maybe I'll get my refrigerated
Crock pot
Biscottini
Munich
Next year
Go for it
But only picking 10 I mean
That's
Brilliant
Yes it is you're going to be one of the 10
You're welcome
Little tiny other things
Things to mention
One Google now has a podcast
And I know a lot of our audience listens to things
On the web or
Variety podcast
Less than half of you actually listen on iTune
So if you're one of those people who are listening on an Android phone
Or the Google home
Now you have a podcast
You can use
You do and even cooler I think
Is that when you listen to a podcast on your Google home you can posit
And in the podcast app on your phone you can say
Resume playing whatever the podcast is and it takes up with your phone left off
Well that's nice
Say when someone listens to it on the
That
Podcast
No
Yusuf Yusuf
Okay and we have to clarify
Haitian
Last
All right
Buckle up
You guys
If you thought it was confusing last week prepare to be
In last week's episode we talked about 3
When talking about the nest connect
Device
And this is a device that acts as a bridge from your Wi-Fi network to
The other
Thread and
Bluetooth networks in the house
We said
Did it was thread ready and that it would run open
It is
Running open
Thread but it is also
Thread ready
Those are two separate
We also said Google Nest thread ready software was called
Open thread is actually an open-source thread
Group certified reference staff
That you used to build actual thread
Supposed to
Thread ready devices
So the nest connect runs open
Thread but is actually still a threat Reddit
Oh my gosh
Without asking
Yes that's all I can say yes
That help
I think part of the confusion I don't know if he said this last week or not is that
Some of these Hardware products came out while
The thread spec was kind of an
Slight
And
It looks like there's transition in the works to following the truth.
If that makes sense
Hey I just got an email from the wise
Since a lot of you guys love
Hear wyze cameras Amazon skill
Ready so they're working on Final certification now
And they're going to let us
And now it's time for
Coyote
Listener
Hotline
So
We have a winner
From our
Prior hotline contest
You are going to get my old ecobee SI thermostat
That's my exciting
And this week we are going to
Introduce a new giveaway
So the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by slave
And now you're going to have the chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart
Deadbolt and Wifi adapter
So you enter to win
Leading us up
Voicemail
At 5 1/2
237 4
And at the end of the month
We will pick
Pick a winner so for this one you have until
Midnight
Eastern Time
On June 30th
To win
So leave us a voicemail
And remember
Smarter
Start
Wish Lake
All right
And Ken
You are not only are lucky winner this week you are actually
The person who
Question we're going to answer
So
Let's hear from Ken
Hi
Stacy and Kevin
I've got a
Question for you regarding
Smart Home
Have you guys
Tried using
Getting your Alexa devices
Such as your Fire tablet
Or your ex
Spot
Or your Amazon Fire TV have you tried saying
Padme
Show me the front door
Have you been successful in
Connecting to the ring video doorbell or two Arlo
Pro Camera
And if yes
How is
Speed
Versus
Just using the smartphone app
Or
Yap on the table
Just wanted to get your experience on that
Is the experience Key West
Compared to using Alexa and
Siri
Okay
This is
I'm sorry to disappoint you I have done some of these things but
I have used my Amazon
Echo Show
To see what is happening
For my Arlo cameras and to see what's happen
On my
Video doorbell which is by
August
Not by
So
I can tell you
That there is
In my experience so far it is not faster
Everything going into
And
It's kind of a bummer
But it makes sense though
There's a technical reason why opening the app on your phone is going to be quicker
And that's because it's a lot quicker to just tap a nap and have
It opened immediately as opposed to speaking to a voice assistant where that
Recordings to go to the cloud has to come back
And then
The voice assistant
Toddler has to make the thing happen
So there's going to be at least I'm going to say one two three seconds minimum
So what difference early days when I first tried it out the August was like rough
Play seven seconds
Shane
They felt like that are I'm not even to put that much debt are in the
But
It did get a little better
But it never got
To the same
That being said sometimes it's nice and
It's not going to catch the
Yes man right I used my Arlo on the
I actually put an Arlo camera on a roof deck and I would use it to check in on
The kids when they
Stuck so
I would just
Down in the kitchen I be
Show me the roof
And poof
I can see what was happy
I think so in that case
It didn't matter
It would be terrible in a
A Security Site
So
I'm glad can ask this though because I actually forgot that Madame a is built into my fire
10 HD tablet and I have actually turned her off on that because I'm almost always around a Madam a device
But the advantage of the tablet is it has a screen
And I never thought to
Try and really use it in that way kind of like a show or a spot
So thank you for that kind I will probably turn her back on and do some testing now as a result of this
Correct
So
And I don't have Siri
On anything that's connected to anything
That Siri
Control cell
I don't know and for what it's worth I do have
Google Assistant built into my TV set-top box
In my office which is connected to a big 4K TV and I do use that to say hey
G show me the
Front window where I have a nest camera
It does work but again you got that latency
Tilted my point is this is not unique to Amazon this is the way this is all architected for all of them
Remember
If you would like to be entered
To win a
Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt which I have tried and is really good
Plus a Wi-Fi adapter
Call us before
Midnight
On June 30th
At 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
Can I enter I want one
Family members
Read the fine print
All right
That is it
New segment
Stay tuned
For a jet ski
Who is the CEO of flow Technologies it's a water leak
Leak detection
So we're spending a lot of time talking about insurance
How
To get them
Isis the first a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is praetorian praetorian provides end end iot security testing that he
Helps organizations balanced-risk
What time to Market
Pressures praetorian Engineers help you strengthen the security of your iot products
Chipped cloud
Turn security
Learning is third-party certified
Vacation from Pretoria
The leaders and iot
Microsoft recognize praetorian as
Best Inn
So when you think praetorian think iot security expert
Check out the case study online
Praetorian help Samsung strengths
In the security of it
Platform
By visiting Stacey on iot
Dot-com
That Stacey on iot cam security
Haverhill
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Gabe halimi who is the co-founder and CEO of flow technology
I gave thanks
You're coming hey Stacy thanks for having me
Several months ago I wrote about
Bunch of startups that are disrupting
Leak Detection space
Inflow is one of those startups
So it really fast
Telus
What flow does
Yes flow is a water monitoring and shut off technology
G for the home
One device
Install Azan
The main water supply line
Proactively monitors the Integrity of the whole plumbing system to prevent
Catastrophic water damage
From happening at all we learned habits of the home
And we detect things that lead to leak
Slight high pressure thermal expansion freezing pipes
And by monitoring for those things
We can alert the homeowner and if something catastrophic happens
Can automatically shut off the water thereby preventing claims
So you do catastrophic like oh my gosh my pipe has burst it's crazy
Do you also do things
Absolutely so our technology
It detects something this
Small as a drop of water a day
Allison mosto Leak Detection falls into
A couple of different cat
You either have technologies that
Do not install on the main water supply line or ones that do
So like you just covered my friends at Roost and notion I would put those in the category of like the point sensor cattle
They're not on the main line
Many of other technologies that install on the mainline those generally can catch League
You know anywhere in the home like ours can
I think our technology is very unique
And that
We also have pressure sensor
Capability which is allows us
To catch things like micro leaks
So by doing pressure test
Yes we can identify
Leaks that are tiny behind the wall underneath the slab of the home that generally cannot be found by just
Monitoring the flow
Another category
Which is those that turn the water off
And those that
And you guys actually will
Turn the water off
Absolute
You're right those are the two different ways that we kind of breakouts at
Competitive land
Landscape now there is
A lot of questions around pricing
Installation art technology
Does required
Professional insulation
Technology
Do not but I think what you get for that in the end of the day is
A technology that
And really help prevent water damage
From happening in the first place which I think is really any
And I'll just toss out some of those competitors so you don't have to say their names
Falcon
Flume
And some others
Lots of options out there and leave
Super hot police tube
Be right now
Why
First of all
When you look at it
Homeowners insurance claims that happen every year
Water dam
As a result of Plumbing failures is the leading
Things every year
More than five times likely they'll have a water damage claim versus
Or fire
And that's usually where people mine
When they think of homeowners insurance and what they're trying to protect against it's about 9 billion dollars every year
Worth of losses for the insurance
Industry and it's five times more likely
That you'll have water damage in your home
Then a fire claim
Or a ceph
So by frequency it is
Deleting cars
Claims about 25
Percent of all homeowners
Insurance claim
And so even though people's minds homeowners Minds frequently go to you know fire theft
There's really a lot of human Peril involves are the insurance industry it definitely has a
The focus on the water damage claim
And it is preventable
I mean you can
Really prevent a hurricane
Through it a neighborhood
But seems like fire things like that
Things like Plumbing failures
These are things that can be prevented with the right
Two technologies
We've been working on this for about 10 years my father is my co-founder and
Inventor and
She has been a mechanical engineer for years
For the plumbing industry he was a manufacturer but really notable
Here was that he was actually an expert witness
Miss for the plumbing industry
Defending
Subrogation claim
Games from insurance
Plumbing failure would happen
Put in a home maybe a water connector pops off of the main water supply line
An insurance company would maybe payout that claim and then turn around
Send file a subrogation claim against
Plumbing manufacturer who they think may be responsible maybe a legend
Product liability or negligence
And my father had defended over a thousand
None of those claims he was seeing these astronomical
Client app
And here he is the Forefront of Plumbing innovation
He said previous and bench
Sensitive sold over 18 million units and he's seeing these crazy claims happening as a result of Plumbing
Failures and he decided that they're needed
To be a better way
So this gets us
Send to one of my favorite topics
Switches insurance
Because
Gosh it feels like these guys should have a vested interest
I'm putting this kind of product
In the market and getting it into
The consumer's hands
What are you actually finding
When it's released
I think that although
Most insurance
Sweet talk to you I mean every insurance
We talked to understand the value prop
They understand what it is we're doing
They're very intrigued we are also
Similar to our friends in a roost and notion were working with a number of different insurance companies on pilot
But because the technology is expensive and because it needs to be you know professionally installed
We believe the
Why is there and it'll pay for itself to adopt
And we found ourselves
In what seemed like an endless
Cycle of the pilot test
And so we decided was
We were going to collect our own data
And we were going to get ourselves comfort
Trouble with our ability to actually help prevent claims
Susan Drive down
The frequency and severity
And
Come out with our own guarantee
To homeowners
Is that if they adopt our technology
And if they act reasonably by
You know taking care of their alerts when they happen
And maintaining their home with the tips we give them that we will guarantee that they will not have catastrophic water damage
Pitch in their home
We just took
An approach that work I know
Insurance companies agnostic
If you will until the insurance company comes around
And does ketchup and I believe that they will
Eventually
But in the meantime our value proposition kind of stands for itself
The doorbell company
And now owned by Amazon
Offered a deductible reimbursement process for their stuff
Tattoo they did and
Jamie siminoff
From ring was actually one of my First Investors
In my company and he was one of my early adviser so that was definitely a play out of there
Play book I saw Jamie.
Doing that a long time ago and kind of scratch my head and I was like
That's something that we may be able to do once we collect more data and feel really comfortable now Jamie did that with an insurance
He did that with
American Family Insurance I believe
And so we got so confident
And you know we were kind of
Working with different partners and we just decided hey this is something that we can potentially do ourselves looked at the data that we have been
Collecting from
The many homes that we've installed our technology in and just made the decision internally that this was something that we were just going to go up
About doing ourselves
So from an Actuarial basis
Does Ensure is love
Do you have to have a certain number of like
It's like man years but they're just year
Years of data on
How do you guys
Create models what are confidence intervals what is this look like when you're like setting aside money in escrow
To pay this out
I mean truthfully with the homes that we've been installed with so far
We haven't seen any catastrophic water
Anyone that follows our technology the way that it should be kind of did the math to see how many homes
We would have had to pay out claims
4 so far if every single person
It's signed up for home protect program and we just we didn't have any claim
So to some extent is a
The startup you know you can just
Look at the data you have I wouldn't say that any of the data that we
Collected would get any of the big insurance companies
Comfortable we've been operating as a company for new three years and had a about a product on the market for less than
One so I don't think there is
Any way that we could get an insurance company
But that's kind of the way that we went about it that's why we went about it the way that we did
Let's talk about this from
Perspective only because they care so much about longevity and this is the sort of product where I plan to install this
How often should I
Replace this or think about how often should I have to
The part of our technology that can
Really suffer from wear and tear
Is the mechanical ball valve or technology does turn on and turn off the water every single day that's how
Test every day whether or not there's a leak in the home we know definitively whether or not there are leaks every single day
Turning on and turning off the water
And actually eating that ball Bell
.
Mechanical part could wear
Parent are so we've tested that for well over five years we've actually tested it over 8
We believe that once you install this
You really don't need to think about it for at least five years that's a week
I think the useful life is but it could be much longer
Any device
Nest isn't
Reduce the number of different
You know thermostats ring has introduced new doorbells that technology just gets better and better with time
So I don't believe that this
This is the kind of product that you just going to want to let you know set it and forget it for the next 50 years I believe that
Some point people will probably want to upgrade anyways
Okay so for a while nest on the thermostat front was doing upgrades like
Every 12 to 8
18 months which belt
Like super fast
Granted it was a brand new product so I doubt it but what do you think the logical product update cycle is for something
That is smart
It's closer to about like 24 to 36 months I just believe I think that in our space
They specifically this is
This is so new and there's so much that we can do around water
That I'm going to come tell you you're going to c-diff
Different versions of our product
Released within the next 24 to 36 months
For sure and I think that you know we're all kind of waiting as you've touched on in your previous articles for some
Great connected home platform to kind of bring all these products
Together I think with all the data that were collecting
We're only going to make the home
Smarter from our standpoint
Specifically I can tell you like we're collecting data every second of the day
From a water flow standpoint pressure stamp
Temperature I mean this is all new data that no one is really
You know using yet to make the home more thoughtful and so as differ
Protocols May
Come to the Forefront and whatnot I think for a number of reasons
Maybe 24 to 36 months
Okay
Insurance
It's cuz I didn't quite as much as I wanted to there
Let's talk
Priestly so you guys have started this
I agree that the insurance Market is waiting on data that
I don't know if they'll ever get what do you think
They're going to do in the smart
Cuz there's this idea that they're going to
Remake the way they offer
Policies
Premiums but then there's also a much more
Have Monday and idea that they'll just do it as a competitive differentiator like
In marketing their insurance products which is maybe less exciting
Yeah and I think the ladder is what they've
I've been doing today all the big
Partnerships that we've seen between iot products
Can insurance
I've really been about Mark
It's really been about
The differentiating
Their product
@the insurtech conference
In October of last year
I had the
Share some thoughts on stage
And one of the things I said to insurance companies is
I want a partner with insurance
Companies that actually want
To drive down
Claim frequency and severity
That's what we're doing
People want to
Introduce Flo is a marketing product they can do that
But really we really want to make an impact on insurance
Really want to make an impact on how often homeowners are being inconvenienced by water damage
So far there's a lot of
Talk and I think that you are seeing
Startup insurance
Are seeing the opportunity and are moving you know very quickly to adopt iot and really big That Into You Know.
The way that they are offering Insurance in the way that they're
Apple protecting home so
If they don't
To get it together that's right
The disruption
Is really going to happen
I will say Stacy there was one
Gaia can't name is
Name cuz we were under Andy and I can't even name the insurance company but there was one executive from one of the top five insurance
They said said to me you know what some point the insurance
Industry just needs
Look at each other
And say hey
This is a great thing
You know we can test this
And I mean
Are products
She's probably been tested by most
Insurance companies in there
Employee homes
And I know that they're just
They're all their eyes light up when they
You know in real-time they can see what's happening with their homes water it'll shut off the water for them automatically
So at some point the executives
You know on the business side need to go back to the x-rays and just say hey
We don't
Need
Years worth of data
Like this is just a great thing and it's logical that this is going to help drive down claim and we have to
To do something
And so what he believes was going to happen
Is that at some point you're just going to get
A bunch of people together in a company that just said this is too good to pass up we need to do something aggressive here
And I kind of share that thought with
I don't know if that act
Actuarial
50000 years of data is
Is going to happen before
You just got a few people that are thinking logically that are just willing to put their neck on the line and say this is something we have to adopt
That's more likely to happen first
And if they don't it feels like they risk being cut out and there's a lot of opportunities
According to McKinsey
The insurance company like Google or Amazon
And create an insurance product
Corporates connected devices that would be a much better deal
For consumers because they would have
Again
Products like yours as part of that portfolio
Unclaimed sky
Process
Policy pricing
Do you think that's feasible
Absolutely
I think that not only are we going to
See those kind of companies
Adopt
The right Technologies in the more aggressive way
They're going to know what to do with all the
Data link right now
Even you know I have a nest in my house
I have
Ring doorbell I have
My flow device
And none of them are really talking to each other at least in a very smart way that's helping to
Protect my home and giving me multiples
On that invest
With my device
With the flow device
Installed in a home
Like I said before we're collecting data every second of the day and so we know when
People are home and not home
Just based on their water
So at some point you're going to see
When the flow device
Shows that there's been no water use
DiGiorno flushes of a toilet for example for 24 hours but the alarm has
You should get a ping
You should probably set your alarm it doesn't look like you're home because you haven't had any water running here
Once you are able to connect all of these different devices
You're going to get a home that's much more resilient
Much smarter
And I think that the way that it's looking
It's much more likely than Amazon or Google is going to come in and do that rather than
And insurance
Do you think customers and consumers are going to be excited about sharing all that data providers
I think it's all about
What's a quid pro quo
I think that
Data can be used as a currency so today we don't
Volunteer
Homeowners data
To share with
Insurance Company
However
If a homeowner would like to get some kind of an
Incentive from their care
And their carrier will offer that in
Incentive in exchange
Or some sharing of data then that's a decision that the homeowner
Should be able to make on their own
If they don't want to share the data then
You know they don't have to accept whatever the insurance company is offering
So I think that it's a decision that homeowners have to make I think it's an option for them ultimately I do think they will
Will share their data as long as it's used in a responsible way it will make their premium
Lower not just because of
The incentive that they're getting from
The insurance carrier for the adoption But ultimately when you bring all of these different data points together
It's just going to make the home smarter and better able to protect you
Which will ultimately mean lower premium so I really do believe that it's in everybody's best
Pinterest you mentioned earlier some of the
Cool things that we can do with water in
So I'm curious
So when you can just learn a lot about
Homeowners
You can learn a lot about how they interact
With their home one of the things that I've been
Discussing with insurance
Carriers and the light bulb goes off they get it is
When you
Receiving alert
From Flo that for example you have high
Water pressure
High water pressure essentially is like high blood pressure in your body if you have high blood pressure for long periods of time
That's putting under
The Strain on your veins or arteries eventually organs.
When you have high water pressure in
On your pipes that me
Means that you're putting
Do strain on your pipes
Your fixtures your appliances and eventually something will burst this is part of the preventive side of our technology
So when you have this data
And you have these
Set alerts from Flo they're telling you
Hey you got high water pressure this is a maintenance opportunity you got to do something about it and I'll let say that the homeowner ignores those
They throw caution to the wind
No they don't do anything
Now I think that says something
About
Potentially that homo
Is that the same kind of homeowner that leaves their doors unlock
Doesn't set their alarm
Smell gas and doesn't do any
I think there's a lot that in
Insurance
Learn about customer
Behavior and I don't
Mean to suggest that you know homeowner should be scared of data I think what this is doing is
It's offering more
Opportunities
For homeowners
To see what happen
Behind the black box
That is their Plumbing
Behind all these different
I think the key to a smart home is
Having a home that's
More thoughtful that suggest
To you when there are different problems lurking when you need to act
And not just you know being able to open and close your door by pushing a button
I think it's really about having a home that's smarter that better put
XU so that's one of the things that I'm
Suggesting about
Water data I think it's a great indicator of
Not only occupancy
But it's a great lens into all of the different Acts
Cavities in the home and being able to better protect you from a number of different dimensions
Awesome
Because sometimes I am
I am curious to see this Brave New World
Thank you so much for coming on the show this
Thanks for having me Stacy appreciate it thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more I sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week