Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Kevin tofel
Going to talk about
Automated Factory
Energy harvesting Tech
Details on homekit
Some Google home preview stuff
And
A review of a new device I purchased
Is it a small
It is not the small
But it's never
But first
Before we do anything we must cover this
Most important
Moment of the show
Which is
Last week we talked about wink
Being purchased by William
And I said William after
How much struggle was a member of Alec
Fast and I was wrong
Wish everyone was very quick to point out which I am
I love that your dedication to William
So strong
I have a good thing that wasn't the Daily Double on Today Show
Exactly so William is actually he was a member of The Black Eyed Pea
Which is why Fergie kept
I feel better about that
But moving along to this week's
Coverage
We have no updates on William a twink
Unfortunately
I am waiting
For that
Hey
This week sponsor who is Hico Solutions
And a preview of our guests Michael Spears who is the head of infrastructure cyber
Security at
Honeywell
And he is going to be really fascinating you guys were talking about
How to secure
Physical plants they have totally different threat Landscapes but some of the things they do
The rest of the world probably
I'm as well
So
Stay tuned for that
And now
Message from another
This week sponsor is Eero and let me tell you guys Eros
These are wireless mesh routers there are brand new 2nd generation Eero routers out there
Or and I can tell you that I have them currently installed in my house and they are fast
Eero router said I had installed at my house for the last year-and-a-half
These contain what major Eero a square that looks like kind of the other Eros and then it has
Beacons bees are mesh access points are not Wi-Fi extenders but these mesh access
Test points are smaller you can plug them in and they also act as a night light and the cool thing is
These are backwards compatible with your old Eero so you can upgrade your Eros
By buying a couple new beacons if you want $449 or if you don't have
Mesh wi-fi system yet you can buy the Eero in its original 3-pack configuration of one major
Beacon Sports
Free 99
If you want to buy these zero routers you should go to the Eero ero.com
And when you buy it you should put the code Stacey Stacey
And you'll get free shipping you also tell Eero that you listen podcast will keep getting advertisers
Yay okay so now onto the show
Talk about Adidas
Shadow
We shall
This I thought was a wicked cool story and I can't believe no one else has
Tell me about this sew in
Little Rock Arkansas there is a Chinese company
Tiana Von Karman
Company of Suzhou
Yes
So they signed an agreement with software automation of
Atlanta
Hey to a partnership with the Georgia Tech advanced technology
Development Center
And all of this means that
Jian-yang is going to be producing shirts for Adidas
In a fully automated Factory
Invite fully automated
Basically this thing uses cameras to me
Fabric is using robots to steer the fabric to the sewing needles
And
They're going to make t-shirts for Adidas
A whole lot of t-shirts
Adidas
Because the numbers are mind-blowing to Miyagi
I'm not familiar with Industrial
Production of such things but when I saw
How many T-shirts they can produce I was blown away
Me too I don't know how they're going to sell out
So they will produce 800,000 t-shirts a day for Adidas in this Factory
On 21 production lines
And the crazy part
Is it the Personnel cost for each t-shirt is roughly $0.33
That is like the cheapest labor
One can
Find
Which is good in bed
Yes
I think right because on the green side it's certainly good for Adidas because it
Certainly lower their costs
I wish I could pass on the consumers or they can just take him or process etcetera
But if you're a worker in this industry
It's probably a bad thing
Yeah so this is going to bring 400 new jobs to Arkansas
But
If you imagined 400 jobs
Producing
Thousand t-shirts a day
One every 22 seconds
That is a huge productivity bump that is not being handled
So then the question is
What do people do
And
That is a
Big question that were trying to figure out
Across all Industries I personally think
It frees people up to do
Are creative and fun things
Kwik podcast
Slate podcast
But it also thinks you can think about designing and
Where new cosmic coming from and
I guess
The lower
I don't know what that lower cost of t-shirt
Yeah I mean there's other stuff with positive us
Pics of it and this is really I think
Tip of the iceberg Salt Lake is the first
Production line that is fully automated
Obviously
But
It's a very tangible
Example of what's going on
In manufacturing
Around the world and it's inevitable unfortunately
What is disturbing
Is it feels like this manufacturer the automated Manufacturing
A lot of Chinese companies are in
Investing in this
I would like to in
With much manufacturing is
Already happening
Can China fit Foxconn
Is investing in fully automated
I believe iPhone play
So Foxconn already has 40000 robots on it
Production lines Foxconn is Apple's main iPhone assembler
And basically it is replaced more than half of its Workforce with robots
Since
The launch of the iPhone 6
That is
A lot
And they have men
Lights out
Which are fully automated production lines at some of the
Their factories
And the whole idea is
Tire factories not just production line
Mine's operate
This is a crazy this actually it's not crazy
This is a big deal because
If the future of automation
And Manufacturing
Is
Robots
China is really
Pushing hard on
Leaving ahead here
And that means we can have manufacturing anywhere
Because we've got
It'll be automated
And we'll be looking for things you know
Setting up these industrial cluster so you don't have to ship things as far it's a really interesting kind of
Manufacturing and Industry
You shouldn't kind of vision
But
I am concerned that we are
In the US are not at the
And yeah
It's funny that you mention Foxconn and Apple only because
When you crack your iPhone screen and take it in to get repaired at an Apple store or some third part
Party such as Best Buy
It's not a person who repairs it anymore
It is it is not
And that is why
When you go there and I've had a couple of the kids have crackers screens
It's almost always
Should be done in an hour
I know it's an hour because not because there's a person sitting there saying it's going to take me an hour to do this
Apple has
Created automated machines that do it
For them
Is a comet
Redis
Yikes alright
Yikes
Because there's not a lot we can adhere
It's it's something that I'm constantly thinking about
In reading about
I have no great conclusions like
So let's talk about energy Harvest
Cuz
This was really cool I am a big fan
Of
Energy harvesting
And I've been
Caring about this for so long because I have so many devices that
Batteries in my home
But I'm also thinking about things like hey if we put a bunch of sensors on Bridges
Or sensors under parking spaces are those kind of things
How do we change the batteries in this it's
It's not possible today so
That's why
Anything that harvests its own energy is really cool
We have to look at this I think because Battery Technology really has not
Drastically changed over
Pastor K Square Dallas ISO
And we have more mobile devices they all have batteries of course so how do we recharge them how do we
Get energy back into them quicker without
Using the traditional plug it in method
So this is very big
So this article in a link to in the story is from CNN
Engineering
News not CNN
Betsy and
Eaton
Worth noticing
In the cupboard
Some things I knew so the main forms of energy harvesting
AR
Solar
Solar power things there's pie co which takes
Like motion energy
And converts it into
There's also
Temperature differentials can be used as well
In certain sensors
This article talked about something I hadn't dealt
Before
It's a rare earth magnet the moves on Springs alongside a wire coil and generates electricity
It produces between 50 and 90 million watts of power that's milliwatts you
Guys not a lot right much
But that's enough to energy like to power temperature sensor
A mems device like a mems accelerometer and a wireless transmitter
So this is from a company called perpetuum
I do like its name
This could work under they filter rail system so it goes under a passenger or Freight cars in rails and
Grabs information send it to a Gateway and then it goes to the
To the cloud
Real workers can act on any of the data
Like
It's a little extra bumpy here I could see something like this working for detecting potholes
In a city using like a Laura
Radio
Maybe
Which
We talked about it the show
So
I thought the magnets kind of thing was cool but basically I just wanted to draw y'all's attention to this because
I don't think we talked about it enough
I don't think there's a lot of research happening here that
Sleek
I mean I talk to an ocean which is the big name in this field and they've been around for
17 years
They do great things but
I'm kind of like
What else is there
Yeah I mean this is a field that I think is right for
Further
Rationed probably further investment
We need to rethink how we
How are things
Because the things themselves have gotten so small and don't use as much energy
Required for a hardwired power saw
Source or a battery you know what I mean the batteries are larger than the sensors at this point
And we should also note
When I talk to people in like the industrial World about
Sensing and battery-powered
Sensors they talk about it being a psychological choice
I was like what are you talking about
Psychology element
And basically what they're talking about
Is this idea
A mighty world we want to know everything that's happening
All the time
Breakdown
And in some of the industrial world
They're like hey
How often really do I need the
This
And it's a very simple fact that if you have your
Item only update
Three times a day
Uses less power than going to waking up every 20 seconds to send it
These guys actually think about that as part of their design
Their overall systems
They're from a worldview which is very
Power constrained in very sensitive just this sort of
Think so I thought that was kind of an interesting way
Think about
How often do I need my
Water sensor if it's
Not
Reporting a leak
To wake up
You know maybe once a day just to tell me the temperature is fine
And then when something goes wrong it could be like
So that's really all I have to say about this I recommend you check out the article and you know if you guys have some great ideas or
Cool energy harvesting
God send it to me I am like
Really
Really want to nerd out Deep
Cell
Moving right along to slightly less
Pistol dirty but in a good way
It's more accessible because it's Apple by golly
So I have been the biggest doubter
I really had next to me next
To see whose outcome Campmor
We might have less doubts now
Fewer doubts
I'm in a few workouts you can have left
And thicker Marian's listening to the shokan
So
Apple
Said cryptically
It was going to make homekit available to a wider
Number of
Partners
And I had Adam Justice on the show then and he pointed that out to me
And he's like I don't know
And then we saw the release of
Products like
Ikea's tradfri
Lamps and actually announced that it would work with Apple
In the future
His travel
Apple has required you to have a certification ship
It's all part of it security
And so that's why you got all these like
You got to buy a new hub
Which kind of sucked if you were a consumer
Which is why I did not like it
But now
Box it looks
Black people are actually implementing
The
Mfi certification chip
Less version of home gym
And that's exciting
And then there's one other piece of this that
Seems kind of exciting that
The Verge
They had a column from the internet of
I can't say it on this show and keep my
Berating soda
The internet
But he was a write-up
The point or she
With no nose
Sonos
Homekit
With the homepod in December
To make it accessible to Android and Apple homes the mixed homes as it
And I think that would be a smart move if that's the case said it was already seen one major
Apple service
Compatible with Android and that was
Apple music
That's actually one of the reasons I think that Apple music subscriptions are going up because there's a wider group of potential
Customer ser
And partly that's because
That what music is really came from Beats Music which was already
Android-compatible so that just made sense to continue it
But yeah I mean if you could get the
Homepod
Working with Android
Again you broaden your potential audience at smart
Well and I look at this from a business perspective
Apple has historically made everything work with their phone their phone was the flagship of the business of that lie
Talk about computers later
But
Mobile
Hadoop operating system
The phone was it and that was the key
Computer for everything
With his signals
Possibly
Is a realization
That
You can still own the consumer
Without owning the home
And still provide
A viable ecosystem
And I don't know how apples going to make money off of this with homekit I don't know if you have to pay
I mean you have to pay
An mfi fee for the certification chips you have to be of mfi certified
Developer
Etcetera
But
I like this because Apple
Has come a long way with the design
There's still some things I don't
But
It is user-friendly and
This is where things get a little weird and
Developers are
Like apple what you doing and apples like
So you can actually set up a device
Using homekit and use it only in the whole map you don't have to actually set up the
App for the
Device
Right you can say you're reducing the number of apps required to manage your devices number one
That's a simpler
Sign up in end pairing type of process
Ben Franklin my ecobee it just showed up
Installment that's it I mean
It was there
The developers on the other hand are doing everything they can
Play as much as I can with apple but also get you to download the app so they have your
Formation your email
So someone like a lot
Might make you calibrate the lock in their own app
Where is after that point
You can move to
You know
The Apple
Experience
So this is producing a lot of tension so we'll see what happens
As part of this I'll just tell you that there's a brand-new homekit enabled
Light bulb from Sylvania
Name brand
A colorful light bulb it is $45 no hub
So if you're like looking at the Hue Lights and you're like
Oh that should be home
Love it
This is a Sylvania
Sylvania
And it works
Use
Bluetooth
Yeah
Homekit
Friendly friendly
You wouldn't want this
If you're an apple house
And eventually after we test the homepod maybe we'll tell you what it's like to live in a mixed house and have these
Vices
This is good and
I imagine that eventually this will use Bluetooth
If it does
It's a double for pre-order for
For $45 so it's not an expensive but it's not too bad either
Well actually the beer
39 teens in the BR30 that's it
I feel like the 19th
You land this year have a hub
So I'll get a test version of that
And I'll tell you how the
The lights work
And you can
Look forward to that they will not ship until
Just so you know
Okay
Movie from the homekit news let's go to the Google
This is interesting and I will say right up front that I have not signed up for this yet but there is a preview
Program if you had a Google home
You may sign up for the preview program and will happen is
Kind of like what they do with the Chromecast where they sent you
Advanced features sooner 4 beta testing essentially
MC make it new firmware on your Google home before everybody else
New features and so on
I generally
Can't pass up a beta program so once I put my Google home back in my home office which is
Undergoing renovation right now
I will sign up for this so I don't know what they might bring to us
We want to see but you can sign up maybe we can click the link in the show notes
We will
I will also sign up
Even though my Google home does not get the usage
Voice control Amazon Echo
Control TVs
Certain TVs
Yeah and
For me my TV is not supported
Officially but
If you have an Amazon Fire TV box which I do connected to my TV you can then pair your Echo with the Fire TV box
Cowboys control the TV that way
And in a speculative new story
Amazon echos make it multi-room audio
I thought you would like that
I'm just going to get
Ricky forum
Where the heck is my Sonos
Where the hell is my Sonos I have
I've been buying Echoes and I don't want to buy the full Echoes because
I have all these lovely Sonos isn't in my room and talk card
Frustrated
Well if multi-room audio comes to Echo devices I don't know that
There's a ton of incentive for Amazon to
Bring it to something
That's I'm not saying that's what they do
I'm just saying
I wouldn't be surprised if you never see that person
I don't think they promised they said they were going to do it
They did say that
Did not text
I promise you
Right
I actually reached out to Sonos about two weeks ago maybe three weeks
And ask for an update
And then I will get that to you and then no one
That to me
I'm going to have to reach out again I guess
Moving on
Because it feels negative to complain all the time
On the show
Let's talk about
Cool story before we get our little review
Future of Home Building
I thought this was really interesting this is from Cee Pro
And
Basically
Ideas and Linares home Linares home builder
They have stopped
Putting low-voltage wiring this is the wiring for your speakers for doorbells for all kinds of things
They built the first Wi-Fi certified smart
Holmes and this is something the Wi-Fi alliance-certified earlier this summer
Yeah we remember we talked about and I was kind of scratching my head over
What Linares doing is they're going to pull CAT5 or 6 cable
2 WiFi access points as well as the doorbell look
Location
But they're not going to pull it to home office locations or entertainment center
So no speaker wire
Coax is only going to go to two TV locations in the majority of their new
This is a big freaking deal
Yes
This is a big freaking deal because it means another step closer towards Wireless whether you want it or not
And I don't want it I'm going to say I built my home in 2012
And I put Cat6 not CAT5 because it's Cat6 gigabit proof and I'm still hoping to get gigabit internet but it's not happening
Side note little bitterness
I tell people when they ask about future-proofing their home
To stick
Cable
Running into an Ethernet Jack
Every room
I would agree and I know people hate hugs
By god it feels
And maybe
You know I'm thinking about
My original Eros actually I had them
I wired them
I meant so they weren't actually at 10
Because they were wired in
Wi-Fi assist
With the beacons
There is
There is no
That is fully Wireless so maybe I'm right behind the
X
Well
I mean the benefits of wired
Is it's pretty much guaranteed consistency right whereas wireless networks will fluctuate
Based on signal strength
And other things so
I agree with your concerns
On the flip side
I literally just bought a small 4K set
TV set
And I put it in our bedroom is wall-mounted
Enemies in Wi-Fi to watch 4K TV on it
Just like I do in the 4K set
In my office and we have a
1080p sets
Downstairs that was actually hardwired
But everything else is
Wireless mouse, don't have the Jacks in a cat stick
With the right
Wireless network you know it can work
Minutes working for me
What I could say to me multiple 4K streams and so on
So I guess even though I'm concerned
Hypocritical here because it is working for me all Wireless
That's a question
Are we
Ready for this
In
Maybe we are I think about
You know Eero which is managing your connectivity
Are managing your signal strength in
Doing all of that
Prioritizing
Amazing
I'm in their services like plume that do similar things but only in the cloud
And Comcast is better than Samsung
Plume
So it's possible
It is which of the point now where Wireless
Speeds from routers and such
Are far faster than the
Piper the Broadband the wire Broadband of people get to the houses being with so
Maybe maybe this time
Maybe it's certainly lowers the cost of building a house and if your home builder you know
Ages copper
It's copper wiring so if you can
Stop
Wiring things to speakers that's that's
Very economical
I don't know y'all
Sacher listener test
Some thoughts I'd be curious to hear that
Cynosure
I should say
Because I got a question I actually got two questions about the
That's so quick note I always tell people
How much I like netatmo stuff
And then I got an email from an frustrated user because netatmo went down this weekend
Did a terrible job communicating to their customers about what happened
So
I heard back from that app they said the issues
Has been solved
Both issues have been thought they had two issues one as people cannot install their net out
Cameras
So please try again if
If you can install it
In two notifications were delayed in the camera missed events and that issue has also been solved
They didn't explain what happened
Hopefully if you had a netatmo camera that wasn't work
Working this weekend
Try everything again
Restart it
And see what happens
It still doesn't work let me know and I will
Come back to them and be
All right guys
That's up to you there
And then finally
A tiny little review
A tiny little review of a tiny little device that I was so excited to have
Okay you guys probably remember
That I wanted a standalone Spotify
Player to take on walks with
My dog
And I bought the mighty
It's the mighty player in this is the be mighty
Dotcom is so
Website
This is a $95
It looks like an iPod Shuffle
Yes the tiny little ones you can't control
It works
So well
So
They promised me five hours of battery life
Pushed it to four and a half and then I was like if I don't charge now I won't have access to my music tomorrow morning
Fullback is a
It's a fit like it's a
Probably 1 and 1/2 inch by 1 and 1/2 inch I'm not looking directly at the specs
Device
But the whole back is the clip so it's not like there's a smaller clip so it's a little awkward
Sometimes to put on my
My outfit
Going out to walk the dog
Works with both
Bluetooth headphones and wired headphones so gay
And
Actually has made me want to get wired
Are wireless headphones now
It
It's user interface is really simple it does take kind of a long time to
Move up play move your playlist over
Alright alright playlist over via WiFi
Your home Wi-Fi and that's I'm assuming we're it's also doing the DRM
Play Spotify
Checking in but it also will do things like
There's an option to
Succumbing option I didn't see it yet on my thing
But keep it fresh which means some of their playlist that you might have Daya
Update
Pretty lady
And that'll automatically update it when it's on your Wi-Fi network
In the house
I looked at it works exactly like I thought it was going to work
3 weeks and
By God
I suspect that you have to sink that
To Spotify
Once at least every month or so
Possibly
MX
And the reason I say that is because
Gosh this is going way back I think the Microsoft Zune
Wood
Do that you could
Download stuff from your music apps for Microsoft
As long as you had your subscription pay the zoompass I think it was called
10 bucks a month or something
But you had to exert a check in from a different perspective at least once every 30 days or would not just
Cease working for you
And that was just to make sure your Pandora subscription witches and Spotify as a subscription service
Makes sense
Write this does only work
You pay for the
Spotify premium
Right
But if this need is something you guys have
I really recommend this product it's great
It's not really a coyote
But it's still connected
That's about it for us this week we shall
Take a moment for a message from our sponsor and after that we will have
Mike's Beer
From Honeywell talk to you about
Cybersecurity and how they think about it on the industrial iot
Plantside
Which is very different from how we think about it
In
I don't know the IT world or even the whole bar
But you can learn from it
Yes you can
All right
Stay tuned for that and now a message from our sponsor everyone we are breaking into the
The Internet of Things podcast
From haikou
Hey Marcus how are you doing today
I'm doing great Stacy thanks so much for having me
Excellent
Glad you're here so
Remind us all again what it is that high cosolutions
We are in advance
Iot engineering Solutions provider with Development Centers based in Eastern Europe
Recall primarily US based clients
By providing engineering teams that included numbers
Allowing us to help
Our partners
Design and build
End and custom iot Solutions
All right so you mentioned that you guys come by the number of skills to build these teams
Can you talk about those
We really combined skill and what we describe is Three core areas
Number one embedded firmware in electrical engineering
So thank you
PCB design Electronics
Component selection
Knowledge of the different Wireless protocols
Are there more standard or
Zigbee Z-Wave Lora
Amongst many others
Number to mathematical data processing
Do we have a team of phds focus
In discrete mathematics
Computational geometry statistical analysis
Really work on building custom algorithmics
Solutions using Advanced machine-learning Techniques
And the number 3 digital experience
Were suffering
Engineering we employed several hundred software engineers
Mosto
An educational background in mathematics
You working a plethora of different programming languages
For both mobile and web applications
Play end-to-end Solutions what we really mean is that
We combine all of these
Skills to build teams that help our clients with everything from
Designing the electronic
Components within a connected device
Using mathematicians to drive value out of a date of this coming from the sensors within those devices
Software engineering teams to build interfaces for those applications
I like it
So what is the typical client
Our clients come in all shapes and sizes
Pittsburgh
Early industry agnostic
But we work with
Funded startups to the Fortune 50
What they generally have in common is that they're looking for highly Advanced engineering skill that is both difficult
And expensive to Source locally
They're generally looking for a partner who can ramp up teams within a few weeks at a very reasonable cost
I believe they find
The combination of skills in the number of things they can accomplish with one partner
Hard to find anywhere else
Excellent so where can we get more information
Website
Can get white papers case studies technology roadmaps project
Description
All available at www.schluter.com hiq oh
Dash solutions.com
Excellent thank you Marcus
Thank you Stacey
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Mike
Speaker who is a global operations manager for a
Industrial cybersecurity
Add Honeywell
Hi Stacy doing well thanks
Man I'm super excited to have you on the show because
I went to this
User group meeting and I saw you speak about
Cybersecurity and securing
Manufacturing
I was kind of Blown Away I was like
Wow they have a totally different
Threat landscape
And they're thinking about it in kind of a way that maybe it organization should also start
Matador other businesses who are dealing
Coyote
So let's kick it off with
What year did charge of sick
What you doing
Okay well I'm responsible for the on-site delivery
Cyber Solutions for the industrial Market
Industrial Market as Define
Bios SB oil and gas refining
Petrochemical paper the processing
And we try to help is as you mentioned the operations technology is often referred to as the OT environment
Secure their systems
Balancing the need of
Conduction which is
Their Paramount importance and safety
With that of
Security tolerance
So I lead the team around the globe
That I'll go to the sides and
Meet with the customers understand
Risk tolerance risk appetite
And then we come up with the solutions that help them mitigate the levels of risk that they feel that Dane
I need to
Mitigate
Okay we're going to talk about
But good
Good that's why I signed up to come on the show
But first we're going to talk about
Process manufacturing vs. discrete manufacturing
Cuz it's possibly worth it to
Break this up because Manufacturing
Is the same
Can you
Kaplan
For me process Industries is that take something
L on the input side and I turn it into something
Altonio
Passat so I take off
A wood chips in on a paper I take wall in and I make gas I take chemicals in and I made
Pills
Where is discrete manufacturing
For me is more of an assembly
I'm putting a car together
I'm making an iPhone
The process Industries
Again more processing raw input
Into a usable while slightly different app
Okay in the process industry has had sensors
For a long time this is not new to start throwing sensors in in measuring
The stuff where is in other Industries
It might be
So what is actually changed with quote-unquote
The internet
Things
I think the Internet of Things is a hole
New future Direction
For the process
Streets again up until
We would say in the short history
The process Industries where or very proprietary environment
Meaning the communication between the sensors all the way up to the controls
Was a proprietary boss
Riesling and say the last 10 years or so
Cost and other factors in in in the need for additional information has driven
The industry to what they call the open architecture
Therein lies
The openness
Of the structure
So so now everything once we brought the
Ethernet cable shall we say
To the plant for that opens up the capabilities in the flexibility
To do more get more information to optimize
Improve the security and safety of the overall environment
At what that also becomes the need then more
To get more of that information up to the business level so that businesses can make real-time decisions based
Directly down the what's going on
At the process
Level at the sensor level chart
All right
So you guys have been starting to
The old-school proprietary
Communications
Ran in factories for a while
With now
New school it
Ethernet
Specific word like stuff
Let's talk about how you thought about security
When you started this and what you're thinking about secure
Security now so how that perspective is change
Call gimatic Lychee
In the beginning with a proprietary system of the communication protocols
The access within the environment was the limited to those who understood the protocol
A noun with an open protocol or nope
Open system as we say where I be quote-unquote Centric
Now it's the same common language at the entire world
Uses weather as your bank or your
Financial systems use your Walmart
Shell gas station
All that technology it is very similar now most businesses
People I've been dealing with this for
For 20 years you know it's just now recently
The. Same technology has
Becoming dated into the plant
Floor now I'll be at
It's not a direct one to one
You can't do a lot of the things that the plant level
That you could for example on your business ID
One of the things that we use as an example for example if your it group want you to reboot your
Workstation
That's a pretty non-invasive activity whereas that
Can a plant floor
Automatically rebooting A system can have very catastrophic country
So it has to be done with care
Same with God communication protocols in the interruptions of a
Of communication that the plant level
It can be
Much more
I'm a safety standpoint
Severe impacts then it would
If you lose
For example your email
Show me big big change at the at the plant level
Okay so now that you've brought this in
How do you educate
People in the it security world and then
How do you educate your existing security or
Even Personnel on the floor
How to behave cuz
The feels like
Your workers are probably really well-trained
Comes to safety issues like
Hey that's a bad hydrochloric acid
You probably shouldn't touch that
Maybe you should wear certain
Gear around it but when it comes to the IT world
Maybe they don't get the same things like hay
You should not send your bank account over email
Hopefully everyone knows that but
Just in case
You'd be surprised
But absolutely I think
About definition
That they're different
Resources or are the people running the plants or are different mindset
Almost a process Focus chemical Engineers again
They're interested in making whatever it is they're making
They're not
Focus so much on on the it side because that's not something that deal with
Again the very leery of having the it
Their it group actually come in and do stuff at the plant level
That's one of the biggest things I think in the in the Takata I kind of gave that example of a anybody
Anaplan
It's a song of rickety old ladder leaned against the
A wall and somebody climbing up
50 lb bag
What's a haze
Call OSHA that's a safety has
But if they were walking in the parking lot and said the CEO salary
On a USB stick
999 would go in and plug it into the
Computer they don't have that same level of
Diligence
Governance
I at the plant level around these type
Security program
And that's one of the messages were trying to get out there
It's more than just
Putting in a firewall or or
Segmenting a network it's the people process technology
People are your biggest
Is one of your biggest risk factor
I am so this whole awareness
Educating
The plant people
On what to look for in what to do
And so that when events do happen they know exactly
The right reaction they say
She takes
To an event that may potentially cause severe damage to the to the plant and production inbox
In extreme circumstances safety
So how do you train people in what are the things you're trying to train your workers on when it comes to
Thai tea
It's two different training aspects that
When you refer to workers
19rr very
Specialized
They are
Typically this is very new in this space
There's not a lot of people with 20 years ago
Experience and in doing industrial it
So we typically recruit from
How did the industry and get the senior the set call an IT expert
We bring them into our organization and and weedy to them and it take somewhere between 3 to 6
Sometimes 9 months daddy totem
Anybody to know Mommy
Taking all that technology
Experience and knowledge and certifications that you had any idea what all can modify them
To apply them
To the industrial world and it's only after they've gained the whole
Knowledge of all those things
Do we actually let him go out and actually service our customer
Only
Other side
For our customers
We're offering a variety of a
We start with awareness training
Again it goes to the whole concept of
Your what should you do when what should you look for what are some of the basics around cyber
You should be thinking about when you're
Designing implementing
Will purchasing a new control system
. all the way up to
For some of my mom
Amateur customers
You know I'm going to put in a Sim what does that look like lettuce train you on the advantages of us M LeSabre
Versus
You know another security control
It ranges the whole gamut on the list, customer side
Okay what are the biggest things you have to
Your it
Folks honor what are what are the things that they need
The most help
That's a lot of stuff I mean I got I want to get too technical lovey landing and some of the
The technical things that you
You can do
An AIT environment
You just cannot
Do
In a process environment
Duda responsiveness this required
Loss of view in a control system for a minute is a big deal
You know where house if you're
Screen at your laptop goes out for a minute it's
Kinosaki end of the world
In a plant it could cause catastrophic results
So it's really training him around that it's awesome
Walking into a plant that mean you going
I'm very
Hazardous areas you know how do you operate in these hazardous areas
Think about it if I plug
The cable
In the wrong places
Create a control Loop you know the impact of a
Cover Refinery doing that versus
Let's say seven eleven
Is significantly different
Okay that's kind of Awesome
Let's talk about risk mitigation because
Couple people I talk to you at this time
You know I was asking him
Very security questions and they were like
Really Stacy this is a psychological issue
It's basically how secure do you really feel like you need to be
And once you get past that then you can say
Your printer
That's even an option
To think about how secure you need to be
That's crazy I just want to be secure
Help me with the the industrial security mindset
In terms of figuring out
How to think about risk
Risk is to as
That's right you got risk tolerance which is
You know how much can the business actually tolerate
And in Risk appetite which is how much can you really afford to do
Put it in comparison to your house
You can lock your front door
That may be a good real
You can put bars on your windows
You can put an alarm
If you're trying to mitigate the risk against an assassin trying to shoot you
They may be good things but you may want to wear
Kevlar vest
There's all these different Soul levels
Depending on what it is you're trying to protect yourself against
And in only the business
Meaning the customer
Can I answer that question
My version of protection may be different than your version of protection
So it is somewhat psychological shall we say but
But more in terms of appetite versus watching the business take
Can you afford to have this process line down for six weeks
That type of and you have to do these type of a
Mitigation Of valuations of risk calculation
To determine what level of security
That you need to implement in your sister
Fciac 62443 which is kind of the guidelines for
Control systems
You know eat lays it out in terms of
Who you trying to protect yourself against
Are you trying to protect yourself against Stacy who may come in and
Accidentally plug your laptop into the control system
And her husband was playing Star Wars or some game on the
I dated myself there with with their laptop and infection
The system
Or are you trying to
Protect yourself against node in there somebody that's
You're trying to do harmful within the walls or are you trying to protect yourself from a nation
State each of these once you determine what you're trying to protect yourself again
Then there's a set of mitigating controls
Did you can implement
Good rest
One of the interesting things that we tried to tell everybody because they get hung up in this hole
Conversation around you know
Do I bake a
Bull the world world or do I just
Take a drink
Percent what we found 3835
Of the attacks or or issues that we find or we called involved in
Originate within the four walls of the plant
Know what does that mean that means
It's either an innocent employee doing something of vendor coming in doing something which by the way
In these plants vendors are in there every day and then he's Control Systems they need access to
Control system did you updates to do
Repairs things like that or disgruntled employee so there's a set of controls
And procedures in in governance around
Protecting yourself at that level
Some parts of the world and then our customers that we deal with are really targeted by Nation
The states so therefore we have to do
Significantly more
Protective type of litigation strategy for those
So it's not a one-size-fit-all
Speaking of Nations
There's a lot of attention right now.
Hacks
Nation states and different types of attacks may be using tools from
DSA perhaps so things like wannacry notpetya
All of that feels
Like everyone's more aware of
So how does that change the environment you guys operate
I think the positive from our side is
You know we've been
We've been seeing this as you mentioned for years
But now that's brought it to a
Different level of awareness
Now we're seeing that the
Plants in the people that are involved in this
Are now looking and saying hey wait a second
This is happening in the industrial space this could happen to me
What are we doing
We get called in Austin
How the cause of an executive is asked
The plant
What are we doing are we protected against the wannacry
In the plant goes
I'm not sure but that's the wrong answer
The right so the awareness level has increased dramatically I would say
In the last six
The 12 months
I am by that they're coming to
Companies like Honeywell going very been doing this for a while
And saying hey where do we start
I think that's the biggest
Challenge for most of the people we talked to
I want cyber
Security
To your point earlier do I want the $5,000 Scott cybersecurity other $5000000
Which do I need a don't know where to start
In companies like Honeywell we can come in and say okay let's talk about this look at your risk mitigation watch
I didn't come up with a solution that's that helps him get started
But the bottom line
Is the awareness is a
Increased significantly
And that has helped everybody
To actually put in the action
Could start getting their system secure
This is kind of an interesting
Idea but let's say you've got
An oil refinery and maybe it's it's
Crucial oil refinery
Of supplying
I don't know part of the United States
And they pick a risk mitigation plan that feels maybe like
Not enough
So what is your role as someone who consults with these guys
In that case and then
Where should the funding
Our role is that of
Alyssa is a
Trusted advisor
I mean we're going to tell them
What we think
Is there right mitigation strategy
And it will be based on the standards
On these
Market levels that we seen with other customers so kind of gives them a point of reference
We see the funding coming from
A couple different sources sometimes corporate funds it
Sometimes the actual plants are left to find it
Because at the end
If the direct correlation
Who is two products
Self is more of a
Protection cost on on production
State funded on objects at times other times depending on what it is you're doing
They may have to come out of capex or some multiple sources
On the funding
If I was your question
Yeah I know that part of me wonders
If you have a process that baby doesn't feel essential but
To be polluting or something if it were
Or preached and then have a severe detrimental effect
And nuclear power is kind of something everyone's worried about right but it could even be you know
Paper mill
Killing a river I don't know
It may not become a financial priority for
Plant operators
End
That feels like
A question we should all be thinking about as we
Things online
Absolutely in you and you see around the globe many countries now
Are passing regulatory
Tissues that
If you have a Cyber attack in a critical in
The structure
Impact
The economy or whatever then
The plants are being liable
I'll see you at we're seeing a growing increase
Round the global of regulatory
Compliancy type of a requirement Chalisa
And I think you're going to see that increase increase to your point
That makes it
Skin in the game show
Where do you see these regulations happening
Fastest or where do you look at
Could you like hey these guys are actually building a really good model for reggae
This sort of thing
By far the deleters are some of the countries in the Middle East again they're in a different
Meaning of environment
Did that maybe
Some of the other parts of the world
I know of France
In Europe there also
I'll coming on board pretty rapidly
I'm in the u.s. is doing some things nurx Elf on the power side
Canada on S pasta are pushing some of their
About Alberta
Compliance nurx F-Type
So it's it's running the glow but but if you had to say you know who was the
The ones that
I would have to
To say the middle of Base
All right
And words of wisdom
4 people in the it side we're looking at the
Plant as a source of Revenue
Wow we should just get in there
These guys are so old school and we could make this awesome for them
What would you say to her
Look before you leap again I as I mentioned earlier in the end of discussion
The Technologies of the same
The applications are
Significantly different
And the consequences are significantly differ
Part of what we bring to the party is is we
Bring both git knowledge
And what we call the process knowledge
And the two combined is what you need to actually
Work in this thing called the OT environment
All right
Mike thank you so much for coming on the show.
Haha you're welcome
That's it for this week's show
Thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy nose
At Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Will see you next week