Hey everyone is the Internet of Things podcast
And this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your other host
Kevin tofel
And this week we have some awesome stuff for you beginning with
Anti-poaching effort
In South Africa
Not eggs
Rhinoceros
Living with our friend
The algorithm
And how
Is it worth it
We'll also talk about
Best Buy in The Geek Squad and our guest this week
Is David Newman who is the guy who helped
Target build its new retail concept for The Internet of Things
There's definitely a French theme running through this
This week's podcast
Spot It
So
Kevin
Let's get started with
Poached rhinos
Is this is interesting that you pointed this out to me I had not heard of this story but this is a way to use the Internet of Things
To basically connect rhinos to protect them from poachers
And you are a story about this so how are they doing this
This is an effort by an organization called
Protect and they are funded by The Humane Society
The international
Humane Society
It's actually kind of crazy
Take
Rhinoceros
Rhinos
Rhinos thank you
And
Surgically implant a video
In their secondary horn
So
Do a little rhinoplasty
They also
Add a heart rate monitor
The Rhinoceros
Rhino
Dry nose
And
They had a GPS
And what they do is they track the rhino
And when the heart rate monitor spikes
Check to see through the video camera
What has happened to cause that Spike
And if it is
Is an injury or some kind of problem
Share the GPS location
With the Rangers that protect the rhinos
And they send a helicopter
And helicopter come speeding in
Apparently hopefully catches a posher
In
Action and hopefully before it actually
Kills the rhinos
That's the key the timing is the key here
It is because what happens is
Your
If you're a ranger in Africa you're trying to protect
Thousands of miles or
Thousands of kilometers
As they would say
Of Savannah
You really can't do that very effectively
It's too difficult because it's too broad of an area there's a limited connectivity and so on so
It's kind of interesting to me that they're essentially instrumenting the rhinos
Scare
For you know Health monitoring reasons end of the video camera
I mean I don't want to sound morbid at all but you don't
Thinking Out Loud here
You'll be able to tell
By the video if perhaps something
Scared the Rhino and it's okay or something like that that made the hearts way
Obviously it's like they see the
Camera view
Sideways or something obvious to the Rhinos down
Yan in the show notes will include this but they also
You also get
Rhinocam
Which is a
Rhino horns I view of the world
Which I think would be kind of a fun
Perspective as they fight or
Run around
Doing Rhino things
They're kind of solitary animals so I'm not sure if
Good footage
They have is
Hey here
Grassland scrub
Oh
Awesome
It's still kind of interesting and
Because the admission early there's
No connectivity challenges in these areas
Corrector using satellites
For the connection
They're actually a lot of technical challenges here outside of the
The challenges
Hunting down a rhino putting it to sleep in
Surgically implanting a camera in it
It snows I think this is a really interesting project
It is daunting
I still think
Hey it's worthwhile that they've gotten the proof-of-concept out
The Prototype
There's like one prototype running around there to have a couple more and the idea is
To actually expand this program to elephants and tigers they're starting to develop those proof of Concepts this year
And within a couple months
This will be
Kind of
The prototypes will be on the ground in South Africa
On the rhinos
And
Yeah it seems like a really cool project so
If you're interested I'll
Information
I'm watching the video feed
That you have in your story in
The camera quality outstanding except there's this giant horn in the way that lock
Yes yes you do just so you guys know if you want to go check this out you're not
How can I get the complete picture
You know if you saw the
Jornada
R2 that would
Kind of time defeats the purpose
That sounds like a good startup opportunity for somebody Cash Out million
Sorry
You are terrible
So moving for a rhino horn
Prince and the plains of South Africa
Sorry go ahead
Could you outrun a rhino these are questions that
Maybe we should
Ponder
As we watch that video
I'm going to have to see him run
Cuz he's going back and forth night looking at plants and eating so
Is this interesting
I watch a lot of Discovery Channel and National Geographic and so on and
I really get into this kind of thing so yeah I mean I'm mesmerised
Did you not
Alright so Kevin is going to be one of the first
Backers of the rhino
Sodexo
Moving on from
Fran okay I'm going to move into actually
Smart Home Care
Earlier this year I tested the netatmo
Is that the doorbell camera or
No this is
Is a Pringles can
I made it look like it look like a smaller print
And it looks more like a
It look more like a hairspray can remove scan
It's a little skinnier
For those of you who use product
In your hair
Does if you could do not it's just skinnier than a Pringles can and shorter
And it is beautiful it is champagne colored aluminum
And
It purports to have facial recognition and it learns via algorithm who the people in your family are
And it starts alerting you
And get your notifications instead of saying I detect
Movement it says things like
In my house it would be Stacy just into the house
Which is a little bit more useful and you don't even have to click through to the app
To be like oh who just enter
I told you
So I've been to
Testing that
And then
I've also tested things like the canary which is an all-in-one security device and then there's the classic
The Nest so I thought it'd be kind of fun Kevin for you and I to talk about like
Life with an algorithm
Because a lot more Smart Home Products are touting this idea of
An algorithm is being
Epic selling
Like I think we're still trying to figure we Izzy and industries are trying to figure out how to make these things
Work in a smart way when we say smart home
To me that's not just these individual devices if the algorithms that tie Services Android devices
Together
And didn't take it off and doesn't work the way you think it might work the way you want it to and I suspect that's what you've been finding out
In testing all these things but I'm taking a wild stab here
It's a little like that so
The key point I think the
Anytime you see the word algorithm
With these products is
That you have to remember is you have to train them
And that's kind of what I'm getting at
Because a lot of these
Annie's products
Take the nest requires about a week-long train
And that's fine
And that week-long training. With
The Nest Is You by The Nest you install it in for a week you treat it like any other thermos
You know when you're high
You go walk to the nest or you
Use your phone
When you're like
Hey I'm hot
After about a week of that the nest
Dislike
You know what
I think I got your schedule and then it starts
Working on its own
If it's based on your behavior
Learn from your behaviors and starts
Reacting to or acting upon
Your behavior without you manually giving input
Yes
So
With the facial recognition because the canary has a
And
What is trying to do is its trying to identify things
Things like
Oh hey that's a dog so when your dog comes in sets off the motion sensor I'm not going to call in a lot
Right
Which
That's awesome right
Oh that's great because in the old days which was not long ago
If you had motion detection sensors
We did we had an alarm system
And the cats
Would actually be able to set it off we weren't home
So then we had to buy special motion sensors that were programmed to ignore
Sings
Moving around under roughly 40 lb
So
If that's not ideal if you can have actual recognition that's the way to go
Right
Things like that so
In the welcome camera ideas it recognizes
Is people's faces who live in the house so it can give you better
Data
Slack better notifications
How can I deal with notify
Vacation fatigue
Great
So
The challenge with both of those system
Was that
The training. Didn't actually
Stop
After a week
It never ends
And so what would it what would happen is
At first you know
So we'll start with a welcome
Everyone in my house had to go in front of the camera in
Antenna
Faking it was like
Here we are
Like 3 or 4 days
Every time it was show you
A list of faces basically in
It would be you would just be like this is dispersed
This is
Righteverywhere
Every face
It wasn't
They made it nice
It after while. Really good
But it's still with throw up faces for you like every morning when I open the app it would be like
Here like 15 faces would like
For you to identify
Or
Sure
14 faces
Can you confirm that the following six are Stacy
And you would hit them
What I was actually really impressed with was some of them
I couldn't even identify a state
These are pictures of
Purportedly of me
And I be like
And the pressure is on actually to get it right
Because
If you get it
If you were like
I don't know
You're kind of like I miss him with an algorithm
And decreasing the probability that it
Be able to identify me
Right sure you don't want to be the one that weaken the algorithms intelligence
Just might be
So
I felt like
After a certain point in time I wanted it to stop at
Like after a month I was I was really done with
Interactive
Yeah it's it's a shame that it
Doesn't really ever end
Yeah I bet you don't maybe if they showed it to me like
Hey do you have time to go through
Some faces
And they made it like a fun game or something
You know there's value in going through every especially like I have a small child too
You know her face changes
Overtime
So there's value in that
And you know when new people come in
It's like hey I just saw a totally new person
We care about that person
Every morning I would wake up
Here's 15 new faces of your husband
I know that's
Again they got to put
Some limits on that to decrease the number of times over the
How often does that because
It just it just loses value
Kind of interesting because
Mei I have no problem with the facial-recognition approach I know a lot of people will and then that's fine that you know
Privacy issues etc etc I'm not going to go there
But there's one device that I've had for the past
I'll say three years
That is
Does an outstanding job at recognizing everybody in my family as well as some of the neighbors
I don't think you'll ever guess
I will not ever
Your talk
Well yes that are there is that
Bedtime
He's going to be around forever and for tonight
The Microsoft Xbox Kinect is fan
Tastic
And identification
Fantastic
So I don't know if it's any use multiple sensors it's not just a camera that use infrared
But you some type of RGB camera
They have multiple sensors in that connect
And they do a fantastic job with it
I don't think
It's ever actually do because
When you set it up
You know it takes your picture and so on
You said your accounts and etc etc
And then
Anytime you walk
If you have it set up this way every time you walk in front of the Xbox it literally will just automatically sign you in if you have a configure to do so
I'm almost wish they would license it out because
Think these products would benefit greatly from that
Who that would be
If your buddy at the echo somewhere behind you I won't say
Shi shoes
She who shall not be named
We call her in our house
Doubt that could be really compelling
Are there kind of creepy
So moving right along
Living with algorithms
And maybe something
Might be better about training
Since we're going to see a lot more of them and they should get better
Because that is the only way we're going to handle the information overflow that we're going to
Reconnect
Get the information day loser
Is
There is there is more help on the way other than better AI
Best Buy wants to help
Speaking at brainstorm Tech the CEO of Best Buy
To bear
Judicially
Got on stage and I can't believe I forgot to talk about this last week
He said that his retailer as a retailer Best Buy is
This is super poised to help
With the Internet of Things
Because not only will they sell connected devices
They also
Well
How people install and troubleshoot
The stuff that you know Kevin you and I do like
Hours at a time on weekends
What do you think about that
Well
Say hello and I say this I don't want to categorize every single Geek Squad member as being fantastic or terrible
As long as
You barely can guarantee a certain minimum level of performance I think it's a great idea
Because most people either a don't have the time that you and I have to devote
To this kind of thing
How to troubleshoot everything
Time
And Emily just before the show we were kind of laughing out loud saying
Anytime there's any small problem with any of our systems are other devices
What are apps
If he comes this
Debacle of things that
Take hours to resolve
And people don't want to invest that kind of time that the whole point of all these connected devices
Is that you're pretty smart things in your house and around you
So you get some of your time back and you get some value
So I'm
Fine with
Best Buy being the Apple Genius bar for my smart home provided
You know it's
It's not me spending two hours trouble shooting
I'd rather do than have them spend
2 hours or 3 hours and not be able to figure it out
Right cuz
You & I we generally figure this stuff out
We do although I will say
When I think it's a gene
What I think of the Geeks
Squad
Sorry
Oh I did it again
What I have on the brain
Sorry God
Going to try it takes. T Squad Squad
Tutu issues
What is
Guys have fun
Corn on your
Computer I really do
So you bring it in and they like rifle Terraria
Your folders on your heart
For like
Improvising stuff
There's been some horror stories about that yes
Poking around your house near
My house that I know of
I was going to say Stacy specifically not saying
They don't want to hurt you if you wanted to find a point in her house she did something happen to find anything and
So
The other thing is
You don't the hard thing about the Internet of Things
Is that your combining both it in like
Physical
Infrastructure
It's it's like people call it it and OT
God help me if I ever use
It is true you have to have
Physical like
There's Electric
Afraid so I got stymied by intellect
But this weekend
Not and then I got signed by a network
Arkansas
So you got to have those two things
And you know I was tok
Usually about
Like are you going to bring in like electricians because I would be really interesting service for BestBuy to offer if I could just call them up and get like
An installation Network
Work is well
And that doesn't seem to be in the plans because there's licensing things that differ by each state
That's the tougher things
To sell
Although I think that would be amazing
Stop ride Amazon with it
Amazon Home Services is actual
I coming in real strong there
But so I feel like that would be like a much more compelling thing
That's those are two things that Best Buy really with its Geek Squad would have to address
Before I'm like
Yeah
This is a really compelling offering
Come on over
Geek Squad
Yeah I mean
Computers phones those are all very personal devices but there's nothing more personal to probably anybody then
What's going on in their home their home itself and so on
Cancel
There is the trust issue that they have to work on and I think it's
We can take some time I I suspect
He saying what he should be saying you know in Defence of his company hey we have something nobody else offers
That's true
But a lot of people will not
Be swayed by that
I don't I don't think
Yeah I mean cuz like if you think about it Comcast AT&T
Verizon I mean those guys all have an installer Network and a smartphone Prada
Actually Verizon
I don't think has a small
AT&T and Comcast have
ATT has one
Alarm.com Vivint all of those guys
Do and they have
The same sort of expertise
Yeah I mean I get what he's driving at and I agree with you if they offer
You no more
Technical electrical type install services that would probably
Be element
Make it more compelling
But
The reality is these products are being designed so that
Hopefully
Somebody can just go to a Best Buy or whatever store they buy their gear out or get it from Amazon
And literally be up and running
On their own
It in a short
Matter of time
So
You know it's it kind of defeats the purpose of these devices
It to some degree if it's going to require a Geek Squad or
AT&T tech or an electrician
The promise of the Smart Hub you know it's brings all the Simplicity and everything else but if you have to pull your hair out trying to get it installed
And you don't be on the phone with support for an hour or two
It's frustrating it's like
The promise has not been met here
Course without it we wouldn't have a show so
On that note
Good point
We should end the show but before we do
Kevin and I are taking a much-needed break because it will be
August
In August is a great month
To take a break
Cuz that would just be
Puppy lazy
I'm not lazy
Asellina
No
So
We're going to take the next week off you're not go
Can I hear from us
So really make this make this guest count
Stay tuned for David Newman who is
In charge of Target open house
Bedo iot retail concept
Xfinity
Store is pioneering
And I believe if you are Kevin you pronounce it
What the Metreon
El tarde
Tire chains keeping with the French theme French Steam
So
Stay tuned for David and thank you so much for this
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is Stacey Higginbotham and your guest today is David noon
David is the director of Enterprise growth initiatives at
Target
Maybe you guys have heard of
I don't know
Thanks for coming on the show today
Thank you Stacey pleasure to be here
I am super excited
Because a couple weeks ago we talked about this Kevin and I on the show
About Target
Open house
This is a brand new retail concept for Target
So David do you want to tell us a little bit about open house
Yeah absolutely open house is the culmination of
Work we've been doing in the Internet of Things stays for
18 months
An ultimately with open house
We set out to create a very
Fun educational
Experiential retail space
Where consumers can come in and experience
The Internet of Things in the connected home in a very easy to understand way
Okay you got about fifty products
Dinner in the space end
I have yet to visit because I am not in San Francisco but let me tell you I have gotten text form about
A dozen people who've
So far showed up so you guys
It's only been like two weeks
When we're recording this
But this is been open but already a dozen people have sent me
Text an email saying hey I've been in this this amazing experience happened to me
You have
Clear furniture that is showing the stuff off to Lake
Crazy degrees you got Interactive
Tables you got
A lot of documentation that shows these things working together
So tell me a little bit about
If I go in there
What am I going to say
Cnexps
Sure will you mention the furniture
And the first thing you're going to see walking into open
Open house is
Very literally
In open house so we have a cross section
The house
Location appropriate house it's a
Victorian home
And we have all the various rooms
Tibet House
And it's made out of
Clear acrylic and the purpose of that actually came out of a number of
Design experiments that
Weed in San Francisco
I all around this idea of showcasing
Vinyasa
Products work
Getting together so
Our first
Our first-ever we call these iot playground
That's when we did that
And for any of your listeners who saw these around San Francisco we didn't brand them as targets
I'm the first one we set up a living room with actual furniture and connect
Good products and show various vignettes
So someone coming home and lights
Turning on
Music coming on different interactions all possible today with the various
Out there
It was interesting and I was as you can imagine
You walk into a space with locks
Living room furniture and some very
Smart connected products
And
It looks like you're in a living room
You notice the couch
Table you noticed
And so we realize that once we explain to people what we were doing they were interested in the technology
But it was too
Scared when
1 1st Ave
Encountered
So the next experiment we ran we actually took
A difference
Set of vignettes all around the babies
And went to a different location in San Fran
Cisco and for another 3 days we set up our next iot playground
Did the team win
And we
Set up baby furniture and this time we made me
We spray painted everything White
And in the baby's room we had
Activate monitor we had
Sonos speaker
And once again we found that while we work to obscure the fern
We still had big furniture
Even though it's all painted white it just look like a room full of white furniture
Iran
Small products
So all of this design experimentation let us
To the recognition that if we really wanted to show these products working together in sit you in these various room
Rooms of a home
That we really needed to
Make that furniture both literally and figuratively transparent
Like make the product
The Stars
And show the data interactions
And the very real daily life
Problems that we all want help solving
Unfolding before our eyes and
And how these products
You're helping so
To your question of what do you see when you walk in you first see this house and
And you go from the living room into
To the bedroom into a baby's room a kitchen
And a garage and a backyard area each that has the appropriate connected products or literally show
Showing entire home
Experience from the front door to the back door and
The backyard and everything in between
So both with the house and with the Deep dive tables
A big part of the
The design is all around the stories of how these products connect and work
Work together
And then lastly there is a tree
Traditional shelf that has
It's along the backbone
The sidewalk
That has products out of their boxes UK
Pick him up you can
Interact with them via the device that is paired to eat
Each one and so that's more
Opportunity to engage with
The product as is
As an individual product
They're the least number of products on that shelf as compared to the Deep dive
Got it
And
Is consumers you can actually purchase products
Guess
Every product we show is for sale
So
You guys have now been open
As of this conversation about a couple weeks
So
What have you seen so far
Because
This is an entirely new way
And I have to applaud you for selling this way because
It is by far the most comprehensive plan I think I've seen for selling the Internet of Things
I've had a lot of retailers on the show in
And visited just about every store that sells connected gadgets
Kind of understand
How this is being sold
Because it's
Is very complicated you're trying to show
Most people are just popping single-use devices on a shelf or a hub on a Shelf
So it's hard to understand
What products work
With what other
So I really like what you're doing
There are no plans though now to
Anywhere between
Right
You're right now this is a one-of-a-kind space and it's
Purpose of experimentation
So we put it there
Because all of the question
Is that
One of your listeners might ask
Or a Sceptre
Think about the overall connected-home and iot
T-space my ass
We think there's validity of every one of those question
We're focused on trying to get to the
Rather this is a place where we think we bring all of the right parties together in a salon like way
And just have dialogue that we never felt we could effectively had around the conference
Around my table
We can state that we're serious week
Can state that we intend to do certain things
But when you're standing inside that space and you and you
You see the care and
Design that went into what
We felt
It just makes for a very different conversation with the makers
In the platform players
Consumers I think they see it and it's a different way of
I've just understanding and for many who come in the space
It's the first time
But they're saying that they may not have the friends who have
Put Nest up on their wall or have a Sonos speaker in their house
So it's a it's
It's an opportunity to really just have a gift
Start a conversation in and gather a different set of observations
We thought we could do without it
So what are you seeing what are what are those conversations link
Are people buying
Your people are buying me I think first and foremost
Consumer response and they're sponsoring the target gas that have come through has been really
People really get it people find it very very educational and we find that both from those who know this
Space is lost those who down at the very least those who know the space
I probably seeing a few products is only read about or maybe haven't even
Inseam before
A people definitely appreciate seeing how they work
Together and those little story
One of my favorite is just
The role of a connector
Speaker in a baby
When the baby wakes up
If you have that connected baby monitor
Then if you want Beethoven playing at plays
Baby wakes up in the middle of the night
You have this option to either notify you immediately or to play some white noise
4 Hour lullaby
A minute or two to see if baby goes back to sleep
And when people see that I think they the
Promise of the
These products comes
Life
So there's been a lot of excitement
Hearing some vendors and other companies in the iot
T space is pretty
Consistently
This is what we need
We needed the space like this where week
Cast and weak
Can observe and we can do that
On a consistent basis and do it in in close proximity to all these other great Prada
So it's the dedication of the space has really resonated with the vendors and
I think it would be also really interesting from a troubleshooting perspective
Like for example
My house is
Probably not as
Pretty my friend is none of my furniture is
Is clear
I can't see my devices
Just setting up devices together and trying to get them to work together
Is educational
Not just for me but for some of the vendors where I'm like
You see this works together but when I put them together
Did they actually don't work
Updater app
So have you had any
Examples where I don't know maybe
Maybe things didn't quite work out as planned and you helped kind of broker
Apache or maybe
To manufacturers like hey wait a second
Just by virtue of being in the same room with these guys we suddenly seeing it would be a great idea that we
We if we
Built-in
Integration together
It's a great question in fact we probably
Had the most
Experience
In This Very topic
As we were designing the
Space where
There were stories we wanted to tell but
Products didn't necessarily there made one of the products maybe didn't yet have an open
API
Or you had a more restrictive API where access needed
Be granted to a
Platformer differ
Product
So it was really interesting exciting just to have those early conversations with these companies and some of them
Has opened
Things up
Haven't had an open up app that API access
Prior
Or they've agreed to open it up so long as we have
The space up so they may be saying hey world will keep this open and as long as Target is doing this and
And committed to it will continue to serve
Supportive
Aspen grade
We've yet to run into any problems
Games with any of the
The products that we have connect
And part of that is acceleration that went into
Because we did The Upfront work to make sure everything works
We also did the diligence to ensure that
Yeah we were going to know if apis ever changed or
Any of those
Particulars that can
Can keep things from working
Together
It's also get that why we don't have every we're not trying to have every product available in the space
Is part of what goes into a select
Sing a product for the space
Is making sure that
It has that openness
And that reliability
Before we put it in the
Nice
So I have to ask because there's a huge component here
I'm bringing startups and interesting ideas to Target
Which
Is awesome
So if I am an iot startup or smart home startup
Who do I contact if I call you
To get into the space because
This isn't just
Hi
I want to I want to put a device here you're also talking about
Letting
Companies come in and
You know create focus groups to talk to
And I'm not sure how great it would be to talk to the San Francisco focus groups I think talking maybe to the people in Boise might be better
But you know
Still getting in front of you so she would be good
So how how did
What kind of programs do you envision for startups
Then how can I get involved
Well first off in terms of talking to that
Consumer from Boise the nice thing about the location being directly across from the Moscone Center
Is that we do get a lot of traffic from the conventions
There there which is really interesting because
You're on any given day
Last week the semicon
Conference
Which is all about for the semiconductor industry
And so understandably a lot of interest in the space
Many of the makers of these chips that are in the products were coming
Through
And so everyone was from
Someplace different
And so that's that's an exciting
Part about the location and why we sleep
Which shows that this is the singular location for this one
Find face
In terms of
Companies wanting to
Come into the space the first thing is
We have to get familiar with what we're doing
Before we even start talking
The best thing to do is you only have a website that can give you a high level overview that's open house. Target.com
And then by all means if you're in the area
Come on Inn
Explore the space
And then in terms of actually putting a product
In others there's a couple ways we recommend on that website open house. Target.com we have our email
Address we also have instructions of how to contact us BR Twitter handle
And give us awareness of your product and that will that will set off a
A series of follow-up conversation
And what's really exciting is
You're giving that weed this is not our
This is not a date
Restore roll out of this experience
The conversations are not of that nature of how do you get a peg or how do you get a
A space on the Shelf but rather
How do you fit into this eco
What are those what are those everyday life
Scenarios
You're helping.
Solve and make better
And how would you fit in in this house
Put you in the house what room would you be
What other products if any would you be interacting
And same with the tables we can point out how
Product on the on the interact
Cable it doesn't connect to any
Is actually less interesting from that Interactive
Experience Ben are other products bad
Have a whole lot of
And frankly we found this.
Unexpected on their side so if they're used to wanting your getting questions about
Their supply chain efficiency or their packaging or what not
And we really want to know is you and what what
What's the story what story are we telling here because
This is all part of
A bigger
Endeavor on our behalf to understand
What role do we target play in this overall ecosystem how do we bring broader value to it
And how does the consumer Bennett
Cuz I want all those pieces come together that's when that's when an industry is really that's when it really starts
Takeoff
I like that I like that kind of mentality
Although Supply chains will eventually come in handy that's not your focus here
I think it's worth pointing
Out
Because
You're not the steppingstone necessarily to all 1800 Target
Acrostic
No but we certainly we are part of Target and we can help with
Are Merchants I was just just recently with our electronics and home
Merchandising leadership and brainstorming on all of the different things they want
What to do on the space
Whether it's a product launch where if it's
Thanks
Target do we Leverage
Space to launch it
It's certainly a lot around prospecting new and exciting products
And also around
Sometimes
It's the right product the way we operate very big box
And so the right product in the wrong space
Can be another challenge end
You take a product like tile everyone under
Stand for you
Yorkies
But where do you where do Yorkies come into play in your shopping app
Experience in our box is it as you're looking at a bike and you're thinking about a bike lock and you're losing your key
Your bike lock keys while you're on a bike ride is that a great place
Sonos
Has application in the baby's room and in the living room and
In electronics and
That's a you know that is a new challenge from multi-category retailer to
Kcon
So that some of those it those are the conversations we want to be having and that's where I can
Take the bridge between what we're doing it open
In house and what goes on Bradley at Target I think that's
That's one of those big connection
That's true
Although
I'm not sure the
The merchants are not the merchant
DIA
Manufacturers
The product companies field
No we want the stores
I should say because Kevin and I talked about this a couple of weeks ago when this lunch
And
You guys took issue with how he described it which I totally understand so Kevin and I said that this was in
The basement
Of the city Target across from a scone
And you were quick to point out that this is not actually a basement which sperm any probably conjures up get of darkened
Dingy places that
We're scared of
This is actually at the ground floor level
We I was just thinking it
Underneath the the main target which starts at the second floor
Ourself
This is street level
Florida City Target
Not the basement
So that that was one
One big
You know things that we should clarify for
People it's at 4th and Mission so
If you were there
And I'm hoping to be there at the
End of August so
You know I will let you guys know so I can pop in and
Play around but
I think David
I
I have really enjoyed talking
Into you I cannot wait to go
Play
And see
I'm going to ask you
Has it have you changed anything do you have any connected Gadgets in your house or you know
Found a use case that you hadn't thought of in in putting this together
You use casewise those aha moments
We keep having them in
The happening at unusual moment
So
Things like
The role of Sonos in a babies
The important
Where in your house might you be most in
Interested in having the
Screen that shows
And the ring what's happening on your ring doorbell
Or what are you picking up on your Dropcam
I think when you see it in in the house you get to actually imagine
Products
Different location
We were doing as we were designing these early playgrounds we were talking
Consumers in their home
In their homes and
When you should one of them
Tile product which they haven't seen before
They were in process
Storing a bunch of boxes in their garage
And ask the question will can I put a tile in
Chinese box
And then link that tile to the right
Piece of my spreadsheet
To tell me so I can quickly find anything that I put away and so a year from now I'll remember end
That was another one of those aha moments it also gets into interesting question
Around that use case and the
Expected battery life
Thailand so
There are all sorts of these moments
It's undeniable that this
This is coming you'll be very hard-pressed to find a baby monitor in the next few years it is
Connected
Lost Art probably owning a piece of apparel that might have
Ships
Sensors in it
I'm wrong thermostats are probably going to Aldi connected
Shemar Moore store
These products will be
Connected and that means that we we need good answers to how do you showcase
Please because if you put them all together into a single connected
Kidspace what do you do when everything is finally connected and you have to start taking it
Apart again
Tell for me I'm following the curves of what the market research
Search is telling us that the growth rate for these products in the in a home is
Upwards of 30
2% so I went from one couple years ago to 2 to 6
Send
When you're growing fast so I
I continue to enjoy experimenting and
We look forward to having you in our space
Awesome I can't wait will David thank you so much for coming on the show and chatting with me
And iiii will course
Visit and report back to all of the listeners
Well that was a great show thank you guys for listening I hope you guys remember that next week we will not be having
Hangzhou show
So
Feel free to skip the download
But make sure you come back the following week
When we will have more goodies for you and as always thanks for listening