Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy
M&J co-host
Kevin tofel
And we are on
Episode
Vio
Today we're going to be talking about final thoughts from CES
A little bit about iot device
Surety
Actually a lot about iot.
Kevin's local supermarket is implementing
Robots
Excited about that we're to be talking about skills form anime
Little bit of privacy information
And a lighting
Position
Plus we are going to hear from fair come about its iot Edge database
And
Hear from
Ghetto giraffe who is the chief
Chief digital officer of ABB
The 34 billion dollar a year and Rev
The new company that
You may not have heard of but we're going to be talking about what he
He calls Maslow's
Hierarchy of
Coyote
It is an
Awesome in
I was really impressed
I think you'll enjoy it
And now
It's time for
A message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
Are you looking for an iot platform
Figure out why Kenmore and dealing
Pharaoh
Avero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction
In time to Market
99% pure support calls
And a 10x higher activation
Plus they can we use 90% of their work from one project to the neck
To learn more visit a pharaoh
. IO
That's a f
Ero.
IO
Okay
Let's get this started with
CES we're going to mop up the last bits of
CES trends that we saw in
Tested
Play with it
Lord only knows what else so
Kevin you came back
With CES play so we're just going to apologize right now for any
Any weirdness in Kevin's Voice or demeanor
Yeah
Kevin is on Sudafed for like the fifth day in a row so
We'll see how this goes
So something
Cuz I wanted to
I wanted a mop up some Gadget
It's cuz I covered them in various
Articles
Possibly in the CES
Episode
But there are a couple things that I thought were
One is Schlage
Does sponsor or voicemail
They introduced a Wi-Fi
And
You know I think that's a big deal it's part of a
Bigger trend
Towards adding Wi-Fi to as many things as possible
That we saw at CES basically people don't want to have a
So they're like
Hey can we do this with Wi-Fi or
Which makes
Bluetooth matches getting better so we're seeing
More low-powered sensors and such
Bluetooth
The endless leads to something we've been talking about recently and that prior shows
Zigbee and Z-Wave
I mean
They're just slowly fading away from at least on the consumer side
It seems it like you said people don't want to hug you don't even know what the benefit is
Which mainly is Automation and there are
Non-hub automation methods so
I don't know
Pino's Disick B&C way folks say just
I think it'll be part of the pursuit
I mean Amazon did put zigbee in the air
Plus
And I don't think it'll take that out
But yeah I don't think
I think if you're just
Casually trying to
Connect sump light switches to your
Amazon Echo or
No door locks are video cameras you're going to try for all wife
World
Write in a treehouse of my take on that on the CBS fam
It was like not even part of the conversation I'm curious since we split up most days did you hear Company stock
Only the zootopia lion
Switch text back..
Which is
There
Ziggy Ansah
Thread combination
Thanks so this is a
Deeply nerdy Wireless protocol for folks red was actually created by Nest way back in
The day and
With a bunch of other
And it is
Basically it uses the CB radio
Also 802
15.4
I hope tomorrow is like
So it's the same underlying radio
But it has software on top that lets it do things like
Go directly to the internet
IPv6 enabled
Smash therapy
Low power
So the idea is your zigbee stuff could actually be
Updated
Possibly.
Banana chips
Set to
Work with
With thread
And vice versa
Doesn't interrupt ability after they're also trying to bring it over Wi-Fi
Which again
So
Will see that would be
Thread over wife
Not
It feels
It feels like that ship may have sailed but
They said they'll be
Products and 22
23rd work
With DOT.
You know I look for products in the other standards news there's
Open connect
Ulta beauty Foundation
And they have their iotivity standard
This was
It was Intel's effort
They kind of subsumed all these Qualcomm alljoyn engineers
And basically I thought we'd hear from them at sea
But we didn't so I didn't know what to say to you guys
Is on the standard side
I'm feeling a big
Yeah
You know
Boc F gas
Say that their products out there there's nothing that's not a Gateway really
You know maybe in 2019 we're going to see stuff but I really am not going to hold my
My breath on this y'all so
Your standards are
Pretty much going to be Madame a witch
We call Amazon's ecosystem
Or Google
And
And homekit in Wi-Fi and blue
So those are kind of diff
Layers
For most people
Those are kind of going to
Work with
So
That's
Is that the bad news that's just how the smart
And that is where we are
So back to his wife I like
Loxo Schlage introduces Wi-Fi lock
Wi-Fi is a huge power suck
So
That's why we hadn't seen a lot of Wi-Fi locks up until this moment
Company called Hampton
Arabian
Break Stuff they had a Wi-Fi locked
They have solar power in it
Help offset the battery drain
If you get the Schlage Wifi lock
Depending on temperature depending on
Number two
Packers like how often you
Open your door and use this
You're probably looking at maybe a 2-month lifespan
Inn on the batteries
Yeah that's a lot of batteries but it is
Is Wi-Fi
The Sleep books actually
They told me they thought it could last forever
At four months
I feel that's really
But maybe I'm just
I haven't tested it
The alarm test so
Want to see
So it's taking middle-ground and say it's 3 months
My Z-Wave lock
Usually 6
Easley the grant that I needed some I need a hub for that
So
Tentative get on the Wi-Fi network
Communicate with everything but
I don't know I don't know the people want to change their
Front door batteries every 3 months or 2 to 4 months or whatever it's going to be but we'll have to see him in the Proctors
In use for x amount of months
To be honest yes and it will vary
I mean weather drain your battery
If you got a hard lock to close and shut you know that my
Have some issues
You know any other thing I noticed
With my zigbee and Z-Wave
Blocks they actually if
If you didn't connect them to the hub their batteries drained a lot faster
Because they were constantly trying
Connect to something so
Emma switch the locks would kind of be reversed in that the bolt that goes from the door where the lock is into the
Frame of the door
It actually came through the frame into the door
Because then you can actually wire it
Oh that's a really in
Yeah I don't know if it says secure
I can't see why it would be
Alright we'll see if
Hey if you work in the lock industry and have thoughts on that give us a call I mean that would be a
Something you have to build in that would be kind of a pain to Retro retrofit project old door frame out
Although it's a yes I talked to the mowing guys and they're changing the way they do
Plumbing a new houses so
Because these like
They're talking about like having connectivity in
The shower so that means you got to have electricity in with your showers
So what they're doing
Instead of putting a
Electricity right by
Behind the shower wall
Pudding
They're basically
Putting it
In a junction box where all the
The pipes for the shower
And that's where they're trying to add the elec
Atrocity
And I thought that was kind of an interesting thing
Now if you're doing a bathroom
Which is probably when you put the stuff in
You could do that fairly easy
So it's kind of an interesting
I think about how the Smart Home
Like these connectivity Alamo
Interchange
Design of Art
Okay
Another thing that
I feel like we should talk about because it's
Pretty freaking awesome
Is Chamberlain
They did a deal with Amazon
So now you can use the Amazon key
Key Program Ashley it's not now.
It'll be later this year
The first half
This year what will happen is
If you sign up as a Prime member for the Amazon
Key Program
You can actually
Have the
Amazon delivery person open York
Garage door if you have a Chamberlain MyQ compatible garage door
And that is so much better in my opinion because
Nobody's actually Ortega
In your house as soon as your door from the house into the garage is locked in.
Yes
And I'm like super excited about this one because I live in
Texas where we have huge homes in
Lots of people in Costco so
A lot of people actually have her
Refrigerators or freezers in there
Garage
And so imagine being able to do grocery delivery into someone's garage as opposed to leaving it on
Porch if only amazon-owned
Although here I will tell you guys
That we get our groceries delivered on the rare occasion or sometimes
But they always take everything in a
Which is terrible if you have bananas
Cuz then they come out Brown
That is it so if you're going to
You're going to buy like four
The grocery store
You should not buy bananas
That is not a smartphone
Pro tip that is just a general
Privileged
That's a produce tip
A produce tip
Thank you
So I thought that program was really
Interesting there no fees for the consumer for
For that it does open up like you could deliver a lot more interesting things
Like you could order a larger TV
Computer I have no idea what I would order
But I like it
And I think it's probably something I would sign up for
Where is Amazon key I would not touch that with a
12 foot pole
I am right there with you even though I'm home most of the time I still don't
Amazon
Yes oh I should tell you that
Y'all
It is going to only go live in 37 C
Austin is one of them
I don't know about Harleys
I'm thinking not cuz we're not really a city classified as a village
Yeah
The village of Harleysville is what greets you on the side when you
Drive to miles
Strep throat
The other thing that I was excited about it CES was a lot of health and wearables
Some of it felt like digital snake
Best Buy
We'll have an algorithm then it will help you pick your
Best foods for your metabolism or we have an algorithm in it will help
Help you
I don't know
Use your brain better
So those
Agreed with a lot of
But
I will say that
I felt like we actually saw some really interesting devices that took
Like the last generation
Snuff devices
Where you're like oh I'm going to give you information about
But your steps
And took that into like
Dunkin give you actual actual
Information about your
Yeah there was quite a few of those some of the snake oil things I've actually having fun taking pictures of people trying them
People accept out in special massage chairs and wearing like a thing on their head that would massage their brain man was
Pine, Co
But there's definitely been some advancements useful advancements in this area
And I think podcast
Pryor when we're at CVS
Thinking about next gen tie products
Why things came out with their moves
ECG watch $429 which adds the same ucg type
Functionality that the Apple watch 4 has
Obviously too much lower price
And
You know I thought I thought price-point the addition of that to their existing line
Was rather smart on their part
Yes
And we also had some
Smart
Blind
News I mention this because every that is like one of the number one request once you get your license
I would like to make
My blind smarter
And there's been a bunch of Kickstarter efforts
Really have
There's also a
Company called mysmartblinds
It's about $150
For that
Retrofit
On your existing wooden slat blinds so it's kind of expensive
But I ran into
Access
In this company actually
She has like a little motorized thing that you attach
Hatched here existing
Chords
Has to be a continuous loop
Court that's the one thing
It's kind of a pain
But if you have that you attach this connected device
What the motor in it
He'll actually raise and lower your blinds for
It's $250
It's available now in Amazon
And
I thought that was
Pretty neat but
At the same time
Ikea
Announced smart
This is about
Time I went to Ikea like
Gosh last
I think it was last brainless summer
I don't remember
It was months ago I remember you telling me
So long
Hand
They showed me this
And they were
And they were going to be
So cheap
Kevin do you remember how much they cost
I think they start at $113 and go to Lake 180 or so depending on the width
So that's a little more than they
Lacoste at the time
But that's fine cuz still those are really real
And these are all
These are a whole set of shape
This is not a right
Right and the retrofit would not work for me because I
Considered it but I buy cellular
Shades with no cord
So there's no
When I can retrofit there's nothing to
Winder online if I had a motor there
I may go look at the I can try
For the shades
There you go
So yeah so smart blind World finally opening up
Woohoo
I mean I know this is a silly thing to get excited about but I guarantee you a lot of people are going to be excited
I don't think it's silly because most of the
Smart blinds to date
You're literally you're starting it for $300 a window
Yeah
Yeah it's very expensive
And if you want to go like
Crazy higher-end shades are you have a lot of fiber
Then you're looking at like
I'll tell you guys I have these like
10 x 14
Cheap windows
My shades basanti Shades I have Earth
$10,000 a window
I mean it is
TQ
Yeah and
I had to spend
An extra Lake
Six hundred bucks to get a retrofit
Play the special proprietary Radio 2
Z-Wave
Converter
That is not my favorite to buy some he did actually announced a
Cubs it does there
Proprietary
WiFi camera
So now that it's
And I'm assuming he's require the tradfri Hub
They do require
Expensive
No not that one
I got one of everything
Okay
Other cesa
You know anything else that stuck out at you or you were like
You know I hate to be maybe it's cuz of my medicine me I hate to be the downer but I can wait from CES
Just kind of
Attitude
Any other cool gadgets and you mentioned a bunch
Instagram
Talk about them in the last show but you know
I don't maybe my expectations are too high this smart home is still not smart I'm wondering in this is what I wanted to say
CTS where is the predictive
Learning and
Machine learning and AI
Big Data
We can
Using devices for years several years now and all this data is collected on how we use the
Protocol Smart Home
But we still basically have voice control and program yourself automation
Why doesn't the home say hey I notice you turn your lights on within 5
It's still very manual and I don't understand that
I don't either I mean I don't know about you but I signed up for the Amazon hunches which is the closest we're getting to that so far but
I haven't actually gotten
There are no
I have a hunch it's not that exciting
Well maybe but you know
Oh I should mention briefly
Digital assistants in cars was
Totally a thing
So
Send I thought of that
Because I still haven't been invited to try out the Amazon Echo
Car think so
And related to what I was talking about and digital assistants
Google did
Announce
Through its partner Hard Rock Orlando valet
4 inch touch screen smart clock
It's $79
It's like the other smart displays obviously smaller microphone no camera for his touch screen as I said speaker
And
It will actually this is kind of what I'm hoping to see for
It will suggest alarm times based on your morning and evening routines
And my hope is
Since Google knows the events on your calendar like if you got an early meeting or something and traffic is bad and already knows that
Can tell you that
Practically maybe we'll start using that data to suggest
Alarm times and such
Sure wake you up early
Yeah see that's now that's a smart home
Example that's the stuff
I want to see and
That was like the only real
Glen said that that I got it for you
Yeah maybe next year
I didn't actually say that every year
I was disappointed by the
The lack of like soup
Check everyone is very focused on
5G or Smart Home
Connect with Google
Madam
In that to me was like
There was just an extension of last year
Yeah I felt like
I didn't see anything cool with like
I don't know designs for better battery life
The things that I
Look for that are
Blow me out of the
The water like oh this actually could change the way we build products
I didn't see any of that I usually see some
But I did see
So in 2017 I saw a device like
I thought it was a meme space
Projector
You can interact with
It was from basa basa actually product
So that was kind of
But sadly no one else seems to be using
Sing its own kind of like
Oh
Oh well
Let's talk about let's talk about security which no one talked about
Yes I didn't get a lot of
Security and privacy
Personally I don't know
Nope
This is actually more on
The Enterprise
Industrial site but it's chilling nonetheless
Gemalto found that nearly half of work
Organization state
Actually can't tell if they're iot devices were breached
So this is
This is a call for
Auditing
You guys which is it
Erie Airport
To have his party
If your security rep
So gemalto surveyed 950 it and business decision-makers for this
Report that they made
So most organization
Consider iot
Security to be a priori
Nearly two-thirds so that's 57% of survey
Ben said their organizations
Have adopted a security by Design approach
Search for creating their own iot
And
Fewer than that so 46% said they thought that
Securities the main consideration
Customers
I can go with that
Even consumers choose based on price
Enterprises
Their security
Concerned so I'm not sure
Who these people they in
Radar
So if it's
Consumer
If they're selling to
Consumer marketer in Enterprise
Other services found
Upwards of 80% of Enterprise users iot security is their biggest
Barrier to adoption
So security is typically right up there
No question
But less than 14% of the survey respondents iotv
Kids are going towards
So
That's
That's not green
And less than 2/3
Only 59% says their organization and Crips all the day today
The capture or store Vio
That one jumped out of me that kind of
Shock Me
Yeso
I'm a little concerned everybody should be storing their stuff in it
Everybody should actually be doing
Security by Design
And you know everybody needs to have auditability so they understand
Like when
Things happened that they should know about
This is it expensive it's hard but if you're going to actually put centers on everything and start Gathering the data that you need in
And storing it
You have to protect that data
I find it interesting that if
Security is like a number one priority
One of the easiest ways to
Check the data is to encrypted and yet companies are investing the time and effort to encrypt
Okay there we go
And
I don't know what else to say
But
For the more advanced people who are like
Encryption is not enough
Take it a step further
The IEEE
Has a solution
And boy howdy
It is quite the same
Solution
So
It is quite the name as well
It is so they're calling this
A reconfigurable secure
Security framework for iot
The acronym is
Res iot
The idea is you
You put a software-based security agent
On a wireless router a base station
Or a gateway
Spice so you put this on
Somewhere in your organization
You can talk to this
And it
Basically lets
That's kind of is a gateway security Gateway yes
The GateKeeper
It makes sense
Community can protect everything from the router on down this way
Gear
In much better shape what I don't understand
And this comes from
My other hat when I read about Chromebooks
Chromebooks are secure because every Chromebook
Has a TPM or trusted platform module
Which is a piece of hardware
And that
Checks up on boot up every time to make sure that the
The system firmware has not been tampered with
If it is
Totally useless to that point because it's been infected whatever
I don't understand why
Routers or some type of
Gatekeeping devices haven't used
This type of approach from a hardware standpoint other than cost
It just makes sense
Yeah
I mean in it could
I mean they say it
Require changes in Ark
Catchers and it doesn't but it does require
Maybe a smarter router or
Gateway and that's not something that people
Think about
And then the other thing is when you start thinking about that
You're bringing your it system in your sensor system which is usually an operational technology system that's been air-gapped
You bringing those
And that can be
Disturbing so this is America
Architecture we see actually
Industrial
So they have their sensor networks that are
The OT
Talk to
A dedicated game
That Gateway
Handle security and all the in
Information flowing up
From
At the machinery
And then the it infrastructure
Connects down to it and you can't actually
It's designs for you
You can't have the it stuff
Talk down to the Cent
The design of a car
Car should be right so your
Canvassing
Ethernet never actually
That has been
Proven unsafe as in
Charlie Miller Jeep
But
That's the idea
And you know
Depending on how you do it you're actually
So take a look at this will link to
The story about this it's definitely interesting it's deaf
Currently a nice way
To you know maybe retrofit
Security into
Your organization although you should still be encrypting in auditing and
Other things
Speaking of sex
Security Trend Micro released
Report
Tell me about RFK
Taxo this is radio frequency hack
And
It is scary as all get-out so the report's findings
I found
Problems
In cranes drills mining Machinery in other industrial device
Produced by the 7 most commonly.
They are huge point
Securityweek
This is because they are connected there
Expensive to replace in there
Painting
The patch and they exist in the field
A decade or
So This research is saying that
That they have
No rolling code
No crypto
And no software
Protection
So you can have all kinds of
Previous
Show again
Encrypt
Over-the-air updates
It's no thinking about cashing an industrial system
I think we're going to actually need some dude
Parameters around that to me
Dispatching
Is not the same
In
Factory or a mine
As it is in an IT organization
But still
We got to fix it snow treat an IT organization in the race to do that
Yes but
But it is easier
You can lose billions
Shut your factory
By accident during a
I mean it's a pain when your
Computers go down
Don't get me wrong
Okay as anyone can tell you like
Flying in the
Turkish Airlines
Peter's go down
Okay so let's move on
Security and scary things and talk about
Fun things like
Kevin
Your Supermarket is implementing robot
Yeah but you could be scary but
The supermarket is adding big googly eyes to this robot suit looks dirty
Approachable
The chain of supermarkets is called Giant
Giant supermarkets which is based in Pennsylvania
200 stores not just in Pennsylvania but
They are
Implementing robots in their stores or Technologies
It's rather tall it doesn't look like a robot it kind of looks like a
Oh I don't know about
Stalk on a base that just kind of Roads around that's why they put the face on that so it doesn't look
Weird
And have a lidar in it
Took a nap and never get the store it's got hi-res three-d depth cameras for navigation and
Data acquisition
Basically this thing can run for 12 hours on a charge and what
Does in the store
Is it
Looks
Tripping slip hazards on the floor
Which could be
You know anywhere that and they don't want me baby
Hurt themselves
Ricky Nelson
Yeah we're lawsuit yeah but he can also read unit tags and recognize if things are out of stock on the shelf and then
An alert employees when those items are available in the stockroom for restocking
But doesn't have arms that's not going to restock for you unfortunately
And it also can
Scan the prices and make sure
By checking the prices against
What's on the shelter's what's in the register database if the prices are accurate
So can actually let people know hey we need to update this tag
It doesn't seem to be really
Taking the place of Annie
People which I think is a good thing but it seems
Are useful way to gather data and compare data to make sure the shopping experiences
Best as it can be so
I am looking forward I will take photos or video this thing when I see it
And Chase it down
Chase
Oh okay
Okay
And next up is
Hey Kevin is there money in creating cuss
Custom Madame Isabelle's
I wouldn't think so
But then I just read this article on axial saying that the New York Times is planning to make
Money building
Madame a skills
And
I'm surprised that they're getting into this
Basically
Time is going to create custom skills for advertisers
Enceladus
Is there a white label service
And they're not making any money
After they create the skills there's no like Kickback on the ads or not. It's just
Wheedle it you take it and go
I'm really surprised they've 175 people dedicated to this
And
They're expecting it'll take about three months per skill to make a custom skill and
I guess I don't know what they're charging for it but
I'm just shocked it's so it's like an ad agency
Kind of service
It is but did you expect the time or somebody to do is I did not they try and
Once
Right now so you got it you got it
Make money where you can
Damn
Show me self
Let's talk about this
Hack that you found to protect my private conversations from my Google home or my Amazon Echo
Yet we for the number of
Stories in people with bowel concerns about how these microphones are always listening somehow
Every once in awhile the private conversations aren't so private and
Are two people that created the
How to hack basic cuz that's what it is
This hack
Under the name project alias
And what project Alias does or will do it's not ready for prime time yet
It will literally create white noise
For the speaker
Until you say the the keyword
And because of this
It will not
Hear your private conversations
Innocent a white noise what kind of balance battery during the gate that out
I think it's brilliant
Yeah I think
We honestly
These two companies were talking about Amazon or Google
She really buy it
Because
Mission implemented themselves at the device level
Well so what's interesting is
Cuz I'm less concerned about Amazon or Google hearing my stuff all the time
I'm more concerned
About someone
Hacking my microphones in those device
If that makes sense
So this way
That's
Correct
Yeah I'd be all about that
So what
It's not out yet
That's so
We should just go check it out
What is Project alias
Project alias
All right welding
Okay
We got a little acquisition news
For everybody in the lighting world
Let you guys know how much I love my Lutron gear
Yay
They
Do not advertise
I just left them
And they acquired an outdoor lighting
Limelight
B
Purse price wasn't
Disclose
But we should be able to love my hope is like we should get awesome outdoor lighting
Tied into the existing
Lighting controls offer by Lutron
And Wallah
We have integrated lighting Oliver home
Amazeballs
Is it
It's just a tiny
Little thing but
Worth noting
And
That's probably sufficient for the news this week
Sure there's
We didn't ever because
Good Lord so much news
But that's the stuff we cared about
So let's take a moment to go to our voicemail
This week's voice mail
Is sponsored by
Do not miss your chance to win
Ashley
Connect smart deadbolt
Now it is Zippy certified
With Amazon key compatible
So you can upgrade your smart home with a safety Simplicity and style
Schlage
And if you want us to answer your question
Please give us a call
At 5 1/2
And this week's voicemail is from
Let's hear it
Hello this is bread
Commuter
I have a friend
To son is in a wheelchair
And
And when he gets
Home from
The
School
On the bus
Did like to be alerted
Dipping the car
Lakeville
Here I come
I love to put something on the
Wheelchair that is either Wi-Fi or
Bluetooth enabled or something that would
Alert them
Their child
When the bus is arrived.
The child survived
So that they can meet him
Andorno's Italy
So you have any ideas he's asleep
Tile
And
A few other option
Just didn't seem dope
Alert remotely
Inn at the distance
That we wanted
Thanks
I want like it's used
Case it's very practical
I love those practical use case
So much
And we have a really easy solution
It is going to cost in Escanaba
Scription cost but it is the Samsung
SmartThings LTE tracker
Yes this was announced
Couple months ago we saw it on the FCC database before they even announced it
Samsung site
It's 9999 for the tracker
It has GPS
LTE
It's water-resistant so I think it's
Perfect for
Attaching to
The wheelchair or any similar device that somebody wants to track for people
It does have a subscription that you mention Stacey but for the first year
That's actually included
So the cellular service is included
First 12 months
After that it's $5 a month or $50 per year
You know this is a very important use case I think
It's probably worth the cost in this case for
Rap
Margarita
I don't believe you need a SmartThings Hub with this because
Does require the SmartThings app and that indicates to me that you can get push notifications when the Wii
Wheelchair new gets into the geo-fenced home area Etc
An
There's no Hub needed there so I think you're fine with just this
Tracker and the app I don't know if your friend's son has a phone
But if they do have
A phone
Then you can use if
So ifttt
And basically load the app on the phone
And then create an apple
That basically win the phone gets within Wi-Fi range
Home it will
Send a notification
Vacation Center
To someone
So this is an option that is
Completely free
It's going to have some downsides such as
Latency
It may also be a little weird depending on
The wifi radius so
It may
Trigger a little early or maybe a little late
And if there's no Wi-Fi network
The phone doesn't have the Wi-Fi network turned on that's not going to work
So that is an option
That way and
And you also have
Right there's no fee involved.
All right
So
That concludes this portion of the show
Stay tuned
Fergie toes you're a loser
Is the chief digital officer of ABB
They make everything from
Plastic zip ties to
Industrial robot
So this is
A ginormous Company 290
We did not get into
I can talk to this man 4 hours
But we focused on
His Maslow's
Hierarchy
Iot needs
And
Business models
That might arise from
Basically usage-based
Pricing for
Industrial
So stay tuned for that
Everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is database provider
Are command I have aloe vera
Who is here
Compare Cobb to talk to us
About their age
Summa question I see a lot of people asking
Is
What should their iot Edge
You guys have actually built to database
The edge
LC Tri Edge
So do you have any recommendations
To share with our audio
Depends on what is needed by the business
Sanlitun
Things to decide on so we try to help by making it a business
For example user can store all the data at the edge and
Send nothing of that to the cloud or if I decide that's going to send everything
The clouds just or just the date of the thingy that the edge and almost kind of fractured his claws
In some cases
Just do what they actually need is to come
Control the data in real-time
And dolcenero
Strongly recommend
Tasha Smith
Process to the edge
Especially on the decision-making that you're trying to run
Okay so
I'm deciding between the edge in the cloud
What are some of the things I need to
To take him to come
Consideration
Well you have to consider
First acknowledge
Both the edge in the cloud VR different roles
That used different.
Acknowledges and if
Protocols
That's pretty much
The market has been discussing ass
The Clash
Between racial technology and information technology
Make sure that you are.
Technologies that support different protocols
Especialista our standards already in place
Saw some other things that I think it's very important to consider like for example whatever database
Alaska
Assisted on the edge this database needs to be able
Go to provide you with flexible schema mainly because of the
All kind of different types and in many cases
Is the closer
Just able to handle the data
Producing native format the better for you
Application here is really being able to store data like for a simple Time series
Basecamp Alaska state of for you but it's
The same time calculate averages in the medians automatically so you don't have to go back in Cuero today
Crossed your data set stats
Stop your real time
Process in many ways
What's worth talking about your is
Nosql database
And we definitely just I know SQL database is the best candidate for an adjective
And some of the things that I think of
As being really important
For the edge
Would be
Security
How do you guys
Help with that
That's a very good point if you decide if you're going to have to
Transfer some of your decision-making to the edge you definitely going to have to talk to have to persist data locally
For example.
Historical data
This immediately leads to the need for encryption
That's absolutely mandatory if your select
Sister theater on the edge
How many ways I was teased about combining the real time information
Let's be produced by machines and equipments that you're controlling their be measured by its digital sensor
What's so-called operational technology
Or the corporate it Department that has
Decentralized fuel of all its systems with information like historical date of orders cost and dementor
We considered making sure that this information flows
States with managed
Project
So where can we find out more about faircom address
Tea tree Edge
Database
You can check website
Sarcoma
Dot-com
1 / coyote
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is ghetto Jared who is this
Chief digital officer
Officer at ABB
So how are you doing
I'm doing
Thank you very much
Okay
Just impress everyone
I think you should tell us
What ABB
Is and does
ABB is one of the
Industrial companies remake
Technologies that helps to turn electricity into motion
So we make robots
Motors
Control system circuit breakers
We are
34 billion dollar company
48000 employees
And we have been around for a little bit over on
Exactly this is one of those companies that you will never hear
In your day-to-day life
But they are everywhere and
So
They're doing amazing stuff
With the internet estate
So let's just Orient
Ask the chief digital officer
How do you think about the internet
Really a sumac
There's a consumer Internet of Things where we talked about
Colored light bulbs and home alarm systems and all kinds of connected speakers and devices like that
Dustrial internet of things which is the other part of this equation
We're talking about
Devices that are connected but they're operating inside of chemical plants and facts
Inside of mine
Oil and gas field
So as a chief
It's afraid I'm trying to inject
Digital Technologies in every product
Conservative
That is a
Call order
And I know that we have spoken
About your maslov
Hierarchy
Of iot
Because I think it's a good way that companies can
Can look it up
Assess where they are
Signatureny
The basically making more efficient use of their
People their processes
Resources
I'd love to do that explain a little bit why I came up
It's because the internet
There's use cases that are different industries that are different
Technology stocks everything from the very
Small light sensors communicating analytic software
In the Gateway at the yard Jordan
Cloud
Machine learning drone technology
Too much to get your head wrapped around
Companies and customers you're doing with the Internet of Things
All the sudden
Like mouthwash
Iraq
How do you say Stephens
Community
Classify
Aldi's
Hundreds of thousands of individual application
Really only about
Five different capabilities AR level
Dorney Park
Whole bunch of application but nothing more than
This thing we're going to put a little chip on it it's going to be able to talk we communicate and it tells us how it's doing
Why do we care
Mantra
Because you can then at least go from taipei
Maintenance schedule
Commission-based
Quite beneficial because there's a lot of equipment in construction
Deployed and of course
Maintaining it properly is important
That's the base of the mount Lafayette
If you can read
You can probably also
Meaning you can change value
In that system you can write
Naked
The robot
You can make it
Do new things
As a result
You can go beyond monitoring and you can label a class of application but I call often
You can make things on
Faster
Consume less energy be more reliable
And of course this all depends on what the customer wants
Memphis Behavioral
As a supplier
Because you can say to your customer would you like me to optimize this device for you
During its operation to better serve your needs
Devastation that's mostly where we are today
Exactly right
Probably
60 70%
NVM
And it's very safe to just read as big as opposed to actually
Got it
So now let's keep moving
Where can we ask
Aspire to be
Stacy the world
Nice because you can put two versions
People that make
Look up music
Motors
Transformer
We put all this time and effort in R&D and we have no idea which features are customers really do
Because we have no feedback
Or at least we didn't until now
Feedback loops that lets us monitor the characteristics of the device
Also tells us which button people do push and which dial people
When you get all this data back
Can you know which features they're using you know which components inside of your machine wear out
Fastest all this wealth of data so you can now for the first time
Make your products better
Baseball music
And I think that's really cool
Byproduct of just having fun
And what do you call that
I call that product
2.0 I called the idea that this was
Product 2.0 because this is a product which actually based on this
Digital feedback loop
You keep improving
You keep it already
You keep making it better.
So I think that's important
Holding on because I think that changes the way a lot of
Business works
So we'll come back to what it was
Support
Nate
Product 2.0
But let's
Keep moving up your higher
Okay so now we're ready for a level four
Welcome people save all the smartphone getting expensive
Well
Yes or no
Inexpensive
Your smartphone means that you no longer have to buy any
Pocket camera for that you don't need to buy an alarm clock or that you don't need to have a
What's happened is
Those who become after those are features
But you can add this is about
Converge
And of course if you have
A piece of machinery and intelligence
You can do new things like a witch
It's like every other circuit breaker except that it has a computer inside and now it can do things like
Measure the power quality
Coming into the plant
Pecan shed
If you want to participate in demand response for you're getting paid
Powerful
And those extra features
Apps you can download onto the circus
Computer inside
The last one is really the
Changing of the business model
If I'm not connected I have these downloadable apps
To pay for this product would you like to pay for it
He's done with me or would you like to go
Trifold in the maintenance the remote monitoring the remote optimization
Staying up last month and at the end of that product
Like me to charge you based on usage because
Utilization
I know how
Spanish you like
I can work out a system whereby you pay me the more you use it and if you don't give it a thought you think of that
Of course the dialogue
Conversation between the maker of that product
Customer that products
But those are very
Industrial
Economy hasn't haven't had before
I agree
And we will talk about that
Let's go back to this idea of product
Because in our previous conversation
And you mentioned that
Tesla is a good example of this
What's the matter with this idea that
The car is continually being
Updated with software
And
It changes it usually ideally gets better over
So with that that's fundamentally
Is a different business
As for a lot of come
So if you're going to go from
Making a robot
I thought you said one
Maybe you offer a service
Contractor maintenance
Contract for 5 years
To making a robot
Is going to
Constantly get better and have a continuing relation
Customer
That feels like it changes
Cell cycle
Warranty obligations that changes your
Cost of operating
Producing a product
Breakdown
Relationship
One of those things that is both
Potentially
Changed as a result if you have a product
And in many cases the members should you have a complex system business where you make something that required integration
Deployment
They would have to cater you typically work with a channel system integrator people that store your product
Past the point of sale is both an opportunity for the makers of the things she perceived as a
Weather Channel
So you may
Put your Channel
Because they feel like you might use this
To perceive to be bringing
I'll install that if he
And the maker of the robot
You may not know where that's going because that's being done by a system integrator or some kind of engineering company
Connection changes
Relationship
Because they see value in 10 Connected for the company that makes
Have to do that just like in the world of Automotive it's best to have its own dealers or have that
It is essentially altering the relationship that would exist
Continue by dealer
So you're talking about the company making it as well
Clearly
Where the R&D
Shock the Moon
From Hardware increasing video software
Change for companies with traditional have relied on Material Science innovation
Better Dentistry
Understanding those deep
Physical properties
Ways to make the product better
Janelle being able to do a lot of
And that's a huge shift and kind of people that were looking to hire
Materials engineering Stihl
Ladders
And so
But you can affect the outcome of something
Why does it
In software
Where
Course Material Science may give you that Quantum Leap for that Improvement
But that laugh
Extra bit can usually be done
Of the various components
And I am curious because you guys deal with heavy Industrial
And what if he
I'm not going to call it an epiphany
Because it wasn't quite so bright
Is bad but
Talking to somebody a John Deere about
The right to repair issue
And that is basically
Machines
Bear
Forcing farmers
To rely on the dealers to
Repair
A lot of people are very
Upset by this and I get it
First century
People have bought a Prada
Repaired at them
Selves in bed response
Before and after
As we start putting
Software in it
The number of people who have that
Joseph
But it also
Creates the snoo
Relationship that some people don't seem to be willing to
To give up and this ties to you know John Deere this might be the people who used to fix
Your robots
At various
Factories that may not have access to as much as
The things that might be causing the
The problems anyway
And even in a smart home
I'm starting to
Relegate some things over to software I'm losing the ability
Tweaker cam
I think it's kind of a natural
Abstraction that happens when you get things over to software but I'm curious
Collier
Talking to your customer base or how you're thinking about
Good question
One example of that so you know
This thing is huge debate
Privacy
I see a data who owns potato
There's a similar
Type of debate happening on the industrial side up
The business side of this equation when it's really busy
Property and data ownership
Who owns what data
And of course as all these devices
We do get data back and one of the ways that we've tried to have that debate
Clarify
The different types of
The data are so we have
Identity data who you are we have
Essentially Telemetry data which is the individual value that you
Machine by sending back their temperature energy consumption
Inside
Which is you take all of that and you turn it into
Friends and prediction
And clearly the most sensitive of all of this Susie identity data
Married to the Dilemma
Why
The weather like in healthcare in u.s. government has embraced something called Healthcare information
Essentially mandates that identity data be stored separately from Telemetry data or measurement
Potentially a good used to be made
Public public
Healthcare data because if we analyzed it better we might be able to determine
But we can understand why people wouldn't want that individual disease information to be tied back to them especially if it could
Check insurance rates
To be made
In the separation of
Data
Only part of this equation
Being able to fix things and repair things I do think it's more more devices haven't better software than taking that into
Prepare yourself is increasingly difficult
What you do find is that
Increasingly people want to make things work together
That's very similar to be knowledge of your smart home
Speaker
How do I do that and that's the same that's happening in industry it's not that they want to think about the light bulb
Driver Motors
And there's a strong interest in driving towards greater standardization
And this is where the industrial world has been
Low because we have seen a great convergence away from
Token ring and sddi and all these things 2 words pretty much Wi-Fi ethernet
IP
Let's talk about business
So one of the things
Charging based on use
And I think that is
Incredibly fast
And I started out my career covering
Cloud compute
And that the big Trend there was moving your
Capital expenditures in your it
Infrastructure
To an operating X
Nature
Payout
No as needed
Amazon
Microsoft whomever and
When I think about
It sounds
Awesome
But it also
Changes the wave
Businesses are built
The creation of wealth it's always been about
Building up
Your infrastructure
Historically
Right and owning saying
And then taking advantage of those so like owning your own car than you
Hire it out to people if you were
Want to make money
If you're thinking about your
The car is at
You pay for it
You still never owned it
And I think that's a very big shift work
Going I'm curious about your
Thoughts
How to change the business mod
How does that change
Ideas of wealth in
Halloween
Can actually build wealth up
So you mention cloud computing
An interesting analogy but I think we're
Gets a bit more problematic because it's a little bit
Expected
The nice thing about cloud computing is of course you can move the computer
Centralized Batman as long as the work is getting done and good response you don't need to know
And the reason why
What's economically is that an Enterprise was using a server at 30% of its capacity
The cloud provider says I will host
Computing loads for you
Daikin double up Triple up those
Get loan from multiple customers
Use less
Total Hardware
Tree companies using service at 30% cloud provider might be able to get away with
With all those
If you have a factory that's only use that 30% of its capacity it's really hard to rent out your factory
We have to do when we're thinking about pay-per-use models for industrial
Is
Somebody somewhere
But Nina has to be the company that makes beer
And this is where there's a very interesting
Economy for companies that want to own
Long life
Understand
If we wanted to rent out those Transformers to customers based on a pay-per-use Model if we ended up
Providing that
Former but we retain title to the app
If the customer doesn't start using it
It becomes very expensive capital
Activity
There are other company
Very happy
Pension fund know they have long-term liabilities they need to pay out
So they're looking for
Big infrastructure things that are very
Very stable
Utilization of the times that we need data
Interesting question around who owns an asset
Who is able to use the app
Who makes better
So tonight
We ended up staying connected
With a digital read that when we die
Which as we know where it is
I was getting used and who owns it
Everybody can
Eventually get the benefit of that
Wow I think you just blew my mind
I love it
Okay
Let's go then to the next obvious question
I will probably
And here before everyone else is just
Play this too much to think about here
What are the things
Yes we need to
To make this sort of vision
Possible because we are still you talked
About standard
We talked about different business model
I'm thinking about things
But hey we probably need some sort of assurance
Security those kind of things so
What are the technology
That we need to move up this nurse loves
So yes it starts with conductivity
Of course if we can't connect to the device then it doesn't work
What the good thing is
Ethernet to Wi-Fi Bluetooth
3G 4G 5G coming
Activities in increasing be solved
Earlier we'd have an additional things like time-sensitive networking
You end up with
OPC UA and other ways of standardizing the data
Change as well that's good
We definitely need
Both cloud and on-premise or fog computing
Some people think that it's all going to go to the cloud but the problem is
As we have
Huge amount of data
Latency YouTube
And we have sort of health and safety limits
Which means
Take all of those loops
Stop control and automation all the way back to the cloud
Are there we need Fantastic Tools to be able to analyze machine learning
Fantastic visualization tool
See and make sense of all of this data
Augmented reality
Visualization tools made the cameras enabled on drones
Stock us technologies that need to be assembled not to mention of course that you mentioned earlier in fiber
To make all of this effect
And it's
Almost like the moon shot
Hibachi it's a bit like
We have to get
Everything
Well aligned working
Very well
Ultimately benefits from you
And to be able to make it foolproof and plug and pray and
Do you think we'll be able to do that
I think we will be able to do it and I think we'll do that by eating the elephant
Walmart
Network connectivity technology available such as Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Stop this would work but increasingly
Incredibly reliable incredibly capable technology than
She didn't even better as time goes by
Excellent all right you know thanks so much
For coming on the show today
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Dot-com will see you next week