Hey everyone welcome to the internet
I got this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel and we have a show for you today
We're going to be talking about all of the iot news from
Microsoft build
From Google IO
We got lots of updates
Google Assistant
We actually also have updates on Amazon
Because it's a day that in
SNY
We've got ring has a new app for
Borrow has a new home
Skip button
Netgear has a new Wi-Fi update to stop screwing around with your
Homekit devices
And
We've got some quick other news bits including
The wise version 2 camera view
You and me talking about
My experience so far with the nest hello in the nest
In jail
And this week's cast is going to be Microsoft's head of iot Sam George
Because by golly I happened to meet him at the show and we talked
Are podcasts this week
Sponsored by machine
And
This week's podcast is sponsored by twilio
Twilio programmable Wireless makes it easy for developers to program cellular connectivity whether you're working with a few devices
Is or thousand get connected fast using no Shenanigans no contract and pay-as-you-go pricing
Connect devices and over 120 countries around the world programmable Wireless offers you the scale and strength of
The twilio network trusted by millions of developers all over the world check out twilio.com
Wireless okay let's get our party started with
Android
All right I should tell you guys first that I am in
Seattle
Seoul broadcasting here from Seattle so
Apologies for any weirdness
That is not my usual weirdness and
Kevin is still located in his home base somewhere outside of
Android things
Yes
So even before Google IO
Which is what I was monitoring while you are at the Microsoft build
It is now version 1.0
100000 downloads of Android SDK
They also announced support for some more
Chips and Boards there's a catalyst for
Supported
Ford Atlas
Point
I kind of thought Google with you
Android things to build a home hub that I was dead wrong because
It's really a platform for everybody other Hardware Partners to use and manage iot devices and so on
Big news which I guess is somewhat controversial is that Google will be
Squirting
Automatic software updates for Android things devices for up to three years by default
With an option for device makers to extend that support
I say controversial cuz I thought this was good
I thought it was kind of
Lame because one
Qualcomm for example in their Snapdragon embedded chips design for iot Stuff
Their support
Is going to be
7 to 10 years depending on the form
Microsoft
With its Azure sphere is supporting it
10 years
And neither of those were
Required Edition
Now qualcomm's a little different cuz they're not supporting the OS there to support him
Hardware under
Twitter updates
Patches but Microsoft security stuff
Is based on 10 years of support and it only is
Buy it when you buy the chip
Basically so you're buying into all of
So this feels
In Kevin I know you talked about like device lifecycle so
Things is actually a fairly
Fat operating system
It's like a requires like 1 megabytes of memory I believe
That's a fair point the lowest
Memory requirement is 512 Meg of RAM and it goes up to one or two on the other boards from NXT
Qualcomm
So I a yes because a lot of new devices
We talked about Housley
A miniscule amount of storage or memory
Right into those I guess would end up with Android Wear
Or something else
It's okay so it depends on what the device is because
Google has been very specific
Bandits
Terms on what you can use Android things for
And here's the quote that I pulled out from their program housing
You are prohibited from the commercialization of products built on Android things
Who's form factors defined as a device type by the Android TV device
Such as handheld
Watches television
Automotive
Any other device categories in the future
The reason is they have
Android auto for cars they have wear OS 4 watches they have Android for tablets that Andrew TV for
TV
This is a totally separate thing you notice relate
So I could put Android things in a hub but I might also want to put it in like a thermostat
Smart display
You could do that
Okay
So but some of those devices
Arnott
You notice away devices and
That's where I'm getting kind of like you know I've had like my connected Outlets
Which probably are not a good cattle
Thanks but I had those for 6 years now
So I'm not sure
Again. I also think on the life cycle Park
I really think Android thinks it's more of the consumer device as opposed to an industrial
In which case
New Chips new capabilities are coming out quicker and quicker
What is computer vision or whatever maybe AI
So I think Google can imagine their bets on that life cycle
Okay well I was going to say art June oven runs Android
It doesn't run Android things but it does running
That's true because Android things didn't exist
Right
No but you're right because Android it has run in
What color embedded systems
Stitches the June oven
Such as the wink relay
So yeah and those are things but I'd be hacked off if my $1,500 Oven broke after
3 years
Okay that's
Also from
Google IO
Not a pre-launch of exciting iot platform
They updated a lot with Google Assistant
So it now can handle multiple
Command something
At The Echo
And it also says
Supports customized routine
In the notable thing on customize routines I thought that was interesting
Was that it allows for scheduling
Which currently madhumeh in the Amazon Echo do not do so
Google kind of LeapFrog them a little bit there in that actually does kind of turn your Google home into a home health aide
It's like a pseudo help now and came functions like that.
Correct so
Pittsburgh promising
They definitely showed off their AI chops with a demo
Showing multiple commands totally unrelated commands
Interesting
Probably worth a watch if you didn't see the keynote which is available on YouTube
YouTube so
I'm excited
Really
Now embedded in the
Google home
System
I'm going to go pick up buy any more Echo stuff
I like what you're doing
Me too so I'll
Wait till you hear the nest doorbell stuff that I'm going to
Okay now I did talk to a couple people about this and they were like with the continued
Command or continue conversations they were like
So it's listening all the time
And they were like super freaked out by the
So I'm very curious where the normal peep
The world
Fallenness
Line
Yes but but but
Listen for another 5 Seconds as well now because you can say Ma
She wasn't for that so
That's already happened on the echo for at least 5 more seconds
True oh you can also tell your Google you can set it up so you have to ask it
Is it pretty please or just please teachers called pretty please but you don't have to say pretty please
That's good cuz I think the last time I said pretty please I was probably 15 and begging for like
My mom to buy me some clothes
Okay
So
Blissey
And then we'll get to what I will call these super cool / creepy / questionable section of the
Google IO demo
Which was assistant making it was
Call Google duplex in a basically let
Assistant
Call something on your behalf ask
For information and negotiate
Which if you haven't heard it you got to listen because
Kind of mind-blowing
I really thought they Outsource
Humans to make appointments for people when they demoed the appointment when they send you a Google make me a haircut appointment
At this time in this day
And then you heard a phone call to a salon I thought it was
I mean I'm like torrent Asus passes this use case
And Google says they're going to use this they could see themselves using this to like automatically update restaurant
Flowers and get information from real people that currently they can't do so like things like
Is is closed on Superbowl Sunday
The robot. Text
You know that doesn't tell you that necessarily so Google Now can just call
People in ask
Shifts the burden of
You know information the restaurant may not update their website to show hours and so I said what's up how do you find out what you call
They have
Made it
I made it to do that and they gather information and they can update their website
So yes
Crazy crazy that's my insightful commentary they're crazy crazy
So
At Microsoft build which is where I am
And you'll hear more about some of the stuff they announce their when
Talk with Sam
But
They also demoed
Another digital assistant
Several actually they did mode
Madame a talking to
Microsoft score
Cortana
This was something announced a while back but no one knew how it was going to work
Really but a couple things I called to say you I bust when I was reading about it
Because the latency was true
Tremendous so I started out with this woman asked
Padme open Cortana
Hi this is Cortana Houck
Can I help you
And she said what's on my calendar for the day
And then
Cortana after saying what was on her calendar with say
Can I help you with anything else and then she might ask a follow-up
Question that was
Fine like DUI sounds good but in
Action
There was a huge like a 2 to 3 second
Latency
Even the demo words were talking over
The assistant
So it was definitely
A little clunky
And then Microsoft is talking about Microsoft will be handling your business
And
Madame able to your
How many
But in another example they had
He was talking to Cortana and he was getting his information
Cortana the news like
Cortana ask to open battle
And then he wanted an Uber ride
Uber ride to me is not either a business or a personal
I think that is just a thing you do in both Realms and how would you remember
Offer you
And that's
The key right there that's the obstacle to me now after associate and assistant name with different tasks
Sorel contact
And I just think it's horrible
It's just
Satya Nadella in his keynote actually talked about giving
He's like voice apps are big
They're going to have to be a branded experience and I don't want branded experiences
That I have to remember it
Call aansoo Jee actually has a cook
Cooking assistant called Geneva
That you can control the amount of a with
You know if you have
GE Appliances
Bosch has one called
Hey it's me K or Mikey
Maggie's baby and
See I can't even remember yet I have a Bosch dishwasher and a Bosch microwave
So
Holy cow
I just this is too much for me from I mean I can barely remember my family members names when I'm shouting out commands to them so
Lord help me when I'm trying to remember
Branded voice app names
I don't know how they would actually
Make this work
So I can get
It just doesn't work
Agreed
I wasn't too keen on that you can sign up when click the link in the show notes
And
Test this out for yourself sometime
After an invite and then hopefully it will be available I think it's
Speed before the end of this year
So we'll see
Amazon also last week launched the general availability of in skill pay me
And I don't know if
We have not been following the concert
Vince Gill payments but basically what this is
Any customer can buy something within
And outside skill without having to leave that skill
So as a merchant you have to register with Amazon pay so I can
Can use my details in my Amazon
An account to pay for
For your product
So some of the companies that are using this already or TGI Fridays 1-800
Flowers
So I can now
Order everything
I say Madam a open Fridays I start the process
And then
I can order everything I want
And please
So
Yeah I like this I mean I don't do a lot of shopping by voice but
All the cards I would use for online shopping already registered with Amazon anyway so
It's a smart move
Ya think of that override you could just have it
Charge you back
Which means you could actually I know you can send people Ubers finally now but like you could it as the account owner
Call an Uber for like a drunk friend at your house in
Send them on their way
Don't be nice
Or drunk friend at the office but then would you ask Cortana
What would you ask me
Metal man who knows
Depends on the level of employee
Kind of items so ring has a new neighbors
And
Kevin you want to tell us what this is
Yeah so bring already had like a neighborhood type
Sharing
Aspect to it if you want to opt into it so like if I
My ring
Doorbell sees something sketchy in the neighborhood you know other people in my area
Has a ring advenir popped it in information about it but now apparently that information
Just be sent directly to the
Police are probably some parameters in Hopkins for this as well but it's a nice expansion of the neighborhood
Neighborhood watch
System
Yes so what happens is
Yes it will send it automatically to the police
But also if the police
I have started casefile on something they can actually start
With that case File
Requesting data from other ring cameras in the vicinity
Now I don't know if
Refuse that request or not
But there are some implications here in this is the same applications that played next door which
You know I don't know if you're on next door but I am in
Every now and then you get
Some people are like there's an African American man walking down the street and you're like oh yeah he lives there
So there's a lot of danger
For things like racial profiling
And that I had asked Jamie siminoff about this years ago when we talked about it
Because his goal was to create this quote-unquote ring us
Security run
Better Home and neighborhood
And he said they were trying to do things to encourage
People to kind of think carefully before reporting a situation to avoid some of that racial
I've never actually seen that
In the Ring app but I don't use it consistently I use it probably once every
Your 18-month says I'm testing out a new to
Device so I'm curious what kind of things that they will include in that because Amazon can't be
Unaware
This is a
Definite thing that's going to happen
The other aspect of this that I think is kind of interesting is
Package delivery is a huge problem for Amazon
They now own ring
What is kind of Private Eyes
The cops to work on behalf of Amazon.
Prevent package theft
So that is kind of
That's my crazy
Actually I've not Elites that make sense
So we'll see
How that is in action and if
If you have a ring doorbell
Feel free to like
Tell us if it's like
Letting you racially profile
Alright others news bits time for the news bits
Kevin I know you were excited
Excited about
Excited because you love this little thing this is bethabara button
That we saw at CES it is now available
And this is the homekit
$60
$10 more than the regular button
Yes
Which seems to be the going rate from tomorrow for any homekit
Version of existing device
I think it has three actions you can do a one tab to do something to Taps for something else and hold it
Down for a third action
Turn All the Lights may be adored and how many clicks are tabs
Mine has like five taps
Any homekit does only three I don't know
Yeah mine has way more apps
Double the action
So okay so that's out if you're into the fibaro
You like those sensors
Would you recommend that to homekit user
Sbarro sensors
Yeah absolutely I think they're among the best out there they just seem to be the most consistently
Swimming
But they are expensive
You know what they are expensive
All right Indie Wi-Fi is tough
Category
The Netgear Orbeez actually did an update a while back B
Because I don't know if you guys all remember
If you had a Google home
They were flooded your router
Packets and it was
Is causing problems
For people who had Google Home Products in
I think some other baby
Comcast products
In the Netgear orbi World in some other mesh Wi-Fi routers
So
Netgear updated that unfortunately when they did that they
Apparently broke some homekit
Functionality for their home kit use
So
Now they have launched a workaround for that while they figure out
A permanent work around
For all issues
Associated with Wi-Fi
So there you go
Intel capital and the NBA are team
Bring up to invest in sports this is a i n Sports this is iot in sports is whatever pickup
Buzzword blockchain
Anythink
Basically concept is how to make Sports better because Sports is a wonderful source of
And there's really a lot of opportunity here so I'm I'm really kind of curious to see what comes out of
If you have a good idea
For this areata
For basketball
Hindi actual Rita
Call Intel capital
Trend Micro did a great report on the habits of
People who hack into surveillance
So this was a really
Fun is probably the wrong word
Word for this
But they took a look at
All of the networks that
Offer in traffic in exposed
Iot cameras weather at surveillance weather
Webcams
In the freakiest thing
I found out what it was
You basically buy these
Or you can buy access to the cameras used by access to the videos
In
The pricing for this is
Reticular soyu
The prevalent model is called the paper camera
Or paper package model
The price usually ranges from
A buck 50 to $5 per item and I could go for less than a dollar
For like
Items that are on sale so
If you're like a hot lady who's got a webcam that's been hacked
You're probably going to be on
$5 into the scale otherwise
Hacked baby monitors maybe at the dollar end of the scale item
I'd have to pay people to watch me on a camera
I don't know I might pay like $0.50 to watch Norm jump up and down on the couch
So we'll link to the report
Cuz it's
I thought it was really
And then
There's also a new version of the $20 wyze camera we put this on our gift guide last
And tried it out and thought it was lovely
I will note because we were a little confused at first this is not a
Totally local camera
There is an SD card slot
But you do actually there's also cloud storage associated with it in
And that stuff does go to
The cloud so if you want the remote
It's going to be fun
SO3
It is free for like 14 days
Is ridiculously long amount of time
So the new Weis 2 camera views has basically
It's 20 bucks why not it's actually really good with the exception of
One weird thing that people don't like which is that it's hard to
To find your
Stored videos
Recorded video clips
Are difficult to find
And that is it for immigration purposes it works with the Amazon Echo and also with a person
Knots
Save you have a SmartThings however in their self
I still may drop 20 bucks on one just to try it out don't you know
The store everything and alert me and everything in it
Histamine
I could buy a wyze cam to every two months for the price of a
Nest subscription
Exactly
Now there is shipping so your total price for this if
If you buy at NYC
It's going to be
$6
I can live with that
Okay there you go I'm like they're not offering you free shipping on your $20 camera
Which yeah okay
So yeah
For you guys that are looking at a camera in your Leica do I need this do I want this
You could buy this in
See
And if you don't we have our setup in front of our fish tank and we had like
Fish Camp
Speaking of
Reviews
So I finally
Between travel in glitches with devices got my nest
Hello doorbell in my nest
Yale lock
Installed
All together
Accuracy purposes these are not on the same door because I
I can't the doors where my doorbell is
Do not search
Support connected locksmith
Because they were weird locking
So that's the
Crazy details about my house
I will tell you I love
The hello nest
I have tried many many many many doorbells
Yes this is expensive
Yes I wish I did not
Have to pay a subscription
I would love to have 24 hours of my video recording without paying a subscription
But hot diggity it isn't
Awesome low-latency doorbell
Great image quality at night
Pitch Black
With the porch light and the facial recognition feature is awesome because my notifications now say
Your camera spotted Andrew
At the
Fedor and I'm like
I don't care about Andrew
He can come and go with you
Please just put them
It's like your camera spotted the delivery man in the
Pictures
Pulls out of people's faces
Is phenomenal like I don't even know what my FedEx delivery guy looks like
But my Nest cam now does because it
Grabs like a split second that he turns towards the door and is like boom
I got it
So I like the store
A lot
Considering actually
So now the Yale lock
I had trouble with my first HELOC because I think
A hardware problem if this was just a straight-up I don't think the touchpad worked
I'm still waiting for nest to get back to me on the post-mortem on
The device I sent back to them
Was it me
But they sent me a new lock right away and
I installed a tin
Like 10 minutes
Possible glass
Super easy
Everything work so I'm thinking the first experience
What's a total animal
Although I will say the custom
Support Xperia
Was pretty good for what
Were they any smarter than I was probably not but I am also
And they did the handoff rights
So the
Your luck is
It's a sturdy lock
You can feel it like I replaced a Kwikset lock in
Daniela
Way sturdier the touchpad is nice
We don't actually use the remote
Capability for it very much
I tested it out with the doorbell like so the doorbell rings and then I'm like open the lock
And that happens very quickly
It's not going to work for like the FedEx guy who like just Rings my doorbell and runs down the stairs
But it would work for like a
A friend whose
Expecting this sort of
Direction to home
So
I don't know send me your questions about this because
I am happy
Answer them I don't know if I'll keep it long enough to get battery life for you guys over the long term but we'll see
Am I next effort on this is actually two
Hook this up to
The Chromecast so I can start talking to it via Google home and getting those announcements cuz right now I have it setup to get the announcements
But I'm not getting the
Is it serious when someone comes to your door in the nest
Stork Bell news who it is they will say
Andrew as it at your door
Which is cool
Chromecast integration
In my Android TV so that I can just say
Show me my Nest cam right to the TV input
I can see you it is for sale
Excellent
All right so that's that so far I should tell you the nest hello is $239 and the
Nest Yale lock is
$279
That's pricey
But it is very pretty
I will say it's
The prettiest lock
Okay
Moving on to our
Iot podcast listener hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic locks
Schlage electronic locks offer unparalleled convenience and simplicity all on their own right out of the box so you don't have
Have to have a smart home system to benefit
To see what's possible is it schlage.com
To learn more
And in this week's
Iot podcast listener hotline
We have Robert
So let's roll that clip
Hi my name is Robert from Phoenix
I have multiple
Amazon devices in my house
Upstairs and downstairs and
Good morning I'm getting ready I'd like to listen to You music and stuff upstairs on a playlist
Is there a way to continue
Exact
Point in the playlist
Thanks let me guess you
Oh Robert
This is a totally reasonable thing to want to do and unfortunately
You can't do it with what you have
I just
Yet I could that could change but
So what you can do now
Is
You can you play your song
You can stop it
You cannot resume
Another room
You can send your songs to
Like you can play them in all the rooms at once
So maybe you just play it throughout the whole house
Annoying everyone who lives there or you can buy a Sonos
Which we
Stick
Woodworks
Like this
So Kevin you want to tell him how you think
Two of the sunless units that support Madam a
Unfortunately I have them in the same room so I
I haven't been able to test this however
Installing the web for solution
Apparently you can ask Matt Ma on the Sonos
Pause
Music
Or resume in another room so that would work
In theory again have not tested it
But if it doesn't help you because that's not the devices that you have
That would stink Amazon could easily add this
It doesn't seem too difficult and do as they see matching already support multi-room audio so
Hopefully Amazon is listening to our please here and add this feature in the near future
Yes
Will see surface lately bad news but hey it's a great excuse to
To blow the $200 for the Sonos one
It is too hard I don't know if they still have the pair for 352 competing
I don't believe
So there you go
So yeah you would have to blow at least 400 if you
Stereo One
So there you have it Robert sorry for the bad news Amazon get on Roberts problem cuz it's a problem we all have
If you have a question for The Internet of Things
Podcast
Listener hotline give us a call at 512-623-7424
We would love to answer your questions
By testing it on our own devices
Scouring the web or possibly calling the company and saying
Hey
You do this or not
And now I think we've got
Plenty of news taken care of
Stay tuned for
My conversation with Microsoft's head of iot Sam George he's going to talk about the stuff that Microsoft announced it
To build
+ how businesses
Avoid getting stuck in
Can pilot purgatory
So it is a good conversation good insight into your own business transformation
And Microsoft strategy for iot
But before you can hear Sam
Stay tuned for a message from this week sponsor
Everyone weird taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Machineq which is a Comcast
Service
And I have alipay
Scrum who is GM of machine
With you Alex glad to have you back
So remind us what is machine key
Machineq
Is Comcast enterprise-grade network specifically built for iot we support B2B
MP3 PC iot solution is cases and we were growing and robust portfolio Business Solutions
So providing the end-users as well
In previous conversations you told me that one of the largest users of these low-power wide area networks is metering
Can you talk about why
Sure some music classic sort of LP when use case
That lorawan
Protocol we chosen initially
Sauce for really well
The solution is in the lead for the client is power constrained environments
These metering devices are required to be in the field for many years
They said roughly did every 15 minutes or so any devices are generally located in short of challenged
Radio frequency environment
Basements Etc the reason why is ideal is because it allows Solutions companies to get information from
New devices whenever they need
Enemy during space you have a client that you recently announced called Neptune
Why did they choose machineq
Over something
As solution providers begin to understand what it takes to have their devices out in the seal for many many years
If you come to recognize and realize that all networks are not built equal
Being part of Comcast
Machineq has the ability to build dense iot Networks
Working with a company like Neptune which is the leader in the space at the end they realize that again if I'm able to send
Information for my water meter
Closer to a Gateway the Comcast machine Q has in the neighborhood
Around 300 feet are 200 ft from that location
Pacific traditional wireless bill which might be going to a cell tower it changes the whole calculus for that partner connect
Actually enter the market
They can now use less power which means I can spend less on building the actual device
Which means our form factor changes and ultimately what happens if machine cues building a platform so every IQ solution provider
Actually change their form factors reduce their cost to be more competitive
To their ultimate end-user in this case being that is analogous
So what can you do once you have these dents iot networks in cities
Once we have the base Network
In place for cities
Cities can easily add additional services like lighting Leak Detection anything you can imagine
Smart City applications can be layered on now that the Network's already there
Awesome so where can we go to find out more
You can start for the website and the Cinque. Com recent great white papers on the site including our latest on dense Network
There's Technical and business product information services including device conversion guides for anyone looking to develop
Machineq and we also have network coverage details and information about getting connected both
In footprint and out of the Comcast from Turkish well
Everybody Welcome Back To The Internet of Things podcast and today's guest is
Sam George
Github Microsoft iot
The effort
Microsoft
Seattle and
Call from Sam
Hi Sam how are you thanks
Thanks for coming
Come on
A while back
And we talked
Call X
So we're going to start with the news
From build
So I
It felt like Microsoft gave me this
Huge magical strategies
Your job saying
Explain the magical strata
To us
X-wind all right let me just say that focus of ours and IRT
Is the help customers
Benefit very quickly
At this point we built out a very sophisticated set of services
Lacrosse
Cloud
And so we've been focused a lot on
Big Mac
Easy to deploy
Holistically with iot Solutions
Accelerators
Generally available this week
Bathhouse a Peyote Central and update Focus
Has been Edge
And so you saw it Edge in our Keynote
Where we were demonstrating
AI model
Fancy Qualcomm cameras
We've developed a partnership with them
As well as DJI drone
So Microsoft has actually been
Tearing
Doing a lot with iot
Forever maybe the last three
I feel like you guys
Really made an effort
This week feels like
The culmination
Learned
In those last
2 years
Some of the big news that we had this week
All around
How companies
Using
Iot devices
Not just
Or sensing the world
Or phoritto receiving commands
The cloud for running
Cloud workloads right on the
One of the insights that we had
Add from working with pasta
Is that
Data has gravity
And as
Lots of data generated out on the edge
Such as video data
To take
Yankee
You can put it right on the device and operating on it there
It's sort of forms this balance be
In the cloud
Legend in Iowa
Since around the edge as a supporting platform
Source address
Yes
You guys are doing
Pillsbury
Weird,
4 Microsoft
Some of the reasons why Roku
In addition to
Increase transparency in trust that it provides
Is that
Switch crossplay
Runtime runs on mobile versions of Linux
Windows iot
As customers wanted to go to
Platforms
We want to enable them
How to do that and so open-sourcing and then managing those concert
King bed
You know each customer has a slightly
We different requirements
Quite frankly we don't want to be the bottom
The edges of Jerry Hot Topic right now
And so we want to
20 able them to bring their best work as well be able to contribute
Azure sphere
Microsoft is still
Scary clown
In the sense that
You call the stuff not necessarily but
It needs to be able to
Call back to the cloud to get security updates to maybe
Lincoln with AI Trading
Etc
In your world you
A way for things to run
Completely Cloud into
Or how do you hand
Kill those things with
Yes absolutely
Just last week
We announced that we are bringing
Azure iot Hub to Azure stack
Which can run Inspire Leon promises
Disconnect
Super Masher
You can still work with Azure iot Edge
So within a box
Adapter stack
Connect
Did you
Intelligence
Security service
Right now is running in
And then we'll have to talk about that as well
The reason why we're running in an hour
All of the in
Imports worldwide
And so as we see threats emerging in one part of the world
We can get ahead of that
And in that kind of a
Me and Louis ever be Cloud free
Not that I necessarily want that
Let's talk about.
Because that you had a couple
Cool video demo
Where do you see video
Enterprise
Industrial
What are the reasons why we show
Video
Particular video + AI
Because in a lot of ways
Video and AI
Can produce the ultimate sin
Can provide sensors that can sense things
So if you think about us traditional sense
Temperature humidity and vibration
When you're looking at things like
Pipes
There's no sense
But me I running over video
There are
Sensors
Use today to me
Yes and if your
Monitoring
You know hundreds of thousands
Miles
It could be impractical
Athletes that large versus having
I'm bored bright a very powerful sensor
Capability
If I change that
I accepted
Worldview and it does feel very compelling
Where do you think that's cool
Because I sat there and I watched like if I'm in a city
Las Vegas and I noticed the street lights have
Rediff
Cameras
When was Flex
Parking no one was in a different angle
Police station
Simon Magic
Police cameras everywhere
And all of that begin with so
Go all in on video
The misperception that we're going all-in on
I do think that it's another tool on the toolbox
But in this example that you bring up because
Is your imagine of proliferation of the
Cameras
String that video to Some central location weather for the cloud
Really impractical
Instead I'll take the park
Example of this
The police camera
They might be watching
Super Speeders
Right
Short clip + the license plate
As opposed to
Stream videos
To the cloud
So it's another example of processing on the edge
You guys actually do
Yes brain wave
So okay y'all
They're using fpga switch
Programmable chip
The best way to think about it
And I feel like the edge
The Edge is actually still
Powerful
Sensor
But you're putting this thing at the Gateway
Unless you figure out what kind of workload
This device is going
Need to do
4.
Machine learning
And
Program your chip
Is optimize the hardware
Specific
A little bit about the problem
What's that
Especially running on the edge
So you think about running
High scale in Princeton NJ
Recognizing some patterns and complex signal
If that's running in software
That's running
What's lower than it is
Nfpga chapter
Interesting because they're basically programmable chips
And so I can program them
Optimize
And so what you're seeing as 2 is to
Secret support
Machine learning in the cloud Target
These brainwave chips on the edge going to be able to bring down not just the programming for those chips
Programming
It makes these Edge devices
General
And so today I might be recognizing license plates
But I can
What I think is really
Cool is you actually are working
Patni Reg
If you guys
Not enough
Pga's but optimizing
Recognition
At the super super powers the power sipping it
We call it Big Little Lies
Keeping simple
Skinnyish probably doesn't
We'll figure this out
Send me an email if you have
Have a great idea
All right
When is a little nerdy but bear with us cuz this is the way the world's going
You're doing iot
Do you really actually
Yes all right
Go into
Why you guys
Yes
When we were looking at our
Egg strategy
2 years ago
It became clear
That
Why the biggest innovation
Computing was going to be workload portability
And at the same time iot was happy
What's happening
Full swing in the cloud
And so
And containers are great needs affordability as well and
Cloud
Fuse containers
Affordability
Anal containers
I should have defined the term
Are you guys
Little Blobs of it
Infrastructure that you can
Food places that run
Code that you need so I can take all the libraries every
You need an idea is
Basically everything you need in this container that contains the storage the
Compute
Is it
You're basically
Kirby copy
You're spitting up in one place or another
So that's what
We're seeing a lot of things
I'm actually one of the craziest things I'm seeing is a lot of
Container platform
Study Edge
Which
Okay why not
And talk about what makes you good for this
What is it just portability why does that matter
Is portability
Speed
Conceptually you can think it's not entirely correct conceptually can think
Container is a very very small
In fact it is
Back at the delta
A very small difference of
A base level operating system
And so it enables massive portability
Because they're very small quick and copy over networks and
Things like that
As we were designing our Edge platform
Status portability
The other reason why
Is because there's already an open ecosystem of things that run
And we wanted to make those available on the edges well Susan example
If I'm a developer and I'm very fond of
Nosql for
Flanders Rd
Container and Docker hub for it
Wait up my device and wagon
And so we love.
She reproached
Is it was very
Open approach
Because all those things already exist in the open
Amazing pools people are already
Wheels
So you guys
Goodwin little deeper y'all
Orchestration layer
Containers
So what
The heck
Is a verb
Virtual
So for a little context
We recently announced
Kubernetes support for hire
Which might seem like
A little bit of an announcement
Explanation
Annex devices
Taking your Raspberry Pi
Kubernetes cluster is typically spanning
In the cloud running very powerful work
You know hundred thousand
10 mm
So we done
Is the weight
Kubernetes work
Places that
It's placed with series of what's all kubernetes node
And working with the community
Which uses topic
Concept
Virtual node
And so in my kubernetes cluster I can only have nodes that are bound to Virtual machines that I can
Course placement
But I can also have
This virtual kubelet
And we just introduced
Just one call.
Iot Edge virtual provider
And the way it works is it runs in the cloud
And then anytime in kubernetes
That
Kubernetes deployment which has a virtual coupon
AT&T provider
If you push a container
Instead of placing it on a VM
We redirect it down to an iot edge device
Sneaky sneaky
Okay
It's what effect would that does it
You now have a kubernetes
Posture
This pants cloud and Edge
And deploy workloads across both at the same time
Kubernetes
Comes your OS
The cloud and orchestrator for the cloud of the edge
She's very excited
Ennis gets into this
I've been evolving with analysts and smart people like yourself here
Which is weird
Going for the
SeaWorld we're going to have the cloud
You're going to have
Snapchat
BH
Iot devices
And
What you found with
The virtual
Couplets
Is awaited
How to spend that all
Wrap it all
New York loud
Yep Edgewood can run these
Containers cloud
Devices which really purpose-built connected to sensor
Things like that so
We see the kubernetes cluster spanning cloud and Edge but then being able to
After being able to work
With iot
Like I said
There are light bulbs now that run docker
There are some of those yet
So okay
You're hoping to hear
You are use cases and I feel like you and I have talked in the past about Rockwell
Hershey's
There is
Continuing issue
In the business space
And then nothing
Amber goes very far
So what are
Are you guys seeing
How are you adapting to
Appliance getting stuck
So I sang isn't iot causes
What were talking about that
The digital part is super easy at the
It's the transformation part and so something that we've been doing recently
With customers
Inwood Park
Is that we have
About how I odoo
How to impact your
For example there are now very clear best practice
Rite-Way tool
What's the best way to
Start and build upon it
What are some of the pitfalls
What are some of the things that have going
I require like as you get into
Business models like service model
Where some of those breasts practice especially if you work organization that's not from
Those are awesome
That will delineate
A company having a
Pilot
And a production
It's not the technology
It's the people
OKC
He's online so I will
Link to them
I am sure all of you
Would like to eat
Thank you so much
The pleasure's all the station that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more IO
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Week