Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel and we have
A very fun show for you today so get your credit cards out
And your gift list
Ready because
We are talking about 16
17 items
That we think
You should think about buying
For you or others
This year we're also going to be doing
Quick little newspaper
Basically
Two things on it
Since you can find out what those are
And we'll have a message from
Armour sponsor Spark
Cognition and will answer a listener
So
Let us get on with the show
But first
A message from one of our sponsors
Home isn't just a place it's a feeling the feeling that you're safe to enjoy the things that matter most
Weather for your home and Business ATT helps keep you safe so you can feel protected wherever you are introducing the eight
ADT Security starter kit everything you need to get started with ADT Pulse and putting a camera professionally install
Only $49 visit att.com podcast today to learn more
Requires 36-month monitoring contract installation and activation fees apply easy pay require
Certain markets are excluded licenses available at att.com Florida a through F 0
00 1121 Louisiana F-16
Okay
I am so excited because
Almost
This is going to be
Before the holiday so if you're listening happy
Turkey
In the US
Later on for you guys in
Happy to giving
Thanksgiving
I think we did
Yes October
Starting November I don't even know
I'm sorry Canada
And for the rest of the world that may or may not celebrate Thanksgiving
I'm actually sorry to
Because
Who doesn't love a day where you just sitting
Okay
We
Are going to zoom through the news
Because there's really very little of it so far
The biggest news is
The Apple homepod
Which is Apple's answer to the Amazon Echo and Google home
Has been delayed
This is surprise you Kevin
It does surprise me it delayed
Yes it does
It's a price because they showed this off several several months ago they even had units working units for the press to listen to
Do you understand that software
One piece of it that maybe they need to work on still
Siri they certainly need to work out of my pay
Opinion and they said he'll be out by the holidays and now it's not coming out until early 2018 I don't think it's like a supplier
Supply chain issue a parts issue anything custom internal and Hardware
I guess it is software and maybe
Like I'm hoping there was still working on making Siri smarter
I was going to say I bet it's a Siri issue
I bet it's also
Okay so
Part of me that is so frustrated with apple in their smart home efforts and
Continually
Oh we're good at home kit
This announcement of homekit and then this gradual like
Roll out of services and then this retrenchment with
Okay
Maybe don't need a search chip
After a bunch of
Companies
Went out and did that
So that's all very frustrating
What I will say though
Is
So I didn't find this surprising
At all because Apple his
Consistently
Pushed forward with his incomplete version of
What it thinks
The smart home show
And
It feels to me that it
Not only does it not really have a Clear Vision
I think it's also getting stuck with its privacy
And
Kind of the way that it's segmented its
Entire ecosystem
So I think we see that with a couple things I think we see it with
You know it's decision to change out
Desertification chip-in make
It software authentication base
I think we're going to see
It with the problems with Siri we've seen so far
So I think what's Happening Here is probably apples trying really hard to
Figure out how to push forward in the Smart Home
The way it is historically push forward
In the mobile ecosystem and I think it's kind of realizing that it doesn't
Always work
And I don't disagree with anything you said
Especially at a high-level I think
The series is going to be in the homepod it's going to be the same Siri that exist today in a phone to control things and they already
So again
Noah
No argument there it's not great but
And maybe that's why they haven't they realized
Of course I realize that Siri is not
The best experience for users I have to
Thanks ad
But they realize when you put that in a
You're trying to conquer a new ecosystem with
The terrible AI witch
In some ways might need that Apple realizes that the AI is but
For the Smart Home
I don't know I could be I am frustrated with Apple
Because it kind of jerks around
What's the industry in Industry adoption
In a lot of ways a lot of people
Are holding off on the smart home to get homekit certified stuff
And
Right now if you're going all-in at home kit you don't have
Kind of a democratic
Accessible way to control your
Your home
You know that isn't based off the phone and I think that's
Really is stumbling block
See that's true I mean a lot of homekit devices obviously will work with other hugs as well and that's
That's why I don't think it's hurt the market too much but I don't disagree they move markets and
This is not helping in general
Even their partner
Are freshmen
I cannot tell you how many times I have
Sad
About that
If you were hoping to get that for the holidays
You can just now
Series taking the holidays off
There you go alright so we have a correction to me
Because last week
We got a call
And I feel terrible that I answered this run
This is why you should play with their gadgets from
More than a day before Easter
Bad Stacy
Wise
$20 Home Security
That we talked about
I said that you didn't send stuff to the cloud
That is because I was not
Testing it
At first with
Motion detection
I was just texting you
Playing with it as a live camera cuz I tend to play with things minimal features first and then build up
To all of them but when you build up
Can you add motion detection all your data is sent
The cloud so we did say that it did not send things
But it does
So that's really important to know
You can save everything to an SD card
That is all still true
And if you don't want to send anything
I think the cloud I did talk to one of the founders of the company and she said that if you don't use the motion detection
Then basically everything candy store to your device which is effectively what I was doing
It's interesting that they can't do the motion detection on device admin
Are they using
The cloud to do processing or the video up to the cloud in store
Now there is no storage fee for
So
It's actually really interesting
Company I talk to the founders
And
Sunset from a company in China so the camera Hardware is licensed
Company of China
But the software they did themselves and their whole model is these are people from Amazon their model is to
Basically build the cheapest products they can
And then Branch out and other stuff
They're like it's Amazon metal great customer service at a low low price
The merchants
Solo margins to them
Low-cost to you
But presumably this she says it's the same Hardware that's inside the nest I
Like really
And they do have
The money
They've said they built in the capability obviously
Store your videos so just store the motion capture
Videos
And not
Which really motion-capture isn't going to take up gigs and get to space
That's right you're not doing everything
But still
I was really intrigued by this cuz
You know that this is just the same gear Hardware that's inside the nest cam
When a nest cam sells for
Joshua
Ridiculous
After 1:30 I nest
Pretty astonishing
So yeah just Kim basic Nest cam two hundred bucks
So this is
A tenth of the price
Very audacious
Product
Very nice
Cell
That is our correction
But
We're going to keep talking about it because
Oh I we should have Jingle Bells
I don't have any
Sorry
Where's my any one of those like radio DJ
Sound machine
Need a soundboard
You're welcome
This is our Internet of Things podcast 2017
Holiday gift
Guide
So we
For our holiday gift guide everything on it we have tested unless we tell you otherwise we will be very
Clear because we don't want to send you
Home with a crummy product
We also try to do different things each year so this is why you won't see my old favorites like neutrons are Hue Lights
It's which we all
Can we talk about all the time
Play we like them
We don't have a single bulb on here traditional bow
We don't
Yeah that's a big
Departure for us
So
We
Have broken up into categories
Set wake up a smart home
We've got
Kids stuff
We are stocking stuffers
And we have
Crazy expensive
Yes
Because
What's not
Why not
Let's get this party started with the reason you probably listen to the show which is smart home stuff
My first pick is
The wyze cam
Which is wyze
It is $20 this is the one we just talked about
And
Gosh
You can actually use it as a
It is very small
There's a fully-functioning security camera it works really well
I bought one a couple
Weeks ago it arrived
Gosh
I feel like I could just like set this up any
And it's one of the few that you could
In-store on the MicroSD card
Yes you can store your data on the MicroSD card it will go to the cloud though
And
What else
About it
It's got everything it's got HD it's got night vision
It's got
Two-way audio
It's cut
Music detection
It's one of the few though it doesn't yet work with any of existing smart home hubs or does it
It does not work with any smart home hubs now I will say that when I talked to the founders they were like
Okay honestly
Not everybody has a hug.
So this is actually it you know cuz a lot of them would
Rick Larsen
Kevin Grayson so that's fine
Yeah so if you are like
What's a smart home security stuff people are all worried about her maybe are going out of town and you want to have a camera you just keep in the drawer and you just
Throw up when you know
Leaving
Twenty bucks wyzecam
Check it out
Okay
Speaking of cameras
We got a lot of requests for the outdoor camp
And
My favorite
Floor bang for your buck good price is the Arlo Pro Outdoor
Now
There are three versions of the Arlo camera
There is a
Wireless
Outdoor camera
Has moral batteries don't get that it's expensive compared to the pro which is what we recommend
And that is it
Wireless
Outdoor camera
It's rechargeable
Mikasa by a little extra
Sure thing if you wanted to slide it in
And in charge
I like this
It is again motion detection activated
You can arm it when you leave and you'll get all these notifications
People come in and out
I think it's a great product
These but you still have a rechargeable battery so there's no hard wiring so it's simple to install
I suppose use these indoors if you need to but there
Certainly rated to be used Outdoors as well
Yes
And I've had my
In those places
They are lovely
They do have a pro to version
It is more expensive and has a siren and that's designed act as a moor
Featured security system
I believe that one does 1080p video where is the one we're recommending is
720P
I don't really think that's a huge deal breaker by any means
You know
This is if you just want to see what
Exactly exactly
Mine actually don't
I don't have them up most of the time I throw them up when I go out of town or when I have kids on my roof then I set them up
On the roof so weak
You can keep an eye on them
I actually work with a lot of
What devices we went through and we thought about
Which cameras work with the most
Thanks The Nest also work with a lot of things but we didn't like them mostly because their Hardware
Tired so
You have to have an outlet
Okay moving on to the smart speaker sex
Yeah we actually have
2 in looks plain why I'll take the first one then stay so you can
Take the second one
If you're all in on Amazon's platform for a digital assistant
Or you would like a choice in the future
I wish dental assistant to use I would recommend wholeheartedly the Sonos one which is
Pretty much a brand new products
Obviously Sonos has been around smart speakers for a long time they pretty much pioneered multi-room audio
Wireless multi-room audio in the house and
This works with just about every music
Streaming service known to man it's ridiculous how much support it has
Waiters work with
Amazon voice services
Today and Sonos is going to be adding Google Assistant support in 2018
So it's nice because you don't make a choice
These are $199 each the sound quality is outstanding better than any of the other Smart Homes
Speakers that I've tried which are mostly the smaller size ones like your
Echo dots
Google mini and so on even the regular Echo and the Google home
This is better sounding than that so for 199
Don't know if I have any Black Friday deals on this cuz it's so new of a product but you know what
I would pay full price have one for this
But if you are looking for a bull
And you maybe you're like
My other smart speaker recommendation is the Google home
This is great if you are all in on Google
Like me
Google file
But even a thing
It's also the better of the
You're looking at Google vs madam
Google is actually smarter and
I have
Doubled up in my house and I'm finding that I'm using Google for more and more things like just last night I added
To my calendar
And it just happened it was
Awesome
You know those kind of things are starting to be
They just
Seamless so it's pretty cool it works
The Google home now last year we didn't recommend it because it didn't work with this many smart home devices
What does
It works with a lot of the big one
It doesn't work with everything
But it does work with a lot of the Philips Hue the SmartThings the wing
Like 72
Devices so
Lots of toys
And the Black Friday deals are looking like
You could get one of these
499 bucks
So
Go on in that's a good price and I waited to buy mine until I got all the decorations with the smarthome bits
So I agree we was not worth the recommendation last year but it's really good
Okay so
Google home if you like it
If you're looking for a hug though
Kevin
Yeah people know I have a soft spot for this hug
Because I purchased the first edition of it but now they have a second edition so I would recommend
Especially because it's on sale for the holidays
The wink Hub 2
Find it for about 69 bucks right now
I work so just about every device I can think of because it's got all the right radios inside it's got
Phi Phi Scott Bluetooth and Scott
Cindy it's got Z-Wave
So
I've purchased my own
Very happy with it the second generation was well worth the upgrade because there's more memory inside more storage of faster processor
There's much less lag when I say
To a Google home or some other device turn this light on it just happens quickly now so
Very very happy with the wink Hub 2
And I would say that if you know what those radios are in your interest in this
Can you somehow still don't have a hub
I would say do this over the Amazon Echo Plus
Cell which is
Advertising itself as a smart home hub but
Isn't it supposed to be
There's one more Hub / media / everything
Yeah I kind of feel funny putting this in here
But
I have to recommend something that I bought and use everyday it's the Nvidia Shield TV
You're probably saying why is he recommending an Android TV
Boxwell
Couple recent one it's on sale for $150 or $107 with the actual game controller
And that way you can play Android games obviously runs Android apps
It's Android TV as well it's got Google Assistant built in
So you can use either the remote switch has a microphone or the game controller which has a microphone and speak to Google Assistant
At any time when using the TV
Indeed it will also be adding little microphones
That you can plug in around your house
And that will communicate to Google Assistant as well those are not out yet
I have not used them yet but
This is one reason I bought the shield TV
But on top of that
Recently Samsung being selling the SmartThings link
For $40
I actually snag one for $10 on sale I don't know what the sale prices are going to be over the holidays
But even for $40 what it is
Is a USB stick that you plug into the back of the Nvidia Shield TV
And it basically has a SmartThings software and add zigbee radio to the Nvidia Shield TV so now
Essentially turn your set-top box
Into
A SmartThings Hub as well so you kind of get it
Two-for-one special
Crate
Video streamer 4K
HDR I can handle anything
And then you get the smart home hub bits as well
Got it
Cities next to devices are rounding out our Smart Home
And that is the
Are the smart thermostat we are picking for the ecobee
Wishes
The ecobee thermostat has all the fun features you know and love and
Makeupplus the sensor
Plus
It's gotten anime inside so you
You can talk to it
Have things happen and it's only $200 on Amazon
Which is a pretty good price
And it does work with homekit as well so you don't have to
You can use it in an iOS alarm
And then
Wi-Fi mesh networks are
Smoking hot again this year and
We're torn
We're just going to be our
We can recommend to that's fine
All right
I will unequivocally recommend a mesh Network
For anyone who's going to get in to
So
Our two favorite
Chris Kevin's is
It's the Google Wi-Fi
And that's because
3 pack only cost
289 at full price I'm sure there will be some on sale in the coming weeks and it's just drop dead simple it works really real
Well I know some reviews said that other
Products had better Ranger better throughput but
Everybody I know and
I bought my own 3 pack everybody I know says it's
Plenty good it may not have the advanced features of some other mesh network products but
Again simple setup
Anybody can set it up and it just works
And I am going to is expensive
Remind me to do my Eero Plus
And this is the second generation Eros
It's got one
Main brain
Euro and then it has to beacons and beacons also double as Night Lights this will cover up
Scubbers my house just fine
And that is 399
Love these things
So yeah if you have a 1 to 2 bedroom home
You can probably get away with a $300 set
Supposed to $400 set
And then it also offers a lot of really good
Kind of add-on features
Trolls Plus
If you want to spend money
An additional $10 a month gets you
Parental safety kind of features
And a security service
Those are mesh Wi-Fi
So before we continue on with our gift list let's take
A moment for a word from our sponsor we are taking a break from the podcast
Message from this week sponsor sponsor is sparkcognition and I've got
Shuja was general manager of the industrial internet-of-things effort
To talk about
Sparkcognition
Respond spark ignition is an AI company and you guys are really working to help
Industrial iot companies improve their efficiency
And improve their
Safety
Is correct we are you
Bringing together a lot of different
Capabilities within order
Intelligence
Data analytics app
B1
Caviar dressing use cases such as predicted failure
All catastrophic events
And also automating a lot of the prophecies
Industrial world looking at security data Within These industrial environments to make sure that nobody should ever
What is happening
So data analytics is a big piece of it
But we are bringing different pieces of artificial intelligence to make that analysis and make that the application
Tomorrow bus
Thinking tactically
Do you have an example of maybe one of your clients and how they used AI to change their
Business absolutely Flowserve
Which is the largest
Pump manufacturer
In the US is one of her clients
Take a predictive failure in a
Bump a few hours in advance
The applied are algorithms
And now they can extend
Forewarning of a pump failure by 6
Today's status fundamentally change their business
They can sell prediction of the service which is really supercharged aftermarket business
What are some of the critical steps to ensuring a successful implementation
The key to successful implementation would be to think big
Strategically and act
Practically
What that means
Addressing the big picture problems concerning The Bold and the c-suite intend addressing the business outcomes
Building a good Roi story
AI at the end of the day is a technology it should be dyed
Close liquor.
Is outcome the second thing that very important is the people Aster Cafe because it's new technology
And fix unproven technology or a lot of
The client's feet got to
Engage the people and get to buy and so they don't feel nervous about it and they start trusting the technology that it can
Delivers the business outcomes that are looking for
The biggest risk that I seen
And people jumping
To conclusions about what the technology can do
The dog building the right foundation
Safari examples
The organizational structure could be something that is
It's not supportive of an AI implementation
It could be the lack of data or available data within the ideal environment to be able to support some of the artificial intelligence
Algorithm soap between the organizational structure and people
And the
Technical infrastructure needed to deliver a i Solutions
The two big things that I've seen
Text major risk
And where can we find out more
To find out more
Visit sparkcognition
Dot-com
Now what is go beyond the smart home into
For children I'm going to do both of these cuz I have my daughter playing with some of the stuff so first off for kids
Two are probably between the ages of
If I don't know 5 and 8
Diving
Maybe the Kano motion
Cat this is $30 all this is it's a little tiny sensor you can plug into
Computer and
You wave your hand over it and things happen
So your kid can
Beatbox vacant like
Use it to control different
Games and they also
As everybody loves to do as a parent
Can use it to teacher
Decode style tell you
When my daughter saw the learn-to-code feature shoes
I want this again
She's a little over it
But it's so easy to use I made her set everything up she was totally fine my daughter is 11
So she's a little out of the age
But she said it was fun
So
Fun little present you can get for a kid
The other is
For the older set and that is the littlebits R2D2 Droid inventor kit
For a hundred bucks
And I have not tried this
So this is one of those that we
We have not tried
But I have use a little bit stuff extensively
And it's
Awesome
It's well put together
My daughter loves her Lil
And so
What does kit is is you build a little R2D2
So cute
And
You get all these parts
An app that goes with it and you basically
Build it I don't know how to say that you build the
Little Droid
And then you learn how to use all these other
Parts so
I kind of want this to get a little 12-inch artoo-detoo is got a Servo control of a DC motor proximity sensor
A lot of fun with us
It's a little nicer
We've had the little bit
Like they make a kit
It has all of this stuff in
And you can buy that use that but it's not sometimes for kids without a project idea
This is nice because it gives them something to build for
But then they can always use these parts with the other little bit stuff and
How to start building their own stuff after
Switches
QR
Cute
OtterBox
Verisign kid tested mom
Who used to say that
I forget but I
I can remember the commercial that I've heard it a gazillion times
You did not come up with that Stacy
All right to the stocking stuffer
Well you cannot go wrong with a Bluetooth tracking device in my opinion I mean these things are like the size of a roughly a quarter quarter
Dollar and
You can attach them to bags you can attach them to weave hatching the keys actually attached one to my mailbox key so that
Play we all know where the mailbox key is cuz
Somebody in and I won't name names but I usually leave it in my
Pants pocket after getting the mail and then nobody can get the mail
So I'm going to recommend the tracker
Pixel
Which is the newer model the old Bravo as I think
Tumi be discontinued but the pixels
Are now the latest model
You can listen to make noise using your phone so that way you can find whatever you're attached to
They're speaking the Bluetooth in your phone to get closer and closer to them so you don't lose anything
Right now looks like they're on sale 5 pack and be found
4999 so 10 bucks
Apopka attach to whatever it is that you need to keep track of
You got a Bluetooth tracker makes it easy to find whatever you need
Got it okay
Now here's my controversial pic
I know that you know that I do not own this
I have played with it
In the beta store
And I will also say that I
Can't say it cuz my husband listens
Cast but I might get this
So this is the floss time
This is a $40 device
Granted
It's a little silly
This is for people like me who don't floss as religiously as they should
It is a
Pretty looking device that you stick on your mirror and basically every night it looks at you and it gives you an LED :-) or
Turn LED sad faces smiley faces if you pull out the floss and presumably floss your teeth
And is this something that would motivate me to floss my teeth
It actually proud
I would want to smile at me
Also I would be like somewhere there's a server that says oh my God she never fought this
Validation
Yeah I don't
Most of my things
What's flossing
You know if you have kids you can get for them and
They have little
Snap-on covers the earth
I like frogs and stuff
Never cute
That you do have to buy a special
Show results
So is this
Smokin hot deals
Is this a really interesting device
Yeah
40 bucks
And
Stocking stuffer is for the smart home Aficionado in your
Who is likes to touched
Mike's buttons
Which totally describes me
So this is the fibaro Z-Wave button
It comes in eight different colors
They are
Gorgeous I love you sexy
It has six scenes that you
You can set up
And it's
You set up a scene it's triggered by different Taps so 1 tap 2 taps
Set an alarm for
I don't have any
It's a fight app setup on
Cuz that's a lot of tapping
I love to sing
It's pretty it's out of my
Set a table by my couch and I just
Monitor wall if you want it does only
It only works with smart
Or if you want to use like for Barros hubs you need a hub that will support all of the
Fibaro features in right now
Link does not to
SmartThings
Only
Does it work with if this then that or no
It will work with this
It works with them
But only three
Gotcha
No k
Oh by the way
This is news
Gift guide
Pek
Your room is now
Work with it
Yeah
Give a cat a ride around the house
Tops on
All right in
Finally
My favorite cat
What About Bob
Okay so here's my first crazy expensive pic
It's almost like a light bulb but it's not
It's the nanoleaf Aurora
Rhythm
This
Is an awesome product that one of my friends house and I played
It for like an hour and I love it
It is $230 for the starter kit it is both homekit and
Madam a enabled
Plus there's an app
And
It what are these are these like six triangles that are connected to the internet
Colors
You
Can set them up in a pattern so it's like artwork
Aura night light
It's brighter than a night light but it's pretty non-functional
It's just cool
Is this how you spell
Spotted it dances to music
That's the Rhythm
This pretty sweet
And you can control it control base features with
So I like this
The really neat looking like.
I don't like you said their triangular and then
You get these little connectors and you just
Daisy chain them together in any pattern that you want and then
Let me see you can constantly change the light panel in your house it's kind of
It's just like a really in
Interesting
Transport up to 30
Panels on one
A lot
Yeah
I get the duty of explaining why something cost $1,500 is
On our list
The June oven I know we've talked about it so many times you had that you had
Because Stacy bought hers then
She told me about it I'm like maybe I'll try this for my wife
My wife loves it and we use it every single day
So if on the off chance you haven't heard about it the June oven is a Smart Oven
It looks like a
Big toaster oven
Not something to put a 20lb turkey in
But for most other things it's perfectly fine I've got ceramic heating element it's got a
Built-in camera inside the oven
It runs on Android it's got a nice really nice looking touch screen panel to
Put any presets in or change the temperature or set the timer it even now works with Madam a so I know
SA
Pay meteme preheat the June oven for me and I wanted to stunt it it's great
Really interesting in that they have a food database so when it recognizes the food that you put in
It literally knows how long to cook it and it tells you either you're on your smartphone or on my Apple watch reasonable
The food is done it just
I have not been able to cook something poorly with a just Cooks
Perfect for us every single time and recently I love that they've added new recipes
They will walk you through how to make something and then you just put in the oven and boom it's done
So couldn't recommend it enough for use it every single day
My husband even
Hey are you going to put the June on this list
As like
Okay good
So the non-smartphone loving people in our lives
It is pricey
The crazy expensive
Finally in the crazy expensive
SeaTac
Throw this out here cuz I've wanted one for like a year
You're in a half
Almost two years actually
Because I first saw that CSN
So
Almost two years the cleverpet
This is a $300
Connected
Toys for your
Dog
It's like Simple Simon
To treat dispensing Simple Simon
4 less than 20
4 hours
I'm recommending it because I've already had two
Your dog may not like
This is kind of a crazy
Purchase but I put it on here because
ICarly
It's kind of Awesome
So
You know if your dog goes for it I could see them really going
For it and it it's so far entertain my dog
It's got like three lights built-ins as you said Simple Simon and the Dogwood n Tryon
Hit the Light
You're the lights get the food
The end goal is the lights will go off in a pattern
And your dog will mimic that pattern to
Get a treat dispenser
Do it nice
He's at the stage where it will
Hit
The light
To get the tree
Again we are only
Flowers in
So
It seems dirty
My dog has already attacked it
I want the treats
I'm like forget the lights
Mrs. Japan
So there you go
Set fire to 3
$300
You could do worse
Already
That
That is our gift
Playlist
We got our cheapest thing at 2
Think about boats
Discounts for the
Trackers
All the way up to 1500
Hope you guys enjoy
Your holiday
Your Black Friday shopping
And now
We should go answer a question
From our Internet of Things
Podcast hotline
Git podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic locks Schlage electronic locks can make life
So much easier
No more keeping track of extra house keys each member of your family can have their own Acts
Access code
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
Hi Stacy and Kevin
This is Aaron from Wilberforce Ontario Canada
Do you have any recommendations
4 ways to control outdoor Christmas lights
Is there anything capable of running a high-wattage deicing cable
We got three
The school last night here
Definitely in need
Aaron
What a really appropriate question right ahead of the holidays
And
We can only answer half
Because while I am very familiar with outdoor modules and
Light control
Living in Texas I have no sense
I didn't even know you could actually put things on your
I got to get rid of that ice and snow in Canada
Nothing
Popped out at
I think so if anyone knows
And lives in the great Frozen North
And has an automated or connected solution to
Heating cables on roofs hey info at iot podcast. Calm and we will share that
So question
Many people will benefit from
Outdoor holiday lighting
And how to make it smart
I have
Options
The first is what I have used for the last
Which is the Jasco Z-Wave
On off outdoor module
He's our big ugly and
Again might have been working for three years so there
According to your number for in
I just keep buying more
I keep adding more lights
Please work with
SmartThings with wink
With any hub
Speaks Z-Wave so that's where all of you guys who have that capability
If you don't
There are now
Wonderful new options
That I have not
But
So I would recommend these are all in the same price range
The Z-Wave ones are 35 they get more expensive actually
Closer to Holiday
You might pay as much as
But I also see in these are
Well rated
The G by outdoor WiFi plugs that work with Madam
And with an app
I would recommend an app go mad at me all the way
Wifi-enabled
Switches they have to
They are also
Outdoor rated make sure you use outdoor-rated ones though case cuz you don't want to mess around
Not appropriate
Covers for your lights cuz if they're GFI they're going to go off in
Miss out on your holiday lighting
So the options on the Wi-Fi front
IHome also makes a Wi-Fi one for 40 bucks that only has one Outlet
Which may or may not
Be fine for you and again Wifi works
Google Assistant
And Siri voice
Which means it has a
For the home
People I devices also make
An outdoor
Module
It is $70 usually
It's between 60 and $75 to pen
It has two outlets so if that's something you could take advantage of its basically like
If you've got two right next to each other you might as well just get that one
And you
Consolidating
The same price
Those are your options for outdoor lighting
My other Pro tip
For you
Is
Instead of doing if you got a mixed-media like you've got a bunch of different options like in Dora
Maybe switches made for
From somebody else put it all through voice can
Sedgwick
Google Assistant
Spell routine
Build the scene through Amazon a
Are do it with homekit so you can just
Activate
Because if your house is anything like mine what it is
Will end up with this like I'll just tell
I have seven
Or a
I think I have eight
Christmas light
All play
So I just group them all on
And then I'm like
Madam
Turn on
Christmas
And that poop everything comes out
And if you're crazy like me you can also do
Matinee
Turn on Christmas Eve which for me is like
Quieter setting
So it's
Like a little less festive
Pure lights just for Christmas Eve
That is my advice to you
Again heating information
If you know any things
A lot of people
And if you guys have
Have a question
Kevin what is that
That number is 512
To 4
Our gift guide our news
Are turkey day extravaganza
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast remember if you want more iot news
Please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com thanks for listening and we'll see
See you next week