Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higgins
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Show for you today
As always we got until oh my God are they getting out of the iot
We got arm
Patent licensing fee
Fuse for a new program
A new ring doorbell
An acquisition in the smart home space that
Caillou were talking about
New lights from hue
They're pricey as heck
And
Tesla got a new
Do head
Program
Plus
Some Amazon news because it's not a week without Amazon
After that we have a message from our sponsor TE Connectivity and then
An awesome guess Paul Brody who is a principal at NY
And
He is going to talk about using blockchain to Build a Better World and better IO.
Tea business mod
Now
Let's go to work
From another one of our sponsors
Affiliated monitoring
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about Affiliated monitoring
In response to a trigger from any connected device Affiliated to professionally trained live agents can follow
Protocol and reach out to your customers their loved ones and local emergency services Affiliated works with
Hundreds of smart home security help and other iot businesses visit affiliated.
Iot to read a case study on how they helped a connected car startup turn an idea into a thrive
Having business with a 100 million dollar exit that's Affiliated. Com
Flash IOD
Alright Kevin
Here we go
Chips Ahoy
Laxative news that's okay
So
It was Intel
They're going to discontinue their
Jewel
Edison and Galileo product
And for those big eyes were like what
Edison was there additional May
Bored Galileo was
Another one
And Jewel with the really
Anyone that you
No word on what's going to happen to that chip I did ask
Until did confirm that all of these products
Are being disc
Set me a very nun
Exciting States
Things
Theme statement as it stands
AR
Iot remains an important
And we are committed to
To the iot market segment
Access analyze and share data
These include retail industrial automotive and video
All right
I would expect them to say that however however
That we should clarify all these
End-of-life by
The end of this calendar year from the mistaken
Yes
They are ended
This calendar year
Yunnan discounts
You might see some discounts that put it in the right so the challenge here
In my
My humble
Is that
Intel put a lot of money into these boards that you can actually fun to that TV show the Great
Movie show
And
These boards were
Expensive
By comparison by comparison to things like the raspberry
Reply
Yep still because Galileo when it first came out with like $70
And then the version 2
Was $80
Yeah I'm in the other the competing boards
10 to go down in price while adding features and such
That's one issue but I suspect you're going to raise that but I think it's the second issue in a minute
Man they're hot
Bingo we have a winner
I was at a Maker Faire and you know
Of course I walked over to that
Intel Edison
Because it was Giant
So much marketing
And
You know I was I was
Feeling these
Boards that we're running these projects
Holy mackerel
Very warm
In fairness I will give until credit that they have really scale down the power performance why
What are the past couple years with their chips
They do have many fanless design winds right now
With core M3 and such so
That's a given credit there but they've been behind the 8-ball so catching it
It's a constant catching up battle
And they got to figure out when to stop trying to catch up you know and that's what I guess they're doing on these boards
It's just not worth it to them right
Exactly
They also have this
Problem last year when they discontinued their wearables
The bassist
Purchase
It was basis was the name of the
I think was peaked Peak was the company they bought in 2014 which was making the basis watch it
One of the best
Health tracking watches
I would say at the time
They discontinue that they got out of wearables in one thing that you're going to notice about the categories they're still in retail and
Industrial Automotive in video
Those are
All categories
Exception of automotive
That are going to require
A gateway
Device switch
Can pack a lot of computing
Empower into
It's going to be plugged in
You have to worry about
I'm too hot and
They're going to analyze and share data which
Again is great
For the general
Computing that in
What does
So that's
Basically these are going to be computers
They're going to keep
Selling
Switch
But
In this world that were entering into
That's going to become a smaller in
And smaller
Segment
And they're also catching competition on all sides now on the server side on the automotive side
Where are those they're still actually in wearables is that they're there in the tag are connected watch
But not many other watches right now
It's just the competition know when I look at an Invidia or something like somebody like that but it's just intensified for men
Honestly
Coming out with a new service
You know I covered AMG for over a decade
Okay so I'm not going to like
I'm not going to count until out because AMD always know
Conciliating
Awesome designs
What you know
Snatching Victory from the
Also though in in this will give you some perspective alarm
Actually arm witch
Is a company that lets you license
Their design
4 tiny tiny low-power chip
Chips therein
Your phones
Wearables therefore
They even have some
Powerful ones
They're trying to put the
And they don't run is hot
Arm has expanded their design start
To include the arm cortex M3 processor
In addition to the cortex
In 04
If you guys are like what what is a really tiny
Tiny very very
Tips for where
But what this does is you don't have to pay a licensing
Fee to start tinkering and playing around with the design
This is really important for some of these markets where
Form factor
Matter so if you're designing a wearable
Being able to design your own SOC
Lets you
Hey
Reduce the surface area of
Have your bored but it also let
Lets you tweak
Like designs to
Consume as little
Power is pasta
You can do this
Right until what you can do all that design work without paying any money but then if if you do bring a product
To market after many generations for free so to speak
Then you would pay your licensing fees per product
Yeah it's kind of like getting hooked on drugs
I'll take your word for it
You'll pay for ever
Alright so
Couple things to note here that I thought were
When was
These process
Have shipped more than 20 billion units
He's a pain in the last couple years
With the internet
So
Ye into
Kevin you want to say
Talk about what some of these
The m0 is more it's not powering a computer or a phone or anything like that this is really for my crooked
Controllers
Atm3
Would be in something that I think everybody knows and that is the Apple A9 chip
Apple tweeted and they call it their M9 motion coprocessor so
I suspected him more than just like the black iPhones on such because you know iPads also use a chips and
So
I don't know how many
Devices have an A9 but I mean it's couple probably a couple hundred million right off the bat
I'm also Samsung's Exodus their 7420 processor which isn't some of their phones also uses
The M3 so those are just two simple examples of the scope and reach of this
Yes and
It's not just for wearables I should tell you this because arm gives his lovely example
Industrial control application
So a company called S3 group
Developed an army base
Custom SO3 for that use case and
Cuz they were allowed to
Mess around with
Hair Design
They reduced
The power requirements
By 70%
Custom parts
80%
And the board size
Spice 75
Which in that was for a valve controller for the oil and gas in
So
That's actually really
And it also gives
When you do a custom board that means
Harder for other companies to
Function
Competitive
Differentiator
So right
I know most of you guys especially if you're just here for the like doorbell review
Like I don't care but this is
I just noticed the Arduino due board
Due
I also has the cortex M3
At the it runs it runs in at MailChimp
For the soc but they integrated in cortex M3
Get your maker on
And then
If you like what you've done
You can start
Messing around
All right now that's a doorbell
Ring
There's actually two pieces of doorbell news
Ring has
A
New doorbell video doorbell 2
It's basically a little bit bigger than the lower end
Welders
It's 3 now
So the initial ring doorbell is still there it is notable because it is big
It is both wired and Battery powers
Either way
720p camera on that one that's one key difference
And then the
Ring Pro is a skinnier doorbell
Patio doors
Right it's it's $250 as opposed to 179 and that get you full HD and it's hardwired
Yes
So now we have this they're actually going to sell that for $200 Which is less than the
The big changes you can swap out
Your battery pack
Right so it's hardwired
Removable battery or rechargeable battery or recharge
And it has 1080
Corral if you were going to buy the older version
You might as well just
By this is
20 bucks more
Also
The ring
Pro which is the
$250 one
Is
Actually that
It's going to be home
So they either built ecert chip in there
Or
This is part of apples like
Cryptic remarks about making it easier to add
Products to hump
So I'm not sure what is going on
What happened this won't happen
Winter Shield
Harbor Gateway fire
That is a possibility that's one way to do it
Interesting
I'm leery my eyebrows up I know it already cannot see it but my eyebrows raised right now because
You come out with a new product and it's going to be homekit compatible
Well this is not the new product
Crow the existing
Well even so
That makes the case even more
Yeah
Unless there's a retrofit here just Papas little security shipping your doorbell now and you're okay compatible I don't think that's happening
No I don't think Apple wants a
William Security Agency
So if you have one
You know
Good news for next year
Also in doorbell news
This I'm just going to talk about briefly
Because
I have been testing for bells
For the longest time
And my doorbell transformer is not up to speed
So most homes come with a
18 volt
Doorbell
Between 16 and 24
My challenge was I was running to video doorbell
And experiencing some issues
So I upgraded my doorbell transformer
24-volt
And now
Working like a charm
So I'm going to tell you that if you are interested in these video doorbells
Check
Former
Especially if your admin
Warehouse a lot of them say 16.
And that's
Willie Morris
Probably better in the
Cuz I was I was having some
Real
Charging
And did you do the Transformer swap yourself electrician to come out
Located wiring
It was basically like while you're here
So it cost I think $35 plus the
Cost of the trance
So it was not expensive
It is something you
You could do yourself
YouTube there plenty of instructions online I just
The guy was there and
So that was
Just DIY project especially if you're experiencing troubles with your doorbell charging
And pulling up
Video really quickly that could
People to Wi-Fi but it might be
Our issue
So there you go
Let's talk about
Smartlab
Because we put this in the newsletter last week
But you didn't read that you don't know that
Yes a lot of people don't know the name smartlabs how much they do know insteon which has made
Iot Smart Home Products for years
I'm smart
Parent company of behind insteon and they also have a retail site called Smart Home
Which is where you can buy a lot of these insteon products so I use the many times before spending a great resource in a great site for
But you're right they have a new CEO Rob and I may get his name wrong willingness
He was the CEO of mideo systems that was later
Taking over by
Nokia's here group
But he left
Mario and his purchase smartlabs
Gets insteon and smart home has as part of that deal
Looks like he work with a private investment firm
Richmond Capital which invested 7.3 million dollars in smartlabs
Which is based in Irvine always has been but now willingness is looking to
Make
A second presents in Seattle
Previously were from Microsoft so I'm not surprised he's going to be in the Seattle market so
New owner and CEO for all of the
Insteon products
So maybe we'll see some new
Products are made
Radiosai I don't know new things from insteon
I don't know I mean I guess he saw I don't know if he has plans to you no bills out the product line or
Tikahtnu directions and are not so we'll have to see
I mean there's a lot of people still use insteon it was at this one of the first batch of products are used when setting up my smart home
Back in 2010
Before I'm getting
All the other fun stuff we have today so
What I liked about insteon was it was a lot of do-it-yourself and you could you could have control when you didn't have to have a server in the cloud
Carolina service and such so
Baby troll control over the system which was nice
Yay
Alright other little tiny bit of news
Hugh
Now makes a candle
C12
The Candelabra
Look for my piano
Pollo piano
Birthday for your chandelier but also every time somebody says candy
I just think Liberace I'm sorry
Okay Be Our Guest
Traffic
Trying to light up
This is an option it is a ambient white light
Light
And it is thirty bucks above which
I've got a chandelier that has nine bulbs in it
And I will not be
Instead I can
Nextbit to AC
$5
$60
Lutron switch
And that
Can just fine
Yeah
But
You know if you got
You know maybe some sconces
Something exciting
And these lights will be available we don't know
They're available for pre-order now and I think I called them C12 and if I did there actually E12 lights
My bad if that indeed
All right moving right along
Other
Shall we talk about
Well yeah it's exciting not in a good way for Tesla they actually it hired away
Play somebody from Apple
Chris lattner about 6 months ago
And if you don't know the name Chris lattner that's understandable he's in a lot of behind-the-scenes stuff such as
Contributing to the xcode developer platform that
Used to develop Apple apps
But I also development companies Swift programming language so I mean this is yeah this is
The smart dude
And he went to Tesla
And January
And they made him the VP of autopilot software for the car company
And he just announced this week Twitter yesterday in fact
He's leaving his tweet says turns out Tesla isn't a good fit for me after all
I'm interested to hear about interesting rules for a seasoned engineering leader so
I don't know what that means for Tesla I mean obviously got other smart people they're working on their autopilot project
We was going to work on it before Chris lattner no continue working on it but
Now I don't know what the skinny is on that one why he left
Yeah that's pretty public waves
So
Lot of weirdness
I still have mine
Tessa I'm not worried
MattyB
The money and the frothiness around
AI in autopilot
Self-driving cars
Executives
To run it is
Small number of people have
Skills needed
So all right
Bayou Vista news
We can't do a show without talking about on Friday
What does tell you about that you know that already
I wrote a little thing about what I think it might mean for
Pursued I do realize that this is
All about
You know the last mile Disturbed
Navigation
Amazon
But there really some cool options
How about one of those
Because
The Amazon Dash wand is back
Its back
This is a tiny little $20 stick that can scan things
Your groceries
Talk to it and tell it what to
Put on your list
And if you're in an Amazon Fresh area
What are them for you
If you ask it to
It also has
Natomas
She does speak bacteria so you can ask you could ask questions and such and I can play music on this thing
Honda this thing and whatever comes with like it does not play music
Looking at it it's like this tiny little
Metal wand
Not everything needs
No no did you order one
By the time I was in Costa Rica last week
Wake you guys and I was not ordering
Products sold by the time I ordered it it was on backorder so who knows when I'll get mine
I did see that the echo show is going to come
Next week
So you pay $20 cuz they're subsidizing this you paid $20 for it or you will pay 20
And then you'll get $20 back on your eligible for social purchase
She registered it so again just like the dash buttons and all its all subsidized
Runs on 2 AAA batteries
Convenient
I think
Yeah be tested something called the Haiku it was a grocery store product.
It was 2 years ago
And you know
I don't buy the groceries in my house
We had fun because
Press the button
What are bananas
Or
You can scan things
Scanner
My husband felt it
Sometimes it did not pull the right stuff
For the grocery
We also meal plan
And so
It was great for tracking stuff that
We ran out of but it was kind of
A pain to sit and talk
Order the grocer
We wanted to order
Basically
Ended up with two
Right right
Yeah that's not good so I wonder I mean it's obviously very early since this thing just came out
But I wonder if the response is positive and Amazon will know if it's positive cuz they have all the Analytics
I wonder if you start seeing this integrated into refrigerators in like a
Connecting pain kind of thing
Just like some of the dash buttons are in somebody appliances now
Yeah that would be
I don't want to talk to your fridge is opposed to your
Echo a lot of
Those are in the
Pusher
Let's do it
There's also trash can
Scanner
You can buy that
You know as you throw some
Take away
Barcode on it
Clever
There's a lot of things out there
All right and now we have a surprise for both
The audience and myself
Yes cuz you don't know what my favorite new Amazon Echo skill is
I don't Kevin
What is it it's not that exciting but I'm excited I don't know maybe I'm the only one
But I remember saying multiple times
What are the reasons I wasn't too keen on getting in trust me this relates
Getting a Google home was that
It doesn't work with the music services that I subscribe to
And one of them is SiriusXM and sure enough there's a new SiriusXM skill as of yesterday so I can just
Tell my echo to play The Beatles channel on Sirius XM now when she link the accounts it's good to go
I'm so happy
Nice I didn't think people this actually gets Sirius XM out of the car to
Which is probably do that for
I listen to
SiriusXM more out of the car than I do in the car
I pay extra for that it's an extra five bucks a month I think
Oh yeah
Awesome
So that was a lot of stuff happened in this week
Stay tuned
For a message from our sponsor
Aunt
Argus
Call Brody
Who is going to talk to us about
Blockchain
And iot business models
We can't leave that behind
Hey everybody we are breaking into this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is TE Connectivity and I have Paul Lachlan
Who is the CTO and VP of engineering
For the appliances business at TE Connectivity first off let's remind everybody what TE Connectivity does
The range of solutions
For the home appliance industry
Everything from
Dishwashers microwaves ovens
Refrigerators
And nowadays unless else
Small appliances hitting smart devices in the home think about us smart doorbells
Smoke detectors thermostats
We are working on a range of solutions for many of those types of products that involved
Three endings challenges much difference to us relations convention Association
Iqiyi within the conventional home appliances industry
Got it and you actually talk to me about some of these
Challenges he mentioned moving from
Iot 1.0
So now we're in iot
2.0 can you talk to me about what you meant by
Blake on iot 1.0
Consistency of Simply connection discreet devices to the very limited functionality you have made the ability to Country
Light switch and Appliance or other device through your phone to a calculation why that was interesting it was not really significant
However nowhere in treating what I'd like to call your TT 2.0
Brady Industries Inc ESPN a large part in the Essence alternative to the fundamental connectivity issues and challenges
We know a t e have the capability of combining json and unique ways
Our customers
Develop incredible solutions for end consumers
This will allow them to enhance improve and learn more about their
Behaviors
Etc in the home this will create a really meaningful difference and generous
Play with color true value proposition
So you mentioned some challenges
Associated with iot 2.0
How is TE Connectivity
Alvin companies adapt
In terms of challenges security is a very real concern for many of our customers
There's too many stories of device isn't a site being hacked with heard stories of video feeds and security cameras and baby monitors
Being hijacked
So she eats for taking great care to ensure all solutions we provide to our customers are making the strictest standards in the industry
All the factors of importance for Tes performance in harsh environments
We're playing intelligence into our devices
Turn off in your typical
Consumer products
Open washing machines dishwashers Etc this is what I believe
GE has a fundamental advantage over other competitors and sweep and sometimes Heidi reliable Solutions into harsh environment
Patience for many years
I don't know which option best expertise for the Smart Home
A lot more easily than any of our competitors who don't have that experience
Impulse
Where can we go to find out
Learn more about this exciting space it just coacht.com connected home
Hey everyone
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Paul Brody
Who is a principal and
Global Innovation leader
Watching at
Why
Hey Paul how are you doing
I'm doing great Stacy thanks for having me on
People who has been listening to the show
For like 4 or 5 years might remember Paul because he came on
To talk about
Building
Blockchain payment model
Pause for iot
Yikes
Today we're not going to talk about that actually
Because
We're going to talk about
Building a better world and
Building business models that work
For consumer iot
Let's see where this goes
Paul Ekman
What topics should we tackle first
Helix jump on this question of
How we build consumer models for iot
Promoted because I am feeling really down in the dumps I feel like we're about to see a lot of products
They'll get acquired are they won't be able to support
Their customers
Because they can't
Ongoing costs
Security
Software up
How do you spell that
Why don't know for sure how we completely solve it but I think this is actually
It's actually an amazingly not new problem and it I think it stems from from a couple of things one of them is it what I like
Make a call business model Envy
So a lot of companies in the space
Want to have a razor and Blades business model
And I think one of the problems they're having is an expectation
From consumers their hope of having a razor blades model is running smack into the desire of consumers
Not to have to pay a subscription fee to use their door locks
And so it's little things like that are in a mismatching expectation
Has meant that in general
Iot consumer it business models have had not as much revenue
On the one hand
If they had help
And on the other hand they're discovering
It's darned expensive to maintain
Over the long-term the software and the technology infrastructure required to support smart connected devices
Let's first talk about the subscription model
Challenge
And then we'll get in
Check back in
Cuz there's there's different answers
So
When I think about subscription model
If I'm a company
Trying to charge
People for
I don't know access to Cloud video storage is a
Another popular one might
Security or
Parental controls
Rules for like your router
Some of those seem like
Something I
Hey
So where do you think a company can get away with
Subscription
I think we're companies can get away with their subscription Melissa live they're providing something
That is
Meaningfully more valuable than the base functionality
So
I want to have a door lock and I want to have an electronic door locking that that's great there certain basic simple things that I want with the door lock
But then there's perhaps more advanced functionality does like to have as well
I think a freemium model works best where you don't have to be locked into it
And then to figure out what the additional services are right so a very simple model that just threw the allows
Unlock door with your phone and is electronic unless you replaced it
Physical key with a n d Marco Torres thumbprint maybe that's a no subscription model but if you want to have
A door lock that is directly connected to VRBO or
Allows you know ups and others to deliver packages and brought them inside your hallway
And record the video of them doing that
Then that's kind of a perfect
Example of where you could add some additional value
So I think one thing for opportunities for companies to think about what is the base functionality
But I'm going to provide for everybody and it's going to be simple and it's going to be a One-Shot deal you buy it you use it forever
What are the extra features that some subset the possibly pay for and that will help fund some of my ongoing up
Beyond devices I spend a lot of time thinking about
What happens when everything be
Becomes a service
I actually kind of mean everything because right now I buy my music as a service I buy
All of my entertainment and television
I guess my book scitech
Download
Candles soap
Service but there is that Kindle reading service
And I look at that as we move out
The cars or
I don't know
Wells Fargo customer service for sure coming right in
Vacation rentals as a service all of these things anything that can be fractionalized
Is likely to become a service
So what does that mean for wealth creation and
How people
I just think about
It used to be if you bought your home
For example
That was a way to
Create wealth and now it feels like if I buy
Several homes I might be able to generate
Wealth rule
Airbnb or those kind of options
But for people who don't have that option it feels like it's just going to get wider and wider and they're going to be
Slowly like
Paying out all of their income and having no chance
Instasave just to me
The basic services
Really
Dystopian
I do think
So do I write I worried about that as well and I try to think about is there some Flipside benefit and I think
We are headed towards a world where there could be some significant benefits for people
Who are not in the top 1% right so the people who have ordinary incomes and have ordinary aspiration
And one of the ones that I think we're going to see most immediately is in fractional vehicle ownership
So today
We all need a card has won the most essential things you need especially if you live in the United States we don't have a lot of public transport
You have to have a card
To work
Today we'd be happy to buy cars but they actually sit idle most of the time
And so in the future when we have
Self-driving
Cars in that future is very close by
You know if we drive our cars on average 10% of the day
We only need about 10% of a car
But today we have to buy a whole car
Because it impractical to share your car on a daily basis you know sharing keys and stuff like that if you can't go in and out of
So what's fractional vehicle ownership
We can have self-driving cars to take us to work and then they go and they will they work for others
We believe and we're working very hard on that
It's fractional
Ownership of asset not only does it hugely reduce the cost that individual people have to pay
This is a very good application for blockchain technology where we can make these
Decentralized autonomous organization
The future could be full of
Cooperative
Entities right nonprofit Cooperative that allow people to share assets very very fish
Okay now
I like that vision
It sounds really awesome
But I look at
Like things like I think
Tesla had a good example of this they had in there
Contract with
If you win do you buy the car
They don't want you driving that for anybody else except
For them and it's
Almost done clear if you would actually get the benefits
Of owning that Tess
Tesla or
If Tesla would
So it feels like there
Might be in the midst of this subscription
Subscription ization of every
Did the
Companies who are building these
Products
Might try to grab as much of
Revenue app
They're definitely going to and what's really interesting about this to me
Is that we are seeing a replay
Previous big industrial Transformations and I
I didn't study history at school but I become a bit of a history buff because I love looking at these past examples and what do they want
It was really interesting to me is that many people don't realize this is that United Airlines used to be the bow
Going consumer air Transport company
Right they used to be the passenger service Division and
There's a trend here that we see over and over again which is in times of
Significant transformational technology
Companies pursue high levels of vertical integration because they're capturing that value
And typically what happened in the past with antitrust authorities
Forest unbundling of those services to improve competition
And for sure I think we're not many years away
Potentially from some kind of
New antitrust Authority looking at those kind of digital integration
But we have something new and different that exist today which is
The open-source software
And even though Tesla for example is extremely far ahead of a lot of companies in this capability
Lots and lots of open-source activities going around around machine learning
And image recognition and autonomous vehicles
That I think maybe not right away but over time
Will empower
Consumers Cooperative
To build alternative
And to create the kind of it a new
Cooperative culture that's built on digital collaboration
Let's talk about what that needs and how that might
So I think
The Prototype the model for this
Is in the world of software
If you look at blocked and unblocked him is a really good example
Almost all the big Innovations in blockchain and all of the foundational capabilities have been built in an open sore
Forest Manor and open source technology is at the foundation of almost every major kind of digital technology
Platform
What's been missing
Is the translation of Open Source in a
Technology industry into open source and collaboration as a
Physical product
And I think that that is the next step in the next big opportunity for people
Is Frosty
Create a open-source collaborative or cooperative movement that brings it into the physical world
So with that look like my neighborhood Co-op we're like 50 of my closest friends and neighbors get together and we
I don't know
A car is an asset
Cars
The cars are good example trucks
Solar panels
So we creep is Co-op we all Buy in
We put our money into this and then
We would need to buy some sort of software or
I assume it's open source so we would then have to
The download
We would have to pay someone somehow
Management
Attain this cuz that's a field
Not a lot of people
What have
And
Then
We would allocate
The resource
Watching like
So we could do a couple of things first of all we can raise the money
For this Cooperative venture
Through things like an initial coin offering right initial coin offering
We can talk about later and we're experiencing a little bit of a kind of an explosive bubble of excitement around them
They are a very cool blocking base way of crowdsourcing
New initiative
And so you could imagine raising the money for a community solar farm through an initial coin offering that pays for the solar farm
Farm and then you can imagine managing that
Through a blockchain based system that met that's attached to your home electricity meter
And so did.
From your bill
The amount that was generated by the solar farm at the time that you can
And that all of the software required to maintain that and manage that process is part of a
Open source
Community-supported software program
And chances are if you have something a very high volume
Like a community solar farm
Or a neighborhood car sharing service
You're going to have huge number people around the world and think it's a great and you know very rewarding about open source
Software
50 or 75 or a hundred collaborators around the world working together
Create infrastructure that's used by millions
And
That would be their job or do you think that's something they do in their spare time from
Many of these are supported by people who do work in their spare time you know are people at ey they do a ton of
Contributions to non-profit
And open stores
Communities we actually inform me when I hire developers one of the chief thinks that I look for is a track record
Contributing to open source environment
Because the standard of coding is high the level of inspection is high
And it kind of just the spirit of community involvement is a great signal that you know what you do with your spare time
Means a lot about how you approach your work
So now I got this
Managed that feels like
Model for sharing assets
Maybe a strike against
Stay
Scarier
Corporate-owned
Let us go back
Which was
How to build
Sustainable business models for a connected device
So
The first thing was
We talked about subscription but you also talked about
How do you build iot
In a way that makes
Cheaper Tumi
Maintain over
And I think we're going to get back to
We are and there's a bunch of key issues at the top of the list is first of all there's a cost of the infrastructure required to
To support this large-scale
And that infrastructure costs
Comes in a couple of ways first of all
You need data centers and CDN for Distributing content
And secondly overtime what's interesting is
As devices and asset age
One of the problems that that
You got if it's sometimes the infrastructure that supports them ages as well it may age faster than the devices in
In the field
So for sure we believe a big part of this is
As much software as you can
You should be building on open source
Especially if it's got a robust Community because then
All the cost of maintaining that software is not falling on your shoulders
And that's really important especially when it comes to security
You want a
Robust community
Are people who are looking for bugs and 0 day
When it comes to the
Infrastructure kind of cost in architecture as a whole
I think we're still architecting things in a way that's a little bit out of date
Retreating
Computing cost especially the edge of something that still cost money but actually it's basically free
And these devices that we have out of the ads are very very powerful today and they're not
Especially for ones that are sitting in a car
Bar connected to Mains power they have a lot of compute power and in many cases they have quite a bit of bandwidth
As well I'm a big believer in and one of my original interest in blockchain
Came around this idea of taking
The workload
That has traditionally been centralized in an expensive data center or through a CDN and distributing it out to the edges
The network as a blockchain based distributed computing infrastructure with peer-to-peer
IMessaging and transfer
That is a mouthful sorry yes but the bottom line kind of key bottom line that we found out with that
From an infrastructure standpoint it can be up to 99% less expensive to maintain a distributed infrastructure
Compared to a centralized Data Center
Now that's not all of your cost but it's a meaningful chunk
I feel like we're
Getting there
Perhaps maybe not in the consumer side as much but
I'm looking at things like
This month AWS just announced AWS Greengrass
And that's going to be pushing
Services to
A Gateway device
Microsoft has kind of iot at the edge there's a lot of cops
He's building the super
For powerful
Devices that
They're so it feels like
There's interest at the edge but it is not
Blockchain
So I'm kind of curious
If those two things
Might somehow
Are they will definitely meet if you look at all of the major players in this base
Every single one of them is in the process of experimenting with our thinking through
Blockchain technology
At the end of the day
I'm not sure that it matters so much what the technology is so long as we move some of the stuff out to the edge
What I can tell you is we had an interesting debate back when I was at IBM
As we started digging into the use of blockchain for iot and we kept asking ourselves
Do you say lots of different distributed computing Arkansas
Why do we care about blocking why we doing this are we just doing it because like every time you say Bitcoin somebody
DNR compliance Department freaks out and
Fun to watch that
Or is it because we have a better reason
And what we settled on the better reason that we settled on
And I think it's a good one is
It came back to this question
What is the internet of things for
And at the end of the day if it's not on the consumer side if it's one the business side
The Internet of Things if design some how to create economic value
And with need about blockchain as a
Distributed computing architecture
Is there Heritage in Bitcoin
Which is all about moving and storing value in a network
And at the end of the day
Whatever we do with with the are distributed iot infrastructure
We wanted somehow to be involved in generating money making payments and the economic exchange of value
And that's why
I think blockchain
Will become over time a very attractive choice for companies
That want to build high-value hbase empress
I like that that make sense
And now
Let us move Beyond value and subscriptions and into this idea of blockchain for social good
You brought this up in
I feel like we spent a lot of time talking about data
Send money
Business transformation but we don't actually talk about how we can make the world a little bit better
So
Expound on your idea
Creating a network of social good are people who care about social
Yes I feel like such a silly parody of the TV show Silicon Valley every time I say we just want to make the world a better place
But it's funny in part because so many people believe it's true and I for one think of blockchain sare
And nice unique opportunity for us to read decentralized
The internet and I didn't coined that phrase but I think it was
Icori doctor or somebody
The elf very famous but it's a great idea right at the internet we started off with thinking this is somehow away
Giving people more control
Over their lies
More autonomy
And in some ways it's become a powerful tool of social control
And high level of centralization
And I think we should remember that in fact
In many cases
What's powerful and empowering is to give people the tools
And access to assets that they couldn't previously
So why change Railway Distributing at work
And sharing it out either work or assets or other things
In a way
That seems as efficient and integrated
Centralized infrastructure
But without all of that overhead
Or centralization
And another analogy here is in a Bitcoin
Got a bunch of people who don't know each other
To work together collaboratively to create a reliable digital banking
We can do the same with
Sharing assets
Building digital infrastructure
Sharing responsibility for ownership of things or maintenance
Right we have the ability to create shared infrastructure
It has no
Central Authority
No sgna
Right it's community-based Cooperative types
The business model
Bradley successfactor
It's how many people to be served
How much profit get
Then how are we going to make money
So not everything has to be about making money
Right and I I think
One of the things that has been great about the USS I think we have an incredible so anthropic sector
Right and I think about for example how Charities raise money
Write initials coin offerings for Charities blockchain tokens for charity the ability to raise money for Charities to help manage
Charitable contributions of product and service to a blockchain
Has huge
Because of its ability to get rid of
A lot of administrative overhead and distribute money efficient
Okay
Man that feels like a lot Paul we have we have solved the
The iot subscription problem
We have
Apparently solved
The problem of dealing with assets
In our shared asset
Using
Watching
And anything else
That's a lot of problem solving for one day
No one can accuse us of lacking ambition
No
So I
Appreciate you coming on the show and giving me a lot of food for thought
Thank you
It's always a delight to be invited me huge fan and I send around the link to your show
To all of my colleagues at ey every time a New Edition comes out that's it for this week
Thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy
New things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week