Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy Higgins
Ender Cohoes
Kevin tofel
Today we have an awesome show for you we are going to be kicking it off
Lenovo smart
Home Products
Recently about Madam and Amazon adding motion sensors to
That platform
We got a hug
Speaker WiFi
I don't even know what
But Kevin likes
Target was making a lineup
Connected products
Kind of like the Amazon Dash
They killed it
We've also got some lonely hacker
Hindus including an iot botnet and Google employees hacking things
Nest new temperature sensor a 300 million dollar acquisition in the industrial iot
And a parapet
Too big and dust
What's we have our guest
Vikram kothari
Who is
CEO of Lucic San Jose
Company that launched
Yesterday
Focusing on
Indoor location
And
We're going to talk about why indoor location matters
What the challenges are there and what you can really do with that
So
We're also going to have a message from one of our sponsors
SAS
Big analytics company I know you guys will hurry up and
Now we should go to a message from one of our other spots
This week's show is sponsored by chocolate
Your customers are not a distributed error tracking
What's 64% of iot users in countering performance issues
You need chocolate
The Edge first
Problem finding software
What uses Advanced function analysis and deep learning techniques
Identify errors and performance bottlenecks across yours
Tired
Chocolate brings you the traces
Systemmetrics
An environmental conditions you need to fix issues
For your customer
Get started for free at chocolate
That I owe that's a u
Koe T. IO
Man
I would really enjoy it if
Companies actually work
Harder to find errors
What about you
Aqi tester
It's always cheaper to find errors earlier
Okay so let's get started with
Lenovo news
And now we have the details
Right we knew about this because of the FCC filing that we found I don't know maybe six weeks ago but it wasn't until last
Last week at the equator show that
Lenovo actually outages some new Smart Home Products and they are because they
Which runs
Google home Google Assistant settings
So this is not totally new expansion of smart home
And now have a dedicated smartphone
Spark plug
Eleanor smart
Camera
Last week with very little information
This week we have more
Sitting availability price
You should know these are all Wi-Fi
Capable devices
They are all 2.4 gigahertz with some smart home devices running solely on
Frequency but it is what it is
They're not available
But they will
Available
November exactly
Plug will be 2999
Camera v99
Availability
Willie was wondering what they were trying to do but now I sort of get it
Because if you think about it
There a competitor to Samsung
Between laptops
What laptops in particular I would say
And
They want to Augustine
Devices that lower selling prices
Send the stuff was happening
Everybody's going to multiple
This will work with the Google Assistant will work with Madam as well there are two versions of their app
Called Lenovo and Lync link app will be available soon
For IOS and Android
Who is this I would say
You can sing
People think is important
Smart light bulbs
They check everybody wants it
Even
Renters
But also a smart plug
Camera
This ties into
Very first devices
Buy I don't
Web cameras
So I don't recommend people by that but definitely a light bulb or a smart outlet to like
Remotely controlled
What is a great first step so
What's the bare minimum you need to
Yeah speaking of bare minimums I also noticed just now on the Smart Home
Website that they have
They have a smart
Speaker stand on speaker that works with Madam
This may have been out before but I think it's going under our radar unless you seen this before it it looks like an echo essentially
Can Intel Atom Processor inside it's got all the
Yeah right
I want trouble 10 watt woofer
99 bucks
Everyone who sends us the questions asking to the heck is what we call Amazon
Digital assistant so we don't set everyone's
Just so you know
Okay
We did last week
I don't know how I missed this but Amazon has added motion sensors
As a category
And that means that device
Owners
Start integrating
Their sensors
Which makes
Automation Way
So
You're going to be able to stay if
UC motion
Camera
Turn on my porch
Yay
Something that the
Device manufacturers
First so smart things as one of the early adopter
They're doing it around their multi-purpose sensor and their motion sensor
Today
Any how to use
14 function
Write this is a new API essential
Biggie at something that the as you said that app makers and developers and
So I have to integrate
Oh my gosh this please you that I want to start playing with this the other device that uses this
Surprisingly is the Echo Plus
That is a few things so that if you have
Centralite sensors
Or Sylvania and
Birthing Centers Portland
If you have centralized Sylvania sensor
And an Echo Plus
You actually
Start using this
And others again
Center companies
Oh this is all
So others ABS sensor base
You'll have to certify
And why do you think that is
Answer this
Because what
Radio is missing from the Amazon hub
Oh okay
Do you have a scandalous story about a
Tell me more
Yes
Yes the Echo Plus which is their hub
And we should explain for people who don't know what these
Zigbee and Z-Wave R2 networking
Analogies have been used in the home
Really long
And they're low power
Networking
Wireless protocols
It's great for your battery powered sensors and things like that
Even door locks
But with things like Home Care
A lot of the new functionality
It's unclear exactly and Z-Wave are going to still be like
The masters of Hawaiian nation that they used
That's why we're devoting so much time
To that aspect
Okay so
I would say hey everybody
Please
Do this
It will be awesome
Because I really love
Having things automated based on
Although it can be kind of a pain to fingers
I was drinking and spent like
Six months trying to figure out how to create like a automated go to bed
Routine for my house
I never said
It was terrible
Not slept in 6 months no I just I didn't want to say like goodnight
I just wanted like
Oh
Haven't walked in the following
Hallway and these lights are out
And this person
Basically
It just would all go to hell
Whenever
There's so many variables that's the tricky part
Exactly
Moving right along
Also
We got news that the
Amazon
Digital
Assistant that works with over 20000 devices
This is why you often say that first
Platform that smart home devices
Amazon
It's true they start with Amazon first
They've now started with Amazon first to move to Google and then they follow with it
Usually
And
I'll be curious with homekit with apple lightning up some of their requirements will see a bigger chunk.
Just to put this number in contacts
The beginning of the year
4000 devices
The number of brands
Went from 1200 at the beginning of this year to 3500
So
They are making big strides
There's also 50000 Madam a skills
Inside actually start with
If you are trying to predict what's happening and how the Smart Home
I was going to get easier over time
Look at
The API integration
Alexa motion sensor
About or
Last week
GE announced
You no longer have to talk to G-Eazy
Assistant
Control the oven
And other Home Appliances
And that's because
They now have
Native support for ovens and microwaves and things like that inside
So this is a big deal because what is going in able to
Interoperability
So
Geez ovens work
Pretty much the same way that
Oh
Ashes of an acre
On off
So once you have that you can just say
Your particular device
To say hey
Turn the oven to 350
The echo figures all that
One other thought in case we have some enterprising individuals that listen to the show
I thought it was interesting
That
Amazon
Mentioned a 22 year old college student
Is making $10,000 a month
With his
Word of the day skill
That
Opportunity
Yes people up there
You probably should come
Okay
Speaking of apis this is rather interesting as well
Samsung
Third-party developers to build apps for Bixby
And I don't think we're going to call Bixby Mister because I don't really know anybody using Bixby
50 States but that is
Good news for
Developers
I want you
Target another platform
I don't know I am a little too late a minutes expected to happen
Samsung to do list
But
I just I don't see a baby
Push for Bixby these days
Maybe in other parts of the world
Is Bixby begin
The thing about Bixby
Is just not a good implementation
Perfect example Galaxy Note 9 just came out Us phone out right now
Every single review I read
Bixby is half-baked Bixby doesn't respond Expedia spins for 30 seconds and then says I don't know
I know they put on a good show with Bixby at there
Home speaker for example
Developer on Samsung
Not it's not nearly as bad
Having use both but yes
And
We should mention this week kind of bypass these standards
Part of this
Last week
Also on Thursday
Earliest version 2 of the io tivity Sanders
And
For all of you guys have been following us for years we've talked about this because this was supposed to be like
A unifying standard for the internet
Especially in the smart
It might be but no one else's
So LG Samsung
And
Higher are all going to
Tivity certified devices
Coming to Market
That is next year
I'm really
I mean I wrote about this
When I go to be the first version launch there were
It only ran on
Giant machines like hugs and
Things running Atom Processor
It just was not great for the internet
Right way too much memory all that
And
They took a really long time
Security spy
I've been worried about the OCS
Quite some time
I feel like this is
Too little too late
I've been watching this particular effort
Oh
3 years
Maybe for years now and then
Prior to that I was watching
Qualcomm
All join
Choose another effort to like have these Universal data C
So what it looks like we're getting a
We're going to have
Amazon Echo take over
This I guess and maybe Google home
That's what I was going to say
If you take too long to come out with a standard and somebody else develops to censor their own standards
That generally come for the universal or standard coming in late
Biscuit is not adding a standard at all
So
This is
This morning but there are I still actually need lots of people who want to use the open
Connectivity Foundation standards
You know maybe I'll be surprised
Will keep it up there
See what happens
All right
Lot of little products in things
Talk about so let's talk about or via voice
You been waiting for this
Not this particular
Well maybe not particular this device but yes I am looking for expect the next
Has to be a consolidation and by that I mean we don't need a box of bridge at HUB etcetera for everything we do
Why not put them all in integration where you can and that's what Netgear is doing with her or be voice
So what it is
It is
Part of their orbi
Mesh wi-fi system
Also is a smart speaker
So you get decent sound assistant and you extend your network
So
That's
This type of process exactly what I've been working
I mean I get this product
Yes I forsee many
Similar products from various vendors now
Yay
All right
Tattoos
Target
They are products
Vinyl Products
Couple times
But
And he was in the newsletter
Amazon Dash except they built
Connection
Bluetooth
And when it was almost empty it would reordered
Yourself
Kind of cool
People did not support it if they launched as a crowdfunding
Nobody decided to
And I think it's probably a couple things
Actually talked about
That's not the best way to do it
The den 2
Many many many
We talked about
Dogs
Dog food scoop
Order more dog food as you scoop it out basically
Anyway
It was really hard because when you were trying to assess value is at
You're like
Changes the equation
You like his convenience worth
The little prince premium
I don't know
And most people probably said
And I think it's because they hadn't experienced that
Didn't make sense I mean
We're getting bombarded with a shift
Two subscription-based things
Celebree ordering
When you're low on something smartly
Makes sense but it's also like to I want another kind of things I think you were struggling
All right if he doesn't talk about this kind of thing
You want to use it
I don't know
All right
What's up
We got a
OK Google employee hacking the Google door
I was like
Yeah I know it's actually very good
Google
Sunnyvale offices were hacked by one of his own employees
You're somebody else
Because I couldn't really bad but one of these employees on Sunnyvale
Found out to get into the
Uses I think was NFC
RFID
Is RFID there we go
Software House
Software House exactly will suffer house needs to take a look at it software because encrypted messages
Sending across the network
And this
Employee discovered a hard-coded encryption key Software House devices
So he replicated the key commands and was able to lock
Fellow employees out of the building
So the good news is
He reported at 10
Is being address
Google's probably very happy that
This raises an interesting challenge that I worry about
In our future for as a consumer for example because the locks
Didn't have enough memory to be upgraded with the fix
So literally you had to
Not you will have to physically have those locks
And that's like gr device makers considering
You know
Memory constraints and such
For something like that she got to have some overhead in case something drastic goes wrong so that way they're not sending new devices
Not everybody
So that's actually
Even around
Basic functionality
So having enough overhead in your
Teal
People
You're going to bump up against especially because
My gosh we just keep making software bigger
Historically a lot of like
Locks
Appliance makers
What do you like that
You don't remember it was like an extra building materials
Straight hair like no just play it to the Bone you need to
Nothing until they're actually haven't
To do
And how they think about
Building there
Products
The Internet of Things
And
But it is
It is definitely
Something that I don't think
4 years ago
They were thinking about and now they are and they're having to start designing this kind of
Extra overhead in
And you know it will run out so
Fisher Hawaii
Modular
Yeah the good thing is we
Come along way with remotely managing updating industrial and elsewhere
And if the device itself doesn't have enough
Memory to handle that that's an issue it's so it has to be part of the design process that think ahead
Let's talk about
Caillou
Yes a new iot botnet
As you mentioned
D-Link Huawei and Realtek
Routers so
Is the Japanese word for according to
Yeah this is just your typical I'm going to get on your router and I have donut services and I'm going to pin
Report I can see what's on your network
The password or what has
Hard coded
You know from the device maker pastor
Have you didn't change it so you could access
Wi-Fi cameras on your network
Consumer Reports
Yeah that's not good
I believe
There's no
Fix for this yet I have not
Scene record of one
Okay we're optimistic news relare
Which is a
Enterprise
An industrial iot
Acquired by insurance
Munich re
This is a deal that valuable are
Million-dollar
This is about this is
Blair's been doing this for a while. They help companies tie a lot of their
Next products
Together using
Customers
They also offer Analytics
And this makes a lot of sense because
I believe there is a
Promising understanding
And things
Maintenance schedules all of this
Actuarial world of Ensure
So
Getting that kind of data
Pulling it
Being able to
Actually see it
Is going to be important
Going forward
I don't know if the
Companies working with relay or going to be excited about sharing
Christina with insurance
Companies so we'll see how that
Doylestown
But
I do think this is a highly strategic
And one
Interesting one of the investors in
One of the later rounds of funding
For this company
Got to get in early on
Indy industrial internet
Corporate and strategic investors are wonderful Sunday
Industrial
I will say
Also
In this kind of industrial world
Google the company that makes
All kinds of things this contract
Manufacture they are working with Cisco which I associate with
Analytics software
To make a
So if you don't want to design your own board
With it up Memories by the way
In handle all the
Analytics aspects and getting all that data to the cloud
Offering out there that
So while we're building your
Washing machine we can also have this word in
You can start pulling data off of it very easily
So
For companies that don't want to have to
Some tiny little product
We don't talk too much about these but lucky
Is a crowd-sourced thing
On Kickstarter
Crowdsourcing is like a Bluetooth
Teething
You know where it is
Weider Home
Without your key and it also has a sensor in at the tracks when the key was
Turn so you actually know if you lock your door
You can't change anything
You can't remotely fix it
He makes Yorkie sort of smart but not so much Sherlock
Exactly
Yes also
At least it's temperature sensors
Rainbow colors
I think this is fine but
Are some negative reviews out there
Yeah there's a review just
Earlier this week
By the Virgin the basically the biggest upgrade
Disappointment
Goodness hasn't changed that much
This is an upgrade
And they say does the bare minimum which is
Is the temperature sensor doesn't have presents for example so you can't
He's in a room is very limited as programmability because you only have certain blocks of time where you can
Set the temperature
Sensor 2
A certain temperature
Perhaps
Even early riser you want to have somebody new I have a cooler room or warm room at 5 a.m. while you really can't do that with this
What is a temperature sensor
Doesn't you know she's not going to do much more I don't think
Yeah you sure that I feel like
It should be way smarter so yeah
Is it temperature
We might think that
It would be better to have a temper
Your presence and air quality
Deciding
Right that's the key so if you wanted to have all these extra things what would you expect the price to pay if you expect
Pack 499 sensors
No. Like right now at this time
Alright skip ahead
2 AR
Voicemail from the iot podcast hotline
But first
Tell you
We did our drawing for August
And we have a winner
Michael Graves
From Houston
Alright this week we have a voicemail from beg
Know that the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Don't miss your chance to win a Schlage
Sense smart deadbolt
In Wi-Fi adapter
Enter to win all you have to do is call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
And we
Will answer your questions
Motorhome
Start
Which leg
I really have to tell you
Schlage lock
Is really nice
This is a very high-quality locked
Installing I've installed any locks
Really good
Super sturdy
Tell that this is a medium
End
It works really well so we're excited to offer this
You guys cuz it is
And Michael got the one for August so does that mean we are getting one away and September
We are
In September
This is not a huge Drive
I'll tell you when we get about 20 voicemails a month and what we do is we stick them in a spreadsheet
And we use a random number generator to draw these so your chances are
And I don't just say that cuz they do
It is a really nice
I'm going to call right after the show
Outside of the US
Sorry England
All the other places
Good people College
Okay
Let's hear from
Hi my name is Megan I'm from
Southeastern washing
We're in the process of building home in Colorado
The Builder uses a group
Saw their home automation products
Soyuz
Ultrasound thanks from interlogix
Further hub
We now have a home that has a Wink 2 hub
And a lot of
Miss A
Compatible products
I'm not comfortable using
A group as an ultra sink from
Interlogix
God never heard of since
She is in the midst their own by gng is in the midst of it Sebastian
Future
Should we just
Have them installed the Catholics
Cable and audio and go your own way
Do you have another pinion
Oh okay this is a good question because I bet a lot of people deal with it
Yeah this is the system we put in take it or leave it
In this case I'm going to tell you that
Britney actually no longer
Intralogic
Bye
So you don't have to worry about these troubles there
And
I think for us
The big question in this is going to be for you
Rather not
Is
Do you want to put this in your house
And just ignore it which is a possibility
Do you want to not have it in your house at all which I don't know what that's possibility
Or do you want to try to use it
If you try to use it
You're going to be there are some limitations
You will be stuck buying
Interlogix products
You can however integrate those with things like that
So
So as far as like crazy Smart Home
Integrating it
Necessarily with things like
Or
But you could use the voice control of matter made of
Turn things on and off
That's one
And then Kevin
Yeah my thought was
Ucenter already using like a DIY system you have wink Frozen after he said
As do I you not paying any monthly fees
Right now
Obviously
I would check in the building should be able to tell you if
The interlogix system has a monthly
I personally would not want that which is why I have went and I assume
You feel the same way but
You can change your mind
Maybe there isn't a fee maybe they discount it
I only say this because interlogix
Products are sold install through dealers
It's not an off-the-shelf anything or you just install it yourself
As a DIY person so I'm assuming
There may be a monthly fee involved
Yes if you want to
So
What we have to tell you
I'm not 100% sure what you're actually
Like so hopefully this helps
You don't at least have to worry about the bees.
And
If you
Want to it might be kind of nice
To just be like
Justine Smith anime app
It really depends on how you
In how much time
Bat
It's all we have for this week
Remember if you would like to call us and ask this question for your chance to win a Schlage lock
Call 651-2623
7/4
I remember
Murder hole
Start with sleep
Let's get ready now or
Our Guest
This week who is going to be talking about indoor geolocation
Really hard problem for iot
So I guess is Vikram Parvati
CEO of Lowe's
Before we get to him we're going to have a message
We got a new sponsor this week in
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Fast and I have json man who is VP of iot
Louis asked you to talk to her
Alright so let's just get started
Talking about
Sassy
And iot
Chaz has been in the analytics space for
A long time
Can you give us a few updates until us
What you guys are doing
With the internet
Most people are familiar with sass
As as leader
In Analytics
Within the space
More than 42 years
And the change.
Has been presented
Respect to the iot market is the
The fact that
A huge explosion of data being generated by the
And the data is
Is distributed
ATS device
2 hour
Response to that
An investment
And streaming technology
Being able to
Chicken Little
From the previous.
Processes
Be able to apply those
Penn State in motion
IRT is
Big data problem
The dolphin x x
Kyushin is required again small bits of data that are
Moving quite rapidly
Alarm
Incapability
Will Alice generator
Environment
Shasta's created a new iot division
Kendall Oliver
What is that mean forecast
So yes we did create a new division within SAS
The goal was be able to
Full resources
Together from R&D
An archipelago
Operation
Marketing
Product management
Ford sells all of these
Capabilities
Brought together to
Focus
Only iot opportunity
Globally
Customers is a couple things most of the use case
Houses that we see around Iowa
Peores on yield Improvement efficient
NC failure to text
Or
A better engage
Is there an customer
Safari
Class of problem
Improve my
You see the capability to reduce the latency and the decisioning
The origin of data
Closer to the origin
Of the problem
And on the customer engagement it really
Provides the ability for a unique message to a customer
In a unique position
Respect to geolocation
To an incap proximity to
Healthcare device
A couple of categories that
Do you skate
Leverage
So openness is a big deal in the internet
How is SAS handling
That
Yes so certainly UC wide mark
Adoption
Some of the open-source capabilities while using example as
Python modeling
But what we have found through
Evaluation
Concepts
Stockwell
You can generate inside
Which is quite difficult
To the point that in
Enterprise
Environment
For sustained value of
Overtime
An hour and 4
To support the full
Iot analytics life cycle
It allows you to
Consume those open-source model
Languages
An example but then provide
Capability
Play.
And maintain
Improve those models of
X
Continue to
Justine Valley
All right and Jason where can we go to
To find out more about SAS and its efforts and iot
Absolutely so you can go to
Tous ask.com.
And that provides
The basis for now.
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Vikram
Hibachi who is CEO of Lucic
Ink hive
How are you
ICC how are you
I am super well so
We are talking about
Location today
Neighborly
What you can do with
Highly granular location
In the iot and why it matters
So
You guys just launched your company
But this is something you guys have been working on for
5 years almost
Absolutely
The Genesis of the accompanying idea founding the company really started Nelly for 5 years ago
Okay so
Let's Orient
People kiss people may not be
Really like
Why do I need such awesomely granular location
People may not even realize we don't
Have greater
Location for Io
So let's talk about the problem
A little bit what is difficult about
Finding thing
Yes I think we already familiar with using
GPS driven
Babson
Location Technologies in the outdoor
Environment
I can imagine people navigating without Google Maps or Apple Maps today in the Outdoor World
But once we comes to an indoor environment which includes all the way from
You know what your commercial buildings off
Retail to factory
Warehouse and Logistics
Facilities and also your home
Wiki Lac today Stacy is a very precise way of localization
Indoors by precise indoor localization
So important is because in terms of
Warehouse logistics for example if you want to be able to accurately locate assets
Which includes a patient they cook Mayan people
And ability to locate and then
Track them as they moved to these Logistics centers allow or custom
Smurfs to be more efficient increase productivity
And get a lot of visibility on what's Happening
Inside their operations
On The Other Extreme for example you can imagine having precise localization indoors in your home and buy
Understanding where all these devices are that are connecting to each other and you can create a contextually Aver
Environment where consumers can
Use these to automate a lot of their in our daily chores that otherwise take a lot of effort to initialize
And then in between you have
Different
Application
Schleich locating
A certain hospitals
Assets in factories
And cilantro for indoor localization
And the position of diet really enables people to be more efficient or productive
Can get more visibility on the how things are happening inside their environment
And this is also a challenge just when you think about it once I've put a bunch of sensor someplace
Sometimes they move sometimes
Happen
And you want to be able to
Know where they are for maintenance
Battery changing
Absolutely and you'll be amazed as to how
You know you take the context of just operation and maintenance rate in a commercial building
Pick up large
Skyscraper in you have seen on thousands of HP AC units are going to have light bulbs or
Lamps all of these overtime in the course of a building life of a building can be 25-30 years
You have no idea where these
What was it stored where and what happened
And so you know even something as simple as
Smoke detectors
And understanding for example knowing the location of these detectors you can
Visualize where exactly the fire started wedding has
Initiate advice propagating
On The Other Extreme
My lamp is not operating in Bronson semaphore
And I can send that right
Technician
The 6-8 even before the customer complains about it
Idea of location is really really important to an operation in Renton
And it goes all the way from commercial buildings you know including a home for example today when you install your smart home devices you have
Physically going in log into location for example I have all these Alexa devices
Tooth in my home
That's exactly going
And locate right and so I've no contextually
No spatial awareness of a desert
Putting in
User representation for that so I descale in Osprey large buildings
That issue gets magnified even more
I can't even imagine I hate having to deal with
So
Let's talk about
We've needed this for a while
But we don't have it yet
About the challenges of
Joking this inside different in fire
The three major challenges that have plagued indoor localization one of them is that the environment that we are trying to
Track and locate things is a dynamic
Imagine a
I Logistics facility today where things are moving constantly when we are living in the world of e-commerce where this summer
Which Automation and velocity has increased
So dramatically over the last spinner 510
15 years so the dynamic nature makes it very difficult for us to use traditional Technologies every fingerprint
And then try to assess if things are actually right they were supposed to be
The second one is that it or buildings indoor environments have a lot of obstruction
You don't have traditional line of sight Technologies like Optical or what even are asking actually
See you at the king or the person that you're trying to locate
So this non-line-of-sight is it a significant Challenge and even beyond that once you get past these do you have
Have what you call it
Multipass like a selection severe physically you can have
You know 16 deflections of a given signal and then which one was the real one and which one weather reflection
So this idea of eliminating multipath has really played the industry for God's for the longest time so
Three main challenges and of course it has to be affordable and
Scalable and cost-effective
And you don't want to be deploying something which is not based on a standard those are the main challenges that doesn't look like this
It has faced over the last 4 years
Man you went for like 3 to 6
R7
Lots of companies
I have tried to do this and I'm just going to run people through a brief history of indoor location
Nothing
GPS GPS and GPS didn't work well with GPS + Wi-Fi so we had
Departure companies like Skyhook
Companies trying to do this
And now we're trying to add other radio so there's efforts
Laura Bluetooth location efforts
So let's talk about
Why you guys went
Wi-Fi
Also subject
Yes it is 5 V bucks was driven by a
Tina recognition.
Two things were happening when is that you know his wife I now become as important as water
I mean every building in the world now has Wi-Fi and consumers customers all depend
Don by 5 for data communication talk to you in for voice so Wi-Fi
Really are the most ubiquitous
Infrastructure that is already present
And will continue to be present
That was one very important reason for going with Wi-Fi
That reduces the cost and
The scale issues that you have it other newer technology
Do you like you and Bluetooth are ultra-wideband
The second part that we recognize many years ago was that there's an effort to increase the bandwidth in Wi-Fi
By that allows Wi-Fi to be even more interesting from a localization
Ocean Point of View and that's what really started a few years ago and we were able to understand that
And leverage that a lot in our solution
Today so we use our global standard call 11ac
Are witches high bandwidth
And which allows us to take advantage of the advances in Wi-Fi kind of combines the two is that
What Vidal ice was that
It's a lot of it has to do with the algorithm
And the ability to to do machine learning once you have captured the data that's the reason why by Begin video
Attractive
Beyond. Just so you know Global standardization
Baby looney that Wi-Fi device working in Japan would work in the US or in
Germany or China
Produces a lot of concerns with our customers and the ability to use mobile phones is very important as well.
Something that newer Technologies would find difficult to do
And then the sub gigahertz
Component be used mainly for communication
Cam site is 2 reduced by 5-day power intensive protocol to the ability to use sub
Gigahertz allows us to den
Communicate and maintain the network without leveraging the high-power and Smith and receive functions of Wi-Fi
So you guys use radio
ORF to understand location but you also have something called a visual sensor
About why you're doing
When we started looking at this challenge of
Uniqa capture and really visualizing
The physical space Wikipedia lies was that a lot of the algorithms.
People have developed especially on Dai side leverage ratio data
And we are very good at image and video Analytics
But the challenge then is that most of the devices that people use in commercial buildings or invade houses
6 personalities
Security you tend to use a lot of buy a camera
And these are expensive very difficult to win
Install into fuel have a million-square-foot facility in a warehouse distribution center
You can't deploy these Violet sensors if I have cameras all over these
Large building
Most of the cost is not in the hardware but in the insulation the maintenance the reconfiguration and if you take the lifetime cost
Cost-effective becomes really high invented is a visual sensor what you do is
How to use standard
Image sensing
Components we have not did nothing
You know anything exciting about those but then we have modified the protocol of use out on wireless sensor Network in total
Call that allows us to transmit image data
And video clips that they look Park
Consumption by doing that now if you can do is you can deploy these
These cameras
Battery operated cameras all over your facility and if you take an image and video streaming devices
For that device cameras do really well with a lots of times you want to take images once a minute once an hour and some cases
Customers even take images
Once a day so that kind of operation original sensor product is really good so now you can take images from Hyundai
Different locations within your facility
And use Ai and advanced Analytics
To get actionable insights and take the
Decisions make decisions that you know otherwise would not have been possible
Example UK
If you have an implementation in a bat house baby use up wireless cameras for tracking
What you call a smart truck doc application
She just literally walking to her house to tease wireless cameras and start monitoring the docks in the warehouse and
You got visual data every few minutes or every 5 minutes
Vision. You can analyze truck birth utilisation you can take the license plate of the truck you can make it
Intelligent Decisions on who the truck driver was with a truck owner was
What was the grill time
You can essentially come up with a really intelligent kpi now
And monitor the operational efficiency of how your dogs are cooperating
Inside the red house just an example or you can
Beautiful security
Can you get four understanding space utilisation
In complex areas within your facility
I know you could always use it for security and for surveillance as well
So why would I use that
The differences.
Bayit camera or the video camera
Essentially
Everett have to major in
This one is that it has to be fired because you're in or trying to take data and streaming across a high bandwidth
Vire
Insulation cost goes up
The maintenance Costco's are because you and also operating cost
Because now you're taking large band with files and trying to store them or pasta
System in the cloud
So what happens then they refused.
If you're taking data from just one location or maybe five or six locations
That's fine because you can easily afford to do that
What if I want to take data from thousands of location
Within a million-square-foot
Facility or a $54 building you know the cost of both of data capture
Analytics
And storage becomes
Really high
Best Buy
Our situation allows you to cost-effectively capture the data across very large spaces and then you can visualize and digit
What's the outdoor right sofa example you can literally walk up
Low.sex visual sensor devices
Hook them up on two different things outdoors
And start collecting
Data from them
And you don't need any fires you don't need an electrician that could easily move them across from one part of the outdoor location
That's what makes this so different from anything else that's out there in the market
Let's talk about
Developing the
While how are people using
This two areas have you seen the most significant interest one is from the warehouse and Logistics Market
And the second one is from commercial building operation and maintenance
Steve Matson Logistics the interest level is very high on understanding
Space and acid realization
And then enabling his capture to operate
Increase efficiency increase productivity gain more visibility and their operation
Inside these Logistics centers
A lot of it states has been given by e-commerce there's a strong
Organization of their houses real estate costs are going up for these facilities as
Consumers are demanding product
Closer to their homes
Which happens to be no burn areas so in the past you have had a distribution center in Tracy but now it's coming right into your into South
San Francisco going all the way into downtown Sanford
Just go and see if you take more complex cities like Tokyo and New York the cost of organized spaces
Is really high
So understanding space utilization is one of the most interesting
Use cases that you have seen to the ability to use both the visual sensor and our location local positioning system
Our customers can understand how space is being utilized and there's a part of that then
Becomes an expert know how much
Forklift people resources at the right resources available at the right time at the right space
What did I place those are actionable insights that customers really are interested in pain. Commercial side there's a lot of interest on
Commercial buildings lot of interest also by the way in specialization as you know Laura
Usra
Inside Global buildings are underutilized
And so using our visual sensor and location devices people will become more efficient in how they
Do you space within commercial offices in using our products for operation maintenance
People are using a cameras for examples for
American rooftops in
In other parts of the building
Security and surveillance reading a much larger
Scope of security within larger complexes which are traditional camera Solutions cannot cover some of the interesting
Can you say seductive come across so far
You like many companies are building a platform
That could really
Go in any number of Industry
But it's also so far been very easy to see that
Many of the most successful
Iot in the Enterprise in industrial space focus on just a few areas
Sino Logistics is
Big deal for you
Are there other areas where you
You guys are going to
Try to be high
You think Logistics is definitely the the primary focus of the company
But then once you go beyond
Logistics commercial buildings
Because again as you know a lot of iot solutions have not been very successful with commercial buildings
Security and surveillance dance
To be the one that people look at but if you
Take a step back in
Once you have better indoor location
What can I do with that if I can improve office occupancy space utilization
Then can I be more efficient with not only space but also work operations
Tobacco
You know kind of look at
Our Technologies as applicable to smart home it's just like that's a slightly different Market
Not our main focus directly right now but in a partnering with some of the
Larger companies were
Sinnoh focused on Smart Home Technology to build in location into the home which is has you no sodium
Missing at this point
Yes or if not missing
Manually inputted
Anything that
PSD to set up a smart home today
This is also kind of nice because it can auto update
Correct if I move something around
It's like
Now it's different
Inertial sensors in all devices
Tuesday similar to your phone so if you move to example interview are using them already in our warehouse application example
I know that now it's on the move and so now we can start tracking
That makes the device lot more efficient in terms of power consumption and
The New York
Cinnamon tanning everyday
A meaningful strike
An optimization of housing
Things are specially placed within your environment of Interest
All right
Thank you so much for
Thanks thanks for the opportunity
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
Remember it
If you'd like more Ayo
Sign up for my newsletter
An iota
Dot-com
Next week