Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today for episode 186
Set the podcast we have an awesome show
We're going to be talking about the news from arms
Techcon conference
This week
We are also giving you an update
8 on Facebook
Device and guess what
It's not as private as you thought it was
Plus we've got
A secure device framework from the UK that looks awesome
We could talk a little bit about GitHub actions and what that might mean for the iot
We got new products from SimpliSafe
We've got
Discontinued products from my o
And
The industrial iot gets a new place to
Go to find out
Good information about what things work together
Plus Kevin is going to talk about to new toys that he has
And then
We're going to hear from the CEO of espresso
Which makes an iot chip that has been sick
Crazy
Successful
All of this
And a message from our sponsor cognizant
Always you this show
So let's get it started with
IMessage from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is chocolate
What's 64% of iot consumers reporting performance issues you need an edge first album
Application performance monitoring solution to zoklet the problem solving software that watches your application
System
And their environments for issues from device anomalies to fleet-wide Aires chocolate will provide you with the Intel
You need to solve problems before your customers buy them sign up today at chocolate. IO
That's a UK
Let
Dot IO
Goodness Kevin
I am not at that time last year I was there
Good conference
I just
Was tired of traveling but
Two big announcements coming out of there
Arm is bringing Intel Arduino my devices and everything
Into their
Iot device management
You want to talk about this
Yeah and actually to talk about this we should probably backtrack maybe two months because arm purchased a day
Data Management Services layer
Company called treasure data back then what they've done this week is announce that
Treasure data for the data Management Services there
Waste Management Services
Swiss army man bed which is their iot platform and connectivity Management Services are all bundled into the pale
Xi'an iot platform forearm
So
That gets us to today or this week
Now I'm saying hey we've got some new partners with our
Kalyan platform
And his partners are
Intel as well as my devices
So what's happening here is
Is now bring you more
Silicon partners
I don't know that that's a big deal for the Intel bit
It is on the side of smaller chips and in particular Arduino which is the little program
Expensive creeper prototyping devices
Are doing it was actually partner and also with
Kelly on connectivity management system so that way they can scale out pretty quickly with devices and so on so
Is kind of a big deal
People who has companies that want to get into the it space the hardware space
I was surprised that
Arms mbed OS which is their operating system for microcontrollers
Has 350,000 developers according to arm that seems like a large number
Yeah I mean
For the embedded
Operating
These are artists
Access real time operating system
So
You can't run.
So there are lots of options free are tosses one of the
Biggest
The most widely used ones in Amazon actually brought in the developer of free artist
Into
But you know in bed was kind of lagging so it must have really hopped up in the last year or so
Yeah by comparison like when I look at phone makers and other device makers that have their own little development platforms
That just seems like a large relatively large number of I mean typically I'm teasing we have 10,000 Developers
Using this SDK or whatever
At Racine
Well it may be
What does Jesus mean
Perhaps people have downloaded this just to check it out cuz you know there's tons of people using arm stuff out there
But I don't give it to him because
We don't know any better so if you guys are using arm in bed or if you think you're one of these 350,000 who's like
Download it to see what it is and then
Never touched
Let It Snow
Okay also in arm news
Is they launched
Their knee over
Wine
Which sounds really cool
The Matrix
It does seem like meow
This is their infrastructure
Branding
A roadmap associated
Neil verse is
Kind of like arms cortex
Brand
Cortex is there smartphone high-end
Very powerful process
Assessor's office is
High-end very powerful process
Scissors but it's going to be designed for infrastructure
Purdue vs they're going to start pushing this into servers
Routers
Gateway's even base stations they have their cortex
Chips and some of these places now
But this new line is
It's going to be
Focus Barre
And the big Focus that they're talking about her
Today's big buzzwords
Iot
Edge Computing and 5G
So what arm has taken to doing and I'm not sure I love this but
It's in line with other chip manufacturers is
They are
Pre releasing
What their future Corsicana
Like it used to be the Armwood only announce
Or when it was ready to go
Now there
Basically giving a hint
This is a really impressive roadmap for
It's going to have a lot of the same
CPUs that power the cortex chips
The cosmos platform is the one that's going to be
It's out today
But they got an Aries platform for next year the Zeus platform for 20/20 and the Poseidon platform
2021 +
Is Aries and Zeus are going to be 7 nanometers
Assignment
5 minutes
That is be latest
Manufacturing process for 7
Mattress Walmart
That's what we're talking about
We're talking about cramming
More transistors on a chip
Make some
Faster better and more power-efficient
Yay
And I'll have a bunch of different
Ways of
Putting together different modules on these chips to
Bethany
Needs of whatever device they're going to be in
So the thing to know and take away from this is our MS
Basically using this
Neil verse line is a way to compete with Intel
Going forward in some of the areas where Intel is
Huge
And trying to get
Tigger
How unlike Intel arm just licenses
Corso it license is it
Scores to companies like Qualcomm
And Fry
Others
So you're not going to see
Are making chips you're just going to see it partnering with
Companies
Produce these higher-end
More powerful
Semiconductor
Bright orange design
Chip architecture and then licenses it help
And you know there's that idea here and you hear this wet from Intel a lot which is is end-to-end Edge to Cloud kind of thing
So there are
Possibly advantages
There are
You could get around
Of having the same chip
Ginger server that talks
G reg device
Both of them could be running the same kind of software that allows for more
Medication security between the two so arm is going to be touting that just
Until although the news about the Pelly and platform
If you're working within arm's device management
It's going to be heterogeneous
So that means it could actually have if you're working through that
It would actually be tight
Intel
So that's the big arm news it is a big deal
Will see again
It's kind of far out so we'll see
How this works out
Now
Out of the cloud
And the crazy on device silicone layer where you're like I don't know what you're talk to you about
What's 50 something we all care about
Privacy
Yeah let's move out of the cloud and into the home show in because
Last week and I know we mentioned this on the show and neither one of us were too enthused by this I'm sure a lot of people actually aren't
Facebook announced
Portal which is it
Video conferencing
Speaker smart speaker it is integrated with Madam a
Baby-facebook had said
Totally privacy
Conscious no problem no data will be collected through portal not even call log data or app usage data
Etc
Now they're kind of walk in that back a little bit and they're saying that
Because portals
Built on Facebook's messenger infrastructure they will be collecting the same types of information that they collect
For Messenger such as the length of a call frequency of a call possibly how much you use
Other apps
And that feeds into the information that they will use to serve ads in Facebook to you
So you won't see
Hands-On the Portal Device
Which makes sense
But you are giving up
Some of your
Data
To Facebook continuing to give it up I should say
And that is not what they said this product
Yeah at best
This is an example of Facebook not realizing
At worst what this is is someone at Facebook
Realizing that hey
We have been caught before on this exact same thing so let's
Preamps that story in a couple weeks where someone
Monitors
Are portal thing
Facebook
Sending us all these
Really
Yay for not being
Complete
Horrible people
Yeah I do the whole thing was
Confusing relaunch
Hey Cortana
A part of it
Louis to do this but I'll give Facebook the benefit of the doubt a little bit here and say
Maybe they were interpreting the question about
Data privacy and Adam photo as
Are you going to show ads on Portal based on the data that collects
The answer would be no
But that's not the fear everyone has about
Facebook
Collecting all this data
The most
Common believe it or not
I get this question a lot when I gosip
Speak to people there like
Hey so what about Facebook listening it on my phone
To my conversations cuz I always see ads after I
I talked about in Facebook is actually
Address that very worrying
But portal in this case
It's actually kind of what they would be doing is pulling in that data to show you as on Facebook
Okay
So you still not buying when I say
I can't
See anyone
I wonder if this will you know
Fail faster than Google's Nexus Q
I have to look at that black
Spherical things
If they launch to do TV stream
It could be I mean
Abby
Curious to see how many they sell or if they continue sell them six months beyond the launch date
All right
Speaking of
Security though
We have good news
Honest friend
Good news especially if you were in the
UK because the UK government
Actually finalized
This
Weekend this last weekend they finalized their rules
Consumer iot device
So
Watch this code of practice they started talking about it in March and they finally
Other comments and everything
Done
And basically finalized it this last
And it is really strong
Guys it is I'm going to include a link
Go check this out
Because it is really long
As you might imagine guidelines are the same sort of things that we
Talked about new default password
Implement of vulnerability disclosure policy
So if
You have advice
You need to have a person that people can check when within a website that people can check in with
To say hey
Is this device affected by this phone ability
Keep your software updated
Securely store your credentials and
Securely store sensitive data
Which surprisingly
Does not always happen
Believe it or not
Communicate
And they actually in this state
Ask for open peer-reviewed internet
Minimize exposed surface attacks
So operate on the principle of least privilege
Leave ports open
Try not to have Hardware that exposes you to access
Access for everyone
So
It is good here ensure software Integrity so
Please verify your software using 6
Mechanism
If devices
Have unauthorised changes
Kafka consumer and no
Say hey
Your devices
Ensure your personal data is protected
Make systems resilient
Outages
I really like this take into account the possibility of adages
Data networks and Power
So as much as you can have these devices remain operational
And functional obviously your lights aren't going to work when the power's out
But
Your door lock should work
Even with a key or maybe if it's battery powered with keypad access if the internet is
Nutrisystem Telemetry data this is something the best companies do right now
So if you're Gathering data from devices
You should be looking for a note
Right now as a consumer I can buy
Security add-ons to
My mesh routers
Pitbull actually
Look for this
Oh hey
Stacy all of a sudden your TV is downloading a lot of stuff and it's
Calling
Korea
Probably like
Weird
And I think a lot of the devices are available today actually
Capable of capturing the Telemetry data puts the missing piece which is what comes into play here is actually monitoring it
Yeah there are actually some companies like
The Judas
And I'm not
I say which ones but they're
So
Make it easy for consumers
To delete person
I am so for this you guys I cannot tell you how many times I go to uninstall a device
I can actually delete anything
I'm just going to
So
Make installation and maintenance of devices easy
Please
Invalidate input data
So this is a little
Esoteric
But just look for data
Wacky
And if you see it
Don't necessarily
So one of the examples that give is out of range
Data so a temperature value that is beyond the limits
So if it says it's a hundred and fifty degrees Fahrenheit
Inside someone's house
That's probably out of Ray
French that's not something
It should be
They're so
You're going to validate that and make sure that it
Accurate Buffet
Are you actually take a
These are just guidelines just to be clear
The UK government does
Plan to
Review how to actually Implement these
Through legislation as well but there's
Smartly taking their time to evaluate how to do that
So at some point the future some maybe all these things will be enforceable but at the moment they're just guidelines
There have been two companies they say HP And Hive
That have signed on and committed
The following is code so that's promising much better than what we have here in the US which I knew last week we talked about the new law
California time
I mean that's just a
Bare minimum first step
This goes well beyond
We didn't see an expiration date
For devices which I still strongly want
But
Still think this is
Really
Excellent
Policy
So go UK and for consumers cuz that's mostly aimed at device manufacturers
And platform players
But for consumers they have a shorter consumer guidelines also linked
To that
They're pretty much the things Kevin and I already tell you to
Hey don't use the default password
Make sure it's a strong password when you put your past
If it has two factors
You should do that
Make sure you update your
Software and apps
Just keep it scare and
They even have this section that I appreciate cuz this is
Honestly
Really confusing for
But if you become aware of an incident and think it affects your device they tell you what to do
Unfortunately they really only tell you to visit the manufacturer's website to see if they have information
And then they also have a
National cybersecurity Center
That might also off
Offer guidance
So that mean a lot of times like I was talking to somebody about hack television so they're like what if my TV is high
There are no software updates I was like
But you need to disconnect from the internet
That's all you get to do here people like I don't want to do that
Filia
So that is really exciting check out those links
It's really funny
But it really is because
Security
Julie effects
University of Kenya
It's cold in here
It's cold and rainy
Have fun
GitHub
Something we talked about that often GitHub
No we don't the reason we are as because we think that this announcement is a big freaking deal
And is
Probably something
People who are building iot devices and services
Would take advantage of
Right and to be clear this is something that
Any developer using GitHub could take advantage of but
There is definitely a sub-sector of iot developers that would
Benefit from this talking about his actions and GitHub connect what is doing
Making it a lot easier
2 basically pull in code and packages into your
Programming allow you to
Used
Create workflows
Poor actions
So
Me neither one of us has a heavy-duty programmer and I've only touched
The service of GitHub so I don't want to get too in-depth here just basically because
I don't have a good feel for how this is going to work but it seems to me like if you wanted to for example build your own if this then that
In the cloud using GitHub actions you theoretically could
It's a way for you to just pull in the other
It's a code
And create workflows that will run as a programmer service
And this is big for iot because
A lot of our current devices have cloud-to-cloud connections
So we'll take the consumer site
It's just easier to illustrate
My hue light bulbs communicate
Pierre cloud-to-cloud interface with
Thermostat so if my Nest Thermostat senses I'm not home you can tell my hue light bulbs
Do something
That's
Really cool
But it's also something
Those guys
Do right
I have no
Influence on this
The idea here is that
Using GitHub
Actions
You can actually create that
Slow and let people
Download that
On their own
Eventually they're talking about possibly having a Marketplace for these
And again
In the world that were entering we're going to have our devices to a lot of the mediation
For us and those devices are doing that mediation via API
And this is a way
The Corral that control that in
Make it accessible to everyone in a way that it isn't
Today
So that's why we think
Embassy
There's a lot of future stuff here
But I think
All right
No
Go back to the home
And how about doorbells
Woohoo doorbells
SimpliSafe has a new video doorbell
Google's kind of like the nest
Halo
It's just like a nest hello
What kind of
Oh yeah okay
A lot like it
It was a little fatter
But yes it's got a super wide
162 diagonal
Diagonal
Field of view
What is a diagonal
If you don't think I know it's the right but it's okay
You can see
Weider
The normal types usually 130 degrees
Usually
Mina sidor
It is it is it's cheaper than the nest hello. I will say that it's $169 and
I don't think Nest has
Infrared sensor
Yes he does has a dual-sensor
PIR sensor
And also the camera obviously so the idea there is
They'll be more effective to figure out
Person from just some other moving object its maybe in his field of vision
Like the nest hello doorbell this has
Infrared sensors that distinguish you know people from things you don't care about their moving maybe leaves blowing or
Car passing by so that's good
Google Assistant it does however work with
Padme so if you're in the Medical University looking for doorbell video doorbell
Yes
And I fully expect actually I got a question
This week about the
I fully expect that nest
Stan Google are going to make
The doorbell
Camera Integrations part of their
The reason to be in their home
So if you have a
Google digital assistant
The Nest doorbells config
If you have
An Amazon Echo
Digital assistant ecosystem you're probably going to want to stick with ring or check out
And
Speaking
Hello and Google integration Kevin
You had some experience with
I did I did I received a loaner unit of the pixel 3XL phone last
Streak at the Google event
And I also got the pixel stand which is
Expensive $80
It's a wireless charger for the phone will charge any phone wirelessly if you have a pixel 3 or pixel 3 XL
It has some additional functionality in that
As you leave the phone on the charger
It will
Kind of creep like a mini
Google home
Experience of visual one kind of like the
Smart display so it will display photo frames or photo album and other things but
Also has a nest integration that so far
Has been the best I've ever seen
When somebody rings the doorbell and Nest doorbell
Normally today I would like to tell my TV or my Smart TV to pay show me who's at the front door
6 seconds later I see that
Person standing there
Communicate with them
This just
Pops up the video automatically on your phone when it's on the pixel stand only takes about a second
I am super impressed I don't know how they're doing that and maybe some Services running in the background
Do not know
Very impressive
Nice I am still waiting for that feature set to get in
Google
Smart display because it is eventually going
It should be
Outside of the doorbell world let's go back to the industrial
Grab
Your
Grab your pipes were going to be talking about
Beat industrial iot Consortium
It was a big event in
Barcelona this week
That I also
Because again too much travel
But as part of this
Bay industrial iot Consortium announced a website that you can now go to
Basically find out how to structure big
So this is the iic resource hub
Include a link to it
But the most interesting thing
I think
Is the fact that they have these
Test beds
Intestines are where
They get a bunch of their vendors
Together to build
In this case and intelligent Urban water supply
Oray track-and-trace
Or a micro grid
It's very hard to say
And you get a sense of what vendors
You might work with but
More importantly you see what you're going to need to build all this
That's because it isn't exactly intuitive
To figure out how to put some
So I like these they include things like
Conclude
The security layers than clue
Analytics
Edge Computing and how to get your
Data
And clean
So these are very deep
And if you're trying to
Get a sense of how you want to do these
These projects this is a really good resource
And that's probably all on
Essay about that
Cuz really
We could probably spend an entire show talk to you about one test
Cuz if that's
Go check it out
Unless you're not at all
Austin Industrial
No I'm more of a consumer of home
All right
I guess back to Consumer I don't know
Inspiration
Kevin
What happened to Mya
My chester-based
The myo armband you talking about
Text wrap it on your forearm and you could use it for gestures to control things and came from Thelma collabs
Switch Amazon actually backed
They were founded in 2012 and raised about 135 million in funding
The myo armband is a daughter
I tried them
I actually had a demo version
And I tried it in
It was weird because their problem was they had the inner
Your face
They did not have the other side of the
Get some things using it so the only thing I could do with it was actually
He was integrated with like son
Microsoft Office or something so I can move my PowerPoint slides
It was
It was pretty nice
Exciting
No
Actual commercial Apple
Location so they had developers building all this cool stuff for you
Operating room
At the end of the day
No one actually built any of these things
So
You had no reason to buy the arm
Sad sad
It is it's
It felt like a little bit ahead of its time
Or maybe it wasn't the right like I still strongly believe in gesture-based controls
I don't know if it's going to be
Wearable that doesn't or if it's going to be like camera base so like
Bitconnect
But I do believe this is a thing that we're going to see
Sunday Funday
Someday
Right
And in other really cool toys
Vector
How do you say yes tell me about your adorable little robot
Yes I I think I mentioned him before I kick started
The Rector
Anki robot
Which I don't know
Why don't you
Kickstarter because they're established
Device maker already in available already in retail stores and online so it's $250
Is patterned after the previous robot cozmo they look identical
Perhaps the colors are different that's about the only way you can tell on the inside though Cosmo pretty much
Didn't have a lot of his own smarts
Interphase through a smartphone app
Vector has
PetSmarts in my smart I mean like a Qualcomm 200-level chip
Bluetooth and Wi-Fi the same sensors as Cosmo horoscope and IR laser
Capacitive touch
Chicanos heads you can pet him seem cute little
Display for screen
Speakers and this also has for beamforming microphone
Switch Cosmo tonight and that's because you can voice control Factor
So I am going to pay 199 and I don't regret it for a second even I will say
This is not something I think you should rush out and buy it's not a home things it is a small
Handheld robot that can move around independently autonomously
Cancerous charger is he smart have to go back to his charger by himself when his battery is low you can ask him things
The weather
Work time or even some
Basic information
I like how they do this that little animation on a screen
Show like the actual weather outside and he gets sad when it's cloudy
And all that so it's a cute little robot just as cute as Cosmo was my wife actually likes us and she likes very few of my
Check purchases 360 autonomous nature of him that
Appeals to me the fact that he's cloud-connected all the time and that they're going to have an SDK available in betta into
December so I can use Python to make him do my own little things you know make him speak
Certain things maybe trigger events will
Adam say hey the Dow is up 2% today
Something whatever I haven't decided yet
My Bitcoin all I could easily leverage that could once I have their SDK absolutely
So he is cute and he speaks back to any of spatial recognition and can take photos of you and what not again
Not a ton of utility yet
However I should add that just this week
Monkey said hey we've asked all your kickstarter's what you want to see the first big feature integration is and guess what it was
You got it
So that's what they're working on there's no timeline yet but it's in the works
And that'll be handyman I have somebody smart speakers are in the house I don't need another one but
I would use this one because he's like a little companion or I can just say what's next on my calendar
I would much rather talk to
So cute robot and have it
Hey
What's the weather outside
Cuz oh my God
Boise speaks the weather to a Ministry due to the temperature and everything
So
I think
Looking at this one is adorable
Do you think it's a good for
Kids and programming
I would say yes you just have to keep your expectations in check and by that I mean the SDK is in
Beta in December I'm actually going to get access to an early Alpha of it next week
So
It's probably going to be
Halo hair mess in terms of making him a few things through programming
Just as a little companion robot with a smidge of utility right now in a lot of potential yeah I think so
You have Cosmo
Your daughter
And I think you told me
She play with them for a little while but then she got bored
And I get that because
How did she have to control him is all through a smartphone app and
It was and he only had at the time
Cosmopolitan
The tablet
Yeah and see you only use a smartphone with a smartphone app
To connect him one time and that's just to set up the Wi-Fi
Stuff at that point he's doing his thing if he gets bored
He'll come off a charger start beeping and booping playing with his cute we're starting to play with them and I think I'm more Interactive
Autonomous type robot would be more
Appealing to somebody over the older Cosmo
Yeah
Sad I don't know if I really want to spend another 250 bucks on
A smart toy that my daughter does
Play with
Okay
Well
It is that time Kevin it is time
To turn
Voicemail
Which
We have gotten many of
But before we get into our voicemail I wanted to clarify something that we said on
Earlier show
Because there seems to be a little confusion about it
Haven't talked about
Putting a smart plug in front of a
Connected Hub as a way to power cycle
On or off
If need be
But
He did not say that you should put that in front of you
Router
The power
Brick Oven
That's correct cuz once you do that you don't have access to
Internet access to turn the plug back on
Which one of our listeners
Put it out to us and we're like
Yes but that's not what we were going after
Just to be clear for you guys
I'm sure if you tried it yourself in front of your router you would quickly discovered that this is not the ideal thing to do
But this is for in front of your house
Okay
Let's get to
This week's voice mail
And just a reminder the iot podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
They have a variety of stylish
Secure electronic locks to choose from
And
Newt that smarter homes
Start with Schlage
We also have a chance for you to win a Schlage
Lock
And the Wi-Fi adapter
To do so you just need to call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
24 and leave us a question
Yay
And when you do that you will be entered to win we will draw this one at the end of October so midnight
Night October 31st is your last chance to enter
To win this month's lock
And now
Let's go
To this week
Question
From Paul
IStation Kevin
I'm looking
4-H
Smart Lock
@works natively
On Wi-Fi
Rocks types
Scene
Are you Bluetooth
Or some other iot
Play Network
That requires
Conversion
The internet
I should say WiFi
This is
A good question
How many thoughts
The reason that you don't find a lot of Wi-Fi locks out there is because a lot of power and people typically don't like
Changing the batteries on their locks
But
There is a Wi-Fi lock out there it is
Hampton
R rela
It just launched
Couple weeks ago
And this has both Wi-Fi and solar power
So this is outside your front door
You could actually avoid changing your lock on this thing
Six months or so
If it's inside
I got a garage or something like that and doesn't get
Sunlight
It's probably only going to last a month
So
Keep that in mind
And know that you would change batteries
Another thing to keep in mind about this particular
It's 300
$19
Which is which
Kind of expensive but that's because you're paying for
The solar power
Probably mostly
And it's a nice looking like I mean
Materials
So you can only buy this right now for the Hampton website
And the
Ace Hardware Ace Hardware yes Ace Hardware Store
So those are your options
There
Although I would say
Here's here's my option for you a lot of the connected locks out there have a Wi-Fi
Rich see you don't actually have to get
Like a crazy wink or SmartThings smart home hub
You can just buy the bridge so August offers this
Nest
The Nest by Yale or the hill by Nest lock off purses
Schlage lock
And I think actually the Kwikset locks
Do as well
So almost all of them have the lock Plus
The Wi-Fi bridge that allows you that room
And that about wraps it up for this week show remember if you have a question
Give us a call at 512-623-7424
And you will also be entered
To win a Schlage
Now
Stay tuned for our guest
This week's guest is
Tio
Sui on
Who is the CEO of espresso
Which makes
Esp32
To chip that a lot of people are using in their projects
And you're going to want to hear his thoughts on
China
Shipping
Iot devices secure and working for a
What years in the future and more
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Is cod
10th and we are welcoming back
Frank antos Whois
Cognizant
Global Market
It's leader for iot
T services
Drake
It's a secret to be back
Last week
You gave us a
Cool example of how cognitive
Customers
It was a global grocery chain
Using and iot solutions
Keep food safe
Fan save energy
What's up for today
Yes last week keeping food fresh
And did I even fresher
Play moving water
Food and water
Both things
We definitely
We seen a lot of activity with industrial Giant
Navigating the shift to adopt iot
In response to their business
What if i get appium client
Mix complex
Industrial water pump
Drinking water to cities and villages
Wastewater for industrial applications
Like Dixie Brewing
Also Heating and Cooling
You also have access to a fluorescent tube
Water pressure and volume pump is working
Lauren performance
I go to the water
Old client is used
Bumps
Flight information
Performance
But also on the chemical composition of the water table
How is it used
They understand the consumption
What changes they need to make their product design itself
Insulting customer
For the customers they have like
Sacbee understand
The chemical composition of bottled water
Chicken sub chemical spikes in water supply
It's a safety issue
They have to investigate
Distance from Kingston
Love you
In the context of
Industrial application
If the pressure of volume
That is going through their system School Beyond
That could blow up some sisters in town
Early Warning Systems from the applications are using sensors
Help prevent our customers customers
Having these.
Immensely valuable
I'm so bad customer
Delegate to the spa
Sounds like a win-win
Adopting
Digital
Database iot solution
Are you busy Avenue better monitoring
Safety label grooming products
That was a great example of
With industrial IO
Where can we go to find
You can find out a lot more about this use case and many more
Adult website called msm.com iot
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is Teal Swan who is the CEO and founder
Espresso
Hi sweetheart
I'm so glad you could join us today
Hi Stacy
Is my cousin to be here
Okay for those of you who don't know espressif makes
Very popular chips that makers
It companies
All kinds of folks use they sold over a hundred million iot chips
And Sweden is here
To talk to us about
Basically the company and what he thinks is ahead for the internet
So let's get started with why did you start
Espressif
Expressive in a 2000
Because
Thinking that that would be a market full
Indeed
Light switches and
This was the basic idea
Wi-Fi into all these devices
And this was like back then we in the US were not really thinking too much about iot
But in China this was a thing that was happen
Yes I do it distinctly remember talking to
In a number of people about days
And people who sing that
This is the way to go
The only company
Okay and it took you 5 years to get your first ship out
Which was the ESP
80-66
That was like revolutionary
I think you could buy it for really low price it actually worked
For very excited
And then
You guys launched
Esp32 which had both Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Now you guys are working on a new chip correct
Yes
Can you tell me a little bit more
What we have done
Accepted
It's unable to small
Artificial intelligence competition
Literature
Efficient
We already do some
AI related stop on GSP
Face recognition
Voice recognition
And
Earlier on you talk to me about your feelings
About how the iot is going to develop and how AI
Will become part of everyday life
Can you tell me a little bit about that
Being in the technology business
Ideas
Cookie Lyon
Twister
We are at the tops of a revolution in the way
And is unable by a couple of things possible
Progressive technology
Allows this to happen
Iot the cloud
So we saw a lot of data about cellphone the car
And then that's the development
Artificial intelligence
Gibson's powerful technology
So this alarm
ISpy
Which recall contacts
Be aware
Surrounding if you have a copy machine
Coffee machine
Understand
Spacey
A certain kind of coffee
Coffee machine
Also have a camera
That sees you coming
Is database
What you want to have coffee today
What we sing is exciting
I don't disagree with you it's a fun Vision although there's some aspects all cool with them
What do you think that framework is to allow these devices to talk to each other
Because right now we're kind of in this Lake
World where there are no real Frameworks there's a couple companies trying and then there's things that are like becoming de facto standard
It's like Alexa or
Google
I think one of the crucial
Technology
Be used to enable this is reinforcement learning
Facebook
Helping
Should behave
I think it's almost impossible
Everyone's use
Machine
But if you do
You think the wall
For reinforcement learning
I'm just imagining my coffee machine might come with a basic model
Looks like what to read
But yes
I'm going to end up having to train it and if I imagine selling let's say it
10 million coffee machines that's 10 million trainings that are going to have to happen or those going to happen in the cloud or on
On the device
For that kind of level of personalization
Well that training happens in the cloud
Maybe in the device it depends on
Intermodal
Cuz that's a lot I mean the training for reinforcements
Personalized level for X number of coffee machines
It's a lot of Computer Resources
I need that is not insignificant
Yes
Beyond
Behavior of humans
Weather similar
Predicting what model
Okay
That makes sense feel like daily coffee drinker Maybe
Coffee drinker
Final exams are coming up
Knowing that this is Sunday or Saturday
So then how would a person because then I start thinking about how you use this because
When I Envision this time Pike
It's good
AI is pretty seamless write your hobbies like hey do you want your coffee
If it's bad you're like no I don't want coffee quit asking me
And then you multiply that by your fridge
Hey usually do
So how
This world is things both asking us for stuff and maybe even automatically deciding
How does that how do we develop
User interfaces for that
Well I think that
Eventually
This is where
Human being
Should be interesting
Things to do
Flight Washington
GloZell
Because it might help to reduce the amount of
Tell me more about
Rustic
Mineral water bottle
Okay
Because it's convenient
So that might look like a water bottle that communicates with me I need to drink
We don't really know but we sing that
Wait
Drinking water
We always do
Neither one of these clubs
Maybe
Maybe buying a soda
So then I have to ask
What is your vision for
Robots do you think it's just smarter appliances like your coffee machine
Is kind of a robot
It's a very different type of
So
How do you view
Robot
And we are the ones who are building
Vices
Established contacts
So this is how we look at
We like the nervous system
Let's go this is a fun future it's a good future for you because you know you
You got lots of chips in everything
And let's talk about what that means
Products
My coffee machine
Crazy super automated coffee machine
So it'll probably last five to seven
If I think about that being
Connected
Will I have a shorter lifetime because most chipmakers do not most
Companies that build things probably don't want to support it for that long
You mean on the cloud
Both on the cloud cloud or security updates those kind
It shouldn't be that bad
It should not be
But
Today today there's some very like
3 years feels like
Yeah I could have a device and expect you know full support both on the chip level the OS level and
The device level
For about three years seems reasonable that's kind of a smartphone
Ice-T
As we do with this devices
To reduce consumption of raw material
The human race
Waffle
When we
Singapore
Yuan to Singapore
Malleable
And it will last for a very long time
How are you guys doing that
I mean at the chip
This is one of the
In a feature
We open source
In a public domain for a long time
People have support
For the whole 20 years
I don't know
But this is the best apple
Open sourcing.
So what are your big concerns
About
The whole market for the internet
I feel like this could really screw us over as we're trying to
Put chips in everything
Everyone is concerned about
Security
That's one major thing
And I think that happened
What happened
Some incident recently
Security is a huge
Departmentation
But we don't know how
Which
It may not
As long as things can talk
To each other
Yes or no the way we look at it
We are trying to cheat
Within the Wi-Fi
Reseda
Distance problems
What we think about
Basa fish
Innisfree
So if you want to do AI
What is the most
But it's such a power hog most people are trying to
Avoid Wi-Fi companies that are avoiding Wi-Fi are putting
Yeah Bluetooth in things like
Oxygen sensors that require
Batteries
I can't be plugged
Do you think wife I will get more power efficient
Or better batteries for the
We sing that wife I will get more power efficient
There is nothing in Wi-Fi
Stop
From building
Very efficient low-power chip
How would we go about doing
Expressive
ESPN
Another device by device
So you don't
You can power
And a cheesy bread low power consumption
How low is very low power
Consumption what kind of let's do it in terms of like if I have a
Wi-Fi sensor that's waking up to talk to something maybe once a day what would be the battery life on that I know that's a lot of
There's a lot of variables there but
We are talking about
5 microamps
ESPN
Translate
That would be
I think 400 million
No conversions
Okay there is so much activity happening in China
Can you just give me a sense of what is happening what is most exciting there
Where China is just
Surpassing everybody else
In terms of what it is
Well I have no idea because
Frankly Speaking
In what China is doing on
Everyone
Is doing 80 devices
And they come from all around the world
Received
Everyone is
Basically right now getting connectivity
We don't see that
Okay
That sort of makes me feel better
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week