Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
JC Higgins
Kevin tofel
We have
Some show for you this week
We're going to be talking about what everyone's talking about Strava and privacy Rose going to talk about how to make a noose
Skill
ATS Google Assistant
Getting some new
Tricks of layoffs in the iot
And
All about Davos
The industrial internet-of-things
Plus we got some news in the industrial side with PTC teaming up with Microsoft and to do I don't want to call it a skill but
A company offering a Madam a for ITC
Support Plus
We have this week
Add from
Think Central
And
Our Guest
Ciara
Pisticci who is a gdpr in
Privacy
And she and I had a really good conversation
About what gdpr means for iot
And for consumers
But first
What's have a message from Mars
This week sponsor is building an iot device or solution start ahead with a Renee Smith's energy plant
Begin your iot device designs at the software API layer and leave the details to replace him
Iot Solutions quickly with the AE Cloud One kitten connect to Amazon web services Microsoft azure
Google cloud or your choice of cloud within minutes for a limited time get 50% off of 8
Cloud one kid look for the Renee Society sandbox discussion thread on the red Aces rules for him go to state
Stacey on iot cam cloudkit to be forwarded to the discussion thread and get your coupon
Bet Stacey on iot. Com
Cloudkid
Kevin
Let's get this show on the road
Let's talk about Strava
Let's summarize
First for those of you guys who've been living under a rock
What happened
Let's tell me what Strava is for sex
Exercise tracking applications been around for a long time I've used it in the past four foot certain
Smart watches and obviously with phones
When you run or exercise you can track your location to GPS and I do this kind of thing with a different app called
RunKeeper that way I can see where I ran on
Elevation salon
Oops trouble puts out heat maps of
All of the runners data and it's all anonymous
Stencil on what it was recently found out that you could
C on the heat Maps if you search for say a nuclear facility or
Army base
See
Strava users
Around
That area which is a obvious privacy
Problem
At a very high level and recently had a very lower level
Was found out that you could even get the names of people find their heart rate and so on you knew how to do so
That information came out of wired
Just earlier this week so
That's a big problem and I know strawberries looking into this they had a post on their company blog from the leadership there
It's an issue
It's a big issue
Yes it is
And
We talked about it a little with our guest
So that'll happen
But the big thing that we got to keep in mind here is
Apart of these people share their data voluntarily
Top 10 things in place what they didn't account for is what happened to the data what was combined with other
I think what does tells us
Is that
It is impossible to see what you search
Your data is going
Really unnerving when we start thinking about how we can combine information and different ways to
Help people or two
Discover new things about
It becomes
Searchable online
And
It stays there for
Yeah you're absolutely right
Again I like with Strava does in theory with the heat map is showing people you know it's Community where people are running
Exercising like if I travel say to a London
And I'll go look for a running route it's very easy to go to Strava and say hey a lot of people run
Right here and nice 5 Mile Loop
So it's useful to me as a user
But
Obviously that data can be used in other ways and like you said you don't know how it's going to be used and
It is voluntary to provide that data I actually again I use RunKeeper
I share my map dated with my friends on RunKeeper people that I know and trust
Crunchy person put out heat Maps or anything but if they did
You know what's the policy there because I'm not
Sharing my information publicly would they not use it in their heat map I don't know it's a lot of questions here on how the baby is you
You said you would said
And
You will learn more
This whole conversation
It's not a way for me to
Pumper next guest
Something
There was a really good article in the New York Times about data being
Treated as a
Public good
Because not only is it my data is at risk but
Because of this particular instance
It's also National
Security data
Or if you think about a town that maybe has a lot of pollution
Insurance companies
Look at that see it Based on data
Variety of other sensors
And say hey we're going to charge everybody who lives there a lot
So we're going to start
Conversations emerge where
It honestly
In America because we're such an individualistic society and we put a lot of Burden
Only individual
I'm really interested to see how this will
Play out
Because
This is kind of a community
Good
Evidence
Soar Community problems
Evolution
To a new talent that Madam a half
We tested this
Morning
From your Android phone you can send
An SMS text
Using
Madam so all you have to do is say not Ma
Send a text
Message to and pick someone in your contacts
Next iPad
Kevin
So I said
Send a text message to Kevin tofel
And
She said
Kevin tofel right
And I said yes
And she said
What is the message
April the message
And lo and behold a moment later
Received it
I received it and I also got a little link
To hear the actual audio of your message as well so what you recorded or
What she recorded you saying I got that as well
Which is useful because maybe something doesn't transcribe properly
Play so it is only working with
Android phones for USA sender as a recipient I got it on my iPhone but I could not
Reply back or send
Being mad at me I would have to do that in my messages app
Okay
So
Other music
She is not
Getting ads
Anytime soon according to a story in the information
So
The story ran
Earlier this week and basically Sony
Apparently was
Complaining to
Anime that works really hard on his Jeopardy game and it can't make any money from it
In
Amazon folks are like well
We'll see what we can do
And what they're thinking of doing is making basically
Premium type of off
So
You can use the Jeopardy skill but maybe you pay extra like a buck 99 a month
Extraco
If you're a hardcore Japanese lover
You're running out of questions
Get more
Just for tuba
Don't know if that's going to work but would you pay for something like that
I would I do that I do a lot of in-app purchases for extra features on my phone so I probably would if I really like the skin
I don't think I would do it for Jeopardy personally but that's just me but I do like this better than what we thought was going to happen cuz a few weeks back
Backward recording on
Pyramid
Companies like Procter & Gamble and others were going to
Potentially Hadlock sponsored
Slots on
In search results on a
An echo device
And it looks like that's not going to happen either now because Amazon's kind of saying look we know
The ads are a distracting thing in a conversational user interface so
And we're thinking no ads
And I have to agree with
I do not
I did take a picture the other day
Because you know how if you cut the Echo Show there's a little thing at the bottoms like ask
Not of age
To do this how to say good morning in Japanese
Which was a reason
One that I was like yes how do you say that
So maybe they could run an ad there
But that was about it
That's not a lot of people have Echo
Okay
Next
Google Assistant
I'm going to tell you guys right now we're going to do a little update unsolicited update on the Google
Assistant experiment
It is not going well
But
Google only half the time does Google recognize my voice which means
Only half the time can I turn on my television
So
Frustrating
Cuz that is status through
Next riot
So that's for sure
Let me ask you this is it just not recognizing the commanders at your voice meaning you've got multi-user
Set up
I don't actually even have multi-user setup but I do the voice
Taproot like I did
I have it recognized my
I still want it doesn't it's like
I don't know.
Right
It's about
50/50
So what device does that occur is it a home or is it a home Mini
It's a home
Straight home
And
Yeah
Tip not loving it
So far
Now I did get some lovely
Lovely
Bubbly recommendations
Clairaudience who said Stacy
If you don't like Harmony talking to you in the middle and who would
Why don't you run it through
You know me
Or stringify
Or any of these other things and so
That is a great suggestion I did run it through you know me
And that is helpful
And now I do no longer have to listen
Harmony
Righty Paisley cut out the middleman Bots
But it's less disrupted from a user
Experience because
You're not having something else talk to you now
It's a better
Right so yes
So that is where that
Hole
Experiment stands
My family hates
And I'm not sure how long it's going to continue
We're still there
That was the unsolicited update
Where is
What we were supposed to be talking about
Custom hot or maybe getting custom hot words
Dual calling on
Smartscreen switch Kevin Love
How to buy and
I think that's it
There's a couple things in here but those are the two main ones as you said an innocent all comes from a teardown
Hey Google I'm sorry 95 Google
Went and looked at the latest Google app
Paisley model around the code to see what's in there and they can see the strings for creating custom hot words for the Google assist
Stenton and so on
You have to train the hotword have to see about that
But also in there yes Google Duo for smart displays I do want that
Smart display that we saw at CES that was the without Lenovo or LG
Yeah
Yes
Yes what you can put in portrait or landscape I just really like the design of that
I don't think I'd use it for duo and main reason is I don't know anybody using Duo so
Oh absolutely anyone almost always could
IOS Android emulator
No no I thought you
What do a without
Them having
That could be
I don't see again I don't use because
I don't really know anybody who does
But we'll have to try it
See you guys Kevin never
Calls me
I know but Stacy sends me text messages
Compare Echo
Exactly
And you will have to see if these all come to pass it's very common for Google and any company really to put things in there
Software for potential future features
But we'll have to see if he's going to pass out
It keeps them up with Amazon I mean right now
Jack.
The Amazon calling between Echo switch I've never use cuz I don't know anybody else with the show
So
Right
In other news
We've got
Details
On how many echos at home devices are out there
And
So far
Unsurprisingly Amazon is ahead with 69% of the market share according to
Yes they consumer intelligence research partners
They put out a new report based on survey data and see us only and basically it's like set
Seven out of every ten smart
Speakers made by either Amazon or Google is sold by Amazon
I kind of question this a little bit only because the numbers they have from the survey they're saying that us installed base
They estimate about
31 million
Amazon Echo devices vs 14 million Google home devices
I get us only it just seems really low to me on the Amazon side just because they've been around much longer and
And I realized it took a while for people to understand what an echo is and there was
It took time for Amazon to come out with the dot on the top
31 million just seems
Loaded me if
Assuming the Google home figure is correct at 14 million I just I don't know
I just seems like to me
I don't know if this is super low or not
I don't have a sense
But we did
See
Earlier this month
And survey from NPR that said that there were about 39 million
People
In the US
16% of America
So it's about 39 million
So that kind of
Funeral
Well
Clean out my thought process is how many people just buy one
Well that is true
So
Yes 6
Canzona smart
There are going to be able to just have one
Homeworld one Echo and I get that you want to get started
But with the low prices of the dots in the minis
And the fact that you might use them in different rooms your house I'm in kind of people are going to put one in every room like we might do
I think there's more people that have
Multiple
Smart speakers as opposed to
People that have just one
Which Casey's numbers would be low
The thing is we have to guess at it because these companies don't share these numbers really
Frustrating quite honestly from my perspective but logically it seems love
And it doesn't even count
For what I think is really interesting is putting you know
Assistant or Echo into other devices
Assistant
Is just getting started here but Echo you know you
Buy thermostats
Bipolar
Actually maybe you can buy light bulbs you can buy light switches
The fire TVs with the remote
They all have
Voice
Yeah there you go by the keeper make such a great refrigerator
Put that next to your cute cat
There we go
Okay so
We're still not sure but there's some more information
Simorgh estimates on echo.and home devices out in Market
And that means there's
Plenty of room to grow
If people want that
So now
Move to subdue as pets
Starting with
Sad news
This kind of follows along something we talked about you the last show of the show before because we were mentioning that
I can tile had some layoffs recently
And this week we heard that tracker
Which makes a similar product Bluetooth tracking device has laid off
Approximately 42 employees that's according to sources talking to
TechCrunch
Yeah they just raised about 15 million dollars in August
Tracker did and I know they're trying to get there
They're trying to expand their product into
A service that will work when you know and
Other small
Things like key holders are pens and whatnot but
That's what I said last week you know you have to have a broader
Product-based adjusting Bluetooth tracker
I think I'm not saying that's the cause of this but that's my gut for the long-term
And yes
You're probably right
It's going to come down to just
Okay
Davos
Otherwise known as the world economic Forum you guys probably
Are very familiar with it or at least have
Clocked it
On Twitter
Dallas
Big Focus there was the Industrial internet-of-things
With the world economic
Squirrel adding more centers
The fourth Industrial Revolution or industry 4.0
All those are fancy ways of saying
Industrial iot
Yes
So what they are doing is they had more than 400 sessions
And they're really freaking out everyone's freaking out about
Sensors everywhere
What is going
Best case
I'm less worried about that I think we've got a long way to go before we actually start implementing this stuff at any sort of scary level it's
Still very difficult to do that open to Center in Sanford
Francisco for
The fourth Industrial Revolution
And now
They're opening new centers in India
Japan
And the UAE
And the Earth
Also are announcing a fellowship for postdocs to work in any of these centers
Trying to figure out issues associated with the industrial
Iot
And it is created three councils
One is called the global artificial intelligence Council
The other is global iot
The internet
It kind of feels like
All the hot buzzwords
The goal is to identify ways to regulate these
Share learnings about
Different groups around the world it's the basic
World economic
Together we shall probably think
He's out because
The world
Have a wall built around Chino
Where is Countryside
Work radiator cap
I thought that was interesting
Curious what comes out of it I would like to see what comes out of especially like the postdoc Research into all this
Maybe nothing will but you know
Smart people are finally thinking about all of this and
Government officials are finally thinking about it and
Talking about it whether they'll take action
I don't know
In other industrial news
PTC and Microsoft have
Teamed up
At first I was like is this really a thing
Actually it is because PTC thingworx
Which is a platform for The Internet of Things
So you can basically
Implement all kinds of
Sensors
Automations on top of it
It now will run
On
Usher so we offered as a managed service on top
This is important because many
Industrial client
Anson figure named clients are little leery
About using AWS
So azure
Is familiar to their it Department
Love it
And I'm sure actually has some really strong
Strong iot offerings
Both of the SAS and the pass level
I remember few shows back when we were talking about where's Google
Iot platform we compared it a little bit to Microsoft which has a lot of great tools and ways to implement and manage device
Isis in a couple weeks I'll actually be able to tell you something
Etsy yes a company that is building out a massive iot Solution on Google Cloud
I know so
Apparently it's there and exist
And this person actually told me that one of the reasons why they did it is because
Google's really
Pushing hard in this area once
Good clients so they're really working
Yay
To learn more about that but not for a
And let's see what other news item
Pulling out here
This is
Missed it is a company that makes
Wireless
Access point
Spit off of Wi-Fi
But they also let you do things like establish virtual Bluetooth beacons
And a bunch of other services on
So
It's a very powerful
You know probably a decade ago
Can I go I was really excited when
Rocky King
It was a whole new way of thinking about Enterprise WiFi
Well I feel like missed is kind of like the Moroccan
Of what Wi-Fi needs to be
Within the internet of Things
So excited to see that they have been out
Cathay pacific
I'm not so it's like Mavis Beacon
And
Jarvis had a baby
But you can
Network questions it questions like how many smartphones are on this
Explorer
How many computers on this floor
Linux
All of these questions why is Bob smartphone behaving so poorly
And apparently Marta switch
Be able to
So
Free cool
That would be good so I could use that help
I'm not going to get into my fiber troubleshooting issue right now but I could use that help
Yes Kevin squeezing a battle
New gigabit
Well it's labeled gigabit but it is so not too bad
We won't go there right now
It's not going to spend a lot of time
I've spent a lot of time on that
That's true
Okay
Let's move to
Are voicemail
On the Internet of Things
Hotline
If you want to ask
As a question and have as possibly answer it
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And we
Answer your question
And you make it
We are here
Vioc podcast listener hotline today is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of Irwin
China clock
Electronic lock
Can make life so much easier and working
No more keeping track of extra house keys each member of your family can have their own ass
Access code
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
And now for the voicemail
Hi my name is Doris cast
I love the show and I just wanted to ask
How do you know if your
Google home
Or it could be like
If it has been hacked
And
If so how do you
Get rid of all removed the person being are your
Device being hacked
Bright lights and my name is Isaac in
Have a great day
So that's a good question from Isaac wondering you know how would you know if
Your smart speaker was hacked and what can you do about it
I'm not so sure you really ever know that's the one tricky bit here
I mean if you wanted to try and like Trace network data and all that it might be able to
Find out what
I would say this
If you feel that your home or Echo device has been hacked
Concerned the thing that I would probably do I would factory reset it because any kind of hacks
Are likely things that have altered software somehow or maybe they are capturing Network output from your
Device so I would probably just do a factory reset on my speaker just to make sure
But again it's so hard to determine if it's truly been hacked
Winnacunnet but you know It's Tricky that some of these hacks we don't find out about until somebody who has
Ashley created a hack
And then told the company manufacture the products hey you got a flaw here
And then it's
Hopefully fix
And then publicly announce so
That's why I say it's very tricky to find out if one of these things has
In hat
Chances are though if if that device has been hacked has probably come to your network and you probably have a bigger issue I would say
Yes in now that a larger question
Which isn't actually your question but I'll tell you about it anyway
You can actually
Is there a
Devices you can attach to your network that will monitor your traffic
And see if it's behaving up
Anime stop stalking to
Amazon and start stalking
Something in Shenzhen
Maybe
There's an issue
And it will flag.
So you could even go higher level you could just see if when your device
It when you're not using it if a lot of network data is being
Sent to work from that device
Yes that is true
So those are
Those devices Cujo is one think bitdefender has one
There's a bunch of router type
Products that
Attached to your router or there's actually routers that have
This feature built
2 Euro has acid
Security offering that you can
Pay for
Or if they're going to announce
What actually does Google have
Something like that
I don't believe so
Pretty basic I mean may have things going on in the background like just this morning I found out has a built-in firewall which obviously it should
But you don't have access to it and you wouldn't know it by looking at the apps
In a lot of back and stuff in there
So I don't know that anything I don't want to say they don't because I don't know but I haven't seen anything that indicates I do
Okay so
That
That's all the help we can provide here I also will say that some of these and this is something I've been looking at more in the Enterprise space
But I think it's coming to the
Consumer space
Actually Comcast showed off something like this at CES
Coming out later this year
Is it not only will it warn you it will actually automatically quarantine the device or take it off the network
So I thought that was actually pretty cool
Cuz then what you'll get it
This is notification
It says
This guy
Not only was weird it was weird in a way that was
Approve with
Malicious and so we just
Pop-up blocker
And I think
That's interesting if something's weird they might
Hey your kids laptop
Is behaving kind of funny
You may want to
So thanks Isaac for calling in and as a reminder that number is 512
6 to 3
Temperature to 4
As I had a momentary brainlab
Boxer
Stay tuned now for a message from this week sponsor
Decentraland
For our guest
Kiara
Stitches
Who is going to tell you
Why gdpr is good even for those of us in the US
Taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is point Central
And I have Sean Miller president of pointcentral here to talk to her
So quick
Let's remind our audience what it is
The point Central
So pointcentral is a subsidiary of alarm.com enterprise-grade home automation Solutions
As a business tool
The short-term and long-term managers of single-family and multi-family properties
From the writers point of view
What does life in a smart apartment
As we've seen her last
Computers and home automation has grown in adoption amongst mostly homeowners
Renters have been left a little bit the Dust
Austin place over there
Reasons for get left in the dust are common with people who are buying home automation for the home such as
Just Coster
Install and setup fears develop a problem with
How to deal with the landlord
Cuz the landlord wanted to install these things what happens after they move out
What we've done is make sure that our solution again is not only a tool for the property manager but it's also really an acid in half
That's been for that recipe
For the resin perspective that really starts when they first
CA unit that's on occupied that they're thinking about renting will that be a single-family home or an apartment
Building and it really gives him a wow factor
If you look at the demographics of a lot of ranchers today Millennials tend to dominate it and Millennials also tend to be some of the biggest
Enthusiast of home automation tax when they walk into a
A unit and see that
The thermostat there locks their lights
All controllable from an app
And from one app that tends to get them excited and then there's opportunities to add a little more wild to it
We've had certain partners that will say
Add a voice control unit in there so when someone's touring the home they could just see how quick and easy it is for them to use their voice
And control things around their house
And once I am in
Impressed then I go live there
What are the advantages
The first benefit residency when they move in is Energy savings
Other Heating and Cooling bills from having a Kinect
Thermostat what we see is residents typically see a savings of about 10 to 50% off their monthly bills
The next benefit residence
She is wearing a sanax
And while this may be a little for it first
What wasn't really start to love and enjoy his
Now that get
Download control who has access to the home from the palm of their hand or from a website but also no
Just at home when and where the weather be a child
A pet Walker
Or friend visiting and Couchsurfing for the week
You can control and know who came in and when
All from right there within the app as I mentioned in the app how to see one big benefit is
Of the Energy savings and access to many other services we offer the residents all these Services come together in one app
For the residents of the not worried about
Messing with multiple apps
At all the hardware is already set up and go
Configure so they essentially move in and get to use this system right away and all the data
That these devices are generating
Is being encrypted and transmitted
To our hearts and cloud or we have a very robust
State of policy to make sure that all the consumers data is protected and secure
The sounds great
Where can I go to find out more about
To learn more about essential oils benefits for both
Property managers and residence
Please visit point central.com
Haley would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Kiara Richie and independent analysts covering gdpr and privacy
Hi Kara how are you doing today
Husky say I'm fine how are you
So I really excited I've been waiting for like 2 months to get
A gdpr expert on the show
Let's get started with a quick overview
What is gdpr mean
4 can soup
Thunderman
Shoes it is essentially
Consumer
Human rights
And the difference is substantial
You
How to write
Stop the gdpr The General
Sexual relations with you
Because you buy something
Simply because you're a human being that's the beauty of human rights law
In many ways
It has a deep and profound effect
Hummus
But it's not as such consumer human rights
I would like to add
Not to be pedantic
Really
Regulate
The treatment
Personal doctor needs to get
Rather than privacy
Perseids
Privity of the data rather than individual
Same statement
There's nothing
Private about your personal data
It still have
To be treated according to the rules
Is that clear
Redis clear
If I run around
You know broadcasting my GPS to everyone
It doesn't matter that
Authorities may say oh well you're telling everybody where you are all the time so it's no longer private information
What matters is
Cathay pacific
Protected by the
Just to get the boring bit
How to lose weight fast illegally
To say that it's a regulation Digger jogging it means. It will be
Directions to picabo too old
Member states of european union
We have your kids
Trying to write letter
One continent
Not trying to minimize the different interpretations that might
She let National parliament in trying these principles into the National Registry
The EU regulator
Okay
Cenotes in the foot on the pedal
As of the 26th
One set of rules for the
She wants from individuals defective whatever you are
Okay
So we've got this we talked about the consumer now from the manufacturer so I give us a quick summary of The Sword
Things are going to be expect
Did you do
Under gdpr
Okay what exactly.
Regulating away.
Somehow goodnight was regulator
Give an example
Don't do regulated India
And you know that there is a financial.
Right suit
Everybody knows that.
Regulate
By default
It contains customer
Even if it's not regulated by Financial regulation is not regulated by
Pharma medical Pacific regulation it will still full
We're coming to the
That may contain personal information
Why do I quickly
RumChata
Do you and your
Dismiss
Country fair treatment basin
Skip to be on the right side of the moon
Would you like me to do that
Please summarize
Don't show you what manufactures out the gate right
Individual
Chanel
Kinds of data
Collecting about you
You have to know why
What time does
What legal basis
Organizations collecting
Provision
Chickens
Hope your day is your day going
I have to tell you how long they're going to cancel how long they're going to hold on to that data for
Talking to the big thing
Is it Duke roof lining
I need to tell you
Baby Christie
The following is
The regulation
Any form of inference
Predict
What determines Behavior likely
Preferences in Chinese
The definition
It's no problem
Situated trying to capture the reality of
Predictive
You have to be told
Anytime
Yoga
Predicting behavior
Twisted
You have to do
I mean to say that you have to write to get together
Santa
Christmas tree map
I don't want you to do that
This is a group of things that you need to know
You make cool out the truth
Things that you can achieve demand
Cities that right
Action figures
Json
You can ask a business
To withdraw your consent it's okay I give you consent to that enough change my mind
How to stop
You can tell them
To erase the date
You have the right to demand
Porches Dayton from a Christmas tree
Right see what they said to have your eyes
Correct if it's wrong
Episode 3 of the right to eject
Anyway
Tricky right with your school district processing
What that means cool
The only reason
I have to be able to point to
Give you an actual way of exercising one of these rights
So I have to have him trained
Precision mechanisms
Ultimate
Tri-City Hospital
They talk about you
Images
It is big
Now that this is happening what do you think
This means
Four companies a lot of connected device companies are collecting data not just
A lot of them collect a lot of data that they
Frankly don't need like my wife I
Address and all kinds of other stuff so that probably is not going to be painful for them
Get rid of but there are other
How my refrigerator is working so they can do remote Diagnostics
The feels really interesting income
How do you sync
The customer experience will change under this regime
Will come back to the shop but it's not just people in the EU but I see your point
What is likely to happen to the connected consumer
Because there's no denying.
Personalized
Expensive frictionless
Which that boy is based on a certain amount of
Algorithms
Peanuts know what you're about to
And I'm ready for you
And the fact that you
You may not want to
Dodge manufacturer
Provide the service
Did you find
2 things that will
Stop
Sophisticated
Commission interface
Coconut
Anal to devices
Creative enough to be
Easy-to-Read
Easy to understand.
Granular enough
So that you can tell the device
Okay
Location data
Not my
Gyroscope
Today's I don't want you to know what I want the first or the last
Greater
When it is going
Force between you and your device and hopefully
Obesely
Companies
Specializing in this such as new interface
Content management
It's crazy
If it is
Nutcracker
The resident
Ruby station so they do understand that please
Yet at the same time though take-no-prisoners and
Buying setting
Customized date
Come down on you
In the US
Obviously
Several
Business
Change
A lot of business models
Baseball
And it will require
Creativity no tomato
Phone number customer information request
You can see this
Going around
Right
Deployment
Machine learning
Address to predict what altitude
Start a pitching machine in the human
You mentioned enforcement so we should probably talk about what this is going to look like
I mean I'm a 26er bunch of coming
You are totally not
The coordinates are these
Are there any lawsuits
Well depression
Strategy strategies
We're here to
How to get it right
Favoritism number of steps
The ultimate in the signs
Financial
Turn to the Flying
They can send me give advice
Southern Cremations
Question answer you start seeing
A lot of communication coming out to companies
Come out of the very nature protection authority for example
Forget that the sensible information The Regulators
Lights
Data entry
Is it supposed to look good for accountability first and also I need the guide
Great to meet you guys and daughter then
Vacations
One thing that I am looking forward to is actually journalist across the EU looking
And requesting their data so what day do you have on me
And once people start to see that I'm very curious like we just had this Strava
I'm sure you saw the guard
Basically showing anyone
Where military US military bases
Based on
Those people's exercise soldiers exercise habits
So I looked at that and I was like
Actually maybe not
What's Travis for you
Use it to show people your runs in your routes
But you don't mean that context becomes problematic so I'm like oh does the military set rules against that
Two-sided nature of the Beast rating Pittacus
OMG that's a sharing platform of consent involved
The world of data Schlitterbahn intended consequences and so frankly is the date of the world of this regulation
We try to do our best
I'm sure
People who signed up to
The service
Nutrition data
What they probably didn't know that
Get cross reference without a date
Nobody quotes
Combination
Combinations of data points
Can identify
State precisely
You know you're Italian
What date does
When it sheds
Because of manufacturing is because the biggest change now is that by default
2 and Pregnant
Catchphrase
Is that you really have to
Side
How much
Trisha
What it means to
Deformed granular
You never find yourself in a situation where you're over sharing
Don't understand
Should be set to do not share
Presumably
Military personnel should have been trained
Say okay
I do not open to the sharing.
Kind of information
Results from a combined
Right and I would say maybe Strava in combining
Fitness data from everybody with geolocation to create these beautiful Maps
Maybe they put that out as a marketing
Effort
Primarily encouragement for their user base but also a marketing effort look at
What people in Strawberry doing you could be them two
So from that standpoint Maybe
Be a part of the fault lies in
Did you really need to use that to Market you could have just kept all that there and lived
People share within the
Community
That just makes it a little little
More difficult
To start
Creating a struct
Competition cycle
Okay
I'm going to go he mentioned that this isn't just about
People in the EU
What did you mean by that
Okay
About Timothy you have these rights
Your bone in your pinyin
You need to have some connection with your opinion I thought you'd have some connection with your opinion but
It's nothing to do with your citizenship States
So let me give you an example
You have
Personal data
If you are
Continue
You're not going to eat you but you're dating
Handled by business database
Or even not even you know your
Kendall Electric
Got the business that makes the decision
How you doing
Should be collected handle manipulative
Is based in European Union without using too much
Jogging butt
Or the best
Netflix Adesa auto business.
Make the decision about this
Collected about how this
Summer connect
Then
Territorial scope
Because you can think of
Outfit ideas without
Source data
India
All the major corporation to go to operations all over the world
And this is from
Did the service call centers
Alyssa
But
I thought you were
Same time
Companies report into major
You Beast
Nationals
Lego
They will
Quotes
Netflix
The data wherever this data is in the world
There is one connection
Piety Street
Wow so everybody who's got their based in France
Those who have Whiting / Nokia gear
Also based in the EU
All of that data suddenly
Wow
See how that works
Let's talk about the implications for innovation
And we touched on this a little bit a lot of
Google's efforts when it comes to computer vision in Facebook's efforts there
Have been because they've been using
Photographs
You know they created this amazing image database
Of crowdsourced
Photos from us their users
In some cases I don't know if people know what they're going to do with
Potato sets one thing but the second is
Some of these services are incredibly handy and I don't know what it means I mean we profile what a
The point of teaching a computer how to see is profiling in a lot of
Always like this is what human does Heather likely to behave
This becomes really important for like autonomous cars
So how do we balance these thing
When does the gdpr do a good job
I didn't know
I think the important thing is that a regulation
Any piece of Little Canada
I can give you the guidelines
Can you be the Principal
ITS Technologies jobs
Find Solutions describe
So it's not a regulation that will ever be disbanded
Technical standards
Technical a specification doesn't work in the future
Sunday
What type of weave
In Innovation terms
How do you make that
To the individuals to stay tight
Flexing
That unless
Think about that date
They were not be able to
That's fine
Blackmail
Either your data or no service
Wilson
Typical moving in
Set a timer
Mourinho chisme personalized
Heated products
Different shades
Renovation
Different
Commission on
Personalization in return for that
You talking about large quantities of data set
The consent change Toronto
Commission
Trailers
Is it a problem
You do not have grandfathering rights
Even if
Centos
In the previous of the previous
Regular
So you count just recycle them
Stata
Send it as a big Trend towards re consenting
Descent
Finding ways to connect fresh date
Smoke
Worthy lineage
Reliance
Something
Continue down to the essentials that you need
Animal
Wow
I feel like we've learned a lot I feel like I could ask you a lot more but
We are out of time so
Thanks so much for coming on the show this week
Thank you so much for inviting me
Fantastic challenge
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week