Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
This week's
We're going to talk about
Security principles
Much Ado over privacy
Related to Facebook and possibly as Hardware plans
We're also going to test out something new with the Google Assistant
We got some news bits about
Companies buying other companies in the space
And Kevin is going to share his experience with the
Fibaro plug
We'll share some news about Philips Hue Lights
Details on August
Latest up
So
+ Dr Leslie Saxon who's going to talk about the
The future of
Healthcare
As our guest this week and we're going to have Samsung talking about arctic for the industrial
But first
Let's hear from you
This week sponsor is ring
Rings mission is to make neighborhood safer
Stay over a million people use the amazing ring video doorbell to help protect their
Bring those that security begins at the front door but it doesn't end there
So they're extending that same level of security to the rest of your home with the ring floodlight cam just like Rings doorbell
Floodlight cam is a motion-activated camera and floodlight that connects right to your phone with HD video into
Two-way audio that lets you know the moment anyone steps on your property
You can see and speak to visitors even set up an alarm right from your phone so when ring floodlight cam when things
You'll immediately know what it is
Ring floodlight offers the ultimate in home security with high-visibility floodlights and a powerful HD
Camera that puts Security in your hands so with ring you're always home you guys can save up to a
$150 off a ring of security kit
When you go to ring.com Stacy that's ring.com
Stacy check it out and help support our show
Okay Kevin
Probably
Men that feel like there's two big stories this week there's like
The continuing
Privacy debacle is everyone's like holy cow
These companies are collecting your data
And then on the iot side
Weave
Combine Belkin witch
I know that when you saw that you sent me
And emailed it so eloquent
I said whoa
But all I can think of at the time now
I thought that too that was my splits I was like
Actually I think was more like
So
Let's start with that Foxconn which is a contract manufacturer that we all know and love
Because they
Make the iPhone
They build a lot of products that you probably not aware of yes the iPhone but also laptops by other manufacturers
Windows machines in particular
I think they may
Put some Chromebooks together but
Yeah I mean they must remind me of HTC if you're familiar with HTC which many people are not these days because they're kind
Going downhill
They were at like a manufacturer
Picture of phones
Specifically and then decided to Branch out and make their own stuff
And put their brand and logo on things and I don't know if that's what fox
Complaints to do I suspect actually not
If they purchase Belkin for the 866 million dollars that they plan to spend on it
I don't think a Belkin name goes away I don't think you see Foxconn on anyting
Most of you guys are probably some
Belkin owns
Couple things that
Like hey it's the Belkin
Batteries cables
Accessories
Absolutely so they do all that but they also own the WeMo brand of connected home devices
Which includes Outlets
Lights switches and
Pics of sensors they also own fin
I got a joint venture with fin which actually is a smart leak detection
Company that is actually sold through plumber so it's a different distribution
It's not right to consume
And then they also have the Linksys brand of routers that way back in the day Cisco bought Linksys
Because you know
Radish Wikipedia
Hot Because the Internet was going to be hot and then Cisco is like
Falcon
All of these things are now
Possibly going to Foxconn
I say possibly because this is a deal that probably will be subject to approval from the US committee on foreign
Investment
So
Dismay
Not happen
This committee has recent
The kibosh on broadcom
Qualcomm
And that idea here is that you don't want to let foreign companies by strategic assets for the
I would imagine that the same committee that's involved with saying
Don't buy Huawei phones in the US which apparently had to carrier deals earlier this year
Basically fall through Verizon and AT&T
So you can't buy Huawei phones unless you buy direct or through
Amazon
Payback Best Buy's dropping a line as well for the same types of recents
Sew-in given this Administration which we just don't know how this
So there's that
Now what
I think it's kind of
Interesting here in Kevin and I tried to find a
Got this out we don't know who makes
Has been in business since 1983
Its Revenue last year was what was its Revenue Kevin
700 and let me get the exact number for 789 million
Dollars
This is not
Awesome deal this is not
Exactly this sounds like maybe welcome site
Let's have an X
So what I find most interesting is
This idea
Contract manufacturers getting into
Its own branded line of stuff so is it going to what does that mean for a company like Flex
Here in the US that are also big contra
Best manufacturers
They've actually seen their businesses change a lot all of these companies in the last cup
Couple of years probably
Last for five years as more connected devices come on the
So they're investing a lot in
Helping companies that were not in the tech manufacturing space get into
It's so when I visited Flex
Example of couple
It's back I saw that they had a partnership with a clothing manufacturer to make smart clothing
And
They had a whole team of Engineers that
Just like testing out crazy stuff to offer
Non tech companies in Partnership
And I thought that was kind of like an interesting way to move that business forward a little bit
I'm curious if we'll see them try to buy their own stuff and kind of go upmarket if you remember it's a possibility
I don't know
Yeah I don't know if that's a tough call it and it's I think it's very challenging for a contract manufacturer to do their own thing
You know they're behind the scenes company they're not known to Consumers by name I don't know I mean
Part of me says maybe they're buying this for the patents apparently r700 patents involved in this deal as well
Petabytes
I know they were saying and we're about to see a lot of patent Act
Activity in
Consumer IO
He's so maybe but
I don't know
I just I feel like
It's tough for a company like this to
Make your own
Stuff and sell and also make
Gear for other companies that may compete in the same space that that's going to be an issue I think
And for consumers that are sitting there going to wait I liked my Belkin stuff
For the US and now I don't know if I'm going to trust routers from China I thought this instantly
I was like
China is a scary place with a surveillance technology
Bent
But I would say to you that
A lot of you probably have tp-link
Gear with
Which is a Chinese
Yeah
Maybe
Maybe you should
I do that feels like
That is what we know about this deal
So let's move on to our other big story which is
Facebook
We'll just call it Facebook and just data
Data over Beach I mean
Everybody coming to grips and being aware that this is happening
When we've been talking about it
Are your side
Yeah I mean we all knew that Facebook and they're not the only one obviously but Facebook was collecting our data
Right
You always say you are the product
You're using something like Facebook
This is a mess because
It's still a question of did Facebook really do anything wrong when it comes to third parties getting access to that
Data
Through various apis and creating apps on Facebook
Quizzes and so on and so forth
So
I'm still in kind of trying figure out do I blame Facebook or do I not for one thing and I don't know how you feel about that
I think what we're
This is an apple
I think this is us coming to Reckoning
Reckoning with the model that we built
And you see this in this type of
Conversation but you also see this right now with all the paintballs that are being erected
For various
Journalism sites
Write the internet used to be
Free and
Everybody was open it was free it was all these things
And what's happening is
We're gradually locking away parts of
That doesn't have to be a bad thing I know you know anytime you take away something that was free it feels awful but it's all
I also like we talked about with iot the business models
But we've accepted somewhere like wait a second what is this mean
Maybe I don't want to accept that
I don't think people really understood
Entirely
Not what they were getting into but the ramen
Applications of
And you can see these ramifications
Like we talked about
Digitization makes everything searchable by
So it's much more accessible in a way that it isn't mine just
You're relying on
People's memory
Right and then
It is also stored forever even these stupid things that you don't even
And it can be instantly search so
When you have those dumb tweets that you fired off at 2 a.m. during your college Years you know that maybe you're like
Oh yeah
I don't think that
It's still there
And that people are coming to terms with that they're like I don't like that that's scary
And I think the next step is
Realizing that could be used for
4 and we talked about this a lot on the show but things like
China's kind of surveillance State and what they're doing with their
Social credit
That's
We're not that far from it
I mean ensures they look at in credit card companies they look at Facebook
Understand your credit report
You're right when you say it's we're not that far away and and
China is a perfect example because I don't remember exactly when but I'm going to guess about six months ago so we
First started on the show talking about the scoring
That China is using for all of its citizens
At the time like I wonder what they're going to do with that
And since then they've done a lot with that in just before the show
You would point out an article where
Now if you are jaywalking and
Shanghai I guess it is
Shenzhen
If your jaywalking in Shenzhen
A camera will notice
You use facial recognition through the system
To find out who you are
Put your photo up near that
Street and then send you a text message for your fine
Mean
This is moving
Fast once you have a date at start figuring out how to use it
I want to see a quick and easy implementation cuz I know it's not but if that's what it seems like from the outside
Yeah and that is a fully automated Circle right
That is like
You break the law
Like a camera sees it
Publicly shame you
I mean ask it all happened before you have finished crossing the street at the
Yeah
And then everyone
Fat guy
Don't be that guy
So bringing this back to Facebook cuz
That's where I
I feel like I can look what I brought these kind of examples up to
Because maybe they didn't read dystopia
In science fiction
I'm like hey guys this is
So
You know what would make him stop laughing
Doing what I did what's all this news had a couple days back
And I don't know if you did but I would recommend everybody do this just to get
Some perceptions
Ideas on visualization here
I downloaded my data file from
Facebook and I went through it
And mine was not as bad as some people because a lot of people are complaining that
Every single call but they have made on their phone or phones that they had Facebook install on
There was a log of those calls who they called how long he spoke etcetera Etc
I did not have that aspect of it because
Turns out I never enable Messenger to have
My phone number Access and so on so forth
But
All of my contacts
Friends
Place I checked in
Every post
Every
Photo it's all there I mean I did was a large file
I would recommend people do that just to get some scoop on what they really have you don't think about it but when you see it
It makes you could be a wake-up call in some people need I think
Yeah well in mind I actually
I never had Facebook on my phone
I don't know
Xiamen Facebook
But I did it for Instagram
I had to say yes and then I noticed that yes oh my gosh it had all my calls and that's a
Journalist that's terrifying
Alex just because
And are you have sources that you're trying to
At 10
Think about God what do they know
The other thing I can recommend is if you go to Google
Dot-com take out
You can get your Google
Which is actually to me
In some ways its carrier
Because it's so much more
But it's also I knew Google was doing
And I will also say that Google builds a lot of products that make
Really convenient to share
The stuff with him
I'm not saying that's better
But I am saying that
You know I feel like I get more bang for my buck from Google
Ian Connor related it to because I can test back to Facebook in a second so bear with me
A lot of
People complain about
Privacy aspect of Google
Which I totally got
You're getting free products and services they're getting your data they're getting ad Revenue Etc
That's all on the consumer side if you don't want that you can actually pay
Free G suite and a Google account
Gmail and all that so much less
You can't do anything
Well
They don't have the data now so you're not going to get targeted ads and so on and so forth
But you're right
There's a convenience factor you give up you couldn't complain
Me all the time about this and complain
You can't use Google assistant on Google home
To its fullest extent with your
Book techniques that with your G Suite account that you have cuz you pay for that
And Google doesn't mine that data
So bring it back to Facebook I meant to do that for a sorry
Would people actually
Consider paying for Facebook
As opposed to using it for free
And not having Facebook collect maybe as much then again it gets back to that lack of convenience you won't be able to do as much with I don't know I don't know the answer
Well the challenge with paying for Facebook is
I think if you want people to pay for things you have to become a truly Universal kind
Platform
Standard right and I don't know if Facebook is actually there
So that's it and we talked about this
For the show but we were talking about cuz
Facebook the big story for this weekend
Facebook
Is that the data kerfuffle his
Let It Go
Decide not to release some smart home
Products
At f8 in May
So there's two stories one is from Bloomberg
Saying that it won't release its smart speaker
And then
The information has a story talking about
A device called portal that would use facial recognition technology
To help set up video
Friends and family
Facebook
On that device now plans to process and store the video data
On it rather than in the
Company servers
So
And they might even
Andele por
I would imagine that's tied to that the smart home speaker or display smart
Screen
Yeah but
I got to be honest do you know anybody that wants
It's a product like that from Facebook to begin with even before this date of thing I don't
I can't
I just don't
I don't I mean Facebook has so many users in so many people use messenger like as their default communication between the
My friend so
So maybe something like this but this gets to what we were talking to
My brother uses messenger
I do not
So we communicate via text
Because he
Do you know he sends me messages and I'm like
I'm not inside
So
Horrifying
I don't have an Amazon to talk to some people in
Facebook speaker to talk to some other people in like it's like the
Free carterfone
Landlines
The makery
And then I realize a lot of people to use Facebook for day-to-day message
I use it when I'm on an Android phone with my family because they're all on iPhones I couldn't
You know I can't use iMessage and text and all that but they complain whatever
Yeah that's it is a mess right now it is
All right
So let's move on
From things that are messy to
Things that are
Positive I don't know if it's positive now that we've discussed all this mess but you got a survey from JFK
Found it over 1/4 so 27% of us consumers have more than
3 smart home devices
And another
7%
On two or three
It's actually less than
So 34% have two or more is another way of saying it I don't know they surveyed
So that's
Yeah and that surprises me a little bit too because it's usually if you buy a smart speaker you tend to buy
More of them
For other rooms and that's why we have these small products like the echo
. in the home mini and so on
Sorry I'm a little surprised that it's low on terms of owning multiple
Mayan
Yeah I mean I can see if you would hang out in one main room and
But not
You know I can see it
Course the group that owns
The most is Millennials age 25 to 34
Their ownership is at 64%
They seem to be the type of people that I guess I'm talking about in terms of having one for every room
What we just talked about almost 7 and 10
Millennials
Expect devices from
Avengers 2
That's right cuz people do not want to be in these
Ecosystems get that through your head
Manufacturers
I agree
Before we forget only cuz this is related to I know we're going to go to some other smaller news items
I noticed that the UK has put a draft out
Establishing survey peyote security principles in the funny thing to me was
They were very common sense
There are things that we talked about on the show many many times before
It's just a draft I would love to see this come to the US and other countries
But real quick
The five items in here are
No default passwords on iot devices
All companies providing
Devices-and-services must have a public point of contact for reporting issues
Companies must keep all iot software updated yay
Personal data shall be processed and accordingly
Applicable data protection
Is the best y'all
As part of the musky pelayo
The functionality of
And
Companies must publish an end-of-life policy stating the minimum length
The time that a device
Will receive software
That is our expiration date
Yes
Isaac
And then finally
Customers should be able to delete their personal data easily
Which I totally understand you're going to disable a device tell it whatever replace it so
Yeah this is going to be out for
Public
Comed in the UK through April 25th so I'm looking forward to seeing what happens there and I hope this spreads
Me
To this was released by the UK's department for digital culture media and Sport
So if your look
Insport okay
Alright so you know if you kick that soccer ball on the
Left on the pitch last it will know
And keep your data
Protective
There are
Footballs and basketballs
I got a cigarette
All right
Kevin is
Pro football
Pro soccer
Yeah
Let's see let's talk about some short news bits
Here to help you throughout your day here are some things you can try saying to get started
Treetop
Set timer Google sister real quick
You can finally send money to People by asking Google assist
Let's see what happens
I'm going to try it I tried it actually Google it does not support that yet just so people are aware but let's see
Send $1 to Stacey Higginbotham
Example you can say
The first one
Alright which payment method do you want to use
I'll have to tap
Sorry for this order
I hooked up my
Yeah there's another way the way I set up on Google pay
Before the show which I connect my PayPal account
I'm going to stop her because she's going to repeat everything I just said
Huh
Interesting
Oak stop
Well that didn't work at all
Well alright we'll see this is what happens
Or pre-recorded demos that will keep in because we want you to experience exactly what it's like
Use
Thanks
Awful maybe because I didn't
Connect Google pay to assistant maybe I have to do that first I don't know
But
What are the steps that you
Or what does it say you should do and what
I don't know if there are any steps other than having
Having Google pay setup
The recipient will have to have Google pay to receive the funds
You even get to that part though I don't think that's it
I don't think that's it and I know that eventually they're just going to have a
A separate
App for this a Google pay send app for peer-to-peer payments but
Odd
Can I use it on an Android phone to
All right
Well
Seriously this is possible
Little Google story Philips Hue scenes are Now natively supported by
Assistant
Yay
If he doesn't remember this is my challenge with my Philips Hue scenes
I can never remember
Weatherall called
If you can remember them
You can now use Google Assistant
Send it to actually play the scene
That is correct
It's in the home control settings of the Google home app so you have to do that
They originally supported
Not reason but eventually supported Philips Hue Lights just for the basics right the lights yes but not the same so that's the part that's new
Yes and
You can always support your
Seems like you know me or SmartThings
And those also work
Assistant so this is just native
I did notice that Google and Amazon both have a different
Feeling for what a warm white light is
I don't know what I did a video on it and I was like
That's weird but if I tell Google to turn my living room lights to a warm White
It turns it to a almost yellow color
But Amazon turns mine too
A white color
Daylight
What they all need
All of these assistants need a setting for
You defining the
Color temperature
So that way
I'm going to disagree with you
Because I don't have any people
I think they should have
Universal RGB code cuz that actually exist and they should adopt that
Lakeside whatever Phillips says is warm white they should
My hunch is the API
Could be
I'm going to keep it simple to not have to configure that I agree most people don't want to do that
But I'm not one of those people who want to do that
People like me
Louis, and I'm going to stay at in the middle
Yeah that's
The lowest common denominator in the first place
We also have news from particle it is an iot development board
And they have
Acquired
A company called red bear labs
It is
Weather
Closest professional partners
Redbear does
They make
Connectivity
So this is basically
Is a company that's been making iot
Hardware platforms plus their device cloud and device OS
They really wanted to get deeper on to the
It's interesting that
Red bear
The first product was a Kickstarter
Yes just like particle
Oh well there you go
I'm interested seems interested in me.
A Kickstarter product would be eventually a company gets purchased but
I didn't know particle was a Kickstarter as well
Or maybe it was an Indiegogo
It was a crowdfund
Apparently the particle mesh boards that have
Paris latest
Version of
Hardware development kits
They have
Mesh capabilities for Wi-Fi Bluetooth
Is Aunt
I think cellular
Maybe
Baidu for cellular and yes
So
Those were developed in conjunction with
They're so you've already seen the results of their collaboration
Just to bring him on in
Yay
That is a little bit of news on that front it's it's actually good news because you know I remember when particle
Particle launched
They launched with
Dozens of other companies that
We're trading iot development
Forum boards
Very few of those companies are still around there are still some
Imagine
Most of them died or just cut it
Went away for lack of you so we're going to see a consolidation
And we also have August
We have been remiss we have not talked about these updates on the August
Locks and doorbell products but in the last month or so
I've been a couple big news items from them
At
Nice items will be honest
Is those of you guys who have an August doorbell
Like me now get 24 hours of
Recordings
Free
So this actually I thought was awesome because it's like the doorbell games getting kind of competitive now that Amazon has bought
Ring and
Lawsuits from
Skybell and nest
But their doorbell
Also basically
24-hours free
That's really useful
I think
Cuz if you missed the call you can go right back and see
And then they've been able to
Lock
On Siri
Yeah you can actually unlock
With Siri using anything but a homepod and I guess
The idea there is those are devices you carry with you where is the homepod is in your house or somebody might be able to scream through your door hey hey
Unlock the door
All right so, do you want to talk about the
Fibaro
I do I'm actually going to talk about two things because they're tied together
Because I couldn't use the fibaro plug
Until I set up the Nvidia Shield
SmartThings link
Because you need SmartThings for the fibaro plug
Well it's a Z-Wave plug
I'll get more to that in a second
But I just want to mention poor folks who are familiar with SmartThings this basically this USB dongle of East
SmartThings link
Plugs into Nvidia Shield set-top box which is what I have and turns the set-top box into
A SmartThings Hub
I was not that familiar with SmartThings list my first real foray into things
With it I have taken everything off my wink hub
And set it up with SmartThings on the Nvidia Shield
And it's no different use the same SmartThings app use the classic app for now
And it was fantastic and in fact I'm finding that the
USB
Dongle which houses the zigbee and Z-Wave radios
Has much better range than I found in the past mother products hubs in particular
I don't have to put my Z-Wave devices for example real close to the hub
Which is outstanding so
Having said all that
What's the weather tomorrow plugged in
Because I had to use it with SmartThings
It's
It's very nicely designed it like all of them
List of all products it is essentially a
Three prong outlet that you plug in
It monitors in real-time the amount of energy that's being used by something is plugged into it
You can also know if you're using SmartThings you can turn it on and off remotely
Outside the US
Deport which is very very nice to have
And it's
Also designed so that it doesn't take up any rooms that you can still use the second Outlet in your wall which is awesome
Yeah this is a Z-Wave model again with the USB plug
So
The interesting thing is
Even with SmartThings and I had to install a custom device Handler that tomorrow provided me in order to get it to work with SmartThings
I can see it I can remotely turn it on and off in the app
I can see how much juice it's using right now our voicemail Raspberry Pi is running on it
It has even peaked at more than
2 Watts at any given time
So that's obviously a low-power device
The little LED ring around
The front
The plug
It will glow in a different color based on how much output
Energy is being used so that's really cool
I can't do much on the automation side and that's really because to do that you need the fibaro
Controller which is their Hub and I don't have that so I would love
Smart things to say
Hey when
Certain devices turned on in my wife's hair dryer in the morning after she takes a shower
Turn on the lights downstairs cuz that's what she's going next
Every single day without fail
But I can't do that type of automation
Solely through SmartThings unfortunately so if you're going to be limited if you don't have enough
Sbarro
Controller
Other than that
Really nice I like it
I like I like it and how much is it and would you pay that
It's you that's the thing tomorrow pricing there tend to be a little bit higher like if I go back to see my remote inside
Switch and I think that might have cost me thirty bucks
This Is 50 without the USB
60 with USB
You are
Okay
And now
Let's go
Are this week
This is the last so basically if you send us a voicemail
By the end of this month so
Say as of midnight on the 31st of March and will call that midnight Central Time
You will be entered to win a wyze camera
So
All right
Voicemail I should tell you to call
Where to call five one two
6 to 3
7 4
And
Today we have a question from Dom about smart
Fox today's iot podcast listener hotline is brought to you by Schlage maker of electronic locks
Schlage electronic locks make life so much easier and more convenient
No more keeping track of extra house keys each member of your family can have their own access code
To see what's possible
Visit schlage.com to learn more
Hey Stacy
My name is Dom
Actually I find it a little bit ironic that
That message was brought to me by Schlage smart locks
Because I actually had a question about a Smart Lock
I was wondering I've been seeing
Smart locks around in
Interested in getting one
My house but
What is the
Standard for or what is the normal practice
What to do with the
Because usually I see the smart locks they only really replace
Like a deadbolt
Or like
Two smart locks
For one door or is there a Smart Lock where they're connected to
Or do you have
Smart deadbolt and then a regular door handle with a lock built in
Which kind of seems to me to defeat the purpose of having a Smart Lock if you have one of them
That's digitally locked in the other one that has to have
Cuz I ain't know the goal to me is to
Remove the key from the equation that way
With you
So I was
Just curious whether you have done
This on at your house
Speak on that topic or
You've heard of
Anyone else doing it I just don't know what to do like what's the standard package
When you're replacing regular locks
Smart locks
Just one
If you can speak on that I would really appreciate
Preciate it thanks
Okay. This is a really good question
And I'm still at Kevin answer because right now it is thundering and my dog
Going.
Yes so it is a good question because a lot of people do have both a
Keylog as well as a keyed deadbolt
Unfortunately.
Most if not
All the locks that I can think of
Tend to work with the deadbolt only
In which case
Yeah the key to part
Traditional lager
Becomes kind of moot
We have one and I don't like that at all
It would be nice if we could see that ice maker is take that into consideration for people who want a key lock as well that maybe they
That works in conjunction with the deadbolt but right now it seems to be deadbolt only
So you would have to leave that
Main door lock
Unlock all the time if that's your situation
What is the key lock in the door knob
Well that would be for if you maybe you didn't have a deadbolt at first maybe you added a deadbolt later
Minister minimum level of security are you going to get
Yeah you're going to have a key door lock
And then maybe you add
The deadbolt door as a secondary thing but no matter what your front door's always going to come in at
Keyed door lock
Okay yes and I never really thought about this
Because yes I do have one and we just leave it alone
Same as me
So that's your thoughts
Process. And if you're looking at this sort of thing
Think carefully about what you're looking for in a Smart Lock
There's things like the August and those don't have key pads at all they're just remote
Lock and unlock
There's things like the Kevo which also don't have it
Keypad
Press it in
It's theoretically unlocks mine was a little iffy sometimes
And then there are those with keypads and those are candy because you don't actually need your phone you can just
Punch in the keypad number and then it opens
But the remote connectivity is also nice because then you can set up
Cool like
Automations
So
There's a whole wide world
Blocks out there
All of the Bluetooth ones
Be aware that if you're going to buy a Bluetooth lock
Did you just going to
Need your phone to be around it and you can't do anything remotely
To unlock it
R Lockett
Unless you have one of their
They sell these Bluetooth Wi-Fi converters that are basic
If you have a Z-Wave or zigbee lock
You're going to tie that into a something like a wink or SmartThings Hub
And then you're going to have remote access
Those are just some things to consider as you
You're buying
All right I think that's it for this portion of the show
We have Leslie Saxon who's talk about the future of healthcare you're definitely want to hear that because it's it's
It's a little surprising her vision
And a message from our sponsor, hey everyone we are taking a break for The Intern
Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Samsung artik and we're going to be talking about the end of
Was Sarah Peach
Who is the senior director for business development
At Samsung
Just a reminder for our listeners what is Samsung
Samsung
Smart iot
Keep that phone is an enterprise-grade peyote plant
That combines
Hardware
Cloud services with built-in security
Peaches and ecosystem of tools and totnes
What we're trying to do is help
Customers get to Market pasta with c
Secure and scalable
Iot Solutions
Okay and what is Samsung doing in the industrial space
With a Samsung
We are trying to help a number of different industrial customer
One of the key groups of the industrial OEM
So these are companies that want to develop connected, and they want to deliver services
Based on those connected products
The date if it's coming from those products another group
Is manufacturer
Initiative
Integrated looking to Ida manage the assets better or to get better insight into that productivity
And what kind of use cases are you seeing soap
Wishing a very wide range of use cases for the most common one we have
Is asset management
Either an oem is wanting to
To track and understand
The usage of an asset
Being deployed in the field or a manufacturer
Please try to understand the productivity of the assets
A usage and the health
Of that acid
We actually have a very exciting
On improving efficiency of plant workers in an assembly process work
Spend a lot of time checking
On pot inventory levels
Got something wasted time
Go to check the level and it's still fine
$2 taking a break from the other activity joke
Working together with a couple of Partners
Shoreline iot
And high packs
We're helping that customer
Can monitor their inventory in real time and that is still
Communicate to the workers on the plant for what's going on with that invent relevel
How we do that is with wearable
Samsung Gear SmartWatches for the one by those were cousin guide those workers
As to when and where replenishment is needed
K&S you built these things what do you see as some of the big challenges
Customers have
Seeing customers
To need a very clear veginal investment for the iot project it's important for them to be able to do
Define that
Before the project begin
And really understand what the value by Disney
Timing for that value
We also seeing customers for whom iot security is a big concern so it's a very important for them to do
Sign in security
From the outside
And a Samsung artik
Already helped with a multitude of security service
And if you guys want to find out more on how you can use Samsung artik for the industrial iot
Visit www Stacey on iot
/ Samsung artik
Okay so you guys will be at Hannover fair at the end of April
That's absolutely right we'll be showcasing some of the
Impact the Industrial internet Consortium
Member Pavilion
Wiki happy
With anyone who wants to learn more about the Samsung artik iot platform
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And I'm joined by dr. Leslie Saxon who is the executive director
Abbe Center for body Computing at
USC
I'm talking to her at South by Southwest is part of the IEEE
Tech for Humanity
All right
Soccer socks and thanks so much
Coming on the show this week
It's great to be here at South Pine to see you
Awesome okay so let's just Dive Right In
You are talking about a wholesale change in the way we get medical care
Edgewater
Connected
Well telemedicine I assumed as part of this their wearables are all
Kinds of crazy stuff Soto
Talk to me about your vision
Great I'm actually here at South by Southwest talking about to be part of that vision is part of the IEEE
Tech for Humanity series
Can a few different years and
As the program has about them now talking about a really important part of building the new healthcare
And that's Iris security
So we talked about that at this meet
Eating about how to protect
Digital Data one of the great things about
Digital health is that
It has the potential to really support the health care of every individual
Digitally anybody with access to the internet
So that's kind of a Phenom
People who live in places without infrastructure
People get Healthcare anywhere
Iview what is
A very important movement
Healthcare because instead of sort of
Dummy down Healthcare and making it the quality and experience for everybody
Digital Health can make at the Four Seasons experience forever
That's what everybody
Desserts
Be able to access the best
Technologies
Expertise that Healthcare provides so
We sing
That
Virtual care will constitute 80% of Medical Care in
And that
Bricks-and-mortar care
Hospital visits
Clinic visits will be maybe
90%
Why is that good
First of all it's good because you're leveraging your experts
Over
More people
Secondly it's good because
You can reach more people on thirdly it's really cost
But it's complicated
Okay that was a lot to take in
First off when does this Future come about where 80% of our care is done via some sort of
Internet-based care
Part of it's already happened
I think we're seeing it
Last
What 3-4 years
When no Americans
We're tracking her health even with non medical grade sensors
About thirty 40% of Americans have it some
Quantify themselves with a wrist-worn or some other type of activity sensor just with
Their phone
So what we're seeing now is we're seeing this sort of merger of personally collected Healthcare data with traditional data
So you know Apple announced this ability to support
Are there platform
Traditional Medical
Electronic medical data as well as personal data
And so
We're now moving toward that virtual care Vision Telehealth is one small step
It doesn't really scale
I'll tell housemates as you can get a docker
Toronto screen a realtor
And that's good
But we're trying to do is beyond that so we've created a virtual human me
Simon expert in cardiac rhythm disorder
And my virtual human is fueled by voice recognition AI
She can provide unbelievable in-depth content to you
And a very deeply personal way
When you see my virtual human
Do you mean this is personalized to you or is this just
Something you built that is a virtue
So
Now it's very easy to create
Very realistic furniture
This looks like me
So this is your digital twin with your health data
Yes this is my digital
Play who after you see me in a clinic Hazard if you've never met me
Senior Living in Bangladesh you can ask me questions about heart
Rhythm disorders
Am I
Answers are based on
30 years of experience answering
Impatience questions and every
Buddy L Seidel who answer page
Questions
Data-driven guideline
Data
Lies to you because it's an AI engine
I can learn
And has already templated 36
Questions commonly asked question
And it gets smarter and smarter so what we found is that people
Feel
Learn and understand better when they are in control you're not pushing information
To them they're pulling it
When they want it
Plus my virtual human is
Constantly in the same mood
She's very interested she's
My virtual human has
Standardizing
Information doesn't deliver one way one day
Smarter than me
She doesn't prescribe yet
But since you'll be able to read the emotion in your face
And understand how you're feeling about some
But she'll get smarter and smarter so that virtual human
Really scales I think one of the first things we have to build out
In this virtual system is
High-end medical information form
In the virtual care system it's not the usual
Paternalistic care of the patient is has unimpressive
Play control their the orchestra
Just like other things
You decide when you're going to read The Wall Street Journal
Purses that have posed for
Whatever
Patience
They access things when they want they disclose things when they want
They can
Retrieve deeply personal for
Formation that's a super hard thing
Can you get the other things that I'm trying to sell for just
Yours
It's frustrating to try and deliver excellent Medical Care is
The gaps
We have the best experts and Technologies in the world how did we leave it all together for a patient there fam
How do we allow them to deeply learn things they don't get so
Traumatized by
No major diagnosis for chronic diseases they have to deal with
And I think
We can make that a lot better
Potential
So we're really on The Cutting Edge of building all the things that it takes and we want these experience to happen everywhere
In your car
Airplane
I can't wait till I'm in a plane and I'm like
Oh my gosh virtual doctor
I'm having a panic attack
Just think about how disgusting
Planes are and how they're not healthy
Now they could be
It could be a place to Enlighten for
I love planes I love playing this kind of
I do everything like a car to play this kind of iPhone I just have to build house offer
Turn Services on
Okay well let's back up just a little bit because I want to talk about the pieces that need to be in place cuz you've mentioned
And obviously software in Crazy places
Or to be
I feel crazy you've also mentioned personalized
Not just you
Being
Export it someplace but also a personalized experience based on
My personal health which implies machine learning
Or models about me so let's break down the
Pieces that need to be in place to deliver this kind
First of all we need to be able to
Get information from you
Anytime
Right
That's medical-grade diagnostic information
Pretty good so
We have a lot of those things already I can get real-time EKG from anybody
I can get
A lot of physiologic sensor soon
Will be able to get metabolic
Information
Continuous glucose lactate blood values that allow me to make it
Safe decision and allow you to understand your
We need to provide people with very high and
Information that's personal
It's easy to say you get a diagnosis of breast cancer to do a Google search
It's very different if you're pre-med
Tulsa breast cancer
How do you continue to get
A very meaningful
Shred to you how do you understand
How your environment may impact your wrist
If you have a genetic predisposition or something
So it's a combination of
Contacts
Learning
And being able to be on you early
What sensors understand how you're feeling where you are where you go
And collect that data and then sort of rational
It's a very difficult challenge because even in my area
Cardiac rhythm
I'm seeing data for instance we have
Programs in performance military athletic
The warfighters are professional athletes that
Isn't my area of expertise but because it's
Continuous data
I'm not used to seeing
So
I don't know what it means
And it scares me
That's why I have to Benchmark
Two things I do know
And I have to wait
Collect clinical events trailer
Dangerous is at
So it's going to take a fair amount of Science and patience to do that but given the amount of data use
Accumulate so fast that will happen you know
Exponentially faster than
Medical progress is half
So this kind of clinically valuable data
Seems like a key element and then understanding what
To make of it like my doctor have a cardiologist and he does not want to see any of my
So
It feels like we need both
Advice for
Medical grade information gathering
But then also
The studies
Will say to you
Hey
Here's a 10-year history of someone in
And here's with this sort of pattern over that 10 years books
Correct are people doing that work
Yeah we're doing that
Work so we can start to develop
The Predictive Analytics but the
Wrist-worn and other senses are getting
Continue get more active
Any one of I think RX
Expertise in the centers we can take
A regulated sensor
Reply to an athlete or Warfighter in it
Non-regulated sensor
Reply to a patient it doesn't matter it's all going to be the same
Wellness will merge with
What's chronic diseases Halo continue
Tomorrow weather 1.1 August 2nd
Another pointer Daiso
How do we get the most hated we can to start that deliver meeting back and when you have more people delivering the state
Collated and contextualize it it's really important
So we talked about having sensor data what about the human environment
Privacy environment what other aspects do we need to consider when we're talking about
Virtual care I don't even know what to call this
Avocado
Virtual care no more
Continuous model
So it's really complicated right just a regulatory isb
Because digital is
Right it's not
Border
So hot
I think of data
We definitely are
Previous
Conception of data keeping
What's good to keep a private lock it away
Digital health is slightly
So we've been working for instance with the FDA
Weird about the global
Model for what software for help to regulate
Chloe
That's been a huge accomplishment
Over the last say three four years so that was pretty clear guidelines
What's a regulated vs. unregulated piece of soft
What about cyber security
Text Achilles heel of digital health
To have health data breach
Cybersecurity is really a
Control shift
It's more
I think about it like
You know it started with sort of young people at the drive-in
I feel like
It starts with
Things like how to say
Create culture awareness of what are good cyber habits because cybersecurity is
Shared responsibility
The patient the manufacturer of the widget
The tax
The cell phone maker the carrier right
The government
So we have to start to build resiliency in our system cybersecurity will be something we have to
Continuously deal with
Don't be breaches but we have to build resilience systems and that's
All the way down the chain
So we work very hard on that
So along the issue of cybersecurity closely related to this is privacy
And I will say that my mom
It's probably at 1 far end
The spectrum that she is
So
So worried
Privacy
She keep seeing
Seeing stories about pharmaceutical companies wanting to use patient data to help
Improve
Trek discovery
And things like that really freaked her
Her out so I think is
We have these discussions about Cyrus
Security we should also talk
What's happening in
The Privacy Rule
So there's privacy in the sense that you don't want your name disclosed or associated with
Right and then there's the ability to take large amounts of data for instance let's say you want to look at all approved drugs
And try to look at all the outcome measures that you have on those trucks to see if you
You can use them for others
I don't think anybody would have jacks
So that's the kind of
In a really
Important area then there's
This privacy discussion
The societies
Impressions
Feelings about privacy are highly generation
To your mother may feel very intrusive to share any bit of data
2 yoga person they may give up an enormous amount of data
For the greater
Could not
Concerned about it so privacy is a really in
Part of this
Pick one of the tenants of cyber security and privacy is that an individual should
Have the ability to
To take them self off
She may be giving your heart rate or giving dated insurance company to show that you're healthy to get a lower
Rate for life insurance or health insurance
You may be voluntarily giving day to you
Employer so you don't want to do that
You should be able to take yourself off
But that right without pain
We're seeing this play out a lot professional
Princess professional NBA players just putting their last negotiating agreement that they won't
Where player
Performance sensors
Because
They don't know if the data is accurate
They don't know how it's going
Secure
And so
Part of that that has to be explained to them
I think that kind of thing
Gift of the governance around
It before you start to
Developing that's all go
Start to happen
What are the policies around
The governor
Medical Data that's collected
Performance or for health
And we don't we have HIPAA everyone don't worry about it
Is HIPAA a enough
It was a very small
Pizza Hut
You know it's really about the collective data in your own ability to cut
Control your data
Because it was clear to us in
When we started building the virtual care system
I look around everybody I said late when I got to do this the wrong way before we go. Let's figure out what are values admission is
Our mission is to supply the best
Healthcare to everybody on the globe anytime
And we are directed toward the patient
Or the athlete or the Warfighter that is our interest
Not
The medical system not the government not the lead not the team it's the individual
That helps us a lot as we start to determine what the government
HEB
It is trying to represent the best interests of the individual is providing the day
One thing I worry about with this sort of effort
Is in the internet we have
Continually pushed
The burden of
Handling
Ticketing at ticketing is just the easiest thing I can think of right now but even bill paying all of this the bird
Chest back to the individual there's a lot of
There's a lot of effort
Were there and so on
Curious what it means
What the role of the individual is
This individual
Continuous virtual
That's a great question I wish I was asked more to really insightful
Question answer
This is going to be different it's not doctor tells you what to do
This is having a real stake a dog in the fight
In your own Healthcare and controlling it and I think that that's the only way we get behavioral change
Is we get engagement
If people have to convince themselves and learn that they feel better with healthier habits it's better for them
Whoever there
Take care of whether it's their kids their parents their spouse
So I I'm all for it but does require a lot more
Without
Keeping patients down on the farm
Staff to understand their drugs
There to engage in their care and they have to partner with us to make it better because I I don't
I spend a lot of time
Interrogating a patient
Like I'm a cop on did you do this or that and then feeling judge I want them to come to me
As a partner
And I'm going to add my little expertise and I'm going to be Captain Sully on the Hudson
Because I need translators 34 years old to sit there and interrogate patients
And everybody
I've done that for too long I really want to be able to
Focus on the people who need me
Everybody else feel care for
And protected but
Takes a lot of
Personal responsibility
From the patient
And the pair models have to follow and they're not there yet
The business is going to meet so many needs
That will create a new
Awesome thank you so much that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you
You like more iot news sign up for my newsletter
Letterhead Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week