Everyone welcome
To The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofu
We have an
Amazing show for you today we're going to be talking about new skills for Madam a
New products as well
We've got some crazy news out of the University
We got some
Fun Wireless
Camera technology
Smart walls
And
And iot
A little bit of news on
A new social media
Comcast Iowa
Subscribers
Mary
New iot chip with Mesh networking
Anthony
Spark
Airrouter
Kevin is upset
About a choice
The key made in
Smart Home
I'll tell you why
And what he's going to do about it
This week I am
Sweden so I interviewed
Two ladies from Ikea
Rebecca Torrey man who is in charge of
Battery lights
And Liana
Kobach
Who's in charge of Arceus
Sustainability effort
And we're going to be talking about
Ikea's Beatrice Markham stuff
How you can design a Greener
Connected products
Also here
A little bit
Privacy
And now
Let's go to another one of our sponsors
Twilio
Twilio programmable Wireless makes it easy for developers to program cellular connectivity whether you're working with a few device
4000k connection fast using no Shenanigans no-contract pay-as-you-go pricing
Devices in over a hundred and twenty countries around the world programmable Wireless offers you the scale and strength
William Network trusted by millions of developers all over the world check out twilio.com
Flash Wireless
All right
Kevin
Big news today
Actually big news last week
I think was last
Amazon
Announce
Blueprints
Basically this is
Templates that allow you to make
Custom skill
And I would do this and I was like
The rest of you guys made
Maybe like this is stupid
But what you can do is
You basically set one of these
Quiz template
And you can
Build your own quiz game
You can also do a fairytale one
You can do it
Trivia one
And
You can actually even do like
Cards for like foreign languages or anything else
I chose
The template for
Houseguest
To try to help them understand
My connected
So it's
Very easy it walks
Through every
You are limited by the types of quest
Selwyn house
Where can I find
Whatever you wanted them to find
And then
Anime with answers
They also had how do I
Was one of the eye
And then I had a car
So
I filled out
One I did notice
That
It's very hard to guess what someone
So
I did a very generic
How do I turn on the lights cuz I didn't want to do 20 commands for turning on all the lights
Variations of a
And how do I work the thermostat
The other thing I noticed is that
When it came time to name my skill cuz
Would actually using
This would actually go in
Madam
Open
I wanted it to be
Stacy's helpful house
But
Was way too complicated for
Madam
And it warned me
So I just called at my house
If you walk into my house
And you say
Turn on my helpful house
You'll get this prompt from Madam and you can customize this
It says hi
Valpo house
What can I do to you can ask me
The following
So
It took me all of five minutes
It wasn't like the most well considered skill probably
But very easy
And I don't know if it's going to help people or not
Well I think
I don't know if it's going to help people or not but obviously the potential is there and I think it's brilliant of Amazon to make it easier to create
Skills mean
Anything they can do to add more smart
Sandra personalization to these devices is going to help and now they don't have to rely on developers to do that when you can do this
Is yourself in a relatively easy format
The houseguest one is a perfect ones probably the one I would have started with two because I remember my dad whenever he would be at my house look like
Hey before you go like he would watch the house when we went out
He would say how do I change the channel
Because of the technology we had in the house that he didn't have any these are the kinds of things that can really
Add benefits of
It's all about personalization and expansion of the echo ecosystem from a service standpoint I think it's
Again very very smart ass Amazon
Agreed and I wonder
Because as they get into business they're actually letting businesses do
Their own custom
Skills for a business
When is this is
India similar
Format for that
It could be I mean just because it's simple and easy but I suspected businesses maybe they don't have an IT department
Probably yes businesses that do have
A lot of Technical Resources
They'll probably just use the regular skills apis and such
Because you can program them very easily and those folks would understand how to do that so
Yeah makes sense
Well I got excited about
Blueprints
Amazon has also
Bloomberg actually discovered that
Building
Robot
Making Kevin and I
Super psychic
Cuz we were just talking about
Tell us a little bit about
Amazon Vesta
Well that's
We don't know much for sure this is all reporting out of Bloomberg as you mentioned a code name of the robot
Effort is Vesta
Which is the Roman goddess of Hearth home and family so that kind of gives you an indication of hopefully where Amazon is heading here
Appears that this will be a mobile
Roving type
Robot that can navigate self navigate actually among different rooms based on early prototypes
I would imagine it has it's exactly what I said to two or three weeks
Exactly exactly
And people may think this is a little crazy but to be honest Amazon bought a robotics company
Back in 2012 I think it's called
Kiva systems
Yeah it is
775 million dollars and Navy use that investment to create
Robots in their warehouse
Does any have
As of
Early 2017 have 45000 of these
Amazon design build robots that
Move pallets around the warehouse is in such they're not picking items for delivery because they don't have the fine motor
Skills to do that
And I don't think
The best iRobot will do that either and I know that makes you sad Stacy because two weeks ago you said I want a robot with arms
I agree with you I do too many think we're there yet I don't see this as a
Task-based robot
The fold laundry and iron your clothes
I see this is more than informational
Robot that could help with presence detection in the house
Customize
Different
Settings in the home for you
Expected will have a camera with
Computer vision
And it'd be an information source that can do no
Follow me around and
I don't mind a camera in the house provided I have control over it
I don't want a camera in every room though so this to me is perfect as I can say robot go away I don't want you looking in here
Sitting here in my
PJ's watching TV whatever
I'm excited by the potential of us that's all I
Inside right now
Sure
You know how's it going to handle
Stairs
Facebook
Yeah
I'm not as excited as possibly Kevin
That's not
Actually kind of funny
Kevin was not a fan of the original Echo
And then
Okay I can see this being is
The original Echo had very little
Final bit of news on the echo
There is now a
New Amazon Echo
Kids edition
I've used the Kindle Freetime app when my daughter is younger on
Kindle Fire tablet
And that was the most aggravating
Confusing interface
I think I've really ever
So I don't know if I'm thrilled about this
Yeah I did my kids are older so we don't use any of the free time type things on the Amazon devices but you know
This is an $80 Echo.
It said I got a case on it
It also includes the free time
I'm not as bad as you would said
If you want you can actually just add
Free time on near existing. For $3 a month
She don't want to buy the new.
Basically
What does is ad
Specific content that kid friendly such as certain skills audible books and other things
You can
Keep track of
Limit their music in a knot
Share explicit tunes and so on and so forth
It's from the anime
Will a lot of your right and a lot of the echo focus it presupposes that you're a a Prime member bu
Subscribe to everything that Amazon offers and so on so forth so
Yes it does it could be though that you could limit adjust the Amazon music service as part of the parental
You know
South exit is a logical extension of what
Amazon already has with the echo
I don't think they needed to come out with a new device cuz it's really the same device just with a little case on it
But it's a way for them to customize it for a different market segments they've been very specific about the privacy
That's obviously an issue when it comes to kids
They said that no data is collected for advertising purposes the only date it that's used is used to make the product
Better I still wonder about that from a
Copper standpoint here in the US
But they haven't said anything about that
Okay
And now moving on to her
What caused the university be
Because we've got some
Some crazy fun news
First step is
Smart walls from Chris Harrison who is a professor with a human can
Computer interaction
Carnegie Mellon
He's got two projects out
One is a digital interact
Out of paper
But the second one
Is something I could
Sienna smart
It's called wall
Plus plus
And basically it
Turns your wall into a
Positive
Touchstone
In the cost for this
So far they estimated
Just about $20
Per square meter
So it's not exactly cheap
But it's not like in
Insanely expensive
And you can do without tools so you just
Put the substance
On wall and then yuan
Paint over it and then you attach sensors to the baseboard
And your wall becomes this
Capacitive touch
From there you can
Can build
Psoriasis on top of it like apps that will say hey I'm touching the wall here this may
Means that
It can figure out
What electronic
Objects are in a room and if they're on or off like lights
Computers are televisions and
This just seemed to really intriguing it was not where I thought of Summer
Smartwall would go
I can see that so you can just walk in and slap your wall and turn things on
Or you could
Touch your wall
I got to say that I do not like the other PDF
But
Yeah you don't have to actually touch the lobby so you get finer resolution in terms of the sensors if you are touching them all but you're so
Standing close enough to it it can actually do
Determine your pose and so on and so forth
It's an interesting approach to mean basically these are little squares
That each one is a pixel essentially like a pixel in a display
And you just
Set these up in a crisscross pattern and then connect them all up with some wire in the sensor then you got a touch-sensitive Wallen
I agree with you this didn't go the way I thought it would I didn't think the smart why would be a sensor I thought I'd be more of a display
Lick with a projector or something like that but
This was
Kind of interesting and I'd be curious to see what people can do with it
Yeso
Will put his link to that in the show notes
And
Can a baby with Chris
Montauk in the shower
The fun project
Alright other crazy news
In the University of Washington has created a
A way to train
Transmit video
Using
Less power
Basically what they've done is
They're using
Backscatter and I should tell you the University of Washington
Has a really impressive Wireless wreath
So
They have
Done research on light detecting wear
People are in a room
The destruction
Your body's make
NRS
Dickinson other cool things around the
Wireless power
Transmission so
These people
University of Washington
They got their Wireless down
So basically what you
You can do is send
Full color HD
The signal is
60 frames per second
For less than a y
What is still huge
Samsung 4 battery power
But you can also send a 7:20
Image at 10
Per second that can be sent
4 under 80 microwave
And that gets a lot closer to
So maybe it's like
Grainger doorbell
Shoot the video from the doorbell
To screen
Without having
Go
To the cloud
Swepco
And because it's low power it could be a battery powered device at that point
Yeah there's some really cool things
The tech is already lights
Jeeva Wireless
So you might be able to see this
Intake
Woo
And final cool Universal
Princeton
University
Was kind of a letdown
I mean it's a letdown to me only in that I can actually use the tool that they came out with its called the IRT
Inspector project
Basically the project tries to figure out what your attitude devices talk to what information is gathered
And are the devices hacked
12 very important things
Fortunately they're going to
Open source this tool
To let you inspect your own iot devices and you have to email them to join a waitlist but
I mean that's the only let down to me is that I can't get it right now I'm just curious what
Information provides
And when I find out
Hopefully we'll be able to tell you more about
Play my devices
But you guys try not to
All right
News
There is a social media law
Brought to
And
I read it
I'm sad
I'm sad because this is
Sewickley for online platforms
And it doesn't look like it's going to help people
In the iot it doesn't look like it's going to deal with collecting I
Iot data
So the rule will deal with covered online platforms
And that means
An online platform that collects
Data during the online behavior of a user
The online platform
Which
I'm not online with my nest
Collecting data about me
Meandering
I'm not online
Where am I
You are not that your devices are like when you're asleep for example and things are being sensed and recorded in motion is.
Detective because the dog walk past a camera
The device like I said is online that is online you are not
So yeah
In the term online platform use any public face
Website web application
Digital application
Including a mobile
Includes
The Social Network
Add Network
Mobile OS
Search engine
Email service
Again
I want some clarity here for iot
I think they belong in the
Digital
Protection
The rights in here are not great
Basically saying look at
What you're collecting
And give them a chance
Opt out if they opt out
They just no longer they don't have to
Which is different from the gdpr because I believe you can opt out of data collection
Still use
Which
Or just different
So this
Proposed legislation
Is very far from
Coming along so we may never
It seems like the beginning of
Gdpr effort
Us
See where it goes
And hopefully
Anywhere
Comcast
Just a little update
Because they reported earnings they now have
One point
In Xfinity
Subscriber stats
About 44%
End
That's really all I have to say about that
Xfinity home
Custom is one of the larger players
They're making progress I have a feeling a lot of it has to do with potential bundling of service
I don't have anything more to say about it than that other than
Not the fact that they can do that as an advantage for them
Yes it is actually
Ashley helping them even if they lose cable
Subscribers
Their revenue
Producer is still up
So looking for
Increase broadband
But also
Opposite to me
Same or more
Money-making ability as
Right so Canary
I don't know how many Canary users there are out there but I am one so I just want to mention to ask Canary folks that
Recently Canary devices got person detection that I think it was back in February
Now with the latest Apple update
You can set your devices to record all motion
Just people only or not to record it all and motion alerts themselves can be configured for all motion people on Leon
Or nothing so
This kind of cleaned up some of the noise in the canary timeline and notifications
Systems the people detections actually pretty good although it still recognizes nor my dog is up first
But that's right
Donut he is
I can't argue with that
Alright other little gadgety updates
Google
Assistant.
Two new partners
Sensi the Sensi home
Stat from Emerson
Sun and and also
After I
Complain about it two weeks ago
Tradfri lights from
Ikea are now also
Supported by
Google home
Probably should have to
I was just going to ask you're going to put them back
I am
What kind of begrudgingly
I'm not turning back in my husband's bed
Side table lamp
That really makes them
All right
Let's see there is a
Really popular chip out there
Now that people are using for building iot device
Expressive
ESP
So this is a chips that a lot of hackers and fun
People kind of you
Can I play around with
End
Harry Potter
And it just the new version of it has now Wi-Fi mesh
Networking
So now you can use mesh WiFi stuff for your Gadget
Is that your building with
And it is
Makes it a little bit more
I don't have much to say Beyond this but I know there's a certain subset of our list
So excited
And finally
Who's has a new mesh Wi-Fi assist
And it's got built-in
Insecurities from Trend Micro
I think so I mean the fact that
It has begun
Security through trends
Micro work basically hits their Cloud database of known malware sites and Sachin else protect you from them witches
Constantly updated
Which is nice
You have that service for the lifetime of the products or it's not like a subscription it's not like you get for 3 months
You have for lifetime of the product which I think is very nice
These are kind of interesting mean we seen Odyssey mesh Wi-Fi routers and access points before
These are a little unique in that they almost look like
Cheese irons that you would use to iron your clothes there like a pyramid in fact
And the reason there a pyramid is because the antennas are aligned to send the signals
Horizontally
And vertically so that helps with multi-level homes this is also three-by-three mymo which
Is 3 antennas in each unit so that should help with coverage as well
299 on pre-order at Amazon
And I'm trying to see when I think they come out in May
We don't have long
All right
And now
I have been waiting for
Kevin Hayes
It's made
Well
I'm not up
Set about my home
Smart home right now but I'm not happy with it
All the unhappiness aim for me to start when I went over to SmartThings
And we just
Talk about
You know which
Smart home hubs are available which ones are the best which ones are the ones we recommend for most people and we typically do recommend either
SmartThings or wink and I've had both that I know you've had booked Stacy I'm going back to wink
Because
The SmartThings software just
Doesn't if not as responsive as waiting for one thing it just seems like it always has to refresh
For 2 seconds every time I open the app and check
Device States and so on and so forth
Even if the app is open in the background
I don't know I know you can do more with SmartThings if you want to get into device handlers and custom things have but I'm over that
So I think I'm going to move everything back to wink which is kind of a shame because I just moved everything over to SmartThings couple weeks ago
So I don't know what maybe it's just me what do you think
Could you please. Yeah I think you're actually right so and you actually did you some of the device Handler
To play with some
I think for
Everybody who does not want
If you don't have some weird device you're trying to say
Support or some
Grandiose automation
This game that you're trying to support wink is the way to go
I just worry
Now that it's owned by William
I don't know what's going to happen
Do it but it's a great platform
I'm still for
Everybody
Yeah we've had concerns about wink as a
Product line for a while because
They were kind of in limbo and yeah they were
Quirky + GE and then sold there still around
So I mean that doesn't mean any for the future but maybe maybe we were worried about it for nothing I don't know I should also point out and
State Cinema if you saw this
We
Got a comment on our Facebook page about the news
SmartThings app cuz they do have two apps right now they have classic and then the newer one
And in the new one it's
Says
In the FAQ is that you cannot
Connect Madam a Google home
Or Cortana if you try to connect
And even for the first time using smart
This is under the new app
If you've already been connected with those digital assistants in the classic app and then you update
You can use those devices
I don't know if that means
They're getting rid of that support once you get for new users on the new app or not
Okay so I sent an email to Alex Hawkinson
Who's the CEO of SmartThings
When I saw that
I sent him a comment and I was like
What
Is this really true and he says
It's definitely not true
He says we are planning to be even more open
And he promised to talk to me
Now I am in Sweden so it's very difficult to get ahold of
So I will have more clarity
Before you guys on this
Next episode
Cuz I saw that I was
What what
I think that was your like bread-and-butter say
Samsung loves being
So guys take that with a grain of
That's good news I mean
It kind of sounded like they were just going to go to Bixby
And that is not
Obviously not open and not what
Everybody wants
The odd thing to me is
It's right there in the app if it uses I double checked it myself so
They can resolve their own issues right away by
Fixing that FAQ page
I agree with you
That's why we're to have a follow-up conversation when I'm back from Sweden
So stay tuned on
Bat
Right
Now
Time to go to our hotline
By the way you guys
I'd like to thank Schlage for sponsoring our hotline for the last
5 months
The sponsorship is now becoming available so if you'd like to sponsor The Listener hotline
Please reach out to Andrew
At iot podcast
Okay
Today's hotline is
Brought to you by
Maker of electronic lock
Schlage electronic lock
You make life so much easier and more
No more keeping track of extra house keys
Each member of your family can have their own access code
Does he was possible is it schlage.com
To learn more
And here we have our question of the week from Dan
PlayStation Kevin
This is Dan from North Carolina
I'm a longtime listener but a first-time caller we're having a
Complete kitchen makeover done this summer on our house
Including knocking over wall new cabinets
Appliances everything
I'm a SmartThings user with about
20.
Two things currently
Besides considering
Smart Appliance
This is like the June oven and others
What are the top few ice
Do things you'd recommend I do in the kitchen
Given that I'm in that uniques
Situation of a clean slate to work
Smart switches on overhead lighting are a definite for me
Summer to do that
Do you have any other recommendations
Thanks again
Oh
Dan I
So
So envious of
Love you I hope you're going for one of those big farmhouse
Because personally when we did our kitchen
I said
No I don't need anything like that
Credit everyday
Don't let this happen
Do you accept on your smart stuff B
Because I guarantee in five years you're going to be like
Probably made the wrong choice
Just because it's strange
My first recommendation
Into you is
Yes smart switches
Pick your favorite I'm going to offer to you
If your kitchen is an open floor plan cuz you mentioned you were
Knocking out a wall
I might actually take that opportunity to try the noon
Smart
Home lights because I've been really intrigued in this
The product it designs the lights
It's for you
It detects what kind of lighting you have and then
Built-ins around
Before you automatically
I think it's kind of compelling
And kind of expensive but wrapped in a Renault it could definitely work
And
It all depends though if you're doing
Open
If not then go with the straight up I recommend Lutron because
They're my favorite you will need a hub
But
I would also install some smart Outlets
With USB ports in
If you're going to go with a smart outlet a zigbee or Z-Wave should be just fine
You may depending on your current host
System chooses a day because
Their support for it from like the Amazon Echo has
Automatic
Recipes for dinner
But I don't think it really matters
And that way you don't have to have these Outlets cramming
Things up
Still have that ability to turn Appliance
How to charge your car
Connected devices
Yay
Casper Smart Appliance
This is
Hard for me
Because I
You know I would love for you to install the June oven
It's awesome and they do have a in wall oven
But
There's a lot of compelling
Use cases are arguing
Commence for
Buying
Appliances all for one
And that kind of makes me feel gross
I don't know but they didn't match in that comes in big as a nice looking for you has good resale ability so
GE has
Probably worked the hardest
I'm building out like
Integration
And thinking about the kitchen is an in
Integrated whole
So they've done a good job
I don't particularly know about there
Quality though and I don't think you should
You should choose your Appliance
Is based on
How well they function is there me
Main function not is how well they
Play function with
Smart stuff
So that's a ten
Kevin anything else
You would install
I don't know that I would install it but I'm very disappointed Stacy
Because you did not mention the one thing I thought you were going to mention
Ceiling mounts for MS
Ace
Smart
Faucet
For your sake
I forgot about that
Okay two things
Because you're putting it into the delta
Capacitive touch
To its touch
2 hour touch O2 faucet
Speaks to
Because it's
And if you don't want to do that
Just going to capacitive touch faucet your first couple days you could be like why did I do this
This is weird and then you're never going to want to turn on your closet any other
This is my
Pledge to you
Santo Rosario
I do I kept you around for
Yes
All right
So those are thoughts there Dan
Wish you luck
I'm sad that I can't think of any other off
But there's a number of smart scales and
Smart pots and smart
Other devices
They're all stand-alone kind of thing for the most part
Maybe some smart blinds
You know sometimes I like to wash dishes at night and then
People looking at me
Okay
Venetian we've got the
It's called smart blinds
Venetian style blinds that flip open
Clothes for you we don't really have we have to Hunter Douglas in the Lutron Serena Shades if you
Wanted to go out.
Traditional
Shades
And yeah
Alright then good luck with your kitchen renovation
If you have a question
The podcast
Give us a call at 5 1/2
Before
And
Through the end of April
We are giving away my old netatmo welcome camera so if you leave a voicemail you'll also be entered to win
And
Will let you know
Inmate
And now
Stay tuned
Message from
One of our sponsors and to hear more about designing products that are connected and sustainable
And a bit of more about the keys product we are taking a break from the internet
The thing is podcast for a message from our sponsor cuz we sponsor is for trop and we are going to talk about privacy
Is brand Equity with Ben Goodman
VP of strategy and innovation
Ben first off let's remind people what for truck
Is it
Send our scale of flexibility let's our customers
Movie on the traditional
Identity use cases that people use me Enterprise so things like provisioning employee access
We do a lot more
One of our biggest difference
Is that we've focused really heavily on
Privacy
So we have
Craft the standard
Call user managed access
Which helps users gain control of who has access
Personal data
We were the first commercially available products
Incorporated
Uma really is a
Great framework for building
Privacy and consent program
And I can help customers with things like
Gdpr
Compliance which is a
Standard in the European Union for privacy and consent
We haven't talked to you in the last few weeks about Cambridge analytica and what it means to
Give consent to the use of your data you explain to me that you actually think this was a breach when a lot of
People are trying to make the de
Distinction that it
Yeah I think it's time that we really reimagine what makes up a bridge
I mean if someone gets access to our data in a way that we didn't
Anticipate
Consent to
That is a breach
For example just because Cambridge analytica was working with in Facebook's terms
Service
It doesn't mean it wasn't a breach
When someone misleads me to do something like taking online trivia test
And uses that to harvest my personal data
And the date of my friend
How can I be anything but
This really is a modern social media version of a phishing attack
Okay so do you think this is going to change how
Consumers
View consent
I hope that this really does
Create an Awakening in the end
Consumer
I think for the first time people realize that
If they're getting a service
Jeffrey dende and their data are the actual product
Respect that people are going to suddenly start reading 50
Epays terms of services or end-user license
What I do expect
Text is that there's that now collect a lot of data are going to have to find ways to
Surface what they're doing with people data in a way which is much easier for them to consume and understand
And how does
Ford truck help
We believe that identity is a
Privacy
You know you really have to understand a person and their attributes in order to provide privacy
As I mentioned the beginning
Was really designed from the ground up to be a key supporting technology
Before any further
And we were the first commercial product
It support this user managed access
Which citizenship
Privacy and consent dashboards
That can be added into our customer
Products to help them as a brand
Who's quickly to show that they care about a customer's privacy
Protection
And really give a customer the levers
Have a control over their own personal data
Sounds good
So where can we go to find out more
Define amorous
Pacifically about
Stufful doing with privacy
Please go to www
Ford rock.com
Flash privacy
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today I have not one but two
I am here at
Kids headquarters in Elmhurst
Sweden
And I am learning the correct pronunciation for trustee and eating meatballs
So let's get this started we got to guess we got Rebecca
Tori man who's in charge of the
Tradfri products
Okay I will let her say it
Wow
Okay
And then after we talked to her for a little bit we're going to talk to
Rihanna
Call back who is in charge of Designing and Manufacturing products
So I am super pumped about all of this
So Rebecca by the end of this maybe I pronounce this correctly
Alright so
I purchase the lights and
Apparently
A couple weeks ago I put mine away for awhile.
Twerking
But for all of those if they've been out in the market for a year so let's talk about what you've learned
Since they've been out in the market
Our customers finding them
Do they come in asking for them at the store or do they just cut it
Buy them by
Running across them what is that process
I think when we start to develop
Bismarck shooting range
Two feet
The normal Eye Care customer that is also take gate usually and that's also we're about all of this technology that that exist
And we learn
Is that we attract
Many new type of
So many customers that I love Ben and I care for a couple of years and now they have actually read
That we have something that is connected and they are coming but we are also that in the track
Our normal
The one that doesn't know that there is something that is called zigbee or connected lighting
It just once
Steam daylight
I have been very fun to see that
We got traction from both of those types of
Because that is so wasted just a cold Manchester
Try and
Work
And they also said a lot about Sarah because people also want to be able to steer their products away via
Of course also when you get to get to get the connection supplement and Amazon
Google so I'll spread to all of our customers
And you have a sense of how many customers
Hi their stuff back to Amazon or Google or
So when customers buy these from the store
How do you educate them about what they can do how are you selling this
In the market
Exactly
We have an education package.
Wheels have of course location in the store so she can do and then if you have by the age and of course browser
To do we don't have so many things yet
We have of course individual steering we have the ability for stability
To do timers
And then they seem to get ratified
The back is fine but then of course when it comes to these equations
Now we talk
Both into storage sign of course our partners also talked about that now it's possible to go connect to switch
Flights to this in this area
So you guys are done lighting so far
You've done wireless charging that everyone
So excited
And you done
New Bluetooth speakers what's next
HomeSmart
Yasso lighting is very important
Important so we're adding on
Products and features
So when we are then them
Hopefully morning in the whole month of our customers
We're also not to say we have also launched the Bluetooth
Speakers
Cannabis
Sound that's what it's like to use a very
Important
Components to create a go.
So it would also then
Continue the journey towards some plastic sound
And we're doing back with some of them.
What are you doing with soda
So many secrets you guys
Cheer in Sweden
Okay and what are other areas that you're excited about
There's sound obviously you mentioned earlier hell
Insecurity is another kind of Maslow's hierarchy of needs
Perspective
You know we're looking into them what could either area
But we're not entering those areas if it is not soda profound very good music
Surfers looking at the customers racing okay what are the pinpoints what do they want to have and then we are creating then
Preston sport. NECC security maybe not so much for us while the safety National cleaning safe
Very important
Peace of mind
Could be about 10
Aunt is also set
Very interesting process if we could do sings there when it comes
Free sample to sleeping
Esther how could we support people to do that so there are very many interesting areas so we're looking into it doesn't have
To be with connected products
Shouldn't say easier but that but without the types of products
Package to the point that you have
Just hammered home with me today it's
Smart doesn't mean
So in some cases smart could be
I don't know
Wireless charger
Wireless charging that's smart without really being connected to
To make something smart what are your attempt design
What does it mean to make something
Yeah we are at all of those talks about their under the umbrella
And when we traded HomeSmart we didn't create smartphones we're going to tell smart so we put the home first very important for us
So I think in order for us to pray
HomeSmart products or a smart car
When you should take King
I think Moana to component that we are done tweaking a normal eye care product
Way to be better
So then would like thing we added on
Connectivity migas Dan you have
Many other ways that you can atop otherwise
Stair Lighting in to have the Fantastic atmosphere that we want people to be able to
So another
Music it that we couldn't do otherwise
And that's why we think that it's mine
When you think about Partnerships with other companies
In this area how do you evaluate your
Partnerships what do you look
Pressing stat
We are not doing currently at the other people or other partners than are doing back there
So for some people working with Sonos gives us
Company.
Nose
Unlocked and have a great experience into sound and the really gives
Working with our partners in Amazon and Google and I put of course gives our customers the ability to
Two boys are the products of course I don't have the types of products that we don't have
And to have that they go system if they want
So it's to create other types of music is it that we aren't currently offering them
Alright guys I was Rebecca
One day
Okay let's move to Liana perkovich
Men
I am so disappointed right now and iot because we are just not talking about to me the big issues where this could really help
So we'll start with Ikea obviously
Picture
One of the challenges and Ikea Ikea has been a really innovative
Company about managing
Supply chain in designing its products
To recycle to reclaim
What is the philosophy at Ikea just big nature around us
I think first of all is starts with the design actually and because the sign will also its
Precept a lot of the other environmental impact or the social impact for that matter where you actually producer products
We have an approach where we say everything is within democratic
Define democratic design for Ikea is that everything you do we have to think about five Dimensions is for its
Function
Is low prices quality energy sustainability
And it is actually Define
The perfect solution there
Sustainability is part of the design principles right away
Which attempt receptive course
What is
What we call
I'm building sustainability is what comes for the Prada
It's the material you select
It's how you produce it's how you transported them everything around it
Then we have the function which is also a sustainable Park
And that function could actually be
Perfectly improving your life or it could actually make you become more sustainable or it could use
Alot of energy and it could be the opposite
So when you look at it you really have to look at it
I should ask for everyone listening that Ikea put
Security and a focus on security as part of their quality
Part of that design
No everyone wondering like
But are they secure
Apparently so
Given that that's your design process
What are the risks of adding technology to everything
Is
Some of these
Materials are toxic or not
So how do you think about designing those into products
My ultimately feel a little disposable event
First of all I think it's extremely important to look at it both from an input point of view
So when you design the product actually decide what are the materials that should be in the product as such
There's a lot of things that could be done there just very being smart in your selection of the materials also in electronic components
Antibiotics that you're using and everything around it
So think about it from the beginning then on the other hand you can't really decide if the material is
Switch from a sustainability point of view if you don't know the function
You always have to look at the function and sustainability at the same time please
Smile about it because we say that you know if you would only look at the materials you would end up to have it
Kitchen sinks out of paper and the other types of materials that wouldn't really
Function at all
But they are highly recyclable but not very durable and long-standing
For the function
But I think when it comes to enter Electronics you are pointing out a very critical
Discussion first of all if you embed
And the electronic part in a piece of furniture we need to think about whether this is a platform where you could actually
Exchange it and which part
Is actually living longer
It's not necessarily so
Parts it could be that the battery lives longer than the lamp and another cases is the laptop live longer than the battery
Because the life length of some of these factories are very long now so how you design it will depend on course how long
Is the lifeline
The product and then also what is the biggest satellite most likely
Solution for it at the end of life
Okay so
Let's hit the battery-powered lamp
I don't have any battery power
What is this thing she's talking about
But that were thinking about the if you have solar panel if you have any other kind of rechargeable at you can actually have a
Battery in that it's more the possibilities than our backs you making sure that
After you recycle
So in this case it would be the battery would last longer than the lamp so that the battery
Recyclable is part of
You make it to Quick come if you don't
Remove the very small battery that disappears
Very easily at from the recycling so but you actually maintained it in the lamp so it's taken care of at the end of life
Use of thinking that the battery is the one that's going to be changed it
Thanks many times
But you actually have to look at it and some cases it's the opposite
When the light blinks becoming very long and in that case
I would just return it
Ikea or is there a recycling programs that
That's the other thing
Right now I haven't really have a big old bag in my closet
And I bring it to
My electronic recycling center and I don't know what happens to it
When we start thinking about like your lamp example if I brought the lamps of them they probably just be like
They should take care of it everything but that's just
But no I think the trust of course the infrastructure of recycling in many countries since we're a global company.
There is a many different possibilities of the infrastructure some of its really good and some still ways to go and will you have it
Different setups depending on where we are globally to support that in some cases it the enforcer
Picture is so good that we are supporting they Society the recycling system in another we actually collected ourselves
But maybe the most important part 2 also is to enable the possibility of our products
To actually be prolonged in society and right now we are designing the products according to what we call the circular principal
So what is the material that is it possible to repair the product is it possible to make it this is
Assembled and make it possible so that we have a lot of these design principles that were thinking into the product design right
When dealing with technology
I have to imagine that
The life of Technology
Matters is part of this design
How do you think of like your lamp example kind of throws me because I like
What the battery lasting longer than that lamp itself that's crazy talk so
If I'm thinking about more traditional technology that I'm putting in things that might last
25 or 30 years
How do you design
For that summer
Modularity seems to be
Modularity is key and also to prepare for that day
Could be completed
Technology of course it was interesting though I think is that the life length of a project when you talk
Do Ikea is by Italy you have everything from something in the paper napkin that lasts very shortly
Sterilize things
Table or a couch that maybe last 400 years depending on what it actually is so of course again you have to
Looking to where is
Is the application where is the function and how does this fit
Atlanta it can be a very long living loud like we should also think about it that it could be a short
If it is a bit shorter lifelinks we have less material invested in it
And it should be highly recycle
Okay and how does
Bradley not just in products for the consumer home
How does IKEA think about using
Iot to help
Push sustainability or push efficient
I think it's really interesting journey and I think we're really in the beginning on this one
And I think if you look at it where we are right now it's been a lot in the talks about
Efficiency
So the starting point of course efficiency we talked about health
Safety
But you can also look at
If you start to look at that that's a better product solution
Investor home
We're now starting to see how this connects to behavior in the home and if you start to think about behavior in the home assistant
Consumption Nissan
Lifestyle
There's a whole other perspective into what this could do
And there were just looking into
At the moment
See with the two Dimension though all the time not to be mixed up there is
Disability and sustainability agenda that we will be very strict on we will not compromise on our efficiency and our way
Designing products with the materials we select and how we produce them
We will also look at the function and the combination of that
Could be the greatest possibility when you log into new homes
So is my smart lights I can never expect my smart lights from Ikea to be like
Burn more fuel stay on all the time I'm looking for more things that
We were brainstorming things like 5 minutes
Things I'd like help you
What is your process for trying out new technologies is it developed in Alice to go to Partners
Are we both I mean we're not doing I think the interesting thing now is of course looking into the whole creation of Pi
Possibilities not only think that we are the one that can solve everything but actually go great with others
Open up alot to see you a kind of everything from how we mix
New materials and find out new production technology for recycling for example to a function of a product
Two ideas in good ideas so it's opening up I think a lot and it's
Synopsis
Awesome alright so thank you so much thank you
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for this
Remember
If you'd like more iot
Tino's sign up
For my newsletter
Stacey on iot
Dot-com
See you next week