Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Higginbotham abbesses
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have an amazing show for you today we're going to talk about
Google's iot Cloud Samsung artik
And some new stuff there
We've got a lot of news about Amazon Echo and
Developer services
Plus we're going to talk about Honeywell starting a new 100 million dollar Venture fund
There's also a new place to shop that I'm super excited about here in Austin Texas
Where to make some
Some speculation about Spotify
And this week
Sponsor is Arris
And after hearing from them we are going to hear from our guest Bill Gardner from GE Appliances
Smart kitchens and
When you will be able to buy one
Some of y'all
Hard Luck
First
Speaking of smart kitchens
The smart Kitchen Summit is the only event of its kind to tackle the future of food cooking and the kitchen
Decision-makers and disruptors across food cooking appliances retail and Technology with two
Couple days of content discussions networking and product showcases p2017 smart kitchen
It will be held at the Benaroya Hall in Seattle on October 10th through 11th listeners can use the code
Food
You got to spell it right guys Stacey for a 25% discount on tickets at WWE
W. Smart Kitchen Summit. Com
All right
The timing of today's podcast is interesting
Because in about
4 hours after we recorded this Google IO kicks off with a keynote witch
Kind of leads me to my typical disclosure that I do work for Google as a consultant
In their Enterprise area for devices not coyote or anything like that so all opinions are my own
So we know something because Google just announced some things but we know Google's kind of probably enough some more things
And Kevin doesn't actually know those
So he can't give us a sneak peek knowing that tomorrow this would
You guys are just going to have to get a slightly
Steel pot
We ask Google to push everything up a day but they didn't listen
I don't I don't have any pull there
You know
Kevin
Slacker
Call Cinderella
Make it so
Let's get started with Google launching a beta version of
An iot Cloud platform is part of its cloud computing efforts a private beta
Private beta
Which is like extra beta
Not quite Alpha but it's almost
So this is Google Cloud iot
So when I'm looking at a new iot Cloud platform I look for
I look for the ability to
Vision
Ingest data
Device management
And
Probably some other things that I'm not thinking about
Like I said Daddy Analytics
Open firmware
Thank you
Yeah which this has some of those
It definitely has firmware updates
At least for Android things devices Google says the firmware updates can be automatic
I don't know much about the provisioning side for four other
Devices
But certainly the analytics are there I mean this ties into
Google Cloud platform bigtable bigquery even their Cloud machine learning aspects
So there's there's some
I think that would explain why it's still in private beta and they've also got a lot of device partners
So it's impossible
Certain modules you buy from this device partners
Are going to be able to be managed in
That's very similar AWS has something like that and they work with lots of other
Nxp arm until other companies to pull device in producer
And it's mostly the same players hear minutes is clearly an attempt to
Show developers hey you know you don't have to go AWS if you don't want to you if you want to take advantage of Google Cloud platform in
All the service is there
Come on over here
Yeah and honestly
Google it's not a huge player in the
Industrial or the
Even manufacturers
Consumer devices
And this actually doesn't change anything because this is such a limit
Beta
Right now
AWS is by far and away
According to Lexi
Eclipse developer survey
I think it's 40 something
10% of 12
Followed by Azure which is got
Yeah I was just I was just going to say Microsoft has a strong number two there and and Google's trying to catch up
So this makes sense
But
It is good that Google's doing
She needs to do
Looks like they have support for mqtt I'm not seeing support for like a MP
Did you or AMT
Can never remember
But mqtt is a Communications protocol data
So
This is good it needs to happen so that's all I can say about it right now
My Hope
And I don't know
But my hope is that at I owe more information comes out or even some
Additional features support Etc because
It was interesting to me that this blog post on Google Cloud blog
Will publish the day before I outright
It's not like this is
Ayo news
If it was when I hold the fry alright semana
Kind of hoping there's some follow-up
Information
Me too
Also in the Google Sphere
The Google verse I don't know what to call it
Google sings we're in there going to talk about this because there's a developer session but they did the Android things
Preview for
And basically
We see it works with iot
Cloud we also know that there is newborn support
For some new stuff from NXT
They got a lot of voice
Which is a good follow-up from earlier this month
Magpi magazine folks like to use raspberry pies that community
There was a do-it-yourself
Google Assistant kit
In there you had to add your own pie to it but there's a cardboard kitten
And add on boards and so on and you can download software and basic build your own little
Google assistant device through it
So that's where I
I think the first real voice kit
Aspect came into play so it's a follow-up to that
Yes with dp4
The necessary drivers are provided to support the Google Assistant SDK on all Android things certified development
Right
So now we can
Oh
So this is really good because it's saying that Google's like hey you know what we're going to talk to her thanks
Which we kind of knew
We've been saying that for years
I wish we would hear a little bit more about
Weave
At
Epi staying at Google IO
Weed is their Communications device Discovery protocol
You know they talk to sup
It competes with the
Iotivity standard that isn't really designed actually for small things yet
And there's a lot of
Play happening here but maybe
Google's like you know what
The standard thing is not work it out let's just forget about it
I don't I don't know
So
I don't know I mean that home messaging has been kind of
Murky for the better part of at least two years I did see in the developer preview news of a side in a will
We talk more about this
And they pay the live stream link so anybody can TuneIn
My Hope Is that we do hear more
Is it the last couple years maybe we just been throwing we even berlo and Android things around
And now Brillo is
Right
So
We need some clarity
We would love some
I bet I bet inside sometimes I feel like the
No comment
It's all good it's all good
Okay speaking of clouds
A lot of clouds in this week's podcast
Ultiworld is happening in California as well this week and Samsung did some Jews related to its
Arctic
Iot platform
An artic is both a cloud platform
But it's also a series of modules that Samsung has built
It is
Super Chinese super Harden's relatively cheap and it's designed for
Medical devices connected home appliances Building Products
So
This has a bunch of videos that has chips it has pretty much everything you need to just pop it in and
Build something
And then Samsung artik is also in there clouds outside
Which
Arctic is famous for having all these clouds
Connectors where you
You can
Print services like I could blink my
Washing machine to my
Google home for example
Through
He hasn't link to Google Assistant basically I think you're foreshadowing there
I might be
Anyway so
Oh that's why
I know I know I read the notes I saw the guest
Podcast
You guys this
Just all over
So big before we leave this
Arctic dead
I also saw that Samsung's work with VMware
On their partner program with our take
Add VMware has VMware pulse iot Center
Which is basically a control panel to get information and visibility to the health of
You are iot devices so
Rather smart of them to two
If I can't deal with themselves rather smart of Samsung
Apartment with somebody who can
Help manage
These devices and make sure they're all on the up-and-up
Right so you can
Connect all kinds of things to that
Iot
Stop pulse iot Center
All right
You know we should have made today a drinking game so every time we said iot cloud or iot we should
I would have swapped my coffee out LOL
Arctic
Right in two
The Amazon
Echo
So much stuff
All right
Let's just get the first big news exciting thing out of the way
Money
Amazon
Developers
The skill developer Sia
Guess
And this is something I actually thought about I wrote about it when I
Fortune
Over a year ago saying
Hey is this going to really be an App Store Willow
Amazon let it let developers monetize
Madam a
It's kind of just getting started though I don't
People get all excited their penis is kind of limited it's only game skills at first
So
Yes cuz Amazon
Has actually
I remember where I saw this if it was in the letter to shareholders or it was in a conference somewhere but Amazon said it was really beef
Picking up its game
Efforts so smart home Focus was last year and now it really wants to have
So
That makes sense
Pay game makers to build
It's kind of an interesting place to start they must be because those are very popular but has been scratching my head like I never
Never once
Play keno play like a quiz game or any other
Game return Echo
Barbie no no I mean I totally get it I'm not going to try to disable I get it but
I can't
Imagine it's that popular it must be you know I'm an outlier I don't have to say
Well I don't think on the echo that you are an outlier
That's what I say
Amazon's really hoping
We find the next big
The next style of Gaming
That's like me sitting around playing
Chess with my kids but only I voice control the board by telling my kids what move to me
I just don't get it
Maybe we're not the right I mean
Play song
Yeah it me up
Someone who's older
Cher
Airport that that's me pretty soon.
All right
Apparently
With Madeline
Alright other exciting news especially for us
Consumerism
People who have
Echoes every
There
Doing a program
For allowing notify
Vacations
Amazon is announcing notifications for Madame a coming soon
Right now you just sign up
Basically this is going to
Not just in this is something I saw that the Google home and I was like
So basically you're going around your day
I think about all the times that like
Google Now or something pings you in his life
China leave
So those are the things so
It's going to enable notifications for
Select skills and shopping updates
On most devices with
Seoul AccuWeather
Life360 which is a really great
Program for tracking your family members
Those are going to be the first update their skills with
Vacation
The Washington Post
Just eat
Yeah it's interesting cuz the Echoes have pretty much been very passive devices
Up until now although just last week we saw the first
Alipay active
Data where the echo actually
Tells you something without your asking it
And that was
The calling
Yes
Right and I wouldn't call that notification but you could see where they're going with it's now it's going to
Tempstar
You're reaching out to you when something happens and that's definitely needed
Yes and all the skills will require users to opt-in
And you can
You can disable notifications for skills
Or suppress notifications temporarily by putting devices in Do Not Disturb mode
By voice
Or through the Echo app which is good
Good good good yes last week
Echo Show
And
A little bit later that afternoon after work
For the show
Kevin says I spam
The feature and I was on this week
Google so
Call
Live on the air she called me
Oh yeah I was sitting here at my home office instead of a sudden
Little. That I have in here lights up green and says
Collarspace
And I tried to answer it and fortunately didn't work I don't know why
I think I was just taken aback and I didn't say the right to man so I called you back on the air
But the point here is
It's just like having a landline phone again
Yeah
And I actually I was really in trouble
Kevin you don't know that the angst inside of me
Yeah I tweeted that they see to spam called me
On the Amazon Echo and iPad
Night and day I didn't mind at all
I'm sorry
I thought it was funny
I did too
Everybody who liked my tweet where I said I was a jerk
Impressed with you
My response was
Well I am a jerk
I got so many likes
So all of you
Now I'm shaking my head at you
Brady
This notification but actually plays into another one of our topics and that is Amazon has a new
TV out
Amazon TV
4K are they safe 4K and it's low price
I mean I'm an HD guy from
Back before we had HD it does have 4K UHD but no HDR
High dynamic range says whatever
But more importantly
It has basically has the Amazon Fire
Interface just built in the software feels right and so you don't need a Fire TV stick or a box
And of course with that
Comes
Your assistant
And I was just thinking about this like if I'm watching TV
I don't want an echo notification on my TV you know popping up
Oh really
Cuz that's one of the things is like somewhere in the corner
People's homes like
AT&T used to have it I'm sure Comcast had it where you could get caller ID on your television
And I shut it off
I went on Netflix and don't mess with me okay that's me time
You like what I maven
Yeah
No no I'm watching Bosch back off caller
Well that's what you're not
True true for folks who don't have an echo again this is another way for Amazon the propagate this whole service into
Smart Home
Atticus's TV start for 99
That's for the
Damn
Not
The only downside to me I pray
After plugging a box
Into
TV because I'd rather buy a TV with the highest picture quality and so on so forth
And I don't want to be locked into the
Smart
Hardware that's built-in for Reno that put chip processor and so on
Building for the interface in the software
You want to dump
Yeah
Yeah so that's what I bought I have a dumb awesome 4K screen and I plug in
Well either an Amazon Fire TV or Nvidia Shield TV so yeah
Okay so there is an
I don't want I mean what happens when Amazon gets real pistol
Google and they stop
YouTube and
I would hope that doesn't happen for any of the
People who are content providers and such yeah
Let's see
Other
Other news bets
Which
I know we've had them on the show as a guest but Honeywell his
Created a hundred million dollar Venture Capital firm
The focus here is on anything that will help it scale its businesses
The reason we mention it here is because they are really big in the industrial internet-of-things
Already offering
Things as a service to customers and they
They also make consumer devices but
I don't know if this Venture fund really focuses on the
Consumer side
It looks more Industrial
The point here
New Venture Capital arm so if you are trying to sell people on
HVAC stuff building management
Industrial processes
Iggy Pop on over to Honeywell
And see what they got
Okay
Other news
We talked about this in the past
Spotify
There were Rumours a while back but it might build his own
Hardware device
And Kevin was like
Rewind a minute
I
Spotify customer just got a survey
And they ask me all these questions about me
My physical fitness
Am I crazy about my physical fitness or not
And what I like to listen to music and all this other great stuff
So my fingers are crossed that maybe they're going to make a wearable that's truly wearable and not just a controller
We're not just attached to my smartphone
Where will I'm exercising
So I was
Kind of
Down on this idea when it was first announced they were thinking about entering the wearable Market
I'm even more so now and I'll tell you why
I actually just bought a new wearable although it's
Technically an old one if it came out last year almost a year ago
Ibotta
Yeah I bought and I bought this a year ago in fact
Last year I bought a Samsung Gear Fit
2 and one of the big things that had just how does having is it's got Spotify
When I bought it
Only to find out it's Justice
Spotify
The app that control Spotify on your phone so you still need to carry your phone when you work out
Which is kind of silly cuz this thing can store music
There are still
Tons and tons of foreign post
People complaining about this thing
So I ended up returning it the year ago
Technically because it didn't integrate with RunKeeper which is what I use for my book of record for exercising
It now does and I found a refurbished
Unit
Probably the same one that returned a year ago for $85 so I bought it
It's working great
Spotify still is the same as just a controller
Here's my point long story short
Play Spotify comes out with its own Hardware wearable device that allows offline music player
What happens to all these other wearables that either work with Spotify in a limited fashion or what
They're probably never going to have offline playback capability and I just think that's terrible
Oh-so Spotify with key
Keep offline play
Prince self
Bada Bing
Mancan
So that was that was why I was so interested in the
Pebble
Or I think it's what it was called
Cancel that
Right right
I'm sitting here a lot of
There a lot of Spotify smartwatch
Apps that you can put Spotify on your watch or whatever and these watches cab storage can store
Play music so you can go exercising listen which is what I always do when I go out and run I always listen to music
But I think Spotify with the hold that back
If I were them
What is a consumer on like
I'm at
But you'll be happy
Alrighty
And final bit of news
This is for people who live in Austin
This is me
I'll just be honest
Bata store so we've talked about them before this is a
Can super store where you can try all kinds of connected devices not just connected home stuff but
Actually you can try Innovative products cuz I actually saw pillow in the Austin store that had no connectivity whatsoever it was just a cool fact
That stay cool
But you can try out virtual reality headsets
Ride on bikes UK
Listen to speakers
So
They're opening a store in Austin if you're in Austin it's in the domain
Area
If you're not in Austin they also stores in Seattle Santa Monica
And Palo Alto Alto
Going to have one in San Francisco but that is tdd
When that happen
Yeah I went in I got to see lots of devices
Quite frankly I'm very worried that I
Near me
When I go out to Google and I just haven't had the time but I plan on going out there
I know there's some really great stuff
That's kind of the fun part
Yay
And know I feel like we talked about a lot really quickly
But
We got our guest still to come
And we're going to have a word from our sponsor Arris
This week's guest is actually Bill Gardner
From GE Appliances
And this week
Geappliances said all of its
Connected appliances will now work with the Google
Home
And that closes the foreshadowing live for today
I was so I had no idea
So
Bill is not going to talk about that but he is going to talk about the future of smart kitchens what people do with their appliances
Has an echo
And he will introduce you to Geneva
Who is the smartest assistant that works with both
The Google home now and the Amazon Echo
Stay tuned for that
Message from Eros
Hey everyone this is Stacy and I'm breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a quick message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
And I have
Z Hussain who is the CTO and co-founder of
Eros
So last week we talked about what Heroes does
But can you give us a quick Refresher
It was the company that provides
B data services
For iot applications all the way from the remote
Device
Tell me what device that gathers information
Back to the networks
Both within the US and internationally
Data centers and storage and analytics systems that
Take appropriate action on the data that is being gathered and then I can also provide the most
All the devices that are out now
That's a big job one of the biggest aspects of that has connectivity
What are the options out there for the internet
That's a very good question Stacey I think it depends very strongly on the requirements of the application
In truly mobile or physically mobile application cellular is a natural choice because it provides
The capability of using a network transport that's available everywhere that people are or that people will send their iot device
Asus2
If the device is located within a residence or a business there other options
Clearly
You can have wifi-connected devices
It's a short-range device that communicates with a cell phone
Bratz use Bluetooth or zigbee
Options exist and of course there are some Next Generation
Low-power wide area networks that are being deployed within the United States and overseas that can provide
Lower cost
Short-range and long-range and medium to long-range connectivity
For these kinds of application
The choices depend very heavily on what the applications requirement for what they cost model for
The services that they're providing can be etc etc
Every one of these connectivity options has pros and cons and the decision for which one could use is something that we can help guide
There's an estimate that about 30%
29 to 30% of the devices being deployed for M2M iot applications
By 2025 will be the cellular or some form of low-power wide area network
What are my options
For us or global
Are you deployed it application within the us or internationally
It was generally deployed I cellular application of course radio modules
Cellular Arabic more expensive
Then other Technologies on the other hand
Cellular is available pretty much anywhere around the world you may have to compensate for the frequency difference isn't technology differences that may
Craigslist in other parts of the world
That's relatively easy to do we have that information and depending on the
The requirements for the iot application has or do the transport you will make choices
I make decisions about betrayal
NZ where can I go to find out more
Let's refer people to the e-book that I have publishes available freely on our website www.arris.com
And the our podcast is also available at the same site www.eros.com podcast
Hey everyone welcome back to the intern
Turn out of things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Bill Gardner
Who is manager of connected
Partnerships
A GE Appliances
I didn't great steaks
Neon
Man I'm super excited about this
Because because I have many appliances
But this is a place where I'm like connectivity could make my life really awesome
But it's also a place where am I
Are we even going to get to this point
Hopefully this conversation you're going to buy all new
Muji appliances here to be so excited
Oh that's a tall order my friend I just bought a house built in 2012
I have Wi-Fi
They're still really good
CC
You can do this by faith
So let's get started with what is GE Appliances
Doing here
Cuz I
I've written about like
Some effort you guys had way back with
Wink 2 characters retrofit
You guys so
What is the overall strategy
Connect to this really important Uchi appliances
The ability to deliver firmware updates
Appliance connected
A really exciting thing to sell people
I do not buy the appliance
Day one thinking
Pine-Sol
Some years down the road I can get a service update
How to say you better
A trip to my house
Partnerships with value-added
Tires in in the smart home field
And
Creno's use cases are making people want to connect
I will talk about several of them today but
Did you give the person
The real value their
And make that extra step to get that plants connected
Which is really good for them the long-term and short-term as well cuz it may get there really nice shoes case
The how to solve their everyday
And it's really good for you guys because there's a
There's a huge benefit
Set for y'all to see how the
The appliances
Performing in the feet
Oso
We have tons
Identify a problem
An appliance and maybe even a person doesn't need to know about
Contact a consumer
Consumer
I left another appliances in performing optimally
Talk to them send a service tech or pushing update to really build a relationship with consumer
Inn of the appliances that
You guys have out there is your whole line connected now
Disconnected you have the refrigerator
Dishwasher
The wall of in the rain
The washer the dryer
Window air conditioner
You don't have microwave yet
You don't have art
Handsome yet
The full product line for the most part is connected
So how long ago did you guys start at 8
Really in mass that starting around 2014
Where you started to see appliances Roloff in
Significant numbers off the production line
Jaguar Wi-Fi capable last year we had 70s
Use connected this year they'll be
Over a hundred when it's all said and done this year
Alright so since you guys have been doing this for
Do consumers care about Wi-Fi
Is an appliance
And
Once they bought it an appliance with Wi-Fi do they bother to
That's a great question
Unless you can imagine
It's not if they're not strongly connected
You'll find a lot of iot
Devices in the home
Light switches garage door opener
Because those have that everyday up and down on off
These cases for appliances the home a little more complicated so people don't
Intuitively always see
The reason to connect.
But you're starting to see more and more of these Partnerships which is
Really driving
Does integration to have
We can specifically talk about one that's really been an explosion in the spaces when the echo came online
What's that keeps building you don't have to
People hands
Free in the kitchen
There's always a Time
In the kitchen
When you could use one or two or three more hands to complete your action right
They're full of bacteria from your chicken that you're preparing their dirty
Cookie dough you may have a child
At your leg like
Find a cook
All those things
Right really restrict what you can do you have to use your that old elbow trick where you kind of
Kiddo
At the water faucet to turn it on to wash your hands to go
Touch your oven
Now that that boys experience
Annex connected Wi-Fi Appliance
Now
I'm really starting to see the value in the home is how do I fi
Capabilities really tries diet
My everyday life
Munchkin
By far our most
Common function through voice control is preheating out that people come down
They get ready to get into the refrigerator to get out their meat or the protein rather going to fix
Nhsa
Geneva preheat the oven to 350
Uso Geneva is your
Assistant coach Geneva is actually Amazon
Skilled so you can activate that skill connect your TV connect Appliance to that skill
And then you can talk to Geneva and she can control all of our connected points
Got it okay I was like who is this Geneva woman and where is she what is she doing in my kitchen
Designs by as originally had
Gel for the oven the skill for the refrigerator
Appliances would want to talk to each other
And have you remember which one to talk to
Would be a pain point for the consumer so we just a always talk to Geneva
She is the broker of all that information and she'll get the information to the right of plane
I like that yeah that's definitely an issue that
I think we're going to see a lot more of his voice control mousse places
Cuz I do not want to think
Oh I'm trying to text my ex Geneva
And I want to know
Text someone so now I'm going to ask Google
And it's okay
So you guys are working with Partners to give people a reason to connect
Beyond just the
Cool stuff that can do for
And I will say every
I don't have a GE fridge
Have a Samsung fridge
But
Couple weeks ago
It started making this weird funky noise
And we were like what is happening and I wanted a connected fridge more than anything in the
The world at that moment so I could just be like
Hey
Samsung take a virtual look at my fridge
Tell me what's wrong so we can just fix
And it said I had to call a little refrigerator app
Do something
Antipsychotics exactly
That's what you were trying to
Kataka right there if we give you a recent connect that refrigerator
At the time of purchase
When a problem occurs
There's a good chance at night
Are you identified or when that check comes to your house we can guarantee in the first time they come there
It doesn't have the right parts on there
Trusted to deliver you
I fixed Appliance
I know
So you guys do want connected Appliance
For the one possibly two or never X
Set this thing might break
So that's the reason I connect the second reason to connect is probably cool things like voice control
Let's talk about intelligence so when you connect
Do this for awhile so a while back
Are 2013
People were like so we can remotely control it
For example for my smartphone
For most people it didn't feel like a good enough reason to spend the extra dollars for
But now what I'm seeing is things like
My favorite device the June oven
Which is a
Oven is connected but the connectivity is sideline for the fact that it's
Smart it has
Your sensors in the feet that way the food it's got
Preprogrammed recipes in it
Just
You know I istick basically a piece of fish in there and it's like hey is the same and I'm like yes
It's like you want it
Well done
And I'm like
Yes
Isn't it just
Does it
And that to me is like where we should be heading
Supposed to like
Can control it for me
So what are your thoughts where are you guys
I couldn't agree with you more so I think that is
Exactly where you want to go
Caribou some of that difficulty of controlling
The appliance since we make appliances we also know how to control it
Better than a lot of consumers do
But to get used to using a certain example so
Your oven has a lot of modes a lot of people don't know when to use convection when to not use convection
If you tell us
You're making food X
Rights that we can intelligently go through in and recommend emotes you can always override it maybe you're a better Chef than we are Maybe
You got a specialty technique you want to use
Of what the best notes
And that teacher you saw actually going back to boys
Came into this
What is the most popular thing people are doing
So what did you see us do be rolled in a lot of precepts
So now you can say
I want cookies
I want pizza I want chicken nuggets I want lasagna
All those things come through now we say
Hey
This is Geneva we would we recommend putting your husband with convection baked at 350
At sets at there so the user doesn't have necessary notes this is great
Teenagers
Aspiring cook stats that don't quite know all the fancy features maybe they're having to do
Tell us the food that you want to cook and we're going to recommend emotes
And that's great because the control panel can't have a mode on it for every possible food combination
But he can't let that boy is not connected experience has no inattentive what you're trying to do which is cook that food
Now we can deliver specialty mode to you so you'll see overtime
Athletic tons of new specialty modes to the users to that interface
That's great so do I end up saying something Lake Geneva
Preheat the oven for cookies or is it more like
Initiate a conversation
And Geneva's like
You want to cook
So right now it's
You're giving her that preset please say Geneva
I'll be able to preheat for cookies
That's where we are right now but as we go you're going to find these conversational systems to be more open-ended to really kind of
Get it what you want
I love it okay this is very smart
So let's think about
Since we're in the kitchen let's stay in the kitchen we won't
We will head to the laundry room just yet what do you think of when we talk about a smart
Kitchen
I'm curious like
In 3 to 5 years
What is my cooking or my kitchen experience going to be like in the GE appliance world
I really think it's the assisted cooking
It's going to really I revolutionized the kitchen
Is it's going to be the recipe app
Interacting
The appliance
Take over once you've done the basic
Brace
It's going to know that you need to set temperature eggs for 30 minutes
And then boil for the last minute
Or you going to see exciting things on it
Going to hold 375 for 5 minutes and then automatically turn it down
The recipe for
2:30 explicit directions
To the Appliance
I think that's really big
Siding parts
It's going up a lot of people's cookie
Kitchen
That is exciting in
I've been excited about this for a long time
And I think one of the key elements that we don't talk about
What is the concept of how do we digitize
Recipes in have computers understand what food is being cooked
And you guys
So it's one thing for me to tell the oven hey I'm making
Cookies
Four examples and it to figure
Out what I need to do from there in the case of that unit uses
Pictures
Video image
You have a relationship
Trap is really fundamentally
Remaking dresses
So I'm curious like
How you guys see
Digital recipezaar instructions
How that's going to cut of my grade
Into the kitchen
Partner
Stop static create user experience
And they're really taking that recipe to the next level by minimizing the number of bowls that a person needs to use for
Pear recipe
By making sure their step by step by doing
Unit conversions if you don't have enough milk or you don't have enough of the greedy day
Sizing recipe so you can
Make it perfectly
What's what you do have
That's really great siding and then you tie that into the oven
So it knows exactly when the preheat and knows exactly the temperature in set the timers and everything comes out
Coordinate at the end
It was really a very exciting partnership
I think you're going to see
Many more of those types of Partnerships
With our connect appliances over the next coming years
So we got this vision is like assisted cook
What else needs to come together to make that a reality
We have
The connected Appliance
Switch digital recipes
What else might we need
So that's a great question
So one thing that I think is
Overlook sometimes is knowing what's in the pants
So you have that
Really have that Inventory management kind of Concepts a really connect everything so that the recipe
Is recommending recipes
The Grinch you have on him
No use giving you recipes that you
Have to go to specialty store to get ingredient for you don't have on hand
I think another important thing is people are very health conscious
So being able to
Know that I have stole some lose weight or lower my cholesterol or have better heart health
Constraint that is part of
My recipes
And then I think you're going to continue C
The appliances
The Livermore
Sensors
Four different types
The things since the food is done this sir
Content level different types of elements
Did occur during cooking
Sensors you going to have
Inventory management
You're going to have this health-conscious kind of gold silver all working
Together
Deliver a good experience
This sounds magical
But
I'm not excited enough yet
Yet
To go out and buy all new appliances
So how do we I guess there's two questions
What is how long till we get to something like this but to
Is there a way to retrofit are you guys thinking about that or is it just
New staff
Get me to the mall
Are plants is the way we architect our cloud
We always are looking to be backwards
Apple so we don't
Deliver capability and it's only available on
Appliances in Newark
We want to make sure they're always carrying our existing
A customer base
In line so that when it comes out
Wait we don't leave you.
So do those from where updates into that connected
Experienced then we can
Make that Appliance
If it supports the mode
Capable for that new capabilities
That is definitely in the Forefront of these new content part
I love this anymore here listening
You got exciting new integration
There give me a call would love to talk to you about
How we bring next
Because it's agnostic
Some people are want to cook on drop
And that's how they want to use
MSP
Platform
We want to be that connecting piece in middle cuz that's why they always have to put it in the oven to bake it
So we want to be open to all these Integrations as they come cuz we know it's a very exciting space a lot of
Startups are out there every day with new and innovative ideas and we're open to
I'm sad about my lack of retrofit
Pets but I am excited
About your kind of forward-thinking
Hiiraan
Teacher availability
So
One of the things I've been thinking about
With connected appliances especially things like ovens which should last for
I don't know 10 to 15 years
How do you kind of building
I guess is it margin or build a way to knowing that you're going to have to support this thing for you know the next decade
Decade and a half
Budgeting for that
How do you communicate that to
Customer
AC I'd love to answer that question
That's not really in my ballpark being a large company we have a lots of teams with
Distinct responsibilities and there are people looking at that but as you mentioned that's new
Adventure that we're getting into as how to manage the software that Appliance
Much much longer than we used to
So I would have to defer to
All nests
Question
Sounds good
Yes
There's probably nothing worse than in the oven
Actually probably a refrigerator that bricks itself
Toby turtle
Let's move into the laundry
Mostly because
I can't think of what I'd want in a connected washer and dryer other than like energy management features
Assured by people in the industry
That there are features that I
So I would love to hear you
The teacher that makes the most sense
In this laundry space is that
Often times people have that Bond repair on a different floor than they're spending the majority of their time you'll see it often
Basement
You'll see it
Oftentimes upstairs in a bedroom
We're on that
Saturday maybe where you're doing your chores you're going around the house when you're cleaning and you have to do laundry
You have to walk up and down those stairs
The laundry is done how many times have you walked
Upstairs
Got to the
To the unit and then realize it has 5 minutes left
Are you go back downstairs
Can you come back up
Being able to know the status of that unit
In itself is a very valuable thing
Manage your time
Because often times people don't love to do laundry
It's kind of a task that has to be
Did you have to do
Every weekend and you want to do it in a short a time as you can
Are we have Partnerships with
Amazon TRS
So that you can automatically reorder dryer sheets
So now you don't have to worry
About how many times have you reached over to put a load in there
And realized that was the last dryer sheet or maybe you were out
Right so having that automatically
Replenishment
Come along
Connect appliances
Another exciting example is been fixed and the tumble
You're busy doing something you can't quite get there you don't want your clothes wrinkle
If you found out that the timeout expired just extended tumble
Turn off the heat and let the clothes
Continue the temple so they don't wrinkle soap
There's three or four
Use cases fat laundry care
Terilli's Breakside
Okay
I always feel like my washer and dryer to high-tech features on there
I don't even know what the
This particular laundry cycle.
How do I make this easier
Or maybe I don't
That's an exciting question
Think about your laundry and all those Cycles you don't know what they mean
Let's take it back
To where we mention
Presets for foods
Let's say you know you have grass stains
On Cotton
Are bougie
Why don't you just tell the unit
So something in the future
You should be smart enough to
Understand
I have Scott Fabrics
Grass stains or wine or ketchup or whatever this thing that beats
I figure out the best cycle for
I like it
Okay
So here's the biggest most difficult question I have
When it comes to appliances
Which is
Right now I have
Appliances I I do have GE Appliances but I also have
The Samsung refrigerator I have
Bosch
Stuff
So I have
Different stuff in my house
And I bump I actually built my house and bought all my appliances at the same time but I chose different
Appliances for that reason
Are you guys ever going to work with you know
Bosch
Or is there going to be another middle person
To handle all that for me
But you do see us as you see is working with home hub so you see is working
With
Echo
Don't be out there home hub
That we will work with
As people adopt the home hub and they so excited there's passionate
Energy around the whole pup you'll see us
Develop for that as well
It is possible that that becomes
Who's the broker for the appliances
To work together
Well
Don't thank you so much for coming on the show today I am sad that I will not be able to try Geneva but at some point in time maybe I'll
I'll pop into a store and see if I can check this out because
It kind of sounds awesome
Definitely
Next time I'm in the market for appliances
Why don't you check them out
And you see them in the stores and you interact with them you're going to love them and you're going to be a customer for life
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up
For my newsletter Stacy knows things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you now
Next week