Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacy Higgins
Kevin tofel
Thank you Stacey
Alright this week we have
Awesome show we are gonna be
We talkin about
Should we buy the apple homepod or not
Layoffs in consumer iot
Big money for ring
Power Wheel
Are Google home experience
Kevin
New purchase and Kevin's new project
Plus
We have
Sponsor
Pointcentral coming up for you and our cat
Matt turck Firstmark capital
Who every two years does an iot landscape
Map and blog
Post it is incredibly Epic
He distills all of that down
1 in an interview
Is the Memory Maker of iot
And this is not a 500 swiper
It is pretty long but it's not five
The first
Let's go to a message from
Our sponsor
This week sponsor is CBT Nuggets
How does the iot change the way we do business
For many organizations it means a proliferation of devices and tools and every device connected to your network is another
Potential vulnerability you may think your greatest security threat is malicious hackers but really it's an unsecured Smart Watch worn by
But if everyone on your team is trained in security best practices it significantly reduces your chance of
Data breach for the severity of that bridge CBT Nuggets has been a top training choice for it Professionals for decades
And now they're making the same high-quality online training solutions for end-user security so your team can read
Recognize and stop threats before they make it
Go to CBT Nuggets. To find out more about how end-user security training can protect your
Network in the iot
Okay Kevin
So much news
So they could add some
The pad but let's kick it off with
News on Apple's homepod
Which was due out
He was an early January
Yeah before the end of the year and they deleted come December they announced the delay
If you're listening to this podcast on Thursday
Comes out you have
Friday until Friday to get ready to order your homepod for
At 49
Dollars
It will be delivered on February
Correct correct and I have an alarm set to get a
At 3 a.m. eastern time
I can order one for us
So we can test it
Obviously won't have it till February 9th at the earliest but
I was actually thinking about this would I buy this if we weren't going to review this
Am I answer is probably not
But obviously we're still going to
And you're not an
Apple ecosystem user so I'm assuming you would not buy this either
I'm not even sure we should
Buy it
Chicken spot
We are going to buy it
For the show because I think a lot of you guys are listeners really want
To understand what this products about and I totally get
So we're doing it
I will say looking at the features it really does not seem like a smart home
At all
And that is because they were not marketing it primarily as one
And that kind of fits in with apples standard operating for
Procedure what they'll do is they will
Look at the highlights of something and stress those
Like such as it's going to have awesome music and sound quality inn
You can pair two of these and a stereo sound like
Other devices that are used today although that's a feature that's coming later in the year with a soft
It's all about the sound and everything else
And the Siri
Part of it
Is all about music Control
And oh by the way you can control homekit stuff
How to I think it's because they just
Have a
A ton of slew of homekit devices out there on the market by comparison a relatively speaking
Other platforms
NP
Siri just
Isn't still that good I mean I don't know how else to say it
Acceptable at best
It seems so
I because everyone who's following in the footsteps of
Everyone is following in the footsteps of Apple in the developing
App Store
Right so back
To develop
Like their developer programs for
Voice
Smart Switch
I just
Apples either apples got some magical big plan that we don't see and it sees the market going in a totally
Different direction which
Maybe but it feels like
It's coming out in the smart speaker space with a product that ignores what people seem to be mostly doing
What smart speaker
Although most people are setting timers and listening to
So we could be
True true I mean there's a lot of people affect Apple even said they now have 500 million people using Siri through all
All devices and obviously iOS devices through
Do they count when I ask
Accidentally activate
You know I I don't know the details but it would not surprise me to be honest but it is what it is it's just a number so
Sure people are using Siri but
Are they frustrated by Siri I'd say not an equal number of series or but I had a heck of a lot of them certainly are
I read through Forums on the other products that are out there and then they're like yep I went with Google home or an echo because
Siri just isn't cutting it for me I can do so much more and so on and so forth
So there are some unsatisfied series with out there in that 500 million number
For sure
Will this product
Sway them
Not on day one I don't think
Because
There's no major Siri improvements that have been mentioned or expected
My guess is to get this out there focus on the home
Audio features
In Italian with Apple
Music subscriptions and so on
And then later at WWDC
Show off some better series Smart's cuz it's just
But I actually expected that when this came out or last year's WWDC so I was disappointed in both instances
So I could will be disappointed this
Summer when WWDC happens in
I really don't do much with Siri in terms of smart on
And we should not forget that actually the Amazon Echo when it came out as a
One of the weird beta products where you had to get an invite to order it
When that came out in December 2014
It didn't have any smart home stuff
I didn't get that until
March Bible
So and that's actually when I ordered it I did not order it out of the box
Because of that reason once they added the partners and the
Smart home stuff that's when I went all-in
So you're right
Possible
It's coming I don't know
Swedish will be a homekit hub for what it's worth
So you can remotely access things
Google Now
Multi-room audio
It does not
Launch
And it does not have the ability to use other music Services which I actually thought was
Kind of astonishing
Deckstats app
I know but
Even put Google actually
Compared to Amazon Google is very limited in its Music Services
And again that may be a reason to go to
We'll talk about Google in a
In a bit because we've actually both transitioned to try and use
Local Taco
Homepod
We are on the fence
Where can I buy it
Heaven's going to test it
And then we're going to come back and tell you what we think
And it's probably just going to be an ongoing segna
As hopefully features are added
So I would say to you guys
If you're all in an apple
And you got 350 bucks burning a hole in your pocket
If you don't already have like a similar system such as a Sonos or or something else with your bottom speaker
Yeah okay that I see but
It's like what you already have
I tend to agree with you and that and I say that as a
Person who in a family of four we all use iOS devices
We have an apple music subscription
Family subscription
I would still
Be hesitant
Coyote park
All right
Bad news
Layoffs in the
Samurai
I didn't realize you're going to make yourself
All right
TechCrunch is reporting that Sparrow
Laid off
Dozens of
People as
It had a bad holiday season and also reported the tile
Laid off dozens of
People after a disappointing holiday season
And
That is unsurprising
Consumer electronics are merciless and the holiday season
Make a break
But it is kind of
It's a sad sign for the consumer
Iot Market
Get in we're just talked about this with our guests met her
But later
Short of it is
Man
Fisher
2017 has been brutal
For consumer
Hardware iot
And I don't seek it.
It has I think the companies that are doing
Better or have a
More brighter future are the ones that are expanding their product line
When I look at something like a tile they make a great product as a Bluetooth tracker
And they tweet the design and then features little bit but
That's all they make
Well that's not true
So they actually
Have a platform
They're trying to be a platformer
Capabilities of tile into lots of
Products so they have a deal with an umbrella maker they had a deal with
Land Rover
They have deals with
Companies
Fix your phone
So
Okay let me just stop or say about because that
Well I didn't know about that and that is good
It's still the underlying
Product feature and they're trying together Partners as opposed to
Creighton work a range of devices
And Gathering Partners is not always easy and especially when it's something that
SS fundamental as Bluetooth tracking when there are
Multiple products that can do this
Either apps on your phone that can do
I mean
That's
Just not an expansion of
Products to me
Well so I think it's actually a smarter
Business
Kind of Port Hardware
I just think it does
Take a lot
It takes time
So that makes sense and
On Spiro that what they just were bitten by the fact that
You know if you bought one round bb8 saying he probably didn't need the next version
And they basically
Trying to shift its focus from
Education
Which is where they kind of started
Out a little bit so we'll see I mean it's possible that Sphero is a decent company but it's probably never going to be that big
Maybe I could spot by another
Toy company
Speaking of
Consumer iot
Ring is raising money
Evaluation of almost 1 billion dollars according to the information
This is a story I too was chasing
They just snack
Snack before I could
Fully confer
Is it good publication I trust him
I've heard the Same Rivers
I am
By this news
I cannot fathom
The ring would be worth
Billion dollars
They sell
Granite they've done what you said
They've expanded their product line
But with her
Their lawsuit with ADT which I have also heard
Is close to or has reached a set
It doesn't make sense to me
If it would be worth that much
I just don't see it
Well I tend to agree with you when I just look at the numbers but then when I step back
I can like what was
Net worth
When they only had a couple products
Nest was in a fluffy exciting time back in
In 2014 and they had Tony fadell who by the way just moved
France
Okay yeah he's got offices now and some French Hardware
Startup
Oh I can't think of the French word for cool
Okay
True. Very true
I don't I'm not saying I see
Ring is worth a billion dollars it's not for me to say anyway cuz I'm not a financial analyst
I sort of get it
I mean the smart home and iot space is all you see is
Reports of
X billion devices
The next five years and summer
I'm really from a consumer standpoint
At the very beginning of this Market
So you're going to have inflated value so I'm not saying again
They're worth a billion but I can see
Why people think they might be
I feel like
If I look at
The stuff in it
And I'm talk to some of their
Pliers
I don't think they're making much margin
Countertop corbels
They still have
It's a relatively High bomb but they also pay licensing fees for all of their video processing
So I look at that and I'm like
That could be
And
The security products
Is actually really calm
Telling but it's not on the market
And meanwhile dark
Senators are
Going all out to
Black security available
Michelle
Briefly talk about that because Comcast
Actually reported
Their earnings on
Wednesday 12
And they now have one point
13 billion
Home automation and Security customer
Merced CS
They basically made
Home automation
Available to 15 million
After customers with
Their fanciest
Right
So I look at that I'm like
The holy cow 4% of Comcast
Broadband subscribe
Drivers have made the choice
Call Beth and said I want this
Right and I'm willing to pay for it
And I'm willing to pay for it and now
Everyone can have it
And call up in
It's on like
They don't have to call
I should have to do
I'm sure they do with God
That's all I'm going to say
I know you have strong feel
So so I look at that and then alarm.com has about 5 million
ATT is getting actually more active with SmartThings and they've got 7.2 million business and
Presidential Kush
That's a little different
Maybe ring is
This is just me off the top of my head maybe ring is positioning itself to be purchased by another security company
Yes they have their own security products coming out
They do have the doorbells
They have
It just announced at CES some new outdoor
Lights as a result of purchasing mr. beams
I don't recall how much they paid for mr. Bean's butt
They're getting to outdoor LED lighting
Maybe they're just set themselves up to be to be blunt I don't know
I would not need none of the security cam
Buy them at
We're just
Let's talk
Briefly
It's because I
Transitioned in the last week to using
My Google home
And a Google mini
Tell Google home what downstairs in my
Open plan living dining
Kitchen area
And then a Google mini
It is in my bedroom
I'm trying to force my
They're like
Metal
Tell me this
Come up with
So you sound flummoxed
It's a frustrating experience in part just because now I have to touch all of these things that
Previously worked
Work cell
Keeping that in mind
I will say first off
Google has some awesome features like the ability to add
Really easily
Things to my Google Calendar
The challenges I can't use the Google home with my
Professional
Google
Accounts
Right not a Google Apps account that is correct and that is just
Cos Amino end of
Pain
Because I add things but it goes to the
Open calendar and I share the calendars but
I apparently can't share them both ways I'm experiencing some
Trouble
This has been a long-term challenge for Google and a lot of people validly complain about it
And I keep coming back to the fact that from a business standpoint
People use Google Apps own their data
So Google
Doesn't
Put a lot of functionality smart functionality in those accounts it doesn't work with them because
You know
It's different on the consumers
I would actually give Google
Cuz I think there's a huge value-add to being able to ask
Cuz right now if I ask Google what's on my
My calendar for the day
It doesn't cuz most of my
Appointments are on my
Apps
And so
It's like
You don't have anything today
Yes madam
Can tie into my Google
And this is
I'm like
NN people are probably people who
Use it for work I probably like this is awesome
But they're giving up something that they said they never want to give up on that is giving a work date at 2
Right but I'm okay and I don't know if we get it
Yeah but I have to make some major policy changes terms of service and so on I don't know that all the people who are try or you
Using say a Amazon Echo with a work Google account
Understand that the very thing they said they never wanted to do they're actually doing I don't think they're putting two and two together
But hopefully now they
Cuz you adjust
Okay
The other thing that is driving me bonkers
Outside the musical
Is
The Google shortcut
Some of my work
Some of mine
But Lord I cannot tell
Why they don't
And this is driving me bonkers
They're also very limited in my experience
They are limited it is also I will say it was frustrating
Like to do my
Harmony so with my television
When I because Harmony is not a device that
You can add from
App you have to verbally say
Okay g
Add Harmony
And then it says
Okay I'm showing you a card to link your account
And then you link
But then when you say you have to then say
Call me to okg ask Harmony to turn on
Yes
And what's weird
Is then
Your TV turns on
And then
Sometimes
Completely do voice comes on
I'm Harmony
How can I help you
So it's funny you mention that to me it's almost like
Adding a bot
That's what they've done Nevada. Chatbot for
Some of these products
Like I have the canary and I added finally got the canary linkage to work with Google Assistant
And it's exact same thing
So when I want to find out who is home or was not home which Canary can do that with his geolocation
I have to say you have to ask G to talk to Canary
And then the different voice because it's a canary bot comes in and says
What can I help you
Who is home
And it will tell me who is Homer
So it's
It's a freaking point
Because it's not a native integration and it's very I totally read this very first
So that was that and I did turn in the other
Harmony is a good example of this actually because then I created a short
That's so now I can say Okay g turn on TV
I can also turn on
Options to SATA
Then you have to make a second
Turn off TV
Adventure
Volume
And each time Harmony comes back on even though you
And talk to you
Yes to thoughts on that one I actually don't have that problem only
Because
My TV is connected to the Nvidia Shield which is an Android TV box
So I can just say Okay g
Turn TV on and it fires up both my
My TV and the shield box because it's actually working through the shield box
And I can do the same thing with turn off and it shuts both of them off
So if you go with an a native
Chromecast capable thing it works well
And I know that you're not doing that
I'm just pointing out for those who have that
If you have Chrome Cast
Yes
My other thought on these shortcuts is
I can't
When do scenes or routines with multiple things happen
I think so what I did was
I hooked up with has a recent integration I hooked up you know me
Into Google
And now when I walk into my room which I typically
Want to chill out
At night time and watch TV or something listen to music I say Haji activate relaxation
And I set that up and you know me too
Turn on the light at 50%
It's not you bright and fire up my Sonos with some easy listening music so I tie together things that weigh
And by the way
Because we did have someone ask this question
We're bad people
Coconut
Has a problem
You know me is spelled y o n o m
Augmentin
All of your Googling in the world may not get you there
But let us know
So
Tell me if you can spell me
Roof
Disappointed as one of their labs
Hurts so
Your mileage may vary
All right
Google Voice match works with Netflix profiles now which would be
Be cool if Google Voice match actually
Yeah that's true and then because I'm the only one who talked to anything in my house and my family still is not even on The Voice
I can only test
I can't really test voice match
Just throw that out there
But that's handy if it does work for you because we have multiple profiles in Netflix
If I could get them to use it
You know my daughter could say hey G
Watch whatever it was Grey's Anatomy on Netflix a would pick up where she left off versus where I left off a little I don't watch crazy
Netflix
All right and then Kevin you found a smoking hot
Google home Mini
Yes and I just verify before the show that it's still active Google how many was easy to get on sale over the holidays but all those say
Disappear now it's full price pretty much
Because you and I are making this move to kind of transition away and test the waters more with Google home
I went and found a Google home Mini 2 pack deals
You got one in charcoal one and chalk you cannot pick the color to get one of each
For $88
Shipt
Expedited shipping is included
88 bucks no sales tax either unless you live in New Jersey or New York
Go to B&H
Toto and you can get two Google home minis for 88 bucks
Which is what I did
I think that delivered yesterday
Call me based on what we're saying you may not get excited about the
We're still experimenting
It's possible.
Even out the Kinks
All right
We got some quick news bits
So
Trouble in the world of
Low-power wide area
Networks this is from fiercewireless
Cuz they've been following this
Sigfox
Confirmed earlier this year that it's us Chief is no longer with the
The company and that it didn't reach its network coverage goals for 27
Which feels like bad news
Allen poythress
Who is president of sick-box North America
Is left
Is Secaucus station to part ways
Which feels like you
And then
In the story they also talked about John Horn who would left ingenue
Which was another low power wide area Networks
Last spring I haven't heard much at all from ingenue
Can you
Since probably 2016
I feel that that's probably
I would not be excited about
So just to step back on both of these
Companies that you're mentioning
These are I don't want to leave incorrect made out of these proprietary low power
Their proprietary
Right End to me
At this point in time
You know when they conceived the idea I think it was a great idea
But at this point in time I think they're challenge
Is obviously
The more standard
Wireless protocols and implementation
That carriers are starting to pick up on but I don't know if you agree or not I think there's still a role for these kinds of
They're going to be increasingly pressed between
Laura
Which is kind of a white area but
It doesn't have to have
Play Nationwide coverage right
And these private Networks
People are setting
Using Laura and then also
Nb-iot and Cat
At 1 a.m.
Networks that the carriers are
Exactly that's the issue I think it is a matter of timing
And more
Standard
Implementation send anything else but that's just my guess
Indeed
And this is a little bit of
Sad song
Security news but
Rescue button
People buy
These are Bluetooth face buttons
Women or protesters or anybody who worries about personal safety you can press the button on these and they're supposed to alert
Someone with like
Hey I've arrived at the
This place or it might be like
Attacked help
And it sends data
From the device to your phone and then the
The phone sends usually at
So Duo security has done research and they found
But unfortunately
Three major devices we're safe revolar
And
The roar personal safety system known as
Athena all have some sort of
Compromised
So the best one is the Athena from
Roar personal safety
The other two have some issues
On their Bluetooth security so they can be
You could be trapped
Using Bluetooth
On both of these other devices and they are subject to denial
Service attack
And this is a problem I think the denial-of-service attack is probably not some random guy is going to bug you is probably more for like
Local government using it against protesters but
The fact that you can be
Tracked via Bluetooth is a problem because this is a kind of device that women who have stalkers often
Look for
And if you have a stalker it's possible that they will actually just instead use it to track you
The actual problem is trying to solve actually contribute to the
Pulling to this in the show notes cuz it's an interesting study is it important
Issue ID
I've never bought one of these but I have considered them
And I have a daughter and I'm like hey you know
It might be nice for her to have just a quick button
Although
Probably just forget it
That is
All our news basically so let's talk about
Kevin has bought a new
Yeah you called it a curable before the show which is sorta is but at my first true hearable
Was purchased
Just to level set
I have noticed over the past several years that I am having problems
Scaring people in conversation when
There's a lot of background noise multiple
People talking and so on
And I don't think it's an issue when I listen to music more than that because I crank
Turn the volume up
Seems my TV and pack my family is like
Why is your TV so loud in your office and we're down here we can hear your TV
It sounds great to me but that's because
I'm obviously starting to experience some hearing challenges
And
I mean I know that embarrasses some people that I've no issue
You know admitting to it so I'd rather fix it
So
What I did was
I actually found a free app
And it's you can get it at for iOS only it's called FedEx Fe and NEX
Go to FedEx. IO to hear about it it's an augmented hearing application
It's free it works with Bluetooth headphones and iPhone
What does is it basically pipes the sound from an iPhone to your headphones
She put an iPhone next to say the TV
And it captures through the microphone of the phone
All of the audio
Comes up to your ears and you can adjust the sound and so on so I can turn the TV down so my family doesn't hear it
But I hear it just as loud because it's being Bluetooth fed to my ears it was free and then like Alyssa's not
Bad but I would have to use the
The phone has the microphone all the time so it's not ideal as a long-term solution for me
Purchased iqbuds witch
Are basically Bluetooth wireless
Earbuds
Just like the airpod
How to put one in each ear but they also have two microphones
In each
Earbud
And that will amplify sounds you can
Get rid of some noise as noise suppression which is fully configurable
There a difference
Cenarios wrecking Sam at home I'm in a meeting I'm in a
Cara
Plane
You can set different environments
And
Maybe they look a little goofy to me
But I'm certainly not ready for a hearing aid yet
They're working really well they're not cheap they're a lot cheaper than during any other $299
Battery life is not
Mary exceptionalists
Literally four hours if you're going to listen to music and hear the outside world with eight hours if you just want to hear and amplify
Sound for conversation
In such a little wireless charging case airpods 2
Overall I'm pretty happy with them they have great conversations in my family to test them
Pictures of much better
I could turn my TV down in my office late at night and still hear the sound really really loud if I want
So you know you've mentioned parables in the past they sit and Ivory
It's always kind of scoffing at am I let's just silly butt
Now that I need the money
What's coughing anymore and this is an interesting experience
That's why we don't use video when we do the podcast I be shaking my head like Yoruba
That's just silly
What I bought Heroes
All right and then you've got another
Project
Yeah you want make a quick
I always have a project and I can probably talk for 2 hours on this. Don't worry
Yes I will yes I will and I will share code and so on and so forth
So I have long said I want my smart home to be smarter
It has so much data but I can't get it that day though
I can't make things talk to each other unless the device makers make things talk to each other not frustrate as all heck
So as a programming newbie
I decided to start tackling some of these personal challenges and my smart home to get more value
Of the date of its being
In this particular instance I'm not capturing data from the home I'm having my home intelligently
Notify me with Ambien notify
Vacations
Things that are happening in the world that I care about
In particular
I have
Tied into the API
Of a crypto coin exchange I used to buy and trade coins
I want to know when I wake up or anytime of the day without going out
Route to an app or the Weber thanks
How am I doing on my coins making money today or they losing money
So I tied into the
API for binance which is the exchange of values
And I also tied into the API for lifx bulbs
Which are homekit compatible bulbs similar to Philips Hue in that you can change the color of them
And so on so forth
What I did was
Every two minutes I have a python if I created that uses an API to get
The value of
Acrylic point and then it takes that data
And conditionally changes the light bulb color from green to red I mean the plus a negative
And it
Take the percentage gain or loss
And be that as a brightness
Parameter to the lifx bulb
So if I wake up and I've got a bright green light in my office I know
I had a good night in the crypto coin invest
I don't want to see red obviously
Right now I'm seeing a little bit of red
As we speak
Not good but
It's really interesting to me to
Have my home
Notify me of
External
Data such as that like I care about
And people may not care about crypto coins you could have caused anything
You could make a quick
Weather
App that scans for the actual temperature outside and
Lights the bulb 2
A certain color and so much there's a lot of implementation so you could do
So I'm going to say I've been doing this for
4 years using
I've told you for years from
Used it to show like I actually used to have a light that lit up in my
My office if
Stock that I followed on Yahoo
Finance was moving more than
5%
Which
It's awesome
If you are and you should follow Kevin cuz he can probably get more granular
Left and there's less of latency
But if you're not you can do a similar thing
Absolutely absolutely
No no no you're hungry
Can't write because not everybody wants
2 code
And I
Took this as a to
Factor thing one I want
To get that information with a glance
Batu and also trying to learn to code
Let me know when
Stops and starts and what not as I get older it's just it's a fun thing for me
So I'd like to even expand this
Yes to having notifications
From a voice assistant
That says
So-and-so is home now
Meaning to my canary has that it tells me in the timeline of events
I just got home
And that data is available in the event logs for an API so I just need to figure that out
It's a wide range of applications that you could do any right you don't have a code for it but it's
It's really
Really a fun experience for me
So I will write this out and again you could apply at theoretically to any bit of information or any type of
Device that might give you ambien or actual notifications
It is time for our
Internet of Things podcast
Listener
Brought you
Ashley
Maker of electronic
Clocks with slate you can have a brand new electronic lock installed in minutes with just a screwdriver and your own two hands
And they're easy to setup and use
To see what's possible is it schlage.com
To learn more
So
Here's this week's
Stacey Kevin
Thank you for the continuous flow of great information
When I bought my home it had a pre-existing home security system
Hardwired window and doors
Pictures Etc
Play Never activated it for monitoring little security
Do you know of any iot type devices or systems
I can tap into this pre-existing Hardware I would love to use the existing sensors to either build my own
Do-it-yourself security system
Or just incorporate them
It's my smartphone
I've been looking your system such as SimpliSafe
Sensors from Elgato
Sensors
Windows and doors right next to the listing sensors that are already hard-wired in
Thank you for anybody she might have
Okay we have
An easy solution for you
And it's actually very recent solution so you should enjoy this I actually have tested this device out I need to write a
But connected
That is connected with a k
And it's connected. IO
Cells and they will ship in March a connected alarm pad
That is basically
Like a little Arduino that
Hooks into your
Existing alarm system and you wire the individual wires
To the
Arduino and
Poop it converts those Wyatt signals into digital signals
SmartThings
When it arrives you're going to be like what the what
Because I'm basically bored
But if you can install a thermostat
You can install this
And
Once you have installed you install SmartThings
And you tie it to that and then you have
The ability using SmartThings to
You control this if you don't have summer things
I don't think you can
Right right so you can look a little daunting if you
He purchases thing in
Like you said to take out the box and go what the what
You were literally getting a small microprocessor board
And
You got a
Isomers instructions that explain what
Wires may go to what IO ports and pins on this thing
But you're literally bridging digital
In a wireless and wired with us
That's exactly what I think somebody
Cool as a wire system wired sensors
Would want to
Cortical modernized
It certainly is a lot cheaper than ripping everything out and replacing all your sensors because it
Depending on how many
Sensors that you have makeup but I probably say sensors
They range from sickness zones to 24 zones
And the prices anywhere from Etsy $675
In 24 zones would be up to $165 if you have
24 less sensors or up to 20% and 165 bucks is a lot cheaper than replacing All Those sensors
And if it looks truly intimidating
I'm a magic video installs
So
Video insults video instructions
So they were almost 1800 backers of this
Kickstarter and
A percentage of those people are going to share their experiences that God chose how they did it what work what did
These type of devices usually have a fanbase for a crowd that is
More than willing to share information so that everybody benefits
Yes and remember you will have to buy a SmartThings Hub but I think those are
Or somewhere between fifty and a hundred bucks
Depending on sales and
They're very expensive
Relatively speaking yes
That is our advice
To you
If you have an iot
Question feel free to call us
The Highline at
6 to 3
742 4
And maybe we'll play on the air and
We probably will
Cuz we're so nice
Hats
That's a lot of stuff
From Kevin and I so stay tuned for a message from our sponsor and
Our Guest Matt Turk
Who is going to explain
What happened last year and what will happen
Next year
Brother this year
Can The Internet of Things
Hey rewind we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Weather is point Central
And I have Sean Miller president
A poinsettia
Scared to talk to her
Let's kick it off with
Ascent
Point Center
What is it
Pointcentral is a leading
Provider of home automation technology to short and long-term
Property manager
What we've done is turn
Home automation Tech from Individual gadgets that a homeowner made deploying their individual home into an Enterprise
Sweet the property managers do
Deploy software and Hardware costs all the homes they manage
They both improve their operational efficiency and Delight the resident
Okay so you probably have a good sense of
What's happening
The Smart Home
What's new
Coming off the heels of Cs
One of the big trends that
Seems to be continuing to grow with voice
We're really excited about voicemail voice has come a long way in three years to feel like it's in the research get the same approximate penetration
Home automation in that time
And it really helps
Residents who are for the first time stepping into a smart home in arcade paid the way for them interact that home and away they find
Comfortable
Boise and credited with doing away with a lot of the standards drama around the smart
For consumers
But if someone is actually enabling Smart Home
Spore customer
You still have to
Think about that
What are some of the technology
When you look at the space out there today they're Z-Wave zigbee
Thread
Bluetooth Wi-Fi we rely on
Z-Wave for the predominant amount of our device communication because we can encrypt it
And being in a mesh Network that allows us to
To make sure the communication is
Reliable and also very low power
Turn Wii U
A private
Encrypted
Cellular line
You get the data
Security Torx
Purse I think you'll see a lot of the conversations around
What's the right
Protocol
Settle down probably two winners
This year really excited about outside of that was this other thread that was prevalent in CS with this idea
Home start to become smart
Write that kind of convenience
Savings of people may see as you can look at a mass adopter really needs to
Beacon proact
I'm at something Point Central really excited about and then
With a company alarm.com if you put a lot of resources into
What is that look
1 servers were rolling out
This year is an actual HVAC
Predictive notification
Conservice so collectively with our parent company alarm.com we have over 5 million homes on her sister
Look across
AutoZone jumper
Performing
Dive into a specific area and notice an average so for example
We may see in Phoenix in summer time that it takes 2 hours for home decor for degree
Them something when we noticed one home
Take 6 hours to cool those same
2 degrees we can driving notification to the property manager that says hey
There's something going on
But you now have the option to go take care of
This problem before the resident is upset
B
Allura cosplay
Because you won't be rushing someone out there and dealing with a big problem
But rather now can go out and deal with the problem proactively when it's a lower-cost and probably just part of making
Gosh
I want that now
Where can I go to find out more about boys
The best place to learn about us is point central.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And I am here with today's guest
Matt Turk who is a managing director
Firstmark
I met her
I'm doing great Heights
Man I'm super excited because once again
You have produced
It feels wrong to call it a
It is like an epic time
Of all of iot
In three Char sexual
So
I love this thing every time
Yes
Yes and the blog post this is even longer than the stuff
I write you guys
Lord knows
Let's
Let's break it down for people who don't want to go
To the blog post anichart
What are the top
Noticed and then that your
Yes sir
Has been a little bit
Chicago
Trading
Courtyard cheerleading at Jewel
Halyard
Republic
Belongs
Principal
Company failure but I think what I have
Beyond
There is
Mystic way of looking at the states which is that
Thank you very much
Berkshire Building
Cycle
CPAC for the last couple of years but
You're not around cloud computing
Computing
Because it's more
We're going to take him to Olive
And more
So let's kick it off
In
2017 and is continuing
I think to struggle going into
This year
Holiday layoffs
Are post-holiday layoffs
If I
The head of a consumer iot
Do I just give up and go home I think this year is about to be about
Major price pressure
China
So I am curious what your advice to the
Send
Lily the drone company
Calling you
Doppler labs
One's very promising
Brandon Joseph
In between
Competitors
Lil Wayne
Number of
Manufacturers in a row cause
China
By the way
Companies that are
Absolutely no longer
Western
Products
Another set of computer at the top of the market
Largest
Companies that we're always
Space but I've already started coming to the stage
In the Life 2
I think she looks very particular at 1
Space with you
Voice platforms
You see that very quickly has become
Racine Country Club
Google
Coming into the state as well
Eaton company
Excluded
From decorations
Companies
To be able to play in this
Now
But yeah
Ultimately what you want to be
Buy The Watch Company
We are witnessing Vienna of sage
Electrical fire
Yours
That could perhaps Colby Brenda experiment
Yorkshire yours then
The Hope was running
Why I didn't connect
Dumb products
Smart products
You could create
Products products that brought so much more value
Rush to buy them
Much higher prices
And then the other part was
That's hardware was finally getting less hard
Your Hardware was
But you can go much faster
Getaway.
So fast forward to
Today
I think we need
The end of that phase
Where
To posting quite pan out
Maybe it's because I started out in the
Enterprise
It always struck me as odd
Having
Venture firms investing
Consumer products
That were
Hardware-based and had fundamentally
So
Do you think Venture firm should still
Be investing in
In consumer
Barry White
Square knot
Categories app
This is where you like them
Even
Cordon of course
I love you
Because
Marv Jenson
Part of the excitement
Was that affected connectivity
The hardware parts
Would become less important
N.
Software update
Woodstock Outlet
Entirely different category
Business model
And open the door to Ultrazone
2 today
Tianjin Pool Products
So let's move
From consumers
It's so dead
Let's talk about this idea
Building infrastructure for the iot
Because I think that's going to get us into some
Enterprise efforts and some of the Industrial
So
When you're talking about
Infrastructure you brought it to Cloud Edge
Connectivity
I'm curious
Where you sink kind of the most action
Happened in the most mature sex
CBD
In the lab
You're good news for the entire space
Thundercloud
Pink weave
The first phase were a lot of the top 5 providers
Largely assumed that
Their core Legacy Cloud offering
Turn the needs of iot companies
Pretty well
But I think
As always
The detail nothing Quinn company started working on top of the clouds
The good news is that so
You're the story of announcements providers offering
Google jumped into The Fray and launched the iot Cloud Core
So now you have
Which Cloud offering Hawaii
Because
As we all know cloud computing
Accelerate
The number
Edge computing
No mortgage
Intelligence
Two node level sensor
They can do different things we can decide what
Come to the cloud
Send everything
That's even better
Is true actually have the notes
Decision
That's one step
Direction intelligence
Connect to eventually
And what about the
Connectivity is Richmond
Shooting range connectivity witches in the world
Your Bluetooth and wifi
Front Range Clinic
That is a Shelly
Well-dressed problems
Up until now how much
Lift well
Problem with long range
Guanaria Weathersby
So early entrance like the clock example that's created a
Network
Connect in a way that
Consuming too much
Battery for the question
Things to do
Waiting for a response
NB iot
Call Frank
Launch carriers as well as some during 15
Are thinking about this issue and that therefore this issue
Eventually go away
Picture if I think about
In the space force
I'm interested
Space but just technology
Feel like we have
Moved
Towards
More distributed
Ways of
And now
With the Internet of Things
We're trying to make something
Even more disturbing
More diffuse
And so when I look at startups in this space
That's what gets me really excited
Sinister decentralisation aspect
You mentioned in your
SA
So I feel like we should talk about the rule of blotchy
The blockchain conceptually
Well with the name
Call Steve mobile
Connected objects one
Kia Spectra
Providing
Shorty
Which says that we know has become
Dairy
Important aspect
Wait. You're moving into my next topic
So
We'll talk about that in the second like I think it's interesting
One of the things I can
Authentication
Which is sort of like secure
Credibility
And I also think it's interesting
For things like
Micropenis
Antenna digital transactions
Without between are things which I think is
I think that is if that's not going to be a big trend
This coming year it should be a big trend
The following
Because it's essential and we can't get any
The General
Concepts of data Exchange
Your
Temperature to talk to your connected
Refrigerator
Or
Object
But if you can tie those objects
What's the blockchain
Where is the other objects next week
Friction labs
Kill
Skip forward to
Security and it's cousin privacy
Because
You talked a lot about security
Port so I'm curious but then you didn't talk at all about
Privacy
And I'm really interested in how both on the consumer side and on the Enterprise how concerns about
Privacy and what happens to people
Will stay that changes your investment PCS
How the sort of thing will develop what we
So let's kick it off with security
Assurity is
Ultimate
Look at the time
Enterprise
Security and the cheerleaders to Portuguese there
Security for
The company's
People building products that don't
Emergency
API type company books
Bill
And I used to products
Can you get insurance in your product
YouTube
Security Experts
How do you spell
Problem for the industry in general because he continues to be
Not because
They don't think that's dirty
Is importance butts
Because
To be able to ship the products
Product review
Sell more products
And then you know I have a little bit of sincerity but then.
Later when
Global products in the field
So now let's talk about privacy
Because
I didn't see it and I'm curious about your thoughts
How
Concerns over privacy and data
On the consumer
Enterprise side
Affect us in the area
Privacy
Influenza
Dermatologist
Obviously
Kingsley Portland
Something that the entire industry need to
Think about
Becoming
Zion
Location
Tricky situations tomorrow
In some cases a lack of privacy in the ability to
Collect data
Core of a lot of these business model
Whether it's consumer or if it
Is aggregating
Information on
Like what how a motor sound so you
Predictably predict
I think that is
True at the same time
Think you can address
Privacy
Fairly effectively
Priority
So they are
Sydney
Video
Where which are a well-known that there are
Shade
Locally
For example
Benton deicide
What you want to use what you want
Cell
Multiple ways
It's all about the animals game because
AIU
State a test but you can make
The business decision to spend a fair amount of time and effort
To make sure that whatever you provide to
Let's do one
Final question
You witches
What are you
Excited about
For 2018
What type of Investments are
Broadway
Don't have the hardware components that are
Interesting
Usually important and Aries that's far as I know no
Clear winner
I think that's such a good investment
Thomas vehicle to Vertical farming
Is interesting a thing
Industrial internet-of-things
Used to be
Very large Market
Because you
Do you work with industrial that comes
Software background
At some point you'll get from
Turn off downstairs two pilots two
Early deployment to full production appointments and the companies that do get to the full production deployment
Will
Chattanooga
Apsara Slaton
Buzzy's on the word or two ago but that's the same
Has been built a company that experiment
And what
A dream or just a concept will be by Bebe
If you look at this face
Issue
The good news is that Logan has been built
So
General World weather
Men's Adidas iniki
Connected hardware
I think all of this is part of the
Big emerging paradigm
Volleyball towards a connected world
Love object
I agree all right Matt face
Thank you very much that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like me
More iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week