Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Higginbotham
Your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have an awesome show for you today Gateway
Old homepod review
World's going to keep
On the Apple topic
By discussing their damage in the house
Healthcare Market
Netgear is taking part of Arlo public
We got some news on Canary Amazon Intel and Sonos Kevin's going to tell you
A little bit
About his WeMo
Rich and have a message from our sponsor Point Central
And our guest is Bruce Chatterley's CEO of
Set it
He's going to talk to us about
Laura
And Laura net worth
Lyrics We got some use cases
Some crazy functionality that I didn't
Actually know Laura had
So before we get into all of this
Let's get a message
Witch from another one
Building an iot device or solution start ahead with a Renee sauce energy
Begin your iot device designs at the software API later and leave the details to renaisa
Cloud-based iot Solutions quickly with the AE Cloud 1 kit
Amazon web services Microsoft Azure Google cloud or your choice of cloud within minutes
We're loaded time get 50% off the AE Cloud 1 kit look for the Renee sauce iot
The sandbox discussion thread on the Renee sauce rules for a go to Stacey on iot. Com
Splash cloudkit to be forwarded to the discussion thread and get your coupon that Stacey on iot
Jd.com
Cloudkit
I believe we should start
Most exciting
For us which is Mozilla
Coyote
Gateway South
This
I was excited I know for many of our listeners
This is probably right up your alley
Because you guys are the ones who tell me about homebridge and openhab and all the stuff in this
It's right here within that kind of thing although it looks a little easier
Yeah I'm super excited as well this was announced last year this is the project
Things effort from Mozilla
To allow you to have your own Gateway your own iot device Gateway in your home
Using Raspberry Pi with mid they may support other pieces of Hardware in the future
And they're giving every device in your home
Are URL and you're going to be using a web app
To control everything through the Gateway so this is definitely a DIY project and
Stacy you and I I know I am
Yes
He's really experienced
I totaled
We can't even get started
Yet though because what we could but
It be limited you can start today with a pie and the download from Mozilla to get your things Gateway go away
We are waiting on some Z-Wave dongles USB dongles
To control Z-Wave devices
So would I not starting until that gets here at all if you're going to jump the gun and try and play with us earlier
I didn't have a spare
Hi-so actually end
Z-Wave
Dongle
You're doing this it's worth noting that you have to do it for
Your country
Frequencies for four different around the
And you also need to
Make sure it has Z-Wave
Plus which is the latest iteration
It is probably worth mentioning there's a Wiki
Of supported Hardware that Mozilla is keeping track of their a couple of Z-Wave dongles
And aside from the point that you just made Stacy about
What you need to look out for the
Aeon Tac is that the right one
That's the only got I'm part of the reason that I would have gotten this one anyway
One thing I seem to have massive amounts of wireless range and second-rate have a built-in battery
So we can run for I think it said forecast 15 days if it needed to if you if you want plugged-in I guess maybe you're running your pie
High on the battery I don't know it's
Rather interesting how it all works but
The pie plugged in
That makes sense because
Perry on Z-Wave sometimes works really really much
Better when you're right next to the device
Yes no I'm not sure
I guess it's you
Is the pairing of the radios
Exactly
I seem like a cool feature
And I have tons
A lot of them are
Installed so this is actually nice
I can't move my door locks I mean I could but that would be
Uninstall
Actually my Hub to the door lock just temporarily just two
Outback
Yeah but
Anyway so this is all like a small web-based interface
Yet I don't know if there will be
So like
I think my sim is going to go nuts myself using this website which is like a dedicated URL from my Gateway
A my house as opposed to say the Wink app
Don't tell just have to do with I suppose
Dietitian
The ideas you program all your automation so the goal is never to touch
The app
It is truly supposed to be
Morada
So you set up your rules and such
Pull out
As many sensors is you
Can find because you're going to want
Let It Go
I also
Yeah whatever it's a mish-mosh over here just like
Just like you have I'll probably just put a couple devices on this for testing purposes that way
I can learn I can explain
Here on the show and then my family doesn't go nuts with the devices that use all the time cuz you can go hog-wild with this thing there's even a floor plan
10 piece of the app where you can kind of figure out where drag-and-drop where you're going to put things in a rather interesting
But again my family does not
I care about that stuff
And for all of you guys who are excited about
Control
That's what this offers and that makes sense
It's not going to change the fact that your devices are still going
You're seawave devices.
Don't necessarily
But you know this is so
What word nut
Over here at the iot podcast
Is the
Homepod
So reviews are out
We are still getting one
Kevin has one on order and it should arrive
This Friday
That's correct
So next week we'll talk about our experience with
Hybrid Mean Time
Looks like people
People thought it sounded great
And it wasn't a small
What we expected
And I said
Yeah I mean I was hoping to be wrong
But there's still a lot of
I don't want to say
It seems that the smart part of it
Apple really wants to be focused on the speaker side they are smart speakers it's smart
Technology they're using for the audio piece
Thanks
If you think about it with the beamforming and auto-tuning and
Constant changing of your listen to the music so that we can adjust on the Fly and smoke
I get that that's
Rather
Smart
Services for our listeners the smart as in smart home
Smart devices
That's
Sorely lacking faculty
Siri on the phone and tablet is actually smarter than Siri on the home but they're still
A lot of limitations there's no voice recognition in terms of
Multiple users
Couldn't see you calendars I mean
Things that just couldn't do sure you can control homekit devices
Yeah
Shut off your routine
Which
You know this is
Be smart speakers
In my life
How much more of a digital assistant
And it does things
Ranging from
What's the recipe for this drink
Drop it on my kid
Call me an Uber
I really I really value that
Do you I know you do rely heavily on the digital assistant with
Voice control on such
Do you ever set timers
I'm sure you do
Do you ever sit too at the same time would like when cooking
HEI set a rice timer and then I'll set
Broccoli timer
And that was one of the things that a couple of reviewers
She can't Siri can't do two timers on the homepod
Oh
I mean
It's like it's like a toned-down version of Siri which
I don't understand why that is there's an A8
Chip processor
I think that was in the iPhone
XR7
It's more than capable
Doing this type of request
And having a smart sand
Why is it like I sub Siri
In thumb part of my question
Maybe it'll get better
Country
Apple said that they were working on this
For 6 years however
And I think most of the focus was on the sound
That just understand why they couldn't take what they currently have for Siri
Sarpullido burlesque
Wants to share that with
Are confused
Of Apple
Let's talk about some place they're doing well which is
Healthcare
I think there's a lot to like here so I just saw story this week
About
Is 4
Group called cardiogram and they did a study called
It's part of the deep heart study
Cardiogram
UCSF
But
This one says we Apple watch can detect diabetes with an 85%
Accuracy
I thought that was
Beijing
They've already been shown to
Detect abnormal heart rhythms with 97%
Accuracy sleep apnea with 90% accuracy
And even hypertension
So in this is using
Cardiograms ail
So
It's using the date of honey
Watch to run
Reading that data is the resting heart rate and heart rate variability which is the metric they added
With the latest
Version of
Watch it was if I recall correctly so
Caring the data for the two of those is what's giving them the insight as to who may have diabetes
And I think that's
Awesome I think
What apple is do in healthcare
Is pretty impressive
Its reputation for privacy and making the consumer experience
Easier I think is really going to
Gwen in this market
Frustration is you cannot win in this market unless you buy
Crazy expensive
Watch in a
Crazy expensive phone
Can you buy into
Ecosystem that's definitely true there are some companies and stores that have looked at giving Apple
Watches to the customers and so on so you may not have to spend the money at least not upfront maybe party or premium who knows
No argument there
I have to say I remember going to the Apple event where they launched a Apple watch
And I think I went to another one where they upgraded it
Which was most impressed with the health kit
Information
As opposed to the hardware and software the Apple watch itself
The amount of data that they are
Wrangling properly I would say it's on studies such as the one you just mention
Is mind-blowing
It really is a lot of other companies that make
Devices wearable devices I can do this kind of stuff too
Apple seems to have
Beyblade do more with that data working with its medical partners
And
As an example of this
Actually just in January
They did an update to iOS 11
3 lets people see their medical
Records
That is amazing and they work with Johns Hopkins
Cedars-Sinai pain
Hospitals
To get those records in for their
The patients in
You know I don't know
S i a Gemini
Holy cow I forgotten so many aspects of
Overtime that
And so
I would love to have this cuz right now my health records are all basically in an epic system
Locked away
Like 20 different.
Offices
Same here and I don't know that any other big company any of Apple's competitors lesao
Google Microsoft or Amazon
Have the
What's called the
Approach to privacy that would allow
Healthcare professionals to work with them
Because obviously Healthcare data is very private we have laws on that here I'm sure there
Elsewhere as well
So I think they've got a big
Advantage here with that and speaking of health records one of the things that I recently did was
I told my family they all have iPhones
Go put everything in your medical ID card
For your Apple Health app on your phone all the medications are taken
Something happens to you I don't know what you
You taking I don't know all your allergies and what not
And that's all accessible right through the medical ID part of Apple health so I have them do that
Again there's other apps that will do this as well but into Apple health and what they're doing here
Man if you could just print that out that would save you so much time when
On your first docker
So yes I think apple has a
Huge Advantage here and I actually I wonder as I get older
If I would invest in the ecosystem simply for the health
That's right or the health app
As much as I dislike
Constrained closed Apple world
I got to say
4Health it makes sense
If only it were cheaper
All right
Let's talk about
Arlo Netgear
This week announced
Its board has approved the separation of its are Lucic
Camera
Into except
Business
And it's going to offer an initial public offering
A shares in Arlo Technologies
It is going to issue less
20% of its common stock and IPOs so
Netgear still going to have it
Pretty powerful
Shakiness
I got to be honest
I don't know if I buy it at
It doesn't feel like a
Picking up business
Terry Lee
And IPO to be a standalone business is kind
There's the cameras
And then there's
Subscription offering so it's kind of an interesting business model
I just
I don't love that it's mostly Hardware
So I guess I'm just kind of like
I kind of feel the same way I'd say if that unit is
Profitable or has
Great Expectations keep it in-house you're still going to have it work with your other networking Year anyway
I'm not sure why they're doing this
I mean I look at it as hey if I was Netgear
X number years ago I figure hey there going to be a router or two and every house let's see no
And now I'm going to be multiple cameras in every house
Is that a whole business by itself does it need to be myself I'm not sure why they feel the need to do this
Money money money money I will say
With Amazon
Launch of like the wise camera
Knickers
Offering their own connect
2 cameras
Is a highly saturated market so maybe they just want to get a capital
Infusion to do something
Cool what that cool thing is I
I don't know
So that's our financial advice for the
Arlo
Now for the rapid
Here we go
First step
Speaking of
Camera scanner just rolled out their person detection algorithms that they announced several months ago
My canary devices were updated just happens automatically
Interessant they're going to roll this out over the next two weeks
There's nothing that users need to do
And this is really good I think
I get pictures and notifications of my dog all day long running around the house and I don't really care about that
Partially because I'm home as well
Moving around so this does exactly that
A little Pro tip if you want to enable this and only see people
Set your sensitivity on the notifications
Or emotion
3 or less
Unfortunate cut out all the cute pictures of my dog but really that's what you want for personification
Got it
What's the Super Bowl last on Amazon
The echo commercial and
How when you set my demise name
On the TV
Is she did not respond
And the reason is because Amazon is doing a little in audible tone
Before
Saying her name
So it doesn't actually activate
I wish we could
I wish we could use that tone for the show
Meet
Padme is kind of an awkward thing
Plus
Now I kind of think about that way and so sometimes
Yeah that's not her name
Maybe hey anyone at Amazon how can we get one of these
And speaking of Amazon are filed a patent
For a wristband that tracks workers movement so they can make sure that they are
Performing
I guess
Appropriate level
I don't know I meant they already have carts that they push around that track how far they walk in salon but
What Amazon could do is make sure the people are in the right spot for the right products
Naked
See perhaps somebody's working too hard by the heart rate there's a lot of things they could do
In a warehouse
People on construction sites who actually want to measure the
Vital signs
Workers so if they're dehydrated
Can tell him to go
So it's not all
Work faster or else a few but it is probably the most productivity out of a person by
I totally digitizing a reading all the signals that they can be like oh
This person is not as productive because they are
They're thirsty
Quick
It could even be safety I mean what's a pallet full of
I don't know Apple watches fall on somebody
You know their heart rates going to spike big time
There's a lot of
A lot of aspects
Yeah and I've actually so there's a company
That was called
Clue
The software on Apple watches that can
They actually use it for weight loss
Food tracking so attracts
Your motions of your wrists they can discern between
Glass of water
Or holding a wine glass
And they use that to say hey this is how
How many calories are consumed
This is why I drink my wine out of water glasses
I was talking to someone in the restaurant industry
You can actually use something like that to see if your workers are
Performing like chopping
Pink skirt
And I could be like a very good education
Feedback
Watch vibrate
When you're not doing it
So
The flipside is all of that data can also be a
I think I said when I talked about it on the show I was like
How you can tell if I was going to slap in my kid around
That's probably something
The people would want
But once you have this information you can apply
All kinds of algorithms to it to determine
Oh my God is that person picking their nose or are they drinking a glass of wine
Yikes
Okay
That I lied to you
You know me
That software that we constantly
Play talk about
We have been lately
They have announced
Native integration
With Sonos which means there are third-party integration that all the you know me
People have known and loved
It's going to go away and with it
This is sad
Is the text-to-speech announcement
So I at one point in time cuz I was silly
We had my you know
When I came
And
So that's going to go away
Which Native Integrations tend to be better anyway
Man middleware etcetera
Which makes me wonder about that you know me is the string of size and someone eventually is more Partners get made
Giving equations to the resistance what happens to these things
Like what
Middle players
I think they still have a good role to play as an energy
Greater so like I do routines through these things that I could not otherwise do
Through the Amazon
Or the Google
True
But you're right I don't know what happens to them
And you know he has an entirely different business on the backend so
And stringify is now part of Comcast
Belle Delphine
All right and now it's time for Kevin
Review of
Changing my 7 word review
WeMo Bridge
It's a bridge
Portofino
More information
I can expand upon that I did write this up over at Stacy and I were too.
Calm so you can
Read my thoughts
This is a $40
Bridge device that adds homekit support for WeMo devices
Not all of them very important that you realized
WeMo bulbs will not be added or supported by this
So if you have Outlets
Or switches
Go by Wiimote anyone integrate those into your home app
On iOS devices and Siri to control them this will do that just not for the bulbs
It does work very well
It took me all of
3 minutes to set up and get working at fantastic one of the things I'm not a fan of and this is a personal preference
I'm not trying to
Say this applies to everybody
It does require a wider
Connection to your network so you need to have an open ethernet port and also requires
Power on a sew-in so you need a power outlet near it
This is why I like wireless devices
But that's just me
I don't have a lot of ports on my router
If you can live with those two things and really need Siri and or home support
We're spending if you've got a lot of WeMo devices
I'm fine just using that Ma and Google for August
Steelworks and cancer
I will probably just kind of takis off my network as a result I don't need it on homekit but it's really really
And
If you are sad
May I recommend my favorite
Switch which I have all over my house is
It's 25 bucks
And
I have three of them
For possibly more
Read out I don't know how many I have
I have many ports
So if you're out there it's not
Proposition
Switch to your home
Okay this is someone
And after we recorded most the show but we thought was worth
Canon
And we're talking about
Nest
Google alphabet Zoo
Absorb
All right so what happened is
Fiscally today set the nest
Into the
Started
Where it
No it didn't start with perfect
Is purchased by
14 / 3.2
And after
4 years of
Not much excitement the nest
We saw three directions of the nest we saw more iterations of the
Nest cam what used to be Dropcam which was a complete for purchase
That was
Actually nothing St
After that
Spawn that all out
The point is Google bringing this
They're saying it's because they want to take advantage of
Infrastructure that Google
Kevin
Esketit
Well if that were true that would indicate they didn't have access to Google
MLA I Envision recognition which I find that very hard to believe
Took advantage of
Exactly so would the reasons for this be publicly Spoken Reasons by the executives
Ring a little Hollow to me person
See this is alphabet / Google trying to save face here because let's be honest message
Pretty stagnant
I would say
What the headlines you said the tree decorations of the nest thermostat they had the Dropcam purchase which became Nest cams
And they have since out of the nest security system
Toward the tail end of 2017
Other than that
They do have the nest for
We cannot forget this
Smoke alarm
Was
Not as awesome
Initially wanted
Which is actually a good tagline
I think nest + Tony fadell came on
With this vision for the Smart Home
Really was awesome and very compelling a very intuitive Smart Home
And the fact of the matter is it's very hard to build something
With
Not being able to control every single device
Yeah but I would say I would say this I personally have a lot of faith in Rick osterloh who was
Charge of some Hardware at Motorola
Both prior to and when Google actually on the road
Then they brought
He's in charge of Google's Hardware
And between the pixel slate
And the pixelbook
The purchase will not purchase
About the hiring of about 2000 HTC employees
What's more likely for the phone group
Oscar Lopez
Could the right person to be in charge of Hardware that's where the existing person
He will report to Rick osterloh
Kinesio marwen
The wise
Will report to
Rick osterloh
Yes and
Actually
For the Telecom
2sao
These guys
Is recent past correct
So this is
Yeah
This is a face-saving
You can't idea was basically they were going to have
Beaver sell nest
And
Or spit it back in
I would also say for companies that are
Ring searching for evaluation right now it's part of their fundraising up a billion dollars and
Netgear
As we talked about earlier
Doing the Arlo
IPO
I think this is actually bad news for like
Harbor players
I think
Yeah I mean with the right strategy and mean if I spend up make sense and spin-off make sense to spin-off just for the sake
Lakers raising money and so on I'm not so sure that that's going to fly long-term
I will be very curious to see if going back to the first thing I said if nest
Continues to stagnate I'm hoping not I'm hoping now that Google
Pushes the product
Rideout
And to be honest there's a lot of
Google partners that can do some of the same stuff that you think I could do
Because they
Partner on Android
I would love to see
Could be pushed to do
I would love to see presents because I don't think anybody does that well in the home
And be honest well anyone could do it this way I'm thinking Google could do it through Bluetooth
Which almost like a Tracker
Which Bluetooth
Device are you closest to in your house whether it's a Bluetooth thing you're wearing in on a Android Wear watch
If you have all these Google homes and Nest products around which one are you closest to and I can start putting more context around that present
That's what I'm going to say
Yes eyes Kevin and I both said we think that the Value Inn
Big influence as it were in the smart home is
Google home and Google Assistant
The question is really
How does nest
How does Nest Hardware fit into that
Catfishing
Presences
End
Maybe they could
Outlets would be a way to get presents but
Who needs another Outlet light switches
I like your Bluetooth
I should also
According to CNET
In an interview they did
Is part of the snooze
Nestle sold 11 million devices which
I actually think it's a little low
I would agree with you
Compared to
You know the Amazon Echo which is really like
The chiller killer
I don't know I'm
After all this time I would agree with you
Maybe they can actually drive the price down for
These devices Fitness high prices are
They're challenged I would agree with that and if you're working in one Hardware division where you can manage the supply chain from one point of presence
I think you're right that can help
So what do you think
Set the nest brand which obviously makes sense to keep the nest brand right now
Eating at last
So cuz I'm not so sure it doesn't
I'd like it as a brand
It conveys all kinds of things
Google
Haji does it do
Right so Google Assistant
Connecting with consumers problem
I would love to see Nest help
So I hope the brand stays and they actually invest in
Mean things a little more consumer-friendly cuz that has been
A nice aspect
It is very
I'm going to play Devil's Advocate and I don't know which of us is going
As a brand last for maybe 18 or 24 months and they just become part of the Google home brand
All right we shall see 18 months from now
And whoever wins gets
All right
Well
That's it for this little
News on our thing 2nd and
Google move on
Previously recorded
Now
What is go
2 hour
Iot podcast
Listener hotline
Question of the week
Ashley before I do that
If you have a question for us give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7:40
To 4
The iot podcast listener hotline is brought to
Schlage
Maker of electronic locks
Electronic locks
Much easier in
PCH member of your family can have their own access code
To see what's possible
Dot-com
All right
Play that message
Hi Kevin hi Stacy love the show
According to me like a kingdom
We haven't talked yet
So we will be shortly
I'm an alcoholic
I thought 5 Alexa
Someone one of my friends
What you like
Moving
Or just one
Alexis should I re
Cinemax
But you can help speak too soon take care of the show
OKC
I
I have
You may not like it because
It's going to involve
Psychic powers on behalf
The person you're trying
Call or who's trying to call you
First off you have to name all of your Amazon echos
Thanks so pretty
My daughter
Anna original
My husband and I
10 to
Banana as opposed to drop in on Amazon
Anna's room
Right
Yes
I change that
So every room of your house should have every Echo should have a
And then
When someone wants to
They actually have
To call you
And that's the second
Well
I would agree with you but
ICU
Could
Could be
A little less psychic because there are settings in The Madam a app
That allows you to a have drop-in supported work being not supported
And also their setting for only my household so if you don't want space if you don't want me dropping in
To your house on
Anna you could just say only my household for Anna's room
It's in the settings of the device
She have to go into each individual device and then down towards the bottom
Under General there's a drop in
Setting
Oh okay so this is where you would go anyway to change
That is correct same tap yes
So
I'm doing that
Yes
So drop in
But you can say only my household
Utah P if I do
Course I'm right I'm looking at the screen
So now I am too so I totally believe you okay
So that may help Sam a little bit
I kind of choosing which
Echo devices you would accept
Outside drop in calls from
Send me
Heaven
On my living
Amazon Echo Show
Oh but that has a video camera
This is true
Very fun
Okay so I hope that helps
And if it doesn't help
Carlos Bacca
All right
Remember if you would like us to answer your
Questions
Stay tuned for our guest
Bruce Charlie CEO of Senate
Talking about
Specifically Laura roaming and
Pretty fun use cases
Stop before that let's go to a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we're taking a break from this week's podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
President
So let's get started with what
Display Central do
Pointcentral is
City of alarm.com and we are the leading provider of enterprise-grade home automation Solutions as a business tool
Too short and long-term managers of single-family and multi-family property
So let's talk about the property manager
Why are they into
Home automation
Today's property managers have a
Presidents that have needs always trying to find people to rent on TalkBack homes or trying to manage and turn those
Homes especially as possible and Technologies really starting to emerge as a tool that can use it points to improve
Presidents and how they run their business
The two buckets
DC property managers
See benefits from home automation in operational efficiency
Is an asset protection
As well as
Asset enhancement
Okay so tell me about those
Grape from the acid enhancement
Point of view we touched on this a little bit last week
What really helps
Turn the acid from a rental unit
Into a home for the resident
Because it brings this technology into their lives and it's easy and accessible way
From an operational efficiency standpoint there several ways the property manager
She's been
First channel access
Control the weather it's a vendor
Maintenance staff for the units occupied or unoccupied
They know who's entering the property at all times they're saving time from people having to run and get
Keys and check them out of a front office and they're also protecting themselves from rekey cost when Keys it inevitably get lost and a half
How to go change a lock out
From HVAC perspective to get the benefit of the thermostat controlling the temperature in on I-5 units and as we talked about
First podcast we also features in HVAC to help them
Be notified
When an HVAC unit
Meat service
Waters Another bitbucket
Property managers
Water sensors around
A water heater around main lines coming in under a sink Etc
Are very cost-effective and can help them avoid very costly water leak damage
And lastly propertyware tasso Weatherby
Doorbell cameras exterior cameras
Sensors Etc
Do we want to watch and see
Who's at a property in our people entering a property when that property should be unoccupied
Tell me about the underlying system
It takes care of
So with alarm.com
We collectively have
5 million individual households on our cloud
George very familiar with what we need to do to provide
Secure and reliable test
We do that by
Utilizing Z-Wave at the local level and encrypting devices there will use a private cellular lines
That we encrypt to get the data out of the household
I never had a real bus
Data privacy policy
That helps keep all of that individual household information safe on our cloud
So where can the stars go to find out more about points
To learn all about what we can do for both property managers
And residence
Feel free to visit point central.com
Welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is Bruce
Chatterley who is the CEO of
Send it
Hi Bruce how are you doing today
I'm doing great thank you
Well thanks for doing this
We spend a lot of time talking about low-power wide area network
Works for the Internet of Things
And it's nice to have someone who
Talk to us
About
Laura specifically
Lorawan
So let's get started
Let's get people excited about Laura
Let's talk about some of the use cases that so far people are using it
This might be a good opportunity to describe
A little bit house in it
Became a player in the Lord's face we were founded in
As one of the first iot Apple
Locations that has really scaled
It was an application that put a monitor on
Propane or fuel tanks in a residential environment
You know those big White Tanks it's outside of rural homes in
Farms in
Industrial era
At the time
We decided that the Lora Technology Way
It was a really good set
For this application because once you place a
There's usually no power at the
These tanks so you have to have a battery-powered sensor
In many of these sensors are in hard to get to are these tanks from hard to get to places
So you want it basic
Be able to put a sensor down and walk away for 10 years and having
Communicate flawless
And so we built out
We built our own sensors
We built our own base stations
Because there was no lure ecosystem
The time and then we built our own cloud-based software and services
Is to manage both the network and the
Devices and
We deploy this app
Location and scaled
Dramatically
One day we sat back
Instead we've got the
Large Lauren that work we can do more than just
Tank monitor
And so
We
Put an umbrella company
Place called Senate
Which was really designed to deliver horizontal app
Applications across the
Does not work one of the largest cities in the United States
The city passed an ordinance last year that said that the
Department of Public Health needed
To know where every food truck and food cart
In the city
Is at any given time so they can
Do random help
Inspections
One that deal with a systems integrator and we are pulling Network as we
Speak in a major city
We are putting trackers on
Initial 5000
Food trucks and food carts
And we are also working with the city
Who gave us access
To their public building
To deploy the base stations and in our parlance
Discord Gateway
To serve that Network
And now this
We have a network
The city is looking at
Applying multiple
Tencent net worth
Which is exciting
Case for Laura LP when were you want to put a tracker on a phone
Food cart could be a hot dog cart or whatever and
You don't want to have to
Replace it all the time
Can your battery life is really important
Can you talk to me about the difference between Laura and Laura Wang
Well I've been in there commingle so maybe the best way to de
Describe it is to put it in
Context of the industry and so
We kind of view the end of
History is being divided in
Three segments
The first segment
Is really about things that are close
To the sensor
And are powered
And are close to the communications technology
Sosebee bike application
Who's that can use Bluetooth or Wi-Fi or
Connected eats
And that's not what
We're focused on
The second segment
Is applications that
Require
Should have more high bandwidth
Two-way real-time Communications and that would be like telematics
Driverless cars those kinds
And that's a technology that 5G is being Ark
Architected for
Is really sore the Bastion
Big cellular comp
Would license technology and then the third category which we think represents about 55% of
Potential connector
Devices
Internet of Things
Is called the low powered wide area
Networking in really this segment
Is divided up into
To a couple players first is
Technology
People may have heard this referred to as nb-iot or cat
And so it's really designed
To be a slower speed and more cost-effective
Then kind of like your home cellular sir
The second category of Sky technology in this space is
What I would call
Proprietary
How do you say these are closed ecosystem
Companies that have built their own technology using
Spectrum
Meaning the company didn't have to pay billions of dollars to get over-the-air Spectrum
And they do some
Close technology
Which means they're the only ones that can
Control NYC
And manufacture the hardware
And the networking
Equipment associated with that
Those are companies examples of companies in that category would be a French company called sick Fox
An American company
Call Don
And on the third category is Laura LP win
And Laura LT win uses unlicensed
Spectrum
So essentially available to anyone for use much like your homework
Cordless phone uses
This kind of
Spectrum
And essentially
It uses of Lora protocol
To create a what I would call a trickle data
Connection
So very low speed very small
Small amounts of data
To communicate with what I would call massively
Scales
Sensor application
So these are
Applications
Is that where the requirement is for them to be deployed
In either the hundreds of thousand
Dinosaur the Millions
In terms of device cam
And for application
Things that require very long battery
So what we're finding and Laura is up to
10 year battery life
In some cases longer
And require very efficient Network
Deployment so
With the Lora technology I think the world record for a sensor
Communicating with a Gateway or a base station is 70 MI
What I mean by efficient as you don't need a lot of base station
To get
Really really good cover
In the United States
You know it's pretty common knowledge that Laura
And
The cellular license Technologies for LP when are going to be the winners and the Laura ecosystem
Time is growing dramatica
Play inside I was at a conference last week where they
Show statistics that the Laura Alliance which is gone from 0 to over 500
Numbers
Is one of the fastest growing technology alliances
In history so it's got a lot of them
Lets people a little bit with
With this characterization because I talked to a lot of people who are really excited about law
But they are very concerned about being pulled into Semtech witch
Is the
Primary maker of Lora chips
They're sorry I'm curious this is an issue that came up
How many years ago was
Z-Wave
Because signal was there
Producer so I'm just curious your thoughts on
Well I think the first thought is
Is that the reason were excited about Laura is
Is that it's an open standard
So it's published and anyone can actually
Create technology both hardware and software
To connect in
The standard
NBA player in
Any part of the Eagles
The second thing I would say is
Is that some tax
Is actually license
Sing the chip technology for manufacturer
Two other chip maker
And so we're starting
Can you see that
Ecosystem
Groin
In fact it wisely
The manufacturer
Floor chips
Tutu
Very very large chip
Is one is microchip and I believe the other is
Stmicro
So we're starting to
Some diversification
Significant
Verification
Insource of chips
You know while simtek is the
Original owner of the
The protocol
I think the
The technology itself is getting more and more pervasive
In the public domain and there are more and more
Either license
Store participating innovators in
In the ecosystem
So let's go to this idea because
It's one thing to track location using something like this
It's another thing to get lots of data on a Lowrance
I'm at work so it's not about the constraints of the technology
My understanding is your data rates are
Are fairly Limited
Yep they are highly
Red so
You really young and that's why in my view
When I talked about the landscape of the industry
Is that
You know the iot industry is not homogeneous
There are opportunities for multiple Technologies
And it's really a matter of
Sitting
The characteristic
Except the technology
Lead to the ideal application and so
What we're looking for our application
Things that require
Very limited data that
Require very long battery life
And so obviously not powered
And require a network that's very efficiently
Deployed and so the end result of that ends up being that you need
End up
Serving
An application
With a network
Gets down into a couple dollars a year
Per device for monthly recurring
Cars
So it's really important
Automatically give me another example in the Smart City space were working with the largest water meter
Manufacture
In the world and in fact
Water
As a utility is
Perfect application
Because
Usually
The water meters are on
Empowered they're usually in very hard to get
Two places and that's another
Strength of Laura because of the 900 megahertz specs
Scott very good propagation characteristics
Meaning of
Penetrate concrete
Water meters are usually in pits
So they're very hard to get to and so
Will be announcing in the neck
Week or two of full City that we've deployed with a water meter manufacturer
So that's another really good example and by the way they communicate once or twice a day and they just Bass
We take a reading
A very small package
So to your point
The perfect fit
For the Lord technology
So let's talk about the carriers because
While you mentioned 5G but they're also
Working
Some of them not all of them
On nb iot and Cat M1
These look very competitive with what Laura's doing except it would be obviously
Bison Spectrum
And I'm just curious your thoughts there I believe the modules are also
More expensive so it's more expensive to put that capability in the end device
Right it's less flexible from a deployment
One of the things that's interesting about iot and I've started in this
Business in June of last year
And one of those things I've learned is the only thing certain and by the way this goes for wireless carriers as well as for us
The only thing certain when an application provider comes to us
Is that we won't have coverage
100% of the places they need it
And one of the strengths of Laura is
To buy a gateway
And create coverage and other gateways
Run anywhere from 3,000 to $5,000
Versus
What we all know about
Cell tower Gateway
C&R or a base stations very very
So while the NB iot guys were
Will tell you that
It's just a software update
What do they do when you need coverage in a farmer's field where you don't currently have coverage
And
We have a great model for that will put a Gateway on top of
The grain silo
And that will then cover
That application and by the way once we've done that
Tank monitoring
Send a play
Soil moisture monitoring
Yeah there's a variety of Apple
Locations we can do on that day station so I think there are also and I'm not an ex
Expert in NB iot but from
Comparison standpoint
We have better battery life
Regardless of what you're reading we've done side-by-side comparison
Their cost azure
He said
Fire
Because of the technology in the
Device and the cost of services
Just hire so there are limitations
That we don't have in fact
We were the first ones in the United States
To demonstrate back in
In Las Vegas a couple weeks ago
A new capability that Laura has
It's called geolocation
And just a quick
Description
The way Laura works
What is very
Cell towers
In that a sensor Allura sense
Is it cancer
Cafa station
It will
Communicate with
So for example if I've deployed 5
Gateway's
Air base station
China City
NF sensor
Can see all five
It will simultaneously
Communicate with all five
And what that creates is an opportunity
To take readings
From all five of those
Antennas and send that data to what's called a solver
And
Basically create a fairly accurate location for that ass
It's all done without GPS
Which has a couple dentist
1 GPS
Chips are expense
Relative basis
Casino in terms of
The end device
And to GPS is a big battery
And by the way the advantage of GPS is a
It's very precise and
You know it's limited by the
In terms of how precise it is with the Laura Kate
Disability I think it's
Yeah probably
Safe to say that you can get within 50 Mi of the asset
Now there other carriers doing Laura deployment so
There's orange in France has a lower deployment and then I'm also thinking of Comcast has a division called machine
Thank you that's doing lorawan
Are you guys involved in that or is that just Tianjin
That is tangential so Comcast has announced
So they're going to deploy 12 cities I believe and I believe they've only deployed three
You know I think it's good
It's a good anointing of the Lora technology that a company like Comcast
Has chosen it
As its iot Network so I think that's positive
And then the second thing I would say is you're right there are many Network
Deployed around the world
In particular from incumbent Wireless carriers like orange and
Kpn
Niy Friday bother
And what's interesting is we were also the
The first in the US to demonstrate
In Las Vegas at CES
The new roaming interface for Laura
Call one version
And it's a roaming interface
What'll be interesting is if you're orange and you have an Enterprise
That's the point sensors for a global app
Application through this roaming interface you could place devices on the Senate Network
Can the United States and Canada
What kind of pricing your house
How would that work I think about Romanian you know my wallet instinct
Whenever so is that going to follow kind of the cellular model
Will it look different I mean
Business
Terms are being negotiated as we
We speak but
What I could say is
It has to
You cannot follow
Cellular model
That model was designed on a $50 per month kind of
And as I said earlier we're talking $2 to $2
Per year per device
And so there's a unique model that need
Be created here
That
Yahweh centrally is
Ends up being
In the pennies if anything at all and I think you're going to see a lot of partnership
Versus caffe
Roaming
Commercial agreement
They are based on the economics of the business
And what me
No one other Innovation that sun it announced last year
So when are customers too
Deploy Lora network
We allowed them
How to register
Their Network
They stations to what's called a LPN virtual Network
Work sucks whenever we Implement a customer
Whether it be a carrier or a systems integrator or a application
Provider
We always connect does not work
Works together virtually through this lvm
And essentially what that allows is
As long as they're on our LVN
Any one of our customers can put a device on any one of our other custom
And whoever the hosting network is
Will get a share of
Is revenue
From that
Devices Revenue
Okay
And what's interesting is that open up business models that we didn't even
Contemplate when we conceived of this LDN
And I'll give you an example we're talkin
Two owners of commercial cell towers who are saying hey
That means I can buy the Gateway
Put it up on my cell tower
And I can sit back
Flask devices
Disconnect
Can generate
And so we're doing that
We're also talking
The owners of commercial signs and billboards
And so in fact
Dinner Las Vegas Network that we
2.4 CES
Three of our gateways are on
Commercial dildo
And they're doing the same thing I've got these assets
Empowered and usually connected to the internet these
Laura
Gateways are very small you know maybe
6in by 6in
12in by 12in
And they put them up on their goboard
And because of the LDN model they can generate Revenue stream off
And let's talk about how many devices you can serve on one
I know that's highly dependent on how often they're paying the Gateway
Datastream
And all of that but
Like I mean even cellular Networks
You can only
You can only cram so many bits
So
What are those limitations look
Yeah it's
Obviously highly dependent on which Gateway you choose but if you have a macro cell that's a high-capacity macro cell
AR testing is showing you know up to 200000 device
Gateway
The other things it to know is
Is that as I said earlier that
A single device
Will most likely be
Communicating with multiple gateways simultaneously
So if there's a capacity
Constrain on one it will automatically
You know switch to another
All right I feel like I know a lot more about Laura now
Thank you so much Bruce I appreciate you coming on the show today
Yeah thank you for your time
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot. Com