Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is you
Your hostess
Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And this is episode 185 of the show and it's
Going to be amazing
Kevin Went to the Google event yesterday we're going to talk about all of that or all of the smart home stuff assoc
Shaded with that
We're also going to talk
About I was at the Smart Kitchen Summit
This weekend I have all kinds of updates on the smart
Kitchen for you
Plus we've got new software updates for both Google and Madam a
The Amazon Echo
Digital assistant as we like to call her
What Facebook did something super nuts
And we're finally seeing a little bit of a push for
Privacy and
Security laws
Coming from the government
4 connected devices
This week we've got a lot to cover so we are not including
August 2nd
That's so it's going to be
Kevin and I
And then we got our message from our sponsor cognizant and then it'll be more
Kevin ISO
A lot is going to happen
Stay tuned for
The first
A message from one of ours
This week sponsor is
Chocolate
64% of iot consumers report problems with their iot products
Don't waste time and money by manually identifying errors are using a tool belt for a web server
Aquatrax architecture Regional patterns system usage and your application
Identify win where and what caused beer stop settling and start fixing problems before your
Your customers find them get started today Oakland that I owe
That's a UK
Let
Dot IO
Okay Kevin let's start with the biggest news which
Just probably
Oh
You think Google
I think it is we have to talk about that cuz I'm still reeling from the event
As of yesterday I need coffee
Yasso
3 things are an ounce
To really don't
Concern our audience
But the one thing that does is what we already knew was coming or at least what we expected based on leaks
The Google home hub which you can already order for 100
$49
It is a smart display similar to the Lenovo and
JBL
Companion products
That aren't they are Google Hardware partner so they're all using Android things
This is a little different it's
Cheaper than those which is interesting but I think I understand why now that I've
Actually seen and use the device
Super starters
It's hard to tell in the pictures
But it is a very
Small device
It's a 7-inch display
You can hold the base of it in your hand quite easily
It's just
Really I think you're towards
Being a smart
Controlling device with a little bit of media
And I say that because the screen is not as big as the Lenovo for example of the 10-inch Lenovo with a 1080p 10 inch
Screen this is 7 in
And they're giving
Dating Google is giving you
Three months of YouTube
Premium
With this device
If you purchase it not YouTube TV which is actually what I use
Mysmartice play for
Quite a bit so
You can certainly you know use this device
For media but it is really all about the new home View
And that is going to be coming to the other smart displays I'm explain what that is
At any point in time you can just walk up at the display
Of course you can control your home devices
Cuz my voice but if you slide down from the top you get a brand new
Homeview which shows you what's going on in the room you're currently and such as
What temperature brass
Mustang with sensors you have installed
Your lighting
Situation at the moment etcetera
And then you
Controls to everything else in the house as well
Oh my gosh
Everything old is New Again
So basically they've reinvented the fancy touchscreen the wall base touch screens that
Like high-end
Yeah it is since they really have
They really have
And
It basically aggravates it gets rid of all those
External apps you might be using which you can still use for all your devices but
It just aggravates everything in one spot which is already done in the home mobile app
But now it's
A little easier on the eye and it's little more intuitive because
You have pretty much everything you want to see where you are at the right time in one spot
Okay so it's kind of like home OS
Switch is the Apple homekit version of this
In a sense I would say yes
A little more
Text to Lynette
Because
If I'm using the home app
On my iPhone 4 sample
It's not going to say you know
What the lights
State is in the room I'm in
It'll show with the light state for every light in the house and home
Got it
So
So that
Feature will be coming to the old
Smart displays they're not that old but the Lenovo in the JBL
Additionally it's a big
Interaction of rather interface with Google Assistant of course it will show your routines if you want
And it you can even program the routine standings
Include the display in those routines
So your good morning routine could of course show you news weather Etc appointments whatever he will automatic
Dim at night
Good night and you don't even need to set a routine for that if I
Google touted this ambient EQ which is a light sensor and basically they're going to smartly reduce the
The brightness Depending on time of day and if you're not in the room it's not going to do that because there's no sensor to show
Show motion which the other ones actually do have
I walk in my room to Lenovo smart display actually brightens up but will Google says it to trying to reduce the billboard effect and what they
I mean is they don't want your eye drawn to a bright rectangle
In the room when you walk in
They want you to look at this device
When you want to look at it when you need to look at it so
That makes a lot of sense it's but again it's a fancy ambient light sensor implementation
That
Someone else
Let me ask you
Because there's a lot
Oh does it have any radios like zigbee or Z-Wave I know that
We love those in our home hub
We love those two and unfortunately no I say unfortunately for us
A lot of mainstream people who have not invested in zbr Z-Wave devices
Don't care because you're not missing anything so there's no new radios with Bluetooth 5.0 and 802 11
AC wifi both 2.4 and 5 gigahertz
Okay
That's good on the Wi-Fi
Is it Hey Kevin is it Wi-Fi for Wi-Fi
Yeah I didn't go there
Is it really
What is 11 AC is going to be named
Now I'm totally lost.
Okay
Pictures of you guys who miss last week show that they did
The Wi-Fi Alliance
Instant credit
Read my hand
Okay so then the big question is
You said that you've got
Yours and I have mine
So would you buy this
I would not from me
And that is because I like the immersive media
Experience provided by the larger
Lenovo smart display
So
If
You're all in on say homekit obviously this is not for you
You're all in on Madam and The Echoes
This isn't going to do much for either unless you plan to switch
Show away from mad at me because by and large most of the same devices are supported on both of those platforms
I will confess that I actually have a better experience on madam
Hey
Despite the fact that I'm a heavy Google Apps and Android user
Because Google Apps actually
Works on madhumeha but because of my weird account issues
It doesn't work
On
The Google devices
Continuing frustration so I'm like
Google I love you but no
Yeah obviously if you have a g Suite account
As opposed to regular Google account
Yeah you're going to run into that issue time and time again with your phones and Google assistant general Shore
What about the
And so that's
That's what I was going to bring up because this is one thing you can't get with your second Echo Show for example so I think
You have the nest doorbell ring
I do
Okay as do I
And you know you can certainly go into the app today and look at
See who's at the front door at 7.
But when somebody rings the doorbell today you literally have to
Tell a display or device to
To show who's out there
What they did here is
Is Google integrated with Nest so that any time
Somebody Rings Your Nest doorbell
The video stream will immediately
Pop up unannounced
If you want to do anything or say anything
It just pops up on the Google home hub
And then you can have a two-way conversation or if you don't want to talk to the person there's some pre-canned
Responses
So you can just say sorry not interested tap that little
You don't have to say anything
I can just tap the sorry we're not interested in
That's what it will say to whoever's out there
Does it say in your voice tube
Yes you. Don't record it
You don't
We are at entry
Yeah Google does the voices in
I color I think right so
Cyan for me would say sorry not interested
We're not even going
Okay
So I feel like
I know
If I should buy this or not
That's good
And I will say
For people interested in seeing the nest
If you have Nest gear Nest cameras
Google has been pretty shy about sharing the camera base
Rest apis with other partners
So
You may never
I'm not not anything I know for a fact but I will say that people
Are companies out there that would love access to that
But they don't get it
And this may become like a
Competitive advantage
Google
If I would agree with that and I don't know anything either but I suspect you're right I think this is a platform play for Google and
I mean if you spend 3.2 billion on Nest I would imagine
That makes a lot of sense
I'm one other quick thing only because this relates to something else that was announced yesterday
For those who use the or will use the Google home hub or any other smart display for photos
Because integrates
Is Google photos and you can just view albums all day long on the devices
They have added a live albums
And using their search smart so you can say I want to see pictures of
Nor my dog or Beano
My wife my husband whatever
It will search
Do your photos and create a live album and show those on the display of the Google home hub
As you add more photos
Of that person or pet
Not to the album it will automatically add them to that album
For you for the Google home hub which I thought was
It's cool though that's lovely
Yes
And as it relates to something else
That's sort of related
Not quite our audience
The pixel 3XL
Has a new pixel stand
Twitches a wireless stand
To charge your pixel 3 or 3XL
When you put the phone on the
Charger it can show you photo albums
Also on the phone
And will show you the nest
Camera from the doorbell
When that phone is sitting there so kind of beans on mini smart display with very limited functionality
That's kind of cool knots it
Well actually I don't ring my phone everywhere in the house
So that might be
Fix for me if I were going to buy
Can I get a software update for my original
Cancel my pixel 2
I don't know about that I think they're telling us as a pixel 3
Function a pox on their people
Well
Let's
Move actually
Before we move on be on Google
There's there's one of the thing GE announced
Some smart light bulbs the C by GE
Lights
I'm just going to say this straight
GE has the world's most confusing connected lightbulb strategy
See I have ever
They have branded this
These light I have owned a variation of the GE connected lights
That we're not great at all
And then they went out and they rebranded or lunch new light
That were
Pakistan
Circadian rhythms are Auto tuning
According to the day and they had it a night version that you were night bulb and a daytime bulb
So the idea was you would put like the night bulb in your bedside table in the daytime bold maybe at you
Your desk and
I thought that was
You saying strange as well
Now
And that was under the sea brand
Letter c as in Charlie
Yes
And so now they have
The
Google C
So these new
Google
See lights are Bluetooth Bass
Much like there
Prettiest
And I
They audit at me when you screw them in
The Inn you have a Google
Home hub
They're going to automatically be detected
I'm not sure what the network authentication process is if
It's like a barcode if it's some sort of weird handshake
But
These are getting these sorts of automatic Discovery are becoming more common Amazon actually showed a lot of that
Shut off last month
@its
Fun exciting
We lunch 70 things in one day kind of event
But I'm still not keen on Bluetooth Baseline
I know Bluetooth mesh makes this better
I still
Yeah I still remember like being able to be like
Walk downstairs and suddenly losing the ability to control my lights and that was
Sake
So I'm curious about this one
Yeah I'm curious to I mean this is all and this kind of goes with the theme of yesterday's event with the Google home hub
Although these work with any Google home product and I'm a mini etcetera it's all about simplicity
And that's
Southpaw for mainstream people who are just getting started in this morning we're having on started it also
That's what they're going for here literally you plug these in and then just go to the Google home app and they say
And start controlling that's it
So I think that
That's great I'm curious as you are about
You know the implementation of that from a security standpoint I don't
Think you're scanning anything we could do it in the plug these in and powder them up but Google has a Google has my wife I could
Maybe they're running tests on anyway I did send them an email and
We'll try to figure that out for you guys cuz
That's how dedicated we are to the nitty-gritty of these Marton
Also
Related
To Google
This is a story that I wrote last week
I've been working on this for a little while but
How does a little bit
I have been hearing from Smart Home
Device makers
That Walmart
If you wanted to be sold in Walmart
You needed to have
Support
And if you had only met him a support
Can I come back when you can support Google
And talk to her
Six different people they all confirm this
Walmart
Still has not gotten back
Test me on this
Kind of losing her
But in a baby
Maybe
And the other thing is that was Universal was it if you support Madam a
That's fine
But don't emphasize that
Need to put that on the side of the box or the back of the box
And then I talked to some other people
Who said that they were actually encouraged to move their operation
Off of AWS Amazon web service
And they were also encouraged
To not use a smart
Home hub
And in this make sense
Is anywhere talk about Simplicity or talk about normal people
That's kind of I think the theme of this year would be the normalization of
The Smart Home
Not
Like 4
Like my mom and dad are not like all the smart home is normal but it's prepping it to become normal so making it so normal people
Can adopt
That is a big strides
And closing the loop on this
About the normal fee
Normal people don't know or care about zigbee and Z-Wave
But normal people pretty much know about Bluetooth and WiFi and I think that's
Really worried there's
Getting rid of the Hub that's coming from
Keeping the products simpler and using those two radios
Yeah and that makes sense. I think there will always be room in a market
For the foreseeable
Future Percocet B&C way
It's just
That's like your leveling up
Alright while we're on this topic of simplicity
Amazon release the new software update
Four battle
And
I downloaded it
I always have the worst experience
With my
Madame Mao
I'll be honest
Even actually what I had the Amazon guy over to like
Hit my house basically see what he said
Is like gosh your app run so slowly
I think it's because I have
A lot
Devices
But
What do you think
Yeah I updated it on my phone and it's actually kind of similar to what Google's going for with their home
Review on the Google home hub it's more of an aggregator of here's all your devices here's all your groups and rooms you can even
To see what skills you have in your smart home
I like it so far it's visually very pleasing to me
I often find these apps to Beatrice
Kind of fairy
Bright
And this is a very low-key relaxing pestilli color I don't know if I
If you saw the same but
It was the first thing that jumped out at me quite honestly and then everything's very well-organized I think
Yes it's like
Dark blue and then they it's a
Brighter blue but it's not like a super bright blue it's very
Just chill seafoam green or nice
Purple
So are ya at the color palette did actually job is like
Oh that's a little
Weird alright it actually kind of felt a little old-fashioned it reminded me of color palettes I saw on smart-home things back in like
I think Peak
Which was Best Buys
Smart home hub
Had a similar color palette
I am talking about color palettes let's talk about grouping
Cuz I said that's important with this at the groupies
What is happening
This is an area where Amazon has always excelled they let you put you can have as many groups as you want
I have about half a dozen
Which might be
Bring so slow and I put I have a Christmas grouping I have a downstairs grouping I
Groupings for me
My rooms
And
Here's a pro tip for you guys because I recently had a hue light bulb just go offline
I don't know why
You just happened
So I had to delete that bulb and then re-add it
And
I re-added it in the hue
App
Got to do that
And then I had to
Delete the old bald from the Amazon
Echo app
And then
Put the new one into
Groups
I realize that I had had it
Living room
Group
But then when I
Created my downstairs group in which is all of my lights downstairs
Instead of
Adding
The room group
To that
Teen I'd added two things individually
This is too convoluted for everyone
Are we following this hence the Simplicity Factor everybody's going for these days
So the point is
You can add things to a routine you get out of group
To your routine
So
From now on I'm treating like
Hey that's the living room group and now I'm just putting that hoe
Croup into my room
So I went back and read it on my
Around that beat
Cuz
If something happens you can just swap one thing out in
Right
And that makes sense from a contextual standpoint because let's say you have a movie night routine in the living room everything in
Living room is going to be affecting or most everything
The lights perhaps my dim the TV might come on the Fire TV Etc perhaps even have a connected speaker system
That fires up and then turns everything to say Netflix so
That makes sense you can just do everything at once with a group
You think is worth it
Netflix movie night or Amazon Prime movie night
I actually have had this debate in my
House beside our movie night
Yeah I'm okay with picking and choosing from my TV screen what I
What service I want to watch and we have like
Three or four of them sick I'm right there with you but
Yeah we bounced around its
Buy show for us
Let It Go stay
Related before we get off at topic
Google's
Omeprazole so updated
And if you want a peek
At what the hungry looks like on the Hub if the same cohesive interface on the new Google home app
And I really like what's been done here in fact I like it better than the Mad MAF refresh
Okay yeah you know I like it is brighter it's got
Lovely things I love being able to like
Turn the light on
Make it brighter make it dimmer
Change the color like all of that is really
Very nice
Simple simple
Simple again
So I do Wonder though is that
Again is that a function of the Google Engineers coming up with that or is that
Four devices that are little weird or off that might not be in there
Do you get to pick your own or how does that work
How did those visual elements
Transfer over
Who did Ryan yeah with a manufacturer has some say what they're EPI and so on I presume that Google knows that
Yeah this is it maybe a tunable bulb and therefore we need this interface my guess is they know the attributes somehow
3D apis
To dynamically show the correct control but I don't have a ton of those
Unique
Idevices so I couldn't say for sure
Well I am still traveling but
After this week I will be home and I'll go check that out I'll be like
Here's my weird connected device what do you think it is
Cuz I really think Amazon Nails it when they talked about having
Yeah mon
Range and on-off
Toggle I think that's a really good way to start thinking about these things
On off Circle
Range is volume maybe it's
Lighting colors
And then mode is anything specific to a device like
In lights it might be a scene
In a washing machine that might be permanent press clothes
Okay
Before we get started talking about everything else because there's a
Whole lot more including spark Kitchen in Facebook
Let's
Take a moment for a word from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Cognizant
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Sponsor is cognizant
And I have with me again today
Anti sob
Global markets leader
For iot at
Frank we talked last week about how cognizant is
Is helping companies
Please connect the physical and digital worlds with iot
Can you share
Any success stories
Absolutely
How large they are playing
Collections agency
Libya Shoppers don't even think about what it takes to keep on at Food sessions
Call detail
Derrick White
This is why
Ashley helpful
Bioskop music to help reduce
School bus ticket $7 to euro
Kinesiology
Wow okay that's important
So this was a big retailer
How to make problem
How did you guys have
Small chunks
Distance to Punta Gorda
That was the problem
Responsible for
Alarm 7 Dees refrigeration systems malfunction
Senators on any of the stores
But if you eat your maintenance operations
36 hours
And that is way too long
There's no mechanism
Collectively bargain refrigeration systems
You can only imagine what that means for food safety
Poop has to be disposed of immediately
We talked about those in the traffic
So is the solution iot
Dissolution list reduction in food and energy
Music
This is a real ID
At still
What I mean by scale is activating a pilot the full-scale production of thousands of refrigerator
What's the chemical in Dana Point
Acrostic
Delta flight tracking demoted equipment
Consumption
It's not a simple problem be solved by any means
Required team to retrofit a connector refrigerator
To send data to a cloud platform
Debbie employment
Advanced Analytics
To the central control team
King restaurant in Rio Center inside
Toyota response times from 36 hours Delta fibers
I need to reduce food wastage in the coming year
And the practice Maitland
This is just one example
Invite be a wonderful meeting ID service providers in Dubai
Wheat Delaware iot a scale
That was a great example
I look forward to hearing
Success stories
In the meantime
Frank work
Go to find out more
About cotton
You can go to our website at cognizant.com
Okay
We have almost exhausted
Smart Home Smart displays but
Not
Quite
Big news
And I'm going to say something that underlies the need for trust
Lost in the space
Is Facebook launch
Display that has a
The camera that tracks you and you can call people on it
And
I don't know why
And it has an assistant integration to
Does
Triple would you be
Let me think about
Not at all
I'm kidding I'm not even thinking
Basically this is the new portal from Facebook which is the
Cassius we talkin about a
Some type of smart device from them for quite some time it's
Again similar to say smart display or nekoshou but it's a little bit more limited in that
It's really meant for
Video call
So obviously there's a camera on here
And I think that's going to be
The biggest challenge for Facebook
Who already has
I say probably one of the least trusted large companies with personal information
This this is what trips me out people still ask
They're like
Hey
You know how when you talk about something and then you get an ad for it on Facebook
I didn't think it on your phone
In this case
Again
So if you can imagine you know that
Put in your house
I mean
Right
Not with Facebook I mean I wouldn't say no one's not go
Do it but I
Fewer people are going to do it
With them versus with Amazon or Google in my opinion
Shoe department
Why did they release the
I am not sure quite honestly because it is really limited it mean yes it is
It's got to be always listening because there is a matinee integration and they're going to add a Google integration
The future
It doesn't even it's not like you can use
Facebook Messenger to talk to people Center April literally just a video.
Type device
With an always listening assistant
And it's not cheap either
It's 199 for the 10-inch display and 350
For a 15.6 in
Display that rotates from portrait to landscape I mean it's like a big old slab of a tablet
Santander
Yeah telepresence
From Facebook
You know
All your corporate and family secrets
Xposed
And
And on the product page they have you know
Here's the
All the features and privacy is on the pig
I just don't need it asked us for phone numbers for two-factor authentication and then
Used that phone
For this is not a cup
But I don't honestly know I mean I feel like in the media we
Dog and face
A lot
We see this
I don't actually know how many normal like truly normal
We're outside this world they I feel like they have a bag distrust but they may not understand the actual
You know is it evil it's certainly Machiavellian
Facebook
Yeah that's it there's a trust issue because of what they've done with data and then got basically caught doing
To their credit I mean they are trying here from a privacy standpoint there saying you can completely disable the camera microphone with a single
Or you can block the camera lens with the provider camera cover
So there's that then they also say they don't listen to view or keep
Your video calls
Everything stays between you and the person you've talked
The smart camera uses AI that runs locally not on their servers
Am I smart camera this is actually pretty cool tack it follows
People basically original around the room keeps them in focus and so on so that's nice I like that
But they don't use facial recognition or identify who you are so so they say
And are they only send the voice commands to their servers after you say the hot word
Which is a portal
I didn't tell you.
But I see why they need to do that they have to do something on mobile right
They had to do some soap couple years back they were all in on mobile because people were like a ghost
What's the weather
So if you think about we're moving to a world without screens or that we don't look at the screens or utilize the screens are pockets
It does become important to have
Communication or
A way into
The home in four people are going to spend time trying to think again connect which is what their fundamental mission is
Sure. And I get it too because they missed the boat in terms of mobile they actually tried to do a quote-unquote Facebook phone with h
HTC and that totally bombed
And now they're trying to do the Facebook portal in
Before it gets too late
So I get it too but I can tell you
No way will I buy one
Not
So outside
Crazy
Facebook screens
I am going to tell you about the number
The Enquirer
Redible number of screens I saw at
The smart Kitchen Summit so every year since don't need screens
Like your kitchen
Could actually end up with more screens than
Like an editing any other room in the house
So
This Is It event this is the fourth year that this event happen
And I love going to it because
But you know I love to cook I love song
And food there is always food there delicious food I actually ate
3D printed
Dragon fruit
Juice
How do I go
Juicy gummy I don't even know it was 3D printed liquids which was
Bonkers
You are not going to buy this
3D printed beef jerky
No that's not a liquid
Time
Sprite imagine 3D printed
Sprite YouTube
Okay we're not talking about that
Weird thing about screens everywhere
So I saw a smart
Cookshop
Where
It was a cooktop
Glass kind of
Cooktop induction
Kitchen range I'm assuming
And it had a TV in it
So like why you were cooking you can look down and
Things happen it was actually also a touchscreen which
I'm just going to go out on a limb here and say
Maybe not a great idea to combine your cooktop and range
Everything
Together in a touch screen
It happened no but I could see watching you know afternoon cooking shows
The next following along cooking right there and just doing what they're doing
Just avoiding
Yes
So that is one place where you might one day or you have the option where you could have asked
The other is if you look up from your cooktop you'll have a vent
Right most homes have event
Range hood range hood
Also
GE was showing off
This was a huge scream like
Like 20 in
It was very large
Cover the whole range hood
And the range hood had a camera in so you
Gazebo
Had a camera on the top of the thing so it could like look at you and get
Your kitchen view but it also had a camera underneath the range hood also
Got whatever you
You're cooking and it was it had the full internet they were showing but I thought that was really interesting mostly it was
Is an Android Base thing so there was
Google Duo
Calling my mom on Duo and being like Mom is this Austin yet
What consistency
That would be really
I could see something similar used in restaurants
Yeah between the cokes in the head
Jefferson and maybe the head waiter Etc
Yeah if you could get actually some AI in there and be like hey there's plenty of sear on that steak flip it
You know friends that like that could be
So that was another screen and then there was the everyone's favorite the refrigerator
And then
There's all these smart devices I mean
The Lenovo tablet and the Echo Show are basically like
The kitchen TV
My house
So
Ayo Kevin I felt kind of exhausted by
All the screens
Expensive good Lord
Sure
So that was that was one thing and it would it felt like
In this makes sense because then the kitchen voices
Awesome
Because your hands are there
Right you're like oh I can tell things but you're also like if you're going to follow rest beard anything
Do I actually want to
Yeah I kind of
Like the idea of the projector approach
As opposed to this because
You couldn't
Moving navigate with gestures not touch anything you know or you if you did touch like your countertop cuz
Maybe the recipe video is being shot on your countertop it's okay that countertops going to get messy anyway I would not want like Grease
Busy fingers all over a touchscreen device
Yes and
I actually asked some people about projection and they were not keen on it
I was really bummed about that cuz
Bosch actually showed her off at Eva and
In the kitchen
I actually think
Projectors
Is a there more economical they don't break as much
GE showed off his like little vents to keep the grease off your range hood but
Is anyone who's ever
Like how to clean the range hood that sucker is like a
The Greaseman
I want a camera or
Beautiful screen there
No I would love to see somebody basically create a projector for almost like a can light and overhead light
For my kitchen island for example
Yeah or just even I mean
There are many projectors that you could just
Pop on the top of a
Girl for a couple or like a Madam a speaker
Pitztal
But yeah we'll see so that was
Kind of the big takeaway they also had Wireless
Power
Howard
Counters item
We've got of Wireless power standard
Finally it's
The cheese stands
It's the same standard we use you know to charge our phones
Now
They're doing a high-powered version of that standard to power things like blenders or food processors
Or I don't know
Coffee grinders whatever
Kitchen appliance
George Foreman grills
So what they're showing off is
This bills into account
And it is kind of neat cuz they'll just they had a special Phillips and higher are making
Appliances for this right now
They just pulled out like a Phillips
Chopper
Stuck it on there.
Ezra like whoa
Record
Nopor
Look model cord
So that actually was
Kennedy I would like that basically your whole food prep
Space can also be up top you know you're not limits very specific cook
Spots
So wake me I haven't even told people
Oh no they have that
So they have that
Oh yeah
So I want that again
Wireless charging is induction which
Anyone who's like
Better high-end kitchen induction
Pop song
All the rage
You do need a special pan
So they done two things
In the future it would be possible with the right kind of counter-service and pan
Actually just put
Pain on the couch
Countertop
It would heat up
You could just
On your counter
What they're showing off now
Is a
It's like a coaster looking devices
1 inch thick device
And it has the
The circle on it so you know where to put your pan
But yeah so you just popped out anywhere on your counter where it has this
Higher
Wattage
Power Inn
You can cook
Crazy
It's bananas
So I was kind of keen on this I thought it was neat
I don't
See it happening
For another five or six having the standards not even be finalized till the middle of next year but
I'll keep an eye on that
Considering how long it's taking the QI standard to evolve and become the de facto
Which is you were talking at least 10 years
But I would agree with you would probably a half a decade outfit
Real accommodations here
Which is a bummer alright a couple other things I saw there that were
Worth mention
You're going to see this in the newsletter youku
Daiso
Sign up for the newsletter if you don't but
Thought of you asked me about this
Robot
Cooking device called the rotimatic
It makes Roshes
Switches a
South Asian flatbread
And it also makes tortillas
Or pizza dough
So this is a
This is a $1,000 real
That sits in your kitchen
It's fairly large
Yeah it's pretty large
But you just put all the ingredients on topping
Mix a little ball of dough
Bruise around a whole bunch in it
Makes it go down into this cavity and
Squishies at Platt
And then
Cough up which is important rotis
And then it
Fix it
And
Slide it out like a printer fits like a printer tray
Your life
Down the chute
Set out of paper
Richie gym
Roti Jam
So I would say
They sold forty
I know and they don't even sell it in India they sell it only in the US UK and
Arts of Asia
Yeah check that out because the video is
Pretty freaking phenomenal and the companies
Been doing this a long time it took a lot after
And then
The June oven Kevin's in my favorite
Damn didn't update the ties them into Whole Foods all of a sudden to the Whole Foods right now and you're doing oven which might be
President marketing
Decide
But it will bake
The 365 brand pizzas there's some sweet potato Puffs there's all kinds of things
That you can just
Click the button and it automatically has
Settings
I eat it's a little clunky cuz it's kind of a long list you go through I don't know how automated
This could be I mean if I'd be better if you could scan a barcode or if it actually recognized the things but
How would it know that it's a 365 brand of frozen pizza one
So yeah barcode scanning I guess I don't know
Will they don't have
Have a way to scan the
I don't even
On my watch I have it on my phone
You're not here but I like to know who's doing what in my house when I'm not there I'll be out running at night and all of a sudden so many fires at the junior like
Really see it on my watch
Who's making a cake in there
Hey
Sometimes they make stuff and I come home and everything's cleaned up in the food is like missing gone like
I didn't get any
Yeah I got got to keep an eye on that
COK
Yes June
The oven for
Controlling parents everywhere
All right so those were two things I saw there that were pretty cool I also ate food from the Brava oven it is another
Late
Crazy eye color
So no heat
Comes off of it
You know the light is
Do not know I get that yes but like
When were using our June oven like you can feel some heat it's pretty well insulated but you can still feel some heat
I just wonder if
It's any different from an outside
Experience
Oh I didn't touch the oven
So I don't know I'm so
That is okay
I texted you know that I'm good you nice
Okay we're going to move right along for a minute
Caressing his oven
A story in the New York Times
Which is a column
By Farhad manjoo
About
The iot
And
I took away two things for this
I felt like
He is a good barometer of where
The rest of the
Yes right and I was kind of surprised that people were like just coming around to the fact that
People want to come put
Computer center
Everything internet
Go to the Internet cuz I feel like we've been talking about that
We have but we're nitzsche friends
There is a radical technologists in that regard
Wow I've never been in The Fringe radical Technologies category I feel like
But
Finally
I guess
He's talking to people about
Privacy and security and so he talked to Bruce
Schneier who
You know every year
We don't we get some mainstream publication talking to him and realizing that this is a really bad idea to
To put computers and everything and connected to the internet without any sort of
So I'm hopeful
In light of the Privacy hearings that are going on now
And in light of this particular
Column that we might
Almost
Be to the point where we can get some privacy and some
Cyber security standards around connected devices
That are legit
Especially since California
Did just pass their law
So I don't know what do you think Kevin
Yeah I mean in an ideal world and I know this is going to happen but in an Ideal World all the big companies involved here
Are we get together
And say we need to work on the
Together
Because it's a problem
For all of us the issue there is
They want the data of course so they want if they don't
Necessarily want all these
Regulations and controls in place
But again in an Ideal World I would like to see them do this as opposed to what
Expect will happen if the government
What governments will try and do this
And they will do it
Probably wrong and they won't take too long to do it
So I'm actually worried that the government will work with these guys
And they will do two things one
They will just Outsource the writing of this legislation.
Facebook and Google and Amazon
And I'll fight it out amongst themselves
And we'll get something but
Not much as
And I'm worried that they'll leave out like whole swathes of Industry where data is being collected
And used in ways that are
A little disconcerting
So do you know
Tell me about Dayton Burgers they won't think about right
Hey John Hancock
Spell pricing Insurance based on
The data should we check that data is actually a
Accurate mean something
Actuarially
Effectiveness
That I don't know
I think you are
Your fears are valid
I would love to see you and I don't know what the official name of the group is that consumer protection group
Who's working with consumer reports and the
Open technology
Initiative oti
And they are actually trying to create
Some rules around this so
Stay tuned for more on that
Cuz I'm going to be talking to them
About where that's heading and what we need
Feel free to like
Share your opinions on
Good Lord
It would be
New laws are bad but having the wrong law
When training a terrible loss
Apetamin works
Camille Garcia
So okay
We've talked for a long time Kevin
We'd have enough just
More
I know what it is
All right you want to introduce it
Dorit is this week's
Call from the iot podcast
Hotline which is brought to you by Schlage
With a variety of stylish and secure electronic to choose from
Smarter home start with
Play learn more at
Schlage.com
/ iot
And I have to
To tell you guys
That you did a great job there
We are still doing a Schlage contest
So you should know that you could win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wi-Fi adapter if
If you call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7424 and ask us
Your questions
And so
Let us move to this week
Question
Who is this from
Ryan
I guess rhinestone
Murrieta California
In addition to Smart doorbell
I'd like to add
Alzheimer's
Health Access to power outlets isn't going
Shout out those cameras
Inside the home
Any products that could help converts a light socket
Thank you for the show
Orion this is a really good question and it's also
It's mostly good cuz it's really easy to answer
On the security front
Security camera front
There are the Arlo cameras which you can
Purchase and there are two versions
About more than
Persian chicken be looking for the wire free ones
And they haven't
Cheaper one that is battery powered I'm not going to recommend you go with that
I recommend you go with the more expensive one
That has a ring
Rechargeable battery
And the reason why is because the batteries on this thing run out like
But there
Good cameras there weather
Weathersafe
There
I don't know what else to say about them
If you don't want to do that and
You want to stay in the same ecosystem
My advice to you is going to be ring because they have their stick up cams
That they have wireless ones
But they also have a doorbell
The two doorbells actually the older model and then a newer model
That is battery powered so
You don't have to actually
Wire it
Raise the video doorbell the old one is $99 and the new video doorbell 2 is 199
That has a quick-release battery which is nice
Yes
I do like those quick-release batteries and you can buy extra batteries in
Just leave them charging and just swap them out
Which is what I think peep
So
Those are your two like those are the two most pet adoptions I've tried all of
That you're in
It's pretty good
Weather pretty good it's really good that means the ring is quality doorbell
So if you have a front door that
Get some sunlight
Ring even sells a solar trickle charger for the video doorbell 2
Hell yeah and for the cameras
Oh yes I forgot about that solar panel
I had that in my
Part of my review kit but I never tried it
Cuz yeah it's $50
To add that it kind of fits around the entire base of the
Video doorbell 2 and then there's a little solar panels on the top of it
So there you go so good options for you Ryan or anybody else who's looking
Looking for
Wireless
Cameras outside your house
N wireless store
And we actually do get that question for a little time because a lot of people don't have
Power to run for these or maybe there's no Outlet nearby or you don't want to have
Chord
Yeah right next to your front door for example
Text your doorbell or camera whatever it is so
It's a great question and we do get this one a lot I will say
This is important for your wireless
It might be thrilling
To be like oh my God I could totally stick this up in a tree or someplace crazy
Which is actually what I did with
My first Arlo
And then when the batteries ran out after like a month
And a half I was
So consider access to batteries
When you're placing
That's my
Big word of advice
Okay
Kevin
Excellent show this week I feel like
So much as a
Happened and we
You covered a lot of it
And for all of our listeners thank you so much for being a part of the show and listening and submitting your voicemail
And
If you want more iot news you can find it at Stacey on iot. Com or if you can sign up
Newsletter if you want more Kevin you can find him also on Stacey on iot. Com or on about Chromebook
.com
Thanks have a great week you guys