Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have got a Whopper of a show for you today we're going to talk about Brit
Smart locks
$35 Echo Power
Eufy Genie smart speaker
A crazy expensive bassinet for baby
Once again I'm going to warn you about devices in your smart home
Scheduling
How to clean your office
Deadpool for Enterprise efforts
Handsome
Tiny little bits
Plus we've got a new gadget for a cat
It Hall of Shame
Andar
Guest this week
Is Daniel
Cooley
Is VP of iot at silicon labs
And he's going to talk about
The hard problems that we need to solve
For The Internet of Things tours
We're also going to have a message from our sponsor haikou solution
And now let's go to another message
This week's sponsor is Eero earobics a Wi-Fi router that uses
Mesh WiFi entire house in to make it really easy to set up
Wi-Fi in areas that may be hard to reach so we're talking about the new
2nd generation mesh wi-fi system the Euro introduced earlier this year
Eero the taxes that have main router and then one to two beacons these are mesh access points
That plug right into the wall they have a night light they're super cool and all of this can be
Be yours for 399 for that one arrow in the two beacons you can also if you have existing
Heroes you can actually buy additional begins if you just want to extend your system
Night Beach
In the far up north area
The Canada if this sounds good to you Cody Eero e e r o
. calm and you can get free shipping if you include the code
Stacy
A before we get back to our show
Actually wanted to tell you the story because I have one of my Eero beacons upstairs on my roof deck
The power like
My Sonos system up there and some lights
And I got an email the other day from
Hero they were just like by the way we noticed that your
Roof Eero Beacon is having some erratic
Performance issues
And
We just wanted to get some information about it so we can
Find out what's going on
So
Isotope
Back to thing
Hey it's outside on my roof
Inside a metal cabinet so that probably explains why it's not working
They were like
Yes
Could you listen don't place your router's a faraday cage
Exactly
Also
Apparently these are only good at temperatures below 95
Switch is not
Summertime so
I move that
And
You know I just want you to know that if you buy these things you apparently get proactive service calls
Some things are not working
Yay
All right
Now back to the show
Let's start off talking about
Bricks
Actually we're going to talk about locks that turn into bricks
Yay
So
What state
They make lox
And they make locks actually that are used in Airbnb
Their profession that there should be professional-grade I guess is what I'm
Button
They sent out an update last Monday in
We did see this
Did brixham is there
Fox and so they got the software update
And then suddenly they were like I can't connect back to the home service
Or any other
So what that means is
Then they couldn't fix the problem without either
Padding the person uninstall the lock-in
Send it back to them or physically sending a person to
Real remote access to do anything to the lock was just
Gone and
Basically customers of these lost could either
Channellock back
And it would take between 14 and 18 days for replacements
I guess maybe they could send somebody out to fix it
Luckily
It was only I say only an elder
It's all relative course
Customers were
I'm totally affected
And 200 of them were those were Airbnb host
These are all first generation
6000i models
Of the wok
So it's not like
Thousands or millions of blocks but
Still
Make a few reasons for Airbnb and it kind of puts out of business in a sentence right
Yeah because
You still have
But
But that make nearby that's a challenge yes that's how they are you have a rental home
Far far away and you just are being bit and now you got to work on the logistics of getting somebody the key
Getting the key back from them and so on
So this is actually not a new phenomenon back
Probably 2 years ago I think it was wink smart home hub
They actually had an update
The break their devices
Certification there DNS service
Vacation broke during a software update so
I couldn't call back to home
And what it meant
And this was a huge deal for them and I think probably contributed to kind of some of the problems and Corky's eventual bankruptcy
Was that
They had their
Customers send back there
Cubs
Or
You can actually go in on your own
In a log into your router and change the
DNS settings
For some people that was just too much
Touch in Sol
Those people
Week actually sent them
A box
You shipped it to them and then you got a new one back with all the
Your programming
So two things come to mind with a story to me
The one is that lockstate says they can manually update the lockup have physical access to it
Clearly
There's some communication Sports
On the device on the lock itself that is not
Rely upon
Wireless connectivity so I wonder
If
In the future some of these locks should be designed with actual customer access to that
Because that would save a lot of time if you could
Update your own firmware number one but you can't do it
Without access to that poor
Well so here's the downside though
Where that Port is
It may not be something you
He want on a lock
Because some thief
Is there only
USB with their own firmware on it
Indication for
Hahaha
I got you the crew
That's totally another Point ioi reason because
According to the weather reports I read lockstate
It says they can manually update the lock up their physical access to it meaning to me
Citrus swapping it out they're updating the firmware so that
Actually exist as how I'm reading
I could be wrong
No no that make sense
And the other thing is
You may disagree
But one of the reasons I've never
Look at the
Type of Smart Lock that fit over existing
Lock
Is
I want to make sure that I've got key access and other ways to get into something
Right I've always stayed with the traditional looking type locks which could happen
Type of problem as well but
Yeah exactly
There are cases like if your renting then this kind of lock
Baby
More acceptable to a landlord
But yes I'm I'm with you a hundred
2%
What kind of deadbolt turning lock that would be like in August or some
Ratatouille those have key access or no
I'm trying to remember I'm done
I had an August installed
It was like 2 years ago and now I'm like did it have a
I can't tell you
I don't know. Okay
It's okay I'm actually looking right now on there
On the product site
I'm just curious it looks like
There is a
Key type lock
So you do have access is probably not the same key as you would have for your door
It might be actually LOL
Actually
Yeah yeah so you're not covering the the locked
The key tumbler part
So you could do
Secrets
I rescind my point yes
Aventura
That's alright that's okay William
Sorry
Okay
Which makes all kinds of thing
Starbucks
Yes back in 2011 or 2012 or the software developers from Google Afton
Move to Shenzhen and traded
You say uncle right anchor but you're probably right
And then another
Key Personnel Google
Join him
And yeah they make
Y'all kind of terrestrial spring
Start with smart batteries now they make cables and adapters all things but
Now they make
Something else which is intriguing
You think it's the eufy genie
I think it is the eufy
Genie
Such a strange
Yuki Cheney $35
Madame GAO powers
Smart speed
So
This was a big deal people wrote about it a lot
Clare County review on CNBC and they were like
15 bus more just buy the echo instead because it has slightly
More capabilities
And so
I don't know
Well I mean on paper that you feed looks and sounds good is slightly bigger than an echo.
As you said it's $15 less expensive they say that the audio driver inside
Deliver stronger base in 20% more volume. Which I don't know because I have not seen this yet
One of the things that jumped out at me though is
It only has
A two microphone array
And I think the.
I want to say it's use the same 7 Michael raise the echo
Okay do you need sound from CNBC said that the sound was not that
Gotcha
That far field
Michael Ray is actually just mentions cuz interesting I didn't realize this is powered by synaptics
Who recently
Bought
Connexient
And it's actually connections product that does the the audio or the the microphone
Okay so you can tow and that thing that
They were sad about his cuz
It is not actually an echo
You could do some things that you can do with an echo but not others like calling other Echo
Amazon specific Services then
So so this has the voice Services behind the echo but not
Every single other Amazon service
I don't know I have yet to
Use other than calling you that
One time
I have yet to use
Any of my echo calling features including people call people on my Echo Show
Which is kind of a bummer I really want my mom to get one
Because of privacy
I can't talk to him
And I agree with you on that and I can also verify cousin looking at Amazon's pitching out the echo Dot drugs have 7 for free
Real microphones so there's a potential difference
Okay
So
That's that now
From the really cheap end
To directions to Tracy
What is talk about snoo
Because
There's a review out for the snoo and if you're like Stacy bless you
No
This is a party at you yes
What's new
It is a smart sleeping bassinet
Fur babies
You guys we remember this because it actually came out last year I actually saw it
In
CES it actually I think I saw it again in the beta store here in
In Austin
So but I don't have a baby
So I couldn't text review it and say
So baby tell me how did you sleep last night
Right
No one was willing to let me borrow a newborn
Go figure
Put in some crazy crib that comes with
You know basically a straight track
Well alright you turn the baby into a little caterpillar
There's a little
Yeah it's a sleepsuit so that the baby is he right kind of like in a straight jacket
Yeah
What's better
But
So this is a $1,200 crib
It's designed by Yves Behar
Doctor
It's the guy who wrote the happiest baby on the Block
Magikarp
Yes
And this is attachment parenting book it's
I read it when I was a boy
I paid my child sleep in the closet so I clearly
Maybe I shouldn't
People should not let me go
Options
But she's very high
Dispatch
Which it is only a bassinet apparently works for this one baby that tray
I don't the parent who did the review did not say if their baby was a
A good sleeper
Anyway
But she did say
Baby got 8 hours of sleep
At
8 weeks old
Which is
Uninterrupted sleep now
Yeah I would
I'll be honest
Yeah and then that's
We talked about pay for it we we are dimensions $1,200
Thing is it has a very limited
Shelf life because
After about three months in this particular parents case
The baby was too big for it
So you're paying basically $400 a month
For the most challenging
30 months have any babies
Wife and parents life
Definitely those first few months you're dying
You would do anything
I put your baby in
So if there's a safety factor involved because the the little swaddling
Burrito that you put the baby in
I'll keep them on their back but can't roll over
Great and you don't want your baby to roll over B
Danger of SIDS
All your doctors are going to be like
Can you put your baby on your back
So
Do we actually say what how it works
No I was just about to say what it does
That's the best part
Velcro your baby into the swaddle
You stick your baby into this water
And then the crib
It rocks back and
Fourth not rocking like a rocker but it goes from side to side
And then
Does it have sound does it detect when your baby's crying
Basically it has sensors it has sound and there's a white noise
Option
But you can have and it rocks the baby when it senses that they're not sleeping
It's kind of got some smarts involve plus there's an app that you can actually
Engaged
White Noise turn on turn off or turn the rocking motion on or off
So I actually kind of want this
I think it would be amazing for adults to have a
Sleep Number
I have a Sleep Number and it doesn't do that
I know
See when you when you kind of like like oh they're having trouble sleeping
I'm a 45 by the way
Free sleep number for something
I'm not asleep
No number for you
Next
Alright we had a couple people asked us to talk about this
So we're going to talk about this
NPR did a story on
It's a sensor developed by MIT it's called the super sensor
And basically this is a tiny sensor you stick it someplace and it uses
Audio signals to determine what's happening in a
Suenos
It's got algorithms it's a oh that's series of noises sounds like a shower or at that series of noises sounds like someone shedding
The microwave door
It's really clear what's happening in the
Home based on sale
Very small
It is it's like
It's a tube Square you just plug it into your wall
This is really cool we've actually talked about this many months ago
But NPR did a story that
Was basically like
Are you guys sure you want to put all the smart stuff in your
Home because
It sure a lot of
NPR is not wrong and we talked about this before like I have
Devices in my home that measure sound
Or humidity and I can tell things like
Oh hey
My family is in the kitchen eating dinner even though I'm not
At home
Or I can tell when someone's taking a shower
A sun-like humidity reading Spike
In certain rooms of my house
And people don't often think about the privacy and
Locations of this and that's one of the things we do on our show is we try to explain
Hey by the way
Used to drive what you're doing
And even who you're doing it with
So
Let me ask you this because I agree
Call Heartland the whole privacy aspect we have talked about it many times
In your home
I assume that your family has
Agreed to give up their privacy to you which
She's not a big deal you're a happy family
Are you talking about privacy that goes outside beyond the home and other companies
And the reason why
It's kind of a two prong
There is
And worried about companies getting the data
And or I guess I should say my case
Family is not too keen on me knowing
Where they are mother doing
So they were different
Yes so I think that you're right there
Definitely tula
We don't have gas family decided we don't want cameras inside our house
Face inside the house unless we're gone and then we position like Arlo's we got
Does fun Arlo cameras will position those differ
Places
And you know when my parents are here at there's an echo dot in the guest room
They turn that off
I don't want that
Yeah when we have a sitter or someone like when we had when we went out of town
We actually told the person who is in our house I was like
Hey by the way there's cameras located here here
Because I trust her and I
I think she's going to do anything bad but I didn't want her to be caught
Picking her nose on the cameras up
I thought
So there's that level and I think there's a set of
And then there's the
Surveillance
Kind of Internet surveillance in
1 companies are not great with
What's using data we actually just saw the FTC this week find Uber
For having their employees finding out who is
Driving
Where is showing
That kind of thing
Is really unsettling to me like I am very aware that when I'm testing doorbell
When I go out at my front door
Grungy clothes in my hair's all a mess
Oh my God you know if I
Pissed off his company and they were immature they could like totally
What
Play something
Sure
Yeah and then that's a thought that we talked about that topic many times
It's interesting
For me and my family when we got our Nest cam
The only way they would let me actually install it my family that is
Was
To make sure use all of the features
That use their phones for locations for them when they are
In the house it does not come on
And also to schedule it so that it goes
Automatically on the bed and it was
Off automatically
Before they go to bed and go downstairs and you know get themselves ready for the day
So they they set up Wii workout rules
To actually implement this
So it was compromised
You can't just start setting the stuff up
And I think the other thing that the story brings out that
People may not be aware of
Is
Not just bad or immature actors that accompanied
Doing something stupid
But there's also a lot of questions about
You know if you can tell
That there are three people who live in my home
And you can tell when we take showers and you can tell that we apparently use the microwave a whole lot
That data may be valuable
Malta Subway
Absolutely you know and if you can tell from the sound my appliances make maybe you can figure out what kind of appliances I have
Then you can start selling that data to others
That gets a little creepy
I think it should creep people out
Because
It's surprising to them
I think it's surprising to a lot of
People
We think of cameras
Is like
But we don't think about that
In relation to a lot
Which is funny because
We have thought about in the past but she said gone away just a smartphone itself which is been around
Modern version for amino 10 years now
It's got a camera it's got a microphone
I've got GPS
The cellular
Carriers know where you are apps can know where you are
A whole Treasure Trove of that that's up there
And yet we've kind of mostly gotten over that
I think so and maybe that's why
Manufacturers of reliable
French
I don't know how to solve this
I dunno
You should definitely
And now
We're going to talk about the Internet of Things expanding outside of this
Into the city streets
Does an MIT project called carioca
I made it uses
Toll tag
On cars
Basically determine where they are in the city and ideas you could use this for
Figuring out
Where cars are parked and understand a little bit more about traffic patterns
And
You know figure out
Parking options
The challenge here is
Again privacy do you really want to know he don't do you want
Anyone else to know that you parked in front of
When you're at the grocery store right
Is any of the ads
I mean if it's if it's to help me find parking
Innocence I'm okay with that as long as I could Billy determine that
Technology honor off these are like an EZ Pass RFID type tags you don't turn them on or off
But
You know it's
An application that would
Work in conjunction with this but I can say okay I'd like to find a place to
The park you may use my location to help me
Cinema
I mean this is just an MIT research project
EXO
It's worth looking at because you know things like parking
Are not just inconvenient for you
How to circulating lights look
Looking for parking spaces
It causes congestion in the city
Pollution so
Who knows
This is a pilot project this is not something you need to worry about today
But maybe tomorrow
For those of you who are privacy mind
Let's go to the
To the small news bits that are kind of fun for
So
My small newspaper
Is actually like a cool little story that someone sent me about
Scheduling a Roomba
To clean
Your
Office
FaceTime
Outlook
So
Which is an IP licensing company
Did the license for MP3s
So they're developing an intelligent cleaning Concepts
And
Schedule something in Outlook and then your room
Go
And you can put the put the bookings in
Prioritize things
And then the robots going to basically update
Band
Go
Wander around
So if I had had that in my office
Environment I think I would try to find a way to hack it so that it
I could schedule the Roomba leg drop
Cherry was Oliver somebody's Florida prank
There you go. Yes if you dislike your boss
You could probably use this
Yay
I will say
They use the
Roomba 6
50 Robot vacuum
Camo that they're doing and not the
It's a 900 model
Don't worry about that
Recently was in the news
Because the CEO was like hey maybe we could sell its mapping data
Yasso different Roomba
Not the one whose data is getting sold cuz you probably don't want your
Maybe you do maybe you don't want your
Office
Layout
I cannot
Thinking.
Superfine
I have a small bit of news I just found out yesterday there is a new June oven
Model that is
Hungry soon was just announced
For those who are not familiar the June oven is a smart
Oven
That
Has WiFi has
Cameras ceramic heating elements
As a touch screen display
And basically identifies
Is food you just put it in and it has recipes for so many types of foods
I just cook sporty it's fantastic
Pretty sure that you
Still have one yes
I do I still love it
We both purchased our genes
I think it was $1,500 is not cheap obviously but unfortunately the new June oven model
Is even not cheaper because it's 1995 so another $500
But the difference is
Sedative being built
In as a standalone unit
And I think it's all aluminum
Right now
There's a built-in version with
Stainless steel
Food grade stainless steel and
You got has venting built-in as well so you can now
Dodgers
Put it right into a wall in your kid
Kitchen soap for people who want to insert an oven in there
The June oven is now insertable if you buy this model
It's all the same size and everything else there's no additional features
So it's still relatively small
I think I cooked up to a 5 and 1/2
Chicken
So in that was crammed in there
So this is basically a built-in version of the June
It's $500 more and
If you're building a house this would make an excellent secondary other
And it's not
Crazy like my two ovens in my house are Bosch ovens and they are my built ins and they were eating 15
Another.
I'm kind of like I wish I were building a house
I honestly can't remember the last time user full size oven
I really can't
I use mine in addition to I use one of mine because sometimes I'm doing two
Two things at once
So that's just me that's why I had
Okay other bit
Final small bits of news
Pulse which is used to be a company called cell Savers has raised 25 million dollars to switch its business model to be
Become
Not just someone who comes out and repairs your cell phone or your tablet when you break it but
To deal with smart home devices when they are broken so they will actually set up voice Act
Activated smart home stuff they will help repair things if they're broken or
You're experiencing trouble
And
This is part of an ongoing Trend in the Amazon team is
Experimenting with their own version of The Geek Squad The Geek Squad has its own version of
Geek Squad
Installations and
I imagine we're going to see a lot more
Yeah these folks
They repaired more than 100,000 devices
So far I'm actually in the last year
They're all smart phones and tablet
Topically so broken screens and whatever else might happen
It doesn't make sense to expand their
Yeah because
I mean if you think about it everybody has one maybe two smartphones maybe other tablets better than once a couple people whatever
But the house might have like how many devices do you have Stacy that could
He could breathable
Shrek
Right so bye-bye expanding into this Market
Their area of
The types of devices that can do an
Who knows how my devices are going to repair next year I'll be very curious to see if people
Use this new service
I'll be very curious maybe I should get
That's most of the news we also have a gadget for our Gadget Hall of Shame
We brought you the smoke
Few weeks back
And now we're bringing you
The sound
So
The sound caddy is
I know what it sounds like if a Bluetooth speaker that's in the shape of a golf club has a
A shaft in golf
Looking head on it so it looks like you could even put with it but I wouldn't do that that's not what it's for
But it plays
Music from your phone over Bluetooth and can also recharge device
Sisters take us a bit of a battery last on a battery in there
But so you can connect it maybe smartphone
And you can even turn it upside down and
Shopping is at the ground while you're at the dry ranch or something like that
$129 for this
As of sometime not very good golfer
I would go absolutely berserk if somebody brought this thing to
The driving range next to me or Alto Golf Course
Just blaring music is not what conference talk about it is not acceptable so yes
I mean you can't even clap at golf tournaments you got to do the quotient.
Deer camera with a shutter though
Tell you did it out of here
No noise
So
This feels like a gimmick
Doesn't have a lot of
Purpose unless you're going to use it to charge
But that's what those
Anker / Anker charging
Right listen I've been on golf outings where we
Get a Little Rock SC
Noisy and whatnot
Okay maybe that would be fun
This would be fun for that
But that's not what most golfers about so I say to Mickey
So the sound caddy
Panera in the release disgusting
In the product golf is hard enough
But the sound caddy is helping to lighten things up while attracting Millennials and curious participant
To try so this is Millennials entry into golf
All right
So that concludes this week show
And stay tuned for a message from our sponsor haikou solution
Hand
Argos
Daniel
Cooley of silicon Labs who is going to talk about how we bring math to the edge
How We Do data models for iot is a really awesome segment so
I hope you guys enjoy it
And thanks for playing Kevin
Thank you
Hey everyone this is Stacy breaking into the Internet of Things podcast with a message from this week sponsor this
Sponsor is haiku Solutions
And I have stanislav
Twist out hair
To talk to us about
Haikou
Hastatus love how are you doing
Hi Stacy I'm doing good how are you
Excellent
So first off remind me once again
What is it that high code
We got light at full range of services for it related projects
Mainly for US base camp
Emphasis is iot and what we call mdp
Mathematical data processing
Okay so what is mathematical data Pro
Play mathematical data processing
Cleaning the application of mathematical and scientific
Excuse to a wide range of problem
Mdp
Enclose machine learning computation geometry or statistical and numerical mathematics and daughters
The elderly clients to make sense of
Usually overwhelm anymore
What's the date today
And then
Help them to make better business
Excellent so you build algorithms
But there are a lot of platforms
Who's that provide
What makes Haiku different
Good questions to ask
Indeed provide great pieces of functionality
Machu Picchu
Bear in mind that there is no one-size-fits-all solution when it comes to real-world cases
Send a text tomorrow
You quick but often meteor crater
Did you find this
Is customized
Sleeper light I get to develop
Mathematical
Based on what the client requires we can often make a recommendation as to
What data needs to be collected
And provided as an equal to this model
Subject matter expertise
Essential
And to work closely with our clients
Understand babies
Sunday needs
Who developed the perfect
End this way bro scientific perspective becomes important
So could you give me an
Want religious comes to mind is where the girl was too focused price ranges of collect
And working together with our client would you like some water
Play Someday.
Sociology
And Kids TV
Slater
We applied a similar process in the financial in the
Our task was to recognize specific types of motion
Quotes on waiting
Play some ocean parameters
Flick speed and acceleration
This comes from a wearable
Using this data
Chanel booties
The detainment
The motion and gave
The proper recommendation
And to do this we borrow the knowledge of Arrow season
Knicks and police
And implemented
International navigation system
To estimate velocity and orientation with respect to gravity
Really cool because I am
Not good
Building outdoor
So where can I get more information
Go to www.icloud.com
That's www.har.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Daniel Cooley who is senior vice president
Of iot at silicon labs
Hi Daniel
I'm doing great thanks for having me Stacy and I am super excited to have you
We're going to talk about
The tough problems the heart problems that were not thinking about you
With the Internet of Things
You mentioned to me that there are four main things that you want to talk about
So let's hit him
First just broadly so we know what's got
Sure so this is a
But working on it the Silicon level to enable and if
Future so these are the things that take a long time to play out
What is Edge computing
Iot data models
Human machine interfaces
And shifting business models around iot that impact of silicon
Awesome and we touched an Aldis so I'm looking forward to getting your perspective
Kick it off with Edge computing
Because I kind of feel like cloud is so yesterday
So
What do you mean when you're talking about
Edge Computing what are headed how do you define
First
That's a great question
So I I don't mean kind of the fog iot fog
That people may read about
Which is most recent around gateway's gateways in the home gateways in retail commercial Factory application
I mean doing computations at the actual end devices
In the iot
Doing math and making decisions on a door window sensor on a power tool
On a piece of equipment that sitting out there
Because today those devices
Necessitate provide
Actually don't make too many
Decisions
More massive power at the edge
Because there alot of trade-offs
This really comes down to things like memory
Rock compute for decision-making DSP for math I need a battery
Because a lot of these these cases have
Battery-powered devices to any efforts they can you know
Do they make better batteries is always good right now we're seeing as we've seen a big shift in the last few years from 8-bit to three
32-bit architecture
Stuff that was traditionally run on 851 Coors or or simpler architecture ship to 32 bit
Nothing great or the Eagles
But going forward is going to be a lot more need before
DSP
Computations in the math domain
As well to make better decisions around Sensor Fusion and was starting to Branch into topics like
Machine learning
At the edge
So that you can I know it's kind of out there but it is real and it's going to happen when I talk
Machine learning algorithms that get trained at the edge but
Ticket implemented out there
All right you just brought up like
Think so let's
I meant to say break it down a lot in the show
Let's talk about DSP
Because when I think of DSP
Math I think cellular base station
Voice process
So kind of threw that out there are we talkin about
Building Lee
Really power fishing DSP that are going to sit at the very edge is part of like a
An SOC or something
Pretty much it
Actually it's not that complicated
For the last few years
People making a lot of efforts on making better decisions
But that's not
Now people need a lot more math
How to make those decisions in this could be a fifties
Play fft
Fast Fourier transforms this could be
Yes
This could be voice recognition like think about
Something like Alexa
Sitting down in your sock to talk to a door lock how do you do that it's battery powered it's not plugged in
This could be in the form of image recognition this could be
Glass break detectors on running as with with a microphone as a sensor not necessarily for boys but for others
Presence detection
Is a lot of reasons people want to do more math at the most energy constrain in the most cost
Constrained devices
And putting a big DSP chip
Sitting in that system just doesn't work economically or powerful it's not very powerful
That's today so in the future we're going to make tsp smaller
Or are we going to do something completely different
We're just going to architect soc's for the iot
I'll say that most of the
DSP that you
You could have brought up in
You think about her knees
Big Iron
Applications or or centered around
Strict audio but in the future we're going to make the right products for the iot just like we've done with the wireless
Systems and processors willing to do the same for math
Okay and now let's go into machine learning
Because this is something that the coolest product
It came out recent
Read to me was the Intel movidius
Dongle stick
It's like a stick you plug into the edge and it's using the movidius computer vision
Chips in architecture to
For robotics for other cool and stuff so I'm like
This is not what you're talking about
Middle part of it so those kind of sticks that are running our
Le running Linux systems with gigabytes of
In a Flash and RAM and
I mean this is what it in my world this is
Is pretty processor
Intensive
But the applications are going into don't necessarily need that
That's where they're starting to
The same kind of applications can be implemented in a much
Smaller architecture a much simpler software architecture and a much lower energy flicker
Once you kind of decide what you need it doesn't have to be this generic linux-based system it can be something that kind of extends
Bring the cost down so can be adopted more widely
So that's kind of what I'm talking about here is in these iot use cases as they come up and they really come into their full form
You start to see more silicon
Tailored towards those use cases unless I caught generic architectures
Is it going to be generic in the sense of
In the cloud Microsoft and
EBay Google are looking at
Specifically architected chips for a certain workload
Big fat
When we bring that down to the iot are we going to be doing those same sort of
Custom architectures
In some cases yeah it's not nice
Necessarily that is
Divine for a specific application like a cell phone or a TV or something like that
But you look far enough commonality
When the volume justifies it
You go out into the system around then you can think about application
Mclighting
Being one here where there's a lot of lighting Products
Ticket shipping is about 4 billion
Products physical units that get shipped every year in lining
And it's not commonality across that segment
You can think about doing
Specific applications around lighting Building Products specifically for that
And you know they started by just doing lighting control and then they
You know Branch into other
Functions within the lighting system
Such as
Dippin Dots
Sensing relaying information these light bulbs are plugged in their power
Do a lot of relaying are they
P****** sand in these networks so there's a lot of
Functions of these are
See maybe in terms of sensing but there's a lot of fun
I don't see in terms of routing
So they're their partner an integral part of a network
In a lot of somewhere
Ford leaving architectures that are coming into the market and some of them are in the home but most of them
Kind of these kind of applications are outside of the home
All right in another area where I feel
Like we might have some custom chips and maybe some algorithms is around voice not just using tsp is
But also in
Machine learning
Now you're exactly right voice is starting to come up
Very very big
Element of the environment
Something environment who's there what do they need
What they saying identifying you as a person
There's a lot of that I know in this kind of starts branching into the human machine interface
She took my Segway
Yeah
So
How you interface with
Electronics is changing and
These Electronics want to know who you are on in Taylor they
The used towards you itself so they can do this with vision they can do this
I can do this in a number of ways
Your phone already doesn't with fingerprint
It's right your finger up your phone knows who you are based on
That was a big step forward
Machine interface actually
You may not think about it that way but that's the way the engineering side
Engineer thinking about this so
In the more that these Electronics
Taylor there
Application in their operation to the person
Using it it matters
I think about the lord always
Is like
I want a
Put my hand on a door lock
It knows who I am by the time I start turning it
Is either going to unlock or not
Think about it that way
You're more generous that I am I think it should unlock or it should send it. Electricity
Orgeat
Exactly and so just the way you interface Electronics
Products
In general is changing but you need a lot of electronics
To do that
Decapitation
Is a lot of privacy security needs around that
A lot of data that has to be shared a different levels in the car called iot food chain
And soul is driving laws
Security needs but it's ultimately about tailoring the product experience to the user interfaces I feel like everyone's
High voice I love your perspective about
Prince but then
It feels like we've gone from voice
To like all of this like you will communicate directly via telepathy if you think of like Elon Musk and some of the Facebook ever
And I feel like we've Miss like a huge chunk of the middle going straight for a veto I'm going to tell you to do something that I didn't think it and it will happen
Being perhaps more practical cuz you have to sell actual products to
Just like real
Customers
What do you think the interfaces are going to be or how are you thinking about
The future here
Twister tracks
Because I love that
That angle here my head is making a big shift away from physical button
Athens to capacitive button
For example
This is super practical
Because the performance is better and less things break
If there's not a mechanical switch anymore so it's easier to manufacture it's either produce less Q's but it doesn't really stop there I think
The product companies that were working with right now
Want to remove as much you as possible
It is kind of a strange way to think about it but they want to remove as in decision-making and I think you can see that in his face
Use casein in remote controls that are
Being shipped with
Televisions are over-the-top box
You know just recently actually I had table service
Installed in in in a property that I own
And I haven't had cable
4 years
And they gave me this giant remotes like 50 buttons
What would I do with this I'm used to my
Single remote from Amazon and so everybody's driving
Simplify simplify simplify and as much as possible and
I remove as much interface if they can really Taylor The Experience around what they want and not know
Necessarily try to provide every single hook on hook and knob out there
Okay so tedious feel almost like a bad example because you got a screen which makes you
You able to do more with
Four buttons rate it gives you a lot of like
Assistant mousing over but pushing over whatever
When you're talking about interfaces
Devices that don't have
Screens
Voices obviously win
What else is there
I'm to get seems like haptic feedback
Car
I don't know
Does haptic feedback there's lights
So anything visual is always bigger eyes are fantastic
Sense8 sensory objects
This voice that comes into play like your Alexa is it in and all the products that are coming out around boys
Control
That's a huge question and one that's going to be big because it's the one of the most natural things
You don't actually
If you have to learn how to read
Right
You don't have to learn how to
Speak it just
Gym Kids
You seeing this as an adult
But I think that's one of the big things going for is anything that you can talk to you probably will be able to talk to
I just came back from
You know I'm partner meetings and it was a big push around
Fencing again it's more about figuring out who you are and
Maybe how you're responding to
Environment or two what's going on then examples of company that
Was trying to
Or actually has
It'll mean a lot of Technology on EKG
To not only identify you
As a person uniquely
But if you're stressed
If you're dehydrated
If your
Hungry all of the other trying to figure out it interesting ways to actually do this
And so
If you want to think about that
Enter the human machine interface you can it bathe they were selling this as being able to identify
People on a factory floor
And I like that scary that's 19
84 territory for me
Okay so you brought up business model
Let's talk about that beat
Because I spend
Just a crazy amount of time thinking about how we're going to make this a hardware
More money from
So
What is the future look like to you what are you what future are you building
The question of businessman
I guess the idea for me is that
All products should be able to be
Be connected to the in
Scary
I certainly is for me
Intellij idea
Is powerful though
And
The way that people built products
The way they roll them out over time
And the way that what you expect out of them all fundamentally
Change
So if you can get with Kinect
The internet or some service
Think about it that way
Is
Pretty dramatic
But I think it hasn't really been done before
Other than for cellular technology
+ 4
Set top boxes
In a few of these other application
Transport for the consumer site
But it's
Edit you sweet on proprietary wise brother application
Smart metering
That is a great example
The internet but they are connected to some service
You're certainly being transacted on how much energy you use
We use at all times
So this idea is that
This is kind of my fear of
Oh my God everything is going to become a subscription so I will subscribe to
Turn on my door locks are my car or
You name it I'm going to subscribe to these connect two things
Which is kind of cool in some ways
What do you need to make that a reality
On your end
What do we need to make a reality in technology standpoint is
It's actually not that
You need consistent data connectivity to that device
And you need to do it securely
Most of the other stuff starting place
Actually so people can buy chips that are pretty cheap to go build a door lock
It's not the hardest thing
But getting data in and out securely and reliably is a big problem that people are trying to solve right now
But I think that's not the hardest for the hardest part here as in technology
It's about convincing people to shift over
There's a certain generation gap is a certain fear adapters a certain
Y'all got going a lot of places where people just won't rent a device as a service
Eustasis so compelling I'll just do it
And there's not a whole lot of those right now so I think there's Marcus going to take a little while to adopt it
Consumer side
Onyx flip
Of that the industrial commercial space
This is normal
You know you have service contracts left and right in an in a retail environment in a in a in a business environment in a factory
You already have services for security near have services for a hundred other things
This is being adopted a lot faster
Actually in the in the commercial and Industrial side that's the focus
That kind of a building for our products and those
Same specs
Meet the consumer need
At the same time
So it's mostly securities
Industrial side
Yeah there's a lot there secure boot authentication certification Key storage generation
Acceleration all these kind of things
Go to the kind things were building into our chips and in
The whole industry
Actually is racing towards
To do this right now this is not just me
So as a
Average person running around out there going
Why do we need all this
What's the worst case scenario if you
You don't have this and you have soups
Scription baserva
I think it just won't scale it won't take off in the volumes whenever materialized
The flywheel Easthampton
Think about it that way
I think that
It only takes a few hacks really takes a few
You know family members telling you no way don't go do that thing
And then you wouldn't do it
That's not out of the realm of happening I think that
Working hard to make sure that doesn't happen but that iote's happening in fits and starts along the way
I think in the end that the real use cases are
Pretty compelling out there and
DIYs too big to ignore so it's just
It's not a matter of of S but when
It's just going to be how how long does it take to get to security angle worked out and it's not just about songs
Security and that's an enabler for everything else
Really it's not about
Making the most secure devices like without a secure device nothing else
Is really going to scale
Okay well let's go to the biggest I don't know if this is the biggest elephant but it does feel like a
Huge elephant
Which is data models
She talked to me about what you mean by data bottles cuz people throw around that phrase a lot meeting a bunch of different thing
Serenity by data models is
Is the code running on device
That device
And if you don't have
Consistent data models to just stop going to work
You know I could take lighting for example and you install 20 or 10 light bulbs and
Can you start replacing them over the years 3 4 5 years down the line
They all need to work together
All the time
On off dim color
Control if you need that there is it has to be
Process
The same way
So that that apis
If you think about it that way or the
The definition of that light bulb
In soccer have to be
And if you're relying on
Fifty or a hundred proprietary
Implementations of what that looks like it just won't scale
It's not going to go back up
So that will be a standardization
There's a half a dozen of these
Things that are in play right now
And she's going to be there any two or three in the end
So this is a big philosophical
Question
I remember in the early days of the week
For the wind
The open web is dead everything's an app in
Even things like amp services like that it killed it so it feels like every business has looked at that and said
Hey you know what we can handle proprietary
We can try to push people
To buy all
Philips hue light bulbs are all Cree light bulbs
I know there are standards trying to make this work but it feels like
The industry is not interested in listening to what is probably good for consumers or businesses
They might be beating themselves against this light app to find
For years to come
I think that
Part of the reason of doing that right now is
Because
They're looking for ways to differentiate and that's how they differentiate today
And I just don't
Think that's how they're going to differentiate
I don't have a
A more concrete answer than that but I do know all these companies are looking for different ways to differentiate
Because they see
The Legacy stop being commoditized
Pretty rapidly
So
Having a connected device
Enable fat
You know I think that defining what a light bulb looks like an software isn't Phillips
Just trying to do
I think they're trying to do
And I'm using that as an example
You brought up the hill
In which is in one that everybody knows and
You know they're looking for other ways
Differentiate whether it's working with different ecosystems are out there for the
Control elements
How you turn light bulb on and off and software isn't so important
To them it's not where they differentiate their products
Those are the kind of companies and whether it's lighting or or anything else in the home
They're going to look for different ways to differentiate in the future that they don't have to do
Today we made
Really want their proprietary way of doing it
To be standardized that's still yet to play out but I think that they're going to look for other ways to differentiate the future
And do you guys have
I guess a dog in that hunt in the standardization effort in the data model effort are you trying to push the industry one way or the other
Different models are you just like please guys settlement
Yes
We are actually
So there's kind of three entry points into the iot from a technology perspective
There's the datacentre the Gateway and the edge device
And
Depending on where you start you'll try to drive
Decisions that actually impact all the others without realizing it or maybe you're doing it on purpose
It's a data models that are birth out of organizations that starting
The cloud
Practical to implement for
Certain cost energy
Complexity budget at the edge starting the gateways
Usually Implement security requirements on National devices that just don't work you can't implement
Certain kind of security at a
There's a lot of I keep saying that the cost word because that's what the price
Optical element throwing the stuff out so we push Verde tomatoes that are light
It has appropriate amounts
Security and Trust
Put on the IRT and so let you know I don't just want to go into all the ones that still come out to
Pushing through the standards bodies right now
But we're
In general
Shooting for lightweight
Models that Define only what they need to define a nothing more
And then have security elements built in at the chip level
And yeah
Okay
Security requirements
Encryption
4 key storage generation 4
Boots certifying firmware images
Already
Mostly. And then it becomes how do you put all this together to Define what a product looks like
Software
Oh my gosh why can't wait to talk to you in like three maybe four years to see if we've actually done this
Because my hopes are not high
We'll see I think that you're going to see
No not one
I think there will be more
All right will Daniel thank you so much for
Thank you for having me
That's it for this week show thank you so much for listening and if you want more.
Tnews you can sign up for my newsletter Stacy knows things at
Stacey on iot cam will see you next week