Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Cohoes
Kevin tofel
And we've got
An amazing show for you this week
We have
News
How much news from nest
We have news from
August
We have speculation about the Amazon Echo or Google home
Getting some new
Form factor
We got some Eminem both on the industrial and the consumer side and Kevin's going to talk about his Apple watch
We also are going to talk a little bit about it
Security from our sponsor
Portrait
And we have a guest this
Rob Tiffany was the CIO of lumada
And we are going to talk about the big news Warehouse
Itachi
Has reorganized itself
Pete
On the industrial iot side
Basically hitachi's answer to ge's critics
And Industrial iot push
It's a big deal
A word
From another one of our sponsors
Shively
Did you know that over half of companies who build their own Solutions
Connected manage their iot products say they'd never
Do it again
Lively offers everything you need
To lunch and scale your connected product business
Including tools to manage devices and users
And a white label mobile app
Plus business Integrations to make your data actionable
So don't let technology
Sidetrack you from reaching your iot business goals
We take care of the iot
So you can take care of your business
Visit Valladolid
That's x i v e l y
. com for more information
Right
Heaven
Let's get started with a big
News of
Week
Which is
Nat Nast
Yay
Wednesday they had a massive press
And we have known about this for a while
Speculation was rampant at cedia we talked about things like
Oh my gosh they're going to doorbell
Oh my gosh
They're doing a security system
Oh my God
They're doing all of that
So quick rundown
So you got a sensor
What's happening
This all went live yesterday
But
Hardware elements
And then there's this
Cool
Little additional feature let's hit the additional feature first
What's the biggest news I think
Really alright
Kevin's biggest news Google Assistant
Coming to the nest
Cam IQ
Indoor
So that's $300 camera that Nest announced
Fairly recently
It's got neat features like Nest aware
They come on in and now
It's basically like
In a lot of respects
It is and I think it's great news but I'm also like I just want a regular Nest cam
So if I didn't know this was coming I might have waited
Splurge on the nicer one
Well maybe this will make you feel better
There's going to be no Direct Media playback
On this device
So you know how you can tell it to play songs for
Spotify if you're not going to be able to do
And that's okay because that's exactly what those little Invidia Underwood called that we talked about two weeks ago the plugin
Mike's
We just enable you to speak commands for maybe media playback elsewhere or the house or whatever it's on okay with that
Okay yes and you can use it to play media back actually you can tell Google to play things on
Other speaker
You just can't play it from there
Turn lights on unlock a door give commands
Yes
You all of that
So but I actually don't think that's the biggest news I goofed
I wasn't sure the order you're going in there I thought you will get through it and then I'll jump back in and say that I think this is the big
Okay so we'll go in order of complexity
Nest is also announcing a
Nest
Cam IQ
Outdoor
To all of the functionality of I should say
The Google Assistant that's going to happen
So it's going to be
Nest cam outdoor it's coming
That's going to happen in November
That's pretty much an outdoor camera only thing that
Maybe worth noting is it
Super water resistant
Because it's ip66
There's this crazy readings
Any other thing you should know about it is
It actually plugs in
Through
Inside
So you got to drill a hole through your house
My hunch is going to be more professional installer
Nothing but
You can DIY this
I know they have
Like the face ID stuff where they can
Yeah I wish you could apply that to say to a delivery truck such as UPS FedEx Etc because it's always handy to know
When they pull up you can just come get them at the door that's just me or I get stuff delivered a lot too but
So like that
All right we're going to ask nest
Think about identifying
Track ID
For all the gadgets
All six of us all right
They also are going to do a doorbell
Nest
Hello
Is the name of the doorbell it will also be Nest aware and have some of your face
Recognition the other thing is
As adorable so it's a little bit unique
It's going to be closer got a 4:3 aspect ratio
Which is kind of like the August doorbell
So
Up and down
As opposed to kind of the wide-angle that
News24 rain
Skybell in those guys
And I kind of like it looks nice on the phone and
You can see your packages
You can always do
Hypocrite in the wrong spot like right under the doorbell
Okay so the other thing about that that's interesting is those quick actions that they talked about it's a list of all
Options that you can have happened when the doorbell rang
Sole
In our case with the UPS man who does Rings it runs you know it might can have it say leave the package by the door
Are you going to be
Not your voice
But
Leave the package by the door
Human voice
It's like that
Spotify
Gotcha so that'll be
Excited
And that is going to be
Turtles are hard
Don't come out until
G1
So we'll see it at CES
Yeah
Yes
And finally the big exciting
Plicated crazy
Which is
The session border can
Stroller
Yes
So
This is the big news
But that's what it is
So this is Nest overalls
Security system
And we'll get into the features
You probably already read about those
But there's two elements here that
Really
Fighting one is the return of
Weave which is
Speakable protocol for
Device Communications
In home so like it'll be like hey
I would like I can turn on and off that's kind of what we've does every device
Can say what it does
Aunt
All the other devices
We know it's like
So the other piece of news
Is the other thing that Kevin is really excited about I don't
Blame him
Is there going to be the nest
Connect
Which is a device that's going to both.
Heater for light
Red
Stuff in your home
And thread is a nest
Designed
Protocol that actually is a wireless
Protocol
It's on par with like
Zigbee or Z-Wave
So it is a mesh Network
Dang it runs over the same radio actually that
Sopitas
Anyway
This thing also access
What is attacked at
I get the
Session border controller SBC
Indecision
Because what it could theoretically do if we're right
Session border controller skin kind of create or Bridge networks together that use in Enterprise and even when I carry
Facilities and what you could do is
Essentially have that
Secure
Iot Network kind of inside your regular home network with this
Again if we're understanding this correct
Yes
So
Lots of questions and actually next week
That writers of Nest will be here in the park
So this would be exciting it would add
A lot of security we think it
The most
Interesting news here because this real problem
Meeting is private.
Now this network
Weave
This is important for your security system because you know
But it helps keep it more tamper-proof
Hopefully but let's talk quickly about the
Security system
Cuz there's some things to like in a
Things I wish
So
Thirsty
It's $500
So this is actually
Reasonable price
For what is a
Hub 2 sensors and then to kind of presence detection pops
Sonus Calls the Heart but guard and
It has a motion sensor it has a siren on it
And it has
So it works like an alarm system you come in and
Can't you punch in the keypad or
You can come in and use one of the
The presence of tag
Stacks and you wave it over it or you can disarm it
I kind of
I wanted something
Like my favorite feature in the entire world
Apple Smart Home
And I'm so sad no one else does it is netatmo has a facial recognition you can train it to recognize
People eater
And then
It arms itself at a certain point like you
Until it's 15 minutes after you don't see anyone in my family
Armed and so it automatically arms
I like it when someone come
If you want to disarm
And you can actually I believe say disarm
So you don't think that would be a fun
Option for the nest because then you don't have to
Wear something punch something or
Do something
Ennis
They have the camera
So I have to assume something like that
Could be updated
And then finally there's these Nest detect
Spencer's they're little
Multi sensors date
Door window
The clothes in the mail so act as a motion sensor
Pop it on your wall and it will be
Which is kind of unique thing
Most overdosed sensors in motion
Separate
And if you want to buy more of them you can they're $59 and then the tags that you have more than two people in your family
Starter pack comes with two you can buy more of those for
$25
These are also kind of like
Tiles in the sea
When you run out of battery on
So
That's all the News That's fit to
Or talk about
Unnest
Thoughts here are
I like this idea
Of
You know having this
Extender that also acts as like a
A bridge between your network
I feel like they cut it a little bit more innovative
Anna home security front
But maybe we're just going to wait and see
It's a start I'm actually more excited because this is really in my opinion the first time since Google
Alphabet bought nest
That we've had a true integration between what Google currently offers and what Nest has
It's been a long time
As long time, cuz basically
All we saw that was that
Hey just always worked with your Google home
Google assist
Not always
It was one of the first
Innovations that was.
And I was being sent up there
So you're right that is good and I I also like that this is actually a very easy alarm system
Car security system
To build an a
Install
But also public cellular backup
Prices are details on that yet but cellular backup in a battery so
But it is still DIY so a lot of people might say
Oh that's cool I want to do that
And it kinda reminds me like a
Abode or less a SimpliSafe cuz I've got a monitor
This could have a manager component if you want it later
Nestos plan to introduce that at some point in future
So I don't know I feel like this is a pretty approachable way
To do security
Do people like Ark
Color last week actually
But
Best of them alone
We're going to see a lot more companies coming in with this ring is building an alarm system and
We also have
Comcast and their scheme of the existing alarm systems although ATT
Stopped with
Soap
I don't know what time
And we might have a alarm system from another company that we all know which I never to talk about a few minutes
Sexy saying we are
Yeah tell me
Don't keep me in suspense
Amazon
All right talk about that
Answer this news just hit this week and it is just a report in the financial times
That Amazon is reportedly making
Two things
1 is a pair of smart glasses with
She shall not be named assistant built in
Apparently her camera glass did I kind of wish it will have a camera
Pictures more for scanning objects when I'm shopping I can just take a picture of something
What it is and tell me what the cheapest prices on Amazon
Security bit
The financial times says that Amazon's working at home security camera
It's Echo devices
So I don't know if they are reading into what the echo look does
Or they just have some good inside sources but it could be that
We have amazon security systems in the near future
So I have some thoughts about that because I actually
Use the Echo Show
Because I have these doorbells that work with it from August
I actually
Can see like I can see who's at my door on my show and then I can actually with her
See what's happening
So you can put your own system together now with Amazon as part of it but I'm wondering are they going to supply a hole
System and maybe even
Inexpensive monitoring system
Maybe because they actually have been
Show me the news at cedia was that they've been pressuring their Partners to really
Go all-in.
To get a madame a badge
You have you have to bring your
Camera stuff
Into
The show
So
That would it
Explain
Why they're soaked
Keen on that
Some of their partners are like really really I just
I want to
Just a plain old skill that says
I feel that does the things I wanted to I don't want to
Do the formal
Amazon
Programs it gets me this bad but now I kind of need a badge
Because I don't work
Work with the echo
Very interesting
So yeah if glasses are confusing to me
They sounds like glasses that act like the airpods
Because it's not going to have a screen or a camera
Conduction speaker which is exactly what
Which was easy to hear and other people really couldn't hear it when they're around you so that's a way to get that assistant
Type information only into your brain and not out in the general conversation
Why not to
Maybe
Peapod's yes
Yeah yeah
Don't know
I mean yeah so what do you need glasses
Yes he that's kind of why I'm thinking maybe they do have a camera because what do they do today in the Amazon app you can scan
Items and it magically
You sees them and determines what it is and it returns
I think if you're going to have glasses I think you're going to have a
A camera just for that reason
Not to take pictures of people in space
Record things
Stop Chatham
But two
Get you to buy more stuff
From Amazon
That's always what it comes out to
And nobody should take pictures of themselves
Whippies
Let's talk now about
August
Everything's getting over shattered so much news
But August this week
Launched
New devices
And theater
Lovely devices I installed
One of them but doing really good
Play with it so next week I will tell you all about it
So the three things they added are a
Fancy 279
Smart Lock
Row
And that is
It's basically like the homekit
Smart Lock that they really
Lease last year
Siri
Google Assistant but it also has the August
And I think they were you triggered some things and then they
The big news is they added
Capability
Doorsense
So this
This has a sensor built into the Locking a sensor that comes separately that you stick on the door
Basically says hey is this door open
Closed cuz what happens is
What's some people say
They walk out the remotely enable the door lock
At the door
Is actually still
And there's actually no way
Tell that
Without
So you be like your walking around
All day
Your doors wide open
And that is a sad
So that is what August
Doorsense
Does
Yay
You'll know if your doors closed
I actually I run into this problem all the time because my daughter takes
A jar slightly just a little bit in the door lock
Can't get into its insertion point so and I don't know that
So that it is a problem for me but in your case
Just as it
Unlocked cell
It does
That's true if I go check that's correct
Now
I will say also
Tapered deadbolt
But there is more there is a noun
Cheaper smart
Is 149
That's going to replace
It's
Baidu
It's a bottom-line Smart Lock but that's what it is so
Entry-level thank you thank you
But it is
It is funky
This
I don't know how you just have to look at a pic
Picture it's funky looking it's not the Yves Behar designed around chunk it looks more like a traditional lock.
That goes over your door
Kind of big
Some people will like it some people want
As is the case in
So
It also will have doorsense
But it won't support hose
And then finally
The news
Did I am super
Super
Super excited about introduced another doorbell Cam and maybe this time
I don't have this
But I will get one
II
Did it comes out
Because I love
The look at the August doorbell
I liked a lot of the features but
It was a terrible
Two reasons one connectivity was always kind of an issue is very sensitive that way and it drew a lot of
Power so that's what
They say that they redone the
Antenna design
So the connectivity is better but they also have solved another problem
Which was they didn't actually put any sort of
Camera that can
Can see in the dark
So no IR no night vision
Hang on there so it when it's dark you can't actually see who's at your
A lot of people may not have an issue with this because they're street lights and stuff and it does well in those situation
But now it has a flood like it holy cow
A floodlight looks
Peri-Peri
So that's
Adventure
I don't know if I wanted like black people in the face with light with a ring or doorbell
But we'll see
So I can't wait to test that and next week I'll tell you all about how
Deluxe work
Compared to the
So that is a lot of news
I feel
Bright Kevin
So let's move over into some of the
Quaker newspaper
Before getting to LT watches from Apple and
Ready Google home mini go
Google how many $49 is there in may hear about this on October 4th it looks like a small
Speaker just like you'd expect round, pill shape that would call it doesn't do anything different that we're going to
If you're into the Google home ecosystem and you don't want
Dad Echo dots you could add a Google home Mini
Perhaps after October 4th is my guess
Or
You can just wait till sometime in winter
Enable it on your fancy fancy camera
You can't have it
Silver Springs which is a
Smart grid startup
It's publicly traded company has been around for a really long time
They built
A smart grid system
In the early aughts
And they were bought
Buy itron
Interesting here
They were bought for 1625 per share
That was just a premium of 25%
Silver Springs
Its Revenue growth was not everything it should be
Its total value was eight hundred
30 million
And
Basically
Silver Spring was trying to transition from the smart grid into
Smart cities and Lighting
Itron is a
Company in the
Energy Spa
So you basically they do energy and water usage so they try to help
Utilities
Cities manage our resources
Sufficiently so this makes sense
It makes me feel like the Silver Springs
Smart cities efforts
When panning out
Or maybe itron is just going in
Big news
Finally
Comcast bought
Stringify
Comcast is not commenting
On the deal but
I got an email from
Subscriber user whatever the word is
And
I got an email and everything
So Comcast isn't talking about it
But basically stringify was a way to
Paul
Services
So many devices
Together for users in the
Idea was
Companies would also
Payit2
Get there
Connected device
Together so I'm not sure what this is
Really a consumer-focused thing for Comcast or if this is
Part of like they're bigger business leanings
Cuz they got their machine
Two kind of
Offerings so that's what I'm actually looking forward to hearing about when they start
Which
They are not
Cuz I did not
To my request
I know these guys have in common
And we probably don't know the answer to this book stringified today is a
Free product for consumers to use right
Yeah my guess is we're going to find out very soon that it's not
So
Now that we've been through
Most of them
Yeah so I think last time we said or I said I was considering purchasing one and I can
Tell people now that I did
It's not here yet they will be here in time for the next show so I'll be able to discuss my thoughts on that I do have an Apple Watch series 2
So really this is just
Newer Hardware inside obviously LTE connection the reviews are hitting
I've already hit and I read through most of them and it seems like there are a fair number of issues probably the most negative Apple
Product reviews I've read amongst everyone
Reviews and total in probably forever quite honestly
Lots of challenges that are even appears to be an issue that apple is admitted to wear the watch is trying to connect to unknown
Wifi networks
And it will drop its LTE connection
And they are going to address any software update is what they say so there I would you to make rice
What LTE and any wearable is really
For because
All of the reviews have just gone
Off about the battery life when your
Talking
Making phone calls with this in lieu of your phone and I get that but
You have a much smaller battery than you would have been
Pinterest with this watch
An hour of talk time is not good this should not be a primary phone for anybody
It's a secondary phone device at
Best and I think people need to really understand that
The way apple is doing this from
Apple watches connected to your phone via Bluetooth it's going to use that connection
If it's not in Bluetooth range of a phone but it has more power
If it's not near your phone at all minis left the phone at home
Which is what most people try and do it this thing people then go up to the highest power connection that is LTE
Switching between connections here but don't think
That you're going to put your phone down at the house and walk out of the house for 8 hours and you're going to be
Fine just like you had your phone with you cuz that's not the case so I just one thing I want to point out with all these reviews I think they're all well worth reading
I think they're legitimate issues but I also think
You have to either
You got manager connections are going to manage your expectations so it's just a thought before I get my watch will see how it actually works when I get
Vintager connections
Can we trademark
Try
Alright
Now
Let's go
To the hotline
Would you like to remind people of the hotline where we will solve your pressing iot issues or
We will admit to Battlement
Because not every issue can be solved
I will try all you have to do is call and leave a voicemail at 5 1/2
623-7424
Shut up
And this week's voicemail is from Bruce
Santa Fe
Stacy and Kevin
Hi this is
Spruce in Santa Fe
You can use this on
Broadcast
If you like my question is this
Moved into a new non-automated house
Adding Hue bulbs and
Things like that over the course of
Is that drive up in
Evening
Hit my garage door open
It seems to me that I had to be able to
Homelink
Italian pie
Hue bulbs in
Turn on my lights near the garage in
Dali courtyard
Make my travels that much easier if
As we get into fall and winter
The Dark Knight
I need your help
And I hope you have a great aunt
Thanks so much
Oh
Reus we have
Options for youth
Exciting
And they're not
Credibly
Except for Spencer
Yellow realtor
Relatively
So basically you want
In need
Ewe
To see if your garage door is open and closed
And your luck because I have exactly what you want already set up in my house and it works like a
Charm and I love it
But I did have to buy some
So I don't mind with the Chamberlain MyQ
And we actually recently talked about it because they're starting a program
With it we're
You have to buy the device and its $99 ish
Sometimes I see it for a little bit more sometimes I see it for Less so you buy this device you install it and what it does
Tells you if your garage door is open or closed and there's an app that will open and close it for you
So it's very nice I had a little reminder setup so after
15 minutes of my garage door is open I get a notification on my phone
Shut it
So you need that
It won't interfere with Homelink
Because I have that on my car too
And that will act
As a trigger
Here's where you have two options
I have set mine up and had my running for over a year
On the wink hub
In the wink Hub works with Chamberlain
And
The only caveat I have there is Wink recently changed ownership and we're not really sure how long that's going to last
They're not expensive
So if you buy the wink hub
You set up they called a robot it's like a
And
I have connected mine to actually my front porch lights in
The robot says
If the garage
Store open
After
Dark
And there's a sunrise Sun
Set option so after Dark
During these times
It's 30 minutes after sunset
Till sunrise
Turn on
Porch lights
Neither Lutron enabled lights but it would work with
Hue Lights
Whatever else
Wink so that's how I've done it
Now they also recently did this affect integration
So for a dollar a month
Or $10 a year you can
Control your Chamberlain
So
It's a way to connect to the MyQ to other things in your house and then
Yeah and then you won't by the way
You won't need that
But you will pay $10
To keep them
So I don't wake up by the wake up
Yeah I did
You just get so much more flexibility cuz now you can truly said he doesn't have a smart home if you think you want to get into the Smart Home
And eventually add more things get The Hub and that way you can just keep adding to your heart's content
And I can see wink hubs
They're on sale for like 60 bucks
You can buy one used
Original version
So
You know it another thought if we're going to go down this wink Hub pass or Bruce
Could he just get an inexpensive
Sensor
Like a door open sensor and use that
For the garage door
The challenge is
So you
But you won't know if it's open or closed
There's some logic
The Chamberlain knows if it's open or closed
So
Well if it's magnetic
You have one piece yet one piece on the wall one piece on the door that's not far or less
Expensive way to go like a Z-Wave door sensor
Okay so you could do that but then you got to think it was so here's the thing.
You got to think about whether
So thinking about weather and then you also have to think about
Usually Those sensors because their battery powered they're going to rain
Stickney or Z-Wave your garage is
Kind of far out if you don't have other
Take me to Z-Wave devices on the network you're going to want your wink Hub to be pretty close to it
Correct
I would worry about
Weather
This is something that
I've looked at in there at their other ways
To do this there fancier ways that involve
Programming
People if you Google
Connected garage
Store UK
Arduino zener
You can do some crazy
So you're right this is by no means
The only way
This is one
Bruce
Pick your level of
That is it
Sweet show
We are going to take a break for
A word from our
Car sponsor and then after that we're going to have Rob Tiffany the CEO of
Itachi's
Ramada Plaza
Talking about the creation of a new
Company called band
Aura and
We get into the industrial but for those who are interested in that what's going to happen
With the industrial iot it's going to be a good in stay tuned everyone we are breaking into the internet
Better things podcast with a message from our sponsor
Shrek is a digital identity management
For talking about
Edge security
So can you explain
What the problem
Is here
Two interconnected world where we make business decisions based on data that comes from devices or device
Vices make decision based on data that comes from other devices we really need to establish trust in these devices
Whether it's at the humans Trust
The data is coming from the device is authentic that the data has not been tampered with or that device is also Trust
The date of that I was coming from each other so in order to establish Trust
Devices
We have to have a
Picture process that establishes an identity
Can be used and trusted by all different players in the ecosystem
All right so can you tell us what forgerock is doing
Help securities iot
So there's two main pieces in our new Ford Rockledge security offering is coming up later this fall the first one is called the I dunno
The Edge controller
And if you think about what
People need to do to establish Trust
Online or evening person there's different levels of trust
For example you trust a passport more than you trust a driver's license but you trust more than a year lanyard that you
You get out of conference
What you need to provide your driver's license to get
Versus a business card that anyone can have printed up so those are examples of credentials that provide different levels of
Insurance for humans super devices they also need
Those credentials and different devices
Different levels of a shirt
But you need to be sure that if you have a solution that you can get that highest
Level of assurance and Trust in the device like the passport level
Security in a nutshell the identity Edge controller provides process and technology and software that allows
Devices to establish that high level of trust or lower levels of trust depending on what these cases
So weird
Sending our platform
And the code that runs our platform
You also run on edge devices to help
Establish trusted device identities course then credentials authentication and authorization for devices which
Also help
Ashley this is great
So where can I learn more about forgerock in it
A Dracula for drug.com or we've got a whole page that decayed Tourette's
Security where you can look at case studies and even see a link to a recent webinar about the
This very subject
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacy Higginbotham of it and today's guest is rough
Tiffany who is the CTO and Global product manager for the LaMotta iot
Platform at
Tai Chi hi Rob how you doing
Hey Stacy how are you
Excellent so we're here because
Itachi this week unveiled
A major industrial iot initiative
That was a little weird about this as we are recording it before the unveiling
If we don't actually know what it's called
But by the time this publishes
You will know what is
But everything else
Is going to stay the same
So
Let's talk about
Why Hitachi
It's doing this
Sure so Itachi
As you know one of the major yeah there's only a handful of really giant Global industrial conglomerates you know they make bullet train
Windmill turbines
Giant mining trucks
Factory machines all that kind of fun stuff has been around for like over a hundred and six years in that.
Space building all this stuff but also Itachi
He's been at the it
T space
Or like 57
Urine stay actually made bed frame
So there is at lineage
Actual legit it and OT experience for a woman long time
I believe the sinking is while it's great to
Made it this far for over a hundred years
Being a big Industrial conglomerates
The sinking is moving forward into the future
It's going to be harder and harder to
Survived another Hunter
Years without a large tibbitts
Coyote
IAAI
To get more value out of the Machinery that we're selling to our house
So Hitachi is really looking to the Future and it sees an existential threat
We mentioned earlier some things businesses might fall away
Some of the storage option
You guys have
So what kind of challenges do you guys see specifically as a threat to
The way that
Business operates
Or what it sells today
Sure I think in a big way so I just kind of generically think of all the type of heavy equipment and stuff does Itachi make
Picture of Japan think of Germany
Ultra high-end
High quality product but more expensive labor forces
Covington
Compete against lower-cost
Equipment
Machinery coming from China right and as
You start adding
Machine learning and Ai and you instruments all that equipment the threat I would say the threat is
Is good enough
Machinery or equipment and lower-cost
And so
How do you differentiate yourself how do you make your equipment more valuable than
Brand X
Right
And so what can you do with software and all of our experience
And ML and AI to create a differentiator
Hitachi equipment across the border
And it launched its own predix platform it started internal
Equipment
Those
To start building this canal software-based
Asset in terms of
Predictive failure
Guess to what Hitachi
Absolutely
And it's not like this is new to Itachi
Play like a lots of big companies Itachi has been
Manufacturing instrumented equipment
Three years you know what their own microcontroller reason sending Telemetry but
Is there probably well aware if you think of the forerunners to iot things like machines
Machine in the bed stuff
Going on for a long time
Siloed
Orbitz airline to different business units or product line
Sometimes everybody's got their own thing so how to do this is not new
Since you been doing it for so long to try to get all of the touchy machinery and then ultimately external machinery and you're right
Very analogous
Say what Jesus has done
All right we're going to get to that
First I want to bring up
Conceptual challenge
In the industrialized
Just actually
Scale back some of its Ambitions around
Going to work with
Just a few months ago it basically said
Hey you know how we're going to do all Industrial
3 core areas where
We've already got
Customer said that was
Energy
And I am forgetting
Especially the industry's took this and said hey
It's really hard to do industrial iot well across a huge swath of Industries
Redis doesn't scale
And so I'm curious if you guys are
Looking at that
Insane oh
Should we take a lesson from there or do you have technology or something that you think actually changes that equation
I think we have a lot of humility
Hitachi
Every know in advance that animated generic sense trying to be all things to everyone
Usually leads to failure at this whole order and so we didn't have such ambitions
Even though our
Portfolio products
Renee is very similar
GE makes and what Siemens make
We had no designs
To try to just overnight go and have a platform and tackle and try to support everything we do
So I think we're taking things with simpler
Steps even if you think of we're only going to do what we know it's still too much
Okay and what are the industries are going to focus on first
You know how
Peyote
In general people think of kind of broad use cases
Besides several specific ones
Play Bunny
Score better customer service just really generic
I didn't even hear people say and I'm going to change my business model
And I'm going to transfer my business and other sound really flowering it
Ambiguous
But a specific instance of that transforming
Model has to do with our bullet train
I'll tell you the story about what's going on in the UK
How does time zones
Perspectives Nevada is not just some iot platform that stretches out everything we're doing so it's the machine
Together to make sure we have a good holistic
We make bullet train Japan
You play never seen a Japanese
You know if you're writing on the page a baby in France or you're in ice
Something like that
UK government
Has all these Intercity trains going all over the country in as you can imagine if you ridden on some of them
They've been around for a while and they like some new one
They like to replace
Entities that want to replace something they say ever inducted in our feet and get people to put in proposals
Tens of billions
Pounce in this case to do that it's an expensive tall order and so you can imagine all The Usual Suspects showing up
And yes I'll be happy to.
Things for you
So he who has no presents
And Europe showed up
What the different kind of proposal
Which composer
Trains as a service
Instead because we're putting our money where our mouth is
We Believe
Are trains with tens of thousands
Sensors
And our LaMotta Telemetry you know our acquisition of telemetry being able to do stuff and rml and Rai
Find systems
Well enough
We're going to take that risk
So our proposal was
You don't have to pay it's anything
You're going to do train social service and working to build these trains for you
And then you're going to start using them and we're going to have to hit your SLA
Pay-as-you-go
Would be really attractive
To any governments are next who's looking at having to pay tens of billions of dollars or pounds are you
To have someone show up
You know what on our time and that's taking out risk
We will build these trains
In advance
And we will deliver them to you and then you'll just start
Paint as you go
Wow
So actually these trains are operational and you guys are delivering them as a service today or they are about to be
Operational I think there's already some trains are running now
So now let's talk about some of the technology
So you guys are creating a new company new name
And talk to me about what assets you're sticking under that new company to kind of help
With
This whole
Delivering things as a service enabling Iowa
Across your bows
That certainly includes assets
Itachi inside group that has been building LaMotta and again when I say building alibata ITP
Platform
It's not like we're just figuring it out from
Scratch we're going around
I thought you were decades event am experiencing analytics and pulling the best stuff together to make this reality so
Spotlights
Something came off the top of her head
It's
Pentaho which is Analytics
Machine learning Big Data company we acquired a few years ago that does a great job of
Enterprise Integration
Hundreds of connectors to connect to any kind of
Back-end system the customer have you have databases
Components of our storage business
Hitachi make
Really high-end
Storage
Computer systems
Battle still be apart of this
And so you know we'll be delivering to
Hyper-converged solution
Where to pre-configure
Giant stack of ultra high-end servers and terabytes
Storage
And I'll demonic platform in pentaho and all that
Technology already to go where customers
Get up and running in the industrial Spain
Unlike the consumer space
You talk to people all the time
Are they tell you hey
The day that doesn't leave my factory or can't leave my plant and it's not always
For the reasons like I'm afraid of the cloud or I'm worried about shaqiri
Sometimes it's just practical reason
You to imagine a lot of
Industrial settings
Putting off terabytes of data each day
Baby shower and sometimes
It's just not practical to try to ship all that data to it
Sometimes not even practical to do so
Some kind of hybrid
Sometimes everything needs to be
Right there on Crown
And sometimes I'm not
Just talking about
Cuz they want that like clothes into the factory or a power plant or whatever 2.2 meet the customer where they are
So that one friend storage stuff comes in there we've got the stick called Foundry
That is the underpinning of
Connect to servers
Text software that we build that makes our technology easy to be portable as far as other part that
This new company was lots of it in Japan
Factory
Easter part of that there's all kinds of data science organization
Better part of it I think we have all the right pieces
Inside the center
To drive us forward
You know in a meaningful way
Let's go back to this R&D component
So looking forward
After this new companies creation what kind of cool things is Hitachi working on that could be pulled into this that
We want to look forward
Certainly
No one to talk about people making a difference
It's the data scientist
And it's the domain experts
Whenever you for a particular piece of Machinery you want to build some ml models
Around
Cricket cellular analytics are remaining useful life or whatever it happens
Has to be you have to have
Two types of people there you have to have the Domain expert at that
Your type of machinery and those every last thing about it.
Theme parks in USA
You know actual data scientist
You're going to pick the algorithms you're going to
Create a model train the model and work on that to get that
Just wright
And that's no easy task and see if the right people
Do that
Imagine we've got those
People here already
They can make that a reality
For us
Having that know-how and not just hoping
But a customer has some of it is a big thing
Awesome alright Rob thank you so much for coming on the show this way
Sweet to talk about
Absolutely my pleasure
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign
Sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week