Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And this week we have some sad
Security
We talkin about
Rack
We got a great
Story about
Personal trackers
Happened there
Add a review of the Sonos one the one that talks to Matt on the a
GE and Apple
Our get together on the industrial iot
We've got some data on the Smart Home
A split
From Honeywell
And I've tested The Madam a voice recognition
Multiple users
I'll tell you what I think
Plus we in partnership with you
Have
Come up with a bunch of
Yay
So stay tuned for that
And we have a message
Qualcomm
And our guests
Who is John Murray the chief administrative
Officer for the
Lower Colorado River Authority
If you guys are going well
He talks about what it's like
To have
800 miles of river
Covered by flood Center
This is a big deal especially post-hurricane
Steve Harvey so
We find out
Were there
And now
IMessage from another one of our spots
Sap
All right everybody sap Leonardo live is coming up
You will want to attend because you were going to walk away with the game plan for the internet of things instead of brochures
You are going to experience Technologies
You're going to be able to start innovating instead of just talking about it you're going to get your hands on
Experience with Innovations in iot
Machine learning Analytics
Data intelligence
All enabled by the sap Cloud platform in design thinking Services you're going to hear how their customers
Start interviewing with these Solutions customers will include caterpillar parkwhiz
Wedding plus you're going to hear from Visionary speakers like best-selling author Andrew McAfee from am I
Walter Isaacson who just have a new book out on Leonardo DaVinci and so much more
Or attendant sap Leonardo live in Chicago November 2nd through 3rd and four more
More information visit sap.com sap Leonardo live in a
That's a Whopper so if
If you want to be closing
Check it out
Enough
Let's talk about
Iraq
The show is on crack
All right
So the two a vulnerability discovered
Wifi
Just
Wi-Fi
All of it
All of life I-80
Major
Protocol breach
WPA2
Yes which is a security standard
802. 11n
The problem is
In the
Handshake so what happens is during
Handshake
Someone who
Who wants to
You can basically
Reset
So they can go
And there's lots of
Technical stuff here in a
If you really want that working
Link to that mashona
But the bottom line
Is basically anything that uses
Wi-Fi
And follows the Wi-Fi protocol
There traffic can now be
Bright and granted we're talk about Wi-Fi so this is any potential attacks or X
Exploits would have to happen within range of your wireless network so it's not a remote type
Attack
Russian
But
For any of us who remember
Are the birth of Wi-Fi
We're driving and driving around
Checking out
So I remember
Having someone I've had someone try to attack my
Wi-Fi network
My house
Registering a Brute Force attack
After they get the handshake
And they managed to get that data by sitting
Actually on the street behind my house
And using a
Antenna
So
Is this
A great attack
Back from a scalability perspective but if you have a creepy technically Savvy neighbor who wants to get naked
Get pictures from your webcam
Might happen
I can't believe I thought of that
Okay
So for all of you guys were like Oh Stacy that's awful
What do we do
I need it really bad
You actually have to update both your router and the client side of eye
Paises earlier on it look like maybe wouldn't have to
Update
But Kevin and I
Octopus
And we talked to some security
To err on the side of safety
Yeah yeah I'm always hoping I could just update my router I have a Google Wi-Fi router I'm thinking okay we'll
No Google is one of the many companies
That was notified about this back in August and they're working on a patch
But that's not going to cut it it
It's going to have to be client-side devices to so when Google does its patch the routers
Best Android phones
And that's going to be a tough update to get to every single phone for them because
It may depend on if they can push it directly or they have to go through carriers around the world and so on so forth but that's just one particular
Instance
I'm more concerned about and I think
Our listeners are probably more concerned about
All of the other connected devices it typically don't get updated that often
Wangjing routers typically don't
What about your webcams
What about your locks what about any Wi-Fi
Iot device you have
This is actually a one-time run like
I'm kind of glad not that many of my devices use Wi-Fi but
Darca market so this is a concern
So I will just say
Comcast said
Probably about a year ago that their average
Number of Wi-Fi devices in the
Is 11
On their Network
Most of those are
Computers Kindles phones
Printers
My printer is never sent me a
Right
But you probably have to do that manually by the way printers are known for their automatic updates
So I just looked
My Eero wi-fi system
Which by the way Euro has a fix
That is coming out soon
But is not out
It will update automatically
I got 31 devices that are currently on my network
And they're about five or six that were
We recently on my network
Including
Somebody's MacBook
That's my job
My daughters
So here's the rundown of popular things because
Cuz we found it
Lovely List
That we will also
Link to it
Update
So I talked to linksys Linksys
Is aware of the issue
Tp-link says they don't know what they're affected
Which
Terrafin
This why I'm actually very
Concerned with t
Tp-link stuff even though I have their switches
My house I don't like their Casa stuff
Not because it's bad but because I worry about their ability to
Updating
They have so many things and they're not great
I should note only because I mentioned it earlier the original Google onhub there's tp-link made one of those two versions
So that's concerning to me
I feel like
I regret
Amazon is in the process of reviewing
Nest
Has told me that it is in the process
Of updating its devices and those updates will roll out automatically
Knickers where the problem
Raspberry Pi
Is
Fixed Jesse and the stretch
Squeezy and others
Barbusa system is good.
Our Voice Mail system
He will be
Intel has released firmware updates for
For all of its chipset so a lot of the ones in your
Computers
That'll be good
Windows
Good
Linux
Mac OS
It's the
1011.
Beta
They're still working on that that's correct
Let's see what other ones do we
I can tell you what I care about cuz I'm looking through the list of devices in my Google Wi-Fi app
My wink hub
And I would think people have Samsung SmartThings hubs
Don't know yet
Samsung is not doing so
Skin Samsung
How about my Roku TV
It's actually built into the TV so I need to get a software update
Roku via
The app
On the TV maker
Worried about Ray
Kevin arjune
I was just going to say the dirtiest thing in my list
Your Nevins exactly
My ecobee thermostat
My Amazon Kindle
Everything pretty much pretty much so that's a list of things that I sent out a bunch of emails I'm still sending out
Maybe next week we'll have a wonderful update for you
With everything that
We talked about this
Patched
I'm not holding my breath but
That's cracked
And to be fair with me we're not getting to the low-level technical details of this because there are so many details to understand
So definitely you click the link that we're going to have in the show notes
I mean I just went to crack a tax.com which is spelled it all out
You better make a couple cups of coffee to read through all this
It's a lot
We did read through it
If you want to know what
I did not know what announces now I know
Nonces are
So I spent the whole time
Is a number that is not necessarily
What is meant only to be used once and never repeated
So the key is the flaw in WP
Pa2 allows that knots
To be repeated
So then you can
Use that session key
Now you know what an answer
I wonder if it stands for number once knots
Until the caffeine stick it in can I say
You be like heaven you're exactly right
But now it makes sense but no don't go in Jeopardy without
Not true
All right
So
Let's move on from
Cracked beak
I am not disabled
My Wi-Fi network
I am not
Taking devices offline
Mostly because they don't have cameras facing
Inside if I did
Take those offline
So can we talk about another Downer story
How I spent my Monday
I spent mine researching crack Kevin
Driving 230 miles round-trip unexpectedly to this is just background for the next news item so
Spare me
One minute here to tell little personal story on Sunday night when my son returned
From home to college
She goes to Bloomsburg University
Which is about 110 miles away from where we live
He got there at 10 at night on Sunday night and I don't have my apartment key
It was at his girlfriend's near my house
What is good to build a Do
The key and drives it all the way up there on Monday
Drives all the way back home
And I said guess what you're getting an early Christmas gift
My friend you were getting a Bluetooth tracker for your apartment keys
And that leads us to our news item related to this that Samsung
Actually just announced and will be showing off this week or deliver next week
A GPS tracker
That uses nb-iot cat M so basically it's
On the IRT
And Cat and that is correct I had a slash in the show notes
My bad I did not say
You are correct
They're going to showing that off this weekend
Samsung developer
Protect actually going on today they say it's small It's relatively small and smaller track
Widen one point
2 centimeters thick
Is waterproof and dustproof you have to recharge it
The battery inside last for
7 Days on a single charge
You can certainly attach it to anything you like just like
Traditional
Tracking device
Martha GPS as I said wifi-based positioning and cellular ID so
It's got a lot of ways to be found I don't know what it's going to cost or anything like that but I'm kind of interested in this especially because
It can be use pretty much anywhere there's a
Narrowband Network
And that's in more and more places especially in Europe although the cat enemas going to help
Other than T-Mobile most of the carriers
More focused
Uncat am
As opposed to NBA
Although
I'm going to say I think
Your AT&T to Verizon
AT&T is doing cat am I know that
Okay so let's talk about why you chose
I thank you because
I may have missed it in my research but I know that you've looked at these I'm sure some of our listeners have looking
The tiles the
Trackers there's various ones out there
I was looking for a very specific function
And I only found one device that could do it and that function is a walk away or separation
An alert and it seems to me again
My research
Maybe baby is lacking
Only the older
Tracker
Bravo
Nothing new trackr pixel
Can do separation alerts meaning
If my son has one attached to his keys
Any walks out of Bluetooth range
From those keys when you left them behind 30 feet away or whatever it is is phone will get an alert at 9
I dummy you left your keys in
So I ended up
He's getting today from Amazon he's getting a tree
Bravo
I couldn't find any other trackers that do that and I don't understand why that is
And you had some thoughts
Before the show witch
Are valid thoughts would you want to share them cuz I'm not
Sure so 1 is
There's also a battery
They're not always
2 is
Not everybody wants like
I walk out of Bluetooth
Stranger in my house all the time
Nikes for exam
And I would hate for it to beep every time
Absolutely not
Sure and I would have the same problem
Yeah I would have the same problem in my home if I used
I totally get that
Okay so what so what
I countered
I see your I don't want this feature within I'll raise you that a that feature should be optional it is
You have to enable it
In the tracker app
In this particular instance number one or number two
Why aren't these things smarter
And I mean that because we already have
Sensors that they can leverage it on her phone they work with a phone with a companion to your phone so why not have a
GPS geofence
That says hey
Disable this feature when I'm at home
And I've walked away without my
Mikey's cuz granted if I walk out of the house without me
My car keys
I kicked my car obviously I know I have left
My keys at the house
I don't need to know that when I'm at home
When I'm out and about the GPS from the
Hey let's start
Doing separation
Because now you're out and about
I just
Why we not leveraging that wire at maker
There's not do not the app makers book
Device makers with their apps not doing that
Well and that's a good question because we've talked actually you talked about this with your airpods so we'll bring the same cuz this is kind of a
Bluetooth means
I don't know what to do
The Bluetooth aspect that needs
To be smarter
Or if it's at makers need to adapt their apps to Bluetooth being on
Thinx
And talking to the phone more often and what that will do for
Core power consumption
Your airpod
Sample is actually really
It's the other side of the same
Well I think you're letting to my Apple watch with LTE
Because one of the points that I had made again continuing on the app makers need to
Add more smart
A nest cam use just your phone at the home away feature
Right so you can set it up to not record when you're at home and it uses the GPS new phone to say
Your home check the cameras don't need it
The issue I have with nest and probably with other apps is
When I leave the phone at home and go for
Run
I have my Apple watch LTE
Add and find my friends my wife can see where I am find my friends are smart enough to know a his phone is at home he's out and about
With the watch
He was where he is on the roads right now
But Nest does not know
Has any other device that uses my
IPhone as
The primary
Point of presence
So
Third party app makers and device makers are going to have to start thinking as you just said
For more Bluetooth devices more devices that let you still be connected away from the phone that's something that I would love to see
Happen very soon
OC and I was talking about your airpod
Challenges of if you're listening to TV
Your TV on them and then you look off in Iraq
Your phone is
And that is a guy that's a little aggressive it automatically switches me to the phone if it sent as a video I might want to listen to
On the browser on the phone
Disconnect from the TV
What I didn't want to be
Heaven is that because we thought
Mini Bluetooth devices acting is
But we also have many different
Computer sources
Soda used to be only our phone right that these devices talk to
But now it could be your watch or
Your
Amazon Echo
Or your television
Suddenly both the Computing device in the apps running on them to be smarter about what
Computer to use
But also
The Bluetooth devices need to be smarter about when to switch to these diff
Different devices it's
Kind of a night
I would think it's hard
Contacts
Of
Device usage is hard
When you're switching between multiple connected devices so I'm not trying to rag on these companies
Too much because I get the challenge I do
I hope they recognize the challenge and they start to do something about it is really my point
Yes
All right
Let's talk about
Some devices
Sonos
You
Did a review
I did I did I so I spent a week with the new Sonos one and wrote up a review
Over at Stacey on iot. Calm so you can read the whole thing if you'd like but the
Too long didn't read version is
I haven't never use a sauna
And having
Purchase for Echo devices and one Google home device
I'm pretty much sold on replacing some Echoes with
Bassano's once I'm going to send the review unit back
I'm going to buy
Possibly one or two
Sonos one devices to replace them because
The sound quality is outstanding
Edit does work really well as a
Digital assistant
With a few limitation
Remember this is not an a
Echo device is a Sonos device using Alexa voice Services which is done through this Sonos
Alexa skill and by limitations I mean
You can't use the drop-in feature
For example on a Sonos you can do voice calls on it
Echo with matter baby
Cannot do it on the Sonos at least not yet
And I questioned you ever will be able to I think Amazon
Hold on to those and have some product differentiation as they allow voice services to expand.
Other devices
I couldn't group Bassano's with
Echo is for speakers
Mix and match groups here she come out and we'll have to go all in if you want
Multi-room audio
So it works really well as a personal digital assistant with a few limitations I should say
And it is 199 and the cool feature that is coming
Don't know
You obviously didn't ask
It's not out there yet
Is
It will have Google Assistant
Also
In addition to madam
That's correct and that's a big
Piece of my decision making process because Sonos is smartly being
Assistant agnostic are there also adding air place
Support next year as well which
I presume will allow you to
Voice control Apple music and other things
So that
Choice of assistant
Is really appealing to me personally
I switch between
I don't want to have to be locked in a sense to an assistant ecosystem as it were
All right
Now let's see
Some fun Halloween
Here we go
Smart home devices have reached 15% of households that's up from 10%
Last eight
Last April being able to
So this is from the MPD
So
Yay
Progress
Honeywell Honeywell last week
Best investor that way
Was saying hey get rid of your Aerospace
Division in Honeywell turned around and said no
Instead we're going to get rid of her
Car parts
Diagnostics of and our home security business
Which includes
The Smart Home
Home stuff
So this is
Dollars worth of Revenue on the home security business that's going to include
You know the lyrics
Home cameras the formal home security Honeywell does have a home security business much like
80 +
They also
This week
Actually announced that they are going to go on Indiegogo to sell a all-in-one sink
Security device that has a camera and some sensors kind of like the
Piper are the
Canary
Dictionary
Which is kind of struggling and
So
Before that that should
To be out in
On Indiegogo
Also wanted to talk about ADT Pulse briefly because a couple weeks ago we did a thing on security and ADT
Hey pulse is still around Stacy we actually have over 2 million installs and in
April we integrated with
Amazon
Echo
So for all of you who are wondering ATT
The pulse is the
ATT home automation
It still exist
And now they also have their
SmartThings
A meeting with ADT.
How those two things
Things are actually
So it's not often we talk about Apple and Industrial iot but just today
The company announced via press release that they are ruining with General Electric
GE to offer a
Predix
SDK 4
IOS apps that will be downloadable next week
Basically it will help developers build apps for iPhones and iPads using predicts data collection analysis and
And I was wondering why they're doing this
I kind of think
Minato wants to certainly make industrial and
Enterprise apps
For the mobile devices I get that but I also think that GE decided hey if we standardize on iOS devices
And Max
You know maybe we can get a little bit of a break here so let's do a little deal and as a result GE is going to do just that
Guys on iPhones iPads at Max
Thousand
Employees so that's a big device win for Apple overtime and then all those users will get
To use apps with geez products on their iOS devices
So that was their first big partnership I believe
Enterprise
All right
Also this week we should probably have done this earlier on in the show but that's okay
Can't we got some fun test
So Amazon Echo added voice recognition
To its devices
Who You Are
Or
Dashie
Where does
Google home
A while back
Couple months ago they released it so six different users
It would recognize us 264
User voice profiles
Hey, Mama
My mom
A my husband when he says, I'm
It's going to call his mom
So we tested this at my house in
This is what we
It is not consistent so here we go
Sometimes it works sometimes it doesn't
Yay live TV
Oar radio
Alexa
Who am I
I'm not sure who
Not sure who's speaking but your instincts is account I'm actually I tested
And I had the same problem although I was not in Europe
I was in mine
Like
There's a lot of Pies going out on this
What's happening
We tested this
It's a little iffy and it worked for my husband sometimes
And it didn't work for him when he fakely
Mages voice deeper
It doesn't work for me it only works for me
So I'm not sure what's going
What you do is you go into
To your settings
What's on your bottom
And you go into
Voice
And you're going to
Basically say
I'm me
Or maybe you're someone else if you're not you
And you're in someone else's account
The matinee
And then you just say 10 phrases and
Principally that
The challenge I had was with my daughter who doesn't actually have a handset
That right now because I'm using her phone
For my own
While I wait for my pixel
And so to get her
On the thing
I would have to
Find a third device in my
A household that she could use
Golang
And she would also need an Amazon Echo
So and she doesn't have
Because she's 11
What was a little wacky for
And I also think
Kids
Their voices
Change
So if you're going to use this in a family setting keep that in mind because as the kids get older they may need to retrain the voice right
Definition for their
Profile
Final
Super fun you guys
So if
Was inspired
Possibly buy
They say it was
So it was inspired
Buy a video idea
Madame turn on Christmas
And they
Have done it
Turn on Halloween
And so
We actually abused
If
To create Apple
Halloween stuff
And now
If this done this formally so we're going to like to a blog post that has all of the
But
Some of them include like
Changing your Hue Lights to Orange
On Halloween
You can do it so it pulses your lights
When your skybell doorbell detects motion so as those trick-or-treaters come up
Strobe effect
Scare the kids that's good
Don't
You can also set up a motion
And
Haven't
You know that someone's
I'm coming up to your door
We've been the past actually used it to set up a motion sensor
And then had
Blow dryer
Plugged in
On a ghost
We made and so it would turn on the blow dryer in the
I can picture that I can see it in my head
There's a bunch of
Seas including
Automate some scare so if you press a button
Here.
Start cleaning
Which I guess if you stuck something
Great
Those are basically kind of
Some fun
Set up
It set up a motion sensor and have it trigger your tongue
Lots of fun
And check these recipes out
Adapt them for your products and
Level of scariness you want to
Create and
Happy happy
No she's not
Sorry
Why should say this was in
In place of
Vioc hot
Cuz we didn't want to have so many
Don't forget feel free to give us a call
Iot hotline
And that number is
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
Next week will be back
Answering your
So
I think that instead
News portion of the show Anne
Stay tuned for a message from our sponsor Qualcomm
And
An awesome interview with John Murray
About environmental sensing
And what it takes to actually key
Flood sensor
And what it actually takes
Keep flood sensors online during an actual play it's harder than you think
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message
From our sponsor this week sponsor is Qualcomm
And I have Anthony Murray
Who is SVP and GM
A voice in music
At Qualcomm technology
Alright so it seems like there's a lot going on around voice interfaces speakers headphones
What are the big underlying trend
Yeah it's amazing, no industry and in all the years of being in the spice
I haven't seen this many major
Changes oil
Come together at one time
Uses release
Streaming the Odeon
The contents rather than downloading it as they use
Doing this is really driving the
Requirements
Very robust
Wireless communication
Then we see some of the handset manufacturers not removing the
Traditional three-and-a-half millimeter audio jack
And that's really feeling the mark
Looking for wireless speakers and head
And then the number of the Odyssey
Assistant devices
Ominously
Plexus is damaged
Is an ex-felon Google home in this is really
Educating consumers and the Mons
Full voice interaction and voice control of their products within the Hein
We'll see this
Trend we're really
People of China
Enterprise a new category which has been
Old Spice and this is taking a headset which Disney did it say music
Voice
A step further in adding
Functions
Hearing assist
Potential even biometric monitor
Activities except
That is a lot of computing
Empower patent
This seems like a really hard
Thing to build
How is Qualcomm supporting these
This category represent some big technical challenges
You've got a separate left and right earbuds
What is a lot of interact
Between the two and how do you do that and then
Pics of RF Mana
Guilin China
Cancel the ambient noise cancellation in your environment
Wilson need to make sure that there's absolutely
Audio quality
Holcomb's aptx
HD Kodak
And then the device has to be always listening to use us that you can access your favorite child service
So this functionality has so many Act
Components that need to run all day
And miniature to the point that occur
Powers absolutely of Paramount
Houghton Holcomb does this really brings it all together and
Xiaomi package
And efficient enough to be able to run all day Alpena
Customers realize the vision
I'll be here about
Goldie
Awesome so we're can listeners learn more and get started using qualcomm's Technologies for hearable
Let him go to Qualcomm. Calm and search
Search for voice and music
Then I'll find lots of information on our platform offerings
As well as some consumer research that we've done
And as well as various products that leverage our kokum technology
That's qualcomm.com and search for voice and music
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is
Mary who is the chief
Administrative officer
Hi John how are you doing today
I'm great Stacy thanks I'm glad to be with you
Man I am super excited because
You guys
So we should first start off by letting everybody know what the LCRA is
So I'll let you do.
Sure sue the LCRA was started 80 years ago
By the Texas legislature
And it stands for the lower Colorado River Authority which just
These are National and international listeners is based in Austin Texas
So there's actually another Colorado River that's into
Texas was created in 1935 in the middle of the
The Great Depression with a very important public mission
Provide
Water to Central Texas
Do flood control and tell people from a watershed
Supplying water safety standpoint but it was done at a time
When
The state didn't have any money
So the way they created on Sirius has a selfie
Supporting government entity so they gave us the ability to sell this newfangled thing called electricity on which turned out pretty
Also we also are a wholesale electricity provider
And the second largest
Electric transmission provider in the state of Texas
Awesome so
The reason I actually asked you on the show is because I was looking during Hurricane
Because I was checking
Is this River going to Crest
So I thought
Hey let's get John on the show.
Talk about
Things are happening
Definitely crazy
How should we think about
Offering
Real time
Citizens
You guys have been doing this for years so let's talk about
How you guys monitor
Two Rivers
Started his mission like I said from 80 years ago has started with
Troll Austin is a beautiful city but it's a great representative City in the sand
In what meteorologists call flash flood alley
Play so there are a lot of rivers that converge into Austin and then the number of cities along
The river all the way out to the coast that had before this very persistent problem
Ysleta gun to flood control
Keeping people safe from floods with something that else Siri is always been in the business
The end
Results I think the way we've tried
To live out that mission has changed as technology
It literally started with people who live along the river with log books
Who would come in a hurry down to LCRA and
Tell us their data and then it turned into people who would call LCRA on
Newfangled Stone Mountain's Intelius
What was going on with the river and we've progressed and how we do that overtime to try to keep pace
With you using the technology that's out there
Can meet at Mission to understand where the water is now and where we think it's going to be and so LCRA has
Is a system now that's called hydromat
That was designed
2 years ago and it is a that's the kind of digital version of what we used to do in that very analog
Manual way so we have a network is 270
What sensors that are placed in strategic locations along more than eight hundred miles of the river we collect data from
Those that data gets
Processed
And
Provided back out to the public First Responders and the media
Via an internet website
Hydromet. Lcra.org
And that provides
What are the county judges in our area called at the great truther
It's being able to provide a common data set
Reading this
In a real-time digital format that everybody can use across
Cities counties
National Weather Service
You name it
That's kind of where l-series not right now is to
Maintain and provide that data
Back under this kind of
Platform looks like ourselves will use for flood
Okay so what's the internet Network for
Because
How much do these cost
How real time is the real time
LCRA
Estimate
Step by this point we've spent
Seek on the order of about 20 million dollars building
System so it's been a pretty significant in bus
A lot of the investment is actually in
Maintenance
Sending data collection
So we built
A 900 megahertz
Radio Network
Work that is designed to get they deduct from Oliver
Including transmission
Electric generation and water
But that's one of the hardest points as you need a way to get you know over 800 miles
Class of river you need a way to get the data back from the sensor
So that's where a lot of that cost is gone isn't it building radio towers in the infrastructure to connect to the sensors
With l-series Homebase the sensors themselves
Are great their top-of-the-line that's really the
Jewel of the Nile is what National Weather Service USGS others use
The cheapest and best flood sensors you can use these days cost between 25
50000 CM * $75,000
Santa have a lot of
Yeah that's pretty expensive they tend to have a lot of maintenance
So typically a technician
Lisa glancy the Mary
12 weeks
And when you spread them out over 800 miles that that's a pretty labor-intensive crop
Possession Sarah
It's a great system but I think it's a system that we're trying to
Find ways to drive that cost down so that we could scale it to provide
In a better data from a larger
Region
Why didn't you guys choose a cellular network
Network or is it because
Spread across power generation
We're doing a good chunk of research now on
Cellular as a possible alternatives to at or either as an alternative or to augment
The radio coverage
It was timing though so at the time that the system was built to the cellular provider is didn't have enough coverage
And they didn't have enough data rates to be able to get this type of information back not that radio is it pretty
Piccadilly high-bandwidth mechanism but we really just
Fundamentally doesn't have the coverage we needed to be able to get
The data any other way now the cellular Networks
Are advancing so much and have increased their coverage so much
And with these new standards around what they called LTE - M
There's more cellular carriers that are trying to make their Networks
Play well with devices as opposed to West voice
My phone so I think it's promising that there is some potential that cellular could end up to be a good now
I work for us but at the time we just really couldn't get the coverage
And the bad wreck that we needed we also need for this type of Aspen application do we need Public Safety level reliability soap
If we operate our radios on that same network
A lot of police departments a lot of we have actually 10,000 devices connected to radio not working only 18 of them
RLC replay song
The rest are either devices sensors or
First Responders in communities
So you need kind of
Lots of coverage good data rates
Very very high Public Safety level reliability
Cellular really wasn't there
When we built it but I think
It may be there now
So we're really looking pretty intensely to see whether that's something we can transition
Alright so let's go back to the mission
Because I sit there
Look at this stuff
Is it flooding
I'm sorry
It's really sad State of Affairs for me
How quickly is this date coming in
The website is to talk about what happened
You're a freak rainstorm
During a flood
What happens in your operations
The typical refresh rate
For the sensors that we have an hour about
Every 15 minutes for a lot of folks I think we would consider that to be fairly close to real time
That being said
We are doing a pretty extensive research project now to see if we can increase that or have the ability to
First to the sampling rate to be much faster during kind of peak conditions
So you know can we take readings every minute or multiple times a minute
But it's still you know that's still see really close to real-time but in its last flood
Situation
Specialist First Responders we really want to be able
Multi gather data at a higher
Playwright
The travel time it takes to get the data process from the sensors out onto the website is actually
Are they close to real time and we like to tell folks that
One of the nice principles about these types of systems is that the peak speed at The Inferno
Formation can travel under Network
Is fairly close to the speed of light which is a lot faster than water moves
So we should be able to get the information before the water gets there
In the real physical world so the processing side of its pretty near-instantaneous the sampling rate about every 15 minutes
Approved
Okay and so
If there's a hurricane or a massive
What do guys like
Yeah so that's another reason
That the radio network comes in
In a flood event
It typically you'll see a lot more activity around that hydroment
So the first thing we'll do in anticipation of a flooded start a fire Emergency Operations
We have a river operations center that stopped 24/7 all the time
But in an emergency will kind of kick that up to a higher response level
So additional groups will come in
Are Public Safety team which is one of the groups in my organization comes in and coordinates and run the unified incident command
Structure
And then that can be stuffed up to 24 hours a day as well
Also the whole company kind of shift
So wavy
From what it's
Normally doing and kind of moves them
Just over to this Emergency Operations fitting so what happens in the field then
Is it becomes
Absolutely essential to make sure those kids are up at
So will have filled Cruz that'll be dispatched all over if there's any
Songs with either radio conductivity the gauges themselves and you can't imagine you in a flood that gauges sometimes need
Need to be moved
Is it possible for them to be impacted by debris or washed away Telecom Towers can lose power which means
We have to go get
Fuel out to them to keep them up and running
So we'll have us a
Siri
High degree of operational focus on maintaining that Network
Keeping it running during the
Slides and all of our Emergency Operations
Calls
During a flood start with Hydro
So the first thing we do is look at the weather forecast and Hydromet to see where the water is going and it's really the backbone
As everything else that happen
It's beyond that to make decisions about opening and closing dams
Send dispatching First Responders everything is based off of that data that comes
Turn up system so one of the highest
Priorities
System running it is not uncommon that we have multiple Crews headed out
Go either protector gauge or move it or
In augmented to make sure that that system
Stays up and running
Emergency
So what you have this day
What then
You have obviously update the website you got the public safety camp
How does that
Going to play
His role is really in a
As a data provider so generally that's the
Part of the equation
Network doing ourselves but one of the things were spending a lot of time working on is
Figuring out
How local Jurassic
Cities and counties in
Particular can do more things with the data and so we've got some real active research in a program
Calling smart alert switches
How do you take
Real-time sensor data
And apply rules and
Models to it
So that in a real evacuation a real emergency
Those First Responders are
Empowered with much more micro targeted capabilities for alerting
What are the challenges that First Responders have now without that
Is many times evacuating a city for ants
Is an all-or-nothing proposition I live in the city of Cedar Park if you're there emergency manager there
You either evacuate 70000 people or you don't it's kind of All or Nothing
What would you like to do is be able to use these types of sensors to provide a platform
That those types of First Responders can use to say you know what what if I could micro-target this information figure out exactly which house
Exactly which neighborhoods are in Tanger and get targeted messages out to them and not alarm the entire rest
Maybe maybe 65
Housing people in Cedar Park are fine
And it's just 5,000 that need to get an immediate message we want to try to improve the granularity and
Does quality of those alerts
So that First Responders who use our data have a better
Experience and better outcomes
Meeting people out of the way or out of Harm's Way
LCRA would never see ourselves as the ones to actually generate the other
Because we're kind of the backend service provider but we're trying to do is to make it easier for those who actually have that Authority on the
Underground
To be able to have a signer green control has hounded activation happens
How their response to a s*** happen
Okay and actually tied to that would be better information not just from maybe hydromat data
But also date actual flooding
And things that I don't even know if we
Calculator
A lot of people were told to evacuate
Probably
I can't evacuate cuz I don't know where to
Those city managers
And First Responders are actually going to need
Not just your day. But
Other data
So that's also right and we would like to try to help them
Find a way to combine our data
With other data they have
Or either didn't know they can acquire as a city more effectively and I'll give you a great example that
One of the great science fiction authors William Gibson
Said something to the effect of the future is already here it's just not evenly distributed
So I'm trying to drive to work this morning
Coming from a wreck
Using Google GPS with amazing data knows to route me around the Austin City Limits music
I didn't know it started Friday I thought it started
Saturday but I didn't need to worry about it because now that's some revelers and some folks are in the way no worries Google can rob me right around
We haven't caught up to that
Safety
So there are a lot of dangers
That a city would love to Route their folks around
But the data is not managed and combined with the same ease that Apple and Google can do
Do with traffic data
That's a huge gap and I think we'd love to try to bring
The sophistication that's already there
In other places with these GPS companies with OnStar
Others and somehow give First Responders a way to combine that with a type of data that got from folks
To be able to have any more effective
Smarter
Basement outside
Evacuation because there's so many of those things like you say that just don't
Makes sense in one of the challenges that First Responders have
Cuz we also don't realize quite how difficult
Their job is most of the time they have to develop I mean it's standard best practice if they develop all their evacuation plan
Years in advance of an actual situation
How do you ever get that right cuz every situation is different in every situation requires these kind of real-time chain
Angels and many times those things that looks too silly to us in retrospect comes from the fact that they had to build their plans
So far ahead of the axles
Situation that they can't really solve
Problem with great level
Awesome
And scary
All right now I'd like in theaters
So we'll look for an API to get your data in through Google
Maybe I'll keep talking to Google
During life
Crises
So what did I do
Would you like that you don't have
I think there's
Two main things that I
Want
If we don't have a
I think one is just more of the type of day that we have and the cost
Actor comes into
Play there right so keyed up budgets are limited Sea-Doo dust you can write and we can put as many gauges out there as we can visit
A lot of smaller communities is
To extend coverage to that the problem is
The cost is
Primitive
So you want to put five more gauges in now the capital Investments 250,000 500,000
Dollars you got to train up new workers to go maintain them that gets expensive very fast
So we're really trying hard to find
Cheaper and better ways to just drive the cost of those
The data collection down it would be great to just have more data points of the same type
Hypo spino water level water flosser
Be kind of info
But I think you know the other part of your question about
What data do you want but you don't
Is other types of data other categories of
Water levels and water velocity and then we have weather data
And that's pretty much it weather radar that's that's typically all week have would like to expand to have
Other types of sensors on the network so you know water quality sensors to measuring I mean in this is just kind of blue
This guy type Vision but if we could measure Environmental Quality
Of the water
You know are there any
Clinton said that things
Like that happen in soil moisture is
I need a really really useful for flood modeling
Very difficult
Information
Other types of
Ambien information data sets would be really helpful
The final question
For you
As we add sensors to everything it feels like we can do
Much higher resolution
Pictures of the world around us
When it comes to
Environmental monitoring
Public Safety
You stink
Guess I guess I feel like we have this idea that we could get perfect information
Know the near future
How realistic do you think that is
On the ground with
Information
Trying to react
I think it's at the dream
And the vision
There I mean especially when you think about it to you in general I think the dream in the vision is right I think that people are
Potentially under estimating the difficulty of getting there
And
It is pretty hard work because I think when you think about you know we like to say another teach Community oh great we just
Weirdest magic wand is this
Every device that's connected everywhere suddenly smart and connect
With the internet and the reality is that is easier
Said than done I mean
The power consumption of adding microprocessors to every device is not insignificant
Getting the number of devices out there is
Actor and when you look at the electric consumption
Adjustive running things you never so used to having
The internet you know how to fingertips and being able to connect with any device and any website you know globally but
I saw stop the other day that's just
Is the internet itself was a country it would be the fifth largest consumer of
Electricity to the actual tactical difficulty of getting a huge number of sensors and
Movie theater around 3
Weekly and processing it in real
To get that kind of real high you know how most sort of
Hey I like you know intelligence in the network
I think is
The great concept that we should shoot for
But I think a lot of practitioners are just
Under estimating
How much elbow grease and hard work and cost
Dress together
Definition of iot in general is a little bit more like putting an astronaut on Mars that it is like putting a
We should go there but it's an orders of magnitude harder than
Alright thank you so much for
For coming on the show
Really appreciate
My pleasure glad to be here
That's all for this week's Internet of Things podcast
Remember if you want more iot news please sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Tom thanks for listening and we'll see you next week