Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Add rocotos
Kevin tofel
This week show is cha
Things that rhyme with eels eels
Nowell's
I just silly again this week
So we're going to talk about
Amazon smart home consultant
Apples
Retail store experience
Send
New networking technology
Plus we have as our guest this week
Alex Titan
Lighthouse which is a startup providing a
Computer vision offering
At home we're going to talk about a brand new type of sensor
That anybody can use
Excited
Plus this week
TED talks about how to buy
Let's get started with another message from one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is Affiliated monitoring
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business
You need to hear about Affiliated monitoring
In response to a trigger from any connected device affiliate is professionally trained live agent scan
Follow protocol and reach out to your customers their loved ones and local emergency services
Kid works with hundreds of smart home security health and other iot businesses visit Affiliated. Com
Slash IRT to read a case study on how they helped a connected
100 million-dollar exit that's Affiliated. Com iot
Alrighty Kevin
Let's kick it off with
Did you buy anything
I didn't attend this might be the
First time in ages that I didn't my son got a good deal on
Amazon Echo tap I can for $79
K-129 from mine
But other than that I don't
All right I bought
An Amazon
And the reason and we talked about this a little bit last week
Is the Echo Show that's downstairs in our kitchen living room area it doesn't seem to pick up my voice
As well as the original cylinder so my husband was like you know what I don't want that downstairs it's utility is not as great for
I had already given the
Amazon Echo cylinder to my daughter and I didn't want to steal it back
Apparently didn't want to put the show in
That's a No-No
So
I'm not moving to show to my office
So if anyone wants to drop in during off
Flowers
Actually that
Brings me to this idea
The show for drop in
Should have office hours
Chris Lake
When I'm sitting here at my desk working
I actually have no problem with a wide variety
Anyway
So back to that so we bought the original Echo
For $90
And
That's it that's a good deal I mean if you wanted a
If you wanted an Amazon device of any kind
Whether it's a tablet or an echo
The deals were fantastic
Yeah nothing else really jumped out of there was some smart home deals but none of them
Expedia
So I am going to let you know
Mother
I don't know how it taste like these tiny little sensors attached to it
It's a cute seahub it's it looks like an upside down light bulb with little :-) on it
French OK it's
Self expression
Necklaces that say
It's sophisticated it will ignore you
I will not turn on your light
Right now I'm busy
I have other things
That was my Russian
Mother is on sale for $99 for the
Hot it normally is 299
So this is actually
Good deal
And I think I'm going to buy one
I had played with this probably three or four years ago
It what I was a kid
And I wrote about it that I thought this was
A really great hub for
People who don't want to connect smart devices they just want to know where stuff is happening or where it is in the
Their house is very sensor Centric
Yes
And for 99 bucks plus you can get a package of four different kinds of sensors
Call peanuts
How cute is that
Horrible date they really are
Battery life
Applebee's
When I tried it out UK
Reach
Hard
I'm trying to remember how that worked
I do remember
They have
The sensors that are little bit more generic
And then they have
The peanuts and there's three kinds of peanuts there's a guard peanut
I'm thermopeanut
And a
And so
Those have special algorithms on them that track things like sleep
Or ambient temperature changes in car peanut tracks like when stuff moves basic
And then I have some more generic
Stead
Also track those
Specific
And basically
I really liked this
I noticed they had an activity tracking peanut at when I tested it out and that was not good
But it did not track that
Accurately
I tried to sleep peanut and that was okay
But I think
I would try it again measured against my Fitbit
Because sleep tracking has gotten a lot better than
The last time I tested this
And they had a prescription
Like a potion peanut that tracked motion and I put that on a pill bottle to make sure I was taking my medicine every day
That was actually really handy
Because it would send a notification
If I hadn't taken it
By a certain time
Red so
I don't know
I ate a good deal at 99 much better do obviously the 299 this is not a prime deal this is
Direct
Purchase steel from mother
From Central
Sense
Dot-dot essay
Not to be confused with
Hello shenzhen
Businessman
Electricity
It actually saying going-out-of-business reminds me so why do you think this is discounted I hate to think you can go there
They're still active on their accounts
And one of the things I really like about them they don't sell the data
They specifically say your date is your day that you can delete it from our
Servers at a time if you're done with it
At least I thought I had an in terms of that from
Take us back from day one
Yes I think it's part of their
They are French
At my other favorite French Camp
Netatmo and they don't share
So
You know if you want to build a French Smart Home
This is not about
We do not share
Speaking of
I I I wanted to do the speaking of French
Segway that she tried
I just now you'll say people don't worry
For this moment
Going back to Amazon
Amazon has launched smart home consulting services in Chinese
Seattle Portland
Price of California
Not in Texas City
Philadelphia
But
What it is is you can hire this
Amazon expert
Set up
Madam a smart home
I don't know what do you think
I think Best Buy is not happy with the Geek Squad because they do the same thing and BestBuy stock took a hit
As soon as this news hit the waves so that's not good
I don't know any I get it it's an a potential
Revenue Edition
Stream for Amazon part of me says the products themselves are designed in a way that their prey
Pretty simple to set up and
I mean I almost want to say if you need the service Amazon fail at the design
I don't think they did
Well okay
So I think people listening to the show
Probably not
The audience for this
I got a lot of people who
They're like
I don't want this it looks sneaky
I don't know where to go from
But I have an Amazon Echo
I want to set up smart
Light switch smart lights do I buy
So this is actually
This could help Amazon
Yeah
Any more thing
In
I should say we should because they don't sell enough things today
This boost value
Cuz if you're just using Echo and I think
Was it most people use it still is a kitchen timer
If you just use it as that
We actually got data from
Talking about
Boy stuff and it's worth bringing in now because it's super
Let's talk about some of the things we establish
Don't you have a voice assistant
You actually
Which I was like
Yeah in a sense this data are going to talk about a second isn't
Shocking but it reinforces the idea that people are using
This voice assistant
Exactly what they were designed for as well as other
Pictures but mainly for
For that the key features
Yes it is sampled 1500 if
Pretty
Self-selecting
People Like Us
Does the smart home show
Sorry about that
All right
Us
Who have
All these devices so 62%
People
Who own an Amazon Echo or Google home
Home Smart lighting
42% also owns smart thermostats in 40%
I want to Smart Hub
So that's
Pretty high
Jeff
Yeah I mean that the hubsan assistance themselves are useful
But obviously they're far more useful as you add more things right
The reason people bought these things
I'm a 79% markup to stream music
70% control Smart lighting
And so what's crazy to me is there actually using it
For what they think
75%
Music
Well 60% control Smart lighting so there's a little Gap there
So maybe Amazon wants to
Clothes that capital
This is among the more sophisticated people
Right said what's interesting also is going along with the whole
Ecosystem aspect of it
91% of those surveyed say that their system has made them more likely to buy another connected device in the future
So that obviously I can't get to the
Add more items to it
And I thought this was kind of interesting because a lot of people
He's just having a conversation on Twitter with somebody about
Amazon's hardware for
It's Darius
Smart devices
98% of if users believe they'll still be in their voice assistance 5 years
I get a lot of questions about yesterday add that to the hardware like no
The hardware itself isn't
The thing that's going to evolve at this point
It's
The software is
The service is it's what they can connect to
So I totally
Agree with that
Vast majority if users that say that
You don't Amazon built this with relatively at the time
The latest and greatest
Hot diggity chips and this isn't a product that
Requires this and that
It's a really interesting way to think about building
For the whole because these devices
Especially not that connecting your devices to the Amazon is hard
If you think about adding more of it like replacing
Connected home devices
It's not something people want
Yeah and it's
It's actually anime B
Wrong here I'm picking up
Stop my head
I think it's one of the most widely adopted
Consumer Cloud devices
Because really that's what it's doing it's better I don't need the heavy-duty Hardware
Everything is taking place in the cloud
Rethink mainstream people how many
Millions of these devices are out there now
That's a real Testament to to clock
Computing on the consumer level
For everybody
Hello
Mother incense how important is integration with your voice assistant when choosing a connected device 60%
2% said somewhat
Yeah
Yeah that's interesting
Also related miles apart in here now I just got to study from Walker Sands community
Haitians
Saying that they did at a future of retail
Study
And they say that nearly one-in-five consumers has made a voice purchase through an echo or other voice control devices
And another 33%
Set a ties into the hole
The shopping aspect
Things to
Although I would say
I didn't realize this would happen
Cuz I'm a space cadet
Where's my Amazon
Comprende
Through
And I got a $10 credit
Yes
That was that was part of the deal
So I guess I paid $80
Now
Back to selling connected devices which is this Amazon thing is
Probably mostly about
Apple
Has created
A retail experience
The Smart Home
Antique stores
Obviously based on homekit
I saw this and I was like well of course it did
Cuz you need this
To sell the smart home and then I instantly thought of retail smart home efforts out there
We can pick it off with staples connect which was our first
Which is now
Ring
That company first came to my attention because they built this
Connected store experience for Staples
And that did not go well
The thing is it was a great way to Showcase surprise fantastic demo is gave you ideas of ways to use the
The Hub and connected devices
So I don't think it's failed because of the
In-store demo metal
I think people just didn't
By there
Products from
Staples
Hangout
Experiment
It down in San Francisco across the street from Moscone
I actually this year revamped it
It's more like a beta store concept where you actually play with things cuz the original concept was to show all these connected devices
This working together
And I had this like clear lucite
Furniture
Getting all these connected products and there was a really
Demo coneria but
Be kind of tweak that
Because
It's something I felt like a smart home is not
It's not coming together for
That's another retail
Concept
AOL
In the beta store
Is going well but they don't show it like
They don't show Smart Home Stuff working
Like the integration
Watsons store
So yeah so with the Apple I'm curious what you think of
What they're doing
I'm not sure if
I'm not sure either I think it's
28 stores around the
Country
Not including Union Square in San Francisco World Trade Center and Williamsburg
I guess and then 15 stores outside of the US
How much did you say a non-interactive homekit experience will be out at all of that
So
At least you'll get to see things to play with them
This is the kind of product you have to demo you have to show off you have to let people play in
Hit a button to make a light go on and say okay to get them thinking about how they can use it so
I think it's a brilliant play I just
I still feel that homekit does not have the momentum of other platforms for
Various reasons
And by having a special section
The store that's focused on homekit
We're finally ready and with the homepod launching in December it could be that they're like going to build this
In-store
Ecosystem like that
Amazon is trying
To do with
The echo
I could see that and I could also see them doing their one-on-one training and Group Training like I do
For all their other products that's a big thing that
San Amazon can't do because they don't have a physical presence
Bread
Haven't used homekit
It is
Freaking easy
The biggest
Catches in homekit
Things up is going to be actually how you names
Understand you
So
I can actually see a year from now
Is the products are super compelling and maybe they offer install for some of the more complicated things like light switch
I can see this actually being kind of a cool thing for apple and getting homekit more Wiley.
I'm not a huge fan but you know it could happen
It could I I don't see them ever actually getting into installation may be contracted out but they don't
Think so cuz they like that control everything
I think it's more about showing how to use it
Anything else
Because it works across their entire product line on the mobile side new iPads
IPhones Apple watch
So you throw all those in the next
Chances are a customer has one or multiple one or more of those things
To show how easy it works across other devices probably what they're going to highlight
That sounds
Appellee
Awesome
Segway about
Speaking of France
Responsive media Francis
Several seconds ago
Louis Vuitton Louis Vuitton
Louis Vuitton
Sure
Fancy maker of luggage and leather goods
Is doing a smartwatch in
Kevin
Ascots
Oh Lewis
No no no
So
Let's talk about what it is
First they came out with
3 smart watches that are
Uniquely designed when you when you look at
Most smart watches today there
I know
I want a cookie cutter but they're very similar
So this is slightly different than maybe the other SmartWatches use singing and then that's fine
Button inside of course it's a Qualcomm chip and it's running Google Android Wear software so it's
Functionally and technically no different than
$99 or $200 Android Wear watch you can buy today
Of course being Louis Vuitton this is not $99 this is going to start at
Dollars and steel and the
A black version of it is $2,900
So
A Japanese
Smart Home
Yeah for a year I mean
Yeah I get listen I get
Fashion luxury brands
In certain products I do I get it and I spent
Some good money in sky
Yeah and I spent some good money on a Tissot or some other while call low and
Not luxury watches you know but nice watches
When it comes to Tech I don't see the fashion brands
Working and then tag or has already tried this
With
Android watches
And in fact it was Emma's $1,500 I think for the first one that tag are sold
And they I think they knew that it was a stretch because they even gave you the option of getting
A mechanical
Insert that you would take the Smartwatch out and put the mechanical
Tag Heuer watch
Automatic movement into the
Band
And now they give you both of them for one price
I I just don't see a massive market for this
And I think that's okay
Their standards
What I'm saying
20th century
It didn't mean we were going to turn into Boeing or Airbus
But are they part of that conversation now
Swellinfo
And that's the question
Is fashion going to take over wearables or is
Tech going to take over
That side of
Red fashion
In route
I would be sad like I would love to see
A Qualcomm dresses reference designs for
Fashion companies in fossil did by
Misfit wearables
I'm in his integrating some of that technology into straight up Fossil Watches Witcher
Dino stretch of the imagination super high-end
I like ideas having
A wearable that Ida strap-on
To my wrist and just
Mashing it to my outfit I think the challenge has been
On the software side
If I don't wear the same watch everyday
Put something else on it I wanted to just talk to
One app
Right
In what is it
That actually
Outside of price or anything else I think is what's holding back
More
Fashion
Gerbils
I would agree with him and you can anything Jazz things up with bands watch bands and so on
A failed experiment hearing is not one of the companies that we
Just talked about
It was the original $10,000 Apple watch
They don't sell it anymore
Wow
I can't imagine why not
I mean that to me that was like we're going to try and do the the fashion luxury brand
Addition
And I'm sure they sold a couple of them
But they don't sell them anymore than the most expensive one now is
I don't know maybe $1,500
Wiltshire I mean and that's a lot you didn't get it it's ceramic
You know I got the stainless steel model
My Apple watch was 599 when the
399 aluminum one would have been just fine it
They're out of him and I
Didn't want to wait Bass
Whatever
I don't know why I don't see it at
The other thing is
There's a hole
I'll call it an underground market for
Developers who create and I know this is not legal but they create watch faces digital watch faces that mimic
That's fancy to the 5,000 or $10,000 luxury brand watches
So if you want to Rolex watch base you know what you can buy for $0.99 you know until
Shut it down and they just pop up somewhere else
So I just don't think it's worth it for these companies to
Do this and I think
Take me to find that out should just do a
Affordable
Custom watch face
$30
I mean you'd probably get more sales of that then
Then watch it $20 box
I'm really excited
Because I am a networking
Is Misha
I can't say his name I'm sorry Michelle
I am terrible
But she is a co-founder of a company called Open Garden
Which is a peer-to-peer messaging
For smartphones
He actually started a new company called no.
And this company is basically trying to create a location tracking Network for iot
You know you guys know that I'm super high on location tracking
And they're running software
So The Challenge location tracking and iot is it is really expensive if you use cellular and that uses batteries
Companies like tile and tracker
Things like
There is
You have to have a pretty phenomenal Network
Closer to real time
Applications if you're out in the middle of nowhere
Tile app installed in your phone
It's basically a crowd-sourced network essentially
So
Side deal with nodal is
That instead of just helping consumers by these devices
They're actually paying Developers
To put
Their software into
Popular apps that use Bluetooth
And then so the network gets bigger faster and us there's more utility
Location track
So this isn't a consumer-oriented
To think it's like
Getting developers and then they're going to sell access to this network
Which
Building networks is always hard
Never easy
But I am really fascinated
Buy this idea in because
I followed Open Garden
I love the way they're thinking and I think that we've had it on a couple of shows ago this idea of
Building a truly distributed Network
For iot
I don't know it's interesting approach
So yeah so
Guys go check out noodle I'm going to write about it more in this week
Because I love it
I think that's it
This section the new section of the show and that's why the message from our sponsor and then
Alex
Lighthouse talking about
For computer vision so stay tuned for all that we are taking a break from the
Internet of Things podcast from our sponsor this week sponsor is Allegiant
The maker of Schlage Locks
Rob Martin
Who is a futuristic
Guys Rob is actually friend
Very smart women
X to the smart
Different questions
Intro to him cuz he thinks about this
Not just as a consumer but also as a company that makes
I want to make my home smart
What should I buy
Bye
Devices based on what it is specifically designed to do not what you hope it can
There's a lot of interesting use cases out there
But if you go shopping and are kind of
Floating
Looking for something cool you're not necessarily going to get something that's practical for you day today
All right
So
There's a lot about security how should I be thinking about
Security
Well there are lots of things to consider with security and it's not just cyber
Obviously with all
Ransomware attacks and other things going on it's a
Big consideration
But you should also think about the physical security when it comes to a product like ours
Locks is that Hardware Graydon
In other words does it have a bhma rating
That allows you to have the best security
Durability and function
Personality in the product
Perspective
I always look for over the air update if your device is not able to take on new technology whether that be in the
Form of new firmware
New applications and other things not only are you probably missing out on some new functionality
But you're probably missing out on some of the most important security updates that you're going to need
Now you mentioned
To bhma
Grading
And I have no idea what that is
Bhma stands for builders hardware manufacturers
Association
And so what it is is a residential lock grading system
So it's broken into three
Components
Security
Durability in Finnish
So security is what it sounds like it's a measure of safety
But there's some cool components in there things like Sledgehammer attacks
Attempts to manually
Call the lock from the door or
Wait like a child hanging from a door lever or something like that
The second element is durability
So that's a measure of functionality
So for example
Working at Estes
The equivalent of 100 Year life
And making sure that the
The Mechanicals are still working
And then finish
So finishes the measure of resilience against
Elements
So you know scratching wear-and-tear salt
Humidity UV rays all that good stuff
Wow so do you have a sledgehammer test room or you guys beat your
We do so if you look at our sense product
Or our connect product both of our touchscreen deadbolt their aaa-rated bhma which means they get the
Top rating
Across those categories I just mentioned security durability and finish
Awesome
Where can I go to find out
Stay so you can find me on schlage.com
Slashdot leadership or on Twitter my handle is at Schleich futurist
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Is Alex
Who is the CEO and co-founder of lighthouse
Hi Alex how are you doing
Good morning Stacy Angie
Thank you so much for coming on the show today
We are very excited to talk about
3D sensing let's get started with a real quick
3D sensing
So
Laid out for me
What is
3D sensing
Is a relatively new kind of sensor
So you can think of
I kind of like a camera
Rather than a camera that sees colors
In the worlds the way we're used to
We are used to perceiving the world
Discount received
Things like at every point it will say hey that's off lights and 3.72 meters away dark brown
And that's 2.85 me
Anchors Aweigh
And you get that for the whole field of vision
For this kind of
Kelly changes what you can do
With computer vision games
Like how
So the short version is that 3D sensing
Essentially
Makes many difficult some problems of computer vision
Substantially easier or relatively trivial to solve
Not also problems of computer vision
But many of them
Interesting topics to
To look at it to think about because
People are so good at division
Like our brains are so good at Vision that we never think about how hard it actually is
Using any extra technique you can to make that problem easier
Anthony something is just want to be
Okay so it does things like the ability to track distance
And not just color it just shape of
A computer to understand if I'm walking
Towards it or away from it
But it might also that it
Understand
Like how I'm walking into a relation of a room like these are kind of the things I'm
What is what these subproblems are
One good example here is that moving shadows and changing lighting conditions
Common
It starts at confusion
Four typical computer vision systems that use just regular color camera
And would you have a 3D sensor those moving shadows and changing lighting position
They're not changes in the 3D structure of the inventor
So they don't confuse
You can imagine the sensor
Essentially giving you a full 3D model of the environment
This is used widely in self-driving cars
Because
Having that direct access to a
Real-time stream of the 3D structure of the environment
Exactly what made it possible to finish the self-driving car races back in 2005 and 2007 in the dark
Lego
Okay so
You guys have
Taking the sense
And you have made it smaller and stuck it not in the car but in a camera for people's homes
And
Tell us a little bit more about
Lighthouse and why you started it
That's right the lighthouses I do kind of interactive assist
You can tell it what you care about
And it will tell you when those things happen
For example you can say let me know if you don't see the kids by 4 p.m.
And it understands what
Children look like
It makes use of this 3D sensing capabilities to to be able to understand what a child actually is
What time it is and if it doesn't see any children by 4 p.m.
And then you can go check in and make sure that everything
Okay
Because there's a lot of things happen
It sounds so easy
Are simple
So you got more accurate
Peter vision
Is that a decent way to say it
False positive
Dramatically increase
Capabilities
Camera with superpowers you've also got
Natural language processing
You've got
Some sort of
Programming in the back and see if I don't then I need to do this what else
Might be back there
Deep learning is the other really big
The way we think about the the really the really gnarly
Computer vision problems that were tackling
It's this combination of 3D sensing and deep learning
That really makes it go
And in particular gets its recurrent neural networks
That are analyzing time series data
Navigate from
Maybe worth mentioning 3D sensing one of those some problems that we talked about
Is
Fighting the segmentation about Jack
Right understanding that like hey this is where the subject begins and ends
And
Something it doesn't know what it is yet
And then the neural network will take a look at that
Running to the house this looks like a dog
Is there training associated with your camera
Like if I am a user
The short answer is no there's not almost everything works out of the box
The one thing that the user does have to set up
Because we don't know who is who
When like we arrived in your house for the first time
Right
So that one parts that user has to set up everything else works out of the box
Okay
So walk me through a day in the life with this camera so
People get a sense of How It's a little bit different
And some of the other things out on them
There's a very broad spectrum of things that that Lighthouse is capable of still one is the saying hey if you don't see the kids by 4 p.m. let me know
But you can do similar things for say the dog walker
He's working right now actually
But you say tell me if you don't see anyone with the dog at the front door on weekday after
It understands what you're asking for it understands what a dog looks like it and understands what a person looks like
And if it doesn't see those two things together
In Jessica's front door camera
Then it will let her know
When everything is happening normally in her home
But when something is out of the ordinary for some reason the dog walker hasn't shown up
Then
Is pretty exciting for a lot of different people with a lot of different
Specific problem
So we heard things like coffee shop owner doesn't especially want to get there at 5 a.m.
To like to open things up everyday and would really like to know that you know.
Let me know if you like don't see anyone there
By 5 a.m. and like it understands what people look like and it didn't understand the time constraints and it will it will actually
Do with us this coffee shop
And similarly for elderly care
His mother lived alone in Germany and
This kind of capability
Really useful to know
Hayden szeto
Eczema
And if not I should know about it so I can give her a ring and just make sure everything is okay
And she has this arrangement
Spell incredible
Security camera
Now the ability just said to check in on what's going on there
Let me go back to your
Coffee shop
Example because this
This is kind of interesting
Commercial applications
Or maybe even four
Me and my favorite
Coffee shop I would love to be able to say
If there are more than 30 people
At my coffee shop that is so tiny
And has
Let me know
Haha or some variation of that
And you know that would be really interesting from an
App perspective like
That would get me
I totally to download
Coffee shop
So is that something that you guys can
Can do or that
Maybe you're not doing today but might
Do some other time
Cuz I'm not something you do just yet
But that's absolutely in scope
The kinds of problems
We're interested in solid
Will basically be guided by what
What are customers asked for
And we'll stick with other opportunities for a minute
Come back to the home
There's also a really interesting
Location with things like
Oh tracking
Because it understands relationships
Space
Tracking packages or maybe offering better ways to load trucks and that's what
So are you Siri
You said commercial or small business interest but are you seeing interest or could this be applied
Really Broad
Or are there other
But he's doing it
This kind of interactive assistance were reduced you tell it what you care about that you make a request of it
Admit it take some action on your behalf or circuses some data for you
As far as we know nobody else is doing this
The closest comparable here is something like Alexa or one of the other Home assistants better
Speaker Bass
They're extraordinarily good for playing music
And a few other things like asking factual sorts of questions about the world you know what is the nest
Subway this kind of
Like interactive assistant
And let's go to your business model
Because it's it's a little bit interesting so the camera itself
That cost except
And then there's also a service fee associated
Set monthly
Yearly
We are about sanya mentally we are in AI
We have to build Hardware to get there that Hardware component is essential but
But really what we are providing
Is this this amazing
So that the hardware is $299 and then it's $10 a month or $100 a year
Fournier service
Okay and everything goes to the cloud which some people get a little freaked out about
So let's talk about your security
So we understand that
Nail trust is essential to this product
Bankrate
Security across the board so for example every connection between the device
And your phone in the back end
Stop those are all encrypted
With industry-leading techniques
TLS with 2048-bit keys
Aes-256 session
Kitchen
Is encrypted at rest in the back end
Software on the device
Is awesome cryptographically secure
So like that software running on there has to be signed by our product key for a cat run
Angle do things like
Shutdown Bluetooth connection
When they're not needed
It's like that's what that's not leave that open
As a channel to be tested by people with malicious intent
That has been a recent
A recent hack two people have been exploding
Separate
How do you help users
Because some of this is things like password so I'm curious how you helped users
Perhaps
Be better
At security and force them to do things better a little bit
More rigorous didn't
The hell yes
I'm glad you asked that actually it is another explicit thing we do there
It's a technique of key stretching
Login time
We're not just sending your username and password over the the encrypted Channel where we're actually running York
Password
Through essentially inexpensive hash function that many many times
There's a lot of
Computer work that your phone has to do that login time
And so what does. It is not something you can circumvent you like you have to
Do that Taki station if you want to to login
So for a regular user login you don't really notice anything
That delay and that's just like this normally just ask Fades into the background of everything else
What's happening but if you if you were to try oh I want to run 10,000 random passwords in like see if I can get into your account
Especially Yours
Weak passwords
That are commonly used
That would be very hard. It would take a lot of computational effort
Essentially makes your password login
Significantly more secure
Pacific star that's pbkdf2
For people who are so inclined
Right on
Peanut butter jelly
3 +
K peanut butter and
Crafts
Okay
Let's talk about
The fun stuff here so we're going to we're going to continue on our nerdy journey into
3D sensors because I love
I love new sensors
Genuinely
On the lookout for them because
Every time you add a new sensor you add a new capability
To basically the Internet of Things
And this is a monster
Capabilities
Computer vision
So let's talk about
The trade-offs here
You guys had your specifically designed the optical piece for the sensor
Where is design for you it's custom
So what is the sensor made of and what are sky
What is it actually measuring and how should I think about the pros and cons
Ascensor
It is custom objects in a custom objects module for us
And the general principle here is that it's a time of flight camera
That's one of several different types of 3D sensors
Roughly speaking at a high-level what's happening is we're sending out modulated lights
Is it the environment
So you can think of that as just like it's turning on and off
Very rapid
And then we look at
Basically how long it takes for that to come back and the fact that it modulated lets you measure that
In a fairly cost-effective way
Essentially looking for a spaceships between
The output signal
A reference signal and The Returned
Did you know when you sent the dogs and you can say alright in the analog circuitry here like figure out you know how much are these two signals
Overlapping
And then that tells you how long it actually took for it to go out and come back
And then you know how far away are
Hey does this reverie Point Indiana
So this is kind of like sonar
You can think of it a little bit like sonar
But with lights
But it's a particularly clever
Way of stuff measuring just
Soap with someone you're typically
Actually just measuring your like starting a stopwatch and then stopping the stopwatch
To to measure how long something goes out how long something takes for the signal to go out and come back
But with this it's not just like start the stopwatch and then stopped
The stopwatch
Because light goes so quickly would be on the order of ghetto nanoseconds that you have to measure and you can do that but
It's pretty expensive
Actually the kind of sensor that is used on self-driving cars
Is that Google actually just measure
Directly that amount of time with essentially the stopwatch method
And that's all
That's also based on
Collimated
Lazarbeam
Going out to the environment
We coming back where this is diffusely
Instead of the stopwatch method
It's more like
Look at how much these two different signals overlap
That if they overlap a lot
That it didn't take very much time for the signal to go out and come back and they overlap just a little bit
That must have taken a long time for
This is awesome so
Your camera is is somewhat expense
I mean it's not like break the bank expensive but it's definitely up there in the
The IP camera work
I know it's smarter
But how much of that like how expensive
Are the sensor
Can I stick this in
Just listen by how much they are
Because that's going to dictate
What I can use them
It's fair to say they are more expensive than a traditional camera there is more going on
But they're not prohibitively expensive like it is possible for us to sell things at 299
How do you say
A wonderful
But we had to work very hard
To get it to that price
There's no question
And what about power consumption
Is this a giant powerhawk
It's not a joint but it's not something
You would tell her with that
All right we talked about consumer use we talked about crazy ideas for business
And this is actually what you guys are filters
One part of an entire category
A 3D sensing
So
What else is there in the
So we got a timer
Cancer and two particular other options there for 3D sensing include structured lights and Laser Rangefinder
Into a structured light system
What that's doing is it sending out
A particular pattern
The flight into the environment and then there's a camera
That's looking at that pattern
Typically that turns an infrared so human eyes don't see it
But this camera infrared so it seems that pattern
Triangulate
And so that is actually just like using
Middle School trigonometry to say hey this piece of the pattern I see it at this pixel
And I know that I sent it out of this part of the projector
And so I can just like see where those two lines meet
And that's how far away that point is
And that's the technique that was used in the original Microsoft Kinect
That was from a company called primesense
Way back when
Connect cameras very good
I just sawed scanning dinosaur bones
Yep that was maybe the
What was one of the first Billy successful uses of Guthrie Center
And maybe the first year particularly notable example was in self-driving car aspect back in the DARPA challenge
So that's where the other
That last
3D sensing I mentioned really comes into the Laser Rangefinder
Where they're sending out individual collimated
Lazarbeam
Out into the environment
And indirectly measuring
How many nanoseconds have passed
Before that that beam of light
Comes back
Anatomically do that with approximately no 64 or 32 beams all at the same time
Laser rangefinders lidar systems
They have the longest range
By a wide margin
And they're really really good for outdoor use
Really really good for for self-driving cars
In particular
Ton of money
They are very expensive
AR
Stella moving parts
I didn't like those mechanical parts
Those are police
Is not very good
Fortnite
What exactly why we don't use it
Where's the time of flight camera
Is really great for night vision
That is very good on the cost
Cytosine substantially better than lidar systems
Is a little less good
For something like
Simultaneous localization and mapping
Backup
Simultaneous something something in math
Location of mapping
Is that just knowing where I am now showing up on a
That is building a map
And knowing where you are at the same time
I'm terrible at that as a person
Okay so
China flight centers are also bad at that
Good that's bad at it per say they're just a little bit less good
Because they tend to be
Slightly less
Metrically accurate the exact distances that they measure or a little bit less good
Then something like a structured light system or or laser range
For the kind of application Lighthouse uses it for its purpose
Because now it gives us great night vision gives us a really good cost performance
And we're not actually moving around in the environment trying to build up a map where sitting stationary
In the corner of your room trying to understand is that your kid is that your dog what it what is happening
Got it so I won't put it on a Roomba
Exactly exciting possible
News
USA Auto
Caveat the heck out of this then the next generation iPhone
Have 3D
Sensing and it to recognize people's faces as part of their
Your password
So since you're an expert on
3D sensing
I figured I'd ask you about that
Like I said
Decent use case what
That's in a battery powered device
I feel like there's a lot of constraints
Possibilities here what do you think
Totally
Answer for my battery point of view
That's totally fine because they're only running it once in a rare while when you go to unlock
You're screening rightly
Now you're basically
Obviously had no like actual inside information about what's happening there in like I'm only speculating here but like if I were using it
I would only be like
Running at that Center once in a while
Battery usage point of view
Not that big a deal
Probably only run that when the accelerometer says Hey the phone is moving like somebody just pick me up
Okay run the three sensor once every seconds or something rather than 30 frames
So I can actually
Add some crazy knowledge to
Cuz I
Technology that Qualcomm is built
It is a
Tiny little sensor on a chip that's basically can Detective
Face
What's computer vision Auto module
Did Reds it sub to milliwatts
Power so. Is low power consumption in all it's going to do is
Hey
A person is looking directly at me
And then it's going to say
Wake up good sensor
Now measure the face
So perfect
The right thing to do
If you were to hold a printed out
No paper like
Somebody's face you have a picture of it you held it in front of the camera like that one would say hey I see a face
Nf3 sensor turns on
Edit measures it and it says this looks awfully slaps
I think I will not unlock this
Yes
Very cool
Okay
So in this case
It's not waking up very long so we
Worry less about battery
It is tracking
Presumably we all have different depths
From our nose and
Is that what
It's measuring
It would also be measuring that
Very likely and at that range you would probably get
Depending on the details of their sensor you would probably get pretty good structural information
About that person's face
And I know you could use like nice that wanted to work with my sunglasses are on and I kind of things they like you wouldn't be able to use ever
Everything about it you're different hairstyles
Could using their
But you could certainly look at like
Yeah what is the distance of like the tip of the nose to like the tip of the chin there's something like that
That kind of technique
An analog about technique has been used in pure computer vision likes color cameras only actually for sometime
Is very effective
And I would imagine that kind of thing in 3D sensing would also be very attacked
Oh my gosh this is so funny so what if I like
Because I v i broken my nose
So then I'm like I would have stopped working if I have a plaster on my nose
That you'll just have to try to find out
Or plastic surgery I would have to retrain it
Can you imagine lights
Alex you have taught me a lot I love I love
Loved
Having you on the show so thank you so much
Hey thanks for having me as has been released on
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news
You can sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week