Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Edger Cohoes
Kevin tofel
And we are doing episode 190 of The Internet of Things podcast we have an awesome show for you
You working me talking about in TI's new federal
Privacy frame
Lots to
Discuss
They're my gosh
And we got some button
Is because you know today ending in y until has a brand new neural network
Stick that everyone loved the last time around seoul
We'll talk about that
Amazon
Got their new microwave out there plus we're going to be talking about
Some challenges with setting up routines and what the heck
Is happening there
Also
Buttons
Routine
Bring a button to your map a
Google
We see
Enterprise glass
Aspersion
News from Google home
We got new services on if
A brand new
Activity tracker
An update on a big funding from last week
And
Some data about iot security
Plus in
Instead of a voicemail where we help
You guys
We had one of our listeners
Help all of us
So
Yay Beyond
Look out for
That
Our Guest this week is Emily Silverman who is a
Project manager at
Denver she is in charge of their Smart City effort so we talked about things like
Oh I don't know data privacy
How to make cities smart in even data manager
Which sounds really boring but it's actually
Really essential and you will want to hear it
We also have a message from our sponsor bitdefender
Talking about
Securing
Routers
Aunt
We are now going to be on Pandora
And you'll be able to find us there if
You sign up
Or their beta version
I have instructions in the show notes for that
And so if you are a big Pandora user and want to listen to us there
Around mid-December you should be able to if you sign up for the beta
Okay that's
All the updates I have for you this week let's get on with the show with a message
Which from Mars
Sponsor
This week sponsor is
Cognizant
With Dominica
Epicenter of today's value chain delivering engaging products
And experiences
Even more important
Time is it a global leader in business and IT services
Helps companies engage
Customers by envisioning Innovative products and experience
And inventing disruptive new business model
With these inside cognizant collaborates with clients to build smart products
Disruptive strategies and new ways of engaging customers across every channel
That uses the power of iot
Learn more about cognizant iot services and solutions at cognizant.com
Flash iot
Tea
Awesome you guys
Man I feel like the last couple episodes we spent a lot of time talking about privacy
And
It looks like
Now we're actually getting
Somewhere in the legislative
World
Yay
So the ntia which is the national telecommunications infrastructure Asia
See it's part of the department
They also handle like rural Broadband in
Stuff that you like what
I don't know about the NCAA
You may have to
Because
They have been responsible for
Are coming up with some
Updated privacy
They were published
Actually in
September
In the Federal Register
Which is very good reading
Curl up with that every night
I'm glad we have lawyers
What is a journalist
Come over this stuff but recently what happened as everybody had to submit comment
And so we're seeing a lot of comments now for various agencies and organizations talking about
So it's time to dig
Basically the ntia is trying to figure out the
The administration's approach to Consumer privacy
They settled on the FTC the Federal Trade Commission
For taking care of enforcement
For this so it's not going to be an auntie a thing cuz they're already handles things like deceptive advertising
Consumer privacy and other areas
To the FTC
Bfcc by the way
Is it a common saying
Let's dig into what
Ntia thinks we should be
First step
So I like the approach that they've taken here because they got two sections where they
Highlighted about 7 privacy outcome so we know what to expect or what these
Ideas wealth APUSH
For Consumer privacy and then 8 high-level goals for federal action so we've got the outcome based
Situation here that they're outlining so what do you want to go through the Privacy outcomes first
Sure but first I want to say
Outcome-based
Best approach is really important
Because
We're dealing with an area that is so cool
Quickly changing
But we can't have something to prescriptive because it's going to become outdated weight
So I think that's a really important
Starting now to the why these will be very off a high-level generic
So they can be modified
Under certain sections in the future if things change I would think
Yeah and that you have discretion
So the agency responsible for enforcement and this is both a good thing and a bad thing it depends on who's in charge of
Discretion does
Ideally
It will
B2
Better
Boss basically that are little bit more Flex
Example of something that
Ongoing anime
So how come
Let's talk about him first step
Transparency
You should be able to understand how people collect and share your
Your data what's really noteworthy here is baseball
Specifically call out
The idea of Leslie notices
Describing a company's privacy program
Consumers initial point of interaction
The product does not lead
Adequate
That is basically a
Stabbot
Euless it is it is an we talked about this before I would like to know that before I even buy the product now.
Get into how track sleep
Make it happen
Weather going
And last week when we were taught.
I think it was last
When we had the person talk about the digital standard on the show she actually suggested that when you put something in your
Your Amazon
UC
Basic
Privacy
And kind of data sharing
Framework
Notice which I actually thought was
I like that I like that
So hey Amazon if you're listening
About that
Okay
Next up
Control
You should be able to
Exercise reasonable control over the collection use storage and desk
Disclosure of your personal info
Information that you
Provide
This is
Interesting it reminds me of when you install an app on your phone where permissions are asked
You know what you want to Grant this app permission to see your contacts
I like this type of data use your GPS Etc
I don't think
Sometimes we just say yes blindly to all those permission requests
If you're not going to use a particular function if you're not going to use location-based functions of a device
The whole device should still work except for that function that a lot of times you can't even use a device or nap unless you agree to all of them
What's up when they say control I kind of read into it that way and maybe I'm reading into it too much but that's what I like to see
Will have talked about it doesn't really get
Into
Now it does say that you should be able to rescind your permissions as well
Which is nice
So moving on a reasonable minimization
Data collection should
Deminimize
It needs to be
Weighed against the risk of privacy
Harp
So it also talks in this is tied into the next
Security
The company collecting this data needs to have
In place
So if you're going to collect the state of you as a user should expect that the company is keeping it
Secure
And that the companies Gathering it should
To take measures appropriate to the level of risk associated if you lose it
Which means if you're like an experience
Saying that
Oh well
We had a password
Are servers that has
All of your sensitive credit card Medical
Financial info
That's not good enough
Especially the password
Password
They want to see a lot more
Also in the security section may discuss securing personal data at all stages
It's not just that collection computation storage but even the transfer of raw and processed data which
Is a must in my opinion
Cuz that actually makes it a bear
Access
Correction
Is user should have access to the data that you collected on them and
They should be able to have a process to change it
Which is really important as we start talking about things like oh I don't know
Your health insurance information being collected from your Fitbit
Maybe you lost it for a day
And it's not accurate
You should be able to have a process by which
To say that
I agree I just end this is an edge case I worry about
People who made
Do nefarious things and then go back in
Scrub
Make the sound captured by a smart device when they take that nefarious thing later you know
I'm okay with
Cuz even scrubbing the data
So in the Kate like if I murdered someone and then went back in
Erase those
Sound files from my echo
They're still circumstantial evidence
Oh hey what were they doing
Yeah I wasn't going there
Management
This is
Kind of Tide with the security stuff but basically
Hey
Try not to expose people's personal data
And
Basically I don't say this because this is how they're
Pitching this
Risk management is the core of this Administration
Approach as it provides the flexibility to encourage innovation in business models and
Privacy tools while focusing on potential consumer harm and maximizing private
It's also a really hard thing to legislate
Yeah
Accountability
Organization should be accountable both internally and externally
For collecting and using personal information
A-Team
Also if you
Collect data you need to make sure that your third party
Companies that have access
Better service provider
They are also accountable for the use
That one's yeah because then we just had this many times in the show Once the data is
Casino
Original company doesn't really have any control until after the fact
Third party company uses that private data
Wrongly
Sure you can shut them down and shut down access but they still have all that old data at this is a really tricky situation
It is although I think it does encourage people to be a little bit more circumspect about who their share data with in the first place
It's right Yep this is basically a scribe
Hopefully penalties to the improper use of
Which right now there aren't really
It's unclear exactly what these penalties would be the F2
DC that's the power to fine people that has the power to censure them doesn't
Have
Lck
Those were the Privacy outcomes
Let's talk about
High-level goals
So these are again
Big picture they want
They want to harmonize the regulatory lives
Skip that makes sense
Not a lot of lies they want legal Clarity while maintaining the
Flexibility
What about that
Comprehensive application
Eniac
Addressing
Super privacy should apply to
Do all private
That is nice
Because right now the only legislation that
We have it a federal level it was an attempt is legislation that
Applied only to government contractors
It was more about
And that was kind of like
Everyone must play
Play Risk and outcome based approach
That could come back and bite us olbia
As consumers it may not be the most consumer-friendly
That'll be an Aries
I don't want to watch
Interoperability
Time is very excited about it
So when I first read this I kind of thought interoperability in terms of like
Platform is talking to each other and so on but it's not so much that it's just a step back saying we realize that
Two events
No smart devices and all these new
Services are coming out based on personal data you know they are based on personal data so we don't want to cut down and make it difficult for
Play services
We still have to make sure the personal data is
Protected so it's
And they're saying we should
Sika reduce friction placed on data flows better developing a landscape landscape
Trademarks
Around the world that the United States participates in and so on so I think this is kind of like just a high-level thing saying no
We got to be carefully balanced
Privacy risks
It's versus stifling Innovation we don't want to do that
And
It would stifle innovation
If there was like
Our rules were really different from like
Gdpr
Yes
They also call for incentivizing privacy research
Yay money
For privacy reason
FTC enforcement we talked about that
And scalability
Administration should ensure that the proverbial
Sticks used to incentivize drunk
Consumer privacy outcomes are deployed in
Portion to the scale and scope of the information an organization is
Mishandling
So small businesses that don't have a lot of information
They probably shouldn't be the big targets
So basically
Facebook Google
Experian
OU big toes
Target on your back
If you don't behave
So
So far feedback has been
Mostly like hey the ftc's good for this
Privacy watchdog
Good with a lot of things
In aggregate
Question the small print
Flexibility so those are where you're going to see the vice and then the
Yunnan libertarian
Anti-privacy people are like
This goes too far
So we'll keep an eye on that
She is in December and February holding their own hearings on privacy
So we're going to be hearing a lot more
It was a lot about private
At least you guys didn't have to read through it
Yeah they should
Federal Register
Oh yeah
All right that's why we are
Okay
Let's talk about body
That's because this is why
Cheapest kind of popped up out of nowhere but it's
I don't say it's an old story but it's an old
Yeah I don't know
So back in January 2013 there was an advisory so back in 2013 it was an advisory released
Explaining a critical flaw in affected routers from Big names fraud, Sue Cisco tp-link
D-Link Netcare u.s. robotics or there's an opening for you
And it turns out that last week
That
Issue was looked into again at netlab 360 that researchers that look into these exploits and such
It's still around
And apparently is taking control of about 100000 different home and small office routers from that range of menu
Bashers I don't know why I was never fixed I guess
Didn't seem an issue at the time I don't know
It all
Revolves around universal plug and play
Here's the thing most people
In-the-know don't use UPnP or Universal plug-and-play they disable it whenever possible
Problem is there are still some Modern services and devices that require UPnP
I think I'm almost positive but the Chromecast still does
Chromecast
Requires up
Exactly the problem is with UPnP you're pretty much opening up your network to always be scan
Scanning for other UPnP type devices so just
So we just work so that's great from a user experience standpoint but it's
Terrible from a security standpoint
Yes
In fact
If you search for Chromecast and
UPnP you get all these things
Please help me use my Chromecast
UPnP
And fortunately Google says
Yeah I know
If you do have UPnP enabled and you have one of these Spartan 16 models of routers
Leaving Atlanta 360 has a list of them you should check to see if there's a router update or it
Patch available
I would agree with you on that I know routers can get expensive and all that but yeah I would agree
All right
Those are big
Let's talk about neural networks
Intel has a new one it's based on the movie Diaz
Chip Caray
Several years ago now
They launched one of these a year ago and it was
Huge
Hit people loved it it basically gives you
AI Computing capabilities
Edge device
Some people
Optimind drones and other things just to start like
Creating these new models
This version is
A hundred bucks
It's a bit more powerful and
You know same functionality
I expect this to sell very well
Community info
Developers who are trying
Figure out how to bring AI to the edge
So check that out
Yeah just a little USB stick
Plug into your computer
Apparently
Which that makes sense to me but I don't think you know everyday consumers going to rush out and say I want to make my drone smart let me go get this is going to be for
People who are kind of tinkering and making devices which many which
Are built on you know some piece of Linux
This is definitely
I would say
Professional Developers
Paper streamers
Nerds of the world
All right
Amazon
So much Amazon stock
Basilisk
They have their voice controlled microwave now available 6
Starbucks
Call Amazon's digital assistant
Cook baked potato in poof
It happens
This is not
To make your life easier
Because you think everyone talks about this microwave in there like
Okay I still have to get up
And put the thing in the microwave
And like that is not
Help that this is providing
Voice Control in this is providing all the thinking behind the scenes
Thanks for setting the time
Time to roast a baked potato
In the microwave
Or to make pop
It's almost late and I know we talked about this
Prayer because we both have one it's almost like the smarts of a June oven
Shrunken down into a microwave and with a voice
Control to access those smart as opposed to with the June we have a keypad in some other weekend use matinee to preheat
And also available as the Fire TV recast
Which is the
Antenna it's kind of like a personal Arrow
Remember that
It allows you to get digital TV signals and record it
Which over-the-air
DTV over-the-air over-the-air
I'm excited about that actually because I can't get over there television on
So I have to either buy it from
Play Swerve maybe this device will finally work
Who knows finally help me
I've had so many antennas
Just nothing
And also
You can add devices to
A room
Using your voice and
Microwave the recast in this voice
Adding devices via voice capability all of this was announced in September
With the Amazons gigantic
Very difficult cover
Very cool
So
Devices which
Use
React
Madame a Connect
Kit
They will
Actually
You can
Plug those devices in or
Just basically give those devices
The power they're going to
Fire up
And they're going to be able to
Locate themselves on your Wi-Fi
Work if Amazon has your Wi-Fi credentials
They will connect and then your Madame a device
She's going to say
Hey I see a smart plug
What would you like to call it
To be like I'd like to call the kitchen
And it'll be like
Would you like to put it in a room
How do you say yes please put in the kitchen
And all of that is done via
Awesome
That's all I'm making a setup experience easier the plug-and-play in a sense having itself discover
And then adding the room by voice and it does not get any easier than that no app needed
And that's why
When all this
Just came out in September and I
Talked about this being like apple like in its Simplicity and I think this is a big
Huge
Step four
Amazon
In
Identifying the problems with a smart home
Solving it
And I can't describe the big trend for next year which is the normalization in mainstream
Smart Home
So
Moving on
Amazon also announced
This is actually a new announcement
An actual happening
Routines will not work with the echo buttons
So if you have one of those Echo buttons that
Timeout I think last year in basically
Sounds like you could use some to play games and
Nobody
But now you basically have a button
And you can actually do this using after other things
Now you can have it a little bit part usually with Amazon
And you
Take one of these buttons
When you press it it
Movie time
Or whatever
I did not buy one of the buttons but now I swear to wish I did because there are times when I want to fire up a routine and don't want to go into an
And or don't want to speak aloud because maybe every sleeping or something so just having fun
My next to me
How awesome would it be to have a party time button
That you just have in your house and you're just like
Guys
I just got a promotion
What what
I think that would be like
Awesome if you have small kids and they come home with a Great Raid on their paper
I mean
Play seriously mention
And that this would be
Kind of meat for the disabled
Or people who have
Service dogs
Because dogs
Press the button
Which I was like
Wow
Okay but now we have to have a little bit of real talk about Amazon routine
Here Comes
It is not good
I can't control anything with Amazon return
There are no devices
Right just before the show
Stacy had me double check
Alipay app
And going to routines
And there's not a band there for devices
My couldn't find any devices that would work with a routine and then you only found one
So
This aspect would be semi automation but
There's nothing there and I have a lot like I wanted to cuz we had had it
Question last week about
Cameras
And
Bringing in
Emotion detection
Or something like that
Right
So I did
And I
It feels like I have
3 different cameras on there I have the wise cam I have the August doorbell Cam and I have
Oh gosh Arlo's
All tied in there and none of them
Internet scams won't be
Nest camera API so I'm like
I guess ring maybe is supportive and I just don't happen to have a ring cam right now so
Yeah I'm not understanding it either
Dispensary
Very odd to have that devices tab under routines and then nothing showing up when things that you work with
Padme
Just keeping that up there
You know we'll keep back on
What's on my Google
Google Glass
Enterprise Beach
Me to Kevin what has happened there
Will last year there were some
Lakes rivers Etc of Google
Creating a new Google Glass for the Enterprise
We never really heard much of anything since
However this week
The
Second gen Google Glass Enterprise Edition
Got through the FCC certifications
So it's a real product cuz they tested it
And
Can't really say what the specs are I mean we have some leak specs from last year that still include a camera
Intel atom chip and apparently 32
K-Cup storage wood
I'm not sure why you would want that so but specs aside
There is I think I market for Google Glass in the answer
Surprise
Target I see it all the time heads-up displays are
Huge when I go to these Industrial
So yes
Yeah I mean I wonder if you could kind of do some of the same things from a contextual notification standpoint like maybe
You need to get an alert that
Production line for is down or there is
An issue something is heating up maybe a smartwatch would do it but
I kind of like
The fact that you could just
Panda Pop up in front of your eye
Left about
That and it's more about fixing or repairing
Pairing
So these people aren't wearing them all the time
On the factory line it's more like you put them on or an engineer puts them on to go diagnose
Deal with a piece of equipment
So
That and that makes sense
Sure sure I suspect that
AR goggles and glasses will take the place of that beat
Pause the Google Glass
Screen
Low-res and small
Looking up product information and
Justin
Justin okay alright
Google Glass heads up to
Sure
Yes alright let's move on to the Google home
2.7
No I have not received the version of Google home to 7 on my
But the folks at 9 to 5 Google took the Android version and kind of pecans I do this often
And they say among all the different improvements are coming
They see a lot of Google Wi-Fi settings
Being listed in your not used yet
But basically a bunch of
Strings that are suggesting that you'll be
Configuring your changing your Google Wi-Fi stop
In the Google home app
And I have mixed emotions about that I wrote a post
The earlier this week about it saying is it time for a Google home and Google Wi-Fi to merge
Super Muscle perspective it almost sounds like that's happening
I'm not a fan of it because
Google just make the Google home at much more simple with the last release
Yes
And it was so white
It is nice and fat guy finally after 2 weeks 2 weeks after you I got it on my Lenovo smart
You can see all of your Google home devices and all its wonderful
But I don't want my Wi-Fi
Crap cluttering up all the hats
The flipside is from a hardware perspective
I think it makes a lot of sense
And I'm not saying
But that's what Google is doing
I'm thinking about it I'd like to see a color higher-end Google home
Product that includes
MiFi
Mesh capabilities
I want less boxes and things in my house always have been already there but it just makes sense to
Combine the two in my opinion
I would like to see Google simplify I would have liked
To see Wi-Fi and home all be one
One place but you know that may never happen
But
Let's move on to
Quick
Ready here we go
If
New service
SpongeBob
One of them I care deeply about
Salty
The rest
I'm kind of like a lot of them are actually International
So we got
Link smart home we've got Mitsubishi electric remote cloud
But you do
Home environment
Airtouch
Other thermostat stuff
There's the roost leak detector
Which I don't know if you guys remember Roost they do
Smart smoke detector batteries they all have to leave
Are the Logitech Circle cam is now in there
We have a dutch
Grocer that I'm not even a try
Jews and we also have a German grocer
In South Asia Asia and Oceania
They have
Japan's number-one business chat
That work
And
There's the Sun
Take control
Connect to
So I don't
Summer and then
In India they've added base with
Which is a
Fun way to manage your money
I don't know if it's like a venmo for India but
By the way
So all of these Services now on if
Looking good for them
Also in the exciting bits
Call them that helped
Fitness
Wellness Health and Wellness smart devices
They have a new
Tracker the pulse HR which
Looks remarkably a lot like a Fitbit
This $130
I actually I'm kind of a little tempted by it I'll be honest I had to pull sway back in
14 or something and
I thought I did a really good job at track heart rate steps
Other stuff
It integrates with a Majors like apples Health you can
Pull it into MyFitnessPal and some other
Services out there
I kind of hate to get up all my Fitbit data but I might
Sleep monitoring and up to 20 days on a single charge which is amazing
Thank you Kevin for pointing that out
All right
Last week we talked about view which was a smart Windows company that raised 1.1 billion dollars
Now this week we know why they raised so much
I talked to them
And they are
Basically going to
To try to
Because all of their Windows have a microcontroller
And a network
They decided that they will be the
Platform
From which to smartify your office
You may recall that they're letting companies out there that way
Parking sensor company
Deplatformed
Your office building
So it's
Sure
Go4it
Smart windows
Sure
Their argument is they come in very early in the bill process
So you can
Can tie into their system
Very quickly and easily
During the design phase before all these other
Chanced
The bid for the biz
So the first product is part of this
This is going to be a
Security thing that detects
Window breaks
So instead of using glass break detection
Which is an auditory sensor
Kind of thing
They're actually if you break one of their Windows it interrupts their electric current
Changes the ions in the glass to make it darker or lighter
And they know automatically
Because
EBay slippers
So that's the first service
Hopefully I heard flying into the window does not
Yeah
Although I feel bad for the birds
Okay
That's got a grim note there
Let's talk about Enterprise
Coyotes
Security
There's data out there from a company called digicert that hired a
Group out of Dallas
S2
Survey 700 organizations
Five countries those companies had to have done some iot
Option one of the big challenges in any idea.
Is people are worried about
Security
And
The survey found
That there's definitely an upper tier
They are focused on
Iot security and making sure devices they bring in R6
Secure that they follow best practice
In those companies only a third of them had any sort of
Security breach
During the time frame of the survey
In the bottom half
The companies that aren't doing anything
They
Some sort of security data breach
So you know
That makes sense
They also said that
Those in the bottom
They all had an incident
They were more than six times as likely to experience 10 iot based denial-of-service attack
More than six times as likely to experience
Unauthorized access to iot devices
And 4.5 times as likely to experience iot based malware or ransomware
Those
That had those
Issues
They found those issues
Cost at least 34 million in the last
S2
Years
And that's just of the surveyed companies
That is ridiculous
Don't be a bottom to your
Company B a top-tier company
And most of that is in monetary damages but some of that is like reputational.
And stock price
So some of that is
Tangible
I can I just say I was
Extremely scared when I read the very first line of this survey
It's four words
Machines are taking over
Start out very
Yeah
Just a bit
And they're going to cost you money and be insecure
So we'll link to that survey so you can Panic on your
And now
We will move
What I'm going to say is like one of my favorite things so far
I've ever had in the iot podcast hotline which is somebody telling us
What we should do
Which
I'm sure all of you guys are now.
This is a good win from less
So
This is for everyone out there who is looking for
Outdoor
Camera and try to figure out how to turn
Actually if it has a USB cord
This might apply to a lot of people looking for out
Stuff so
Take it away less
Hi this is less I've got a reverse
Question you have
People calling app
Kabob House
Security cameras outside
And the Dilemma is having
Power them
Some have built-in batteries
Some charge
USB device
I've actually put
A webcam outside
Used a
Battery pack that you use
Charge your phone
To be able to remotely
Charge my device
When the battery runs low
I just bring the
Battery pack in and recharge that
Save me having to take down
Security camera
Just hope that it helps
Thanks so much
Spy
Okay
That was awesome
Les and you and
Kevin and I are looking at this
We went and looked for ruggedized battery packs
Kevin hasson
Look for an IP 66-65 rating on those and Kevin has some tips on
How big that battery should
Yeah I mean granted these are typically used for phones and they'll charge a phone you know $10,000 I have one my Charter phone
Six seven times
I think that's the minimum you want to go with for something like this
Granted
The most juice
From that battery pack is going to use when the wireless camera is streaming
So if you don't have continuous streaming
It will be using power much power all the time for Ruth's Chris motion detection such it won't be so bad but you probably are
I don't know
I'm thinking a couple days you might be stretched out to a week
With only battery packs if you go for something with maybe 20-25 thousand milliamps
That might be a stretch but
You'll have to swap them out pretty quick
But it's an option is and it's one I hadn't thought of so I was
Plated and when you get the bigger bricks
You're going to pay a much larger price so
10000 milliamps
Sprout highly ruggedized battery
Looks like you could get it for like
Below twenty bucks
If you move up to
Like 20,000 milliamps then you're looking at like 6.
So just keep that in mind
I still like
Exactly
Cheaper than Alexa
So this week's pirt podcast
Lister hotline was brought to you by Schlage
With a variety of stylish electronic locks
Choose from
Smart home start which leg and you can learn more at schlage.com
Slash
Iot
And if you want to be entered to win
A Schlage Smart Lock
Which
You should because
These are actually really good smart locks
You can call us
At 5 1/2
6 to 3
7:40
24 and leave us a message
We will be pulling our winter
30th of November for this month
So get those calls in
Before then and
Thank you SLI
Alrighty
That brings us
To the end of the News segment
Please
Stay tuned for a conversation about smart cities with
Emily Silverman who is a project manager in Denver
And
IMessage for this week sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for MS
Message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is bitdefender and I have Alex Milan who is achieved
Security researcher at the
Defender here to talk to us
All right we talked about
Cyberbullying we talk about securing your router
And now
Let's talk about smart devices and security regulation
Smart devices are
Fun small new
And no one really wants to think about all the dangers associated
Manufacturers
Sapphires North
There a lot of third-party entities that have started to regulate the internet
Do we really need this
What year
Basic standards need to be imposed
To make sure that
Because
Device
Having very bad
In August
Devices were hot
Bicycle
Passwords
Are some basic
80 practices that can be applied
We strongly believe that
That's going to make
Manufacturers
Have some babies
Mosto
Are iot manufacturers doing enough
How to make their products
We
Unfortunately
Then five or 6%.
What is synonyms of manufacturers
Why do smart devices need secure
Fall because they
Most of them don't have any
Indication
I love this point in time
Packers
Will hack
That's you
Much more on a plane
These undefended
And can a security device or a service
Protect all the smart devices in my
If it's a good
I hate to say that we launched
Sometime ago
What currently providing
Fiction book
So we have to get back to the station
Nanjing
That doesn't have many many many
And where can I buy listeners go to find out more
About bitdefender
Simply tubidy.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
What is Emily Silverman
Who is the Denver Smart City
Program
Manager
Hello Emily how are you doing today
I'm great how are you
I am
Super
Excited to talk to you
Let's just get started with
Talk to us
About what you're doing
Related to making Denver
Into a smarter City
To be like
Think that
In order for Denver to be a smart
City we have
To empower not only city workers
But residents
Businesses and even those who come to Denver
To get the best information
To make this a safe
Healthy place
For all
How do you define I mean that sounded almost like a definition of the
But how do you know when a city is released
What is second
Take me through it
So what we're doing is we are really
Progressively embracing
But I'm going to emphasize that aggressively because of
We see this as a real paradigm shift
And we want to do it in a thoughtful manner so we're testing
New and better ways
To deploy technology
This idea of creating two way communication between smart devices and using data to improve services
Search for residence
Businesses in Austin visitors
When I think of what it really boils down to
It's the idea of using data to make our city better and what does that mean
Cities already have really intelligent people who are doing great
Things on a daily basis
How do we add value
To those efforts
Such a specific surround air quality
Congestion
And then ask people are driving
Extrude
And what does that do
That helps us get people to
To where they need to be faster it helps us really understand the house
Love our kids
I'm making sure that we get them
School and where they need to be
To be on those ladders of opportunity
Thrift they can really achieve everything that they want
Those are big and
Pretty awesome goals
So
It's very easy to say hey this is what we're after
It's a lot harder to actually Implement something that
Make even some of those things
Breakdown how Denver is due
You and your team
How are you at
This problem
Yeah so we were really galvanized by
Three main things and then I really wanted to
Talk with you about what our strategy is
From a higher level in that week
Dive into details to
The three items that
Really got us energized around smart cities and the value that it
Bring
The people that we serve more among mayor Hancock
Efforts around p
Peak Academy
Which is this really Innovative program
Using lean Six Sigma process
Improvement
But saying
Every person who worked at the city
Is an expert in
Something
How did they get empowered
To make the best decisions improve prophecies
To deliver the services in a manner that really helps
The resident
Who need it most
An example that mayor Hancock uses is really looking at efficiency for examples with
Food stamps are the Department of Motor Vehicle to reduce wait time
Any chance between when somebody comes in and needs a 30 service and that service
Delivered the second catalyst
Is that we were a finalist
The US Department of Transportation smart cities
Challenge only one of seven finalists we saw the value of working
Together because it was
Cross-functional teams among departments that really put together that apple
Haitian anniversary thing we're great strategic partnership
That we have
Not only with our existing partners with an attack
Technology space
But also with Partners such a
Panasonic
Amazon North American headquarters to a transit-oriented
Development within the City and County of Denver
We also took a look
At what smart city did
Cuz as you mentioned it means
So many things
Some people for us we really wanted to understand that this is an emerging industry one thing I think about is it
We want to work with people who know how to work on complex
Projects
I don't necessarily call themselves
Experts in a smart City space
Because we're all learning it
Together and she will eat it if we did a very
Tactical strategy
Existing funding that worked on from Africa
Three major departments
Including the mayor's office and then technology services
Does the Department of Public Health and environment
And Public Works
And then we try to work
Together to develop
Some additional funding mechanisms and we wanted to really test
Some of the
Technology
And look at what it was
Shazam be able to think so
So how do we do this what we started looking at a living life
Contact so what we did is we wanted to focus in on
Specific Geographic areas
I didn't really start
Use cases
Integra Technologies
In the field and a safe and secure manner in order to really understand what works
And the last thing that we did over all of this
Build a really strong internal governance
So that people at every level both were empowered to do work following after mayor Hancock
Lead with Peak Academy was still getting direction to make sure that we're all part of what really makes the
The City and County of Denver both work and
Continue to improve
Okay so what is your job and all
So I think we are almost as if we're a startup within the City and County of Denver
We really have is entrepreneurial lens
And so I think I wear lots of
Making sure that everybody has
What they need
Able to remove barriers from specific projects
And then
Doing the organizational ties
To make sure that we're all working
Words with the same goals and utilizing our best assets
In the ice
Ctd information and communication technology
Space so that we're really growing
Together
Okay so
Since you guys have created this system
I'm really curious how if I were in your
Department of Public
Healthfirst
How I might go
Talk to you guys about creating an air quality monitor
We actually went through this about a year ago so the partnership started about 18
So how we organized our program was amongst Florida
Portfolio
And we purposely have names that really about delivering value rather than
Kind of a typical program and Department
One of the portfolios is
Healthy people and places and that portfolio manager was in
The Department of Public Health and environment
But his Focus really was in electric
Vacation he had a colleague
Who was interested in is an air quality expert and had a great idea this happened to coincide with the blind
That happened last year that was
The first round
And so he brought
This gentleman who had a great idea to the implementation team and our implementation team is kind of that mid-level
Group of Representatives
From the
Apartments
So the gentleman
6 Michael Court
They started talking about this idea he had about real-time hyperlocal air quality data
And getting that information into the hands of parents and teachers and nurses
So the team really looked at the effort force of impact
What are current projects were and could we add value to even his idea where he was
And so we were able to push that forward to our Executives and our executive steering committee and they were
Really interested
So we all worked at
Together bonjour
The umbrella of
A challenge for the Bloomberg mayor
And submitted application
And we're one of 35
Cities who were awarded that proposal
And so
To give you a little bit more specific what we did is we help support some of the work here
He was doing as part of a team
He really focused
Doing user-centered design so working with the principles and the teachers and the students
To say what type of information
What help you understand what air quality
Even is
And understanding that as it released
2 for example stop idling
An example is I have a friend
Who is child ghost
School downtown where we do have some congestion
And she would like
Additional information.
Understand what days are good or bad for her son's practice
In addition we know the air quality isn't just a local problem it doesn't stop at a border so we need to really work
How we do this region Elite
Really move the needle in a positive direction
Hey we're going to move on to Regional stuff
Moment but first
Can you
Give me a sense of the
Procurement process
This is it just like he had an idea
And then he started talking to you guys and then y'all supported in throughout
Getting data did you
Like how do you choose vendors and something like this what is that look
I don't think that there's a one-size-fits-all
We do have a vendor in
Partner also process form I do really
I think that there's a lot of value in creating good process
That way it doesn't just rely on me or somebody else but we start creating a system
And I really do think that we're creating in so many ways are these system of systems
What's not people and spread
Sheets were talking
And communicating in
Kind of their own forms of Silence but working
Together so if someone is interested in partnering with us for example they go to our website they fill out a form
And then we go through a very
Internal process
Do you understand do we have any active funding that we can use
Can we look at Nick future funding and try to partner with them
Palace Pacific example Don air quality
Air quality expert did some initial analysis the things that we
Really wanted to understand
We're really focused around
Are four main focuses
Mention this before but we wanted to make
Make sure and when Michael Ogletree was starting to talk with Thunders you know do we understand local
Control of data
Can we base everything or most things on Oppa
Open source node
Can we look at Federal and Industry
Standards to be
Standard space
And also are we looking interoperability
Will you look at that
About a year ago
We started realizing that we wanted to partner with a starter
Partnered with a local startup called lunar Outpost
Tuco develop ascent
It would really have this open data and
Follow what we wanted
To do in order to
Create the speakers
That's awesome
Do you get a lot of pushback from vendors on your
Things like Open Standards
Data-sharing policy
You know I think so
The terror has been some really interesting transformation even in the last year for example I know
Somebody was looking at a firm even a couple of years ago related to air quality
And it's more of an ash
And originally they really wanted to hold onto
But I think at the industry talking about how it's an emerging industry is changing so rapidly and then
People are understanding that interoperability and data sharing maybe that there's other ways
Commoditized
Beacon sites that are game for the value that is
Skate or being that experts
To help analyze the data but holding onto the data I don't think we're the only ones and realizing
That doesn't
Create a good system
That is my son
From where the industry is ice
I think that there may be all over the board but
People are understanding the value of sharing data and then understanding that there still other ways to
Create Revenue
Because Justice is still need to operate
I can't think that we're all
Here just doing work together for the betterment of people that's very important
But part of our own economic Vitality is having good businesses
Here in Denver in Colorado
Got it okay well that actually segues nicely into
A pretty big conversation that's happening right now in the Smart City space
How do you guys think about
User-data in
Privacy because
Do we really want all of this information gathered up and
Possibly used
That it's really important
Considerate and not a Xanax
What is a very basic
Foundation and Howard building
So when we are looking at about how we're going to manage data privacy
Can security issue
We think
Key components
Is maintaining ownership of our data
To be able to address of privacy answer
Security issues upfront
And directly with our city park
Understand our vendors
But we try to do is be identified the data
So we ensure that we work with are
Protocol from
National Organization
Make sure that we're compliant with cjis
HIPAA
And other standards are already out there
We're very careful with data in
Making sure that if you need for example if
Q
Are trying to understand traffic patterns
There's unique identifier
That are given to have nothing
Dude with anything that could be traced back
Two color of a car
Type of car definitely no data related
To the person in the car
A notch
Really important because from the very start there's no way to correlate
That
Specifically with
And then the last thing I just wanted
Is it what really interested in understanding and creating the business
Just want to leave any type of
Possible
PPI data at the edge
So that we're bringing in MIDI either something that has a huge
Deviation from the standard but we do that with aggregated or insights that comes
From the information
Rather than any of that data that could have PPI infer
Formation
And there's a lot of debate happening about like
Hey data that doesn't feel like it might be
Personally identifiable
Could become identifiable
Can a monitor my car if
Coke this car always comes from this direction
And holy cow we can establish a route back to
To someone's house
That is kind of crazy and out there but it is still something
And I'm glad to see that you
You guys try to be identify the data and are thinking about
Control of it
For those kind
Future cases
So ye onyame
Just to kind of follow through on the vehicle LED
So let's say I am going
3 blocks
In the same direction every day on Monday
But I'm just using this is an example right
My vehicle is
3 2 1 5
Right and maybe it's going through again we're doing some experiments around can
Connected vehicle technology
But in that one day within a 5-minute time it's 32516 the next morning I'm going in the same direction
Possibly that vehicle is
7321 and then the next
Kinda goes through an intersection with in a very short. Time
Want to imagine
Day today we need to all be responsible for the fact that we can't create the
Same information from the same users in the same way
But creating a
Pattern
It really is aggregated a higher-level to understand patterns rather than individuals
Oh that's actually really great exam
And I promise we get back to regionalism
And I'd love to do that with
Asportation cuz that's a really good example
How people actually live I may
Having experience in Denver but I might also be driving
The boulder Inn
Denver's only part of that I'm driving from the airport to Boulder Inn
Again
Denver's only part of that
So how do you think about
Expanding your program or even working with other
Groups around the state or local areas
Smarter region
Yes AC that is a really great question
Because no matter how smart or wise or intelligent Denver
Either is or will be it is
Pendant and it is
Key importance
Let me think about this regionally
Just as I was talking about how air quality doesn't know the
Boundaries
I don't care whether it during
Denver
Boulder
Or all of the borders that we share with
Many cities and so
What we really are doing
Is creating and being a part of other Partnerships as well
So two examples are the Colorado smart cities Alliance
Which was formed by Denver south economic
Partnership
I think currently there's oversee
Team cities around the state that are involved in this Alliance
And it's not just an alliance with cities but it's also with
University and private partners
There was a recent Announcement by Arrow Electronics and in partnership with AECOM
They're working on
What time does Regional
So we can all work
Together with they also are really helping with that information share
And then another really important organization
That I wanted to talk about with our Denver Regional Council of governments
So that is our local Municipal planning organization
They are involved in many efforts
But I really looking at this
Smart Regional
And then we're working with them
What ideas could we have where we're learning from other cities
Even things that they're doing in the region and then maybe there's things that we're doing for example in the
Connected vehicle or open architecture space that they can learn from us
So we're not saying This Is Us
The standard this is information that we can all work on
And then hopefully with those two organization
We can really build on some
Regional in
Statewide
Who calls
That we can use and really learn from each other
Not to share that information but grow with each
Ellie the sounds great so
Can you give me
One project that you guys are Maybe
Most proud of or maybe it's just simply that is most complete
So thanks for asking Stacy I am really excited about what we're doing
Around our living lab that we have on Federal Boulevard
The Federal Boulevard
Is
Really
Important
Way for people to get to their homes into businesses
In an area is
Well where we have some of our most
Spirit a health outcome
Even around are
Air quality and what we really realizes is by focusing in on this area
We can really help understand
What are the various things that we can do either small steps are big stuff
2 mm
Prove the experience of living
Working and being around Federal Boulevard
So specific UK sweetheart is around emerging
NC vehicle preemption
And our vehicles and station 12 which is it
26th and federal there are
Two major fire trucks
And then there a chief has an SUV
And when there's an emergency
Re-Use
System
That emits a series of Lights
To do preamp
So that means
For many of us
When a vehicle
Pecans we don't actually
Really know where it's coming from and we're using the sights and sound to try to figure out where they are and then the light often
Quickly changes for them
That's needed for tourism
Just wanted to clear traffic out of the way and then it helps them get through to where they need
What we are really using is this new connected vehicle technology
Call dsrc which is dedicated shortwave communication
Directly
Communicate with the signals
Signal the signal
This is really important
Because they often turn off whether it's based on traffic or other things
In two other roads and so we want to make sure that they're able
Keto signal by signal and get the right information that they need
A really key component
Is actually the
Two-way communication that this new technology will alpha
So what they'll be able to do if they'll actually be able to see the signal information
How many more seconds until it turns green
And other information
Directly back into their vehicles which will help them make better decisions
In addition by the signal the signal changes what that'll do is it it will hopefully disrupt the network left
So that means
Sometimes when an emergency vehicle comes through like a fire truck it can take hours
Florida
People to get back
To the normal pattern of the road
Until we think that there's going to be a faster turnaround time
Between when an emergency happens and when people can continue
To go where they need to go
In a manner that deficient
And also safe
Awesome
Anything to get me out of trash
All right we'll Emily thanks so much for coming on the show this
I really appreciate
Thank you for having me Stacy that's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week