Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacy
And this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
And today we have an amazing show for you
We're going to talk about
Some more things that we've noticed living with it a new integration and
A way to get a free Google
We're also have some industrial iot news with zebra
Launching a new
Really awesome Logistics
We're to talk about virtual beacons and why they matter
We got a bunch of smart home data coming out from
Providers that we
Talk about
Fancy fancy lights for the city of Channel
Security holes in Tyson
And a bunch of smaller news that's going to be super fun including
A possible
Cure for snoring
Dot-dot-dot
Do you have
Samsung
Artic and after that we're going to have our guests who is Simon
Vulgar
Who is going to talk about smart labs and how The Internet of Things is affecting
R&D
Before that let me do a quick
Message from
Another sponsor this week
Hey this week sponsor is me
I'm going to tell you that if you want to advertise on the Internet of Things podcast you should email Andrew at
Iot podcast. Com or if you wanted to know more about the internet of things you can sign up for
For My Weekly Newsletter at Stacey on iot. Calm it's not the same size
After we talked about on the show
But there is a lot less Kevin
Okay Kevin
Let's get
Started
Let's talk about
Google home
But first off
I guess I am a contractor working a Google not on Google home or anything coyote related so funny opinions
Are my own and I'll even disclose I don't own a Google home
Doesn't yet meet my needs
I'm just flattered
Okay well last week's big news was like
That's very honest
Okay
So last week's big news was that Google added
11 partners
For its Smart Home
Integrations not all of them are live yet
But many of them are including Kevin's favorite hope which is be
And almost with that that integration almost got me to buy one
To be honest
See so I'm going to say that that integration
Plus
A new one that they announced a little later in the week but after
The podcast app
The Logitech
Harmony Hub
Which is
Integrates basically your television
If you're not chromecasting
It's always hats
Comcast but it does have great
This adds
The Logitech Harmony Hub
To your Google home
That plus the wink
Means that this week I am putting it downstairs putting the Google home downstairs in the Amazon Echo that
House with downstairs
This is going up into my daughter's room
I will say Logitech for its Google home integration
Does something a little different
So you don't actually add it from the
Apps on the phone
The home app
Instead you say Okay g ask Harmony to
Connect
And then what's supposed to happen
When is the Google Assistant
Will display a
Hard in the Google home
You launch the app
You tap discover and then link
You're going to sign in using your Logitech
Harmony account
Information
And then you get the option
You'll see all your activities
Activities
Watch Netflix
Turn on television
All of those and you actually get to name them
I was just going to say I was actually hang out with some people at Google the other day talking about Google home
And the common theme is
That when they
Use the hot word
Their phones also start listening and kind of hoses things up so does that
Still happen for you
Multiple tries
It does say specifically it says turn to your Google home
And say this
It maybe I wasn't
Like I did eventually get right up in his face and leave my phone away
Run to the phone
What happened was it kept opening
My phone and my phone is like
Because it has to be
It has to be done through the assistant or the unturned through Google home and sell the can be done through the phone
Right
Because you need the phone
Your first instinct is going to be like I'll bring my phone with me
Because I'm going to
But you're better off putting your phone in another room
Standing with the Google home
Say What You Need to Say
This is my Pro tip for you
Start stringify is another app that does
The integration this way and I see Mrs indicatives
Kind of skills versus
Native support
I would kindergarten
Yeah because of that the Integrations the native Integrations all take place in the
Home app in the settings
Carrier getting off a Google Now card essentially so
There's some other
Mechanism or interface involved I tend to agree with you it's probably not a native thing is probably a skills types
Cards thing
Yeah
Once it's done
It's awesome
And because I feel that Google home is a better listener than the echo I'm actually really excited about tearing the
Google home has been in
My master bathroom
Which is actually worked out really well cuz what I'm showering I
You think then from a hardware perspective the microphone array
Works better for you with Google home in post for the echo
Worlds
Google home is a better listener
And it's a
More accurate like gives you better results
Right right I think it passed into a much broader database of information
How much is one of the things I don't like about the echo
Having a lot of questions
I can ask my phone
I use Google assistant on
Similar to home
And I get better results
What with Google assistant so I can I get that and if it listens better maybe maybe your smile
It listens better and it's more flexible in its
Command structure
From a natural language processing
Json
I don't know so
After this week will I'll come back with the
The definitive
And the Logitech Harmony
Hub
I think it was $99 a month
99.
And that does not include any of the remotes your phone becomes your remote or in our case we use our same remote sandwich
We just use
So basically I spent $99
To have voice
Right
Obviously it works with Logitech remotes are they required or could one person just say I'm just going to add voice
Voice to my TV through Google home
So I only spent $90 on the Hub
How comes with a little IR Blaster so
And that has to be out
Right so basically if you want to change channels or not that you can do that all by voice
I can bring up the program
A channel that I
I want and I can say
Turn on Disney
But I can't
Volume up and volume down
For my system
Do not work some people systems it will work
Gotcha
How to depend on your TV Hardware in Sun
So my activities that I use
Is our turn on Netflix
Turn on television
Turn off entertainment center
The default settings so
Amazon Prime
And the reason I'm asking about this is because we get older TV through the internet
We don't use the smart TV apps built into our TV we use a Fire TV
And what are use a Nvidia Shield TV in my office
So it's all
App-based
TV and channels and I'm not curious how that would work maybe I have to
Create presets and such
Okay and the other is Kevin you pointed out to me
If the Google home sounds
Interesting to
New smartphone
You can get both of those
Well without paying for the Google home and I don't
I don't know that we talked about this before we don't talk about smartphones
210e
Can you tell Whitney level detail here with
The LG G6 actually got my attention when it launched in February and it's still
I believe it's available for Verizon customers in the US now and everywhere else it's pre-order through the carriers
An LG will be selling a unlocked version
If you like in the future
This was
One of the first smartphones to be almost all display the top and bottom bezels are mostly on the Galaxy S8
Actually has even smaller bezels so whatever
Depends on what you want
But the nice thing is LG not the carriers but LG is giving people a free Google home if you buy
Buy a G6 smartphone
And I
Look at this because it's a pretty nice phone and I can get a free Google home
The deal is when you purchase your phone you had to do so between March 17th
Which is already passed out asleep and Sunday April 30th service there are still plenty of time to pre-order in-store purchase
Ag6 and qualify for this promotion
I mean to submit through LG through May 15th or by May 15th
They will send you a free Google home
Which is $129 value so
I don't know $650 for that smartphone on my carrier
Free Google home
Some of the new Innovations Maybe
Maybe I don't want to put it but maybe
Will you have
Foreca
Hi dive two dots are tap and an echo
Yeah I'm tapped out
I just don't know where
I would have to do what you're doing like swap it with
It's something I swap out in that go and put you know
There's no room right now that needs more listening
Do you have one in your bath
No I don't
I'm telling you it's going to be
The amount of time that I'm in the bathroom in a given day is literally
.1% of my day
Showering
Doing
I guess you don't do
Do your hair and makeup
Not so much I'm not on camera anymore
I work from home and I don't
Yeah I'm in sweatpants right now though I have not yet showered this morning so again
It might not be the best place
I'll tell you what I'll find a place I'll find a home for Google home
If
I do take advantage of this G6 free offer I'm on the fence I might do it
Am I heading wink really went a long way
Yeah well
But but but we should say just before the show we realize this
We realize that
Even though the wink integration is there in Google home
It does not work with locks neither your lock nor my luck
Are showing up there
Right
So both of us have our locks
Cubs
Right
They are not on there neither is the MyQ garage door
Which is something else I have in
Isn't surprising my guess is there's probably some security
Same security issues that
Echo had
But it's actually a little weird because
The echo right now I can ask that
Garage door unlocked
And it will say
Yes
It'll check the state of the locks absolutely and you can still lock lock
Walks through
The echo
And you can unlock
Yet with the echo
You cannot unlock
Those locks you can unlock the
August
Right and that requires like a pin
To make sure it's you
Yes
So that is the current status status
Fancy we went
Let us move
Two more Industrial
Specs
Welcome back
But I think this is actually
Pretty freaking cool
Zebra
Which is a
Gosh they are
What do they do
They were big in RFID and NFC
Kind of
Helping
Big companies handle Logistics and transport
Retail operation
National Sports business that
Tracks
Football and soccer players
Yeah they have failed a lot
A really cool
Iot Staffing they've been doing it before
Since before i t i o t was
They have a new
King Anu
Product for the transportation Logistics business it's called the smart Pack trailer
And
It's basically a tiny little 3D sensor / camera that you
Pop in the top of a a trailer
Tractor trailer truck bed
Basically check the status of
Whatever is in that truck
Which is
Really cool and it
If they've also packaged analytics on top of this
So this camera
Obviously sees things but then it can also be like
Hey
This is how fast is getting loaded
Fishing it is
Come up with your own metrics I believe
I work with them on that
I don't know I think this is like super cool
Oh it's it's a brilliant use of the technology I mean you know it's all about speed and efficiency when you're transporting matter
Orioles and
They're talking about
The hardware This Afternoon lyrics
Can determine
Like things like volumetric efficiency load rate when a load is near completion
I want to load is about to be freed up so that the new load can begin I mean
Again it's all about as you said Logistics and I think it's a brilliant application
And it also works with other people's grpc
Enterprise resource planning systems so like your sap
Software
This is actually so
I remember watching a video about the port of Hamburg
In Germany
And it was really fascinated like a giant essay
Case study
But
What it does is basically
Because it's so small
The
Companies that are the trucks that are taking the containers away
They have to
Like basically state park outside of the
And what happens is as below zar
Getting
It's like as they're getting ready to
Finish a load basically they're like already notifying that trailer
There is
Trailer guy
To be like all right
Start your engines
Come on in and so it's like
Instant you know like
This guy drives away this guy pulls
It's all fancy
You know again this is a case study so I'm sure it
They should be only the perfect things
But
The stuff is actually really cool it reduces like idling time which has Allah
Fishing
You're a small port with no
Please put things are if you got a small loading dock this is really cool
I would agree and just think
Taking it to the next level
There's a lot of work being done on
Autonomous tractor trailer driving
And when you start pairing these two things together you're going to have even more efficiency so it's really really interesting
Course that may get to like oh how long till people stop
I don't know
The robots are coming to take a stickler jobs
I can't take it podcast
Bruker
Oh I don't know Kevin we probably could be easily replaced by robots
Somebody smarter than me yes I agree with that
Also on the industrial side and this is what the industrial and Enterprise
I don't know
We really want to get into
But this is
This is about beacons I was a Bluetooth World last week and they were little estimate beacons just everywhere
I was reminded
How inefficient
I think pékin
Because the battery powered
Stuck in gear places people
Boobs
But
A company called missed that I have written about before
And I think we may have talked about
They have come up with
A
Technology that lets you do virtual bee
So what it is it software that you
Put on your Wi-Fi access Play
Points
I think you have to buy the
Hardware for them
You get this image overlay of your offices basic
And then you take it
And you can like
Establish virtual beacons silver virtual Bluetooth beacons basically using their technology
You're like oh I want one by the bathroom so I can see
How many people are using their phones on the toilet
You probably should not do
But
You can see how many people are in the bathroom
Could even tell you that you need more bathroom facilities
7 yes
This is
So but
Companies are actually using this for things like wayfinding so you can put these virtual beacons
Along the long hallway
Beard
University of Stanford University is actually using it
And
They're also using it in warehouses
4like Logistics efforts to like
Track where people are getting gummed up
You can even use it for asset tracking if you put sensors on like machinery
So if you put a Bluetooth sensor module on like a big robot that you love
You can always know where that robot is
By creating like this Forest a virtual begins around it as opposed to the physical begins
I've Loved missed four
Yeah I think cell most common sense
To actually move the
Beacon technology into existing
It Network infrastructure because
8 more flexible
Can use theoretically devices you already have
Bekins nothing is estimate and all the pain now the others can make the physical beacons
But just
Having
Piece of Hardware that's dedicated to just basically Bluetooth signals
I just doesn't make sense to me
You know what in terms of cost and efficiency and so on so I love this idea
Mist
That's the company
It's pretty cool
All right
Smart home data
We in the last week or two
Both came out at the same time
Yes Euro put out
Report called a peek inside the connected home
Put out some data about devices
So let's start with
Eero
Because
What I felt like it was a little bit more
One thing it was only five pages versus 33
Thanks wink
It is device-specific so we're heroes are
Definitely
Few people who bought it for
Can I hear
A lot of that
And they're probably upper-upper income
So with that in mind though
The Eero guy said hey
There's an average of 10 device Types on Eero Network
Now that's not number of devices that's device types
The top one
Are iPhones than iPad Spotify Sonos
Then Android
Then Apple TV
The nest
MacBook Pros HP printers
Candles in Amazon echos
So that's actually surprised since
25 + 6 million
Sowell represent
Well yeah
I'm not surprised too but it's interesting that they're considering
Phones and tablets traditional Computing devices as
Separate device types
Chris Wright
You know like an iPhone an Android device
Likely phones
Obviously iPhone isn't Android devices will likely at a phone
South butt
There is value in knowing
What type of
Sonos
Stowe
Data about
Sonos
Crazy 25% of all Eero Network
Have Sonos
That actually makes sense to me because I consider Sonos it's a great product
I considered a higher-end product in terms of pricing
In its category
And so is the year of a kind of just fits
It does
So maybe
Maybe Sonos and Eero should get together and
And do a little
Imesh WiFi
So
Was someone has
Connected devices
Sunny single net
I kind of think that's an awful
Either that or that's somebody
That does this for a living
Does IRT type stuff for a living
I don't know
Cuz
I will I will tell you that my Eero
My network
Which has a lot of crazy stuff
So I've got 32 online but many of my computers and phones are not running around
Right now
That's probably the most
Anything else jump out at you from the Eero stuff
So much for the Eero stuff I we talked about the wink
Edits
Here Wego 2.3 million products are connected to the
Link platform
Yeah that's a lot
Cuz I only have
Yeah I think I have about 2:12 or 12
What else
This is interesting and we're kind of
Scratching their heads over the definition of this but it says weeks has the 27% of Americans which is overseas
66 million Americans
I purchase a connected product for their home
Smith sounds like a high percentage
But there's a question of is it is it actual people or is it household and
What's a connected product
Kira was including
I don't know
Big number I just wish they would
Explain to have expunged little bit more yeah because Forrester put out data in 2016 saying that only 6%
At homes
Bought
Household salary house
And so
These numbers feel
Wildly
But again
And they have 20% of households with
Household income under 50000
Purchased a connected product
This a few minutes but
I can't say it enough
Making your Home Smart does not need to cost that much money
That was the other big take
Json
Kevin Nutella
Let me let me scroll down the 33 page
Wink ask people how much they think it would cost to turn your home into a smart home and 34% of American and said
About $5,000 or more
Still seems kind of high but whatever
9% of Americans
$20,000 and I have to assume that either a
They're not really
Conscious of the
Inexpensive products are out there or be
They really want to go with a hardwired system which will certainly add cost
Yes maybe maybe they called it a Crestron
Chris Savant dealer was like
Hey
I want Nathan myhrvold house
Interlinc
Here you go that's my thoughts
I will tell you guys though that I spent about $9,000 on
In my house
Granted I am an edge case really weird
Ahead of the curve trying lots of different things I'm not surprised at
I would think
I didn't add it up but I gotta believe I spent
Less than $1,000
Beasley
Yeah cuz most hubs cost about a hundred
Connect to thermostat you can L buy it
At 154 my lock
So we're closing in on a thousand but then you end but the rest of the products are all
$40 switches
$15 light bulbs
It's not like I'm a hundred light bulbs are connected in my house if I have 6 or 8 Maybe
I was like the light bulbs Canada
I've spent
Probably 300
My motion like
Motion sense putting motion sensing in my utility room in my closet
And my
Hold on
I'm counting light bulbs
$3,600
Automate 3
Sa36
That's better
That's better I'm not crazy
Did the nice thing is
With that there's there's a ranger product then it doesn't matter what platform product you choose you got to choose what's best for you
No matter what you choose
You know you can get started for
Like I said a hundred bucks
You can just add some switches are light bulbs for you know anywhere from 15 to $40
Apopka
Sapulpa
Switch whenever
You can get started and add-on
Very simple and very cheap
Oh hey by the way
I should tell you
That you can buy
All of April
That's what I have
Although
Since there is a
SEC privacy
Keep that in mind but if you like to ecobee3 with sensor you can buy it for $200
And it's homekit
That's a random little note there
Okay moving on
Little bits of news
Fun things
August has a
Pro
Lock
This is a Z-Wave based
August lock
This is for professional installers is called a Smart Lock
Lock Pro
It is only available to August Pro members and those are people who sell the security dealers and integrators who do custom homes
Does anybody know why
It's
Kind of
It's not something you can't buy you have to get it through a security distributor
Probably because it's
I don't know maybe
I mean I have a Z-Wave lock
I do too
Installed it I bought it at Lowes
I'm guessing they want to push more people to
There are more money
Well I imagine
Oh I mean on the installation
Regardless of the product
The Mindy Project has a price yes but then you're going to pay for installer
Well so and I will say actually cuz this just happen
The news
Security protocol actually went live
And so now everything that is Z-Wave has to follow the Z-Wave
S2 security
And that happened as of this weekend
I think it's April 2nd
So
It's probably a security thing if I'm doing a custom install in a client wants an August lock and probably go to be like look I can't man
App for you
Because it's Wi-Fi and that's that's too far gone but
A lot of these they can manage
To Rahab
Does that mean that
As the weather gets more secure
We will have less products that you can purchase and install yourself
I hope not cuz that would be very bad thing for Z-Wave in my opinion
Yeah I wouldn't I wouldn't sweat
The security is more retroactive
Holy crap people are hacking everything
Yeah
Oh I should also say I've been saying August uses Wi-Fi
It doesn't it uses Bluetooth
It has Wi-Fi capabilities like if you wanted to talk to your Google home or the echo
You have to have
Abridge
Basically have an August connect
I know
I know I meant I'm inside Bridge
I know your aunt
Sorry
Tyson
Titans
Security holes
Will this is not good
Take on Samsung particular because every platform is
Constantly under
Threat of
Malware and other
Issues
Butts
This is not good so
Tyson is the iot platform that Samsung uses a platform that use variety I should say for the LG devices such as SmartThings
I believe so yes
That's the plan
I'll bet they're smart TVs for example of do their watches do
They're they're connected watches and such
In any case
So an article came out
That's a researcher in Israel discovered
Kaizen
That would
Yeah 40 that would allow hackers
Remote access to the millions of tizen device
Around the world
This is an actual quote
From the researcher
Talk about Tyson
It may be the worst code I've ever seen
Everything everything you can do wrong there they do it
Yikes
Yasso
Happily Samsung has reached out to the researcher and said we're going to work with you on your findings and close these holes and so on
Haven't heard anything more official from Samsung that is so
All I'm going to say is if you're using tizen at all just keep an eye on things because this information
Wildin
Doesn't mean you're being hacked or exploited
Opportunity certainly there
Yes and I should know that the vulnerabilities allow hackers to take control of a tizen device
Remotely
Superbad which is super bad cuz a lot of a lot of iot stuff is actually
You need physical access to hack it or you need to be within a few
Of the device
On the same network
That's not great news for tizen
But let's move on I have found
A fantastic
Be interesting
Product it's called Nora
And you can fight it at smartnora.com
What it does is it to text snoring and then it inflates your pillow
So your head position change
Presumably
Stop snore
I just going to come out to you guys I snore
My husband will
Always tell me about it he actually has earplugs and is a very sad man because I
I do snore so I'm looking at this it's $279
Which feels like a lot of money
But but it's a smart
Pillows with a sensor that you put on your nightstand and listens for snoring
Brook Soso
I like the prices too bad
Well yeah that actually stops
Snoring there is a pek
There is a pebble thing the pebble thing is what listens for
The snoring and there is a
Case
Apparently holds the other apparatus
People seem to like it
So I may just
See how this works
A little bit though on the website whenever someone purchases it
You see Rachel from Sugarland
Just purchased one of these
DC Stacy
From Austin just purchased
Yeah
Adding to that $9,000 bill
You can use this with any pillow I thought they ask at a specific pillow but now it's that you put the sum
Module underneath
The pillow that you use
Yeah it looks like
It kind of looks like my
Ice packs
Yeah yeah yeah
It's a little air pump AC
Interesting to me
I will not buy to talk and I'll tell you I ate I don't
Which is good
My wife and I we invested in the
Sleep Number beds a couple years back
And we got
The kind that you can actually
Raise or lower your head in your feet and such
And it uses air pump to inflate
The mattress to your suite number whatever
It's very similar technology this is just automatic on the pillow specifically
Yeah there's a 60-day satisfaction
Brad in Winston-Salem
Chess purchase
Way to go grad
There's like a telephone
I might buy one.
The shout-out to Brad who will no longer snore thanks to Nora
This is what I'm going to
I will test this out
Spy Carly
It seems like it's a good
Lattice 60-day money-back guarantee I mean if it's if it's terrible
It's Jeremy in Tempe
Arizona desert
And one final bit of news
Because
AT&T
They got a contract
About what is they got the contract for the First Responders system that
We have been waiting for since 911
Nationwide
16 years in the making
Now it's going to maybe start
Interested in is
Contract with B
Maxwell Air Force Base to bring the internet of things to base operations
Which means that they are going to
First off create a proof-of-concept
It will demonstrate smart parameters gate monitoring notifications
Weight management all partes making
You know Air Force bases more
I have many questions
Stop this and I am going to ask AT&T or maybe Maxwell Air face
Air Force Base
To talk about this because
It scares the bejesus outta me
Put sensors on our Air Force Base given the security problems
We have been happy
This is going to kill a major plot device for many
Many movies
Having well monitored
Perimeters on our bases that aren't just like
You know barbed wire
And maybe a century
And I'm thinking this because in stranger things
They had to sneak into an Arab
Air Force
It wasn't
And they were able to do so which helped Advance the plot and then to
I am currently watching the Americans and
FaZe nikan Twitter
Actually it may not be
A some sort of
Bass and
By golly they just
Right
So I'm overly distressed
I understand that I'm curious
Weather beijing today for like
Keep monitoring and such
You know probably
Isabel Madre
So what yeah yeah
Sitting
Then we don't know the scope of this yet
But I mean they could be
RFID swipe cards and such don't know yet
I'll be curious to see what they're using what the hell they're going to smartify base
Okay and as we are closing at the show the information just published
Lovely little story
That talks about
Google's new hardware
How to take on the Amazon Echo
The information is saying that
Google
Well combined their Google home intelligent speaker device with a mesh WiFi
Router such as
Wi-Fi Google Wi-Fi
Time the name
So
Basically this makes a lot of sense
Unless
This makes a lot of sense if you keep your router's Etc out
And I see a lot of
People considering making everything from light switches to speakers into Wi-Fi
This is not crazy
B almonds
3 actually is
It works
They actually have all the Smart Home
Hubstaff
The Browder itself
So
Basically sticking a speaker in your router
Yeah
It does make sense I'm going to look at it. I added a Google Wi-Fi unit
To the
Onhub that I previously purchased
I even thought about adding another Google Wi-Fi unit to expand the network further
It would just make sense of those could double
You know as
Intelligent assistance in sonder already in several rooms
If you can have a mesh Network right you're going to
Have these things in multiple rooms so maybe make sense
Boxes
More ports
Yay
That's our new theme
Okay
Well we have talked enough
Let us move
To a message from our sponsor and then
To Our Guest
Who is going to talk about how iot
Changes R&D everyone we are interrupting the podcast with a message from
Our sponsor
And I have Mark Wright director of product management
At Samsung
Arctic from the very beginning
I have heard much about Samsung artik module Hardware side and also on the cloud side
Can you just give me a quick overview.
Put the salt
Together for me Arctic is an antonym platform that integrates modules with security at pre-pro
Grand the connectivity so that they have secure transport
Into a cloud
So where we can virtualize products
We can then store data from those products
Control products manage those products
And then
It's also wrapped
In an API first design methodology so people can
Then also write strong apps
For those products
And also do connections
Two other services and other clouds
Okay so this sounds a lot like something bit manufacturers might be interested in
Systems integrators and I heard you say security a couple times so I'd love for you to talk to me
About what's unique
Cheer on Arctic
We have an end-to-end platform
For manufacturers
Systems integrators
To use in creating product iot connect
Good products but as We Know
You know from many of the reports and
Even things that are going on in the world right now security is top-of-mind
Sweetfields platform development
That's the best place to put
Security think it through at the beginning
And
Been implemented
And what we've implemented for security is a best-in-class methodology known as AAA security
It's Authentication
Authorization
And the ability to audit
So what we do there is we authenticate
The user and a device
So that falls into the module offering that we have right and in the software we have for that software for
Onboarding
The end product
We
Them secure the transport into the cloud
So the second thing we offer is authorization
So what authorization is
Is the user that utilizing this product
Do they have the proper role are they authorized to do what they are trying to
What to do and we use certificate-based Authentication
For that process and then we have the ability to audit what has happened in addition to security what are the other benefit
Fits of having an end-to-end
Tell the benefits of an end-to-end platform
Are that when a manufacturer is looking at
Building a thing to be iot connected
It's a change in their business
Generally for a manufacturer
There's the electronics there's the software there's the product
But now on top of that they have taken
Consider RF design they have to consider protocol they have to consider cloud
We also have to consider
Mobile app development
And each of these
Are additional software development efforts that they have to do on top of their normal product developer
So utilizing an end-to-end platform
Simplify stock
And gives them single SDK
To find out more about Samsung artik Cloud
Go2www
Dot art
Dot IO
Slash
Build vs. Buy
That's www
. artik
Dot IO
Slash build
Vs Buy
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your hope Stacey Higginbotham
Today's guest is Simon Bomgaars who is the co-founder and CEO of a
Gitlab
Hi Simon how are you doing
Hello sexy I'm good how are you
I am excellent
So we have you
Voting in all the way from Germany
And we're here to talk about what the Smart Lab of the future is in
What we're talking about is basically how people do research
And University labs and bio pharmaceutical Labs or maybe it's just pharmaceutical labs and biology labs
There's a real
Potential
Iot to change kind of
The way research is done in the lives of
People doing the research
So Simon
Why don't you lay it out for me
What is the lab
The future
If you
Singapore
Have a look at the house today looks like they to get the traffic looks like
And guess you have to to see that that's a lot of manual work involved still so
And there's some apps that I cried
Automated already for example in English pharmaceutical production so I'm like the production of a dragon
We're closing Research Laboratories is kind of what of handwork
Hand cross
That that's going on there so
Is it 79 in the state of transition everything is going to be getting more digital
Devices instruments in the laboratory getting more intelligent and connected to other
Assassin in platforms
This is beta Chi also look like in any area in recession chemistry
Biotech
And the evening and dos
Many workers still happening lots of process will be at the alternator to end it would be easy for people
Set up stay where I used to do
Mendeley
And then just let the wrong and let the black run for its also by the kitchen ultimate eating time
Experiments and Tiny bits of data research
So if for example I was I don't know preparing tissue samples by hand
I might have to
Scrapy
Beat it something and then
You know I'm a little pipettes dropping things in
200 x across my samples and then sticking them somewhere and letting it grow so
That's where the thing
There's been Machinery like machine advances in the last couple
Full of yourself
Automated some of that
It's the truth but this was all this kind of like Island solution so that they robbed a kind of
Only liking able to do with 1 pound of Travis's like one
Giacometti
Entire process
That's being changed
It's transforming into that eating dose electrostatics that you are not automated
Before also can be automated
Very easy way meaning of it will be always like kind of manual steps in between but you will be able to
Flexibly combined different steps that you did she have to do in a laboratory. When mixing something
Using device to device I am adding some substance substance p
And we can combine these steps and
Get this into a much more automated workflow
So how does this change
Science like how science is
Of course it will be a huge change in X update on if that's going to to be produced at 6
Going to the generator because
Like alternating the workflow is not only one side and you will also be like
That it would be awesome by July 7th
Analyze
Buy instruments
Flow back to the tuna to the researcher
So that's that his task will be more
Really analyzing them then they sat and then actually generating it so now I would say
The time research has bands in the lab doing experiments using his hands
Shaking the reagent tubes
That model S 60 to 70%
This will be in the future. Maybe only 10% or 20% of his time
The rest of this time will be more on the side of analyzing the data going really index
There was a chance of data crunching
I'm finding more details
Happy overlooked before because the data was not that
Stan's and not that affect quality and it's it's becoming to automated data generation
Wow okay so then how does that change the skills needed
A scientist
Become a scientist
I had four really boring repetitive work but
So what
Do you need to know
I guess some people will read it misses a day today at work
I think I still think it's it's a good skill to to have to to know what's really going on in lap so because of
Comedian stand for
But yeah you're right I mean it will be more like you'd like to discuss a recession
The future is like not really analyzing data and being a prostitute
Connect data from different sources to make the available or not
Another way that they do it right now
It would be more in front of the computer
Standing in the laptop
Okay it what does this mean for sciences that involve going out into
The real world for part of the time I'm thinking of like you nobody your geology year
I don't know the people go check to Antarctica to pull up by scores of the world
How does that change
Their jobs
Out in the world
What is just out going upstairs now much more material
Toys R Us to Manchester
Do something
Video of selling animals in the wild Zora digging in the soil or something
Something at Aeropostale has been not saying she would not be done by robots in the future so that's something that's it
What is the Subspace for adventure Inn in research
Okay
What about it
Let's think about
We talked about kind of skills as a scientist does this mean they'll spend less time overall in the lab cuz I think about
The Graduate students in their lives are like
Pretty awful in Subway
Nazareth are married to their lives in
Trying to
Perform experiments does that change things
Well yeah I think so but nothing else it's so it's right I mean I can experience it
I was wondering why I still have to dissect to some insects and like each other mind some plans and
Lisa plants something
Aquatic exercise to get some basic skills
In the lab to see what's really going on to it to really understand how some things work and then I
But at the same time I think.
Time the people
Spans
On
I think it's going to be much more important in the future
All right
In what about obstacles to making all of this worked
Because you mentioned earlier that tanks were essentially siloed and now things are kind of coming together a little bit more
How is that happening are people
Killik scientist build so much of their own stuff
Their budget constraint
Really smart
How old is come about
I think actually in comparison to other areas the lab environment
Snow in Byram
It's also why it because lost it
Builds for for for ages like ability to endure
I mean the depreciation time for for Terry devices at 15 years old
Everyone with being in the lab most attended a lot of all the equipment around in this
All the cooking going to be able to connect Xfinity software iot
So this is definitely an obstacle that you have a lot of older cooking the wrong and yeah you're right I mean
Like ideas DIY people and then blockable their own stuff so
But it's just getting more and more tools available so that people can actually connect
What day does to other environments
Proprietary system software problem that's the steel manufacturers out there that think that
They can build their own solution that the best applications for fall for devices and epidemiology is only going to stay with
I don't think
Laboratory equipment
Now you guys created that folder is actually a company that helps bring together disparate parts of the lab so can you tell me a little
If it's not hardware-based
Can you think of software
Softworks
Can you tell me just a little bit
What you're doing there
We started to build a electronic lock
Replace the paper that people
Used to like that they don't
On Lake Valley today.
Why do they turn into PhD accessibility office
But we soon realized that building an addition
I don't like this
Piece of the entire workflow
But in reality it's reader
The car off the entire left environment because of connect so my sister.
Center of data is collected or being at the store
But also the center where baby kitten experiments are planned
So
Flexing after having that we we should get that people also want to have a
Repository to Saudi
Standard procedures
Stand By the Sea one thing led to the other and now we're
Yes I'm kind of splat for Mrs because of the operating system for Laboratory
Being able to connect to devices and receive data from devices
So that's basically
Throw it away.
If we were
Science is right now dealing with a replication
Were they just can't reproduce the experiments
The same way that they had in the past
And
I'm very curious how it is having this level of granular data and
More objective data
Well
Maybe help solve this problem
Yes sir I I really think so because
This application
Already too much data from too many different sauces around
Pieper electric problems managing this situation
Cancel data
Just needs to the possibility that people can treat that a tire or only showed those results that they
Infected area hypothesis
And I really think that's giving people a platform
So that a tattoo to reading manage their research data
And also do this and that in the easy and transparent way
Reedy house
To change the mindset the Plex on the TV can collect data and combination within within two alike with it with an
Environment
Either they have two EZ shouted
They actually are the most straightforward way to just solving two-step problem
All right
Thank you Simon
And I am so glad we had this
Yes me too
Well that's it for another episode of The Internet of Things podcast please join us next week
When we have another amazing show for you and if in the meantime you are hankering for some iot news
Sign up for my newsletter it Stacey on iot. Com
Thanks for listening