Podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have an awesome show for you today
UCM already singing
We're going to be talking about a brand new smart home company
Resideo
They just went public this week
So we're talking about that
Russell talking about the death of the Smart Home
How to get a lot of feedback on this but without debatable death
The debatable.
IRobot is going to share your room but data with
We've got some security flaws to talk about and we're going to talk about the death of beacons
What happened there
Microsoft has a vision for the smart campus we've talked a little bit about it
I thought we're going to talk some more about it today
And
We have our guest this week
Is Alexandra deschamps Encino who has a brand new book about the Smart Home
Actually really good
And where to talk to her about servant Dynamics
Women in the Smart Home
And
Why we're currently at this weird impasse where
Nothing works together and we hate
But it is
This is a Downriver show death death and Hate
It is a bit of a crib
Episode but
As always we will Shepherd you through
The care and cents
Tiffany and I'm sure
We also are going to hear from our sponsor
Bitdefender
Brand new sponsor this week
Yeah but the fender and
Are other sponsor
Let's hear from the now
This week sponsor is cognate
Sent with demanding customers at the center of today's value chain delivering engaging products and experiences
It's even more important in business and IT services helps companies engage customers
My envisioning Innovative products and service
Or inventing disruptive new business models with these insights cognizant collaborates with clients
To build smart products
Disruptive strategies and new ways and engaging customers across every channel that use the power of iot
Learn more about cognizant Scioto services and solutions at cognizant
/ coyote
Cake heaven
I am excited
I am super excited about this news because resideo
What is the name of
Honeywell Smart Home
Security spin-off
And it's actually going to be based in Austin
Which is where I now live
Yay
It is
Honeywell over a year ago and now it said it was going to spin off some of its businesses to
Streamline this is
A popular thing that happens
Every I don't know decade or so
Get really big and then everything and
It goes on and
Sperry fun
This time Honeywell is doing the resideo spinoff
It will be based in
In Austin
And it joins alarm.com control
Scott is not
Public so it's going to become one of the Smart Home
Security publicly traded companies out there
In I think this is kind of interesting
Because it ties to something else you wrote
Kevin which is
About the death of the Smart Home
And I think there's a couple big themes
It's the debatable.
If I look at this the macro picture is
We have set the stage for the smart
Home in the sense that
People are interested in
Their understanding that they can provide
Greater security.
Which is why I think a lot of these companies are doing
Pretty well or
Thinking they will do pretty well
But I also think it's still way too complex for normal
Which is where we're getting things
Dislike
The Professional Services in isps getting
To descend actually
A company called kaylex which
I Used to Know
Decades ago when it
Fiber and isps
Those guys actually launch day
Smart home Gateway
That will be sold through is
Spews and has Amazons
Madam a inside of it
Remember you guys met him a is what we
We call Amazon's digital assistants so as not to set off
Assistance
And this is actually it's all part of this larger theme wear
DIY feels almost dead
And let's talk
I know I said this was about hubs but it relates Kevin you want to
Can I talk about the death
The Hub debatable yeah yeah I'll talk about that
To clarify. Make sure for my own
Information the Presidio
Business that's more focused on like consumer residential type where is Honeywell still doing like industrial things
They are I do think it's weird that they
Facebook that often
I thought there's a
God help me
Synergies
It could be had
No actually I think it's a good idea because of those synergies I mean from a technology standpoint
There are obvious synergies there but yet the implementation standpoint are very different between industrial and consumer
I think it's
A good idea
Okay well there you go and I'm thinking not industrial I'm taking more Enterprise
Christ-like
That's where
The health and safety those kind of things that
Honeywell is so good at both on the residential and Enterprise side
I think it'll be sad
Will Sable send me that just went public so we'll find out in the future
But getting back to Hubs and I understand I'm probably going to get a lot of negative feedback
From the die-hard readers that have had hubs
For years and years you know we had
Maybe they had
Extend stuff go in an insteon hubs and so on and so forth
And trust me I didn't like writing this because I don't want to admit
Defeat but I am admitting defeat to a point
It seems to me like the hubs of today that we talked about over the past few years say your Samsung SmartThings or wink
Many others that are out there that people are using
Hyundai people I mean listeners and readers of the site not
Norml's
Back to their home DIY that you were talking about
I think they've been
Usurped
Bye
Apple Amazon and Google
Cause
Those three are
Are focused far less on adding more radios to support things which we don't want to hear because
Ravens EP devices but these guys are focusing mainly on Bluetooth and Wi-Fi
Instead of focusing on radios
Deep focus on user interface
Moving over to
Or away from smartphones and into
Speakers for voice control as well as smart displays
And they also reached out to extend their
Integrations with
Brands
I look at some statistics as of last week Amazon says that the number of Madame a compatible devices
Tupac year to date
Two more than 20,000 devices from over 3,500 France
Google is also doing well they
I got the home holiday just introduced probably this month Google Assistant works with over 10,000 smart devices
Brands I don't think you can say the same about Samsung or wink or any of the other hubs that people that are
Our core audience might be using
So I think I'm illustrating the difference in the approach
And what's going to happen here is
Okay so the automation side of things that are missing from
The Big Trees I say the apples that Amazon's in
Google that's going to comment 3 oz Apple already has that
They got some automations that you can do with home
Get Sophie already there
I could easily see Amazon
And Google just keep building that bass apparently there's been a 50 million installed smart speakers from those two company
Nice so far in the US only
And once they keep building it up and it becomes just a matter of time y'all together in the cloud
And maybe pushing down local automations and such so
I kind of feel like the traditional smart on love is kind of dying away
I think
And it may not be dying so much as
It's just not right for the DIY
So and I would be remiss if I did not say that Amazon does have the Echo Plus
Which does have a CB radio in it
I would say that it is complicated and
I think
That ties back to the
Resideo and
Piknu
Kalyx box for isps which is
If you want crazy home automation
Really good detailed stuff you're going to get that from someone else you're going to hire that
If you are ignored
And
I think the challenge for
For those guys
Will be to establish business models that
Work for
Consumers
So the traditional business model
There's two one is
You buy all the gear and
You pay someone to put it in and then you pay them
And come back every now and
Or you
Pay fee and get all the gear
Which seems to be what you know the isps
Att's the alarm.com r28 which is
They supply all the equipment for a fixed fee
You're going to pay off that equipment
With a service contract
And the question is
Will people
Want to do that
And I think it depends on the values you get and security is still the number one value leader for
Not home automation
Yeah I'd be curious just bring it down to it less expensive
Products I'd be curious how many
Smart home webcam
Devices and companies
Actually
Turn those purchases into
Subscriptions for cloud storage of photos and such was actually really impressed so I've talked to a couple of company
Used to get numbers on their subscription services and I can't name any of them be
Because I would just be very upset with me
Me for saying this
If I named them
Ignominious
The top companies
The cloud subscriptions are above 50
50% in some cases their above
80%
Wow which is actually really
That the Hyatt at REI
Yeah
Subscription rate in those are $5 to $10 depending on the number of cameras depending on what you wanted to do
They're also not country
That's another thing to think about
Not right that they make it very easy to sign up for
Can you put this device in
In your house you get like an email
Yeah send us your credit card here like okay
In some cases you don't even have to do that
Yeah let's do it
And then every month I
In my case with Google I get an email saying hey by the way we're going to charge you this
Okay cool
I do the same with nest and Canary right now
Yeah so it's a very different model
Then
The old one
Show
I think all of these stories are interrelated
In a way that
Going into
29th
I think based on what we're seeing from Google Amazon in
An apple mostly Amazon
To be honest to me
Attaching things easier and
Voice programming easier
I think they're going to win at the DIY stuff
And these
Formal
Is formal installs with
Probably
Higher level of security more sensors
More
Baby home automation
Those guys
Are going to
Do well there but I do think I'll have to adjust their business
On the plus side something I said earlier this year is probably also wrong now if it's a
The future that were talking about
When I said hey
Smart home hubs are probably going to kill off the immigration services such as Afton stringify and so on
Maybe not let me get into the houses and people want all Nation
The service is certainly a value
Well we talked about this last week
But I saw GitHub actions remember how we talked about
That wasn't last week that was a couple weeks ago
That's kind of like
Yeah it's always been alternative
It is in Comcast bought stringify so they'll be building that into their
Again cloud-based services
So maybe we'll see if gets snapped up by
Somebody who wants to make
Life a little easier to integrate or
Maybe
Amazon
I thought I wrote something about it I just talked to you about it like a hundred times already
Yes
It isn't yes to both probably Kevin has been very consistent
He would like Amazon to buy a gift and also pink
I'm not saying a liking to I'm just saying I could see it happen I could see why it would make sense
All right
Speaking of things that
Makes sense
Or rather don't make
Let's talk about the death of
A Bluetooth Beacon
This is a really
I'm mad that I didn't write this story because I seen this coming for years and apparently there was a news Peg that got venturebeat
Write about it so
Yay venturebeat
Paying attention
That news but it was actually Google turning off
Locations nearby
In
Android
Yeah nearby notifications is gone
And most people will not miss it because
I can tell you
The only time I encounter nearby
Notifications popping up on my phone was at Bluetooth world
And I think once when I visited
If it doesn't have any Bluetooth for all you know it's dead
So basically the problem with vegans
Is actually very similar to some of the problems a smart home has
Text no
It's Halloween you guys
Goofy as all get-out
She does this all the time not just on Halloween
But I digress
Standards there were two competing standards
That's always tear
Plus battery issues
If you put a beacon somewhere
You would have to find it again later and change the batteries
In some cases
People would actually movie
It was probably more like trickster ISM or sometimes it was just a fly
You know they put it someplace else
So batteries
Things that move you don't know where they are these are actually common problems with sensors that are
Deployed in
Enterprises and even in the home I have
Low battery notices uncensor sound like
There's a couple other things to a mean
Beacons art out as being very inexpensive and relatively speaking they are
However
I think almost all the major league baseball stadiums put them in
And it's not like they just put in a few pecans
They're everywhere
When you start going
And buying up hundreds and hundreds if not thousands of deacons That Azz Up really quickly
So from that perspective a big
Location it's not exactly cheap
And second
The value you get back is really limited by something not in your control
Do the people at your Venue have their Bluetooth
I never have my Bluetooth on
And
Not only do they have to have Bluetooth on in many cases they actually have to have
That works with
Can write on
Black
Yeah there's no native
Integration with Google to try that
Buffets nearby locations in Chrome and sunset
What's the even so that
Completely out of their control
If you don't have your Bluetooth on
We just spent all that money for no
Goodbye
I have a thought
I would still love to see these Technologies weathers ibeacon or Eddystone Etc I would still love to see
CDs continue in the home because
I think they could work well for
Presence even if I had to wear a silly little Bluetooth tag on my belt or something
Why would you need that
You have your phone on you
At all times
That's not true but I don't leave again I don't leave Bluetooth on I guess I would in that case
So I think
Instead of physical because there's a lot of
Interesting plays here around virtual
So there are companies like missed that are creating
Basically they
Could access points and now that we're seeing
Bluetooth actually in Wi-Fi hubs
This is possible in other places
That's where you basically
Can
Be a software
Create
Oracle pékin
Place them in a
Room or place them in where the Wi-Fi
Knows there's a
Basically
And
While I you have presence detection you have some of the same functionality
If there were a standard for this would you be amazing then
Other
Smart home devices or Enterprise devices
Could use it in the Enterprise
You may actually
Senior Corp
Phone have something
When you're inside the
Campus so it's less of a
They're what we need their though
Is
One Bluetooth and ask
Access points possibly that standard and three
Really good mapping
Which
Good sake
Brings us to our next story
Owosso
Which is
IRobot
The makers behind Roomba
Have
Can I deal with Google where they will mine
Google's going to use the mapping data that comes off of certain Roomba Vacuum
And
Then it can establish
Accurate Maps
In a sense I can add presents
For a Roomba service you can say
Hey Google
Tell Roomba to clean
He will know where the family room is
Because it has the mapping
And Google Assistant
Target that particular room so that that's more value to the room itself
So I think that is actually that's a really good point to make because I think that is the bare minimum you have to
Tudu tudu Dada
You have to offer the user some value
And tell Google she's very smart
He said he hears about you can say go do this
But
It also allows Google to understand
What's in your
Where it is
And
It's a possibility that hey that could be either matchcrete those for
To be a way to understand
Kevin you said presents but
You know usually I leave when my
Is there so I'm not in
All of this is supposed to be opt
And it will not be used by Google's ad service
So that's that's a big plus for a lot of people like that
And Google is quoted in one of the stories that we read about the
This as
Saying this is basically
Not just a smart home but a way to create a thoughtful
It requires less information from
In Kevin and I call this context
And I do think
That's actually true so
Yay
I may have to get a room again
Victor doesn't clean up the
Crumbs to Willy's only like 3 inches tall so
Takes a long time to clean up and vacuum
Oh he could be like honey when you're in a fancy restaurant like
Get I just got the alpha of the SDK for Vector so maybe home
There you go
You do need to come
I'll look forward to that video
And could you put them in a little touch
I could do that
I could
All right so that's the
Roomba Google News
Who's and
Speaking of context
Microsoft has a vision for the smart office
Bad
They showed off in a video that
You know
I actually saw the watch
It's worth a watch to see what you can
Do eggs also kind of a UI cluster
In my opinion
But that could just be like the demonstration ask
So
In this video you swipe your employee badge again
And something in the wall
It knows where you are in the
It also can't answer it Scott
Cortana in there so it's answering
Questions about the
Hey where can I find sushi
I like oh it's in this cafeteria
Here's the menu items
Oh hey I'm here for my meeting
That ties into Outlook and you
You can send out
Boom everybody's in the meeting except you where are you
All that seems cool
That is cool and I've actually been looking at bikes Mart
Workspaces
Couple years when I was back with Google it was fun
Topix I was researching and so on what I like about this aside from those examples of a show-off
They also
Show how
Again contacts the right information at the right place and time is super important for pretty much anything in the office
Presently said we can put one of these
In the bathroom or near the bathroom
And if there is maybe a water issue it is a leak or something
You could swipe your badge
It knows where you are knows who you are
And says what can I help you with
There's a leak in this bathroom please open a trouble ticket but system would say okay got it
Trouble ticket
Assigned and opened and I know where the bathroom is I know what the problem is
And the reason they say that
It's important because
In a regular office you probably to go all the way back to your desk
To make a phone call to facilities and so on what you're more than likely going to get stop by other people on your way back to the desk you're going to be thinking about work
Things and you're not going remember to actually open the ticket
That is true in
Here's what I'd like to
Just based on that and this was again a video with
Anchor was talking to a person about
The project
Sweating your badge
Before like to exchange information
But the system
Felt like
Not a lot of work but you may not
Right so I felt like for things like notifying you of a water leak
Having a screen there
Would be really helpful
They can say hey what are they
Right or conference in progress and a lot of these screens exist
Places today
The other aspect
Abyss that I didn't love was there still a lot of things you shouldn't do.
Voice so like when it started listening
The places where I can find sushi
I was like oh my God
Stop talking
But but but it also did say for more information and it wanted you to an internal campus
App for the map and that's been using all that I would love to see
I agree
Open the app to see this
The echo a party does this Google does this
What's Google Assistant
I know that Microsoft
They're not a lot of Microsoft phones
Are there still Microsoft phones out there
But there's still some out there there's no new ones
But there are still some out
Either shoot it over my phone or have it at programmable NFC tag or something that opens the app for me or something
Yes cuz I already got a swipe
Something other than swiping
So many things
Hajj will be
My phone my NFC chip will be in my hand
Or that
But then you see this stuff
Okay
So that's Microsoft smart
Office I will also say
To me this was probably super practical but
The coolest Microsoft smartoffice demo I've ever seen
It's still the one from build
Where you walked into the conference room it had like
Cortana on this magical pyramid sitting on the
The conference room table that hand
The calls and also had eye thing
Take a camera and
Recognize who is in the room
And they were using a AI that would
Basically create
To do notes from your meeting
The conversation so if someone said okay I'm going to follow up on that
I'll check
Calendar date
Get back to you
It would actually we need that we so need that
Yeah until it breaks down and then all office product
What happens today when email or Slack
There's a lot of hanging this show
Sorry you guys
Oh and speaking of
Let's talk about security issues Kevin
Scary research say that the Google home hub is in
Sure
Google unsurprisingly is
Saints
Insecure
What's new
There's a lot of houhai about this over the past few days and it all comes from the source of a personal blog by
Jerry
Gambling
ESI Security advocate
He started nosing around
Once you got a Google home harbin
I scanned the network
And saw what I was doing and he saw a bunch of open TCP ports after about 15
5 minutes
He figured out using an
Undocumented API
That was one crew command he could reboot the Google home hub which puts it right back up in setup mode
Google home app
And I totally understand that probably should not be allowed
Insecure
All kinds of back doors and people getting information there's no information that can be gotten from resetting
The Hub
By this method
And the fact is you have to be on the same Wi-Fi network to actually exploit this
So there's an awful lot of
Parameters here that I don't think
Make this a huge issue
That's what Google was unsurprisingly saying you know
If you do reset it
Wouldn't cuz you're not loading them through
Because like resets would be bad for someone like
Those are actually on the device
Itself so that
Descanso
If you just reset this basically you're going to lose your
So somebody resets whether they unplug my Hub bore do this I mean yeah that is going to cause those kind of pro
For sure but
Again I'm like
Is it really insecurity kind of thing
Going to come from a standpoint I don't think so
Shouldn't be allowed in happen to know what's your name Google search Patchett
I just saw so many stories this weekend I know I don't have a Google home hub so I wasn't gets her to begin with
I don't think people need to be overly concerned about this
Yeah I have
The sunset
I tell people I'm like look
You got to evaluate
Ideas for what they really
Do in German
Profiling that's not something apparently most media do yet
Unfortunate
Is there some really scary things out
Hey speaking of scary other things that we
Is
What's the weather hijacking
Connected Construction
Because I feels like
I could be related to related question where you just recently in Vegas
I was
Did you know that the official City bird is a crane
That used to be the joke in Austin
I'm sorry
Why were using City jokes now anyway
Yeah so this is a very unique interesting
Security issue
Connected Construction crane made by telecrane that literally has a connections that the
Operator the crane has some assistance in terms of how to
Run this thing and
But there is an exploit
That has been documented
That is an authentication bypass by capture replay
And what happens if a Suleiman in the middle attack
And somebody could theoretically
Spoof commands to hijacker
Crane and that's really bad because that's not just like a simple reboot where nobody gets hurt that somebody could like
Demolish a building for all we know
So
Like you never know
That is an example of something that
It's unlikely but the potential harp
Is huge exactly
So
We should probably be a little bit more worried about that
Nanjing
We are so are they going to patch it
They actually have in the latest firmware telecrane has it available so construction companies can actually get it and
Betty
Transformer
Yay
So actually if you're operating a telegram
Update
Chicken wire
Firmware
Okay
And because I am on the show
Kevin is
Kind person that let's talk about chips
Because
For all of us who care so much about Edge AI
There is a
It's actually not a new chip
Company I've written about it very briefly
Before in the newsletter but this is a company doing a j i
And they're doing it
Increasingly low power
Which is awesome
It's sentient
And it has
Scored 25 million in a series B round it is led by Microsoft Amazon
Mattamy fund Intel capital
And other investors who are like
Yes please can we get low-power AI at the edge
What's cool about sentient
And there's no
Are you doing the style
Of processing called Mythic
Is they are getting their low-power by doing the computation in memory
As opposed to on
The processor
This is a fundamental change in the way
Computers
And
It's pretty exciting
We'll have to see how this works
In the real world
But it's power consumption
Is crazy low
Kevin do you remember what the
Assumption was
I don't think I mentioned the power consumption but they said that it's 8:20
Cara Operations
Yes
Which is
So yes this is a
Possibly big game-changing kind of piece of
Technology
As it with all chip stories
Kind of debate
But keep an eye on it
Cuz
We definitely need to
Okay
No
He feels like time
We're actually getting kind of roof riser
4r voicemail from the iot podcast hotline
Which by the way is brought to you by Schlage
With a variety of stylish and secure electronic lock statue
Smarter home start
Schlage
You can learn more at schlage.com Coyote
And
We have a winner this month for our door lock
Test
Let me grab that guy's name
Our winner is
Michael who is actually the person who we're taking the voicemail from this weekend
Coincidence that has now happened
And we will start the contest a new
In November so if you would like to
When a Schlage door lock
Plus Wi-Fi adapter and this is a very nice store
Please
Call
Leave us a message on the IRT
Podcast
And you will be entered to win
That number is 512
7 4
To 4
And
Now let's hear from Michael
PlayStation Kevin
This is Michael
Rochester New York
I don't know what I'm looking for exist
But I'm hoping you can help me
I have a few lifx smart bulbs
Only recently dawned on me
A place to put another ball
The laundry room by the motion sensor
This way
I don't currently have any kind
Smart Hub
I'm trying to avoid getting one is a lifx bulbs work on Wi-Fi
I tried searching for wifi-connected motionsense
But all I could find were some that are part of
Home security kit
I couldn't tell if they would work with stringify
Do you know of any Wi-Fi motion sensor
That would work with what I'm trying to
Do and if not
Which Smart Hub
Ecosystem
Will you recommend I get into
I'm also wondering if you're aware of any weather
I can use
Is whatever solution I need to go with
My laundry room
I have a couple of the lifx Plus
Bulbs in my flood light above the front door
Help with the night-vision.
Hello doorbell
Okay
It is the death of Hub having a rate
Here
So it's unclear from your voicemail Michael
If you are using
Homekit
So we decided to answer this question in two ways one
If you're using homekit we have a solution
For you and two if you're not using home
Explain
Why that may be kind of an issue for you in
Talk to you around it
Sounds like you're using stringify
If you're using homekit
What you could do is get a pumpkin motion sensor say one from fibaro
Search for the laundry room door
Typically close our door so we don't have to hear all that noise
But either one would work
And because those are Bluetooth sensors you would not need a hub
Although you technically would have a hug with homekit anyway
Could with an Apple iPad or an Apple TV regardless in the home app you can create an automation to have that work
Okay
And so evil also makes one of these sensors I'm going to add a little
Caveat there
You will want a hub in your home
Because if you doing laundry and you don't have your phone with you
It's not going to
Well it depends on how far your laundry room is
Sy what
That is
Now I will say macroview
Is a great
Great system
I actually have the exact same thing in my laundry room
And I love it
Here's where it gets complicated
It if you don't use home
You might find a Wi-Fi sensor and we did find several
But there's no way necessarily
To tell that Wi-Fi motion sensor
To turn on your lifx light
Because you don't have that
Interoperability
Lair
Which is what homework
So
In that case
You can buy a
Wi-Fi sensor
And the bad news is
There's none that are great
Police are the reviews that we've seen at least for the reviews iHome makes one there's a
A couple of no-name brands
Make one so what you're going to look for
D-Link actually has one
That works with
If you're going to look for something that works with
But if or stringify
Is a wifi-based sensor
And then
Gil Hughes after stringify to set up the
When this detects motion
Turn on lights and then you're also going to have a toggle that says
After a certain number of minutes turn off the lights
Emotions.
So keep that in my
I'm going to
Tell you
Hugh
Makes
Everything you need to do this it is a little bit expensive
But that's what I'm using in my
Laundry room and in my master bedroom
I use plain white hue light bulbs and I
Use a Hue motion sensor and I set that up inside
So that way you're not going
Whole home hub
And the Hue hub
Talk stoop
Google
Anime
And homekit
So
That would be what I would tell you to do I know it's not ideal
And then you do have a hub
So I've all those options
I feel like we've given you the tools you need to
Find the right
Do you have a preference on HUB ecosystem at all
Personally
You know the Hue ecosystem is really nice
They keep working on it
So
Now if we're talking about like
SmartThings
Or wink
Iperf
Wink
As do I
Because it's just easier to
So
Michael
I hope this helps you feel free
To let us know what you decide to go with
Curious and
Hopefully this helps anyone else out there and I will say I do love that particular interaction
Very helpful
That really
That takes us to the end of the News 7
Event for this week
And stay tuned
Our Guest Alexander Edition
Who is going to be
Really dropping some serious knowledge about building a smart home
Home design
And business
Opportunities in
What has happened
In the last
120 years and
So stay tuned for that
And now let's hear a message from our sponsor good Defender
Taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is bitdefender and I have Alex belant who is Chiefs
Security researcher
So this week we're talking about
Parental control
And bitdefender box
This is your smart home Cyrus
And as a parent
I wanted to ask you
Can technology
Parents concerns around things like
Bling
Shirts online
Yes absolutely
Think about it
Because most solutions
Tacolicious
Oriental
We've designed a component
That's going to be notified
Can parents rely
Watford
With somebody
Or when there's an exchange
Or when somebody ask
Apple
Have a conversation
Okay how does this protect my
My child
How exactly
Can technology help with
Allaying
Parents concerns
Technologies.
Will be able to monitor
Domestication to the Palace
You will have to have a
Privacy
This sounds reassuring
So where
H&R the stairs
How to find out
Absolutely they can go to
Everyone will go back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Alexandra deschamps sonsino
Alex
She is an industrial designer and the author of a brand new book
Call smarter homes
How technology will change your whole life
Hi Alex how are you doing today
I'm really well Stacey thank you for having me probably
And we've actually communicated for years you are
Add iot watch on Twitter
Product for the internet
Cash was at 2013
Good night lamp
I actually came up with in 2005 but will ignore them
I made my
First batch in 20
So and this was a great idea
This was basically
When you turned on this lamp
Somewhere else in the world to someone who has a corresponding lamp it would turn on
For them
The idea was just a
Easy way to communicate
Guess where you were in your day
Describe
Well I like to think of it as a nice way of sharing presence and availability
4 family members in a different time zone it's really nice
They're saying
Colin Moran right now
And it just opens up that space and that day-to-day routine with your family
You been doing this awhile
You have practical experience
I feel like we are war-torn individuals in a smart home
So what made you
Do this
I wanted to write a book for the longest time
And I sort of looked at the smart home space because designing the goodnight land being an industrial designer by training
Working with
Super large brands
Customers through the years as a consultant
I sort of knew a lot about the space and I thought oh well I'm sure you know I
I can do more research but someone else is booked to and I really couldn't find anything beyond a bunch of
Chiropractor
Pickle
Somehow
You know quite dry books
Networking in the house
But most of them were very old
And most of them were very very specific
And I'm a little bit of a design because well coming from industrial design and interaction design so I thought it would
Would be really interesting to look at
How often we've heard
About
What's this idea of the home of the future
Really
50s
Efficient home at the turn of the last century but we've always had to serve obsession with
And I wanted to explore that in the book
Going back through history
What has changed cuz when I take a smart home now I think
Oh internet connectivity and that's probably what most people
Or actually
If you had asked me
Probably
Six or seven years ago that's what I
What I said
And now
I feel like I would say oh well it's got to be connected to the internet but more importantly it has to have some sort of
Intuitive help
For me it has to have some sort of AI
Capabilities so it's not just
Code access to
But I'm curious what your
Take on the evolution of the efficient home
To the Smart Home
But I think that your description is pretty accurate
In the sense that
I think for both you and I are
People working in the technology space and we probably think of a smart home is being a technologically enabled home
Where is actually free to
Become a reality quote
Get a lot more people to buy something that turns their home
From what they have now which they might not think of his smart
They just think of is their home into a quote-unquote smart home and how you get someone
The face really is I think the history of every new consumer technology
So we might try to convince people to voice assistant right now
Connected thermostat
But that's because
We tried to convince people to buy
Completely you
Brand spanking new homes with loads
Things embedded in it we used to call it domotics in the 90s
Comes back to a bunch
People who met actually in the US
Something called the smart house project in 1987
And the point there was to say how it's going to be like
Even IBM got involved and has
And you could buy the retrofitting of your entire home with connectivity which
Set the timer
The web as we know it now but
Early internet aurelly technologies and early app
Applications of
New technologies for your home to make your home life better
Quote unquote
What I found
Was that actually the definition of what makes a home better is
Exactly the same definition as 50 years ago which is not
Too far away from
Years ago so
The story of how we talked about
Conductivity in the home hasn't changed
And that I was really shocked
Okay yes
And I remember going to an IBM smart home in like 2004 and they had like RFID interactions like an
Kitchen counter that would interact
Food bags in your medicine
It was crazy out there
Kind of need
Disintegrated
Which brings me to something you've written about in your book
Witches
The way that
This sort of stuff Creeps in is not the way the tech world
Tends to work
Eclipse in individually
Entire cyst
Yeah absolutely
I think there's something kind of quite fun and interesting about how
Technology Giants tend to look at the homes face as if it was a comprehensive system like Vino etcetera
A coyote
Mathematically
Ansible system of things that connect other things and somehow there's a trickle-down effect
Between the use of one thing
Intriguer other things
Because that
Systems diagram is so appealing
Mathematically and computationally
And that's how we build against the web but it's really not how we build
Tom making and how we operate and think about our homes most of us
Want to
Turn the key in the morning to leave for work and not think about the house forever more
But somehow we are
You know meant to be buying
Products that will make us think about the home all the time
Notifications all the time about the home space
Which we were kind of hoping we're just leave behind and get on with our day and
Go see your friends or go out or whatever it is
But now we have this kind of needy child
It's part of a larger system that includes our location
You have this
Square systems affect that's being created for us that I don't think is really that appealing
I think it's also a weird thing to want to
Get people to do which is to just change their lifestyle from one day to the next
Because
Technology
Change your life
Lifestyle even when it's just
Baez sterilizer
Eat your vegetables in the shape of spaghetti it's a lifestyle change
For those of you guys who are into the zoodles are
Bikini noodles
So I think every purchase is a leap of faith and
To think that an average
Normal household
Who have you know so many other fish to fry they've got jobs to keep they've got families Health to come
Kind of tend to
Did they suddenly want a whole bunch of
Complex interdependence interactions with their home
I think is really
Strange
That actually is true
Feel like a couple weeks ago there were a couple articles out
Talked about this
Backlash in this idea that the whole movie
Neurotic so somebody wrote about their
Connected doorbell and they were like you know
Every now and then I get these
Notifications and they say something happened outside my home
Can I freaked out and then I'm like
Eventually this person took it out cuz they were like
I don't want these nuts
Location
Very astute
So where can technology
Actually help
Improve our life
Still work with it
Existing
I guess systems are what we think we
But I think that there
Key and core
Marketplaces for smart
Technology
Trying
New technologies the most around me and this is anecdotal
It's always been you parrot
New parents who are supportive
Completely
You know I'm taken aback by the task
Skip and a new task at hand of raising a small child and
Suddenly Annie
Time that you can shave off of even switching the lights on is a welcome
Intrusion in a sentence and so I do think that
For some people these applications
Useful
It's just they're not useful at scale that I think most
Large companies would be happy with because apart from home computers mobile phones
Large appliances we share almost nothing of our home life
We don't have the same
Furniture we don't
The same decorations you know we don't share the same
Comings and goings and so we can't buy
Unmask
The same things
Yes we'll probably all by you
The usual toilet paper ends
Instant coffee or something but
That's actually rare
And so I think that there is
Going to be very nice uses for
Specific products to
Make our lives easier to a degree but I also think that we probably have
Comcast
The point where we do want to make our lives
Home easier
I think we want our lives
Outside of home to be easier especially women especially in 2018
And I think that there is
An interesting dynamic
For companies to think about
The think about what
Women's lives
Because women tend to be the audience for smart home devices and what their needs
Because actually remote access might be something that you really want but
Not necessarily for the doorbell
Might be for something else entirely so thinking laterally and think
Thinking outside of the
The helm box is it where I think is really
The next job for large companies
OC and I'm thinking about you know hey I would love for it to be easier to buy my toilet paper and that's where things like you know
Amazon has the dash buttons
Are some interesting Fifth Element
Things out their ideas that have been tried Target try to program
Carfax
You had like
Connected soap dispensers and I think I connected toilet paper roll actually
It would
Put this in your home
Connected to the internet
And when it
Became low you could set it to automatic
Reorder things
People didn't trust it
Betch didn't even make all of its money that
I think there's also something
Sunny
About
Treating the home in this is something that comes back to early 1900s sort of ear I would just treating the home
The factory floor
Like things have to be
Fulfilled like you are you know
Buying new materials to
Make a jet engine
Car
That's not the relationship
People have with
Something even a stupid is toilet paper or soap
You make different decisions on soap
Continuously
I'm always kind of
Trying new brands
Actually Four brand this is really important for them competitive
Stapled to the point that people just completely stopped thinking
It's been a case for British banks for example
As everyone moves to digital banking people don't necessarily
Know about any other bank
Keep the physical
Stores in the physical bank tellers they have
Retail presence in order for people to know that there are there bags
And so I think in the home we always want to know you know what what is the newest so by could be buying
Because it's you know sulfate-free paraben-free whatever
What are the better decisions like
I could be making for my family
Play end I want to keep those options open
I am not
Running a industrial facility I'm running a home
I like that okay so running a home what are the things then where are the opportunities
For companies to come in
And make a difference you talked about new pair
Terrence yeah I think aging-in-place is interesting but there is a paradox at most
We're older
They don't want to be monitored
This feels very invasive
Are my privacy
So
Totally I mean
Yeah
Beijing conundrum is also a social
And I think that companies example
Voice assist
I would love
To see them take more of a leap of faith in actually supporting families who have
Complex needs
I don't really see why
Assistant with any voice functionality wooden
Also unable
Someone who falls in their home to
Call out for help
And for the service to be called true that boys assist
That should be something that companies do want to take on
It might be done through
Some more open source Voice assistance and might be something that's already come out but I mean I just haven't heard about it and I
I think that that
Social care peace is not necessarily going to be resolved by something you can buy
But it is definitely going to be something that something like the goodnight lamp in part does That Trick
Which is to make people more at ease about
But there are
How to be others
There ought to be other ways in which someone can actually
Connect their neighbors connect to their Community connect their City
Because most older people are living alone
And that's the
So all the effort that we put into convincing people to buy more soap or soap more consistently I think we ought to think about
How to get people to socialize
I like it
Talking about
People you have an interesting point
About
Power dynamic
Next and how
In the home we've had
A history of
If you're super richer
Well off that you had servants and
Even now
Dynamic
Are digital assist
Hector called assistance you tell them what to do
And seemed to be that we shouldn't be developing to
Schools that replicate that
Yeah I think it's a really interesting and very dangerous Dynamics
To constantly think of
Technology services in the home space is being some kind of subservient entity
The fact that most assistance it's not changing
Women's names
Now I saw this yesterday
A smoke alarm sounds like a woman is more likely to or sounds like at someone's mother is more likely to wake up the kids
There's this const
Dealing with Automation in the home space in a way that
Moves away from this idea of servitude
Most people you know
If they have Maids or cleaners who come in once a week or so they will
Usually clean before the maid comes in
Because they started feel so guilty about
Using
Someone else for their
Ponies and part of this is because we live in
Especially North America we live in home sitter
Enormous
Compared to the space that we used to have a hundred years ago
Still have these tasks
We feel need
To be done at the United Pace that is incredible
We have basically removed
Most germs from
Children's environments to the point where now we're actively encouraging parents to
Make sure that their kids eat dirt somewhere and Beak
Because otherwise it
Immune system doesn't develop so we've
Assertive overdone it on the home side
And I think this idea of
Having someone
Help you do that is something that we probably should
In terms of language in terms of application
Maybe you can have
A friend has something with you and that's a completely different
Powerdyne
Can having an assistant
And it's also completely different Dynamic than having someone come into your home and help you do something
Help and it's not necessarily
Subservience you know a friend can help you your parents can have
How to do something
But somehow the language that we use commercially is still very tied to this idea
Service and servitude
If you compared to a hundred years ago well you know
People have made some live-in maids and living Cooks
But they also
Cared for them and they were pay they were housed they were
Unless you were superb
Rich you actually usually
See you later
Buses to Downton Abbey Upstairs Downstairs
Situation which was pretty
Reserved for it was the elite and they actually were the ones who really didn't understand you took
Allergies because electricity men's
Especially Plumbing mint
Wouldn't necessarily have a servant
Bring water
They just didn't get the point
Would have a completely different facility operate yourself
They're like this is a
Downsizing of
What I have now
So they're not necessarily the best
Look to for inspiration
Got it okay
Well the book is available in the US on
Amazon it's called smarter homes how technology will change your whole life
And it's also available in the UK from the a press.com website
And it's 20 lb if you're in the UK and it's about $30 for the digital version
In the US
Alexandra thank you so much for
Coming on the show this week
Thank you for having me Stacy it's always a pleasure to talk to you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
Remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter
Stacey on iot
Cops will be next week