Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacy Higginbotham edger co-host
And we have a marvelous show
For you this week
Z-Wave security issues
Why Amazon
Will buy a secure
Security firm
Sun
New cellular products for the
The industrial internet
And Kevin and I tried out Amazon smart scheduling we're going to tell you how that we
Us we also have questions about the essential
Phone and what that means for
Home app
Arlo
Has been born
For several days
Talk a little bit about that and then we're going to get into some news from LG
Delgado
Schlage
Anne Phillips
Plus our guest this week
Is
Jesse Clayton
Of Nvidia he's talking about Jets and which is
Actually wanted
The fastest growing industrial iot platforms
Mostly because it can
AI at the edge
So you learned a lot about that stay tuned for it
We're also going to have a message from praetorian
A security
A voicemail
Talking about
Enterprise
Echo skill
Pretty sweet so let's get it all started with a message
From our sponsor
This week sponsor is Bosch interested in all things iot the Bosch connected World log covers
A wide range of iot topics from around the world
Such as industry for a mobility blockchain and adtech checkout blog
Bosch - s i.com for articles case studies
Interviews and more actually one of my favorite blogs I do find myself thinking too though
Those often so check it out
Now
Let's talk about our favorite topic
Gdpr
Okay
Gdpr stands for
General data protection regulation
This was a lot it was actually
Enacted
A while back
By the EU
But just came into effect on May 25th so last Friday
And it's been a mess
Yes
Everyone was kind of only this actually
Is actually going to have an impact
Beyond just all the Privacy regulation
Have you had a lot of privacy regulations
Coming in your email
I've had more
Privacy regulation notifications
And
Re-up on subscriptions to email addresses that I don't really care about then I normally get at CES
I mean it's been in Spain
And it's so bad
And some companies are so unprepared for this which I don't understand why cuz we knew it was coming that
Certain
Content providers news outlets
Are actually providing different
Sites of their news
To the EU areas
I believe USA Today is one
In fact it's much faster because
Pause
There's no tracking information JavaScript and all kinds of other
Fun stuff just HTML pictures Alonzo for sale
It is Miss I should actually take the
The time to say to all of our EU
Citizens and listeners
And pretty much everyone who listens because I actually care about you
Your privacy when you listen to
Cast when you go to the website
We don't
Track you for add purposes because our sponsors actually pay for every
They don't get your
Information
Information if you sign up for the newsletter I do get your email address and I will use it
To send you the newsletter
And then also I do use it
Marketing on
Facebook to you
Sometimes
So but not in any weird crazy way
I don't think it's any
Just so you know about our ad policies
We try to keep it
Really respectful and
I don't want your information sorry
And Kevin Kevin wants another
I don't want anything
Do you want to send that to
No no no
Alright so what's happening with iot devices is
A little bit uncertain so far
What we have seen is a couple devices
Installing offline
Actually one noted case it's a
Light from
Company in China
Great white
They stop supporting their app
The Apple Barn
Yeah I don't think I meant to because
Accents fixed it
No
No no that's right Guy season announcement the European server service will be restored within a week and some people there
Devices work going to a
Server in Germany
And that's where they couldn't access the server
So
Do you enterprising yeelight on her said I'm just switching the server to your Singapore Airline and that's how they got around us but that's
It's not the answer
Hardcore
Route to take
For your lights to work
And this is why we should have cloudless hugs
Exactly
So
A couple other connected devices what you would see is things like there's a picture on Twitter of
Someone's Samsung
Smart
Refrigerator family Hub refrigerator
Displaying a gdpr privacy notice
Now it's worth noting that
This person pointed out
They said this is just a notification to go to Samsung
When you clicked okay
You're actually
Not opting in
You're just saying
Seeing that I need
So that was
A good way to do it next also
If people went over to turn their thermostats
On stay actually showed them
Similar
Application so most people seem to be working
There's just a lot of thing
I'll tell you
I am reading through a lot of these policies especially
Connected devices IP
To have something on that
Soon
But I am
I may be reading for quite some time
All right
So that's
Gdpr
Now we'll move into last week
And a little bit into this week's big story which was
Holy cow
Z-Wave has been hacked
Only
Like many iot
Hacking stories this is maybe less scandalous that it first.
Here's what this is talking about is
Back in 2013 and I believe again in 2016
Hackers found a way to get access to Z-Wave
Devices Inc
Was it difficult because you had to be
Within 30 to 40
It was possible
So
The Z-Wave Alliance actually changed their sick
Security stand
In all devices that were
Where are certified after April 2nd
A flask
Had to comply with what
Called S2 secure
A lot of devices out there that are not S2
Compliant
Titan II but this latest security hack
Is very similar
To the ones from
A couple years back
Basically what happens is
The researchers have found a way
Trollback NES to device
0 which means
They can basically perpetrate
Trait that same hat
Freak out
Kevin and I are not so worried
Because again this requires
Really close physical
Proximity
It feels like the same
Height of level of danger of someone trying to get access to your Wi-Fi password
Sneaking in and trying to see the Authentication
And getting access to the
Encrypted password
Router tries to kill
New devices the threat window for somebody trying to do the Z-Wave hack is like 20 milliseconds
It has to be very precise
Have to be close by I mean is it possible sure
It's possible but if you were s to device
Does get rolled back or if you add an S 0 device to Z-Wave Network
You should actually get notified
That such a thing as half
So we got all excited about this
But
There's kind of a little bit of a downside which is
Not many hubs rs2 certified
So we looked at the wink hub
Not as to certify
According to
It's
That that's the wink Hub to the newest one
Is the wink Hub 2
We look for small things also does not appear to have
Which means if you were happy
You wouldn't know
We should probably put the link
In the show notes to the catalog on Z-Wave Alliance where you can actually look up on the database what devices
Are certified and if you look
For your device
It'll actually say if it has S2
Compliance
We will do it
Okay so that is the
Scoop
On the Z-Wave
Challenges
Now
What else do we
Have you rebooted your
Louder yet Kevin
I have not even though the FBI is suggesting please reboot your router everybody
And I
This actually all started last week with a
I guess it would be called a botnet
Attack
I think it was targeted towards the Ukrainian electrical grid but obviously it's
To create the attack it's not just using routers and things in Ukraine season 2 from all over the world
I think it's called vpnfilter
Attitude Target certain routers
Turn Linksys mikrotik Netgear and tp-link +
What the FBI is saying and they actually took control of the server that was spreading this so that's good
Goodbye still may be out there on routers
They're saying just reboot your router
I don't think that's enough and if you're that concerned
I think what you really need to do is factory reset your router because rebooting it if the code is
Persistent
It's going to be there when you reboot so
I know that resetting a router is
A challenges of pain
But if you're that concerned I think we should do the extra step and do that
Reset it
Note to you guys especially if you have lots of connected devices
Your house when you reset your router
Make sure you do the exact password otherwise
Like a crazy person
Resetting your SSID and password
On
Yeah I mean that's the thing you have to determine how far you want to go here because some people may say well I don't even want you the same
SSID Android password
What what you're going to do that if you don't use it is exactly what you said Stacy you're not to go back and every single device that connects to your voice
Wi-Fi network is going to be reconfigured to work with a new coil coating new network
Have fun you guys
All right
So after
Rebooted router
Continue listening to our show so you
You can find out why Amazon whole biosecurity firm
I thought this was a really good article
Call Julie Jacobson / @cee Pro
She Wrote
A story about
Amazon's need for a security firm
Because
As we talked about
Forever on the show
Security is the gateway drug to this
Amazon needs to have
This Plus
They need actual boots on the ground and a security company already has those and we've talked about companies like
Ben has been on the market
They have been for sale so it's totally possible
That you would see Amazon pick up a cup
Company like Vivint maybe like an ATT they have private Equity arnaud's now that
Might want to sell that
My money would be on Vivint
Because they've basically been owned by the same product
For a while
Aunt
It's getting raped
So
Julie points out a couple really
Stupid things
Amazon can't install their own security
Products without having alarm certification
So they need to get that
They also want
More technicians for their Amazon expert service
And they want
To basically
Sell more devices so
If you have an alarm code
You got it
That's a ton of stuff
And
That gives them service revenue from
Remote network monitoring system
And they can become
I'm like this amazing managed service
Which is something the Broadband come
Please also would like to
To be in the security
Amazon
Would be in a better position because they have
Madam a
Assistant
And
That gives her
Car more intelligent
It's kind of a win
So I'm not going to say Julie's wrong I still think Amazon ends up buying wink
Cuz I don't think they Echo Hub or Echo Plus is all that but that's just me
And Amazon is deploying when Cubs through their Smart Home Security
Offering the strange thing is Julie points out that they need
To be certified
Installers in because of certain laws regulations and such to shed their very quirky laws Amazon is already installing
Chinese with Amazon employees
So she kind of lost me there I got to be honest
There are rules in
Each state
About
Can do what associate
So it may be that there installing this but there
I could be
So
If Julie if you're listening let us know
I still think
I do think it's a good idea
I'm not going to lie
I think it's probably
Pretty smart so we'll see what happens
Maybe we'll have fancy fancy news from
Amazon
Okay and now let's talk about
Low-power wide area Networks
And
Let's go
So basically
Ways to get Enterprise in industrial stuff online
So there's a new
Partnership between two companies one we've talked about before which is sick Fox they have a proprietary
Networks that they are trying to roll out around the world
And here Technologies which
Does a lot of mapping data location type information
Their location sweet the here location Suite references
Billions of Wi-Fi hotspots and when you combine the Wi-Fi hotspots with sigfox as Network now you've got
Hit capability to track
Tag Assets in the supply chain and Logistics area
So that's what they're doing their dancing a partnership to develop and deploy a global location service
For supply chain Logistics they don't mention anybody using it so this is brand-new this is just a partnership
Chip and they're talking about the baking a 1.9 trillion dollar opportunity for Global supply chain and Logistics
But I think it's a smart partnership because they're bringing together to readily accessible Technologies here
Providing an option to the traditional cellular companies and you know nb-iot and other Technologies for
This type of thing
Speaking of it
Electric amp which makes
A module it was
Originally
Was more secure and
Provided you connect Electric
Saint Cloud so basically it was like
Iot in a box
So now I have intercellular which is a cellular version it offers LTE Cat 1 in 3-g
And you can do lots of it's got Computing on it every
And then
Eventually they're going to add
Q4
A cat
Mnb iot
And just for you guys who may not be super familiar with various cellular
Low power wide area Networks
Cat 1M
Allows you to
Use more data
So
How to make
Did I believe it
It is end
The cellular providers can roll that out
Pretty much with a software
Nb-iot
You're looking at smaller data
So are slower data
So you can transfer less data and the other providers actually have to update their infrastructure
A little bit more
War at their towers
Worst to support
They are supporting it it's
Becoming very much the standard
But you gotta figure application
And one makes sense
Smaller less data rich
Nb-iot
So is this good news
Electric imp has done a really good job for Enterprise customers of making it
Very easy to get something online and keep it consistent
Around the world
So this is been popular in regulated Industries
Where you can get approvals for
Your cloud provider
Cellular provider and then
You're done
Which is nice so
We'll see more about this pricing for the cellular connectivity is going to be based on the number of devices connected
And it'll just automatically go through
Count
Your devices that
Are charged in the US that use T-Mobile AT&T
Wherever you have the best cover
So it sounds a lot like what twilio is doing with their
Wireless connectivity
Deprogram as well
It's great because we're seeing a lot of these middlemen come in
And provide
Cellular connectivity without companies having to go and try to do deals with a site
Which if you're not a big company
It's tough
And even if you are a big company
You may want something that's a bit more
Mike Lobel
You can actually pre-order this module 2 and get it around July 30th through 85 bucks which isn't too terrible X
Expensive if you want to do some prototyping and testing
All right
Let's go on to
You are experienced
Yesterday Kevin and I
Hey let's test out that Amazon smart scheduling stuff
About last week end
We spent like an hour
It was surprising
That's kind of because you really have to be preconfigured in a sense to use it effectively and the more we
Set it up
The more I realize this is not something consumers are going to use this is more of it
Enterprise
Type service and it's going to be Enterprise within your own
Surprise so this is
Probably great for intern
Turn on meeting so what this is is basically your
Able to say
Madam
And again
We do that to avoid setting off your
Amazon Echo
Madam
Schedule a meeting with
And
Then theoretically she's supposed to say
What time is the meeting
Or she might
Suggest a schedule
Yoshi first check
Both calendars to see what options are available explains you are both available from this time this time and this
This time to this time when would you like to meet
SEPTA
To make this all work cuz it sounds awesome cuz you have to pay to schedule meeting
It's right to make this work you have to
Have a couple things going
You have to have your
Calendar linked to
The Amazon Echo
You actually have to share your calendar access
With the person you're trying to make
Appointment
That's why I say this is more of an Enterprise play
Yes so
I did share my calendar with
Then he shared his with
But this is not something
We would normally do
And you also
How to make sure your contacts are
Queen when they go into
So for example I had an old email
Address for Kevin
In one of my contacts in that unfortunately is the
Madame Mao
Looks at
So you can't edit your contacts for
From within
The app
The Amazon app
You have to go to York on
Text app
And then once you've done that
It doesn't actually propagate right away to
Amazon and that depends for me it did propagate cuz I did at Stacy's
Information as well in my native contacts app I did it on my iPhone and it propagated immediately you did it on your
I don't know which Android phone you have and it didn't
It didn't propagate for like
It now has the
It's a cool
Service without a doubt
And to be honest I mean I would schedule meetings with third-parties when I worked in corporate all the time and if there
In my contacts that might have their information
I wouldn't necessarily be sharing calendars with them so it would not work for that
You can set a calendar hold oh so you can actually do it
And what'll happen is
The calendar invite will be
Email to them
And then they can see it
Yeah that's
Nice the other nice thing about this I thought maybe it was
Specific to Amazon made Echo devices only has some features
Are only for Amazon devices
But I tried it this morning on the Sonos one that has met him a built-in
And I was able to do the exact same thing with Miss Stacy so it
Does work on 3rd party Echo devices
So there you have it in this is compatible with Microsoft
Google G suite and several other popular
Corporate email applications so
Yeah maybe
If you got people you schedule meetings with a lot and this is something you're interested in
Maybe just
Connect with them and you're like hey let's do this calendar sharing
So a rhetorical question why doesn't the Google home do this
Yeah
Let Me Ride Along I did actually run into Mark Speights who's in charge of Google speakers efforts
Add a conference I was at last week
And I asked him about that and he actually said
But that is a common complaint
And their works
I didn't feel much better but you don't
There we have
All right
Essential phone
Kevin I saw this and I was really sad because
Cuz the essential phone is not doing well
The company Maybe
Not develop the essential phone 2
Might be able to sell that
Business what's going
Yeah there's been some talk of essential putting itself up for sale definitely cancelling II essential
The first one it has not sold well the estimates are like a hundred fifty thousand
Diamonds which is nothing in the grand scheme of things
Basically brought the Android operating system to Google
When Google purchased Android
He's in charge of essential and he put a tweet out saying you know we're constantly evaluating our products and
We are
Still focused on creating great mobile and Home Products and
Products we do care about because
Andy had said when
The company launched that they were going to
Bring forth the ambient OS that would tie all of our home devices together
We haven't seen that I've spoken to the central at CES and pretty much got a no comment you know things are in the works when we haven't
Oracle share what is this mean for ambient OS I don't know I mean if they get sold maybe they still plow ahead with that
Maybe they don't I don't know is a lot up in the air right now
Was really excited to see Andy Robinson
Interpretation of
Like a smart home
So I am too but I was always concerned about it and I still am because
He and said that they're just going to work with public apis from all the different device makers to tie everything together and those epi
Does change all the time
So I don't know
All right
We won't stay depressed over that
Let's talk
Be smart cameras made by
For some users they haven't been able to log into their app for so
Days
And
I got to save
The response to this has not been awesome so
Took a while to figure this out
And then they're saying it's a DNS issue
For users and user should reset their DNS setting
Switch
That's a pretty ticket
Nothing to ask
Sweet easy to do but most people
It just happens automatically don't worry about it with a lot of people have never been into the DNS settings
Suck ya
That's not the answer
Also this week D-Link has some new Wi-Fi cameras and they have home connectivity
Play with
Google
Assistant
Amazon Alexa and if they send that there's a trio of cameras the HD Wi-Fi camera which will cost
5999 there's a full HD Wi-Fi camera for 8999 and then a full HD pan-and-tilt
Wi-Fi camera for 9999
What I like about these they offer for different service levels if you want to subscribe or not that's up to you
Cloud storage of the video they have a free option
That works with three cameras and has a 24-hour rolling
History of what's being captured
Do they have a basic option for a week
But you can get
For 25 bucks a year
Premium option
For 14 days and also adds two more cameras 05 cameras for $50 a year
In the pro version Story video for
30 days in the cloud but you have 10 cameras and is $100 a year I actually like that pricing scheme and I wish
Companies would kind of look at that give you those kind of different levels and even up the number of devices as well
Opportunity
So we also have a quick update LG 2018 TVs now work with the
Amazon Echo
So you can talk to Madam a
Using your LG
Already had Google Assistant social condition of
Amazon
And I don't really care
For homekit
But I'm really excited about the
These devices so Elgato
Which makes
Homekit enabled sensor
And other connected
Devices
Sprinkler
Control system actually it's like a hose control system
Andale
Lamp called the eve
Claire so
Kevin thought I'd be excited by the
Slayer lamp
But I do love my lighting and this is homekit enabled
Portable LED lamp
Commercially available
Europe
Gdpr compliant
It reminds me the Phillips has one called the Goliath
And that's out like a light it looks like a bowl
Close
So that is available
It's 99 years
And then
Elgato
Aqua
Is basically
A little irrigation controller so far
But this is homekit enabled it's
Create schedules for the cult your sprinkler system
This really attaches to a spigot
And then you can control your outdoor irrigation
And that's going to be 9995
And it can be pre-ordered from the Elgato website in the
Us
As of now
So
If your homekit enabled
That's actually pretty cool and maybe I would buy it and just use homekit for that
I don't know
We'll see how so we got a quick update for the Schlage sense deadbolt
Which is now compatible with Google assistant so you can ask Google if your door is locked
You can say lock my door
You cannot unlock the door like you can with certain locks and the echo when you do that with an echo it will actually a
Ask for a PIN to unlock
Adore as well as
The command to unlock it
For security reasons so maybe they will add that but for the moment you can lock or check the status with a Schlage sense deadbolt
And finally
Philips Hue has a new app
And I'm going to tell you
Guys it's really good
I have not been I don't use my Philips
Q app.
I got most of it automated
You just control it
Voice
But the new app
Especially for a colors and scenes
I like it so give that a try if you are a Philips Hue
And let us know what you think
Finally we have a quick correction
Couple weeks ago we were talking about habitat which is a
Local
It's also connect
The idea is that it is a locally control
We said that it had WiFi
It is not
It connects to
Your router via is
So there you have it
You don't like hubs like Kevin doesn't like
I Cubs this mean
Or rather
You don't like the direct connection
And it's just a location thing for me sometimes people's routers are not in a central area in which case smart home device
Isis man range issues
So that's my bigger concern that in
Ports on my router but that's a whole nother issue
Do not get him started
Don't get me started
Bad
So we can distract you
Quick quick
Let's go to our
Iot podcast listener hotline
And guess what
You guys I have an ecobee SI it works with Google Assistant it works with Amazon
On Echo it is not the pretty cool awesome
Ecobee that I like
But it is
A really nice connected thermostat
And if you want to get a connect to thermostat or free just call and leave us voicemail
On the iot podcast hotline at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
R24
We will be doing this one until
June 5th
Teeth so that can chew
Wow two whole weeks
To call in
Leave us a question
Entered
Guinda and
Ecobee SI
Worst case scenario you get a free internet connected thermostat
It works
What's not to love
Okay so this week
Voicemail is
Actually a really cool suggestion
The brings us back into this Enterprise area of
Merrimack
Some Kevin in Raleigh
Hi Stacy and Kevin Kevin and Raleigh
Remember Stacy
Saying something I believe it might have been on
Enterprise
And iot
Devices not sensors but things like the echo Etc
There is a company anyways has been integrating the echo device
With servicenow
It service management
So that people in the Enterprise can do things like
Change request
Thought you might find it interesting and something
How to keep an eye on
Okay
Heaven
That's actually a really good idea
And I thought it sounded
Kevin who's actually
Question does a job
He has actually paid
Answer informed
Yes many moons ago I was starting on a technical help desk and a Fortune 100 company and I remember opening
Closing service tickets like a maniac well it turns out Kevin from Raleigh mention
Servicenow
Which has worked with a company called
Decibel apps least based on the research I found
And they have a skill you can say mad at me
Ask ticket now to create an incident so basically in the Enterprise if you're on a help desk or
Your tracking any kind of incidents you could
Just create them by voice if you've got echoes in the Enterprise so
It's pretty cool skill I know that at the AWS event in November last year they had a hat
Check your office
Little party where people trying to create skills for the Enterprise and I don't know if this came out of it or not
I know this is available and there is a white paper written on how to create
Skills with the Echo and service now so there's probably like a whole market for these kind of things that we probably don't
About you often so I'm glad Kevin brought this up cuz I would not know nothing about this I've been wondering
How do we get
These Voice assistance in the Enterprise and this is a perfect example of one way to do it
Easier service tickets and
Scheduling meeting
Remember the iot podcast listener hotline
Is brought to you by Schlage
Maker of electronically
Schlage smart locks work with most Smart Home & Security Systems so you can get the most out of your
Whether you're an
Apple homekit user
Are you love
Amazon
To see what's possible visit schlage.com
To learn more
And again if you want to leave SMS
Message just give us a call at 512-623-7424 and you will be entered to win
An ecobee
SI
And now
Stay tuned
Jesse Clayton who is a product manager for NVIDIA Jetson
He's actually going to explain a lot of things that you're going to want to hear such as
What the heck is happening
Let me talk about AI
Why Jetson
Is becoming so popular in the industrial iot
Some really cool use cases for
Computer vision
So stay tuned for all of that and now here's a message from our sponsor
Answer is praetorian praetorian provides end-to-end iot security testing that helps organization
Oceans balance risk with time-to-market
Praetorian Engineers help you strengthen the security of your iot products from ship to Cloud
Turn security into York
Competitive advantage
Ironing a third-party certification
Praetorian
The leaders in iot secure
Microsoft recognize
Praetorian as best-in-class
When you think pretorius
Think iot security Expo
Check out the case study online to see how praetorian help Samsung
Strengthen the security of is iot
By visiting
Stacey on iot
/ 6
That's Stacy
We on iot. Com
/ security
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
Does your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Today's guests
Jessie
Clayton who is a senior manager for product
Export IntelliJ
Machines at
Nvidia
Hi Jessie how are you doing today
I'm doing well how are you
I'm super excited to talk to you
Because
We have been so focused here at the show on edge computing
Machine learning at the edge
Vision
Enable and
Feel like in videos
What's going on there
Which is actually
Quite unusual from where I thought Nvidia was going to go so let's get started with your main product that you guys are pushing
Computer vision at the edge is that a fair assessment
Maybe it's Prada
I think artificial intelligence at the edge is probably the right Category 2
But this okay so this is a board this is the Jetson
Tx2 is the latest version of
So tell me a little bit about what you guys are doing
Absolutely so it in video where laser focused on artist
Videos of worlds
Leading AI platform and we build
Products to help
Floyd
Use cases
Now the iot is really
About computation
Communication and specifically where do you put
The computation for
The problem that you're trying to solve
Doesn't make sense
The computation or the AI
In the cloud
Or at the edge
Or somewhere in between in many cases it belongs in the
In the cloud or the data center but there's some use cases where that's just not possible
Either because of net
Work van with constraints
Soar latency
Privacy
Availability and so
For those use cases
They really need
The AI running a
There's two important technologies that Nvidia is building for AISD
Jetson is NVIDIA splat
AI
The Jetson tx2 is a credit card-sized device that runs
Advanced AI in
10 watts at our customers
Use it in autonomous machines
Like robots and drones
4 manufacturing
And Logistics
And further applications
In the industrial internet-of-things like
Predictive maintenance
Now there's also some of these cases where even Jetson is too big and I
Making of the trillions of sensors
Wearables
Mobile devices in these devices
Can still benefit
From AI
So for these Nvidia has
Deep learning Excel
Or nvdla nvdla is
Hardware
Make sure that Nvidia has open sourced to enable companies to benefit
From our own AI research and to incorporate this design into their own products
Now we just announced recently that nvdla will be available
As part of arms
Trillium
Platform and the partnership makes it simple
Wolf or coyote chip company
Integrate AI into their design so nvdla is new so it hasn't been
Corporated antenna
Products yet with
Exception of some of them.
Motor Products
So I've been covering in video for
Decade
And I watched it start
Gpus then go into mobile phone processing fee
The logic was
Does koshka Graphics need to be everywhere
So what tipped you off or got you guys
Thinking about
Creating the smaller profile technology
You correctly stated that are
Nvidia got its start in
In designing processors cheap used for computer graphic
And as it turned out that highly
Parallel architecture
For computer graphics
Is also very good for many other testing
Shooting and most recently artificial intelligence now today a lot of
Intelligence happen
Data Center
Turn the cloud but
We realized
Terminated
Play some of these capabilities out to the network at
Automotive self-driving cars was the first example where we really saw it
An important role that vehicle
Play and help
Bring that technology but of course
Are there devices
Microbots
Portable Medical
What devices can all potentially benefit
Artificial intelligence and so
Sort of combining those two
To heritage's the one of Designing highly parallel processor
What can be used for artificial
Intelligence
And then designing low-power chips
For going into
Mobile products like phones and tablets
We realized that we
Could produce something
Sing that was almost uniquely qualified to deliver artificial intelligence 2
Biatch
All right and for people who are maybe less
Differences between training and the computer needs there
Executioner
So maybe I can give a little bit of an example
The first step in modern artificial intelligence and specifically deep learning is training
A neural network
This is when you're showing the neural network many many instances of the things
But you wanted to learn so if you wanted to learn
Aztec people you show it lots of pictures of people
These are people
Or if you wanted to learn to detect cats you should
Lots of pictures
The cat
Are cats and through that process
Of training it learns to distinguish
Patterns
People and cats and whatever else it is that you decide
It's a train that neural network
Now the result of that training activity is a
The train model
Network which can then be deployed for the second part
Deep learning which is called inference
An inference you're exposing it to new data that it hasn't seen but
Before and it's drawing
Conclusions from that date or drawing inferences
From that day to see you show it
A person that it's never seemed
Warren tells you that
The person who showed a cat that has never seen before and it tells you that that's a cat
Now the training part of this is very very computation
Ideal you want to be
Running this in a super
Computer in the cloud but inference while still computationally intensive
It can be scaled down
To fit into summer
Edge device
Okay and so we were talking about doing inference at the edge where the architectural decisions what do you need
Has it turned out good for doing both the train peace and the in
And the reason why that is
When you're training
What you're really doing is running the data through the neural network the neural networks spits out and ants
So let's say you show a picture of a cat and it says car
Can you say no that's not a car that's a cat go back and readjust your weights
To an algorithm
Notice backpropagation and then
Run the same data
Through the neural network again it through this process eventually at Tunes all the settings
Network until it can correctly produce the answer
How many move on to the next image in the next image and so far
So that first
Pass that forecast is actually the same thing as in
Prince's own training are doing
Fordpass and the backpack
For inference you're only doing the fordpass and so that's why
Can you see these architecture
Is GPU architecture is being replicated for both
Training in a server in the cloud as well as inference out at
And so to answer your
Questions to Simply
You need a general-purpose highly
Parallelize architecture in order to run inference for these neural networks efficiently
Okay
You just don't need it
Many
That's correct so inference is one pass
The neural network
Where is with training you're doing many many forward passes
Many many backwards
And so that's why you need much
Resources for the training side than you do
Inference inference is still computationally
Complexion
Is continuing to
To grow researchers are advancing
In the research today there
Designing new
Neural network designs and the
Depth and the size of those
Neural networks is increasing and so in order to keep up with
Today's
Research you really need a platform that's
Continuing to in
Increase of performance
Abilities year-over-year
Okay we're going to talk about that
When we start talking about
Let's go back to kind of business decisions that invidious
So I originally reached out to you guys because I had heard that the Jetson tx1
One of the fastest rising
From a percentage
Iot platforms out there
Let's talk about what people are
Doing
Sure so
Jetson is suitable for application
Where you need a lot of coffee
Realize that your
So for example
In robotics there
A big deed for
4 AI capabilities but
It turns out it's really hard to do
Because you need this massive
Amounts of
Compute in the size and Power on blue
It's typical of these Edge devices like robots in order to optimize
Crop yields
And reduce the use of spray.
Chemicals Blue River technology uses cameras mounted on tractors to differentiate crops
From weeds and to deploy treatment only where it's needed
This allows them to
Dramatically
Reduce the amount of spray can
Chemicals and the speed at which they can drive the tractor
Depends on how fast
The processor
Process the image so for them Jackson is really critical to productivity
We also see a lot of
Work in navigation where robots
Using AI to low
Localizan navigate like last mile delivery robots made by marble
Her by Robbie Jetsons also being used to manufacture
View robotics develops technology
For collaborative robots
I can work alongside humans and FANUC uses AI for opt
Inspection on its robots
Consumer drone that can autonomously navigate through complex environments like
Mountains and Forest and Pelt film people's Great Moments so those are all based on AI process
Video data but
There's a lot of other applications outside
Robotics using other types
Update as well one really cool use case is predictive maintenance using anomaly
Detection on Time series
So there's this really clever Tech
Technique called an auto in
What you basically train a neural network to in
Encode and decode a signal coming
From this time series data
Like let's say the current draw
From a water heater
Turn your home now that data
The current draw is going to change normally over the course of the day and the seasons but if something abnormal
The encoder won't be able to
Go to properly because it's never seen it
And so that's a signal that something
Abnormal is happening
And in many cases
Is it points to an impending failure
So the homeowner can schedule
The water heater breaks another really cool applications
South Dakota virtual sensor so let's say that
You really want to build is a redundant fuel flow measurement
For an aircraft now you know that
Fuel consumption
Is a function of air temperature and pressure in
Temperature at altitude speed but you don't know exactly what
You can train a neural network
On these data and
Increte what is essentially
A virtual fuel flow sensor
From these other son
We see Jetson
Being used for AI at the edge
A lot of ways that we anticipated but also in a lot of edge application
Is that we never really considered
That's actually really cool
Marshall Center
This reminds me actually of something
I feel like I hear a lot of
Video examples and I feel like a lot of the big Tech firms are pushing this concept of video at the edge
Show me before finding a parking space that might be monitoring of manufacturing process to understand
What's going wrong
I'm curious
How you guys feel
Video versus maybe some of the other sensors out
Is video always the best option when should you use video over
Patterson
All videos great because it's such a rich sensor
You're sending 1080p
4K of pixels at 30 frames a second there's just a lot of data
Which you can infer a lot of things but your point there's a lot of cases
Video doesn't
It doesn't work in the dark for instance
It wouldn't work deep underwater
The same reasons or if you're trying to do things like measure the characteristics of a robot or the water he
Example that I use video is not going
There are all of these other sensors out there that are
Producing data where we think there is a lot of Art
Opportunity
To use artificial intelligence to draw insights from
That data I think
Exactly as you said most of the research and development is happening on video today because it's such a
Which sensor but there is also a lot of work
Getting less attention
Types of sensors
And let's
About the future
So as you guys are developing
It should be ahead of the Curve
Because my gosh
It takes a lot longer to build something in silicone then it does and software
So what are the workloads that you guys
Being interesting going
So what are the things we found in our work
With Jetson is that Jetsons
Incapable of solving
Many problems
Robotics
4 using artificial intelligence at the edge but there are many other
Challenges out there the
Because they demand
So much more
We can deliver today and there's two things that I'm really excited about the We Believe with future Generations will be able to
To address the first is on the robotic side
Automation
Is already used to manufacture
It takes so much effort
Automated production
Slime that you only do it
Very large
IPhone for example github
Tremendous efficiency benefit from automation
Which might be really Innovative doesn't get that same benefits of
Cost of stamps
Say more per unit to manufacture
Can I take this as a negative
Impact on innovation
Robots that can
Quickly learn to adapt
New jobs in
Products could make automation much more flexible
Introduce the barriers of
Bringing that
Innovation tomorrow
We believe that with
Increase comp
Vegetation coming in the
The future will be able to take on
More and more of these Manufacturing
Logistics tasks that can't yet
The second thing I'm really excited about is in portable Medical
Devices
Are there so many places in the world that the Physicians don't have good access to
Technology as I'm really excited about the
Potential
Judge has
Like I care in ultrasound
With the Next Generation
Processors
Capabilities
Companies will be able to address some of those challenges I also like being
Surprised by Innovation that I never
Would have thought of
The Jetsons
And I am super excited about this portable medicine idea
Kind of fun
I like it
So let's talk about the ecosystem because
Boomer type at the internet of things it's not like
You buy a board and
You just use it right you've got
All kinds of stuff
To have to work with the cloud with
Various other Edge providers
So how do you guys work
Companies maybe it's Microsoft Azure maybe it's Amazon
AWS maybe it's smaller platforms for the gala
It seems to be very consistent Trend that you have to
Link your boards to other people's clouds and services because a lot of these companies are building these
Which devices they're not as Technic
Yeah I think there's no question that
Products made from Jets
Going to exist in a large
Ecosystem
Delivering pay I at
Hearts of
The network topology
I'll give you one example so json is used today in
Amazon Greengrass platform
So this is a platform that Amazon has developed to help
It's custom
Manage Apple
Locations for
The industrial internet-of-things and so Jetson
Can be deployed out at the edge to manage
Some of these sensors that you
Find Floyd
Coyote
Run AI workload on them and then manage
That Jets North at
Collection of Jetsons
Through this higher level Amazon Greengrass platform
And so we see the sort of a
Approach being replicated other areas we believe it's really going to help our customers and their customers to play the technology more
So today working with Amazon eventually at work
Yeah that's correct so Jetson isn't open
Enable our partners and our customers to integrate their technology
West Jackson
Amazon green grass
Are the first ones that have been announced in
We expect many more announcements in the future
And let's just quickly to Circle back to the nvdla stuff
Because I I saw that
Announcement and I was really fascinated
Because I covered the arm Trillium announcement
Just a quick reminder for you guys the arm Trillium is a machine learning
Architecture
For the power arm chips
Too much snot
Sew-in putting nvdla
On the arm silica
What should I take away from that
At first like all of this small
Companies that are out there trying to develop
Really low power
Machinery
Green chips
Yeah one of the things that we recognize is that there is this
Need for artificial
Intelligence to solve problems
Xen devices
That Judson simply dozen
Now of course we've done lot of
Research and develop
Machine learning artificial intelligence Hardware here at Nvidia leverage. Hardware ourselves
But wouldn't it be great if
Companies can leverage that research
We've done to solve these problems
For which Nvidia does not bill
So that's what the nvdla is all about companies can
Can leverage cm
Nvdla it's been
Open source the RTL is available for download
People can find it on nvdla. Org and they can design it into their
Own
The partnership
Enables all of arms
And licensees
The Easley leverage the nvdla technology into their designs and so we expect in the
In the future you'll see
Many many
Products that are
Designed
Around
Architecture and incorporate the nvdla
Deep learning inference
Out to all of this
Tiny iot
Devices that are off
2 watt range
Historically in videos works with a fairly limited number
Partners
Because
There are only a few server makers out there
Are there only a few game console makers
So as you advance and start selling these boards how are you guys changing
Cheap because iot is vastly different than any other
Tech ecosystems
Yeah that's absolutely
Play cracked I think one of the things that we realized early on with Judson
Is that
Instead of having
We typically have had
In the past which is a small number of large customers
In json we have a very large number
Of relatively smaller
So rather than having
Tens or maybe a hundred large customers now we have thousands
Ten thousands of small Cuts person so just from a scale perspective it's not possible
More for us to engage Direct
Every one of those customers
We realize that in order for Jetson to be successful we had to make everything publicly-available we had to enable
Whether it's a start-up Warren oh yeah Morgan is garage
Need to enable them to go
From an idea all the way to
The final product without having
Ticket on the phone and track somebody down from
Nvidia
When is thinks we're seeing is now the chip vendors are really getting serious about providing
Security updates patching
For the life cycle of some of these embedded products
So we saw Qualcomm do a 7 and 10 year support for their Snapdragon Inn
Microsoft announced a 10-year support
With their projects Oprah's security
Dirty chips so
With these products the Jetson products
What kind of support are you guys offering today and then what are you kind of looking to do for the
The future sure we actually think about this into different kind of
Categories of
The products
We have
Products that are more commercial
In nature and for those products we support those for five years since the launch
And so by support that means
They're still available
Purchase
You also get software updates from Nvidia
Which in the beginning will focus on functional and four
Performance improvements
Chords to longer life with
The project will include security updates to make sure that any vulnerabilities are being patched
So five years for
Commercial now we realize that that's not enough
For some apps
Locations particularly in industrial use cases customers are demanding
10 year lifetime
And so for a version of our Jetson tk1
Base platform
And also for
A product we just announced called
The Jetson tx2 I we offered
10 years
Of support
Although this is saddening to me because I have
I see it's a one-and-a-half-year-old June oven
With an Invidia this is a Tegra processor
Oh my gosh I only have three and a half years left on my oven
Triple B's
Supported
Alright Jesse thank you so much for coming on the show today
Thank you very much for having
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week