Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham at your co-host
Kevin tofel
We have an awesome show for you today we've got some news from
Amazon
We got Google's new speakers
And bringing iot to water utilities also to the insurance world and
Sprint's got a new iot platforms
I will talk briefly about
And blackberry is
Also
Watching a news
Security platform for iot
Plus we have on the show
Kim Kelly who is the CEO of Hampton products International they are the company behind the Brinks brand of locks
I got a new connected product
We talked a little bit about that
But we spend a lot of time talking about the impact
Tariffs on
Iot devices
So you're going to want to stay tuned to that if you are making devices or if you plan on buying them
And hopefully not spending quite as much money
So this podcast is sponsored by SAS and analytics software provider and also
Chocolate so let's hear from one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is chocolate
With 64% of iot consumers reporting performance issues
You need an edge first application performance monitoring solution
Choose the problem-solving software that watches your application
System
And their environments for issues
From device in a release to fleet-wide errors chocolate will provide you with the Intel you need to solve problems before
For your customers find them
Sign up today at chocolate. IO
That's a u k l e
ATT. IO
Okay Kevin this show is going to be a bit of a
Challenge because one of our big stories
Is Amazon planning to release
At least eight new
Madame a powered gadgets
Set a reminder to everybody listening that Madame a is
The Amazon echos digital assist
So these devices include a microwave
Amplifier
Dim sum in car garage
I expect we're going to see these
Pretty soon because the holiday season is
Is coming up
So we're not going to talk
Whole lot about
I want everyone to stay tuned
For Amazon news
Because if and when these come out we're going to be
Audit right Kevin
Absolutely
It could happen at any time you never know with Amazon
That's how to cut a trumpet the way you
Evidence I'm sorry
Okay we're going to talk about Terrace later don't worry you don't have to do that cuz I know that that's a favorite topic right there
So we can talk
What is actually happening
With the Amazon ecosystem that they launched this week something called
Madam egg gadgets toolkit
And this
This is a really kind of
I think this is actually really cool thing what this is is this lets your devices
Interact
With the Amazon
Echo device
Kevin do you want to give an example
Yeah these devices which work over Bluetooth and I say these devices meeting these are devices that will be coming people
We'll have to make these devices are add these feature
Existing device
They can
Send events
To an echo where they can receive
Information from an echo so some examples that Amazon gives because against is all
A software development
Kid it's not an actual product
You just go out and buy
They have like wake word to text
Frank Zappa you are Gadget could respond when it hears the Madam a wake word
So if you had
It's not great example but
A Bluetooth connected cuckoo clock it could pop its head out whenever
You say mad at me
So you can add some things to your house that can do other things like they even say
Maybe have a robot that can lip-sync Asmat America local weather
It would appear as if
The robot attacks
She saying the word
Odoo notifications timers and alarms on
Even music I thought the music example
What kind of cool cuz
I don't know
Growing up you saw these on dashboards of cars
Oh my gosh are you serious that's exactly
It's exactly about so here's what they say the music aspect of this
Gadget sdks coming soon you can't do this yet
I didn't say for example you could create visual performances with music
Such as a hula girl that sways her hips when songs are playing on
Amazon music
So it's kind of extending
The
Echo into other devices not
For providing information per se but more for interactive thing
Right and it's clearly Amazon is looking at this for games
Probably heading into the holiday season because
They
Talk a lot about using it with
Toys
Baby products
So I think this is interesting because big picture
We should talk about this I think I'm last week show where we said that basically
Google +
Amazon
Ecosystem are basically the standards and iot
And from that perspective this basically gives
The echo
A data schema that other devices can now
I'll see so we can understand when
Madam
Alerted it
Darius
Samantha
Information
Things that it can do
So this is a pretty powerful tool and it sounds like
I mean if you think about the native support for various
Devices like light bulbs
Wasn't switches
Even ovens down
Those are also data schemas for those devices that only work with
Madam a
Until they're kind of building the standard out here
And is it
Great because
It's not interoperable well
No but
It is happening
Yeah I agree I say no it's not great that it wouldn't be interoperable
Between everything in the house for example
But I'd rather at least have
A platform that has its own standard
Yes so that way all of the devices that work with that platform
Suggested words with Madam a
Logo and such
You know it's going to work
You know I think it's smart of Amazon to do this
Yeah I wish it was more open but it is what it is
Yeah and if I mean if you only end up with
Google Amazon
Do we still count homekit
Yeah we can have to count it
So okay
So yes
Those might end up being our
And I mean that's not
Terrible it's
And if you're a developer Building C
New product it is possible to get all those three things working on a device even though it is
Really freaking hard
So it's better than having a degree
Every other
You mention that there's going to be some kid Focus product
That could work with this in fact
Amazon announced that later this year
The Meta make gadgets for
Kids would be implemented and they have four five different
Car makers that plans already brushed spots by while we while we are thinking
Small little robots and things but
They're making smart toothbrushes
Call Brock Bots
San Antonio
Measure motion and cents
It's the motion so that way and the time of kids brushing their teeth
And that could interact with
Matinee
Through this gadgets for
Kids so they
Like how you can make games because
You can have an Interactive
But this toothbrush
Lots of potential
I think so
That really excited plus you tie that to last week
Snooze that we talked about and I think was actually 2 weeks
Which was the
Mattamy talking to sensors
And expanding
Capability
To Central light sensors and sensor stuck to the SmartThings system
And we're starting to see
Some really powerful stuff
With
The
So
Again
Really excited
Don't overlook waddles the smart duck
Waddles the smart. Yes
The rubber ducky that plays music and
Talks to the echo.and
Hangs out with you and your kid
Skip
Okay I joke but man
When my daughter was born you guys it was
And I want you to know that the iPhone wasn't
Get out
Get out so I tell people
Like new moms are like oh you know at least I have my phone while my baby sleeping or nursing or whatever and I'm like
I had nothing
I didn't even have a Kindle
It was a dark time
So
It's good to be a parent
Okay
Peking
Of giant
Smart home platforms let's talk about
Google
I did get my new Google speaker I haven't been home
Witches
Tougher smart home reporter so I haven't been able to install it
But
Soon soon I will be as excited about it as
That's the Lenovo smart cast
Yes but
Their new products
Allegedly
This is the week for alleged products
Let's talk about Google's I believe this is real this looks like a very legitimate
Leak
We knew that Google was going to do its own smart speakers or had plans to do its own it just work with Lenovo and Jay
JBL first
Earlier this year
But a
Site called mysmartprice.,
Apparently has all the leaked information on the
Brand new coming soon
Google home hub
Which is their smart speaker it's a 7-inch display I would anticipate
It will be debuting on October 9th
Because that is the Google Hardware event in New York
And
I like this in I don't like this
That's because
It is very similar in terms of functionality to the existing smart displays
However Stacy you have a camera on your Lenovo smart display along a little privacy shutter and you use that
Duo calls
Surprisingly
There is no camera
On this
This device this device is like a 7in
Tablet in landscape mode
It's patch the back of a
Speaker Bass
Which the speaker bass looks much bigger than what's currently available from the other smart
This place
That's good but I'm shocked ordino Duo support no
Camera that maybe because this is a landscape only device
You know I also think it might be
Might be smart because
People are a little iffy about Google it right at this particular moment in
In time
There's even remember the location drama
Oh yeah
Ghetto in more so than Amazon which has a business model that we
Tend to think we understand
Which you like
They sell us stuff
That's their business
Google is still they have this kind of weird
Add
Director of data broker is what they are
Yeah so I can
See why there might be a little hesitant on this Plus
Harley lowers
The cost a little bit
Good and they also have
Maybe it makes sense cuz you're not cannibalizing their other of their partner
But that's the funny part of it it's almost like hey people don't trust us with data so
We're going to be a little more private up the camera
But he Partners you go ahead and put your
September 2nd
That is
It's kind of funny but whatever
So everything that you're
Smart display
But you haven't had chance to use yet
Can do
This will do so you can
Stream music
Chromecast receiver
You can watch YouTube videos on it you can use the Google Assistant
Controlling your home getting information
Etc and you have the display for all that time
Screen display
So everything we talked about with the
LG Smart display
You can
Do
Here's the thing
The rumor
Is
Which is cheaper than the smart display even the 8in
So that's
Good
Here's the thing that I said I was kind of not excited about
I said back in March
Time for Google to make a smart home hub
And this only supports
2.4 gigahertz and 5 gigahertz Wi-Fi as well as Bluetooth
So I will
Have liked to seen zubeen
Seaway videos in a product like
Or even even
Make it a Google Wi-Fi router
As well.
I don't see any indication of that
This just feels like I'm
Missed opportunity but maybe I'm too needy I don't know
Man you are so focused you
Kevin you're like
Having dreams of
Yes so
You got that straight you like I hate her
But I want a hub
The issue here
And this is a big challenge in
The smart home is for most products that people are buying today
The one-off
Products there like I needed
Hubs
What you want is it be in Z-Wave
Which makes sense
But those are sensor-based products those are for things
Light switches and all kinds
For the most part the only thing we don't really have
Great stuff in
In the Wi-Fi and Bluetooth world
Is sensor
Because you have Wi-Fi
Is battery hog
Bluetooth mesh
Took a while coming and
And it's starting so we might see some Bluetooth sensors that are really capable
But for now
That's what
And I think that'll actually
Relatively
And if it does I'll be okay
I'll be okay
I told about me obviously it's all about it
You know something really cool stuff requires
And
Yeah so I know you
I know you hate the
There's a really good reason they're not out there
If everyone started clamoring for sensors and wanted to really like deeply program their smart home I think we get there
But until then
I don't think
And I should say that you're going to be at this event so
The podcast coming out the week of the Google News
Kevin will have been there
He'll give us all his
Also
Speaking of Google
Little step for you
The Google home Mini
What's the best selling
Turn speaker into tube was it really sold or was it just packaged along with every single device I felt like
I don't know why it's really it's shipments not sales this is a report from strategy Analytics
At a pretty good regardless of the word they use sales or shipment
They say in the second quarter
That
The Google home have 2.3 million Global shipments compared to the echo Dot
Stupid
Tonight
Pretty darn close but
I think
This may be the first time that has happened
Ask could will be
I don't know
I think it's the first time
And speaking of all of this
Especially the housing
I should say because I wrote about it for the newsletter but if you don't read the newsletter
Which is okay
You only listen to us
I had an Amazon smart person
Coming to my house
House and set it to rights
Guess you paid 50 bucks for that
I think it's 4995 and I had a
Lovely gentleman
Who's actually employed by Amazon
Show up at my house
Cost for a hour-long comp
Application
And
Some people ask they were like
Did you do it just to show him up at
I was like I did not I really want it I had some problems with
My implementation
Defects in
Let me tell you guys
This fellow knew
What he was talking about he walks in he's like wow you already have a lot of stuff like within 2 minutes of my home yet identified like all
All of these brands of products
Even identify my Logitech Harmony Hub just a little IR
Receiver that was stuck on top of the cab
And just to be clear
He did not know
Who you were that you do this show or anything like that you
Winter the typical customer process
Yes
I did while he was there
Tell him
You know cuz he was like
You really have a lot of stuff and I'm like
I do this for a living I
Gadgets for
And I'm not mentioning his name
There was absolutely nothing wrong with the experience
Set there had been
Talked about it before we talked
But
I will say
He was prepared to install he was
Prepared to give me advice on which things to buy what we ended up doing because
We have a lot of things
Installed
Is we ended up
Focusing on programming a few
Because I find it so too
I like I'll make him do the boring stuff and maybe I'll have ideas for things I can include
So
We also talked about my naming a
So I have
A lot of devices and sometimes
When I asked
The echo to turn something on or off
Madame Abel be like
Which device did you mean
And I have to say it again
So his advice to me was actually to name everything that was in my living room
Living room light fun
Living room light 2
Living room lights for the group
And
Living room blinds
Sitting room fan
All of these things
Is that actually for some reason help I have been trying to come up with creative names for everything
Because it seemed easier with
Other systems
But I just kind of acquiesced
He did say
Couple things I didn't realize you could add for
Teens if you create a grouping of Lights you can just add the group into the
So you don't have to add the light
Italy witch
Helpful if everyone else do that
Good on that but I didn't
And I was like who
Thank you
And then the other thing
He told me is if I could if I wanted to name things only in The Madam a app
If I didn't want
To do it like my Lutron lights for example like either name them in the Lutron app
And then those would populate because
Is my Lutron hub
Shares data with
Madam
With Siri and
With Google
Or I could just change the names in Madam hey if I didn't
Want to mess up
The names in the other two
This is important
Because
For a while
Google
Really hated it that I named everything in the living
I personally do not want
Different names for everything in each differ
Ecosystem
So I'm still
Dealing with the frustration of certain
Systems like
Different naming
Procedures butt
You know if your
Really organized and you want you
Devices to basically have three different names
You could
So is this available for pretty much anybody wants to
To call Amazon and say Hey I want somebody come to my house or 49 bucks or whatever it is
Help me get started or whatever
So I'm not sure
It came up as an option in my Amazon
Because they're an employee
Of Amazon
My hunch is if you're out in the middle of nowhere
Maybe not
But I bet
You could find it
You're near major city
Right I probably could do it
I don't know that I will but
It sounds like you had a pretty good experience
And
Like would you recommend this
For somebody who's Brand New
That's like the typical question and get right
You know I don't know where to start but I know what I want I don't know what I want to do I don't know what I want to have but I want us tomorrow
So would this be good for those people
Yes
He would be
This one guy
Just this one guy I mean I'm assuming and I should tell you he was a genius before he was so it Apple Genius before he work for
He did
The Border
Where the Rubicon
Not sure which one
So this particular individual
I feel confident saying that if you called this person to your house
That he would be able to help you
Setting stuff up he actually gently prompted me for he's like
What can I see in July
Do you want
Let's do movie time and have a conversation
And I explained what I was after he's like oh yeah that's really cool okay and then he actually even Mesa
Superlative suggestions
Based on the prices I had
And
He suggests he looked around he's like
Oh the Lutron light I love those actually recommend those
Everybody
And you know he liked the wink Hub he liked the ledge.
Lake Harmony
He did not force me to buy a Fire TV infrared
Cute saying
So overall I would say it was a really good experience even
Bless his heart tried to help me find
A Smart Lock
For my front door
Impossible
Because of the Locking
Because he was like already he was gung-ho ready to try it
I text you if I find
If he find something he's now going to be elevated till I coyote hero but
Pradel
I got really positive experience
$50
For an hour of this person
Time you if you didn't feel comfortable installing you probably have to do it at least two
Because you would want this person and there's additional installation piece
But coming out and saying
Oh this is your life will to hear some ideas that might work for you
And here's the products
You should buy
Or I think
You should buy and I think you would actually have a good
Experience
Okay hey
Let's talk about utilities Kevin
Woohoo
Yeah let's do that with Telstra
Right so Telstra down in Australia
Which has now
Iot Networks
So they have a
NB iot Network as well as a cat
M
Network they have hooked up with
Some major water utilities down there we don't know which one
But basically this will allow the water utilities
To track and monitor water usage
Conservation
Netty leak
Etc said something that you as a consumer going to use but maybe it's offered through your utility
Nowthis uses their NB iot Network which covers 3.5
Million square kilometers down there
And
They do have
As I said the cat m
Network as well but they're not using for this and that's because of the amount of data
They're two networks depending on what it is you want
To do
With our team one is better suited than the other
I was just going to remind people nb-iot
Cat M1
Up to
Megabit per second of data so you can do a little bit more
Exactly
Isolate for instance
The water services don't need a ton of
But Telstra does sell three different
Tracking devices
Slap need more bandwidth and therefore
They use the cat M1 Network
Yay
And in other
Exciting
Exciting news
After the utilities is
Insurance
So
A company called a hippo insurance
Is
Doing a deal with a company called no show
And I've written about notion they make these
Discs
Is the best
Hockey they're not hockey
Not that our sensors they have
Temperature humidity water leak
Lot of information motion
Very easy to use
So hippo has done
A deal with notion
To give new hippo cast
Samaritan qualifying States
A notion smart home starter kit
When they sign up for an insurance policy
This is like
About their time and be
Could have what we talked about for a while
Which is trying to
Get insurance companies to subsidize
What is kind of a high price for a lot of smart home devices
Does people feel
Water leak sensors
Kind of pricey I'd rather do something cool like a color-changing bulb
Or nothing
That's probably the more common thing
Things to say
But this is you know your insurance providers helping you out with this kid and
It is also created a policy that integrates the information
From this
It's also the first policy to integrate this information into their pricing so what will happen is not only do you like a lot
Like a 5% discount if you
Add like a security system
Things like that
This they're basically
Lowering the cost as long as you have this kit
Installed
And I think it'll be great to see what kind of data
They get from that
So it's an exciting deal I would keep an eye on it because
If this I think
Actually is
The future
Okay moving right along
What about standards
Iot security standard
Are we excited yet
Going from utilities to standards I don't know in the world I don't know so Sprint has launched
What it's
Calling
The Curiosity iot platform
Oh I kind of made fun of this when it came out
Cuz who needs another iot platform
But here we are
With yet another one
This one has a lot of moving parts so it's not just
Sprint order
Sprint
Portsmouth SoftBank
Who
Now owns arm
Yeah so there's the
Arm for connectivity management and
Sim Solutions
Dislike for provisioning
Cellular devices with iot
As well as something called
Packets another SoftBank company softbank's really smart they're taking the buying all these other companies that are in the space
And then just
Putting together Thomas like being a smart venture capitalist you know using your own
Investment companies
Put things together
But packet
Enables an advanced Network
With bare metal servers at the edge
Watch that can be activated in minutes
Going to Sprint
Yeah and so the bare metal servers are important because the underlying feature here is basic
That you control your Edge Network
Yourself
As a customer and that means you can put your own containers or virtualize it
However you want it also means that you can reduce latency because you're going to run everything at the edge
This is okay right now the network for it is going to be LTE and Cat m
There
They're very excited seeing 5G is coming
Isn't everybody excited by that
Yes I'm like
But let's see other things that are good they thought about power consumption
Which is good they allow you to run this with different operators and different
Countries which is good for you know if your
Monitoring things to travel around
The world and
Their plan is to launch it
In eight areas in November 14th of February and then
150 + 29
Team so that's the Curiosity core they also have an operating system that ties into this and handles
Device and data management all that
Fun stuff that every iot platform
Have anime have on top of that with their call coyotes
Solutions
These are actually pretty
Packaged
Clusters of features for things like vehicle and Fleet Management
Or personal safety
And smart cities
But some of these are
Really aimed it like
Companies that don't want to have to do all this integration work and build everything
And that makes sense because you can
The platform out there but if nobody wants to do the world to use it it's not going to go anywhere so by targeting different verticals use cases
Isn't providing a
Place to start Sara speak or even a whole Solution that's how you're going to get
Customers
Anne-Marie to see if that it will see I mean the devil's in the details on these so we'll see
How Wellspring to straddle the line between
Customized enough
And
Flexibility
Which is everybody
So again nice package will see if people are going to use it
I feel like there's a lot out there but this could give someone a run for their money
Alright next up
Is
BlackBerry
And I'm surprised it took blackberry's so long to really
Get into the iot space but that's what they're doing. They been in there for a while remember cute
Way back in 28 12 2011
They were touting q and x which is an embedded
System software development
As something appropriate for iot
It really wasn't because it didn't have like a
Jeffrey Artis
Yeah qnx was
It still is heavily
In Automotive
Fur entertainment systems and such
And I think they want to leverage infected
Tried to once with their BlackBerry PlayBook
Tablet that went nowhere
So yeah
You're right I guess you could say they tried to
Pivot qnx into something that it really wasn't but
It's okay cuz now they have Blackberry Spark
Exactly
Kevin
What is black
So this is their plan
Top form for it security so it like for example it could cut off a devices connectivity
Send location when deciding on a risk factor
It has unified endpoint management so
That is part of the deployment and updating for devices also notification
Social Security threats
And
Oh I wasn't saying that that's about it however
They also are including something or calling London Shield
And this
Will
Use the data from the system
This could be some people may not like this
It will
Take data from businesses and people that use this technology and use it
Train the AI software
In spark
And therefore the more secure organizations individuals will be at home
People use it and that makes
Sent him a technical standpoint but I wonder if anybody's going to be concerned about
Privacy on these iot devices
Well if it's just this
Security threats incursions that's actually something that a lot of
Security companies actually offer today
A pull that data in and
Then train their bottles and send out
They're paid him for the latest threats and then we also have like
Their groups you
Send your
Threat information
Take a pilot
Panda sounds like that
I don't know there's not a lot of details on London
Okay well we'll wait
Find out for
And in the meantime
It's time to
To talk about
Our question of the day
Rather
Re-entry for the iot podcast hotline
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Don't miss your chance to win a Schlage sense smart deadbolt in Wi-Fi adapter this month
You can enter to win by calling us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And leave us a question
Ben
At the end of this month
Which
Inside September 30th at midnight Eastern Time
Then
We will
Cut off new entries
And we will dry name and announce you guys on the next show and send you out a
Schlage sense smart deadbolt and Wi-Fi adapter
Very nice
Is that a tie
Remember smarter homes start with
Play
Okay so this week
We have
Hazard question
Voicemail from Alistair
Hey Stacy it's Alice to hear from Sydney Australia I'm a long time listener and I'm looking for a solution
For a
Adobada and remote into come
For my apartment that I live in
I have a current you to come
System by scr Electronics
And look around at a few Solutions
Like Melo and
Monkey
But just wanted to know your thoughts and if you had any solutions that's I guess would work better or if there was any kind of
Solution
That would be great thanks for not much
LOL Alistar about a year ago someone else had this exact
Same question for me
And they too were looking at
Nelo
And just so you know the monkey
Popcorn that you're taking out actually became mellow hits started as a Kickstarter for monkey
And now it is
Hello
Really trying say the word mellow
Okay
So what this is
This is a speaker that you pop on the intercom
Button area in
Your apartment
And
Yes your existing
And it's inside your apartment
And it basically it communicates with the electrical signals
That are happening so you can
Talk to the person at the door if
Want to and
You can also
Send a signal to open the
Now that's all well and good
If you want them to come
All the way up into your
Apartment though
After you post them in you're going to need a Smart Lock
On your door
And you're going to have to
Open that
So that's kind of how that
Works
Danella website
If you know your intercom Baker they
Give you
Compatibility information
They seem pretty compatible slots
Announce have a 30-day money-back
Guarantee
So if it doesn't work you
I don't know how hard it is to install I don't have this problem so I haven't tried this device
Based on the Nilla website
It doesn't seem too difficult to install
Stop it literally connecting to your existing intercom
System in your apartment,
And therefore it's not any
Drilling ordering like that
You literally
Canada
Connected via jumpers
To your existing intercom so
System and when you're done when you move in that complex you can actually unwire and take it with you so it doesn't seem so
So bad but it's going to be late
500 euros
Back
That's a lot of money
But if you never want to get off the couch
It might be worth it
True
A lot of money
No I mean there are people with like mobility issues
Or you don't do parents
You got a baby in one hand
Amazon Echo in another
This is high drama
Waddle the Ducks running around I mean let it slide
So yeah Alistair that seems to be the best option and
The nice thing is it doesn't require your landlord
Cuz I was thinking of
Nest doorbell out there type
Black butt
Then you got to talk to your dorm in a lot of
Apartments have
That's actually another thing depending on your apartment
Depending on your country's regulations
You may not be able to install a Smart Lock on Europe
Apartment because there rules about
Someone having a master key
Need to give emergency
Personal workers
In cases of fire in
That sort of thing so just be aware
Of that
Good point
But you could at least get the Buzzard
Okay
Or you can actually do that not worried about fires
Your call
It's up to you
Okay
So if you have a question or you would like to enter to win
Can a Schlage sense smart deadbolt wifi adapter
Give us a call at 512-262-3742
24 and we met
Answer your question
All right
It is time to move on to our guest this week's guest is Kim Kelly the CEO of Hampton products
And he's going to talk about a new Wi-Fi powered
Smart Lock that they
Last week the impact of tariffs
On iot devices
Other consumer devices
This is big news
In the World At Large so
And now
A word from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Where is Basque
And I have json man who is VP of iot it's at
Ask you to talk to us
In the last few weeks we talked about sass
Edge computing
And what it's doing with iot
This week we're going to talk about the iot
Partner ecosystem you guys are
Can you tell us a little bit of
Jordans the critical element
And I empty space
The fact is there most
Components that are
Required to bring together two
Complete the total solution
Infor customers
If you think about the accident
Played
Locomotive
Or turbine
Or windmills
Abscess
Some cells that are generating the data with all of the
Appointments around
There's a storage Networks
Weatherby cloud or crimmins the network itself
In the Methodist
The transport
The data and there's so many variations
Snare from
Satellite
Will power win Networks
5G
Xiaomi next
Matisse is certainly critical
And we think certainly an important
Component of that is analytic
So we really feel like
These ecosystems have
Define tested verified for
A total salon
Where do you see the examples of this ecosystem approach
Helping customers get better
Results so you do see it across
Industry what are folks
Just identified
These industry clouds
Partners that are in the
Space coyote
Key platforms
Non example and then work
Put them to plug Sasson as he Analytics
Choice a great example of that is important
We have with g
Transportation
And their ads
Offering
Where SAS is
Embedded
And their device
In this case those devices
Deployed locomotives but they can be deployed to any high top
Last. End
Helpful
What's processing at the edge
And the prep for data is
Get back into
The server found
So that's one example where we're seeing Great Sea
Success with helping
Dwell time
Holly sociated
Fuel burn
An early in the
Indication of
Central failures.
The Operators
And it sounds like when you're dealing with
Lots of Partners
In the iot we are that
Openness
This is really a big
How do you guys a
Dress that it certainly is Bears wide Market adopt
What we have to be
Be sure of is that we're not
Displacement technology
Around Latin invest
Center Channel partners
Or operators have
What some of the open
Resource capability
How use Python path
Example
BYU Sadat with respect
Creating models what we do find is that there is an issue with
With being able to transition
Modeling language
Into operation
Employment where
Do you have Enterprise scale in
Sustainment
Being a primary object
And we try to help
Xplatform
As a basis
This for that token
Value
Excellent where can we go to find out more about SAS
The best place for iot information in our ecosystem
We found golang
Chess.com
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Kim Kelly the CEO of Hampton products
Hi Kim how are you doing today
I'm great Stacy how are you
Superb
And I am excited to talk to you because
Just this month
You guys launched a
Ran
Connect a lock on them
And it's kind of different than most connected
So we're going to talk about that but first
Let's level set with
Hampton products International
What is that
Canton was established to create a security Hardware platform
Initially and padlocks
Portable security
We call it now
And we knew that over time we would be able to create Barry
Innovative
Branded security Hardware
Not only in padlocks button door locks in
Security Hardware in electronics
No one at that point
Forshaw
The Advent of iron
Chase and The Internet of Things
But that has given us a real opportunity to create some very distinctive
Security Hardware products
Underboss the Brinks
And the Hampton brand name
So we did launch Deer Point last
Thursday we announce that the array deadbolt would begin shipping on or about October 1st to Consumers
And we're really excited about that lawn
Okay when I saw the lock I was
Most impressed by the fact that it uses
Wi-Fi
And it has
Solar panels
It so it can charge if it's outdoors
Obviously not if you installed this
Patrick Rodgers
Why go with Wi-Fi Bluetooth
Some of the other
Technologies out there
2010 when we started this what has become an odyssey and we designed
Connected home platform we knew that consumers
Told us that they wanted to start with the deadbolt
They call that kind of a handshake as you're going into the house
And so for years ago weed
Cat outline
The structure of
The way this deadbolt should be built and as we interviewed consumers and we talked to lots of people in the iot world
They all said
If there's a way for you to do this without creating a hot or a Gateway and it could just connect directly to the home router
That would be awesome
What we knew would be a challenge
Most people in residential loan don't have power to the front door so we knew we'd have to come up with a really robust battery
Software configuration that would
Extend battery life behind just a couple of weeks
Over the last 4 years
By combining the solar
Technology with some really Innovative battery and circuitry
Technologies
We've been able to create a platform where
Is this lock is in
Installed in your phone
Contour you make that up to seven eight or nine months
Battery life out of a
A single battery
If you get indirect sunlight
Your 90 days and if it's installed in your garage to your point
Then it's going to be probably 30 days max
So to account for that
We elected ultimately to put
5200 milliamp batteries in each package so that the consumer can keep one battery fully charged
When they
Array app tells you that your battery is down to maybe 10% life left
Then you can pull it out and put in your second battery in that process takes about 5 Seconds
With this locket
MSRP used
Compared to some of the other locks
The closest is going to be the nest by Yale lock
Its 2:40
Are you concerned that you're coming in high
In this market
We really have challenge ourselves in her thinking about the value and originally our Target price was to be between 249
To build in
The solar technology and
Give consumers to $50 suggested retail price batteries in a single package
Forced us to take the
Suggested retail price to 299 initially expecting like a
Every consumer product
In the
Field that over time we're going to be able to squeeze cost out and check right now we're working on a new prove battery
Allergy and to your point of Non Solo version that could be installed in the garage with Superior battery life and clearly a
Lower price because we wouldn't have the solar technology built into the lot
So yes I think it's relatively high price
Very premium products going in it's a great to deadbolts
Which will mean something to a locksmith and consumer some consumers a lot too
Customers who insist on a real high-quality deadbolt product
The foundation for these iot devices
But over time we do expect
Text that it would be able to be
Reduced in cost that it would still connect directly to the consumer
Router near home Wi-Fi
And that battery life could be extended as the Technologies continue to improve
The focus of the show isn't actually on the product but I did want to talk about it
What you do
And
What I really wanted to talk to you
To about his something that's actually on our minds this week
Because
It's happening again is Terrace
And this weekend
The Trump Administration
Said they might
Actually go forward with another round of tariffs
Roughly 200 billion dollars worth of
Chinese Goods
A lot of these are going to hit the Consumer Electronics
So I'm very curious
About your take
So Pro tariff
Or not protest
Well mostly I'm in favor as I think the administration is
Of a Level Playing Field
And for sure
Coming into the United States and moving into China
The playing field isn't level across all categories
Witness racing has focused on
At this point in the additional
200 billion dollars worth of
China Imports into the United States as you pointed out
And I think any change
Interest
He's going to significantly impact most us busy
This proposal will impact
Thousands of
Businesses in the United States
If we didn't do anything and simply absorb the tariffs
And we're unable to pass our pricing long
It would put our company out of this
So I'm going to guess that there
A number of
Unknown
An unintended consequences
That would be associated with this move
For sure most companies in our industry are going to be impacted by this proposed next round of tariffs
But you understand the impact
Or the background
You really have to understand
What consumers in the United States have grown to expect and what retailers
Have gone out of their way to be able to provide for them
The retailers
Feel that there's
Appropriately
An obligation for them to give consumers the
The best value
On each one of the products that they offer
So that is the highest quality products
The best price
And to ensure that in a global market
The retailer
Jet that value they hold line reviews virtually every year and every product
Hampton has spent 27 years
In Southeast Asia
Principally in China
Making sure that we could provide the
The best value
To our customers
And then on to
There
Consumers so that we remain competitive
That we're going through a process of
Continuous Improvement
And that were able to meet
Our customers and their consumers expectations
That makes sense I do love buying things for cheap
So let's talk about your history
With Chinese Manufacturing
Because
Obviously this company has been around for a while
And where is it manufactured
Its products
When we bought the Old Hampton Lock Company back in 1990 would actually did have any 85% ownership in a small
Allied manufacturing concern in Taiwan
Shortly after that
Because I have been going to church
3 years
We ended up moving most of the manufacturer
Bring into China
Because we found in one case that there was generations of
Experience making the products that we were interested in making an expanding
The change that we've seen in China has been
Lab Hood
Significant
But it's taken Generations
To take
China from a relatively primitive Manufacturing
Concern in the 80s
To a world leader in a number of different Industries today
They've got great Labor
Phenomenal work ethic
Access to Quality raw materials
They're operating in Global Market
The key Shoppers Best Value in raw materials anywhere in the world
They've got a willingness to co-invest in the equipment in the tooling and
People training
Especially engineering
Over the last 30 years they've built
Terrific Inland transfer
Irritation improve their ports
Their powers
Supply and more recently there
Concern about environmental and
Sustainability issues has become
Much more acute
We got an example in one of our Pact
Where 80% of our power
For the factory plus
The seven dormitory
That we operate on this facility
Are solar power
And there are many factories like that even in the United States today
So
The significant investor
That people have made in wages and benefits
Healthcare and families and quality of life
To be upset by
Tariff
Dispute
And so we're hoping that the
The trade War
Doesn't happen it will have
As I said not known and unintended consequences not hundreds of thousands of businesses including ours
Okay so would you be able to or willing
To move manufacturing somewhere else
We may be forced to
A couple of points on this
Hampton Inn 1999
Made significant commitment to manufacturing facilities in
Southeast Asia we continue to make those Investments until 2008 9 and 10 when it be
Became clear that if the trends continue
Economic labor environmental health care if the trends continued in China
That we were seeing an ocean Freight continue to be as expensive as it had become
But it might make sense for us to move manufacturing back to the United States which in three or four categories we did in two
2013 14 and 15
So we know exactly
To the penny
How much it cost
To make these products
In the United States
And after three and a half years of trying
We also know we ended up having to shut her those factories and move it back to Southeast Asia because we couldn't be competitive in the
Long-term with other countries manufacturing if we were to move our Manufacturing
Across the street
Within one country it would take a year it would create incredible disruption and it would be very expensive
To move it to another country is increasingly
Expensive and increasingly complicated
Because you got to deal with different
Cultures
Different languages
Different environmental regulation different labor laws Etc and that's his takes time
And the issue that we've all got
The people in are in the sky
Have with the Tariff proposal is there's no time
July
Proposal was that the Tariff
Burden on the
200 billion dollars
And imports
Would be around 10
First that number increases
25%
Any tariff
Will have a meaningful impact
Not only are cost
But potentially ultimately the cost of the American Consumer one could argue that it could be short-term but
Short-term pain
Which some have described as
Relatively insignificant short-term pain
Versus the big picture we believe is true
But for us to move manufacturing to another country
Will take time
And there are no guarantees that we're going to be able to
Replicate all of the different things that we were able to create in China
Okay so let's talk about something a little bit more fun let's talk about innovation
You guys
Last year
Actually established a relationship with a company called benjilock
It was on Shark Tank for having a
Connected padlock
I would love to get your take and some tips from you
On how to bring
Something that
Very cool very Innovative but
May not be up to
The quality standards of a physical
Device
And kind of smelled those two worlds together effect
It's been an exciting Journey
One of the things that we've learned over
The last 27 years is that nearly every product sold in the United States is way more complicated than it looks
We looked at categories that you look you'd say
How's difficult
Could that be I'm not once you begin to understand with the standards in the industry and the consumers expectations
And Manufacturing process
He's been required
We walked away from
But we do know how to make padlock
Actually know how to make door locks and we know how to make lighting and Electric
Products and so with benjilock
When we saw this product at CES in January 2017
And it had one and Innovation award at Cas and we said
How can a padlock when the Innovation award
An electronic
Michelle and we met Robbie Cabral the inventor and we said while this is a really cool product and boy is it going to be tough
Because we understand what it takes
The bill padlocks we didn't know a lot about
And we didn't know a lot about the electronics that would have to support the two of them how you integrate
We work with Robbie
And we looked at this
Technology
There's a way for us to deliver this technology to the consumer in a way that
Could really Delight
The consumer and it could
Meet or maybe even exceed
The expectations of the event
Fast forward to October
And Robbie goes on Shark Tank
And he develops a relationship and ultimately
Secures investment from Kevin o leary mr wonderful
And in November
Kevin and Robbie
Gucci Mane
And I ended up negotiating a
License arrangement
Where to buy Hampton Wood manufacturing Market benjilock initially in North America and we went on TV
Robbie finally on November 30th
Live on
CNBC
Halftime report
Live on CNBC
We met for the first time live our team has been working with Robbie
4/8 months but he and I didn't actually meet
Until we saw each other live
On CNBC
It was a real feel good moment
And the last eight months
Has been filled with
Engineering back-and-forth testing
Penetration testing all the stuff that goes with making a reliable
Sakura product that's got some cool technology
My point is that building a reliable
Your Hardware Prada
Is difficult
Understanding technology
Today
Is relatively simple
But marrying the two
Is
Varidesk
So when you're looking for a way to take a
Very complicated piece of technology and put it into a relatively simple
Security pro
Padlock
Deadbolt door lock or security lighter
Coach light fixture or even a camera you've got to pick the right partners
He's got to figure out a way to Roadmaster products
So that
The Partnerships that you've created and the technologies that are going to be required anticipate not only the
Consumer needs in the market
Condition of today but can have some kind of line of sight to see what's going to happen Downstream nothing
Thing is more
Complicated today then
Creating roadmap for The Internet of Things
Okay I agree with you it is hard to create product lines for the inter
What are the big challenges assoc
Well first you got to start with being able to market the profit
So
As we're looking at security Hardware products
We think we're pretty good at making reliable
Figure products
Since we've been in business we've sold over a billion and a half
Units of locks and Light
Adding an electrical
And we made years of Investments and in some cases we got generations of skill
That's required
To build these products
Understanding the teks
Is pretty straightforward
But the steps that we went through were
Pretty straightforward
For a consumer packaged Goods
So the first thing you have to decide is can it be done
The internal sessions that we had talking about can we build
Connected
Dental that will connect directly to
Consumers Wi-Fi and would not have power
And just because you can do it doesn't mean that you should
So we went out and talked to a bunch
What do you really want in this product and in our case it was
Security and convenience
The combination of two except to the extent that your product ends up not being either secure or it becomes an
Then you missed the mark and then you got understand
What your core competency
What are you good at and then you got to go out and rims
The rest of it so we need security Hardware
But we didn't know anything about Cloud technology or the software in the firmware in the app development that would
Deport all that so we have to go out and interview partners
And what made that tough
And pretty
What's the whole list of unknown unknown
Because you're talking to people who are going to help you invent something or create something
That's never been done before
So how do they point
To something that says in my area of expertise I know I can do this
Because they've never done
Before so
Iot platform
AR
Covering a whole bunch of different Prada
But just because it's an iot product doesn't mean that
Somebody who has X
Rotation one area biote is actually going to be able
Translate their skills into another area
So I might be able to create an iot voice-activated platform but it doesn't mean that I can make a deadbolt I might be
Able to create a security camera or a light switch
Coyote but it doesn't mean that I can create a deadbolt
So we went through and we identified
Embedded a whole bunch of different partners
And
While we're developing the product we have to
Continue to do market research to make sure that the world in passes by
While we were busy developing the widget that we had identified back on day one
And so the array product
AcuRite head bolt
And then she like
Have gone through in the case of a race 70
Different iterations
Over the four years
Most of them in the last 12 months
And benjilock we made most of our changes to the design and development of the product in the last
90 days before launch
We launched benjilock
Annie
August of 2018
And as I said we wants to write last Thursday and September and will begin shipping that on or about October 1st
Awesome alright but we've come full circle in this interview
Kim I really
You coming on the show
It's been my pleasure
And remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter
Butter and Stacy on
Coyote
Dot-com will see you next week