Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
EvanTube
And today we have a
An amazing show for you we are actually
Recording from CES
Could I be honest
Where to Bar in Vegas and so
We're going to see how this goes hopefully you enjoy the slice
Life is that were offering you here
This is episode
197 of the show The Show sponsored by Farrakhan which has a new C3 iot
Database
To talk about later on in the show
And you're going to hear all the news that we've seen so far at
CVS
Plus you're from our guest
Jacob atalla
With Katie Holmes
Talking about how they built
The next generation of Home including
Connected devices a focus on Wellness
Sustainability and more
You're going to like it
I wish I lived in
This home now
And now a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a marrow
Are you looking for an iot flat
Find out my Kenmore and D-Link makes a pharaoh
Apparel customers
Have experienced as much as an 80%
Reduction in time to Market
Support calls in a 10 expire activation rate
Plus they can reuse 90% of their work from one project
The next
To learn more does it a pharaoh
Dot IO
That's a f e r o
So let's get started with
I don't know the biggest news we probably saw was
I'm going to go with
Google home
Yes a Google had a press only event
Before CS even open on day one
Discussions about what they were going to do because they have this
What looks like a ride
Set up in the parking lot
And there was a ride
I went on it
But the big news was
Really they're trying to expand
Make it easier for Hardware makers to implement
Google Assistant
Devices
Amazon has done with the Echo and the details are scarce it
Coming soon
For heartburn
Makers and you're talking about assistant
Kitchenettes correct
In that
Almost
Compares to
BMO
Amazon
Connect kit
But that is a hardware base
System that lets you build
Basically slot this thing into your device
You have all the
Functionality
Connect to
Google when is in a hardware device
Yet it may one day also have a hardware component
It's not
What else should we know about it
Right so developers and Hardware makers will find out in the coming weeks how they can
Unemployment Pat
There are some new devices
I guess you could call them new form factors is a small little 4 inch touch screen
Lenovo device that is
Looks like a little mini
Google home hub
Really called the
Google Smart Lock
So
The speaker has a microphone backtracking to watch
Videos on it
At least not yet you're not going to see Google photos on it
At least not yet
It's really meant for
Setting Smart Alarm which it will
Set based on your morning and evening routines
It's only $79
Set those routines
Well it's probably going to suggest some
But you could have a ride or you
You can set your own
When you think about an hour
Use Google Assistant it knows where do you work when you work
You're commuting all that
So based on
Traffic
I say hey will you get up earlier today
Etc
It should take care of that for you they said it will suggest
Based on your roots
That's pretty cool it will not show you photos
That's okay
And now that we're talking
He better than like I was Google's news the biggest news I don't know the bigger news might be the Samsung ecosystem
I'm kind of effort news
What do you think the TV news with
Remote control with
Of course your buddy Bixby and
Matinee and hey Google
And I
Stepanek coming out of nowhere for Samsung to partner up
Smart TVs with Apple
But yeah so
A lot of the Samsung president was
Arie hasit the last ice age two years to be honest
They were very few alipay product announcements and more of the vision
And that vision is still Bixby
But I think I said last week in a post that
If they do
Partner up with somebody else
That maybe that's the white flag
Bixby
And that's what they've done they are
Partnering with Google
You'll have Google assistant on all Samsung
Smart TVs
This year
The family Hub is getting upgraded the family Hub 2.0 and that's for the fridges
Things I've integrated screens I mean they showed up
Photo frame
Picture of that again but I
You don't want to spend $1,000 on a fridge for a photo frame
However
It did have recipe suggest
Chin through Bixby
Nano however is here I'm not going to spend
$8,000 on a fridge with a giant
Ice cream that has
Limited value
Another drink and you might
Yeah I agree
That's the trying to do too much I think
The fridge
They had in a washing machines that would
Give me notifications when the washing machine is done your laundry is ready to be
Put in the dryer were folded in
How do I set notifications
We kind of joke
Inside will buy a new washer and dryer but really that's
What's happening
So yes
Defiance
Space
I'm just going to say are you guys ready
Need to have a range hood
It has a
Screen init or some sort of crazy a i in it
Mge
Appliances
Which is now actually owned by higher
The Chinese company
They were showing off and I see
4-H
7 inch
Touchscreen beautiful things
Is part of your downdraft
We are still
And I mean it's like the Hub of your kitchen it shows recipes
It doesn't lie
But I don't
Feel like I do this
It's crazy expensive
Bosch also
Nothing much smaller than that but also did have
Screen functionality
Holiday in intelligence associated with
What are those things called
When I don't know
No no it's the thing that comes over this
Stove in like sucks all the bad Arrow
Fan
Yeah okay
Anyway
So I was running around
Like looking at some of the smarter kitchen
Haier washer
Against
Same thing what is
Become very clear though is you will not be able to buy a device
Connected to the internet
The fridge
Probably even a dishwasher
Definitely an oven or stove and probably a wash
So your major appliances
Does are going to be connected and when I didn't hear anyone talk about what I asked about
Was like how the heck they plan
Sporty's and how long they plan to support these
Because it's
Cyber security risk
And please
Some of these are built on like
They're not built on Android things anymore they used to be built under like Android tablet
It was like scary as all hell
I don't know what feels risky
Elsa
Maybe not as
How much value
Send a lot of money on
I would say
Honestly
Team here has been disappointment
I've been looking
For like really cool things in Granite were only a day in
Days Inn
I'm not seeing anything this like
Future technology
I would agree and we said last year how you saw Madame a
Google home everywhere
But this year it's actually
There are more
Mentions are products with those Integrations than
There are we
Without those ID
Integrations
So it's even more than last year
In a lot of wacky stuff
I don't know technology companies trying to like
Add smart or something to
Sleep
And
We must address
Which is the color
Smart toilet that has mattamy built
Intuit
And I like Poler stuff
They have a powered faucet they have
You that are going to let you know have lighting
Recipes for your bath
Routine
But I don't know. I don't think I need toilet what about you
I certainly do not
And
What you could do and I saw this at the color connect
Today
They do have
A voice integration
In their mirrors now
So That's Amore
Replace I think for it
I don't need you know my personal information about my toilet going
You don't want Amazon I don't particularly care
My privacy
But most people
Probably don't want to hey he just did a number two
I think you need a little more toilet paper
Yeah
So I like what colors doing
On the Kinect stuff
With the
Faucets
Shower seems we're going to customize shower routines
Thanks for individuals you know they menstruate
But I don't think it needs to be in a toilet I like
The mirror
I'm looking at that
That's not my intent
Actually smart mirrors here mostly from smaller companies and then things like color
So what are you looking for in a smart mirror
I'm just curious because
I feel so obvious but then I'm like
Wait a second do I really need that
I have a Google home in the bathroom I talk to it all the time and it gives me a lot of information I would
In the mirror
I think that would be redundant then
I think most
People do not have
Like a home hub in the bathroom
No screens
In the bathroom
Sorry it's not a home hub it's a mini
It's a Google mini so there's no screens but I mean I asked
My calendar I asked you
The news
I guess I can play the
Play videos
In the news right now
Smart mirror in my bathroom but
Yeah there's something about having the visuals
When you ask for information like what's the weather today
You don't just get
Hear what today is happening
A visual hour-by-hour perhaps
Cloud with
Little raindrop
Important to
Or vector with his little eyes crying
Cuz it's raining
Oh and let's bring this up because Kevin
Haven't managed to find the only
Possibly madhumeh powered robot in the whole place
And he is very excited and happy
And I am
Not
Super excited
What is this product and why are you excited about it
Alright the robot's name is Timmy
If the company is rowboats Hemi
It's a $1,500 robot companion robot only obviously more expensive
Repeat all
Shut up
Really nice high resolution
Display
Hilton Fallsview
Camera
Since you can use it for video conferencing you can use it for getting information
But they have announced that they are
Landing
I didn't do it yet they're planning
The coming month
Amazon announced
So I think that's going to happen
What is 15
$100 so I don't know
Icing on the cake
Behind Chinese
Robotic had there's a place
Temperature Conan Wireless
Does your phone battery last for 8 hours
Did you know that
My house
I'm sure it will be a very fulfilled and happy robot Kevin
Happy divorce
Fraternity
Kevin
What is $1,500 robot
It's not even
In other anime
We had
A bunch of products
Just come out
They can be controlled by Maddow
Leviton Boeing
Blah blah blah
More interesting Lee was I
Yeah launch their new smart roller blinds
Control through matinee
I saw these acts
Ashley backlash
Spring I think when I was in
Whenever I visited Ikea I got to
And they're pretty cool
Enterprise points
Pretty
Cheap I don't know do you
Did Ikea
I didn't see
Pricing but I
No
They they are fairly the pricing they gave me
It was pretty cheap
So let's see
Other than that
You know there's a lot of
One-off little device
Isis there was a lot of stuff with the Amazon
An automotive
So ties in with
Pioneer
Electra bed
Some other companies I'm still waiting for Miami
Nissan auto device
Actually
Really and it's interesting because today
Google also announced to
New our Hardware Partners JBLM
Anker
So basically you plug this into your
Cigarette lighter
And then it was
Actually let's
SU
Connect your phone to your car and it
Has its own
Canceling
Microphone
To make it better for your input
In the car so
I don't know pricing on those they were
Turn off today but
Yeah they want in the car as well
In addition
Amazon there was actually one kind of peace
Snooze that I thought was really interesting is that Chamberlain
When is working with them to bring
MyQ garage door ecosystem
For Amazon Prime members now you can have your package
Is delivered through Amazon
Key Program to your garage
Which I was like all there for that
Amazon key
Amazon people in my home no Amazon people in my garage
I don't know Kevin
Yeah that makes more sense
Wouldn't work for me because we leave the
Inside door opener
Unlock rather
But
Open and close at
No that's okay I just
I locked myself out one too many times I just leave it unlocked now but
Most people would
Haven't set up where we safer more secure
And they be comfortable letting Amazon drop
The packaging
Garage sales
Yeah yeah think about it this way you can put a refrigerator in your garage a lot of people already have something like that
Groceries in crazy stuff
Oh yeah
See okay
So that's going to be in 37 cities
And there's not a fee associated with that
Peoples were like Diehard Chamberlain users may be surprised by that because
Cuz they did a
Associated with their if this then that integration
People were up in
In arms
I talked to Jeff Meredith who is the president
And CEO of Chamberlain about this
And he said that they are evaluating their
A strategy and they don't think they're going to do that going
Forward
I don't know what's going to happen
Maybe you want
See that happening
I hope not because most people use
If services
Free so they add on
People the wrong way and I understand that
Should go back the other way to free but it's up to them
Does it cost money for companies to act
Their services
Those are not free
They're free for us but
What is subsidized
Survivor
Iherb
Cheap small news item
Consider worth talking
About let's see D-Link has
Outdoor
Outlet
That's going to be about
P44 rated
So not the best
Best version of that but it is a Wi-Fi outdoor
Do you want an ip64 rated which means you can drop it
You would actually
Go with the new tp-link
Casa
Lineup they actually are
Launch in outdoor rated
IPC
64 version
Apple WiFi Outlet
That's pretty sweet
They
Tp-link guys are actually putting in a whole bunch of new Prada
Ismart Camera
Outlets
A bunch of stuff and they're actually going to create some
Smart AI
We're going to be trying that one
Later
So one other thing that I really like
Because I want to get rid of devices and boxes in my house
And I'm not saying I'm going to replace all this
However
I was very impressed by the
The First Alert onelink smoke detectors that
Have
Mesh Network
So there is smoke detector carbon monoxide detector
They have matinee built-ins they don't like it
Speaker so now that you can play music on them
There's a Google Assistant model in the works
Unfortunately it sounds like you're going to have to
Choose
Dubai V matinee version
Google Assistant version
They're working on it
There's no pricing yet I know the current model without mesh Network
Is 249
So my guess is you're looking at least $300
War
These things however
These are your
Wi-Fi
Access points throughout your house they get rid of all the other
Devices that you know you smart speakers
What's your
Best access point
So you're free up a lot of outlets
Everything is big
Best networking threats your house that's a bonus
They're smart in the sense that
Detect some issue it knows
Roommates and just like when you set up
Lights in particular room in your Smart Hub
Anakin say hey there's a fire in your office or whatever
I'm sorry it is too or
$300
Weather for 249 without the mess right now
So 249 without them
I have at least
10 smoke detector
In my house replace the mall you can have a very capable mesh network with just maybe 2 or 3 days
I don't think so Kevin
Let's see what else do
Solutran
ISmart
Fan control switch
This is
Nice
Because it controls your fan all
Different speed element
We get a lot of requests
For this
Most people want Wi-Fi
And not like the Lutron
Proprietary but if you have
I said
It'll be lovely
Try to think of what else
OGE actually has a new
Switch
It is a wife
Lots of people are
Sick of having hub
Which Kevin and I will
Delivery with Kevin
Like waving his hands like
Yes yes
I'm not sick of having
I kind of gave in wave the white flag and said I guess I'll die
Cuz you're dying a slow painful death
That you wouldn't believe that if you went past
Boots like I did today there lots of lots of products there
Manufacturers are
They're starting to move forward
Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
Send natively work with
The digital assistants so that way there's
Ange's new CEO
So those
Work with
Bluetooth
The Google home
And they're $30 for your regular ball than
44 Eur
BR30 bright
It's a little bit expensive but
You know
I'm thinking about do I just pull the plug on my way
Now cuz I don't really use too many sensors
So
Igo hubless
Oh my God
I cannot go homeless
Mistake 4 and all my holiday lighting is on a Z-Wave outdoor
Switch
But now with all the wifi options
The D-League option
Tp-link options
You could actually do this in a lot of people are just now getting into the Smart Hub
Probably not though
People think they're pretty people out there who are
Wifiby
And we saw it mean if I'm going to pick trends
For the show that
Definitely
Oh my God why fire
Do not give me anything weird
Newsies
Death of the Hub is what it seems like
Alright so we're killing the Hub
We're going to call at CES 2019
Yeah I've given Kevin a moment cuz I say any words
Is it like a eulogy for the Hub
I'll miss my hub
Because there are a lot of autumn
Instead I set up there
That
Especially with sensors
You know what's going to happen
They're still motion
Panthers and
Door sensors
My garage door sensor
Z-Wave or zigbee
Mike reebals
You know Kevin is
Assuming the Hub right now to bring it back
I will say I ran into two sensors Bluetooth based on sir
From Rubio
I'm going to try to get
Review units for those to see how long they last
Loose you didn't know
Improvement
And also
Profiles
Smart Home
Going to start doing is
It done profiles for lighting
Forever
But as the expenditure more and more types of
The devices are trying to build
Easier to like Herman what they are and how they
Sew in
2019-2020
Start seeing that
A different
In the number
Hang out there
About protocols and stuff
We'll talk about
Hey guess what
Read Macbeth.
If you listen to us
Episode
Is the third year that
We've heard about the bread
Alliance pushing.
Uniform stand
Dbrand
We're just still here on that
We're not going to see those products
Yeah we've been
Is third time around now
Are waiting waiting waiting so I don't understand what's happening there
Your interoperability is coming from Amazon Echo or Google home right now
That is
The reality that
Scene in the show
Baidu
I didn't
A lot of really cool tack but I did like
Bosch
He AI
Which is
Sims 4 projections
And it's basically a
Projector is it is
Display you mount it underneath a cabinet
Kitchen in a project
Videos
It can
Play
That she could even estimate the weight of things like
Which I thought was
Crazy
Can identify food
It's very much designed right now
I've long thought the smart
Needed a flexible
Screen option
So I'm kind of excited by this but a lot of other
It's not going to work
Well I don't know what the cost is so that could be an issue
Flexible screens aren't she be there so
I think in the kitchen right now you're looking at a small
Smart display
And inexpensive
Having a smart display
I don't know the price and it's going to come out
In China
In March is what
She saying
And in the US
You know
Buy flexible I mean more like I could
Projected
Anywhere
And I could interact with it is
Supposed to flexible light foldable
Which I'm sure they're both
Prince here at CES
What would I do like about it was that you could interact
Little bit
Interesting Lee
Like so like there was a demo where they shooting
Or actually they showed a demo of like
Ikaw you're like
Which part of the cow are you
Are you wanting to eat
Depressed it was a diagram
Are you press it and it would talk to you about how to
Rapper take care of that state while you have your state next to you
I don't want to see like a picture of a real cow
Bambi was a deer
But still
I like the thing I like the projection on the cake where you have a slider under the cake
And you can say I want
Taking this many
Pieces
And you would slide and the protector
That was awesome
Exact
Silver $300
I would not cuz I don't need a lot of cake well you can also instead of a screen that you have
In your kitchen
It's not
I mean if you bet
Sticky hands
Does it matter
Satanic like a smart
Display the
Turn
You need it I don't know I'm kind of one of those little hand sanitizer so I don't have to
What does SUS mean
Alright Kevin clearly doesn't
I'm like at some point in time you have to get hands and you just need to get
Why don't eat ribs or corn on the cob
Summers where the food okay
That's distressing
We find out if
Fiesta
Alright let's see
Before we end
What other things
Do we think
We're worth noting
Iowa
Through until smooth it was a lot of 5G I should tell everybody
If you're into 5G
Place to be
So much
Surprising again that's that I'm like nothing
Super Innovative and I was really
If you want to fix
She be great if you want to connect an appliance
Also fine
ACV with
Very little for cake
Yet we were in one of those Cycles right now right you have
Something that really moves the needle and for a couple years
Add apps
Does whatever that new
Today is
But now we're next like love
Smart speakers digital assistants
WhatsApp
Connectivity everything and we're just riding the wave
The next big thing
Alright so
My prediction for the next big thing
Interfaces
How about
Interfaces that are like embedded in your ears and on your eyeballs
Not your eyeballs
Kevin and I tribe
North glass
McLeod
My big thing
You know I'm not going to
Surprise you
Companions robot assistance
I just look at my eye roll here
Visible or Audible
Gyro
She loved
What's my Vector I send her videos of vector doing all kinds of cool thing
And she loves every single one of them
First of all
Alright so
We got a mind let's take a moment to go to the Internet of Things podcast
Highline
Hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Smarter home
Start with slave
And by the way we did
CSA Wi-Fi powered sled lock which is a first
And pretty significant for anybody who doesn't want to deal with
Bluetooth CD or
So all of that
Is now out there
Raichu
Firefly cast
Hotline
If you would like to leave us a voicemail
Message give us a call
623 7
4 to 4
And we've met
Just answer your question
Let's get to this
Question
Which is
Scrum
Josh
Hi Kevin
Joshua Castillo
Minnesota
Love the podcast appreciate all the info
Operation
My question is about
The far-field Mike's
Christian Amazon Echo
A Google home wondering why they don't just put those in
Phone
Turn your phone into basically a portable echo or
Google home
I like to just be able to go wherever I am take my phone out of my pocket put it on the on the table and
I got my assistant right there so why can't they are why don't they put those far-field Mike's
Answer the phone
That's a great
Question.
Because of the Samsung press event
Their new smart TV remotes that have
Fairfield Metro
And that's awesome because instead of having the remote in your hand or needing to
You can be anywhere in the room right now
Centerview
Living room
Frontier TV
You can just talk to it
Her phone so
That's probably not a typical use case
And I don't think the phone manufacturer
We Care About That Bass
Good microphone
In there for phone calls and
Salon
Not so much for voice assistants so
I don't think it's going to happen
But I don't think so it's not a typical use case because you always have your phone with you yes
You may put it down and walk away from it
And therefore you need a far field microphone but
That's not the use case that most
Ace Hardware
Manufacturers of phones
Think about so I don't think it's going to happen
We'll see but that's
I know why they don't have it
Okay
That's it
You guys have a question for us
Call at
623-7424
Stay tuned for our interview with Jacob atallah of KB Home talking about how they built
A smart home
Here in Vegas
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is fair come a database come
And I have it all.
Oliveira here to talk to us from Farrakhan
Terracom lunch
Sitri Edge as an iot database back in June
And I'm really curious why does the edge need
A database
Bus station that's a great question
I guess it's closer related to why I'd Computing at all right
My short answer his response time is really a major transits opening different types of
For the market
Effaced a few years ago *
04 vs of big data but mostly volume velocity variety
Spencer's at the same time
But of course there is the more complex it gets
12th Street me all this data to the cloud in order to make this decisions is definitely an all natural way to handle this challenge
Have several problems
Like the network latency for example the reliability of the connection with the cloud and of course cost
Cloud is not cheap at all I think that's where is Computing really comes into
Houses change the application development
Well extracting meaningful information out this date in real time this will certainly require more robust infrastructure
Fortification point-of-view especially the edge Computing application
Make it easier to develop
And I think you're going to have to talk about what would be such database to definitely see that they certainly needs to
Redesign knowing all the constraint like having for a simple with small footprint gateways on the edge have a girl over the frosting
It's very important for this database
Ford flexible data schemas
All kinds of different variety of data and different types of sensors everyday
Everything definitely needs to be extremely fast that I'm out of data points are produced
Buy sensors in real time and buy controllers that you have to control it's absolutely incredible
Complexity of the environment for this application
Did you mentioned other platform
What else
Can an edge database do to help make a developer's life easier
Absolutely important because
The truth is that the way a application are being developed right now is on top of different types of
What does pacific order in series
Usually timestamps for you automatically collecting metadata from the sensors
Application
I think those are all features that an education would benefit from having a database on the edge
Wow that is a lot of information about databases
It's at the edge where can we find out more about this and about Fair
We have actually a great white paper that helps you decide until laxative his privates
You can check us at our website it said
Star cam.com
/.
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is
Jacob atalla
DPS sustainability at
KB Homes
Hi Jacob how are you today
I'm very wealthy
Thank you for having us
On your podcast
I am super excited I hear that you are in
Lovely Vegas which is where
I will be when the show actually airs
And y'all are showing off something
Pretty neat at CES do you want to tell me about it
We are
Very pleased
To be pulling out the KB Home
Project
Where tomorrow weed
On
Power cell
The Cask
To explore where the future will be
We strongly believe in innovation
And we know that if you want to predict the future the best way to do that
Is to make it yourself
So we're exploring the edges are
Technology and homebuilding back in
Intersection between the two and coming up with a very nice home that will be proud to
Showcase at the crime of Celia
So what this is is a project that is designed to show several things so
Innovation
Sustainability
Anson Smart Home
Why don't we start with
Probably the sustainability or should we go with Innovation which would you like to start with
What word starts with j something about
Because today in today's environment
Sustainable T is tablespoon
Everything
Start for us at KB Homes
Starts with a very quality high-quality home that
Is also high-performance home that's where it's at
So every home we produce is
Energy star label at home
That means
Our customers enjoy a home with less utility bills
And more Comfort now with our contact home
Project
We went beyond that
So
Here we looked at how can a home be
Energy Independence
Ansel
Went beyond
Our products
Auction homes to home.
Is
NetZero
And has battery storage system in it so that it
Can be fully Off the Grid
As much as possible that's where the customer has very little electricity bill to pay
The same time as the
Stability and security of energy storage in their home
In case the grid goes down at anytime
So that some of the sustainability effort
Let's talk about
The construction Innovation that
You guys are experimenting
Because I think that's
Really honestly. Maybe more game-changing than anything that you're doing here but
I don't know we'll see
Well there are many
Game changers in the home
And one of them
Is the
Outside
Fully integrated fabrication
Off the home which took place in a factory
First
You start with
What's called
Building information
Modeling Bim Bim models are very very precise
They also can visually help
An architect
See where there are conflicts
Between elements of the home
Address
These complex when everything is clear and the pain model
It's ready
Then in a factory setting
CNC machines take over and
Just got up all day
Parts of the house
In terms of
Wolves wall panels
Floor panel and
Not ready for
Shipping to the site
We actually took
Technologies are available today in terms of off-site fabrication
Step further
We innovated with the factory to include the insulation
At the factory
Install it there
And also the weatherization
Sheathing from the outside as well
So the house
Came to the side
With insulation in place
And reduce the amount of Labor needed for insulation on site when the house came on
Insight that we had a cranberry that pulled up the house
Today's we have the whole frame
Structure of the house done
So from that point on
It was a matter of just finishing up the house the finishes of the house
The trim and fixtures
And
Not want to be missed are all the iot devices and printers that
Reports in the house
We will get to those
And now so prefabrication
Sustainability are there other
Building
Technologies that
You guys explored in this that you should talk about
Or that you want to share
Certainly there are many
As a
Said earlier
We added
Insulation in the factory bugged
Form of therapy
Insulation
Was also very innovative
It wasn't
Fiberglass batt insulation and it was not spray foam
Insulation either it was phenolic type of insulation
That has
Double the amount of
Insulation value
Corrine
Dan
Other systems that are on the market
It's right now
It is a technology coming
From Europe
That's we adapted here and because it comes in solid panel
It was easy for us to cut the fence
Sea machines
Put them in the wall base
And have the insulation already done in the house
That's just one example of several
Super materials and material innovation
That we are leveraged in this house
Oh man I was so excited when I got the spray foam
Play my house so now there's a
Insulation R-value
Gosh all right
It's better with the spray foam insulation than what you see
5 years ago
It is true
Go technology
Okay
Let's talk about some of the other Technologies
Putting in the house I promise people
Smart home stuff in
I'm sure you will deliver before we go into like specific devices talk to me about how you thought
About adding
Connected devices and smart
To this
Particular home
What's a seaweed
Leverage
Technology
To add to the
Comfort of the home
The easel
Living at home
The wellness house comes
From living in a
Healthy
Well-constructed
We wanted
Technology to serve
The homeowner
In meaningful ways
Beyond where
Technologies are at right now
We started with
Understanding of what Foundation
We want to have in the house
And we know that
Intelligent
Is very important
We can transcend
The current automated
Home
Smartphone
From
Simply smart 2
Smart home or even to think
Walking home that will do things on behalf of the homeowner
Show
Artificial intelligence
We got it
Trump
Google we have Google as our platform
In the home
Boston artificial intelligence
And in mesh Wi-Fi network
These are two important
Foundation
From which
We built on centers built
Event wall lighting
Smart appliances that are smart air conditioning thermostat
System back are very responsive
To the environment if the home band results was
We are getting closer to a pinking home that will do things for you
Okay so there's a lot to unpack there
And we'll start with this idea of
Good connectivity makes for a good home
Which I totally agree
Like Yay let's get Wi-Fi everywhere
How do you build that into a home
Amica
Easy
For the homeowner so what is the process there
We started with great partners
That understood that
The systems
Four of them have to be simple
And easy to use for the homeowner
This is how we can give back time to the homeowner not to give them it's very complex
The truth of the matter is
That the home of the future could have awkward
75 Wi-Fi device
And may have
Advocated mesh Network
Show
It's not that easy
Going forward then I think we all still need to innovate
Little bit more towards an easier system to manage
I would say Google did a great thing in October
2018 when they
Revamp the Google home
Which now incorporates all the
We don't have to go to
20 different apps
Open your
Doron look at the light
Other things it's all in
In one app
Within the Google home
So it's Innovations like that then
Will make it
Easier in the future for customers
The Google mesh network is also very user-friendly you don't have
To worry about a lot of IP address
Seven Salon
Lot of it
Ask away from the consumer so that
You just have to enjoy I got a new item I can plug it
Into the network and it will join the network Tennessee
I think
Innovations come from many parts but we still have some room to improve in that area going forward
Let's talk about things like having sensors built into the walls
Thermostats and that sort of thing
Even just a few moments ago we were talking about installation
Technology has changed so much
5 years
So that's something I probably wouldn't mess with
Because you know you're not going to open up the walls of your home for a while hopefully
But how do you think about building in technology which tends to have a much shorter life cycle than traditional building
There's no better time
Built-in
Technology
Then when you're starting from a blank canvas
It's easier
Include items
Built into the wall but to your point
Even these sensors
May be surpassed in
Few years so the Innovation that we did
Put them
In junction box
And so you can I park RV
We passed to each juncture box
Cat5 cable and just in case if that particular sensor or are you
Device is not Wi-Fi
It will have available to it
The cable if we need to use
When you create it
Provided with power and will
Communication
Caribou
Is future proof
To the best
Know-how at this time
What we have in them
Right now are indoor air quality
And then you put a cover plate on that juncture bar
Women slap in the cover plate so that the air quality
Dissenters can continue to sample the air in the house and passively in the background
Would be able to
Say okay
This room
Perhaps they tried something
And that kitchen this will mean
More air at this time
And if then sends a signal to the air conditioning system which is zoom we have
Glow Housewives
Signal to the air conditioning system where
This is considered pump no fresh air into that zone
So that's just one example of built-in iot
And how we might
Keep them to keep the house youku
For the future
So let's say I purchase this home
How do I get it set up to work with
My family and then who do I call if in
Six or seven months
I don't know something breaks or I get
Confused her I'd like to set up a movie timer
More
Sophisticated
To the extent that
We would anytime KB Home build a relationship with our customers we always wanted
To be a Wonderful World
A wonderful experience for our customers
10 KB Home has
Collaboration
Dish smart home services
Using the same network that dish satellite
TV entertainment have on the country they have teams that are specialized
And smart home services and we work with them to give our customers at this time
So initially after a homeowner movies in
We asked them
To call
Dish smart home services
And ask them to come in
At the convenience of the customer
They come in to help them
Get up there
The Nest hello doorbell at the front door
The house
And the thermostat from
Carrier and mesh
Wi-Fi network from goo
Panda
Speakers that Google home
Speakers
So they come in
And Ben couple hours with the customer
In my estimation if the customer was going to do this
All on their own
Digression the weekend
Want to do it no and we prefer it based on the kind of relationships we want to have with our customers
That it is done
At the convenience of the customer and within a couple hours the couple hours are taken
2 /
Shut off the network and connect all the items to it do
Show the customer house
And then
Leave them with
Information where they can call for the next 6 months
They can call and get
Support either online or by phone on any other device that bring to the home
Say if they going they buy a new
TV that has Chromecast built into it and they bring it to him and they want to connect
To the network they can get support
To do any of these
Additional iot item
Around the house
Got it
Okay and let's talk about how this fits in with
KB Home and it's
Plans going forward
So there is Ben
Probably for the last
10 years or so efforts in the Home Building community
To provide
Services
Is after the sale
So this might be warranties this might be
Pest detection
How is something like this new KB Home Project
Fit within that
I guess additional Revenue
I think the future
May hold
Room for
Somebody
That can
Continue to provide service
As for the home
It could be in
Different areas
Whether it is
The digital
Smart home area or in
And the Health and Wellness Water
Purification air filters
There is room for that
And I think some business models are evolve
So
From our perspective at KB for this particular house
It does
Have health and wellness system with air purification
Water purification systems in it as well and these things do need the filters changed over time
Whether we leave it to the customer if they are very much do it
Myself type of person then they can do it themselves
Ordering the filters or it can be a service provided
To come in and change the filters air and water filters for them
Regular base
Is that the app will continue to remind them when that mean
To happen
So if they do it then
They still have some reminders
Got it in the app is the generic Google hours of KB Home
Darwin Wellness intelligence application or system and an application related to it
It controls
Indoor air quality sensors that I mentioned earlier but it's also controls lighting
Filtration purification system
For the house as well the water and the air
And then of course
Can allow you to
The system also can passively
Do the lights
According
True that hour of
And according to
Perhaps some precepts
So that's how the Darwin
System works
And it's app is
We be a front interface use it if you'd like
But if you leave it alone the house will still be maintained in a nice way for a healthy wellness way
Because of the
Precepts in the system
Okay so in addition to this home.
Prefabricated
As part of the building materials you also have made it flexible
Imus modular inside
Can you talk a little bit about that
ACS we did that we designed a home that can
Flex with the life stages of the homo
Trust me it's a two-story home
With
Secondary bedrooms upstairs
That can be used by the
Homeowner if they have children or boomeranging
Children and Swan however
At their later life stages where they may not need that
They could separate the first floor from second
Very easily because we already built the entrance to the second floor that too independent and a way to separate
2 floors
So they can separate them
For the rental or for a caregiver to be in the Upper Floor and have full
Units of their for their private use
At the same time we built
On the first floor flexible wall
Moves via electricity and a motor
It moves
Forwards and backwards into a space that were calling a flex space
When the wall is all the way to the outside of that Flex space
That room can be a bedroom
Or an office
And it
Even has wall bed that comes down and
Certainly becomes a bedroom and it has a built-in desk as well for
An office
When the wall is
All the way back
Internet speed
It gives a space over to the great room so if you have
40 you have family over you are using more of that
Room for the open
Room that makes the great space and is the place to socialize
Jacob that is a lot I can't wait to see
This whole
In action
This is a project home
Is this something that will be available for people on the market or how do you plan to use your learnings from this going forward
That's certainly this is a contact home we built it to it
Store work tomorrow
And to the extent that we experience
Many things in this
We know there are some items that we would love
To start bringing into our production home and make it available to our customers very soon Cason
Is the Darwin
Wellness
Intelligence
We're going to be a pilot and get
10 offering it in certain Market see it through
Start building on it from a base package
Growing get going
The same with
Other Technologies in the home many of them are already offered by a bee home
Smart appliances
Many others as well
So there is a lot that we learn from it
And we hope to be
Making them more production-oriented and bring them to the Market within months and coming years
Awesome alright will Jacob thank you so much for sharing with us this vision of the future
One possible home of the few
Thank you I enjoyed being with you
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot, will see you next week