Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
We have an amazing show for you today we're going to talk a lot about the Google home
After a life-changing experience
CES we're going to be talking about blockchain in a couple different ways
One shipping to
Newchip
And then we got a bunch of fun news items for you including what happens to stringify and deposition
My BMW and a wireless module that
Years
We also have a message from a brand new sponsor pointcentral and our guest this week
Is Chad
Sharma who is an awesome tell, and a list
We talked both about what happens with 5G and low-power wide area network
And
We talked about how to regulate
Companies
When data is the new oil so you're going to want to stick around for some
What is a life-changing
Thoughts there
Now let's go to another
One of our sponsors
This week sponsor is CBT Nuggets
How does the iot change the way we do business for many organizations it means a proliferation of devices and tools
In every device connecting to your network is another potential vulnerability
You may think that your greatest security threat as a malicious hacker but what if it's really an unsecured smartwatch
Someone on your team
But if everyone on your team is trained and security best practices
It significantly reduces your chance of a data breach or the severity of the
CBT Nuggets is going to talk training choice for it Professionals for decades and now they're making that same
High quality online training solution for end-user security
So that your team can recognize and stop threats before they make it onto your neck
Go to CBT Nuggets. IO to find out more about how end-user security training
Protect your network
In the internet
Thanks
Okay
I didn't get the
Did you
No this is one of the first times that I did not get sick
From
CES which is
Nearly impossible to avoid because you have all those people in
Confined spaces for days upon days upon days
No no honey I'm good
Yeah
So
I feel like
Will be struck down with something
Ten times worse
But I'm really excited
I got back
I was tired so I didn't do this yet
After seeing everything happening
With voice
It CS
I realized it
I should probably switch over to using Google home
Instead of Madam
So my family is going to kill me but I am switching over
Because
I tested out a couple of the
I have been testing out
Google related
Integrations and they work
Really well in
Just Google is so much better than madame
When it comes to answering
When it called the big question
Yes yes and it's really ironic that you bring this up
Because and we did not coordinate this
I'm actually doing the same thing
You know the one place that Google falls down
Amazon music
So a couple of my rooms
Can Aleve
Echo in like my daughter because she plays music all the time Google is
Terrible
When it comes to it like I asked for a song it almost always gives me the
Karaoke
I don't know why
It just it always gives me the wackiest version of the song I wanted to
Play so
That is one place where I'm like nope I can't
I can't rely on
In your Google Maps history do you have like a
Series of searches for karaoke bar
That's really odd but and it's funny cuz I thought you're going to say something else about music I agree with you that the music is where it falls down
For the most part there's another variable probably talk about it
You're very limited music choices to set
As your you know to link rather
Nature Google play music person
Yeah you're good
But
I'm Apple music
So Spotify
6 weird songs
It's
So in my default settings
It's just
Google's brain just
Maybe Google just feels like I should be
Maybe I hear you singing on the show I don't know
I do have it in my bath
Could be could be
Falls down for me a little bit still in the smart home area but it has gotten better like in October
They added support
In Google Assistant which we didn't transfer over to Google home
For Canary integration
I'm having problems setting it up
Probably on my end I don't know
They recently added
Sbarro
Fathers that come up recently been at it since they haven't quite caught up to Amazon in the terms of those integration
But they're getting much closer for me
Yes so I'm going to use my Google home
It's moving out of the master bathroom
It's moving into
Bedroom
And then actually
The Google home will move downstairs to the kitchen
And then
Google mini
Will move
Into the bedroom
Replacing an echo
Yeah see you're in a better spot than I am because
I only have
A Google home and everything else is an echo device so I would have to be replacing with some Minis and things and I just I want to get the
Lenovo smart
Screen that has
Google home integration
For the smaller and
Correct
I'll wait for that but I'll probably in a couple minutes and unfortunately they're not $29 anymore they're back up to $49 so
I swear
Just walk in
Sign up for the New York Times you got it
I see the free mini
Yeah but they usually with things I don't need
I already have that Supply have any Kobe
Not that don't figure that part again you're better place from it
And as far as going back to the music for singing I'll still stick with the Sonos Play 1 with the matinee
Integration for now
Because I also works with it
Music services that I love you so
Show control music but Google home will do everything else is my thought
Well there's an opportunity because Google has now hooked up with yonomi
Which
Is
One of my favorites
All-time favorite apps they actually just got 5 million last week
Not for their smart home stuff but because they have this really awesome architecture that lowers the cost of
Devices of supporting connected devices so on the backend so companies
Like
Sonos
Can look at
You know me is cloud
And be like oh it's so much easier to operate
Yay
The cool thing is with Google being integrated with
You know me
Yonomi control Sonos stuff
And it actually does a really good job I've had it
Controlling my son has stuff for a while
You can't get it to play a particular song on
On the Sonos
Which is better outside
Whether you got that's all I need because I tune into channels typically like on XM
Serious
Satellite for example
So I can already set that as a favorite in Sonos app so I should be good
Yeah so like if I'm looking it allows you to play favorite
Or play a playlist
You can also have
It tell you things
Can make your own text
Welcome to study law.
How may I ask
That's actually pretty scared
So all of those things you can do volume mute unmute
Next
Previous
Play and pause so those are all the commands
And
Yeah so it's actually fairly Flex
I once when I was first playing with you know me I actually had set it up
All of my Sonos is around my house
Play my favorites when I walked in
And what happened was
Their geolocation was still kind
It apparently at 4 in the morning and decided I'd come home
And all of my sodas
This Sunday started playing late
Public Radio
Middle of the night rave party
Husband was not impressed
Let's see what else about the Google home
We want to talk about it messing with our Wi-Fi cuz that was a big
Well it still is a big deal is being fixed however a couple people
Start reporting issues and was looked into it turns out that Google's
Cast protocol which is used in the Chromecast as well as Google home and other Google devices was causing Wi-Fi
Issues in people with what's going on in my WiFi why can't misers
Not working at all
Turns out that the
Cast feature sends packets as a keep alive for a connection
For like the Google home
Unfortunately when a Chromecast device go to sleep
The packets buildup
So what happens is when something that uses the Google Cast protocol comes back online
It floods your router
Two boards of
Tens or hundreds of thousands of packets
And the memory fills up on the router and causes like an overflow error
And it just have to reboot the router
Obviously I don't like pictures the issue temporarily so what's going to happen is Google is working on a fix to
Not have that happened I don't think I change the protocol because I think they're using UDP
And yeah and that's
Probably not the way to go if you want to
Control the
The packets in this kind of situation so
It's more of a a setting or configuration that they need to fix it's nothing a user and user can do
But if you do have Wi-Fi issues
Give Me Maybe due to Google Cast type products in your house
And this will be fixed in the very near future some router
Companies are already fixing it
I know Linksys has a firmware update Netgear is working on tp-link which actually makes my Google
Call this now Google WiFi
Router
Google
That's it on Hub
Yasso
So it's getting fixed
Wifi issues recently this could be the problem
Right right
Google Google when messing with your WiFi
Okay
Let's see other this is actually an interesting reason to maybe switch over to Google home especially for you guys who want
Troll Kevin
Discovered
Yeah well I discovered something somebody else's guy
Android police wrote an article earlier this week saying Google home as a hidden API that local devices can use
My eyebrows
You raise the eyebrow
Sleep with this little bit will put a link in the show notes
But basically yeah you couldn't as long as you know the IP address of your Google home there is a you can just plug it into your bra
Browser search bar and then there are some commands you can do for getting and posting HTTP requests
I was able to just before the show like sent a request and just get the wireless network
That Google is connected to in my house for example I got all the
The SSID
WPA information so on and so forth
I was not able to act
How to change anything on my Google home but that's because
You do need to install a small little helper app to
Configure your request
So I seen pictures of this working I'm sure it's working but I have not actually gotten it to work at so you can enable Bluetooth mode
You can change the night mode settings and such from command line so
It's interesting and Google doesn't talk about this
And they don't offer any type of interface for it and Teresa see if they ever
Open it up so it's
So for those of us who
Terminal user
What is the benefit of this
User
Why would I want to
From a user standpoint you probably don't because all these things
It's already begun
Seriously
They can already be done in
The app
Got it
Okay
What but if you wanted to create your own version of a Google home app
And do different things
As a developer could be interesting
I look forward to seeing what you decide
Yeah and user / sudo developer
I might want
How to change the Wi-Fi network my device connects to when I walk in the house because I'm going to use that Network for streaming video
I can do that with a command line potential
Say
So that's it on Google home but because
Switch our stuff over we're probably going to learn a lot
And we will share that knowledge
Actually
I do have
Cher
That's why I listen to you
This is he
Pro tip
From one of our listeners Marty
Champs
Cuz one of my big complaints about the Google home is
I can't always tell if it's hurt
Right
Is a little
It's on the diagonal
And a little light goes off
And so
This person
Email me to let me know that if I go into the accessibility settings
I can actually
Make it give me a little
To let me know that it's hurt
So
You could actually do that at the end of a command as well if you want to yes
So I needed that
And that his
Significantly
Enhanced my
Sepia and I actually do have that turned on because I asked for the very same reason I'm just not sure if it has heard me and I don't want
Want to have to look at it
So yes
And so
Guys
I now take away that feature and thanks Marty for
Telling you that
Apparently Kevin do it and didn't tell me
Well I didn't know you didn't know
Alright let's move on to some really interesting blockchain
We'll talk first about IBM and Maersk
The shipping Giant
Building
A joint venture
To track shipping around the world I thought this was fast
Last year IBM and Maersk created a partnership to focus on digitizing
Supply chain
And IBM spin a big black
3 years
And they were looking at it mostly for
Transactions
This is more about understanding worth
Bizarre
And now
After playing with this
4 year so they've decided there's enough to create like a whole new company
And they're going to put a
Global trade digitization platform built on Open Standards
For everyone and make it available
So what's going to happen is using blockchain they're going to make a record of all the transactions that occur in the global Shipping
Supply chain
And
That's a
Pretty significant
Thing to do
And it's also very iot Focus because
To do this you're going to have to have a way for these
Shipping pallets and things that are being tracked
Talk to one another
I look at this
And I cannot wait to see it's going to use IBM's cloud
Some of that Watson stuff
And then
Is ginormous a
Bishop
How many first
The global staff
The global stuff
So
The project has been piloted by Dow Chemical DuPont
And US Customs in
Border
So
This is cool cuz like you could see it being really useful for
Like hazardous materials
Counterfeit
Very excite
Yeah it's interesting that the Customs bit in determining if a product has made it to his destination as
Expected Hino
It's going from one country to another coming into our country
Yeah it's a wonder if they're going to have
They being IBM and Maersk are going to have a first-mover status here because this is a big undertaking
The one that can add tremendous value to any company
Around the world
Chips and
Like I said anything and anybody
That's a lot of them you know not services companies how to say but anybody produce something or
Keeps inventory and sells things you know your Walmarts you're all of your big
Supermarkets in such a penis
This is a good move right by these two companies I think
We'll have to see if it pays off
But I can
Citron Menace II out of this
Which is a startup
Filament labs
They've actually announced a new chip
The block lit
Chip
In what district does is you can put it on to any device
And
What is a secure
Transaction it runs
A variety of different
Blockchain so it becomes a secure transaction generator
On
Ascensor
This is kind of hard to think about but it's really revolutionary
Because
What you can do with this is the date of that stored and transmitted via the
Watching
Can be used to do transactions at
It can be used to
Calculate like
How much your old like you could even look up
You can even do like
For lookups like
How often are you pinning this device to
Find out where it is for example like much like GPS was monetized in the early days by lookups
So you can monetize it based on that
There's a lot of interesting things you could do with this and so filament
His creative basically this
Secure side
A way to do this securely in a trusted
The platform
With
A chip
So you buy this chip and all of the hard stuff is done on the security
You then enable your blockchain
Whichever one you want Sports ethereal and it supports
Bitcoin it support
Others
And then you've got to weigh to basically build this into a system
Yeah it is and I'm the security side of things
I think it's more along the lines
Being able to feel comfortable that whatever
Code is supposed to run on that device and
Sensor is
Legitimate trusted
Code
Meaning
Nobody could mess with the firmware or the colonel or anything else because obviously been anything that happened
Your packets of data could be siphoned off to somewhere else and somebody's getting that information so
If they manage that it's I think it's almost like a Chromebook can't wait to always secure because the special chip inside checks
To make sure it's secure and running the most
Current validsoft
Work basically
Yes they are doing deals so they run as a trusted execution environment for both Intel
And
The arms.
Arm-based chips
They also so that the chip design is an existing silicon they
Put a microcontroller
But that's the kind of combined it a different way so they put a microcontroller on there
Solopower low processing
The Odyssey real flash storage they have
Handle some of the
Reads and writes
And then a cryptographic key storage and an engine so there's a co-processor doing all the
Photography
Then again that's good for
So I think this is really
Really exciting
They've been developing this for like the last five years but actually just last year arm announced
The thing we're going to be able to put
A trusted execution environment on their microcontrollers
So before that this didn't even exist so these guys were building it ahead of the big
Japan during the space which is armed
So
It's really
I just really
It's one of them that I noticed in their white paper
They said they're saying the currency involved
For now for the people who are doing the the hashing and verifying all the information that comes through
The blockchain
It's Exchange in private side chains that are separate from the public Bitcoin blockchain
Therefore
These are shielded from bitcoin's transaction cost which can be very high when you talk about
Millions of iot devices using something like this transaction cause you to have to watch that
So that is another interesting aspect to me
Alright so that's our
Blockchain
Blah blah blah
Talk for the day
Let's go to
Some quick news
Will Kevin
Did you watch the Viking
I did and it was down to the final play of the game
The Saints to lose it but Vikings want it and what happened was
It was so much back and forth towards the tail end of that
Apple watches for telling people that they might be having heart attacks
I love this story because it is like it's an example of Wind Lake
The mass phenomenon of like sports and all that meets our custom data
Highly personalized data effort
We're all the same
So did you rap
Where you at Vesta
No I wasn't that vested in the game and it was a good game I watched it and saw the final play but no
Mine did not I'm kind of disappointed in this sense
I guess
When the Apple watch to text your resting but then your heart rate is above 120 beats per minute
That's when it send you your little alert which is super handy I love it I think it's great
But obviously in this case it was not a valid use
There we go
Moving outside
But still in a TV ish Realm
Comcast we talked about this Sunday special CES edition of the iot
It's worth mentioning here
Comcast
Is
They bought stringify and they are now
Allowing for home automation for up to 15 million household
So hey if you're in one of those 15 million households you should totally be listening to us
Talk about automation
But
This is a big deal this is how they're going to use stringify and if you're stringify user like me and not in the country
Cast household
You don't have to worry because
Cuz they're still supporting stringify for
Other user
If you don't like stringify you could try to do it with you know me but stringify is incredibly complicated and can let you do a lot of really
But again
Comcast
I was actually going to ask you but I waited until you brought up the stringify bit if you could only pick one third party app
Right now to use with home automation I you know me
Struvite what would it be
Yeah I would have to go through what devices probably would be my first step
Second step
Oh
I probably would go with you know me
Because they have some nice automation features but I haven't use stringify since
Since Comcast started fiddling with
That so I don't know if
Change Street
It's a it's not as into it as I think I think you know me is much more to it is
So I I would tend to agree with him right there
And if
They've added more complexity but it's still not
It's not to the level I was
But for normal people I would totally recommend using IF
Okay
Mossy BMW has acquired parkmobile
Which is a an app that helps you find
Parking
I cannot wait till I have sensors or
Sensors embedded under every parking space or maybe cameras
Use computer vision to tell me where parking spaces are so I do not have to Circle
Roblox
And even better I would like to see my car work with blockchain to automatically just make a
Machine machine
Purchase for my parking so I don't have
How to do it
And since we're on the subject of vehicles and self-driving cars that's worth noting that
Blackberry just launched
A new cybersecurity software
For these vehicles
It did this earlier this week
And it's interesting it's called Jarvis which is kind of a bummer cuz Jarvis
There's like
Smart Home
And awesome
Yeah and those aren't words that I would equate with Blackberry no offense Blackberry fans
China
Just not feeling it
In any case Blackberry Jarvis is going to be marketed towards automakers
And it's not
This is interesting it's not security running on the vehicle itself
It's actually software to help the software designers
Check for issues and security
Potential issues as they're developing software for self driving cars
And that makes a lot of sense I was a QA manager for
Wait a while myself for business and
It is so much
Cheaper to catch these types of issues well before things go out in production
The sooner in the life cycle that you
Attach an issue or potential issue security problem whatever maybe
It's so much cheaper so
This does two things it reduces the cost of software development in general
Because fixing something later is going to cost a ton of money
And two it should improve the security of the software that's used in the
Autonomous vehicles
Do you think Blackberry can make it come around to come back with the autofocus with
Everything
Sue
I would say
Probably
I mean anything can happen they've obviously gotten out of the hardware business
Is there still BlackBerry
Handsets that are made but those are made by
Alcatel One
TCL I believe in
Just Brandon
BlackBerry
They're focused on services and software and actually you know they have long been in this business and they know software
Security
I do think so
I really I really do that mean never be as big as they were back in their heyday
But I do think they will survive and slowly thrive
And final bit of small news4u Sierra Wireless has a new module
And why are we telling you this because it's actually a very exciting much
It has a 15-year battery life which is
Very impressive
And it can work on NB iot
Katem networks and
Fall back for 2G so this is the kind of module you would see in smart cities
Having that 15 year life
Really gives it the ability
Desiigner the ability to
Put this on a bridge for example in a hard-to-reach place because you're not going to want to come back out there every year
5 years to
Replace it
So you can have things measuring likes
Tension
Vibration Zoe
Tell when something's about to fail
So I thought this was actually
It's kind of dirty but it's also really interesting
Fort Apache
Yeah and it's currently sampling right now it's not available it will be available in the third quarter of this year is the presumption but I agree
Pretty for something that doesn't send a lot of data
That is
Remote
You know not something easily accessible
15 your battery life is very impressed
Yay
All right let us move
To our voicemail
Call from a listener this week
Just a reminder if you want to ask us a
A question
Give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And
Here we go
Hey Kevin and Stacey love the show
Really like the balance
What you guys to bring a different devices
Technology
Change so quickly
My question for you guys is
Do you think about
Safety a personal health safety police devices be connected
Admissions of different waves back and forth
Bluetooth technology research
Who sings I'm
Going down this journey with smart devices and a part of me wonders
How much faster are going to get cancer because of this
Hope to hear from you
Thanks a lot
Okay
This is a question that I almost feel guilty that I haven't
Really thought about
So
Will a
It's a good question
My initial take is you know with smartphone something that's
Cellular radio waves and its next year
Your brain basically
We do have a measurement program it's the SAR testing to determine how much radiation is coming off that device
That could impact you physically we don't in the home I'm not as concerned we don't have any testing for that
Any formal test
Should say
But I'm not as concerned I mean we've had Wi-Fi forever not forever but for
Two decades whenever
People still wear Bluetooth headsets
Switch I think you have star ratings
By the way
Just with the devices in our house I'm just not concerned about that
Maybe I should be
But I haven't seen any
Danger signs any studies that say Hey you shouldn't have all these wireless devices in the home so again
I'm not overly concerned
Okay well
That was this week's question again if you have a question and want to stop us
Or
Can the pinyin
Possibly a knowledgeable opinion
Possibly.
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And now
Stay tuned for our
Guess who is going to talk to us about
5G
Low-power wide area Networks
And
How we should think about regulation in this new era where data is King
And now a message from our sponsor hey everyone we're taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast
Read message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Central and I have Sean Miller president
Here to talk to us
Tell us just a little bit about what point Central does
1 Central in the Metro what we always were the leading provider
Home automation solutions to property manage
We've been in business for about five years and where are you supposed to re-up alarm.com
Collectively Pete of substantive alarm.com Adidas a lot of
What time is it
We have expensive
Experience working with property managers
As well as the ability to really be a long-term partner
Pop emoji
Smart Home Solutions
All right you guys offer a bunch of products from big-name vendors like Amazon
OGE Lutron
Google home nest
Skybell
And so what's the advantage of bringing all of these well-known consumer brands
Together under the
Point Central
So we're interested and had a tough time
Getting smart home devices
By partnering with a lot of deleting devices
Windows brands
Choose residence
What we do on the back
Is we make sure all those devices are connected to our system
Alexis Toulouse
Hempstead public security privacy
And also operational efficiency
For the property man
So for example
Opera
Element homes or apartment unit
The system automatically revert control today
The tenant
I'm allowed to tended to have the full experience
Turn the thermostat with the Amazon Echo
Turn lights on from iOS or Android app
If they needed to get someone into shape
Fix a leaky faucet
Or understand what was going on
And allowing them to
Mortician on how they help support.
Okay so you serve essentially to customer bases the renter
And the property manager
How does that influence how you design your solution
I want him is really exciting because you get to tap into a lot of
Passionate creature that got the computer level
The Beast design
The property man
Rochester news
Structure
As a business tool
Something at the property managers
She is a valuable addition
I mentioned earlier security
Until the Privacy order us another
Austin missed connection
To get the device data
Summerville Georgia
Out of the home and into our cloud
We found that just helps provide a much more reliable connection as well
And where can we go
To find out more about
Really easy anyone can go to point central.com to learn more about what we do and Who We Are
Go back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Chetan Sharma who is one of my favorite Telecom analyst
Head of HR
Hi how are you doing today
Thanks Sissy
Rihanna
Super excited because while I was at CES
Debate topics
When was 5G
And the other
Holy cow
What kind of low-power wide area network
So we're going to get to that
First
I really would love for you to break down
Since you've been doing this for a really really really long time
Bricktown
What you think carriers in operators need to
Do s
Part of the Internet of Things
Can you call that your fourth
Yasso
Yes.
Emanated from
The notion of where the next
Generation of Revenue is going to come from
Stabbing Family Feud Big W cycle
Huntington voice
17th and going on strong
Calvin decline
Next game
Impacted by ITB Packaging
Good point where
Spelling in Many Nations
And then I'll just
Country experience
Indira
But eventually even the deer has grown little peep and Deborah
Soul Eater Laporte wave
Meaning the next cycle of innovation as well as Revenue generation
Have to be focused on
Anthem of Pakistan
Adopted the framework
Guan ping
AT&T Verizon
Docomo kddi
And so the notion of course
That while you focus on your bread-and-butter business of providing access
Is going to come from
Like advertising or like
What's security
Verticals like healthcare
Nutella
Until under the broad umbrella
Also invite other
By the way others to the ecosystem
Populist have to compete
Very differently
Then they have
Umbrella
Isabel
So you mentioned that iot is going to become
Warriors
What do you mean
They have to really figure out
Misdirection
Ultron
Rich Porter
Deployed
Aot
Play in the low power
Pandaria
He wants that determine out of it play
On
Today this part number somebody to create their own
Strindberg and ecosystem
That's settled then we have to worry about
Awkward Orlando services today
Corte De agua
Xcel Energy
Fairy Tail transportation
Okay let's go deeper here because we should talk about
5G
When they talk about 5G
What are they talking about
And what are they hoping
I definitely hoping for the 5G is going to generate
The next generation of growth Obama
And took
Historically
Heat cycle on 192 Porgy
Has
Pastor meaning number of subscribers on the network
In the past 10 years
Has X-rated
Additionally Ethan racing
Typically
Ben 10 PS3 Avenue
Enterprise hope is that
The bad news is
Barely
Complicated
Snot
Simple as
Figure out which way to go first
Mobility
X Wireless
Coyote
All of them in what time frame hammock stand
Where do you see them
If I look at AT&T and Verizon
It looks like they're going
Fixed wire
It varies depending on the job
Stop it in Korean
On Mobility fixed Wireless
Gladiator motivational
The US
Mobility
Back is not available in product
Yes
Verizon and AT&T
Frozen 2
Something that might be available later this year
Lycamobile
Miskelly
Gunning for
IMobile
IGN
If you look at that cannot accept fix wireless I'm not completely convinced that
Nationwide
I think
Verizon and AT&T in Philadelphia
Netflix
Locally
A use case that my
IFix Wireless
Either neighborhoods are
Quality wireless access to apartment buildings or factories or Healthcare
What does a blanket
Off my feet
Alex Wiley
Discada
Apple stock
Come to the market by
And we might see more
EBay
Actually funny
Let's talk about the edge specifically
How we're going to
Connectivity to all of these sensors at
There is a
It's still ongoing debate about which low-power wide area network
Work for you
And we got
Proprietary companies
6 public radio reference
Help us
Make sense of
Yasso
Iot as you might realize it's already used
Epix
And so
Anastasia look like almost Park
And so it really comes down to requirements
And the Sun rises
So if somebody is looking for a Time rising of 2 years to 5 years
It might require and
August
If you are looking for 5
Play Store
Damn you might deploy
Different strategy
I'm so
Ecosystem provides a very compelling Sparrow
Properties in Comstock
Dad
You can be up and running
To address
Problem
And in those cases security might not be a consideration
Or updating
And the sensors
Tesla software
Might not be a critical element
You might consider going
Unlicensed in areas that require internet
Oregon police
Make the bacon
And you need to update or Cara
An update
LCM
Capable
Douglas paektu
Noble
Is also
The number of players on China
Is investing in a project that requires
Investment
They would be safer to go away
Longer than song
Thumbs down to a number of factors for a given project
Basted eggs
Jasmine
And in the number of the cases going to be the Laurel and six packs of the world
Because
Really low car
An important occasion
Panthers Kentucky
And so if I'm asking myself questions
Something about 10
It sounds like I should think about security
Longevity of my product
Cost
And
Any others
Do you know how many suppliers can you have
And the type of modules might be
Hanukkah celebration
Can be done
Yo what's the projection for
Ditto evolution
Because it could be
Increase in 5 years
Then
Project
So you have to kind of plan out
Spreadsheet and database
Scenarios and that'll help you narrow down
Which wire is orbit technology on my Toshiba
Is part of this
I feel like you also have to ask
Carriers want to do business
It's still an ongoing complaint
Surprising
A lot of companies
We're doing work on Prototype
Or even smaller companies
Sensor
Based
Products
Very hard time talking to the
What role do you think carriers need to
To play with
Backing this innovation
Younger
Nothing depends on what country
Somebody like you
Dabbing dealing with
Reaction time
And so if you think
Bonita Park activity or want to get a module
American Senior Verizon whoever it is
You should be able to get in a matter of hours
Sanlitun beijing
Then the court system needs to be
Robeson of scallopini
Sports app
Volume Five
You should be able to get it
Betty Lake Whitney
Alka-Seltzer help you
Disorder access
And showed up on the doorstep
In a matter of hours
Reaction time
Easterby
Speed of how China
Like to work
Let's move over to
Regulation
Because
Gosh I feel like this was a couple years ago but you published a really insightful publication
About how we should think about regulation
In the digital age
Do you want to give me an overview
Yeah sure
Current regulatory regime
Countries
Is really based on 30-40 your idea of regulating
And subsequently the internet provider
GameWorks
Antipathy
State Farm
Advertising
Bop-It extreme
The Google open the Facebook in the world
If you look at a transportation
Uber
Stilettos
Williams
Who are the various
Entity
I'll be suspending to 1
Requires a different mindset after all one word
Really
The problem
I'm not doing that
In the sense that if you look at
Dell Avenue
I mean from the ecosystem
It used to be 85% of the revenue
In the wireless Market used to be coming
And now that has dropped down to less than 50
The new growth
Clearly coming from
Newark bears
Apples in Pittsburgh
Uber
New revenue for the
The market
Focus on the task
You will miss out what's happening on the lyrics about
Only the second side on the device side
And more importantly on the application
The most important component
By their own admission did Aizen uol
But apparently they're not
Article about house
Think about that
Saeran lemon aesthetically
Acquisition of one player
Acquire
Stronger player
Spectrum
Or not
The problems we have you don't have to to measure
Competitive strength
Indifferent
How do you compare AT&T with Google
And come up with an answer
And so the papers price
Got it okay so we're going to break some of this down but we talked about things at the access layer probably the most well-known
Neutrality
Under your ideas do you think net neutrality
Still needs to
Exist
Layers in the ecosystem need to be very transparent about
How did Adidas
And the mystical concept
Me too
Mature
Frontpageafrica
Amazon denying consumers Google
Or vice versa in motion of the 9th
And so I think it's a really
Be honest about
Net neutrality
It shouldn't go up and down the chain
But only for certain things
I mean it doesn't make sense
PS of course
Who have a massive platform
Breakfast on big one
Or Android
Are back from life awf
That you be transparent and be equal
Everybody
Albuquerque, new players that are coming on
And responsibility after you go to a certain time
That are you be confident than welcome to
And so do you think it's
A size like number of users would be the threshold is it dependent on the type of platform
Is it
There's so many ways to
This cat as it were
Yeah I mean I don't know what the right
What I would like to
Steers motivate about it as to what the right answer car
And my pimples are and how should Dental Community think about
Having
But clearly you don't want you to say
Probably different
Fly
Emmanuel covering maybe 5 or 10%.
Saturday
Are you the bacon
And because of that added
Cyberbass
The added responsibility
Not everybody is willing to
Going up to
Without agriculture in French
Okay and let's talk
Creating anticap
Competitive
A framework for measuring anti camp
Murderers
Yeah so I think they're thinking about how they want to be
And
Yeah they have
If it is indeed the new oil
Or if it's the new
Instead of Revenue stream for giving Nation
Then we should figure out how to
And they doesn't get abused
Concentrated
Revenue
That one has to worry about
Kalyan.
Advances that you're seeing in AI
Adidas
Modicum meaning
Unless we come up with you
In order to compete with
Messing
One has to wonder
You know what those regulations
Like look like
Or
Annabelle release
Eminem
Granted
Should have a beautiful daughter
Understanding
What kind of
Beautiful
Bilby
Available through the player who's acquiring a
Some of the conditions
And I don't know what the right answers are but I think topic for
Depression discussion
Negatory level
Don't leave it in the country
Call
Derek Anderson
Anywhere
Anderson Chrysler
Heading for the loss of the problems as well as
Do we need
Boundary some guidance
That allow
The Grove
But also the big Powers not abused
I feel smarter already
Thank you so much
Coming on the show
Thanks busy thanks for having me on cooking
Things to remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot