Welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And this is episode 196
And for our post
Holiday Blues episode
We have
A fun one for you
We are going to do all
Q&A
This is where you guys
Are the show
And we are able to do this
Thanks to
Are generous sponsor of the iot
Podcast listener hotline
Schlage and you still have time to win a Schlage lock
Don't miss your chance to win the brand new zigbee certified
Amazon
Key version
Of the Schlage
Connect smart deadbolt
You actually get to choose what you want but you could choose the one that's
Compatible with the Amazon Key Program
You can upgrade your smart home with the safety Simplicity and style of
Leg so
To make this possible all you have to do is give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4 and you will automatically be entered to win you just have to do it before midnight
Close of the year
Okay
Kevin
I love the steps
Because
I always feel bad when we can't answer everybody's questions
That we get so I'm like woah yay
We still can
Well hopefully today we will provide some good age to the Q that people have called in on
College try
So
First step
We have a message from
Frank
Big eyes
Love the show thank you
So much for
All you do
Coyote
Chifans
I'm trying
Find some way
To use sensors or
Other iot
Qi devices
To trigger
An announcement
Could be the weather
Close or something but
It seems very complicated online
She is my
SmartThings setup
To trigger in an ounce
Very kind
And wondering if you have
An easy way to do things
I also think that
The new Amazon
Routine
My shortcut
Process quite a bit
I wanted your thoughts
Thank you so much
Oh
Frank
I am sad to tell you
There's a little confusion about
We couldn't figure out
Migraine wanted
Have
Make SmartThings talk to my connect
Active speakers and make them
Say things to me but I think what you actually
Why is smart speakers
Have things trigger on them
We actually talked about this about a month ago
When we talked about an app called notify me
So
There is
That and that is for the Amazon Echo
Devices
And
The other option
Is in routines
They're actually a
A few devices that will be able to trigger a notification on your Amazon
Echo devices
Right now they're pretty limited ring is one of them
And so Emotion Detector on your ring doorbell cam
Actually trigger notify
Vacation on your Amazon
Echo the challenges
It doesn't actually say anything out loud
It just turns the light
Ring
Yellowy color and then you say
Mel Torme
Do I have notifications
And she
I will say
Yes
Do you want to hear them
Will say yes
And then she will tell you what happened
So it's
It's not really a push situation but that's
Probably less annoying
For most cases
I don't know what do you think yeah it's not ideal I certainly understand why it's been implemented that way and I see
Sync Amazon in any other speaker maker should add an option to say if I have a notification just
Shout it out don't put that extra step in there
Unfortunate that extra step is there right now so
Yeah I'd like to see like where you could opt
But I also see Bryant
You probably want to opt into it and it probably only want to opt into it
But during certain times of the
Just like your phone notifications which is how all of these devices send you notifications today typically so yeah let's
Can replicate the notification controls that we have in these apps
Right on the speakers
Now if you want to use your SmartThings
Things to trigger announcements or things to happen
On your speakers
Right now you can't do it for your smart speakers but you can do it for the Bose soundtouch and various Samsung
Multi-room speakers
And in that case what you can do as you connect those devices to SmartThings
And if a certain person enters the room or something happens
Your speakers
Play a noise
So that is not exactly what you're after
But it may get you part way there
So Frank I am sorry for the bad news
If anybody else has some ideas
4 franc
Boy let us know
Okay
Next up
We have a message from
Dylan also
Tell me about smart speakers
Hey Kevin it's tasty
Texas
Podcast
Eric Westervelt
Smart speakers
So I'm feeling
And
Install door speakers
Stealing that are
The ceiling
Simplifying one manufacturer
That
Snakes a CO2
Smoke detector
Bose speaker
Just looking for something that
Compatible with Google or
Assistance
Hockey stores
Don't have any preference
But why
Your preferences
Old houses on the market
Feeling Sparks
So we have good news for Dylan because
He's an advantageous
Situation right now
If he's got a new home build it's a lot easier to do speaker mounts for some of these smart speakers
And it's actually not too expensive
There is a company that makes
A flush mount system for walls or ceilings
Or either I guess I should say the
Echo Dot
And the Google home Mini
Sell the company or the brand is Mount
Genie
I have not used these I do not have a new home build butt
Food ideas with a
Drywall saw a little bit of wiring the more expensive one surprisingly are for the Amazon
Echo dot M14 20 bucks
A 5-pack if you have a bunch of speakers not is 90 bucks
A free Google home Mini
SB company makes or sells one for $15 or 5 for $50 so if you have a choice
I probably go with the Google home Mini
Devices and then use the speaker mounts because they're like cheaper in any case they come with everything you need is a template to
Cut into drywall but of course if you have a new home build you really
Aren't cutting into
Existing drywall you like a little work around it
And they also come with
Wires that will connect for the power
I noticed one thing for the one that
The echo.dot uses it cuz of the ten foot cord
Where's the one with the Google home mini they only supplies 6 foot cord
Brigand new home build you can probably have your electrician use whatever power
Wires he or she wants to use just a wire these up
So expensive the sound might be a little Waffle they seem to have like a Sound Chamber to help with that because some of those be
Figures the. So particular the sound comes from the base
Of the echo Dot and that
Kind of gets covered up by this little speak so
Probably another reason consider the home mini ones but that's just my opinion so it's not too expensive if you're a do-it-yourself kind of purse
Person and don't mind doing a little wiring you should be able to do this
And it's not again a new home build just asked for electrician to do it
They love that
They'll do that for you all
Day
As long as you're paying yes they will
That and just so you know cuz usually speakers when you put them in your ceiling the slow low voltage thing but
Actually Mount smart
Speakers that will be a normal voltage thing
Which maven
Someone else can help do it or it made me different
Code required
It depends on your jurisdiction and your local building codes
Okay
Let's take our next
Color
Which is
From Kimberly
And she
Has a question about
Homekit
And outdoor lighting
This is actually a fairly common question
Variations of History Fair
Common question
So
I think many of you will find this valuable
Okay let's hear from Kimberly
Hi this is
Kimberly from Florida
And my husband and I have Smart Home
We have a
Arlo cameras
I'm outside
With Hue motion sensor light
And we have homekit
And my question is
Can we write an essay
Statement
Is there a way
To make it so that when the motion sensor light comes on
The after a period of time it will go off
Right now
We have a raccoon or other little
Visitor
The light goes on
And it stays on until Emmanuel
Shut the light off
Thank you so much
Have a great day
So this was actually pretty easy to resolve kind of threw
But if you would like a hidden setting in the
Philips Hue software the mobile app
There is
A way to create routines in the Philips Hue app
One of those routines is actually a timer
And what you can do Kimberly is go right into the
Two routines tab in the app
You'll see a timers button
Tap that and it'll just say hey click the plus button hurt your first timer you can name it then you could
Then put in the
Time of the timer like how long do you want before something happens to your lights
So
It could be 1 minute 35 whatever you'd like couldn't be ours if you'd like but I think
For a light to come on due to motion sense you're probably looking at about 5 minutes or so
Then you just choose where
This is going to run meaning what
Seen or rooms
I probably put the lights
In a room by themselves called outside or maybe the by the drive I call it driveway for example
Once you
Said where you can then choose what action to take
And when you
See the actions
There's a bunch of
Different choices such as dim night light mode last on staybright
There's also an author
Option which is what you want so choose the off option
Save it
And you should be all set
Therefore when your Arlo camera detects motion and turns on your Hue Lights
That should trigger this Hue routine for the timer
Which would then shut the light off after the time you specified when you set it up
Just keep in mind that once you set this timer up it's going to continuously run so if you're using those lights
Or any other purpose which
I suspect you're not because you're using motion detection
Fire them off
They're going to just keep shutting off every X number of minutes however
That's you sad so that's something to consider it's kind of like you may want to use these lights off a single purpose
At this point because if you're using them for like outdoor parties
Well the lights are going to shut off on everybody for 5 minutes
Which might could make a really cool party games
Everybody freeze when the lights go off
I take a shot
No okay
I don't know what kind of parties are
Probably not
All right
Now
I have disappointing news
For Sherry
I Sherry centos
Really
Great idea
And so
We'll listen to that and
Will tell her what we found out
Hi this is Sherry from North
North Carolina
Just Alexa knows who I am when I ask a question
Can she automatically increase the volume
When answering a question
I am curious to know because I'm hard of hearing
Thank you
Sherry
Like I said this is disappointing
I actually reached out to Amazon and there met him a group
And they said
Oh
No
She can't do that
There's nothing in there that is even remotely able to do that however
On the plus side they said that sounds like a really good idea
And so they forwarded that on to
To their team
What does that mean
I don't know
Maybe one day you'll get the speech
It does sound like a good idea to have different levels of volume for different
Recognize voices
I mean obviously that's not going to help us hear Tech that makes things worse
But you never know they could take this as feedback and create
Custom volumes for different people
Which would be awesome although I will caution you that it
It's always louder for you
That might be
Really bad depending on the certain times of day or What's happen
But I do like it
So
Sorry that you had to have it before the Amazon people implemented
You're getting all the bad news questions
I know
Okay
Well we have kind of good news for free
This is his second call but
Poor man apparently has had his lights on for 3 weeks now according
This message by the time we've answered it it's been
But
Frank has sensors on everything
And wants to know how to
Take those off so
Your strengths
Call Lynn
Hi guys my name is Frank
Love the show very much
Very very
Have your help
I'm
Big fan
Sensors
Sensors on everything I can think of
10 reasons to turn things on
I guess I did
Seal
Like we talked about it
Because my
She's our
How to turn
Things back office
Either
Besan
An action
The center or a period of time
But you can run through that that would
The awesome
And if you could do it quickly.
Because my life
Lebanon Napa
3 weeks
With the sensors and I don't know how to turn
Okay
First offering
I'm going to apologize
Thanks for leaving you with your lights on
For forever
Long time
I'm I'm you may have solved this but
This is actually something that
I was puzzled by until I realized
The solution and it's such a
Silly solution I felt kind of like an idiot but it is also
I paid some kind of like really is this the best way to do this
But it kinda is
And that is for every time that you have a a light
It goes on automatically you have to set an automation to
Make it go
African
You can do it like we talked about with
Kimberly setting a timer so if you have a light that
How is only going to be
Motion activated or activated that way
Doing something like that
If you are
Probably more like oriented around time like bedtime
Then you probably need to set up another
Timer for
After this time of night
Turn this off
So that is
Unfortunately how that's going to have
After work and
What sensors it is tricky I have one in my home office or a motion sensor that after a certain hour
The day I walk in
Obviously it sees me and it turns on the office lights
But if I don't do anything about it those office lights will always stay on
Those lights are voice-controlled so I actually just want to go to the office I tell Google home in my case
Shut these lights
Yeah
And I'm trying to think of other
I mean I talk to
Timatim a lot
Turn off my lights
So you have to do it once you're out of the sensor range in a sense you have to legally leave the room almost Sensei it that's the thing
Yeah or not here's another option let's say it's all down
Stairs or something like that you could program like a smart button
And do the button to turn them off
And just leave that button in whatever room
You're not it
Or good night routine at the end of the day
There's lots of ways to do it but
You actually have to program
Automatically
So
That is our good news bad news
Hey more opportunities to learn and enjoy home automation
Okay here is another question
About madhumeh
Clearly
Amazon is doing really well in this world because we get a lot of questions about Madam and not that many belt
So here we go this is from Chris and he wants to know
How to
Who helped make Madam a a little bit more
Convenient
His iPhone
Let's hear it
Hi Kevin
Stacy
Chris
Wisconsin
Question
I have
Amanda May
Smart home devices
Morning and night and
They run
FaceTime
Man words
I would like to
No it's pause
Apple is
We have
IPhone
Wondering if
When we give the command
Anime
To say good night
Phones
And do not disturb mode and in
In the morning
Wake up they would come out
You could help me out any that would
Be great
So Chris I am right there with you cuz I typically do use an iPhone
I'm not a
Big user of homekit
Unfortunately for you and for me
There's really no way to do this at least not one that I have found
After extensive searching and testing
Creating all kinds of routines and such
The problem is
Apple really locks down
What has access to its
Phone's features
You can use Siri to set your phone to go into Do Not Disturb mode or you could program it by time
Without side of the Apple world I have not found a way to
To do that so I mean I've even looked at trying to use the homekit features in the home
Software app
2 when you shut a light that's homekit enabled do something in the phone but unfortunately in the home app you can only control
Other homekit devices in the iPhone is not a homekit device in that regard so
There's just no easy way to do it with Madam and I have found so that means you need to either speak another come on before
It's time for bed or you need to schedule it
Not great options
But those are the only two we have at this point
Glad I don't have an iPhone
So that's
It's pretty straightforward our next answer
In question really is not a straightforward so
We're going to get in here
Jamie wants our opinion of the home assistant DIY Pro
And this is kind of like openhab or homebridge it's another kind of
You run it yourself
Some other computer in your house
Sand
It's really powerful but it is also
Maybe not the friendliest ecosystem for newbies
This particular person's question
Covers
Olive home assistant and specifically
Using it
With wired alarms
So let's hear from Jamie
Hi Stacy and Kevin
Mine Jamie Campbell and I'd like to know what your opinion is of the
Home assistant
Open source DIY home automation project
Shameless episodes ago Stacy mentions the konnected alarm panel it sounds like the
Perfect solution using all the wired Burglar Alarm sensors which are already installed in our house
Integration with modern home automation wired sensors are reliable and
Batteries connected panel works
Where's the Home assistant project which sounds interesting
And your opinion will the home assistant project be viable in the long run
Is it easy enough to use for the next owner of our house to consider it an asset and how well does it integrate with
Other office shelf sensors
Thanks a lots look forward to your answer by
Okay Jamie
Because you know what home assistant is
I'm going to assume that you're
Self-selecting into the type of people who are like
They don't see a board
Can go by the way what is that
Yes I can play and customize and do crazy things
If you are that person home assistant
Is lovely
It actually has
Much better
Interface
It still could be prettier
But it's
It's much better than it used to be
And it has a large
Community of people who are
Putting things on the home assistant Forum boards that
You can find all kinds of ways to cook
Control example Utah
Wired alarms
There are honestly
Doesn't
You can actually connect and with lovey instruct
If you were comfortable doing that
I'm going to go ahead and recommend
Connected with a k
Alarm system because that's actually easy enough
I could do it
It was still a little intimidating but it wasn't
I didn't have to
I have my own life
Relays
Tri-center suck it whatever is in
Things that I barely
Comprehend what they are this was a very simple process
WhatsApp videos online
Support me through it and if you already have wired device isn't connected panel there's a
Decent chance it may work with that depending on the brand
Yeah they have
Tons
So
That's part of it and then the other thing is
I'm going to stay home assistant
If you want to go that route
I wouldn't feel
If you're comfortable spending that time and effort I would say go for it is
A community the people who are doing it
Die Hard
Fans of the stuff I don't
See it like it has a very robust
Community that is still contributing it's not like I seen it drop off
In fact I've seen the community grow over time
So
I will also drop a link into the show notes to a epic video it's an hour-long update published in
About how home assistant is doing and what's coming next
It will help you
They have some big things planned so
If you're up for it
Do it
And one of the other reasons to consider doing it it's all local there's no
Cloud involved in a lot of people like that local ability to
Keep their data kind of within the home
Yeah that is very true
I will say
Since I'm in this mindset right now is some
Someone who's selling their home
Everything you do
It's not something you're going to be able to hand over to somebody
Later so
You're going to move in a year
Maybe don't do
That's just where it again
And that's where my headspace is at right now
Are you guys I'm just like a hoe
How am I going to document
The stuff for people
I can't
This goes out
Alright let's take a break
For a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor for the Q&A episode
Again you guys
Is Schlage
They make connected locks
That we just
Love and if you guys want a chance to win your own Schlage lock
You can call us before December 31st at midnight
Yes that's right right from your New Year's Eve party you guys
Just call us at 512-623-7424
And you will be entered to win a Schlage lock
Is a really good luck
So
By golly
Start your new year off right with a smarter home
Thanks to Schlage
I'm a call in from our New Year's party
Yeah Kevin you're not allergic
For the win
No no I know but it damn sure didn't message because of music
True
I didn't think about that part of it
Please do,
I would love to hear it and publish it on the show
Okay
Let's get
Back
To it
Back to the grindstone Kevin we have got more
Questions to
Answer
This one
We get a variation of this every week so
Let's do it this one is from Brent with a quest
About Wi-Fi
Let's hear from Brent
Hi this is
Is Brandt from Roy Utah
I have a shop that I'm building its back into my property is not that far from the house but
I definitely will need to put in
Something.
Extend the Wi-Fi out there
So I can monitor a 3D printer in a few weather
Items like that
I know how to extend it but I'm looking for options that might be
A little bit more functional or maybe even
Cool
I know I've heard there's some
Start speakers
That maybe work is
Place an extender I'm just looking for ideas
Let me know
Thanks
So this
Question is actually fairly easy because there are so many good options
I am kind of particular to using
Google Wi-Fi but there are other
Mesh
Options out there Linksys has one
Orbi
I mean there's so many euro
But part of me says if your
Building a shop out back
Depending how far it is I don't know Stacy you think it makes sense actually run a wired connection out there and then
Maybe
Extended that way
True
I mean okay
Okay so this is me I love wired I literally have an ethernet port
It sometimes too in every single room of my house including my kitchen
So you're talking to a lady whose like hey can I rent some conduit
Flush some Cat6 cables and ethernet through here
If you answered yes then by God
That's what I'm going to do
So if you have that option
I'm all for that
Because then you could do cool stuff like have like 4K video
Out there
That's going to be a little bit better but no maybe you don't need that yet
Again if you're going to extend just Wifi really any mesh the
It's going to be good
Would you actually wait until it like a new
Round of mesh routers comes out because Brian was saying you know do we know of anything coming down the pike that might be useful
In terms of
Smart Homes with Wi-Fi anytime soon
With those in terms of new products
But you have to remember is even if your router is like the sickest
Most awesome WiFi 6 router out there
And now we're no longer calling it like a x
Even if you do that
You got to remember that the other the receiving
Also have
Has to be a x
Or Wi-Fi 6
Compatible
To get all of those
Advantages right so most bones right now
Especially all the
Connected gear that were throwing out to
That's all like
Wales school it's like
Wi-Fi for
Or three even
So
You know having
The latest and greatest is really going to only affect you when they start seeing that in devices so I think you're going to be fine for a while
Okay our next question
Is all about
Outdoors
We got a couple outdoor question
Is coming our way so let's get started first
With j
Let's hear from Jay
Maybe third time's the charm
Kevin and Stacy
Is Jade
From Santa Clarita
Question is
Temperature sensor
I've got the
Keen home vents
Paired up with my ecobee thermostat and there's temp
Retreat centers in
Room but there indoor only of course
That looking for an outdoor temperature
Scepter don't want to go around.
Weather station if necessary
So wondering if you can make any recommendation I also have the
Habitat
Iot hub
And I've got some
Smoke detectors and another
Just after 2
Gird up to that so
When are you going to recommend
Amsterdam temperature sensor for outdoors at all
Zigbee or Z-Wave
How to hook up to the habitat
Thank you very much in a great show
Enjoy listening
Figure
Okay
Jay
I want to do like
Give you a temp sensor cuz I assume you want your temps
Center to actually work
With your smart
So they're plenty of devices out there that
You can like just look outside your like it's 42 degrees
What is really frustrating to me is a lot of connected
Devices like doorbells and even some outdoor cameras
How temperature sensors in them but they're not visible to you unless you're pulling up something like openhab or Eve
Even Homosassa
So I'm going to assume that you're a normal person who isn't going to do that
And you're going to need a dedicated outdoor
Temperature sensor
Inference that
I am going to recommend
Bnet at
They actually just got bought by a grand they have a netatmo weather station
And it is
I am expensive it's usually on sale around the holidays
This is what I've used
In the past to know what the weather is outside it is
$180
You can also buy it with
The rain gauge
If you want and
And then you can actually get it for like 200
And
Yeah that's my big recommendation cuz you can actually pull that data in through other services like a gift
And then
Tie that information
Did you like your Hue Lights or something like that
And if you don't want to buy anything new because
Why not save money right
You can always
Speaking again
If go use Weather Underground
See if anyone has like a weather station near you
And that might be
Close enough
To work and then you can basic
Just pull that data end
Weather Underground says it's 42 degrees do the following with
At home stuff
And that's actually something that I've done
In the past I've turned my Hue Lights blue when it was below freezing outside
And
Yeah that was
Kind of a fun little thing I did when I was
Trying to get ready early in the morning with the dog and
Now I just look at
My Fatima a device
Do using somebody else's weatherstation what's next somebody else's wife I never
Never never mind
Okay
So that I probably use you
No no they don't
I have a lovely
Oh actually they could be
Because they have the guest
Knots
It's possible
That's my new excuse for any weird downloads that we see on my Wi-Fi
From my IP
The address okay other outdoor sensor questions
This one comes from Bruce
Let's hear it
Santa Fe
I live on a
1/2 Lots
In our driveways by 300 feet long I'd love to have some sort of the
Sensor that tells me when somebody is pulled into our driveway in
Send me notification of some
Is that something that can be done relatively
By the way since I live in Santa Fe
Where were you
30 days
Every year
This word set up
Solar recharging
Look forward to your response
Okay Bruce
I don't know how long your driveway is which does change my recommendation
Just a little bit
But the bottom line is if it's too far away if you can't use any of the popular thing
Things like Wi-Fi or Bluetooth
Were 50 years away
So that throws you into this weird other
So that's
If your driveway super long you're going to be in the land of
Dedicated
Driveway sensors
Which companies like Chamberlain
I found a company called guard line
It also makes a really well-reviewed system
These are going to use a different radio
Technology that
I can go farther
In
Guidelines
In particular
They have one that will go
Auto quarter mile
And then they have one for a little bit closer
What they do is
The
Sensor
Is battery powered
When it's triggered
It'll send an alarm at alert
Alarm
And that's good enough for you and the alarm can be back
Back in your house
Then that's great
If you wanted to actually do something like turn on your porch light
That's where things
Skyline lets you
Tie into a
A 12-volt switch so what you can do is you take the receiver you take off the back
Can you wire
Whatever switch you want
To that
Device
And then when the sensor is triggered
And instead of like the alarm actually going off on the receiver what'll it do it is it
Google say hey
Something just happened
My state just changed
Now
To bring that back and
Smart home you're going to need some
I'm pretty heavy lift
SmartThings is going to be your best
Because they have a dedicated community
So import
And
There's plenty of discussion
About wifi-based
Relays
For 12 volt
Contact
Sensors
Yeah those are all things you're going to want to go
Until what you'll do is you'll take your 12 volt contact
Center that converts to Wi-Fi
Wire that too
State changes
Send a notification over Wi-Fi
Then
You're going to have to program
SmartThings
App that you watch
Actually
Do something with that
So that's a really long way of saying it's going to be kind of a pain in the butt so
This may not be the
Best option
The Garland stuff is about a hundred bucks
You can buy the Wi-Fi
The12volt to.wifi stuff for
Between actually
10 +
5 + $20
The other option I want to give you especially if you have Wi-Fi
Play all the way out there
Is
Kind of Overkill
But it will work
Ring make
Fix a camera
Called the spotlight
If you take the ring Spotlight cam
In a solar panel
You can actually put that out there
If you have the Wi-Fi
I think can get that far out
Then
That will actually send you that ties directly into
You all kinds of smart home systems
And you can do that so
That tho will cost you
$229
For the camera and the solar panel
But
It is a stand-alone thing
Is predicated though
Are you having Wi-Fi as far out as the edge
Keep your driveway and then you get both the camera and emotion
Which I know it feels like Overkill but really there are
No outdoor capable
Wifi-based sensors that we
Find
If any of you out there
Have them
It also alleviates any wiring
Which is a big big plus I think
All of the solutions I told you where wire
Well except for the
Oh I see the voltage that I was thinking about like none of these things have
But yes
That the wiring
That's not hard wiring you could totally do it
Okay
Just don't like it
I mean
Could you look it
I'm like have you ever licked a 9 volt battery
At my daddy
To do that to me cuz he's
Sometimes I let the dog like it pay does not like that you are so mean
Small children
Okay
Norm
I feel like we're done with Outdoors let's go indoors
Two Echo skills for middle schoolers
Dean has like a raped
And we cannot
Wait
To tell you what
So let's hear
From Dean
Try this one more time
16 and I'm a designer body
Steve Perry
I have the genius our kids that just loved
You thought you were talking about writing
Nikolas and so on
And why isn't it
Can we write
Stills or
NFL
Can we do something with iot and I was curious how
Still at 8
This Quest
In and see it from the perspective of middle schoolers
Because they are native to this
Technology
Any help would be
Great I
Would appreciate
Thanks in advance in
Totally love your show
So can I just say I love this question Dean I'm a big believer in
Stem
Young people learning to code in Tinker and make
So this is awesome
And you are in luck if you have not seen it yet
On the
Amazon developer site
Madam age
Skills
There is a kids
Section end
We'll put a link in the show notes all that you could probably just Google Madam a skills
Kit for kids which is how I found this at I spent like an hour
Just pulling through everything on here
So everything here is geared towards
Kids under the age of 13 and that's important because
Amazon provide all the information you need to satisfy the privacy and
Compliance laws
And the parental consent laws for kids cuz that's obviously a part of this even if you're just doing this
In a classroom I think you
Probably seems to want to follow those
There's also some amazing little
How do I say
Tips not just tips but some really cool tools you can use
Have you heard of speech cons before
Con con
See I have not
I'm going to play one or two the right now
Speech cons are little interjections
Can you can have Madam a reed
Any word
As
In a certain way let me give you an example
Alrighty
Aloha
Yoga
Certain interjections kind of got a little more personality than the same old same old
And I think it would just love you too faced Peach concept
There's hundreds of them there's hundreds of them and on top of all that getting back to the heart of the question
There are
Kids
Skill tutorials and I followed through with one
And I'm not going to lie. There's some
Working bother me an Amazon has made this easy as possible but it's more than just like building say the
Voice interface and the responses
You have to go through after you've done that because
For example they build a quiz
Game skill in there tutorial on Michael this is easy once you get the first part done then you have to go and build
Amazon AWS Lambda function
And then link
Wii user interface to that code
So not trying to scare you I'm just saying you may want to
Do the Lambda function for the kids and let them work on the user interface you link the two
And then they can test it customize it and heck
If it's
Really awesome and they want to share it with other kids
You all can publish it to the Alexa skills
Library so another good reason to follow all those legalities and things in case you decide you want to publish it so just
At the site go through it I don't think you need to be a heavy-duty Kotor to get
What you want done and again I think of you
The kids focus on the voice user interface you can tell them how you're going to tie it together with
AWS in the cloud
But you probably won't do that part yourself
Very cool
I kind of want to do this now too
I want it to say awooga
All the time
Actually I don't know why that
What's tickling me so much
But it really is
Okay
Sorry there's just so many and you can just keep clicking on them up here's one of my favorites before we leave this one
Alright does Google have anything like this
I am not
Seen anything like this I'm sure they have ways to modulate the voice but
I've not seen like a web page
Filled with hundreds of these that you can play back and then just you know listen to and that you were that's the one I want to use
You have John Legend
His voice
They don't have that though
All right
Teen hopefully this gets you started with projects for your kids for the new year
Okay
That concludes
Who's our Q&A episode hopefully you guys
Feel smarter
Weiser have more ideas for gadgets to buy or things
Connect
And we want to thank our sponsor for this
Schlage
Who makes
Smart locks for the connected home
Do you guys want to win a Schlage give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
Leave us a question
Will try to get to it
And
Thank you guys for listening and I hope you have a wonderful New Year
What about you Kevin I hope you have a wonderful New Year
I hope I do too
Oh oh wait no I hope everybody
All right
Be safe have fun and thanks
Thanks for listening
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Dot-com
Will see you next week