Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacy Higginbotham at this is your co-host
Kevin tofel
Is chock-full of great news for you today we've got
Roomba and the map gate we're going to call at Mapco
Elon Musk news embedded RFID tags in employees
I'm going to talk about the Amazon wand
We got a dead company we've got an acquisition and we've got a funding
Plus Kevin has a book
Recommendation for you
All of this
Followed
Buy an interview
With
Alex khurram who is in charge of
Comcast
Corwin efforts
It's called machineq so we can learn a lot about that
After we hear from
Our sponsor this week
Schlage
Now
Let's get the show started with a message from another one of our sponsor
Smart Kitchen Summit is the only event of his kind to tackle the future of food cookie
And the kitchen with decision-makers and disruptors across the food
Cooking appliance retail and Technology Industries
With two full days of content discussions networking and product showcases the 2017 Smart Kitchen Summit
Will be held at Benaroya Hall in Seattle
On October 10th at 11
My listeners get to take 25% off of any ticket type with the code
Stacey Stacey
Don't wait
Because early bird ticket pricing ends July 31st
An added bonus
Or not I don't know
I'll be there
All right
Is it a bonus
That's a bonus
Kevin's hang out with me in person
It's a bonus people trust me
So okay
I am actually in Seattle this week
So
It's nice up here
Maybe one day the show
All the time
So let's get started with
Embedded RFID tags because I don't know
Kevin yes or no yes or no so so that the news isn't that a company is
Implanting
Microchips and some of its employees little RFID tags
They're certainly not the first
People to have these I've seen for a couple years now people
Actually putting a little RFID chips in the webbing between their thumb and their
A palm in their hand
These are just they're doing in cells
Albert is actually employee a three Square Market is the name of the company in Wisconsin
About 50 employees are
Can you get implanted with RFID tags and why are they doing that
So it's easier to buy snacks and things from kiosks there at the
Office without using a credit card cash or smartphone
So
A lot of people read this and say exactly what you did say say it's creepy because it's so they're going to know everything
There's no tracking your GPS or like that so I don't know how creepy it really is
Why do you say it's creepy
Pékin planting things in your body to buy
Snickers bars is
A step too far now we should clarify this
Voluntary
We should also clarify that
For the most part you have to actually get pretty close to it a reader that reads RR
Yes you have this thing in your body
But you have to get
Usually within a
Oh my God
A couple inches
There's passive and active
Enticing
The Pacifier
I would imagine that they are everything to keep them as small as possible I would never agree with you
So
If you don't eat just
But I've been to it so Facebook you know that they've had these for a while you can
They have vending machines full of like
All kinds of stuff and you just input your employer code
You get your thing
So that's also cashless
Facebook pay pay for it but it other places you could
Tie it to someone
Paycheck
If there's obviously there are alternatives to this
You know you could use your smartphone and ID badge watch Etc
I thought about doing this myself a couple years back and to test it
I don't know if you remember this but I'm going to say back in 20
12 or so
Samsung was selling programmable NFC stickers
Yeah
So I said before I put something in my body let me put something on my body cuz it at that time there was no
NFC
Smart watches and things like that it was we knew they were coming
Am I going to stick this on my
On the back of my hand for a couple days I put an NFC Reader in my
Mudroom door to get in the house when I came in I would just swipe my hand over the reader and all the lights would come on so I was doing some kind of automation
If I did this myself
I don't see that there's any
Creepy Factor new Big Brother Factor but
I can understand people not wanting a company into an item I would not want to companies do that either
I think we're getting to the point now where you can program these things
Easily
And you could actually do this yourself and not
And you have control I guess that's really what it comes down to
Because it comes it comes down to it being voluntary
Implicit question with a poises does it some point it become
Coercive
Like if you were the only person who is like
Yeah you know what I don't want
That's a pretty picture
Invasive
Crispy definition
That's where I am
I have this feels like a slippery slope that we're going down
What if it was you and I'm not saying that you would do this but what if you said you would if you had total
Control over it so you could program it to your door locks and
Your bank accounts
Send
Maybe three API through a place that you worked out and they would just allow
You did
No enter in
Country security with
You had control
That feels like a step too far just in turkey oven if I had control because I'm not sure that I would have control and then they become
What are some
You know tapped into that API
Pulling out information
Are there mechanisms to change that without having to
Remove the implant and pop another
Oh you can you can reprogram these things
I reprogram it with my phone
Mini
Yeah you just tell the program what you want to do what you want the NFC tag to represent
I just tap it and it reprogrammed
Probably
It's not give me the instructions
Instructions
But it's
Is it's kind of
Caring for lack of a better word
And can they be spoofed
Magic anything can be smooth
10 min but I don't think it would be easy
These are the questions that I would want before I post
Like
There's also you know how long do electronics
Nothing to deserve because they're encased in some kind of capsule
That's about the size of a grain of rice
Pink
But they're good for about 10 years
So it's like a microchip in a dog
Is it okay to do to the dog
Really really
You know I will
Alright so
This is happening you guys
And if you think this is awesome
Then you know there's a company in Wisconsin plus you
Cheese curds
Which
Apparently our delicious
Moving right along into
Possibly
Google is equal to
Let's talk about the Roomba
I was saying if you thought poop
Apocalypse was bad you should see Matt gaetz
But then Kevin and I discussed how hard it was
Say that words
Remember how rubos were taking people's apparently their pets
Poop on the carpet
Everywhere I never was a guy
Why robots
The comedy behind
Is that again
Bad press
This time about
Liru bizarre it's the 900 in
80 I believe
Ribeye so the ones with Wi-Fi the 980
Evolution 2015
Maps your home
And apparently according to the terms of service
You can actually send that mapping data
And people are like
We don't like this
Well yeah I mean I don't
Biscuits Pakistani talk about a week or two ago consumer awareness and and maybe putting
And very clear print on the packaging of these things what happens to the data what are you
I know there's that you learned all that but
People don't read that and it's just
Not simple to read
So
There's got to be a better way to communicate it
Because if you agree to it then room is doing there within their bounds
Yes and
Here's again like
Like you said
We talked about
Companies that want
To be proactive about this are going to do better
Because right now everyone is
Freaking out
Roomba said in that it was
Committed to the absolute privacy of their customer related data
They can use
The rainbow without connecting it
Go to the internet and you can opt out of sending that data to the cloud through switch on the mobile app
The company also said that no data is sold to third parties no data will be shared with third parties without informed consent
Of our customer
Zoe
I read
About half of the hughleys in terms of service in terms of service in the privacy policy or two different
Document
I read those in about half of my
Barely Legal
These are not things that
Explain stuff
Very clearly
I read a lot of them so I
Have a sense
What's me
Done but no one reads the terms of service on their back
Just like I didn't read the terms
Service that appeared
My oven
We don't have time for that
It's not consumer-friendly it's not that day it's all legally isn't and what time did you need to know what you're looking for
I think
Before you understand it and it's just not easy
Absent regulation which I do think we need
We need
Friendly ways to say hey
Here's how to opt-out
And it should be like
Possibly like
Permissions on like an Android app for an iPhone app with a like this company is trying to
Is asking for access
Could be something as simple as
The Roomba
Wants to
Cher
So this is what I think we need to get to
Otherwise
People are not like
I guarantee like
People read this were like
And if you already did
You're like okay well I'm going to turn that off
No data for you
In a sense that the problem because room is using
You said that mapping data to the cloud so that I could get better
Right
And so that's why
Topic need to be like
Transparent about was happy
Not transparent
Phuket legalese for transparency
Hey we're going to do this with your data
Yeah it's a tricky because a lot of these products you provide better Services when they crowdsource the data that they all cap
Right they can make the devices smarter and
Optimize and so on on the flipside people have to have a
Clear wedge opt-in or opt-out early early on
I need to know what they're opting in or out to
Okay
That's rude
So what's worse
Sharing your spreading your dog's paw
I'm sure for some people exposed
All right
Let's see August
B-connected door lock maker
About 25 million dollars in additional
Funding
This is on top of
Around the Rays last year
Here is
They've actually launched
A bunch of products
They launched a prologue
A new version of their locked
Tomcat version ticket
Valentines
The goal here is to boost their access August access Services Program
Lets people into your house
When you
Can see what it is
Or you can give codes
Do people like
Delivery folks
Etcetera
So
This is pretty cool
In addition to a funding
Gay good news we have an acquisition
This is an industrial internet
Things
Acquisition this is a company called
It is acquired a company called a rant
You may not recognize these companies
Because they
Direct consumer
Is iot services provider to a lot of company
Big Appliance makers
Basically have been doing this since 2006
So they're old school
They can connecting devices to the internet and managing those connections for a long time
I don't know how much the deal was for
Protea is a really strange company
They came out of nowhere
Is my 2015 with a hundred million dollars
In funding
It's the Ansari family who does the Ansari x-prize
The cell
An operating system for the Smart Home
To telcos and service providers
And I was kind of like really is that is that going to be a big business
But what they've done here is
They're still doing that line of business but with the acquisition of a rayon
They now basically have a
God I hate these words end in solution oh my God but they can do everything
And it really approaching it from that Telco mentality of
It's five nines reliability and all that
The one thing that I think is
Interesting and we never talked about this and it's a really big deal
Is they have
Really flexible
Pricing
For creating iot services
That's actually a big deal in the Telco space because a lot of these companies like when you have a cell phone plan
The software that manages all of that for the billing perspective is Arcane and in
Tents and it's slow
So a service provider champs-elysees
Swap out my
Plants I want to change things up a little
That takes weeks
So what these guys have done if they made it on demand
They have that capability to create an on-demand service
Program I'm just using one
I wonder that also helps
Companies
Startups actually
Get their connectivity easier in a sense of you know sometimes if you're not big enough Verizon AT&T is not going to talk to you
They will work with startups
You can call
But this is more for like a big company
Come in and say hey
All of these connected devices
I want you guys to connect them and manager
What my customers when I have 10 million customers
What services thereby in charge them
Inappropriately for them
Got it
The scalability then
Yeah it's hard
I know it sounds really excruciating lead all it does
But it's hard
This is
Not a small thing
Okay
We got our funding
We got in a position and sadly
We have a company that has stopped
I hate this
So finkton
Which
How do upstairs
I left the founders I would have met with him a bunch of times
It was a consumer-oriented
Text based
Home automation
So basically it was kind of conversational interface
It was tied to your Twitter account
Any idea was like
Your things knew who you were in there
I knew your friends were
It would even if I remember correctly reach out to you it's not like you would just not like a chatbot where you have to initiate the conversation
And it may notice something from a sensor or location of a friend or something and it would tell you something
Yeah so this was a really friendly in
Cute in
Fun idea for how to communicate with
That is not where the bark
It's going so
Tom Coates a co-founder he he said that
It's not working
Southington is is dead
Nice interface
So
All right
Elon Musk
So we've got
Funny acquisition death and
Something more exciting stuff and now we have something boring
Flooring
Literally
Not too much to tell but it's kind of cool the boring car elevator from Elon Musk
He tweeted out a video of
The first demonstration
Showing a
Tesla of course pulling up to a little
Platform and then down down down the car went and this is
I can choose this before we were talking about
Just before the show started
I was thinking hyperlipid this actually doesn't have any idea what the hyperloop this is going to
The platform's going to bring cars down to almost like a conveyor belt
Type of solution for underneath cities
This is at this is your cortical on-ramp
Yes this is so basically you drive on it there's a really great Debo it's
Super fun in your life
Real
The cars
Elevator that
Disguised as a parking space
Ghost
And it drops you into this
Zips along underneath the ground
Either Menard report or iRobot
In the movie
Yeah I guess it's like that but I remember is that the highways on one of those two movies I think it was iRobot work
It would drop
Cars down to lower levels
And whatnot and they were just
Be automated
No traffic you know everything was happy
Pappy and Autumn
Yeah
So boring not doing it
But
That's what's happening there
How far are we from this
Lord Only Knows do we want this
Although
With automation
You know
Maybe we should get there without having to dig tunnels underneath the ground
Baby you know adding more freeways
Has never solved
Traffic
Really I don't know
Places like Houston we have
Luckily freeways
There still traffic so with autonomous driving
More
Space may be helpful but I think autonomous-driving is probably the bigger
Solution to this
Exactly
So also an industrial news
Because it's fun
We got two reports worth checking out
Actually we've got one report was checking out in the news that the industrial internet-of-things
Consortium
Has put out April
Vocabulary
For the industrial internet-of-things
Can I can I just
Reading that is like a dictionary and then that's the ultimate
Boring example
Yes
Yes that's true we we miss our great Segway
Sorry
Nope
So basically what this is is they've added 16 new words so
You know what we're talking about when we have the inner
We're talking about the industrial internet-of-things
This isn't
Bad idea
Because even just two weeks ago I wrote a story where is it I don't even know what the edge of the network
Cuz everyone's come throws these terms around in you
What is
So now
They actually have a definition not of the edge but they do have the edge Gateway in here
I'm still out of luck at my definition for the edge but that's okay
So they've defined things
Using their own standards but also ISO standards for people who are going to have to be
Compliant which is a big deal for me
Manufacturing
If it turns a definer is mundane as
Mosquito cryptography
Data-at-rest
Who is esoteric as
A cross-cutting
Concern or a cross-cutting function
By the way those are things that affect the whole system
It may impact
Multiple viewpoints of the architecture
Cross-cutting function is a function that may be applied and realize across multiple functional domains
Describe the architecture to address
Cross-cutting
Concerns
So you can see this is riveting stuff
But if you're in the industrial internet-of-things
You may want to check it out
Also in the white paper
World
We actually have a really cool paper
We won't dig into it but we going to link to it and I'll probably do it my newsletter as well be
That rich
And inciting
Arm has put out a paper a white paper on
The internet of things and the economics of a trillion connected devices
Because when arm was bought by soft
DC or something
Came out to there
Add event last year and was like
You know how people are like
20 billion connected devices
Inside
It was actually really great
Talk in this paper basically backs that up and then gets lots of data on
What that's going to cost but it's going to need to tail
In my favorite chart
Is
A chart that basically gives you the cost
There it just made it cost
A different iot
Modules
Was that your favorite chart
I like that chart I think
There
I'm a little more optimistic the prices will come down faster than what they say but they do take something in consideration that you pointed out to me
And that is the power for these modules such as using solar cells to power a lot of them
And that'll increase cost so
I see where they're coming from
I like to have a broken down by industry to on
How much each industry will
Benefit financially
Switching over to iot tech devices
Yes
So
I think everyone should actually check this out
Because
You're going to feel smarter after
I promise you
And you're going to be smarter with actual data
Which is the best
Okay
We each have two things
To talk about
Kevin's got a book recommendation and then I was going to tell you about my life with the Amazon
His theme
With a wand
The echo Dot
The echo wand
I thought this
A while back but we haven't talked about it
Basically this is a
This is my gateway to Amazon shopping
In the market and I bought it because of that
Whole Foods deal
You can only buy things
It's like a track sure
Your quest
Here at the shopping list you can talk to it and
Scan things
So
But it only buys things on Amazon
Put it on your Amazon list
Switch
How convenient
Yeah I guess you know Amazon's not that great
Does not
Grocery shopping
So I don't actually use it
Except I do scan these three things I buy an Amazon all the time I will use the one to
Escaneador
But
It also has
So what is actually kind of fun for is
You have to hold down the button
Can I talk to it
But
I gave it to my mom when she was staying over and it became like this little remote control cuz there's no. In the
Bedroom or an echo in the bedroom
Does she got to like
Control things like
Hey
If it's too cold for you at night
Press this button and say Madam a
Turn the ecobee to blah blah blah
So that was kind of nice cuz it was twenty bucks and was actually free
Because I got into $20 Amazon credit
So basically I got like a little remote
Controls for my echo
Yeah I actually never thought of it like that. I did not buy one because I'm Mighty now that I have Dash buttons for certain things I've heard
Amazon grocery wise
Didn't see the need for one that you're right I mean you can walk around the whole house
It's like carrying an echo in your pocket
So
It's not design
If you're carrying a
IPhone
Brighten also have that yeah
I found it useful for that
And I saw actually somebody
Link to it someone put an echo dot in there
Your car
Wichita that I wanted to do so I was like hell
Can I bring this into my
Far
But I don't have an always-on Wi-Fi
But I am constantly in my
My car and I want to ask
Questions
So that was
What was certain smartphones you can do that now
That is true or I could just ask Google who's actually smart
Questions I usually come up
Do squirrels have opposing
Thumbs
They do not
Titans
Good to know
Will there be a child
This is this is what happens when you're at a red light and you're watching a squirrel like I was
Doing origami
Somebody's been driving too much
Yeah yeah that's not drinking just right
So that's
Kevin Kevin maybe house
Well since we gave people some
Good reading song
I still think boring reading here some exciting reading and I didn't realize you would already read this
I'm not ready for the show but I read a book
By Matthew Mather
Called darknet
Activate mobile me
Well in bookstores obviously and I read it on my Kindle on tickets
Part of Kindle unlimited so if you already parking on unlimited you can read it
Free or
Prescription if not the Kindle prices $5.99
It's so hard
Talk about this book without giving too much away
But
I why am recommending it is because we've always talked about all these sensors around the world and
Only can have more than one trillion size arm
Nai and autonomous this and that
And privacy concerns and spoofing
Yes
So I'm not going to say anymore but
It's all that and a bag of chips
So
Wrapped in a story
Maybe years ago
Think about it
Yeah because it's one of those sci-fi books that way after you read it especially because it's now to wish years old
Any industry
Ramps up so fast that you're like
2 years ago this was science
Fiction now it's not even so much
Fiction
I want to see anymore
Yes
I will say that
Will be reading future
Underground bunkers with absolutely no connectivity
Etiwanda
That's not coming
All right
That's a good stopping
For this week
Next up we are going to have a word for
And after that
We are going to
To hear from Alex
Scrum who is in charge of
Comcast
Machineq Network
And this is not just Comcast
Life
In X with machine Cube It's all about Laura
Low power
Wide area network
Technology and how
You can use that you're gonna learn a lot about power constraints bandwidth
Security
Is chock-full of awesome stuff in a lot of
It's really useful for asset tracking
Stay tuned for that
And now a word from our sponsor
Everyone we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is Al
Legion which makes
Schlage Locks
I've got robbed
Set futuristics Lake here to talk to us
Yesterday hi Rob how are you doing
I'm great Stacy how are you
Excellent
So what are some considerations
In choosing a Smart Lock
Stacy I have some thoughts
Surround electronic lock
Consideration or selection for your viewers
Basics candy Left Behind when you're thinking about technology first
So one of the things we recommend is
Make sure first and foremost that you get a good grated lock
So Beacham a grading is important
But also things like understanding
Hey
Can I replace the deadbolt
Or do I need to go with a retrofit
Solution
Now the benefits of replacing your deadbolt parts
Control
If you replace the deadbolt
You're guaranteed that all the keys that you may have delivered
Neighbors
Friends
Whoever
Overtime
Are not going to work
And that deadbolt
So when you replace the deadbolt you have the benefit of key
Control
Other things to consider when you buy
An electronic deadbolt touchscreen deadbolt solution
Does it have a tapered deadbolt
If you don't replace the original deadbolt
You're going to have a traditional deadbolt that's not tape
Rob
What is a tapered deadbolt
A tapered deadbolt is exactly that it's a deadbolt that's slightly tapered
On each end
This is important for door alignment
Door alignment is important because
With heat your door expand
With called your dorm a shrink
And if that deadbolt isn't aligned properly
It will never
Close fully
Secondly
The other thing associated with that is
Motors
It's important have a strong motor on your touch
Screen deadbolt
So that has enough strength
Where is that taper deadbolt
Couches
Pull the door closed
Any other considerations
So Stacy one of the things
That we focus on is ease of installation
We like to think
That you can
Install one of our touchscreen deadbolt in less than 10 minutes
With just a Phillips head screwdriver
Another thing
Consider is battery life we don't believe in using proprietary batteries we think they should be conveniently available
We also
Specify are touchscreen deadbolt
What's the last at least
12 month
Width for double a batteries
And that doesn't mean
That is just
On
Day in and day out that means testing it with a minimum of 10 usages a day
Fourier
Hot diggity
That's pretty awesome
So where can I go to find out more
You can go to schlage.com
And if you'd like to know more about what I'm working on you
You can go to schlage.com thought leadership
Or follow me on Twitter on a Schlage features
Hey we would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Alex Karim who is
General manager at machineq
Which is Comcast
Lorawan Network effort
Alex how are you doing today
I'm doing great thanks Stacy
I am excited to have you on the show
About a year ago Comcast
Excited about law
And I was like who
This could be fine and we didn't hear much from you until a couple weeks ago when you guys run doubt to total of 15 markets
Adam-12 markets
And here you are today to talk not just about Comcast's efforts but also what people should think of
When they think of Laura
Tall order can you handle it
Yes
And thank you for having
Guess
Alright let's get started with
Why
Laura
Laura win
For Comcast
How did this all come about
About two years ago we started looking at low-power wide area Networks
There's an opportunity for Comcast
To provide a whole
New set of services
To its client
Primarily business clients
Conversations business and Bose technical
Looking at the competing on license
Opportunities out there
As you know probably that recently we actually acquired Spectrum as well
But at that point we are focused primarily on license opportunities
And so
Begin a pretty intensive
R&D research effort
Travel the globe
Supposed to different carriers both Wireline and Wireless
Understand how they were thinking about iot in the future
And after having their own field trials here in Philadelphia and having looked at
Are the dishes opportunities visibility the unlicensed Technologies
Became pretty obvious to us when you had
Interrupting
Thirtysomething or Plus
Types of carriers mobile carriers in NY line carriers
Adopted lorwyn standard that the ecosystem was
Going to be critical going for
And Laura Wang
Heather ecosystem
In addition to Hardware companies I Cisco who are who are supported Etc thrust feeling of Laurel and all fertile
The best long-term strategy
Future-proof having
And iot Enterprise iot
Got it now
Let's talk about
Laura as a standard
Because there's a lot going on there and it's not like everybody
What Laura in
As you mentioned it's unlicensed
Work
Let's talk about bandwidth rates and all of that kind
Power consumption
Sure seal or Bay City is a physical communication protocol that
Have traction
Primarily is New Beginning days is a camp
Campus
Regional opportunity
But you were able to set up a Gateway and start managing
Tickler device using the Laura
Protocol he did such a great job of
Doing that and I'm providing the right propagation and because of you it's very low-power depending on certain what they require
Apartments off of the device
Allura
Battery powered device can remain out in the field for about a decade
That
Carriage got together and started thinking through
Can we create a mock layer basically a way for this to move out of the campus of Art and more into true
Why the area of arm
Weekend blanket
Cities Region's countries
With this applicant with his protocol
Okay so. Laura
In one of the band width what are the up and downs
Flora and
Downelink
It's probably about you 20 kilobits to seconds
These were saying in the field
I think we're talking about
The 5 to 10 kilobits
Most of the Transmissions we see
Domestic limited I think it differs by market depending on need of what the unlicensed regime You Are by 9:15
Hiossen Bandit States
But I'd say like if you're looking to build an application devices
Sub 5 kilobits per second
Then this is the ideal protocol for you
And there is no Universal
Laura Spectrum
SWAT so if you're going to build a Lora based products
You're going to have to build different radios for
Each different country
Right I think there's definitely
Some countries have very similar artists in South Korea share the same band that were using on
And so today is your sort of decision to
Manufacturer product for booth
Certain markets
Europeans have a different subsets of Standards but that's correct that you have to do some
Testing
You have to get certifications in in these sort of domestic country to before you can launch that
Going Global is always hard
Alright so
Let's talk about the challenges
Because you you correct me earlier and I appreciate
I'm thinking Laura
Laura is Laura
And this is
The radio protocol Plus
Next level
Standardization turn Zalora Network
Work into something broader so
What is that architecture
Look like broccoli
What devices have what cave
Sure so
After tracking
It's easy to go put Alora wanker
Client
Module into a an asset tracker
It requires a lot less battery power than traditional cellular Technologies
They can remain in the field for years
The reason why again it's
We've mentioned or versus or when
Laura Wynn
It can work
Across different country so orange is an example just publicly announced that they're working on Laurel and roaming in Europe for
For next year so I think that's where things are going as I said it should have started out as this
Greycampus
Tool but it became a domestic cool now it's becoming international roaming tool
Why were all on
Different sort of as you mention standards in terms of the band
That is
There's ways of making sure that we can serve Rome among each other but the vast majority of devices that were focused on it
I think the other carriage for the Doppler Wendy's are things that really happen
Connected to the cloud they want to connect it wannabe
Providing information quite frankly to visit businesses to improve operations and improve Services everything from
Pallets
Two containers
And we just had a hackathon in Philadelphia recently actually
And some of the winners had some amazing things that they came up with
Number one
It's a device that basically just monitors temperature in the real use case was for elderly people
Monkey living by themselves
To make sure that
You can go put this in parts of their homes
They might have another connected device in the house
They might not want to pair something with their smartphone but it would be able to alert anyone that needed to be alerted it is certain
Temperature threshold is met
That there's a danger here for that person
And that you can do with Laurel and it sort of set in Africa
Hackathon winners Nikes you know would love to commercialize and ghosts
Citgo pry this to
Folks and you can go put it into let's say one of our markets over building in it would automatically sort of authenticate over-the-air and it be nice
Easy sort of on-ramp and you would solve that problem for
That's subset of the market is someone of the second prize winners was a tool that would go into it was a kraut source
Pothole tool
The application was to go and put a little sensor on this
Extensions
As Municipal vehicles
They put on the fire truck in front of police vehicle in a particular area and it goes down a certain number of degrees it would
Identify where the wheel would go down
And actually have a GPS coordinates recorded events ended up and eventually you have enough of this data to predict until the city officials
It's probably a bunch of potholes developing here you probably should go check this out
But those are things quite frankly that before
Be difficult to sort of the field
I think like right around 5 to $10
So these modules
The gateways as opposed to going straight up to the end
That's correct
So how many lorawan Network
How many gateways do I need
Cover a square mile
Depends on sword of the use case if you if you're looking to cover a square mile for
An outdoor only use case and there's no sort of high buildings for Square mall you can if you have a high enough power
In this case
Anybody put two or three gateways new cover that
But the reality is is that
I mean I think you know
But each one of these devices has its own sort of particular use case so if you're looking to Culver City
But
Your application requires getting into a
Parking garage
Two floors down
Different types of Gateway Tennessee show me there
And I'm trying to remember
10 megahertz
How does that travel
Walter Wallace this is something that's going to work indoors
Yes I think it propagations excellent soil
Clearly that one of the reasons why laurel-ann Works in many ways for most of these iety industrial applications because of
It can penetrate
A lot better than other bands this person is always been there for vism industrial science and medical devices
So what does propagate very well but it going to goes back to
Making sure you still have the right Gateway density in the right locations which goes back to one of the reasons why I think
We were able to successfully work with within Comcast cable to make sure that
You look at the long-term vision of how lower way I could be the toilets multi-user of nodal
And it's just in the way of looking at building a network it's not I'm just going to go build a mackerel layer
Towers
But you can look at potentially putting it on strands of your looks a data cable operator
You can put them in homes or other locations if you want to put into CPE
And this is not unlike what the Europeans I couldn't have been
You're looking at for about a year or so that
Real use public examples of what they've done but I think an orange has been a leader in the space for quite a while.
Build a macro based
Cell tower filled out in France
With lorawan
And then they were experimenting with putting in home devices like a lorawan lamp for some employees
It's a Gateway effectively
Okay
Identification in Paris
All right to Comcast having all of this
Consumer promise equipment so basically it's any gear that you get from Comcast could we possibly one day see you guys
Okay
Let's make this more dense let's put this in homes because it makes sense for like smoke detectors or other crazy ideas
Restless Papo Gateway into our routers are
Set up exercise
That's exactly right I think all those options on the table
And I think if you look at sort of what other folks are looking to deploy globally and get ourselves that
I think naturally that the more more applications in the more B2B to see the more consumer applications be fine for I
30th and cook good more likely to start saying companies like ourselves considered adoption
All right now
If I have a business
Sitting here and like I don't really care
In Great Neck
Work staff who should care about
You've got this
Siri you can send small amounts of data pretty far distances really cheaply
Play so
What kind of use cases can we see
Loose cases Racine
Stan
Ferreus Industries
So if you look at the most natural ones
Asset heavy Industries which have
High-value devices are assets in the field and needed pracna crucially couldn't track them because they lack the power
That's a no-brainer
We've seen that
I think you look at heavy machinery II metering
Do you want to know where something is
Geo-fence something
Vegetable with a cost of the modules coming
Further down leaving sub $5 and in
Put it in the near future
Now using the return on investment should I spend you know
10 $15 put a tracker on this device
And pay Comcast
We're just in this case our partner will pay us
Disconnect
That device for them and feel for your so
To make sure that I know where all this devices are they leave this particular area I should know
Do you have that sort of that side of the equation the other side there's people who are looking
Revolutionize everything from
Parts of the pharmaceutical industry or mention adherents
I'll put it out there
Dispenser to this
Dream to be able to have a connected Hilltop it didn't require constant battery patio
Replenishing
How does the device like this
Help solve problems ie
How many times has this person has a station opened up
That device
License office
Even advertising we've seen other interesting spaces were
I can't get into specifics but more or less
I think about the prettiest trees and being able to track
What people are doing
On catalogs
Wait people still get catalogs
Play get on the questions do they open or not
Okay
That feels kind of like spine
You send me mail and suddenly I've got this like sensor on it that's a poop
These are the examples of people are coming up with them out there in the field
But you ask
What are use cases in my point is everything from
Yo heavy Industrial
Pharma the advertising the pest control
Ozium
Smart now
That's awesome
Exactly so
That's been through my conversation to given day of the week she's been all those people
Flooring
And those opportunities
Understanding what the technology is capable of doing
It is wonderful seeing
Their brains race to think about how this can help their business
All right now I'm going to go into some of the things that
Concern me
Because it's always fun to talk about the trade-offs and every technology
Does happen
So
The Gatorades here
It worries me because
It's a very small amount
A data and
Security being what it is I feel like things are going to need more over the air updates in the
Future not fewer
Sub-5 kilobits
Per second
Is that enough
To keep things updated
Transmit neusoft
Yes we went
Through this analysis we definitely thought about Serta firm over there updates is being
Critical analysis especially when these devices
Requirements of being out in the field for many many years
And as I said before it right now but the average type of
Interactional
Floral and device I've seen anyway it's looking for Farmer 5 kilobits but in terms of downlink
You can go to 25 kilobits per second
They'll get it
Still nowhere near what you expect from trishul cellular Technologies
Requirements
But
That's part of the value of working
Comcast and other folks in the others a huge ecosystem
All the partners in the in the Laurel and Alliance
Is working on firmware over-the-air serve best practice standards
So
We can do things
Hush
Silent the rest of the Network's we can sort of make sure that this client
10000 devices are going to be updated over an ex
Happy Days
For this upgrade
An actual. Talk about scale how many devices can you put on a Gateway or
How big can is net worth
Work schedule
Get it comes down to being serve application
Specifically our trials we put things on tracking that immitracker needs
To talk every couple seconds versus be put of the lights out there we need to talk every year
Putting General work Hawking
Tens of thousands if not hundreds of thousands of devices potentially forget what
That feels
Doable
All right
Now Comcast
You guys have embarked upon Wireless
And
Then you guys were
Why create your own iot
Wireless net
I think
The reason why we're
Pitabilities networks and to get in
This is because there's no other Alternatives today
That we're not looking too
Sorted offer
This is not a cytotechnologist
Right there's a lot of business has a lot of
Opportunities for
Provide some real value here
For Industries which until another alternative comes up
That we
Put it upon ourselves looking at was out there
We have a network we have the assets we have the relationships
We provide a service which is valuable not only to businesses but also you communities
Geauga CCR Smart City vertical being pretty important
And we've been in these
Calories for 50 plus years of time
As you start hearing about Urban landscape Suburban rural needs
It became obvious that seeing other carriers globally what they're doing and why they're doing it that it made sense for us considering the
Mixture of assets available to us
And how is Comcast
Going to sell this so
In this case
Your building these networks in the 15 cities
Partybell temp
You're going to sell these two
And users or
Systems integrators or the cities themselves how does a
Key question I think that
Having
Barton
Being a public trial 6 months ago in October
Become obvious that are our first
Sweet spot is working with partners partners being those who are manufacturing device
They have
The expertise
Understand the technology
Coming to us
Looking to
Connect other devices to us
Avenues partners
Have verticals and channel expertise industry expertise
Busy themselves with once they've connected to us they're going to bomb a bath together
And going to work with their channels to sell so
Yes indeed a we are in the Smart City
Space
But right now we don't see ourselves as going in
Raising her hand becoming a prime
Contractors
Do any Municipal requests comes in
However our partners are
And
You also are looking for partners among startups in other develop
That's right so I think it's
It one of the fascinating things is we're dealing with Fortune 500 companies and also startups
So on both sides of the spectrum
You see a lot of big corporations doing pilots and proof of Concepts and their
We're working on them
And proving out that this particular need they have
The technology is exactly what fits for their needs
Economics work for them
And they have no natural teams thinking about how to Andino add sensors if you will
2 horse float existing businesses
But they have
And
That levels of excavate
Some of them have that deep level of expertise and I have all the skill sets and how some of them don't
Torquing them on the other side of the spectrum
Plus startup sir also engaging
I have been using that quite frankly other types of Wireless protocols
Heather now looking dust insecticide might have used you know XYZ before
I was only a wifi-only device or I was a Bluetooth only device
Right here that you were offering lorwyn in my market are you and your spending this I like to work with you on how I can help my device
Right onto them to network
Still working in Spanish
Got it okay well Alex thanks so much for coming on and sharing all this great information about Laurel or away
When and even
Comcast plans
My pleasure and again Stacy thanks for having me
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news
You can sign up for my newsletter Stacey knows things at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week