Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
Did this is your hope Stacy
And this is your
Kevin tofel
And we are doing a little funky with our timing so
We're recording this
A week before for vacation purposes but don't worry we have lots of great stuff for you that you're going to
Here we got
New routers from Eero
Test it out some cool Services we're going to talk to you about there's a brand new
Wi-Fi Home Design certification
And we're going to talk about some of last week's news such as the launch of AWS Greengrass
And SoftBank
Plus
Spend a little more time with that WeMo dimmer and I
Questions
Message from this we sponsor
TE Connectivity
It
We're going to talk to DaVita herzl who is the CEO of Acoma
Which
Put sensors on cars to test air pollution and
Man this is great iot use case we're going to talk about all kinds of challenges she faced
First
Let's kick off the show with a
Message from another one of this week's sponsors
Affiliated monitoring
If you're hunting for a subscription Revenue model for your iot business you need to hear about affiliated
Monitoring in response to a trigger from any connected device Affiliated professionally trained live agent scan
Follow protocol and reach out to your customers their loved ones and local emergency services
Works with hundreds of smart home security help and other iot businesses visit affiliated
Cam coyote to read a case study on how they helped a connected car startup turn an idea into a
Writing business with a 100 million dollar exit that's Affiliated. Com
Coyote
All right, let's kick it off with
New WiFi products
Because we love the Wi-Fi
Gyro
Which I have Eero
Routers at
My house
Where are you going to the wife I still
I am still tired I detest the Arizona was very very happy with
New products be two of the Eero routers don't worry dies
Your V ones are still cool
So what did Johnny say John 3 things that change the form factor
Did adding a radio protocol and
Get out of services so let's break that down
New form factor what they've done
They've taken a
Normal Euro
The square with rounded edges
That's going to be the
Primary hero that plugs into your router and has two ethernet ports that you can use for switches and all that other good stuff
And that caused what is that cost 7
The original gyro
At no
Actually the original arrows were three for $500 for 99
And then I went down I think by 100.
Nosey
The new version
I will the new version is I-10 and 10 Beacon which American talk about is
$299
Pekin is confusing
Beacons Ark
Completely new form factor for them
And they plug into the wall so they kind of remind me of the plume Wi-Fi pods
So think of this is a WiFi pod
It also happens to double as a nightlight so it might be something nice you put in your hallway
Forget Wi-Fi in
Hallway spaces
I got half the size of the original gyro
Yeah
And so
That's the idea is you will by the mainiero and then for many people just plugging in a couple Bekins around their house
Cows are going to be sufficient
This one factor is is it's good I can see how this would work
Free People
I would be sticking with my
Eero
Crow zero normal zero with ethernet
Sims 3 full-sized Euros are 499
Got it
Okay so
That is State that's back to that
And ideas 1 0 and 1 begin
For 299 is going to cover a 1/2 to bed
A two to three bedroom home you're going to want to add another Beacon
Play with that a little bit
And the pro
The three
Euro Pros
That's like a five to six bedroom
So that's one of those massive
Massive houses like we haven't
So I'm liking this
I think what I'm going to do with my setup
Because I have wired Lan and I have a lot of sweets
I keep my exist
But I might
Actually you know
Spring for an extra Peak energy
Brights right and in my case I do not have wire
Ethernet throughout the house so I have to go with a wireless solution so
I would if it were me
I'm take a look at the I-10 and
One or two because I got to figure that out based on homes us make sense
Yasso
This
I don't know what this feels
Pretty good for them
The other bits though
I think really excite
They've added
Thread
Capability
To there
And I know many of you guys are going to be like
What
That's still around
So thread is a low-power wireless protocol
That was developed by nest
Samsung
Couple other companies
And it's
It's basically a replacement or more modern
Replacement for zigbee and Z-Wave
So think about it's a mesh Network
Talks directly to the Internet so it support IPv6
And
For the longest time
Most people have been like I'm not all
I'm not that excited about the red most people are not into the red
I was one of those people
So yeah I just talked about manufacturer so I asked Nick Weaver the CEO of Iran like
A threat he's like well
It's a great protocol and he thinks that
One of the reasons manufacturers aren't into it is because there's nothing to act as a
Hub for it so there's nothing to support
Unless you've got Nest products in your house you don't have
The thread Network that
You need like for my Mashburn
So
It's going to act as a thread border router
End
That will be exciting if
Stats
I don't think it's a Bad Bet and I'm trying to think
Are there any other routers right now that have
Thread support
Google why is my yeah I think it I think it might
I have to check out to be sure but
That's the only one I can think of you know and that's
It without the support the network support the vertical support you're not going to have products that work with it so sleepy I start somewhere so
Kudos to you
Chicken and egg
Barrister providing
Snow the chicken
Is the router the egg or the chicken
All right and then the final thing for this news is Eero is adding services
So
Then creating basically a $10 a month service
And you get applications over the net
Work the first two they're launching
Is security so network security
Through the network
And then the
Other one is Parental Control
Drools like more
Right now you have the ability to like pause devices
On your Eros
And you don't set like
My kids stuff can't go online at this place in
If you don't let you do things like
Summer editor's let you
Play whitelist sites
But as a parent I'm excited because they have things like
I can enable Google safe search for all devices associated
My daughter
And she actually can't change that
So
Is Edison Pointe timeout
Get smarter
They just Google for the answer to figure out how to get around the Google
That is part of this service as well so I'm excited to see the
I'm in the security stuff
It's actually very similar to what
The Almond router offers the Almond router from securifi has similar security
Features I don't believe they charge for them
Well and normally
I'm not a fan of
Paying for monthly services with smart home taipei
Things and
But not but
In this case I probably would make an exception
Because
What we talked about all the time or the challenges at IRT and smartphones and such
Is the security
So if this can help protect against
And I are going to have a lot of malicious website or s or some other exploit I'm all for it
You know and that's the promise I mean that the promises he will understand like
Hey
Should your nest thermostat really be talking to China
Herbert
And so that's the exciting part
Again I would pay I honestly would Pages for
Trolls because my daughter is a little
Younger than your kid
It's and curious to see
A security research firm really take a look at that's only because the promise is is pretty big men
Euro says that it's got built-in protections as a database of threats and that database
Has millions of malicious websites and net
It's updated every second so there's a lot of
Cloud stuff going on there
And it sounds very promising
But but seeing practice
That's the news
It's pretty big update
Very exciting will get the new routers
Here to test and we'll hear more about those win
When the time comes
So
Also
In Wi-Fi
The Wi-Fi Alliance is doing a home design Serta
Patient and I
I mean I think that's a great idea
Work so
Kevin you want to tell him what
Well to this is a really not force a consumer this is for home builders
Desertification project if you're going to build a house 2
You integrate Wi-Fi networks in the in the design of your home construction
So
They're going to suggest where you put access points and so on and so forth
I'm wondering how many
Builders
Will use this
What the cost benefit is to running you know either net and so on so forth.
Granted it's expensive to run
Cabling so there's got to be a cost-savings there
I don't know because
So we built our house in 2012
And we ran cable and ethernet
Every room
End
I'm so glad we did
Because
Almighty
And
It'd be really interesting like as acedia contractor you know like you could come in and have someone outfit your house for like
Smart home and
Retroact
What if we do this but like in the design phase
I don't know if I really buy into saying Go Wireless over
Wired
Right right
It's a tough decision because you know what is it you don't know what your home buyers
Needs will be in terms of services that are they going to do you know 4K video streaming on
And every bedroom
You just don't know
So
It's an interesting concept
I'm just not sure about the practicality of it yet
And maybe it's too far ahead of its time cuz I remember we had Scott Jensen who actually
He's a design dude he actually works at Google but
He came on to talk about like design considerations and Construction in one of the things he mentioned was as Wireless
Technology gets better
It becomes really
Telling to not have to like
4 light switches you wouldn't have a light switch you just have
Bluetooth switch
But
So you would eliminate the need for like
Wiring in huge parts of
The home
This is kind of that same idea and that's
That is a cost-savings especially when you talk about copper wiring when you're talking about like Cat6 cable
Alyssa
Rite Aid cost savings but now I'm trying to think of it from a homebuyer perspective
If
Your cell phone is Houston say what we've gone through the Wi-Fi Alliance Home Design products so
We can tell you where the best
Places to put
Your router isn't over
I don't know if somebody really cares about that
Enough they made this a worldwide rather have
Wired how much does that cost you know
And then if they're smart enough to know they need a wire there probably smart enough to figure out where the best place to buy routers and someone anyway
Pro Wireless Tampa
Well in so weird
We're probably thinking
We're overthinking this we probably what's going to happen is
Again it's going to fade in the background and consumers will just have their Wi-Fi stuff
Right I think it was going to happen
All of your connected devices that wireless doorbell that you want that's going to work
So maybe it's a waiter like
But it's not really selling point maybe it's just the way to reduce
And cost
And
You guys can say hello to my neighbor
Pradaxa
Haven't having a field day today
All right so that's
So let's talk about services
Last week Kevin and I talked about
Opening his door
Through his Google
Home
Amazon figure out
How to do that
What you can't eat meat
But Scott Jones
Sent us an email he was like guys
It was actually
But he's right he's right we are
I did this with the echo because that's
That happens to be downstairs in my house and I know Kevin is an echo dude
So I set up
The way you're going to do this
To natively lock or unlock your doors have to be to separate commands
Is I went into wink
And I created a shortcut
It was called
Lock garage door
So I went into it
After setting the shortcut and I
Tied it to my Amazon Echo and then I said
I gave it
Command so
Ended
Precursor to any commands
Giver is Madame a trigger
And then whatever were you like
So
I did garage
Oh I know I did
Trigger
Lock garage
So
I probably should have
Extra lock
And you said that up and then you
Say if
Madame a trigger and then you go to then
You go to the wink
And then it's going to say shortcuts and it's going to give you a list of your shortcuts you pick the
Block version
And then
When I ran the command my latency was about admit it
It wasn't very long at all so
I really
Sutherlands great now you are good at to set up a separate
For unlocking it
And you mean
Try to get your Echo
Yeah shame on us for forgetting about half
Is Sia
That that's
Yeah I did I fell
I felt really
Will it away I mean that's
It's telling that the native services are getting better on these devices that you don't need
Some kind of backend Cloud Plumbing like afternoon in a lot of cases but
It is a great service and we shouldn't we should have overlooked it so it's kind of I kind of do feel silly as well
And this works because the wink
Actually can see the lock
And in my case the home
Can see the wing
But I can't see the lock on the way
See everything else on the way
Wake so
So this is a way to get around that
Yay and
We also noticed that in the Wink app
Should you want to
And Kevin says this has been around for a while
I
I have my Christmas lights
Do things on the Winker cuz I have to spread my Gloria my Gloria cross many hubs
I got it all
So he was like oh my God they have this and he's like
But I didn't tell you that in case you didn't know
You can set a mode change on link and have it work
Through
Google
Home
So you can have vacation mode and you can set a Cascade of events to happen
Turn off devices connected to your
And it will happen
When you say
I won't say the words but hey G
Is it telwink
Or is it just
Vacation mode
I mode
So
Haiti
Vacation mode
And
Gualala
It happens
Yeah this is this is been a beta for voice actions
With Google in wink
For a while and it actually now makes sense that they have shortcuts in Google
Which we talked about it to Mid to shows like
I wonder if the beta set information into that actual and finished product
So I actually try to shortcuts
I tried the Logitech Harmony volume up volume down shortcut
So far that is not working
So I am still troubleshooting that because I really wanted
At some point in time I'm going to figure it out you guys and then I'll come back to you
Say this is
Or
One of you astute listeners
Who's
Way better and things of things like if
Y'all can tell me how you did it because
Nothing I say
Why were talking services in wink
On the last episode we mention that
Wink added services
Two of them home sitter and Moonlight and I didn't try home sitter because
I work from home so I don't want the lights going on and off at various times to make it look like I'm home
Cuz I'm already home
Yes yes
But I'm home at 9
I can just see the girls downstairs watching TV hey the lights just went out
Make it look like we're not home
Moonlight I did use Moonlight witch
I actually used a manual version of this by setting up schedules and pack
I'm going to correct myself because in the last time I said they were robots
They were not realize they were schedules in the Wind Gap see so confusing
And that's the whole point of moonlight is to make it not confusing
Two brand-new
Wink Hub owners
So what Winky
Add was the Moonlight service which
Ask your lights turn on when it gets dark outside
And I was already doing that in the schedules are they said but in Moonlight I set it up
It's pretty simple to nice clean interface you pick which lights you want to go on
Are you
And put the location which basically it uses GPS to determine your home location to make sure I can sync up with when's sunset
When Sunset is
At your home
And then you choose timing and this is what it kind of fell down a little bit for me but I understand why
When do you want to turn your lights on and on and off is what it says and give you three options
Sunset to midnight
Sunset to 2 a.m.
Sunset to Sunrise
I had scheduled for like Sunset to like 10 or 11 p.m. you can't change the times in here you get three
Hard-code
Credit choices
I get the concept it's to make it simple and useful
I guess I would like to see a little spinner option to change
The time regardless of that
I set it up
Saved it turn it on and Moonlight is working perfectly fine
If I fits overriding my schedule
To my lights didn't go off at like 10:11 or 11 even though the schedule is still active
So if you have a schedule
I think moonlights can override that so
Those are pretty much the devices in
Stuff we tried this
Actually no I tried the WeMo dimmer
I tried installed it
Before last show and I didn't get a chance to test out some of the stuff but now that I've lived with it for a little bit longer
Wi-Fi dimmer switch for $80
Okay here's some cool features they've got
Nighttime
Tricep nighttime tula
20%
I think it's at by default
And the 20% means that between
The default setting is like 11 and 6 a.m.
When you hit the light switch in your room
Are you down
It's turn on it turns on at only 20%
Which is super nice in that just happen automatically
Automatic
Nice
The other thing it does
Pretty cool is it calibrates two different LEDs and so actually
Started with different LEDs in there
And what time is it
The calibration process has you turn it to its lowest setting
And then it has you run up and down the dimmer
To see if it flickers and if it flickers it tries again
So
That was actually really cool because flicker is annoying as all get-out
And how many years as well but I told others
I couldn't hear him from either the alley
Daiso
And
It appears that when you turn it on and off
It goes to the last remembered setting
So if you didn't have them 200% you turn the lights on it's going to go to whatever you like
Last Hyderabad
What you like or not
Things that are little counterintuitive
AR
There's a Dipper thing on it
That touch sensitive dimmer
Chocolate Groove
You would think that you could
Move your hand on it and turn it on but you can't you have to click it and then move up the
So it's only for the light
Outputs not for light on light off
Yes
And then the other thing is they have a long
Press option that was really excited about so you can actually control other we nose and in my bedroom
Which is where these are
Are the WeMo dimmer controller for camp
And then I have
A WeMo Insight switch that controls my husband's beds
Side table lamp
Hey
Worcester long press and turn everything
That would be awesome
And I told it to do that like
8 different times in
It never ever work
So the laundress
I don't know what's going
But it's not working
But it sounds very prompt
Yeah I mean they're both Wi-Fi devices I can assume and I can fit into each other
Yeah WeMo in the app conceive
It's very simple you're like
It's like settling press you press that
A toast to the thing where it's like
You can toggle something you can turn it on you can turn it off and I feel like you do
Another thing
So I just said turn off
And then it gives you all the WeMo devices it's found so in my house there
So I can
Dimmer and
Bedside table lamp
It's safe and when I hit save it was like
The screen just got a flash but I didn't
Forget the lag time
Strange
So we know
Alright news
There is some news
From the week before that we can get to in last week's podcast the biggest
AWS Greengrass
Y'all are like what
So this is for the Enterprise crew
What happened is Amazon has Amazon web services which is AWS
Huge business for them cloud
But
Green grass actually it brings
Iot to the edge
So
What you do is you can run AWS Greengrass core on an edge device
It will allow a lot of things to happen
And it talks to AWS Lambda serve
So some of the things that lets you do is it's going to help me in a state
On devices even when there's no internet connected
It helps
Communicate between
Other devices that talk to
The Gateway device so if you have
AWS iot SDK on
Vice
Those devices were all talk to AWS
Green grass running
Devices
Even if there's no
Haven't did that make sense to you
I felt like I was
Using a lot of
Words that didn't make sense to a lot of normal teeth
SO2 translate to normal
What this does is this pools
Amazon web services away from the cloud
Put on
A Gateway device
It extends Amazon's Cloud capabilities to the industrial
Because those guys
If tons of data a lot of it needs to happen without any latency so think about a blade
In a manufacturing plant that you know is chopping chickens to bits in
You know if it senses a finger in the way it's got to stop
So this is a really big Market
Everyone Microsoft has introduced
Azure at the iot
Azure at the iot edge does the same thing
Kind of links the cloud to the Gateway
Going to see a lot more this
And if you want to know more about 8
Green grass I did do a whole Amazon
Industry in the newsletter so
You could have Stacey on iot
Shameless plug for me
The other big news
Roblox
So we will talk about robots that much
Know what is that
There's a mean there's only so many cool things have
What is pretty
Sometimes they're scary
And I think that has a lot to do with what we're going to talk about next to be honest
This would be a good place for a nap
It's so scary
Tuscany
Yasso remember back in 2013 Google bought
Boston Dynamics
Text which makes those
Bipedal quad
People
Robots that
You can't take them over they look like when was like mechanical deer or Buffalo and they look like demons
See that there's the scary.
Giant
Loping
Jibon looking thing
That is really cool but scary as all get-out and they recently made a
Bipedal
Jump over stuff
Just scaring
It's so scary
Anyway there's been a lot of ammunition covered like you said these videos and a lot of people walking away
Terry and
I don't know the Google is happy with that but
It also made me the fact that
I don't know that they found a way to make money
From it
So
I think about a year ago it was rumored that they were looking to sell Boston Dynamics I think Toyota was actually in the mix for that
But regardless tire is not in the mix now because SoftBank
Has bought
Boston Dynamics SoftBank Japan
Do they have any of the robotics
I'm trying to think I do
It's the company is the French company that made pepper they have a big investment there
I so yes they have never going to put pepper heads on scary demon
I also bought
Is it shaft
Another robotics firm
Not a lot of news about shop it's like a secretive kind of
Incubator type
Project from jsk robotics Lab at University of Tokyo
Yeah
So that they might be willing
It's something even scarier so
They might be because I went to their website and it said that permission forbidden like I couldn't go to the Republic website today
Yeah boy
All right
So let's piece this all together cuz softbank's been doing some really interesting things in the iot space first off I think there's going to be like
100 million
Connected devices which goes beyond
Or a hundred billion I mean it's
That's baby
Everything's gonna be connect
Stopping speed
And what they've done is they've got a huge investment
An arm
Embedded chip firm
Chip design firm
Actually recently just made a
Acquisition of
A lot of stairs
An acquisition of a stake in a company called OSI soft which does Industrial Automation
Software
And when we start thinking about
Embedded Computing everywhere
Industrial Automation
And robots
What are we doing
It's the future
Yes
The SoftBank is basically
Say hey we're going to be connected
We're going to need
Software-based ways to mediate that and we're going to need robots doing
A lot of the tasks
Spent humans using and
Environments that
Are less friendly
And they can also chase us down and kill us
We could you end up in reality self
It's obviously a big Vision player when you put it all together
I'm so I guess it's not surprising
To see SoftBank purchase Boston Dynamics
Terms of the deal
Not available
Don't think Google ever said what they paid for Boston Dynamics I don't know if they're making money or losing money but
Again big picture yeah there
Southbank is positioning itself for
Industrial
World domination
Alright so
After that scary bit
Let's take a moment for a
Message from our sponsor and then we'll go into
A conversation that's going to make you feel good about the internet
We're going to have the CEO of Aqaba
Davida herzl
Talk about
How we can actually improve data collection for really granular Environmental
Yay we're going to do what's polluting
Stay tuned for all of that
Hey everyone we are taking a break in The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Where is TE Connectivity and I have shed
Cragar a general manager at TE Connectivity
How about smart
Appliances
So Chad
Remind us what to eat
We make connectors and sensors
That collect data and Power
And
Many devices across the world but particularly in
Home appliances
We connect refrigerators and washers and dryers
As well as
New connected devices like
Robotic vacuums doorbells
Thermostat
And video
Let's talk about these appliances
What kind of changes and Trends are you seeing
And we're seeing a real revolution in conductivity
In home appliances many of the things that are
Customers are looking to put into their appliances Ark raiding
A better user experience
And that user experience is providing devices that are smarter and connected with each other as well as providing
Better safety
More reliability and greater energy efficient
There are a lot of other connected devices in the home now how is that impacting
Appliances
3D digital assistants
Enabling
They large home appliance makers to move faster
Adopting
Smart conductivity between appliances
In many cases a digital assistant
Are serving as the gateway to connect
The devices
In the home
So how does TE Connectivity come into that interaction
Betsy conductivity were providing antennas
And sensors and connectors that are allowing
The communication
Between the device
And the digital assistant we are sensing the information
Inside the appliance
And through our connectors and antennas communicating that back to the digital assistant
I'm expecting a lot of really awesome
Connected features in my new appliances
But holy cow
Those are really tough environments
What kind of things is TE Connectivity doing to him
Prove reliability the risk of all these additional features and appliances there's more power in the appliances Mezmur
Power is in the appliance
The risk is
That there could be a failure and if there's a failure in Appliance
And many times can lead to
The fire
And that's of course something we are here to provide
And we're putting
New materials
R&R products
That actually prevent
In many cases it can eliminate
These potentials for fire risk or four
Other types of electrical failures
So how are you guys making your components
Reliable and put a really challenging in fire
With the Internet of Things there's a
Excellent opportunity
To provide
Better sensing of
The devices that can give our consumers and our customers information about the
Reliability and potentially predictive failure
Of their products
Chad
That sounds awesome except for the kitchen fire
How can I find out
You can find out more about our products at tep.com Connected home
Hey everyone welcome
Into the Internet of Things podcast this is your house is Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Herzl who is the CEO of
Hi Stacy thanks so much for having me today
Oh I am so excited thanks for coming on the show
Because you guys are doing something near and dear to my heart
Constantly telling people about how to iot
Is really a way to
Get information at scale
Very little money
And then use it to do something
And you guys are doing that so you just announced this big project with Google do you want to tell us about that
So what we announced
Is that is the result of I work that we've been doing allihoopa we've instrumented Google Street View car
Cars with our environmental intelligence platform
To measure air quality and
Climate
Scale
And in our announcement
We launched the first map
From Oakland
Which we generated in in partnership with Google and the environment
And so what was the result
The study study generated one of the largest data sets on Urban Air Pollution ever assembled
And the results were
Resultz1
It demonstrates that our approach is highly scalable highly effective and cost-effective
To generate higher
Pollution
Maps of air quality and it also showed us that air quality
Is much more variable
Then anybody had ever expect
So you can have
Best air quality
And the worst air quality on the same block
And that's really important
For decision-makers you know whether it's urban planners
Or health insurers or
Citizens understand how they are affected
Air pollution
You really need
Highly granular
Highly localized information and
Proven that we can do it with
Are platform and with this
Methodology
Awesome so let's dig into some of the tech here just for fun
Just for funsies
You called at the environmental intelligence
So is that just a sensor is that
Cloud service what is it
Our environmental intelligence platform is a fully integrated from sensor
Backend 8A manager
Algorithm
That makes sense of the
Data coming off
Answers to the management system
Manage
All of the remotely
Play sensors
Data visualization software in the Analytics
So it's a fully integrated end-to-end stocking
Threesome
Selena great it is that we really see this as a massive signal processing Challenge and
We're trying to do
Capture signal
Songs about within the environment
And turn it into
Information that we
And that platform
Deployed
And multiple settings
Take me to Coit indoors in buildings
It can be deployed Outdoors
I'm stationary settings
The tops of buildings
And it can also be deployed on moving vehicles
And be able to
Degenerate
Insights from
Spencer's at highly granular
I'm resolution that haven't been possible before
Okay and in this case how are the sensors communicating the data back to the
The sensors are commute
Indicating
True Cellular Connection
And they're communicating in real-time so they're sending up data once every second
And they're also
Communicating
Location in a lot of other metadata
It's really important
For managing the networks
When they're deployed in the field but also
Making sense of the data after it's been
Collective
Okay and I saw some of this
Estate I mean
How much data are we talking about in I don't know
Sure so we all at once
Per second and weekly cover this particular study
We collected data
From May 2015 to May 26
We collected 2.7 million data points over 14,000 miles and 100
50 days of driving and this is this is one of the largest if not the largest data sets on Urban Air Pollution
Ever ever assembled
Wow okay
So that's a lot of data to take
A lot of companies are dealing with this right now is there
Thinking about iot
Do you have advice for them on
Taking in that kind of data
In turning it into something that
Actually useful
For policymakers or people who are not date
How do you do that at school
For users right I mean I think I think so much of the focus on
IRT is either you know
Either talking about the janitor
The value of the data but there's a lot of work that has to be done
Translate that data is
Into information that people can
Use end
One of the things that that we've been doing and then there's admittedly I think an iot there's a chicken and egg
Challenge right
Because you have to
Collect the data
To understand what value is in it
And then you have to understand what value is in the data to understand how to optimize your data collection
We're doing here in Oakland
Is that we over stamp
That mean we just
The quantities of Jade are so huge
Because what we were really trying to do was
Learn learn where is the valley
The data how do we turn it into those information product
That people can use and we've been very intentional over the course of the last year we made a commitment in 2015 with Google to
Map communities across California
And what we've been doing is really using that as an opportunity to explore applications of the data and so
You have to creep
Room for this kind of iteration cycle but you have to be very intentional about
About the fact that there is there is a need to collect data to surface the data into then talk to users about ways the
They need
That data represented and so we've been talking
Two users in the urban planning space
Space space really under
Understand the ways in which that data needs to be reduced
An analyzed to deliver really useful information
How do you
Take the massive amounts of data that you
You have
And go to the process of making that useful to each differ
Do bring people in from that Community do you guys employee all those folks.
Have a magical machine learning box
We have a highly
MN
And what we've done is yes on our team we have domain expert
Who are
Looking at the data and using our tools to look at it through the lens of users
In the communities that they represent so whether it's a scientific Community or for example
In the built environment
We have
Former director of research
The US Green Building
It is about bringing those Jame next
In those areas of application
Reprioritize
And then having those
Domain expert
Directly engage
The Industries or User Group
That we're selling our services into to refine
Rrd2 products
And then work working very closely with our product team
Visualization and an interface
Team
Ensure that
We are creating data products
Serve the needs of those user groups
Operating
New territory right this is the key challenge around
Turning
Industrial or enterprise-scale iot data in
She's really meaningful
Invaluable information
I agree
So then the question is how do you charge for that do you charge based on insights and if so
What is that mean or do you just charge
Buy data iPad a pipe
We have a number of different application areas been in the building space for example
We saw environmental ontology
As a service
So these are managed
Sensor Networks
And there are
Subscription fee is
And for management of that network but subscription fees to the date of product
Intelligence that the Analytics
Provide
From the Sun
Your data and
The sensor data alone
Does not solve problem
For users in the in the built environment it's really important
That we that we translated into those meaningful data products and
And we saw them as a service
Let's talk about this cuz you got in this Oakland example there was some really interesting findings and I'd like to dig into some of these
Is because
There's one about it and I don't remember the street but there's one area where
You noticed that there was huge pollution
Brightest people were entering onto the Bay Bridge and I guess the theory was his people accelerate to
I guess get past the light and get on the bridge they just
It's been a lot of pollution
That kind of thing seems
Really interesting but it also seems
Really threatening
To maybe
Someone who owns an apartment that's right at that address and so would I look at how granular this data is
I'm reminded of
Talk to somebody in Singapore cuz they it outfitted an area of the city with noise pollution sensors in
They got a lot of complaints from people who owned
Apartments around places where the noise was Dean tires
Because it was affecting the real estate values
And so I feel like we're entering this Brave New connected world where information is just so available
How are you seeing people react
This sort of
The availability of this
Overall it has been
Very positive and there's demand for more
Right because I think in this case the data that we
We collected directly relevant
Demon House
Enter people's house
And the challenge I mean it in many ways
No it's
Equivalent to Revolution that we've seen in
Genomic sequencing and the availability of data about your
DNA
Right it's empowering
Empowering
Choices
More intelligent delivery of healthcare
And so we think that there's an equivalent opportunity when it comes to environmental health
You know when we talk about things like climate
These are really abstract Concepts
But when you
They look at the same emissions are changing our climate
At the type of local scale if he
Becomes really relevant at
The human
The human health lens
And that's information
People want
People need and
You know if I have a child
Asthma or
Or if I'm an insurer that you know that is seeing
Section of my population that's being
For example a respiratory disease or
Or other forms of diseases are connect
I want to be able to take care of my members to take care of
My child
I'm in incorporate that in
Information into decision-making so I think there's a. Of during which we have to come to
Terms with this availability availability of this kind of information
But I think it's up to us collectively to ensure that we're serving
Public good
What are the things I feel like we don't do enough of in The Internet of Things
Community is
Making sure the data that we're generating is actually
Useful valid and tested so this could be anything from wearables and making sure they're actually
Getting the right information
All the way to something like environmental data Sol
How do you make sure it's it's peer-review that it's high-quality that so people can
Can actually trust it
Thank you that's it that's a really
Important
Conversation
Because I think
All of this new data
Informing decision and in the case of environmental data
Urban planning
Policy
Care delivery
Consumer choices and
What's really important
That we deliver quality data and so
The fresh one of the ways we've been doing that is through a number partner
What's the scientific name
Immunity to validate
The ways that
Comparing our sensors
Hybrid laboratory equipment
Getting our methods validated and doing this with organizations like the EPA like Lawrence Berkeley National Lab
The case of the Oakland study with the environmental defense fund and the University of Texas and
It took us a long time
We were collecting data in Oakland for year
Getting it
Right
Is really important
Ensuring that were
Or creative people can rely on and
And delivering on our mission of really using the iot for good
So I looked at the state and I'm like I can see government officials being interested in
But I could also see something like
A community organization like
Do you know what PTA to school I would love to be able to drill down to my school's level NC
A community may not make that available
So
Are you thinking of ways to make
Actionable insights available to people beyond the folks that will actively by the platform
Yes and that's one of the most exciting aspects of gar
Partnership with Google
Is that
There's a real life
Kennedy to you imagine
In a day
Where this is as available as traffic
And where this is as available as you have Street data is on
Google Maps application
Today
And so I think
You know there is such absolute
One of the things that we're exploring
And part of
You know what we'd love to accomplish together
That's awesome
And it kind of brings up this idea that when you have the sensors you really can put them
On a lot of different places
So
Where do you think the ideal places for this kind of data capture
We talked about header
Genius Network
Brookstone networks that
That combine data from sensors
Floyd in a lot of location
So
And we we deploy our sensor
I'm building
Today
Some of the largest air quality
About the largest air quality sensor
Turn networks to play today inside a building
And then we also.
Deploy them
Tops of buildings
We can play them on light post
Stationary
That gives you a view of the environment overtime right and so we can get a really good temporal
Air quality or climate emission
But by putting them on vehicle
And what's really exciting about
Trends
Vehicles
Mobility
Is that vehicles
Become a network since olives and that gives us
Facebook
Suddenly we can cover an entire
City
And do it at a
Speed
And scale
It would be very difficult
Stationary networks and what are
The Oakland study shows
Is that
You need that kind of coverage because pollution is hypervariable
Hyperlocal
And so
If you're limited
Stationery sets
Pictures you're not going to
Have data but you need to understand pollution and emission
I'm sure it's also a little bit
Temporal
I imagine pollution
Winter in the middle of
Yeah
Yes
Exactly
Yeah and so what we've done is in a really developed a methodology to be able to create a representative
Snapshot
That shows us where the hot spots are
So just a few weeks ago Brian krzanich the CEO of Intel actually was talking about self-driving vehicles and
Using them for things like
Putting surveillance cameras on them this feels
Very much in line with
Are you looking at expanding the app
Platform Beyond Maybe
Air quality sensor
Yes what we care about
Is understanding the health of our environment and there's ways to to do that not just
Direct measure
Air quality sensor
But there is
Many other sensors that can
Can be integrated into our platform
The capture this kind of information
And we're really you know again tonight
Think that the
Trend
Self-driving
Cars and
The mobility shift that were staying in Mobility
Offers up a notch
Opportunity
New capabilities Beyond just seeing what they're using today whether it's lidar other forms
Cameras
Visual senses
All these other capabilities
Scale
Distribution
Vehicles would be tremendously valuable for
Companies for
For policy-makers are
Planners and I'm really excited about
Boring
Those kind of application
Got it so the car isn't just going to be a computer it's going to be a big sensor
That's right a big sensor that can
Free all these others
Sitel benefit beyond the permeability play
Awesome so if you had one thing you could wish for
One maybe technology maybe it's a business a I don't know
What would it be what are we lacking today
That you would love to see us implement or
That you would love to buy off the shelf
I think
Power store
Is that are pink one of the
You know we've been we started at 9 corporate
Mm
And back then
Cloud computing
So now that clock
Computing is
Probably available
Diffusion a player and so we should have been living through over
Several years
All of these enabling Technologies coming into into being and
Turing
And one of the one of the big ones for us
Is just is really excited about is
It's the work that's been happening in
And being able to power these
In a way that
That is doesn't require intervention
Got it okay well
DaVita thank you so much for coming on the show that
No thank you for having me really really excited to continue the conversation in the Itt
Community I think
Great stuff is coming and we're glad to be a part of the community
For this week show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up for my news
Just let her stay see those things at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week