Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And today we have
New services for the Amazon Echo
How to talk about Amazon web services going down and what it took with it
We also discuss
Hack teddy bears
Stuff that makes the smart home
I said suck butt
Just not very fun for users
Go to talk about my Logitech Harmony
And how that worked out for me and we got some cool new smart home gadgets that are coming on them
Also have a word from this week sponsor spin dance
And our guest is star
Jaskiewicz
Of Comedy called Audrey
And he's actually going to talk about what it means when everything becomes a service and how that affects the Enterprise
Value chain and how small our company
Can actually
Create value and work with bigger cam
It's a really
Thought-provoking interview
At least it was for me
You guys may all be a lot smarter
Who knows
Before we get to all of that I have another message from our spot
This week's weather is Wolf SSL the world's top three automakers use wolf SSL to secure
Their vehicles and they aren't alone secures 2 billion connections across a multitude of eye
Iot sectors including Automotive connected home industrial military and medical device
What the Mirai botnet in the growing threat of ransomware attacks on the Internet of Things companies have to pay to
The security or wrist litigation bad PR and their brand value
Securing the iot is hard but wolf SSL has the experience and specialized expertise to help
Shouldn't you be using both SSL
To find out more
Is it wolf SSL
Dot-com
All right
Kevin
Let's pick a topic you want to talk about
Oh that's just go right to the big news this week which is
So far
We should say this week so far because this week is only halfway over when we start recording
But on Tuesday Amazon web services
Experienced an outage in
Virginia Virginia
I was trying to remember what it's called but it's their Virginia Datacenter this guy goes down all the time
It's super old
85 years anyway
It's their least reliable
Data Center
Basically when you hear problems it's almost
Almost guaranteed to be that pretty
But
A lot of stuff
I think it's called East
Stash one cuz they'll have designations obviously
And I noticed
It's happening yesterday afternoon
When I was listening to satellite radio over the web
So SiriusXM was using the app
As I was working at a sudden stop playing music and I'm like well that's weird
And then I might go switch to Apple music as a screenplay he couldn't play that
Then I told my echo to
Play music you know I listen you age
Play new agent
She said okay Shuffle new age
And then I went to the web and saw that the East one
Amazon data center was having problems and
That the list of companies that
Were affected
They're at their several dozen
Sympathizer
Canary apparently admitted to struggles ring connect to doorbell maker had some issues
Piper another all-in-one security product
Hazmat shoes
And the assistant that mean
Caused a lot of problems
People were complaining that
Oh my gosh I can't turn on my lights
Which
I wish I was a little bit bad
Because if this then that
What are you doing tell him to get a proper hug or something
Italy
I know I did
When the internet
Goes down
Sure
If this then that goes down
So Kevin
Is going to use this
Time to
You knew I was going to go there today
See I had no problems had to test this be right away as soon as I did
Amazon server issue
Powercloud issue I started
Tell me my echo to turn lights on and off
And
It still work
Because the how did I use the wink Hub does allow for local
Type commands and schedules and so on so what it's not completely Cloud Reliant
So I know I said it before it's one of the reasons I
I decided to stick with it I'm not going to say it's the best hub
But obviously in this instance it was
Still working out for my smart home so that was
It's something to keep in mind
And if you want
Would also
Turn on things
And
I believe SmartThings
Would too because they thought local control
Even though SmartThings is actually hosted in
AWS
And so this gets into a topic that we probably should talk about more
We don't
But a lot of people were like
Oh no this is a problem because everything is hosted in the cloud
It's actually not
It's a problem because of the way the systems architect
In Amazon is by far the most popular
Platform
For smart home services it's the backend for services
We've already mentioned but it's also the back in for platforms like SmartThings
Ala network switch
Actually provides service for Hunter fans and a lot of other
The devices
Until what
Companies need to take into account is you need to design for resiliency and Netflix actually doesn't excellent
People talking about chaos monkeys what they're talking about is Netflix's design philosophy
54 their architecture which is basically like
Plan for
Crap to happen and things to go down including
Amazon
InDesign across multiple regions
So that means don't put all your eggs in one data center basic
This is going to be complicated is going to be slightly more expensive
But you're going to have up time
When the sort of thing happens so
Despite the fact that AWS
And
I think it's a great time to talk about
Finding hubs that work locally even when the cloud is down
People who design their
Cloud architectures
Who are hosted on AWS to think about hosting across multiple availability zones and resiliency which can be
Be done
We also want to talk about some new
Echo skills
The big one
Is if you have a wink Hub Kevin you're going to appreciate this
You can now connect several types of locks
You can connect your Schlage Locks
Your Kwikset lock
Fox Andrew yellow
To work with wink
And you can use the echo to check if a door is locked or unlocked
And luck
You cannot use the echo 2
Unlocked
But you're right
It is true that if you have an August lock
You can unlock your door using the
Just so you're aware
I tested it
I should actually tell you how to do this
So if you haven't done it
Connect your locks
Through the wink hub
Which I done already
And you have to set individual names
I'm going to tell you that my naming convention
My garage door is actually garage lock
Don't do that
Cathay garage door
Call your front door back door
Sep just just a little warning for you
Then
If you haven't been able to link scale with the Echo app
And then sign into all that good stuff and then tell the echo to discover new devices
Once that's done
You are
Done and then you can say
Is garage door
Locked
Ilse
Hold on checking on that
And it's come back and tell you
Or you can say hey
Lock the garage door
So again
When you're naming your lock you may want to go back in and rename it needed something you want to say to
Yep and I actually just ran through the steps cuz I already had a
Kwikset lockset already connected to my wink hub
I went into the Amazon app for my echo and didn't discover devices and I now see you lock
Which I don't really like the name of but I can change that later
Yes you will probably want value only have one but you may want to
I may have more later I don't know
There you go
Only because your lock is actually part of a ruler
Run through that maybe sometime this week and see cuz one of the things with Smart Home
Products
Is state
So
If you change it from
One type of app
Instead of the other
Sometimes they don't always the state doesn't match up so
If you lock it in one app
The other apps may still think they not know
Yeah yeah
Alluding to is the one I set up to automatically lock my front door
It's lock is unlocked for 5 minutes
Because
Kids are leaving the front door unlocked so it does that automatically survival test
Okay
So I tried this out
Works like a charm
It's very nice so
I'm excited by this
Speaking of the Amazon Echo you can now connect your Netgear orbi or
Nighthawk routers to the echo
Which means you can ask it things like
Echo
Ask Netgear to enable guest Network
Ask Netgear to enable disable 5G Gessner
And
What are my WiFi
Settings
Which is
Is very handy
So
These are all very good
We will include a link in the show so you can see which Nighthawk routers
And which Netgear routers work with us
You're going to have to go enable the skill
It's not a direct kind of Hub things so
Very easy very fun
And
Are useful if you
Do you have the sword
I
I use my Eero settings on the echo to pause the network
Work on occasion
Which is super fun
I'm just frustrated everyone in my
That's nice
Evil family dinner time should not be
Put the phones down
Actually they can't unpositive
Akame unpause
Sneaky
Yeah
All right before we stop talking about
Echoes can I just throw one more thing
I should have been I will
I will also it seems like there's a concerted effort
By phone makers
2 *
Bringing
The echo services in 2 handsets
And we saw this at the Consumer Electronics Show I believe it was Huawei that said we're going to have
Android app built right into a phone it's not there yet it's still there still working on that
But interesting land enough at Mobile World Congress last week
Was it Lenovo
Who owns Motorola
Showed off
A concept video of a new Moto mod annies
These mods or add-ons that you would buy the name attached to your Motorola phones
Could be a speaker could be projector
A better camera Etc they have a couple of them out right now
They're going to have a new one I showed it off at
Mwc
And basically it turns the phone into a portable Amazon Echo
So that the mod stick to the back of the Moto Z for example
You put your phone face down and use the back as a speaker
Even has the blue glow around the edges so it knows so you know rather when you were speaking to it just like you would be true
Additional Echo Hardware
So it's coming later this month
Expectedly no price or anything but
It's just interesting that
Companies have been working on their own voice Service as an AI for quite a while
And
Now they're really embracing Amazon in a big way
Well it's that they did a lot of the high
Work for you so
Why not
Why Google
Haven't really pushed its
Natural language processing
Like its speech recognition
AI for Developers
Very much
Because
There's clearly a hunger for this
I would say so I'd I don't know
What
Google has provided to developers in that respect but I do know that
The Google Assistant
Which was the exclusive to the pixel phones is now coming to all
Android 6.0 and 7.0 phone so that's no yeah I no longer going to be an exclusive
That's kind of interesting
Doesn't answer your question about what can developer so much
But at least it's coming to a much wider audience
And I'm taking my comments about developers from people who've been developing speech Rec
Recognition apps for a
What's the weather this is and they many of them in this is about
8 months ago hit reached out to Google in
They figured there was something there but Google just
WhatsApp
What's this
That's interesting and I'm not disputing that at all I just don't know but I look back to my Wink app
And
I can create
There's a beta for like Google
Voice-activated shortcuts that use
Use that so there's got to be some hooks available to folks
Creating apps and such but I don't know what they are with to the extent they are
Yes they do have them
Hadn't been marketing them
In some cases
You kind of had to ask and then you were stuck in a queue forever
But
With the Google home that is changing
So
Yay we should also mention
Kevin
I do I'm a consultant for Google
An Android Chrome sided
Mark was the IRT focuser
Google Assistant jokes
To make assistant available in other places because I have a Nexus 5
Do I have an exercise yes I have a Nexus 5X
And I
Very excited
Futures you get an assist
Continue getting the system
And you get an assist
I had nothing to do with it
It was all over
So
Let's now talk about
This is also a hot story
Hacked
Teddy bears
I wanted a satyr
That was actually much saturated it much better than I did. I'm in a good mood
This is like
This is aggravating
Sounds like a recurring Story 2 because it's not the first time this has happened with children's toys that have
Some type of microphones and so on
Yes basically if you're making a children's toy
Get your security in at the beginning so what happened here is a company called
It's spiral toys to make a product called cloud
And they basically contracted out to a company to do there
Connectivity and
Grab like they're filled out the backend architecture for this connect
Teddy bear
And that company basically left
An open mongodb database
Just hanging out there not secured
On the internet
Which over 800,000 account records
Yes and
To make matters worse
They dropped all of their files the recording files over two million of them were stored in an Amazon S3
Repository and like
I don't want a server
Instant thank you that is the word
Imagine it was multiple instance
But you could actually find that file wasn't protected so if you knew where to look
In this this is a little bit less agree
God storing passwords
Just on the internet in a database with no security that
Yeah that's just a tough time in this toys
Interesting in that you could
Record a message to your kids and send it over the Internet to the teddy bear and all
But now the account information on an icing recordings are all stored as well
Geez I mean as a people getting into these
Teddy bears in like sending
Disturbing messages to
People's teddy bear switch
Cool
As a hacker I can see how it be super funny in your head to send a terrifying message to a toddler
But you know
It's it's Dad that's over the line I mean
Obviously
Everybody has their own Line in the Sand it to me that's over the line
Yeah someone had a Twitter
They showed it where
I will eat your
Face
RushCard
That's great
Haha but
That is the situation
The
Okay
I swear to God I say this all the time
But
You guys are getting the Internet of Things a bad name
When you build a connected product
You have to think of security
From the ground up
Killer Contract
Have to think of Siri
Underground
And there are companies out there
Who do this
And is a consumer
You're going to have
I was just going to say that's what it comes down to I think it's cost
And
You know it's so
A company and I'm not trying to single out that the company that has spiral toys here but any companies making a
Device it's connected
Different want to keep costs down obviously I totally get that
It's not in the end
Yeah there you go in this situation
I love
The idea of being able to
Do this but
Plenty of teddy bears out there that you
You can record your voice and
By golly guys and if you're a consumer
Maybe don't buy the stuff
Or maybe
Don't buy it
Cheap I hate to say that
One of the things you can look for is to see if the company making the product
Has a bug Bounty program
That's actually really good way to look and be like
Care about Security in this case
This company was actually informed of the breach
In December and January
And never did anything about it
That feels like a situation
No
It's getting to the point where it like any product it comes down to who do you trust what company or brand do you trust and
With Fire TV because it's a relatively new
Industry
Consumer level
And we still don't know
You don't know all the security practices of all these companies either
So it's it's really ad
Tricky situation
Any product on the Internet
It's going to be hot or has the potential to be high
If your device if you're designing a product is going to be connected
You probably want to design for resiliency
Stuff happen
So you have to build your product
With a mindset that you're always going to be tinker
You're always going to be testing it for 6
Breeches
You're always going to be testing at for resiliency challenges
And this is a very new mindset for a lot of
Companies
And you got to get it right
Otherwise
You're going to just stick us right back in in in some people are like
Yeah okay that's fine I don't need it
But it's bigger than that that's
The problem so it's you know I might want to put a new camera in my house because I've got to be my security system
But do I want to do that
Considering you know
Somebody might be able to hack in and see
In my house
Speaking of security cameras
Oh I did
I did
Really I don't know that I needed any kind of camera but I'm like you know I should have I used to have them
That's much smaller house so you know I'm working from home for 5 days a week
I got a good discount on it on Amazon site I did my Nest Cam and I set it up on Sunday night in fact
Sunday afternoon
Set up Sunday night
And I don't see it paid for itself
In the first 5 minutes of us on Monday but boy did it make for an entertaining video
Because I came downstairs at 7:30 in the morning on Monday
I found my dog
The kitchen island as I often do
And like you know what
I'm going to see how you got up there cuz I don't know and I'm going to see when you went up there
And sure enough
I would like 7 in the morning after I went back into the logs
I saw my wife and stepdaughter go out the front door to work and school
Answered a few minutes later good old Norm
I see how he does it now it turns the Barstool hopped up there and
That's why I found them up there so
It made for an entertaining video
Kim Kardashian
If you don't however
Watch the video is a tiny poodle
He is not a dog that
And he's very agile
Are you smart
.
Insufficient phrase
I do not know why
Missouri temperamental
But he is very agile
He is
You're crazy
Crazy agile dog
Of course so he's not really in trouble
He made for entertaining video
Yeah don't leave chocolate
We have actually
Some
Cool smart home thing you said I wanted to point out because a couple people have been asking me about
One is a product this is only available in the UK
And it has a camera and it also uses sound
Protect your house so
It basically is very powerful microphone to understand
Like if doors have been opened
It's kind of like a glass break sensor
So I think it's kind of an interesting way to do this and then obviously wants it to text something
Turn the camera on and then
You can check and be like
It's 159 pounds
Again
UK
Andrew on the sight word Amazon
And I kind of want to try it out
So
It's an interesting take on security because when you think of home security think I got a table or instrument all these doors and windows
And from what I gather
They're saying no you don't because
It can learn the sounds of your house
House doors opening and people
And
If it detects sound of something
Different like glass breaking
Then it can you know whether to send out a 90 decibel siren
Show you you know what's going on based on the camera
So I suspect
You could use fewer of these as opposed to you know like a good 20 doors and windows
Enable 20
Sensors
Exactly
That's kind of what I wanted to ask
Cuz right now I don't have sensor
I have them they're just now
So that's one for people who are
Excited
I also
This is a pre-order kind of situation so I try not to do too much of these just because
You never know
I could spend my entire show telling you about the kickstarter
This is a device called brilliant
What is the light switch
But it's a light switch with a capacitive touchscreen
It also has these
Touch-sensitive sliders so what you do is if you have a 1 single light switch you're going to replace your light switch with
You can also it's got two three and four gang switches basic
Which is one screen with like
Four different slider
It's got Amazon Echo voice is so Amazon voice Services built in
You can talk to it and order it to
Things just like you
It's got a motion sensor ambient light sensors
And you can
Quote you can do like this swiping up and down to turn things on or off
Hold your finger to Dimmitt
And it's got a mic so you can use it as an intercom
Tom in your home
There's a lot to like
I would agree with you as I look at it though it's
Whitney reminds me of
It reminds me of the wink relay that I have in my bedroom
It has a very similar look and feel I do like a sliders as opposed to the two Hardware
Switches that the wink uses
And the week doesn't had a can beat the Winx
Canby
Intercoms butt
They don't have Amazon voice Services built-in so that's nice
This works with Sonos and nest and other stuff
I like
The look at this and I just noticed
I just noticed that they have it at the Target open house
In San Francisco and guess where I'll be next week not on the show
I'll be in San Francisco right across the street from the Metreon there in the Target so I may go take a look at this
Don't you get my hopes up
I will try to take a look I promise I will try
I really like to look at
Extremely similar and it has more functionality
It kind of reminds me that we talked about this but the nucleus
It's a I want to say it's like a picture frame kind of device but it's it's a video conference call it's a dedicated video conference call
Or an intercom system for your house
So you can
Put one downstairs it also has the
Echo voice services
You put one downstairs one upstairs and you could be like
Hey
Dinner's ready
I'm actually just updated the skill there in case you have them
So you can actually
Now just
Hey nucleus call kids bedroom
And it'll do it
Which is nice cuz before he had to touch it to make that
Do you know the price on this the pre-orders are already done so I don't know what this went for the pre-orders were too
$2 for single switch up to 350 4 for switch
Yeah
And I think the pre-orders had
$20 off
Now this won't be available so here comes
The cracks you guys
It is
Not going to be available again for sale until late
So when we find out that it is for sale again and maybe he'll send a review unit
Who knows
Kevin
I won't make you do any more light switches
That is this product so if you're interested in lighting
If you're listening to this
Time for some device
Updates
I talked last week about the Logitech Harmony which I purchased
And I purchased it
For the stupidest reason
Or the most brilliant
And I'm not
Excited yet basically I wouldn't
And you know you know modern TVs if you got a receiver you got you know
Afro to wear a DVD player and all the stuff I wanted to turn it on
So now I can say
Shiva shall not be named
Turn on television
End
Everything turns off
I can say turn on Netflix and we could all the way
So I had some trouble setting it up
But I don't
I think it was just a glitch
But nobody Logitech they were very good on the customer support side night I went through normal customer support
And I basically uninstalled everything reset everything from my router all the way down to
Turn out the light reflecting and uninstalling the app on my phone
And then read it
And I will tell you
It has gotten a lot better we actually
400th episode I went back and listen to it like
Some of our final episode
Play podcast in
Particular episode that I listen to a Logitech Harmony
Oh geez that's funny
A lot has changed so
The
Logitech app actually
Send a text a lot of the devices on your home network so you don't even have to set
You do have to you know like we said on that previous episode
The database is key so all I did was insert the model numbers of
My devices
And I ran into some trouble because it only allows for 8 connected devices
So
Have more than that that work with this thing so I had to make a call so I made the call to only have it be my
My television stuff and then a Sonos speaker
Because of my sister my receiver so it's kind
But I can't actually tell it to play certain songs on the Sonos I can only tell it to start up and it'll play my
Right
It is still nice to get the receiver
Direction control
That was a lie
Is a much better experience is much cleaner they've done a great job in their Echo skill is really phenomenal.
Because you link the skill
And you actually get the choice of like
It offers you multiple sayings that it thinks will work for what you're trying to do
The call
The things you're trying to do activities so it's like
Return on television
It's like
Turn on television and turn on TV and I'll let you know
You can even create
Amateur
So that way you don't have anything say multiple ways which is good
So
All in all
Yay
So I got a product update
Hitch all right then Stacy has no idea what I'm about to say I didn't tell her
In advance
Self
I mentioned last week that we got last week or two weeks ago we got a June oven
And I'm bringing this up for a couple reasons why
People should know that we put our money where our mouth is we both bought
I do not but I mean
When do you know if it's not working
Yeah yeah so I wanted to give a quick update and tell you how
This is being troubleshooted and what's being done about it
So basically
2 days ago
You haven't started freezing up like
Not literally cuz it's nothing nice box
But the display widget
Freezer
Time
Left to cook would you stop
Anime what's going on here don't know I'm so
We couldn't even turn it off
So
We were able to continue cooking cycles and so on so forth any more and more often
In addition to that and this may have been from day one I do not know
The one of the four ceramic heating elements at the top of the furthest back one
I noticed wasn't
Lighting up even when it should be on it and even when the app
Does the app tells you which elements are on which fans are on all that
The Apple showing it was on
But it wasn't
So I'm like that's really interesting
I did what I should do I
Reach out to support I just did this yesterday in fact yesterday morning and explained what was going on
And the support Folks at June oven I got to be honest I've been fantastic now.
I didn't say ideas podcast I didn't say we're working like that to them as far as I know I'm just regular customers
Just wanna put that out there
Try and pull anything special
They asked me a bunch of questions they also asked me for the serial number so that and my permission to look at the logs
Because the thing runs
Connected with Wi-Fi
They checked the logs they could really see that the element was not working and I'm not surprised because the
What's showing that it was working as well so they asked me to take some pictures of it and I put on broil and take a picture and sound
I did all that no problem
And
They
Said seems like a hardware issue
Sears return label
Pack it up and original packaging which I still had cuz there was a hundred day no questions asked
Florentine all return policy
And they've already
Shipped out a new one
Did not put a hold on my credit card or anything which I'm amazed for
$59 Prada
Simon and the way back
Wow I'm sorry you had that occur
Experience
I'm glad that they were
Careful in nice to you about it but
Here's the thing I mean you and I are early adopters and our families have to put up with
Right
I can only speak for my family
But my family is often frustrated by my earlier adopter
Product purchases and so on so forth
I would imagine you get a little that as well
You should have seen me the TV wasn't
Okay
But here's the thing
My wife
Is not upset about this at all which I'm shocked
I'm shocked
She said she really likes this
It's working well when we was working it works fantastic I had some of the best food
So
She's like okay
Alright let's see what happens
At normal she be like
Send it back get your money back I told you not to buy that thing or whatever did she say
Not this time I'm really surprised
I can only say that
I'm sorry this is happening but my husband would be the same way there's only there's very few devices that
She actually loves in our house
The junas win the echo was another
MyQ garage door
Everything else
Well he likes me
Really everything else can just
We have four Echoes and I'm the only one that uses
Everyone hates talking to me
So
They really don't Embrace many of the products so that's
Probably why I have a separate office and they just leave me alone with the door shut
But this is an exception
So awesome
That is a wonderful note to end
And on Kevin
Thanks for spending your morning with me here and
Please stay tuned for
Luis Arias kibbutz
Of augury
Who's going to talk about what it means when everything becomes a service and how
Startups can take advantage of that and what it means for big businesses
Before we get to sorry though
We're going to take a
Rake
Message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we're taking a break for the podcast for a moment for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Then dance
And I have Brian told her again to talk about
Spin dance and first Bryan
Can you remind everyone with
You guys do
Yeah spin dance
Develops and builds iot software for Fortune 500 organization
Buy Kwikset locks
Whirlpool and Ford
And we also work with smaller manufacturers and startup we don't just build the software we also host
We have a dedicated team that designs and supports infrastructure for iot products
So let's talk about this infrastructure what is so unique about designing and hosting a
Infrastructure for
It's very familiar to anybody who's done any cloud
Posting a lot of the best practices in the principles are the same but the fact is winter starting to deal with physics
Google devices that can really drastically change the equation for updates cross embedded cloud and mobile
Can be tricky and it's definitely a place where you want expert help debugging IRT problems is another important skill to have
We recently Tree hours to prominence fanfiber vendors including multiple cell phone providers it was a really tricky to
To get to the bottom of what was going on that's not something you typically see which is cloud-based software
So what are some common mistakes you see organizations
We see a lot of cloud-to-cloud
Free sample six months ago integrated
The Nest thermostat with whirlpools Jenn-Air oven
Kind of cloud
Occasionally quite challenging
Secondly we see a lot of organizations making mistakes estimating their ongoing infrastructure costs
Especially around integration and regression
And we see a lot of companies trying to use their internal it team to manage their iot products
Which we think is an anti pattern we really think you need a dedicated team focused on iot
Why do companies need that dedicated
The organization's we've seen be really successful iot use a product development mindset
Connects not typically the mode of operation
Nit group
RX station hosting team work side-by-side with our developers in their customers and they kind of have that natural
Psychedelic mindset that you really need to make great iot decisions
So if people have questions where can they learn more about spin dance
Angular services
Including
Hosting
People can download a free white paper
NetSpend dance.com coyote email at hello it's been dance.com
Thank you
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is SAR
Jaskiewicz
Who is
Founder and CEO of a company called
I'm doing great thank you
Glad to be here I am super excited to have you on the show
What we're going to do
Who is first
I'd love for you to tell everybody
What artery does
Should we listen to machines
And based on the noise that they may you can tell if you're working properly used to have them a function
And even what type of malfunction they have so we're kind of like Shazam
Four machines
I like that
How do you guys
Listen to stuff is it is it
Put their phone up next to it is there like
How does that work
So we actually have two ways of asking to machine
Our first product was a portable diagnostic tool that connects a vibration sensor to the ticket
Ignition iPhone or Android device
And he basically walks up to the machine attaches the sensor with a magnet
Wait for a couple of seconds
And then he gets
The results on the spot
I will also have a continuous monitoring solution
Where we leave the sensors on the machine
We connect that to the internet and then can give
Continuous feedback and alerts if anything goes wrong
Basically what you're doing is listening to
And you developed an algorithm that can basically tell
Howa malfunctioning
Machine sounds
Straight correct so he's amassed a huge malfunction dictionary
If you will
Of how different malfunction sound in
The machines across the focusing on
I will check that are pumps fans
Compressors
How did you guys get
Definition of chicken leg of every machine learning
Right I was out
Therefore you don't have any customers
Amazon customer service have any data
What we initially did is we partnered with the largest maintenance company
In our Market
And had their
Ignition
Start recording
And then we manually
Analyze
This machine
And built the diction
That's awesome so how did you build trust with that part
Because that is
Like you explained
Crux of any sort of startup
That's kind of
It's a very hard
Salt
We were lucky to have good partners that are forward-thinking
And really wanted to see how technology can improve and and frankly disrupt lyrics
Market
You guys are
Israeli machine learning
So when you reached out to these guys did you have
Is your company
Already did you know what you were going to do
We spent the first two years of the company
Bootstrapping
And because both of us come from the technology side from engineering backgrounds
We built the first prototype by ourselves
So when we approach this customer we already had something
Adipose work
That connected vibration sensors to an iPhone
Send the data to work to the cloud for servers
Where we analyzed it and returns a result of the phone
Got it and I'm excited about with the internet
Is that it
Basically
We got cheap analytics cheap computer
So we have this ability to take information in a scale that is
For the impossible
And I think that's really going to change the world
So
How did you guys kind of come to this idea
Why is now the right
To do something
The iPhone changed ever
So two major trends that happened over the past
Years is
First every technician now has a supercomputer in
Pocket
Which we can leverage to do
Some of the Computing as well as
User interface
And the second trend is
Cloud computing where
As you said
Computing became very very cheap
And storing data became very very
Cheap as well
These two
Abilities or capabilities just didn't exist 5 years ago
And now is the time to really connect
Everything you can and monitor every Spencer and every
Signal
In order to create insights from Alta Strada
What is changing here and what is the end
So that the end goal is to provide insights
Sinatra.
So
For us to be able to tell the user
The technician or the
Reliability manager if you do not
Replace this bearing
Over the next quarter
Your machines Nitro breakdown
April cost you this much to repair it
Alright
Today
Some sensors are wired into a building management system
But most of the sensors
Uneven wire to that
So you haven't
Technician going through the morning and evening crowds
And just looking at all these
Data points
Temperature pressure and not even walking
So you can't create inside if you don't have
If you don't have the backlog
Behavior
The history of the behavior
How do I know
What track
Insulting
Heavily industrialized
You guys obviously are optimizing
Around noise but there's also
Or heat sensor anywhere and make meaning from the date overtime and
How do you know which one you should choose So today we're focusing on
3 sensor
I want is vibration II
Ultrasound we also have a temperature and magnetic and
Well we chose these for sensors because they give us the best value for the least expensive
System
Right over time
As we gain more and more Exodus
Into the machines
They working with the OEM filter manufacturers
We want to use
All the day.
We can have existing sensors we want all that data
To give better diagnostic
So don't they want to do this themselves why would they come to you
Companies are amazing at
Designing and building mechanical systems using very traditional tools
But they don't know how to connect sensors to the internet
They don't know how to store
Petabytes or zettabytes worth of data
I don't have the algorithmic abilities
To design and run the algorithms
I feel like there's a huge value-add for you guys that you are a neutral party is supposed to lock it locked inside
1 Bender
Correct so if
You know if you look at a more complex machine even not even enough time for a fan
You have the motor supplier
Right you have the fan supplier you have bearings have a lot of different components and if we are able to work
All of them
We can give a holistic view of the machine
And provide the best eggnog
Other possible
Insights are going to be the huge kind of value-add
In the industrial world
What happens to companies that have historically
Mayday equipment
Which singers are interesting Trent now
Which is very similar to software-as-a-service
Are we called
And it started in the very high-end marker
Queso in jet engines
White Rolls-Royce
Stop selling jet engine
Start selling flight hours
That you have there is that most they can get
Better margins
On the spare parts and the aftermarket services
Then they could
By selling
Add equipment
And we see the same trend
Going down Market
I told you they're in
In Chillers which are the more
Expensive piece of equipment
But we expected to reach all the way to Clemson fans and eventually maybe even two
Washing machines and refrigerators
So the oems are looking for ways to
Preach
And sell more services
And they need to rely on technology in order to
Biscuits into this idea of everything
So how does that change the value chain
For providers
And even the buyers
Paso doble yams should look at the value chain today you have the
Original equipment
Tribution chain you have the
Service companies
And then you have aftermarket
Parts
The OEM One
To own as much as
They cancelled
And this may mean that independent service companies
Will have to consolidate with a larger OEM server
As well as the distribution channels
Because this is what is the big kind of
Conundrums I see as the OEM start
Hey I want to offer this as a service
And they don't want to piss off their distributors
Too much because they also have
This lovely day
Just that his
How did the Distributors and the service companies who are servicing these this equipment
Look at this kid how do they find their own belly
It's a great question I think we'll need to see how the market
Lights out
And innocence it's not that different from what we see in the automotive in the
Right eye with autonomous car
GM is working on their own fleet of cars
Have together with Lyft
Is working on autonomous athletes as well
So this notion of
Transportation
The service
Is very similar to coolangatta serve
Right on the market
Now we're moving forward in this
Concept new value chain
Basically
Where is a company that provides algorithm
Yeah so by being a jerk party that works with
Are all these
Manufactured
We are impartial
And then we can transfer Knowledge from one market
The other
Boss on the algorithm
Night if we see something working
Which Sans weekend
Shareit with the pump
And
Hopefully
Will be able to
Build an open platform
That's what moves the whole Market
Okay so
The future being I am an oem so I actually make
I have another role which is
Insight
Delivery
Which is actually tell customers
Useful information but you can also give information back to OEM about how to make
Better products
And then you have
A customer so it's a little bit more
When we look at working with OEM we want to work with him over the
Stages of the product life cycle
ISO initially in the research say
Would help them
Define
The right sensors and
Placements of the sensors
We find you the algorithm for this
Product
Then factoring line will give the much better quality control
So if they can run these tests on the manufacturing line
They can identify a lot of the malfunction
This would have happened during the war
I did then they can save a lot of
Operational cost
The third step you know once
In the Wild on the customer
Sites
We
Keep monitoring this
Operating the algorithm
To get better and better Diagnostics
But as just said
We also track
All of these
Taylor statistics
As well as
Usage pattern
And then
OEM can take this
When designing
And this brings us back to the research base
It seems like you guys would be a better fit
For a service
Media service company that provides
Services to
What happens if the aftermarket
When everything's a service is the OEM one at home
The actor Mark
Parts
For sure that's where they seem or most of the margins today
And they want to login
Customer
Longer contract
Swarthmore
Value
Okay so in this Brave New World
What is that mean for your company
You've only been doing this for five years but
Everybody's thinking about the
Best cell
Building a large company that will be sustainable and independent
We're starting with
The commercial
Air conditioning Market but our goal eventually has to be inside everything that has
And this could be your washing machine refrigerator dishwasher
Even car right
So we're really here to for the long run
Insights not me
Consumer
Because I'm going to be buying my washing machine is a service
Correct end up with
Bright
Hundreds of Millions
Sumer's you just deal with
Eight or nine Giant
Manufacturer
So wonderful
Yes and isn't working very well what's next
Do we have a couple of Marcus in mind
Orc machine types
Commercial
Or industrial market and we're not going to there
Consumer residential yet
Kobe elevator
Example
The whole culture
Wright Refrigeration in the factory
Drink transportation of it
Either
Antrax
Train tour
Overseas
It also has a very lucrative Market
Okay elevators is a really interesting because ThyssenKrupp actually has an elevator
Risky Business
I'm sure there's another elevator manufacturer
In a situation like that
Which is kind of a weird
Well it's a good point that the elevator Market
Switch to the desert service model
Because there are more
Expensive
Require a lot of maintenance
The way that we
Yeah
Is we want to work with these manufacturer
So today they offer a service
But if we can decrease their malfunctions by 75
Percent
Weekend
Saving a lot of money
So basically you'll be going to
Already analyzing the data
Salmista
Crack of the question is what data are the analyzing
How advanced are there Outlet
So it's just purely better
Magic Machine learning
Machine learning understanding machine
10/3 m
So I can tell you the fact that you're not
Operational data
Look at mechanical
I can see that.
All right
Latisse or anything else you want to tell me
Another very interesting trend
Is
What happens to insurance
When everything is continuously monitored and diagnose
Yes and
In a sense you can say that the OEM
If they do move to this equipment as a service model
They become an insurance
Cuz they hold off the risk if anything goes
Bong
Not wanting to trade insurance
Christine
Moving from a annual rate and annual flat rate
Actions that are based on the actual
Dishes
So if you're a Progressive auto insurance customer to get the small black box that measures if you're a safe
And that just a few name on the side
Or if you drive after midnight
Raining
You pay higher
And very similar in our markets
If you take good
Care of your machines
And they're inaccessible condition
There is a lower risk
A failure
Therefore you will pay in the
We want to become the standard
Pipe for this data
Oxford Insurance
So you want to do this for insurance companies or do you want to do this for the OEM to help them build
Insurance fraud
So
From our discussions that Williams aren't interested in building Insurance product
But if we are working with the largest oh yeah music
Control 80% of the market
We can very easily
Turn the switch and
Give this data to the insurance companies
So they can sell their products today
Okay well I look forward to this
Brave New World of insurance
You guys see such a huge Market
I hope it actually comes to pass
I used to be very excited about a raw data market
And so
Having an insight
Developed
I think that would be compelling
Is the goal of
Every Big Data or machine Learning Company
How do you
Take the raw data
Transform it into knowledge and then into inside
So why didn't the market
Workout
Was it just that nobody knew what to do with it or if people just didn't want to share it but people are willing to share it exchanged
So exactly that
Your Facebook see
Instagrammer
Advertising or what not
So much data out there
But you get overwhelmed
And we are putting our trust in
Help you focus on what matters
And it's not that different from what we
Awesome
I look forward to this I'm hoping it will actually work
Sorry sorry
It's already working
Already here
Alright thank you so much sir
Well that's it for this week's podcast thank you for listening and we'll see you next week on the internet
Nothing's podcast
But if you are so eager for more iot content please go to Stacey on iot
Goatee and sign up for my Weekly Newsletter this last week we talked about cool things like expiration dates for your kin
Connected products and how quickly the smart home is being adopted so sign up for that if you're interested otherwise
Will see you next week