Welcome to the internet
Stacey Higginbotham
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And this is episode 183 of the podcast
And welcome all we're going to be talking about Amazon Amazon Amazon so much Amazon based on all the news
It was out last week
Microsoft ignite is happening so we can be talking about some updates with Microsoft including Cortana and
Azure
Plus
We got a new whiting's watch we're going to see if Kevin wants it
Dulux a new sprinkler and
Maybe
A quick update on my brilliant lights
Plus this week we've got a guest Rayford Smith of
Entergy
Do I talk to at the SAS Analytics
Summit
We're going to talk about all about how to manage a digital transformation
And speaking of SAS they are a sponsor of this week's podcast although I did pay my own way for the summer
So all of that and more awaits you
But first
Let's get a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is aqua keep your iot Fleet growing and trade in the days of remoting into your car
Customers devices to identify and resolve bugs upgrade to Aqua 10 minutes unless it's Edge verse
Problem solving software do the heavy lifting for you chocolate automatically finds performance issues and then tracks
Stem from released release collecting all the Intel you need to rapidly identify root causes for the errors play
Waking you and your customers register for free today chocolate. IO that's a you
K letv
Dot IO
Okay Kevin last week
I was at the Amazon announcement
Which word actually 70 pieces of news released in about an hour and a half
Was like getting shot in the head with
It's about a hundred water balloons was very exciting
And we're going to cover all 70 in-depth today
What is with Amazon in their timing they know we do this podcast so certain day the weekend yet they had their event right
After we did our podcast
I know I can't believe they're not appreciating us
Subscribers list
It's on our calendars Amazon you can see it
School on them okay so
We've already written a couple things about it
So if you want to discover the 11:00 new Echo devices from clocks to microwaves
All kinds of crazy stuff
That's on the website
I also talked about the strategy
There's a couple things we didn't cover
In that news that we can talk about and there's actually a couple questions that you guys sent to us the first one
And will cover this at the very end so stay tuned for that but that is
Based on all of this news
Would we go to being a straight Google or straight Amazon
Does this mean that
What should somebody
So
You got in mind as we talked about some
Pictures so
In addition to all of these devices
Amazon
A really cool thing
Is basically now turned all of your echos
An echo Dot
Security alarm
Watch the service called guard and this is something
You can say is you're walking out of the house
And it will
All of your echos turn into
Glass break sensors so they're listening for the sound of glass breaking the sound
Smoke detectors or carbon monoxide alarms going
And if they hear these I'll actually send you a notice
Vacation
If it's monitored security you can actually send it to your monitored security system
Intel
Do whatever they do
I thought this was really cool
Waste not just cool it's brilliant
Because it doesn't require people to buy any new hardware basically the microphones are all
Very very good in the
Echo products
And noticed repurposing them for a very useful service
Yeah and it's free so
Is that now in addition to your wake word
That you have selected Amazon is going to always be listening
For glass breaking and the sound of your smoke alarm
So in some ways they're using security as a way to
Encroach on privacy
Look at that way which some people will
I don't necessarily think so they're always listening anyway
Well yes but now you've got
A greater number of triggers that will
Trigger something happen
And take an action in store that
Snip it to the cloud
If that's fine they want to listen to the sound of breaking glass all day that's
I need the it is a valuable service
Your privacy
Skytran if you're discussing a murder
Baby don't break glass
They just in Corgi
Funny hangout let me add that to my rules of when I'm discussing these things
Tuck near broken flask
Got it or if you are in the midst of murdering
TriNet
Could you step away from the window for psych thank you okay
So
The other thing to think about here is
They're adding a lot of
Intelligence at the edge so now
I talked to their
When you're always listening this is happy
This doesn't get sent to the
Alright so now they've got three compressed model sitting at
The edge
What's the Wake word one for class 1
Smoke detection you know if you're in the AI world or the edge processor
That's kind of an interesting
And also
Also speaking of the edge
Amazon announced
Local support
4 commands at this event
Animalistic
Don't know when it is coming they said in a cup
Who knows
But
This is. This means if your
Internet goes out
You could actually still say things like turn on the lights and the lights will go out
This was a huge reason I've actually done with Wink in the past
I don't want to see the first but they were among the first to have localized commands in a hub
So that was key for me
Not that we losing a lot
Take a trip over themselves if they had to use them
I'm pretty sure they
In the dark I don't know
I thought that was
Really noteworthy
I got two questions though
What about the guard service not a question why should I comment
Did I understand correctly you're also going to automate your smart lights when you're not at home
Yes they are so you
You can actually set that up so when you turn on guard it will automate
Your smart lights
Which by the way is a fee
Feature that I had with
Nasty
But it didn't work super well
And I think wink also offers this feature as part of their hubs
An automation
Controls your lights when
But
This is still super awesome.
Because a lot of people don't have a
Exactly the other thing
You're talking about the machine learning models now they've got a couple of them now in these devices
And this is just a general question as
We seem more
AI machine learning push to Edge devices in the homes
Wilda
Current Hardware be able to keep up I mean I'm thinking about it from a memory standpoint from a CPU standpoint Sonora
As our devices get more complex through these algorithmic learning models
We actually need to upgrade in a couple years
I think we probably will
If I took one thing away from this event is
You know your four-year-old at those they actually are getting a lot of
The big difference right now is that
Speakers sound better in the
I'm wondering if maybe we'll get this product iteration and then we'll get
The next one is when
Can you swap so maybe we're looking at a smart speaker lifespan of me
It yours
With enough
Overhead in memory for these
Things I don't know
Considering the prices at the thing that's not crazy I would agree and also you won't have to upgrade you just maybe
Some of the newest features
What was really interesting is how they talked about
What they did on the AI back into shrink
These models
It's not
Worth diving into here
They have given a lot of thought
I'm trying to make sure every
Is close to the edge as possible so you get lots for Stuff
The other thing they have and we didn't talk about this
Is whisper mode
So I love it
If you whisper to your Echo
In the coming weeks
Eco Whisper back
Because you're whispering
I love love love this because I never said this on multiple servers I stay up late everybody to sleep
And when I leave my room my office I will tell one of my assistants shut the light and whoever assistant it is whichever is
It's really loud
Super
Google has actually something similar with the Google home
You have
You can turn it on
In the Google home app
Under devices
You can do a setting called night mode
And then
You choose it from one time to another time
And when you have that
Mute notifications in any boot up sound switch
I don't know if the powers ever gone out
Overnight with your Amazon Echo
She comes and she's like
Hello
Searching for Wi-Fi at everyone said what what just happened
Burglar in the house searching for Wi-Fi
Exactly
So it didn't your LED lights
And it
So those are all really nice things
This is a little more intuitive because it just automatically does it when
Can you whisper as opposed to having to set a setting
But just so you know if you're in the Google verse
This is still
Something that you
So
That was
The Amazon stock
Was so exciting because they
Came out with not just a bunch of devices
But actually an entire way of
Thinking about the Smart Home
Ecosystem that gets us closer to this contextual
Easy world that Kevin and I think we should already be in
So they announced
Some things to make it easier to set up Wi-Fi
They talked about creating
Module called
Mute your Echoes for this
The Alexa
Connecticut which is a development
Ford
Bluetooth and WiFi module
That connects to Amazon
What's interesting there
Is that you
You can actually buy that
Ian
Your cost will be covered
Without initial fee for that module
I just made all your clothes
A bird like you're going to send it video that's probably not going to
Before a lot of like sensors or one-off devices this is a great thing cuz you no longer have to worry about
He's crazy cost every single year with the
Set device
It solves a lot of the business
Problems and what that's going to like even more if you can imagine
More matinee devices
Yes
So this is great
The Amazon ecosystem
Devices
Especially since their support for sensors
So they're really pushing
Forward with
A vision for the smart home and I said this before and I'll say it again that really rivals
Apple did with the smart
I just came out of this feeling like God
Apple
What are you doing man this is the sort of thing that you guys used to be so good at
In
Amazon's really doing so
It gets back to something you said a show or two ago that pretty much they're setting the standard and I just mean the standard for
The products but standards
For how these products work
Yes
And it's going to be awesome
So
Knowing all of this
More devices cheaper devices Whimsical devices like $60 microwave for $30
Would I
Invest still
Ecosystem
So
That was the question
That someone
Is it good question
I am all in on the Google ecosystem for my
Web services soap
Email and all that even
You know sometimes it's
Came to get my
Google Apps account
To do anything with me
I think I'm going to connect all of my devices
Tomato mayonnaise
For the time being
I'd Focus there for the smart
Hamster but I probably key
Cheap T I have the Lenovo smart display finally
I would keep one of those in my house
As a way to Lake
Interact with my
I guess my professional Inc
Computer-based life
If that makes sense
And just have Amazon
Show me my smart home base life
That makes sense that makes sense 710 G7
Siri in my life 503
And it's
It's confusing as all get-out to be talking at three different things in the same room for one thing but it's
This is what we do and there's a reason we do it
I don't think I would commit to any one of them just because of what I
Here with you and so on but if I had to
I'm probably would be leaning to go back
To Madame a
Because I just
The Integrations are into so many more types of products
Yeso
Speaking of Integrations this is a big one
The smart
Home skills API
They update
Play the updated in a way that makes me feel like they are coming after
Device
Data schema
We talked about a lot of show
And that's basically
A universal way for device to say hey this is what I am
This is what I meant
Right now we don't have that we have company
Ocf
Create standards around this
And what we have with Amazon is this smart home skills API
Set allows for
Three different settings
So it has a toggle setting that turns things on or off
Has a range of options that let you set a range that could be a temperature it could be
Oven thermostat temperature
Sound
It has a range
It has a mode option that lets a device maker program a
Text function
So this is where you're going to get like in an oven
Is a baker is it real
In a washing machine
Permanent press
Cotton
Owls
Those kind of specific
And
That actually covers quite a wide range
Things that devices can do
And it's going to be really powerful for developers to have this be
Because
Then you can
Basic reading skill
Easily
And then they also talked about
Natural invocation
And this is very powerful
As well
This is where you're going to be able to ask Madame just do some
Turn on the vacuum
And it's going to understand what the back
Team is based on patterns of
Usage that it seemed
Mystify senior
So this is some of this where it's always going to be learning based on your information
Formation that's happening in your specific home
And it's going to be tied back to that hoe
It's smart contacts its Blossom once we get there
Yeah so
Very exciting stuff
And now
We talked a lot about it
How to cut a donut hole show on
Zip through to another seattle-based company
Microsoft
Because they
Are doing their big event
This week Microsoft
And they have shown off actually things for Cortana that make it seem like
It's just like Amazon's doing the Smart Home
Cortana
And then a lot of industrial support for things like digital twin
Let's talk about how Microsoft is
Making Cortana
I don't know
Turn up from a Halo from Halo perspective which is where they got the name Cortana school but other than that I'm not really
Jazz
But then again I don't work in an Enterprise anymore if I still did
Sure I'd be super psyched over this you know show me our sales figures for last month or even
You know what's the trend of help desk calls over the last six months and Y or whatever what's the big mean root cause
It's just another user interface didn't get it Analytics
Yes and it's called Cortana skills for Enterprise
And this is the first major update to
Improve the way Cortana works
Web Developers
So
Really exciting
And
We'll see how this
Works out
Is a proof-of-concept Microsoft did an IT Help Desk kill for Cortana to help people file tickets
Which
Back in the day when I was in a large cup
Pain in the butt so
Jay
Is it also this will tie into
Microsoft
But they should have to build
Earlier this year where they had like the super intelligent
Cortana powered conference room
Maps physical spaces
Recognize people
Tok notes for you
Ridiculous
Microsoft at
Ignite did talk about
Rodney gets aif
They also
On the industrial iot side
Agri services
So
Azure data box
Set of products
That's going to
Enable
Russian restaurant
Brunetti's which is an orchestration
Orchestrate
Services that run at the edge
And the cloud
So they're going to
Bring two birdies
As well
They're going to
Update
Windows server
And it's going to support some Azure services this is a big
There are some
Devices out there running Windows server
Need to be able to talk
Computing model with gateways and sensors and
Clouds at all
Talk to each other
Microsoft
Is adding
Digital twins
One of the brand new cloud services that Microsoft is going
Offer
On Asher in this is a big deal
Because
The industrial world
Love's
Some digital
ABC has been one of the big
Companies pushing this
Concept but basically
It's a virtual version of any machine
Run it
Sensor data from the physical
Device
You run it against your virtual version of that device and you can use it for predictive maintenance to understand things
Things that are going wrong
It's both a big validation at PTC
Which has been touting this
Yours
And also a necessary component for a lot of Microsoft azure
Industrial
And you can even use this as like make a digital copy of your workspace maybe fit a large office or
Datacenter whatever might be created digital version of it
Duplicated essentially and again
Titan sensor data you could have just things maybe when I just temperatures and see if that affects traffic patterns or
Machinery whatever my paper
Cons of opportunity sir this is a really cool stuff
It is and I actually like the fact that Microsoft is
It's aiming this more at the
Do you say says it's showing off Hair Design War for Enterprise office space which I thought was interesting
Because PTC is all about like
I will borrow your steam trap or your flow meter or is all these crazy
Crazy devices that are very
Where is Microsoft
Hey what's create a virtual version of your office
See what you can do
Can I see why they did that to be honest right at first hand I cannot tell you how much time I would waste
This was a Google anywhere city which was a city block in 15 stories going USA conference room
Wasn't supposed to be occupied but still
Or
Decided to go to the
11th floor cafeteria for burritos
When the line on the fourth floor was like
Nothing it was nobody there right now so I can go up to 11 tonight
Waste for your resources on so many environmental things
So this is really exciting and we are going to find out
More maybe we'll get something from Microsoft to come on the show to talk about what this makes pasta
Because
Okay it's like I'm from Boston all of a sudden
Let's talk about
Some quickness bit Sunday
Whiting's
Switch
They came out with their newest
Hybrid Smartwatch I called a hybrid because it looks like a traditional watch
Perry mechanical
Looking
Regular watch but has a small OLED display in it for your heart rate because there's a heart rate sensor in there you can check
Are sleep patterns in their through a Connected app
It will track your workouts
Just got sensors for all that
GPS you have to have it connected GPS you have to have a phone with you if you going to go running with this thing but
Some people still do that that's fine two hundred bucks killer battery life
Because it's a very small OLED display like a circular display that just had a limited amount of space in art
Backlight on
25 day battery life which is amazing
$200
It's not for me because I want a GPS in a heart rate and everything standalone
Which is why I wear an Apple watch
Tonight full fledge Smartwatch not take calls on it
But for a large number of people this is a perfect
Hybrid device it gives you what you want without
Too many constraints such as you know charging every day and so on or looking like a smartwatch so I like it if you get enough for me
I like what why things is doing
Okay
And I like that you're like it's not full-featured I mean you can't make phone calls on
This is not a feature that I have demanded
I was messing with my walkie-talkie feature yesterday on the Apple watch with my daughter so I'm into that stuff
No III
If I wanted
The stuff they showed off at the Apple event a couple weeks back with fall detection
Play something that I've been trying to
Program into my life
Forever
Using
Amalgamated sensors
East recipes
It pull it all into one and I was very excited but not excited enough to go buy an iPhone
So I understand
Please
Please rest of the world
Get on that okay
Let's talk about
Okay last year
Was purchased by Assa abloy
Maker of
Now it's Yale locks
A credit to work with your August
App
So the August lock is not
Deadbolt
Replacement
It is
Replace it over
And this is
This is great for some people they like it it's less
Install
But
If you're one of those people who feel like way more secure with
Replacement
But you like the August app
Because it works with
Martinson is kind of interesting
You could actually
This feels kind of niche
There's like a homekit module
You could update your
Yale lock
Homekit module that you plug into
With that battery case
And it's going to work
With the August app and
That's kind of nice for a certain segment of the body
Chelation
No doubt about it I mean
Kathy August features like door sensor don't know if the door is locked or unlocked if it's open or closed you know it's
You know dog has to make sense
This
Also desert Choir in very small Wi-Fi Bridge just to get the information from the lock to your network
It's not a
Like a big box of a bridge is more of a gesture
It sits on your outlet somewhere nearby
That exists now for those of you guys who are interested in that
Speaking of homekit
There is a new rachio sprinkler
It is getting homekit support
So
Yay yashow this is
Free if you have the one or two
You're not going to get it
You can tell Stacy doesn't use an iPhone
Population says I'm going home kit for good reason and that's fine
So this is good news
If you're that population
Here's a
Rachio which is
They're Gen 2 I tested their Gen 2 sprinkler and bought it actually for my father-in-law
And it's great he loves it
It's helped him quite a bit
So
Now you can ask Siri
Hey
Turn on my sprinklers
Or stop watering the vegetable garden
And this is $230 the Retro 3s
Expensive newer model
Okay this is just an update because I had written about this and talked about
Twitter
So I have these brilliant
Light switches
I just had someone
Come out and
Replace them for me cuz I had a pre-production unit.
They felt was not
Behaving as well
So we're going back to the drawing board
Mini the things about
I stand by
And they would happen regardless of the hardware it's just the
The criminal light into this thing
So
I'm going to try that out again
And hopefully it will be a better experience
So stay tuned for that probably in another
And now
Let us go to a
Question
From our
Audience
This is a question on the iot podcast hotline which is brought to you
Do not miss you guys
Your chance
Schlage sense smart deadbolt
You can enter to win by calling us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
I'm leaving us a question
You must do this before September 30th at midnight Eastern
To be entered to win
This particular law
And remember starter homes
Start
Show this week's voicemail is from
Brent
Hello this is Brent mehr I'm calling from Utah
I have
A problem with my
Freezer have I
Stand up
Vertical
Freezer that
Kids
Well sometimes leave open
Circus last 10 years I've lost
The contents of it
Three times and we've tried locks but sometimes they get in the way I'd really love something that would alert
Me when
The
Freezer is left open or even perhaps if
Temperature changes within the freezer
Thanks
Okay Brent
This is one of those
This is so easy I can't believe we have to answer question about this
Start at the gate
So
Kevin
You get started
With your solution
All right book
Probably the least expensive solution I can think of is to buy a
Door / window sensor Brands because their battery powered there
Inexpensive
One part goes on the
Frame of the freezer and one goes on the door and basically when the doors open
The center says hey I'm open and you can be notified that the doors open however you don't want to know exactly
Open
Left open
So in order to do that
It's a little more expensive
Traps
What we don't know is if you have a smart home hub
You can easily set
I will alert that says have the sensors been part or the door's been open for more than say 2 or 3 minutes
Send me a notification
So we don't know if you have a hub if you do is pretty easy
If you don't I don't
You know that this is going to work because you're only get me notified that the door open
What clothes you're not going to know
If it left open unless you physically go back and check after you were notified it was open
Yes
Okay so that was one option
And I have some other options
None of them are
But we found lots of
Bluetooth
Sensors that measure
Temperature and a lot of them have
Why are based temperature probe so what you would do is you take
The temperature probe
Plug it into the sensor
You stick the temperature probe inside
The freezer
Can you leave
Temperature
Nothing on the outside
Because you eat the freezer is kind of like it's going to block all signals so he part of this the part with the radio has to be outside
The freezer
Is a giant ferret
How do I have left open
Signal
Then you know
Temperature
This is a $40
Inkbird smart sensor
This is $40
And
Use case
The exception of this is blue toothpaste so you have to be within
Feet are so
So I don't
Love it for this because it's not going to
It can send you alerts
But it's only going to send you alerts when
When you walk with him
You're not going to be able to remotely be away from home and know that the door has been left open for example either
Let you sit pretty
Why is sampling intervals so Lake
Between 10 seconds
I would say for your freezer a 10 minute intervals probably good and will save
Battery life
So that's just
Book If you're looking for sampling
And so that's one option
We did find
And
We don't love this for another reason
We found it lacrosse Mobile Wireless monitoring system
This one comes with a dry probe that should work just 4 in
Inside your freezer
It has its own little Gateway this is a $30 device
Gateway gives you the Wi-Fi
Please and that you need to plug in
But
To get data to your phone after the first 3 months is going to cost you
99 Cent Store
So that's a subscription fee associated with this
Device that space
12 bucks
Which is a lot cheaper than hundreds of dollars of frozen food defrosted
Yes
So
That is an option I have had lacrosse sensors in the past they tended to work for me for about 2 years before dying
So keep that in mind
This is
Particular
Is only 30 bucks
And then we found
The temp stick wireless temperature sensor
$449
Which is pricey as heck
But it's Wi-Fi
Connect to a gateway
You're going to have to be
Changing the batteries on
Quite a bit
But this gives you everything all in
So you can be anywhere at the notified for example the freezer is open so
Option fee on that one right
But it's a big upfront cost
More than this
$30 +
$12
I think it's worth pointing out also that when we went down a big rabbit hole looking for all kinds of different solutions here
I noticed that a lot of the
Manufacturers of
Fridges and freezers are now starting to include sensors for this type of thing such a Samsung NGE for example
So they're in the future
When you do replace the freezer cuz he said it was 10 years old Can I some point it's going to have to get replaced
I would consider looking at one that has a sensor built-in
Yes
What's the magic
All right
So hopefully bread
This helps you
Otherwise
I think you should get rid
We don't really know how did they get past the locks
All right
So
That is a lot we discussed this week
We hope you guys
Enjoy this segment of the show
Please stay tuned
A conversation with
Rayford Smith
Who is with Entergy
A utility that serves 3 million customers as he explains
Holy cow
How they're bringing
That company
2 current digital standard
It's a pretty involved process in
I think it's an interesting interview so stay tuned for that and for a message from our sponsor hey everyone.
Taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is SAS
And I have json man who is the VP of iot at SAS
Here to talk to us
We talked about SAS at the edge
A new iot division
And his partner ecosystem
Let's talk about
Hey I and II.
So which comes first
Iot data
Rai
That's a good question
You seen a lot of ink
Towards both topics
Am I singing though it's
Iot data
Certainly a I in
Capabilities
Analytic evaluation
Associated
With that is critical but the fact is
AI
Routines Alberta
R train
Against data
Anorexic cute
In my opinion
Okidata is required it comes first before you can achieve value
Applied artificial
How does AI in iot
Work together
AI is certainly a path
To incite
Passive value
Decisioning iot infrastructure
On the other hand
Provides
The foundational element
4X
Execution of Iowa
Key principles
What you think about
To first question
The data is critical
But also as you look to the distributed environment in many cases
Just pushing to the edge
The models may be trained in a persistent environment AI models
In there but the execution
The volume
This generator from EX
Execution
Scoring of the models
Self can only be achieved when you have that infrastructure
Ford appointment
We talked about reduce latency
Can be a primary driver
Latency is reduced by pushing his decision and closer to the source
Updated so you can have the best
AI model in the world
But if you don't have the
The ability to apply at
At the right time
Right place
The value
Is quickly
Power companies applying AI to their iot data today
Switching examples across multiple annies
Mysteries usually in cases where the
Requirement is to
SF state of volume
Games that are just outside
One example is in Hi-Tech
Manufacturing what are using video.
Detect effect
At the most granular level all the way down
Pixel levels
Within high definition picture
And it provides the ability to
To do this at scale and generate inside into Gildan
Improve throughput that
You just couldn't do
Human interaction
More required
Awesome json so
Where can we go to find out more about how fast
Just helping customers use AI
In iot
So we have a landing page
Sas.com coyote it's a great starting point
For both industry use cases in horizontal messaging around on their feet
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Today's guest is Reaper Smith with VP of energy technology and Analytics
Entergy
Which is an electricity and gas provider
Million customers
So
Raeford
Let's talk about your journey because you came into this
Two-and-a-half years ago
You describe it is
Right it feels like a monster
Beginning of the Bible right in the beginning it was voided for Maleficent
Overtime in a we had seven days
More like two and a half years of trying to
Come up with
What defining analytic
Coming up with a guiding Prince
Coming up with our roadmap or strategy
And then ultimately now shifting into development end
Appointment of antelope
Okay so he started
You guys from the Dark Ages
You started with nothing
Now you are in a relation
22 people
You help a company
Deliver a 12s
Investment
I'm assuming buying analytics software but maybe there's more to this
So
Let's start
With some of the concrete
Sure
I was just coming up with a common definition of what
Analytics
It's amazing certain terms get used and people
Variation of
What they mean
But we came up with it which is really that analytics are meant to help us
Use data to predict
Create some sort of valuable out
That really been led to
What that's what analytics is
What are the rules of the road for how we should go about doing
And we came up with a series
Guiding principles that informed our development
One being
That we think analytics is synonymous with
Strategy
And as such
Cuz it's this key capability we should naps work
Instead we needed to develop
Those capabilities in house
And because it's that important that relevant
Toonami the growth and direction of Art
Future
The analects wasn't so much about technology
Tencent about
How many weird sounding things I could get in and get the objectives to pay for like Pig
Baidu
Spark and whatever it was really around
Change manager
How do you get
An organization of 13000 people
Already got a hundred plus years
Process
History and everything else on the way they do things
To fundamentally alter
That way of doing business
So how did you do
Pick a project
Pick up
System
You're kind of talking philosophically the lips
So yeah so it's really important so we set about creating an analytics roadmap
Which was our strategy is a three-year strategy for how to act
And fundamentally create that chain
The route map in and of itself the process to create it was the first step in creating the change
We gave it The Guiding principles we gave it
Architectural high-level architecture what we wanted to accomplish
We really executed the change through a whole series of workshops that we
We did it
The first of which was to identify where the value was that we
And more than just Fanta results
Conan just on financial results you
Send it when I called the Grim Reaper affect which
I'm here and I'm using air quotes I'm here to help
And you cut the budget just once and then you're never invited back
And so we knew we needed to get outside of just the narrow or myopic
Benefit
The workshops really helped us do that we would go eat
Speak with the executives and then later we do
For the workshops with
13 * 2
Identify
Pain points
What kind of value they thought they
Create Beyond just the dollars
Sense that process also help us uncover
Talent within our own organization
We as a company didn't think we had if I well we're just going to have to build the organization from
Hiring everyone from the outside there's no one inside the company
Can you walk with you
An example of one of the workshops that what the team did what they were trying to tell you to tackle
Sure sure so. It's important who was in the workshop
So the first workshops we would typically do they were about 2 hours long
And in the workshop we had a purse
Me or someone from the Enterprise analytics area
Meaning we also brought in
Consulting outside support
We wanted to bring him
Someone to facilitate that conversation that kind of been there done that
So that they could help
Guide the conversation
As a neutral third-party
I think it also layer in
Hey I've seen this elsewhere here something
Hangouts you haven't thought of where you
And then of course we also brought it with
Our organization is not
Part of the information technology
Organization where I actually like I said
If analytics is strategies
Strategies
But we did bring it because there a key player in
Getting access
Most of the data standing up
System
Keeping it patched
And then we also started at least the first conversations
2 hour one
Executive Suite to the major organ
That typically the way the process will always start with
What is Analytics
Write just a simple question
Trying to get everybody to bring out their ideas have a conversation around largely to coalesce around that
Forward-looking view up
You want to use Analytics
Freedom Valu black
Predictive
That was usually the first 30 to 45 minutes
And the remainder the conversation was on
High-level paint
Where in your organization
You really see opportunity
Interspersed into that we would give them a state of what is the art of the possible
That was tuned to the area
Supply chain
It was another reason why we brought third party
Military wise
Have a conversation Saved By the way supply chain
Outside of our industry
What's your summer
Interesting things you can do
We'll use that is kind of a way to stir the pot and help create
Interest
We would ask him vaguely high-level questions but where's your data
Where your Key Systems those switches
That's the first
Conversation
We then would go to in-depth conversation
Update full day
Then based on the areas that they identified in that
How long did this process
Within different word
About a 3-month process
We spend another two months after that though harmonizing all the results
We found so we
At the end of the day we created not only a series of use cases
Christmas tree
This is of interest to us
This is the value we think we
Free from it
Here's where the data we think
We need for that is
And here's the rough Bar Association we might want
We have a synthesizer harmonize all that because obviously how one team might make an assumption of Valium
Different than another
We need a time to come
Bring all that stuff together so roughly from
Initiation to about the six-month mark
Is how long it took
To go through the full process
Workshops interviews executive updates and then
Harmonization and ultimately creating this roadmap in terms of where we
Okay so now you have a road map
This when you brought inventors or
Did you have them in beforehand like
What's after the route
Yeah well so there's one key question you have to ask while doing the roadmap that we had to get in
And that is
What kind of way do you want to cross
Another word for towards
The places with the low-hanging fruit or readily available data
Or do you want it
Step back and take a more Enterprise
We call them that no business unit left
Behind strategy
But we went around we surveyed all the senior
With focusing on one or two areas
But that creates the halves
And the Have Nots
And you may be a have
But you're likely going to be a half not are you okay with that
By the way if we do the Haves and Have Nots
We might go a little faster
To start with
But it might create some unintended
It's right because the Have Nots my team up and go well
I really didn't work for me
Alt-right terrible Silo don't want to create silage from the
Heading into a person every one of the leaders
Demon energy said
We want you to go with the Enterprise
Which was really great because it allowed us to take a longer View
And it's far more comprehensive you about how to
Roulette
Architected and ultimately emblem
So when we got the business cases and all the roadmap in the strategy that we
You said okay this is what word
It been created the next
Fertilprep to do which is okay now we have to go pick tools
That conform with our architecture on our strategy
We need to hire
Do we have
Literally knows that
And we have to do this in a very short amount of time because
Company wants to start recognizing benefits as soon as they
So we went down a couple Tracker boats hiring
And
Going out until you shoot a whole bunch of rfps for particular components that we went through
Define nauseous the tools like
Yale tour guide
Are you going to govern your data what are you going to store it in
But also
Some more importantly was
Are you going to enhance the data that you already got
We knew from the very moment that we started that our data wasn't very good
And there was a lot of data we just didn't
And so we knew we had to augment our data as much as we
We had a manager
Relaunch recipes
We Begin the hiring process
And by the end of the year we had selected
Vendors that we thought we really wanted
And we had also begun rnfl pirate we did not finish the hiring though
About
Really up until about the last two weeks
So the me
On the vendor side
What kinds of things
You decide to
So what are they
So I would say that I like to explain things
The two are senior Executives using
Cartoons
RIT infrastructure and our human capital
Spring from the womb and
Work effort something 30 years in our industry
Knowing the ins-and-outs about analytics
And so far everything into four different categories of things using a card
Arthur really
Simple easy to understand we said really there for parts to RL example
The first
Human capital write the driver or the passengers are really important
They're going to tell you where you're going and they're going to steer the car
Second part of it is
The fuel for the car which is your data right
How do you move your data how do you manage your data how do you augment
Governor
That's the second major category
The third was the engine
Consumes the fuel to create the
Does the mechanical energy to move you down the road
It is the inside itself right
I had a meeting with Executives and said I'd like to talk to you about a generalized autoregressive conditional heteroskedasticity
Fastest way to end a meeting right
Beijing
Don't want to talk about that
But you say I'd like to talk about
I'm inside a really cool inside that we did for your area
That resonates far more
I've got to find a way to take the math that you built in the engine
Visualize it and created and put it in a way that
Really helps Executives understand
Just what the hell
In my car exhaust right
It helps you see what the engine produce
But it also helps you monitor what's happening what's going on
And so forth
Key components of what we're doing
And we're going to try and RFP and
Find Partners to helping
Obviously human capital were going to hire
How we did it that's how we went about structuring it
And each of those areas that we also had to be mindful because the company isn't just trying to transform using Analytics
Trying to transform everything
All at once
We are doing our smart meter deployment or Ami deployment going on right now
We are at the same time changing out roughly 70% of our it infrastructure
Adult management
You name it it's all in there and then change out
The same time we are trying to rebuild our infrastructure for Analytics
We're attempting to launch products and services with our customers
Remake and rebuild our grid
Shelley Angela not all this change going on simultaneously
So we had two in that contact we had to also coordinate with all those other teams and go like
NRP for this but we need you all to be part of that RFP process because while you're putting in your things
We have to put in our time we all got to sing Kumbaya
And have one big group hug at the end of this to make sure that we're going in the same direction
So those were all resolved
Credited sent out
Yes absolutely.
So now you
Biot that are thieves out
Starting on YouTube
Where are you and what are your
Shores
You really get a diversity of responses
In or instance we got a whole bunch of results
Anyone tried to do what
You were doing
And our executive became a little worried they were like
We really like what you're doing the world so nervous about it
We had to talk to them through about How We Do lyrics
Re-implement
Risking the process to select even vendors and partners
Which is to say that an alarm strategy was really built around Flex
Ability
Around standards
Around broad industry acceptance not just our own engine
We found that
Taper example
Open source is great
But at the same time I have a CFO I have a
General counsel
Eva CEO and they worry incessantly over the operations of our business
Are compromised in wanting to get the flexibility and the growth in the capability that open source off
Was to buy a license
After all Hadoop is
And itself an open-source capability but
License
Similarly we went with a platform
What size because it really was broadly used
Well beyond
I never really intended just for RN
We knew we could Flex
Really quickly
On any number of problems that are Executives might come up with whether it was a safety
Customer
Audit supply chain nuclear anything they could come up with
If we picked those tools and conform to those prints
And did you also as you were evaluating them
Test how well these things could work together in these
Player's head work together
Correctly
Because
These things have to work together as a system and that could be
Yeah oh yeah could be a huge pain point in Nebraska
That's why
We in the rfps as well as in our roadmap development we spent a lot of time talking
Architecture
And about how those different pieces
Integrate well with each other
We really wanted to make sure that to the extent you're going to pick
One solution
That it work well in an ecosystem and had a proven track record of working well on ecosystem
Studio Luxe year-and-a-half
So what came after that where we ended
Yeah so we started we continue to hire
We started out with hiring five data scientist
3D to Engineers one director for the organization
As well as a data governance manager in an agile
Savory necessary early components
Infamous meeting with our CFO general counsel saying what we've got lots of different ways to prioritize use
This case is here
What do you want to start with
And there at least 8 different ways we came up
Yeah which means if you have a way to prioritize you have no way to prioritize
The end
Customer is our number one issue right now
You really need to work on customers
Go find some easy winds are from the customer
So that's where we started
With our while we were doing all the hiring everything else we've also started to try some of this risk
In that time we prosecuted 19 of our initial 100
42 use case
142 use cases
Gas are really well and what's so funny is
We did after we will start work on the 19 what's really important that we get back
Hell
All the executives
What we've been up to but we kind of went quiet there at wework
Wake of the RFP process if we were picking Solutions Contracting
Tell everybody
I'm afraid that was really meant to go around and talk to all the executives
Here's what you saw
Here's what we've done
Are the results we've gotten
Today
That's r12x return
The good part about the parade that was
What person every executive every leadership team that we talked with reservation was blown away with the results
Gotten so far
Those were primarily all in a customer area everything from food forecasting to
Segmentation and propensity models
Things we could use again and again and again
Providing instant benefits
Company
They were also some that we could use in our future deployments for technology Ami Advanced metering infrastructure
Takes years to deploy
We are ready now with some of those capabilities because we
Filthy early stop
Priortax
We went around to the parade deck
The unintended
Someone into the consequence was that now
All those Executives were so excited by what we had done already they wanted us to work on
Right there feeling like half
Right exactly into that triggered the next round of why we need to start hiring is
We need to go ahead and staff up those capabilities but if your resources come on and shocks
You really need to flex
Capabilities that you bring in from the outside
And so what we've been doing in that process
We have Consulting agreements
Long as we can form with the architecture in the standards of what we've done
To use third parties to come in and
Help us
Manage our workload between your initial hiring to our next level of hiring a smoothie
Capabilities for all these different organization saying
Me too I want some of this stuff also
Until these are things that can be easily codified in
So
Random
People outside the organization
Yasmin use case
Development process from initial idea all the way to hand over
We do not own any of the models at the end of the day that's really important
From a change management perspective because of the results
But if a business owns the model and they own the result and therefore they
Change
Just one of our key drivers
But for us when we think about this
Journey and pain
Getting to where they were ization
Has this innate capability
Are you skis process has a really rigorous.
Tatian process wrapped around it
We also invited a lot of different players we invite in finance
If you want them to document the benefits that are coming
We don't think that keeps us honest and also keep us out of the Grim Reaper business of trying to cut other people's budget
We bring an it because they are critically important that getting the data and getting access
Make sure the infrastructure is up and running the way it ought to
And we do that and of course the business units the customer themselves
They're the domain X
May we bring data science City engineering Adida governance
We use that process Auto to dictate our order in which we govern data upgrade infrastructure Etc
Use cases determine the order
Exciting is probably not the right word but that was really educational that was a very good to dive into something that's so many
Thank you
Thank you appreciate it that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like
Moraiyo to sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot, will see you next week