Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Your co-host Kevin tofel
And we have
A stellar show for you today I am calling in from
My hotel room at Google Cloud next
Which we will talk about briefly and then we'll be
And we will also cover some exciting things like a brand-new SmartThings tracker
Didn't adding Google Assistant support
Google Assistant also taking video calls for the
Yet-to-be-released video screen
Functionality
There's I do
Security flaw in the aisle
Kevin's going to talk a little bit about
Is cloud headache you guys are going to want to
To stay for this
And
We are bringing back our
Is this the worst
Connected idea of the week
Because
Well we found something new
Was pretty bad
You can let us know what you think
Who's there and our guest this week is Elana Fishman
The CEO of wise
Labs and you guys are probably familiar with this because we've talked about the wise cam
She's going to explain how the heck they get those so
So
Before we get into all of this
Let's hear a word from
Our sponsor
A pharaoh
Looking for an iot platform find out why Kenmore and D-Link picked a pharaoh Pharaoh customers have Xperia
As much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market 99% pure support calls antenna
Text higher activation rates plus they can reuse 90% of their work from one project to the next to learn more
Visita Ferro. IO that's a fer
IO
Hook head
Heaven
So I am at
Google this week
Probably just get to your Google
Disclosure out-of-the-way
I'm so glad you mentioned it because I forgot
I am
Freelancing for Google reading some blog posts for them is strictly in their
Romeria has nothing to do with
Ayote
Tuyet also new influencer anything there
And the other thing I want to say is I'm so excited that your Google Cloud next because
Last year when I had it I was working for Google full-time and I had such a blast working at event
I think it's a cool if I could just eat all cloud and let me know if your developer you are really into it I'm sure but it's still some neat stuff coming out
Lots of really good custom
Choosing Google Cloud
Consider worth mentioning for The Internet of Things
For you actually by the way you guys
Chromebooks
Dot-com
So
If you have time for another hobby after IRT come visit
Do you know I think they're easier
Let's talk about Google's news
This week they announced
Kubernetes on
Prim and for all
This is an orchestration layer
It's actually
Turning out to be the orchestration therefore
Iot to tie the Cloud 2
What everyone calls the edge and we can defer
A little bit
The Edge actually is the point is
If you're going to build something
As a developer both places
Today because I
Internet places you mean in the cloud as well as maybe on-premises at your place of business
Premises at your place of business and eventually you want to write things that run in the cloud and on like
Cars
And other computers that are running around like Gateway devices on premise
So it's not just like
Super
Server computer
So Microsoft announced something called cubelets
They're actually virtual Cuba
That allows
Have his orchestration there been both places unless you manage everything
Incoherent
It's a big thing
I'm not going to get too technical with you guys because you're probably like
Stop
I don't know what it is anyway they have them at Thanksgiving we have giblets in
Right I saw your joke
I'm sorry
Okay
So
Google announce kubernetes
On premise which is a step closer to getting these things
Working everywhere
This is an important project
Pay attention
They also announced age TP
To use
Gpus are there tensorflow processors are tensor processors which is their machine
Processors there specially designed ships just for
Machine learning
These are not
Media camera things that run Linux
I'm in the also announced Cloud iot Edge
Which is pretty much the same thing Microsoft
How's their iot Edge software in this is
Again just a way to
Annette
Door
Device with limited computing power
Back to the cloud
So that's what
Now everybody has
Everybody I really just want Google Amazon
Microsoft Google has been a laggard in the iot space
So these announcements really loud
Catch up with things
One more qualifier here in case people have not heard of kubernetes is a container
Solution
So you can not worry about the setting up virtual machines and servers and all that you literally just have a container without a plant
Uninstall Dimmitt on demand
Kubernetes is open source button is doing is they have their gke kubernetes engine
The tie into all of their iot stuff
End
Letter
So I'm not going to
Picture story
Microsoft and Amazon
Go Google and actually last bit we talked
Probably six months ago on this podcast is Google's IRT strategy and I think we've got a better answer that now
You just talked about
Next it's becoming a little more cohesive it's an easier story to tell
Yes
Yay
Okay
No moving on to
Fun and exciting thing
Kevin had a scoop this week
And
Yeah I had to scoop this week
Oh you want to really talk about it sure
I actually for my Chromebook stuff I actually scour the FCC database here in the US because any devices
That emit wireless radio signals are tested by the SEC before they can go on sale and that's how I found about new Chromebooks another device
And I found a new device
Not only that I think is the
First
In the US anyway the first
T consumer device that will use either
Cat M1 or NB iot Networks
Through either Verizon or
AT&T
The device is the Samsung SmartThings tracker it has not been announced during the US so that's where the
Scoop part comes in however
They launched
A
Product that looks exactly the same as the same functionality in Korea back in October and they called that the Samsung
Connect tag
And basically what this device is it
I like a Bluetooth tracker that you might put on your car keys or a backpack or whatever is my pay whatever possession
Have we might carry it around with you even I'll tell you why in a second it's got
Bluetooth GPS
But then it connects
Next to the iot networks imagine
And what that will do is
It will allow you to remotely find these
Devices
Are your possessions with the devices attached you can't do that with say a Tracker or a tile unless you get crowdsource
Information from other users and such
This will be just like a Find My Phone type
The function so I don't know the price yet don't know what the service cost will be a couple bucks a month for sure it also has a button
On it so that you can press the button and send your location to anyone in your contacts and
Smartphone component that many people may not realize
You could use this
Is a way to geofence your home
Close your home your drive close to your home you could tie into SmartThings Hub because it is a SmartThings device have your garage door opener
Turn lights go on soap
Using your phone for the geofencing you could use the Samsung connect tracker based on what I believe is coming
Got it yes and
I actually wouldn't have my SmartThings
The presence detector was one of my favorite items is part of like the little bundle because I put one in my
Husband's car and I used to have him
When she was getting closer
DiGiorno you put that in
Okay and I wasn't stalking him
I just want
I just wanted when he got close enough to get to my house I want to be able to add a light flash
Run downstairs
Who is my
Yeah I never empty the dishwasher and when blood comes home I get yelled at so I like this I did okay
It's B get out of jail
I don't know how much
Will find out
All right
Next
We're going to talk about
I don't know what to call this but I saw two stories this week
When was from Slate and it was talking about it was a guy who would install the ring video doorbell
And she loved it but he found himself
Freaking out because of the notify
Patience
And there were two components to this one is
He didn't realize that he could fine-tune as notifications
II was
He still
After you done that
Still kind of freaked out knowing all this stuff any kind of developed an unhealthy relationship with her
Does ring video doorbell
Maybe less safe in Disney World
The other story
Was
And it talked about
It basically talked about
Trying to piggyback on
This President moved into a house with smart gadgets and had a lot of trouble
Cutting them up and installing them
And then they also had an issue with the nest because
They were trying to program The Nest Thermostat
I don't know how cold do you want to be what time do you want to change
That's a little ironic because the nest actually if you just reset it and live with it for a week it'll figure that out so but
2 things I thought were
We're talking about from the stories one
Smart home devices are still really difficult
There's a lot of questions and information with the setup process
People kind of take for granted
First aid for granite I don't think they should because it is hard when you put these things into try to figure out
I know how many zones does my sprinkler have what type of dirt do I have
No
I mean part as I read that article this late one in particular I thought he was over react
However I get it and I still think he was to a point but less
So now as I think about your average consumer who just says over
The features that are touted are great you can see who's coming up your walkway before you can get there you can have it to a voice conversation
There is benefit there but what comes with that isn't talked about
And
So I sort of get his point that you know he's like this
Too much information
Information overload
I feel like the house is wearing Google Glass he said
I sorta
Get that now
It comes back to planning what you want you can just go out and buy a product
Without planning
Because you need to understand what it's going to do when it's
Going to do that you like
What's going to do it you don't like what kind of information is going to capture
And you need to fine-tune your settings I think a lot of his beefs could have been handled better in terms of
The notification center
So you're right though it is still complicated
It's a long way of saying
And there are
Like my husband
How to Fitbit and he took it off because it's dead into like certain the rosies he had he was like I don't like it it's not making me healthier
More focused on this thing
I understand that I think also as he gets older he's going to find his child has a baby
Gets older he's going to have an unintended side-effect of when I'm traveling I actually love check it out by video doorbell because
My daughter Whitney
See her everyday when she left
So that was just a nice thing that
And then also
When she leaves stuff at school
We can always check the video doorbell evidence
Wearing a jacket when you came home
So
Yeah I think if your
Type of person who wants that
Connection to your property in your family and your pets in Saint Beast
Obviously there's a lot of great devices that can do that
If you're the type of person who says I get too many notifications on my phone today and I don't even have Smart Home devices if you suffer from it
Information overload
You may want to think twice about
Really invested in some of these products
Yes
Speaking of doorbells
Which is best for you guys when is Kevin swapped out his doorbell
You swapped out your ring
I did
I did I have been having some issues with the ring doorbell and turn
Is connectivity and I couldn't even do a hard reset for some reason the kids would never get me through to the setup process to
Find my wireless network
And
I suspected
Probably
Firmware or Hardware issue at this point in the reason I say that is
Because I recently purchased a nest by Yale lock
Lock so I decided to let's go with a nest doorbell to replace the ring
Bring a buddy who's installed and it is video doorbells if you have a regular old chime you know you have like little jumper cables
To install in the chime itself
And I did that with the ring and everything was working for a while then it stopped working
Hello comes with the same type of
Connections and let you know what
I bet you
It's pretty much the same from an electric
Circuit standpoint
Pulling out the doorbell itself the ring doorbell putting in the nest hello
I went through the setup process and it does work so I didn't have to go into the time so
Text a good thing people want to swap doorbells
Probably don't have to get into your old chime again
Yeah
The other thing is
It went right like I said through the setup process flawlessly ATS working 100% like no issues whatsoever so
Again I think I probably have
Battering units
Probably should have
Complain about it
Send it back but
I don't know either
Starting to go all nest in that regard
Hey
So final bit of doorbell
This is
Arlo is going to add a doorbell to it
Lineup of products
The timing on that is certain but
It's not a video.
Fedora Wireless
You just push it and it notifies you
Your phone
Talk to the person
Are you on your
Ankle tie it into the existing Arlo video products
That's why it can be battery powered off a two-way batteries for
Two double a batteries for
Yeah I remember we had a call or question about video doorbells that were battery-powered and
The issue is the video component
And that's what's gone from this particular device in that way they can run on those you said to batteries
Spray year you can't do that with video we just can't and that's why they're typically wired so
I see why this might appeal to a
Swap
People but
Not a very large swath not homeowners
I mean
A lot of people
Videos
So I don't know but there's like the guide
So
Okay
Speaking of getting uncomfortable
Let's talk about the latest security flaw
Yeah yeah and the Bluetooth Sig is already spoken up about it most of the coverage that I read about
Thought this was really about
Bluetooth devices such as your phones and things
I think there's actually IRT component because there are blue toothpaste iot devices so that's the only reason I bring this
Because it has to do with the
Bluetooth standard simple secure pairing process and Bluetooth LE secure connections pairing process
Entirety devices can use those
It basically
Has to do with the key pairs in the security
Part of the pairing process
And the only way if
This was an iot device repair
The only way somebody could
Possibly intercept and inject malicious code
They have to be in range
Your devices as you are Perry
So you know any time you're going to pair Bluetooth devices just make sure Nobody's around for 350 I guess at the other the best I can say
Try to avoid that guy walking
It's always
And see if you had a video doorbell you know where it was but that's a whole nother issue
Basically Microsoft said their devices are not affected Google hasn't said any about Android based devices not Center
Because there are a few I have two devices that are android-based but Apple broadcom Intel have all deployed fixes for the bugs
And Qualcomm has as well
I don't have a list of devices on the IRT side that have been affected because nobody has put that together but I just thought I'd throw it out there
All right
About
One didn't his attitude
Google Assistant support
Smart Home Products
So
Sign up with Vivint are giving every new customer
Two Google home mini devices now
And also they are adding support
For The Nest Thermostat
E and Google Wi-Fi
Yeah okay
Google Assistant can now start video calls
Duo
Weather
I could really get it
Of my hundreds of contacts I think
Six or seven of them
Wow
Wow that's pretty good
You know cuz I'm used to help with
I did dog food when I'm sick Google but haven't used it since
This is phone Centric right now it's
You can then use your phone with Google Assistant simulator Android phone
USAA
When I can say it but hey G
No call so-and-so on Duo
And hopefully won't say on who I place the call
Okay
Did you go I think we have expanded now yes I'm sorry
Maybe that's why people top music hits
What it is
Regardless so for video calling you can use Duo yet
It's only for phones right now
I think of this could be a precursor to Google home devices with screens maybe that
Smart
Display that we saw at CES for example
601 from Lenovo
Is take my money
But even like my Nvidia Shield has Google Assistant built-in and is obviously connected to a TV because it's an Android TV
Set up box
So if there was a video camera that I could be adding to the Nvidia boom I can do it that way as well there's lots of possibilities
Don't get too excited yet cuz it's really just for phones at the MoMA
And it's doing
Something got to
Moving right along
Let's talk about
Your cloud
Xperia
I'm very curious
About acting
Voicemail
Which we already did once we originally started on a Raspberry Pi and we've had some issues because
Is the dog likes to yank on the power cord and when I happens there is no iron
Voicemail
So I moved everything up to Google Cloud
It was
Pretty easy
And I didn't under the free tier but unfortunately one of the services it's using is not free
So we look
At AWS
And I spent
At least
Four times as much time
Getting it to run on AWS
The whole user experience was
So much more challenging to me
And you know I'm not a developer by trade I don't have any formal training this is me hacking way tinkering and figuring things out soon
Maybe it's me I will say that
But at least with Google I could actually write code in the cloud I want to hear through their Cloud9 editor but here I had to do it
Locally and put it all up and I had to even send it all up through
A terminal
Command line interface
Any before can use that I had to install the command line interface to a Linux
Turn it all on my Chrome but it was just
So many steps
And in the end even though I got it working it failed after a day
Now that could be the way I implemented I will say that I'm not cutting AWS on this one
And the weird thing is like with Google you sign out of your terminal at your service still runs here through the command line terminal when I killed
My connection
The service just stop so I need
To figure out how to make a keep running and all that but
I'm so fed up with it
That it's like I almost don't want to figure it out
Cloud headache doesn't describe a time I spent so many hours and
Just got
So
Frustrated
So if you have help for Kevin
I'm sure he would welcome to us
Send Advil
This is just
I thought it was an experience guy's perspective
The stuff
You know you may be an expert in AWS
I'm trying to convert over to Google
Everything speaks to how
Easier it is to
From one to the other so we're not taking a lot
People especially since our audience likes to
Do this word
Alright hey
You want to talk about
Worst iot
The idea of the week
I almost don't have to reading what it was
But yes we should because everyone should share in our misery unless there's a few people who want Bluetooth LE
Jeans from Tommy Hilfiger
Yes
This week
Today
Wednesday Tommy
I don't even know
Pink slacks
They actually announced the
Tommy jeans
Explorer
Which are jeans with a Bluetooth
Low-energy chip in them
And they are
I don't know how to explain
You activated
And the app
Basically
Talk to your jeans in your phone
You don't have to wear your pear
You get points based on how often
One-of-a-kind rewards and experiences this basically
Buy some jeans with a chip in it so we can
That's exactly what it is because at the tail end of this they try and sell it
Take me to tell you what is marketing plan
If they say the integrated technology in the product allows for brand engagement and interaction Beyond tradition
Because I got to finish this one this one made me laugh
True Rewards experiences an interactive hotspots located across the country so you got to go certain places
The app brings users together creating a community of high engaged micro brand ambassador
Yeah so this is
Rebecca Minkoff who makes
Accessories
She actually herbrand actually did one of these
And I thought it was stupid when you suck these on purses although there was I think
Tracking
Yeah this
This is not what you
However if you are out there to do
You want this
Please share with us
Why
Interconnected hoodies as well
Those cost a hundred bucks
Inogen cost
So
You'd have to pay me a hundred twenty bucks and is his key
You have to create a VR apps like
Pokemon go where I can walk around New York City with my jeans and look
VR to see who else is wearing Tommy jeans
And
Tagging to get points
Cuz that would be fun but other than that now
Yeah they do have a Tommy
Sport duffel bag
Still no
It doesn't mention in the duffle bag
Bluetooth
Which I think is actually kind of a waste
Yeah maybe have it right there somebody steals your duffle bag gets 30 feet away your tummy app should tell you
Right
You should integrate with
Something else where
Tatami tile
This is
In our opinion
A silly stupid idea
Like I buy a lot of
Connected things in
But if you do let us know
You can actually
Watch this which is
Conical
Waterproof protection in there any smart clothing would have that I mean I've learned some more
Vests and socks and things and just throw up
There's usually up
Yeah but there's a maybe maybe Tommy didn't think about that part too well we don't know
Okay
Silly ideas
Of the week
Let's now go to our voicemail for this week for the iot podcast listener hotline
Hotline is brought to you by Schlage
And
For our listeners
People who leave messages you can have a chance to win a Schlage sense
Smart deadbolt
And Wi-Fi
Soda enter to win
You just need to give us a call at 5 1/2
Leave us a question
At the end of this month
Draw winner
Midnight
YouTube
Here this week
Actually listen to your podcast recent
Stumbled upon
My question is
Why doesn't
Every
Sparkle
Accessory manufacturer looks like
Or any other brain
Why don't y'all just work with Alexa
Why is there
Is it more than just
Hello Google vs Alexa
Like I said
Extension
Why are there different
Protocols
Lexi way
Why wouldn't everything
Can you work with Alexa right out the box
Or maybe just work with Google
Mark good good question
Yes excellent question
And we tend to take it for granted the people know about this but
That's a dumb thing on our behalf because
Why would you want to know this much about the intern
Show Kevin
Bricktown
The issues here
Yeah there's a couple of questions and this one is more opinion than anything and you can chime in if you disagree with
So why doesn't every smart home device makers
Work with matinee or
Google
Dothan salon
I do think there is
I will look at your device maker at market share who's got
More speakers out there who do you want to partner with
I don't think
I believe that most of the device makers want to work with everything as much as possible
Apple certainly limits that
Because device makers have to make
A homekit version of a device as well as I don't get version it would work with
Mad at me or Google home etcetera so
I think that's part of it I don't think there's anything nefarious about
Choosing one over the other if your device maker but that's just my take on the first part I
I don't know if you agree
You're right Madam is the most popular but it's not the only one
I'm so later when we do our interview with the
That one first because
By golly
That's whatever
Get into the fair question
Which is what is
It sounds almost like what is Z-Wave why is he wave
That is a function of
Those are older Sanders
They've been around
Everyone wants to be the standard in the
We haven't actually come
With one that's going to stick so far
And so you still need those and it's partially because
The smart digital assistants
For the most part
They don't have the radios needed
They're just actually a voice in Her
And it actually takes a lot
To get new device
So both Google and Amazon have
Established
Frameworks
Now for things like thermostats and lights that say
Hey
If you make a light bulb you just use that framework in
Everything's very easy but if you make something like an oven or kitchen faucet you actually have to develop that framework
With Google in Amazon
To start
Mykonos things easy
That I should gets back to homekit
It is actually easier and requires less
Hardware on the Hub side because Apple chose not to use any of those other particles they only use what's
Readily available
Heating WiFi and Bluetooth
In which case
Apple iOS devices
Does radios by default phones tablets the Apple TV
Homepod
That's why they can be Apple's homekit hub
When you start introducing Z-Wave products
Zigbee products
Get away from Wi-Fi and Bluetooth are good reasons to use those radio protocols they might be one of them had Mesh networking
Extend the range of your devices
You need a hub to manage that
Radio chatter because the Google home doesn't have that radio inside so it doesn't understand anything
Take me to go back to a hub and get that information now there is Amazon does have a hub it's the Echo Plus I believe
It is and it has zigbee
Seaway band
Not all zigbee devices actually work
So
And that gets into a d
You are right
Don't want this to be simple and easy
And you shouldn't have to learn all this
And
Great answer
But it is
Hey
I think we've done a pretty good job.
Accepting the news of the week
Kevin
Now
Hear word from our sponsor but all of you guys
Stay tuned
To hear
An interview with Elana Fishman who's the CEO of wyze labs
You talk to us about
Wyze cameras
A bunch of questions about security and privacy you guys have been asking for quite some time
Before we come to Atlanta let's take a word from our sponsor
Switch sponsor is the Smart Kitchen Summit Global event series and Community Focus
The future of food
Cooking in the kitchen
It's announcing its
Spore thaniel North America
The flagship event
Seattle washing
On October 8th and 9th
At the world-renowned Benaroya
This year the smart Kitchen Summit is going to explore
Technology is transforming the meal Journey from food growing
And production all the way to the
Consumer plate
2 days of speaking sessions Fireside
Conversations
Product demonstrations and more if you are interested you can take 25%
Off of your tickets with the
Code
Stacy
At smart Kitchen Summit.
Tom
Stacey Stacey
I know
I don't know why it's
If you are at all interested in the future of food or anything like that
You should definitely come to this
I will be
There and
Now on to our guest
Elana Fishman
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
Is a lot of fishmen
Who is the CEO and co-founder at Weis
Labs which as you guys probably ask
They're the makers of the wyze camera and the wyze pan Cam that we
I so excited about it
So high a lot of how you doing
Awesome alright
We're just going to go right into the big question
Which is
You guys are selling a really highly capable camera
For not a lot
Of money it feels like
Someone's got to throw away
Pull the rug right out from under us and do something crazy with this
How are you managing to sell a
$20
HD camera or a $30
Can camera
Yes so that is a topic
Question that we
Ultimately comes from
Core belief in what way
Starting this
High quality
Awesome technology products
Radar products
Things from
Efficiencies on a supply chain
To our sales channels
Customer
The porch and word-of-mouth
People telling people about our product
Parkour proponents of RC
Esl at the very lowest pop
Apple price
Because we believe that certain powers
You can do so much more when it camera cost
22 $30
You can buy five of them and play with them and do a lot of really
Creative things in
Court of what we're trying to do
So I have to ask
Do you actually make money on these things are you just
Venture-backed startup that's like
Seed round last year
Break even
So we are not this is not
Sword
Future on subscription
Are cameras come with free cloud storage and we are committed to doing that
We're not looking for other revenue streams
Okay so how do you achieve
Break even
Such
Incredibly low prices let's talk about
Manufacturing
How you came across
I hear building a business
Sure so we have an amazing man
Partner that we partner with end
One of the things we will look for as the ability to produce
So when we can
Scale
Recognized as cost efficiencies
You sold over 500000
Bring the pricing down
Consumers
Holy cow 500000 of these things
That is
Amazing
Are people buying
Five or six or they bite
It's a lot of them
Sure so a lot of people buy one too
To start we see a lot of
People that don't really believe 4:20
$30 in
And then they come back
So are our average user has more than one camera a lot of people start with
Video is so expensive to host in the cloud I've seen a lot of
Startups offer
7 days or 14 days
Storage but then they're like holy cow
This is way too much money we have to charge
So how are you guys
Making that work
Because that is an ongoing cost
Associated with
Every camera
Yeah and that's something that we price into r
Pricing so it was something that we forecasted in and accounted for from the beginning
How did you get the
Experience or how do you know
How accurate were your forecast
Cast I guess is what I'm wondering
Perspective
People
Obviously
I try to think about
Then give me the reality and they're like in Ark
Text well for a
Any number
Yeah
Sure
It's the one piece of it is
Cher
Local storage options with
The Cloud app
Adoption wolver
Record a 12-second clip
When the camera detects motion or sound
Search for local storage to be able to get continuous recording or longer Clips when there is
People
SD card for local storage if they want more that longer
More storage time
Cloud storage
To those 12
Continuous
Recording all the way to an SD card
Yeah so you insert a microSD card in any of our cameras and there's two options
You can either send it to continuous record so it'll record 24/7
With a 32 gig card can get about two to three days
Footage automatically replace
What's the oldest
Only record when there's an event
So the camera work words in 1 minute increments
Reviews about 1 minute increment and if there is
It saves it
If there isn't
It doesn't for your customers
What percentage error using S
So we see about half of our customers will a democracy
SD card
What are your customers doing with this is it mostly security or they watching their dogs
Do you have a sense of that
Yeah we engaged
Customers pretty regularly and we have a very robust
Community vet
Just in case
Are firmware or are at
Also Alpha test
Testing new products
That we're working on
We get a lot of visibility and I would say
There's a fair number of people that are looking for that traditional stuff
Security or keeping an eye on their house
Create
Size of the price point brats
People will set them up to watch there
3D printer and watch the progress Theron
For errors during printing
Or put it in the crawl space
Maybe just stick it in their garage to be able to
Please check if I remembered
Close the garage
Morning people using in a lot of
Creative ways
We had one user
Actually set it up in the nursery
Actually brought them to
Monitor the breathing
His infant child
Based on the
Feed from our camera
That's a lot of
People like to Tinker we have a very
And I find that interesting because I mean yes
The price point
I'm totally like
Why wouldn't you just buy
$30
But it also seems like
A very mainstream
Thanks for someone who looks at a nest cam inside
Like that's $200 and I'm not really sure I need a camera
So what is your audience
What is the makeup
What percentage is
Like more mainstream purses
People who are crazy
Bret whissel mix
It's a challenge for us
To be able to make a product that Appeals
I think at lunch it was very much
Tinkerer community
We saw this is
Really cool products
How hard it was for us
To deliver a product
With the specs
Teachers are cameras have
At the price that we are
People were very much I think in that
Continue to engage
Like I was saying on the beta in the product development
But as the product
Places like Amazon and website
We started to get more people that worries
Sisterly
Community are just a more mainstream
Person looking for a baby monitor
Or a way to check
And so making sure that
Easy and the US
The simple for people that have never used before
Is a big part of what we
We do we think about
Got it
Really easy
I did appreciate
So let's go back to the
$20
When we talked
Probably
Not a year ago maybe
I don't remember when this
But after it initially launched
You talked about you guys are from Amazon
And kind of the founding ethos
And how
You guys envisioned
The future of the smartphone
Can you talk a little bit about that
Sure yes of the
Four of us who founded wise Matt while we're working at Amazon
Very close ties
Believe in that same ethos of
Customer-centric
Experience
Everything that we
Is centered around feedback from
Are users and continuing to improve
Experience and so
You're at lunch we had a
Pretty simple
Camera with focus on a camera
And worked
Cameron more and more valuable
Overtime
The listening to our user as finding out what
Features they want
Find firmware updates
Our biggest announcement was last week
Set Alexa certification
Camera
It was especially challenging for us
Because we did have limitations from a hardware
Because of the price we don't have
Robust internal
Components
Extra hard to get that
Certification and make it work with our Hardware
Okay and then the first one to Jen when it does
Upgraded some of the internal components between
2 Gentoo
Or that planet
Features like Alexa
Because gen 1 components
Didn't support it
So we did not increase the price for a customer is it
Price for our cameras even though we moved
Json better internal components to
Plan for the future
And yet you're still break-even how did that happen
Supply chain side and given the volume that we were able to secure a component
Price that worked for us
And do you guys design the camera or did you find someone who made a really good camera
Opponents at a low cost
How did that work
Yes at the manufacturing partner that we work with sdp
Experience making cameras and so you will actually
Other cameras that have a similar industrial design to ferment
External pressure
Respective look the same as ours
So we license the industrial design the overall
Outside
Customize the internal components
Android our own firmware and software
To customize
Cameras for ru sinforoso
While the camera may look the same as
Border cameras out there
It's not compatible and it's a completely different
My camera
From an internal
And this is a Chinese manufacturer
Piss
Okay cuz a lot of people in there
Can't believe it's so cheap effort have looked at like their packets and where those go and they noticed that some of them go to
China and they were a little concerned about that
Do you want to talk about
Why that might be
We did see some comments from customers of this is early feedback.
I just are two pieces of this so one piece
Peer-to-peer connection that's made between the phone and the camera
And we using
Actual service from that it was
The commercial service from a
Pretty standard company that does that
Rivers all over the world
So we were just using never server happened
At the time
Customer was calling up
So we
Went back to that service provider
She worked with them to restrict
Our traffic
To us server
So far cameras
And then you guys do all the software here and there hosted here
Correct
Yes it's all
Nawsa
Weird
Let's go back to the integration with
Anime
I know that a lot of your customers were asked
That's so
I'm assuming that's why you went first but are you looking for new partners or you going to do this with other
Vendors as well
This was
Based on customer
D-backs we put out a surveys on a number of different areas asking customers what kind of integration
State wanted
And so
Madam
Top requested that was the first one we started working on
We did actually integrate with if
TT first
That was our first integration that we announce
About a month ago
And we will continue to look at other options again
It'll be based on what
Customers are off
Asking for
And how does that affect
Your cost as you start thinking about going for it
Madam
Is there a limit
There definitely are cost associated with
With those
Cost benefit analysis
So
There's a cost associated with it but it also
Opens us up to
Just so many more users and makes our products
So much more you
Useful to Arco
Sides of that and we make a business decision
Ultimately were looking to provide the best
Restaurants to our users because
Ultimately
Bring more people into the Paw
As we scale we can sense
Poor tire cost with other
Integrations
It is the cool to be talked about providing low-cost products and doing a really awesome job at the software and
Cervicide is the coldest just be a camera company or you going to add more stuff more features
Yeah sure and I do want to be clear that
Why we offer
You're awesome prices are goals not to
To be the low cost
Option and that's not we hope that's not white
Camera is our goal is always to make an awesome
Camera
The fact that only cost $20
Is an added
Are cameras
Perform peer-to-peer spot
I would say all of the mainstream camera
Lights out there
So why is the nest
10 times more expensive
Good question for NASA
I would look at
They have a very different distribution model so when you're in large retail stores there's a
Chrysler profit that goes to that retail Channel there is
Profitability of the company itself
There's marketing branding
Sea lard
Corporate sponsorships
Large celebrity sponsorship
Those are things
We pay for his customers and we don't think our
Customers want to pay for all of that out really just focus on what is the cost
Making an awesome product
And so
Okay sorry
Now you can go back to
To telling me
What you guys
Teachers and continue to improve our
Testing products
It support them overtime
We are looking at other cameras as well so
I don't think the secret that a lot of our customers ask for
For an outdoor camera
So that is something that
We have on our radar it's
Yeah that's a challenging thing to do so it will take a
That is something we have
Topper
Concrete
Share or announce
We do hope to go beyond cameras
Awesome in final question for you
Let's talk about
Security and privacy
Because he's our big issues
With cameras
So what kind of security steps are you guys
Is taking both to encourage users to behave better and then also on your end
And to make sure
Yes definitely
Security and safety is
Top priority for us incredibly in
The huge responsibility for us
When customers bring a camera of ours into their home and
Take that
Paramount
So we
Stuck on the security side
The AWS servers all of this
Connections are made
Bhcc
GPS
For the alert videos
We use symmetric and asymmetric
Consistent hashing and some other
Things on the back end
Make sure that our user information is to
Secure and can't be
Stolen
And then what about privacy
What is your philosophy
Sofia round
Customer data
Yeah
Of course
Thinking about that as
Oliver
LifeStream connections are done via UPS
Peer-to-peer connection between the
Users phone and the camera so
Has no visibility into that
For all of the
Alert videos that are stored in the cloud
Those are directly from the cloud to
Users and wise
The individual videos of r
And also to give our users more control over their private
Jesse we really focus on
Features within the app
To be able to turn off
The camera for for example turn off sound in the recording of videos
So
Our recent app
Update we actually added
Turn on and off the camera
And with Integrations with
You can actually use geolocation I use the location of your phone
To control the on-off
Your camera so that you can turn it off when you're at home
According that's awesome
Wow you're listening
China corporate. As much as
Excellent alright well a lot of thanks so much for
For coming on the show
Thanks so much for having me that's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy on
Coyote
Will see you next week