Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Omad your co-host
Kevin tofel
We got a great show for you today we're going to kick it off
With Apple news
Free to talk about a Bluetooth vulnerability
Free to talk about Chamberlain
Making some changes to its subscription plans
We're taking a look at the Tesla Crash from last year in discussing how we should engage with autonomous
Vehicles and other devices
You got a little bit on a startup
From Jesse Robbins
And some other news bits
Plus we've got our guest this week who is David Martin of power Ledger he's going to be talking about using the block
Chain for distributed energy
And we got a question from one of our listeners about
Security
Less
Fort Rock is one of our sponsors talking about connected
Cars
And now
Let's go to another one of our sponsors Shively did you know that over half of companies who build their own soul
Solutions to connect and manage their iot products say they never do it again
Xiphoid offers everything you need to launch and scale your connect
New product business including tools to manage devices and users
White label mobile apps and business Integrations to make sure your data is actionable
Don't let the technology Sidetrack you from reaching your iot business tools let's Lively take care of the iot
So you can take care of your business this is ivory.com
That's x i
Belly
. com for more information
Already Kevin did you watch the
Apple
Chino products lunch newsreels / press conference
The Extravaganza yes I did a whole two hours of it which we're not going to discuss in detail a lot
What they talk about
Partly because they didn't talk at all about
Homekit not much about Siri the dimensional homepod that's coming out
Is there assistant with speaker so there isn't
With a lot of iron T stuff I came out of that
True I'm wondering
Do you think
So you've watched
Long time
Longer than
So do you think the lack of
Any message in your own home kit or homepod is indicative of any like lateness for the product which is supposed to be
December
I personally think they've had a continued
Lateness for a lot of their
Homekit + Smart Home
Efforts quite honestly this is so I'm not surprised
I really did it
Specs that serious selfie would show off how much better it's gotten
That was what I was
Exactly exactly so they didn't do that
Instead it focused on the traditional products app
Apple TV iPhones and Apple watch
So yeah maybe the
Apple homepod event
Later in the year and that's when I say look how great Siri is for this device and all your other devices
I don't know
We'll wait and see
We don't have anything today
But I was surprised
We talked about whereabouts
Especially
With Kevin tofel Runner extraordinaire on the show so
Let's talk about the Apple watch
Which ticket
Big
Did did basically the biggest feature that they're adding is
As rumored in LTE radio
And
I'm actually considering on this is crazy cuz I'm not
Big I'm paying for additional
Pictures and such that they don't use that much but
I'm actually think about buying or upgrading my Apple Watch 2 to an Apple Watch 3 with cellular
I believe it has about $79 to the cost just for that radio edition and then of course it's the service
That's really got me kind of hung up because I was hoping to be like five bucks a month at most
Unfortunately it looks like all the carriers are going to at least in the US are going to
Offer
Three months of free service to try it and then it will be $10 per month
Going forward
And the thing is if we use the same phone number as you were Apple phone which is convenient
That's great but there's color issues with battery life
We can talk about that in a second
+ 2
Is it really worth adding an LTE option for $10 a month on someone's going to use such little data and
They charge $10 a month at a tablet where with the big screen you can use gobs of data
Disparity that I'm not
Comfortable with self
That's cuz you
Now most people in this is what
Cellular carrier
Counting on
These look like
Oh
Look I have always-on access to music and whatever on my watch
I have Wi-Fi
But I don't have my phone with
Right at work
$10
Most people say no
I really do
I don't know we'll have to see it meaning
It's a personal choice obviously
Because the question is are you doing something that
You need your phone with you or you can leave it behind in my particular use case I run everyday
And I also now I write out small scooter motorcycle type device and having my phone with me of course in emergencies important
But
If I can have the added convenience of leaving the pain behind if
I'm in an emergency situation and
Make a call from iWatch
That's handy I'm out by myself in all of these cases
So
Well that's a good
Until what we should talk about battery life cuz I
I think that's a big issue but I've also
Thinking about let's take it a little bit further
Imagine like a nearpod world
Phone is essentially on your wrist not need your phone then
For very
All when you're just going out
Casually not mean right if you're going to be out
For a while
Browse the internet but if you're just
Suddenly becomes kind of like this is the next version
At the computer in your hand maybe it's a computer and
Tristan
It's kind of compelling
Yeah it is kind of compelling they also in this
Kind of coincides
Because you now have connectivity
You can
And I'm surprised you're doing this because of battery life you can stream songs
Directly from Apple music
So they're saying hey you got 49 songs on your wrist now you can obviously take and receive calls and messages get notifications
Is that I don't care about what I'm running
But interesting
Siri will work
End
She can now talk
As opposed to today's Apple watches you have to look at the screen
So with the connectivity and the boosted speaker
You can actually interact with Siri to ask questions get directions
And so on without having your phone
So $10 a month
I don't know I'm actually thinking about it that prefer it was five
Included
There's a lot of these cases
I know
Stock. The battery
How far can you
You running
Well I'll be okay so
Overall
Annapolis testing they say you can pretty much get 18 hours
On a charge and they base that on 4 hours of an LTE Connection in 14 hours connect to your phone via Bluetooth
They even say it's you know it works out to like 90 notifications 90 time checks 45 minutes of Athens in a 30-minute
Workout with music
I Ran 2 hours on Sunday morning
Just a GPS and my heart rate
So I need
Battery life and I usually listen to music
So again
I need battery life
I think 18 hours in combination
It's fine
You're gonna have to charge it every night
That's fine
Using the LTE connection to tok
You can do that for about one hour on the watch and then your battery is dead
Which I mean
No one's going to have
Like a heartfelt conversation
I could be
It's a secondary phone device in my opinion so I agree with you you know that I have to make a phone call
My family is call me in an emergency when I'm out on the roads it's going to be less than a five-minute call so I'm fine with that I just want to
Should be aware
If you think you just leave it from behind all day or leave it at home and use this
Watch as your phone all day
Probably not going to work
All right
Well so we don't know if Kevin's going to buy an Apple Watch but he seems to be leaning towards it
I assume you sell your old one on eBay
Not eBay but you also assure
Alright let's talk about
Nasty new security vulnerability
Discovered
This week actually
I think was it this week
Last week I believe it was this week
Okay Blue Barn not to be confused with Bluebeard the murderous pirate
I believe
Automatic this is a security flaw that
Books at people's Bluetooth connections and if
Can connect to it it will take over your device in some cases or it will use it for
A man-in-the-middle attack
No
Bueno
And
A lot of devices are still four more
Going to talk to us about how many
Yeah actually to just put this in perspective because this
Effects Bluetooth devices
This is not just like
A one-off
Device type where we talk
Before about light connected DVRs and security cameras this is like anything with Bluetooth
Which is
Mind when you think of the scope of devices
Spell potentially
So we should say this was found that April and released to various companies so that they can patch it and some have his
We were just going to say
Several Android devices iPhones already been patched Windows devices Linux devices
But we have to keep in mind that
Not all of those devices when I think of these as when your phones and tablets are running Android not all them are going to get up to
Because there's a lot of older phones anymore but
.0 and up
So that's good if you're an older phone there could be issue
Samsung Galaxy LG watch pumpkin car audio on Android
These are all Impact
Active devices
Apple's not immune to this
They have patched it
And the nice thing is with Apple
Roughly 89% of those devices
Consumers upgrade the software when they get a security update notes
Much less fragmented
There's not as many device types
So that examples in a better spot here then say OK Google or another device maker
Question is what happens to
Iot devices in the house like Bluetooth locks and such
Where we typically don't update the software or it's not made available to us these updates from the manufacturer
Well I was going to say
Here's yes
I imagine that if your Bluetooth lock maker you were going to be on this at least at the public release maybe you didn't get a call back in a
April because
That's another thing if you're sick
Security firm
You know you can't notify
Right if you're going to try to do something behind the scenes in
Proactively
You can get the big guys but you can't call every Bluetooth
April distinctly I agree with you but all of those devices should be registered through the Bluetooth Sig and I wonder if they should have coordinate
Maybe they do I do not know
That's an interesting
So I was going to say that Linux is also a
Assassins
And they
Talk about the most commercial and super int
Two platforms
Linux is tizen Samsung operating system
This is going to affect your Samsung
The gear S3 smartwatch
You're smart TVs and your smart refrigerator
And this is where it gets interesting to me
Because
Samsung
Will probably push out
But is anyone who sat there and wanted to watch TV turns on their television and
Update now or later you're like
I got my popcorn ready
Later
Later becomes never
Exactly what I wanted even think about a fridge because like I have had fridges in my home that I've owned for 10
Even 11 years and I don't know if Samsung
Patch field
Apollo information to maybe
Give an indication if they will
Hi I just noticed in the report that are missed the company that actually found this
They share details on who they contacted
And what the response was
So good was contacting April and
They have updated as of September 4th
Microsoft also in April and
Updates are made in July so that's good
Apple was contacted in August and I'm going to just clarify something as I thought that ability affected them Apple had no longer doing in his
Current version so they may have pre patch that may have done something before August
But here's the interesting relevant
Samsung
I'm just going to read this out loud
Contact on three separate occasions in April May and June
No response was received from any Outreach
Alright Samsung
I know their pee
You guys if you want to be a credible iot
Vendor to Consumers and businesses because we're going to talk about later that's
That is unacceptable
You should have if you don't already
And maybe they couldn't find it a bug Bounty program
And you should have a way for security people
Contact you
Because that's how a lot of things are being found out
Vulnerabilities are really nasty
Yeah and it's even better to
Have a response
Weather
Affects you or not because at least explain to people that you're looking into it your way the situation and you're doing something or you don't need to
Do something about it
Write a message with
Bingo
Cuz guess if people know that you have policies and you should advertise
Because let's say
You say hey
If we get your vulnerability
We will acknowledge its receipt
Meet people if they don't get the acknowledgement
They will
Look for other ways to
Otherwise they're just like
Recordable Teddy
So you send out
Enquiries Into The Ether and then suddenly
If you don't get anything back after awhile you just stop
So
Samsung
Not cool man
All right
They're coming up later
Let's talk now
About something not as scary
Superstar.
Please buy this
So what this is
This is
Last week Chamberlain
Put a message on it
Sift page basically saying that if you want to connect your garage door to a service like if
Or even possibly Google home
You're going to have to pay a dollar a month
End
The outrage was not tremendous cuz I don't know how many people are alive
On this device
Although I do and
What's connected to it
But the people noticed we're not please
Now I know they actually reached out to us on Twitter and that's how we found out about it and I wonder if
A lot of people leaving
Do you know about this yet
Yes so I sent some questions to Chamberlain yesterday
Trying to figure out the Twitter account for Chamberlain
Was like yes we are charging
So it is a real thing
They didn't
Acknowledge the
So
I asked him what
Services
They were going to start charging
Why
And
Didn't hear back so
Kevin the absence of Chamberlain
Think about this
Yeah as soon as I saw this on Twitter I started digging around the gift page and I noticed that they
I had a link for partners and like I wonder if Chamberlain is now a partner and what is it really mean cuz I didn't know anybody and
Any listener if you want to create your own if this then that recipe and all that you can certainly do that there's no charge
X-ray with that that has not changed but if you go into the partner program
We noticed that
There are two pricing tiers
That Partners have
Hey and one is $199 a month for and that allows a partner to create a single service and
It's triggers
And therefore a to make that available as a service
I don't think that's what
Chamberlain is doing I think they're in the partner plus program
Because what partner
Surplus does is it gives you the ability to make multiple products and services available with triggers and if
It gives you an unlimited number of end users
Square Dashboard you have
Prioritize
Server space in
Nashua is
Yeah CSI lazerport
Exactly
So
It sounds to me like
Chamberlain is probably done this taking it into the partner plus program and that gets into the
The pricing and it's a minimum of $499 per month
Duck-billed annually and that
Minimum is because the price will vary based on company size number of services and customizations to Chamberlain's paying at least five
The month I suspect
To offer the gift integration
And
Having to recoup some of that well looks like they said let's start of people at Buck a month or $10 I think it's
The $10 annual fee if you want to do it that way so well I
Get it
I understand the need to make money back if it's really comes back again so the question we can talk about buying Hardware services
You know when you bought a Chamberlain MyQ Stacy you didn't expect that you would have to pay this for example if you want to connect right
I will admit that it was a long time ago
I don't think it actually had an ifta integration bee
Because the Chamberlin guys
So worried about it from a secure
Perspectives it was highly demanded
When I bought it it's not like they're taking a
It is
I am sure Golling
Oh my God I can't wait to connect this cuz it's a connected thing and being connected means you should be able to
So that
User
And I'm not I can't fault them for
Doing this because Integrations
Take developer time they're going to take a continual amount of developer time be
Because it will make platform updates
Minimum to be
Partner when you start
Multiplying that out
Across lots and lots
Jasmine
Right plus the partners have scalability included in the so as they get more users or add devices
We'll have more service pays more dedicated bandwidth and so on and those resources involved here as well
But
You know if you bought your device
Thinking you're buying connected
Set device that would open up this entire new
SeaWorld
Suddenly that world seems
Not moving for you without more money
I feel that way about
My doorbell
Having an additional charge on it
To get historical views
Ever
I'll pay for
4 extra
Extra
24-hour. To see my videos
I'll pay for anything.
It does irk me that I'm like
Oh so basically I can talk to my
When they're outside my door
Oh well yeah
So I get it
Yeah it sucks again maybe Chamberlain
Will clarify
The conversation that you're having with them
The communications I should say and we can get some information I suspect we should probably prepare ourselves for other
Ifft partners that are going to have to
A charge unless they're going to eat these costs
In the future
Eat the cost
So we have a start-up that I have followed for a while because I knew its founder Jesse Robbins who is
Chef
Which is a
Cloud configuration manager
If you guys are like what the heck
Just ignore it
The point is I've known him for a while
A couple years ago he started a pushed
To talk device
Ryan and this company basically you
Got a little microphone speaker thing
He clipped it under your shirt or your lapel when you push it
And you say something
And then a team member whose part of that Circle
To hear it
I like walkie talkies like
They're fun so I like the idea and now
What they're doing is real-time translation
I actually thought that was a really powerful
Thing to put
On a walkie-talkie like device that is
Just attached to your lapel
Kevin says
I fail to see why people keep trying to companies keep trying to
Reinvent things add-ons
Stand-alone devices when
All the functionality could easily be done with the phone that you would likely already have because this Tech is very cool don't get me wrong
I know you like a saying
Can you show me the video and it definitely changed my mind that's what they're doing here but
These are little clip on
Microphone speakers
That you press
To talk Wichita
They're bluetooth-connected so you can only do this from
You know within 30 feet or so charge your phone
It actually goes back to your phone and there's an app
Cat with the translation and so on so you're already relying on a phone I'm just struggling why
They're doing another device approach
To be honest
I think it's up to me I'm excited
Hands-free
Or mostly hands
So I don't have to hold my phone
If my phone is in my pocket and it's on and I'm trying to communicate with someone doing real time
Speech-to-text is going to be muffled because it's in my pocket so that was
My thought
I'm like this is just clicked on your body just hit it
Yeah and I get that I do it it's to that extent it snow a little wearable device
I don't know if you have to push talk before you say everything or it's just the one time on and one time off but I mean again
They're leveraging the cloud in the phone
Foreign the app
All the communication bits and so on so to me it's like
My phone can be used hands-free it's already got the mic and speaker in the Bluetooth built-in
Why do I need another Mike going to speaker
I think
I don't know
I think the functionality
Stacy and Kevin
Sad
Sympatico we are at
So let's do some quick news fits before we get to our voicemail question
Do shorter are actually I guess it would be do Samantha
Of the week but
District 7 fancy dress
Samsung
Which we have talked about earlier
Has joined Edge X Foundry
Which
You don't have to remember
But this is an industrial iot
Middleware
Organization
Which again not the sexiest
Staying in the world
But crucially
I like this project it feels to me like what pivotal was for cloud cam
Shooting people still don't use pivotal
Enterprises do
Amazon
All those guys are
We got our own cloud
These guys for industrial iot I feel like it's
Probably going to be really relevant
Because not everybody wants to
Put all their industrial secret data
In the clouds
Amazons
Measure
So edgex Foundry
You may not but I
Actually really hot
Optimistic about it
Sociocentric
And
They did it because they want to do their Industrial iot
And make sure
It is applicable
To all of the
Potential industry
Customers so
They have been working with
Ocf
Activity Foundation
And
This is just to ads
So just just a little news bit
I suspect that they also are doing this because it's less of a compartmentalised
Approach like some of the other vendors that you mentioned
If this is a Linux Foundation
Project
And Tyson is
Linux paste
Samsung's iot platform so I can do it with don't want to be shut out
In terms of industrial iot when it comes to tizen
Samsung
Security game online
All right we also headache
Kickstarter projects
Is
Glow
More energy
And
Just came across my radar this
Past weekend it is still an open
In project if you'd like to back it it's an all-or-nothing project as well so it's only fun that it reaches its Gold by fry
Geez September 14th
It did reach the goal
So I'd go with 75000 something 96,000 reminds me when I look at the device itself
Reminds me a lot of
Hey Google
Device has the same similar air freshener shape but it doesn't do anything except
Show a light
And that light will be
Ranging in color from green to red
Depending on how much energy you're currently using in your house
And at the other piece of this there is a
A device that you put on top of
Your outdoor
Smart
Meter in that sensor uses magnetoresistance technology to wirelessly measure power usage
So it's simple to install and
And use
And when using a lot of juice
Spending the lights candy red also web-based dashboard so that you can see real-time innovation
If I repair air conditioner Heat
You'll see a jumper spike in that and so on
This thing about this I do find it very interesting obviously I would have brought it up
We seen other more complex systems that offer for more info
Permission and I think
Do you still have a system like that that gets down to the Circuit level
Baidu
I don't have it on anymore because
And here's my issue
All of these things are like
Yo you're using a lot of energy
But I have taken as a homeowner
Almost all the steps
Without
Really impact
Quality of life
Things but I'm not going to keep my air conditioner.
AT&T middle of the summer
I totally get that I think if you've gone as far as you and I have as well
It's more of a behavioral thing like Jesus did somebody leave lights on or something cuz we were using a lot of juice that we don't normally use here
Automated the heck out of our house so
Don't usually
I'm not against this I think at CD I saw some more interesting energy monitoring things so so
Which is a professional installer product
Had a really interesting
System that work
Plug into your all of your Breakers
And control them so like
1/2 generator power you
You could say hey you know what I want my generator only to power my fridge and
And my freezer
And actually that you could do if you hardwire
My dad
Crazy so he hardwired his Jenner
For most people that's
There was also some interesting battery storage options
Like Sonnen has one
It allows you to automatic
Are the powerful
Batteries
Which again
Is super cool especially if you
Do you have like an event
That was like a this is kind of cute to be good for
For kids like I could see installing when in the classroom
Middle school tutor
Educate people about this
Take a piss
I didn't want
Yeah they close not for me either I'm going to do think it's very interesting but you and I are at a different stage when it comes to a home automation
Energy monitoring
For somebody who
Is new to energy monitoring and doesn't have a lot of devices that can already going to be automated to help reduce electricity
Might be worth it
So is going to cost you $199 right now which is 30% off the expected retail price
So much cheap
So cheap
Which energy does a
That's an LED bulb inside at least
Alright let's take a question
From our hotline
But first
Let us tell you what are iot hotline is
It is the number is
6 to 3
742 4
Awesome so call us with your question
And this week
We have a question
From
Anita
This is
Kevin from Raleigh
In Raleigh North Carolina
And yes you can use this on the air
I'm
In possession of a butterfly
15 + year old home security system
It's not very high tech
Works fine
And what I'd like to do is do away with the dialer
And monitoring clause
And leverage that are newer
Internet-based and wondering if there's a way to breach the two
I know it matters a lot as
To which one
Generically
Can we use that as an uplink
Instead of the
Cellular.
They provide
Some kind of a
Thanks a lot look forward to more info
Okay Kevin that is a tough question but probably a really common one
And we are going to punt a little bit
We think your best option is probably to
I'll be honest you may have to make
I could get rid of that monitor
That's definitely an option I mean I hate to say that when there's probably a lot of wired sensors that are still good obviously they see you say they stole
I work everything works well with
You know you're paying a service fee to somebody and so on plus you're stuck on a dial-up line for the canoe
Nativity to the vet system
Again if you want to keep what you
You want that
Fine they're actually options to do that
Depending on your service provider if its ATT or some other
Similar service they will likely offer you at a very low cost or maybe even free an option to switch from dial
Does cellular for the
Modern bits
So that way you don't need to have the landline and kind of upgraded you'll still obviously pay your service
But at least you can do that but you can also look into the options to do that you're
Self such as using devices like the or the magicJack
Which will switch you from
Cellular used to
Voice over IP but again if you try to give her the service fee I hate to say it but it's going to be really tough
What to do with a fifteen-year-old system in my opinion I mean unless you want to do some heavy-duty coding and monitor these old sis
Distance yourself
Frankly I think it's well worth your time and effort to just to upgrade it
Yes if you are technically minded I believe
Asterix
Has you can look for some code
That you can use
Using Asterix that will actually
Communicate
With the wired alarm system
As a dialer
That's that's
Pretty hardcore
If you want to go hardcore
That's what
It comes down to it what are you going to do with the data from that system then if not somebody else isn't going to monitor it and because it's old
JL torticollis old approaches old
It's going to be a challenge I just I really don't know that would be worth it in the long run
But if you want a new security system
Can we have some option
Abode
Is actually very good
Biotin install it but it's very easy to install I've Heard lots of good things about it
SimpliSafe a lot of people like it it does have a monitoring
Component but
It is
Most expensive
And another option that if you want to keep a monitored security system you could also call
Call someone like an alarm.com and see what
They will do
U-kiss baby
Be able to provide
An integration kind of
From the old sensors to a new platform
Before but alarm has the added bow
Jonas
Colados
And actually I mean I used to have an ADT system exactly what Kevin is describing and I wasn't thrilled with a
Tengo Madre service after a couple of years so today at just throwing it out there
I'm using my wink Hub which is relatively inexpensive a bunch of different door window sensors and an Eskimo
And I admire it myself there's no
Fee for any of that so I can check in on the system at any time from wherever I am
Maybe even coming up a lot
It wouldn't be that expensive to change out the
Depending on how many
Things you need monitoring if you got 50 windows
5 doors obviously it's going to
Add up quick but
Depending on how you do it or how much you need it can be relatively inexpensive
And you could also do things with motions
Detection that you used to
You have to have a
Like a window
Thinking outside the box
Are you call somebody like
The Canary Islands
Let's see what happens
Options
None of which are exactly what you're after but hopefully this gives you the direction depending on how you decide
Play this you have some
You have some pads
That is it
For this part of the show
Stay tuned
A message from our sponsor
And
Our Guest
David Martin
Who is a
Jolly Old Australian
Talking about how to build a distributed and resilient energy
Using
Blockchain
Yeah it's a really timely one given
Catastrophes that we
Experienced recently
Us and also because
Blockchain is like
Oh my God.
Did you enjoy it
It's super fun and
Really thoughtful
Forget about the future of our Energy System stay tuned we are breaking into the Internet of Things podcast
What's with the message from our sponsor portrait Ashley Stevenson here who is the identity and Technology director
We're going to talk about personalizing cars using for trucks digital identity manager
Which rock is working with auto manufacturers like Toyota on a bunch of digital
Initiatives
Why is identity technology needed
It is
Is really needed more now than ever before because of something that is disrupting the automotive
Industry
Needing to monetize services
Through the vehicle platforms
Just like apple did with their
Play music in order to do that
The Autumn Manufacturing
Know who the user is inside of the car not just for personalization but also for monetizing public services
Kaitlyn
Wow that is a lot of really cool
Cool things
My vehicle so
We are hearing more about the
Automotive grade Linux
Can you tell us what that's about what role for truck
Absolutely so Automotive grade Linux
Is an organization under the Linux foundation and it was put together by
Consortium of
Different Automotive OEM
To basically cut the cost initially of the infotainment system in a vehicle that was engineered separately
Different build cycle
Instead it's
Secure
Baseline operating so
Vehicle
Any auto manufacturer
On top of it
I feel but that they would get a secure Base Line operating system on top of which they could build
Years ago and we have become the identity layer of automotive
So that Vehicles can actually be identity aware and can authenticate user
Susan understand who the user is in the context of the vehicle
Not just the driver but also the past
Vehicles with the baby for a vehicle that they're renting or just
No I'm not sure the general listener understands
Tao complex
The overall connected-car environment
Can you talk to me about what's going on with
Vehicle 2 cloud vehicle
Vehicle-to-infrastructure you
Personalization inside the vehicle is only half
The battle because the connected car is
Is essentially a note on the internet once that cellular radio goes live every vehicle is essentially a rolling iot
To that end
The vehicle itself and all the components inside of the vehicle
Also needs
Secure digital identities and relationships between each other
In order to secure their active
So for a vehicle to make a call to the clouds
Azure cloud service
Send a secure aliviar update to a vehicle or traffic signal
Vehicles
Json has to be
Be trusted
And Trust comes back to understanding the identity of an attribution of what that vehicle itself actually is
All right that is a lot to digest
Where can I go to find out more
About 4
Edible.com in under one of the dropdowns we have this
Page dedicated to are connected.
Hey everyone welcome back to the intern
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is David Martin
Who is the CEO of
Power Ledger
Hi David how are you doing
I sent you I'm really well thank you
Awesome
So I have been told
That I always tell people that I
Really excited
So today
I am not real
Ecstatic
To have you on the show
So we are going to talk about
Something near and dear to my heart which is
Blockchain
Renewable energy
Alright David
You're the CEO of the
Why don't you tell us
What it is that you're trying
We're trying to become
That distributed Ledger after I distributed Energy Future I'm not distributed Energy Future is typically renewable and
And it's typically owned by the citizens of the world so I quit trying to do it
Put the power to manage the Energy System back in the hands of every diaper
Oh my gosh
The power to the
Literally
All right
So you guys have started out with a trial
In Perth Australia
Waukesha
Through what this
So actually started a trial phase in October Alaska
Manafort trial
A place called Bustleton it's about 200 kilometers south of Perth
And it was in a lost dog
Can we had something about 20
Consuming some with payday and some of that and we installed
Marches
Each of the Alameda and we started reading how much energy that are producing and consuming as a group
Were these people living
Totally off the
That were tied into an embedded net worth
Worksite pteropodidae a lifestyle Village
And that Village had a single point of connection to the local grid and then an embedded Network. Supply.
Private Network
Supplied all of the
Consumers
In that embedded almost microgrid scenario sorry some of those consumers have payday panels already
And when I still going to be in
Into the network that I wasn't getting anything for it so I thought I need making money off their solar panels on the roof when they were harmed
Trinity side rather than just
Spilling that energy
Make directed into a
Capoeira
Energy bars
Acreage by the energy
And then I remember right the generator for their trouble sorry we use the blockchain to
Disintermediate the whole energy supply chain process
Music generated directly in touch with a consumer and zap prices
Then in real-time measures
Generation output
Consumption
King size three things together as a physical transaction
And because of the blockchain giving us an immutable record of all the terms and conditions and values in the transaction Bravo the time
Financial trends
Instead of saying to a customer you're not going to get anything
If your energy that you're storing it
The great inside you can sell it to next door neighbor
Next door neighbor Robinson you have to
Depay
The energy that you're buying from the grid how about you pay your next-door neighbor $0.20
Identify Gap in the middle
Finding the local distribution Network tonight imma keep it upright
Wow that was a whole lot
So we're going to break some things down
You did a great job explaining
Why I generator
Somewhere in there
They're usually utilities are
Are people who put an investment in a
Grid system
And we are still using
That Grid 2
Send power back
Can 4th even
In the scenario
Absolutely
Using a local network is really important
Because it's tacky point out to Big investment
Is billions of dollars of
Investment locked up in in networks around the world. And we're not trying to destroy value while we're trying to disrupt the energy
What we're saying is that consumers who are using that net
I've been
Unfairly
Charge for the amount of the network that actually use
And the value of their investment
In Renewables
Something Family Guy
We're looking at a while
Of making sure that consumers
I finally got them out of the network that I use
And that dream directly Translate
Interesting engagement or sales process with
I need a picture of Len plus proximity Tatum
Okay so
Y tho what are utility
Want to let you in on their power meter
Paris to do
This that's the important
Thanks
If we look at what's actually happening
In energy Supply around the world
Is it normal to protecting from the Greek
In some way so they buying this energy
That process going to it's almost your logical
Conclusion
Batteries get cheaper consumer
Houston net worth less and less and less
The cost of running
The networks
Australia the regulated tariff process
An impact of consumers going off grid with Paving storage
And you got 10 years Tom Alico Network business will be losing a hundred million dollars a year
Going to Raytown tariffs as well as lose
Of revenues because of that fall in consumer purchasing
The worst thing for the network is that more and more consumers
Eloquent
Because it's Network pricing website
Not like bikes
Demandforce the project
McDonald's app
I'm sorry we get this
Death spiral Dynamics
SQL consumers use the
Is it going to rain Sunday
Spotify
Active life
Check my network
Allowing consumers to use the network as a
Are really strong incentive
Had to kick the network utilized
Highlights of the distribution metal
At night time the body of networks I belong to
Talk to me about the economic so what do you get out of this
Guess what are you selling
And then
What do the utilities get out
I understand it
You can tell them hey
You're not going to die cuz not everyone's going to leave you
But at the same time
They probably want some
Nothing today plus they got the investment they need
Continue making
In the local
That's right side what way I will to do is pull out some of
The cost associated with
With the existing
Power supply Dalian China
When you're buying electricity or buying
A combination of energy of energy transport a transmission
Distribution level
Operation
Retail operations
Andre, what we're trying to do is pull out as many of those cost
Since we can't set that those costs can be shared
That the generator
In consumer we need to understand
What it actually cost
How to use just save 50 of the distribution Network at the end
Inside this is how much
Pasta wheel
From your last one night or two
Two Doors Down
Bet networks provide that the high-level
Aram system stability
Insecurities and I saw
Prices. Costs need to be worth
Going to understand if a consumer is only using
I really small slice of
Distribution Network
What actually is a fair price
Bearing in mind that we can't get that right
Bill Kennedy
Thanks but nice
I'll put a battery in my garage
And I'll see you later
Well it we've also discovered that there are a lot of hidden costs
They may be hidden costs they may be actually the externalities associated with some of this dysentery
Mediation so I'm thinking about things like
The health and safety of workers with Uber taking
The sheriff
Ride sharing app
So what do you see like
When I hear you talk about this I worry about
The cost associated with operating
The backbone
The pig
Nationwide
What we have at the moment is an energy bar
That is splitting down the
The same way we've always had the view that large-scale generators exist somewhere a long way away
Why were you can't hear the most smell the most
And I push electricity through
Transmission systems in distribution system
Deliver electricity to your front door and that's the way that the physical system is always locked
What's evaporated
Givenchy Frameworks of operated
But now in the last 10 years
More and more consumers
7 Stone
Power stations on the road specially
And there's more of an input
Distributed generation outweigh the consumers
Whole Market model doesn't make sense any
The industry
Kind of force
Small plastic play I bought a big Market Rose doesn't make sense
Trying to track my fat rolls that. Big blast off right in the same like a little guy so it doesn't
So what we need to do is text talk
What the market actually looks like we have
A primary and a secondary
So we just need to sit back take a deep breath
Understand that this change is happening the Genie's out of the bottle consumers will continue to do and Siemens do
We need to change that the market Frameworks in the regulatory Frameworks to reflect the fact that the system doesn't look like it's OS
So we've got this by 4
Located
And on one side we've got
The Long Haul generation
Transmission
On the other side we have microgrids local
Peavey neighborhood-based things
Neighborhoods that have access to renewable
Falls in
Possibly battery storage that
Could create their own
Market inter
Absolutely
Cuz you're going to need to still
Call on the larger generation facilities you know in the middle of the night
The wind doesn't blow
Ain't that sort of thing
In my we use electricity to keep out fridge is running in
Electricity we don't use it for electricity so I can use it for the amenity
What we get from the analogy of security is it fair that we don't need to have huge backup Taylor Swift
It's a huge Camino back up for some rich there because there are markets available
And services about
We can replace one or we can with a lot of pretty quickly
So we'll go in the future for energy Supply
So we can't really live without future thinking of the energy
System 5
Assisting framework to sign up we will always need large-scale backup over
Made some phone
Redundancy summary
Will probably always need some form of alternate
But what that looks like
Like in the shark attacks in the next 5 to 10 years is
He said five years ago you wouldn't need a taxi because the guy next door to you has another by and you
Controlling up on your phone
To an app
I'm getting to deliver you where you need
Now we really used to Aruba
Since I woke my battery is running down I've had 3 days of really heavy Cloud love you so my energy energy storage
An app to get somebody with an electric vehicle
Blocking my driveway plugging and discharges battery into my battery
That's the sort of redundancy the sort of market for energy
Future
Again before we get into the technical stuff
Which I promise you will do
What happens when you have something
Like
Harvey or something when you have like a massive situation
It maybe this doesn't happen
TVs are real
I don't know
Cuz that's what people
Build the grid
For today
So in this model
How should we be thinking about the
The future in
Managing catastrophe
Thank you point is it for you but I don't know if you're aware of the Rave New York progress
That was developed after Hurricane
Find Sandy Hurricane Sandy
Transmission systems
A New Yorkers black
4 a number
Happy City
Without any looking at how you bring distributed energy sources back
And it's not just paleo
Backup generator
Gonzaga University campus
Actually bringing the generations back to where they can soon as outside
There are two things going on number things going on
Whether it's renewable or what
Generation if you're bringing generation back to where the
Consumers
You're the making the system more resilient in the face of things like anime
Hurricane Sandy
Catastrophe
Alright and now
Now it is
I should stress that the reason
Dave is on the show is
Because none of this would be
Possible
Without
Hbase.
Computing which
And connective
Which is basically The Internet of Things
You can't do this without having some sort of distributed
Processing
Acacia Network
Just a bit
Update for you
Let's talk
About
What this entails
We talked about the blockchain
But let's break it down further
What else are using in addition to the
We trade all the makers all the time
So we can tell how much a consumer is
How much is generator
Generating
Awaken Paradise 2 inputs and outputs together
Using the blockchain as an immutable record
Permanent historical record of the
Transaction has taken place
And because we have that certainty around the physical contribution to the transaction we can then tie Financial
Transaction to a very quick time in the energy in tuvalu marketing tool in which the energy is produced and consumed
Speaking Thai Financial
Transaction to that as well
And the blockchain aspect
Of this is part of your software
So you got your software that runs in the cloud
Are the trading
Okay it's figuring out pricing and
And
You've got
Is it aetherium is a
Bitcoin is it something about yourself
It's something we build ourselves we use of private blockchain
Can cold Pikachu
We created ourselves
It's a proof of
Start blockchain
And we use it as I
Close look
Triton Bar
So we have trusted nodes
Recording. Tattoo that blockchain
And if we don't have enough noise on the but trying to give a sip sufficient security that we made with
Entangle that. I with the
Consumers and regulators and Banks
A level of comfort.
The energy that's being traded
Fallout rain jacket
Is not being used for any other
Southway next door neighbor for a value
I got baggage handler games for
Application
China
Apple cash
But I can see my who's buying energy in that
Can log into the pallet of sod but I can pre-purchase they spend that you talking to me that you buy mobile telephone minutes
She can buy tokens that represent
Set the value of energy stock
Taipei
So you got the lowest denomination
Where you're from and then
It depends at conditions of the Triad identified by your energy
94 / $0.20
And you get $0.15 in the network gets $0.05
Spend I will transfer 20 spots
Into that environment
You'll get 15 of them
The network will get father
Guys fighting to the networks and your online wallet and Iver. Of time as you
Fact fluency
Fox you can go back to the system
Everything nice box with cash
Oh okay so there is Sparks for cash at the
Cuz I was thinking about the poor utility who's going to have all these you
Lisa Sparxxx
Every trading act within that writing
Environment will be able to
Exchange kilowatt hours
Sparks
And then as I exit. Trying varmint this box I've been redeemed
Crude from the initial purchase
That we reduce the risk of numpy
Because you've got to
We also improve cash flows
Because you imagine you're the network and you'll get in five stock to every throw it out if he's being transact
Your balance is going to rush it out really quickly
Every die every 3 days rather than Whiting
60 days or 3 months to get paid
Improve
Cash flow
Network business as well
Okay
That was really
Awesome from your perspective are you guys a tech company
How do you think
Registration document in the office of the time
How a blockchain company Huawei in energy
On the energy guide
In the business so I've got to
Particular by spit I think one of the things that strikes me around
China
At the moment is it's a remarkable piece of chicken
Send amazing things
But if you're not directing it towards a particular opportunity or dressing particular problem in many respects it's just
Solution looking for a problem rather than a problem looking for a solution
With the energy issue wait time for the engine
Expected we saw Allied defection
And falling you like I should
The problem we saw apartment buildings that couldn't Bondi
That's fine with that allowed
Tenants to install payday as a problem
And we realize it has a really good solution to those two
A problem sorry Energy company that uses
Is the blockchain
Provide solution
Because I'm very curious what you think all of the currency speculation
I don't know how else to put it but the
Currency speculation around
Blockchain
Ethically cerium and pick
Kind of what that means for a company whose trying to use this
I think it's kind of being tended
Purpose which is distributed trusted
Transactions
On the internet
But that doesn't
That's a utility token
And that allows application host with the network business is our apartment building managers
ShopRite
The Den Bar
Amanda Lawson
Inside the pouch hiking
Would be
I Surrender door and held in escrow by pallet jack
Animatronic device Paltalk and we will give
The application has the license
How to use the platform and a pool of stocks to operate riding in barn
And then that training environment because the stock is pegged
To the lowest form
The local currency there's no volatility so we don't get that the impact of speculation
Cryptocurrencies flowing through into.
That why either
Consumers are protect
Wicked from any volatility
But we still get the benefit of a distributed Ledger that allows does specific training barnsby
Interoperable
Platform
Awesome alright with David this was fascinating and I really appreciate you going so deep
Deep into the Stop
Absolute pleasure
Thanks for coming on the
A Nissan
That's it for this week's show thank you so much for listening and if you want more iot news you can sign up
For my newsletter estacio
News things at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week