Hey everyone welcome to the 216th episode of The Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's co-host
Kevin tofel
Ed we have a stoop
10 - 04
We're going to keep talking a little bit about
Google's crazy news last week
Killing the works with Nest program and give you guys some alternatives
You want to have a more open ecosystem
Amazon has now announced
Smarter routines and Asgard we're going to talk a little bit about that
Verizon has a new NBA
We've got facial recognition getting banned
San Francisco
Couple little funding
Some rumors on the homekit
And
We got Lenovo introducing an iot Gateway for the edge
Plus
The Wi-Fi
Smart
Home certification is out
And we got an update
That
This week we will also hear from our sponsor
Dell Technologies talking about vmware's pulse
And our guest is
Divisive
Who is the head of global business at
Finn
She's doing a deep dive
And
Why
Home insurance
Having such a hard time getting
In on the smart
All of this in this week show
The first
Let's hear from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is Nordic semiconductor
Nordic semiconductor is the world's leading company and low power Wireless chips
And it's hosting a free technical seminar
Call Nordic tattoos beginning in June
A NordicTrack tour seminar is a day crammed full of knowledge and learning about wireless devices
And free software that Nordic provides
That makes almost any application a possibility
The seminars are totally free you'll even get a complimentary Nordic
A52 multi-sensor prototyping kit
And
An NRF
528 40 dongle
To take home and start inventing with
You'll be taken through topic such as Bluetooth LE
Bread and zigbee as well as low-power cellular iot
Lte-m and nb-iot
Find out more in sign up for a Nordic tattoo event near you
Www
. Nordic semi
Dot-com
/ NTT
Actually sounds pretty cool I would totally get a dongle all right
Let's move on
To this way
Freak Show Kevin
I feel like we've got to do a little bit of recap
So
We spent a long time talking
About Google because last week Google announced it
It did really announcer put up a blood
It said it was going to kill its works with nest
So we don't last week with a lot of the Rama
Vacations
In the biggest ramification
To sum it up is if you have a nest device
Nest devices used to talk
On their own out other devices
Nest devices will talk to the
Google home hub
And Google home
And
Which has been rebranded
Tattoo yes
Which has a new name
Turn up Nest homes
There's the nest home hub there's the old Google how there's the Google
Mini
That's the weird thing summer rebranded summer not but regardless yes
Rabbit aggression is going away
Yes and so basically you're messed up when I talk to Google home devices
And then all of your other devices will
Google home
So basically there's a middle man in the middle
Which is where those metal bands like to hang out
People were really upset
It breaks a lot of functionality of all of your existing
Google
Integrations in route
Teen service
WeChat
Third-party services such as
Yonomi stringify
Those if you have routines for your nest
Those will not work
Wendy
Integration shuts down which I believe is planned for August 3rd
First
Yes the end of August
And starting the middle of June Google's going to let you know that you can migrate Your Nest account
To the Google home
You should not do that
Until
You know that your other Integrations arson
That's why
Okay or other advice is we've gotten a lot of questions
People are like this is terrible I'm so mad what other devices
So we wanted to run down we mentioned the Honeywell thermostats the T5 is an excellent thermostat Honeywell actually just put
39 + 2
T10 thermostat
Those play with gift
With Google
With homekit in many cases and
Also with
Amazon
Ecobee
Is another thermostat brand that works with
A lot of other things
And I would be a little cautious there because Amazon did from them out of the
But
They are an independent
Canadian Cup
So and we loved
Are the doorbell front
August
I hated their first doorbell their second doorbell I haven't tried yet because I
In the middle of moving
But they do have a doorbell out it works with
Other ecosystem
Arlo is announcing a doorbell that actually looks just like the nest hello so I don't know if
Bee Hardware inside will be as good
And then let's see
Cameras
Are Lumix cameras if you can
You could go all in on Arlo
Given this news
And Arlo does actually have
Gud madhumeh integration
And that shows you
Your Arlo cameras on
Madam a device with a display
Let's see what other things would we want to know about
Smoke detector
I can't really in good conscience recommend the First Alert
Is it so expensive but it is a connected smoke
Detector
I will say that if you are
Maybe doing the Google Amazon route
Amazon did just this week and I'm scarred
Which is an interesting way to start getting remote notifications from your smoke detector
Because guard
When you leave your house
You basically turn this functionality on your Amazon
Echo it will listen for both glass breaking
Amazon of a smoke alarm or a
Carbon monoxide
And that will just send a notification to
The account owner's phone
Just some people are aware
You're going to get a text message we need an in-app notification
It doesn't go to the whole family
Just that one individual
It will however send an alert
You
Thruway monitored security service or will send an alert to your monitored security service if you're using the ring
Security service or ADT Security services
So you can actually elect
To turn on guard and have it send those notifications to your Professional Security firm
If you have
If not
Send it to you via in-app notification
At least notifying notification option theory is
But it's a free service that you did just because you happen to buy an echo
So you know
Always options
Those are for people who are not happy with the situation
And want to move away from Google ecosystem I presume
Yes
And I will say I don't I mean our audience cues very heavily towards
DIY I will say most
People I bet there's actually
Very large contingent of people who are going to get emails from Google
Rather nasty stuff in there to be like
What Google owns what
Best
What do I do I think there's going to be a lot of
Because most people are not that wired
Write my point was
You want you could choose to just completely
Change your whole smart speaker to ecosystem
Keep in mind that while Google has shut down works with nest
When will be shutting down
They will be working with
A limited number of integration partners
Going forward
An Amazon is a perfect example.
Working with Amazon to keep
Ness
Working with the
Amazon Echo products
So
It may turn out that over the next couple months as that
Horse of that program wines down
The third-party services you use may come on board with the new
System service
My point is
Don't trash all your smart speakers today if your on Google
You may want to wait and see what have
Indeed or all your smart devices
Better made by
So those are some
Lovely options out there
For you on the nest
Front let's talk about
Temperature
Google Assistant appearing on a new device
Oh yeah and with only waited I think 19 months for Sonos to get this integration
Hotel of elephants
So you know
Trixie I don't know I'll look that up after the show
But yes
It is available for me it became available earlier this week
When they announced that they said that software update would be required
And I got the software update I have a pair of
Are Sonos one speakers
Right here in my home office in fact
The setup
Typical of any
Third-party hardware setup with Google Assistant can I get bounced around from the device
App to the Google assistant app back and forth and whatnot so I'm kind of used to it but I don't like it
But once you get that done it works perfectly fine I tested it
With a bunch of my Smart Home Products
Any other Google Assistant
Google home device in my house
There are a few limitations
Processor third party
Device
Namely
If you use the Google homes that you have
To make or receive calls well that's not going to work here
Additionally
There are fewer
Music services that Google Assistant works with
Compared to
Madame a and I say that because the Sonos
Speakers got madhumeh integration
A while ago
Well over a year ago
And there are more music Services you can't control their
So that's another limitation
But other than that
I'm pretty happy with it
I guess I'm wondering why I need a Google home hub in front of me
And Google Assistant power
Sonos devices next to me now
So
I'm not sure what I'm going to do
Kevin you're going to keep everything so you can
Contest all the news
Latest greatest
So I'm going to keep everything so I can test the latest and greatest
Yes
I see I want put the Google home hub here because I can say hey
G show my front door when somebody is at the front door
I can't do that with a Sonos speaker says they have no screen off
Play Soho
Yeah I guess I'll keep both right now the home hub is muted
And the speakers are
Not but
We'll see
I wait long time for unhappy with us
And I didn't realize this but
Play no doubt you can get this on the Sonos beam
As well
II was about
I'm looking at one of those because
As part of my boob I will lose my surround sound that was built
My house
I now need one of those things that hangs above
TV
S7 work with my digital assist
All right so we've talked about a lot of digital assistant news one little other thing
Amazon we can talk of this last week
Sunset and sunrise
Notifications
So now you can use
That is a
A trigger when they
Routine
And
Google smart displays and now get
Their own
Routine button
Which I don't know if you want to talk
I would love to because again I have the Google home
It's not that exciting literally if you swipe down
On a Google home
Smart
Display
Where it normally would have no hear cure lights
Lights media
Broadcast MSS cameras Etc
There's a new button
Access routines
And if I tap it
I can see the names of my routines
Basically it's a way to quietly run any routine
Excellent
Okay
Yay routine
I'm not looking forward to having to set all of us up
But
It'll be a fun story a learning experience
Alright let's move away from the digital assistant world for just a little while
And talk about
The NB iot
SeaWorld last week we talked about
AT&T launching NB iot
Yay
Not to be outdone this week at iot world
Verizon announced
Their own
Nb-iot
Which puts the US now where Europe is
In the US the carriers
Sprint first with LTE
Cat 1M
Which has more bandwidth
But it isn't as battery efficient
Is it cost more so people were not thrilled
And now they're all like oh we made a mistake everybody wants nb-iot
So Verizon's network is now available over 92% of the US
Population
Control America
And NB iot just as a quick reminder is cellular
Very small data
Very tiny
And Verizon standard and big price plan is going to be
$1 monthly access fee
Her device
Very different than AT&T
Which is like
Here's $5
Her device
So
Verizon were already looking at $12
Per year
And
AT&T didn't really talk
That also I should tell you it was a starting
Well I can look at the consumer side of things I'm like I'm not paying for it but
Obviously if you are a business that's rolling out thousands and thousands of
Cellular connected devices for sensors and such that's going to add up quick
Avesis
Yeah there's a consumer you might see this like you might buy at a smoke detector for example that has an NB iot sensor
Granite not really care about it'll configure automatically to the network when you download your a porter
Turn it on
And what it will do is if anything happen
Like smoke is detected will send a signal that
Will either text you or give you
A notification
And that sort of thing
Will probably just be built into the
What device is my
Probably I would agree to be honest
I think I would want to see that in certain centers as a backup system because if my home internet is out
Whenever I get the notification
Your security alarm may be a flood leak detector
In a smart city they're looking at using mbit for temperature sensors maybe for
Bridge maintenance type of sensors.
So
Parking meters
Is there a transaction oriented that's a batter
It could be like yes someone is parked here right now
But I don't
Actually sending
Yep make sense
So
That is the Verizon NB iot Network
AT&T he retired SeaWorld
Not to be outdone by Verizon
Launched a
$1000000 collaboration
With the city of San Jose
Really this is mostly technical
And San Jose saying sure you could play
Play on our Network for Smart City stuff
So what they're doing is they're adding smart lighting
Controllers and lights to 14 Parks across San Jose so this is go + 100 + 1
Wi-Fi extenders
Yay
And
What they called digital infrastructure notes that will help improve Public Safety
Digital infrastructure is AT&T schedule for a piece of Hardware that you install online
A Lamppost or something
Like that
And it's designed for
The Smart City
And people can use that data
Pull the data from it
Lovely apps
Muttley
Plus AT&T is going to give Sam
San Jose to
$2,000
I assume so they could
Use this as
Case study
Press release
So
Go San Jose get it get it
All right
We also have in City News San Francisco
Band
Facial recognition is the first city in the US to do so
Ironic
Given the
A technical document of the people or maybe it's not ironic there's like
Yeah
The stuff is Daisy and or William as all get-out
So
Let's talk about this Kevin what has happened
Yeah so this is a new
He said a ban on facial recognition technology
But the devil's kind of in the details
Always hatin
Yeah yeah
When I first saw it on like
So nobody
Anywhere within the confines of
The city of
San Francisco will be able to use facial recognition
But that's not true it's the city itself
Basically if
City agencies would have to get approval to get
Surveillance devices in such an edit includes police body cameras license plate readers
Etc
They can continue use what they already have expenses
Sleeper new stuff
Private entities
Are not banned
Just to be clear
If you walking
Their private
Cuz they're private entities exactly
If you're walking around the Streets of San Francisco going forward you know you shouldn't
After really worried
About facial recognition in use
Other than maybe again private entities that are monitoring
I just walking past their front doors and such
Retailers use it inside their stores
Check for shoplifters
They have an own database of shoplifters and
If you get in there yet
Escorted out
Even things like Amazon go
I
Actually do they use facial
Ignition node
They use the app on your
Right
Mission to know what you buy
I'm not on the shoplifters database output
In the casinos
A little sketchy
Anyway
Are you dating the blackjack tables I'm like tell me where Kevin
Okay
The main reason
For that is something we talked about before these facial recognition systems
Are pretty much heavily biased
Against people of color
They're not accurate and then that
Has led to some very valid concerns about
Being I don't know people database for not doing anything just
Because
System
Can't detect
Your skin color properly
It's a it's a
Anyway
That's what's happening
I'm not against this I'll be honest
Alright let's move on to
So little bit of industrial news here we're going to talk about Lenovo they have introduced a new iot Gateway for the edge
Which combines menu
The hot exciting words that we talked about today at 8
Industrial iot
We got a
Wechat Gateway
We've got
We don't have a IR blaster
So
What is exciting about this
Anyting
Just new hardware
Hardware Ace
Kind of PC base I cannot with two small pc-based systems
Republic Bank Center Nano m90np
And also the M90 and iot
It's a small I guess I call it a brick
Runs on Intel processors
You can use Lenovo software on it or you can use Microsoft software on it if you'd like
I'm just basically more like an industrial Gateway
Know that whatever was getting into
Course that's where all the money is
Wasn't considering the price is going to list for $539
Damaged shipping
Equitation is August
Yes indeed in their time back into Microsoft's cloud
So
Diesel
Optimized for that nut
Two other things
But ye
Making the industrial iot
That's actually a huge theme
And we've been seeing
So yes I'm still sick
Iot world
We could have started approaching the Enterprise and Industrial iot with this perrytech Folk
Perspective which was like a jeweler will help you like to all the pieces together
And everyone was like we do not want that
We want you to build us a natural solution because we do not want a thing
Take that hard about
And so
That is
Happening you're still getting a more modular approach where you can buy a certain
Hardware in the
Match it to your cloud
But we are seeing lots of Si systems integrators at other company
He's coming in in
And basically hand-holding people through that process because it's still hard
And I don't think we're entirely there yet we're going to have some silos
Built up here in the next couple of years that will take
I don't know a few more years and more maturity
The breakdown
So that's where we are
Big picture that's the big Trend kind of thing I'm seeing here
And
Little bits of news that we forgot about
There's a rumor out there that ring
Has now finally been certified in a developer platform somewhere with
Apple homekit
This is something that's been promised since 2016
People that ring doorbells
Really want this to work
And I'm a little surprised by this
Really
Yes all I know was promised
But that was before Amazon bought ring
Yes but
They promised even after they bought it
That was one of the first questions we had in this actually all this ties into something that we didn't really talk about
We probably should have
Which is this idea that when you buy these products
You're not only buying a promise like Rings promise that it will one day work with homekit
What's the buy a promise that the device will stay
Functionally
The same
And that does not seem to be
Actually playing out
As we saw with the Google works with nest
As I saw actually
And everyone else all with the wise sensors and the changing of the privacy policy earlier
This month in preparation for the launch of it
Sense system
I wrote about this actually in the newsletter
This isn't a new topic
Because we
But it's this idea that all of your Hardware is now
I don't know how to feel about
Because there are clear advantage
Right and we've been through this with
The Kindle
Where you purchase a book on your Kindle you understand that you're buying basically
DRM protect
I could piece of work that may get pulled or changed and
Amazon will do the right thing
What you know
Give you money back and all that sort
But it's still not the same as owning
Write a book stores not going to come back to your house and take the book
Away from you that you purchase where is Amazon actually did do that at one point in time barrier Leon
I forget what what book it was on the Kindle the 1980s
That's how ironic
Help itching
Great example
Yes
Gold-plated I already there
Yes and so
I think
We have to get used to this with
Scented products
I think if we're going to buy them we have to recognize a
Set this is the new car
But I don't think we should just Advocate Oliver
So I think there should be some
Better Behavior
Around
If you're going to revoke us
Feature that is a
Definite
Downer
Customer
You should do it
A sugary treat
So not just a carrot mistake you should
You should give like
Ice cream sandwich
And
If you're going to revoke a future I think you need to offer something pretty substantial
I also think that if you're going to change
Change the privacy policy
I don't know Kevin is probably unrealistic that you
The challenge with the wise privacy policy
Sea change
You're like if you keep using this device you will agree to this change
If I had spent $600 on
Device
What am I going to do
I'm not going to throw away my $600
Right that's the thing I mean
Physical physical harder at that point
Yeah with these companies
Consider refunding your
Purchase pricing if you turn the product back in
They won't
I would love to see them do that because it would kind of force them to
Really hard
Evaluate if they're ever going to change.
Physical
Hardware return and refund policy
They're not likely going to
Change their price
Or they might
Because laws change
Acquisitions happen
They're actually very legitimate business reasons or
Legal reason
How to change your privacy
This is a good example it didn't fit the mini Marcus had a new product line with new features coming
And those features happen to work
The camera
So
I think transparency is the first thing
I think
Maybe it is a probation or maybe it is a coupe
So hard
If any of you guys have brilliant ideas send them to us this is
This is an area I'd like to explore a lot more
Because this isn't a problem
It's going to go away
And
We've probably only get worse to be honest
Yes
Thank you Kevin for that at dystopian
Cynical world view
Nevertheless.
All right my little
Find a little bit of news for you the this is for people
Pacquiao
The Wi-Fi Alliance has now extended it
Wi-Fi certified Home Design program
For single-family
Homes
Multi-family units and
Apartments
So basically everybody living in an apartment kind of
Just don't wear the smart home the smart
Homes
For wild it had this program
It's a way to design
Wi-Fi
Part of the
This means it's going to have awesome coverage everywhere in the home
And
They've got all kinds of
Tools
Ways to make this happen and it's something that the homebuilder does or the apartment
So if you are moving into a place that has Wi-Fi certified home design
It means
You're going to get a network connectivity
Attic
Forever Young
This is very forward-looking at the Wi-Fi Alliance I don't think many of us care about it as much today but
I think it's great that they're building this in
And also
Huge props to them for building their standard into
Episcopal homes
Yeah
Lennar is headed
Wi-Fi Home Design 262 new multifamily communities
Nationwide
Which that's a big deal in our bills
Ginormous
Planned community
All around I know in Texas we've got a bunch I went to visit one
And Pennsylvania
Yeah
And speaking of Wi-Fi
Kevin
I do believe it is time
The Internet of Things podcast
What do you say
This week's iot podcast
Is brought to you by Ashley
She likes white variety of smart locks let you create a smart home of your dream
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions
Compatibility with Amazon and Apple products
Siri
Google Assistant
Ashley.com
Slash
This week
We're going to get to your question but first I need to tell you
Y'all
Please
Hollis
If you would like to be featured on the iot podcast hotline
Ask us your question there is no question too dumb
Like we're just like no
That's not on you
If you call us you will be entered to win
A
Schlage
Block this is a very nice
What is a
I should have said that first
And
Fabulous beautiful piece of Hardware or so please
Collis at 5 1/2
6 to 3
To 4
If you call him by the end of the month which is when we're going to pick our winner
You're pretty good for you because we have not had that many
So
Did you question did your highly likely
You could win
Or more likely than normal
Plus we are planning on doing any questions only
Episode very soon so
Cinnamon because otherwise
It's going to be a very very short
Already that is 5 1/2
623-7424
And let's get to this week's question which is from
Istation
My name is Jeff
What's on the show
Quick question regarding
System
Purchase the Google Wi-Fi mesh
I like it the only question I have is
My other competitors make one
Buckmore Wi-Fi
My backyard
Is there a way to hook up an X
To it
If not you have a different solution that would be
Island Pacific Market shell in Ark
Okay Jeff
We have
An answer for you
Which is
Good thing
And a really pricey thing
So you were not
Google Wi-Fi does not make an outdoor extender
But
Netgear orbi
Does
And when did be cool Kevin if he could just like
Put that extender in there and it would use that cool Wi-Fi mesh technology we talked about a year ago that was a standard
Would be so cool if it used ezmatch but it doesn't so you can
Because
Without the ezmatch standard implemented
You can only stand a mesh network with the
Same brand
That you have today in your home
What a bummer which is why we said this is kind of
Sake
Inexpensive because
If you buy the Netgear orbi one which obviously will not work there wi-fi your Google Wi-Fi
Just the outdoor extender is $350
You also have to replace your tire in home Mesh networking system with orbi gear
And the router alone is $150 I think
I think it's 200
IS 250
Yeah so you're looking at like $600 just to extend
Tier outdoor so unfortunately
It's your money if you were my money and my
Use case
I don't use
Outdoor WiFi that much
And when I do
I actually have a Google wifi unit close to the back of the house so
Niacinamide deck Outdoors
I get a decent signal
Do you have to go property or you don't have a
Access point near me
You're Outdoors we're going to use your Wi-Fi
Maybe this works
$600
That's that's not a primary use case for me is another way of saying that I would not
You may want to
Yeah it really depends on your setup if you're going to do the indoor to Outdoor Connection
You know setting it up near a window will help
Help your signal light stand a little bit in the home that you just sold
Stacy you had
Roof deck
I did and I had actually I put an Eero Beacon cuz I had a covered area in the room
But and here's the here's the caveat with that I had an Eero Beacon that I plugged in under there that would
Be protective for the weather
What day did not think about was that it is not protected
Sheet
Texas Sun
And we get up to 100
10 Degrees apus
Cabinet
And
Tequipment couldn't handle
So you don't just have to depend on where you live you don't just have to
To protect from the elements you have to protect from
Cold temperature extremes
So
Keep that in mind
The other thing I would say to you is I actually tried out the orbit gear
It is very powerful I have
Three of the traditional arrows in my house
And
One Beacon and that is
More than sufficient
But two of the Orbeez so the Domaine orbea then one satellite orbi
Covered my entire
So you may find
That the outdoor orbi
And1 indoor orbi
Works for you
So keep that in my you may not need like as many Google Wi-Fi
All right
Will Jeff
I hope that answers your question I ever curious if you have a $350 outdoor extender
Use case
You're like yes it is totally worth it
All right that is included
This week's
Use portion of the podcast please stay tuned
To hear from
Muriel Davis
Who is
The head of global business development at Finn
Talking about insurtech
And
What is going to take to get insurance companies to help pay for our smart home devices in why we met
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from Mars
Sponsor sponsor is Dell Technologies and I have
Mimi spear who is a VP of the edge
Iot business
Y'all launched pulse.
Control center
2.
Can you tell us a little bit more about
The news
So we just announced
Call Coyote Center
Fast and now we have both gas and on-prem
Dissolution is those for the it organization and ot to have complete disability
Advices
Edge computing
Unconnected Center
This allows them to onboard their devices
And have security across the device the data the application and the network
Excellent so how does this fit into Dell Technologies and VMware
Iot and Edge
We are developing an entire digital Foundation
It is a natural extension to what we are doing across multi-cloud
Ignition system
Which are gateways
Vices and Spencer
And that's what profile tri-center fits in then we all last week
Which is really
Jennifer classic BMW
Closer to where the things reside
So that when you wanted you cuz she's learning and Ai and you want to have real
Decision making
Car or in a retail store
You now can do the processing at the edge
And this is a full-service provided by VMware with Dell Hardware
And we managed
So that you can have it for your followers and delete
Branches
What's Factory and then we got to manage the crazy
All of your different types of network protocols
Extension of
How you connect your wide area network
Software-defined Network
So why should I
Customer shoes
VMware
In Delta
The Ouija
Reasons for cuts
The first is BR extending our digital Foundation
This provides a flexible
An open framework for our customers be able to choose
Any application on any Cloud for any device
Definitely we are providing your foundation
Any iot endpoint or Edge Computing Phillips
Stop providing with
Guaranteed intrinsic security across their data
Their devices and applications and the network finally we're going to help
Speed up Innovation by providing them with more
Building without technology
Where can I buy listeners go to find out more about VMware Zedge in iot
Please go to our solution
Www.bn.com
Lash solution
Everyone welcome back to this week
Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Mario's of Asa
Who is the global head of Business Development
At 10
And Gray Station thanks for having me
Oh I am super excited for a couple reasons one we're going to talk a lot about intertek
So why insurance companies what they can do and get out of SmartThings
But two were also going to get an update on spin which is company I've been following for a while
Why don't you start
By telling us
A little bit about thin what it is what has just happened
Truciciel we have an intelligent water monitoring device
So what that is
The sensor that attaches to the main water line
And it measures three different things that measures the temperature at the point of installation measures how much flow is going through the
How much water using
I mean also measure pressure
Which will get into a little bit later on but what that allows it to do is to be able to understand how much water you're using
How your use
Senior water and if there's any leaks or anything that normal
So meaning when you we can tell you when you take a shower how long your shower is how much water
And we can tell you the difference between
A shower
A toilet a week
And we have the ability to turn off your water a remotely
You're on vacation and you get a call and it says Waters come
Feeling I don't know what
You do what you can just pull out your phone press a button
Turn the water off
Are you can automatically have
Turn the water off for you
Awesome
Yes it's going to be exciting music
We had it
The last we spoke
What's the 4 CS of last year the company
Stop a sound in 20
With over 10 years of
History and research
That started back
In 2009
The University of
3 commercially founded the company
2016 started selling a product in April
2018 and then last week
Anuel funding of $12
Awesome and what are you guys going to do
Latest round of
Two parties for Global expansion so we have Pilots running a multiple continents
This is really exciting
And then also on the product development and
Enhancement and in growing the team
Great so let's get into this idea of the smart home and how a device like this fits into
And you actually come from the insurance world you were at Farmers Insurance correct
That's right I was there for
Show all different parts
From forecasting the chief of staff to last week I was head of innovation
So connected home
Is very important
Send it
Industry-first living insurance
Related to the Harlem exit Smart Home
Waterlox
Severely import
Aspect
The second most frequent claim that is
Is files and over 10 billion of
Cleans annually and so understanding water loss and having be able to
To prevent it was really important and then looking at the car companies I was really impressed with
Send when they were first in beta stage
I meant rather progressions
Constantly stayed in touch with them and and was very
Continue to be impressed and I joined them last year
Awesome and I can tell you as a as a
Customer
I was with farmers and I believe you guys processed at least two water claims from miso
What happens it happens it's kind of crazy
It's at 2% of all homeowners so when out of 50 will have a water
Steam every year
And so when you start to look at that with the average cost
$9,600
Repair that home and then also average time out of that home 90 days
You really want to limit not only from a loft bed for a month
Perspective but also in the homeowner side and having to deal with contractors and
Special mold issues is an interesting out of your home we can prevent that
That's an amazing thing and that's before
So let's talk about this cuz the phone device
It's 699 which is in
Insanely expensive thinking about how much a water Insurance claim cost
What is also
Pretty expensive when you think that most
American households can't handle
Unexpected expensive forehead
This is a lot of money
And so
When we look at buying something like this
Do you think
It's going to be the end consumer who puts this on their home or you trying to get insurance companies to pay for part of the
How do we get this in people's homes
Yeah great question I think it's a mix of all I think that
When you first start you'll have first movers which will be those that really want the tech gadgets and really
To be on The Cutting Edge and bleeding
In technology and that's what we're seeing also from an insurance perspective it absolutely mitigates losses
Progressive carriers it is something
I bet they're looking at
I think that it comes into the cost and the amount of profit that in
Miniature house on a homeowner policy and then also there are some legal ramifications
Rebating and indifferent things that make it a bit more challenging but from certainly from a lost perspective having
These types of devices installed in the home
Is a material at dating
For the insurance
So what that translates to is having the consumer who buys it
Not only
Installing it but also earning discounts on their insurance so most carriers will offer between
5 + 10
Percent off of their insurance premium for having one of these devices
Stop doing that in the near-term I think that you'll see more of the discounts happening
And then Isaac
Continues to Progressive
Become more normal then you're gonna
Start to see it embedded in new bills and
Construction and then also retrofit
And in like new bills and constructions is that going to be something that the builders do as a competitive advantage
Is that going to be something that
Insurors I can be like yeah we need this in this neighborhood
How does that start to happen
But I think it'll start with Builders I mix of Builders and utilities
So when we when the company was founded it looked at
3 million macro-trends that were happening one being increasing population the other being changes in
Inclimate
And water being a dick
Feeding resource in the third being aging infrastructure both at the municipality level and then also at the house
Home level
And so as we start to see water
Continue to be stressed over the years I think it's going to become more and more important
To be able to limit that will rather understand water used
And prevent leaks from happening
And so
As we think about it that happen
Search for Builders and increasing what is really a smart home and how do you provide benefits back to the customer
Lowe's on the experience and also on the cost-saving side
What's switch back to the insurance world
Because there is so much there
And
Honestly I'm a little disappointed I thought I'd be seeing a lot more
Insurance participation
On the water leakage side on the security side
You like a basically get a 5 to 10% discount
On
One option so if I have a
Ismartalarm system
Attic fan really doesn't help me
Because I don't get an additional
Discount
And I don't see much
You know other than a few co-marketing agreement
I don't see much from the insurance forms
Pushing this so I'm
I'm really curious like
Why this hasn't gone
Farther faster
Yeah I mean I think that's from an insurance perspective there are a couple of things that make it a little bit more challenging
Or just rather areas by
Need to be looked at
And Revisited
How something like this can be embedded into a carrier
When is the car
The Coffee Bean
Several hundred dollars that can be
You challenging Furniture because inter-process
Other percentages are not
What you would think of a normal technology company you know it's
It sucks
Percent is so in some years
It can be very very thin
And so when you're looking at an average policy of $1,000
Any device has several hundred
The cost
Justification doesn't make sense to make sense over 10 years
But those carriers are not sure how long this
Consumers are going to stay in the retention
Which one aspect
The second is that
There's also rebating laws
Which limit how much an insurer can provide to a customer for free so that they giving them a device
Because in many states that maximum is up to $25 per year
So that's a bit very small
The minimum amount and thirdly it sounded deicide
ISO general insurers of risk-averse company
And they want to validate
That an increase
Discount is warranted
And how they would do that is on average they look for a thousand coins
But if you think about that a new technology
It's going to take decades
To be able to validate
ISO a progressive carrier it's going to be one that is going to look at the indication
Who sang if I can turn the water off in someone's house
What's when an incident happens
Before that happened
That's going to be materials bathing that's going to be 75 90% reduction in the water lost cause
And so that's where
You know we're working with great partners and in doing
In discussions of
Of how we can
Strengthen what the carrier could do from A Loss Prevention side
That makes sense now what about some of the legal implications or the liability implications
Associated with like remotely turning off the water
Or maybe it's
Remotely
Doing something else based on a smart device in the
And I'm trying to come up with a really awesome
Example and I'm really having a hard time but
Like maybe there's a fire in the hole man someone's trying to like cool things down by turning on all the shower heads
And fins like there's a leak
And turns off the water that could be a problem
I know this is a really random
But
Sure that insurance
Companies are thick
Talking about
Liability
Remotely control
Things in people's homes
We haven't gotten concerns
From from that aspect
Find the carrier from the
Consumer yes
Concern on
Am I going to be in the shower and you know his grandma going to be in the shower and the water's going
Turn off I don't want the device to do that
And that's where it gets to be for fan
Two key principles that they fight for us in
Chords to what we do is one is that the
The hardware
The solid Construction
Is it something that it's not just your main water line so we want something that's very durable and is maintenance-free for the?
And into is on a dating site so really important to be able to understand the difference between
A shower
A regular shower and a leak
A pipe is burst
And so then I tried technology
Play where we are not only just measuring flow switch
Next one meter
But we also measure
Pressure
And so every device but every picture that you
Having your house as a different signature
If you can imagine when a toilet flapper goes up and it goes down
Steph Curry
A wave
Pattern in your water in your pipe
And I can tell us the difference
Search between a toilet
Extinct a faucet
Analy
And so
Always we put this in the hands of the
Consumer where we don't automatically fin would never automatically turn off your system your home
This is not something that you have passed
To you
Auto shut-off capabilities enabled by the homeowner
And then also when there is an alert
The consumer does receive
Is a text message and a push notification
Navigation before the water is shut off as well
And then once the water shut off there's also notification
We are very respectful of what
Customer wants to do
And also in informing them of what has happened
And what they may want to do as an extra
Got it
Okay
Let's talk about the insurance landscape from the perspective of
Data and new entrants into the market
Because when I see those Accenture Deloitte
Intertek
Reports that constantly harping on the fact that Google or Amazon
Come in with their smart home data
And basically offer competitive products
And I'm very curious from someone at a startup
And from someone who's worked in the insurance business
How do you view this idea of the big tech companies using all the data that they have to come into this Ma
I think there's a real advantage
It's two things one is that the insurance industry in and of itself is not a high-margin business so that's one of the challenges
Weather attack on
When you want to
Go into it themselves or not
To be crushed
Is there room for disruption absolute
And that's what you're seeing with new startups where they're just really
Changing the process
Instead of having something a policy being written taking
You you're signing up for a policy and in a legacy some that might take 30 minutes a new startup is doing that in 3 minutes
5 minutes
How are they doing that they're taking advantage of a lot of data that exist and they're also using
Other data sources to be able to validate what that loss ratio is if we just think about it
That is going to spend 699 on a water detection on a water shut-off device is offend
I'm installing it in the house is a customer that on
Their first blush
There a customer that cares about their house they don't want to have damaged their more engage this is an indicator of a better policy
Older than your average book of business
And so these kinds of things are indicators for what a carrier could look at in the
Future and certainly by having the data
A purchasing behavior of understanding
Alerts of understanding what types of devices they have changes the risk profile potentially
And so I think that's a company that has the most data will win
The company that knows how to use that data
Will be the winner
And what about our current legislation around privacy and data use
People are very concerned about how insurers may take their data and charge them more
Or less based on new facts
Basically
Honestly that's what insurance
What's is its
If you would behave in a risky manner
You should
Pay extra for it
But people are like
I used to know how insurance Price there in
Prince now I'm like oh they have so many more options
I guess how do you think about that and how that may change the relationship
Laws that are out there
Ice cream bed
Data absolutely
Is very important than privacy is data
Are we take very seriously it's been a couple of things important
Carrier one is that the data needs to be accurate and consistent
Across the devices
So that's where the
Hardware
Discussion becomes important because the accuracy between one device and another device should be very similar
So that you understand that your data set is producing the right kind of data
Inside
To be able to Warrant a result
So once you get those thousand
Clean
Then I can use that from an Actuarial perspective
So let's work they want to start using that data
Potentially and also to be able to understand okay how much of a loss difference is there if someone has one of these.
Spices do they ever file a claim
Do they file other claims
Is water an indication of the riskiness of that household other inside statue
Wicked Game
No you'd have to insure has to get that data from a cut
And it can only get that with consent for the cusp
And so in order to get consent from the customer the customer has to
See the value that they Co
Is worthwhile
For the data that they're giving out they might they will who's ever going to do that though it's similar to when you first started seeing telematics
So this is when and Progressive was the first to do this to their program stop shop where you put a little OBD device it's been on
Onboard diagnostic device
Provided Data Insights on how the
And they received it this
Count in any industry moved into that we're now most carriers have some sort of telematics program
And what they do is they will offer a discount
And it is based on sharing the data so what you could see is that in the future now you're just receiving a blind
Discount on having one of these devices but in the future could be that you would receive a tiered discount
Perhaps higher
Significantly higher
By providing that data
And so for some consumers then that's
Going to be the triggers what they'll say you know what I'm I'm a good rest
And I should not be paying
This much
Premium because I'm off setting someone who's a bad risk
And I'm a good rest so then I want the discount and I'm okay to share that data and I think that's where you're going to start
To see that s***
We're consumers are going to be okay with sharing
Yeah I can see it
You know it might be really interesting if I purchased a fin
And if I could say to myself
Well I own this data and now I can offer that data through any sort of API ports to my
Insurance Company
And they will provide me possibly it
Tell her they will be like yes we will fight for your business I would love to see them did for my business based on my
My device data from
Is that crazy
No I think that's
Exactly where it needs
To go I think that you're you're the perfect example you have
You have so many
Devices but you're very connect
Is your ear connected to your home
Tuesday that's coming into your home
Which means that you are much much better risk for loss is not to happen in Euro
Because you're so connect
And because of that and because you've invested in your home and you put these devices in and you're monitoring them
Because you're a better risk
You should learn better this
Until I seen that what you're going to start to see carriers
So what's going to happen
And when you look at some carriers were there 50% Auto V
80% home
And you look way down the road
Shorter some say longer
Whenever it is it will happen
When it's on his cars
Come into play
The personalized
Auto premium as it is today goes away
That becomes a commercial policy the risk profile changes because now it's more product liability
So that premium has to be replaced with something
What is that something
You know that the home that's going to continue to be there and you're going to continue to have these smart devices
And more and more data
Soap
Where Progressive carriers
Are looking
Is to be not only there when
Claim happened and be there at the back end
To repair the home
But they're looking at how did they come in in the front end
Mdproactive
And health Act
Consumer before that clean even happen
And create a halo effect in just shifting but dynamic
A between an insurer and a consumer
Awesome I will look forward to that day
I think it's coming I think that there are some carriers that are really looking at it I think also the challenge with some Legacy
Companies is that they have very large books of business so in order to put one of these devices and then every one of those days
Nursing home
Is a massive Capital dream
And so some of the startups they have a real Advantage by being able to
Implement this new technology as their book Rose
Because the benefits are not
Not necessarily in your 1-year to it's in your 3 for pain
And so that's where you start to really see the benefits ended
Going to be a material Improvement for the book of business and their loss ratios for sure
Excellent all right we'll Muriel I feel smarter both about
What's going on with Finn and
How I might get to a better Insurance World thanks to all of my smart room Gadget
So thank you so much for coming on the show this week
Perfect thanks so much Stacy really appreciate it
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Com
Will see you next week