Hey everyone welcome to D200 end
27th episode of The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we haven't
Amazing show
We talking about
Sleep tracking
Beds
Cheshire Cat
Trolls
Dicey Behavior
Ring
The FTC is looking at ruling around voice activated speakers and
And kids
What's Apple also uses contractors to listen to your Siri recordings
People don't trust all of the iot come
Please and
We got another
Security Vault
That
Bless our guests this week
Is
Mike nefkens who is the CEO of resideo which is the Honeywell spin
He's going to talk about what the heck resideo is doing and why it's buying so many come
Please plus its vision for the future of the summer
And you'll also hear from our sponsor this week it's a new one
Nutanix
So all of this and more
Awaits you
After
A message
Another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is digitalocean
The digitalocean developer Cloud simplifies modern app creation by combining the powers of Simplicity love
For the developer community and Obsession for customer service and the advantages of Open Source
Iot businesses love digitalocean for their simple predictable pay-as-you-go pricing for cloud infrastructure
With flat rates across all day to Setters digitalocean makes it easy to scale-up and expand globally without being
Surprised by your Cloud bill each month get started for free with a $50 digitalocean credit at
Do. Co / Stacy
Dio
.
Co
/ Stacey
Already
Heaven
I'm going to get this started off with
Smart
Beds
This is partially because I love
Tracking my sleep
Fitbit
I think the Whiting sleep tracker
I've done a lot here
Because I am
About sleep
And what is happening is Tempur-Pedic is launching a new not connected mattress but a connected mattress
Bass
Actually
Detects if someone is snoring
And activates the bass
To stop
So my husband is really excited about it
Cuz I'll be honest you guys
I snore
I think I
If you remember but I did try that
Snoring device
And actually it did something similar that idea was
Had
Microphones
And when it
Heard me snoring it would inflate The Sting in my pillow
And lift my head up
That didn't work so well for
But the idea is similar on the temp
Orthopedic face except
It doesn't have any mic
Car phones what it does is it to text vibration
Set I like better than a microphone in the
Bedroom
That's what I thought you would say in this works with the Tempurpedic line of mattresses
They didn't test it with any other mattress but it's possible it
Other
And the bed doesn't just measure snoring it also measures
Heart and breathing
So
The tracker will sense the vibrations from snoring
Just the bed
And
It's also going to tell you how I used
So we have a non-connected bed
And base that's very similar to this we have the Sleep Number beds with the
Remote sensor wire remotes for each side of the bed obviously you can change your sleep number by adding more of us are
2 mattress
But also they raise your head and or your feet
When I was snoring will I do so
When I snore my wife occasionally
Tries to raise up the bed manually
And this would obviously
Get rid of that manual activity buddy comes in a car
The cost of the smart base is 1799
Queen size bed
I mean we paid a lot for Arnon
Non snoring
Sites in line that is totally in line with it
If
Now
I have a smart
Well I don't have a smart base I do have a base with Wi-Fi
I do not ask me why
The only time we've used it is when my husband was playing
Which was
Turning on the vibration on the bed
Itau
And I was like what is happening
It must be malfunctioning
And then like
He'd hit a button
Calculator
I didn't realize I had
The point is that is literally the only time
Here
But it does too
If it's with my idea
Which is we will start seeing smart embedded in product
Just as part of the basic
Going forward I expect this sort of thing
In a lot of
And it'll be just an added little bonus
Hey if you're storing the soul
So just out of
There's tons of
Potential products like that I mean I'm leaving back in my chair with very bad posture right now sensor could
Protect that
Move the chair
Color for example
Yeah exactly in so we'll see that and then
This actually is nice because it's offering you tracking
But it's also offering
Action so it's actually
In the sense that it's going to do some
Not just
So
Actionable information
There we go
So fancy
Alright so I'm Pro the Tempurpedic smart bed if that's something you want
If it's not then that's okay
Next up is something that Kevin and I
We don't often does a
Which probably makes the show super boring
No disagreement here
Google
Talked about
Project soli
Gosh
Five or six years
And I was excited about it this is a gesture-based technology
Ultrasonic
And
Now they showed a video for the pixel 4
That involves
Project soli
Which is gesture-based can
Trolls
And you can use it to swipe
In the air
To move things around
I think it's cool
I think it's
Cool
But here's there's nothing it just to be clear Google has not.
Announce the pixel for what they're doing slowly leaking
Information such as
What it's going to look like they did last month this month it's heavy
Up at the top in that
Paper bezel the reason has a big bezels because it's got
Face unlock
Top projectors like the iPhone and IR cameras for face unlock
A light sensor
Salon also has the project
Sweet radar chip
And I filled your songs that you mention
Yes it's cool
And they have a 20 second video showing how you can unlock your phone with your face the pics
Performing the song
And you can swipe over the phone or from the phone to scroll through web pages and content and such
And I think I'm not jazzed about it because we seen this before
Regardless of the technology used
It doesn't add or hasn't yet at a tremendous amount of value
So that's my big beef with us
You feel otherwise
The reason I feel otherwise
Cuz I have not changed my smartphone
This is not a smartphone
This is a
Television
This is a I'm cooking and I have a display a Google home display and I want to move it with
Touching her using my
My voice that is what this is
So imagine your Google display
I know we both love
Imagine being able to gesture to
I don't disagree with everything you said in your car
Their places were voice is cumbersome and like
You know saying
Haji skip
You know when you hit the microphone the Music Stops
I think so this is why
And I get that I think the difference is you're looking at the broader picture
And I'm looking at a product that has no need for
Soli radar Japan
So the reason they're putting it there
I would argue is to build the economies of scale necessary
Although
Not the pixel phone
It's basically to get the economies of scale
That make it cheap enough and reasonable enough
Definition of device
That's
Yeah I get it I get ice I suspect
So they'd be better off putting it in a new smart display
Because they probably sell
More of those and they sell pixel devices quite honestly
Alright Google ignore the pixel 4
Put it in the next
Ness
Set the nest
What is the Google Nest hub
Yeah
All right
So that's our disagreement Dushore or of the month
I'd like to know
I don't know
But
Let's talk about Amazon ring
And
This is been coming up this idea that Amazon
With this ring doorbells is
Building
Penn Optical
And I believe will
Called it
It's that it is working with police.
Or ring is working with police departments
Gather data on neighborhood
Crime so when a crime
Occurs in
People have ring doorbells
There's a neighbor's app
And what happens is the police can ask for
The video doorbell
Recordings from people in the area
They have to have a case number
And they have to
Ask permission so they can't just pull this date
But what's squeaking people out
Is the police are actually working with ring
Inner getting incentives
From ring
Promote the ring doorbell specifically
And
The more people who sign up for the Neighbors app
The more doorbells
The police
It gets to dispense
And this rub
People the wrong way
Aniket why
Everyone says they put in safeguards by the fact that you know
Police can't just go through a database and scroll through
Randall
Doorbell sound
You have to have a case number
I have two requests in the
A person has to agree
But police are promoting one particular type
Because they're getting
One particular type of video.
About that's why
It does
Turn a neighborhood walk into kind of the potential of being
Surveilled
Yeah and I have a
Camera that faces
Front of my house in people do walk past people obviously Drive pass
They probably don't know that they're being caught on camera
I talked about this once before in the show it's a homeless feel like I should have a sign
Cat says hey
Just so you know
There's a camera here
When you walk past your going to be on it
I don't use the data for anything
Other than
When I need to such as when my car was hit and that was a good thing I needed to do that because the person
Said they didn't hit my car
And clearly they did
Let me ask you
And so
If for example there was a crime
Down the street or two streets over and
Police said hey
I know you
What do you have a ring
I don't have a ring out that that that has front camera is a wise and then my front door which is Ash on the side of the townhouse unit
Is a nest hello
Okay so they just maybe they saw your
So they call and they say hey
Can we get your camera data for this crime that was someone stole a computer broke in
Two streets over
We want to see if
Can catch the
Which way they turned on
On your street
Right
Would you say yes
I probably would've you everything first
Myself
Because I wouldn't want to send the video of a my neighbor's doing something else incriminating
Okay see ya
So then
You review it first and if your neighbor is out smoking weed on
Porch uibe
Maybe I could scrub that out in myself like a
I get a pet video obviously cuz it has and it's my right to do so
As far as I'm
Anna and it's not hurting the police for what they're looking for
So
That's probably what I would do
I'm a good neighbor I think
So with neighbors they just get the raw file so that's an interesting
Correct and there's no and I looked
Document cloud is some of the documentation
Between
Ringing in the ear
Some of the police
Apartments
It was nothing in there that
Kind of allows for that
I just get it like you said
Marilyn I want to help if there's if there's an issue and I can provide helpful Evan some happy to do it
But it's a personal choice everybody sing feel differently about this
Yashow Kevin isn't in conflict with me this time
Time he's now in conflict
With himself
All right we'll see if we're in agreement on this issue
The FTC last week said that it will host a workshop on
Coppa the children's online protection
Privacy
Rule
And
The idea here is there going to host a workshop to see if changes are needed
And this is news and I was surprised that people did not
Pick this up very much in the reason is because the FTC every
10 years is supposed to check out
See how the
A couple rules
Doing
So do they fit the current standards yes or no
The last time they did it they didn't
So they're doing this earlier in the reason they're doing it
Is because they're worried about
Voice
Speakers
What they're going to ask is a bunch of questions of
The industry
They are going to be talking about websites cuz I know YouTube and children's access to advertisements and children's access to
Various other things on
But
They also are going to be talking about what are the implications for
Copa enforcement
Raised by technology such as interactive television Interactive
Gaming or similar in Iraq
And should the commission consider a specific exemption
Parental consent
For the use of Education Tech
In schools
And there they actually do talk about voice
And then should the commission modify the rule to encourage General audience platforms to identify and police
Child-directed
Content
Uploaded by
That's the YouTube
So
Did publish something in the Federal Register and I've been a link to that
Cuz that talks a lot about
All the questions
There
Asking
But in the education section
Like hey should schools use this technology and also
What about the collection of audio files is a
Replacement for text
Where the audio files are promptly
Deleted
In line with what the agency hit issue
Years ago
And this is again related to the fact that Amazon
And I believe Google have both come out saying
Yeah we can't delete everything
Because
Benes service
Kezar
I a scroll through this there are tons of questions here
I have a question for you and that is
Because it says
You can comment on this on or before October 23rd 2019
Does that mean this is for public, so could parents actually read this and respond to some of these things
Yes
I think there's a lot of
I'm actually going to spend a lot of time with this and I'm probably going to come up with like
Things that I think
AR
As a parent
That I care about
Cuz my daughter uses
A lot of this type
LG schools we actually just had a question from somebody was a teacher who wanted to
They have there
Class Dubois skills
I I think that there's a lot of
Stuff here like should parents be able to do
Request deletion of personal information
Collective II
Leaders of Technology
And that's within the school setting
But at the same time I understand why companies want some of the state up because they need to make their services better
I mean I see this as you said an early review basically because of the rise of smart speakers microphones Etc
School
Center
The technology is quickly changing we're finding out
More about what really happens with your recording or not talk about that
Some more in a second
I think it's smarter than to do this I think what they're trying to do is kind of educate themselves a little bit
And see
How well
Are the current laws applicable how often are they actually use such as you know if somebody
Request a parent request deletion or review their child's data
How often does it happen and how often
Are companies complying with that Etc
It seems to be like a
Let's
Research this little bit more up since the landscape has changed
I will say
There's been plenty of
App company instead of taking advantage of Chile
People I mean
If you can make money by taking advantage of children it is
Literally like taking candy
For this case money
From a baby
And so we see a lot of
Malicious
Is a malicious isn't
Various I feel like I've
Where is here
But shame
Slimy
Yes
Slimy Behavior
On behalf of certain
No this isn't Google this isn't
Apple but these are
Platforms that allow for slimy companies to come in contact
With your children and
Get them to
Give data
Gift I mean
I can totally see you know
Things asking for personal data from children
Just two
Maybe make it easier to hack
Neither
So much out there or you could ask kids questions
What brand of milk do you have in your fridge and it's like a little Focus
Cancel think that's fine
So
I think this is necessary I think research is good I'm going to spend some
Really hard
Time to Kill
What
Makes sense
And I should mention this
The FTC wants to know also
What kind of bird needs rules
Create on
Bigger companies smaller
Etcetera
So not every company is going to be able to create
Neutral age-gate
Concept India
Here which is a
Creating a subsection of your
Platform that is
For people who don't have it
NH
The assumption is there kids
And if you
Speak up
Can small cavities
And that's what's happening here if you want more information I
Link to the Federal Register
You guys can go read it for yourselves
And common
Andkon
All right
Let's do some
Quick bits
Apple also uses contractors
Just like Google just like Amazon
Just like we said everyone would have to do is a form of QA
And these contractors can listen to your Siri
Kevin event
Yeah I mean we just wanted to point it out because
It would be unfair to point out the issues
From
Other companies in an appointment for Apple
Interesting to me is that
The
Apple watch and the homepod
Apparently had the most frequent sources of mistaken
Activations I guess and
The contractor that regarding spoke with
Said they could definitely hear a doctor and a patient so they can your medical history
Pedir a car with engine background noise it sounded like a drug deal
And then of course people engaging in into
Ax
Apple's no different Bible says less than 1% of all
Are these recordings were because of
Norfolk positive
Inactivation that was wrong
But that's a big number when you think about how many iPhones watches and
Sutter out there with Siri
Oh yeah we talked about this son this weekend Google
Which is a show that
Kevin is sometimes on and I'm
Nicole host
And
You know we were talking about it and
Not this particular issue is I believe the Amazon issue and
Somebody's iPhone activated Siri and poop
Suddenly there's a transcript apus
So we all seem to trust apple and
What about the other companies what it companies do consumers most trust and mistrust will
Pcmag ran a survey on their own
2000 us consumers participated back in May
And the results are code I expected as far as the trust
It was actually Google first then Amazon or buy Microsoft and Samsung
LG products
Career
10% and then Facebook
Was actually being least trusted in fact
The mistress
Chart if you want to take a look at it will Lincoln the show notes is off the charts after Facebook the mistrust was 48
Percent of consumers
Mistrust
Facebook
Every other company in here in the survey
Was at 10% or less for mistrust so
I'm not surprised to hear you have a little surprise while they did this before
Is the big back
Clash over
Listen to my voice recordings
So is that could skew these results now sure
It's not a smartphone
Coyote
Which is why it's not on
Well apples not
How to make TVs Motors Facebook obviously they don't make smart
Displays
Just make
Psalms and the homepod
Yes pretty much mobile devices aside from the homepod which we know hasn't really taken off so
I guess they're just not a big enough player to be asking about in this particular question
Okay that would have been in
I would have had the mother
All right
Speaking
Trust
There's another
There's another vulnerability
And this one is the
Amcrest ip2
Um blah blah
It's a cheap camera
In this particular
Case
You can connect to the audio stream
Septimus
Write your Monday notes to use so somebody could be listening at all time
There's no record or anything it just
Is listening because of the abilities
It is a low-cost like a $58 camera
On Crestor amcrest rather I don't know that brand
And I tend to stick with brands that I know for this very reason
Not the brands the big Brands don't have their security issues to
What concerns me is
Amazon Celsius and I wish Amazon start cracking down on selling things that aren't
Safe number one number two
I think a lot of people bought this because it has
Nearly 12000 customer reviews + 857 answer
Questions
That leaves me to believe a lot of people at the scammer
Yeah and
They thought it was
So the next question is
What is
Company to get in this is a rebranded hardware from another come
Japanese
They probably did the soft
So the question is
Can you fix
So this has a common vulnerabilities and exposures or CVV numbers
Official reported
As far as a
Fix
It says n a for proposed
I don't know
It's a no sign
To tenable network security Inc
So as of now I do not see any
Alright so in that case unplugged
That's
Edward
Okay and now it is time
To answer
Questions
Scrum
Listener
This is the iot podcast hotline
And it is sponsored by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio in the world Affair o provides a
Ruben iot
It doesn't risk your boy
Affero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Ma
Antenna X higher activation
You can learn more at a pharaoh. IO
Pics of arrow for sponsoring the iot podcast hotline
Guys
We
Are doing this recording before we can actually
Announce our winner for
July
And we are moving into the month of August where we have a new prize so it
If you call us
6 to 3
742 4
To ask us your question you will be entered to win
Ecobee
Madame empowered
Light switch
If you have our favorite thermostat which episode of the ecobee thermostat and you're all in on this ecobee ecosystem and you need
This
Product
For you
Will send that out to yet if
You enter
All right
Next week we'll announce our winner for this
Stay tuned for that
And I also want to say that
Last week
So much timing
Last week we talked about outdoor light bulbs
And we got so many people telling us that they use their Hue bulbs outdoors in
Minnesota
In Sweden
In Norway
So
We discuss the temperature ranges be
Because neither as well I didn't live in a place where my outdoor Hue bulbs ever got below freezing
And
Kevin's
Wasn't using
That so
He's not a huge fan
But apparently lots of people use their Hue bulbs outdoors in the
Just fine
Richard
Goforth
Accu
This week
We have a question about ceiling fan
Let's
Stacy and Kevin
This is Andre in Virginia
Thank you for your podcast
All the time that you guys put into
I just installed a
Ceiling fan
My daughter's room
And
It has an RF
Remote
109 ideas
To have to find a remote to turn off the lights
And leave the fan one
So
I see that the
I just recommended
Bond
Hub
Thinking of your yard
Sycophant
Google home Alexa
So what not
And I'm wondering
If you have any other recommendations in the other alternatives to bond
As in
Really I don't
Want to spend
$90
One device
Control
Fan lights
Okay Andre
We have
More work for you to do
And we may ultimately have bad news
When I heard your question
For you said you didn't
That will solve all your problems
But I got it $90 is a lot of money you can find it for $70 on Amazon site
And I think sometimes it goes on sale
But still a lot of money
So we found a product
It depends on your fan and your remote
And Andre I sympathize xiamen the same
Boat as you
I have a Hampton Bay fan and
A remotes
And I wish I could make it smart but
I've been frustrated and I do want to spend $90 on the bond together
So
What Ninja for you to do is see if you can find out
The frequency
That your remote uses and we presume that is RF and not IR because you said RF
In either case if it's IR or RF
What do we find something from broadlink of the wave
Yes we found the broadlink RM 33
Pro
Inappropriate
Plus
This is like a little
What's an IR + RF
Plus WiFi
It's very much like the boss
This is a $40
It may be 43
$3
Depending on who
Do you buy it from
Device
The challenge is
It is only going to
Court
Hertz is the RF
So
If your
Ceiling fan
Is 433 megahertz
You are great
But ceiling fans can operate it
315 for 30
And several others
And the bond actually supports all of them
Is why they reckon
The two way you can call him today and figure this out
You could actually also look on the SEC sticker on
Spice it may tell you there
Or you can
Take the serial number of your fan
And look it up in the FCC database and see what
Or you could do what I would do
And that is just buy it from Amazon
Try it if it didn't work I would send it
The other thing about working with the broadly
In tying it into Amazon or Google
Is that it is
Works like a remote can
Control for a TV
So you're going to have to tell Amazon
That is a television
But you can also do
When you're setting it
Or
You can create a scene around it
So
If you do the scene then you create your own voice command and then it's going to
But you will still have to set it up as a
A television room
Just so you know
Yeah and one other possible got you
It is only supported on 2.4 gigahertz Wi-Fi
I need the Wi-Fi to
Tire near me
Smart speakers
Just be aware
Based on your home network that this is a 2.4 gigahertz
Wi-Fi radio
Kind of a lot of gachas there
But
Is the bond is $70
And this is $40
Is it worth $30 to have to
The call into this
If it is
Do it
Or it maybe it's not even worth 40.
And then you'll be like yeah
We're just going to work with a non smart
I'm just going to make sure the remotes Always by the bedside.
I suppose I could always by and try it I just don't know that if I have the exact
Same fan configuration that Andreas
There is also a Hampton Bay Universal Remote
For $50
What works with wink
But you have to buy a wink
Which temperature
You back
The price
Exactly
We're not ready
For a couple
Already have a wink
If you already have a wink then
Google Hampton Bay Universal
Okay
That is a less than satisfactory
I just said that's not our fault
No
If you would like your own
Satisfactory or maybe less than satisfactory answer to a smartphone question give us a call at 5 1/2
7424 Angelo also be entered to win that
Ecobeast
Already
It feels like the end of the News segment of the show in time for us to
Actuary guess so please stay tuned
For Mike nefkens who is the CEO of resideo
The publicly-traded spin-out
Howdy Wells
Security and smart
We're going to be talking about
Why they're making all these Acquisitions and the future of the smartphone
You want to hear it
After a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is
Nutanix
Everyone we are taking a quick break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
Answer is nutanix and I have
Sacem vakani hear from the company
So netonix we all think of that as a leader in hyper-converged
Infrastructure and now it's offering products and services in the iot area
Can you tell us what drove
Accompany misdirection
It's been quite a revelation space
License to Enterprise Al
We are going to be true to our mission
Enterprise computing
Vauto address
Find a lot of time
Computing solutions for the wall of humans
Ohio State requires us to think about
Can you talk about some of the customer scenarios you've encountered as you go
There's a quite a lot of diversity in the type of use cases for instance
Customers in retail and solve problems
Things like loyalty number identification in their stores
Loss prevention
And we want to work with them to create new experiences
Fortune 500 Food Service
Existing data that is collected using
Machine Telemetry data
Girl from Human based Meat Inspection process
Individualized inspection process
We see similar Trends in oil and gas
Juicing machines
And what is your high level learning so far
There's so many but let me share
For 1
Let It Go
Elan new project
It is asthma
About respecting the prison
As it is about building for the future
Flat affect
We need to respect
Although the infrastructure that is already in place and the dealer collection that is already in place
Why
Create new business processes and experiences
Leveraging
Potato
Nicktoons R&D projects about technology
And I are taking but they also need to plan around people
Different set of skills
Last but not the least
We need to budget for failure
Just like Halloween projects for sex
Iot projects take a long time to fertilize
And then to apologize
Project point in time project
Where can people go to find out more about nutanix and its efforts in the iot
To find out more at
Sign up for the free trial
Hey everyone welcome back.
The Internet of Things podcast this is your house today and today's guest is
Mike nefkens who is the president and CEO of resideo
Hello Mike how are you
I said she doing great thanks for having me on the show
I am really excited so
Gosh way back
October of last year was video spun out of Honeywell and I'm going to ask you
How that's going but first
I have to say
Congratulations you moved to my former hometown of Austin and I
You are having a great time there
I've been here about two months and so far so good A bit hotter than we
Expected but but we're really enjoying that we opened our new headquarters about two or three weeks ago and we are fully up and running
Excellent all right
Let's just get started with getting an update
I should we should tell people who may not be familiar didn't read articles I wrote about this but
Talk to us about
Why Presidio spun out of Honeywell
What
Resideo is today
Grassy the process started about a year-and-a-half ago where a Honeywell
Being a
Omega Industrial Corporation has multiple business lines from building
Chemicals Etc and what they realized was they had a few businesses
It will actually be
Cunning
More consumer eyes than then what they're
Teaching Focus was becoming
Honeywell focuses on creating topics for airplanes and you know creating
Huge Building Solutions
So they were for businesses in Honeywell
One was all that distribution business which is low voltage security the other was a comfort business which is really focused
Are thermostats
Web security business as well and then a what we call an energy business which is really gassy
And they brought those for businesses into one and that is what ridiculous
Honeywell in October and turn on publicly traded companies do about at 5
Billion dollars annually right now
And we're bringing all those assets together now to really focus on the Smart Home
What makes us unique as we don't sell to consumer-direct we do everything through the pro Channel
So once or business has spent over a hundred years building up
Coaching with a very very loyal customer base
And that's what
Will bring those businesses together
To bring a really unique experience to the pros and to the homeowners and work on the company resideo Technologies
We do still have the Honeywell brand work on the Honeywell Home
On certain product over the pros will continue to see that going
Oh yes I was going to ask him I, but I still have Honeywell
In also I feel like I can buy Honeywell thermostats at Home Depot or someplace like that like the tea
It's maybe the T9 there's a lot of
Is T5
Also
That is correct
We do about 3% of our business
Home Depot Lone Star Best Buy really really what it is
Those products are not do-it-yourself products and then you can buy them
Do you need a prototype
Now we're learning about the consumer through Home Depot we want that touchpoint that late customers of ours but our Focus
You and my husband agree on that we need a pro to install thermos
I personally am
I could do it
Why we stopped people don't cut the red wire
All right
Let's talk about some of the Acquisitions you guys have
With me because you done about the
3believe Bowie
Was one of the first it was a
Device that you can stick on your
Your water main
And it
Monitor flow if it shut things off it was very cool I saw to see us a couple years ago
You'll find the IP from whisker lab
Angebot LifeWay
We're so kind of a lot happening here so
What is the strategy
Yeah so let me back in just talk about
What about the home itself
Soaps
Right where people are buying the product
Donald called one of the gadget
Now that you can put in your home and somewhere on his camera can be a doorbell whatever maybe
But what's really happening is there so many more critical systems and networks in the home
That's until those are being monitored and you're able to get the data and then really be able to understand how you can
People that give to those
We consider the homeless
And I really the best example I have to know what you think about that
Which mean the most people have some kind of
Security system
And that's the monitor
To the last 30-40 years you can buy
So you're out of the home and Intruder comes in somebody calls the police they come
But the rest of the home water neck
The air mattress
Air quality in temperature
The gas Network
Your electrical net
The homeowner is left all to themselves
Also have to figure out how to maintain and how to ensure that those things are working properly
What we're looking to do as we are looking to take monitoring
From
Security and start to monitor those other networks in the home your water your are your gas in your left
So we can provide
Call home
So that's the big the big chain
Solidify know our value proposition to the Pro-Am to the homeowner
We want to make sure that we can tell the homeowner
What's happening in the water Network in your home do you have any leaks what kind of water flow do you have the right
What time is your water safe to drink in all of those things in
The best example that on water is
Know when you leave your home if you have a leak you won't know about
If you're losing hundreds
Thousands of gallons of water because your sprinkler system is leaking you're not going to know about
Until you find a wet spot outside or until you see a really crazy water bill
We're going to be doing is just like him security if somebody breaks in your house or if you have a window open the moment that there is a pressure
If you were working the water losing pressure leaking between 2 and 4 in the morning we will advise the homeowner just like
Security that you have a problem in your house
And even better will send what we're calling our home hero which is our contractor
Immediately out to help you sleep
Same goes for the air Network
There's so much focus on thermostat
That's really cares about is your temperature 6970 more
I think the industry got that figured out what people care about now is your well-being in the home they want to know the quality is good
A window that shakes
And they wanted to do something about it when there's a problem so the same there were to be providing alerts when your indoor air quality is not
Semi satisfactory Ariel
And then really looking at the home Behind the Walls
There's so much going on behind Network young electrical Network
The best example I like to give there as you know your hot water heater
How many people are coming home turn on the hot water for a shower and I had a long day and there's no hot water
Is that hot water heater will tell you
A couple weeks before or Jeter using more electricity and we're going to be able to proactively tell you
There's a change
Turn on the hot water heater and we're going to send out a home here in to take a look at it in Six Pack Unit before it actually break
So that's what we're looking to provide to the homeowners you take a look
Bowie is key for us on the waterline whisker Labs is going to help us with energy management from sure we can save the homeowner
More money on your energy and life where is going to support us
On providing data
India on the gas electrical.
Excellent so it sounds like you have most of this figured out
I'm curious on the HVAC Network in air
Is that something you guys have everything there do you need to buy any bud
I think this will be a a constant you know as new technologies pump or will be adding insult
Acquisitions to help us go faster
You know we we have a majority but we need to have a very good offering you know we're always looking to see if you know where
Where else we can now pop in Subutex
Lily Drive
What I call your savings to the homeowner improve time improving the homeowners well-being
Okay and
With this in mind
And I I like to break this down cuz I feel like we're in the middle of a very big tree
Transition
That's between this
We're monitoring it or we're just reacting to take as they're happening to
What is
I was saying much smarter
And to make this happen it feels like you know we need monitoring
And then we need that layer of intelligence
It sounds like you're arguing that we need a layer of Professional Services to come in and deal with it with
But it's
What's something happy
It's also
What's really interesting is we have all the products
Already on those main lines remain in the house and a lot of our competitors they are dying
That's why they're losing hundreds of dollars on every
Cardwell
Gadget picture onto the house because they want data on the homeowner
We are ready at $151
That's what makes us unique we already have
The contractor Network
It wants to work through us
What you just said is exactly right but I think you use the word Gadget burnout
Right now so somebody's got to bring
This information together
And what we're looking at
And that's how you win a gray
You have been a great through these various applications and frankly
So what we're looking to do with we're looking to put them intelligence play on top of that
Bb1 application
It allows us to drive
All of them
Nation on those networks I just described
And allows your pro
See the data that you want them to
And get alerts so that they can come out and help you
So we are Vision in this is why we have headquartered in Austin we got a big development team here
Our vision is a we will build
An application
That will be an application people use no other 15 applications or so they use in their daily life
And it will allow you to monitor
And it will allow you to
See the information you need on those critical.
Examples hot water heater
Nobody wants to go deep into a hot water heater
And see what are the corrosive levels what's going on from the exact temperature in the tank and you know how is it
The gas burning in a what's the control unit doing people up here they just want to know
And if not let me know
And that's the kind of information wouldn't be providing and when we let the homeowner know we'll let the pro know as well
Immediate
Okay now this is a big shift
And I think
What happened in the smart home is people have bought gadgets because there is a subset of
Homeowners who are like
Hey meet it's a cool Gadget I want to I want to play a 1/2
And I think that's where we've been
The challenge here is
This is expensive in I don't know if a lot of people are ready to invest in something they can
Can't see so there's like the cedia channel
Offers you cool AV stuff like that turn on and off and it's very funky and find people
Pay for that
It seems really tough to get people to Shell out for something like
We're going to make sure your hot water heater doesn't light
And I know it's a big deal and I know people hate it when it happens but I am
Really impressed
By people short-sightedness
When I asked them about
Hey would you buy it like a belief system or something like that they're like
Ar500 or $600 I don't know
How do you convince people that they
They want this they need this in their car
Payforit
How do you make
Pricing
Works for that
You got it to look the first thing is we're going to be launching in December when we're going to be launching exactly how these models
So much more to come on that but what I can tell you now is think of it really as
A lot of homeowners 20%
They bite their HVAC Pro they buy medicinal warranty that Pro comes out twice a year
So what we want to do what we want to do that
As a warranty
I think of it that when were everything will be included. They're going to be certain models where you you can either Buy.
Hardware yourself
Or you can actually do it through as you go monthly warranty
So that's our big announcement that will be having at the end of the year and we're looking to make this very simple for the homeowner
No you're paying for two or three warranties and different parts of your house you can come by
One and even even better I'll give an example if you have the water Protection Service that we have you can print off a certificate
Like your insurance company gets really significant discount on your insurance
So we were confident we're going to be able to save the Homeland quite a bit of money by doing this and save them time and hassle you know when the
I have to stop this will be able to put down
Given the direction that you're moving
In this idea of monitoring all the vital systems in the
How important is it that
Everything in the home be made by Honeywell
I'm sitting in a house that
I'm sitting in a rental house but
Even in my older house I
Mixed and matched
France so
What is the philosophy
Typically been an open company and we are
Looking to add many many partners
To our service
No just like to run ATI Branch we have
The largest distribution of low voltage Security in the world with 200 locations we only sell about
15% of what soul do that is residual products so we want to make sure that
No the homeowner is able to get a whole Home Solution
And the residual product is the best for that great
And if there are others out there they complete the solution we will partner will make sure that that's accessible to what to the homeowner
Okay so that makes a lot of sense
But now let's talk about kind of the role of the pro cuz I'm hearing a lot of
Pro install Pro everything
Does this mean you guys are going to
Back out of
The DIYs
Well we're really not in the DIY space like I said about 3% of our revenues isn't DIY
What you just said is it's so important in the real battle going on right now is Pro versus DIY
And we are doubling down on the pro
Elizabeth
The house is only going to become more complex
And with that you would support if you take a look at your daily life
Rights for your body you have a position for your car you have a mechanic
Office Buildings at building manager
But against the home we leave it was really not trains or doesn't have the time or skills
To manage a lot of these systems in the home that are behind the wall
Sure they can maybe manager Gadget or two on the wall
We're going to focus on elevating
The professionalism of the pro
Making them a home hero
Helping support the homeowner with all this drip system
You're still going to be Gadget so you can buy and we don't want to play with him
So there will be a DIY more Market that will continue
But for these big critical systems around water around gas around electrical around security
PowerPoint of Ulysses are pro products
And by doing so that we can save the homeowner time money and improve their well-being
Let's talk about the impact to your bottom line
So
This is a big
And
Part of I know that you've talked about in previous earnings calls has been the shift to recurring Revenue so things like monitoring
How do you guys in vision
Making that flip for my product to a
Services kind of company and
What's that going to look
Now we're starting that now the first piece is going to be bringing the multiple applications we have together until
So that's the first step
So when we do that we're going to be able to offer the pro and homeowner we're going to be a thought for them straight up
Sell a product that's what they choose for will be able to offer them a subscription service so that they can really get the service
Just pay as they go and will we will keep their Tech up-to-date in their home
You know I'm 3 years. They have a thermostat to Russian 3 years will replace it to the next newest one if they so choose so
We're starting at flip now we already have a chunk of our business
Recurring Revenue
And yes we're looking to grow that
So I told the market that know that recurring Revenue
What we have now
And I work all that we can make it to that knowledge
No stress the recurring Services if the quality is right and we can do this right margins movie Higher
And we also think their value will be better for us for the program for the homeowner so it's a win-win for everybody
Excellent
But how do you adjust your business
The deal with the fact that you're no longer selling a product
But you're really selling this relationship
Yeah that's really
That's exactly
What we want is we want
Proactive
Continuous relationship with
Customer
We want resideo to be the home hero
And our vision in the future is that know when homes are built they will be certified homes that have all
All this equipment so that way you can just turn on the service and
Monitored
In your home is safe efficient and healthy
That's what I'm looking for last longer
Excellent all right
Let's move from the future of resideo
You just brought questions about
Building devices
I have to ask
Tariffs are big topic now I'm seeing some companies push out higher pricing be
Because of them
How is that affecting you guys
At this point there is no Sac a majority of our products
Armada next
On the borders when the trade free zone so you know we went through a bit of a scare when the US and Mexico
We're talking about tariffs
But it looks like we made it through that we also do a lot of manufacturing when you asked a lot of Eastern Europe as well the Wii manufacturer
Close to where are markets are in markets are which is the position we like
And look we're just going to have to kind of roll with what's happening politically and economically
I just like everybody else but I like her hand versus having everything done in China if something changes
Have to have to mitigate that but we like the hand we have with our men's fashion right now
Ok Mike thanks so much for coming on the show this week
I really appreciate it
Skip thank you enjoy it
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Snooze sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week