Hey everyone welcome to the 213th episode of The Internet of Things podcast this is your
Stacey Higginbotham
Hydrocodone
Kevin tofel
And we have an excellent show for you today we're going to talk about a new
Venture fund investing in Industry 4.0
We got a fundraising for an iot industrial security company
Got a new solution out for folks
On the smart home side Amazon key is now available for your garage
Arlo may have a video doorbell
End
Why is beta testing
Google Assistant integration
Plus the FAA is Paving the way for alphabet
To make the first US drone deliveries and
Google Assistant
Will be integrated with
Couple of our favorite smart home devices
And for all of you out there who have allergies you're going to want to hear about this wearable EpiPen
Researchers have died
Developed
We're also going to hear it from our sponsor software AG talk about its keeper lacity platform
And we've got
Our Guest Danny Huang who helped create the
The iot inspector software that we talked about last week
He's going to tell us a lot more about
Data privacy on this thing what it means for your network and
A little bit about what they discovered in the
Few weeks it's been out
All this and more awaits you
But now
Let's go to another message from our sponsor
Iot world
You're invited to iot world it's the intersection of Industries and iot innovation
Happening May 13th thru 16th at the Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon Valley
Iot World brings together
12500 iot strategist technologist developers and implementers within
Key industry verticals
Plus
I'll be there
We have an exclusive listener discount for 25% off your pass with the code Stacy 25
Stacey 25
Prices to go up tomorrow on April 26th
So visit iot world event.com to register and if you're there please
Say hi
Okay Kevin
Let's kick this party off with
Venture
Do a lot of this on the show because most Venture capitalists fund iot stuff just is
You're part of their regular
Regular ginormous funds
But clear Ventures
Just announced
On Wednesday
A 180 million dollar second fund
It is dedicated
Specifically to
Iot
It's
Industry 4.0
Architectures that
Will help
Make this possible
So I talked to one of the co-founders
At Clear Ventures it is Chris rust
And he actually was the second employee Roadrunner
All of you guys were
So here I had a great conversation about
What happens when we connect
Bunch of machines
To each other
One of my favorite insides that he had
Was
When we combine
Sensors and sensor data
With machine learning we're basically going to start having machines that
I can learn from each other
Way faster
Then they can learn from us as people
Which means we're going to have to think about
How to build
Machines that can talk to each other learn from each other trust each other
And do all of this in a way that doesn't involve
People getting in the
This is a big
Crazy idea
And I'm very excited to see
What they do with it
In terms of the types of Investments they make
Clear Ventures is a venture fund that is very technically driven this founder in the other
The co-founder
Really go deep on architecture their last bundle mosto
Cloud-based architectures
But
This time they're going to go
Deeper into
Umai
Probably going to see some
Cool container orchestration news I know you guys are like
Like a block
But it is actually
For eyes
It is enough for the entrepreneurs out there who are in these fields you mentioned a eye but there's a
Also
IRT in general Big Data V Garver robotics
Self-driving vehicles
It was of the kinds of
Disruptive
Startups that the clear fund is looking at
So
Stay tuned for that
Or
Reach out to them if
Do you have a brother
Okay
Next Step
We've got
Another fundraising
This is
Yeah we don't know if it's his Voodoo or V2 I'm going with voodoo
X video oh so I'm going with V2
So
Voodoo or video
Raised 32 million in
Second-round financing and this is a company that does iot device security at the embedded
And I actually wrote about them
Probably a year ago
They want to do two things
I want to make it really easy for every device
Sneaker
To get security on their devices
And they want to make it really easy to
The way they do this is they're trying to create this database of device types
Vulnerabilities and best practices associated with each device
It's doing this on its own without
Work from the companies for building devices
So it's trying to extract this information from websites from
Various
LPS
And then it's trying to use AI to assign rules to
Taxo
If it's an HVAC controller for example it's going to say hey in HVAC controller should never talk to any website
Except for the manufacture
So if it sees anything outside of those rules your behavior outside of those
It won't let it
Happen
What's
Exciting here is it doing that automatically Sono it person has to sit down
Figure out every device on the network
And figure out rules for the
This is like an AI kind of play almost ASU said like identify the
Potential threats of a device-level
And also some big data analysis from what I gather because
What they've done is they've a dataset of 70 million
Embedded system binaries
So walked between the firmware and the software that run on devices
And
According to them
This is true or not but doing less
18 months they say
That they've helped mitigate
Total of 150 zero-day vulnerabilities
And more than 100000 security issues on
A large number of devices so
Yeah if you had to do this company by company or device by device on your own
It would probably take forever they're just
Looking at the whole market and try to figure out where they can
Add value by scanning these things in advance
It's a pretty cool
System they also have a test lab so when they see devices they run them in their test lab and they actually
Run them on what is essentially open networks and they see what kind of vulnerabilities and attacks
Hit these devices
And then they let the manufacturer
No
So is it
How to fold Microsoft actually has one of these they have a
I think it is a Honeypot lab but they have a formal night
Yeah I don't know the name of that interesting I just realized these folks are based in Tel Aviv
They are
Call the good iot security firms for piston
Did somewhere in Israel and they all have peoples in the IDF
Because
Man your IDF training
Apparently
Good stuff right
Okay and one more industrial Enterprise E I O T story of VMware
They have released their second version of their pulse iot Platte
This is a platform that does a lot of stuff
This is for companies who want
Device management
They want to integrate their devices and applications for the
The edge
To the cloud
Feels like I'm saying a lot of jargon here but these are
Kind of crucial things that
Have
They also do Edge device lifecycle management
Which means like
All these things at the edge
I need to know what they are you need to be able to say
Hey this is the software version running on them roll that back
If you have an update
All of that
Is what this song
Scary
Yeah device management platform I mean that over the air updates support container management there's that word again
Containers
Alerts and notifications so
This is kind of your
Platform management system for iot devices
Moe's at the edge I presume
It's both of the edge and in the cloud is basically what you're going to do is if you have
Iot devices and an application that's pulling for these devices it lets you see
The infrastructure associated with that apple
Application in
Absolutely make sense
I know they're competing platforms that do similar things
Microsoft Google and Amazon so
Throw your hat in the ring VMware I love it
This is for people who are doing things on premise
You probably can do this I know that VMware has deals with AWS and I believe with Microsoft
What's I'm unclear as to how
Deeply you could
Integrate with their systems are on their clouds
With us but
Just more tools out there for the
Shirley Caesar and
Let's talk about the smart home for a little bit we've got Amazon
He
You guys are probably familiar with this program
Don't need a lot of people who have it implemented
But what it does is the Amazon Key Program
Let's
Amazon
Packages be delivered inside your house if you have certain door locks
Camera for your car
Now it's expanding to
Your car rise thanks to a deal that we talked about
Before with Chamberlain and it's my cue
Platform
I wonder how many people's garages are clean enough to leave up
I'm so upset you guys cuz I pooped out
Literally
Literally on Monday
And this news came out on Tuesday
And the ability to test it out
Came out then two
So I couldn't test out this functionality but I think it's probably going to be super appealing to a lot of people
Who didn't want to let an Amazon delivery person inside their house
But letting someone inside
Garages usually lower
Right right because typically you'll have an interior door to your garage from your home and most people I think we keep that locked
A lot of people don't actually lock it
I just called into slippers Amazon
Let those Amazon people in the house
You could start locking
Or you could have her
An automatic lock that you can remotely lock When You're Expecting Amazon
But
I like this idea I like the idea of letting someone
My garage the nice thing about the Chamberlain is it
Amazon person forgets to close the garage which they shouldn't be
Because there's going to be
Integration
Their stuff that says they closed it
But if they haven't the Chamberlain thing will actually let you
Angie.
Amazon
Should add as a service for this the ability to say
When the package is
Asteria meaning it's about to be delivered to my house
Make sure that my garage door
The interior door is locked if it's not lock it
I like it
Okay
And speaking of doors
Arlo
Is going to the front door
They're going to release a video doorbell according to Dave Zach's from
Zatznotfunny
Tom harbin
Are you excited about an hour
Well I don't really use
Any Arlo products and as I look at this it kind of looks like the nest
To me which is what I do use
So
I'm not in the market for one but if I was I would be interested in this yes
I'm kind of like
Why does everyone need a video doorbell
The market is totally saturated like how many options
Well you could say the same about webcams you can say the same night
Oh I will
It's not out yet
This is still theoretical
We should talk about our Lotus briefly because it is now
Publicly traded companies so it makes sense that they have to
Expand their product line Beyond cameras
And that's why it exists quite frankly it doesn't do anything differently it's
Snow 2 megapixel camera full HD video quality
I watch you love you two way audio etcetera so it's no different than anything else on the market but
You're right they have to expand the product line
And we have pricing on this
We do not we have basically a photo screenshot of the doorbell
As well as a
Marketing piece that shows the suite of products including the doorbell
Price might be the differentiator although it's not in the Arlo cameras which are high quality
Price commensurate with
Quality
We'll just see
If you're in the market for a video doorbell and you've already got Arlo gear
This probably would make a lot of sense to buy
Although if you're in the market for a video doorbell and you have a Google Assistant I would steer you to the nest
And if you had Amazon
Deeply embedded in your life I would still YouTube
So I'm kind of like
Yeah
Pick your platform
Pick your platform and will Arlo make it as a platform
Big shrug
Alright let's have a drone delivery
Garage delivery
Drone delivery
This package will come down your chimney
Now I really want probably could manage that but I don't think you want that
What's interesting about this and we're talking about
The FAA has now allowed work given
Certification
US air carrier certification
Two alphabets Wing Aviation unit
Which is the part that does the drones
I did not realize that they would need
Air carrier certification for this it's rather interesting that they did
And now they have it
When can I start
Delivering
2 homes
Whatever price you were there supporting
So what is air carrier
Ignition status
That's the interesting thing to me it kind of means they have to follow the same rules and regulations as traditional aircraft
A drone is not a planet does not passengers and so on so I'm not
Quite sure that's why I was surprised he needed the air
Carrier designation here
Well I mean planes carry cargo
Sometimes I mean like FedEx in
UPS hub
Athleta cargo plane
I assume I I just look like one of the rules associated
I don't know
Yeah that I do not know I mean
The question
The certifications good for two years I know that much
And this was interesting as well
One Pilot obviously not a pilot inside the Drone was there really small
Can operate up to 5 phones at once
And only during the day as a result of the certification
That makes sense so I've been talking to people quite a bit about my driverless cars and tell operation
And idea that you'll have one person responsible for
And the people I've talked
They're doing
Commercial vehicle
Commercial truck
Transport
They have
One person operating
Autonomous vehicles
And so
It's kind of an interesting
This idea of like
How are we
Going to have these autonomous futures
And by how much can you reduce the human
Presents
Because basically we think of this is like the robots are taking over but what's really happening is the robot for help
Happiness scale
And you saw this back in the day when we had
Servers Avenue used to be like
Way Back Inn
Backwood everyone had a server Closet in their office
Late 90s early aughts you had like one person can manage 5 to 10
Cerberus basically
And then what has happened is now where to point where it
Google Amazon one person can manage
And
We're probably going to see something similar as our Automation and management gets better for
Autonomous vehicles
I would even say things like
Connected devices like right now in a
Building when you have a building management system
You might have one facilities person who manages
A floor
Connected devices usually it's broken down by the
Types of pie
Alexa one person for the lighting platform on
Window platform
But
We often forget that there's this huge intermediate step in
Little intermittent
Leaps of progress we're basically just
Allowing one person to manage
And letting software
Take over the rest
How many times we have that for the smart home because
You and I are probably the point people in our homes for the many dozens of devices that we have
But yeah
It's all about scalability
I totally agree with that
Yes we are evaluating
Things this is how I mean
Personally this is one of the ways I have value
News
Things just how I look at the world I'm like hey
How can that scale how many devices can one person now managed with this particular advice
You're not the only
It's a good one
It is what it is
Synthesis in the us obviously
During start deliveries in the US
Planning to start
Commercial package delivery in Blacksburg Virginia later this year
And Wing already does deliveries
And Australia
And I believe they're about to be in testing and Helsinki
It was just there
I know
You could order something by drone
That kind of makes up Helsinki Salo City
For what that's worth
It's a low City there's not a lot of skyscrapers so
I think there were like two or
3 and they were really skyscrapers they were like
20 story building
And they were more in Espanol
Helsinki
Okay
Stop saying that
All right
Wise
Is beta testing Google Assistant integration
Man $30 and $20 cameras just
Keep getting
Better
So yeah release date like that
Timbre in the wise community
Site you can follow along with those who are beta testing
You may still be able to apply I'm not sure on that one but it's worth reading
What they did to testers are seeing their seeing some issues I mean that's what a beta test is
You know kind of weed those out get them fixed such as
Super long latency times on one person reported like a
15 second delay
Before they were actually able to see their camera on sale OK Google home
Humphreys amp over the phone
But they're getting there and that's important I've been watching for wise to add Google Assistant support as well as Sono switch
I know that was supposed to be out last year
Management perspective this year but
New news on the Sonos front
And I love the fact that we like
Second delay
Life is terrible
Well it means
It isn't real use case I just love how
How spoiled I was just going to say we're so spoiled
Like I remember when I would wait like a minute and a half for a webpage to live
That I had when you were on Roadrunner
All right
Also Google Assistant news we've got
Can call them skills
Integrations
Interactions routine
I think it's if does applets
Google dance routines
Animated skills
Amana Bay by the way is our version of
Amazon speaker
Amazon stick
Special Assistant
Okay
So
What can we do
We can do more with water
Water
So now you can integrate
Leak Detectors such as the leak smart or the Flow by Moen
To get notifications
Your pipes leak
And you can even tell the assistant
Shut off your water
And also for you gardeners out there
Audi rsq3
Smart sprinkler controller
Is now available
To integrate with the Google Assistant
They're looking to they been Google
Adding support for the rain Birds
Irrigation controllers in the coming weeks as well
Exciting
So this is kind of an earth day thing talk about
Hey
Save water so the flow system the Flow by Bowen
You don't have to have Moen
Pictures for this to work
Basically the flow system is a $500
Device
Thing that your water
Yeah I was like what is that thing but water mean
Water
So you can get this
At Home Depot and Amazon we've actually had the CEO of this company on
Podcast before
Gables lovely
But it will show you
What the what are you saying it to text things like slow leaks
Which is really important
Because they're
Usually very hard to detect
Pipe bursting
Like water is raining down on you you're like
Oh yeah dude
So this allows you to turn off
Where is well
It's one of the less-expensive options out there some of the others are about $800
So
That's exciting
And
I think I'm going to install one of these when I get to a new house that I actually own which is going to be a while
Very sad about that
But
I
I think this is the sort of thing that makes a lot of sense if you have the income in
Want to focus on
I habitat
Happy, I want to focus on prevention here so I like
I also like the idea of like
What a prank you could have
Haji
Turn off the water
When somebody's in the shower
Oh that's so bad
See this is why we need
Admin privileges
Yes I agree
I agree
I am terrible no one would ever
All right
What's in the news portion on
An exciting bit of news that I found in
I have a husband who is allergic to fire ants
And so we used to
In college together we'd go out places with our friends and
Fight places to wear Outdoors over who would have to inject his EpiPen
If he got bit by a fire ant
Count me out
Yeah
We rise like Madden
Now that he's my husband I totally would.
Bananas fiber
Right
So the folks at Rice University
I built a prototype
Device that you
Where on your wrist
And it does the injection for you so you press this button and
Can you inject epinephrine into someone's system so this is
For children
Mostly or but it could have been for my
My husband back in the day
You're so squeamish
And this is not something you can buy yet
But it is really exciting I think
That you have this device that you
You can wear around your wrist very clunky and you just press this button is like
It's a smart app rotates a little bulky obviously this is a prototype
But this is fantastic not connected I could
I'd like to see somebody get out
People hit like that panic button on their phone or watch to be able to
Have it automatically inject if it detects whatever needs to be detected I don't know
Can before you go into
Anaphylactic shock there must be some way to detect that
I also wonder if this ever comes to Market if it
Piers in
What's a combat uniforms or gear
Oh that's really interesting
Yeah you could like give your soldier a burst of
Yeah
Here's your adrenaline shot get up Soldier
Wow
The same size
Cuz that's totally built it as a built-in feature in all of the lake
Space suit
Combat suits
Yeah, batsuits Bae Suzy and I
I'm building my own for the zombie apocalypse I think they'll include this
Yeah get that in there so we'll look in here for this it's obviously still a prototype really interesting
Plus it's from one of my favorite sites
Medgadget
Is just as awesome site
If you're interested in health
And Technology
Can I plug it enough
Just love it
So that's how about it for news this week
I will tell you guys next week
All about
My smart home moving Adventures since I'm now officially out of my house in
I temporarily
Temporarily temporarily officially out of one house into a
Apartment
Where I'm not installing anything
Well actually I am so I'll tell you about that
And now it is time for The Internet of Things podcast
Hotline
We have a wonderful voice mail asking about sensors
The podcast
Hotline is sponsored by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio in the world afero provides a
Iproven iot platform that doesn't risk your brand
Apeiro customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market and tenex higher activation
You
Can learn more at a pharaoh
Dot IO
So this week's voicemail is from
Json and if you
Would like to leave a voicemail and ask us a question
You will be entered to win a
Next. IO alarm system
The ties into
Your existing
Wired alarm system
And connect via SmartThings
This kind of nerdy DIY project
But I know you guys are out there
So
Do you want to be entered to win that
Call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
And leave us your question
Or
You could just leave us here
We may or may not answer
We'd love to hear from you
Alright this week's voicemail is from
Json
IStation Kevin this is JC
I've been automating my home but I'm
I was wondering
You could recommend
A sensor to put in each
Set monitor sings like
Humidity motion and Light
I don't currently have a hub
But that isn't ever the question
Your suggestions would be helped
Jason I'm so glad you asked this question because now I can tell you about my
Spirit Center
In like the whole wide world
I'm not kidding
You guys this is the aeotec
Multisensor 6
I
Love this
Pretty
Dysfunctional
And you can actually install it
Recessed
So it's not even like super visible
Catches
It is expensive
It's about 60 bucks
But for all of that you get a motion sensor
A temperature sensor
A light sensor
Humidity sensor
A vibration sensor and
A UV sensor
All of that is
Pretty freaking awesome and I will tell you having tested the sensor out
It is very accurate
And
Latency is
Greeley
Low on
The SmartThings platform which is what I tried it up again
So this is a Z-Wave sensor you will need
Hub with
I would recommend SmartThings
The Furious stuff works well with it works well with openhab home assistant
Lots of other products
So
Yeah there are some other alternatives
On the market for Barro's motion sensors also the same price range about $60
It's lacking humidity if I recall correctly so
Obviously at the same price I probably go with
Aerotek
Stacey recommended
$60 per room kinetic quickly so I only mention this with a caveat
Monoprice makes a Z-Wave Plus
Sensor for motion temperature humidity and Light
It's only $30
However
Most of the reviews on Amazon where you can purchase it for $30 are in the negative category so
Treme I probably spend $90 and get one of each the Monoprice in the Aerotek
You can always return the one that's
Not working well for you and then
Equip all of the rooms at the one that does work best for you
Yes and there's also a device from
Zoos
Z o o z
That is
$33
This particular sensor only works with
Open system so the securifi almond
Which is popcorn we don't talk a lot about
What is a good platform
Home assistant habitat SmartThings you are going to need a custom device Handler
Murphy's on Spa
Thanks lots of options
Lots of options
Yay go sensor it up
And actually
Let us know what you think
We always love feedback
So in terms of like hate this works really well for being this case but not really well in that
And remember if you guys want to
Call us and ask us a question
You can
Just call us at 512-623-7424
And get on the show definitely be entered to win
And that's it for this week
News segment
Stay tuned for
Denny Huang who is one of the creators of the iot inspector software that lets you know what
Devices you have on your network and how they're behaving
He's going to tell us about
The creation of this product and answer some questions
Stay tuned for that
After a message
From our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is so
Software Ag and I have John Weiss
Who is the director of solution
Texture for iot and analytics at software AG
Hi John how are you doing
Hey Stacey great to be here thanks for having
All right we'll John we talked about Edge robotics what to do with data and a
A lot more so far in the series
This week we're going to talk about software AG being
Open an
But first
What's reminder audience
What it is that software AG does
And what it has to offer the io
Software AG has been an Innovative software company
50 years
We're global company headquartered in Germany
And 70% of Fortune 1000 companies use our Solutions we're best known for our integration in
Business process and
Of course iot
And Analytics
Specifically
We have a platform called cumulus City Iowa
Which is a very highly ranked
Open
Independent platform that does
Everything from managing devices to
Condition-based monitoring
Predictive Analytics
And everything in between
Best of all
You can get up and running in a matter of
Minutes
Not weeks
Not much
Using our intuitive
Drag and drop interface
At available s
Nice
All right so companies use the phrase open and independent
A lot
What do you guys mean
Buy open
Buy open I mean the whole platform is a
Accessible via secure API
Which allow you to interface
Chewy
From other Solutions
As well as completely Taylor VII
Platform to your name
This what you access your data anywhere anytime
Buy
I mean we are one of the
Only vendor
They can take the same code base
And run it anywhere
At the edge on Prim
In a data center
Private cloud
Public cloud
The possibilities are
Endless we have customers running the platform in AWS Azure Alibaba
And a private data centers all over the
This flexibility
Gives you the freedom to choose your own desk
You decide
Where do you host Your solution
And how your data is stored
If your plans change and you decided
Remove
Cantu
That sounds excellent
So where can I go to find out more about software AG
And
Camila sodi
You can go to software AG
Dot-com iot now to start your free no commitment trial today
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host and today's guest
Is Danny Fong
Who is a postdoc fellow
@prince
Stemscopes Ida paw
So
He's probably
How are you doing
Hi Stacy
Me and I am so excited to have you on the show
You were part of a team that released something just a few weeks ago called iot inspector
That allows me to run this program on Micah
And then see what devices are on my network
We're going to try my best day so let's kick it off with why the heck did you guys built this
Demolition started in November last year Thanksgiving when a few friends of mine receive
Need the number of iot devices asked
Presents and they're like
Should we use these iot
And they knew that I
And I was doing iot research
Is there a way for us to figure out if he's i'll devices are easy to use
Like one way is to send those devices to Denny's
Danny's colonies in the lab and analyze
Play some but either way so that was struggling motivation
How we started
Doing this project the whole goal is to make it
Super easy for an average
Consumer
To check if their iot devices are safe or not
In their home
Or you know before
They decide to return their products back to Amazon or something
Whether they should keep using it
Sebastian motivation
I guess run average
Consumer it is very difficult for them to do what we do in the lab
Such a setting up a wireless network with running
Wireshark and analyze the traffic
So we decided that
On average
Consumer we need a
Do them something simple something clickable
That they can use almost instantaneously to figure out if they're iot devices
Are trustworthy
Sabattus
How we started this project
Okay so if the goal is to figure out
If these devices are safe to use and run
How are you guys measuring
What are the things you're looking
Coyote NC
To help our users determine if
A particular iot device
Inspector
Shows visualization that answers to Broad question
The first question is
Are my devices
Talkin to the internet
When they're not supposed
And a second question is
To whom were my iot devices talking
Occiput first point we have visualization
Such as a graph that shows
At what time your devices
We're talkin sending and receiving traffic
Say for instance we have a camera in the lab
We could see that when we're using it
Now we can see spikes
In the bed with the consumer
Overtime
When it's not being used obviously there should not be any traffic
Received
Another instance is we have an Amazon Echo
In our lab as well we ran I'll Constructor
Analyze the echo
You found that there's constant
Stream of traffic being received and sent by Amazon Echo
Presumably it while the Amazon Echo was
Contacting the server
Maybe for Harvey
Kings or something
That's one classic question
Thataylaa Construction
Answer the second question is
I to whom my devices were talking to
Show at the answer this question I expect a present
Cables
In points
Dad go devices were talking to buy in points
I meant
What is the name of the server what is it
IP address what country is what type of
Server
Your devices
Say for instance we have a smart TV or Roku Smart TV
Money started that watching say Princeton's Bloomberg live news
We could see that the TV was talking to
Not only bloomberg.com but also
Video hosting Services run by Google
As well as a number of advertising or tracking services such as Google Analytics
This table will allow us to visualize exactly
Which
Parties for a contact
These could be first parties
In this case of fire
Boombah.com
Could be start party
Team is case you could be the advertising services such as school Analytics
Got it
So I haven't used it those are somewhat
I think the fact that some devices do
Like share State information so there's kind of a their heart
Ping or maybe
Connected devices that are connected to other devices have some sort
Back-channel
Communication
And there's things like overnight updates like sometimes my devices when I'm not using them
Arsenic
Lot of traffic which can look a little weird
You're like oh
That's what that
I love having the visibility into that
I do think it's important to understand like
What's happening on the back end and I'm curious how do you think device makers should communicate
Both on Howell
Often their devices are communicating to the network
And then we're there
Communicating
In the current setting
Some smart TVs made her such as Roku and Amazon would say that in their privacy policies
Especially
Bad the devices contacts
Hardee's
So if consumers
Read these privacy policies carefully it should not be a surprising
Facts that their TVs
We're talking to a range of third-party services
That is state right now for Smart TV
Stay right now for non-smart TV such
Hive smart plugs
Is little unclear so one example is we have a smart plug a WeMo plug and some people
It was
Talking to
Some third-party iot
Control service
That would allow a user to turn on and off the switch remotely is not clear
A user
That when they bought the product from Amazon it is not clear the user with know that they're smart plug with top
Talk to a service other than the manufacturer in bloom cell
Status of current state
In terms of
Question about what we think I should do
I definitely believe that there should be more transparency and privacy
Policy
How to say thatto your product will talk to these third parties where you know he's sure that you'll be some constant stream of coming
Location
But in reality I'm not sure how
Weather that would help
For two reasons
The first reason is sad
I don't know if they haven't sent it for saying something like that in other words
If a vendor says that your smart plug will be talking to an iot control strawberry such as tuya in China
Pc-1 example
Thinking out loud
I don't know how consumers would take that and that might reduce number of sales
Tessa Brooks recent
Second reasons.
I'm not sure if
Many consumers
Understand what that means I am with you
Both of those reasons are excellent reason
And I think
There's a lack of vendor
Desire to do this because it could hurt sales
We're sending your data to some place
Chinese platform
Provider you know some
Even though it
It's totally the
Other vendors
Right inside the traffic was talking about me not be like
Any private information this could be just
Someone turning on and off switch
And I'm too someone to consume
They may just freaked out
But there's also the need to educate the overall Market about
What is problematic Behavior
What isn't
So let's go and do something else at this tracks which is
Poor encryption or weekend
And I believe there
Three things that I can see I can see devices with
No sort of security on them
Weak encryption and
Insecure
Practices
In terms of
Security of neutralization we show
Instances of no encryption
Secure encryption or we can cryption those can be very confusing labels and we are still working on the way to
Fine-tune those labels that's what these labels mean is the following
No encryption
Meaning
A device is talking to the server using
In this case
Http unencrypted
We've seen lots of instances of those
We don't know if
Devices were actually sending
Sensitive information to the clouds or not we don't have the data but it is
Away
Rest assured that all your devices
Talking to the cloud without encryption
This is actually pretty common
Even happens on
My phone sometime
Android pixel 2
I sometimes talk to the clouds without encryption
Sometimes you just to test working City
Status no encryption
Insecure encryption
The very bad case
So when Taliban cryption their various encryption methods
The most
The industry-standard today is this encryption card TLS 1.0
In supposed to be secure and it's difficult to break
But they're still exist
Outdated ink
Encryption methods such as TLS 1.0
Depression that predates
Current at 1.2
Researchers have found ways to
Sportpaleis 1.0 such that if your device is running on July 2108 encryption
There's a potentially a hacker May intercept your traffic
Extract
Potentially sensitive information in your Indian communication
Because he is well known that he
Insecure yet
We still
See
A small number of devices
Whisk LS1
10 being used in the encryption
I am not going to say what company
Some major company that makes Smart TVs
In fact
We talked to one of their customer representative
And ask if their devices used
State-of-the-art encryption
Their customer rap say something long line of yes we all in
One of the TV channels
We communicate with the cloud using TLS 1.0
Oh so they're actively lying
So not cool
Actually is aware of what's going on
You're right you are a much nicer
Alright so that's insecure
And then week is
If you show the devices using Beacon
It means that a device
Support
Weak ciphers
It doesn't necessarily mean that they are asked
Free using we Cipher Suites in their last communication always saying is that these devices
So
In a case
Where a server actually
Yes using weak Cipher Suites
The entire communication
Will be using weeks
Always saying that if we label device
Add honey wheat encryption the device supports weeks
There are way more devices
With weak encryption
I'm insecure encryption
I don't know why
Potentially devices with weak encryption
That is devices with weak Cipher Suites
Could be a because of backward compatibility but don't know why
But it may not be as bad as insecure encryption that is pieces using TLS 1.0
Okay
So it's kind of like
If I send my daughter to school with
Lunch money
She may go to the cookie stand or she make it a chicken sandwich
But both are on offer in with her money she could buy both
Are either and so I don't actually know if she's
That is correct that is a very good analogy
So that explains kind of what you guys are measuring
Let's talk about how companies have reacted
That's because now it's been in the market
Kit for a while you guys have been testing
Before it was you
At least
Are you talking to some of the vendors at these devices are there reaching out in the saying
Hey
There's an issue or maybe even offering more clarity I know that sometimes when
I'm looking at some of the places my thing is talking to him like
I take that belongs to the company but I don't know
We have actually not talk to you any
For some reason I just talked about like
Devices that use TLS 1.0
We have not reached out
Company say that old
Your devices are not our talking 1.0 we are
Time to do that once we gather more concrete evidence
Got it
So let's talk about actually
What you guys are doing with this
That's cuz there's a couple caveat by thinker
Importance for people in
1 is
The data you guys are gathering is for research for
Purposes
It's possible for me to delete it
But you probably would rather I didn't tell you
Look at it is that
I mean I know you're analyzing
In the state of
Congratulation
That is correct
We'd rather you not delete it but we give you the option
To easily be today like you want to say Frances
You accidentally capture a sensitive data
From a sensitive device always together
As much data
As possible because
So far there isn't
We haven't seen any
Non-proprietary death
Coyote research Community to look into
Ashley security privacy problems
We want to be the first
Studio session label
Where individual devices word labeled
Buy users
So that we know exactly
Which
Device
What type of device
Off this device
Was sending what kind of traffic
And there's also the issue that this has to run on
Computer
Fairly constantly
Yes
To get the data
Installed
Actually you don't need to run this offer constant
You can run this for however however long you like
Just look at the data right now
7 days
In a medium case
Users running ourselves
17 minutes
Presumably to scan their Network
See what devices are network
Just have a brief overview of whom their devices were talking to
Although we have a very long tail love you
Startran this offer for as long as ours
Hours
So we can receive a variety of use
Encases people ran this offer for 17 minutes
Okay and do they refund it or do they
Just run it once in
Check it out and then move on
Bible said that's a good question
Okay
And this is tracking my traffic on my
Mywifi net
This is tracking
The traffic
Of devices
A Wi-Fi network that you exist
Explicitly wanted monitor
Right I do have to
Check the
What is an option model
So it's not going to pick up my like
Weird zigbee things are Bluetooth things unless they talk back
That is correct inspector only looks at the
Wi-Fi
Should I expect Network
Congestion
Yes you will
In fact the way this offer work sister
It does Arby's
To intercept the network
Traffic what does it mean to stat
Let's say that you're watching
A smart TV
And normally your smart TV will be talkin trapeze
Router but with respect to running your smart TV traffic
Spurs
Go to the router
Rather for the traffic to your computer running
I need a computer for traffic back to the router
Before the traffic goes back to the internet
NYC / so you can see that there's extra packets being sent or received in the air
Absolutely airwave Esprit muschamp
With twice
Amount of traffic
Our case we've experienced
Reduced
Network quality especially if you're on a home network that is slow
That's one of the risks
I'll running out in Spanish
Is you get the greatest Network appointments although in my own experience
I have not seen any significant degradation like I can still watch TV on normally
Maybe sometimes see the image quality made a little bit blurry but I can still watch TV
Okay
SI I didn't notice any problems but this is another reason that maybe you want to run it and then shut it down
I've been having done this in
I know it hasn't been out super long
What are your takeaways so far
Have you changed your friends Minds do they want to return their products are they okay
I see one of my friends
Smart plug that send information to China every 5 Seconds
He was not happy about it
I'm not sure whether he is going to send send it back to Amazon but he was not happy about
Tupac talking to China
A lot of companies use Chinese platforms because they are cheaper or sometimes devices from
China are cheaper and people tend to vote with their wallets and so far consumers are not willing to spend more money
On something that
Maybe doesn't have an affiliation
Is that something
That you think might change as we publicize the results of your research
That's probably be pragmatic kind and that's probably be anal
I tend to fall into the pragmatic kind
I don't care
Who my devices talking to As Long As I believe that there's no personal information being lost
So I'm probably fine
When using smart plug
That talks to Sage we are
By the way yes
My smart plug
Was talking
A server is actually located in Amazon AWS
My guess is that
The traffic
In this case
It's mostly mqtt traffic or xmpp traffic
Physically iot control traffic
That is unlikely to have my name or other part of very personal information in it
I most likely find
On the other hand it's the kind that may not be comfortable
As my smart plug is talking to China even though
The communication isn't likely to include personal information
Someone in
Those companies
May still infer my
Living habits
When I turn on turn off the switch or your when I get home
Disinformation
I'm also
There's a smart TVs
I'm constantly talk to Truckers
The same way you would process web and then
Your web pages
Advertisement ads
Salvini
The other day it was still very difficult to take actions
Because
Tracking services are very
How to block
So here's why
Weekly install say
And then we would still be able to browse
Google web pages
Astronaut in iot World we're not sure if we turn off access to say
Yaga cam.com
Access to our servers
We're not sure if
Anymore because
BSR services
Dad
Are essential
Functionalities
All iot devices
The same case goes with smart TVs
We tried blocking some of the actual names in smart TVs
Some channels
So it is
Quite difficult to take
This point even though you know that your devices are potentially talking to data aggregators
Chinese servers
At this point
There's little you can do
Well that is demoralizing
I feel like on that note we should end this conversation
I don't know how well consumers understand this I think tools like what you guys are offering is a
Great first step to
Help them understand so I really appreciate you doing that
And
Coming on the show this week
Thank you so much for having me
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like me
Moraiyo Tino's sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Dot-com will see you next week