Hey everyone welcome to be 200 m
30th episode of The Internet of Things podcast
Hospice is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a stroke
Depend a show for you today we're going to be talking about a brand-new consumer-focused
Water meter monitor
That's a lot of words
And we're going to talk about Ikea's brand new
HomeSmart business you
Plus a little bit more news from Ikea about those smart blinds everyone's waiting for
Kevin migrated from his nest to a Google account he's going to tell you all about
What to expect
And Amazon
What's matinee in every car
And we have fun
What's new products from SimpliSafe
A mighty is created in underwater Center that can do its own energy harvesting
And
We've got some
Interesting news out of a Chinese
Camera company
But I wonder if it's maybe
Trend
We're also going to hear from our sponsor
Nutanix
And
Our Guest this week is Tim Ferriss
Who is
The head of a company called TMF associate
What's important about Tim
Is he's an expert
On satellites and we are going to be talking about the viability of
Satellite
Connectivity for iot
To start into it and he's predicting
The failure of
Several company
So you're going to want to stay tuned for this
Canal
A message
I'm another one of our sponsors this week's episode is sponsored by digitalocean digitalocean.
Celebrate Cloud simplifies modern app creation by combining the power of Simplicity love for the develop
Community
An obsession for customer services and the advantages of
Open source iot businesses love digitalocean for their simple predictable pay-as-you-go pricing for
Cloud infrastructure services with flat Race Across all data centers digital ocean makes it easy to scan
Caleb and expand globally without being surprised by your Cloud bill each month get started for free with a 50.
Dollar digitalocean credit at diodato Stacy
Deo. Co / Stacy
Okay
Cake
Heaven
It's time
M4
Water meters and water monitoring
So thin is a company that we have talked about a whole bunch I've even had people from the
Company on the show as a guest
And
This is an
Spit out from Belkin
And uponor which is a
Professional Plumbing
A couple years ago
Created
A
Was about $800 sensor in since gun down to 619
But this was a sensor that
Plumber installed on your water meter
And it monitored
Your home for
Ford leaks slow leaks past leagues all time
And
I loved it
I thought it was cool
I thought it was way too much money
So
What they've done now is created a $299
Product
It's under your sink
It goes under the kitchen sink so what you need to do
Anyone can install it you don't have to have a plumber
You sick
You unthread your
Curse you turn off your water
That's the first part sorry
Then you unthread
You enter at the hot water line to cold water line you stick a sensor up on each side
And then you plug this thing in
Which means you do need to have power under your
And
Guala
You now have something it will monitor water flow
It cannot turn off the wall
Water if a leak is data
So what you'll get is a series about
Alerts
And that's very different from those 699 version which does turn off your water
Yes but
I think people really didn't
Want to pay
I'm curious how with
Ashley Manor is the entire hot and cold water flow of the house just from that
One set of pipes in the kitchen
Algorithm
Algorithms are best friends
This is my favorite answer I'd like to know if your secret magic algorithm
But what they've done is they taken I mean and they do have a lot of research on how water
Close to the house
They're basically using that research and
The accompanying sensors
To understand water pressure
Carflo
And
What's cool on this particular one because they have both the hot and the cold
Water
And there I guess inside the house
They can tell you a little bit more great early what device is being used so
On the
External expensive model
They can say hey a shower is
Running
But here they can actually tell you
It's a shower in the master bedroom
Or it's your teenager shower
Holy cow
Using all the hot water
So I thought that was kind of interesting in this won't come out
Until September
But it's something I really want
To try
Because
This
It sounds like it'll do
Most of what I wanted to do
And worst case scenario I can call my neighbor
Turn off the water it's leaking
Yeah it's
Obviously much more cost-effective and I wonder if this has something to do with it because
On the prowl page it says if you have a leak or abnormal you said you didn't alert
The Smart Water assistant gives you the option to contact a plumber in app
Partnership with HomeAdvisor
Oh yeah they do have it
I don't think that's
Nefarious
I just wonder if that's another Revenue stream that partnership in that can help keep the cost lower than it would have been without it
I think the thing that keeps the cost as low as possible
Is the fact that you don't have a motor that store
Which is a shut-off that's a very expensive thing to do and you have to over engineer it because you're
Essentially dealing
With the water in
And people sound so you don't answer that
So yeah I'm excited
I am one of those weird people who don't have power under my sink so I'm going to have to have an electrician come in in
And install an outlet
Most people will
Because they've got a garbage disposal
This is something I talked about actually when I installed the Madam a power
Faucet
Thank the Delta faucet
And
Not everybody has power
Ran under my sink I do score
But in my new house I don't
Soho
I'm a little sad but I do have a junction box
For my dishwasher
You're in a place that doesn't have a dishwasher or a garbage disposal I'm going to bet you don't
Empower under your sink
And
You may we should just you should just move
Basically
Just leave same if you don't have neutral wire
It's just go
Oh it is terrible
But yeah and if you're building a new house in this sort of thing sounds interesting to you
Maybe you'll make sure there's power
Under your sink
Would also recommend power somehow behind your shower
If you are interested in smart showers
@stacy
Plumbing and electricity to go together tip
For today
This is a cool product I'm excited
Try it out and I'm sure once I do
I will
Be able to tell you more it's going to work by the way with
Madame a Google Assistant
And with if
Okay moving over from under the sink technology
Let's talk about
Lights
Blinds
No action
This is a terrible Segway
But we're sticking with
Ikea
My favorite furniture store has launched
It's
HomeSmart business
As a separate business
And it will be headed by your block who's been on the show twice
Congratulations Bjorn
All right that feels about a seller
Victoria's Swedish
I don't know
I actually did not realize it the Ikea smart home effort started back in 2012
Yes they've been doing this a while
While and what's interesting about the
HomeSmart
Business
Or what apparently was not its own business
Was that
The whole goal was not actually create things that were
Connected to the internet it was to integrate technology into things
Furniture so things like remember they have that table that does wireless charging
So
I did not say that
I did not have enough
Ivan maisel
But the
If since
Really focused on and they have a very different idea it's not just adding connect
Nativity it's like
Hey how can we make products in the hole
Man Furniture in Chennai
Easier to
And that is their core
Which is
Why they made some of the decisions
Around
Things like
Connectivity Technologies the fact that
Tri-City lights are their own system and
All of that work together it doesn't
Integrated out with other stuff although it does
Work with Madam a
Homekit
These others
And I think they're one of the few problems or tan companies because it's the say now they smart unit
This makes sense is the most obvious
What's design
Into
These products in a different way because
Products typically a that look like Ikea products and be
They don't look
Like smart
Products
Fit naturally in the home
Yes and
I thought this was really nice when I went to Ikea and talk to them about
They also have a sustainability
Focus
Most comfy
Probably don't have
So
They're not going to make connected things that just get through
They have a certain liking
Locations for anything that's connected it has to have a certain shelf life and
You know this won't go outside
A year so
That's kind of nice
And probably
But for all of us are waiting for those Ikea smart blinds
She theater
Anime eyes
I'll leave that to you to mess up Stacy
They will not be home care
Compatible
At launch
And this is going to display
This actually happened with the truck pretty smart plug
Because that was going to support homekit lawn sprayer
It was like a six-month delay before got that support so
Kind of importunate
This is becoming a trend
Regardless it is with the promise of homekit I'm sure it will happen
It's just not going to happen when the blinds actually wants
Which is fine because the blind
Already a little
We were expecting
Women April
In the fall
Hopefully they will stick to that fall dead
But I'm excited
Liking.
Ikea smart things I actually like my tradfri lights
Put them back in after they fix their Google in
Immigration
And that's something
That we probably don't say enough
But we probably should say more often on the show
With connected Home Products if you don't like it
Wait 6 months and a software updates going to come along
And probably make it a lot better
You'll just love it wait 6 months
I'm not saying that
These are not static products which is nice in most cases
Belews functionalities in most cases because
Let us talk about improvements losing functionality and software updates
Chadwick
Yeah
To those who do not know you can now
Migrate you are
Nest account to a Google account
This was
Announced back in May that would be happening at the Google IO
Event where they rebranded
Some of the Google Home Products become
Nest products specifically bee nest Hub and the nest
Max
They're killing the works with
What's nest Pro
Is probably so
That's what they said
Originally there were like we're going to kill the whole thing just Deadpool
As of August
31st people freaked out
Because
Legitimately pets
What's the big news to take in
So now what they're doing is they're offering you a choice
You can migrate your stuff over
Nest stuff into York
Google Assistant
Google home stuff you migrate all that over to
To your Google account
Or
You can maintain your nest account but after August 31st it's going to be static
And nothing will change
Machines it won't get better
Add a circuit
Correct
Correct and if you don't want to do that so you don't want to migrate Your Nest account into your Google account this way this way
If you do it after August 31st
If you like read it you can't go back
So it if you migrate
You can't go back
I don't think I don't think I can go back
Cuz I did this I ran through the process and
I'm flabbergasted
Frankly
Because
Nest has been a part of either Google or alphabet or Google again
For five years
Clearly
Google has
Smart home information that we
Put into our Google accounts with Google home
And Nest has the information for all the nest products
And yet
The process
Migraine
M&S account-to-account
It's a little daunting it's actually very easy but it's like 9 steps and there's all kinds of little guachos and things that I'm concerned
Not everybody will be the same concern products but for example
I have the nest by Yale lock
And
As soon as I migrated my account
I had to invite
My family to be part of the new Google account for the home
And until they accept that they can't get in the front door
Because they're
Passcode is no longer good
Once they migrate
My family is not too quick on the uptake for these things so
I haven't even invited them to the new home yet I'm just going to
Let them ring the doorbell other issue that I see
Is that Google says that
Call members
Have the same level of access control as you meaning me
Who used to be the homeowner
Ennis
System
Now anybody can delete me in my home or invite other people to our home and
I don't think that's a very good idea but that's just me
So
You seem like so many steps were taken here that
Shortcut it because the information is already available in nest and Google and
I'm just shocked
Adjust flapper
So I would say I wouldn't
I've wondered when hearing about your experience
With everyone having admin
Enright's
I wonder if this was a response to some of the
Domestic abuse
Complaints or
People using the Smart Home
Houses
And this puts control right back
If they're going to invite them in
You really want to come
Control your spouse I guess you just leave
People blocked out at all times
So maybe you just never invite
But that's one thought is
You just give them a guest passcode for the door lock tell them that they were part of the home even when they're not
I mean
Yeah there's ways around that I think
Partially right
I don't know if there are other legal reasons or Iona
And we should say that the reason we suspect Google
Who is doing this is because
It was very comp
Placated to manage all these integration
Are two different
So now what's going to happen is instead of having a nest brain and a Google home brain you're going to have one Google home brain
The entire experience
Which
Make sense it doesn't make sense it's going to make
Google's life easier it's going to make
Controlling who has access to certain
Apis way easier
And that sort of thing
But it is going to frustrate users who
Baby relied on Nest having
Its own brain tool
Like Thai and
Other products and systems like it
For example
Right and there's no solution yet for
This new I guess works with Google
Thrift for example
Right everything's going to be now control
Home account so things like
Are Nest temperature triggers and things like that
Will stop working if you migrate
Over and you rely on if
For those things
Sofibella
Sensor that says hey when my Nest thermostat is
It's like 60 degrees turn on my space heater
Those things are going to break and it's not
Clear
If Google's going to allow the same tree
Triggers is
Right now if you don't do this migration it will still work
Eventually they're going to
You can manually do this now right in your nest app
Which isn't going away
Your point about having all the apis and everything in one place make sense
But yet we still up to app switch
I don't really get but that's all motorists entirely
You can manually upgrade or I'm sorry migrate to your account now or you can wait for your quote-unquote invitation email
Which is probably going to be
You have to do this at some point now
Yeah and I think August 31st is
The changeover
I'm glad you did this
Ivan died I've seriously been Kevin and I should talk about who's going to my grave
Maybe I shouldn't migrate and then I'll see how deprecated I
My life gets
That's one way to do it
The challenge I have is I no longer have some of my Nest gear cuz I had a nest hello doorbell I had a nest thermostat
Stat
In a rental house I
I have none of these things
Write it made sense for me to do it because
We're pretty much all in on the Google
Home
Ecosystem here
And I do have the nest hello doorbell as well as the nest by Yale lock
So what you just made sense
That's where I was going.
Yeah
This would be you because you're
More on the echo side of things
And this was a big pool
Google announced this back in
Mets
Basically
Matinee Integrations with stopped working skills and such
However they took that feedback too hard and a longer than everything migration they announced that there is a new
Madame a skill
I have not installed it yet but that should
Allow you to
Use my tab a with your Google Nest products
All right well we'll look forward to next week
Carrying your
Haha
Amazon
Once met a man every
Car according to Bloomberg
This is not surprising
Amazon is in talks with
Automakers to
Play Padme in cars I don't know how else to say that
And
They have already signed up
BMW and Audi
Wanted to say something
Also thank you
So they've already signed a BMW and Audi
He said this
It's basically like you know you have
Carplay
And
Android
I always forget what
Trites Carthage
Android auto
You would also have
What I
Really found fun about the story is they talk to a guy who had the Amazon Echo Auto
Which I have had
It just did not work
For me and
I felt a little bad about that
Cuz like I really hate when
I have
It has no
Fishers
That's how this article actually starts because the person who tested it
Talk about all the bugs and issues and basically said my part of a beta program I don't understand why the project is not work
Because
It's connected to your phone where the matinee at is team anime app is driving all the smarts and everything else
It's just a speaker microphone with Bluetooth connection to your phone is so dodgy
Doesn't seem to work as well I think having the app on all the time causes problems
There's a lot of issues
And I think the car environment is a difficult
TV Guide
Road noise if that's car speaker noise you got all of that so
Really I'm going to say
90% of the problems we had with our
Echo Auto in my husband's car and in mine were related to
And there's a lot of variables there's so many different types of cars are so many did
Different types of phones
Close permutations together and
It's a lot
But there's not a good experience
I was sort of part of the beta program
Because
I will say I did get a survey the other day
It was from Amazon
Tell us about your experience with this
As we seek to make it better
So
Having it integrated
The car should
Solve some of the
Those
I definitely should because most people who use these in-car entertainment systems whether it's a
Built-in from the manufacturer or its
Android auto or carplay
Pretty darn well so
Are you people are like why do you need your
Echo in the car
Are in the answer
Is
The answer is probably you don't I like it because
At least once during
Every car trip we have a question that we
Oh how many is this
And then we just don't know
And yes we could squeeze our foe or I could squeeze my phone and ask Google and sometimes I do
But sometimes it's just nice to not have to
To pick up a phone while you're driving and just to say
Hey
Do that sort and yes I know I could also talk
It's usually in my
Curse it's usually not
Listening
Yeah I just I connect my
I don't understand
No no no I mean what was for this week Bobby so yes you could talk to your phone we could have done that before all these Integrations came into play
The speakers and microphones in these in car systems are
Probably better suited for
That kind of use hands-free number one
So I I just plug my pixel 3XL into
My car and just use the in-car stuff that integrates through Android auto
Flawlessly
Yeah and that's really what I want
But like I said maybe in six months it's going to be amazing
Or maybe a
Amazon will do these deals and it
Google totally deaf
Look at the product and nothing will change
Baby I spent $25 just to be
All right
Let's talk about SimpliSafe
Which is a home security company I'm sure lots of you guys have
It's very
Easy to install and now they have
A brand new door lock
Yes it's $99 it will be available next
Restaurants directly from SimpliSafe later it'll come to Best Buy thing in October
Keypad on the outside and in very
August lock
Right look inside to me
Is it route
It's definitely not round design features yes
Without a doubt it just reminds me of the August lock but
Deadbolt lock or is it like does it have a
Is it an actual lock that you install or is it just a deadbolt
Does the August lock of the day
As opposed to
This looks to me like a
Integrated
Dentals
Cuz it's
Does not look like it fits over an existing one
But the interesting thing is
It will automatically lock
And when you set your SimpliSafe home alarm just
The one downside
If you want to use an app
To unlock your door
Then you're going to have to be
Part of the company's monthly service
Yeah she's not
It's true that's true
No no no
What are people who don't use them on ring
Are you going to choose to pay for the monitoring to
Unlock my app just not going to use that picture at all because it's not free
Alright well
We also have a brand new breakthrough in energy harvesting
Which is really important
Because
If we're going to have a kajillion sensors everywhere
We cannot spend the time changing batteries I don't care
What people tell you about battery life
Even if it's every ten years you're either going to toss that sensor
Because it's cheap enough in
Environmentally friendly
Or
You're going to need something this energy
Harvesting because
We're just knocking
MIT has created an underwater sensor
That does not need
It is exciting
Its energy harvesting method it's using
Which is
Physical
Connecticut
When something moves
That's my
Non scientific version of that for everyone
But they're using
That
And
Backscatter
This is basically
When
RFC
Radio waves or in this case acoustical waves are sent through the water
They generate energy
In the piezoelectric
Center
Converts that energy to a zero
And once were in zeros and ones
Or digital
And voila
We can do things
This is actually
Old school both Technologies are
Well-researched
Piezoelectric sensors have been
Around forever
I actually have one in my Hue tap and I love
Every time I tap it it generates enough energy to
Keep that thing power
And Backscatter is something that's been around for
It's been around as long as
Talking about harvesting it for energy for the last decade or so in
We're getting better
Better at it
The cool part of this
Is
We could use this both on Earth underwater in places
But we can also use it
For space exploration and putting sensors
In place
They can generate their own energy so
You know for kids
Crazy
We can talk about
The article talks about
Putting it on
Titan
Which is Saturn's largest moon
Jersey Giant sub surface
Is ocean and we know nothing about it we could drop one of these in there
Invokana
Information
I saw that this was three
Pillow Pets
Per second
Across up to 10
Yes
Well ghetto
Bees acoustical waves
Don't have that much power
Like blowing on some
Supposed to happen
It's something
I should have saved
Because I'm so obsessed with energy harvesting I know there are also other efforts for underwater sensors that use temperature
Gradient differences
Basically there's some
Authentic column
Where are you got cold water the bottom and
Where what are the top in it
Moves that rotates
So those kind of things are also being used
Power
Underwater sensors
Those temperature changes
So there's actually a lot of really cool work Happening Here
And I mean again
Not going to send a lot of data but
Maybe we shouldn't be so
Data hockey anyway
All right
I think this might be our final story I got some news that. Way which is a Chinese
IP camera manufacturer these cameras are
Everywhere
They
Just signed a deal with a company here in the US
Pepper iot
Pepper is
Iot platform company that provides the cloud computing and
Underlying
Ties management and all that fun stuff
What's notable here is this is a Chinese company that is specifically moving to use
A u.s. based platform that is
Optimized for security
Pepper's actually done a deal with a
Iot security company that
Has certified it keeps
Pentesting monitoring their platform
As a way to ensure
The devices on the spot
So I thought this was notable
Because
Most Chinese companies they might do
Do it themselves to make you something
I like to you
This seems like a real security play insensitive IP camera company I thought it was worth noting since I
Leica cameras are so
The worst
So I don't know
Maybe this is a trend
Maybe it's not but now I feel
Maybe a little better
About buying
Cameras
When you can buy
And they're much cheaper
I think it's about time for our voice mail what do you think
That sounds good
Okay for the section of the iot podcast
Hotline
I should let everyone know that if you call us asthma
Once you are competing to win
An ecobee
Smart light switch with
Madam
Very exciting if you want to be entered to win or if you have a pressing question you would like us to maybe answer it give us a call at 511
6 to 3
E74
R24
And I should let you know the iot podcast hotline is sponsored by
Pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio the world
Afero provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk your brand
Affero customers have experienced as much as a 80% reduction in time to bark
Antennax higher activation rate
You can learn more at a pharaoh
Dot IO
This week's question comes from Joshua
Who is shopping
Hairstyles Joshua
I'm coming about 8
Spartan lights
Switch
At Walmart
Some company called Merkury Innovations
Genie
I really don't know which is which
That's a lot of information about them online and I'm just trying to
Ceased
If you guys have heard anything or you can try them out
Barry singing to take a price but
I'm not sure if it's worth money cheat in try
You can let me know I'd appreciate it
Oh Joshua I'd lied
You ask this because I noticed probably a year ago or so that Walmart had this whole Brandon I did a little bit of research into it
This is a company that
The products I actually bought a
Connected
Outlet has like a light switch no not
I'd Outlet
Place where you plug in things
And
Download the app the app is all right
It's not awesome there's nothing
It's not terrible
But it's not great
The app is the genie part that Joshua asked about because he was unsure of the name is
Merkury Innovations that Genie
Puccini is the app
And
It's a fine Prada
I will say that the company underlying Merkury Innovations with
Platform
Is a company called to you
Which is a Chinese company
They also
Do tons of business there
I think Charlie the second most popular maybe now the most pop
Popular iot
And
Those guys
They are based in China so you're going to see traffic from your Merkury Innovations products going to China
Because of
Patrulla connection
It is up to you to decide how
I
Didn't see anything horribly problematic
But I'm also not a secure
Dirty researcher
I think for the light switch I probably be okay with
I know they make other products such as cameras and such
Be a little more concerned
But
Light switch in this case
Ibuprofen
There's two issues right there's the issue of them can
Controlling are seeing the date
Camera light switch the other issue is
That could create a hole in your network
To which they could go to you
To see other things
That's bad
I'm not saying that they can
I'm saying that would be
The point here is
Is Deezer cheaper devices
Chuuya has been responsive to security
Abilities
So and I hate to be like a Chinese fear monger
Radii
I feel questionable about that but at the same time I'm also
It's not
Completely outlandish to be
Aware of that
I guess so
Be aware of that
The experience is
Okay
If there's nothing
Terribly fabulous
Terrible about it
I have that same feeling actually when I
I work with tp-link Kasa line of stuff
Honest and so
It's on par with that maybe
Less smooth
A little less fancy
Colossia
But you're you're just paying for utility Hermina says $18.88 for a Wi-Fi switch
You don't need a hug
He works with Madam a Google assistant and even Cortana issues Cortana
When does the
Phasing Cortana out of the homes
That's not
Batter for two
I can't wait to find out more about that
Because I'm sure you saw this but Microsoft hired bill
Stacy
Stasi
Who's the guy in charge of Siri
And so
I was really excited about this I'm like oh man is he going to be doing something cool with
Cortana
Maybe
Did he do anything cool with Siri I don't know
I just say that because I I find it to be the worst of the
The Big Three
All right
You'll find out
He's going to be heading up in AI
Microsoft
Who knows
But it does say
He'll quote
Where to help Align Technology strategies across the
Company
So maybe Cortana will get integrated into more Microsoft and products and maybe we'll finally see some of the cool stuff they keep
Keep showing us around Boise and enter
Surprise
All right
That feels like a bunch of dudes that
Was fun to talk about but it's time
For us to move on
To our guests this week's guest is Tim Ferriss
TMF Associates were going to be talking about
The likelihood of all of these iot satellite companies even the small set companies
How likely is it that they will succeed
So
Stay tuned for that after a message from our sponsor
Internet of Things podcast
Message from our sponsor sponsor is nutanix and I have such him
Donnie here from nutanix
Here to talk to us
Sasha
Iot is projected to be more than a trillion dollar market by 2025
What are the obstacles in the way of that actually happened
I see there's two kinds of obstacles Technical and non-technical
It is a combination of many different
Technology challenges
Challenges around containerizing
Application
Using Advanced data processing Concepts
It's a large application and device security
Literally Planet scale and so on and so forth
These technical challenges
Translate
Two non technical challenges for an organization as well they feel stretched in terms of the type of talent
Destiny 2 how to make an IT project
Successful Danita combination of talents
Kubernetes
Tensorflow
Insecurities
Vanity projects
Are you in special Starmount of time and resources connect to dedicate to them
Got it I have heard this a problem
So what is nutanix working on to get rid of these Ops 2
We have too many different things but just to give you some concrete examples
In one instance
Re-creators Nai service
Complexity of end-users having to deal with many different kinds of
Can focus more on the business logic
I'm on the machine models
Unless on how does models make of operationalize
Introduction
In another and sensory Walker Street partners
Highest rated systems integrators
To create an application Library which provides end-to-end working out the application
Is that they can get started
Reasonably complex Highway projects
And in a different incense
Rick and Morty trial
Cloud computing infrastructure
All hosted in the cloud
Electrical
Start creating Enterprise ID application
On the edge without having to deploy a single device
Nice
It's very comprehensive
So where can I buy lister's go to find out more
About nutanix
Hey everyone welcome back to the
The Internet of Things podcast
Is
Tim Ferriss
Who is president of TMF associate
He has done Consulting in the satellite industry for
Over 25 years
And I have
Talk to him
For probably the last
20 years
Various satellite issues
Tim thanks for joining me
Text Stacy
I am super excited to have you we're going to be talking
About iot and satellites
As promised
So let's
Kick it off with an understanding of
Where does satellite fit into the iot
I always think of
Hey maybe I could be good for
Obviously remote areas with no connectivity but also things like
Pallets across the ocean
What do you think
But I think the idea that
Extending connectivity everywhere it's a really important thing to
Consider the many
Customers but the question about whether they want to pay for it is a particularly relevant issue
And if you go back 25 years at home then was talking about satellite phones and say all we want time open
Call 712 Cafe why we going to
How to stop light component in that will go mom to that whenever we go outside temperature
And what happened in the end well if people didn't really want to pay for
But they were trying to buy the idea of a phone that works anywhere but when it came to it and more expensive phone with a big on
Antenna
Having to pee alot for the moving time and then he went outside coverage of a small percentage
Did the time in the end the market turned out to
Not very exciting people didn't
Black mom to stop slicing
People use that to stay within a disaster or they win
In a war
Or other
Yo situations what did I say
In the middle of the ocean but they didn't use it as a
Aphrodite
Feature that moves outside
Iot
Satellite connectivity
10 years ago people say okay well people use satellites as a backup to terrestrial lobomon to that week
Incorporate
Listen to all these iot devices and what's happened is it
Terrestrial is FM's by leaps
Sometimes the cost of satellite equipment
Cost of satellite ad time is still a great deal higher than it is on
Terrestrial side and it remains to be seen whether that's enough
Need
Satellite to justify adding in that
Satellite capability
Transporting nuclear fuel around the country. You probably want to know where it is every minute of the day but if you're transported in Utah
What's the food around the countries that maybe it's not quite so important to not so much with thankful
Exactly I'd like to buy container of $5 t-shirts
It fell into the ocean
That's alright okay so before we go much deeper I feel like it's probably important
To talk about
The costs associated
With satellites
This'll give us a good context for when we
We switch from
Like a traditional to some of the small SAS
Recall that down
Tranquilizer designed specifically for iot with a classic
Old-time system
Let's be told called where they have relatively small satellite they spend
Something like two hundred million dollars on building I like you
System and its really only good for small amounts of data
In contrast you have satellites Adamo generally adoptable
Iridium being a classic example wedding
Just spent about asleep billion dollars upgrading next
Jumpits iot is only a small part of that total offering and they have most of that business phone
Mobile phones and a growing proportion
Humble Bundle
In both of those cases they are looking
To drive iotv
Space Wolf
The cost of that systems and the amount of capacity on those satellites
Well yeah that a long way away
The beams are pretty big they might have two stacks
Very limited
And soak this about a small amount of capacity compared to what you might have honestly jio4g
5G Network on the ground and when we talkin about the cost of the end-user you also need a relatively high up
Teletubby know if you have complex Electronics because you go to deal with a non sanded and unsanded interface
All those things
Me and that you were talking about terminal cost
Twitch started
Show me like $100 for the transceiver but once you put it into a terminal lights
Hundreds of dollars
And you talk about a time call switch today at generally in the range of thousands of dollars per megabyte
So many of the services because you're paying by the message in the message of a few bites might cost
Sample sentence with even the hot 10 or $0.20
Message
And that's been the big
Acmarket
The satellite providers which is expensive if you want to use this for like LTE data services but if you got like a
Single message that goes out once or twice a day
It's just a few bites
It's relatively
Inexpensive
What I'm hearing though is on the receiving side of the radio sign in
Device that
Still probably
Add a lot of cost of the device it depends what you need if you are application
Is being designed to take advantage of Lte and you're looking at transmitting two hats SFO megabytes ammo
Then you really have to do something
Pretty different Matt uses satellite when you're paying your by the message
Can you paint multiple sensor
Ten cents the message then you really need
To be just
Setting the most
So one of the challenges
This is Ben.
Yeah maybe
10 to 15 years ago satellite and terrestrial
You know what we had to G on the ground GPRS sounds like wasn't so far behind and you can maybe implement the same after
Applications
Co satellites Inuit Westfield Lincoln things would be simpler now you have to implement
It's quite different to satellite in many cases and
That means that there's an extra virgin on the end user to really decide whether they want to go to that trouble bussin
Southwest side
On the hardware side in adding the cost of a satellite transceiver
All right
We have talked to the past about some of the bigger classic satellite providers who
Giant birds in constellations way up there in Spanish
What we're seeing now
Is a launch
Spa Sasse
In every time I talk to somebody who's talking about lunch a bunch of small sets for the iot and ideas
Is beside a satellite you could just toss them out there cheaper
They fly closer to
To the ground and
They're going to just change the world
Talk to me about
How should be
Because some of them actually
He seemed really
Track lights
I've got more efficient but it's important to know the old car
What's the original small satellite its original satellite launched back in the mid-to-late 1990s anyway
Wait a few tens
Kilograms in choosing format to Eva
Smaller today but the old
The capabilities are they still have to have access to
The Spectrum which is a big.
I don't comes fighting with some people who trying to get shared access to its own Bond
Other people have talked about accessing other satellite band
Switch fa.
Does Sally have playoffs device to access they may have looked at things like unlicensed
Spectrum laugh it's not really clear that the rules committee
Use of some of those on lights
Suspense by satellite to access dispatch
Big barrier-to-entry the technology has definitely improved
But things are not as different as you might have see it
Maybe in the group and weld it is different
That in most of the existing satellites on GO station
Turn red when talking about multi-ton satellites and we're going down to a few
Kilograms. In the world
You know we've had a video and old, vans for
20 + years they've got dispatch
Kitchen lights on
Improving ability to operate that got
Sales channels and infrastructure in different
Peace around the world end
These new satellites
Will light be sufficient
Different well
I don't even know if
Oldham will get the rights to operate in terms of access to
The Spectrum
You know that's a big area
Pressure on
Access to satellites bad
This is not is not available to Dedicated satellite purpose
It might have been in the past so a lot of this comes back to
Spectrum evening fuel Technologies Advance you have the right to operate
Can you get access
Can you deliver a compelling service building the infrastructure building the disc
Distribution getting people to adopt this is all challenging as well
Alright Spectrum I will keep that in mind is like the big scary thing to look at
I will say I feel like on a distribution side and getting
Cost Eleanor
It is just a marketing channel but when I look at deals like Amazon working with iridium on that 3 billion dollar upgrade
Example of
For iot
That feels like perhaps a really significant sales Channel and curious how you look at some of these Partnerships
Is that going to help change the name of the game
But I think it really depends on how customers decide to use satellite capability
It's not the light stays is that last resort solution just like a satellite phone is and it's
Something you
Leaving the cupboards and you take out when you going out to the middle of the ocean oil
Transporting nuclear fuel Calgary around the country or whatever then.
Something where it's a more widely accepted part of your everyday infrastructure
Can you come by month
It's not clear that the economics of change
Distribution
Can the special wine has all the economics going to work to include this in people's everyday use of iot
I don't know I don't think I don't
You seen that yet
In general I would say to rescue Lisa found
So fast but it's very very difficult for satellite to keep up
Satellites
The most serious is full and feather behind to Asheville expectations
In the last 20 years Boston getting
Closer to meeting to ask Alexa
They might meet something that someone wants because they made special expectations
From 10 or 15 or 20 years ago
But it doesn't keep Pace with what the latest is on the celestial side and X
Detectability
Okay it in terms of those capabilities are you talking about things like Gatorade
Lights or
Again the biggest argument that people make that satellite can
Can actually win with iot is because there
Relatively few and relatively small messages
I guess you're saying that the economics just still don't
Make sense
Because they're relatively few in relatively soon
Small messages
Text messages are expensive
AstroWorld iot really shift
To a study intermittent
Transmission
All very small amount
What's the date
We could meet that but the
Idea of Shifting to that
Small amounts of intermittent data is that the cost goes to a very very low
Boats to the hardware Evans
I'm so
You know when we're talkin about satellites look
How to get all twos in the multiple dollars per month
Andrew Luck
Looking at Hardware costs which are in the hundreds
DiBella's engine
Then
It's very difficult to to converge events
If you can deliver
That smoke
Statues of people
Alesso SF
Pacific visa application
I think there will be a market for that but I don't understand how
Fraud that will be
And you're right
They're already workarounds for things like
Containers at Sea and tracking those a lot of the times they're like yeah we'll just put something like a lorawan
Situation at a port
And as the ships
Come hear it enough
They're still there
So I share your Sceptre
That's not to say that there is
Significant growth that we have several million terminals out that operating
Talk like that
But
If you look at for example some of the application
Play music in the past
That idea of tracking cargo at sea
Attack while on top of one another and if you was at like 7
We need to see the satellites going over head in the
The sky is on the bottom of the stack of Thea for containers send division to ability to make a line of sight to the
And so
The ideas that everything will be direct bicycle lights
Has transmuted into
For example using
Children's Wireless on board the ship transmitting
Get to a terminal on the shed which is a single B-side terminal sending it back to a regular cycle
It's going by satellite that's not what most people are thinking about when they thinking about sex
Flight iot
You're right
That is not worth it
But that as a Gateway kind of
What is a bridge technology makes a lot of sense plus ships already have satellite links on them
Because hey
Their ships
Out of the middle of the ocean
Alright Tim I know this is a little out of your purview possibly but I am curious for everyone who listens and every time
Write about satellite
Space trash
What about it all these small satellites there going to be a problem do you have a taker possibilities of dealing with it
Well I think that
There is a move towards deploying smaller and smaller satellites because of the Haya capabilities
Is available for
Miniature isoelectronic operators who might be fairly unsophisticated in tons
Satellite because they come at this from the iot world that
Coming from the south y well they said okay well then we can build a
Flight Hardware
In space
Maybe someone
Laughlin chica launch state in the future
That will enable people to do things if they're not careful
Which could cause problems
The future
Steven Stasi secret pretty irate with a
Company that launched
Small satellites without necessarily getting
Who commissioned the SEC is resolved its disagreement
Things that I've moved forward but there is a level of response
Disability that is needed
On the pulse of people who want
How to do things in space
It's not a good idea to move faster
Drake sings
In space
If you do that to you
I still hang up a lot of problem
Into the future because I lost these satellites world
Hangman phrases
Ronaldo people says well space has a big
Places not like that much of a likelihood of collision
You know we had a collision of an iridium satellite with a defensive action satellite about 10 years ago which came as in
Message to everyone
Since then people started to wake up but
Ask new people coming to the end
Without necessarily the history thinking that they can do
You clever thing
Songs with miniature satellite they do have to be careful and
Knox
Story problems for everyone else
Wise words I wish we had followed them here on the ground
Actually for a while
Alright what is the big news for this coming year what are the things that you are looking at in the satellite and just
Tree that you actually think her interesting or worth monitoring
What we going to love focus on these assets by potential new end
We've got
A lot of interesting
Pay to Elon Musk
SpaceX launch
Consolation
Installing a lawn six
Osaka lights
A few months ago that plan to have a couple more launches before the end of the year and then more launches next year that's really good
Xcelerate broadband
And those efforts are progressing
Fast people look up Gold Bond has a multibillion-dollar market
What's getting less attention all that the many of the smaller satellites where people are looking at
Predominantly iota
Key Focus to the pin some struggle sky and space Global is Walnut made a big splash in a year or so ago
With the motor that says they talking like they talked about
Capabilities and iot
They could also in
Nigeria and other places and they have run into Financial challenges in terms of getting
The money that they need to complete that constellation
And I think if you go back to the set of stalling situation
Diamond device
With one lap hoop in the ground
A few more years
Who also now
Plank flooring
Dozens of satellites over the next few months
100 over the next couple of years.
Tumulty's multibillion-dollar bulbine consolation
In some ways is sucking the oxygen out of the market for some of these smaller sounds like
License those people may only need to raise tensor a couple of hundred million dollars
Paying attention to the big glass and everyone's worried about to face a condor Amazon might do next
Without iron plant open consolation
They worry that these small price will get
Crushed under the circle to deploy
Because it's a very new set of application
Shenzhen iot no one quite knows
How big fat mouth
It is going to be
Whether that new distribution Partnerships will
Materialize it in in terms of Revenue generation and it's easy to look at Bull bandhan sale KY
Well that's a multibillion-dollar market already know we've got a couple of million people in North America already paying for satellite
Hope and maybe they'll be lots more of those overtime
I'd say okay that's why we're so concerned about 8 I would like to buy some people like you I must ingest that sauce and maybe wear
Not going to give money to these more
Lower-profile Boulevard
The case then people are going to run into the sand over the next year 18 months I think we're on the point at which we met
I see some failures
All these small players
Over the next 12 months
I'm so sorry
Which would be a bad sign if we see something bigger than that
We see a major multibillion-dollar Soco system
So then that would be even worse but I think we're at the point where I some of these small players are need to push up or shut
Andres
Multiple times in millions of dollars in the diary near-term some signs of the red circles going on at the moment
And what happens when a satellite company
Does that a business
What happens to their constellation I know a lot of these only have either done some
Demo launches
But they still have stuff up
Yes that's right and to some degree that they do have a level of responsibilities for deorbiting face craft
If they have lost things
As we talked about before things like lights glad and Tara start writing medetai spectravite
Unconverted
Did the terrestrial Spectrum the maybe some assets that go on here so people who have satellites faction lights won't
Mother ties it to Estrellita if they caught make a business after satellites
Whistle to say
How that comes about other how that develops but if these people got to a point where they they don't believe they can
Consult that sounds like business they made much with other people who might be able to take Advanced L license
Was it say they may try
Something like
Converting the satellite license
To address your license
Princess Anne country 6 * 5
Got it thanks so much for coming on the show this
This week I really have learned a lot and I appreciate you taking the time
Price AC to stingrays
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Snooze sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week