Welcome to the 203rd episode of
The Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
We have a
Big fat show for you today
We are going to be talking about Amazon
News about Arrow so he got a lot of thoughts
About that
That we have
A crazy new device
Slash idea from Ford than balls of all things
Your mattress
We have a bunch of
Security companies buying into the do it for me
We have
Kevin's thoughts
On the habitat
Hub Plus
We've got some iot platform changes.
So
And there's lots of
Our Guest this week is
Loic
Literature
Who is the CEO of greenwave Technology they are building a risk
5 based
Processor for The Internet of Things
And is part of this
Talk about
What the heck
Risc V is
The show is brought to you
Dubai
Urban X
An accelerator for
Improving City Life
And Western Digital
Which has its own risk five
So let's hear
From our sponsor
This week's monster is Western Digital
Barry Nelson the risc V swerve core and instruction set simulator
Problem Western Digital
It's open source
It's completely configurable
It's dead already and a purpose-built processor designed for today's
Data-centric Edge
Applications
Start building your swerve court today at Western Digital
Dot-com
And if that meant nothing to you
Stay tuned for our guest
And I promise
All will be explained
All right
Let us talk
All the news that
Talk about
Correction last week when we were answering
Something on the iot
The podcast hotline
We said
That idevices switches do not work
They have had an Android app for quite some time
So know that
You're the Android User I have an iPhone
So I'm in the clear
Yes this was all my
Alright Kevin
Let's get started with our big news
The day which is Amazon
Asbat
Eero
Actually
They've announced that they plan to buy
Deal is not yet closed
There is no
Price tag associated with
Bastille so it is a big mystery
I did ask
No one told me
Show me a surprise if we get that number and it was quite a surprise that this even happen
Yasso Iero if you guys are on
Familiar is a mesh Wi-Fi router
I use it in my house
Actually ever
It basically makes it super easy to
Create a WiFi network
It covers your whole home
Eero has been one of the
Big pioneers and mesh Wi-Fi
Why they're not the first to do it
But they definitely made it a household name
So I wrote a story about the
Best and in it I talked about
Why Amazon is doing
In the first reason is
All homes need a good wifi system
Just because you put smart device
System places you might never bring a PC
So wifi
Like nooks and crannies really
They also bought it
Because 0 has access to a lot of data
I don't know and we'll talk about this in a minute if
Amazon is ever going to change arrows privacy practices zero says right now that they're not
But right now
Euro nose
All the devices in my home
Wifi base
They also know where I go on the web
Because
It's my router
It's a lot of data there
And then third
Eero has a Cyrus
Security service called Eero plus actually subscribe to it just to see if it was worth
And this is both cyber-security soap
Protect against malware is
Set a beta ad blocker
It also allows for parental
Controls in this is a kind of service that I can see Amazon wanting to either offer Maybe
2 prime number
Or just in general to have a good
Cyber security
Or connected
Devices service because
It's seeming to become
Comcast offers one
CES
Comedies like bitdefender
Cujo Norton has a
Save a little
Hexagonal
Looking device
The core
So there's a bunch of these devices out there
So it makes sense that Amazon wants to
This game
It also makes sense to offer it as a service
Then
Does it include a VPN option
It does I get a VP
PM Plus I also get a password
There's a lot there
So those are like the
3 reasons I think
In
There's also I would say Kevin is probably going
About this
There is the potential
To put
Eero
In Wi-Fi
And combined it into a spa
My home hub
What you think
I think I wrote the story that thing that somebody should do just that about nine months ago and we don't know if they're going to do
Obviously in a lot of people in fact a lot of the readers of that said they don't want
They want to keep their smart home stuff and their Network your separate and that's totally understandable
But I wonder if that will come as an option
As an all-in-one package they wouldn't be the first to do that they being Amazon combined with Eero until I got high
Because Samsung's done this with their SmartThings wi-fi system which
Includes Mesh networking and a SmartThings Hub all-in-one base
This is
Appliance on the market
Today not from Amazon not from Google I really expected them to do it so they have Google Wi-Fi and Google home
I would expect that we Elysium
I'm from Amazon the future on this
Yes and it's worth noting the
The competitive Batman
So Google has their mesh wi-fi system
Samsung
Has decided to
Partner with
Plume
Chipotle basically wifi
SmartThings Hub and eventually into other products
And I do think that's someplace we might go which is
Instead of having
These like
Little access points around our house plugged in places we might just see it built into like light switches or smart speakers
Or a variety of other things that are already in
And that would be nice
Cuz I I'll be honest
I'm kind of overwhelmed
I was just going to say less boxes less wires it starts to become
More The Hidden
Teacher in the home cuz Franklin give me something to look nice
I really want to see them all over the house I do now
Oh wait no
I don't want this in my lighting though because I don't
What I mean Wi-Fi changes so fast
3 years from now I don't want to switch out
So I take my comment back I do want it in like a hub that I can
But I don't want it better than
I'm a guy so it doesn't bother me
You're so straight
Change
Oh wait no no you're not strange you just have a different
Perspective it that's why you're awesome on the show
That's what you meant to say yeah
All right
So tied to this and what we saw it in the wake of
Hit the snooze witch
Shows how little we trust
Please is this idea that
Oh my gosh
I don't want Amazon doing all of that about me
Oh and a lot of people said you know
Where they were going to dump your oh and by the way if you want to jump your Eros
You're small
Ubiquiti
Netgear has orbi although they do have Madam a
Integrations so
You wouldn't want to act
Say that there's also
Linksys has their velop
System
And a company called so
Securifi
They actually
I don't know they pioneered the match but they were one of the
First companies out there with a
Mesh system
And they're actually a startup
Company so they have
A mesh Wi-Fi
Dumb as well
So those are some options if your
I can't have this
Okay
The other ass
That we should talk about is the idea that Amazon is sucking
What the state of right after they did the Eero aqua
Position story came out in Bloomberg
That interviewed some of the people who are working with the
Madam a
Program and it talks about
Amazon trying to get
Accessed
Data
About
When your turn
Lights on and off
When you're using things
Not just when you ask Madame a to do it
But all the time
Wonderful
In
You don't
Amazon says and I actually believe them
They're getting this because they wanted antissa
If they want to understand
How someone
Daily life at
So you can
See patterns.
Anticipated
We talk about this
The time on the show
But
Most people are like
I don't trust you
Are you going to use it for advertising
Today Amazon says they do not
Might be in the feet
Sure
And that's where
There's a huge breakdown and Trust
With the iot
I really don't know how we're going to solve
Yeah there's two thoughts that come to mind here from an advertising perspective I don't
Think that's going to be an issue in the reason I say that is
What's a your surfing on the web know you're giving Google maybe all this data
Right where you go what you're looking for
And it will recommend products
Why when you talk about off home
And devices in the home
You're not
Doing that much with them yours turn things on or off the closing door the only thing I can think of
Much wider range of information is from the TV and we're going to talk about that later in the show because that's
Voicemail question has to do with privacy and security on smart TVs
So I'm not concerned from an advertising perspective and I don't think most people should be
However
There is a
Very valid perception that win
An individual buy something
What is the phone tablet
It's up to them how they use it
And
I think people will have a problem with Amazon and Google and other company
Knowing
Am I home right now
Did I go out through this door
How many people are in the house and so on
That's where I think people are and should rightly be concerned about
And honestly I mean it's very clear from my patterns at home that I work
Or maybe I don't work
Maybe I look
Like a stay-at-home mom
I don't know but those are not things I necessarily want
No and then the other flip side of this is and I don't worry about the so much with Amazon and Google
But what if that data gets hacked
What if I can see into my house and you know exactly
Person is clearly on vacation
Yeah I mean innocent the smart home is both the solution and the problem
The solution is having
Smart devices that indicate
Your house being broken into
How did they even in your house
So
Honest friend
This is not something
For now
I'm going to trust Amazon with
But I don't feel as blase is
And I am seriously
Rethinking a lot of my
Relationships with these cup
Unfortunately I'm not sure what I'm going to
That you about it
Gizmodo has a great article actually from
Kashmir Hill
This week and it is called
I cut the Big 5 Tech Giants for my life
It was hell
And holy cow it was I really recommend to put a link to this
A story that you read this because
Was very hard for her to do her
Her job and
I think it was like a series were
Birchwood live without one of the major tech companies
Products and services for a week
So I don't know if the store you have is a wrap up
Yeah she live without one of them for a week and then
The final
Yeah it is an omen
Situation
Mary Harper
So
Sirius. Here I do fundamentally believe
That we can use this kind of data to make our lives easier and more
More convenient but I also do believe that things
Gotten way out of
Also we should
Be rethinking
This
And I'm not even sure how to do
Define this so
This is what I'm worth
On for like the next month or so
That's because this is changing
Let's move on to something a little bit more fun
And useful
Possibly used
That's true
So I don't know about you but
Baidu
Fight with my husband in bed
Over his Mosaic cover Steeler I'll be honest
And I'm actually
Can crutches on his territory
I like sprawled out in the
So
Ford may have a solution
Yeah I don't fight with your husband in bed but I still think this is an interesting situation and it came from
Fords
Lotus Group in Dallas
Got a one-off
Products
That is Courtney Ford Lane keeping bed now you understand the auto rep
This is a bed that is built with a conveyor belt inside it
And issue is when somebody rolls over to hog up the bed
Conveyor belt will move entire both of you in the bed to even out
The bet so you're not
Infringing on somebody's Lane
Second sister
Cars
It's pretty interesting I would have liked it more if it actually lift it up and roll the person over who is trying to hog the bed
But it doesn't do that it just shifts both people back to the middle of the bed because the bed is gone
And uses
Pressure points to determine when maybe somebody is not on their side so
Rather interesting funny video to say quite honestly
And you can't buy this is a concept
What I would like
His Biz basically reminds me of I don't know if you have siblings
We be at the back
The car
And like you draw the line.
He's such a he's touching me
I put my finger over the imaginary
Maybe like hahaha
This might be good actually in the backseat of a car
It's you could just like conveyor them
Little electric shock to win
In other news there's been two deals in the homestead
Security world
And as you guys
Remember security is basically the Trojan Horse to get a lot of consumers into the smartphone
So you see a lot of
Annie's buying security-focused products
Because
Consumers will
We spend money on
Where is they may not spend it on can
Thermostat
First
Then it's a foot in the door
So yes they get their foot in the door and then poof
People start buying all kinds
So
A company called
Bode
They make a really good actually
Security
They partnered with a company called
Hellotalk
Hellotech will actually
Do it for peace
They will install the security
Customs for them
Which is nice because there's a whole crowd of people out there who are like
Yeah the smart home stuff is too intimidating I want to mess
And then ATT
Which is
B name
Is actually acquired
Company called lifeshield
And like Shield
Actually make
XA DIY
Security system
So this way ATT is moving deeper into the DIY mark
Pick up some of that Mark
Because basically
The security Market
Professional and has been stuck around 20%
Are monitored
And
ATT camp
This growth
At the bottom
So two deals in that space
Worth
And now let's talk about iot
At 4
There've been some retrenchment
Yes
Unexpected ones
Yes well one of them's unexpected
Because we missed it
So I'll confess that back in December Samsung said that they were closing their iot module business
Does the arctic module business and this
Surprised us mostly because
We saw a notice on the Arctic
Cloud website saying
Hey for shutting this down
What what happened
Luckily business Korea was on top of the situation because they're about the only ones who reported
Yes
So basically in December Samsung said there
After 4 years
They're pulling the plug on Arctic
It employed slightly fewer than a hundred employees
Arctic wolf
This module and it was also a cloud platform
It makes sense
That this happened
I had talked to people who said Arctic was kind of not
All that when it came to doing scaled out
Deployment it was good for
Prototyping butt
In Samsung also wanted to get all in on their SmartThings cloud
Or iot
So I think those two things
Probably
Tight end to end
And surprisingly
Samsung's decision to
And this back in December at now
It's going to close as of
So it already closed
February 1st
You can no longer
But it's not the only one
No it's not the only one
This comes as a bit of a shock as well
Google has an update on Android things that other platform that we don't talk about it too much
And that's probably cuz nobody really uses it and I think what they're saying is
Partners to create products
Android things the successes if only come in smart speakers and smart displays
So as of this week
They say they are refocusing enjoy things as a platform
Just those two devices
So you no longer want to be a widespread build all your IRT stuff on Android things and
Sissy putting this out in previous podcast
Android things was a little chunky
In terms of
Creating devices with a very thin footprint when it comes to software it just was to
Monkey could really make anything
Yes and you had to have
Way more memory
And way more process
Power that most like
Edge true sensors and true
Anything running on MCU
Without a team is 1 gig of memory
It was up there I don't recall the exact words
Reset devices with small amounts
It was the bottom line is it
Or is he
Which is not good
For you know
Right so of course Google still has an astounding in this announcement cloud
What do they really have for the small device
Market
Nothing yeah I think it's really
We're just going to give you the ability to build
Google home actions and routines and such
And maybe we'll see an acquisition
I'll ponder that
All right let's go to some
Small
Arlo
Which is the publicly traded company
Netgear spun out for its Arlo security camera business they had really good
Q4 revenues probably everybody getting our local
They are expecting Revenue
Instafollow
19 +
That is unsub
Uprising
They
Reported Revenue in the fourth quarter of
Almost 130 million
So yay
And total 2018 Revenue was 472
But
They actually predict in 2019 they're going to make less than
Significantly less than
That almost a hundred million less than that
Or maybe just
Which is
And I think it speaks to the same thing that happened with GoPro and Fitbit and
Everyone
The tries to get into the connected consumer Hardware Mar
It is hard
So
I don't know what to say about that
Other than
Having a single device strategy
Is tough and Arlo's going to bring out new products but
It's still tough
I wouldn't wish it on my worst enemy
All right
Apple Smartwatch news
Yes I better wearable
Which is this is an interesting Twist on wearables
Sony has something a baby
Actually a product I've had in Japan for quite some time but they just brought to the UK I have not heard of it until this week is
It's called the winner
Wrist wrap
Basically
You can get it with a watch face from Sony or you can just get the strap and attach it to
Your Rolex if you have on it's up to you
What is Stone is it's taken all the smarts from a smartwatch and put it into a module that goes on the band
Any watch as notifications Fitness tracking contact list
Payments
Very small OLED screen to show the incoming messages notifications they have an act
Actor model with a much larger screen regardless it's not something I look at all the time in the fact
Watch
Lastrap you're literally going to be looking at
Back of your wrist not the watch face for all these notifications
It's also not cheap
It's about
$50 US
Yeah
GPS in the act in one heart rate sensor and someone
I don't know a price I don't see it really being
Widespread success
Watch out there if you've got that much money.
You're probably going to be using that right
Well yes but keep in mind
Android has about 80% of the worldwide smartphone market and therefore
20% or less have Apple devices which are required for the Apple watch so you're still a big pool of potential customers
But it doesn't matter I mean this is just way too much
Apple Smartwatch for Android
200 $300
It's interesting that they did not go with an Android Wear Google Wear OS watch the guy said let's try this
Do they have one of the past
But it's been a couple years since it was updated I think four years now so
But maybe we'll learn something
I say that every year
By the way
Resume
Okay
So other news
Define a little bit for you
Lucy Foxx
They are
Low-power wide area
They're based
And
Basically this is not a lot of bandwidth
But
So tell me about the data
Really cheap you can bet these sensors and things and then
Kafka communication
And it's for like smoke detectors or parking
Sensors are all kinds
Well I've always been a little skeptical of it
Because they're
More like Laura is
What is more open
But sick foxes
Is all-purpose
But
This week
They basically said that on the client side they're making public their radios
This means anybody can
Develop and build sigfox radios
With the spec
If you want to make those radios talk back to
To the cloud you're going to have to pay
Server-side
Services
That's worth
But
It's actually a
Good move
Because now
We can one see how popular
People decide they want
Embed this Orville radios for this into
You know this could broaden their market and make it a lot
Along with the radio spec to have an API
Matt will talk back to sigfox in the cloud
So that's another way that we can track how many developers actually using an API
So we can keep an eye on that
I think it's smart because they try to go It Alone
For so long
And
Benzo
Dietary they still are least
They're trying to Branch out because the only way they're going to probably expand against the competition is to open up a little bit more if not
Additionally in the future
And we are also seeing so with low-power wide-area
We're basically seeing
Laura on the unlicensed side we're seeing cellular nb-iot
And a little bit of cat M1 if you're in the
Nikki West
And then a lot of the other companies
It started in the space
Fallen by the wayside
So there was
I can't even remember the name of
There are a couple other come
How do you spell boxes
Still around
And hopefully this
Guess this helps them
Guilin at the potential to
So there's all that
SNL
Talk about
Habitat
Kevin yes
Some of our listeners have
Call us about habitat
Muslim love it
Quite frankly
And what habitat is the biggest draw for Habitat which is a smart home hub that has all the four major radios Bluetooth wife
Sicp in Z-Wave
The biggest draw is that it's all local all the data all the rules all the animations all happened on the
The device there's no Cloud involved from that aspect
And that helps you from a privacy standpoint that helps that your internet connection is down but your home Wi-Fi still up you haven't lost
Any functionality to your devices
I totally got that
However if there's ever been a product and all the products I've reviewed since 2003
Simultaneously love
And hate at the same time it is the habitat
Oh wow those are big words for
Kevin tissue usually
Kevin is the nicest
He's Fair
And he's also like
It may not be for me but it's for someone
And actually
It's funny you say that because there is definitely a crowd I would
Heartily recommend the habitat
Elevation Hub 2
And there's a whole crowd that I would say do not
Touch this light
It reminds me let me go to the crowd that I don't recommend it for. Explain why
It reminded me all the setup process reminded me of
What it takes to get Linux running
Honor PC you got to get into the Cody got to get into Eternal you have to download drivers and things like that
Tweakin tweakin tweakin to it
And for a lot of people in the smartphone space
They don't want to do that and there are perfectly good products probably good hubs that
Make it very easy to add devices to set up
Automations in routine
How to connect multiple devices together into rooms in group and so on and so forth
And you have a nice pretty little app it just does everything for you
It's nice and easy to look at and use and so on so forth
Habitat is not bad
In fact I talked to the folks at habitat
Couple weeks back when discussing this
Product and I said
It seems to me like the your Hub is really like an if this then that on steroids and relaxing is very powerful
So that's a good thing
But it's not
It's not as user-friendly as some of the other options that are out there
And it doesn't seem to be for controlling devices and what I mean by that is there is no app for habit
Literally there is a small web server
Running locally on the device that you access
Google browser
On a phone
Computer Etc
That's what shows all your devices at 3 set everything up and so on
To get to controls we actually turn something on or off you have to create your own little dashboard switch is it took me awhile
I'll figure it out I'll just leave it at that
It's just not meant for the same purpose it is
Who hardly meant for automation
You just set it up and forget about it
An unexpected Works fantastic
It's great setting things up though is a challenge
I struggle sometimes I even had to
Try and install some device Handler tour drivers
Similar to if your SmartThings Hub user you may have seen drivers wear it with your building groovy that turn Java like it
Change the language
And that will
Get your device working
You know I struggle with that I even downloaded and and try to install when I got a ton of hers and I don't know why the good news is there's a hole
Big passion community
With habitat they have a lot of
Community Forum activity
The documentation is a little weak in my opinion than your little to give in a box and then told to go to the website to figure it out
You have to want to
Spend the time
To get rid of Isis
Discovered
Groot
Get your dashboard tiles if you want to do actual on off by touch screen and so on and you can add
Voice control with
Matinee and with Google that works fine
Again except for the crowd who probably either already has grown or outgrown the traditional easy hub
Or somebody plays with openhab or home automation and raspberry pies
If you want those people this is great it's a great products $99 no fee or anything like that
The bee breath of devices are
Square very good what you going to spend a lot of time
And if you want to take her
Do it to your heart's content this isn't device radio
That whole intersection of the DIY I just want to
Plug it in and have it work in
Set up automation
Macro icons in an app
I just can't recommend it for those folks as they're going to get frustrated even I was frustrated at times and I've
Set up a bunch of hot so that's where I stand on it it's
A great product for the right group of people
That's fair
I mean in nuts
I try to be fair
I feel that you were totally fair
Cuz yes I was looking at some of this and I miss
I was excited about it but I also
I won't lie I was looking at that and I was like
I think I would have kept in it
How is Kevin review.
That's how I got this review you and I see yeah I think
Listen to you and I I mean having done this kind of stuff for years now
We could make this work for sure I've no doubt and I did make it work
But it was
Not easy at Ransom challenges some errors
At one point you would send me a Samsung button for example of zigbee button
I use that to try and turn on my Cree bulb once I hooked up the button and had I had to tell the button what to do
Turn the light on
I did it I hit it
And I took a while to troubleshoot all that and it's just
We can figure this stuff out and a lot of our listeners here
Could figure it out
Petit mass-market
Didn't want to figure it out they just want us to work
I'm pretty sure some of our listeners
Great listeners
Yeah
And I also know that some of them
This Hub and they love it
Obvious reasons privacy
There's no redundancy you don't need anything
Always be running and they have total control over everything so I get it I really do
Well if you want more on this Kevin has postage
Review and we will link to it in the show.
So look
For that and speaking of privacy
This brings us to
Are iot podcast
Hotline question from this week
So
A little note for y'all the iot podcast hotline
When is Father's Day
Buy a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio in the world
Arrow provides a proven
Peyote plant
It doesn't risk
Your brand apparel customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction
TuneIn time-to-market
Antenna
Next higher activation
Learn more at a pharaoh.
That's a f e r o. IO
And
This month we are giving away a
WeMo
Dimmer switch
He would like to be entered to win
You can call and enter to win or leave us a voicemail question
At 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
Now
Let's go to this week's question
It is from
Chris
Hi Stacy and Kevin
My name is Chris and I'm calling from Winnipeg Manitoba
Canada and my question relates
2 Smart TV
Home theater package
I know there's a lot of smart TVs these days
Some will have digital assistants
Various
Streaming services
We currently have no Smart Hub
Or smart devices
Except for our Chromecast device in our current
TV
We're planning a run over base
And I want the technology
But I also want
Security
I don't want a television with a
Camera built-in
I want to limit the amount of information sharing
And if I get a digital assistants
Is Google or madam
I want the ability to turn off
Microphone
Play Don Juan
Cordings occur
Do either of you have any recommendations
I love listening to The Show by the way
Okay
Chris
I too would want to
Nice basement renovation
If I were living in Winnipeg
Good Lord
That is
That is cold
So
This is a hard question
And I'm glad you asked
Because we learned a lot about Smart Television
I was aware that is hard to buy a brand new awesome
Big screen TV that is amazing
And not have it
Smart that's
Pretty much impossible
But we also learned
That there to privacy things you should worry about with you
Televisions
One is called
Automatic content
Ignition and basically
This is something that TV makers of
Putting in their TV
2015 and they basically try to identify
Every television show that you are watch
And send that data to the
TV maker so they
Target advertising
Sounds like
But two and this is what I think you're mostly talking
Is
Microphone
What's a lot of these televisions have microphones on them
Where the remotes have mic
It's girly
It's hard to tell
If they do or not
So Kevin's going to talk about microphones
And then I'll talk about how to disable automatic
Microphones
Yeah we did some research I literally went to Samsung
TV site because Samsung is probably the premier brand right now it's
It's not the top one it's got to be in the top three for anybody's looking for a TV
Renovation like you're talking about Chris
And
They talked about Bixby and how it works a little bit but I had to go into the device manual
Before even learning how
Basalt
Shakes down
So some TVs
Have the remote with microphone built-in
Well actually all of them do
As far as I can tell from Samsung
What others
Also have I can always listening mode
Pink Samsung calls it to me like
Voice
Wake up or something to that effect
You can disable that which is good
It's not clear though from the spec sheet if those TVs
As a microphone built into the TV or not even doesn't say that the remote has a macro
In aspects even though we know it does from looking at pictures of microphone in the end the mail how to use Bixby
So
What I would recommend is no matter what TV you think you're going to buy
Before you buy it
Look
Online for user manual
And see
If you can shut the microphone off
If you can
If there is a microphone exactly
The reason I say this because there is in the manual I think says hey if you want to use Bixby
Just press the button on the remote but on a newer TV it says that an additional and says you can change the setting to
Wake up
To be on or off
To me that's always listening
So you could use the button or not use the button for that particular set
So you got to make sure that there's a way to disable the always listening functionality
Quite honestly and it is so hard to tell I would not buy the TV and then try and figure this out I would try and figure this out and then by the T
TV that suits my needs and requirements
So basically we're telling you you have to read the manual
And you should probably
We also read
The Privacy policies to understand
What date of the TV is even
And again you should do this before you actually perch
And yes
This does suck
It's unfair
And I hate it
And
The other aspect of
This which is the automatic content recognition
Ignition which may or may not upset you
A link to an article
Talks about this
Consumer Reports but basically
A lot of the televisions that now have
Smart's built into it
You can turn that off
But it's different
And the settings were very good
Vitality
In some cases though there are certain TVs such as those that are built on the
Android platform
So like Sony televisions you actually can't opt out of
Google's privacy policies
When you
Turn that TV on
So you're going to be sharing data with
Situation and
Yeah that's concerning to mean it's not just Android TVs because I've had a Vizio TV for example
That if you can set the terms of service and those included
That means you
Sharing
Your viewing habits with potential advertisers
If you did not accept that the TV would not work
And the same thing with the Amazon Fire
TV's those won't work unless you
Looks like on okay
And you may be like well of course
Amazon television
But
Again the fact that you have to buy the device
To see this is really concern
To me and I will also say that video
A couple years ago actually got in trouble with the FTC because they did not make that data collection and then sharing very
Very clear
DC find them
What I will say here
And I don't like it
Is Whit television
You got to do a lot of research
Before you buy
And once you buy you may actually get caught off guard
Bye
The terms of service
They may not be in the mail
He may not be able to see it there
Kevin and I think that in your spec sheet
You should probably say if you have a mic
I think that's probably good for all connected devices going for
And the same goes for cameras and Chris brought that up and I haven't seen too many TVs that have cameras are out there I think that
Easy to avoid
So I would call on manufacturers to
City that I would call and Regulators to start me
That those words
Things Are
Very explicit
You buy something
And cut it around out here
Your question
If you buy a TV and
Can you read all this in this research and
You feel like you're sick
Then I would say if you have a Google home
Or
Amazon device
Those all have
Have the ability to
Manually shut off
So
Again I think
If you want to voice control your television
You're kind of stuck
Sharing a lot of data that
That you may not want to share
And that's unfortunate
Cuz it is kind of
Matinee turn on Netflix
Haji
Turn on
YouTube TV
Turn on YouTube TV
So with convenience comes apparently a loss of privacy
And what's even worse is that loss of privacy may not be explicit
So sorry for the bad news there
And the long research project
Ahead of you
Good luck with your basement
Renovation
If you guys have a question for the iot
Remember give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
If you call us before midnight
On February
It's midnight Eastern Time
To win a WeMo dimmer switch
Yay
And now
Stay tuned for
Our Guest
This week
Louis LaTour
Who is the
CEO of greenwave
And we are going to be talking about
The risc V
Architecture
Superchips which sounds super nerdy but we're talking about how it can really improve
Battery life
For The Internet of Things
Everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Urban X
It is an accelerator for startups reimagining the city life and I have one of the participants in the urban Expo
Program here to talk to us today
Meet seraphim who is the CEO
Of Newman
So why don't we get started by having you tell me a little bit about what numina
What is a data utility for City what that really means is we make a sensor that sounds delightful
And measures all different modes of traffic and streets
The where traditionally bunnies have only looked at car traffic
We actually attack
Graphtreon bicycle scooters wheelchairs by the trash can you name it even among the hickey alert
Traffic we differentiate
Cars and buses from track
And other types
Vehicle
In a completely privacy persuade cuz I are main differentiator from other State traffic cameras
We're really focused on providing intelligence without surveillance
And this intelligence
Empowered
Interactive design places
Not just for cars but for
Do you have a big vision for the future of cities
Yeah I think
We Are Young
Especially in the United
State cities being kind of grades of drinks for cars and what's really exciting to me is
Thinking about all the ways that we can use our public and shared
When we don't have to allocate so much space to cars when either cars are shared or
Or cities are just
Do things prioritize other modes of travel and that's what you meant it. We provide data around all the things
Newton Street so that we can design our street
To equitably accommodate not just cars but everything else then maybe that in the future is real
Watch that automatically pick up your trash
Shore dancing green face instead of mint
You guys were the first cohort
Of the urban X Program
What did you get out of it
Applying to or joining Urban
We had
A prototype that was really Frankenstein together
It was.
Playpen D cell batteries and a lot of special part
We were excited about urbanaxes because it gave us access to BMW engineer
You actually help us design our first design for manufacture and that first version of our sensor
We did manufacturer and deploy in for City we also broke that version a hundred different ways
And now we have our Gen 2 Center will be live in about a dozen community
Quitter and Wild
It's a bit more refined now
We actually still
Use a lot of the same design principles and the same form factor that are organized
Designer
Hawkeye
Breach
Excellent so weird
People go to find out more about urbanex
Or
If you're interested in urban axes amazing accelerator you can apply now at Urban
I've been asked.
Lashify
And to learn more about numina
Go to numina
. co. Numina. Co and we're hiring
Everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest
What is Louis
Leo Tire
Who is the CEO of Green Wave technology
Hello how are you
Good morning I will thank you
Awesome alright so I promised our listeners that we would be talking about
Chip's my favorite
And you guys are building
Processor for The Internet of Things
That uses
Risc V Technologies
So let's start
By telling them a little bit about your startup
And what you're trying to do
This is what we call a coyote application processor
Application processor a processor
Not specialized bikes
Shooting to do very well certain application
It's about to come to an understanding
Typically it's about analyzing image down vibration but also biological
And we do that
Is an extreme energy efficient
What we are looking after our use cases that works on the battery for yours
Got it so something they can take it in
It sounds like both analog
And digital
And process them
With low battery
Absolutely
We have no power sensors or small processors
You stick it on the wall and you forget it for you
I like it I love forgetting about
I hate when they
Me for battery changes
Okay
So
Let's talk about why
You guys turned
But before you do that
I got ahead of myself
We should talk about what the heck risk V is for anybody out there
What
Time taken to know about arm
Talk to us about what
Spiders
Where in Santo died
Dolese sporty forty years ago in Brooklyn and the same guy
Who invented that's what years ago
Revisit to the risk architecture
Picture of cross
Yours and came out with what we put on instruction set
Hockey pictures
The construction that
You used to program
Instead of making
The decider together with Becca University
To make it available for free
How to take over world
So they made it available launch Foundation
Which missions
How do you make the chicken
And I must say that
These four years ago
This has to momentum engine.
I'm to be Frank's for years ago when I was teaching
Mira's five bass processor
60% of the time I was
Pronoun
Not anymore everybody's list
Let's go to the idea of
Why an end consumer should
So I obviously
Like oh my gosh nerdout on Newmarket
Most people are going to think
Man you know I don't need to know this
How does this benefit
Want to get some pool.
Country music
Logos of the
Bands that you wear can be a watch or not to watch that Will analyze your movements
Analyze your biological signal
Application that is well-known
You can use iron processor today
She wants to really analyze those
And if you have a cheap solution
Today is the only thing that that band will be able to do is analyze your
But nothing else
So if you have the stuff
DU Battery Life
Ouija one day
You sure use a processor that use hydro energy
Battery life we move from one day
On this has value for the consumer
That's one example
Docker example
More of
Industrial / infrastructure business
Smoke consumer
So I can give you an example that receive
Richest people accounting
Sensors in a meeting room
I'm counting people
Every minutes
For five years or for the duration of the leaves of the building
It has a lot of value
A company in order to understand how they're building out use interrupt United so you can see
Alright so now we have an instruction set
I think what's important here is
Risc V isn't just
For the iot
As an instruction set why would you use something
So why would someone choose the least five
Designer process
You can trust me because there are as many answers company or research T-Mobile
You should talk to people all over the world
Primer in China but not only
People who say well if I receive a respite I don't have to
To pay anything to anyone
Yes or no
True that it's free so you can use it
You have one you have
Correspondence manual
And you still have to develop
The processor.
He's able
Interpret
Gold instruction
Socio there companies that are a licensee designing but processor cores on license
Cub Sport
I am not buying one of those so I don't know how much
But I would think that you have to
Play what we put on the wall
I don't know you so it's a one-time payment
I done you can use the processor with nothing royalty
The cost of your product
On the other hand you have also a lot of
This is where it gets interesting
That's Takis instructions
And innovate around
In the rocking themselves
Process of course
The one that we are using
He's coming from a project called pulp
Ulp
From xinjiang University
But you look more interesting
You can read it you know that I can discern that
Enrich
The sense that we have a.
Instructions
That's all very well chune for the type of algorism
That we want to run well on my machine
Remarkable
TV Kodi on benchmarks that
We have
The number of cycles of the number of instruction that you need
Full-time lights
Then watch it would be
Veggie curry spice processor
I need to be the same Suite to full-time better
Done what you could be on an arm processor
Translate directly
Almost directly into energy saving
Because you have
List Cycles on 2-cycle is Reggie Watts consume energy
So do in summer
People are getting off service 5
I don't think this is the most interesting
That's even better if you chant you know that was all the freedom that you
Annual notes obliging.
Licensee mobile to East batch
To the community
You're cool. You can decide to do it or you can keep it to yourself
Got it so if I wanted to do something like that with arm I would have
Very expensive art
Protect your license
And to differentiate
I couldn't do it at all with X8
Yes. What's respite
Rock
Use the Lost Community everybody
Because you could have started
Teriyaki pictures that you would go and license from the usual intellectual property
Cheap flights from seoul
The synopsis for the Cadence of the world
But she
You don't benefit from the huge community
To use an architecture that that's a lost community
What is that is that
The tools that are used by your last Community are always much better and much
And they all future-proof
So that's generally so
So people are
Cheap
No one ever says no to
Jeffrey
And then there's the possibility for innovation
The huge community
No
Why are people turning to risc V
For iot
By the way I think
Most of the application.
Louis V
I'll let you know you
I'm not saying that we are alone
But the reason is that in most cases today
R u t means microcontroller processor.
And microcontroller
So you don't want to
Frankly you find watch NGO
It's also for people that are selling Arm based processor
In a very large number
It's a very competitive
Business on you get extremely good pricing from cheap vendors
Only if you want to innovate so if you want to have architecture
To do very well symptoms
Okay if you want just to do a me to processor
Keke coutee a microcontroller in iot would cost you anything between
Gucci 50 Cent
Saving you a couple of Sons of licensees node
The same time East Rogers
You are doing your processor that use
50 timeline
Ganja benefits
I want to be able to innovate and therefore you have to
So it's only
4 power consumption
He's not for crusty iot
Sensors based on your processor
Will be more expensive but they will also have a longer battery
Flight status the trade-offs
Companies who choose that will make
Yes
That's to put season in Prospect
Let's assume that I sell twice as much as
Michael conforto
I have one customer that has a radio sensor
But it has
Uses 10 battery
Honey we moved from 10 batteries
1 battery
So in that case there is ample room for the
The customer to reduce his cost
Sure not just reduce your costs but
You can probably actually reduce the entire size of your board that's your product get smaller
Yay
As well
So let's talk about complexities here because
I feel like when we start talking about newsha Park
People are like they get very excited
We're like oh my gosh this could change the world
But then a lot of time
We don't see adoption
In this happened you know I remember this
Saint Cloud Computing I feel like we're kind of at that moment
Where everyone's like oh my God new architectures for AI
So what is it take to have a new architecture
Adopted by the world
At Large
Do you even need that
Broadly in the cop shooting scene there is a new architectural that she's adopted every time you're so
You're right it's very difficult
Very difficult and people hate
Uc's
Primarily because of what I said before primarily because of the tools
The tools have
Expedia
Because a lot of
People use that and you need something you need a really really strong case
Greek architecture
For those days
New architecture
Significant
Today Ambush movie
20 defunct proposal in the world
Maybe one maybe
What would make it the last one I think that made it was gpus
But you can use all your
So why would people want
2 greens Market
Is when they are
Fundamentally
Algorism because
This is what you
Weather in Beijing now
Performance and increasing income of power consumption
At some points are given architecture how to sleep
Dress you can get off as a stopped up we have
Take you under the council's decision.
Something you
No the same
AI
Forgetting about iot
We are very much classy guy so we are not
Trying to reinvent the wheel
We are statue in the number of
Architectural
Very well-known
The programmer
We stores
Building blocks we are making a cheat that
To avoid that you architecture syndrome adults
So the underlying RK
Conjecture
The programmers don't actually have
Have to care about it
No
To be French and we just
Publix
She's almost as if they were using a well-known research process
Would be respite that don't matter that teaches by using your programming
We provide them all the tools to hide
There is some subtlety behind you
Picture but we are hiding for the programmer of the fact that
Architecture
It's just like
Irregular process
With risk 5
If we have seen some big companies in videos using it actually to design internally
A Management Corp
Western Digital
Which by the way is the sponsor of the
This week show
Is also using theirs and introduced a
Core for internal use basically these are big
But they're not really by the way
And Google's doing it okay
As a startup is this
An advantage for you does it matter does it
Promote respect
It helps a lot
And I have an outside one of those guys
Are using the same chords
Ulta beauty supplies that have verification needs
EPL 2 hours
Unda verified the same Growers hours
The song bugs
Updates
Just really the value in software you only add
What differentiate yourself
But you benefit
From the community
That comes from the fact that thousands of people are using the same
Glass companies adopting RS5 for the
Gdb embedded
The Santa Clause I'm not processing
That they offer football team
Straight
Adult
Respite
Just because B companies just because
They don't need to go to the purchasing department
Legal department
Music
I don't same way software engineer download the library open source and use it
Not asking anybody
I like that
Has no impact on industry from
Can just make the engineering you're welcome all products
Hey productive engineers
Lower costs
Yes
All right
Will the week thank you so much for
For coming on the show this way
I really appreciate
Thank you very much
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
And remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week