Hey everyone welcome to the 218th Ave
Episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have an awesome show for you today it's a little shorter than usual but we're good we talking about nvidia's new Edgecomb
Computing platform
Sony's new low-power wide area network
Another option for those of you looking for a job
And
Some updates on news from
Amazon
Apple
And
A new law that could use
Some smart things
Plus we're going to have as our guests this week
Jerome Grand Hotel
Who is the CEO of Eve and he is actually going to give us a big update on all things
Homekit
And a bit about Eve
Itself
And we'll also hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies
So let's kick this show off with
A message from another one of our sponsors
Nordic semiconductor
Are you planning to build a product using cellular iot technology
Chicopee nrf91 60 the most advanced multimode cellular iot
Device on the market today
It supports the two cellular standards for iot applications
Lte-m narrow band iot it also supports up to 15 LTE bands making
And a true global
Compatible cellular iot solution
Also has on chip GPS making it ideal for asset tracking and monitoring
Application power and security comes in the form of arms latest cortex m33 CPU
And Arm trustzone Security and 1GB Flash in 256 gigabytes of RAM
They're integrated RF front-end and adaptive power management on the S I P
The NRF 9160 is your first consideration when designing cellular iot Prada
Find out more at ww.w. Nordic semi. Com
Slash 9160
Okay Kevin let's kick this off with some industrial action
Nvidia at
Computech
I can't believe computex is still happen
It's crazy so
So Nvidia has this new egx
Platform
Machine learning at the edge and this is not a surprise for me because Nvidia has been selling their Jets and Nana
Processors which are very that's their smallest version of the processor
They've been selling cards that support this in the industrial iot for
Few years now they actually just launched a
Machine learning support for that
I'm single stick
Which is pretty cool
But I talked to Lots
The people who are using this
In a server or on a dongle at the edge of their industrial Network to manage like to understand it
A perform predictive modeling
Or to do
Computer vision
So these are all very popular use cases that are already happening
So this is basically saying hey
BECU customer
We know you want this so what we're doing
Is we're going to create this platform and it's a set of software and Driver
Chris is going to run
All the way across several
Leadership so it will include the Jetson
And it will move all the way up to
Micro Data Center so you can have a rack of Nvidia T4 based servers
Sticker do 10 trillion operation
Is per second
That are running this song
This is good news for anybody who's basically trying to do
Lots of machine learning at the edge and
People who are trying to process a lot
In
Many of you guys might be like
Why is this even necessary but I still talk to people who are like we're not putting our
Very valuable data up
We don't want any of that being trained there we don't want to be
Infer there we want none of it
Yeah it mean if it is really been an amazing company to watch every obviously they're probably best known for the
The GPU Technologies
That was Prince I guess in gaming for the place where they started but
Damn movie
Automobiles now
And two other Ai and ml with vision recognition and so on
And you can even do image recognition with that
Little Jetson Nano
It just is a few watts of power button
That you mentioned that the 10 trillion
Operations per second for the T4 servers
A half a trillion operations per second
And that kind of processing power at the edge
When you need that
When you're using it safe for image recognition in a vehicle
That milliseconds or microseconds matter
You need to have that kind of
Accessing power at the edge so that's impressive
And I will also say that it's
Oh wow
I don't actually do with the number
Okay so
Nvidia has also done a partnership
For this so it software will integrate in with red hat openshift
Kubernetes container network
Registration platform
So that's important because a lot of people are running containers at the edge and
You want everything
Working all the way together
And
If it is also working with tons of companies from Dell
Which is a sponsor of the show Cisco hpe Lenovo
Alta bring out
Servers that are going to be
Egx
Gray Tennessee GX platform
Is
How to fix part of or is compatible with one of the two with their Edge stack Nvidia Edge stack
Can be tied in with
AWS iot Greengrass or Microsoft
Azure iot Edge so
You get device management
As well with us
What time it is I don't say Google
But I was going to say that but
User
Get uncomfortable
It was interesting ly I mean Google's got tensorflow and its Hardware partners and makes its own chips for that
I don't think this work with tensorflow but I saw mention of
Some other
Tensor cortical product
Tensor RT that's it
I'll tell you Google is not in high demand among any when I talk
Santa Fe Enterprise in India
Maybe one day
They're trying to change that but it hasn't happened yet
What it's going to take a little bit
But they do have them in their Thomas kurian
It could happen
Happys Pizza for Oracle
Sales guy so
He's an article I thought
He lives in the cave
I predict cloud computing will be big
Oh I don't think Oracle did that
Cloud computing jokes
Let's talk about Sony
They came out of nowhere
With their own low-power wide area network
And they built a chip that basically will be optimized for it
This is basically
Right
I'm kind of Blown Away that I read this correctly or is it a mistake
Transmission up to 60 miles
Yeah it can transport that's what it says 60 miles work in a noisy Urban environments
Object moving at high speed
I mean this is different
From some of the other option so I'm actually going to reach out to so need to try to get someone on the show to talk about the
This is crazy
They're talking about finding this using it to find people using
Things
It's going to transmit in the 920 megahertz band
And Sony calls at the
El trece
E l t r e s
That band
That's a long-range band we have a lot in the US we have 915
Is where you see a lot of
Long range
But that's online
So again
A lot of questions
Mostly about
Who's going to use it
Who's going to use it as an Technologies going to be in
Japan I was going to stay with that
I like using that particular
Wireless
Spectrum
Means it couldn't be in the
Us I wouldn't
Dick butt
Raichu close to our
Unlicensed
But
Sony is going to try it Japan
Show it off and
It got their special chip for it and they launched an application program
That interested companies can apply
To trap a check
We'll have to see who actually does this an influencer
Tries to use it
You mentioned like tracking things and whatnot so she's cars or
Buses
They have a drone location monitoring of a drone I would love to like control and drone
Like a half hour that would be pretty cool
Don't like
Control it so looking I don't think so
Looking at the specs
Halo as a hunter
Yeah I got something
If that's why they say location monitoring of a drill not not actual control of it unfortunately for me but
Am home delivery tracking
Automated
External defibrillator
Yacht Race tracking something I do all the time
Master time
Marine rescue Landslide reports MN
Things that take place further away than
Most other things
60 miles
Coyote
Lorawan
Which is another low-power wide array
That transmits it
Small amount of data for about a mile
So that's
Is your next longest then you got nb-iot
Which
Uses the cellular network so there's just existing
This is really interesting LLC if we can't find someone to talk
All right
Let's move from
The industrial Edge and the low-power wide area Networks
To the home
People ask us all the time
About hubs
For your smart ones that are not just Bluetooth and Wi-Fi but maybe have
Zigbee and Z-Wave
And it's always looking around this weekend on the web
I saw
Tp-link deco mesh
Network
There's no different than any other
Mesh product out there so just Google WiFi orbi velop whatever
Except
The Deco M9 Plus
Doubles
As a smart home hub
With Bluetooth WiFi and zigbee
Sonos Z-Wave
But this is
Interesting it's not necessarily new but it's not something that I had seen before
Some thinking about trying to get a review unit because
I'm happy with my wing but I don't know what's going to happen with it in the future so
What options do I have other than say
SmartThings or habitat
It's just another interesting option
And I love the fact that it's built into
Wi-fi system just like
You can do with Samsung does that they have an offering a dozen
I think so
This doesn't have Z-Wave so this looks
Kind of like the Echo Plus
You know that's a good point
Any octopuses in something I really look at only because I
Don't
Have really imagine a home that much anymore
So you're right
But the Echo Plus isn't like a mesh Network system
No it is not
As a home
Hub
Yeah from what I can see here
It's kind of limited in what it supports even though it has the three radios
Tp-link says
Roughly over a hundred devices are supported
Yeah
SmartThings has the most
Yes will it also has that additional Z-Wave radio
But the challenge with zigbee and I found this when I was playing with the Echo Plus has
Sometimes you'll bring a device in just
The network
Detected the software doesn't
Might work together
Is gym difficult
And you mentioned the Echo Plus
Tp-link Deco M9 plus is compatible with madhumeh and works with if this then that
It does not mention anything about
Google Assistant
So
I mean I'm still surprised that with the Sonos integration
Google Assistant you have to choose between one or the other so I imagine that bifurcations just going to get
More and more
Clear to us and Them
I think so I mean I don't really think people want multiple
Give me options but they don't want
To use multiple
PetSmart
Assistance in the home
I think I use it on a daily basis but I am a little
This reminds me Kevin last We we forgot to share the big news from Google / nest
So we should probably talk about it today which is
2 weeks ago
The world was all aflutter because of Google IO Google said
That
Nest
It would basically kill API access to Nest devices
And all Nest Integrations would then go through
Google home
Right after recorded the pot
The day after we recorded the podcast
Google had got so much pushback
Haha just kidding
So now
This we should have talked about last week
But now what's going to happen is
If you have a nest device that is part of a supported
Integration right now
It will stay the way it is
So nothing will break
But if you want
Provided you do not
Switch from a nest account to a Google account
Right so you
You can't add anything and you can't
You can't change it
That's basically it so
It's kind of like you know
You remember the old unlimited data
Actually in love
The grandfather people kept
10 still have yes yes but you can't change anything
You must always pay your bill on time and everything must be perfect
This is that kind of thing
So if you want to be grandfathered into your existing nest Integrations and your home works just fine
Don't do anything
Now
What Google says is eventually they're going to start launching new features through the Google
Home
Nest
Version of that I don't even know what to call it
I haven't named it yet really going forward with that and so new features will
Come there and you may miss out
You know if you're happy with what you
But I would say wait
Don't you agree
And then if a new feature comes out that you
Look how it got to have that
Recognize that
You're going to trade that feature
For basically reconstructing although
Integration City
Which may be worth it
Open my Facebook
What does she do not only is it better for everybody who has things that work with Nest today
This
Helps give more time to the third party to do the Integrations
Because basically it was a complete surprise to all of them when Google announced this
So I talked to him and they were like
Can we do about it
Oh
Yeah I know
So
Some of my people were told
Totally floored
We're not
Silly nda's
Silly silly
Wanted to give you guys update on that cuz I felt terrible this
It was just bad timing
So
Let's talk about
Madam
Yeah this is nothing major but I noticed on the
Amazon Madam a Blog
That they are introducing announcements on Madam a built-in devices
So
If you have a third-party device
Orbs you
Having fun with your own
Amazon voice Services implementation may be with a Raspberry Pi
You will be able to put the announcements
Feature in your device so that's kind of cool
There's so many good third party app
You know that work with matinee and Google home for that matter
But you always end up getting limited by what
You can't do as much as the native
Yeah and I wish that you know Amazon would be a little bit more clear about some of these things so like
I would love to have guard
Ansible
Other devices
Just to act as back-up
Capsule maybe there's an Amazon capable device in my house
That's not
It's in another room
Right
And I would like for that to be guard
But so far it's not
It's actually quite common for
Both
Amazon and Google to
Keep things
On their own devices for a little while to help sell product and then eventually open it up
In fact
Google pixel phones typically get these really cool whiz-bang features
And then three four months later they start filtering down to other
Harvard Partners devices
I know it sucks but it's the
I got it
It is
All right
So this is good news
6 representatives in the US House have an ounce
Legislation called the hot cars Act
And what this is it's going to require
Automakers to offer safety alerts
To prevent leaving kids
In a backseat in there
RC's unattended
So what happens is every year during the summer
Especially
Texas where I live
Stories will start popping up
As a parent who is left their child unattended the backseat of
And
Basically what usually happens as the parent goes to
Twerk
Forgot maybe they don't normally take the kid
I thought they dropped him off at daycare
I just got out of the car they're on autopilot they walk into work and then come back and there's a day
It's terribly sad yes
So
The idea is
Dad
This particular legislation
They want cars to alert drivers
When there is a child left on
In the backseat
And the representatives are basically saying
We are to do this we leave your keys in the car
Do you leave your door open all of those things give you away
The reason why we're talking about it one is cuz it's
I don't know what is a parent
And that's what it was in one of these states where this happens
A dozen times each summer
Is it a big issue
And it's
Terrible and I feel like there should be some sort of connected device
Help with it
Son of actually seen several
Companies
Come forth
Trying
A solution for this
But none of them have actually come to market yet and I'm very curious as to why
Yeah I mean it's certainly a fixable problem and
We first before the show star talk about it I'm like I mean
People really do that come on but then you pointed out that and how many deaths there were in your state just last year long
We don't have them here because it's been so many just doesn't nearly
Isn't nearly as hot
Maybe we do have them but I don't I don't care about the most
You could probably jerry-rig your own kind of thing with maybe a Bluetooth
Tracker or something but I mean you shouldn't be sticking things on your
Your kids are the car seat you know but
This really is avoidable and we have the technology to do it probably on the cheap
So
Why the heck not
There's companies that have like Smart Fabric Center so if you put like if you are a car seat manufacturer and you
Put a
Weighted sensor
Can someone's
RC
And I could tie to the parents
Phone I mean most people do have phones while they're driving in the
Their car
That could be like an
Yeezy
Jessie easy Ops
There is a device called the eclipse and you clip that too
Your baby's car seat
And if you leave them in the car seat in the car stops moving
It basically starts
Is beeping at you
And this is a $50 device so
That's one option there
And they did a Kickstarter
Fairly recent
They also have an accessory strap that you
You can use to strap the
Put other things
I think these sorts of things are really important
I think it's
If it's regulated and mandated
It'd be safer if it were part of the integrated car system to be honest
Like the latch system is in cars
So I would I would really like to
To see something like this
Because
In the last two decades 800 children
Have died
Yes it's two decades but these are highly preventable and horrifying desk exactly you can't put a price
Song somebody's life especially innocent
Child and infant
Or even coming over extends to pets
Sports like if that's one thing we do hear about here in Pennsylvania
People leaving their pets in a hot car and
What a torturous thing to do and then it's
Even if it's accidental let me know
It still
Horrendous
Putting out
That's a little bit of a downer topic but
We'll move on to something
May not
Be as much of a downer who knows
This may not be a great Segway photos
WWDC which is the Apple worldwide developer conference is coming up
When is it next week
It is next week or first week of June
And
We're always hopeful for him
You don't care about the fifth year in a row we're hopeful
Yeah
I think it's only the third year
Last year there wasn't me
If there's homekit news
Yay
The only other thing that's interesting is
There's been some rumors about Apple launching a
Tile like device that would tie into the iPhone
Help you find
Keys
Well it's whatever
Kids kids
Who knows
It's always a Bluetooth Bass Tracker is what they're possibly lunch
You know part of me is like
Jay
But the other part of me is like
It kind of sucks because I really like something that's
Not just integrated in the Apple system
You know
True but there is a benefit here if the rumor pans out because the rumor is that
Sensitive Bluetooth device it would act like
Airpods and bat
Pairing
Is managed through
ICloud
And what that means this is like with airpods I can switch from one Mac to another to an iPhone whatever
Are the iPods because
All that has handles on the cloud side
This would presumably work the same way so your Bluetooth tracker is
Madison iCloud
And as a result
Unlike the tiles
Today and other Bluetooth trackers were you have to hope
Somebody crowdsources
Finds it.
Tile or somebody else with the tile
Is ready
Is running
Exactly the difference here is
In theory you haven't
Tire iOS population
Looking for your device passively they never know it but if they stumble within range and their Bluetooth on
ICloud wouldn't know and the user of the Lost
Item will get a notification
So
It should handle privacy
Very well and
It should
Massive expansion
The base of people who are looking for you know they don't know they looking for
Your lost item
Well in areas where Apple
Well yeah that's it in there
Well they're sold all over the place
But there's definitely parts of
The world
True
True true
Probably don't have
You know the other thing is tile has been working very hard on a partnership program so you can buy like Land Rovers and Penn
Umbrellas that
Have integrated tile
Technology basically it's not even a tile it's just a Bluetooth chip with their software running
And
That might be an interesting business
Applicant
Right
Running putting a Bluetooth sensor inside every object and then having it run on this iOS
Network
Suddenly you have
Just a cute arant trackable
And that's an interesting future
Although again
I hate that is a closed because
Right there with you
Alright well we'll hear more about Apple actually because our guest this week is your room Greco who is
The CEO of Eve and they are a popular
Sensor maker they bet entirely on homekit that's all Eve sells is homekit Bay sensors and Smart Home Products
So he's going to talk about
Kind of where he's at with that and his take on what Apple's been doing in the
Ecosystem
But before that
We're going to hear from
Are iot podcast
Hotline
Which this month is brought to you by
Lions wide variety of Smart Lock
Lets you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions Inc
Compatibility with Amazon
An Apple product
Siri
Google Assistant
And more at Schlage
Flash IO
Okay so this week
We have a voicemail from Dodie
Blue cheese from
Canada
And she is looking for a smart home
So let's hear it. Stacey I'm calling from Prince Edward Island in Canada
My name is Jody crane
And I'm in the planning stages for a new
House
My question is in your opinion
What are the
Top five
Must have
Smart Home
Components that I
Should include
In the design of my new place
Thanks a lot from Canada
Psy
Dan Cody
Being a part of this
So I'm going to say like two of these probably two of my top five
Probably depend on your use cases so
But I will say
I think every house
Should have some sort of smart
They can connect out
I chose Lutron in my house so
That's just me and I did that because the light switches are nice I like having a Smart Switch
Philips is actually change the game
Also with LaShawn because they've launched a new device called the
Aurora that attaches to
Existing switch
How to use Smart bulbs
But still for most people I would say
To swap out all your light switches with Lutron light switches
Get a Lutron hub
And then Wallah
You have smart
She's talking about new house design would you
Is he just did this couple years back.
That house built
Would you
Strictly go with mesh Wi-Fi
Which we both use today
Where would you put in
Wired ethernet ports pretty much everywhere as well
I love myself some wires I
I would want mesh Wi-Fi
But I would put
For sure
I would put ethernet in every room of the house I did it last time
I don't regret it
If
I wanted to skip
On ethernet I would put it where I knew I was going to have televisions
So I could at least wire in my televisions
And I would probably put ethernet in the
The office
Yeah so they're obviously the time to do it is when duties
Designing building her new house I mean after the fact it's
Palacios to do and I would say when you're building a new house
Deeper than expected
Switch boxes because that'll help you with like your Lutron lights cuz they're smarter and they take up more of your
The switch box
So that's the light
We decided on
Need high-quality mesh Wi-Fi
I also think
A nest hello doorbell unless you're a die-hard madame a user
And then I would go with the ring door
But
I think having a video doorbell
Nice
You know we didn't include we didn't include door locks
That was so we didn't we were remiss
So I would also include
Keypad door lock
It doesn't have to be
Smart II don't get a lot of value out of having a Smart Lock
Some people really like having it
Like a good night routine that will
Lock your door for you
So if that's important to you but I do like having a keypad entry
Because then you don't have to
Nikes
That is a win
And some people do ever change for when I get home then. They don't want to rely on geofencing
So they might highlights or music or something to
Unlocking the door for preheating an oven absolutely
And then I would say smart thermostat there's no reason not to put a smart thermostat on your
Agreed
And
That we like ecobee
Nest is fine
Again depends on if your
How do you feel about
Google ecosystem versus the Amazon ecosystem be Kobe plays well with both
Honeywell I tried 35 that just launched the T9 and T
T10 thermostats those are nice
So those are some good option
It's like my ecobee because of the remote sensor so I think other people are there companies are adding them
And I think Nest has it you can buy a nest for
Remote sensor
The reason I didn't I think it's because you could be had them first and I switched
So I went from Nest to go get here
And then finally in your Smart House
I threw in a securities
You could design a wired security system in your house
That is so retro
Does Effy wrestler you get
It does I think
Securities personal not everybody wants to spend the money to do it and today you can really do a lot of it yourself with some
Strategic planning on
Where to put webcams for apps or sound sensors or other sensors so
Just think about where you might want to be monitoring things with certain doors and windows
Rooms and areas
If you can do it yourself in or some good
Options out there
Your packages
Okay
I was going to recommend
Abode or SimpliSafe
If you're going to do it yourself
I guess those are my top five you may want you know smart speakers throughout
Your house
Really depends on your use case
But I would add one more thing that's not necessarily for Smart's but
For convenience
I am getting such a thrill out of swapping out all of my
Electrical outlets the old ones with
Newer Outlets that also include USB ports
Yeah and it's not just for charging devices a lot of
Smaller
Smart devices even webcams and what
Eventually you are running on like micro USB
Dallas
Yes that is actually
When I'm
Doing my next home
That is going to be one of my first
Renovations is
Yep take all those
Maybe not all of them but like in
Areas where
My kitchen counter
I know that
Behind my bed
Pics of the bed
Cassoulet or were you going to have you have a webcam or something else that can run off USB
I know that's why I'm retrofitting all of mine
All right we'll Dodi I hope that helps you
And good luck
With your new home
All right
I think we've reached the end of this second of the podcast and
I would love for you guys to stay tuned
Jerome Greco
Talking about
If sensors
And the future of homekit
Stay tuned for that
And now a word from our sponsor
Hey everyone we're taking a quick break for The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Where is Dell Technologies and I have
Hendel's
The general manager of Dell Technologies industry iot
Iot Safety and Security
And computer vision
That is a lot of titles
So what is your business exactly
Our excited to be here and sponsor this second
Most people in the podcast probably know that
Surveillance cameras
It has been used for calorie video gated at the edge
For over 20 years
Don't be a sensor to become much more intelligent
Much more capable
This is a quiet customer
Look at 6
Security in Asbury new paradigm
Insecurities
And also wanted to integrate this video
Iot data
Good morning to apply analytics to make their decision
This is happening across all of our customer
It's a real challenge that we have right now
A few months ago Dell Technologies lunch the Dell Technologies iot solution for surveillance
He told me that this solution can handle
Some enormous use cases
I believe that one customer with over 250000 cameras
And another who is dealing with a hundred and twenty petabyte
Video store
That is an enormous amount of
Cameras and data
How has the solution changed
From the time that you've launched
We started with those complex cost
Bat size range
Challenges
Density of cameras and not quantity
Storage want to stop there
Downtobuck smaller system
Cities in deployment
Envoy management and lifecycle management
10 days.
30 days
Years
Want to make it easier for scalable
Cost-effective blog
I said all right. Who would benefit most
From this type of
Absolution
What great things about today
Security data
That affects everybody it doesn't matter if your hospital
School stadium
Assateague
Enterprise customer
Transformers technology that is a quart
Address problems
Regardless of the customer type
But really where customers need a very supportable scalable
Secure solution to the boy named it to the Rockets game
Great so can where can folks go to learn more about Dell Technologies
And the iot solution for surveillance
PlayStation 4 shake the time
Adele technology.com
Everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Jerome
Kraken
Who is the CEO of Eve
Systems
Hello Jerome how are you today
I'm doing great
Excellent
All right
You guys have been around for a really long time in the Smart Home Park
Do you want to just tell us a little bit about Eve's Origins
In the Smart Home
So even being a pretty 20 years ago in Los Gatos in California
And we people cheat on business free times
Our last move was to sell of a gaming activity in July last year
And since then we are fully dedicated to Connected home device
Under The Apple homekit
Platform
Okay well let's start there because
It feels like
Held so much promise early on
I feels like actually entire smart home ecosystem held so much promise early on in the 2013-2014 timeframe
Feels like things have stalled a little bit not just in the overall Home Market but also with Apple's homekit
Can you give us a sense of
Where do you think the market is today
So
Social
Is true that everyone was thinking 2:20 or so smart to a market with very very big
Promise
How eyebrows
Penetration of smartwatch
Mitsubishi in Europe
Is quite slow
And this is my schedule of
Education the consumer on
What are the benefits
That jeep
Connected home product and it's not too much related to the technology which platform
But about which use case Are you delivering to the consumer
And refilling that
Homekit is a great benefit
What was the consumer because it solved free major problem
The first one
It gives you the pussy BDT to have a seamless installation
Ulcer products
Ordon products
Install in one click
Your dress
Take a picture
The Opera
Trueaccord on the product
And you can cornhole
Zip product formula iPhone
Your iPod or your iWatch
You do not need to install
Home hub
20 Wi-Fi Hotel
Or any Gateway
Not all
Specific app
And your phone
Hopper app is on old iPhone
Origins
So in one second
You are installing and controlling a product
And this is a key benefit
That's right getting 12 uses
Okay and that makes sense
It feels like the connectivity part has really changed a little bit over the years Apple did
Make this seamless
But Amazon and Google are now working with
Gorham seamless Wi-Fi ever
What else has Apple done
To make this
Is smart home effort easier
In fact I like talking husband on
But I lost a little things
Has been communicated to the consumer
So I also work
Apple benefit
Especially in Tamil
Security
And data privacy
To be
Numbers most home away
This is the third largest island that we are
So
Today that is not anymore
Technological
Challenge
Which is more
Emotional
Challenge to cool Bay
Does key benefit of the Apple homekit platform
Twitter user on a group
And not only
So few authors fan
Well knowing what
About
Hyperdontia
Okay
Ease-of-use
Ease of installation and privacy are those the three things that have made kind of Apple's ecosystem a little bit different
It is one of Sophie and or so we should not forgot
Security aspect
Because with Apple homekit
You are really a fool
Data encryption
Between you product
Cell phone
M2 operating costs
We don't have any Cloud infrastructure
Connected home experience
Just only have
Local product
And iPhone
There is no Cloud infrastructure in between
So what does it mean
It's raining.
Stay inside the product
So what
Spiritual
American Deli Brown. Privacy
The user at the global scale
That's interesting so how do you guys work with some of the Integrations that you have I know that you have an integration with
Hue bulbs for example or
Maybe how does that privacy stance
Interfere with your ability to do some of the energy
So we are integrating other devices
The Apple homekit
Infrastructure
So it is only cheated with
Home hub
Apple TV
All the iPod and behind it happened crossword clue
But anyway
There is no
Infrastructure
To make integration happen between frog party
Product
Okay
It felt like apple came a little bit late which is fine that's totally what Apple does but
Then it also felt like with the rise of the Amazon Echo and Google home assistant
Markets that Apple through kind of the homepod over the fence and then left it there
And it feels like we haven't seen a lot from Apple on the smart
Are you disappointed in that
Disappointment
Is that
Alex Amazon Alexa or Google home
Have driving connected Home Products
Things to boys
Colt Ford
And what we see he
In Europe country
The adoption of
See if he has a voice phone call
Online phone call
Connected home device penetration is quite true
People are not using as much
Sealy as we can see in the US market
Cheer in Europe
And this is one of the challenge that we have
Yes we stopped at home key travel course your boys going forward but in fact
People eating you up on the choosing it
It is there
I figured that summer language reason is you speak to me in English I was I live in the u.s. doing 10
Speak English like this
So I think that some difficulty to be understood in your local language
Oh that makes sense
It's okay I lack of accent
It's tough you know you're out there you're speaking a second language possibly a third and then you get dinged for it
Do you feel
Because there is a lot of communication with apple when you're producing home kit
Products Daredevil
Very rigorous
Set of rules associated with
Is Apple still serious about the Smart Home
Wii theme song
How many
Apple product inside the home
Going from
The iPhone
The MacBook Pro the iPad DIY
So homepod
The Apple TV
Wishing that apple have radius
Trump ecosystem inside the home
I believe
But I mean we strongly believe
That's awkward takes a home
Shutter speed
Today it is true
Down facing some competition with
Amazon Alexa and Google home that seems to
To be in front of his friends
Watching the long run we are still feminine.
Apple has a key
Leading position in this market
And this is why we are going at 12 everyday and try to develop a pecan kit
East Cuisine
Product
It's true you guys you guys are consistently putting out new stuff which I really appreciate and I'm sure
All the people out there who are homekit enabled
Appreciate as well we get a lot of requests
For homekit
Capable products
With that in mind
I actually saw
You guys had a wonderful blog post probably about a year-and-a-half ago
About creating a homekit capable security system
I was wondering if you could talk a little bit about some of the products
Could be used to do that
Because there are lots of consumers out there who are like
I really want to do this security thing but I don't know if I want another hub
A bunch of other devices
Can you talk briefly about that
So you know it's true that we see that the smartphone market is
3 + 5
Security application
And on our side
Remember want to be a number two and number three
Inside a category
And what receiver got shenzhen IP camera in the high-tech camera
GE Profile
We're already
Quite loud so we decided to do not invest
Indus category
But for sure we are looking
How to grow
More song inside the secret aspect
And little girl wedgie
On
The fence all that
Github
Rich
Subduing window sensor
Some
Smoke pencil
A movement detector
And it's easy to set all that up as a security system using is it
Conditions are routines what is it that apple
Calls there
Turn alchemation of
I think if you're leaving a apartment
The most easy way to set up a security system
Is to cool a door and window
Sensor
On your front
Adult
Because the statistics show that
You should live in Aberdeen
If there is a break-in
Take me to enter through the main door entrance
I'm just by touching
A door and window sensor
Wikipedia for Deadpool at $49
You get another
Thanks to Apple homekit
Once a door is open
Normandin Falls always open
And let's talk about sensors forum
Because you guys have been developing Bluetooth Pace sensors because Apple supports only Wi-Fi and Bluetooth
And
This is been a tough
Area to find products in so I'm very curious
What are the challenges associated with
Bluetooth sensor
As soon as battery
I don't know
Foster to adopt
I want Wireless
Technology
There is many
Radio protocol available
And what drivers you know decision
Waze
Which protocol are inside
This Smartphone
Inside the smartphone
According to protocol
Bluetooth one
Enzo WiFi
And as many of us
Stencils
Iranian currency and battery power
Reviews for us
Den WiFi
Wasn't that possibility because it rain
Hibachi
Reality
Bluetooth
Knowing that
You had one drawback
Which is the range of the wireless photocard
And we are
Walking
You know that all to expand
These French
This is a Frost Bank
And the circle under
What we see
Easter
Ascenso
Walkie on Bluetooth
And we see that our consumer and I'll buy you one sensor
And many times
Two or three other products
Paris time
Prove that
Syringe
Is not an issue
Oh that's good yes cuz I I will say that I
And I lived in a strange house but I always had a lot of problems of like
I want to turn off my lights upstairs but I'm downstairs in the range is terrible
What about something like Bluetooth mesh now that that technology is come out and is certified is that something that you're
I'm looking at
Of course we have to investigate or Alive grade of Bluetooth and we are
Isis theme song
And do you have a sense of the
Drawbacks I I've been told that Bluetooth mesh does have higher battery consumptions just
Based on the fact that it's waking up a little bit more often
This is correct
Highway patrol office software company
Is how can we develop
A software you know that
To avoid the throwback on the battery lifetime
Off
Annies
Improvement on the Bluetooth range
And is a connected device company are you
Predominantly making your money just from the sale of Hardware are you looking at other options I know a lot of smart home companies
They're like we're going to sell the hardware but we're also going to
I don't know magically build a Data Business
Password krita subscription model
So how do you think about being in the business of
Operating something that is going to exist in a consumer's life for maybe five years or have to support it for that life cycle
Ubi clearly focusing on the hardware and I think
It's a question of pokerus because
As mentioned before Mini
Player
Are disappointed with your result of the smart or medium of Hogan you in term of business
And they trying one that tries to how do I have they tried to watch tonight it does not work so well
Let's improve my business
And moving to a doctor
A substitution
More than
And the.
If you player a successful so far
On our side we are here for the long run
And other told you before we can get apple homekit will be a winner
On the long run
And
Aspect
Ebenezer AAA is nuts
A turkey for many consumer
You really want
Internal run and we are preparing this long-term asset
And by
Digital King
Beautifully design
Products
And oh by the way
A seamless user experience
Truck consumer
This is where he's I want for Christmas
And I'm going to assume that that's why you feel like you can compete with some of the
Mega players that look like
Are now in the smart home so you got Amazon who's
Purchased ring has purchased Eero you've got Google which has there
Best line of products in there are tons of others there's Arlo there's netatmo over in Europe that are all
I'll try to compete against these guys even though they're smaller
How do you view that competition and what difference
If I look about some of their figure all that out official
How about towards appear that you mention in the number of products sold
Contrary to our story so far 750,000 connected products
That's mean we will reach 1 million product
By end of
Table 19
And in Europe beautiful player wear a bra
To delete off.
Wasanas
For what
I've mentioned before
Vintage Schumann pergola
Patrice Watson gaming
It's only since July last year that we are
Dedicated as a horse
To the connected home
And
Why would I ever
Have such product that has such numbers and such poor
Is because we are focusing
Onza a political system
And today is true well mostly
People who buy out
Product of a person
And they don't have only one if product in there
House
Athena parade
They have pork product
What home product
End
Is very high
That's what I am
Ice cream that is
A lot of
Schumer
Sin City 2
Experience
We've got the security and data privacy
And this benefit
Hazel naked
And we are seeing it as we are going and we think about going faster
The Mineola playlist
Excellent so I have to ask because I live in a mixed household I have an Android Apple home
What is your advice for people who want to use your products
And apple homekit in a bit
Mixed household
So we have developed a product two years ago which is a button
What gives you the opportunity to
Cukor
GE products
Especially if you are on void user
Okay so
I get a button
All right it is a beautiful button
And I will say okay
Thank you so much for
For coming on the show I feel like I've learned a lot about Apple
I won't count them out just yet
End
I am excited about better Bluetooth sensors coming
Hopefully down the pike
Thank you thank you
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week