Hey everyone welcome to the 228 episode of the internet
The things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
I'm going to call it a nerve-wracking show for you today
Origami talking about
Follow up on
Smart speakers additional assistance with people listening on the other end
We got a hacker warning on
Iot devices
Plus we got another follow-up on the ring
And police story
And we also have news related to Google's new Wi-Fi Hardware
A
New Alliance for location
Plus a scoop about Walmart smart home ever
We got little bit too news about
Hub for all cameras we've got
Homekit support for a new device and we've got
Mobile digital assistant robot
Capture Kevin is
Super pumped
You betcha
We're also going to hear from our sponsor nutanix
And
We have mirror of Allred who is the CEO of versatile dentures
Here on the show to talk about
Bringing iot to the
The construction industry
And you're going to stay tuned for that because
We could be building things
More efficiently
But before we do any of that
Let's hear for this week sponsor
This week sponsor is
Digital ocean
Digitalocean developer Cloud simplifies modern
App creation by combining the power of Simplicity love for the developer community
An obsession for customer service and the advantages of Open Source iot businesses loved
Digitalocean for their simple predictable pay-as-you-go pricing for cloud infrastructure services with
Flat rates across all data centers digital ocean makes it easy to scale-up and expand globally without being surprised
Spidercloud bill each month get started for free with a $50 digitalocean credit at do.
/ Stacy
That's.
. Co / Stacey Stacey
And do it just to support the show
Alrighty
Let's get started with
News about devices listening in since it was reported that
Both Google
And Madame a have contractors who listening
Two other entities
We've seen
Taliban all the three other digital
With the exception of Bixby
NY
So Apple also came out and
Said that yes it has contractors listening in
On a rotisserie improved
The quality of voice recognition and
Now
Microsoft
They have contractors that listen to both Skype and Cortana
So
The Skype calls actually
They could be listening in right now
Because they don't say anything
Okay so in response to this
Google has always allowed
People to
Opt out of having
Calls record
Now
Amazon for Padme has
Now said that
You can do the same thing
And they added to their terms of service that some of
Calls could be recorded
Tencent
Apple
Says it is going to stop having people listen to series
Utterances
Entirely
And
Microsoft
We don't know what they're going to
I do yet but
I'm sure they're going to come up with something
Probably
Akin to Amazon
Or Google's
So
I don't know Kevin
Do we feel good about this yet
Well hell yeah everybody got caught with their hand in the cookie jar so to speak
And everybody
Exit Microsoft so far has
Come to a
What I consider reasonable
Solution
4 people
Protect our privacy and terms of the voice recordings
An actual contractors are humans listening
A Microsoft for its Skype stuff uses in the Skype
Translation
It does say in an FAQ that
Skype does collector in
Information conversation to help a
Improve products and services
It does not say that
People are listening
Nor does the Microsoft privacy
There's room to be better
People don't mind
Computers in last after they really have a problem with
Which finger
The only other choice for these companies to make the services better is actually to ask
The users of the services to manually review
Audio activity and responses and so on
And I don't know enough people would do that so I get why they do it
But they should have always been very upfront about
You can contractors and then having people listening
Agreed
All right
He also a Microsoft
News Microsoft says that it has
The Russian State hackers
Rather Russian State hackers
Using iot devices to
To breach net worth
Is this surprising
No basically the Microsoft threat Intelligence Center wrote that there are
Are lots of printers video decoders and other iot devices being used as a way to get into
Networks
It's interesting that devices that they found this on
Because you're not a question but you put it on Twitter which got a lot of responses
Is a printer
An iot device
Cause
Microsoft discovered attacks in April
When
Some devices a voice over IP phone and office printer
We're communicating with
Russian servers
Exactly
And this is this got me thinking because I get very frustrated when we we talked about
Iot devices
Is a group in basically he would find out that the culprit is like
Network DVR system
Which was a big deal in Boracay
I asked and I was being completely serious do people think that a printer
Is an iot device
And lo and behold
Over a hundred people
Give me the response
So good responses
Pull the mountain
Three category
One was the group of people who tended to be old
Who are like
No it's more M2M it's not really iot
Then there with the litter list
Call them there like it is a thing it is connected to the internet
Does it is an iot device
To which I say
I don't sweat
Computers
What about
Everything else
And then the third group of people who
Probably or closer to me
Those people said
It is only an iot device
Connected to the internet
It has sensors and then
People use the sensor information
N2
Survive some business value
And that's the iot device like when I'm thinking about is he.
But
I will say
If you were an infosec
Responsible for corporate security
Then yes
A printer is probably at iot device because it
Does
Provide this whole into your network
Wrinkly sure one of those people you don't care what's call you want to make sure it's secure
And if it's
Connected to your network and or the internet
Hat is upgradable software firmware Etc
And has
Data
I can be
Captured I guess is the best way to say maybe from a print queue
Or the Wi-Fi SSID if it's a wireless printer I yeah you got to worry about this stuff
And you know they can pull stuff
If it's hacked which means I could get your secret printed
Corporate documents
Although I should say like four people were like
Wait
Why are people still using print
Which I'm like
But do not live in the
Picture
So I guess from this perspective
I would say
That we should start thinking about network security and iot security
Maybe a little bit more
Greater lady a little bit with a little bit more sophistication
Is a printer is a network device it does you have to have security around it
And you should update the firmware and that's what
Also
Two of the Microsoft attacks were using default passwords
And here's my recommendation to you
Anything in your corporate Network that has a default password should be unplugged
And recycle
Jacinda story
You should not have that on your network
Ever done
Okay
I like okay we solve that problem
But I don't know
So I'm a link to this you guys feel free to continue the discussion I
I am very
All right speaking of tough questions there are more tough
Questions for ring and various police departments that are working with Ring the video doorbell company now on
Buy Amazon
Vice
They actually reported last time that ring
Contracts with police departments to get the
Them two
Sign people up for the Neighbors app they give them
Free ring doorbells to giveaway
The neighbors app
Is an app that you
You can download
Basically lets you
Upload
Your footage
If you feel that there's a security problem
Can you search talk about security
Problems in your neighbor
Police departments
AR
Able to
Ask
Homeowners
For their video footage
If there is a crime
To get this footage police officers have
Ask the homeowner end
And they have to have a case number
To go with that
But people are upset because it's
Apus search
Vice is really upset with ring because
Has noticed a pattern
Of ring helping police departments
Encourage people to download the neighbors app and to submit their video
So there
Encouraging Police Department's to
Be on social networks and to share video footage and to
Ask for help and that sort of thing and that will boost
Both
Downloads of the neighbors app and boost the willingness of people to opt into
Police request for
Video data
What's really disturb
Kevin go ahead
More news came out to this week we saw / on govtech.com
That's
Even if a
Ring
Homeowner
Decides not to share video the police can just go to Amazon which owns ring
And essentially subpoenaed the video
That's totally different
Mille Lacs there and I'm kind of bothered
Tony's body the public information officer for the sheriff's office in Fresno County
Which is one of those
But we
Apartments that's partnered with Amazon and ring on this
He disagrees with the claims of privacy violations here is
His
I would say to anybody to think this is another case of Big Brother watching
Poor us trying to invade privacy go to Step One
It took the consumer to invest in the product
They chose to pay for a service that enables it to be viewed by either us
Ring
I don't agree with that last part
Me either in this is what's really frustrating
Ring is actually soliciting police departments as their own Salesforce
As a new sales Channel
Yes so
We got this weird circular logic where you're like
Hey
We're going to give you access to all of this video data if you get people to sign up for the app in
You know you can get away these doorbells and talked about it a lot and then people will be like
I trust my Police Department I will totally Buy
So
And and then
They're like
Well yes they did voluntarily by this but they bought it because they're police
Has been
Essentially selling it
Even getting incentives
The police department's from ring
Yes to sell it so
The sort of logic is is not my
And I don't like
This in this sort of thing is going to
Hurt
Iot come
It's very subtle
I don't like it
Yeah and I think the other thing is in this story every time the word subpoena is mentioned it soon quotes
Which leads me to believe it's not a subpoena process
They talked about just requesting the day
Yeah when you just go to Amazon and get it yeah
They mate if they have a case number Amazon may decide to give it
Is that even if they don't have a case number I is how I read it and
Listen I'm for this in general this type of
Providing the information to the police
I mean I actually did that when my car was hit
The video camera out front captured
Basically you could say was a hit-and-run but the
Person who hid it was across the street so they run very far
Disputed hitting my car and I took the video and I provided it to the police
That's different to me then
We can just go look at everybody's video
Exactly
And if you say no they still have a recourse it's not like we can still look at everybody video
Veterinary courses Amazon so before you buy a ring doorbell
You may want to consider that
Please have a bath
All right
So we're not excited about
We are excited
About story that Kevin scooped a while back
Tell us about it
Jumpsuit
I don't recall when exactly I do and it's right here
Story April 3rd
And we talked about this on the podcast
I was strolling through the FCC database looking for new devices and found
A device from Google that was certified
Wi-Fi
And it's called Mistral that's the code name we won't be called mister all winning if and when it comes to Market
But essentially the code name is draw lines up with Gale and Gale is the current
The existing Google WiFi products
So that led me to believe that this is going to be some type of mesh Wi-Fi device
The very least
And possibly only because of the chipsets being used could even be
Could have
Digital assistants built-in and maybe even a screen will see what Google does I suspect we'll see this device in October
Presumably when Google has its Hardware lunch
9to5 Google latched onto that
This week with some more information
Honda
Saying that it will support Wi-Fi 6
And I'm actually excited by this because
There are some Wi-Fi six Chromebooks and other devices that are in the world right now
But they're useless
6% of unless you have a Wi-Fi six
Router
So we sing I've seen some pre-certified Wi-Fi 6 router so this leads me to believe that
This why I should be a certified device not it
Pre-certified away
Got it
Okay well I am excited is that something you would
I would
I want Google to actually
Undulates
Digital
Assistant smart speaker stuff into Google WiFi
And I still think that's we're going to do here
But if they don't even if they don't I probably would
Best Wi-Fi network
All right speaking of
Wi-Fi
Guess who might be getting into the
You'll never guess
Walmart
Actually they won't be producing
A router necessarily they're looking at doing a
A bridge
Under its project Franklin
Hard worker
So
We found
An FCC filing
Actually our friend
Works at variety found
It sent it over
But he found a
SEC filing for a Walmart wi-fi to Z-Wave bridge that will control a garage door opener
And this is fascinating
Because I actually think egg
Garage door
Open R type
Product is wonderful I've even bought them
People who are not in.
So it's a nice little gateway drug or just a useful thing
I'm going to throw it in the useful thing
But
Pfcc application
It was filed on behalf of Walmart by project
Franklin LLC
And if you're asking what the heck project Franklin is
It is a consumer
Hardware
Start
Inside Walmart store number 8 building
Our friends over at the spoon basically broke the story about project Franklin all the way back in June
So not bad
And because it was making
A
Frozen yogurt machine
And the idea behind this is that Walmart
Wants to
Have some sort of
Connected devices in the home that
Can collect consumer
Because they're looking at
The data that Amazon is able to connect through all of its
Products
What's matinee inside in there like
Yeah we need that
Stay tuned for more on that and for a possible launch of a Walmart
Garage door open
Yay
Okay
And in other news I can't do a creative Segway here because
It's really random
Last week
Actually it was Thursday the day that the show
Went live
A New Consortium
Botched called
The fira
Consortium
This was
Spirit stands for fine
Ranging
And this is a Consortium created by Assa abloy which is balad company that owns Yale locks and August
Nxp semiconductors Samsung
End
Bosch
They created this
To use ultra-wideband radio.
Technology to locate objects
In space
Cell
Sort of like the new Bluetooth
Yeah like the new Bluetooth
So what's happening here is ultra-wideband
I covered this all the way back in 2000
This is How old is
We were excited about it way back when
Because it allows you to send
A lot of data
Really
Fast
Puerto Rico
Say hi to be nearby
You can send fax
Memes of data the idea was going to be that it was going to be a wireless
Monitor Solutions you can stick your
Computer next to a bigger Monitor and you wouldn't have
Connect anything
Elekta 60 gigahertz
Which is very short range
Very very fast lots of data
Yes
So the folks at nxp or saying the
Technology never got a fair Shake
Because Wi-Fi just got better and better so we just didn't need
We didn't
So now they want to do it
Finding locations
They're saying that Bluetooth accuracy right now is to meters
Now they don't take into account the fact
The Bluetooth has their latest version Bluetooth
They can actually do within a
Couple inches
But that's basically the area that this
Consortium
I don't know it's going to need a new radio
It's
You're going right down the path I was going to go and then they mention all the verticals you want to Target
And specific use cases you know for like vehicle-to-vehicle
Communication
Maybe ride or fight sharing applications AR
Access Control
Drones
I don't know
So I don't know I'm talking to nxp I'm going to try to get someone maybe for Bosch to come on the show and talked about this a little
Bit more cuz I
I have a lot of questions
And very few answer
Look at you some quick news bits
I found an Indiegogo campaign that might interest a lot of
It's called
Connect
It's a terrible name
Betsy a.m.
And Camera connect
It's a hug that allows you to connect a bunch of cameras and then you can monitor them anywhere
I'm it works with
Most security Brands they're showing pictures of Arlo
What looks to be a real security cameras look like
But what looks to be a nest cam
Baby orangutan
They say you can select just about any brand of Cameron they support over 50 Brands including wise Nest Arlo
Another so
The interesting thing is it lets you put your
Camera footage on the Hub to get a terabyte of storage
There is a cloud option if
If you want it
This way
You don't have to work with
Weird clouds from other camera vendors
And
I don't know what this is this is a meat product
But I don't know how it works but
I'm very
Interested in it
It's an aggregator Centigrade Orville your video so that it doesn't go to the cloud
It stays local
The nice thing is
There's no subscription fee unless
You would like to access that video when you are away from home
$60 a year
Cuz video
Hugely fat
Which makes it
That's why
I don't know I think they're just flipping a switch to and poke a hole in your firewall to give you the access
They're not providing bandwidth
Is taurine okay so they're running it from your
Start running at 5
To you that's still a lot
Or it could be
Oh yeah
I see your poop
All right
Hey
Speaking of cameras
Arlo Pro Lines
No
R homekit
Compatible
Yay
But we are going to talk about
I actually have been excited about this for 2 years when it was first announced
I doubt many people remember
Jesus
Ashley created
Robot which has digital system capabilities
Nyfi
Mobile so it has little wheels in it
Travel around your home for a sample it's called the zenbo zenbo
Your smart little companion
They actually just like two years ago and have a bunch of videos showing
How venmo can help you and your smart TV
Turn the light to red
Even zendo can proactively say hey
Motion sensor just detected somebody open the fridge
So there's this whole ecosystem play here with a sus
Smart Home Products
Zendo never arrived
I just was again trolling the FCC database
And then but was certified for use in the US which typically leads to
Rock debut
And I'm really intrigued by this because
Most people listen to show no I like my little Vector robot
It's got built-in Madam and whatnot and
This is like that because it's very expressive
Has a 6-inch screen for the face
This thing's 18in tall so this is like
Very big compared to Vector which is about 2 inches tall and 3 1/2 inches long
So
There's cameras there is microphones or speakers
Connectivity so I'm curious about then.
Yeah well even today you were just telling me on your way to
Record the show that
You're walking by
Vector was like
Hey Kevin play with
Yes he recognized me he heard me walk into the room got off a little
Power station
Italo's cheery face and waved and then
Recognize Kevin
So I played in a couple minutes I was almost late to the show
Oh I love the fact that
Siap
All right do you think
December will be a
As
You know the pics are like
Like the Anki folkestad for the Expressions but the video is kind of
Show promise to me
And now
It is time for the iot podcast
Hotline
This is an exciting moment because
It's the end of the month or rather
It's the beginning of a new month
Or we have a winner
That's the point
We have a winner
And July from July
And we have
Paul
Who has now won
A Schlage
Lock
So congratulations to you Paul
Yay
And now it's time for the August
Contest so if you want to win an
Ecobee
Madam a
Connected
Light switch
Boom
It's very exciting
You should call us
And inter
Can call us at 5 1/2
623-7424
And
We
Will
Possibly
Play your question on the air and answer it
But worst case scenario
You might win the
Remember the RT Podcast hotline is sponsored by pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio in the world
Pharaoh provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk your brand
Atturo customers have experienced as much as 80% reduction in time to Market
Antenex higher activation rates
Learn more at a pharaoh. IO
Yay
And this week's question is from Jeff
So let's hear it
Hi Stacy hi Kevin this is Jeff from New York
I can love you she'll
A quick question
My son is really excited about what about the weather so I was wondering if it was a connected device
I seen something in the stars but not connected were
You look like you're Outdoors working tell you what the weather is going to be how much rain you're going to get
Fight someone told me that there might be a Wi-Fi or connected device version
I'm not looking God and also
On that Mill is there a way to connect it into the nest
Thermostat
In order to make sure that it could have just accordingly as well
Depending on racing AP AC or the heat preciate it once again and have a great day
This is a great question
And your dear to my heart because I like weather
In fact I have purchased many weatherstation although most of them
Word using proprietary Wireless technology
So you'll find that in lacrosse stuff
You'll find it in Davis stuff
You find a lot of weather stations ranging in
But because you wanted to connect to nest and it sounds like you want it just to be
Connected in general
We came up with two options for
One is the netatmo
Weather station
And this is a product netatmo is a brand from
France is owned by The Grand
It is a
Quality product
You could also buy just the indoor models the outdoor models
And then you can buy
Ring gauge
Anand
I can never say
When an indemnitor
Improving speed
And that
Whole package
If you want to get everything together is
But the devil often does a sale
So keep an eye on
Read it if you don't want the rain gauge or the wind speed you can actually just get the weather station which is 180.
Yeah but
Weather
Oh yeah
The weather station maybe for a birthday and then you add on later at Christmas
And the devil often does sales
I often times get
Like $20 off
Or even $40
Softsoap
If you sign up
And this works with Madam a
And also with if this then that which is how you were tied into
It's at
The other option is cheaper
It looks more like a traditional weather station
This is the Ambien
Weather
WS
What E90 to a
Yeah
There's a bunch of these you can find them on Amazon
The company that makes it is called ambient weather
And
Basically the different models
Bad things
The higher-end models have solar power
Power
So you may or may not want that but you can see that
This is their base model
Is $170
And
It looks like a weather station
And it's got a little wind cups that will spin around
For your attendance
It's going to rain gauge
And his wife I can
So this will connect to your Wi-Fi it connects
Incense data up to Weather Underground
It also connects directly
If
So if you wanted to do
Your
Nest
You would actually tie
This weather station or the netatmo
You would set a nifft recipe
Says hey
It's the weather
Hits
90 degrees
Turn on
Test
80 degrees
Probably
But I don't know where you
So
That's how you do this
And those are the
They both work with Madam a&f so I don't think you can go wrong actually seem to get a little bit more information from the
Ambient weather one such as UV and
Heat index
Dewpoint and all that so it depends on the how into whether you really are
Yeah
I mean I'm fat into
Icicle
I should also mention that there are
Build it yourself weather
So if you go to like a site like SparkFun or Adafruit
Searching for weather kids
If your son is that interested in it he may want to build his own and that is completely an option it just
Men at Work with your smart
System
But
Supercuts
All right just thanks for the question and now please stay tuned for more of or and who is the CEO of versatile nature
Talking about bringing iot and AI into the
Construction
Industry
The first a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is nutanix
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Nutanix
And I have such a bagani here
So such an eye associate nutanix with
Hyper converged infrastructure
What is it specifically that you guys offer in the internet
It is called
Cirt
That allows you
Modernity application
Flextime manager
LittleBigPlanet 2
Salon central point of control
And last but not least
It enables users so do deer processing across the aisle in the clock for ID
This week let's talk about 5G and iot
There's so much talk about that
What do you make a follower
5e and ideas fascinating
He's so much bandwidth
PlayStation
Set the Bangles between the PlayStation on the cloud is going to be the limiting factor
Open Saavn
Immense opportunity
Telecom providers to provide
On this IGN
Applications
Put on a RV
And I have two tens to be an overwhelming Undertaker
Making Arthur ways to make iot projects more accessible and successful across a wide range of ghosts
You need to put together
Dislike security and scaling
What we have done
Call IRT application Library
Play whenever I squeeze and its eyes so into an RDA
And this is just like all the other delivery fired
Extension into an application just like all the installed database
We want to make iot as accessible as a smartphone app
Is today
They want to dramatically reduced number of vendors and the number of moving parts that a customer needs to deal
Concept called The Library
And number two
We want to enable and users to instantiate dramatically
Impactful
And complicated ID applications into an
All the way from sensors to the edge to the cloud in one
Excellent if people want to find out more about nutanix where should they go
Stacy I'd like to invite you to come visit us
And sign up for the free trial
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Friend who is the co-founder and CEO of versatile nature
Hi Mom how are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing great how are you
Excellent
I'm excited as I told you guys before we be talking about
The construction industry coyote there today so we're off and tell us what it is
That you guys are
I doing it versatile
Sure thing
Pleasure to be here
Thank you thanks for having me
Spyfall
Non-intrusive
Data harvesting
Technology for construction today we actually have our own iot multi-sensor device
And using appdata
We can actually enable
Better decision-making
True understanding and control of
Possibly the most fragmented and unstructured Manufacturing floor we have ever come across which is
I love that I love the idea of thinking about construction as a Manufacturing
It feels like maybe a super stretched analogy because
One is so controlled and
I mean I'm used to clean rooms in Seneca
Construction
Maybe she'll break down
The big challenges associated with
Construction
I know there's regulation there's individual environments what else
I think the
One thing that sets
Construction parties really how many
People and trade Direction bulb
Motorcycle Factory
Controlled by a single unit World War
The same person on the same organization we're looking at
Different individuals reporting
Different organizations sometimes having
Someone has a different idea of the
And then you have the general contractor
Responsible for coordinating
I'm making sure
Casper turned over on time and thing back
Seaflo
To come from
Telephone directory
Trust me.
Cold environment
What we used to call machine-to-machine really works like you understand what the machines are telling you
Youku
What's a clean room
This is what we actually bring
New construction
That's corny knock the way things work and usually few
Gotham something wrong on Step 1
You would
Noli not be able to correct it on steps
But you're probably not even know
But you got it wrong
Until it's too late and the state store
But I don't
You think about it
It is a factory
It is a manufacturer
I'm demoted looking at that way
Des Moines we could digitize it
And actually help people
Shein
Be better at what they do and just more done and actually got back to the kids
Safely
And earlier
Best route construction is super dangerous we don't always think about that but there are lots of
Things that could happen to cause someone to
Have an injury
All right
So what is the end
Product
You got this multi-purpose sensor on a crane
I assume it's measuring things that the crane is doing loads that it's taking
What is the end person and who is being person that
It's the data
Source I think one of the things that kind of makes us special is there multiple and people and they have
Different news
To help them understand
Tax credit
Or Windows 10 overs actually happen
So we take the daytime and we okay manipulated or learn
The story
To actually understand
What is really happening on the jump 5
Boys telling a relief
Diamond from the visual
Goal for us
Is Kraft Foods
I'll actually spend people are stupid
The safety director just need of the Daytona right now but you spend them
Curated
Messages
Usually we communicate over text
Is today to just
Tell them what they need to know and what they need to make
Then they can log into our interface
Can you give me an example of what one of those two
Text my
Looks like her sound
Yes it could be packed a
Conceited on youku
Coordinate stuff B
Call
The subcontractor for this task. Should be on site
A certain time
It could be
A simpler text that just says book time
Is being with you
And it should be about the
Hook time
Ya book time would be completely related to the crane but we do actually know
Time Warner hook right we know who's using the hook
We also know when it's not you
Or when it's for you
Sometimes
Let's talk about
The challenge because this seems the guy I like your text messages which seem
Terry appropriate for someone who's in construction but let some of the challenges
Rigging
Ai and iot into
Really what is an old line industry
What have you encountered and how did you get people excited or interested in
This technology because it's not like construction workers are
Excited about
Yeah let's go
Yeah so you'll be
Surprised I think that slowly but surely coming around you could look at it
Showing
Call Greg
In terms of the approaching the Treehouse to technology and what is Karachi
She do for them
But you're right there
An industry where
Based on
Incredible professional
MJ can get the job done
I think part of my understanding or my
Coach
Today no fee
I totally come from the fact that I grew up in the fingers.
Do people feel really connected to them to Simply say
We don't necessarily know exactly where the value is for you so let's go on this journey together
Change too much
Or technology tracks
Tibia labeled
If we could just gather data without asking
Imports
And if we could then as I said cut through the noise and give them what they need
Pure
Volume
Measure at the end of the day
I think that's the right approach for
What's ecology
Construction
And this is how you use sensor
How you don't ask people to record and Report
Aai's how you actually
Becreateful incredible inside Fender fast learning.
Incredible as the people aren't they can see and be everywhere
If we can help them actually know where they are
In the process
And What needs
To happen next and what's missing then you're helpful
I think jelly our coaching the way
I personally look at the industry
Exactly.
Stay out of the professional way and a Dilaudid value
Anderson paak ichnology will actually filter in and find its place in the incredibly professional
And I think that's an important thing to think about I think a lot of companies are approaching this space get very enamored of there
Technology and they forget about how to deliver it to the people who have to deal with the information
And this idea that you're
You're going to like bring technology and disrupt an industry seems maybe not the right
Croach
As opposed to saying
Hey I can make your life easier and you won't have to change part of your process so and curious if there other things
Things other than saying hey
You're not going to change your process for this
Help
Make it easier
To bring in something new to a very old-school industry
I think it starts with this approach
I'm sure it doesn't help when you're not totally in love with your technology but actually in love with adding value
Well it's not about asking
Change like they would just pick them up at 1
It's about what is it that they're getting
How is this help
Right now
Because one other thing about this industry is
Alcoa intermediate
Why is calculated in so many different ways
Tricky questions
So when you did all right
Honestly
In my view right now what the technology needs
To do is
Make
People
Shein
If we could get everyone better what they do that we want everyone
That's my
And speaking of Technology
And disruption
I think what's interesting is there's this idea in construction that
At the exciting thing to look at is
Robots
Build a wall or
3D printed houses and we see a lot about that
As opposed to what you guys are
So I'm curious where
What you're doing fits in with like
The future of construction
And maybe how those other things fit in
The brain understanding
Process that makes somebody fashion floor
Next few valuable
Pretty much no matter what
Evolution actually happen I would also say your every technology has its place and things will
Fishing to play
Right now
Empowering
People making
Everyone do
More
It's just not the same time with
The same resources
I think work
Technology on all its kind of
Shades and colors should go definitely where we're going and powering
A good place
Start
We do
See an issue
Construction would come to
Recruiting
Newman power in today in between I think the college as a
Volta play there too
Other than the fact that the younger generation probably likes
To feed the industry word of working
Having more technology it's also about
What automation
Can be done I look is not necessarily what
Oil companies out there that are looking to automate
The
Color of low-hanging fruit where there are issues
Injecting labour
I think every technology as I said we'll probably find it
Play being the brains behind
It's all and
Extremely
Supporting to the people
What
Ricardo
And that makes sense and I do think we're going to see an interesting shift in the next few years in the workforce
As we bring more AI in most companies I talked to they want to hire people who are eight
Able to make decisions
Based on having access to
More data
And that means we're going to see hopefully more skilled workers and workers that are trained up
To deal with this order
Mustang individually
The one thing I would agree with you is the
Daily non-skilled non-traded
People that are sometimes there just to cover I guess
Or the shortage in labor
This is I think we're going to Safety House bigger
Bicycle doctor killed people
Professional
I've been doing this for years those are the ones that I would be
Stray dog
I would either
Train to be professionals or coulombic technology to help solve that problem
And hopefully by saving money in terms of preventing delays or things like that you
You can actually pay these p
People cuz I know part of it is just
Hey
Having some cheap labor around is always lovely but skilled labor is more expensive so
Maybe that's where the cost start patching up
Let's talk about how you do this because you got this multi-purpose sensor I know I've talked to other companies who are
Trying to
Add intelligence to the construction industry and their using lots of cameras and
Haven just didn't interview just a few weeks ago with someone actually in the chip industry and they were talking about how cameras are the most relevant
Iot sensor and everyone should be using them
And I think you have a little bit of a different opinion here so I'd love to hear your take on
Cameras as part of the Industrial iot in
How you're using them in
Maybe
Why you're relying on other sensors
Sure thing I guess I have a different or slightly different take
Amazing
Specific role to play with other than being the sole
Data
I think what it comes to feeding AI systems while you're using
Visual recognition to connect only it just takes longer to learn
And much longer to add value world
Our approach with a multi sensor direction is
We have so much
Using terms of theta long before we even look at the camera and that enable
Police officer learning
What comes to Ai and machine learning
We could probably do things
10 times faster so it's a different approach
But I think when you start utilizing more than just cameras
When you could
Dive higher value to your
Factor Garden camera
At all we do
As I said
I just don't think of the Soul
Send for it is
Incredibly valuable and some people with argue
It sounds like if you're using just a camera it's going to take you a little bit longer to get the data uni
The flipside is you only have one sensor to deal
Curious actually 4matic
Perspective
Getting this onto a construction site
What are the technology challenges of putting your
Sensor package on the crane and then making sure it has connectivity in that sort of
A challenge for you guys or is that pretty much salt
I believe we can smoke.
How did you sell
Mixology I'll be talking about
Stanley we're not experiencing connectivity issues
Our device
Sandpoint
Just so many ways to go about
Conductivity
I'll say wifi-only. One of them being so I can't
Overwhelming probably all our customers
Stop.
Have not been one of our challenge
What has been one of your Channel
We've had plenty just as I got were talking about and a challenging the industry with
Harsh conditions
Making sure you actually have
The robustness that you need to actually face the challenges of a jump bike
One thing that we had to tackle
Extremely early I just getting this to be with you
Something that people don't look up and say what
Is that
It probably takes
Left in the day now for the
On the job site
Nothing absolutely no special attention
Okay make it HF.
Got it
What's in by talking about
The future of construction
So let's visit a job site
In
I don't know five years and then maybe 10 years item
Pick your favorite time frame in
Tell me what you think or how you think this is going to operate
From the people
That are involved all the way to
The centers are
I don't know cameras whatever robots
And the types of information that are going to be
Babe
Oh wow
Probably 10 more than 5 years those things are rapidly advancing
I have said before I'll
Please play again
You
The job site
Future almost Intel clean room and you would laugh right
Right now
Anymore
Data flowing
Tina Turner
Turtleboy evolve
Punjab
People empowered
To make decisions on the Fly
Call Delancey have access
And overall
Control
On Manufacturing
So what you think about production control and coffee
Alder Faye Advance Pro
Where to find Apache
Same amount
People
Just getting a lot more done the industry needs to actually address the growing did not
We could use that exact
Same number of resources to
Double
The productivity
That would be an incredible achievement I think a lot of them a lot of people in it
We will not see
Your keyboard fuel resources will just be
Dramatically improve productivity
Yeah $60
Clin rheumatology
How data flows and how decisions be made
Okie dokie track cheap
Control
I said that analogy
As a former chip reporter I even
I embrace it
Alright
Thank you so much for coming on the show this week
I really appreciate it
Thanks for having me stay Stadium
That's it for this week thanks
How much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Coyote.com