Hey everyone welcome to the 211 episode of The Internet of Things podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And we have a jam-packed show for you today we're going to kick it off by Todd
Talking about
Stringify shutting down
Offer some Alternatives and talk about it being be end of the Wild West era and the smart
Wechat
Google announcing their anthos Cloud platform
Bury it
For the edge will explain why
Sonos and Ikea have launched a
Group of products that we have questions about
This week at a big security conference
Cameras with inference at the edge
Are a big deal we'll talk about what that means for suppliers in
And for us as regular humans
Kevin also has an update on the mysterious Google Mistral
Device that
We will talk about
And there is a new homekit enabled energy strip
Available for all of you
You are still
Dedicated home kit bands and
JD Powers is getting in on the eye
Coyote
Russell didn't hear from her sponsor
Software AG
On how to
Implement better data collection
4 a.m.
And our guest this week is Andy corvo's who is the CEO of Electro labs
She's going to be talking about what it means to bring iot into
Clinical trials
And about her time at the FDA
And what that agency is doing to help Drive innovation in
In digital health
With today's consumer devices
So all of this and more away to
After a message
From our sponsor iot world are you going iot world as it intersects
Fashion of Industries in iot Innovation it is May 13th through 16th at the Santa Clara Convention Center in Silicon
Valley iot world will welcome over 12500 iot professionals 400 speaker
There's an 300 exhibitors and startups you can meet thousands of iot leaders from Boeing
CVS Health ExxonMobil Ford
Google Procter & Gamble Starbucks UPS
More and we have an exclusive listener discount
A 25% off your pass with a code Stacy 25
Ccsjc eye5 and you have to visit iot world event.com
To register
So you're listening to the show you're interested in iot so go check that out and don't forget that
Food Stacy 25
All right
Kevin
Shake It Off
What a Sad start to this week
I know
In
Mandt
So stringify we got it we got an email all of the people who use string of
By which is a software-based program that allowed you
Basically they called him flows
These really complicated recipe
PS4 iot
Devices
I used it a lot to create things like
I had
The ability to tell Google or
My Amazon Echo
Yoga time
And what would happen if
Is my
Shades would come down
My lights went dim
Television would turn on Socastee
I do yoga
So all of this happened and my air conditioning would actually go.
Is hot yoga Is For Fools
So all of that would happen just with the words yoga time
Time it was
Awesome
And now I can no longer have you
Will you can have yoga time but you won't have yoga time with stringify
When Comcast
Purchase
Stringify
And this was about 80
Yes
We said
Caprichos both of us that said
When do they shut it down
Play makes sense
Comcast what is stringify
Because
I have complicated feelings about Comcast
But when it comes to the Smart Home
They're doing
Bang up job
Creating
A really good interface
For people to use in
Stringify help them get that
This is what they're X1 platform right
Yes there
Xfinity home
X1
They all have the same
Games
In Comcast is actually doing a three-front a job there approving Wi-Fi
And they're doing a good job without with
Improving security
Excited about your new security services for
Connect devices and their improving
Their voice interface with
Set the X1 platform
Yeah
It got all of that
Stringify means
It did and I know we have people that listen to this podcast we're very passionate about stringify and love it and I guess
It's it's great
I lean towards
If this then that personally but the same concept
And it provides a valuable service for you to connect things that are not otherwise natively connectable
My butt
To be fair
I don't think a massive amount of people are going to be affected by this CS again people here Elizabeth show probably
Fairmount
But we looked at what was it the download numbers for the stringify app compared to the If This Then That app
And what do we find
We found
Very sad
So the stringify app
By the way you guys the stringify app
Is no longer there
Did the cash version
For March 30th
We saw that it had
Over a hundred thousand
Switch actually surprise me
But if
Has over 5 million
Downloads
It is in the Google Play Store
Lot of people using this more people than I anticipated but not quite as many as you know a super star break
So it makes sense that Comcast would
Be like yeah we don't need to stop
And if you have your stringify flows
Those are going to be available to you until June
And then they're going to die
So I guess I have you a good time till
Which kind of leads into 2
Related topic
Extra questions
What do you do where do you go
Instead of stringify like we can tackle that first
Then the second question is
How do you get your stuff out of stringify and the easy answer is
You really don't
I hate to say it and there needs to be a new and I see we've been talking about this
For the past couple days
All of these
Routine type platforms
Are built on standards to a point because they're using
The available apis for all of these devices and hugs and such
And they put up a nice interface
Front of them and make them work together
So
Those are out there and available for anybody
But
The interphase part there's no import there's no export so it's not like you can
Get those routines out and moves away from stringify to an if this then that person
So yes you have to
You have to say to yourself I am prepared to spend another few hours
Taking all the things I did on stringify and moving it over to another
It is unfortunate I would love for the industry to come up
With
Because he's are all API calls are most of these are API calls it does
Make a challenging but I would love for them to come up with
Looks like a file format where
Pull these API calls and be like hey
I want the same thing to happen
In this new play
Some people might just shrug and be like that's what you get for being an early adopter
I think it also will help with things like vendor lock-in
So I've had people ask me there like God are you worried that you know
If you adopt Google then you can adopt Amazon later and I
Like actually I have
But I see
Super
Options if you're asking if I use Arduino
If this then that
Would you say node-red is another potential option
Yeah actually know red would be
Interested now
You have to run node red on a
So you still
They put on a Raspberry Pi or something
Yes you have
You can't just like be like
Go to the web
You can't just have your phone
There's no node red app for your phone
That's going to be a little bit of an issue
In there a lot of
Things like that out
They're so you can run that on a Raspberry Pi and that has
Very similar
Flow-based it's two ways you like run things around and
Oh no
Bad
The Raspberry Pi is your typical device that you would run node red on cuz a pie in the most you can spend on your Raspberry Pi like $35
You can run it locally you can actually have a
Create a Docker container if you have a Linux machine you could do it there
You can
Do it with
An Arduino or a
Beaglebone black
Or if you use
And I know a lot about be familiar with us but I've used it before
The termux app in Android
Which is basically a terminal emulator you could run it there
Or
If you were like me and
Gravitating towards the crack cloud
You can put on IBM Cloud sent Technic
Fred
Never heard of that
Amazon web services or Microsoft azure
What's right I got a check for that after the
So you had a lot of options but nobody like you said says no like
App to download to your phone and just get going
So
And in that same day there a lot of other platform
So you could use it or not
Read so you can use openhab
You could use home assistant
You could use
Homebridge
And all of those are
Open source base programs that let you download their
Trolls basically to a Raspberry Pi
Blink all that up
And like stringify these are actually incredibly
Create all sorts of
But
Directions
I I find myself in some way
I'm Paralyzed by
You don't like all my God there's so many features
Like you can see sensors and your devices that
Even the manufacturer
Yeah it gets down to how a how technical you want to get like
If you want to get into building things with HTML and JavaScript
And you're comfortable with that
Yeah I know right can do that for you at work
Can offer that to you
But you can be tinkering a lot
How do you know if same width
The other is that you
You know you mentioned you're going to be tinkering
This is not none of these are like a cortical off-the-shelf solution
But those are the off the shelf
Shirley software-based
The same way that stringify was
Would be something like you know me yonomi
They have a software platform
It doesn't have as much granularity but it is really easy to use and the cool thing about you know me is you can
Actually
Run the app
It'll discover a lot of the devices at your house
And will actually automatically start suggesting
Recipezaar floser
Apps that lets whatever you want to call them
For you using the particular devices
Since you have which
I think is really used
I like that a lot that that starts getting this
Putting the smart in the smart home and it's only got mad amazed been doing with the the hunches
Yes although I haven't seen her
No and I'm home all the time I couldn't let me out so I'm shocked
Do you know
I'm pretty I have a very repeatable process between
Coffee writing naptime Netflix and so on so I don't get it
Yeah and I haven't gotten guard either I signed up for the beta program
None of them have happened for me that's where the echo will listen for broken glass as a security feature
Yes okay if that was a little Segway Sino
That wasn't a Segway
A day in the life of Stacy and Kevin
Bats you so other than you know me there is everybody's favorite if
Which
We actually talked about
Fairly recently there's some
Turmoil ifft leadership changes that sort of
Think so
I still say they get bought
Yeah yeah
I say they get bought by a Google or Amazon
We'll see
So if this
Still a good option it is
Not you can't do the multi-pronged
Applets you
You have to do everything into
If it really so it's not as powerful
And then
If you're a SmartThings user you could actually build
Your own apps for some of the stuff
Ann Dunham Google
Oh you're groovies cuz
Groovy language
And if you're an Amazon Echo or a Google home user
Could actually build some routines
And
Uses for voice control the cool thing about
The
Stringify thing was they didn't actually
They have to be based on voice
Json
Voice but they could have been based on
Jamaica Center trick
We are any trigger event
You can't get if your home cat though you can use sensors as a
For certain
Because I believe the column automations in the home app
Automation
So many so many
Okay
So those are your alternatives
In just we wrote it I wrote a post about this on the site I said that
Stringify
And
The post earlier this week about
People being like we can't recommend the wink Hub anymore which
Kevin and I are also
Little cautious about the
I said this was the end of the Wild West era
In
Just put that in perspective I thought I really did I really thought back in 2012
When we started this that
You were going to be able to pull Lake
Sensors and outlets and connected devices and in the create your own stuff with
Kind of like Yahoo
Pipes
Yes
But just just build your own experiences in a way that was pretty easy in
I'm pretty
Reliable
That never happen
Yeah I mean because things are getting siloed unfortunately
To the different platforms
There is still the the open-source options that you mentioned and mainstream people are not going to likely
Get a Raspberry Pi install openhab or something like that
But your vision but you had in 2012
Is available to people if they want to put the time and effort into it
Yeah I just thought I'd be more
It is available to everyone but not everybody wants
To invest the time and Technical knowledge and learning
To do it yeah I was hoping
I was hoping you'd be the kind of like creating a Wix or Squarespace
That's where we are
That's a lot of talk about that
Let's move on Google is having its
Cloud next event
This week which
Where it talks about all the cool stuff happening
Google Cloud universe
In the iot space Google is
Decidedly behind Amazon and Microsoft when it comes to hosting different Enterprises in
Building iot things
However
Google has taken that weakness and turn it into boom
Strength
Very jiu-jitsu
They announced anthos
Which is Google clouds new platform that let you run a nap anywhere
And it is using Open Standards
It lets you run your
Apps in Google Cloud Amazon Cloud Microsoft cloud and
It also pulls it down to the
The Edge and it does that
With that support for kubernetes which is
An open-source
Management platform
I don't really want to get too into the weeds here
But yeah
Liquid with a smart thing as you said they took a weakness and turn it into a strength
Basically anthers
Innocence becomes your Cloud management platform
Regardless of the cloud you use or
Where it is
It doesn't even have to be in the cloud
Yes that's correct it could be hybrid Cloud yes absolutely so you could have
And it nap something last year the Google offered by play some Google
They brought kubernetes to on-prem or on-site
So you could actually have
Have your stuff in the cloud and you could have her stuff locally or have redundancy between local and
Cloud and saucer worth
But now they be silly put like I a cloud management layer on top of
Everybody's Cloud which is really smart
And what that does if you're a developer or you're an it a business decision maker
You can literally go to One dashboard one portal
And manage or subscribe to
Move from one Cloud to another
In one place yours
Support is there for all of your class you are
Billing is there for all of your closet doesn't matter if you use Google or not
Cloud
And
That is really really smart my opinion of Google
Yeah you know I last year when I was at Microsoft build conference which actually build will be in a
Weeks in May
But I thought Microsoft was going to
This I thought Microsoft was going to create this overarching
Multi-cloud management system
Both at the cloud and at the edge
Because of their support for kubernetes and some of the things they were doing with things called that cubelets
Which where
Kubernetes for managing container
Containerized software
So maybe we're going to see Microsoft launched something like this in a cup
And that would be
Yeah maybe
It would be interesting I think
Google certainly knows they're behind and they would love for people to come to Google Cloud for everything I get it
Microsoft's obviously one of the biggest players here
Repeating mostly against
Amazon
So
I don't know if Microsoft needs
Do that's what Google is doing
They might just to say we can do that too
The reason the world is going to end
Need this
Is
Cuz
In a business setting
You're not just going to have your cloud
How to manage like if you think of like a Supply Chain management thing
You're going to have other people you're going to want to see data and run applications
That tie back to your business
On other
Peoples
It infrastructure
Infrastructure
Yeah actually me
Maybe the movie infrastructure savings or something
I see this actually be really important
And it could
Zach Edwards tell me about containers which are
Are easily Deployable like
Basically applications using only
Imagine you can just throw an application on
One of your
Suppliers
Edge so you can monitor what you need to
Having that management layer becomes really essential
It might make sense just not just as Google turn in
Weakness into a strength but also because the world were going to live in to Manza in this actually would be better than like
Pulling like 8
Ati's and that's worth
Secure
Customization
Control
A lot of flexibility yes struggle with like
Maintaining them making shirts
Like communicating with people about like
What's going to go down
I don't know
So I think this is a really big deal and it's a really big shift and
It'll be very important
For all these companies were like
I'm going to use iot to make my everything better
Yeah and just to mention a couple companies of
We're partners
Spanish for this
Platform anthes
Google has enlisted some of the usual suspects but now I'm something that surprised me as well VMware and Dell
They they are very often
Google Partners as well as partners with the other cloud services
Hpe
Intel and Lenovo
It's not like they have
Small no-name company set of
Glommed onto this so
Yeah that's what you're going to need if you're going to if you're going to succeed with us
That's a good start
Next up
We're going to be talking about a collaboration between Sonos and Ikea B
Furniture store
And the smart speaker
Company
The connected Speaker Company have launched a
Well-to-do speakers one
Is a bookshelf speaker
That is about 99 bucks
Electrolux
It's pretty good. The other is $179 table lamp
That is also a smart speaker
And it
It's ugly
It yet
It's it's typical Ikea design one color I could live with the other color that's going to be available in August I could not
So but
It's $179 for the
Lamp that has the speaker built-in and it's 99 for the
Connected bookshelf speaker which definitely looks nice and
I don't know it sounds like that because
But
It probably sounds so it probably doesn't mean if they work with Sonos I'm sure there was some kind of specifications and tuning and so on
The strange thing is
They're kind of dumping he's a smart speaker
But there's no microphones built in so I thought originally like
Maybe I could replace one of the
You dozens of smart speakers I have in the house like a Google home
Mini
With this lamp
Because it's a smart speaker
But there's no microphones built into either one of these
Yeah and that's because Ikea was worried about
Turning off privacy phone
People and I think when they call it a smart speaker they're talking about it as a connected
Again we're getting connected and Sonos I mean
I have Sonos speakers since like 2007
They weren't smart they were just connected but basically
They're connected the internet so they can play your Spotify or Pandora
Ever so that's what
They're talking about their
I'm not on board with this person
I'm about to go into a new house and it's
Could be rented so I can see picking up a
A couple I mean I loved so
Sonos speakers that sound great
Work really well
So
I've been making a big push to add like they added Amazon's voice Services last year and this year they're
The waiting on it
One day soon
We supposed to be last year they're supposed to add to Google Assistant support but they haven't done that yet that's in the works
So it's weird to me like they're making this big push and yet
Bucyrus Brandon
Speakers won't stream and Ikea you know they've done kind of their own path with
Stuff so it's possible that this is
What people want
And we're just crazy
I guess
Who knows
Okay let's talk about inference at the edge specifically with regards to smart
Videoke
There is a conference happening right now this
This is ISC West this is an international
Security and control systems
And you can
Sensors
Can see all kinds of
Cool stuff
Big trend
Apparently is
Video cameras with built-in surveillance
They have chips that are capable of running at the edge so running these models
To determine who people are
Baby
Are they people
Are they doing something weird
Maybe even identifying people
Who are supposed to be there
So this is not brand new
But it is definitely
Going to be it's going to start being much more difficult to buy a video cam
It doesn't happen
So Western Digital announced their new storage system
These cameras
Set ability to process
Crap ton of data with
Best 4K video cameras
And it also allows for storage and in
The edge
Call, announce the new chips so they have the Qualcomm Vision intelligence 400 and 300 platforms they're using
Latest
Qcs 605 and qcs 603 soces
That was a lot of
Data and nobody really needs to know
Anything about them except
You can basically do
Advanced
All of that for
That has computer
Back to mention a ton of partners that are planning to use these chips
It's like
Well over a dozen
That's kind of surprising
Yeah the bullets it's becoming very much a
It's just an integral part people want cameras they want surveillance cameras and
They want
If you add computer vision at the edge or some sort of modeling capability
You can do two things
S1 you reduce the amount of data that you send that to
The cloud cuz you don't
How to send everything
To you can build a system for alerts
Like there are people in this area when there's not supposed to be people
Or these are unrecognized people in this area
You're being super rich
If you got a super amazing
Algorithm running
Cuz we've long had
Cameras right the challenge though is you got all this camera data and pee
People have to sort through it and
And it's time to
Impossible
And uses a lot of bandwidth as you said so if you can
Keep all that locally and have it processed with a
Model that is already trained
You don't have to send that data to the cloud I would think
That might help some people
Because it's a little scary in
One side you want surveillance the other side you don't want to be surveilled right
You know if you want surveillance if you're home early
Wechat business
And you don't want the
Cloud provider to have the information
What the camera sees
This could resolve that problem
Yeah in and having all that locally process data means you can dump it
And then
It's a little bit more privacy
It may not be
I believe it's faster to interns the recognition because
Yeah
Alright so
I think trans coming out of is
Next up
What's an update on the mysterious mr. Aldridge
So we talked about
Mistral on the last project
A quick recap is that
In Google
Chromium public codebase which I read for fun
I found a bunch of code for a new device called Mistral
And tied to that code was Gale and Gale is the current Google Wi-Fi device
Gail was the codename for that
So I get to speculation and some more digging running
Code and said huh
They're using the new Qualcomm QSC 404 and 405 chips
Which have
On-device voice recognition they have a zigbee chip
I5 cores
Have a smart speaker
Capabilities
Schedule sitting capabilities I should say
So my speculation was huh this could be
The next Google Wi-Fi product as either 2 in 1 or 3 in 1 device
So it'd be your Mesh networking
Product
Cluster Google
Assistance
Such as in a Google home
Plus potentially and actual
3 radio
Smart home hub
Well I still don't know about the last bit because I haven't seen any mention of the zigbee radio in any code yet
However this week as I was
Spending my fun time reading through code I noticed
That there are now numerous mentions of mesh
Wi-Fi capabilities
In this device
And for LED lights just like what device that you have right now Stacy
Google home
I don't know what to think of happy for you
He's probably true you probably do have lots of them but my specific in Frontier is
Yeah this is
Definitely at least a two-in-one now
Azure mesh Wi-Fi
Access point and War
As well as a Google home device
So I'm still waiting to see if there's any zigbee code Adam and I will keep
Looking because I love to Rico
Yay
Alright other
Cool news bits
Eve
IT company that makes sensors just for Apple's homekit program
They have a new energy strip that is available
This is like
Protectors any
Individually control different Outlets
And that is what that is
What is it it's a smart
Power strip that work with tonkatsu
It has three
Regular
Electrical outlets in it
As well as it looks like
Possibly
Q yuan
Babies
How to tell from the pictures
It does it does have a couple USBS
It is a surge protector as well
Drax actor
Yeah it has direct Wi-Fi connection so it should be very easy to set up so it's not like you're gonna have to
Mess around with an e
Your network settings to too much there
And then obviously you could use
Homekit automations to
Turn things on or off that are plugged into this
And it'll be a hoe
All right
Another newspaper JD Powers
Where's the company that we
I associated with JD Power Ranking
Kingsbury sing so like how awesome a company is and turn
Consumer sentiment surveys
But they also do benchmarking and they are
They've signed a deal with company called uptake
That is based in
Chicago
And take
Basically pulls in tons of data and they suggest models to make
Prediction
Take whatever action you think
So
The two companies have gotten together to
Create new benchmarks based on the automotive industry in this is really interesting what they're doing is there pool
Pulling in data from
Connected factories from connected cars
And they're trying to
Figure out
What kind of metrics might make sense for
Future vehicles in terms of
How long it takes for
Service how happy people are with them that sort of
So
It's really fascinating and I'm actually going to try to get JD Powers to come on the show to talk about what they're hoping to get out of this in
Workouts because are also going to apply this to the
The Telecommunications industry
And the utilities industry
So
Discount of a little teaser expect more to come on this because I'm
Really interested in how they're going to pull industry-wide data and make that
Useful for consume
Yeah I am related to this and it's not
A direct relation but I noticed that on the Amazon developer blog this week
They showed a JD Power survey
Consumer purchasing preferences of
Cars
And its related because 76% of the respondents
Said they would
Want the same brand of resource they have at home
Triana next vehicle
Sure that makes total sense you don't want multiple
Assistance one for him and one for your car
But more importantly
59%
Said they were more likely to buy a certain
Car or from a certain car company
If the voice service is available in the
Car so almost 6 and 10 car buyers
Want voice services in a car
According to JD Power survey with Amazon Amazon send me my auto echo my echo Auto
Please
That's right you ordered that into I did
Pussy pussy if you're worthy to have lunch
Boy come on man
All right
Okay I think it's time for our voice mail
For the week
It feels like we've covered a lot of snow
Stuff today
Let's go now to
This week's iot podcast
Listener hotline
Is hotline is brought to you by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent portfolio the world afero provides a proven iot platform that doesn't risk your brain
Apparel customer service experience as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
Antennax higher activation
Learn more at a pharaoh.
If you want to call the iot
She podcast listener hotline give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
You can leave us a message and we may play it on the show
As part of that you will be entered to
To win this month's prize which is
A Connect
IO
System
And what this does is this actually can turn your
Older alarm system that is wired
Into
Connected alarm system
Using the SmartThings platform
Do you win this you're going to want to SmartThings platform
You'll get the connected IO board
This is a tinker stream this is not for a probably normal people I'm just going to
Right upfront
But it's really cool
So
Let's hear from this week's scholar
Free to use this on the show
Myquest
Is I have a
Google home
My issue is whenever I have guests over if they like
To turn Z-Wave
I'd like to know how to stop my gas
From
Turning out the temperature for my Google Assistant
Thank you
All right
The first
I have bad news for
If these are your friends
That's how it's been how to stop this don't invite these people over anymore
Let's let's assume your friends are actually
Pretty decent human beings they just have to
Spunside
There's really one way to help
But it's going to be
It's it's a way that
I don't know if
You're going to want to
So
Google actually lets you do voice matching for this
Car sound system
B
All you do is
You can turn this on in your settings in the
Google home and then you will train your Google Assistant
To recognize your voice it's like you
Repeat phrases 3 times
And then it recognizes you
And then
Walla
Only when you say some
You're the admin of your house witch
Rate
Have all the power
Patella
If anyone else wants to use it back to train their voice
So if you live with
More than just you
You're going to want to train their voice if you have children
You have to then implement this insane
So it takes forever
Where you have to create an account
Kids count
It it's not fun
It will take you time
And that's if they're under 13
That's if they're under 30
Is there over 13 they just have to have a Google account and
A Google Assistant
And then they Trade It
If they're going to trade it on your phone
Pro-tip they're not going to check your child age
But you still have to then they have to have a separate device to turn
Chapter
And then finally
As someone who is actually implemented voice
On voice matching on their Google device
It doesn't always work
So sometimes we even when I'm asking Google for something
It's like
I'm sorry
I can't help you with that
If you would like to train your voice go and do this
Google I can't speak to that because I did not turn on voice match because
Say I don't have any friends so nobody comes
And be my everything work my family they would be very upset
Yeah my family it basically my house is Haji turn on television
And then she says
I have permission to
And then you hear
Harem anime
Turn on television
Group the time
That's usually how that operation
That and that explains why you have both
Pussy system
There you go
And this is an underlying problem that is not being addressed
In these
Which is
Peaceably admin rights for individual
So
Not everybody in your house should be
Be able to turn the
Heating and
Maybe not everyone in your house should have access to
The water's edge
Maybe not maybe not everyone in your house should have
The ability to
Invite people to open your door locks
That's actually most relaxed do actually have those say
So you can let p
People in
As an admin
Where's a gas
But it seems like there should be another layer of security in here at some point in the future
To say
Yes I am the admin of the house
And only the admin
Can change the thermostat or only the admin and these people
So the kind that gets one more granular as opposed to
Voice match which is an all-or-none situation number one and number two we have other devices that can help
Determine who's actually
In the room for example I presume that this person is gas or doing it when he's not in the room
You know and
If you have a camera in the room
Maybe the voices can say it wait
Anybody can turn ya now
You're not here that doesn't make sense
I was going to say what we actually need us both
You need the ability to know you recognize who is asking for something
And then you need a layer of
Basically like active directory for your home
Oh my God
I can't believe you went there hello
CD for the smart home ad for iot the newest Azure service
Well I'm at Grimm
End
Devastated
The awful
I don't want to spend more time in
Skinny to make it easier
It's called at the end of
This week's news section that stay tuned for a message from our sponsor
And
For our guest
Andy carvos who is
Really awesome and is going to talk about
How
We need to think about biomarkers for medical devices and how we're authenticating and actually doing some
Some reviewing of
Claims about certain
Digital medicine
And
She's also going to talk about how the FDA
Is
Really
Becoming a model for other Regulatory Agencies who want to address
Digital transfer
All of this and more
After a message
Dispenser is software AG hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast
I guess for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is software Ag and I have John MacTavish
Who's in the iot group as software AG
This week we're going to talk about how to succeed in the iot
But before we do that
Can you remind us what it is
Software AG does
India
We really provide great Solutions
Simplifying connect
Software applications devices
Richard can be your iot devices
Are people to really quickly abuse business value
Really get that data to work
So quickly
Jelly to make really great
Shania TNA
And we also have
Different Analytics
Solution second layer on top
We're here to talk about how we can Succeed In The Internet of Things
What are the first things we should think about
Taking this on
A couple things
Drive to project really map to keep it
It's really been driven down by a bee
Why I say that is
Make it successful you really have to have by in that
Iot can solve a critical Miss
That's really the basic tonight
Project going
Successful iot project understanding ecosystem
Ic3 critical parts
The hardware Park
Safari Park
And the application
Analytics Spark
Personally I'd like to talk about
Hardware
Understand that
Securing Hardware
Installing Hardware
It's a critical part and not every company has strength
In the space
That is one part of the
Ecosystem yet understand either to do that internally or Outsource
The second part Stacey is really getting the date of slowing and that's what team lost
What's the data
Percentage outside
Shenzhen Hardware
Jimmy John's Pekin
Manage that data
To the application layer
And the third part of the ecosystem
Really see application
Quinoa as a great application
Quickly I design applications to get data
To the business
People that need them
We also have three different Analytics
Solutions II
That has a greater layer of value
Ways to make a really really great decision
Change within you
Okay and what are some of the common pitfalls when trying to implement
Some sort of Iota
T strategy
Moving too fast too quickly it's one of the things I see these these projects can take a long long time diplomats
And trying to bite off more than
What is that really mean
He's really to try to connect
Quite different multiple products at once
Let's just pick one product
Through the volume
Business case
And then move on
Prescribed
In John where can I go to find out more about software Ag and the cumulus
Please call this operation
.com
Enable your 30-day free trial
Access to iot
Success during the trial
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Andy Corbett
Who is the CEO and co-founder of Elektra
Hi Eddie how are you
Hygrate
Thanks for having me
I am super excited because we are going to talk about
Iot
In healthcare
That's my happy noise
Alright so let's kick it off with telling everybody
What it is that you were trying to do with Electra
So we are working with connected devices that can remote monitor people in their own homes
Where we really started was over time we realized that people are increasingly more honest with their phones and their with their
And if you ask anyone
Including myself
How many times do you work out last week I would probably give you a number that's far higher than what my Fitbit says
I mean if you think about
A lot of people like we hate filling out surveys to get any sort of remote data and so a lot of these Technologies
Finally got Joe point where they're collecting clinical-grade data they can do and pass away in your own home
And they don't look terrible no more and more people wearing connected products
And so what we're doing with Electra is helping
Mostly today Pharma companies in overtime doctors and payers and providers use resource
Connected jewels
Remotely and have better relationships with their
Okay
That is awesome and exciting and really promising and also scary as all get-out
So we're going to dig into
All of
But first
Just the idea of being able to do this
Is
Confusing to me in some ways because I feel like
I have a lot of these connected devices and that might range for my Fitbit 2
I used to have this
Crazy like anti-snoring
Device Italy
Attract my story made all sorts of
Correlations about my health
But
All of these things
They're not
Really FDA-approved necessarily or peer-reviewed so I kind of called them digital snake
So I'm really curious how you guys are
Thinking about
Making sure
These devices are actually
Trying to write
Conclusions at your house
Counts from the data
The Wanted
Things that off
Healthcare is Eid around
Digital health
What happened with a lot of visual health is
Really think about what not to do
So anything that has stopped wearing Healthcare from
Medical records
And other connected devices to app seem to be in the surrounding digital house which sometimes feels a little bit more oily than having actual
Find it there's been a movement because
People don't realize that these
Did Jules have a pretty meaningful way to really change how we deliver care and and you need
To think about how do we actually build a regulatory strategy and instead of trust around
Quality
And so there's been a movement towards
Call digital medicine
Where did medicine is a subset of
Is your house that has that level of Clue
And many people split into about three different categories so stop wearing algorithms
Take a measurement
Stop that do some sort of diagnosis
Measure and diagnose
Treat and there's a whole realm of new product called digital Therapeutics that have that sort of treating capability
Okay that is a lot
And what is the goal of your company in this white
Talked about
Biomarkers in
Acting is Cisco
Pharmacy
For digital Health Products what is that actually
Yes we focus on the measure
JD around digital biomarkers
And using software younger than that can measure some sort of Behavioral physiological
Should I be something like
Step count with picture
Height weight age
Gyroscope accelerometer and then predict whether or not you make
So all of these artificial by markers are forms of types of algorithm that then
Can be used to either inform
Or drive
Different parts of care
Specifically we work with armor
Companies that are
Doing something called decentralized clinical trials which means they're collecting data outside of the clinic
And are collecting things like vital signs are tremors
Or any sort of product that
Expecting some sort of digital biomarker
Bedford assessment
Are you certifying the algorithms or
We have an atlas
That has six hundred and
40 different types
Chef products
And so
General Lee a Pharma company needs to think about which type of product they would want to use a cross for spectrum so wanted
Kaiser on verification and validation verification being if I walk a hundred steps
Is it measure on your stuff
Invalidation is does 100 step mean something for
I could just see you or for my Parkinson's or what my clinical population is
Second is around usability what's the battery life not worth it in the shower
It look like a prison bracelet
I wear it
Third is around the security principles for this don't like how do I actually manage the risk
If I'm instrumenting someone with multiple sensors like how do I think about the attack servicenow the person that something from hasn't released
Before
And enforce
Is around
BK Racing Engine
Accurate even if it's relatively usable even if it's relatively secure doesn't solve the Cambridge
Issue
Where
Data were shared and not
But we're here in a way that people did not enter
And what we do is we have instead of objective measures across
Insidious
Four Concepts and then
We
Score that effectively like Nutrish
Where you might say okay really need to make sure this has a peer-reviewed paper or it's been used
In an FDA level study and
Can cover how you think about accuracy
I don't really care if you can be used in the shower now that's not so
Important to us
And then you can make trade-offs
To decide which
Type of choice quotes
Forgiven
Environment
I had never thought about that side effects may include dry mouth and hacking
Oh my gosh
Okay yeah so this would be something like my Fitbit or my Apple watch and I would just
I bring that in and it would be that for a specific type of use case cuz
My Fitbit might be awesome for steps the Apple watch might be
Great for measuring certain types of heart issues is at the way to think about it
Yeah and what's really been interesting as I think people historically is that okay we have
Consumer devices and then we have
Clinical devices in these things are totally different.
Starting to happen is that they're merging so many of the clinical device
Companies have been partnering with tech companies that have created more Nimble and
Products
Depending on what they need you might go for either
And so for many of the more traditionally consumer products they've been working with the FDA to the FDA has a new program called.
Pre-certification program and a number of
Big tech companies have been involved in it so damn son
Fairly which is an ox
Google
Apple
Fitbit and number of others are all working with the FDA to create higher evidence-based products that they can then submit and have part of
Regulatory and Healthcare.
Okay and we will get to the FDA soon
But before we do
Let's talk about the big elephant in the room which is
Privacy
Actually guess it's not the other
Because you're totally named it but
Not this earlier
So
You mentioned that right now
This is mostly for pharmaceutical companies that
They're using this
And it is for their clinical trials so let's talk first about
What is this mean and how would you use this in a clinic
Michael trial
And then we'll talk about what this means is it
Expands to a broader pop
Population in town
How we're going to think about
Listening coyote in clinical trials what does it look like today
Yes I think privacy kind of has two ways that I generally think about it so privacy being more like 1
Affected the security part where maybe somebody's attacking assistant and then there's also privacy where you
You don't necessarily have an attack but you're the way that the date eraser structure and somebody can do
Alexey moron
Security
Contact
Start has never really had to
To think about anything like that before the date of the fifth collected
Clinical trials
Blood drives or other things that are relatively standard and they have most of their data
Stored in
Ways that they have to four
Science
And I never really had to use the
Things that are internet connected on multiple
Time today that are remote from
And so this kind of creates an entirely new type of infrastructure that they
I think I'll have to think about it
Are they looking at using this data for
In a clinical trial setting I assume that this data is isolated for that setting or they trying to create massive
Stores of
Potential patient data what are the rules in place that they
Thinking up when trying to use
I think many of this is up for play
The most Pharma companies when they think about running a clinical trial their data has always been their data so they run is steady and
The Last of Us
Father of the study
What's different about a lot of connects
It's all these they don't necessarily have back
Can fit them better just going to store clinical trial date anyone
They pull out of it together
And in fact many is a wearable companies use that data to retrain their models over time and they don't have a way of splitting it out
This is pretty new for them to think about it okay if you're going to collect
Data auto
Relatively vulnerable patient population
How do I
Ensure that these data maintain private or that
We know
How something
Has been consented overtime and we can manage it away that's responsible for our
Okay and let's go big picture in it
That's because you you mentioned
Earlier that the concept of personalized medicine is
Basically surveillance
Because
To deliver this care you're going to have to understand someone
Inside and out in a way that's really kind of
Is it raining
That's a big responsibility
How should we
Think about that world is that something we should really welcome or the benefits outweighing the
The cost
I think the constant question is just making sure the benefits outweigh the cost in some instances they will and some they won't
Bermuda thing that starts get more important is really thinking about some of the Norms that we have the questions that people with
Identify
And at some point you collect so much data that the identification become
Analogies thinking about
How would you be identified by
You can't write like my genome is unique
Me and if it were truly G identify
Then it went really do
Might be able to strip out parts of personally identifiable information
U-Store-It but if I ever had a snip it you'd be able to
Parrot back 30 seconds of walked in and I'm a uniquely identifiable person
Thinking about things like so who owns the day that there's not really data ownership is
It's really much more about data governance and who gets access to it
And really thinking about okay if we're going to be in a system where things
Can TD identified
How do we make sure that only the right people have access to it and they're using it in a way that's
And how far away are we from
It really all depends on how the registry is or how the data are stored
Armentine
And then the thing that I really like about working with Pharma is that
They think a lot about him
Subjects research
That's the whole work that they do
And so there's a lot of norms
And thoughts around informed
And making sure that that consent is
Truly
Informed if you think about post-market and
Text companies we're constantly and human subjects test
I'm sure Facebook running a number of experiments with me about what they're showing me on the news feed and how I respond but that's
Pretty much unconsented
Human subjects research
Ento
The thing that I'm more nervous about is not necessarily would have
Structures but as it starts to move out and Warren Moore this check is used in a non-regulated
How do you make sure that somebody actually consented and know each other information is being used over.
Alright which seems like a good segue into
The FDA
You were recently in
Entrepreneur-in-residence
At the FDA
And
What were you doing with him
Isn't that the FDA would call the special government employee I've never acted as I no longer
Pepsi employee
What I was doing with the time is
Becky has been very forward thinking about how to handle some of these
I think there's so much opportunity and they recognized that holding things back is
In many ways a different way of
Stopping someone from getting care so we definitely don't want to have things that
Hurt or harm people but also having a solution that you don't allow people to get access to causing the different type of harm
She has realized we need to rethink how we manage diaper products
So today
You're not making constant
Changes to drugs over time but we are making
Changes to Software
If you had your imagined that Facebook could only
Check one software update a year that would be crazy and we don't expect Facebook to maintain order
Stay in somebody's life
We need to rethink as a
Society and at the regulatory
Institution
How do we add a whole group of people working in software wants to maintain a certain regulatory update
Okay and that is key so like
How do we adapt the
Approval process
For medical devices is one aspect
That I know the fda's
Another is actually a big topic that we've had people in the show talk about which is
How do you create
A security framework
That these devices can be both
Tested and make sure that they're not vulnerable to hacks and then also
Updated on a regular
Killer bases this can be
Heart attack
Regulatory approval process
That we just talked about
But it could also be
Possibly making sure that things actually get updated
Which doesn't always happen especially in
I like the first one because
One of the pilot program today
It's quite interesting and then the second
What are the pilot programs yes she is working on
Play something called preacher
Any idea behind precert is that you would precertify
Company under a series at excellence
Principles
Include cyber security responsibilities quality safety
And companies that have this level of Excellence Banner able to ship updates in a way that they can do that a lot faster
There and have a different type of faster review
Amazing
I'm totally different from how the FDA has ever regulated a product before
We don't say hey Pfizer you make good drugs like kind of
Ship is made under this paradigm
Something that is currently being
Bears
A lot of different ways that the FDA
Thinking about this
They've released a free market and post Market Guidance the last year
2 years
One of the big topics that has come out of that is thinking about something called
Cyber security or software billing
Materials and the idea behind materials is thinking about a piece of software
Like a nutrition label
So today nobody Bill Cipher from scratch we all put in through three components into that
And if you have a third-party component that has a vulnerability how do you make sure that one you know that that component
Event your piece of software and that you've been able
Do the update
Any idea around having a list
Ingredients
First Security building materials then you would be able to
To maintain and manage that process overtime
And what else is the FDA working on those the two big issues that the FDA cares about when it comes to
Connected medical devices
They definitely check out that your guidance is that they has one of things I think it's been really interesting about the way the FDA taking this approach
Which is making sure that they're not just building something in house and then releasing it out but how do they do the best type of collaboration
Security conference has been
Surprisingly
Perhaps your many people place where the FDA has found out a lot of new information and has really been expanding its
Thinking around how to deal with
Security vulnerabilities and working
Security researchers
That 3 years ago the FDA went to Defcon for the first time
Which is amazing
Inogen.com is not a place that says generally go publicly
I think many TANF
Kind of go undercover but they don't show up as a Fed
There's a game called find the Fed
You do not want to be found
The biohacking Village
Which is one of the villages under
Domayne desk
Kind which looks at a lot of
Tracking devices in different stores biohacking
Products and has been
Working collaboratively with them
The one thing that has been
Kind of meat is
In January the FDA had a very large public Workshop around cybersecurity and they launched a new initiative called
#sweetheart hacker
And if you go to sweetheart hacker
Dr. Org
This is
An initiative where the FDA has been working to build more collaboration around
Medical device communities and
The security research community
So Abbott thermofisher
Celebs
BB&T
Companies that all committed to attend Defcon this year
And I work collaboratively with
Researchers and regulator
And this is actually been a model that I personally think should be applied to other Industries
For example
We actually talked about this Kevin and I are earlier on another show
With regards to the Boeing 737 Max
And
The sensor malfunction
And idea here is if the FAA actually
Had a process that mirrored some of the things that
The FDA is doing
We may not have had that issue and
Also just going forward as we're talking about like autonomous cars and
Giving computers more control
For more things
This sort of framework
Makes a lot of sense
I know I think that's important
The thing that has been really interesting and amazing for me is before the FDA got involved it to communities
Had trouble working together
So that
Security research community
Started researching a couple different devices one of the first ones that they were looking at with pacemakers
Pacemakers generally try to maintain as long as battery life that they can
And not do anything that's computationally expensive
Turn that encryption of many types are found is computational expensive
I'm so
A lot of them work
So they're relatively trivial exploits that you could do that could reverse-engineer protocol
Drain the battery and or
Initiate a shock
So for many of the researchers and I found this they said hey we should disclose and
Help them do an update
I mean they were doing the disclosures
I'm like any normal tech company when you didn't disclosure there's something
Like a responsible and coordinated disclosure that you can then have the update maybe have a bug Bounty and every
It's fine with the connected devices
The device companies okay thanks for doing this we're going to see you
And that researchers like wait what
Are you doing this medical you tampered with our device
You can't we just can't ship updates whenever we want we regulated
And so the FBI stepped in and said hey
We are not going to be the problem here also that is a fallacy
You do have a security incident you can
Until we want to make sure that this sort of feedback mechanism is
Getting better
Is it has been a really big part of some of this
We're too it's helping some of these bigger companies for learning how to do things like coordinated
Disclosure
Can do it in a way that they can
What's it more of these sorts of updates
And that is a really important thing to say
So everybody out there listening
If you have a medical device and you need to update it for security reasons the FDA is totally okay with
Okay
What Andy
I have learned a lot
I am cautiously optimistic about the future of personalized medicine I love that you're helping address the digital snake
Coil problem and
I appreciate what you've done actually with the FDA as a person who
Uses battle
So the one thing I try to balance
A train is like not being to fudge like it does scare the crap out of me for a lot of this stuff
And also
How to use
They sold responsibly and safely
I think it has a lot of textures the whole movie fast
And break things and that means people die right in healthcare but the nice thing about Healthcare being a bit slower is we might
A chance to design systems that better serve people
And I think this is a really powerful time boats for Regulators for
Companies that are trying to develop trustworthy systems or more people are competing on trust so how can we make
Make sure
That way partner
Responsible and really hopeful. Some of the biggest issues that we have
So thanks for coming on the show
Thank you for having me that's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you
I'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next