Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things
Podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham
Your co-host
Kevin tofel and we have a wild episode number
200 lb
The Internet of Things podcast for you
All right
We are going to be talking about
So many things
We've got a crazy story about
Connected devices in rental units
What kind of
Choices the residence
Get to make we're going to be talking about Kevin and I both
I've gone and somewhat of a gadget and subs
Description
And we've got some new low-power Wi-Fi chip
Microsoft admitting me
Little DP
4 quart
We got the
Apple Gen 2 gateway to talk
Walkabout and Amazon is making the echos natural language processing borax
Put some interesting rumors about airpods
And a
Fun service that's like it's on steroids that Kevin has recently rediscovered
And I wrote about so many years ago and it's
It's a really cool
Anastasis way of saying Kevin really needs to read Stacy stuff more often
Basically
Yes that's a gentle
All right
We also have
Our sponsor this week Fair, ditzy Tri Edge
Iot database you'll hear more about that
The Advocate and our guest
Is my former colleague Mike
Wolf quiz now publisher of
The spoon and the founder of the smart Kitchen Summit he is going to give you guys
Excellent
Advice about what to demand in
You're next
Kitchen
Appliances
You're kind of really want to stay tuned for some of the crazy stuff
That you can soon get
So let's kick this off
With a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is a
Vero
Are you looking for an iot platform
Find out why Kenmore in dealing
Arrow apparel customers have experienced
80% reduction in time to Market
99 /
Percent
Support calls
Antenna
Tire activation
Plus their customers can we use 90% of their work one project to the
To learn more visit a pharaoh
Dot IO
That's a f e r o
All right
Kevin
Let's kick it off this week with
Some tweets
I don't know if you've seen this but
So Leslie Carhartt
Is it at
Hacks for pancakes
What's a numeral for tweeted last week about
Having to move
Because she is getting a smart
In her
Apartment building
However it is not just
Smart Lock
It is also a
Iot hub
And I
Connected thermostat
And all of this has to be connected to
Broadband and
Apparently she doesn't have a way to opt
Out
So this was an interesting thread we will link to
But basically Carhartt is a
Security professional
And she looked at this
And was like
Hello
This is a big risk
I reached out to talk
To her about this but she said she did not feel comfortable
Because of
She's in the middle of this and there might be legal or other rabbit
I totally get that
That your butt
I did find out more about the system
That her apartment complex is using
It's mandating basically
It's mandating it's a system from a company called
Smart rent their basement Phoenix Arizona
They've raised 5 million in fund
Actually just as recently as November 28th
And
They
Are using
A couple
Devices now
This I did not get from Leslie
So it's possible that there
Pitching something
Completely new
But that seems
Unlikely because their website is full of this in
So they're pitching a
Hub made by zapato
It's a Chinese smartphone
Company they've actually
People ask me about their stuff at
Decent in there
Using a Yale lock that is for residential
Services
And then the
Modem inside the Hub is from Huawei
And there's a thermostat in
Leak sensor I'm not sure
Who makes the thermostat or the leaks
Let's dig into some of the issues
I mean cuz we talked about and we actually get many questions from renters about how that you know
Mayfair
Play smart
This is different in that the complex is mandating this is what you're going to use and you have
Have to have it
There are a lot of issues here
Yes the first issue I have is
It's not up
Writing that is a problem
A multitude of
Let's say even if it were opt out
I think there's actually some
Serious wedding issues
Happened here and there's also some questions I Think About by Billie
So let's talk about the issues first
Go into liability
So
The modem
That they're using inside this
And the fact that
Domodomo
A zebra
And it's been accused of being an attack vector
And there hasn't been
Patches
So
People who live in these
Their thermostats there leak sensor
Interlocks are going to
Connect to this thing but they actually
Don't own the house
Nor can they patch The Hub
I want to
So any time there's an issue
Vulnerability
Basically they're relying on
Smart rent
And zapato
Or the underlying
Hardware vendors
Providing service inside this
Zapato hub
Hatchet
And as we all know that doesn't all
Right and to be honest with me we kind of
Have the same issue to a degree in that
Like if my wink Hub has some kind of vulnerability I'm relying upon wings
But I also have the choice to say I'm ditching Wing because you guys don't pack your stuff and these folks won't have that option
Write in a real estate management
Who's installing this
They may be excellent
Property Management
Are they extradite
Team management
Insofar
Nothing that they are
Inside out priority
For them
Necessarily to get this
Commend
Did you want it bad
Ashley to go to smart
And get them to lean on their van
Really long chain
And even aside from that I mean the fact that
The modem itself is
Huawei modem
Personally I'm not
Sold on
Using modems from Chinese companies as a major
But you're obviously it's a concern
Other people including the US government
And other countries governments to say
Don't be using these because
We found a lot of
Townhomes to China sending data and so on so forth so that's an issue right there is all the same device
Yeah I mean imagine if your a government employee
You're not supposed to
To take your work home
Care physician
But even if you're not in a highly secure position
You do have to question you know
Oh man is my modem doing something
And again
This is not something you choose
We also have
A GitHub
Repository on
A hack of this
Particular Hub so
There was a gentleman
Andrew McFerrin who's basically got this Hub in his house and he's like oh
This is neat but I don't want to use the
Smart rent software I want to use
Call my sister
So he basically created an empty
Bridge and brought all the device
Capabilities into his own
Which is great but I meant to say 99% of the renters in this complex are not going to do that
And now let's move to the door lock
This is actually where
ICD
Serious problems but also
A reasonable solution
Already exists
So smart when is apparently using a Gehl door lock that is for residential
Not for multi
And you guys maybe thinking a who cares but
Multi-family unit
Metso apartment building
Actually have different
Regulations around fire code and safety issues
So this is why a lot of us can't put smart locks in our apartment buildings because the
Apartment building has to have access and they have to be able to give the fire department access
Cyst every apartment
Write with these residential locks if you don't have centralized
Control
Is unclear if smart
Is actually providing that
You don't actually have
The capability to let
And and there's also
Surprisingly
Backups
So this product doesn't have a mechanical
Just as a father I guess like a Bluetooth file.
It has no physical it's a punch button or a phonak
So yeah recommends that used product in an environment where there additional entry points
That may not be the case in the park
In fact it's likely not the case
And also with the
Power goes out or the internet goes out the lock doesn't work
Yeah
Yeah me and your keys are a big deal
You may not have it on you but at least a nap
Apartment building
You can go downstairs
A super I'll give you the key
So
That's a little issue
Yeah
Those are some of the things
Ring's End
If you think about
Using Z-Wave
With
Apartment building
There is a possibility of interfere
There's also concerns about ADA Act
So American with
Disabilities Act
Says everything has to be accessible for people
And I'm not
100% clear on how this might
Affect people
But you know it's worth asking
The questions
Checking if you are blind
You can't punch in your
Keypad
You don't code
That's
Not usually do not have the ability
They light up butts
Real on them so that's an issue
And then
There's an interesting thing that I hadn't really thought a lot about
Shabbat
Follow
Shabbat which is resting on the Sabbath
Which is Saturday
And
In that time you
You can't use electricity you can't do a lot of
Xterra lots of
I've had a couple friends were
Ox and it's always really intriguing to learn about the
That's hardcore
So if you think about having an electronic lock
It may not be Shabbat
This is not Orange
Two people in the smart helmet
Actually Whirlpool has a Shabbat
Be sure on their connected washers and dryers
Which I thought was kind of neat
So I don't know if that's something the smart right people are thinking about but
It's something you have to
Think about especially if something's mandatory
Yeah this it's a unique situation because I've never heard of a mandatory
Smart apartment in Ohio
Cassidy and I totally understand where he's coming from because of that
Backer alone and I mean
She was kind of mommy she wasn't joking but I mean when she first told her that she's like I guess I have to move
And that's kind of what I thought of it I laughed and then
He brought this up again before the show and there's a really long it's right about this and like she serious she may have to move because she can't
What does not want to abide by this
Mandatory nature of
These devices these particular devices
What it would mean for our everyday usage
I guess she have to supply the power of the internet as well so she's paying for that
Yeah
Yeah and I will say
So
Looking at this
I talk to lots of smart
Apartment
Actually interview the CEOs of 2
To companies that
Provide smart
Capabilities for apartment building
Felicity Mormon who's
Stratus
And say Pike
Who is a Toyota
In Direction the ones who helped
Educate me many years ago
How about some of the requirements
Swift connected
Homes in apartment
It's in those are voluntary
And they do a lot
Like I had an hour-long conversation
About locks
This is not something that should be
Be taken lightly
And
This feels very ominous
It feels like
The beginning of a backlash
This could create a backlash against
Connectivity
Connected device
In general
If it's not rolled out the right way
And I will also say
And Titus back to what I saw at CES and even my interview with Mike Wolfe later on
We're actually seeing a lot of companies install de-facto Wi-Fi or connectivity in their products
There won't be a non-connected
Adoption
Are we holding back the future I don't know but we still have so many data in
Privacy and security issues that I think it's okay that people are like yeah I don't trust
You know it's not like a
To me it's not like a
But I ate
Knee-jerk let it react
Right now it's
There should always be an option for a non-smart
Device I mean even
In the future however far you want to take it out
No I mean you can't buy a car today without
You know certain
Electronic safety features in
Those
I need my mom is
Fairy
Anti
Digitization of cars
But you won't buy a new car right now because
She doesn't want all of them
Electronic features
True but I mean those are
Those are safety features
You know these are not safety features these are convenience features
Well some of them are and some of them
So a leak sensor icon
Seaway apartment
That I actually had
My apartment flooded because
The apartment above mine
And had a burst pipe
Any regrets
I can see a legitimate reason why apartment community might want that in the
But that's very different than men dating
Connectify
Or
How did the resident
So there are other ways
I'm with you
Alright so we're not going to solve this
But stay tuned because hopefully we'll find out a little bit more I reach out to
Smartvent and its investment team
To try to figure this out
And
Maybe
Maybe she doesn't have to move
That would be nice
Breaking your lease is always a
Pain in the proving that you're not breaking your lease
Police terms
Change is always a pain
Okay that's how we feel about
So good luck
Good luck anyway
Who actually has
Actually if you have to do this you should drop us a line
Intelius cuz I'm very curious how these things are working out for
Okay
Speaking of
Marie kondo
We haven't spoken to her yet I was going to say
I don't know what we're speaking of you guys I'm
Worst singer ever
Worst Segway ever speaking of that
This
We are actually last week
Was inspired by
The life-changing Magic
Tidying up in the Marie kondo show on Netflix
Todoist Gadget
I wrote about it in the newsletter but I'm going to give you the free thing
You guys know I'm moving in
Roughly six months
5 months now
And I was
We're about to put our house on the market and they're like
EBay what are you going to leave on the walls
So
I did the condo-style thing where I shoved all of my
Two devices or their boxes if they were installed in the
The wall and I shut them all in the couch
And I touch them and I said hey do you Spark
Do I actually
And
I decided which two
In which
I didn't want to keep it was really helpful.
Because of this I was trying to figure out what
Put in there and I just couldn't come up
System I kept waffling back and forth
I don't know
Do I want to keep this do I want to uninstall it
Put a new person coming into the house finest
Incredibly complicated and never use it
Columbia West End
Possibly a vulnerability
The results
Keeping the connected thermostat on the wall
So those will convey with the
My Lutron switches will convey with the
The house
Has will the Lutron hub
The monitor
What else
My beloved
Delta touch
To. O
With Madame a
Stalled is going to stick around
I know
I can't see a reason to like
I mean
Yeah you love that thing I do love that too
But I love it so much that in my new house
Not my rental house I'm going to be staying in for a year but in my new house
I will actually get one of those
So that stays in the house the MyQ
Who stays in the house
Chamberlain garage door
I will probably buy a new one
I even buy a new one of those
It's unclear cuz who knows what
What that situation will be
Going to take all my hue light bulbs with me
So that goes away and I'm probably going to install a Lutron
Switch actually where they
The Hue bulbs were
Just to make sure that
Are the main living room area the house has
Attractive light
Write paper be a consistent experience
I also have
A bunch of different connected lights in my house
And I'm getting rid of all of the ones that are not Lutron
Because I don't want somebody to have to like
Install Apache wraps basement
Here's the Leviton app
Remember when they come in they're going to bring their own mattimeo
Google or nothing
And the Lutron lights work
Even if you have nothing
They're still wonderful dimming light
It's just nice
And if they decide they want them to work with something else
They work with
Homekit Google matinee
P
Thermostats
The Nest will work
With Google and Madam a
Will not work with
Door lock
I didn't keep any of the connected door locks because my connect
The door locks are all Z-Wave
And one was an STL. But that was a review genocidas in the back
So I decided nothing Z-Wave or zigbee with stay because I don't want them to have to deal with the
And finally
The connected doorbell
I talk to my realtor
And
He said a connected doorbell with
Be good I had to get back the nest doorbell but I did reinstall my August doorbell
So they have that and then I left the normal doorbell
So that's basically what
Will convey with my
And
How I kind of came to that process
Yes or no like I said don't have like a more consistent cohesive experience because you've kind of outfit at the house
And leaving your leaving the house with Lutron
And everything else would work without a hub so
Let me know it's a nice selling point and yeah you love your play some things but hopefully it
Is Keeling
To potential buyer
Because in a couple wet in six months or so I'll be talking about hello here's how I outfitted my
Rachel house
And it's funny that you wrote this up
And took this Plunge
Which is actually similar to when you don't want to know about a year-and-a-half ago you read it here
Completely remember he went through all your devices
I did my other gadgets
I think it was
Yeah but the difference is you know it was what did you want to use versus now what are you going to leave behind
And you got me thinking of a subscription cleanse
Smart Home
And I've already started it because
I have
Have a nest
Camera in my front window of my home even though the door to my house that's on the side of the house cuz we have an end unit
In the Townhomes here
And it just looks out of the driveway and it's been well worth the subscription price because
When our car got hit last
Summer I guess it was we captured on video I had this
Social service and go back and look at all my video
And
You know I got $1,500
Switches what the repair bill was from the offending
Driver's insurance company no questions asked because
But I really need to pay like $10 a month for that
I don't think I do and this is not a solution to everybody would do and I totally get that but I'm like you know what
I'm just going to save that money and I'm going to throw an SD card or microSD card in a wyzecam which is a $20 camera
I don't need alerts for out there I only need that to see after the fact of something happened
I don't need a subscription for that was my thought
And I canceled the nest subscription on that camera and then actually
Added in a subscription set pretty much a wash and triple savings
On to the nest hello doorbell
Because I do want the history of that in case somebody like it is trying to mess with the front door or anything like that or package
I just get taken that's it out there so it's worth paying for that but for any area that I just want to
See after the fact and go back in time
I don't need a subscription with wyze Cam SD card
So I'm going to continue I think paint
Canary subscription because that covers multiple
Cameras and is kind of like if somebody breaks into the house and I can cash
Capture video from two different angles so
I'm really starting to take a hard look at that and I know how you feel we talked about subscriptions in the past I'm not a fan but you raise a good point from
Business continuity perspective for these companies
So not going anti subscription
But I'm trying to think about where does it make sense
Where must I have one where I was where do I really not even well in how many subscriptions as part of this cleanse did
Tally help how much you spend a month
Well at a higher level idea
But they were not your smart
Home subscriptions are also music and video services
If you have any of those
I didn't get rid of any however I have saved money B
Cause
Even though I am almost an AARP card number officially
I am back in school and now that I have an edu address
I'm getting
Hulu showtime and Spotify for $5 a month as a student
Which is far cheaper than
Elaine's
Yeah Spotify is it the family or individual
Individual that's okay
That's still like $20 savings right there
Outside I save on that and there's others subscription deals I'm looking at as a student as well
I'm just trying to figure out what you how much I really need to like outlay for
Things I must have from Subs
Description standpoint in general
I like it
All right
Well Keep On Keepin On my friend
We'll see let's go to
News
There are new logo
Power Wifi chips
Silicon labs
And this is exciting because I have
Happen
Skeptical that Wi-Fi can get to a low enough PowerPoint
We're talking for example of
Getting rid of Z-Wave and zigbee stuff
In my house and
One of the reasons is that requires a
But one of the reasons there are so prevalent is because they're super low power and they're mesh
So
They're extra resilient and they don't
Long battery life
So
I'm always excited about things like me
Bluetooth and now
Low-power Wi-Fi so this is half the power of existing Wi-Fi according to
Now there are a lot of caveat
Can we talk about radios and
Power consumption
There's things like
Hey
Is the RF environment really noisy that means like are there lots of devices trying to transmit be
Because that makes it
More power intensive to transmit
Or is it farther away from the Hub
Because that also require
It basically has two quote-unquote Shout
Louder
To be heard
So you got to think about all of those things
These are benchmarked
Ideal performance situations
So you're real mileage
Mayberry but we are seeing Wi-Fi
In battery-powered situations
Etsy yes we saw the new Schlage
WiFi powerlock Hampton products
Has their new Wi-Fi power array lock
So there's a lot Happening Here
And with these new chipsets
There should be
Hopefully
Even more
Yeah and I'm interested from a different perspective and at y'all probably being overly optimistic here I know these are for
Iot applications
But I still want to see
Li-fi
Headphones
That can connect to the cloud for assistant
Not this day I put an assistant in your ear that has to connect to your phone
Open Bluetooth
Yeah you keep dreaming my friend I know and I wanted hope AR 300
Episode will be talkin
That's two years away
Pirate
Microsoft they admit is
Defeat for court
They're pulling a big speak no no just kidding
Microsoft is interesting you know with the whole smart
Speaker space
We don't see too many speakers with Cortana in there
And I have a feeling we're not going to see him anymore and that's because
Satya nadella the CEO of Microsoft
Basically said that
We don't really see Cortana as a competitor to Madame a or the Google Assistant
We really think it should be a
Skill
That should work with those assistance
And that's
To me a small bit of tooth
Feet in terms of
The smart speaker space
It also means that they're going after work
More with
Google Amazon to do for their Integrations
With Cortana and Amazon actually has which is
Promising for them but I don't know I don't think it's going to have with Google
To me this is so fascinating
Because
Microsoft
Cloud level so it's Azure Cloud competes
Very heavily with
AWS and
Less so with Google Cloud cuz
Microsoft azure
Number two in the space
And I'm just like
Peso
Interesting
Dislike
Another word for inside another level
Peter Leahy
Yeah that's the way it is in this market
So
I will say goodbye to Cortana on devices
Possibly hello to
To telling matamata
Activate Cortana to do something on my
Windows
All right
Let's talk about
Abode this is
The
Security system it's
Excellent
I have
Heard from
So many people
Who have this
But they love it
And this is the Abode gen1 but now
Thursday bojan
To Gateway
This will begin shipping next
And
It features 4G cellular back
Z-Wave in it
And those are the big new things
But Kevin
Will tell you a bit more about what the heck this
Yes so the above systems you haven't heard about it
It's really more of a it's a hub as well as like I said
Security type system because
They make motion sensors in
Door window sensors and such
So as you said it also has 40 backup so it's next
Next gen for them
People who bought the first gen which generally have been very happy with it
They don't have to pay the full price for it because the
Full price just for the basic bundle is 279
With the Gateway
And it goes up from there if you want to add like their Kinect bundle over there
Sakura bundle you can pay $360
But you can get the Gateway if your
Previous abode
Gen 1 hour for 199 so it's going to save you $80
You're not going to have a transition
From the old device to the new one in a sense because
You have to manually re-enroll all your connected devices so there's no
Automatic
Set up enforcement with a new one
If you have a gen 1 device and you love it
You don't have to
They're going to keep supporting both gen 1 and gen
Can two devices
Sense is true
This is true
They're bringing better Z-Wave connectivity to
The Gentoo so it would mean that's one possible reason you might want to upgrade and the 4G cellular backup is also in the
Another reason but if you don't need those
You can just stick with what you got unrelated note there's no announcement that they have homekit support
40 yet
With abode
They do say that
There's an apple and they plan to have additional news to announce soon as we continue to work with the Apple homekit
Getting so it sounds like a
A near certainty that's going to happen soon
Ring made similar nouns
And we've been waiting for a year-and-a-half on
Well they'll sign acquisition
Okay fine
Alright let's talk about quick news bits or more quick news bits
Airpod 2
With Rupert health
I am excited about the
Cuz I believe that
Well I don't just believe this
Proven fact
That you can get a lot of information
And from your ears
You can get
High quality
Brain data high quality
Heart rate data
High quality
Galvanic skin response
Stata big word
And
Did you take a
Skeptical
No doubt about it
And we have talked about this before you're bullish on this I'm kind of bearish on this because
I have an Apple Watch which has
All those types of sensors are most of them I do not have the Apple watch 4 with the ECG but
Don't want that so that's fine
So do you have the current airpod switch don't have any sensors whatsoever but I wear them when I run in the griefer
Stream music from iWatch
If I have the watch
I have no interest in airpod 2 with
Health Center Schoharie have the health center
Additionally
Emily Catherine data
When I wear the headphones it's not going to be like all day. Because you're not going to wear these all day so
Don't have an Apple Watch against
I just want to track
It's another way maybe to track like your runs or something if you don't want an Apple watch
Those are very expensive
You pop that your pots in to go running and you can grab data
I will also in I'm with you on the airpod
I'm kind of like a do we need that no but
Icees
Starkey
The hearing aid come
Actually showed off something
Really cool wish this their new Livio
Hearing aid
That has
A lot of sensors in it already
And they're actually tracking
Steps but they're also doing things like fall data
Text now with
A hearing aid is something that you actually leave in almost all
I thought that was
That's one of the reasons that I'm so delicious
Excited about this cuz I see a future where
We going to convergence
Earphones
And things like
Medical hearing device
And suddenly you have the
These things basically in your ear all the
The time in a performing a useful function
And having that battery life
We'll see
Multi
So
Taobao
Yes let's talk about node-red which I thought was a brand-new thing but Stacy correctly informed me
That she wrote about in 2013 and we talked about it at least once before the show
My favorite was the fact that we've had this conversation
Before like a year ago
Yeah
Oh it is
Awesome I have check
Memory upgrade
For those who don't remember such as many talking about node-red it is very interesting and worthwhile look if you go to no draw
Red. Org
It's basically
I call it
If this then that on steroids because
It has so many
He usage has so many integration points
It's rather technical support more technical than if this then that
And yet it's not at the same time because it's a drag and drop interface almost like
The MIT programming language
We keep old blocks into make me know to create program
He got a flowchart out what you want your devices to do how you want them to communicate
And
Send messages notifications and you can connect things to databases that mean that you could go hog-wild and the only reason
My radar again today is because somebody on the Reddit home automation subgroup
Had completely outfitted a
Many many devices entire home
With no dragon head always float charge and I was like oh this is
School so yes we have talked about it before no it is not
Specifically new
It's worth a look if you're looking for a
Different way to automate your
Home automation in your smart home and you can run it locally like on a Raspberry Pi or you can run
In the cloud through AWS Microsoft Azure Etc
So it's another option
And you can use it
With home assistant
So home assistant is one of those
Downloadable
It's like open have
Homebridge
Is it downloadable thing
Run another pie and run all your devices
And you can actually use node red on top of
Have an easier way to program your
Pair devices
So why should
Say it isn't just for this
It's actually very
Popular in becoming more popular in the industrial iot
So we're seeing some people in the OT World Maybe
More familiar with this type of user interface trying to
To adopt it
For setting rules around here
Smart buildings
And also
So this is I mean it's a pretty robust platform it was developed at IBM
Wayback
14 is Kevin said and it's
It's a good soft
I like it
I think that covers a lot of stuff
This week please run the gamut
Let's go now to Riot podcast listener hotline
Hotline is
Sponsored by Schlage
Don't miss your chance
Schlage connect
Smart deadbolt
Now it is zigbee certified and has Amazon key compatible
Upgrade your smart home with the
Safety Simplicity and
Style
Ashley
And
We did not have for all of the month of January
A giveaway
Changing that as of today so everyone who has called so far in January is now enter to win a
Google
Home this is
Open Google home that this is part of my device
I'm so if you don't want it that's okay I'm not a fan
Apple
You do want to be entered
You still have a few days left
We'll go up to January 31st at midnight
And all you have to do is call us on a voicemail
5126 to 3
7:40
To 4
And leave a message
So let's get to this week's
Voicemail
This one is from John
Stacy and Kevin
Calling regarding
Wi-Fi
Lights
Interested
And your recommendation
Brightest
Normal bike
A19 size
What
150 watt type
Size bulbs
Seems to me
There's not too many very bright ones out there
Strictly shouldn't wenzhou
Hubless
Are Wi-Fi
Songs that don't need a hug
Cheats that most of
Topping out at
Seawater
Maybe 75-watt
Mange
Monkey looking back
I'm looking for a soft light dimmable
Situation
And I'm also curious if maybe it's
Smarter better
You get a c
Smart
And then just use regular
So this is an interesting question because most of the smart bulbs that we
Found
Pretty much max out at like a 75-watt equivalent lifx
Seems to be the brightest in terms of lumens
We started looking 450-watt Replacements we came up short
There are
Definitely LED bulbs
We did find a couple but we would not recommend them
Because they are from
Randall
Random
This is true
Books that we're not very familiar with I guess I should say yes
To your thought about
Getting a Smart Switch is
Probably the way to go and
Because of that you're going to save on the cost of your balls because the bulbs won't be smart
Your switch would then be no obviously cost your maybe forty $50 but you can find
Many many LED bulbs that are in the range of
Any word from
15 at least 1600 lumens
If you want to go with the inexpensive route EcoSmart
Has 100 watt replacement LED bulbs
They are
Basically
Price of $10 27 for a two pack
So that's where you're saving your money since the smarts aren't there
Cree also makes 100 watt replacement LED bulb but there could be a little more Spencer your PayPal
$13 for a dimmable LED from them
We definitely found all doable because you mentioned him both so it was one non-dimmable I'll just mention in kg
She decided don't need that effort every single light
Phillips does make
A 100 watt replacement non-dimmable LED with about
Lumens
And that'll cost you about it
$12 97 for a two packs are the same as 1 crib also
You're obviously paying a little bit more for the dimmable Factor if you want that but
You got a bunch of options there
I would go with the switch quite honestly
There's just if you need that kind of brightness
And then Tim ability Factor
Might as well save money on the balls I just put the switches in
Yeah I agree
And having
And having it be dimmable is probably really awesome
Awesome because
It's not all the time you want multiple light bulb
I was giving you $100
What's right
Sometimes
Dial it back a little
Yeah these are all soft whites as well so just put that into the
Equation as well
Stacy you're more of a light switch off Smart Switch person than I am so what are your favorites
And what are the cost
Sister Joan has an idea
Torso
Lutron
If you want it
To work with
Assistance you're going to need a hub
So you may not
Want to go that route
Route those are about 50 V bucks
Her
Switch
The other options are Leviton
And those are about 40 to $50 but they don't require Hub their Wi-Fi switches
WeMo has a Wi-Fi
Switch that works really well
But I don't love the fact that it's really bright
Has all these lights on it so it's not great for like
And
Those are good
Brilliant
What is a light
Panel but it's
Overkill if you just want
Lights it also acts kind of a smart home
So it's coming to Mableton
Integrates with cubed integrates with all this other stuff
It's a neat concept
But it's a lot of work to program and
It may be Overkill
And it's far more expensive as well
So it's brilliant a 1 gang switch cost $300
Or the control a two gang switch
It's going to cost $350
Echoes up for their
You can use the fancy
Capacitive touch screen
Boxer thermostat
Music
All kinds of stuff
You pay more but you're getting more in that case of if John wants
To add features he has that option then
John I don't know if
I need to go that far
I mean if you want to go that far it's a nice enough
It's your money
All right
Well I feel that we have reached
Good closing
Remember
You have until January 31st to get
Just call at 5 1/2
623-7424 and
Enter to win a Google home
It has been used
It feels kind of lame
Stacy's trash is your treasure
Exactly
Thanks Marie kondo
T2 now for our guests this week Michael Wolff of the spoon
And the founder of the smart Kitchen Summit he's going to be talking about connected kitchens
And the features you should look for in your next big appliances
Hey everyone we are taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is database provider
And we have evolved
Aloe vera
Who is here too
I talked to us about farrakhan's new
Sitri Edge
Database
You go to database
Specifically for the iot
Tea tree Edge
Why
To answer your question why was to try to help solving the problem
Bridging the Gap that exists today between
Is that two roles that they already
Connecting the sheer amount of operational sensors that are producing thousands of data points per second
Is provided by the information technology systems
Okay and how does a database
Justin Bieber
But you can also have
Edible just like chains
Hub spoke or even met too many repetitions with filters to separate which they deliver sent where
It's almost like a fool
Are the basics care of that for you
Motor model database this entity provides both SQL and nosql
A computer requires
SPAC High School
I forgot to give you the flexibility of the skin
Kevo store interfaces
You can drop hundreds of thousands of data points per second
Still having to worry with the extra latency traduced by relationships are complex SQL queries
Traditional relational database for example
SQL database
So you can integrate your business intelligence your machine learning
Or any other bit of processing system that requires a standard interface has inquired it in real time
This can be done directly on the edge
Or on your central repository for
And what about
Security
It supports most of the algebraic systems like raspbian Windows RT Oracle decor
Karate application without having to write a single line of code
Not to mention the sport to Ida platforms like thing works from PC
That sounds great
So where can I buy listeners find out more information
About seats
Sensor data in real-time
Supplication to put a belt on a Raspberry Pi that you can easily do by yourself if you want
It's available on fire cam. Cam
If you'd like to watch it
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things
Podcast today's guest
Is Michael Wolff
Who is founder of the smart Kitchen Summit and
Publisher of the
Spoon he's also a former colleague of mine
Gigaohm and he's
Now on
Bigger better
Smarter things
So Michael are you doing
Be good Stacey thanks for having me on
Man thanks for coming
And so I love
Smart kitchen gadgets
Like my favorite thing in the world
Actually it is not my favorite thing in the world
My favorite thing in the world is probably my nanoleaf lights they don't do anything
Next up is the kitchen
We just got back from
What I saw was a lot of the big Appliance
Fans are now actually offering real connected devices in the kitchen not just
You know things are wifi-connected but actually trying to build smarts into
I saw a fridges that
Eye cameras in it
I saw lots of ovens with
You know AI
You cooking
What are the big trends that you're seeing
From the major
Yeah I think you had a right
One of the things I wrote about for malachor this year was We would see
The big Appliance maker
Finally integrating
Intelligence
Features
Things like cameras and
Kind of things that understand what's in the cook
So I think you saw that cross the board was it at
Since they had their countertop oven this Century what I would call in sick of June like oven they also have their smart
That word actually had
Augmented reality on top of that memory as you cook
You can put stuff in then come does an overweight
Video screen
They also have this
Really kind of interesting modular oven
From KitchenAid that Elijah Wood
Steamer like a grill in there you also saw this
From Samsung they're entering the fourth generation of the family of Samsung's been going at it for a while now with the refrigerator and freezer talk about quite a bit in
For the first time really
Family Hub refrigerator actually has food recognition
So they've had the camera in there for a while if you're shopping
You can see what you forgot
That's okay that's kind of interesting but like the ability to actually recognize
Food pantry opens up some other interesting applications
I think what we saw from the big Appliance makers is moving beyond this idea just like
Adding WiFi and app control
Adding more intelligent creatures around cooking like Machine Vision play GE Building in the Hesston capabilities or the countertop
Cooktop is that you
She talking to the bachelor
Cookware to all these different things
Together showed me that the big of ice makers are really kind of making a Porsche
Into the kitchen
And adding work
Okay so then my question to you becomes as a consumer
Let's pretend that I am building a house
Cuz one day soon I will be
And I'm looking at all of the
The stuff
I feel like they're still several ecos
There's like whirlpools got there yummly stuff
Dimension GE and Heston
So
How is that working
I think we're still early stages right so even though the big eyes art
Getting in we are still
In these worlds were there separate Island
Technology nothing really in her Opera
You have guys like in it that are trying to ascend
Is an operating system if you will
You mentioned yummy that's really kind of whirlpools play the kind of build your own the other bag of ice
I figure they said hey why don't we just build her
Tire wall Garden
Technology
But I think that
That's kind of the challenge of early-stage markets we saw the same thing in the Smyrna or nothing really kind of work together
I think that's kind of.
State Route with
The kitchen until I take the challenges
Moving forward as I had to get these things dinner Opera
So I think Amazon Echo
AG I think those are kind of the deaf
Acto interoperability layers where they basically kind of circum
Vented and circumnavigated
What the kind of War
Smart kitchen Technology support on Technologies were trying to be
Stepping back into your question of if you're trying to build a home
I still think it's so early that I don't think a lot of
People who are building homes in
Customizable kitchen if you're redoing your kitchen so I can $50,000 thing the Challenger is like
Okay what do I put in there from a technology purse
The water this app isn't available
So all people really think he is a Sub-Zero fridge
Why won't like the G
Cafe line about technology I think if you're moving into new home you're thinking maybe about smart home but I just
Don't think you were there right now think about I want really advanced technology make
It is early
And let's just be selfish just for me since I have you in urine
And it like 18 months
I am going to be
Moving into
To a new home
Buy new Appliance
So maybe not witch
Companies I should look at but what are the technologies that you
You think will be there that I should be like
I will not settle for anything less than
Well I don't know if it's
Too early but I think it'd be really cool. Is building a new kitchen
The new home to have
The wireless power Consortium technology and my countertops like that'll be really cool
To have a inductive kind of
Power transfer technology
You can be silly have a
Qi Power Pad in your countertop that'll be pretty cool
I think it may be too early 18 months might be
Be kind of kind of course I know that they're trying to push it
Kelly's big guys are really pushing hard to get more
Technology for offerings in their high-end and
Keep pushing you down towards their kind of mainstream
Start off on the high end products of the moving into their Main Street
Tokaji eats a GE Cafe line
Pretty high-end
The challenges
You may have to have a mix
Brand type of kitchen if you want like the most advanced cooktop the most brands like if he wants like Steam
I've been like you want most
Refrigerator you need to sound like this hodgepodge a brands
It's cuz like right now you can't really look at anyone Brandon say Hey Dad this great line up across all the built-in Technologies
That have great smart technology really ban
They're all different
Let me break it down maybe this way so you don't have to tell me that Brands but like
What should I look for in my
Prevention cameras
Maybe food recognition so let's do that tell me which are the Advanced Technologies I should need in
Jacob replied
It's a so we'll start with the fur
I mean Samsung
I think LG
Has been there as well really trying to make the refrigerator the Showcase in the
Location of Ike more advanced
Technology
We're on the fourth generation family Hub refrigerator like I said this is the first year that there cameras inside really understand what
Food is I think it's pretty
Interesting
The channel for me is like iced tea packets
Say how committed to Samsung long-term
Do I want to spend $4,000 on a Samsung family hub
And will that have a Tinder why cycle it seems like they're really committed it's like they've been going at the store
For 5 years now it seems like they're going to be there
Everything from the second generation on
Upgrades to the latest software
If I were working in a fridge you know you probably go a Samsung or LG
I would definitely want cameras inside and Wi-Fi connectivity
Other than that like there's nothing really
From the mainstream technology perspective
That you can get much more than that
Does not the electronic nose built into these fridges yet right there's nothing like that
Some of these
Kaiser think about putting like warming
Defrosters in the fridges so having like Beyond freezing at you going to warming but that's not available yet
Okay and then let's talk about my other
I demanded my Smart Oven
In 18 months
I would love to have
An oven with a
Cool
Screen on it weathers to television
Or like a monitor or like an augmented reality
Translucent screen like you saw with like a Whirlpool I think that it really cool I think
You've grown to like your June
So having something
That recognizes what's in
Inside and kind of
Programs
The cook
In monitors the cook I think that'll be pretty cool not Technologies definitely moving into the built-in appliances I would demand that
I like the idea modularity
KitchenAid have this module
New
You be able to add steam functionality or add like a grill function out in there or I got cooking Stone
So is that in
Inside the oven
It's inside the oven
And it's basically add-on
So there's actually like
Can interface at the back of the venue
Depandi sings In
Haha okay cool
My stove top
I would go with induction
I know that induction cooking isn't as popular in the US
But I think that there
So much more you can do
Your kid is less likely to get burned or just less likely for a fire to start
And you can do things like high-precision cooking like what the heck
I like the GE oven with Heston technology built in
You could do this guy to cooking her
Hi Precision cooking you can't actually do that with fire
Felicio
How about my dishwasher
That's a great question
I would like
Kind of love these little countertop
A big built-in kitchen with
He's really kind of
High-end appliances
But like the tetris going to be shipping I think
By mid-year and there's another one I forgot the name of it there's another smart
Countertop dishwasher that actually
Uses like a fraction of the water
In a much smaller washwell
I really like this
I just think it's such a smart idea
Would you say
Cuz I was envisioning
So I'm on the market for those
Drawers that pull out
Dishwasher drawers that are not full size dishwashers coz
I have a family of three so
It's like two of those wood
Do just fine for me but
What are you talking about is this an actual countertop
Yeah so he works
Announce
In 2018 SES the Tetra dishwasher is a truly cool
Dishwasher design Fathead that frog design
Design company frog made it look so sexy it uses a gallon of water
I can do to spice up
So it's a much
Ecological footprint like it waste Way West water weigh less energy
It also has
If you're living out of an RV or if you're living in a dorm meeting at U of a dishwasher
All right I'm seeing these
Okay and then let's see
I feel like
There's tons of countertop appliances
That people can draw
Just buy those feel great for like a retrofit are there any standout
You know countertop appliances that you're like oh my gosh
If you buy a dumb coffee maker
You're making a huge mistake
You know coffee is like
Waiting on the
NetSpend
Copy machine for a while
But there are some interesting connected coffee makers coming out
I'm waiting for a Kelvin coffee roaster one thing I've been waiting to do that
You trying to roast Tech coffee in the home and does it cost a roaster called Kelvin that should be shipping this year they're actually running a little late but that
It's kind of fun what's your coffee drinking habits are you someone who drinks everyday
Super automatic
Coffee maker
Bruised it but hey
I've been looking at the bonaverde
I'm not going to
I think looks amazing
We try that other problem is you really need to
Capital One apply
Right I think the roast grind Brew
It's like
I think that at one picture too much I think the roasting
Built into an appliance that also crying that bruises maybe too much
You're saying that's over
I tasted the coffee and I was
I am so here for
But okay
We will not worry about that
Let's talk
Talk about any other countertop Appliance
I should be like
This must have intelligence
No I mean
I don't think you want to add a total
This retarded sake
I think
Steam is underrated
Yeah Wilson Rothman of the Wall Street Journal that has the same thing he said it ever been like that's a category he's waiting
The pop
Waiting for customers just makes your food taste
So you saw 2 Ball come out there generation
Do this like about a couple months ago I did a review of it I really like the
The taste of food this is another new guys
It's always a
Countertop oven
Smartest
But it has female tattoo
And such a little cheaper than the June
There are some like I said I mention the whirlpool one that actually has steam capability they can add as a feature
I do think if you're moving to new house I think
Steam is like 7 years real look at cuz it just makes food taste so much better
Induction and
Steam
Keep that in mind
So also
With the Samsung family fridge for example there's a
GE just showed a downdraft
Kind of system with that
27 in
Screen audit
I feel like I saw something else
The screen on it and I was kind of like
So what
Talk about where the Hub in the kitchen should be or where we need all these screen cuz I certainly don't need every Appliance.
Come with a really expensive
Beautiful screen that I'm just going to get grease all over
I mean I think that Amazon or Google
Marcus plays
That was really smart
Because if you look at the kitchen like it's where we spend so much time it's the Gathering
Spot and we were making food purchasing decisions and you can't do all that as much as I like
Amazon wants you to avoid shopping
You're not going to do out
Was I not filling out a
React shopping list
So I think that this idea of having the smartest ways on countertops
Really is
Martin you're seeing those really take off what appliances
Should take a belfie
I just don't know if it's going to be the refrigerator
I think this refrigerator has a very center
Space in most homes
Don't know if I could going to see tens of millions of like family have pepper
Refrigerators at
Speak strength screen
It's not a bad idea but I think that's kind of a limited set of people they're going to do that
BGE large
Display GE I think that's
Pretty interesting idea I think it's probably
Refrigerator conversation
So I don't know
If I can pick a winner
I think it may be a mix of all these in a water smart countertops
Swayze I think that did you see the Whirlpool oven with augmented reality on it
Yeah I said it
I just don't know if people who watch a lot of television on that everything but I do think I got to be like
Really interesting
Into manager cook and maybe do some shopping on
Okay
And I feel that we have to talk about the
We have talked a lot about Trends but it's time to get
Time to get in the now
So The Wirecutter just put out a review it was
January 15th
I love The Wirecutter I've actually in
Full disclosure arrive at work for the wire
Hair cutter and done some reviews for them
But they are headline
It broke my heart
June oven review
Not the countertop oven used
You should buy and basically the wire cutters Michael Sullivan
Who I don't know
I'm sure he's a wonderful person who knows what he's talking about he basically said that you nothing at $600 is not
Not better than their
Cake toaster oven
Is the Cuisinart
Tob 26
0 + 1
That'll stick with you
They're like you know what cost more and it doesn't do as much and they're big beef seem to be the
What's frustrating to find programs I don't know if
Is food just wasn't recognized
He couldn't adjust time in increments that work for him I don't know so I was curious
Your take on this
That's because you know I know that you know that you enough and in one of your
Your colleagues really loves his
I mean I feel like people when they do reviews
The projected WaterOne
What this means for like ever one right
I think people are so unique and how they cook
And have such
Specific views and what works for them
Michael Sullivan I don't know him I haven't read the review in full by like
I'm sure he's
Trying to extrapolate like how he likes his
Kitchener like and what he kind of likes and fell faults but
You have someone like
You I think you have the June one
Chris Albrecht with June to em both love it
I know that a lot of kids would that you and because it's very easy to cook with her kids so I can't really speak to what his mean
Problem was I do think there's
It's right I think that their society by
It's a small countertop oven
I also just think that there's
General Luddite feeling among a lot of people and a lot of editorial people that just reject on his face like
More technology in the kitchen they just want us to use kind of old-school tool to grew up with we don't need more SmartThings
This is glass maker space
Face in the home one of the things he talked about was the cameras fun to use but it doesn't make
Cooking easier
Which
Rang very false
Because to me it makes it tremendously easy because I just put something in and I don't know how that if it identifies
Then I don't have to know how to
Yeah I mean
Are we all do this
Are people right but I think often times the articles are written before review things and I feel like
And I can't speak to the
This Michael Sullivan tennis article
I know I've had people
Write about
Things just go get that remind me up for
It might just be that he rejects the idea by more technology in the kitchen
Or he just found it you didn't like it
Like maybe he was had to struggle
What's a recognizing his bacon
Yeah and I wonder if you tried to cook
Some fancy
Cuz he's talking about the
Camera getting stumped a lot
And I mean every now and then mine gets
Stumped
We can go like a month without it not recognizing
Something because I mean we tend to cook the same things we're not
I like super
You have 2 player Adventure SP
So I don't know
This wounded me to the core of my
My soul so I was
No I mean I think he has a point where I'm looking at article now I do think that the main
Probably have is like the June is actually
It's right like it's just doesn't have that big a cavity and that's what I
Pushing and asking and wondering win the big geyser
Forgetting in getting back what we talked about earlier having these big built-in appliances
Whisper capabilities I think it's going to
Really be interesting cuz
You can't cook it
A turkey
I can only do so much with these small cavity of mine doesn't even the Jim Bilton like his beastly the
Is the countertop in a
Hilton
Container it was a really like a wall up and it was more than
You're sticking the June countertop in the wall
And I I will agree with
With that I do wish this were in my larger ovenly
Okay
Well
I just I had to bring that up
And I am looking forward to your next smart kitchen event
Wherever it may be
Where to going to be
At houseware show in March I have to go to that that's
It's a great show for countertop appliances in
In San Francisco on the future of food robots Chris Albrecht and I and that whole whole spoon team will be doing a food web
It's a very small bet that we're having the guy who's behind the Sony aibo Ravin
The head of Google brain come and just getting all these nerves in her room cuz I talked about how robotics will change the world of food
And so that will be on April
Intemperance
It's called articulate
Awesome
Well thank you so much Michael I appreciate you coming on the show this week
And your future inside says I'm building my new home
Awesome
Thanks Stacy
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week