Hey everyone welcome to the 206 episode of
The Internet of Things
Podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
And this week we have a
Pretty tremendous chauffeur
Today
At the edge
We've got Apple buying some patent
Consider of in
I want an echo Auto
We got a new August video doorbell
Get some tips for madam
A
Got a dead robot
Plus
We got a lot of advice
Saint hubs
And
We're going to hear how
Mitsubishi Bank
Has
Connected
Any devices using the affair
We're going to hear from Chrissy Mayer Who is a partner at root Ventures
She's going to explain why Ark
Connected devices cost
Souderton
Let's get this party started
But first
A message
From our sponsor
This week sponsor is Western Digital Western Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to see
The biggest challenges
What's your digital is introducing its most advanced flash storage solution the eu5
511 this is built to empower 5G mobile devices it'll allow you to
Play board games save more memories and binge more videos so get ready for
5G future at Western Digital.
Okay
Kevin
I guess we're going to start off with
Machine learning
So Google has
Anu
Development board
Let's talk about that
Actually announced
This last year at the Google next conference that's a big cloud conference
Products
Now they are
Launched in beta
Name is coral as you would said
When is a USB stick
Raspberry Pi
Ginormous
Heatsink and fan on the processor I would have thought it was a Raspberry Pi but it's not it is
I'm bored
Google's Edge TPU that's their tensorflow processing unit
So for example you could connect this to a camera device
What
Google says it can use state-of-the-art mobile Vision models up to a hundred or more frames per second
Power efficient manner
Very specific types of processing again at the edge
I think these are development
This is really geared towards people that want to build products using it so
Other product announcements but this has tons of potential and I know you're all about processing at the edge so
You're going to tell us what the potential as I suspect
Yes so
This is in line with what movie is Intel with its movidius stick
Actually offered about a year-and-a-half ago
And
Right now we're looking at these on Lake
Computers these are USB sticks
Do you plug in the computers but imagine being able to plug this into
Like a video camera is Kevin mentioned
Or even unlike an industrial iot Gateway
And what you're going to be able to do is you're going to have
You'll have to
Pre-trained your algorithm in the cloud
But this allows you to do
Inference at the edge
It's computer vision is one thing you could do
Predictive maintenance kind of algorithms
You could actually do a lot like even like anomaly detection
Would be a really good one
So
The sky's the limit here and we don't actually even really know how we're going to use
I can even see it
Processor
Inside a car but
Getting your bikes
That I don't know
Think about all these fun
Computer vision or better AI
Oil processing would be another
Oh yeah they doing
Expanding your wake word
Capabilities might be an option
So much
Very exciting
Look for that if you are into building this sort of thing if you're not
Send all those people were building it look for in like a year to having
Just even better machine learning at the edge that could be applied to Machine Vision
Anomaly detection
Audio
I don't even know what
Whatever you desire
As long as you have $150 cuz that's the cost of the coral to report
Okay
Wicked
Actually I did mention this to the beginning which is
A shape
We have a bankruptcy filing in the smart home space
So I feel like
Last month in February
Centralite
Which makes
Bunch of sensors in
It is supposed to be sent
They filed for chapter 7
And chapter 7 means
Are not coming back from
Chapter 11 is restructuring chapter 7 is like we are done
We are closing
This looks like
Someone had sent this into us and they're like this might be because of
You know the end of Lowe's Iris central nervous system
Shut that system down or is in the process of shutting that system down
They also made the sensors that were used by Xfinity
And some other
Pink are two things here
When is the end of the year
Companies buying this trap in their own
Phone brand to sell
Lesson focus on sensors and
We all thought this was going to be like
People were going to buy these cool sensors
Create these cool longtail applications for iot
Way back at the early days of this
That's not actually what happened
Instead what we seeing is
A lot of the heavy lifting has been done by you
Amazon Echo
And sensors have been a pretty small part of
For the mainstream
Hyatt
So
I tried to get a list of deaths that these guys have all like
Could get was the list of creditors
Pretty much as you would expect
Their basic
Lourdes
Cable service providers
Nothing really exceptional
I didn't see anything
And if you bite
You have until
May 28th
This year
To file your
Claims
He comes later in the show. But maybe we should talk about something else too
Say goodbye to
Wish I could say something a saying goodbye to us if you think about it
Yes we also have another goodbye
We actually saw this goodbye
Lighthouse which made a connected
Which also had a Time
A flight
Sensor in it they gave it
Really exceptional
Depth perception
This allowed it to get a lot
More information about the environment
Even more accurate
But beyond that
It had voice recognition that it been translated into automatic
So I might tell the camera do you like your lighthouse
If you don't see my dog walker by 4 p.m. today send me a note
Application
And what it would do is it would take that command which is really complicated
To do it would recognize it and then parse that out and then
If it did not see the person it new as your dog walker
By that time
It would be like
Hey yo your dog
That kind of usability is
Pretty exceptional
The downside was It was a
Very expensive
A subscription
The associate
So
The company did not do well
Shut down
But
There's been a lot of talk about
Siri
The homepod and how it's
It's not an awesome experience
But
With something like
That capability
Become an awesome experience
What will be interesting is
Such a platform would have to be expensive because you would need all that ready
Are you ready for this
That machine learning at the edge that we talked about
To really understand it
Parse all those commands
And understand what it was looking
And somehow that dated actually does have to get to the Cloud
I guess it could be aggregated data so what we'll see how it does that
It still has that app
Privacy
I think
Lighthouse
Was ahead of its time
Nothing much
But I suspect that in the business model you know what
Subscription to use Etc
It's what heard it and it's typical Apple to wait for a great product
Market open up
And then go Apple Magic to make it simple to use etcetera so
I'll be interested to see if they use it for any
Homekit
Devices of Their Own
Cuz I don't think they would
License without 2
Other Hardware makers
It's also possible they just want to improve face detection on the phone
That's true I mean
Possible
Awesome Face detach
All right
So that's
Not so long ago.
There is actually a recent death
Cash
The most morbid podcast
The my buddy that actually glad I did not drop $900 on
Jibo robot
Which we knew that Jibo was shutting down
And everybody who bought a Jeep
So you going to have a useless
Jibo robot
It's done
The company credit
Geebo itself
The robot itself in people's homes is
Saying things like
Around
It's kind of cute and funny it's up to make
Bad situation somewhat
Easier to deal with but
$900 brick
I came close to buy on two
I know you did
This was a case
It being announced really early and then the functionality just
Skyrocketing ahead in this was like going to be like a Amazon Echo on Wheels basically
Amazon Echo
Got so much better so
Satchel
There is a new product out
And it's worth talking about
August
Made the August lock and the August video doorbell
And was bought by us
Has a brain bailout
Meet
It is neat for a couple of reasons one
It has no wires
It is $230
And 3 It is Well designed and unlike the last doorbell switch
Cool looking squares this is
Something that quote
Looks like a doorbell
It does it looks like a doorbell there's lots of different options at least 8 to choose from to match your
Homes exterior
230 on the prices
Nest hello is why
And this has a remote
Thought I paid 204 - 2
You probably got it on a cool day
MSRP
Oh I could be
So I'm going to hold off
Being very excited about this until I can try it in the reason is because I actually have
The first gen and 2nd gen
August doorbell camera
The first gen was it
Nautica
I'll just be honest
Didn't have
You know at night
It had no
Lighting options
If your street was dark you were just out of luck you can see who is at your door
This kind of glitchy
I didn't love it
The next version fixed a lot of those
HD video resolution it's got night vision
Digital Zoom
It's got the remote chime
So yeah we're going to just see how it works
It also has a little bit of a limitation unless you want to pay five bucks a month
Does it how it has a
Video recording
Yeah so you can do a livestream at anytime if you want to see eclipse
Set a recording when it sees motion you can only see 5 seconds and they only hang around for the last 24 hours
If you want to pay
See
So actually I don't have a problem with the current setting I have
So prior to August
Sickness
Press on the
And I do pay $10 a month
Two nest for my Nest hello doorbell video
I had a nest cam in my front window
And an SD card
Yes
Cheap
We are cheap cheap
I am singing
Okay
Other than August video doorbell
I'll try it
When it comes out and let you guys know
Pretty much every doorbell out there
And have strong feelings about the
There's something else you want to try and I don't I guess I don't know why
Yeah I want the echo Auto I saw a story in wired about how Amazon
Did voice recognition and search for the noisy car environment
For the echo Auto
And I don't have my invite yet Amazon is
It's getting them out an invite only basis
Really want
And the reason is
I
Constantly want to ask
Not necessarily to do anything in my home
I'm just like
Hey what's that
What's that song and you like Stacy why don't you do that
Google Assistant
On your phone
The answer is
I can't get Google Assistant
My song because
It doesn't recognize
SYM
Now I understand
There She Goes she's talking to me but she will never ever answer my request because
I logged into the wrong account
And you guys maybe like Stacy or an idiot but I swear to you guys I have
I have spent
Trying to figure out
Reason is
My daughter wants to be able to she doesn't like to
Google she doesn't have her own
Spice so she wants to just be able
Able to ask Matt
I don't know if it's going to allow you to play liked songs from Spotify over your car stereo
But
That would be awesome if it did or if it just played them for me
There
That would also be a reason to why
Want that despite the fact
I have a Tesla
Ask it to play me all kinds of
I really just want to talk to one taken
Great. Now I get it it's fifty bucks for this
It's not expensive it's it you know you can plug it into USB or if you have an older car with a cigarette lighter 12 volt
You can connect it to your car speakers
So I suspect you can have
Play music if you
Tulsa design
Road noise
Other things so using the phone may not be the best
Smartwatch
Get information by voice
And we have a ton of
Questions I mean
When you get a twelve-year-old riding in the backseat or multiple 12 year olds
We have a lot of things we want to inquire about
Randomly on the road
Okay
What's the difference between a dairy cow and a beef cow
I don't know
Probably
Mattamy doesn't know either
Actually a new device gets
Support for that
System
Roku
Which I am super excited about
Because right now I have a Roku that's attached to a Harmony
Disattached all my TV stuff but this would have give me
A little bit more granularity in the
Control and
I kind of like that cuz right now the only remote controller I use now
When we're watching TV is the Roku
Because you'll be able to ask Madame a Define comedies or
Or open
Hulu apps on Roku changed
And
Now
Submitting content on the show
So we're going to have a broad discussion about
First off
We're going to start with
The Wirecutter
Last week
Put out after last show they put out a
Update on
Do you need a smart home hub
And
Which is the best way
Wirecutter was basically like
Most of you do not need
And I think they're right
Most of you probably
And if you do need one
They picked SmartThings which runs counter to what
I would do but I
For everyone else they're like you know what just use like an Amazon Echo or a goo
Google home
I will say
Did we have had push back
From some of our listeners who are like
Guys
You really should put people
Zigbee and Z-Wave devices because they're little bit more secure and you have a extra layer between the internet
In a device
And that is a good point
But I still think it's too,
I don't know what you think about the wire
They have to appeal to as many of broad set of readers as possible so I completely understand
Why they
Position the article this way and I don't
Disagree with that either
You and I are hubpeople
Like true how people not
Voice assistance
Concord as a hub
More automation that may not be easily done
Without
I get it I agree with you I'm not a SmartThings user these days I pretty much
Run everything on wink
I think it's
SmartThings does have some
Devices
And you can eat you know when I create custom device handlers
Gradle groovy you can do that
Great for people who need that
I don't think most people me that I don't think of wire cutters audience really needs that
So I get it
It depends what you want to do you just want to keep things simple
You can do that with just
Voice commands in memory
My devices
If you want to start expanding things
Get a broader range of devices
Sure
So that was The Wirecutter
Now as dedicated hub
As a warning sign
For you
Kevin has a
I'm a dummy story
Because I feel like a dummy in summer
Considering we when I say si switch
Hubs and devices so often for testing reasons
I'm going to get myself a little bit
Flog you today
Not today
Yes I wrote a story on the Block
Listen
Here is why you should always remove
What smart devices from the old one
And it sounds like common sense
But I'm going to tell you what happens if you don't do that because quite often
We got a hobbit a style just like unplug my wink
Who set up a new home
Put devices on it
Put everything back on wink real quick cuz
I got to get it back
Enough for the family
And that's exactly what I did when I tested the SmartThings
USB
Stick on the Nvidia Shield TV last year was infected
I tested it with some devices on it did my review
Took everything off and went back to wink
I never removed everything from that
Cub and what I found out
Was
I signed into my SmartThings app
Earlier this week
And I have a developer account over there because I had some custom device Handler
And I noticed
It's still listed
On Samsung server
But I had connected to that
SmartThings Hub
Wasn't a total panic at first but then I realized
Especially the Wi-Fi devices although I'm seeing I'll call a heartbeat pain coming from zigbee and Z-Wave
Which is very strange to me
Because they
Don't have
Access to the internet through the SmartThings Hub anymore
Connect to my wink hub
But we're going to break that process down into
But first off
Let's tell people
The process
Purchased basic
Hub removal
Suggestion
The first thing you should do to a new house Etc
Go to the app
Your current hub
And one by one delete
All your devices
It's especially important if you've got Z-Wave and zigbee devices
The Secret of Isis should
Wander off on their own when you delete them
Z-Wave devices you actually I know when the wink
You have to actually manually remove them by clicking
Edifice
So I go in the week to go to the hub
Section
Remove Z-Wave.
That's how you need to do it in the SmartThings app also has
Remove Z-Wave
Devices function
Where you're actually going to hit that button
And then you actually physically press the radio the Z-Wave there's always a button
Turns the radio into pairing
That's going to physically on
Reason you do that is because a Z-Wave and zigbee radio
Can only be paired to
Onehub
It just becomes really relevant
In a moment
Correct and even though I didn't have the SmartThings Hub running for the last year
I put the SmartThings
App back on my phone
This week
And I'm still able to use it to control some of these devices so I know these are actively talking to Samsung
And there's a lot of data there any devices that are no longer
Active
It shows the last state so you could see like the temperature in my home when
Mac addresses of devices IP address
No and this is something I'm thinking is
Manually delete your
Your account basically
Let's get into this weird
Question
That we have which is some of Kevin Z-Wave
Somehow getting
This data
And we for the life of us
Can I figure out how
Right because those devices cannot directly connect to the internet on their own
They need to go through
Wireless
Device
And it can only be
Sakura
Any event log I have all kinds of events
Look at the most recent events
And the only thing I can think of all the stuff
Some of those
Devices
Zigbee and Z-Wave
Art at
To my voice commands and also routines
I don't know how they would still have
Access to the
Internet to get back to Samsung servers but maybe
Something is triggering something
And I will continue researching obviously
This is our mystery of
The day
Or week
Maybe it's going to be a whole week's worth of Mystery
Guys who know so we'll update
On what's happening there
As we figure it out this is like our own iot podcast hotline
This is also good for people who like you Stacy are moving you need to
Undo everything and reset it all up and so on
If you switch a hub this is I think something that most people know they should do I don't know if everybody does it
I didn't
Shame on me for that but
Really makes you think
When you are doing some type of migration
Uninstall everything properly
Speaking up this whole thing was sparked by a question
Hey
Guys
I lost all the data on my Hub and I had to reset it
And
It took 7 hours
That sucks
He's like is there anyway
For us too
An answer to that is
Not really
Not really I mean that there might be some hubs that juice supported but the mainstream type hubs do not not with wings
SmartThings
Don't even with insteon
The safest bet like as I'm
Isn't dismantling my house
And taking things off
Beside his bed is actually to do a reset of
Everything so delete all the data
Cuz I'm having some weird issues because I didn't do that
But some of my
Lutron lights in my Amazon Echo
It's just not worth contact
And smart home devices I think a little more finicky than any other
Joyce's used today so
I think you're right
But speaking of the iot podcast hotline
I believe it is time to take a
Question
From
That particular hot
But before we do
I should tell you
That we
We have a winner our winner is
John
And
WeMo dimmer switch
So we're going to send that out to
To him so congratulations
If you would like to be in
To win in the March contest
Please give us a call at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
To 4
And
May answer your question but you will definitely
Be entered to win
Marches
Price which is
Ashley Gann
That's right it's the new
Wi-Fi
Lock from Schlage
Very excited
This week's iot podcast hotline sponsor
Is SLI
Shrek's wife
Lets you create a smartphone
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon and Apple products
Siri
Google Assistant
And more at schlage.com
/ iot
Okay so this week's question
Comes from Derek
Let's hear it
Hey Stacy Hey Kevin this is Derek coming from Gilroy started to leave you a message I'm not sure if it
Sager. Anyway you can use this on me
Section 8 regarding vehicle tracking
So you be have something out there and
Sprint offered something call the Sprint Drive and so
I guess I'm curious Are there any
Concerns that I may have you know I currently have
That's my primary provider so
Resume in addition to Google spent probably already knows where I'm at and what I'm doing anyway
But I'm getting wanting to get one of these for my
Teenage kids so I can see no, see where they're going Heather Drive in and give him some
Feedback
Just curious if you guys have any experience with the
Is there any privacy concerns and
Is there something that's even better out on the market
Okay Derek
At first I was like privacy and then I heard
Teenage driver and I was like
We don't need privacy we need to keep an eye on our teenage driver
And here you have a bunch of solutions
And you named a couple of them already
You could use a Tracker
Just to know where they are
But I don't like that because
Are teenage driver I actually do feel like
There's a lot of benefit for knowing how they're driving
So I'm going to suggest an OBD Port monitor
Device
And I'm actually going to suggest
You can actually do any number
Thursday
Two variations the cheaper ones usually connect via Wi-Fi or something
Over your phone so the data is not
Continuously sent to you
The more expensive ones that come with a subscription be like Verizon Tom or the Sprint one that you mentioned
Those are connected
Cellular and you can get real-time
Status updates
Where they are
How fast
How they are applying their brakes and all kind
Which is pretty useful for a new driver has I think
The Privacy aspect I think
Eric is writing at this point
The carriers and these are
Solutions you just mentioned
Which is why I bring this up
They already have so much information from the smartphones that we all have those of us have today so
Yeah you're giving him a little bit more
Hey how fast is this person going
How are they breaking
Where are they going
The flipside is
Based on
Set time of
Driving the captured data saver 30-60 days Etc
From
That device and you will get a discount
You headache
Relatively safe
Driving. So
Save your money again. You're giving up data to somebody else but
And that's up to you to decide if that's
Worth anything
Potential cost savings but
Turn on privacy standpoint it's just a teeny weeny bit more information than they probably already have
He and I
Keep an eye on this
The zoo
Or the automatic also doesn't integration with if
This is interesting be
Because you can actually use that data
Put their driving date or their location data into spreadsheets
And then you could apply that to like a map and see what
Like Bradley
What your team
Avatar
Or you could just get you
You can also set up like notify
Applications for
You can get an email when the car's engine is having
Or attacks
And that sort of thing might be really interesting to
I would say check out
Put automatic in zube because of those
Connections I'm sure you can set up that on Verizon's hum as well or the Sprint thing
But I think
It just has a
Richard
Bass option so Derek that is our advice for you
Good luck with your team driver
I'm not there yet but I'm really nervous about
All right
That concludes the news portion of this week's show stay tuned for a conversation with Krissy Meyer
Who is a partner at
Root Ventures
She also was a product manager at companies like square and apple and is going to talk about
How to build hardware for Consumer and Enterprise
Iot
As well as explained to us
Why the heck
Connected devices
Costume
And what you can do for your favorite companies to support them and give them a little extra margin
Woo
Before that
Let's hear from our sponsor this week sponsor is a pharaoh hey everyone we are taking a break from the in
Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor sponsor is a pharaoh and I have
CEO Joe Britt back on the show
With us in the next four episodes were going to cover a range of topics
Text with Joe
SoJO last time we talked we talked about Mitsubishi Bank combining iot
Banking before we get to that
Can you remind our listeners what a pharaoh.
Of course
And thank you Stacey it
Really good to be back
Can talking with you again
Cheryl provides
Everything that you need to connect
Anything to the internet
From helping you build a business case
All the way
To roll out
Ongoing management and data analytics
Our customers tell us that a pharaoh is the best choice for a great end-user experience and developer productivity
It's also beautiful design
Really easy to use
Very fast
And very very secure
Alright so let's talk about what's happening with the Pharaoh in Mitsubishi
This is the largest bank of Japan one of the largest in the world
And it has a pretty long hair
That's right
Mitsubishi ufj Financial Group
Dates back to the 1880s
It's actually the world's fifth-largest Bank by total assets
About 2.5 trillion dollars
This project with Mitsubishi ufg is really one of the killer wraps if I owed
Connected things of course deliver value
And in many occasions
That leads to a financial
Transaction fees things typically transaction
Person holding a mobile phone but down the line will also be able to transact
Directly with each other based on Smart contracts and things like that
We called it project the bank of things
Why is Mitsubishi bad
Creating this
Mitsubishi bank is creating the bank of things
To exponentially increase the surface area
Of
Devices
That can actually be paid for digitally
Most of these devices are things that fade into the background
Crown dinner so
Cost constraint or resource constraints
It doesn't make sense to attach a traditional
Expensive pain at terminal
To the actual device
But using a pharaoh
With a very inexpensive and simple but secure Bluetooth connect
Mitsubishi Bank
Can allow their customers
To make secure payments
Almost any kind of device at almost any price point
The idea is
You got things like parking meters
Vending machines why aren't all those things connected to the internet. All connected because it's really expensive
Either have to put a cellular radio in each one which would cost a lot
And then you have to provide some Wi-Fi connection nearby but with the affair a solution all you need is a really Annex
Expensive Bluetooth radio
And then we're able to set up a
Secure connection through the user smartphone
Back to the intern
And we use that secure Bluetooth connect
To the cloud
Command the device to do something after the payment has been processed
Apeiro. IOS
Go - big
Is always the best place to
Start if your developer
You can also check out
Developer.
Affero. IO and check out all the resources that we have on the Pharaoh. IO
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Chrissy Meyer
Partner
A true Adventures
And who is a product designer at a bunch of Hardware startups
Hi Chrissy how are you
I'm good baby thanks for having me
Super excited we're going to talk about crazy things you are building in your own we're going to talk about Venture Capital Trends in consumer
Versus Enterprise iot and if we're really lucky
Managing Supply chains
So much fun
Let's get started
Why don't you tell us a little bit about root Ventures and
Thrift Ventures is a venture capital firm
We are hard
Tech investor
Let me focus on
The seed stage the basically what that mean
Making investment really early and
Startup company
Who are solving
Very hard
Things like
Hardware
Iot
Robotics
Manufacturing and developer tools
I spent the past
Decade
Golang
Consumer electronics products
So at huge companies
Light
Apple and square
Skeleton mask
Volume
And then all the way to very early stage
Hardware startup
Kingdom Builder organizations
Heart of China inside factories and Empire
Suppliers mostly in Asia
Now I got to take everything that I learned over the
Horses that career and use it to help guide
Roots investment Visa
And also help advise all of the company that we in Bastion
Awesome so let's use that expertise and talk first off
About at route in
Specifically as a venture investor cuz that isn't that is a different mindset than someone who's an entrepreneur
Product designer with income
What are you looking for when you evaluate consumer iot
Hardware in Bessemer
So not many investors
Shaving
But I really
The Sounders that we're most excited
You are the one
To walk into our office with
1/2
Prototype rather than a
A super polish
Ed stock
So
We're looking for
Deeply technical founder
With a bold idea and
The experience
And who have the know-how
To be able to
It's funny that people
People showing me demos are often
Super apologetic that's their robot didn't work or that their software hit a bug or that there
Hearts were 3D printed and not injection-molded but
Honestly like as a technical investor
That's really what I wanted
I feel like I want to talk about the Chow
But they're having and I want to see the areas that are super high res can I want to hear about their planet
How they're going
To overcome those issues
Okay so guess if I bring you my
My disassembled prototype
I'm I'm already
Looking good
What are the pitfalls you see in the consumer iot
Around Hardware startup so once here's
You started on your journey
Maybe it's got something awesome
Where do you see companies or maybe Founders start to
Make the mistakes and it Hardware your mistakes
Can really cause a lot of problems you can't fix it quite as easily as soft
Definitely true
Enterprise's car and I don't want to downplay that at all
But building Hardware
Consumers is
Even harder
I feel like on the
Riverside
More than half the battle is
Figuring out who the
Hack is going to buy your products it's really not as straightforward as people often.
So once you have that figured out and you know
Who your target
Market is that you have to figure out distribution
So another words like how are you going to get your
Product to those customers that
It retail stores
Amazon
Direct online
My partnering with other businesses
Bundling it with
Products like those are all a
People fail to realize a lot about building
Consumer Hardware
Really difficult to make any money
The product
It's so before we get to kind of
Laying out all the
Costs associated with the connected device which I think
Trying to build one and people who are
Find one will appreciate
Let's go back to this idea of identifying your
Your Market because I do see a lot of people
Build things
Did seem to solve a particular problem for them which in some cases like Dropbox
Is awesome and in other cases like maybe
Juicero comes to Pint it feels like who that was so nice and
It cost so much
How do people find their target
It's not an easy thing it takes a lot of time it takes a lot of Blood Sweat and Tears in it and take a lot of getting out and
Walking to the
Customer
The number one
Better than Vice that I like to give the people if
To test early and test offense oh
I don't care if you had like 3D printed parts and I don't care if your prototype is
Is barely held together like
Cheap prototype
Even if you have something that you can
Has even a subset of the functionality
Get out there and get people using it because that is how you find
People and what does
And that's also how you
You find out
Who
It wasn't it was and who it doesn't run
Can respond your product-based
But the real challenge with it takes a lot of
Another get out
Those customers again and again and again and doing that as much on the
Brunch and a view
Possibly can because
Further
You get along
In
Product design
Further you get along in manufacturing it gets
Harder and harder to unwind wrong decision
It's hard to iterate when you've already produced a millionaire
10000 device
Okay so let's talk about cost
And
My favorite word
Bomb
Which stands for bill of materials
It's basically a fancy way of saying
How much it cost
Let's break that down because you shared a surprising stat with me about I have a cost to produce something of
Like a bill of materials for $100 then I actually have to sell this for likes
Yep
Unfortunate reality of shipping
Timber Hardware
People don't always fully under
Understand that
I can't build a device for $100 and sell it for $200 and make money
Not how it works
So there's so many things that you have to add in like so don't be teasing Freight charges and warranty
Using credit cards
To keep going
The reality of this
Situation is that if you
Build a hundred dollar device
$100
To assemble a $100 Bond, then
That might bring you up to like
$130 if I'm lucky
By the time I check on all
And then if you're selling through retail you have to turn around and go
Thanks to the retail store for every single product that
So
And that's just the difference
Wholesale in
Yeah and it's it's to the point that I will every retailer
Expect to take margin
To actually stop your products
Inventory and put it on their shelves so now this product that cost $100
To build
I just thought for $200
Just to break even
And then I have to sell it
$300 if I want to make
Any real margin or making it real money
So it's it's
The bends when you're building a
Product and you've got to remember that your
Average
Consumers
Pretty price-sensitive
After selling a product for $100
$300 might make Lee
Huge impact on their decision whether or not to buy it
Okay and this is why is consumers we see a lot of companies like launch their products sell only on their website and made
Maybe sell to Amazon how does
How does Amazon hire from
Putting something on a fist
Spell Shelf
Amazon also takes a fairly significant margin so they'll also take a pretty significant chunk off the top
But they're able to do so at a much
Encourage you
Physical retail stores that are carrying
Significant
Mentori
So if you really love a startup
You should buy for the
Absolutely they would love you
Before that
Okay so let's say we talked a bit about consumer let's talk about Enterprise how is investing in Enterprise
Fry's iot
Company is different and specifically the hardware
What are the differences
In
Selling Hardware to Enterprise
So on the Enterprise side
We are selling products
Companies you got to remember that
Sales cycle can be
Painfully painfully long
I can make a really long time
Close the contract
Really want him to get a purchase order approved
Five levels of the management change to get signatures from everyone
You might have to go through multiple rounds
Pilot
Before you get anywhere
Close to even
Clothing that that contract
At the end of the day if
Cast by episode
Same time like
You can sustain and you can
Grow a successful business by selling primarily in the Fortune 500 companies are bigger Enterprise customers
And on the Enterprise side when you're building hardware for them
Do you have to worry quite so much about
Things like always just the prettiest package is
Does this have that space age
White shiny Apple designer that
Fabric-covered I don't even know there's all kinds of design Trends happen
On the consumer side what do Enterprises look for when they buy
That's a really good point usually you don't
But sometimes you do it very dramatically based on who your customer is here selling to
The product is
And what it does
Interesting
Square for a while
And we were building the little credit card reader
We were not selling
Zoomers we were selling the business as they were small and medium-sized businesses
But it was still a business
Business
Play
It was
Has the piece of Hardware was going to be storefront for them when they were interacting
What's in there
It was very important
Have a level polish that you would expect in a in a consumer product so I think it really depends on
Depends on who you're selling it to and how it's going to be
Alright in Seoul
For any of these companies Enterprise
Consumer
Let's break down some of the challenges that you might have
In
Your supply chain in getting this sort of thing
Built and manufactured
You know a lot of this happens in Asia
All hear horror stories
We also hear horror stories about
Do I get in the US
So what kind of advice can you offer
People about physically
Manufacturing the device and then managing the
Supply chain
Go into it
Play I Like It
People that you can have
Product design in the world but if
You don't have a supply chain
Playoff you're never going to make it to Market with your product
I spend
A pretty significant check on my China advising new hardware companies were just starting to think about how to go about
Shutting up
Supply chain
And there's a few mistakes that I've seen people make and if it fits of advice that I like
Tell people outside and one is that your manufacturing partner
Has to be
Well mat
To your company Sage
And also to your
Product complexity
You have to look Beyond
Justice
Technical capabilities that they can check all the boxes on the technical side
Culture fit an attitude
Is super important
To that they're not willing to move it at speed that you're you
It's not going to be a good set
Asia isn't always the answer so people I see the people are
Consider the hardwood products made it to Asia but I don't think that's the right way to think about it I think that you need to be
Pushing really significant volumes for Asia to make sense and even then it
It doesn't always make
You shouldn't make that leap
To Manufacturing in Asia until you know
That you're really
Read me ready
The last
Mistake but I see it
People assuming that like bigger is better
That I want to work with the biggest
Factory Partners I can find because they have a big name in there will know and of course they're going to do a good job but
Being a small customer at a large
Talk to your
Supplier means that we run into
At 1
You're going to struggle to get resources
Then you're going to struggle to get attention
I've had that problem many times over any one time I was I was working with a start-up when we were partnered with us
Very well-known top-tier Factory I'm not going to name any names but
We have been given
Empathic
A+ players they were doing
An amazing job
Hijack and then
Again tired team
Disappeared
Overnight and was replaced by like
Newly-hired
Engineers and I mean like they're bad
Warm hunting
Literally people that they had hired
Like 2 to 3 days
Beforehand
And of course I freaked out
But it turned out that like my
Amazing
Like a big famous customer and since we were such as
Small startup working with this big fat
There really wasn't anything I
I can do about it and that is the key
Problem
That you can run into if you haven't been really dirty Jacob Frey and if you aren't well match
With your supply chain partners
Okay
And as a consumer I sit here and I am looking at all of this and probably the number one concern I have with
My Hardware devices is actually security and it's very similar in the Enterprise
What are you seeing I mean we hear a lot about like design with security in my
We hear a lot about like the bare minimum should be no hard go to passwords in
Encrypt everything
And we got a lot of new standards coming out UL is working on a standard arm just announce something on the
The device side I get lot of chatter about this so what are you advising your companies to do what are you
Thinking isn't
Security is
Q
Personally I'm glad to see that we're moving towards
More and more legislation around that but
First artist that I work with it's something that I like to stress
Need attention from
Day 1 like a cannot be an afterthought I mean it from the moment
That you start architecture
Your product
You should be thinking about data usage
Privacy
You should understand the concept of pii like personally identifiable information you should understand what it is
How you're going to have
Handle it and if you're building a
Consumer product you should
Probably this load what type of sensors are inside of it
When you think that you have all of your bases
When you think you're in a really good place
Don't shop there
And bring in an expert
Let them poke holes
And how you're handling
Ring security
How you're handling user data
Trust me like hiring
Security consultant
Now bikes
Expensive especially if you're in early
PlayStation startup but
If it prevents
Product returns or even worse if it prevents
A walk through door really bad headline
It's worth every
All right and we talked
How to briefly before the show about some of the cool things that you've done actually in your own home
And so since we have all these crazy
Consumers who
Do I know what I know you guys out there listening to a lot of fun stuff so
Tell me what's your favorite projects
They've done so far in your
Atrovent Rosier one of the earliest
Ambassadors Inn
Particle
Talk about article on your show before but
The great thing about
Particle is that as a
Iot development platform
They have they really nailed the integration
Cloud
Firmware
Hardware
Credibly easy-to-use
Way I would never
Seem to be
A software developer
But I've been able to get particles out
All over me
I think my
Everett project
Is that I use one to connect my
Fireplace
To the cloud
So
Now I can turn the fireplace on and off
With Madame and I never
Amazing
I have to ask
What is your command
Place I really wanted to
To get
It's pretty boy
Madam a
Tiger the fire
I feel like
Madame a it's getting hot in here
Excellent
All right
I think I might have to go update it now
Another one
To the land of my
Dog food container
Show that now I get notifications anytime
My husband feed the dogs because we were having problems where they were getting fed
Wy'east I it it was happening more often than we'd like to admit
Next time I should realize I want to go back in there
And add a
Notification
In the event that the dog
Don't get bad and we forget this but if you actually a little bit
I don't think it would be the worst thing in the world if they skipped a meal or two
So that your least favorite automation is what I meant
We had it so good
Okay
Chrissy thanks so much for coming on the show
For sharing all of your hard-won knowledge
Pretty Hardwood
Manufacturing Hardware my pleasure thanks so much baby that's it for this week thanks
So much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacy on
Coyote.com will see you next week