Hey everyone welcome to the 215 episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your house
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a
Stellar show for you today we're going to be talking about
Google IO
We're also going to be talking about Google killing its works with Nest program what that means war
Developers the industry and
You
The consumer
We're also going to be talking about Amazon's
New products
And how much is
Digital assistant
We like to refer to as Madam a
Nose
Will surprise
All right
And after that another Tech Conference
On the industrial side we have seen a lot of new announcer
Apple close at the show with a lot of little update such as
An update on Bluetooth and a legal decision that could change how your
Apartment
Everyone has asked us about how the wise
Sense
System works
And we have a review for you
Our Guest this week is going to be kylo all good she's be head of iot and Automotive at Erickson
She just took that role after having rolls it
Qualcomm NDG
She's kind of like this person who is followed the industrial iot everywhere
And it's a really good interview
So stay tuned for that
After a message
Our new sponsor
Dell
Dell Technologies
Before we get to the show let's hear from another one of our
Car sponsors
This week sponsor is Nordic semiconductor
Nordic semiconductor is the world's leading provider of ultra-low-power Wireless solution
I'm over 2 billion chips shipped to date and you're probably no more than a few meters away from
Nordic Technologies
It's inside everything from watches toys coffee makers keyboards and game controllers Plus
Medical monitors
Smart Home Products and wireless mics
Nordic ships at the brains and the boys behind all those everyday connected products you depend upon and love
How to use they deliver multi-protocol devices and have a strange supporting software and tools to build a maze
Amazing cutting-edge Wireless products with technology such as Bluetooth low energy
Red NB iot and lte-m
Your mission is to provide everything necessary for anyone to build an amazing secure connect Apple products the performance
Absolute Max of what is technologically possible
Nordic semiconductor
Helping you connect anything
Go to www. Nordic simmi.com to find out more about Nordic Center
Connector
Okay
Heaven
What a week
I already tired and we haven't even started
And it's not just because I'm traveling
I'll let everyone know that I'm recording this week from a hotel room
So any weirdness in the sound that is my fault
And
You can
Certain send me emails telling me all about how you don't like it
Or how you do like
Whichever
It won't change anything but you can send this
You can tell me how you
So let's talk about
Google IO
Cuz this week
We had two big Tech
Is Google IO and Microsoft bills
Both are really important in our space so we'll start with
Google because
So much yes there's so much
Yes I actually watched the live Keynote
Providing commentary on
Watching it
There was a ton obviously some of it does not apply to this particular show
But if you're not aware there are new pixel phones that are
Half the price of the current ones and still have all the
Good photo qualities etcetera
What's a fungi always
For our purposes there are at least three or four
Key aspects I just want to bring up
Today
And I want to emphasize how privacy and security was
Underline message
Google IO for the Keynote
And that's that's obviously important to our listeners
For all their connected devices
So in that regard
Google demonstrated and discussed
How they're doing
Natural language
Process
This is mainly taking place on the phone
Today
Google said they basically compressed like
A language down from the learning model rather from
100 GB
Down to
I have a gig which fits on a phone obviously
And what that does is it
Brinks privacy when you're speaking to devices that have on device NLP
Presume this will be coming to the
Approximately in the near future but it's for phones right now
Protect your privacy because the
Things you say don't go to the cloud it's all happening on device because
Already there
So that is important
Additionally Google is talking about their next
Generation
Assistant
Of course
In the home
People that Google Home Products that's very relevant
Discussion again was around on device processing
Also what they're doing with the assistant
Last year they had duplex were they
Yeah you can speak
Reservations
Which you can do that now
I took about a year
Blowout etcetera but it's here
In actually
Just a quick
I didn't realize this duplex like full duplex
Conversations basically mean a conversation where
Highest person can say something and then
Another person responds so it's a
Actual Back info
So I had no idea that's where the name Duke
Oh yeah I mean I thought about it from like modem
Yes I don't know why I didn't make that connection
That's okay
Back to the 80s
Anyway
So they're bringing duplex to the web
And they showed off how you can book a car
Next trip for example you're on a trip
Google on a trip because you probably have email saying that right
Yes Google knows where I'm staying at night how I'm getting there when I'm getting there
Yes
So what you could do in the demo anyway
Sho Nuff you could say hey G
Book a car with national for my next trip
Instead of going through all the steps in on the way International app
The assistant
Refills in all the information based on where you are when you're going to need a car
What car you might have enjoyed using last time etcetera because has that
So it can
Free fill everything in and can say okay I've got your car books
Do you want to pick up class
Chose this class last time
And literally make a reservation happen
4 Yuan
That's really cool to be even cooler if I can save book the cheapest car and it can go find
I would not surprise me if
I always want more Kevin
Also they should work on switch
However
Because again Google has this information
Later this summer you're going to see on Smart displays a new feature called pics
For you not
Pictures for you but pics
Such as suggestions of recipes events and podcasts
Which is fantastic because podcast Discovery is a
Huge cow
Yes why aren't more people listening to
I didn't go there but yes
All over the place
All right
We got gesture control
Gesture controls in the home and I wrote a post about this not that long ago
Isn't all that when it comes to the home
There are times you want to do things without waking somebody up or shouting to speaker
An amazing new
Google
Nest
Hubmax will talk about short languages
Their next smart display
It has a camera and that camera has
Face match
Meaning if you allow it to
Recognize faces you have to train it
When people sit in your house they will save their calendar information pop-up which is rather interesting
From a Jester standpoint when it's
Laying
Music or something like that maybe your phone rings you want to stop
You don't have to shout out hey
Instead you can just wave your hand or put a talk to the hand gesture out there
It will stop playing
Now I kind of wanted to do that automatically
With yonomi
Once I discovered my devices
Actually automatically whenever my phone would ring
It would stop on my Sonos
It was kind of cool but it did kind of
I had to take my daughter Sonos out
She got really mad when my phone
In her music interview
Greenwood stop
However
Pennisi privacy implication again
What Google is doing is it is switching
The learning models for language
And switching to the edge so what happens now or will happen
The learning model happened on your phone or your Google assistant device
And only the
Model itself
Will go back up to the cloud to make everyone's model better
So your date is going to stay local you won't be sending it to the cloud goes we sending
Model information
Excellent and going back to your own device natural language
This is something I wrote about unless
Swix newsletter I talked about
With something like this and a microphone
People could actually build voice control devices that aren't connected to
The cloud exactly now this will only work for Less sophisticated
Things like you're obviously not going to go
Here we go full duplex
With some of it isn't cloud-connected but
There are lots of things where you could actually
Have
Functioning NLP model Plus
Sense of
Commands available to the device
It would make a lot of sense.
So a washing machine
One of my favorites
Because
Little complicated you're like I've got a bunch of sweaters or jeans
If you could just tell it
I'm washing a load of jeans
It could actually pick the settings
For you
Yeah without the cloud
That seems like a really good use cases
Reducing
The intellectual load
For the person
And also enabling a computer
Voice control to make it
Easy to do something
Kind of help can I get the sense from Google IO that that's where they're heading with all of this which is wonderful because
Today everything has to be connected for a Google home
If you don't have
Internet connection
Google home as useless as our other products
Eczema products such as mathematics
You have to wonder though
Google's big revenue is it sad business
So where does an inn we don't need to answer this today
I don't think we're going to but
My overarching question
Google is going to be
I know that they're using data to build
Better products
Siddharth said
At some point in
Time if you're not advertising
Sing what are you do
And it makes sense everywhere and you don't have screens everywhere you do have to flip
So just keep that in my
Home Products are going to get better in one way
And yet they're going to get worse in another
So Google has killed
It's works with Nest program
Or rather it is killing it
After June 25th you'll be asked to migrate your
Nest accounts
It sounds like your Google Wi-Fi
Google
Home
Yes because it's kind of vicious
There's a lot of
Duplicity there
Duplicity that's lying
There's a lot of vacations there has been a long week
3200k
So you're basically
In some ways this makes sense
So what's happening
Is there killing their works with me
You will be asked to migrate Your Nest account
Your Google Wi-Fi account all of this into one
Google home
Google assist
And the reason they're doing this is because they're changing the way the nest device
Historically
Developers have been able to use apis to call for info
Information from Nest devices so like
I might have my hue light bulbs talk to Nest to say
Is Stacey home or away right now
And if I go away it will actually change my lighting
Because I'm away and it's nice that makes my house look more lived-in and secure even if I'm on vacation
So
That is going to change
No longer will devices be able to grab
Data
From Nest device
So if you are another Smart Home
Company
Or a service such as if
Etc
You will now have to go through Google home
To talk to Nest device
And you won't
Be able to get
Data from
So instead of
I look at it like
In the older
System all of my Nest devices in my Google devices they work together through
Formal integration that I did
My Nest devices
Other devices through formal integration
And basically every device had a brain
And many of them
What's going to happen is all of my Nest devices are basically losing their brain
Inability to
They're only going to talk to
And the implications of this are
If you have Nest devices those Integrations will break
As of the end of
August
And that means if you got
Thermostats at
Store
Are any of that all of that goes away
Some of them
Will be reinstated
But not all of them
Google actually
Had been
Very
Considered
About how it used its API so
It actually limited the API calls on Nest devices
Is it wouldn't actually give you video
Turn Nest devices to other
Video capable screams unless they were Google
So
Some of this week and moving toward
But there's a bunch of applications
Consumers
So let's talk about
What is
Every smart home now
Needs a hug that's the model we have clearly moved
So in Google's world it wants it to be the Google home
In Amazon's World it wants
To be madame
The funny thing is we
This is kind of reverse ending for the past I'd say year I've kind of been
Giving up on hubs
NSYNC
I want a hug
But I guess
Market dozen
Now the market soccer
Right
So this begs the question hey what happens to
Companies that have acted as like virtual hubs or physical Hub so like a SmartThings
Wink
You know me
Etcetera
I look at
Dislike
SmartThings will probably
Now go
Talk to Nest devices through the goo
I see that
It'll be an interesting test for WIC
To see how really on top of things they are
Because
This is going to be a development of
There's going to be a pool here that you have to make
And I don't know if link is going to do it
And then
With a company like you know me which is all virtual
Don't know how this is
I am very eager to talk to them
Send out some emails
End with ant if
It says that it will not hurt it at all
Rishi Chandra
Who is
Ahead of Hardware over at
Google
He actually spoke to a colleague of ours yonko
Add variety
And he basically said
This kills
Didn't basically
You said it will break
It
So that's
Not great news for EFT
When people who really rely on if they mean there's going to be a lot of upset people with they haven't heard this news already
Yes
So
You're like oh my gosh
I love my smartphone
What should I do
Well the scorched-earth protective gear
Google to the curb
But this is going to be happening
Everywhere because what's happening is
Your Hardware devices are providing valuable data
They're also providing that dated other places and it's become too hard for a cup
Company to control
So long with fist
Announcement Google is actually put out
Really good
Guidelines for
What sensors are in it
Devices
Hello sensors are used
And
How the data from the
Centers are you
That's not something it could do if it was actually sending this out 2/3
Parties
So in some ways this taking back up
Control benefits you as a
As a user
Better perspective
Understanding
Who has your data in
Now
As a consumer
Sort of hate
I get why it's at
I do hate the fact that now all my Nest devices are
That they're no longer like
I don't know if they're going to work in Google's going to do it
Man
Integration right Nest at 1
Will Google
No idea
So
That
Could be a problem
The other thing is
There are plenty of smart thermostat
Out there in the world there are plenty of sick
Security systems out there
It may be that
If you go all in on Google
You get to seamless
Apple like experience right
And a lot of people like
And they don't mind being that limited
So they will keep that
Imagine a lot of our listeners will
Probably steer closer to
Another device
Maybe it's the ecobee thermostat
That is really awesome
Maybe they do something with Honeywell
2 works with both Google and madam
End
Siri
So they're still options if
If you want to have fun
Multi-Device
Household
You're going to have to
To go independent and you're going to have to work a little harder
That's the downside of meanness make things more difficult in the decision-making and setup process
Planning process it's going back to a side load model
Wish app
Has pretty much a solid model
Now looks like Google's going that way in yet
They don't
Truly have like a multi radio
And one thing it was not announced was that next gen
Google WiFi product
All-in-one with a Mesh networking and potentially
As a hub that I've been talked about
Before
Mr. All That device is still in the works
So is there a Google home
True upcoming I don't know
Yeah me either
So
That's pretty much all we have time for but we'll we'll probably keep talking about this as more information comes out and where vendors are
And in a lot of it you're going to see in your home a lot of emails over the next few days telling you
This particular device is going to change his functionality
We didn't even get into like the idea of
How device functionality changes but will do that later
Okay before we get away from Google I O I just want to
7/32 invention that Google
Nest hubmax which is a new product
It's a 10 inch smart display very
It's identical to the smaller
What used to be called Google home hub
It's now called the
Nest hub
This has one more prone to tweeters for Better Sound it's got a camera
What you can turn off electronically not with a shutter
And
That camera can be used
Like a nest cam to monitor
The room around it
Got a security feature as well
The original
Google home hub
Yes
I should probably dig into the Google privacy
Palisades
Okay
Look for my newsletter it's going to be
Full of exciting
All right moving along
Not very far just to the next digital assistant over Madam a
Amazon's digital assistant
Do we calm anime because
Cuz we don't want to set everyone
Jeff Eller over at the Washington Post did a wonderful deep dive on his Madam a
Differences these are the things you say or every time that
Madam
Wakes up
And says yes
It starts recording so he went and listened to all of his recordings over the years of living with
And what he found is
A lot of
Totally normal
Interactions where he's like
Turn on the lights
Play the song
Set a timer
Videos about a lot of times where it was mistakenly activated and lots of fragments of conversations that
Should have never been recorded
Much less
Tencent up to the cloud for bras
So
People read this and he said he is actually dumping his
Amazon Echo and his Google.
He's like yeah I'm done
Not doing it
I know this is how she
And I went through and I actually on my Google device change the way
It works because you can go in on your Google devices
Pause the
Recordings
So it won't actually record your utterances when
You say something
Like a g
Now
That means it won't go
Get better so that is the trade-off your make
Getting there
However I was like yeah I'll make that
Straight up at school
There's not an option
Palazzo
I don't know what do you think Kevin I'm like should I
Don't matter to me
And I know this is happening
It's a very personal choice on it so I can't make a blanket statement telling people what to do
I think you have the right approach you have a good understanding of
What it says what it sends to the cloud
And you're making that choice you know between convenience and privacy
Don't use a madhumeh my house is outfitted with Google products
Cause
I just prefer those products in the way they work it has nothing to do with the privacy
So
I don't know I mean this is not something I mean I don't think anybody should be terribly surprised by this
4 years putting a microphone and or cameras in your house
Ways to privacy
Challenges and
Oh yeah
If that's the kind of environment you want to live in where you have the convenience
Of the features that these bring them
You're going to have to live with those privacy application
Right and as part of that or maybe it was
Was totally into
Over a taxi ozena freed who is
Excellent
Said or did an article on what Amazon knows about you
And it's pretty astonishing
I mean
It's not astonishing
You know if you
Oh yeah Amazon
Video
Or what how many books are read on my Kindle including for me my library books because I get
A lot of library books
Hand with key
Amazon go in nose
And it was
It was a pretty good overview some of the link to that so you can have
More educated decision
I didn't really talk about Amazon's credit cards
Chase Bank
I have one of those along with many other people in
Look at those quite a bit about that too
Nina also has Links at the bottom of that
With similar articles about what Google knows about you Facebook
Tesla Etc and they are also well worth the read
Alright here's some
Little Amazon product
Amazon has
Dependents man of a ring integration with person detection alerts
About time
Yeah so this is a new feature you can find in the settings for your ring camera just
Disabled person
Detection
And I assume it works similar to like the nest hello person detect
She better notification that tells you who's at your door or in the middle
I don't even have to open
I just need to know Kevin
Amazon is also a blink XT
T2 camera
Is a battery powered
Camera Amazon bought blink
2 years ago
Link head
Been a chip company that had a really cool image processing chip that
Was very low power
And
That didn't sell very well or didn't sell it high enough margins for them so they decided they were going to make a camera
And I sold the camera
And it's worked really well and Amazon bought it so they got a
A camera company but they also got a really cool
Silicon provider
As part of that
Background of Link
The blink
Xt2
Is an indoor outdoor battery-powered 1080
PhD video camera
Two-way audio
It's going to be 90 bucks with free cloud storage and no monthly fees
I will say
We got a lot of requests for a
Wireless
Outdoor cam
This
It does amazed at the battery life they claim
Two double a batteries
Would last up to 2 years of battery life
That is the medical power of optimized silicon
Yep
So I'm going to get one of these cuz
Why not
Wireless outdoor camera in $90
Is that why is kimchi
No but it's not crazy
Much less
Soho k
Moving on to the next big Tech
Compass Microsoft
Also happening this
And a lot of stuff on the industrial sites
Things We Should Know Windows 10 iot
They actually are making it a lot
Easier
To get your old
I don't include industrial but you're old
Stuff that's running older versions of Windows like Windows CE
Over to Windows iot
Windows 10
So that migration was really important
Because there's tons of old stuff out there
It is susceptible to all kinds of security flaws
We just need to tell
But you can't kill something that you spent $1000000 on it runs like some highly
Proprietary process
But now you can migrate it
Yay
Microsoft also announced
Rather it's AI in robotics
Cool kid
Any limited preview for Windows
So you can
And as your tools
Physical systems
Yay
Now basically this is the really embedded part of
The internet
Things in Microsoft
There's ways to get them running a modern secure operating system
That will conveniently
Tie back into a cloud
All right
Also at build twilio
Announced that they will have
Some of their iot SIM cards
Will Ty and very easily to Microsoft azure iot
SKB part of Microsoft iot plug-and-play connectivity effort in
Microsoft
Way way way back in the day when you actually connected your printer and keyboards and stuff to your computer they had a plug and play poker
So you didn't have to download driver
Microsoft Word with all these device manufacturers that they were like
Where can I build everything we need
So someone can just come in and plug in a printer to this machine
That's basically what they're doing with iot plug and play but they're working with manufacturers
Devices into the Azure cloud
So
Similar
Concept
Slightly different index
And so these are smart Sims
Run by twilio I think this is going to be a big deal for people who want to
Plugin brand
Two devices
So large scale
And deploy large
Yes
The other two things that are worth noting is
Microsoft also launched better conversational skills
Cortana
And again while
Google and Amazon are very focused
Smart home Microsoft
Very focused
Enterprise
It's doing a lot of the same thing
NLP on device
Thinking about privacy and basically trying to figure out how to deploy
Conversational based agents throughout offices
If you think about this this is a really great area for my
Microsoft understands that
Hey
You can't
Who does advances because it might be someone's like
Secure earnings
Who are other data
So Enterprises are very concerned about this
Sorts of things
So looking for Microsoft to do a lot of cool stuff there
We're seeing a
A couple of last year
I was at build and I saw a really
Awesome demo
We're basically this device in the middle of a table
R MTG
Tok notes
Flag action items
Concentra portal
Everyone who is a
The meeting this is the kind of
Technology that
Fairy Tail
So
Yay looking forward to that
And then there's one that everyone was talking about
On Twitter
Was a demonstration of recommendation engine
Interpolated drive-thrus
Starbucks
It was very cool
I'm not going to go into that because you know Microsoft just bought a compass
Neither does the same thing
I fully expect recommendations
Everywhere I am
Anyting
But
What's cool about the Starbucks demo
They're putting iot and all sorts of Starbucks gear
For the predictive maintenance and making sure everything's
Running
Well in the
Physical stores
But also they're using
Azure sphere to do it
Azure sphere Grew From
Microsoft Project sober
A couple years ago
This is Microsoft sway
Keurig iot
It involves a secured ship
That talks to the cloud and gets data from the cloud
Certified as being
What it's supposed to be
And all of the information passing between the devices
McLeod isn't
And
It's in the cloud
Checking for vulnerabilities as they
Come up and then
Letting
Updating the chip and letting the
Manufacturer
So this is kind of like an ongoing
Physical 2
To Cloud
Security solution
Microsoft just talked about for a while but I haven't actually seen anyone using
But now I have
And that's good because for a while
When they announced it a lot of people are very skeptical they're like
Yeah I don't think this is really
I know it is
Okay
Few other stories to get to
Bluetooth
The Bluetooth Sig
Special interest group
Has released a report will link to it in the show notes
Basically it's telling us that
There is a lot of blue
For example
There are now
Bluetooth Sig members
That is a
70%
Birth rate in Alaska
5 years
Witches
In 2018 there now 3.7
Billion Bluetooth devices shipped
A dumper they expect to grow
25.4 billion
By 22
That's per year
Well that's not cumulative that's amazing
Yeah
Okay so there's a lot of really good information in here like
Hey of those shipments how many are for audio streaming
Versus
Just straight up
Sensors and health and wellness in others
So we'll dig into that a little bit more
The newsletter
You can read the report
From the links in the show notes
Okay in the update to a story we talked about last week we talked about
Tenants in a New York apartment building
Suing their landlord who wanted to put latch
Deadlox
The building
In that case is now settled
So
The results of the settlement
NR that
Tenants
Get physical keys
If they want that they argued that their privacy issues
Play etcetera
The downside is this is a settlement
This isn't any sort of legal
Decision solution
President being set here really
Except for other
Kudzu in
Point of this settlement
I guess
But
This is bad news for latch
Or maybe it's bad news for landlords who want to cheap out and buy only electronic systems
Without physical keys because latch actually does
Offer a physical keys
And so in the settlement
The judge said that
Hey physical keys are a required service for landlords
So a smart entry system
It's not considered
A required service so at the landlord doesn't provide physical keys
The tenants could bring this to court
Again so
Keep that in mind you guys if you
You're getting a smart lock system in your apartment building and
You don't
Want to give up
Physical key
Yeah it's not just a privacy the people concern within one particular person in the
And the case is 93 years old
Says he's not capable of using a phone anytime self trapped in his home because the Smart Lock
Yep that's the sort of thing people love to read about
All right
Adele
It is time
For The Internet of Things podcast
Best hotline
This week's hotline is brought to you by Schlage Schlage wide variety of smart locks let you create a smart home
Of your dreams
You can learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions
Compatibility with Amazon and Apple products
Google Assistant
And more at Schlage
DACA
/ iot
We're not going to be playing a voicemail because we got
Several voicemails asking us about the wise
Since
System
And this is a kit
Sensors made by
But the wise camera
And I've been testing this in my
Actually for the last few weeks
And it's time for me to tell you what I say
First step
The wise since
Package
Is $20
You for that price get a bridge
You get
Open close sensors and one motion sensor
All of these
Work with a wise
The bridge plugs into the back of the wise
Cameras
So basically what you're looking at is for
4250 bucks
You get this like me
Security system
It is not monitored
So keep that in mind but it is a really convenient way
To set up
You should call it security maybe we should just call it information
I mean it's nice nice to know
When people are coming and going in my house so I set this up
In about 15 minutes
Plugged in
The camera I put the bridge and I said everything up but got a comprehensive
Review on this site
The bridge goes into the actual camera
It does so Kevin eat this is a bridge you would not mind
Exactly cuz it's not another box sitting somewhere on a table
And I put in my camera at the
Front door
My apartment
And I stuck the
Open close sensor on there and every time I set it up so every time that door opens it record the snippet of video
And
It works
I don't know how to say actually since I'm traveling
I've used it to check on my dog who spends all day by the front door waiting
I decided
I'm not going to lie it's really sad to watch
And I said
Another sensor I set it up on the back door and then I set up a motion sensor
At the back window
Because we got
Paint it it looks over the balcony that we have
Pick up painters on the balcony
A psychologist
Wanted to
I'll keep an eye on them
For that setup though I would need another camera where I guess I would do the pancam to go pay on where the motion was
I don't know if it actually does that
Cuz I don't have a pan
Nuts
Okay
It works I don't know how else to say it. Latency is incredibly low these are sensors that only work with wise there on a
Totally proprietary sub gigahertz frequency
They're small
I cannot emphasize to you guys house small
The sensors are
Bear less than an inch
It is
Crazy to me
Haven't worked with these like to install motion sensors
Also crazy is the price what you're getting for your 20s
Oh yeah
Granted you have to have a $20 wyzecam so case was for 40 bucks to really use it
But still
I get a camera
Motion sensor
To open close sensors
And have that kind of functionality for literally 40 bucks you have nothing to wise products now
That is crazy cheap cuz I just one motion sensor can easily cost you
20 bucks if not more
Oh yeah and
This is quality Care
I obviously have not been testing it for a year longer
So I can't tell you how the battery life
Going to work
I can tell you
It comes
The tape already on the back so you don't have
Mess with that
Having tested
Dozens
These sorts of devices over the last few
Sears this is easily
Up there in build
Lovely
The other thing that people who are privacy-focused my
Want to know about his wife lets you record everything to an SD card
On the camera
And yes
But you don't have to have the SD card if you do the event-based recording it will go to the cloud
So you need to know that
And
They use encryption on the device they have two-factor authentication which we love
Because
Two factors the way to go
End
Yeah
I did this just to play with it
It's also a great gift graduation is coming up here
Your kids are going to be moving the college are moving to
Apartments
Something like this is a really nice way to get them
Okay
So
The show has been crazy long
Going longer still
Please
Stay tuned for our guest
Kiva all good who is the brand new head of iot and Automotive at Erickson
We're going to be talking about
IG
We're also going to be talking about
Why the industrial internet-of-things has not
Got me adoption
It deserves
And a lot more
So stay tuned for her
And for a message from our sponsor
This week sponsor is Dell Technologies
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is
Dell Technologies and we are here with bask Iyer who is
And general manager for Edge and iot at Dell Technologies
Bascule bikini next week at iot world
And one of the big
Is how organizations
Can learn to be digital organization
Do you have any insights
To offer our audience on that
Yeah
Digital is not just technology it's about people process and Technology
And we found that in all this is the time to hire good talent
People who actually understand digital who actually understand real time
You know your business excetera you cannot just Outsource this
And we going to talk about process we going to steal a few things from
The world of software development and introduced the concept of the edge I'm not just for software development but the whole company
And then obviously technology as a big play
So it's not just technology but equal
So we talked about people across the same technology and culture the culture is a culture of innovation culture of doing
Something trying out and if it fails come back very quickly
Concert is going to be very important in this world of moving to digital as well
And I understand you're going to be bringing a case study
Along with you
Can you tell me more about that
Sure this is going to be exciting we going to bring an actual case study we going to
Showcase the city of Las Vegas how they're trying to improve the efficiency and safety and drive Innovation obviously
BM Arendelle Technologies and her partner
ATT
And how we create an ecosystem of large-scale iot and its solution
So Cal Technologies
Is working with a lot of companies in building ecosystems
So where does Dell Technologies and VMware play in that
When should folks call you
We actually believe that we want to encourage is ecosystem
You know we don't believe one player can dominate or should dominate this whole Space
Iot and Edge is very big it's going to benefit
All of human society worldwide
Strongly believe that didn't
Believer ecosystem
Please show that before BMX well-known
To promote multiple ecosystems multiple partners multiple storage vendors multiple Drive cloud
We call ourselves the multi-cloud multi-application Multi-Device company
So that's why the ecosystem is important and quite honestly the people we're going to be working in iot and Edge are people
People such as Honeywell Siemens MSI such as NDT Emerson
Tillotson and Allen Bradley and so on and so on and so on
Ecosystem for all it players all OT players
And all system integrators so we can provide what is Right Seneca
Excellent so where can we go
To learn more about Dell technology
Well you could come to the Dell Technologies, iot and we'll have a lot of information
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Kiva Allgood who is the head of iot and Automotive
Akita how are you
I'm great sweetie how are you
Excellent
It's all right so you recently
Joint efforts now so let's talk about
How you look at the iot
Yes all things iot and Automotive
So you know anything that's not a handset I'm super excited to be part of the air
Family and team and from my point of view iot is a slightly over
Word internet of things or industrial internet
The reality is it
The platform of the future
The way I look
So all the transformation that we've seen over the last 10 years
Connecting People via phone so you no longer attached
To the wall you can go anywhere globally and that really means everything
He says you think about
Transitioning from a analog world
To a digital world that's happening in your car
What's happening in Europe
Appliances
Happening
Industrial
Dance floor
That's happening
Turn thermostat elevators you think about anything we start to touch
It is being transformed by connectivity
And so
From my point of view
It's a it's a perfect place to be because they're going to be driving the
Forefront of that change
I agree with you actually I am very much that iot is a platform of light Broadband was kind of like the mobile
The internet was having everything be connected and having data streams from all of them is going to enable entirely new ecosystem
Systems services
Is it going to be
But
We're not there yet so
Let's talk about
You worked at Qualcomm which is on the chip side doing building that actual infrastructure u42 GE which is very applied
And now you're on the kind of networking site at Erickson so
Given that you have this
Wide-ranging view of what we need to make iot
T possible
Let's run through some of the big challenges
A lot of people talk about there being like a billion connected to
Devices switch feels like a lot but even if we want to get to you know
100 million
We're still dealing with some basic challenges of scale
Which ones
Are you thinking
In order for that Internet of Things
Become truly that
Format p
Can design develop
Tree ecosystem
Become the next millionaire off of we are going to need to strive for
Interoperability
And interoperability will drive
Scalability which
Without the combination of those two things
It's really difficult
Get to that prophet
I also think one of the key things that
Is bullying thing
Holding
Say it isn't technology
It's human behavior
So if you think about where we're starting to connect things it's on a plant floor
The factory already exists
There's in billions of dollars spent
How to build backpack
Now we're going to retrofit and
Connected wirelessly with 5G cuz you can
The latency and the
Performance is the same as if it was wired
Plus you get a whole bunch of other productivity cuz you could rework the the factory floor
In a day
But a plant manager is going to be resistant
Because they're so used
Kind of the way things are and the way the factories laid out today to tell them
They could reconfigure their floor in a day
They would be
No way because they're the ones
Responsible for the outfit
Plus there's a lot of
Systems and things designed in Ms
Example that industrial example
That would have to also be flat
You have to keep your OSHA ratings you have to have documentation how things work
How to keep your eyesight
Certification
Sport in the
Wireless space we were just replacing a phone on the wall and putting it in your pocket and then it became a soup
Computer
Standards bodies like
3gpp and others that were working collectively together
Bring those things to Market we have to start to see that in the internet
There's a lot of work being done and gone 3gp
AEP and other standards bodies but now they have to find their way into other forms and other places that people work
So that's like the National Association for water utilities Naruto or the electrical certification contortion
Since he's got all of these standards
And standards bodies that also have to be in school
Understand the value
That wireless connectivity can bring in the iot can bring
And I was this year at Hanover I'll tell your personal story
The 5G was at the Forefront
Insecure you've got this
Historic event
That's I've had the pleasure of being
An attendee at
Over probably the last six
Yours and connectivity with a component of it but it wasn't at
Forefront of the show and this year it really was
Searching for starting we're at the tip of that transition where the people's behavior and recognizing that
You can do it differently is going to start to change people's behavior
Start to change
Kisses but you have to get to interoperability to get to
The scalability
To get to profitability in the eye
To space and that means people are going to have to change the
The Technology's finally there it's available
So it's not a technical issue
At the people performance and positioning issue
In my opinion
Okay
I also agree with you on the standard size
End
I would say what is interesting about iot
And there are parallels is
That this is something that's going to be adopted unevenly across differ
Industries
In
We don't actually have bass technical standards yet
Which I think are really important
Forgetting things at the
Network layer to talk to each other
Standards around security
Babies in interoperability around certain types of devices
But I also think we're going to have them at the industry level and
I'm curious if you think the industry is going to adopt standards around iot faster than maybe they
They did around mobile or even
Broadband
I would hope so I mean I I think to your point if we do a double click this on battery life
To me that's not a
Technical issues forum
Can't be solved
And that's how I think about it's a matter of
A lot of times we don't understand the use
I'll give a good example of a water
Project in Australia where
Company was spending millions of dollars sending people out text out to measure Lakes
Because they had to for a commitment to build a building
And
In part because they felt like they
Couldn't use wireless for some reason even though it was actually
Fully covered
And it was because
The people who were tried to sell them a product it was sending a signal every 15 seconds
Will they only send a person out there once a month to measure the depth
The lake
So you could put in software that would say hey if they're like one above or below this
Then send a signal Center reports
And I took the battery life from basically a week
5 years
So I think
You have to really really really understand
How the technology is going to be
Applied
And then figure it out
I think there's been a lot of ice
I'd say false
Oh that will never work
Because people haven't taken the time to really understand the technical application
Are the use case
Required
Okay
And that gets to this idea of resilience
Which in the side of the world in the industrial World these are systems that are made to be
Resilient
They have backups they have
Five nines it's not uncommon
Even more nines is he better
When we get to the tech world
That's not always the case we are getting much better but you know it's only been a few years since you don't
Twitter
But go down all the time so I can't do this Facebook was just out a couple weeks ago
How do we bring the Innovation and the kind of flexibility associated with the tech world and build that way
With the resilience and redundancy needed by the
The industrial world
Match these two things
Together
Yeah that's a fantastic
And I think it's one that also
Causes people to shrivel up
Because they have those user experiences with a tech
World on a daily basis
And so also from security breach
So you brought
Security which is also could be a technical guy
To the point of is
Good enough
If someone can hack their way into a factory and shut it down for the day
Then again
The impact of that is more than someone losing their phone for
Today so I think
It goes in both.
And I think that's
Actually unique opportunity for
Is Ericsson
Strives for more than 5 9
I understand what it means to stand up a network
Working as we move into
Dirt space we're doing it with that
Framework
So I'd say
To date that hasn't
Surly been the case
Some other folks that they definitely that all will just stand up and that work
But they don't realize it
Really really difficult
Computer network
And redundant
And Performing all of the
And that's what's going to be required in order for us
Austin Moon
And really make the reality of iot
Happen in profit
And I think that now we're at a point where the network
Finally with 5G
Work will be able to provide that for these berries
Specific use case
And you'll start to see the products in the services stand up around though
Not everything's going to be in the cloud
I think you're going to see a lot more Edge compute
If you think about what does a Industrial
They're having those for today they have a computer usually
Sometimes they have internet access but not always
Cuz that's back NBA
It's red so I I'm confident you'll end up with
Services
It notable get married and they will both be resilient
Excellent
Okay
End
You keep bringing it up so let's talk about 5G
What industries do you see adopting 5G first will it be like
Consumers will it be factories with a
Cars
Obviously with our carrier partners
The faster that there is
Deploy Network
It's going to be a lower cost per gigabyte than the current 4G so there's a huge incentive there even for the consumer
Strongly believe that
It's going to be
A transition for the carrier partners and then for their customer So the faster we can drive that
Clicker that equals 2
System will continue involved after the carrier marketing consumers I do believe that it's going to be industrial and Autumn
For sure
Those are two use cases where
5G create
Competitive advantage
They're not as hot sensitive when you're
Turn off terabytes of data off
Vehicle
It has to be real time and it has to be reliable
5G is the best
Same thing for the end.
Lipstick into the industrial use case
This is because Factory floors are
Horrible environments for Nerf
I love the factory floor
There's one of my
They're horrible 4rf
If we're talking about deploying 5G in these situations especially with
At some of the higher frequency
Spectrum
How does that
Work what will that end up looking
And in one of the big games that the factory floor will get
From deploying
Basically five
Yeah again you get the low lately
You get the high throughput
High performance
It really doesn't able to the point where you can cut the cord
Angular my view and my vision is
Especially when you start to look at the
The transformation at the
Crying in a manufacturing environment
I hate they want this specialized 3D printed thing for themselves they want their Uggs
Was just smashed with that or they want their
Invisalign or plastic
If you're starting to get to an economy of one
Which means manufacturing now has
To be more specialized
If you could reconfigure the facts
Before and
Pull and Pay
And place different things based off of what was ordered every hour first
Every month that gives you a ton of flex
Now 5G if you're able to do that wirelessly at the same output
Same
Reliability and seams
Security as if you had everything connected
Then that's a huge that's a leapfrog that's a big step
We're at that point now
Partners like a TV and others were we've demonstrated the fact
That you can get that thing for
Performance where you haven't been able to
With others
And I know from my past
Experience that we use technologies that on paper that based on science
If you were to put this radio inside out
A windmill
You wouldn't have interference
But once you did and I'm the window started turning in the generator started
I'm annoyed that was actually created inside
Giant thing
It didn't work the Way You Are
You didn't get the
That reliable
I think now you're finally at
Point where the radio in the connectivity and a connection
Is going to be able to provide
The same type of
Experience
But you can sometimes better cuz you don't have to issue a rats or people tripping or something cutting
Did you actually get a ton more
Flexibility
As the current user nodejs
Yeah and I think the flexibility is a really interesting use cases I haven't thought about rats but sure rats also
When you have programmable
When you start seeing more AI on the factory
Floors
You can actually start moving your equipment around and reprogramming it
As it were in a way that
I don't think you could do with a wired system so I talked to a BB and
A couple other
Companies about that sort of thing in
It's pretty exciting
Titty transformational especially to if you start to think about yeah that's really pretty
Space that really gives you the flexibility long-term to to have multiple discs
Lines
Allows
La devise a ingenuity
Start to find its way into Factory
For which I think is
Frontier it's really going to be
The platform of the future it's just going to be redefined
Economy in a lot of other things coming
It's a lot more interesting
If you're trying to find people
To work at a factory
If it is more of a robot and it looks more like a phone
You're going to be able to hire them
Stokes and Trainor
It's a lot more effectively and efficient
So I have been talking with Ericsson
For probably the last five or six years by iot
The company has really been very forward-looking
In building out services in ecosystems
Json
I'm curious
Are we there yet
I feel like we started talking about it and things weren't real excited and then
Things had a plateau where people were doing pilot projects
Really happened
So
Do you see us
Accelerated with iot are we still kind of at this place where we're like a lot of talk and not a lot of action
Yeah I mean again I I've been here for
Coming up on a month
My focus is action
For sure so you know what I love to do is to take a company from
A couple hundred million to a billion
I have faith that the core capabilities are here the core products are here we're getting a lot of traction with the carrier Park
Partners and they're getting a lot of
Pull from industrial and Enterprise Partners on wanting to do things to
Differently sometimes it start
With a
He mentioned
Proof of concept that we're really he's got 32 Partners in the ecosystem around the industrial space
Had a ton of sick
Sauce with regard
To our connectivity manager
Product and our device management product
As well as our connectivity management product so we're scaling as quickly as he passed
I think now it's a matter of can we scale as quickly as the market would like us to and I think that's where I feel
Canker sore relief
What are those use cases where we can create the most value and where
Are those partners
And partners I think that's one key thing that the internet did so well is it allowed
Multiple player
To win to be successful
Now we're transitioning what I would say is a very traditional closed
Systems if you think about
Anna players and
Oil and gas
Or
Even manufacturing for they sold the hardware they sold to
The software and then they never let anybody else
Now
We actually have
I really think about that transition
And we have to find the right Partners that'll help us bring our products and
Solutions to Market as quickly as we pop
We're going to have to partner fast
So I think from that
Perspective
It's taking our core capabilities
Matching those up with the system integrators
And the players in the space under
Like I said mentioned ABB they know
Factory floors
We have a fax
Before but we don't live in a fact
We can connect all of the things that we need
The partners to help us
Let's get there and create that more open ecosystem that allows a lot of pee
How to be success
Certain product
After entity so
I'd say that's going to be a slightly different
Lens and I think we are there
Oh good cuz I've been waiting for these use cases
I have been waiting for years
Alright keep it thanks so much for coming on the show
You better thank you for taking the time and I appreciate it that's it for this week thanks so much for list
And remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week