Hey everyone welcome back to the internet
Podcast this is your house
Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have
Awesome show for the 201st episode of The Internet of Things podcast we're going to be talking about
Bluetooth snooze okay
Turn Services
Talking about a new smart lamp
From a mattress company because
When is got a smart
We've got
New
Light switches
Cameras in disguise
Big companies getting in
Home electricity
A new way to harvest
Energy
In Japan
People's devices for good
So we also have
Ken
Kolderup who is the VP of marketing at the Bluetooth Sig who is going to be talking in detail about what we can
Can expect from the
New Bluetooth specifications
And
He's going to explain what happened
With beacons for us
If we're going to hear from this week sponsor Farrakhan
So all of this
And more
Ready for you
A moment from another one of our sponsors
Guys this week we are
Bring it a new sponsor Western Digital
Western Digital creates environment
For data to thrive on your phone in your car
Throughout your home
Atrocities
Where data lives
Western Digital is there to drive the Innovation necessary for the
The best result
Today and tomorrow
New devices new system
New Solutions and world-class data infrastructure
All optimized
Tune to create the right conditions for data to realize its full potential
Learn more at data make
Is possible
Dot-com
That's database
Possible
Dot-com
Okay
Hey
Kevin
We won't go.
Too much into the Bluetooth news because we've got a deep dive
Some can holder upcoming
But
We should tell p
WhatsApp
So on Monday the 6th
I said that
They are announcing new location based services for Bluetooth
Basically this means that
Your Bluetooth low-energy radios
They will now be able
How to tell where they are
Within about a few cents
Which is pretty cool
It is and I'm glad Candice here because I wrote a post this week about what I think we could use this technology
Before some Curious to hear what he has to say about the new feature in general the features called direction finder
So with current Bluetooth Solutions like you may have like a Bluetooth
Tracking device like a tile or a Tracker or whatever you might have
And you can use the mobile app and it will track the signal of that
Tracking device
And kind of
Tell you how far away you are from an as you get closer you may find lost keys where's my bus
What I use a Bluetooth tracker for my house
Direction finding feature
Takes it to a whole nother level
And was going to rain
Potential possibilities such as indoor positioning asset tracking again like you said down to the centimeter
Level my thought isn't
Maybe I'm thinking too hard on this
This could be huge for the Smart Home
And I don't think it's more I'm going to see it right away I think it's going to be more than like acid
Tracking inventory type Solutions at first
But if it comes to the smart home think about this
You could have actual person alive
Presence detection with this to the centimeter level meaning if I have a phone with this technology or maybe
Maybe a device like a
Clip-on to myself or I put in my pocket for example my smart home
Actually tell
Where I am exactly Mouse and who I am because I would register that device
So now instead of like using a camera or motion sensor that says there's somebody in that room
You can say Hey Kevin is in his office
In this spot and when he's in the spot he likes this music playing in this light on this temperature and so on this could
Could bring a lot more context
To the smart home is at least that's what I'm hoping
You are right to help for that
It will
A little while now
The way youth
Suggested it could work
So one of the challenges with the
This new feature
Is that handset makers are going to have
Adapter
But the sense when the consumer side you're not going to see it on handsets
Until people get new Bluetooth
Tooth chips in there
Which means new handset
So that's a little ways
On the industrial side they're actually
Companies Rd
Using
Precursors
So that's happening already
Asset tracker
With your idea what you would have
Have to do is basically by
A whole.new
So you would have your dedicated thing
Your clip-on belt loop whatever thing
And then you would have to have
Some sort of Beacon infrastructure that's new around your home with the appropriate
Antennas
That could happen
And so
Will look for that
We'll see and
That was supposed to happen
Check with pekin
Again
You guys will enjoy the interview
Hugo's fairly deep on all of this stuff
Explains what happens with pekin
Hey
Speaking of beacons
Is a weird yusuke's but
I think it's weird
It doesn't feel like
What ways is using Bluetooth beacons in New York
Cities tunnels
And bridges
Where you might lose your
GPS signal
They're putting beacons
Every 40 meters
Roughly
So that's what 42 m per mile
That's 42 beacons for my Lotus
And at a cost of $28 and change
It's about $8,000 a mile to
Implement
And ideas you could be able
How to say hey when you're driving through there's a
Pekin inside a car driven
By subway
And
That would actually
To tell you how long it take
To Traverse that
Particular Bridge or tunnel
I get it
I just don't think this is the best
Radio
Stalogy for that but
Well it means there are few alternatives to good GPS
Signal and when you think about the tunnels that they have in New York City as well as the
Gwb the George Washington Bridge has
2 levels of fear on the underneath level you might lose GPS because you've got no
Stephen Stephen cars in top of Yuan
Top-level
I'm not sure what the alternative is other than say well just no signal I mean
You don't need it for directions
Companies probably want it for data such as the traffic
Information you how long is it taking to get across the gwb today at work through the Lincoln Tunnel
That's true and we don't have
Great vehicle to vehicle or vehicle-to-infrastructure coming
And so
We've been talking about for a few years with Wi-Fi and other
Things with the word 5gf
Fix it
Yeah it's magic
Oh yeah
Jionet
All right
That was sarcasm
For everyone who was not aware
Alright let's
Suck it up lighting
Because there's two crazy lighting Products
When is actually not cry
Crazy one is
A big surprise egg
Woke up with a surprise first
Casper the maker of
Beds
Yeah I order online and get the mattress sent to your house in a box and expand isn't and I fat
Yeah I mean I have a
Leesa mattress in our house
House so it's
It's not a Casper but
For Pioneer this
They're getting into the smart home space with a lamp
Is called the Casper glow
Is actually a pretty cool device
You know how I always help you
People I need the
Be smart this is actually pretty smart
It is designed to dim
In Brighton based
Saint
Your circadian
So different type of light in the morning verse
It is
Designer gradually dim at bedtime
I've actually had
It's that have been designed
So this is not
Tortellini
But it is kind of a pretty
In a neat form factor and it does not work
So it also has this ambient light sensor
Gives that
Apparently modifies the light
For the environment you're in
Yeah kind of gets rid of the blue light
Didn't miss a warm Hue based on the
Ambient light
So that way it's not messing with your sleep patterns
And the cool thing is
You turn it off by flipping it over
Which iPhone
That's a clever implementation because
Essenza behave like
Power charging
So yeah you just flip it over it still stays on Rico's off and it's not losing power that way
Yeah and then there's a bunch of other stuff now
The other cool thing is
Portable so you can bring it
Places obviously you have
Have to charge it
Normal use most of the time
You can bring the glow with you
You so they talk about you know
Going to bathroom
Getting a drink of water you can bring the lamp in Italy
Glow softly for you
Feels like summer
Need to see to believe
I have solar powered LED lamps
My house for the zombie apocalypse
So I keep one by the band KISS you have on YouTube
Stuff around the house
I can literally just looked it up on the basement lights up
It's not smart but it works
I doubt it last as long as Piccolo because you can
Havis
Beyond continuously for up to seven hours on battery
These clothes will not come
The single glow will cost $89 and
How to pack that sticks together will cost
100 +
$69
So Kevin are you in
I
Think not I can only sleep for 45 hours at a time anyway so I'll just stick with my connected bulbs in my bedroom
Okay
So
Sticking with lights and circadian rhythms a new startup
Has come out
Called Oro
And Oro is
Connected lights
That
There are so many
But
This one is a little bit unique
It actually reminds me of
FB stock
Lighting but those were bulbs
Years ago
Kind of had
Both AI motion
Sensors presents
Detection in the light bulb
And they would learn based on your habits
In the balls with dammit
Figure things out
It was magic
I tried them out they were
Pretty good they weren't as magic as I thought they'd be
They do get better over time
The Oro does all of this
In a light
So the switch
You replace it requires a neutral wire
It
It's on your wall that can
Check when someone's in the room that learns your habits over
Time in it
Basically Tunes the lighting
Two again your circadian rhythm so cooler light in the morning
While doing stuff
And then dimming and turning orange year
Or at night
Yeah what I like about this is the number of sensors in here because they're like switches with this motion detection
They're not whatever cost
Smart they just replace one type of switch with another
Logitech motion switch goes on
These have I can
For sensors in them so it detects motion but also sound proximity and the ambient light
To understand when somebody's in the room
So aside from the Smart Learning aspect of it
I think these would be better more effective than just a traditional motion sensor switch
Now
These are persons
I was going to say All Those sensors in this market, the price
They're 199
Persuade
And that is a single game
Ouch
It's expensive
So this is probably actually it's not that much more expensive than outfit in your house with something
Like the noon switch
And those if you guys were
Recall our switches that
Have pre-programmed lighting recipe
Already in them
Basically
Figure out what lights you have in you
Your house
And then cry
Create the recipe
Is based on that
Automatically
So again what we're seeing is more automation
More AI
That's what I'm
Curious about is it
When do you live with
How
The AI meets up
Because that's always the
The question will be
Start automating
Right it's one thing to say it
Can learn but how well does it learn
Because remember when everyone
You don't remember when this
Just came out never
And people still have issues
I mean mine have mostly
Subsided but part of that was just a learning curve
+
Yeah we'll see how that works with something is integral
That's something you notice right away when I
Yep
Okay in the creepy factor for the
We have Panasonic launching a
The home security camera that's
Part of a
Floor lamp
Be home Hawk
This isn't Kickstarter so this is
You know maybe if no one will find it but basically this is a
The lamp with a hidden
High definition
Security camera built-in
And
I don't love cameras in the home you guys already know this but
I think the Verge put a story out about this
This is an Airbnb nightmare
As someone who stayed in airbnb's in
And found cameras I'm like
Yeah
Now I'm going to
I have to have like CIA level bugged
Detection happen
Anyone I've dealt with today and I Airbnb you
Yeah but I mean it is integrated the cameras integrated into the lamp
It's not
Truly camouflage lyrics
Take a look at it you can see the camera sensor
Toronto
Major looking for it you'll see it
If you're not paying attention maybe somebody has it in their house and you're in the house
You might not notice sediment I wouldn't walk around and check her even Lambs
Decided to stay in that house but
It's not like
Totally
Yeah but it's not for me that's for sure either
And I should clarify it is on Indiegogo it is
Not
Kickstarter my badge
Sew in
I don't like this I don't like
You know
Yeah
One nice thing I will say it obviously plugged into a wall with making a traditional lamp and you don't
Need a smart bulb in there any like that but if the power goes out this can all run up there up to 90 minutes on 8 double a batteries
Sienna backup power source for your camouflage camera
You're never going to make me like this
Okay go to making a speaker you can talk to somebody from far away right from the lamp
Stop reading
Get your feet off my couch
I could see why homeowners want to do this but I'm also kind of like
Is the trade-off for the sharing economy is
Surveillance
Constantly
That's not
What were signed up for
Are there other countries to move to if you want that
Anyway alright so let's talk about
Let's talk about
Google in Amazon
Getting into
Electricity
4 Google this will actually be the second time around
They actually had a Smart Energy program so it Microsoft
Way back into
Mm
11 in mm
But this is a story from the Wall Street Journal.
Talking about
How the big players are looking at home automation
And all the data that's being
Sterilizing
Hey
We could be better energy
Better utilities
It's Marta me where was wonder what are companies doing with all of this
Smart home data
It's probably not good what song is this
During a solar eclipse in 2017 obviously every red solar panel
Wasn't generating any electricity which
Could affect the grid as well because
A lot of solar panels
Search to bring tide today
Feed energy in Lynnhaven overabundance of it and
Google apparently encouraged Nest owners to opt into a program that
Cool off devices
Second step in the summer time during the eclipse
Cluster homes around there before the power supply
Spell because we eclipse
And then during the eclipse
Set the thermostat to turn the temp up a few degrees so that the air conditioning is not running and apparently they had three
The million customers participating and they reduce the energy consumption by 700 megawatts which is
No small bit of power
Oh yeah and this makes sense
A demand response has been around for a while utilities have participated in base
Controlling people
You sign up
You control someone
Nest thermostat in UK
Saola
We got a lot of Demand right now let's
Turn everybody's thermostats up by a little
People can opt out
But
When you start having more
Connected devices
You can actually start making an impact
Weider squat
In there still going any the biggest energy consumption devices in the home are hbac so HVAC
Air conditioning inside
And water heater
And they're already
Utilities that are looking at Connected water heat
Insane
Hey
Maybe we can control that
After that we get into
Washers and dryers are
Ovens
Whirlpool I know his talked
Do utilities about this
But
It would be much easier
1 monolithic
Company who has X
Statistician
Do these types of things
As opposed to it like a Whirlpool making deals with
Utility providers there are across the US
But there's more than just
And there's a consumer benefit true this is almost time for giving up there to get you
Something back in return
A lot of
Regions have
Variable energy rates
Panthers
No I'm very high demand rates can Skyrocket so if you pre-cooled your hombres happel
You might be able to do so at the lower rate
And just kind of weather the storm where demand is high and therefore prices Ric mashup Payless
And still feel relatively the same Comfort level
That is the
Doesn't always happen as someone who has dealt with
Demand response but that is the goal
Okay
Speaking of energy use on a
Smaller-scale
A team of researchers out of MIT
Has developed a material that
Could lead to a break
Through in energy harvesting
And that is
Grabbing small bits of energy to power sensors or
Tiny
Battery powered device
Isis today
This is really important you guys
Why is the Internet of Things
We cannot be changed
Can batteries if we're going to have 50 billion
We have to have things that
Have energy harvesting
So
This particular research
Has basically created a two-dimensional material that
Striatum
That can convert radio signals from
Any sort of radio
Yosoo WiFi selfie
Phone or whatever
Into
Our
It's pretty cool cat
Yeah it's really cool I mean they call or two dimensional material
Because it's
Small 3 atoms tickets made of the film made of molybdenum disulfide
Pronounce that wrong but I can act as an antenna
But additionally it can Harvest energy from the ready ways that antenna is gathering as well so
You're not going to generate tons of electricity this way but for small devices small low-power devices may be aware of
Probably pushing but maybe
You could essentially maybe have no battery in it
And these are the effort to get
Power out of
RF signal
Is not new
This is actually something that's
Been happening for a long time you could actually even think of things like
Hey Wireless power is
Basically that
These sorts of
Things are being
Researched in
Lots of
Right now what's interesting is
Today we only have a
Couple energy
Pek energy harvesting
Technologies
They are
Pythiosis movement-based
Clicking
Changing things anything kinetic
Temperature differences can also generate power
And then solar
So like
Those are all probably more efficient
At this moment and they're not very efficient especially at small rages I mean solders pretty efficient but
You got a small device
You have a small solar panel on top of it
It will generate as much
But
We've got to get better
We got to do more
So it's really important to have the
Right and then she said this has been around for awhile in practice because
Anybody sees an RFID Card safe to enter a building for example
That has
An antenna in it
It has no power than a battery
But when it received a signal
It can get a little bit of juice just enough to
Basically say hey
Send a signal back or read the signal and and therefore unlock a door
For example so
We have a second ology but we're not using it in ways that we need to fry.
So
Let's go friend
Cool energy Harvest
Let's keep that up y'all
All the way to
Japan
Kevin
What are the Japanese do
What the Japanese
Government is going to hack into millions
Japanese citizens connected devices
But it's not a bad thing
It's actually being done to improve cyber-security so what they're doing and by that I mean Japan's National Institute of information
Animation and Communications
Technology Group
Is going to basically use default passwords and password dictionaries of basic passwords
A break until about 200 million devices
Liquor store with webcams and router so I don't have to actually
Move beyond that at the phones and other things but regardless
When they do that if they're successfully gaining access to a device
They're going to contact the owner of that device to advise them hey you might want to change your password
The finding out who owns what
Found them but I think this is a great program
Because
Too many people have the weak link is that password or maybe it's the router in the home and so on so this is a thing from
Good not for evil so this is one hack that I like
Okay and
Finally let's talk about Amazon making it easier to build
Skills for metal
Yep if your developer and making Amazon
Echo skills
You may be doing two things one building a scale but to worrying about all the backend stuff on the server to host
Stair and do processing and so on and so forth
Amazon actually has a beta program
Madame a hosted skills
And that is now available to all developers that was very limited
Can a private preview but it's open to everybody now and what this does is instead of
Worrying about the hosting for your AWS Lambda bits and all
Amazon washable just hosted for you and they have a free tier with access to AWS Lambda
5 gigs of storage and 15 gig of monthly data transfer
So you don't have to worry about
Setting up a server or setting up some instant somewhere else on the cloud that's not Amazon
Take all that away and that way you can just focus on
Skillet
And I have an update from last
So last week we talked about smart
Apartments
I assume you guys
We talked about a
Particular woman who was
She as a security researcher was not come
Pitbull with her partner
Ain't going
With automated door locks mostly but just an overall automate
We talked about why we thought
Hey this may not be the best implementation of this
Cuz she wasn't given a choice
Lesley Carhart
Who is the White House
Packer who did this
She actually wrote
Blog post about it
Talk about security things to consider when you're
Apartment goes
Smart and
She talks
Bit about
The situation
But she also brings up some really good points
I think or were
Sharing with
So she talks about when assessing the sort of thing
What is your threat mod
And for her
It's pretty high be
Because she is a professional hair
Packer of nation states and other
People end
If those kind of people
They might often becomes hard
So bad for her it's a big deal
For maybe
Kevin or I am I
Not be a big deal especially because we live in a single-family home
If someone were going to go to the trouble to want to break into our house we are door locks
It'd probably be better off just using
A screwdriver
Crowbar
Now in an apartment building
Because there's
The potential for someone to be able to open
A bunch of doors
Once that does change the threat
Model there even if your
So that was one point I thought
And then she also did a really deep dive I'm linked to this
Listen to
How you define
Smart Lock and how
Basically
Key box or taking care of Howell
PIN codes work
Etcetera
And it's actually a really good look
About how the locks work
Indifferent exploitation methods that have been used to break them in the
So did she say she's moving
She did not say that she
Okay and then she went into the issues associated with the Hub
We talked actually about
A lot of fees
To her credit she actually talks
About why a landlord might
Want some
And I do think that there are benefits
To Orlando
Lord and if done correctly
Everybody wins
That's the thing I don't think any
Either you me or her have an issue
With smart of finding an apartment it's the implementation that's being done in this
Particular case
So
I love this story I love the death and what she goes
You should probably check it out
And maybe a sass
How you feel about your old smartphone
Insecurities in the way
All right
Let's
I know that's
For someone like me
All kinds of craziness in my house
But I actually do
Consider every device I bring in and I talked
People about the security
So not this
Crazy pell-mell
Adoption of technology that makes sound
The shower
Okay
Now it is time
For our iot podcast hotline
Voicemail
So this week we have a new sponsor
For the hotline
Except
It's an existing sponsor that you guys are probably really familiar with
A pharaoh has taken over this month sponsorship of
The iot podcast
Ferromex platform that helps companies get their devices on the internet
Kenmore and dealing
Have both used a pharaoh
And as part of that they have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99%
Your support calls
Antenex higher Act
So
If you were in the market for an iot
Provider or someone to help you
Build your
Connected products
Go visit
A pharaoh
To learn more
That's
A fer
Dot IO
Okay
This week's color is
Monte who wants to find
Appropriate
Z-Wave hub
Let's hear from him
Kevin and Noah
If you're listening
This is Monty
Salt Lake
Just starting to do some smart
Trying to find a Best
Z-Wave
What's a github
Thank you
Okay mighty
I'm actually going to steer you away from a hub
If you are just beginning
I don't know if I would recommend
Bringing
Z-Wave into your house
And I think there are plenty of other options even in the sensor depart
I thought you could get away with
Just using Bluetooth
And Wi-Fi
And probably something like a Google home or a madam
Hate that idea
Kevin has some excellent Z-Wave Wrecking
Yep since Monty says he's kind of just getting started out I would say was keep it simple
And go with either a Samsung SmartThings Hub
Or a wink Hub because both of those would have
Bluetooth Wi-Fi
NZ wave
Do not too expensive the relatively easy to set up
If you want to get into a little more
Technical
Solution
Habitat woodwork
For you but again it's not for somebody just starting out and actually in the process of finishing up my review of The Hobbit
And even if somebody is
It's been playing with these things
For the better part of eight years
It's a bit of a
Learning curve on setting up and automating things
I should have come up with two other options
Tremonte if my teacher looking for
A Z-Wave Hub and you're also in the market
To add
Some smarts to a television set
You might want to think about the Nvidia
Shield TV box which is an Android TV box so you can stream all kinds of online things services
Pretty much anything and everything other than iTunes right now and what you can do is they sell a
SmartThings
USB dongle which turns it into a SmartThings Hub as well
It's two-for-one you're going to pay more obviously you're looking at probably about $170 for the Nvidia Shield TV
And then another 30 or 40 for the jungle but I just want to put that out there so last week if all you want is a Z-Wave
Play pop and I don't think that's what you want but just in case
Sbarro actually they make the Home Center to it doesn't have Wi-Fi it doesn't have Bluetooth but it does have Z-Wave so
It's a nice use case
It doesn't give you
Probably what you want in the future but it's something that considers well ideally that's just me
Relatively the easiest one to use
Has been Rock Solid for me
I will endorse
Wink
And SmartThings as a distant second
If you are
Willing to get into
Some kind of flake
You're really into DIYs
My things is the way
Again I would encourage you to look for Bluetooth and Wi-Fi so
Solutions you actually don't have to go Z-Wave anymore there are even Bluetooth
WiFi locks out there
There are plenty of light switches
Yeah it depends money on what you're trying to make smart
Take a look and see what options that device or devices have
If they're just Z-Wave okay you need your Z-Wave Hub but if there are options for Bluetooth or Wi-Fi for the same product
I consider those we talked about this quite a bit in the last few months
It seems like the industry is just simplifying and going with
Consolidated WiFi and Bluetooth
Solution in the smartphone these days
And if you decide that
I don't need Z-Wave but I really want to be
You could get the Amazon Echo Plus
Is a slightly easier
User experience
But that will work with every single zigbee
Their self
Just bare all that in mind
All right
If you guys have a question
And that you would like us
To answer
Please
Give us a call on the iot podcast hotline
At 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
Next week we will announce our January winner
Of the this is a Google home device
Use Google home device
As part of my
Spring cleaning
Oh my God I'm moving
I will be getting the winter of our February contest
A WeMo
So
It is used
But it is
Lovely candy
Even will have the boss
So if you want
Call us at 5 1/2
623 7
424 I do will be entered to win
Call before January 31st
Will be entered to win a
Google home
You call after that
You'll be entered to win
A WeMo switch
This is a Wi-Fi dimmer
It's lovely
All right that's it for the news portion of the show now
Stay tuned
For our guest
Ken kolderup
Who is VP of marketing at the Bluetooth
He'll be talking about Bluetooth new location
Auction Services
What happened to Beacon
+ 4
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Where is database provider Farrakhan
And we have Aldo
Who is here to talk to us about fear comes New sitri Edge
Database
Has developed
What about the cloud what role does it have fridge
Computing and how can a database
Are they called is absolutely critical for IRT looking for a complication there's no question about it
Especially because of the incredible amount of
Rasta pasta
See you in a little sister to eat at the club brings to the table
However some of the limitations
The cloud has they might be a problem price
Typical Cloud latency like hundreds of milliseconds are way too high if you're trying to
Control somehow they destroy multi million dollar equipment
Imagine that some critical sensors has been triggered and indicate an obstruction that made damage your machine that you have about 10
20 milliseconds
Stop the machine is going to be done with the cloud as part of the critical path
Has a much better alternative is to make sure you have all this data readily available on the edge
Write beside them
Machines or tricycle
So that's what I database really makes a difference
And how does that help in Edge application developer
Application your add application needs to be able to read the state as fact
Responsible with minimum layers in between application of the date itself
Making sure you guarantee that the state is also
Properly persisted is critical for a later on
Trinity mitigate root causes
And last but not least
Keeping the sequence of events like a typical transactional system
Will help you to understand the events that triggered
This place is all features of what
Provide and they're all covered by
Excellent so can you explain house
Sitri Edge helps
Customers to address all of these concerns
Sure design with this requirements in mind let's talk about throughput
Ultra-fast keto store
Facebook application
Just acquired it
With all typical extra leaders that the SQL database is usually introduced
Complex SQL relational queries are necessary Friday Saturday.
Example of using all the power of Iquitos for Engine 2
Sports Wheels
Another good point is the guarantee of
Persistence intrinsic
Did you add score engine is a full transactional database
Starting acid compliance
Relieving application from concerns like making sure that it is properly written to the Discord
Autosource can rely on database
Did you know for sure that they
Historical data
Fatty past events
Automatically to remote location like the cloud
It's not important feature that you can provide and do it for you without the need to develop
Application that does that
About last week
Situations highly secured with 256 AES encryption
Finally
Also provides multicollinearity microservices
That makes integration with your application much easier like providing an embedded
Sympathy broker as part of the solution
So where can our listeners find out more information
About Fair Combs
Sitri Edge database
What we just published a great video
Xiaomi
Simple running on a Raspberry Pi that collects data
Sensors in real time
Persistent data you can check it out in our website
It's available pets track home
Dot-com IV
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is
Ken kolderup
Who is VP of marketing at the Bluetooth
Hi Ken how are you doing
I am doing very well
Thank you for having me on the show
We are glad to have you
Because Bluetooth is
I'm going to go with
Pretty important
For The Internet of Things
And
There's a lot going on with Bluetooth about a year-and-a-half ago you launched
Bluetooth mesh
Which will cover I'm sure but this week you actually just launched
A new capability which is better location
Can you tell us a little bit about that
Yell the last couple years that you mentioned we've been introducing than the community really is the one who does all the work here
Adding up
Capabilities Bluetooth
To help out in
Either opening up new opportunities or trying to do a better job and some of the
Aries
She's already plays
Five longer range connection
Kaspersky connection
And so now the community actually just this next week is going to be adding a new capability called
Directions
What's fractions
At a very high level this is a new feature
That will enable one Bluetooth device to determine the direction
Another Bluetooth
Device
Aura lightning
I only belay
Bluetooth receiver to be able to determine the direction of a signal is coming from
So very simple concept
Direction of a Bluetooth
The reason
This is so important than Kathy applications of this is
The members really added this capability to help out in this hole
Location
Services
3-4 years
What's going on here is it today
Bluetooth location services everything from
He's going to consumer-level item finding products like those
Tiles and trackers is little personal asset tags
Your wallet or things like that so either those kind of more Simple consumer-level Solutions
Sophisticated enterprise-level real-time locating systems that are used
People looking kind of locations like hospitals
All of them
Simple
Building block with Bluetooth
Bluetooth devices
Really understand when they're in range of each other and then to use signal strength measurement
Between them so that little basic capabilities
Powering
This whole location services Market which is expected to go to
400 million
Unity
Couple of years
So basically this is the equivalent of standing in a crowded room and shouting here I am here I am and someone else
Beijing how far you are
I'm basically
Sounds like she's about
20 feet away
That's right so it's we use and Bluetooth using signal strength you how loud do I hear you two then estimate
How far away you are
But now imagine if my smartphone can only use
Signal
Francs to determine the distance to another device
So now that I have my smartphone couldn't tell me how far away it is
Point me in the right direction
Agreed so when were talking about Direction this means like I'm going north or south
The writer left her how does that work
The directions to go back to that analogy you yelling and be trying to hear you not only could I kind of
Justify how loud I hear
Or you can get to me how far away
Now I can actually determine which direction you are in
It's not north south east kind of direction or coordinate they can just
Understand
Where that signal is coming from
The boys out of your mouth
Understand where it is Miss Kay's Bluetooth
A Bluetooth receiver
Can understand
In which direction
A Bluetooth transmitter happens to be
360 around you wherever it might happen to be a
Okay and so if I'm a developer and I'm building an application
And I wants to take
Take advantage of this
How would I Implement that for the end
Consumer what does that mean
Oliver's building and then people who are with their building
But in this one
Is more consumer anyone
This one requires a handset guys
To add this capability
Things I need to do including
The addition of an antenna array inside the devices
So that may take some time but once that's done I would presume that the hazard vendor in
Coordination with their
Other suppliers
Within surface apis to the developer community that would be able to then yes the information
From the Bluetooth radios
In order to estimate determine signal Direction
And then that could be built into berries
Stations like this item finding one we talked about
So this is the application you expect to develop first or is this the other more
Consumer-friendly
A different one
Yeah anytime a new capability and it
Necessary for the handset vendors include
Yeah that takes time
Cycles that are involved
There is another
Kia Rio location services where I think we might start seeing Direction finding included
Sooner and that's in those more sophisticated Solutions I mentioned earlier those
Enterprise level real-time locating systems like asset tracking and things like that
They use that same basic building block we talked about earlier with two devices understanding range and signal strength measurements
Distance between
There are number of
Bluetooth locator devices that are deployed
Young six locations throughout
Building in those locators are
Constantly listening for
Your Bluetooth
Tags or tabs
Mobile
Are people with him
In a system is tracking allegations of
Ethos locators is also
Reporting back to a central server all the time
As well as
Signal strength
Distance from the locator to each of the tags attic
And using that data from all the locators
Calculator
Exactly the physical location of any tags
Three or more locators
And today using that kind of technique
We just talked about
These systems are able to
Determine the location of something with so-called meter level a
They can figure it out right here within kind of
12102 penny
Now he's locators can Donnelly report back
After the server the signal strength coming from the tags that also the directions
So not only do I hear it at a certain level
And by
Reporting back all that additional information to server can out romantically improve his
Accuracy of determining
Where something is going from
Meter level of Acura
Required for the deployment
Saudi systems
Where the hands is not
Necessarily
It just locators
Things like that that's what I think you'll start to see this direction finding feature
Brats first and that's there's actually you commercial
Bluetooth Bass
Systems today that are doing it they're just doing it with a free-standing implementation.
Direction finding capability
That's why I think you'll be coming
I think some of those folks maybe you upgrading their existing systems to now.
True standard
Got it so you said within centimeter accuracy
Pretty impressive and then also does have a sense of up-and-down so if I'm in a multi-story building
Can I find things
That way
Right now
If it's required and there are vendors out there they're doing
Deposition something in real time
Within 10 to 20 cm
So
The really really
And yeah the nice thing about this
Multiple locators all getting a signal
Elevation as well
Okay
So when should we start seeing it
You say soon
Now that the standard is out there when will we start seeing this an Enterprise application
And then when will we see it maybe in consumer
And yes the handset Cycles will matter
That's right
Certainly this year I think we'd expect
See some of those
Existing systems upgrade
Standard and potentially some of the others are in the space adding this capability
Consumer level applications that require
Yachts always hard for us to give guidance there that really is up to us a few players out there and we
These capabilities
Maybe this time next year
Sing some stuff come to Market
It looks talk about some of the news you guys
Disgust at CES
Which was profile
And you know if I can take folks back down memory lane
Bluetooth
Has been around for a long time
But historically it's been I say historically cuz I'm old
It was focused on audio and
Being able to transmit yunnan
Audio to EUR
Speaker to Bluetooth
Speaker audio to your headphones
And now we're really
Taking something
Deped
Pretty narrow focus in
And turning it into something that is
Really applicable
For everything from you.
Sensor readings
All the way up to location
Even things like old light bulbs
So
Talk to me about
Come to the journey that Bluetooth has made
In the concession
The shake is trying to
Tries to
Build out these use cases
Which is better
Usually buried
That's riding
And I mentioned earlier that you that's one thing it's always
Impress me about
Community as it doesn't stand still it's the community's continually adding
Can you keep abilities to address
Demarcus
Multiple levels I mean
If you go back far enough
Bluetooth
Classic Radio
Community added a whole new radio
And that wonderful opportunities and another cell
But not only the rails layer but even now that he look at more of the ways that the cookies enabled devices to
Tanisha you mentioned it was all about
A simple point-to-point connections of streaming audio between my handset and speaker
Expanded to broadcast
So allowing one device
Many around it that's what's power the whole
Bluetooth speaker
Talk about it many many use cases for using Bluetooth broadcast
And then
The community added yet another way with mesh Network
So allowing
Tens hundreds thousands
To all be able to communicate to each other in a many-to-many kind of
Apologies
Shirley reliably and with high performance be able to exchange messages
Get to really be a catalyst or an enabler for a lot of
Emerging-markets lifesmart almonds
Building
Will you have that need for
Many many devices
To be able to
Securely and reliably able
Eachother one another
One of the markets at this Mesh networking technology was targeted at is
And a lot of progress
That market has evolved a lot over the last
Gears
If I take a little bit
The back put into different
Connected home and then
Animation
The connected home is where
Lucas is being used to disconnect lots of things in the home
It's kind of stuff you looted to earlier TVs are connected
Soundbars gamebox
Controllers my smartphone is connect
How to test tools
Poise toothbrushes lots of things in the home and there's probably
Half a billion
Just as last year alone in
Marcus and then there's a more
The kind of full home automation
Areaware
Sophisticated Solutions being deployed
Control and automation
Home
Lighting heating cooling
Security
And things like that and that's the one that is
Almost a hundred billion units is last year in that area
But it's one that I decided to see a lot of Prague
We made
Couple of years we've seen
You lie for me it's been good to see the big Tech players
You're stepping in hearing
Providing tubs next order to some of the chaos
In this market for a while
The Google and Amazon domestically
Alibaba and xiaomi friends
China
Chinese companies are really coming in and then they have the wherewithal to really
Hold things together to create large enough ecosystems to attract
The developer community and to deliver truly
Italian experiences
And things like that
And we've been excited that
About that happening cuz I think it's going to represent the next Crow and we've had several these big ecosystems now make
Strategic
Decision to
Select Bluetooth and specifically Bluetooth match
Protocol for their overall
Smart Home
Strategy
The number of products
Little booties matter
6 months
If 6 month since we lost
Spectre re30 qualify products
After 12 months it was up to
After 18 months
It was just about a month ago there were over a hundred
Does growing really rapidly on this
Doubling up after every 6 months and based on everything I've seen
I think we should expect that
Continue for a while
Alright let's talk about the Enterprise and
Industrial use
I know that there are a variety of
Hub makers and companies from
Khasiyat
We're trying to
Help bring
Make Bluetooth
Is a little bit more
Accessible for Enterprises
How is that going and what are five of the things that those use case
Need that
Yeah it is just a couple of
Emerging markets for Bluetooth
Really big growth Opera
Enterprise or we just generally referred to as the smart building Market is absolutely
You're one of those
You're right now we're seeing really strong growth on a couple of fronts
Relates to the one we were talking about earlier in this whole area location
And services which has been
Your building very well for
Also Bluetooth
So
Large facilities in Enterprises
English shopping malls
Plano systems to
Facilitate visitors navigations routed Airport
Do the same so visitors
Find a way to Gabe's in the manatees routed
Location services
You're the other newer area and smart
Billy has really started with this whole laundromats networking
Want to go in the big bright spot
And
You know what we've been seeing is that
Humana commercial buildings
And I'm making this rapid shift from
Compact fluorescent lighting to LED lighting
At the same time they're doing that they're looking to move to wireless lighting feature
It provides lower-cost
Ability
Next level of sophistication to me
Regulatory requirements things like that
And that has been building
You're very well so you can seen a lot of lighting vendors
Especially over this last
80 months
That whole shift to Car Smart connected lighting
Seems to be a really really good growth area for us right now
Make Bluetooth with matches
Very well positioned
And as Bluetooth evolves I'd love to talk to you
About Beacon
Because they felt
So promising
And then they ended up being
So not from
Sing and yet a lot of the technology
These were talking about
In this conversation are things that we thought we'd do with pica
And now we're basically going to do it
With gateways and other devices
So can you kind of talk to me about
I guess what happened with beak
Then how that concept has adapt
2 maybe what we hope
Yeah sure I think the
If you take it back far enough this goes back to
What happens with many technology
This community added Bluetooth low energy again one of the things that got introduced with that was the ability to
Broadcast
We talked about the Bluetooth device canal
Messaging messages and any device around you can hear those
And you're the community's been very creative with ways to use and that's what led
If you go with your member a little bit of the progression apples and one that introduced the ivy can protocol
As a means
The kind of figure out how to
Let's use that capability to
Support
Point of Interest information Deacons
Are using broadcast apology to serve
Variety different
Opportunities
A lot of interesting ways to use Bluetooth broadcast one is as a
June support these Point address information
A lot of
Museums putting these deacons on exhibit
Allow visitors to get more information
Retail environments
Deplane Deacon's on various products and end aisle displays and so4 2
Facilitator
Experience
Bluetooth broadcast capability Servicing
But that broadcast capability Bluetooth for many many different
Thanks so it's actually the fundamental technology behind
So the network are actually using
Broadcast
Telecommunications is a way for them to communicate to each other
Oh I just answering your question yes it is
And this is partly I mean this is as you point out this is technology adapting
This is basically like
Where can I put a capability out there
See how people react to it
What they do with it
So this
This makes sense
Add onto that
You're in another area code so friends
Solutions that use Bluetooth they can choose any different way to communicate
Gateway
They can use a broadcast
Communication is kind of Beacon communication to communicate information
Go back to a gateway
So that's one of the things this developers really like about Bluetooth is this
Flexibility
Not just one way to communicate
Communicate
What connection I can do Dover broadcast connection
Flexible platform
Is the right approach for them
Alright thank you so much again for coming on the show this week
Of course thank you for having me
That's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week