Hey everyone welcome to the 205th episode
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
Kevin tofel
We have a stellar show for you today
Live Industrial in Enterprise news
Is a big deal this week
On its PSA security platform
And programs at work
Talk about
Kevin has a story for the smart home all about gestures
It actually ties into Microsoft newconnect
Camera
For business
Free to talk about
Using a matinee in the Amazon Echo in hospitals
We got some new chips out
Matter of a capabilities
Discuss
And
We asked the question who should enforce
Federal Privacy Law
If we get one
Then we're going to run down some industrial iot news from both embedded world and Mobile World Congress that have
This week
Plus
Our Guest this week is Beth Carlin who is the CEO and founder of this sea change
Institute
We're going to be talking about how utilities are
Looking at the Smart Home
I'm going to
Control
Energy consumption
And we'll hear from our sponsor urbanex in
And what are their startups in the construction space so
All of this is
Coming at you in just a moment
Let's hear from another one of our sponsors
Western Digital Western Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to solve is bigger
Is challenges introducing their most advanced flash storage solution
It is built it power 5G mobile devices
You can play more games save more memories and binge
More videos so get ready for your 5G future at Western Digital.
Onan Kevin we are going to be talking about 5T later on the show
Woohoo
Jennifer topic
So get your jargon hat
The first
Let's talk about arm
Teechip licensing
Capri that is basically the heart of a
Every smartphone out there
Has a really big vision
OT
The chairman of SoftBank
Has his vision of a trillion connected devices by
And I don't know if we're going to get there
If we do we're going to have to improve security
Holier than
Catholic Church
Church
What arm is doing
Is
Usher at
Attack on the announcing they called the
The PSA
And that is their security platform
What the channel is created a certification program
For it and apis make it easy for non semiconductor Engineers to enable the security
Elements
So
If you want something that security at the device level
You have to have
Some sort of
Hardware isolation
Hardware-based root of trust
And
A place for life
Cryptography and Key Management
And if all those words meant nothing to you
Basically imaginative
A little separate room on a chip
It allows you to put all your secrets in there
And you
Can understand if someone's actually tried
Guided access
It's also
A place that can generate
Typography
So generate
Code for more secrets
It will boot up on its own without talking to anything else in the chips with the rest of the chip is infected
This area
There's more to what they've done I are going to
Talk about it
Remind me
Is partially out of something I said
Couple months ago
Everyone has a trusted platform module
And that
Chip basically verifies that the firmware on the device in this case a Chromebook
Has not been tampered with
This does more than that
But it is very similar
Yes so
This is design
Anythink
And
Tiny tiny MCE use big smartphone platforms
All of the above
This sort of
Little secret room on a chip
Has been around for awhile to calm trusted execution environments or trusted
Execution modules tm30 he's chipmakers have been putting them on their silicon
While
The challenge has been
If you don't know how to engineer
Silicon
If you're just like this normal person who's but you don't have the budget to hire like a hundred really smart people
Develop your bored
What happens as you don't actually usually enable
Secure element so it's their butt
You don't actually have
It really doesn't have any security if you don't use it
Yes
I got this awesome room in my house if we never go into it
So what they've done is they've added apis that make it really easy for you to like
Open up the door to that room and start playing
With those tools in a way that is familiar
And now it's actually leverage some of the stuff I can learning in my Java class
So there's encapsulated all of this functionality
And the data
Accessible
Harbin manufacturer arrest actually add software to the product to make it work
Can mess around with us they have access to it to use it and beef up security
But in a
Controlled way
So this is good
And even better is
They basically set different levels
A certification
At level 1 you can most basic security
Level two
Little fancy rat takes about a month to get your level 2 certification
We don't even know what it is yet it's super super fancy and
It's going to take a while nobody has that yet but
Cypress microchip Nordic nxp
St micro silicon labs
Taiwanese company called new vote on all of those guys are implemented
Best so
Most of them will have level 1 certified chips out on the market
They're going to beat that up as time goes on
It also this whole platform that arm is introduced with
PSA
Is also
Ties into other security efforts likes UL has their own security
This fits in with
So
What we're seeing is both
The ability to standardize some basic good security practices for
Hardware level
Cross a bunch of different standards organizations which should help
Pool industry
And they're making it easier for application developer
Actually
So this is a big deal
Really promise
I'm very excited
It is it's very good we heart on security for iot devices all the time for good reason
There is a downside
And that is
Tell me the towns
None of the devices you have or capable of this today
So you're going to have to buy a new devices it
You want this type of security
And you do you want this type of security
Alright well
After Kevin has Rain on My Parade with
To let him get you all excited about something
Fresh poke and
At Mobile World Congress lots of news about gesture
Based phones
And Automotive
Even
Camera for Enterprise
Rochester
I do talk about gestures and yes this is listen to that funky loopy space that I often find myself in as unforward
You would mention some of the announcements it
Mwc the sweet BMW for example with showing off their natural interaction
Platform which is expected in 2021
It uses voice capabilities as most new cars do today either
Natively or through a f****** cuz I see you can answer the car
They're going to add gesture controls as well and I love that because
I'm driving I-90 to say change the radio
Station of do something
Take me to look away
That's bad
So which gestures you can
Potentially at your radio and maybe flip your finger up and we go to the next
Channel for example so that is cool
It also adding smarts to it will see if they deliver on this but
You'll be able to actually
Point at things that you're driving past
System recognize your gestures
Winter
To that thing the cars have cameras and other sensors
GPS as well
Anyconnect tell you about the place
Additionally
Images phones and LG
Announce their G8
Thank you
That's their new flagship phone
And they have a time of flight sensor in there and they're not the first to do this but
They are the latest to do this and what that allows them to do is
Touchless gestures to the phone interface
It can even skam
Home of user a few inches away
Unlock the phone so
Wishing all these new applications for these type of sensor
Camera Caesar more of
The Jetsons
Exactly
It's basically like
Radar
Plus math
So get a time of flight sensory there they're sending out
The signal
It bounces back
They do math to see how it fits within the map Thief
Created of the road
It's a very cool things the same technology that was actually the lighthouse cameras
We talked about a while back
Heather CEO
Podcast talking about the sensors
Unfortunately lighthouses now
Business but the fact that these are going to be in smartphones and possibly in cars
These are things that sell
A lot of devices which means the cost of this technology in the number of people who can develop against it will expand
Which makes it more accessible
When other use cases so that's
Harry Potter
And that's where it would be interesting to see in the home because today
Is home control is done through voice and make sure there's apps as well that
Why are we buying all these
Smart speakers oleana
Control things with our voice
Once you start having lower-cost sensors
Do other things such as determine or read gestures and interpret them
That was a whole new level of
Interaction
Pizza possibilities
For it so with a lower cost of these sensors
Wouldn't be surprised if we start seeing
Quieter Smart Home
Where you could
Maybe somebody sleeping next to you is your
Reading a book
You want to turn the heat up
Thermostat
And then maybe a gesture to raise the Heat or lower it whatever
If there's a world of possibilities here so it's kind of interesting and an early precursor to all this with the Xbox
Connect
Which had a duct sensor is an IR sensor in an RGB camera
You actually work it just
The application for with gaming obviously but
To do my Disco
And I could not figure out
Easy way to like
Establish that gesture
Connect it to my
Smart home stuff so
PartyLite the Hue Lights would go on for Disco Night
Yeah
Make the connection
Into there is not and never will be a disco night at my house
But Microsoft is bringing the Kinect back
This ties back to something I saw last year
If they were seated
Start a ticket was crazy so I'm
I'm curious
Like how that's going to be
I'd like to follow that and see how successful it is because that condemned translate into what we might see in the home
And I'll just leave
Everybody hanging with one last thought because it
It's not just about jesters
And control
It's also about adding more smarts and context through the home
Yes cuz otherwise you're going to get
Crazy false positive
Like I can't believe it something
Assume
My dog
I know I'm weird
I wave to people in my house I wave to people on Skype
I can vouch for that
There's going to be some development
It needs to take
Never Say Never
Right
Let's see what are we
We have
Madam
This is a really interesting article I read over at Gizmodo there's about a hundred patient rooms
At Cedars-Sinai Hospital
They're equipped with Madame a echo devices
There's a Madam a Power Platform of the hospital called Ava
And this allows
Patience to say matinee change the channel
Matinee tell the nurse I need
To use the bathroom
So
It's an easier way for patients to communicate either with the nurses or directly with
Items in their room
And I just never thought of it that way
Matinee in hospital room
Concerns that
What are the questions is how do you bring voice
Everywhere
And still follow the rules of particular
In hospitals you can have to pick about HIPAA I have to think about a device that is
Either protected from germs
Weird stuff that happens
Hospitals
In an Enterprise you're going to have to take
Victaulic Edmonton
Information rights
Access
If that's all figured out and I don't know that it is or isn't my scene like terms of service or anything here
It really opens up additional possibilities in fact there are already using some of them
Sofa
Patient says I need
Painkillers example
Said that to their Echo
A nurse would actually get that request
If
It's some other requests perhaps especially
Coming to a checkup
Southern
That also provides
The cloud with some
Personal
Patient information
Well speaking of which this is how we refer to
Amazon's digital assistant
So it's not to set off
Yours there are two chip announcement
It's worth mentioning
Nxp is come out with a microcontroller that has
ABS which is
Is madam a voice services
And this is really
Meet
This is
Basically
I didn't see you as fairy
Low-power very dumb
Kind of devices inside a list sensors
For a while
Microwave
Washing machines have MCU
Hardcore embedded chips
What's interesting here
Capabilities
Makeup on
MCU
Which
Well that means
How to make glitter everywhere
It's a little disconcerting
So a little obviously a little chip microcontroller
Centimeter Square
Yeah
Impressive
The internet
The connection back to the
Giant brain
The other
Haven't found this in Sin City
Tyson
We talked about
Qualcomm is doing a reference design
Amazon
Chip with
CVS
Voice services
Isn't that funny because I think somebody wrote an article about
Disa
Smart speakers really should be integrated use as mesh
Points
Qualcomm has it smart audio development kit for Amazon AVS
It's
Far more than that microcontroller we just talked about this is an actual
CPU that might be used inside Halo and smartphone insulin
Seems to be the Snapdragon 410 series
Based on the information at Qualcomm has provided in what ways, to do so
It's got everything I can drive up to 720p on display
It has obviously has Wi-Fi 8 or 2:11 AC
It has Bluetooth it has
The kitchen sink
It's all in there
Can playback high definition audio music do you have a GPU
Quick Charge support which is interesting enough that will ever be used
Terminado de Wi-Fi
Exactly exactly but I mean this could lead to what I was thinking a natural all in one
Smart speaker /
Access points we can start reducing the number of things that we have to plug in and connect to her house
Could be something like a
But it wouldn't be that because this is
Echo Show
720 which is in
Awesome but you know a small
Echo spot
So something like that
Teal screen
Wi-Fi access point
Judicial assistant
Lots of news out of
Congress will talk a little bit more about some other bits
But ask
A question
He asked question which is who should enforce a federal Privacy Law
Us
And the idea here is if the US gets a gdpr
Privacy
What agency
Wood and
I had assumed it would be the f
HTC button
Much like the FTC doesn't actually have
Penalties against
And that's kind of something
Make it hurt
GPR charges up to 4%
That's crazy
So the FCC does want this job they have done some privacy
Cases usually
Not as effectively there's some
Weird Regular Show
Blocks in place for
But
They do have some experience
The other option would be State Attorneys General
And we see that a lot the downside to something like that is if you don't get
California or New York basic
Estate attorneys
So
You'll have to have
Stateline
If North Dakota does this I can see someone being like you
Need to sell in North Dakota
Sorry
That's something to think about
I tend to hate the idea of creating a whole new agency
We have so many agencies already
The Privacy folks are actually
Kind of excited about that
I think new agencies maybe have
Few years of Effectiveness before there
They're suffering from regulatory capture something
Impro FTC
Yeah but
They have to change the ftc's
Scope of power nuts could lead to other issues
I hate to say it but a new agency
For this and related things may be a good thing because
All these agencies are created well before
Internet little on the edge of IRT
I hate to say it but
Maybe the best thing
Agencies
That is a fight that
What happened in Washington
If we ever get Federal
Cell
In the meantime
Let's go to California in
And their law that should go to
All right
Let's talk
We'll start with new world
Yeah we've talked before.
Google Cloud iot
Which is Google's platform to
Manage devices they now have
A cloud iot device SDK
And that will allow
Product makers and developers to connect
Embedded iot devices to the Google Cloud iot Core so that
Makes things easier
If you want
Yes
If you want to use Google platform
They don't mention a specific
MC use they're saying a wide array
Will be able to use them across various real-time operating systems such as
Arm mbed OS free are pots and mortar
So
They're looking at ways to make it easier for the really small chips to get connected to their
Iot platform
That's good I mean Microsoft
Catching up again
Alright Wind River
Which they've been in the bed of software forever
Until
Didn't I was like nevermind
Wood River has done
SMU software for embedded iot systems
All the helix
Platform
Basically this is designed to give you a call
Systems that need to be high-risk are high lyrics
Avionics
Industrial
Utilities
We're seeing a lot of stuff
About
This
Is going to use when rivers are toss real time
The song
Another
Industrial iot
A company that has been in space
Sap
Has announced that
They are
Boosting their Leonardo
Toolcat Leonardo was something they announced
Probably 2 years ago
Everytime I hear Leonardo I think of the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtle stuff
Different people
Basically the sap Leonardo iot Suite is going to let you
Use sap
On your iot
So you going to be able to pull your iot data
Old school staff into essay
Easy
As if he also did a deal with Microsoft
They're going to
Net use azure iot
Hub azure
Connectivity and device management
Beer iot data
Settings down at the edge going to be able to do this
I'm assuming
Bastille also makes it
Easier cuz right now it's not
It's very easy to use Microsoft Azure iot hub
At the age
I know that Microsoft says it's super easy but they haven't
Mtt super robust
Are people so adding this sap
Leonardo
Might make that
Easier
Set sap
Leonardo news Microsoft has announced the release of Windows server iot
Yay
So this is
What Microsoft calls the binary equivalent to Windows server
What's notable here is support
Insiders extended support giving you a whole whopping 10 years
I support
Figure iot
Devices
Deal
Most companies don't want to support things that long but in my
20 years
But so far they
Things change so much in 10c the 20
Makes temperature
Industrial
It makes sense because there a fee if it isn't broke
Don't fix it
Set because they
Because he got to get that certified
FAA analysis
And basically this is a big
Shiftboard
And we don't really talk about that a lot
But it's worth
And then at Mobile World Congress
Bausch and Qualcomm teamed up for
Industrial iot for
5G NR
Henry
Heather like what
Is the next generation
Release
The standard for 5G on
Mobile networks is set by a group called The 3gpp
And those guys are looking at how we can use 5G in industrial Empire
Couple things you're going to need
Are doing that in industrial environments
One of them is the ability to
Have deterministic networking so basically
Let certain packets go through if they have to
We talked about this a little bit in the newsletter
This is things like
Hey if you're streaming a Netflix video
And
You got to control system
Industrial
Cement mixer
Those systems
Chapelle
Before your
Make sense
Yeah
They call it
Communications or urllc
Yeah exactly so we're not going to say that
We're just going to say hey
You got to prioritize your safety stuff
In
Control system stuff
Head of your Netflix
Which I don't know why you're watching it
Puts on the factory floor anyway
I do not know
They also are going to be looking at factories which is really crappy
Happy Radio environment
There's a lot of metal machinery
It's moving around
There's liquids slurries and things like that that will attenuate Wireless signals
So they're actually looking at how to
Create
A wireless signal that works in that have iron
Liability
So if you're curious just cuz you like acronyms if you're wondering what the NRA is
It is 5G
New radio
Yep which is really odd
Corset new radio
The new technology
So that
Lots of other World Congress
Embedded world but we thought we were excited
Or maybe just
Can I get excited about industrialized
I sure can
Kevin's light
You talk about that
Yes exactly
Okay
Now it is time to
Podcast
Yay
The iot podcast hotline is sponsored by a pharaoh
What the fifth largest iot patent
Portfolio in the world
Iot platform that doesn't risk your brand
Affero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
Antennax higher activation
Learn more at a pharaoh
This
Sky's is the
Last day actually Thursday is the last day for you to be entered to win a WeMo dimmer switch if you call us and leave us a
Question on the hotline
So get those in
Before midnight Eastern on
February 28th
Next month
I don't know what we're giving away yet but I'll figure it out
Let's hear
From this week's color about his
Best Buy
Hi Kevin Spacey I have a quick question for you
I used to use a ring
Doorbell
For some reason it just wasn't working out for me so I switched over
Too late that's hello video doorbell
One thing I liked about the ring doorbell was I could put remote
Is various areas of the house
I don't see the nest
Hello alternate capability
Do you know of any work around or is there any kind of a remote chime
For the best hello doorbell
Appreciate it thanks bye
I actually had the system setup in my house so this is easy
Basically in
Nest does not have an extra
Turn off chime but what you can do
Is go out and buy a $39 Google mini or
Spotify subscription
OK Google
I don't know
Buy lots of things and get a Google mini
So upstairs
In the settings section
Where he will enable voice announcements is what it's
Then
Magically when your doorbell rings not what emotion
It's triggered
Just when someone pushes the button
It will do an announcement that says summer
Mine is at the door
You have face recognition enabled
In the person is recognizable actually tell you
Sophia is at the door
It is kind of cool but there's a catch as we found out this morning before the show when I double checked
The setup in my home as well
I got a couple minis around the house and I have several
Smart displays as well
And when I went to the setup steps
It was not working for me
However
We researched and it appears that you need to have
Personal results on in your Google
Home / assistant settings
So that's it it's not working for you when you go through the setup steps you'll want to enable that once
I had that set up everything
Chimed in my house and
Video showed up on my Smart displays when I tested the doorbell ringing
Just be aware that you may need to turn personal results on
Yes
And for those of you have a question I realized I did not tell you
The secret number you should call it is 512
As what you're going to call
To leave us a voicemail
Asking your question
Enter to win that WeMo
Dimmer switch
Now if y'all will stay tuned
We're going to have fun who is the CEO and founder of the sea change Institute
Talk about how utilities are
Trying to control
Energy usage in the Smart Home
And how Amazon Google and whatnot
So
Hey everyone we are taking a break from this week's Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
Alter is urban X
It is an accelerator for startups reimagining the city light and we have one of the participants in the program
Ralph Lauren
Who is the co-founder and CEO of
Versatile natures
Let's get started with just a quick understanding of what versatile Natures does
Transform construction sites into a smart data collection field
Allowing for detailed analysis
Phone the project status
Well actually dramatically improving on-site safety
We installed a box
Ohio T sensors on the hook
Of the crane on the job site
Giving a view of the entire fight
The collected data
Is actually an alive
To provide real-time insights
Helping to improve
Not only productivity buzz on my side
Safety as well
Our proprietary crane view system is the most non invasive
The system in the market today
Annie's very much
Roi positive
Excellent
With the Internet of Things
How do you think the world of construction
From our perspective
Utilizing what is
Technically industrial iot we're doing that from the heart
Of the job site
Controlling a data stream understanding 24/7 of
Pretty much everything going on on the job site
Enable learning and understanding I look at
Any other
Manufacturing industry and if you think about it this is
It's just not
Connected today
Is fragmented
And no structured but if you still look at it from a factory perspective
It will run closer to
What's a did
BMW 5 series or Intel where most of my team comes from
I believe that's where construction should and is heading
And why did you decide to join the urban Expo
Openx
Was actually one of the best decisions
We graduated about a year ago on what Drew us into the program was
Incredible value proposition what comes to entrepreneurs and residents helping with design
Hardware and even though some of the software effect
BMW Mini and old enough or extremely synergetic and that proves
To be extremely valuable
I would gently recommend it to anyone
What he's thinking about applying
Excellent
All right and where can we go to learn more about versatile natures
And how to apply for urban axes program
Oh you could definitely live with us but versatile. AI
For Almanac you should check out Orban -
. com / apply
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Beth Carlin
Who is the founder and CEO of
Of the sea change Institute
Hi how are you
I'm doing great how are you Stacy
I am excellent so let's get it started
Quick question on what is
The sea change
Institute
Teachings is a research institute
I'm a research psychologist by training and work
Comprised of
Various primarily
A scientist that have decided that we wanted to leave the Ivory Tower and conduct science on
Change program for
Social and environment
Okay and if I met Beth
A couple years ago when she was working with a large utility
Trying to figure out does the smart home actually help
The answer to that was it depends
A little bit about that and a little bit about the utilities think about the smart home and then probably something while
Crazy just a surprise assault
Last time we talked
We talked about
How to Smart Home
May help reduce energy
After years of looking at that do you think it does
I think as you said
I think it's a pain
It started getting into this work
Before we even had a smart home as smart as we
Did you now I was starting my doctor
About
12 years ago
And
At that time
Google
Had just put out
Way before we had any smart thermostat they just put out something called the power meter
If people had information
About
The energy used in their home they could use it to change their behavior
Right now if you think about when you get a monthly bill you get one number that tells you how much energy
Higher home use
Entire month is not broken down by day
The hour or by the sea
Can your house not broken down by television
Computer versus refrigerator
It's like if you went to the grocery store and you can
Fujitsu take food and you got a bill from Trader Joe's
In the context
You give people information they can change their behavior
And the answer the truth is
Yes they can't that doesn't mean they will
Graeter's nutritional information
On the back of all of our food
People still eat Oreo cookies
Even though they're too saturated grams of fat
The Smart Home
Combine
Information
Ecosystem
With a second affordance which is control
Information about energy
You being used in our home
MC
When are you
Which might help us
Make better decisions
If we want
A smartphone
Should I turn off the lights when I left
Can chat and turn them off so there's all of this
Does not save
So the answer is
Yeah if
People shoes
I will say
That I have tried a lot of
Connected devices that are supposed to help me with my energy
She is starting with smart thermostats which was kind of nice but ultimately because I work from home and I don't want to work in an hour
Office that's 80 degrees during the summer it didn't save me that much
And then the next level was
Putting this device
On my circuit breaker box and having it tell me like hey
Your TV is used as much energy and your ovens use this much energy
But again after a certain point it's not like I could swap out my oven
To get something more energy efficient
And so is there a way for me to really start changing how I use energy
Based on the
Information again
I think you're getting at the right
It's about the incent
It is possible to use the current product
Ecosystem
To save energy in for people who are
Even your cooking it
Example
Could
Really wanted
Optimized for cookie
You could cook
A small thing like a chicken or a
Morning waffles
Inure
And then in a smaller convection oven
And if you have that data
Wow
If something doesn't need use a large oven when I cook it in a smaller convection oven it does use a lot less energy and I care so much
About that small amount of savings a Time
Start cooking in that small convection oven
Need to go to that amount
Oh dear I already know that
It's not worth it
Energy is largely inelastic
Because our energy bills not huge were not always as motivated as we might be
If it was something like
Calories and weight as an analogy a lot like
Behavioral changes in the way we eat based on the data about
Nutritional information
When we care about either
Losing weight
Getting fat
Running a mile in under sea
6 Minute whatever it is
Because energy is largely in
Inexpensive a lot of
Changes to a very little money and so it doesn't
Seem like it's worth it
And it also depends on
There are
People for
I'm getting a smart thermostat
Because they used to just
Leave the heater on
Used to leave their heat on all the time they had a programmable thermostat
Never programmed it
So they just had it set to
72 the entire winter
And now they've learned because they put in a smart thermostat
When they go to bed at night
It can actually go down a little bit when they wake up in the morning it's okay when they leave the house
It's fine
If it gets much
Cooler until they get home
For someone who is already program in their throat
Very little
Name for someone who wasn't
They might be more
So it depends on
Motivation
And the replaced
What were you doing before
If you were already eating really healthy
And you cut out
One additional item
Pretty healthy
Can you just cut out that one afternoon cookie
You might not lose weight
If you were eating a lot of fast food
Completely
Please tired or something else
You might see more weight
And it's the same thing with energy
Got it in that makes sense so it feels like maybe the incentives are not on the
Consumer side so I can't do much
If I do want to do something it's pretty hard
I probably not going to rip out all my old appliances
It might be less energy-efficient although I don't feel like
Dick Hannah Subaru
Efficient
So then maybe we should be talking about what utilities
Because
How did they look at this
Space and idea concert
Yeah it's a really interesting question be
Because Bratayley is not a single household Write Your Average
Utility has thousands tens of thousands
A lot of people don't realize this but most energy
Utilities
Want their customers
Use less electricity
It's hard to imagine a company that wants to sell you less of what they're selling
Super energy utilities
Almost all
They're large
Publicly reggae
So our energy
Utilities there are
Municipal so they're either provided by the government or their regular
By the government
Because energy electricity
At this point
In our modern era
Considered
Something that should be offered
Because we have a lot of if not at the national level and most of our state and cities
Climate regulations
In place to reduce emissions that is often
From the city or state level passed along
Judy's Beauty utilities
Aggressive Target every year
That are given to utilities
And their authorized
Spend
Some of our rape hair
Money
Wepay on her
Tiffany Bell
Message back to us
And provide things like
Rebates and incentives for energy-efficient products of Smart Home Products
They will be talk using lesson
The one reason is another is that our utilities are trying to stabilize the
Seeking grid stabilization
If you think the route
Good day
And throughout the year
The amount of energy
Suffused on average
Changes based on the weather
And if you think that most utilities have their own sources of either
Cool nuclear power plants solar Farms that they provide
If you think that when energy
On that really really hot day in July
You want to open up a new
200 million-dollar nuclear plant for 4 to 12 hours a year
Do they have to end up paying
Hydrate
Third party
When I have a more stable grid table during the day and stable during the year
Rosemead
Internally
For those reasons
Utilities are strongly encouraged
Incentivize
Both financially and
MR2
Try and get
People to use
Less energy at all times
And use more
Austin Energy
Mapreduce
Energy
What are the ways they've been doing this is demand response
And I've been part of a demand response program for
Why isn't a decade I don't know a really long time
And my utility
Peak demand
Hey we're going to stop your air conditioner for a while if I don't want
Sr utility
That's where we've been for a while
I talked to people and they're like
Hey maybe
It'll be involuntary
Or maybe it'll be like will just automatically throttle everything back
That we can like hot water heaters are can hbac those kind of things
And then you can opt back in
Some people talk about like instead of Isaac based on pricing
If I want to do my dryer dry my clothes during that time it's going to cost a lot more
How do you think
Those sorts of programs will evolve as more and more things become
Connected to the internet
And have you know a lot of work
Computing capabilities
They are.
Something about right now
You were just talking about this time of you
Becoming more and more prevalent
So like I said I'm in California and California were switching right now
Daily demand response
As opposed
The programs you're talking about
Dorothy
Have not been daily so that I can return your
Down
Now we're moving
Let's try and stem it almost every
3 day and a lot of this is from a good thing
Because we're moving some more renewable sources so as we rely more and more
On solar
We see that solar has provided the most
During the day
And then if electricity is used the least
Higher average household at night
Sleeping so there's this
I'm stopping her for to the doctor but you look better
The daily load
In the utility looks a lot like
Depending on the region
And that's also when we're getting
Amount of solar
Rate solar starting
Houston starting to increase
And so what utilities want is for you to use less optional energy
Doesn't mean don't do anything it means like you said
Maybe dry your clothes after
Baby Charger car
What we're seeing as
Is introduces like car charging right if we really can Electrify and we get off coffee
Stop going to increase our electric to me
And we don't want every
Ricard America
Start charging
People that charge maybe at 10
When you get home is when you want to plug it in so utilities are looking for ways to allow you
To put the clothing in the dryer
You think about it
Plug in the car when you think about it
But have the energy start
You win
The most beneficial to the grid and then
Either rewarding you depending on how you look at it for doing that or
Punishing you
You don't
I feel like my utility has had
Time of day but it's been
Very blunt
As an instrument
Till like after 9 at night
Till 6 in the morning
Between 10 in the morning
It's cheaper
Kilowatt per hour
Our bases
What I am hearing from people is
It may start making sense during a demand response event or
Maybe just to modulate certain devices to certain
Times of day there's a lot of talk about
Doing something like that or even having
If it's connected product even when I turn on my washing machine or my dryer
It'll say if you wait 2 hours
It'll cost you this much to run
Yeah
The few ways
We think about
The control
Capabilities
Smart Home Products
You can think of it in a few kind of bucket
The one is
User base
Control right through that mean
I'm going to give you information about whether your lights are on
Hair dryers running
And allow you
To manually turn it on or not
I'm just going to either give you the data
Worth available on a grass Bird app
And you can
Control your phone
A second
Is Ruby
Or schedule
Older programmable
Stop so you can say
You know what don't run my dishwasher
Press the button that says turn on my dryer
But don't turn it on until 10
Is third party
And that's like this demand response
Smart
Programs like you were talking about
Free utility says
Will you allow us
When we really need
Stabilized
The grid will you let us kind of go in
And turn your thermostat up or down a degree or two
If you don't like what we're doing
You can override it but you're allowing
Third party
And then the force is algorithm
I'm not what we're seeing in
Things like nest
Swear it just starts
The word
Machine learning algorithm
Your habit
You don't have to put in rules
Stay at 10
Turn the thermostat from
Because I'm going to bed
I just started learning that when you go to bed you go
Turn it down
And it starts figuring out when you go to work and when you
You come home and buy this algorithm
Start becoming more
And do the utilities want to get into this or do you think they'll
Outsource some of this to maybe
Google are the Amazon or maybe a completely different provider
The answer to both of those Quest
Yes
The energy in
Do you want to get into this and the way they are getting in
Is typically through 3rd party vendor LED program
Most
Utility offering
They're provided by Sia
Utility staff
Through a third party
Operator
Common
So historically for example you know for
Years they've been incentivizing
Energy efficient
Light bulb
And dishwashers and washing
Machines and fridges
But utilities weren't getting in the business of selling
They were just providing a pricing
The pricing signal
As well as if they're also mailing
You might consider
I'm more energy efficient fridge if you buy one
It will give you $50 off if you buy one of the one
As they're moving into this new world
Not just
Let me look at
Going from an energy efficient
Dryer which is just one where
When you dry it
The dryer itself
Uses less energy regardless of anything
You do or don't do
It's just a more efficient
Model
The only thing they need to get you to do is buy the dryer and then they're done
I can pop and stuff on the back
Good job
Time for lunch but if you buy a smart dryer
It doesn't necessarily
I mean that
You have to wash out
After 10 p.m.
You have the option
To set those settings right
You can buy
A smart thermostat and keep your house
It's not going to stop
It's just going to give you the tools with which to make more energy efficient
He's so cute and so now you
The new world
We can't just offer the rebate and then
Go to lunch
Once they get the thermostat or the smart washer
We have to figure out how to
Motivate
An able
Encourage engaged
Customers
To use those products
Efficiently
Because in and of themselves they are
And I'll tell you right now we're also trying
Figure it out
That part
Because we do not live in a country
Foremost
People want
Their utility
To be telling them how to use that
Right I pay for it I can
Can use it however I want
I'm paying
Don't tell me how hot or cold
Yeah we love our
I wanted to have Sidetrack you just a little bit and ask about this idea of as we put more
More connected things in our homes and I actually got a question about this on Earth
Which was
Hey I've been stalling my SmartThings today but their Wi-Fi connections
Require more energy
And I was just curious if
If you guys have done research on that or thought about things like
I've got connected light bulbs that got to come
Connect washer dryer increase my energy
Yeah it's a great question and the answer is
Yes of course I mean anything that uses plug load is going to be using
Thumb Electric
It's a small amount
So adding a hob and that's also why they're just
Connective protocols
You bought that smart lights to minimize that they have a hub
Connecting the light by us
Bluetooth low energy
Enter WiFi zone
So we are looking
More and less
Efficient
Communication protocol for Bluetooth low energy
Bluetooth which is going to be slightly more
It does use a small amount of things
You have plugged in
To your home
Drawing electricity
The more electricity you will be
They do not use
Largemouth
Official
Cincy is Jane
Baia
Changes in Behavior those changes in Behavior
You should more than make up
For the increase efficiency
Also it depends on what your replaced
If you replace
An old-school incandescent light bulb or a CFL light bulb
With the smart light
Smart light bulbs
I'm pretty sure 100% of the time I've never seen a smart light bulb it's not
A very high efficient LED
So just the Energy Efficiency of that light bulb
It's going to use Life Energy
Then if you connect
For five of those
That one Hub disconnecting them
Is going to take off a small amount of energy
But the light bulbs are more efficient and if you
You use that
2 then
Keep the lights in the house on for the first hour you leave the home and then turn them off or something where you would have left them on all night or
All day
Then you're going to see
Increase in efficiency
If you use the light
Exactly as you use your old life
Then you only
Decrease in energy use is going to be just by the efficiency of the bulb itself
That's kind of along the lines of what I thought
I'm like oh man
I'm kind of sad now that I
Think about all the
Things I plugged into my house okay we are a bunch of Gadget heads over here so I have to ask
If my focus is energy conservation
Saving money or just saving energy
What is probably the best item
Nectar Gadget
I could buy
Mosto
Home
The largest use of energy
DNR home
Is related to Heating
Super Bowl
Anything related to
Your thermostat
Home Heating and Cooling
Is going to be the most important thing
To replace
Really
I think
Another way of thinking
Think about it is to look at your
Dial M for
Household thermite
Did you travel a lot
It's so
Think about your
Travel bag
You can go when I go out
How am I
Burning off as many things of ice
And that's where the smart home really helps
If we have a family where we all leave during the day
Is are we really getting our base load of lowest cost
I'm so when you look at whatever you're setting up
Really look at your lifestyle and dope
When do I think I'm using things that I don't
Meet or don't even know I'm using
And how can this Markle
Ecosystem help me see that better
And get rid
The weather at
A dollar or $100 a month
Those little things like we said when you think about everyone in the
Country can really add up
Awesome alright well thank you so much for coming on the show today
Set for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my
Newsletter and Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week