Hey everyone welcome to the 202
10th episode
The Internet of Things podcast this is your host
Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have fun
Awesome
Erie industrial show for you
Today
We're going to be talking about a bunch of news coming out of Hannover Messe
Which is an industrial
Sandblaster automation is probably an industrial conference in Germany
Forgive you talking about
Beethoven industry 4.0 Alliance
We talking about
Walmart allowing voice with Google Assistant
Amazon has a new drone pet
Google may have a
Home hub device
And we're going to talk about
Surveillance
Smart cities
Ever going to hear from software AG
About
Connected factories
Aunt
We're going to hear from our guest
Keith Kirkland who is from where works
We're going to be talking about haptic
Feedback in haptic instruction
This is a super fun interview
Really enjoyed
So
Stay tuned for all of this
The first a message from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is iot world
You and you and you are invited to iot world is the intersection of iot
Innovation & Industries it's held May 14th thru 17th at the Santa Clara Convention
Center in Silicon Valley and is celebrating its sixth anniversary this year iot world will welcome
Over 12500 iot professionals 400 speakers and 300X
Exhibitors and startups you can go to connect the strategist technologist developers and
Letters to put iot into action within key industry verticals to learn more and to register to attend
Send visit iot world event.com
Okay
Hey this week
I am in Stockholm
Last week was Helsinki this week is Stockholm
So much
Fun I should be though
In Hanover
Actually try but it's too hard to get
A ticket
It was crazy expensive and then plates
And hotels were sold out it was
I never realized how big
Hannover Messi is
Is actually
Bigger than CES
Ncees
And
It is
Crazy in this
Actually in the last five or so years we've seen more and more
It come
Companies going to CES it really ramping up their presences
Starting probably
Actually it was
Microsoft CEO Saatchi
Nutella actually gave it
Keno
This year we saw the biggest Trends coming out of this world
Probably 5G
Inland Industrial
Libation and this isn't just because I care about these things it's because those are the hottest
Qualcomm was a
Big vendor this year they did
Cool 5G
Pavilion
Where they set up a
5G Network and had several companies
Using that that work for things like
Autonomous
Vehicle that was
Hopefully operated
I know
Autonomous vehicles and remote operators what is that
It's basically when the autonomous vehicle doesn't
Remote operator takes over
But that was operating over if I cheat
They are GE Network right now
It was a joke at work
If you and I couldn't bring are 5G capable phones
Those exist now
I know they've been showed I don't know if they're actually being sold
Yes yes I know Samsung has a 5G phone that they've announcement shown I don't think you can buy any
True 5G phones yet
Gabby we don't care
Because this is industrial
So
We saw a video transfers over
5G Network so this is HD video we saw a machine control
So lots of
Robot arms Kuka was showing some stuff with their robot arms for wireless control with them
And
We also
Sausage stuffer
ABB
Basically all the big names
Orit robot
Except for your name
Except for my name
Which I wouldn't expect
Because I wasn't there next year
I'm going I'm going to book early so I can actually get my stuff
So
Some things that happen though that are worth mentioning for everyone
Is Microsoft and the BMW group they launched something called the open Manufacturing
Program
And you guys might be like
Blah blah
But you should
Here's why
This is an open standard that Microsoft in BMW recruiting
It will also work with the reference Frame Works from
Different standards group
Call Dentistry for. O which is a bigger
European standards
Holden manufacturing plant
They're trying
How to create a smart Factory
Tree platform
Ties back
Azure
And it's basically reference designs that BMWs
Contributing to the splat
Form in what's important here
These quote-unquote open platforms are really reference
And the reference architectures that used for
Particular
Solutions
So
Particular software particular cloud backup
Cans and they make it really easy
This is not an open effort in the sense that they're creating a standard that makes it easy to like move or cloud
The cloud Iran
Get data from different machines at different places this is
I'm just going to say this a lot of Market
It is valuable
Because a lot of these companies do not
Have
Expertise
Pulling together it
So they can just go and pick up a reference to
Right yes and this is actually related to something that was in your newsletter last week prior to Hannover Messe
Microsoft announced a bunch of azure for industrial iot advancements with their so
Security Center for iot Azure Sentinel as your IP hub
And ironically also in the newsletter
Very similar
Announcement was made but not with Microsoft it was Volkswagen teaming up with Amazon
For AWS iot services
And Amazon's going to power
Volkswagens industrial cloud
To integrate like 30,000 facilities in 1500 supplier so
It's like everybody's trying to
Aggregator
Production now with coyote McCloud so that it seems like the fight is on between these big cloud companies
Yes and I will say that Microsoft has been
Way ahead of Amazon
Google I don't even think they can
OK Google
Cloud in the
But Microsoft has really done a lot of work Packaging
And hand-holding
Solutions for
Industrial
And it shows because they are by far and away
And they're basically just digging in
An offering more and more features they've taken a page from AWS in the terms of
Saying hey what are people building
Oh
We should offer that is a particular feature
And in really repackaging things in Perry
Easy to implement
Ways for different industry verticals
So I want to give them props here
It's a big
Amazon's less awesome at that but I think they're going
Get more awesome and I would say also Amazon has the
Developer base
Demeans people can't
There plenty of Developers
Who are working with in Amazon to build iot Solutions
Instead of working from
Particular reference framework
The people of design
They're just like
Make it ourselves
And that's what
So that's kind of maybe the battle to look at is Developers
Versus pre-packaged solutions that
Big giant Corp
There's also
The open industry for. LOL
Swiss
And this is a group of European
Companies
Including
Who got the robotics manufacturer
And sap
And they are
Basically trying to
Build an operating system
In an open operating system ecosystem
4 connected robots and
Connected processing
This is not new
There's a bunch of effort
It's like this they're usually offender
Specific
But here what they've done is they've created a network of
Couple different suppliers
Again
Putting the word open in your name putting the word Alliance does not
Necessarily mean that it is open
And that everyone
Use it or
Want to use it there's always the danger of login
There is a
Definite Trend we're seeing happened here which is
Probably 20 years ago when you were in the it
SeaWorld
You saw these things proliferate
And then
With the launch of virtualization and services like AWS we actually saw that
Whole underlying
Computing architecture
And even solution base
Get kind of
People developed apis people
Developer platforms and services
It made it a lot easier to create offerings for differ
Letters and Interpol them all together
In a way that let you
Pick and choose
A little bit more
Breezly and worried
There still.
But theoretically
You could get around
That makes sense
These days the big companies are
It's not that they're ignoring standards for their just creating their own
I think or maybe in parallel with existing standards
But it is a different world
Nit and iot than it was 20 years ago for sure
Iot
Will mature
It's just less mature
Are the stands now so that
It makes sense
Okay so we talked about 5G we talked about various open platform
And
The other thing
It's kind of a tangent with 5G
But I did want to mention this
Wireless
Is also
A big trend
And it may not be 5G it might be proprietary Wireless but we are seeing a lot
Of companies
Creating
Either private 5G or private proprietary networks for the industrial iot
This is new because
Historically
Factory environments are really crappy for wireless
Lots of metal objects run
Hang around
There lots of security concerns about someone being able to
Talk to a robotic arm and use it for ill
And
There are latency issue
So
5G will address some of this other Wireless standards have
Already happened
To address this but we're going to see more and more factories
Total Wireless
And like I said in my newsletter last week
Actually opens up a lot of interesting opportunities around
Agility in the fact
Tree floor in the ability to customize things
Customized Manufacturing
Processes for differ
Products in Boots
Things about
So I think it's going to be kind of cool
That was a lot
It's a big show it's a big show we just summarized like all of it
Sore quickly
Let's move away from Hannover Germany and into
News
From Walmart
Walmart to
I think
Before this news are about to talk about I think
Could voice
Order things from Walmart possibly through Google Express which is
Not something I use
Now Walmart is introducing
What they called Walmart voice
Order
So they have integrated
They're saying they're going to integrate across platforms
With multiple partners but the first one is
Google
And basically you will be able to order things or put things in your Walmart shopping card
To your Google home devices in the Google Assistant
And then. You do that over the course of a couple days perhaps
And then you say okay I'm ready to check out now and
You're good to go you
Purchase all your items
So this isn't quite new I think it's more of a revamp or refocus a little bit
So with you could do reordering
Through Google Express
Quit Walmart
What's up what you could voice reorder products
It went through the Google Express platform
On your Google
And now basically this is
Better in a
Migration on the
It's not through Google Express and
It has that
You just were talking about this ability to learn
Yep
So it's rolling out slowly but rolling out now so you should
See something come to your Google Assistant with Walmart tablet saying that's coming weeks
Yeah I think this will be interesting to watch him very I don't actually do a lot of voice ordering on the
Amazon books
Cuz you people do that's the thing when you look at all these reports and charts to come out of recorder
Voice ordering with shopping is still very low on the list of activities
Reason why is I will tell it to reorder it like a good option would be my arc I get these dog toothbrush bones Bass
Play for my dog and I ordered them all the time I have a virtual Dash
So I would like to be able to like Amazon reorder this
Spy on Amazon
There's like four different prices for the same size properties
Sometimes it defaults to the highest price sometimes it doesn't but I don't feel comfortable doing that
Right and then the other thing is I have to say the product
Exactly
Perfectly every time
This particular partnership addresses
Both of those
Concerns when it learns what I'm actually ordering
To my hope is that Walmart only has one price for
For these items so if I like this price
I can just be like yes I don't have
Double check
Right and price comparisons using voice is not ideal in my experience
No it's terrible cuz you can't even tell
Cheapest kids
On Amazon
Okay then you'll get it
7 weeks
You won't get exactly what you
So that's good
Amazon. Does
What kind of a fun
They do have a fun patent
We spoke about
Drone deliveries I believe it was in Australia
A couple weeks ago on the show
And people were a little upset because the Drone noise for the deliveries
Was basically causing issues with pets
And I've seen that before with my dog because these drums
Ultrasonic frequencies that we can hear but animals can
And then there's just the regular drone noise that's kind of a buzz and annoying to all of us
So
Amazon file for patent back in 2016 but
Was just granted it this week
And it should address the
Drum noise problem to a large extent if they ever implemented
The idea is that their delivery drones would have an inflatable balloon in the and the Drone will take off
With your product from the warehouse it will come to your house
But then the balloon will inflate
And that's the mechanism that the Drone will descend with so you won't hear the drum noise because it won't
Using its propellers of that point would be using the balloon to come down and then the balloon would re-inflate to go
Make the Drone go back up so I presume there's some
Helium
Tank in this drum to refill the balloon
It's rather interesting it's a clever solution to a real problem
Imagine it's not helium helium is actually
I imagine it's he
When it just
I don't know
I know it has to be
Something lighter than typical are asked to be enough of it to
Carry enough weight so I don't know we're very concerned about
Supplies Outlet
This is where a little bit of knowledge that you very little good
Yeah I'm all for that I hate the sound of drones
Innocent
You Kevin
Have discovered
Something
Before we get to that should we talk about your Discovery first or should we talk about
The
Other people's stuff
Let's talk about the other people's discover these are very related items so earlier this week
Android police notice
That
On the Google
Storefronts the online storefront
Taking their connected devices are they were showing something called The Nest
Hub
Max witch
Obviously has not been announced or we would have been talking about it
This is supposed to be according to the images and what was leaked
On the storefront it's no longer there obviously this is supposed to be a 10 inch smart display
With a nest camera
So you would not only be able to make
Video calls on Duo on the nest hubmax
But then you could keep an eye on things at home we could build a nest cam
Get your motion and sound alerts
Also supposed to have stereo speakers so something I guess
I guess something similar to our Google home hubs little 7in
Smart display
And the Google
What's the speaker the Google home Max
Google home Max
The big speaker
The big speaker like the $400 speaker
It sounds like a combination of those two products
If it's legit and considering it was actually on Google site
Yeah I think somebody hit the
Publish this page
Button a little too soon
So
We don't know anything else about it but presumably
If it's a real
Really coming tomorrow
I'm thinking I owe next month
Good time to make that an hour
And then
Website although
Maybe a little more clandestine
Kevin you did some digging into
Discovered
I discovered many many references to a color a board not a device because
Is Google names all of the boards for its products
Not the devices pick the code name for a boards
Was spotted in
The chromium commit log which is open source so that's why it's all available to the public is where I find out all the Chromebook news
The name of the board is called Mistral
And to clarify we should say
So when Kevin says bored most of you know this but if you don't
It is a collection of it is a physical
Board with chips on it that is used
Slap that into a product and connect all the connectors and then poop
You have
Computer or smart display or thermostat or whatever
Or whatever it might be correct
Correct
So Mistral has a mini code references to the recently announced
I'll come
Qcs 400s Oasys
And why is that important or relevant well that is
Outcomes
New AI enabled soc for smart speakers and
Digital assistants
An AV receivers
And it has
Mesh Wi-Fi capabilities Bluetooth LE mesh capabilities on device
Voice recognition
As well as a zigbee radios
I kind of put two and two and two together
Looks to me like all these code references
Indicate Google is working on a new
Either smart display or smart speaker or both
Because one of the chips
Has a GPU
The Qualcomm has
Created one of those not so
They could go either way here and I
Eating
It really sucks to me
Google's combining its Google Home Products
And possibly a Google
Wi-Fi product which is something I'd said they should do and also
Likely or at least possible that this could actually be a
True Hub at try radio hub with
Li-fi
Bluetooth and zigbee
So lots of unknowns here but I do know they're working actively on
A product
Will we see it I don't know
Will it be what I think it is
Again I don't know
But it is definitely something to look forward to I do not think this would be in time for next month's
Google IO I think this would be more of a fall announcement with their
Typical pixel products that they do roughly September October
And with a zippy radio
Couple things
Amazon has their Echo Plus which combines
A tri-band radio so Bluetooth WiFi and zigbee
For smartphone control
It does not act as a Wi-Fi router
It did bite
Euro so maybe
That's coming
Mississippi Braves
Could also be
Thread
Because they both use the same underlying
For the radio
So is the point is this
Define predefined Zippy or could it be possibly threat
Is it yours it just 802.
That's a good question and just the fact that there is a CD radio on this SOC doesn't mean they'll use it
That's true there was a CB radio in the Google Wi-Fi
ASAP I said they never
So
That is true
By the way and then this is just a little
I don't know maybe it will be on Jeopardy someday
Do you know what a Mistral is
Do a mystery
Is it a bird straw-like
No it's a strong cold north-westerly wind that
Those through southern France
Meaning in winter
Why do I bring that up
Because the code name of the board and Google Wi-Fi
Is Gail
G a l e
Oh
Wi-Fi with the wind theme
I like yes
I wish I knew more power Regional wind
I'm like yeah I'm
They're good at parties to people
And that's all I know
But okay
There's a theme there we'll see if we see any cool
Google home hubs that's good news
Because I do think
We need to see continuing innovation
And let us move on
To something we probably don't talk
Enough about
Which is
Surveillance
I didn't mean to make my voice sound all robotic
Keep it kind of did
So The Intercept published the story about
Sidewalk Labs which is
One of alphabets independent companies
Doing smart cities efforts
And
They actually
I have a program called replica
They're offering two cities that shows
Basically how users are using city streets and where they're moving around in that sort of thing
What's noteworthy
Is the cities don't actually
Know where the state is coming from
Speculated is from
Cell phone data
They're probably right
This relates back to
Foursquare
Which showed off a product
Is a concept product at South by Southwest
But you see
Hot spots in the city
Of Austin
Based on people
Vocation
Around town and their cell phone location
What they were doing is Foursquare provides location infrastructure for
Apps like Twitter in Uber
So everybody's phone that has those apps on it basically is checking into
Wish I could handle for square butt for square noses
And so they were trying to aggregate that data
So if you were single person moving around it wasn't showing that data
But if someone
And a bunch of people were at 8
Place it would show
There's a lot of people right here
Anna's house
Kind of like what sidewalk slabs is off
Offering for
What's with replicas
Now
This is where it gets dicey
Like are we okay
With
This data being used in an
Aggregated
I would say yes as long as it doesn't
They don't
I would like the next track I know they're track
As long as they don't show individual
Pat's
Or I mean you can get a lot of
Personal information just from your device and I don't mean the personal data
What's your email and such I mean
Specific device identifiers that are tied to maybe your cell phone account for example so they have to be very careful
About what day do they collect here
It should all be at
Corrugated when they're showing
Because in this brings me back to like Strava and
Nets heatmap remembered
The year or two ago when they
Publisher keep mapping
You could see all Strava users
Were sharing location
You can see like
Oh hey there
A couple people using the sap running around in the middle of nowhere in the desert
Then people
Oh
That's a US Army base
Secret operations you have to
Implement something so if there are fewer than a hundred or I don't know what the no
Number is
That certain number of people in a
Location
You shouldn't show it
Outlier should be shown
You shouldn't be able to
Track one person's
Half through
For the day
End
As these things become
Boar
Useful than I would say they are useful
That's the other thing
I mean if I want to know how many people are at my favorite restaurant right now is
Is it busy right now
Different kind of information that would tell me that Google actually offers this
Google
You like search a restaurant and a location on your phone
Ashley sweet
Super busy
The other thing is it would be nice for against leaders to have access to the state of
People like if you're looking at an emergency room it would be really useful to see
Pads of
People
A places so people tracking is actually really important
It's just very difficult
Lot of places are trying to do a
Sensors mounted
Doorways and that's what
Best
So
Is this awesome
It's all in how it's implemented I think
Yammy Google could I have a really important data
Product to sell
Can you could even use cell phones as a
Can detect three ways does it is a means to detect traffic
Right you could use that you can sell that data to Lake
Companies for occupancy in for
Formation
Again
Depending on how it's used
So I have a very serious question
Okay
Does anybody use Foursquare anymore
You don't have to
Your app so I know in the in the background that I know a lot of apps do this yes
Realize necessarily
You realize it when Twitter put your location
Actually in like
You know if you're using Uber
Uber has to know where you are
And it's not magic now the fact that it's running all the time in the background
That's kind of
That could be disclosed
What's better and actually there was
This is a little bit different but there wasn't
SA
This week in the knee
Times about
Cell phone companies selling
Upset
No I don't know if that should go up to the airport
Patient level
Soda cell phone companies that are providing the
Physical Hardware should your applications failed to sell this data if your
Cell provider is it
I don't know I'd rather see it at the app level because consumers have more control in terms of permissions and
And so on
Just aggregated data that the carriers have I don't care that they sold me my device I'm paying for the device it's my device
I don't really want them
Getting into the space personally
That sounds okay
Now I don't trust any
Okay
She doesn't even shared her location with me
You don't know where I am actually got to know where I am in Stockholm
Okay
So last week on the Internet of Things podcast
Hotline
A question about
How
You can use Madam a
To control automated blinds
Because there isn't currently like
I really awesome blind function
This person was using the wink
Separate
Heaven and I
We have an answer but it really wasn't a full answer and you guys were like you guys didn't tell them there are options
Farthest was cuz I wanted to test it out at home
I wasn't sure what I could do from here
But
Everyone pointed out that
They can do this with if
And with stringify
Stringify as a company that, cast by
And you can still download it it's free
Very complex
But
Several people gave us the instructions so we're going to share those
But before I do that
Have to tell you that the Internet of Things podcast outline is sponsored by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest
Iot patent portfolio in the world
Pharaoh
Provides a
Proven iot platform that doesn't risk your brain
Avero customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction and time-to-market in
10x higher activation
Learn more at a pharaoh. IO
You can call us on the iot podcast
5126 to 3
7 4
And
If you are feeling especially nerdy this
Month surprise
You're going to love it
It is a Kinect
IO
And the board basically
You plug it into your existing wired alarm system and then
You can control it through the SmartThings Hub
So this is kind of a limited use case but
You're going to like it
Is it let you use your old
Wired alarm systems
Unless you talk to it through SmartThings
That's why people there are people looking for that product because we get calls on that how do I
Extend my old wired
Security system to make it Wireless so
Perfect yay
All right so that is going to be April's
Price
To be in charge when you just need to call us at 512-623-7424
Read us a question
And it be entered to win
While we're at it
We get to this answer for you
We should announce
March is winter
Who doesn't
Have a name
So he does he just didn't provide it but that's okay because we can text him and
Cadiz information
So we did choose a winner you'll be
Schlage connect
Lock
And no name
Thanks for listening thanks for leaving a message and
You'll be hearing
Okay
So let's get back to
How this thing
The original question was about a Z-Wave motor
Engraver
And that was the two
Raise and lower smart blinds
And wink
Can do that
However
Madame a cannot
Understand what do that for you through wink
However
If you create a shortcut in Wink 2
Raise or lower your blinds Jose to shortcuts
You can then connect
Madame a with wings through EFT
Create a recipe that says hey when I say this to Madame a run this wink shortcut
So that's the way to link those because you can't do it natively
And
On the stringify side and this is going to be much
Much more.
So first off stringify needs to see the blood
Then you create
A flow
So once you got stringify
Able to see the blinds usually you could do that and wink or smart
So however
Then you basically create a stringify flow
And you included as a c
Courtesy
Can you have that flow tied to
Madame makeup
Also actually use it for a
Vim commands
And then you can
Through the scene
Do you say Madam a
Start
Blah blah blah
You may have to say a stringify to start but I think I say a stringify to run
And then it will do so
So that is how you would do that on
And remember both shift and string
And just to be clear this is Wink specific because the caller had wink and the Graber smart blind motor
For smart thing you can actually do this natively with
There's a device Handler
Where you can change your
Blinds and stringify to beat act like a dimmer switch
Yes
Lots of options for our color last
We are sorry that we
Progestin
And propstore listeners are we got several emails and voicemails on
Exactly what we just explained with
EFT and stringify
So we didn't give a complete answer because of Stacy said she really want to test it before we actually
Could say yeah this will work
But I haven't been home in 2 weeks
So exactly very difficult
It's just me. I would know that if you shared your location with me
So that concludes the new portion of this week's podcast
And stay tuned for a
Conversation
Chief Kirkland from where works
His company is building a
Device to help
Visually impaired people Wayside using haptic
Can we talk about
That particular product
We also talked about
How we should be using haptics and tips for designers on building haptic feedback into their devices
Json products you're going to like it
A message from
Our sponsor
This would sponsor is software
AG
Hey everyone we're taking a break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is soft
Software Ag and I have Bruce Cain was part of the software AG iot
Supers let's kick it off with telling people
What is software AG doing with the
Internet of Things
Capri Jesus 50 year old soccer
Company
Bread-and-butter is with integration
Software
So we allowed
Companies to talk
To each other in the internet of things we have
Cumulocity iot plan
Ashley platform
Is a full iot platform that can be run at the edge
As well as in the cloud and that's very important because now we can do a lot more work at the edge
Then just up in the club
Excellent in Edge Computing is all the rage these days
And I understand that you have a great story involving robot
They can really underscore the importance of edge
Can you share absolute
Are cars painted when you buy a new
New car is a robot
Comes in and does all the paint
No more human
Great thing about this is that the robots can analyze
Howard's
Painting how fast the arm is moving so you get a perfect
Paint job
Downside though is that takes a lot of data
Can make that happen
The other side is we as consumers are a lot more particular than we used to be and we look for every
Little defect if there's one tiny blemish in my paint I don't want that car I want another one
So because of that the paint jobs have to be part
There's a lot that goes into a perk
Paint job
That's not just a paint in the air mixture but also the
Humidity in surroundings
Temperature
There's an awful lot
Of data that needs to be consumed by these robots in order for them to
In the past
They would send that data up to the cloud
The cloud would do the analytics and decide G it's getting a little more humid so let's put a little more
Paint to air mixture and would do those adjustments
Then the command down the adjustment would be made in Italy
Continue to paint
Problem is you'd be on the 3rd
Ask before you got that information
So that robot needed
That data at the edge
Quinoa ciot being installed at the edge running all this
Analytics at the edge remove that late
See time from sending that date up to the cloud they're able to do much better paint jobs less blemishes
Which means less reduce or less
Cost to the manufacturer
Excellent so if I wanted to experiment with software AG Eskimi lacity platform
Where can I go to find out more
Yes you can download a trial at sacree jd.com iot now and I really
Encourage you to do so because you can connect a device
Less than 2 minutes
Create some analytics in less than a minute and a half
Create dashboards
So in less than 5 minutes
You can beat
Behrman thing with your devices connected to an iot platform
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is Keith
Kirkland's
Annie's Biko founder
Where were
And we are going to be talking today about haptic
Hi Keith how are you today
And on fantastic how are you
Man I am super excited
I love happy
Dixon for everybody who's like
It's basically using vibration to like indicate to you
Touch it's basically touch
To indicate something
I really wanted to tell me my right for my left because I'm not very good at that
But we're going to explore all the ways
So
First off
Keep let's talk about
Whatwears works
We design products and experiences that communicate information through touch
Parkway band is a wearable haptic navigation bicycle
Basically we forgot it would have got people to what in a destination using vibrating shoes
Without the need for any
Visual audio
And
Back in 2017 we use that technology to help us Blind Side
New York City marathon
Which is awesome and you
You kind of have to tell us
Why only the first 15 miles
Did he get tired
Oh yes
So basically you know
The Merritt Island
It was Marathon day and
We were getting everything
Kevin my co-founder also ran the race with Simon
And we put all the devices that everything
And it turned out that the weather
Was really really bad
And so it ended up
Raining for most of the marathon
And about 15 miles then
We basically ate you know
Put together the night before and didn't think about what I said was thinking about trying to get him through this race
That was a sound like a surprise ride
At some point
Midwifery that divides Gatos
Stop working because of the rain
That is such a bummer but it's also like
Valuable life lessons
What is provocative
All right
So I have been excited by haptics
For really long time like I said I have a terrible sense of direction
I've always wanted my phone.
Book that is right no not that way
Go the other way
That's my settle
And we've had it in
Actually phones for a while in terms of like
That little vibration that you get when you touch your phone screen
That is haptic feedback
But you actually got started
In a way that I think is super cool for iot and wearables Market which was trying to build
A suit to teach you Kung Fu can you tell me about
I had always been a
Big movement Lerner and
I always ended up with you
Weird injuries ww3 stop me from doing that movement that I started to love
Learning how to do
And so
Program at Pride
Add a previous background mechanical engineering and then
Did that for that and then I decided to
Come back and see if she make her and sad and so I knew that.
And I can see the sign that if I see
I was going to Industry for a while mainly going handbag stuff
A better time at lesportsac and Calvin Klein and coach
Anytime came out lyrics Dance With My Father
Amazon handbags
Bios
Is a great way to use designer for Humanity and someone back to school
The Grand Design to figure out what that might be and along the way I ended up being study
Brooklyn
Renovation design program which
That allowed me to go to town what's that mean
Technology
How do I integrate
Technology and Society
So much, until I do something that
Is really really great and so at the time
Still kind of
End it movement challenges that I was having I kind of put together the pieces that was like okay I think
It's possible for you to make a suit that can help you to
Learn kung fu
And I got that
See something inside that I had and I thought I was totally super duper original I was like wow
Like the Matrix is now
And then now all of
All the sudden
I go and I do a go to research since when I realized that you have been built at MIT card to check goes to
And basically they kind of validated all this
That I had when I was
Thinking of
And that was basically like how do you use hotfix to come correct from
Posture
And so that was kind of the permits and the idea but
Challenging that suit with a
What was kind of really started
Groovy Cambodia parent is that
But I want you to raise your breasts 2 inches off of your lap
Using vibration how do I tell you to do that
How do you tell me to do that
That was my next question for you
So I can put a motor to top of your
Dress right
And maybe it will feel like you should be pulled up
Apple at the bottom of your results
Krista at work kind of
Hadn't really been done yet and there was no
Things are kind of based off of like what we start to call a haptic language away of
How can I signal to you to do information without having to tell you what to do
Without having to explain it
How can I be so intuitive
That you can just understand that this is
And that's kind of what we talked about haptic design
We're like we're using tots
And the same way that a graphical designer uses
Schedule
2 light design experience
For our users
And where
Just kind of talking into a different sense
You know why not
Is kind of often overlooked in the in the design space
I like it this is actually something that I
Read about and I've actually wanted for a while so not kung fu
Stupid I do a lot of Pilates
As part of that
I sit there and
Like I do if I just had a little vibration here that was like
Activate this muscle
Right here
Or
You're doing it wrong but then I did quickly realize that
What you're talkin about this language
Haptics
What apps come into play like
What is like
Activate that muscle versus
Stay put but
You guys
Kind of figured it out on the way finder
Makes sense so talk to me about
Your haptic portal
Yes I have two quarter is this idea
I kind of got coin through kind of
Are using
The device and having the experience and
Basically what it is
You can imagine
You're looking forward
That you know I'm not sure you know I feel like most people play Pac-Man
Or have cut out a large enough lights
Pie crust baked pie
Either way you look at it at your face
Infobear you're kind of like BMP
Pac-Man
That's the correct
Lego basic
Everything else is some basic Lisa
Some varying degree of wrong from that and so will be
We did it we decided 360 have to experience it as you change orientation
Is it bad to give you constant feedback to let you know
Exactly how wrong you are and whether you're getting stronger or whether you're turning more into
What we consider the correct direction
Which is why the device happens
Got it why choose to do it that way
I mean my gut when thinking about communication right
And communication
Your touch is like
Like we have to figure out this like intuitive language for haptic feedback just like we did for like
Touch-sensitive screens on devices were all in a Lego pinch-to-zoom and swiping so
Why go with something that's a little bit more
I want to say generic maybe more basic
One of the things is that
Language acquisition is
Really challenging
You know like
Currently learning Swedish outside learning Japanese
German
Spanish is probably my best bet so far and you know it just takes a lot of time
How to learn a language
It's the one of the things that we're both
Be careful about while we're going to tap that language is
That we need to make sure that the language acquisition time that the time that it takes for you to understand.
Experience is a short at Papa
And now so the way we've done that
The language creation and the two major components
Suppression of your haptic experiences
And how experiences are
Wheatley design
Haptic
Experiences
That deliver
Piece of information is critical to the function of the device
Extremely effectively and very intuitive William very quickly
Anastasis I have to corridor
That would have the court order
We get people in the life
We say
Do a 360 spin
And we tell them to spin again at the stop in the direction that they think
Is the right way to go
And most people can figure out
Within about 15 seconds
And those are the only instructions that they have
And so we had to make sure that
The main function of the device could be Mastered by any person that picked up a spice
Straight Out of the Box
And then
The second part of that is
Optic
Russians have expressions and more like worth
Experiences have like a chips right you know that.
Immediate thing there's an immediate reaction is very intuitive
You know whether you like it or not this one thing but you know like
The experience and understanding that something just occurred of instantaneous
Bright
And then we have to have to get special
Kids like us
Because you got an A on your paper today so I'm whatever right
Self-expression
Communicate some discrete piece of information that is important
A left turn is coming up in 30 ft
Please take a little bit more time to learn and I'm still trying to simplify these as well to make them really distinctive that
Experiences
The more advanced features
They give you more advanced and you want some information enter the experience
I wanted you to understand the initial experience
The haptic experience
They can go into the expressions and get more
Kind of like important and significant information for their travels
But we had to design something that worked out of the box.
BG's instantaneously it was it was super important
So you guys are designing this for people who are blind or visually impaired but
I kind of look at this and I'm like
I wouldn't mind having the sort of
Feedback in my day-to-day life especially for things like Anna wayfinding and different
Office Buildings or
Hiking trails trying to find the actual Trail is supposed to like
Now I'm suddenly stuck in a Ravine and I don't know how I'm getting there
So I'm curious Lake
What do you need to make this happen and then
Could it go beyond just the visually impaired
Initially when we started
We were just trying to get people out of their phones and back into the real world
And so we saw all these opportunities where
The screen based devices that we were using
We're requiring a huge amount of our visual attention
We thought that
You know navigation
Inherently visual
And so
To be able to navigate and use your vision
Functionally while navigating a getting there
Information system other senses
And so we see kind of have to
The next Frontier you look at every other sense
There is
A hundred billion dollar Industries built around them
You know like I'm with the
The immersion of arbr
You know have
Full 360 4K
You know high-definition video you have
3D Audios in the box drop 20 feet behind you over your left shoulder but then when you go to pick up that box
You still have the experience of
Having to pretend that there's something your hands when there is that so
We seek on Apopka
Texas kind of life
Kunming industry
That's going to start
Create an impact in
Media and designers and
And it's on right and right now
We kind of see that
Working with the Blind and Visually Impaired
For the first part of the experience
Want it really
WorkSource Prince because
Tabata visually impaired
Population
They actually have the greatest
Understanding of tactile acuity
The best possible
Designing for
And so we understand that like and we can really nail. You safe than every other use
Case of follow suit binder
And so, that's our plan right now
You guys have been doing this for a while
And
You've learned valuable things about water
But
When you mentioned like in gaming and picking up a box and that's where thing I'm like oh
Yes please
So what are some of the things you've learned in playing with haptics as much as you guys have
I know you felt away ban but
You guys have also built
You thought your kung fu suit or tried to fill part of that
Text me about the things you've learned that you could pass along to other designers who are like
I'd love to get involved in that
What do I need to know
So I think the first thing is is bad
You got to have a bit of understanding and physiology
Different parts of the body have different resume
Wish instead
You know that your hands your lips
Your time. Pretty amazing
You know your back is pretty bad
And so when you're designing you have to experience
Usually has to be pressing against some forcing of the skin to be effective and it depending on what part of the body that you're
Designing for
It really changes kind of like this
Applications of the thing that you're building
The underside of the wrist for example
You know it is
Super Suds vibration activation
Even though the resolution is below a light
Cotswolds
Send the signal
Butt on your back
Act like that sensitivity is it
There's a lot that's so
Pay attention to what part of the body you're working with and understand the physiology kind of like of that body part that you're working with
How it responds to touch
It's kind of like a good first step
Additionally
I think the biggest thing is just to kind of go in
I really have fun with it
You know like that so much inspiration
And
You know this world of
Using
A different sense
It's the kind of as a foundation for the work that you want to do any work that you want to explore
Verity
Inspiration is that you
Kind of full from
You know like
Awesome fiction but
And I really kind of like pop culture or just anywhere
Tennessee
What types of things
You really could
Be doing
If you didn't have to
Look at it or
Hear it
Understand
And I think God
Just kind of being in that space playing in that space
Kind of like documenting kind of what your understanding is
Because right now I think
The other Opera
90s R&B in the state says that
We're all trying to figure out how to make us stuff and documents
Stop
Write this stuff that we recall haptics with that we're still figuring out
Right now there aren't really any
Three platforms that make it simple
Or
These types of possibility
Be created
Bye
Doctor Who
Pick it up in the same way you have as Photoshop or illustrator
And that was like I think there's a huge opportunity
Anastasis
Really
Explore different ways of
Howard Dr
Work
Answer
Share that work on Sunday with one another so that we can all move that District forward like together
I like it
Quick question for you this is a very practical question but
You know I'm a very practical person
So there's the way band idea and I think looking at the spec sheet that is probably way out of date
It was like 3 hour battery
When I'm thinking about haptics what is that do for battery life
What is that implementation really look like if I'm going to have a phone that communicates to a device or device that I'm in a
We're all day
Navigation purposes
It doesn't really horribly affect battery life vibrating Motors definitely have a drain on battery
That's pretty clear
But
The thing is is that like
You're not navigating so much of the day and so while you're out use
Device
The average
Walker
Thing is probably about like
I know usually at that point people using public transportation
You know like within that kind of a distance
You're walking like
Maybe an hour a day maybe two hours a day maximum
So
The battery life on the device last for days without being charged
True that's a good point probably one of those tips that we should really thing
Think about like when implementing something
This is really exciting and you guys are going to do a crowdfunding campaign in
August or September correct
Yes that's correct
Tell me more about this campaign
So in August or September will be watching
Kickstarter campaign
I will be delivering the very first playback devices
To the public
And so everyone will have enough
Free water
I've been based off of those
Well Manufacturing
The goal is to deliver the product
By April of 2020
Super excited
Getting everything ready and
It's a big moment for us. It's just been a long time in the making
It sounds like it okay
Well awesome Wilke thanks for coming on the show this week
And good luck to you that's it for this week thanks so much for
For listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Dot-com will see you next week