Hey everyone welcome to the 208
Episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham and your co-host
Not
Kevin tofel
That's right
Instead of Kevin who is off
Watching his beloved
Hear the Sun Devils his
His team is Arizona State University so
He's actually at a nearby game
And he's very excited to be there so I've got
Michael host
Whois
Actually The Godfather of this podcast
Chris Albrecht
Yes
Yes I made you an offer you couldn't
Refuse that was basically at Chris Forest both Kevin and I into the podcasting game
Low these five years
Hates Chris
Hey you're welcome and it's a pleasure to be here I don't want people to feel
Like a Miss Kevin too much so I'll be sure to drop a bunch of Beatles references as we're chatting
Excellent and if you could be overly optimistic and not at all privacy-conscious.
Also help
With a
Kevin tofel
Okay
We have a big show we're going to be talking a lot actually
About connected cars
The federal government is ripping up some of their efforts with an iot security bill
And a facial recognition bill
Talk about we've got yet
Another
Machine learning at the edge stick this time from Nvidia
We could be talking about for borrow doing a deal with SmartThings
And
Welcomes smarter chips
Are smarter
Speakers
Plus
Robots Galore
I guess this week is going to be Bjorn block from Ikea
We're going to be talking about Ikea's plans in the smartphone
Including the smart blinds and an upcoming partnership with
Sonos
We're also going to hear from our sponsor of feral
And how to make Bluetooth a secure
Communications medium for payments and other
Cool stuff
And finally we've got another message
From another one of our sponsors
This one is Western Digital
Western Digital builds Data Solutions that enable the world to solve its biggest challenges introducing suffer
First DME SSD to its award-winning WD blue
Portfolio build for Content creators and PC enthusiasts it is designed for near instant
Access to 4K at 8K video files and it's trusted for a track record of reliability
So Step Up 2 nvme performance at Western Digital
Dot-com
And for all of you who are like
Nvme
Just think to yourself
It's wicked
So
Chris
Let us get started with
News about securing our cars
Didn't which is a security company
They have added a new program
That basically
Brings all of those OBD
To Port
Devices
So does things you plug into your car they're connected they can tell you where the car is been they could tell you
How it's breaking all of that
They now tie that into your smartphone
What's a villain
Security package you can get
A OBD port
Monitor device and
Then it will do things like if someone bumps into your car
It will trigger the accelerometer inside that device
That device
Will go over a cellular modem connection
Into the cloud
Clown calls back down to your house
And it turns on
Camera
It's watching your driveway
And it'll be like
Oh dude it was your neighbor
I totally back today
What do you think
Well
Is it something you would get like
Let me ask you that cuz I don't
I don't think I would
But I live in a pretty room
Rural area
So
I'm not as concerned about it but is this something you would want
Plugged in
Tight end do you need to know that much about what's going on
So I don't but I don't park my car in the street
I think if I did
My car in the street
Might be nice
The other thing is
Apparently
According to the people at Vivint a lot of people
Don't really know much about these OBD
We got to find a better name
I hate saying this
Basically they're little things you plug into your car they're connected usually cellular
Via cellular modems and
Again they monitor where cars been
How fast is going
Breaking
Bumps all kind of
We actually just answered a question last week from somebody who's like I'm a teen driver and I'm thinking that might be a good thing to get
Yes
Do you need to link it to your house Vivint is going to charge you
$10 a month for
One and then $5 a month for every subsequent device you want to connect in through their platform
And then you'll also need a camera
Right pointed at your car
Yes
They also offer that
And
I think for some people this is going to be
Relatively
I mean it's
It's not terribly expensive
If you think about like it's got a data plan associated with it.
They're paying
So
Some people will like it there probably like
More so than like weren't being worried about their car getting bumped they probably will want
The Peace of Mind of being able to look and see where their car is
I know that because I have a Tesla I can see where the
The Tesla is parked
And so I always know like
Where am I
My car is gone with like my husband and child
For they are
Which country
Get you don't part of me
As I think about these things and I think about
Protecting my home
And property or whatever I get some point I just I don't want to go down a rabbit hole on it
For something like this
If someone bumped my car and they take off
Do I really want to go through the process of tracking them down
Finding them confronting them
Making it like a big
Deal
You know depending on the size with dang
Just taking care of it like I just think of the number of times that my car whether I've lived in a city or not
Has actually been hit
And you know I don't know this could just be the old curmudgeon in me but I just wear like a you know what sometimes
Life happens and I can't prepare for everything and I don't need to know
Yeah I don't need to be able to track down whoever done me wrong every single time
I think you wouldn't do it cuz this is not like a
A Jack Reacher novel I think what would probably happen is that you would give it to the police in the insurance
Couple and they will take care of
What yeah I know I don't forget I am not saying that I would
I am not saying I would
Right
Yeah it was just a matter of like how much more
Work is going to go into it versus just taking care of it and just you know
On the ongoing again get ive lived in dense cities
And
In the case of a car being. Again you said there's something with like a teenager there might be something of value that and maybe
10 years down the road I could see value in it with my own kid
But I don't know for right now it's you can really you can over ensure things
Thanks to a point to where it's
Statues of going to happen man
Yes I feel even better about this since you know I'm
Actually going to live near you at some point in the very near-term
If I didn't your car I'm going to be like
Stuff happens
If you make the trip to ding my car I'm going to let it go
Did you get to put the work in I'll respect that
Excellent so
In other car related news on Amazon
What color Madame a Blog and if you remember what we called
Amazon digital assistant so as not to set off every
Devices
They actually with the launch of the echo Auto
Which again I talked about a couple weeks ago cuz I really want Madam and my car
Kevin Dixon crazy but I'm all for it
What
Madam
To build skills for these devices to recognize what kind of device there are
This is really important because it gets to our favorite topic
Fake witches contacts
So if someone
What is the weather
And The Echoes
Realize there in a car
They can pick the most appropriate weather to that low
Location or maybe they can tailor something a little bit more specific to
The car
I don't really know what
You would do with weather in the car that was terrible
But this is really good I think it's really
It also
Anna speaks to the fact that Madame is getting embedded in more and more devices so this will become more and more important
Because there are certain things you want
If you ask it on like a dick
Display
Versus if you ask it
Nest Thermostat
I don't know if your thoughts
Tennis grass or if you want the ecowatt
Do you want Amazon in
I really don't
This whole conversation is setting me up to be an old curmudgeon get off of my lawn
But what I have
So I drive a Chevy Volt
And
I have a hard enough time getting
Carplay to work
Like it for some reason I don't know if I just have a bad thing or whatever but it is super infuriating to try and use apple carplay
Play the car if the phone is plugged in
I don't really use all the time needing the
A question answered or some kind of
Smart assistant other than Mike Maps
However what is kind of interesting is if you can
Pull the camera back right
So in terms of contacts
And the assistant and an echo in your car
As Amazon
Start building out more things like an Amazon grocery store
Right
That talks possibly to your
Amazon fridge or Dash replenishment
System it could say hey you're near an Amazon grocery remember you needed to get coffee
Do you want to pop in and get it we can have somebody waiting for it you know automated I'm just
Obviously a long enough timeline sure
Or just pour the coffee directly into your mouth but
It is interesting to think of context
In terms of connecting all your Amazon Services which I use a lot of
I haven't found that I use
Or have been wanting a smart assistant too much in my car
Let alone one
That requires an extra step so I already have carplay so I can use Siri
Whenever I want should I want
The idea I get it Siri is not the greatest
Voice Assistant platform in the world however
It is there and four basic questions
She could answer
But can I put a side note in here about the problem with Madam a
Yeah just personal anecdote
So I read to my son every night and we are currently reading the Wildwood series of books
And two of the main characters in this book
Are named Alexandra and Alexei
And so when you trying to get your son to go to sleep
And every time you mention one of the characters
And then there's a beep
Because misses a pop song
I just kind of
Authors of the world please stop using those two names
Will my solution for you
Sleepy
Oh yeah I guess I couldn't I would require work
Already got him trained
To say
You know my son already knows how to use Alexa I don't need to switch it up on him now
I think that would be a lot of fun actually to to suddenly change all the a digital assistant names in your house
Watch how long it
Teehee
Fun up until like 4 in the morning
When he wants Astoria is trying to go back to bed and keeps yelling anywhere
Hayward
Okay
Moving along to
Federal government
The US federal government
That's where we are based even though not all of her audience is there
This week
For senators
Co-authored and introduced
The Internet of Things cybersecurity Improvement Act of
Is the following act when they introduced
T17
Images of
Very different
And I would say it a lot of ways it's much better
The prior act required
Lots of
Things it spent time to finding firmware
Time to finding a server
It's bedtime saying hey you
You can't sell a device to the government that has hard-coded passwords in
How to cut of a long list of things
A lot of those things were perfectly fine
The idea of setting
Something like
What you need to be secure and stone like that
Felt really
Dumb
Because security is an ever-changing
Moving Target as it were
We're so this next version basically says
Hey
Before the federal government buys connected devices
They need to
Golang
Make sure they follow security guidelines that are set forth by the National Institute of Standards and Technology
Earnest
So
When a Sac passes nist has 180 days to basically say
Here's some of the rules we think you should follow here some of the vulnerabilities out there
Don't do this
And then
The
OMG the Office of Management and budget is going to basically say okay nist thank you and it will tell each agency
How they should follow those rules
And then presumably
The agencies will follow the rules
And then it also says
Over every five years missed Will Come Back in
Do this whole process over again
So it also recognizes the fact
Hey
Security
Again
Will change vulnerabilities will change and it lets the government update
In some cases
Industries have been reluctant
Patch because I feel like
They're not allowed to patch and in some Industries they're actually not allowed to patch so this could
Possibly alleviate
It's kind of
That's what I said
Do you think five years is too long
But I also think that this is the federal government
Hopefully
There's a couple things I'd like to say
I'd like to see a budget set aside for something
I like this is part of the bill
Because you know
Unfunded mandates are everybody's
And I would like to see the time limit shrink a little bit
But I recognize
That
When your is huge as the federal government
You can't just be
There is no agile
And the Federal
Most companies when I talked to them about how they're thinking about security they're following kind of
A devops or an Agile development Strat
Around it
The government really isn't great at that
I'd love for them to get there but I don't think
A bill is the best place to start
Necessarily
It's like turning a battleship
And then turning it again in 5 years and then turn at me like it is there is a lot of inertia behind it
So you said you don't think this is going to go anywhere this bill
You know I don't know
Maybe it will
You know what's it's being introduced to both the House and Senate this is a senate version
We'll have to see if it gets too
Committee
I mean it's about darn time
We need something
And this is a decent way of going about
Not doing it
I don't know if it's goes into effect it won't go into effect until March 31st
But you know
Hey
Almost a year away and government timeline
That is true
That's that's pretty good
You know what this article got me thinking about I actually grew up in military housing
And it got me thinking cuz I know you've written stuff about like
Smart home stuff in apartments
And what you can and can't do
But the idea of
You know Security in iot
And consumer adoption when that consumer adoption happens to be
On a military base with military families
I just thought that was kind of I hadn't thought about before
Because you never ate while I am
Confident
But you know
People aren't spilling Secrets over the dinner table
Are you dumb
In military housing you know there are still
People get together and chat and if you've got microphones everywhere that's just I wonder if there are any
Regulations around that
What people are allowed and aren't allowed to do
I'm sure people have thought about it but it just something you know
I never thought about you know
Growing up we didn't have these kind of things but they're still especially with like the nest Revelation and I don't know if you would put a nest if you were in a
Military home buy
I don't know maybe you like to Tinker and you would
Or just an echo device listens to the show military housing
Let us know do you have an attitude or their documents are guidelines about that sort of thing
I know that the
Department of Defense after the whole Strava
That really wasn't
And it was just
Widespread release of public data on
The Strava running app
And then it showed
The location of military bases could be
Construed from looking at
Everybody
Don't use Strava
Especially if you running on an undisclosed military base
Which
So I don't know
Let us know
Can call and tell us something
Flight at 5 12623
That was early
Okay another piece of legislation
We're not just caring about internet
Security
We are also caring about
Facial recognition
So I think it was last week Kevin and I talked about using facial recognition
US airports for
Basically tracking people as they come into the country to make sure they're not on
Crazy watch list
We were like
Hey
That's kind of iffy because nobody actually
With the none of this went through public
Comment
I'm and there were no limitations placed on the Airlines and how they decided to use that facial
Recognition data
So
Kevin and I worry
We're not in Peru
But
It sounds like
Might have
I don't know what real
This
Is a bipartisan acts that means a Democrat and a Republican
Holy cow working together submitted this
This is the commercial facial recognition privacy
And basically
It's
Saying that users would be notified
Whenever their facial recognition data is used or collected
This is also part of the backlash we saw
Probably a week ago
About
IBM pulling data from
Flickr
And
Using that to build
Best biased
Facial recognition
And people who had their photos on Flickr we're kind of like
Hey what you did what with my foot but I didn't say
Yes to that
And it upset people
So this law would prevent that
And
Again who knows if it will pass
It could be useful
I don't know
You want to get currently
So let's tie this in with the Vivint story from earlier
How does that work in terms of like if your facial if your security camera captures my face
And is used
Howl like a bystander basically captures a bystander
In a case like that my hunches
If your Vivid you can't actually use that
Image data
From that camera
To train an algorithm
For facial
Cognition
Use a facial recognition
Let's say you have a database
You probably couldn't run it against a database
Especially for a consumer used in the
Or something like that
Is my gas without permission
Like I have cameras that record
But I have actually opted
And I've tried
Help me hear
He helped me understand the importance of it
Because
There are so many things
But I know I should care about
And this is one where I just had sort of resigned myself and it's like I'm always going to be under surveillance I'm always somebody's always going to be
The appearing somewhere on
Camera at some point
And it's going to be used for something
And I know I should
Mindful and care about it I get the big like macro pictures and
Issues surrounding it but help me like
Help me want to
You care more about it
I think surveillance in public areas is something that has
We all acknowledge that there are cameras everywhere
There are fewer actually in the US Senate
Places that there are cameras everywhere in Pueblo
The question is if you are going to use facial
Recognition ansan
Right now the cameras just see you going about you
Your day but the computer system doesn't
Special recognition
The system
With tag you
And what's
Really worrisome to lots of pee
Is it might tag you and also have
Scary information about you
Even this is actually happening
King in China so
It might be like
Oh
That guy walking
Where is Chris Albrecht
And he has a parking
At the
In the city of Seattle
And
He is delinquent on his student loans
That it might share that information
Information with people
So the key
Here I think
Isn't the surveillance other that's good
Frustrating
It's the surveillance of the actual knowledge
And the ability to tie that knowledge to other data to derive insights about you
That is so
Worrisome to me
Part of me is just like
You actually
Bring up a really great points right at I totally understand that
And it's also
Target has feels like it's a sort of
Inevitable
And bearing down on us and I realized that the sort of an A-list a point of view but like
What chance does this bill have of passing out
In its current form
Probably not much although both Texas and
I believe it's
Iowa
It's a nice State there's Iowa Idaho in
Illinois
It's Illinois
However it is Illinois in Texas
Have
Laws actually against collecting and using
Which means like cool things like
Google look like your art
It was a Google thing a couple years ago were there like what
Art do you look like
You take a picture and it would
Show you
That was actually just a grab to get a bunch of a state
And also I'm sorry
Sorry show you the world's museums
So stuff like that wasn't actually legal in those places so I couldn't do it
For example
There are rules about that
That I think we're actually going to come down for
Pretty hard on
Not necessarily the surveillance
But how we link
That surveillance to knowledge and especially how we link the knowledge of who a person is to other data
That third step is really what
Is dicey
And
Is very easily done but I don't think we're going to do it except in a few
Cases I do think we'll probably do it wherever lights to light
Like security inside countries
Maybe there will be places where when you enter them you'll have to voluntarily sign
Away those rights
And that's going to feel kind of iffy
Weird and we may not
I like that
Right
But that's my thought
Maybe look at you go to school
Pick up your kid
It's so creepy I don't like it
You convinced me
Have I
You can't just be like I was going to happen
To not be seen
That's staying in
It yes yes it will
In other news
A video did a big conference this weekend at it
They announced
The Jetsons
Nano
Device this is basically machine learning at the edge which
Holy cow might sound familiar cuz we talked about it with
Google's Coral project
I believe it was last week
And then we've also talked about it with Intel's movidius project
This is noteworthy because
A lot
Of people
Industrial iot are using Nvidia Jetson
They have a board basically and people are building a lot of industrial iot gateways on
Because it is
Crazy powerful
This is $99
Can basically get you 472 gigaflops of computing power
It's got a quad-core arm a57 processor
Set 128 quart Nvidia Maxwell GPU
And 4 gigabytes of
Ram
It's going to support tensorflow
Caffe
Pytorch all these other Frameworks for AI
This is going to be crazy
You will have to plug it in
This is not battery powered
This is going to be awesome
It should open
Machine learning at the edge
Uptmor peep
Cuz the original boards for like three hundred and $400 so you actually in a lot of cases had to
Requisition
But this at a hundred bucks
Easy peasy
You just go out and get one and you play with it and you do something cool
$250 autonomous robotics kit
And if you want to play with that
And it also has like a little robot chassis Motors
Battery pack
It's battery powered
And you can build your own little robot
I don't know Chris Do you want to build your own robot maybe you or your son
You know we've gone through that phase and you build it and then
You kind of make it move back and forth and get a little bits one
R2D2 little bits
He programmed it
So
Now I have a dismantled R2D2 sitting in a box somewhere
But I want to know
Like this
Explain to me just cuz you know obviously I don't write about iot
And all this industrial stuff can you tell me what it like
Are there other products like this out there
And
Where do you think the big opportunity for this Nano is
So there are there's like a pension the Intel movidius stick
And the Google
Oral
And I think the opportunity for this is basically for people who are both obvious
It also
People inside companies that are trying to figure out how to use iot
They're the people who these things are
And the idea is
You will say to yourself
Man
If I you know I got this great model
It says if my engine sounds like this could you put some kush
That it's going to fail with it
2 days
And
If I could just get something
To recognize that could chunk chunk chunk
And then send an alert
We have this awesome monitoring system
And so
What you would do is you would basically
Train it to
Recognize that ketchup Coachella
And put it on this device and then stick this device
Somewhere near your mission
And then all of a sudden you've got this late
Maybe you spent like
130 bucks
Are they monitoring project save you some serious down
That's the idea
Is that
You'll find all kinds of crazy use cases
That you never even thought of
Before and
You'll do it because it's cheap and
And I think that's right
Oh good
Is it out now
Is not available
Today at you can pre-order it
On the Nvidia website and it supposed to ship
At the end of March
You probably should by now be
Because I remember when Intel launch their movidius stick
Get on it
You guys
All right
Next up
SmartThings
Users who also love for borrow
Rejoice
Because fibaro which makes a line of popular Z-Wave
Sensors
They have finally collaborated with SmartThings so you no longer have to download basically these separate device Handler stick
Get the football gear to work as intended on the SmartThings platform
Yay
That's basically all we have
And then in other
Sun News
Qualcomm
Is announcing a new
System-on-a-chip DQ SC400
It is basically going to go its design for smart speakers and it should let them hear you better even with background
And it should
Let them basically respond a little bit more
Quickly to you
Yay so so yes please
It's incremental but it's important increments
Yeah no like anything that improves that
To get cuz you can just stand in our house
If someone says misses a or
You know the mr. G or Miss G or gender-neutral Geodon
Locate Haji
Then you know there's nothing more frustrating
For both the person trying to
Ask a question or listening to that person ask a question then not finding that connection right not being heard
And then having to repeat it anyway I'm just saying there's no down
You're right there isn't a downside and they announce
Another new chip
Fit basically it puts a higher-quality amplifier
On your smarts
Speaker switch
It's not going to be magic
You know you're not going to suddenly have these masterful Bose sound systems or anything but
It will sound better
So go Qualcomm for incremental improvements to Smart speakers
This was a category that did not exist a few years ago and now we're at
Okay
What are you listen to your music on now
In-ceiling speakers that are powered by my Sonos we almost exclusively listen to it on
On the echo or the Google
Yeah I am the same way
Just to make you sad
You know what actually it doesn't cuz I sold
Oh that my Sonos stuff
A while back but it was amazing how quickly I've gave up Fidelity for
Convenience
Don't let your wife
All right
Moving right along
Cool thing that I would totally Buy
I don't know about you
So this is a Kickstarter I'm going to tell you that so you don't
This is not something that may ever come to
Fruition however I thought it was so darn cute.
And I really want one
This is a therapy dog
It is called the tomboc puppy
It is being funded now in
Kickstarter
It has reached its $20,000 goal and basically this is a $500 robot
Puppy
Is 4
Patients with dementia and Alzheimer's and it just interacts with them
It's dark cute
Man I just wanted and I think my daughter would want it because
Bissell Pet
That flaps its ears up and down at
Looks adorable
It's kind of like the aibo except it's only going to be like $500 when it launches its
$300 if
Support the kickstarter
But
I really well and also it's got fur
Ribose just digit hard plastic
Yes
Exactly
It's it's just supposed to be this
Companion dog
I mean
Yeah I want it
I don't know if I told the guy it is hard for me to
Dump on this idea when it's
For the target audience where you know it's older people with dementia who just needs a companion in this
Potentially provide some sort of relief
It's just a bummer that it
On Kickstarter because
Kickstarter I just I write about projects at Hardware projects in particular
On Kickstarter that just
Never see the light of day
Because people just miss
Plan in terms of
How much manufacturing is going to cost and what
Things are going to happen
But it is cute and it certainly is something that you know for me I wouldn't get it on to let it out at the middle
Schneider you don't have to
Board it when you go on vacation
Now
That probably doesn't for this week's news announcements let's go now to our
Voicemail
Remember that
Podcast hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Slade's wide variety of smart locks
Of your dreams
Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon and Apple products
What's Google Assistant
And more
Schlage.com iot
All right
You guys if you call us and leave us a voicemail he will be entered to win a Schlage
Lock
So
Give us a call before and we close this competition at
31st of March at midnight Eastern
Leave us your question baby will answer it on the air
Maybe we will
But I do I enter to win
And if you want to do this give us a call at 512-6237 for
To 4
This week's voicemail is from
Casey
Hey Stacy and Kevin
Circassian
Welcome uses
On the show
I'm receiving emails from Monoprice
I see things from their overtime
And I see that they have some kind of
Smart home home automation
I haven't really been able to find much information on it so
If you have a chance
Okay Casey I looked up this
Product
Bee Stitch by Monoprice and it sounds kind of good right you're like
Hey it's a hubless
Sensor thing
Sensor Network
Yay
The pricing is not unreasonable it's in Lima
With other devices
But my concern here
Is twofold one is Wi-Fi
Which means a lot of these sensors that you place around your house
Depending on how enthusiastic you get your going to have to change their batteries probably within six to eight months is
And that may be fine for one particular sensor but I'm going to tell you
When you have a bunch of these
Or if you have one another
Place where it goes off often
It's going to happen
Rapidly and you're going to get really
So that's why WI-Fi sensors I tend to
Billy just not go
So that's one part
I feel like the Grinch yourself
Think I'm the commissioner now
The other thing is
I don't know who makes this and
I don't like that
I don't like that there's not a lot of information
In here about the underlined platform
Provider
I don't see a lot about it
It's security efforts
Usually when I look for a product
Smart home product I try to
Google
The maker obviously
And I look for hay
Does it have a bug Bounty program
If there has been a vulnerability disclosure
How is it handled it
What other people say about how it handles it I look for information about a
Encryption I didn't see anything
I have some questions about
I thought overall security
Against you made
Those are kind of thoughts in
I also just looking at it
It got really terrible
And for the price I would recommend going with something
That maybe isn't Wi-Fi maybe do Abode that is a wonderful system
People love it
It's high performance
If you're focused mostly on security than do SimpliSafe
It's another option if you really want smart home automation efforts
SmartThings
Has a learning curve but it's pretty high quality
And Kevin if he were here would tell you
Hey there's always the wink
And I wouldn't especially type in on this thinking that
You're going to build it and it will work for a while
And now it's time to say goodbye to
Chris Chris thank you so much for hosting and
Just for our audience
Please
Can you tell me about the show you're doing with robots in San Francisco
Cuz I think they'll like it
I think they will too and thank you for letting me be a part of this day
It's always fun to chat with you Stacy I write for a publication called the spoon.
And I want two things that cover his food robot
And we are actually putting on a food robot conference
In San Francisco on April 16th is called articulate who got speakers from Sony Google Discraft
Robomart
Starship
Kiwi
Cafe X briggo from Austin
Again it's articulate on April 16th and San Francisco I highly recommend if you are at all interested in robots
These are all jammed with iot things to so you know
There's a business case for that day or for this audience
All right I will leave a
Lincoln the show notes
Again I am moving the day before otherwise I would be there
It sounds awesome
So
Steve Wilkos
Call and let me know how
Thank you Chris
Now stay tuned
Our Guest
Who is Bjorn block who is part of Ikea's
HomeSmart effort and he's going to talk about connected blinds
Their partnership
Sonos and a lot
All this after
Your message from our sponsor hey everyone we are taking a break from the internet
The things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor is a pharaoh and I have CEO
Joe Britt here to talk to
Hi Joe how are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing great how are you
Excellent so we talked in the past about
The bank of things in the work you guys did with Mitsubishi bank and we also talked about building a platform
Approach
Chayote
This week I'd like to talk to you about
Radios
But
First
I'd love for you to remind our listeners what it is that a pharaoh does
Acero provides an iot platform
Simplify
How you connect anything to the internet we can help you build
Business case as well and take you all the way to
Rollout and ongoing management
Maven data analytics
For whatever your connect
The product is
Our customers tell us that a pharaoh is the best choice
Sprint user experience
And developer productivity
It's also beautifully designed
Really easy to use
Fast
Very very secure
So down onto the radio
Recently I did an article that talks about combining bleh
And cellular on the same chip in the main point was that you could get to the internet through Bluetooth
And last week you actually made a pass a Brethren stew
Solution that your team
He created a
So what's your take
Bluetooth or
Specifically ble Bluetooth low energy is really interesting technology because
We've already got it and all of our smart
And you can probably guess from the name Lou energy it uses very little power so
You can build battery operated
Is that run for a long time but
Unlike
Networking Technologies such as
Is LTE or WiFi ble devices don't connect to the internet Direct
Play it on their own
They need to have some help you use a pharaoh
We provide
Technology in the form of
The software St
That you can embed in your mobile application
To enable
Pharaoh power
Ble device
To securely and automatically
Connect through whatever connection
Caesars mobile phone already has
What Pharaoh was really done is
Created a custom ble profile that not only ensures that
Secure connection
But also enables
Acero ble devices and gateways such as phones
To find each other
And set up internet
Connections automatically
This way
As your phone comes within range of these Sakura Pharaoh ble device
They will automatically form a connection back
To the internet
Using policies that are entirely set and governed by rules
Running in the cloud
We call a table for a fair of ele
That sounds a lot like what we talked about
When we talked about the bank of things idea
Let's talk a little bit about data piece of AI
Before we go please remind us where people can go to get more information
Sounds great Stacy
Arrow. IO
GoDaddy
Watch Big
Is the best place to start
If you're a developer
You can also check out
Developer.
A pharaoh.
And check out all the resources that we have on afera. IO
Hey everyone welcome to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Bjorn block
Who is
The business leader
Ikea Home Smart
He is returning to the show so how
Hi Stacy how are you I am great I am super excited to have you back and
We're going to be talking
Why it's so hard to sell connected devices at retail
And get a little bit more information on these blinds
When is super excited about
Let's start with the Kinect
Sublime's what was your vision there
But I think it's coming back to what we always do at Ikea Wheatley always start with the dilemmas
I'm trying to solve problem to make things better
That was really the starting point for our connected lines as well as well
Spotlighting
Are equate severe on and how to make people feel
Safe at home using using lighting
The journey started
Many years ago when Ikea actually on the
Norma blinds
Took away the street
Help with children and so on
Same day dental course you can have applications
Are you completely blind
If you don't have the strength to
To put it down
And that is a little bit of a problem at home
And coming together with us working with HomeSmart what we
The wireless
We can actually control things
Atwood
Adding the two and say why don't we start controlling the blinds
In a wireless
I need to reach them you can just use voice or use the app
Controlling
Journey together without fencing
Textile department at Ikea where
What they seek the old insights and knowledge that you need to know about
Rolling up and down the blinds will put it down the correct answer
And so on so it's
Publix we took it on as a Sears task and wanted to make sure that we don't something that is said
12 class and then the u16 status
Street tacos
I feel like when I visited Ikea about a year ago
I saw an early iteration of them and it was kind of very exciting for me because it was a huge Prada
The people have been demanding for a long time in the smart home space
And I'm curious what did you learn
Along the way
Have superheroes relief
Really fun having you in Alma Thomas Estates it was a privilege to
Show Yorkie and that's kind of hard to like Kia Soul. You have to come
And the connected lines
Associative starting with that
I shouldn't say simple tasks but at least a fairly commission will be want to touch it
If you going to
Dual Wireless blind there's no point having
Apollo Court
Because then you're
Norman string to pull them up and down you get the power cord
We learn from amanda initiativ stats
Taking away
Power chords it's a good way of making your home more beautiful
So we need to put the task and then
The challenge quite high in order to make them
Completely wireless so will therefore we also put the bar saying that they needed to be battery operated
We don't know
Do you know how big
Can you make
The power pack and how long should it last
How often do you need to recharge the battery because we don't want that disposable batteries
So we put the ball really high to make
Blind that works in many locations is super easy to install completely wireless
I bought some the control limits on the power perspective
Visa to recharge and so on so you continue to use it over and over and over again
A bit of a challenge of course
But right now
What we have learned
Again
Good-looking and I can't stop.
We're going to try to be stubborn about
Not letting go of a functionality and also not letting go
Leading with the lowest price sewing
We design the price tag
First reset the
Tri-City want to reach and saying this is what we think it's an important that we should achieve with this product
Both the functionality on the Aesthetics
Outsole
Market leader of coursing in Commonwealth
Affordable solution
Just for the audience these blinds
Are going to range from between
113 u.s. dollars to $181 US dollars and that's
Dependent on the wit
Correct that's correct
Excellent
Alright in the widest they're going to go is 76
Y'all so
It's a pretty big window
Dauin might guess
Is the reason you can't go bigger is because it's hard
For a battery-operated motor
The pull that much battery
Right
Yeah I think it's also for us
To to give ourselves a decent starting points in order to meet the masses in elections I'm pretty
Expand the range symbols
More expression Santander
More weeds
Variations as we move along
Debbie sing like a
A good ranged
2 * 20
Window sizes on the
The greatest tactical shotguns from from day one so yeah you're cracking up a little
I appreciate this in
For reference
If you guys want to just be like
I have automated Shades in my house and they cover a 10-foot wide window so it's very big
Much larger
Netspot
They cost 10000
Dollars
That is
Insane
And a lot of that was for the motor and because there wasn't a lot of competition in this
Space so
Yay Ikea
In the US you're doing the blackout Shades those are the I'm going to make you say it so everyone knows the proper way to say it
The future
How do you say
I was pretty good they call C2
Future
All right and then
You have the semi-transparent ones in those are like to me it looks like
Typical Ikea butcher
Consonance
It's a Wee Willie Europa glow Shalom school because the semi-sheer
Horsham Sunoco
Back at 1 which is 10 cold
Digital retailer
Target lowering prices
So we will see if you also open this up to USA
However we expanding
The range of connected lines in the US
This is not a technical question but as a person who has to live with blinds at my house
Do these come in different Fabrics
It only coming into Fabrics to start off with so they come in the in the in the block out on the semi share about again
We made
The solution we made it support scalable so we can build on this Ranch
Moving forward so I'm sure we could learn some in the first years outside so we can we can expand ourselves more expressions
Sound and color variations on and so on and so on
Okay so right now if you want smart blinds that are affordable
Your choice
Is Darkrai
Alright it's kind of like Henry Ford and his Model T
T4 little
All right
These are coming out in April
But you have had the tradfri lights
Out for
80 months to years a really long time it feels like
Internet of Things face
And I
Curious to hear what you've learned after having those on the market I know the last time we talked I was in a bit of a snit
Because my
Tradfri lights were not working well with my
Home assistance
I put them back
And there better now
Also that's
But what if you learned
Yeah you mentioned Appliance will be on Salem in April they will actually be on sale in Europe
Before summer time and day will it be on sale in US
In August
Disappointing August is a pig
But what if you learned
I think we're learning lost in the space and I think it's one thing that we have really
Taking all me now
In a serious manner East importance of having a system that is
Stable anambra boss does not fail on you when it comes to
Nativity Mendoza
It made some efforts in order to improve the
The trophy Aspen and experience without the making sure that it
Safeway
Work to ensure that we stay in compliance
I mean working with
Amazon Apple and Google
We need to make sure that
Doc user experience is also to the best possible that you take two
Constantly make sure that this is what needs to be but
Of course the beauty of working with
Food product that is
Is a life that you have to take care of any proven and bites lice all the time so I think we are super excited
We are also taking it in a very serious way
Okay in French
Kiss from a business perspective
How does the tribe free product line
In terms of employees and people working on the project has it stayed relatively consistent to
Because as you mentioned it's alive so I'm
Very curious how that's changed how you
Port and
Maintain that purses
I don't know
The mom
Dressers or
That's a good question of course our heritage is our
Conventional Furniture pieces
Furniture Airport
Coworkers in the stores and Ambien customers
Fortis want to relate to our
It's good products so far
So there you have it
A pretty steep learning curve and also how we are
Putting resources behind our
All connected products
So I think what you will see
Looking at this as we are investing by traveling to this face and we of course want to put more
More efforts on and make our safe solution better in the stores we want to educate that we staff
Want to get a customer support
Learning a lot right now and it is a space that just been identified as being really important for Ikea moving forward
So a my last trip
Through the IKEA store which was only
Only a week ago
I noticed that I had a hard time finding
The tradfri light
And I wondered if
There was a reason behind
That and I asked because
I saw a Bluetooth speakers prominently to
Displayed also in the last few months we also saw
Lowe's
Take out their Iris
Smart home platform
And prior to that we've seen
Tons of retailers
Try and then just
Hoback
On smarthome in iot things so I feel like
Maybe we don't know how to sell this well yet or what's happened
It's not that we are trying to hide a name and it's all three lights are on is not lighting the stores.
In the car but we are building up
The rain should wear building off the retail solution it takes a little bit of time in the
Ikea Machinery to get everything sorted
After summer I'm sure you will see some really good Improvement in a
Store nearby you because we are launching you
Eureka concert pole for the smart home arena
After summertime
Started with a big sound
Together with the complete smart home solar
I'm really excited about this and I'm pretty confident that we would have them
Ace that can be encouraged to
Amtrak
Play with the products and also learn a lot to buy
Enjoy your sin in the starting lineup
Okay it sounds like
You don't want to tell me too much more about
But can you give us any hints about
What's some of the issues that
You guys had seen and are trying to solve
I think they are being reminded every now and then
Getting the day fixing place in a sentence on the way saying when I went to speakers
Bluetooth speaker for accomplish
Is turned on
We sent twice as many
Amedisys
Simple us. That people want to interact and see and touch and feel
The greatest compliment that we have
I could webpage son and a good eCommerce solution.
The touching feeling playing around in the
Neglected
It's really important to have that
And I think that's what we are male excited about that we can desecrate the space
So are you able to play with the blinds table
Symphonic speakers and pinyin
See what
Capable of playing what type of music
Okay and we've talked about them now
For a while. You guys have a partnership coming up with Sonos where you're going to be releasing
Much
Anticipated speaker
And that's going to also happen in August
Account disabled start is in August
They will be safe
North America same time but we are having a big
Launch event in April in the Bronx
This year so
That's what we really going to reveal in first to the public which is going to be very fond of course
Can you tell me anything more about the speaker
Should I cook my dinner
I wish they could bust
Innocence of collaboration with
So much fun and the such a good journey from from day one.
We literally reached out to
To take the next step in
In creating atmosphere we had that
Quite a few insights about what it is to create atmosphere at home
People we talked to Rich
Should do quite a lot of the year with you quite a few people
59% of those two
Music is the number one factor
Creating atmosphere
So having smart Lighting in place or at this grasping up on we thought it was
I needed that we also took on the task of the
Having
Music and Sound
In order to do that then
We reached out to Sonos
And the same thing was said when we did reach out to them
The other day
Maybe they would like to reach out to Ikea that work with us
Okay let's see so far you guys have
Connected lights so you have connected blinds
We're going to see
The partnership with the Sonos / speakers
And that's all about creating this this atmosphere
We've also seen I introduce wireless charging
You guys have embraced
Connectivity and Technology where it seems to make sense in the home
Where do you think you'll go neck
We know where we going next
But I think it's more to say I think that the luxury we have on
Being home smart
Reading Ikea
History of Acts
To every rule
And I think this is really a luxury in this space.
Dictated to a certain space or a certain activity we can actually
Nothing to whatever activity or scenario or identify a big nose
Most important elements in Life
Right now it's very lucky
Keep hiding in fear being working with lighting and shadows of darkness and
Sliding in
Sound of Music 2
Of course Ruston
Next step is a course to start combining the two but you know when you really can get the the scenes going with
Appliance of the music and the lighting and everything in in harmony
Thing that we are
What comes after summer time and work with Dustin and also release set of course
To the greater area stuff we will enter after that then turns off
Today we have to
To keep your eyes and ears open for that moving help but we are definitely serious about the categories
Orbitz Amsterdam
Okay I didn't make my guess which is actually you're going to go into Wellness
One because I feel like we talked about into
Prepping for this interview I read about your air-purifying curtain concept
That just blew me away
And I think that actually indoor air quality
And health and wellness we're seeing a bunch of come
Companies
Head that direction
That's just me you don't have to answer
Guys if I'm kidnapped this is
Because I guessed Ikea secret plan to help us all get better
Alright thanks so much for
For coming on the show today that's it for this week thanks so much
Search for listening and remember if you'd like more I sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Jd.com will see you next week