Hey everyone welcome to the 220 first episode of The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin and we have a rocking chair
Today
80s disc jockey voice their we're going to be talking about the new thread protocol
We got
A Google Assistant
For the
Office
With real estate Giant jll
We've got dish introducing a smart home service
It got some bad news on the Samsung smart
TV front
And
We've got some security updates that we should talk
Talk about 4
OT
Tons of news we've got
Medical device testing from
IPhone
We have a new homekit outlet
And
We have some speculation about the Galaxy home and an update on those Ikea smart
If we have time we're going to get to a lawsuit
Kids voices on the Amazon Echo
And
You'll hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies talking about
Edgex Foundry
Plus
Our Guest this week
Is
Schneider Electric CIO
Elizabeth haakenson
And she's going to talk about how the energy management firm
Handles the itot Divide
Plus
How it thinks about cybersecurity
All of this awaits you in just a few moments but first
IMessage from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is Nordic semiconductor
Are you planning to build a product using cellular iot technology
Check out the NRF 9160
It's the most advanced multimode cellular iot device in the market today it supports the two cellular stand
Standards for iot applications
Lte-m
And narrowband iot
A single device
It also supports up to 15 LTE bands making it truly globally compatible
It also has on-chip GPS which makes it ideal for any asset tracking and monitoring a
Application
Bus application power and security come in the form of arms latest cortex and 33 CPU
An arm's trustzone security
With one megabyte of Flash and 256 GB of RAM
They're integrated RF front ends and adaptive Power Manager dsip
The NRF 9160 is your first consideration when designing cellular iot
Tea products so find out more at www
. Nordic semi
Dot-com
Slash 9160
Heart rate
Heaven
First off I have to tell everybody I am now in my home studio on Bainbridge Island
Yay yay
All the craziness is now behind me
Some of the craziness is still ahead of me
Such a setting up my smart home
Work so you can expect to hear more
About all of that
Probably in the next week or two
People have asked about that previously before you
I think you just
Mention last week when you miss the most
I did and yes
But it is not the first thing
I think what I took out all the stuff I realized
How much moving a smart home
Process of moving impact
Singing organized most
I'm sitting here looking at my boxes of
Surface word
But I don't want to set it up right
Rent rent
Anyway let's start the show with
Updates on
Read this is
Great news
It's big news
Thread is a wireless radio protocol
The things that you would need to know about thread is it
It is IPv6
Compatible which means you can go straight up
And it is low power
So this is a network that competes with things like zigbee Bluetooth
Z-Wave
We talked about it before what's exciting about it is actually a whole new protocol just for the Smart Home
The folks at Nest Samsung
Deep bands
And a couple other companies
Designed it several years ago
And we've been waiting for it to like really take off
It really has
And with red
1.2 this is their latest version of thread they've done three things
They're really
Interesting
So first off
They've been working on this for 3
Little longer
I think the first thread device or capable device I saw was the original Google
Onhub router
Oh wow yeah that
You still have that
That I do not I replace with a regular Google Wi-Fi
Just kidding
I'm so excited for you
But no
Nope
Okay
So let's talk about this
Three main things that thread 1.2
It is
Lowering the power requirement
So it extends the battery life of iot
Yay it puts it in the same
World is Bluetooth
The other thing it's done
Is a credit extensions for Bluetooth low in
Which means
That this protocol will work over Bluetooth radios
This means that if you have a Bluetooth bass device as a note on your network
You can actually have it talk to your
Sprint network
Provided
There's another note
Thread Network that speaks
That sounds really complicated
But it's actually not
No it's kind of like if you have a fax machine need to
Have somebody else that has a fax machine to or you can use it that makes sense to me
The real question is
Is it backwards compatible with existing Bluetooth devices on the mortgage
It is
No new hardware required
You're probably going to have to have a firmware update list
You've got like a brand new device
Got a chip that already has a firmware in it but
It will work with your old Bluetooth stuff
Bluetooth low energy
This is
Cool what it can do is if you have maybe a Bluetooth sensor for example and you wanted to work with your
Thread based air conditioning or your threat
Lights
It will actually
Become part of that Network so that sensor could easily communicate
With those lights
Yay
Awesome
Yeah it is awesome
And then the other thing that they've done is
They call it commercial extension
Chance and there's two things they did he
The first part is they've made it
Possible to have
Larger networks of thread device
Places to thread Taps out
An individual Network at around 300
Devices is kind of
The General
Which is a lie
Yeah it's plenty for a home but not forsake an Enterprise
Right word
It's a really big hug
I'm like
I'm kind of surprised I mean I have like
My other house did you get there
Butera my current house has no light bulbs there are no light bulbs in this house it's really weird
Summer jobs don't have a
Almost none of my Tinder
Yeah I don't know what that is
What has a head a t light
So I can see if you had like
80 Light Bulbs Plus temperature sensors and all these other things
And you had a larger house that I had
You could probably get to
The point is
Now you're not limited by that what happens is
They created like a virtual overlay so
A
Physical Network
Thread devices
Talk to
The router
And you can join them
Up with another physical one so
When you're talking to like that
IP addresses you can actually address
All 700 or all however mininet
Works you have as one Unified
So
Many networks now look like when
That's very
And then
This is the
Somebody
They've added enterprise-grade lifecycle device management
So
In the home when I connect a thread device I do QR code why do some
That right
In the Enterprise that is stupid
Because
You don't want everybody to be able
How to add devices
So they've tied in with Cisco
Some other open protocols to give you admin
Rights for
Commissioning and decommissioning
Devices
That's probably a lot quicker to I wouldn't want to be going around in Enterprise and scanning a QR code for every single device that I was trying to
Choi
Can you imagine like having a good day
Efficient
Where's the QR code
So that's what threads done
And to provide some context here
To me this looks like a continual
Want to say
Retrenchment is
The smart home isn't going where we all kind of hoped it
We go
It is becoming
Much more locked into these Fender ecosystems built
Voice assist
Silence
And the wireless protocols that we were like I'll be open and cool and everything will talk to each other that's not
So it makes sense that thread would say
If we want to remain relevant we got to go to
Verizon Bluetooth is actually
Dummy
Did there still fine in the
And everywhere else but they've also made of
Branch out in
Price
So
That's I guess the context you
Yeah I've always looked at it from the smart home perspective cuz I've been out of Enterprise for 15 years
I've been waiting to see
Some thread implementation
At the device level that would be make me go wow this is awesome got to have it and haven't seen that yet
But again that you said
Everything's going Wi-Fi Bluetooth
Silo digital assistant
So
In automatic
So hopefully
We hear about soon some
Rehabilitation
In the threat group has like osram and Zeidman's they're actually they join the Border
So
You know this isn't crazy
It makes a lot of sense +
Unlike zippy
Which is it doesn't go out to
CB is very popular
In the Enterprise
It's not IPv6
Compatible so you still have to make that
Next
Where is thread is
So
It'll Tire Lake lighting system
Some directly into
You know what we're going to get all the haters now because they always say you're always
Disinfecting and we're not doing that
It's just a technical limitation that some people
Can't work with
Yeah I mean
I'm not dissing
I have no
Feelings whatsoever
Positive or negative
So you thread the one other piece of news that they released this week
Switch on the smart home side is interesting is
Lutron has joined the
Thread
Word
So yeah but which I enjoyed the thread group supported Iraq
And
The first thing I thought was
Holy mackerel
What's going to happen to Lucia
Proprietary protocols
Which
Clear connect
And then
Fancier larger
Professional installations they have
Radio raw 2
And
I don't know I reached out to Lutron they have
Have not gotten
But I will also as a hint
Say that
Recently they released the Aurora product
Which works with
JPay
Which is the same radio that
Runs over
They released this product that
Hold your light switch open
For your hue light bulbs that works with a hue light bulb system using
So I saw that was like Hey That's not using Lutron
Interesting
And now it's loose when turning
Do I think they totally ditch their proprietary protocol
Probably not
But
I like the fact
I thought they might be working more broadly with a more open today
Stick on kind of clamps
Right yeah it's a round dimmer switch that
You screw it it's
It's like tension mounted
Screw it
Onto your
Lights
Switch but there's no wiring
It's $40
I actually have it in front of me in the second I get my Hue bulbs in which is going to happen this weekend
Can I test this out so weak
We can all see
Yates by the way that only works with the toggle
Switches that stick out for them
Yeah traditional light switch
Warrant wine
Okay
Well it's okay you won't see that you won't see the old ugly light switch anymore
That's true you see a beautiful dimmer switch
Okay
Let's talk about more enterprisenews
Man this is exciting
Jll which is a
Real estate
Behemoth
They've teamed up with Google Assistant to create a smart assistant
Four offices
So this is like
Asking hey assistant is the conference room open
And getting an answer
This is
Dick Amazon is working with other companies to try to bring
Listen to businesses so is Microsoft with Cortana that's actually where
Are most likely to Secor
Cortana succeed
And lo and behold Google's just like sweat. In
And made this work
Yeah and I remember when I used to work at Google I go into the New York City office once a week
We didn't use
Google Assistant
Carpenters and such
It was an automated
System
Using the Google Calendar what not you could search
Say find me a room from
This time this time it's open
I'd like to have
Video whiteboard or video calling whatever
And the system will just do it I mean
Basically they had everything
There but the voice capability right
So
I'm not surprised at that Google is the want to do this today probably didn't take much effort to extend what they already have
Yes indeed jll they managed offices
Like we said their system is called Jill
Of course it is in there because I have been given to understand that you really were
Want a double or triple syllable word is your voice assistant
Because it's harder to
It's easier for the AI to differentiate
Which I have to say hey Jill
Hey Jill
Book me up
Okay don't butcher my
Kevin can handle a lot of my singing
All right
So that you're a bad singer it's what you're doing to the world
Yeah okay
This is on your smartphone this is not actually on a physical device in the room
Just yet
This is
Download the app
But it does bring in stuff
You would normally
I need to do like Hayes
Are these deaths Abuela
Book me a task if
Hot desking
Place
I like the fact that even though it runs on Google Cloud on the back that's obviously using
Google
It doesn't just integrate with G Suite calendars it also will integrate with Microsoft 365 which is obvious
The Behemoth of
Activity Suites
It is it the Kraken of office
Sweets
Yes
So they're trying this out with customers one of the first customers is going to be
Procter & gamb
My Hope Is
I actually
Reached out to the jll team
How people are actually using this
If
People are actually
So hopefully that will happen
All right
Moving right along
Dish
The satellite company satellite TV is
They have launched a smart
Home Services Unit
And they're going to basically come in and help
Set up your smartphone
They will be working with Nest ring
Linksys
Rio 2
And a couple audio companies
Comcast has been doing this for a while AT&T and Verizon both started these business units but they
Actually backed out of them so Comcast is only one I know if it's doing it right
Indeed
Diospi space
I don't see this as a big Market I think that's why
The others were already in it at scaled-back so surprised at this is doing this
There are definitely people who just like you to hate 7-Eleven
But I don't think it's a large percentage of people because the products these days
Pretty easy to set up
Yes
And
Are we still going to do what the Amazon
Guided for you and like
What kind of routine is Yuan
Richest device setup
For like
Routines
And that sort of thing
Okay
So and I will say
You may not be aware of the
Does Kevin butt dishes
Shed
They have not done it yet
But they are said they're going to launch an NB iot
So
Yeah I could see that and it would tie into this yes
They're vying for the Spectrum from
T-Mobile Sprint
If it was to get together and have to divest some things
Even look at the Boost Mobile
Investment as well so
Yeah okay
I don't know if this is going to be huge but you also a man think about like alarm.com has done
Pretty good job building
A smart phone capability as well now they offer the devices
Exact services
Sodus Vivint
So yeah it's
I don't know I mean
I think there is a market
For this sort of thing
I don't know how big it is I think there's lots of little independent
Companies that was won in Austin
Smart House
H o u
Smart home systems
4 people and I
Actually think there's
There's a tiny
I don't know the scale but I think it feels more like a Consulting
I agree
But we'll see
Let's talk security
Because OMG
The world went nuts
This week
Because they noticed
Because Samsung
Told them
Samsung tweeted something that will read word for word in a second
Potentially that the Tweet witch
Is really interesting in and of itself
So I don't have any Samsung Smart TV that I have you do
I do not
I'm sure some of our listeners to
So this is the Tweet that's Samsung support USA Center
Scanning your computer for malware viruses is important to keep it running smoothly
This is also true for your qled TV if it's connected to Wi-Fi
Prevent malicious software texting your TV
Scanning for viruses
Is on your TV every few weeks
Here's how
That's
Not smart Samsung
So I think a lot of people if they saw that tweet we're like
Why do they send it I could have viruses on my
Sure you could
So and yes
Smart TVs are in Notorious place for
Pirates SB
Because they're not up to
Some people might be like gay Samsung pointing out that there's fire the antivirus
I don't think we want to live in a future where are connected devices are so badly engineered
We have to run virus scan
Yeah
Enter
Samsung Smart TVs run Samsung tizen
So it's not a platform to talk about offense it's probably not a platform that really is
Attacked all that much either because I should know it was attack remember they had like
40 security vulnerabilities in
Because Samsung originally wanted everything
Right that's right
That's right I do recall that
That was for about 2 years ago
I haven't heard about it since then that's kind of why I was like
But you're right it wasn't engineer with security in mind I would say
Yasso
When we're doing our Sonos I just put this on the show that says this is a bad fuse
This is a future I don't want
But
For me
I don't
Connect my TV to the internet I instead use a Roku and connect it to the internet via real
I also
Another option here
It would help is I know I've been skeptical
That maybe this sort of thing will change my
Is having a connected
Service that
Monitors are
And says hey did you know your TV is sending Dobbs of data
Not just when it's on but to weird places
Malaysia I'm so glad you said that because
I'm hoping we're going to review a product that will help with that
Want to get into right now but I'm looking for something along those lines and we stumbled upon one
Earlier this morning
You should just tell people what it is
Excited
Look at themselves
Now I don't
Oh you're such a tease
I'll tell people cuz I
It's called the firewalla
Yes and I think it was
Cisco people to put it together it
To be honest it's like a consumer derivative of something like that you could do on your own with a Raspberry Pi if you wanted to
Silversmith plug-and-play and you have to worry about
Setting up your figuring coating etcetera
But it does
Many things I'm one of the thing says yes it's monitoring where your traffic is going from all your devices
So something like that could help and then you could be like
Holy cow it's time to run virus scan
And get rid of those on my
Ideally
If you're going to make something smart you need to make acid
Secure as well
I didn't know you were set top.box person
Yeah I mean I've been a core cutter forever and
Same here same here I use to Android TVs
Nvidia Shield or iWatch directly on my Chromebook
I do have both a Fire TV stick and a Chromecast but we actually don't use them
We're pretty simple we only have one TV in our
House
I'm not going to tell you how many we have how many strings are here
Well you know I guess we
Peking watch
Amazon Echo Show
Okay
Let's talk about other security
Kevin
TPM
TPM trusted platform module and I said this
Adderall 5 times in the last 2 years
I want trusted platform module in my iot devices
Why do I want that
Because
The same reason I have them and want them in my Chromebooks that I did was praise she should tell people what it is
Trusted platform module
So basically it is a specific chip although I think it can be implemented
Coprocessor
And I say I'm thinking yes
Yes
Either way
It's an Authentication
Basically
It has cryptographically stored keys
That
Protect your device from having say the
Operating system Flash without your knowledge or tweak without your knowledge where maybe a virus could
Actually say wet install this routine and get all the information from your computer
Behind the scenes
What does several
Things are very low-level but at a high-level it protects your device from being
Change without your knowledge purification systems of the yes
This is working as intended is not an acid cetera
Got it
So I'm curious because
In the world of can
Computing arm
For example has a trusted
At The Trestle
And they have that actually on microcontroller switches
One of the challenges of these types of
Devices that don't work
No resource
Devices so things with microphone
Controllers without
And so
Arm has had something and they brought it down to the MCU
And
Nxp in a couple other microcontroller makers are now implementing
So you can buy these
I wonder if there's a difference though with the trust in zone because I think like to the iPhone where they have the trusted Enclave for your finger
My understanding I can very well be wrong is that doze
Zones
AR for storing
Protective
Data not for verifying the system
Has or hasn't been compromised
So trust so
It will run a check
To make sure
It's basically a Sandbox to run
Secure
Program so you can run an app
In that area so you can load the app in that area
And nothing can modify
Okay so there is a slight difference in please a TPM is
It's not a Sandbox it doesn't run app verifies like the BIOS
Okay so then that sounds like
I just read about it
And they don't do it on a processor side they do it on the flash memory size
Which is
When is something gets in over the air update
For example
It checks it and says
Hey this is actually fun
Right way to use Etc
Does it have signed keys
And is it trying to change some
Something
Mission Beach
Change
So that happened but that's on the memory size
So I think
I agree with you
I think we have to be a lot smarter to
Figure out the proper
Mechanism
To do this
But I'm with you
We do need this sort of
Functionality
Yeah it's me it's it's not going to protect my iot data it's not going to stop something from sending data somewhere else
Right
Is malicious prevent someone from trying to take over your
Your device
We're all in agreement
Unsure
The right
Do it
Imagine
Everybody's going to have a slightly different take
But feel free to talk to us if you're smarter than this
Cuz we're working our way through it
Slowly but surely
All right let's do some quick news bits
Kevin iPhone camera
IPhone camera so a paper
By the Royal Society of chemistry
Is coming soon get ready yet
They demonstrate the use of an iPhone
And thin-film Jamaica
Spectrometer
Spectrometry sensor
Okay
Yes
So basically what they're doing is they're using the Flash
I have an iPhone and it's thin
Film
Hold some type of
Bodily fluid or DNA Etc
And what they can do is
Literally performance
Imma treat analysis
On the iPhone with it
I was kind of cool
It is cool
Another update is on Ikea blinds we had talked to your block who's head of the
Ikea
Smart home efforts
He told us that these smart blinds that were also excited about
Is there going to be cheaper and
From Ikea
Those are delayed
And they were going to be out in August
They're still going to be out in August in Europe but in the US we're going to see
October 1st
Launch date
And yet still cool
All right we still we still don't have a price on those two
We don't
I think if they're going to be about a hundred
Okay and it depends on the size
What about this homekit
Can I look for you I'll get folks you can now
Jewelsmart
Outlet
From Hitachi and I don't know if I'm saying that correctly
It's
Just like any other smart home Outlet it's a dual plug so you turn one of your
Plugs into
Two outlets
And then you can control
Tyson application because it's
Obviously it's WiFi
Apple
That is true
I see a price it is
T999 which sounds like a lot for Smart Eye leopard again
You kind of getting to outlets
In that one device
Alright and hey
Bixby is it bad
Was it ever here
Specifically the Galaxy home
The fondue pot speaker with Bixby built in
Oh yeah that's yeah the Galaxy home oh yeah they announce that what are you
It's still not for sale
It still isn't but rumor has it that Samsung will be debuting its next
Galaxy Note 10
On August 7th in New York invited not going out but The Insider scoop is that
August 7th is the date
I am going to predict we finally see the Galaxy with a ship date
Where the price
And probably a little baby Galaxy home because I've been SEC filings for something
Smaller and smaller fondue pot
Kind of like the
Echo mini or the
Like a warm case of chafing dish
There you go exactly one chip at a time
Thank you Bixby
Awesome alright we
Try that or not
I have no I don't know if anybody will at this
All right and then find a little bit of news Amazon is being sued
Privacy violations
Kids
This is actually something we've
Talked about in the
Switches
The children's online protection and something something
Privacy Act
Privacy.
Privacy protection
Protection and Privacy Act
Prevents
Japanese from Gathering data from children under the age of
And
A long time ago when I had my echo device I was like hey
Recording my daughter's voice she is not yet
That feels like Batman
I like that
The FTC actually did a
Noted like a year maybe
A year-and-a-half ago that said
We're not super worried as long as your
Selling that
But
Two lawsuits were filed
Last week in Seattle
All that said
Hey you know what this is a problem
And it's a problem for a couple reasons
They basically said that Amazon is
Recording all of these boys
Friends of Children
And
That's not
Cool it's without their consent or the consent of
Their parents
They are saying that Amazon's privacy policies
Isn't this is the important thing
Sing to me that say if you use the Amazon
Echo device
And talk to madam
M a
You're basically
Consenting
To this
Privacy
If you don't accept it you may not user
But
The lawsuit is saying
In the you here because this is a device that's in a household
Are all people in the household
Consenting to this
No
Probably not
Which is kind of interesting because
I often consent to privacy policies on behalf of my entire home
And you know
I can see my husband being
No
So
And what about guess what about people just come over to your house
Yeah
I never thought of that
To be honest from the consent stand for
Yeah I mean it's a mean if you have like my mom
She is very privacy
She does not like
My house she actually will walk through my house like
Turning off the mic
Even though she knows she's like
Physical kill switches
There's a lot of meat here in this lawsuit and
You know it's worth
Look at the following song
Put them in there
Aaron's
That's this weekend iot news
But think it's time to go to our voicemail what do you think
I do and even though it's the middle of June we actually have to go back a month
We got a winner for May
Yes we forgot the May winner partially because we had pre-recorded an episode
It doesn't matter
We still have a prize for
Are winner gets a Schlage
Lock
Yay
In the May winner was
Lynn and we actually answered his question last week Solin
Not only did you get your question
Congratulations question to what's her most underrated smart home function feature Etc
It was
And this month
What's iot podcast hotline
Is sponsored by a pharaoh
With the fifth largest iot patent
Portfolio on the world Affair o provides a
The Proven iot
Platform bed
Doesn't risk your brand
A pharaoh customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction and time-to-market
Antennax higher activation
You learn more at a pharaoh
Dot IO
And I'm going to encourage everyone to
Call in
Enter to win the wise
Sensor kit
And a camera
Lee's
Call us at 512-623-7424
And ask us your question
And now it's time for this week's
Question
Witches from Jeff
Let's hear it
Hi Stacy and Kevin
The question is
Longest wait is was cuddling on the counter and
Clever and make sure that you know Amazon order
Make targets music
Exporting answering keep up the great work
Turquoise Adidas on the Shelf thank you
So we got this question like once every 6 months and I love this question because it kind of confirms what I've been saying we have to
Too many smart speakers in the house cluttering up every single
Would you can do something about that Jeff as you said you know you asked if they're ceiling mounts are any lights
There are several ceiling mounts available for either
Echo dots
Home Minis
Witcher similarly-sized what did you have to buy the proper amount for it
I'm not going to recommend one because there's so many to choose from on Amazon
They're all run around 15 to $18 each
It doesn't look too difficult to install in fact
Some people that would recommend these two if
That'll get your speaker out of the way
Up in the ceiling
If you want if you don't feel like installing anything for about the same price
There's a couple vendors on Amazon that also make
Plug-in modules that you literally
It's a mount system and you mount your
Smart speaker small smart speaker to the wall essentially you plug this into an outlet and your speaker sits on top of it and it's plugged in
So that way you don't have cords all over either and it's out of the way
You good
As far as other devices with smart speakers that can remove the traditional ones
I know Stacy you tried the first alerts the smoke detectors that have died
Marinade
Pretty sure they're working on it I can see you after I said Google Assistant as well
Yes so the First Alert smoke detectors they're expensive they're like $200
Is there a smoke detector
It sounds really good it actually has an amazing speaker in there
And they mount to your ceiling
Exactly where
Your old smoke detector
Here's my issue
If you want just to talk to her and you don't want it to play music
This is a good option but a lot of the devices like I've had met him inside light switches
Thermostat with Madam inside
It's weird the placement is not ideal for a lot of pee
Bee stings for like listening
Music
My thermostats are
Come to the back of a hallway
Even your smoke detectors are in a
Weird spot
Ring sometime
They're not in the middle of the sea
Not going to be full Fidelity sound there
If you're just wanting to talk to it then yes it is
It's totally fine but
Sometimes it's a little weird having your light switch play music
Your mileage may vary
He may not care about sound quality maybe like this is totally sufficient
Get rid of stuff on my
Chosen
Places it's all out there for
The one caveat I will say with a lot of these devices
You want to check to see which Amazon services are
Example the First Alert does not support the newest amazon echo
That's kind of common with third-party implementations of these voice services
Now that's typically the newest features come to
Name brand eat the ones made by Amazon her by Google Etc
Eventually a lot of them filter down to third parties but not always
Yeah like some of the smart light switches and I think my
Ecobee
Thermostat doesn't play me
Right
Timothy
Vector
Which does have met him a built-in that you can get one pretty cheap since the company is
Perfect for turning lights on or asking the weather isn't such but I wouldn't play music
Actually
Which is a shame cuz you know DJ Roomba
He does dance if you're asking
All right
I feel like we're moving off now that we're talking about
What robots can do
Let's call it quits for this segment of the show I'd love for you to stay tuned because I have Elizabeth haakenson
Who is the CIO Schneider Electric
This is a
25 billion Euro company
She's talking about their steps to do a digital transformation The itot Divide
Ian
So there's a lot of meat to this
Please stay tuned for that
And in the meantime here's a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Where is Dell Technologies and I have
Hendel's
The general manager of Dell Technologies industry iot
Iot safety answer
Security
And computer vision
That is a lot of titles
So what is your business exactly
Excited to be here and sponsor this second
First people on the podcast probably know that
Surveillance cameras
For over 20 years
Don't be a sensor to become much more intelligent
Much more capable are driving a lot
This is requiring a customer
Look at 6
Security in a very new paradigm
Insecurities
And also wanted to integrate this video
Iot data
They wanted to apply analytics to make better decisions
This is happening
All about customer service
Oliver cast
It's a real challenge that we have right now
A few months ago Dell Technologies lunch the Dell Technologies iot solution for surveillance
He told me that this solution can handle
Some enormous use cases
I believe you got one customer with over 250000 cameras
And another who is dealing with
100 in
20 petabytes
A video store
That is an enormous amount of
Cameras and data
How has the solution changed
From the time that you've launched
We started with those complex cost
Bat size range
Challenges
Density of cameras and not quantity
Storage want to stop there
Downtobuck smaller system
What customers still have complexities and deployment
Envoy management life cycle management of all that begins
10 days.
Just 30 days
Years
Make it easier more scalable
Technology and Storage
That's what all right
Who would benefit most
From this type of
What great things about today
Security data
That affects everybody
It doesn't matter if your hospital
School stadium
Assateague
Enterprise customer
Frances oldest technologies that is a quart
Address problems
Regardless of the customer type
But really where customers need a very supportable
Scalable
Secure solution to the boy named it surveillance at scale
Great so can wear kinfolks
Let's go to learn more about Dell Technologies
And the iot solution for survey
PlayStation 4 second time
Solutions for bringing the market.com
Everyone welcome back to the internet
Out of things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And today's guest is Elizabeth haakenson
Who is the CEO of Schneider
Hello Elizabeth how are you today
I'm great how are you Stacy
I am fantastic
So let's start with Schneider Electric
Tell us a little bit
About
Because it is
It is huge
It does a lot of different things
How should we do
Electric is a global company
And we're leading the digital transformation of energy management and automation
Across
Multiple Market
Which include industry powerbuilding
Stata Center in other infrastructure
Projects
We have
Over a hundred thirty thousand employees
In more than
100 countries
We had 25.7
Billion Euro in Revenue in 2018
And we spend about five
Percent of our Revenue devoted
To R&D
All right and what I want my audience to understand is Schneider Electric is kind of the original
OT type
Accompanied
This is a company that makes
Circuit breaker should make building management software these are people who are dealing with
Gott's
A buildings and
They don't necessarily take kindly
Thai tea
So that's why you're on this week
And I wanted to ask you first
How do you view your role
Is a CIO
When we're in the midst of this big digital transfer
Ayo for quite some time now I would say it's probably one of the most
Exciting times
To be a CIA
Even the digital transformation because it doesn't matter what industry that you are in
Your customers are what countries are located in we're all experienced
And seeing the benefits
Digital Technologies in so as CIO it's really important to get
Close to your customers and your business peers and determine how best
We go on
Digital Journey
Together and depending upon the company or with some cios are actually the one
Leading
The company
Digital efforts and then there's like Schneider
It was so big and we have so much going on with digital that two years ago the company
Decided to create a new rule called the chief digital officer
And Reporting into that role
Are folks like me
Myself she is the chief data officer
Other
Levels at the at the sea level
Who are also focusing on
Customer experience
Car services experience
So we're really a
Collection
Individual
To have deep experience and everything
From marketing service R&D
It security all coming together
Under the chief digital officer
Umbrella
To help lead the digital transformation
The company
Other companies do it could be very different from that in and asking either a CTO or
Ciot
Digital transformation but here we have a much broader scope of individuals working together to drive the tree
Information
That's why it's with a hundred thirty thousand people I can't imagine trying to
Change the course of that ship so
Makes a lot of sense
So in the role of CIO I'm really curious because we talked a lot about in these digital transformations
There's an itot divide and that's the
IT staff
An operational staff
You talked about it as a convergence which I think is totally Act
Can you talk a little bit about how that is working inside Schneider Electric as you guys undergo this digital
Transformation
As you mentioned we believe I can OT is about a convergent
And not a divided although it may be some who continue think that way
When cyber security started to become
More and more of a concern
Accompanies we realize that as we began
Take these traditional OT devices that didn't connect
2 to the internet and now do connect to the internet that's with B
Acronym of all your tears we realize that
There was no longer
The separation
Between OT and it they now we're going to begin to be on the same network communicate
Did together
Different types of
Systems that might be in factories excetera so it's blinking really be Enterprise
Systems to the systems that were contained in the past
But saying factories for example
So which is Convergence
We found that
More started to come into the IT realm or even to the CIO because
Many of our colleagues
Let's say here in plants and factories
Dismiss early pay a lot of attention to systems in the past most of what they use for self
Contained and all of a sudden they have their systems being exposed to the internet which means that they are now.
Vulnerable potentially for a Cyber attack
So I would say that the it organization and
Has been managing
Cyber-security for
Hazard enterprise system
I've been on the internet for you know at least a decade is not war we were very knowledgeable and aware
Of the different
Security practices that you would need only from access control but also different uses of software
To protect from cyber-attacks
So this convergence
For us
Schneider
Probably easier
Then maybe others
Just you two are
Extensive
It footprint not only in our offices but also within our plants in our factories
And I'm curious because when I go and visit plants and factories and I talked to them about security
I feel like a lot of these operationally focused individuals
They have
Wonderful training
And they have things like OSHA rules are ISO rules that they have to follow for security and safety
And I look at that and I think
Hey a lot of times that's sort of training and probably documentation would be actually really X
Excellent in the IT world and we don't have things like that
Go out maybe to all of the employees for example
And I'm curious maybe what are the best practices each side could take from each other to improve security
I would say that it's a partnership
Speak about
Our company because that's the one I'm I'm closest to on the subject in the gentleman who leads our
Supply chain
His team and I would say the chief
Digital officer
Teams
We are very tightly coupled as well as our chief
Information
Security officer so
We look at the group's working hand-in-hand
So while we certainly will I Upon Our plants in our distribution center
To implement the nist standards and framework
For cyber-security you know obviously we're always willing
To learn
And in fact
The way we look at protecting our FAQ
Factories in our distribution centers is with an individual from the global
Who is coming from
More of the safety background
In the plant
And we're we're merging
Viewpoint the best of both
Operational best practices as well as it in cyber best
And I do believe that
The pace at which we are moving and implementing
Our plans
Is phenomenal
I know I talked to a lot of other cio2 Vikings are still trying to figure out maybe the the division
Between the organizations and what we decided to do and I think it was just part of
The wave
Some of the leaders are we took down all the higher keys and and the different lines between us
And we realized that we were better working together than as a as a divide
And being open to any of the best practices that we could bring to the table
Excellent
And another challenge on this side
What is that
It
Typically has
You know you think of things like a child which is a very big
Development process that everyone's espousing and you think of things like
Hey if your plant manager
You don't want to change everything you just want something that works and you want to stick with it
Hopefully it doesn't break right so it feels like these are very different worldviews that have evolved for
Really good reasons how do you build compromise how do you take from each world how do those things work in practice it
Because I know that you know I've got cio's of hospitals were like
Don't know how I talk to these people
This is a big challenge people don't know where things are and you don't talk to cios in other Industries and they're just
Are flummoxed they don't know how
How to do this
What I would say that one needs to start with
Maybe
The internet
The iot products
Because
We have to be talking to someone in our company would be
The head of the plan for the distribution center and Hospital you know it would probably be the facilities group
They are getting very excited about these internet
Things because it's allowing them to better manage
Are acid they can
And get real-time visibility and insight into the connected assets they can look at energy efficient
Be more readily
As we get excited about implement
These new capabilities in the conversation that has to happen about
Safety
Around this because in many cases
Again the information is being stored on
Cloud so there is an internet connection and even though
You were and maybe the data encrypted on the way up and down
You're still vulnerable
Tubitv a cybersecurity attack
So you have to
Talk to each other in terms that you want
Not talking in fiber Buzz language
And it's talking about
What are the risk
What are the mitigation Settlers Ridge
How do we work together
And again listening to each other because I
I feel what happens is that sometimes you put the wrong people in front of each other we take the technical
Cheap person or the heavy technical cyber person and we're putting them in front of
Maybe an individual who knows how to run their plant or Hospital
But he's not as familiar with what
A cloud
What do you mean my information is being stored somewhere else
So I really think it's about
Listening to each other
And making sure that you're using the most
Basic terms in Landen
Because this is so very new to a lot of people and I think the first thing we do is just not her headache
Each other
You don't think okay that I don't know what that person
Nothing but I believe them and I I just moved over with my job instead of really taking the time to say I don't
Understand what that means I don't understand the risk how does this work and really be able to talk
People at their level
And using language that sings Aaliyah
I like it
I think that's always a good idea
So you actually are doing something with this at Schneider Electric you guys not only have launched
A product called ether structure which is
Organize building management infrastructure
But
You guys are implementing this in your own facilities so can you tell us a little bit about ecostruxure
And what you're doing with that
So we can structure fits nicely into what we call our
Factory program
So we use the our ecostruxure iot Technologies in our manufacturing plant
Facilities
And even many of our offices as we would offer it
To our custom
Start everything from building Energy Management to Internet of Things
Operators
We actually showcase these to our customers and we've done this in France
India
In China we implemented
A couple of our products Under the ecostruxure Umbrella one was augmented operator advisor and
Enables
Are operators
To use augmented reality to speed up an operation and maintenance
And we've been delivering between 2 and 7%
Guinea productivity
We also have implemented our ecostruxure resource advisor
Which delivers up to 30% Energy savings
And contribute
Two continuous Improvement throughout the years
So those are just two examples of us
Showcasing to our customers ecostruxure iot
Products that we are
Using ourselves
And sharing
Obviously the productivity gains
And where the energy
Keysavings
And we plan to implement
These products and services in
Our Industrial
Footprint which today includes
Over 200 factories
8 / 44
Countries that we are Representatives
As part of this implementation how involved do you get
And what is your role is the CIO in trying to roll this ecostruxure platform out to more and more
Plants or building
The first thing we need to do is make sure that the connectivity
Is available in the planter the Distribution Center so that traditionally
Those clients have not been opened up
To the Internet so we have to make sure one that they have the right level of
Connectivity and bandwidth to this is all wireless connected so we have to make sure there's enough
Points within the facilities
To ensure that the Internet of Things devices
Can actually communicate and if I talkin to cio's out there
I would say this is probably the biggest learning
Is one having enough bandwidth
Ain't you making sure that there are enough taxes
Points because
Access twins get congested very very quickly even within being 20 to 25 feet apart
So that's a big learning how do we make sure that we have all the
Connectivity in place
Then it's really ensuring that
We can protect
The assets that are in that facility from a cyber perspective so it's putting in different types of
Software
One two names
Is Clarity which allows us to discover assets
In
The plant or the Distribution Center
And alert us if something new
Is identify we put in all of our best practices around
Certain pieces of equipment
And then of course we're layering different authentication layers as to who
Maintain these systems and maybe upgrade them
So aside from ensuring
Add all of these pieces of equipment can actually communicate to each other then we move into ensuring that there is proper
Security around the environment
Got it
Real fast on the security front because I think this is something that's really important
Drive-In
Which is
An IT side
I see a lot of
People emphasizing
Two different types of security one is Network
Apus security so monitoring device traffic on your network
Sample and saying hey this is behaving weird
And then to
Is are things like Microsoft Azure sphere is one it's this device base security
It also does a handshake
To the cloud it's usually key based
So Microsoft has something arm PSA
Is a way to implement this as well
Those two things seem very complimentary
But
I'm curious if that's enough for the OT World which historically hasn't been as security
Focused because
It hasn't been on the internet
Or are you seeing other
Types of security related to
The address to physical
That's what we're seeing very targeted companies
Focused on
Unsecured eGo-T
So the first thing that we
We need to do is make sure that weird
Discovering
All of the assets
That are
Within the plant
Or the distribution center in so we are using
Suffer from a company
Cold clarity
So that's helping us
Identify things that maybe we didn't know
Run the network but then we also have
Have to figure out once we identify some
That is new what do we do with it
Containerize it
Is it actually a thread
Is it just a new piece of equipment that
Came onto the scene that we
Might not have known about
So those types of
Technologies
AR
And
I would say that at this
Point
The best approaches multi-layered which is
What I believe we're doing from
The network perspective shows
Securing
And
Segmenting
Let's say the factories the distribution centers the hospital
And then having a discovery layer
On top of that then having policies
That can help us determine if we identify a new acid should it be there
And then we're also beginning to test software
On
Behavioral Analytics
So there is
A lot of data that can be captured
And we can look for Behavior pattern
But I think we're going to continue to see the advancement
A multi-layered
Security
Not
Very similar to what we already have been building for decades in the traditional it sent
Excellent
All right will Elizabeth this is been really
Helpful
I feel smarter about the OT it convergence I feel
Less terrified about cyber-physical security
And I appreciate you coming on the show this week thank you so much that's it for this week
Thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at today
Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week