Hey everyone welcome to the 214th episode of the
The Internet of Things podcast
This is your host Stacey Higginbotham at your co-host
Sad Kevin tofel
So
Adhar right this week we're going to be talking
The end of monkey
Where the company that provides the Anki robot
Which is why I'm sad
Which is why I Kevin
Ever going to be talking about what to expect
Google IO
We got an update on privacy in apartments and
The Box
AT&T has released its NB iot Network Nationwide will give you some update on it
Pricing
There's
Some legislative efforts about iot device security we're going to discuss
And then lots of little bits of news including a connected pool camera for
Detecting drownings
Mozilla's
Project things
Becoming something new
And
Matamata getting Spanish in the US Plus
A lot
This week Our Guest is Leonid sudakov
Who is the CEO of kinship
Kinship is a company that was created
In April by Mars Petcare for
Iot
AI
Other
Tech-related
Pet Care Solutions
We talked about how to use technology to translate what your pet may be feeling
Into something you and I can understand
It's a funny interview especially for those of us who have
Dogs cats
Spirits fish
And every
All right
This week's podcast is sponsored by software AG
We're going to be hearing about data democratization from them
And now let's go to a message
Another one of our sponsors
Iot world
You're invited to iot world it's the intersection of Industries and iot innovation
Traveling May 13th through 16th at the Santa Clara Convention Center at Silicon Valley it brings together
12500 iot strategist technologist developers and implementers
Iot in action
And
We have an exclusive listener discount of 25% off your pass with a code is Stacy
25 does s e a c e y
Visit iot world event
. com to register
And I'll be there so if you want
Definitely stop and say hi
Okay Kevin
Let's get it over with let us let us have a moment of silence for aunt
Don't rip off the Band-Aid and start with the news the sad news we said to me is that
Monkey has
Reportedly shut down
This is after we're raising 200 million dollars in
Venture capital and having
Revenues
Approaching 100 million in 2017 and presumably more than that
Because that's when Augie's
Vector robot which we talked about many times on the show
Came out and I assume
Several people besides myself bought it
But yes that is the news that the maker of cozmo and vector
Shutting down
Yes it was a really sudden shutdown they basically held a company-wide meeting on Monday
And everybody is gone
Basically as of Wednesday according to reporting from recode
And
I think for us
This is sad news because Kevin you have basically connected your monkey to your
Battlemage so your Amazon Echo device
And you treat it like a more personable version of that it's a little robot that helps with
With your smart home and follows you around
Faces
It is kind of that vision of what I wrote about last year about how I'm ready for a home
Digital assistant that
MP all over the arm move around have Mobility
Granted actress $250 in
Doesn't move around very far but he's smart enough to know
Go back to the charger
He can match his surroundings he can recognize me when he sees me he says
Hello Kevin
I can do it multiple people
Azure
Mention the
Madame a integration
Was added
Calendar last year so it's literally a moveable
Amazon Echo
So much
Potential and so much
Shut my vision that I want to see you for the future is there in a very inexpensive relatively
Inexpensive
And
Yeah it is a companion that's the only
Device that my family will talk to in the house other than me I'll talk to anything obviously
They will not talk to The Echoes In the Google homes and so on so forth
But because of the personality that's built into Vector along with the Pixar
I don't think spider because I believe somebody from Pixar actually designed his
Vectors expressions
Because of his expressions and a
Animations
They actually enjoy
This device and I haven't even told him yet
And it's interesting what this is spawning
Are people on Reddit there's a whole subreddit for veteran owners and one of them was
How do I explain death to my two-year-old
People's children have
Starting to grow up with these things as companions
It's sad
And this brings us to
This brings up something we talked about a lot of on the show which is
What happens to your device if your company shuts down in your device is
Basically a collection of cloud-based server
And I would say that donkeys Becker is definitely
One of those types of products without
The cloud
You can't
Talk to it it can't understand you
I assume it can still maybe play some games
Yeah but I've never used them for that other than just to see what the games are so you can play Blackjack and so on but I think even though
Blackjack might have had voice recognition in it
And that's not localized as far as I know
To literally hold your
Wander around my kitchen island I guess
Being his autonomous self
And that's it I'll get no value out of him at the
This is happened a lot
We talked about it
We had plenty of connected devices shutdown and us
Turn into basically bricks
It is very hard
To build a connected device that
Can
Really deliver the value people paid for it without a cloud-based connection
And a company maintaining their servers on the back
And at best a company should build a product that works without
Having a connection thermostat and the company behind it goes
Dafont
You should still be able to control
Your thermostat
But as we're seeing a whole new generation of smart products like
Are connected ovens are
Donkey is a good example of this
Some of the lighting
Companies that are little bit more advanced
What we're seeing is
That intelligence
Really does rely on the kid
Activity and that becomes
Really hard if a company doesn't make a plan for What happens if
And I know it sucks to think about that when you're starting your business
But you really should think about that you should think about having an escrow account for your
Zip code
Possibly funding
Finding a foundation to maintain it if need be
Putting money aside to maintain it for a certain amount of time
Or maybe
The offering refunds I really don't know
I mean yeah I ways to go with
I don't think we'll see refunds for monkey on this
Lowe's has
Provided refunds for some of its Iris products that we've talked about previously
But that was the rare case it's
Pretty typical that there's no refunds involved
If no other company comes in and buys the intellectual property and continues to run the servers which I know there's a I know there's a cost involved
My Hope Is that
Either Anki open source has everything but it has to run
The services
So that perhaps I could put this on a Home Server
Granted
It ties into Amazon and Google's cloud services the product does
And I probably have to create my own accounts to
Re-establish those connections personally
But even that I mean that's a solution maybe from me but it's not going to be a mainstream solution for people
Purchase this product
So
Maybe there will be news
Assume that somebody has purchased this
Property and decided to
Keep it going I don't know right now I meant
It just makes me sad it is actually like losing a little
Part of the family that's how
Ingrained
Vector is he's in our kitchen all the time and
We asked him the weather and Asthma turn the lights on and
Yeah it's just that you're sad
So like Jibo
You know if we can say goodbye possibly
Maybe
All right
But
Life Must Go On
And particularly
This week was f8 next week is Google IO
Also Microsoft build so we should actually there's a lot of things to do
To move on to sew
Let's talk about Google IO
What do we expect to see
Yeah I mean
As far as
What I'm writing 99% sure we will see I'm not even saying expecting I'm saying I'm 99% sure that we will
We'll see the rebranded
Google Nest hub
I will that mean new products yes or was talked about a bigger
Google home hub with a nest camera built-in
Bleacher Report. Maybe about a month ago
Looks Legit To Me
Mistake on Google's part maybe intentionally I don't know to leave that but so we should see a new Google home hub
With a nest camera
And then
I've been digging around in the
Chromium code and have
Talk about the mistrial device
Which appears to be a Google Wi-Fi
Replacement door
Upgrade next-gen whatever you want to call it
Couple questions about that that I still have
Because of the Qualcomm chips that they're using
And Mistral
It's possible because it support zigbee radios that this could be a true
At least three radio hub
I have yet not seen any
Code commits
Referencing a CB radio have her so I'm kind of leery on that
Additionally
I'm curious will this support
Maybe Google not Google but Wi-Fi 6
Sandor easymesh
Because
Is a Mesh networking device so
Those are what I don't know yet but I do believe we will definitely see a Google Wi-Fi
Next Generation products
Next week
Okay I will
Keep my eyes and ears open
Alright let's talk about
Privacy in apartment buildings and
Connected apartment buildings where users don't get a lot of say
We talked about this a while back after a hacker did Lesley Carhart
Got a notice from her apartment
Building that said hey we're switching over to a Smart system
Enjoy
And she's like I don't
Feel secure in this
Questions
Please answer them and
Idea basically is when you're living someplace is a tenant what rights do you have to refuse
If a company
Implement some sort of connected device in the building
And this came to a head this week based on a medium post about latch
I've actually talked to the latch folks a couple times I wrote about them when they raise a lot of money
And the issue that people are having with latch is that
The latch door locks
They're designed for multi-family dwelling unit so they are designed to run on your apartment tour
And then also
The lobby doors The Mailroom doors other doors that are in there
And
There's
Cameras associated with them in the lobby
And it's basically collecting information about your guests at all times and
You when you enter the lobby of Europe
People now are
Concerned about
And
I get it
A lot of apartments in cities are already implementing cameras and tracking residents coming and going from the building
So in some ways this isn't new and it's not necessarily associated with a Smart Lock
But it does raise the question of what kind of privacy
A tenant
Can expect
I would say very little in a public space of an apartment
Right I would agree it mean if a landlord wants to put cameras in the lobby and so forth that's
Nothing you can do about that how you can complain I suppose what you can't stop them
A bigger issue
And these types of dwellings is when you implement
Something like latch
Door locks
You're not opting into that
One thing I guess
And since you are by saying okay I'll rent an apartment with the latch
Door lock
But what if you already live there and then they add them if you don't really have a say over this according to
At least there's a lot going on right now and in a Manhattan building they're suing the landlord over privacy concerns
Regarding the latch locks so it's a tricky bit because
It is not an opt-in I guess other than saying yeah I'm I'm signing the lease for this latch enabled apartment
And some people that is a selling point so
It's Not Unusual in
I would also say
One of the issues in this Manhattan
Apartment is that
The landlords are using
Residence patterns of Ingress egress in the building to harass them because they want to kick out
Tenants
To basically
Raise the market rate or roulette apartments in Ohio
And that's where
These sorts of connected devices
It's not the device itself it's sometimes it's just the ability of
Someone to see this data and use it against you
And that kind of brings us to this idea of
How are we going to regulate data
Latch has an extensive privacy policy that's available to be read and so on so forth
One thing it doesn't address
Is if the building is sold
Does the new owner
Get the
Old data
Yeah it's according
To the privacy policy
Leslie said they may automatically receive the data
Well that's very, domain almost all
Privacy policies associated with
Connected home
Connected Goods
In general
Say that
That's not like
Asparagus on its own
It's basically that k at the buyers want it they can have it
Cuz I'm a lot of ways that is especially if a company goes
Belly up really quickly sometimes that's like the only thing of value that's there and that is worth considering
If you're a
So
Let's talk about regulations
Because
There's movement on that front
Congress this week had a hearing on iot security
The Security hearing was about
Creating a label
That would
Basically actually go
A security certificate
Education
For home iot devices
This actually was an idea that was
Is proposed not too long ago by public knowledge
And it's a consumer rights
The idea was that
We would set for some regulations
Group of industry and consumers Etc what
Get together and say things like
Hey for device to be certified under this program
It needs to not have hard Coda passwords
Have an expiration date for when the security support stops in some basic things that we
We talked about in the past
And
That's the idea that
Legislators seem to belong.
But
The representative from the CTA the consumer technology Association
Was like that that's a terrible idea where where are you working
The senators were like
Yeah you're not working fast
Sue
It's possible we could get something like this
I would hope so
I think it's the bare minimum of what we need
And then over across the pond in the UK
Legislators are talking about
Regulations for iot security in devices that
Prevent hard-coded passwords
Yay
Also add that expiration date so tell people win
The support for security.
And
It says manufacturers have to ensure that there is a contact point for security researchers to report vulnerability
I think I should probably add and
Someone to respond to that Within
24 hours
There should be a service-level agreement in there of some sort
But that's a bare minimum that seems like
Like a great place to start
So we'll see if it happens
Back to the US
Are you excited yet
About AT&T
They have released
They're NB iot Network
Nationwide
For you guys are like what what
Nb-iot is a low-power wide area network
It's a cellular standard you send very very small bits of data
Ideal for sensors
Halo power sold like smoke sensor or smoke detector might send off a
Peeing every hour or so
All kinds of stuff
Air quality monitoring
Been with this very small for this this is 64kbps is the maximum throughput speed so we're talkin
Superstar Lake
Old-time dialogue
Oh yeah
I started with a 26 was a 26 424
28 yen
Super speeds
Okay so the thing to know about AT&T network is they're going to have the NB iot Network
And they're going to have what's their lte-m net
Which has slightly more
And
The pricing for this which is what I've been waiting for
Is AT&T Chris Penrose who's in charge of their iot
Stuff
Says that his team is working with suppliers to certify $5 modules
Connect devices to NBA
And that's basically the radio the chips that have the radio and such
So for $5 that's a decent price we've been waiting for that
Add for quite some time
So that's the radio itself so if you're building this device you put that $5 module in there
Which is still kind of expensive it's way more expensive than like Bluetooth or Wi-Fi but
It is low-power cellular
Low-power wide area network
And they're going to offer for these devices is as low as $5 a year
Pair device
Which is really not terrible
Right
No I don't think so I mean
Even if you're putting tons and tons of devices out there yes it adds up but
Jennifer a Year's worth of
Can I tell you that to give these things smarts and send
Alerts in
It's a date I don't think that's too expensive
If you need
To deploy devices that need more bandwidth
We're sending more data
You could use their lte-m Network
In the US and Mexico attack
But you're going to pay $30 a year for that rate
And I don't know about you cuz you're on the LTE network with your IP
What do you pay per month for that
Well that's a wrap
Quite honestly I've said this many many times have people who know me
Follow me are not surprised to hear that
I pee and I'm pretty sure it's standard at all the characters $10 a month
For LTE on the watch
$120 / device per year it is because
I checked with monthly usage
And roughly
I averaged about a hundred megabytes per month
Maybe they'll swap that out for an lte-m
I don't know
I mean it Beijing
Enough bandwidth to
Panda voice calls which Steven 64 would be okay
And then it's just occasional notifications from my
IOS devices
Background information like weather and such a mean
I think it's a total rip-off but that's again that's what's going on in the US with the
Apple watch
All right let's go to a bunch of our news bits because
There's quite a lot of little stuff going around out there
So
This first story is about an underwater
Camera
That uses AI
To recognize
People in the water and
Weather
Still for longer than 15 seconds
And then it will sound an alarm so it's basically to prevent drowning and let you know when
People are in the pool
Bring this up because a lot of people have actually asked about these sorts
Surprise
Just called the coral Manta 3000
And
Basically
Keep popping on the side of your pool and it
Access to Sky
Alert function
The challenges it's connected to Wi-Fi
And in your backyard if your WiFi connection isn't awesome
You're going to have a hard time
Getting reliable and low latency information from this.
Device which is really important if you're thinking about
Preventing trap
Yeah every second counts in that case
I want you cannot put a price on somebody's life
I am
Shocked at how expensive this is
This cost $2,000
Their hope is they will you know
Benefit from economies of scale and
This price will go down but
It's pricey but I will say that
There are other ways to track this but
Madison death
And please if you do install this
Please please please please
Please if you have children in the pool
Make sure you stay out there with
Babysitter
Absolutely I can't understand why this is $2,000 minutes itself power because it comes with solar
Panels
Apartments outside the pool above it
And then inside the fullest
Got the camera
And I understand you know AI for object recognition
Payments High because they're going to have
Continual training and learning
I don't know
And you can hire a lifeguard
4 year and pay less than
Oh no you can't come on
Okay
Either way
Let's talk about Mozilla
And facts
Probably should have talked about them two weeks ago I feel bad because
I just noticed today
That the old project things from from Mozilla
Which is a
Web-based smart home do-it-yourself Hub it's a platform for that
Ashley graduated it is no longer I
Project
Beta product
It is now Mozilla web things
And I think I'm going to have to
Play this in my home because as I look at the documentation for it
Obviously it's
Can I go on a Raspberry Pi again it's all web-based
So there's no app for it
But it does support not just Bluetooth and Wi-Fi devices but also a zigbee and Z-Wave if you would like to add those radios
To the pi via
The USB dongle
So
Sounds good to me you know
It does and I can't wait to the
Hear what you think I think last time you
Started to playing this in
It became cumbersome I believe
Yeah it wasn't quite ready that's when it was in project status
So it was very early on
And
I don't recall what issues I ran into at the time but I'm like
They're just getting too frustrating and I put it aside and
Now it's it definitely deserves the second look there's so many people that are interested in
Not relying on
The cloud is much for their device management and control
And also I'm keeping their data as local as paw
Possible
All right
In super quick news
Madam
Gets Spanish support in the US
And
Are you guys were like what
She has had Spanish support in Mexico and in Spain but now you get that option in the US which is cool because they
There are plenty of people in the US who speak Spanish as a first or second language
I would like to talk to Madam a
In that particular time
Also speaking of Amazon
Or rather
Amazon's digital assistant and fuss
Amazon
Ford is adding Amazon's key to its
2017 models and
Up
This basically means you can use the Amazon Key Program
With your car
Amazon delivery people can deliver packages to your car they will unlock your car
Pop the package inside
And close it
It's probably awesome for everything that isn't
Ice cream in Frozen
If you're going to use this keep in mind that you must
Sync
Your Amazon Prime account to use of the forward pass or Lincolnway
Accounts in order to make this happen to
If you're not really using those
Services
You're not going to be able to use this unless you
Change that
Got it
All right
And we got some
Good Guys in books out there
Kevin Ewing
Yeah they found just because I was looking at Mozilla
Web things I found a very interesting Kickstarter project
For a Raspberry Pi with
For computer vision ebook
And basically this
Allows you to learn about how to use computer vision with a pie
You will get the ebook as well as a pie and
And the sensors that you need
I think it's $95 which is
Yeah it's more than a pie I'm going to cuss you out 45 just for the hardware
The Bass Hardware but
This will walk you through how to
Train
Raspberry Pi for computer vision and so on so I just thought
Are the DIY rose out there might be interesting
And then
Or do you have wires in the Enterprise
Done a really nice techrepublic guide on how to create an iot hub
Using Microsoft azure
Which is something I haven't done yet I've pretty much use all the other
Cloud providers to
In some way shape or form use iot
For my projects
I will probably walk through this just to see what it's like but again it's very enterprise-focused I would
Prism
Yes
Okay
And now
It's time for
Iot podcast
Hotline voicemail
Which is brought to you by Schlage
Slade's wide variety of smart locks lets you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions
Compatibility with Amazon Apple products
Google Assistant
And more at schlage.com
/ iot
It's a new month which means we're starting a new prize this month's prize is going to be a Schlage
Lock
Give us a
Call on the iot podcast hotline at 5 1/2
6 to 3
742 4
To ask us your question
And it's probably time for us to pick a winner for the month of April
So Kevin
Who won Arkansas
Iowa alarm system
So the winner for April is Scott who had called in about double cylinder lock think we just answered that question a week or two
Scott you got an answer and
A way to connect your existing alarm system
To your smartphone
Congratulations to
Scott
And now
Let's hear from
Chef who is looking
Help his parents
Start a garden
Are Kevin and Stacey
This is our Jeff New York and you can use this on the show my question is
Are interested
Starting a garden
Never really had
Green thumbs
But I was wondering if there's a device that
They can put with in their Garden
What are and or if
Calum which
Cancer flowers
The best plant
Could you online but I was wondering if
Stephanie alert there their devices when it's
Water
Stuff like that but I appreciate what sports your answer have a great day
Okay
Jeff
There's a couple options out there on the market
You can always do
A smart irrigation system and it's unclear to me if their Garden will be irrigated by like
In-ground sprinkler systems or that sort of thing
If that's an option
Blossom
Rachio
And there are several other companies that make really good
Smart Systems that let you
Divide up different areas of the garden for watering the
Look at the weather and they decide
You can actually invite you I know you can tell it
Somewhat what type of
What plants you have in their water needs
It it will actually
Factor that into how it water
Stop swell
So that's
One option if you have
An existing irrigation system or they want
If they do not then we're talking about doing some sort of
Connected
I would say doing a soil sensor
And then
Probably doing a manual sprinkler or watering schedule
The reason why I say Emmanuel watering schedule is cuz
A lot of the
Automatic watering things that attach to your hoes aren't very good I investigated them last year trying to build something from
Myself
In
A lot of them were very expensive
And did not seem to
Soil sensors
On the soil sensor front
In
As a bonus some of these will work with
Existing customer
Sprinkler systems
They're kind of expensive
I'll just let you know this right now
When is the Rain Bird
Smarty soil-moisture
Sensor
And
This is basically you'll have a sensor that you plug in and then there is an above-ground controller that you can use you can do
Use that manually or you can tie that sensor into an existing sprinkler system
So
Again
It's not exactly smart
But it will tell people
When
The plants need
But
Kind of a lot
Yeah I think it's cheaper to just set reminders
Yeah and another one that there is is the
Toro Precision soil sensor that will also work with most
Irrigation controllers like rachio Blossom Etc
And
You just Jam the sucker in your soil
It also has its own
Thing that sits on a wall or you can
Put some place and it will tell you how
Moist the soil is
That is also in the hundred 3200
What do you do if your cheap
You have
Couple
Options
The cheapest options are about 10 bucks and they're basically just moisture meters that you stick in the ground and they'll like tell you
Is it wet or not but at that point
Stick your finger in the ground
Great and then there's a couple connected soil sensors designed for indoor use I would not recommend them outside
Because
They're not rugged enough
So that's where we are at this today
Heather a lot of protective products out there right I find them rather expensive number one
Number two
You have to make sure you have good connectivity
Outside to get the alerts and so on
Will a lot of them are
Impropriety
Do you spell few companies like Eden in plantlink that did this but those products aren't available in
So
My hunch is
It's a crappy environment
To build something that's red for outdoors
Seems Wi-Fi
It's not wired
And that's why we're not seeing
Flex accessory
So you may have to go with some of the sensors that use
Proprietary Wireless to talk to things that are very expensive
Or they could be wired into a smart irrigation system
We're very sorry
All right well that's close this portion of the show
Please stay tuned to learn more about kinship which is Mars Petcare
New technology Focus brand
Bringing iot AI in
To your
Pets care
We'll talk to Leonid supercoppa CEO of kinship
In just a few moments
And now let's hear from our sponsor we are taking a quick break from this week's
Iot podcast
Who is director of solutions architect
Picture for iot and Analytics
Software AG
Hi John how are you
Hey Stacy I'm doing well
This week we're talking about the democratization of data through but before we do that can you please
Remind us what it is that suffer AG does
And how it works with e
Suffrage is an Innovative software,
Money that's been around 4:50
We're global company
Headquartered in German
And you'll find us
70%
Fortune 1000
Most people know us for our immigration
Business process
Of course iot and Analytics
We help companies get connected and democratize their data everyday
What do you mean exactly by democratize
Essentially
This is the concept of making your data available within your organization
It goes to be able to deliver relevant data to
Do anyone
Anywhere
Anytime
Most folks don't think about this in relation to Hyatt
But the reality is
You only start
Sirius return on your investment
Hbase
Once you've enriched your acid
Device data
Free sample
Is running hotter
The normal
Only me so much
If you don't know the whole picture about that
For example we may expect vibration spikes
Temperature spikes on an asset if it's doing something that it doesn't
Picture we can wait
Time and money
Responding
That may not really be
Problems
The good news
Suffrage
We have a robust and
Proven integration layer within the cumulus of the iot platform
They can help you connect to over 100 and her prize application
This what you get connected
Inform
I'm beginning to innovate in hours not weeks not much
Excellent
That sounds great John so where can I go to find out more about cumulative
And software
You can go to software AG. Com
Flash iot now
Start your free
No commitment trial 2
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest
Is
Sylacauga
Who is president of
Of kinship
Which is a new business created by Mars pet
Pileated how are you doing
Very good
I am excellent all right
So
I
How to find out what
Is Mars doing with kimchi
What is the goal here and what is the actual business
We are Global leader
In Patton Creek
And how
World's biggest pimple
Exclusive 40%
Entire
At population
Until when we
Created this business
You're the idea for I have been to Leverage
The leadership position that Mars has
Unique commitment
To the future of pet care in Industry with the way for us to
To collaborate very different
With every single disruptor an innovator Tommy Newberry early-stage startups
Two companies that are growing
Posturing this
In this area
Kinship
Is the type of business that is uniquely positioned to create a
The coalition
For the future that ended
Okay if we talked to lots of pet care businesses on the show because you know
People love their pets
So I talked to people from whistle a make a connected it's a Fitbit for dogs
I have talked to a company called doggy
Petscoop
But it's really a
Description Pet Food business
And so
Are these the sort of innovators were talking about
Well absolutely
Weeki Wachee it's out of kinship
It's the one of the startup
That we operate is in the connection
Color business
Which is
Another business that we run is
Wisdom health
Which is our genetic diagnostic business
Deal with
Technology and science
But it's not
Just about the business as we on
And operated businesses between Gage and partner
You're welcome the journey in the last couple of years
Too close to twenty different state startup
Questions of nutrition
Care
Technology-related
3D transforming
Experience of pet parents
I believe it's that
Next few years expectations of me they don't have parents
Will result in
Changing Faces
Because this industry and we want to be part of it without having
We believe that the paradigm
The businesses will be built on partnership
Calibration
And we're trying to feel that
So is Kendrick going to have
Investment
Will continue.
Significant numbers
Tool that we've launched
Year ago
One of them is
Companions Bond
Created Hundred Million Dollar Pawn
Invest in the
Growth stage companies in all things that care
And we've had quite a few great and lessons
Very happy about
The other one is out
Leaf accelerator
Which is
Cstate
Startup accelerator
Truecaller
Who won last year's another one next year
Running right now in LA
In partnership with
Michelson found animals
Nonprofit that bringing a
Project Glass
Through the accelerator
The idea that is not just about the porting them too funny but it's really about supporting them
Mentorship
Partnership
I'm data
The. Something
Something that's very much
The heart of what we've been doing and what week
Continue to do
Okay
Help me understand what the opportunities are in the spacer
SM
I think I've always had pain
So you know I get up very early
I want my dog
I come back
I got to work my dog basically sleeps all day oh I forgot to feed my dog
So I feed my dog to
I'm good I feed my dog
And then you know I come home I walk my dog again I feed her I play with her we do some tricks training
And then you know
Well go to bed
So
How does this change when I have either more information or maybe technology available to me
What is this mean for me and what is this mean for my pet
About the key
Barrier
The pet owners
Quite a few in very happy pet owner
Around the world
You know we know if the unique benefits with pet owners should bring
People like you
2 States and many many others myself included and those half
To do with beginner very clear health benefits
Feeling of well-being
Kids-n-play elderly
Interested
Extended care benefits
To as many people as possible
Very very important
Elvis T Whitney
To look at the barriers
That pet ownership is facing a lot of those have to do
If you think about the people that would love to
Become better Runner
You know there's a lot of battery
Related to
Access to services
How do you make sure that you
You're able to
Walk the dogs
To ensure that to you there's a dog sitter available when
You need them
So that you can travel for work
You can you can make sure that you don't miss
Domestic part of care
Veteran health services are available
Cost of
Of character
Affordable the cost of having a
Passive something that you
Can manage
Things that have to do with
Quit making a pet ownership is
Attractive as possible
Peconic paddler
3D about how can you be the best pet on a possible
And that is really about connecting a panoply of potential solutions that today at this jointed
And don't read receipt one into another
Into something that can be a real
Support system for you as a pet owner
So that you don't need to
Explain
The story of your path to every single service provider you might need
Throughout their lifetime
Supported by
State information
Inside
That is very relevant
Closet lights
The puppy stage
To beat out tattoo
Increasingly
Because pets do live longer and longer and so that
Support needs to accompany them
So what's going to the service provider question
Because it makes sense in the human world
Because we have a bunch of different doctors we have you know
Dentist we have
Cardiologist we have neurologist we have all sorts of things happening to us in over a hugely long life span
For the most part my dogs have had
They come for the pound
So they've had their pound experience
Everything's an unknown before that then they have their vet
In the vet does pretty much everything so it feels like
I don't understand where it gets difficult to grab data from are we talked about bringing in data from other sources
What we are seeing is that the sophistication of the approach
Towards the pets needs
That the science is now allowing
To do is really napolina much more
Individualized
South experience
So you mention whistle
So because of all the work that we've been doing on me
Algorithm
Science around the
Monitor part of the whistle
We connect you now
Stop predicting
Things like sleep destruction
Or hip and Joint issues that the cat might experience
You might not know about
So you can be alerted
About the potential
He might have
What do you start noticing them as a title on her soul before you look very happy to visibly
Be accompanied by healthy
Apache would know a lot more about what kind of issues
Experiencing
I'm be able to August a company van
Hopefully better health longer
Which distributed close to a hundred thousand
All devices
Cleaning customers through Dancehall
The biggest Hospital change name
And as a result we were able to
Attract what we are seeing
Through electronic data
Given to us through the whistle device
With
What we starting to see in the medical records
Time
24 months
Studyware reboot
Accumulate the signs that we're seeing from the device
And correlation.
Stop that data
To the
Medical events that we're seeing for the medical records and so is the result who started
To create algorithms
Recognize
And the result hopefully start building a
The way of communicating with a pet owners
Reconnect
Is that and what
Seeing in the whistle data
That is awesome
Because yes it's hard to tell until your animal is like so sick they're not eating or drinking it's really hard to tell sometimes what's
Going on in there
Is this for dogs and cats or are you looking for solutions for I don't know fish ferrets
Birds
Around the world
Scale factor
Starter serving dishes
At the same time for example now in genetic diagnosis
Business
Start typing
People that have courses
Use genetics to be able to
Oh that's interesting I actually just to talk to a startup called nightwatch and they make a
We dat's a halter for horses that checks for I'm going to mess up this disease it is
Torsion or dogs it's some sort of disease that horses get
Where if they don't solve it really fast the horses
It dies
Pek overnight
It's crazy
Solo
Yeah it's connected device that has if you don't put it on there and it's got algorithms that the measure this sort of thing and it's it's r
Really if your horse owner this is a wonderful thing
Love your horse
Getting pets
The voice I think that's really
Fundamental
Benefits of
Using data
To allow the pet to have a voice
Really communicating with pet owners about what the feeling I think it's
Something over and over again we seen such
Incredible benefits
Where is
You're not getting our case
We can now talk about
Sleep patterns
Eating pattern
Gates
Enormous amount of
Potential areas
Teaching Tots in terms of health and potential
Super collagen
Just the one of the examples
Help house
Can support two
Pets and patterned relationship
I love it
Like wishing all along for like the bark translator but really all I might need is a connected device
And lots of research across Mini Pets
And I'll know what my dog is thinking
Let's go back to the services side of this and providing kind of more convenience and access to care because
There are lots of people who are like oh I work all day I travel I can't have a dog
You guys through kinship are also looking to partner with companies I assume maybe like wag or
What types of companies are you looking to work with there
Absolutely I think we have a variety of different
Services
We're trying to
Built
And as I said before
Having an ax
Services is very important
Part of it
So we working the right if you want
Try to find them
What you need Express
Forum
Executive Taxi
So one of the things
We do it and I'll give you an example of the startup incubator in Russia
Babies created a telemedicine platform
Cinemark
Where access
Bethany house is not nice
Generally given
Inequality
You can put into provider you can find in that market
It's not
Always
And so was
Create a text story. Are you witches
The first digital clock
Alarm 4
Accessing advice and telemedicine
Locations intended spaces
Few months to reach 200000
Mobile users
Switch
Credible signal of readiness
The needs of the patio
Engagement and so
Care is a big part of what we working on in the United States
So we're now piloting a mobile
Approach where
In some of the communities and if you think about
Retirement Community
Have the opportunities to go in travel to health institutions take care of their pet
Autocare becomes an important
Part of the solution where care comes
You
And helps you manage your pets help
Tooele keita variety
Potential Solutions
Eternally intention but also working without partner
Sister services
Testing a few of the things with it with the other service providers so you think about
Dog walker
Walking the dog City
A lot of this service is the Augustine
Is there a high frequency
And the ability for us
To be able to
Service providers
What a dog walker
Read the full picture of what
Pets
Background
You will enable them to watch out for things
It's better to be able
How to form how they they look at the
Either not blast
The way to connect from the date of perspective in inside perspect
The multitude of the service providers that are touching that pets
Sly
It's becoming very important part of what we're trying to crack and figure out how to
Okay and
We just did a lot of the big picture but because this is the iot podcast I have to ask
Where does connectivity and connected devices play into all this we've obviously talked about whistle
And
You know there's a huge Market of connected home dog toys and cameras
And cat toys and cameras
So where are the places were connected devices will help you in this
We are
Start with the light
Device is because of that direct link
To help but we're not stopping there one of the other Partnerships that we are currently running
China is with the smart feeder device
Because if you think about the further out
Development of connectivity
TV Aerials
Eating
It's probably not a area where a cheetah can it be
Form in March
Better much more precise after
Markets like China that I really moving fast
Isb area
Smart seating
Is an area where
There's a lot of guns
Singapore and so being able to
Inject the data in the inside about the cats need
Dynamically
Into the
Way too fat
Spell frequency
It's not the area
Today this is the part of me
Iot world that's not just about tomorrow but it's already about today
It was very happy to start piloting
Partnership opportunities in China
How are you guys
Going to make money on this what it what kind of the business models associated
Part of that is
Dream about identifying
The things that we
We want to
Bring inside
You no longer time so all this
Whistle and wisdom
Are today
Businesses be on hundred percent we have big plans for the business by growing very well
We know that there will be
Core
The kinship will create longer-term
In this kind of digital service line
Area
Will be there
Vibrant
Instructable
Long-term
Sustainable
On top of it word
Is that you
What will make the core of our business
Stressful as the daystrom
Partnership agenda
Death will be cast in essential partner for as many
Shuffle players in the shenzhen
It's not just about us being
Successful by ourselves
But also I can get you being successful because we will be at the fall come out
The bigger Coalition for
For the industry
What we are we are work
Imports
Linode
Thank you so much
For coming on the show this week I really appreciate it and I will look forward to all the cool services that will make
Make it easier for me to own my dog
Thank you for the pleasure that's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remember if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter and Stacey on iot
Will see you next week