Hey everyone welcome to the 226 episode of The Internet of Things podcast
C Higginbotham and your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a spectacular show for you today we're going to be talking about Google
Deciding
Against the Smart Home
Microsoft has done something
Huge
For the Enterprise iot
Tile the location tracker company has raised
He's a lot of money and it's surprising
Also going to talk about
Google
New algorithms to predict energy usage at the device level
A device that we're not sure we need and question why
Why is it doing a scale
Plus we've got a little bit of news from Huawei
More from Google
A little bit
Toby
And LG
Kevin has also been trying out a new iot security device that you are
Want to hear about
Plus this week our sponsor is Dell Technologies talking about building solutions for the medical
Price Industries
And our guest is Jana welander of a
Company that is launching today
Called crascall
We're going to find out more about that company
And everything else
After message
Another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is a pharaoh
Are you doing multiple iot projects
That work well together in a single app that strengthens your brand that is really tough and it requires
Where's the right platform
Would have Arrow Kenmore lunch 42 smart Appliance models in just two years of Arrow customers have Experian
As much as an 80% reduction in time-to-market 99% fewer support calls and 10
Tennis higher activation rates
Bus
They can we use 90% of their work from one project to the next
Show pic of pharaoh just like Kenmore Mitsubishi bank ufj group and dealing did that beat your competition
Patient with a solution that your team loves to build on and your customers love to use
Learn more at a pharaoh. IO
Flash go big
So first up we have news from
Google specifically for
Reishi
Chandra who is VP of product in general manager at
And
Reishi
Kind of shocked a bunch of
People by talking
About
How he doesn't believe in the Smart Home
But really that was kind of clickbait
Edsbs
Google does believe in the smart home Google just doesn't want us to call
I want to call it
Helpful home
And as people who have
Covered
Google's smart home efforts since they purchase Nest even before then actually
A covered Nest all the way back in
When Tony fadell was
The founder Inn
Add Google
This is not a big shift
Google Now wants to call this The Helpful home and they want enable it by
What they call ambient
I feel like we've even used Ambien
Computing it used to be a big thing back
2013 I think it was actually like
Ambien information or ambient display
Which is basically this idea of the devices around you
Are connected somehow and they're going to pull information from
Apis
Other devices
Your personal data
And deliver information in a way that isn't like a notification
Screen
So good example would be
An umbrella that lights up when it's
Plan to rain today so you can just grab it on your way out
China products
Would you cuz
The problem is we all said hey we buy that
But then
The business models made it impossible you have to
A subscription for that umbrella and
If the company went out of business then you'd have this really expensive umbrella if my
Maybe like
$4 for it
This is true so I will just use the dark sky API and make my own little ambient bulbs next to my umbrella
Right there a bunch of challenges he
1 is
Probably first and foremost is cost that's how
Consumers rate
Who sings cost
A lot of money and that's historic
In the next big thing for developers and
Has been there's no standard to make
These things worked
Surrey she is acknowledging this
He's not really offering a great solution
I'll be honest he is saying to Google's efforts to get rid of the nest API
Part of that solution because it
It sounds like he's trying to simplify
I'm skeptical hat on and say he's just trying to build
First ecosystem
But time will tell
Yeah I mean you're right everything you said I agree with its it's this is not a New Concept we talked about ambient computing
We're still waiting for
The Ambien Os from
Essential Indie Ruben's company
I think she probably
Keep waiting on
You're waiting
I think so
I do see this as not a rebranding but a
Focus away from your privacy and data
Because of all of the
People's concern valid concerns about giving up your data
Because this is actually part of the Google Assistant
Mantra to its be more helpful assistant that would be madaio helpful helpful helpful
I think they're tying it all together now with the hardware products number one
And to buy saying helpful assistant
Your focus Less on
Smart sand data and such when yes the beta model doesn't change you still need to give up
Some data
To have the this helpfulness
Maybe people will think about
Giving up that date as much
Well I think what's important to think
Here
Is that your giving up your data
To get something
Back right you're giving update but it's
Presumably
Or service that you
In Google has been very
Even as far back as like to
And talking to Google about this thing
Google doesn't work
Advertise to yuan wants to use this data to build better
Hair products
Now
You may hate that
Because they are going to
Design products that
Based on your data
And those products maybes things like services
Hardware
Timeously
It's using your data and service of
Which some people
Data is the new gold Royal so they're not the only ones doing
I do actually I do
If it's the new oil is
I think the insights derived from the
Are the True Value
I think
The idea of
Because I also think
Unlike oil
Which you know
The people want to control and Chorale the data
You can get data from a lot of different places
There's no one logon
Data streams necessarily
There's a few items were
There's going to be a cop
And it also encourages this model of scarcity
In a way that I don't think is going to
Help with that
The creation of Standards or getting us to a place where like the internet is
So if you want ambient
Computing
That date is going to have to
Cher
Burdensome meaning
Format
Across different
Where consumers have to buy into like a
Open
This is true but that also leads directly to our next door
I'm so glad
I saw that coming a mile away
Yeah it was
Speaking of data share
Microsoft
And this is why I'm excited about
Has created three pre-design licensing
For data sharing
They're basically trying to do
4-Digit sharing
What open source
It's so
Bees licensing agreements
Will let people
Do
A couple different things so
There is an open use of data
And that's for use with open datasets don't have any personal data and they're not
Set the most open
Least restrictive
Creative Commons
But with that
Creative Commons of data
And then they have a computational Yusuf
And this is designed for using different datasets for AI training purposes that contain third-party batiri
So it's a contract for use with a database
It will have open data but also copyright
Protectable
Pieces of data like photos or
Maybe some text
You can use it to train
But you can't
Republish that data
Or redistributed
The
Protected
And so think of something
Like
Maybe it's
Imagery
Definition for Ana
Animals and maybe they pull data from
Customers homes
Or maybe is image recognition for brands of
Do dinner
Pulling data from smart
Cartridges
And so would be training for that
Training for like recognizing different foods that could then be used in life
Point of sale systems at grocery stores
Grey and the data itself would be used for the modeling and learning
But would not be directly shared like those images for sample would not be
Shared across
Platform Beer Company
And then they've created the most restrictive license
Switch is there data use agreement for open
Development
And this is basically
Proprietary data
This is for sharing stuff
2 train models
What date is it
Proprietary
I'm actually really excited by this
And we talked a little bit about why that matters
Ambient computing
What is also really important for things like in a world where we're going to have
Gdpr and you're trying to build
Algorithmic models
For doing something
Having this sort of contract in place is going to make it cheaper in
Faster
To share releve
Data entry
Rest on pretty secure Legal Foundation
Interesting
Is if these contracts hold up against something like gdpr where
Retroactively
Information
Like if I could send the right hook
Data
My image dated for exam
Then
Do they have to pull that from Mike
Any training since we don't know yet
Until these are proposals are actually publicly available so you can comment on this proposal
Yeah I taken the whole open approach
I think there's another benefit here from the consumer side like
We typically don't want our
Told us that we capture on our phones
Scanned and such right
We know that happens
Today napping say with Google photos for example
I knew
That
As example table Google
Says we subscribe to the
Second
On the computational use of data agreement
We're just going to use this for
Training are models and none of your data will ever be on that so you didn't steal your data
What we will use is the aggregated machine learning model
Gather for everybody maybe a little bit
More of a sense of security from a consumer standpoint
Percent
And I also think in the corporate Realm
One of the things that has been very challenging
Is
The legal teams are looking at some of the data that like an industrial Manufacturing
That you can get from the lines and they're like
Whoa Nelly
We don't want to share this highly proprietary
Information with anyone
And in that makes sense but
There's no contracts right now for that
People are trying to develop them and this gives
Those companies and those legal teams a starting
Place they may not want their stuff to be licensed this way
But it at least gives
Them the added haft of Microsoft's legal team
Helping them
Define terms in in
Pick things out
I'm really excited about this I think it's a big deal and I will also say that Microsoft
Has been thinking about building marketplaces for data and sharing data like this
Basically the last 10 year
I have talked to people on is
All the way back when I was
Was brand new
2009 2008
And I have been waiting for this
Okay
Just
Kevin
Yeah
We were both surprised to see this but we'll share the good news for tile
Bluetooth Tracking Company
45 million dollars in a series
Beef Underground
Yeah
Kevin Kline
Well and I say that because I think it was
Last year that they laid off a bunch of folks
They
Jigger pivoted their products to be at
Subscription service and they're also going to license their technology
And I didn't think that was going to really work for them at the time but apparently it is and that seems counter to 2
Since they just raised more money you think maybe there is
Now they're running out of funds
You know they haven't shared
Figures from their new subscription premium services
It is vastly exceeded expectations so
I guess they want the money to expand beyond what
Products they have in the current subscription service I do not know
So here's what this is about
There's a cop
What is bride fundraising in
Inflation
Your resentment wheezing is just across the
Everybody's raising
That's one but two is something I wrote about
So it is about Bluetooth
Back when
The most recent iteration of Bluetooth
Came out
What came out with it is granular tracking
This granular tracking let you
Basically understand where something is
Few inches
So not just like oh it's in your study but
You can say
Your keys are in your city on the table
Provided you know
What the table is
So that's really important for location tracking
Which is a huge
Industrial and Enterprise iot
And it's also good for
The other side is tile has
Put their SDK
Nordic Bluetooth chips Bluetooth chips from Silicon labs
And I think from
Other big Bluetooth
Herbs
Insta
Now a company can actually just buy a Bluetooth chip that already has tile integrated on it
Which means just like
With Apple's location finding feature for MacBooks
You could have
Location finding
Chess pie
Virtue of having a boy
Bluetooth device
Even if you're not carrying it
Southern Network expands
So this money will help tile go up against
In Google Google is also supposedly
About a Bluetooth tape
So
What we could see is tile
Genuine the consumer but also releasing tags for any number of things
And basically creating a really good Bluetooth based location
More power to him I hope it works out
Yeah well I think that's I mean it's a good play
They will need money for it so
That's what I
Stinky
Okay so let's turn to
Cool uses of data
Yeah I would never say combination IRT in machine learning
What is
So Google has posted on its Google Cloud blog a really detailed
Technical
Blog post about the real time prediction
Operation status of appliances
But using machine learning
They're not the first
People to do this to me we seen actual products that
Can monitor
Down to the individual circuit level of
What power draw is coming from an appliance and
Give you insights into that
Those typically do it with
Hardware at the circuit level
This is actually using machine learning
To predict which
Device in your home which appliance is currently on or should be on
We shouldn't be on based on the
Time of day I mean if your TV
Turns on in the middle of the night that would be workable cause an abnormal situation for most people
Not for me because I sometimes watch TV in the middle of night
And the idea here it with this project is to
Make the system Smarter with machine learning
To hopefully predict
When appliances go on go off
How much power they should use and then gather insects
Again it's rather technical but I think it's a good read
Let's tie back to ambient Computing cuz basically This falls back into that same category
Let's look at what's happening in your home
Let's make some educated guesses
And then the next step after years
Confident
This person is watching TV in the middle of the night which is weird the Ambien computer
May make a
Suggestion about
Do you want a glass of warm milk
Or maybe it'll
Add that to your
Yourhealthfile there's a lot of potential
Some of its goods
Could be used against us
So
Take it forward
All right
Let's talk about not a smart ambient
Computing kind of device
Justify
Nice
Another head scratcher
This is a
Product
It's Kathy
It's a product
It's called the omnific
And it's a device you stick on your keyring
Scotch apolos tracking software in it
And it
Has buttons on it that will let you do things like
That you can program to do
Turn your lights on
I don't know you're not excited about this
Too much only because it's a Kickstarter project and that doesn't mean I shouldn't be excited excited about those before
It's at a lower price right now it will be expect
Tip for $120
It's as you said that the Bluetooth locator power bi
Is a remote shutter button for your phone a panic button to send a preset text message in your GPS coordinates
Little mini flashlight
I guess
I sit here and look at this and say
My phone could really do all this and I carry my phone
Pretty much everywhere so why do I need to carry a fob to
Maybe it's just me by the person does not carry your phone everywhere so maybe
Something you're interested in
Baby and it also has an LCD screen
Which is worth noting cuz that helps you understand
And what exactly you're about to
To me it's like the Swiss army knife or one of those like Leatherman Multi-Tool
Some people need them
Some people
Don't I'm going to go with I don't need something like this nothing about this appeals to me
If you're the type of person who like wants to go running
Keysight
I don't know
I talked to them
And the guys that
Make this keeper
It is not a device for me it's probably a device for Subway
And if it's a device for you if you're like a Swiss army knife person the Leatherman Tool
But the digital equivalent of that then
Check this out
Yeah and your example is actually a good one because I I run and I often have a toenail to you can I could watch or something
That most people
Sade
But even so I don't think this has any Wi-Fi or LTE
Connectivity to a server
If you hit the panic button for example
It's going to need your phone to send the message
It's a head-scratcher
People who don't want to open their phone but just want a quick access to
Physical
I don't know
Not for us
Wait we've got one more head scratcher
Kevin
Why is Weis doing
A scale
This is
Actually it's not super
But why scale we've heard about this
Descale actually reach at the SEC so there's photos
It looks like a smart scale
I don't know how else to
This is a totally different direction for lies because it's no health-related
That leads me to believe they'll have more health-related products with a scale alone isn't going to
Do much other than you know send the data to your
For your phone
It's just a new
I can you plot twist in the wild strategy
Yeah and they are doing the pre-orders for their plug
Looks like
So if you are a y subscriber pre-orders
Set the plugged in Tuesday the 30th of July
And
You can check those
Out
Two plugs for twenty bucks is pretty good to I-5 closed
Yeah
There you go and I ain't a couple weeks ago said that this is a smart company
Smart home company to watch because I think it's cheap
Chinky
Is easy to experiment with this and let people play and it's pretty easy for
For people to actually implement
You don't Maybe
Health is a big
Market
Being able to monitor people from afar
Is probably
Useful for a lots of
And doing so
Cameras a little intrusive
But having a scale and maybe some
Sensors somewhere
Make sense
And heck
If I had a digital scale that was like 40 or 50 bucks I buy it
Not sold
Unlikely hundred
$100 scales that are out there that
Connect to like my Fitbit or my
Whatever
Other systems there are
I actually am
I mean I step on the scale so rarely
No I'm like
I can manually
I bought the Fitbit Aria and I do use it so
Long-term insights into my
Burgeoning belly instructions
Excellent
We'll see what happens
Some quick
News beds
Are you ready
Chloe
Vice president at Wawa
Chinese firm
Has confirmed that there OS is for the iot
Not for smartphone
This is notable because
Couple months ago
The US said hey don't use any quality stuff
Google is like
That's okay we have our own
Weather
Say that
So
Ndk
Beaver
Kunming OSS variety people
Trademarks and Sachin figured just assumed basically
It's going to be the Android replacement or Plan B for a while I so
Maybe I'll mango s is for iot
We don't know
Always founder said
I'm saying is not designed for phones as everyone thinks we didn't develop the OS
Replace Google
Google does withdraws iOS for Huawei we will need to start building an ecosystem because we don't have a clear plan
That's his quote
And that's pretty good
So maybe he's telling the truth that he would really like
All right
What else do we have we have Google assistance
They're better now
If you're using the Abode security system
Yeah that's good I think up till now you can only use the Google Assistant to control
Light switches and smart plugs
You can ask assistant you are Marigold system
And even disarm the security system
PIN code
The assistant commands also move beyond the original
Liberty devices now to include smart locks crossword
Router range of support on Abode for Google assistant voice commands
Voice command
Adobe has put out some new research related to their voice Summit
What is happening
This week
What they found is 91% of brands are already making a big investment
Improving the user experience
However
Most consumers are saying
Yes voice
Technologies easy-to-use but over half report that finding the process of using
Voice technology Nantes
And
49% say they
Don't necessarily know how to begin to accomplish a
And that makes sense that's things like hay
Madam a
Open blah blah blah to do
That's
And what a Dobby and actually Amazon's people are doing response
Need for boys designer
So this is a ux designer
Turquoise and
In Amazon is come out and said hey you should use things like storyboarding when you are designing a skill for madam
And that's what Adobe is talk about the US
Requirements
With the screen without a screen
And
I agree
I do think
Voice right now we are still at the very early stages we need the equivalent of
Like I was caught in a pinch to zoom for voice which is basically
A universal set of
Commands
That work for
Aperitif
Small setup
That makes sense I look beyond that and say with machine learning and AI
You should be able to ask
For something in
Any way shape or form that make sense to you and the system she correctly interpreted
But that's not today that is the future
Yeah
In part of it isn't the understanding of the speech it's time that speech back to
The API call or the app that needs to be
Engaged
Write to me it's context
The problem here isn't necessarily understanding
What we want
It's snowing how to implement that
Bingo
And that stuff for
Library
So
Pussy
Finally for those of you guys who are into
And you are also into LG
ATVs
Guess what
Your LG TV
Gets
Homekit enabled
Play
Apple music
On
And you can control the TV via Siri
It's pretty basic
But
We dishonor home care that it doesn't move forward enough and this is a step forward for people going
Go to the new LG TV
Really new TV
That
Feels like enough news for this experience with a new device
Let's do that and I will try to keep this short because
Hey there is so much to talk about
I have a written review of it
That you can go and see all the details and screenshots
Firewalla
And what is his
Depending on the model you purchase freezer 110 or $180
It
Basically
Monitor your home network
When I'm at home at work I don't just mean
What people are surfing on their phones and what you're watching on TV
But also
What servers your iot device data is going through because
We think we know where that's going to trust these companies to say that we're just going to take your data to make better products
Learn how to
Protect a person in from our webcam
Do you really know
You don't
You're kind of trust
With the fire wallet you really know because
It literally shows the entire network flow
Every device in your home
And shows
Where daddy is going the servers
Who owns the servers with the IP address of the servers are
Maybe has the
Ownership of the URLs I mean even what country and location
And luckily
After adding a firewall to my house
Defer my devices with going where I expected it to go so that's a good thing
But again I tend to buy the name brand stuff with
Friends I trust
This is a super small device it's literally the size of a USB phone charger it's really small
It's just a small processor and SD card for the operating system
Ethernet port to plug into your router and
USB for power
App that comes with it
Very very good
Literally shows you every device on your network
What the upload and downloads are the bandwidth used
And again where those devices are surfing to
Even what types of apps are using this gets into some of the aspects
But
If you're using social media a lot on your phone it will group activity by social media activity or email activity or
Messaging activity
In which case you can use some of the one touch control is to
Turn off all social networking on my network for an hour and have family time
Or maybe you want to block
Sites access to gaming sites or p******** or whatever you like
There's a ton of
Control such as that
Some other things that it has
It
Will surface alerts
Detect abnormal uploads or downloads from one device and interesting Lee
I get that other quite a bit from the June oven
That's only because firewall abnormal
So in the middle of the night maybe two Mega potato was set up to
AWS servers I found that out thinks of fire wallet because June now uses for AWS
You can block that any of its if you think it's abnormal you can block that from happening again or I just mute the June oven now because
I don't care that it's sending its data to
Lejeune folks
Yes indeed
Think of it as if it was sending my videos from my
A camera to submergence a China or Russia I would see that I could block it
And start wondering should I be using a device anymore
Very handy
Another Nifty feature
You get a built-in VPN server on this little box
And that is awesome because a you should be using a VPN server when you're out and about on public Wi-Fi
There's no subscription fee which is typically
Something that comes with a VPN server
Because a third party will have to operate a server
Since the servers in your house there's no fee
And even better
This was a huge concern I had
If I am out of town they live in another country say we're Netflix
How can I use this
You know how can I watch Netflix
Because the VPN servers in my home
Netflix thinks I am still at home in Pennsylvania
And therefore I can watch Netflix it would not block if I was in a country that does not support it so
No fees and the location of the VPN server is your home location
I love that that was
Huge concern
Where can I watch it
All of our all of our online content is online no more cable so
YouTube TV Amazon Prime that's about
It protects against malware there's a built-in ad blocker I turn that on
If we don't have to
Blockers on all of my individual devices
It's just off
How much
If you get the red version they're coming to Colors the red version is if your home internet speeds are
100 megabits per second or less
That is normally 129 I see it for 109 right now
I tested the blue firewalla which is for
Internet speeds
Approaching or Beyond 1 gigabit per second
Which is what happened to house at my house
4 speeds
That is normally 199 I see it for 179 right now
And just
To point out I did test it adding a firewall
Slows my home internet or my internal Wi-Fi
It didn't seem to I didn't lots of testing and in my house with my configuration
I don't see any noticeable
Speed difference
You may see that depending on the brand of router to use or the technology or
Your home's architecture I do not know but
I did not see that
I have to point out the one flaw that I found because it
We're going for
There's a known issue
When using fire wallet with Google Wi-Fi
They believe the company thinks it's related to how
Google either refresh Azar flushes it's DNS every 2 to 3 hours
And the reason
I knew about it was because every two to three hours after using this with my Google Wi-Fi
My home internet when have no access to the outside
It was
Crazy frustrating
Resolution for now
Which does work
Is to take you a Google WiFi access point
Put it into bridge mode
Which works however that means you've disabled Mesh networking over Wi-Fi and therefore I have a Google Wi-Fi
Fastest plane
Your mouth is doing absolutely nothing
I got to say
Frustrating as it is to not have my with Mesh networking coverage
I am so impressed by this product that I almost don't mind
Wow
And I'm looking at this and I'm like okay I'm paying ten bucks to Eero for monitor
This actually offers me more
So
I got a hundred twenty bucks a year going to Eero
And that could be for the foreseeable future
Which Year by the way is
Amazon
And I'm like
Oh you know for a hundred eighty bucks maybe I just
On this for a while
It sounds better
Yeah I mean I don't think and I don't know for sure cuz I don't have any row but I don't think you can monitor down to the
Low-level all the way through to the end servers
I can see data have
It has the ad blocker it has parental
What controls but I can't see the level 2
Which you can see
Let's put it this way if you don't want to see that level of detail I'm sure
You do and I do but not everybody does so what I'm going to say is
If you're happy with the network monitoring that you have in place today
No, I wouldn't buy this
Unless you want to add a VPN or have those fine-grained controls
Spitfire wallet
If you want the net worth of clothes for your device date is going
There are other options you could build your own you could run a Raspberry Pi to monitor Network traffic
But this is really well done from an end-user standpoint with the app that
I probably wouldn't bother building I would just get this
Got it will thank you so much Kevin for testing that out for us I will link to the review in the show notes
And now it is.
The Internet of Things podcast
Hotline
Where we take your voicemails and we answer
Your question
The hotline is sponsored
Buy Schlage
Slade's wide variety of Smart Lock
Let's let you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions and compatibility with Amazon's apples and Google products
All that plus or at schlage.com
Iot
Okay
The sweeper combining basically to voicemail
And
You'll hear
One from Dean and then we have another question from Richard
Who's
Doing for something slightly Sims
So
Let's go
PlayStation Kevin
Totally love your show
I am Dean I live in Minnesota
I real simple question but I
Sing to find the answers on eye
Search this
I use Hue Lights
In my house and
As a gift I was given
Three more to which I use
For my
Lights on the outside on the garage in the entryway
What is the safe
Is it safe car what are the risks
Whether it be Heat
Or as we can experience Minnesota extreme cold
Keeping them out there or is there any
And if not what are some options without adding
Other
Devices
Father system
My iot world
Thanks the time
Bubba Show
Talk to you later
Alright so we have
Question out there in
Frozen Frigid North
And Richard
Had a similar question which was about smart outdoor lights and battery powered switches
He was trying to avoid a hug but I don't think
First step
Deed
Hue Lights
They are lovely
I love them
There only one pair of hue outdoor lights
The par38
Those are rated to use down
-4 degrees
Which
Provident Credit in Minnesota
Yeah that's your outdoor lights if you're using an indoor light outdoor there rated to use to -10 degrees
Celsius which is 14 degrees
Which I know.
Brexit would be fine here
In Seattle
But that's one
That's what they're rated for they may work in lower temperatures but you're obviously you're taking a chance
Yeah so we did not find
A lot of smart
Puerto Rico Primus net worth
That's just a function of
She will also offers a few outdoor
Pictures
But we could not find
At their ip44 rated which protects against debris
But we could not find information about temperature
So
The bottom line is I'm not sure how those are going to fair in your
Hirsch Minnesota
Feel free to let us know
If you guys have a harsh winter and have Hue Lights deployed outside
Talk to us about them
Otherwise
There's not a lot of options
One option is
Keeping your
Old balls in swapping out
For a smarter switch that might be in
Protected
Area
But that involves playing
Dealing with
Richard
Who is a related voicemail he wanted
Smart outdoor lights and a battery-powered switch because his house has terrible wiring
So he would like
Switch inside that
Controls outdoor
He wanted
Because of power consumption
There are no Wireless WiFi switches
That we can find
An option is Bluetooth
I don't know how far away
Star from your switch
My best
Recommend
Station
Was actually
To do
He's in Massachusetts so there are temperature construe
Prince here as well but
Is to do maybe the Hue bulbs outside
Especially if they're honest like a protected enclosure
And get the $25
Light switch that can be mounted to a wallet
Control those ball
Now
That does require buying a hue hub
If you don't want to do that you want to watch near a tub
I would recommend doing
A SmartThings Hub
And then do a zigbee
Z-Wave switch indoor to control
The lights can be Wi-Fi power they can be whatever you want as long as they work
SmartThings
A couple of options therapy
Publicist
Really tough
Publison Wi-Fi
WiFi stuff for battery power
Constraint
Purposes
And so if you don't want to plug something in
Wireless is tough
And
Publicis. Smith you can't do by Fire Bluetooth
Bluetooth is tough because of
Brain tissues
Psy
The smart home is still an ongoing effort
All right
Don't call this Mark Thomas The Helpful hunt That's right The Helpful Home full of ambient Computing is still an ongoing effort
I just doesn't have
If you would like us to answer your question
On the hotline
You can call us at 5 1/2
6 to 3
7 4
Too far
And
You will be entered to win
A Schlage lock
If
You call us before July 31st at midnight
Pause after that point
You're going to be after doing some
And no
Stay tuned
For our guest Jana welinder of
Craftable
Crossville is a brand new company launching today the bills apps for companies that don't want to do
Their own
And we talked about why that might be necessary the advantages disadvantages
This whole business
After
A words
From our sponsor
This would sponsor is Dell Technologies
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week
How far is Dell Technologies and today
We're doing by Brian Jones was a general manager for the OEM and iot solutions
@delta
Brian
I understand you were also recently asked to serve as one of the executive sponsors
4 Dell Technologies iot and Edge bed
Can you briefly share with us how your group
Is helping cost
Thanks for having me on it's really great to have an opportunity to chat with you
So from an oem perspective focused on
Helping them take their IP combined it with our technology and create a new product that they take tomorrow
In our customers have been doing iot since long before
Iot had a name
Natural place to help with the iot and Edge of division
And so what we do is we really help customers focus on and deliver three things
Help them to press their time-to-market
So they focus on their it we focus on
The technology platform in the integration of the two
The second piece is really delivering tier-1 technology
And that should one technology gets them the very best Quality Inn
Customer experience
And then the last piece is one of their multinational or they're a small software startup we help them scale globally reduce
Cost and complexity
And taking their product to a global market
Excellent
And I understand that your division
Is pretty
Compared to what most of my audience thinks about when they think about Dell Technologies
They're thinking servers NPCs but your division focuses more on Factory floors than Data Center
It's ot not it
Is that right
That's right
Example of an oem customer is their developing software
So a lot of
CAT scan for medical devices
They're developing the software in the actual CAT scan device itself but all of that needs to run on a server
Maybe it's very hard
Operational environment high temperature dust
Vibration and so we help them develop the platform
Wanted days in any great into their solution
Still put your logo on it and they sell it out to their customer as their insulin
Okay and so how does your OEM division
Really help those cost
Get ahead
We are really focus on first
The it that they're developing is at
And we help them surround that it with the right technology classes
And we're drawing from all of Dell technology
Two notches Deli and seeing Hardware but also VMware
Everything that makes up Dell Technologies is part of the pallet that we can help a customer
Paint your product picture front and so at the Dell Technologies level
Hardware software Services program management engineering
All of that together too
Creating that new product based on their IP and our technology
But that customer then takes the market
Awesome
So we're kin folks
Let's go to learn
For more information
Inforce Solutions
Go out to Dell EMC. Com
Hey everyone
Would welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham and today's guest is yellow
Skylander who is co-founder and CEO of
I'm grateful excited to be here
Awesome
So you would reach out to me
About your startup which was founded this year has to work it if
And
What is it that you guys are doing at
So we provide
User-friendly mobile app for home company so that they can stay focused on building Great Park
Light companies
Gboss
Lutron
Hardware over the digital music
Hardware store
In-house expertise in software and the results is usually a lot of
Put some apps that have a few download
Square app store rating
Even the nest
Weekend Hardware companies the experience of having their own Silicon Valley software team
Providing white label app on the cloud service
Upgrade analytics to help
Improve the odds
Overtime
Device-based
Feedback
Gold generally has to make the digital interface
More user-friendly and accessible more people
And enjoy the benefits of smart home devices
That is a lot of things to think about I will agree with you 100%
Bad experiences from Hardware people
In fact I feel like I have tried
Couple devices
Are awesome and
15 spine or like you know what we're just going to do it cuz we don't even want to mess with
I feel you on this
I think it's probably hard how do you set this to someone do you just go up to the lake
Illusion and say hey
Your app is really tired
I think a lot of
Hardware Enterprises
I understand that we're moving to a world where
Every product
I will be connected and they need to get to my cat's first with the best Schenectady
And so a lot of these companies when we're talking with them
We are cleaning out the things that can be done better and how we are providing
A good user experience but
Generally they see that mean
They don't have available to develop
And they know that focusing on both hardware and software
Chris Hart
Digital first companies Commission
Decipher gas card so generally they're excited about the opportunity to gift someone to support
Which their mobile app so that they can focus on their heart or Friday
I think sometimes though
Bad Hardware also leads to poor apps
So I'm sure that every time the nest app goes down
Or the thermostat gets cut off from the cloud from
Server issue
I will take it out here
But I thought it'd be great to talk to you given that you're
Design-centric kind of thinking and
We had a good conversation earlier about
Where companies have gone wrong so far in selling the smart
I think it's really interesting because we're in this place right now where we had all this hype and excitement and
Power users coming in and kind of dictating the terms of
A lot of apps
And I'm not sure that that's really helping other people
Adopt the smart
So first talk to me about
Where you see mainstream
Adoption
That's a great point because
Right now
I think
And the biggest
Change that is coming for smart
Are getting cheaper and cheaper
You know connected light bulb it's pretty much
Cross the same as regular lights
I'm going to start using some devices
That means image option is going to challenge
Up until now
Complicated you exposed because they're going to be poking around until they find what they're looking for
And sometimes even kind of enjoy
Cracking
That's not obvious problem mainstream users are not going to have that technical savviness for the patient
Stop music smart home companies movie
Need to get
Much more user-friendly
He said that audience
Just being able to
Show the benefits of the Nile
Quickly
The benefits of a connected device quickly it shouldn't take you that long to set up a device Paula shouldn't take you that long to
Starting the key features in the eye
What are some good design principles where do you think
The focus of
An app for lighting for example
What time building I lighting
Product what should I be looking for
For I know that I and I'm kind of a power user but I'm also really lazy
So I'm like
What do I really want
Out of my ass
What do you think
Yeah I think what we've seen is a lot of fact that are good at
Leveraging intuitions that you could have built up from attracting but
Provides for a better
To turn on and off traditional light switch with dimmer at the laptop model that behavior
Instead of inventing interface with users never-seen-before tend to be more intuitive a big thing for a smart
Is that the most common use cases they're basically replacing a switch on the wall
They need to be to make up most common interaction
As simple as possible as simple as just like walking over
New Orleans
In flipping a switch
Really easy to connect the life you wrote about how he did
Wasn't
Consumers
About devices
Setting up a wife caption require you to get familiar with the entire ecosystem
Don't forget that
Similarly
I think that I'm boarding
It's important
Mobility 2
Use the lights without much configuration siwa has done a good job in reading on thereafter
Yes
That's the one thing that you just really love
Are default installation to start using and don't
Need to do a lot of work
On the flip side
Surfacing the on-off switch on the home screen is really important
Complain when
They can't find Zora takes them a few clicks to get the on-off switch with a dimmer
Make
Purchasing additional light bulbs
Myprovident
The musician like
Well that's cool and all but I've already bought one light bulb and I want to be able to control
Before I buy additional
Okay so let's break some of that down cuz some of its Universal like onboarding
I feel like individual ecosystems are getting better about onboarding
Like the busy way folks they have there
I can't think of the name of it right now to get things online Amazon has an effort there
If you buy a product from them it and automatically be linked to your existing Wi-Fi credentials if you have given them to it
How do we make onboarding
Easy especially for devices that may not have asked
That's a good question anything cuz I'm waiting can be made easier by just making sure that the
Letter sent out
NBA Park clearly
Defined a lot of apps
I feel like they've always been designed for a difference
Device
Because it doesn't refer to
The specific like what you're doing
Feels like
A generalized interface design for any kind of connector
The device
Just covering all the different bases
Wedding expectation
Clearly
This could be
Much clearer
Sometimes you don't need to have that many
That's another
If something goes wrong for you
But if make me feel like you're done pumping
On the flip side it could be like sisters
Actually something that the user could do differently in
Then they should be there and it should be very clear
Could be improved by making sure that
Clear concise language that applies specifically to
Yes I have had mystery error messages
Let's talk about the business
Ecosystem that you're into
Because
It honestly feels to me
Like designing a nap it feels like maybe a
Feature not necessarily a full-on product
For a company if I'm like Whirlpool I'm already talking to
A2 yarndale are some other company to provide my cloud back in baby I've got
Another company doing my business Analytics
Now I bring you into
Make my app
App for
Consumers
How do you see that evolving
I think a lot of
The platforms that are customers
Already
Used today
We do work alongside the existing system
Babcock McCallum place
More often those are especially system
Since that are supporting product
Caribbean Market
Cancel our goal is
To help
Customers with upgrade
Give experience
One half of the experience that they're offering their own music
The device connect
Smart's from dealership
Plugging into the the system that they haven't placed with their working
Already are working with
Sun platform
We're offering them a partial solution so that they can continue working with the it's our job
To help them with
Customer experience
Not to make restricted
Technology or platform recommendation
If I'm a company trying to
Look at this and like I asked you know I feel like I can build an app
What else do you guys
Offer
Solution is a complete software Solutions so we support everything.
About the software on the device itself
. include
The
Square both IOS and Android
And then we have cloud services
Support those apps will think about that
Like push notification
Location services
ICloud
Dentist appointment provide that as well and then we also provide analytics. Using contractions
Jeff Graham.
And also machine learning analysis of quote the review
The book where the specific
And also other apps in the same category when looking at how are you there
Responding to
Provide recommendations
Batman
Makes a ton of sense and I assume you guys also will update the app
Overtime
And do you handle things like
Don't know security vulnerabilities and thinking about like how to patch that
Yeah
We definitely are offering include regular updates to be
Any kind of
Regular things that happened across the board like a new operating system
Specifically for security though
We obviously
Follow all of the best practices
Data
Interested in a trust anonymizing analytic data requesting granular permissions in the butt
Makes classical unique is that we leverage our economies
Yogurt to build
Picture features one and then share that functionality with all the apps
Picture apps that when you're starting from scratch
You really need to
Toyota 7-seater
In that context it's really easy to understand why so many
Have struck a bad balance when it comes
Security
What you get
You're the best experience baidu
Does your Apple benefits from something like
Two-factor off you'll have that from
The one
And it's basically like a no-cost decision
That is related
Setting so I think that level of is kind of like standardization or expertise in this area I think is really important
Ye all right
Can you talk about any of your customer
Quick question
Cancel
But what I can say is
Collaborating with around a dozen of the biggest
Household.
To help them with
For things like my thermostat
Various home appliances Fortune 500 company
Established in the traditional
Hardware device Beijing
At some point in their digital transformation Journey but it's also kind of some devices he's talked about.
Early on
You were formed this year
Have you raised any fun
We are backed by y combinator Argo obviously has to be a a b c
Currently funded by, but I think there's a big
In a way. Operating as an agency or developing
My shop wouldn't allow us to cheat with
It's crucial for us to be ABC.
So it doesn't seem like a super scalable business bottle though it does seem more like an agency business model
So how do you plan to make that way
Work for adventure
The way we work as bait
Traditional agency model we start from a
Aux flow that is optimized
For the best music experience in a particular category like light for thermostat
And then we add additional support for distinct features
In
And the customers
Hardware
And then we apply visual identity and branding on top of that which means that we are actually building these.
Got it awesome
Alright thanks so much
For coming on the show this week
I really appreciate it thank you for having me
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening
I remembered if you'd like more iot news sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot
Will see you next week