Hey everyone welcome to the 224th episode of the internet
Net of things podcast this is your host Stacey Higginbotham
And your co-host
Kevin tofel
And we have a stellar chauffeur
Are you today we are going to be talking about the latest in Z-Wave
Less version 2
What does that mean
It's a bad news on the
Medical front
Going to say as per usual
Plus I just tried out the why is light bulbs I'm going to tell you a little bit about those so you know what to expect
And we've also tried out the wise
People detection
Woop woop
Plus
We're going to be talking about some tradfri updates Nest hello updates
New device from
ATT Life Shield program
And Google's developer preview of local home control is now
Live
Also
I tried out the Amazon Echo Auto
Finally
All about it
We'll also hear from our sponsor Dell Technologies
It's actually in Telugu
Talk to us this week
And
Our Guest this week is
Good night
Diddy from
Relare
And he's going to talk about
Basically Financial engineering
For the iot and getting around this whole capex Apex thing when we start selling every
Living as a server
It's fun complicated and you will
Want to listen
If you want to know what's a
So
Let's get this party started with a message from another one of our sponsors
This week sponsor is a pharaoh are you doing multiple iot projects that are
Going to work well together
In a single app to strengthen your brand
It's a really tough so it requires the right platform and a pharaoh is the one to choose
With a pharaoh Kenmore launch 42 smart Appliance models in 2 years
Barrel customers have experienced as much as an 80% reduction in time to Market
99% pure support calls and 10x higher activation rate plus they can
We use 90% of their work from one project to the next pick up Arrow just like him more Mitsubishi Bank
D-Link did it beat your competition with a solution that your team loves to build and your customers love to you
Use learn more at a pharaoh go big
Rite Aid
Let's get
Heineken
Kevin
So
Parsnip
Let's talk about the new Z-Wave plus version 2 certification
Good
Lord
For those of you guys are like what
Z-Wave is one of the connection Technologies we talked about
It's like a zigbee and that it's a mesh
And
It is
Well is it
Proprietary I'm going to say yes
The
Chip company that makes zwave chips is silicon Labs now
Originally
And
I like it I have lots of Z-Wave gear in my house
Most people seem to be moving away
Play from it but
It's still out there and it will probably be out there for
For quite some time
I'm so
This is basically the latest update
This is for anything built on the
Next Generation Z Wave
What is has is SmartStart it is now required
And Smart Start is where you buy a device
And
You can connect it
Automatically is pre-registered
For your existing Z-Wave Network so if you buy something from like Amazon
It will connect to your
Device that Sardinia
So
Yay on that
Do you have to scan something I think
You do scan
QR codes right
Other thing it does
Is it allows you to have
A light
So all of these devices will have
A device identification through an LED light on the product
Confirm to people that the Hub is correctly set up and pairing in that sort of thing
This sounds silly
But as someone who has installed and reinstalled many a Z-Wave device
I can tell you that that light is actually really help
I have these Jasco outdoor switches
And that you just press a button and you're like
I hope it's connected
I don't know
When you have the light like when I'm pairing to my wink Hub which does have a lie
I've always a little bit more relieved
When I'm pairing to something
It doesn't
Just like
Hope it a prayer guy
You just don't know what's happening at the time you know the app
That you're using to maybe pair this
Device it's like spending and spending there's no notification so this is a huge
Huge benefit from a setup process
And
This is
The second version of Z-Wave
Plus and Z-Wave Plus
Came out
April of 2 years ago actually
And
That was all about security
And securing your zeal
It's in this
SB
Z-Wave Plus
Persian to Dido
It continues with that but
Basically those two things we talked about
Which is allowing you to more easily set up these devices
Is WhatsApp
Sukhumvit Smart Start
Everything
It does
In
Why not
Sounds a lot like summer
Other smart
Smart
Start
Okay
So
Look for that
Z-Wave device
Okay
Morphin
Let's talk about
Scary hosp
Little news Kevin
Yeah it sounds scary in the surface and it's not a good thing but I don't think anybody's been actually hurt by this
Healthcare security firm cyber MDX
Has reported that the protocol and certain GE devices that
AR
Used with
Anesthesia and respiratory machines
Can kind of be hot
Taxi very easy Homeland Security
Here in the US actually release an advisory saying with the flaws
Required low-level skill deck
Exploit
Basically if you know your way around terminal another ride commands you could silence alarms on the machines you could alter
The records
And this is the scariest part of it although again
I'm you could actually change the composition of
Aspirating
Gases in both of these devices which
I mean I guess you can make somebody
Sleep a lot longer or
I didn't want to go there but you could probably do that by removing other oxygen
I am the evil
Yeah so what
Not good she is actually said that
Yeah it knows about it and they said we determine that the
Potential implementation scenario
For such a hack doesn't really introduce clinical Hazard to direct patient risk
I don't know about that I continue to do something about this
Even if they do something
The medical is a tough
Because medical devices
Even if the device manufacturer Shoji in this case fixes it
An issues a patch may not actually
Download
In talking to both cesos at hospitals
Companies in the medical device space I am
Kind of appalled at the lack of rigor around
Patching in
There I know for a fact that there are unpatched
Vulnerable devices in Benny
Us hospitals
Actually talk to somebody on the show
A few months back from a security firm who
He told us about
A hospital that
Discovered one of their
Infusion pumps was
Hackable
And that
There was a vulnerability out there that
People were exploiting
And they had to actually put a nurse
Next to the patient who had that particular
Pump on the
At the time
They mistakenly use that pump and so then they had to have a whole person sitting there making sure that
The patient didn't die
Which
That is not scale
So
The only good news and
I'm trying to make
Some good news out of this
Gaskin City hack
Is only on anesthesia devices sold prior to 2009
So that's a good thing however I know that
Devices don't get updated like every year in the hospital as well so I'm sure there's a bunch of these still out there
Oh yeah
Alright let's move to something more fun
Let's talk about why there's two big updates
Trump lies
One everyone got
Or everyone should have
Is the availability of
Person detection
71a tells about the
I actually just
Updated the firmware on my wyze cam and I should say this is only for wyze cam version 2
Were the pancam that they sell so if you have the original wyzecam
You do not have this feature but
Once you update your firmware
You get a new
Option to enable person detection
Which is powered by you say if they see cuz I
I don't want to
Axon or x n o r.
This is
On device person detection which is awesome
Something worth the edgemoore Machine Vision at the ads
So I have a wyzecam
Obviously because I update the firmware
And I get
Tons of notifications so many that I turned it off because the motion detection
Trips
Notification system all the time and usually it's just a car driving by my house
I don't care really
Frankly about that I do want to know when there are people around my house or walking up to the house and that's a person detection will do
And in fact
You can even just hit a button in the wyze cam app
Angie
Only see person
Notifications and events which is awesome so
I'm not going to be flooded with him and turn my notifications back on solely for person detection
Well and you know what you can also do they have an away mode in an honorable
You can also
Organize your
Notifications by that so if your
In
Non away mode it won't send you anything
But when you click away
Since I'm really never away
Oh that is you
That's just me so what you're right for people who have normal life and leave the house everyday and come home
Good idea but for me I want the notifications all the time because I'm always home
That's right and if you're looking for people around
Your house this makes much more
Alright I like him too
So
That's free
Just enable it on your wife
The other thing
Is I was one of the early purchasers of their smartphone
So I got those yesterday
And
I paid a total of 4140
44 bulbs
The
Shipping and tax return
Yes tax and shipping
Your lists price is going to be 2999
And these are tunable White
Bulbs with dimmer
So
I set them up their wifi-enabled
So you can just have
Don't even think you need a wyze camera
I wouldn't think you need
Annie
Hanging Minister supported by
Matinee
The chi
You should be okay with that
So
I just occurred to me I'm like I have a wyze camera so I just
But when I set it up it was just a straight-up
Install Wi-Fi bulbs so
I put the bulbs in
They are lovely
The lake quality is good
The Deming quality is good I don't get Flickr
When I'm dipping
Lower
Did you hear any humming
Check right now
Let's all listen
Right now
I don't hear any humming
Yeah
So no humming
You can group your lights
You can
Do some weird schedule
So here's the thing this is Early Access I think everybody will be able to buy them at some
Point soon
So
I'm hoping we see a little bit more refinement here
Right now I can
Turn the lights off
Ouran after a certain number of hours but I can't schedule something like
Days and times
So that's a little weird for weird
It it's like
Turn them on
X number of hours and minutes
Not like turn them on at 8 a.m.
Sound like
8 a.m. would be 23 hours from now
So that's
Bizarro
But
They do let you
Do scenes so you can set your
I created a bright day and a
Warm night
Scene
So and then I can activate those by talking to my Google assistant or Madam a
Because wise integrates with both of those
The other thing I can't do that surprised me
I have the wise sense sensors
And I was hoping to be able to
Do a motion detection because this is a much cheaper option than the
My Hue motion.
Detection
So I was hoping to do it so like when the light
Either when motion is detected or when a contact sensor opened and closed
I would be able to turn the light on
And then also have it
Turn off after certain time
Minutes
But I can't do that yet
Sounds good
Doesn't it
Because the sensors are not yet communicating with
And I don't know
The can't be a trigger event for anything but a notification
Or
Turning the camera
Honor off
Right
Now
I can't do vacation
If I turn that on its going to turn my wise bulbs on and off so it looks like I'm
Which is nice
I find it weird that that's called vacation mode
Yen isn't part of away mode
But you know
I'm just going to roll with it
Because I think this is early
Yeah it mean if you have Early Access end
The software and firmware updates just
Running to support this and also.
It sounds like there's still things in the works you could
Use the motion sensor
Where
EFT
Yes
I'm trying to simplify my life here
Are people I am not
I'm done with
I need native is always better and we'll talk about why a little bit actually another one of our top
So
Let's move on
Little bits of news
Hello
Yeah this is interesting on 95 Google routinely looks at Android app
Packages basically the software you install
It's called an APK file
They open these things up using Android studio and other
It's a software
And they look and see what's coming
Because
Google will usually
Put certain bits of information in there about future features to prepare for them
And the one I found was package detection which I love this I forget it
Package protection for nest hello
And what this
Will do according to the data that's currently in the nest hello
App with an s that I should say
Is it will
Tag your hello doorbell footage when it thinks a package was delivered and or picked up
So that's very cool because
Sometimes I get
Like I said before notifications too many notifications say from my cameras
When morning was actually very important but I can't tell the difference between
So this sounds awesome
It's
Not sure if this will come to pass or when it will
Looks like Google is actually working on it
Yay
Show me the nest aware subscription just so you know for this
Just just saying
Let's go for a cheaper
A less Rich option
Ikea's
Crabtree
I can't do it you guys I'm sorry for all the I can't people who listen or the Swedish people who listen
Tradfri
So
What do we have
We have some new products nootropic products a filament style light bulb
That's either a19 or e26
A19 is the normal light bulb size
The king 826 is
Itsy 26
Yes
So the bulb
$16 has three different color temperatures
Temps on porch light
806 lumens of brightness obviously works with the chakra system
Also a candelabra
E12 base color and white light bulb
$30
Yowza
That's expensive
Answer
I know
I know but they're so small
You should be paying less for that topic
Anyway and one other
Interesting I'm going to say this wrong when interesting product
The float float alt maybe it's blowout
Light panels
They're similar to what maybe like Nana race mix
They're bigger
Have all the cool fancy pictures of Natalie
Can house
But they so you can get a square Light Panel 12 by 12 for $70
You would like it
Square white panel is 129
And then finally a 12 x 35 inch panel also for 129
So against three different color temperatures Warm Glow Warm White and cool White
Nice
I think with those kind of light panels I think
Colors are super
But that's cuz I use mine
Art installation
Yeah we have the microphone as well which of the light panels change colors based on what it hears
Yo
Okay so
I should tell you
The wise light bulbs are 800 lumens for
For the people who are counting their lumens
So there
But they're cheaper
Yay
What's cheaper
They're not homekit compatible but the freezer
All right
Brighter homekit compatible
Adjust the to nobility
Is
Truncated
Slightly slightly joinable
Fully dimmable
Alright so
Next up also doorbell news
Exciting doorbell news if you are a member of the ADT
Lifeshield
Which is beta program which
Program I don't run
Lifeshield is
A
DIY
Program for ADT that lets you buy products connector products
Dual monitor
Bring in that sort of thing
So
They have released a new HD video doorbell
Yay has 2-way audio
It has people detection
It has 180 HD resolution video 170 degrees weidler
That's actually pretty good
Many stop it
35 or 1/4
And
You can
Locations in
So
It's not cheap
It's not
How much is it
It's $200
That's that's pretty money in the nest hello is
Isn't that true
Where is one more expensive
But it also works
System
Right now you can get the nest hello for 189
There you go
If you want it if you want to try the doorbell do anything with
The lifeshield HD video don't you have to use
If it's from that
Can
Really do much
So if you've already
He got your own system
Maybe deal with either ringer
Nest
PayPal Amazon
It pains me to say that
Depending on Amazon
But
Speaking of Google
Let's talk about local home
Control
Yes and this gets back to what I said earlier about Native
Voice type
Activities at Rio Google IO back in May
They showed off
Renounce I guess I should say they're local SDK
Basically what that does is
It's a way for device makers in the Google ecosystem Google St
Allowed
Local
Processing of
Smart home commands
Weed States and so on
So what that means is instead of going out to the cloud every time to process language in commands
Which can take some time
It'll happen Basie on a
Google home device
Somebody
Previews out now they've already announced the early Partners which is
GE
Lifx Philips Hue tp-link and WeMo
None of those Partners have announced any local home support yet
Although I'm sure they got access to this before the developer preview in life
This week
So hopefully very soon we will
See local home commands
I would fall back to the cloud
In the Google home ecosystem
I'm hoping I'm going to see if I can find some time to try
INXS one of the apis for one of these
Device makers and
Actually test it and time
The local versus the cloud-based commands
Nice alright
If it's anything based on like Google's local voice transcription
That is so much faster in
It's so cool
I'm serious
All right
And now
I thanks to a wonderful listener thing
I have been testing an echo
Auto
Which I had wanted forever because I wanted the Amazon Echo in
In my car
My car happens to be a Tesla which is not play nicely with a lot of the other
Android 8 doesn't play nice with Android auto
Or
What's the other one
Are plecos like apples something
And so I was like really excited because I constantly I have questions like I'm thinking in the car and I'm like
What was that what date was that
Battle of
How many teeth does a cat have
Yeah just
Just silly question
I don't mind just never sleeps
It shouldn't sleep I'm driving okay
So I tested this out
It works basically from your phone
So it creates a constant Bluetooth connection to your phone
And what it does is it allows you to do
Calling
Send text messages and it has all the basic features of Madame a so I can
The weather icon
Commute times I can ask
Keep the cat hats
So all of that is available now
In my car
And it
Also
Hook me up to Spotify and granted I had this in my car cuz I have a Bluetooth
Connection to my phone
But it's really cool cuz
In might and I drive a Tesla so in my Tesla I can say
I press a button on my steering wheel and I say
Play
Mega Sonic on El Toro by Rosalie
And
It will
Play that
Sometimes
It's a little nip
It's a little fussy and it doesn't work from Spotify it works from
Different service
Recall the name of the service
The comes with the Tesla
But now
I just say
Matinee
Play Con El Torah
And
You don't have to have to hit the voice button on your steering wheel for that
I don't hit the voice button and it's pulling from Spotify
Which is
Awesome because I'm already at
Like I prefer Spotify to whatever
The Tesla has because it doesn't always play the song he wants sometimes a try something
Close to it
So yeah
I was really excited
Unleavened
The downside
The cost the cost is not downside itsfunneh
The downside is
I'm having trouble
It's only works when my phone is in the
Car repair
Amazon says I can bring in
Another phone
Like my partner's phone for example
And it will pair two
His phone
It basically connects to the last phone that was in the
Car with most bones are present
Into parrot you're supposed to be able to say
Madam a
Pair
That does not seem to work
At this moment
In time so we have not been able to
Parrot yet
To his phone
But theoretically it's possible
When I figure out why this isn't work
I'll let y'all know
Or if you have paired to phone successfully
I don't think that's a huge
Issue though because typically if it's your car you're the primary driver you want this
Echo 2
Be connected to your phone if I'm a passenger I can open up my matinee happen
Hit a button and do all the same things when I'm not driving
So
I don't think it's a huge issue but maybe others will disagree
I just think the seamlessness is now
Nice when you think you could just
Walk-in in
Works for you in it
We also share
Like if you share a car
Which we do cuz all right we've been electric in
Combustible
Gatsby c i c e
And so we tend to drive the elect
Vehicle whatever we
Cancel
We don't have to get gas
But that's just us
It's a little specific but I know there's lots of people who do share
Like a minivan with all the car seats in
Those people probably
Don't trade the car seats out all the time anyway
Know that going in
When I figure out how to solve that
I will let you know it'll probably be up
It's part of my exhaustive review
So
Stay tuned for that
Okay and Kevin
Now
I feel like it's time for the voice mail what do you think
I think so
All right
For those of you guys who are curious this is the Internet of Things podcast hotline where you call us and
Ask us your questions and we
Pick one to answer
When we listen to it
We're also putting you in the running
For a
Slay
Lock
So you can
Call us in the enter to win a Schlage lock at the end of the month we will
Pick a winner
So
Give us a call at 5 1/2
7 4
A24
And maybe you'll have a chance to win
The hotline is brought to you by Schlage
Legs wide variety of smart locks lets you create the smart home of your dreams
Learn more about Schlage Smart Home Solutions Inc
Compatibility with Amazon
Apple and Google products
Atchley
DACA
/ iot
This week we have a question from Jerry
Who's looking for a smart
Button
Let's hear it
Palatable
With my day
All right Sherry
Actually
You already have most of what you need because you said you have SmartThings if you want
A button for scenes
Samsung actually makes a SmartThings button
It works topically natively with
The SmartThings Hub that you have
Cost $15
Which is not too expensive
And you can program it to do whatever you like could be for seeing that could be for
Turning lights on and off
Anything that you would like to program
So that's
Actually the way I would go
I originally had thought about the fibaro button just cuz it's a really nice-looking button
Looks more like a button
But
It's not
Natively supported that I know of you may have to install like a separate device Handler for SmartThings for that
Probably wouldn't bother that I would just go out and spend 15 bucks on the
On the Samsung SmartThings button
You can even have a bunch of different
Actions on it like a double click does one thing a single click does another
Press and hold or something else so one button can do multiple things for her
I was going to offer an even more expensive option
Just because that's me
Especially if you have a lot of
Of things this Airtech
They make a lot of
Z-Wave stuff
They sell a Z-Wave button
That is their minimote to it is $45 but you can control 8 scenes
If you have eight whole scenes and you don't want to buy
History of the SmartThings buttons
Actually that's the same
Cost so
I really don't know why you would buy this
Let's just go
Like I really flummox but if you want
A smart button that is a reliable smart button
I've used it
Control
Actually the problem I have with
The smart button
Is
A lot of them
Control many scenes and then I can
Never forget what
I'm supposed to be like
4 klicks plus a right click + left click in a shake
Turn these lights on
I just go with voice
But this one is rechargeable
So you can either recharge it via a USB which is nice or there's a battery
And I don't know about the SmartThings one if it's rechargeable but you could end up buying a lot of battery
Hibiscus
Using a smart button is fun
And you tend
Run out the battery in
I think I run out my battery in
Bees in about 6 months
Probably this is a rechargeable battery
Cr2450 battery replace
So
Those are your options
There's tons of Z-Wave buttons out there there's tons of zika
B button spec
If you have SmartThings you have that
Enjoy
Let us know actually what you
I'm curious if anyone buys the
All right that feels pretty good for
This week show please stay tuned
For Goonies
BD
Who is going to talk about
How companies were trying to sell their products as a service can match their revenue stream
Dreams in the future and the role of insurance on the
Corporate Industrial
Coyote size
So
All of that and more
Is coming up
After a message from our sponsor
Hey everyone we are taking a quick break from The Internet of Things podcast for a message from our sponsor this week sponsor
Is Dell Technologies and I have
Craig Wetzel
Who is director of iot channels
Intel
Here to talk to you about their relationship with Dell
So Intel Works closely with Dell Technologies as they've been building their Edge and iot business for the last few
How would you describe that partnership
Saudi Dell Intel relationship
Has had a long history success
Starting with the first PCS that Michael Dell created in his dorm room we've worked together on
Desktops in
Servers and Anna conversion for structures in Cloud Solutions in
Together along this journey
It's been very tight-knit and close
And now we're moving into the iot
SeaWorld together
And this engagement with Delta critical one
Specifically when we collaborate a Numark
It's like a coyote
Dell has their seven individual companies
And David able to use the technology to create function-specific capabilities
Stickley brought together
To make complete list
Solutions
As you know iot Solutions aren't created using a
Single
Electronic Solutions are created by different layers of technology and products coming together which allow customer not just
To collect data
But use it for businesses
With Dell we have partnered with an organization that has the
Key infrastructure and capabilities to which our partners and customers
Can add that analytics another pieces
Jamaica complete solution
Can you give us an example of where Dylan and tell if collaborated to deliver a solution into the iot market
Actually let me give you two examples of our joining key
In one case Dylan until work
Together with a large
US city
Templum in a situational awareness solution
It will allow the city to implement a matrix
Cue components from cameras to servers
To collect and analyze data
Those analytics create actions that provide one
AC4 living and working condition for residence
To better management planning for infrastructure improvements
Reduce pedestrian-vehicle traffic
+ 3
Provide additional analytic insights that were needed to make better
By the city's urban planners in short the collaboration improve the lives of
The city's residents today
And for years to come
And the second reason
Still work with the US based entertainment company to develop a solution for their golfing
This solution allows a golfer to analyze their swing real time and make adjustments immediately on the driving range
This example of collaboration by Dell and Intel enable this us retailer to write Cutting Edge
Experiences for their golfers in
And what does Intel see is the main barrier of adoption
And iot market and how are Intel and Dell working together
To break through that barrier
Weixin incredible interest from comp
But almost all of them are struggling with
How can we turn data into actionable information that drives meaningful business outcomes
We are working with Delta
Deploy solutions that allow for Analytics
To happen where it matters
While it matters
And often this is at
By moving analytics closer to the point of data collection introduces latency improve real-time responses
And relieves Demand on network bandwidth
Thank you Craig and where can we go to find out more about the packages that Intel has created for the Internet of Things
And what they're doing without
Check out these offerings as well as many others on Dell Technology stock cam coyote
Hey everyone welcome back to the Internet of Things podcast this is your house Stacey Higginbotham
And this week I will be joined by my guest
Granite City police chief Revenue officer at relare
And I could eat how are you doing
Hey Stacy I'm doing well thank you for having me here and I'm excited
It's talk to you more about
Industrial legs
Let's kick it off with a quick
Hey what is it that real layered
Does
Industrial iot software and technology company
Did you say insurance and finance Solutions
Trying to solve a problem
Holiday
Early go to market with the kinetic product
The combination which I'll talk more about a insurance finance and Technology allows the traditional in
Shoe companies to really think of New Delhi models with Kinect
Such as impaired Hugo or exhale we do this a lock the mid-market
Saturday used to be a venture-backed startup
5 years
Let's talk about Munich re
And give us an overview about Mewtwo
Uber in the market
Lenny Gonzaga
Definition of venture capital
But then you know we called.
Munich re email the US Army's Hartford steam boiler
And said hey you know if you can really make things smart
We have
4 million Dixon industrial think that we would love to make smart
And get intelligence
Compressor
Today I mean
Equipment breakdown insurance
I did not know
They have 1600 + PhD
Likely right models
Do understand equipment failure
Cisco's all these models
Coyote
Real-time data
Starting to put in the Bible
Better Solutions
That would be
Viniq liqueur
So you don't eat with us for three years really like what you doing
Nimble iot
Independence
Prospectors but we have the luxury of having the credibility in the balance sheet of the day
How do we help the other industrial companies to do similar
Equipment breakdown that equipment breakdown
Electrical terminal service
Real data
Disconnected products
Better
Or prevent failures
Alright so let's dig into that because the first thing I would think of
When
Listening to what you do is why do we need an insurance element
I'm in a lot of ways this is a deal between to come
Kinesis is the
Equipment provider saying here you go
This is going to work and when it breaks down I'm going to know in advance
So I will
Send someone out proactive
Italy to fix it
Until it feels like a two-party relationship
Adding insurance why it is that needed
The first element of whether risk prevention happens on insurance
Perspective
Connecting a product and making it
Smart and connected are not sure if this is working then I'm sure they should invest
And that's the delivery warranties
Are almost giving the peace of mind for these equipment manufacturers that
They can go to this digital transformation
And this would work
He can't get it out of school old school machines like more than Thompson in a boilers give them a lot of confidence
II
All services equipment I will guarantee you up time but you know because it's new to them
You're somebody else will that be playing
Northeast Equipment Sales
You're so confident that it will actually pay you money
That should be the two areas when insurance comes out to be a teacher
Excellent so we are going to get you those examples in a minute
But let's dig into one of the elements hair which is always fascinated
Which is this idea that
If I am a small to medium-sized manufacturer
And I'm making a pick-and-place machine
And now I'm selling it as a service
What happens is
I'm taking something that used to be
Big lump sum
Peanut
And now it's going to be
Paid out over time
And if you're Amazon in doing something like that or one of the big companies maybe you have a capital to do that
But if you're a smaller
Company
It seems impossible you can't turn hay
Products business into a Services business overnight
The cost of making the product and then your incoming Revenue stream
Just don't match up
So is there a way for you guys to
Open that
Absolutely
Perspective
Spotify
I think it did something old school records our kids know we're saying that in a why not the stuffed every other Market
Discuss the big challenge with you talk about it be that expensive capital
So then been going off the expense of Capital Equipment
Like you just said
I got a big check up song
Lost equipment sale
The disadvantage of course is that
I only get that check maybe 10 years
Leader again and then it's kind of weird that I don't touch my customer for
Aneurysm
I was making a million dollars at Frankford and she treatment plant
Equipment
And then suddenly Out start making on a 200000 a year
Which is great over 10 years
But it's not great
Because we won by
Unsteady Capital heavy are large balance sheet organization
Is some balance sheet the engineering tools
They want to do is be take the assets
Eliza manufactures an art books
Create an object 70 model for the End customer temporary
Like I said you don't want us to customers see this working
They get the money upfront and of course you know that there is some cost
They understand that the market will expand because the
And you leave the state
It would just not get it
In the middle
It's which the good news is that a lot of companies which I make Market on North
Publicly traded
So I'll look at it as a concern is not as much concern to show
Explain it to the market
I mean that's that's how we being sold
Technology
Without getting this data out of these.
On top of that we can do some Dollar Tree flea engineering to give them tomorrow
Transition it to me and still get that money up front
I just found myself and my leaving company
A hundred thousand a year I'll give you the heat treatment plant
Animal getting beat up time
Very compelling value prop
Excellent and what is the things that I thought was really intriguing about
Having
You guys involved in the financial insurance side
Was how it helps make small to medium-sized businesses a real player in this market
Can you elaborate Maybe by giving an example
One of the examples close to my heart is the small company Taco Barn
Public case study the UK
This is a company that sells very specialized CNC machines are diamond polishing and grinding
These machines cost anywhere from 300 to 400 thousand
Svn customers using cider
Gemstones
Spectre
But the challenge was twofold one
10-second was really missing out on the smaller Target segments
The smaller binder sometimes
Don't want to be that 400000
Grunt when they don't know their Market
Zoeva B&B NSB
Create an offer now we're Coburn
Machines
And that coupon care is there
These machines are interested in
Peter collection
Secrets in particular groups on top of that
Which is sold as a fixed price service
13 certain versions of that be also getting PDF.
Coupon machine
Uptime guarantee
And give the end customers of penalty or like a better word it's a machine.
So that's the first way there cuz I'm going to Market
Hey you know
If you have Coban care and Coburn together instead of buying a $400,000 machine
6000 a month
Mayport base
Utilisation
Like I said the financial engineering of taking these
Kubernetes
Used books
Thousand
The biggest mistake by the 6018 elation
Everybody makes money if
They use more
But also
In the Sky 5000b iot plays because
And besides guarantee eternity acid
This is the other beauty of having your own iot connect
Aftermarket Revenue with Services which is never that before
As well as
Opex model do really expand the market
So let's talk about elevators and you guys are helping some of the smaller operators
On the insurance site so can you talk to us about
What you're doing there
Interesting
The smallest service providers
Not the dog Force
But you know who serviced a lot of the older elevators after the contract with the oldest ocean that expires
Is a target segment from their perspective
Then this servicing these elevators by a customer services
Hanging on of course there's a big Challenger
Call of Duty expectedly service there's an efficiently service this without I going there all the time so we've have been
Analyze anything going wrong in the elevator before they go there
Results of compliance Tango in in Germany
I would say that are you know you need to inspect another that can yeast once a month
I'm just going to stay
It's once a year
Germany's every month
So you know
Really helps
Our customers in the service.
Hotel or Hospital around Airport
I would guarantee the up time and make sure
Seven of the eight elevators are running all days
And if they don't I'll pay you been up to you and that's penalties ready
And takes the risk
Let's hope we're going to be elevator space
I will say this but more about
How do you enable better service with a elevator
Family doctor by insurance
So they can confidently sell up time
Wedding envelope time
It does happen
It's not Insurance paxton ma
Okay so you have had a lot of experience in building out Revenue models for the iot
What are some takeaways for small to medium-sized businesses who are looking at this and are saying
And how do I get in on this
What are the questions I should be asking themselves how should they be looking at their business at
They want to try to
Your Excellency this is really hard it's not an easy question to answer for everybody
The first thing we are seeing as a trend
Is that if our customers customers their customers
I seen macroeconomic issues
Bacon.
Anna Place Large orders at equipment
I've been this becomes very interesting example of
Spectre the swords in the BMWs are going to a big transition and you know they cannot
Forecast
Cars anymore
Suppliers suppliers with Supply
City of heat treatment of the service for example you have while cutting
Working with Doc Optical Leone versus all the cables for the body
Only working because we Automotive
Customers are feeling the pressure
And then they like to get new Revenue models
Number one market
It's pretty hard to do this without stakeholder alignment solid sounds very soft and you not talking
Edge technology
Besides the technology we have to do a lot of Consulting
To get in on the ITT in the service system the operations team together
I'm Works only if the
Engaged
Motivated to do this
And then make sure you understand that this is not easy
It's not just putting a sensor and putting it in the cloud
Excellent yes and I think it's important that we had this conversation because we talked a lot in the show about the
Technology
But we don't talk about the financial and the economic
Things that you have to get in place to make this a reality
So thank you so much for coming on the show this week
Absolutely thank you for having me station
That's it for this week thanks so much for listening and remember if you'd like more iot
Sign up for my newsletter at Stacey on iot. Cam will see you next week